<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Boerhaave: Boerhaave's Aphorisms.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Herman Boerhaave</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Boerhaave's aphorisms: concerning the knowledge and the cure of
              diseases.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">N15473</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N15473"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for B. Cowse, and W. Innys, in St. Paul's Church-Yard, MDCCXV. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1715</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="19"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="400"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">Countway Library of Medicine</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107151642</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="General treatises"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="19"/>
    <body>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="4"/>
      <div type="section">
        <pb n="5"/>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Diſtempers of the ſolid ſimple <hi rend="roman">Fibre</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>21. Thoſe Parts (which being ſeparated from <lb/>the fluid contained in the Veſſels,
          are applied and <lb/>ſticking to each other by the ſtrength of the living <lb/>Body, and
          make the leaſt Fibre) are the leaſt, the <lb/>ſimpleſt, earthy and hardly changeable from
          or by <lb/>vertue of any Cauſe, which are found in our living <lb/>Bodies. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>22. Hence the reaſon, why in them, ſeparately <lb/>conſidered, no one Diſtemper was
          ever, obſerved by <lb/>Phyſicians, or mentioned as having been cured. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>23. But in the leaſt Fibre, grown from the Con- <lb/>junction of thoſe Parts (21.)
          the following moſt <lb/>ſimple Diſeaſes from 24. to 38. deſerve to be taken <lb/>notice
          of: for they are frequent, and lay the foun- <lb/>dation for underſtanding of others;
          notwithſtand- <lb/>ing they have hitherto been overlook'd, or not well <lb/>enough
          underſtood. <note place="inline" rend="italic">* <hi rend="roman">Baglivi</hi> has
            publiſh'd a <lb/>Treatiſe with the Title, <hi rend="roman">De fibra motrice &amp; mor-
              <lb/>boſa</hi>. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Diſtempers of a Laxe and Weak <hi rend="roman">Fibre</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>24. <hi rend="italic">The weakneſs of the Fibre</hi> is that cohæſion <lb/>of the
          minuteſt Parts deſcribed (21.) which is ſo <pb n="6"/>
          <lb/>looſly linked, that it may be pulled aſunder even <lb/>by that degree of Motion which
          is requiſite in heal- <lb/>thy Bodies, or not much exceeding it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/> 25. The ſame <hi rend="italic">is preceeded</hi>, 1. By the con- <lb/>verſion of the
          Aliments into the Nature of heal- <lb/>thy vital Juices obſtructed; which is owing to
          <lb/>the too great conſumption of good Fluids, and to <lb/>the Sluggiſhneſs of the
          powerful ſtrength of the <lb/>Solids over the Fluids; Or to the too great tough- <lb/>neſs
          of the Aliments overcoming the Powers that <lb/>ſhould alter them in the Body. 2. By the
          too weak <lb/>application of one Part (21.) to the other, which <lb/>proceeds from the too
          weak motion of the Fluids, <lb/>and this again moſtly from a Want or a Defect of <lb/>the
          Muſcular motion. 3. By a too great pulling of <lb/>the Fibre, being near to a Breaking. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>26. The Weakneſs <hi rend="italic">produceth</hi> eaſily a Stretching <lb/>and a
          Breaking of the ſmall Veſſels made up of <lb/>thoſe weak Fibres (24.) and conſequently
          abates of <lb/>their power over the Fluids therein contained; <lb/>from which diſtenſions
          ariſe Tumors; from the <lb/>ſtopping or extravaſated Fluids Putrefactions; and
          <lb/>farther all ſuch innumerable Ills, as are the Con- <lb/>ſequences of them both. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/> 27. From what has been ſaid in (24, 25, 26.) <lb/>one may ſurely know when any
          Diſtemper from <lb/>weak Fibres is preſent, paſt, or coming on; the <lb/>Effects thereof
          may be foreſeen, and what is ne- <lb/>ceſſary towards the Cure is ſurely known. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/> 28. The Cure muſt be obtained; 1. By <lb/>ſuch Aliments as abound in ſuch matter as
          is de- <lb/>ſcribed (21.) and which be almoſt ſo prepared <lb/>beforehand as it is in a
          ſtrong and healthy Bo- <pb n="7"/>
          <lb/>dy; Such are Milk, Eggs, Fleſh-broaths, Pana- <lb/>does rightly prepared of Bread
          that was well fer- <lb/>mented; and rough Wines. All which muſt be <lb/>given in ſmall
          quantities, but often. 2. By en- <lb/>creaſing and invigorating the motion of the Solids
          <lb/>and Fluids by means of frictions with a Fleſh-bruſh <lb/>or with Flannel; of riding
          on Horſeback, and in <lb/>a Coach, or being carried in a Boat; and laſtly, <lb/>of
          walking, running, and other bodily Exerciſes. <lb/>3. By a gentle preſſure or bandage upon
          the Veſ- <lb/>ſels, and a moderate repelling of the Liquids there- <lb/>in contained: 4.
          By Medicines both acid and au- <lb/>ſtere, but applied with great caution and gentle-
          <lb/>neſs. 5. By any means as will remove and reme- <lb/>dy the too great pulling of them. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>29. <hi rend="italic">That Fibre is ſaid to be Laxe and Looſe</hi>
          <lb/>whereof the Parts are in that degree of Coheſion, <lb/>that the ſame Fibre may with
          very little pains and <lb/>pulling, be made longer than it was before; from <lb/>whence it
          appears, that this is that Sort of weak- <lb/>neſs as in (24.) and that the aptneſs to
          bend doth <lb/>depend from hence; and conſequently, that all <lb/>theſe Effects, as well
          as <hi rend="italic">the leſſen'd Elaſticity of <lb/>the Fibre</hi> are clearly underſtood
          from what has <lb/>been ſaid from (21 to 28.) </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>30. And even from thence Anſwers are ready <lb/>to all the following Difficulties
          objected, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> Why <lb/>watry and fat Aliments occaſion a weakneſs
          in the <lb/>Fibres? Why the ſame Fibres are weak in People <lb/>of a cold Conſtitution, in
          young People, ſuch as <lb/>move little, and ſuch as are ſtill growing? Why <lb/>earthy
          Aliments, and ſuch as have a moderate <lb/>roughneſs ſtrengthen the Fibres? Why People of
            <pb n="8"/>
          <lb/>a hot Conſtitution, and ſuch as exerciſe much, <lb/>have ſtrong Fibres? Why the
          Fibres have an Ela- <lb/>ſticity proportioned to their Strength? </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Diſtempers of the Stiff and Elaſtick <hi rend="roman">Fibre</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>31. <hi rend="italic">The too great ſtiffneſs of the Fibre</hi> is that <lb/>ſticking
          together of the minuteſt Parts (21.) which <lb/>cauſes them to be link'd ſo cloſely
          together, that <lb/>they will not, or cannot give way to that power <lb/>of the Fluids,
          which in a ſtate of perfect health <lb/>ought to overcome their reſiſtance. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>32. <hi rend="italic">The ſame is occaſioned</hi> by all thoſe Cauſes, <lb/>which
          have been mentioned (28.) as neceſſary to <lb/>cure the weakneſs of the Fibres, if thoſe
          means <lb/>are applied or continued too long. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>33. The effects of that ſtiffneſs (31.) of the <lb/>Fibres are to cauſe the Veſſels
          made up of them <lb/>to be leſs flexible, narrower, ſhorter, too much <lb/>reſiſting and
          hindring the free motion of the Li- <lb/>quids, aud occaſion all the Diſaſters mentioned
          <lb/>in (50, 51, 52, 53.) by a neceſſary Conſequence. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>34. From which one may know this Diſtem- <lb/>per (31.) when preſent, and alſo
          foretell the Con- <lb/>ſequences; nor is the Method of Curing the <lb/>ſame leſs apparent. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>35. The Cure is effected 1. by ſuch Meat and <lb/>Drink as is thin and watry without
          any rough- <lb/>neſs, chiefly the continued uſe of Milk-whey, of <lb/>the ſofteſt Herbs
          and Sallads, and unfermented <lb/>Liquors. 2. By avoiding of Exerciſe, and dwel- <lb/>ling
          in a moiſt cooliſh Air, and taking long Sleeps. <lb/>3. by the taking or outwardly
          applying watry, <lb/>lukewarm, taſteleſs Medicines, and, ſuch as con- <lb/>tain the
          lighteſt and ſofteſt Oyls. </p>
        <pb n="9"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>36. From hence is underſtood <hi rend="italic">the too great <lb/>Elaſticity</hi> of
          the Fibre, and likewiſe how to cure <lb/>the ſame, as being generally the Companion or
          <lb/>the Effect of the too great ſtiffneſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>37. And alſo, why Childrens, Womens, and <lb/>idle Peoples Fibres are generally lax
          and looſe; <lb/>and on the contrary, why the Fibres and gene- <lb/>rally all the ſolid
          parts of full-grown People, of <lb/>the Male-ſex, of laborious People and ſuch as ex-
          <lb/>erciſe much, are moſtly ſtiff and rigid: And why <lb/>in thoſe, when afflicted with a
          Palſie, there is a <lb/>ſtrong contraction of the affected Parts. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Diſtempers of the leſs and larger <hi rend="roman">Veſſels</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>38. The Diſeaſes of the leaſt Veſſels made up <lb/>of the ſimpleſt Fibres (21. 22.)
          (either by an <lb/>Application or a twiſting of ſeveral together) <lb/>proceed from the
          ſame Cauſes, have the ſame Na- <lb/>ture and Conſequences, and require the ſame Cure;
          <lb/>and conſequently may be learn'd from (21. to <lb/>30.) </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>39. The larger Veſſels made up of the ſmall <lb/>ones by the application or twiſting
          of ſeveral to- <lb/>gether, are ſubject to two ſeveral kinds of Diſ- <lb/>eaſes. The firſt
          of theſe depends on the Diſ- <lb/>eaſes of the ſmalleſt Veſſels, which make up this
          <lb/>large one; ſo that the Riſe, Nature, Effects, and <lb/>the Cure thereof muſt be taken
          from thence. (38.) <lb/>But the latter Sort depends, 1. From the ſtrength <lb/>with which
          the Fluid running through this large <lb/>Veſſel doth preſs upon the ſides of that Veſſel
          in <lb/>extending the ſame: Which Sides, being made <lb/>up of the ſmaller Veſſels, are by
          this preſſure de- <pb n="10"/>
          <lb/>prived of their Fluid; and if continued they grow <lb/>together, and into a ſolid
          Fibre, but in a larger <lb/>Sort than that deſcribed (21. 23.) Which Effect <lb/>may alſo
          be propagated to the next adjoining ſmall <lb/>Veſſels. 2. From the nature of the Fluid
          which <lb/>thickens and ſticks to the ſides of its proper <lb/>Veſſel. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>40. From hence may clearly be underſtood, <lb/>how Veſſels are ſaid to be weak, laxe,
          ſtrong, <lb/>ſtiff, and elaſtic; whereof the Ignorant talk much <lb/>without any true
          Meaning. And the Subject is <lb/>ſo noble, that it deſerves being treated of more <lb/>at
          large. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Diſtempers of weak and laxe <hi rend="roman">Entrails</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/> 41. The weakneſs of the Veſſels and Entrails <lb/>we call that coheſion of the
          Parts, conſtituting <lb/>the ſame, which may be broke with ſo ſmall a <lb/>Motion as to
          make them incapable of perform- <lb/>ing, what not only a living but a healthy ſtate of
          <lb/>Body doth require of them. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>42. Which are different according to the dif- <lb/>ferent Age or Sex. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/> 43. This Weakneſs proceeds, 1. From the <lb/>weakneſs of the Fibre and the Cauſes
          thereof. <lb/>2. From the weakneſs of the ſmalleſt Veſſels, <lb/>and its Cauſes. 3. From
          the ſluggiſhneſs of the <lb/>Liquid flowing through the larger Veſſels, which <lb/>may
          proceed from its Quantity being leſſened, or <lb/>the increaſing of its watry unſpirituous
          Nature; <lb/>or laſtly from the muſcular Motion being grown <lb/>ſlower and duller. </p>
        <pb n="11"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>44. From the ſaid (41.) Weakneſs occaſioned <lb/>by the Cauſes juſt mentioned ariſe
          many Diſeaſes; <lb/>which are falſly attributed to a bad Conſtitution, <lb/>or ſuppoſed to
          be born with the Patient. The <lb/>chief are, 1. An eaſie Dilatation of the Veſſels
          <lb/>and Tumors: An eaſie Compreſſion of the ſame <lb/>and emptineſs: A ſtagnation of the
          Liquids: A <lb/>more difficult and even reſiſting Motion of the <lb/>Heart: A crudity of
          the Liquids, which were to <lb/>acquire a farther degree of Coction there: A Pu-
          <lb/>trefaction of the ſame ſucceeding thereon: An in- <lb/>capacity thereupon of
          performing the vital, ani- <lb/>mal or natural Functions: And conſequently, all <lb/>the
          Miſchiefs that muſt follow from theſe; which <lb/>as they are infinite in Number, ſo be
          they moſt <lb/>difficult to cure, and very fruitful in producing <lb/>new and unheard of
          Diſtempers; and chiefly <lb/>theſe two general ones, which are noted by the <lb/>Names of
            Κα<unclear>η</unclear>εξια and Κα<unclear>ηο</unclear>χυμία. An eaſie diſſo- <lb/>lution
          or breaking of the Veſſels, either from in- <lb/>ward or outward Cauſes, being either
          ſharp or <lb/>acted violently; from thence an effuſion, a ſtag- <lb/>nation, a corruption
          and emptying of the Liquid, <lb/>which is neceſſary to life and health: An inter-
          <lb/>ception of the Motion of the Fluid, through the <lb/>broken Veſſels, and their
          Putrefaction; which <lb/>were preſerved entire by means of thoſe Fluids <lb/>moving
          through them: Theſe again are many; <lb/>and chiefly Φθίσις, Εμπύημα, ΰδρωψ, and ατροφία.
          x <lb/><hi rend="italic">Conſumptions, Impoſthumes in the Cheaſt, Dropſies, <lb/>falling
            away and loſs of Fleſh.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>45. Which if any one accurately conſiders, he <lb/>ſhall not only know the Origin,
          the preſence and <pb n="12"/>
          <lb/>the event of this (41.) but alſo of an infinite <lb/>number of other and very
          difficult Diſeaſes, and <lb/>he alone can have ſucceſs in the finding out and
          <lb/>applying of ſufficient and ſafe Remedies. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>46. And as for the application of thoſe, the ve- <lb/>ry weakneſs of the Part
          commands to take Time <lb/>for the Cure; for in no other Caſe is a ſudden <lb/>Change more
          pernitious. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>47. Therefore Remedies ought to be admini- <lb/>ſtred ſlowly, cautiouſly, and riſe by
          degrees in <lb/>the very efficacie of 'em: And after the Veſſels <lb/>ſhall be
          ſtrengthen'd by their uſe, then and no <lb/>ſooner let the Muſcles be put into a vigorous
          and <lb/>ſtrong Motion, till it appears from every Particu- <lb/>lar, that now the Veſſels
          and Entrails are be- <lb/>come ſufficiently compact, ſolid and healed with- <lb/>out a
          fear of breaking there anew. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>48. From hence it appears, that what is re- <lb/>ported of the Power of Aliments is
          falſe in one <lb/>Senſe and true in another. That the exerciſe of <lb/>the Muſcles doth
          ſtrengthen the Fibres; That <lb/>the exerciſe of Riding doth diſſolve the thickned
          <lb/>Humors, ſtrengthen the laxe Parts without diſ- <lb/>ſipating bodily Strength or the
          Spirits: That the <lb/>very Blood of the ſtrongeſt People is very thick, <lb/>ſoft and
          kind; that of the weakeſt and tendereſt <lb/>on the contrary, broken, light, and ſharp:
          That <lb/>a number of Diſeaſes, in appearance very diffe- <lb/>rent, may yet be Branches
          of the ſame Tree, <lb/>the Root of which being cut they are all cured <lb/>of courſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>49. From the ſame Principles may be known <lb/>and cured the laxneſs of the Veſſels
          and En- <lb/>trails. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="13"/>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Diſtempers of the too ſtrong and ſtiff <hi rend="roman">Entrails</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/> 50. The too great ſtiffneſs of the Veſſels and <lb/>Entrails is that cohærence of
          the Parts of which <lb/>they are made up, as will not give way to that <lb/>degree of
          Motion, which was to change and <lb/>move them, that all ſuch Things might be per-
          <lb/>formed, as in a living and healthy State did de- <lb/>pend upon, and were occaſioned
          by, that Change. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>51. It proceeds, 1. From all the Cauſes that <lb/>occaſioned too great a ſtiffneſs in
          the Fibres (32.) <lb/>2. but chiefly from the Fibres being ſtrongly preſ- <lb/>ſed upon
          each other by the overpowering ſtrength <lb/>of the ſtrongly moving Fluids. 3. From.the
          grow- <lb/>ing together of the ſides of the ſmall Veſſels de- <lb/>prived of their Liquid
          by that ſtrongs preſſure, by <lb/>which; the vital Liquid of the Arteries preſſeth
          <lb/>the ſides of the larger Canals; which Effect is <lb/>moſt commonly produced and
          carried to a height <lb/>by any violent exerciſe of the Muſcles. 4. From <lb/>a Veſſel
          which its proper, thickned, dried <lb/>up and coagulated Juice is ſhut up and grown
          <lb/>into a Solid. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>52. Where this takes place in Veſſels, the <lb/>Effects are, 1. Reſembling or the
          ſame with thoſe <lb/>that proceeded from too ſtiff a Fibre. 2. It oc- <lb/>caſions a
          ſtrong Labour; So that the Fibres endea- <lb/>vour to bring themſelves, from the
          circumference <lb/>of the Veſſel to its center; to make its hollow <lb/>narrower; to
          preſs, to ſqueeze, to repell and even <lb/>to expell its Fluids; and conſequently to
          hinder <lb/>their protuſion from the Heart, and alſo the acti- <lb/>on of the Heart it
          ſelf; So that they hardly re- <pb n="14"/>
          <lb/>move again to their proper extent; from hence <lb/>interrupt the even Motion and
          Circulation of the <lb/>Blood, and conſequently the ſeveral Secretions; <lb/>they leſſen
          the quantity of Blood which the Heart <lb/>ought to ſend forth at each beating; they
          hinder <lb/>the Heart from emptying itſelf entirely; they pro- <lb/>duce Polypuſſes from
          that very remaining Blood, <lb/>which being ſqueezed and robbed of its Fluid <lb/>Parts,
          the Polypus grows harder and bigger, <lb/>which at laſt produceth Choakings and ſudden
          <lb/>Death. 3. In Veſſels wounded it occaſions great <lb/>Gaps, becauſe of the great
          ſtrength wherewith the <lb/>ſeveral Parts of the Veſſels do pull towards their
          <lb/>faſtnings: And when they are cut aſunder entire- <lb/>ly, the Cavity is much leſſened
          at both ends, <lb/>or ſometimes entirely ſhut up. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>53. From theſe ſet down in 31. to 37. and <lb/>50 to 52. and clearly apprehended, any
          intelli- <lb/>gent Body may frame to himſelf Rules, by which <lb/>he muſt underſtand the
          paſt, preſent and future <lb/>ſtiffneſs, elaſticity, and power of the Veſſels, their
          <lb/>preſent or approaching action, and the proper Cure <lb/>for all. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>54. For this is effected, 1. By all the Re- <lb/>medies which were ſet down as proper
          to cure <lb/>the ſtiffneſs of the Fibres (35.) 2. And chiefly <lb/>by all ſuch as leſſen
          the quantity, the thickneſs <lb/>and the preſſure of the Blood. 3. By ſuch as ſu-
          <lb/>ſpend the Motion of the Muſcles. 4. By all ſuch, <lb/>as moiſten, ſoften, open,
          dilute, reſolve and cleanſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>55. From all theſe, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> 21. to 55. are ſuffi- <lb/>ciently
          underſtood and a Method ſhewn for curing <lb/>all the Diſeaſes which are peculiarly
          belonging to <pb n="15"/>
          <lb/>the ſolid Parts of the Body: And from thence alſo <lb/>appears what muſt be anſwered
          to the following <lb/>Queries. Which be the difference of the Structure <lb/>of the Solid
          Parts in the different Ages of Life? <lb/>Why Man grows, continues for ſome Years of
          <lb/>the ſame height; and afterwards in old Age <lb/>grows ſhorter again, and leſs? Why he
          is ſome- <lb/>times of a looſe texture, ſometimes of a ſtrong <lb/>and ſtiff one? Why he
          is ſometimes Moiſt and <lb/>full, at other times Dry? Why he dies a natural <lb/>Death,
          and muſt needs die when he is come to <lb/>a pitch of old Age? And then of what illneſs he
          <lb/>moſt commonly dieth? What Diſtempers are moſt <lb/>common to each particular Age?
          What Diet, <lb/>what ſort of Life, what Medicines are the moſt <lb/>adapted to the ſeveral
          Seaſons of Life? How far <lb/>one ought to believe, and of what uſe it is, what <lb/>has
          been ſaid about the ſtiffnefs or laxeneſs of the <lb/>Solids, <hi rend="italic"
            >&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/> 56. We ought now after the moſt ſimple Di- <lb/>ſeaſes of the Solids to treat of the
          Wounds (16.) <lb/>But as they always bring along with them Di- <lb/>ſeaſes of the Liquids
          as from their own Nature, <lb/>we chuſe to treat of thoſe things firſt, which <lb/>ought
          to be known before a compleat Hiſtory of <lb/>the Wounds be given. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>57. So that we ſhall treat firſt of thoſe Diſtem- <lb/>pers of the Fluids, which
          naturally befall them, <lb/>either when they are left to themſelves, without <lb/>being
          any ways affected from their Veſſels, or <lb/>when they are put into too violent, or too
          ſlug- <lb/>giſh a Motion. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="16"/>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Of the moſt ſimple Defects of the Fluids and <lb/>ſuch as come of their own accord. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>58. The ſeveral Humors which are to be <lb/>found in a living Man, are either yet
          crude, re- <lb/>taining the Nature of ſuch Aliments as were late- <lb/>ly taken,or have
          through the Power of the Na- <lb/>tural Functions, and the mixture with the other
          <lb/>pre-exiſtent humours in Man, acquired a Nature <lb/>very like unto them. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>59. The firſt mentioned are generally taken <lb/>from Plants, or from the Fleſh of
          other Animals. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Spontaneous Diſeaſes from an <hi rend="roman">acid Humor</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>60. Our Liquids made up from meally Plants, <lb/>or Garden Fruits, either raw or
          fermented, if <lb/>they overcome the Power of our innate Juices <lb/>and of Life, acquire
          in us that nature and diſpo- <lb/>ſition, as they owe to the Nature of their Produ-
          <lb/>cers when fomented in a moiſt and moderate heat. <lb/>From hence chiefly we muſt
          derive the <hi rend="italic">acid A- <lb/>crimony</hi>, and the more hurtful <hi
            rend="italic">glutinous Fat</hi>. The <lb/>firſt proceeds chiefly from fermented and not
          fer- <lb/>mented Juices; The latter from <hi rend="italic">mealy (unfer- <lb/>mented or
            boyled)</hi> Aliments. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>61. This acid Acrimony is igenerally the Pro- <lb/>duct 1. Of mealy Aliments, juicy
          Acids, as are <lb/>new; crude, actually working, or of ſuch Vege- <lb/>tables as have
          fermented already. 2. Of a want <lb/>of good Blood in that Body which takes the
          <lb/>forementioned Food. 3. Of a Weak texture of <lb/>the Fibres in the Veſſels and
          Entrails (24. 29. <lb/>41.) 4. Of a Defect of the Animal Motion. </p>
        <pb n="17"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/> 62. It firſt takes its Seat in the firſt Digeſters, <lb/>ſuch as the Stomach and the
          Duodenum, from <lb/>thence it advances with a ſlower pace into the <lb/>Blood, and at laſt
          taints all the Humors of <lb/>the Body. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>63. It occaſions ſowre belchings, hunger, a <lb/>gnawing pain in the Stomach, moſt
          terrible Co- <lb/>licks, with Wind and even Convulſions in the <lb/>Guts; a ſluggiſhneſs
          of the Bilis, and many <lb/>changes and alterations of the ſame; it renders <lb/>the Chyle
          ſowre, and the very Excrements by <lb/>Stool ſtink ſowriſh: Theſe are its Effects in the
          <lb/>Stomach and in the Guts. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>64. When got into the Blood, it cauſeth it to <lb/>look pale, and turns the Serum
          newly come out <lb/>of the Chyle ſowre; it makes the very Spittle <lb/>ſowre; from hence
          Itchings, Obſtructions, Pim- <lb/>ples, Ulcers, Coagulations of the Blood made <lb/>unable
          to circulate; afterwards prickings of the <lb/>Brain and the Nerves, from whence
          Convulſions, <lb/>the whole Circulation of all the Humors inter- <lb/>rupted, and laſtly
          Death it ſelf. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>65. From theſe deſcribed from 60 to 65. one <lb/>may have a certain Knowledge, when
          this acid <lb/>Acrimony is preſent, coming, or paſt; hence al- <lb/>ſo are ſeen its
          Effects; and may the Cure be <lb/>conceived. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>66. Which is effected, 1. With Aliments as <lb/>deſtroy Sourneſs whether taken from
          Animals or <lb/>the vegetable Kind. 2. With Juices like unto <lb/>well-conditioned Blood,
          which one may find in <lb/>Birds of prey. 9. Strengthners. 4. With a ſtrong <lb/>Motion.
          5. With Medicines as do abſorb and <pb n="18"/>
          <lb/>ſoak in the Acids, as dilute them, as blunts the <lb/>Edges of them, and changes 'em. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>67. Whereof the Choice, Preparation, Doſe, and <lb/>timely Application are known to
          the Phyſician <lb/>from the knowledge of the Diſeaſe, its Seat, the <lb/>Patient's perſon
          and conſtitution, and many more <lb/>Circumſtances. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>68. From hence it appears, why the Diſeaſes <lb/>of this Kind are ſo common to
          Children, to Sloth- <lb/>ful people, to Poor people and certain Tradeſmen; <lb/>whereupon
          conſult <hi rend="italic">Ramazzini de Morbis artificum</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Diſeaſes from a ſpontaneous Glew. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>69. The Glutinous fat Humors from Vege- <lb/>tables is occaſioned, 1. By crude and
          mealy Ali- <lb/>ments, and by unripe rough Fruits. 2. By a <lb/>want of good Blood. 3. By
          a Weakneſs of the <lb/>Veſſels, of the Entrails and of the Choler. 4. By <lb/>the
          leſſening of the Animal Motion. 5. By a <lb/>diſſipation of the moſt fluid Parts of the
          Blood <lb/>through the relaxed ſecretory Veſſels. 6. By the <lb/>Retention of the thicker
          parts of the Blood and <lb/>Humors from the weakneſs of thoſe Veſſels and <lb/>Inſtruments
          as ſhou'd thruſt them out. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>70. It appears firſt in the firſt Digeſters, from <lb/>hence it flows into the Blood,
          and afterwards in <lb/>all the other Liquids that are derived from the <lb/>Blood. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>71. In the firſt Paſſages it occaſions a proſtrate <lb/>Appetite, a feeling of
          Fulneſs; a Nauſeating, Vo- <lb/>mitings, want of Digeſtion; a ſluggiſhneſs of the
          <lb/>Choler, its growing ſlimy and conſuming; it <lb/>breeds naſty Phlegms in the Stomach
          and Guts; <pb n="19"/>
          <lb/>binds up and ſwells the Belly; hinders the ma- <lb/>king, the perfecting and the
          ſeparating of the <lb/>Chyle into the Milk-veſſels. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>72. In the Blood it produceth a toughneſs and <lb/>a paleneſs, making its Circulation
          almoſt impoſſi- <lb/>ble; in the Veſſels Obſtructions, Concretions; a <lb/>pale Urine with
          ſcarce any Smell; a ſlow Spit- <lb/>tle; a white Swelling; and almoſt all the ani-
          <lb/>mal Secretions obſtructed; a defect of the fineſt <lb/>Juices; and from all theſe the
          ſmalleſt Veſſels <lb/>do ſhut up and grow together. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>73. From hence are all the Coctions, Circu- <lb/>lations, Secretions, Excretions, all
          the Vital, Na- <lb/>tural, and Animal Motions diſorder'd, from whence <lb/>Choakings and
          Death. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>74. From theſe (69. to 73.) appear the Diag- <lb/>noſtic, the Prognoſtic, and the
          remembrance of <lb/>this Diſeaſe; nor can it be difficult to conclude <lb/>what muſt be
          neceſſary towards the Cure. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>75. Which maybe obtained, 1. With uſing a <lb/>Diet of things that have fermented
          well, and are <lb/>ſeaſoned with Salt and Spices. 2. With Broath <lb/>made of Volatiles.
          With whatever may ſtrengthen <lb/>the Veſſels and Bowels. 4. With a gradual in-
          <lb/>creaſe of Motion and Exerciſe. 5. With diluting, <lb/>reſolving, ſtimulating
          Medicines, ſuch as carry <lb/>along with them wherewithal to ſupply the want <lb/>of
          Choler, and are of a ſoapy Nature. 6. With <lb/>Frictions, Heat, Baths, and Bliſterings.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Diſtempers of a Spontaneous <hi rend="roman">Alkali</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/> 76. Some Plants abound in a matter, which, <lb/>if putrefied of its own accord, doth
          not turn into <pb n="20"/>
          <lb/>an acid Subſtance, nor run together, but melts <lb/>away into a ſtinking fat Alcali:
          Such are moſt <lb/>all aromatick Plants as have a very ſharp taſte: <lb/>But it's very
          ſeldom that ſo much is taken of them <lb/>as will from its peculiar nature create an
          illneſs: <lb/>But if it ſhou'd happen, that Diſeaſe ought to be <lb/>ranked among thoſe
          occaſioned by a ſharp and <lb/>oleous Alcali. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>77. Our Juices formed from the feeding upon <lb/>Meat muſt vary, 1. According to the
          Food as the <lb/>Beaſts were fed with. 2. According to the diffe- <lb/>rent parts we eat
          of them. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>78. For thoſe Animals which feed upon Herbs <lb/>and Water make a Chyle either
          ſowriſh or eaſily <lb/>turning ſo, and conſequently give Milk of the <lb/>ſame nature,
          which being taken for Food by <lb/>us, muſt needs preſerve the ſame Nature as if <lb/>we
          our ſelves had fed upon thoſe Herbs and <lb/>Waters, and creates commonly in our Stomachs,
          <lb/>and firſt Paſſages, a ropy Matter like unto new <lb/>Cheeſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>79. Thoſe that feed upon Animals of another <lb/>Kind, their Juices turn eaſily into
          an Alcali. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>80. When Aliments with the ſtrength of our <lb/>Bodies are ſo ſar attenuated as to be
          converted <lb/>into Liquors, ſuch as have been found in <lb/>healthy and ſtrong Bodies in
          four and twenty <lb/>Hours from the taking of Nouriſhment; If the <lb/>ſame are left to
          themſelves in a warm place un- <lb/>diſturbed, or are violently ſhook, they'll always
          <lb/>acquire the Nature of that beginning Putrefaction. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>81. But in Aliments from other Animals this <lb/>diſpoſition to a ſudden Putrefaction
          is there alrea- <pb n="21"/>
          <lb/>dy of its own accord without needing that altera- <lb/>tion which they undergo in our
          Bodies. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>82. This Corruption indicates that ſtate of the <lb/>Humors, which obligeth the watry
          Parts to ex- <lb/>hale; the ſaline Matter being attenuated, deprived <lb/>of its Acid, or
          even altered, to grow ſharp, volatil <lb/>and of an alcali Nature; The oily Part alſo
          being <lb/>thinner in one Part, deprived of its Earth, mixed <lb/>with that ſharp Salt,
          groweth harſh, volatile, and <lb/>ſtinking: But t'other part of the Oyl being moſt
          <lb/>firmly united with that Earth, which was depri- <lb/>ved of its Water, Salt and the
          firſt mentioned Oyl <lb/>turns into black, thick Dreggs incapable of flow- <lb/>ing. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>83. Inſects, Fiſhes, amphibious Creatures, Birds, <lb/>Beaſts of all Kinds, and
          Reptiles, and even Man <lb/>himſelf do of their own Nature, when dead, all <lb/>turn into
          that Corruption juſt now deſcribed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>84. The Cauſes which makes this Corruption <lb/>to follow are, 1. Aliments from
          living Creatures <lb/>(except the Milk of grazing Cattle) chiefly from <lb/>Inſects,
          Fiſhes, Birds of prey, and ſuch Vegeta- <lb/>bles as are apt to turn into an Alkali. 2. A
          ful- <lb/>neſs either of good Blood, or of ſuch as was al- <lb/>ready tending to
          Corruption. 3. A great ſtrength <lb/>of the Veſſels, of the Bowels and of Choler. 4. A
          <lb/>ſtanding or ſtopping of the Fluids, or too great a <lb/>hurry of the ſame at the
          animal Motions being ei- <lb/>ther too quick or too ſlow. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>85. In the firſt Paſſage it occaſions Thirſt, loſs <lb/>of Appetite, ſtinking
          Belches; it fills the Mouth, <lb/>Tongue, Palate and Throat with bitter ſtinking
          <lb/>Filth; it creates nauſeouſneſs and vomitings of <pb n="22"/>
          <lb/>corrupt bilious Matter; a ſtinking Crudity; a <lb/>Looſeneſs with much Choler,
          inflammatory iliac <lb/>Pains, and a very troubleſome Heat. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>86. When carried into the Blood it occaſions <lb/>it to be diſſolved into a putrid
          Maſs, it creates <lb/>there an Alcali, oleous, volatil Acrimony; it ren- <lb/>ders it
          unfit for nutrition, it makes it apt to con- <lb/>ſume, deſtroys the leaſt Veſſels, and ſo
          on; di- <lb/>ſturbs, confounds and undoth all the Functions of <lb/>the ſolid and fluid
          Parts; ſo that the circulation, <lb/>ſecretion, and excretion of Humors keep no lon-
          <lb/>ger their Courſe; and there ſucceeds burning hot <lb/>Fevers, the Urine and all the
          ſeparated Juices be- <lb/>come fetid and rotten, comes on Inflammations, <lb/>Impoſthumes,
          Gangrenes, Mortifications, and at <lb/>laſt Death it ſelf. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>87. From what has been ſaid (from 76. to 86.) <lb/>one may again know, prognoſticate,
          and even find <lb/>out the Method to cure this Diſtemper eaſily. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>88. The Cure may be obtained by, 1. Aliments <lb/>as will ſpeedily grow ſowre, or
          ſuch as are acid <lb/>already; ſuch are all ſorts of mealy Eatables <lb/>boyl'd in Water,
          or being left to ferment till <lb/>they begin to corrupt; Milk and all that can be
          <lb/>made from it, carrying along with it the Quality <lb/>of the Herb; all ripe Fruits,
          the Juices thereof <lb/>whether raw or fermented and ſowred; ſuch as <lb/>Cyder and Perry.
          2. Acid Medicines from the <lb/>raw Vegetables, or fermented, or from Salts and
          <lb/>Brimſtone converted into Acids by the ſtrength of <lb/>Fire. 3. Such Salts as do
          devour the Alcali, as <lb/>Sal Gem, Sea-ſalt and Nitre. 4. Watry Diluters. <lb/>5. Such as
          gently do blunt, as Emulſions made of <pb n="23"/>
          <lb/>the Seeds of Vegetables, or Decoctions of the <lb/>ſame. 6. Soapy cleanſing Medicines
          mix'd of A- <lb/>cids and Oyls; Oxymel, and acid Conſerves and <lb/>Extracts. 7. Laſtly by
          Reſt, Sleep, Steam-bath <lb/>or Fomentations. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>89. From whence it appears, where and why <lb/>ſowre Belchings are good ſucceeding
          ſtinking Bel- <lb/>ches. Why and what recovering People do com- <lb/>plain of a
          troubleſome Taſte of Salt Ammoniac? <lb/>Why it is a good Sign in accute Diſeaſes when the
          <lb/>Patients Sweat ſmells ſowre? What ſort of Acri- <lb/>mony it is, which ought to be
          called Acid, which <lb/>are Alcaline, Bilious or Oleous? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>90. Hence laſtly may be known, what harm <lb/>doth the too great or the too little
          Motion of the <lb/>circulating Fluids; and how much its Conſequen- <lb/>ces and Effects
          vary according to the variety of Pla- <lb/>ces, where they ſtop, and of the Humours upon
          <lb/>which it operates: What Damages from a ſtop- <lb/>ping Humour, and what from
          extravaſated and <lb/>lurking. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>91. Having conſidered all the ſeveral Diſeaſes of <lb/>the Solids and the Fluids (as
          were the Simpleſt) <lb/>ſeverally; follows now to treat of thoſe, which <lb/>occur
          together both in the Solids and in the Flu- <lb/>ids, beginning alſo with the Simpleſt.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Of Diſeaſes acknowledging no other Cauſe beſides <lb/>the too quick circulatory
          Motion. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>92. All the Fluids which are contained in any <lb/>Veſſel, that has its riſe from the
          great Artery, are <lb/>ſeparated from that Blood only, which a little <lb/>while before
          was thoroughly united and mixed in <pb n="24"/>
          <lb/>the right and left Ventricles of the Heart, carry- <lb/>ing no other Face than of one
          even and homoge- <lb/>neous Liquor. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>93. It has notwithſtanding already in thoſe very <lb/>Places ſome Globules greater
          than others, of a <lb/>particular Size, of a changeable Figure, of a red <lb/>Colour; and
          a tranſparent Water, lighter, thin- <lb/>ner, of ſmaller Particles, but becauſe of their
          <lb/>tranſparency hardly diſtinguiſhable from each o- <lb/>ther. The firſt is called <hi
            rend="italic">Gore</hi>, and the latter <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>.
          <lb/>Magnifying-glaſſes have demonſtrated both. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>94. The red Gore being ſettled and ſeparated <lb/>from the Serum in another Veſſel,
          is from its ly- <lb/>ing ſtill only, and the looſneſs of its Parts reſol- <lb/>ved alſo
          into Serum, which ſeems at laſt to be the <lb/>true firſt Principle of the whole Maſs of
          Blood. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>95. The Serum being long kept in a moderate <lb/>warm and moiſt Air, from lying
          ſtill, and the <lb/>looſneſs of its Texture is reſolved into a thinner, <lb/>lighter, and
          more tranſparent Liquid. Which is <lb/>more ſo, according to the Time it hath been de-
          <lb/>prived of Motion, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>96. The whole Blood by means of a ſmall <lb/>Heat, little more than what is
          healthful, and of <lb/>little exhalations, runs together into a ſolid Maſs <lb/>ſeparable
          with a Knife, not reſolvable by Water, <lb/>Salt, Oyl nor Spirits. And the ſame peculiar
          <lb/>ſort of Concretion will befal the Blood by a de- <lb/>gree of Heat juſt mentioned
          tho' convey'd into it <lb/>by moiſt Bodies. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>97. The redneſs and the running together of <lb/>the Serum In the Blood is owing to
          the Action of <lb/>the Veſſels and to the power of Circulation; as is <pb n="25"/>
          <lb/>ſhewn from the change of the Chyle, Milk and <lb/>Blood, and is confirmed by the
          Obſervations made <lb/>with Microſcopes. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>98. The increaſe of the Motion of the Blood <lb/>through the Veſſels, proceeds from
          the Heart's be- <lb/>ing oftner and ſtronger contracted. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>99. The Heart is oftner and ſtronger contract- <lb/>ed. <list>
            <item>1. When the Brain and its production the <lb/>little Brain are ſo ſtrongly preſſed
              as to ſend forth <lb/>too great a Quantity of the nervous Juice, as it <lb/>hapneth in
              the paſſions of the Mind or in Pains. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/>2. When the Heart it ſelf is irritated by occaſion- <lb/>ing the returning Blood
              through the Veins to run <lb/>quicker than uſual, being puſh'd on by rubbing <lb/>or
              the action of the Muſcles; or by ſome ſharp- <lb/>neſs being preſent in the Blood,
              whether aroma- <lb/>tic, ſaline, acid, alcali, purulent, ichorous, or <lb/>putrefied.
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>100. The Motion of the Blood being increaſed <lb/>in the Veſſels, occaſions the Blood
          to run ſtronger <lb/>upon and towards the Veſſels, which are to re- <lb/>ceive the ſame; a
          ſtronger reſiſtance of the Veſ- <lb/>ſels againſt the Blood; a ſtrong preſſure of the
          <lb/>Blood upon the ſides of the Veſſels, a violent rub- <lb/>bing of the Veſſels and the
          Blood againſt each o- <lb/>ther; a ſtrong rubbing of the ſeveral parts of the <lb/>Blood
          among each other; a greater Heat of the <lb/>whole, a drying up of the Blood from the
          diſſipa- <lb/>ting of the moſt thin watry Particles; a growing <lb/>Toughneſs of the ſame,
          eaſily ſettling and inflam- <lb/>ing; a breaking of the Blood into ſharp and vola-
          <lb/>til Salts and Oyls; The Mouths of the Veſſels at <lb/>their beginnings becoming
          wider, a forcing of the <pb n="26"/>
          <lb/>thickned Juices into the ſmaller Veſſels: The fol- <lb/>lowing Obſtructions of the
          ſame hereupon, De- <lb/>ſtructions, Inflammations, converſion into Pus, <lb/>Gangrenes,
          Mortifications, or if in glandular Parts, <lb/>into hardneſſes called Schirri, and
          innumerable <lb/>more Ills, which follow from all theſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>101. The increaſe of the Circulation therefore <lb/>is known from its Cauſes (99.)
          and its Effects <lb/>(100.) but chiefly from a quick Pulſe, and a hard <lb/>beating of the
          Artery; from a ſwift and laborious <lb/>breathing, and a great Heat. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>102. The Remedies therefore for to reſtrain <lb/>the too violent Motion of the
          Humours are the <lb/>ſame, as are able and muſt needs leſſen the too <lb/>frequent and
          ſtrong Contraction of the Heart. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>103. Whereof the firſt regard the Mind, the <lb/>latter the bodily Faculties. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>104. The firſt are ſuch as will allay and mode- <lb/>rate great Paſſions by
          reaſoning, by either cauſing <lb/>contrary Paſſions or Diverſions from the ſame by a-
          <lb/>ny Method. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>105. The latter operates by cauſing the Muſ- <lb/>cles to keep quiet, by looſening
          the Veins in all <lb/>ſuch Manners as have been mentioned (54.) by <lb/>aſſwaging the
          ſharpneſs of any kind with proper <lb/>Remedies, either diluting or blunting the edges of
          <lb/>it (66, 67, 68.) and by removing the Cauſes of <lb/>Pain. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Of Diſtempers from the defects of Circulation and <lb/>a <hi rend="roman"
            >Plethora</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>106. The Diſeaſes proceeding from the defects <lb/>of circulation in the Humours, are
          very near the <pb n="27"/>
          <lb/>ſame with ſuch as were occaſioned by the ſponta- <lb/>neous ſtopping of the ſame from
          (58, to 80.) ſo <lb/>that one muſt look back to them for to know them <lb/>and to obtain a
          Cure. And from all theſe one <lb/>may eaſily underſtand what is meant by a <hi
            rend="italic">Pletho- <lb/>ra</hi>, and know its Cauſes, Effects, Signs, and Re-
          <lb/>medies, chiefly if the following Things be well <lb/>minded, <list>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>α. A Plethora is a greater quantity of well con- <lb/>ditioned Blood, than what
              will undergo thoſe <lb/>Changes, which in Life are unavoidable, unleſs <lb/>Diſtempers
              intervene, and diſturbs them. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>β. The ſame is created by every thing as ma- <lb/>keth a great Quantity of good
              Chyle and Blood, <lb/>and at the ſame time hindereth their attenuation,
              <lb/>conſumption and perſpiration through the Pores of <lb/>the Skin. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>γ. Hereto refer a great power of the Bowels <lb/>which are employed in the
              Chylification to ſtrain <lb/>themſelves, which is alſo in the Heart and Arte-
              <lb/>ries; and at the ſame time a looſer Texture in the <lb/>Veins and other ſmall
              Veſſels: Hereto contribute <lb/>alſo ſuch ſoft Aliments as are eaſily converted into
              <lb/>Chyle; much Sleep; an eaſie Mind; a reſt of the <lb/>Muſcles, a habit of
              Bleeding, whether naturally <lb/>or with the Launcet. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>δ. The Effects of a Plethora proceed altogether <lb/>from that ſort of inward
              Motion of the Blood and <lb/>Juices, which doth not come up to a Fermentati- <lb/>on,
              and which we call a <hi rend="italic">Rarefaction</hi>, and from <lb/>the Heat
              occaſioned thereby: From hence a Dila- <lb/>tation or a widening of the Blood and
              lymphatic <lb/>Arteries; the change and interruption of the Se- <pb n="28"/>
              <lb/>cretion; a compreſſion of all the Veins, both <lb/>them as carry back the Lympha,
              and ſuch as car- <lb/>ry the Blood; a ſtifling of what ſhou'd circulate;
              <lb/>Inflammations; a breaking of the Veſſels; Im- <lb/>poſthumes; Gangrenes and then
              Death. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>ε. So that it is eaſie to know when this Diſeaſe <lb/>is preſent, and to foreſee
              the Effects of it. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>ζ. The Cure is performed, by letting of Blood; <lb/>Exerciſe and Waking; by a
              more ſharp Dyet af- <lb/>ter due Evacuations; and leaving them off gradu- <lb/>ally.
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Diſeaſes the leaſt Compound, Obſtructions and <lb/>Wounds. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>107. An Obſtruction is the ſhutting up of a <lb/>Canal, and denying the Paſſage to a
          Liquid which <lb/>ſhould go and flow through the ſame; whether it <lb/>be vital, found or
          depraved; proceeding from the <lb/>ſize of the Matter that ſhould paſs, exceeding the
          <lb/>Cavity of the Canal through which it ſhould be <lb/>let paſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>108. Which may again proceed from the nar- <lb/>rowneſs of the Veſſel, the bigneſs of
          the preſent- <lb/>ing Body, or both happening together. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>109. The Veſſel may become too narrow if out- <lb/>wardly preſſed; if it contracts it
          ſelf, or if the <lb/>ſides of the Veſſel grow thicker. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>110. The bulk of the ſmall Bodies grows too <lb/>big, either by the ſlymineſs of the
          Fluid, or by <lb/>having miſtaken their Paſſage. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>111. When theſe two meet together, the Ob- <lb/>ſtruction is the more obſtinate and
          difficult to re- <lb/>move. </p>
        <pb n="29"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>112. The Veſſels may be preſſed outwardly. <list>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>1. By a neighbouring Tumor from fulneſs, <lb/>which is inflamed, full of Matter,
              Schirrous, <lb/>Cancerous, Pituitous, pufft up in the form of a <lb/>Bottle, from a
              diſtended Arterie called <hi rend="italic">Aneuriſma</hi>, <lb/>or a Vein called <hi
                rend="italic">Varix</hi>; by knobs in the Bones or <lb/>Calloſities, or ſome Slyme
              or Stones. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>2. By ſome hard and ſolid Parts, ſuch as Bones <lb/>being broke, disjointed,
              diſtorted, or drawn out <lb/>of their natural Poſition, and ſo preſſing upon the
              <lb/>neighbouring ſofter Parts, as muſt give way. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/> 3. By any Cauſe, which draws the Veſſels too <lb/>much and makes 'em longer,
              whether it be a Tu- <lb/>mour, or the preſſure of a part out of its due Po-
              <lb/>ſition, or any external pulling Agent. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>4. By external Cauſes out of the Body, ſuch <lb/>are too narrow Cloaths, Girdles,
              the weight of <lb/>the Body reſting too much upon one Part, Liga- <lb/>tures, <hi
                rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> Here alſo belongs the moving, the <lb/>rubbing, the
              embracing of other Bodies too eager- <lb/>ly with ſome particular Part. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/> 113. When that Contraction which is peculi- <lb/>ar to each Veſſel is increaſed,
          chiefly ſuch as have <lb/>winding Fibres, and alſo ſuch as have them long, <lb/>the cavity
          of the Veſſel is made narrow, and pro- <lb/>ceeds <list>
            <item>1. From any cauſe which doth increaſe the <lb/>elaſtick power of the Fibre, of the
              Veſſel and of <lb/>the Bowel, mentioned (31, 36, 40, 50, 51.) </item>
            <item>
              <lb/> 2. From a Tumour of them leſſer Veſſels, out of <lb/>which the ſides of the
              large ones and the Canals <lb/>are form'd, when too much filled. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>3. From the leſſening of the Cauſe, which ex- <lb/>tends the Veſſels, whether it
              be emptineſs or <pb n="30"/>
              <lb/><choice>
                <corr>ſloathfulneſs</corr>
                <sic>fulneſs</sic>
              </choice>: From whence follows that the Canals be- <lb/>ing cut aſſunder will ſoon
              ſtop the running out of <lb/>their proper Fluid. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>114. The thickneſs is encreaſed in the very <lb/>Membrane of the Veſſel, <list>
            <item>1. By any Tumour <lb/>(112. No. 1.) in any of thoſe Veſſels whoſe uni- <lb/>on and
              contexture makes up the Membrane. </item>
            <item> 2. By <lb/>Calloſities grown there; whether cartilagineous, <lb/>membranous or
              even oſſeous (51.) </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>115. The bulk of the fluid Parts is increaſed to <lb/>that Degree as to be incapable
          of flowing, <list>
            <item>1. Ei- <lb/>ther by changing their ſpherical Figure into ano- <lb/>ther,
              preſenting it ſelf in a larger Size to the <lb/>Mouth of the Canal. </item>
            <item>2. Or by the joining toge- <lb/>ther into one ſeveral, which were ſingle before.
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>116. The Figure is chiefly altered, when that <lb/>even preſſure of the ſmalleſt
          Particles, now left to <lb/>their own elaſticity, which uſed to work and to <lb/>preſs
          from all ſides together and equally, is ceaſ- <lb/>ed; that is when Motion is become
          languid, or <lb/>the Veſſel looſened, or the quantity of the Liquid <lb/>is leſſened. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>117. The ſmall Particles run into one, by too <lb/>great a reſt, cold, froſt, drying,
          heat, a violent <lb/>circular Motion, and the preſſing of a ſtrong Veſ- <lb/>ſel; by an
          acid, auſtere, ſpirituous or abſorbing <lb/>Coagulum, by a Slyme or an Oyl. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>118. The Particles of Fluids having miſtaken <lb/>their Paſſage are ſtopt, when a
          ſmall Body of them <lb/>runs into the dilated Mouth of a Canal, the Extre- <lb/>mities
          whereof they cannot paſs. This Dilatati- <lb/>on is chiefly created by a fullneſs, an
          increaſed <lb/>Motion, a rarefaction of the Fluid, a relaxation <pb n="31"/>
          <lb/>of the Veſſel; and moſt of all, if theſe have pre- <lb/>ceeded, the contraries moſt
          commonly follow ſoon <lb/>after. <hi rend="italic">Which is the moſt immediate Cauſe of
            all <lb/>Colds</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>119. Hence are manifeſt the cauſes and nature <lb/>of all Obſtructions whatſoever. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>120. Which happening in a living Body hin- <lb/>dreth the Paſſage of ſuch Matters as
          ſhou'd flow <lb/>on; they ſtop as many as runs in upon 'em; they <lb/>receive their ſhock;
          the thinneſt Parts are ſquees'd <lb/>out; the thicker run into one Maſs; the Veſſel is
          <lb/>extended, dilated, made thinner, diſſolv'd; the <lb/>ſtagnating Liquor is thickned;
          the function de- <lb/>pending from the regular flux of the Liquid is de- <lb/>ſtroy'd; the
          Veſſels which were to be ſupply'd <lb/>from thence run empty, and dry; the Veſſels are
          <lb/>leſs and leſs able to tranſmit their Liquids: The <lb/>quantity of Liquids in the
          Veſſels free from this <lb/>Obſtruction increaſes, and ſo doth the quickneſs <lb/>of the
          Motion; and conſequently produces all the <lb/>Ills which may be occaſioned thereby. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>121. Hence according to the difference of the <lb/>Veſſel obſtructed and of the
          Matter cauſing the <lb/>Obſtruction do thoſe Effects (120.) appear accom- <lb/>panied by
          different Symptoms. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>122. In arterious Blood-Veſſels are produced <lb/>Inflammations of the firſt Kind: In
          the lymphatic <lb/>Arteries dilated Inflammations of the ſecond Kind; <lb/>in the larger
          Lymphatics pituitous Swellings; in <lb/>the leſſer Lymphatics Pains without any apparent
          <lb/>Tumour; and different are the Effects of Obſtru- <lb/>ctions in the producers of Fat,
          in the Veſſels of the <lb/>Bones, of the Marrow, of the Nerves, and of Choler. </p>
        <pb n="32"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>123. So that whoever knows what has been <lb/>ſaid from 107, to <choice>
            <corr>123.</corr>
            <sic>723.</sic>
          </choice> of the nature, the mat- <lb/>ter, the cauſes and effects of Obſtructions, he
          <lb/>cannot be ignorant of the Signs of an approaching <lb/>or already preſent Obſtruction
          and the Effects <lb/>thereof. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>124. And if once he knows the different Sorts <lb/>thereof, it will not be very
          difficult for him to <lb/>find out the proper Cure and the Means thereof. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>125. For that Obſtruction which ariſeth from <lb/>an external Preſſure (112.)
          requireth the remo- <lb/>ving of whatever is the cauſe of that Preſſure, <lb/>which, were
          it poſſible, muſt be taken from its <lb/>Deſcription to follow hereafter. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>126. But that, which ariſeth from the increaſ- <lb/>ed contraction of the Fibres, is
          known from the <lb/>Signs, which ſhew the contraction of the Bowel, <lb/>of the Veſſel and
          of the Fibre (34, 36, 40, 50, <lb/>53.) And ſo is that known, where that Contracti-
          <lb/>on proceeds from the ſecond Cauſe (113. No. 2.) <lb/><hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
          Tumours in the ſmall Veſſels which conſti- <lb/>tute the Membrane of the Canal; and alſo
          the lat- <lb/>ter, which is occaſioned by a contracting of the <lb/>Veſſel, after a great
          loſs of Blood or Fluid proper <lb/>to the Veſſel. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>127. This Obſtruction deſcribed (113, 126.) <lb/>is cured, <list>
            <item>1. By ſuch Remedies as will correct the <lb/>too great contraction of the Fibre,
              of the Veſſel <lb/>and of the Entrail. (35, 36, 38, 54, 55.) </item>
            <item>2. <lb/>Chiefly if they can be applied to the very Part af- <lb/>fected, and their
              Virtue communicated; and chiefly <lb/>by Steams, Fomentations, Bathings, Liniments,
              <lb/>or Plaiſters. </item>
            <item>3. By ſuch helps, as will empty the <pb n="33"/>
              <lb/>Veſſels of the Membranes, when too much diſ- <lb/>tended and fill'd. Whereto
              belong all Evacua- <lb/>tions in general, but chiefly ſuch as can be <lb/>applied to
              theſe ſame Veſſels; Such are the <lb/>looſening, diluting, reſolving, attenuating,
              clean- <lb/>ſing, evacuating Medicines. </item>
            <item>4. By ſuch as are <lb/>capable to melt and diſſolve a Calloſity already
              <lb/>created. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>128. But this latter Sort of Obſtruction can <lb/>ſeldom if ever be cured. Emollient
          and opening <lb/>Medicines are the Chief: from whence it follows <lb/>that the Animal
          cannot avoid dying; And that it <lb/>is matter of very great difficulty to procure a long
          <lb/>Life even with the help of the moſt proper and <lb/>beſt applied Medicines. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>129. When the Fluid is become incapable of <lb/>paſſing through, which proceeds from
          the loſs of <lb/>its Spherical Figure, it is known from looking <lb/>into the Cauſes
          thereof (116.) for they are moſt- <lb/>ly apparent to the Eye, or the helping Glaſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><choice>
            <corr>130.</corr>
            <sic>139.</sic>
          </choice> This Obſtruction is cured with the help <lb/>of ſuch Remedies as do reſtore that
          Figure to the <lb/>Fluid; which are ſuch as increaſe their Motion <lb/>through the Veſſels
          and Bowels; Such are al- <lb/>ſo moſt all ſtimulating and ſlrengthning Medi- <lb/>cines;
          And laſtly, an increaſe of the animal <lb/>Motion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>131. And whereas the too great thickneſs of <lb/>the Liquid, and its tenacity
          proceeds from ſo <lb/>many and ſo widely different Cauſes, (117.) They <lb/>require
          therefore different Methods of Cure, and <lb/>different Remedies according to their
          Nature; <lb/>which difference being enquired into in each par- <pb n="34"/>
          <lb/>ticular Diſeaſe, will indicate its proper and pecu- <lb/>liar Remedies and
          Applications. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>132. But the thickneſs of the Liquids in ge- <lb/>neral is remedied, <list>
            <item>1. By inducing an alternative <lb/>Motion in the Veſſels. </item>
            <item>2. By diluting. </item>
            <item>3. By <lb/>an attenuating Liquor being carried into it, mix- <lb/>ed and moved
              with it. </item>
            <item>4. By fetching out or <lb/>evacuating the Cauſe which did coagulate, and
              <lb/>thicken. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>133. Thoſe things will bring an alternative <lb/>Motion in the Veſſel, <list>
            <item>1. Which do temperate <lb/>whatever occaſioned the too great diſtenſion of
              <lb/>the Veſſel. Such is Bleeding. </item>
            <item>2. Which do <lb/>ſtrengthen the Veſſels (28, 29. 45, 46, 47. 49.) </item>
            <item>
              <lb/>3. Rubbings, and the Motion of the Muſcle. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/>4. Stimulating Medicines. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>134. <hi rend="italic">Diluting</hi> may be performed by warm <lb/>Water chiefly if
          drank in great Quantity, if in- <lb/>jected by way of Glyſters, or the Steams thereof
          <lb/>be received, if applied outwardly to the Part, and <lb/>as much as poſſible be drove
          to the Part where <lb/>the Obſtruction is, and wants to be removed. <lb/>Hereto belong
          ſuch as turn another way, as draw <lb/>on, and puſh forwards. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>135. The following Things do <hi rend="italic">Attenuate</hi>, <list>
            <item>1. Water. </item>
            <item>2. Common Salt, Sal Gemm, Ar- <lb/>moniac, Nitre, Borax, fix'd or volatil Alcali. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/>3. Natural Soaps conſiſting of an Alcali and an <lb/>Oyl; or compound, ſooty,
              volatil, fix'd, or Cho- <lb/>ler it ſelf. </item>
            <item>4. Mercurial Preparations. Which <lb/>may be convey'd to the place affected, by
              ſuch <lb/>as turn the Humor another way, ſuch as draw <lb/>and puſh towards it.
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <pb n="35"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>136. The Coagulating and Thickning Cauſe <lb/>is fetch'd out by drawing of another
          Liquor <lb/>whoſe drawing power is ſtronger. Thus the <lb/>Acids work upon the Alcalis,
          the Oyls upon the <lb/>Alcalis, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> which are chiefly found out
          from <lb/>Experiments in Chymie. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>137. But when a Liquid is got into a wrong <lb/>and ſtrange place, and cannot clear
          its Paſſage, <lb/>and ſo forms Obſtructions, then are many and <lb/>very malignant
          Diſeaſes created; ſo that this Ill <lb/>ought and deſerveth to be moſt carefully minded. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>138. We know this to be the Caſe. <list>
            <item>
              <lb/>1. If we <lb/>are acquainted that its Cauſes (118.) have pre- <lb/>ceeded, which
              are generally eaſily noted. </item>
            <item>2. That <lb/>the Contrary Operations have ſoon after followed. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/>3. If we ſee its Effects very diſtinctly, as ſet down <lb/>(120, 121, 122.)
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>139. And it is alſo eaſie to foretel what will <lb/>be the Conſequence of this Ill,
          if we look back <lb/>to 120. to 123. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>140. The Cure is perform'd, <list>
            <item>1. By puſhing <lb/>the obſtructed Matter backwards by a retrograde <lb/>Motion
              into the larger Veſſels. </item>
            <item>2. By reſolving <lb/>the ſame. </item>
            <item>3. relaxing the Veſſel. </item>
            <item>4. or ſup- <lb/>purating the Matter it ſelf. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>141. This Matter may be brought back again <lb/>from its Priſon, <list>
            <item>1. By evacuating the Liquor, <lb/>which is preſſing in upon it and driving it in
              <lb/>cloſer; <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> a large, and ſudden opening of a <lb/>Vein,
              which will occaſion a Straining in the ve- <lb/>ry Veſſel obſtructed, and ſo the
              Matter will be <lb/>puſh'd back again. </item>
            <item>2. By Rubbings from the <lb/>Extremities to the Mouth of the Veſſel. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <pb n="36"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>142. It may be reſolved by Medicines named <lb/>above from (133. to 137.) </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>143. The Veſſels may be made looſer by means <lb/>mentioned in (35, 36. 54.) </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>144. Of the Manner of promoting Suppura- <lb/>tion, or the turning into Pus or
          Matter, we ſhall <lb/>ſpeak more at large when we come to treat of <lb/>Inflammations.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Of Wounds in General. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>145. A Wound is the Separation of the Union <lb/>of ſoft Parts by hard and ſharp
          Bodies. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>146. The ſenſible and mechanical Cauſe there- <lb/>fore is the hardneſs, the
          ſharpneſs, and the mo- <lb/>tion of the wounding Inſtrument. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>147. The Receiver muſt be a ſoft Part, conſe- <lb/>quentIy a knot or contexture of
          Blood-veſſels, <lb/>Lymphatics, ſuch as are adipous, nervous, mem- <lb/>branous,
          tendinous, and laſtly full of ſuch little <lb/>Bladders as are made of them. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>148. In which Receiver the Inſtrument cauſes <lb/>a Separation of what was united,
          and the ſhed- <lb/>ing of the contain'd Liquids. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>149. So that it diſturbs the Actions, which <lb/>depend from the integrity, wholeneſs
          of thoſe <lb/>Parts, and from a determin'd Courſe of thoſe Li- <lb/>quors through the
          Veſſels. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>150. All Wounds therefore as invade ſuch <lb/>Parts, whereof the wholeneſs is
          neceſſary to make <lb/>Life ſubſiſt, are call'd <hi rend="italic">Mortal</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>151. Of theſe there are ſuch as occaſion Death <lb/>unavoidably. </p>
        <pb n="37"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>152. Others, if left to themſelves, occaſion <lb/>Death; But may ſo far be remedied
          by the Art <lb/>of Surgery, that the danger of Death ceaſeth. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>153. Laſtly, ſome Wounds may become or be <lb/>made mortal, which were not ſo of
          their own <lb/>nature when neglected, or when wrong Applica- <lb/>tions are made to 'em. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>154. According to the different Actions, which <lb/>were before performed by the
          whole and un- <lb/>wounded Parts, do ariſe the ſeveral other Effects <lb/>of Wounds, and
          acquire from thence their ſeve- <lb/>ral Names, which are ſeldom unknown to any <lb/>one
          acquainted with the Functions of the ſeveral <lb/>Parts of the ſound Body. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>155. Nor is the difference of Names, Forms, <lb/>and Effects of the ſeveral Wounds
          leſs, from the <lb/>different Cauſe or Weapon occaſioning or giving <lb/>the Wound, from
          the difference of its Shape, <lb/>manner of Aſſault, either by pointing, cutting,
          <lb/>hewing, or by moving to and fro; from the de- <lb/>gree of Strength in driving in and
          removing out of <lb/>the Wound, the time of its remaining there, and <lb/>the poiſonous
          quality of the ſame. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>156. Theſe again vary according to the diffe- <lb/>rence of each Part receiving the
          Wound, its hard- <lb/>neſs, ſoftneſs, connexion, ſituation, effect, the <lb/>ſeveral
          Liquids thereto flowing, and the great <lb/>change in its Shape. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>157. Though it is neceſſary to know exactly <lb/>well all the many and different
          Beginnings of it, <lb/>yet is there little occaſion to dwell here upon a <lb/>nice Hiſtory
          of its ſeveral Names. </p>
        <pb n="38"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>158. If a Wound is made in a healthy and <lb/>ſtrong Body, in a viſible place, not
          containing <lb/>any large Artery; nor very tendinous, the fol- <lb/>lowing Symptoms ariſe. <list>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>1. The Parts, between which the wounding <lb/>Inſtrument has been thruſt, do part
              gradually <lb/>more and more aſunder, notwithſtanding the In- <lb/>ſtrument be
              removed; unleſs it be a very ſmall <lb/>puncture. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>2. The Blood runs out at firſt with Violence, <lb/>and ſtops afterwards gradually
              of it ſelf. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>3. Then grows a bloody cruſt in at the hollow <lb/>of the Wounds. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>4. And a thin Liquor, ſomewhat reddiſh and <lb/>faint-colour'd flows out of the
              ſeparated Fibres. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>5. Now begin the Lips of the Wound to grow <lb/>red, hot, painful, to ſwell and
              to turn back. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>6. At the ſame time the Patient grows ſen- <lb/>ſible of a little Fever, with
              heat and thirſt. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>7. About the third or fourth Day, ſooner or <lb/>later begin to appear in the
              Wound a ſticking Li- <lb/>quor, white, fattiſh, even, which we call <hi rend="italic"
                >Pus</hi> or <lb/><hi rend="italic">Matter</hi>. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>8. At the ſame time you find the redneſs, heat, <lb/>pain, ſwelling, the drawing
              or turning of the <lb/>Lips, and the Fever either to ceaſe entirely or <lb/>to relent. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>9. And by degrees the hollow of the Wound <lb/>is fill'd with growing Fleſh from
              the bottom <lb/>upwards, and from the circumference to the Cen- <lb/>ter; the Brims
              getting together by means of a <lb/>white, bluiſh, ſoft and even Subſtance. </item>
            <pb n="39"/>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>10. Laſtly, the Wound is dry'd up, and co- <lb/>vered over with a Scar. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>159. If an Artery (not of a very large Dia- <lb/>meter) not too near the Heart, is
          entirely cut <lb/>aſunder, it ſhrinks back and hides it ſelf among <lb/>its neighbouring
          Solids, and ſo ſtops up its own <lb/>ſelf, and then follow all what has been mention-
          <lb/>ed (158.) juſt now. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>160. If the ſame is wounded a-croſs but not <lb/>entirely cut aſunder, the Wound is
          made wider <lb/>through the pulling of the Fibres, from whence <lb/>an inceſſant Loſs of
          Blood, and after that is ſtop- <lb/>ped, an <hi rend="italic">Aneuriſme</hi> from the
          thinneſs of the Skin <lb/>growing over the Wound, which for that Reaſon <lb/>gives way,
          and is extended into the ſhape and <lb/>nature of a Bag. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>161. If a large Arterie be entirely cut aſunder, <lb/>there follows an inceſſant
          bleeding until Swoon- <lb/>ing or Death; the Parts below the Arterie fall <lb/>away, and
          are at laſt conſumed by an ugly but <lb/>ſlow Gangrene. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>162. If any Nerves be entirely cut aſunder <lb/>they ſhrink back, hide themſelves,
          draw the <lb/>Branches that are a little above the Wound, <lb/>ſtretch them, create in the
          neighbouring Parts <lb/>Obſtructions and Pain; and as to the Parts be- <lb/>low the Wound,
          they become inſenſible, immove- <lb/>able, and waſte away. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>163. Nerves that are prick'd or half cut aſun- <lb/>der, creite Pains which at firſt
          are ſometimes dull <lb/>and ſometimes very quick and acute; firſt in the <lb/>wounded
          place it ſelf, and then in all the adjoin- <lb/>ing and neighbouring Nerves, from hence
          Heats, <pb n="40"/>
          <lb/>Tumours, Redneſſes widely ſpreading, Fevers, <lb/>a Delirium, Convulſions, an
          Inflammation; an <lb/>opening of the inflamed Part with a running <lb/>of a ſharp, thin,
          and often copious Serum; af- <lb/>terwards follow the loſs of Feeling, a Stiffneſs, <lb/>a
          Drying up, and Unmoveableneſs of the Part, <lb/>or otherways a Gangrene and Death. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>164. All which (162, 163.) with very little <lb/>difference happen in the wounded
          Tendons. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>165. And the Membranes are ſubject to the <lb/>ſame Diſaſters, as being moſtly
          Compounds and <lb/>Products of Nerves and Tendons. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>166. What Lymphatic Veſſels, ſuch as con- <lb/>tain Fat, and the Veins and ſmall
          Bladders do <lb/>undergo in Wounds, what they will occaſion, is <lb/>eaſily underſtood
          from the Laws of Circulation, <lb/>and by conſidering the nature of their Neigh-
          <lb/>bourhood. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>167. If the Wound lyeth open to view, it is <lb/>ſoon known to be, and its Nature is
          alſo ſoon <lb/>underſtood. <list>
            <item>1. By the Sight it ſelf, having re- <lb/>moved what covered it, and having ſtop'd
              the <lb/>running and loſs of Blood. </item>
            <item>2. By having an Ana- <lb/>tomical Knowledge of the neighbouring Parts. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>168. But the preſence of a hidden Wound <lb/>and its Nature are known, <list>
            <item>1. From Anatomical <lb/>Knowledge, from the poſition the Patient was in, <lb/>when
              he receiv'd the Wound, from the manner <lb/>and ſtrength wherewith it was given. </item>
            <item>2. From <lb/>the defect of the Function following the Wound. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/>3. From the diſcharge of the Wound, whether <lb/>within or without the Body. </item>
            <item>4. From the conſe- <lb/>quent Symptoms, ſuch as Pain, Hiccough, Con- <lb/>vulſion,
              Tumour, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <pb n="41"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>169. From knowing (167, 168.) it is eaſie <lb/>to foretell the Events. <list>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>1. Whether the wounded Patient will live or <lb/>die. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>2. Whether the Cures be poſſible or impoſſi- <lb/>ble, entire or only in part. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>3. Whether the Cure be eaſie, or difficult, like <lb/>to be long or ſhort. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>4. What effects from the Wound will remain <lb/>after the Cure; whether a
              waſting, numneſs, ſtiff- <lb/>neſs and unmoveableneſs, the Figure ſpoil'd. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>170. Unavoidable Death from a Wound fol- <lb/>lows from five Effects, and
          conſequently before a <lb/>Jury ſuch muſt be called mortal Wounds, <list>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>1. As cut off the Influx of the nervous Juice <lb/>from the hind Brain to the
              Heart, <list>
                <item>α. The <lb/>Wounds of the little or hind Brain called <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cerebel-<lb/>lum</hi>, and ſuch of the Brain as are deep enough to <lb/>inflict
                  a great Wound in the long marrow <hi rend="italic">Medulla <lb/>oblongata</hi>. </item>
                <item>β. The Blood-Veſſels within the Skul <lb/>being broke with an effuſion of
                  Blood, which kills <lb/>either by preſſing hard or by putrifying there, <lb/>when
                  it cannot be taken out by means of Trepan- <lb/>ning by reaſon of the Place where
                  that Operation <lb/>cannot be performed; which are chiefly the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Fon-<lb/>tanelle</hi> of the Head in Children; the Sutures, the
                  <lb/>ſuperciliary Sinus, the Temples, the inferior parts <lb/>of the Head, <hi
                    rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
                </item>
                <item>γ. Deep Wounds in the Mar- <lb/>row of the Back-bone near the Neck. </item>
                <item>δ. And <lb/>laſtly, ſuch as cut off the Nerves of the Heart, <lb/>call'd <hi
                    rend="italic">Nervi Cardiaci</hi>. </item>
              </list>
            </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>2. Such as occaſion the Blood of the Heart to <lb/>ruſh forth through the
              Orifices of its pierc'd Ven- <pb n="42"/>
              <lb/>tricles: So that all Wounds of the Heart deep e- <lb/>nough to penetrate into
              either of its Ventricles are <lb/>mortal. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>3. Such as turn off the Blood from the Heart, <lb/>from the Brain and little
              Brain, either into the <lb/>Cavities of the Body or out of the Body it ſelf, <lb/>and
              cannot be healed becauſe of their Situation. <lb/>Such are the large Wounds in the
              Lungs, Liver, <lb/>Spleen, Kidneys, Pancreas, Meſentery, Stomach <lb/>and Guts; of the
              Womb in pregnant Women, of <lb/>the Bladder near its large Arteries; of the Aorta,
              <lb/>the Carotick and vertebral Arteries, and other Ar- <lb/>teries and Veins of the
              like Importance and difficult <lb/>Acceſs. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>4. Such as intercept Reſpiration or Breathing <lb/>intirely, as the cutting of
              the Larinx when the <lb/>ſeparated Pipe is withdrawn; large Wounds of the
              <lb/>Bronchia, of both the Cavities of the Cheſt let- <lb/>ting in the Air, of the
              Diaphragme penetrating <lb/>through both ſides of the Mediaſtinum of the <lb/>Cheſt,
              or cutting its Sinews aſunder. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>5. Such as hinder the Motion of the Chyle to- <lb/>wards the Heart; as the
              cutting through of the <lb/>Gullet, large Wounds in the Stomach, of the thin <lb/>Guts
              chiefly, if cut through at the Beginnings; a <lb/>Wound in the <hi rend="italic"
                >Thoracick duct</hi> or Cyſtern of the <lb/>Chyle. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>171. Wounds, of their own Nature mortal, but <lb/>curable by Art, are as follows, and
          may be re- <lb/>ported as ſuch: <list>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>1. Wounds of the Brain that are com'attable by <lb/>trepanning. </item>
            <pb n="43"/>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>2. Wounds of large Arteries or Veins ſituated ſo as <lb/>to admit the Hand and
              Application of the Surgeon. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>3. Wounds of Bowels, where the Hand and <lb/>Medicines may not only be applied
              but alſo re- <lb/>tained long enough to heal them. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>4. Such as kill by letting out their Liquids in- <lb/>to ſuch Cavities from
              whence they may be taken <lb/>out without endangering Life; as the Cheſt, the
              <lb/>lower Belly, the Ureters, Bladder and ſome <lb/>Wounds of the Guts. <hi
                rend="italic">N. B.</hi>
              <q rend="diple">A Cure of this <lb/>laſt mentioned was very lately per- <lb/>formed by
                a Surgeon <note place="inline" n="*" rend="italic size(0.75)">* Brownhill. </note>
                of St. <hi rend="italic">Anns</hi>
                <lb/>Pariſh, <hi rend="italic">Weſtminſter</hi>, on the Body of a Captain <lb/>of
                his Majeſty's Guards. </q>
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>172. One may foretell a Wound ſhall be mor- <lb/>tal, which was not ſuch of its own
          Nature, from <lb/>theſe Cauſes, <list>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>1. From omitting the cleanſing and taking out <lb/>of extravaſated Pus, from
              whence a Waſting; or <lb/>the leaving of extravaſated Blood in ſuch Cavities,
              <lb/>where it muſt needs putrify. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>2. From Errors committed in the Non-naturals; <lb/>of which ſee our Author's
              Inſtitutions at large, <lb/>lately made <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi>. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>3. From a neglect or a miſtake of the Surgeon. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>4. From the natural or ſickly Conſtitution of <lb/>the Patient. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>173. From theſe may be fetch'd Depoſitions of <lb/>Surgeons concerning Wounds, and
          judge of the <lb/>Time within which they'll prove mortal or kill <lb/>actually. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>174. Hence a Declaration may be made on <lb/>Wounds, and a probable Eſtimate given of
          the <lb/>Time of their mortality. </p>
        <pb n="44"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>175. But the different Symptoms (159, 159.) <lb/>as to their Cauſes are eaſily known
          to any one, <lb/>who underſtands how and with what Inſtrument <lb/>the vital and animal
          Functions are perform'd. <lb/>Look back to what has been premiſed of the Diſ- <lb/>eaſes
          of the Solids and Fluids. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>176. When the outward Coat of an Arterie <lb/>(the inward remaining entire) is either
          prick'd, <lb/>cut, bruiſed, drawn aſunder, or corroded, the <lb/>Arterie through the force
          of the Blood is dilated <lb/>and forms a Purſe or Bag, which by degrees will <lb/>grow to
          the bigneſs of an Egg; acquireth Sides <lb/>or Membranes, which at length grow callous;
          <lb/>the ſame beats ſtrong, in proportion to its Size; <lb/>ſhines with a reddiſh Colour;
          if ſqueezed it <lb/>diſappears, the Blood retiring into its natural <lb/>Channel the
          Arterie, and comes again when preſ- <lb/>ſing is diſcontinued; it makes its Arterie wider;
          <lb/>and the neighbouring Veſſels, by preſſing upon <lb/>'em, narrower: This is call'd <hi
            rend="italic">a true Aneuriſme</hi>
          <lb/>(160.) whereof the Cauſe, Signs, and Effects are <lb/>plainly diſcovered. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>177. If an Arterie is wounded by the ſame <lb/>Cauſes, and is not well enough
          conſolidated, the <lb/>ſame Effects will follow as in (176.) </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>178. When from the ſame Cauſes all the Coats <lb/>of an Arterie are broke at once,
          and let out its <lb/>Blood into the next extended Parts without void- <lb/>ing the ſame;
          there is ſoon made a Swelling from <lb/>the collection of the extravaſated Blood ſtill en-
          <lb/>creaſing without meaſure, which Swelling is ſoft, <lb/>hardly beating, the Skin
          livid, ſcarce giving way <lb/>when preſſed, ſoon rottening, and ſoon occaſion- <pb n="45"/>
          <lb/>ing a Gangrene of the adjacent Parts. This is <hi rend="italic">the <lb/>Spurious
            Aneuriſme</hi> (160.) whereof the Cauſe, <lb/>Signs and Effects are eaſily known from
          this ve- <lb/>ry Deſcription. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>179. Other effects from the cutting of a large <lb/>Artery are ſoon known out of the
          Phyſiology as <lb/>well as the Signs and Effects which appear im- <lb/>mediately upon the
          cutting of a Nerve aſunder, <lb/>(161, 162.) </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>180. But that we may have juſt and clear No- <lb/>tions whence the ſtupendous Effects
          proceed of <lb/>the prick'd or half-divided Nerves, as in (163, <lb/>164, 165.) We muſt
          conſider what follows, <lb/>fetch'd from the knowledge of Anatomy and the <lb/>Alimal
          Œconomy. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>181. Every Nerve that is viſible is a ſmall <lb/>bundle of leſs Nerves ty'd together
          by ſmall <lb/>Skins, Arteries, Veins, and interwoven Lym- <lb/>phatics, which afterwards
          are all covered over <lb/>with one common Membrane. Through all <lb/>theſe little Veſſels
          as make up the Nerve, there <lb/>flows continually a Liquor proper to each Chan- <lb/>nel,
          from the Heart, Brain, <hi rend="italic">Cerebellum</hi> and the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Medudulla Spinalis</hi>. All theſe have ever a pretty <lb/>ſtrong power of contracting
          themſelves, </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>182. Therefore the Parts of a Nerve entirely <lb/>cut aſunder, do ſhrink back from
          the place where <lb/>the Wound was given, towards the firm Parts <lb/>to which they are
          annexed; they hide them- <lb/>ſelves among the adjacent and ſurrounding Solids, <lb/>they
          are kept under by their preſſure, their Ori- <lb/>fices ſhut up together with thoſe of all
          its Veſſels; <lb/>ſo that no other damage follows than what was <lb/>ſaid in (162.) </p>
        <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="9"/>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="346"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
