<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: A letter to George Cheyne</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">A letter to George Cheyne, M. D. F.R.S. Shewing, the danger of laying
              down general rules to those who are not acquainted with animal oeconomy,
              &amp;c.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T38125</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T38125"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed: and sold by J. Graves, in St. James's-Street, J. Hooke,
                  over-against St. Dunstan's Church, in Fleet-Street, and F. Jefferies, in
                  Ludgate-Street, 1724.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1724</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="3"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="72"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107318565</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="General treatises"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="3"/>
    <body>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>An ornamented rectangular block. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>TO <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0) space">George Cheyne, <hi rend="italic">M. D.</hi>
        </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic size(2.0) space">FELLOW </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="space">OF THE </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="blackletter size(2.5) space">Royal Society. </hi>
      </head>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A horizontal line spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <salute rend="sc size(1.25) indent">
        <lb/>Sir, </salute>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(5)">I</hi>F any Thing in this <lb/>World, be worthy of <lb/>a wiſe Man's
        Care, <lb/>it is Health; and as <lb/>Mankind, cannot ſuf- <lb/>ficiently teſtify their
        Gratitude to <lb/>thoſe, who labour in the Practice <pb n="2"/>
        <lb/>of healing Diſeaſes, with Diligence, <lb/>Candour, and Judgment; ſo on <lb/>the other
        hand, they cannot enough <lb/>deteſt thoſe who ſet up for the <hi rend="italic">Art <lb/>of
          Healing</hi>, without any other Qua- <lb/>lification, but their <hi rend="italic"
          >Diploma</hi>, to Re- <lb/>commend them; and having nothing <lb/>in their view, but making
        or mend- <lb/>ing their Fortunes, neglect that <lb/>Knowledge, which is abſolutely ne-
        <lb/>ceſſary, to make their Practice Ho- <lb/>nourable and Succeſsful. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They who write Well and Ill, <lb/>on the Subject of Health, ought in <lb/>like-manner,
        to be ſet in oppoſtion <lb/>to one another, and as their Labours <lb/>tend to the
        Preſervation or Preju- <lb/>dice of Health, ſo ought they to <lb/>become the Objects of our
        Favour, <lb/>or Contempt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As all Mankind, are more or leſs <lb/>frail, they therefore ought to bear a <lb/>great
        deal from one anothers Folly; <lb/>and the trade of Scribling, among the <lb/>reſt of Men's
        folly's, may be ſo far <lb/>indulged, as not to be cenſured, ſo <pb n="3"/>
        <lb/>long as it continues harmeleſs and <lb/>innocent; but as ſoon as it ceaſes <lb/>to be
        ſo, it is every reaſonable Man's <lb/>duty, to endeavour to ſtop its tor- <lb/>rent, and
        divert as much as poſſibly <lb/>he can, the Miſchief it threatens. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If a Man imagines he can oblige <lb/>the World, by communicating ſome <lb/>thing
        uſeful; as he ought by no <lb/>means to ſuppreſs it, ſo what he <lb/>advances, ought to be
        attended with <lb/>the Reaſons that led him into his <lb/>Opinion; and theſe ſhou'd be of-
        <lb/>fered to the Conſideration of ſuch <lb/>only, whoſe application in that way <lb/>to
        which they tend, hath made them <lb/>Judges of their Sufficiency; and then <lb/>if his
        Arguments ſhou'd prove too <lb/>weak, to ſupport his Oppinion, no <lb/>other harm will
        enſue, but his Loſs <lb/>of Labour, and that ſhare of Praiſe, <lb/>which probably he might
        expect as <lb/>the Reward of it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But when a <hi rend="italic">Phyſician</hi> ſhall pre- <lb/>ſume, to lay down <hi
          rend="italic">Practical Rules</hi>, <lb/>to all Mankind without Diſtinction, <pb n="4"/>
        <lb/>for the Preſervation of Health; and if <lb/>theſe Rules ſhou'd prove pernicious
        <lb/>and deſtructive to it, People will be <lb/>apt to imagine, that he puts himſelf
        <lb/>upon a Level with theſe <hi rend="italic">Savages</hi>
        <lb/>on the Sea-coaſt, who ſet out falſe <lb/>Lights, to invite diſtreſſed <hi rend="italic"
          >Mariners</hi>
        <lb/>to their deſtruction; that they may <lb/>reap the Benefit of the Ship-wreck. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>You beſt know <hi rend="sc">Sir</hi>, what were <lb/>the Motives, that prompted you to
        <lb/>publiſh your <hi rend="italic">Eſſay of Health and <lb/>long Life</hi>, as you call it;
        but I <lb/>doubt, many will have Reaſon to <lb/>wiſh it had never appear'd; it is <lb/>now
        almoſt in every bodys hand, <lb/>and that ſeeming ſelf-deniedneſs in <lb/>your Preface, that
        Air of <hi rend="italic">Piety</hi> that <lb/>you put on, in almoſt every other <lb/>Period,
        will perſwade many to be- <lb/>lieve, ſo good a Man, wou'd never <lb/>publiſh a Book to
        pamper his Vani- <lb/>ty, and wou'd never pretend to the <lb/>Knowledge of any thing he was
        an <lb/>abſolute Stranger to; theſe Con- <lb/>ſiderations, will, I am affraid weigh
        <lb/>with many to their Diſtruction. </p>
      <pb n="5"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I intend by this to ſhow, that e- <lb/>very Attempt of this kind muſt be
        <lb/>fruitleſs, if not pernicious, by en- <lb/>couraging People to tamper with <lb/>their
        Conſtitutions, which they <lb/>cannot poſſibly regulate by any <lb/>General Rules. And if
        your Per- <lb/>formance proves, that your know- <lb/>ledge of the <hi rend="italic">Animal
          Oeconomy</hi>, is not <lb/>quite ſo extenſive as perhaps it ought <lb/>to be; you muſt not
        take it amiſs <lb/>if I point out a few of thoſe Paſ- <lb/>ſages, from whence that unhappy
        <lb/>Concluſion naturaly flows. If the <lb/>Reaſons I ſhall offer to this purpoſe, <lb/>are
        not ſufficient to make it appear, <lb/>they cannot hurt you; but on the <lb/>Contrary, if
        they happen to be juſt <lb/>and convincing, no good Man will <lb/>blame me for undeceiving
        People, <lb/>in what regards a thing, ſo eſſential <lb/>to their Well-being as Health. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I have no Inclination to trace you <lb/>thro' every thing that I think wrong <lb/>in
        this Performance, becauſe, beſide <lb/>the irkſome Employment of finding <pb n="6"/>
        <lb/>fault, that wou'd oblige me to write <lb/>a Book at leaſt as large as yours. I
        <lb/>ſhall endeavour therefore, to be as <lb/>ſhort as the Subject will allow me. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is a common Saying, as you <lb/>obſerve, that a Man paſt Forty, is <lb/>either a
        Fool, or a Phyſician; and <lb/>if it means any thing, it only im- <lb/>plys, that by ſo long
        experience, a <lb/>Man that is not a Fool, will know <lb/>what things have beſt agreed with
        <lb/>him; and his Reaſon will direct him <lb/>to continue the Uſe of them, till <lb/>ſome
        alteration in his Conſtitution <lb/>makes them hurtful; and when that <lb/>happens, he will
        find there is ſome- <lb/>thing elſe required to make a Man <lb/>a Phyſician, beſides living
        forty <lb/>Years in the World; for beſide <lb/>Diſeaſes, old Age will alter a Man's
        <lb/>Conſtitution, and bring on Symp- <lb/>toms, which he could have no expe- <lb/>rience
        of, when leſs advanced in <lb/>Years. Of what uſe then, can his <lb/>former Experience be to
        him, in Cir- <lb/>cumſtances he never was in before? </p>
      <pb n="7"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But let us ſuppoſe , that by forty <lb/>Years Experience, a Man may have
        <lb/>diſcover'd the proper Method he <lb/>ſhou'd follow, through all the dif- <lb/>ferent
        Stages and Accidents of Life, <lb/>to preſerve his Health, and prolong <lb/>his Days; yet
        this Method will only <lb/>be applicable to himſelf, and ſuch <lb/>Conſtitutions as exactly
        reſemble his <lb/>own, in every Circumſtance; and <lb/>ſuch another, perhaps will not be to
        <lb/>be found among all the reſt of Man- <lb/>kind. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="†">
        <lb/>You tell us <note place="margin" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† Page 4.</note>
        <q rend="diple">The Reflection <lb/>is not more common than juſt, <lb/>that he who lives
          Phyſicaly lives <lb/>Miſerably, the truth is too great <lb/>a nicety and exactneſs about
          e- <lb/>very minute Circumſtance that <lb/>may impare our Health, is ſuch <lb/>a Yoke and
          Slavery, as no Man <lb/>of a free and generous Spirit <lb/>wou'd ſubmit to; 'tis as the
            <hi rend="italic">Poet</hi>
          <lb/>expreſſes it, to dye for fear of <lb/>dying. </q>
      </p>
      <pb n="8"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If this had been the Effect of any <lb/>previous Reflection, or if you had
        <lb/>believ'd it, <hi rend="italic">Charity</hi> inclines me to <lb/>think, that you wou'd
        not have been <lb/>ſo induſtrious to contradict it, as <lb/>appears from your ſubſequent <hi
          rend="italic">Rules <lb/>of Health</hi>; (as you are pleaſed to call <lb/>them,) but have
        left Mankind to <lb/>act for the Benefit of their Health, <lb/>as Reaſon and Experience
        ſhould <lb/>dictate to them; and when they are <lb/>Indiſpos'd, to call in thoſe Aids that
        <lb/>are proper to give them Relief; I <lb/>mean ſuch Phyſicians, whoſe Skill <lb/>in the
          <hi rend="italic">Animal Oeconomy</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic">Ma- <lb/>teria
          Medica</hi>, hath render'd them <lb/>capable to judge of the Nature of a <lb/>Diſtemper,
        and to apply the pro- <lb/>per Means to remove it. I am ſure <lb/>every reaſonable Man is a
        better <lb/>Judge of what he ought to do, for <lb/>the Benefit of his Health, than any
        <lb/>Phyſician can be, who is not inti- <lb/>mately acquainted with all the Cir-
        <lb/>cumſtances of his Conſtitution. </p>
      <pb n="9"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When a Man has acquired a com- <lb/>petent Knowledge of the <hi rend="italic">Animal
          Oe- <lb/>conomy</hi>, and of the Power and Effi- <lb/>cacy of theſe Medicines, proper to
        <lb/>reſtore and preſerve Health, to ſuch <lb/>a Man, I believe it is poſſible to lay
        <lb/>down ſuch general Rules, and Di- <lb/>rections, as may enable him to prac- <lb/>tice
        the <hi rend="italic">Art of healing</hi>, with ſucceſs <lb/>and eaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But to pretend to direct Men ig- <lb/>norant of theſe things, how to go- <lb/>vern
        themſelves, to preſerve or re- <lb/>ſtore their Health, is equally reaſo- <lb/>nable, as if
        one ſhould give Direct- <lb/>ions to a blind Man, to go a long <lb/>Journey by himſelf,
        thro' ways that <lb/>he never cou'd poſſibly have any <lb/><hi rend="italic">Idea</hi> of,
        and where every ſtep out <lb/>of the way wou'd endanger if not <lb/>deſtroy his Life. For
        how ſhall Men <lb/>be able to adjuſt either the Kind or <lb/>Quantity of Diet or Medicine,
        that <lb/>may be neceſſary, to<choice>
          <corr> </corr>
          <sic/>
        </choice>Conſtitutions <lb/>they are Strangers to? How ſhall they <lb/>be able to judge for
        themſelves, of <pb n="10"/>
        <lb/>that Exerciſe, and Air, that is proper <lb/>for them, when they are unacquaint- <lb/>ed
        with the Nature of thoſe Symp- <lb/>toms, that can only enable them to <lb/>diſtinguiſh. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>You will perhaps ſay, that you <lb/>have acquainted them with theſe <lb/>Symptoms to
        which your Directions <lb/>are ſuitable; but may not a Perſon <lb/>be afflicted with any
        Symptoms you <lb/>can mention, and at the ſame time <lb/>have others, which wou'd make the
        <lb/>Method that might be proper to re- <lb/>move ſuch Symptoms, were they <lb/>alone,
        deſtructive to the Patient, <lb/>now they are complicated with o- <lb/>thers, which you
        cou'd not poſſibly <lb/>foreſee. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>What then muſt become of that <lb/>Perſon, who having theſe Symp- <lb/>toms you
        mention, follows your <lb/>Advice, and whoſe want of Know- <lb/>ledge will make him
        diſregard thoſe <lb/>other Symptoms that will make your <lb/>preſcription pernicious? </p>
      <pb n="11"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Many Attempts have been made <lb/>to lay down general Rules, for <lb/>Mankind without
        diſtinction, to pre- <lb/>ſerve their Health and prolong their <lb/>Lives; but theſe
        Productions never <lb/>obtain'd the End they aim'd at; be- <lb/>cauſe the Conſtitutions and
        Habits <lb/>of Mens bodies differ ſo much from <lb/>one another, that any general Rule
        <lb/>laid down to any number of Men <lb/>for this Purpoſe, muſt be deſtruct- <lb/>ive, at
        leaſt to the greateſt Part of <lb/>them, if they all comply with it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For if every Man, was exactly to <lb/>purſue that method to <hi rend="italic">Health
          and <lb/>long Life</hi>, that is proper for him to <lb/>follow, perhaps we ſhould not find
        <lb/>two in ten thouſand, exactly purſu- <lb/>ing the ſame Courſe, though their <lb/>End
        wou'd be all the ſame; ſo that <lb/>any general Rule enioyn'd to theſe <lb/>ten thouſand,
        wou'd but at beſt be <lb/>uſeful to two, and hurtful or de- <lb/>ſtructive to all the reſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It very rarely, or never happens, <lb/>that Diſeaſes, even of the ſame De- <pb n="12"/>
        <lb/>nomination, ever affected two Per- <lb/>ſons, in the ſame manner, in every
        <lb/>Symptom, and the Method of Cure <lb/>ought always to vary with the Symp- <lb/>toms. How
        then can you tell a Man, <lb/>after what manner he ſhou'd govern <lb/>himſelf in a Diſorder,
        when you <lb/>cannot poſſibly know, in what man- <lb/>ner he is to be affected with it? Or
        <lb/>tell how a Conſtitution ſhou'd be <lb/><choice>
          <corr/>
          <sic>be</sic>
        </choice>regulated, which you are altoge- <lb/>ther a Stranger to? And theſe va-
        <lb/>letudinary crazy Conſtutions, that <lb/>you addreſs your ſelf to, actually <lb/>labour
        under Diſtempers, or they <lb/>wou'd not be ſo; and perhaps there <lb/>are not two ſuch in
        all <hi rend="italic">England</hi>, <lb/>whoſe Complaints, and Conſtitu- <lb/>tions don't
        differ in many Circum- <lb/>ſtances. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>So infinite is the variety of Diſ- <lb/>eaſes and Conſtitutions, that the <lb/>beſt
        Phyſician in the World, can <lb/>only determine, for theſe he is inti- <lb/>mately
        acquainted with, and whoſe <lb/>Symptoms he himſelf hath examin'd, <pb n="13"/>
        <lb/>and cannot with any ſafety, de- <lb/>pend upon any thing , but the con- <lb/>viction of
        his own Senſes, to regu- <lb/>late his Practice by. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>What then muſt the Complexion <lb/>of your Merit be, who pretending <lb/>to point out
        the way to <hi rend="italic">Health and <lb/>long Life</hi>, lay down Rules for Man-
        <lb/>kind to follow, which perhaps will <lb/>never be uſeful to any, and may be <lb/>hurtful
        and deſtructive to all, who <lb/>regard your Advice? and the great- <lb/>er your Reputation
        as a Phyſician, <lb/>the worſe will be the Conſequences, <lb/>and conſequently the greater
        your <lb/>Guilt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Your Rules for Health, are all <lb/>of them, either ſuch as have been <lb/>known to all
        Mankind, ſince the <lb/>World began; or miſtaken Notions, <lb/>founded upon no Principles
        that <lb/>ever reaſon dictated. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When, or by whom was it ever <lb/>denied, or even ſo much as doubted <lb/>by the
        Thinking-Part of Mankind, <lb/>(and you tell us, you dont write <pb n="14"/>
        <lb/>to the Inſenſible) that Eating and <lb/>Drinking to exceſs, were deſtruct- <lb/>ive to
        Health; but then it muſt be <lb/>own'd, that no Body before you, <lb/>ever preſumed to
        determine the <lb/>Quantity of Meat and Drink, that <lb/>a Man ſhould take, and preſcribed
        <lb/>that quantity to every Body, with- <lb/>out diſtinction; this is indeed in- <lb/>tirely
        New, and I hope in Charity <lb/>to the reſt of Mankind, that you <lb/>are the only Man in
        being, capable <lb/>of laying down ſuch a Rule. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That a very great regard ought <lb/>to be had to the Conſtitution of the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Air</hi>, to reſtore and preſerve Health, <lb/>is a greater Truth than you
        ſeem to <lb/>be aware of; but then, it is as true, <lb/>that no one Conſtitution of <hi
          rend="italic">Air</hi>, will <lb/>agree with every habit of Body; <lb/>and a Phyſician
        muſt be intimately <lb/>acquainted with a Man's Conſtitu- <lb/>tion, before he can preſcribe
        a pro- <lb/>per Temperament of <hi rend="italic">Air</hi> for him to <lb/>live in. </p>
      <pb n="15"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>You affirm <note place="margin" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Pag. 46.</note>
        <q rend="diple quotes">That you have <lb/>conſtantly obſerved good Effects <lb/>from leaving
          off ſuddenly great <lb/>quantities of Wine and Fleſh- <lb/>meats too, by thoſe long
          accuſt- <lb/>omed to both </q>. I will not here <lb/>diſpute what you ſay is Fact; but
        <lb/>I ſhall beg leave to enquire a little <lb/>into the Arguments you give us, <lb/>to
        ſupport the Reaſonableneſs of <lb/>this Affertion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>You tell us <note place="margin" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† Page 45.</note>
        <q rend="diple quotes">That nothing is more <lb/>rediculous than the common Plea <lb/>for
          continuing in drinking on large <lb/>quantities of ſpirituous Liquours, <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">viz.</hi> Becauſe they have been ac- <lb/>cuſtom'd ſo to do, and they
          think <lb/>it dangerous to leave it off of a <lb/>ſudden, it were as reaſonable for
          <lb/>him that is fallen into the Fire <lb/>or Water to lie there, becauſe <lb/>of the
          Danger of removing him <lb/>ſuddenly </q>. But this Argument <lb/>of yours is to no
        Purpoſe, unleſs <lb/>you can prove, that a Perſeverance, <lb/>in that Life a Man has been
        accuſt- <pb n="16"/>
        <lb/>omed to, will as ſuddenly deſtroy <lb/>his Life, as lying in the Fire or Wa- <lb/>ter
        will; and your other Argument <lb/>is, <note place="margin" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† page
          45.</note>
        <q rend="diple">That no man was ever a- <lb/>fraid to forbear ſtrong Liquours <lb/>in an
          acute Diſtemper, what <lb/>quantity ſoever he might have <lb/>drank in his Health. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Here <hi rend="sc">Sir</hi>, you muſt give me leave <lb/>to inform you, that Diſeaſes
        and <lb/>Health, are Circumſtances, directly <lb/>oppoſite to one another, and what <lb/>may
        be proper and fit to be done in <lb/>the one, may by no means be ſafe, <lb/>or convenient in
        the other. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">e. g.</hi> In a continued Fever, where <lb/>Obſtructions prevail in
        moſt of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Capillary Veſſels</hi>, and the uſual diſ- <lb/>charges
        from the body, by inſenſi- <lb/>ble Perſpiration, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c</hi> Being Ob-
        <lb/>ſtructed, the larger and paſſable Veſ- <lb/>ſels, to which the circulating Fluid
        <lb/>is confin'd, are for that reaſon over- <lb/>charg'd, and to give a Perſon in this
        <lb/>Caſe, even that kind, and quantity <lb/>of meat and drink, that wou'd be <pb n="17"/>
        <lb/>necceſſary in a ſtate of Health to pre- <lb/>ſerve it wou'd increaſe the Diſtem-
        <lb/>per, by increaſing the quantity of <lb/>Fluid, in the paſſable or pervious
        <lb/>Veſſels. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In all theſe we call acute Caſes, <lb/>the circulating Fluid is not only con-
        <lb/>fined to a ſmaller number of Veſſels, <lb/>but there being a Check put to the
        <lb/>uſual Expence and Diſcharge from <lb/>it, by the ſeveral <hi rend="italic"
          >Emunctories</hi> of the <lb/>Body, which made the former ſup- <lb/>ply from eating and
        drinking in a <lb/>State of Health uſeful: <hi rend="italic">Temperance</hi>
        <lb/>therefore, whatever hath been a Man's <lb/>way of living, is not only ſafe, but
        <lb/>abſolutely neceſſary, till theſe Ob- <lb/>ſtructions which are the Diſeaſe, be
        <lb/>removed; and the ſeveral <hi rend="italic">Excretory's</hi>
        <lb/>are again qualified, to throw off the <lb/>Superfluities, from the Maſs of Blood.
        <lb/>Care muſt likewiſe be taken in theſe <lb/>Caſes, to dilute the Blood, and re- <lb/>lax
        the Fibres; and theſe Medicines <lb/>which can effect this, will diſſolve <lb/>the Union of
        the combin'd Particles, <pb n="18"/>
        <lb/>that obſtructed the <hi rend="italic">Capillary's</hi>, and <lb/>ſtood in the Way of
        the circulating <lb/>Fluid, or Extra-corporeal Secretions. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But if theſe diluteing Medicines, <lb/>which are convenient in this Caſe, <lb/>were
        given to one, where the Quan- <lb/>tity of Secretions, are to the Quan- <lb/>tity of Fluid
        in the Body, in that <lb/>juſt Proportion, that is neceſſary to <lb/>Health; they wou'd
        increaſe the <lb/>Secretions, deſtroy that neceſſary <lb/>Proportion, and beget Diſeaſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And if a Man in a good State of <lb/>Health, who has accuſtom'd himſelf <lb/>to eat and
        drink plentifully, ſhou'd <lb/>ſuddenly leave of that Method, and <lb/>betake himſelf to a
        ſpare Diet all at <lb/>once; the <hi rend="italic">Excretory's</hi> which throw <lb/>of the
        Extra-corporeal Secretions, <lb/>being large enough to carry off the <lb/>Refuſe of his
        Extravagance, would <lb/>upon ſo ſudden a Change, throw <lb/>off more than ſuch an
        abſtenious-diet <lb/>cou'd ſpare, and leave too little in <lb/>the Veſſels, to ſupport the
        Circula- <lb/>tion, with that velocity that is neceſ- <pb n="19"/>
        <lb/>ſary to Health, for that the Blood may <lb/>be propelled with that degree of ve-
        <lb/>locity, that is neceſſary to preſerve <lb/>Health, the Veſſels muſt all be fill'd
        <lb/>in ſuch a manner, as the Impulſe of <lb/>the Fluid, and the Re-action of the
        <lb/>Veſſels, may be adjuſted to this ne- <lb/>ceſſary velocity; more or leſs will
        <lb/>beget a Diſeaſe: And the Blood- <lb/>veſſels, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> Being
        ſuddenly drain'd, <lb/>and depriv'd of their uſual ſupply, <lb/>the preſſure of the Fluid
        agaiſt them <lb/>will decreaſe with the Quantity of <lb/>it; and the Impulſe of the Fluid,
        <lb/>and the Re-action of the Veſſels be- <lb/>ing equal, ſuch a Diminution, from <lb/>a
        Conſtitution that is not labouring <lb/>under an acute Diſtemper, muſt ne- <lb/>ceſſarily
        leſſen the Velocity of the <lb/>Fluid proportionaly. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Hence it is evident, that the ſud- <lb/>den Change which you recommend, <lb/>wou'd make
        ſuch a Diſproportion <lb/>between the Quantity of Fluid, and <lb/>the Dimenſions of the
        Veſſels, as <lb/>wou'd render the Circulation very <pb n="20"/>
        <lb/>languid; and this ſlow motion of <lb/>the Fluid, wou'd give its Parts an
        <lb/>Opportunity of combineing, and for- <lb/>ming Bodies too groſs, to paſs thro' <lb/>the
        more minute <hi rend="italic">Capillary</hi>'s, and the <lb/>Obſtructions that wou'd enſue
        from <lb/>thence, wou'd conſequently be the <lb/>Fountain of many grievous Diſtem-
        <lb/>pers. The ill Conſequences of ſuch <lb/>ſudden Changes, have been taken <lb/>Notice of,
        by every Judicious Ob- <lb/>ſerver in Phyſick, ſince <hi rend="italic">Hippocrates</hi>;
        <lb/>and as many of them, as have wrote <lb/>upon this Subject, have faithfully
        <lb/>caution'd Mankind againſt them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I have already given my Reaſons, <lb/>why I think it dangerous to pre- <lb/>ſcribe
        either Diet, or Medicine at <lb/>random. And now give me leave <lb/>to point at ſome things,
        which ap- <lb/>pear to me in a very odd Light. In <lb/>the Directions you have given to re-
        <lb/>gulate the quantity of Food. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>You obſerve <note place="margin" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Page 39.</note>
        <q rend="diple quotes">"Since our Ap- <lb/>"petites are deceitful, and Weight <lb/>"and
          Meaſure troubleſome and <pb n="21"/>
          <lb/>"Singular; we muſt have recourſe <lb/>"to a Rule independent of <choice>
            <corr>our</corr>
            <sic>onr</sic>
          </choice> Sen- <lb/>"ſations, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c</hi>
        </q>. You propoſe here, <lb/>to give us a Rule for meaſuring the <lb/>Quantity of our Food,
        independent <lb/>of our Senſations; and if this has <lb/>any meaning at all, it muſt be di-
        <lb/>recting us, to eat and drink by gueſs, <lb/>without any regard to the Quantity;
        <lb/>for we cannot poſſibly form a Judg- <lb/>ment of any thing, without the <lb/>Aſſiſtance
        of our Senſes. But after- <lb/>wards you adviſe us <note n="†" place="margin"
          rend="size(0.5)">† Page 40.</note>
        <hi rend="italic">to meaſure the <lb/>Quantity by our Eye</hi>, but then there <lb/>is one
        of the Senſations employ'd, <lb/>unleſs you deny Viſion to be a Sen- <lb/>ſation. Then you
        go on; <note place="margin" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† Page 40.</note>
        <q rend="diple quotes">"Thus, <lb/>"the two Wings of a middling Pullet, <lb/>"or one Wing
          and both Legs; three <lb/>"Ribs of a middling Neck of Mut- <lb/>"ton; two middling Slices
          of a Leg <lb/>"or Shoulder of Mutton, ſomewhat <lb/>"leſs of Beef may be ſufficient, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c</hi>
        </q>". </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Now if it were prudent or reaſo- <lb/>nable, to determine the Quantity <lb/>of Meat,
        that a Man ſhould take, <pb n="22"/>
        <lb/>without being appriſed of the Na- <lb/>ture of his Conſtitution; what can <lb/>any Body
        make of this Direction? <lb/>As if a middling Slice of Meat, was <lb/>a determined Quantity,
        which every <lb/>Body knew; however People may <lb/>determine what they themſelves call
        <lb/>a middling Slice, yet I am ſure, it <lb/>is impoſſible for any Body, that has <lb/>not
        been accuſtomed to ſee you eat, <lb/>to tell what you mean by it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Every thinking Man, I believe is <lb/>an Enemy to Debauching in ſtrong <lb/>Liquours,
        but I cannot be of your <lb/>Opinion, when you recommend and <lb/>prefer ſmall Wines to the
        ſtronger <lb/>Kind. Indeed if a Man was oblig- <lb/>ed to drink a large Quantity of
        <lb/>Wine every Day, then ſmall Wines <lb/>ſhould be prefer'd, provided they <lb/>were
        ſound: But as no Man is <lb/>obliged to drink more than he cares <lb/>for, I ſhould prefer a
        convenient <lb/>Quantity of the more generous ſort, <lb/>either by it ſelf, or mix'd with
        Wa- <lb/>ter; if it was for no other Reaſon, <pb n="23"/>
        <lb/>but becauſe ſuch Wines, being much <lb/>leſs Subject to Putrefaction than the
        <lb/>ſmaller Kind, People will have a <lb/>much better Chance, for drinking <lb/>that which
        is Good. For notwith- <lb/>ſtanding the vaſt Quantity of Wine <lb/>drank in <hi
          rend="italic">England</hi>, very few are <lb/>Judges when it is good of its Kind, <lb/>or
        otherwiſe, unleſs it happen to <lb/>be ſpoil'd to a very great Degree. <lb/>And you your
        ſelf confeſs the good <lb/>Effects of generous Wines and Food, <lb/>not only moderately, but
        plentifully <lb/>taken: where you ſay, <note place="margin" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Page
          14.</note>
        <q rend="diple quotes">"That <lb/>"thoſe who have drank ſtrong <lb/>"Liquours ſo
          plentifully, as to have <lb/>"thereby a ſtrong Circulation and <lb/>"full Perſpiration,
          ſeldom or never <lb/>"catch Cold. And this is the <lb/>"Reaſon why rich Foods and gene-
          <lb/>"rous Wines, moderately uſed, <lb/>"become ſo excellent an Antedote <lb/>"in
          Infectious and Epedemick <lb/>"Diſtempers, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c</hi>
        </q>". You are ſo <lb/>far in the Right in my Opinion, in <lb/>imagining that Men are leſs
        apt to <pb n="24"/>
        <lb/>receive injuries from the <hi rend="italic">Circumam- <lb/>bient Air</hi>, when their
        Veſſels are <lb/>filled by rich Food and generous <lb/>Wines, than diſeaſed People are,
        <lb/>whoſe Veſſels are lank for want of <lb/>that competent Quantity of Fluid <lb/>neceſſary
        to Health. But this truth <lb/>is the Conſequence of a Cauſe, <lb/>quite different from what
        you ima- <lb/>gine it. You ſuppoſe the violence <lb/>with which the matter of Perſpira-
        <lb/>tion flys from the Body (which you <lb/>call a brisk <hi rend="italic">Atmoſphere</hi>)
        reſiſts the <lb/>preſſure of the Circumambient Air, <lb/>and prevents its having acceſs to
        the <lb/>Body. Your Words are theſe, <lb/>ſpeaking of the effects of rich Food <lb/>and
        generous Wines, you ſay they <lb/>
        <note place="margin" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Page 15.</note>
        <q rend="diple">Not only baniſh Fear and Terror, <lb/>but as they make ſo full and free a
          <lb/>ſtream of Perſpiration, and main- <lb/>tain ſo active and brisk an <hi rend="italic"
            >Atmo- <lb/>ſphere</hi>, as ſuffers no noxious ſteams <lb/>or mixtures, in the Air to
          come <lb/>within it, but drives and beats off <lb/>the Enemy to a diſtance; but <pb n="25"/>
          <lb/>Perſons of viſcous heavy Fluids, of <lb/>poor and ſizey Juices, of little or <lb/>no
          Perſpiration, ſuch as generally <lb/>all Studious, Sedentary and ſickly <lb/>Perſons are,
          but eſpecially thoſe <lb/>that are ſubject to Nervous Diſ- <lb/>orders, muſt neceſſarily
          ſuffer <lb/>under theſe poiſonous Mixtures <lb/>in the Air, if they do not cauti-
          <lb/>ouſly and carefully <unclear>f</unclear>ence againſt <lb/>them, or take not a preſent
          Re- <lb/>medy and Antidote when tainted, <lb/>for beſides the Air that gets thro' <lb/>the
          Perſpiratory Ducts into our <lb/>Blood, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Doctor <hi rend="italic">James Keill</hi>, in his Eſſays <lb/>upon the <hi
          rend="italic">Animal Oeconomy</hi>, com- <lb/>puted the force of the Heart, equal <lb/>to
        the Weight of 5 Ounces only; <lb/>and that the velocity of the Blood <lb/>at the Heart, to
        that in the minute <lb/><hi rend="italic">Capillary</hi>'s (and he did not deſcend <lb/>ſo
        far as the <hi rend="italic">Excretory</hi>'s of inſenſible <lb/>Perſpiration) was as 5.233
        to 1. <lb/>And here you ſuppoſe, that the mat- <lb/>ter of inſenſible Perſpiration, whoſe
          <pb n="26"/>
        <lb/>velocity is the leaſt of any, is upon <lb/>ſome occaſions, propelled with a <lb/>Force,
        ſufficient to repell the Preſſure <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Atmoſphere</hi>, upon the
        Surface <lb/>of a Man's Body, which in a Me- <lb/>dium is computed to be equal to be-
        <lb/>tween 39.900 and 40.000 Pound. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I confeſs Dr. <hi rend="italic">Keill</hi> was miſtaken <lb/>in this Calculation; for
        if the force, <lb/>which propells the <hi rend="italic">Animal</hi> Fluids, <lb/>was ſo much
        inferior to the Preſ- <lb/>ſure of the <hi rend="italic">Atmoſphere</hi>, the Circu-
        <lb/>lation cou'd not be carried on, and <lb/>Conſequently no <hi rend="italic">Animal</hi>
        cou'd ex- <lb/>iſt in the Air we live in; for that <lb/>Reaſon, I ſhall not preſs this Doct-
        <lb/>rine as an Argument againſt you; <lb/>nor is it neceſſary here, to deter- <lb/>mine,
        how much you are miſtaken in <lb/>the other Extream. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But the true Cauſe, why People <lb/>whoſe Veſſels are well filles with <lb/>good
        Nouriſhment, from rich Food, <lb/>and generous Wines, are not apt <lb/>to catch Cold, or be
        tainted with <lb/>infectious Diſtempers, is becauſe, <lb/>when the Veſſels are all thus
        filled, <pb n="27"/>
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Excretory</hi>'s, upon the Surface of <lb/>the Body, are charged
        in proportion, <lb/>and being ſwell'd with the Matter <lb/>of Perſpiration, they preſs
        againſt, <lb/>and ſhut up theſe Orrifices, which <lb/>convey the Air, or any thing elſe
        <lb/>from the Surface of our Bodies, to <lb/>our Maſs of Blood; and when the <lb/>Veſſels
        are not filled as they ought <lb/>to be, from Sickneſs, or any other <lb/>Cauſe, the <hi
          rend="italic">Excretory</hi>'s of Perſpira- <lb/>tion are proportionaly empty, and
        <lb/>conſequently can't preſs upon theſe <lb/>Orrifices, but will leave them open <lb/>to
        receive the Air, or any kind of <lb/>Fluid, that may happen to be ap- <lb/>plied to the Skin
        of ſuch a Perſon. <lb/>Theſe <hi rend="italic">Excretory</hi>'s that emitt the <lb/>Matter
        of inſenſible Perſpiration, <lb/>can never be the ſame, which receive <lb/>any thing into
        the Blood from with- <lb/>out us; becauſe if they are not Ob- <lb/>ſtructed, they are
        conſtantly throw- <lb/>ing out the Matter of inſenſible <lb/>Perſpiration, and they cannot
        poſ- <lb/>ſibly, give acces to one Fluid from <pb n="28"/>
        <lb/>without, at the ſame time they are <lb/>diſcharging another from within; <lb/>and if
        they are obſtucted, they can <lb/>neither do the one nor the other. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That Fat is harder to digeſt, than <lb/>the more ſolid part of <hi rend="italic"
          >Animals</hi>, <note place="margin" rend="size(0.5)" n="†">† Page 25.</note> is <lb/>a
        Poſition you ſeem to be very cer- <lb/>tain of<unclear>,</unclear> and quote <hi rend="sc"
          >SIR</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">Iſaac Newton</hi>'s <lb/>Authority, to ſupport your Opinion; <lb/>and
        though the Juſtice which the <lb/>World has done to the Character of <lb/>that great Man,
        will leave but few <lb/>Diſſenters, from any Opinion of his; <lb/>yet ſince the beſt may
        err, and the <lb/>greateſt Genious may be ſometime <lb/>miſtaken, I have ventur'd to think
        <lb/>differently, and ſhall give you my <lb/>Reaſons why I do ſo. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Don't we find, that Fat diſolves <lb/>more eaſily, than any other part of <lb/><choice>
          <corr/>
          <sic>of </sic>
        </choice>the <hi rend="italic">Animal</hi> ſubſtance, by all <lb/>the Trials we can make to
        that pur- <lb/>poſe out of the Stomach; what <lb/>then ſhould make it leſs ſoluble in
        <lb/>the Stomach, than any where elſe? <lb/>And don't we find that a much leſs <pb n="29"/>
        <lb/>degree of Heat, than is in the Sto- <lb/>mach of any <hi rend="italic">Animal</hi>,
        will diſolve it <lb/>infinitely ſooner, than any other <lb/>part of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Animal</hi> can be diſſolved, <lb/>by all the artful Contrivances we <lb/>can think of?
        So that abſtracting <lb/>from the Action of the Stomach, <lb/>the heat alone, wou'd diſſolve
        or di- <lb/>geſt it ſooner, than any other Sub- <lb/>ſtance can be. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And if becauſe of its ſmoothneſs, <lb/>as you imagine, it cou'd in ſome <lb/>meaſure
        elude the Action of the <lb/>Stomach, yet its Parts being leſs <lb/>tenacious, than that of
        any other <lb/>ſubſtance, the leſs force would be <lb/>ſufficient to divide them. But when
        <lb/>the Stomach is contracted to pro- <lb/>mote digeſtion, the Contraction be- <lb/>ing
        equal in every part of it, the <lb/>Matter contain'd in it, cannot poſ- <lb/>ſibly evade the
        Preſſure, tho it ſhou'd <lb/>ſhift its Place. And I am informed <lb/>by Men of great
        Probity, who tell <lb/>me from their own Experience, that <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >Turtle</hi>, which they eat frequently <pb n="30"/>
        <lb/>in the <hi rend="italic">Weſt-Indies</hi>, is the fatteſt of <lb/>all <hi rend="italic"
          >Animals</hi>; and that it is the <lb/>wholeſomeſt, and lighteſt Food in <lb/>the World. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I can't imagine, why all theſe <lb/><hi rend="italic">Invectives</hi> againſt <hi
          rend="italic">Punch</hi>; as <hi rend="italic">Rack- <lb/>Punch</hi> is commonly made in
          <hi rend="italic">Eng- <lb/>land</hi>, tho' I believe this Compoſi- <lb/>tion may not be
        agreeable to every <lb/>Conſtitution, yet I imagine by the <lb/>generality of People, it may
        be <lb/>drank as ſafely, as an equal quan- <lb/>tity of Wine; for ſince it contains <lb/>a
        ſmaller quantity of Spirits, it will <lb/>conſequently be leſs apt to heat us. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>You ſay <note place="margin" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Page 55.</note>
        <q rend="diple quotes">"every thing that has <lb/>"paſſed the Fire, ſo that it has had
          <lb/>"due time to divide and penetrate <lb/>"its Parts, as far as it poſſibly can,
          <lb/>"retains a Cauſtick burning quality <lb/>"ever after, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c</hi>
        </q>". This Obſerva- <lb/>tion holds true, in Bodies which <lb/>have been calcined; but the
        Fire <lb/>never has that effect upon any mat- <lb/>ter, while its Parts continue defen-
        <lb/>ded and diluted with water; (and <pb n="31"/>
        <lb/>Water is the Baſis of every Liquid, <lb/>expect Oil) this is evident in that
        <lb/>ſingle Inſtance of Hartſhorn, which <lb/>when calcin'd, is in ſome degree
        <lb/>Corroſive, and receives that quality <lb/>from the Fire; but are not the Parts <lb/>of
        this ſame Subſtance, divided and <lb/>ſeperated by the force of the Fire, <lb/>when it is
        boil'd in Water to make <lb/>Jelly? And did ever any body ap- <lb/>prehend a Cauſtick
        burning quality <lb/>in Hartſhorn Jelly? Has not the <lb/>Fire the ſame acceſs to the
        Plants, <lb/>from whence, the ſimple inſiped <lb/>Waters of the Shops are diſtill'd, <lb/>as
        to Wine, from whence you diſtill <lb/>Brandy? Does it not ſeperate their <lb/>Parts in the
        ſame manner? And is <lb/>there any thing cauſtick either in the <lb/>Plants which remain in
        the <hi rend="italic">Alembick</hi>, <lb/>or in the Water drawn from them? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>According to your Notion, it <lb/>would add to the fiery Quality of <lb/>Brandy, or any
        other Spirit, to boil <lb/>it over a Fire; but make that Ex- <lb/>periment when you will,
        and you <pb n="32" copyOf=""/>
        <lb/>will find it produce a very contrary <lb/>Effect, tho' you ſtop it ſo cloſe that
        <lb/>nothing can eſcape, but what paſ- <lb/>ſes thro' the Pores of the Veſſel; <lb/>and tho'
        the ſubtile Parts of the Fire, <lb/>may get acceſs thro' the Pores of the <lb/>Veſſel, yet
        it can never affect any <lb/>Particle of Matter contain'd in it ſo <lb/>as to burn it, as
        long as there re- <lb/>mains any Water, to dilute and <lb/>defend it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That there is Oil in the Compo- <lb/>ſition of all inflamable Spirits I own; <lb/>But
        every body knows, whenever <lb/>Fire gets acceſs to Oil, it ſets it in <lb/>a Flame; and if
        the Parts of the <lb/>Fire, did incorporate with this Oil, <lb/>as you ſay it does, wou'd it
        not <lb/>have the ſame Effect and deſtroy it? <lb/>This is obvious from your own Ob-
        <lb/>ſervation, of the <hi rend="italic">continued Diſtilla- <lb/>tion of Spirits</hi>, they
        will at laſt, when <lb/>they come off without any Water <lb/>to defend them, as you ſay, <hi
          rend="italic">be re- <lb/>duced into liquid Flames, which will <lb/>of themſelves
          evaporate into viſible <lb/>Flames and Fumes</hi>. </p>
      <pb n="33"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is not my buſineſs in this Place, <lb/>to write a Diſertation upon the Na- <lb/>ture
        of Fire, and Cauſticks; it is <lb/>ſufficient to ſhow you, (and I think <lb/>it is evident
        from what I have ſaid,) <lb/>that the Fire contributes nothing to <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Arrack</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Brandy</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Rum</hi>, &amp;c. but
        <lb/>as it ſeperates theſe Spirits from <lb/>groſſer Bodies, from which they are <lb/>drawn,
        and in which they actually <lb/>exiſted, before Diſtillation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Juices of <hi rend="italic">Lemons</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Oranges</hi>,
        <lb/>(and we uſe no other in <hi rend="italic">England</hi>, but <lb/>what are brought from
        Abroad) are <lb/>every Day given with good ſucceſs, <lb/>by Phyſicians, who juſtly deſerve
        <lb/>that Character, to their Patiens, in <lb/>ſeveral Caſes, in much greater Quan-
        <lb/>tities, than People, who are not Drun- <lb/>kard's ever taken them in <hi rend="italic"
          >Punch</hi>. And <lb/>you own that Sugar and Water are <lb/>no Enemies to our
        Conſtitutions. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>You ſay <note place="margin" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† Page 57.</note>
        <q rend="diple quotes">in the <hi rend="italic">Weſt Indies</hi>, <lb/>where from the
          neceſſity of drink- <lb/>ing much, becauſe of the violence <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic"
            >Heat</hi>, and from the want <pb n="34"/>
          <lb/>"of Proper Liquors there, they are <lb/>"forced to drink much <hi rend="italic"
            >Punch</hi>, tho' <lb/>"<hi rend="italic">Lemons</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
          >Oranges</hi>, be in their <lb/>"full Perfection, they are univerſal- <lb/>"ly afflicted
          with <hi rend="italic">nervous</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mor- <lb/>"tal</hi> dry <hi
            rend="italic">Belly-aches</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Palſies</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >Cramps</hi>
          <lb/>"and <hi rend="italic">Convulſions</hi>; which cut them <lb/>"off in a few Days,
          entirely owing <lb/>"to this <hi rend="italic">poiſonous</hi> Mixture, <hi rend="italic"
            >&amp;c</hi>" </q>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Now I wou'd fain ask you, if <lb/>all the People in the <hi rend="italic"
          >Weſt-Indies</hi> are <lb/>afflicted with this Diſtemper, and if <lb/>it cuts them off in
        a few Days, how <lb/>could ever that Place be Inhabited? <lb/>But perhaps you only mean
        thoſe <lb/>who drink <hi rend="italic">Punch</hi>; however that be, <lb/>you are miſinformed
        of the State of <lb/>that Country, for they have plenty of <lb/>Wines, from all the Counries
        which <lb/>produce it, and <hi rend="italic">Ale</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Cyder</hi> from
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">England</hi>; and are under no neceſſity <lb/>of drinking much <hi
          rend="italic">Punch</hi>, for want of <lb/>other Liquors; <hi rend="italic">Madera</hi>
        Wine and <lb/>Water, is the moſt agreeable and <lb/>wholeſomeſt drink imaginable, and
        <lb/>this they have in ſo great Plenty, <pb n="35"/>
        <lb/>that they make it ſerve the com- <lb/>mon Purpoſes of drinking, as we <lb/>do ſmall
        Beer in <hi rend="italic">England</hi>. Nor is <lb/>it to be ſuppos'd, that a People
        <lb/>whoſe Commerce obliges them to <lb/>have Dealings, with every Country <lb/>in <hi
          rend="italic">Europe</hi>, wou'd want any Conveni- <lb/>ency that <hi rend="italic">Europe
        </hi>can afford. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And I am inform'd by a Gentle- <lb/>man of good Underſtanding, and <lb/>great
        Integrity, who lived upwards <lb/>of 30 Years in the <hi rend="italic">Weſt-Indies</hi>, and
        <lb/>but lately came from it; that the <lb/>Diſeaſe called the Belly-Ach, <lb/>which is ſo
        perculiar to that Country, <lb/>attacks the Women as well as the <lb/>Men; and that the
        Women there, <lb/>are particularly Remarkable for their <lb/>Temperance, and abſtinence from
        <lb/>ſtrong Liquors; and that many of <lb/>both Sexes, who never taſted <hi rend="italic"
          >Punch</hi>, <lb/>or indulg'd in any ſtrong Liquor in <lb/>their Lives, are afflicted with
        this <lb/>Diſtemper; if this be true, and I <lb/>have no reaſon to doubt my Infor-
        <lb/>mation, then this Diſtemper muſt <pb n="36"/>
        <lb/>have ſome other Source than <hi rend="italic">Punch</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And if the <hi rend="italic">Bath</hi> be the only Cure <lb/>for this Diſtemper, as you
        boldly <lb/>affirm it is; how comes it to paſs, <lb/>that ſo many are cured of it in the
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Weſt-Indies</hi>? And tho' the meaning <lb/>of your recommending
        the <hi rend="italic">Bath</hi>, <lb/>and of your Encomiums upon the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Water</hi>, and other Conveniencies of <lb/>that Place, upon ſeveral Occaſions, <lb/>is
        by no means Myſterious; yet you <lb/>have raſhly ſrain'd that Point too <lb/>far in this
        Place, and it will never <lb/>contribute to the End for which I <lb/>believe you deſign'd
        it; for pro- <lb/>bably you never can have any Pa- <lb/>tients, under theſe Circumſtances,
        <lb/>but from the <hi rend="italic">Weſt-Indies</hi>, who at <lb/>the ſame time they read
        your Re- <lb/>commendation of the <hi rend="italic">Bath</hi>, to Save <lb/>and Cure them,
        they will find your <lb/>Miſtake, in ſaying it is the only Re- <lb/>medy; ſince they all
        know, that <lb/>many more are cured of if at Home, <lb/>than ever came to the <hi
          rend="italic">Bath</hi> to find <lb/>Relief; and that going to a colder <pb n="37"/>
        <lb/>Climate, never fails to produce a <lb/>Cure of this Diſtemper, without <lb/>taking any
        other Remedy. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And this Diſeaſe, is ſo far from <lb/>always cutting them off in a few <lb/>Days, that
        they who live ſoberly <lb/>when they are ſo afflicted, generally <lb/>recover in a very
        little Time; and <lb/>it will hold thoſe, who continue the <lb/>exceſſive uſe of ſtrong
        Liquors many <lb/>Months, nay Years, before they are <lb/>either kill'd by it, or cured of
        it. <lb/>Theſe things, which every Body in <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Weſt-Indies</hi> know
        to be true, <lb/>will neceſſarily make them conclude, <lb/>that you know nothing of the Na-
        <lb/>ture of this Diſtemper. And if this <lb/>be true, your telling them that the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Bath</hi> is their only Remedy, will <lb/>hardly bring them there to become
        <lb/>your Patients. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Beſides we cannot ſuppoſe, with- <lb/>out reflecting upon the good Senſe <lb/>of theſe
        People, that they would <lb/>indulge themſelves in a Liquor ſo <lb/>pernicious to them, as
        you think <pb n="38"/>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Punch</hi> is, when they have variety of <lb/>other Liquors, that
        would anſwer <lb/>all the Purpoſes of drinking. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This Diſeaſe that you aſcribe to <lb/><hi rend="italic">Punch</hi>, is I am told, the
        Effect of <lb/>cathing cold in that Country, which <lb/>the ſober People carefully guard a-
        <lb/>gainſt; but thoſe who uſe to intoxi- <lb/>cate themſelves with ſtrong Liquors,
        <lb/>often neglect the proper Means to <lb/>prevent taking cold, by ſleeping <lb/>ſometimes
        in the open Air, or not <lb/>takin the proper Care to avoid this <lb/>ill, by Means that are
        neceſſary to <lb/>be uſed within Doors. For tho' a <lb/>Man is leſs apt to catch cold, when
        <lb/>his Veſſels are all turg'd with the <lb/>Liquor that hath made him drunk; <lb/>yet
        after ſome time, when the ſeveral <lb/><hi rend="italic">Emunctory's</hi> of the Body, have
        diſ- <lb/>charged the ſuperfluous Fluid from <lb/>the Veſſels, they will become more
        <lb/>lank, and the Pores of the Skin will <lb/>be more open, to admitt any nox- <lb/>ious
        Steams that may be in the Air, <lb/>than they were before; and there- <pb n="39"/>
        <lb/>fore, a more than common Care, is <lb/>requiſite to prevent a Man's taking <lb/>cold in
        this State. And if a Man <lb/>catches cold there, after being drunk, <lb/>he will be ſeized
        with this Diſtem- <lb/>per, whatever Liquor he debauch'd <lb/>in. Indeed as all the
        Ingredients of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Rum-Punch</hi>, are the Product of that <lb/>Country,
        they are conſequently to <lb/>be purchas'd very cheap, and for <lb/>this Reaſon the poorer
        ſort of Peo- <lb/>ple, and the Sailors that go thither <lb/>(who are the Bulk of thoſe who
        <lb/>delight in drinking to Exceſs) often <lb/>get the dry Belly-Ach, <hi rend="italic"
          >&amp;c.</hi> By <lb/>cathing cold, after being drunk <lb/>with <hi rend="italic"
          >Punch</hi>. But ſince <hi rend="italic">Punch</hi> is no <lb/>more acceſſary to this
        Diſtemper, <lb/>than any other ſtrong Liquor, that <lb/>a Man debauches in, and ſince ſo-
        <lb/>ber Perſons who never taſted <hi rend="italic">Punch</hi>, <lb/>are ſubject to this
        Diſtemper, I <lb/>think it very unreaſonable, to attri- <lb/>bute this Miſchief wholy to <hi
          rend="italic">Punch</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When you wrote your Eſſay of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Gout</hi>, &amp;c. You took a
        Fancy to <pb n="40"/>
        <lb/>ſay, that the Nerves were ſolid <lb/>without Cavities; and therefore <lb/>contained no
        Fluid. This Notion, <lb/>has led you into many extravagant <lb/>Expreſſions, about the
        Condition of <lb/>the Nerves; which this laſt Product- <lb/>ion of yours is crouded with.
          <hi rend="italic">e g.</hi>
        <lb/>What <hi rend="italic">Idea</hi>, can be annex'd to that <lb/>Expreſſion (ſo often uſed
        by you) <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Bracing</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Winding</hi> up the
        <lb/>Nerves? Every one knows how a <lb/>Drum is braced, and how a Fiddle <lb/>ſtring is
        wound up; but how thoſe <lb/>Operations can be applied to the <lb/>Nerves, in any part of
        the <hi rend="italic">Animal</hi>
        <lb/>Body, is what I am ſure no Man can <lb/>imagine. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In your Treatiſe of the <hi rend="italic">Gout</hi>, &amp;c. <lb/>you have theſe Words
          <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5) indent">* Eſſay of the Gout, Page 91. </note>
        <q rend="diple quotes">"I have a <lb/>"long time ſuſpected the reaſon- <lb/>"ings of <hi
            rend="italic">Phyſicians</hi>, and the Ac- <lb/>"counts given by them of the Na-
          <lb/>"ture of Diſeaſes, that were <lb/>"found on <hi rend="italic">Nervous</hi> Juices,
          and <lb/>"<hi rend="italic">Fluids</hi>, their Motion, Nature, <lb/>"and Qualities: And
          yet it will be <pb n="41"/>
          <lb/>a great Baulk on the <hi rend="italic">Theory</hi> of <lb/>Diſtempers, the boaſted
            <hi rend="italic">Politeneſs</hi>, <lb/>and admired <hi rend="italic">Fineneſs</hi> of
          the pre- <lb/>ſent Age has advanced, ſhould <lb/>there really be no ſuch Fluids in
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Animal Body's</hi>" </q>. This, as you ob- <lb/>ſerve, wou'd have
        been no ſmall Sur- <lb/>priſe to the learned World; and <lb/>I'll tell you anotherthing,
        (which <lb/>perhaps you do <choice>
          <corr>not know</corr>
          <sic>notknow</sic>
        </choice>) it wou'd <lb/>have been no ſmall Addition to their <lb/>Surpriſe, to have found
        that you <lb/>had made the Diſcovery. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Now, tho' the Arguments you <lb/>bring to ſupport your Opinion, that <lb/>the Nerves
        contain no Fluid, are <lb/>of ſuch a Nature, that it may ſeem <lb/>trifling to take Notice
        of them, yet <lb/>I ſhall be at ſome Pains with the laſt <lb/>thing you ſay in defence of
        this <lb/>Notion; becauſe I preſume you <lb/>brought it thus in the Rear, as <lb/>thinking
        it the ſtrongeſt and moſt <lb/>conducive to your Purpoſe. The <lb/>Sum of this laſt Argument
        is, be- <lb/>cauſe the Nerves are <hi rend="italic">Cylindrical</hi>
        <pb n="42"/>
        <lb/>Tubes, whereas the Arteries and <lb/>Veins, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> which
        evidently con- <lb/>tain Fluid are <hi rend="italic">Conical</hi>, and Nature <lb/>being
        uniform in her Operations, <lb/>therefore you conclude, that the <lb/>Nerves contain no
        Fluid. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Arteries by dividing into <lb/>Branches, muſt grow gradually nar- <lb/>rower, and
        for that Reaſon are <hi rend="italic">Con- <lb/>ical</hi>; and the Nerves are <hi
          rend="italic">Cylinders</hi>
        <lb/>becauſe they do not communicate <lb/>with one another, but run on in ſe- <lb/>parate
        Canal's, from their Origines <lb/>to their Extremities. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <q rend="italic">
          <lb/>And the Wiſdom of our Creator is <lb/>ſignaly manifeſted in contriveing the
          <lb/>Structure of the Nerves, different from <lb/>that of all the other Veſſels in the <hi
            rend="roman">Ani- <lb/>mal</hi> Body. For as the Nerves do not <lb/>communicate with one
          another, but run <lb/>on in ſeperate Canal's from their O- <lb/>rigins to their
          Extremities: An im- <lb/>pulſe, or addition of Fluid, to any <lb/>Quantity of Nerves,
          determin'd to <lb/>move a Muſcle or Muſcles, runs on, <lb/>or is propagated their
          Extremities, <pb n="43"/>
          <lb/>without communicating their additio- <lb/>nal Fluid, or Impulſe, to any of the
          <lb/>other Nerves; which cou'd not happen, <lb/>if their Structure was like that of the
          <lb/>Arteries: For if the Nerves that ſerve <lb/>in bending and extending of a Limb,
          <lb/>were Branches from a common Trunk <lb/>with which they had a Communication, <lb/>any
          impulſe at the Trunk, would be <lb/>propagated equally to all the Branches, <lb/>the
          Benders and Extenders. So that <lb/>inſtead of regular and voluntary Mo- <lb/>tions, we
          ſhould be Diſtorted with <lb/>Convulſions. <hi rend="roman">e. g.</hi> Suppoſe a Power <cb
            n="1"/>
          <lb/>at <hi rend="roman">A.</hi> determining to <lb/>affect <hi rend="roman">C.</hi> by
          means of <lb/>a Fluid contain'd in <lb/>the Veſſel <hi rend="roman">A.</hi> which
          <lb/>communicates equal- <lb/>ly with <hi rend="roman">B.</hi> as with <lb/><hi
            rend="roman">C.</hi> Any impulſe upon <cb n="2"/>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>An illustration of a tube that forks into two branches at its base. </figDesc>
          </figure>
          <cb n="1 2"/>
          <lb/>the Fluid at <hi rend="roman">A.</hi> will affect <hi rend="roman">B</hi> equally
          <lb/>with <hi rend="roman">C.</hi> without a poſſibility of deter- <lb/>mining its <hi
            rend="roman">Momentum</hi>, more to the <lb/>one than to the other. </q>
      </p>
      <pb n="44"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This Demonſtration, I have bor- <lb/>rowed from a Syſtem of <hi rend="italic">Animal
          <lb/>Oeconomy</hi>, that is not yet publiſhed; <lb/>I wiſh when it is, it may be
        effectual, <lb/>to put an End to all that unintelli- <lb/>gible Babbling, which hath
        hitherto <lb/>confounded this uſeful Knowledge. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is no difficult Matter to con- <lb/>ceive, how the Fibres may be con- <lb/>tracted,
        by increaſing the Quantity <lb/>of Fluid in the Veſſels which they <lb/>compoſe. But by what
        power in <lb/>Nature, <note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† Eſſay of the Gout.
        </note> can the Fibres be drawn in, <lb/>and ſink into their own Subſtance? <lb/>which you
        ſay is the Caſe in Muſ- <lb/>cular Motion. You are realy ſo <lb/>unhappy in all your
        Expreſſions, <lb/>that if I was not certain, you live <lb/>by the <hi rend="italic"
          >Trade</hi> of Phyſick, I ſhould <lb/>Imagine you wrote purpoſely to <lb/>turn it into
        Redicule. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>this <hi rend="sc">Sir</hi>, is a very incredulous <lb/>Age we live in; and theſe <hi
          rend="italic">Infidels</hi>, <lb/>whom Providence hath favoured <pb n="45"/>
        <lb/>with Knowledge and Underſtand- <lb/>ing, will never regard an Opinion, <lb/>without
        good Reaſons to ſupport it, <lb/>be it never ſo boldly Afferted. So <lb/>obſtinate are they
        in their Averſion <lb/>to Folly, that a Man who Speaks <lb/>and Writes without thinking, may
        <lb/>babble and ſcribble from his <hi rend="italic">Cradle</hi>
        <lb/>to his <hi rend="italic">Grave</hi>, without meeting any <lb/>other Recompence, but <hi
          rend="italic">Redicule</hi> for <lb/>his Pains. And by this Means, they <lb/>vainly
        imagine to reſtrain the Folly <lb/>of Writing and Speaking at ran- <lb/>dom; I ſay vainly
        imagine it, be- <lb/>cauſe <hi rend="italic">you know</hi> it is attempting an
        <lb/>Impoſſibility. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To be <hi rend="italic">humbly Proud</hi> is no new <lb/>Character, and yet I believe
        you <lb/>may juſtly boaſt, that no Body ever <lb/>came up to it ſo fully as you have
        <lb/>done; a ſingular <hi rend="italic">Ambition</hi>, peculiar <lb/>to your ſelf, hath made
        you (upon <lb/>ſome Occaſion or other) reject e- <lb/>very Opinion, that has been com-
        <lb/>monly received in that Way, you <lb/>wou'd fain perſwade the World <pb n="46"/>
        <lb/>you was Bred in; yet when Oc- <lb/>caſion ſerves, you can truckle to any <lb/>Opinion
        that ever was invented in <lb/>that Way. and at the ſame time <lb/>you are denying and
        deſpiſing the <lb/>moſt reaſonable Notions, of the beſt <lb/>Phyſicians, you condeſcend to
        ex- <lb/>preſs your ſelf, in all the unintelli- <lb/>gible <hi rend="italic">Jargon</hi> of
        the <hi rend="italic">Mountebanks</hi>
        <lb/>(tho' I preſume they are your Aver- <lb/><choice>
          <corr>ſion</corr>
          <sic>on</sic>
        </choice>, for the ſame reaſon that they <lb/>hate one another) and treat us with <lb/>whole
        Pages of uncouth Words and <lb/>Phraſes, with as much meaning, as <lb/>the wandring Orator
        delivers them <lb/>from the Stage. This Method may <lb/>get you the Applauſe of the Igno-
        <lb/>rant, who are always fond of what <lb/>they do not underſtand; and they <lb/>being the
        greateſt part of Mankind, <lb/>and generally the richeſt, you may <lb/>advance by it, what
        the unthinking <lb/>herd of Men, miſtake for Intereſt: <lb/>but ſure <hi rend="italic"
          >you</hi> can be under no neceſ- <lb/>ſity of ſtooping ſuch meanneſs! <pb n="47"/>
        <lb/>tho' <hi rend="italic">Quackery</hi>, like <hi rend="italic">Thieving</hi>, is not
        <lb/>always prompted by Neceſſity. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Your fondneſs of Novelty, which <lb/>you have in common with all thoſe, <lb/>who do not
        know how to judge right- <lb/>ly of things, made you aſſert (what <lb/>a great Man only
        ſuggeſted, and <lb/>was far from being poſitive about it) <lb/>that the Nerves were ſolid,
        and con- <lb/>tain'd no Fluid. I have already <lb/>taken Notice of your Intention to be
        <lb/>Witty, upon the refigned modern <lb/>Opinion, as you are pleaſed to call <lb/>it. And
        ſhall not repeat it again. <lb/>But when it is convenient for you, <lb/>to make your
        favourite <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Eſſay of the Gout. </note>
        <hi rend="italic">Bath-Water</hi>
        <lb/>do every thing, by aſcribing Qualitys <lb/>to it, directly oppoſite to one ano-
        <lb/>ther, or which is the ſame thing <lb/>making it have effects directly con- <lb/>trary;
        you thought (pardon me if <lb/>I miſtake in ſaying ſo) that it was <lb/>neceſſary, to fall
        in with the very <lb/>Opinion, that you had but a few <lb/>Pages before, condemn'd with the
        <lb/>greateſt Contempt. </p>
      <pb n="48"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And then you ſay, that the Re- <lb/>laxation of the Muſcles in Palſies, <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">&amp;c</hi>, proceeds from Obſtruction in <lb/>the Nerves; for how can the
        Nerves <lb/>be obſtructed if they contain no <lb/>Fluid? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The deſire of Knowledge, is a <lb/>very laudable Quality as any human <lb/>Nature can
        boaſt of; But he who en- <lb/>deavours, to graſp at the Knowledge <lb/>of a Thing, beyond
        the reach of <lb/>his Capacity, and notwithſtanding <lb/>this, will pretend to all the Know-
        <lb/>ledge of it, that a <hi rend="italic">Genious</hi> equal to <lb/>the Task, could
        poſſibly arrive at; <lb/>is a Character much of a Piece with <lb/>him, who deſcribes foreign
        Coun- <lb/>tries, and the particular Qualities <lb/>of Great Perſons, as if he had been
        <lb/>moſt intimately acquainted with <lb/>them, when he never poſſibly cou'd <lb/>have
        acceſs to know any thing a- <lb/>bout them, but what publick Fame, <lb/>gave him in common
        with all Man- <lb/>kind; and all this from the Vanity <lb/>of being thought a Man of Conſe-
          <pb n="49"/>
        <lb/>quence, and not ignorant of what <lb/>any Body would deſire to know. <lb/>That there
        are many ſuch Charact- <lb/>ers in the World, is a melancholy <lb/>Truth beyond
        Contradiction; and <lb/>the deſpicable appearance they make <lb/>in Society when detected,
        is obvi- <lb/>ous to every Man of Senſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>You preſcribe Exerciſe indefinitely <lb/>to all Mankind, as if reſt was never
        <lb/>neceſſary, and Exerciſe never hurt- <lb/>ful. That Exerciſe is an excellent <lb/>Remedy
        in ſome Caſes, to reſtore <lb/>and preſerve Health is very true; <lb/>but what Rules have
        you laid down, <lb/>or could you lay down, to teach all <lb/>Men, what kind and quantity of
        <lb/>Exerciſe is proper for them all, un- <lb/>der their ſeveral Circumſtances to <lb/><choice>
          <corr/>
          <sic>to </sic>
        </choice>take. And it is impoſſible, for <lb/>Men Ignorant of the Nature of their
        <lb/>Conſtitutions, and of any Bodily <lb/>Diſtemper, they may happen to la- <lb/>bour
        under, to judge aptly for <lb/>themſelves in this matter. </p>
      <pb n="50"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When you come to mention the <lb/>Uſe of <hi rend="italic">Opium</hi>, you acknowledge,
        <lb/>that Phyſicians are the only proper <lb/>Judges, when, and in what Quan- <lb/>tity it
        is to be exhibited; now as <lb/>one great Effect of this Medicine, is <lb/>to calm and
        diſpoſe Men to reſt, <lb/>which is the Oppoſite of Exerciſe; <lb/>does it not follow, that
        they muſt <lb/>likewiſe, be the only Judges of the <lb/>Quantity of Exerciſe, that Men
        <lb/>ſhould take? For when it is fit for <lb/>Men to be quiet, then moſt cer- <lb/>tainly it
        is fit for them to leave off <lb/>Exerciſe; and of Conſequence, if <lb/>Men who are not
        Phyſicians cannot <lb/>Judge for themſelves of the one, <lb/>they cannot poſſibly determine
        the <lb/>proper Seaſons, and Quantity of <lb/>the other. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In another Place, you ſeem to <lb/>give your Aſſent to what I have <lb/>been alledging
        in plainer Terms, <lb/>where you ſay, <note place="margin" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† Page
          27</note> from theſe gene- <lb/>ral Rules, <hi rend="italic">taking in the particular
          <lb/>Complexions and Habits</hi>, &amp;c. Here <pb n="51"/>
        <lb/>you ſeem to make it neceſſary, to <lb/>have regard to the particular Cir-
        <lb/>cumſtances of People, in order to <lb/>preſcribe juſtly for them. But who <lb/>are to
        be the Judges of theſe parti- <lb/>cular Circumſtances? Muſt theſe <lb/>eſſential things be
        left to the Diſ- <lb/>cretion of Men, who cannot poſſibly <lb/>have any knowledge of them?
        The <lb/>Practice of Phyſick <hi rend="sc">Sir</hi>, is a ſharp <lb/>Edged-Tool, and ſeldom
        or never <lb/>fails of having very ill Conſequen- <lb/>ces, when put into unskillful Hands. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To ſhow you how conſiſtant you <lb/>are with your ſelf; in your <hi rend="italic">Eſſay
          <lb/>of the Gout</hi>, &amp;c. where you treat of <lb/>Bathing, you ſay <note
          place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Eſſay of the Gout, Page 67. </note>
        <q rend="diple italic">If People will <lb/>bath indifferantly without Advice, <lb/>without
          duly preparing their Bodies, <lb/>and cleanſing the Alimentary-Paſſages <lb/>without any
          diſtinct knowledge of their <lb/>Caſe, their Strength, the proper Sea- <lb/>ſon of
          Bathing, or the Time they ought <lb/>to ſtay in at once; there muſt neceſ- <pb n="52"/>
          <lb/>ſarily happen (as there have hap- <lb/>pen'd) unlucky Accidents, which tend <lb/>to
          diſcourage and diſgrace bathing in <lb/>General. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And a little further in the ſame <lb/>Treatiſe, you ſay <note place="bottom" n="†"
          rend="size(0.5)">† Eſſay of the Gout, Page 65: </note>
        <q rend="diple italic">It is impoſſible <lb/>to lay down a general Rule about the
          <lb/>Quantity of <hi rend="roman">Bath-Water</hi>, which it <lb/>is convenient to drink
          daily; that be- <lb/>ing to be varied, according to ſome <lb/>Circumſtances of the
          Patient, and <lb/>the Nature of the Diſtemper. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When we conſider theſe Paſſages, <lb/>together with your <hi rend="italic">Eſſay of
          Health</hi>, <lb/>we find that at the <hi rend="italic">Bath</hi>, People ig- <lb/>norant
        of Phyſick, muſt not pretend <lb/>to act for themſelves, and muſt be <lb/>directed in every
        ſtep they take, by <lb/>the Advice of a Phyſician. But <lb/>every where elſe, your general
        Rules <lb/>are ſufficient to guide them without <lb/>any other Aſſiſtance. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If you had not ſome private Rea- <lb/>ſons to conceal it, it wou'd be ſome
        <lb/>ſatisfaction to know for what reaſon, <pb n="53"/>
        <lb/>you have excluded the People at the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Bath</hi> from the benefit
        of your general <lb/>Rules? Is it not as eaſy to give Di- <lb/>rections for bathing and
        drinking the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Bath-water</hi>, under Circumſtances that <lb/>you are
        not acquainted with, as to <lb/>direct People any where elſe in their <lb/>Diet and
        Medicine, whoſe Con- <lb/>ſtitutions you are equally a Stranger <lb/>to? Or wou'd you have
        us under- <lb/>ſtand by this, that People had better <lb/>truſt to the their own Management,
        <lb/>than to the Advice of any Phyſician, <lb/>except juſt in that Place where Dr. <lb/><hi
          rend="sc">Cheyne</hi>, is to be conſulted with? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I do not know how you may <lb/>have ſucceeded in this way, but I <lb/>think you are by
        far leſs artful in <lb/>your Addreſſes to the Publick, than <lb/>
        <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* For let us our Brethren the <hi rend="italic">Quacks</hi> brag what we
              <lb/>will.—<hi rend="italic">Tollere nodoſam neſcit Medicina padagram</hi>. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Eſſay of the Gout, Page 133. </p>
        </note> thoſe you are pleaſed to call your <lb/>Brethren; for tho' I believe your <lb/>Ends
        are all the ſame, yet theſe <lb/>ſtrenouſly declare, that the good of <pb n="54"/>
        <lb/>Mankind is their only Aim; while <lb/>you tacitly own that ſordid ſelf- <lb/>intereſt
        is yours. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And here (pardon the Compari- <lb/>ſon) like the Dog in the Fable, you <lb/>drop the
        Subſtance to ſnatch at the <lb/>Shadow; and when you intend to <lb/>make a Monopoly of all
        the Pract- <lb/>ice in the Kindom to your ſelf, <lb/>you are induſtrious to loſe what
        <lb/>you have already got; for notwith- <lb/>ſtanding all the fine Things you <lb/>have ſaid
        of the <hi rend="italic">Bath</hi>, who do you <lb/>think will be at the Expence and
        <lb/>Trouble of going thither, and where, <lb/>to add to that Expence, they muſt <lb/>fee a
        Phyſician, to regulate them, <lb/>according to the various Circum- <lb/>ſtances of their
        Conſtitutions? When <lb/>every where elſe with the Aſſiſtance <lb/>of your Rules only, they
        can act <lb/>for themſelves, without being be- <lb/>holden to any Phyſician. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Give me leave to obſerve by the <lb/>by, that you give a very extraordi- <lb/>nary
        Latitude in taking <hi rend="italic">Opium</hi>; <pb n="55"/>
        <lb/>when you ſay, <note place="margin" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Page 219</note>
        <q rend="diple quotes">That they who <lb/>in the Opinion of the World, <lb/>have died of too
          much <hi rend="italic">Opium</hi>, <lb/>cou'd not have liv'd many Days <lb/>without it"
        </q>: And yet where you <lb/>decry the Exceſſive uſe of Drams, <lb/>you tell us, <note
          place="margin" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Page <gap reason="illegible"/></note> they will as
        certainly <lb/>kill as <hi rend="italic">Laudanum</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Arſenick</hi>;
        now <lb/>if <hi rend="italic">Laudanum</hi> can certainly kill, how <lb/>are you certain,
        that no Body was <lb/>ever killed by it, ſince it is a Drug <lb/>ſo much in uſe, and which
        every <lb/>Man hath acceſs to at his Pleaſure? <lb/>A Man that hath murder'd another,
        <lb/>may as reaſonably urge in his de- <lb/>fence, that the Perſon he deſtroyed <lb/>cou'd
        not poſſibly have lived many <lb/>Days, though he had avoided that <lb/>Fate. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Your 7th Chap. contains Rea- <lb/>ſoning of a very extraordinary Na- <lb/>ture: There
        you are pleaſed to ſay <lb/>
        <note place="margin" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Page 213</note>
        <q rend="diple">Pain Conſtricts, Criſps up and <lb/>ſhortens the <hi rend="italic"
            >Animal</hi> Fibres, it acts <lb/>like a Wedge in tearing and <lb/>renking, and
          dividing, thoſe ſmall <pb n="56"/>
          <lb/>Filaments; it does to them what <lb/>the Points of Salts do to all <hi rend="italic"
            >Ani- <lb/>mal</hi> Subſtances, which are to be <lb/>preſerved for Food, <hi
            rend="italic">viz.</hi> hard- <lb/>ens, ſtiffens, and contracts them. <lb/>The fibres of
          live <hi rend="italic">Animals</hi> being <lb/>Contractile, Tonick, and ſpringy <lb/>when
          a hard pointed Body enters <lb/>them (which is the Caſe in all <lb/>bodily Pain) the parts
          by their <lb/>contractile Nature, fly from, re- <lb/>cede as much as poſſibly they can
          <lb/>the wounding Inſtrument; this <lb/>appears from the large gaſh of a <lb/>Wound, made
          acroſs the Fi- <lb/>bres of a Muſcle; in the conti- <lb/>nual bending to the other Side,
          <lb/>when any Part of us is pain'd; in <lb/>the Cramps and Convulſions, <lb/>nay, and
          ſometimes Fevers pro- <lb/>duced by intenſe acute Pain. <lb/>Pleaſure on the contary,
          relaxes <lb/>the Fibres by a ſoft and Bland <lb/>(or as the Mathematicians ſpeak) <lb/>a
          Commenſurate and Harmonious <lb/>Touch, it acts on the Fibres as <pb n="57"/>
          <lb/>two uniſon and concordant Mu- <lb/>ſical Inſtruments act on one an- <lb/>other; and
          by ſtroaking, ſoftning, <lb/>and ſmoothing, comes at laſt in- <lb/>tirely to relax and
          unbend them. <lb/>The Parts of the Fibres run after, <lb/>follow, and purſue, and at laſt
          <lb/>break their Union in ſome degree <lb/>to reach ſuch a demulcent touch. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Wou'd not any one that impli- <lb/>citly believed in you, imagine from <lb/>this
        paſſage, that every individual <lb/><hi rend="italic">Animal Fibre</hi>, was a rational
        Being, <lb/>and had the Power of diſcerning at <lb/>a diſtance, what was convenient or
        <lb/>hurtful to it? Since you ſay they <lb/>fly from a deſtructive Object, and <lb/>purſue
        that from which they can <lb/>receive Benefit. And if your Ar- <lb/>gument of the great Gaſh
        in a Muſ- <lb/>cle, from the Fibres being cut tranſ- <lb/>verſly, be of any weight, they
        muſt <lb/>out-live the Perſon to whom they <lb/>belong; for the ſame thing happens <lb/>in
        the Muſcles of a dead Body, a <lb/>conſiderable Time after Life is ex- <pb n="58"/>
        <lb/>tinguiſhed. This is a Circumſtance <lb/>very well known to all thoſe, who <lb/>have
        ſtudied <hi rend="italic">Anatomy</hi>, in that me- <lb/>thod by which the Knowledge of it
        <lb/>can only be attained. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When one winds up a Fiddle <lb/>ſtring till it breaks, does not the <lb/>two Ends fly
        back in the ſame man- <lb/>ner, as the Fibres of a Muſcle when <lb/>cut tranſverſly? Here,
        contrary to <lb/>your <hi rend="italic">Chimera</hi>, the broken Ends of the <lb/>String
        retreat from one another to- <lb/>wards the deſtructive Powers that <lb/>divided it.And this
        will happen <lb/>to every <hi rend="italic">Elaſtick Fibre</hi>, whether you <lb/>cut it, or
        extend it till it breaks. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Muſcles in all live Bodies, <lb/>even in what we call their relaxed <lb/>State, are
        in ſome meaſure Inflated, <lb/>and their Fibres endure a proporti- <lb/>onable degree of
        Tenſion, for if <lb/>they were not inflated they could <lb/>not be extended, and if they
        were <lb/>not <note place="bottom" n="" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>‖ <hi rend="italic" n="‖">Fibræ nullam habent Elaſticitatem, niſi certa cum <gap
                reason="illegible"/>
              <lb/><unclear>ſint tenſæ</unclear></hi>. <hi rend="align-right">S'Graveſand, de <hi
                rend="italic">Elaſt</hi>.</hi>
          </p>
        </note> extended they wou'd not be <pb n="59"/>
        <lb/>Elaſtick, and if they were not Ela- <lb/>ſtick the cut ends wou'd not recede <lb/>from
        one another. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And in Muſcular motion, tho' the <lb/>Extremity's of the Muſcles are <lb/>brought
        nearer, yet we will find <lb/>the length of the Fibres increaſed <lb/>by this Action, if we
        conſider them <lb/>through all the Angles, made by the <lb/>tranſverſe Fibres which bind
        them <lb/>together. And the Fibres of a <hi rend="italic">Muſ- <lb/>cle</hi>, being extended
        in Proportion <lb/>as it is inflated, it is therefore, that <lb/>exquiſite pain is felt in
        violent <lb/>Cramps and Convulſions, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If a Fibre's being made longer, at <lb/>the ſame time its Extremities are <lb/>brought
        nearer, ſhou'd ſeem a pa- <lb/>radox to you; only conſider what <lb/>happens to a
        Bow-ſtring, when one <lb/>draws it to ſhoot off an Arrow; in <lb/>this Action, tho' the two
        Ends of <lb/>the String are brought nearer, yet <lb/>the length of it will be increaſed,
        <lb/>in proportion to the reſiſtance of the <lb/>Bow, and the Power which draws <lb/>the
        String. </p>
      <pb n="60"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>What we call (but very impro- <lb/>perly) bodily pain, never happens <lb/>but when the
        Fibres are extended <lb/>beyond their Natural length; and <lb/>for that reaſon, an Inciſion
        made <lb/>with a blunt Inſtrument, ragged in <lb/>the Edge, gives more pain, than <lb/>that
        which is made with one that is <lb/>ſharp and ſmoother; becauſe the <lb/>firſt draws the
        Fibres a greater length, <lb/><unclear>bef</unclear>ore it can divide them, than the
          <lb/><unclear>laſt</unclear>. And hence it is, that in <hi rend="italic">Am-
          <lb/>putations</hi> they always with a ſharp <lb/>Inſtrument carefully ſeparate the
          <lb/><hi rend="italic"><unclear>Perioſtium</unclear></hi> from the Bone, where the
        <lb/>Saw is to be apply'd, to avoid the <lb/>painful Tenſion of its Fibres, by <lb/>the
        Teeth of the Saw. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And when ſuch Pain is produced <lb/>from an internal Cauſe, it happens <lb/>from the
        Obſtruction of ſome part <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Animal Fluid</hi>, by which
        <lb/>means the Veſſels in that part ſwell, <lb/>and the Fibres which compoſe their
        <lb/>Sides, are ſtretch'd and in danger <lb/>of being broke, and tore aſſunder, <pb n="61"/>
        <lb/>in proportion to the increaſe of the <lb/>obſtructed Fluid. And the Intenſe- <lb/>neſs
        of the Pain increaſes with the <lb/>Tumor. Are not the Fibres ex- <lb/>tended in the Tumor,
        while an Ab- <lb/>ſceſs is forming? And in the Caſe <lb/>of an Exoſtoſis, does not the Tumor
        <lb/>of the Bone, extend the Fibres of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Perioſtium</hi>? Is it not
        from the <lb/>Tenſion then, and not from the <lb/>Criſping up of the Fibres, as you
        <lb/>Term it, that theſe Diſeaſes cauſe <lb/>Pain? Theſe things are ſo well <lb/>known to
        every one, who deſerves <lb/>the Name of a Phyſician, that I am <lb/>ſorry I ſhou'd have
        occaſion to men- <lb/>tion them to you. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But you are poſitive <note place="margin" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Page 215</note>
        <q rend="diple quotes">"That <lb/>"Pain moſt certainly criſps up, con- <lb/>"ſtricts and
          contracts the <hi rend="italic">Animal <lb/>Fibres</hi>" </q>: Now if the Fibres are
        <lb/>ſometimes ſhortn'd and criſp'd up, <lb/>as you call it, and if it be a Diſeaſe,
        <lb/>then according to you, the Pain <lb/>muſt precede the Diſorder, but how <lb/>pain
        ſhou'd exiſt by it ſelf whithout <pb n="62"/>
        <lb/>a Diſeaſe to produce it, is what I <lb/>dare ſay no body can imagine. <lb/>What is
        commonly called bodily <lb/>Pain, as I take it, (and I believe I <lb/>ſpeak the ſenſe of
        every reaſonable <lb/>Man) is a diſagreeable Senſation, <lb/>ariſing from ſome Diſorder in
        the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Animal Machine</hi>; it is often the <lb/>Conſequence, but never
        can be the <lb/>Cauſe of any Diſorder. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>What I have ſaid, I think ſuffi- <lb/>ciently ſhows, how far your Know- <lb/>ledge in
        the <hi rend="italic">Animal Oeconomy</hi> ex- <lb/>tends; as to your Skill in <hi
          rend="italic">Pharmacy</hi>, <lb/>every Apothecary that reads the <lb/>Receipt of you
        Cordial, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> may <lb/>determine. And that no Man can <lb/>be
        quallified for a Phyſician, that is <lb/>ignorant of both or any of theſe, I <lb/>may
        venture to affirm, is a Truth <lb/>as evident as any Propoſition in <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Euclid</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Nor have you ſucceeded better in <lb/>you Philoſophical Diſſertation upon <lb/>the
        Paſſions, you ſay, <note place="margin" n="‖" rend="size(0.5)">‖ Page 152</note>
        <q rend="diple quotes">Paſſion may <lb/>be denied, the Sentiments pro- <pb n="63"/>
          <lb/>duced on the Soul, by external <lb/>Objects, either Spiritual ones im-
          <lb/>mediately, or Material ones, by <lb/>the mediation of the Organs of <lb/>the Body.
          Now how can the <lb/>Soul perceive any thing from out- <lb/>ward Object, without receiving
          <lb/>ſome impreſſion from them? And <lb/>how can ſuch impreſſions get acceſs <lb/>to our
          Minds, but by the mediation <lb/>and avenues of our Senſes? And <lb/>are not all the
          Organs of our Senſes <lb/>bodily Organs? </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>You tell us <note place="margin" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† Page153</note>
        <q rend="diple quotes">The acute Paſſi- <lb/>ons whether pleaſurable or pain- <lb/>ful have
          much the ſame effect, <lb/>and work after the ſame manner, <lb/>as acute Diſeaſes do, they
          effect <lb/>a brisk and lively Circulation of <lb/>the Fuids, criſp up and conſtrict
          <lb/>the Solids for ſome time. Thus <lb/>ſudden guſts of Joy or Grief, <lb/>Pleaſure of
          Pain, ſtimulate and <lb/>ſpur the nervous Fibres, and <lb/>Coats of the <hi rend="italic"
            >Animal Tubes</hi>; and <lb/>thereby give a celerity and brisker <pb n="64"/>
          <lb/>motion to their included Fluids". <lb/>There is ſomething ſo extravagantly <lb/>wild
          in this Notion (tho' you have <lb/>often expreſs'd your ſelf much to <lb/>the ſame
          Purpoſe) that I am truly <lb/>at a loſs what Anſwer to make to <lb/>ſo odd a propoſition
            <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> that the <lb/>Perceptions and Senſations of the <lb/>Mind
          fly about the Body in the form <lb/>of a palpable Fluid, which contains <lb/>hard and
          pointed Bodies; for ſuch <lb/>they muſt be, to ſtimulate the Fibres <lb/>in the manner you
          contend for. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That a great part of the nervous <lb/>Fluid is govern'd by the affections <lb/>of the
        Mind, is evident from the <lb/>Bodily motions which depend upon <lb/>the Will. And as the
          <hi rend="italic">Mind</hi> is dif- <lb/>ferently affected, it may no doubt <lb/>reſtrain
        or increaſe the flow of <lb/>this Fluid to the detriment of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >Animal Oeconomy</hi>. But you af- <lb/>firm that theſe very Senſations and
        <lb/>Affections of the <hi rend="italic">Mind</hi>, which we <lb/>term Pain and Pleaſure
        (not as they <lb/>prevail upon the <hi rend="italic">Mind</hi> to act upon <pb n="65"/>
        <lb/>its Organs,) but act as Solids them- <lb/>ſelves, to Deſtroy or Preſerve us. <lb/>And
        thus you ſay the Senſations of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Mind</hi> create <hi rend="italic"
          >Bodily Pain</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But all Senſations, whether plea- <lb/>ſant or painful, exiſt no where but <lb/>in the
          <hi rend="italic">Mind</hi>, and however it be <lb/>common to call that diſagreeable
        <lb/>Senſation, which ariſes from any <lb/>Diſorder in the <hi rend="italic">Animal
          Organs</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Bo- <lb/>dily Pain</hi>, to diſtinguiſh it from o-
        <lb/>ther painful Affections of the <hi rend="italic">Mind</hi>, <lb/>which do not proceed
        from that <lb/>Cauſe; yet in <hi rend="italic">Philoſophical Reaſon- <lb/>ing</hi>, no
        Phraſe nor Expreſſion, ſhou'd <lb/>be admitted, that is not ſtrictly a- <lb/>greeable to
        Truth. And tho' the <lb/>Soul readily perceives, when the Bo- <lb/>dy is either diſorder'd,
        or better diſ- <lb/>poſed for performing the Functions <lb/>neceſſary to <hi rend="italic"
          >Life and Health</hi>; yet <lb/>the Organs themſelves are incapable <lb/>of any Senſation,
        and conſequently <lb/>there is no ſuch thing in Nature as <lb/><hi rend="italic">Bodily
          Pain</hi>; and therefore that <lb/>Phraſe ought never to be uſed, e- <pb n="66"/>
        <lb/>ſpecially where cloſe Reaſoning is <lb/>required. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But you ſeem to be of another <lb/>Opinion, and tell us † <note place="margin" n="†"
          rend="size(0.5)">† Page 163</note>
        <q rend="diple quotes">That <lb/>Beauty or Perfection gives plea- <lb/>ſure to both Parts of
          the Com- <lb/>pound </q>. That is to the <hi rend="italic">Mind</hi> and <lb/>its Organs;
        I thought there had not <lb/>been a thinking Man in Being, who <lb/>did not know, that the
        Organs of the <lb/>Body were compoſed of meer Matter, <lb/>and conſequently incapable of any
        <lb/>Senſation; and that Knowledge and <lb/>Perception, can only exiſt in the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Mind</hi>, and is the diſtinguiſhing Cha- <lb/>racter of it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I have a better Opinion of you, <lb/>than to believe you mean, what I <lb/>think this
        Paſſage implys; for ſince <lb/>Knowledge and Perception, are theſe <lb/>eſſential Quallities
        of the Soul, which <lb/>denote its exiſtence; and ſince all <lb/>things which are endued
        with the <lb/>ſame Properties, muſt neceſſarily be <lb/>of the ſame Species and Nature;
        <lb/>why ſhou'd we then believe the Soul <pb n="67"/>
        <lb/>immortal, if theſe Properties from <lb/>whence we derive our belief of its
        <lb/>Immortallity, are common to the <lb/>Body which evidently periſhes? <lb/>Nor does the
        Abſurdity of this No- <lb/>tion of yours end here, for when <lb/>we conſider it, with what
        you call <lb/>the 4th <hi rend="italic">Prop.</hi> of this Diſſertation, <lb/>we will find
        them amount to the <lb/>moſt hideous <hi rend="italic">Hypotheſis</hi> that ever <lb/>was
        imagin'd; equally ſhocking and <lb/>repugnant to Reaſon: Your Words <lb/>are theſe, <note
          place="margin" n="‖" rend="size(0.5)">‖ Page 149</note>
        <q rend="diple quotes">As in Bodies there is <lb/>a Principle of <hi rend="italic"
            >Gravity</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Attract- <lb/>ion</hi>, whereby, <hi rend="italic">in
            vacuo</hi>, they tend <lb/>to one another, and wou'd unite <lb/>according to certain <hi
            rend="italic">Laws</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Li- <lb/>mitations</hi> eſtabliſh'd by the
            <hi rend="italic">Author</hi>
          <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>: So there is an <hi rend="italic">Analo- <lb/>gous
            Principle</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Spirits</hi>, whereby <lb/>they wou'd as certainly,
          in their <lb/>proper vacuity, be <hi rend="italic">attracted</hi> by, <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">tend</hi> to, and <hi rend="italic">unite</hi> with one ano- <lb/>ther;
          and their firſt <hi rend="italic">Author</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Cen- <lb/>tre</hi>, and
          the <hi rend="italic">Rock out of which <lb/>they were hewn</hi> (to uſe a Scripture <pb
            n="68"/>
          <lb/>Phraſe) as the <hi rend="italic">Planets</hi> wou'd to <lb/>one another, and to the
            <hi rend="italic">Sun</hi>
        </q>. &amp;c. <lb/>Now if the Sun be to the <hi rend="italic">Supreme <lb/>Power</hi>, as
        the Stone is to the Rock <lb/>from whence it is hewn, then the <lb/>Soul muſt be of the ſame
        Nature <lb/>and Species with GOD himſelf; <lb/>and not only this; but if the Pro-
        <lb/>perties of the Soul are common to <lb/>the Body (as you have ſaid they are) <lb/>then
        not only the Soul, but the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Supreme Power</hi> it ſelf, muſt be of
        <lb/>the ſame Nature with the Body, <lb/>which every Days Experience ſhows <lb/>us, is <hi
          rend="italic">Finite</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Corruptible</hi>. But <lb/>as this
        pretended Reaſoning of yours <lb/>cou'd only be the produce of a per- <lb/>plexed
        imagination, it deſerves Pity <lb/>rather than Reprehenſion; and a <lb/>Man muſt be diveſted
        of all Regard <lb/>to the dignity of <hi rend="italic">Human Nature</hi>, to <lb/>be able to
        read it, without having <lb/>Compaſſion for the Author. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <note place="margin" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† Page 1<gap reason="illegible"/></note> You
        deſire the Tender and the <lb/>Valetudinary to guard againſt Paſ- <lb/>ſion: You may as well
        propoſe to <pb n="69"/>
        <lb/>cure a Man of a Fever by bidding <lb/>him be well; for as the Paſſions of <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">Mind</hi> depend upon the Habit <lb/>and Conſtitution of the Body, a
        <lb/>Man whoſe Habit of Body, natura- <lb/>ly produces theſe Emotions we call <lb/>Paſſions,
        can as well hinder his Pulſe <lb/>to beat, as ſuppreſs them, till that <lb/>Habit which
        gives them Birth is <lb/>changed: Indeed there may ſome- <lb/>times ſuch means be uſed, as
        will al- <lb/>ter in ſome meaſure this untoward <lb/>Habit, and give a Man conſiderable
        <lb/>relief, and make him leſs ſubject to <lb/>theſe miſerable Diſorders; yet there
        <lb/>being great variety of Cauſes, which <lb/>produce theſe Ills upon the <hi rend="italic"
          >Minds</hi>
        <lb/>of Men; to preſcribe a Method for <lb/>curing this Ill, without knowing <lb/>the true
        Cauſe, it will be ſo far from <lb/>having an equal Chance of bringing <lb/>about the deſired
        Effect, that there <lb/>will be as many Odds againſt it, for <lb/>making the Caſe more
        deſperate, <lb/>as there are Cauſes more that one <lb/>capable of producing the Diſtemper. </p>
      <pb n="70"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If you or any Body ſhould <lb/>think me too ſevere, and alledge in <lb/>your behalf,
        that however faulty <lb/>your Performance may be, yet ſince <lb/>you did your beſt, Mankind
        are ſtill <lb/>oblig'd to you for your Endeavours. <lb/>I wou'd ask you, or any that wou'd
        <lb/>plead in this manner for you, if you <lb/>were to purchaſe any thing for your
        <lb/>conveniency, that you cou'd not be <lb/>a competent Judge of, till you had <lb/>tried
        it; and if a Perſon whoſe In- <lb/>tegrity you depend upon, ſhould <lb/>ſell you that which
        is damaged and <lb/>good for nothing, for the very beſt <lb/>of its Kind; and ſuppoſe the
        Pre- <lb/>ſervation or Loſs of your Life, or <lb/>Health, depended upon the differ-
        <lb/>ence; I wou'd, I ſay, ask how far <lb/>this Man's telling you, it was the beſt <lb/>he
        had to diſpoſe of, would ſerve <lb/>to preſerve his Credit with you? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I would not here be miſunder- <lb/>ſtood, and ſuppoſed to write this <lb/>for the
        Benefit of Phyſicians, who I <lb/>look upon generally Speaking, to <pb n="71"/>
        <lb/>be the Bane of Mankind. And I <lb/>believe it wou'd be better for the <lb/>World, that
        the Practice of Phyſick <lb/>was quite aboliſhed; for tho' many <lb/>wou'd ſuffer in wanting
        theſe helps <lb/>that they might receive from the <lb/>Hands of able Phyſicians, yet I am
        <lb/>perſwaded their number wou'd be ſo <lb/>ſmall, in proportion to thoſe who <lb/>are
        daily tortur'd and murder'd, by <lb/>ignorant Pretenders to that <hi rend="italic">Art</hi>,
        that <lb/>People in general wou'd receive great <lb/>benefit and relief by being freed from
        <lb/>ſo great a Curſe as Phyſicians gene- <lb/>rally are, </p>
      <signed rend="italic">I am, <lb/><hi rend="align-right"><hi rend="roman">SIR</hi>, &amp;c.
        </hi>
      </signed>
      <dateline rend="size(0.75) hanging indentall">
        <lb/>London, <hi rend="italic">November</hi>, <lb/>1724. </dateline>
      <postscript rend="italic">
        <label rend="roman space indent">
          <lb/>P. S. </label>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">Y</hi>OU very obligeingly inſinuate <lb/>in the Preface to your<hi
            rend="roman"> Eſſay of <lb/>Health</hi>, that this was the laſt time you <lb/>wou'd
          treſpaſs upon the <hi rend="roman">Publick</hi> in <lb/><unclear>t</unclear>his manner;
          this I thought was very <lb/>kind in you, and I was in Hopes it <lb/>wou'd have attoned
          for all that was <pb n="72"/>
          <lb/>to follow; but upon reading further, <lb/>I found my ſelf miſtaken. And if I <lb/>had
          any Influence over you, I wou'd <lb/>perſwade you once more to appear in <lb/><hi
            rend="roman">Print</hi>, and acknowledge your <hi rend="roman">Fault</hi> for <lb/>this
          laſt performance; which is (if <lb/>poſſible) worſe performed, and may <lb/>be of much
          worſe conſequence than any <lb/>of your former<choice>
            <corr>.</corr>
            <sic/>
          </choice>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>You ſay <note place="margin" rend="roman size(0.5)" n="*">* Page 92.</note>
          <q rend="diple quotes">God was forced to <lb/>ſhorten the Life of Man, to prevent <lb/>the
            Increaſe of wickedneſs, <hi rend="roman">&amp;c</hi>
          </q>. If <lb/>you had been able to prove this, Man- <lb/>kind might have thought
          Charitably of <lb/>your performance, and believed you in- <lb/>tended a further
          Reformation, by mak- <lb/>ing their Lives yet <hi rend="roman">Shorter</hi> and more
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">Miſerable</hi>; but as the matter now <lb/>ſtands, I know but one
          thing you can <lb/>plead for your excuſe, which I leave you <lb/>to gueſs at: And then
          your Book may <lb/>be of ſome uſe, ſince it contains almoſt <lb/>in every Page an ample
          and convince- <lb/>ing Teſtimony of it. </p>
      </postscript>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
