<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: An essay on the power of nature and art, in curing
          diseases</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">AN ESSAY On the POWER of NATURE and ART, IN Curing DISEASES: To which
              are annexed Impartial Reflections on JAMES's Powder.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T61150</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T61150"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for W. Owen, at Temple-Bar.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1753</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="3"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="51"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3306558678</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K053196.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="General treatises"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <head rend="align-center space"><lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">PREFACE. </hi></head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">THE medical reader will readily <w part="I"
              >diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">cover</w> part of the following <hi rend="roman">Eſſay,</hi>
            to<lb/>be extracted from the works of the celebrated <lb/><hi rend="roman">Hoffman,</hi>
            a name well known to the learned <lb/>world.</hi></p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">The obſervations 'tis apprehended will be
            <lb/>ſupported by the authorities</hi><note place="bottom" n="*">* Vid. Hippocrates,
            Celſus, Caelius Aurelianus, <lb/>Lommius, Sydenham, Baglivi, Hoffman, Friend, <lb/>Mead,
            Bacon, Boyle, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> to whom we have <lb/>not conſtantly
            referred, in order to avoid prolixity, <lb/>except where the nature of the ſubject
            abſolutely <lb/>require their own words; but the ſentiments of theſe <lb/>authors, will
            eaſily be diſcovered in the abſtract, <lb/>by thoſe acquainted with them. </note>
          <hi rend="italic">produced, the <lb/>univerſal aſſent of all the <hi rend="roman"
              >rationaliſts</hi> in <lb/>phyſic, and indeed we hope of every rational <lb/>man</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">A plain and perſpicuous ſtyle is what we <lb/>have
            chiefly aimed at, in order to adapt the <lb/>ſubject, to the comprehenſion of every
            reader; <lb/>and we can't help wiſhing this method more <lb/>frequently purſued by
            phyſical writers, that <lb/>the medical ſtudy might be rendered more <w part="I"
              >en-</w><lb/><w part="F">tertaining</w> and general: for we are <w part="I"
              >thorough-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> ſatisfyed, the art would be no ſufferer
            <lb/>thereby, but the imputations it is charged with, </hi><pb xml:id="page_3"/><lb/><hi
            rend="italic">as an obſure, perplexing ſtudy, by this means <lb/>baniſhed, and itſelf
            receive new luſtre, in <lb/>proportion to its being more diffuſed.</hi></p>

        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">The many errors ſo frequently committed in <lb/>the
            adminiſtring of <hi rend="roman">Noſtrums, Univerſal <w part="I">Me-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >dicines</w>,</hi> and particularly for ſome time paſt, <lb/>of <hi rend="italic"
              >James</hi>'s <hi rend="italic">powder,</hi> induced us to point out to <lb/>the <hi
              rend="italic">favourers</hi> of ſuch medicines, the <w part="I">inconve-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">niences</w> and danger, they ſometimes expoſe <lb/>themſelves too, by their
            imprudence, and <w part="I">cre-</w><lb/><w part="F">dulity</w>; in attaching themſelves
            to <hi rend="roman">this,</hi> or <hi rend="roman">any <lb/>other medicine,</hi> without
            proper reſtrictions. </hi></p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>To guard therefore againſt ſuch deluſions, <lb/>and to render the <hi
            rend="roman">unphyſical</hi> reader better <lb/>qualified to decide, in an affair of ſo
          much <lb/>importance, as his own health, and life, is <lb/>the purport of this <hi
            rend="roman">Eſſay;</hi> where by <w part="I">demon-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtrating</w>
          the influence <hi rend="roman">Nature</hi> has over many <lb/>diſeaſes, he may the readier
          judge of <w part="I">medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cal</w> aſſiſtance in general, and on what
          plan, <lb/>it can beſt be conducted. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Should we have ſet this affair in a clearer <lb/>light, than it has
          yet appeared in, to the <hi rend="italic">gene-<lb/>rality,</hi> our deſign will be
          ſufficiently anſwered, <lb/>and as truth and impartiality were our cheif <lb/>motives, we
          ſhall as little regard cenſure, as <lb/>we court applauſe; </p>

        <p rend="italic"><lb/><note place="inset"><hi rend="roman">Content, if hence th' unlearn'd
              their wants may view, <lb/>Th' learn'd reflect on what before they knew</hi></note>.
        </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_4"/>
        <head rend="align-center space"><lb/>AN <lb/><hi rend="size(2.5)">ESSAY</hi>
          <lb/>ON THE <lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)">Power <hi rend="italic">of</hi> NATURE <hi
              rend="italic">and</hi> ART,</hi>
          <lb/>IN <lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)">Curing DISEASES, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
          </hi></head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>Decorative frame around the letter "N".</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <hi rend="dc(5)">N</hi>OTwithſtanding the <w part="I">indefa-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tigable</w> labours of ſo many <lb/>able men, for more than two <lb/>thouſand years
          paſt, to bring <lb/>the art of phyſick to a <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">gree</w>
          of perfection the other ſciences have <lb/>attained; notwithſtanding the great <w part="I"
            >pro-</w>
          <pb xml:id="page_5" n="2"/><lb/><w part="F">gress</w>,that has been made in many branches
          <lb/>of this art; and how enlightened ſoever we <lb/>may have been by the improvements and
          <lb/>diſcoveries of the laſt century; yet it muſt <lb/>be confeſſed, that the cure of many
            <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">eaſes</w>, is not yet arrived to a degree of
          <lb/>perfection; or is <hi rend="italic">infallibility</hi> ever like to be <lb/>an
          attribute of phyſick. To free a man <lb/>from pain, and to ſave him from <w part="I"
            >deſtruc-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, is in itſelf noble and god-like, nor is <lb/>it
          to be wondered, that the firſt <w part="I">phyſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cians</w> were
          deified, or that thoſe, who <lb/>have excelled in this art ſince, have been <lb/>highly
          eſteemed and honoured; for as in <lb/><hi rend="italic">natural</hi> things, the <hi
            rend="italic">ſun</hi> is the author and <lb/>fountain of life, ſo the phyſician who <w
            part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerves</w> life, ſeems a ſecond origin <w part="I"
            >there-</w><lb/><w part="F">of</w>.<note place="bottom" n="*">* Lord Bacon's doctrine of
            the human body. <lb/>Shaw's edit. Sect. 9. vol. 1. </note> Yet happy would it be for
          mankind, <lb/>if a more expeditious method of curing <lb/>ſome <hi rend="italic"
            >fevers</hi> could be diſcovered, <w part="I">conſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtent</w> with
          the patients ſafety? What <w part="I">emo-</w><lb/><w part="F">luments</w> and applauſes
          would that man <lb/>deſerve of his country, whoſe ſtudies had <pb xml:id="page_6" n="3"
          /><lb/>been ſo fortunate to diſcover a medicine, <lb/>which had the power of checking the
          <lb/>exorbitance of a <hi rend="italic">fever,</hi> eluding its force, <lb/>and entirely
          eradicating the latent cauſe? <lb/>How happy, I ſay, if this could be <w part="I"
            >effect-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> without waiting the tedious courſe, <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">nature</hi> is ſometimes obſerved to take, in <lb/>fitting and preparing
          the <hi rend="italic">febrile</hi> matter for <lb/>a ſeparation, and expulſion from the
          blood, <lb/>in order to a ſalutary <hi rend="italic">criſis;</hi> or if even <lb/>thoſe
          aſſiſtances <hi rend="italic">art</hi> has hitherto employed, <lb/>in accelerating theſe
            <hi rend="italic">criſes,</hi> or rendering <lb/>them unneceſſary, could be effected
          <lb/>with leſs danger. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Such a purſuit and ſtudy is <w part="I">undoubt-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >edly</w> laudable and beneficent, and tho' <lb/>the whole ſcience may be too abſtruſe,
          <lb/>and extenſive, for the human mind to <lb/>comprehend;<lb/><note place="bottom" n="†"
            >† Of all the things that <hi rend="italic">nature</hi> hath created, <lb/>the <hi
              rend="italic">human body</hi> is moſt capable of <hi rend="italic">relief;</hi> tho'
            this <lb/><hi rend="italic">relief</hi> be the moſt liable to error. For as the <w
              part="I">ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F">tilty</w>, and variety of the ſubject affords many
              <w part="I">oppor-</w><lb/><w part="F">tunities</w> of <hi rend="italic">cure;</hi> ſo
            likewiſe great facility of <hi rend="italic">miſtake.</hi>
            <lb/>And therefore, as this <hi rend="italic">art,</hi> eſpecially at preſent,
            <lb/>ſtands among the moſt <hi rend="italic">conjectural ones,</hi> ſo the <w part="I"
              >en-</w><lb/><w part="F">quiry</w> into it, is to be placed among the moſt <w part="I"
              >ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F">tile</w> and difficult. Lord <hi rend="italic">Bacon,</hi>
            ib. </note> though, like the <hi rend="italic">philoſo-</hi>
          <pb xml:id="page_7" n="4"/><lb/><hi rend="italic">pher's ſtone</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
            >longitude,</hi> it ſeems <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tended</w> with
          inſuperable difficulties; yet, <lb/>when diſcoveries, in particular branches, <lb/>are
          offered to us with modeſty, candour, <lb/>and impartiality, abſtracted from <hi
            rend="italic">merce-<lb/>nary views,</hi> or the arts of <hi rend="italic">deſigning
            men;</hi>
          <lb/>they certainly merit our notice, and <w part="I">ſtrong-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w>
          demand our attention: but ſhould we <lb/>find they want theſe intrinſic characters,
          <lb/>theſe genuine marks of truth; that they <lb/>are ſupported by the <hi rend="italic"
            >ſophiſtry</hi> of the <lb/>artful and deſigning, or protected by the <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">bigottry</hi> of <hi rend="italic">credulous</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
            >improper judges;</hi>
          <lb/>ſure it becomes high time to unmask the <lb/><hi rend="italic">impoſtors,</hi> and
          detect the chicanerie; <w part="I">eſpe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cially</w> in ſo important a
          cauſe as that, <lb/>wherein our <hi rend="italic">healths</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
            >lives</hi> are ſo <w part="I">prin-</w><lb/><w part="F">cipally</w> concerned: for as
          all ages have <lb/>abounded with falſe <hi rend="italic">pretenders,</hi> who have
          <lb/>deluded the unwary, under the ſpecious <lb/>appearance of ſerving the publick, ſo <hi
            rend="italic">me-<lb/>dical</hi> impoſitions have been more <w part="I">noto-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">rious</w>, and ſucceſſful: nor indeed is it to <lb/>be wondered at, that this
            <hi rend="italic">tribe</hi> ſhould be ſo <lb/>numerous and prevalent, when ſuch <w
            part="I">en-</w><lb/><w part="F">couragements</w> are given them; and when <pb
            xml:id="page_8" n="5"/><lb/>we conſider how few are qualified to judge <lb/>properly,
          either of <hi rend="italic">diſeaſes,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">remedies;</hi>
          <lb/>or to diſtinguiſh between the <hi rend="italic">powers of <lb/>art,</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">the influence of nature.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Theſe</hi> are the chief points we ſhall
          <lb/>endeavour to render more obvious and <lb/>familiar, for it is neither our deſign, or
          <lb/>intention, to enquire into the cauſes, which <lb/>have retarded this wiſhed for
          perfection; <lb/>or to point out the obſtacles, which by <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſome</hi>
          are thought to have impeded the <lb/>completion of ſo noble a <hi rend="italic"
            >fabrick,</hi> after ſo <lb/>fair a foundation laid by our <hi rend="italic"
            >predeceſſors</hi>
          <lb/>of old: we ſhall therefore firſt obſerve, <lb/>that poſſibly an invariable method of
          <lb/>curing diſeaſes, can never be laid down, ſo <lb/>long as different temperaments of
          the air, <lb/>climates, ſeaſons, and conſtitutions, are ſo <lb/>frequently introducing new
          and various <lb/>diſeaſes; which, tho' often in many <w part="I">reſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >pects</w> ſimilar to others, which have <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceeded</w>
          them, yet do they differ from them <lb/>very eſſentially, and of courſe require very
          <lb/>different treatment. Without having <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">courſe</w> to
          the authorities of ſuch ſagacious <pb xml:id="page_9" n="6"/><lb/>writers, as Hippocrates,
          Sydenham, <w part="I">Boer-</w><lb/><w part="F">haave</w>, Hoffman, <hi rend="italic"
            >&amp;c.</hi> whoſe accurate and <lb/>faithful obſervations would be <w part="I"
            >indiſputa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w> in ſuch a point; Who is there <w part="I"
            >capa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w> of making proper remarks in practice, <lb/>to whom
          this truth has not occurred? <lb/>And who but from hence muſt have been <lb/>convinced,
          that in the direction of <hi rend="italic">medicine,</hi>
          <lb/>due attention muſt be paid to <hi rend="italic">particular <lb/>ſymptoms,</hi>
          without being ſlaviſhly attached <lb/>to <hi rend="italic">particular forms?</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But as the diligent obſervers<lb/><note place="bottom" n="§">§ Vid.
            Hippocrates, de morb. vulg. Lib. vi. Sect. <lb/>v. Celſus lib. 3. ch. 1. Lommii com. de
            ſanit. <lb/>tuend. Sydenham chap. of the continued fevers <lb/>of 1673-4-5. Swan<hi
              rend="italic">'s</hi> edit. p. 197. Hoffman in variis <lb/>locis. Baglivi. ch. 1.
            Boerhaavi orat: de <w part="I">commen-</w><lb/><w part="F">dando</w> ſtud. Hippocrates
            Van Sweiten in aphoriſm. <lb/>Boerhaavi in variis locis.</note> of <hi rend="italic"
            >nature's <lb/>laws,</hi> ingenuouſly confeſs, that in many <lb/>caſes ſhe is her own,
          and beſt phyſician; <lb/>and that we often attribute effects to <lb/>wrong cauſes, by
          charging that to the <hi rend="italic">re-<lb/>medy,</hi> which is due only to her <hi
            rend="italic">own efforts;</hi>
          <lb/>it may be neceſſary to conſider how far <lb/><hi rend="italic">nature</hi> may be
          ſaid to cure <hi rend="italic">diſeaſes,</hi>
          <w part="I">un-</w>
          <pb xml:id="page_10" n="7"/><lb/><w part="F">aſſiſted</w> by <hi rend="italic">art;</hi>
          to point out when it is in <lb/>her power to relieve <hi rend="italic">herſelf,</hi> and
          when <lb/>without the help of <hi rend="italic">art,</hi> ſhe would deſtroy <lb/>herſelf;
          and this will naturally lead us to <lb/>the true ſtudy of the <hi rend="italic">medical
            art.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As the word <hi rend="italic">nature</hi> is variouſly defined,
          <lb/>we deſire to be underſtood by it, the laws <lb/>of motion, originally implanted in
          the <lb/><hi rend="italic">machine,</hi> in order to ſet it in action, and <lb/>preſerve
          it ſo; by this natural mechaniſm <lb/>of our bodies, whatever prove injurious to <lb/>us
          is often thrown off ſome way, or other, <lb/>provided the courſe of <hi rend="italic"
            >nature</hi> be not <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">terrupted</w>. This power of <hi
            rend="italic">nature</hi> is ſo <lb/>extraordinary in ſome conſtitutions, that <lb/>in
          ſpite of all the blunders that are <w part="I">fre-</w><lb/><w part="F">quently</w>
          committed, men recover even from <lb/>the moſt dangerous fevers. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>That we may the better judge of the <lb/>nature of a diſeaſe, or
          fever, it may by <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſome</hi> perhaps be thought no uſeleſs <w
            part="I">digreſſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">on</w>, to enquire wherein <hi rend="italic"
            >health</hi> conſiſts, that <lb/>by a proper definition of the term, we may <lb/>the
          better underſtand, when it is perverted, <pb xml:id="page_11" n="8"/><lb/>and by what
          means, either of <hi rend="italic">nature,</hi> or <lb/><hi rend="italic">art,</hi> it is
          again reſtored. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The <hi rend="italic">health</hi> then of every animal body
          <lb/>depends on a regular, moderate, and <w part="I">equa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w>
          circulation, of a proper condition'd <lb/>blood, a due ſecretion, and execretion,<lb/> of
          the <hi rend="italic">juices</hi> or <hi rend="italic">humours</hi> from it, and a proper
          <lb/>degree of elaſticity in the ſolids. This <w part="I">cir-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >culation</w> once diſturbed, and theſe <w part="I">ſecreti-</w><lb/><w part="F">ons</w>
          once perverted, are the cauſe of almoſt <lb/>all diſeaſes. Thus from obſtructed <w
            part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſpiration</w>, or ſweats ſuddenly ſuppreſſed, the
          <lb/>fluids that ſhould freely flow off through <lb/>the pores and glands of the skin,
          recoil on <lb/>the blood, increaſe its quantity, and pervert <lb/>its quality: a
          redundancy of bile, or an <lb/>undue ſecretion of it in the liver, becomes <lb/>productive
          of many and various diſeaſes, <lb/>ſuch as bilious cholics, jaundices, <w part="I"
            >inflam-</w><lb/><w part="F">mations</w> of the liver, St. Anthony's fire, <lb/>fevers,
          and many other diſorders ariſing <lb/>from its acrimony and ſtimulus. From <lb/>this
          ſpecimen, we may judge of the ill <lb/>effects, which are the conſequence of the
          <lb/>reſt; for whenever theſe ſecretions are not <pb xml:id="page_12" n="9"
          /><lb/>regularly carried on, the conſtitution is ſure <lb/>to be injured; and theſe <hi
            rend="italic">humours</hi> or <hi rend="italic">juices</hi>
          <lb/>ſo amicable before, by being now <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">praved</w>, are
          made capable of producing <lb/>an infinity of diſorders. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>We come now to explain, what we <lb/>mean by <hi rend="italic"
            >nature</hi> curing diſeaſes, and how <lb/>or by what ways ſhe effects this purpoſe
          <lb/>and here among many others <hi rend="italic">ſhe</hi> takes, <lb/>to remove an
          offending enemy, brought <lb/>on frequently by a ſuppreſſion of one, <lb/>or other, of the
          above <hi rend="italic">ſecretions;</hi> if the <lb/>cauſe be ſlight, <hi rend="italic"
            >ſhe</hi> frequently throws off <lb/>the load of impure ſerum, by the glands <lb/>of the
          noſe and fauces, by coughs, a <w part="I">looſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w>, urine, and
          ſweats; which if untimely <lb/>ſuppreſſed by <hi rend="italic">art,</hi> are ſure to bring
          life <lb/>in danger, or at leaſt foretell a future <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >eaſe</w>. But her moſt general method, when <lb/>the diſeaſe is more important, is by
          raiſing <lb/>a <hi rend="italic">fever</hi> for her relief, and increaſing the <lb/>motion
          of the circulating fluids;<lb/><note place="bottom" n="*">* Vid. Hale's Haemaſtaticks,
            vol. ii. P. 101. </note> by this <lb/>means ſhe removes obſtructions, which <pb
            xml:id="page_13" n="10"/><lb/>threaten life; by this the ſuperfluous, <lb/>impure, and
          viſcid fluids, which choak up <lb/>the veſſels, are attenuated, diſperſed, and <lb/>thrown
          off by urine, ſtool, or perſpiration: <lb/>in other caſes, when the veſſels are too
          <lb/>turgid, <hi rend="italic">ſhe</hi> often relieves their diſtending <lb/>fullneſs, by
          burſting open their mouths, <lb/>and bringing on a ſalutary bleeding, by <lb/>thoſe of the
            <hi rend="italic">naſe, uterus,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">anus;</hi> and <lb/>thus
          delivers <hi rend="italic">berſelf</hi> from the oppreſſive <lb/>load. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe are ſome of the ways ſhe takes to <lb/>relieve herſelf in acute
          diſorders, as fevers: <lb/>nor is ſhe ſometimes leſs ſucceſſful, in the <lb/>cure of old,
          ſtubborn, and chronical <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">eaſes</w>; Aſthma's of long
          ſtanding have been <lb/>cured by a St. Anthony's fire thrown out <lb/>on the ſurface;
          epilepſies by ſcorbutic <lb/>eruptions; and even melancholy and <w part="I"
            >mad-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w> by the piles. However it muſt be <lb/>confeſſed that
          the <hi rend="italic">power of nature</hi> is not ſo <lb/>often manifeſt in the cure of
            <hi rend="italic">chronic,</hi> as <lb/><hi rend="italic">acute</hi> diſorders, which
          latter are often <lb/>effected ſolely by her own means, as the <lb/>former generally are
          by <hi rend="italic">art.</hi>
        </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_14" n="11"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>After having taken notice of the <w part="I">vari-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ous</w> ways <hi rend="italic">nature</hi> takes to relieve herſelf, <lb/>and obſerved,
          that the moſt greivous <lb/>diſeaſes are ſometimes happily terminated <lb/>and cured,
          without <hi rend="italic">medical</hi> aſſiſtance; few <lb/>arguments can be thought
          neceſſary to <lb/>inforce this ſtudy of <hi rend="italic">nature</hi> and her laws,
          <lb/>as preferable to any other; for if it is <lb/>moſt certain, that nature often
          prevails <lb/>over art, which ſhould always be her <lb/><hi rend="italic">aſſiſtant</hi>
          and <hi rend="italic">imitator,</hi> we may juſtly <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >clude</w>, that the method by which nature <lb/>alone cures diſeaſes ſhould be ſtudied,
          as <lb/>worthy our imitation, and more particular <lb/>regard. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>For whoever doth not attend to natures <lb/>motions in relieving her,
          will moſt <w part="I">cer-</w><lb/><w part="F">tainly</w> do her great injury; which is <w
            part="I">fre-</w><lb/><w part="F">quently</w> the caſe with thoſe, who before <lb/>the
          febrile matter is moveable and diſſolved, <lb/>or prepared for ſeparation, endeavour to <w
            part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">pel</w> it untimely, and by ways neither <w part="I"
            >adapt-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> to that purpoſe, or to which ſhe has <lb/>any
          tendency herſelf. Thus as Hoffman <w part="I">ob-</w><pb xml:id="page_15" n="12"/><lb/><w
            part="F">ſerves</w> * it is to be lamented, that we every <lb/>day ſee unskillful
          phyſicians, truſting too <lb/>much to their <hi rend="sc">Nostrums</hi>, without having
          <lb/>any regard to indications, method, or time, <lb/>with reſpect to the diſeaſe, and
          thereby <lb/>often bring the patient into extreme <w part="I">dan-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ger</w>; but if <hi rend="italic">nature</hi> be powerful enough <lb/>to elude the
          force of the medicine, and <lb/>triumph over the diſeaſe, they then <w part="I"
            >ar-</w><lb/><w part="F">rogantly</w> boaſt of the importance of the <lb/>cure, and gain
          both fame and rewards <lb/>by their raſhneſs; but ſuch imprudent <lb/>men are not to be
          truſted, for ſure it is <lb/>not the leaſt part of the phyſicians art, to <lb/>know the
          courſe, genius, and ſalutary <lb/>ways of nature, that he may not diſturb <lb/>her
          operations, or aſſiſt her improperly. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But notwithſtanding this power of <w part="I">na-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ture</w> in curing diſeaſes, 'tis evident there <lb/>are many, where ſhe wants
          aſſiſtance, and <lb/>would often deſtroy herſelf without timely <lb/>relief, by the very
          means ſhe endeavours <lb/>for her preſervation; the ſymptoms brought<lb/><note
            place="bottom">F. Hoffman, opera omnia phiſico medica fol. de <lb/>natura &amp; art.
            officac. vol. vi. p. 261. </note>
          <pb xml:id="page_16" n="13"/><lb/>on by her own efforts, being often more <lb/>dangerous
          than the diſeaſe itſelf; ſo that in <lb/>many diſeaſes, a great part of the phyſicians
          <lb/>work, is to appeaſe her fury, and correct <lb/>her errors; for being ſometimes
          tranſported <lb/>as it were, with a blind and impetuous <lb/>paſſion, ſhe unſeaſonable
          produces thoſe <lb/>dangerous, diſorders in the body, that <lb/>demand the ſuccour of art.
          Thus to what <lb/>ſalutary purpoſe are thoſe violent ſpaſms <lb/>which ariſe from ſome
          poiſons taken <w part="I">inter-</w><lb/><w part="F">nally</w>, but to retain the enemy,
          ſhe wants <lb/>to expell? Of what uſe to her, are thoſe <lb/>various convulſions, which
          ariſe from <w part="I">fla-</w><lb/><w part="F">tulencies</w> and worms in the bowels? To
          <lb/>what purpoſe thoſe direful pains, thoſe <lb/>vehement, and acute fevers, which ariſe
          <lb/>from the ſlighteſt injury, or puncture of <lb/>nerve, or tendon? Certainly theſe <w
            part="I">enor-</w><lb/><w part="F">mous</w> commotions are worſe than the <lb/>cauſe,
          for whoſe ſake according the <w part="I">Hel-</w><lb/><w part="F">montians</w>, they were
          by provident nature <lb/>appointed for her relief; for unleſs art <lb/>ſoon runs to her
          aſſiſtance, they will moſt <lb/>inevitably bring her into great danger, if <lb/>not
          deſtroy her. What ſuccour can nature <pb xml:id="page_17" n="14"/><lb/>bring to fixed
          inflammations of the head, <lb/>lungs, uterus, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> without the
          help of art. <lb/>The venereal lues was never cured by <lb/>nature. The dry and bilious
          cholic, with <lb/>ſome others, require the immediate <w part="I">aſſiſt-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ance</w> of art: inveterate ſchrophulous, <w part="I">ſcor-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >butic</w>, and leprous diſorders, nature never <lb/>removed. The gout, epilepſy,
          madneſs, <lb/>dropſies, gravel and ſtone, worms, and <lb/>many other diſorders that might
          be <w part="I">enu-</w><lb/><w part="F">merated</w>, tho' all of them are ſtrong proofs
          <lb/>of the little power nature has over them, <lb/>yet many of them are known to be cured
          by <lb/>the efficacy of medicine, and all of them <lb/>have been alleviated thereby. In
          ſhort with <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Boyle,</hi><note place="bottom" n="†">† Free inquiry
            into the vulgar notion of nature<lb/> Shaw's edit. p. 143. </note> we may look on a good
            <w part="I">phy-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſician</w>, not properly as a ſervant to nature,
          <lb/>but a counſellor, and a friendly aſſiſtant; <lb/>who in his patients body furthers
          thoſe <lb/>motions, and other things, that he judges <lb/>conducive to the welfare and
          recovery of <lb/>it; but as to thoſe he perceives likely to <lb/>be hurtful, either by
          encreaſing the diſeaſe, <pb xml:id="page_18" n="15"/><lb/>or otherwiſe endangering the
          patient, he <lb/>thinks it is his part to oppoſe or hinder, <lb/>tho' nature manifeſtly
          ſeems to endeavour <lb/>to increaſe, or carry on thoſe hurtful <w part="I">mo-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tions</w>. Thus many of the miſeries, to <lb/>which human nature is ſubject,
          may be <lb/>relieved by proper aſſiſtances, and with <lb/>Aſclepiades we may ſay, <hi
            rend="italic">naturam et prodeſſe <lb/>&amp; nocere.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It may be neceſſary to obſerve here, <lb/>that tho' <hi rend="italic"
            >art</hi> is chiefly inſtrumental in <lb/>the cure of chronical diſeaſes, yet it is
          <lb/>under the auſpices of <hi rend="italic">nature,</hi> and effected <lb/>by a proper
          imitation of her ways. What <lb/>elſe is meant by giving warm, ſtimulating, <lb/>pungent,
          and volatile medicines, with ſteel <lb/>and mineral waters, but to encreaſe the
          <lb/>motion of the circulating fluids, and <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">mote</w> a
          certain degree of <hi rend="italic">fever.</hi> Are not <lb/>the cures of ſome
          rheumatiſms, palſys, and <lb/>many other diſorders, accompliſhed by <lb/>theſe means; by
          attenuating and melting <lb/>down the viſcid fluids, and opening their <lb/>obſtructed
          channels by this accelerated <lb/>motion. Thus as a certain degree of <hi rend="italic"
            >fever</hi>
          <pb xml:id="page_19" n="16"/><lb/>is neceſſary to remove acute, ſo alſo <w part="I"
            >chroni-</w><lb/><w part="F">cal</w> diſorders; and as a late writer has <w part="I"
            >ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerved</w>, could a phyſician certainly raiſe a <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">fever,</hi> and keep it to what height he pleaſed, <lb/>many chronic
          diſorders might be thus <lb/>cured; but tho' this cannot be effected by <lb/>art, yet
          nature may be imitated by <w part="I">direct-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> the above
          medicines, which by <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">perience</w> have been found
          ſucceſſful for <lb/>this purpoſe, ſo that in many caſes, it may <lb/>be ſaid, the <hi
            rend="italic">fever</hi> is not the <hi rend="italic">diſeaſe,</hi> but <lb/>the <hi
            rend="italic">remedy, et dolor, eſt medicina doloris.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>From hence then we learn, that though <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >nature</hi> often cures diſeaſes, yet ſhe often <lb/>ſtands in need of medical help;
          tho' it is <lb/>more evidently obſerved in <hi rend="italic">chronic,</hi> than <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">acute</hi> caſes; for we ſpeak not of thoſe <lb/>which come under the
          ſurgeon's cogniſance, <lb/>where ſhe muſt often be deſtroyed, <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">out</w> immediate manual aſſiſtance. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nor is it the leaſt part of the phyſicians <lb/>skill to know when to
          give it, and to <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtinguſh</w> between the force of
          nature and <lb/>art, between the effects and bounds of <w part="I">me-</w>
          <pb xml:id="page_20" n="17"/><lb/><w part="F">dicine</w>. Happy is he then, who has made
          <lb/>nature his ſtudy, who knows when to <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtrain</w>
          her exorbitant, and when to rouſe <lb/>her languid motions; who foreſees when <lb/>to give
          her timely ſuccour, and can <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtinguiſh</w> when he does
          her moſt ſervice, by <lb/>attempting to do leaſt for her; for 'tis a <lb/>grand miſtake to
          conclude that <hi rend="italic">nature</hi>
          <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">ways</w> wants the aſſiſtance of <hi rend="italic"
            >art,</hi> it being <lb/>the beſt remedy ſometimes to <hi rend="italic">uſe none at
            all</hi>
          <lb/>But according to Lord <hi rend="italic">Bacon,</hi> men <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">monly</w> take a view of nature, as from a <lb/>remote eminence; and are too
          much <w part="I">a-</w><lb/><w part="F">muſed</w> with <hi rend="italic"
            >generalities:</hi> whereas if they <lb/>would deſcend and approach nearer to <w
            part="I">par-</w><lb/><w part="F">ticulars</w>, and more exactly and <w part="I"
            >conſiderate-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> examines into things themſelves, they
          <lb/>might make more ſolid and uſeful <w part="I">diſco-</w><lb/><w part="F">veries</w>.
          No doubt therefore, if phyſicians, <lb/>leaving generalities for a while, would
          <lb/>advance towards nature; they might be <lb/>able to <hi rend="italic">vary their art
            as diſtempers vary.</hi><lb/><note place="bottom" n="*">* Doctrine of the human body.
            Shaw's ed. <lb/>p. 97. </note>
        </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_21" n="18"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This knowledge however can only be <lb/>attained by experience, and
          ſedulous <w part="I">obſer-</w><lb/><w part="F">vation</w>, and a perfect acquaintance
          with <lb/>thoſe <hi rend="italic">indefatigable guides,</hi> who ſtudied <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">nature</hi> carefully, and have left us the fruits <lb/>of thoſe ſtudies
          on record: to this end <lb/>alſo a man ſhould be well acquainted with <lb/>natural
          philoſophy, the materia medica, <lb/>and the animal oeconomy; have a genius, <lb/>and
          penetrating ſagacity, to be able to <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtinguiſh</w> the
          true cauſes of diſeaſe, from <lb/>effects; the certain powers of medicine, <lb/>with the
          bounds of <hi rend="italic">nature</hi> and <hi rend="italic">art;</hi>for <lb/>there are
          in phyſick, as in the natural and <lb/>moral world, general laws, univerſal <w part="I"
            >pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſitions</w>, and a perpetual analogy, between <lb/>art and
          nature, that runs through the <lb/>whole ſcience for that purpoſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Let us therefore, ſays the great <hi rend="italic"
            >Pitcairn,</hi><lb/><note place="bottom" n="*">* Orat. on the art of phyſick. </note>
          <lb/>if we are inclined to deſerve well of the <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >publick</w> of phyſick, that is, of all mankind, <lb/>follow this excellent rule; for
          it is our duty <lb/>to compare the obſervations that have been <lb/>made by others, and
          continue to be made <pb xml:id="page_22" n="19"/><lb/>every where, upon diſeaſes and their
            <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">medies</w>, without any regard to opinions:
          <lb/>which are nothing in compariſon to the <lb/>certain conviction of our ſenſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But how few, as Dr. <hi rend="italic">Friend,</hi> has taken
          <lb/>notice, are qualified to make judicious <lb/>obſervations on their experience?<note
            place="bottom" n="†">† Hiſtory of phyſick, p. 308. vol. 1. </note> For the <lb/>word is
          often made uſe of, when the effects <lb/>do not plainly appear. He farther obſerves,
          <lb/>that a man may practice and practice all the <lb/>days of his life, and yet be never
          the wiſer <lb/>for his experience, if he neglects to make <lb/>the proper obſervations,
          which that <w part="I">expe-</w><lb/><w part="F">rience</w> might ſuggeſt to him; and it
          is not <lb/>very likely, he ſhould be over nice in his <lb/>obſervations, who conſtantly
          goes on in his <lb/>firſt tract, and has no other ſcheme, but <lb/>his own narrow notions
          in his view: <lb/>whereas the ſearcher of authors, has the <lb/>benefit of other men's
          experience, together <lb/>with his own, and it is from the joint <w part="I"
            >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">currence</w>, that we can hope for any <w part="I"
            >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſiderable</w> advancements of knowledge. <pb xml:id="page_23"
            n="20"/><lb/>Were it not for this, the oldeſt phyſician <lb/>would always be the beſt
          phyſician; and <lb/>there would be little or no difference, even <lb/>as to the <hi
            rend="italic">ſcientific</hi> part, between an old <lb/>nurſe, and the moſt regular
          profeſſor. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Thus is it plain that practice <hi rend="italic">alone</hi> will
          <lb/>not teach a man the art;<note place="bottom" n="*">* Barker's eſſay on the <hi
              rend="italic">agreement</hi> between <w part="I">an-</w><lb/><w part="F">tient</w> and
            modern phyſicians, p. 73. </note> for there are not <lb/>wanting inſtances of
          practitioners, who are <lb/>grown old in buſineſs, but for want of being <lb/>early
          inſtructed in the principles of the art, <lb/>are almoſt as abſolute ſtrangers to it, as
          <lb/>they were at firſt ſetting out. The practice <lb/>of theſe men has always been,
          empirical <lb/>and by receipts, and as their minds have <lb/>never been ſufficiently
          enlightened with <lb/>true ſcience, to purſue it properly; ſo they <lb/>catch at every <hi
            rend="italic">new medicine,</hi> like <w part="I">drown-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> men
          at every twig, in hopes of <w part="I">ſup-</w><lb/><w part="F">porting</w> a little
          longer a ſinking reputation. <lb/>Such is the fluctuating ſtate of the mind, <lb/>unleſs a
          man is thoroughly grounded in the <lb/>rudiments of his art; for like one perplexed
          <lb/>in a labyrinth, unleſs the right path is <pb xml:id="page_24" n="21"/><lb/>purſued,
          he is continually erring and <w part="I">miſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">taking</w> his way;
          treading again and again <lb/>in the ſame tract, till he is tired; yet is he <lb/>often
          deceived in the mazey round, and <lb/>frequently flatters himſelf, with the purſuit
          <lb/>of the true path. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This naturally leads us to enquire into <lb/>the force, and power, of
          ſome favourite <lb/>medicines, which are given in <hi rend="italic">acute fevers;</hi>
          <lb/>and are ſuppoſed now and then, to work <lb/>ſuch ſpeedy recoveries; when the cure in
          <lb/>general, rather depends upon a <hi rend="italic">due</hi>
          <w part="I">regula-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> in diet, and proper regimen in other
          <lb/>reſpects, than any <hi rend="italic">peculiar medicine:</hi> but <lb/>our fondneſs to
          ſuch remedies, generally <lb/>riſes in proportion to our <hi rend="italic">credulity, <w
              part="I">igno-</w><lb/><w part="F">rance</w>,</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
            >prejudices;</hi> for rather than <w part="I">attri-</w><lb/><w part="F">bute</w> any
          good change in the diſtemper, to <lb/>the power of ſuch regimen; it flatters the
          <lb/>vanity of ſome, to aſcribe it to a medicine <lb/>of his own preſcribing, tho' ever ſo
            <w part="I">inſig-</w><lb/><w part="F">nificant</w>. How often have the moſt ſimple
          <lb/>things, luckily timed at the criſis of a <lb/>fever, been applauded for effects, they
          had <lb/>no pretenſions to; for nature who often <pb xml:id="page_25" n="22"
          /><lb/>triumphs over ſlight obſtacles, little cares <lb/>to whom the honour is attributed,
          ſo that <lb/>ſhe herſelf comes off victorious. This <lb/>might be abundantly exemplified
          in a great <lb/>variety of inſtances, to the conviction of <lb/>the moſt ſanguine bigot:
          and indeed <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F">partial</w>, and competent judges, will
          readily <lb/>confeſs, that nothing is more difficult to <lb/>aſcertain, than the <hi
            rend="italic">true virtue</hi> of medicines: <lb/>for their effects in general rather
          take their <lb/>force, from the judgment of the phyſician, <lb/>in their juſt application,
          than from any <lb/>conſtant and inherent virtue of their own. <lb/>The learned Dr. <hi
            rend="italic">Friend</hi><note place="bottom" n="*">* Friend Emmenologia, de remediorum
            viribus. </note> hath curiouſly <lb/>obſerved, and ſhewn, that the different
          <lb/>operation of remedies, ariſes not from any <lb/>change of virtue in the medicament,
          which <lb/>continues always the ſame; but from the <lb/>different ſtate of the body,
          wherein it is <lb/>applied. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Thus the <hi rend="italic">bark</hi> taken in the fever fit,
          <lb/>ſhall often purge, between it, bind; <hi rend="italic">Opium</hi>
          <lb/>inſtead of controuling watchings, ſhall <w part="I">fre-</w>
          <pb xml:id="page_26" n="23"/><lb/><w part="F">quently</w> increaſe them; <hi rend="italic"
            >Aloes</hi> whoſe <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">perty</w> is to purge, ſhall in
          ſome caſes, tho' <lb/>given for that purpoſe, not operate at all; <lb/>while reſtringents,
          ſhall in other <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtitutions</w> occaſion purging. <hi
            rend="italic">Steel, Antimony, <lb/>Mercury,</hi> &amp;c. might be brought to <w
            part="I">eluci-</w><lb/><w part="F">date</w> this truth; and prove their different
          <lb/>effects on different conſtitutions; as well as <lb/>when they are injudiciouſly
          directed. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But as it may be neceſſary, to ſet this <lb/>affair in a clearer
          light, to prevent being <lb/>miſunderſtood; and to ſhew, when <hi rend="italic"
            >nature</hi>
          <lb/>can do without <hi rend="italic">art,</hi> and where the latter <lb/>is requiſite; I
          muſt beg leave to explain <lb/>myſelf a little farther, on both theſe <lb/>heads. Who
          then, ever ſo ſlightly <w part="I">acquaint-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> with acute
          diſorders, but muſt have <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerved</w>, that fevers in
          their infancy, are <lb/>frequently and eaſily removed, by very <lb/>ſimple means; or
          rather that the <hi rend="sc">Fever</hi>, <lb/>which is nature's inſtrument, aſſiſted by
            <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F">lution</w> with ſmall liquors, and abſtinence
          <lb/>from animal diet, ſeldom wants any other <lb/>helps; but where bleeding and gentle <w
            part="I">eva-</w><lb/><w part="F">cuations</w> are joined to theſe, the end is <w
            part="I">gene-</w><lb/><w part="F">rally</w> accompliſhed in a few days; for by <pb
            xml:id="page_27" n="24"/><lb/>this; method, the fluids are diluted, the <w part="I"
            >ſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cretions</w> renewed, and the fullneſs of the <lb/>veſſels
          abated: and to ſpeak ingenuouſly, <lb/>'tis extremely probable, that faſting, and
          <lb/>abſtemiouſneſs, would cure many, and <lb/>prevent moſt diſtempers; had men <w
            part="I">reſolu-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> enough to purſue it for a ſufficient
          <lb/>length of time, under proper regulations. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But when this method has been <w part="I">neglect-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ed</w>, and repeated colds, or acts of <w part="I">intempe-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >rance</w>, are urged on one another; <w part="I">aggrava-</w><lb/><w part="F">ted</w>
          by a <hi rend="italic">heating</hi> regimen, or <hi rend="italic">hotter</hi>
          <w part="I">medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cines</w>; we muſt not wonder at the <w part="I"
            >difficul-</w><lb/><w part="F">ties</w> that often attend the removal of <hi
            rend="italic">ſuch a <lb/>fever;</hi> for the blood and other juices, are <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">now</hi> become too viſcid or ſizey, to <w part="I">circu-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">late</w> in the finer veſſels; hence frequently <lb/>from ſuch obſtructions,
          ariſe <w part="I">inflammati-</w><lb/><w part="F">ons</w> in particular parts; which if
          not ſoon <lb/>removed by <hi rend="italic">art,</hi> terminate in matter, or <lb/>fatal
          gangrenes. In other <hi rend="italic">fevers,</hi> the blood <lb/>is in the reverſe ſtate,
          being too rare, thin, <lb/>and acrimonious; tending to diſſolution, <lb/>and putrefaction;
          which by the rapidity of <lb/>the circulation, is frequently forced thro' <pb
            xml:id="page_28" n="25"/><lb/>the extremities of the ſmall arteries, and <lb/>are the
          cauſe of malignant eruptions, and <lb/>violent bleedings. Here indeed it is high <lb/>time
          for <hi rend="italic">art</hi> to interpoſe, for <hi rend="italic">nature</hi> is no
          <lb/>longer her own aſſiſtant, but will ſoon <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtroy</w>
          herſelf, without timely ſuccour: <lb/>under theſe different circumſtances, the
          <lb/>skillful phyſician has ſufficient <w part="I">opportuni-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ties</w>, of diſtinguiſhing his prudence, and <lb/>abilities, for the ſtorm is now
          raiſed, the <lb/>pungent pains are become inſupportable; <lb/>the diſturbed functions of
          the mind, call <lb/>aloud to be be-calm'd, that reaſon may <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">aſſume</w> her throne; now is the time to <lb/>aſſiſt her effectually, either
          by curbing her <lb/>inordinate tranſports, or ſuccouring her <lb/>languiſhing ſtruggles:
          Here the cautious <lb/>preſcriber, will guard well againſt either <lb/>extream, leaſt by
          an injudi cious <w part="I">applica-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, he may aggravate the
          cauſe, by adding <lb/>fuel to a fire which burns but too intenſily <lb/>already, or check
          that <hi rend="italic">vital flame,</hi> that is <lb/>but too nigh extinguiſhed. Here <hi
            rend="italic">he</hi> who <lb/>has carefully ſtudied the laws of <hi rend="italic"
            >nature</hi>
          <lb/>and obſerved the ways <hi rend="italic">ſhe</hi> ſometimes takes <lb/>to relieve
          herſelf, will be beſt able, to give <pb xml:id="page_29" n="26"/><lb/>her that aſſiſtance,
          ſhe now ſo much wants; <lb/>while <hi rend="italic">he,</hi> who is only acquainted with
          her <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">ſpeculation,</hi> will ſtand amazed, and <lb/>affrighted at
          ſymptoms he never ſuſpected, <lb/>and impotently attack the diſeaſe, on the <lb/>ſtrength
          of ſome favourite <hi rend="italic">hypotheſis,</hi> or <lb/>ſome darling <hi rend="sc"
            >Nostrum</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>From this portrait, or deſcription of two <lb/>different kinds of
          fevers only, one may <w part="I">rea-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſonable</w> inquire how far any
          one method, <lb/>or <hi rend="italic">medicine,</hi> is like to anſwer both <w part="I"
            >inten-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w>; but before we venture to mention <lb/>our own
          thoughts on this head, let us take <lb/>the opinion of the immortal <hi rend="italic"
            >Sydenham,</hi>
          <lb/>that candid, and judicious obſerver; who <lb/>ſays,<note place="bottom" n="*">*
            Swan's Sydenham, p. 293. </note> there are various kinds of fevers, <lb/>moſt of which
          require their <hi rend="italic">peculiar method</hi>
          <lb/>of cure, different from the reſt; and that <lb/>the ſame individual fever, of
          whatever kind <lb/>it be, requires one treatment at the firſt, <lb/>and another ſomewhat
          different, through <lb/>all its ſtages, as long as it continues. Many <lb/>other ſimilar
          paſſages might be extracted <pb xml:id="page_30" n="27"/><lb/>from this great man's works.
          Let us hear <lb/>alſo the experienced <hi rend="italic">Baglivi,</hi> who ſays,<note
            place="bottom" n="†">† Baglivi's practice of phyſick, p. 271. </note> a <lb/>great many
          have ſuch an affection to ſome <lb/>one remedy, that they think it alone <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">titled</w> to a ſovereign virtue, and power, of <lb/>curing
          almoſt all diſeaſes; either by reaſon <lb/>of a lucky event, obſerved now and then <lb/>to
          enſue the uſe of it, or rather by a <lb/>certain innate propenſity that they have,
          <lb/>not only of crying up ſome medicines, but <lb/>aſcribing to them <hi rend="italic"
            >fictitious</hi> virtues: but I <lb/>muſt obſerve by the bye, ſays he, that no
          <lb/>phyſician can cure a fever happily, <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w part="F">out</w> he
          informs himſelf of the febrile ſtate <lb/>of the blood; whether it is too rapid,
          <lb/>thin, or inflammable, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> or on the other <lb/>hand, apt
          to congeal, thick, malignant, <lb/><hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> For in ſuch different
          ſtates of the <lb/>blood, the indications of cure muſt be <lb/>diverſifyed accordingly.
          The honourable <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="sc">Boyle</hi> in his treatiſe on the <w part="I"
            >uſefull-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w> of philoſophy, obſerves, that it is <lb/>much
          more difficult, than men can imagine, <lb/>to make an accurate experiment in phyſic, <pb
            xml:id="page_31" n="28"/><lb/>for often the ſame diſeaſe proceeding, in <lb/>ſeveral
          perſons, from quite different cauſes, <lb/>will be increaſed in one, by the ſame <w
            part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">medy</w>, which has cured it in an other <lb/>and not
          only the <hi rend="italic">conſtitutions</hi> of patients, <lb/>may as much alter the <hi
            rend="italic">effects</hi> as the <hi rend="italic">cauſes</hi> of <lb/>diſeaſes; but
          even in the ſame patient, and <lb/>in the ſame diſeaſe, the ſingle <w part="I"
            >circum-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtance</w> of time, may have almoſt as great <lb/>an
          operation upon the ſucceſs of the <w part="I">medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cine</w>, as
          either of the two former <w part="I">particu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lars</w>. The learned
            <hi rend="sc">Friend</hi><note place="bottom" n="*">* Shaw's edit. vol. 1. p. 176.
          </note> on this <w part="I">occa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſion</w> alſo obſerves, that a man
          who has the <lb/>leaſt acquaintance with phyſic, muſt be <lb/>ſenſible, that a univerſal
          medicine muſt <lb/>be a <hi rend="italic">cheat;</hi> and though it be ever ſo good
          <lb/>and valuable a medicine itſelf, yet it is <lb/>utterly impoſſible it can be equally
            <w part="I">appli-</w><lb/><w part="F">cable</w> to all perſons, in all caſes, and at
          <lb/>all junctures; and therefore it muſt be <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >termined</w> by the skill of ſome diſcerning <lb/>phyſician, who is well appriſed of
          the <w part="I">na-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w> and ſymptoms of the diſeaſe,
            where<lb/><note place="bottom" n="†">† Hiſtory of phyſick, vol. 1. p. 78. </note>
          <pb xml:id="page_32" n="29"/><lb/>to give it, and where to forbear. We <lb/>need not go
          far for a proof of this: we <lb/>have a convincing one in that great, and <lb/>perhaps the
            <hi rend="italic">only ſpecifick,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">bark:</hi> which <lb/>if
          uſed indifferently, and without <w part="I">judge-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w>, even in
          intermitting caſes, has a <lb/>chance to do as much hurt as good. But <lb/>I forbear
          making further quotations, from <lb/>other writers of equal eminence, that the
          <lb/>reader, may not be tired. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>If theſe things be true, if ſuch <hi rend="italic"
            >autho-<lb/>rities</hi> are to be relied on, how abſurd is it, <lb/>to ſuppoſe <hi
            rend="italic">any medicine</hi> can be poſſeſs'd of <lb/>the unerring faculty, of
          removing all <lb/>fevers; and yet this opinion, however <lb/>diſſonant to reaſon, and
          common ſenſe it <lb/>may be, appears to have it's <hi rend="italic">abettors;</hi> and
          <lb/>I am ſorry to ſay it, among ſome <hi rend="italic">few</hi> too, <lb/>who call
          themſelves <hi rend="italic">phyſician;</hi> contrary <lb/>indeed to the ingenuous
          declaration of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">learned publiſher</hi> of this remedy, who in
          <lb/>the following paſſages in his diſſertation on <lb/>fevers, as well as in his <hi
            rend="italic">daily practice,</hi>
          <lb/>manifeſtly diſavows ſuch a <hi rend="italic">general</hi> power <lb/>in his
          preparation. I am obliged ſays <pb xml:id="page_33" n="30"/><lb/>he,<note place="bottom"
            n="*">* James's diſſertation on fevers, p. 40. </note> to own, that as I eſteemed life
          too <lb/>ſacred to be hazarded, for the ſake of an <lb/>experiment, I have <hi
            rend="italic">never</hi> neglected to call <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">all other medicinal
            aids,</hi> to my aſſiſtance, <lb/>when I thought the caſe required them, <lb/>and
          believed that they would be of ſervice. <lb/>Again<note place="bottom" n="†">† Ib. p. 46.
          </note> as I would be extreamly cautious <lb/>of leading any one into error, in an affair
          <lb/>of ſo much importance, as is that of life, <lb/>I muſt remark, that when violent <w
            part="I">inflam-</w><lb/><w part="F">mations</w> of the vital parts threaten <w part="I"
            >imme-</w><lb/><w part="F">diate</w> deſtruction, I ſhould think it <w part="I"
            >impru-</w><lb/><w part="F">dent</w> to neglect repeated bleedings, purges,
          <lb/>clyſters, and <hi rend="italic">all other aſſiſtances,</hi> which the <lb/>art of
          medicine can afford. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>After ſuch plain and candid conceſſions, <lb/>one would think it was
          impoſſible, that <lb/>any but ſtupid bigots, or ſuperſtitious old <lb/>women, unacquainted
          with ſuch <w part="I">auxilia-</w><lb/><w part="F">ries</w>, would ſolely depend upon this
            <w part="I">reme-</w><lb/><w part="F">dy</w>, and in the moſt deſperate caſes. Does
          <lb/>it not hence evidently appear that Dr. <pb xml:id="page_34" n="31"/><lb/><hi
            rend="italic">James</hi> himſelf does not? Do not ſome of <lb/>his caſes prove it, where
          we find <hi rend="italic">Bleeding, <lb/>Nitre, Musk, ſtimulating Cataplaſms,
            <lb/>Bliſters,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Purges,</hi> directed as aſſociates <lb/>with
          the medicine.<note place="bottom" n="*">* Vid. p. 13.27.33. </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And who, among ſuch a <hi rend="italic">group of <w part="I"
              >auxi-</w><lb/><w part="F">laries</w>,</hi> can pretend to ſay, what ſhare of
          <lb/>merit, becomes due to <hi rend="italic">the powder?</hi> The <lb/>Dr. himſelf
          ingenuouſly confeſſes, he <w part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F">times</w> could not
          determine how far it was <lb/>inſtrumental in the cure;<note place="bottom" n="†">†
            James's diſſertation on fevers, p. 34.-13. </note> nor indeed how <lb/>ſhould he. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>How abſurd then muſt it appear to <lb/>every <hi rend="italic"
            >impartial</hi> man, who reflects cooly, <lb/>that a medicine, which it is acknowledged
          <lb/>may demand all theſe <hi rend="italic">occaſional aſſiſtances,</hi>
          <lb/>ſhould without reſtrictions, be thus <hi rend="italic">raſhly</hi>
          <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">univerſally</hi> recommended <hi rend="italic">by ſome</hi> in
          all <lb/>fevers; for whatever limitations may be <lb/>hinted at in the treatiſe, can it be
            <w part="I">ſup-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſed</w>, that thoſe unacquainted with the <pb
            xml:id="page_35" n="32"/><lb/>ſcience of phyſic, can diſtinguiſh, from <lb/>the rules
          there laid down, <hi rend="italic">when</hi> to employ <lb/>theſe auxilaries? Neither can
          Dr. <hi rend="italic">James,</hi>
          <lb/>always be at hand to, direct them, and who <lb/>leſs acquainted with that medicine,
          would <lb/>risk their reputations, by being concerned <lb/>with it, on ſuch important
          occaſions, <lb/>where lives are at ſtake; much leſs can it <lb/>be poſſible, that the
          promiſcuous <w part="I">admini-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtration</w> of this remedy, to
          diſeaſes of ſuch <lb/><hi rend="italic">general Names,</hi> as are mentioned in the
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">advertiſement,</hi> can be ſucceſſful; when the <lb/>conditions
          of theſe diſeaſes, do ſo <w part="I">perpetu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ally</w> vary. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But if the operation, and effects of this <lb/>medicine are to be <hi
            rend="italic">rationally,</hi> and not <hi rend="italic">empi-<lb/>rically</hi>
          accounted for; if it is to be <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">amined</w> by the ſame
          teſts, that all others <lb/>are; we ſhall find, that like them, it muſt <lb/>be directed,
          and given with prudence, and <lb/>skill, to render it efficacious, and prevent <lb/>it's
          being injurious. For example if it has <lb/>been found ſucceſſful in thinning and <w
            part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tenuating</w> the <hi rend="italic">viſcid, ſizy</hi>
          blood and fluids, <lb/>is it not likely to be prejudicial in caſes, <pb xml:id="page_36"
            n="33"/><lb/>where the fluids are already too <hi rend="italic">thin</hi>
          <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">rare?</hi> If it has been found uſeful, in <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">creaſing</w> the ſecretions of the glands of <lb/>the skin,
          inteſtines, and kidneys, by <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">moting</w> ſtools, urine,
          and ſweats, may it <lb/>not be injurious, in thoſe caſes, where theſe <lb/>ſecretions are
          but too <hi rend="italic">liberal</hi> already? That <lb/>this is evidently the caſe in
          ſome <hi rend="italic">colli-<lb/>quative fevers,</hi> appears by the broken <w part="I"
            >tex-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w> of the blood; where the particles <lb/>being too much
          diſſolved, are daily <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">hauſting</w> the patient, by
          running off too <lb/>faſt, through the pores, by melting ſweats, <lb/>or the bowels by
          watery ſtools. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>How prepoſterous, how inconſiſtent then <lb/>muſt be the practice of
          thoſe, who give it <lb/>thus indiſcriminately; and who thus <w part="I">wan-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tonly</w> trifle with <hi rend="italic">lives,</hi> they are intruſted
          <lb/>with? But ſurely the folly of ſuch <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceedure</w>
          can want no illuſtration. Could a <lb/>man alſo without horror reflect, on being
          <lb/>acceſſory to the untimely death of a friend, <lb/>or neighbour, by the vomiting power
          of <lb/>an antimonial medicine, given without <lb/>previous, or proper bleedings, in <w
            part="I">inflamma-</w>
          <pb xml:id="page_37" n="34"/><lb/><w part="F">tions</w>of the <hi rend="italic"
            >lungs,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">brain,</hi> truſting to <lb/>this medicine <hi
            rend="italic">ſolely,</hi> in ſuch <hi rend="italic">important</hi>
          <lb/>diſeaſes, contrary to the expreſs rules of <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">James?</hi>
          This though a real <w part="I">proſtitu-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of it, yet has been
          done, and by <lb/>the direction of ſome, who ought to <lb/>know better; for can the moſt
          ſanguine <lb/>abettors of this medicine, pretend to <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >vent</w> this operation, as it is one of its <w part="I">gene-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ral</w> effects,<note place="bottom" n="*">* Vid. James's paper of inſtructions, where
            he <lb/>ſays, this medicine is ſometimes found to operate <lb/>pretty briskly by way of
            vomiting, &amp;c. </note> the continuance of which may <lb/>depend on the juices it
          accidentally meets <lb/>with in the ſtomach? Under ſuch <w part="I">threat-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ning</w> cicumſtances, with violent pains in <lb/>the head, or ſides, attended
          with the <w part="I">ut-</w><lb/><w part="F">moſt</w> difficulty in breathing; what a
          truly <lb/>piteous ſituation, muſt be that of the <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >fortunate</w> patient, under the vomiting <lb/>power of this medicine? How muſt the
          <lb/>acute, pungent pangs, be thereby <w part="I">aggra-</w><lb/><w part="F">vated?</w>
          The turgid and diſtended veſſels <lb/>ſtretched, even to burſting? Or at leaſt ſuch <lb/>a
          quantity of fluids may thereby be derived <pb xml:id="page_38" n="35"/><lb/>on parts,
          already but too much loaded, <lb/>ſo as to fi<unclear>x</unclear> immoveable obſtructions,
          and <lb/>occaſion fatal gangrenes. Theſe are <w part="I">warn-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ings</w> that ſhould be given by ſomebody, as <lb/>they are not the reſult of imaginary
            <w part="I">ſpecula-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w>, but are real facts, which have
          occurred; <lb/>and though the <hi rend="italic">farmers</hi> loſs may not be <lb/>greatly
          increaſed, by the additional expence, <lb/>attending the purchaſe of<note place="bottom"
            n="*">* Vid. Daily Advertiſer. </note> the medicine, <lb/>for his cows and oxen; yet his
          family may <lb/>ſuſtain an irreparable one, by an untimely <lb/>and injudicious taking of
          it himſelf. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But if ſuch be the barrenneſs of the <w part="I">ma-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">teria</w> medica. or the <hi rend="italic">incapacity</hi> of the <w part="I"
            >phy-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſician</w>, in drawing his indications of cure, <lb/>that this
          muſt be the <hi rend="italic">popular,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">faſhion-<lb/>able</hi>
          remedy; let us at leaſt have the <hi rend="italic">wiſdom</hi>
          <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">honeſty,</hi> to treat it, as we do other <lb/>medicines; for
          by theſe means only, can <lb/>it obtain a juſt reputation: let us then <w part="I"
            >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">fine</w> it within its proper ſphere of action <lb/>and give
          it in ſuch caſes only, as it appears, <lb/>calculated for; which from our <w part="I"
            >obſerva-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w>, ſeems chiefly to be in the beginning of <pb
            xml:id="page_39" n="36"/><lb/>ſlight fevers, which ariſe from indigeſtions, <lb/>or
          taking cold; for by its ſtimulus on the <lb/>ſtomach and bowels, thoſe organs may be
          <lb/>thus cleanſed of their indigeſted particles, <lb/>their, feculencys thereby removed,
          and the <lb/>ſweats it generally procures, aſſiſted by <lb/>plentiful dilution, may ſet
          open the <w part="I">ſecre-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w>; and thus by removing the
          ſurcharge <lb/>early, nature is left at more liberty to <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">cover</w> cover herſelf. Should it on <hi rend="italic">fair trials</hi> be
          <lb/>found to ſuit other <hi rend="italic">indications,</hi> let it be <lb/>given with
          diſcretion; but if our views are <lb/>not anſwered ſoon, let us not, <hi rend="italic"
            >Sangrado</hi>
          <lb/>like, obſtinately perſevere as <hi rend="italic">ſome</hi> do, to <lb/>the patients
          deſtruction; that we may <w part="I">a-</w><lb/><w part="F">void</w> the juſt reproaches
          of an injured family, <lb/>who may be made ſufferers by our <w part="I">wanton-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ness</w>, and imprudence; and prevent thoſe <lb/>bitter reflections, that will
          recoil onour own <lb/>minds, by being thus acceſſory to them. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Medicines of this kind, as <hi rend="italic">generally <w part="I"
              >gi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ven</w>,</hi> tis true may ſave <hi rend="italic">ſome</hi>
          the trouble <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">thinking,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ſearching</hi>
          for indications; <lb/>which every prudent man thinks abſolutely <lb/>neceſſary, before, he
          preſcribes; but this <lb/>compendious method cancels all tyes, or <pb xml:id="page_40"
            n="37"/><lb/>duty of this kind; abjures this ſlaviſh <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tachment</w> to the ſtudy of <hi rend="italic">nature,</hi> and her <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">laws,</hi> as deluſive, and deſultory; reduces <lb/>the ſcience of phyſic
          to a narrower <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">pass</w>, and inſtead of leading, or
          kindly <lb/>aſſiſting nature, forces her to be obedient, <lb/>and follow the ways they
          chooſe to <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſcribe</w> her. Such implements however in
          <lb/>phyſic, are like edge tools in the hands <lb/>of children, or weapons of deſtruction
          <lb/>in thoſe of madmen; the ſimplicity of the one, <lb/>converting them to their own
          prejudice, <lb/>and the inſanity of the other, to the <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſtruction</w> of thoſe about them: and this <lb/>obſervation we apprehend will always
          hold <lb/>true, that this or any other valuable <w part="I">medi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cine</w>, can only be of <hi rend="italic">real ſervice,</hi> when <w part="I"
            >di-</w><lb/><w part="F">rected</w> with judgment; and that it is the <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">judicious timeing,</hi> and adapting the <hi rend="italic">medicine,</hi>
          <lb/>to the <hi rend="italic">diſeaſe,</hi> that makes it either a <w part="I"
            >bene-</w><lb/><w part="F">ficial</w>
          <hi rend="italic">remedy,</hi> or a <hi rend="italic">deſtructive poiſon.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>We deſire it may particularly be <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >marked</w>, that the violent ſweats extorted <lb/>by ſudoriſic medicines in fevers, but
          too <lb/>often aggravate the diſorder, though they <pb xml:id="page_41" n="38"
          /><lb/>ſeemingly give preſent relief;<note place="bottom" n="†">† Vid. Sydenham,
            Boerhaave, in variis locis. <lb/>Vid. James's diſſertation on fevers, P. 5. where he
            <lb/>ſays that ſweats, which are not ſpontaneous, but <lb/>extorted, generally prove
            ſymptomatical and noxious, <lb/>inſtead of being critical and ſalutary. </note> for
          unleſs <lb/>this evacuation be critical, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> by carrying <lb/>off
          the cauſe of the fever, the blood is <w part="I">there-</w><lb/><w part="F">by</w>
          defrauded of its thinner, and finer parts, <lb/>and the remainder left ſo thickened, that
          <lb/>'tis rendered unfit for circulation in <lb/>the finer veſſels, and often occaſions <w
            part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtructions</w>, that terminate fatally. This <lb/>has
            <hi rend="italic">remarkably</hi> been obſerved to be the caſe <lb/>with <hi
            rend="italic">this medicine,</hi> where after having <lb/>cauſed <hi rend="italic"
            >profuſe</hi> ſweats, for ſeveral days, the <lb/>blood on examination for that purpoſe,
          ſo <lb/>far from being attenuated by the medicine, <lb/>(as is the property generally
          aſcribed to it) <lb/>hath on the contrary, been found more <lb/>tenacious, and ſizey; and
          ſo unfit for <w part="I">circu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lation</w>, as to occaſion conſtant
          watchings, <lb/>delirium, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> which in <hi rend="italic"
            >ſome</hi> caſes ſubſiſted <lb/>till bliſters, and more powerful attenuants <lb/>removed
          thoſe ſymptoms; in <hi rend="italic">others</hi> till <lb/>death put an end to them. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_42" n="39"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nor is it leſs neceſſary, to guard againſt <lb/>the promiſcuous uſe of
          this powder, in <lb/>eruptive fevers, particularly thoſe called <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >miliary;</hi> as it is evident to the <hi rend="italic">obſerving</hi>
          <lb/>practitioner, that the eruptions once <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">pelled</w>,
          the patient is thereby often brought <lb/>into the moſt eminent danger of his life:
          <lb/>and if this has often been found to be the <lb/>caſe, by a few ſlight ſtools, what <w
            part="I">conſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">quences</w> may we not apprehend from <lb/>a
          medicine, whoſe <hi rend="italic">known effect</hi> is <w part="I">acknowledg-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ed</w>, ſometimes to purge <hi rend="italic">pretty briskly.</hi><note
            place="bottom" n="*">* Vid. Dr. James's paper inſtructions, and caſes. </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As Dr. <hi rend="italic">James</hi> ſeems ſo ſinngular in his <w
            part="I">no-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w> concerning <hi rend="italic">miliary
            fevers,</hi> and ſuſpects <lb/>them to be <hi rend="italic">entirely the children of
            art</hi><note place="bottom" n="†">† James's diſſertat. on fevers, p. 36.37. </note>
          <lb/>as he has ſo ludicrouſly treated this <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F">portant</w>
          ſubject, which has been ſo <w part="I">accurate-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> deſcribed by
          Sir <hi rend="italic">David Hamilton, <lb/>Hoffman, Mead,</hi> &amp;c. and probably too ſo
          <lb/>far, as to lead ſome of his <hi rend="italic">pupils</hi> into <lb/>fatal errors; I
          thought it the more <w part="I">incum-</w><pb xml:id="page_43" n="40"/><lb/><w part="F"
            >bent</w> on me, to give this caution; and the <lb/>more particularly, as in his <hi
            rend="italic">paper <w part="I">inſtruc-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w>,</hi> he
          recommends this powder <lb/>for <hi rend="italic">miliary fevers,</hi> and all <hi
            rend="italic">others</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">erup-<lb/>tive</hi> kind; and ſays
          that there is no reaſon <lb/>to fear a moderate number of ſtools, at the <lb/>latter end
          of a <hi rend="italic">fever, or at any other <lb/>time.</hi><note place="bottom" n="*">*
            Vid. James's paper inſtructions. </note> The latter part of this paragraph, <lb/>is
          ſurely too bold an aſſertion, eſpecially if <lb/>relative to this fever; where a very <w
            part="I">mode-</w><lb/><w part="F">rate</w> number of ſtools, has frequently <w part="I"
            >pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">cipitated</w> the patients fate, by the ſudden <lb/>repulſion
          of the eruptions. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>From what then has been advanced in <lb/>relation to the powers of <hi
            rend="italic">nature</hi> and <hi rend="italic">art;</hi>
          <lb/>in regard to the uſe of medicine <hi rend="italic">in general,</hi>
          <lb/>and this <hi rend="italic">powder</hi> in particular; we may <w part="I"
            >ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerve</w> that in many acute diſorders, or <lb/>fevers, <hi
            rend="italic">nature</hi> is often her own, and beſt <lb/>phyſician; that the
          aſſiſtances from art <lb/>ſhould <hi rend="italic">in general</hi> be cautiouſly directed;
            <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">ways</w> drawn, from ſuch indications, as the
          <lb/>ſymptoms point out, and muſt be varied <pb xml:id="page_44" n="41"/><lb/>in
          proportion to the nature of the diſeaſe: <lb/>That <hi rend="italic">no one medicine,</hi>
          can ever anſwer <lb/>ſo many different purpoſes; more <w part="I">eſpeci-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ally</w> one whoſe <hi rend="italic">operations</hi> are ſo <hi rend="italic"
            >precarious;</hi>
          <lb/>and which we are convinced from the <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">cess</w> of,
          (which is no ſecret to the world) <lb/>that tho' it may be uſeful in ſome caſes, <lb/>it
          muſt be prejudicial in others; that a <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">miſcuous</w>,
          unlimited power of giving it, <lb/><hi rend="italic">according to ſome,</hi> has to our
          knowledge, <lb/>been productive of many, and great <w part="I">miſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >carriages</w>: How often has nature been <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſturbed</w>, and a favourable criſis prevented <lb/>by this, and other ill-timed
          medicines? <lb/>And how eaſily diſtempers ſlight in them-<lb/>ſelves, are often converted
          into important <lb/>ones, by <hi rend="italic">untimely</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
            >injudicious</hi>
          <w part="I">applica-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w>, is well known to the careful obſerver.
          <lb/>Caſes of this kind have occured where <lb/><hi rend="italic">nature</hi> tho' feeble,
          and oppreſſed, yet <w part="I">labour-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> hard to relieve
          herſelf, and depurate <lb/>the blood by critical ſwellings, has been <lb/>moſt
          prepoſterouſly teized and thwarted <lb/>with the ſtools, and ſweats, incited by this
          <lb/>medicine, till ſhe had nigh ſunk under the <pb xml:id="page_45" n="42"
          /><lb/>oppreſſion; yet has ſhe at laſt happily <w part="I">e-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >merged</w>, and accompliſhed her deſigns, <lb/>after having obtained a truce with it
          for a <lb/>few days. So true is <hi rend="italic">that</hi> obſervation of <lb/>Dr. <hi
            rend="italic">James</hi>*<note place="inset">James's Diſſert. on fevers, p.5</note> that
            <hi rend="italic">ſome few</hi> are ſo happy in <lb/>an <hi rend="italic"
            >unextinguiſhable</hi> ſtrength of <w part="I">conſtituti-</w><lb/><w part="F">on</w>,
          that they even at laſt miraculouſly <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">cover</w>, <hi
            rend="italic">notwithſtanding the moſt abſurd <lb/>treatment.</hi> In colliquative
          caſes, where <lb/>the ſecretions were too liberal, it has ſunk <lb/>many untimely; and in
          fevers of ſeveral <lb/>days ſtanding, where the veſſels are too <w part="I"
            >tur-</w><lb/><w part="F">gid</w>, the pulſe vehement, the blood ſo gluey <lb/>and
          viſcid, that it cannot freely paſs the <lb/>finer veſſels, or ſo fuſed, and broken, that
          it <lb/>threatens to eſcape them; when <w part="I">inflam-</w><lb/><w part="F">mations</w>
          are alſo fixed on the nobler parts, <lb/>foreboding inevitable deſtruction without
          <lb/>ſpeedy relief; ſurely on ſuch emergencies, <lb/>it would be madneſs <hi rend="italic"
            >indeed</hi> to truſt to this, <lb/>or any one medicine, without calling in <lb/>every
          other help, that reaſon, and <w part="I">expe-</w><lb/><w part="F">rience</w> dictate on
          ſuch occaſions; and this <lb/>we are juſtified in aſſerting, not from the <pb
            xml:id="page_46" n="43"/><lb/>reaſon of the thing only, but from the <lb/>authority
          likewiſe of Dr. <hi rend="italic">James himſelf,</hi> in <lb/>the places above cited. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I cannot conclude without taking notice, <lb/>of a ridiculous
          inſinuation, advanced <hi rend="italic">by <lb/>ſome,</hi> as a reaſon, why the gentlemen
          of <lb/>the faculty do not patronize this medicine; <lb/>which is, that it would be
          deſtructive of <lb/>their private intereſts, by making ſuch <lb/>ſpeedy cures. But this
          objection, the trite, <lb/>and ſtale artifice of every empirick to <w part="I"
            >re-</w><lb/><w part="F">commend</w> his <hi rend="sc">Nostrum</hi>, is as mean, and
          <lb/>contemptible, as it is falſe; 'tis an artful <lb/>lure, thrown out only as a decoy
          for the <lb/>publick, that they may the more readily <lb/>become their dupes. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>For are not the phyſicians of this nation <lb/>in general, and of <hi
            rend="italic">London</hi> in particular, <lb/>men of liberal educations, whoſe learning,
          <lb/>and abilities are equal to any in <hi rend="italic">Europe?</hi>
          <lb/>Are not many of them, as conſpicuous for <lb/>their humanity, benevolence, and <w
            part="I">tender-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w>, as they are for their independant
          <lb/>fortunes? What could induce ſuch men, <pb xml:id="page_47" n="44"/><lb/>to <hi
            rend="italic">procraſtinate</hi> the cures of thoſe <w part="I">commit-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ed</w> to their charge, but a certain conviction <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic"
            >inefficacy,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">incertitude,</hi> of <hi rend="italic">general
            <lb/>medicines?</hi> Is it not then baſe, and infamous, <lb/>to inſinuate, that theſe
          men would <w part="I">ſacri-</w><lb/><w part="F">fice</w> all conſiderations of <hi
            rend="italic">honour, juſtice,</hi>
          <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">compaſſion,</hi> merely to oppoſe ſuch a <lb/>univerſal
          medicine? Is it not notorious, <lb/>that many of them in their private practice, <lb/>as
          well as by repeated trials in our <hi rend="italic">hoſpi-<lb/>tals,</hi> have found it
          was by no means to <lb/>be relied on? or can it deſerve credit from <lb/>any ſenſible, and
          unprejudiced minds, that <lb/>thoſe few practitioners <hi rend="italic">who do</hi>
          eſpouſe <lb/>this medicine, have <hi rend="italic">alone</hi> monopolized the <lb/>amiable
          qualities of truth, diſintereſtedneſs, <lb/>and common honeſty? Surely it would be
          <lb/>more ingenuous, and candid, to conclude, <lb/>that nothing but this <hi rend="italic"
            >certain conviction</hi> of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">incertitude,</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">inefficacy,</hi> of <hi rend="italic">general <w part="I">me-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">dicines</w>,</hi> and of this in <hi rend="italic">particular,</hi> (whoſe
          <lb/>virtues like all others, can only ariſe, by <lb/>being rationally adapted to <hi
            rend="italic">particular <w part="I">cir-</w><lb/><w part="F">cumſtances</w>, and ſtates
            of diſeaſes</hi>) could be <lb/>the true and only cauſe of leading <w part="I"
            >phyſici-</w><lb/><w part="F">ans</w>, to forbear its general uſe; whatever <pb
            xml:id="page_48" n="45"/><lb/>bold aſſertions, ignorant, and deſigning men may advance
          to the contrary. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe are <hi rend="italic">ſome</hi> of the obſervations, that
          <lb/>have occured, and 'tis to be apprehended <lb/>will have ſome weight with the
          impartial: <lb/>for if neither <hi rend="italic">honour, conſcience, humanity,</hi>
          <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">independance,</hi> can be thought to have <lb/>any influence
          over the conduct, of ſuch <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">feſſors</w> of phyſic; we
          muſt be under a <w part="I">ne-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceſſity</w> of condemning, a body of
          men, as <lb/>monſters in nature, who have hitherto <lb/>been eſteemed <hi rend="italic"
            >real ornaments</hi> to their <lb/>country, and <hi rend="italic">reſpectable,</hi> as
          well as <hi rend="italic">uſeful</hi>
          <lb/>members of ſociety. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_49"/>
        <head rend="align-center space"><lb/><hi rend="size(2.5)">POSTCRIPT</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>IN order to form a more general, and <lb/>comprehenſive idea of <hi
            rend="italic">this Powder, we</hi>
          <lb/>have thought proper to inſert here, its <lb/>various, and common operations, in thoſe
          <lb/>caſes Dr. <hi rend="italic">James</hi> himſelf has publiſhed, in <lb/>his
          diſſertation on fevers. In his <hi rend="italic">paper <lb/>inſtructions,</hi> he remarks,
          that it is found <lb/>ſometimes to operate <hi rend="italic">pretty briskly,</hi> by way
          <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">vomiting</hi> and <hi rend="italic">purging,</hi> as indeed
          ſeveral <lb/>of his caſes prove; ſo that the judicious <lb/>reader may hence obſerve, as
          well as from <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">uncertainty</hi> of its operation; that it
          <lb/>ought to be given with great caution, and <lb/>circumſpection: for though ſome few
          <lb/>conſtitutions, may be able to ſupport <hi rend="italic">theſe</hi>
          <lb/>operations without injury, while the body <lb/>is <hi rend="italic">ſtrong,</hi> and
            <hi rend="italic">vigorous;</hi> yet under many <lb/>circumſtances, which we have
          pointed <lb/>out, as well as when the patient is <hi rend="italic">reduced</hi>
          <pb xml:id="page_50" n="47"/><lb/>by the diſeaſe; how far <hi rend="italic">profuſe
            ſweats</hi>
          <lb/>continued for four and twenty hours, and <lb/>renewed; with <hi rend="italic"
            >brisk,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">frequent <w part="I">vomit-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ing</w>,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">purging,</hi> may ſuit ſuch, and <lb/>every other
          indication, is ſubmitted to the <lb/>deciſion of <hi rend="italic">competent</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">impartial</hi> judges. </p>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center space"><lb/><hi rend="italic">The various</hi> EFFECTS <hi
              rend="italic">of the</hi> POWDER <lb/><hi rend="italic">according to</hi> Dr. JAMES. </head>

          <p rend="indent" n="9"><lb/>Page 9. Diſſertation on fevers. Mrs. <hi rend="italic">M.</hi>
            <lb/>on taking one paper, <hi rend="italic">ſweated profuſely</hi>
            <lb/>ſix hours; on repeating the ſame, the <lb/>two ſubſequent nights, it operated in
            <lb/>the ſame manner. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="10"><lb/>10. Mr. <hi rend="italic">W.</hi> had a nauſea, and
            inclination <lb/>to vomit, with ſome gentle pukes, and <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſeveral
              purging ſtools,</hi> and beſide this, a <lb/>pretty plentiful ſweat. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="12"><lb/>12. Mr. <hi rend="italic">H.</hi> ſweat very moderately, and
            <lb/>had three purging ſtools. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="13"><lb/>13. Mr. <hi rend="italic">C.</hi> had a gentle ſweat and no
            <lb/>ſtools. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="14"><lb/>14. Mr. <hi rend="italic">J. B.</hi> had <hi rend="italic"
              >profuſe</hi> ſweats for four <lb/>hours, purged <hi rend="italic">conſiderably.</hi>
          </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_51" n="48"/>
          <p rend="indent" n="14"><lb/>14. Mr. <hi rend="italic">W. B.</hi> ſweat pretty much, and
            <lb/>purged three times. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="15"><lb/>15. Mrs: <hi rend="italic">B.</hi> ſweat a good deal, and
            purged <lb/>three or four times. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="17"><lb/>17. Miſs <hi rend="italic">S.</hi> vomited once, <hi
              rend="italic">purged five <lb/>times,</hi> ſweat a little, the next day another
            <lb/>doſe <hi rend="italic">vomited three or four time,</hi>
            <w part="I">purg-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>
            <hi rend="italic">four, or five,</hi> and ſweat a little. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="18"><lb/>18. Mr. <hi rend="italic">D.</hi> had <hi rend="italic"
              >ſeveral pukes,</hi> a <hi rend="italic">profuſe</hi>
            <lb/>ſweat of many hours continuance. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="19"><lb/>19. Mr. <hi rend="italic">E.</hi> puked gently twice, and had
            <lb/>three ſtools. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="20"><lb/>20. Mrs. <hi rend="italic">E.</hi> a copious ſweat. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="21"><lb/>21. Mrs. <hi rend="italic">F.</hi> vomited <hi rend="italic"
              >ſeveral</hi> times, purged <lb/><hi rend="italic">frequently</hi> and ſweated <hi
              rend="italic">profuſely.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="21"><lb/>21. Mrs. <hi rend="italic">E. F.</hi> operated nearly in the
            <lb/>ſame manner. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="22"><lb/>22. Mrs. <hi rend="italic">S.</hi> took ſix doſes, and had
              <hi rend="italic">no <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceiveable</w>
              operation.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="23"><lb/>23. Mrs <hi rend="italic">D.</hi> had at firſt no viſible <w
              part="I">opera-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, afterwards purged gently. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="24"><lb/>24. Mr. <hi rend="italic">J. D.</hi> brought on a great
            ſweat, <lb/>purged twice. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="25"><lb/>25. Mr. <hi rend="italic">P. vomited three or four</hi>
            times, <lb/>and ſweated pretty much, for four, or <lb/>five hours. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_52" n="49"/>
          <p rend="indent" n="26"><lb/>26 Mr. <hi rend="italic">H.</hi> vomited <hi rend="italic"
              >ſeveral times,</hi> purged <lb/><hi rend="italic">very often,</hi> and ſweat
            plentifully. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="26"><lb/>26. Mr. <hi rend="italic">N.</hi> had three ſtools, ſweat <w
              part="I">plen-</w><lb/><w part="F">tifully</w> about three hours. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="27"><lb/>27. Mr. <hi rend="italic">H.</hi> vomited <hi rend="italic"
              >three</hi> or <hi rend="italic">four</hi> times, <lb/>purged <hi rend="italic"
              >ſeveral times,</hi> and ſweat <w part="I">plenti-</w><lb/><w part="F">fully</w> for
            about twenty-four hours. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="28"><lb/>28. Mr. <hi rend="italic">L.</hi> vomited two or three times,
            <lb/>and purged <hi rend="italic">often.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="29"><lb/>29. Mrs. <hi rend="italic">B.</hi> made <hi rend="italic"
              >very ſick,</hi> vomited <hi rend="italic">pretty <lb/>much,</hi> purged <hi
              rend="italic">three</hi> or <hi rend="italic">four</hi> times, ſweat <lb/>all night. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="30"><lb/>30. Mr. <hi rend="italic">J. B.</hi> puked once, ſweat
            profuſely. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="31"><lb/>31. Mr. <hi rend="italic">S.</hi> vomited gently <hi
              rend="italic">four</hi> or <hi rend="italic">five</hi>
            <lb/>times, purged <hi rend="italic">ſeveral times.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="33"><lb/>33. Miſs. <hi rend="italic">E.</hi> had no ſenſible operation
            with <lb/>three doſes; was bled, had a bliſter put <lb/>on her head, cataplaſms to her
            feet, <lb/>a clyſter, and <hi rend="italic">Glauber</hi> ſalts, which purged <lb/>twice. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="38"><lb/>38. Mr. <hi rend="italic">D.</hi> had a copious ſweat, for <w
              part="I">four-</w><lb/><w part="F">teen</w> hours; and three ſtools. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Thus we may obſerve, that in eight <lb/>caſes, <hi rend="italic">the
              powder</hi> both <hi rend="italic">vomited, purged,</hi> and <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >ſweat;</hi> and theſe generally <hi rend="italic">profuſe</hi> ſweats; <pb
              xml:id="page_53" n="50"/><lb/><hi rend="italic">pretty ſmart, conſiderable, and
              frequent</hi>
            <w part="I">purg-</w><lb/><w part="F">ings</w>, and vomiting <hi rend="italic">ſeveral
              times.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>In ſeven caſes, it operated by <hi rend="italic">ſweats,</hi>
            <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">purging;</hi> ſometimes moderately, but in <lb/>general <hi
              rend="italic">profuſely,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">conſiderably</hi> both ways. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>In three, it <hi rend="italic">vomited</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
              >ſweated;</hi> and in <lb/>three more, it <hi rend="italic">ſweat only.</hi> Three
            alſo it <lb/><hi rend="italic">vomited</hi> and <hi rend="italic">purged,</hi> in one
            moderately, in <lb/>the others, it vomited three or four times, <lb/>and purged <hi
              rend="italic">ſeveral;</hi> in one caſe it purged <lb/>only, and in two had no
            operation at all. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>So that out of twenty ſeven caſes, it <lb/>operated by ſtool in
            nineteen, and in ten <lb/>of them <hi rend="italic">ſmartly,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
              >conſiderably.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe are the general effects and <w part="I">opera-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">tions</w> which followed the taking <hi rend="italic">this <w part="I"
                >medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cine</w>,</hi> with ſometimes a copious ſediment <lb/>in
            the urine; and may we not from hence <lb/>fairly conclude, that in thoſe caſes, where
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">vomiting, purging,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ſweating</hi> are
              <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">nicious</w>, (and many ſuch there are) that the
            <lb/>uſe of <hi rend="italic">this powder</hi> ſhould be ſuſpended? <lb/>When the
            conſtitution alſo is lowered, or <pb xml:id="page_54" n="51"/><lb/>greatly reduced by
            the diſeaſe, may not the <lb/>evacuations above mentioned, eſpecially <lb/>when <hi
              rend="italic">profuſe, ſmart,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">frequent,</hi> in many
            <lb/>caſes, precipitate the patient's fate? But if <lb/>the indication be to <hi
              rend="italic">ſweat, purge,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">vomit</hi>
            <lb/>ſingly, can we ever be ſure of anſwering any <lb/>one of theſe intentions alone,
            without <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">moting</w> others, we do not want, and
            which <lb/>may prove of dangerous conſequence? Such <lb/>ſeems to be the uncertainty of
            this medicine. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>When given in ſmall quantities, it poſſibly <lb/>may be leſs
            hazardous, though perhaps leſs <lb/>efficacious, as ſome <hi rend="italic"
              >operation</hi> ſeems always <lb/>expected from it. But as Dr. <hi rend="italic"
              >James</hi> has <lb/>not yet thought proper, to furniſh us with <lb/>caſes of this
            ſort, we ſhall for the preſent <lb/>decline any further animadverſions: nor <w part="I"
              >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">deed</w> ſhould we have troubled the public <lb/>with theſe,
            had we not thought they were <lb/>become abſolutely neceſſary, both for the
            <lb/>reputation of <hi rend="italic">the medicine,</hi> as well as for <lb/>the <hi
              rend="italic">patient's</hi> ſafety. </p>
        </div>
        <trailer rend="italic align-center"><lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_55"/>
        <head rend="align-center space"><lb/>ERRATA. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>PAGE 18. L. 17. for <hi rend="italic">runs,</hi> read <hi
            rend="italic">run.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>P. 25. l. 2. for <hi rend="italic">are,</hi> read <hi rend="italic"
            >is.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>P. 32. l. 5. for <hi rend="italic">that,</hi> read <hi rend="italic"
            >the.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>P. 8. l. 6. for <hi rend="italic">execretions</hi> read <hi
            rend="italic">excretions.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>P. 13. l. 20. read <hi rend="italic">according to the</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>P. 29. l. 17. after abettors, add, <hi rend="italic">in regard to</hi>
          James's <hi rend="italic">powder.</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
    </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
