<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Tissot: Advice to the People in General, with Regard to their
          Health</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Samuel Auguste David Tissot</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Advice to the People in General, with Regard to their Health: But
              more particularly calculated for those, who, by their Distance from regular
              Physicians, or other very experienced Practitioners, are the most unlikely to be
              seasonably provided with the best Advice and Assistance, in acute Diseases, or upon
              any sudden inward or outward Accident. With A Table of the most cheap, yet effectual
              Remedies, and the plainest Directions for preparing them readily. Translated from the
              French Edition of Dr. Tissot's Avis au Peuple, &amp;c. Printed at Lyons; with all his
              own Notes; a few of his medical Editor's at Lyons; and several occasional Notes,
              adapted to this English Translation.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T76081</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T76081"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for T. Becket and P.A. de Hondt, at Tully's Head, near
                  Surry-Street, in the Strand, MDCCLXV.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1765</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="31"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="608"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="28"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107351460</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="General treatises"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="60"/>
      <div type="chapter">
        <pb n="31"/>
        <head rend="sc align-center">
          <lb/>CHAPTER I. </head>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Of the moſt uſual Cauſes of popular Maladies. </head>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="sc align-center space">
            <lb/>SECT. I. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(5)">T</hi>HE moſt frequent Cauſes of Diſeaſes <lb/>commonly incident
            to Country <lb/>People are, 1. Exceſſive Labour, <lb/>continued for a very conſiderable
            <lb/>Time. Sometimes they ſink down <lb/>at once in a State of Exhauſtion and Faintneſs,
            <lb/>from which they ſeldom recover: but they are <lb/>oftener attacked with ſome
            inflammatory Diſeaſe, <lb/>as a Quinſey, a Pleuriſy, or an Inflammation of <lb/>the
            Breaſt. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>There are two Methods of preventing theſe <lb/>Evils: one is, to avoid the Cauſe
            which pro- <pb n="32"/>
            <lb/>duces them; but this is frequently impoſſible. <lb/>Another is, when ſuch exceſſive
            Labour has been <lb/>unavoidable, to allay their Fatigue, by a free <lb/>Uſe of ſome
            temperate refreſhing Drink; eſpe- <lb/>cially by ſweet Whey, by Butter-milk, or by <lb/>
            <note rend="size(0.5)" place="bottom" n="*">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* This ſuppoſes they are not greatly heated, as well as fa- <lb/>tigued, by
                their Labour or Exerciſe, in which Circumſtance <lb/>free and ſudden Draughts of
                cooling Liquors might be very <lb/>pernicious: and it evidently alſo ſuppoſes theſe
                Drinks to be <lb/>thus given, rather in Summer, than in very cold Weather, as
                <lb/>the Juice of the unripe Grapes, and the other freſh Fruits ſuf- <lb/>ficiently
                aſcertain the Seaſon of the Year. We think the Ad- <lb/>dition of Vinegar to their
                Water will ſcarcely ever be neceſſary <lb/>in this or the adjoining Iſland, on ſuch
                Occaſions. The Cau- <lb/>tion recommended in this Note is abundantly enforced by Dr.
                  <lb/><unclear>Tiſſot</unclear>, § 4: but conſidering the Perſons, to whom this
                Work <lb/>is more particularly addreſſed, we were willing to prevent <lb/>every
                Poſſibility of a Miſtake, in ſo neceſſary, and ſometimes <lb/>ſo vital a Point. <hi
                  rend="italic">K.</hi>
              </p>
            </note>
            <lb/>Water, to a Quart of which a Wine-glaſs of <lb/>Vinegar may be added; or, inſtead
            of that, the <lb/>expreſſed Juice of Grapes not fully ripe, or even <lb/>of Gooſberries
            or Cherries: which wholeſome <lb/>and agreeable Liquors are refreſhing and cordial.
            <lb/>I ſhall treat, a little lower, of inflammatory Diſ- <lb/>orders. The Inanition or
            Emptineſs, though ac- <lb/>companied with Symptoms different from the <lb/>former, have
            yet ſome Affinity to them with <lb/>Reſpect to their Cauſe, which is a kind of gene-
            <lb/>ral Exſiccation or Dryneſs. I have known ſome <lb/>cured from this Cauſe by Whey,
            ſucceeded by <lb/>tepid Baths, and afterwards by Cow's Milk: for <lb/>in ſuch Caſes hot
            Medicines and high Nouriſh- <lb/>ment are fatal. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 2. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>There is another Kind of Exhauſtion or <lb/>Emptineſs, which may be termed real
            Empti- <pb n="33"/>
            <lb/>neſs, and is the Conſequence of great Poverty, <lb/>the Want of ſufficient
            Nouriſhment, bad Food, <lb/>unwholeſome Drink, and exceſſive Labour. In <lb/>Caſes thus
            circumſtanced, good Soups and a little <lb/>Wine are very proper. Such happen however
            <lb/>very ſeldom in this Country: I believe they are <lb/>frequent in ſome others,
            eſpecially in many Pro- <lb/>vinces of <hi rend="italic">France</hi>. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 3. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>A ſecond and very common Source of <lb/>Diſorders ariſes, from Peoples' lying down
            and <lb/>repoſing, when very hot, in a cold Place. This <lb/>at once ſtops Perſpiration,
            the Matter of which <lb/>being thrown upon ſome internal Part, proves <lb/>the Cauſe of
            many violent Diſeaſes, particularly <lb/>of Quinſeys, Inflammations of the Breaſt, Pleu-
            <lb/>riſies, and inflammatory Cholics. Theſe Evils, <lb/>from this Cauſe, may always be
            avoided by avoid- <lb/>ing the Cauſe, which is one of thoſe that deſtroy <lb/>a great
            Number of People. However, when it <lb/>has occurred, as ſoon as the firſt Symptoms of
            <lb/>the Malady are perceiveable, which ſometimes <lb/>does not happen till ſeveral Days
            after, the Pati- <lb/>ent ſhould immediately be bled; his Legs ſhould <lb/>be put into
            Water moderately hot, and he ſhould <lb/>drink plentifully of the tepid Infuſion marked
            <lb/>No. 1. Such Aſſiſtances frequently prevent the <lb/>Increaſe of theſe Diſorders;
            which, on the con- <lb/>trary, are greatly aggravated, if hot Medicines are <lb/>given
            to ſweat the Patient. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 4. </head>
          <p>A third Cauſe is drinking cold Water, <lb/>when a Perſon is extremely hot. This acts in
            <lb/>the ſame Manner with the ſecond; but its Con- <pb n="34"/>
            <lb/>ſequences are commonly more ſudden and vio- <lb/>lent. I have ſeen moſt terrible
            Examples of it, <lb/>in Quinſeys, Inflammations of the Breaſt, Cholics,
            <lb/>Inflammations of the Liver, and all the Parts of <lb/>the Belly, with prodigious
            Swellings, Vomitings, <lb/>Suppreſſions of Urine, and inexpreſſible Anguiſh. <lb/>The
            moſt available Remedies in ſuch Caſes, from <lb/>this Cauſe, are, a plentiful Bleeding
            at the Onſet, <lb/>a very copious Drinking of warm Water, to <lb/>which one fifth Part
            of Whey ſhould be added; <lb/>or of the Ptiſan No. 2, or of an Emulſion of <lb/>Almonds,
            all taken warm. Fomentations of <lb/>warm Water ſhould alſo be applied to the Throat,
            <lb/>the Breaſt and Belly, with Glyſters of the ſame, <lb/>and a little Milk. In this
            Caſe, as well as in the <lb/>preceding one, (§ 3.) a <hi rend="italic">Semicupium</hi>,
            or Half- <lb/>bath of warm Water has ſometimes been attend- <lb/>ed with immediate
            Relief. It ſeems really aſto- <lb/>niſhing, that labouring People ſhould ſo often
            <lb/>habituate themſelves to this pernicious Cuſtom, <lb/>which they know to be ſo very
            dangerous to <lb/>their very Beaſts. There are none of them, who <lb/>will not prevent
            their Horſes from drinking <lb/>while they are hot, eſpecially if they are juſt go-
            <lb/>ing to put them up. Each of them knows, that <lb/>if he lets them drink in that
            State, they might <lb/>poſſibly burſt with it; nevertheleſs he is not <lb/>afraid of
            incurring the like Danger himſelf. How- <lb/>ever, this is not the only Caſe, in which
            the <lb/>Peaſant ſeems to have more Attention to the <lb/>Health of his Cattle, than to
            his own. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="35"/>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 5. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>The fourth Cauſe, which indeed affects <lb/>every Body, but more particularly the
            Labour- <lb/>er, is, the Inconſtancy of the Weather. We <lb/>ſhift all at once, many
            times a Day, from Hot <lb/>to Cold, and from Cold to Hot, in a more re- <lb/>markable
            Manner, and more ſuddenly, than in <lb/>moſt other Countries. This makes Diſtempers
            <lb/>from Defluxion and Cold ſo common with us: <lb/>and it ſhould make us careful to go
            rather a <lb/>little more warmly cloathed, than the Seaſon may <lb/>ſeem to require; to
            have Recourſe to our Winter- <lb/>cloathing early in Autumn, and not to part with
            <lb/>it too early in the Spring. Prudent Labour- <lb/>ers, who ſtrip while they are at
            Work, take care <lb/>to put on their Cloaths in the Evening when <lb/>they return home.
              <note rend="size(0.5)" n="*" place="bottom">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* This good Advice is enforced in a Note, by the Editor of <lb/><hi
                  rend="italic">Lyons</hi>, who obſerves, it ſhould be ſtill more cloſely attended
                to, <lb/>in Places, where Rivers, Woods or Mountains retain, as it <lb/>were, a
                conſiderable Humidity; and where the Evenings are, <lb/>in every Seaſon, cold and
                moiſt.—It is a very proper Caution <lb/>too in our own variable Climate, and in many
                of our Colonies <lb/>in North <hi rend="italic">America</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
                  >K.</hi>
              </p>
            </note>
            <lb/>Thoſe, who from Negli- <lb/>gence, are ſatisfied with hanging them upon their
            <lb/>Country Tools, frequently experience, on their <lb/>Return, the very unhappy
            Effects of it. There <lb/>are ſome, tho' not many Places, where the Air <lb/>itſelf is
            unwholſome, more from its particular <lb/>Quality, than from its Changes of Temperature,
            <lb/>as at <hi rend="italic">Villeneuve</hi>, and ſtill more at <hi rend="italic"
              >Noville</hi>, and <lb/>in ſome other Villages ſituated among the Marſh- <lb/>es which
            border on the <hi rend="italic">Rhone</hi>. Theſe Countries <pb n="36"/>
            <lb/>are particularly ſubject to intermitting Fevers, of <lb/>which I ſhall treat
            briefly hereafter. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 6. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>Such ſudden Changes are often attend- <lb/>ed with great Showers of Rain, and even
            cold <lb/>Rain, in the Middle of a very hot Day; when <lb/>the Labourer who was bathed,
            as it were, in a <lb/>hot Sweat, is at once moiſtened in cold Water; <lb/>which
            occaſions the ſame Diſtempers, as the ſud- <lb/>den Tranſition from Heat to Cold, and
            requires <lb/>the ſame Remedies. If the Sun or a hot Air <lb/>ſucceed immediately to
            ſuch a Shower, the Evil <lb/>is conſiderably lighter: but if the Cold continues,
            <lb/>many are often greatly incommoded by it. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>A Traveller is ſometimes thoroughly and un- <lb/>avoidably wet with Mud; the ill
            Conſequence <lb/>of which is often inconſiderable, provided he <lb/>changes his Cloaths
            immediately, when he ſets <lb/>up. I have known fatal Pleuriſies enſue from
            <lb/>omitting this Caution. Whenever the Body or <lb/>the Limbs are wet, nothing can be
            more uſeful <lb/>than bathing them in warm Water. If the Legs <lb/>only have been wet,
            it may be ſufficient to bath <lb/>them. I have radically, thoroughly, cured Per-
            <lb/>ſons ſubject to violent Cholics, as often as their <lb/>Feet were wet, by
            perſuading them to purſue this <lb/>Advice. The Bath proves ſtill more effectual,
            <lb/>if a little Soap be diſſolved in it. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 7. </head>
          <p>A fifth Cauſe, which is ſeldom attended <lb/>to, probably indeed becauſe it produces
            leſs vio- <lb/>lent Conſequences, and yet is certainly hurtful, <lb/>is the common
            Cuſtom in all Villages, of having <lb/>their Ditches or Dunghills directly under their
              <pb n="37"/>
            <lb/>Windows. Corrupted Vapours are continually <lb/>exhaling from them, which in Time
            cannot fail <lb/>of being prejudicial, and muſt contribute to pro- <lb/>duce putrid
            Diſeaſes. Thoſe who are accuſtom- <lb/>ed to the Smell, become inſenſible of it: but the
            <lb/>Cauſe, nevertheleſs, does not ceaſe to be un- <lb/>wholeſomly active; and ſuch as
            are unuſed to it <lb/>perceive the Impreſſion in all its Force. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 8. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>There are ſome Villages, in which, after <lb/>the Curtain Lines are eraſed, watery
            marſhy Places <lb/>remain in the Room of them. The Effect of this <lb/>is ſtill more
            dangerous, becauſe that putrify'd <lb/>Water, which ſtagnates during the hot Seaſon,
            <lb/>ſuffers its Vapours to exhale more eaſily, and more <lb/>abundantly, than that in
            the Curtain Lines did. <lb/>Having ſet out for <hi rend="italic">Pully le Grand</hi>, in
            1759, on <lb/>Account of an epidemical putrid Fever which <lb/>raged there, I was
            ſenſible, on traverſing the <lb/>Village, of the Infection from thoſe Marſhes; nor
            <lb/>could I doubt of their being the Cauſe of this <lb/>Diſeaſe, as well as of another
            like it, which had <lb/>prevailed there five Years before. In other Re- <lb/>ſpects the
            Village is wholeſomly ſituated. It <lb/>were to be wiſhed ſuch Accidents were obviated
            <lb/>by avoiding theſe ſtagnated Places; or, at leaſt, <lb/>by removing them and the
            Dunghils, as far as <lb/>poſſible from the Spot, where we live and lodge. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 9. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>To this Cauſe may alſo be added the <lb/>Neglect of the Peaſants to air their
            Lodgings. It <lb/>is well known that too cloſe an Air occaſions the <lb/>moſt perplexing
            malignant Fevers; and the poor <lb/>Country People reſpire no other in their own <pb
              n="38"/>
            <lb/>Houſes. Their Lodgings, which are very ſmall, <lb/>and which notwithſtanding
            incloſe, (both Day and <lb/>Night) the Father, Mother, and ſeven or eight <lb/>Children,
            beſides ſome Animals, are never kept <lb/>open during ſix Months in the Year, and very
            <lb/>ſeldom during the other ſix. I have found the <lb/>Air ſo bad in many of theſe
            Houſes, that I am <lb/>perſuaded, if their Inhabitants did not often go <lb/>out into
            the free open Air, they muſt all periſh <lb/>in a little Time. It is eaſy, however, to
            prevent <lb/>all the Evils ariſing from this Source, by opening <lb/>the Windows daily:
            ſo very practicable a Precau- <lb/>tion muſt be followed with the happieſt Conſe-
            <lb/>quences. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 10. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>I conſider Drunkenneſs as a ſixth Cauſe, <lb/>not indeed as producing epidemical
            Diſeaſes, but <lb/>which deſtroys, as it were, by Retail, at all <lb/>times, and every
            where. The poor Wretches, <lb/>who abandon themſelves to it, are ſubject to
            <lb/>frequent Inflammations of the Breaſt, and to <lb/>Pleuriſies, which often carry
            them off in the <lb/>Flower of their Age. If they ſometimes eſcape <lb/>through theſe
            violent Maladies, they ſink, a long <lb/>Time before the ordinary Approach of old Age,
            <lb/>into all its Infirmities, and eſpecially into an <lb/>Aſthma, which terminates in a
            Dropſy of the <lb/>Breaſt. Their Bodies, worn out by Exceſs, do <lb/>not comply and
            concur, as they ought, with the <lb/>Force or Operation of Remedies; and Diſeaſes
            <lb/>of Weakneſs, reſulting from this Cauſe, are al- <lb/>moſt always incurable. It
            ſeems happy enough, <lb/>that Society loſes nothing in parting with theſe <pb n="39"/>
            <lb/>Subjects, who are a Diſhonour to it; and whoſe <lb/>brutal Souls are, in ſome
            Meaſure, dead, long <lb/>before their Carcaſes. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 11. </head>
          <p>The Proviſions of the common People <lb/>are alſo frequently one Cauſe of popular Mala-
            <lb/>dies. This happens 1ſt, whenever the Corn, <lb/>not well ripened, or not well got
            in, in bad <note rend="size(0.5)" type="footnote" n="*" place="bottom">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* Thus I have ventured to tranſlate <hi rend="italic">Etés (Summers)</hi> to
                ap- <lb/>ply it to this and the neighbouring Iſlands. Their Harveſts <lb/>in <hi
                  rend="italic">Swiſſerland</hi> perhaps are earlier, and may occur in <hi
                  rend="italic">Auguſt</hi>, and <lb/>that of ſome particular Grain, probably ſtill
                earlier. <hi rend="italic">K.</hi>
              </p>
            </note>
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Harveſts</hi>, has contracted an unwholeſome Qua- <lb/>lity.
            Fortunately however this is ſeldom the <lb/>Caſe; and the Danger attending the Uſe of
            it, <lb/>may be leſſened by ſome Precautions, ſuch as <lb/>thoſe of waſhing and drying
            the Grain compleat- <lb/>ly; of mixing a little Wine with the Dough, in <lb/>kneading
            it; by allowing it a little more Time to <lb/>ſwell or riſe, and by baking it a little
            more. 2dly, <lb/>The fairer and better ſaved Part of the Wheat is <lb/>ſometimes damaged
            in the Farmers Houſe; ei- <lb/>ther becauſe he does not take due Care of it, or
            <lb/>becauſe he has no convenient Place to preſerve it, <lb/>only from one Summer to the
            next. It has often <lb/>happened to me, on entering one of theſe bad <lb/>Houſes, to be
            ſtruck with the Smell of Wheat <lb/>that has been ſpoiled. Nevertheleſs, there are
            <lb/>known and eaſy Methods to provide againſt this <lb/>by a little Care; though I
            ſhall not enter into a <lb/>Detail of them. It is ſufficient to make the Peo- <lb/>ple
            ſenſible, that ſince their chief Suſtenance con- <lb/>ſiſts of Corn, their Health muſt
            neceſſarily be <pb n="40"/>
            <lb/>impaired by what is bad. 3dly, That Wheat, <lb/>which is good, is often made into
            bad Bread, by <lb/>not letting it riſe ſufficiently; by baking it too <lb/>little, and
            by keeping it too long. All theſe Er- <lb/>rors have their troubleſome Conſequences on
            thoſe <lb/>who eat it; but in a greater Degree on Children <lb/>and Valetudinarians, or
            weakly People. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Tarts or Cakes may be conſidered as an Abuſe <lb/>of Bread, and this in ſome
            Villages is increaſed <lb/>to a very pernicious Height. The Dough is al- <lb/>moſt
            conſtantly bad, and often unleavened, ill <lb/>baked, greaſy, and ſtuffed with either
            fat or ſour <lb/>Ingredients, which compound one of the moſt in- <lb/>digeſtible
            Aliments imaginable. Women and <lb/>Children conſume the moſt of this Food, and <lb/>are
            the very Subjects for whom it is the moſt <lb/>improper: little Children eſpecially, who
            live <lb/>ſometimes for many ſucceſſive Days on theſe <lb/>Tarts, are, for the greater
            Part, unable to digeſt <lb/>them perfectly. Hence they receive a <note rend="size(0.5)"
              n="*" place="bottom">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>*The Abuſe juſt mentioned can ſcarcely be intended to for- <lb/>bid the
                moderate Uſe of good Paſtry, the Dough of which is <lb/>well raiſed and well baked,
                the Flower and other Ingredients <lb/>ſound, and the Paſte not overcharged with
                Butter, even though <lb/>it were ſweet and freſh. But the Abuſe of Alum and other
                <lb/>pernicious Materials introduced by our Bakers, may too juſtly <lb/>be
                conſidered as one horrible Source of thoſe Diſeaſes of Chil- <lb/>dren, &amp;c.
                which our humane and judicious Author mentions <lb/>here. What he adds, concerning
                the Paſtries being rendered <lb/>ſtill more unwholeſome by the ſour Fruits ſometimes
                baked in <lb/>it, is true with Reſpect to thoſe Children and others, who are
                <lb/>liable to Complaints from Acidities abounding in the Bowels; <lb/>and for all
                thoſe who are ricketty or ſcrophulous, from a cold <lb/>and viſcid State of their
                Humours. But as to healthy ſanguine <pb n="41" type="footnote"/>
                <lb/>Children, who are advanced and lively, and others of a ſanguine <lb/>or bilious
                Temperament, we are not to ſuppoſe a moderate Va- <lb/>riety of this Food injurious
                to them; when we conſider, that <lb/>the Sharpneſs and Crudity of the Fruit is
                conſiderably correct- <lb/>ed by the long Application of Fire; and that they are the
                Pro- <lb/>duce of Summer, when bilious Diſeaſes are moſt frequent. <lb/>This
                ſuggeſts however <unclear>no</unclear> bad Hint againſt making them im-
                <lb/>moderately ſweet. <hi rend="italic">K.</hi>
              </p>
            </note> Source <pb n="41"/>
            <lb/>of Obſtructions in the Bowels of the Belly, and <lb/>of a ſlimy Viſcidity or
            Thickiſhneſs, throughout <lb/>the Maſs of Humours, which throws them into <lb/>various
            Diſeaſes from Weakneſs; ſlow Fevers, a <lb/>Hectic, the Rickets, the King's Evil, and
            Feeble- <lb/>neſs; for the miſerable Remainder of their Days. <lb/>Probably indeed there
            is nothing more unwhole- <lb/>ſome than Dough not ſufficiently leavened, ill-
            <lb/>baked, greaſy, and ſoured by the Addition of <lb/>Fruits. Beſides, if we conſider
            theſe Tarts in an <lb/>oeconomical View, they muſt be found incon- <lb/>venient alſo for
            the Peaſant on that Account. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Some other Cauſes of Maladies may alſo be <lb/>referred to the Article of Food,
            tho' leſs grievous <lb/>and leſs frequent, into a full Detail of which it is <lb/>very
            difficult to enter: I ſhall therefore conclude <lb/>that Article with this general
            Remark; that it <lb/>is the Care which Peaſants uſually take in eating <lb/>ſlowly, and
            in chewing very well, that very <lb/>greatly leſſens the Dangers from a bad Regimen:
            <lb/>and I am convinced they conſtitute one of the <lb/>greateſt Cauſes of that Health
            they enjoy. We <lb/>may further add indeed the Exerciſe which <lb/>the Peaſant uſes, his
            long abiding in the open Air, <lb/>where he paſſes three fourths of his Life; beſides
              <pb n="42"/>
            <lb/>(which are alſo conſiderable Advantages) his <lb/>happy Cuſtom of going ſoon to
            Bed, and of riſing <lb/>very early. It were to be wiſhed, that in theſe <lb/>Reſpects,
            and perhaps on many other Accounts, <lb/>the Inhabitants of the Country were effectually
            <lb/>propoſed as Models for reforming the Citizens. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 12. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>We ſhould not omit, in enumerating <lb/>the Cauſes of Maladies among Country
            People, <lb/>the Conſtruction of their Houſes, a great many <lb/>of which either lean,
            as it were, cloſe to a <lb/>higher Ground, or are ſunk a little in the Earth. <lb/>Each
            of theſe Situations ſubjects them to conſi- <lb/>derable Humidity; which is certain
            greatly to <lb/>incommode the Inhabitants, and to ſpoil their <lb/>Proviſions, if they
            have any Quantity in Store; <lb/>which, as we have obſerved, is another, and <lb/>not
            the leaſt important, Source of their Diſeaſes. <lb/>A hardy Labourer is not immediately
            ſenſible of <lb/>the bad Influence of this moiſt and marſhy Ha- <lb/>bitation; but they
            operate at the long Run, and <lb/>I have abundantly obſerved their moſt evident <lb/>bad
            Effects, eſpecially on Women in Child-bed, <lb/>on Children, and in Perſons recovering
            of a pre- <lb/>ceding Diſeaſe. It would be eaſy to prevent <lb/>this Inconvenience, by
            raiſing the Ground on <lb/>which the Houſe ſtood, ſome, or ſeveral, In- <lb/>ches above
            the Level of the adjacent Soil, by a <lb/>Bed of Gravel, of ſmall Flints, pounded
            Bricks, <lb/>Coals, or ſuch other Materials; and by avoiding <lb/>to build immediately
            cloſe to, or, as it were, <lb/>under a much higher Soil. This Object, per- <pb n="43"/>
            <lb/>haps, may well deſerve the Attention of the <lb/>Publick; and I earneſtly adviſe as
            many as do <lb/>build, to obſerve the neceſſary Precautions on <lb/>this Head. Another,
            which would coſt ſtill <lb/>leſs Trouble, is to give the Front of their <lb/>Houſes an
            Expoſure to the South-Eaſt. This <lb/>Expoſure, ſuppoſing all other Circumſtances of
            <lb/>the Building and its Situation to be alike, is <lb/>both the moſt wholeſome and
            advantageous. I <lb/>have ſeen it, notwithſtanding, very often neg- <lb/>lected, without
            the leaſt Reaſon being aſſigned <lb/>for not preferring it. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Theſe Admonitions may poſſibly be thought <lb/>of little Conſequence by three
            fourths of the Peo- <lb/>ple. I take the Liberty of reminding them, <lb/>however, that
            they are more important than they <lb/>may be ſuppoſed; and ſo many Cauſes concur to
            <lb/>the Deſtruction of Men, that none of the Means <lb/>ſhould be neglected, which may
            contribute to <lb/>their Preſervation. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 13. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>The Country People in <hi rend="italic">Swiſſerland</hi>
            <lb/>drink, either 1, pure Water, 2, ſome Wine, 3, <lb/>Perry, made from wild Pears, or
            ſometimes Cy- <lb/>der from Apples, and, 4, a ſmall Liquor which <lb/>they call <hi
              rend="italic">Piquette</hi>, that is Water, which has <lb/>fermented with the Cake or
            Huſks of the <lb/>Grapes, after their Juice has been expreſſed. <lb/>Water however is
            their moſt general Drink; <lb/>Wine rarely falling in their Way, but when <lb/>they are
            employed by rich Folks; or when they <lb/>can ſpare Money enough for a Debauch. Fruit-
              <pb n="44"/>
            <lb/>Wines and the <note rend="size(0.5)" type="footnote" n="*" place="bottom">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* This Word's occurring in the plural Number will proba- <lb/>bly imply, the
                  <hi rend="italic">Swiſs</hi> make more than one Species of this ſmall <lb/>Drink,
                by pouring Water on the Cake or Remainder of their <lb/>other Fruits, after they
                have been expreſſed; as our People in <lb/>the Cyder, and perhaps in the Perry,
                Counties, make what <lb/>they call <hi rend="italic">Cyderkin</hi>, <hi
                  rend="italic">Perkin</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> It ſhould ſeem too from
                this <lb/>Section, that the laborious Countrymen in <hi rend="italic"
                  >Swiſſerland</hi> drink no <lb/>Malt Liquor, though the Ingredients may be
                ſuppoſed to grow <lb/>in their Climate. Now Beer, of different Strength, making
                <lb/>the greater Part of our moſt common Drink, it may be proper <lb/>to obſerve
                here, that when it is not ſtrong and heady, but a <lb/>middling well-brewed
                Small-beer, neither too new, nor hard <lb/>or ſour, it is full as wholeſome a Drink
                for laborious People in <lb/>Health as any other, and perhaps generally preferable
                to Wa- <lb/>ter for ſuch; which may be too thin and light for thoſe who are
                <lb/>unaccuſtomed to it; and more dangerous too, when the la- <lb/>bouring Man is
                very hot, as well as thirſty. The holding a <lb/>Mouthful of any weak cold Liquor in
                the Mouth without <lb/>ſwallowing 'till it becomes warm there, and ſpurting it out
                <lb/>before a Draught is taken down would be prudent; and in <lb/>Caſe of great
                Heat, to take the requiſite Quantity rather at <lb/>two Draughts, with a little
                Interval between them, than to <lb/>ſwallow the Whole precipitately at one, would be
                more ſafe, <lb/>and equally refreſhing, though perhaps leſs grateful. <hi
                  rend="italic">K.</hi>
              </p>
            </note>
            <hi rend="italic">Piquettes</hi> are not uſed in all <lb/>Parts of the Country; they are
            not made in all <lb/>Years; and keep but for ſome Months. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Our Waters in general, are pretty good; ſo <lb/>that we have little Occaſion to
            trouble ourſelves <lb/>about purifying them; and they are well known <lb/>in thoſe
            Provinces where they are chiefly and <lb/>neceſſarily uſed. <note rend="size(0.5)"
              n="(I)" place="bottom">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>(I) The bad Quality of Water is another common Cauſe of <lb/>Country Diſeaſes;
                either where the Waters are unwholeſome, <lb/>from the Soils in which they are
                found, as when they flow <lb/>through, or ſettle, on Banks of Shells; or where they
                become <lb/>ſuch, from the Neighbourhood of, or Drainings from Dung- <lb/>hills and
                Marſhes. </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>When Water is unclear and turbid, it is generally ſufficient <lb/>to let it
                ſettle in order to clear itſelf, by dropping its Sedi- <pb n="45" type="footnote"/>
                <lb/>ment. But if that is not effected, or if it be ſlimy or muddy, <lb/>it need
                only be poured into a large Veſſel, half filled with fine <lb/>Sand, or, for want of
                that, with Chalk; and then to ſhake <lb/>and ſtir it about heartily for ſome
                Minutes. When this Agita- <lb/>tion is over, the Sand, in falling to the Bottom of
                the Veſſel, <lb/>will attract ſome of the Foulneſs ſuſpended in the Water. <lb/>Or,
                which is ſtill better, and very eaſy to do, two large Veſ- <lb/>ſels may be ſet near
                together, one of which ſhould be placed <lb/>conſiderably higher than the other. The
                higheſt ſhould be half <lb/>filled with Sand. Into this the turbid, or ſlimy muddy
                Water <lb/>is to be poured; whence it will filter itſelf through the Body of
                <lb/>Sand, and paſs off clear by an Opening or Orifice made at the <lb/>Bottom of
                the Veſſel; and fall from thence into the lower one, <lb/>which ſerves as a
                Reſervoir. When the Water is impregnated <lb/>with Particles from the Beds of
                Selenites, or of any Spar (which <lb/>Water we call hard, becauſe Soap will not
                eaſily diſſolve in it, <lb/>and Puls and other farinaceous Subſtances grow hard
                inſtead of <lb/>ſoft, after boiling in it) ſuch Water ſhould be expoſed to the
                <lb/>Sun, or boiled with the Addition of ſome Puls, or leguminous <lb/>Vegetables,
                or Bread toaſted, or untoaſted. When Water is <lb/>in its putrid State, it may be
                kept till it recovers its natural <lb/>ſweet one: but if this cannot be waited for,
                a little Sea Salt <lb/>ſhould be diſſolved in it, or ſome Vinegar may be added, in
                <lb/>which ſome grateful aromatic Plant has been infuſed. It fre- <lb/>quently
                happens, that the publick Wells are corrupted by foul <lb/>Mud at the Bottom, and by
                different Animals which tumble in <lb/>and putrify there. Drinking Snow-water ſhould
                be avoided, <lb/>when the Snow is but lately fallen, as it ſeems to be the Cauſe
                <lb/>of thoſe ſwelling wenny Throats in the Inhabitants of ſome <lb/>Mountains; and
                of endemic Cholics in many Perſons. As <lb/>Water is ſo continually uſed, great Care
                ſhould be taken to <lb/>have what is good. Bad Water, like bad Air, is one of the
                <lb/>moſt general Cauſes of Diſeaſes; that which produces the <lb/>greater Number of
                them, the moſt grieveous ones; and often <lb/>introduces ſuch as are epidemical. <hi
                  rend="italic">E. L.</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the Editor of <hi rend="italic">Lyons</hi>. </p>
            </note>
            <lb/>The pernicious Methods <pb n="45"/>
            <lb/>taken to improve or meliorate, as it is falſely <lb/>called, bad Wines, are not as
            yet ſufficiently <lb/>practiced among us, for me to treat of them here: <lb/>and as our
            Wines are not hurtful, of themſelves, <lb/>they become hurtful only from their Quantity.
            <lb/>The Conſumption of made Wines and <hi rend="italic">Piquettes</hi>
            <lb/>is but inconſiderable, and I have not hitherto <pb n="46"/>
            <lb/>known of any ill Effects from them, ſo that our <lb/>Liquors cannot be conſidered
            as Cauſes of Diſ- <lb/>tempers in our Country; but in Proportion to <lb/>our Abuſe of
            them by Exceſs. The Caſe is dif- <lb/>ferently circumſtanced in ſome <note
              rend="size(0.5)" place="end" n="(I)">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>(I) Many Perſons, With a Deſign to preſerve their Wines, <lb/>add Shot to them,
                or Preparations of Lead, Alum, &amp;c. The <lb/>Government ſhould forbid, under the
                moſt ſevere Penalties, all <lb/>ſuch Adulterations, as tend to introduce the moſt
                painful Cho- <lb/>lics, Obſtruction, and a long Train of Evils, which it ſome-
                <lb/>times proves difficult to trace to this peculiar Cauſe; while <lb/>they ſhorten
                the Lives of, or cruelly torment, ſuch over credu- <lb/>lous Purchaſers, as lay in a
                Stock of bad Wines, or drink of <lb/>them, without diſtinction, from every Wine
                Merchant or <lb/>Tavern. <hi rend="italic">E. L.</hi>
              </p>
              <p rend="indent italic">
                <lb/>This Note, from the Editor at <hi rend="roman">Lyons</hi>, we have ſufficient
                Reaſon <lb/>for retaining here. K. </p>
            </note>
            <lb/>other Coun- <lb/>tries; and it is the Province of Phyſicians who <lb/>reſide in
            them, to point out to their Country- <lb/>Men the Methods of preſerving their Health; as
            <lb/>well as the proper and neceſſary Remedies in <lb/>their Sickneſs. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="4"> </space>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>Triangular ornament in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <pb n="47"/>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>An ornamented horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <div type="chapter">
        <head rend="sc align-center space">
          <lb/>CHAPTER II. </head>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Of the Cauſes which aggravate the Diſeaſes of the <lb/>People. General
          Conſiderations. </head>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="sc align-center space">
            <lb/>SECT. 14. </head>
          <lb/>
          <p><hi rend="dc(4)">T</hi>HE Cauſes already enumerated in <lb/>the firſt Chapter occaſion
            Diſeaſes; <lb/>and the bad Regimen, or Conduct of <lb/>the People, on the Invaſion of
            them, <lb/>render them ſtill more perplexing, and very often <lb/>mortal. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>There is a prevailing Prejudice among them, <lb/>which is every Year attended with
            the Death of <lb/>ſome Hundreds in this Country, and it is this— <lb/>That all
            Diſtempers are cured by Sweat; and <lb/>that to procure Sweat, they muſt take Abundance
            <lb/>of hot and heating things, and keep themſelves <lb/>very hot. This is a Miſtake in
            both Reſpects, <lb/>very fatal to the Population of the State; and it <lb/>cannot be too
            much inculcated into Country <lb/>People; that by thus endeavouring to force Sweat-
            <lb/>ing, at the very Beginning of a Diſeaſe, they are <lb/>with great Probability,
            taking Pains to kill them- <lb/>ſelves. I have ſeen ſome Caſes, in which the
            <lb/>continual Care to provoke this Sweating, has as <lb/>manifeſtly killed the Patient,
            as if a Ball had <lb/>been ſhot through his Brains; as ſuch a precipitate <pb n="48"/>
            <lb/>and untimely Diſcharge carries off the thinner Part <lb/>of the Blood, leaving the
            Maſs more dry, more viſcid <lb/>and inflamed. Now as in all acute Diſeaſes (if we
            <lb/>except a very few, and thoſe too much leſs fre- <lb/>quent) the Blood is already
            too thick; ſuch a <lb/>Diſcharge muſt evidently increaſe the Diſorder, <lb/>by
            co-operating with its Cauſe. Inſtead of for- <lb/>cing out the watery, the thinner Part
            of the <lb/>Blood, we ſhould rather endeavour to increaſe it. <lb/>There is not a ſingle
            Peaſant perhaps, who does <lb/>not ſay, when he has a Pleuriſy, or an Inflamma-
            <lb/>tion of his Breaſt, that his Blood is too thick, and <lb/>that it cannot circulate.
            On ſeeing it in the <lb/>Baſon after Bleeding, he finds it <hi rend="italic">black, dry,
              burnt</hi>; <lb/>theſe are his very Words. How ſtrange is it <lb/>then, that common
            Senſe ſhould not aſſure him, <lb/>that, far from forcing out the <hi rend="italic"
              >Serum</hi>, the watery <lb/>Part, of ſuch a Blood by ſweating, there is a Ne-
            <lb/>ceſſity to increaſe it? </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 15. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>But ſuppoſing it were as certain, as it is <lb/>erroneous, that Sweating was
            beneficial at the <lb/>Beginning of Diſeaſes, the Means which they <lb/>uſe to excite it
            would not prove the leſs fatal. <lb/>The firſt Endeavour is, to ſtifle the Patient with
            <lb/>the Heat of a cloſe Apartment, and a Load of <lb/>Covering. Extraordinary Care is
            taken to prevent <lb/>a Breath of freſh Air's ſqueezing into the Room; <lb/>from which
            Circumſtance, the Air already in it <lb/>is ſpeedily and extremely corrupted: and ſuch a
            <lb/>Degree of Heat is procured by the Weight of the <lb/>Patient's Bed-cloaths, that
            theſe two Cauſes alone <lb/>are ſufficient to excite a moſt ardent Fever, and <pb n="49"/>
            <lb/>an Inflammation of the Breaſt, even in a healthy <lb/>Man. More than once have I
            found myſelf <lb/>ſeized with a Difficulty of breathing, on entering <lb/>ſuch Chambers,
            from which I have been imme- <lb/>diately relieved, on obliging them to open all
            <lb/>the Windows. Perſons of Education muſt find <lb/>a Pleaſure, I conceive, in making
            People un- <lb/>derſtand, on theſe Occaſions, which are ſo fre- <lb/>quent, that the Air
            being more indiſpenſably ne- <lb/>ceſſary to us, if poſſible, than Water is to a Fiſh,
            <lb/>our Health muſt immediately ſuffer, whenever <lb/>that ceaſes to be pure; and in
            aſſuring them <lb/>alſo, that nothing corrupts it ſooner than thoſe <lb/>Vapours, which
            continually ſteam from the Bo- <lb/>dies of many Perſons incloſed within a little
            <lb/>Chamber, from which the Air is excluded. <lb/>The Abſurdity of ſuch Conduct is a
            ſelf-evident <lb/>Certainty. Let in a little freſh Air on theſe <lb/>miſerable Patients,
            and leſſen the oppreſſing Bur- <lb/>then of their Coverings, and you generally ſee
            <lb/>upon the Spot, their Fever and Oppreſſion, their <lb/>Anguiſh and Raving, to abate.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 16. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>The ſecond Method taken to raiſe a <lb/>Sweat in theſe Patients is, to give them
            nothing <lb/>but hot things, eſpecially Venice Treacle, Wine, <lb/>or ſome <note
              rend="size(0.5)" n="*" place="bottom">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* This Word, which muſt be of German, not of French Ex- <lb/>traction, ſtrictly
                ſignifies, <hi rend="italic">Drink for a Fall</hi>, as we ſay <hi rend="italic"
                  >Pulvis ad <lb/>Caſum</hi>, &amp;c. Powder for a Fall, or a ſuppoſed inward
                Bruiſe. <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Tiſſot</hi> informs me, it is otherwiſe called
                the vulnerary Herbs, <lb/>or the Swiſs Tea; and that it is an injudicious <hi
                  rend="italic">Farrago</hi> or Med- <pb n="50" type="footnote"/>
                <lb/>ley of Herbs and Flowers, blended with Bitters, with ſtimula- <lb/>ting, harſh
                and aſtringent Ingredients, being employed indiſ- <lb/>criminately in all their
                Diſtempers by the Country People in <lb/><hi rend="italic"
                    ><unclear>Swiſſerland</unclear></hi>. <hi rend="italic">K.</hi>
              </p>
            </note><hi rend="italic">Faltranc</hi>, the greater Part of the Ingredi- <pb n="50"/>
            <lb/>ents of which are dangerous, whenever there is <lb/>an evident Fever; beſides
            Saffron, which is ſtill <lb/>more pernicious. In all feveriſh Diſorders we <lb/>ſhould
            gently cool, and keep the Belly mode- <lb/>rately open; while the Medicines juſt
            mentioned <lb/>both heat and bind; and hence we may eaſily <lb/>judge of their
            inevitable ill Conſequences. A <lb/>healthy Perſon would certainly be ſeized with an
            <lb/>inflammatory Fever, on taking the ſame Quan- <lb/>tity of Wine, of Venice Treacle,
            or of <hi rend="italic">Faltranc</hi>, <lb/>which the Peaſant takes now and then, when
            he <lb/>is attacked by one of theſe Diſorders. How <lb/>then ſhould a ſick Perſon eſcape
            dying by them? <lb/>Die indeed he <hi rend="italic">generally</hi> does, and ſometimes
            with <lb/>aſtoniſhing Speed. I have publiſhed ſome dread- <lb/>ful Inſtances of ſuch
            Fatality ſome Years ſince, <lb/>in another Treatiſe. In fact they ſtill daily oc-
            <lb/>cur, and unhappily every Perſon may obſerve <lb/>ſome of them in his own
            Neighbourhood. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 17. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>But I ſhall be told perhaps, that Diſeaſes <lb/>are often carried off by Sweat, and
            that we ought <lb/>to be guided by Experience. To this I anſwer, <lb/>it is very true,
            that Sweating cures ſome particu- <lb/>lar Diſorders, as it were, at their very Onſet,
            for <lb/>Inſtance, thoſe Stitches that are called ſpurious <lb/>or falſe Pleuriſies,
            ſome rheumatic Pains, and <lb/>ſome Colds or Defluxions. But this only hap- <lb/>pens
            when the Diſorders depend ſolely and ſim- <pb n="51"/>
            <lb/>ply on ſtopt or abated Perſpiration, to which ſuch <lb/>Pain inſtantly ſucceeds;
            and where immediately, <lb/>before the Fever has thickened the Blood, and <lb/>inflamed
            the Humours; and where before any <lb/>internal Infarction, any Load, is formed, ſome
            <lb/>warm Drinks are given, ſuch as <hi rend="italic">Faltranc</hi> and <lb/>Honey; and
            which, by reſtoring Tranſpiration, <lb/>remove the very Cauſe of the Diſorder. Never-
            <lb/>theleſs, even in ſuch a Caſe, great Care ſhould <lb/>be had not to raiſe too
            violent a Commotion in <lb/>the Blood, which would rather reſtrain, than pro- <lb/>mote,
            Sweat, to effect which Elder-flowers are <lb/>in my Opinion preferable to <hi
              rend="italic">Faltranc</hi>. Sweating <lb/>is alſo of Service in Diſeaſes, when their
            Cauſes <lb/>are extinguiſhed, as it were, by plentiful Dilu- <lb/>tion: then indeed it
            relieves, by drawing off, <lb/>with itſelf, ſome Part of the diſtempered Hu- <lb/>mours;
            after which their groſſer Parts have paſſed <lb/>off by Stool and by Urine: beſides
            which, the <lb/>Sweat has alſo ſerved to carry off that extraor- <lb/>dinary Quantity of
            Water, we were obliged to <lb/>convey into the Blood, and which was become
            <lb/>ſuperfluous there. Under ſuch Circumſtances, <lb/>and at ſuch a Juncture, it is of
            the utmoſt Im- <lb/>portance indeed, not to check the Sweat, whether <lb/>by Choice, or
            for Want of Care. There might <lb/>often be as much Danger in doing this, as there
            <lb/>would have been in endeavouring to force a <lb/>Sweat, immediately upon the
            Invaſion of the <lb/>Diſorder; ſince the arreſting of this Diſcharge, <lb/>under the
            preceding Circumſtances, might fre- <lb/>quently occaſion a more dangerous Diſtemper, by
              <pb n="52"/>
            <lb/>repelling the Humour on ſome inward vital <lb/>Part. As much Care therefore ſhould
            be taken <lb/>not to check, imprudently, that Evacuation by <lb/>the Skin, which
            naturally occurs towards the <lb/>Concluſion of Diſeaſes, as not to force it at their
            <lb/>Beginning; the former being almoſt conſtantly <lb/>beneficial, the latter as
            conſtantly pernicious. <lb/>Beſides, were it even neceſſary, it might be very
            <lb/>dangerous to force it violently; ſince by heating <lb/>the Patients greatly, a
            vehement Fever is excited; <lb/>they become ſcorched up in a Manner, and the <lb/>Skin
            proves extremely dry. Warm Water, in <lb/>ſhort, is the beſt of Sudorifics. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If the Sick are ſweated very plentifully for a <lb/>Day or two, which may make them
            eaſier for <lb/>ſome Hours; theſe Sweats ſoon terminate, and <lb/>cannot be excited
            again by the ſame Medicines. <lb/>The Doſe thence is doubled, the Inflammation is
            <lb/>increaſed, and the Patient expires in terrible An- <lb/>guiſh, with all the Marks
            of a general Inflamma- <lb/>tion. His Death is aſcribed to his Want of <lb/>Sweating;
            when it really was the Conſequence <lb/>of his Sweating too much at firſt; and of his
            <lb/>taking Wine and hot Sudorifics. An able Swiſs <lb/>Phyſician had long ſince aſſured
            his Country- <lb/>men, that Wine was fatal to them in Fevers; I <lb/>take leave to
            repeat it again and again, and wiſh it <lb/>may not be with as little Succeſs. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Our Country Folks, who in Health, natu- <lb/>rally diſlike red Wine, prefer it when
            Sick; <lb/>which is wrong, as it binds them up more than <lb/>white Wine. It does not
            promote Urine as well; <pb n="53"/>
            <lb/>but increaſes the Force of the circulating Arte- <lb/>ries, and the Thickneſs of
            the Blood, which <lb/>were already too conſiderable. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 18. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>Their Diſeaſes are alſo further aggrava- <lb/>ted by the Food that is generally
            given them. <lb/>They muſt undoubtedly prove weak, in Conſe- <lb/>quence of their being
            ſick; and the ridiculous Fear <lb/>of the Patients' dying of Weakneſs, diſpoſes their
            <lb/>Friends to force them to eat; which, increaſing <lb/>their Diſorder, renders the
            Fever mortal. This <lb/>Fear is abſolutely chimerical; never yet did a <lb/>Perſon in a
            Fever die merely from Weakneſs. <lb/>They may be ſupported, even for ſome Weeks, <lb/>by
            Water only; and are ſtronger at the End of <lb/>that Time, than if they had taken more
            ſolid <lb/>Nouriſhment; ſince, far from ſtrengthening <lb/>them, their Food increaſes
            their Diſeaſe, and <lb/>thence increaſes their Weakneſs. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 19. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>From the firſt Invaſion of a Fever, Di- <lb/>geſtion ceaſes. Whatever ſolid Food is
            taken <lb/>corrupts, and proves a Source of Putridity, which <lb/>adds nothing to the
            Strength of the Sick, but <lb/>greatly to that of the Diſtemper. There are in <lb/>fact
            a thouſand Examples to prove, that it be- <lb/>comes a real Poiſon: and we may ſenſibly
            per- <lb/>ceive theſe poor Creatures, who are thus com- <lb/>pelled to eat, loſe their
            Strength, and fall into <lb/>Anxiety and Ravings, in Proportion as they ſwal- <lb/>low.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 20. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>They are alſo further injured by the <lb/>Quality, as well as the Quantity, of
            their Food. <lb/>They are forced to ſup ſtrong Gravey Soups, <pb n="54"/>
            <lb/>Eggs, Biſcuits, and even Fleſh, if they have but <lb/>juſt Strength and Reſolution
            to chew it. It ſeems <lb/>abſolutely impoſſible for them to ſurvive all this <lb/>Traſh.
            Should a Man in perfect Health be <lb/>compelled to eat ſtinking Meat, rotten Eggs,
            <lb/>ſtale ſour Broth, he is attacked with as violent <lb/>Symptoms, as if he had taken
            real Poiſon, which, <lb/>in Effect, he has. He is ſeized with Vomiting, <lb/>Anguiſh, a
            violent Purging, and a Fever, with <lb/>Raving, and eruptive Spots, which we call the
            <lb/>Purple Fever. Now when the very ſame Arti- <lb/>cles of Food, in their ſoundeſt
            State, are given <lb/>to a Perſon in a Fever, the Heat, and the mor- <lb/>bid Matter
            already in his Stomach, quickly pu- <lb/>trify them; and after a few Hours produce all
            <lb/>the abovementioned Effects. Let any Man judge <lb/>then, if the leaſt Service can
            be expected from <lb/>them. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 21. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>It is a Truth eſtabliſhed by the firſt of <lb/>Phyſicians, above two thouſand Years
            paſt, and <lb/>ſtill further ratified by his Succeſſors, that as long <lb/>as a ſick
            Perſon has a bad Humour or Ferment <lb/>in his Stomach, his Weakneſs increaſes, in Pro-
            <lb/>portion to the Food he receives. For this being <lb/>corrupted by the infected
            Matter it meets there, <lb/>proves incapable of nouriſhing, and becomes a <lb/>conjunct
            or additional Cauſe of the Diſtemper. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The moſt obſerving Perſons conſtantly remark, <lb/>that whenever a feveriſh Patient
            ſups, what is <lb/>commonly called ſome good Broth, the Fever ga- <lb/>thers Strength
            and the Patient Weakneſs. The giv- <lb/>ing ſuch a Soup or Broth, though of the freſheſt
              <pb n="55"/>
            <lb/>ſoundeſt Meat, to a Man who has a high Fever, <lb/>or putrid Humours in his
            Stomach, is to do him <lb/>exactly the ſame Service, as if you had given him, <lb/>two
            or three Hours later, ſtale putrid Soup. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 22. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>I muſt alſo affirm, that this fatal Pre- <lb/>judice, of keeping up the Patients'
            Strength by <lb/>Food, is ſtill too much propagated, even among <lb/>thoſe very Perſons,
            whoſe Talents and whoſe <lb/>Education might be expected to exempt them <lb/>from any
            ſuch groſs Error. It were happy for <lb/>Mankind, and the Duration of their Lives would
            <lb/>generally be more extended, if they could be <lb/>thoroughly perſuaded of this
            medical, and ſo <lb/>very demonſtrable, Truth; — That the only <lb/>things which can
            ſtrengthen ſick Perſons are <lb/>thoſe, which are able to weaken their Diſeaſe; <lb/>but
            their Obſtinacy in this Reſpect is inconceiv- <lb/>able: it is another Evil ſuperadded
            to that of the <lb/>Diſeaſe, and ſometimes the more grievous one. <lb/>Out of twenty
            ſick Perſons, who are loſt in the <lb/>Country, more than two Thirds might often have
            <lb/>been cured, if being only lodged in a Place de- <lb/>fended from the Injuries of
            the Air, they were <lb/>ſupplied with Abundance of good Water. But <lb/>that moſt
            miſtaken Care and Regimen I have <lb/>been treating of, ſcarcely ſuffers one of the
            twenty <lb/>to ſurvive them. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 23. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>What further increaſes our Horror at <lb/>this enormous Propenſity to heat, dry up,
            and <lb/>cram the ſick is, that it is totally oppoſite to what <lb/>Nature herſelf
            indicates in ſuch Circumſtances. <lb/>The burning Heat of which they complain; the <pb
              n="56"/>
            <lb/>Dryneſs of the Lips, Tongue and Throat; the <lb/>flaming high Colour of their
            Urine; the great <lb/>Longing they have for cooling things; the Plea- <lb/>ſure and
            ſenſible Benefit they enjoy from freſh <lb/>Air, are ſo many Signs, or rather Proofs,
            which <lb/>cry out with a loud Voice, that we ought to at- <lb/>temperate and cool them
            moderately, by all <lb/>means. Their foul Tongues, which ſhew the <lb/>Stomach to be in
            the like Condition; their Loath- <lb/>ing, their Propenſity to vomit, their utter Aver-
            <lb/>ſion to all ſolid Food, and eſpecially to Fleſh; the <lb/>diſagreeable Stench of
            their Breath; their Diſ- <lb/>charge of fetid Wind upwards and downwards, <lb/>and
            frequently the extraordinary Offenſiveneſs of <lb/>their Excrements, demonſtrate, that
            their Bowels <lb/>are full of putrid Contents, which muſt corrupt <lb/>all the Aliments
            ſuperadded to them; and that <lb/>the only thing, which can prudently be done, is
            <lb/>to dilute and attemper them by plentiful Draughts <lb/>of refreſhing cooling
            Drinks, which may pro- <lb/>mote an eaſy Diſcharge of them. I affirm it <lb/>again, and
            I heartily wiſh it may be thoroughly <lb/>attended to, that as long as there is any
            Taſte of <lb/>Bitterneſs, or of Putreſcence; as long as there is <lb/>a <hi
              rend="italic">Nauſea</hi> or Loathing, a bad Breath, Heat and <lb/>Feveriſhneſs with
            fetid Stools, and little and high- <lb/>coloured Urine; ſo long all Fleſh, and
            Fleſh-Soup, <lb/>Eggs, and all kind of Food compoſed of them, <lb/>or of any of them,
            and all Venice Treacle, Wine, <lb/>and all heating things are ſo many abſolute Poi-
            <lb/>ſons. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 24. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>I may poſſibly be cenſured as extrava- <lb/>gant and exceſſive on theſe Heads by
            the Pub <pb n="57"/>
            <lb/>lick, and even by ſome Phyſicians: but the true <lb/>and enlightened Phyſicians,
            thoſe who attend to <lb/>the Effects of every Particular, will find on the
            <lb/>contrary, that far from exceeding in this Reſpect, <lb/>I have rather feebly
            expreſſed their own Judg- <lb/>ment, in which they agree with that of all the <lb/>good
            ones, who have exiſted within more than <lb/>two thouſand Years; that very Judgment
            which <lb/>Reaſon approves, and continual Experience con- <lb/>firms. The Prejudices I
            have been contending <lb/>againſt have coſt <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi> ſome Millions
            of Lives. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 25. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>Neither ſhould it be omitted, that even <lb/>when a Patient has very fortunately
            eſcaped <lb/>Death, notwithſtanding all this Care to obtain it, <lb/>the Miſchief is not
            ended; the Conſequences of <lb/>the high Aliments and heating Medicines being, <lb/>to
            leave behind the Seed, the Principle, of ſome <lb/>low and chronical Diſeaſe; which
            increaſing in- <lb/>ſenſibly, burſts out at length, and finally procures <lb/>him the
            Death he has even wiſhed for, to put an <lb/>End to his tedious Sufferings. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 26. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>I muſt alſo take Notice of another dange- <lb/>rous common Practice; which is that
            of purging, <lb/>or vomiting a Patient, at the very Beginning of a <lb/>Diſtemper.
            Infinite Miſchiefs are occaſioned by <lb/>it. There are ſome Caſes indeed, in which eva-
            <lb/>cuating Medicines, at the Beginning of a Diſeaſe, <lb/>are convenient and even
            neceſſary. Such Caſes <lb/>ſhall be particularly mentioned in ſome other <lb/>Chapters:
            but as long as we are unacquainted <lb/>with them, it ſhould be conſidered as a general
            <lb/>Rule, that they are hurtſul at the Beginning; this <pb n="58"/>
            <lb/>being true very often; and always, when the Diſ- <lb/>eaſes are ſtrictly
            inflammatory. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 27. </head>
          <p>It is hoped by their Aſſiſtance, at that <lb/>Time, to remove the Load and Oppreſſion
            of the <lb/>Stomach, the Cauſe of a Diſpoſition to vomit, of <lb/>a dry Mouth, of
            Thirſt, and of much Uneaſineſs; <lb/>and to leſſen the Leaven or Ferment of the Fever.
            <lb/>But in this Hope they are very often deceived; <lb/>ſince the Cauſes of theſe
            Symptoms are ſeldom <lb/>of a Nature to yield to theſe Evacuations. By the
            <lb/>extraordinary Viſcidity or Thickneſs of the Hu- <lb/>mours, that foul the Tongue,
            we ſhould form our <lb/>Notions of thoſe, which line the Stomach and <lb/>the Bowels. It
            may be waſhed, gargled and <lb/>even ſcraped to very little good Purpoſe. It does
            <lb/>not happen, until the Patient has drank for many <lb/>Days, and the Heat, the Fever
            and the great Si- <lb/>zineſs of the Humours are abated, that this Filth <lb/>can he
            thoroughly removed, which by Degrees <lb/>ſeparates of itſelf. The State of the Stomach
            <lb/>being conformable to that of the Tongue, no <lb/>Method can effectually ſcour and
            clean it at the <lb/>Beginning: but by giving refreſhing and diluting <lb/>Remedies
            plentifully, it gradually frees itſelf; and <lb/>the Propenſity to vomit, with its other
            Effects and <lb/>Uneaſineſſes, go off naturally, and without Pur- <lb/>ges. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 28. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>Neither are theſe Evacuations only ne- <lb/>gatively wrong, merely from doing no
            Good; <lb/>for conſiderable Evil poſitively enſues from the <lb/>Application of thoſe
            acrid irritating Medicines, <lb/>which increaſe the Pain and Inflammation; draw- <pb
              n="59"/>
            <lb/>ing the Humours upon thoſe Parts that were al- <lb/>ready overloaded with them;
            which by no means <lb/>expel the Cauſe of the Diſeaſe, that not being at this <lb/>time
            fitted for Expulſion, as not ſufficiently con- <lb/>cocted or ripe: and yet which, at
            the ſame Time, <lb/>diſcharge the thinneſt Part of the Blood, whence <lb/>the Remainder
            becomes more thick; in ſhort <lb/>which carry off the uſeful, and leave the hurtful
            <lb/>Humours behind. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 29. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>The Vomit eſpecially, being given in <lb/>an inflammatory Diſeaſe, and even without
            any <lb/>Diſtinction in all acute ones, before the Humours <lb/>have been diminiſhed by
            Bleeding, and diluted by <lb/>plentiful ſmall Drinks, is productive of the great-
            <lb/>eſt Evils; of Inflammations of the Stomach, of <lb/>the Lungs and Liver, of
            Suffocations and Fren- <lb/>zies. Purges ſometimes occaſion a general In-
            <lb/>flammation of the Guts, which <note rend="size(0.5)" type="footnote" n="*"
              place="bottom">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* It is pretty common to <hi rend="italic">hear</hi> of Perſons recovering from
                <lb/>Inflammations of the Bowels, or Guts, which our Author more <lb/>juſtly and
                ingenuouſly conſiders as general Paſſports to Death: <lb/>for it is difficult to
                conceive, that a real and <hi rend="italic">conſiderable</hi> In- <lb/>flammation of
                ſuch thin, membranous, irritable Parts, lined <lb/>with ſuch putreſcent Humours and
                Contents, and in ſo hot and <lb/>cloſe a Situation, could be reſtored to a ſound and
                healthy State <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſo often</hi> as Rumour affirms it. This makes
                it ſo important a <lb/>Point, to avert every Tendency to an Inflammation of theſe
                <lb/>feculent Parts, as to juſtify a Bleeding directed, ſolely, from <lb/>this
                Precaution, and which might have been no otherwiſe indi- <lb/>cated by a Diſeaſe,
                attended with any Symptom, that threatened <lb/>ſuch an Inflammation. But when a
                Perſon recovers, there can <lb/>be no anatomical Search for ſuch Inflammations, or
                its Effects, <lb/>the real or imaginary Cure of which may well amaze the Pa-
                <lb/>tient, and muſt greatly redound to the Honour of his Preſcri- <lb/>ber; ſo that
                there may be Policy ſometimes in giving a mode- <lb/>rate Diſeaſe a very bad Name.
                  <hi rend="italic">K.</hi>
              </p>
            </note> terminates in <lb/>Death. Some Inſtances of each of theſe terrible <pb n="60"/>
            <lb/>Conſequences have I ſeen, from blundering Te- <lb/>merity, Imprudence and
            Ignorance. The Effect <lb/>of ſuch Medicines, in theſe Circumſtances, are <lb/>much the
            ſame with thoſe we might reaſonably <lb/>expect, from the Application of Salt and Pepper
            <lb/>to a dry, inflamed and foul Tongue, in Order to <lb/>moiſten and clean it. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent">
            <lb/>§ 30. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>Every Perſon of ſound plain Senſe is <lb/>capable of perceiving the Truth of
            whatever I <lb/>have advanced in this Chapter: and there would <lb/>be ſome Degree of
            Prudence, even in thoſe who <lb/>do not perceive the real good Tendency of my
            <lb/>Advice, not to defy nor oppoſe it too hardily. <lb/>The Queſtion relates to a very
            important Ob- <lb/>ject; and in a Matter quite foreign to themſelves, <lb/>they
            undoubtedly owe ſome Deference to the <lb/>Judgment of Perſons, who have made it the
            <lb/>Study and Buſineſs of their whole Lives. It is <lb/>not to myſelf that I hope for
            their Attention, but <lb/>to the greateſt Phyſicians, whoſe feeble Inſtru- <lb/>ment and
            Eccho I am. What Intereſt have any <lb/>of us in forbidding ſick People to eat, to be
            ſtifled, <lb/>or to drink ſuch heating things as heighten their <lb/>Fever? What
            Advantage can accrue to us from <lb/>oppoſing the fatal Torrent, which ſweeps them
            <lb/>off? What Arguments can perſuade People, that <lb/>ſome thouſand Men of Genius, of
            Knowledge, <lb/>and of Experience, who paſs their Lives among <lb/>a Croud and
            Succeſſion of Patients; who are en- <lb/>tirely employed to take Care of them, and to
            ob- <lb/>ſerve all that paſſes, have been only amuſing and <lb/>deceiving themſelves, on
            the Effects of Food, of <pb n="61"/>
            <lb/>Regimen and of Remedies? Can it enter into <lb/>any ſenſible Head, that a Nurſe,
            who adviſes <lb/>Soup, an Egg, or a Biſcuit, deſerves a Patients <lb/>Confidence, better
            than a Phyſician who forbids <lb/>them? Nothing can be more diſagreeable to the
            <lb/>latter, than his being obliged to diſpute continu- <lb/>ally in Behalf of the poor
            Patients; and to be in <lb/>conſtant Terror, leſt this mortally officious At-
            <lb/>tendance, by giving ſuch Food as augments all <lb/>the Cauſes of the Diſeaſe,
            ſhould defeat the Effi- <lb/>cacy of all the Remedies he adminiſters to remove <lb/>it;
            and ſhould feſter and aggravate the Wound, <lb/>in Proportion to the Pains he takes to
            dreſs it. <lb/>The more ſuch abſurd People love a Patient, the <lb/>more they urge him
            to eat, which, in Effect, ve- <lb/>rifies the Proverb of <hi rend="italic">killing one
              with Kindneſs</hi>. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="517"/>
      <div type="chapter">
        <pb n="579"/>
        <head rend="sc align-center space">
          <lb/>CHAPTER XXXIV. </head>
        <head rend="italic hanging space">
          <lb/>Containing Queſtions abſolutely neceſſary to be an- <lb/>ſwered exactly by the
          Patient, who conſults a <lb/>Phyſician. </head>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="sc align-center space">
            <lb/>SECT. 588. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(4)">G</hi>REAT Conſideration and Experience <lb/>are neceſſary to form
            a right Judg- <lb/>ment of the State of a Patient, whom <lb/>the Phyſician has not
            perſonally ſeen; <lb/>even though he ſhould receive the beſt Infor- <lb/>mation it is
            poſſible to give him, at a Diſtance <lb/>from the Patient. But this Difficulty is
            greatly <lb/>augmented, or rather changed into an Impoſſi- <lb/>bility, when his
            Information is not exact and <lb/>ſufficient. It has frequently happened to myſelf,
            <lb/>that after having examined Peaſants who came <lb/>to get Advice for others, I did
            not venture to <lb/>preſcribe, becauſe they were not able to give me <lb/>a ſufficient
            Information, in order to my being <pb n="580"/>
            <lb/>certain of the Diſtemper. To prevent this great <lb/>Inconvenience, I ſubjoin a
            Liſt of ſuch Queſtions, <lb/>as indiſpenſably require clear and direct An- <lb/>ſwers. </p>
          <floatingText>
            <body>
              <head rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>General Queſtions. </head>
              <p rend="indent space">
                <lb/>What is the Patient's Age? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Is he generally a healthy Perſon? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>What is his general Courſe of Life? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>How long has he been ſick? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>In what Manner did his preſent Sickneſs be- <lb/>gin, or appear? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Has he any Fever? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Is his Pulſe hard or ſoft? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Has he ſtill tolerable Strength, or is he weak? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Does he keep his Bed in the Day Time, or <lb/>quit it? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Is he in the ſame Condition throughout the <lb/>whole Day? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Is he ſtill, or reſtleſs? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Is he hot, or cold? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Has he Pains in the Head, the Throat, the <lb/>Breaſt, the Stomach, the Belly,
                the Loins, or in <lb/>the Limbs, the Extremities of the Body? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Is his Tongue dry? does he complain of <lb/>Thirſt? of an ill Taſt in his
                Mouth? of Reach- <lb/>ings to vomit, or of an Averſion to Food? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Does he go to ſtool often or ſeldom? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>What Appearance have his Stools, and what <lb/>is their uſual Quantity? </p>
              <pb n="581"/>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Does he make much Urine? What Appear- <lb/>ance has his Urine, as to Colour and
                Contents? <lb/>Are they generally much alike, or do they <lb/>change often? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Does he ſweat? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Does he expectorate, or cough up? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Does he get Sleep? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Does he draw his Breath eaſily? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>What Regimen does he obſerve in his Sick- <lb/>neſs? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>What Medicines has he taken? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>What Effects have they produced? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Has he never had the ſame Diſtemper before? </p>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent space">
            <lb/>§ 589. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>The Diſeaſes of Women and Children <lb/>are attended with peculiar Circumſtances;
            ſo <lb/>that when Advice is aſked for them, Anſwers <lb/>muſt be given, not only to the
            preceding Queſ- <lb/>tions, which relate to ſick Perſons in general; <lb/>but alſo to
            the following, which regard theſe <lb/>particularly. </p>
          <floatingText>
            <body>
              <head rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>Queſtions with Reſpect to Women. </head>
              <p rend="indent space">
                <lb/>Have they arrived at their monthly Diſcharges, <lb/>and are theſe regular? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Are they pregnant? If ſo, how long ſince? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Are they in Child-bed? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Has their Delivery been happily accompliſhed? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Has the Mother cleanſed ſufficiently? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Has her Milk come in due Time and Quan- <lb/>tity? </p>
              <pb n="582"/>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Does ſhe ſuckle the Infant herſelf? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Is ſhe ſubject to the Whites? </p>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
          <floatingText>
            <body>
              <head rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>Queſtions relating to Children. </head>
              <p rend="indent space">
                <lb/>What is the Child's exact Age? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>How many Teeth has he cut? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Does he cut them painfully? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Is he any-wiſe ricketty, or ſubject to Knots or <lb/>Kernels? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Has he had the Small Pocks? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Does the Child void Worms, upwards or <lb/>downwards? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Is his Belly large, ſwelled, or hard? </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Is his Sleep quiet, or otherwiſe? </p>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="indent space">
            <lb/>§ 590. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>Beſides theſe general Queſtions, com- <lb/>mon in all the Diſeaſes of the different
            Sexes and <lb/>Ages, the Perſon conſulting muſt alſo anſwer to <lb/>thoſe, which have a
            cloſe and direct Relation to <lb/>the Diſeaſe, at that very Time affecting the
            <lb/>Sick. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>For Example, in the Quinſey, the Condition <lb/>of the Throat muſt be exactly
            inquired into. In <lb/>Diſeaſes of the Breaſt, an Account muſt be given <lb/>of the
            Patient's Pains; of his Cough; of the Op- <lb/>preſſion, and of his Breathing, and
            Expectora- <lb/>tion. I ſhall not enter upon a more particular <lb/>Detail; common Senſe
            will ſufficiently extend <lb/>this Plan or Specimen to other Diſeaſes; and <lb/>though
            theſe Queſtions may ſeem numerous, it <lb/>will always be eaſy to write down their
            Anſwers <pb n="583"/>
            <lb/>in as little Room, as the Queſtions take up here. <lb/>It were even to be wiſhed
            that Perſons of every <lb/>Rank, who occaſionally write for medical Ad- <lb/>vice and
            Directions, would obſerve ſuch a Plan <lb/>or Succeſſion, in the Body of their Letters.
            By <lb/>this Means they would frequently procure the <lb/>moſt ſatisfactory Anſwers; and
            ſave themſelves <lb/>the Trouble of writing ſecond Letters, to give a <lb/>neceſſary
            Explanation of the firſt. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The Succeſs of Remedies depends, in a very <lb/>great Meaſure, on a very exact
            Knowledge of <lb/>the Diſeaſe; and that Knowledge on the pre- <lb/>ciſe Information of
            it, which is laid before the <lb/>Phyſician. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="8"> </space>
      <trailer rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
