<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Fordyce: Elements of the practice of physic</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>George Fordyce</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Elements of the practice of physic. Part the first. Containing the
              natural history of the human body. By George Fordyce, M.D. Of the Royal College of
              Physicians, and Reader on the Practice of Physic in London.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">N1363</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N1363"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for Johnson and Payne, (at No. 8.) in Pater-Noster Row,
                  MDCCLXX.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1770</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="2"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="64"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">Countway Library of Medicine</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3307163639</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K000841.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="General treatises"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <p rend="align-center">
          <lb/>THIS ESSAY <lb/>ON THE ART OF HEALING, <lb/>IN TESTIMONY OF THE AUTHOR'S
          <lb/>GRATITUDE, IS WITH THE GREATEST RESPECT, <lb/>INSCRIBED <lb/>TO HIS GRACE <lb/> HUGH
          DUKE OF NORTHUMBERLAND, <lb/>A LOVER AND A PROMOTER <lb/>OF USEFUL ARTS, BY HIS GRACE'S
          <lb/>MOST OBEDIENT SERVANT, <lb/>GEORGE FORDYCE. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_3"/>
      <head rend="sc align-center space">
        <lb/>THE <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">NATURAL HISTORY </hi>
        <lb/>of the <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">HUMAN BODY. </hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Diſeaſe is ſuch an alteration of the chemical <lb/>properties
        of the fluids or ſolids, or of their <lb/>organization; or of the action of the moving
        power; <lb/>as produces an inability or difficulty of performing <lb/>the functions of the
        whole, or any part of the ſyſtem, <lb/>or pain, or a preternatural evacuation. </p>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
          <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Chemical Properties</hi> of the <lb/>FLUIDS. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE fluids may be divided into <list>
            <item rend="indent space">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">1ſt</hi>, The blood. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">2dly</hi>, Thoſe formed during digeſtion, before the <lb/>food
              is converted into blood. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">3dly</hi>, The ſecreted fluids. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The blood conſiſts of <list>
            <item rend="indent space">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">1ſt</hi>, The ſerum. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">2dly</hi>, The coagulable lymph. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">3dly</hi>, The red part. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">4thly</hi>, The ſuperfluous water. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">5thly</hi>, Extraneous ſubſtances introduced. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_4" n="2"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The ſerum, coagulable lymph, and ſuperfluous wa- <lb/>ter, are diffuſed through one
          another; and the red <lb/>part is mechanically mixed with them. Some of the
          <lb/>extraneous ſubſtances are alſo mechanically mixed <lb/>with them, and ſome diffuſed
          through them. </p>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/><hi rend="sc">Properties</hi> of the <hi rend="sc">Serum</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>T is fluid in any degree of heat between 30 and <lb/>160 of
            Fahrenheit's thermometer. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In a leſſer heat it freezes, in a greater it coagu- <lb/>lates. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Coagulation is a ſeparation of an animal or vege- <lb/>table matter from the water
            in which it was diſſolved; <lb/>and is at the ſame time a change of the properties of
            <lb/>that matter, rendering it inſoluble in water again by <lb/>commixture alone. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The ſerum conſiſts chemically of a coagulable mat- <lb/>ter, and water in which
            common ſal ammoniac and <lb/>phoſphoric ammoniac, and generally common ſalt, <lb/>and
            frequently ſelenites, and fixed ammoniac, are diſ- <lb/>ſolved; but it is a queſtion,
            whether the water che- <lb/>mically combined in the ſerum is alſo united with <lb/>thoſe
            neutral ſalts, or whether the ſerum, and the <lb/>ſolution of theſe, are only diffuſed
            through one <lb/>another. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is probably in itſelf colourleſs, and inodorous; <lb/>but it receives a
            yellowiſh or browniſh hue from the <lb/>putreſcent part of the blood, and acquires a
            ſmell <lb/>from the eſſential oil. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If it contained no neutral ſalts, it would be inſipid, <lb/>and incapable of
            ſtimulating. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_5" n="3"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The ſuperfluous water may be ſeparated from it <lb/>by filtration in the body, but
            that which is chemi- <lb/>cally combined with the other parts cannot. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>All the water may be evaporated from it by a leſſer <lb/>heat than 140 degrees of
            Fahrenheit's thermometer, <lb/>if it be expoſed to the air. The other parts remain
            <lb/>after this operation ſolid, and ſoluble again in water <lb/>by commixture alone. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The ſeparation or addition of ſuperfluous water <lb/>does not affect its viſcidity,
            ſo far as that is of any <lb/>conſequence in the circulation; but the ſeparation of
            <lb/>that water which is in chemical combination, may <lb/>render it more viſcid. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The water in chemical combination is never ſe- <lb/>parated, while the ſerum is
            contained in the blood- <lb/>veſſels; and of conſequence this part of the blood <lb/>is
            always equally viſcid, ſo far as its viſcidity can <lb/>affect the circulation or
            ſecretions. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It may be coagulated by acids, oils, alcohol, &amp;c. <lb/>but no ſubſtance can get
            into the blood-veſſels in a <lb/>ſufficient degree of concentration to coagulate it, ex-
            <lb/>cepting by injection. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It may be coagulated by a juice ſecreted in the <lb/>ſtomach. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It has ſeldom, if ever, been found coagulated in <lb/>the body. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The only perceptible difference which has ap- <lb/>peared in the coagulable part of
            the ſerum, from any <lb/>obſervation hitherto made public, is, that ſometimes <lb/>in
            coagulating its parts adhere more or leſs firmly, <lb/>and that ſometimes it is of a
            deeper or lighter brown <lb/>colour. </p>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_6" n="4"/>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/><hi rend="sc">Properties</hi> of the <hi rend="sc">Coagulable <lb/>Lymph</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="sc"><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>T</hi> is a compound of water and a coagulable
            <lb/>matter. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>As long as it continues in the courſe of circulation, <lb/>it is fluid in any
            degree of heat between 30 and 120 <lb/>degrees of Fahrenheit's thermometer. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When it is taken out of the blood-veſſels, it coagu- <lb/>lates; whether it be in
            motion or at reſt, expoſed to <lb/>the air or not, or in the heat of the human body, or
            <lb/>in any other degree of heat. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If it be retained in a blood-veſſel, it continues fluid <lb/>for more than three
            hours in any degree of heat be- <lb/>tween 30 and 120 of Fahrenheit's thermometer, and
            <lb/>that whether it be in motion or at reſt. The ſmaller <lb/>the blood-veſſel, the
            longer it continues fluid. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It has hardly ever been found coagulated in the <lb/>blood-veſſels of a living
            animal, unleſs they have <lb/>been enlarged into aneuriſms or varices. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It has generally been found coagulated in the large <lb/>veſſels of the human body
            on diſſection, and ſome- <lb/>times ſeparated from the other parts; but to all ap-
            <lb/>pearance theſe coagulations have almoſt always taken <lb/>place after death. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When it is taken out of the blood-veſſels, it may <lb/>be prevented from
            coagulating, by ſaturating the <lb/>whole blood with common, ſea-ſalt, and perhaps by
            <lb/>ſome of the other neutral ſalts. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Although the coagulable part of the ſerum and <lb/>coagulable lymph have different
            properties, the co- <lb/>agulum formed from both is pretty nearly the ſame. <pb
              xml:id="page_7" n="5"/>
            <lb/>The coagulum may be diſſolved in water by boiling <lb/>or putrefaction; and may be
            united with concen- <lb/>trated acids, with cauſtic alkalis, and calcarious earth,
            <lb/>and with ſome metallic ſalts, into a ſubſtance ſoluble <lb/>in water: but none of
            theſe can get into the ſyſtem <lb/>by abſorption, ſo as to produce this effect. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Both the ſuperfluous water and ſerum are capable <lb/>of being ſeparated from the
            coagulable lymph, by fil- <lb/>tration in the body. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When the blood is received into a proper veſſel, <lb/>the coagulation of this part
            gives an appearance of <lb/>ſolidity to the whole: but ſoon after the whole be-
            <lb/>comes thus apparently ſolid, part of the ſerum, of the <lb/>ſuperfluous water, and
            of the water which was com- <lb/>bined with the coagulable lymph, ouzes out from the
            <lb/>whole maſs, and brings along with it part of any <lb/>extraneous fluid that may be
            contained in the blood- <lb/>veſſels; leaving behind what is commonly called the
            <lb/>red globules, the coagulum of the coagulable lymph, <lb/>and any ſolid particles
            that may have been in the <lb/>blood. This is called the ſpontaneous ſeparation. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When the arteries are acting ſtrongly, whether <lb/>the whole habit be ſtrong or
            not, the coagulable <lb/>lymph is more fluid, and longer in coagulating. Of
            <lb/>conſequence it lets the red particles, which are the <lb/>heavieſt part of the
            blood, fall down towards the bot- <lb/>tom, before it coagulates: and upon the
            ſpontaneous <lb/>ſeparation, the coagulum is divided into two parts; <lb/>the upper,
            conſiſting of the coagulum of the co- <lb/>agulable lymph alone (which has in this caſe
            been <lb/>called the buff); the under, conſiſting partly of this, <lb/>and partly of the
            red particles. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Although part of the coagulable lymph would <lb/>ſeparate from the red particles,
            may be prevented by <lb/>taking the blood from a ſmall veſſel, or from a ſmall <pb
              xml:id="page_8" n="6"/>
            <lb/>orifice, or by letting it run along the ſkin before it falls <lb/>into the veſſel
            into which it is received, or by re- <lb/>ceiving it into a veſſel whoſe ſurface is
            large in pro- <lb/>portion to its contents; as in all theſe caſes the co- <lb/>agulation
            is forwarded. On the other hand, if it <lb/>ſtagnate in the blood-veſſel for ſome time
            before it is <lb/>taken out, there will be a ſeparation, when none <lb/>would otherwiſe
            have happened. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Whether the coagulable lymph ſeparates in part <lb/>from the red particles, or not,
            it coagulates ſometimes <lb/>into a firmer, ſometimes into a looſer maſs, generally
            <lb/>in proportion to the ſtrength of the ſyſtem. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>All the ſubſtances which coagulate the ſerum, have <lb/>the ſame effect on the
            coagulable lymph; but none <lb/>can be applied to it in the blood-veſſels, excepting by
            <lb/>injection in a ſufficient degree of concentration to <lb/>coagulate it. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The coagulable lymph is probably in itſelf colour- <lb/>leſs, inſipid, inodorous,
            and incapable of ſtimulating. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Whilſt it remains in the blood-veſſels, it is che- <lb/>mically combined with a
            certain proportion of water, <lb/>from which it cannot be ſeparated but by coagulation;
            <lb/>neither will it combine with a larger proportion. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Water mechanically mixed with it has no effect on <lb/>its viſcidity, ſo far as
            that affects the circulation <lb/>or ſecretions. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>No other differences beſides thoſe already taken <lb/>notice of are obſervable in
            its properties. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The coagulable lymph and ſerum are both capable <lb/>of putrefaction, and are
            converted by it into a muci- <lb/>laginous matter, not coagulable by any of the methods
            <lb/>recited above. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If this mucilaginous matter ſhould undergo a fur- <lb/>ther putrefaction, it emits
            a fœtid vapour, and is con- <lb/>verted into ſaline ſubſtances and calcarious earth.
          </p>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_9" n="7"/>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/><hi rend="sc">Properties</hi> of the <hi rend="sc">Red Part</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">U</hi>PON viewing this part of the blood with a deep
            <lb/>magnifier in the ſolar microſcope, as it circulates <lb/>in the blood-veſſels of a
            living animal, it appears to <lb/>be divided into a number of ſmall particles, which are
            <lb/>apparently annular, and exceedingly flexible. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>While the animal is reſpiring, and the blood cir- <lb/>culating, it is of a ſcarlet
            colour in the arteries, and <lb/>of a Modena red in the veins; but if the reſpiration
            <lb/>be ſtopped, that blood which circulates afterwards <lb/>through the lungs continues
            of a Modena red. If it <lb/>be taken out of the veins, kept moiſt, and expoſed to
            <lb/>reſpirable air, it becomes of a ſcarlet colour; if it be <lb/>taken out of the
            arteries, and covered from the air, <lb/>or if it ſtagnate in them, its colour is
            changed to a <lb/>Modena red. A light ſhade of Modena red is not <lb/>ſcarlet, neither
            is a deep ſcarlet a Modena red. Va- <lb/>rious other ſubſtances alter the colour of this
            part. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It ſeems to have a ſweetiſh taſle, to be inodorous, <lb/>and void of ſtimulus. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Its ſpecific gravity is but a very little more than <lb/>the ſerum or coagulable
            lymph. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is more inflammable than the other parts; and, <lb/>on performing its chemical
            analyſis, it yields a large <lb/>proportion of empyreumatic oil. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is readily ſoluble in water, but not in the <lb/>ſerum. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is not ſoluble in a ſaturated ſolution of neutral <lb/>ſalts. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_10" n="8"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is capable of undergoing the putrefactive fer- <lb/>mentation, the firſt ſtage
            of which breaks it down <lb/>into ſmaller particles, and renders it of a dark colour.
            <lb/>It afterwards is converted into a mucilage, and be- <lb/>comes ſoluble in the
            ſerum. </p>
        </div>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Superfluous Water</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>T is diffuſed through the ſerum and coagulable <lb/>lymph. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It contains a part, perhaps the whole, of the ſalts. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Theſe ſalts are chemically combined with a part <lb/>of it only, and this ſolution
            is diffuſed through the <lb/>remaining part. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The water diffuſed may be ſeparated from the ſo- <lb/>lution by filtration in the
            body. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The ſolid part of the blood, left after evaporation <lb/>of the water by a heat
            leſs than that of boiling water, <lb/>amounts to from one fourth to one fifth of the
            whole. </p>
        </div>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/><hi rend="sc">Extraneous Substances</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Great variety of extraneous ſubſtances, both fluid <lb/>and
            ſolid, may be introduced into the blood- <lb/>veſſels by abſorption; but none of them in
            ſuch pro- <lb/>portion as to produce any alteration in the blood, ex- <lb/>cept by
            fermentation. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When any ferment is introduced into the blood- <lb/>veſſels, it acts upon a part of
            the blood only; the <lb/>greateſt part remaining to all experiment exactly the <lb/>ſame
            as before. </p>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_11" n="9"/>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/>Of the <hi rend="sc">Putrefaction</hi> of the <lb/><hi rend="sc">Blood</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">F</hi>Ermentation is the converſion of one compound <lb/>into
            another, by a new arrangement or manner <lb/>of combination of its elements. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>What is commonly called putrefaction conſiſts of <lb/>two fermentations, which we
            ſhall call by the names <lb/>of the firſt and ſecond ſtage. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>All animal ſolid and fluids may be reduced by the <lb/>firſt into a mucilaginous
            maſs, ſoluble in water, and <lb/>diffuſible through any quantity of it. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The red part of the blood firſt breaks down into <lb/>ſmaller particles, before it
            is formed into a perfect <lb/>mucilage. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The firſt ſtage takes place without any effer- <lb/>veſcence. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The ſecond ſtage converts this mucilage into earths, <lb/>and ſalts, a fœtid
            vapour, and fixable air. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The firſt and ſecond ſtage of putrefaction take <lb/>place in a ſmall part of the
            blood, or it is deſtroyed <lb/>by ſome other operation; for </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>After having coagulated the ſerum, if we ſqueeze <lb/>out the water, and evaporate
            it, there is left a mu- <lb/>cilaginous matter ſimilar to that formed by putre-
            <lb/>faction. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The ſalts formed in the blood-veſſels, excepting <lb/>phoſphoric ammoniac, may be
            formed by the laſt <lb/>ſtage of putrefaction; and thoſe formed by the laſt <lb/>ſtage
            are found in the blood-veſſels, excepting nitrous <lb/>ſelenites, and nitrous ammoniac. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_12" n="10"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This mucilage, and theſe ſalts, are always carrying <lb/>off by urine; the preſent
            blood is always diminiſhing, <lb/>and the veſſels require a freſh ſupply from the food. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The blood is always in the moſt powerful cir- <lb/>cumſtances of putrefaction;
            which are, a heat of 98 <lb/>degrees of Fahrenheit's thermometer, fluidity, a mo-
            <lb/>derate expoſure to air, and motion: but it is pre- <lb/>vented from putrifying by
            the action of the veſſels; <lb/>nor can any ferment or other circumſtance induce the
            <lb/>fermentation, till this action is altered, except per- <lb/>haps the introduction
            of chyle intermixed with putrid <lb/>matter. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In diſeaſes, the firſt ſtage often takes place in part <lb/>of the blood; the
            ſecond ſtage ſometimes, although <lb/>ſeldom. </p>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_13" n="11"/>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/>Of <hi rend="sc">Digestion</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">D</hi>IGESTION is the converſion of the food into <lb/>chyle, and
            afterwards into blood. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The food may conſiſt of farinaceous or muci- <lb/>laginous vegetable ſubſtances, or
            native vegetable acid, <lb/>or ſugar, or expreſſed oil, or animal ſolids, or animal
            <lb/>fluids containing a mucilaginous matter. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Theſe ſubſtances may be digeſted, if they be taken <lb/>ſingly, or if they be mixed
            together. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The blood formed does not differ ſenſibly in its <lb/>properties, whether the one
            or the other of them be <lb/>uſed ſingly, or ſeveral of them together; provided <lb/>the
            organs of digeſtion be ſufficiently powerful <lb/>convert them into blood. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If the food be ſolid, it is generally broke down by <lb/>the teeth, or by ſome
            other apparatus. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>But maſhing it down with water is not ſufficient <lb/>to alter its chemical
            properties, and convert it into <lb/>chyle and blood. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is mixed in the ſtomach with the watery fluids <lb/>we drink, and with the
            mucilaginous watery fluids <lb/>ſecreted by the ſalivary and other glands. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is ſometimes diſſolved in water before it is uſed: <lb/>but it is often rendered
            ſolid by a previous prepa- <lb/>ration, or coagulated by a ſubſtance ſecreted in the
            <lb/>ſtomach. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Simple ſolution in water does not convert it into <lb/>chyle or blood. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If it be previouſly diſſolved in water, it affords leſs <lb/>nouriſhment than if
            exhibited ſolid. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_14" n="12"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is neceſſary that it remain in the ſtomach for <lb/>ſome time, in order to its
            digeſtion. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The only proceſs it can go through in the organs <lb/>of digeſtion, that is capable
            of altering its chemical <lb/>properties, is fermentation. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Its fermentation is not attended with efferveſcence <lb/>in a healthy ſtomach. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If vegetable food be uſed, an acid is produced. <lb/>This acid is deſtroyed in the
            duodenum by the bile. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If animal food be uſed alone, no acid is produced. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The ſtronger the ſtomach, and the more perfect the <lb/>digeſtion, the leſs acid is
            formed from vegetable food. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>No ſtage of the putrefactive fermentation takes <lb/>place, during the converſion
            of it into chyle and <lb/>blood, if the digeſtion be perfect. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The fermentation which takes place is peculiar to <lb/>the organs of digeſtion, and
            has never been produced <lb/>by any artificial means yet attempted. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The fermentation which takes place in the ſtomach, <lb/>forwards the ſolution of
            ſolid food in the watery <lb/>menſtruums. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Solid foods diſſolve ſooner in the ſtomach than they <lb/>can be diſſolved in water
            in the ſame heat, by any <lb/>means hitherto found out. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If the ſtomach does not act properly, ſolid food <lb/>remains undiſſolved;
            vegetable, and mixtures of ve- <lb/>getable, and animal ſubſtances become more acid;
            <lb/>animal ſubſtances putrify; a quantity of air is ſepa- <lb/>rated; and the food is
            not digeſted and converted <lb/>into chyle. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Only that part of the food which is digeſted affords <lb/>nouriſhment; the
            nouriſhment therefore is in pro- <lb/>portion to the food and the digeſtion. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When food, either from its quantity or quality, <lb/>cannot be digeſted, it is apt
            to occaſion great diſ- <pb xml:id="page_15" n="13"/>
            <lb/>turbances in the ſyſtem, while it is contained in the <lb/>ſtomach and inteſtines. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The only ſenſible alterations produced in the blood <lb/>by different foods, are in
            its quantity; or in the pro- <lb/>portion of ſuperfluous water; or that ſometimes a
            <lb/>long uſe of animal food brings on a degree of pu- <lb/>trefaction. </p>
        </div>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/>Of the <hi rend="sc">Chyle</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE chyle is formed from the food in the in- <lb/>teſtines,
            and abſorbed by the lacteals. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The whole fluid abſorbed is not chyle, but a mix- <lb/>ture of chyle, and the
            ſolution of thoſe ſubſtances, <lb/>which were ſimply diſſolved in water without being
            <lb/>digeſted. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Quere</hi>, Whether a ſimple ſolution of mucilaginous,
            <lb/>animal, or vegetable ſubſtances, can be converted <lb/>into blood, without being
            formed into chyle in the <lb/>ſtomach and inteſtines? </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Chyle is fluid, while in the lacteals; when expoſed <lb/>to the air, it coagulates;
            it is rendered white, from <lb/>a mixture of expreſſed oil. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When coagulated, a fluid may be ſqueezed out, <lb/>which probably contains a
            coagulable matter, and <lb/>ſugar. </p>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_16" n="14"/>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Secreted Fluids</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HEY either </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Exiſt in the blood-veſſels, being mechanically <lb/>mixed with the other fluids,
            and require only a me- <lb/>chanical ſeparation; </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Or they do not exiſt in the blood-veſſels, their <lb/>elements only being contained
            there: but theſe ele- <lb/>ments are not combined, ſo as actually to form the
            <lb/>ſecreted fluid. It is therefore requiſite, that ſome <lb/>chemical operation ſhould
            take place in the ſecretory <lb/>organ, by which the elements ſhall be combined ſo as
            <lb/>to form the matter ſecreted. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The chemical operation by which they are formed, <lb/>is fermentation. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The fluids ſeparated mechanically, are <list rend="space">
              <item rend="indent">
                <lb/>The matter of the inſenſible perſpiration. </item>
              <item rend="indent">
                <lb/>The urine. </item>
              <item rend="indent">
                <lb/>The ſweat. </item>
              <item rend="indent">
                <lb/>The milk. </item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The fluids formed in the ſecretory organ by a che- <lb/>mical operation, are <list
              rend="space">
              <item rend="indent">
                <lb/>The mucus. </item>
              <item rend="indent">
                <lb/>The ſaliva. </item>
              <item rend="indent">
                <lb/>The pancreatic juice. </item>
              <item rend="indent">
                <lb/>The ſemen. </item>
              <item rend="indent">
                <lb/>The bile. </item>
              <item rend="indent">
                <lb/>The wax in the ear. </item>
              <item rend="indent">
                <lb/>The ſebaceous matter. </item>
              <item rend="indent">
                <lb/>The coagulating matter of the ſtomach, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
              </item>
            </list>
          </p>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_17" n="15"/>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Matter</hi> of the <hi rend="sc">Insensible Perspiration</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>T is ſeparated from the ſurface of the lungs, and <lb/>from
            the ſkin, by evaporation. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The quantity evaporated depends upon the quan- <lb/>tity of ſuperfluous water in
            the blood-veſſels, the heat <lb/>of the air, the quantity of air applied, and the con-
            <lb/>traction or relaxation of the veſſels from whence the <lb/>evaporation takes place. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When the body is in its natural ſtate, that part of <lb/>the inſenſible
            perſpiration, which is capable of con- <lb/>denſation, conſiſts of water, with a very
            ſmall pro- <lb/>portion of a mucilaginous matter and eſſential oil, <lb/>and ſometimes
            perhaps volatile alkali. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>There is no reaſon to ſuppoſe, that any matter flies <lb/>off that cannot be
            condenſed, from any experiment <lb/>hitherto made; but it is rather probable that there
            <lb/>is not. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Should any other ſubſtance, capable of emitting <lb/>vapour in the heat of the
            human body, get into the <lb/>blood-veſſels, or be formed on the ſurface of the ſkin,
            <lb/>lungs, or in any of the paſſages of the air in breathing, <lb/>it may be mixed with
            the inſenſible perſpiration. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Some of theſe ſubſtances may be putrid vapour, va- <lb/>riolous, morbillous, and
            other infectious matters, alco- <lb/>hol, and other extraneous volatile ſubſtances,
            &amp;c. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The matters thrown off by inſenſible perſpiration, <lb/>may be evacuated by the
            other excretions. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The health is not in proportion to the quantity of <lb/>inſenſible perſpiration.
          </p>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_18" n="16"/>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Urine</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE urine, in the common ſtate of the body, is <lb/>a
            tranſparent browniſh fluid, which upon cool- <lb/>ing has a mucilaginous matter
            ſeparated, capable of <lb/>being rediſſolved in heat. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In health, the ſeparating mucilage is generally in <lb/>ſuch quantity as to remain
            ſuſpended in the urine <lb/>after its ſeparation, forming what has been called <lb/>the
            cloud. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is ſometimes totally abſent in health, but much <lb/>more frequently in
            diſeaſes; ſometimes it is in quan- <lb/>tity ſufficiently to carry the cloud to the
            bottom, and <lb/>form a mucous ſediment; and ſometimes it falls down <lb/>in a flaky
            powder, and forms what has been called <lb/>a lateritious ſediment, which is commonly of
            a brick <lb/>colour, and now and then white. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This laſt appearance often takes place on the going <lb/>off of acute diſeaſes; but
            it alſo happens in health, <lb/>and while diſeaſes ſubſiſt in their full force, parti-
            <lb/>cularly when they affect the urinary paſſages, or parts <lb/>near them. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Sometimes the ſeparating mucilage is ſeparated in <lb/>a powder, remains ſuſpended
            in the urine, and renders <lb/>it turbid. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>After the ſeparating mucilage is ſeparated, if the <lb/>urine be filtrated from it,
            it is tranſparent, conſiſting <lb/>of water which contains a mucilage, and ſalts. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="1">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">1ſt</hi>, A mucilage, ſimilar to that formed by the firſt
            <lb/>ſtage of putrefaction. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This mucilage is of a browniſh colour, and gives <lb/>the greateſt part of the
            colour to the urine. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_19" n="17"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Its quantity varies conſiderably; but the proportion <lb/>of it in the urine is
            always ſmall. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If the water be evaporated from it, it will rediſſolve, <lb/>and it may be diffuſed
            through any quantity of water <lb/>in any heat. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is not coagulable. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="2">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">2dly</hi>, The ſalts are common ſalt, common ſal am- <lb/>moniac,
            phoſphoric ammoniac, vitriolic ſelenites, and <lb/>muriatic ſelenites. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Common ſalt is contained in the urine, in conſe- <lb/>quence of its being uſed in
            the food, or drink; and <lb/>it is in proportion to the quantity uſed. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The other ſalts are contained in the urine indepen- <lb/>dent of any ſaline
            ſubſtance taken into the body, <lb/>except perhaps the vitriolic ſelenites. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The quantity of ſelenitic ſalts is commonly very <lb/>ſmall; but ſometimes the
            urine is ſaturated with vi- <lb/>triolic ſelenites, which ſeparates, and chryſtalizes,
            <lb/>upon the urine's ſtanding to cool. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The proportion of the ſalts varies conſiderably, <lb/>but is always ſo ſmall as to
            form a diluted ſolution. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The ſolution is generally ſufficiently concentrated, <lb/>to ſtimulate a very
            irritable part, but not always. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The dilution depends on the quantity of ſuper- <lb/>fluous water in the
            blood-veſſels, and on the quantity <lb/>of that ſuperfluous water evacuated by the
            kidneys: <lb/>ſo that, when the quantity ſecreted is large, the ſo- <lb/>lution is
            generally diluted; when ſmall, more con- <lb/>centrated. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Watery fluids may paſs through the blood-veſſels, <lb/>and by the kidneys, hardly
            carrying off any thing <lb/>with them, eſpecially if large quantities be drank at <lb/>a
            time, and the external veſſels be contracted. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_20" n="18"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Sometimes a quantity of calcareous earth is found <lb/>in the urine, ſuſpended by
            mechanical mixture, or at <lb/>leaſt not combined with an acid. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Any extraneous ſubſtance, ſoluble in water, that <lb/>may get into the
            blood-veſſels, may be evacuated <lb/>along with the urine; ſuch as acids, alkalies,
            neutral <lb/>and other ſaline ſubſtances; infuſion of rhubarb, and <lb/>other
            mucilaginous vegetable juices; bile, pus, and <lb/>other fluids formed in the body. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If the kidneys are relaxed, or ſtimulated; chyle, <lb/>ſerum, coagulable lymph, and
            even the red part of <lb/>the blood may be thrown out. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The red part may alſo be broke down by putre- <lb/>faction, and paſs off by the
            kidneys, of a very dark <lb/>colour, diſturbing the tranſparency, and ſometimes
            <lb/>forming a ſediment. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If the heart and arteries act more ſtrongly, or fre- <lb/>quently, than they do in
            their natural ſtate, a quan- <lb/>tity of expreſſed oil comes away with the urine, and
            <lb/>forms a film on the ſurface, or a ring round the veſſel <lb/>into which it is
            received. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The urine always contains a portion of the eſſential <lb/>oil of the urinary
            paſſages, and ſometimes a portion <lb/>of their mucus. </p>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_21" n="19"/>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Sweat</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>S far as we are capable of judging from the ſmall
            <lb/>quantity that can be collected, it contains nearly <lb/>the ſame ſubſtances as the
            urine; only that inſtead of <lb/>the eſſential oil of the urinary paſſages, it is mixed
            <lb/>with the ſebacious matter of the ſkin, which gives it <lb/>a degree of whiteneſs,
            and a ſmell different from that <lb/>of the urine. </p>
        </div>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Milk</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>T is ſecreted naturally in the breaſts of women <lb/>for the
            nouriſhment of their young, ſometimes <lb/>during pregnancy, and always after
            child-birth. <lb/>There are ſaid to have been inſtances of its being <lb/>ſecreted at
            other times, and from other parts of the <lb/>body. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is a whitiſh fluid, which ſeparates into two parts <lb/>upon being left at reſt
            in a moderate degree of heat: <lb/>The upper part conſiſts principally of expreſſed oil,
            <lb/>with a mixture of the other part, and is whiter and <lb/>more opaque. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The under part conſiſts of a ſolution of coagulable <lb/>matter and ſugar, in
            water; with a ſmall mixture <lb/>of expreſſed oil, and is called the ſkim-milk. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The expreſſed oil is fluid in the heat of the human <lb/>body, but ſolid in the
            heat of the atmoſphere. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_22" n="20"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is only mechanically mixed with the other part. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is tinged with, and receives a flavour from, the <lb/>eſſential oil of the food
            and of the body. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is found not only in different proportions in the <lb/>milk of different women,
            but alſo in the milk of the <lb/>ſame woman at different times, and even in that
            <lb/>which iſſues from the different excretory ducts of the <lb/>glands of the ſame
            breaſt. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The coagulable matter only differs from the coagu- <lb/>lable matter of the ſerum,
            in its coagulability, and <lb/>its proportion to the water. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is not coagulable by a leſs heat than that of <lb/>boiling water, and by that
            only, if the water be eva- <lb/>porated from it. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It may be coagulated by acids, alcohol, ſeveral <lb/>metallic and aluminous ſalts,
            and vegetable juices; <lb/>but it requires that they ſhould be applied to it in a
            <lb/>greater degree of concentration than the ſerum does, <lb/>in order to its
            coagulation. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Heat aſſiſts the coagulating power of theſe ſub- <lb/>ſtances. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is readily coagulable by the coagulating juices <lb/>of the ſtomach, and
            coagulates in the ſtomach of a <lb/>living animal, whether any acid be contained in it
            or <lb/>not. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The ſugar contained in the milk does not differ in <lb/>its properties from that of
            the ſugar-cane. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Its proportion is always ſmall. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When a woman makes uſe of vegetable food, it <lb/>ſeems to be in greater proportion
            than when ſhe uſes <lb/>animal. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The milk of a bitch, uſing animal food alone, con- <lb/>tains ſugar. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_23" n="21"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If milk be kept for ſome time expoſed to the air, <lb/>and in the heat of the
            atmoſphere, or of the human <lb/>body, the ſugar ferments, and is converted into vine-
            <lb/>gar, which coagulates the coagulable matter. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The ſame change may take place in the breaſt, if <lb/>it ſtagnate there for ſome
            time, or if the woman be <lb/>ſuddenly affected with any of the paſſions of the
            <lb/>mind that are attended with anxiety. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If blood be taken from the arm after a full meal, <lb/>the ſerum is often mixed
            with a ſubſtance which gives <lb/>it a degree of whiteneſs and opacity. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The milk is ſecreted after a full meal in larger pro- <lb/>portion, than after a
            woman has faſted for ſome time. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In the latter caſe, the proportion of the expreſſed <lb/>oil, coagulable matter,
            and ſugar, likewiſe dimi- <lb/>niſhes, and the milk contains beſides theſe the neutral
            <lb/>ſalts of the blood, and acquires a bitterneſs from the <lb/>ſebacious matter of the
            glands of the nipples. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In ſome women the milk always contains the ſalts <lb/>of the blood, or the
            ſebacious matter of the nipples. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The ſebacious matter not only gives it a bitter <lb/>taſte, but alſo, ſometimes, a
            yellowiſh colour and a <lb/>thicker appearance. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The milk may contain any ſubſtance which is <lb/>thrown into the ſtomach, and
            ſimply diſſolved in <lb/>water, without going through the digeſtive fermenta-
            <lb/>tions, and being converted into chyle. </p>
        </div>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Mucus</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>T covers the ſurfaces of the membranes that are ex-
            <lb/>poſed to any extraneous matter, ſuch as the ſkin <lb/>and internal membrane of the
            mouth, noſe, lungs, <lb/>æſophagus, ſtomach, inteſtines, urinary paſſages, &amp;c. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_24" n="22"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is a fluid of an adheſive viſcidity approaching to <lb/>a ſolid, and of greater
            viſcidity in one part than in <lb/>another. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is a compound of a coagulable matter and <lb/>water. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is more or leſs viſcid, according to the quantity <lb/>of water with which it is
            combined. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is of different degrees of viſcidity in different <lb/>parts of the body. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It will not combine with more water than what is <lb/>already contained in it;
            neither can its viſcidity be <lb/>altered by digeſting it with water, unleſs it begin to
            <lb/>putrify; nor can the more viſcid mucus of one part <lb/>be converted into the leſs
            viſcid of another. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If the water be evaporated from it by a gentle heat, <lb/>the coagulable matter
            remains ſolid: if this be im- <lb/>merſed in water, it will abſorb that quantity which
            <lb/>evaporated from it, but no more, and it will regain <lb/>its former fluidity and
            viſcidity. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It, for the moſt part, contains either no neutral <lb/>ſalts, or ſo ſmall a
            proportion as cannot eaſily be ren- <lb/>dered ſenſible to experiment. It is colourleſs,
            inſipid, <lb/>inodorous, and incapable of ſtimulating. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It combines with concentrated vitriolic, nitrous, <lb/>and muriatic acids, with
            concentrated ſolutions of <lb/>ſome metallic ſalts, and alſo with concentrated or
            <lb/>diluted ſolutions of cauſtic alkalies and cauſtic calca- <lb/>rious earth, into
            compounds ſoluble in, and diffu- <lb/>ſible through water. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Acids and ſome metallic ſalts diſſolved in water, <lb/>and concentrated, but not to
            that degree as to diſſolve <lb/>it, alcohol and aluminous ſalts coagulate it. It is
            <lb/>alſo coagulable by the heat of boiling water, but not <lb/>by a leſs degree of
            heat. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_25" n="23"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The mucus defends the membranes from being ſo <lb/>much ſtimulated by any
            application as they would be, <lb/>if they were not covered with it. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If the ſecretion be ſuddenly increaſed, the matter <lb/>ſecreted is often a thin
            watery fluid containing the <lb/>ſalts of the blood, and in conſequence of them capa-
            <lb/>ble of ſtimulating; and the membranes are not de- <lb/>fended from external
            applications. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If a greater ſecretion ſhould continue than what <lb/>naturally takes place, the
            mucus retains the ſalts, but <lb/>often acquires a viſcidity, and becomes incapable of
            <lb/>being diffuſed through water: its colour alſo often <lb/>grows white, greeniſh, or
            yellow; and now and then <lb/>it acquires a ſmell. </p>
        </div>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Saliva</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>T is ſecreted by ſeveral glands in the mouth; and <lb/>the
            principal part of it is thrown down into the <lb/>ſtomach, to anſwer ſome purpoſe in the
            digeſtion of <lb/>the food. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is a fluid of an adheſive viſcidity, with difficulty <lb/>diffuſible through
            water. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It conſiſts of water, a coagulable matter ſimilar to <lb/>that of the mucus, and
            the ſalts of the blood, but <lb/>not in ſo large a proportion as they are contained in
            <lb/>the ſerum. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It contains a larger proportion of water than the <lb/>mucus. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In its other properties it is ſimilar to the mucus. </p>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_26" n="24"/>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Pancreatic Juice</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>T appears to be ſimilar to the ſaliva, except that <lb/>it
            is leſs viſcid, and contains a larger proportion of <lb/>the ſalts of the blood. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The ſaliva and pancreatic juice are probably wa- <lb/>tery menſtrua for the
            ſolution of the food in the <lb/>ſtomach and inteſtines, their viſcidity preventing them
            <lb/>from being abſorbed before they produce that effect. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>They have been ſaid to act as ferments during the <lb/>digeſtion; but as the
            fermentations of the ſtomach <lb/>have never been made to take place out of it, we
            <lb/>cannot judge of this by any experiment hitherto com- <lb/>municated to the public.
          </p>
        </div>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Bile</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE blood from which the bile is formed has <lb/>probably
            gone through one circulation, without <lb/>being expoſed to the air in the lungs, or
            mixed with <lb/>the fluids brought by the lymphatics from the diffe- <lb/>rent parts of
            the body. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The blood, from which the bile is formed, paſſes <lb/>through the veſſels of the
            abdominal viſcera, before it <lb/>arrives at the liver; but it does not take up any ſub-
            <lb/>ſtance from them, or at leaſt not in ſuch a quantity <lb/>as to be ſenſible to any
            experiment yet made; but, <lb/>on the contrary, it appears perfectly ſimilar in all ſen-
              <pb xml:id="page_27" n="25"/>
            <lb/>ſible qualities to the blood returning by the veins from <lb/>the other parts of
            the body. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>There is no appearance of bile in the vena porta- <lb/>rum of a living animal. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When bile in the jaundice is contained in the <lb/>blood-veſſels, it is ſecreted by
            all the ſecretory or- <lb/>gans, and it is evidently contained in all the ſecre-
            <lb/>tions. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The bile is formed from the blood in the ſecretory <lb/>veſſels of the liver. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It runs along the hepatic ducts into the ductus com- <lb/>munis cholidochus, and
            from thence partly into the <lb/>duodenum, and partly into the gall-bladder. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It continues for ſome time in the gall-bladder, and <lb/>becomes more perfect in
            its properties there; from <lb/>thence it returns into the ductus communis cholido-
            <lb/>chus, and paſſes into the duodenum. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The bile is a fluid of an oleaginous viſcidity, con- <lb/>ſiſting of a ſolution of
            a ſolid matter in water. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If the water be not evaporated from it, no altera- <lb/>tion is produced on it by
            any heat between 32 and <lb/>112 degrees of Fahrenheit's thermometer. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The bile is diffuſible in any proportion of water. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If the water be evaporated from the ſolid part by <lb/>a heat not exceeding 112
            degrees of Fahrenheit's ther- <lb/>mometer, it is ſoluble in, and diffuſible through,
            any <lb/>quantity of water. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The ſolid matter of the bile melts if it be heated, <lb/>and is decompoſed if the
            heat be encreaſed. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If it is diſtilled by itſelf, it yields a larger propor- <lb/>tion of empyreumatic
            oil than any of the other fluids, <lb/>except the expreſſed oil and red part of the
            blood. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is of a yellow colour, and a ſweetiſh bitter taſte. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When it is not combined with more water than it <lb/>generally is in the
            gall-bladder, it does not putrify <pb xml:id="page_28" n="26"/>
            <lb/>more readily than the blood; but if it be diluted with <lb/>water or watery fluids,
            it putrifies more readily. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Acids and ſome of their compounds decompoſe it, <lb/>and precipitate from it a
            reſinous matter. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The acidity of the acid is loſt by its combination <lb/>with the other part; but if
            more acid be employed <lb/>than what is neceſſary for the decompoſition, the aci-
            <lb/>dity of the ſuperfluous quantity remains. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The matter precipitated has the peculiar ſmell of <lb/>the animal. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is ſolid in the heat of the atmoſphere, melts in <lb/>a moderate degree of heat,
            and burns very readily. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is not ſoluble in water. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is partly ſoluble in alcohol. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If the paſſage of the bile into the duodenum be <lb/>ſtopt, acidities are apt to
            take place in the inteſtinal <lb/>canal, the periſtaltic motion does not go on properly,
            <lb/>the fæces loſe their peculiar colour and ſmell, and <lb/>often acquire a more
            putrid fœtor, and the digeſtion <lb/>is hurt, but not entirely prevented. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The properties of the other ſecreted fluids have not <lb/>been ſufficiently
            inveſtigated by experiments for us to <lb/>be able to give any ſatisfactory account of
            them. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <pb xml:id="page_29" n="27"/>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
          <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Chemical Properties</hi> of the <lb/><hi rend="sc">Animal
            Solids</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HEY are a compound of coagulable matter <lb/>and water. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>They are naturally flexible; but, if the water be <lb/>evaporated from them by a
          gentle heat, they become <lb/>friable. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The water chemically combined, cannot be ſepa- <lb/>rated from them by expreſſion.
          Expoſed to about a <lb/>red heat, they are decompoſed; and if they be diſtill- <lb/>ed by
          themſelves, volatile alcali, empyreumatic oil, <lb/>water, and calcareous earth, are
          formed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When free from eſſential oil, blood, and the ſalts <lb/>of the fluids, they are
          colourleſs, inſipid, and ino- <lb/>dorous. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>They differ in their flexibility and elaſticity. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Fibres and membranes are readily flexible, not ca- <lb/>pable of being broke by
          bending, and have a leſs de- <lb/>gree of elaſticity. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Cartilage is leſs flexible, capable in general of <lb/>being broke by bending, and
          more elaſtic. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Cartilage often ſupplies the place of bone in young <lb/>animals. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Heat, dilute acids, neutral ſalts, alcohol, metalic, <lb/>and aluminous ſalts,
          aſtringent juices of vegetables, <lb/>and ſeveral other ſubſtances, coagulate them, <hi
            rend="italic">i. e.</hi> ſe- <lb/>parate part of the water chemically combined, and of
          <lb/>conſequence contract them, diminiſh their flexibility, <lb/>and harden them.
          Subſtances coagulating the animal <lb/>ſolids, are called Aſtringents. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_30" n="28"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If they be expoſed to a freezing cold, the water <lb/>freezes; and upon thawing their
          texture is found to <lb/>be altered. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Concentrated vitriolic, nitrous, and muriatic acids, <lb/>cauſtic alkali's, even in a
          diluted ſolution, quick lime, <lb/>and ſeveral of the metallic ſalts, combine with them
          <lb/>into a ſubſtance diffuſible through, or ſoluble in, wa- <lb/>ter, and deſtroy their
          texture. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>They are capable of putrefaction in the ſame man- <lb/>ner as the animal fluids. </p>
      </div>
      <pb xml:id="page_31" n="29"/>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="size(1.5) align-center">
          <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">General Structure</hi> of <lb/>the <hi rend="sc">Body</hi>. </head>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Blood-Vessels</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HERE are cavities in the body, called blood- <lb/>veſſels,
            in which the red part of the blood, the <lb/>coagulable lymph, and part of the ſerum and
            ſuper- <lb/>fluous water, are uſually contained. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>They conſiſt of the heart, arteries, capillaries, and <lb/>veins. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The heart conſiſts eſſentially of two cavities, there <lb/>being two hearts,
            properly ſpeaking, joined together <lb/>in the human body, ſerving for two circulations
            of <lb/>the blood; one through every part of the body, and <lb/>one through the lungs. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The left ſide of the heart ſerves for the general cir- <lb/>culation, and conſiſts
            of two cavities, the auricle <lb/>and the ventricle. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The auricle is a cavity which opens into the pul- <lb/>monary veins at one end, and
            into the ventricle at the <lb/>other. There is a valve placed at the opening into
            <lb/>the ventricle, which prevents any fluid from paſſing <lb/>from the ventricle into
            the auricle. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The auricle is in part covered with muſcular fibres. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The ventricle is a cavity ſurrounded with muſcular <lb/>fibres, having one opening
            into the auricle, and an- <lb/>other into a pipe, called the aorta or great artery. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>At the opening into the aorta, there are valves, <lb/>which prevent any fluid from
            paſſing from the aorta <lb/>into the ventricle. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_32" n="30"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The aorta is a tube which begins at the heart, <lb/>and dividing into ſeveral
            branches, goes to every part <lb/>of the body. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It does not divide at once, but branches out as it <lb/>paſſes along. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When it has arrived at any part, and divided into <lb/>very ſmall branches, theſe
            open into one another, ſo <lb/>as to have a free and perfect communication every
            <lb/>way: from theſe ariſe a ſmaller ſet of tubes, which <lb/>alſo communicate in the
            ſame manner; and from <lb/>them again ariſe a larger ſet, which have likewiſe a
            <lb/>free communication. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The firſt ſet have been called capillary, or anaſto- <lb/>moſing arteries: the
            ſecond have not got a name: <lb/>the third have been called capillary veins; but I
            <lb/>would term all of them capillary veſſels. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>From the third ſet ariſe tubes which terminate in <lb/>the heart, joining together
            as they go on towards it, <lb/>and forming principally two large tubes, which open
            <lb/>into the right auricle. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Theſe are called veins. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The veins which are ſubject to frequent compreſ- <lb/>ſion, from the action of the
            muſcles, have valves <lb/>which open towards the heart. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Each artery, capillary, and vein, is nearly cylin- <lb/>drical, but ſomewhat
            irregular in its diameter. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>No muſcular fibres appear on the arteries, capilla- <lb/>ries, or veins in the
            human body. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Theſe veſſels are all of them elaſtic, and capable <lb/>of being diſtended, ſo as
            to contain a larger quantity <lb/>of fluid than what is neceſſary to render them cylin-
            <lb/>drical. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Their elaſticity is not ſufficient to overcome the <lb/>weight of their ſides and
            keep them cylindrical, if <pb xml:id="page_33" n="31"/>
            <lb/>they are not filled with a fluid, excepting in that part <lb/>of the aorta neareſt
            the heart. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When an animal is dead, and no chemical or me- <lb/>chanical change has taken place
            in the veſſels, the <lb/>elaſticity is the ſame as when the animal was alive. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When an animal is dead, and the veſſels act by <lb/>their elaſticity alone, they
            are incapable of contract- <lb/>ing to half the ſize they are of at their utmoſt diſten-
            <lb/>tion, ſuppoſing them to continue cylindrical. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When an animal is alive, the blood-veſſels are al- <lb/>ways cylindrical, excepting
            when they are compreſſed <lb/>by a conſiderable external force. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>They are always full of blood. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When an animal is alive, the veins, capillaries, <lb/>and ſmall arteries, are
            ſometimes contracted to leſs <lb/>than half the ſize they are of at other times; there-
            <lb/>fore the veins, capillaries, and ſmall arteries, in a <lb/>living animal, have a
            contractile power independent <lb/>of their elaſticity, by which they adapt themſelves
            to <lb/>the blood, and continue cylindrical. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This power is ſimilar to the muſcular power. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When the veſſels contain more blood they become <lb/>longer, or their diameter is
            enlarged, or both; and, <lb/><hi rend="italic">e contra</hi>, </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When they contain leſs blood, they become ſhort- <lb/>er, or their diameter
            diminiſhes, or both. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The contractile power of the veſſels is capable of <lb/>diminiſhing either their
            length or diameter. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When an animal dies, the arteries and veins loſe <lb/>their cylindrical form, and
            are flattened, and the ca- <lb/>pillaries contain leſs blood in them. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The arteries, veins, and capillaries of a living ani- <lb/>mal, are commonly
            contracted to a greater degree <lb/>than they can be by their elaſticity. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_34" n="32"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The elaſticity is commonly endeavouring to diſtend <lb/>them. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If the veſſels are emptied to ſuch a degree that they <lb/>cannot adapt themſelves
            to the blood, and continue <lb/>cylindrical, the animal dies. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The moſt eſſential effort of the living power, is, to <lb/>adapt the veſſels to the
            blood. </p>
        </div>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Course</hi> of the <hi rend="sc">Circulation</hi> of <lb/>the <hi
              rend="sc">Blood</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE blood paſſes from the left auricle of the heart <lb/>into
            the left ventricle, from the left ventricle <lb/>into the aorta, and from thence by the
            ſmaller arte- <lb/>ries to the capillaries in every part of the body; from <lb/>theſe it
            returns by the veins to the right auricle of the <lb/>heart. The blood, for the moſt
            part, moves in one <lb/>uniform direction in each artery, viz. from the heart
            <lb/>towards the capillaries: it alſo moves in one uniform <lb/>direction in each vein,
            viz. from the capillaries to- <lb/>wards the heart; but although it moves in general
            <lb/>from the arteries through the capillaries into the <lb/>veins, yet its direction in
            any one capillary may be, <lb/>and often is, altered and reverſed. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Both the general velocity with which the blood <lb/>moves through the whole ſyſtem,
            and the proporti- <lb/>onal velocity of its motion in particular veſſels, are
            <lb/>conſtantly varying. </p>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_35" n="33"/>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Powers</hi> producing the <hi rend="sc"> Circu- <lb/>lation</hi>
            of the <hi rend="sc">Blood</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE force with which the blood moves in the <lb/>veins, and
            the muſcular contraction of the au- <lb/>ricle, which takes place during the relaxation
            of the <lb/>ventricle, propels the blood into the ventricle. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When a certain quantity of blood is propelled into <lb/>the ventricle, its muſcular
            fibres contract, being pro- <lb/>bably ſtimulated thereto by the blood. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This contraction of the muſcular fibres of the right <lb/>ventricle diminiſhes or
            obliterates it, and propels the <lb/>whole, or part of the blood contained in it, into
            the <lb/>aorta; the valve placed at the opening of the auricle <lb/>into the ventricle,
            preventing its return into the au- <lb/>ricle. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When the ventricle has emptied itſelf into the <lb/>aorta, it relaxes and receives
            a freſh quantity of blood <lb/>from the auricle; the blood being prevented from re-
            <lb/>turning from the aorta by the valves placed at its <lb/>opening into the heart. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The action of the heart tends to produce an equal <lb/>and uniform circulation in
            every part of the body. </p>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Circulation</hi> doth not depend on the <hi rend="sc"
                >Action</hi>
              <lb/> of the <hi rend="sc">Heart</hi> alone. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>The circulation is not equal and uniform through <lb/>the whole body, but the
              ſame quantity of blood flow- <lb/>ing from the heart, a greater proportion of it ſome-
              <lb/>times circulates through one part, ſometimes through <lb/>another. </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_36" n="34"/>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If the heart be the ſole power propelling the blood <lb/>forward, the circulation
              can only be increaſed in any <lb/>one part by an increaſe in the ſize of the veſſels,
              or <lb/>removal of ſome obſtruction to the circulation there, <lb/>or a diminution of
              the ſize of the veſſels, or obſtruct- <lb/>tion to the circulation in the reſt of the
              body; and <lb/><hi rend="italic">e contra</hi> the circulation can only be diminiſhed
              in one <lb/>part by a diminution of the ſize of the veſſels, or ob- <lb/>ſtruction to
              the circulation there, or an increaſe of <lb/>the ſize of the veſſels, or a removal of
              ſome obſtruct- <lb/>tion to the circulation in the other parts of the body. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The principal cauſes producing an alteration of the <lb/>ſize of the veſſels, or
              an obſtruction to the circulation, <lb/>are, <list>
                <item rend="indent">
                  <lb/><hi rend="italic">1ſt</hi>, An increaſe or diminution in the diſpoſition
                  <lb/>to contraction in the capillary veſſels, or in the ex- <lb/>ternal preſſure. </item>
                <item rend="indent">
                  <lb/><hi rend="italic">2dly</hi>, The meeting of the ſtreams of blood in the
                  <lb/>anaſtomoſing veſſels. </item>
                <item rend="indent">
                  <lb/><hi rend="italic">3dly</hi>, The attraction of the blood to the ſides of the
                  <lb/>veſſels. </item>
              </list>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The diſpoſition to contraction in the capillaries of <lb/>a particular part, or
              the external preſſure, may be in- <lb/>creaſed, ſo as actually to produce a diminution
              of the <lb/>ſize of the veſſels of that part, (notwithſtanding the <lb/>action of the
              heart,) and by conſequence a diminution <lb/>of the circulation of the blood in that
              part. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>As the obſtruction ariſing from the meeting of <lb/>the ſtreams of blood in the
              anaſtomoſing veſſels de- <lb/>pends on the velocity with which it moves, it tends
              <lb/>to render the circulation in a part equal, by pre- <lb/>venting an increaſe or
              diminution of it. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>As the blood is thoroughly mixed in the right ven- <lb/>tricle of the heart, and
              is diſtributed from thence to <lb/>the different parts, no alteration in its
              attraction to <pb xml:id="page_37" n="35"/>
              <lb/>the ſides of the veſſels can produce an increaſe or <lb/>diminution of the
              circulation in a particular part. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>It has been ſuppoſed, that a viſcidity in the fluids, <lb/>or an increaſe of the
              ſize of their particles, often <lb/>produced an obſtruction to the circulation; but
              this <lb/>opinion has not been proved, or rendered probable, <lb/>by any experiment
              hitherto made public: on the con- <lb/>trary, the red globules appear to be always
              nearly of <lb/>the ſame ſize, except when they are broke down by <lb/>putrefaction:
              the ſerum and coagulable lymph ſeldom <lb/>or ever appear more viſcid than when in
              their common <lb/>ſtate; and, if they were, their viſcidity would affect <lb/>the
              ſyſtem equally. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The diſpoſition to contraction in the capillary veſ- <lb/>ſels, or the external
              preſſure, may be ſo much dimi- <lb/>niſhed, as that the action of the heart continuing
              the <lb/>ſame, the ſize of the veſſels of a part may be in- <lb/>creaſed, ſo as
              actually to occaſion a greater circula- <lb/>tion of blood in that part. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If the heart be the ſole cauſe of the circulation, the <lb/>only material
              alteration that could take place in the <lb/>proportion of the circulation in the
              different parts, <lb/>muſt depend on an increaſe or diminution of the diſ-
              <lb/>poſition to contraction in the veſſels, or on an altera- <lb/>tion in the
              external preſſure. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>But the circulation may be increaſed in a particu- <lb/>lar part, the motion of
              the heart continuing the ſame, <lb/>by cauſes which do not diminiſh the diſpoſition to
              <lb/>contraction of the veſſels of that part, nor increaſe <lb/>the diſpoſition to
              contraction in the veſſels in the <lb/>other parts of the body, nor produce any effect
              on <lb/>the external preſſure. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Therefore the heart is not the ſole power which <lb/>propels the fluids through
              the part in which the circu- <lb/>lation is thus increaſed. </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_38" n="36"/>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The cauſes capable of increaſing the circulation in <lb/>a part, are generally
              ſuch as tend to excite muſcular <lb/>motion, and are called ſtimuli. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Some part of the body, brought into action by <lb/>theſe ſtimuli, is capable of
              increaſing the circulation <lb/>independent of the action of the heart. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The arteries are endowed with a muſcular motion, <lb/>by which they may increaſe
              the circulation in a par- <lb/>ticular part, or aſſiſt the heart in the general
              circula- <lb/>tion of the blood. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The arteries at each contraction of the heart are <lb/>diſtended; at each
              relaxation they contract. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>This alternate contraction and dilatation might <lb/>depend on their elaſticity. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If their contractions and dilatations depended on <lb/>their elaſticity, their
              ſize at their utmoſt contraction <lb/>in the living body ſhould be equal to that
              produced <lb/>by a fluid injected into them, with a force capable of <lb/>overcoming
              the reſiſtance the blood meets with in the <lb/>capillary veſſels, which, in the human
              body, is pro- <lb/>bably equal to eight feet perpendicular height of <lb/>water. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>But their ſize, even at their utmoſt ſtate of dila- <lb/>tation, is leſs than
              that produced by a fluid injected <lb/>into them, with a force equal to one foot
              perpendi- <lb/>cular height of water, when the animal is dead. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Therefore their contractions and dilatations do not <lb/>depend on their
              elaſticity. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The additional force which occaſions an increaſe <lb/>of the circulation, in a
              particular part, muſt depend <lb/>on the action of the arteries or capillaries. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>As the capillaries do not contract and dilate alter- <lb/>nately, and as the
              direction of the blood in any one <pb xml:id="page_39" n="37"/>
              <lb/>of them is quite undetermined, this additional force <lb/>cannot depend on the
              action of the capillaries. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If the arteries contracted and dilated by their elaſti- <lb/>city, no additional
              force could be applied from their <lb/>contraction and dilatation; ſince the heart
              would loſe <lb/>more force, in diſtending the arteries, than they <lb/>would re-apply
              to the blood in contracting. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If the arteries, upon being diſtended by the blood <lb/>thrown into them by the
              heart, are excited to a muſ- <lb/>cular contraction, and when they have performed
              <lb/>this contraction relax, and like the ventricle of the <lb/>heart, receive the
              blood eaſily into them, and when <lb/>they are again diſtended, are excited to a
              ſecond con- <lb/>traction, they may apply an additional force to that <lb/>of the
              heart, ſo as to promote the circulation through <lb/>the whole body. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If ſuch contractions and dilatations be greater in <lb/>any particular part, they
              will promote the circulation <lb/>in that part; in as much as, when they are relaxed
              <lb/>to a greater degree, they will ſuffer the blood to paſs <lb/>through them more
              readily into the capillaries; and, <lb/>when they contract, they will empty themſelves
              more <lb/>thoroughly into the capillaries. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The arteries have a muſcular contraction and dila- <lb/>tation, ſimilar to that
              of the ventricles of the heart, <lb/>by which they apply an additional power to that
              of <lb/>the heart, ſo as to promote the general circulation <lb/>through the whole
              body, and often to increaſe the <lb/>proportional circulation in a particular part. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The motion of the blood is regulated by the action <lb/>of the heart and
              arteries, and the contraction of the <lb/>capillary veſſels; and theſe are meaſured by
              the pulſe. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_40" n="38"/>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Pulse</hi>. </head>
          <table rows="10" cols="3">
            <row role="label" rend="space align-center">
              <cell>Indicates </cell>
              <cell>by </cell>
              <cell>It is called </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><hi rend="italic">1ſt</hi>, <hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE ſtrength of <lb/>the
                contraction <lb/>of the heart, </cell>
              <cell>Strength, <lb/>Weakneſs, </cell>
              <cell>Strong. <lb/>Weak. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="indent"><hi rend="italic">2dly</hi>, The quantity of <lb/>blood thrown out
                at <lb/>each contraction, </cell>
              <cell>Fulneſs, <lb/>Smallneſs, </cell>
              <cell>Full. <lb/>Small. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="indent"><hi rend="italic">3dly</hi>, The number of <lb/>contractions, </cell>
              <cell>Frequency, <lb/>Slowneſs, </cell>
              <cell>Frequent. <lb/>Slow. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="indent">
                <lb/><hi rend="italic">4thly</hi>, The regularity <lb/>of its action, as to
                <lb/>ſtrength, quantity or <lb/>frequency, </cell>
              <cell>Regularity, <lb/>Irregularity, <lb/>Intermiſſion, </cell>
              <cell>Regular. <lb/>Irregular. <lb/>Intermittent. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="indent"><hi rend="italic">5thly</hi>, The ſtrength of <lb/>the action of
                the arte- <lb/>ries, </cell>
              <cell>Hardneſs, <lb/>Softneſs, <lb/>Redoubling, <lb/>Trembling, </cell>
              <cell>Hard. <lb/>Soft. <lb/>Redoubling. <lb/>Trembling. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="indent"><hi rend="italic">6thly</hi>, The irritability <lb/>of the
                veſſels, </cell>
              <cell>Quickneſs, <lb/>Regularity, <lb/>Slowneſs, </cell>
              <cell>Quick. <lb/>Regular. <lb/>Slow. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="indent"><hi rend="italic">7thly</hi>, The medium <lb/>diameter of the
                arteries, </cell>
              <cell>Dilatation, <lb/>Contraction, </cell>
              <cell>Great. <lb/>Small. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="indent"><hi rend="italic">8thly</hi>, The quantity <lb/>of blood in the
                veſſels, </cell>
              <cell>Oppreſſion, <lb/>Smallneſs, </cell>
              <cell>Oppreſſed. <lb/>Empty. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="indent"><hi rend="italic">9thly</hi>, The contracti- <lb/>on of the
                capillaries, </cell>
              <cell>Obſtruction, <lb/>Freedom, </cell>
              <cell>Obſtructed. <lb/>Free. </cell>
            </row>
          </table>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_41" n="39"/>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Structure</hi> of the <hi rend="sc">Lungs</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HERE is a ſet of veſſels in the lungs which con- <lb/>tain
            air, and another which contain blood. </p>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Air Vessels</hi>. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The air veſſels conſiſt of a pipe, called the trachea; <lb/>one end of which
              opens into the throat, and commu- <lb/>nicates with the <choice>
                <corr>atmoſphere</corr>
                <sic>amtoſphere</sic>
              </choice> by the noſtrils and mouth; <lb/>the other divides into branches which go to
              every part <lb/>of the lungs, and whoſe ends open into ſmall cavities, <lb/>or cells. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The air in the lungs is generally in motion; for ei- <lb/>ther that which is at
              preſent contained in the cells, is <lb/>paſſing through the trachea into the
              atmoſphere, or a <lb/>freſh parcel is paſſing from the external atmoſphere
              <lb/>through the trachea into the cells. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The whole of this motion is called reſpiration: <lb/>when the air is paſſing in,
              it is called inſpiration; <lb/>when it is thrown out, expiration. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>When the thorax is enlarged by the action of one <lb/>ſet of its muſcles, the
              preſſure of the external atmo- <lb/>ſphere forces the air into the lungs; the other
              ſet of <lb/>muſcles which contract the thorax when put in action, <lb/>force the air
              out of the lungs into the atmoſphere. <lb/>But the preſſure of the atmoſphere on the
              ſurface of <lb/>the body counterbalancing its preſſure on the ſurface <lb/>of the
              lungs, neither the muſcles of inſpiration nor <lb/>thoſe of expiration are aſſiſted or
              counteracted by it. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If the air continues at reſt in the lungs for many <lb/>minutes, or if a man
              continues to reſpire the ſame <pb xml:id="page_42" n="40"/>
              <lb/>air, or if he breathes air that hath ſerved for the in- <lb/>flammation of fuel
              or pure fixable air, he dies. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>It is not determined whether pure inflammable air <lb/>will ſerve for
              reſpiration. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Some vapours kill immediately if taken into the <lb/>lungs, independent of their
              being unfit for reſpira- <lb/>tion. </p>
            <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Blood-Vessels</hi>. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The air veſſels of the lungs conſiſt of two ſets, viz. <list rend="indentall">
                <item>
                  <lb/><hi rend="italic">1ſt</hi>, The Pulmonary. </item>
                <item>
                  <lb/><hi rend="italic">2dly</hi>, The Bronchial. </item>
              </list>
            </p></div>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Pulmonary Vessels</hi>. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The right ſide of the heart is ſimilar to the left, ex- <lb/>cepting that both
              the auricle and ventricle have fewer <lb/>muſcular fibres, and that the auricle
              receives blood <lb/>from the venæ cavæ, and the ventricle throws it into <lb/>the
              pulmonary artery. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The pulmonary artery begins at the right ventricle <lb/>of the heart, and goes
              from thence to every part of the <lb/>lungs in the ſame manner that the aorta goes to
              every <lb/>part of the body. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>When the pulmonary artery hath divided into very <lb/>ſmall branches, theſe do
              not open into one another <lb/>and form anaſtomoſing veſſels like the ſmall branches
              <lb/>of the aorta; but they join again, and form veins, <lb/>which uniting together,
              go to the left auricle of the <lb/>heart commonly in five trunks. </p>
          </div>
          <pb xml:id="page_43" n="41"/>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Circulation</hi> of the <hi rend="sc">Blood</hi> through the
                <lb/><hi rend="sc">Pulmonary Vessels</hi>. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The blood paſſes from the right auricle into the <lb/>right ventricle, from the
              right ventricle into the pul- <lb/>monary artery, from the pulmonary artery into the
              <lb/>pulmonary veins, and from the pulmonary veins into <lb/>the left auricle. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Powers</hi> propelling the <hi rend="sc">Blood</hi> through the
                <lb/><hi rend="sc">Lungs</hi>. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The muſcular fibres of the right auricle contract- <lb/>ing, propel part of the
              blood contained in it into <lb/>the right ventricle, and they are aſſiſted by the
              force <lb/>with which the blood moves in the veins. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The muſcular fibres of the right ventricle being ſti- <lb/>mulated to contract
              when it is full, propel part or the <lb/>whole of the blood contained in it into the
              pulmonary <lb/>artery, the blood being prevented from returning into <lb/>the auricle
              by the valve placed at the opening of the <lb/>auricle into the ventricle. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>After the ventricle has contracted, it relaxes and <lb/>receives the blood from
              the auricle, it being prevented <lb/>from returning from the pulmonary artery by the
              <lb/>valves placed at the opening of the pulmonary artery <lb/>into the ventricle. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The blood is thrown by the right ventricle through <lb/>the pulmonary artery and
              veins into the left au- <lb/>ricle. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Perhaps the pulmonary artery hath a muſcular <lb/>power, ſimilar to the muſcular
              power of the other ar- <lb/>teries, by which it promotes the circulation of the
              <lb/>blood through the lungs. </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_44" n="42"/>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The blood meets with the ſame obſtructions in its <lb/>paſſage through the lungs
              that it does in its paſſage <lb/>through the other parts of the body, excepting that
              <lb/>there being no anaſtomoſing veſſels, there is no ob- <lb/>ſtruction from the
              ſtreams of the blood meeting in <lb/>them, and oppoſing each others motion. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The blood meets with ſome additional obſtructions <lb/>in its paſſage through the
              pulmonary veſſels, beſides <lb/>thoſe it meets with in the other parts of the body,
              <lb/>viz. <list>
                <item rend="indent">
                  <lb/><hi rend="italic">1ſt</hi>, The motion of the lungs in reſpiration, as
                  <lb/>there are no valves in the veſſels, tends to retard the <lb/>circulation,
                  although the reverſe hath been aſſerted. </item>
                <item rend="indent">
                  <lb/><hi rend="italic">2dly</hi>, If a ſufficient quantity of reſpirable air be
                  not <lb/>received into, and thrown out of the lungs, the mo- <lb/>tion of the
                  blood in the pulmonary veſſels is con- <lb/>ſiderably retarded. </item>
              </list>
            </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Bronchial Vessels</hi>. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>An artery ariſes from the aorta, and ſpreads itſelf <lb/>through the lungs,
              terminating in anaſtomoſing capil- <lb/>lary veſſels, which open into veins in the
              ſame man- <lb/>ner as the other branches of the aorta in other parts <lb/>of the body. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The blood circulates in theſe veſſels in the ſame <lb/>manner as in the other
              veſſels, ariſing from the aorta <lb/>in other parts of the body. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_45" n="43"/>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Extravasation</hi> and <hi rend="sc">Absorption</hi>
            <lb/>of the <hi rend="sc">Lymph</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">P</hi>ART of the ſuperfluous water and ſerum is con- <lb/>tinually
            paſſing through the ſides of the veſſels, <lb/>particularly the capillaries, into the
            cellular mem- <lb/>brane, and all the cavities of the body, ſo as to keep <lb/>their
            ſurfaces moiſt. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It has been ſuppoſed that they paſſed through tubes <lb/>appended to the ſides of
            the blood-veſſels; but ſuch <lb/>veſſels have never been demonſtrated, nor is there any
            <lb/>reaſon for ſuppoſing that they exiſt, excepting in the <lb/>glands. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The fluids, commonly extravaſated, have been <lb/>called the lymph. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is uncertain whether it paſſes through the acci- <lb/>dental pores in the ſides
            of the veſſels, or by cy- <lb/>lindrical organiſed holes; but it is moſt probable that
            <lb/>it paſſes through organiſed holes, as the ſecretion is <lb/>regular and conſtant. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The pores or veſſels it paſſes through, are called <lb/>exhalants. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is abſorbed by the lymphatics. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>A lymphatic is a tube nearly cylindrical, divided by <lb/>valves, ſo as to have the
            reſemblance of joints. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>They ariſe from the cellular membrane, and cavi- <lb/>ties, and the greateſt part
            of them go to the thoracic <lb/>duct. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The valves allow the lymph to paſs from the cavi- <lb/>ties to the thoracic duct,
            but prevent its paſſing from <lb/>the thoracic duct to the cavities. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_46" n="44"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The lymphatics in paſſing from the cavities to the <lb/>thoracic duct, go through
            the lymphatic glands. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The ſtructure and uſe of theſe glands are not as yet <lb/>aſcertained. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The thoracic duct is a tube which begins near the <lb/>diaphragm, and commonly
            terminates in the left ſub- <lb/>clavian vein. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>At its opening into the left ſubclavian vein, there is <lb/>a valve which allows
            the lymph to paſs from it into <lb/>the vein, but prevents the running of the blood from
            <lb/>the vein into the thoracic duct. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Some of the lymphatics terminate in veins. Theſe <lb/>are ſimilar in ſtructure to
            thoſe which terminate in the <lb/>thoracic duct. </p>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Powers</hi> producing the <hi rend="sc">Extravasation</hi> and
                <lb/><hi rend="sc">Absorption</hi> of the <hi rend="sc">Lymph</hi>. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The contractile power of the blood-veſſels ſqueezes <lb/>the lymph into the
              cellular membrane and cavities. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The quantity thrown out is in proportion to the <lb/>force of the circulation,
              the fluidity of the ſubſtances <lb/>contained in the blood-veſſels, or the quantity of
              the <lb/>more fluid ſubſtances, and the degree of contraction <lb/>of the capillaries
              and exhalants. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The joint of a lymphatic opening into a cavity, en- <lb/>deavours to fill itſelf
              from that cavity by its action as <lb/>a capillary tube, the valves preventing the
              return of <lb/>the lymph from the other part of the lymphatic. <lb/>In like manner a
              lymphatic may fill itſelf entirely <lb/>from the cavity in which it terminates, but
              its action <lb/>as a capillary tube will not tend in the ſmalleſt degree <lb/>to
              propel the lymph into the veins. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>It is moſt probable that the joint of the lymphatic, <lb/>next to the cavity,
              having abſorbed a ſufficient quan- <pb xml:id="page_47" n="45"/>
              <lb/>tity of lymph to fill it, is ſtimulated to contract and <lb/>propel the fluid
              into the next joint, and ſo on to the <lb/>thoracic duct, or vein, in which it
              terminates; and <lb/>having emptied itſelf, and being relaxed, it fills itſelf
              <lb/>again from the cavity, and ſo continues to act: for <lb/>there is apparently no
              other power in the body capable <lb/>of producing a regular flow of the lymph through
              the <lb/>lymphatics into the blood-veſſels. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>For in a living animal where the veins are con- <lb/>tracting, and preſſing the
              blood, if one end of a ca- <lb/>pillary tube terminate in a vein, and the other in a
              <lb/>cavity; and if there be no action in that tube, ex- <lb/>cepting that which
              ariſes from its being a capillary <lb/>one, or from the motion of the blood in the
              vein; if <lb/>there be any motion in that tube after it is full, it will <lb/>always
              be from the vein into the cavity, and never <lb/>from the cavity into the vein, let
              the tube be of any <lb/>ſize or ſhape whatever. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Further; the alternate preſſure of the lymphatics <lb/>ariſing from the alternate
              contractions and relaxations <lb/>of the blood-veſſels, or muſcles, is not
              ſufficiently <lb/>powerful, univerſal, or equal, to produce a regular <lb/>flow of the
              lymph through the lymphatics into the <lb/>blood-veſſels. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Neither does the cellular membrane and cavities <lb/>force the lymph into the
              lymphatics, and through <lb/>them into the veins. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The extravaſation of fluids from the blood-veſſels <lb/>in to the cellular
              membrane and cavities, and their re- <lb/>abſorption, generally take place in the
              above man- <lb/>ner. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Sometimes the coagulable lymph is thrown out by <lb/>the exhalants. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>When the coagulable lymph is thrown out, it moſt <lb/>commonly coagulates. </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_48" n="46"/>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If it coagulate, it cannot be taken up by the <choice>
                <corr>lympha-</corr>
                <sic>lymha-</sic>
              </choice>
              <lb/>tics, till it be rediſſolved. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>In many caſes it rediſſolves, and is abſorbed much <lb/>ſooner than it can be
              rendered ſoluble in water, by <lb/>putrefaction when out of the body. At other times
              <lb/>it continues in the cavity for many years. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The red part of the blood is alſo ſometimes thrown <lb/>out by the exhalants. In
              this caſe, its particles are <lb/>broke down probably by the firſt ſtage of
              putrefaction, <lb/>and it is afterwards reabſorbed. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The ſame things may happen, if the red particles <lb/>and coagulable lymph are
              extravaſated in conſequence <lb/>of the rupture of a blood-veſſel. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>In particular parts, as in the corpora cavernoſa <lb/>penis, the extravaſation
              and abſorption is probably <lb/>performed in a different manner, and by different
              <lb/>veſſels. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>All abſorbent veſſels muſt have a power of propel- <lb/>ling the fluids into the
              blood-veſſels, ſufficient to <lb/>overcome the force of their contraction, by which
              <lb/>they endeavour to propel the blood out of any <lb/>opening. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="18"/>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
