<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Aitken: Medical improvement: an address read to the Medical
          Society</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>John Aitken</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">MEDICAL IMPROVEMENT: AN ADDRESS READ TO THE MEDICAL SOCIETY</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">N3814</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N3814"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: printed for and sold by John Bell, M,DCC,LXXVII.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1777</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="3"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="35"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">National Library of Medicines</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3308560619</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K002449.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="General treatises"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <p rend="align-center space"><lb/>THE FOLLOWING PAGES <lb/>ARE MOST RESPECTFULLY INSCRIBED
          <lb/>TO THE <lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)">PRESIDENTS</hi> AND OTHER <hi rend="size(1.7)"
            >MEMBERS</hi>
          <lb/>OF THE <lb/><hi rend="size(2.2)">MEDICAL SOCIETY</hi>. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_3"/>
      <pb xml:id="page_4"/>
      <head rend="align-center space"><lb/>AN <lb/>ADDRESS, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
      </head>
      <salute>GENTLEMEN, </salute>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">I</hi>T is with much diffidence that I <w part="I"
          >offi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cially</w> preſume to deliver a few <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">tach'd</w> thoughts, chiefly reſpecting <hi rend="sc"><w part="I"
            >Medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cal</w> Improvement</hi>; as an addreſs <w part="I"
          >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">troductory</w> to the commencement of our <lb/>literary buſineſs
        in this place. Your <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">dulgent</w> candour which I have ſo
        often <lb/>experienced, I flatter myſelf, will, on this <lb/>occaſion, impute the faults
        which you <lb/>will doubtleſs diſcover, not to intention, <lb/>but inability or
        miſconception. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I chearfully embrace this opportunity <lb/>to expreſs the moſt grateful
        impreſſions I <pb xml:id="page_5" n="8"/><lb/>entertain of the great and unſollicited
        <lb/>honour you have been pleaſed to confer <lb/>upon me, by twice calling me to the <w
          part="I">of-</w><lb/><w part="F">fice</w> of <hi rend="sc">President</hi>. Had my powers
        been <lb/>equal to my wiſhes, no part of my <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">duct</w> in
        that elevated character, had been <lb/>unworthy of you, or of this chair. <w part="I"
          >Al-</w><lb/><w part="F">tho'</w> indiſpenſible avocation permits me <lb/>no longer to
        hold any office among you; <lb/>yet will I loſe no opportunity of being <lb/>preſent, and,
        as far as I may be able, of <lb/>aſſiſting in your inſtructive ſpeculations; <lb/>and of
        promoting to the utmoſt of my <lb/>power, the general proſperity of a Society <lb/>to which
        I ever have been ſo much <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tached</w>. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the commercial world, it is allowed <lb/>by all, that the comparative
        rate of <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">change</w>, is a juſt <hi rend="italic"
          >index</hi> of the proſperous <lb/>or adverſe ſtate of trade in different <lb/>countries
        individually, or relatively <w part="I">con-</w><pb xml:id="page_6" n="9"/><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſidered</w>. With no leſs truth, in my <lb/>opnion, the comparative degree of
        <lb/>cultivation to which <hi rend="italic">Belles Lettres</hi> and <lb/>philoſophy, or the
        fine and uſeful arts, <lb/>arrive in different kingdoms may be <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">garded</w> as demonſtrative of their <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >lative</w> civilization. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Judging by this criterion, altho' in <lb/>this reſpect <hi rend="sc"
          >Caledonia</hi> may not juſtly <lb/>boaſt of being the firſt, ſhe is by no <lb/>means the
        laſt of the European nations: <lb/>Her progreſs in the walk of general <lb/>ſcience and
        liberality is rapid, and I <lb/>hope will long continue ſo. Juſtice, <lb/>however,
        conſtrains me to confeſs, that <lb/>long, too long, in a great degree, ſhe had
        <lb/>neglected the <hi rend="sc">Medical Philosophy</hi>. <lb/>In an <hi rend="italic"
          >Aera</hi> not beyond the recollection <lb/>of ſome preſent, the immortal honour of
        <lb/>planting a medical ſchool in this <hi rend="italic">Metropo-<lb/>lis;</hi> now indeed
        ſecond in fame and <lb/>erudition to none in Europe, was <w part="I">reſerv-</w><pb
          xml:id="page_7" n="10"/><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> to a diſtinguiſhed, a fortunate <hi
          rend="sc"><w part="I">Mon-</w><lb/><w part="F">ro</w>.</hi> To his memory conſenting
        nations <lb/>pay that juſt tribute of applauſe, which <lb/>his country in general, but this
        City and <lb/>its Univerſity in particular, ought to <lb/>perpetuate by a ſtatue. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>By a <hi rend="sc">Worthy Select Band</hi>of the <lb/>numerous ſtudents,
        who flocked from all <lb/>quarters, allured by the riſing fame of <lb/>the Edinburgh
        Univerſity; this <hi rend="sc">Medical <lb/>Society</hi> in 1737, was happily <w part="I"
          >inſtitu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ted</w>. Of its various progreſs and preſent
        <lb/>flouriſhing independent ſtate, I preſume <lb/>you to be well informed; and <w part="I"
          >there-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w> avoid attempting any particular <w part="I"
          >hiſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">torical</w> narration of theſe circumſtances at <lb/>preſent. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The Building</hi><note place="bottom" n="*">* The <hi
            rend="sc">Medical Hall</hi>,—A handſome <w part="I">Edi-</w><lb/><w part="F">fice</w> of
          various elegant appartments with a <hi rend="italic">Cupola</hi>
          <lb/>and Spire, ornamented with the <hi rend="italic">Inſignia</hi> of <w part="I"
            >Aeſcu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lapius</w>, erected chiefly by the liberal contributions
          <lb/>of the Members. </note> in which we are now <pb xml:id="page_8" n="11"
        /><lb/>aſſembled is a grand <hi rend="italic">phenomenon</hi> of <w part="I"
          >medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cal</w> ardor, unparallelled in any country; <lb/>and may
        juſtly be regarded as a temple <lb/>ſacred to <hi rend="sc">Æsculapius</hi>, reared by the
        <lb/>virtuous zeal of his youthful votaries, <lb/>for purpoſes the moſt liberal and <w
          part="I">praiſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">worthy</w>. The <hi rend="sc">Friends of
        Science</hi>, not <lb/>of your number,<note place="bottom" n="*">* Many Gentlemen,
          applauding the noble <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">tentions</w> of the Society, have
          been generouſly <lb/>pleaſed to contribute towards defraying the <w part="I"
            >ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">pence</w> of building the Hall,—Liſts of whom are
          <lb/>ſuſpended in the principal appartment. </note> who have generouſly <lb/>contributed
        towards its ſtructure; are <lb/>entitled to our moſt grateful thanks. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Contemplating this <hi rend="sc">Fabric</hi>, and the <lb/>many other
        aids which the preſent <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">vantageous</w> ſtate of our
        ſociety affords <lb/>to facilitate ſtudy; you muſt have <w part="I">anti-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">cipated</w> me in this reflection, that, while <lb/>our minds are gratefully
        affected to <lb/>our <hi rend="sc">Meritorious Predecessors</hi>, our <pb xml:id="page_9"
          n="12"/><lb/>every power ought to be exerted, if not <lb/>to advance, at leaſt, to
        maintain our <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">tended</w> reputation: that, the verdant <w
          part="I">lau-</w><lb/><w part="F">rels</w> they have tranſmitted may not <w part="I"
          >wi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> in our hands, overwhelming us with <lb/>indelible
        ignominy and diſgrace. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>'Tis with the higheſt pleaſure, I <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ceive</w>, without being chargeable with <lb/>adulation, I can fairly aver, that this <w
          part="I">So-</w><lb/><w part="F">ciety</w> at no period of its exiſtence has <lb/>been
        more ſecure of progreſs than at <lb/>preſent: the learning, genius and manly <lb/>liberality
        of ſentiment, which I know you <lb/>poſſeſs, and which, with much <w part="I"
          >ſatisfac-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> and inſtruction, I have ſo often <w part="I"
          >ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerved</w> animating your debates; conſtitute <lb/>the foundation
        on which this aſſertion reſts. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>You are not to be informed that the <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >bined</w> powers of <hi rend="sc">Genius</hi> and <hi rend="sc">Industry</hi>
        <lb/>muſt perſeveringly operate thro' the <lb/>courſe of ſeveral years, that a tolerably <pb
          xml:id="page_10" n="13"/><lb/>complete knowledge of even the <w part="I"
          >elemen-</w><lb/><w part="F">tary</w> parts of the ſcience of medicine, as <lb/>already
        aſcertained and taught, may be <lb/>acquired. To have proceeded ſo far in <lb/>medical
        ſtudy, is indeed to have made no <lb/>deſpicable progreſs: But I truſt your <lb/>ardent
        ambition is more aſpiring than to <lb/>remain ſatisfied with the acquiſition of a <lb/>bare
        acquaintance of the <hi rend="italic">dogmata</hi> of this, <lb/>or the other <hi rend="sc"
          >Medical Sect</hi> or <hi rend="sc">professor</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> of
        the preſent ſtate of the healing art. <lb/>It would be offering an undeſerved inſult to
        <lb/>your ſagacity, were I but once to <lb/>imagine, that you could entertain a <w part="I"
          >be-</w><lb/><w part="F">lief</w>, that the Medical Philoſophy had <w part="I"
          >al-</w><lb/><w part="F">ready</w> attained the utmoſt perfection of <lb/>which it is
        ſuſceptible. You well know, <lb/>that the unexplored regions of the <hi rend="italic">terra
          <lb/>incognita Medicinalis,</hi> ſo to ſpeak, ſtill <w part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ford</w> abundant ſcope for your moſt <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">tracted</w>
        labours; ſo juſt is the <w part="I">obſerva-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, <hi rend="italic"
          >ars longa, vita brevis.</hi>
      </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_11" n="14"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Anatomy</hi>, as being the <hi rend="italic">grand
          baſis</hi>
        <lb/>of the Medical Fabric, from the earlieſt <lb/>periods of ſociety, in every civilized <w
          part="I">coun-</w><lb/><w part="F">try</w>, has been cultivated with the moſt
        <lb/>unrelenting ardor of inveſtigation, which <lb/>many moſt material improvements have
        <lb/>from time to time rewarded. Are there <lb/>not ſtill, however, many very intereſting
        <lb/>parts and circumſtances of the ſtructure <lb/>of the <hi rend="sc">Animal
          Automaton</hi> which we <lb/>but little know? and many others of <lb/>great importance, of
        which we are <w part="I">total-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> ignorant? What anatomiſt has <w
          part="I">hither-</w><lb/><w part="F">to</w> been able ſucceſſfully to evolve the
        <lb/>texture of the <hi rend="sc">Spleen</hi>; an organ of <lb/>conſiderable ſize, and
        probably of <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">portional</w> importance in the animal <w
          part="I">œco-</w><lb/><w part="F">nomy?</w> Very lately it has been ſuppoſed <lb/>the ſole
        fabricator of the globular part of <lb/>the blood<note place="bottom" n="*">* The late
          ingenious Mr Hewſon of London, <lb/>endeavoured to eſtabliſh this opinion. </note>. The
        ſame queſtion may be <lb/>put with reſpect to the ſtructure of the <lb/><hi rend="sc"
          >Muscular Fibre</hi>, or <hi rend="sc">Living Solid</hi>; <pb xml:id="page_12" n="15"
        /><lb/>and that <hi rend="sc">Specific Configuration</hi> of <lb/>the ſeveral orders of the
          <hi rend="sc">Secretory <lb/>Organs</hi>, upon which ſuch a wonderful <lb/>variety and
        oppoſition of ſecreted liquors <lb/>probably depends. But, above all, it <lb/>may be put
        with reſpect to the <hi rend="sc">Brain</hi>, <lb/>and <hi rend="sc">Its Appendages</hi>;
        parts eſſential to <lb/>life, often the ſeat of diſeaſe, evidently <lb/>variouſly organized,
        of great volume and <lb/>ſurprizingly diverſified in their external form. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I will be pardoned for expreſſing my <lb/>fears, that few anatomical
        improvements <lb/>are to be expected from you while <w part="I">reſi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ding</w> in this country; at leaſt, while its <lb/>preſent TONE continues, however great
        <lb/>your ability and ardor: becauſe an <w part="I">inſu-</w><lb/><w part="F">perable</w>
        barrier is oppoſed to your <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">gress</w>; I mean the <hi
          rend="sc">want of private <lb/>Dissection</hi>. In the end of the <w part="I"
          >eight-</w><lb/><w part="F">teenth</w> century, when philoſophical <w part="I"
          >libera-</w><lb/><w part="F">lity</w> is diffuſed from Pole to Pole, what a <pb
          xml:id="page_13" n="16"/><lb/>pity, or rather what a ſhame, that, even <lb/>in the
        Metropolis of a kingdom, not <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">civilized</w>, and in its
        principal <w part="I">Univerſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ty</w> too, where the circle of
        education <lb/>is otherwiſe tolerably complete; this <lb/><hi rend="sc">Grand</hi> and
        almoſt <hi rend="sc">only Avenue</hi> to <lb/>the <hi rend="sc">Æsculapian</hi> Temple,
        ſhould <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">main</w> moſt barbarouſly blocked up! </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>A public courſe of anatomical <w part="I">demon-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſtration</w>, exceeded by none, and equalled <lb/>by few, is, I confeſs, annually made
        here; <lb/>by a learned, diſcerning, accurate, <w part="I">inde-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >fatigable</w> Profeſſor: whom none of you <lb/>can more reſpect than I do. I, <w part="I"
          >notwith-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtanding</w>, heſitate not to declare it as my <lb/>poſitive
        opinion, and I will venture to ſay <lb/>it is not ſolitary, that, no public <w part="I"
          >anatomi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cal</w> exhibitions, where the ſtudent is <w part="I"
          >mere-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> a <hi rend="sc">passive Spectator</hi>, are ſufficient
        <lb/>to convey and impreſs thoſe preciſe and <lb/>multifarious ideas of this important
        <lb/>branch of natural knowledge, <w part="I">abſolute-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> requiſite
        to complete the medical <pb xml:id="page_14" n="17"/><lb/>character; throwing diſcovery
        altogether <lb/>out of the queſtion. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>To acquire a tolerable knowledge of <lb/>even the great outlines of
        anatomy, it is <lb/>indiſpenſibly neceſſary to take the knife <lb/>in hand, and, with the
        moſt unremitting <lb/>attention, diſſect a variety of bodies of <lb/>different ſizes, ages,
        and ſexes, properly <lb/>choſen, and prepared for the purpoſe: <lb/>Much more muſt this plan
        be followed, <lb/>if it be propoſed to ſoar in the regions of <lb/>diſcovery and
        improvement. I can <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">perimentally</w> aſſert, that more
        anatomical <lb/>information will be reaped from the well <lb/>conducted diſſection of one
        body, than <lb/>from repeated public courſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>If this opinion be well founded, it is <lb/>a ſelf-evident conſequence,
        that attending <lb/>one or two public courſes of anatomy, <lb/>muſt be much inadequate to
        accompliſh <lb/>the medical philoſopher; eſpecially, if <lb/>the practice of ſurgery, the
        moſt <w part="I">evident-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> uſeful part of the healing art, be his
          <pb xml:id="page_15" n="18"/><lb/>deſtination. Humanity revolts at the <lb/>idea of the
        many unavoidable, and, I <lb/>fear, too often fatal blunders that muſt <lb/>reſult from this
        capital defect of the <w part="I">me-</w><lb/><w part="F">dical</w> education to be obtained
        in this <lb/>country. It is abundantly mortifying <lb/>indeed, to obſerve thoſe who wiſh to
          <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tain</w> a proper degree of anatomical <w part="I"
          >know-</w><lb/><w part="F">ledge</w>, after ſpending ſeveral years at our
        <lb/>Univerſities, and probably attaining their <lb/>higheſt honours, reduced to the <w
          part="I">alterna-</w><lb/><w part="F">tive</w> of either undertaking expenſive <w part="I"
          >ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">peditions</w> into foreign countries, in this <lb/>reſpect more
        civilized than ours; or of <lb/>remaining dangerouſly uninformed. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>If one ſhould attempt to adjuſt the <lb/>wheels and ſprings of a nice
        and delicate <lb/>mechaniſm, he, perhaps, had never <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >fore</w> ſeen, or, at leaſt, never minutely <lb/>conſidered; with what indignant contempt
        <lb/>would we treat the rude audacious <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">tender?</w>
        Thouſands, alas! are daily <w part="I">ſub-</w><pb xml:id="page_16" n="19"/><lb/><w part="F"
          >jected</w> to the unpractiſed knife of <w part="I">opera-</w><lb/><w part="F">tors</w> of
        neceſſity aukward, I had almoſt <lb/>ſaid unskilled; becauſe they never could <lb/>enjoy the
        requiſite opportunity, of either <lb/>acquiring proper dexterity to perform <lb/>any
        propoſed operation with due addreſs; <lb/>or full knowledge of the parts <w part="I"
          >concern-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>: from the want of acceſs to the dead <lb/>human body. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>This alarming conſideration is ſurely of <lb/>ſufficient force to
        conquer the vulgar <lb/>prejudices againſt private diſſection, <w part="I">whe-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ther</w> the offſpring of ſuperſtition or <w part="I">igno-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >rance</w>. The violation of the ſepulchre or <lb/>the clandeſtine robbery of the tomb,
        <lb/>is moſt juſtly regarded as a crime of a <lb/>deep dye; but certainly private <w
          part="I">diſſecti-</w><lb/><w part="F">on</w>, under proper regulations, is <w part="I"
          >compa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tible</w> with the moſt abſolute ſecurity in <lb/>this
        reſpect. Of this the practice of <lb/>moſt of the European countries is an <w part="I"
          >ir-</w><lb/><w part="F">refragable</w> proof; <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> of theſe
        countries <lb/>to which our ſtudents are compelled to <pb xml:id="page_17" n="20"
        /><lb/>reſort, to obtain opportunities of <w part="I">diffec-</w><lb/><w part="F">ting</w>
        which might ſo eaſily be afforded at <lb/>home. Were a proportional number of <lb/>dead
        human bodies annually furniſhed <lb/>by authority, to the medical Students in <lb/>the
        different towns of Scotland in <w part="I">gene-</w><lb/><w part="F">ral</w>, and to thoſe
        attending our <w part="I">Univerſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ties</w>, in particular, for private
        diſſection: <lb/>the ſalutary conſequences would ſoon <lb/>ſurpaſs conception. It is truly
          <w part="I">aſtoniſh-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>, that a matter of ſuch endleſs <w
          part="I">impor-</w><lb/><w part="F">tance</w> had not, long e'er now, challenged <lb/>the
        notice, and rouſed the attention of <lb/>the <hi rend="sc">Honourable Superintendants</hi>
        <lb/>of our Police, or even of the <hi rend="sc"><w part="I">Legisla-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ture</w></hi> itſelf. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Criminal</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
          >Flagitious,</hi> whether <lb/>they expire under the hands of the <w part="I"
          >exe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cutioner</w>, or by diſeaſe; ought always to <lb/>be conſigned
        to the anatomical knife: <lb/>that thus, in ſome degree, when dead, <lb/>they may attone to
        ſociety for their <w part="I">de-</w>
        <pb xml:id="page_18" n="21"/><lb/><w part="F">predation</w> and turbulence when alive.
        <lb/>Public utility ſeems likewiſe to have a <lb/>good title to the uſe of the dead <w
          part="I">bo-</w><lb/><w part="F">dies</w> of thoſe who by idleneſs and <w part="I"
          >diſſipa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, have rendered themſelves objects of <lb/>public
        charity; and conſequently, <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">haps</w> for many years,
        have been cloathed <lb/>and fed at the public expence. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Humanity, Patriotiſm, and even ſelf-<lb/>intereſt conſpire, to ſtimulate
        every <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">dividual</w> to promote, at leaſt, not to <w
          part="I">op-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſe</w> the eſtabliſhment of a meaſure ſo <lb/>pregnant
        with the moſt ſolid advantages <lb/>to mankind. The advancing liberality <lb/>of this
        country, affords the ſtrongeſt <w part="I">rea-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſons</w> to hope that
        the auſpicious <hi rend="italic">Æra</hi> is <lb/>not very diſtant, when medical <w part="I"
          >improve-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w> ſhall be no more retarded by the <lb/>impoſſibility
        of acquiring anatomical <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">formation</w> in the only way
        that it can <lb/>be acquired; a miſchief hitherto ſo <w part="I">op-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >probrious</w>, fatal, and gigantic. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_19" n="22"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>If Anatomy be defective, <hi rend="sc">Phisiology</hi>
        <lb/>which teaches the functions of the <w part="I">va-</w><lb/><w part="F">rious</w> organs
        and parts detected by <w part="I">ana-</w><lb/><w part="F">tomy</w>, muſt neceſſarily be
        proportionally <lb/>defective. Not only is this the fact, but <lb/>the uſes even of many
        parts which the <lb/>anatomiſt has deſcribed with tolerable <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">curacy</w>, are far, very far, from being <w part="I">ſuf-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ficiently</w> explained by the phiſiologiſt; <lb/><hi rend="italic">e. g.</hi> Of ſeveral
        of the <hi rend="sc">generative <lb/> Organs</hi>, of the <hi rend="sc">different</hi>
        <hi rend="sc"><w part="I">Sub-</w><lb/><w part="F">stances</w></hi> and <hi rend="sc"
          >Protuberances</hi> of the <lb/><hi rend="sc">Brain</hi>, of the <hi rend="sc"
          >Ganglions</hi>, &amp;c. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>In like manner, many of the <w part="I">gene-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ral</w> laws and principles of the living <w part="I">ſyſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">tem</w>
        are not illuſtrated with ſatisfactory <lb/>preciſion; while one phyſiologiſt affirms
        <lb/>that <hi rend="sc">Menstruation</hi> depends on <hi rend="sc"><w part="I"
            >to-</w><lb/><w part="F">pical</w></hi>, another refers it to <hi rend="sc">general
          <lb/>Plethora</hi>. Some contend that <hi rend="sc"><w part="I">Nutri-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tion</w></hi> is effected by the <hi rend="sc">Nerves</hi>, others <lb/>by the <hi
          rend="sc">Vessels</hi>: and a variety of facts <pb xml:id="page_20" n="23"/><lb/>are
        artfully adduced, to eſtabliſh theſe <lb/>oppoſite doctrines. With reſpect to <lb/>many
        other phyſiological diſquiſitions the <lb/>ſame contrariety of opinion exiſts. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>If the queſtion be put, "What ſhall be <lb/>ſaid when Doctors diſagree?"
        I reply, <lb/>recur to nature, collect uſeful facts, from <lb/>them draw manly, liberal,
        chaſte <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">cluſions</w>; diſregard ideal, cobweb, flimſy
        <lb/>theories, the baſeleſs fabric of a viſion. <lb/><hi rend="sc">General Principles</hi>,
        rationally <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">duced</w> as corrollaries from eſtabliſhed
        <lb/>facts, only, in my opinion, can juſtly <lb/>claim the dignified appellation of <hi
          rend="sc"><w part="I">Theo-</w><lb/><w part="F">ry</w></hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Pathology</hi>, you know, treats of the <lb/><hi rend="sc"
          >morbid States</hi> of animal nature, with <lb/>a view to effect their <hi rend="sc"
          >Prevention, <w part="I">Al-</w><lb/><w part="F">leviation</w></hi> or <hi rend="sc"
          >Cure</hi>. Many anatomical <lb/>and phyſiological ſpeculations are more <lb/>curious than
        uſeful, and may, therefore, <lb/>altho' not ſtrictly juſt, have the merit <pb
          xml:id="page_21" n="24"/><lb/>of being innocent. Pathological <w part="I"
          >diſqui-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſitions</w>, on the contrary, muſt always <w part="I"
          >pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duce</w> the moſt ſerious conſequences; <w part="I"
          >be-</w><lb/><w part="F">cauſe</w> they influence the medical conduct <lb/>of diſeaſe. Our
        ſmall knowledge, or <lb/>rather our great ignorance, of this <w part="I">depart-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ment</w>, affords but a melancholy theme to <lb/>the anxious philoſophic
        inquirer. The <w part="I">va-</w><lb/><w part="F">riety</w> and oppoſition, the abſurdity
        and <lb/>confuſion of numberleſs futile conceits, <lb/>wild imaginations, fanciful opinions,
          <w part="I">dig-</w><lb/><w part="F">nified</w> forſooth with the name of <hi rend="sc"><w
            part="I">Doct-</w><lb/><w part="F">rines</w></hi>, are the <hi rend="italic"
          >opprobrium</hi> of the <w part="I">medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cal</w> profeſſion: and
        preſent to the <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">templative</w> mind, the idea of
        primæval <lb/><hi rend="italic">Chaos,</hi> when darkneſs brooded over the <lb/>great abyſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Altho' I poſſeſſed ability, neither your <lb/>time nor patience permit
        me to attempt <lb/>a particular enumeration of the ſtriking <lb/>abſurdities, which have, in
        a great <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">gree</w>, hitherto overwhelmed pathology, <pb
          xml:id="page_22" n="25"/><lb/>depreſſing medicine far beneath the <lb/>rank of her ſiſter
        arts; becauſe theſe <lb/>arts are eſtabliſhed in the evolved <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">alterable</w> laws of nature. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>One claſs of pathologiſts have recourſe <lb/>to the <hi rend="sc"
          >sensible qualities</hi> of the <hi rend="sc"><w part="I">At-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >mosphere</w></hi>, as chiefly contributing to <lb/>create the numerous and important
        tribe <lb/>of febrile diſorders; and endeavour to <lb/>ſupport their reaſonings by <w
          part="I">meteorologi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cal</w> regiſters and obſervations without
        <lb/>end. With equal confidence, another <lb/>tribe, diſregarding in a great meaſure, this
        <lb/>opinion, muſter up <hi rend="sc">invisible <w part="I">miaſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >mata</w></hi> and <hi rend="sc">floating Poisons</hi>, to untie <lb/>every gordian
        knot; either as principal <lb/>agents, or complete efficients. In like <lb/>manner, while
        the favourite ſyſtem of one <lb/>period, refers us, with much plauſibility, <lb/>to the <hi
          rend="sc">Fluids</hi>, and <hi rend="sc">morbific matter</hi>
        <lb/>there exiſting, for the <hi rend="sc">Seat</hi> and <hi rend="sc">Causes</hi><lb/>of
        many diſeaſes; that of another, with <pb xml:id="page_23" n="26"/><lb/>at leaſt equal
        probability, directs our <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tention</w> almoſt ſolely to
          <hi rend="sc">spasm</hi> and other <lb/><hi rend="sc">affections</hi> of the <hi rend="sc"
          >Solids</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I cannot avoid here to remark, that <lb/>were the ſcience of medicine
        like <w part="I">fluxi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ons</w>, infiniteſimals, the quadrature of the
        <lb/>circle, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c. i. e.</hi> purely a matter of <lb/>curious
        unintereſting ſpeculation; we <lb/>might view the <hi rend="sc">fluctuating <w part="I"
            >insta-</w><lb/><w part="F">bility</w></hi> of its <hi rend="sc">Dogmata</hi> or <hi
          rend="sc">Doctrines</hi>, <lb/>as they are called; with the ſame Tone of <lb/>mind with
        which we contemplate the <lb/>fantaſtic ſhiftings of the <hi rend="italic">aurora
          borealis,</hi>
        <lb/>or viſions of the night. But how <w part="I">diame-</w><lb/><w part="F">trically</w>
        oppoſite muſt be the feelings of <lb/>humanity, reflecting that theſe ſucceſſive
        <lb/>doctrines have reſpectively, during their <lb/>faſhionable periods of domination,
        greatly <lb/>influenced the medical management of <lb/>diſeaſe; compelling the paſſive <w
          part="I">entramel-</w><lb/><w part="F">led</w>, bewildered practitioner, to employ
        <lb/>the moſt oppoſite curative means, in the <pb xml:id="page_24" n="27"/><lb/>ſame morbid
        ſtates: the conſequent <w part="I">ha-</w><lb/><w part="F">vock</w>, devaſtation, and
        maſſacre of <w part="I">man-</w><lb/><w part="F">kind</w> is more eaſily imagined than <w
          part="I">deſcri-</w><lb/><w part="F">bed</w>. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The ancient maxim <q rend="italic">in medio <w part="I"
            >tutiſſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">mus</w> ibis, </q> ſhould perhaps never be <w part="I"
          >en-</w><lb/><w part="F">tirely</w> neglected. It ſeems exceedingly <lb/>probable <hi
          rend="italic">a priori,</hi> that, the fluids being <lb/>made or elaborated by the ſolids;
        and <lb/>theſe, on the other hand, ſupported by <lb/>the fluids; their affections will not
        long <lb/>remain diſtinct, but rather always be <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ciprocal</w>: However, <lb/><hi rend="italic"><q rend="quotes">Non noſtrum tantas
            componere lites.</q></hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Moreover, how little we do know with <lb/>tolerable certainty,
        reſpecting the <hi rend="sc"><w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F">pressions</w></hi> made on
        the <hi rend="sc">sentient parts</hi>
        <lb/>of our bodies, by what are named the <lb/><hi rend="italic">potentiae nocentes;</hi> or
        of the <hi rend="sc"><w part="I">derange-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w>
        </hi>of <hi rend="sc">Organization</hi>; or of the <lb/><hi rend="sc">Number</hi> and <hi
          rend="sc">Nature</hi> of the <hi rend="sc">morbid <lb/>alterations</hi> thence conſequent!
        yet <pb xml:id="page_25" n="28"/><lb/>it ſeems abſolutely neceſſary that theſe
        <lb/>particulars be marked with the utmoſt <lb/>poſſible preciſion. For inſtance, we are
        <lb/>told, that there are two <hi rend="italic">ſpecies</hi> of <hi rend="sc"><w part="I"
            >fe-</w><lb/><w part="F">brile</w> delirium</hi>, requiring the moſt oppoſite
        <lb/>treatment; but who has <w part="I">hither-</w><lb/><w part="F">to</w> pointed out, with
        ſufficient accuracy, <lb/>the ſymptoms aſcertaining their important <lb/>diſcrimination? If,
        therefore, in ſuch <lb/>a perilous predicament the <hi rend="sc">Genius</hi> of <lb/>blunder
        ſhould but for a moment <w part="I">over-</w><lb/><w part="F">cloud</w> the practitioner's
        diſcernment, <lb/>which is a very ſuppoſable, but I hope, <lb/>a rare occurence; <hi
          rend="italic">conclamatum eſt.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>'Till pathology, therefore, is more <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >termined</w> and complete, don't caſes beſet <lb/>with dubiety and peril, ſeem juſtly to
          <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">mand</w> a ſuſpenſion of hoſtilities (ſo to
        <lb/>ſpeak) or of our therapeutic efforts; <lb/>which, permit me to ſay, may often with
        <lb/>juſtice be termed the impertinence of <lb/>art? Theſe daring practitioners, who in <pb
          xml:id="page_26" n="29"/><lb/>the advanced critical febrile ſtates, which <lb/>they by no
        means underſtand, exhibit <lb/><hi rend="sc">febrifuge nostrums</hi>,<note place="bottom"
          n="*">* Such as James's Powders. </note> with a <w part="I">teme-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >rity</w> that equally ſhocks our feelings, and <lb/>alarms our fears; may not ineptly be
        <lb/>compared to the nonplus'd ſtateſman; <lb/>who, to ſmother diſſention and broil, of
        <lb/>which his mal-adminiſtration is probably <lb/>the cauſe, risks the very exiſtence of
        the <lb/>ſtate itſelf, by plunging it headlong into <lb/>general combuſtion, and foreign
        war. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is with much pleaſure I <w part="I">acknow-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ledge</w>, that, in this moſt eſſential <w part="I">depart-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w>
        of the medical philoſophy, light <lb/>and order happily begin to diffuſe their <lb/>genial
        influence over darkneſs and <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">fuſion</w>. The <hi
          rend="sc">genius</hi> and <hi rend="sc">labours</hi>
        <lb/>of ſome whom this Society can reckon <lb/>among her honorary ſons, have <w part="I"
          >al-</w><lb/><w part="F">ready</w> contributed, in no ſmall degree, <pb xml:id="page_27"
          n="30"/><lb/>to this moſt deſirable purpoſe. I am <lb/>confident I ſpeak your ſentiments,
        and <lb/>moſt aſſuredly my own, when I mention <lb/>with the moſt particular gratitude, the
        <lb/>great advantages we have ſo often and <lb/>ſo happily reaped in our inquiries, from
        <lb/>the <hi rend="sc">Cullenian Nosology</hi>: a work <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſpicuous</w> tho' conciſe, elaborate yet not <lb/>voluminous, in every part demonſtrative
        <lb/>of the liberal views, and extenſive <w part="I">medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cal</w>
        erudition of its very reſpectable and <lb/>accompliſhed author, who with truth <lb/>may ſay,
          <lb/><hi rend="italic"><q rend="quotes">Exegi monumentum aere perennius.</q>
        </hi></p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Suppoſing juſt indications of cure to <lb/>be formed, in conſequence of
        an <w part="I">advan-</w><lb/><w part="F">ced</w> and chaſte pathology, to be then
        <lb/>provided with proper and active <hi rend="sc">Agents</hi>
        <lb/>or <hi rend="sc">Remedies</hi> to fulfil theſe indications; <lb/>becomes a matter of
        moſt important <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">cern</w>. The jarring opinions of
        authors <pb xml:id="page_28" n="31"/><lb/>reſpecting the nature, activity, doſe and
        <lb/>mode of exhibition, of almoſt every <w part="I">ar-</w><lb/><w part="F">ticle</w> of
        the <hi rend="sc">Materia Medica</hi>; preſent <lb/>a moſt extenſive field for uſeful <w
          part="I">experi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w> and inveſtigation. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>With reſpect to medical improvement, <lb/>I ſhall only in general add,
        that, your <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">pectations</w>, in my opinion, are leſs
        likely <lb/>to be fruſtrated, if you look for it to <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſult</w> more from anatomical phyſiological <lb/>and pathological progreſs, than from the
        <lb/>diſcovery of any addition to the Materia <lb/>Medica. This part of the medical <w
          part="I">ſci-</w><lb/><w part="F">ence</w> is by no means to be neglected, altho' <lb/>it
        be probable, that advancing but a ſingle <lb/>ſtep in any of the other walks, may be
        <lb/>productive of more real and ſolid <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F">provement</w> and
        utility, than the <w part="I">acquiſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of a thouſand ſimples;
        if it be true, <lb/>that it is an eaſier buſineſs to fulfil, than <lb/>inſtitute proper
        curative indications. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_29" n="32"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Be aſſured that the <hi rend="sc">Physician</hi> towers <lb/>above the
          <hi rend="italic">Empiric,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">nurſe</hi> and <hi rend="italic">old
          wo-<lb/>man</hi> almoſt only in proportion to his <w part="I">ſu-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >perior</w> information reſpecting the <hi rend="sc">parts</hi>, <lb/>the <hi rend="sc"
          >laws</hi>, and <hi rend="sc">morbid states</hi> of <w part="I">ani-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >mal</w> nature; the more perfect his <w part="I">acquire-</w><lb/><w part="F">ments</w>
        in theſe particulars, the higher his <lb/>pre-eminence among the ſons of <w part="I"
          >Aeſcu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lapius</w>. No mode of inauguration <w part="I"
          >how-</w><lb/><w part="F">ever</w> ſolemn, no academic rites or <w part="I"
          >autho-</w><lb/><w part="F">rity</w> however great or antient, can elevate <lb/>to the
        honourable rank of Phyſician, a <lb/>perſon of an oppoſite deſcription. Such a <lb/>one
        could only be regarded as an <hi rend="sc">empty <lb/>dignified form</hi>, around whoſe
        blighting <lb/>temples, the <hi rend="sc">venal</hi>, the <hi rend="sc">surreptitious</hi>,
        <lb/>the <hi rend="sc">prostituted laurels</hi> of <hi rend="sc"><w part="I"
            >Apol-</w><lb/><w part="F">lo</w></hi> muſt baſely fade to the utter diſcredit <lb/>of
        all concerned; a more melancholy <lb/>conſequence ſtill would be, that his <w part="I"
          >prac-</w><lb/><w part="F">tice</w> could not fail to prove the bane of <w part="I"
          >ſo-</w><lb/><w part="F">ciety</w>, operating the deſtruction of ſuch <w part="I"
          >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">dividuals</w>
        <pb xml:id="page_30" n="33"/><lb/>as might become the <w part="I">unfortu-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">nate</w> ſubjects of his temerity. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>If therefore to become a Phyſician, <lb/>(<hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi>
        to be qualified to mark with <w part="I">preci-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſion</w>, the almoſt
        infinitely various <w part="I">affec-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w> of animated matter, ſo
        as to direct, <lb/>as far as may be, its movements to the <lb/>bliſſful abode of longaevity
        and health,) <lb/>be a task only terminating with life, <lb/>to be exhauſted by no labour,
        and to <lb/>which the moſt diſcriminating mental <lb/>powers are not ſuperior; the folly,
        not <lb/>to ſay criminality of attempts<note place="bottom" n="*">* Such as thoſe of <hi
            rend="sc">Tissot</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </note> to incite <lb/>vulgar vanity to tamper with the moſt <lb/>precious intereſts of
        mankind, needs <lb/>no illuſtration. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>In every ſpecies of philoſophical <w part="I">inveſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tigation</w>, particularly thoſe of a medical <lb/>nature, where certainty is ſo
        difficultly <lb/>attained; to guard againſt <hi rend="sc">credulity</hi>, <lb/>is a counſel,
        I deem of ſuch infinite <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F">portance</w>, that, before I put
        an end to this <pb xml:id="page_31" n="34"/><lb/>addreſs, I cannot help tendering it in the
        <lb/>moſt earneſt manner to the particular <w part="I">no-</w><lb/><w part="F">tice</w> of
        my <hi rend="sc">younger Socii</hi>. In all <lb/>caſes, where there is not abſolute <w
          part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">monſtration</w>, or at leaſt as high a degree <lb/>of
        evidence, as the nature of the <w part="I">argu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w> admits; to
        ſuſpend belief or to <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">erciſe</w> a proper degree of
        ſcepticiſm, till <lb/>mature examination and reflection ſhall <lb/>compel aſſent: I regard
        as a meaſure <w part="I">pru-</w><lb/><w part="F">dent</w>, rational and philoſophic. The <w
          part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſupported</w>
        <hi rend="italic">ipſe dixit</hi> of any man, however <lb/>great his name in ſcience, I
        always <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſider</w> as a very weak argument: <w part="I"
          >Recan-</w><lb/><w part="F">tation</w> at beſt is exceedingly diſagreeable. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The conſtitution of our Society, or its <lb/>preſent ſyſtem of laws, I
        am far from <lb/>reckoning perfect; many meliorations, I <lb/>doubt not will be made from
        time to <lb/>time. No good reaſon can be aſſigned <lb/>why our meetings ſhould be <w
          part="I">ſuſpend-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> during half the year: In ſummer <w part="I"
          >in-</w>
        <pb xml:id="page_32" n="35"/><lb/><w part="F">deed</w>they might probably be thin; but it
        <lb/>does not follow, that your ſpeculations on <lb/>that account would be leſs inſtructive,
        or <lb/>your eſſays more imperfect. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I conclude by congratulating you <w part="I">up-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >on</w> your affairs being now happily in <lb/>ſuch a proſperous train, as to afford the
        <lb/>moſt flattering proſpects. I contemplate <lb/>the riſing glory, and future greatneſs of
        <lb/>the Medical Society, with no ſmall degree <lb/>of pleaſurable ecſtaſy and expectation:
        <lb/>Methinks, I hear its <hi rend="sc">towering genius</hi>
        <lb/>with the moſt complacent exultation <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">claim</w>
        <q rend="italic">"ſublimi feriam ſidera vertice. "</q>
      </p>
      <trailer rend="align-center"><lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
