<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Smith: An enlarged syllabus of philosophical lectures.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Hugh Smith</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">n enlarged syllabus of philosophical lectures: delivered by Hugh
              Smith ... With the principles on which his conjectures are founded concerning animal
              life, and the laws of the animal oeconomy. These principles are applied not only to
              the general doctrine of the glands, but likewise to some new thoughts on the nervous
              system, the gout, and paralytic complaints.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">N3443</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N3443"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for L. Davis, Holborn; J. Robson, New Bond-Street; J.
                  Dodsley, Pall-Mall; T. Cadell, Strand; G. Kearsly, Fleet-Street; G. Robinson, and
                  T. Evans, Pater-Noster-Row; and Messrs. Richardson and Urquhart, Royal-Exchange.
                  Where also Dr. Smith's other Publications are to be bought,
                  MDCCLXXVIII.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1778</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="9"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="40"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">Harvard University Houghton Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3307406649</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K002208.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="General treatises"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_1"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>PHILOSOPHY OF PHYSIC. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>(PRICE ONE SHILLING AND SIX-PENCE.) </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_3"/>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/><hi rend="size(1)">INTRODUCTORY PREFACE.</hi></head>
        <head type="sub" rend="italic">
          <lb/>To thoſe Gentlemen in particular who honoured <lb/>DR. SMITH by their obliging
          Condeſcenſion <lb/>in attending his Lectures on the Philoſophy <lb/>of Phyſic—and to the
          Public in general. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I SHOULD be much wanting in reſpect, much more ſo <lb/> in gratitude, did I not in
          this addreſs acknowledge the <lb/>pleaſing remembrance of that very candid reception,
          <lb/>with which my noble and truly liberal auditors have been <lb/>pleaſed to honour ſome
          very imperfect endeavours to eſta- <lb/>bliſh the firſt elements of Phyſic. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>CONSCIOUS of the many inaccuracies to be diſcovered throughout the Courſe of my
          Lectures, I have not preſumed <lb/>to ſtile them more than rude preparatory outlines; con-
          <lb/>cluding there was little more to be expected than <hi rend="italic">perhaps</hi> an
          approbation of the deſign; and for this I truſted to the <lb/>known indulgence of liberal
          minds. In theſe expectations <pb xml:id="page_4" n="6"/>
          <lb/>I have been agreeably deceived: — I have been moſt <lb/>kindly ſupported by the
          favour and countenance of men dis- <lb/>tinguiſhed for abilities and learning: which
          emboldens me <lb/>to hope the preſent enlargement of my Syllabus may likewiſe eſcape the
          cenſure of the Public.—In my Introductory Lec- <lb/>ture I mentioned that the deſign had
          been many years in contemplation; but, fearful of my own want of importance, <lb/>awed by
          the formidable appearance of the task, and the al- <lb/>moſt infurmountable difficulties
          attending the promulging <lb/>a new doctrine, with ſuch a degree of ſucceſs as might in-
          <lb/>title it to a fair and candid diſquiſition,—I could not before ſummon the fortitude
          neceſſary to appeal to the Public. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">When</hi> the Lectures were compiled, many doubts remained
          <lb/>concerning the propriety of delivering the Conjectures on <lb/>Animal Life; and had
          it not been for the perſuaſion of <lb/>ſome friends, whoſe judgments I have ever
          reſpected, the <lb/>Conjectures had been ſuppreſſed: they obſerved, and with
          <lb/>propriety, my Lectures would be imperfect, unleſs the Prin- <lb/>ciples were
          communicated on which my own maxims were <lb/>founded. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>To their determination I ſubmitted, not without reluc- <lb/>tance, being fearful of
          the event; leſt I ſhould either have <lb/>been deceived in my reaſonings, or might not be
          able to <lb/>expreſs myſelf, ſo as to be clearly underſtood. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>IT is even now my moſt earneſt deſire, the Principles on <lb/>which the Conjectures
          are founded ſhould be coolly and deli- <lb/>berately enquired into. Many of the opinions
          are undoubt- <lb/>edly <pb xml:id="page_5" n="7"/>
          <lb/>new and ſingular: Truth being the great object of my <lb/>purſuit, I ſhould have
          reaſon to lament the partiality of my <lb/> friends, if I ſuffered myſelf to be prevailed
          on to propagate <lb/>errors, however plauſible they might appear: For theſe rea- <lb/>ſons
          I have withſtood many reſpectable applications to deliver <lb/>another Courſe of Lectures;
          and am determined not to <lb/>repeat them, till the Public have had a fair opportunity of
          <lb/>examining the truth of the Principles, on which thoſe Con- <lb/>jectures are founded,
          that ſupport the practical obſervations delivered in the Lectures. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>IT is well known, that all learned and wiſe men ever re- <lb/>gard new ſyſtems with a
          jealous eye; and their ſo doing is <lb/>to be accounted a mark of wiſdom. I wiſh my
          principles <lb/>to be received with a manly diſtruſt; ſuffer them, however, <lb/>to
          undergo a full and candid examination. I am ſenſible it will require ſome degree of
          attention for gentlemen to <lb/>comprehend the whole of them; eſpecially thoſe who have
          <lb/>not ſeen the experiments, and who are unacquainted with the <lb/>reaſonings by which
          the principles have been ſupported. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>THESE difficulties may perhaps occaſion doubts in the <lb/>minds of ſome medical, and
          other learned men; ſo far it <lb/>muſt be acknowledged they will operate againſt me. I am
          <lb/>content it ſhould be ſo. Poſſibly thoſe doubts may excite <lb/>ſome more able perſons
          to ſearch after the truth; and, as I <lb/>am not wedded to my own opinions, I ſhall moſt
          readily <lb/>join in their condemnation, whenever they are proved to be <lb/>erroneous. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_6" n="8"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> enlargement of my Syllabus will, I apprehend, <lb/>prove
          acceptable to many of thoſe Gentlemen who honoured <lb/> my Lectures by their preſence;
          ſome of them indeeed have <lb/>applied to me on this ſubject. The Public at large, per-
          <lb/>haps, may be pleaſed with having an opportunity of know- <lb/>ing the principles; and
          generous minds ever ſhew favour to <lb/>an attempt, however poorly executed, that has for
          its ob- <lb/>jects the information and happineſs of mankind. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">Shall</hi> beg leave to repeat what was delivered in one of <lb/>my
          Lectures— </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>
          <q rend="quotes">I <hi rend="sc">Love</hi> the profeſſion of phyſic. I honour able medical
            <lb/>practitioners. I wiſh to convince mankind of the benefits <lb/>that may be derived
            from a practice of phyſic founded on <lb/>liberal and rational principles. I have uſed
            my beſt en- <lb/>deavours to convey clear and adequate ideas concerning <lb/>animal
            life, and the laws of the animal oeconomy; with <lb/>a full hope and firm perſuaſion,
            that thereby the practice <lb/>of phyſic may be rendered more univerſally beneficial;
            <lb/>and with a ſincere deſire that farther dignity may be <lb/>added to the profeſſion.
          </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Whether</hi> my maxims be true or falſe, permit me to add, <lb/>if I
          cannot, by a generous and candid behaviour on my own <lb/> part, ſuppreſs the envy and
          jealouſy of illiberal minds,—I <lb/>can pity and forgive ſuch men. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is my earneſt deſire to promote medical knowledge; <lb/>to
          render the philoſophy of phyſic, an eaſy, pleaſing, and <pb xml:id="page_7" n="9"/>
          <lb/>rational ſtudy; and to point out to gentlemen of fortune <lb/>the propriety of their
          becoming acquainted with the firſt <lb/>elements of a ſcience—founded in the knowledge of
          the <lb/>Laws of Nature, reſpecting animal life. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">most</hi> ſincerely wiſh my fellow labourers, in the healing
          <lb/>art, may with unanimity join me in this undertaking—let us <lb/>endeavour to convince
          mankind it is their intereſt, on all <lb/>occaſions, to apply to able medical
          practitioners—more eſpe- <lb/>cially in that claſs of complaints termed <hi rend="italic"
            >Chronic,</hi> which is at <lb/>preſent the great field of quackery. </p>
        <dateline><hi rend="italic">Hatton-ſtreet,</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 16, 1778. </dateline>
        <signed>
          <lb/>HUGH SMITH. </signed>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_8" n="11"/>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/><hi rend="size(1)">TO THE</hi>
          <lb/>
          <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">R E A D E R. </hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> following is the Syllabus firſt publiſhed, <lb/>in which no
          mention is made of the Conjectures to <lb/>be delivered after the Lectures, concerning the
          firſt <lb/>material cauſe of animal life, and the laws of the animal <lb/>oeconomy. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">If</hi> it be asked, why this part of the deſign was not taken
          <lb/>notice of?—I refer my reader to the doubts already ex- <lb/>preſſed in the
          Introductory Preface.—I was likewiſe fearful <lb/>this attempt might be treated as
          altogether chimerical—and <pb xml:id="page_9" n="12"/>
          <lb/>did not care to run the risk of premature ridicule; well <lb/>knowing that, <hi
            rend="italic">ſometimes,</hi> where ſolid objections are not ad- <lb/>vanced, private
          whiſpers, and ironical buffoonery, may <lb/>create inſuperable prejudices againſt a man
          who dares to <lb/>venture out of the beaten paths of Science. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_10" n="13"/>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A horizontal double-line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A horizontal double-line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <head rend="align-center space">
        <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">PHILOSOPHICAL LECTURES </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">on the </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="sc size(1.5) space">PRACTICE of PHYSIC: </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5) space">By <hi rend="italic">HUGH SMITH</hi>, M. D. </hi>
        <lb/>Of <hi rend="sc">Hatton-Street, London</hi>. </head>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HESE Lectures are intended to render the Practice <lb/>of Phyſic
        a liberal ſcience; as derived from the <lb/>known and eſtabliſhed laws of Natural
        Philoſophy— <lb/>to open a new theory, adapted to practice, and correſpon- <lb/>dent to
        thoſe laws. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">No</hi> perſon, it is believed, on this plan, has ever yet at-
        <lb/>tempted to bring the rudiments of the ſcience of Medicine, <lb/>into one general and
        compendious point of view. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_11" n="14"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> the execution of the plan, <hi rend="italic">poſſibly</hi> ſome
        practical rules <lb/>may ariſe, ſupported on eſtabliſhed principles, tending to <lb/>the
        improvement of the ſcience <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* This alludes to matters of fact evident to the ſenſes ſet forth in the Fourth
              <lb/>Lecture—<hi rend="sc">on NUTRITION</hi>. </p>
        </note>. By a chain of rational <lb/>and philoſophical reaſoning it is deſigned to call
        forth that <lb/>knowledge obtained by detached ſtudies; and to apply it to <lb/>the great
        end and purpoſe for which thoſe ſtudies were inſti- <lb/>tuted. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Men</hi> are often poſſeſſed of powers and talents, to which <lb/>they
        themſelves, in ſome degree, are ſtrangers—and great <lb/>abilities are often buried in
        oblivion, for want of right rules <lb/>in practice. The truth of this obſervation many
        medical <lb/>men have the mortification to experience; and on this ac- <lb/>count <hi
          rend="italic">only</hi> perhaps they paſs their lives in obſcurity; and <lb/>their
        knowledge is loſt to the world. <hi rend="italic">The preſent Lectures, <lb/>therefore, are
          particularly recommended to medical ſtudents.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">To</hi> men of letters human nature is acknowledged to be an
        <lb/>agreeable object of contemplation. Can it be leſs entertaining <lb/>to any man of good
        natural underſtanding? The knowledge <lb/>of <hi rend="sc">nature</hi> is not <hi
          rend="italic">ſurely</hi> above the reach of common ſenſe — <lb/>Conſidered liberally, and
        freed from all unneceſſary terms of <lb/>art, it will be found a pleaſing ſcience. Theſe
        Lectures, <lb/>probably, may throw a new light on the ſubject; by open- <lb/>ing to familiar
        view the firſt ſprings of life; <note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† The reader may now perceive this paſſage alludes to the Conjectures on
            <lb/>Animal Life. </p>
        </note> the cauſes of <pb xml:id="page_12" n="15"/>
        <lb/>man's gradual riſe; neceſſary decay; and the cauſes likewiſe <lb/>of the diſeaſes to
        which he is liable. Is not every human <lb/>being intereſted in this inquiry? How many men
        <lb/>have been rendered miſerable by dipping into medical <lb/>authors, for want of a
        conſiſtent view of the leading prin- <lb/>ciples of the ſcience? In theſe Lectures, though
        on medical <lb/>ſubjects, every thing myſterious being removed, <hi rend="italic">man</hi>
        properly <lb/>becomes the object of rational, or philoſophical contempla- <lb/>tion.—It is
        to be hoped, likewiſe, the practice of phyſic may <lb/>be rendered more univerſally
        beneficial, and <hi rend="italic">poſſibly</hi> freſh <lb/>dignity may be added to the
        profeſſion. </p>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="3"> </space>
      <div>
        <head rend="size(1.5) align-center">
          <lb/>SYLLABUS. </head>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">First Lecture</hi>—Introductory.—The Importance of the <lb/>Deſign—not
          confined to men of the profeſſion—but of <lb/>utility to all gentlemen of liberal
          education—the propriety of <lb/>their becoming acquainted with the elements of the ſcience
          <lb/>of Medicine enforced. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Second Lecture</hi>—Hiſtorical,—but <hi rend="italic">principally</hi>
          in regard <lb/>to the Practice of Phyſic.—It is not only uſual, but uſeful <lb/>and
          entertaining, to trace the origin of whatever engages our <lb/>inquiry. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Third Lecture</hi>—On Animal Life.—It is impoſſible to <lb/>eſtabliſh
          the Practice of Phyſic, on liberal and rational prin- <pb xml:id="page_13" n="16"/>
          <lb/>ciples, without clear and fixed ideas concerning Animal Life <lb/>—the great deſign
          of the art being to aſſiſt Nature, in order <lb/>to preſerve the lives of Animals. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Fourth Lecture</hi>—On Nutrition.—The deſign of this <lb/>Lecture is to
          inquire into the mode of Nutrition, as it is <lb/>performed in animal bodies—to point out
          certain facts, as <lb/><hi rend="italic">data</hi>, to prove that Nutrition is univerſally
          carried on, in <lb/>animal bodies, by the glandular ſyſtem. <note place="bottom" n="*"
            rend="size(0.5)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* For an explanation of the word Gland, ſee page 19. </p>
          </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Fifth Lecture</hi>—The ſubject of Nutrition continued.— <lb/>This
          doctrine, though perhaps allowed, in <hi rend="italic">part</hi>, by many <lb/>able
          practitioners, has never yet been proved in the <hi rend="italic">whole</hi>— <lb/>its
          novelty <hi rend="italic">therefore</hi> might induce ſome to diſpute the truth of
          <lb/>it, if the matter of fact reſted <hi rend="italic">only</hi> on a ſingle perſon's
          prac- <lb/>tical diſcoveries; or on a few ſimple facts, <hi rend="italic">however
            evident</hi> to <lb/>the ſenſes.—We ſhall therefore confirm this doctrine by phy-
          <lb/>ſiological reſearches, and mathematical reaſonings founded on <lb/>the eſtabliſhed
            <hi rend="italic">data</hi> contained in the Fourth Lecture. <note place="bottom" n="†"
            rend="size(0.5)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>† I do not wiſh to be underſtood, nor do I mean, ſtrict mathematical demon-
              <lb/>ſtration, for that can admit of no doubt; but a cloſe method of reaſoning, in
              <lb/>imitation of that uſed by mathematicians; which, in ſubjects not ſtrictly mathe-
              <lb/>matical, never amounts to more than the higheſt degree of probability. </p>
          </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Sixth Lecture</hi>—A continuation of the ſame ſubject.— <lb/>No proof
          ought to be withheld, that can rationally be ad- <lb/>vanced, in ſupport of principles in
          themſelves important, but <lb/>not generally eſtabliſhed.—We ſhall therefore, by
          mechanical <pb xml:id="page_14" n="17"/>
          <lb/>reaſoning, farther confirm this doctrine of Nutrition being <lb/>univerſally carried
          on by the glandular ſyſtem. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Seventh Lecture</hi>—On Diſeaſes.—Here we mean to <lb/>prove, agreeable
          to the principles before-mentioned, from <lb/>practical experience, that the primary
          errors in animal <lb/>bodies, which may juſtly be ſtyled the <hi rend="italic">internal,
            incipient</hi>, <lb/>cauſes of diſeaſes, are, <hi rend="italic">univerſally</hi>, ſeated
          in the glandular <lb/>ſyſtem.—This, if well ſupported, muſt neceſſarily eſtabliſh <lb/>our
          doctrine concerning Nutrition beyond the poſſibility of <lb/>doubt.—It muſt likewiſe be
          productive of new theories in <lb/>many caſes; and alter the preſent mode of practice,
          with <lb/>regard to the curative intentions, in various diſeaſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Eighth Lecture</hi>—How a Phyſician differs from a <lb/>Quack.—Having
          in the former Lecture eſtabliſhed fixed <lb/>principles, as a ſolid foundation for a
          liberal and rational <lb/>practice of Phyſic, the preſent philoſophic inquiry ſeems
          <lb/>properly to take place. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Ninth Lecture</hi>—Will ſet forth the ſuperiority of a ra- <lb/>tional
          Practice of Phyſic over empiriciſm and quackery. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Tenth Lecture</hi>—Acute and Chronic Diſeaſes diſtin- <lb/>guiſhed.—In
          this Lecture we ſhall take the liberty of drawing <lb/>the line of diſtinction, in ſome
          meaſure different from that <lb/>already given by medical writers; but <hi rend="italic"
            >perhaps</hi> neceſſary to <lb/>eſtabliſh the Practice of Phyſic, on liberal and
          rational <lb/>principles—which regularly leads to— </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_15" n="18"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Eleventh Lecture</hi>—An inquiry into the cauſes of <lb/>Quackery. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Twelfth and last Lecture</hi>—Contains ſome rules, that <lb/>we humbly
          conceive will be found uſeful; eſpecially, to <lb/>younger practitioners, in their conduct
          towards patients, <lb/>both in acute and chronic diſeaſes; in order to obtain their
          <lb/>rational confidence, and to convince them of the benefits <lb/>that may be derived
          from a Practice of Phyſic, founded on <lb/>liberal and rational principles. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <pb xml:id="page_16" n="19"/>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="3"> </space>
        <head rend="sc align-center">
          <lb/>DESCRIPTION <lb/><hi rend="space">of a </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0) space">GLAND. </hi>
        </head>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HAT no confuſion may ariſe in our ideas, and with a <lb/>view
          to be clearly underſtood by every one into <lb/>whoſe hands this Syllabus may fall, it
          will not be improper <lb/>to ſubjoin an explanation of the word <hi rend="sc">Gland</hi>,
          as it is applied <lb/>in the Lectures. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">All</hi> medical writers agree in this point, that a <hi rend="sc"
            >Gland</hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſerves to ſeparate a particular humour from the blood</hi>. <hi
            rend="sc">Glands</hi>
          <lb/>are diſtinguiſhed, by anatomiſts, into ſimple and compound; <lb/>accurate
          deſcriptions have been given of many that are <lb/>viſible, and new <hi rend="sc"
            >Glands</hi> are continually diſcovered. It <lb/>concerns not our preſent purpoſe to
          inquire into their <lb/>ſtructures: Different <hi rend="sc">Glands</hi> are evidently
          appointed for <lb/>different uſes—Whether, therefore, they be ſimple or com- <lb/>pound;
          or whether they be any thing more than the ulti- <lb/>mate terminations of ſingle
          arteries, convoluted, or not; <pb xml:id="page_17" n="20"/>
          <lb/>every part of the animal œconomy muſt be allowed to be a <lb/><hi rend="sc"
            >Gland</hi>, whoſe office it is to <hi rend="italic">ſeparate</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >percolate</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">drain</hi> a <lb/>particular humour from the
          blood; which humour, when <lb/>thus ſeparated, is no longer blood. </p>
        <p rend="italic indent space">
          <lb/>In ſtrict conformity to Phyſiology, this Deſcription eſtabliſhes <lb/>a clear and
          adequate idea to be conveyed by the word <hi rend="sc">Gland</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <pb xml:id="page_18" n="21"/>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <head rend="sc align-center">
          <lb/><hi rend="size(1.25)">SOME ACCOUNT </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="space">of the </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5) space">CONJECTURES </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="space">on </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5) space">ANIMAL LIFE, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
          </hi>
        </head>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HROUGHOUT the courſe of our Lectures, we <lb/>endeavoured from
          effects to lead to cauſes—and <lb/>thereby to account for Nutrition—and the primary cauſes
          of <lb/>Diſeaſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Our</hi> Conjectures concerning the firſt active material cauſe <lb/>of
          Animal Life, and the laws of the Animal Oeconomy, <lb/>for obvious reaſons, were totally
          detached from the Lec- <lb/>tures—on theſe points, we endeavoured to trace effects from
          <lb/>cauſes; and, by arguments founded on experimental proofs, <lb/>we hope at leaſt to
          have ſtrengthened ſome of the opinions <lb/>delivered in our Lectures; though perhaps we
          have not <lb/>been able fully to eſtabliſh any point contended for. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_19" n="22"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is neceſſary, however, to be remarked, that nothing <lb/>new is
          meant to be advanced concerning the properties of <lb/>air, nor is it intended to enter
          into its properties at large— <lb/>the application of its properties to Animal Life, is
          all we <lb/>aim at: Some Conjectures are offered, that ſeem to ſhew the <lb/>probability
          of air, put into motion by heat, being not only <lb/>the firſt active material cauſe of
          new life, but the actual <lb/>ſupport of life, throughout every different ſtage of our
          <lb/>animated exiſtence. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">These</hi> Conjectures, if admitted, ſhew the Moſaic account <lb/>of
          the creation of man to be philoſophically true— <q rend="diple quotes italic">that
            <lb/>the Lord God formed man of the duſt of the ground, and <lb/>breathed into his
            noſtrils the breath of life, and man became <lb/>a living ſoul, </q> (Gen. ch. ii. v.
          7.)—and that the laws of <lb/>generation are the means appointed by our Creator to pre-
          <lb/>ſerve this active operative cauſe of life, ſo given: For the <lb/>Conjectures ſeem to
          evince what we term <hi rend="sc">vital air</hi>, to be <lb/>the firſt cauſe of motion,
          not only in man, but throughout <lb/>the whole animated creation. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Our</hi> leading aphoriſm runs thus— </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In all Animals, Life, Heat, and Motion, are <lb/>Inseparable</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">We</hi> maintained the truth of this aphoriſm, not only by <lb/>death
          and its conſequences, but likewiſe by life and its <lb/>effects: It ſeems alſo to be
          farther illuſtrated by the follow- <lb/>ing Principles—from which many other important
          con- <lb/>cluſions have been drawn. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <pb xml:id="page_20" n="23"/>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="3"> </space>
        <head rend="sc align-center">
          <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">PRINCIPLES </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="space">on which the </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5) space">CONJECTURES </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="space">ARE FOUNDED. </hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="italic hanging">
          <lb/>Each Night, before the Lecture, a variety of Experiments <lb/>were exhibited, to
          demonſtrate the Truth of the following <lb/>Principles: many of which will not be denied
          by ſcientific <lb/>Men; and where it ſeems neceſſary, the others are attempted <lb/>to be
          explained. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>I. </label>
        <p n="1">
          <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">A</hi>IR is matter. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>II. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="2">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Matter</hi> is of itſelf inactive, but capable of being put <lb/>into
          motion. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_21" n="24"/>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>III. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="3">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Air</hi>, as matter, is capable of different arrangements,
          <lb/>modifications, and combinations, in obedience to the ge- <lb/>neral laws of matter. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>IV. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="4">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Air</hi> is a fluid—but has properties peculiar to itſelf, and
          <lb/>different from other fluids;—for, </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>V. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="5">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Air</hi> is an elaſtic fluid, and the force of its ſpring is pro-
          <lb/>portionable to its weight. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>VI. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="6">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Air</hi> poſſeſſes the property of rarefaction, or expanſion. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>VII. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="7">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Heat</hi>—by which we mean a ſimilar effect to that pro- <lb/>duced by
          fire, will rarefy or expand air. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_22" n="25"/>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>VIII. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="8">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Air</hi> poſſeſſes the property of compreſſion, or condenſation. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>IX. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="9">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">External</hi> preſſure will condenſe, or compreſs air. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>X. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="10">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Cold</hi> will condenſe, or compreſs air. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XI. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="11">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Air</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">then</hi> is rarefied by heat, and compreſſed by cold. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XII. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="12">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Air</hi> exiſts in all bodies, fluid and ſolid. </p>
        <p rend="italic indent space">
          <lb/>This, perhaps, will not be doubted by ſuch as are acquainted <lb/>with experiments on
          air—for the ſatisfaction of others, the <lb/>truth of the Principle was proved by
          experiments on gold, <lb/>ſilver, copper, braſs, lead, marble, various other ſtones, wood,
          <lb/>&amp;c. Air viſibly iſſued from them all; more from ſome, than <lb/>from others, in
          proportion to their poroſity—the poroſity of <pb xml:id="page_23" n="26"/>
          <lb/>wood, ſtone and metals, by help of a microſcope, may be curi- <lb/>ouſly diſplayed to
          the eye. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XIII. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="13">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">When</hi> bodies are deprived of internal heat and motion, <lb/>the air
          contained within them may be ſaid to be at a ſtate of <lb/>reſt; it being then only
          ſubject to the variations of the <lb/>atmoſphere. </p>
        <p rend="italic indent space">
          <lb/>This may be proved by the Thermometer. The following curious <lb/>experiment farther
          illuſtrates the matter of fact, and may <lb/>lead to other diſcoveries: Let the bulb of a
          Thermometer be <lb/>put into two ounces of cold water; the air, apparently at reſt <lb/>in
          the quickſilver, by the effect of cold being more compreſſed, <lb/>the mercury will
          quickly deſcend ſeveral degrees; when the <lb/>quickſilver is again apparently at reſt,
          let thirty drops of oil <lb/>of vitriol be put into the water; this produces heat, and the
          <lb/>air contained in the quickſilver will as quickly be expanded; by <lb/>the effect of
          this internal heat communicated to the fluid, the <lb/>quickſilver will riſe two or three
          degrees: Let a little chalk be <lb/>now added to the fluid, the internal heat will be
          farther in- <lb/>creaſed, and the quickſilver will aſcend two or three degrees <lb/>more.
          — Does not this experiment likewiſe ſhew that heat accompanies internal motion in fluids?
          — This obſervation, <lb/>perhaps, may not prove unworthy the attention of ſuch Gentle-
          <lb/>men as entertain themſelves with experiments on what is termed <lb/><hi rend="roman"
            >fixed air</hi>. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_24" n="27"/>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XIV. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="14">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">On</hi> the application of heat to a fluid, the firſt evident <lb/>ſign
          of internal motion is an air-bubble. </p>
        <p rend="italic indent space">
          <lb/>This is experimentally ſhewn, by putting any tranſparent liquor <lb/>into a ſpoon,
          and placing it over a candle, or a lamp; in dif- <lb/>ferent fluids, different appearances
          may be obſerved, not un- <lb/>worthy the attention of the curious. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XV. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="15">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> this ſtate of the fluid the air contained in it is more
          <lb/>rarefied, and expanded, than in the cold ſtate of the fluid. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XVI. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="16">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> air contained in moſt fluids becomes ſo far rarefied as
          <lb/>to be put into motion by a degree of heat below that of the <lb/>blood; we may then
          fairly conclude, from the degree of <lb/>heat accompanying animal life, that the air
          contained in the <lb/>fluids of an animal body is continually in motion. </p>
        <p rend="italic indent space">
          <lb/>This was confirmed by a variety of experiments (oleaginous <lb/>fluids excepted) by
          placing the fluids over a lamp, and regu- <lb/>lating the heat by a Thermometer. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_25" n="28"/>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XVII. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="17">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> tunic, or coat of every diſtinct air-bubble, is evi-
          <lb/>dently formed of the ſurrounding fluid. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XVIII. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="18">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Each</hi> diſtinct bubble of air has a diſtinct and ſeparate
          <lb/>motion. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XIX. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="19">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> different fluids, different degrees of heat are required
          <lb/>to render theſe air-bubbles viſibly active. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XX. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="20">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> the more thin and tranſparent fluids, air-bubbles are
          <lb/>ſooner viſible; and the air becomes fugitive below the de- <lb/>gree of blood heat. </p>
        <p rend="italic indent space">
          <lb/>Water acidulated with ſpirit of vitriol, or diſtilled vinegar, <lb/>becomes more
          tranſparent, and will prove the truth of this <lb/>Principle; it may likewiſe be ſhewn by
          many of the white <lb/>wines, and other fluids. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_26" n="29"/>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XXI. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="21">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">These</hi> bubbles of air, being ſpecifically lighter than the
          <lb/>ſurrounding fluid, naturally tend to the ſurface; and there, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >ſoon burſting</hi>, this rarefied air eſcapes, and mixes with the <lb/>common
          atmoſphere, unleſs it be prevented by proper reci- <lb/>pients. </p>
        <p rend="italic indent space">
          <lb/>Since the preſſure of the atmoſphere is the ſame on all fluids, <lb/>how happens it
          that in ſome the air-bubbles are longer detained <lb/>than in others? </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XXII. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="22">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Different</hi> fluids poſſeſs different degrees of tenacity or
          <lb/>coheſion: this tenacity is weaker in thin tranſparent fluids. <lb/>—<hi rend="italic"
            >Air-bubbles, therefore, become ſooner fugitive in ſuch fluids</hi>. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XXIII. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="23">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Glue</hi>, gum, or ſugar, ſuſpended in fluids, render them <lb/>more
          tenacious, or coheſive.—<hi rend="sc">Air-bubbles therefore are longer restrained from
            becoming fugitive in such <lb/>fluids</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="italic indent space">
          <lb/>If our conjectures prove right, this obſervation may afford <lb/>a clew to examine
          into the laws of life in the vegetable king- <lb/>dom.—This idea is thrown out for the
          conſideration of ingenious <lb/>men; the ſubject itſelf, at preſent, not being within our
          ſphere. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_27" n="30"/>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XXIV. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="24">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">External</hi> heat being removed from a fluid, although the
          <lb/>preſſure of the cold atmoſphere be freely admitted; it is, <lb/>nevertheleſs, a
          conſiderable time before the air, rarefied by <lb/>heat, returns to a ſtate of reſt. </p>
        <p rend="italic indent space">
          <lb/>The truth of this principle may be illuſtrated by a ſpoon, in <lb/>the manner before
          mentioned; <hi rend="roman">(Principle XIV.)</hi> and it is worthy <lb/>attention. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XXV. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="25">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Earthy</hi> particles may be ſuſpended in a tranſparent fluid. </p>
        <p rend="italic indent space">
          <lb/>The proceſs for making magneſia alba proves this—it is no <lb/>contemptible
          experiment, though in familiar practice. </p>
        <p rend="italic indent space">
          <lb/>Two tranſparent liquors being mixed, they inſtantly loſe both <lb/>their tranſparency
          and fluidity, and become one intire white in- <lb/>ſpiſſated ſubſtance—this being
          repeatedly waſhed with water, <lb/>the white earth, when dried, is the common magneſia
          alba of the <lb/>ſhops. </p>
        <p rend="italic indent space">
          <lb/>It is well known this white earth was originally ſuſpended in <lb/>an aqueous
          menſtruum, by means of the vitriolic acid; and in <lb/>this proceſs, it is precipitated by
          the fixed alkaline. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_28" n="31"/>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XXVI. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="26">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Earthy</hi> particles may float in air. </p>
        <p rend="italic indent space">
          <lb/>If any one doubts the truth of this, let him admit a ray of <lb/>light into a
          darkened room, and he will be convinced of the <lb/>matter of fact. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XXVII. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="27">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Air</hi> does exiſt in the circulating fluids of an animal. </p>
        <p rend="italic indent space">
          <lb/>This was proved by the blood-veſſel of a bullock, being <lb/>ſecured by ligatures,
          before it was ſeparated from the body of <lb/>the living animal—it was farther confirmed
          by live cray- <lb/>fiſh, tench, &amp;c. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XXVIII. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="28">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Air</hi> does exiſt in the medullary ſubſtance of the brain. </p>
        <p rend="italic indent space">
          <lb/>This is one of the moſt beautiful experiments that can be <lb/>exhibited by the
          air-pump—if it be well ſhewn, the reſiſtance <lb/>of the medullary and cortical ſubſtance
          of the brain is ſo <lb/>great, as to produce a kind of perpetual motion. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XXIX. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="29">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Air-bubbles</hi>, though ſpecifically lighter than the ſur-
          <lb/>rounding fluid, cannot eſcape till the reſiſtance ariſing from <lb/>the coheſion of
          the parts of the ſurrounding fluid itſelf be <lb/>overcome. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_29" n="32"/>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XXX. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="30">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> reſiſtance, ariſing from the coheſion of the parts of
          <lb/>the fluid, is proportioned to the different degrees of tenacity <lb/>proper to
          different fluids; as before ſhewn. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XXXI. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="31">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> coheſive property in fluids, <hi rend="italic">then</hi>, is
          the bond that <lb/>reſtrains the air from becoming fugitive; or, in other words, <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">it is the bond of union</hi>. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XXXII. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="32">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">animal</hi> jelly, or gluten, expoſed to the common atmo- <lb/>ſphere,
          and ſurrounding a globule of air, is ſufficiently co- <lb/>heſive to prevent this moving
          air eſcaping in a degree of <lb/>heat ſomewhat ſuperior to that of blood heat. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XXXIII. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="33">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> being highly neceſſary to fix ſome ſtandard to regulate
          <lb/>our inquiries—Air rarefied, in motion, detained in animal <lb/>bodies by glandular
          ſecretions, or circulating with the fluids <lb/>in the vaſcular ſyſtem, permit us to call
            <hi rend="sc">Vital Air</hi>. </p>
        <label rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>XXXIV. </label>
        <p rend="indent" n="34">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Vital</hi> Air, Heat, and Motion, then, appear to be inſe-
          <lb/>parable, in animal life. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_30" n="33"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">On</hi> theſe principles our arguments are founded, concern- <lb/>ing
          the firſt active material cauſe of animal life; and from <lb/>theſe principles our
          conjectures are drawn, concerning the <lb/>laws of generation, and thoſe of the animal
          œconomy. For <lb/>the ſatisfaction of the learned, and curious, it will not be
          <lb/>improper to add a few words concerning <hi rend="sc">Vital Air</hi>, which we
          <lb/>preſume to be the firſt <hi rend="italic">material</hi> cauſe of motion in animal
          life. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> conjecture we have endeavoured to ſupport by argu- <lb/>ments
          drawn from experiments; all tending to ſhew the ra- <lb/>tional probability of air
          exiſting in an active and circulating <lb/>ſtate in animal bodies. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> will be remembered, we proved air did actually exiſt in
          <lb/>the blood of a living animal; and likewiſe in the medullary <lb/>ſubſtance of the
          brain. We alſo proved, that in the degree <lb/>of heat proper to animal life, this air
          muſt be in a rarefied <lb/>and active ſtate; and we farther endeavoured to ſhew, by
          <lb/>arguments drawn from an incubated egg, and other points, <lb/>the rational
          probability, that the propelling force of air, thus <lb/>rarefied, and confined in a
          vaſcular ſyſtem, was the firſt ma- <lb/>terial cauſe of the circulation of the blood, and
          other fluids, <lb/>in an animal body. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> reaction of the vaſcular ſyſtem we preſume to be the
          <lb/>ſecondary cauſe, in conjunction with the former, producing <lb/>what is termed <hi
            rend="italic">involuntary muſcular motion</hi>—this motion, in <lb/>the beginning of new
          life, is firſt diſcoverable at the <hi rend="italic">punctum <lb/>ſaliens</hi>, or leaping
          point; which afterwards becomes the <lb/>heart of the fœtus. The heart we have preſumed to
          ſtile <pb xml:id="page_31" n="34"/>
          <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">centre of motion</hi>; by which the circulation of the blood is
          <lb/>regulated and maintained. The blood we conſider to be a <lb/>paſſive fluid, the
          common menſtruum from whence nutrition <lb/>is derived, by means of the glands.—We preſume
          that ſome <lb/>one order or more of the glands muſt be injured, debilitated, <lb/>or
          totally obſtructed, before the blood of an animal becomes <lb/>impure. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">By</hi> the propelling force of <hi rend="sc">Vital Air</hi> we preſume
          all <lb/>glandular ſecretions to be performed, and the lymphatic cir- <lb/>culations to be
          ſupported by the ſame power—and by means <lb/>of the glands we preſume the laws of
          generation to be main- <lb/>tained. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> the beginning of new life, the motion of Vital Air <lb/>ſeems
          to be ſupported by the natural heat of the parent, or by <lb/>ſome adequate external
          means—this appears to be a general <lb/>law, throughout nature, till <hi rend="italic"
            >involuntary muſcular motion</hi> be- <lb/>comes ſufficiently powerful to communicate
          that degree of <lb/>internal heat, peculiarly proper to Vital Air: When this <lb/>period
          arrives, the act of incubation ceaſes, with all oviparous <lb/>animals; the fœtus opening
          to itſelf a paſſage in order to breathe <lb/>the common atmoſphere; and, in viviparous
          animals, the <lb/>natural birth takes place, by the united efforts of the parent <lb/>and
          fœtus. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> may perhaps be expected that ſomething ſhould be ſaid
          <lb/>concerning the brain and nervous ſyſtem.—In this ſummary <lb/>way I cannot hope to
          perſuade ſcientific men to think with <lb/>me—however, by mentioning the points contended
          for, <pb xml:id="page_32" n="35"/>
          <lb/>poſſibly objections will be ſtarted, that eventually may lead <lb/>to the diſcovery
          of truth. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">We</hi> took notice in ſome of our conjectures, that man <lb/>having a
          material body, it was but reaſonable to conclude it <lb/>ſhould anſwer the various
          purpoſes for which it was ſo cu- <lb/>riouſly formed; and that every diſtinct member
          ſhould <lb/>have its deſtined office. We endeavoured to prove that, in <lb/>the buſineſs
          of motion and ſenſation, the nerves, proceeding <lb/>from the brain and ſpinal marrow,
          though the chief, were <lb/>not the only inſtruments; and from numerous experimental
          <lb/>proofs, we concluded that the reaction of the vaſcular <lb/>ſyſtem, voluntary motion,
          and the exerciſe of the external <lb/>ſenſes, could not be ſupported without the aid of
          the ner- <lb/>vous ſyſtem. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> will be recollected we uſed many arguments to ſhew <lb/>the <hi
            rend="italic">proper ſenſe of feeling</hi> ſeemed to ariſe from the due re-
          <lb/>ſiſtance of the medullary ſubſtance of the brain, or nervous <lb/>matter, oppoſed to
          the propelling force of Vital Air. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">We</hi> took occaſion to obſerve, that all the other ſenſes <lb/>were
          obedient to the <hi rend="italic">proper ſenſe of feeling</hi>; and endeavoured <lb/>to
          ſhew that hearing, ſeeing, ſmelling, and taſting, were <lb/>nothing more than the effects
          ariſing from feeling, which <lb/>we conſidered as their primary cauſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">As</hi> we have, under certain limitations, acknowledged the
          <lb/>nervous ſyſtem to be the ſeat of feeling, we inquired into <lb/>the effects produced
          by any conſiderable variation in the <pb xml:id="page_33" n="36"/>
          <lb/>Vital Air, peculiarly exiſting in the nervous matter—and <lb/>having before ſhewn the
          rational probability of <hi rend="italic">pain</hi> ariſing <lb/>from the propelling force
          of too highly rarefied air, we <lb/>ſeemed to be warranted in drawing the following
          conclu- <lb/>ſions:—The ſenſe of feeling is ſeated in the nervous ſyſtem— <lb/>the ſenſe
          of feeling becoming too exquiſite produces pain <lb/>—the nervous ſyſtem is <hi
            rend="italic">then</hi> the ſeat of pain.—Gouty <lb/>ſymptoms, therefore, whether fixed
          or wandering, being <lb/>ever accompanied with that too exquiſite degree of ſenſibi-
          <lb/>lity, that either produces unhappy ſenſations, or acute <lb/>pain, we preſume the
          nervous ſyſtem to be principally <lb/>affected in gouty patients. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">We</hi> endeavoured to ſtrengthen, and ſupport our conjectures
          <lb/>concerning gouty, and what are termed nervous complaints, <lb/>not only from
          practical experience; but likewiſe by ſhewing <lb/>that a partial, or total loſs of motion
          and feeling, in para- <lb/>lytic complaints and nervous apoplexies, probably ariſes
          <lb/>from an oppoſite cauſe—namely, from the propelling force <lb/>of Vital Air exiſting
          in the nervous matter, or in the me- <lb/>dullary ſubſtance of the brain, being too much
          abated; or <lb/>from its becoming a body at reſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">These</hi> are ſome of the practical inferences, ariſing from <lb/>our
          conjectures, concerning the brain and nervous ſyſtem: <lb/>happy ſhall I think myſelf if
          they prove any way inſtru- <lb/>mental towards alleviating the diſtreſſes of mankind. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">With</hi> regard to the ſentient principle, or ſpirit of man, <lb/>we
          obſerved, that although ſimple ideas might be ſtirred up <pb xml:id="page_34" n="37"/>
          <lb/>in the mind by the mediation of the nervous ſyſtem; yet, <lb/><hi rend="italic">our
            ideas are not matter</hi>: ſomething more than a material <lb/>ſyſtem, therefore, ſeems
          neceſſary and requiſite to thinking. <lb/>And if <hi rend="sc">Vital Air</hi> be the firſt
          material cauſe of motion, the <lb/>vaſcular ſyſtem can be conſidered only as the ſecondary
          <lb/>cauſe:—Is it not highly improbable, then, that the ſentient <lb/>principle ſhould
          depend on this ſecondary cauſe, <hi rend="italic">namely</hi>, on <lb/>a ſyſtem of
          organized matter?—Be this as it may, it is out <lb/>of my province to enter into
          metaphyſical controverſies; and, <lb/>as obſerved in my Lectures, I am unequal to the
          taſk: How- <lb/>ever, that the ſentient principle is not material, we verily <lb/>believe,
          and endeavoured to confirm by many other argu- <lb/>ments;—and if the mind be not
          material, experimental <lb/>reſearches after this <hi rend="italic">immaterial
            principle</hi> muſt ever prove <lb/>in vain. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">We</hi> ventured to add, that if there be a connection be- <lb/>tween
          groſs material, and immaterial ſubſtances, it is pro- <lb/>bably effected by ſome <hi
            rend="italic">rare medium</hi>; and therefore, that <lb/>this union was not unlikely to
          be formed by means of <hi rend="sc">Vital <lb/>Air</hi>. Whether our general arguments on
          this point were <lb/>forcible or not, muſt be left to the determination of others; <lb/>we
          however concluded this ſubject in the following manner. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">We</hi> have endeavoured to ſhew that life depends on <hi rend="sc"
            >Vital <lb/>Air</hi>; and that not only motion, but all the external ſenſes <lb/>depend
          on it likewiſe—and if ſo, it ſeems a fair concluſion, <lb/>that the nervous fluid, or
          animal ſpirits, is nothing more <lb/>than <hi rend="sc">Vital Air</hi>. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_35" n="38"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">I am</hi> compelled, from my practical experience in the <lb/>gout, in
          paralytic complaints, and other errors in the ner- <lb/>vous ſyſtem, to believe this—and
          from what has been ad- <lb/>vanced, am I not authoriſed to conclude, the Moſaic accounts
          <lb/>of the creation of man, and of the laws of generation, are <lb/>philoſophically true? </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Having</hi> thus ſet forth what may probably be deemed <lb/>ſufficient
          to enable medical and other ſcientific men to <lb/>judge of the rationality of our
          ſyſtem—I leave it to their <lb/>conſideration, whether we mean to captivate the credulous,
          <lb/>or to appeal to men of ſenſe in purſuit of truth. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Such</hi> gentlemen as have honoured me by their attention, <lb/>will
          be enabled, from theſe outlines, to recall many of our <lb/>conjectures concerning animal
          life, and the laws of the ani- <lb/>mal œconomy; which, I flatter myſelf, will afford them
          <lb/>ſome degree of ſatisfaction. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">I do</hi> not expect this ſyſtem, even if it ſhould prove to be
          <lb/>true, to be eſtabliſhed without oppoſition; I am prepared to <lb/>receive all
          objections that may be advanced, whether it be <lb/>in my power to anſwer them or not—I am
          prepared to re- <lb/>ceive them, let me repeat, becauſe I wiſh the principles to <lb/>paſs
          through the ſtricteſt ſcrutiny. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">If</hi> the principles be admitted, it is preſumed the rationa-
          <lb/>lity of the conjectures, on animal life, will add no little degree <lb/>of weight to
          the doctrines contended for in the courſe of our <lb/>Lectures; <hi rend="italic"
            >namely</hi>, that nutrition is carried on by means of <pb xml:id="page_36" n="39"/>
          <lb/>the glandular ſyſtem; and that the internal, incipient cauſes <lb/>of diſeaſes are
            <hi rend="italic">univerſally</hi> ſeated in the glands. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is proper, <hi rend="italic">however</hi>, to obſerve, whether
          the principles <lb/>be admitted, and our conjectures allowed, or not; it does <lb/>not
          follow, that our practical inferences, reſpecting diſeaſes, <lb/>originally drawn from
          matters of fact evident to the ſenſes, <lb/>are to be conſidered as altogether
          erroneous.—All that I aſk, <lb/>is, to be judged with candour; and moſt chearfully ſubmit
          <lb/>to the determination of intelligent men. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">I am</hi> fully perſuaded, thoſe gentlemen who did me the <lb/>honour
          of attending my Lectures, will not heſitate to ſay, <lb/>that my opinions were delivered
          with diffidence; it was my <lb/>earneſt deſire to perſuade; but well knowing the ſcanty
          <lb/>limits of human underſtanding, I believe no man can chal- <lb/>lenge me with having
          advanced any one conjecture as a po- <lb/>ſitive aſſertion: Yet, <hi rend="italic"
            >this</hi> I did ſay, at the concluſion of <lb/>my Lectures— </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>
          <q rend="diple quotes">As a duty incumbent on me, I have, in this public <lb/>manner,
            communicated my thoughts to liberal and learned <lb/>men; that the world at large,
            however they may differ <lb/>in opinion, might not charge me with having reſerved my
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">principles</hi> as <hi rend="sc">secrets</hi>: But having
            entered into ſo very <lb/>wide a field, I am certain, you, gentlemen, would not
            <lb/>wiſh me too haſtily to commit to the preſs, the preſent <lb/>crude and imperfect
            ideas, on ſubjects of ſuch import- <lb/>ance.—If the principles on which our opinions
            are founded, can be fairly overturned, by arguments drawn from expe- <pb
              xml:id="page_37" n="40"/>
            <lb/>riments—<hi rend="italic">let them fall</hi>.—If not, I truſt more able advo-
            <lb/>cates than myſelf will not be wanting, to ſupport the <lb/>truth of our doctrines;
            and to enlarge the bounds of our <lb/>knowledge, with regard to the theory, and cure of
            <lb/>diſeaſes. </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <trailer rend="align-center space">
        <lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
