<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: A dissertation upon the nervous system to show its
          influence upon the soul.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">A dissertation upon the nervous system to show its influence upon the
              soul. ...</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T53796</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T53796"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Published September, 1780.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1780</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="2"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="64"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3321111719</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K048330.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="General treatises"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_1"/>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <figure>
          <q>MY TRUST IS IN GOD </q>
          <figDesc>an angel ſtanding atop the upper half of a globe beneath a banner </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A Diſſertation upon the Nervous <lb/>Syſtem to ſhow its Influence u- <lb/>pon the
          Soul. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Man can know little, and yet he <lb/>wants to know all things, He is con- <lb/>fined
          to a point of time in this life, <lb/>yet extends his Views backwards <lb/>&amp; forwards,
          through Millions of <lb/>Ages, till he is loſt in eternity. He is <lb/>confined to ſome
          minute part of this <lb/>Globe; yet while his feet ſtand on it, his <lb/>Soul is
          travelling through the whole <lb/>planetary Syſtem, traverſing the <lb/>immenſity of
          Space, till he is at laſt loſt in Infinity. </p>
        <p rend="italic">Publiſhed September 1780. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_3"/>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>An ornamented horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <head rend="align-center space">
        <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5) space">DISSERTATION </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="sc space">on the </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(1.25) space">NERVOUS SYSTEM, &amp;c. </hi>
      </head>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A long horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <div n="1" type="section">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>SECTION I. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">B</hi>EFORE we proceed, it will be neceſſary <lb/>to explain, in a
          ſimple manner, the Na- <lb/>ture of thoſe bodily powers, which Conſtitute <lb/>the very
          Principles of Life. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Human Body is ſuſtained and kept a- <lb/>live, by three principal powers, which
          like the <lb/>movements of a Clock or Watch, co-operate <lb/>and aſſiſt each other: The
          firſt is the brain <lb/>and Nervous Syſtem proceeding from it, the <lb/>grand Source of
          all Senſation; The Second, <lb/>is the Heart and Arteries, or blood Veſſels, <lb/>which
          give motion and circulation to the <lb/>Blood; And the Third is the Stomach and
          <lb/>Bowels, which prepare the Aliment and ſup- <lb/>ply Nouriſhment for thoſe, as well as
          all parts <lb/>of the Body. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_4" n="2"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In ſpeaking of Digeſtion it will be remark- <lb/>ed, that the Stomach loſes its power
          when de- <lb/>prived of Nervous Influence; and we ſhould <lb/>here take notice, that the
          Regularity and Vi- <lb/>gour of the Heart's motion, chiefly depend <lb/>on the ſame cauſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As therefore the Brain and Nerves, the <lb/>Heart and Arteries, and the Stomach and
          <lb/>Bowels, are the principal inſtruments of all <lb/>Senſation, Circulation, Nutrition,
          Life and <lb/>Motion, and the very Agents which govern <lb/>and direct the whole Animal
          Machine; It <lb/>will be neceſſarily conſequent, that when any <lb/>of them becomes
          diſconcerted, and put out of <lb/>order, the vital functions of the Body depen- <lb/>ding
          upon them, muſt then be unduly per- <lb/>formed. <q rend="quotes">where one Link's broken,
            the <lb/>whole chain's deſtroyed. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Such is the extraordinary Sympathy and in- <lb/>tercourſe between thoſe ſeveral
          organs, that <lb/>like ſo many little provinces, allied by mutual <lb/>Intereſt, not one
          of them can exerciſe its full <lb/>power without the aſſiſtance and concurrence <lb/>of
          the reſt; for as the Heart and Stomach <lb/>cannot act without the aſſiſtance of the
          Brain, <lb/>or the Stomach Digeſt without receiving a <lb/>due Quantity of blood from the
          Heart; ſo <lb/>neither can the Heart have ſufficient force to <lb/>keep up the
          circulation, without a continual <lb/>ſupply of nouriſhment from the Stomach; <pb
            xml:id="page_5" n="3"/>
          <lb/>or even the Brain itſelf exert its Influence <lb/>over thoſe organs without being
          duly nou- <lb/>riſhed by Both. Although it will evidently <lb/>appear, that the Nerves are
          the Immediate or- <lb/>gans of all vital motion and Senſation, and <lb/>the medium by
          which impreſſions made on <lb/>the Body are inſtantly conveyed to the mind; <lb/>yet the
          preciſe manner by which this miſteri- <lb/>ous intercourſe is carried on, remains a ſec-
          <lb/>ret in nature with which, perhaps, we ſhall <lb/>never be acquainted<choice>
            <corr>.</corr>
            <sic/>
          </choice>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>So intimately connected are the Body and <lb/>Soul, and ſuch their Correſpondence,
          that <lb/>Impreſſions made on the one naturally influ- <lb/>ence the other with the like
          feelings: Thus, <lb/>by immoderate grief the digeſtive faculty of <lb/>the Stomach is
          impaired and taken away, and <lb/>by a blow on the head which injures the <lb/>Brain, the
          Soul is as it were dethroned, and <lb/>loſing its empire over the Body, all ſenſe and
          <lb/>motion are inſtantly deſtroyed. The Soul, <lb/>or Intellect, whilſt confined to the
          Body, <lb/>
          <q rend="quotes">That muddy Veſture of decay, </q> is obliged <lb/>to ſtoop to the ſtate
          and condition of the <lb/>Nerves, whoſe feelings are liable to alteration <lb/>from a
          thouſand accidental or unavoidable <lb/>cauſes, ſo as to occaſion diſeaſes, or being to-
          <lb/>tally aboliſhed, to produce inſtant death. <lb/>Thoſe, as well as many other
          circumſtances, <lb/>concur to prove that the faculties and diſpo- <pb xml:id="page_6"
            n="4"/>
          <lb/>ſition of the mind, in a great meaſure, depend <lb/>on the bodily organs with which
          they co-ope- <lb/>rate, and where thoſe are changed from their <lb/>natural State, ſo are
          its appetites and oper- <lb/>ations. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>How different is the State of the Body and <lb/>Soul when the veſſels are empty or
          full, viz. <lb/>after long faſting, or a plentiful meal, in the <lb/>firſt the pulſe is
          weak and unequal, the Com- <lb/>plexion pale, the Body languid, and the Spi- <lb/>rits
          deſponding: But after eating and the mo- <lb/>derate uſe of wine, the Springs of Life are
          <lb/>wound up, and the Body and Soul are reſtor- <lb/>ed to their native vigour. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The conſent between the Brain and Heart is <lb/>remarkable, for, intenſe Study or
          thinking <lb/>quickens the Pulſe, and a ſudden fright will <lb/>occaſion palpetations or a
          convulſive Struggle <lb/>of the heart, even ſometimes to a mortal ſuf- <lb/>focation: in
          both theſe caſes, the firſt impreſ- <lb/>ſion is made on the Brain, and the Heart,
          <lb/>like a faithfull companion, ſuffers by ſympa- <lb/>thy; but whether the Nerves act as
          Tubes, <lb/>or Vibrating Cords, like the Strings of a mu- <lb/>ſical Inſtrument, or
          whether they ſerve as <lb/>conductors to ſome ſubtle fluid ſimilar to that <lb/>of
          Electric Fire, we are wholly ignorant<choice>
            <corr>.</corr>
            <sic/>
          </choice> The <lb/>Brain ſeems therefore to the Nerves, what <lb/>the Heart is to the
          Blood Veſſels or Arteries; <lb/>for too violent a degree of Action in the laſt, <pb
            xml:id="page_7" n="5"/>
          <lb/>will produce heat and increaſe circulation, as <lb/>may be obſerved after violent
          exerciſe, or in <lb/>the time of a Fever: in like manner, when <lb/>the power of the Brain
          and Nerves is too vio- <lb/>lently impreſſed on the Body or Soul, their <lb/>Senſations
          will be rendered too quick and <lb/>exquiſite; like the motion of a watch, which
          <lb/>becomes rapid and irregular when the main <lb/>ſpring acts too ſtrongly on the
          ſeveral wheels <lb/>and ſubordinate movements. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Impreſſions made on the Soul will often <lb/>totally ſubdue thoſe of the Body: and on
          <lb/>the contrary, ſuch as are made on the Body, <lb/>will remove thoſe of the Soul; all
          which <lb/>may ſupply an Intelligent obſerver with uſe- <lb/>ful hints in the cure of ſuch
          diſeaſes as have <lb/>been unſucceſsfully treated by medicines. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Religious doubts which perplex the Soul <lb/>with alternate Hopes and fears, a
          Sedentary <lb/>life, or warm, damp air, all diſpoſe the con- <lb/>ſtitution to Melancholy,
          by weakning the <lb/>Nervous power. Thoſe are the general cauſes <lb/>of low Spirits, and
          acquired melancholy, <lb/>which always operate moſt powerfully on <lb/>People of nice
          Senſations, whoſe Pleaſures <lb/>and Pains from over-delicacy of the Nervous <lb/>Syſtem,
          are too exquiſite for ſenſe; but the <lb/>preciſe manner in which they produce their
          <lb/>effects, or why ſuch cauſes do not always oc- <lb/>caſion ſimilar conſequences, in
          ſuch a parti- <lb/>cular State of the Nerves, is utterly unknown. <pb xml:id="page_8"
            n="6"/>
          <q rend="diple quotes size(0.75) indentall space">
            <l><lb/>Where Joy moſt revels, Grief doth moſt lament; </l>
            <l><lb/>Grief Joys. Joy grieves, on ſlender accident.</l>
          </q>
          <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"> </space>
          <lb/>Thoſe, on the contrary, of more clumſy or- <lb/>gans, who are poſſeſſed of little
          more than <lb/>Vegetable-feeling, never experience the miſe- <lb/>ry of Nervous Diſorders;
          but if they have <lb/>leſs pleaſure, the account is balanced by their <lb/>enduring leſs
          pain. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>We have already obſerved, that the Body <lb/>and Soul, receive all their information
          by <lb/>means of the Brain and Nerves, and that by <lb/>Thoſe they mutually converſe and
          ſympathize <lb/>with each other; hence it will follow, that <lb/>whenever thoſe Organs are
          Injured, and like <lb/>unfaithful Meſſengers, do not truly execute <lb/>their Office, and
          repreſent things as they are, <lb/>the Patient will then be impoſed upon, by <lb/>Deluſive
          Perception, and figure to herſelf <lb/>things which have no exiſtence, but in her <lb/>own
          diſtempered Brain. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>They ſuppoſe that every one looks upon <lb/>them with a malignant eye, and puts the
          worſt <lb/>conſtruction on what they ſay and do; In <lb/>ſhort, though they are
          induſtrious to torment <lb/>themſelves, by means which appear ludicrous, <lb/>they
          experience ſubſtantial miſery, and are <lb/>ſometimes driven to deſperation, and Suicide;
          <lb/>ſo that in the whole catalogue of earthly evils, <lb/>human Nature cannot preſent an
          object more <lb/>truly pitiable! </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_9" n="7"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>What then ſhall be ſaid of thoſe who either <lb/>from Ambition or the view of gain,
          ſtifle the <lb/>feelings of honour and humanity, and ſordid- <lb/>ly ſubmit to form
          alliances which Entail he- <lb/>reditary miſeries on their poſterity, more grie- <lb/>vous
          than death itſelf! and who, therefore, <lb/>inſtead of remembering the Authors of their
          <lb/>being with filial affection, muſt behold them <lb/>with indignation and ſorrow! </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Retirement and bodily eaſe are not de- <lb/>ſtructive to the melancholy, for whilſt
          they <lb/>ſit ſtill unemployed, they become a prey to <lb/>their own thoughts. On the
          contrary, exer- <lb/>ciſe and ſeverity of Diet, are beneficial; for <lb/>no one can think
          or ſtudy with the ſame at- <lb/>tention, when impreſſed with the diſagreeable
          <lb/>ſenſation of Hunger, or tormented with a ra- <lb/>ging tooth, as when he is perfectly
          at eaſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Since we find that painful ſenſations ap- <lb/>plied to the Body or Mind, often
          deſtroy <lb/>health and occaſion Melancholy; by parity of <lb/>reaſoning it may be
          concluded, that pleaſur- <lb/>able feelings of a contrary nature will bid <lb/>faireſt to
          reſtore it: The chiefeſt of thoſe <lb/>are, Chearful Company, Poetry, Muſic, and
          <lb/>Dramatic entertainments of the Comic kind, <lb/>Frequent exerciſe in the open Fields,
          or <lb/>flower Gardens, the waters of Tunbridge <lb/>or Spa, aſſiſted by that ſovereign
          remedy the <pb xml:id="page_10" n="8"/>
          <lb/>Peruvian Bark, and the uſe of the cold Bath, <lb/>will alſo be found powerfully
          Salutary. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Study of Natural Hiſtory, and em- <lb/>ployment of delineating ſome of its moſt
          beau- <lb/>tiful and minute objects arranged under their <lb/>proper claſſes, as thoſe of
          Birds, Inſects and <lb/>Flowers, will afford very pleaſing and rational <lb/>entertainment
          and aſſiſt in diverting the mind <lb/>from things of a more ſerious nature. Parti-
          <lb/>cular thoughts and reflections of the mind <lb/>are joined with certain conditions of
          the Bo- <lb/>dy; and therefore, our manner of living, in <lb/>a conſiderable Degree,
          changes our manner of <lb/>thinking. Hence by Travelling, the univer- <lb/>ſal benefits of
          Air, Exerciſe and Diet, will at <lb/>once be moſt agreeably obtain'd; all which <lb/>tend
          to ſtrengthen the Conſtitution, and to <lb/>wear out diſagreeable impreſſions made on the
          <lb/>Body or mind by introducing others of a dif- <lb/>ferent nature. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The next Sovereign remedy in diſeaſes of <lb/>the mind is Muſic. Cicero aſſerts it's
          amaz- <lb/>ing power, and Plato Suppoſes the effect of <lb/>harmony on the mind is equal
          to that of air <lb/>on the Body: Its Divine influence is exempli- <lb/>fied by David in
          the Cure of Saul; and the <lb/>Eaſtern Monarch who had conquered the <lb/>world, was
          himſelf Subdued by the Seraphic <lb/>Strains of Timotheus's Harp, which ſo capti-
          <lb/>vated his ear, that he was rouſed into mad- <pb xml:id="page_11" n="9"/>
          <lb/>neſs, or ſoothed into melancholy as the ſounds <lb/>became ſprightly and animated, or
          Solemn <lb/>and Slow. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>So wonderful is the empire of Muſic over <lb/>the mind, as recorded by the antients,
          that <lb/>it leads the ſoldier undaunted to the <q rend="diple quotes">Immi- <lb/>nent
            deadly breach. </q> and alternately ſtops <lb/>the rage of conqueſt by its varied power:
          It <lb/>mitigates bodily pain, ſuſpends the malignant <lb/>force of madneſs and deſpair,
          and lulls the <lb/>Soul into <choice>
            <corr>tranquility</corr>
            <sic>traquility</sic>
          </choice> and peace. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The effect of muſic however will be differ- <lb/>ent according to the ſtile, and
          manner of its <lb/>compoſition, and therefore ſhould be adapted <lb/>to the particular
          ſtate and diſpoſition of the <lb/>mind. The plaintive Tone of ſoft Flutes will <lb/>induce
          a pleaſing languor, and compoſe it when <lb/>tortured with rage or irritated by the more
          <lb/>violent paſſions; and on the Contrary, the <lb/>merry pipe and Tabor will exhilerate,
          and <lb/>raiſe the moping head of melancholy, depreſ- <lb/>ſed by Religious Deſpair,
          Diſapointed Ambi- <lb/>tion, or hopeleſs Love. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Let us appeal to the refined feelings of <lb/>thoſe moſt ſuſceptible of the Divine
          power <lb/>of harmony, to prove its ſovereign influence <lb/>over the mind; that it is the
          true oblivious <lb/>Antidote, the Nepenthe of the Gods, to heal <lb/>a wounded Spirit, to
          exalt the Soul above <lb/>low-thoughted care, and lap it in Elyſium. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_12" n="10"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This great ſenſibility occaſions people of <lb/>Rank to be Victims of their moſt
          favourite <lb/>feelings; all that afflicts or threatens others, <lb/>all the evil incident
          to mankind in general, <lb/>are to them real grievances, affecting them, <lb/>very
          frequently, more than their own private <lb/>complaints, and eſſentially deſtroy their
          health; <lb/>in a word, infinitely more ſenſible of tender <lb/>impreſſions, and expoſed
          to a much greater <lb/>number than the Peaſant, of neceſſity they <lb/>muſt ſuffer much
          more. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Nerves continually agitated by humours <lb/>which are always irritative, by
          diſordering the <lb/>harmony of the Organs, and enfeebling the <lb/>Body, murder the
          mental faculties; which <lb/>are ſo much dependant on the Situation of its
          <lb/>ſurrounding body, that whatever diſorders <lb/>the œconomy of the one, abſolutely
          preju- <lb/>dices the mode of thinking in the other. <q
            rend="diple quotes indentall space size(0.75)">
            <l><lb/>That bright'ning ray, by God himſelf beſtow'd, </l>
            <l><lb/>Blends with our Senſes, and like them grows weak.</l>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Nervous diſorders, that diſpoſition to be <lb/>too eaſily affected and ſuſceptible of
          irregular <lb/>and painful emotions, is one of the moſt cruel <lb/>ſcourges to people of
          rank that has been ad- <lb/>vanced. It moſt commonly occurs, and till <lb/>now, has been
          particularly unhappy in a miſ- <lb/>taken treatment, becauſe its origin had not <pb
            xml:id="page_13" n="11"/>
          <lb/>been ſufficiently inveſtigated: it's different <lb/>Species, which required very
          different reme- <lb/>dies, was left unexamined. This Branch of <lb/>Phyſic is at preſent
          too much confined to <lb/>hypotheſis, the Subject of party diſputes, or <lb/>at leaſt
          influenced by Faſhion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Many Eminent Phyſicians, regarding all <lb/>diſorders of the Nerves as the
          Conſequences <lb/>of relaxed fibres, and weak digeſtions, would <lb/>effect a cure by
          means of remedies which are <lb/>hot, and ſtrengthening, by Gums, Steel, Bit- <lb/>ters,
          Camphire, Caſtor, Muſk, Spirituous <lb/>Tinctures, Opium, &amp;c. which is an error ſi-
          <lb/>milar to the following, in ſpeaking of indi- <lb/>geſtion and Stomachic remedies. In
          attri- <lb/>buting all Nervous complaints to one cauſe, <lb/>they have propoſed but one
          kind of remedy, <lb/>which unhappily has no better ſucceſs than in <lb/>complaints of the
          Stomach. Nerves inflamed <lb/>by the immoderate uſe of Aromatics, are not <lb/>relieved by
          uſing Aſſafœtida; a ſharper Me- <lb/>dicine than the moſt piquant Aromatic: thoſe <lb/>who
          are dried up by the abuſe of Barbadoes <lb/>Water and Maraſquin, will not find aſſiſtance
          <lb/>by drinking great quantities of the Tincture of <lb/>Gentian, of Valerian, or of
          Caſtor; but thoſe <lb/>remedies ſo hurtful, in theſe caſes, are very <lb/>beneficial in
          caſes where a weak fibre, or poor <lb/>and watery Blood are the true cauſes of the
          <lb/>complaint, and ſuch caſes often do occur. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_14" n="12"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>That Tea affects the Nerves of the Stomach <lb/>is evident, by its communicating
          diſagreeable <lb/>Senſations upon the Soul. That the Soul <lb/>becomes affected when the
          digeſtion of the <lb/>Stomach is impaired, is alſo evident, ſo that <lb/>the Soul cannot
          be anſwerable in that caſe, <lb/>for Actions of the Body; for without the <lb/>Nerves are
          braced up to the Standard of the <lb/>Soul, it's ideas are imperfectly connected: <lb/>ſo
          that it is clear, the Nerves operate upon the <lb/>Soul, as the Works of a Clock regulate
          the <lb/>Movement in keeping Time. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>That extreme ſenſibility to all Impreſſions, <lb/>which render many ſo unhappy,
          ſhould be <lb/>treated like diſorders of the Nerves, on which <lb/>it depends, and often
          requires cold Baths, <lb/>Milk diet, much exerciſe, and the courage to <lb/>brave the open
          Air, and thoſe things which <lb/>we moſt dread. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Sometimes the Diſorder only exiſts in the <lb/>Imagination. The vapouriſh perſuade
          them- <lb/>ſelves they are not able to do any thing, when <lb/>they are very ſtrong; they
          fancy every thing <lb/>incommodious which they are very well able <lb/>to bear; they
          deprive themſelves of, and re- <lb/>nounce, all enjoyments, frighten themſelves <lb/>with
          an unexiſting Bugbear, and court a real <lb/>one. Such Caſes require the Phyſicians ut-
          <lb/>moſt penetration: If he is deluded, the Patient <lb/>is loſt; but if he deceives the
          Patient, and gains <pb xml:id="page_15" n="13"/>
          <lb/>his confidence, a Cure is the work of a mi- <lb/>nute. I have ſeen five ſuch Perſons,
          who <lb/>fancied they could neither bear light, noiſe, <lb/>air, or food, keep their Beds
          in a dark and <lb/>matted Chamber, where none were ſuffer'd <lb/>to walk, move, or ſpeak
          out, but with the ut- <lb/>moſt precaution; lived only on Broth and <lb/>Jellies; thought
          themſelves dangerouſly ill, <lb/>ſettled their Affairs, and all this while they <lb/>were
          perfectly well: I compelled them to ſee, <lb/>hear, ſpeak quit their Beds, and even their
          <lb/>Houſe, to eat and act like other People, to <lb/>feel themſelves well, and paſs in
          one quarter <lb/>of an Hour from the greateſt Miſery to the <lb/>greateſt Happineſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>We muſt be perſuaded the Nerves are im- <lb/>mediately affected by the Labours of the
          Soul: <lb/>inactivity is alſo ſufficient to deſtroy them, and <lb/>often produces this
          effect, even in Perſons <lb/>whoſe mind is as indolent as their Body<choice>
            <corr>.</corr>
            <sic/>
          </choice> The <lb/>Nerves are the principal parts of the Machine, <lb/>whenever any of the
          Animal Functions are <lb/>diſturbed, they muſt undoubtedly be injured. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When the Nerves are affected without any <lb/>ſenſible cauſe, one would be led to
          ſuppoſe, <lb/>that ſome diſeaſe would ſoon appear, the <lb/>ſource of which might poſſibly
          be diſcovered <lb/>by attentive obſervation and be the more eaſi- <lb/>ly deſtroyed before
          the diſeaſe had come to <lb/>any height. Some diſorders, (of the Stomach <pb
            xml:id="page_16" n="14"/>
          <lb/>eſpecially) ſhew themſelves more readily by <lb/>the effects they have on the Nerves;
          for they <lb/>being a kind of Medium between the Soul <lb/>and the Body, are expoſed to
          ſuffer from the <lb/>irregularities of each, and communicate to the <lb/>one, the injuries
          they receive from the other: <lb/>thus it is that the Soul becomes prejudicial to <lb/>the
          Body, and the Body hurtful to the Soul, <lb/>and that they are both combined in deſtroy-
          <lb/>ing the Nervous Syſtem. </p>
      </div>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A long horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <div n="2" type="section">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>SECTION II. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">L</hi>ET us now conſider what is to be done <lb/>to obtain a cure in
          Nervous Diſeaſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Firſt then, we are exactly to regulate the <lb/>uſe of non-naturals; For in vain is a
          pre- <lb/>ſcription of medicines, if the Patient is not <lb/>directed and willing to
          obſerve certain regu- <lb/>lations, in relation to Air, diet and Exerciſe. <lb/>Chuſe a
          free open Air, not incumber'd with <lb/>Hills or Woods<choice>
            <corr>.</corr>
            <sic/>
          </choice> A dry cool Air, braces <lb/>and Invigorates the whole Body; while a Hot,
          <lb/>confined, and damp Air, weakens and relaxes <lb/>the Habit. When the Stomach and
          Bowels <lb/>are weak, they ſhould be well guarded againſt <lb/>cold and Damps eſpecially
          in Winter; and <lb/>there is no dreſs better and more neceſſary to <pb xml:id="page_17"
            n="15"/>
          <lb/>keep up a due perſpiration, than Flannels <lb/>worn next the Skin. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Conſtant exerciſe, every day that allows of <lb/>it, either in walking, on
          horſe-back, or in an <lb/>open Chaiſe, is of vaſt ſervice; it ſhould be <lb/>as much as
          the ſtrength will admit, without <lb/>weakneſs, fatigue or hurry; never weary
          <lb/>yourſelf, nor raiſe a Sweat, go no further, <lb/>than you can return with as much
          ſpirit as <lb/>you went out. Exerciſe ſtrengthens the whole <lb/>Nervous Syſtem, aſſiſts
          digeſtion, (but retards <lb/>it after a full meal; therefore after dinner ſit <lb/>a
          while) Sanguification, and the diſtribution <lb/>and ſecretion of all the Animal Fluids.
          By <lb/>muſcular motion, the blood and Juices are <lb/>kept in a due ſtate of Fluidity;
          their Viſcidi- <lb/>dity is broken and diſſolved, and all obſtruc- <lb/>tions either
          prevented or removed. The fleſh <lb/>Bruſh is an excellent thing for ſtrengthening
          <lb/>the Solids; as friction, either with the fleſh <lb/>bruſh, flannel or coarſe Linnen
          Cloth, <lb/>ſtrengthens the Body, promotes the circula- <lb/>tion, and is particularly
          uſeful in weak Bow- <lb/>els. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>People of weak Nerves are generally quick <lb/>thinkers, from the delicacy of their
          ſenſitive <lb/>organs, which we therefore more liable to be <lb/>fatigued and relaxed with
          exerciſe, than thoſe <lb/>of a Coarſer make; whence we ſee the ne- <lb/>ceſſity of keeping
          the mind eaſy, quiet and <pb xml:id="page_18" n="16"/>
          <lb/>chearful, ſince nothing hurts Nervous People <lb/>more, than fear, grief, and
          anxiety. Uſe <lb/>therefore agreeable amuſements, and a little <lb/>ſlight, entertaining
          and diverting reading, <lb/>that requires no thought, for all Study is <lb/>pernicious and
          hurtful. Converſation ſhould <lb/>be agreeable trifling and eaſy, without diſpute <lb/>or
          contradiction; amuſements be Innocent, <lb/>various, and not expenſive: otherways, upon
          <lb/>reflection, the money laid out would do more <lb/>hurt, than the amuſements could
          recompence. <lb/>In a word, all thought and care muſt be laid <lb/>aſide; and rationality
          muſt give place for a <lb/>while, to a way of life, which Bath gives a <lb/>pattern of. I
          cannot but highly approve of <lb/>a practice there, of having muſic, while the
          <lb/>Patients drink the Water; which has a very <lb/>great and good effect upon the motion
          of the <lb/>finer animal Fibres. Muſic has been allow'd, <lb/>in all ages of the world, to
          have a Noble pow- <lb/>er in raiſing the dejected ideas of the Soul. <lb/>Thoſe that have
          the moſt delicate conſtituti- <lb/>ons, are moſt ſenſible of its good effects; it
          <lb/>opens the obſtructions of the fineſt Veſſels; <lb/>aſſuages the paſſions, and at the
          ſame time <lb/>communicates a pleaſure to the Soul, and <lb/>makes its ideas chearful, gay
          and lively; by <lb/>the oſcillatory motion of the Air, vibrating a- <lb/>gainſt the
          tempanum of the ear, there is ſuch <lb/>an impulſive motion given to the fineſt fibres <pb
            xml:id="page_19" n="17"/>
          <lb/>of the Brain, (upon which the Soul more <lb/>immediately diſplays its Faculties) as
          to enable <lb/>them to bring regular impulſes to the ſenſo- <lb/>rium. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But muſic, though it reſtores the Tone of <lb/>the fineſt Fibres of the Brain; yet
          the inferi- <lb/>or organs demand coarſer treatment, to re- <lb/>ſtore them to the
          Standard of health<choice>
            <corr>.</corr>
            <sic/>
          </choice>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>We muſt abridge the Quantity and Quality <lb/>of our food, which ought to be
          nouriſhing, <lb/>eaſy of Digeſtion, and ſuited to the Stomach <lb/>of the Patient. Fat
          meats, and heavy ſauces <lb/>are hurtful; and all exceſs is to be avoided. <lb/>The
          Patient ought never to eat more than <lb/>the Stomach can eaſily digeſt: eat therefore
          <lb/>little at a time, but often, of innocent, plain <lb/>and ſimple meat; for every time
          the ſtomach <lb/>is overloaded, the ſtrength is impaired, and <lb/>its Nerves are
          diſordered. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Above all things, heavy ſuppers ought to <lb/>be avoided; ſince the ſtomach is much
          more <lb/>apt to be oppreſſed with the ſame quantity of <lb/>food, in an horizontal
          poſition, than in any <lb/>erect poſture; and ſince the Digeſton goes on <lb/>Slower in
          time of ſleep than when awake, as <lb/>the veſſels are then much relaxed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is a great bleſſing, that loathing, and <lb/>want of appetite in ſome degree,
          attend all <lb/>diſorders, which prevent many people from <lb/>in fallibly and quickly
          ruining themſelves with- <pb xml:id="page_20" n="18"/>
          <lb/>out reſource. Thoſe who have only a few <lb/>tranſient ſymptoms, and are but in the
          firſt <lb/>ſtage of Nervous Diſeaſes, ſhould live with a <lb/>due degree of temperance
          ſuited to their con- <lb/>ſtitution; and abate a little of the quantity of <lb/>their
          food, while they are more immediately <lb/>under the ſymptoms. Indeed, if the diſorder
          <lb/>is deep, and hath continued ſo long as to pro- <lb/>duce more violent ſymptoms, there
          is a ne- <lb/>ceſſity to be ſtill more careful. Drink ſmall <lb/>Beer, ſoft fine ale, or
          Wine and water; but <lb/>never uſe water alone. Wine in exceſs en- <lb/>feebles the Body,
          and impairs the faculties of <lb/>the Soul; but a few glaſſes of wine, in time <lb/>of
          eating, aſſiſt digeſtion. A Glaſs of wine <lb/>before Dinner, on an empty Stomach, and
          <lb/>when one is Languid, feeble or faint, is of <lb/>great ſervice. Wine in general, is
          preferable <lb/>to Malt Liquor; the beſt Wine is Rheniſh, <lb/>Mountain, or ſmall French
          Wine. When <lb/>the ſtomach and Bowels are troubled with a- <lb/>cidity, water mixed with
          Rum or Brandy, is <lb/>preferable to Wine, or Malt Liquor. That <lb/>too common drink Tea,
          is very hurtful to <lb/>both the ſtomach and Nerves, eſpecially if <lb/>drank hot, with
          little Bread: I would there- <lb/>fore recommend, not the diſuſe, but the <lb/>more
          moderate uſe of Tea: it were, well, if <lb/>ſomething elſe was Joined with it in the morn-
          <lb/>ing; Or inſtead of Tea, which is almoſt con- <pb xml:id="page_21" n="19"/>
          <lb/>ſtantly hurtful to the <choice>
            <corr>Nerves</corr>
            <sic>Neves</sic>
          </choice>, a Tea made of <lb/>Balm and mint, in every diſh of which ſhould <lb/>be put a
          Tea ſpoonful of the Balſamic mix- <lb/>ture of Cream and Yolks of Eggs, with two <lb/>or
          three drops of Oil of Cinnamon; which <lb/>makes an agreeable Beverage, and is highly
          <lb/>grateful to the ſtomach, as I have myſelf had <lb/>occaſion to obſerve. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But of all things, the cold Bath is the <lb/>greateſt ſtrengthener of the Nerves; it
          re- <lb/>moves glandular obſtructions, raiſes the Spi- <lb/>rits, and vivifies and
          ſtrengthens the whole <lb/>Man; for Children, delicate conſtitutions, <lb/>and Women
          liable to miſcarriages, or trou- <lb/>bleſome floodings, nothing can be better. <lb/>Cold
          Bathing, I am perſuaded, is analagous <lb/>to the Bark, which is alſo a very proper Me-
          <lb/>dicine, for it ſtrengthens the Stomach, Muſ- <lb/>cles, Nerves, and even the Soul
          itſelf, and <lb/>enables them to ſupport freſh fatigues. I <lb/>have known ſeveral young
          Perſons throw <lb/>themſelves into the Cold Bath, after being <lb/>wearied and depreſſed
          with Study, who al- <lb/>ways found upon coming out, a peculiar <lb/>ſtrength of mind, and
          a freſh diſpoſition to <lb/>Study. But I ſhall here obſerve, that where <lb/>the Stomach,
          Liver, or other Viſcera are un- <lb/>ſound, the Cold Bath is improper. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>That eminent Phyſician Mr Lewis, ſays, <lb/>
          <q rend="diple quotes">That of all Remedies, whether external or <pb xml:id="page_22"
              n="20"/>
            <lb/>internal, there is none can equal the virtue <lb/>of the Cold Bath:—it cools the
            Body more, <lb/>ſtrengthens the Nerves better, and promotes <lb/>perſpiration more
            effectually than any me- <lb/>dicine taken down the throat can do. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The uſe of Bark and the Cold Bath toge- <lb/>ther is pointed out by the Nature of
          their <lb/>Virtues; they produce the ſame Effects; and <lb/>being combined will cure
          diſorders, which <lb/>every other Remedy would only have en- <lb/>creaſed. Being
          ſtrengthening, ſedative, and <lb/>febrifugal, they reinvigorate, diminiſh the fe-
          <lb/>verous and Nervous heat, and calm the irre- <lb/>gular motions produced by the
          Spaſmodic <lb/>diſpoſition of the Nervous Syſtem; they for- <lb/>tify a weak Stomach, and
          quickly diſſipate <lb/>its attendant pains. They reſtore Appetite, <lb/>they facilitate
          digeſtion and nutrition: they <lb/>promote all the functions, and particularly
          <lb/>perſpiration, which render them ſo efficaci- <lb/>ous in all catarrhous and cutaneous
          diſor- <lb/>ders, in a word, they remove all diſorders <lb/>occaſioned by weakneſs
          provided the Patient <lb/>is not afflicted with indiſſoluble obſtructions,
          <lb/>inflammations, or internal Ulcerous obſceſſes, <lb/>which conditions almoſt
          neceſſarily exclude <lb/>the Cold Bath, but which frequently al- <lb/>low of the Quinquina<choice>
            <corr>.</corr>
            <sic/>
          </choice> From my own <lb/>experience, I can aſſure the Reader, that I <lb/>have my ſelf
          plunged into the Cold Bath, <pb xml:id="page_23" n="21"/>
          <lb/>when I have found my Spirits ſo depreſſed, <lb/>that without the utmoſt exertion of a
          power- <lb/>ful Reſolution, and being as it were ſuperna- <lb/>turaly aſſiſted. I could
          never have attempt- <lb/>ed it. Yet on coming out I have found my <lb/>Nerves ſo Braced,
          and my ſpirits ſo ſtrength- <lb/>ened, that in a manner I viewed an other <lb/>and a
          Spiritual State, with ſuch extacy as <lb/>made me ready and deſirous to enter into it.
          <lb/>I ſhall here too further recite what I once <lb/>met with at Margate in Kent, where
          the late <lb/>King of Britain arrived from Germany, and <lb/>uſed the Cold Bath, and drank
          the Waters <lb/>with great Advantage which is expreſſed, by <lb/>an inſcription on a
          ſtatue erected on purpoſe, <lb/>in this manner. <q rend="quotes size(0.75) indent space">
            <lb/>Thy Baths give Vigour, and thy Waters Health. </q>
          <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"> </space>
          <lb/>For altho' the Water only acts immediately <lb/>on the Cutaneous Nerves and Veſſels,
          yet it's <lb/>ſtrengthening power is, by ſympathy, com- <lb/>municated to the inmoſt parts
          of the Body, <lb/>and mixes radically with the Fluids. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Daily experience convinces us of the power <lb/>of the Soul upon the Stomach. Thoſe
          moſt <lb/>addicted to reflection, perform their Digeſti- <lb/>on with greater difficulty;
          on the contrary, <lb/>thoſe who think little, generally digeſt well. <lb/>We frequently
          ſee Perſons of weak under- <lb/>ſtandings eat and drink very freely, without <pb
            xml:id="page_24" n="22"/>
          <lb/>ſuffering any inconvenience, although they <lb/>lead ſedentary lives, and have not
          remarkably <lb/>ſtrong conſtitutions. On the contrary, how <lb/>many ſenſible Men do we
          ſee, whoſe Digeſtion <lb/>is performed with much pain and difficulty, <lb/>although they
          are of a good habit of Body, <lb/>and uſe ſome exerciſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The connection of the Soul with the Body <lb/>is in fact ſo ſtrong, that it's even
          difficult to <lb/>conceive how one of them ſhould act, and the <lb/>other not be ſenſible,
          in a greater or a leſs <lb/>degree, of that action. The Organs of Senſe <lb/>being put in
          motion, convey the Subject of <lb/>thought to the Mind, by acting on the Fibres <lb/>of
          the Brain; and while the Soul is employ- <lb/>ed in thinking, the parts of the Brain are
          in <lb/>a greater or leſs forcible motion, and in a leſs <lb/>or greater degree of
          tenſion. Theſe Motions <lb/>fatigue the medullary or Nervous portion of <lb/>the Brain;
          and this delicate ſubſtance, after <lb/>a long courſe of Meditation, becomes as much
          <lb/>exhauſted, as a ſtrong Man is after exerciſe. <lb/>Whoever has thought intenſely,
          even once in <lb/>his Life, muſt have experienced this in him- <lb/>ſelf: and there is
          certainly no very Studious <lb/> Man, who has not often felt, on coming out <lb/>of his
          Cloſet, violent pains in his head, at- <lb/>tended with a great degree of heat in this
          part. <lb/>This heat will depend on the proportion of <lb/>wearineſs and inflammatory
          tenſion, which <pb xml:id="page_25" n="23"/>
          <lb/>the medullary ſubſtance has undergone: the <lb/>eyes ſoon become ſenſible of this
          fatigue; and <lb/>if we conſider a Man who is deeply engaged <lb/>in thought, we ſhall ſee
          that the Muſcles of <lb/>his Face are all upon the ſtretch, and ſome- <lb/>times appear
          even convulſed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A great Author has taken notice of the <lb/>Danger of fixing the Attention too
          ſtrongly. <lb/>
          <q rend="diple quotes">When the Action of the Soul is too pow- <lb/>erful, </q>
          ſays he, <q rend="diple quotes">it attacks the Body ſo <lb/>violently, that it
            throws it into a conſuming <lb/>State: if the Soul exerts itſelf in a peculiar
            <lb/>manner, on certain occaſions, the Body is <lb/>made ſenſible of it, and becomes
            heated <lb/>and debilitated. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Another Author of note has obſerved the <lb/>ſame, and ſays; <q rend="diple quotes"
            >The union of the Soul <lb/>with the Body is ſo intimate that they, re- <lb/>ciprocally
            ſhare the good or evil which hap- <lb/>pen to either of them. The Mind or Soul
            <lb/>cannot put forth its powers, when the body <lb/>is tired with immoderate exerciſe:
            and too <lb/>cloſe an application to ſtudy deſtroys the <lb/>Body, by diſſipating the
            Animal ſpirits, <lb/>which are neceſſary to recruit it. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The brain, which is the immediate ſeat of <lb/>theſe emotions, the nerves which ariſe
          from <lb/>it, and the Stomach, which is furniſhed with <lb/>many nerves of an exquiſite
          ſenſation, are the <lb/>parts firſt attacked, and commonly moſt in- <pb xml:id="page_26"
            n="24"/>
          <lb/>jured by the immoderate labour of the mind; <lb/>but if it ſhould continue for any
          length of <lb/>time almoſt all the parts of the body become <lb/>partakers of the injury. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The firſt ſymptoms which indicate a weak- <lb/>neſs of the Nervous Syſtem, are a kind
          of <lb/>puſillanimity we were before ſtrangers to; <lb/>Diffidence, fear, grief, dejection
          and Diſpirit- <lb/>edness: he who was the moſt intrepid man <lb/>now becomes the moſt
          timorous; the ſlighteſt <lb/>undertaking frightens him, the moſt trifling <lb/>unforſeen
          incident makes him tremble; the <lb/>ſlighteſt indiſpoſition appears to him a fatal
          <lb/>diſeaſe; and the idea of Death fills him with <lb/>intolerable horrors. Some Tyrants
          have con- <lb/>demned certain Philoſophers, whom they ha- <lb/>ted, to death, but have
          never been able to <lb/>make them fear it; how much more effectu- <lb/>ally would their
          cruelty have been exerciſed <lb/>if by ſuffering them ſtill to Live, they could <lb/>have
          inſpired them with thoſe fears of Death <lb/>hypochondriacs are tormented with? We ſee
          <lb/>inſtances every day of men of Learning, who <lb/>perceiving the firſt ſigns of this
          diſtemper, <lb/>have been obliged to forſake their favourite <lb/>ſtudies; whoſe Nerves
          being weakened, they <lb/>become incapable of attention; their memory <lb/>fails: their
          Ideas are confuſed; a Senſation of <lb/>heat in the Head, palpitations, a total dejec- <pb
            xml:id="page_27" n="25"/>
          <lb/>tion, and the apprehenſion of death makes <lb/>the pen fall from their hands. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The injury the mind has done the Body <lb/>ſoon recoils upon itſelf; for it has been
          the <lb/>will of the ſupreme Being, that as long as <lb/>theſe two Subſtances continued
          together, the <lb/>labours of the mind ſhould in a certain de- <lb/>gree depend upon the
          health of the Body: <lb/>this truth has been ever acknowledged. An <lb/>Author has
          emphatically declared, that <q rend="diple quotes">the <lb/>props of the Body ſupported
            the Soul, </q>
          <lb/>And that, <q rend="diple quotes">Health increaſes the powers of <lb/>the mind; when
            the body is diſeaſed<unclear>,</unclear> the <lb/>mind is not capable of reflection
            </q><unclear>.</unclear> It is <lb/>not therefore ſurpriſing that the mind ſhould
          <lb/>be weakened, after it has exhauſted the Brain <lb/>and Debilitated the Nerves. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>An Eminent Phyſician who lived long in a <lb/>City where learning is much cultivated,
          ſays, <lb/>That ſtudy begins by impairing the Stomach <lb/>and that if the complaint is
          not relieved, it <lb/>may degenerate into a melancholy. And that <lb/>a vitiated Stomach
          attends Learned People, <lb/>as ſurely as the ſhadow follows the Body. <lb/>That he has
          ſeen Patients who ſuffered for <lb/>this immoderate thirſt of Learning, firſt by a
          <lb/>loſs of appetite, an entire inability of the Di- <lb/>geſting Powers, and a total
          debility which <lb/>enſued; afterwards they have been tormented <pb xml:id="page_28"
            n="26"/>
          <lb/>with ſpaſms, convulſions and at length with <lb/>a total privation of all their
          ſenſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When the Digeſtion is imperfect, the hu- <lb/>mours imbibe a crude quality, which
          renders <lb/>them unfit for their various deſtinations; and <lb/>which particularly
          prevents Nutrition, upon <lb/>which the reparation of all the Powers de- <lb/>pends. To be
          convinced of the general in- <lb/>fluence of the Stomach, it is only neceſſary to
          <lb/>obſerve the State of a Perſon who labours <lb/>under a difficult Digeſtion; the
          Powers are <lb/>loſt in a few minutes, a general uneaſineſs <lb/>makes the weakneſs more
          inſupportable, the <lb/>Organs of Senſe are benumbed, the faculties <lb/>of the Soul are
          exerciſed very imperfectly, the <lb/>Memory, and particularly the Imagination, <lb/>ſeems
          to be annihilated; in a word, nothing <lb/>makes a ſenſible Man ſo much reſemble an
          <lb/>Idiot, as the difficulty of Digeſtion. This <lb/>Obſervation equally points out to
          us, that of <lb/>all Diſorders, there are none which more <lb/>quickly affect the Soul,
          than thoſe of the <lb/>Nervous Syſtem. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>There is one general precaution, which is, <lb/>to refrain from all Liquors in great
          quanti- <lb/>ties; they weaken Digeſtion, by relaxing the <lb/>Stomach, drowning the
          degeſtive Juices, and <lb/>by precipitating the Aliments before they are <lb/>digeſted:
          they relax all the parts, diſſolve the <lb/>humours, excite making Water, or draining <pb
            xml:id="page_29" n="27"/>
          <lb/>Sweats. I have ſeen diſorders occaſioned by <lb/>Weakneſs conſiderably diminiſhed
          without <lb/>any remedy, but the mere retrenching of the <lb/>quantity of Liquor the
          Patient uſually Drunk. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>We know, that an unnatural State of the <lb/>Nerves of the Stomach may either <choice>
            <corr>produce</corr>
            <sic>produc</sic>
          </choice> a <lb/>craving or an averſion to food; that low <lb/>Spirits and Melancholy
          often proceed from <lb/>that cauſe: nor is it to be doubted, that <lb/>when the Nerves of
          the Stomach are, for cer- <lb/>tain cauſes, affected in a manner ſomewhat <lb/>different,
          an indifference for food, a weak <lb/>Digeſtion, a languor and coldneſs, a ſlow
          <lb/>Pulſe, and waſting, may be the conſequences. <lb/>By proper food, the Nerves of the
          Stomach are <lb/>gratefully ſtimulated, and the whole Body is <lb/>thence enlivened and
          ſtrengthened; ſo that, <lb/>beſides its uſe for nutrition, food in the ſto- <lb/>mach
          becomes, altogether neceſſary in ſome <lb/>delicate Nervous People, for keeping up the
          <lb/>ſtrength of the Body, and the due exerciſe <lb/>of all its ſuctions. The morbid
          affection of <lb/>the Nerves of the Stomach, by ſympathy, <lb/>impairs the Vigour and
          energy of the whole <lb/>ſyſtem. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is ſaid in Holy Write, <q rend="diple quotes">That where much <lb/>is given, much
            will be required </q> May I <lb/>preſume then to put a Queſtion, which I wiſh <lb/>to do
          without giving offence to God or the <lb/>world. How it has happened in all ages, <pb
            xml:id="page_30" n="28"/>
          <lb/>That men of the greateſt ſenſibility of Soul, <lb/>ſhould be endued with ſuch
          delicate Nerves, <lb/>as pervert the mental Faculties and prevent <lb/>the Soul from
          exerting its nobleſt Powers, to <lb/>ſhine and illuminate in contemplation of the
          <lb/>Works of God? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I ſhall conclude this Section with Dr Chene's <lb/>obſervation, in his Engliſh
          Malady, the reading <lb/>of which, ſtrikes the Human Mind with aſto- <lb/>niſhment: <q
            rend="diple quotes">But of all the miſeries that af- <lb/>flicts human Life, (ſays that
            Eminent Phy- <lb/>ſician) and which principally relate to the <lb/>Body, in this Valley
            of Tears, I think Ner- <lb/>vous diſorders, in their extreme and laſt <lb/>Degree,
            beyond all compariſon the worſt. </q>
          <lb/>It was the obſervation of a Great Man, that <lb/>he had ſeen perſons labouring under
          the <lb/>Gout, Stone, Cancer and every other diſ- <lb/>order, which could tear the Human
          Ma- <lb/>chine. But had he compared them all (and <lb/>indeed ſcarce any, willing to lay
          down cheer- <lb/>fully the Load of Clay, we will except thoſe, <lb/>who were ſupported by
          divine power) but <lb/>ſuch as laboured under an Internal Anxiety, <lb/>meaning thoſe moſt
          Cruel, Sinking, Suffo- <lb/>cating and Strangling, Nervous Diſorders, <lb/>they greatly
          exceeded. It is almoſt the only <lb/>miſery to be dreaded and avoided in Life, if
          <lb/>poſſible it can be by any means. For when <pb xml:id="page_31" n="29"/>
          <lb/>once the ſupporters are gone, the Diſſolution <lb/>is perfect. </p>
      </div>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A long horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <div n="3" type="section">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>SECTION III. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE Human Body is made up of ſuch frail <lb/>Materials, that
          they muſt neceſſarily de- <lb/>cay, and often be put out of order. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>We are not only ſubject to pain, and diſ- <lb/>eaſes; but alſo to Irregularities of
          the Paſſions, <lb/>and Influence of the Weather; all which af- <lb/>fect the Spirits,
          Intellects and Memory, ſo as <lb/>to render the ſame Perſon very different, at
          <lb/>different times, in thinking, ſpeaking, and <lb/>acting; as any one, who is not
          robuſtly in- <lb/>ſenſible muſt naturally diſcover from his own <lb/>feelings, at one time
          or other. Conſidering <lb/>its admirable Structure, the Number and ex- <lb/>quiſite
          fineneſs of its movements, that in a <lb/>healthy State, all its parts muſt conſpire to
          <lb/>perform their proper office, and that the leaſt <lb/>failure generally occaſions ſome
          diſeaſe; it <lb/>appears matter of aſtoniſhment that we are <lb/>more than the tranſitory
          Beings of a Day. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In this frail and uncertain ſtate, the human <lb/>Syſtem is ſubject to an Inclement
          Atmo- <lb/>ſphere without, and the violent Paſſions with- <pb xml:id="page_32" n="30"/>
          <lb/>in, it may ſuffer from Intemperance in Diet, <lb/>the advances of Age and the
          prevalence of <lb/>Injurious Habits, ſo as to render it more un- <lb/>ſtable than the
          Weather-Glaſs, and in a per- <lb/>petual ſtate of change, from the Cradle to the
          <lb/>Grave. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Well may human Life, thus ſurrounded by <lb/>a train of unavoidable dangers, and
          calamities <lb/>be compared to a fleeting ſhadow which ne- <lb/>ver contiues in one ſtay.
          Like an unballaſted <lb/>bark in a troubled Ocean, it becomes the <lb/>ſport of Winds and
          tides; and without the <lb/>aid of Religion, Reaſon, and Philoſophy, is <lb/>in continual
          danger of being ſwallowed up <lb/>and loſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Perhaps, however, very few can properly <lb/>be ſaid to die of old age merely; for
          even <lb/>the Life of Old Parr might probably have <lb/>been ſtill prolonged, had he not
          changed his <lb/>Air and manner of Living. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Here we may obſerve, that by a kind of <lb/>Fatal Neceſſity, Animal Bodies are worn
          out <lb/>and deſtroyed by that very cauſe which con- <lb/>ſtitutes the principles of Life,
          namely, the <lb/>circulating power of the Blood; and con- <lb/>ſequently, that the number
          of years to which <lb/>man may attain, will probably be in propor- <lb/>tion to the
          Velocity of the Pulſe: If ſo, it will <lb/>then follow, that ſuch a particular ſtate of
          <lb/>the Conſtitution as produces the greateſt de- <pb xml:id="page_33" n="31"/>
          <lb/>gree of ſtrength and vigour in youth, is not <lb/>moſt likely to prolong Life, that
          thoſe of <lb/>weak ſolids, and delicate habits in their early <lb/>ſtate, grow old more
          ſlowly than others; and <lb/>if the Viſcera is ſound, become for a time, <lb/>more ſtrong
          and Healthy from the effect of <lb/>Age<choice>
            <corr>.</corr>
            <sic/>
          </choice>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The diſorders produced by the efforts of <lb/>the mind fall ſooneſt upon ſuch as are
          inceſ- <lb/>ſantly engaged in the contemplation of one <lb/>object<unclear>:</unclear>
          <q rend="diple quotes">Study (ſays Mr Rouſſeau) makes <lb/>men tender, weakens their
            Conſtitution, <lb/>and when once the Body has loſt its pow- <lb/>ers, thoſe of the ſoul
            are not eaſily preſer- <lb/>ved. Application wears out the Machine, <lb/>exhauſts the
            ſpirits, deſtroys the ſtrength, <lb/>enervates the mind, makes us puſillani- <lb/>mous,
            unable either to bear fatigue, or to <lb/>keep our paſſions under. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The whole Body becomes hard in proceſs <lb/>of time, and old age itſelf is a general
          indu- <lb/>ration. In labouring Men, thoſe parts moſt <lb/>uſed in their reſpective
          employments grow <lb/>callous; in men of Letters, the Brain itſelf <lb/>is attacked in
          this manner. They become in- <lb/>capable of connecting ideas, and grow old <lb/>much
          before their time. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In Children the Brain is too ſoft<unclear>,</unclear> in old <lb/>Perſons too hard,
          and in the two extremes it <lb/>is equally unfit to communicate the Oſcillati- <pb
            xml:id="page_34" n="32"/>
          <lb/>ons exerted by thinking. Galen has rightly <lb/>obſerved, that our memory fails
          firſt, and <lb/>forebodes the weakening of our reaſon<choice>
            <corr>.</corr>
            <sic/>
          </choice>
          <lb/>The Nerves are not the only parts affected by deep <lb/>thinking, for, as Gunzius has
          obſerved, the <lb/>wearineſs of the eyes is alone ſufficient to <lb/>produce Nervous
          diſeaſes, There is no one <lb/>but muſt have experienced, as I have often <lb/>done, how
          much the head is weakened by <lb/>long attention of the ſight. If after a Fever <lb/>or
          other Indiſpoſition, it ſhould happen to <lb/>me, before my ſtrength is well
            recruited<unclear>,</unclear> to <lb/>fix my eyes for a long time on any Object, I
          <lb/>am immediately ſeized with Giddineſs, ſick- <lb/>neſs at ſtomach, and my whole Body
          ſuffers <lb/>a painful Senſation of being fatigued and ex- <lb/>hauſted<choice>
            <corr>.</corr>
            <sic/>
          </choice>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If ſuch are the Injuries brought on the <lb/>Conſtitution by irregularity and exceſs
          of the <lb/>Paſſions, it ought to be the care of every <lb/>Rational Being, to guard
          againſt their inſults, <lb/>and to oppoſe their Effects with becoming <lb/>reſolution, and
          a Virtuous Reſignation to the <lb/>Will of Providence. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Happineſs and Miſery are the Lights and <lb/>Shades which fill up the out-lines in
          the Por- <lb/>trait of Human Life<unclear>.</unclear> Every Man naturally <lb/>endeavours
          to attain the one, and avoid the <lb/>other; but by very different means, which <lb/>are
          often diſproportioned to that end. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_35" n="33"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>We frequently deceive ourſelves, both in <lb/>the purſuit and enjoyment of our
          wiſhes. <lb/>Extravagance of Hope often ends in diſap- <lb/>pointment; and even a conſtant
          Series of <lb/>pleaſurable Events will at laſt loſe their power. <lb/>To give them true
          reliſh, and make them <lb/>laſting, the mind muſt refer to ſome former <lb/>painful
          ſenſations. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Thus a Perſon who always poſſeſſed Health, <lb/>is ſcarce ſenſible of its value; but
          when loſt, <lb/>let it again return, and he will bleſs the means <lb/>which reſtored it.
          None enjoy Riches ſo <lb/>much as thoſe who have been at great pains <lb/>to attain them:
          He who always was affluent, <lb/>has no competent idea of Indigence, to con- <lb/>traſt
          ſuch a State, or exalt his enjoyment. <lb/>Were our exquiſite pleaſures too laſting, they
          <lb/>would lay ſo much ſtreſs on the vital powers <lb/>of the Body, as would ſoon wear it
          out. <lb/>Every extreme, therefore, corrects itſelf; and <lb/>every Evil works its own
          cure. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If the violent Paſſions harrow up the Soul, <lb/>and diſturb its union with the Body,
          a Con- <lb/>ſcience pure and uncorrupted, the ineſtima- <lb/>ble reward of Virtue, will
          beſt reconcile them <lb/>to each other, and cauſe them to dwell in <lb/>harmony: That will
          always ſpeak peace to <lb/>the Mind, whatever the World may ſay, and <lb/>ſhield it from
          the impotent attacks of ſlander <lb/>and abuſe. Whoever is overſolicitous about <pb
            xml:id="page_36" n="34"/>
          <lb/>Cenſure, Fame, or the poſſeſſion of temporal <lb/>Enjoyments<unclear>,</unclear> will
          ſeldom find repoſe: an un- <lb/>gratious look from his ſuperiors, or unmerit- <lb/>ed
          inſolence from thoſe below him, will vex <lb/>and diſcompoſe him. If he is anxious for
          <lb/>long life; a Coffin or ſhroud, the apparatus <lb/>of Death, will alarm and appal his
          ſenſes; <lb/>whilſt he who diſpenſes with unavoidable ills <lb/>with a Philoſphic
          indifference, who is neither <lb/>weary of living or affraid to die, will find <lb/>within
          himſelf an inexpreſſible, and perpetual <lb/>calm. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>By giving way to ſorrow, or anger, they <lb/>at laſt become habitual and reign
          triumphant: <lb/>In a word, the government of the paſſions is <lb/>as eſſential towards
          preventing diſeaſes of the <lb/>mind, as Temperance contributes to hinder <lb/>them
          attacking the Body. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>That man ought to be deemed richeſt, <lb/>who is the happieſt; and he is the moſt
          like- <lb/>ly to become ſo, who, with a virtuous reſig- <lb/>nation is prepared for the
          unavoidable evils <lb/>which fleſh is heir to; who expoſtulates with <lb/>the folly and
          extravagance of his own deſires, <lb/>and though a hard taſk, at laſt convinces him-
          <lb/>ſelf that what he likes beſt, is not always beſt <lb/>for him; who preſerves at all
          times, a decent <lb/>equality of mind, is not arrogantly elated <lb/>with the deluſive
          ſmiles of Proſperity, nor <lb/>ſervily caſt down by the ſurly viſage of Miſ- <lb/>fortune. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_37" n="35"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Organs of the Body may be entirely <lb/>unfit to be acted upon by the Soul, when
          it <lb/>remains wrapped up in itſelf, like a criminal <lb/>in a Dungeon. Some people are
          born with <lb/>imperfect nerves, which are ſtopt up, and <lb/>never all their lives,
          unfold themſelves, and <lb/>ſhake off the Clog of Matter which obſtruct <lb/>them. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Though the Soul has a power over the in- <lb/>voluntary motions of the Body, in a
          healthy <lb/>ſtate; yet when the Body is diſeaſed or im- <lb/>perfectly formed, the
          operation of the Soul <lb/>then is irregular. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Even the ſtrength of the Conſtitution is <lb/>itſelf dangerous. Young people of
          excel- <lb/>lent Conſtitutions, apply themſelves to ſtudy <lb/>with indefatigable
          induſtry; the powerful <lb/>action of the Soul increaſes that of the <lb/>Organs, and they
          are attacked with inflam- <lb/>matory diſeaſes, the conſequence of irri- <lb/>tation long
          kept up in vigorous habits. <lb/>Sometimes they expire in the firſt attack; <lb/>more
          commonly they get the better of that; <lb/>and if they find themſelves perfectly re-
          <lb/>covered, their conſtitution recovering its <lb/>vigour, they give themſelves up again
          to the <lb/>ſame labours, and relapſe into the ſame diſ- <lb/>orders. There are frequent
          inſtances of ro- <lb/>buſt young men cloſe applying to ſtudy, who <lb/>are attacked with
          inflammatory fevers every <pb xml:id="page_38" n="36"/>
          <lb/>year; at laſt, in proceſs of time, being worn <lb/>out by theſe attacks and by their
          labours, they <lb/>loſe their ſtrength, and are ſeized with con- <lb/>ſumptive diſeaſes,
          againſt which they are no <lb/>longer able to reſiſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Health is frequently deſtroyed by exceſſive <lb/>devotion. An Author has collected
          ſeveral <lb/>intereſting obſervations on this head, in which <lb/>devout Melancholy is
          well delineated; its <lb/>ſymptoms are very unaccountable, alarming, <lb/>and grievous;
          and there are few practitioners <lb/>who have not had opportunities of ſeeing <lb/>ſome
          ſhocking inſtances of this diſeaſe. The <lb/>greatneſs and excellence of the object, and
          <lb/>the ſatisfaction the Soul experiences in giv- <lb/>ing itſelf up to the contemplation
          of the Al- <lb/>mighty, excites too lively a Senſation, and <lb/>produces in the Brain,
          attention too violent <lb/>and too continual, to be ſupported for a long <lb/>time
          together without Injury; it ſoon throws <lb/>the ſoul into fanatical madneſs, and exhauſts
          <lb/>the Body. Some moſt amiable yung Per- <lb/>ſons, led away by an erronious Syſtem,
          <lb/>fade and fall into decay, neglecting the duties <lb/>of their calling, in order to
          give their thoughts <lb/>up wholly to the ſupreme Author of their
            <lb/><unclear>Being</unclear>, who could not have been more pro- <lb/>perly glorified
          than by a ſtrict Attention to <lb/>thoſe duties. A Student is ſtill regrated, <lb/>One of
          the greateſt abilities, born with ſtrong <pb xml:id="page_39" n="37"/>
          <lb/>powers of the mind, whoſe candour and o- <lb/>ther Virtues would have been an
          acquiſition <lb/>to the Church; But who unfortunately de- <lb/>voted himſelf to a ſect, of
          which he ſoon was <lb/>the victim, the powers of his Body decaying <lb/>as faſt as his
          mind became more zealouſly in- <lb/>flamed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Sometimes even the moſt lucky thoughts <lb/>ariſe in the midſt of recreation. One of
          the <lb/>greateſt Geniuſes of our age computed his <lb/>immortal works walking about in
          the Coun- <lb/>try. The Soul unfolds itſelf in open Air, <lb/>but is impriſoned within the
          confined walls of <lb/>a Study; it is elevated by the fragrance of <lb/>Flowers, depreſſed
          by the ſmell of a Lamp. <lb/>Plutarch's compariſon on this ſubject is <lb/>very juſt and
          excellent: <q rend="quotes">A little water, </q>
          <lb/>(ſays he,) <q rend="diple quotes">nouriſhes and ſtrengthens <lb/>Plants; and
            a greater quantity ſtifles them. </q>
          <lb/>Thus it is with the mind; moderate labour is <lb/>its food; exceſſive labour deſtroys
          it. When <lb/>activity was mentioned as the ſecond cauſe of <lb/>the diſorders here
          treated of, exerciſe was <lb/>certainly repreſented at the ſame time, as one <lb/>of the
          moſt powerful preſervatives and re- <lb/>ſtorers of the health of the Learned. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In the foregoing article, the advantages of <lb/>open air have been conſidered, theſe
          are <lb/>greatly enhanced, if accompanied with ſome <lb/>degree of motion. The Learned in
          general, <pb xml:id="page_40" n="38"/>
          <lb/>are not ſufficiently convinced of the influence <lb/>the Body has on the Soul,
          although it was <lb/>well known to our greateſt men, who have <lb/>been ſenſible that the
          Mind was ſubject to the <lb/>powers of Phyſic as well as the Body, <q rend="diple quotes"
            >The <lb/>Soul, ſays Des Cartes, is ſo much influenc- <lb/>ed by the Conſtitution, and
            the State of <lb/>the Bodily Organs, that if it were poſſible <lb/>to find out a method
            of encreaſing our pe- <lb/>netration, it ſhould certainly be ſought for <lb/>in
            Medicine. </q> Walking alone is very be- <lb/>neficial, but not quite ſufficient; and it
          can- <lb/>not be too much recommended to them to <lb/>ride out frequently on Horſe-back;
          this kind <lb/>of exerciſe is of uſe to the Head, the Breaſt, <lb/>and the Viſcera of the
          lower Belly, eſpecially <lb/>by preventing or diſpelling their obſtructions. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The hypocondriac diſeaſe may alſo be <lb/>reckoned among the Evils learned Men are
          <lb/>expoſed to, from that kind of inactive life, <lb/>which diſturbing the circulation in
          the abdo- <lb/>dominal Viſcera, produces obſtructions in <lb/>them. This diſeaſe generally
          attacks the In- <lb/>dolent, the Luxurious, the Unfortunate, and <lb/>the Studious. Men of
          a Melancholy tem- <lb/>perament, whoſe minds are capable of great <lb/>Attention, and
          whoſe paſſions are not eaſily <lb/>moved, are in the advanced periods of Life, <lb/>moſt
          liable to this diſeaſe. It may rather be <lb/>called a complication of Maladies, than a
            <pb xml:id="page_41" n="39"/>
          <lb/>ſingle one. To what a wretched condition <lb/>are the beſt of Men often reduced by
          it! <lb/>Their ſtrength and appetite fail; a perpetual <lb/>gloom hangs over their minds;
          they live in <lb/>the conſtant dread of death, and are continu- <lb/>ally in ſearch of
          relief from Medicine, where, <lb/>alas! it is not to be found. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Thoſe moſt liable to this Diſeaſe, are the <lb/>Virtuous, the Valiant, the Brave, and
          thoſe <lb/>of an enlarged underſtanding, whom it would <lb/>be the intereſt of the world
          to wiſh, they were <lb/>free from that and every other illneſs; and <lb/>except for that
          alloy, they would have too <lb/>large a ſhare of human happineſs. To this <lb/>we owe the
          irrepareable loſs of Doctor Young, <lb/>and the beſt and moſt approved Men that <lb/>have
          appeared among us. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Hypochandriac perſons ought never to <lb/>faſt long, and their food ſhould be ſolid
          and <lb/>nouriſhing, all aceſcent and windy vegetables <lb/>are to be avoided. Fleſh meats
          agree beſt <lb/>with them, and their drink ſhould be old Cla- <lb/>ret or generous
          Madeira. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In all perſons afflicted with Nervous diſor- <lb/>ders, there is a great, delicacy
          and ſenſibility <lb/>of the whole Nervous Syſtem, and an un- <lb/>common degree of
          weakneſs of the Organs <lb/>of digeſtion. Theſe may be either natural <lb/>or acquired.
          When owing to a defect in the <pb xml:id="page_42" n="40"/>
          <lb/>Conſtitution, they are hardly to be removed; <lb/>but may be mitigated by proper
          care. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But Nervous Affections ariſe more fre- <lb/>quently from cauſes which it is, in a
          great <lb/>meaſure, in our power to avoid, than from <lb/>Diſeaſes, or any Original fault
          in the Conſti- <lb/>tution. Exceſſive grief, intenſe Study, im- <lb/>proper diet, and
          neglect of Exerciſe, are the <lb/>great Sources of this extenſive Claſs of diſ-
          <lb/>eaſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Grief indulged deſtroys the appetite and <lb/>digeſtion depreſſes the ſpirits, and
          induces an <lb/>univerſal relaxation and debility of the whole <lb/>Syſtem. Inſtances of
          this are daily to be ſeen. <lb/>The loſs of a relation, or any other misfor- <lb/>tune in
          Life, is often ſufficient to occaſion <lb/>the moſt complicated ſeries of Nervous ſymp-
          <lb/>toms Such misfortunes indeed are not to <lb/>be avoided, but ſurely their effects, by
          a vigor- <lb/>ous and proper exertion of the mind, might <lb/>be renderd leſs hurtful. The
          effects of in- <lb/>tenſe Study are pretty ſimilar to thoſe occaſi- <lb/>oned by Grief. It
          preys upon the Animal <lb/>Spirits, and deſtroys the appetite and digeſti- <lb/>on<choice>
            <corr>.</corr>
            <sic/>
          </choice> To prevent theſe effects, ſtudious Perſons <lb/>ought, according to the Poet,
            <unclear>To</unclear> Toy with their <lb/>Books. They ſhould never Study too long
          <lb/>at a time; nor attend long to one particular <lb/>Subject, eſpecially if it be of a
          ſerious nature. <lb/>They ought likewiſe to be attentive to their <pb xml:id="page_43"
            n="41"/>
          <lb/>poſture, and ſhould take care frequently to <lb/>unbend their minds by muſic,
          diverſions, or <lb/>agreeable Company. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>With regard to Diet, I ſhall only obſerve <lb/>that Nervous diſeaſes may be
          occaſioned <lb/>either by exceſs or inanition, both theſe extre- <lb/>mes hurt digeſtion,
          and vitiate the humours. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But the moſt general cauſe of Nervous diſ- <lb/>orders is Indolence. The active and
          laborious <lb/>are ſeldom troubled with them<choice>
            <corr>.</corr>
            <sic/>
          </choice> They are <lb/>reſerved for the Children of eaſe and afflu- <lb/>ence, who
          generally feel their keeneſt force. <lb/>All I ſhall ſay to ſuch Perſons is, that the
          <lb/>means of prevention and cure are both in <lb/>their own power. If the Conſtitution of
          hu- <lb/>man nature be ſuch, that man muſt either <lb/>labour or ſuffer diſeaſes, ſurely,
          no individual <lb/>has any right to expect an exemption from <lb/>the general rule. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If the ſtomach is bad, either naturally or <lb/>from errors in diet, this Organ will
          be affected <lb/>by the exerciſe of the mind, while the Nerves <lb/>ſhall remain in a
          ſound ſtate; on the contrary, <lb/>if the Nervous Syſtem is weak, and the Sto- <lb/>mach
          ſtrong, Nervous diſeaſes of great im- <lb/>portance, will be brought on before the Sto-
          <lb/>mach is Injured. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A fit of Illneſs, undigeſted food, or any <lb/>ſimilar cauſe often occaſions broken
          uncon- <lb/>nected dreams, and prevents our receiving the <pb xml:id="page_44" n="42"/>
          <lb/><choice>
            <corr>benefits </corr>
            <sic/>
          </choice>ariſing from ſound ſleep; the reaſon of which <lb/>probably is, the fermentation
          and diſcordance <lb/>of the nutritive juices, incapacitating our ſenſes <lb/>or organs
          (thro' which the ſoul is empowred <lb/>to act) from being in a perfect ſtate of reſt,
          <lb/>the ſoul muſt conſequently partake of that <lb/>irregular and unconnected quality, by
          which <lb/>the bodily organs are at that juncture <lb/>actuated: But in Death the caſe is
          quite re- <lb/>verſed; the Soul, inſtead of being Clogg'd up <lb/>and embarraſſed by
          Bodily impediments is <lb/>abſolutely and entirely freed from them; for <lb/>we cannot
          ſuppoſe it is longer confined to <lb/>Nerves and Arteries, which there is no poſſi-
          <lb/>bility of its ever making any further uſe <lb/>of, ſuch a ſuppoſition muſt be
          ridiculous: So <lb/>that in ſleep the Soul's ſituation is directly <lb/>contrary to what
          it muſt be in death; in <lb/>the firſt caſe it is by material influence pre- <lb/>vented
          from exerting its powers, whereas <lb/>in Death, that is, on its enlargement from <lb/>its
          Material body it finds itſelf for the firſt <lb/>time at full Liberty, and in full power
          of <lb/>expanding and exerting them to the ut- <lb/>moſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is evident that Virtue and Vice are not <lb/>Conſtitutional, and dependent on any
          parti- <lb/>cular habit of Body, and tho' our material <lb/>part, has an influence over
          the ſoul, in regard <lb/>to the exertion of its Faculties, yet that influ- <pb
            xml:id="page_45" n="43"/>
          <lb/>ence extends only to the enlarging or con- <lb/>tracting our intellectual faculties,
          and not to <lb/>our making a good or ill uſe of thoſe facul- <lb/>ties, that reſt ſolely
          in Ourſelves, and if we <lb/>make a wrong uſe of that power; if we un- <lb/>naturalize
          ourſelves, as I may ſay, by deviat- <lb/>ing from the Paths of Virtue, whom are we <lb/>to
          blame? The Deity who has formed us as <lb/>we ſhould be, or ourſelves, who with an un-
          <lb/>grateful hand, rejected the opportunity he has <lb/>given us of attaining virtue, and
          in conſe- <lb/>quence, eternal felicity? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Are we not aſſured too, by the Deity, that <lb/>according to our different abilities,
          ſituation, <lb/>various contingencies &amp;c<choice>
            <corr>.</corr>
            <sic/>
          </choice> we ſhall hereafter <lb/>be judged? Our actions will be ſcrutaniz'd in
          <lb/>proportion to the talents entruſted to us, and <lb/>according to the opportunities
          and incitements <lb/>we have had, to make uſe of them and <lb/>not taken in that
          ſuperficial light, mor- <lb/>tals look on them: It is not thoſe who have <lb/>the greateſt
          ſhare of, but thoſe who make the <lb/>beſt uſe of their moral and intellectual powers,
          <lb/>who will be regarded hereafter; juſtice and <lb/>goodneſs are the Deity's Attributes,
          and by <lb/>them we are hereafter to be judged: As to <lb/>Idiots, &amp;c<choice>
            <corr>.</corr>
            <sic/>
          </choice> who (like the Brute Creation) are <lb/>under the dominion of matter, at leaſt,
          <lb/>have as little power of exerting their facul- <lb/>ties, the Deity's Juſtice will
          hardly expect <pb xml:id="page_46" n="44"/>
          <lb/>from them duties, which it is impoſſible they <lb/>ſhould perform. What uſe they and
          many <lb/>more beings are of in the Creation we know <lb/>not; but let us not, ſhort
          ſighted as we are, <lb/>for that reaſon arraign Divine wiſdom: We <lb/>are ſure every part
          of the Creation was or- <lb/>dain'd for ſome wiſe purpoſe, tho' to what <lb/>end we are
          perhaps ignorant; And in regard <lb/>to the diverſity of power, talents, &amp;c. which
          <lb/>we obſerve among men, ſo far from being a <lb/>blemiſh, they are a great prof of the
          Deity's <lb/>Wiſdom: Inſtead of their being the cauſe of <lb/>confuſion it is on that, the
          link which ſup- <lb/>ports all, chiefly depends: was it otherways, <lb/>half the
          omnipotent's Power and goodneſs on <lb/>earth, would have been in vain. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>We may aſſure ourſelves, That Death, <lb/>(which is indeed but the Souls Birth)
          inſtead <lb/>of being a gloomy Meſſenger, is in reality <lb/>our beſt Friend, ſince by his
          means we ſhall <lb/>be freed from the fetters of the fleſh, and in- <lb/>troduced into a
          ſtate of freedom, Knowledge, <lb/>and (I hope) Happineſs, where our intellect- <lb/>ual
          Powers will have full ſcope: where we <lb/>ſhall be all Ethereal Senſe, and capable of in-
          <lb/>numerable Joys which in our preſent ſtate we <lb/>can have no conception of: as Swans
          are ſaid <lb/>to ſing melodiouſly before Death, from an in- <lb/>ſtinct of ſome
          extraordinary Good approach- <lb/>ing, ſo ſhould good men rejoice on their <pb
            xml:id="page_47" n="45"/>
          <lb/><choice>
            <corr>relinquiſhing</corr>
            <sic>elinquiſhing</sic>
          </choice> this mortal State: let us conſider <lb/>what happineſs even in this life the
          contemp- <lb/>lation of an eternity produces! To indulge in <lb/>the hopes of meeting
          again with our long-loſt <lb/>beſt beloved Friends; of living in intimacy <lb/>and
          converſing with, not only the Heroes <lb/>and Philoſophers of all ages, but with Angels
          <lb/>and other ſuperior Beings; of indulging the <lb/>amiable curioſity of ſearching into
          and ad- <lb/>miring the works of the Deity, thro' the im- <lb/>menſity of the creation,
          where infinite variety <lb/>muſt prove an infinite fund of unſpeakable, <lb/>inſatiable,
          and ever encreaſing happineſs; muſt <lb/>not reflections like theſe animate our Spirits
          <lb/>and ſtimulate us to virtue? I own I often in- <lb/>dulge the thought, and am never ſo
          happy as <lb/>when I am thus, as it were, anticipating eter- <lb/>nity; beſides, nothing
          contributes ſo much <lb/>to cheerfulneſs, Religion, Humanity and all <lb/>the ſocial
          virtues, as the contemplation and <lb/>hopes of a futurity; whereas to the contrary
          <lb/>opinion, is ever united a melancholy which <lb/>rankles within us, which preys upon
          our Spi- <lb/>rits, and which by diveſting us of all fears of <lb/>a future Judgment,
          encourages Vice; and too <lb/>often induces us to give ſuch a looſe to our <lb/>paſſions
          as makes us incapable of Happineſs <lb/>either in this world, or the world to come. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And for the Good and Virtuous, the <lb/>cauſe of their Immortality is continually <pb
            xml:id="page_48" n="46"/>
          <lb/><choice>
            <corr>encreaſing</corr>
            <sic>creaſing</sic>
          </choice> even in this world: The longer they <lb/>exiſt, the more they improve in
          Knowledge <lb/>and virtue and conſequently, the more <lb/>they merit an Eternity. We might
          as <lb/>well ſuppoſe, the Deity ſhould annihilate <lb/>Angels, and other ſuperior Beings,
          as the <lb/>Souls of Virtuous Men. When we moſt <lb/>pleaſe him, to imagine we ſhall be
          moſt ſe- <lb/>verely puniſhed by him, were abſurd; and <lb/>ſurely to the virtuous and
          happy, Annihilation <lb/>muſt be the moſt dreadful of Puniſhments. <lb/>The Immateriality
          of the Soul implies too, <lb/>that it is a Subſtance incorruptible and inva- <lb/>riable
          and conſequently eternal, unleſs it ſhall <lb/>pleaſe the Deity to annihilate it; and can
          we <lb/>ſuppoſe, that Truth and Goodneſs, which <lb/>are emanations from the Divine
          Creator, will <lb/>not eternally exiſt? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Every part of the Creation evinces, in the <lb/>moſt ſtriking characters, the
          Exiſtence of a <lb/>Deity; and becauſe we are not acquainted <lb/>with the Nature and
          Eſſence of the Deity, <lb/>ſhall we for that reaſon alone, doubt there <lb/>is a Deity? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Caſe is the ſame in all immaterial ſub- <lb/>ſtances; nor is it poſſible for us
          to be admit- <lb/>ted to a nearer intimacy with them, while we <lb/>are confined to this
          bodily priſon, where, as <lb/>I before obſerved, we can have no diſtinct idea <pb
            xml:id="page_49" n="47"/>
          <lb/>of any thing but what is material, ſince all our <lb/>perceptions are the effects of
          material impulſ- <lb/>es, and conveyed through material Organs <lb/>to the Soul. The human
          underſtanding <lb/>is limited to every human boundaries<choice>
            <corr>.</corr>
            <sic/>
          </choice> How <lb/>many things are there, even in the ma- <lb/>terial Creation, which ſeem
          myſterious, and <lb/>are kept from us? Yet this ſhould not <lb/>give us the leaſt
          uneaſineſs, ſince what- <lb/>ever is available to our happineſs here, or <lb/>hereafter,
          is laid open to us. The knowledge <lb/>of a Deity, and the Soul's exiſtence, are
          <lb/>truths abſolutely neceſſary to make us happy <lb/>and virtuous. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is worth obſerving, That we are aſſured <lb/>in Scripture,— <q rend="diple quotes"
            >Angels and other ſpiritual <lb/>Beings, neither Marry, nor are given in <lb/>Marriage:
          </q> They all have one common <lb/>Parent, The Almighty. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Our Bodies, like all other material ſyſtems <lb/>are not deſigned for eternal
          duration, are <lb/>ever variable, and ſo ordered, as to ſtand in <lb/>need of daily
          recruits of Food, Sleep, &amp;c.: <lb/>During our ſleep, a ſwoon, or any ſimilar
          <lb/>cauſe, the Soul being embarraſſed and <lb/>clogged up, as it were, is in a ſtate of
          Deliquium <lb/>at leaſt, if it does think, its actions are ſo incon- <lb/>gruous, as not
          to be traced in our waking hours <lb/>notwithſtanding which, we are not to ſuppoſe
          <lb/>that the Soul is in reality more defective then, <pb xml:id="page_50" n="48"/>
          <lb/>than at another time; but the Organs, thro' <lb/>which it is obliged to act, being
          obſtructed, <lb/>its faculties are conſequently impeded. If <lb/>we loſe our Eye-ſight or
          hearing, the Soul is <lb/>not in the leaſt maimed thereby, it has but loſt <lb/>its
          Inſtrument or Bodily Organ, its original <lb/>power is ſtill the ſame; and were our
          optical <lb/>or auditory Organs reduced to order, the <lb/>Soul would again re-exert its
          uſual Faculties. </p>
        <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="8"/>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="8"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
