<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Robinson: Every patient his own doctor</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Lewis Robinson</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Every Patient His own Doctor; or, the sick man's triumph over death
              and the grave. Containing, the most approved methods of curing every disease incident
              to the human body, internal or external; whether owing to Defects of Nature,
              occasioned by Intemperance, contracted by Accident, or caused by Decay. With the best
              remedies Prescribed by the Authority of the most eminent Physicians for removing each
              Disorder, restoring Health, preserving it when restored; and extending Life to an
              honourable Old Age. Including An excellent Collection of the most eminent Receipts for
              Making and Preparing A great Number of cheap, easy, and efficacious Medicines. Among
              these are That Admirable New Discovery, by which the Scurvy, the Grand English
              Disorder, is effectually cured: And for the successful Practice of which, Captain Cook
              received the Premium Medal from the Royal Society, for having preserved himself and
              all his Men from this dreadful Distemper, during the Space of Three Years and Eighteen
              Days, although he passed through all the Varieties of Climate, and Seasons in his late
              Voyage round the World, performed. By the Command of His Majesty. Also The Method used
              by the Humane Society for the Recovery of Persons apparently drowned or suffocated. —
              A certain Cure for the Bite of a Mad Dog, Viper, Adder, &amp;c. — An infallible Remedy
              against the Goal Distemper, Plague, or any other pestilential Disorder, &amp;c.
              &amp;c.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">N23426</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N23426"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Cooke, No 17, Pater-Noster Row.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1785</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="4"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="56"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="10"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">National Library of Medicine</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3308100138</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K013620.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="General treatises"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_1"/>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>FRONTISPIECE. </head>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>man seated in a room with his feet resting on a skeleton</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <p>J. L<unclear>#</unclear>d<unclear>##</unclear>. ſculp <lb/></p>
        <l>The Sick me with the Beſt Advice supply</l>
        <lb/>
        <l>Who Seen may thro<unclear>##</unclear> their uſeleſs <unclear>##</unclear>utches by. </l>
        <lb/>
        <l>Trample on Death aſſiſted by our Ar<unclear>#</unclear>. </l>
        <lb/>
        <l>His Glaſs Demoliſh, and deſtroy his <unclear>#####</unclear>. </l>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_3" n="iii"/>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>PREFACE. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>AS Health is the nobleſt bleſſing of <lb/>this life, the method of pro- <lb/>curing
          it ſhould be our principal en- <lb/>quiry. While poſſeſſed of it, we ſeldom <lb/>pay a
          proper attention to its importance; <lb/>when loſt, we become ſenſible of its <lb/>value,
          but are frequently careleſs con- <lb/>cerning its recovery. The reaſons are <lb/>plain;
          while we have it we trifle with it <lb/>till it flies us; when fled, we trifle with
          <lb/>our misfortune, becauſe we ſuppoſe the <lb/> recovery to be either impoſſible or im-
          <lb/>probable. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_4" n="iv"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>For the benefit of mankind, we here <lb/>furniſh the public with ſome of the beſt
          <lb/>and eaſieſt methods of recovering and <lb/>ſecuring health, and of preſerving life,
          <lb/>which comprehend the greateſt diſco- <lb/>veries in the Medical Art. Theſe will
          <lb/>equally ſuit all ranks of people; the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Poor,</hi> becauſe the
          Remedies may be <lb/><hi rend="italic">cheaply</hi> obtained; and the <hi rend="italic"
            >Rich,</hi> becauſe <lb/>they may be <hi rend="italic">eaſily</hi> put in practice.
          Hence <lb/><hi rend="italic">Health</hi> may be recovered with <hi rend="italic"
            >Facility,</hi>
          <lb/>and a <hi rend="italic">Knowledge</hi> of the powers of me- <lb/>dicine obtained
          without <hi rend="italic">Difficulty.</hi> So <lb/>that our readers may at once ceaſe to
          <lb/>be <hi rend="italic">Patients</hi> themſelves, or, if they pleaſe, <lb/>become <hi
            rend="italic">Practical Phyſicians</hi> to others. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_5" n="5"/>
      <div type="part">
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A horizontal double-line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="size(1.5) align-center space">
          <lb/>Every Patient his own Doctor. </head>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>PART I. <lb/><hi rend="size(1.25) space">INTERNAL DISORDERS. </hi>
        </head>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>SCURVY. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HE Scurvy being the principal diſeaſe inci- <lb/>dent to the
            inhabitants of Great Britain, and <lb/>the ſource from whence many of their other
            <lb/>diſorders flow, we thought it neceſſary to commence <lb/>this ſalutary Work, with
            an account of the nature of, <lb/>and the remedies againſt, this fatal foe to ENGLISH
            <lb/>CONSTITUTIONS. </p>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms</hi>. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>THE ſymptoms or ſigns of this dangerous diſeaſe <lb/>are a frequent lazineſs and
              lowneſs of ſpirits, pains in <lb/>various parts of the body, ſometimes livid ſpots,
              often <lb/>a ſallow complexion, a continual itching of the blood, <lb/>difficulty of
              breathing, ſwelling of the legs, bleeding <pb xml:id="page_6" n="6"/>
              <lb/>at the noſe, and ſpongy gums, ſubject to pains and <lb/>bleedings. But it is to
              be obſerved, that as conſti- <lb/>tutions differ, the ſigns or ſymptoms of the diſeaſe
              <lb/>vary; and people, according to their years, ſituations <lb/>in life, and manner
              of living, are attacked by this <lb/>diſeaſe, under ſeveral appearances; but ſome of
              the <lb/>above ſymptoms always attend it according to the <lb/>conſtitution of thoſe
              afflicted; for whoſe benefit we <lb/>ſhall point out the moſt approved and certain me-
              <lb/>thods of cure hitherto diſcovered. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies</hi>. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>A Milk diet, with weak whey, greens of all kinds, <lb/>freſh vegetables, fruits,
              acids, ſcurvy-graſs ale, freſh <lb/>beer and cyder, tar water taken twice a day, with
              <lb/>camphire, one ſcruple, æthiops mineral, half an <lb/>ounce, powder of
              gum-guaiacum, two drachms, ho- <lb/>ney, one ounce, mix and make an electuary, and
              take <lb/>the bigneſs of a nutmeg every night going to reſt. <lb/>The patient may
              likewiſe drink the decoction of the <lb/>woods. Drinking ſea-water will be found
              extremely <lb/>beneficial, as will bathing in the ſea. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>But for the eaſieſt and moſt efficacious remedy for <lb/>this dreadful diſeaſe,
              we may thank Capt. Cook, who <lb/>in his late voyage round the world, by the command
              <lb/>of his preſent <hi rend="sc">Majesty</hi> in the ſhip <hi rend="italic"
                >Reſolution</hi>, pre- <lb/>ſerved himſelf and all his men from the Scurvy, by
              <lb/>the uſe of a very ſimple medicine; though he paſſed <lb/>through the temperature,
              the frigid and the torrid <lb/>zones, was abſent from England three years and eigh-
              <lb/>teen days, and went through ſuch a variety of cli- <lb/>mates, as were ſufficient
              to make the ſevereſt attacks <lb/>on the moſt robuſt conſtitution. But as his methods
              <lb/>of proceeding will appear with moſt propriety in his <lb/>own words, we ſhall
              preſent our readers with his <lb/>Letter to Sir <hi rend="italic">John Pringle</hi>,
              Bart, Preſident of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Royal Society</hi>, which letter is
              dated <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 5, 1776; <pb xml:id="page_7" n="7"/>
              <lb/>and for which Captain Cook received a Premium <lb/>Medal. </p>
            <floatingText>
              <body>
                <salute rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>SIR, </salute>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>
                  <q rend="paradiple">AS many gentlemen have expreſſed ſome ſurprize <lb/>at the
                    uncommon good ſtate of health which the <lb/>crew of the <hi rend="italic"
                      >Reſolution</hi>, under my command, ex- <lb/>perienced during her late voyage;
                    I take the liberty <lb/>to communicate to you the methods that were taken
                    <lb/>to obtain that end. Much was owing to the ex- <lb/>traordinary attention
                    given by the Admiralty, in <lb/>cauſing ſuch articles to be put on board, as
                    either <lb/>by experience or conjecture were judged to tend moſt <lb/>to
                    preſerve the health of ſeamen. I ſhall not treſpaſs <lb/>upon your time in
                    mentioning all thoſe articles, <lb/>but confine myſelf to ſuch as were found the
                    moſt <lb/>uſeful. </q>
                </p>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>
                  <q rend="paradiple">We had on board a large quantity of malt, <lb/>of which was
                    made ſweet-wort, and given (not only <lb/>to thoſe men who had manifeſt ſymptoms
                    of the <lb/>ſcurvy, but to ſuch alſo as were, from circumſtances, <lb/>judged to
                    be moſt liable to that diſorder) from <lb/>one to two or three pints in the day
                    to each man, <lb/>or in ſuch proportion as the ſurgeon thought neceſſary;
                    <lb/>which ſometimes amounted to three quarts in the <lb/>twenty-four hours.
                    This is without doubt one of <lb/>the beſt antiſcorbutic ſea-medicines yet found
                    out; <lb/>and if given in time will, with proper attention to <lb/>other things,
                    I am perſuaded, prevent the ſcurvy <lb/>from making any great progreſs for a
                    conſiderable <lb/>time: but I am not altogether of opinion, that it <lb/>will
                    cure it in an advanced ſtate at ſea. </q>
                </p>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>
                  <q rend="paradiple">"Sour-krout, of which we had alſo a large pro- <lb/>viſion, is
                    not only a wholeſome vegetable food, but, <lb/>in my judgment, highly
                    antiſcorbutic, and ſpoils <lb/>not by keeping. A pound of it was ſerved to each
                      <pb xml:id="page_8" n="8"/>
                    <lb/>man, when at ſea, twice a week, or oftener when it <lb/>was thought
                    neceſſary. </q>
                </p>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>
                  <q rend="paradiple">Portable ſoup, or broth, was another eſſential <lb/>article,
                    of which we had likewiſe a liberal ſupply. <lb/>An ounce of this to each man, or
                    ſuch other pro- <lb/>portion as was thought neceſſary, was boiled with
                    <lb/>their peas three days in the week; and when we <lb/>were in places where
                    freſh vegetables could be pro- <lb/>cured, it was boiled, with them and with
                    wheat <lb/>or oatmeal, every morning for breakfaſt, and alſo with <lb/>dried
                    peas and freſh vegetables for dinner. It <lb/>enabled us to make ſeveral
                    nouriſhing and whole- <lb/>ſome meſſes, and was the means of making the peo-
                    <lb/>ple eat a greater quantity of greens than they would <lb/>have done
                    otherwiſe. </q>
                </p>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>
                  <q rend="paradiple">Further, we were provided with rob of lemons <lb/>and oranges;
                    which the ſurgeon found uſeful in ſe- <lb/>veral caſes. </q>
                </p>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>
                  <q rend="paradiple">Amongſt other articles of victualling, we were <lb/>furniſhed
                    with ſugar in the room of oil, and with <lb/>wheat inſtead of much oatmeal, and
                    were certainly <lb/>gainers by the exchange. Sugar, I imagine, is a <lb/>very
                    good antiſcorbutic; whereas oil, ſuch at leaſt <lb/>as is uſually given to the
                    navy, I apprehend has the <lb/>contrary effect. But the introduction of the moſt
                    <lb/>ſalutary articles, either as proviſion or medicines will <lb/>generally
                    prove unſucceſsful, unleſs ſupported by <lb/>certain rules of living. </q>
                </p>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>
                  <q rend="paradiple">"On this principle, many years experience, to- <lb/>gether
                    with ſome hints I had from Sir Hugh Palliſer, <lb/>the Captains Campbell,
                    Wallis, and other intelligent <lb/>officers, enabled me to lay down a plan
                    whereby all <lb/>was to be conducted. The crew were at three watches,
                    <lb/>except upon ſome extraordinary occaſions. By this <lb/>means they were not
                    ſo much expoſed to the weather <lb/>as if they had been at watch and watch; and
                    they <lb/>had generally dry cloaths to ſhift themſelves when <pb xml:id="page_9"
                      n="9"/>
                    <lb/>they happened to get wet. Care was alſo taken to <lb/>expoſe them as little
                    as poſſible. Proper methods <lb/>were employed to keep their perſons, hammocks,
                    <lb/>bedding, cloaths, &amp;c. conſtantly clean and dry. <lb/>Equal pains were
                    taken to keep the ſhip clean and <lb/>dry between decks. Once or twice a week
                    ſhe was <lb/>aired with fires; and when this could not be done, <lb/>ſhe was
                    ſmoaked with gunpowder moiſtened with <lb/>vinegar or water. I had alſo
                    frequently a fire made <lb/>in an iron pot at the bottom of the well, which
                    <lb/>greatly purified the air in the lower parts of the ſhip. <lb/>To this and
                    cleanlineſs, as well in the ſhip as amongſt <lb/>the people, too great attention
                    cannot be paid; the <lb/>leaſt neglect occaſions a putrid offenſive ſmell below,
                    <lb/>which nothing but fires will remove; and if theſe <lb/>be not uſed in time,
                    thoſe ſmells will be attended <lb/>with bad conſequences. Proper care was taken
                    of <lb/>the ſhip's coppers, ſo that they were kept conſtantly <lb/>clean. The
                    fat, which boiled out of the ſalt beef <lb/>and pork, I never ſuffered to be
                    given to the people, <lb/>as is cuſtomary; being of opinion that it promotes
                    <lb/>the ſcurvy. I never failed to take in water wherever <lb/>it was to be
                    procured, even when we did not ſeem <lb/>to want it; becauſe I look upon freſh
                    water from <lb/>the ſhore to be much more wholeſome than that which <lb/>has
                    been kept for ſome time on board. Of this eſſen- <lb/>tial article we were never
                    at an allowance, but had <lb/>always abundance for every neceſſary purpoſe. I am
                    <lb/>convinced that with plenty of freſh water, and a cloſe <lb/>attention to
                    cleanlineſs, a ſhip's company will ſeldom <lb/>be much afflicted with the
                    ſcurvy, though they ſhould <lb/>not be provided with any of the antiſcorbutics
                    before- <lb/>mentioned. We came to few places where either <lb/>the art of man
                    or nature did not afford ſome ſort of <lb/>refreſhment or other, either of the
                    animal or vege- <lb/>table kind. It was my firſt care to procure what <lb/>could
                    be met with of either, by every means in my <pb xml:id="page_10" n="10"/>
                    <lb/>power, and to oblige our people to make uſe thereof, <lb/>both by my
                    example and authority; but the benefits <lb/>ariſing from ſuch refreſhments ſoon
                    became ſo obvious, <lb/>that I had little occaſion to employ either the one or
                    <lb/>the other. </q>
                </p>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>
                  <q rend="paradiple">Theſe, Sir, were the methods, under the care of
                    <lb/>Providence, by which the <hi rend="italic">Reſolution</hi> performed a voy-
                    <lb/>age of three years and eighteen days, through all the <lb/>climates from 52
                    degrees north to 71 degrees ſouth, <lb/>with the loſs of one man only by
                    diſeaſe, and who <lb/>died of a complicated and lingering illneſs, without
                    <lb/>any mixture of ſcurvy. Two others were unfortu- <lb/>nately drowned, and
                    one killed by a fall; ſo that of <lb/>the whole number with which I ſet out from
                    England, <lb/>I loſt only four. </q>
                </p>
                <signed rend="align-center">
                  <lb/>
                  <q rend="quotes">I have the honour to be, Sir, &amp;c. </q>
                </signed>
              </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText>
              <body>
                <head rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>Extract of a Letter from Captain <hi rend="roman">Cook</hi> to Sir <hi
                    rend="roman">John <lb/>Pringle</hi>, Bart. dated <hi rend="roman">Plymouth
                    Sound, July 7, 1776.</hi></head>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>
                  <q rend="quotes">I entirely agree with you, that the dearneſs of the <lb/>rob of
                    lemons and oranges will hinder them from <lb/>being furniſhed in large
                    quantities, but I do not think <lb/>this ſo neceſſary; for though they may
                    aſſiſt other <lb/>things, I have no great opinion of them alone. Nor <lb/>have I
                    an higher opinion of vinegar: my people had <lb/>it very ſparingly during the
                    late voyage; and towards <lb/>the latter part, none at all; and yet we
                    experienced no <lb/>ill effects from the want of it. The cuſtom of waſhing
                    <lb/>the inſide of the ſhip with vinegar I ſeldom obſerved, <lb/>thinking, that
                    fire and ſmoak anſwered the purpoſe <lb/>much better. </q>
                </p>
              </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>To the above we ſhall ſubjoin the following re- <lb/>marks on Captain Cook's
              judicious procedure; with <lb/>ſome other intereſting particulars; being a ſummary
              <lb/>of the diſcovery of the great antiſcorbutic virtues of <lb/>ſweet-wort by Dr.
              Macbride, &amp;c. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>
              <q rend="paradiple">"CAPTAIN COOK begins his lift of ſtores with <pb xml:id="page_11"
                  n="11"/>
                <lb/><hi rend="italic">malt</hi>: <q rend="quotes">Of this, </q> he ſays, <q
                  rend="diple quotes">was made ſweet-wort, <lb/>and given not only to thoſe men who
                  had manifeſt <lb/>ſymptoms of the ſcurvy, but to ſuch alſo as were <lb/>judged to
                  be the moſt liable to it. </q> Dr. Macbride, <lb/>who firſt ſuggeſted this
                preparation, was led, as he ſays, <lb/>to the diſcovery by ſome experiments that had
                been <lb/>laid before the Royal Society; by which it appeared, <lb/>that the air
                produced by alimentary fermentation was <lb/>endowed with a power of correcting
                putrefaction. <lb/>The fact he confirmed by numerous trials, and finding <lb/>this
                fluid to be <hi rend="italic">fixed air</hi>, he juſtly concluded, that
                <lb/>whatever ſubſtance proper for food abounded with it, <lb/>and which could be
                conveniently carried to ſea, would <lb/>make one of the beſt proviſions againſt the
                ſcurvy; which <lb/>he then conſidered as a putrid diſeaſe, and as ſuch to be
                <lb/>prevented or cured by that powerful kind of antiſeptic. <lb/>Beer, for
                inſtance, hath always been eſteemed one <lb/>of the beſt antiſcorbutics; but as that
                derived all <lb/>its <hi rend="italic">fixed air</hi> from the malt of which it is
                made, he <lb/>inferred, that malt itſelf was preferable in long <lb/>voyages, as it
                took up leſs room than the brewed li- <lb/>quor, and would keep longer ſound.
                Experience <lb/>hath ſince verified this ingenious theory, and the malt <lb/>hath
                now gained to much credit in the navy, that <lb/>there only wanted ſo long, ſo
                healthful, and ſo cele- <lb/>brated a voyage as this, to rank it among the moſt
                <lb/>indiſpenſable articles of proviſion. For though Cap- <lb/>tain Cook remarks,
                that <q rend="diple quotes">a proper attention to other <lb/>things muſt be joined,
                  and that he is not altogether <lb/>of opinion, that the wort will be able to cure
                  the <lb/>ſcurvy in an advanced ſtate at ſea; yet he is per- <lb/>ſuaded, that it
                  is ſufficient to prevent that diſtem- <lb/>per from making any great progreſs, for
                  a con- <lb/>ſiderable time; </q> and therefore he doth not heſi- <lb/>tate to
                pronounce it, <q rend="diple quotes">one of the beſt antiſcorbutic <lb/>medicines
                  yet found out. </q>
              </q>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <q>
                <lb/>This ſalutary <hi rend="italic">gas</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">fixed air</hi>,
                is contained more <pb xml:id="page_12" n="12"/>
                <lb/>or leſs in all fermentable liquors, and begins to op- <lb/>poſe putrefaction as
                ſoon as the working or inteſtine <lb/>motion commences. </q>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>
              <q>In wine it abounds, and perhaps no vegetable ſub- <lb/>ſtance is more replete with
                it than the fruit of the <lb/>vine. If we join the grateful taſte of wine, we
                <lb/>muſt rank it firſt in the liſt of antiſcorbutic liquors. <lb/>Cyder is likewiſe
                good, with other vinous produc- <lb/>tions from fruit, as alſo the various kinds of
                beer. <lb/>It hath been a conſtant obſervation, that in long <lb/>cruizes or diſtant
                voyages, the ſcurvy is never ſeen <lb/>whilſt the ſmall-beer holds out at a full
                allowance; <lb/>but that when it is all expended, the diſorder ſoon ap- <lb/>pears.
                It were therefore to be wiſhed, that this moſt <lb/>wholeſome beverage could be
                renewed at ſea; but <lb/>our ſhips afford not ſufficient convenience. The
                <lb/>Ruſſians however make a ſhift to prepare at ſea, as <lb/>well as at land, a
                liquor of a middle quality between <lb/>wort and ſmall-beer, in the following
                manner. They <lb/>take ground malt and rye meal in a certain proportion, <lb/>which
                they knead into ſmall loaves, and bake in the <lb/>oven. Theſe they occaſionally
                infuſe in a proper <lb/>quantity of warm water, which begins ſo ſoon to fer-
                <lb/>ment, that in the ſpace of twenty-four hours their <lb/>brewage is compleated,
                in the production of a ſmall, <lb/>briſk, and acidulous liquor, which they call <hi
                  rend="italic">quas</hi>, <lb/>palatable to themſelves, and not diſagreeable to the
                <lb/>taſte of ſtrangers. The late Dr. Mounſey, member of <lb/>the Royal Society, who
                had lived long in Ruſſia, and <lb/>had been <hi rend="italic">Archiater</hi> under
                two ſucceſſive ſovereigns, <lb/>ſays, that the <hi rend="italic">quas</hi> was the
                common and whole- <lb/>ſome drink both of the fleets and armies of that em-
                <lb/>pire, and that it was particularly good againſt the <lb/>ſcurvy. He added, that
                happening to be at Moſcow <lb/>when he peruſed the <q rend="quotes">Obſervations on
                  the Jail- <lb/>Fever, </q> publiſhed here, he had been induced to <lb/>compare
                what he read in that treatiſe with what he <pb xml:id="page_13" n="13"/>
                <lb/>ſhould ſee in the ſeveral priſons of that large city: <lb/>but to his ſurprize,
                after viſiting them all, and find- <lb/>ing them full of malefactors, for the late
                empreſs <lb/>then ſuffered none of thoſe who were convicted of <lb/>capital crimes
                to be put to death, yet he could diſ- <lb/>cover no fever among them, nor learn that
                any acute <lb/>diſtemper peculiar to jails had ever been known there. <lb/>He
                obſerved that ſome of thoſe places of confine- <lb/>ment had a yard, into which the
                priſoners were al- <lb/>lowed to come for the air; but that there were <lb/>others
                without this advantage, yet not ſickly: ſo <lb/>that he could aſſign no other reaſon
                for the health- <lb/>ful condition of thoſe men than the kind of diet they
                <lb/>uſed; which was the ſame with that of the common <lb/>people of the country,
                who not being able to pur- <lb/>chaſe fleſh-meat live moſtly on rye-bread, (the moſt
                <lb/>aceſcent of any bread) and drink <hi rend="italic">quas</hi>. He con-
                <lb/>cluded with ſaying, that upon his return to Peterſ- <lb/>burg, he had made the
                ſame enquiry there, and <lb/>with the ſame reſult. </q>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>
              <q>Thus far my informer<sic>:</sic> from whoſe account it <lb/>would appear, that the
                rye-meal aſſiſted both in <lb/>quickening the fermentation, and adding more fixed
                <lb/>air; ſince the malt alone could not ſo readily pro- <lb/>duce ſo acidulous and
                briſk a liquor. And there is <lb/>little doubt, but that whenever the other grains
                can <lb/>be brought to a proper degree of fermentation, they <lb/>will more or leſs
                in the ſame way become uſeful. <lb/>That oats will, I am ſatisfied, from what I have
                <lb/>been told by one of the intelligent friends of Captain <lb/>Cook. This
                gentleman being on a cruize in a large <lb/>ſhip, in the beginning of the late war,
                and the ſcurvy <lb/>breaking out among his crew, he bethought himſelf <lb/>of a kind
                of food, he had ſeen uſed in ſome parts <lb/>of the country, as the moſt proper on
                this occaſion. <lb/>Some oatmeal is put into a wooden veſſel, hot water <lb/>is
                poured upon it, and the infuſion continues until <pb xml:id="page_14" n="14"/>
                <lb/>the liquor begins to taſte ſouriſh; that is, till a fer- <lb/>mentation comes
                on, which in a place moderately <lb/>warm may be in the ſpace of two days. The water
                <lb/>is then poured off from the grounds, and boiled <lb/>down to the conſiſtence of
                a jelly. This he ordered <lb/>to be made, and dealt out in meſſes, being firſt
                ſweet- <lb/>ened with ſugar, and ſeaſoned with ſome prize-wine <lb/>he had taken,
                which, though turned ſour, yet improved <lb/>the taſte, and made this aliment no
                leſs palatable than <lb/>medicinal. </q>
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>GOUT. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms</hi>. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THE urine of the perſon afflicted is high co- <lb/>loured, and has a ſandy
              ſediment of a reddiſh caſt; <lb/>the part affected looks red and is ſwelled. The pain
              <lb/>is exceedingly acute, as if the bone was broken and, <lb/>is ſucceeded by a
              ſlight fever, and a chilneſs or ſhiver- <lb/>ing, which ſeizes the great toe, ancle,
              heel, calf of the <lb/>leg, &amp;c. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedy. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>BEFORE the afflicted go to bed at night, they <lb/>ſhould take a tea ſpoonful of
              volatile tincture of <lb/>guaiacum in a glaſs of water: keep themſelves warm, <lb/>and
              drink ſack whey. Exerciſe is very requiſite for <lb/>thoſe afflicted with this
              diſorder. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>As the duke of Portland's Gout Powder is re- <lb/>markably efficacious in the
              cure of this diſorder, we <lb/>ſhall here tranſcribe the receipt for making it. </p>
            <floatingText>
              <body>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>TAKE of round birthwort root and gentian root, <lb/>of the tops and leaves of
                  germander, ground pine, and <lb/>centaury: take of all theſe, well dried, powdered
                  and <lb/>ſifted as fine as poſſible, an equal quantity; mix them <lb/>well
                  together, and take one drachm of this mixed <lb/>powder every morning faſting in a
                  cup of wine and <lb/>water, broth, tea, or any other vehicle you like beſt; <pb
                    xml:id="page_15" n="15"/>
                  <lb/>keep faſting an hour and an half after it. Continue <lb/>this medicine for
                  three months without interruption, <lb/>then diminiſh the doſe to three quarters
                  of a drachm <lb/>for three months longer, then to half a drachm for <lb/>ſix
                  months more, taking it regularly every morning if <lb/>poſſible. After the firſt
                  year, it will be ſufficient to <lb/>take half a drachm every other day. As this
                  medicine <lb/>operates inſenſibly, it will take, perhaps, two years <lb/>before
                  you receive any great benefit; ſo you muſt <lb/>not be diſcouraged, though you do
                  not perceive at <lb/>firſt any great amendment; it works ſlow but ſure: <lb/>it
                  doth not confine the patient to any particular diet, <lb/>if he lives ſoberly, and
                  abſtains from thoſe meats <lb/>and liquors that have always been accounted
                  pernicious <lb/>in the gout; as champaign, drams, high ſauces, &amp;c. </p>
              </body>
            </floatingText>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>RHEUMATISM. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>FEVERISH and coſtive body, loſs of appetite, <lb/>coldneſs of the extreme parts,
              heavineſs of the joints, <lb/>chilneſs, ſhivering, and racking pains in the
              <lb/>limbs. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>BE covered warm when you go to bed, and take a <lb/>drachm of powder of
              gum-guaiacum. The duke of <lb/>Portland's Gout Powder is likewiſe uſed in this
              diſorder; <lb/>but it is to be obſerved, that in the rheumatiſm, <lb/>which is only
              accidental and not habitual, a few of the <lb/>drachm doſes may do; but if habitual,
              or has been of <lb/>long duration, then you may take it as for the <lb/>gout. The
              remedy requires patience, as it operates <lb/>but ſlow in both diſtempers. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_16" n="16"/>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>PLEURISY. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>HEAT, thirſt, a troubleſome cough, and a violent <lb/>pain of the ſide. If the
              patient is bled, the blood has <lb/>a reſemblance of tallow when melted. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>FREQUENT bleedings, a bliſter on the ſide, <lb/>and half a pint of the following
              infuſion taken twice <lb/>a-day: a quart of boiling penny royal water, poured <lb/>on
              ſix ounces of freſh horſe dung, ſtrain it when <lb/>cold, and ſweeten it with a
              quarter of an ounce <lb/>of Venice treacle. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>FEVERS. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms.</hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THERE are two principal ſources of fevers, one <lb/>comprehends the cauſes which
              render the blood and <lb/>other fluids of the body too thick; the other includes
              <lb/>thoſe which make them too thin. Let us now exa- <lb/>mine how one ſort may be
              diſtinguiſhed from the <lb/>other. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>It ſhould be obſerved, that in all fevers of every <lb/>kind, there is a morbid
              or malignant quality intro- <lb/>duced and ſubſiſting in the blood as the productive
              <lb/>cauſe; and the proper means for curing them are <lb/>ſuch methods and medicines
              as by experience have <lb/>been found effectual for removing their morbid qua-
              <lb/>lity, and recovering the ſick in the ſhorteſt time. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>In ſome perſons, when there is too much blood, <lb/>ſuch bleeding may be adviſed
              as will draw off the <lb/>exceſs, except in peſtilential diſtempers, in which
              <lb/>blood-letting has proved almoſt always mortal, even <lb/>in the bodies fulleſt of
              blood; this evacuation muſt <pb xml:id="page_17" n="17"/>
              <lb/>be moderately uſed in pleuriſies, as the extremity of <lb/>pain and difficulty of
              breathing ſhall acquire it. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>That the common people (who generally know <lb/>when perſons have fevers) may
              have a little more <lb/>knowledge of theſe acute diſeaſes, and how to diſ-
              <lb/>tinguiſh one kind of them from the other; the per- <lb/>ſon who is to direct for
              the ſick, ſhould carefully <lb/>enquire into the ſtate of his body; he ſhould exa-
              <lb/>mine his pulſe. Let him feel the pulſe of two or <lb/>three that are in health,
              and his own pulſe; and then <lb/>compare them with the pulſe of the patient, and
              <lb/>thereby he will come nearly to know how much it <lb/>differs from the healthful
              ſtandard, as to quickneſs <lb/>or ſlowneſs, and as to its ſtrength and weakneſs, and
              <lb/>be able to deduce ſome concluſions which may guide <lb/>his conduct; then let him
              learn the degree of febrile <lb/>heat; and one way to do this may be by feeling the
              <lb/>ſide of the neck below the ears (through which the <lb/>large blood veſſels paſs
              to and from the brain) and <lb/>thus the degree of the heat of the blood may be
              <lb/>known; and the other ſymptoms of the patient ſhould <lb/>be particularly enquired
              into. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If the heat of the body be exceſſive, the pulſe <lb/>quick and ſtrong, the fleſh
              very dry, the pores of <lb/>the skin very cloſe, and the thirſt very great, it
              <lb/>may be concluded that the cauſe which produced that <lb/>fever has rendered the
              blood too thick. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If the pulſe is too quick, and not ſtrong, and the <lb/>heat of the body not
              great; if the tongue is very <lb/>black or dry, and the thirſt is great, or it the
              patient <lb/>voids blood by urine, or ſpitting, or at his noſe, or <lb/>by ſtool; or
              if he has flat ſpots on his skin, black <lb/>or reddiſh in colour, or if he has a
              great looſeneſs, with <lb/>watery or thin ſtools; or if he has profuſe ſweats,
              <lb/>with a ſenſible ſinking of his ſpirits, and decreaſe of <lb/>ſtrength, it may be
              inſerted, that the fever is of a <lb/>putrid kind. </p>
          </div>
          <pb xml:id="page_18" n="18"/>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies.</hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THE following general rules ſhould be obſerved: <lb/>to drink as plentifully as
              poſſible ſome diluting liquor <lb/>whenever thirſty, ſuch as barley-water, mint and
              balm <lb/>and ſage tea, thin water-gruel, or beef tea made as <lb/>follows: </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Take a pound of lean beef, cut it ſmall, pour upon <lb/>it two quarts of water,
              boil it for the ſpace of five <lb/>minutes, then keep for uſe. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>To uſe ſuch nutritious food, as moſt freely may <lb/>be taken, becauſe it abates
              the acrimony of the blood, <lb/>repairs the waſte of the body, and is one of the beſt
              <lb/>cordials; ſmall whey made with Canary or Mountain <lb/>wine may be frequently
              uſed. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>It may be neceſſary, before we proceed farther, to <lb/>premiſe that in liquid,
              by four table ſpoonfuls, is <lb/>meant half a gill, or two ounces; two ſpoonfuls
              <lb/>one ounce, one ſpoonful half an ounce, or four <lb/>drachms. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If ſeized with any feveriſh complaint, take the fol- <lb/>lowing mixture. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Salt of wormwood, two drachms, lemon juice, or <lb/>any acid, a ſufficient
              quantity to make a neutral me- <lb/>dicine, ſugar about two drachms, common water
              <lb/>about half a pint, and about two ounces of nutmeg <lb/>water, or any ſpirit; mix
              together, and take two <lb/>ſpoonfuls every three hours. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>At night take a little ſweat going to reſt, and the <lb/>next morning continue
              the mixture. Or if incon- <lb/>venient to make up the above medicine, or too poor
              <lb/>to get it, we recommend Salt Petre as an efficacious <lb/>as well as cheap
              remedy. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>We ſhall mention one inſtance of its utility. A <lb/>poor woman aſked advice for
              her huſband (a man <lb/>about forty years of age) who had a fever, with a <lb/>violent
              pain in his ſide, and was light-headed at <lb/>times. </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_19" n="19"/>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>We adviſed her to get an ounce of ſalt-petre, and <lb/>powder it; then to divide
              it into four equal parts, and <lb/>each of them into four others for ſo many doſes,
              <lb/>each of which will contain about half a drachm, <lb/>directing that ſhe ſhould
              give one of them, diſſolved <lb/>in a coffee diſh of ſage tea, ſweetened with ſugar to
              <lb/>his palate every three or four hours; and when he <lb/>had taken this ſalt, ſhe
              came and ſaid, that his fever <lb/>was gone; but that his cough remained. We then
              <lb/>adviſed her to give him about twenty drops of balſam <lb/>capivi, with powder
              ſugar, night and morning; and <lb/>he happily recovered. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>But if troubled with a cough, add, of ſperma-ceti <lb/>in powder two drachms;
              diſſolved with the yolk of <lb/>an egg, to be taken in the ſame manner. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Or, if that cannot be had, the following powder. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Take ſperma-ceti in powder, half an ounce; ſugar <lb/>and ſalt-petre each two
              drachms; mixt together, and <lb/>take as much as will lay on a ſhilling every three or
              <lb/>four hours in any liquid. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If bound, take the following opening mixture. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Take two drachms of ſenna leaves, boil in ten <lb/>ounces of common water to
              eight ounces; ſtrain off, <lb/>and add manna half an ounce, tincture of ſenna one
              <lb/>ounce; mix, and take two table ſpoonfuls every three <lb/>hours, till it
              operates. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>This medicine is eaſily prepared, and very handy <lb/>on many occaſions,
              eſpecially when the body calls for <lb/>a remedy of this nature; it is cooling as well
              as lax- <lb/>ative; waſhes its paſſage through the bowels, without <lb/>any griping or
              diſorder, and ſtands in need at the <lb/>ſame time of no over ſtrict regimen. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Thus far fevers in general; proceed we therefore <lb/>to thoſe more particular.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="italic align-center">
              <lb/>Of an Acute Inflammatory Fever. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THE young, robuſt plethoric habit, will ever be <lb/>moſt liable to
              inflammations; whilſt, on, the contrary, <pb xml:id="page_20" n="20"/>
              <lb/>in the weakly and infirm, the circulation cannot <lb/>readily be worked up to
              ſuch a pitch as is requiſite to <lb/>conſtitute a diſeaſe of an inflammatory kind; in
              both, <lb/>cold or obſtructed perſpiration is almoſt the only <lb/>occaſional cauſe.
              This fever may be eaſily known <lb/>from the conſtitution of the ſick perſon; a quick,
              <lb/>full and tenſe pulſe, hard beyond its natural ſtate; <lb/>florid countenance,
              with great heat and thirſt, acute <lb/>pains in the head, back and loins, &amp;c. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>To the cure of an inflammatory fever therefore it <lb/>is neceſſary, firſt, to
              take away about ſix or eight <lb/>ounces of blood, then give about fifteen grains of
              <lb/>Ipecacuanha in a cup of any liquid, and work it off <lb/>with camomile flower
              tea, having nothing after it <lb/>that night, but a little mulled wine to ſettle the
              <lb/>ſtomach. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Tartar emetic two grains, diaphoretic antimony, <lb/>ten grains, barley water,
              eight ounces; mix and take <lb/>two ſpoonfuls every four hours; and every now and
              <lb/>then about as much ſalt-petre as will lay on a ſhilling <lb/>diſſolved in the
              drink. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If all this ſhould not open the body, it will be ne- <lb/>ceſſary to add an
              emollient clyſter. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If at the end of the diſeaſe the pulſe ſhould flag, <lb/>diſcontinue the
              medicines, and uſe cordials. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If an intermiſſion ſhould happen, with gentle ſweats, <lb/>and turbid urine; the
              bark in ſmall doſes or rather <lb/>a decoction of it, may be thrown in. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Of a nervous Fever. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>THIS low nervous fever is directly oppoſite to <lb/>the acute inflammatory, and
              therefore muſt be dif- <lb/>ferently treated. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>It moſtly happens from profuſe evacuations, and <lb/>to thoſe of relaxed ſolids,
              and diſſolved watery fluids; <lb/>the pulſe, though quick, is here weak and low, the
              <lb/>heat of body but little beyond the natural, and the <pb xml:id="page_21" n="21"/>
              <lb/>ſymptoms in general of the ſpaſmodic kind, and in- <lb/>dependent of
              inflammation. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>In the one it becomes neceſſary to lower the im- <lb/>petus of the circulation,
              by evacuations and coolers; <lb/>in the other, the warm cordial, the ſtimulating me-
              <lb/>dicines are by all means adviſeable to excite the vis <lb/>vitæ, and promote ſuch
              a degree of fever as may <lb/>ſuffice for its expulſion. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Evacuations of blood, and by ſtool, can then be, <lb/>of no ſervice in the cure
              of a low fever, but a great <lb/>detriment. A gentle vomit in the beginning, and a
              <lb/>breathing ſweat throughout its continuance will be <lb/>uſeful. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>A warm, light, nouriſhing diet, and plenty of <lb/>generous wine will be
              expedient, with bliſters and ſi- <lb/>napiſms, or muſtard plaiſters and other drawers
              of <lb/>the feet, for the relief of the ſymptoms. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Firſt then give the ipecacuanha vomit, with the <lb/>mulled wine as before
              deſcribed; and going to bed, <lb/>half a drachm of mithridate. The next day the fol-
              <lb/>lowing mixture. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Take Venice treatle, two drachms, ſyrup of ſaffron, <lb/>half an ounce, ſimple
              mint water, eight ounces, <lb/>ſtrong cinnamon water, two ounces, volatile tincture
              <lb/>of valerian, two drachms, mix, and take two ſpoon- <lb/>fuls every three or four
              hours. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>To theſe may be added, as occaſion requires, a <lb/>little opiate camphire,
              contrayerva, valerian, cochi- <lb/>neal, warm aromatics, and ſome volatile ſalts; and
              <lb/>when better, the gum pills; but if towards the latter <lb/>end of the diſeaſe,
              when gentle ſweats break out, <lb/>and the urine becomes turbid or thick, the bark
              will <lb/>be attended with great advantage, though there ſhould <lb/>appear no
              intermiſſion. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_22" n="22"/>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="sc align-center space">
            <lb/>INTERMITTING FEVER, or AGUE. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>ACCORDING to the air, conſtitution and ſtrength <lb/>of the patient,
              intermittents frequently vary, ſome <lb/>will have a tendency to the inflammatory, or
              degene- <lb/>rate into an acute continual fever, eſpecially if too <lb/>hot a regimen
              has been uſed; which if it ſhould have <lb/>been the caſe, gentle cooling purges will
              reduce it, <lb/>and then give the bark with nitre joined with it. On <lb/>the
              contrary, intermittents will urge on the nervous <lb/>fever; in which caſe join the
              cordial aromatics, ſuch <lb/>as ſnake root, contrayerva, myrrh, camphire, and <lb/>the
              like, with the bark. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>TO cure an intermiſſion, the following is ad- <lb/>viſeable.—Beſt bark, one
              ounce, finely bruiſed; ſnake <lb/>root, two drachms, finely bruiſed; boil in common
              <lb/>water from a pint and a half to one pint, ſtrain it off, <lb/>and take four
              ſpoonfuls every three or four hours. <lb/>If it ſhould purge, add to each doſe five or
              ſix drops <lb/>of liquid laudanum; if it ſhould bind, about five or <lb/>ſix grains of
              powdered rhubarb; if want of appetite, <lb/>about five or ſix drops of elixir of
              vitriol. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>A variety of different medicines have been found <lb/>to ſucceed, but the
              preference has ever been given to <lb/>the bark; twelve drachms of which generally
              puts <lb/>by the fit, though it is neceſſary to continue a few <lb/>doſes more to
              prevent a return. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>One or two grains of Roman vitriol given, during <lb/>the intermiſſion, two,
              three, or four times in the <lb/>twenty-four hours; or about a drachm of allum,
              <lb/>with thirty grains of nutmeg, or ſnake-root, in <lb/>half a pint of warm ale or
              barley water has ſuc- <lb/>ceeded well. </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_23" n="23"/>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Intermitting Fevers, thoſe eſpecially whoſe fits re- <lb/>turn every other day,
              have been often cured with a <lb/>few doſes of cochineal, by taking about half a
              drachm <lb/>of it in powder, ſome time before the acceſſion of <lb/>each fit; and
              others have been recovered, by taking <lb/>five, ſix, or ſeven grains of the Virginian
              ſnake root, <lb/>three times on the days of intermiſſion, at about four <lb/>or five
              hours diſtance; and I have with ſucceſs ad- <lb/>viſed ſome of the poor to drink a
              quarter of a pint <lb/>of tea, made with the root of burdock, every third <lb/>or
              fourth hour, during the intermiſſions, ſweetened <lb/>with ſugar, or not ſweetened, as
              the patient chuſes. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Theſe ſort of intermittents allow a good opportu- <lb/>nity for taking the
              Peruvian bark, and that the poor, <lb/>thoſe great objects of our compaſſion and
              charity, <lb/>may have the benefit of that excellent remedy, at <lb/>the leaſt
              expence, adviſe the following method, viz. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>To buy an ounce of the beſt bark in powder, then <lb/>divide it into eight or
              twelve equal parts, and take a <lb/>doſe of it every third hour, during the
              intermiſſions, <lb/>beginning as ſoon as they are quite free from a fit, <lb/>in the
              following manner, viz. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Mix a doſe of the bark, with a tea cup of hot wa- <lb/>ter, with which it will
              mix eaſily; and when it is <lb/>cool enough, then let the patient drink it, and take
              <lb/>after it a glaſs of punch, made in the common way, <lb/>and take his meals at his
              uſual times. Suppoſe the <lb/>time for taking the bark happens at the time of din-
              <lb/>ing, let him firſt take the bark, and then eat his din- <lb/>ner. I have done ſo
              myſelf. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>We adviſe the patient to take the bark in the <lb/>night, as well as in the day,
              which I have done my- <lb/>ſelf ſeveral times, having a perſon to ſit up and wake
              <lb/>me, when the time for taking the bark comes. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If the patient can take a drachm of the bark for <lb/>a doſe, without finding his
              ſtomach loaded, let that <lb/>quantity be the doſe; and when he has taken one <pb
                xml:id="page_24" n="24"/>
              <lb/>ounce, though he miſſes the fit, yet let the bark be <lb/>prepared, and the doſes
              taken at four hours diſ- <lb/>tance. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>HECTIC FEVERS, <hi rend="italic">attended with Coughs or <lb/>Conſumptions</hi>. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>HECTIC Fevers with coughs, are commonly <lb/>called Conſumptions, on account of
              the great waſte, <lb/>or decreaſe of the bodies afflicted with them. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The ſymptoms, which are obvious, and neceſſary <lb/>conſequences of an ulcerated
              ſtate of the lungs, are <lb/>a cough, a copious ſpitting of a purulent-like mat-
              <lb/>ter, which is thrown up night and morning, and if <lb/>tried, ſinks in water. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Oppreſſion of the breaſt, bad appetite, thirſt great, <lb/>hectic fever,
              colliquative ſweats, which ſucceed night <lb/>and morning alternately, a lowneſs, and
              great diſ- <lb/>charge of urine, the pulſe becomes quick and ſharp, <lb/>the body
              pines, and is emaciated, and its ſeveral <lb/>functions totally impaired and decayed.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies.</hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THE air where the patient lies ought to be free <lb/>and pure, the conſtitution
              muſt be kept in action, and <lb/>take as much exerciſe every day as it can bear. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Horſe-riding, giving the body motion with little <lb/>fatigue, if convenient, is
              preferable to any carriage, <lb/>which ſhould be before dinner, elſe it proves
              hurtful. <lb/>Great care muſt be taken to prevent catching cold by <lb/>damp things or
              otherwiſe. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>A ſouthern voyage by ſea frequently cures, when <lb/>all things elſe fail,
              provided the proviſions are freſh; <lb/>and as milk cannot there be eaſily obtained,
              fruits, <lb/>broths and balſamics muſt ſupply the place. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>A proper regimen, with the patient's own endea- <pb xml:id="page_25" n="25"/>
              <lb/>vours, act moſtly towards the cure; a mind kept <lb/>eaſy, with varying objects
              to divert the attention; <lb/>yet it may be neceſſary to ſubjoin ſome ſerviceable
              <lb/>medicines. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Firſt, I would recommend for diet, light, but re- <lb/>ſtorative, and diluting
              drink. Milk, aſſes milk, (if <lb/>obtainable) water-gruel made of meal, or fine white
              <lb/>flour, with a little butter or ſugar, or cyder whey, <lb/>or barley water, or
              ground-ivy tea ſweetened with <lb/>ſugar or honey, acidulated with the juice of lemon,
              or <lb/>an apple boiled in a pint of water, with one large ſpoon- <lb/>ful of brandy,
              and ſweetened as before directed, as <lb/>neceſſary to promote the ſpitting up the
              phlegm. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Secondly, to remove the fever, give the following <lb/>medicine: </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Salt-petre, two drachms; cochineal, half a drachm; <lb/>pure water, half a pint;
              ſyrup of balſam, or ſugar, <lb/>or honey, ſufficient to pallate; brandy, or rather
              <lb/>rum, two ounces; mix theſe and take two ſpoonfuls <lb/>every third or fourth
              hour. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If there ſhould be a flux, then the following: </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Tincture of roſes, one pint; liquid laudanum, <lb/>twenty grains; drink a cupful
              often. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If reſtleſs at night, take ſtorax pill, four grains. <lb/>When there is great
              difficulty of breathing, the am- <lb/>noniac medicine, with the oxymel of ſquills,
              give <lb/>the moſt relief. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>ULCERATED LUNGS. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>THE SYMPTOMS are deſcribed in the laſt article. </p>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>COMPOUND powder of gum-tragacanth, one <lb/>ſcruple; ſalt-petre, ten grains; make
              a powder to <lb/>be taken in any ſoft liquid, four times a day. </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_26" n="26"/>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If the cheſt or ſtomach ſhould be ſore, emultions of <lb/>ſperma-ceti, or oil of
              almonds will be uſeful, as <lb/>well as twenty drops of the balſam capivi, night and
              <lb/>morning, and continued for ſome weeks, even after <lb/>well; and to ſtrengthen
              all the muſcular fibres and <lb/>veſſels of the body, cloſe with the preparation of
              <lb/>the bark, and elixir of vitriol. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>PESTILENTIAL DISORDERS. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THESE diſorders, which go under the different <lb/>names of morbid, malignant,
              putrid, peſtilential, <lb/>petechial, hoſpital, and goal fevers, differ only in a
              <lb/>degree from each other. They ariſe from many <lb/>cauſes, ſuch as foul air, or
              putrid animal and vege- <lb/>table effluvia, or from confined places, not properly
              <lb/>ventilated or kept clean, or frequently communi- <lb/>cated by contagion. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The ſymptoms in general are laſſitude and weak- <lb/>neſs, or loſs of ſtrength,
              an oppreſſion or pain in the <lb/>ſtomach, pulſe low or weak, bitter taſte in the
              mouth, <lb/>drowth, fœtid breath, a dejected mind, frequently <lb/>ſighing, wanting to
              vomit, great pain in the head, <lb/>back, and loins, tongue black, chaped, though at
              <lb/>firſt white, and ſmall ſpots about the ſkin, reſembling <lb/>the meaſles, but of
              a purple or livid colour. Eyes <lb/>heavy, yellowiſh and inflamed, and frequently pro-
              <lb/>fuſe ſweating. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>BLEEDING here is to be avoided as moſt dan- <lb/>gerous: and the firſt thing,
              clear the ſtomach by Ipe- <lb/>cacuanha wine, about one ounce, worked off with
              <lb/>camomile flower tea, and mulled wine at night. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Then begin and take the recipe preſcribed for in- <lb/>termitting fevers, and
              drink weak mountain whey, <pb xml:id="page_27" n="27"/>
              <lb/>with tincture of roſes plentifully acidulated, with the <lb/>elixir of vitriol.
              Likewiſe the following bolus, three <lb/>times a day, in ſome tormentile root tea, and
              ſweetened <lb/>with the fineſt ſugar. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Powder of valerian, ten grains; powder of ſnake <lb/>root, ten grains, cochineal,
              four grains, gum cam- <lb/>phire, five grains; ſyrup of ſaffron, a ſufficient quan-
              <lb/>tity to bind it. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If bound, the bowels ſhould be gently opened by <lb/>powdered rhubarb, in ſmall
              doles; and, if occaſion, <lb/>emolient clyſters; if a diarrhœ, or purging, cordial
              <lb/>reſtringents, and gentle opiates occaſionally; omit all <lb/>volatiles as
              prejudicial. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If any morbid quality of the blood diſcovers itſelf <lb/>by any ſymptom on the
              ſkin, it is an argument againſt <lb/>every evacuating remedy, which makes a revulſion
              <lb/>from the ſurface of the body; therefore never uſe <lb/>them for the cure of any
              cutaneous diſeaſe. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="sc align-center space">
            <lb/>St. ANTHONY's FIRE. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms.</hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>CHILLNESS, and ſhivering, great thirſt, reſt- <lb/>leſſneſs, the face ſuddenly
              ſwelled, becomes painful <lb/>and appears red and pimply, and the eyes are cloſed
              <lb/>with the ſwelling. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THE patient muſt loſe eight or ten ounces of <lb/>blood, which muſt be repeated
              if the ſymptoms con- <lb/>tinue ſtrong. Apply to the part a pultice of white
              <lb/>bread and milk, and a little hog's lard in it; let the <lb/>pultice be changed
              twice in a day; but flannels <lb/>wrung out of a ſtrong decoction of elder flowers ap-
              <lb/>plied warm afford the ſpeedieſt eaſe and relief; and <lb/>every other morning
              take the following purge, till <lb/>the diſorder is cured, viz. </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_28" n="28"/>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Glaubers ſalt one ounce, manna, half an ounce, <lb/>mix and diſſolve it in warm
              water for one doſe. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The diet in this diſeaſe muſt be very low, chiefly <lb/>water-gruel, or at moſt
              weak broth; all ſtrong liquors <lb/>and fleſh meat muſt be avoided as poiſon. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>APOPLEXY. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms.</hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>SHORT breathings, imaginary noiſes in the ears, <lb/>drowſineſs, loſs of memory,
              tremblings, ſtaggerings, <lb/>a giddineſs in the head, and dimneſs of ſight. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The diſeaſe at its height is a total deprivation of <lb/>all ſenſe and motion,
              reſpiration excepted, and even <lb/>that is performed with great difficulty. It
              greatly <lb/>injures the faculty both of the mind and body, and <lb/>is ſeldom
              perfectly curable. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies.</hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>CUPPING in the nape and ſides of the neck <lb/>is always uſeful, provided the
              ſcarifications are deep <lb/>enough to give a free paſſage to the blood; ſtimu-
              <lb/>lating clyſters and warm purges are alſo of ſervice, <lb/>as is the following
              electuary. Take half an ounce of <lb/>powdered heath valerian, and one ounce and an
              half <lb/>of conſerve of orange peel, and mix them together; <lb/>the doſe is the
              quantity of a nutmeg every four hours, <lb/>diſſolved in a cup-ful of roſemary tea.
              Apply a <lb/>ſtrong bliſter to the back and the legs. The diet <lb/>muſt be very
              ſparing. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>ASTHMA. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms.</hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>A laborious breathing, or obſtruction of the lungs <lb/>attended with great
              anxiety, and a ſtraitneſs about <lb/>the breaſt. </p>
          </div>
          <pb xml:id="page_29" n="29"/>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>BLEEDING, gentle vomits, a large bliſter applied <lb/>to the back or legs,
              ſlender diet and malt liquors to <lb/>be particularly avoided. Likewiſe frequently
              take <lb/>three large ſpoonfuls of the following mixture; two <lb/>drachms of gum
              ammoniacum in half a pint of <lb/>pennyroyal water, intermixed with an ounce of oxy-
              <lb/>mel of ſquills. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>BLOODY FLUX. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>SHIVERING, coldneſs, gripings, quick pulſe, in- <lb/>tenſe thirſt, greaſy ſtools
              frequently mixed with <lb/>blood and filaments which appear like melted ſuet. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>FIRST loſe blood, then take the following vomit: <lb/>Half a drachm of powder of
              ipecacuanha worked off <lb/>with camomile tea: daily repeat this vomit three or
              <lb/>four times. Malt and ſpirituous liquors muſt be <lb/>carefully avoided, and
              between the vomitings the <lb/>patient ſhould every hour take a large ſpoonful warm
              <lb/>of a drink made thus: Diſſolve half an ounce of <lb/>gum arabic, and half an
              ounce of gum tragacanth <lb/>in a pint of barley water, over a gentle fire. Cly-
              <lb/>ſters made of fat mutton broth are of great ſer- <lb/>vice. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="sc align-center">
            <lb/>STONE and GRAVEL. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>A ſuppreſſion, or ſtoppage of urine, may proceed <lb/>from various cauſes, ſuch
              as the kidneys, or the neck <lb/>of the bladder being inflamed, ſmall ſtones lodging
              <lb/>in the urinary paſſages, ſpaſms or contraction of the <lb/>neck of the bladder,
              &amp;c. </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_30" n="30"/>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>In all obſtructions, if the patient's ſtrength will <lb/>admit of it, draw off
              about eight ounces of blood, <lb/>give ſome cooling, gentle, opening medicines, with
              <lb/>a little ſweet oil, and foment the part with a decoction <lb/>of mallows, or
              camomile flowers; let there be drank <lb/>often ſome diluting liquor, with about forty
              nitre <lb/>drops in it, and every ſix hours, about one drachm <lb/>of Caſtile ſoap,
              diſſolved in any liquid, eſpecially if <lb/>ſmall gravel comes away with the urine, or
              it ſhould <lb/>be bloody; for when ſmall ſtones are lodged in the <lb/>kidneys, which
              comes away with the urine, it is <lb/>called gravel; but when they lodge ſome time in
              <lb/>the bladder, they collect together, form a body, <lb/>and accumulate freſh
              matter, begin to be too large <lb/>to paſs off with the urine, and then is called a
              ſtone. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>When afflicted with the ſtone, avoid all aliments <lb/>of a windy or heating
              nature, all ſalt meats, ſour <lb/>fruits, acids of all kinds, uſe every thing that
              pro- <lb/>motes the ſecretion of urine, and keeps the belly <lb/>open, artichoaks,
              aſparagus, lettuces, &amp;c. are pro- <lb/>per; and to drink milk and water, barley
              water, <lb/>decoctions of marſhmallows, parſley, liquorice, lin- <lb/>ſeed, or gin and
              warm water mixt, not too ſtrong; <lb/>uſe gentle exerciſe, and take ſoap lees,
              beginning <lb/>with thirty or forty drops, in a cup of lime water, <lb/>every night
              and morning, and increaſe the doſe re- <lb/>gularly to ſixty drops, as the ſtomach
              will bear. <lb/>Likewiſe nitre drops in marſhmallow tea, with gum <lb/>arabic; or take
              broom ſeed, finely ground, as much <lb/>in quantity as will lay on a ſhilling, in a
              gill of the <lb/>beſt white port, morning and evening. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>TAKE two ſcruples or calcined egg ſhells three <lb/>times a day, in a glaſs of
              any convenient liquor, drink- <lb/>ing after each doſe, a third part of the following
              de- <lb/>coction: </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_31" n="31"/>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Take two ounces of Caſtile ſoap, diſſolve it in a <lb/>quart of ſoft water, and
              ſweeten it according to your <lb/>taſte with honey, or loaf ſugar, If this decoction
              <lb/>is made in a copper veſſel, care muſt be taken that <lb/>it is well tinned. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The taking of theſe medicines muſt be continued <lb/>for ſome time after the
              complaint is removed, leſt any <lb/>part of the ſtone ſhould remain, which being rough
              <lb/>and unequal, might occaſion exquiſite pain. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>It is common, after a few days uſe of theſe medi- <lb/>cines, to have an increaſe
              of pain in making water, <lb/>at which time a ſoft diet, emollient drinks and reſt
              <lb/>are proper. For common drink milk and water, or <lb/>a decoction of marſhmallow
              roots, parſley and li- <lb/>quorice may be uſed; but if the perſon has been uſed
              <lb/>to ſtrong liquors, ſmall punch, made without acid, <lb/>may be drank ſparingly.
              Artichoaks, aſparagus, <lb/>ſpinage, lettuces, ſuccory, parſley, turnips, potatoes,
              <lb/>radiſhes, peas, &amp;c. may be ſafely uſed; but onions, <lb/>leeks, and celery,
              are to be preferred to all other <lb/>vegetables. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The patient ought to drink no more of any liquor <lb/>than is ſufficient to
              quench his thirſt, and he ſhould <lb/>hold his water as long as he can without great
              un- <lb/>eaſineſs, that it may have the longer time to act in <lb/>the ſtone. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If theſe medicines occaſion coſtiveneſs, it will be <lb/>neceſſary, now and then,
              to take a doſe of Glauber'<choice>
                <corr>s</corr>
                <sic/>
              </choice>
              <lb/>ſalt and manna. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>DROPSY. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THE dropſy is cauſed by many irregularities, <lb/>from drinking ſtrong liquors,
              from want of exerciſe, <lb/>from exceſſive evacuations, from too much loſs of <pb
                xml:id="page_32" n="32"/>
              <lb/>blood, from fluxes, &amp;c. It is ſo called from a pre- <lb/>ternatural ſwelling
              of the whole body, occaſioned by <lb/>a collection of water therein. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THE Patient muſt take a vomit, working it off <lb/>with a little camomile flower
              tea, and once a week <lb/>after, take jalop in powder, and cream of tartar <lb/>each
              half a drachm, in a cup of tea, working it off <lb/>with a little broth. In the
              intermediate days, take <lb/>ſalt of nitre, twenty grains, powder of ſquills ten
              <lb/>grains, mix together, take at night going to bed, <lb/>and the firſt thing in the
              morning, in a ſmall glaſs <lb/>of brandy, and let the belly be anointed with a little
              <lb/>warm oil twice every day, wearing a flannel next the <lb/>ſkin, abſtaining as
              much as poſſible from drink, eſ- <lb/>pecially weak and watery liquors, and quench the
              <lb/>thirſt with acids, ſuch as juice of lemons, oranges, <lb/>&amp;c. Let the food be
              dry, and of a healing quality; <lb/>toaſted bread, wild animals roaſted with garlick,
              <lb/>muſtard, onions, creſſes, horſe radiſh, and ſuch like; <lb/>tea biſcuit dipt in
              wine, or a little brandy, now and <lb/>then, will not only quench the thirſt, but
              prove very <lb/>nouriſhing; all diuretic medicines infuſed into <lb/>Rheniſh wine, are
              very ſerviceable. Or take the <lb/>large leaves that grow upon the ſtem of the
              artichoak, <lb/>wipe (not waſh) them; bruiſe them in a mortar, and <lb/>ſtrain out the
              juice through a linen cloth, forcing it <lb/>out; then put a pint of the juice into a
              quart bottle, <lb/>with a pint of Madeira wine, or Mountain, if you <lb/>cannot get
              good Madeira. Take three ſpoonfuls <lb/>every morning faſting, and three ſpoonfuls
              likewiſe <lb/>at going to bed; the doſe may be increaſed to four <lb/>or five, if the
              caſe requires, and the ſtomach will <lb/>bear it. Mind to ſhake the bottle well, when
              you <lb/>take it. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_33" n="33"/>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>CONVULSIONS. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>CONVULSIONS in children are thus to be diſ- <lb/>tinguiſhed. The face turns
              blackiſh, the eyes are <lb/>diſtorted, and the balls ſeem immoveable, the mouth
              <lb/>is drawn awry, and the fiſt is clenched. It is to be <lb/>obſerved that a
              drowſineſs uſually intervenes between <lb/>the fits. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>A BLISTER applied to the nape of the neck <lb/>is ſometimes ſerviceable. Or give
              a few hartſhorn <lb/>drops in a tea-ſpoonful of water frequently, or give <lb/>three
              or four drops of the tincture of wood ſoot in <lb/>the ſame manner. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>DIABETES. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>A great diſcharge of urine, of the ſmell, colour, <lb/>and taſte of honey, a
              decay of the whole frame, and <lb/>an intenſe thirſt. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>INFUSE for three days in one gallon of lime <lb/>water, three ounces of liquorice
              root, two ditto of <lb/>the ſhavings of ſaſſafras, and one of guaiacum. The <lb/>doſe
              is half a pint, three times a day. Lime water <lb/>is made by pouring twelve pints of
              boiling water on <lb/>one pound of unſlacked lime, which is fit for uſe as <lb/>ſoon
              as cold. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Or make allum whey, by boiling four pints of <lb/>milk over a ſlow fire, with
              three drachms of allum, <lb/>till it is turned into whey. When as much as will
              <lb/>fill a four ounce phial may be taken three times a <lb/>day. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_34" n="34"/>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>EAR-ACH. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>A pain in the ear, ariſing from a cold, or a <lb/>diſorder of the nerves of the
              head. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THE ſmoak of tobacco blown into the ear, or <lb/>a roaſted onion or ſalt put into
              the ear, will take <lb/>away the pain, but the head muſt be kept warm. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>DRY BELLY ACH. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THE Symptoms of the dry belly ach, or in other <lb/>words, the nervous cholic,
              are, coſtiveneſs, violent <lb/>pains in the bowels, coldneſs of the hands and feet,
              <lb/>faintings, a kind of paralytic diſorder, great anxiety <lb/>of mind, and
              tremblings. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THE warm bath is an admirable remedy, as is <lb/>balſam of Peru, given inwardly
              from twenty to forty <lb/>drops in a ſpoonful of powdered loaf ſugar, three or
              <lb/>four times a day; beſides which you may give the <lb/>following clyſter. Boil in
              a pint of water an ounce <lb/>of dried mallow leaves, half an ounce of camomile
              <lb/>flowers, and half an ounce of ſweet fennel ſeeds. Half <lb/>a pint of this
              decoction, with half an ounce of Epſom <lb/>ſalts, and two ſpoonfuls of ſweet oil muſt
              be uſed for <lb/>a clyſter, and repeated as often as neceſſary. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>YELLOW JAUNDICE. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>A yellowneſs of the whole body, and more par- <lb/>ticularly about the eyes,
              urine of a ſaffron colour, <lb/>ſtools almoſt white, bitterneſs of the tongue, vomit-
              <lb/>ing of galls, heavineſs and laſſitude of the limbs. </p>
          </div>
          <pb xml:id="page_35" n="35"/>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>TAKE the white of an egg, and two glaſſes of <lb/>ſpring water; beat them well
              together, and drink the <lb/>quantity off at a draught. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>It cools the lungs, which in this diſtemper are <lb/>always inflamed; expels the
              aſthmatic diſorder, which <lb/>alſo always, in ſome degree, afflicts the party
              diſeaſed; <lb/>it ſpeedily procures perſpiration, invigorates the animal <lb/>ſpirits,
              cauſes digeſtion, and creates an appetite. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>By theſe means the late lord Blakeney cured great <lb/>numbers in Ireland,
              Minorca, and in this kingdom; <lb/>and ſaid that he never knew it to fail. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>INDIGESTION. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>FREQUENT belchings, heart-burn, and an op- <lb/>preſſion or weight at the
              ſtomach. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/>Remedies. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>PYRMONT and Spa waters. Or from ten to <lb/>twenty drops of acid elixir of
              vitriol in a glaſs of <lb/>water, two or three times a day, or a large ſpoonful
              <lb/>of tincture of hiera picra, every day an hour before <lb/>dinner. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="sc align-center space">
            <lb/>INFLAMMATION of the BOWELS. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>A feveriſh complaint, a vomiting, a great coſtive- <lb/>neſs, and a burning pain
              in the belly. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>SPARE diets and weak broths ſhould be uſed. <lb/>Juice of lemons taken inwardly
              affords ſurprizing <lb/>relief; or let the patient loſe ten ounces of blood, and
              <lb/>have the bleeding repeated according to the urgency of <pb xml:id="page_36"
                n="36"/>
              <lb/>the complaint. Then, till the patient has had two <lb/>or three ſtools, give
              twice every day the following <lb/>clyſter: </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Take of dried mallow-leaves an ounce; camomile <lb/>flowers, and fennel ſeeds, of
              each half an ounce; boil <lb/>them in a ſufficient quantity of water to ſtrain off
              <lb/>about half a pint; then add two ounces of ſweet oil, <lb/>and it is fit for uſe. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>To eaſe the pain, and ſtop the vomiting, give ten <lb/>drops of liquid laudanum,
              in a little broth, every ſix <lb/>hours. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>MEASLES. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THIRST, drowſineſs, ſlight cough, chillneſs, <lb/>ſhivering, accompanied by a
              fever, great ſickneſs, <lb/>and an effuſion of tears. The little red ſpots, which
              <lb/>do not riſe above the ſurface of the ſkin, appear the <lb/>fourth day. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies.</hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THE diet and management to be the ſame as in <lb/>the ſmall pox; then bleeding
              and frequent purging; <lb/>and let the patient drink plentifully of the following
              <lb/>decoction.—Take pearl barley, raiſins and figs, of <lb/>each two ounces, ſtick
              liquorice bruiſed, half an <lb/>ounce: boil them in four quarts of water, till the
              <lb/>water is reduced to two quarts; ſtrain it for uſe, and <lb/>tincture it with a
              quarter of an ounce of ſalt pru- <lb/>nella. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
      <pb xml:id="page_37" n="37"/>
      <div type="part">
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A horizontal double-line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="size(1.5) align-center space">
          <lb/>Every Patient his own Doctor. </head>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>PART II. <lb/><hi rend="size(1.25) space">EXTERNAL DISORDERS. </hi>
        </head>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>PILES. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="space">
              <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE piles are of a two-fold nature, the bleeding
              <lb/>piles, and the blind piles; the former, when <lb/>there is any diſcharge, the
              latter, when there is not. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Perſons of a bulky ſize, who lead an inactive life, <lb/>and live high, are moſt
              ſubject to this diſeaſe, though <lb/>it is ſometimes hereditary, and then it attacks
              more <lb/>early in life than when it is accidental. They may <lb/>be occaſioned by an
              exceſs of bloody by ſtrong aloetic <lb/>purges, high ſeaſoned foods, by drinking great
              quan- <lb/>tities of wines, the neglect of any cuſtomary eva- <lb/>cuations, much
              riding, great coſtiveneſs, or any thing <lb/>that occaſions hard or difficult ſtools.
              Pregnant wo- <lb/>men are ſometimes afflicted with them. </p>
          </div>
          <pb xml:id="page_38" n="38"/>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>IF only little ſwellings within and without the <lb/>fundament, touch them with a
              little oil of amber. <lb/>Or, take lime water, four ounces, liquid laudanum, <lb/>half
              an ounce, mix together, and make a linament <lb/>to bathe the parts with it very
              often. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If they are bleeding piles, care muſt be taken <lb/>not to ſtop them too ſoon,
              eſpecially if they are pe- <lb/>riodical, and return frequently, as they prove
              ſalutary; <lb/>but if they continue in ſuch quantity as to waſte the <lb/>patient's
              ſtrength, hurt his digeſtion, or impair any <lb/>functions, then a proper regimen and
              aſtringent me- <lb/>dicines muſt check the diſcharge. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>A linen cloth dipped in camphorated ſpirits of <lb/>wine, may be applied to the
              parts, and a bread and <lb/>milk poultice, if exceſſively painful, or a little cool-
              <lb/>ing ointment of elder, equal parts of each mixed <lb/>together; a doſe of manna
              and ſalts, or ſena tea, or <lb/>ſome cooling phyſic given in the morning, and an
              <lb/>electuary made of one ounce of lenitive electuary, <lb/>flower of brimſtone, half
              an ounce, of cream of tar- <lb/>tar, two drachms, ſyrup of roſes, a ſufficient quan-
              <lb/>tity to mix together; then take the bigneſs of a nut- <lb/>meg twice a day,
              occaſionally. Leeches applied to <lb/>the part, or on the pile itſelf, gives great
              relief. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>GREEN WOUNDS. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THE appearance and nature of green wounds <lb/>muſt be various from the nature of
              the accident by <lb/>which they were occaſioned, or the weapons from <lb/>which they
              were received. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>DRESS them daily with yellow baſilicon ſpread <pb xml:id="page_39" n="39"/>
              <lb/>on fine lint, after fomenting them with a fomentation <lb/>made of ſouthernwood
              and wormwood, camomile <lb/>flowers, of each an ounce; bay leaves dried, half an
              <lb/>ounce. Boil them gently in ſix pints of water, and <lb/>ſtrain it off for uſe.
              Foment all green wounds as well <lb/>as old ſores with this before they are dreſſed
              every day. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>BITE of a MAD DOG. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>IT is neceſſary to mention the ſigns by which a <lb/>dog that is mad may be
              known. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>A mad dog is ſeemingly rapacious and thirſty, <lb/>yet eats and drinks nothing;
              his eyes are fierce and <lb/>flaming; he hangs down his ears, and thruſts out <lb/>his
              tongue; froths much at the mouth, and barks at <lb/>his ſhadow; oftentimes runs along
              ſad and anxious <lb/>without barking at all; frequently pants for breath, <lb/>as if
              tired with running; carries his tail bent inwards; <lb/>runs without diſtinction
              againſt all he meets, with <lb/>great fury, and bites; hurrying on in an haſty and un-
              <lb/>certain courſe. Dogs that are well are afraid and <lb/>fly, both at the ſight and
              barking of one that is <lb/>mad. The firſt mad ſymptom in a dog, is an un- <lb/>uſual
              trembling. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>With reſpect to the ſymptoms in perſons bit, they <lb/>are, principally, confuſed
              and miſchievous looks, and <lb/>an utter abhorrence of water. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies.</hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>MIX one pound of common ſalt in a quart of water, <lb/>and then ſqueeze, bathe,
              and waſh the wound with the <lb/>ſame for an hour, and not drink any of it; then bind
              <lb/>a little ſalt to the part affected for twelve hours. But <lb/>be very careful to
              apply it inſtantly after the bite of <lb/>the animal. </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_40" n="40"/>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Take the leaves of rue, picked from the ſtalks and <lb/>bruiſed, ſix ounces;
              garlic picked from the ſtalks and <lb/>bruiſed, Venice treacle and mithridate, and the
              ſcrap- <lb/>ings of pewter, of each four ounces; boil all theſe <lb/>over a ſlow fire,
              in two quarts of ſtrong ale till one <lb/>pint be conſumed; then keep it in a bottle
              cloſe ſtop- <lb/>ped, and give nine ſpoonfuls to a man or woman, warm, <lb/>ſeven
              mornings following, faſting, and ſix ſpoonfuls <lb/>to a dog. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>This will not fail, if it be given within a few days <lb/>after the biting of the
              dog. Apply ſome of the <lb/>ingredients from which the liquor was ſtrained to the
              <lb/>bitten place. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Bathing in the ſea, where the patient can be accom- <lb/>modated with
              conveniences, is likewiſe deemed an ad- <lb/>mirable remedy. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>To this we may add, that, <unclear>t</unclear>o cure the bite of a <lb/>viper or
              adder, if you will rub the part bitten with <lb/>ſome of the fat of the animal, it
              will prevent any bad <lb/>effects from ariſing; but if the fat of the animal can-
              <lb/>not be procured, warm ſallad oil will be attended with <lb/>the ſame good
              conſequences. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>CANCER. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THIS dreadful diſorder originates from a ſmall <lb/>tumour, which often remains
              for years without en- <lb/>creaſing, and does not change the colour of the ſkin.
              <lb/>However, when the humour becomes more active, <lb/>the ſwelling ſuddenly grows
              large, livid, round, un- <lb/>equal, painful, then breaks, and ſharp ſtinking ſores
              <lb/>ſucceed, which eat away the ſound parts, when the <lb/>lips of the wound become
              exceeding diſguſtful to <lb/>the ſight. This diſorder generally affecs the breaſts,
              <lb/>but ſometimes attacks the privities, ears, noſe, and <lb/>arm-pits. </p>
          </div>
          <pb xml:id="page_41" n="41"/>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>A quarter of a pound of guaiacum ſhavings muſt <lb/>be boiled in ſix pints of
              water, till the quantity is <lb/>reduced to four pints, a pint of which, milk warm,
              <lb/>muſt be drank daily. Fomentations of milk and <lb/>water, and poultices of white
              bread and milk muſt <lb/>be uſed externally, and the wounds ſhould be de- <lb/>fended
              from the cold air by a piece of fine linen, <lb/>ſpread with ſpermaceti ointment,
              which ſhould be <lb/>renewed twice or thrice a day. This ointment is <lb/>made thus.
              Take a quarter of a pint of the beſt <lb/>ſallad oil, a quarter of a pound of white
              wax, and <lb/>half an ounce of ſpermaceti. Melt them together <lb/>over a gentle fire,
              and afterwards keep them ſtir- <lb/>ring till the whole is cold. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>CHILBLAINS. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>CHILBLAINS are ſwellings on the hands and <lb/>feet, from exceſſive cold,
              accompanied with into- <lb/>lerable pains, prickings, itchings, heat, and redneſs.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>ON their firſt appearance bathe them with ſnow <lb/>water, if that can be
              procured, or hold them over <lb/>the ſteam of boiling vinegar. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If they grow ſore and break, uſe the fomentation <lb/>mentioned, in the article
              of green wounds, and then <lb/>apply a dreſſing of yellow baſilicon, mixed with a few
              <lb/>drops of ſpirits of turpentine, and ſpread on fine lint. <lb/>A ſparing diet
              ſhould be uſed, and the parts affected <lb/>kept warm. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_42" n="42"/>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>ITCH. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THE itch is moſtly communicated by infection, <lb/>and generally appears in ſmall
              watery puſtules about <lb/>the wriſts, and between the fingers, and affects the
              <lb/>arms, legs, thighs, &amp;c. is attended with intolerable <lb/>itching, when
              ſitting by the fire, but more particu- <lb/>larly when in bed; is never dangerous,
              unleſs ren- <lb/>dered ſo by neglect or improper treatment. It muſt <lb/>not be
              ſuddenly drove in; after cure, have proper <lb/>evacuations. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THE beſt medicine is ſulphur of brimſtone uſed <lb/>externally; or internally,
              take flower of brimſtone <lb/>in treacle or milk, every night and morning, and rub
              <lb/>the parts every night, going to bed, with an ointment <lb/>made of flower of
              brimſtone, two ounces, crude ſalt <lb/>ammoniac in fine powder, half an ounce, hog's
              lard, <lb/>a quarter of a pound, mixed together; the ſmell, if <lb/>diſagreeable, may
              be taken off by adding a few drops <lb/>of eſſence of lemons: if neceſſary, rub the
              whole <lb/>body; let it be done at different times; the linen <lb/>ſhould not be
              changed, and ſhould afterwards be well <lb/>dried and fumigated with brimſtone, to
              prevent a <lb/>freſh infection when cured, and three or four briſk <lb/>purges, at
              different times, taken; it will not be <lb/>amiſs to drink a glaſs of cream of tartar
              whey every <lb/>morning for a week or more, uſing wholeſome food <lb/>and obſerving
              cleanlineſs. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>SORE EYES. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms.</hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THE ſymptoms of ſore eyes are eaſily known, <lb/>being redneſs, a ſtiff
              gummineſs, a ſalt rheum or <pb xml:id="page_43" n="43"/>
              <lb/>water flowing from them, weakneſs of ſight, dim- <lb/>neſs, a painful heat in the
              eye-lids, and many others <lb/>unneceſſary to relate, as thoſe who feel them muſt
              <lb/>be well acquainted with their nature; proceed we <lb/>therefore to the </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies</hi>. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>WE ſhall here preſent our reader with the great <lb/>Sir Hans Sloan's celebrated
              remedies. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Take of prepared tutty, one ounce; of lapis hæ- <lb/>matitis prepared, two
              ſcruples; of the beſt aloes <lb/>prepared, twelve grains; of prepared pearl, four
              <lb/>grains; put them, into a prophyry, or marble mor- <lb/>tar, and rub them with a
              peſtle of the ſame ſtone <lb/>very carefully, with a ſufficient quantity of viper's
              <lb/>greaſe, or fat, to make a liniment; to be uſed daily, <lb/>morning or evening; or
              both, according to the con- <lb/>veniency of the patient. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The doctor preſcribes bleeding and bliſtering in <lb/>the neck, and behind the
              ears, in order to draw off <lb/>the humours from the eyes; and afterwards, accord-
              <lb/>ing to the degree of inflammation, or acrimony of <lb/>the juices, to make a
              drain by iſſues between the <lb/>ſhoulders, or perpetual bliſter. And for waſhing the
              <lb/>eyes, recommends cold ſpring water. And the beſt <lb/>inward medicines, which he
              has experienced, to be <lb/>conſerve of roſemary flowers; anti-epileptic powders,
              <lb/>ſuch as Pulvis ad Guttetam, betony, ſage, roſemary, <lb/>eye-bright, wild
              valerian root, caſtor, &amp;c. waſhed <lb/>down with a tea made of the ſame
              ingredients; as <lb/>alſo drops of ſpirit Lavandulæ Compoſit, and ſal. <lb/>vol.
              oleos. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If the inflammation returns, the Doctor ſays, <lb/>drawing about ſix ounces of
              blood from the temples, <lb/>by leeches, or cupping on the ſhoulders, is very
              <lb/>proper. </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_44" n="44"/>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The liniment is to be applied with a ſmall hair <lb/>pencil, the eye winking, or
              a little opened. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>FISTULA. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>A deep, winding, callous ulcer, with a narrow en- <lb/>trance into a ſpacious
              bottom, and yielding a ſharp <lb/>virulent matter. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/>Remedies. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>A quarter of a pound of elecampane root, three <lb/>quarters of a pound of fennel
              ſeeds, and a quarter <lb/>of a pound of black pepper; pound theſe ſeparately, <lb/>and
              ſift them through a fine ſieve; take half a pound <lb/>of honey and half a pound of
              powder ſugar, melt, the <lb/>honey and the ſugar together over the fire, ſcumming
              <lb/>them continually, till they become bright as amber, <lb/>when they are cool, mix
              and knead them into your <lb/>powder, in the form of a ſmall paſte. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The doſe is the ſize of a nutmeg, morning, noon, <lb/>and night; drinking a glaſs
              of wine or water after it. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If the above ſhould not ſucceed, immediate recourſe <lb/>muſt be had to a ſkilful
              ſurgeon. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>MORTIFICATION. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THE juices loſe their proper motion and ferment, <lb/>and thereby deſtroy the
              texture of the parts, and cor- <lb/>rupt. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies. </hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The part muſt be fomented every night and morn- <lb/>ing with hot flannels, wrung
              out, with the following <lb/>fomentation: </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_45" n="45"/>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Take lime water a pint, and diſſolve in it half an <lb/>ounce of crude ſal
              armoniac; then add three ounces <lb/>of camphorated ſpirits of wine. Afterwards apply
              <lb/>a poultice of ſtale beer grounds and oatmeal, moiſt- <lb/>ened with a little
              hog's lard: when the part begins <lb/>to ſuppurate, apply under the poultice a
              dreſſing of <lb/>black baſilicon inwardly. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Take a dram of the beſt Peruvian bark in fine pow- <lb/>der, every four hours in
              a gill of mountain wine. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>OLD ULCERS. </head>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="sc align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Symptoms.</hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>ULCERS are wounds or ſores of long continu- <lb/>ance, and their ſymptoms
              virulent matter iſſuing from <lb/>them. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>When any ulcer is of long ſtanding, it is dangerous <lb/>to dry it up, without
              ſubſtituting in the place of a <lb/>diſcharge, (which is become almoſt natural,) ſome
              <lb/>others; ſuch as purging from time to time, or cut- <lb/>ting an iſſue near the
              diſeaſed part. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>To forward the cure, ſalt meat, ſpices, and ſtrong <lb/>liquors muſt be moſt
              avoided: the uſual quantity of <lb/>fleſh meat ſhould be leſſened, and the body be
              kept <lb/>moderately open, by a vegetable, or milk diet; and <lb/>if the ulcers are in
              the legs, it is of great importance <lb/>to keep in a lying poſture; for negligence in
              this <lb/>material point changes the ſlighteſt wounds into <lb/>ulcers, and the moſt
              trifling ulcers into obſtinate <lb/>and incurable ones. To cure which, </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Take a quarter of a pound of baſilicon, and an <lb/>ounce and an half of oil of
              olives, and mix therewith <lb/>half an ounce of verdigreaſe; dreſs the ſore with this
              <lb/>ointment, ſpread open a little tow, after fomenting it <lb/>well with a decoction
              made of camomile flowers, and <lb/>mallow leaves. Take frequently a doſe of cooling
              <lb/>phyſic, and live regularly. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="11"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
