<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Wallis: Annual oration, delivered March 8th, 1790.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>George Wallis</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Annual oration, delivered March 8th, 1790, before the Medical
              Society, Bolt Court, Fleet Street, London, by George Wallis, M. D. one of the fellows,
              and lecturer on the theory and practice of Physic.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T21951</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T21951"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for G.C.J. and J. Robinson, Pater-Noster Row,
                  M.DCC.XC.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1790</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="5"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="58"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3308249320</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K030760.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="General treatises"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <head rend="align-center size(1.5)">
          <lb/>PREFACE. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>WHEN the members of the Medical Society, on the day of my delivering this Oration be-
          <lb/>fore them, did me the honor to requeſt its publica- <lb/>tion, I conſidered the
          requeſt as a complimentary cuſtom uſual on that occaſion, and as ſuch received it;
          however, on a ſecond and third application, by order of their Council, amongſt whom
          freedom of debate on any ſubject is expected, and all compli- <lb/>ment and ceremony
          incompatible with their cha- <lb/>racters in that department, I was induced to believe
          that they might have perceived ſome hints, at leaſt, not unworthy further conſideration;
          and, notwith- <lb/>ſtanding, <pb xml:id="page_3" n="iv"/>
          <lb/>I had at firſt asked permiſſion to make ſuch additions, as to me appeared requiſite,
          on find- <lb/>ing they would be infinitely too diffuſive for a work of this nature, and as
          I could claim protection only by adhering ſtrictly to thoſe ſentiments and opinions which
          were to them delivered, and upon which they could alone found a wiſh for my making them
          more public; in that ſtate I now offer them with- <lb/>out alteration, reſerving the
          elucidation of ſeveral parts for ſome future occaſion, as they form the baſis of a larger
          work, which I have an intention of completing as I can find opportunity. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Should therefore the following ſheets, which now make their appearance to the world,
          in compliance with the deſire of the Medical Society, fortunately add the ſlighteſt ray of
          conſequence to that collective Body, and afford the candid Reader ſatisfaction, my labor
          will be amply compenſated; particularly as, <pb xml:id="page_4" n="v"/>
          <lb/>at the ſame time, it will evince the deference I pay to the Impartiality — Judgement
          — and Abilities of ſeveral Members of that inſtitution—as well as the ſenſe of that duty I
          owe to the Community in general. </p>
        <signed>G. W. </signed>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_5"/>
        <head rend="sc align-center">
          <lb/>ADDENDUM. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>After <q rend="quotes">heart,</q> in Page 37, line 7, <hi rend="italic">inſert</hi>
          <q rend="quotes">muſcular fibres.</q>
        </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_6"/>
      <head rend="align-center size(1.5)">
        <lb/>ANNUAL ORATION. </head>
      <salute>Gentlemen, and Fellow-Aſſociates! </salute>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>AS I conſider this inſtitution formed on the broad baſis of univerſal good, the parent
        of general utility, not of ſelfiſh oſtentation; and as this, with its ſiſter kingdoms, may
        be juſtly ſtiled the emporium of medical knowledge, where many of its members, the brighteſt
        luminaries of the Hippocratic ſchool, have not diſdained to convey their diſcoveries to the
        world in the common language of this country — a language, if not eſteemed ſo conciſe and
        elegant, yet full as comprehenſive, <hi rend="italic">full</hi> as replete with deſcrip-
        <lb/>tive <pb xml:id="page_7" n="2"/>
        <lb/>powers, as any of which Greece or Rome could ever boaſt; and as it muſt be allowed,
        that opi- <lb/>nions in any art ought to be delivered in modes diveſted of all ambiguity and
        embarraſſment, cer- <lb/>tainly, conſidering our own vernacular language poſ- <lb/>ſeſſed of
        theſe advantages, as being the moſt fami- <lb/>liar to a very great majority of this
        audience, <hi rend="italic">though learned,</hi> before which I have the honor to preſent
        myſelf, and perfectly underſtood by all — it will not, I hope, be conſtrued want of reſpect,
        or a careleſs inattention to the conſequence and dignity ever annexed to profeſſional bodies
        thus aſſociated, that I have preſumed to deviate from ſome of my predeceſſors, dropping the
        tinſelled trappings of Roman grace, for the plain, but more uſeful orna- <lb/>ment of
        Engliſh perſpicuity; and making uſe of a vehicle, eaſy, as common, to communicate my ob-
        <lb/>ſervations, in order that I might, through the whole of them, be readily followed, and
        not in any part miſunderſtood. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_8" n="3"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For however familiar may be the Latin idiom to readers converſant in that language —
        however eaſy to comprehend in its niceſt points — to au- <lb/>ditors, not conſtantly
        habituated to that ſtyle of delivery, the familiarity, and ready comprehenſion, would be
        defective. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On theſe conſiderations I found ſome ſmall claim to your approbation; and, conſidering
        the arduouſ- <lb/>ness of the preſent undertaking, I flatter myſelf, I ſhall ſtill farther
        experience your indulgence. Unimpreſſed with this idea, inſurmountable indeed would have
        been the difficulties which preſented themſelves to my reflection; but conſcious that
        liberality of ſentiment, with men of erudition, directs the judgement, and ſoftens the
        ſeverity of criticiſm, every obſtacle vaniſhed, and diffidence gave way to duty. For it has
        ever been, <hi rend="italic">with me,</hi> a fixed principle, and laid down as a law
        immutable; That, as every individual in the medical hemiſ- <lb/>phere is ſo cloſely, and ſo
        neceſſarily united to the <pb xml:id="page_9" n="4"/>
        <lb/>welfare of mankind, he is bound by the ſtrongeſt ties, natural and ſocial, to exert his
        abilities, how- <lb/>ever weak, when called to promote any laudable purpoſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Connected therefore as I am with the members of this medical inſtitution — <hi
          rend="italic">with you,</hi> who actuated by philanthropy, make ſcience the pleaſurable
        labour of your lives — and that part of ſcience your parti- <lb/>cular ſtudy, the moſt noble
        which can engage the purſuit of man — framed by Divine Wiſdom for the relief and
        preſervation of the human ſpecies — preventing, mitigating, and ſubduing many of their
        corporal calamities — your wiſhes I conſidered as a mandate — and, as you have thought
        proper to elect me to this office of honor — an office, which would have been far better
        ſupplied by many of your aſſociates — It became me, therefore, to re- <lb/>flect, what there
        was in my power to offer, which might in ſome, though perhaps too ſmall a degree, compenſate
        for your loſs of time and attention to <pb xml:id="page_10" n="5"/>
        <lb/>the conſequential avocation of your profeſſion, which candour would ſubject you to on
        this occa- <lb/>ſion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Converſant as you are with, aſſiduouſly engaged in, the acquiſition of medical
        knowledge, and happy in the promulgation, <hi rend="italic">two points</hi> fell only to my
        elec- <lb/>tion; either to furniſh <hi rend="italic">ſomething new,</hi> for the im-
        <lb/>provement: or <hi rend="italic">ſomething</hi> to clear what might retard and clog the
        progreſs of the healing art. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Of the former, I fear, I have little to lay before you worthy of your attention; even
        vanity cannot ſuggeſt to, or perſuade, me, that any thing has oc- <lb/>curred to my
        obſervation, with which you may not, perhaps, have been long acquainted — My ani-
        <lb/>madverſions muſt therefore, in a great meaſure, be confined to the latter; wherein I
        ſhall only preſume to offer ſome hints, which taken into the conſidera- <lb/>tion of
        ſuperior abilities, may aſſiſt, ſo am I led to hope, in extending our particular art to that
        goal <pb xml:id="page_11" n="6"/>
        <lb/>of perfection, at which human exertions are limited only to arrive. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And, as many obſtacles have been thrown in the way, which have prevented us from riſing
        to that achme, as much as human endeavours, united with ſtrong mental powers and
        indefatigable aſſiduity, judiciouſly conducted, would have accompliſhed; the greateſt of
        which has been the thirſt after theoretic knowledge — it might appear neceſſary to take a
        ſurvey of the progreſs of the medic art, from the time of the divine old man, the firſt
        founder of ſyſ- <lb/>tematic phyſic, to the preſent æra, in which ſome poſſeſs <hi
          rend="italic">no leſs merited, no leſs exalted characters.</hi> But to an audience like
        this, ſo well verſed in the hiſ- <lb/>tory of phyſic, and all its branches, it would pro-
        <lb/>perly be conſidered, a work of preſumption and ſupererogation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I ſhall therefore only, as it is neceſſarily con- <lb/>nected with my ſubject, take a
        conciſe view of the <pb xml:id="page_12" n="7"/>
        <lb/>means by which HIPPOCRATES acquired his know- <lb/>ledge, extenſive as it was,
        conſidering the period in which he lived — in the ſame manner, ſhew how his ſucceſſors
        rather retarded than promoted the utility of the Æſculapian Art, particularly as ſome of our
        Profeſſors ſteer not altogether clear of ſimilar errors; and then attempt to point out,
        where ſome of our preſent modes require the aid of correc- <lb/>tion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>HIPPOCRATES enriched his mind from obſerva- <lb/>tion, and founded his practice on
        facts, ſimply as they appeared to him; who being bleſt with <hi rend="italic">quick</hi>
        perception, <hi rend="italic">nice</hi> diſcrimination, and <hi rend="italic">profound</hi>
        ſaga- <lb/>city, made ſuch diſcoveries — deduced ſuch certain conſequences — and raiſed his
        ſuperſtructures on ſo ſolid a foundation, that he left behind him <hi rend="italic"
          >ſtupen∣dous</hi> monuments of great abilities;—<hi rend="italic">Abilities,</hi> ſo ſu-
        <lb/>perior to his predeceſſors, and cotemporaries, that future ages purſued with avidity,
        and retained with confidence, many documents framed <hi rend="italic">in the in∣fancy</hi>
        <pb xml:id="page_13" n="8"/>
        <lb/>of his art — and happy had it been for later times, had his plan, ſimple and eaſy as it
        was, been religiouſly obſerved. But, alas! <hi rend="italic">Man,</hi> as if uncon-
        <lb/>ſcious of his own weakneſs, <hi rend="italic">vain enough</hi> to ſuppoſe he could
        diſcover the <hi rend="italic">arcana naturæ</hi> — inveſtigate firſt cauſes — and carry his
        curious eye into the darkeſt labyrinths, began to prefer ingenuity to obſerva- <lb/>tion;
        and mounted on the wings of falſe fame, diſ- <lb/>regarded the humble paths of modeſt
        inquiry, and built on vain and conjectural hypotheſis;—and what the reſult? Theory aroſe
        after theory; and each ſucceeding one, though it corrected the errors of that which had been
        before adopted, ſtill, like its predeceſſor, ſunk into oblivion; leaving behind few remains
        worthy of practical purſuit.— </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Nor is it difficult to account for the cauſe, why ſuch different conſequences awaited
        theſe different modes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Hippocrates</hi>, it is ſaid, by the moſt rigid obſer- <lb/>vation of
        every action and motion of nature, <hi rend="italic">of things</hi>
        <pb xml:id="page_14" n="9"/>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">which did in reality exiſt,</hi> acquired a wonderful know-
        <lb/>ledge of the genuine diſpoſition of Diſeaſes; and <lb/>by carefully comparing the ſame
        ſort of diſtempers, <lb/> and their various minute motions in different Pa- <lb/>tients, and
          <hi rend="italic">all</hi> the circumſtances and accidents, <lb/>which uſually preceded,
        and attended them; he <lb/>could readily foretel an approaching malady, and <lb/>after its
        invaſion give a right judgement of its pro- <lb/>gress and event. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As Nature terminated diſeaſes, when left to her- <lb/>ſelf, he obſerved her mode, <hi
          rend="italic">firſt</hi> tracing the manner <lb/>in which the ſymptoms, in thoſe that were
        acute, <lb/>ſucceeded one another; hence aroſe his art of pre- <lb/>ſaging, and thus he
        formed his method of curing <lb/>them, by imitating Nature when ſhe proved herſelf
        defective.—From theſe obſervations, he diſcovered <lb/>the uſe of <hi rend="italic"
          >Bleeding—Scarifications—Iſſues—Setons,</hi>
        <lb/>where, in ſimilar complaints, Nature ſupplied <hi rend="sc"> Hæ- <lb/>morrhages</hi>,
        and <hi rend="sc">Abscesses</hi>—<hi rend="italic">Artificial Diarrhœas,
          <lb/>—Sudorifics—Emetics—Diaphoretics—Diuretics,</hi> &amp;c. be- <pb xml:id="page_15"
          n="10"/>
        <lb/>cauſe he found ſhe, by ſome of theſe means, relie- <lb/>ved the conſtitution under
        particular circumſtances: <lb/>hence then he became her humble imitator, con- <lb/>ſcious,
        that ſhe alone was the moſt judicious di- <lb/>rectress. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But the Theoriſts, forming of themſelves a ſet of <lb/>principles, PRINCIPLES, <hi
          rend="italic">the mere coinage of diſtem- <lb/>pered reaſon,</hi> from them deduced all
        their arguments, <lb/>ſupported all their practice, and endeavoured to <lb/>prove Nature
        obedient to laws ſo founded. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Hence the incongruous, elementary, atomical <lb/>ſyſtems of <hi rend="italic"
          >ſucceeding Sects</hi> — hence the conceits of <lb/>an <hi rend="italic">Helmont</hi> —
        the whimſicalities of a <hi rend="italic">Paracelſus</hi> — <lb/>hence a variety of <hi
          rend="italic">chemical chimæras,</hi> and all the <lb/>inconſiſtencies of <hi
          rend="italic">hydraulic,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mechanic ſubtlety;</hi>
        <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">hence</hi> fell medicine into ſhameful diſrepute, it
        <lb/>becoming more the pride of cavilling ſcepticiſm, <lb/>and ſcholaſtic vanity, to build
        ingenious, though fal- <lb/>lacious doctrines, than after detecting error, labour- <lb/>ing
          <pb xml:id="page_16" n="11"/>
        <lb/>to purſue Nature through her plain and humble <lb/>paths. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And it appears aſtoniſhing to a reflecting mind, <lb/>that notions ſo ridiculous,
        practices ſo abſurd, ſhould <lb/>be countenanced in later times; when it is known, <lb/>that
          <hi rend="italic">all</hi> the labours of the ancients, as well as mo- <lb/>derns, are
        chiefly valuable for the ſimple recitals <lb/>they contain, <hi rend="italic">founded</hi>
        on obſervation, <hi rend="italic">collected</hi> from <lb/>appearances, and <hi
          rend="italic">delivered</hi> with candour: hence the <lb/> præeminence of an <hi
          rend="italic">Hippocrates, Aretæus, Trallian, <lb/>Aurelianus, Celſus, Tulpius, Lommius,
          Morgagni, Sy- <lb/>denham,</hi> and ſome others of more modern date; <lb/>whom to mention,
        might be conſidered as indeli- <lb/>cate, and the reſult of adulation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And indeed this ſimplicity, the more it is pur- <lb/>ſued, the more ſtrongly it
        convinces us of its uti- <lb/>lity; affording the moſt certain, perhaps the only
        <lb/>proper, method of acquiring, and communicating <lb/>medical information. For the
        theories of the preſent <pb xml:id="page_17" n="12"/>
        <lb/>day, though fraught with no ſmall degree of plauſi- <lb/>bility, will not ſtand the
        teſt of critical inquiry; they <lb/><hi rend="italic">all</hi> appear to be <hi
          rend="italic">too generally</hi> applied, in fevers <hi rend="italic">par-
          <lb/>ticularly.</hi> —Can we ſuppoſe, that in ſuch, as from <lb/>their commencement to
        their termination are at- <lb/>tended with profuſe ſweating, or a moiſt ſoft skin, <lb/>a
        conſtriction of the cuticular pores takes place?— <lb/>In thoſe, where the circulation is
        languid—the <lb/>action of the vaſcular ſyſtem torpid—the proſtration <lb/>of ſtrength
        ſudden and extreme, that an <hi rend="italic">active</hi> ſti- <lb/>mulus is the cauſe?—Or,
        in thoſe where no oppreſ- <lb/>ſion, load, nauſea, ſickneſs at the ſtomach, or un-
        <lb/>eaſiness in the inteſtines—no catarrhal or pulmonic <lb/>affections manifeſt
        themſelves, that they deduce <lb/>their origin from too copious and morbid ſecretion <lb/>of
        the mucus in thoſe organs? Surely not. Yet, <lb/>theſe, by different claſſes of
        practitioners, are con- <lb/>ſidered as the proximate cauſe of febrile <lb/>affections, and
        applied in common to all. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_18" n="13"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But within theſe manſions, ſuch a theoretic caco- <lb/>ethes appears not to be
        nurtured. If we examine the <lb/>nature of the proceedings within theſe walls adopt-
        <lb/>ed, what is the roof, by which we are ſheltered, <lb/>but that of an <hi rend="sc">Ædes
          Æsculapiana</hi>? If we advert <lb/>to the public product of your application, what are
        <lb/>your memoirs, ſo juſtly enumerated amongſt the <lb/>moſt valuable labours of the medic
        art, but the <hi rend="sc"> ta- <lb/>bulæ Æneæ templorum</hi>, ornamented by ſimpli-
        <lb/>city, and ſupported by truth. <note place="bottom" n="*">* It muſt be obſerved, that,
          at this period, the Author had not <lb/>ſent any papers on medical ſubjects to the
          Society. </note>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Nor need we take up much time in furniſhing <lb/>proofs of the ſuperiority of ſuch a
        ſcheme over every <lb/>other, which has been produced by the fertility of <lb/>human
        invention. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>View but our Engliſh Hippocrates, SYDENHAM; <lb/>he, by recalling this mode, not only
        contended with, <lb/>but conquered, a theoretic world, notwithſtanding <pb xml:id="page_19"
          n="14"/>
        <lb/>the powerful oppoſition he met with, invidious, as <lb/>violent; and we find his
        deſcriptions ſtand at this <lb/>hour unſhaken, nor can be overthrown but by the <lb/>hand of
        Heaven, when medicine ſhall be no more. <lb/>So firmly ſupported are they by unerring truth;
        ſo <lb/>ſimply, yet ſo juſtly, are they delivered; that they <lb/>are to all intelligible —
        by all valued — by all <lb/>quoted: even thoſe, who, wild with hypotheſis, <lb/>leave
        nothing behind them but reliques ſimilar to <lb/>theſe, which can attract our attention, or
        merit our <lb/>obſervation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Still, notwithſtanding we are convinced of the de- <lb/>captive notions by which ſome
        of our early prede- <lb/>ceſſors were governed — notwithſtanding we can <lb/>view the
        efforts of our cotemporaries not perfectly <lb/>conſiſtent in the application of their
        ſpeculative opi- <lb/>nions — notwithſtanding the advantages, unknown <lb/>to former ages,
        which daily are preſented in every <lb/>branch of medical philoſophy; which are diſcover-
        <lb/>able by ſlight obſervation, and may be truly arranged <pb xml:id="page_20" n="15"/>
        <lb/>with the <hi rend="italic">cauſæ evidentes.</hi> We avail not ourſelves of <lb/>theſe
        advantages, or apply them ſufficiently, to ren- <lb/>der our modus medendi as perfect as it
        might be. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There is too great, too general a ſolicitude in <lb/>ſearching after <hi rend="sc"
          >Specifics</hi>, and inquiring into the <lb/>nature of the ſemina morbi, as if the former
        did <lb/>exiſt—or the latter were within the reach of <lb/>human inveſtigation. We ſeem to
        be more anxious <lb/>about the <hi rend="sc">Agentia Mirifica</hi>, than the <hi rend="sc"
          >Agenda</hi>, as if the <lb/>latter were completely underſtood; that they were <lb/>is
        devoutly to be wiſhed; for they come more ma- <lb/>terially under our conſideration; at
        leaſt it appears <lb/>to me a truth irrefragable, that were we to pay the <lb/>ſtricteſt
        attention to the conſtitution, ſtudy more mi- <lb/>nutely its parts, dependencies, moving
        powers and pe- <lb/>culiarities, practice would be diveſted of many errors, <lb/>with which
        it too unfortunately at preſent abounds. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>However, that we may be enabled to prove the <lb/>validity of this aſſertion, we ſhall
        attempt to ſhew <pb xml:id="page_21" n="16"/>
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">the Fallacy of the first of these Pursuits— <lb/>the Impossibility of
          demonstrating the nature <lb/>of the second, in general</hi> — and, <hi rend="sc">the real
          uti- <lb/>lity of attending closely to the third, and <lb/>its mode of being applied</hi>,
        in order to add to the <lb/>improvement of the Art. </p>
      <p rend="align-center">
        <lb/>And, <hi rend="sc">First</hi>, </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>No idea, perhaps, has done more real injury, <lb/>than <hi rend="italic">that of
          Medicines acting ſpecifically in conquering <lb/>Diſeaſes</hi>—Of this truth, a very
        ſuperficial examina- <lb/>tion will convince us: for it retards our reſearches <lb/>in
        inveſtigating their full and true powers — it pre- <lb/>vents us, conſequently, from
        extending thoſe powers <lb/>ſo as to be as diffuſively uſeful as they might — it <lb/>lays
        the foundation for a thouſand deceptions; <lb/>cauſing us to attribute particular
        conſequences to ma- <lb/>terials, which do not from thence, in reality, origi- <lb/>nate,
        and keeping their true ſource hid from our ob- <lb/>ſervation —nor is this all; it does
        worſe — it often, <lb/>by occaſioning delay, increaſes the malady, reme- <pb
          xml:id="page_22" n="17"/>
        <lb/>dies thus conſidered, are pretended to ſubdue, nay <lb/>frequently generating diſorders
        of a more delete- <lb/>rious nature; overturning that firſt and ſalutary <lb/>caution, which
        directs us in all our efforts, if we fail <lb/>to do good, to do no harm.— <q rend="quotes"
          >Is artis medicæ ſco- <lb/>pus eſt; ut hominem a <hi rend="italic">tot gravibus malis</hi>
          liberet; <lb/>ideoque Medicus <hi rend="italic">nullo modo</hi> nocere, nedum Vitam
          <lb/>deſtruere, aut Sanitatem lædere debet, utpote quum <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Medicina</hi> non <hi rend="italic">nocendi,</hi> ſed <hi rend="italic">juvandi,</hi>
          ſit Scientia. </q>
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Hoffmannus</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Indeed the miſchief ceaſes not here; it proves <lb/>detrimental in another view; for it
        places the cre- <lb/>dulous Philoſopher, and Phyſician, on a footing with <lb/>the impudent
        and ignorant Empiric, and too often <lb/>throws ſuch an odium on the Art itſelf, that Pro-
        <lb/>feſſors of the firſt eminence are frequently held in <lb/>contempt, and treated with
        ridicule, by the injudi- <lb/>cious and illiterate, who fly with confidence to the
        <lb/>cabinet, and depend upon the preſuming arrogance <lb/>of every plundering impoſtor. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_23" n="18"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Still, ſtrange as may be the appearance, painful <lb/>the reflection to an informed
        mind, why ſhould it <lb/>be matter of ſurprize? Do not the Phyſician and <lb/>Medicaſter too
        often aſſign the ſame reaſon for their <lb/>ſucceſs, <hi rend="sc">the specific power of
          their applied an- <lb/>tidote</hi>, and build on the ſame fortuitous exhibi- <lb/>tion?
        And under ſuch circumſtances, the modeſt <lb/>diffidence of the one can never, with the
        million, <lb/>ſtand againſt the bold buſtling ignorance of the <lb/>other—for men of weak
        diſcriminating powers, of <lb/>which <hi rend="italic">nine tenths</hi> of mankind conſiſt,
        at leaſt if we <lb/>confine them to medical underſtanding, will give <lb/>credit to the
        opinions of creatures of their own <lb/>level, and place, as Indians with their painted pa-
        <lb/>gods, confidence in, and pay large tribute to, things <lb/>their folly and ſuperſtition
        have ſet up. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But notwithſtanding the credulity in this point of <lb/>many profeſſors of the art, <hi
          rend="italic">Men</hi> held in the higheſt <lb/>eſtimation adopting ſuch ideas, handing
        them down <lb/>to poſterity, and having them received by ſucceed- <pb xml:id="page_24"
          n="19"/>
        <lb/>ing generations—is it not ſingular, that not <hi rend="italic">one</hi> ſpe- <lb/>cific
        has ever yet been diſcovered, out of the num- <lb/>ber which have acquired the appellation? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It has been, and is now, by ſome, thought due <lb/>to the Bark in an intermittent
        fever—to Quickſilver <lb/>and its preparations in the Syphilis; but in reality, <lb/>even
        theſe merit no ſuch diſtinction: for let us ask, <lb/>Do they in all caſes, as if poſſeſſed
        of ſpecific <lb/>power they would, become infallible? Or, will they <lb/>by any means
        prevent the acceſſion of theſe diſtem- <lb/>pers? Practice proves the contrary; for they
        will <lb/>not alone always cure theſe complaints—and men <lb/>have been ſeized with
        intermittents whilſt under a <lb/>courſe of Bark—and the lues venerea with a mer-
        <lb/>curiated habit. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As well might modeſty and judgement be united <lb/>to the names of <hi rend="italic"
          >M</hi>*******, <hi rend="italic">G</hi>******, or <hi rend="italic">any other <lb/>
          empirical depredators</hi> with which this metropolis is <lb/>loaded; as well might
        infallibility be added to <pb xml:id="page_25" n="20"/>
        <lb/>every noſtrum-monger, as ſpecific powers in curing <lb/>diſeaſes, <hi rend="italic">in
          all conſtitutions,</hi> to any medicine. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Indeed, if we ſearch into the practice of men <lb/>highly elevated in their profeſſion,
        who retain ſuch <lb/>a ſpecies of abſurd faith, we ſhall find ſuch glaring
        <lb/>contradictions—circumſtances militating ſo diametri- <lb/>cally againſt, and ſo totally
        ſubverſive of theſe opi- <lb/>nions, that we muſt be convinced of the fallibility <lb/>of
        ſuch a dogma. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For it is not uncommon to have accounts pub- <lb/>liſhed by ſome of the efficacy of a
        medicine in cer- <lb/>tain complaints, which cures, they tell us, <hi rend="sc"> specifi-
          <lb/>cally</hi>, to which are tacked a long catalogue of caſes <lb/>in proof; whilſt at
        the ſame time, in the hands of <lb/>others of equal eminence, tried under ſimilar cir-
        <lb/>cumſtances, no ſuch ſurprizing effects are manifeſt- <lb/>ed. Need I, to what I have
        already mentioned, add <lb/>the accounts of <hi rend="italic">arſenic, hemlock, deadly
          night-ſhade, <lb/>henbane, flores cardamines, flores zinci, foſſile</hi> alkali, <pb
          xml:id="page_26" n="21"/>
        <lb/>and ſome others, which have been foiſted upon <lb/>the world under ſuch a pretence? All
        having work- <lb/>ed miracles under the direction of ſome, whilſt others <lb/>have failed in
        the adminiſtration. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To what are we to attribute this diverſification? <lb/>Can we diſpute the abilities of
        the authors? It <lb/>would be conſidered preſumptuous.—Can we doubt <lb/>their veracity? It
        would be thought illiberal.—Dare <lb/>we think they are attempting to acquire ſame from
        <lb/>falſe principles? It would be conſtrued invidious. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>What are we to conjecture? Certainly that no <lb/>ſuch ſpecifics exiſt; and that thoſe
        who were fa- <lb/>vourers of ſuch an opinion, unwilling, or unable to <lb/>purſue their
        reſearches, were happy in having ſo <lb/>eaſy a ſupport to reſt upon; or, uninclined to
        leſſen <lb/>their conſequence, by receding from ſentiments once <lb/>adopted, and publicly
        ſanctioned by their fiat, con- <lb/>deſcended to ſuffer ſcience to be cloathed in an
        <lb/>unintelligible jargon, and lead men, credulous as <pb xml:id="page_27" n="22"/>
        <lb/>themſelves, to believe it was impoſſible to proceed <lb/>farther, pleaſed as well with
        the phantom, as the <lb/>reality of knowledge. Hence was a check given to <lb/>particular
        inquiries, by implicit confidence being <lb/>paid to hoary-headed obſtinacy, I had almoſt
        ſaid, <lb/>cunning, creeping under the cloak of falſe expe- <lb/>rience: hence was the
        healing art impeded in its <lb/>progreſs by ſuch a belief; and hence a few charac- <lb/>ters
        called great, made thouſands appear little, and <lb/>live in the ſhade of indolence and
        obſcurity. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Examine but the works of <hi rend="italic">Galen, Diaſcorides, <lb/>Oribaſius, Meſſuë,
          Boerhaave,</hi> and almoſt all the wri- <lb/>ters of the Materia Medica of former ages,
        and <lb/>compare them, with what has been written by ſome <lb/>of the lateſt authors, who
        have made real experience <lb/>the teſt of their opinions, you will find, that a
        <lb/>multiplicity of errors, from time to time, have been <lb/>tranſmitted from one to
        another, forming a con- <lb/>temptible farrago of ſpecific abſurdities.—View but <lb/>the
        imaginary powers beſtowed on <hi rend="sc">Bezoar</hi> and <hi rend="sc">Saf-</hi>
        <pb xml:id="page_28" n="23"/>
        <hi rend="sc">
          <lb/>fron</hi>, two out of the numberleſs inſtances, which <lb/>might be produced. What
        mighty virtues have not <lb/>been attributed to the former, by men renowned for <lb/>medical
        ſagacity? So multifarious, ſo efficacious, <lb/>that almoſt all powerful medicines, or,
        thoſe ima- <lb/>gined ſuch, were called Bezoardics; and what from <lb/>faithful experiment
        is it now proved? one of our <lb/>moſt imperfect abſorbents. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>What has not been ſaid of Saffron? Receiving <lb/>for its ſuppoſed amazing ſpecific
        powers, the pom- <lb/>pous names, <hi rend="italic">Aroma Philoſophorum—ſanguis Herculis—
          <lb/>Rex vegetabilium—Panacea vegetabilis—hortus Lætitiæ— <lb/>medicina Triſtitiæ</hi>—and
        many more, given in ſmall <lb/>quantities. Indeed the great <hi rend="sc">Boerhaave</hi>
        conſiders <lb/>a few drops of the extract of Saffron, inſpiſſated only <lb/>to the
        conſiſtence of oil, and taken in a glaſs of <lb/>rich wine, as highly exhilarant and
        cordial. How <lb/>different from the experience of this day! for ex- <lb/>cept in very large
        doſes, ſaffron is not known to <pb xml:id="page_29" n="24"/>
        <lb/>produce any effects, and of theſe accounts are very <lb/>rare and doubtful. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But as an apology for this credulity, might it not <lb/>be called fanaticiſm? It has
        been aſſerted, that the <lb/>means, by which medicines produced their effects, <lb/>at leaſt
        thoſe to which were attributed a ſpecific <lb/>power, were impoſſible to be detected and
        account- <lb/>ed for; and indeed the ſame notion is too prevalent <lb/>at this day, in many
        caſes. To ſuch a height is it <lb/>carried, that an <hi rend="italic">arcanum
          ſcrophuloſum</hi> has been pro- <lb/>poſed <hi rend="italic">even</hi> to the members of
          <hi rend="italic">this</hi> Society; ſo fla- <lb/>grant is folly in her attempts, yet
        meets, neverthe- <lb/>less, with ſuch enormous encouragement; and, <lb/>though aſſociated
        with ignorance, and ſupported by <lb/>preſumption, is ſo ſucceſſful, it is no wonder that
        <lb/>crude inexperience ſhould be led to conclude he <lb/>might palm his noſtrum on this
        Inſtitution; for <lb/>great medic characters, ſo called at this time, we <lb/>have ſeen
        ſwell the catalogues, and enrich the liſts <lb/>of great Impoſtors. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_30" n="25"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>However, to prove the fallacy of this opinion, let <lb/>us examine one medicine, which
        has long been held <lb/>replete with ſpecific power, and which claims more <lb/>the title,
        could ſuch be allowed, than any other <lb/>medicine with which we are acquainted, if we ex-
        <lb/>cept Quickſilver; we ſhall by that means detect the <lb/>errors accruing from ſuch an
        idea, and perceive the <lb/>benefits ariſing from the diſcovery of its true action
        <lb/>—Benefits, which ſhould ſtimulate us in all caſes <lb/>to ſimilar inquiries: I mean the
          <hi rend="sc">Bark</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This was long conſidered to cure Intermittents <lb/><hi rend="italic"
        >ſpecifically</hi>—that is, we know not how—by ſome la- <lb/>tent inexplicable power; and
        indeed ſuch was the <lb/>confidence placed in this miraculous drug, ſo thought,
        <lb/>incomprehenſible as aſtoniſhing, that in caſes of this <lb/>kind, it was
        indiſcriminately exhibited—though very <lb/>often productive of great miſchief—till from
        long <lb/>continued, and often repeated trials, ſome of the <lb/>more judicious obſervers
        found, that this ſpecific <lb/>power was not always in Intermittents an inoffen- <pb
          xml:id="page_31" n="26"/>
        <lb/>ſive, much leſs a certain curative agent, not even <lb/>of the ſame complaint at
        different times in the ſame <lb/>perſon: hence it became neceſſary to inquire, from
        <lb/>whence this deviation aroſe, and in which ſtate of <lb/>the complaint it might be
        productive of the greateſt <lb/>ſucceſs; and it appeared to be when the conſtitu- <lb/>tion
        had been harraſſed, and the vaſcular ſyſtem ſo <lb/>far oppreſſed, as to be debilitated by
        the preceding <lb/>malady, or was, <hi rend="italic">ab initio,</hi> in that ſtate—For given
        at <lb/>firſt, when the conſtitution was in full vigor, it pro- <lb/>duced very dangerous
        effects, converting quotidians, <lb/>and tertians, into continued Fevers, aggravating, in-
        <lb/>ſtead of alleviating the febrile ſymptoms, and form- <lb/>ing a variety of other
        diſtreſſing conſequences. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On conſidering theſe phænomena, it was manifeſt, <lb/>that what was thought its
        ſpecific power, depended <lb/>upon ſome exertion which occaſioned the ſyſtem to <lb/>act,
        under ſome circumſtances, with too much force, <lb/>by increaſing the vaſcular tone.—Hence
        men, imbi- <lb/>bing this idea, laboured to abate the activity of the <pb xml:id="page_32"
          n="27"/>
        <lb/>conſtitution, by bleeding, purging, &amp;c.—or ſuffered <lb/>it to be weakened by
        delay, before they exhibited <lb/>this medicine, which was then almoſt always ſuc-
        <lb/>ceſſful, unleſs prevented by ſome conſtitutional de- <lb/>fect, that at the ſame time
        required for its allevi- <lb/>ation or ſubduction ſome attention. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It appears therefore obvious, that the virtue of <lb/>this medicine lay not in its
        correcting or deſtroying <lb/>the miaſma, or virus, producing the Intermittent, but <lb/>in
        the exertion of its tonic power; hence a peculiar <lb/>ſtate of the conſtitution was
        neceſſary,—and hence <lb/>the neceſſity of knowing that ſtate before we can <lb/>promiſe
        ſucceſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thus we ſee the particular power of this <hi rend="italic">univer- <lb/>ſally allowed
          ſpecific</hi> was developed, by obſervation <lb/>and experience; and there remains no
        doubt of the <lb/>Bark producing generally, I might have ſaid always, <lb/>the diſagreeable,
        and ſometimes dangerous effects <lb/>above ſpecified, if given too early, or perſiſted in—
          <pb xml:id="page_33" n="28"/>
        <lb/>without it brings on ſome debility at firſt, as it ſome- <lb/>times does, by becoming
        purgative: and it may be <lb/>laid down as an invariable rule in practice, that where
        <lb/>there is in the habit ſtrong vaſcular action, and an <lb/>inflammatory diatheſis of the
        blood, which are, I take <lb/>it, generally conjoined, Bark univerſally does harm,
        <lb/>—where the contrary conſtitution is prevalent, uni- <lb/>verſally good, if no topical
        defect impedes, or coun- <lb/>teracts its action: nor does the Bark being ſucceſſful <lb/>in
        ſome local inflammatory complaints, at all inva- <lb/>lidate the force of the argument; for
        in thoſe caſes, <lb/>the diſorder itſelf is not an active, but a paſſive in-
        <lb/>flammation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Similar arguments might be adduced to the ſame <lb/>purpoſe, proving the known action
        of Quickſilver, <lb/>and its ſaline compounds, capable of producing its <lb/>good effects,
        inſtead of its imaginary <hi rend="italic">ſpecific powers,</hi>
        <lb/>and of ſome others. But what I have advanced will, <lb/>I hope, prove ſufficiently
        ſatisfactory to ſhew, that <lb/>by this idea of medicines acting ſpecifically, no ſmall <pb
          xml:id="page_34" n="29"/>
        <lb/>impediment has been thrown in the way of medical <lb/>improvement: for men, ſatisfied
        with this <hi rend="sc">lusus</hi>, this <lb/><hi rend="sc">larva rationis</hi>, practiſed
        from principles falſely <lb/>founded, nay, <hi rend="italic">very often,</hi> without any
        principles at all <lb/>—occaſioning great loſs of time, and not only doing <lb/>miſchief by
        injudicious application, but keeping the <lb/>extenſive powers of many active medicines
        immerſed <lb/>in obſcurity. Hence, thoſe formerly adminiſtered in <lb/>one malady only, to
        which their <hi rend="italic">ſpecific power</hi> was <lb/>ſuppoſed to be ſingularly
        adapted, we now find, <lb/>their modes of action being brought to light, in <lb/>a variety
        of others extremely uſeful and ineſti- <lb/>mable. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Yet it is very extraordinary, that men flying from <lb/>inquiries after properties it
        may be in their power <lb/>to diſcover, ſhould ruſh forward in purſuit of what <lb/>lies far
        beyond their reach, the <hi rend="sc">Nature of the Se- <lb/>mina Morbi</hi>, the ſecond
        point appropriated for diſ- <lb/>cuſſion. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_35" n="30"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That ſuch an attempt ſhould be made in the early <lb/>periods of an art, while the
        profeſſors were almoſt <lb/>totally ignorant of the nature of the human ma- <lb/>chine, with
        regard to its moving powers, and ſym- <lb/>pathic affections—knew little of the animal
        œcono- <lb/>my—of what different parts the body was formed; <lb/>how they were actuated by
        each other, and by what <lb/>laws they were governed—at a time when philoſo- <lb/>phy was
        ſearching after the Principia Rerum, is not <lb/>to be wondered at. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But, conſidering this inquiry has been ſet on foot <lb/>ever ſince the prevalence of
        Hippocrates' idea of the <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes"><hi rend="italic">Calidum</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">ſalſum;</hi>—<hi
            rend="italic">Calidum</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">acidum;</hi>—<hi rend="italic"
            >Calidum</hi> &amp; <lb/><hi rend="italic">amarum,</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">alia
            innumerabilia:</hi>
        </q> a period of above <lb/>two thouſand years, and has ever continued in the <lb/>ſame
        point of uncertainty. Is it not ſurprizing then, <lb/>that men ſhould for ages perplex
        themſelves in the <lb/>attempt to make diſcoveries, ſo much above the <lb/>power of human
        underſtanding?—that they ſhould <lb/>vainly diſſipate their time in endeavouring to detect
          <pb xml:id="page_36" n="31"/>
        <lb/>the component parts of materials, which are in gene- <lb/>ral too minute to be
        collected—in all, too ſubtle to <lb/>come within the limits of man's ſcrutinizing abilities? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Knowing theſe things, is it not ſtill more aſto- <lb/>niſhing to hear men talk of the
        acidity and alkaleſ- <lb/>cency of the materies morbi; and otherwiſe ſpeci- <lb/>fying the
        particular nature of the acrimony, pro- <lb/>ductive of eruptive complaints? to aſſert
        poſitively, <lb/>that the venereal virus is an alkali, and propoſe to <lb/>cure diſorders
        from that cauſe with muriatic acid, <lb/>traverſing through all the diverſified mazes of the
        <lb/>human body, and there making neutral ſalts by the <lb/>ſpecific combinations? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Yet, ridiculous as is this attempt; fantaſtic this <lb/>enthuſiaſm, ſome modern
        anatomiſts hold up the <lb/>certainty of ſuch diſcoveries, and form from thence <lb/>ſchemes
        of practice, curable and infallible, implant- <lb/>ing in young inexperienced minds, an <hi
          rend="sc">ignis fatuus</hi>, <lb/>unprofitable as viſionary. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_37" n="32"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Let Philoſophers of ſuch a deſcription go in queſt <lb/>of atoms, and the diverſified
        modification of matter, <lb/>mount air balloons, ſeek medical knowledge in the
          <lb/>clouds—<hi rend="italic">Aſtra petant, quomodo formentur,</hi>—be it ours <lb/>to
        inquire how the effects produced by matter, in <lb/>its combined and morbid ſtate, are to be
        remedied, <lb/>and to ſuch heated imaginations be the advice of <lb/><hi rend="sc"
          >Celsus</hi> recommended.— <q rend="quotes">Rationalem quidem puto <lb/>medicinam eſſe
          debere; inſtrui verò ab evidenti- <lb/>bus cauſis; obſcuris omnibus, non à cogitatione
          <lb/>artificis, ſed ab ipsâ arte rejectis. </q>—Advice, ſo <lb/>pregnant with unerring
        truth;—fraught with ſuch <lb/>ſtrong conviction, that on this point it is needleſs to
        <lb/>dwell any longer—the futility of ſuch inquiries—the <lb/>impoſſibility of attaining the
          <hi rend="italic">quid deſideratum,</hi> are ſo <lb/>conſpicuouſly evident to the eye of
        common ſenſe, <lb/>primâ facie, that they need no arguments to be ad- <lb/>duced in proof.
        For what underſtand we more of <lb/>the particular nature of the virus creative of the
        <lb/>Plague—Small Pox—Pemphigus—Cancer—than <pb xml:id="page_38" n="33"/>
        <lb/>the firſt obſervers of theſe diſeaſes?—Virus, which <lb/>might be examined, if any
        could, from the copi- <lb/>ouſness of the matter produced: but we, like them, <lb/>form our
        judgement only from the effects. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It will be more to our purpoſe to examine how <lb/>much greater benefit will be derived
        to mankind, <lb/>by paying attention to that, upon which, to be of <lb/>any ſervice, our
        applications muſt act; for certainly <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">human machine itſelf</hi> is
        the grand object of the <lb/>Phyſician's conſideration; and the <hi rend="italic">moving
          powers</hi> of <lb/>that inſtrument, with what I ſhall, for the preſent, <lb/>call their
          <hi rend="italic">appendiculæ,</hi> the things which require his <lb/>attention, and which
        being too much neglected in <lb/>our deſcriptions of caſes, has retarded, and ſtill re-
        <lb/>tards the progreſs of the healing art. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By <hi rend="sc">the moving Powers</hi>, I mean <hi rend="italic">the muſcular
          <lb/>Fibres</hi> and <hi rend="italic">vaſcular Syſtem poſſeſſed of Irritability</hi>—
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">nervous Syſtem of Incitability</hi>— and <hi rend="italic">the
          ſangui- <pb xml:id="page_39" n="34"/>
          <lb/>nary maſs of Fluids, of the Vis animans &amp; ſervans <lb/>Naturam.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By the <hi rend="sc">Appendiculæ</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Lungs, Stomach, Inteſ-
          <lb/>tines, Uterus, Kidneys,</hi> &amp;c. parts which, affected, have <lb/>ſome influence
        on the moving powers, with reſpect <lb/>to their action. The <hi rend="italic">Brain,</hi>
        and <hi rend="italic">Heart</hi> I include in <lb/>the nervous and vaſcular ſyſtem. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By the incitability, as applied to the nerves, I <lb/>would be underſtood that power
        which is capable <lb/>of being put into action by immateriality, ſuch as <lb/>mental
        affection—ſympathy; though it may be put <lb/>into motion by material ſtimulus; to which
        Irrita- <lb/>bility, <hi rend="italic">itſelf abſtractedly conſidered,</hi> is only
        obedient; <lb/>though that may be alſo rouzed by the connection <lb/>of parts, wherein it
        reſides, with the nervous ſyſ- <lb/>tem, and by means of the nerves thus put into ac-
        <lb/>tion, and ſupported. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_40" n="35"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But, in order to form a proper idea of what I <lb/>mean for your conſideration, I muſt
        beg leave to <lb/>take a ſurvey of the machine, according to my di- <lb/>viſion, in the
        enjoyment of perfect health. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Now in this caſe, the principles of which it is <lb/>formed, muſt be in a ſtate
        exactly, or pretty nearly <lb/>proportioned to each other; ſo that one may aſſiſt <lb/>in
        promoting and ſupporting the vigor of the other, <lb/>and producing thoſe effects with eaſe,
        and conſtancy <lb/>for which they were ordained. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The moving ſolids of the human machine muſt <lb/>have ſuch firmneſs, pliability, and
        elaſticity, as to <lb/>enable them to anſwer to the impulſe of the given <lb/>Irritability. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Irritability of ſuch a nature as to be kept <lb/>in action by the nervous
        incitability. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_41" n="36"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The nerves to be ſo formed, as perpetually to <lb/>ſupply their power, when and where
        wanted, with <lb/>regularity. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The blood and fluids in ſuch quantity, and of <lb/>ſuch conſiſtency, as to receive the
        vis animans, re- <lb/>tain and transfuſe it through the whole ſyſtem in <lb/>an invariable
        current—and ſo bland, that they <lb/>may produce no defect in the ſecretory or excretory or-
        <lb/>gans, ſo as to impede them in their duty. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And the Appendiculæ, ſo complete in their pow- <lb/>ers, that they may perform their
        actions to which <lb/>they are allotted, with conſtancy and freedom. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>While matters are thus conducted, the machine <lb/>remains in perfect health; but if a
        defect ariſes in <lb/>one or more of theſe particulars, diſeaſes ſucceed in <lb/>proportion
        to the magnitude of the defect—and of <lb/>different natures, agreeable to the parts
        affected, <lb/>and their connections, and the changes brought on <pb xml:id="page_42" n="37"/>
        <lb/>in them, which may be either partial or general, <lb/>or idiopathic or ſymptomatic; and
        the cauſe of ſuch <lb/>defect will ariſe from the imperfections, in ſome of <lb/>the
        ſources, from whence the active powers deduce <lb/>their origin, immediately or ſecondarily.
        And as <lb/>we conclude, that the ſources of all activity, are <lb/>either the brain,
        medulla ſpinalis, heart, or blood— <lb/>ſo in ſome of theſe we ſhall find ſomething contrary
        <lb/>to a ſtate of nature, in its moſt perfect form; or a <lb/>derangement in ſome of the
        appendiculæ, by which <lb/>theſe ſources are diſordered. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But that I may be more perfectly underſtood, I <lb/>ſhall treſpaſs only a very little
        on your patience, to <lb/>ſupply two or three ſhort, though common, caſes, <lb/>by way of
        elucidation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Suppoſe <hi rend="italic">a man of ſtrong ſtamina—great vaſcular
          <lb/>irritability—ſtrong equable nervous incitability, abound- <lb/>ing with blood,
          copious and tenacious,</hi> has perſpiration <lb/>obſtructed by what is called <hi
          rend="sc">catching cold</hi>. We <pb xml:id="page_43" n="38"/>
        <lb/>are all acquainted with the general reſult. The mat- <lb/>ter which ought to paſs off
        by the perſpirable pores, <lb/>is retained in the habit; the vaſcular ſyſtem expe-
        <lb/>riences a plenitude—a quick circulation is produced— <lb/>Irritability increaſed—and
        febrile ſymptoms ſucceed: <lb/>here the immediate ſource lies in the heart, and
        <lb/>vaſcular ſyſtem, excited by a ſtimulus from the oc- <lb/>caſional cauſe, conſtriction
        of the cuticular pores; <lb/>and that by the more remote, the application of <lb/>cold;—and
        if there ſhould be in ſuch a conſtitution, <lb/>any defect in the brain, lungs, &amp;c. or
        any other in- <lb/>ternal organ, or part, a topical affection will be the <lb/>conſequence
        of the inflammatory kind, which will <lb/>increaſe and ſupport the fever; or ſhould any of
        <lb/>the organs be affected in the firſt inſtance, that af- <lb/>fection will occaſion the
        ſame effect; and this ariſes <lb/>alſo from the ſource above ſpecified. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But ſhould the remote cauſe operate on one, <hi rend="italic">of a <lb/>weak—relaxed
          habit—poſſeſſed of quick nervous incita- <lb/>bility, but a ſmall portion of vaſcular
          irritability, and <pb xml:id="page_44" n="39"/>
          <lb/>a thin ſate of fluids, with a paucity of blood;</hi>
        <lb/>the conſequences will not be ſo violent—The febrile af- <lb/>fections will be of the
        ſlow kind, attended with <lb/>more nervous ſymptoms, the pulſe will be quick, <lb/>but
        languid; the heat in a ſmall degree increaſed, <lb/>but not ſo permanent, accompanied by
        ſpaſms of <lb/>various parts; depreſſion or ſinking of the ſpirits, <lb/>and ſeldom any
        topical inflammation—here then the <lb/>nervous ſyſtem will be more affected, diſcovered by
        <lb/>the languor of the moving powers, load, and hea- <lb/>viness of the head, coldneſs of
        the extremities, and <lb/>ſuch other ſymptoms, as indicate <hi rend="sc">the source of
          <lb/>motion</hi>, <hi rend="italic">the nervous Syſtem,</hi> the part oppreſſed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But ſuppoſe, laſtly, <hi rend="italic">a Man of good ſtamina, with <lb/>a weak vaſcular
          Irritability,</hi> tho' <hi rend="italic">ſteady, nervous Inci- <lb/>tability,</hi> and
          <hi rend="italic">Blood of a tolerable denſity,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">in mode-
          <lb/>rate quantity,</hi> under the preſent circumſtances—what <lb/>will from thence occur? </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_45" n="40"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The circulation of the Blood will not be ſo greatly accelerated, as in the firſt
        inſtance—the ex- <lb/>tremities will be cold—the perſpiration obſtructed, <lb/>though not in
        ſo great a degree—uneaſy ſenſations <lb/>of coldneſs, and heavineſs of the head—diſturbed
        <lb/>and reſtleſs nights—oppreſſions on the præcordia— <lb/>chillneſs, and fluſhings of heat
        not continued, or <lb/> regular—dejection of ſpirits—and affections, ſome- <lb/>what
        approaching to delirium. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thus we find, from the <hi rend="italic">ſame immediate cauſe,</hi>
        <lb/>different effects will be produced; and they may be <lb/>varied, as the different
        combinations in the conſti- <lb/>tution happen—and we muſt to this add, as the <lb/>blood
        and fluids are in ſuch a particular ſtate to re- <lb/>ceive the vis animans more or leſs
        copiouſly, or to <lb/>transfuſe it more or leſs freely, the effects may be <lb/>increaſed or
        diminiſhed in a proportionate degree— <lb/>or as it may be, more or leſs acrimonious, for
        acri- <lb/>mony always adds a ſtimulus, particularly to the <lb/>vaſcular ſyſtem. Though
        ſome may exert at the <pb xml:id="page_46" n="41"/>
        <lb/>ſame time as a ſedative power on the nerves, and <lb/>therefore the additional ſtimulus
        not be ſo percep- <lb/>tible. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Beſides, we know that the inteſtines, lungs, liver, <lb/>kidneys, bladder, uterus,
        &amp;c. have ſuch univerſal <lb/>connections with the whole machine, particularly <lb/>the
        two former, that they can in many inſtances <lb/>tranſmit their affections ſympathetically
        to the whole, <lb/>or ſome parts of the body which lie at a diſtance; <lb/>hence then, as
        they are more or leſs affected, ſo will <lb/>be the moving powers in adequate proportions:
        in- <lb/>ſtances of which are obſervable in ſome ſymptoma- <lb/>tic, inflammatory,
        catarrhal, hectic, remittent, ver- <lb/>minoſe fevers, &amp;c. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Now, as is the nature of the moving powers; as <lb/>are the different combinations; as
        is the ſtate of the <lb/>fluids, with reſpect to their acrimony or blandneſs, <lb/>texture,
        and capability of receiving and transfuſing <lb/>the vis animans; as is the ſtate of the
        appendiculæ <pb xml:id="page_47" n="42"/>
        <lb/>and muſcular ſtamina, ſo do conſtitutions vary, and <lb/>ſo are different effects
        produced by ſimilar cauſes; <lb/>which we ſee often occur in epidemic, and other
        <lb/>complaints, where, though the leading ſymptoms <lb/>may be ſimilar in a great degree,
        the concomitants <lb/>will be different, and put on various appearances, <lb/>as we find in
        the recitals of the ſame complaints by <lb/>different authors: hence ariſe many of the
        ſpecies <lb/>and varieties of different genera of diſeaſes; hence <lb/>a deviation in our
        modus medendi, and hence the <lb/>good effects of one medicine in ſome inſtances at <lb/>one
        time, which produce no ſuch benefit at another, <lb/>in complaints conſidered as ſimilar:
        and hence, per- <lb/>haps, alſo ariſe the good or bad effects of the ſame <lb/>medicine
        given in different doſes, and likewiſe the <lb/>neceſſity of forming different combinations
        to make <lb/>it act with certainty and ſucceſs in different conſti- <lb/>tutions. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Let us, therefore, take a ſurvey of the effects of <lb/>medicines in different doſes,
        or differently com- <lb/>bined, <pb xml:id="page_48" n="43"/>
        <lb/>and ſee what concluſions we may from thence deduce. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Opium, in full doſes, inſtead of proving anti-ſpaſ- <lb/>modic, anodyne, or narcotic,
        has often created other <lb/>diſtreſſing ſymptoms; and ſo far from taking off ſpaſms,
        <lb/>alleviating pain, or procuring ſleep, occa- <lb/>ſioned nauſea, vertigo, and
        reſtleſſneſs, whilſt in <lb/>ſmaller doſes it has procured every deſired purpoſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mercury alſo, given in a ſimilar manner with re- <lb/>ſpect to the doſe, has alſo
        occaſioned diſagreeable <lb/>conſequences, inſtead of affecting the ſalivary ſyſ- <lb/>tem,
        its chief ſcene of action, producing nauſea, <lb/>gripings, and bloody ſtools, whilſt in
        ſmaller doſes, <lb/>it has readily been abſorbed into the habit, and gra- <lb/>dually
        brought on a ptyaliſm, nay often cured with- <lb/>out any perceptible effect. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Under the ſame circumſtances, Bark has been the <lb/>cauſe of ſickneſs, purging, and
        conſtantly rejected <pb xml:id="page_49" n="44"/>
        <lb/>by vomiting; producing not any of its ſalutary ef- <lb/>fects, either by prolonging the
        apyrexy, or taking <lb/>off the febrile affections, which have been accom- <lb/>pliſhed by
        cold or hot infuſions of this medicine. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the contrary, ſmall doſes of theſe very ac- <lb/>tive materials have been productive
        of no ſenſible or <lb/>curative effect ſometimes, whilſt adminiſtered in <lb/>larger doſes,
        their good conſequences have been <lb/>made manifeſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And again: It is indiſputably true, that theſe <lb/>medicines given in any quantity or
        form, they may, <lb/>the moſt perfectly agreeable to the conſtitution, and <lb/>without
        having any painful concomitant circum- <lb/>ſtances attendant, have by ho means anſwered the
        <lb/>deſired purpoſe; but being joined with other reme- <lb/>dies, have proved ſucceſſful. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>What then can be the cauſe of theſe deviations? <lb/>Is it in the medical ingredient
        itſelf? Impoſſible— <pb xml:id="page_50" n="45"/>
        <lb/>For every medicine conſidered in itſelf, ceteris pa- <lb/>ribus, muſt always be alike;
        its action muſt be in- <lb/>variably the ſame; and in ſimilar conſtitutions, or <lb/>in the
        ſame conſtitutions under ſimilar circumſtances <lb/>muſt univerſally produce the ſame
        effects. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Though I am well aware it may be urged, that <lb/>the ſame medicine in the ſame perſon
        has appeared <lb/>to act, as if it varied its mode of action; this will <lb/>be readily
        granted—but then it has been owing to <lb/>ſome change brought upon the habits by illneſs,
        in- <lb/>diſcretion, or ſome other cauſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For medicines producing in a ſtate of full health <lb/>one effect, will create others
        in a ſtate of illneſs, <lb/>with reſpect to the conſtitution; though the action <lb/>of the
        medicine muſt be the ſame.—For the conſti- <lb/>tution labouring under an indiſpoſition, its
        powers <lb/>are altered, they act not under a ſtate of healthful <lb/>nature, but require
        ſomething to relieve and regu- <lb/>late them—Now the ſame medicine which relieves, <pb
          xml:id="page_51" n="46"/>
        <lb/>and regulates them, during the illneſs, would, when <lb/>the illneſs was conquered, and
        the powers of the <lb/>conſtitution returned to their natural order, or ſtan- <lb/>dard,
        produce bad effects if continued, inaſmuch as <lb/>the ſame action of a medicine in illneſs,
        producing <lb/>the ſame effect on the habit, brings that habit into <lb/>a ſtate of health
        by that very action; which action, <lb/>the body being in an healthful ſtate, is too power-
        <lb/>ful; for it then needing no ſuch aid, would have <lb/>its powers too much increaſed,
        and by that means <lb/>diſtreſs from that very ſource would be occaſioned. <lb/>—The ſame
        argument may be made uſe of, where <lb/>debilitating means have been applied, in order to
        <lb/>reduce the too active powers of the habit, morbidly <lb/>affected. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From what has been advanced I conclude, there- <lb/>fore, that the cauſe of theſe
        deviations depend ſolely <lb/>on the ſtate of the conſtitution, and by no means <lb/>on the
        nature of the medicine. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_52" n="47"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Now, as I conſider the action of medicines, and <lb/>the ſemina morbi, to be exactly
        under the ſame <lb/>point of view, regarding their reſpective operations <lb/>on the
        machine, and effects produced—I ſay, theſe <lb/>depend totally on the nature of the
        conſtitution <lb/>operated upon—for inſtance, </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If a <hi rend="italic">Man of ſtrong ſtamina, great vaſcular irrita- <lb/>bility,
          ſteady, regular, nervous incitability, firm texture <lb/>of the blood,</hi> was to be
        ſeized with an intermittent <lb/>fever, of the quotidian or tertian type, from marſh
        <lb/>miaſma—in order to form his cure, the vaſcular ir- <lb/>ritability muſt be abated, the
        too ſtrong tone of the <lb/>ſolids, and muſcular fibres in ſome degree debilita- <lb/>ted,
        and the coheſive power of the blood weaken- <lb/>ed—by bleeding, purging, cooling, ſaline
        medicines, <lb/>antimonial diaphoretics; — which done, the Bark <lb/>might afterwards be
        adminiſtered. And if a man <lb/>of a ſimilar conſtitution takes ſo large a quantity of
        <lb/>heating ſtimulants as to produce the ſame febrile <lb/>appearances, without
        intermiſſion — the treatment <pb xml:id="page_53" n="48"/>
        <lb/>would be the ſame.—Not from the miaſmata, or <lb/>ſtimulants, having produced theſe
        effects—but from <lb/>the ſame conſtitutional cauſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But was the marſh miaſma to affect a <hi rend="italic">man of de- <lb/>bilitated habit,
          weak nervous incitability, and enfeebled <lb/>vaſcular irritability, with a looſe texture
          of the ſangui- <lb/>nary mass</hi>—cordial, nervous medicines with the uſe <lb/>of
        bliſters might be added to the uſe of the Bark; <lb/>and theſe would be required from
        conſtitutional <lb/>cauſes alſo,—that the conſtitution itſelf might be <lb/>rouzed to feel
        the tonic power of that remedy, and <lb/>experience its good effects. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A variety of other inſtances might be offered in <lb/>proof of the ſame poſitions—and
        this mode of rea- <lb/>ſoning will be found applicable to almoſt all caſes;
        <lb/>particularly, all ſuch as are general in the habit, or <lb/>are owing to general
        affections: and the more it is <lb/>examined into, the more the propriety and neceſ-
        <lb/>ſity of paying particular attention to what has been <pb xml:id="page_54" n="49"/>
        <lb/>ſpecified will appear; but what has been ſaid will, I <lb/>hope, be ſufficient to
        ſupply the propoſed hints, and <lb/>lead me to my laſt propoſition. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes"><hi rend="italic">That one preſent ſource of retarding the progreſs <lb/>of
            the medic art, is the looſe and neglectful manner <lb/>in which caſes and their modes of
            cure, or want of <lb/>ſucceſs, are deſcribed.</hi>
        </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It has, I flatter myſelf, been clearly proved, as <lb/>far as the time allotted upon
        this occaſion will per- <lb/>mit, that the conſtitution, with its different diviſions,
        <lb/>require the firſt attention of the Phyſician; and it <lb/>will readily occur, that in
        practice it is to be con- <lb/>ſidered not only collectively, but abſtractedly; that <lb/>it
        ſhould be found out in what part the conſtitution <lb/>is moſt defective, whether reſpecting
        its <hi rend="italic">nervous In- <lb/>citability— vaſcular Irritability — muſcular Strength
          — <lb/>texture</hi> or <hi rend="italic">compoſition of the Blood</hi>—and <hi
          rend="italic">Fluids</hi>—and <hi rend="italic">the Appendiculæ.</hi>
      </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_55" n="50"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For as all the parts act in combination with each <lb/>other, as they tranſmit to each
        other the principle <lb/>of their power, yet may experience ſeparate affec- <lb/>tions
        inherent in themſelves, which may be gene- <lb/>rally or partially communicated, creative of
        general <lb/>or partial diſturbance — they ſhould always be par- <lb/>ticularly attended to:
        inaſmuch as the neglect of <lb/>ſome, may occaſion too often our endeavours to be- <lb/>come
        abortive. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But we find commonly too little ſaid on the pre- <lb/>valent peculiarities of the
        conſtitution, upon which <lb/>different medicines have been tried in ſimilar diſ-
        <lb/>eaſes, wherein they have ſometimes proved ſucceſſ- <lb/>ful, ſometimes otherwiſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Now, as medicines act differently in different <lb/>quantities—with different
        combinations—in diffe- <lb/>rent conſtitutions—in the ſame conſtitutions at dif- <lb/>ferent
        periods — in the ſame diſeaſe at the different <lb/>times of the malady, with regard to the
        good or bad <pb xml:id="page_56" n="51"/>
        <lb/>effects they produce — and as this apparent diffe- <lb/>rence of action depends upon
        the different ſtates of <lb/>the moving powers, and what I call their appendi- <lb/>culæ,
        the conſtitutional peculiarities ſhould always <lb/>be nicely diſcriminated. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This mode would often enable us to diſcover, on <lb/>what account various remedies had
        been ſucceſſful; <lb/>wherein they had failed, and direct us to the beſt <lb/>method of
        ſelecting and combining medicines, and <lb/>of curing diſeaſes, ſuch as fall immediately
        under <lb/>the Phyſician's care; and aſſiſt, in moſt, to which the <lb/>Surgeon lays claim,
        as little, very little is to be <lb/>done with the ſemina morbi, and the ſpecific power
        <lb/>of our remedies is merely ideal. For as is the ſtate <lb/>of the moving powers and
        fluids, with their combi- <lb/>nations, ſo will be the action of our medicines, and
        <lb/>conſequently ſo will be the indications in our appli- <lb/>cations. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_57" n="52"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Permit me, before I conclude, to offer a caſe, <lb/>by way of exemplification, which
        will afford, I preſume, <lb/>no weak proof of what has been advanced. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. *****, a perſon of middle age, had been <lb/>ſome time afflicted with a diſeaſe,
        ſimilar to what <lb/>is termed <hi rend="sc">Gonorrhæa libidinosa</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>His muſcular ſtamina were tolerably good; he <lb/>had a great deal of nervous
        incitability; weak vaſ- <lb/>cular irritability; the texture of the blood not <lb/>firm, nor
        could be called broken; his digeſtion, tho' <lb/>his appetite was tolerable, defective; he
        had now <lb/>and then chillineſs, ſucceeded by fluſhing heats, <lb/>which came on
        irregularly; his pulſe in general <lb/>was ſlow, and undulating; and when quickened, as
        <lb/>it would now and then be, on ſome extraordinary <lb/>occaſions, weak; his viſcera all
        appeared found; <lb/>
        <note place="bottom" n="*">* Though delicacy prevents the inſertion of the Name, ſtill any
          <lb/>medical Gentleman, deſirous of further information, may acquire it <lb/>by
          application to the author, who, for the ſake of accuracy, read this <lb/>account three
          times to the patient, and he, <hi rend="italic">at that time,</hi> perfectly coin-
          <lb/>cided with the exactitude of the deſcription. </note>
        <pb xml:id="page_58" n="53"/>
        <lb/>his bowels very irregular, ſometimes extremely coſ- <lb/>tive, at others as much the
        reverſe—always in one <lb/>extreme or the other; his urine pale, and limpid for <lb/>the
        moſt part, but now and then depoſiting a whi- <lb/>tiſh, furfuraceous, mucilaginous ſediment
        — he was <lb/>petulant, and iraſcible when trifles perplexed him; <lb/>when not, timid and
        deſpairing—his fluids were acri- <lb/>monious; his memory weak, and his recollection
        <lb/>painful; creative of much uneaſineſs, when he could <lb/>not bring to his mind that of
        which he was in queſt <lb/>—his whole frame was in general ſo languid, that <lb/>ſlight
        motion greatly fatigued him; his extremities <lb/>were in general cold — in eaſterly or
        ſouth-weſt <lb/>winds he always complained of being worſe, and <lb/>was perceptibly ſo — his
        nights were conſtantly reſt- <lb/>less — he had ſometimes two or three emiſſions in <lb/>the
        night; complained of partial heat at the lower <lb/>part of the back, which he ſaid, now and
        then, tranſ- <lb/>fuſed itſelf all over him, and made him extremely <lb/>faint—he was never
        thirſty. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_59" n="54"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In this ſtate he had continued for ten months, <lb/>though now viſibly growing worſe,
        and had been <lb/>under the care of two phyſicians of eminence: <lb/>they had put him under
        a courſe of reſtringent <lb/>medicines — bark, white vitriol, ginſeng, &amp;c. and
        <lb/>ordered him the cold bath; but all proved inef- <lb/>fectual. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>At this period, his conſtitution was conſidered in <lb/>general after the mode above
        recommended; taking <lb/>in alſo the topical affection—a weakneſs of the ſe- <lb/>minal
        veſſels, and determination of the fluids to <lb/>thoſe parts creating heat, and cauſing
        emiſſions. </p>
      <p rend="align-center">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Indications of Cure</hi> were, </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">To determine the Fluids externally, by increaſing <lb/>Perſpiration —
          to ſtrengthen the digeſtive Organs — in- <lb/>creaſe the Irritability of the vaſcular
          ſyſtem — abate the <lb/>nervous Incitability</hi> — and <hi rend="italic">give tone and
          firmneſs to the <lb/>habit in general,</hi> which were accompliſhed by cor- <lb/>dial
        ſaline diaphoretics, warm tonics, camphorated <pb xml:id="page_60" n="55"/>
        <lb/>and æthereal anti-ſpaſmodics, and ſtomachic bitters <lb/>—keeping the body moderately
        and gently open by <lb/>mild aperients. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Under this method, his extremities firſt loſt their <lb/>coldneſs, in a great degree,
        and when warm, he <lb/>always found himſelf relieved; at which time there <lb/>was a great
        itching in his skin, which was diſtend- <lb/>ed, appearing like an univerſal eſſera, the
        matter <lb/>by a general ſtimulus under the skin, elevating the <lb/>whole ſurface
        regularly, not ſhewing any eruptions, <lb/>except here and there, one now and then, on his
        <lb/>breaſt, or on the lower part of the head, juſt above <lb/>the neck, at the roots of the
        hair. He began now <lb/>to recover every day, and when his ſyſtem ſhewed <lb/>it was in ſome
        degree invigorated, bathing in the <lb/>Thames and riding exerciſe eſtabliſhed his cure. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The reaſon why the former Gentlemen had been <lb/>ſo long unſucceſſful, appears very
        obvious: they <lb/>had not paid any attention to the torpid ſtate of <pb xml:id="page_61"
          n="56"/>
        <lb/>the vaſcular ſyſtem, on which account the fluids <lb/>were always crowding upon the
        internal parts, ha- <lb/>ving their acrimony increaſed; and the aſtringent <lb/>medicines,
        not being capable of exerting their ac- <lb/>tion, from a defect of vaſcular irritability,
        the veſ- <lb/>ſels being in ſuch a ſtate of torpor, as not to feel <lb/>the effects. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Hence the ſeminal veſſels, being before in a wea- <lb/>kened ſtate, ſuffered a partial
        irritation, by the <lb/>fluids there collected, occaſioning ſtimulus, and in- <lb/>creaſed
        heat — emiſſions ſucceeded emiſſions — the <lb/>machine became more and more debilitated —
        the <lb/>nervous incitability increaſed; the conſequence of <lb/>which would ſoon have been
        a hectic fever with a <lb/>tabes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Would time permit, a variety of caſes might be <lb/>adduced, in which ſimilar ſucceſs
        from ſimilar rea- <lb/>ſons have confirmed the validity of a practice ſo <lb/>founded — and
        I am fully perſuaded, that in all our <pb xml:id="page_62" n="57"/>
        <lb/>recitals of caſes, whether ſucceſſfully or unſucceſſ- <lb/>fully treated, were we to
        advert to what, perhaps, <lb/>by ſome may be conſidered as minutiæ too trifling <lb/>in the
        preſent ſcale of phyſic, we ſhould find, as <lb/>well from one as the other, much uſeful
        matter proceeding—And I have no doubt but we ſhould <lb/>diſcover, in very many, if not in
        all, the reaſons <lb/>why accounts ſo ſimilar in their deſcriptions, ſo diſ- <lb/>ſimilar in
        their conſequences, have, and do preſent <lb/>themſelves daily to our view. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But I flatter myſelf, what has been already ad- <lb/>vanced will be ſufficient to
        afford hints, that may <lb/>induce ſome more capable to attempt the inveſtiga- <lb/>tion,
        and give ſtill clearer views than lies within the <lb/>compaſs of my very limited knowledge:
        I ſhall, <lb/>therefore, conclude in the words of a favorite au- <lb/>thor, as they are
        expreſſive of my wiſhes— <q rend="quotes">Non <lb/>dicam, quod ad commodiorem &amp;
          certiorem me- <lb/>dendi methodum nihil exinde inveniri poſſit. Doc- <lb/>trinam itaque,
          quemadmodum cum praxi cohæreat, <pb xml:id="page_63" n="58"/>
          <lb/>&amp; quæ utilitas in certam &amp; compendioſam medendi <lb/>methodum inde redundet,
          non hominum ad judi- <lb/>candum ineptorum, non juvenum &amp;c in praxi planè
          <lb/>inexercitatorum, non ſectariorum, &amp; qui veras de- <lb/>monſtrandi, &amp; logicas
          regulas ignorant; ſed veſ- <lb/>tro, <hi rend="sc">Viri solidissima peritia et eruditione
            in- <lb/>structi</hi>, judicio, candori, atque integritati, nec <lb/>non attentiori
          meditationi atque experientiæ etiam <lb/>atque etiam commendo. </q>
      </p>
      <trailer rend="align-right">
        <lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
