<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Webster: Facts, tending to show the connection of the stomach with
          life</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Charles Webster</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Facts, tending to show the connection of the stomach with life,
              disease, and recovery.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T14677</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T14677"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Murray, Fleet-Street; W. Gordon, P. Hill, and G.
                  Mudie, Edinburgh, 1793.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1793</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="3"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="59"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3306964429</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K027597.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="General treatises"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="size(1.75)">A</hi>S there is no medical theory, formed from in-
          <lb/>duction, to enable us to detect what is erroneous <lb/>or falſe in the accounts of
          facts, or to direct us in the <lb/>treatment of new caſes; the following attempt to
          <lb/>connect with an important organ many otherwiſe <lb/>looſe facts, may tend to
          facilitate the recollection and <lb/>application of them, and thus abridge the range of
          <lb/>inquiry. The number ſuggeſted by this view is ſo <lb/>great, that there is leſs
          difficulty in the collection <lb/>than in the choice; their relation and order, familiar
          <lb/>only to one's own habit of aſſociation, may to others <lb/>at firſt be obſcure; and
          ſome of them may be diſputed; <lb/>but the leading ones ſeem to ſhow that the ſtomach
          <lb/>is the ſeat of life, diſeaſe, and recovery, and the main <lb/>organ of a complicated
          ſyſtem. Many authors, <lb/>as Vanhelmont, Rega, Bordeu, Lacaze, Barthez, <lb/>Fouquet, and
          particularly Mr. Hunter, lean, in their <lb/>uſeful writings, to the opinion held in this
          ſummary, <lb/>which was meant as part of heads of lectures on <lb/>Materia Medica, read in
          Edinburgh ſeveral years <lb/>ago. The farther application of the doctrine to prac-
          <lb/>tice, will probably appear ſoon. </p>
        <signed rend="align-right">
          <lb/>CHARLES WEBSTER. </signed>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_3"/>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">By the ſame Author, </hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="align-center">
          <lb/>
          <list>
            <item>Medicinæ Praxeos Syſtema, 3 tom. </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>An Account of the Life and Writings <lb/>of Dr. A. Pitcairn. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_4"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>Facts tending to ſhow the Connexion of the Sto- <lb/>mach with Life, Diſeaſe, and
        Remedy. </head>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="size(1.75)">S</hi>UCH ſimply organized animals as have <lb/>no viſible brain,
        nerves, lungs, heart, <lb/>or blood-veſſels, and even vegetables, con- <lb/>tract and re-act
        on impreſſions being made <lb/>on any part of them; and being cut in <lb/>pieces, each
        becomes a living individual. <lb/>They ſeparate the elements of dead matter <lb/>which
        re-unite within them in various and <lb/>ſpecific proportions, and extend their fibres;
        <lb/>they propagate their kinds whoſe particles <lb/>and fibres are arranged into ſpecific
        forms, <lb/>as all conſolidated fluids are; they have a <lb/>preſerving and reſiſting power
        called vis con- <lb/>ſervatrix and medicatrix naturæ; become de- <lb/>ranged in their
        functions and ſtructure by <pb xml:id="page_5" n="2"/>
        <lb/>exceſs, defect, or peculiarity of impreſſion; <lb/>recover from various morbid ſtates;
        rege- <lb/>nerate loſt ſubſtance; ceaſe at length to an- <lb/>ſwer impreſſions, and
        ſpontaneouſly ſepa- <lb/>rate into their elements, which form new <lb/>combinations in
        nature. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In an animal, which, beſides a ſto- <lb/>mach, the ſeat of the firſt aſſimilation and
        <lb/>ſimple life, has nerves and brain, the me- <lb/>dium of ſenſation and thought, the
        energy <lb/>of which is encreaſed by a heart and lungs; <lb/>the aſſimilating, moving,
        ſentient, and <lb/>thinking powers become parts of one whole, <lb/>neceſſary to the action
        and effect of one ano- <lb/>ther, acting as it were in a circle, modify- <lb/>ing and
        improving the ſyſtem, in which the <lb/>ſmalleſt puncture producing contractility,
        <lb/>pain, and hæmorrage, ſeems to ſhew that <lb/>life, mind, and heart exiſt in every
        point. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Cold-blooded animals, whoſe circulation <lb/>is languid, and reſpiration occaſional,
        live <lb/>and move for ſeveral hours without brain, <pb xml:id="page_6" n="3"/>
        <lb/>heart, or lungs: the heart of a young hot- <lb/>blooded animal continues its motions
        for <lb/>ſome time after its connexion with the <lb/>brain is cut off <note place="bottom"
          n="*">* Whytt. </note>; in phthiſis pulmonalis <lb/>there is ſometimes ſcarcely a veſtige
        of <lb/>lungs left; ſome perſons have the power of <lb/>ſuſpending the action of the heart
          <note place="bottom" n="†">† Gregory. </note>, and it <lb/>is ſometimes ſuſpended without
        the will, <lb/>while the other functions continue entire <note place="bottom" n="†">†
          Hunter. </note>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After decollation, it is ſaid, a viper tra- <lb/>verſed ſeveral walks in a garden; an
        oſtrich <lb/>continued running in a circular courſe <lb/>leading to an accuſtomed place of
        refuge; <lb/>and a cock impulſively continued its motion <lb/>towards ſome grain that had
        been juſt pre- <lb/>ſented to it; a turtle, whoſe ſtrength, con- <lb/>ſidering its maſſy
        ſhell, muſt be very great, <lb/>lives for months without the head <note place="bottom" n="§"
          >§ Redi. </note>: fœtuſes <lb/>have been born alive without brain, cere- <lb/>bellum, or
        ſpinal marrow. In dropſy of the <pb xml:id="page_7" n="4"/>
        <lb/>head, nothing has been found but the <lb/>membranes; ſome have loſt a conſiderable
        <lb/>part of the brain and recovered; all the in- <lb/>voluntary motions, and even the uſe
        of the <lb/>limbs, have continued a day or two after <lb/>the ſpinal marrow has been divided
          <note place="bottom" n="*">* Deſſault. </note>; the <lb/>involuntary ones continue when
        the ſenſes <lb/>and brain are locked up in ſleep, lethargy, <lb/>and apoplexy, and in the
        ſuſpended action <lb/>of the heart and lungs in ſyncope. In <lb/>mania the vigour is often
        increaſed and the <lb/>ſenſibility diminiſhed, while the contrary is <lb/>generally obſerved
        in indigeſtion, gout, and <lb/>nervous diſeaſes, in which the intellect is <lb/> often
        unimpaired. The contractility laſts <lb/>much longer if an animal be killed by de-
        <lb/>ſtroying its brain than otherwiſe <note place="bottom" n="†">† Blane. </note>; death,
        <lb/>occaſioned by over-exertion of the muſcles, <lb/>by the electric, carbonic, or azotic
        fluids, or <lb/>by the poiſon of a viper, prevents the muſcles <pb xml:id="page_8" n="5"/>
        <lb/>from becoming rigid, and diſpoſes to a much <lb/>quicker putrefaction; and the life in
        vege- <lb/>tables, particularly in their ſeeds, in a chick <lb/>before incubation, and in
        the hibernating <lb/>animals, as in the ſwallow, mountain-rat, <lb/>and dormouſe, reſiſts
        the tendency to putre- <lb/>faction, and freezing. The brain of a man, <lb/>in proportion to
        the weight of his body, is <lb/>above thirty times heavier than that of a <lb/>large
        quadruped, and ſtill more ſo than that <lb/>of an amphibious one, as the crocodile, with
        <lb/>proportionably leſs ſtrength. The brain <lb/>has a ſmall proportion likewiſe, in long-
        <lb/>necked birds, fiſhes, and inſects; and is ſin- <lb/>gularly large in ſome ſmall
        animals, as ſmall <lb/>birds and rats. In the lower animals it is <lb/>in general ſpent in
        nerves on the ſenſes, <lb/>face, and jaws, as the ſpinal marrow is in <lb/>thoſe on the
        trunk which are large in pro- <lb/>portion; and in all animals the axillary and <lb/>ſciatic
        nerves and blood-veſſels, as neceſſary <lb/>to ſtrong voluntary motion, are the largeſt. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_9" n="6"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The pulp of the brain and nerves has <lb/>very little contractility. Parts of animals
        <lb/>live and grow without nerves; a limb, <lb/>after its nerve is cut, though it loſes
        <lb/>its power of voluntary motion and ſenſa- <lb/>tion, and, after ſome time, begins to
        waſte, <lb/>yet does not putrefy, but retains its con- <lb/>tractility, temperature, and
        circulation; and <lb/>a wound or fracture in this caſe heals, though <lb/>the nerve be not
        regenerated <note place="bottom" n="*">* Monro. </note>. A muſcle, as <lb/>the heart, whoſe
        nerves bear no proportion <lb/>to its bulk and action, cut off, retains its
        <lb/>contractility. Palſied limbs void of ſenſe <lb/>or motion, or of both, are ſometimes
        ex- <lb/>tremely contractile, inflame, ſuppurate, and <lb/>heal, as in the caſe of a
        bliſter, which does <lb/>not ſo readily happen in a moribund patient; <lb/>and an obſtinate
        ulcer in the affected ſide has <lb/>been known to heal quickly on the attack of
        <lb/>hemiplegia. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>No animal can exiſt without a ſtomach; <lb/>life has remained even in the perfect ani-
          <pb xml:id="page_10" n="7"/>
        <lb/>mals independently of almoſt every other <lb/>organ; the ſtomach is the only organ
        which, <lb/>as in the zoophytes, the hydatid, the <lb/>oyſter, the polypus, and ſome other
        vermes, <lb/>can be ſaid to exiſt as an animal by itſelf; <lb/>theſe animals are capable of
        every muſcular <lb/>motion, and of every living power ſuited <lb/>to their mode of exiſtence
        and the conti- <lb/>nuance of their kind. Placed in the mid- <lb/>dle, the ſtomach is felt
        to be the centre of <lb/>every impreſſion on any part of the body or <lb/>the mind, and the
        ſeat of muſcular exertion <lb/>and fatigue. A blow, or the wind of a <lb/>cannon-ball over
        the ſtomach, kills with- <lb/>out leaving any mark <note place="bottom" n="*">* Blane.
        </note>; if any of its nerves <lb/>be cut or itſelf wounded, the aliment re- <lb/>mains
        unchanged; when healthy it reſiſts, <lb/>arreſts, and reverſes the ſtages of fermen-
        <lb/>tation, ſweetens putrid meat, does not ſuffer <lb/>from the ſyphilitic, variolous,
        viperine or <pb xml:id="page_11" n="8"/>
        <lb/>carbonic poiſons, which injure only the bare <lb/>ſurface or paſſages to the noſe and
        lungs. It <lb/>is the receptacle of food, poiſon, and medi- <lb/>cine, the effects of which
        on itſelf are pro- <lb/>pagated to every other part; it is moſt ſub- <lb/>ject to diſorder,
        moſt acceſſible to remedy, <lb/>regulating, and regulated by, the motions <lb/>and
        ſenſations of the whole ſyſtem, and ſo <lb/>accommodating itſelf as to keep all the parts
        <lb/>in balance. Languido ventriculo omnia lan- <lb/>guent, vegeto vigent. In moſt caſes it
        is the <lb/>firſt organ that feels, and the laſt that fails <note place="bottom" n="*">*
          There is generally a diſcharge of fæces after <lb/>death. </note>
        <lb/>Even the ſtate of the mind or character ſeems <lb/>connected with it, vigorous and
        ferocious <lb/>animals being generally carnivorous, with <lb/>muſcular vigour in proportion
        to their <lb/>voracity. It ſeems to be the centre of <lb/>power and motion from which the
        vital <lb/>principle, whatever it be, is determined <lb/>into the different parts,
        ſupporting the in- <pb xml:id="page_12" n="9"/>
        <lb/>herent power in the moving fibres, <lb/>the thinking power in the brain, ſenſation in
        <lb/>the ſentient extremities, aſſimilation in the <lb/>lymphatic <note place="bottom" n="*"
          >* From fiſhes living and growing in diſtilled water <lb/>and air <note place="bottom"
            n="†">† Fordyce. </note>, from the inſtances of people living ſo <lb/>long in diſeaſe
          and in health, without nouriſhment by the <lb/>mouth, and from the relief of thirſt and
          even hunger, <lb/>by the application of water to the skin, water and air <lb/>ſeem to be
          not only abſorbed and carried, but aſſimi- <lb/>lated by the lymphatics. </note>,
        ſanguiferous, and glandular <lb/>veſſels, and the fulneſs in every part of the <lb/>ſyſtem. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the gaſtric energy is diminiſhed, <lb/>parts ſeem to loſe their motion and ſenſe
        as <lb/>they are diſtant from the ſtomach; as <lb/>the tips of the noſe and ears, the
        fingers <lb/>and toes, and the vaſcular extremities. Like <lb/>the ſenſes, it has ſpecific
        ſenſations, as of <lb/>hunger, thirſt, ſatiety, longing, loathing, <pb xml:id="page_13"
          n="10"/>
        <lb/>ſickneſs, peculiar pain, with a great variety <lb/>of nameleſs ſtates without
        ſenſation, ac- <lb/>companied with correſponding changes, ac- <lb/>cording to prediſpoſition
        in different parts <lb/>of the ſyſtem. A grain of a taſteleſs ſub- <lb/>ſtance will affect
        the ſtomach, and, through <lb/>it, the other parts, or theſe only, while <lb/>various
        acrids, pungent aromatics, and ſpi- <lb/>rits, can often be taken in large quantity,
        <lb/>without producing any remarkable effect <lb/>whatever. Stones of conſiderable ſize have
        <lb/>been ſwallowed, and the ſtomach itſelf, <lb/>though, from its organic contractility, it
        is <lb/>always full, can be in very different ſtates <lb/>of diſtenſion and contraction,
        with even <lb/>morbid tumor, without much inconveni- <lb/>ence. Leidenfroſt mentions a caſe,
        in which <lb/>the application of warm wine to the villous <lb/>coat of a wounded inteſtine
        excited great <lb/>motion without any pain, even on rubbing <lb/>off the mucus ſo as to
        bring blood. There <lb/>is often little or no pain felt in the action of <pb
          xml:id="page_14" n="11"/>
        <lb/>violent vomiting or purging, ſo that living <lb/>motion does not, even in the perfect
        ani- <lb/>mals, imply ſenſibility. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The alimentary canal, which, on open- <lb/>ing a living animal, hardly ſeems to move,
        <lb/>ſhows, as ſoon as the other parts die, <lb/>ſtrongly increaſed motions, which, like the
        <lb/>contractility mentioned above, continue <lb/>for hours <note place="bottom" n="*">*
          Caldani and Fontana. </note>. In the caſe of violent death, <lb/>as that of beheading, the
        ſame increaſed <lb/>motions, after ſome ſhort ſpace, with an <lb/>impetuous ſpring of blood
        from the veſſels, <lb/>are remarkable; which motions may, per- <lb/>haps, independently of
        the gaſtric liquor, <lb/>ſometimes occaſion thoſe perforations in the <lb/>ſtomach obſerved
        in ſuch caſes, particularly <lb/>in infants even after natural death; and to <lb/>ſome
        ſimilar ſtate of bowel may be referred <lb/>the <note place="bottom" n="†">† In Scotland
          this is called earth or yerd-hunger. </note> eſuries and priapiſmus moribundorum.
        <lb/>This reſiſting or reacting power or vis con- <lb/>ſervatrix and medicatrix, in which
        the <pb xml:id="page_15" n="12"/>
        <lb/>power of recovery ſeems to reſide, is evident <lb/>in the caſe of other impreſſions on
        the <lb/>ſtomach, the ſurface, and the mind, as in <lb/>the action of an emetic, the glow
        from the <lb/>cold bath, and the red ſuffuſion produced <lb/>by paſſion; and it is this
        which ſeems chiefly <lb/>to enable a healthy animal to bear changes <lb/>and extremes of the
        ordinary ones, as thoſe <lb/>of temperature, air, food and drink, motion, <lb/>ſenſation,
        and thought, in a remarkable de- <lb/>gree. The powers acting on the ſyſtem, as <lb/>heat,
        air, exerciſe of body and mind, diet, <lb/>poiſon, medicine, and the fluids, tend to in-
        <lb/>creaſe the power of the ſtomach, but ulti- <lb/>mately, or in exceſs, to deſtroy it;
        and are <lb/>called ſtimulants. When defective they <lb/>tend to diminiſh it, and are called
        ſedative, <lb/>which effect, if of a certain degree, is fol- <lb/>lowed by the reaction or
        reſiſtance; and they <lb/>are then called indirect ſtimulants. Hence <lb/>the ſame natural
        morbid and ſalutary im- <lb/>preſſions may, according to their degree, be <pb
          xml:id="page_16" n="13"/>
        <lb/>ſedative or ſtimulant. Some impreſſions, <lb/>both internal and external, affect it
        pecu- <lb/>liarly, and, through it, different parts of <lb/>the ſyſtem. In general, ſtrong
        impreſſions <lb/>excite the reſiſting power, weak ones ſeem <lb/>occaſionally to ſooth,
        diminiſh, or teaſe it, <lb/>ſpecific ones produce ſpecific ſtates in it and <lb/>in
        different parts of the ſyſtem, and on theſe <lb/>fits of reſiſtance, ſeem to depend the
        ſtates <lb/>of periodical diſeaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſtomach is the ſeat of the firſt aſſi- <lb/>milating power, in which the elements
        of <lb/>food and drink, of whatever kind and va- <lb/>riety, ſeparate, and then unite into
        the only <lb/>one combination fit for undergoing the <lb/>other ſpecific changes, for making
        the ſpe- <lb/>cific impreſſions, for giving the due diſten- <lb/>ſion, and repairing the
        continual waſte; and <lb/>its ſpontaneous effort or ſtruggle with local <lb/>injury, ſeems
        to excite that ſymptomatic <lb/>fever, or ſtate of veſſel which renders the <lb/>parts of
        the blood more ſeparable, forming <pb xml:id="page_17" n="14"/>
        <lb/>the buffy-coat, the inflammatory exudation, <lb/>the ſuppuration, and the callus or
        oſſifying <lb/>arteries, ſo as to regenerate deſtroyed parts, <lb/>fill cavities, and form
        skin. On its ſtate <lb/>ſeems to depend that of the chyle, blood, <lb/>ſecretions, every
        ſoft and hard fibre, every <lb/>organ and function of the ſyſtem, and ſuch is <lb/>its
        importance, that it has been emphati- <lb/>cally called the animal, the conſcience of
        <lb/>the body, and even ſuppoſed the ſeat of the <lb/>ſoul <note place="bottom" n="*">*
          Ariſtotle, Vanhelmont, Mandevelle, Hunter. </note>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>During ordinary hunger, its power over <lb/>the muſcles is diminiſhed, which ſtate is
        <lb/>called weakneſs; there is a diminiſhed <lb/>action of the heart and arteries,
        particularly <lb/>at their extremities, as appears from the <lb/>weak and frequent pulſe,
        dryneſs, paleneſs, <lb/>ſhrinking, and lankneſs of the ſurface and <lb/>features; diminiſhed
        ſecretion, as appears <lb/>from the dry mouth and from the flaccid <pb xml:id="page_18"
          n="15"/>
        <lb/>breaſts of nurſes, a leſs free reſpiration, yawn- <lb/>ing, hiccup, weak voice,
        ſenſibility to cold, <lb/>feebleneſs of mind and peeviſhneſs, with <lb/>various other
        ſymptoms in different indi- <lb/>viduals. This eſurient ſtate, like that of <lb/>other
        appetites and temporary ſtates of di- <lb/>ſeaſe, goes off, is apt to change into the
        <lb/>loathing or ſick ſtate, then returns, becom- <lb/>ing irreſiſtible, enabling the
        ſtomach to diſ- <lb/>ſolve leather and other indigeſtible matters; <lb/>and producing
        exceſſive thirſt, delirium, <lb/>and other ſymptoms. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the ſight of food, the mouth fills with <lb/>water; and on taking ſome, the eſurient
        <lb/>ſtate with its ſymptoms is removed, the <lb/>ſtomach feels comfortable, the muſcles and
        <lb/>organs, particularly thoſe moſt fatigued, re- <lb/>cover their ſtrength, the
        circulation is pro- <lb/>moted, the ſecretions flow, the reſpiration <lb/>becomes free, the
        countenance brightens up, <lb/>ſerenity and vigour are imparted to body and <lb/>mind, and
        the heart opens in benevolence. <pb xml:id="page_19" n="16"/>
        <lb/>During this ſated ſtate the new impreſſion, as <lb/>if engroſſing the power of the
        ſtomach, is <lb/>apt to induce a chillineſs, drowſineſs, heat, <lb/>full pulſe and
        perſpiration, the phœnomena <lb/>of ſlight fever, and in ſome, formidable <lb/>ſymptoms. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The effects of food, as of every thing <lb/>elſe, being relative to the ſtate of the
        <lb/>ſtomach, what is light to one is heavy to <lb/>another; and a cordial in ſome ſtates
        occa- <lb/>ſions vomiting. A heavy meal oppreſſes <lb/>the ſtomach, and depreſſes its power
        over <lb/>the other parts of the ſyſtem, often induc- <lb/>ing alarming ſymptoms, which are
        fre- <lb/>quently relieved by a puke, or by ſpirits <lb/>or aromatics, increaſing the power
        of the <lb/>ſtomach. Alcohol, opium, or carbonic acid <lb/>tends like a meal, to induce
        ſerenity and <lb/>vigour of body and mind, but if in exceſs, <lb/>brings on the ebrious
        ſtate of ſtomach, <lb/>which deranges the functions of both. A <lb/>treſpaſs in eating or
        drinking, or any thing <pb xml:id="page_20" n="17"/>
        <lb/>which from temperament, taſte, or aſſocia- <lb/>tion of ideas, happens to diſagree with
        the <lb/>ſtomach, is apt inſtantly to occaſion various <lb/>ſymptoms <note place="bottom"
          n="*">* Thus a raw cucumber, turnip, or raddiſh, ker- <lb/>nels of fruits, muſhrooms,
          bitters, honey, ſpirits, <lb/>acids, eggs, ſhell-fiſh, abſorbent-earth, nitre, any
          <lb/>thing cold when the body is warm, are apt to occa- <lb/>ſion indigeſtion, colic,
          diarrhœa, cholera, hypochon- <lb/>driaſis, hyſteria, gout, palpitation, aſthma, aphonia,
          <lb/>ſyncope, apoplexy, palſy, epilepſy, tetanus, hæmor- <lb/>rhage, ſuppreſſion of
          natural diſcharges, dropſy, <lb/>eruption with fever, to renew and exaſperate a gleet,
          <lb/>a ſore, or the pain of a gouty or rheumatic limb. </note>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>What weakneſs, ſpaſms, pains and <lb/>aches, ſtitches, depravations and depriva-
        <lb/>tions of ſenſe and motion, and uneaſy <lb/>feelings of body and mind, does not a
        <lb/>little air pent up occaſion, and its expul- <lb/>ſion inſtantly relieve? What ſymptom
        has <lb/>not been occaſionally referred to indigeſtion, <lb/>and what remedy does not fall
        under the <pb xml:id="page_21" n="18"/>
        <lb/>treatment of it and its effects? What <lb/>diſeaſe is free from ſome affection of the
        <lb/>ſtomach or canal, and what fever does it <lb/>not mark in its beginning, its progreſs,
        re- <lb/>miſſion, criſis, and cure? The diſeaſes of <lb/>children are acknowledged to be
        moſtly <lb/>from the ſtomach and bowels, and they are <lb/>known to be cured of alarming
        ſymptoms by <lb/>a puke, a glyſter, or a purge. A perſon feels <lb/>weak, loſes colour and
        ſpirits, has head- <lb/>ach, giddineſs, and ſhivering, and the pre- <lb/>diſpoſed ſuffer
        fits of their diſeaſes, without <lb/>ſuſpecting, as there is no ſickneſs, want of
        <lb/>appetite, coſtiveneſs, or affection of the <lb/>ſtomach, that they proceed from it,
        till a <lb/>natural vomiting or looſeneſs, an emetic or <lb/>cathartic relieve the
        complaints. Fits, as <lb/>of aſthma, chin-cough, hyſteria, and gout, <lb/>are generally
        preceded by ſome affection of <lb/>the canal, and diminiſh or go off by the ex- <lb/>pulſion
        of air or other matter. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There does not ſeem to be one ſymptom <lb/>or combination of ſymptoms, but may be <pb
          xml:id="page_22" n="19"/>
        <lb/>produced by ſomething taken into the ſto- <lb/>mach, and, in the caſe of poiſons, its
        orifices <lb/>have been found, on diſſection, ſo conſtricted <lb/>as to have prevented the
        eſcape of any of <lb/>the matter. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The effect of poiſon, like that of food and <lb/>medicine, is relative to the kind and
        ſtate of <lb/>ſtomach. Cows and hares eat hemlock, <lb/>hares eat milk-thiſtle, hogs fatten
        on hen- <lb/>bane, quails on hellebore, and goats on eu- <lb/>phorbium: a horſe can take
        more glaſs of <lb/>antimony than would kill an hundred men, <lb/>a dog more opium than would
        kill an un- <lb/>accuſtomed man, while an ordinary doſe of <lb/>jalap, of nux-vomica, or a
        few bitter almonds, <lb/>would convulſe and kill him. Bitter al- <lb/>monds kill different
        kinds of birds likewiſe, <lb/>and parſley is poiſon to parrots. Indeed <lb/>every animal and
        vegetable poiſon is the <lb/>food of ſome animal, and notwithſtanding this <lb/>difference
        of effect, little or no difference of <lb/>ſtructure in brain, muſcle, membrane, and <pb
          xml:id="page_23" n="20"/>
        <lb/>bone, which form the animal ſolids, can be <lb/>perceived. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That the ſtomach may be in a great va- <lb/>riety of ſtates, appears from the organs of
        <lb/>ſenſe being capable of ſuch variety in re- <lb/>gard to ſenſation, from cauſes external
        or <lb/>internal. Each taſte implies a ſpecific ſtate <lb/>of organ. Alkaline, acid, ſweet,
        bitter, <lb/>aſtringent, acrid, aromatic, and fetid matter <lb/>excite their reſpective
        taſtes, which imply <lb/>ſtates of organ as numerous as the indivi- <lb/>duals of theſe
        claſſes, with their various <lb/>combinations. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Some kinds of matter affect different <lb/>parts of the ſame organ, and the ſenſation
        <lb/>is propagated to a greater or leſs diſtance <lb/>without any probability of abſorption.
        So <lb/>an irritation in the lungs is often felt at the <lb/>epiglottis; in the liver, at
        the ſhoulder; <lb/>in the kidney, at the teſticle and thigh; <lb/>in the bladder, at the end
        of the glans <lb/>penis; in the colon, at the navel; in every <pb xml:id="page_24" n="21"/>
        <lb/>part of the ſyſtem at the ſtomach; and <lb/>in the ſtomach, at every part of the
        ſyſtem. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>An aſtringent, at the tip of the tongue, <lb/>corrugates the whole mouth, and ſtops
        ſome- <lb/>times a remote hæmorrhage: a bit of alum <lb/>diſſolving in the mouth, occaſions
        a thrill <lb/>over the body; ſea-ſalt is felt chiefly at the <lb/>point of the tongue,
        bitter apple at its <lb/>middle, elaterium and mezereon at its root, <lb/>and jalap in the
        gullet. A diſagreeable taſte, <lb/>ſmell, ſight, ſound, or touch, the tickling of <lb/>the
        throat, or coughing, are apt to occaſion <lb/>ſickneſs and vomiting. The mere chewing
        <lb/>of tobacco or rhubarb, has occaſioned vo- <lb/>miting and purging. Taſteleſs warm
        water, <lb/>an antimonial, or the berries of coriaria <lb/>myrtifolia, throw the ſtomach
        into convul- <lb/>ſions. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Belladonna gives a dryneſs and ſtricture <lb/>in the fauces; mercury or muriated
        barytes <lb/>produces ſalivation; arſenic ſets the teeth <lb/>on edge, produces gaſtritis,
        thirſt, black <pb xml:id="page_25" n="22"/>
        <lb/>tongue, ſubſultus tendinum, and delirium, <lb/>as in the laſt ſtage of typhus, in which
        <lb/>fever the ſtomach, on diſſection, is gene- <lb/>rally found morbidly red. A pin, a bit
        of <lb/>cork, nutmeg, or other indigeſtible matter <lb/>in the ſtomach, as if in the lungs,
        has, till <lb/>evacuated, occaſioned a continual cough- <lb/>ing <note place="bottom" n="*"
          >* Hildanus, Saunders, Percival. </note>; and an habitual cough is often ſuſ- <lb/>pended
        during a meal or any ſapid im- <lb/>preſſion. Cicuta produces giddineſs; alco- <lb/>hol,
        opium, fixed air, lead, and, when the <lb/>ſtomach is in a particular ſtate, other things
        <lb/>produce intoxication. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Lead produces gaſtrodynia, peculiar colic, <lb/>with conſtipation, yellow countenance,
        <lb/>palſy, chiefly of the ſupinators and extenſors <lb/>of the fingers, and extenſors of
        the legs, <lb/>with heat and pain in the palms and ſoles. <lb/>Copper occaſions delirium
        with leprous-like <lb/>ſpots on the ſurface. Digitalis, after remark- <pb xml:id="page_26"
          n="23"/>
        <lb/>ably diminiſhing the action of the heart and <lb/>arteries, and promoting abſorption
        and a <lb/>flow of urine, has been thrown up ſeem- <lb/>ingly intire during the deathful
        ſickneſs it <lb/>is apt to occaſion. Cantharides occaſion <lb/>ſtrangury and priapiſm, and
        ſometimes re- <lb/>lieve nervous caſes of the former; <note place="bottom" n="*">* Carmichæl
          Smyth. </note> rho- <lb/>dodendron chryſanthemum occaſions deliri- <lb/>um; ſtramonium
        occaſions itching, inflam- <lb/>mation, eruptions, ſwellings, tremors, fever, <lb/>and
        delirium; ſecale cornutum diſeaſed <lb/>(ergot) produces rhaphania; laurel-water <lb/>kills
        every ſpecies of animal, and in the <lb/>quantity of ſix ounces generally without <lb/>any
        previous ſymptom; an ounce or ſo al- <lb/>lows a reaction, which occaſions inflam-
        <lb/>mation, hæmorrhage, and convulſions. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Wepfer mentions a number of patients <lb/>poiſoned with water-hemlock, and affected
        <lb/>with pain at the ſtomach and in the bowels, <pb xml:id="page_27" n="24"/>
        <lb/>grinding of the teeth, hiccup, locked- <lb/>jaw, difficult reſpiration, an aſpect of
        <lb/>horror, convulſions, with the abolition <lb/>of all the ſenſes, hæmorrhage from the
        <lb/>ears, efforts to vomit, body bent back <lb/>like a bow, and death; after which <lb/>the
        belly and head ſwelled, there was a <lb/>green foam at the mouth, the orifices of <lb/>the
        ſtomach were found quite cloſed, and <lb/>the blood coagulated, as in every violent
        <lb/>death, from an internal cauſe, whereas, <lb/>from an external one, it remains liquid.
        <lb/>In ſome the ſymptoms indicated ludicrous, <lb/>and in others ſerious turns of mind. In
        <lb/>general, the appearance on diſſection of <lb/>animals killed by theſe or other poiſons,
        <lb/>or even by external ones, is redneſs of the <lb/>ſtomach, with livid or black ſpots in
        it, in <lb/>the inteſtines, particularly at the inſertion <lb/>of the ductus choledochus
        into the duo- <lb/>denum, and in the meſentery. So much <lb/>do impreſſions on the ſurface
        affect the <pb xml:id="page_28" n="25"/>
        <lb/>ſtomach, that Bonnet and others have found <lb/>theſe appearances in animals killed by
        the <lb/>bite of the viper; and Fontana mentions <lb/>dogs and cats recovering from the
        bite, in <lb/>proportion to the ſtruggle and violence of <lb/>vomiting. Tobacco oil applied
        externally <lb/>occaſions vomiting; and if the ſurface be <lb/>bare, it kills. The ſtomach
        is found red <lb/>in hydrophobia, and in other caſes connected <lb/>with affections of that
        organ. Morgagni and <lb/>Sprœgel could find no redneſs in rats poi- <lb/>ſoned by arſenic,
        or in rabbits that died on <lb/>taking corroſive ſublimate; nor could the <lb/>Florentine
        academicians find any change in <lb/>the ſolids or fluids of a bull killed by the <lb/>bite
        of a viper. Hence poiſons may deſtroy <lb/>life by diminiſhing the energy of the ſto-
        <lb/>mach beyond the power of reaction. </p>
      <div type="section">
        <pb xml:id="page_29" n="26"/>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic align-center">Emetics. </hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>An emetic induces, even in the ſtrongeſt, <lb/>affections of the natural, vital, and
          animal <lb/>functions, as a ſenſe of languor, laſſitude, <lb/>weakneſs, tremors of the
          limbs and lips; <lb/>diminiſhed action of the heart and its re- <lb/>moteſt veſſels, as
          appears from the ſmall, <lb/>weak, frequent, irregular pulſe, paleneſs <lb/>and ſhrinking
          of the ſurface, the cutis an- <lb/>ſerina, and from their effect on hæmor- <lb/>rhages and
          other diſcharges; difficult re- <lb/>ſpiration, vertigo, rigors, a ſenſe of weari-
          <lb/>ness, weakneſs, or pain in the muſcles of <lb/>the back, partial ſweating, anxiety at
          <lb/>ſtomach, conſtriction of the mouth and <lb/>fauces, ſalivation, expectoration,
          flowing of <lb/>the bile, ſickneſs, colic, vomiting; during <lb/>which exertion the face
          and eyes become <lb/>red, the veins turgid, the pulſe ſtrong, the <lb/>ſweat general, and
          the ſymptoms, which are <pb xml:id="page_30" n="27"/>
          <lb/>thoſe of intermittents and of all other ſto- <lb/>machic, or what are called
          conſtitutional <lb/>diſeaſes, are relieved. The effects of eme- <lb/>tics in incipient
          fever, phthiſis, gout, in- <lb/>flamed teſticle, certain dropſies, manias, and <lb/>other
          diſeaſes ſhew the influence of the ſto- <lb/>mach over every part of the ſyſtem. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Cathartics. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In the continued identical ſtructure from <lb/>the gullet to the rectum, the ſtate of
          <lb/>one part is apt to affect that of another; ſo <lb/>indigeſtion occaſions flatulence,
          ſpaſms and <lb/>pains in the inteſtines, which are often re- <lb/>lieved by a medicine on
          its reaching the <lb/>ſtomach; a looſeneſs occaſionally relieves <lb/>a vomiting, and a
          vomiting relieves a looſe- <lb/>ness; chewing or ſmoking tobacco will <lb/>purge, and a
          tobacco-injection or glyſter <lb/>will produce all the ſymptoms of an eme- <lb/>tic. A
          cathartic, though returned by vo- <pb xml:id="page_31" n="28"/>
          <lb/>miting, often purges, and a draſtic has <lb/>been known to purge ſeverely, and to
          prove <lb/>fatal, when, on diſſection, the ſtomach <lb/>only was found to he inflamed.
          Hoffmann <lb/>mentions a woman in a tertian, who, having <lb/>taken eight grains of glaſs
          of antimony, <lb/>had violent vomiting and purging during <lb/>three ſucceſſive fits, but
          not in the inter- <lb/>vals, that ſhe died in the third fit, that, on <lb/>diſſection, the
          ſtomach and upper inteſtines <lb/>were found inflamed and covered with gan- <lb/>grenous
          ſpots, and that the antimony was <lb/>retained in the villous coat of the ſtomach. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Moſt cathartics, like other matters, are <lb/>decompoſed before they paſs the
          pylorus; <lb/>thoſe which paſs ſeemingly unchanged, as <lb/>ſulphur, oxyd of mercury,
          caſſia, and rhu- <lb/>barb, are in general gentle in their opera- <lb/>tion. Scammony and
          gamboge are apt to <lb/>diſorder the ſtomach peculiarly; hellebore <lb/>occaſions great
          anxiety, with a ſenſe of ſuf- <lb/>focation; colocynth and reſinous pur- <pb
            xml:id="page_32" n="29"/>
          <lb/>gatives, as jalap, are apt to produce colic; <lb/>aloes affects the rectum, and the
          effects of <lb/>elaterium and iris paluſtris are felt at the <lb/>extremities of the
          arterial ſyſtem. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Diuretics, Refrigerants, and Sudorifics. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Diuretics, and mere liquids, ſometimes <lb/>excite urine ſo ſuddenly, that the
          ancients <lb/>imagined a direct communication between <lb/>the ſtomach and bladder. A
          retrograde mo- <lb/>tion in the lymphatics has been ſuppoſed, <lb/>and ingeniouſſly
          ſupported <note place="bottom" n="*">* Darwin. </note>; but the flow <lb/>appears to be
          often analogous to the ſudden <lb/>one of milk from the breaſts of nurſes, and <lb/>other
          ſudden ſecretions. Strangury is a <lb/>conſtant ſymptom of gaſtritis; and affections
          <lb/>of the urinary organs conſtantly affect the <lb/>ſtomach. Digitalis, ſquill, tobacco,
          and <pb xml:id="page_33" n="30"/>
          <lb/>moſt other diuretics are apt, like other <lb/>nauſeants, to be expectorant or
          ſudorific, <lb/>and if they be ſo in a conſiderable degree, <lb/>or if they produce
          vomiting or purging <lb/>early, they fail to induce that ſtate of <lb/>ſtomach which ſeems
          neceſſary to their <lb/>diuretic operation. Two ounces of any <lb/>neutral ſalt is apt to
          be emetic; an ounce <lb/>or ſo, even of alum, to be cathartic; two <lb/>or three drams to
          be diuretic; a dram to be <lb/>refrigerant, and, in a warm temperature, <lb/>ſudorific. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Though our ideas of quantity be <lb/>groſs, yet it cannot be ſuppoſed that ſuch
          <lb/>minute doſes of refrigerants, ſudorifics, or <lb/>antiſpaſmodics, of nitre, an
          antimonial, <lb/>ammonia, opium, <note place="bottom" n="*">* In cholera a grain or two of
            opium often in- <lb/>ſtantly diminiſhes the bilious vomiting, purging, and
            <lb/>ſecretion, the ſpaſms and pains over the body and <lb/>the coldneſs of the
            extremities. It affects the mind <lb/>in various ways, occaſionally producing and allay-
            <lb/>ing delirium. </note> or æther, can operate <pb xml:id="page_34" n="31"/>
          <lb/>by going to every point and pore of the <lb/>body. Alcohol <note place="bottom" n="*"
            >* A dram inſtantly ſteadies every fibre a tre- <lb/>mulous drunkard. </note> and
          aromatics, as curry, <lb/>heat in a cold temperature, and cool in a <lb/>hot one. Cold
          water is apt to produce heat <lb/>and ſweating, warm water to produce cold <lb/>and
          ſhivering. Ammonia, opium, aro- <lb/>matics, or alcohol induce heat in the cold <lb/>fit,
          and diminiſh it in the hot fit of fever; <lb/>an emetic or bark prevents both, and what
          <lb/>are called refrigerants are apt to increaſe <lb/>both. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center ">
          <lb/>Tonics. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Any nauſeous matter, acid, or air in the <lb/>ſtomach, or any diſagreeable
          impreſſion, or <lb/>the abſence of an accuſtomed one, is apt to <lb/>induce that ſtate of
          ſtomach in which its <lb/>power over the muſcles is diminiſhed, and <lb/>on which the
          ſenſe of weakneſs depends. <lb/>Such impreſſions and ſtates being removed, <lb/>the
          balance between the ſtomach and muſ- <pb xml:id="page_35" n="32"/>
          <lb/>cles is reſtored; which removal has been <lb/>called a tonic effect. Acids,
          aſtringents, <lb/>bitters, aromatics, fetids, iron, zinc, cop- <lb/>per, or arſenic may
          remove this ſtate, and <lb/>conſequently its ſymptoms, as weakneſs, <lb/>palſy, tremors,
          ſpaſm, fever, inflammation, <lb/>ulcer, gangrene, hæmorrhage and ſerous <lb/>diſcharge,
          and have been called tonic. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The faulty ſtate of ſtomach is not always <lb/>attended with impaired appetite, which
          <lb/>may be prurient, irregular, and even ex- <lb/>ceſſive; but that, in ſuch caſes, the
          ſtomach <lb/>is not in a natural ſtate is evident from the <lb/>deficient aſſimilation in
          phthiſis, bulimia, and <lb/>ſome moribund caſes; and from the morbid <lb/>one, in
          chloroſis, worms, and ſea-ſcurvy, <lb/>in which laſt the citric-acid taken into the
          <lb/>ſtomach, where it muſt be changed, ſeems <lb/>to counteract the effect of ſalt meat,
          cold <lb/>and moiſture on the ſurface, exceſs or de- <lb/>fect of exerciſe, and
          deſpondence, the uſual <pb xml:id="page_36" n="33"/>
          <lb/>cauſes of the diſeaſe. The ſudden effects <lb/>of ſmall doſes of aromatics, fetids,
          ammo- <lb/>nia, doſes of aromatics, fetids, ammo- <lb/>nia, alcohol, æther, or opium, in
          allaying <lb/>the ſenſe of weakneſs, heat, cold ſweating, <lb/>ſpaſm, pain, and other
          ſymptoms all over <lb/>the body, with depreſſions of mind; and of <lb/>the ſame medicines,
          and the bark in pre- <lb/>venting and arreſting ague-fits, ſhow that <lb/>ſuch ſymptoms
          depend on ſtates of ſtomach, <lb/>and that theſe medicines act on the ſtomach,
          <lb/>inducing changes in it, the effects of which <lb/>are propagated over the ſyſtem.
            <note place="bottom" n="*">* Tonics as exciting the power of the ſtomach <lb/>over every
            part of the body, and thus promoting life, <lb/>are antiſeptic. Life the great
            antiſeptic in nature, <lb/>ſeems to preſerve matters even in its neighbourhood, <lb/>as
            pus in abſceſs, blood in aneuriſm, and water in <lb/>dropſy; and that this does not
            depend on the exclu- <lb/>ſion of air is evident, from putrefaction taking place
            <lb/>within the body as ſoon as life is gone. </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If fever, inflammatory and hæmorrhagic <lb/>diſeaſes, were affections merely of the
            <pb xml:id="page_37" n="34"/>
          <lb/>heart and blood-veſſels; nervous diſeaſes <lb/>of the brain and nerves; dropſy, and
          <lb/>ſcrophula of the lymphatics; ſcirrhus of <lb/>the other glands; ulcers of the skin;
          <lb/>dyſpnæa and cough of the lungs; rheu- <lb/>matiſm of the large joints, and gout of
          the <lb/>ſmall; jaundice of the ducts of the liver, and <lb/>diabetes of the kidneys,
          theſe would oftener <lb/>exiſt together; but being ſymptoms of ſtates <lb/>of ſtomach, and
          as different ſtates of the <lb/>ſame organ cannot exiſt at the ſame time, <lb/>the ſyſtem
          is thus not readily overpowered <lb/>by a confluence of diſeaſes; the ſame <lb/>cauſes
          induce different ſymptoms according <lb/>to prediſpoſition,; the ſame remedy an-
          <lb/>ſwers in various morbid ſtates, and it ſeems <lb/>thus that the balance of ſecretions
          is eſta- <lb/>bliſhed. How often, after death, are <lb/>morbid ſtates of brain, lungs, and
          heart, <lb/>in vain looked for, while the cauſe of all <lb/>the ſymptoms is either
          inviſible or found <pb xml:id="page_38" n="35"/>
          <lb/>in the ſtomach, which had not ſeemed <lb/>previouſly to ſuffer. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Narcotics. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Narcotics ſeem to induce a ſtate of <lb/>ſtomach, which tends to ſupply the want
          <lb/>of neceſſary impreſſions, or reſiſt ſuch as are <lb/>apt to occaſion pain or prevent
          ſleep, the <lb/>natural relief and reſtorer of the ſentient <lb/>part. If a morbid
          impreſſion exiſt, as from <lb/>acid in the ſtomach, ſordes in the bowels, <lb/>of fulneſs
          in the veſſels; or if it be of a me- <lb/>chanical or chemical nature in any other
          <lb/>part, it muſt be removed; or if it be from <lb/>a lacerated nerve, this muſt be
          divided, <lb/>otherwiſe narcotics may not operate, or <lb/>may even aggravate the
          ſymptoms. It is <lb/>the ſtate produced by the impreſſion, as the <lb/>painful ſtate of
          nerve; muſcular ſpaſm; <lb/>or local inflammation, as from bruiſes or <lb/>wounds; ulcer;
          or diſpoſition to gangrene, <pb xml:id="page_39" n="36"/>
          <lb/>as in the toes <note place="bottom" n="*">* Pott. </note>, that narcotics and
          medicines <lb/>uſed in ſuch caſes affect, and that only by <lb/>keeping the aſſimilating
          and reſiſting powers, <lb/>and thereby the other functions in a proper <lb/>ſtate, till
          the morbid impreſſion loſe its <lb/>power, and the morbid ſtate, diſpoſition, and
          <lb/>habit ceaſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>While every part continues under the <lb/>dominion of the ſtomach, no mechanical or
          <lb/>chemical change of a morbid nature can <lb/>take place in the ſolids or fluids of the
          <lb/>ſyſtem; and from the natural accommo- <lb/>dation between the ſtomach and other parts
          <lb/>conſtantly tending to a level, and forming <lb/>an equally, though ſometimes
          ſlenderly, <lb/>balanced conſtitution, morbid impreſſions <lb/>are often reſiſted, local
          complaints ariſing <lb/>in the courſe of diſeaſe become tolerable, <lb/>and changes and
          extremes of the ordinary <lb/>impreſſions, which are all firſt felt at the <pb
            xml:id="page_40" n="37"/>
          <lb/>ſtomach, can be borne in a remarkable de- <lb/>gree; but when the balance between the
          <lb/>ſtomach and other parts, by means of in- <lb/>ternal or external impreſſions, or
          evacua- <lb/>tions, is diminiſhed or loſt, as in an ill or <lb/>broken conſtitution, a
          ſlight change in ordi- <lb/>nary, morbid, or ſalutary impreſſions, is felt. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The ſtomach may be put into a ſtate <lb/>more or leſs ſuſceptible of a particular im-
          <lb/>preſſion. Mercury, whether adminiſtered <lb/>internally or externally, ſeems to
          render it <lb/>more ſenſible to that of the bark in ague, of <lb/>ſquill in dropſy, of
          opium in ſyphilis, and <lb/>of electricity in various diſeaſes. In mania <lb/>the ſtomach
          and ſyſtem are generally very <lb/>inſenſible to impreſſions; but opium given an <lb/>hour
          or two before even an ordinary doſe of <lb/>an emetic, promotes its operation, though
          <lb/>in a combined ſpecific effects are uſually diminiſhed. <lb/>In mania, reaſon is
          generally obſerved to re- <pb xml:id="page_41" n="38"/>
          <lb/>turn in proportion to this ſenſibility of the <lb/>ſtomach. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Impreſſions differ not only in kind, but in <lb/>degree, and are powerful, being leſs
          reſiſted, <lb/>as they are ſudden. Strong ones, as eme- <lb/>tics, warm water, &amp;c. act
          chiefly on the <lb/>ſtomach, while weak ones, ſuch as do not <lb/>even nauſeate, and have
          little ſenſible qua- <lb/>lity, as ſmall doſes of emetics, warm <lb/>water, abſorbents,
          ſarſaparilla, entire muſtard-ſeed, <lb/>and oxyds, affect the remoteſt parts, and <lb/>are
          much uſed in indigeſtion, nervous diſ- <lb/>eaſes, paſſive diſcharges, and ulcers. A
          <lb/>remedy or doſe to the unaccuſtomed, ope- <lb/>rates like an unexpected blow or event,
          <lb/>with proportional forece; a ſtrong impreſſion <lb/>on the ſurface affects the part
          chiefly, <lb/>while tickling, a ſcratch, dentition, a tranſ- <lb/>polanted tooth, and
          other ſeemingly weak <lb/>but peculiar impreſſions, affect the ſtomach <lb/>and ſyſtem
          conſiderably. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <pb xml:id="page_42" n="39"/>
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>External Impreſſions. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Impreſſions on the ſenſes affect the ſto- <lb/>mach. A diſagreeable taſte, ſmell,
          ſound, <lb/>or touch, is apt to occaſion ſickneſs and <lb/>ſhivering, to ſet the teeth on
          edge, or to <lb/>make the mouth water. The ſmell of ſpi- <lb/>rits ſickens and intoxicates
            <note place="bottom" n="*">* It is ſaid that a little in the ſtomach prevents the
            <lb/>intoxicating effect of the ſmell. </note>; ſmells agree- <lb/>able to ſome, make
          others sick, faint, and <lb/>ſuffer abortion; while fetid ones ſometimes <lb/>recover
          people from ſickneſs, ſyncope, or <lb/>hyſteria. Certain motions, as that of a <lb/>ſwing,
          ſhip, or carriage; going backwards, <lb/>turning round, and, in caſes of ill-health,
          <lb/>the poſture of ſtanding, or even ſitting, oc- <lb/>caſions ſickneſs, while that of
          lying prevents <lb/>it and ſyncope. Agreeable ſenſations often <lb/>relieve ſickneſs and
          promote digeſtion; but <lb/>in exceſs, injure the ſtomach exceedingly. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_43" n="40"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Emotions are felt at the ſtomach. The <lb/>modifications of averſion, as fear, anger,
          <lb/>ſhame, and grief, inſtantly impair the keen- <lb/>eſt appetite, and are apt to
          occaſion ſick- <lb/>ness, tremors, paleneſs, fluſhings, weeping, <lb/>various nervous
          affections, looſeneſs, and <lb/>jaundice. One is ſick at the thought of <lb/>anything
          diſagreeable; and an injury is pro- <lb/>perly enough ſaid to ſtick in the ſtomach;
          <lb/>which word itſelf in many languages im- <lb/>plies anger and other ſtates of mind.
          The <lb/>modifications of deſire, as hope, compla- <lb/>cence, and joy, improve the
          appetite and <lb/>promote digeſtion and ſtrength. The <lb/>thought of any thing agreeable
          does one's <lb/>heart good; which common phraſe, like <lb/>that of ſick at heart, refers
          to the ſtomach, <lb/>as the word bowels does to the kindly af- <lb/>fections. Agreeable
          emotions in exceſs are <lb/>apt to produce mania and other diſorders, <lb/>and have been
          ſuddenly fatal. While the <lb/>mind is much ſtruck, or fixed, as in thought, <pb
            xml:id="page_44" n="41"/>
          <lb/>paſſion, affection, or mania, the ſenſibility is <lb/>diminiſhed to other
          impreſſions, as that of <lb/>ſpirits, medicines, contagion, and tempera- <lb/>ture; and
          fits of various diſeaſes are thus <lb/>ſuſpended. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>There is a great analogy between the in- <lb/>ternal ſurface, from the mouth to the
          anus, <lb/>and the external one <note place="bottom" n="*">* Monro, Jackſon. </note>, both
          being continu- <lb/>ous, pervious to fluids by veſſels, quickly <lb/>regenerating loſt
          ſubſtance, covered with <lb/>mucous or ſebaceous matter defending <lb/>the tender
          ſurfaces, liable to abraſion, <lb/>inflammation, thickening, and probably <lb/>the ſame
          eruptive and other diſeaſes, the <lb/>ſtate of the one affecting or alternating <lb/>with
          that of the other. Perhaps the <lb/>growth of hair after death, ſhews ſome
          <lb/>continuance of life in the skin. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As a ſtrong doſe, it was obſerved, <lb/>chiefly affects the ſtomach, ſo a ſtrong <pb
            xml:id="page_45" n="42"/>
          <lb/>impreſſion, as pinching, affects chiefly <lb/>the part; tickling affects the whole
          ſyſ- <lb/>tem, occaſioning itching and laughter, and <lb/>if continued, weakneſs,
          ſickneſs, vomit- <lb/>ing, and convulſions. Gentle pinching <lb/>and friction are
          prevailing eaſtern cuſtoms, <lb/>and exerciſe is univerſally ſo, for promoting
          <lb/>digeſtion. A large bleeding ſickens, and <lb/>ſmall ones are commended in many caſes;
          <lb/>compreſſion allays vomiting and colic; a <lb/>plaſter, by giving ſupport to the
          muſcles of <lb/>the back, ſeems ſometimes to ſteady the ſto- <lb/>mach and ſyſtem; and the
          want of uſual com- <lb/>preſſion, as that of a neck-cloth, ſtays, or <lb/>garters, is apt
          to produce ſickneſs and other <lb/>uneaſy feelings. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Scrophulous-like tumors in the neck <lb/>have been attributed to compreſſion of the
          <lb/>inguinal glands by a truſs; and various diſ- <lb/>eaſes to that of the feet and other
          parts. <lb/>Peculiar impreſſions, or ſlight impreſſions <lb/>in peculiar ſtates, produce
          peculiar ſymp- <pb xml:id="page_46" n="43"/>
          <lb/>toms. A ſcratch produces in ſome, ſwelled <lb/>glands; in others tetanus <note
            place="bottom" n="*">* This occurs particularly in warm climates, where <lb/>there is
            little diſpoſition to inflammation. The ap- <lb/>plication of a ſtimulant, as
            turpentine, to the part ex- <lb/>citing proper inflammation and ſuppuration, has been
            <lb/>found to prevent tetanus; and mercury is probably <lb/>uſeful in it and ſome other
            caſes, by inducing that <lb/>ſtate of ſtomach and veſſel which has been called
            <lb/>phlogiſtic; in which the parts of the blood are in <lb/>that ſeparable ſtate, fit
            for forming a proper ſuppura- <lb/>tion. </note>, with a ſtate of <lb/>ſtomach attended
          with pain, and which <lb/>has borne fifteen hundred grains of good <lb/>opium in ſix days,
          without ſleep, or any <lb/>affection of the head or mind. An old <lb/>and obſtinate
          epilepſy, it is ſaid, has ceaſed <lb/>to return after the extirpation of a wart from
          <lb/>the ſurface. Dentition produces vomiting, <lb/>purging, eruptions, fever, and
          convulſions. <lb/>A tranſplanted tooth has produced appear- <lb/>ances of ſyphilis or
          ſcrophula, cured both <lb/>with and without mercury. A wound <pb xml:id="page_47" n="44"/>
          <lb/>gradually, according to its ſeat or extent, <lb/>affects the ſtomach, as appears from
          the <lb/>indigeſtion, foul tongue, and fever, in- <lb/>ducing, as in pregnancy for the
          fœtus, <lb/>that ſtate of veſſel neceſſary to form the buffy- <lb/>coat, and inſtead of
          blood, that ſuppu- <lb/>ration, ſo remarkably under the influ- <lb/>ence of diet; and
          during which the <lb/>ſtate of ſtomach is ſometimes ſuch, that <lb/>ſolid meat has
          ſuddenly produced great <lb/>weakneſs, with dyſpnæa, delirium, and con- <lb/>vulſions,
          ending in death; and the ſuppura- <lb/>tory or hectic ſtate, if it does not heal,
          <lb/>teaſes, waſtes, and deſtroys. In pregnancy <lb/>the ſtate of ſtomach is peculiar,
          ſeemingly <lb/>neceſſary to the retention of the fœtus; and <lb/>may be the cauſe of its
          reſiſting contagion, <lb/>and arreſting the ſymptoms of phthiſis. A <lb/>ſtate of veſſel
          that teaſes the ſtomach and <lb/>ſyſtem, is often taken off by a ſpontaneous
          <lb/>hæmorrhage or inflammation effected by an <pb xml:id="page_48" n="45"/>
          <lb/>effort of the ſtomach, which a bleeding or <lb/>a bliſter could not allay. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The elements of food and drink in form- <lb/>ing chyle, blood, ſecretions, and ſolid
          parts; <lb/>and the baſe of vital air uniting with theſe by <lb/>the lungs, and perhaps by
          the ſurface, may <lb/>give the blood its colour, its temperature, <lb/>its mobility, its
          coagulability, its power <lb/>of acting on the left ventricle with thoſe <lb/>appearances
          of vitality aſcribed to it by <lb/>Mr. Hunter; and theſe condenſations <lb/>going on leſs
          in a warm temperature, <lb/>and more in a cold one, may by the ac- <lb/>commodating nature
          of the ſtomach with <lb/>the other parts, preſerve the equilibrium <lb/>of heat in the
          ſyſtem. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>That temperature on the ſurface affects <lb/>the ſtomach, is evident from certain
          appli- <lb/>cations of cold exciting vomiting and purg- <lb/>ing; from hot applications,
          or a hot fit re- <lb/>lieving thoſe vomitings which occur in <lb/>fever and the plague;
          and from changes of <pb xml:id="page_49" n="46"/>
          <lb/>temperature inducing or relieving various <lb/>diſeaſes, and fits of diſeaſe of which
          the <lb/>ſtomach is the feat <note place="bottom" n="*">* Mr. Farquhar mentions a patient,
            who, ſince <lb/>the uſe of ice for burns, has continued free for <lb/>a conſiderable
            time from hyſterical complaints of <lb/>long ſtanding. </note>. A warm fomenta-
          <lb/>tion relieves the ſenſe of heat, handling ſnow <lb/>occaſions it, an irritation as
          from a thorn <lb/>produces it, and an irritation in the ſtomach <lb/>occaſions
          alternations of heat and cold. <lb/>Human heat is between 32° and 156°, the <lb/>two
          coagulating points; and the agreeable <lb/>is, excluſively of habit, between 32° and
          <lb/>the human heat. In tropical and polar <lb/>climates the appetite is keen, and the
          ſto- <lb/>mach reſiſts the power of intoxicating <lb/>liquors and of contagion. Seeds,
          eggs, im- <lb/>perfect and young animals and maniacs, <lb/>being, as it were, all ſtomach,
          bear the ef- <lb/>fects of heat and cold remarkably. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Certain degrees of heat and cold diſpoſe <pb xml:id="page_50" n="47"/>
          <lb/>to ſleep; which, in the caſe of cold, or of <lb/>external and internal poiſon,
          ſubduing the <lb/>power of the ſtomach, is apt to prove fatal. <lb/>From the long faſting
          that is borne in <lb/>ſleep, the ſlow operation of a medicine, and <lb/>the ſuſpenſion of
          ſtools, the ſtomach ſeems <lb/>leſs ſenſible in that ſtate; the temperature <lb/>is two
          degrees leſs; and cold is eaſily caught <lb/>in ſleep. If appetite or ſleep paſs its pe-
          <lb/>riods, the diſpoſition ceaſes, and its re- <lb/>turn is the firſt ſymptom of criſis
          in fever. <lb/>Dyſpeptics are apt to ſtart from ſleep or the <lb/>article of ſleep, and
          then other nervous af- <lb/>fections, as aſthma, palpitation, epilepſy, <lb/>and gout, are
          apt to happen, probably from <lb/>the change in the ſtate of the ſtomach. It <lb/>ſeems to
          be only in occaſional ſtates of <lb/>ſtomach that fits from fixed cauſes, and <lb/>other
          periodical diſeaſes, occur. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Friction, fomentations, aromatics, fe- <lb/>tids, acrids, ſpirits, ammonia, æther,
          and <lb/>opium allay vomiting and internal ſpaſms, <pb xml:id="page_51" n="48"/>
          <lb/>prove cathartic, or favour the operation of <lb/>one. In people with whoſe ſtomachs
          ho- <lb/>ney, unctuous matter, or eggs diſagree, <lb/>any application of theſe or of wax
          to a <lb/>ſore, has been obſerved likewiſe to diſ- <lb/>agree. Tartite or muriate of
          antimony ap- <lb/>plied externally, as if taken into the ſto- <lb/>mach, excite vomiting,
          purging, and ſweat- <lb/>ing. Lead, copper, mercury, and other im- <lb/>preſſions, produce
          vomiting and purging. It <lb/>is ſaid that bitters expel worms, that opium <lb/>and
          tobacco produce ebriety, that bark <lb/>cures ague, and that opium applied to the
          <lb/>bare ſurface has deſtroyed life without be- <lb/>ing abſorbed. Ammonia weakened with
          <lb/>oil, ſo as to be applied to the ſurface, fre- <lb/>quently produces nauſea and an
          univerſal <lb/>ſweat. Some ſapids ſo applied, ſeem to <lb/>affect the ſenſe of taſte
          without reaching it. <lb/>Arſenic, the bite of a viper, or of a mad- <lb/>dog, has
          produced death; and, on diſſec- <pb xml:id="page_52" n="49"/>
          <lb/>tion, the ſtomach only has been found in- <lb/>flamed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The ſtate of the tongue and mouth <lb/>is always attended to as a mark of the
          <lb/>ſtate of ſtomach, according to which the <lb/>ſenſations of taſte are various, and
          the <lb/>ſaliva and mucus vary in quantity, con- <lb/>ſiſtence, taſte, ſmell, and colour.
          Hence <lb/>waterineſs, ptyaliſm, ſalivation, or foam- <lb/>ing, is apt to occur on the
          ſight of grateful <lb/>food in indigeſtion, pyroſis, pregnancy, hy- <lb/>drophobia,
          epilepſy, ſcurvy, fever, and <lb/>ſmall-pox; the firſt ſymptom of which <lb/>laſt is pain
          at ſtomach, and the chief re- <lb/>medy cold to the ſurface. Lead, anti- <lb/>mony,
          barytes <note place="bottom" n="*">* Crawford. </note>, fox-glove, opium, or the
          <lb/>guatimala ſerpent, as well as mercury, ex- <lb/>cite ſalivation, which is promoted by
          a <lb/>nauſeant or emetic, or by different degrees <lb/>of temperature. A grain or two of
          a mer- <pb xml:id="page_53" n="50"/>
          <lb/>curialin the ſtomach, or on the bare skin, <lb/>has had the effect; the ſalivation,
          like a <lb/>gleet or mercurial ſore, will ſometimes <lb/>continue for months; and when
          ſuddenly <lb/>ſtopt, is apt to be followed by a violent <lb/>affection of ſtomach, with
          vomiting, only <lb/>to be allayed by mercury <note place="bottom" n="*">* Lond. Med. Obs.
            &amp; Inq. vol. iii. p. 246. </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If infection be removed before the ſpecific <lb/>ſtate of ſtomach and veſſel be
          induced, di- <lb/>ſeaſe does not take place; and the morbid <lb/>ſtate itſelf may, in the
          caſe of ſyphilis, be <lb/>removed, for a time at leaſt, by copper, or <lb/>by a courſe of
          corroſive ſublimate, or by <lb/>fever, while the diſpoſition may remain, and <lb/>break
          out with or without virulence. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Such is the ſenſibility of the skin as well <lb/>as ſtomach, that a cold or hot body,
          or an <lb/>aſtringent applied to either, is apt to pro- <lb/>duce a contraction over all,
          and ſtop ſome <lb/>hæmorrhages. Fantonus mentions a man <pb xml:id="page_54" n="51"/>
          <lb/>in a fever, in whom bliſter-iſſues that had <lb/>dried up, opened and diſcharged
          anew, <lb/>after the application of other bliſters to <lb/>diſtant parts. A plaſter on
          ſome skins ex- <lb/>cites an eruption in other parts. After a <lb/>ſuppuration in the
          fore-arm, a ſwelling has <lb/>taken place ſucceſſively in the arm-pit, the <lb/>parotid,
          the leg, the knee, and the groin. <lb/>A ſwelled teſticle is allowed to be merely
          <lb/>from irritation. A ſucceſſion of tumors <lb/>takes place in the conglobate glands
          <lb/>from the meſentery to the neck, and <lb/>likewiſe from a compreſſion of the in-
          <lb/>guinal glands; in the inguinal and axillary <lb/>from irritation at the toes and
          fingers, <lb/>with or without infection; and in the neck <lb/>and behind the ears from a
          ſcratch, a <lb/>bliſter, or tinea capitis in the neighbour- <lb/>hood. The pain of a
          wound, burn, or <lb/>bruiſe, is ſometimes alleviated as pain be- <lb/>gins in another
          part. Pain, ſpaſm, inflam- <pb xml:id="page_55" n="52"/>
          <lb/>mation, and other ſtates are apt to ſhift, <lb/>as are ulcers, that is peculiar
          ſtates of veſſel <lb/>with peculiar aſſimilation as the ichor of <lb/>cancer, the
          cheeſy-like matter of ſcrofula, <lb/>and the ſtony matter of gout. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Noxious matter ſeems either rejected by <lb/>the abſorbents at the ſurface, or
          aſſimilated <lb/>before it meet the chyle in the thoracic duct. <lb/>A mild ſubſtance like
          milk or mucilage in- <lb/>jected into a vein, is apt to throw the <lb/>ſyſtem into
          convulſions. The fleſh of an <lb/>animal killed by a poiſonous bite or arrow, <lb/>affords
          wholeſome food; during a courſe <lb/>of chalybeates no ſuperfluous iron is de- <lb/>tected
          in the chyle or blood; bile circulat- <lb/>ing in jaundice does not produce giddineſs,
          <lb/>dimneſs of ſight, &amp;c. as when in the ſto- <lb/>mach; colouring and odorous
          particles, as <lb/>of madder, logwood, turpentine, garlic, or <lb/>aſparagus, circulate
          without producing any <lb/>effect; in ſyphilis the fluids, and even ſe- <lb/>condary
          ulcers do not generally infect; and <pb xml:id="page_56" n="53"/>
          <lb/>though a mercurial may loſe, and ſulphur <lb/>acquire oxygen in the ſyſtem, yet it is
          not <lb/>alleged that either is found there but in its <lb/>mild ſtate. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A morbid ſtate or a fever, attended <lb/>with inflammation, eruption or ulcer, often
          <lb/>takes place ſuddenly, and runs its courſe <lb/>without any infection, applied or
          generated, <lb/>or any cauſe or remedy which acts on the <lb/>fluids; in the caſe of
          infection the ſymp- <lb/>toms, as the variolous eruption, ſometimes <lb/>do not appear,
          and ſometimes continue to <lb/>appear when the ſtate or the fever is gone; <lb/>and are
          affected by external temperature, <lb/>while the internal one continues the ſame;
          <lb/>ſome very infectious diſeaſes, as the yaws, <lb/>admit of cure from mere attention to
          the <lb/>general health; an infectious irritation, <lb/>like others, takes time before it
          affects the <lb/>reſiſting and aſſimilating power, ſo as to <lb/>produce the ſpecific
          ſtate of veſſel and ſpe- <lb/>cific matter; during the variolous and ſy- <pb
            xml:id="page_57" n="54"/>
          <lb/>philitic ſtate, though there is nothing to <lb/>prevent abſorption, any new infection
          ſeems <lb/>to have no conſtitutional effect; in the caſe <lb/>of ſmall-pox, yaws, and ſome
          other infec- <lb/>tions, the ſyſtem becomes afterwards in- <lb/>ſuſceptible of their
          action, as it, in ſome <lb/>meaſure, does of that of accuſtomed ones, <lb/>as ſpirits,
          opium, tobacco, and even febrile <lb/>contagion; and no ſatisfying account is <lb/>given
          why the abſorption, multiplication, <lb/>or aſſimilation, with the other effects of an
          <lb/>infectious particle are not more immediate, <lb/>and in proportion to its quantity,
          and why <lb/>after abſorption, it ſhould in any caſe fail <lb/>to aſſimilate. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Morbific matter does not ſeem to be a cauſe <lb/>of gout or of other diſeaſes, called
          hereditary, <lb/>as mania, epilepſy, or ſcrofula, which are <lb/>not infectious, and in
          which, as in all other <lb/>caſes, the ſtate of the fluids muſt depend on <lb/>that of the
          ſolids. Gout often attacks per- <lb/>ſons in ſeemingly good health preceded <pb
            xml:id="page_58" n="55"/>
          <lb/>perhaps only by ſlight ſymptoms of ſome <lb/>affection of the alimentary canal, is
          ſubject <lb/>to frequent, ſudden, and diſtant tranſlations, <lb/>affecting the joints with
          inflammation, but <lb/>the ſtomach with a ſtate ſo oppoſite, that <lb/>highly ſtimulating
          cordials are taken with <lb/>relief; and no antidote to gouty matter <lb/>there, whether
          ſuppoſed acid or otherwiſe <lb/>acrimonious, was ever thought of. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The remedies in ſyphilis tend to bring <lb/>the ſtomach and conſequently the veſſels
          <lb/>from their ſyphilitic ſtate, and to keep the <lb/>functions in a proper condition
          till the im- <lb/>preſſion ceaſe to operate, the morbid ſtate <lb/>be changed, and the
          habit overcome. The <lb/>remedies affect the aſſimilating organs, and <lb/>except perhaps
          the corroſive ſublimate, im- <lb/>prove them, as appears from the corpulence <lb/>to which
          they diſpoſe. Infants have re- <lb/>markably aſſimilating and reſiſting powers,
          <lb/>ſlaver a great deal, are not eaſily affected by <lb/>ſyphilis, or eaſily ſalivated by
          mercury, and <pb xml:id="page_59" n="56"/>
          <lb/>are eaſily cured. Mercury, and opium when <lb/>it ſucceeds, ſeem to put the ſtomach
          in a pe- <lb/>culiar ſtate, ſomewhat, perhaps, like that <lb/>of infancy, and the
          ſalivation does not ap- <lb/>pear to be from abſorption any more than <lb/>when it occurs
          from an emetic, pregnancy, <lb/>or worms; or than giddineſs is when it <lb/>ariſes from
          the uſe of hemlock. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Inflammation by muſtard, &amp;c. does not <lb/>excite ſtrangury, as cantharides are
          apt to <lb/>do. It often ceaſes the moment the bliſter <lb/>is removed, the effect of the
          impreſſion is <lb/>allayed by a poultice, or the ſtomach is <lb/>ſoothed by a diluent, or
          by camphorated <lb/>oil applied to the ſurface. Cantharides in- <lb/>ternally relieve
          paralytic ſtrangury, and in- <lb/>continence of urine; ſtrangury frequently <lb/>occurs
          from affections of the ſtomach, as <lb/>gaſtritis; and the uva urſi, alkali, or ſuper-
          <lb/>carbonated alkali, whoſe effects ſeem chiefly <lb/>confined to the ſtomach,
          occaſionally re- <lb/>lieve even fits of the ſtone. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_60" n="57"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Contagions, whether marſhy, human, or <lb/>ſpecific, are ſometimes traced to ſmells,
          as <lb/>a cadaverous one, a heavy earthy one, that <lb/>of the confluent ſmall-pox,
          dyſenteric ſtools; <lb/>or they may induce the febrile ſtate, the <lb/>only ſteady
          character of which is weakneſs, <lb/>though the impreſſion do not juſt excite the
          <lb/>ſtate of ſenſation. It may be in a way ſ <lb/>imilar to what happens in
          idioſyncraſies in <lb/>regard to cheeſe, a cat, &amp;c. or that of the <lb/>inſenſible
          action of various irritations, as of <lb/>worms. A gentleman who cannot bear <lb/>being in
          a room where there is any cheeſe, <lb/>though he does not ſee or ſmell it in <lb/>the
          leaſt, inſtantly feels a ſenſe of weak- <lb/>ness, after ſome time, ſickneſs with a cold
          <lb/>ſweat, and faints if he endeavour to brave <lb/>it. In this way contagion may,
          through <lb/>the organ of ſmell, affect the ſtomach <lb/>and ſyſtem. Inoculated, it
          produces <lb/>the ſpecific ſtate, inflammation and ſup- <lb/>puration, and in the caſe of
          ſmall-pox <pb xml:id="page_61" n="58"/>
          <lb/>without prediſpoſition, the ſtomach does <lb/>not yield too much, and its energy is
          kept <lb/>up by cold on the ſurface, ſo that a ſlight <lb/>eruption happens ſometimes
          without fever. <lb/>Heat on a part ſeems to increaſe the vario- <lb/>lous ſtate of veſſel.
          Cool air on the ſurface <lb/>recovers perſons from the ſtate induced by <lb/>carbonic,
          azotic, and other noxious airs, the <lb/>firſt ſymptom of which is vomiting; from
          <lb/>ſyncope, and from the ſtill-born ſtate, the <lb/>firſt exertion from which is ſeen to
          be about <lb/>the region of the ſtomach; and the cold <lb/>ſeems to operate, as in
          diſcharges of blood, <lb/>by exciting the ſtomach from its paſſive <lb/>ſtate. Affections
          of the ſtomach, as ob- <lb/>ſerved, mark fever in its attack, progreſs, <lb/>remiſſion,
          criſis, and cure; all its cauſes af- <lb/>fect the ſtomach; it has no ſymptom but
          <lb/>what an immediate application to the ſto- <lb/>mach may produce and its evacuation
          re- <lb/>move; and it is often prevented and cured <lb/>by remedies affecting only that
          organ. <pb xml:id="page_62" n="59"/>
          <lb/>Its forms of intermittent, remittent, conti- <lb/>nual, yellow, bilious, and
          dyſenteric, ſeem <lb/>all related, prevailing at the ſame time, <lb/>changing their types,
          and running into one <lb/>another; and the late obſervations, made in <lb/>different
          climates, tend to ſhow that the <lb/>ſame treatment, properly timed, anſwers <lb/>equally
          with them all. </p>
      </div>
      <trailer rend="align-center">
        <lb/>THE END. </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
