<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Younge: Concerning a Ball, Extracted from a Person</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>James Younge</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Letter from Mr James Young, F. R. S. to Dr Edward Tyson, F.
              R. S. concerning a Ball, Extracted from a Person, Who Had Suffered by, It 30 Years,in
              Which Was a Plumb-Stone</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for S. Smith and B. Walford, Printers to the Royal
                  Society, at the Prince's Arms in St Paul's Church-yard. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1702-1703</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">23</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">1279-1283</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110919082</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi:10.1098/rstl.1702.0035</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT23_1279">
    <body>
      <pb n="1279"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">IV.</hi> A Letter from Mr <hi rend="roman">James Young</hi>, F. R. S.
        to Dr <lb/><hi rend="roman">Edward Tyſon</hi>, F. R. S. concerning a Ball, extract- <lb/>ed
        from a Perſon, who had ſuffered by it 30 years, in which <lb/>was a <choice>
          <corr>Plumb</corr>
          <sic>Plumh</sic>
        </choice>-ſtone, </head>
      <dateline rend="align-center">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Plymouth</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Sept.</hi> 6. 1702. </dateline>
      <salute rend="italic indent space">
        <lb/>Worthy Sir, </salute>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">W</hi>Hen I had laſt the Honour to be at a meeting of the <lb/>Royal
        Society in <hi rend="italic">Greſham</hi> College, there happened <lb/>in a diſcourſe
        concerning Plumbs, which gave me occaſion to <lb/>tell you of one detained in the Guts of a
        Woman above 30 <lb/>years, cauſing ſtrange and grievous accidents, till I drew it <lb/>out
          <hi rend="italic">ex Ano</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>According to my promiſe then, I ſend you now a more <lb/>particular account of that
        wonderful caſe and cure than I <lb/>could give by meer memory. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Her name is <hi rend="italic">Sarah Swayn</hi>, of a thin habit and middle ſta-
        <lb/>ture, who when but ſix years old, was firſt afflicted with a <lb/>violent pain,
        together with a large hard ſwelling on the <lb/>left ſide of her Belly, which laſted twelve
        hours, and then <lb/>went off without uſe of any Remedy or ſenſible evacuation; <lb/>and at
        the end of three months returned, laſted and went off <lb/>as before. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Several years it obſerved that Period, and then changed <lb/>its intermiſſion from 3
        months to 3 weeks, and ſo <choice>
          <corr>continued</corr>
          <sic>continned</sic>
        </choice>
        <lb/>till ſhe was 35 years old, in which time ſhe married, and <lb/>bore one Child, the pain
        of which ſhe averr'd to be much <lb/>leſs than what theſe <hi rend="italic">Paroxiſms</hi>
        gave her. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>During her pregnancy, her Pains nor Intermiſſions had no <lb/>alteration, and in her
        whole Life ſhe found no Diet diſturb'd <lb/>her but Milk and Salt Meats. </p>
      <pb n="1280"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About 9 months before ſhe was cured, the Pain and Tu- <lb/>mour encreaſed to the
        bigneſs of a mans two Fiſts, ſhe en- <lb/>deavoured by many Remedies to get eaſe, but in
        vain, till <lb/>the torment and watching had ſo weakned her, that ſhe <lb/>could not riſe
        out of her Bed nor lie down in it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In this deplorable condition ſhe was adviſed by a Wo- <lb/>man to take a doſe of
        Powder'd Jalop, what the quantity <lb/>was I could not learn, but it operated violently, and
        ſud- <lb/>denly drove the pain from her ſide down to the <hi rend="italic">Anus</hi>, where
        <lb/>it reſembled a <hi rend="italic">Teneſmus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> a conſtant
        and violent inclina- <lb/>tion to ſtools without being able to force off any thing, and
        <lb/>after ſhe had been thus crucified four days her Urine alſo <lb/>ſtopt, and two days
        after that the charitable Neighbours, <lb/>who had all along given her their beſt aſſiſtance
        craved <lb/>mine. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I perceived by their report of the matter, that ſomething <lb/>obſtructed the paſſage
        of her Excrements, and ſoon found it <lb/>ſo by a probe; I then anointed the paſſage with
          <hi rend="italic">Populkeum</hi>, <lb/>and taking hold of the ſubſtance with a pair of
        large For- <lb/>ceps, made to extract Stones from the Bladder after Litho- <lb/>tomy, I drew
        it forth. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Abundance of Wind and Excrements guſht out, and con- <lb/>tinued to flow till her Guts
        were emptied of all the matter, <lb/>which had been ſo long retained; after which I ordered
        her <lb/>an Anodine Clyſter, and a compoſing draught, and ever <lb/>ſince (being ſeveral
        years) ſhe continueth well. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The thing extracted was round, ſomewhat oblong, ha- <lb/>ving on it ſome ſuch
        impreſſions, as mens Fingers make on <lb/>Wax or Plaiſter. It then weighed 10 Drachms, now
        ſcarce <lb/>an Ounce, it was 5 inches in circumference, and altho it felt <lb/>and otherwiſe
        appeared a Stone, it ſwam on Water, which <lb/>made me ſee the inſide of it by cutting it in
        two with a Knife, <lb/>externally it was black, and ſmooth as if varniſht, and no
        <lb/>thicker, which made me before I had conſidered the whole, <lb/>think it the expanded
        skin of the Plumb indurated; next to <lb/>this thin blackneſs was a cruſt of matter like
        Brick, the thick- <pb n="1281"/>
        <lb/>neſs of an half Crown, within that appeared a ſubſtance <lb/><choice>
          <corr>reſembling</corr>
          <sic>reſembliug</sic>
        </choice> Paſte-board or chewed Paper, and within that <lb/>lay a Prune or withered Plumb,
        with the Stone and Kernel <lb/>cut aſunder by my Knife. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I have ſent it for the R. Society to examin, who I pre- <lb/>ſume will think that all
        thoſe wonderful accidents, which <lb/>ſo long moleſted this poor Woman, were occaſioned by
        this <lb/>Plumb ſwallowed ſo many years before; but how thoſe <lb/>different accretions were
        made to it in ſuch a place as the In- <lb/>teſtines? how it ceaſed to torment her at ſo many
        and ſuch <lb/>different <unclear>Intervals</unclear>? where it lurked between thoſe Fits,
        and <lb/>how the Pain and Tumour obſerved ſuch exact Periods for <lb/>ſo many years; at
        firſt every three months, and afterward <lb/>every 3 weeks? are queſtions I am not able to
        reſolve. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Many Authors tell us of various Stones ejected by Stool, <lb/>and of late many of them
        have been found to come out of <note place="margin" rend="italic size(0.7)"><lb/>Miſcell.
          Cur. <lb/><hi rend="roman">vol</hi> 2. obſ. 89. <lb/>136. <lb/>Act. Med. <lb/><hi
            rend="roman">Barth</hi>. vol. 5. <lb/>ob. 65. </note>
        <lb/>the Gall Bladder through the Cholerick Channels of Jaun- <lb/>diced People. I have ſeen
        two ſuch bigger than any I have <lb/>read of, one ſo big as a Pullets Egg, which came from a
        <lb/>Lady in the operation of a ſtrong Cholagogue taken for a <lb/>Jaundice that had
        reſiſted many other Remedies, the other <lb/>as big as a large Nutmeg, driven out by the
        ſame means from <lb/>an aged Man languiſhing in the ſame diſtemper, and both <lb/>of them
        for many days after thoſe Stones came off, eva- <lb/>cuated great quantities of Choler by
        Stool, and were freed <lb/>of the Diſeaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That thoſe two Stones were generated in the <hi rend="italic">Folliculus
          <lb/>Fellis</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ductus Choledochus</hi>, no man will doubt who con-
        <lb/>ſiders the conſequence, and knows that in colour, taſte, weight <lb/>and ſhape, they
        reſembled ſuch as are found in thoſe parts <lb/>upon diſſection of Jaundiced Bodies. I once
        ſaw near an <lb/>handful of them taken out of the Gall Bladder of the <hi rend="italic">Por-
          <lb/>tugal</hi> Ambaſſador that dyed in <hi rend="italic">London</hi>, 1679. and we are
        <lb/>lately told by <hi rend="italic">Baglivius</hi>, that the famous <hi rend="italic"
          >Malpighius</hi>'s was <lb/>full of them, they uſually are of ſubcitrin colour, reſemble
        <lb/>bright Myrrh, and ſeem an aggregate of ſmall Stones, which <choice>
          <corr>
            <pb n="1282"/>
          </corr>
          <sic>
            <pb n="1582"/>
          </sic>
        </choice>
        <lb/>perhaps are made ſingly in the <hi rend="italic">veſicula</hi>, and Coaleſce in the
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ductus</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The conſequence of their coming off ſhews, that they <lb/><choice>
          <corr>cauſed</corr>
          <sic>eauſed</sic>
        </choice> the Jaundice in thoſe two perſons I have mentioned, by <lb/>obſtructing the
        Channels thro which the Bile paſſeth from the <lb/>common receptacle into the <hi
          rend="italic">duodenum</hi>. It may perhaps ſeem <lb/>impoſſible to ſome men, that
        ſubſtances of that magnitude <lb/>could paſs thorough a <hi rend="italic">Meatus</hi> ſo
        ſmall as the common <hi rend="italic">Ductus</hi>
        <lb/>is. But it hath been no wonder to me this twenty years, <lb/>ſince I diſſected a
        Phyſician of this place, who dyed of the <lb/>Jaundice, and found the <hi rend="italic"
          >Ductus Communis</hi> large enough to <lb/>admit my greateſt Finger, as 3 Phyſicians and
        one Surgeon <lb/>beſides myſelf, ſaw to our great ſurprize. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thoſe Stones which are generated in the <choice>
          <corr>Guts</corr>
          <sic>Gutts</sic>
        </choice> are of <lb/>another ſort, and eaſily diſtinguiſhable from thoſe I am <lb/>Writing
        of. <hi rend="italic">Beckers</hi> ſpeaking of ſome Stones voided by <lb/>Stool, ſaid <q
          rend="italic">— Calculos illos in Inteſtinis genitos eſſe, quia <lb/>Colore, pondere &amp;
          figura a choledohis lapillis diſtincti Arbi- <lb/>tratus ſum </q>. Thoſe generated in the
        Gall cauſe the Jaundice, <lb/>thoſe in the Guts, beget Cholical, Splanchnical, Hypocondria-
        <lb/>cal Pains, and ſometimes Nephritical, all which vaniſh <lb/>when they are ejected. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <note place="margin" rend="italic size(0.7)"><lb/>Vol. 3. obſ. <lb/>110. </note>I have ſeen
        Lumps of Stones in a Herſe as big as a Tennis <lb/>Ball taken out of a Bullocks Guts. The
        Authors of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">German</hi> Miſcellany write of one very much bigger.
          <hi rend="italic"><unclear>L.</unclear> Ri- <lb/>verius</hi> of a man that continually
        with all his Stools voided <lb/>
        <note place="margin" rend="italic size(0.7)"><lb/>Ad. Med. vol. <lb/>1. obſ. 100. <lb/>vol.
          5. ob. 65. </note>Stones like thoſe generated in the Kidneys. <hi rend="italic">T.
          Bartholine</hi>
        <lb/>mentions ſeveral, one particularly notable, being ſo big as <lb/>a Pidgeons Egg, which
        was purged off from a Woman by a <lb/>gentle Pill. <q rend="italic">—in exteriore ſuperficie
          ſubcinereum, &amp; dum a <lb/>me clavo ferreo in duas aquales partes diffringitur interius
          inſtar <lb/>cryſtalli albicantem &amp; Rutilantem, ita <gap reason="illegible"/>ut qui
          olim ex <hi rend="roman">Enni</hi>
          <lb/>ſtarcore aurum, hic colligere potuiſſet gemmas. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There are many ſuch in the <hi rend="italic">Miſcell. Cur.</hi> and which re- <lb/>
        <note place="margin" rend="italic size(0.7)"><lb/><gap reason="illegible"/><lb/><unclear
            reason="illegible">19. </unclear></note>ſembles mine, vol. 7. obſ. 90. but there is one
        much <pb n="1283"/>
        <lb/>more ſo in <hi rend="italic">Ambr. Pary, lib. 25. cap. 19.</hi> but neither of them
        <lb/>ſo ſtrange in cauſe or effects as mine. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It's not for want of old Authorities that I have here <lb/>quoted few but Moderns; I
        know <hi rend="italic">Galen</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Crato</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Sennertus</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">M. Donatus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Z.
          Luſitanus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Fernelius</hi>, <hi rend="italic">G. Horſtius</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">Schenckius</hi>, <lb/>and many more before this Age, who have told the world
        <lb/>of Stones generated in, and ejected from the Inteſtines of <lb/>diſeaſed people, but
        none that I know with ſuch ſurprizing <lb/>circumſtances as this ſent you by </p>
      <salute rend="italic indent">
        <lb/>SIR, </salute>
      <signed rend="italic align-right">Your moſt humble Servant, <lb/><hi rend="roman">James Yonge.
        </hi>
      </signed>
      <figure>
        <p rend="indent italic">
          <lb/>The Ball intire is figured No 3, and its inſide and Plumb- <lb/>ſtone by it. </p>
        <figDesc>Illustrations of the ball from the outside, of the plum stone, and of the ball cut
          open, on a separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
