<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Vaughan: Part of Two Letters from Mr Henry Vaughan to the Publisher,
          Containing Some Uncommon Observations</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Henry Vaughan</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Part of Two Letters from Mr Henry Vaughan to the Publisher, Containing Some
              Uncommon Observations Made upon the Dissection of Some Morbid Bodies</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for S. Smith and B. Walford, Printers to the Royal
                  Society, at the Prince's Arms in St Paul's Church-yard. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1702-1703</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">23</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">1244-1246</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110919082</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi:10.1098/rstl.1702.0029</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT23_1244">
    <body>
      <pb n="1244"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">V.</hi> Part of two Letters from Mr <hi rend="roman">Henry
          Vaughan</hi> to <lb/>the Publiſher, containing ſome uncommon Obſervati- <lb/>ons made upon
        the Diſſection of ſome Morbid Bo- <lb/>dies. </head>
      <div>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Gentleman about a month before <hi rend="italic"
            >Chriſtmas</hi> eat <lb/>ſome common Prunes, about two pound, or more, <lb/>and about a
          month or five weeks ago, he eat about a pound <lb/>more: About a fortnight before he dyed
          I found, <lb/>according to his complaint, that he had ſome ſymptoms <lb/>of the Stone. He
          had a violent pain in the neck of his <lb/><hi rend="italic">Veſica</hi>, and about the
            <hi rend="italic">Urethra</hi>, with obſtructions in his <lb/>Urine, <hi rend="italic"
            >&amp;c.</hi> I ordered him a Terebinthinate Clyſter, which <lb/>gave him eaſe; but
          ſeeing his pains increaſed, I adviſed him <lb/>to a Phyſician: He made uſe of one of his
          acquaintance, <lb/>he likewiſe preſcribed Clyſters, with Diureticks and Narco- <lb/>ticks,
          to no purpoſe. Upon his death, I obtained leave of his <lb/>Relations to Diſſect him;
          accordingly I did with the help <lb/>of a Surgeon, Dr <hi rend="italic">Weſt</hi> being
          preſent, with ſeveral others of <lb/>the deceas'd Patient's friends. I found upon the
          Diſſection <lb/>the Prune-ſtones paſſed into the <hi rend="italic">Inteſtinum rectum</hi>,
          and had <lb/>there made a perforation, or rupture into the <hi rend="italic">Pelvis</hi>.
          We <lb/>tyed one part of the Gut, and cut out apiece, and emptied <lb/>it: There was taken
          out 128 Prune-ſtones in number, be- <lb/>ſides what we left behind <hi rend="italic"
            >inſtercore</hi>, in the other part of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Inteſtinum
          Rectum</hi>. There was likewiſe a large <hi rend="italic">Polypus</hi>
          <lb/>taken out of the Left Ventricle of the Heart, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="1245"/>
      <div>
        <dateline rend="space align-right">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">London</hi>, <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 11. 1702. </dateline>
        <salute rend="italic indent">
          <lb/>SIR, </salute>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">Y</hi>Our kind reception of the laſt, encourageth me to <lb/>give
          you a further account of a Youth in your <lb/>Neighbourhood, who I attended about 30
          hours; his Caſe <lb/>was the <hi rend="italic">Iliaca paſſio</hi>, very terrible for the
          time; he was aged <lb/>about 14 years, of a Sanguine Conſtitution. About 3 or 4 hours
          <lb/>before he dyed I adminiſtred a <sic>Terebinthinat</sic> Clyſter, which <lb/>gave,
          during its ſtay, immediate eaſe; he ſo continued about <lb/>an hour, then his Diſeaſe
          returned again as ſevere <lb/>as ever: He ſoon after dyed: but before, ſome time <lb/>he
          voided ſome of his Clyſter by Vomit. The Caſe be- <lb/>ing not very uſual, I applyed my
          ſelf to his Friends, in <lb/>order to Diſſect him; which accordingly I did the next
          <lb/>day. Finding the Liver only ſomething larger than ordi- <lb/>nary, I immediately made
          ſearch from the <hi rend="italic">Ventriculus</hi> quite <lb/>to the lower end of the <hi
            rend="italic">Inteſtinum rectum</hi>: The <hi rend="italic">Ventricle</hi>
          <lb/>was conſiderably extended, a little ſpace from the Gut <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Ileon</hi>, in the <hi rend="italic">Jejunum</hi>, I found the excrements had made a
          <lb/>breach, and ſome quantity was evacuated. I then proceeded <lb/>to the Gut <hi
            rend="italic">Ileum</hi>, I found a conſiderable part of it very li- <lb/>vid, not in
          the leaſt extended; the Colon was much like a <lb/>Contuſed Wound about 3 or 4 days old. I
          inſpected into <lb/>the center of it, where I found it ſomething freſher, not <lb/>ſo
          livid as the outſide. About the beginning of the <hi rend="italic">Inteſti- <lb/>num
            rectum</hi> I found another large ruption, where there was <lb/>more excrements voided.
          There was ſome other ſmall matters <lb/>to be ſeen, not worth while for me to mention to
          you. How- <lb/>ever, Sir, this being matter of fact, as a great many of his Re-
          <lb/>lations can teſtifie, they being preſent, I thought fit to acquaint <lb/>you with it.
          About 18 months ago I diſſected a poor <pb n="1246"/>
          <lb/>Emaciated Creature, that dyed of a <hi rend="italic">Hydrops</hi>, out <lb/>of whom I
          took about 10 Gallons of Liquor meaſured: <lb/>and about a month ago a Child which had an
          Involution <lb/>of the Inteſtines; which, I believe, the Vulgar means, and <lb/>calls the
          Twiſting of the Guts. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
