<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Greenhill: An Account of a Person Deceased of a Scirrhous Tumor in His
          Breast</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Tho. Greenhill</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of a Person Deceased of a Scirrhous Tumor in His Breast. By Mr Tho.
              Greenhill, Surgeon</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for S. Smith and B. Walford, Printers to the Royal
                  Society, at the Prince's Arms in St Paul's Church-yard. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1704-1705</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">24</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">2009-2011</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110463782</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1704.0081</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT24_2009">
    <body>
      <pb n="2009"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">III.</hi> An Account of a Perſon deceaſed of a Scirrhous <lb/>Tumor in
        his Breaſt. By Mr <hi rend="roman">Tho. Greenhill</hi>, <lb/>Surgeon. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>R <hi rend="italic">J. D.</hi> departed this Life the firſt of
        this in- <lb/>ſtant, and was ſuppoſed to dye of a Conſumpti- <lb/>on; foraſmuch as 14 months
        before he had been violently <lb/>ſeized with an Inflamation of his Lungs, accompanied with
        <lb/>a ſharp Feaver, Difficulty of Breathing, Cough, acute <lb/>Stiches, and Pleuritick
        Pains, with a ſpitting Blood, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He was bled largely in the beginning; and often re- <lb/>peated it during his Sickneſs:
        continually taking ſuch pro- <lb/>per Remedies, as were preſcribed him. But notwithſtand-
        <lb/>ing about <hi rend="italic">Eaſter</hi>, there appeared a Tumour on the Breaſt
        <lb/>Bone, Pap, and Pectoral Muſcle, of the Left Side, with a <lb/>fulneſs under the <hi
          rend="italic">Axilla</hi>: From whence there was con- <lb/>jectured to be a collection of
        Purulent Matter in the Cavity <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi>, and that the <hi
          rend="italic">Sternon</hi> was foul. The firſt <lb/>from the aforeſaid Tumors, and his
        ſpitting a bloody and <lb/>purulent Matter, and the latter from the riſing and inequality
        <lb/>of that Part. But opening him the third of this month, I <lb/>found his Caſe very
        different and ſurprizing, which ſeveral <lb/>judicious perſons that attended him in his
        ſickneſs, and were <lb/>preſent when he was opened, can teſtifie. For ſo ſoon as I <lb/>had
        divided and removed the common teguments of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi>, I found,
        inſtead of a riſing of the Bone with Ca- <lb/>rioſity, only an oblong tumor, about four
        fingers in length, <lb/>and two in breadth, and a proportionate thickneſs, weigh- <lb/>ing
        about 3 ounces, it extended itſelf perpendicularly, on <lb/>the ſuperficies of that part of
        the <hi rend="italic">Sternon</hi>, which joyns with <pb n="2010"/>
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Cartilago Enſiformis</hi>. I ſeparated it with my Knife,
        <lb/>eaſily, from the Breaſt bone, and found it to be of that <lb/>ſort of Wens or enciſted
        Tumors called <hi rend="italic">Atheroma</hi>, contain- <lb/>ing a pappy ſubſtance like
        ſodden Barley. Next appeared <lb/>a very large tumor on the Left ſide of the <hi
          rend="italic">Thorax</hi>, cover- <lb/>ing the whole Pap and Pectoral Muſcles forwards,
        with a <lb/>fulneſs under the <hi rend="italic">Axilla</hi> of the ſame Arm. Then opening
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi>, I found the ſame Tumor comprehending the
        <lb/>Intercoſtals, <hi rend="italic">Deltoides</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Subclavian</hi>, and
          <hi rend="italic">Subſcapulary</hi> Muſ- <lb/>cles, and the whole Axillary and Mamillary
        Glands, which <lb/>being obſtructed, and its Veſſels replete with a creamy <lb/>pappy
        Matter, more thick and white than the former, <lb/>there was produced ſuch an induration of
        the aforeſaid <lb/>Glands and Muſcles, which compoſe the upper part of the <lb/>Breaſt, that
        it may more properly be eſteemed a Schirrous. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſame tumor on the outſide of the Breaſt was ſome- <lb/>what bigger than ones Hand,
        extending it ſelf from the <lb/>Clavicle to the lower part of the Pap; and laterally from
        <lb/>the Baſis of the Muſcle quite under the Arm-pit. Internal- <lb/>ly it poſſeſſed a third
        part of the Cavity of the Breaſt, <lb/>crouding the Left Lobe of the Lungs to the Right
        Side, <lb/>and in its upper part firmly growing to it; which it like- <lb/>wiſe did every
        way to the Intercoſtal Muſcles. It was <lb/>about the bigneſs of a Penny Loaf; and the whole
        Tu- <lb/>mor being conſidered together, might reaſonably be allow- <lb/>ed to weigh between
        3 and 4 pounds, which being cut <lb/>into, there ouzed out of it, like an expreſſed Sponge,
        a great <lb/>quantity of thick, white and pappy Matter: And what is <lb/>more particularly
        remarkable, there was form'd a large <lb/>Sink or <hi rend="italic">Pelvis</hi>, in the
        middle of the Axillary Gland, which <lb/>contained a thinner and diſcolour'd Matter, and had
        a free <lb/>Communication to the Veſſels of the Lungs in the upper <lb/>part of it, where I
        told you before it was <unclear>unit</unclear>ed; and <lb/>from hence it was that he
        generally found <unclear>eaſe</unclear> when he <lb/>had ſomewhat emptied it by large
        expectorations, and that <lb/>he could ſo exactly perceive, when any <gap reason="illegible"
        /> Rheums or <pb n="2011"/>
        <lb/>Matter flowed to the part: And it was here only that the <lb/>Lungs were black and
        replete with ſtagnated Blood, and <lb/>ſome Globules of the aforeſaid Matter in its <hi
          rend="italic">Veſſiculæ</hi>. The <lb/>reſt of the Lungs were pretty clear from any Ulcers
        or <lb/>Matter, but of a Sublivid Colour, and ſtrictly adhered on <lb/>both ſides to the <hi
          rend="italic">Pleura</hi>, but particularly on the Left ſide, <lb/>all about the Schirrous
        Tumor. The <hi rend="italic">Veſſica Fellis</hi> or Gall <lb/>Bladder was full of Stones, of
        the bigneſs of a Runcival <lb/>Pea, and conſiſted moſt of odd Angles, and were formed
        <lb/>of a thick Viſcous Sediment of Gall (which we found in <lb/>it) from an obſtruction of
        its Veſſels, or Jaundice, which <lb/>he had ſome years before: They were in number 22, ſome
        <lb/>triangular, quadrangular, quincuncial, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There was nothing more remarkable, beſides a <hi rend="italic">Maraſmus</hi>
        <lb/>of the External parts, the waſhing of the <choice>
          <corr>Gall</corr>
          <sic>Call</sic>
        </choice>, and empty- <lb/>neſs of all the <hi rend="italic">Viſcera</hi> and Blood Veſſels
        in general. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
