<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Oliver: A Relation of an Extraordinary Sleepy Person</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>William Oliver</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Relation of an Extraordinary Sleepy Person, at Tinsbury, Near Bath. By Dr
              William Oliver, F. R. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for S. Smith and B. Walford, Printers to the Royal
                  Society, at the Prince's Arms in St Paul's Church-yard. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date/>
              <biblScope unit="vol">24</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">2177-2182</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110463782</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1704.0109</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT24_2177">
    <body>
      <pb n="2177"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">V.</hi> A Relation of an extraordinary ſleepy Perſon, at <lb/><hi
          rend="roman">Tinsbury</hi>, near <hi rend="roman">Bath</hi>. By Dr <hi rend="roman"
          >William Oliver</hi>, <lb/>F. R. S. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="dc(1.5)">M</hi>Ay</hi> the 13th, <hi rend="italic"
          >Anno</hi> 1694, one <hi rend="italic">Samuel Chilton</hi>, of <hi rend="italic">Tins-
          <lb/>bury</hi> near <hi rend="italic">Bath</hi>, a Labourer, about 25 years of age,
        <lb/>of a robuſt habit of Body, not fat, but fleſhy, and a dark <lb/>brown Hair, happen'd,
        without any viſible cauſe, or evi- <lb/>dent ſign, to fall into a very profound Sleep, out
        of <lb/>which no Art uſed by thoſe that were near him, cou'd <lb/>rouze him, till after a
        months time; then roſe of him- <lb/>ſelf, put on his Cloaths, and went about his buſineſs of
        <lb/>Husbandry as uſual; ſlept, cou'd eat and drink as before, <lb/>but ſpake not one word
        till about a month after. All <lb/>the time he ſlept Victuals ſtood by him; his Mother fear-
        <lb/>ing he wou'd be ſtrarv'd, in that ſullen humour, as ſhe <lb/>thought it, put Bread and
        Cheeſe and Small Beer before <lb/>him, which was ſpent every day, and ſuppoſed by him,
        <lb/>tho no one every ſaw him eat or drink all that time. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From this time he remain'd free of any drowſineſs or <lb/>ſleepineſs till about the 9th
        of <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 1696, and then fell <lb/>into his Sleeping fit again juſt as
        he did before. After <lb/>ſome days they were prevail'd with to try what effect
        <lb/>Medicines might have on him, and accordingly one <lb/>Mr <hi rend="italic">Gibs</hi>, a
        very able Apothecary of <hi rend="italic">Bath</hi>, went to him, <lb/>Bled, Bliſter'd,
        Capp'd and Scarrified him, and uſed all <lb/>the external irritating Medicines he could
        think on, but <lb/>all to no purpoſe, nothing of all theſe making any man- <lb/>ner of
        impreſſion on him; and after the firſt fortnight he <lb/>was never obſerv'd to open his
        Eyes. Victuals ſtood by <pb n="2178"/>
        <lb/>him as before, which he eat of now and then, but no <lb/>body ever ſaw him Eat or
        Evacuate, tho he did both <lb/>very regularly, as he had occaſion; and ſometimes they
        <lb/>have found him faſt aſleep with the Pot in his Hand in <lb/>Bed, and ſometimes with his
        Mouth full of Meat. In <lb/>this manner he lay for about ten weeks, and then could <lb/>eat
        nothing at all, for his Jaws ſeem'd to be ſet, and his <lb/>Teeth clincht ſo cloſe, that
        with all the Art they had with <lb/>their Inſtruments they cou'd not open his Mouth, to put
        <lb/>any thing into it to ſupport him. At laſt, obſerving a hole <lb/>made in his Teeth, by
        holding his Pipe in his Mouth, <lb/>as moſt great Smoakers uſually have, they through a
        <lb/>Quill pour'd ſome Tent into his Throat now and then: <lb/>And this was all he took for
        ſix weeks and four days, <lb/>and of that not above three pints or two quarts, ſome of
        <lb/>which was ſpilt too; he had made water but once, and <lb/>never had a ſtool all that
        time. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Auguſt</hi> the 7th, which is ſeventeen weeks from the 9th <lb/>of
          <hi rend="italic">April</hi>, (when he began to ſleep,) he awaked, put on <lb/>his
        Cloaths, and walkt about the Room, not knowing <lb/>he had ſlept above a night, nor cou'd he
        be perſwaded <lb/>he had lain ſo long, till going out into the Fields he <lb/>found every
        body buſy in getting in their Harveſt, and <lb/>he remember'd very well, when he fell aſleep
        they were <lb/>ſowing of Barley and Oats, which he then ſaw ripe and <lb/>fit to be cut
        down. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There was one thing obſervable, That tho his Fleſh <lb/>was ſomewhat waſted with ſo
        long lying in Bed, and <lb/>faſting for above ſix weeks, yet a worthy Gentleman his
        <lb/>Neighbour aſſured me, when he ſaw him, which was <lb/>the firſt day of his coming
        abroad, he lookt brisker than <lb/>ever he ſaw him in his life before; and asking him whe-
        <lb/>ther the Bed had not made him ſore, he aſſured him and <lb/>every body, that he neither
        found that, nor any other in- <lb/>conveniency at all; and that he had not the leaſt remem-
          <pb n="2179"/>
        <lb/>brance of any thing that paſt or was done to him all that <lb/>while. So he fell again
        to his Husbandry as he uſed to <lb/>do, and remain'd well from that time till <hi
          rend="italic">Auguſt</hi> the 17th, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Anno</hi> 1697, when in the
        morning he complain'd of a <lb/>ſhivering and coldneſs in his Back, vomited once or twice,
        <lb/>and that ſame day fell into his Sleeping fit again. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Being then at the <hi rend="italic">Bath</hi>, and hearing of it, I took Horſe <lb/>on
        the 23d, to inform my ſelf of a matter of fact I <lb/>thought ſo ſtrange. When I came to the
        Houſe, I was <lb/>by the Neighbours (for there was no body at home at <lb/>that time beſides
        this ſick man,) brought to his Bed-ſide, <lb/>where I found him aſleep, as I had been told
        before, <lb/>with a Cup of Beer and a piece of Bread and Cheeſe upon <lb/>a Stool by his Bed
        within his reach: I took him by the <lb/>Hand, felt his Pulſe, which was at that time very
        regu- <lb/>lar; I put my Hand on his Breaſt, and found his Heart <lb/>beat very regular too,
        and his breathing was eaſie and <lb/>free; and all the fault I found was, that I thought his
        <lb/>Pulſe beat a little too ſtrong: He was in a breathing Sweat, <lb/>and had an agreeable
        warmth all over his Body. I then put <lb/>my Mouth to his Ear, and as loud as I cou'd called
        him by <lb/>his Name ſeveral times, pull'd him by the Shoulders, pincht <lb/>his Noſe, ſtopt
        his Mouth and Noſe together, as long as <lb/>I durſt, for fear of Choaking him, but all to
        no purpoſe, <lb/>for in all this time he gave me not the leaſt ſignal of his <lb/>being
        ſenſible. I lifted up his Eye-lids, and found his <lb/>Eye-balls drawn up under his
        Eye-brows, and fixt with- <lb/>out any motion at all. Being baffled with all theſe tryals,
        <lb/>I was reſolv'd to ſee what effects <hi rend="italic">Spirit</hi> of <hi rend="italic"
          >Sal Armoniac</hi>
        <lb/>would have, which I had brought with me, to diſcover <lb/>the Cheat, if it had been
        one; ſo I held my Viol under <lb/>one Noſtril a conſiderable time, which being drawn from
        <lb/>Quick-lime, was a very piercing Spirit, and ſo ſtrong I <lb/>could not bear it under my
        own Noſe a moment without <lb/>making my Eyes water; but he felt it not at all. Then I <pb
          n="2180"/>
        <lb/>threw it at ſeveral times up that ſame Noſtril, it made <lb/>his Noſe run and gleet,
        and his Eye-lids ſhiver and trem- <lb/>ble a very little, and this was all the effect I
        found, tho <lb/>I pour'd up into one Noſtril about a half ounce Bottle of <lb/>this fiery
        Spirit, which was as ſtrong almoſt as Fire itſelf. <lb/>Finding no ſucceſs with this
        neither, I cramm'd that <lb/>Noſtril with Powder of <hi rend="italic">White Hellebore</hi>,
        which I had by <lb/>me, in order to make my farther trials, and I can hardly <lb/>think any
        Impoſtor cou'd ever be inſenſible of what I did. <lb/>I tarried ſome time afterwards in the
        Room to ſee what <lb/>effects all together might have upon him; but he never <lb/>gave any
        token that he felt what I had done, nor diſco- <lb/>ver'd any manner of uneaſineſs, by
        moving or ſtirring <lb/>any one part of his Body, that I could obſerve. Having <lb/>made
        theſe my Experiments I left him, being pretty well <lb/>ſatisfied he was really aſleep, and
        no ſullen Counterfeit, as <lb/>ſome people thought him. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon my return to <hi rend="italic">Bath</hi>, and relating what I had ob- <lb/>ſerv'd,
        and what proofs this Fellow had given me of his <lb/>Sleeping, a great many Gentlemen went
        out to ſee him, <lb/>as I had done, to ſatisfie their Curioſity in a Rarity of that
        <lb/>Nature, who found him in the ſame condition I had left <lb/>him in the day before; only
        his Noſe was inflamed and <lb/>ſwelled very much, and his Lips and the inſide of his
        <lb/>Right Noſtril bliſter'd and ſcabby, with my <hi rend="italic">Spirit</hi> and <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Hellebore</hi>, which I had plentifully dos'd him with the day <lb/>before:
        His Mother upon this for ſome time after wou'd <lb/>ſuffer no body to come near him, for
        fear of more Expe- <lb/>riments upon her Son. About ten days after I had been <lb/>with him,
        Mr <hi rend="italic">Woolmer</hi>, and Experienc'd Apothecary at <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Bath</hi>, called at the Houſe, being near <hi rend="italic">Tinsbury</hi>, went up
        <lb/>into the Room, finding his Pulſe pretty high, as I had <lb/>done, takes out his
        Launcet, lets him Blood about four- <lb/>teen ounces in the Arm, tyes his Arm up again, no
        body <lb/>being in the Houſe, and leaves him as he found him; <pb n="2181"/>
        <lb/>and he aſſured me he never made the leaſt motion in the <lb/>world when he prickt him,
        nor all the while his Arm was <lb/>bleeding. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Several other Experiments were made by thoſe that <lb/>went to ſee him every day from
        the <hi rend="italic">Bath</hi>, but all to no <lb/>purpoſe, as they told me on their
        return: I ſaw him <lb/>my ſelf again the latter end of <hi rend="italic">September</hi>, and
        found him <lb/>juſt in the ſame poſture, lying in his Bed, but remov'd <lb/>from the Houſe
        where he was before about a furlong or <lb/>more; and they told me, when they remov'd him,
        by ac- <lb/>cident, carrying him down Stairs which were ſomewhat <lb/>narrow, they ſtruck
        his Head againſt a Stone, and gave <lb/>him a ſevere knock, which broke his Head, but he
        never <lb/>mov'd any more at it than a dead man wou'd. I found now <lb/>his Pulſe was not
        quite ſo ſtrong, nor had he any Sweats, <lb/>as when I ſaw him before. I try'd him again the
        ſecond <lb/>time, by ſtopping his Noſe and Mouth, but to no pur- <lb/>poſe; and a Gentleman
        then with me ran a large Pin in- <lb/>to his Arm to the very Bone, but he gave us no manner
        <lb/>of tokens of his being ſenſible of any thing we did to <lb/>him. In all this time they
        aſſured me no body had ſeen <lb/>him either eat or drink, tho they endeavour'd it all they
        <lb/>could, but it always ſtood by him, and they obſerv'd <lb/>ſometimes once a day,
        ſometimes once in two days all <lb/>was gone. 'Tis farther obſervable, he never foul'd his
        <lb/>Bed, but did his neceſſary occaſions always in the Pot. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In this manner he lay till the 19th of <hi rend="italic">November</hi>, when <lb/>his
        Mother hearing him make a noiſe, ran immediately <lb/>up to him, and found him Eating; ſhe
        askt him how he <lb/>did? He ſaid, Very well, thank God: She askt him <lb/>again, Which he
        lik'd beſt, Bread and Butter, or Bread <lb/>and Cheeſe? He anſwer'd, Bread and Cheeſe: Upon
        this, <lb/>the poor Woman overjoy'd left him to acquaint his Bro- <lb/>ther with it, and
        they came ſtrait up into the Chamber <lb/>to diſcourſe him, but found him as faſt aſleep
        again as <pb n="2182"/>
        <lb/>ever, and all the Art they had cou'd not wake him. From <lb/>this time to the end of
          <hi rend="italic">January</hi> or the beginning of <hi rend="italic">Fe- <lb/>bruary</hi>,
        (for I cou'd not learn from any body the very day) <lb/>he ſlept not ſo profoundly as
        before, for when they call'd <lb/>him by his name he ſeemed to hear them, and be ſome-
        <lb/>what ſenſible, tho he could not make them any anſwer. <lb/>His Eyes were not now ſhut
        ſo cloſe, and he had fre- <lb/>quently great tremblings of his Eyelids, upon which they
        <lb/>expected every day when he would wake, which happen- <lb/>ed not till about the time
        juſt now mention'd, and then <lb/>he wak'd perfectly well, not remembring any thing that
        <lb/>happened all this while. 'Twas obſerv'd he was very <lb/>little altered in his Fleſh,
        only complained the Cold pincht <lb/>him more than uſually, and ſo preſently fell to
        Husbandry <lb/>as at other times. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I have no reaſon to ſuſpect this to be any Cheat, be- <lb/>cauſe I never heard of any
        gain to the Family by it, tho <lb/>ſo near the <hi rend="italic">Bath</hi>, and ſo many
        People went thither out <lb/>of Curioſity to ſee the Sleeper, who when awake was a
        <lb/>ſupport to his old Mother by his Labour, but now a cer- <lb/>tain charge to her.
        Beſides there was ſeldom any body in <lb/>the Houſe to attend any profit might be made by
        it, he <lb/>being left alone in the Houſe, and every body at liberty <lb/>to go up to his
        Bed-ſide. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
