<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Douglas: An Account of a Very Large Tumour in the Fore Part of the
          Neck</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>James Douglas</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of a Very Large Tumour in the Fore Part of the Neck, etc. By Dr James
              Douglas</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed for B. Walford, Printer to the Royal
                  Society, at the Prince's Arms in St Paul's Church-yard. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1706-1707</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">25</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">2214-2219</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110825648</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1706.0005</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT25_2214">
    <body>
      <pb n="2214"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">V.</hi> An account of a very large Tumour in the fore part <lb/>of the
        Neck, <hi rend="roman">&amp;c.</hi> By <hi rend="roman">Dr James Douglas</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> Lately had the opportunity of opening a Woman, <lb/>about 50
        years old, who had a very large Tumour, <lb/>or hard Swelling, in the fore part of her Neck,
        poſſeſſing <lb/>all the ſpace between the whole extent of the lower Jaw <lb/>and the upper
        part of the <hi rend="italic">Sternum</hi>, with a conſiderable <lb/>riſing in its middle;
        laterally its point inclining to the <lb/>Left ſide, tho the biggeſt part of the Tumour was
        on the <lb/>Right. The Skin on the <hi rend="italic">Apex</hi> of this protuberating part
        <lb/>was thin and ſhrivell'd, of a colour different from the <lb/>reſt, and lookt as if the
        Swelling would have broke in <lb/>that place. </p>
      <pb n="2215"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Skin was exceeding thin, having no Fat under it, <lb/>only in a cavity between two
        Lobes, to be afterwards de- <lb/>ſcribed, on its Right ſide, there was a ſmall appearance
        <lb/>of ſome; for the Skin being leſs ſtretcht there, the Cells <lb/>of the <hi
          rend="italic">Membrana adipoſa</hi> were not quite emptyed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The fleſhy Fibres of the <hi rend="italic">Latiſſimus colli</hi> were ſcarce vi-
        <lb/>ſible. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Maſtoidæus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Coraco-hyoidæus</hi> were
        extremely <lb/>thin, and in their aſcent they adhered very firm to the <lb/>ſubjacent
        Tumour. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Sterno-hyoidæus</hi> and the <hi rend="italic"
          >Sterno-thyreoidæus</hi>, that <lb/>run up the fore part of this Swelling, were diſtended
        ſo <lb/>thin, that it was difficult to ſeparate them from it, eſpe- <lb/>cially the laſt
        named. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Right <hi rend="italic">Carotid</hi> Artery, in its aſcent to the Head, <lb/>run
        along its outer edge, which encreaſing, did much <lb/>obſtruct the current of the Blood that
        way. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Internal <hi rend="italic">Jugular</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Par Vagum</hi>, and
        the Inter- <lb/>coſtal Pair went alſo over ſome part of this Swelling in <lb/>their deſcent
        to the <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi>. Two of the Lymphatick <lb/>Glands of the <hi
          rend="italic">Jugular</hi> Vein were ſwelled to the bigneſs <lb/>of little Eggs, being
        placed at ſome diſtance one from <lb/>another, with a hollow between, where ſome Fat was
        <lb/>found; theſe two Lobes made the Tumour very uneven <lb/>alſo on its Right ſide. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe Muſcles, the <hi rend="italic">Jugular</hi> with the two Glands ad- <lb/>hering
        to it, and the reſt of the fore-named Veſſels being <lb/>removed on both ſides, I could
        eaſily obſerve the bigneſs, <lb/>the figure and the circumſcription or limits of this
        preter- <lb/>natural Tumour, with all its adhæſions to the adjacent <lb/>parts. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In Magnitude it ſeemed to exceed that of two Fiſts <lb/>joyned together. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Its figure was almoſt triangular, with a broad Baſis <lb/>under the Chin, ſloping a
        little on each ſide, as it de- <lb/>ſcended to the upper part of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Sternum</hi>, where its point <pb n="2216"/>
        <lb/>was pretty narrow; its ſurface was made uneven, by <lb/>three riſings, of which the
        largeſt was turned to the Left <lb/>ſide; the other two being placed on the Right, as above
        <lb/>remarked. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It adhered by Membranous Filaments to the <hi rend="italic">Max- <lb/>illar</hi>
        Glands, to the <hi rend="italic">Digaſtrick</hi> Muſcle, and to the <hi rend="italic">Stylo-
          <lb/>hyoidæus</hi>; under which, on the Right ſide, a ſmall por- <lb/>tion of it, in the
        form of a Nipple, did intrude itſelf as <lb/>it were under the Tongue; in the upper and
        fore-part it <lb/>alſo adhered to the <hi rend="italic">Os hyoides</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Laterally it was connected to the <hi rend="italic">Levator Scapulæ</hi>, <lb/>and
        lower down to that part of the <hi rend="italic">Cucullaris</hi> that termi- <lb/>nates into
        the <hi rend="italic">Clavicle</hi>, backwards to all the fore-part <lb/>of the <hi
          rend="italic">Aſpera Arteria</hi>, between its third or fourth Cartila- <lb/>ginous Ring
        and the <hi rend="italic">Os pectoris</hi>, as alſo to that Muſcle <lb/>of the Head called
          <hi rend="italic">Rectus Internus major</hi>, and to ſome <lb/>part of the <hi
          rend="italic">Scaleni</hi>; its lower part was engaged under the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Jugulum</hi>, or lunated part of the Breaſt-bone, to which it <lb/>adhered. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It was eaſily freed from its connexions to all theſe <lb/>different parts, but not ſo
        from the <hi rend="italic">Glandulæ Thyreoidææ</hi>, <lb/>to which it adhered after a far
        different manner; for <lb/>where the <hi rend="italic">Thyroidal</hi> Glands are joyned to
        one another, a <lb/>little below the <hi rend="italic">Cartilago Cricoides</hi>, on the
        fore-part of the <lb/>rough Artery, there was no ſeparating of it without cut- <lb/>ting its
        ſubſtance; whence it plainly appears, that the <lb/>Union of theſe Glands was the root or
        beginning of this <lb/>exceſſive Tumour: And yet, which is very remarkable, <lb/>the Glands
        themſelves kept their uſual figure, and were <lb/>no larger than ordinary. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This Tumour was hard and very firm, being exactly of <lb/>the conſiſtence of a Cows
        Udder when boyled, yet in a <lb/>few places it was ſoftiſh, containing a liquid and thick
        <lb/>Juice. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Its Colour was chiefly of a Whitiſh Yellow, only in <lb/>ſome places it was exceeding
        Red, from its having a <pb n="2217"/>
        <lb/>greater ſtore of Blood Veſſels, and in others it was very <lb/>White. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I was not a little ſurprized to hear the edge of my <lb/>Knife grate againſt ſomething
        hard, while I was cutting <lb/>it, which made me proceed with caution, not to ſpoil
        <lb/>whatever it was that made the reſiſtance; I therefore <lb/>pared off all the ſoft part,
        and the hard ſubſtance that <lb/>remained I boyled, and then cleared it very well, hav-
        <lb/>ing left ſticking to it at one corner a ſoft Cartilaginous <lb/>Body, which poſſibly,
        had the Patient lived longer, <lb/>would have acquired the ſame degree of Induration.
        <lb/>It very much reſembles a piece of white unpoliſhed <lb/>Rock Coral; but whether it may
        be reckoned oſſeous, <lb/>or if it be rather the Viſcid Humour of the Glands hard- <lb/>ned
        and concreted into this irregular Chalky or Gra- <lb/>velly Subſtance, or whatever elſe it
        may be, I leave, Sir, <lb/>to your better Judgment to determine. See Fig. 1. </p>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>An illustration of the hard body described, on a separate page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I remember about two years ago I found in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Proſtates</hi> of
        a very old man a great many hard Bodies, <lb/>like White Peas, being of a Subſtance exactly
        like this, <lb/>only ſmoother on the outſide; some of theſe were in the <lb/>Body of theſe
        Glands, others adhered by ſmall Roots <lb/>to the Muſcular Membrane that Inveſts them. Fig.
        2. </p>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>An illustration of five small bodies of different shapes, on a separate page.
        </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The firſt appearance of this large Swelling was about <lb/>twenty years ago, cauſed by
        the breaking of a Vein, as <lb/>the good Woman uſed to expreſs it, in a hard and very
        <lb/>difficult Labour. It increaſed but very ſlowly, not ar- <lb/>riving to any conſiderable
        bulk till a few years before <lb/>ſhe dyed; it was never very painful, being a true
        <lb/>Schirrhus: Many things by ſeveral Perſons had been <lb/>uſed and applyed
        unſucceſsfully. Its bigneſs at length <lb/>became very troubleſome, in impeding her Swallow-
        <lb/>ing and free Breathing, and at laſt it quite choaked <lb/>her by compreſſing the
        Wind-pipe, upon which it <lb/>lay. </p>
      <pb n="2218"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But beſides this, I obſerved another remarkable ac- <lb/>cident, which did much haſten
        her end, being very <lb/>painful and troubleſome for a year or two before ſhe <lb/>dyed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Uterus</hi> was entirely <choice>
          <corr>Schirrhous</corr>
          <sic>Shirrhous</sic>
        </choice>, and diſtended to <lb/>that degree, that it filled up the whole Capacity of the
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pelvis</hi>. Part of the <hi rend="italic">Colon</hi> and <hi
          rend="italic">Ileon</hi> adhered ſo firmly <lb/>to it, that there could be no Separation
        without tear- <lb/>ing: Both the <hi rend="italic">Ovaria</hi> and the <hi rend="italic"
          >Tubæ</hi> grew cloſe to it; <lb/>and indeed the Confuſion and the Mixture of all theſe
        parts <lb/>was ſo great, that if the <hi rend="italic">Ovaries</hi> had not been ſwelled
        <lb/>here and there with Hydatidal Tumours, I could not <lb/>have diſtinguiſhed them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Neck of the Womb was preſſed down ſo low, <lb/>that upon a very gentle dilatation
        of the <hi rend="italic">Labia</hi> it offer'd <lb/>itſelf to view, being extreamly hard,
        but yet ſmooth <lb/>and even, and ſo cloſely ſhut, that I could paſs nothing <lb/>without
        cutting. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It had ſqueezed the <hi rend="italic">Veſica Urinaria</hi> ſo cloſe againſt <lb/>the
          <hi rend="italic">Os Pubis</hi>, that it could contain but little or no <lb/>Urine, which
        obliged her to make it often, and with <lb/>pain. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The preſſure of this part backwards was ſo great <lb/>upon the <hi rend="italic"
          >Inteſtinum Rectum</hi>, that the evacuation of <hi rend="italic">Fæces</hi>
        <lb/>had been obſtructed for the ſpace of five weeks before <lb/>ſhe dyed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Indeed there was obſerved to come away <hi rend="italic">per Anum</hi>
        <lb/>for ſome conſiderable time a great deal of <hi rend="italic">Pus</hi> and <lb/>Slimy
        Matter, but that proceeded from the <hi rend="italic">Uterus</hi>; <lb/>for the Acrimonious
        Humour, which was wont to be <lb/>diſcharged <hi rend="italic">per Vaginam</hi>, having been
        pent up within its <lb/>Cavity, by the cloſe Conſtriction of the <hi rend="italic">Collum
          Uteri</hi>, <lb/>had corroded, and eat its way through the ſubſtance of <lb/>the Womb into
        the <hi rend="italic">Rectum</hi>, by which it had its vent: <lb/>Which deplorable caſe I
        have more than once obſerved <lb/>in Diſſection. </p>
      <pb n="2219"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The thickneſs of the Womb was near two inches, <lb/>and in its bottom there was a great
        deal of this <unclear>Humour</unclear>, <lb/>White and thick, which upon touching made the
        ends <lb/>of my Fingers white and rough, by ſhrivelling the <hi rend="italic">Cu-
          <lb/>ticula</hi>, as if I had waſhed them with a ſtrong <unclear>Solucion</unclear>
        <lb/>of ſome Acrid Lixivial Salt. Thus the Cauſtick Salt <lb/>lodged in Soap affects the
        Hands of thoſe Women that <lb/>waſh Linnen. It was very hard to take the <hi rend="italic"
          >Uterus</hi> out <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Pelvis</hi>, by reaſon of its ſo cloſe
        adheſion to the <lb/>neighbouring parts. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>I had forgot to take notice, that the <hi rend="italic">Fæces Alvinæ</hi>,
        <lb/>contained in the Guts, were but few, by reaſon ſhe <lb/>could not ſwallow any thing
        ſolid for a long time, but <lb/>very hard, and in ſeveral diſtinct Clots. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
