<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Douglas: An Account of a Hydrops Ovarii</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Dr Douglas</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of a Hydrops Ovarii, with a New and Exact Figure of the Glandulae
              Renales, and of the Uterus in a Puerpera. Communicated by Dr Douglas, F. R. S.
            </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed for B. Walford, Printer to the Royal
                  Society, at the Prince's Arms in St Paul's Church-yard. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1706-1707</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">25</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">2317-2327</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110825648</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1706.0027</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT25_2317">
    <body>
      <pb n="2317"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">II.</hi> An Account of a <hi rend="roman">Hydrops Ovarii</hi>, with a
        new <lb/>and exact Figure of the <hi rend="roman">Glandulæ renales</hi>, and of <lb/>the <hi
          rend="roman">Uterus</hi> in a <hi rend="roman">Puerpera</hi>. Communicated by <lb/>Dr <hi
          rend="roman">Douglas</hi>, F. R. S. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> Lately opened the Body of a Woman, aged 27, who <lb/>dyed the
        third day after Delivery, on which I made <lb/>the following remarks. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>1. She meaſured round the Waſte a yard and three <lb/>quarters, and from the <hi
          rend="italic">Scrobiculus Cordis</hi> to the <hi rend="italic">Os Pubis</hi> a <lb/>yard
        and a quarter. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2. All the cutaneous Veins of the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi> were of a <lb/>very
        unuſual and extraordinary bigneſs, and very much <lb/>diſtended with Blood. From the largeſt
        of them, being <lb/>opened, I extracted ſeveral polypous concretions. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>3. The <hi rend="italic">Cuticula</hi>, from the <hi rend="italic">Umbilicus</hi>
        downwards, was <lb/>rough and ſcaly to the naked Eye. In ſeveral parts it <lb/>appeared
        gangreened, occaſioned probably by the ſharp- <lb/>neſs of the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>
        that always ouzed out of it, when ſhe <lb/>ſcratched the little Pimples or Wheals that aroſe
        on its <lb/>ſurface; theſe for ſome time uſed to go off without <lb/>any Scar, but as her
        ſtrength decayed they became mor- <lb/>tified. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>4. Upon all the <hi rend="italic">Regio Epigaſtrica</hi> the outward Integu- <lb/>ments
        were very thin, little or no fat being viſible: But <lb/>from the upper part of the <hi
          rend="italic">Regio Umbilicalis</hi>, down to <pb n="2318"/>
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Os Pubis</hi>, the Skin was almoſt half an inch thick, of <lb/>a
        whitiſh colour and hard, ſome of it appearing as if it <lb/>were granulated, cauſed by ſome
        obſtructions in the Mil- <lb/>liary cutaneous Glands. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>5. The Fat under this part of the Skin did exceed the <lb/>thickneſs of an inch, being
        diſtinguiſhed into ſeveral Lo- <lb/>bules of an irregular figure, and lodged in ſo many
        Cells <lb/>adhering to the <hi rend="italic">Membrana adipoſa</hi>, which here alſo was
        <lb/>much thicker than it uſually is in a natural ſtate. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>6. Her Thighs, Legs and Feet were all <hi rend="italic">Anaſarcous</hi>, be- <lb/>ing
        extreamly big and ſwelled, eaſily retaining any Im- <lb/>preſſion made by the Fingers: And
        her Nurſe told me, <lb/>that ſhe uſed to wet a great deal of Linnen in drying up <lb/>the
        Water, that would always iſſue out from theſe parts <lb/>on the leaſt rubbing, yet all her
        ſuperiour parts were ex- <lb/>treamly lean and emaciated. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>7. The fleſhy part of the <hi rend="italic">Abdominal</hi> Muſcles was much
        <lb/>extenuated by the great diſtenſion, yet their Tendons <lb/>were as thick as uſual; and
        being very eaſily ſeparable <lb/>one from another, I could plainly obſerve that the Ten-
        <lb/>don of the <hi rend="italic">Obliquus Internus</hi> adhered firmly to that of the
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tranſverſalis</hi>, along the edge of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Muſculus rectus</hi>, and <lb/>was not double, as <hi rend="italic">Realdus
        Columbus</hi>, and all Anato- <lb/>miſts after him, down to <hi rend="italic"
            ><unclear>Diemerbroek</unclear></hi>, who was firſt a- <lb/>ware of this miſtake, have
        maintained: However, this <lb/>ſtreight Muſcle derives the ſame benefit from this ſitua-
        <lb/>tion, being as it were hemm'd in on one ſide by this firm <lb/>adhæſion, and on the
        other by what they call the <hi rend="italic">Linea <lb/>alba</hi>, as if it had indeed been
        Incloſed between the two <lb/>ſuppoſed Tendons of the <hi rend="italic">Obliquus
          aſcendens</hi>; that is, 'tis <lb/>much ſtrengthned thereby in time of acting. I obſerved
        <lb/>alſo, that the Tendons of the two oblique Muſcles, and <lb/>the fleſhy part of the <hi
          rend="italic">Tranſverſalis</hi>, between the Anteri- <lb/>our Spine of the <hi
          rend="italic">Os Ilium</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Pubis</hi>, near its com-
        <lb/>miſſure, did inſeparably join and unite with one another, <lb/>forming as it were a
        thick and hard border, from the <pb n="2319"/>
        <lb/>outſide of which there was continued over the Blood <lb/>Veſſels, Nerves and Muſcles,
        on the fore-part of the <lb/>Thigh, a large <hi rend="italic">Aponeuroſis</hi>, which braced
        them down: <lb/>The two <hi rend="italic">Laminæ</hi> of the Membrane of the <hi
          rend="italic">Abdomen</hi> being <lb/>expanded on its inſide. Now this border is what
        Authors <lb/>call the <hi rend="italic">Ligamentum Pubis</hi>, and what I have in another
        <lb/>place ſuppoſed to be the firm union of the Tendons of <note place="margin"
          rend="italic size(0.7)"><lb/>Vid. Myograph. <lb/>comparat. Spe-<lb/>cim. pag. 5. </note>
        <lb/>theſe three <hi rend="italic">Abdominal</hi> Muſcles with the <hi rend="italic"
          >Peritonæum</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>8. Having perforated the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi> in the moſt conve- <lb/>nient
        depending part, for it would have been endleſs la- <lb/>bour, conſidering the great bulk of
        the Tumour, to have <lb/>laid it bare, by freeing it carefully from the Muſcles and <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Peritonæum</hi>, there iſſued out with great Impetuoſity in a <lb/>riſing
        ſtream a vaſt quantity of ſlimy Viſcid Water, in co- <lb/>lour and conſiſtence very much
        reſembling a brown, thick <lb/>and ropy Syrup. This Water meaſured between 16 and 17
        <lb/>Gallons, beſides what was loſt on the floor, and imbibed <lb/>in Sponges and Linnen
        made uſe of in drying it up. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>9. When the Water was quite emptyed, I fancyed it <lb/>had been all contained in a
        duplicature of the <hi rend="italic">Peritonæ- <lb/>um</hi>, and had made a Dropſy in that
        Membrane, becauſe <lb/>none of the <hi rend="italic">Viſcera</hi> appeared; for in ſuch a
        caſe I have <lb/>more than once obſerved, that the inner <hi rend="italic">Lamella</hi> of
        that <lb/>Membrane of the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi> being ſeparated from the
        <lb/>outer, is forced inward by the weight of the Water upon <lb/>the Bowels, to which it
        cloſely adheres, conſtracting the <lb/>Guts and Meſentery into a very ſmall volume. But upon
        <lb/>a narrower view I perceived that the thick Membrane, <lb/>including the Water, could be
        eaſily ſeparated from the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Viſcera</hi>, having freed it from its
        adheſions by membra- <lb/>nous filaments to the <hi rend="italic">Peritonæum</hi>, and by
        Blood Veſſels to <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi>. Now this Bag reach'd from the <hi
          rend="italic">Pubis</hi> to <lb/>the Midriff, and from the Left Region of the Loins to
        <lb/>the Right; in a word, it filled up the whole cavity of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >Abdomen</hi>, diſtending her Belly ſo far, that a Plate <lb/>could eaſily lye upon it,
        when alive. Having gradually <pb n="2320"/>
        <lb/>freed it from all the neighbouring parts, and rolled it up, <lb/>I found it adher'd
        inſeparably to the Left <hi rend="italic">Tuba fallopiana</hi>, <lb/>the Spermatick Veſſels
        being ramified upon it; and ob- <lb/>ſerving no <hi rend="italic">Ovarium</hi>, which in the
        other ſide was natu- <lb/>rally diſpoſed, I concluded that the Bag was nothing but <lb/>the
        Membrane of the <hi rend="italic">Ovarium</hi> covering the <hi rend="italic">Ova</hi>
        preter- <lb/>naturally thickned and diſtended by the collection of the <lb/>above mentioned
        humour, and that the Diſtemper was a <lb/>true <hi rend="italic">Hydrops ovarii</hi>,
        inaſmuch as all this vaſt quantity of <lb/>Water was included in one Bag, being all of the
        ſame <lb/>colour and conſiſtence. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>10. All the other <hi rend="italic">Viſcera</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>
        were found, <lb/>and in their natural ſtate. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>11. In both Cavities of the Breaſt there was contain'd <lb/>a great quantity of reddiſh
        Water. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>12. The Liquor in the <hi rend="italic">Pericardium</hi> was very abundant, <lb/>and of
        a greeniſh hue. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>13. The Right Lobe of the Lungs was tyed to the <lb/>Membrane of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Thorax</hi>, covering the upper part of <lb/>that cavity, but the Left was free from any
        adheſion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>14. In the Left Ventricle I found a large Polypous or <lb/>Serous Concretion, of a
        round figure, a white colour, <lb/>and of a pretty hard conſiſtence, with ſeveral long Roots
        <lb/>of a Red colour, which extended thro the Auricle and <lb/>Bulb of the Pulmonary Vein
        into its neareſt divarications <lb/>in the Lungs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having carried home this large Bag, with the <hi rend="italic">Uterus</hi>
        <lb/>appendant, cut off below the Orifice of the <hi rend="italic">Meatus Uri-
          <lb/>narius</hi>, and viewed it at leiſure, I obſerved, </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>1. That the Right <hi rend="italic">Spermatick</hi> Vein, which opens into <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">Cava</hi> a little below the <hi rend="italic">Emulgent</hi>, was three
        times <lb/>larger than the Left; and from a little above the <hi rend="italic">Ova-
          <lb/>rium</hi> it was continued, without any diviſion to its termi- <lb/>nation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2. The Right <hi rend="italic">Ovarium</hi> was in a very natural ſtate. <lb/>The <hi
          rend="italic">Cicatrix</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Caruncula</hi>, whence the fæcundated <hi
          rend="italic">Ovu-</hi>
        <pb n="2321"/>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">um</hi> had dropt, was yet remaining, and the Blood Veſſels <lb/>were
        ramified upon this <hi rend="italic">Teſtis</hi>, in a very pleaſant and <lb/>beautiful
        manner. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>3. The <hi rend="italic">Tuba Fallopiana</hi>, with its <hi rend="italic">Fimbria</hi>,
        were all well <lb/>diſpoſed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>4. The Diameter of the Left <hi rend="italic">Spermatick</hi> Vein, which <lb/>opens
        into the <hi rend="italic">Emulgent</hi> of that ſide, was much leſs than <lb/>ordinary. And
        from the extraordinary narrowneſs of the <lb/>bore of this Veſſel we may draw a not very
        improbable <lb/>Reaſon of ſome Cauſe of this Watery Swelling; for the <lb/>Blood being
        hereby hindred in its Reflux to the Heart, <lb/>a great deal of <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>
        or <hi rend="italic">Lympha</hi>, thro its ſlow return, muſt <lb/>needs be thrown off upon
        the <hi rend="italic">Ovarium</hi>, already indiſpoſed, <lb/>whence the gradual Increaſe of
        the Tumor did pro- <lb/>ceed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>5. The two <hi rend="italic">Spermatick</hi> Arteries were contorted, and <lb/>full of
        turnings and windings, from their meeting with <lb/>the Veins to the <hi rend="italic"
          >Ovaria</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tubæ</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>6. A little below the Kidneys each Artery ſent out a <lb/>Branch, which was loſt on the
          <hi rend="italic">Peritonæum</hi>, and fatty <lb/>Membrane of the Kidney: And from the
        ſame places the <lb/>Veins received two conſiderable Branches. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>7. One of the Arteries went off by a narrow Orifice <lb/>from the ſide of the <hi
          rend="italic">Aorta</hi>, the other roſe up from its <lb/>middle, a little below the
        firſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>8. Between the Bag and the <hi rend="italic">Uterus</hi> all theſe Veſſels <lb/>were
        much dilated, making ſeveral Turnings and Cir- <lb/>cumvolutions upon the <hi rend="italic"
          >Peritonæum</hi>, called in this place <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Ligamentum Uteri
          latum</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>9. The Left <hi rend="italic">Tuba Fallopiana</hi> was only remarkable in its
        <lb/>being much longer and larger than uſual. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>10. In the Bag, which was nothing but the Membrane <lb/>called <hi rend="italic"
          >Dartos</hi>, which covers all the <hi rend="italic">Veſſicular</hi> Glands of <lb/>which
        the <hi rend="italic">Ovarium</hi> is compos'd, I obſerv'd ſeveral little <lb/>Bladders of
        different ſizes, diſtinct from one another, <lb/>which contain'd a limpid or clear ſlimy <hi
          rend="italic">Serum</hi>, in Colour <pb n="2322"/>
        <lb/>and Conſiſtence like a Mucilage of the <hi rend="italic">Semen Cydoniorum</hi>,
        <lb/>theſe were either <hi rend="italic">Hydatidal</hi> Tumors only, or the Eggs
        <lb/>themſelves diſtended. This Liquor hardned by a ſlow <lb/>heat into the Conſiſtence and
        Colour of the White of an <lb/>Egg. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>11. All the <hi rend="italic">Fundus Uteri</hi> was about an inch and a <lb/>half
        thick, but near the <hi rend="italic">Collum minus</hi> it grew ſomething <lb/>thinner,
        which did proceed from the diſtention of its <lb/>Spongy and <hi rend="italic"
          >Veſicular</hi> Subſtance, by the Blood in the <lb/>Veſſels running thro it in variety of
        turnings and wind- <lb/>ings; ſo that when it was cut, it very much reſembled <lb/>the
        ſubſtance of the Lungs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>12. Upon the inner Membrane of the <hi rend="italic">Uterus</hi> I ob- <lb/>ſerved,
        upon wiping it with a Sponge, ſeveral little emi- <lb/>nencies, which I took to be the
        Glands mentioned by <lb/><hi rend="italic">Malpighius</hi>, which ſeparate a Humour, to
        Lubricate and <lb/>Moiſten its cavity. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>13. On the upper part of the <hi rend="italic">Fundus Uteri</hi> I took no- <lb/>tice
        of a great number of ſmall Veſſels, like ſlender Fila- <lb/>ments or Threads, running off
        from its Membrane, and <lb/>terminating into a reddiſh and ſoft ſpongy ſort of ſub-
        <lb/>ſtance, not unlike the <hi rend="italic">Uvula</hi>, bating its colour, which <lb/>hung
        down from that ſide of the Womb in form of a <lb/>Nipple. Theſe perhaps are the Veſſels,
        which, in the <lb/>opinion of ſome, do ſeparate and excern the Matter of <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">Lochia</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Menſes</hi>, they being only viſible
        at <lb/>thoſe times. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>14. Near the beginning of the <hi rend="italic">Tubes</hi>, I perceived two <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Tubercles</hi>, or little Bunchings, about the bigneſs of a <lb/>Nut, to
        which perhaps the <hi rend="italic">Placenta</hi> was faſtned, and to <lb/>theſe adhered
        ſeveral Glandules of a Blackiſh colour, of <lb/>different ſizes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>15. The <hi rend="italic">Collum minus</hi> was compoſed, as it were, of <lb/>two <hi
          rend="italic">Labia</hi>, the uppermoſt was moſt protuberating, and up- <lb/>on it I
        obſerved ſeveral ſmall Glands, out of which, up- <lb/>on compreſſion, iſſued a viſcid clear
        Liquor, which is <pb n="2323"/>
        <lb/>ſaid to ſeal and cloſe up this part, in time of Pregnancy. <lb/>The lower <hi
          rend="italic">Labium</hi> was longer and thinner, its Edges be- <lb/>ing cut or indented
        in ſeveral places. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>16. The <hi rend="italic">Rugæ</hi> in the lower part of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Vagina</hi> run as <lb/>they are repreſented in Books, but thoſe in the upper <lb/>part
        had a quite different courſe, as they are exactly deli- <lb/>neated in the annext figure. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>17. Near the Orifice of the <hi rend="italic">Meatus Urinarius</hi> there <lb/>were
        obſervable two very large Caruncles, in ſhape like <lb/>a Mulberry. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This is what I obſerved in the opening of this Wo- <lb/>man. I come in the next place
        to relate, as far as I was <lb/>informed, the Symptoms that accompanyed her big Belly,
        <lb/>and the Method made uſe of for her Recovery. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About three years ago, not long after ſhe had lain in <lb/>of her firſt Child, ſhe had
        a violent blow upon the Left <lb/>ſide of her Belly, very painful for the preſent, but in
        <lb/>two or three days, upon keeping herſelf quiet in Bed, the <lb/>pain and anguiſh went
        off. About two months after <lb/>this, ſhe began to feel ſome ſmall pains in the Left <hi
          rend="italic">Hy- <lb/>pogaſtrick</hi> Region, where ſhe had lately received the
        <lb/>Blow; and ſhe obſerved that ſide of her Belly to <lb/>grow abundantly bigger than the
        other: Theſe pains <lb/>increaſed more and more, till they grew very violent, <lb/>but upon
        Conception, which was three months after ſhe <lb/>was firſt afflicted with them, they went
        off, and her <lb/>Belly ſwelled gradually, as is uſual in Pregnancy, hav- <lb/>ing no other
        Symptoms but what is incident to that ſtate, <lb/>only ſhe was much bigger than ordinary;
        and on that <lb/>account ſhe forbore the uſe of Medicines, which poſſibly <lb/>might have
        been effectual in her beginning Diſtemper, <lb/>had ſhe been well aware of her Danger. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After Delivery, the ſwelling and bulk of her Belly con- <lb/>tinued much the ſame as
        before the Birth, only upon a <lb/>plentiful evacuation of the <hi rend="italic">Lochia</hi>
        it decreaſed a little. <lb/>When her month was up, ſhe adviſed with ſeveral <pb n="2324"/>
        <lb/><choice>
          <corr>Phyſicians</corr>
          <sic>ſicians</sic>
        </choice>, Apothecaries, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> who uſed Emeticks, ſtrong <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Catharticks</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Diuretick</hi> Dyet-drinks, and all the
        train of <lb/>Medicines commonly uſed in a <hi rend="italic">Dropſy</hi>, her ſuppoſed caſe.
        <lb/>All the effect they had, was to prevent the farther In- <lb/>creaſe of the Swelling
        while ſhe uſed them; but, being <lb/>weary of the trouble and charges to no purpoſe, ſhe
        left <lb/>them wholly off, and then the Tumor increaſed very re- <lb/>markably. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thus ſhe continued about one year, and then ſhe Con- <lb/>ceived again, which ſhe
        ſuſpected by the ſtoppage of her <lb/><hi rend="italic">Catamenia</hi>, having always been
        very regular but at ſuch a <lb/>time. Her Stomach was always good, ſhe never was ve- <lb/>ry
        thirſty, ſo drank but little, made Water freely and in <lb/>great quantity, and was attended
        with none of the <lb/>Symptoms of an <hi rend="italic">Aſcites</hi>, except the Swelling of
        her Belly: <lb/>Only when ſhe was half gone, her Legs began to ſwell <lb/>and pit, growing
        very big all of a ſudden; from theſe, <lb/>and likewiſe from her Belly, there would often
        iſſue out <lb/>a great deal of watery Humour upon rubbing, as I <lb/>have mentioned already,
        eſpecially if ſhe ſcratched the <lb/>little Pimples, that would often ariſe in theſe parts.
        <lb/>About this time ſhe began to be afflicted with a difficulty <lb/>in breathing, with a
        violent Trembling and Palpitation <lb/>of her Heart, and to be often ſubject to great and
        invo- <lb/>luntary Sighings. She was not able to lye down, but <lb/>was ſtill obliged to
        ſleep in a ſitting poſture, for fear of <lb/>being choak'd. Now I think it probable, that
        all thoſe <lb/>Symptoms did proceed from the Deluge of Water con- <lb/>tained in the
        Cavities of the <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Pericardium</hi>;
        <lb/>which no doubt did more effectually haſten her end, than <lb/>the bigneſs of her Belly,
        with which ſhe might have lived <lb/>ſeveral years. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After ſhe was brought to Bed of a live Child ſhe be- <lb/>came exceeding weak, being
        unable to fetch her Breath, <lb/>and complained much of a heavy Load and Oppreſſion on
        <lb/>her Breaſt; and the third day ſhe expired. </p>
      <pb n="2325"/>
      <figure>
        <head rend="size(1.6) align-center space">
          <lb/>The Explanation of the Figures. </head>
        <p rend="hanging italic space">
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">Fig. 2.</hi> Repreſenteth the <hi rend="roman">Glandulæ
          Renales</hi>, the <lb/><hi rend="roman">Uterus</hi>, with the parts belonging to it, and
          the <lb/>large Bag or Membrane of the <hi rend="roman">Ovarium</hi> præter- <lb/>naturally
          diſtended. </p>
        <p rend="space italic">
          <list>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">a</hi>
              <hi rend="dc(1.5)">T</hi>He <hi rend="roman">Glandula Renalis</hi> on the Right ſide. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">b</hi> An Eminence, or riſing in its middle. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">c</hi> A Vein that runs from it to the <hi rend="roman"
                >Cava</hi>. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">d</hi> The <hi rend="roman">Glandula Renalis</hi> on the Left
              Side. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">e</hi> A Sulcus or Furrow in its middle. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">f</hi> A Vein running from it to the Emulgent. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">g</hi> A ſmall Vein that comes from the Diaphragm, and opens
              <lb/>into this Vein before it leaves the Gland. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">h h</hi> Two ſmall Arteries from the <hi rend="roman"
              >Aorta</hi>. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">i i</hi> Two Nervous <hi rend="roman">Twigs</hi> from one of the
              Intercoſtal <hi rend="roman">Plexus's</hi>. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">A A</hi> The Kidneys. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">B B</hi> The <hi rend="roman">Uterus</hi> cut off. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">C</hi> The <hi rend="roman">Cava</hi> cut off. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">D</hi> Its Diviſion into the <hi rend="roman">Rami Iliaci</hi>. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">E E</hi> The Internal Branches into which the <hi rend="roman"
                >Hypogaſtricks</hi>
              <lb/>open. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">F F</hi> The Emulgent Veins. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">G</hi> The <hi rend="roman">Aorta</hi> cut off. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">H</hi> Its diviſion into the Iliacks. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">I I</hi> Its Internal Branches, which are ſpread upon the <hi
                rend="roman">Uterus</hi>. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">K K</hi> The external Iliacks of both Veſſels. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">L L</hi> The Emulgent Arteries. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">M M</hi> The Spermatick Veins. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">N N N N</hi> The Spermatick Arteries, very much contorted in
              <lb/>their Progreſs, that on the Right ſide being cut off. </item>
            <pb n="2326"/>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">O</hi> The Union of the Branches of the Spermatick Vein on the
              <lb/>Right ſide. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">P</hi> The Right <hi rend="roman">Ovarium</hi>, with Blood
              Veſſels ramified on its <lb/><unclear>lower</unclear> Membrane. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">Q</hi> The Right Tube. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">q</hi> Its <hi rend="roman">Fimbria</hi>. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">R</hi> The Tube on the Left ſide, its <hi rend="roman"
                >Fimbria</hi> adhering to the <lb/>large Bag. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">S S S</hi> The Membrane of the Left <hi rend="roman"
                >Ovarium</hi>, diſtended to a <lb/>vaſt Bigneſs, with the Blood-Veſſels ramified
              upon it. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">T</hi> Some of the <hi rend="roman">Ovula</hi> grown big. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">W</hi> Some Hydatidal Tumours on the Inſide of the Great Bag. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">V V V</hi> The <hi rend="roman">Ligamenta lata</hi>. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">U</hi> The <hi rend="roman">Fundus Uteri</hi>. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">X X</hi> The <hi rend="roman">Ligamenta Rotunda</hi>; the
              Membrane that covers <lb/>them, being laid open, that the Veſſels of which they are
              <lb/>compos'd may be view'd. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">Y</hi> The <hi rend="roman">Vagina</hi> cut off. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">Z</hi> The <hi rend="roman">Veſica Urinaria</hi>. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">**</hi> A ſmall Artery and Vein on each ſide, the firſt going
              off <lb/>from the Spermatick, is ſpread upon the <hi rend="roman">Membrana Adi-
                <lb/>poſa</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Peritonæum</hi> under the Kidney; the latter
              <lb/>bringing back the Blood from theſe Parts, opens into the <lb/>Spermatick Vein.
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration on a separate fold-out page showing the internal female genitalia
          (and some of the viscera), of which the left ovary is bigger than all the other organs put
          together. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <head rend="space indent italic">
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">Fig. 3.</hi> Sheweth the <hi rend="roman">Vagina</hi> and <hi
            rend="roman">Uterus</hi> cut open. </head>
        <p rend="space hanging italic">
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">A A A</hi> The <hi rend="roman">Fundus Uteri</hi> laid open, and its
          ſides folded <lb/>back. </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of the vagina and uterus cut open, on a separate fold-out page.
        </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <head rend="italic hanging space">
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">Fig. 4.</hi> The inner Spongy Subſtance, with the Orifices <lb/>of
          the Hyſterick Veſſels. </head>
        <p rend="space italic">
          <list rend="hanging">
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">22</hi> The Glands appearing on the Inner Membrane of the
                <lb/><hi rend="roman">Uterus</hi>. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">33</hi> The ſmall Veſſels, by which the <hi rend="roman"
                >Lochia</hi>, <hi rend="roman">&amp;c.</hi> are ſeparated. </item>
            <pb n="2327"/>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">4</hi> A ſoft ſubſtance, depending from the Upper Part of the
                <lb/><hi rend="roman">Uterus</hi>, into which the foreſaid Veſſels terminate. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">5</hi> Two Tubercles, ſeated near the Beginning of the <hi
                rend="roman">Tubæ</hi>, <lb/>to which the <hi rend="roman">Placenta</hi> adher'd. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">B B</hi> The <hi rend="roman">Vagina</hi> laid open. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">6. 6.</hi> The two <hi rend="roman">Labia</hi> of the <hi
                rend="roman">Collum minus</hi>. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">7. 7.</hi> ſeveral ſmall Glands plac'd on the Upper <hi
                rend="roman">Labium</hi>. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">8.</hi> The Courſe of the <hi rend="roman">Rugæ</hi> on the
              upper ſide of the <hi rend="roman">Vagina</hi>. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">9. 9.</hi> Their direction on the under ſide of that part. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">10. 10.</hi> Two Orbicular ſubſtances, near the Orifice of the
                <hi rend="roman">Mea- <lb/>tus Urinarius</hi>. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <figDesc>These refer to the same illustration as the previous figure. </figDesc>
      </figure>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
