<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Yonge: An Account of Balls of Hair Taken from the Uterus and
          Ovaria</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>James Yonge</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of Balls of Hair Taken from the Uterus and Ovaria of Several Women; By
              Mr. James Yonge, F.R.S. Communicated to Dr. Hans Sloane, R.S. Secr.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed for B. Walford, Printer to the Royal
                  Society, at the Prince's Arms in St Paul's Church-yard. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1706-1707</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">25</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">2387-2392</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110825648</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1706.0040</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT25_2387">
    <body>
      <pb n="2387"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VI.</hi> An Account of Balls of Hair taken from the <hi rend="roman"
          >Uterus</hi>
        <lb/>and <hi rend="roman">Ovaria</hi> of ſeveral Women; by Mr. <hi rend="roman">James
          Yonge</hi>, <lb/>F. R. S. Communicated to Dr. <hi rend="roman">Hans Sloane</hi>, R. S.
        Secr. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 1705, I was call'd to deliver
        a Woman 30 <lb/>Years old, who had 4 Days laboured in vain to bring <lb/>forth her firſt
        Child: The Head, being too big for the <lb/>Paſſage, ſtuck immoveable at the <hi
          rend="italic">Os Pubis</hi>; ſo that I <lb/>could neither faſten a Crochet, nor draw it
        out by a <lb/>Cupping-Glaſs fixt to the Scalp with an Air Pump. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In this Extremity I directed my Son to open the <sic>Childs</sic>
        <lb/>Head, and take out all the Brains, with ſo much of the <lb/>Scull as he could; and then
        by a Cord faſtned round the <lb/>Neck with a Nooze, to pull it out, which was ſoon and
        <lb/>eaſily done. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Child was Corrupted and ſtunk much, ſo did the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Lochia</hi>,
        which flowed three Weeks; ſoon after they cea- <lb/>ſed, the <hi rend="italic">Menſtrua</hi>
        appeared, and the Woman went abroad: <lb/>About ſix Weeks after her Delivery, ſhe was ſeized
        with <lb/>violent Convulſions, and Hyſterick Firs, which laſted near <lb/>three Days; when a
        painful Tumor aroſe in the left ſide <lb/>of her Belly, which ended in an Eruption of white
        thick <lb/>Matter near a Pint, with ſmall Knobs of a Subſtance like <lb/>the Yolk of boiled
        Eggs: All Symptoms immediately va- <lb/>niſht, only ſhe complained of the great Hollowneſs
        where <lb/>the Tumor had been. </p>
      <pb n="2388"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Four Days after this, the like Swelling appear'd on the <lb/>right ſide of her Belly,
        which continued with a ſmall <lb/>Flux of Matter about five or ſix Months, in deſpight of
        <lb/>the many Remedies I uſed to cure her. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About that time there appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Pudenda</hi> a <lb/>Bunch of
        ſomething like greaſy Wool, which being drawn <lb/>forth, proved a Ball, or Wad of Hair, the
        bigneſs of a <lb/>Turkeys Egg, immerſed in an Unctuous Slime; adhering <lb/>on one ſide to a
        Membrane ſo large as the Palm of a Mans <lb/>Hand: And in the midſt of it a ſmall Pyramidal
        Bone re- <lb/>ſembling a ſplit Tooth. The Tumor ſunk upon this, and <lb/>the Fluor ceaſed
        immediately, and her Lunary Flux <lb/>(which all this while had not appeared) flowed as
        uſual, <lb/>and ſhe continueth in perfect Health ever ſince, full <lb/>nine Months. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>You will herewith receive the Membrane, (ſomewhat <lb/>ſhrunk and dry,) together with
        the Bone, and <hi rend="italic">Folliculus</hi>, <lb/>to lay before the <hi rend="italic">R.
          Society</hi>, whoſe Sentiments I ſhall <lb/>humbly wait to know. The Bone is perfectly
        ſuch, ſo <lb/>is the Hair, being fine, ſoft, and indifferently ſtrong, of <lb/>no great
        length, of a light brown Colour, intangled like <lb/>a parcel of Combings. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <note rend="size(0.7) italic" place="margin">Dr. <hi rend="roman">Hook</hi>'s <lb/>Phil.
          Collect. <lb/>N. 2. </note>This Caſe, though rare and extraordinary, hath ſome- <lb/>times
        hapned to others. That Famous Naturaliſt Dr. <hi rend="italic">Ty- <lb/>ſon</hi>, who hath
        ſo much obliged the World by his La- <lb/>bours and Diſcoveries, tell us, That in <hi
          rend="italic">November</hi> 1679. <lb/>he diſſected a young Gentlewoman, and found the
        right <lb/>Teſticle, or <hi rend="italic">Ovarium</hi>, ſwoln into two Bags, almoſt ſo big
        <lb/>as a Mans Head, full of a pale <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>, in which floated ſe-
        <lb/>veral Lumps of a ſoft fat Matter, which diſſolved in part <lb/>when put into hot Water.
        One of thoſe Pieces was half <lb/>ſo big as a Man's Fiſt, in which lay a great deal of Hair
        <lb/>(as there did though not ſo plentifully in all the reſt) of <lb/>a Silver Colour, ſoft,
        fine, ſtrong, and above two Foot <lb/>long; it was not faſten'd to, nor ſeemed to grow from
        <lb/>any part, but lay intangled in this Matter, and in it a <pb n="2389"/>
        <lb/>Bony Subſtance exactly reſembling that which is com- <lb/>monly called the Eye or
        Dog-Tooth. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Another time diſſecting a Woman forty Years old, he <lb/>found near the <hi
          rend="italic">Uterus</hi>, a Bag ſo big as a large Turkey- <lb/>Egg, and in it a fatty
        Subſtance, like that above mentio- <lb/>ned, with a great quantity of light ſoft Hair
        faſtned to a <lb/>fleſhy Subſtance: Within this <hi rend="italic">Cyſtis</hi> a Bone, in
        ſome ſort <lb/>reſembling a Mandible, having ſeveral Sockets, in which <lb/>were ſeated <choice>
          <corr>three</corr>
          <sic>there</sic>
        </choice>
        <hi rend="italic">Dentes Molares</hi>, or Grinder Teeth, and <lb/>a fourth not yet quite
        grown out. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Learned and Inquiſitive Doctor <hi rend="italic">Grew</hi> tells us, That <note
          rend="size(0.7) italic" place="margin"><lb/>Muſ. <hi rend="roman">R. S.</hi>
          <lb/>p. 15. </note>
        <lb/>in your <hi rend="italic">Muſæum</hi> lyeth ſuch another Tooth, found by <lb/>Dr. <hi
          rend="italic">Tyſon</hi>, after the ſame manner. And the Doctor him- <lb/>ſelf tells us,
          <hi rend="italic">ubi ſupra</hi>, That the great Dr. <hi rend="italic">Needham</hi> found
        <lb/>a Tooth and Hair in the <hi rend="italic">Ovarium</hi> of a dead Woman. And <lb/>Dr.
          <hi rend="italic">R. Hook</hi> (whoſe Death I have a thouſand Reaſons to <lb/>lament)
        ſaith, That Dr. <hi rend="italic">Samſon</hi> found the like in two <lb/>great Globoſe
        Tumors depending on, or rather parts of <lb/>the extended <hi rend="italic">Ovarium</hi>,
        wrapt up in diſſolvible and inflam- <lb/>mable fat, of a yellow Colour. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About ten Years ſince, Sir <hi rend="italic">Andrew Leak</hi> (who now ly- <lb/>eth in
        the Bead of Honour) gave me a ſmall Bunch of <lb/>Hair, being part of what had been found in
        the Belly of <lb/>a young Woman at <hi rend="italic">Deal</hi>, by Mr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Joſ. Nichols</hi> a Surgeon <lb/>there; I ſend you that Hair, with a ſhort Hiſtory of it,
        <lb/>by leave from the kind Hand who lately imparted it to <lb/>me. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">A. D.</hi> 1696. A Virgin of thirty fell into a Periodi- <lb/>cal
        Fever, and afterward a total ſuppreſſion of her <hi rend="italic">Men- <lb/>ſtrua</hi>;
        which was ſoon followed with a Pain and Tumor <lb/>in the right ſide of her Belly, which
        grew and encreaſed, <lb/>maugre all the Remedies adviſed by the Neighbouring
        <lb/>Phyſicians, till it became bigger and harder than that of <lb/>a Woman in her laſt
        Month. When it had grown a full <lb/>Year, it began to ſoften, and then the Cenſorious
        People <lb/>who ſuſpected her Honeſty, thought her in a Dropſie. <pb n="2390"/>
        <lb/>At fifteen Months end, the Belly was ſo diſtended, that it <lb/>ſeemed ready to Burſt;
        which made the Patient deſire the <lb/>Phyſicians to adviſe Mr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Nichols</hi> to make the <hi rend="italic">Paracenteſis</hi>; <lb/>but all were
        ſurprized, when inſtead of Water there ruſh- <lb/>ed out a pint and half of ſweet
        well-digeſted Matter: <lb/>The next Day he let out as much more, and then percei- <lb/>ved
        Hair four or five Inches long iſſue forth with the <lb/>Matter, but ſo faſtned in the
        Inſide, that he could not <lb/>pull them out, the Woman complaining he would draw <lb/>out a
        piece of her Belly. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>She lived but four Days after the Operation; and on <lb/>Diſſection of her Belly there
        was found ten Quarts of the <lb/>ſame Matter which flowed through the Tap-hole, and in
        <lb/>it floating a Lump of Hair ſo big as an Halfpenny Loaf, <lb/>wrapt up in a fatty
        Matter, from which being cleanſed, <lb/>it weighed full half an Ounce. On the Right ſide of
        the <lb/>Womb he found a Protuberance bigger than a large <lb/>Walnut, from which the Hair
        grew eight Inches long; <lb/>that Tumor, or rather the <hi rend="italic">Ovary</hi> being
        ſeparated from the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Matrix</hi>, there was found in it a perfect
        Dog-Tooth ſock- <lb/>eted in a Bone of a triangular Figure, in which another <lb/>Tooth was
        growing; the Bone had a <hi rend="italic">Perioſtium</hi> on it <lb/>ſurrounded with Fleſh,
        faſtned at the <hi rend="italic">Calvaria</hi> to the <lb/>Scull. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If you deſire to ſee thoſe things, or to have a more <lb/>particular account of this
        Diſſection, Mr. <hi rend="italic">Nichols</hi> will <lb/>oblige you with the ſame freedom
        and readineſs he hath <lb/>done your Servant. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>My Patient's Caſe hath two Difficulties in it which I <lb/>can't get over, <hi
          rend="italic">viz.</hi> How theſe Subſtances got in where <lb/>they lodged? And how they
        got out thence by the way <lb/>they did? Without doubt they were neſted in or near the
        <lb/>Teſticle; the place of Tumor and Pain, and the many <lb/>Anatomical Diſcoveries made by
        thoſe great Philoſophers <lb/>I have quoted, do ev'n demonſtrate it: They could not <lb/>be
        conveyed into that Bowel, and muſt therefore be made <pb n="2391"/>
        <lb/>in it; but how, and of Materials, is a Queſtion to be <lb/>put at <hi rend="italic"
          >Delphos</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Greſham College</hi>, for <hi rend="italic"
        >Apollo</hi>, or the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Royal Society</hi> to Anſwer. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Such Philoſophers who call thoſe extraordinary Appear- <lb/>ances <hi rend="italic"
          >Luſus Naturæ</hi>, ſeem like thoſe of old, who wearied <lb/>in their Natural Searches by
        ſome puzling Difficulty, take <lb/>Refuge in Words, aſcribing the Cauſe of Things which
        <lb/>they can't diſcover or diſcern, to Occult Qualities, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        <lb/>If they mean by <hi rend="italic">Luſus Naturæ</hi>, the Sport or Recreation of
        <lb/>Nature, they accuſe her who doth nothing in vain, and <lb/>is the Author of all the
        Order, Beauty and Benefits we <lb/>enjoy, as delighting to make Monſtrous, Deformed, Uſeleſs
        <lb/>and Miſchievous Things; Things preternatural and con- <lb/>trary to Nature, becauſe
        deſtroying its beſt Works, <lb/>Man. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If by it they mean that Nature being on the Work of <lb/>Generation, miſtook, failed,
        or was diſappointed; and <lb/>inſtead of forming an <hi rend="italic">Embryo</hi> or <hi
          rend="italic">Fœtus</hi>, made a <hi rend="italic">Chaos</hi>, <lb/>turn'd into a confus'd
        Lump of Bone, Fat, Hair and <lb/>Membranes, the Materials or Elements of Animal Bodies,
        <lb/>they greatly err; for in all ſuch Acts of Nature, the Coi- <lb/>tion of both Sexes is
        required, according to the old, or <lb/>either of the new Hypotheſes <hi rend="italic">de
          Generatione Animal.</hi>
        <lb/>which in the Girl of <hi rend="italic">Deal</hi> was wanting; ſhe being found,
        <lb/>upon a very nice and ſtrict Scrutiny of Jealous Eyes, to <lb/>die a Virgin, and Intact. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We are told by many Authors of the beſt Credit, That <lb/>great Quantities of Hair have
        been found in all the Parts <lb/>of Humane Bodies, the Fluids not excepted. Dr. <hi
          rend="italic">Tyſon</hi>
        <lb/>did, about twenty Years ſince, publiſh a large Collection <lb/>from them. That
        Penetrating Eye, beyond the Ken of <lb/>which ſcarce any thing in Nature is concealed,
        reaſons <lb/>like a Philoſopher, on the Nature and Production of Hair <lb/>in Human Bodies,
        Living or Dead; eſpecially in thoſe <lb/>Parts we are writing of: but the Teeth and Bones
        ſeem too <lb/>hard, even for ſo acute an Inveſtigator. He hath indeed <pb n="2392"/>
        <lb/>given us ſome very fine Thoughts, and Ingenious Con- <lb/>jectures concerning their
        Origin and Production; and <lb/>perhaps he may by this time have diſcovered more clearly
        <lb/>their Cauſes. If this Paper of mine occaſion his divulg- <lb/>ing thoſe Sentiments, how
        proud ſhall I be of the Mid- <lb/>wifery! </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This is the only Difficulty all thoſe Stories I have told <lb/>from others are
        incumbred with; but mine hath another <lb/>no leſs hard to reſolve. It's obvious how thoſe
        things <lb/>were got out of the Woman that dyed; but my Patient, <lb/>who ſurvived the
        Evacuation, puzleth me to find the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ductus per Quem</hi> for ſuch a
        Lump to paſs from without <lb/>the Womb into the <hi rend="italic">Vulva</hi>. It was
        certainly lodged with- <lb/>out the <hi rend="italic">Uterus</hi>; But which way could ſuch
        a Lump of <lb/>greaſy Hair, with a Bone, and a large Membrane adhe- <lb/>ring, paſs into it?
        I know none but the <hi rend="italic">Tuba Fallopiana</hi>; <lb/>but the Orifice of that
        into the Womb is ſo ſmall, that <lb/>it ſometimes wont admit an Egg no bigger than a Corn of
        <lb/>Pepper to paſs: Whence thoſe Conceptions which are <lb/>made in that Trunk are
        occaſioned. It will diſtend very <lb/>largely, ſo as to hold a big Fœtus; but where it is
        in- <lb/>ſerted to the Matrix, the <hi rend="italic">Foramen</hi> is too narrow for
        <lb/>Subſtances of ſuch Magnitude to paſs, unleſs ſome very <lb/>extraordinary Accident
        expanded it; and what that can <lb/>be, I can't apprehend. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
