<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Musgrave: Concerning the Jaundice</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>William Musgrave</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Letter from Dr William Musgrave, Fellow of the College of Physicians, and R. S.
              to Dr Hans Sloane, R. S. Secr. concerning the Jaundice, Occasioned by a Stone
              Obstructing the Ductus Communis Bilarius, which was afterwards Voided by Stool</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed for B. Walford, Printer to the Royal
                  Society, at the Prince's Arms in St Paul's Church-yard. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1706-1707</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">25</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">2233-2236</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110825648</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1706.0011</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT25_2233">
    <body>
      <pb n="2233"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">III.</hi> A Letter from Dr <hi rend="roman">William Muſgrave</hi>,
        Fellow of <lb/>the College of Phyſicians, and R. S. to Dr <hi rend="roman">Hans
          <lb/>Sloane</hi>, R. S. Secr. concerning the <hi rend="roman">Jaundice</hi>, occa-
        <lb/>ſioned by a Stone obſtructing the <hi rend="roman">Ductus commu- <lb/>nis
        bilarius</hi>, which was afterwards voided by Stool. </head>
      <salute rend="italic indent">
        <lb/>SIR, </salute>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">B</hi>Eing of late at <hi rend="italic">Clifton</hi>, in <hi
          rend="italic">Dorſetſhire</hi>, the Seat of Mr <lb/><hi rend="italic">Harvey</hi>, Nephew
        to the Celebrated Phyſician of that <lb/>Name, I was there ſhewn a Curioſity, which I
        thought <lb/>remarkable, and may perhaps be worthy your notice. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is a <hi rend="italic">Stone</hi>, that Gentleman voided, ſome years ſince, by
        <lb/>Stool; and which he repreſented to me, as having come <lb/>from the <hi rend="italic"
          >Ductus communis bilarius</hi>: But the Largeneſs of <lb/>it is ſuch, as made the latter
        part of the account ſeem, at <lb/>firſt hearing, ſomewhat dubious. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Figure of this <hi rend="italic">Stone</hi> is Oval; the Length almoſt an
        <lb/>Inch; the Breadth, (or ſhorteſt Diameter) 7/10 of an Inch: <lb/>It weighed 59 Grains,
        when I ſaw it; but, at its coming <lb/>off, was (as I am inform'd) above a Dram in weight:
          <pb n="2234"/>
        <lb/>Some part of it being, by frequent handling, rubb'd away. <lb/>The Surface rough,
        unequal, divided into ſeveral lit- <lb/>tle Riſings, each about the ſize of half a Vetch, or
        ſome- <lb/>what leſs. </p>
      <figure>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>You have in <hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 7. Y. Z. The Proportions exactly drawn. </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of an oval stone, its surface covered with little bumps, on a
          separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The many ſtrong annular Fibres, which appear not only <lb/>at the Orifice, where the
          <hi rend="italic">Ductus communis</hi> opens into the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
        >Duodenum</hi>; but alſo all along the oblique paſſage, of that <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Ductus</hi>, between the Coats of the Inteſtine, (which paſ- <lb/>ſage is, according to
        Dr <hi rend="italic">Gliſſon</hi>'s meaſure, about half an <lb/>inch in length) do, by way
        of Sphincter, keep this end <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Ductus communis</hi> very ſtrait
        and cloſe. And be- <lb/>ſides this ſtraitneſs of the <hi rend="italic">Ductus</hi>, the two
        Oblique In- <lb/>ſertions, it makes at ſome diſtance from one another, thro' <lb/>the two
        outer Coats of the <hi rend="italic">Duodenum</hi>, render it yet more <lb/>difficult, for a
        ſubſtance of any Bulk, to paſs this way. So <lb/>that, however great Stones may be generated
        in the Gall- <lb/>Bladder, <hi rend="italic">Ductus Cyſticus</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Hepaticus</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Communis</hi>, it is not <lb/>eaſy to conceive, How
        a Stone of the Magnitude here de- <lb/>ſcrib'd, could poſſibly, through a paſſage of itſelf
        ſo very <lb/>narrow, ſtrait, and difficult, be conveyed into the <hi rend="italic">Duo-
          <lb/>denum</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From theſe Conſiderations, I was extreamly deſirous to <lb/>hear, what could be ſaid,
        to Prove, That this <hi rend="italic">Stone</hi> was not <lb/>form'd in the <hi
          rend="italic">Fiſtula alimentaris</hi>, but (large, as now it is) <lb/>came this way into
        it. In anſwer to which Inquiry, the <lb/>Gentleman was pleas'd to let me know, </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That, before the Diſcharge of this <hi rend="italic">Stone</hi>, He had the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Jaundice</hi>; which came ſuddenly on him, and continued <lb/>ſeveral
        months, in a ſevere, and moſt exceſſive manner. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That this <hi rend="italic">Jaundice</hi>, beſide the diſcolouring of his Urine
        <lb/>and Skin, to a very great degree; beſide Loſs of Appetite, <lb/>Faintneſs, and many
        other Symptoms, uſual in this Di- <lb/>ſtemper; was alſo accompanyed with a Pain (in, or)
        near <lb/>the Stomach. </p>
      <pb n="2235"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That, during this <hi rend="italic">Jaundice</hi>, his Stools were of a white
        <lb/>colour, as having very little, or no Mixture of Choler in <lb/>them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That, Travelling under theſe circumſtances, more eſpe- <lb/>cially with a conſtant
        Pain, (as before mention'd,) in his <lb/>Coach from <hi rend="italic">London</hi> to <hi
          rend="italic">Clifton</hi>; and, after a little time, to <lb/><hi rend="italic">Bath</hi>;
        he found, a little after his Arrival at <hi rend="italic">Bath</hi>, this <hi rend="italic"
          >Stone</hi>
        <lb/>come off by Stool; and, together with it, almoſt a Spoon- <lb/>ful of <hi rend="italic"
          >Gravelly Matter</hi>; and a conſiderable <choice>
          <corr>quantity</corr>
          <sic>qnantity</sic>
        </choice> of <lb/>Choler, as appear'd from the yellowneſs of the Stools: <lb/>All which
        happen'd ſo ſoon after he came to <hi rend="italic">Bath</hi>, as <lb/>Evidently to prove,
        the Diſcharge of both [Choler and <lb/>Stone] to proceed from the motion of the Coach. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That his deliverance, from the <hi rend="italic">Jaundice</hi>, commenc'd <lb/>from the
        Expulſion of this Stone: For, ſoon after that, the <lb/>Colour of the Skin and Urine, indeed
        all the ill Symptoms <lb/>vaniſh'd; and, in a very little time, (Weakneſs only ex-
        <lb/>cepted) He recovered. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe Propoſitions, put together, make a conſiderable <lb/>Argument, That the Orifice
        of the <hi rend="italic">Ductus communis</hi> (how <lb/>ſtrait, and how ſtrong ſoever) was,
        in this Gentleman, ſo <lb/>far dilated, as to give way to the <hi rend="italic">Stone</hi>,
        here deſcribed; <lb/>that is, dilated to a Circle, in Diameter 7/10 of an Inch, in
        <lb/>Circumference one whole Inch and ¾. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Jaundice</hi> is often obſerv'd, to be a moſt ſtubborn
        <lb/>Diſtemper, not eaſily yielding to our moſt probable <lb/>Methods; and many times to
        none at all. <hi rend="italic">Riverius</hi> poſi- <lb/>tively affirms, That, when it
        proceeds from a Stone ob- <lb/>ſtructing the Current of the Choler, it is incurable: Urg-
        <lb/>ing this reaſon for his opinion; <q rend="italic">Calculus, cum diſſolvi non
          <lb/>poſſit, morbum facit incurabilem </q>. Capite de <hi rend="italic">Ictero</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the <hi rend="italic">Jaundice</hi> is thus difficult of Cure, eſpecially
        <lb/>when there is a probability (whether from a Pain fixt in, <lb/>or near the Region of
        the Liver, or from any good Ar- <lb/>gument whatſoever) That it ariſes from the Cauſe now
        <lb/>mentioned; rather than to Beat over the ſame ground to <pb n="2236"/>
        <lb/>no purpoſe, or other ground equally improbable; it may <lb/>not be amiſs, to adviſe
        Exerciſe on Horſeback, in Coach, <lb/>or any other ſuch way, as ſhall be likely to diſlodge
        the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Stone</hi>, and bring it off. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But, to make this Exerciſe effectual, it ought to be Vio- <lb/>lent, as the Patient can
        well bear it; and in ſuch manner, <lb/>as may, by much agitation of the Body, be moſt condu-
        <lb/>cing to the Deſign in hand. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Hiſtory, here mentioned, does ſufficiently recom- <lb/><choice>
          <corr>mend </corr>
          <sic/>
        </choice>this <hi rend="italic">Gymnaſtic Courſe</hi>; as capable of relieving, in ſome
        <lb/>Caſes of the <hi rend="italic">Jaundice</hi>, when the beſt methods of Phyſick
        <lb/>(for ſuch we ought to ſuppoſe this <choice>
          <corr>Gentleman</corr>
          <sic>Gentlemen</sic>
        </choice> had pre- <lb/>ſcrib'd himſelf) fail of ſucceſs. </p>
      <dateline rend="align-right">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Exon.</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">Feb.</hi> 23. 1705-6. </dateline>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
