<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Adams: Concerning a Monstrous Calf</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Archibald Adams</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Part of a Letter from Dr. Archibald Adams of Norwich, to Dr. Edwaid Tyson, Fellow
              of the College of Physicians and Royal Society; Concerning a Monstrous Calf, and Some
              Things Observable in the Anatomy of a Human Ear </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed for B. Walford, Printer to the Royal
                  Society, at the Prince's Arms in St Paul's Church-yard. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1706-1707</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">25</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">2414-2415</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110825648</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1706.0047</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT25_2414">
    <body>
      <pb n="2414"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging size(1.6)">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">IV.</hi> Part of a Letter from Dr. <hi rend="roman">Archibald
          <lb/>Adams</hi> of <hi rend="roman">Norwich</hi>, to Dr. <hi rend="roman"><choice>
            <corr>Edward</corr>
            <sic>Edwa1d</sic>
          </choice>
          <lb/>Tyſon</hi>, Fellow of the College of Phyſi- <lb/>cians and Royal Society; concerning
        a <lb/>Monſtrous <hi rend="roman">Calf</hi>, and ſome things obſerva- <lb/>ble in the
        Anatomy of a Human Ear. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> Have made what ſearch I could about that Mon- <lb/>ſtrous Calf,
        and I find that its Dam was all that a Poor <lb/>Man had, who finding his <hi rend="italic"
          >Cow</hi> unable to caſt her <lb/>Young, employ'd his Neighbour to aſſiſt her; this
        <lb/>Man not thinking of any ſuch Rarity us'd ſuch violence <lb/>upon the Monſter, that he
        disfigur'd the Head in pulling <lb/>it from the <hi rend="italic">Cow</hi>; notwithſtanding
        it liv'd three Hours, <lb/>and in all probability had lived till this time, if the Aſ-
        <lb/>ſiſtant had made uſe of the beſt Method in that caſe, <lb/>and ſo by deſtroying the
        Owners All, might have ſav'd <lb/>him an Eſtate: then it Dy'd, and being Rip'd up was
        <lb/>found, to the beſt of my Information, to be in all re- <lb/>ſpects like any other of
        the ſame kind, excepting the <lb/>Wings, which to me ſeem to be Bags formed out of the
        <lb/>Membranes, torn and diſtended from the adjacent parts, <lb/>and by freſh ſupplies from
        the circulating Fluids were <lb/>inlarg'd to the bigneſs you now ſee them in. Whether
        <lb/>the Subſtance contain'd in theſe Baggs was Fibrous and <lb/>Muſcular, or only a heap of
        Veſſels incloſed in a <hi rend="italic">Cyſtis</hi>, <lb/>like the <hi rend="italic"
          >Placenta</hi>, The Aſſiſtants Ignorance, and the <lb/>diſtance of time and place, it
        being three Years ago, <lb/>make me uncapable to account for: The place is called <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Wolterton</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Norfolk</hi>. </p>
      <pb n="2415"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>[<hi rend="italic">The Skin of this <hi rend="roman">Calf</hi> is now in the Repoſitory
          of the <lb/><hi rend="roman">Royal Society</hi> in <hi rend="roman">Greſham-College</hi>,
          given to the ſame </hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <hi rend="italic">by Dr. <hi rend="roman">Adams</hi>.</hi>] </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Give me leave to write one thing which to me is <lb/>altogether new. The boney Cavity
        of the Ear is cover- <lb/>ed at each end by a Membrane; the former is called the
        <lb/>Membrane of the Drum, and the other is directly op- <lb/>poſite to it; the outer is
        ſtronger than the inner, ſo I <lb/>call them with ſubmiſſion. They are joined together
        <lb/>by the handle of the <hi rend="italic">Malleus</hi> adhering to the outer, and <lb/>the
        upper part of the Stirrup to the inner, which by <lb/>the intervention of the <hi
          rend="italic">Incus</hi> and the Orbicular Bone <lb/>make a Chain, and they ſeem to be
        acted and re-acted <lb/>by theſe ſmall Bones reciprocally. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Whether Artiſts had any reſpect to this Original, <lb/>when they firſt deviſed Drums, I
        cannot ſay; but no- <lb/>thing can more nearly repreſent the Natural than the
        <lb/>Artificial does; the Skins of this anſwering to the Mem- <lb/>branes of that, the
        Wooden Cylinder to the Boney Ca- <lb/>vity; the ſound of the Drum would be flat without a
        <lb/>Hole in the ſide, and Nature has given a paſſage from <lb/>the Palate to the Ear. The
        Skins of the Drum would <lb/>leſſen the ſound, if they were not kept on the ſtretch; <lb/>ſo
        would thoſe of the other flag, if the handle of the <lb/>Hammer and the Stirrup keep them on
        not the Tenſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This inner Membrane is cloſely ſtretch'd before the <lb/>Labyrinth, the <hi
          rend="italic">Foramen rotundum</hi>, and the paſſage into <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >Cochlea</hi>, (I omit the <hi rend="italic">Foramen Ovale</hi>, becauſe the Foot <lb/>of
        the Stirrup exactly ſhuts it), that ſo the ſound may be <lb/>the bigger upon its approach to
        the Nerves. The Stir- <lb/>rup is generally broke in diſſecting the Ear, <choice>
          <corr>particularly</corr>
          <sic>patricularly</sic>
        </choice>
        <lb/>that Cover which goes over the Bone on each ſide; but <lb/>if it be carefully open'd,
        the Stirrup is entirely cover'd <lb/>with a Membrane, which forms a Cavity flatly Oval,
        <lb/>and the inſide is Excavated. </p>
      <dateline rend="align-right">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Norwich</hi>, <hi rend="italic">December</hi>, 18, 1706. </dateline>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
