<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Mead: An Account of Three Cases of the Hydrophobia</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>R. Mead</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of Three Cases of the Hydrophobia. By R. Mead, M. D. F. R. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for H. Clements, at the Half-Moon in St Paul's
                  Church-yard.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1708-1709</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">26</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">433-438</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO"/>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1708.0069</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT26_0433">
    <body>
      <pb n="433"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VI.</hi> An Account of three Caſes of the <hi rend="roman">Hydropho-
          <lb/>bia</hi>. By <hi rend="roman">R. Mead</hi>, M. D. F. R. S. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE Symptoms from the Bite of a mad Dog are ſo <lb/>ſurprizing
        and terrible, that it is hardly poſſible <lb/>to deſcribe the Agony of a Patient in this
        unhappy Con- <lb/>dition. I have lately had the opportunity to ſee two In- <lb/>ſtances of
        this Caſe. </p>
     <div>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The firſt was of a Lad of about the Age of Nine Years, <lb/>a ſturdy and bold Boy. A
          mad Bitch of the Mungrel <lb/>kind was hunted in the Street, he ſtruck at her with a
          <lb/>Stick, and ſhe flying in his Face, bit him in the right <lb/>Cheek, which was torn
          with a large Wound to the mid- <lb/>dle of the Noſe. This was on the 20th of <hi
            rend="italic">April</hi> laſt. A <lb/>Surgeon cured the Wound in about 14 days time, by
          ap- <lb/>plying for the firſt three Days, <hi rend="italic">Theriac. Andromach.</hi> in
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Sp. Vin.</hi> and afterwards dreſſing it with <hi rend="italic"
            >Liniment. Arcæi</hi>
          <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Balſam. Terebinthin</hi>. No other Care was taken, only <lb/>a
            <hi rend="italic">Bolus</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Theriac. Andromach.</hi> was given him
          every <lb/>Night while under Cure, and quickly after he was bit, <lb/>he was perſuaded to
          eat the whole Liver of the Bitch <lb/>fry'd. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>He continued very brisk and well to the 22d of <hi rend="italic">May</hi>; <lb/>upon
          that day he ſeem'd dull and ſick, would eat no Din- <lb/>ner, except a little boil'd
          Spinnage, walk'd out in the After- <lb/>noon, and in the Evening complained of his Stomach
          and <lb/>Head; his Mother gave him a ſmall Glaſs of Brandy, for <lb/>he would drink
          nothing elſe. In the Night he was very <pb n="434"/>
          <lb/>bad, ſtartled often, and ſcreamed out as in an Agony, eſ- <lb/>pecially when deſired
          to drink, and complained miſera- <lb/>bly whenever he made Urine, ſaying it hurt him. The
          <lb/>next Morning he vomited up the Herbs he had eat the <lb/>day before, unalter'd. I was
          ſent for that Day in the Af- <lb/>ternoon, and found him in a perfect Agony, all in a
          <lb/>ſweat, trembling, toſſing himſelf up and down, talking <lb/>continually, looking very
          wild; his Pulſe low, and ſome- <lb/>times quicker, then ſlower: His Urine made the Night
          be- <lb/>fore as well Colour'd as ordinary. I deſired him to Drink; <lb/>he took a little
          in his Mouth, but as it was going down, <lb/>he threw it out with Violence, ſaying it hurt
          him; and <lb/>praying that he might take no more. We over perſuaded <lb/>him to hold a
          little in his Mouth and ſwallow it by de- <lb/>grees and gently; he did ſo with a little
          more eaſe, but <lb/>was glad when 'twas over. We bid him ſuck the Drink <lb/>thro' a
          Quill; he try'd, but could not get it down by con- <lb/>tinual Gulps, but ſtopt as ſoon as
          a very little was paſs'd, <lb/>ſtill crying out that it hurt him to ſwallow it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I preſently declared the Caſe to be deſperate. However <lb/>for the ſatisfaction of
          the Relations, Bliſtering Plaſters <lb/>were apply'd to the Back and on each ſide of the
          Neck; <lb/>and a Diuretic <hi rend="italic">Bolus</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Sal. Succin.
            Camphor.</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Conſerv. <lb/>Lujul.</hi> was given every ſix Hours;
          for he ſeemed from the <lb/>firſt of his Complaint to have a difficulty of Urine. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The next day, the 24th at Noon, I found him much <lb/>worſe, he had raved all Night;
          could not bear the ſight <lb/>of any thing white, and ſaid, that if all the Women in
          <lb/>the Room who had white Aprons would go out, he <lb/>ſhould be well preſently. He ſaid
          he would drink if we <lb/>would give him it in a black Cup; but when brought <lb/>made
          many Excuſes and could not, tho' at the ſame time <lb/>complain'd he was dry, and pleaſed
          himſelf with talking <lb/>of full Pots. He eat ſome Bread and Butter heartily, but
          <lb/>vomited it up quickly together with a frothy Slime. We <pb n="435"/>
          <lb/>dipp'd him in a Tub of warm Water; he ſaid he was not <lb/>afraid of Water, and was
          quiet in it for a little while, but <lb/>ſoon fell into a Convulſion Fit, which obliged us
          to take <lb/>him out. I obſerved his Eyes to grow more ſtaring, and <lb/>the Pupil to be
          prodiguouſly inlarged. He was thrown <lb/>continually with ſuch Violence from Place to
          Place, that <lb/>it was very hard to keep him in Bed; and quite tired <lb/>and ſpent, fell
          into cold Sweats, and dy'd this day at <lb/>Four in the Afternoon. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The next day I obtain'd leave to open the Body. We <lb/>examin'd the Brain, Throat,
          Breaſt and Stomach, but met <lb/>with no extraordinary appearance any where, excepting
          <lb/>that there was a great quantity of greeniſh viſcid Bile in <lb/>the Stomach. </p>
      </div>
     <div>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The other Patient was a very luſty vigorous Man of 45 <lb/>Years. He had ten Weeks
          before been bit in one of the <lb/>Fore-fingers near the Nail, by a little Naked Dog of
          the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Guinea</hi> Breed. On the 8th of <hi rend="italic"
            >November</hi> in the Morning <lb/>he complained of a great Sickneſs at Stomach, and
          vomit- <lb/>ed green and yellow Choler. The next Morning he took <lb/>a Doſe of <hi
            rend="italic">Rad. Ipecacuanh.</hi> Whilſt he was vomiting, he <lb/>complained of a
          difficulty of ſwallowing; and when <lb/>preſs'd to drink to work off the Medicine,
          contrived him- <lb/>ſelf a way of ſucking the Gruel given him, through a <lb/>piece of a
          Tobacco Pipe, but could not get down a <sic>ove</sic>
          <lb/>one Pint; and tho' he afterwards often try'd this Trick, <lb/>yet it did not ſucceed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On the 10th he had eight Ounces of Blood taken a- <lb/>way at the Arm, and took a <hi
            rend="italic">Bolus</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Theriac. Andromach.</hi>
          <lb/>with <hi rend="italic">Lap. Contrayerv.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I came to him on the 11th; found him ty'd in his <lb/>Bed, raving Mad, biting and
          ſpitting at the By-ſtanders, <lb/>crying out Murder, making an odd Noiſe as if he cough'd
          <lb/>up ſomething from the Throat; this motion I had alſo <pb n="436"/>
          <lb/>took notice of in the Boy, and I ſuppoſe this is what ſome <lb/>Authors have call'd
            <hi rend="italic">Barking</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>He ſay'd he would drink if we would unbind him, and <lb/>give him Water; but as ſoon
          as it came to his Mouth, he <lb/>threw away the Cup with the greateſt Fury imaginable, and
          <lb/>grew ſo unruly, that he was with much ado ty'd down <lb/>again. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I obſerved that he had a Palſie of his right Arm, for he <lb/>moved this only by the
          help of the other; and thoſe <lb/>who attended him, had taken notice that this Symptome
          <lb/>began the Day before, and that at the ſame time he had <lb/>endeavour'd to Read, but
          could not, complaining of a <lb/>Miſt before his Eyes. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As he ſeem'd afraid of every body, ſo he ſhewed the <lb/>greateſt Enmity to thoſe,
          for whom at other times he uſed <lb/>to have the moſt Love and Reſpect. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I ordered a Surgeon to take away 20 Ounces of Blood <lb/>at his Arm: And obſerved it
          to be very thick and black. <lb/>He was very tame after this for a few Minutes, but fell
          <lb/>again into his outragious Fit, in which he ſoon laid him- <lb/>ſelf down quite ſpent,
          and dy'd. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I could not by all poſſible means get leave to open the <lb/>Body. </p>
      </div>
     <div>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Since theſe Accidents I have had an Account ſent me <lb/>by a Surgeon from <hi
            rend="italic">Stamford</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Lincolnſhire</hi>, of a young <lb/>Man
          of about 18 Years, who dy'd <hi rend="italic">Hydrophobus</hi> by the <lb/>Bite of a Mad
          Fox, that had been bit by a mad Dog. <lb/>The Symptoms diſcovered themſelves three Months
          after <lb/>the Wound, which was upon the back of the Hand, and <lb/>being healed by the
          Application of <hi rend="italic">Theriaca Andromach.</hi>
          <lb/>had left a ſmall black Scab behind. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Three days before his Death he was ſeized with a Fever, <lb/>for which he was
          Blooded, Vomited and Bliſtered; he <lb/>bit to pieces the Glaſs in which Drink was given
          him. <pb n="437"/>
          <lb/>When Diſſected, the <hi rend="italic">Fauces</hi> were found very much infla-
          <lb/>med; The left Lobe of the Lungs black, with the Veſicles <lb/>full of black Blood;
          The ſurface in ſome places, which the <lb/>blackneſs had not cover'd, appearing Bliſtered,
          as if raiſed <lb/>by <hi rend="italic">Cantharides</hi>. The Liver was hard and of a
          yellow bi- <lb/>lious Colour. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>During the whole Violence of the Diſtemper, the <hi rend="italic">Penis</hi>
          <lb/>was obſerved to be continually erected, and as hard as <lb/>a Bone. This Symptom is
          particularly taken notice of <lb/>by <hi rend="italic">Cælius Aurelianus</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Surgeon who opened the Body, with his Knife <lb/>ſlightly wounded his
          Fore-finger, and was ſurpriz'd to find <lb/>that it feſtered, and gave him much more Pain
          than a <lb/>greater Cut had at other times done. This I the rather <lb/>take notice of,
          becauſe ſomething of the ſame nature hap- <lb/>pen'd to the Surgeon who Diſſected my
          Patient. His <lb/>Hand the following Night was taken with an <hi rend="italic"
            >Eryſipelas</hi>, <lb/>attended with great Tenſion and Pain: This was owing <lb/>to a
          little Wound made in one of his Fingers a Day or <lb/>two before, from which, in turning
          over the Parts, he had <lb/>rubb'd off the Plaiſter; and it went not off without the con-
          <lb/>tinued Application of Cooling and Diſcutient Medicines. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>From all theſe Hiſtories, it may not perhaps be wrong <note rend="size(0.8)"
            place="margin"><lb/>Vid. <hi rend="italic">Eſ- <lb/>ſays on <lb/>Poiſons. </hi></note>
          <lb/>to conclude, that the <hi rend="italic">Hydrophobia</hi>, (a Name not very
          <lb/>proper for the Diſtemper) is the Effect of a particular kind <lb/>of an Inflammation
          in the Blood, accompany'd with ſo <lb/>great a Tenſion and Dryneſs of the Nervous
          Membranes, <lb/>and ſuch an Elaſticity and Force of the Fluid with <lb/>which they are
          filled, that the moſt common Repreſen- <lb/>tations are made to the Mind with too great
          Effect, and <lb/>the uſual Impreſſions of Objects upon the Organs can- <lb/>not be
          ſuffered: Hence proceed the Timorouſneſs, unac- <lb/>countable Anxiety and Inquietude,
          which are always <lb/>the forerunners of the Dread of Liquids; as alſo did the <pb n="438"/>
          <lb/>Pain in making Water, and the ſtrange Averſion obſerved <lb/>in the Boy at the ſight
          of any thing <hi rend="italic">White</hi>; the <hi rend="italic">Retina</hi> be- <lb/>ing
          really hurt and grieved by the ſtriking of the Rays <lb/>of Light upon it. Nor is it hard
          to conceive that when <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Salival</hi> Liquor is hot, and the
          Throat inflam'd and dry, <lb/>the ſwallowing of Drink ſhould cauſe ſuch an intolerable
          <lb/>Agony; no more than it is that, when things are wrought <lb/>up to this wretched
          Condition, the diſmal Tragedy ſhould <lb/>not laſt above three of four days at moſt, in
          which the <lb/>Patient is perfectly fatigued and torn to Death by the <lb/>Violence of his
          Actions and Efforts. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
