<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Yonge: Concerning Several Solid Bodies Voided by Urine</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>James Yonge</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Letter from Mr. James Yonge, F. R. S. to Dr. Hans Sloane, R. S. Secr.
              concerning Several Solid Bodies Voided by Urine </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for H. Clements, at the Half-Moon in St Paul's
                  Church-yard.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1708-1709</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">26</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">420-423</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO"/>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1708.0066</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT26_0420">
    <body>
      <pb n="420"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">III.</hi> A Letter from Mr. <hi rend="roman">James Yonge</hi>, F. R.
        S. <lb/>to Dr. <hi rend="roman">Hans Sloane</hi>, R. S. Secr. concerning <lb/>ſeveral Solid
        Bodies voided by Urine. </head>
      <salute rend="italic indent space">
        <lb/>Honoured Sir, </salute>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">Y</hi>Eſterday I did again examine the Woman from whom <lb/>the Bunch
        came, as alſo her Daughter, and Ser- <lb/>vant that attended her when it was ejected; and
        they all <lb/>affirm that the Chamber-Pot uſed was a White glazed <lb/>one, and very clean;
        and the Woman tells me ſhe ſenſi- <lb/>bly felt it when it came away, and that a Tumour
        which <lb/>ſhe felt in one ſide of her Belly, did thereupon va- <lb/>niſh. That ever ſince,
        which is eight Months, ſhe hath <lb/>been unmoleſted with thoſe Torments, and other Symp-
        <lb/>tomes which ſeized her frequently before, as I related in <lb/>my laſt: only now and
        then ſome ſmall Pains happen <lb/>about her Loins; and ſometimes ſhe brings off Mucilage
        <lb/>in her Urine. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I am not very credulous, nor did I ſoon believe it <lb/>poſſible for Hair to paſs
        through thoſe impervious ways, <lb/>by which the Urine is conveyed to the Kidneys, <hi
          rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> and <lb/>its natural Ciſtern. But when I conſidered all the
        Cir- <lb/>cumſtances, and how frequently things unaccountable <lb/>happen, the truth of
        which we are well aſſured, and <lb/>that many like this, and ſome more ſtrange are related
        <lb/>by Authors of the beſt Credit, and many as ſurprizing <lb/>(perhaps much more ſo) have
        occurred to me within <lb/>a few Years in this Country; I make no doubt of its <lb/>truth. </p>
      <pb n="421"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Authors and Stories are numerous. <hi rend="italic">Diemerbroeck</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Anat. lib. 1. c. 17.</hi> mentions divers of his own Know-
        <lb/>ledge, and many more from <hi rend="italic">Plutarch</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Langius</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Alex. Be- <lb/>nedictus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">J. M.
          Heſſius</hi>, <hi rend="italic">J. Alexandrinus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">N.
          Florentinus</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">P. Pigræus</hi>, and others, That Needles, Lumps
        of Fat, <lb/>Iron Keys, Roots, Seeds, Nails, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> have come off in
        <lb/>Urine. To theſe may be added <hi rend="italic">Tho. Bartholinus</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Act. <lb/>Med. Vol. 2 Obſ. 125. Vol. 3. Obſ. 68. Vol. 5. Obſ. 57. <lb/>70.</hi> As alſo
        in his <hi rend="italic">Tr. de Lact. Thorac. Cap. 6. 9.</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">Fabr. <lb/>Hildanus, Cent. 5. Obſ. 51.</hi> who write of Pins, <hi
          rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> caſt <lb/>off by Urine. But our Country-Man Dr. <hi
          rend="italic">Farfax</hi>, writes <lb/>of one more ſtrange; A Leaden-bullet ſwallowed by a
        <lb/>Woman for the Cholick, was piſs'd off ſome Years after- <lb/>ward, incruſtated with a
        gravelly, gritty, and ſtony Ac- <lb/>creſion . The Story is publiſhed by Mr. <hi
          rend="italic">Oldenburgh</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Ph. <lb/>Tr.</hi> No. 40. to which I
        refer. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About twenty Years ſince I was aſſured by a Phyſician <lb/>practiſing in the Weſt Part
        of <hi rend="italic">Cornwall</hi>, that he knew a <lb/>Woman that piſs'd out a ſmall
        Plumb-Stone. But there <lb/>happen'd at <hi rend="italic">Loo</hi> in the ſame County, about
        16 Years ago, <lb/>a more ſurprizing Accident of that ſort, which I here <lb/>ſet you down
        as I had it from the Pen of the Phyſitian <lb/>concern'd, who is alive, and the Truth of it
        well known <lb/>in and about the Town where it happen'd. </p>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>
          <q rend="diple"><hi rend="italic">Nathaniel Mitchell</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Loo</hi> in
              <hi rend="italic">Cornwall</hi>, aged about <lb/>50, was in the Summer 1690, ſeized
            with violent Co- <lb/>lical Pains which he mitigated by Glyſters, but could <lb/>not
            perfectly free himſelf of them. About <hi rend="italic">Michaelmas</hi>
            <lb/>1691. his Pains being very violent, he was relieved by <lb/>the ſame Remedy; and by
            the perſuaſion of a skilful <lb/>Woman, he drank the Powder of Nettle-roots in
            <lb/>White Wine: After the firſt or ſecond Doſe he diſ- <lb/>charged a great quantity of
            Urine, with a very ſecu- <lb/>lent Sediment. About the beginning of <hi rend="italic"
              >November</hi> 1691. <lb/>being Coſtive, he eat Mallow roots and Corinths boil'd, <pb
              n="422"/>
            <lb/>and mixed with Butter, (his uſual Medicine to render <lb/>him Laxative.) In a
            little time after eating it, he was <lb/>much diſordered, and complained of an
            Oppreſſion by <lb/>Wind; at length the Wind (as he termed it) ſettled at <lb/>the bottom
            of his Belly, and in a very little time with <lb/>his Urine he emitted ſome of the
            Herbs, with above 40 <lb/>Corinths: A few Days after he piſs'd off ſeveral Parſley-
            <lb/>Leaves, which he had a little before eaten. I was cal- <lb/>led to him about the
            12th of <hi rend="italic">November</hi>, when his U- <lb/>rine being ſhewn me, I thought
            that part of his Excre- <lb/>ments had been evacuated that way, and that ſome La-
            <lb/>tent Ulcer had made a Paſſage through the <hi rend="italic">Inteſtinum
              <lb/>Rectum</hi> into the Bladder, but found it otherwiſe; for <lb/>there was no Fætor
            in the Urine, he had no <hi rend="italic">Teneſmus</hi>, <lb/>nor bloody, nor purulent
            Dejections; but to ſatisfy my <lb/>ſelf further in this Particular, I ordered him a
            Glyſter <lb/>tinctured with Indigo, which he retained above half an <lb/>hour, but his
            Urine was not at all diſcoloured with it. <lb/>I preſcribed Pills of —, two of which
            came off in his <lb/>Urine <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 18. in an oblong form, about
            the big- <lb/>neſs of the end of the firſt Quill in a Gooſe's Wing. The <lb/>Pills I
            have by me, except the half of one, which I rubb'd <lb/>abroad with my Fingers. Some
            time after he piſs'd off <lb/>a piece of a Raiſon. He lived 'till Midſummer 1692.
            <lb/>in which time he ejected at divers times parts of Roots, <lb/>and other things he
            eat. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>His Wife reſiſted all the Importunity that could be <lb/>made to have his Body
          diſſected: So that a great Secret <lb/>was buried with him. </p>
          <signed rend="italic">J. H. </signed></body>
      </floatingText>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Diemerbroeck</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Farfax</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >T. Bartholine</hi>, <hi rend="italic">O. Borichius</hi>, <hi rend="italic">N.
          <lb/>Blegny</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Mr. Pecquet</hi>, and others are of Opinion, that
        <lb/>there is a concealed Channel for the Urine to the Emul- <lb/>gents, <hi rend="italic"
          >&amp;c.</hi> than thoſe commonly ſuppoſed; and they <lb/>think it appears ſo by divers
        Phænomena, Experiments, <lb/>Eſſays, they have made, (though like the Head of <hi
          rend="italic">Nile</hi>
        <pb n="423"/>
        <lb/>it be yet concealed,) and that their Objections againſt the <lb/>common Opinion are
        inſuperable. Its certain the mat- <lb/>ter of an <hi rend="italic">Empyema</hi>, and the
        Corruptions in the Thorax <lb/>in penetrating Wounds thereof, have been piſs'd off, and
        <lb/>to that purpoſe Diureticks are uſed in Vulneraries, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        <lb/>See <hi rend="italic">Malpighius</hi>, <hi rend="italic">N. Blegny</hi>, Serjeant <hi
          rend="italic">Wiſeman</hi>, &amp;c. <lb/>And I have known a large ripe Apoſtumation in the
        <lb/>Thigh ſink ſuddenly, and all the Matter come away by <lb/>Urine from a Woman. Mr. <hi
          rend="italic">Leyſer</hi> hath the like Story <lb/>in his Obſervations. See the <hi
          rend="italic">Philoſ. Tr. No. 50.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I had once a Boy of about 6 Years old, brought me, <lb/>that piſſed off the moſt part
        of his Urine from an Orifice <lb/>in his Navel. I remember <hi rend="italic">Blaſius</hi>,
        or <hi rend="italic">Veſlingius</hi>, relates <lb/>the like, and accounts for it. </p>
      <space dim="vertical" quantity="2"> </space>
      <dateline rend="hanging">
        <lb/>Plimouth, March 9. <lb/>1707. </dateline>
      <signed rend="italic align-right space">
        <lb/>James Yonge </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
