<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Holbrooke, Stoole and Cole: An Abstract out of a Letter from Doctor W.
          Holbrooke to Dr. W. Cole, Concerning Stones Voided by Stoole. </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>W. Holbrooke, Stoole and W. Cole</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Abstract out of a Letter from Doctor W. Holbrooke of Manchester, to Dr. W.
              Cole, Fellow of the College of Physitians in London; Concerning Stones Voided by
              Stoole. With Dr. Cole's Answer to the Same</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for H. Clements, at the Half-Moon, and W. Innys at the
                  Princes-Armes, in St. Paul's Church-yard; and D. Brown, without Temple-Bar.
                </persName>
                </publisher>
              <date>1710-1711</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">27</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">28-32</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110354711</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1710.0005</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT27_0028">
    <body>
      <pb n="28"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">V.</hi> An Abſtract out of a Letter from Doctor <lb/><hi rend="roman"
          >W. Holbrooke</hi> of <hi rend="roman">Mancheſter</hi>, to Dr. <hi rend="roman">W.
          Cole</hi>, <lb/>Fellow of the College of Phyſitians in <hi rend="roman">London</hi>;
        <lb/>concerning Stones voided by Stoole. With Dr. <hi rend="roman">Cole</hi>'s <lb/>Anſwer
        to the ſame. </head>
      <div>
        <dateline rend="space align-right">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Mancheſter</hi>, September 4. 1700. </dateline>
        <salute rend="italic indent">
          <lb/>SIR, </salute>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> Muſt beg your Patience a while longer, and deſire <lb/>your
          Thoughts of what I think a remarkable Caſe. <lb/>One <hi rend="italic">Crumbleholm</hi>
          came to me ſometime ago, and com- <lb/>plain'd of a great loſs of Appetite, with
          Scorbutick Itch, <lb/>and ever and anon ſevere Convulſive Cholicks below <lb/>his Navel,
          all along the <hi rend="italic">Hypogaſtrium</hi>. They laſt not <lb/>above a quarter of
          an Hour, but often return, and raiſe <lb/>Tumours the bigneſs of a large Walnut, which
          diſap- <lb/>pear and remove as the Pain ſhifts. He has been trou- <lb/>bled with it ſome
          Years, and took Phyſick of almoſt <lb/>every one he met with; but, as far as I can
          perceive, <lb/>not in any regular Method, which gave me ſome hopes, <lb/>that I might
          relieve him. Accordingly I began with <lb/>mild Emollient and Carminative Glyſters; purged
          with <lb/><hi rend="italic">Decoct. Sen. Gereon. Syr. de Spin. cervin. &amp; Tinct.
            Sacr.</hi>
          <lb/>In the Intervals of the Purges I gave <hi rend="italic">Æthiops Mineral</hi>,
          <lb/>with bitter Decoctions Alterative, made more Carminative <lb/>with <hi rend="italic"
            >Rad. Zedoar.</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Caſtor</hi>. He was relieved for that
          <lb/>purpoſe; his Appetite and Complexion mended, but <lb/>preſently was as Ill as ever.
          Then he ſhow'd me the <lb/>Stones voided by Stoole, upon a ſlight Mercurial Purge,
          <lb/>which he took laſt <hi rend="italic">Eaſter</hi>. Upon opening one of them, <pb
            n="29"/>
          <lb/>I found he had ſwallowed either ſome Plumb or Apri- <lb/>cock Stones, which by their
          ſtay in the Inteſtines were <lb/>inclos'd in the Excrements, as I take it; and, by the
          <lb/>Purge being diſlodged from their <hi rend="italic">Sinus</hi>, ſent forth, as
          <lb/>you find. Hoping then that by ſtronger Evacuations, <lb/>if I could remove any other
          that might remain, it might <lb/>tend to his Cure, I order'd ſtronger Medicines, of which
          <lb/>the Bearer, who is my particular Friend, and was the <lb/>Apothecary, can give you a
          more particular Account: <lb/>However, I could not get any more from him; and he
          <lb/>being out of hopes, and uneaſy to be kept any longer <lb/>from his Buſineſs, has left
          off taking any thing. Laſt <lb/>Week I ſaw him, and found him much in the ſame
          <lb/>Condition, tho' ſomewhat weaker, and ſunk more in <lb/>his Fleſh. If you think by
          communicating this to any <lb/>of your Friends, or making tryals of the other Stone
          <lb/>untouch'd, you may be better ſatisfy'd in the Young <lb/>Man's Caſe, or may think of
          any thing that may con- <lb/>tribute to his Cure, pleaſe to ſignify it by the Bearer,
          <lb/>and you will mightily oblige, </p>
        <signed rend="italic align-right space">
          <lb/>Your very Humble <lb/>And Obedient Servant, <lb/><hi rend="roman">W. Holbrooke. </hi>
        </signed>
      </div>
      <pb n="30"/>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="roman">Cole</hi>'s Anſwer to the foregoing Letter. </head>
        <salute rend="italic indent space">
          <lb/>Dear Sir, </salute>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> Received yours by Mr. <hi rend="italic">Harriſon</hi>,
          together with your <lb/>very obliging Preſent, the two <hi rend="italic">Human
            Bezoars</hi>, (if <lb/>I may ſo call them;) but have as yet had little opportu-
          <lb/>nity of having the Opinion of many Phyſitians here <lb/>concerning them: One very
          Ingenious Gentleman, to <lb/>whom I ſhowed them, was an Acquaintance of yours, <lb/>Mr <hi
            rend="italic">Roger Kennion</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Cambridge</hi>, who went on <hi
            rend="italic">Monday</hi>
          <lb/>laſt for <hi rend="italic">France</hi>, who with Dr. <hi rend="italic">Hobart</hi>,
          as alſo Dr <hi rend="italic">Sloane</hi>, <lb/>admire them. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And now, <hi rend="italic">Sir</hi>, as to the latter part of your Letter; <lb/>I
          look upon theſe Stones to be not formed of <hi rend="italic">adhering
          <lb/>Excrements</hi>, as you ſeem to ſuppoſe, but to be made <lb/>thus. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When the Plumb-Stones happen to be included in a <lb/>fit Glandulous Receptacle, I
          conceive they may come to <lb/>be thus coated over by the viſcous Liquor ſecreted out
          <lb/>of the Secretory Ducts of thoſe Glandules, which by <lb/>long lying there may come to
          acquire ſo great a Bulk, <lb/>by the continual appulſe of the ſame Liquor. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This Receptacle I gueſs to be the <hi rend="italic">Inteſtinum cæcum</hi>,
          <lb/>which, tho' ſmall naturally, may be, as other Membra- <lb/>nous and Glandulous Parts
          are, capable of a conſidera- <lb/>ble Extenſion: So that, when by reaſon of the <hi
            rend="italic">Periſtal- <lb/>tick</hi> Motion of the <hi rend="italic">Inteſtines</hi>
          above, one of the Plumb- <lb/>Stones may happen to be, by its pointed Extremity, in-
          <lb/>truded; the whole may, by the ſame repeated, tho' <lb/>ſlow Motion, dilate the Cavity
          ſo, that the whole Body <lb/>of the Stone may by the ſame Method be ſtill farther <lb/>and
          farther protruded, till it come to the further Extre- <lb/>mity; which being cloſed, muſt
          be preſumed to detain <lb/>it there, ſince 'tis hard to conceive it can quickly get <pb
            n="31"/>
          <lb/>out again, that <hi rend="italic">Periſtaltick</hi> Motion being always for-
          <lb/>ward. One of theſe Stones being thus enter'd, 'tis eaſy <lb/>to conceive more may be
          admitted, ſince the firſt can- <lb/>not but dilate the Paſſage for another that follows,
          and <lb/>ſo on till the Cavity be full. Whilſt theſe Stones lye <lb/>there, they muſt be
          conceived to offend the part, as <lb/>having extended it beyond its Natural State: So that
          <lb/>the Secretory Ducts of the Gland, of which the inner <lb/>Coat of that, as well as
          the reſt of the Inteſtines, is <lb/>conſtituted, muſt be proportionally dilated; whereby
          <lb/>an eaſier way is made for the Liquor, they ſeparate, to <lb/>be excreted. This being
          of a viſcid and concreſcible <lb/>Nature, muſt, ſince it cannot get forth, be preſum'd to
          <lb/>adhere to the <hi rend="italic">Subſtratum</hi>, the Stones, and ſo by degrees
          <lb/>Incruſt them; which Cruſt by the long confinement <lb/>muſt grow ſo much thicker, for
          the ſame reaſon as it <lb/>began, the Ducts being kept conſtantly open, and the
          <lb/>Cavity more and more dilated the greater the Incruſta- <lb/>tion is. So that I
          conceive the Symptoms are eaſily <lb/>accountable for, from the offence given to the part,
          <lb/>which being ſenſible, as all membranous and fibrous <lb/>Parts are, the Pain muſt
          grow greater, the greater the <lb/>Extenſion is; and the change of the Poſture of the
          <lb/>Tumor may very well be conceived to proceed from <lb/>the different Poſtures the
          Inteſtines put on, by the Chyle <lb/>or Excrements paſſing along them, and ſometimes fill-
          <lb/>ing one part, ſometimes another, as they are protruded <lb/>further and further,
          their Lubricity on the Surface, <lb/>length, and confinement obviouſly favouring that <hi
            rend="italic">Phæ- <lb/>nomenon</hi>. I am of Opinion, the true <hi rend="italic">Bezoar
            Stones</hi> are <lb/>form'd in the Beaſts, that yield them, in the ſame man- <lb/>ner;
          but whether their Stomachs or Inteſtines have o- <lb/>ther Cavities capable of receiving
          and retaining them to <lb/>their full growth, is to be determined by Anatomy. <lb/>This I
          think is certain, that all of them have either a <lb/>Straw, Stick, or other Subſtance
          different from the Ex- <pb n="32"/>
          <lb/>terior Matter, which we call the Stone, in the middle <lb/>of them; and thence I
          conclude the manner of their <lb/>formation to be the ſame. From the continuance of
          <lb/>his Symptoms, I believe there may be more behind; <lb/>and cannot think any other
          Method more likely to ex- <lb/>trude them, than by having his <hi rend="italic"
            >Abdomen</hi> well anointed <lb/>with ſome Emollient Oyles or Liniments, and very well
          <lb/>agitated backward and forward as much and as long as <lb/>he can bear, and this both
          Morning and Evening: <lb/>After a little while, that the Stones may be preſum'd <lb/>by
          this agitation to be ſomewhat diſlodged, ſome gentle <lb/>Purgatives I conceive may be of
          uſe to be now and then <lb/>given to carry them downwards, and with all Emolli- <lb/>ent
          Glyſters to ſollicit it gently, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <signed rend="italic align-right">
          <lb/>W. Cole. </signed>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
