<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Derham: The Case of a Woman Big with Child, Who Recovered of the
          Small-Pox</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>W. Derham</persName>
            </author>
            <title>The Case of a Woman Big with Child, Who Recovered of the Small-Pox, and Was
              Afterwards Delivered of a Dead Child Full of the Pustules of That Distemper. In a
              Letter from the Reverend Mr. W. Derham, F. R. S. to Dr. Hans Sloane, S. R.
              Secr.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for D. Brown, in Exeter Exchange, H. Clements, at the
                  Half-Moon, and W. Innys at the Princes-Armes, in St. Paul's Church-yard.
                </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1712-1713</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">28</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">165-166</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO"/>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1713.0017</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT28_0165">
    <body>
      <pb n="165"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XVII.</hi> The Caſe of a Woman big with Child, who <lb/>recovered of
        the <hi rend="roman">Small-Pox</hi>, and was afterwards <lb/>delivered of a dead Child full
        of the Puſtules of <lb/>that Diſtemper. In a Letter from the Reverend <lb/><hi rend="roman"
          >Mr. W. Derham, F. R. S.</hi> to <hi rend="roman">Dr. Hans Sloane, <lb/>S. R. Secr.</hi>
      </head>
      <dateline rend="space align-center">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Upminſter</hi>, October 7. 1713 </dateline>
      <salute rend="indent italic">
        <lb/>SIR, </salute>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HERE was, in the Pariſh next me, a Great-bellied <lb/>Woman who
        had the Small-Pox, and was pretty <lb/>well recovered, ſo that ſhe was able to take
        ſomething <lb/>to Purge her after it: And on <hi rend="italic">Auguſt</hi> 30. laſt, ſhe
        took a <lb/>Purge (I know not what) which did not work; and on <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >September</hi> the 1<hi rend="italic">ſt</hi>, another Purge, which gave her only <lb/>a
        Stool or two. Upon which, <hi rend="italic">September</hi> the 3d, ſhe <lb/>took another
        ſtronger Purge, that work'd ſo violently <lb/>upwards and downwards, that ſhe fell into
        Faintings <lb/>and Convulſions: about which time I conceive her Child <lb/>within her died,
        but of which ſhe was not deliver'd till <lb/><hi rend="italic">September</hi> the 8<hi
          rend="italic">th</hi>. The Child was a Female, and in ap- <lb/>pearance well made, luſty
        and ſtrong. At its Delivery, <lb/>the Midwife judged it had been dead five or ſix Days; ſo
        <lb/>that the Belly was burſt, and the Bowels came out, and <lb/>the whole Body was
        inclining to be rotten. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But that which ſeem'd moſt remarkable to me, and <lb/>indeed occaſioned me to take
        Notice of the Caſe, was, <lb/>That the Child was very full of the Small Pox, ſo full,
        <lb/>that the Midwife ſaid, hardly a Pins head could be put <lb/>between the Bliſters, which
        were very Plump, and full <pb n="166"/>
        <lb/>of Matter, like the Puſtules of an Adult, when the Small- <lb/>Pox is at the Height,
        only a little depreſſed in the mid- <lb/>dle. But as full as the Child was, the Mother had
        as few, <lb/>and very favourably; her Child, I ſuppoſe, undergoing <lb/>that which would
        have been more ſevere upon her. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having thus related the Caſe to you, as the Midwife <lb/>told it me, I ſhall leave it
        to you, and ſuch good Judges <lb/>as your ſelf, to determine theſe two Things, </p>
      <p rend="hanging space">
        <lb/>I: When a Woman hath the Small-Pox in Pregnancy, <lb/>Whether it be likely that the
        Child ſhould be in dan- <lb/>ger of catching and having that Diſtemper after its <lb/>Birth? </p>
      <p rend="hanging space">
        <lb/>II. Whether the Child I have been ſpeaking of, had the <lb/>Small-Pox at the very ſame
        time the Mother had it, <lb/>and not rather afterwards, by reaſon the Child was <lb/>full of
        it ſome time after the Mother was well reco- <lb/>vered? </p>
      <p rend="indent indentall">
        <lb/>I am inclined to think, that the great Flux and <lb/>tendency of the Blood to the Child
        in the Womb, <lb/>might draw in the Humour, and prevent the greater <lb/>Eruption of the
        Small-Pox in the Mother; and that <lb/>for want of a due Expence thereof, the remainder af-
        <lb/>terwards broke out in the Child, and that the Child <lb/>really had it after the
        Mother; Nature making the <lb/>Diſcharges upon the Child which were not compleat- <lb/>ed on
        the Mother. But I fear I ſhall need your Par- <lb/>don for preſuming to interpoſe my
        Judgment before <lb/>ſo great a Judge— </p>
      <signed>I am, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="sc space align-right">W. Derham. </hi>
      </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
