<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Douglass: Observations on the Glands in the Human Spleen</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>J. Douglass</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Observations on the Glands in the Human Spleen; And on a Fracture in the upper
              Part of the Thigh-Bone. By J. Douglass, M.D. and R. S. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for W. Innys, at the Princes-Arms in St. Paul's
                  Church-Yard.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1714-1716</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">29</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">499-502</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110042474</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1714.0064</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT29_0499">
    <body>
      <pb n="499"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VIII.</hi> Obſervations on the <hi rend="roman">Glands</hi> in the
        Human <lb/><hi rend="roman">Spleen</hi>; and on a Fracture in the upper part of the <lb/><hi
          rend="roman">Thigh-bone</hi>. By <hi rend="roman">J. Douglaſs</hi>, <hi rend="roman">M.
          D.</hi> and <hi rend="roman">R. S. S.</hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>Hat Anatomy, as well as Phyſick and Surgery, has <lb/>received
        much improvement from a careful and <lb/>true obſervation of what was found in the
        Diſſection of <pb n="500"/>
        <lb/>morbid Bodies, will appear from the two following In- <lb/>ſtances, among many more
        that might be adduced for <lb/>that purpoſe. For it is certain, that nothing has contri-
        <lb/>buted ſo much towards forming a right Notion of the <lb/>Nature of the ſeveral
        Diſeaſes, and a true knowledge of <lb/>the Structure of many Parts of the Human Body, as
        <lb/>their appearance in a preternatural State. </p>
      <div>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>My firſt Obſervation is of the Glands viſible to the na- <lb/>ked Eye, that appear
          diſperſed thro' the Fibrous Subſtance <lb/>of the Human <hi rend="italic">Spleen</hi>. The
          Subject I found them in, <lb/>was a Boy of about 4 or 5 Years old, that died of a
          <lb/>general <hi rend="italic">Atrophy</hi>, or Conſumption of all the Muſcular
          <lb/>Fleſhy Parts of the Body, occaſioned without all doubt <lb/>from the numerous
          Glandulous Swellings ſcattered up and <lb/>down the whole Meſentery; which by compreſſing
          the <lb/>Lymphatick Veſſels, called in this place <hi rend="italic">Vaſa lactea</hi>, pre-
          <lb/>vented the acceſs and ſupply of the Chyle, ſo neceſſary <lb/>for the continued
          nouriſhment and increaſe of the Parts. <lb/>For without the conſtant Recruit of this
          whitiſh Balſamick <lb/>Liquor, the Maſs of Blood will in a ſhort time be unfit <lb/>to
          perform any of thoſe goof Offices, which a freſh ac- <lb/>ceſſion of Chyle qualifies it
          for. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In a piece of this <hi rend="italic">Spleen</hi> we might ſee, without the
          <lb/>aſſiſtance of a Glaſs, ſeveral round whitiſh Bodies of a <lb/>pretty hard
          Conſiſtence, and abundance of ſmall white <lb/>and ſofter ſpecks; but both of the ſame
          nature. Theſe, <lb/>to me at leaſt, appear to be ſo many diſtinct Glands be- <lb/>come
          viſible; which in a Natural State are only to be <lb/>ſeen by a fine Glaſs, as the curious
            <hi rend="italic">Malpighius</hi> firſt obſer- <lb/>ved. <hi rend="italic">Vid.</hi> his
          Treatiſe de <hi rend="italic">Liene, Cap. <hi rend="roman">V.</hi> De quihuſdam cor-
            <lb/>poribus per Lienem diſperſis</hi>. <q rend="italic">Minimæ hæ glandulæ </q>, ſays
          he, <lb/>
          <q rend="italic">non æque facile ſeſe produnt in quocunque animalium Liene: i- <lb/>mo
            ſolâ Lienis laceratione innoteſcun <gap reason="illegible"/>n Bove, Ove, <hi
              rend="roman">&amp;c.</hi> In Ho- <lb/>mine vero difficilius emergunt: ſi tamen ex
            morbo univerſum <lb/>glandularum genus turgeat, manifeſtiones
              <unclear>redduntur</unclear>, aucta <pb n="501"/>
            <lb/>ipſarum magnitudine, ut in defuncta puella obſervavi: in <lb/>quâ Lien globulis
            conſpicuis racematim diſperſis totus ſcatebat. </q>
          <lb/>Which Caſe was the very ſame with mine. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The ſecond Obſervation. We had ſtill been in the <lb/>Dark, about the nature of a
          Luxation of the Head of the <lb/>Thigh Bone, had we not carefully examined the Part in
          <lb/>the dead Body. For by that ſort of enquiry, the com- <lb/>mon miſtake of Surgeons was
          detected, and what was <lb/>eſteemed and treated by them as a Luxation of the Head <lb/>of
          the <hi rend="italic">Femur</hi>, was diſcover'd to be nothing elſe but a <lb/>Fracture of
          the ſame Bone, near its Neck; the globular <lb/>Head being ſtill retained cloſe in its own
          Socket, called the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Acetabulum Coxendicis</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Amongſt all the Writers of Surgery and Anatomy, I <lb/>know but three that were
          appriſed of this miſtake: the <lb/>firſt was <hi rend="italic">Ambroſe Paree</hi>, the
          ſecond Dr. <hi rend="italic">Ruyſch</hi> at <hi rend="italic">Amſter- <lb/>dam</hi>, and
          Mr. <hi rend="italic">Cheſelden</hi>, a Member of the <hi rend="italic">Royal
          Society</hi>; <lb/>whoſe Obſervations on this Subject I intend to commu- <lb/>nicate at
          another time, together with an account of the <lb/>true Structure of this Joint; in which
          I will conſider the <lb/>depth of the Articulation; the wonderful ſtrength of the
          <lb/>Muſcles that ſurround it; the many ſtrong ligaments that <lb/>bind the Head within
          the Socket; the ſmallneſs of the <lb/>Neck of the Bone; its poreous and ſpungy Subſtance,
          <lb/>which makes it much weaker than the reſt; and laſt of <lb/>all the diſadvantageous
          oblique poſition of this Neck, <lb/>which expoſes it the more to outward accidents. From
          <lb/>a review of ſuch like Conſiderations, it will plainly appear <lb/>that a Fracture can
          much more eaſily happen, than a Diſlo- <lb/>cation in that Part from an external Cauſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This <hi rend="italic">Os femoris</hi> belonged to an old Woman turn'd of
          <lb/>Fourſcore, who only fell from her Chair whereon ſhe was <lb/>ſitting, and thereby
          ſuffered this breach of continuity in <lb/>the Subſtance of the Bone. She lived three
          Weeks after <lb/>it; and tho' it never was reduc'd, yet ſhe complained of <pb n="502"/>
          <lb/>very little or no pain, which may ſeem very extraordinary. <lb/>It is obſervable that
          the Fracture is not only Oblique, near <lb/>the Neck of the Bone; but that each <hi
            rend="italic">Trochanter</hi>, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the <lb/>two <hi
            rend="italic">proceſſes</hi> near its <hi rend="italic">Cervix</hi>, are likewiſe broke
          ſhort off; <lb/>and that they were both drawn up almoſt as high as the <lb/>Head of the
          Bone it ſelf, by the ſtrong contraction of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Glutei</hi> and
          other Muſcles. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
