<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Jurin: An Account of Some Experiments Relating to the Specifick
          Gravity of Human Blood</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>James Jurin</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of Some Experiments Relating to the Specifick Gravity of Human Blood.
              By James Jurin, M. D. and F. R. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for W. and J. Innys, at the Princes-Arms, at the West
                  Corner of St. Paul's Church-Yard.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1717-1719</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">30</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">1000-1014</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110355615</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1717.0060</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT30_1000">
    <body>
      <pb n="1000"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">III.</hi> An Account of ſome Experiments relating to the
        <lb/>Specifick Gravity of Human Blood. By <hi rend="roman">James <lb/>Jurin</hi>, <hi
          rend="roman">M. D.</hi> and <hi rend="roman">F. R. S.</hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>T is well known from the Obſervations of Mr. <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Leeuwenhoek</hi> and others, that Human Blood conſiſts <lb/>of red globular
        Particles, ſwimming in a pellucid <hi rend="italic">Lym- <lb/><choice>
            <corr>pha</corr>
            <sic>pba</sic>
          </choice></hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>. Which two different Subſtances, tho'
        <lb/>of unequal Specifick Gravities, yet ſo long as they con- <lb/>tinue to circulate in the
        Veins and Arteries, are pre- <lb/>vented from ſeparating by their Motion and Warmth.
        <lb/>But when the Blood comes to ſtagnate and cool in a <lb/>Porringer, the globular
        Particles uniting together by <lb/>their attractive Power, and ſinking by their Weight,
        <lb/>which is greater than that of the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>, form the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Coagulum</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Craſſamentum</hi>, at the bottom of the
        Por- <lb/>ringer, the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> ſwimming above it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Things always happen in this manner, when the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Craſſamentum</hi>
        is at liberty to ſubſide: but it often falls <lb/>out, that, either by its adheſion to the
        ſides of the <lb/>Veſſel, or by the bubbles of Air, which the Blood <pb n="1001"/>
        <lb/>gathers upon falling into the Porringer, and which <lb/>ſtick to it's Surface, the <hi
          rend="italic">Craſſamentum</hi> is kept from ſink- <lb/>ing, and ſeems to float upon the
        top of the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe Accidents ſeem to have given the firſt occa- <lb/>ſion to that Opinion, which, I
        think, has been gene- <lb/>rally entertain'd by thoſe who have writ upon this <lb/>Subject,
        namely, that the globular part of the Blood <lb/>is ſpecifically lighter than the <hi
          rend="italic">Serum</hi>, in which it <lb/>ſwims. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But that which has ſo fully eſtabliſht this perſua- <lb/>ſion, is the <choice>
          <corr>Authority</corr>
          <sic>Authotity</sic>
        </choice> of the late excellent Mr. <hi rend="italic">Boyle</hi>, <lb/>who, among the many
        valuable and curious Experi- <lb/>ments he has given us in his Natural Hiſtory of Human
        <lb/>Blood, has left the following ones upon this Subject. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſpecifick Gravity of <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> of Human Blood <lb/>was found by
        weighing a piece of Sealing Wax firſt in <lb/><hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>, and afterwards
        in Water, to be the ſpecifick <lb/>Gravity of Water, as 1024 to 1000. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In a ſecond Experiment, which for greater accuracy <lb/>was made with an Inſtrument
        contriv'd on purpoſe, <lb/>the ſpecifick Gravity of <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> was found
        to be to that of <lb/>Water, as 1194 to 1000. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In a third Experiment made by the ſame Inſtru- <lb/>ment, and with <hi rend="italic"
          >Serum</hi> from the Blood of another Per- <lb/>ſon, it's ſpecifick Gravity appear'd to be
        1186. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Medium between theſe two laſt Experiments is <lb/>1190, which has ſince been
        univerſally receiv'd for the <lb/>ſpecifick Gravity of <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> of Human
        Blood, the firſt <lb/>Experiment being declar'd by Mr. <hi rend="italic">Boyle</hi> himſelf
        to be <lb/>leſs exactly made than the other. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſpecifick Gravity of Human Blood was found <lb/>by Mr. <hi rend="italic"
        >Boyle</hi>, to be to that of Water, as 1040 to 1000; <lb/>though on account of difficulties
        by him mention'd, <lb/>he was far from being ſatisfy'd with this Experiment, <lb/>and
        recommended the thing to farther tryals. </p>
      <pb n="1002"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe Experiments however having hitherto paſt <lb/>uncontroverted, and it appearing
        from them, that the <lb/>ſpecifick Gravity of <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> was greater than
        that of <lb/>Blood in the proportion of 1190 to 1040, or of 8 <lb/>to 7 nearly; it was a
        neceſſary conſequence of this, <lb/>that the Blood Globules were ſpecifically lighter than
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>, and that in a very great degree, conſide- <lb/>ring
        the ſmall proportion that the bulk of the <hi rend="italic">Craſſa- <lb/>mentum</hi> was
        found to bear to that of the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>, from <lb/>other Experiments. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From this it was not improbably conjectured, that <lb/>theſe Globules were thin
        Veſicles fill'd with an Aereal <lb/>ſubſtance: and this Opinion ſeem'd to receive a great
        <lb/>confirmation, upon it's being obſerv'd, in viewing the <lb/>Circulation by a
        Microſcope, that a Blood Globule, in <lb/>paſſing through a very narrow Veſſel, would change
        <lb/>its ſhape from a Globular to an Oval Form, and would <lb/>recover it's former Figure,
        as ſoon as it was got thro' <lb/>the narrow Paſſage; which appearance ſeem'd to be na-
        <lb/>turally accounted for from the Elaſticity of the included <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Aura</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon this conjecture have been built a great many <lb/>Solutions of the Phænomena
        obſervable in the Animal <lb/>Oeconomy, and the diſorders of it; particularly a late
        <lb/>ingenious account of Muſcular Motion. It <choice>
          <corr>is</corr>
          <sic>it</sic>
        </choice> not my <lb/>buſineſs at preſent to examine any of theſe, nor is it <lb/>my deſign
        to caſt any reflection upon their Authors, <lb/>who were led into this miſtake by the
        natural conſe- <lb/>quence of a matter of Fact, for the thruth of which they <lb/>had ſo
        great an Authority, as that of the excellent Per- <lb/>ſon above-mentioned. But I hope, I
        ſhall eaſily be <lb/>pardon'd for enquiring into the ſoundneſs of the <lb/>Foundation, when
        the Superſtructure erected thereupon <lb/>is ſo conſiderable; and the following Experiments,
        <lb/>however trivial in themſelves, will not appear unworthy <pb n="1003"/>
        <lb/>the conſideration of the <hi rend="italic">Royal Society</hi>, if it be found,
        <lb/>that they may prevent us from running into Errors of <lb/>the greateſt conſequence. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Exp.</hi> I. I have ſeveral times cut off a ſmall part <lb/>of the
          <hi rend="italic">Craſſamentum</hi>, when by its adheſion to the ſides <lb/>of the
        Porringer it has ſeem'd to ſwim upon the Sur- <lb/>face of the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>,
        and have put it into another Veſ- <lb/>ſel fill'd with <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>: upon
        which it has immediately <lb/>ſunk to the Bottom. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Exp.</hi> II. When the <hi rend="italic">Coagulum</hi> has been buoyd
        up in <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> by the bubbles of Air adhering to its Sur-
        <lb/>face, I have ſeparated a ſmall part of it where thoſe <lb/>Bubbles have been thickeſt,
        and put in into a Glaſs of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>, in which it has ſwom, as
        before. Then ſetting <lb/>the Glaſs upon the Air-Pump, thoſe Bubbles burſt af- <lb/>ter one
        another, as the Receiver was exhauſting, and <lb/>the Air being again let into the Receiver,
        the lump <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Craſſamentum</hi> ſunk to the bottom of the Glaſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Exp.</hi> III. I have often placed a drop of <hi rend="italic"
          >Serum</hi> upon <lb/>a clean Glaſs before a Microſcope, in which I had <lb/>diſſolv'd a
        very ſmall quantity of Blood, and obſerv'd, <lb/>that when the Glaſs was held in a
        perpendicular Po- <lb/>ſture, the Blood-Globules ſubſided to the bottom of <lb/>the Drop;
        and inverting the Glaſs, the Globules again <lb/>deſcended thro' the <hi rend="italic"
          >Serum</hi> to the Bottom. I had the <lb/>ſame ſucceſs with a ſmall quantity of <hi
          rend="italic">Serum</hi> and <lb/>Blood in a Capillary Tube. And the ſame thing has
        <lb/>been long ſince obſerv'd by the famous Mr. <hi rend="italic">Leeuwen- <lb/>hoek</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe Experiments undeniably demonſtrate, that the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Craſſamentum</hi>, or globular part of the Blood, is ſpecifi- <lb/>cally heavier than the
          <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>; and conſequently it is <lb/>by no means probable, that the
        Blood Globules are <lb/>Veſicles fill'd with Air, or any other Fluid lighter than <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Serum</hi>. And that they are not fill'd with any ſort of <pb n="1004"/>
        <lb/>Elaſtick Fluid, will appear from the following Experi- <lb/>ment. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Exp.</hi> IV. In a ſmall quantity of <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> of
        Human <lb/>Blood, I diſſolv'd ſo much Blood, as that the Globules <lb/>might not lye too
        thick together, to hinder their being <lb/>ſeen diſtinctly. Then having lodged a ſmall drop
        of <lb/>this Liquor on the inſide of a thin Glaſs Tube, I fitted <lb/>the Tube on to the
        Air-Pump, and placed a Microſ- <lb/>cope by it, ſo that I could ſee the Blood-Globules
        <lb/>through the Tube. This being done, I caus'd the <lb/>Tube to be exhauſted, keeping my
        Eye upon the Glo- <lb/>bules all the time, in order to obſerve whether they <lb/>dilated
        themſelves, as the Air was withdrawn; but <lb/>could not perceive the leaſt alteration, they
        appearing <lb/>exactly of the ſame bigneſs in the <hi rend="italic">Vacuum</hi>, as they
        <lb/>had done before. Whereas if they had been fill'd with <lb/>an Elaſtick Fluid, they
        would either have burſt, or <lb/>have been dilated to at leaſt 70 or 80 times their
        <lb/>former Magnitude. The Stop-cock being afterwards <lb/>turn'd, and the Air ſuffer'd to
        re-enter the Tube, the <lb/>Blood-Globules ſtill retain'd the ſame bigneſs, as in <hi
          rend="italic">Vacuo</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To this it will perhaps be objected, that a learned <lb/>Member of this Society, in a
        Book lately publiſh'd, has <lb/>aſſerted the direct contrary to what I here affirm, and
        <lb/>has aſſur'd us, that the Blood-Globules in an exhauſted <lb/>Receiver, inſtantly ſwell,
        and dilate themſelves ſo, as <lb/>to become incredibly large. But as that Gentleman
        <lb/>does not tell us, upon what Experiment this aſſertion <lb/>is grounded, it may not be
        unreaſonable to ſuppoſe, <lb/>that he was miſled by the common Hypotheſis, which <lb/>he
        there maintains, of the Blood-Globules being fill'd <lb/>with Air, and by what he has heard
        of ſeen of the <lb/>bubbles of Air, which ariſe from Blood in the Air Pump in <lb/>the ſame
        manner as from other Liquors, and which not <lb/>eaſily breaking out from ſo viſcid a Fluid,
        occaſion <pb n="1005"/>
        <lb/>the appearance he mentions. However this may be <lb/>to prevent any diſpute, and avoid
        the coming to <lb/><hi rend="italic">Utri creditis, Quirites?</hi> I ſhall offer a
        Teſtimony, that <lb/>every body will be ſatisfy'd with, namely that of the <lb/>learned and
        ingenious Mr. <hi rend="italic">Machin</hi>, Profeſſor of <hi rend="italic">Aſtro-
          <lb/>nomy</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Greſham Colledge</hi>, and one of our Secretaries,
        <lb/>who having honour'd me with his Company at a re- <lb/>petition of this Experiment, in
        order to be witneſs to <lb/>the Event, was fully ſatisfied upon repeated tryals, <lb/>that
        there was no perceivable difference between the <lb/>Magnitude of the Blood Globules in the
        Air, and in <lb/><hi rend="italic">Vacuo</hi>. Upon this occaſion the two firſt Experiments
        <lb/>were likewiſe repeated in his preſence, with the ſame <lb/>Succeſs, as above related. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Though what has been already ſaid is a ſufficient <lb/>proof of the Opinion
        above-mention'd, yet however <lb/>to prevent the Objections, which may ariſe for want
        <lb/>of Experiments made in the ſame manner with Mr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Boyle</hi>'s, as
        well as for the ſatisfaction of the Curious, <lb/>who may be deſirous to know the true
        Specifick Gra- <lb/>vities of <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> and Blood, I ſhall proceed to
        demon- <lb/>ſtrate the ſame thing by Hydroſtatical Experiments. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Exp.</hi> V. <hi rend="italic">Novemb.</hi> 13. 1713. Having ſuffer'd
        a quan- <lb/>tity of my own Blood to ſtand about 24 Hours in <lb/>the Porringer, and then
        drawing off the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> carefully <lb/>with a ſmall <hi rend="italic"
          >Siphon</hi> into a convenient Glaſs, I found <lb/>by the Hydroſtatical Balance it's
        Specifick Gravity to <lb/>be to that of Water, as 1029,8 to 1000. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Exp.</hi> VI. <hi rend="italic">Feb.</hi> 21. 1716-7. I examin'd the
          <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>
        <lb/>from the Blood of another Perſon in the ſame manner <lb/>and found it's Specifick
        Gravity to be 1028,6. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Exp.</hi> VII. VIII. and IX. <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 8th, 1717.
        I obtain'd <lb/>three ſeveral quantities of <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> from the Blood of
        <lb/>different Perſons. The firſt of theſe was of a deep <pb n="1006"/>
        <lb/>Colour, inclining ſomething to red, and a little Turbid. <lb/>It's Specifick Gravity
        was 1029,7. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſecond was likewiſe a little Turbid, and of a <lb/>pale whitiſh Colour. The
        Specifick Gravity of this <lb/>was 1030,2. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The third quantity of <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> was perfectly clear, and <lb/>of the
        colour of Canary. It's Specifick Gravity was <lb/>found to be 1030. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Though theſe five ſeveral Experiments were all care- <lb/>fully made, and with a
        balance whoſe accuracy I was <lb/>well aſſur'd of, yet for farther Evidence, I thought it
        <lb/>proper to make that which follows, after another man- <lb/>ner. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Exp.</hi> X. <hi rend="italic">Jan.</hi> 15th. 1718-9. I drew off all
        the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> from five or ſix ſeveral Porringers, containing the
        <lb/>Blood of different Perſons. This I found to be a lit- <lb/>tle tinged with Blood, which
        was occaſion'd by my <lb/>being oblig'd to draw it off pretty near to the bottom <lb/>of the
        Porringers, in order to obtain a quantity ſuffi- <lb/>cient for my purpoſe. For this reaſon
        I ſuffer'd it to <lb/>ſtand about two Days, in which time the Globular <lb/>part of the
        Blood was entirely precipitated to the Bot- <lb/>tom, and the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>
        was become perfectly fine and <lb/>tranſparent. I then drew it off with a <hi rend="italic"
          >Siphon</hi> into a <lb/>Glaſs Vial with a narrow Neck, which I fill'd to a <lb/>certain
        mark made in the Neck for that purpoſe. <lb/>This done, I plac'd my Vial in a nice pair of
        Scales, <lb/>in which I had a counterpoiſe for the weight of the <lb/>Vial, and found that
        quantity of <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> to weigh <lb/>2284¼ Grains. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Then pouring out the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>, I fill'd the Vial with <lb/>common
        Water to the ſame mark, and found the <lb/>weight of the Water to be 2219 Grains. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From which it follows, that the Specifick Gravity <lb/>of this <hi rend="italic"
          >Serum</hi> was 1029,4. </p>
      <pb n="1007"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Exp.</hi> XI. <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 14. 1719. I procur'd a
        quantity <lb/>of Blood taken from the temporal Artery, from which <lb/>I drew off the <hi
          rend="italic">Serum</hi> the next Day, and weighing it <lb/>in the ſame manner found it's
        Specifick Gravity to be <lb/>1028,8. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe Experiments agree ſo nearly together, that <lb/>the little difference between
        them may very well be <lb/>attributed to that which is between the <hi rend="italic"
          >Serum</hi> of dif- <lb/>ferent Perſons; or to the variations occaſion'd by heat <lb/>and
        cold in the ſeveral Seaſons of the Year, in which <lb/>they were made. So that from them we
        may ſafely <lb/>determine the Specifick Gravity of <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> of Human
        <lb/>Blood at a Medium to be 1029,5, or in a round num- <lb/>ber 1030. From which the
        greateſt Variation in any <lb/>of theſe Experiments is little more than one in 1000;
        <lb/>whereas the difference between Mr. <hi rend="italic">Boyle</hi>'s Experiments <lb/>and
        mine amounts to 160 in 1000. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Exp.</hi> XII. <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 6. 1717. In order to find
        the <lb/>Specifick Gravity of Human Blood, which, by reaſon <lb/>of it's tenacity, and
        ſudden alterations upon ſtanding, <lb/>cannot be determin'd by the Hydroſtatical Balance; I
        <lb/>took a narrow-neck'd Vial, and fill'd it to a Mark, <lb/>with Blood pour'd immediately
        out of the Porringer, <lb/>as ſoon as the Perſon was blooded. This I weigh'd, <lb/>as I had
        done the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> before, and found it's Speci- <lb/>fick Gravity to be
        1051. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Exp.</hi> XIII. <hi rend="italic">Aug.</hi> 5th. 1717. Having fill'd
        the ſame <lb/>Vial with the Blood of another Perſon, running im- <lb/>mediately out of the
        Vein through a Funnel, it's Spe- <lb/>cifick Gravity was determin'd at 1053. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Suffering this to ſtand till it was cold, I found the <lb/>Blood was ſunk a ſmall
        matter below the Mark in the <lb/>neck of the Vial. This being fill'd up with the Wa-
        <lb/>ter, which in ſo ſmall a quantity could make no ſenſi- <pb n="1008"/>
        <lb/>ble difference from Blood, I found the Specifick Gra- <lb/>vity of cold Blood to be
        1055. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Exp.</hi> XIV. <hi rend="italic">Aug. 6th.</hi> 1718. The laſt
        Experiment <lb/>being repeated in the ſame manner as the Year be- <lb/>fore, the Specifick
        Gravity of cold Blood was again <lb/>found to 1055. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Exp.</hi> XV. <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 14th. 1719. The Arterial
        Blood, <lb/>from which the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> was afterwards drawn off for the
        <lb/>11th Experiment, being weigh'd in the ſame manner, <lb/>it's Specifick Gravity was
        1052,5. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As this Arterial Blood and it's <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>, differ no more <lb/>in
        Specifick Gravity from Venal Blood and <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>, <lb/>than the ſeveral
        Portions of theſe do from one ano- <lb/>ther, it's plain, that the difference in this
        reſpect be- <lb/>tween Arterial and Venal Blood is wholly inconſide- <lb/>rable. The Animal
        Oeconomy indeed teaches us, <lb/>that the <hi rend="italic">Serous</hi> Liquor is
        perpetually drawing off <lb/>from the Arterial Blood by the ſeveral Secretions, but <lb/>as
        the quantity ſeparated in one Circulation is very <lb/>ſmall, the Blood muſt arrive in the
        Veins nearly of <lb/>the ſame denſity, as when it runs through the Arte- <lb/>ries. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the 13th Experiment we obſerv'd, that the Blood <lb/>alter'd it's Specifick Gravity
        upon cooling from 1053 <lb/>to 1055; from which we may infer, that if the Blood <lb/>made
        uſe of in the 12th Experiment had been ſuffered <lb/>to ſtand till it was cold, it's
        Specifick Gravity would <lb/>have been 1053; wherefore, taking a Medium be- <lb/>tween the
        four laſt Experiments, we may allow the <lb/>Specifick Gravity of cold Human Blood to be
        1054. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The difference of 14 Parts in a 1000, between this <lb/>and the Specifick Gravity
        determined by Mr. <hi rend="italic">Boyle</hi>, is <lb/>eaſily accounted for, if we
        conſider, that that Gentle- <lb/>man did not make uſe of a Veſſel with a narrow <lb/>Neck,
        as plainly appears from the circumſtances men- <pb n="1009"/>
        <lb/>tioned in his Experiment; and conſequently a ſmall <lb/>error in the height of the
        Liquor would make a conſi- <lb/>derable alteration in the Specifick Gravity. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Since therefore the Specifick Gravity of Human Blood <lb/>is 1054, and that of its <hi
          rend="italic">Serum</hi> 1030, it is plain, that <lb/>Blood is heavier than <hi
          rend="italic">Serum</hi> by about one part in 43. <lb/>From which it manifeſtly follows,
        that the Globular <lb/>part of the Blood is ſpecifically heavier than the <hi rend="italic"
          >Serum</hi>, <lb/>ſince the Globular part being ſeparated from the Blood <lb/>leaves the
        remainder, or the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>, ſpecifically lighter <lb/>than the intire
        Maſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But in order to determine the exact Specifick Gra- <lb/>vity of the Blood Globules, it
        is firſt neceſſary to know <lb/>the Proportion, which the whole quantity of the <hi
          rend="italic">Craſ- <lb/>ſamentum</hi> contained in Blood bears to the <hi rend="italic"
          >Serum</hi>. To <lb/>this end Mr. <hi rend="italic">Boyle</hi> has given us two ſeveral
        Obſerva- <lb/>tions of the weights of the <hi rend="italic">Craſſamentum</hi> and <hi
          rend="italic">Serum</hi>, af- <lb/>ter they have ſeparated one from another in the Por-
        <lb/>ringer. But beſides the difficulty of making this Ex- <lb/>periment with any tolerable
        exactneſs, it is to be con- <lb/>ſider'd, that there is a great deal of <hi rend="italic"
          >Serum</hi> contain'd in <lb/>the interſtices of the Globules, that compoſe the <hi
          rend="italic">Craſſa- <lb/>mentum</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This difficulty however is in ſome meaſure anſwer'd <lb/>by two other Experiments,
        which Mr. <hi rend="italic">Boyle</hi> made for <lb/>this purpoſe, after the following
        manner. He put a <lb/>quantity of the <hi rend="italic">Craſſamentum</hi> already ſeparated
        from <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> into an Alembick, and diſtill'd off the re-
        <lb/>maining <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> to dryneſs, but without drawing off the <lb/>Oil,
        or Volatile Salt; after which he weigh'd the di- <lb/>ſtill'd Liquor, and the dry Maſs left
        behind. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By comparing theſe Experiments with the two for- <lb/>mer, it will be found that the
        entire weigh of <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>
        <lb/>contain'd in Blood is nearly 13/15 of the whole, and con- <pb n="1010"/>
        <lb/><choice>
          <corr>ſequently</corr>
          <sic>conſequently</sic>
        </choice> the weight of the dry'd <hi rend="italic">Craſſamentum</hi> is <lb/>only two
        fifteenths of the Blood. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But for farther ſatisfaction, an Analyſis was made <lb/>at my deſire with a large
        quantity of Blood, amount- <lb/>ing to four Pounds fourteen Ounces, by that ingeni- <lb/>ous
        and skilfull Chymiſt, Mr. <hi rend="italic">John Brown</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From this was obtain'd, with a very gentle heat, two <lb/>Pounds, fourteen Ounces, and
        ſix Drachms of a <lb/>Phlegmatick Liquor, that had ſcarce any thing of the <lb/>fœtid Scent,
        which is uſual in the diſtillation of Ani- <lb/>mal Subſtances; and its Specifick Gravity
        was nearly <lb/>the ſame with that of common Water, being but <lb/>1000,8. This being mixt
        with a ſtrong ſolution of <lb/>Alum, ſcarce afforded any <hi rend="italic">Coagulum</hi>;
        but exhibited a <lb/>conſiderable one upon mixture with a ſolution of <hi rend="italic">Ro-
          <lb/>man</hi> Vitriol. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The diſtillation being continued with the ſame <lb/>Heat, we had ſeven Ounces more of
        Phlegm conſide- <lb/>rably impregnated with Volatile Salt, as was manifeſt <lb/>from the
        Smell. The Specifick Gravity of this was <lb/>1007, and having mix'd it with <hi
          rend="italic">Tinctura Martis opti- <lb/>ma</hi>, Solution of Alum, and of <hi
          rend="italic">Roman</hi> Vitriol, a large <lb/><hi rend="italic">Coagulum</hi> was
        precipitated. In diſtilling theſe there <lb/>was loſt by Evaporation, two Ounces and two
        Drachms. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The third portion of Liquor, being rais'd with a <lb/>ſtronger Fire, amounted to ſeven
        Ounces ſix Drachms. <lb/>This was reddiſh, and turbid, and ſo ſtrongly charg'd <lb/>with
        Volatile Salts, that it might very well deſerve <lb/>the name of Spirit. Its Specifick
        Gravity was 1080,1. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Beſides theſe we had ſeven Drachms of Volatile <lb/>Salt, an ounce of Oil, and eight
        Ounces four Drachms <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Caput Mortuum</hi>, which ſtill retain'd ſome
        ſmall re- <lb/>mainder of the Oil, as was manifeſt from its taking <lb/>Fire at the flame of
        a Candle. In this latter part of <lb/>the Operation was loſt three Ounces, ſeven Drachms. </p>
      <pb n="1011"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon making due allowance for the difference be- <lb/>tween the Specifick Gravities of
        the three firſt Portions <lb/>of Liquor and that of <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>, as
        likewiſe for what <lb/>was loſt in the two ſeveral parts of the Operation, <lb/>which we may
        reaſonably conclude to have been of a <lb/>Specifick Gravity nearly the ſame with that of
        the Li- <lb/>quor drawn off, it will be found, that the quantity <lb/>of <hi rend="italic"
          >Serum</hi> contain'd in this Maſs of Blood was about 15/17 <lb/>of the whole Weight, and
        conſequently that the quan- <lb/>tity of <hi rend="italic">Craſſamentum</hi> was 2/17 of the
        ſame Weight. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If we calculate therefore upon this Suppoſition, that <lb/>the weight of the Globular
        part of the Blood is 2/17 of <lb/>the whole, we ſhall find the Specifick Gravity of a
        <lb/>Blood Globule to be to that of Water as 1277 to 1000. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If we follow the proportion of 2/15, which reſults from <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Boyle</hi>'s Experiments, the Specifick Gravity of a <lb/>Blood Globule will be 1242. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But this computation is in all appearance a great <lb/>deal too large; for we cannot be
        aſſur'd, that our <lb/>whole quantity of aqueous Liquor was rais'd from the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Serum</hi> of the Blood. On the contrary it is more than <lb/>probable, that
        a conſiderable part of it was afforded <lb/>by the Blood Globules themſelves, eſpecially in
        the <lb/>latter part of the Operation, when their texture muſt of <lb/>neceſſity have been
        broken and diſſolv'd by the ſtrong <lb/>Fire that was made uſe of. To prove this, we need
        <lb/>only conſider the condition of the dry'd <hi rend="italic">Craſſamentum</hi>,
        <lb/>after the Phlegm is drawn off, that being now a hard <lb/>and brittle Subſtance:
        whereas the Globules in their <lb/>natural State are ſoft and yielding. For which reaſons
        <lb/>it may perhaps be more ſatisfactory, if we at- <lb/>tempt to find the quantity of the
        Globular part of the <lb/>Blood after another manner. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It appears therefore from Mr. <hi rend="italic">Boyle</hi>'s Obſervations, <lb/>that
        the quantity of <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>, which may be pour'd off <pb n="1012"/>
        <lb/>from the <hi rend="italic">Craſſamentum</hi>, is about one half of the whole <lb/>Maſs.
        The remaining <hi rend="italic">Craſſamentum</hi> conſiſts of the <lb/>Blood Globules, and a
        quantity of <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> filling up the <lb/>Interſtices between them;
        which, if the Globules keep <lb/>their Spherical Form, may eaſily be found by the prin-
        <lb/>ciples of common Geometry, to be nearly one half of <lb/>the bulk of the <hi
          rend="italic">Craſſamentum</hi>: but if the Globules by <lb/>their preſſure againſt one
        another change their Figure, <lb/>the quantity of <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> will be
        ſomething leſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If this quantity of <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> lying between the Blood <lb/>Globules
        be added to that pour'd off, it appears, that <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>
        contain'd in Blood is about ¾ of the whole <lb/>bulk, and conſequently that the Blood
        Globules make <lb/>about ¼ of the whole. From which we ſhall find the <lb/>Specifick Gravity
        of the Blood Globules to be to that of <lb/>Water as 1126 to 1000. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If we ſuppoſe the Blood Globules to make 1/6, 1/5, ⅓, <lb/>or ½ of the whole bulk,
        their Specifick Gravity will be <lb/>reſpectively 1174, 1150, 1102, or 1078. So that
        <lb/>upon any of theſe Suppoſitions, the Specifick Gravity <lb/>of the Blood Globules will
        be conſiderably greater than <lb/>that of the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>, and conſequently
        they cannot be <lb/>ſuppos'd to be Veſicles fill'd with an Aereal Subſtance. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It will therefore perhaps be askt, What do they re- <lb/>ally conſiſt of? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In order to come to a Solution of this Queſtion, it <lb/>may be proper to take notice, </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That Blood is compos'd of Phlegm, Oil, Volatile <lb/>and fixt Salts, and Earth. For as
        to the Spirit, we <lb/>look upon it with Mr. <hi rend="italic">Boyle</hi>, to conſiſt of the
        Phlegm <lb/>and Volatile Salt united together. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>, upon a Chymical Analyſis, exhibits <lb/>a great
        deal of the firſt of theſe, and the others in a <lb/>very ſmall quantity. </p>
      <pb n="1013"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That on the contrary the <hi rend="italic">Craſſamentum</hi> yields much <lb/>leſs
        Phlegm, but the other Principles much more co- <lb/>piouſly than the <hi rend="italic"
          >Serum</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From which <hi rend="italic">Data</hi>, I think, we may ſafely conclude, <lb/>that the
          <hi rend="italic">Craſſamentum</hi>, or Globular part of the Blood, <lb/>conſiſts of ſome
        Phlegm united with the Oil and <lb/>Salts, and a ſmall quantity of Earth. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But what is the exact proportion of theſe ſeveral <lb/>Principles to one another; what
        alterations are produ- <lb/>ced in the Body by a change of this proportion; how, <lb/>and in
        what part theſe Globules are form'd; by what <lb/>means they preſerve their Figure, without
        diſſolving in <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>, or uniting with one another; what
        varia- <lb/>tions are made in their Specifick Gravities by Heat and <lb/>Cold; and what are
        the effects of thoſe Variations, <lb/>are Queſtions not very eaſy to be ſolv'd, and yet of
        <lb/>ſo much importance to the Animal Oeconomy, that <lb/>it were greatly to be wiſht, we
        had a number of <hi rend="italic">Data</hi>
        <lb/>ſufficient to determine them. </p>
      <postscript>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">P. S.</hi> Since this Paper was ſent to the Preſs, I made <lb/>the
          following Experiments, which ſerving to confirm <lb/>the Method laſt made uſe of, for
          finding the Specifick <lb/>Gravity of the Blood Globules, it may not be impro- <lb/>per to
          relate them. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Auguſt</hi> 6. 1719. I took a lump of the <hi rend="italic"
            >Craſſamen- <lb/>tum</hi>, and waſh'd it gently in fair Water, to free it <lb/>from the
          looſe Globules, which precipitating out of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>, after
          the <hi rend="italic">Coagulum</hi> is form'd, do not unite <lb/>into one Body with it.
          This done, I laid it on a <lb/>ſpungy brown Paper, in order to drain off the ſuper-
          <lb/>fluous Moiſture. After which, weighing it firſt in <lb/>Air, and then in Water, I
          found its Specifick Gravity <lb/>to be 1083½. </p>
        <pb n="1014"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Another lump of the ſame <hi rend="italic">Craſſamentum</hi> being weigh'd <lb/>in
          the ſame manner, its Specifick Gravity was 1082,9. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Sept.</hi> 18. 1719. I found the Specifick Gravity of <lb/>another
          piece of <hi rend="italic">Craſſamentum</hi> to be 1082.1. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A ſecond piece from the Blood of a different Per- <lb/>ſon gave me 1086,1. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A third from the ſame Perſon gave 1086,6. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>From this it follows that the Specifick Gravity of <lb/>the Blood Globules is at
          leaſt 1084, which is the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Medium</hi> between theſe five
          Experiments. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But if we allow one half of the bulk of the <hi rend="italic">Craſſa-
            <lb/>mentum</hi> to conſiſt of <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>, filling up the Spaces be-
          <lb/>tween the Blood Globules, we ſhall find their Spe- <lb/>cifick Gravity to be 1138. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>From this we muſt make a ſmall abatement, becauſe <lb/>ſome part of the <hi
            rend="italic">Serum</hi> muſt have been ſquees'd out <lb/>from between the Globules, by
          their yielding to one <lb/>anothers Preſſure, when the lump of <hi rend="italic"
            >Craſſamentum</hi> lay <lb/>upon the Paper: and this will reduce their Specifick
          <lb/>Gravity ſufficiently near to 1126, as we had before <lb/>determin'd it. </p>
      </postscript>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
