<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Rutty: An Account of a Praeternatural Tumour on the Loins of an
          Infant, Attended with a Cloven Spine. By Dr. Rutty, Fellow of the College of Physicians,
          and of the Royal Society</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Dr. Rutty</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of a Praeternatural Tumour on the Loins of an Infant, Attended with a
              Cloven Spine. By Dr. Rutty, Fellow of the College of Physicians, and of the Royal
              Society</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for W. and J. Innys, at the Princes-Arms, at the West
                  Corner of St. Paul's Church-Yard.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1720-1721</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">31</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">98-102</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110528555</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi:10.1098/rstl.1720.0023</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT31_0098">
    <body>
      <pb n="98"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">III.</hi> An Account of a præternatural Tumour on the <lb/>Loins of an
        Infant, attended with a <hi rend="roman">Cloven <lb/>Spine</hi>. By Dr. <hi rend="roman"
          >Rutty</hi>, Fellow of the College of <lb/>Phyſicians, and of the <hi rend="roman">Royal
          Society</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE curious Mr. <hi rend="italic">Ruyſch</hi>, in an Obſervation
        on <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Spina Bifida</hi>, takes notice that other Writers <lb/>have
        deſcrib'd it to be cloven into two equal parts <lb/>longitudinally, as Butchers ſplit the
        Back-bone of an <lb/>Ox or Sheep; whereas out of ten Subjects, which he <lb/>had an
        opportunity to examine, not one prov'd to be <lb/>in that manner, the Body of the <hi
          rend="italic">Vertebræ</hi> being entire, <lb/>and the <hi rend="italic">Acute
          Proceſſes</hi> only divided. Pretty near this <lb/>Deſcription, is the <hi rend="italic"
          >Spine</hi> to be treated of, and I the <lb/>rather trouble this Society with it, becauſe
        it don't <lb/>appear by the Tranſactions, that it has as yet come <lb/>before us. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Back-bone is of a female Infant ſix Days old; <lb/>whoſe Mother, when ſeven Weeks
        gone with Child, <lb/>upon a fright occaſion'd by her Husband's falling from <lb/>a Horſe
        and very much bruiſing his Loins, gave the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Embryo</hi> this injury;
        but notwithſtanding ſhe went out <lb/>her Time, and the Child was full grown. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There appeared upon the region of the Loins, in <lb/>the ſame place where the Father
        receiv'd his hurt, a <lb/>Tumour about the bigneſs of a ſmall Turnep, with a <lb/>broad <hi
          rend="italic">Baſis</hi>, around which the Skin was diſcolour'd, <lb/>as by an <hi
          rend="italic">Ecchymoſis</hi>, but it grew immediately from <lb/>thence pellucid, like a
        Veſicle rais'd by <hi rend="italic">Cantharides</hi>, and <lb/>continued ſo throughout,
        except juſt at its <hi rend="italic">Apex</hi>, where <lb/>was a Subſtance like a <hi
          rend="italic">Fungus</hi>. This Bladder was fill'd <pb n="99"/>
        <lb/>with a Liquor, which in Scent and Colour reſembled <lb/>the true Urine: inſomuch, that
        upon ſtrictly examining <lb/>the Linnen ſtain'd by what iſſu'd from hence, with that
        <lb/>from the <hi rend="italic">Pudenda</hi>, we cou'd perceive no ſenſible diffe-
        <lb/>rence, and concluded there was a Communication be- <lb/>tween the left Kidney and the
        Orifice, into which the <lb/>Surgeon's Probe paſs'd obliquely upwards, about an <lb/>Inch.
        Of the ſame opinion was Dr. <hi rend="italic">Pellet</hi>, then pre- <lb/>ſent. Whether the
        ſame Similitude may hold, betwixt <lb/>the Urine and this Liquor, in all Caſes of the like
        Na- <lb/>ture, I have not had opportunites to obſerve: but as <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Ruyſch</hi> has taken no notice of it, in ſuch a Number <lb/>of Subjects, that have been
        before him, I am apt to think, <lb/>that it does not; being eaſily perſuaded, that if it
        did, <lb/>it would not ſo often have eſcap'd his inquiſitive Re- <lb/>ſearches. I cou'd have
        wiſh'd however, that this Fluid <lb/>had been ſav'd; to have try'd by Experiments, in what
        <lb/>other Qualities, beſides the Scent and Colour, it might <lb/>correſpond with the Urine;
        which wou'd have given <lb/>us a farther Inſight into the Cauſe of this Affinity be-
        <lb/>tween them, in the particular inſtance now before us. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon opening the Body, where were preſent Dr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pellet</hi>, and
        Mr. <hi rend="italic">Stephens</hi> and ingenious Surgeon, the <lb/>Kidneys, contrary to
        Expectation, were <hi rend="italic">perfect</hi>, and did <lb/>not any way communicate with
        the outward Orifice. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But upon clearing away the Fungous Subſtance, <lb/>which took up all the <hi
          rend="italic">Sulcus</hi> or Hollow of the <hi rend="italic">Spine</hi>, we <lb/>found
        where the Perforation tended; a long Probe eaſily <lb/>paſſing up the Channel, which
        contains the <hi rend="italic">Medulla <lb/>Spinalis</hi>. Throughout this <hi rend="italic"
          >Fungus</hi> were diſpers'd a <lb/>great many endings of ſmall Nerves, from whence di-
        <lb/>ſtill'd this, as it were, Urinous Liquor, which occaſion'd <lb/>the Tumour: the reſt of
        the <hi rend="italic">Medulla</hi> was more compact, <lb/>and fill'd the Cavity of the <hi
          rend="italic">Spine</hi>; tho' in ſome Subjects <lb/>it has been waſted to ſuch a Degree,
        that by blowing <pb n="100"/>
        <lb/>into the Orifice you may inflate the <hi rend="italic">Dura Mater</hi>; as was
        <lb/>done by Mr. <hi rend="italic">Dobyns</hi> a Surgeon, in a Caſe of this Na- <lb/>ture.
        The Coat of the Tumour conſiſted at its <hi rend="italic">Baſis</hi> of <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">Cuticula</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Cutis</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Membrana
          Adipoſa</hi>: the two firſt of <lb/>which forthwith terminating, the <hi rend="italic"
          >Cuticula</hi> only was con- <lb/>tinued; immediately under which appear'd the <hi
          rend="italic">Muſcles</hi>
        <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Fungus</hi> above mention'd. In this it differs from <lb/>thoſe
        of Mr. <hi rend="italic">Ruyſch</hi>, which received their Coats from <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">Membranes</hi> that cover the <hi rend="italic">Medulla</hi>: as likewiſe
        <lb/>from thoſe taken notice of by <hi rend="italic">Tulpius</hi>, which borrow'd
        <lb/>theirs from the <hi rend="italic">Peritonæum</hi>, as he ſays; tho' by his own
        <lb/>Deſcription, it is more likely they proceeded from the <lb/>ſame Membranes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe Tumours conſtantly attend the <hi rend="italic">Spina Bifida</hi>: <lb/>inſomuch,
        that when any of them preſent themſelves <lb/>on the Loins or Back of a new-born Infant, we
        have <lb/>good grounds to pronounce <hi rend="italic">This</hi> to be the Cauſe; but <lb/>we
        may be poſitive in it, if the Child can't move its <lb/>lower Limbs; the want of which
        motion is an infal- <lb/>lible Indication, that the <hi rend="italic">Medulla Spinalis</hi>
        reaches no <lb/>farther than the Swelling, whereby the Nerves are <lb/>not diſtributed to
        thoſe Parts. They appear diffe- <lb/>rently in different Subjects. In ſome the whole Tu-
        <lb/>mour is <hi rend="italic">Opake</hi>; which proceeds from ſmall Filaments of
        <lb/>Nerves propagated in great numbers throughout its <lb/>Coat, and not from the thickneſs
        of the Skin, as <hi rend="italic">Ruyſch</hi>
        <lb/>will have it. In others it is <hi rend="italic">pellucid</hi>; and then the <hi
          rend="italic">Me- <lb/>dulla</hi> terminates at once at the Aperture of the <hi
          rend="italic">Spine</hi>, <lb/>and does not ſhoot out into any Ramifications. This
        <lb/>before us is a Compoſite of both Species, the greater <lb/>part of which was <hi
          rend="italic">pellucid</hi>; the leſs, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> the <hi rend="italic"
          >Apex</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">opake</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Back-bone itſelf, you may obſerve, is not cleft, <lb/>but has its <hi rend="italic"
          >Vertebræ</hi>, with their <hi rend="italic">other Proceſſes</hi> entire, <lb/>and is only
        defective in its <hi rend="italic">Spines</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Acute ones</hi>. But <pb
          n="101"/>
        <lb/>that Portion of the <hi rend="italic">Vertebræ</hi>, which ſhould make an <lb/>acute
        Angle, from whence their <hi rend="italic">Spinal Proceſſes</hi> natu- <lb/>rally ariſe, in
        order to form the <hi rend="italic">Specus</hi> or Paſſage for <lb/>the Marrow, inſtead of
        that, gapes and lies almoſt in <lb/>a ſtrait Line on each ſide; whereby the <hi
          rend="italic">Medulla</hi> is de- <lb/>frauded of its uſual Guard from external Injuries.
        <lb/>This Defect begins at the third <hi rend="italic">Vertebra</hi> of the Loins, <lb/>and
        is continued to the end of the <hi rend="italic">Os Sacrum</hi>: which <lb/>laſt is very
        extraordinary, it ſcarcely ever happening to <lb/>this Bone; the reaſon of which I take to
        be the more <lb/>than ordinary Compactneſs of its <hi rend="italic">Vertebræ</hi>, whereby
        it <lb/>is leſs liable to be injur'd by any Impreſſion. For we <lb/>obſerve, that in Adults
        they grow ſo cloſe together, <lb/>as to unite and form one large and ſolid Bone. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As the Caſe before us is a <hi rend="italic">Vitium Conformationis</hi> ow- <lb/>ing to
        the Mother's Imagination, ſo the Same ſome- <lb/>times is occaſion'd by <hi rend="italic"
          >Matter</hi> lodging upon the <hi rend="italic">Spine</hi>, <lb/>and eroding the <hi
          rend="italic">Vertebræ</hi> by its Acrimony: but then <lb/>you find a <hi rend="italic"
          >carious Bone</hi>, whereas in theſe <hi rend="italic">præternatural</hi>
        <lb/>Caſes, there remain no ſuch Footſteps. This was ob- <lb/>ſerv'd in the Body of the late
        Lord <hi rend="italic">Peterborough</hi>, as <lb/>related by Mr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Cowper</hi>: Upon the opening of which, <lb/>He found a large Tumour, from whence flow'd
        a <lb/>browniſh colour'd Matter; and under it, the upper <lb/>and fore part of the ninth,
        and the lower part of the <lb/>eighth <hi rend="italic">Vertebræ</hi> of the <hi
          rend="italic">Thorax</hi> were conſumed and gone, <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Medulla
          Spinalis</hi> being cover'd with its <hi rend="italic">Membranes <lb/>only</hi>. This gave
        riſe to thoſe Symptoms in that <hi rend="italic">mor- <lb/>bid</hi> Caſe, ſo nearly
        reſembling the above recited in this <lb/><hi rend="italic">præternatural</hi> One. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is manifeſt from what has been ſaid, that theſe <lb/>Caſes are incurable, and muſt
        in a little time kill the <lb/>Patient. But it is almoſt immediate Death to open the
        <lb/>Tumour; which every Surgeon will naturally do, that <lb/>has not ſeen or read
        concerning it: the Fluid ſeeming <pb n="102"/>
        <lb/>to require a Diſcharge. It is for the ſake of thoſe <lb/>Gentlemen that I have taken
        upon me to deſcribe it, <lb/>who poſſibly may not have the above-mention'd Authors <lb/>in
        their Hands; the only Ones that have obſerv'd it <lb/>with any tolerable Accuracy. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
