<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Deverel: Concerning a Case in Chirurgery</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Mr. Deverel</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Part of a Letter from Mr. Deverel Surgeon at Bristol; Concerning a Case in
              Chirurgery, Which is Commonly Mistaken for a Fracture of the Patella</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for W. and J. Innys, at the Princes-Arms, at the West
                  Corner of St. Paul's Church-Yard.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1720-1721</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">31</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">44-46</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110528555</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1720.0013</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT31_0044">
    <body>
      <pb n="44"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">I.</hi> Part of a Letter from Mr. <hi rend="roman">Deveral</hi>
        Surgeon at <lb/><hi rend="roman">Briſtol</hi>; concerning a Caſe in Chirurgery, which
        <lb/>is commonly miſtaken for a Fracture of the Pa- <lb/>tella. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">R</hi><hi rend="italic">ICHARD BURT</hi>, a Gardiner, living with Mrs.
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Lloyd</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Stoke</hi> near <hi rend="italic"
          >Briſtol</hi>, was thrown from his <lb/>Horſe, and in the fall receiv'd ſuch a hurt in one
        of <lb/>his Knees as made him incapable of remounting: He <lb/>felt ſomewhat crack in that
        Knee (as he expreſs'd it) <lb/>before it touch'd the ground. Upon examining the <lb/>Part I
        found (as I then thought) the ends of the <lb/>broken Bone drawn above four fingers diſtance
        from <lb/>each other: But upon a ſtricter examination of the <lb/>parts, I found the <hi
          rend="italic">Patella</hi> (which was drawn upwards <lb/>by the extenſors of the Leg)
        retain'd its natural Figure, <lb/>and that the hardneſs which was felt below was the
        <lb/>end of the torn Ligament that ties it to the <hi rend="italic">Tibia</hi>. <lb/>The
        ends of the Ligament were brought as near as <lb/>poſſible, and kept ſo about three Weeks
        without any <lb/>very remarkable accident intervening. He then began <lb/>to walk, which was
        a little too ſoon, cauſing thereby <lb/>ſome pains, and looſening the Cicatrix, which made
        <lb/>it the longer before it was perfectly firm; however he <lb/>walks without any
        perceptible lameneſs. I have met <lb/>with two others in the ſame caſe, the one a Perſon of
        <lb/>diſtinction, who has not met with the good Fortune of <lb/>walking ſo well as ſhe uſed,
        tho' not for want of all <lb/>the care and circumſpection imaginable; for it is hardly
        <lb/>to be expected that one in ten, to whom this Acci- <lb/>dent happens, ſhould ever go
        right, it being next to <pb n="45"/>
        <lb/>an impoſſibility that the ends of the torn Ligament <lb/>ſhould be ſo exactly plac'd,
        and retain'd as not to lie <lb/>one over the other. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pareè</hi> in the 22d Chapter of his 15th Book af- <lb/>firms, that
        he never ſaw one of thoſe who have had <lb/>this Bone broken, but that halted during the
        reſt of <lb/>their lives: I am very apt to believe what this ex- <lb/>cellent Author affirms
        about the halting, and am ſorry I <lb/>muſt diſſent from his notions of the caſe, and the
        <lb/>cauſe of the Lameneſs. <hi rend="italic">Hildanus</hi> in his <hi rend="italic"
          >Obſervationes <lb/>Chirurgicæ. Cent.</hi> 5th. <hi rend="italic">Obſerv</hi>. 88. P. m.
        485, has given <lb/>us a Hiſtory of a tranſverſe Fracture of this Bone, which, <lb/>after
        all the Symptoms were remov'd, was cur'd. <hi rend="italic">Sed <lb/>claudicatio ac ſumma
          imbecillitas totius cruris ſecuta eſt, <lb/>ita ut non niſi maxima cum difficultate
          ambulare poſſit</hi>. <lb/>He afterwards mentioning the cauſe of the Lameneſs <lb/>makes a
        Quæry, if what <hi rend="italic">Pareè</hi> (to whom this Obſerva- <lb/>tion is dedicated)
        ſays in his <hi rend="italic">Exc. lib. de oſſibus, lib. 4. <lb/>cap. 2.</hi> can be the
        cauſe of the Lameneſs; his words <lb/>are, <q rend="italic">Etſi vero Opinionem hancce
          rationi conſentaneam eſſe <lb/>in dubium revocare minime' conabor, unus tamen reſtat
          <lb/>ſcrupulus, videlicet, an, fractâ patellâ, extuberantia calli <lb/>talis eſſe poſſit,
          ut cavitatem hancce (que inter femur &amp; os <lb/>tibiæ magna eſt) adeo adimpleat, ut
          motum actionemque ge- <lb/>nu impedire poſſit? Videmus enim ut plurimum in reliquis
          <lb/>oſſium fracturis, (niſi contritio oſſis &amp; perioſtei fuerit max- <lb/>ima) naturam
          tam decenter &amp; eleganter connectere oſſa, ut <lb/>rarò relinquatur veſtigium fracturæ.
          Perioſtium enim, quam <lb/>diu integrum eſt, materiam calli retinet, quo minus in ex-
          <lb/>tuberantiam excreſcere poſſit, niſi, &amp;c. Deinde in hoc noſtro <lb/>Ægro callum
          non fuiſſe cauſam claudicationis ex ſequen- <lb/>tibus apparebit: quapropter diſtinctione
          hie opus eſt. </q> Af- <lb/>ter this he goes on to ſhow us how many ways this <lb/>Bone
        may be fractur'd, but doth not obſerve that he <lb/>ever ſaw it any other way broken,
        (unleſs in a Gun- <pb n="46"/>
        <lb/>ſhot-wound) than tranſverſly; if he had, I am perſua- <lb/>ded, that this curious
        Obſervator would never have <lb/>omitted it in his Obſervations. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ruyſch</hi> in his <hi rend="italic">Centuria obſervationum
          Anatomico-Chirur- <lb/>gicarum 4c. obſervatio 3</hi>, writes as follows. <q rend="italic"
          >Patellam <lb/>propter duritiem ſuam haud frangi poſſe nonnulli perverſe <lb/>aſſerunt.
          Nos vero eandem non ſolum à caſu graviori <lb/>in genu frangi experti ſumus, verum etiam
          ſine caſu; cu- <lb/>jus rei Hiſtoriam recenſere animus eſt. Ante tres <lb/>præterpropter
          annos, viſitavi cum Magiſtro Petro Adri- <lb/>ani filio, virum ſatis robuſtum, qui a ponte
          deſcendens in ter- <lb/>ram ferè ceciderat; uno pede lubrico, reſiſtens tamen quan-
          <lb/>tum potuit, in Terram non fuerat prolapſus; ſed ab illa re- <lb/>ſiſtentia
          vehementiſſima tranſverſim fracta ejus patella, &amp; <lb/>adeo quidem evidenter, ut inter
          utrumque locari potuerit <lb/>manus, una <unclear>o</unclear>nim ſupra altera infra genu
          ſentiebatur. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This Obſervation is ſo like in all its circumſtances <lb/>to that which I related
        above, eſpecially in that the <lb/>Fracture was made without a fall, that I am very apt
        <lb/>to believe it is the ſame; and do imagine the might be <lb/>deceived by miſtaking the
        hard end of the Ligament for <lb/>the broken Bone. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And when theſe ſort of Accidents, which are now <lb/>called Fractures of the <hi
          rend="italic">Patella</hi>, come to be nicely ex- <lb/>amined; they will perhaps be found
        to be generally <lb/>of the ſame Nature. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
