<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Atkinson: An Extraordinary Case in Surgery</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Joseph Atkinson</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Extraordinary Case in Surgery, Communicated by Mr. Joseph Atkinson Senior,
              Surgeon</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed for W. and J. Innys, Printers to the Royal Society, at the
                  West End of St. Paul's.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1724-1725</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">33</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">340-342</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110356204</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1724.0063</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT33_0340">
    <body>
      <pb n="340"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/>An extraordinary Caſe in Surgery, communicated <lb/>by Mr. <hi rend="roman">Joſeph
          Atkinſon</hi> Senior, Surgeon. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Maiden, about 20 Years of Age, was brought to <lb/>me about <hi
          rend="italic">Chriſtmas</hi> 1723; who had a Tumour <lb/>on the inſide of her right Thigh,
        extending from the <lb/>Groin to the Knee, which was ſo large, that I judg'd <lb/>it
        contained at leaſt the Quantity of a Gallon; the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cutis</hi> was
        exceedingly diſtended, but of the natural <lb/>Colour, only, the capillary Veins appear'd
        varicous, <lb/>and very numerous; ſhe had alſo a large Tumour on <lb/>the Buttock of the
        ſame Side, of the Bigneſs of a <lb/>Quartern Loaf; but when the Tumour on the Thigh <lb/>was
        preſſed, the Tumour above very much encreas'd, <lb/>which ſhew'd a Communication, and prov'd
        after- <lb/>wards ſo to be: She had alſo another Tumour on her <lb/>right Side, ſtretching
        from the left Side of the <hi rend="italic">Ver- <lb/>tebræ</hi> of the Back to the <hi
          rend="italic">Hypochondrium</hi>, about the <lb/>Bigneſs <choice>
          <corr>of</corr>
          <sic>oſ</sic>
        </choice> a Penny Loaf, her Body was very much <lb/>emaciated, and ſhe could hardly breathe,
        and the little <lb/>Victuals ſhe eat very difficultly paſſed out of the Sto- <lb/>mach. She
        had had the <hi rend="italic">Menſes</hi> but twice or thrice, <lb/>about 12 Months before
        the Beginning of thoſe Tu- <lb/>mours, and it is to be marked, that the Tumour of her
        <lb/>Thigh began firſt, and increaſed to near the Magni- <lb/>tude I firſt ſaw it, before
        the Tumour of the Buttock <lb/>and Hip began; after that, the Tumour of her Back <lb/>began,
        which, as it increas'd, brought on great Diffi- <lb/>culty in Breathing. She had been with
        ſeveral other <lb/>Perſons, who adviſed againſt opening the Tumour of <lb/>her Thigh, moſt
        of them being of the Opinion it <lb/>was from Blood, and that her Caſe was incurable: I <pb
          n="341"/>
        <lb/>confeſs, I was of a contrary Opinion; but being told <lb/>what ſo many others had ſaid,
        I declin'd meddling <lb/>with it at that Time, though her Parent and herſelf <lb/>were
        willing to it: At this Time I diſmiſſed her, ſaying, <lb/>that, if ſhe liv'd, a little Time
        wou'd diſcover more of <lb/>her Caſe. About two Months after I was deſired to <lb/>viſit her
        again, which I did, but the Tumours were <lb/>ſo monſtrously increaſed, and her Body ſo
        waſted, <lb/>that I wonder'd ſhe could live under ſuch Circum- <lb/>ſtances; the Tumour of
        the Thigh was every Way <lb/>yielding to the Preſſure of the Finger, nor was there <lb/>the
        leaſt Hardneſs about the Extremities of it, ſo that <lb/>it might be eaſily miſtaken for an
          <hi rend="italic">Aneuriſma</hi>, had it <lb/>not wanted the grand Characteriſtick,
        Pulſation, which <lb/>ſome ſay, is not to be felt when thoſe are very large, <lb/>the Middle
        of this then look'd a little red, and ſhin- <lb/>ing, and ſeem'd to point a little; I told
        them I be- <lb/>lieved it would break with a ſmall Orifice, and ſhew <lb/>what was
        contain'd, willing them to notify it to me <lb/>if ſuch a Thing happen'd: Three Days after
        they call'd <lb/>me in haſte to this Patient, ſaying, the Swelling of <lb/>her Thigh was
        broke; when I came, I found there <lb/>had been diſcharg'd a ſmall Quantity of matteriſh
        <lb/>Subſtance, much like what is contain'd in a <hi rend="italic">Meliceris</hi>, <lb/>but
        the Opening was ſo ſmall or cloſed, that I could <lb/>not enter my Probe; however, though
        ſhe ſeem'd <lb/>to me ( and to Mr. <hi rend="italic">Wall</hi>, an Apothecary then
        <lb/>preſent) to be ready to expire, yet, at the De- <lb/>ſire of her Parents, I open'd this
        Tumour with my <lb/>Launcet, making an Inciſion about an Inch and <lb/>an half long, through
        which poured three Pint <lb/>Baſons full of Matter, beſides ſeveral ſmaller, which
        <lb/>together contain'd about five Quarts, it was very fœ- <lb/>tid and bloody towards the
        latter End of this Diſ- <lb/>charge; upon this, the Tumour wholly ſubſided, in- <pb n="342"/>
        <lb/>ſomuch that the Thigh inſtantly became as ſmall as <lb/>the other; I put my Finger into
        the Wound, and <lb/>found the <hi rend="italic">Faſcia lata</hi> quite conſum'd, the Muſcles
        lay <lb/>all looſe, ſo that I fairly touch'd the Thigh-Bone be- <lb/>tween them, as I would. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But I ſhould acquaint you, that, immediately upon <lb/>the Diſcharge of this Humour,
        the Tumour on the <lb/>Buttock was conſiderably abated, but there followed <lb/>about two or
        three Spoonfuls of florid Blood; I dreſs'd <lb/>it up for this Time with a proper Digeſtive,
        and a <lb/>ſuitable Bandage; the Day following I viſited her <lb/>again, and found ſhe had
        ſlept pretty well, and was <lb/>much refreſh'd, and not the leaſt Faintneſs had at-
        <lb/>tended her, during my Abſence, which ſhews the ima- <lb/>ginary <hi rend="italic"
          >Synocope</hi>, that is feared to follow ſuch, Evacu- <lb/>ations, to be groundleſs; the
        Day following, tak- <lb/>ing off my Dreſſings, I found the Limb, in its Figure, <lb/>bigger
        than the other; at the third Dreſſing there <lb/>appear'd a ſmall hard Swelling a little
        below the <lb/>Orifice, which was made by ſome grumous Blood <lb/>that lay there, which I
        turn'd out with my Finger, <lb/>in Quantity about four Ounces, this was follow'd <lb/>by a
        florid Blood, which much ſurpriſed me; I then <lb/>judg'd this proceeded from ſome
        Hypogaſtrick Veſſel <lb/>that ſupplied this Tumour, and I deſpair'd of Suc- <lb/>ceſs,
        unleſs I could meet with this Spring; ſo, in or- <lb/>der to it, I laid open the Sinews to
        the Groin, and, <lb/>though I could not diſcover the Veſſel, yet I ſo ſuc- <lb/>ceſsfully
        applied my Aſtringent, that from that <lb/>Time it bled no more; however, there was, for a
        <lb/>Week, a great Flowing of a ferous Matter, which <lb/>wholly ſunk the Tumour of the
        Buttock and Hip, <lb/>and, by boulſtering and compreſſing with ſuitable Ban- <lb/>dage, the
        ſo long ſeparated <hi rend="italic">Cutis</hi> clos'd with the <pb n="343"/>
        <lb/>Muſcles, and all Things, in about a Fortnight, ſeem'd <lb/>to be in a fair Way of
        healing, yet, it was near three <lb/>Months, before this Cure was compleated. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But ſtill (that is, a Fortnight after the Opening of <lb/>the Thigh) the Tumour on her
        Back continu'd, and <lb/>ſhe much ſtraitened for Breath; ſaying, if that was <lb/>opened,
        ſhe ſhould be preſently reliev'd; this Tumour <lb/>I then open'd (which was, I ſaid, as big
        as a Penny <lb/>white Loaf, and there iſſued out about two Quarts <lb/>of Matter, or rather
        more: I was again greatly ſur- <lb/>priſed that ſuch a Quantity, ſo much more than <lb/>what
        poſſibly this viſible Tumour could contain, <lb/>ſhould run out of this Orifice; I enter'd
        my Probe, <lb/>and found it penetrate into the Cavity of the <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi>,
        <lb/>between the ſecond and third ſpurious Rib, reckon- <lb/>ing from beneath, on which ſhe
        reſpired with all <lb/>Freedom, but there was a <hi rend="italic">Halitus</hi> at this
        Wound; I <lb/>continu'd to dreſs this and believe, before this tend- <lb/>ed towards
        Healing, not leſs (at Times) than a Gal- <lb/>lon, or rather five Quarts of Matter, was
        diſcharg'd; <lb/>but, when I thought all was over, it filled again, the <lb/>external Tumour
        became almoſt as big as before, <lb/>and her Breathing as difficult as ever, ſo that I now
        <lb/>thought all my Labour had been in vain; yet I open'd <lb/>it again with a larger
        Orifice, and from that Time <lb/>dreſſed it ſucceſsfully, to the perfect Healing; the
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Menſes</hi> are return'd, the Patient continuing well to <lb/>this
        Day, and in a good State of Health. This Patient <lb/>has been viewed by Mr. <hi
          rend="italic">John Douglaſs</hi>, and he has <lb/>had an ample Account of this Affair.
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
