<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Houstoun: An Account of a Dropsy in the Left Ovary</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Robert Houstoun</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of a Dropsy in the Left Ovary of a Woman, Aged 58. Cured by a Large
              Incision Made in the Side of the Abdomen, by Dr. Robert Houstoun</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed for W. and J. Innys, Printers to the Royal Society, at the
                  West End of St. Paul's.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1724-1725</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">33</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">8-15</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110356204</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1724.0004</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT33_0008">
    <body>
      <pb n="8"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">III.</hi> An Account of a Dropſy in the left Ovary of a <lb/>Woman,
        aged 58. Cured by a large Inciſion <lb/>made in the Side of the <hi rend="roman"
          >Abdomen</hi>, by Dr. <hi rend="roman">Ro- <lb/>bert Houſtoun</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="dc(1.5)">A</hi>UGUST</hi> 1701. I was in the Country, with
        a <lb/>Patient, the Lady <hi rend="italic">Anne Houſtoun</hi>, Wife to Sir <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">John Houſtoun</hi>, Baronet; in the Shire of <hi rend="italic">Renfrew</hi>,
        <lb/>ten Miles from <hi rend="italic">Glaſgow, North Britain</hi>. This <lb/>charitable Lady
        preſs'd me with great Earneſtneſs to <lb/>viſit a Tenant's Wife, who lay bedridden, of an
        un- <lb/>common Diſeaſe, which no Phyſician, or Surgeon, <lb/>who had ſeen her, could give
        any Name to, or ac- <lb/>count for. She inform'd me, the ableſt of that Coun- <lb/>try had
        forſaken her, and declared her incurable, ſo <lb/>that I could loſe no Reputation by the
        Reſult of my <lb/>Endeavours. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In order to oblige this worthy Lady, and in Com- <lb/>paſſion to the Diſtreſs of a poor
        Woman in ſo deplorable <lb/>Condition, deſerted and given over on all ſides, I went,
        <lb/>determined to do every thing in my Power for her Re- <lb/>lief. She was in the 58th
        Year of her Age, her Name <lb/>was <hi rend="italic">Margaret Millar</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>She inform'd me that her Midwiſe, in her laſt <lb/>lying-in, at 45 Years old, having
        violently pull'd away <lb/>the Burthen, ſhe was ſo very ſenſibly affected by a Pain,
        <lb/>which then ſeiz'd her in the left Side, between the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Umbilicus</hi> and Groin, that ſhe ſcarce ever had been <lb/>free from it after, but that
        it had troubled her more, or <lb/>leſs, during 13 Years together; that for two Years paſt
        <lb/>ſhe had been extremely uneaſy, her Belly grew very <pb n="9"/>
        <lb/>large, and a Difficulty of breathing increaſed continu- <lb/>ally upon her; inſomuch
        that for the laſt ſix Months, <lb/>ſhe had ſcarce breath'd at all but with the utmoſt Dif-
        <lb/>ficulty. That in all that Space of Time, having quite <lb/>loſt her Appetite, ſhe had
        ſcarce eat ſo much as would <lb/>nouriſh a ſucking Child; and that for three Months to-
        <lb/>gether ſhe had now been forc'd to lie conſtantly on her <lb/>Back, not daring to move
        at all, to one ſide or other. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This Tumour was grown to ſo monſtrous a Bulk, <lb/>that it engroſs'd the whole left
        Side, from the <hi rend="italic">Umbili- <lb/>cus</hi> to the <hi rend="italic">Pubes</hi>,
        and ſtretch'd the Abdominal Muſcles, <lb/>to ſo unequal a Degree, that I don't remember ever
        to <lb/>have ſeen the like in the whole Courſe of my Practice. <lb/>It drew towards a Point.
        Her being ſo long confined to <lb/>lie continually on her Back, having grievouſly excori-
        <lb/>ated her, added much to her Sufferings, which, with <lb/>want of Reſt and Appetite, had
        waſted her to Skin and <lb/>Bone, as the poor Woman herſelf expreſſed it. Indeed ſhe
        <lb/>needed not to have told me ſo, my Eyes were too faith- <lb/>ful Witneſſes of her low
        and wretched Condition. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Scarce able to ſpeak out, ſhe told me, that having <lb/>heard much of my Succeſs, ſhe
        had ſtrong Hopes of <lb/>Relief, provided I would try at leaſt, and do ſome- <lb/>thing in
        Pity to her Affliction. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I anſwer'd her that I was willing, but afraid, in her <lb/>low State, ſhe would want
        Strength to undergo a large <lb/>Inciſion; that in order effectually to relieve her, I muſt
        <lb/>be oblig'd to lay open a great Part of her Belly, and <lb/>remove the Cauſe of all that
        Swelling: ſhe ſeem'd not <lb/>frightened, but heard me without Diſorder, and, as if
        <lb/>inſpir'd with ſudden Courage, preſs'd, and urg'd me to <lb/>the Operation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I drew (I muſt confeſs) almoſt all my Confidence <lb/>from her unexpected Reſolution,
        ſo that without loſs <lb/>of Time, I prepared what the Place would allow, and <pb n="10"/>
        <lb/>with an Impoſthume Lancet, laid open about an Inch, <lb/>but finding nothing iſſue, I
        enlarged it two Inches, and <lb/>even then nothing came forth but a little thin yellowiſh
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>, ſo I ventured to lay it open about two Inches
        <lb/>more: I was not a little ſtartled, after ſo large an A- <lb/>perture, to find only a
        glutinous Subſtance bung up <lb/>this Orifice. All my Difficulty was to remove it; I
        <lb/>try'd my Probe, I endeavour'd with my Fingers, but <lb/>all was in vain; it was ſo
        ſlippery that it eluded every <lb/>Touch, and the ſtrongeſt hold I could take. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I wanted, in this place, almoſt every thing neceſſary, <lb/>but bethought myſelf of a
        very odd Inſtrument, yet as <lb/>good as the beſt in its Conſequence, becauſe it anſwer'd
        <lb/> the End propos'd. I took a ſtrong Firr-Splinter, ſuch <lb/>as the Poor in that Country
        ordinarily uſe to burn in- <lb/>ſtead of Candles; I wrapt about the End of this Splinter
        <lb/>ſome looſe Lint, and thruſt it into the Wound, and by <lb/>turning and winding it, I
        drew out above two Yards in <lb/>Length of a Subſtance thicker than any Gellie, or ra-
        <lb/>ther like Glue that's freſh made and hung out to dry; <lb/>the Breadth of it was above
        ten Inches; this was fol- <lb/>lowed by nine full Quarts of ſuch Matter, as I have <lb/>met
        with in Steatomatous and Artheromatous Tumours, <lb/>with ſeveral <hi rend="italic"
          >Hydatides</hi>, of various Sizes, containing a <lb/>yellowiſh <hi rend="italic"
          >Serum</hi>, the leaſt of 'em bigger than an O- <lb/>range, with ſeveral large Pieces of
        Membranes, which <lb/>ſeem'd to be Parts of the diſtended Ovary. Then I <lb/>ſqueez'd out
        all I could, and ſtitch'd up the Wound in <lb/>three Places, almoſt equi-diſtant: I was
        oblig'd to make <lb/>uſe of <hi rend="italic">Lucatellus</hi>'s Balſam, which was made by
        her <lb/>Lady for the Uſe of the Poor; with this Balſam I co- <lb/>vered a Pledget, the
        whole Length of the Wound, and <lb/>over that laid ſeveral Compreſſes, dipp'd in warm
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">French</hi> Brandy, and becauſe I judg'd that the Parts <lb/>might
        have loſt their Spring, by ſo vaſt and ſo long a <pb n="11"/>
        <lb/>Diſtention, I dipt in the ſame Brandy a large Napkin <lb/>four times folded, and
        applied it over all the Dreſſings, <lb/>and with a couple of ſtrong Towels, which were alſo
        <lb/>dipt, I ſwathed her round the Body, and then gave her <lb/>about four Ounces of the
        following Mixture, which I <lb/>had from her Lady. </p>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>℞ <hi rend="italic">Aq. Menthæ</hi> ℔ ſs. <hi rend="italic">Aq. Cinnamomi fort.</hi>
          ℔ iſs. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Syr. Diacodii</hi> ℥ vi. <hi rend="italic">M.</hi>
        </p></body>
      </floatingText>
      <p>
        <lb/>The Cinnamon-Water was drawn off from Canary and <lb/>the beſt Cinnamon; indeed it was
        the fineſt and most <lb/>fragrant Cinnamon-Water I ever taſted; of this Mixture <lb/>I
        ordered her 2 or 3 Spoonfuls 4 times a Day. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Next Morning I found her in a breathing Sweat, and <lb/>ſhe informed me, with great
        Tokens of Joy, that <lb/>ſhe had not ſlept ſo much, nor found herſelf ſo well re-
        <lb/>freſh'd, at any Time for three Months paſt. I carefully <lb/>attended her once every
        Day, and as conſtantly dreſſed <lb/>her Wound in the ſame Manner as above, for about
        <lb/>eight Days together; I kept in the lower Part of the <lb/>Wound a ſmall Tent, which
        diſcharged ſome Seroſities <lb/>at every Dreſſing for 4 or 5 Days. But Buſineſs calling
        <lb/>me elſewhere, I left her, having firſt inſtructed her two <lb/>Daughters (both Women,
        who carefully attended her) <lb/>how to dreſs her Wound, and told 'em what Diet I
        <lb/>thought moſt proper, enjoining 'em ſtrictly to obſerve <lb/>what I order'd. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Her chief Food was ſtrong Broth made of an old <lb/>Cock, in each Porringer of which
        was one Spoonful of <lb/>the Lady's Cinnamon-Water; this was repeated 4 times <lb/>a day,
        and gave her new Life and Spirits. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After three Weeks Abſence, I called at her Houſe, <lb/>and finding it ſhut up, was a
        little ſurpriz'd, but had <lb/>not gone far before I was much more ſurprized, when <lb/>I
        found her ſitting wrapt up in Blankets, giving Dire- <lb/>ctions to ſome Labourers who were
        cutting down her <lb/>Corn. </p>
      <pb n="12"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>She mended apace to the Admiration of every body <lb/>thereabouts, recovered
        ſurprizingly, and lived in perfect <lb/>Health from that time, which was in <hi
          rend="italic">Auguſt</hi> 1701, <lb/>till <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 1714. when ſhe
        died in ten Days Sickneſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That this Tumour, or rather Dropſy of the <hi rend="italic">Ovari- <lb/>um</hi>,
        proceeded from the Midwife's Raſhneſs in pulling <lb/>away the <hi rend="italic"
          >Placenta</hi>, not knowing how to ſeparate it <lb/>from the <hi rend="italic">Uterus</hi>
        ſkilfully, ſeems to me plain from <lb/>what the Woman herſelf told me, and what fell out af-
        <lb/>terwards. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Placenta</hi> adhering faſt to the <hi rend="italic">Uterus</hi>,
        required <lb/>more Art to bring it away than ſhe was Miſtreſs of, <lb/>which probably
        induc'd her to uſe Violence; by which <lb/>ſhe forc'd down the <hi rend="italic">Fundus
          Uteri</hi>; ſo overſtrain'd the <lb/>Ligaments, and all that's appended to 'em; eſpecially
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Ligamentum latum</hi> of the left Side and its <hi rend="italic"
          >Ovari- <lb/>um</hi>, which may be reaſonably allow'd to have been <lb/>hurt in the
        Relaxation with the reſt. Hence the Ela- <lb/>ſticity of theſe læſed Parts was not only
        impair'd, but <lb/>the ſmall Lymphaticks ruptur'd, ſo that the extravaſa- <lb/>ted <hi
          rend="italic">Lympha</hi> ruſhing out, thicken'd, and not being able <lb/>to recirculate,
        dilated the injur'd <hi rend="italic">Ovarium</hi>, and thus <lb/>increas'd the Tumour, and
        the Parts being already ex- <lb/>ceſſively diſtended, and being no longer able to reſiſt the
        <lb/>new Influx of freſh Secretions, ruptur'd alſo, and by <lb/>Degrees augmented to that
        huge and enormous Bulk. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cyprianus</hi> in his Letter to Sir <hi rend="italic">Thomas
          Millington</hi>, <lb/>gives ſeveral Inſtances of the Miſchiefs committed by <lb/>Midwives,
        and other ignorant Perſons. When a <hi rend="italic">Pla- <lb/>centa</hi> adheres, then
        (ſays he) they tear all before 'em, <lb/>by pulling rudely, they force down the <hi
          rend="italic">Fundus Ute- <lb/>ri</hi>, conſequently do Violence to the <hi rend="italic"
          >Ovaria</hi> and other <lb/>Parts, whence follow Inflammations, <hi rend="italic"
          >&amp;c.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Foreſtus, l. 28. Obſ. 80.</hi> ſays, that an over-bold <lb/>Midwife
        pulled out the <hi rend="italic">Placenta</hi> too haſtily, and that <pb n="13"/>
        <lb/>the Woman preſently fell into a Swoon, and died im- <lb/>mediately. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Frederick Ruyſch</hi> attributes the Cauſe of a <hi rend="italic"
          >Pla- <lb/>centa</hi>'s adhering cloſe, to a central Inſertion of the Na- <lb/>vel-String
        into the <hi rend="italic">Placenta</hi>, in which Caſe it is hard <lb/>to ſeparate; a Train
        of diſmal Accidents attend thoſe <lb/>who, not knowing how to do it, venture to pull it a-
        <lb/>way by Force. <hi rend="italic">Vide Obſ. Anat. 97. </hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Dionis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">la Motte</hi> have made the ſame
        Remark, <lb/>by the latter of which we are told of innumerable <lb/>Accidents, which he has
        known happen to Women in <lb/>hard Labour, by the Raſhneſs and Ignorance of bold
        <lb/>Pretenders, who, without Rule, Precepts, Practice, or <lb/>any ſuitable Inſtructions,
        venture to practice Deliveries. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The aforeſaid <hi rend="italic">Ruyſch</hi> has a remarkable Inſtance of <lb/>the
        Effects of Violence in hard Labour: The Caſe is <lb/>curious. <hi rend="italic">Vide Obſ.
          Anat. 63. </hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Manget</hi>, in his <hi rend="italic">Theatrum Anat.</hi> tells us
        that in <lb/>all hard Labours, where the <hi rend="italic">Placenta</hi> ſticks, the Li-
        <lb/>gaments ſuffer more or leſs by a raſh and ignorant <lb/>Way of Pulling; Examples of
        which ſee in <hi rend="italic">Platerus</hi>'s <lb/><hi rend="italic">Obſ. lib. 3.
          Bartholin. Cent. 2. Hiſt. 91. Cent. 5. Hiſt. <lb/>19. Marchett. Anat. cap. 7.</hi> and
        others, of which <lb/><hi rend="italic">Blaſius</hi> has given us an ample Liſt in his
        Commenta- <lb/>ries on <hi rend="italic">Veſlingius</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He likewiſe tells us, that the <hi rend="italic">Ovaria</hi> grow to a <lb/>wonderful
        Bulk, and contain ſuch a huge Quantity of <lb/>Liquor, that they become dropſical, whereof
          <hi rend="italic">Skencki- <lb/>us</hi> in his <hi rend="italic">Obſ.</hi> has recorded
        many Examples, as hath <lb/><hi rend="italic">Riolan</hi>, and many others. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Munnicks</hi> in his <hi rend="italic">Bibliothec. Anat.</hi> gives
        us the Hi- <lb/>ſtory of a large Dropſy of the right <hi rend="italic">Ovarium</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Mortgagni</hi> has told us, that he has often met with <lb/>large
        Veſicles in the <hi rend="italic">Ovaria</hi>, and, in morbid Bodies, <lb/>ſometimes full of
        purulent Matter. </p>
      <pb n="14"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Sylvius. Ex lymphaticis læſis tam Virilium, quam <lb/>Muliebrium
          Teſticulorum, &amp;c. Hydrops particularis <lb/>excitari poteſt. </hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Veſlingius cap. 7.</hi> has often met with large Tu- <lb/>mours, from
        Obſtructions in the <hi rend="italic">Ovaria</hi> of Women. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Veſalius</hi> found in the right <hi rend="italic">Ovarium</hi>, 9 or
        10 <hi rend="italic">Glan- <lb/>dules</hi>, like Gooſe Eggs, with Matter not unlike the
        <lb/>Whites of Eggs, or rather thicker. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Gul. Ballon, paradig.</hi> vi. found an Impoſthume of the <lb/>Nature
        of a <hi rend="italic">Steatoma</hi>, near the <hi rend="italic">Collum Uteri</hi>; the Wo-
        <lb/>man had a large Tumour on her Side 16 Years, and had <lb/>only one <hi rend="italic"
          >Ovarium</hi>, which was ſhown as a wonderful <lb/>thing. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>At <hi rend="italic">Weſtminſter</hi>, about two Years ago, I opened the <lb/>Body of a
        Gentlewoman, about 60, whoſe left <hi rend="italic">Ova- <lb/>rium</hi>, of a great Bulk,
        weigh'd vi. ℔. to which ad- <lb/>her'd ſeveral <hi rend="italic">Hydatides</hi> like Pullets
        Eggs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hildan</hi> mentions an <hi rend="italic">Hydropick</hi> Tumour of
        the right <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ovarium</hi>, of a prodigious bulk, ſtuff'd with Hair, <hi
          rend="italic">vide <lb/>Gul. Fab. Hild. Cent. 5. Obſ. 48. Greg. Horſt. Tom. 2. <lb/>l. 4.
          Ob. 53.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ruyſch Obſ. Anat. 17.</hi> A Dropſie (ſays he) of the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Ovarium</hi>, or (if you pleaſe) of the Eggs, is an Affection, <lb/>or
        Diſeaſe, well enough known to others, but I am <lb/>afraid not ſo well conſider'd; Authors
        have agreed to <lb/>call it <hi rend="italic">Hydatis</hi>, with which name I ſhall reſt
        ſatisfied, <lb/>provided we agree about the ſubject of the Di- <lb/>ſtemper. I obſerve this,
        moſt frequently, if not al- <lb/>ways, to be the Egg, but ſo chang'd, and ſometimes
        <lb/>ſwell'd to ſuch a Bulk, that I have often ſeen them <lb/>larger than a Child's Head. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Drelincourt</hi> has given us a very full and exact Ac- <lb/>count of
        a Dropſie of the left <hi rend="italic">Ovarium</hi>, in a Lady of <lb/>35 Years. The
        Tumour, of an enormous Bulk, con- <lb/>tinu'd three Years. The Body of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Ovarium</hi>, with <lb/>all contain'd in it, weigh'd, 60 ℔. It was nothing <pb n="15"/>
        <lb/>but a number of little Globules, cluſter'd together, <lb/>that differ'd in their
        Roundneſs, Form, Colour, and <lb/>Conſiſtence, proceeding from little ſeminary Veſicles
        <lb/>in a Cluſter. Some had Water extremely clear and <lb/>liquid, others a yellowiſh <hi
          rend="italic">Serum</hi> thin, others a glu- <lb/>tinous Matter; ſome were as big as
        Pullets Eggs, <lb/>others bigger than one's Fiſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Let theſe few, out of the many Inſtances which <lb/>I could produce from Authors of
        undoubted Repu- <lb/>tation, ſuffice to prove, that the <hi rend="italic">Ovaria</hi>, as
        well as <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Tubæ Falloppianæ</hi>, Ligaments, and <hi rend="italic"
          >Uterus</hi> itſelf, <lb/>are not free from Dropſies, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> and
        that they pro- <lb/>ceed from Obſtructions, often occaſioned by rude and <lb/>violent
        dealing with Women in difficult Labours, <lb/>which generally bring on a train of diſmal
        Symptoms, <lb/>that ſooner or later, according to the Strength of <lb/>the Sufferer, after a
        miſerable, painful, languiſhing <lb/>Life, end in Death. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The manifeſt Succeſs in this uncommon Caſe may <lb/>be of uſe, and may ſhew, that we
        ought not to diſ- <lb/>pair too ſoon, in Diſtempers that are ſeemingly moſt <lb/>dangerous.
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
