<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Sprengell: Some Observations upon Dr. Eaton's Styptick</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Dr. Sprengell</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Some Observations upon Dr. Eaton's Styptick By Dr. Sprengell, R. S. S. Coll. Med.
              Lond. Lic.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed for W. and J. Innys, Printers to the Royal Society, at the
                  West End of St. Paul's.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1724-1725</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">33</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">108-114</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110356204</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1724.0021</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT33_0108">
    <body>
      <pb n="108"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">V.</hi> Some Obſervations upon Dr. <hi rend="roman">Eaton</hi>'s
        Styptick, <lb/>By Dr. <hi rend="roman">Sprengell</hi>, R. S. S. Coll. Med. Lond. <lb/>Lic. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE Method of curing freſh Wounds in a few <lb/>Days, without
        Suppuration, where neither <lb/>Nerves, large Veſſels, Bones, or any of the <hi
          rend="italic">Viſcera</hi>
        <lb/>were concerned, has been long ago obſerved. <hi rend="italic">Purman</hi>, <lb/>a
        famous Surgeon of <hi rend="italic">Breſlaw</hi>, in his <hi rend="italic">Chirurgia Curi-
          <lb/>oſa</hi>, tells us of a Mountebank, who gave himſelf thir- <lb/>teen Wounds, by
        Inciſion, in the upper Part of his <lb/>Left Arm, and thereupon applied his <hi
          rend="italic">Noſtrum</hi>, and <lb/>with the help of a good Roller, was cured in two
        <lb/>Days Time. Next he mentions a martial Styptick, <lb/>which ſtopped bleeding
        incomparably, and healed freſh <lb/>Wounds (as he ſays) in two Days time, eſpecially if
        <lb/>the Patient took withall a few Drops inwardly. This <lb/>has likewiſe been mentioned by
          <hi rend="italic">Blegny</hi> near thirty <lb/>Years ago. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When I came into <hi rend="italic">France</hi>, I found that many little <lb/>Trials
        were made there alſo, with a Styptick Ball <lb/>mixed with <hi rend="italic">French</hi>
        Brandy, by ſtriking a Cock thro' <lb/>the Head, opening the Crural-Artery of a Dog, or
        <lb/>chopping off a Dog's Leg, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> But I found that it <lb/>did
        not amount to any thing of Conſequence; yet I <lb/>have ſtill a Ball, made about twenty
        Years ago, of Fi- <lb/>lings of Iron, and an equal Quantity of Tartar, mix'd <lb/>well with
          <hi rend="italic">French</hi> Brandy upon a Marble. This, with <lb/>ſome Alteration, was
        afterwards publiſhed by the fa- <lb/>mous <hi rend="italic">Helvetius</hi>, Phyſician to <hi
          rend="italic">Lewis</hi> XIV of <hi rend="italic">France</hi>, <lb/>in a Book called, <hi
          rend="italic">Recueil des Methodes pour la Gueri- <lb/>ſon des diverſes Maladies</hi>,
        which was reprinted in <pb n="109"/>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Holland</hi> in the Year 1710. This Preparation was <lb/>then ſold by
          <hi rend="italic">Pierre Rottermond</hi>, Apothecary at the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Hague</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Holland</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Recipe</hi> for his Medicinal Ball I have tranſlated, <lb/>and is
        as follows: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Take four Pounds of the Filings of Steel, and eight <lb/>Pounds of Tartar, well
        powdered; mix theſe well <lb/>together, and put them in a new Earthen Pot, and <lb/>pour
        thereupon as much <hi rend="italic">French</hi> Brandy as will make <lb/>it into a Poulteſs.
        Let this ſtand fermenting in a Cel- <lb/>lar for four Days, and ſtir it between whiles. Then
        <lb/>put it in <hi rend="italic">Baln-Mar</hi>, and diſtill it <hi rend="italic">S. A.</hi>
        with a mode- <lb/>rate Fire, to draw off the Brandy. When you find <lb/>that nothing but the
        Phlegm comes over, then take <lb/>it from the Fire, and take out the Maſs, ſtamp it very
        <lb/>fine, that not the leaſt Lump may remain; then mix <lb/>it again as before with a
        ſufficient Quantity of Bran- <lb/>dy, and put it in the Cellar to ferment, as before, and
        <lb/>then diſtill it a ſecond Time. This Operation may <lb/>be reiterated ſeven or eight
        times; but the laſt Time <lb/>mix your Maſs well upon a Marble, and form it into <lb/>two
        Ounce-Balls. One of theſe Balls is ſteeped in a <lb/>Pint of good <hi rend="italic"
          >French</hi> Brandy, a little warmed, and <lb/>hung only in it by a Wire, till the Brandy
        has received <lb/>the Colour of the Ball. But if you are in haſte, then <lb/>grate a
        ſufficient Quantity of the Ball in ſome Brandy, <lb/>ſtir it well, and you may uſe it that
        very Inſtant. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>No doubt but the Author thought by often grind- <lb/>ing, fermenting, and diſtilling
        this Maſs, to commi- <lb/>nute and ſubtilize its Particles, ſo as to make it more <lb/>fit
        to contract the Fibres and Veſſels of a Wound, <lb/>and to prevent Stagnations of the
        Fluids, both within <lb/>and without, upon Contuſions; but the Succeſs did <lb/><choice>
          <corr/>
          <sic>did </sic>
        </choice>not anſwer, and therefore it was laid aſide. Nei- <lb/>ther did <hi rend="italic"
          >Helvetius</hi> ever recommend it as an Univerſal <pb n="110"/>
        <lb/>Styptick, aſtringent, or conſolidating Medicine, but <lb/>meerly in freſh Wounds, and
        that only for a firſt Dreſ- <lb/>ſing, and where People lived at a Diſtance, and could
        <lb/>not get immediate Aſſiſtance from a Surgeon. Beſides, <lb/>he makes ſeveral Exceptions
        where it ſhould not be <lb/>uſed; and, in general, adviſes it where Chalybeat Me-
        <lb/>dicines may be made uſe of according to Experi- <lb/>ence. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But laſt Year a Balſamick Styptick was publiſhed by <lb/>one Dr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Eaton</hi>, good to ſtop all manner of Bleeding <lb/>without or within, and that without
        any manner of <lb/>Exceptions. This made me deſirous to ſee it, and as it <lb/>happened that
        ſoon after I had an Opportunity to ex- <lb/>amine it: I found preſently that this was the
        ſame old <lb/>Medicine, which was got hither alſo, after other <lb/>Countries had diſcarded
        it. But I neglected it at that <lb/>Time, as not worthy my notice, till I ſaw lately a Trea-
        <lb/>tiſe of Conſumptions, publiſhed by Sir <hi rend="italic">Richard Black- <lb/>more</hi>,
        Kt. giving Dr. <hi rend="italic">Eaton</hi>'s Styptick the greateſt <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Encomium</hi>, that ever was given to any Invention what- <lb/>ſoever. For, ſays he, <q
          rend="italic">Dr. <hi rend="roman">Eaton</hi>'s Balſamick Styp- <lb/>tick bids fair for
          the Credit of a certain Remedy in <lb/>ſtopping of Blood outwardly or inwardly, where the
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">Craſis</hi> of the Blood is not entirely ruined; and will <lb/>be
          of more Service to Mankind, than all the Diſco- <lb/>veries made by Galenical Compounders
          of Drugs, and <lb/>Syſtematical Methodiſts. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Finding this Remedy recommended in ſo extra- <lb/>ordinary a manner, by ſo eminent a
        Phyſician, <lb/>I began now to think, that poſſibly I might have <lb/>been miſtaken, and
        therefore deſired Mr. <hi rend="italic">Win- <lb/>terbottom</hi>, and Apothecary in <hi
          rend="italic">Bow-Lane</hi>, imme- <lb/>diately to prepare the <hi rend="italic"
          >Recipe</hi>, as deſcibed by <hi rend="italic">Helve- <lb/>tius</hi>. When this was ready,
        I ſent for a Bottle of Dr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Eaton</hi>'s Styptick, and tryed them both
        with Galls, be- <pb n="111"/>
        <lb/>fore ſeveral Gentlemen; the Tincture was the ſame, <lb/>a deep Purple. I then
        precipitated the Contents with <lb/>old Hock, and found the precipitated Matter to be the
        <lb/>ſame in both. Not contented with my own Enquiry, <lb/>I ſent ſeveral ſmall Quantities
        to others, and went my <lb/>ſelf to Mr. <hi rend="italic">Godfrey</hi>, a famous Chymiſt in
          <hi rend="italic">Covent- <lb/>Garden</hi>. They all told me, that there was no Diffe-
        <lb/>rence betwixt them. I tryed ſeveral ways to find out <lb/>its Balſamick Quality, from
        whence it has its Name, <lb/>but found none. Then, I conſeſs, it ſurprized me, <lb/>that a
        Man who had a mind to vend a thing as a Secret, <lb/>had not done ſo much as to alter it
        either in Taſte, <lb/>Smell, or Colour; and yet this might very well have <lb/>been done,
        without robbing it of its Virtue in the <lb/>leaſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>My next Buſineſs was to try theſe two upon the <lb/>Crural-Artery. Having got a good
        middle-ſiz'd Dog, <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Ranby</hi>, Surgeon, laid the Artery bare, and
        open'd <lb/>it with a Lancet the length Way of the Artery, for <lb/>near half an Inch. The
        old Trick uſed to be, to cut <lb/>the Artery croſs ways, and then there was no neceſſi-
        <lb/>ty of a Styptick at all, nor indeed here neither. But <lb/>at firſt <hi rend="italic"
          >Helvetius</hi> his Tincture was applied, and ſtopped <lb/>the Bleeding; then we opened
        the Artery again, and <lb/>tryed Dr. <hi rend="italic">Eaton</hi>'s, with the ſame Succeſs.
        I then had <lb/>the Artery opened in the other Thigh, and tryed it <lb/>only with <hi
          rend="italic">French</hi> Brandy, which, I found, did as <lb/>well as the other two. I
        opened the Artery again, <lb/>and had diſſolved in <hi rend="italic">French</hi> Brandy a
        little <hi rend="italic">Sal Martis</hi>
        <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Saccharum Saturni</hi>, and applied that, and it an- <lb/>ſwered
        in the ſame manner. This made me immedi- <lb/>ately conjecture, that there was but little
        Virtue in <lb/>either of them, but only that the Brandy, by its great <lb/>Heat, did meerly
        contract the Fibres of the Artery, <lb/>which, no doubt, might be a little aſſiſted by the
          <hi rend="italic">Cha-</hi>
        <pb n="112"/>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">lybs</hi>; but this could not be much. I then reflected <lb/>upon the
        ſmallneſs of the Crural Artery in a Dog, and <lb/>that it was no more to be compared to the
        Crural Ar- <lb/>tery of a Man, than a Cock's-Head to a Man's Head, <lb/>and that a little
        Pledget of Lint might ſtop the Blood <lb/>without more to do, as well as the Temporal Artery
        <lb/>when opened with a Lancet, which we did, and the <lb/>Pledget of Lint ſtopped it. We
        then untied the Dog, <lb/>and ſent him going, who ran directly Home to the <lb/>Crown Tavern
        in <hi rend="italic">Bloomſbury</hi>, from whence we had <lb/>taken him. The Miſtreſs of the
        Houſe tore off the <lb/>Pledgets, and had the Dog well waſh'd with Butter <lb/>and Beer
        warmed, ſhe not knowing what had been <lb/>done to him, upon which the Dog fell a Bleeding
        a- <lb/>gain, though not much, and the Blood ſtopp'd of it <lb/>ſelf: Mr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Ranby</hi> and I ſaw the Dog in the Evening <lb/>very well, but he ran away at the Sight
        of us. Thus <lb/>far as to its outward Uſe, and I could wiſh it were as <lb/>harmleſs
        within. If only, according to <hi rend="italic">Helvetius</hi>, it <lb/>had been ordered to
        be taken inwardly, in freſh <lb/>Wounds and Contuſions, a Body might have let it <lb/>paſs;
        but when, without Exception, Dr. <hi rend="italic">Eaton</hi> recom- <lb/>mended it, as alſo
        even Sir <hi rend="italic">Richard</hi>, in all inward Bleed- <lb/>ings, I then thought it
        high Time to make ſome Anim- <lb/>adverſions upon it. For Sir <hi rend="italic">Richard</hi>
        himſelf ſays, <lb/>in his Treatiſe of Conſumptions, <hi rend="italic">p.</hi> 99 and 101,
        That <lb/>in Spitting of Blood there is an Orgaſm, or ſtimulating <lb/>Ferment: What is this
        but a Feveriſh Indiſpoſition? <lb/>And is there any Hermorrhage without? Now, if ſo,
        <lb/>will not Brandy and Chalybeats heighten this? Which <lb/>by their Heat and <hi
          rend="italic">Stimuli</hi> brace and irritate the Fibres, <lb/>and accelerate the Blood's
        Motion. And will not then <lb/>the Blood take up more Room, and preſs harder againſt
        <lb/>the Sides of the Veſſels, and whatſoever oppoſes it? <pb n="113"/>
        <lb/>Is not this the Way to make an Orgaſm, and cauſe an <lb/>Hemorrhage? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Eaton</hi> tells us himſelf in his Book, <hi rend="italic"
          >p.</hi> 57, That <lb/>it did very much over-heat a Gentlewoman, and that <lb/>her
        Bleeding ſtill continued after the taking of it, and <lb/>ſhe might have periſhed if a
        Surgeon had not given <lb/>her a cooling and aſtringent Apozeme. And but juſt <lb/>before,
          <hi rend="italic">p.</hi> 47, he complains of a Phyſician, that was <lb/>not willing that
        his Patient ſhould take it, who had a <lb/>Hectick Fever upon her, becauſe he was afraid
        that <lb/>it was too hot. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Since the former Tryals, on the 10th of <hi rend="italic">June</hi> laſt, <lb/>I
        deſired Mr. <hi rend="italic">Ranby</hi>, Surgeon, to open the Carotide <lb/>Artery of a
        Dog, thinking that this Artery might give <lb/>me more Satisfaction than the Crural Arteries
        had <lb/>done, to try the Styptick Quality of <hi rend="italic">Helvetius</hi> and <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Eaton</hi>'s Tinctures. Having laid bare the Jugular <lb/>Vein, divided, and
        tied it, that its Bleeding might not <lb/>hinder us from finding the Carotide Artery, we
        were <lb/>obliged to cut ſome of the Muſcles through likewiſe, <lb/>till, with ſome
        Difficulty, we found the Artery; which <lb/>being opened with a Lancet, the Blood ſpouting
        <lb/>forth, I applied to it <hi rend="italic">Helvetius</hi>'s Tincture, upon <lb/>which the
        Blood ſtopp'd. I took it off in leſs than a <lb/>Minute, and made it bleed again, but it
        bled but little, <lb/>and then I applied Dr. <hi rend="italic">Eaton</hi>'s Styptick; we
        fill'd up <lb/>the Wound with Lint, and ſtitched up the <hi rend="italic">Cutis</hi>, then
        <lb/>untied the Dog and let him run down Stairs, where, <lb/>after ſome Time, I ſaw him
        again, and found he had <lb/>bled a good deal, and was ſtill bleeding. I was very <lb/>well
        ſatisfied that, the Artery being ſo very ſmall, he <lb/>would not bleed to Death, and if he
        had had nothing <lb/>but Lint upon it, it would have done as well. It muſt <lb/>be obſerved,
        that the Carotide Arteries are largeſt in <lb/>Proportion in Human Bodies, and that this Ar-
          <pb n="114"/>
        <lb/>tery of the Dog was but a ſmall matter bigger <lb/>than the Crural Arteries of the
        former Dog. This <lb/>ſhews, that the Styptick Quality of theſe Tinctures is <lb/>very
        inconſiderable; and that <hi rend="italic">Helvetius</hi>'s Tincture is <lb/>rather better
        than Dr. <hi rend="italic">Eaton</hi>'s, if there is any Diffe- <lb/>rence at all; though
        that, I believe, was owing to the <lb/>Brandy, for my Brandy was ſtronger than Dr. <hi
          rend="italic">Eaton</hi>'s. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I enquired for the Dog the next Morning, and found <lb/>him alive and well, only
        hanging his Head on one <lb/>Side, which proceeded from the Muſcles being cut <lb/>through.
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
