<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Beard: An Account of a Person Kill'd by Lightning at Worcester</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>R. Beard</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of a Person Kill'd by Lightning at Worcester, Communicated in a Letter
              to the Publisher, by R. Beard, M. D. R. S. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed for W. and J. Innys, Printers to the Royal Society, at the
                  West End of St. Paul's.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1726-1727</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">34</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">118-121</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110111944</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1726.0018</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT34_0118">
    <body>
      <pb n="118"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VI.</hi> An Account of a Perſon kill'd by Lightning <lb/>at <hi
          rend="roman">Worceſter</hi>, communicated in a Letter to the <lb/>Publiſher, by <hi
          rend="roman">R. Beard, M. D. R. S. S. </hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="indentall hanging italic space size(0.9)">
        <lb/>The following Account was given to a Gentleman at the <lb/>time the Affair happened;
        but not knowing whether it <lb/>deſerv'd your Conſideration, I deferr'd ſending it till
        <lb/>you were pleas'd to deſire it. </p>
      <div>
        <dateline rend="align-right space size(0.7)">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worceſter, June</hi> 11, 1724. </dateline>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">W</hi>E had laſt Night continu'd Lightning in the Eaſt <lb/>from
          Eight o' clock to Twelve; the Weather <lb/>for ſome time before having been very ſultry,
          the Wind <lb/>at N. E. and the Barometer at ſettled Fair. This Mor- <lb/>ning the Mercury
          ſunk, and the Sky became more <lb/>Cloudy and Temperate, except a few hot Gleams; at
          <lb/>Two in the Afternoon, ſeveral fierce Showers fell, <lb/>attended with Flaſhes of
          Lightning and Claps of Thun- <lb/>der, that ſtill approach'd nearer us: Between Two and
          <lb/>Three, a Flaſh came ſo violently upon me, ſucceeded <lb/>ſo very quick by a low,
          unuſual, dreadful Sound, that <lb/>I immediately went to the door, fearing ſome Miſ-
          <lb/>chief near. I was ſoon call'd to an Officer's Lady (a- <lb/>ged about 18, and
          breeding) kill'd by it in the adjoyn- <lb/>ing Street. I found her yet warm, and that ſhe
          had <lb/>ſurvived the Stroke for 6 or 7 Minutes. The Fire-Marks <lb/>they ſhew'd me, were
          Streaks of a Copper-Colour, bran- <lb/>ched from the Left Shoulder all-over the <hi
            rend="italic">Thorax</hi>, and <lb/>interſperſed here and there with irregular Spots,
          which <lb/>gave occaſion for that Conceit publiſh'd in our News, <pb n="119"/>
          <lb/>that <q rend="italic">curious Plants were drawn on her Boſom, as with the <lb/>fineſt
            Pencil </q>. This fad Accident happen'd in a Par- <lb/>lour-Window next the Street, that
          could contain about <lb/>two Perſons: The Lady, it ſeems, terrified with the <lb/>repeated
          Lightning and Thunder, (it having formerly <lb/>been fatal to her Brother) deſir'd an
          Officer to change <lb/>Places with her, that ſhe might be near her Husband; <lb/>but ſhe
          was no ſooner ſeated by his ſide, than ſhe in- <lb/>clined ſide-ways, and ſpoke ſome
          Words; after ſhe was <lb/>carried to another Room, ſhe ſaid, ſhe was gone, and <lb/>then,
          that ſhe was blind, and ask'd for Water. The <lb/>Husband was thrown along, together with
          the fortu- <lb/>nate Gentleman that had juſt reſign'd his Seat; and a <lb/>large
          Looking-Glaſs was lifted off the Hooks. The <lb/>Landlord's Daughter, at work near the
          Lady, perceiv'd <lb/>ſuch an Impulſe on the ſide of her Head that her <lb/>Hearing was
          much impair'd, <q rend="italic">and upon every Peal of <lb/>Thunder ſince ſhe is affected
            in like manner, tho' not ſo ſtrong- <lb/>ly </q>. The Gentlemen complained, that they
          were ſtu- <lb/>pified, forced down they did not know why, unleſs it <lb/>were for want of
          Breath; and of Pains and Numbneſs <lb/>in their Limbs. They had likewiſe on different
          Parts <lb/>of their Bodies ſuch reddiſh Wheals as were ſeen on the <lb/>Fair Lady's
          Breaſt: But theſe Symptoms vaniſhed the <lb/>next Day. The other two Perſons at the
          further End <lb/>of the Room were untouch'd; they were all ſenſible <lb/>of a ſulphurous
          Smell. The Pane of Glaſs exactly <lb/>behind the Lady's Waſt, was perforated by a round
          <lb/>Hole of an Inch and half Diameter, as if done with a <lb/>Diamond, or rather a
          Wind-Gun; but nowhere there- <lb/>abouts could I diſcern the leaſt Traces of Fire, or
          <lb/>Heat, nor on the Lady's Clothes (having no Stayes <lb/>on) the Signs of any Violence.
          On a more nice Ex- <lb/>amination of the Body, in the Preſence of the Friends, <lb/>that
          Evening, I diſcovered on the left Loin, taking in <pb n="120"/>
          <lb/>part of the Spine of the <hi rend="italic">Os Ilium</hi>, which was <lb/>ſomewhat
          ſwoln, a deep Contuſion of the ſame Di- <lb/>menſion with the Breach in the Glaſs: The
          Skin was <lb/>neither indurated, nor pierc'd: The Blood in the Ca- <lb/>pillaries all
          round, but chiefly up the Back, ſettled, the <lb/>Colour of which was eaſily diſtinguiſhed
          from that of <lb/>the Streaks, and the circular Impreſſion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Phænomenon</hi>, that cauſed this Misfortune, roſe <lb/>from
          the N. E. firſt ſlid off the Gabel-Beam, and the <lb/>Bricks on the back part of the next
          Houſe, fill'd a lit- <lb/>tle Court with Flame and Smoke, then turned a Lead- <lb/>en
          Spout contrary to its former Direction, mounted o- <lb/>ver the Roof, and, cracking a
          Stack of Chimneys, <lb/>dropt down at the Window where the Husband and <lb/>Wife ſate.
          Some credible People that ſaw it, to their <lb/>great Terrour, aſſure me, that it was a
          Ball of Fire, <lb/>and that it burſt with the loudeſt Report they ever <lb/>heard, and
          then with a hiſſing Noiſe, paſs'd about a <lb/>Yard from the Ground through an adjacent
          Street, and <lb/>rowl'd off to<choice>
            <corr/>
            <sic> to</sic>
          </choice> the S. W. Some Workmen there, and <lb/>on a neighbouring Hill, obſerved the
          ſame. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In my Opinion, the Mortality of this Blow may be <lb/>accounted for from the known
          Effects of impriſon'd <lb/>Air only, when ſet at liberty, as the Appearances on <lb/>the
          Skin may, from other active Particles hurried along <lb/>with it at the time of the
          Exploſion. The <hi rend="italic">Impetus</hi> being <lb/>firſt received on the Parts
          deſcrib'd, occaſioned her Death <lb/>to be leſs ſudden than uſual in ſuch Caſes. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline rend="space align-right">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worceſter, June</hi> 4, 1726. </dateline>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>We have had more Lightning and Thunder the Week <lb/>paſt, than ever has been known
          in that ſpace of time: <lb/>And what was more extraordinary, the Continuance of <lb/>it
          for 9 or 10 Hours together, with little or no Inter- <lb/>miſſion, and at ſuch a height
          above us. So far has this <pb n="121"/>
          <lb/>been from doing any great Damage near us, that <lb/>in the Opinion of the
          Country-Farmers, it had very <lb/>good Effects, eſpecially at the beginning during the
          <lb/>Heat: For the little Inſects, that in ſome Places <lb/>threaten'd the Deſtruction of
          the Hops and ſome other <lb/>Plants, fell off like Bees by the Steam of a lighted
          <lb/>Match. I know not whether this has been obſerv'd <lb/>to you before; but I ſaw ſuch
          remarkable Inſtances <lb/>of it in certain Situations, that I could not help giv- <lb/>ing
          you this ſhort Account of it. </p>
      </div>
      <signed rend="italic space align-right">
        <lb/>I am, <hi rend="roman">&amp;c. </hi>
        <lb/>R. Beard. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
