<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Kinneir: Touching the Efficacy of Camphire in Maniacal
          Disorders</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>David Kinneir</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Copy of a Letter from Dr. David Kinneir, Coll. Med. Edingb. Soc. to Dr.
              Campbell, Coll. Med. Lond. Soc. Honorar. Touching the Efficacy of Camphire in Maniacal
              Disorders</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for W. Innys, Printer to the Royal Society, at the
                  West End of St. Paul's.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1727-1728</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">35</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">347-351</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO"/>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1727.0017</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT35_0347">
    <body>
      <pb n="347"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">IV.</hi> A Copy of a Letter from Dr. <hi rend="roman">David Kinneir,
          <lb/>Coll. Med. Edingb. Soc.</hi> to Dr. <hi rend="roman">Campbell, Coll. <lb/>Med. Lond.
          Soc. Honorar.</hi> touching the Effica- <lb/>cy of <hi rend="roman">Camphire</hi> in <hi
          rend="roman">Maniacal</hi> Diſorders. </head>
      <salute rend="space indent italic">
        <lb/>SIR, </salute>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N Converſation, t'other Day, on the Subject of our
        <lb/>Profeſſion, I told you how ſucceſsfully I had us'd <lb/>Camphire in <hi rend="italic"
          >Maniac</hi> Diſorders, which hitherto never <pb n="348"/>
        <lb/>has fail'd my Expectation in the <hi rend="italic">Mania</hi>, and other Ca- <lb/>ſes
        wherein the <hi rend="italic">Genus Nervoſum</hi> and Blood ſeem to <lb/>be affected after
        the ſame Manner, but in a leſs Degree. <lb/>At your Requeſt, I ſend you the Hiſtory of Four
        Caſes, <lb/>with all the Exactneſs my Memory can afford. I own <lb/>I flatter my ſelf, that
        from the Effects of this Medicine <lb/>Phyſicians may be led into a more ſure Way of Reaſon-
        <lb/>ing in <hi rend="italic">Nervous Diſorders</hi>, and therefore give you Leave <lb/>to
        publiſh theſe Hiſtories, if you think they may be of <lb/>Uſe to the Publick. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I. A <hi rend="italic">Gentlewoman of Nineteen Years of Age</hi>, from <lb/>an
        obſtinate Faſting for Two Days, and Averſion to ſee <lb/>Company, in a religious Turn before
          <hi rend="italic">Eaſter</hi>, fell into <lb/>a deep Melancholy, would not talk, nor
        anſwer any <lb/>Queſtion for ſome Time, but moan'd and ſigh'd conti- <lb/>nually; ſlept very
        little for Ten Days. This happen'd <lb/>in the <hi rend="italic">Decline</hi> of the Moon.
        The Night before the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Change</hi> ſhe ſpoke, and call'd for ſome Water
        to drink, <lb/>which being given her, ſhe immediately fell a ſtarting <lb/>and laughing, and
        her Eyes got a Briskneſs in them <lb/>ſomewhat uncommon, (as her Relations told me) then
        <lb/>began to talk wildly, and continu'd ſo all that Night<choice>
          <corr>.</corr>
          <sic>,</sic>
        </choice>
        <lb/>She became next Morning very furious; whereupon a <lb/>Phyſician was call'd, who bled
        her Four Times a Week <lb/>the firſt Fourteen Days, vomited her, purg'd her, us'd <lb/>the
          <hi rend="italic">Cold Bath</hi>, and many other Methods common in <lb/>ſuch Caſes, all to
        no Purpoſe. In this Condition ſhe <lb/>continu'd for Nine Months; then I was apply'd to. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I firſt began her with an Antimonial Vomit, which had <lb/>no other Effect than that of
        ſetting her faſt aſleep for <lb/>Twelve Hours. Next Day I gave her half a Dram of <hi
          rend="italic">Cam- <lb/>phire</hi> in a <hi rend="italic">Bolus</hi>, and as much at
        Night. She continu'd <lb/>to reſt well all that Night, and had a great Moiſtneſs all <pb
          n="349"/>
        <lb/>over her Body, and in the Day-time a plentiful Diſcharge <lb/>by Urine. Thus for Four
        Days I ply'd her, and after- <lb/>wards, in the Day-time, I order'd her Pills of <hi
          rend="italic">Æthiops, <lb/>Gum-guaiac. Cinnab. Antim. &amp; pulv. de Gutteta</hi>; and
        <lb/>at Night, the Doſe of <hi rend="italic">Camphire</hi>. Senſible Alterations <lb/>every
        Day for the better, and in Three Weeks Time ſhe <lb/>enjoy'd the full Uſe of her Reaſon, and
        tho' Nine Years <lb/>ago, at this Time is in a very good State of Health, <lb/>having no
        extraordinary Ailing ever ſince. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>II. A <hi rend="italic">Gentleman</hi> of a good Family, <hi rend="italic">aged
          Seventeen <lb/>Years</hi>, (from ſome Diſappointment) became very ſilly <lb/>and ſtupid.
        He continu'd in that Way for a long Time, <lb/>notwithſtanding he had the beſt Advice. He
        had a <lb/>great Inclination to chaw and eat every thing that came <lb/>in his Way, be it
        what it would. He reſted pretty <lb/>well a Nights, and was delighted with the Sight of
        <lb/>every glaring Object. He hid every thing he could lay <lb/>his Hands on, as well in
        Company as alone, and not <lb/>any ways ill-natur'd. Thus for Half a Year he con-
        <lb/>tinu'd, when he became ſo furious, that Two Men <lb/>could hardly hold him from beating
        every Body that <lb/>came about him. Thus he would continue for Three <lb/>or Four Days
        together, without ſleeping; then he would <lb/>become calmer, after having ſlept ſome Time;
        but was <lb/>a little miſchievous. This was the Way from <hi rend="italic">New
          <lb/>Moon</hi> till the <hi rend="italic">Full</hi>; then he became ſilly and melan-
        <lb/>cholly, ſpeaking little, and looking always down, not <lb/>caring to look one in the
        Face. So it was <hi rend="italic">alternately</hi>
        <lb/>for Fourteen Months. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When I came to him, I found him full of Complaints <lb/>of his ill Treatment; and had
        not I had a watchful <lb/>Eye upon him, I had ſuffer'd from a Blow intended at <lb/>me; but
        I got him to take the <hi rend="italic">Medicines</hi> as <hi rend="italic">before</hi>, <pb
          n="350"/>
        <lb/>and with allowing him a more plentiful Diet, and a <lb/>great Quantity of <hi
          rend="italic">Diluting Drinks</hi>, he became per- <lb/>fectly well in Six Weeks, and has
        enjoy'd a good State <lb/>of Health and ſound Judgement theſe ſeveral Years, and <lb/>is now
        in Buſineſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>III. A <hi rend="italic">Mercer</hi>'s <hi rend="italic">Wife</hi> of <hi rend="italic"
          >Thirty Six Years of Age</hi>, <lb/>having born Four Children, and who was naturally of
        <lb/>a lively, active Diſpoſition, fell ſo ill, all of a ſudden, <lb/>One Day at Sermon,
        that with much ado they could <lb/>get her out of Church with common Decency. She <lb/>tore
        every thing about her, talk'd much, and utter'd <lb/>horrid Oaths. In Fine, ſhe was as much
        diſorder'd as <lb/>you can imagine any one. She had the beſt Advice, <lb/>'twas thought,
        that <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh</hi> could give her. They <lb/>fail'd of Succeſs, and left
        off viſiting her. About Half <lb/>a Year thereafter I was conſulted about her. I treated
        <lb/>her in the <hi rend="italic">foregoing</hi> Manner, and in Four Days there <lb/>was a
        ſenſible Alteration for the better, and in Four <lb/>more ſhe went abroad. I ſtill continu'd
        the Uſe of the <lb/>Medicines for Fourteen Days after Recovery, and now <lb/>ſhe is as well
        as ever ſhe was in her Life. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>IV. A <hi rend="italic">young Man, aged Twenty</hi>, of a full Habit, <lb/>was ſo very
        bad in the ſullen, deſpairing Way, wound- <lb/>ing himſelf with his Teeth and Hands, that
        there was <lb/>a Neceſſity of cloſe watching him. I <hi rend="italic">vomited</hi> him
        <lb/>twice, gave him ſome other Things common in ſuch <lb/>Caſes; then began him with the
          <hi rend="italic">Camphire</hi>, which in <lb/>Ten Days brought him to Reaſon. He relaps'd
        after <lb/>that on the <hi rend="italic">Change</hi> of the Moon, was ill for Three Days,
        <lb/>but not ſo as before. He came out of it again, and <lb/>ſtood the <hi rend="italic"
          >Change</hi> of the next Moon with only a little <lb/>Heavineſs, as in the <hi
          rend="italic">Hypo</hi>. At the Height of the ſame <lb/>Moon, the Day before, he was very
        uneaſy, and ſeem'd <pb n="351"/>
        <lb/>to reſemble a Perſon greatly <hi rend="italic">hypochondriac</hi>. I ſtill con-
        <lb/>tinu'd to him the <hi rend="italic">Camphire</hi>, and the other <hi rend="italic"
          >alterative <lb/>Medicines</hi>, for ſome Time, but in a much ſmaller Doſe <lb/>than what
        I gave him in his Illneſs: So in Nine Weeks <lb/>he was perfectly cur'd, and continues in
        good Health. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This, Sir, is the Subſtance of what I remember of <lb/>the preceding Caſe, wherein I
        lay'd the whole Streſs of <lb/>the Cure on <hi rend="italic">Camphire</hi>. </p>
      <signed rend="italic align-right">
        <lb/>I am, <hi rend="roman">&amp;c.</hi>
      </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
