<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Hall and Sloane: An Account of Some Experiments on the Effects of the
          Poison of the Rattle-Snake</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Captain Hall</persName>
              <persName>Hans Sloane</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of Some Experiments on the Effects of the Poison of the Rattle-Snake.
              By Captain Hall. Communicated by Sir Hans Sloane, Bar. Med Reg &amp;c. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for W. Innys, Printer to the Royal Society, at the
                  West End of St. Paul's.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1727-1728</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">35</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">309-315</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO"/>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1727.0008</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT35_0309">
    <body>
      <pb n="309"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VII.</hi> An Account of ſome Experiments on the Ef- <lb/>fects of the
        Poiſon of the <hi rend="roman">Rattle-Snake</hi>, By <lb/>Captain <hi rend="roman"
        >Hall</hi>. Communicated by Sir <hi rend="roman">Hans <lb/>Sloane, Bar. Med. Reg.</hi>
        &amp;c. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N <hi rend="italic">South Carolina</hi> on the 10<hi
          rend="italic">th</hi> of <hi rend="italic">May</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Anno</hi> 1720,
        <lb/>having got a fine healthful Rattle-Snake about four <lb/>feet long, I perſwaded three
        or four Gentlemen, and <lb/>one Mr. <hi rend="italic">Kidwell</hi> a Surgeon, to aſſiſt me
        in making <lb/>ſome Experiments on the Effects of its Poiſon. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We got three Curr-Dogs, the biggeſt not larger than <lb/>a common Harrier, and the
        leaſt about the bigneſs <lb/>of the largeſt ſiz'd Lap-Dog, all of them ſmooth hair- <lb/>ed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Snake being ty'd and pinn'd down to a Graſs- <lb/>plat, we took the largeſt of
        them, which was a white <lb/>one, and having tied a Chord round his Neck, ſo that <lb/>it
        ſhould not ſtrangle him, another Perſon held one <lb/>end while I held the other; the length
        was not <lb/>more than four Yards each way from the Dog. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Immediately on our bringing the Dog over the <lb/>Snake, the Snake raiſed himſelf near
        two feet, and <lb/>bit the Dog as he was jumping; the Dog yelpt, by <lb/>which I perceived
        he was bitten; and upon it I pull'd <lb/>him to me, as faſt as I could, and perceived his
        Eyes <lb/>fixt, his Tongue between his Teeth, which were clo- <lb/>ſed, his Lips ſo drawn up
        as to leave his Teeth and <lb/>Gums bare: In ſhort, he was quite Dead in a quarter <lb/>of a
        Minute; but one Perſon (beſide my ſelf) was <lb/>of Opinion it was in half that time: The
        firſt <lb/>was the Opinion of the By-ſtanders, who were five or <choice>
          <corr>
            <pb n="310"/>
          </corr>
          <sic>
            <pb n="301"/>
          </sic>
        </choice>
        <lb/>ſix; but I believe, none of them ſo much uſed to mea- <lb/>ſure time as the Gentleman
        and I were, from our <lb/>conſtant making uſe of the half Minute, and quarter <lb/>Minute
        Glaſs at Sea. We could not ſee where the <lb/>Dog was bitten, nor any Blood: Upon which we
        or- <lb/>dered ſome hot Water to ſcald the Hair off; when <lb/>we could find but one
        Puncture, which look'd of a <lb/>bluiſh Green a little round it; it was juſt between his
        <lb/>fore Leg, and his Breaſt; where (when the Legs are <lb/>diſtended) the Hair is much
        thinner than in ſome <lb/>other places. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Half an Hour after the firſt Bite we took a ſecond <lb/>Dog, which was ſomewhat leſs,
        of a Liver-Colour, <lb/>and in like manner brought him over the Sanke, <lb/>which in a very
        little time bit his Ear, ſo that we <lb/>all ſaw it; he yelpt very much, and ſoon ſhew'd the
        <lb/>ſigns of being very ſick, holding that Ear that was bit <lb/>uppermoſt. He reel'd and
        ſtagger'd about for ſome <lb/>time; then he fell down, and ſtruggl'd as if Convul- <lb/>ſed,
        and for two or three times got up, each time wag- <lb/>ging his Tail, tho' ſlowly, and
        attempting to follow a <lb/>Negro-Boy, who uſed to make much of him. We put <lb/>him into a
        Cloſet, and order'd the Boy to look after <lb/>him. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About an Hour after the ſecond was bitten, we <lb/>took the third Dog in like maner:
        the Snake bit <lb/>him on the right ſide of the Belly, about two Inches <lb/>behind the long
        Ribs; for we ſaw he had drawn <lb/>Blood there. The Dog at firſt, I mean for about a
        <lb/>Minute, ſeem'd not to be hurt; ſo we let him go, <lb/>being one we could get again when
        we pleaſed. For <lb/>that Day we put up the Snake, imagining his Poiſon <lb/>was very near,
        if not quite expended. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In a little time after, which was juſt two Hours af- <lb/>ter the ſecond Dog was bit,
        the Boy told us he was dead. </p>
      <pb n="311"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About an Hour after I perſwaded Mr. <hi rend="italic">Kidwell</hi> to open <lb/>him,
        and I was in no ſmall haſte to examine the Heart, <lb/>where I perſwaded my ſelf, I ſhould
        diſcover ſome- <lb/>thing extraordinary; but could not perceive any re- <lb/>markable
        Difference between that and many others <lb/>I had ſeen, where there was no Poiſon in the
        Caſe. <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Kidwell</hi> laid open the Skull, and was of Opinion,
        <lb/>that the Brain was more red and ſwoln than any he <lb/>had ever ſeen; and he told me a
        little while after, <lb/>that the Blood turn'd very black. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For that Day we heard no more of the third <lb/>Dog which was bitten; but the next
        morning the <lb/>Woman who own'd him came to me, complaining of <lb/>my Cruelty for killing
        her Dog. She did not know <lb/>when he died, but ſaid ſhe ſaw him at ſeven that
        <lb/>Evening, which was about 3 hours after he was bit; <lb/>and that he was ſo ſick he
        could ſcarce wagg his Tail. <lb/>None of theſe Dogs were ſwoln before they died. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On <hi rend="italic">Saturday</hi> following, which was the 14<hi rend="italic"
        >th</hi>, we <lb/>got two Dogs both as big as common Bull-Dogs. <lb/>The firſt Dog, which he
        bit on the Inſide of his left <lb/>Thigh, died in half a minute exactly, in the Opinion
        <lb/>of two Gentlemen, who kept their Watches in their <lb/>hands all the while: There were
        two very ſmall Pun- <lb/>ctures in his Thigh, which lookt livid, tho' no Blood <lb/>was
        drawn. This Dog did not ſwell for four hours <lb/>after he was dead. I ſaw him, and order'd
        him to be <lb/>bury'd. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſecond Dog was bit about an Hour after the <lb/>firſt, on the out ſide of his
        Thigh, where we per- <lb/>ceived the Blood at two places: He ſoon ſicken'd, <lb/>and died in
        four Minutes. </p>
      <pb n="312"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We thought his Poiſon was not ſpent; ſo we got a <lb/>Cat (for we could get no more
        Dogs) which he bit <lb/>about an hour after, though I can't ſay where. The <lb/>Cat was very
        ſick, and we put her up in a Cloſet: By <lb/>ſome means the Cat was let out in leſs than an
        Hour <lb/>and a half after ſhe was bitten. The next Morning <lb/>early ſhe was found dead in
        the Garden, and much <lb/>ſwoln; ſo that nobody cared to examine or ſearch <lb/>where ſhe
        was bit. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About a quarter of an Hour after he had bitten the <lb/>Cat, he bit a Hen twice: The
        Hen ſeem'd very ſick <lb/>and drooping, and could not, or did not fly up to her <lb/>uſual
        place of Rooſt among the reſt that Night; but <lb/>the next Day ſhe ſeem'd very well, and
        continued <lb/>ſo till Evening, when I order'd her to be Killed, <lb/>and her <choice>
          <corr>Feathers</corr>
          <sic>Fearhers</sic>
        </choice> ſcalded off: There were 2 Pun- <lb/>ctures in her Thigh, and a Scratch on her
        Breaſt <lb/>over the Craw, all which lookt livid. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About a Week after, having got a large Bull-Frog, <lb/>we brought that over him as
        uſual: He bit it with <lb/>much force; ſo that he ſeem'd to faſten for a ſmall <lb/>ſpace.
        The Frog died in two minutes or there- <lb/>abouts. In leſs than a quarter of an Hour he bit
        a <lb/>Chicken, which was hatcht the <hi rend="italic">February</hi> before, that <lb/>died
        in 3 minutes; I can't ſay where it was bit, <lb/>and I was at a loſs to try any further
        Experiments <lb/>for a long time, for want of proper Subjects. Dogs <lb/>and Cats were not
        to be had; for the good Wo- <lb/>men, whoſe Dogs had been killed, exclaimed ſo <lb/>much,
        that I durſt not meddle with one after- <lb/>wards. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About the Middle of <hi rend="italic">June</hi> I took him out ac- <lb/>cording to
        Cuſtom, and having got a common <lb/>black Snake, not of the of Viper-kind, about two
        <lb/>and a half or near three Feet long, in good Health, <pb n="313"/>
        <lb/>juſt taken; I put them both together, and irritated them <lb/>both, that they bit each
        other, and I perceived the <lb/>black Snake had drawn Blood of the Rattle-Snake be-
        <lb/>fore I took them aſunder. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In leſs than 8 Minutes the black Snake was dead, and <lb/>I could not perceive the
        Rattle-Snake at all the worſe <lb/>or ſick. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the laſt Day of <hi rend="italic">June</hi>, being <hi rend="italic">Friday</hi>, I
        took him <lb/>out to try, whether if he bit himſelf, it would not <lb/>prove mortal to him.
        I hang'd him ſo, that he was <lb/>not above half his Length on the Ground; and with <lb/>two
        Needles at the End of a Stick, one to prick, the <lb/>other to ſcratch, irritated him ſo
        much that he ſoon <lb/>bit himſelf, after having attempted to bite the Stick <lb/>many
        times. I then let him down, and he was quite <lb/>dead in 8 minutes or thereabouts, but am
        ſure it did <lb/>not exceed 12 Minutes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A Gentleman perſwaded me to cut the Snake in five <lb/>Pieces which he gave to a Hog,
        the Head-part firſt, <lb/>in Sight of many of us. The Hog eat up all the Snake, <lb/>and 10
        or 12 Days afterwards I ſaw the ſame Hog a- <lb/>live and in Health. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This was no more than I had ſeen before; but <lb/>doubted there might be a Miſtake, as
        that they had <lb/>taken ſome other Snake for a Rattle-Snake: For being <lb/>at the Houſe of
          <hi rend="italic">Charles Hart</hi> Eſq: they ſhew'd me a <lb/>Snake, which a Negro told
        me he had kill'd juſt be- <lb/>fore; it was in three pieces, the Head of it bruiſed into
        <lb/>the Ground. While I was looking on, a Sow came <lb/>and eat it up very greedily, tho'
        the Negro-man en- <lb/>deavour'd to hinder her, being afraid it would kill her; <lb/>for ſhe
        had Pigs following her. </p>
      <pb n="314"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I never heard ſhe was ſick for it, tho' I inquired; and <lb/>about ten Days after I ſaw
        her in very good Health. I <lb/>have heard fifty Relations of the ſame kind, and am told
        <lb/>that thoſe Hogs which feed in the Marſhes will run <lb/>after the common ſort of
        Water-Snakes, which are <lb/>not poiſonous, and will feed on them greedily: And I
        <lb/>aſſure you, in <hi rend="italic">Maryland</hi> laſt <hi rend="italic">Auguſt</hi> was
        two years I ſaw <lb/>a Hog eat up the Head of a Rattle-Snake juſt cut off, <lb/>and while it
        was gaſping very dreadfully; and I was <lb/>told, it was a common thing, and it would do
        them no <lb/>harm. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 10<hi rend="italic">th</hi> of <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 1723, Mr. <hi
          rend="italic">Thomas Cooper</hi>, a <lb/>Gentleman who practiſes Phyſick at <hi
          rend="italic">Charles Town</hi>, <lb/>and who was late of <hi rend="italic">Wadham-College
          Oxon</hi>, a very In- <lb/>genious Man, ſent to me to let me know, he had <lb/>got a fine
        Rattle-Snake which had been taken not <lb/>above 4 Days, was about three feet and a half
        long, <lb/>and that he deſign'd to try whether he could ſave <lb/>ſome of the Dogs after the
        Snake ſhould bite them. <lb/>He provided a large quantity of <hi rend="italic"
          >Venice-Treacle</hi> or <lb/><hi rend="italic">Mithridate</hi>, I can't poſitively ſay
        whether, which he <lb/>divided into two Potions, each about two Ounces; <lb/>to one of them
        he put a large quantity of <hi rend="italic">Diaphoretic <lb/>Antimony</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The firſt Dog which the Snake bit on the Inſide of <lb/>the Thigh, died ſo ſoon <hi
          rend="italic">(viz.)</hi> in about half a minute, <lb/>that we could not get the Potion,
        which was that <lb/><hi rend="italic">without</hi> Antimony, down his Throat ſoon enough to
        <lb/>expect it could have Effect. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Above an Hour after, the ſecond Dog was bitten <lb/>by him, and had two Punctures or
        Holes in the <lb/>fleſhy part of the Inſide of his fore left Leg, which <lb/>did bleed more
        than any I had ſeen before: We <lb/>immediately got down his Throat that Preparation
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">with Antimony</hi>. He ſoon grew very ſick and ſtrove to <pb
          n="315"/>
        <lb/>vomit; but I think brought up very little, if any; he <lb/>froth'd at the Mouth and bit
        at the Graſs, which he cham- <lb/>ped, as if he were mad; and indeed we were all afraid of
        <lb/>him. We therefore put him into a Room and there <lb/>kept him till next Morning, where
        I ſaw him as I <lb/>thought recover'd: We throw'd him ſome Meat, which <lb/>he eat, ſo we
        let him out and he went home. About a <lb/>Month after that, the Dog's Hair came off, and
        his <lb/>Maſter killed him, being ſo ugly to look at; he told <lb/>me, he lookt like a
        Leprous Perſon, (that was his very <lb/>Expreſſion;) I never heard this Dog ſwell'd. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The third Dog which he bit was a Shaggy Spaniel, <lb/>about an hour and a quarter after
        the ſecond. He was <lb/>bitten on the foremoſt part of his right Shoulder, as we
        <lb/>perceived by the Blood. The Dog ſeem'd to bite at <lb/>the place himſelf, and was very
        ſick for that whole E- <lb/>vening (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>) about 2 or 3 hours; but
        without any means <lb/>or application he recover'd, and I never heard he was <lb/>ſick
        afterwards. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
