<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Dod: An Account of an Aneurysm of the Aorta</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Pierce Dod</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of an Aneurysm of the Aorta, (Dissected in St. Bartholomew's Hospital)
              by Pierce Dod, M. D. Fellow of the College of Physicians, and Physician to That
              Hospital</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for W. Innys, Printer to the Royal Society, at the
                  West End of St. Paul's.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1727-1728</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">35</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">436-440</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO"/>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1727.0035</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT35_0436">
    <body>
      <pb n="436"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">IV.</hi> An Account of an <hi rend="roman">Aneuryſm</hi> of the <hi
          rend="roman">Aorta</hi>, (diſ- <lb/>ſected in St. <hi rend="roman">Bartholomew</hi>'s
        Hoſpital) by <hi rend="roman">Pierce <lb/>Dod</hi>, M. D. Fellow of the College of
        Phyſicians, <lb/>and Phyſician to that Hoſpital. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>N Aneuryſm, without Doubt, is a Tumour ariſing <lb/>from ſome
        Diſorder in an Artery; but what that <lb/>Diſorder is, or whence it ariſes, is not ſo well
        agreed, <lb/>the Accounts which are given of it, being widely dif- <lb/>ferent and
        uncertain. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Name ſeems to imply, that it is a Dilatation of <lb/>the Veſſel; but <hi
          rend="italic">Galen</hi> deſcribes it to be a Tumour, <lb/>which ariſes not from any
        Dilatation or Relaxation of <lb/>an arterial Veſſel, and the Blood therein contain'd; but
        <lb/>from an Extravaſation of the Blood from ſome Rupture <lb/>of the Artery. </p>
      <pb n="437"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Agreeable to this are the Opinions of all the reſt of <lb/>the Antients, as likewiſe of
        the <hi rend="italic">Arabians</hi>, who bor- <lb/>rowed moſt that they have from them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fornelius</hi>, as 'tis ſaid, is the firſt who maintained, <lb/>that
        the Artery was only dilated, and not burſt in an <lb/>Aneuryſm, and that the Blood was
        contain'd within the <lb/>Coats of it, as it is within thoſe of the Vein in a <hi
          rend="italic">Va- <lb/>rix</hi>; which is therefore called by ſome, <hi rend="italic"
          >ήφλέψ άνευρυσ- <lb/>μήνη</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Sennertus</hi> makes it to be a Dilatation, not of both <lb/>the
        Coats, but of the outward one only, the inner or <lb/>muſcular one being firſt burſten, or
        broken, and he is <lb/>followed herein by moſt of thoſe who have ſucceeded <lb/>him,
        excepting <hi rend="italic">Wiſeman</hi> and ſome others, who tell us, <lb/>that it is
        nothing but an Extravaſation of the Blood, <lb/>burſting through the Coats of the Arteries
        into the <lb/>Interſtices of the Muſcles, and there forming a Tu- <lb/>mour ſuitable to the
        Cavity that it findeth, the Artery <lb/>remaining undiſtended or undilated all the While;
        and <lb/>than in all thoſe Aneuryſms, which have come to be <lb/>examined, both the Coats of
        the Artery have conſtant- <lb/>ly been found open. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This being the State of Opinions with relation to an <lb/>Aneuryſm, we had lately an
        Opportunity of examining <lb/>further into it, by Means of a Patient, who was taken
        <lb/>into our Hoſpital. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>She was about four and thirty Years of Age, and of <lb/>a good Conſtitution, but there
        was a Tumour, bigger <lb/>than one's Fiſt, which began from the upper Part of the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Sternum</hi>, between the Origins of the <hi rend="italic">Muſculi Maſtoi-
          <lb/>dæi</hi>, and extended it ſelf to the <hi rend="italic">Pomum Adami</hi>, almoſt
        <lb/>up to her Chin, and poſſeſs'd all the Breadth between <lb/>the two <hi rend="italic"
          >Carotid Arteries</hi>. </p>
      <pb n="438"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Account that ſhe gave of the Occaſion of it was, <lb/>that her Husband, being a
        paſſionate Man, took her by <lb/>the Throat one Day as ſhe was crying out upon ſome
        <lb/>Occaſion or other, and grip'd her ſo hard as almoſt to <lb/>throttle her. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>She was then with Child, and immediately perceiv'd <lb/>ſomething of a Pain a little
        above her Heart, and a few <lb/>Days afterwards there appeared a Tumour about the
        <lb/>Bigneſs of the Top of her Finger, juſt above the <hi rend="italic">Ster- <lb/>num</hi>,
        and ſo continued without Encreaſe or Pulſation, <lb/>till ſhe was brought to Bed, when it
        began to be enlarg- <lb/>ed, upon her having a hard Labour; agreeable to what
        <lb/>Practitioners have obſerv'd, that Accidents of this Na- <lb/>ture often happen to Women
        in Labour. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This was about four Years ſince, and from that Time <lb/>it had continued gradually
        encreaſing, until it was ar- <lb/>rived to almoſt the higheſt Pitch of Extenſion; and ſhe
        <lb/>had all along been trouble'd with a Palpitation, Pain and <lb/>Straitneſs within the
          <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi>, great Interruptions in her <lb/>Reſt, and frequent
        Sinkings, together with a conſtant <lb/>beating along the Cheſt up to the Tumour; in which
        <lb/>likewiſe there was a Pulſation correſpondent to the regu- <lb/>lar Pulſe, ſhaking the
        Tumour at every Stroke, and <lb/>manifeſt to the Eye as well as the Touch. Notwith-
        <lb/>ſtanding this ſhe was otherwiſe hearty, had her <hi rend="italic">Menſes</hi>
        <lb/>regularly, had a good Appetite, and was moſtly chear- <lb/>ful and lively, and never
        more ſo than juſt before the <lb/>fatal Period of the Tumour. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Apex</hi> of the Tumour, which was towards the <lb/>Middle, in
        the prominent Part of it was beginning to <lb/>mortifie, through an over Diſtenſion, and the
        common <lb/>outward Integuments were the firſt that ſeemed to ſuf- <lb/>fer: But the
        Diſtenſion continuing, the Mortification <pb n="439"/>
        <lb/>encreas'd, and was quickly communicated to the outer <lb/>Coat of the Artery likewiſe,
        which therefore ſlough'd <lb/>off as well as the other Integuments, and being at <lb/>Length
        wore away, juſt at the Extremity made a ſud- <lb/>den Aperture, about twice the Bigneſs of a
        Gooſe's <lb/>Quill. The Blood inſtantly guſh'd forth, as from a <lb/>Stream or Torrent, and
        the poor Patient died in leſs <lb/>than a Minute. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon opening the Body, we began from the Heart, <lb/>in which there was little
        remarkable, except that the <lb/>left Ventricle was ſomewhat larger. as were likewiſe the
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Columnæ carneæ</hi>, than they naturally ſhould be. <lb/>There was
        little obſervable likewiſe in the <hi rend="italic">Aorta</hi> it ſelf, <lb/>till we came to
        the Curvature; upon the upper Side of <lb/>which was the <hi rend="italic">Baſis</hi> of the
        Tumour, forming a cy- <lb/>lindrical Stem of four Inches long while in the Cavity <lb/>of
        the <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi>; but extending it ſelf into a circular <lb/>Form of a
        larger Dimenſion, when it became external. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon opening the under Part of the <hi rend="italic">Aorta</hi> oppoſite <lb/>to this
          <hi rend="italic">Baſis</hi>, and carrying the Inciſion throughout its <lb/>whole Extent
        in the <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi>, the Trunk retain'd its uſual <lb/>Form and Dimenſions,
        and was not at all dilated; but <lb/>in the upper Part above deſcrib'd, juſt on this Side
        <lb/>the Orifice of the right <hi rend="italic">ſubclavian Artery</hi> (which was
        <lb/>nearer than uſual to the Orifice of the left <hi rend="italic">Carotid</hi>) <lb/>there
        was a preternatural circular Aperture of half an <lb/>Inch Diameter. Upon dividing this
        Aperture, and car- <lb/>rying on the Inciſion to the <hi rend="italic">Apex</hi> of the
        Tumour, its <lb/>whole internal Subſtance appear'd. The Edges of the <lb/>Aperture at the
        Baſis of the Tumour were hard, and <lb/>almoſt cartilaginous, and ſeemingly the Remains of
        thick <lb/>and fleſhy Fibres; which upon a nicer Inſpection they <lb/>appear'd to be in
        Fact, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> the broken Fibres of the in- <pb n="440"/>
        <lb/>ner, or what is commonly call'd, the muſcular Coat of <lb/>the Artery: which
        terminating here, the Tumour im- <lb/>mediately encreaſ'd to 2 Inches in Diameter, and con-
        <lb/>tinued of that Dimenſion, till it came out at the Neck, <lb/>between the Clavicles; but
        then extended it ſelf circu- <lb/>larly to a Diameter of above 3 Inches, the Covering of
        <lb/>which was nothing elſe but the outer Coat of the ſame <lb/>Artery all along dilated
        from the Baſe, even to the <lb/>Extremity of the Tumour. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Cavity was for the moſt Part fill'd with a Sort <lb/>of <hi rend="italic"
          >Polypus</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Sarcoma</hi>; in which nevertheleſs there <lb/>were
        three Sinuſes, or Paſſages, that were kept open by <lb/>the conſtant Influx of the Blood,
        and communicated <lb/>near the <hi rend="italic">Apex</hi> with one another; (that in the
        Middle <lb/>being the largeſt,) and terminating in one towards the <lb/>Extremity of the
        Tumour, not far from where it <lb/>broke. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Such was the State of the Aneuryſm in this Subject, <lb/>what it may be in others,
        future Enquiries muſt de- <lb/>termine. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
