<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Douglass: A Short Account of the Different Kinds of
          Ipecacuanha</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Dr. Douglass</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Short Account of the Different Kinds of Ipecacuanha, by Dr. Douglass, Med.
              Regin. Extr. &amp; R. S. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for W. Innys, Printer to the Royal Society, at the
                  West End of St. Paul's.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1729-1730</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">36</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">152-158</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110528838</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1729.0020</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT36_0152">
    <body>
      <pb n="152"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">V.</hi> A ſhort Account of the different Kinds of <hi rend="roman"
          >Ipe- <lb/>cacuanha</hi>, by Dr. <hi rend="roman">Douglaſs</hi>, Med. Regin. Extr.
        <lb/>&amp; R. S. S. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> beg Leave to take up a ſmall Part of this honou- <lb/>rable
        Society's Time, in laying before them ſome <lb/>Specimens of that celebrated vomiting Root,
        whe- <lb/>ther truly, or falſly called <hi rend="italic">Ipecacuanha</hi>, which I keep
        <lb/>in my Collection of the <hi rend="italic">Materia Medica</hi>; together <lb/>with a few
        Obſervations concerning their outward <lb/>Appearance, by the Help of which the ſeveral
        Kinds <lb/>thereof may be diſtinguiſhed from one another; and <lb/>an Account of what I have
        hitherto been able to <lb/>learn concerning the true Places of their Growth. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The firſt general Diviſion of theſe Roots muſt be, <lb/>as has been already hinted,
        into true and falſe; and <lb/>each of theſe may be again ſubdivided into ſeveral
        <lb/>Species, the diſtinctive Note of which is principally <lb/>taken from their Colour. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Of the true <hi rend="italic">Ipecacuanha</hi> I have four Kinds, Black, <lb/>Brown,
        Grey, and White; but I cannot pretend to <lb/>determine whether they belong to different
        Plants, <lb/>or are only Varieties of the ſame Plant owing to the <lb/>Soil in which they
        grow, as is affirmed by our wor- <lb/>thy and learned Preſident Sir <hi rend="italic">Hans
          Sloane</hi> Baronet. <lb/>And as theſe Roots are never imported to us entire, it <lb/>is
        impoſſible to give any certain Deſcription of them <lb/>in that State. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>However, by comparing the ſeveral dried Pieces <lb/>as we have them, we may very
        probably conjecture <pb n="153"/>
        <lb/>that a ſhort radical Trunk deſcends from a <hi rend="italic">Cautis</hi>, <lb/>and is
        afterwards divided into ſeveral large Branches, <lb/>and theſe again into ſmaller ones, in
        different Series, <lb/>with minute Filaments or Fibrillæ going out from them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Each Piece is made up of two general Parts, an <lb/>Outer or Cortical, and an Inner or
        Fibrous, which <lb/>like a white Nerve, or ſmooth compact Faſciculus of <lb/>woody
        Filaments, runs through the Center or Axis <lb/>of the Roots, and perhaps encloſes within it
        a ſmall <lb/>Medulla or Pith, which however is hardly diſcern- <lb/>able by the naked Eye. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Cortical Part is corrugated by two Sorts of <lb/>Wrinkles, one ſuperficial,
        conſiſting either in circular <lb/>Rings or little Knots which do not go quite round;
        <lb/>the other penetrating into its Subſtance, being deep <lb/>Inciſures or Fiſſures
        reaching all the Way to the Nerve. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>What Lengths theſe Roots are of when taken out <lb/>of the Ground, cannot be
        determined: I have met <lb/>with ſome Pieces above nine Inches, many above ſix, <lb/>but the
        greateſt Number are ſtill ſhorter. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We find them bent, wreathed, and contorted into <lb/>all Manner of Figures; and indeed
        few Pieces are al- <lb/>together ſtraight for any conſiderable Length. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>What has been hitherto ſaid, agrees to all the true <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Ipecacuanha-roots</hi>; but ſeveral other Things are ſtill <lb/>to be taken Notice of, in
        which they differ. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Black Sort is the ſmalleſt of the four, very <lb/>hard, and the Fiſſures wide and
        numerous. The out- <lb/>ward Colour of the Cortex is not equally black in all <lb/>the
        Pieces of this Kind, and its inner Subſtance, as <lb/>well as the Nerve, is moſtly white,
        tho' not always <lb/>in the ſame Degrees. </p>
      <pb n="154"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Brown Sort is larger than the Black, the Fiſ- <lb/>ſures at larger Diſtances, the
        inner Subſtance of the <lb/>Cortex darker, and the external Colour has ſeveral <lb/>Degrees
        of Redneſs in the ſeveral Pieces. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Third of Grey Sort is ſometimes found of a <lb/>darker, ſometimes of a lighter
        Colour, and the Inner <lb/>Subſtance of the Cortex is Brown ſtreaked with <lb/>White. It is
        much larger than the black Sort, many <lb/>Pieces being above a quarter of an Inch in
        Diameter, <lb/>but the Nerve is ſmaller in Proportion to the cortical <lb/>Part. I have met
        with few Pieces of this Species <lb/>above five Inches in Length; but, as I already obſerv-
        <lb/>ed, nothing can be concluded from thence as to the <lb/>Length of the whole Roots. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Fiſſures are here ſtill fewer than in the brown <lb/>Sort, and in ſome Pieces
        ſcarce any are to be met <lb/>with. The ſuperficial Corrugations are various in
        <lb/>different Roots, ſome being almoſt wholly ſmooth, and <lb/>in others the Wrinkles
        rather longitudal than cir- <lb/>cular. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The white Kind, as far as I can judge by the <lb/>ſmall Sample which I have of it, is
        of very differ- <lb/>ent Sizes, ſome Pieces of it being larger than any of <lb/>the grey
        Sort, and the reſt much leſs. The whitiſh <lb/>Colour of the Cortex is mixed with a
        yellowiſh Caſt, <lb/>and the nervous Part is very large in Proportion to the <lb/>reſt. Very
        few Fiſſures are to be obſerved therein, and <lb/>hardly any reach ſo deep as the Nerve. The
        other <lb/>Corrugations are likewiſe very ſhallow, and moſt of <lb/>them longitudinal; but
        it ſeems to be more knotty <lb/>than the other Kinds, and theſe Knots I take to be
        <lb/>owing chiefly to the <hi rend="italic">Fibrillæ</hi> which go out from the <lb/>larger
        Branches of the Roots. </p>
      <pb n="155"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Loci Natales</hi>, or true Places of Growth of <lb/>theſe
        different Species of <hi rend="italic">Ipecacuanha</hi> have not as yet <lb/>been fully
        ſettled. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Black Sort is hitherto known to come only <lb/>from <hi rend="italic">Braſile</hi>,
        whence we get it by the Way of <hi rend="italic">Liſ- <lb/>bon</hi>, and ſome of our
        Druggiſts for that Reaſon di- <lb/>ſtinguiſh it by the Name of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Braſile</hi> Root. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About the Brown Sort, I am informed by Dr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">James Houſton</hi>,
        who reſided for ſeveral Years in <lb/><hi rend="italic">New-ſpain</hi>, that it grows
        plentifully at ſome Diſtance <lb/>from the City of <hi rend="italic">Cartagena</hi> in the
        Kingdom of <hi rend="italic">New <lb/>Granada</hi>; from whence it is frequently ſent in Sa-
        <lb/>roons or Skins, containing 100 Weight, to <hi rend="italic">Jamaica</hi>, <lb/>and ſo
        to <hi rend="italic">England</hi>; where it is certain we have had <lb/>it of late Years in
        great Abundance. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Grey <hi rend="italic">Ipecacuanha</hi> is with us preferred to all <lb/>the reſt,
        and by far the moſt generally uſed when it <lb/>can be had. It is ſaid by Authors to grow in
          <hi rend="italic">Peru</hi>, <lb/>from whence we get it by the Way of <hi rend="italic"
          >Spain</hi>, it being <lb/>brought from <hi rend="italic">Peru</hi> to <hi rend="italic"
          >Porto-Bello</hi>, and from thence <lb/>into <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi>, by the <hi
          rend="italic">Spaniſh Galleons</hi>. Some Par- <lb/>cels thereof are likewiſe probably
        ſent from <hi rend="italic">Porto- <lb/>Bello</hi> to <hi rend="italic">Jamaica</hi>; for we
        are certain that it has ſome- <lb/>times been imported hither from that Iſland. By ſome
        <lb/>Specimens that were brought me by Mr. <hi rend="italic">Lightbody</hi>, <lb/>an
        ingenious Surgeon, from St. <hi rend="italic">Thomé</hi>, a <hi rend="italic"
          >Portugueſe</hi>
        <lb/>Iſland under the Equinoctial, whither they were ſent <lb/>directly from <hi
          rend="italic">Braſile</hi>, it is evident that this Species is <lb/>likewiſe a Native of
        that Country, and therefore muſt <lb/>either have been included by <hi rend="italic"
          >Piſo</hi> under one of the <lb/>two Species mentioned by him, or elſe diſcovered ſince
        <lb/>his Time. According to Father <hi rend="italic">La Bat</hi>, in his late <pb n="156"/>
        <lb/>Voyage to the Iſlands of <hi rend="italic">America</hi>, this Species grows <lb/>alſo
        plentifully in <hi rend="italic">Martinico</hi>, where for many Years <lb/>paſt it has been
        uſed by the Inhabitants. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The White Sort, called by the <hi rend="italic">Portugueſe</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Ipeca- <lb/>cuanha Blanca</hi>, is ſaid by <hi rend="italic">Piſo</hi> to grow in <hi
          rend="italic">Braſile</hi>, <lb/>and if we may believe Father <hi rend="italic">La
          Bat</hi>, it is likewiſe <lb/>found in <hi rend="italic">Martinico</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe are the four Kinds of true <hi rend="italic">Ipecacuanha</hi> which <lb/>have
        hitherto come to my Knowledge; but I have met <lb/>with two other Roots to which that Name
        has been <lb/>falſely aſcribed, which from their outward Colour I <lb/>ſhall call White and
        Reddiſh Brown. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The White Sort agrees pretty much both in Colour <lb/>and Surface with the true White,
        but it is not near ſo <lb/>knotty. It is likewiſe conſiderably larger in Size,
        <lb/>ſtraighter and ſofter to the Touch. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Brown Sort is of a deeper Colour than the true <lb/>Brown, and many Pieces thereof
        have ſome Mixture <lb/>of Red (from whence it has been ſometimes called <lb/>Red <hi
          rend="italic">Ipecacuanha</hi>) and the inner Subſtance of the Cor- <lb/>tex enclines to a
        reddiſh Yellow. The Pieces thereof <lb/>are much longer than any of the former Sorts, ſome
        <lb/>of them meaſuring ſixteen Inches, and they are of a <lb/>Size between the Black and
        Grey. The Fiſſures <lb/>are at greater Diſtances from one another than in the <lb/>true
        Brown, and the Spaces between them much ſmooth- <lb/>er. In a Word, though this Root when
        mixed with the <lb/>true Brown, to which it bears the greateſt Reſem- <lb/>blance, may
        eaſily be confounded therewith; yet <lb/>when they are attentively compared, their whole Ap-
        <lb/>pearance ſufficiently diſtinguiſhes them. </p>
      <pb n="157"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Both theſe falſe Kinds were brought me from <hi rend="italic">Ma- <lb/>ryland</hi> in
        1725, by one M. <hi rend="italic">Seymour</hi> a Surgeon, who <lb/>informed me that they
        grow there in great Plenty, <lb/>being called <hi rend="italic">Ipecacuanha</hi> by the
        Inhabitants, and uſed <lb/>as a Vomit by thoſe of inferior Rank. I have ſince <lb/>that Time
        received a Sample of the Brown Sort, taken <lb/>from a Parcel which lay in the Cuſtom-houſe,
        above <lb/>twelve Years ago, and called by the Name of wild <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Ipecacuanha</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The forementioned Illuſtrious Sir <hi rend="italic">Hans Sloane</hi>
        <lb/>did me the Honour to inform me that this falſe Brown <lb/>Kind was the ſame that was
        formerly ſent to him <lb/>from <hi rend="italic">Virginia</hi> for the true <hi
          rend="italic">Ipecacuanha</hi>, and which <lb/>he afterwards diſcovered to be the Root of
        a poiſon- <lb/>ous Apocynum deſcribed by him in his <hi rend="italic">Natural Hi- <lb/>ſtory
          of Jamaica</hi>; in which Iſland it is very com- <lb/>mon, and likewiſe in <hi
          rend="italic">New-ſpain</hi>, as appeared to <lb/>him by the Specimens ſent him by his
        Correſpondent <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Burnet</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In his Introduction to the ſecond Volume of that <lb/>excellent Hiſtory, he has obliged
        us with a very full <lb/>and diſtinct Account of what he had learned from his <lb/>Friends
        abroad, concerning the pernicious Effects of <lb/>the ſeveral Parts of this Plant, and of
        the great Pains he <lb/>was at to prevent its being brought into Uſe in this <lb/>Country,
        which was then very much to be apprehend- <lb/>ed. <hi rend="italic">Helvetius</hi>'s Name
        will always be mentioned <lb/>with Honour for the great Share he had in rendering <lb/>the
        Uſe of the true <hi rend="italic">Ipecacuanha</hi> common in <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi>;
        <lb/>and I cannot think that Sir <hi rend="italic">Hans Sloane</hi> deſerves a <lb/>much
        leſs Degree of Praiſe for having detected this <lb/>falſe Kind, which was inſenſibly
        creeping into Uſe, <pb n="158"/>
        <lb/>the Effects whereof might otherwiſe have proved <lb/>as fatal as the other is found to
        be beneficial. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I have only to add, that this poiſonous Kind of A- <lb/>pocynum is now cultivated by
        ſeveral curious Per- <lb/>ſons about <hi rend="italic">London</hi>, and that I deſign with
        all con- <lb/>venient Speed to preſent this Society with a particular <lb/>Deſcription
        thereof, taken from a Plant which I had <lb/>laſt Summer growing in my own Garden. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
