<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Mortimer: Some Experiments concerning the Poisonous Quality of the Simple Water Distilled
          from the Lauro-Cerasus, or Common Laurel</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Cromwell Mortimer</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Some Experiments concerning the Poisonous Quality of the Simple Water Distilled
              from the Lauro-Cerasus, or Common Laurel, Made upon Dogs, at Toppingo-Hall in Essex,
              August the 24th 1731. and Others Made before the Royal Society in Their Repository. By
              Cromwell Mortimer, M. D. R. S. Secret</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for W. Innys and R. Manby, Printers to the Royal Society, at the
                  West End of St. Paul's.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1731-1732</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">37</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">163-173</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111028653</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi:10.1098/rstl.1731.0027</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT37_0163">
    <body>
      <pb n="163"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">III.</hi> Some Experiments concerning the <hi rend="roman">poiſonous
          <lb/>Quality</hi> of the <hi rend="roman">Simple Water</hi> diſtilled from the <lb/><hi
          rend="sc">Lauro-cerasus</hi>, or <hi rend="roman">common Laurel,</hi>
        <lb/>made upon Dogs, at <hi rend="roman">Toppingo-Hall</hi> in <lb/><hi rend="roman"
          >Eſſex</hi>, <hi rend="roman">Auguſt</hi> the <hi rend="roman">24</hi>th <hi rend="roman"
          >1731</hi>. and others <lb/>made before the <hi rend="sc">Royal Society</hi> in their
        <lb/>Repoſitory. By <hi rend="roman">Cromwell Mortimer</hi>, M. D. <lb/>R. S. Secret. </head>
   <div>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> Took a Peck of Laurel Leaves, and put them into <lb/>an
          Alembick with three Gallons of Water, which <pb n="164"/>
          <lb/>I diſtilled in the common Way, as <hi rend="italic">Penny Royal</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">Mint <lb/>Water</hi>, or any Simple Waters are made. The Fire at
          <lb/>firſt being too hot, there came over an Oilineſs with the <lb/>Water, (1.) which made
          it appear milky, till about half <lb/>a Pint had run: This taſted and ſmelt very ſtrong
          like <lb/>Apricock Kernels, as did the next Running, (2.), which <lb/>was clearer. I kept
          the firſt Quart of it by itſelf; then <lb/>I drew off another Quart, (3.) which was not
          near <lb/>ſo ſtrong in Taſte or Smell, but rather reſembled <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Black-Cherry Water</hi>: The Remainder was almoſt <lb/>inſipid. The Leaves after the
          Diſtillation look'd <lb/>browniſh, were brittle, and taſted bitter without the
          <lb/>Roughneſs or Apricock-Kernel Flavour, which they <lb/>have while freſh. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In the Afternoon of the ſame Day I took a Mun- <lb/>grel Puppy, weighing two Pounds
          and an half, <lb/>about ſixteen Days old; it had ſuck'd the Bitch <lb/>in the Forenoon,
          but had now faſted ſix Hours. I <lb/>took one Ounce of the third Water, and gave ſome
          <lb/>of it to the Puppy, gradually by Tea-Spoon- <lb/>fuls, that it might the better
          ſwallow it. When <lb/>it had taken half the Quantity, I let it go; it walk'd <lb/>about
          pretty ſtrongly for five Minutes, when it began <lb/>to foam at the Mouth, and ſoon after
          vomited up ſome <lb/>curdled Milk, and then diſcharged the <hi rend="italic">Fæces
            alvinæ</hi>, <lb/>after which the Sickneſs ſeemd to go off: I then gave <lb/>it three
          Tea-Spoonfuls more; in ten Minutes it be- <lb/>gan to ſtagger, and draw its hind Parts
          after it; it <lb/>ſat upon its Breech, whined, and made ſeveral <lb/>Efforts to vomit, but
          never brought any thing up; <lb/>and then again would walk about, and ſit down and
          <lb/>whine, and again ſeem to recover for about fifteen <lb/>Minutes longer: Then thinking
          the ſecond Water <pb n="165"/>
          <lb/>would diſpatch it ſooner out of its Miſery, it ſeeming <lb/>to be very uneaſy, I took
          one Ounce and half of the <lb/>ſecond Running: I gave it firſt three Tea Spoonfuls,
          <lb/>and ſet it down, when in two Minutes time it became <lb/>ſtrongly convulſed, put out
          the Tongue, and made ſtrong <lb/>Efforts to vomit, but to no Effect; it could not ſtand
          <lb/>on its Legs, but lay with its hind Legs ſtretched out: <lb/>Five Minutes after I gave
          three Tea Spoonfuls more, <lb/>when it was ſtronger convulſed, rolled over and over
          <lb/>ſeveral times, drew its Head back to its Rump, then <lb/>lay on its Side and panted
          much: About eight Mi- <lb/>nutes after, I gave it two Tea Spoonfuls more, and it <lb/>had
          freſh and ſtrong Convulſions, but kept lying on <lb/>its Side, and thus ſtretching out its
          four Legs one <lb/>after another, drawing in its Flanks very quick; in <lb/>fifteen
          Minutes more it died, being in all about an <lb/>Hour from the firſt Doſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>An Hour after it was dead I opened it, and found all <lb/>the Contents of the <hi
            rend="italic">Abdomen</hi> well; the Stomach was <lb/>diſtended with Wind, being opened,
          it appeared empty <lb/>of Milk, but full of Froth, and a clear <hi rend="italic"
            >Mucus</hi> of a <lb/>much thicker Conſiſtence than the <hi rend="italic">Liquor
            Gaſtricus</hi>
          <lb/>naturally is; they had no Smell at all, the inſide of <lb/>the Stomach was not at all
          inflamed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On opening the <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi> I found the Lungs a little <lb/>redder
          than natural, with ſome Veſſels on the out- <lb/>ward Membrane of them very turgid: On
          cutting <lb/>them out a pretty deal of clear red Blood from <lb/>them. The Veins and both
          Ventricles of the Heart <lb/>were turgid and full of coagulated Blood, of a dark-
          <lb/>brown Colour, which tinged my Fingers of a dirty <lb/>yellow, as if ſome Gall had
          been mix'd with it. <pb n="166"/>
          <lb/>There was no Blood in the Arteries; the <hi rend="italic">Foramen <lb/>Ovale</hi> was
          open. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On opening the Head, the <hi rend="italic">Dura Mater</hi> appeared <lb/>livid, as if
          bruiſed, its Veſſels and the <hi rend="italic">Sinus falci-for- <lb/>mis</hi> were turgid
          and full of the ſame Blood, as the <lb/>Heart and Veſſels near it. The cortical Subſtance
          of <lb/>the Brain looked of an unuſual livid blueiſh Colour. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Next Day about Five in the Afternoon I took a <lb/>large Maſtiff Dog weighing
          ſeventy-five Pounds. We <lb/>tied him to a Poſt as he ſtood on his Legs, one hold-
          <lb/>ing him ſtrongly by the Tail, he being very fierce <lb/>and unmanageable: We injected
            <hi rend="italic">per Anum</hi> three <lb/>Ounces of the ſecond Running; in five Minutes
          he <lb/>trembled and ſtagger'd much, would let us handle <lb/>him, he drew his hind Legs
          after him, tumbled on his <lb/>Head, panted and ſlabber'd, but gradually recover'd ſo
          <lb/>as to ſtand up, tho' reeling and often ſinking with his <lb/>hind Legs. Fifteen
          Minutes after, we injected one <lb/>Ounce more; he immediately ſtagger'd and ſunk behind,
          <lb/>ſoon after he made Water plentifully. We then led <lb/>him to another Kennel, where
          he ſoon diſcharged the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fæces alvinæ</hi> plentifully, but of an
          hard Conſiſtence: <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Fæces</hi> ſeem'd moiſten'd with the laſt
          injected <lb/>Ounce, which I imagin'd came away by this Stool; <lb/>I therefore
          immediately injected another Ounce, up- <lb/>on which he ſeemed more uneaſy than before,
          tum- <lb/>bling on one Side, and in about ten Minutes after, he <lb/>fell faſt aſleep,
          breathing with Difficulty; half an <lb/>Hour after, I rouzed him, found him ſlabbering,
          <lb/>drowzy, ſinking behind, and giddy: About an Hour <lb/>and a Quarter after the firſt
          Injection, I found him as <lb/>before, but provoking him with a Stick, he bit at it, <pb
            n="167"/>
          <lb/>and tho' naturally fierce, he was very quiet when I <lb/>did not ſtrike him; in a few
          Minutes he reeled <lb/>and fell a ſnoaring again: About Nine at Night he <lb/>ſeemed very
          well, only drowſy. We left him all that <lb/>Night without Water and Victuals, but thro'
          Hunger <lb/>he eat ſome of the Straw he lay on, as we found af- <lb/>terwards upon opening
          his Stomach. Next Morning, <lb/>being <hi rend="italic">Friday</hi>, we gave him Water and
          Bones; he <lb/>drank greedily, and eat the Bones, Bread, and what- <lb/>ever was given
          him, ſeeming perfectly recover'd <lb/>and well all Day and the next Night, only very thir-
          <lb/>ſty, and a little drowzy, but perfectly gentle. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On <hi rend="italic">Saturday</hi>, about Nine o'clock in the Forenoon, <lb/>we
          faſten'd him to a Poſt, and put a Rope into his <lb/>Mouth, by which his Noſe was ty'd
          faſt to a Rail, <lb/>great Care being taken that there ſhould be no Rope <lb/>about his
          Neck ſo tight, as to hinder his ſwallowing <lb/>or his breathing: I then gave him three
          Ounces of the <lb/>ſecond Running, at three times, with an Horn, ſuch <lb/>as they drench
          Horſes with; he ſwallowed it with <lb/>great Difficulty, and guggled ſome up again: To
          pre- <lb/>vent which, I thruſt the Horn a good way down his <lb/>Throat. We then unty'd
          him from the Poſt, to ſee <lb/>how he could walk, but he inſtantly reeled, fell <lb/>down,
          rolled over and over, diſcharg'd much Urine, <lb/>and ſome hard <hi rend="italic">Fæces
            alvinæ</hi>, had no Motion to vomit, <lb/>but dribbled much, panted, and ſhewed great
          Diffi- <lb/>culty of breathing, ſnuffing up the Air with his No- <lb/>ſtrils, holding his
          Noſe up, as he ſat on his Breech; <lb/>for he could not then ſtand on his hind Legs: He
          often <lb/>ſhook his Head, as if ſtung by ſome Fly: He gradually <lb/>recover'd, and in
          about twenty Minutes time could <pb n="168"/>
          <lb/>walk about very ſteadily on all his Legs, tho' he ſtill <lb/>appear'd weakeſt behind:
          Wherefore imagining he <lb/>might linger a long time, or perhaps recover entirely, <lb/>we
          made him faſt again, and gave him three Ounces <lb/>more, near half of which he ſpilt; and
          indeed out <lb/>of the ſix Ounces, I don't believe above three or four <lb/>enter'd his
          Stomach: He gave one terrible loud Howl, <lb/>and ſunk down at once, before we could untie
          him <lb/>from the Poſt, to ſee whether he could walk or not. <lb/>He never offer'd to riſe
          again, but lay on one Side, <lb/>panted, hung his Tongue out, and ſlabber'd much,
          <lb/>ſtretch'd all four Legs out three or four times, and <lb/>was quite dead and
          motionleſs in about five Minutes <lb/>time. I did not obſerve any Convulſion in the Muſ-
          <lb/>cles of the Neck and Back, nor was his Head and <lb/>Tail drawn nearer together, as
          in the Puppy. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>About half an Hour after I open'd him, being ſtill <lb/>warm. I found the Bladder
          contracted and empty; <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Rectum</hi> ſlightly inflamed, the ſmall
          Guts not di- <lb/>ſtended with Wind, but contracted, and almoſt cloſe; <lb/>the Bile was
          evacuated in a great Quantity into the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Duodenum</hi>, and was very
          thick, appearing like con- <lb/>gealed Honey; the Gall-bladder was almoſt empty; <lb/>but
          what remained in it was as thick as the other; to <lb/>the Inſide of the Gall-bladder
          there adhered ſeveral <lb/>Excreſcencies in Form and Size of Lentils, like <lb/>Drops of
          ſoftiſh yellow Wax: The Liver was exceed- <lb/>ingly inflamed, and almoſt livid: The
          Stomach was <lb/>contracted near the <hi rend="italic">Pylorus</hi>, and again about three
          <lb/>Inches above it; upon opening it, we found ſome <lb/>pieces of Bone in it, a pretty
          deal of Straw, and <lb/>about two Ounces of Fluid, which ſmelt ſtrong of the <pb n="169"/>
          <lb/>Laurel Water; but no <hi rend="italic">Mucus</hi>, as in the Puppy: Some <lb/>of the
            <hi rend="italic">Villi</hi> ſeemed ſlightly inflamed, the Blood Veſ- <lb/>ſels being
          very turgid: There was a great deal of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Mucus</hi> in the <hi
            rend="italic">Oeſophagus</hi>, which did not ſeem in- <lb/>flamed. On opening the <hi
            rend="italic">Thorax</hi>, the Lungs appear'd <lb/>exceedingly contracted, and very red
          and inflamed. <lb/>In this Dog it was very evident, that the <hi rend="italic">Pericar-
            <lb/>dium</hi> did not adhere to the <hi rend="italic">Diaphragm</hi> as in erect
          <lb/>Animals, here being a Diſtance of above two Inches, <lb/>which was fill'd up by an
            <hi rend="italic">Appendix</hi> to the right <lb/>Lung; on removing which the <hi
            rend="italic">Vena cava</hi> run from <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Diaphragm</hi> about
          three Inches to the <hi rend="italic">Pericar- <lb/>dium</hi> quite free, not adhering to
          the Back by any Fi- <lb/>bres or Membranes, and was entirely envelop'd by <lb/>this
          Appendix of the Lung. The <hi rend="italic">Vena cava</hi> and <lb/>all the Veins were
          vaſtly diſtended, and the Blood in <lb/>them coagulated, tho' the Body was yet hot: There
          <lb/>was little or no Blood in the <hi rend="italic">Aorta</hi>; only on preſſing it,
          <lb/>a ſmall Quantity of a tranſparent Fluid, which I took <lb/>for <hi rend="italic"
            >Serum</hi>, flowed out of it. The Blood was ſtrong- <lb/>ly coagulated in the right
          Auricle and Ventricle <lb/>of the Heart, being of a very dark Colour, and <lb/>fill'd them
          quite; but the left Auricle and Ventri- <lb/>cle contained only a ſmall Clot of congealed
          Blood, <lb/>which look'd more red and florid: I kept ſome Clots <lb/>of the Blood out of
          the Vein, and alſo out of the <lb/>left Ventricle, twenty-four Hours, but neither of
          <lb/>them liquified or run into <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>. I had the Head <lb/>cut off,
          but Buſineſs preventing, I did not open it till <lb/>twenty-four Hours after; a great deal
          of Blood drain- <lb/>ed from it, and upon opening it, the Veſſels did not <lb/>then appear
          diſtended, but the <hi rend="italic">Dura Mater</hi> look'd <pb n="170"/>
          <lb/>livid: There was no Blood at all in the <hi rend="italic">Sinus falci-
            <lb/>formis</hi>; the Brain look'd very well; the Veſſels of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
            >Plexus Choroides</hi> in each Ventricle were not di- <lb/>ſtended, but livid, nor were
          they burſt, there being <lb/>no Extravaſation in the Ventricles, only a very ſmall
          <lb/>Quantity of Lymph; which was the Caſe likewiſe <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic"
            >Pericardium</hi>, which had not above a Tea <lb/>Spoonful of Water in it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In both theſe Inſtances this Poiſon ſeems to act by <lb/>coagulating the Blood; ſo
          that it can't paſs the Lungs <lb/>or Brain: And I take it that the Puppy liv'd longer
          <lb/>than the great Dog; becauſe in the Puppy the <hi rend="italic">Fora- <lb/>men
            Ovale</hi> was open, by which the thicken'd Blood <lb/>could paſs, and perform a few
          Circulations more than <lb/>it could have done, had it had the Lungs to paſs thro';
          <lb/>and that in the Puppy the Brain was the Part the <lb/>moſt affected, as was evident
          from the Convulſions it <lb/>had: Whereas the Dog was little convulſed, but ſeem'd <lb/>to
          die of a Difficulty of Breathing; and the greateſt <lb/>Accumulation was found at the
          right Ventricle of <lb/>the Heart. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When I return'd to <hi rend="italic">London</hi>, I got a middling-ſiz'd
          <lb/>Spaniel, on whom I tried the Experiment at the Houſe <lb/>of our Honourable
          Preſident. I pour'd about three <lb/>Ounces of the Laurel Water into an old Coffee-Pot,
          <lb/>and while the Dog was held faſt by another, ſome <lb/>Laurel Water was poured down
          his Throat: He ſtrug- <lb/>gled pretty much at firſt, and whined; but when about <lb/>half
          of it was down, he ceaſed ſtruggling; that <lb/>he might not be too long a dying, the
          Remainder was <lb/>given him; he ſpilt about one third of the whole <lb/>Quantity: He was
          then laid down on the Ground, <pb n="171"/>
          <lb/>but never offer'd to get up, only ſtretching out his <lb/>Legs, expir'd preſently.
          Mr. <hi rend="italic">Ranby</hi>, who aſſiſted <lb/>at the Experiment, open'd him
          immediately; there <lb/>was about two Ounces of the Laurel Water found in <lb/>his
          Stomach, and ſome frothy <hi rend="italic">Mucus</hi>; the Veins in <lb/>general were very
          turgid, but the Blood was ſtill fluid; <lb/>and indeed we could diſcern no Alteration in
          any of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Viſcera</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I gave four Ounces of <hi rend="italic">Laurel Water</hi> to Dr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Porter, <lb/>Coll. Med. Lond. Licentiat.</hi> He forc'd down a pretty large <lb/>Dog
          three Ounces, with no great Difficulty. The Crea- <lb/>ture inſtantly returned about two
          Ounces by Vomit, <lb/>clear and unalter'd; in a few Minutes he grew prodigi- <lb/>ouſly
          convulſed, ſoon after became motionleſs, and to all <lb/>appearance was dying. Within ten
          Minutes he vomited <lb/>a ſecond time, and threw up a ſmall Quantity of a viſ- <lb/>cid,
          green, and very frothy Matter: From which Mo- <lb/>ment he began to recover, and within
          half an Hour <lb/>was perfectly well. He was kept in the Yard all Night, <lb/>and the Next
          Morning not the leaſt Diſorder being to <lb/>be perceived in him, he was turned out of
          Doors. </p>
      </div>
   <div>
        <head rend="italic hanging space">
          <lb/>An Account of the Experiment tried upon a Dog <lb/>with <hi rend="roman">Laurel
            Water</hi>, in the Preſence of ſeveral <lb/>Members of the <hi rend="roman">Royal
            Society</hi>, in their Repoſi- <lb/>tory, upon <hi rend="roman">Thurſday</hi> the <hi
            rend="roman">28</hi>th of <hi rend="roman">October 1731</hi>. <lb/>By <hi rend="roman"
            >Cromwell Mortimer</hi>, R. S. Secr. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>Bout half an Hour after Six in the Evening I <lb/>gave about
          half an Ounce of the <hi rend="italic">Laurel Water</hi>
          <lb/>to a middle-ſiz'd Spaniel weighing near ſixteen Pound, <lb/>which he ſwallowed with
          great Reluctance, ſpilling <pb n="172"/>
          <lb/>near as much more, which I endeavour'd to pour down <lb/>his Throat. Some of the
          Company deſired he might <lb/>be ſet down, to ſee what Effect ſo ſmall a Quantity
          <lb/>would produce: He remained about a Minute and half <lb/>on his Legs; he then began to
          reel, and in about three <lb/>Minutes more fell into moſt violent Convulſions, and
          <lb/>his Neck and Tail were ſtrongly drawn toward each <lb/>other; he neither vomited nor
          purged, but we ex- <lb/>pected he would expire every Minute, the Convulſi- <lb/>ons being
          ſo exceedingly ſtrong, when ſome of the <lb/>Company call'd for ſome Milk, in order to try
          whe- <lb/>ther it would prove an Antidote to ſo <hi rend="italic">deſperate a
            <lb/>Poiſon</hi>. We poured a little Milk into his Throat, <lb/>which at firſt he could
          not ſwallow, but guggled it <lb/>up again as if almoſt ſtrangled with it. After ſeveral
          <lb/>Trials he began to ſwallow ſome, about a ſpoonful at <lb/>a time, and ſeemed a little
          relieved, his Convulſions <lb/>leaving him, only fetching his Breath very hard; but
          <lb/>he lay ſtill and ſnorted, as if in a profound Sleep; <lb/>and the Milk frothed out of
          his Noſe: On rouzing <lb/>him, he opened his Eyes, and ſwallowed the Milk <lb/>better,
          which ſeemed to revive him much; ſo that <lb/>the Company imagining he would entirely
          recover, <lb/>went away. I ſtaid ſome time longer, till at laſt he <lb/>began to lap the
          Milk himſelf when held up to it: <lb/>He vomited up a pretty deal of Milk, which relieved
          <lb/>him more; and then he lapped again, but could not <lb/>ſtand on his Legs. I left him
          in this Condition about <lb/>ſeven o'Clock, thinking he would have recovered, <lb/>and
          left Orders that he ſhould have a Pan of Milk, <lb/>and another of Water, about a Pint of
          each, ſet by <lb/>him, and that he ſhould be kept ſhut up all Night. <pb n="173"/>
          <lb/>About eleven o'Clock he was ſeen alive and walk- <lb/>ing about; but next Morning he
          was found dead, af- <lb/>ter having drank up all the Milk and Water, and hav- <lb/>ing
          vomited and purged pretty much. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Thus we find this ſimple Water diſtilled from a <lb/>Vegetable, equally mortal with
          the Bite of the Rattle- <lb/>Snake, and more quick in its Operation than any Mi-
          <lb/>neral Poiſon; and tho' it may not immediately bring <lb/>on Death, when taken in
          ſmall Quantities, or mixed <lb/>with other Liquors, it being common among our good
          <lb/>Houſewives to put Laurel Leaves into Cream to give <lb/>it the Rattafia or
          Apricock-Kernel Flavour; and <lb/>ſome Compounders of Cordial Waters, to uſe the
          <lb/>Berries of this Plant in Brandy inſtead of Black Cher- <lb/>ries, to mix ſome of the
          diſtilled poiſonous Water <lb/>with Brandy to make Rattafia, or to dilute it with
          <lb/>common Water, till it reſembles Black-Cherry Water <lb/>in Taſte; tho one ſingle
          Draught at a time may not <lb/>prove immediately mortal, yet an habitual Uſe of <lb/>theſe
          Liquors muſt certainly be exceeding prejudicial <lb/>and unwholeſome, and in weakly
          Perſons muſt haſten <lb/>Death. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I am informed that a Gentleman and his Wife, who <lb/>uſed for ſeveral Years to drink
          daily a Dram or two <lb/>of the Brandy in which Laurel Berries were infus'd, <lb/>both
          died paralytic, having loſt their Speech ſome <lb/>time before. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
