<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Houstoun: An Account of the Contrayerva</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>William Houstoun</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of the Contrayerva, by Mr. William Houstoun, Surgeon in the Service of
              the Honourable South-Sea Company</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for W. Innys and R. Manby, Printers to the Royal Society, at the
                  West End of St. Paul's.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1731-1732</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">37</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">195-198</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111028653</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1731.0032</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT37_0195">
    <body>
      <pb n="195"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">II.</hi> An Account of the <hi rend="roman">Contrayerva</hi>, by Mr.
          <hi rend="roman">Wil- <lb/>liam Houſtoun</hi>, Surgeon in the Service of the
        <lb/>Honourable <hi rend="roman">South-Sea</hi> Company. </head>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">C</hi><hi rend="italic">ONTRAYERVA</hi> is a <hi rend="italic"
          >Spaniſh</hi> Word, ſig- <lb/>nifying as much as <hi rend="italic">Herba contra
          [Venena]</hi> or an <lb/>Herb againſt Poiſons. And as there are in all Countries <pb
          n="196"/>
        <lb/>different Plants to which that Virtue is aſcribed, the <lb/>Name of <hi rend="italic"
          >Contrayerva</hi> ſeems to have been given by <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Spaniards</hi> to
        as many of them as have come un- <lb/>der their Knowledge; for <hi rend="italic"
          >Hernandez</hi> has deſcribed a <lb/>Species of <hi rend="italic">Granadilla</hi> by that
        Name, and there are<sic>:</sic>
        <lb/>ſeveral other Roots that are commonly known by it: <lb/>But far from pretending to give
        a Hiſtory of all thoſe <lb/>Roots, I only offer a ſhort Account of that Plant <lb/>whoſe
        Root is called <hi rend="italic">Contrayerva</hi> here in <hi rend="italic">England</hi>,
        <lb/>and is ſo well known to all that any way deal in Me- <lb/>dicines. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Root itſelf being ſo commonly known, it would <lb/>be ſuperfluous to deſcribe it, I
        ſhall therefore confine <lb/>myſelf to the Deſcription of the Plant that produces <lb/>it,
        which I have not hitherto met with to my Satis- <lb/>faction in any Author. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Father <hi rend="italic">Plumier</hi>, in his Book entituled, <hi rend="italic">Nova
          Plan- <lb/>tarum Americanarum Genera</hi>, deſcribes a <hi rend="italic">Genus</hi>
        <lb/>which he calls <hi rend="italic">Dorſtenia</hi>, whereof I have found two <lb/>Species
        in the <hi rend="italic">Weſt-Indies</hi>, the Roots of which are <lb/>gathered and exported
        indifferently, as being very <lb/>much alike, both in Appearance and Virtues. One of
        <lb/>theſe I think may be called </p>
      <figure>
        <p rend="indentall hanging space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Dorſtenia Dentariæ radice, Sphondylii folic, <lb/>placentâ
            ovali</hi>, Fig I. And the other </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of the first species of the plant, on a separate fold-out page.
        </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Dorſtenia Dentariæ radice, folio minus laciniato, <lb/>placentâ
            quadrangulari &amp; undulatâ</hi>, Fig. II. </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of the second species of the plant, on a separate fold-out page.
        </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The firſt Kind ſeems to be the <hi rend="italic">Tuzpatli</hi> of <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Hernandez</hi>, pag. 147. Its Roots, which are pe- <lb/>rennial, put forth
        in the Month of <hi rend="italic">May</hi> (or as <pb n="197"/>
        <lb/>ſoon as it happens to rain) each ſix or eight Leaves <lb/>four or five Inches long, and
        as many broad, cut into <lb/>ſeveral Segments almoſt as deep as the middle Rib,
        <lb/>ſomewhat after the Manner of the <hi rend="italic">Sphondylium</hi>: <lb/>They ſtand
        upon Footſtalks five or ſix Inches long; <lb/>and from the Middle of them come forth other
        Foot- <lb/>ſtalks ſomewhat longer, ſuſtaining each a ſtrange Sort <lb/>of Body, flat, and
        ſituated vertically, or with one <lb/>Edge uppermoſt, which I have called <hi rend="italic"
          >Placenta</hi>. In <lb/>this Species it is of an oval Figure, with its longer <lb/>Axis
        parallel to the Footſtalk. One ſide of it is <lb/>ſmooth and green like the outſide of the
          <hi rend="italic">Calix</hi> in <lb/>other Plants; but from the other ariſe a great many
        <lb/>ſmall yellow coloured Apices; and after they are gone, <lb/>many ſmall roundiſh Seeds
        begin to appear, which <lb/>when ripe are ſomewhat like thoſe of <hi rend="italic"
          >Gromwell</hi> or <lb/><hi rend="italic">Lithoſpermon</hi>. It grows in the Kingdom of <hi
          rend="italic">New <lb/>Spain</hi>, near old <hi rend="italic">Vera Cruz</hi>, on the high
        Ground, by <lb/>the Side of the River. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſecond Kind has much the ſame Number of <lb/>Leaves growing from each Root, as the
        former; but <lb/>of a different Figure, for ſome of them are entire, and <lb/>ſhaped like
        thoſe of a <hi rend="italic">Violet</hi>, others angular, like <lb/>Leaves of <hi
          rend="italic">Ivy</hi>, and ſome almoſt as much divided as <lb/>the Leaves of the common
          <hi rend="italic">Maple</hi>. They are thin, <lb/>and of a dark green Colour, and ſmooth,
        or have only a <lb/>few ſcarce perceptible Hairs on the Back. The Pedicles <lb/>that ſuſtain
        the Flowers ariſe immediately from the <lb/>Root as in the other Species, and attain to the
        ſame <lb/>Height of ſix or eight Inches. But the <hi rend="italic">Placenta</hi>
        <lb/>which ſuſtains the Flowers, is in this Kind Quadran- <lb/>gular, waved about the Edges,
        and broader tranſverſly <pb n="198"/>
        <lb/>than vertically. Yet the Flowers and Seeds themſelves <lb/>are perfectly the ſame as in
        the other. This ſecond <lb/>Kind grows plentifully on the high rocky Grounds <lb/>about <hi
          rend="italic">Campechy</hi>, where I gathered it in Perfection in <lb/>the Beginning of
          <hi rend="italic">November</hi>, 1730. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I cannot gueſs why Father <hi rend="italic">Plumier</hi> has called this <lb/>a
        monopetalous Plant; for that which he calls the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Petalum</hi>, and I
        the <hi rend="italic">Placenta</hi>, is of a green Colour, <lb/>and (which is of more
        Conſequence) ſuſtains the <lb/>Seeds when ripe, and never envelops the Organs of
        <lb/>Generation when young; ſo that I think it can by no <lb/>Means be called a <hi
          rend="italic">Petalum</hi>, nor even properly a <hi rend="italic">Ca- <lb/>lix</hi>, and
        therefore I have given it the Name of <hi rend="italic">Placen- <lb/>ta</hi>, whoſe Office
        it certainly performs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I have not been able to obſerve exactly the Structure <lb/>of the Organs of Generation,
        becauſe of their exceſ- <lb/>ſive Smallneſs; but they appear to the naked Eye as <lb/>they
        are repreſented in the Figures I have given of <lb/>them, and in <hi rend="italic">Plum. N.
          G. Tab.</hi> 8. The <hi rend="italic">Dorſtenia <lb/>Sphondylii folio Dentariæ
        radice</hi>, of <hi rend="italic">Plumier</hi>, dif- <lb/>fers from both of mine; for in his
        Drawings done <lb/>by Order of the late King of <hi rend="italic">France</hi>, whereof I
        have <lb/>ſeen a Copy in the Collection of the late Dr. <hi rend="italic">Sherard</hi>,
        <lb/>the Leaves are repreſented ſerrated, the <hi rend="italic">Placenta</hi> qua-
        <lb/>drangular, and the Roots conſiſting of ſeveral Knobs <lb/>tied together Lengthways.
        From which laſt Particu- <lb/>lar, I am perſwaded that the Root of that Species is <lb/>the
          <hi rend="italic">Drakena Radix</hi>, mentioned by <hi rend="italic">Cluſius</hi> in his
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Exoticks</hi>, pag. 83. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
