<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Belchier: A Remarkable Case of a Gentlewoman Who Died of a Hydrops
          Ovarii</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>John Belchier</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Remarkable Case of a Gentlewoman Who Died of a Hydrops Ovarii, in the
              Thirty-Third Year of Her Age, after Having Been Tapped Fifty-Seven Times. By Mr. John
              Belchier, Surgeon</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for W. Innys and R. Manby, Printers to the Royal Society,
                  at the West End of St. Paul's.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1731-1732</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">37</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">279-284</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111028653</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1731.0049</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT37_0279">
    <body>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <choice>
          <corr>
            <pb n="279"/>
          </corr>
          <sic>
            <pb n="729"/>
          </sic>
        </choice>
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">III.</hi> A remarkable Caſe of a Gentlewoman who died <lb/>of a <hi
          rend="roman">Hydrops Ovarii</hi>, in the Thirty-third <lb/>Year of her Age, after having
        been tapped <lb/>Fifty-ſeven times. By Mr. <hi rend="roman">John Belchier</hi>,
        <lb/>Surgeon. </head>
      <p rend="sapce">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N the Year 1725, the Wife of Mr. <hi rend="italic"
        >Newberry</hi>, a <lb/>Merchant in this City, complained of a Pain in <lb/>her Left-Side,
        near her Groin, internally, which ſen- <pb n="280"/>
        <lb/>ſibly increaſed; and perceiving a Swelling in that <lb/>Part, ſhe at firſt thought
        herſelf with Child; but ha- <lb/>ving other Symptoms not very common with gravid <lb/>Women,
        ſhe ſent for a Phyſician, who immediately <lb/>diſcovered it to be Hydropical, and after
        following his <lb/>Preſcriptions for ſome time, and finding little or no <lb/>Benefit
        thereby, ſhe ſent for another, and ſo for a <lb/>third and fourth; and after between two and
        three <lb/>Years fruitleſs Trial of proper Medicines preſcribed by <lb/>the Phyſicians, ſhe
        growing very big and uneaſy with <lb/>her Burden, was adviſed to be tapped, to which ſhe
        <lb/>accordingly ſubmitted: And on <hi rend="italic">May</hi> the 6th, 1728, <lb/>ſent for
        Mr. <hi rend="italic">Cheſelden</hi>, who took from her between <lb/>four and five Gallons
        of Water; but in a Week or ten <lb/>Days after the Operation ſhe perceived her ſelf to fill
        <lb/>again, in which State ſhe continued to the firſt Day of <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >July</hi> following, when Mr. <hi rend="italic">Cheſelden</hi> tapped her again, <lb/>and
        took from her about the ſame Quantity of Water <lb/>as before; and in this Manner ſhe
        continued to fill <lb/>and be tapped every third or fourth Week, from the <lb/>6th Day of
          <hi rend="italic">May</hi>, 1728, to the 3d of this Inſtant <lb/><hi rend="italic"><choice>
            <corr>March</corr>
            <sic>Marcb</sic>
          </choice></hi>, 173½, when ſhe died, in the Thirty-third <lb/>Year of her Age. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>During the laſt Thirty-ſeven times of her Tapping, <lb/>I conſtantly attended her with
        Mr. <hi rend="italic">Cheſelden</hi>, when <lb/>ſhe always ('till the two laſt times)
        appeared very <lb/>briſk and lively the whole time of the Water's running <lb/>from her, and
        was not in the leaſt ſick or faint after <lb/>the Diſcharge of the Water, as is uſual; and
        though <lb/>ſhe was a very thin emaciated Woman, ſhe would fre- <lb/>quently walk three or
        four Miles the Day before the <lb/>Operation, and moſt commonly went abroad the third
        <lb/>Day after it. </p>
      <pb n="281"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Quantity of Water taken from her each time <lb/>of Tapping was between four and
        five Gallons; and <lb/>during the whole Fifty-ſeven times Tapping, there ne- <lb/>ver was
        above a Quart, or two Quarts at moſt, differ- <lb/>ent in the Quantity, 'till the two laſt
        times, at each <lb/>of which the Quantity did not exceed two Gallons: <lb/>But in the
        Intervals of theſe two laſt Operations, ſhe <lb/>was frequently troubled with Reachings to
        Vo- <lb/>mit, which burſt open the Orifice twice where ſhe <lb/>was tapped, and at each time
        diſcharged about ſix <lb/>Quarts. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Quantity of Water which was taken from her <lb/>each time was always meaſured, and
        upon Computa- <lb/>tion the whole amounts to near Two hundred and <lb/>fifty Gallons. The
        Water that was taken from her <lb/>the two laſt times of Tapping was much more viſcid
        <lb/>than the former. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>At times ſhe frequently complained of a violent Pain <lb/>on her Right Side, and a
        heavy aching Pain in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pelvis</hi>. She had likewiſe a <hi
          rend="italic">Prolapſus Uteri</hi>; and <lb/>ſome time before her Death ſhe could not
        expel her <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fæces</hi> but with great Difficulty and Pain, and at the
        <lb/>ſame time laboured under an Incontinency of <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On <hi rend="italic">Monday</hi> the 6th of this Inſtant I opened her in <lb/>the
        Preſence of her Phyſician, when I found the whole <lb/><hi rend="italic">Viſcera</hi>, from
        the <hi rend="italic">Diaphragm</hi> to the <hi rend="italic">Oſſa Pubis</hi>, <lb/>covered
        with a thick gelatinous Subſtance, which <lb/>ſeemed to be membranous, which at its firſt
        Appear- <lb/>ance I took for the <hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi> in a putrified State; but
        <lb/>after a farther Examination, I found it to be only the <lb/>more viſcid Parts of the
        extravaſated Fluid, which <lb/>could not be diſcharged by the Operation: After <lb/>removing
        this, I found ſeveral Portions of a hard <pb n="282"/>
        <lb/>ſchirrous Subſtance ariſing from the <hi rend="italic">Fundus</hi> of the <lb/>Stomach,
        one large Portion of which was inſerted in- <lb/>to that Part of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Colon</hi> near the Right <hi rend="italic">Kidney</hi>, and <lb/>in Appearance reſembled
        the <hi rend="italic">Pancreatic Gland</hi>. Ano- <lb/>ther Portion, which was Cylindrical,
        and about two <lb/>Thirds of an Inch in Diameter, paſſed ſtreight over <lb/>the Inteſtines,
        adhering ſtrongly to that Part of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Colon</hi> which lies under the
          <hi rend="italic">Stomach</hi>, and was inſerted <lb/>into the <hi rend="italic"
          >Rectum</hi>, in the <hi rend="italic">Pelvis</hi>. Another Portion of <lb/>this Subſtance
        paſſed directly over the <hi rend="italic">Inteſtines</hi> to <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >Pelvis</hi>, but about the Middle of the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi> it <lb/>ſent out
        two ſmaller Portions, the one was inſerted <lb/>into the <hi rend="italic">Meſentery</hi>,
        the other reflecting back, was in- <lb/>ſerted into the <hi rend="italic">Colon</hi> on the
        left Side near the <hi rend="italic">Stomach</hi>. <lb/>As ſoon as I cut into one of theſe
        Portions, I diſco- <lb/>vered it to be a Part of the <hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi> twiſted
        up, and <lb/>contained in a very thick capſular Membrane. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Diaphragm</hi> was forced up ſo far by the Con- <lb/>tents of the
          <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, that the Cavity of the <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi>
        <lb/>was decreaſed to near one Third. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Liver</hi> was much larger than in a natural State, <lb/>and of
        one intire Subſtance, and not divided into <lb/><hi rend="italic">Lobes</hi>, the whole
        Convex Surface adhering firmly <lb/>to the <hi rend="italic">Diaphragm</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Stomach</hi> was very ſmall, as to its Cavity, but <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">Coats</hi> of it were increaſed to ſix times their natu- <lb/>ral Thickneſs
        (as were likewiſe all the <hi rend="italic">Coats</hi> of the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Inteſtines</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Meſentery</hi>) and very much in- <lb/>flamed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Two Thirds of the <hi rend="italic">Stomach</hi> adhered to that Part of <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">Diaphragm</hi> which did not cover the <hi rend="italic">Liver</hi>, and
        <lb/>the other Part adhered to the concave Surface of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Liver</hi>;
        as did likewiſe the <hi rend="italic">Duodenum</hi>, whoſe Cavity <pb n="283"/>
        <lb/>was very large. Below the <hi rend="italic">Duodenum</hi>, the <hi rend="italic"
          >Colon</hi> ad- <lb/>hered to the lower Part of the Concave Surface of the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Liver</hi>, ſo that the whole <hi rend="italic">Liver</hi> was contained in
        a <lb/>kind of <hi rend="italic">Burſa</hi> compoſed of the <hi rend="italic"
        >Diaphragm</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Stomach</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Duodenum</hi> and
          <hi rend="italic">Colon</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Cæcum</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Colon</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
          >Rectum</hi> were much larger <lb/>than in a natural State, and adhered ſo very ſtrongly
        <lb/>to the Parts over which they paſſed, that it was with <lb/>much difficulty I could
        ſeparate them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Spleen</hi> was not one Fourth of its natural Size, <lb/>and one
        Half of its external Surface was entirely Carta- <lb/>laginous. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Pancreas</hi> was ſmaller than uſual, as were like- <lb/>wiſe the
          <hi rend="italic">Kidneys</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Ureters</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
          >Bladder</hi>; and in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pelvis</hi> of each <hi rend="italic"
          >Kidney</hi> there were ſmall ſabulous <lb/>Concretions. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The left <hi rend="italic">Ovarium</hi> was diſtended to ſo large a Size, <lb/>as to
        fill the whole Cavity of the <hi rend="italic">Pelvis</hi> up to the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Os Pubis</hi>; its Surface was Cartalaginous, like that of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >Spleen</hi>, and in it were contained a great Number <lb/>of <hi rend="italic"
          >Hydatides</hi> of different Sizes, whereas the right <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ovary</hi>
        was no ways diſeaſed in the leaſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Difficulty and Pain complained of in the Ex- <lb/>pulſion of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Fæces</hi>, naturally ariſe from the Preſ- <lb/>ſures on the diſeaſed <hi rend="italic"
          >Ovarium</hi>, at the ſame time that its <lb/>increaſed Bulk, by compreſſing the <hi
          rend="italic">Inteſtinum Rectum</hi>
        <lb/>impeded the Egreſs of the <hi rend="italic">Fæces</hi>, and brought on the
        <lb/>Inflammation of the <hi rend="italic">Inteſtines</hi>, which we obſerved. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Prolapſus Uteri</hi>, and the Incapacity of the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Bladder</hi>'s retaining a proper Quantity of <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi>,
        were <lb/>likewiſe occaſioned by the Preſſures of this diſeaſed <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Ovarium</hi> upon thoſe Parts. </p>
      <pb n="284"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But what ſeems moſt material in this Caſe, is the <lb/>viſcid Matter found in the
        Cavity of the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>; <lb/>which as the Waters were originally
        incyſted in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ovary</hi>, was properly extravaſated from the <hi
          rend="italic">Cyſtus</hi>
        <lb/>into the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi> in the two laſt Operations; by <lb/>which, as
        well the Quantity drawn off as the cuſto- <lb/>mary Relief, were very much diminiſhed; in
        lieu of <lb/>which the <hi rend="italic">Stimulus</hi>, from ſuch a Fluid, might reaſona-
        <lb/>bly bring on the Vomiting obſerved from that time. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Quer.</hi> Therefore, if ſuch a Vomiting enſuing the <lb/>Operation
        is not a fatal Symptom? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Quer.</hi> If any Method can be found to prevent ſuch
        <lb/>Extravaſations? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Relations of this Gentlewoman are of Opinion, <lb/>that her Diſeaſe was occaſioned
        by pulling off her <lb/>Cloaths, when ſhe was very hot, to go into a Bathing- <lb/>Tub of
        Water to cool her, when finding the Water <lb/>exceſſive cold, ſhe put only her Legs in, the
        other <lb/>Part of her Body being out of the Water, and naked <lb/>at the ſame time; which
        happened a few Weeks be- <lb/>fore ſhe perceived the Swelling and Pain in her <hi
          rend="italic">Pelvis</hi>; <lb/>and probably this might be the Cauſe. As the Con-
        <lb/>ſtriction of the lower Parts by the cold Water might, <lb/>in a great meaſure, impede
        the <hi rend="italic">Fluids</hi> circulating <lb/>through the lower Parts, and the Blood
        being at the <lb/>ſame time rarified and expanded by the Heat, might <lb/>therefore burſt
        through the more tender <hi rend="italic">Lymphaticks</hi>, <lb/>and produce the
        Extravaſation. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
