<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Madden: An Account of Two Women Being Poisoned by the Simple Distilled
          Water of Laurel-Leaves</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>T. Madden</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Letter from T. Madden, M. D. of Dublin, to Cromwell Mortimer, M. D. R. S. Secr.
              Giving an Account of Two Women Being Poisoned by the Simple Distilled Water of
              Laurel-Leaves, and of Several Experiments upon Dogs; By Which It Appears That This
              Laurel-Water is One of the Most Dangerous Poisons Hitherto Known</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for W. Innys and R. Manby, Printers to the Royal Society, at the
                  West End of St. Paul's.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1731-1732</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">37</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">84-100</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111028653</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1731.0017</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT37_0084">
    <body>
      <pb n="84"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VII.</hi> A Letter from <hi rend="roman">T. Madden</hi>, M. D. of
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">Dublin</hi>, to <hi rend="roman">Cromwell Mortimer</hi>, M. D.
        <lb/>R. S. Secr. giving an Account of two <hi rend="roman">Women <lb/>being poiſoned</hi> by
        the <hi rend="sc">Simple Distilled <lb/>Water of Laurel-Leaves</hi>, and of <lb/>ſeveral
        Experiments upon Dogs; by <hi rend="roman">which</hi> it ap- <lb/>pears that this <hi
          rend="sc">Laurel-Water</hi> is one of <lb/>the moſt <hi rend="sc">Dangerous Poisons</hi>
        hitherto <lb/>known. </head>
      <salute rend="indent space italic">
        <lb/>SIR, </salute>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Very extraordinary Accident that fell out here <lb/>ſome Months
        Ago, has diſcovered to us a moſt <lb/>dangerous Poiſon, which was never before known to
        <lb/>be ſo, though it has been in frequent Uſe among us. <lb/>The Thing I mean is a Simple
        Water, diſtilled from <lb/>the Leaves of the <hi rend="italic">Lauro-ceraſus</hi>. The Water
        is at <pb n="85"/>
        <lb/>firſt of a Milky Colour, but the Oil which comes over <lb/>the Helm with it, being in a
        good Meaſure ſeparated <lb/>from the Phlegm, by paſſing it through a Flannel-Bag, <lb/>it
        becomes as clear as common Water. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It has the Smell of the bitter Almond, or Peach- <lb/>Kernel, and has been for many
        Years in frequent Uſe <lb/>among our Houſewives and Cooks, to give that agree- <lb/>able
        Flavour to their Creams and Puddings. It has alſo <lb/>been much in Uſe among our Drinkers
        of Drams; and <lb/>the Proportion they generally uſe it in, has been one <lb/>Part of <hi
          rend="italic">Laurel-Water</hi> to four of <hi rend="italic">Brandy</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Nor has this Practice (however frequent) ever been <lb/>attended with any apparent ill
        Conſequences, till ſome <lb/>Time in the Month of <hi rend="italic">September</hi>, 1728,
        when it hap- <lb/>pened that one <hi rend="italic">Martha Boyſe</hi>, a Servant, who lived
        <lb/>with a Perſon that ſold great Quantities of this <hi rend="italic">Water</hi>, <lb/>got
        a Bottle of it from her Miſtreſs, and gave it to her <lb/>Mother <hi rend="italic">Anne
          Boyſe</hi> as a very rich Cordial. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Anne Boyſe</hi> made a Preſent of it to <hi rend="italic">Frances
          Eaton</hi>
        <lb/>her Siſter, who was a Shopkeeper in the Town, and <lb/>who, ſhe thought, might oblige
        her Cuſtomers with it. <lb/>Accordingly in a few Days ſhe gave about two Ounces <lb/>of the
          <hi rend="italic">Water</hi> to a Woman called <hi rend="italic">Mary Whaley</hi>, who
        <lb/>had bought ſome Goods of her. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Mary Whaley</hi> drank about two Thirds of what <lb/>was filled out,
        and went away. <hi rend="italic">Frances Eaton</hi> drank <lb/>the reſt. <hi rend="italic"
          >Mary Whaley</hi> went to another Shop to buy <lb/>ſomewhat elſe, and in about a quarter
        of an Hour af- <lb/>ter ſhe had drank the <hi rend="italic">Water</hi> (as I am informed)
        ſhe <lb/>complained of a violent Diſorder in her Stomach. She <lb/>was carried Home, and
        from that Time ſhe lost her <pb n="86"/>
        <lb/>Speech, and died in about an Hour, without Vomiting, <lb/>or Purging, or any
        Convulſion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Shopkeeper, <hi rend="italic">Francis Eaton</hi>, ſent Word to her <lb/>Siſter <hi
          rend="italic">Ann Boyſe</hi> of what had happened, who came <lb/>to her upon the Meſſage,
        and affirmed, that it was not <lb/>poſſible the Cordial (as ſhe called it) could have oc-
        <lb/>caſioned the Death of the Woman; and to convince <lb/>her of it, ſhe filled out about
        three Spoonfuls, and <lb/>drank it. She continued talking with <hi rend="italic">Francis
          Eaton</hi>
        <lb/>about two Minutes longer, and was ſo earneſt to per- <lb/>ſuade her of the Liquor's
        being inoffenſive, that ſhe filled <lb/>out two Spoonfuls more, and drank it off likewiſe.
        She <lb/>was hardly well ſeated in her Chair, when ſhe died, <lb/>without the leaſt Groan or
        Convulſion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Frances Eaton</hi>, who, as was before obſerved, had <lb/>drank
        ſomewhat above a Spoonful, found no Diſorder <lb/>in her Stomach, or elſewhere; but to
        prevent any ill <lb/>Conſequence, ſhe took a Vomit immediately, and has <lb/>been well ever
        ſince. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Mary Whaley</hi> was buried without being examined <lb/>by any one,
        that I can find, except the Coroner. I <lb/>went to ſee <hi rend="italic">Ann Boyſe</hi>
        about Twenty-four Hours af- <lb/>ter her Death, but could not prevail to have her open-
        <lb/>ed. She was about ſixty Years old; her Countenance <lb/>and Skin appeared well
        coloured, and her Features were <lb/>hardly altered, ſo that ſhe looked as one aſleep. Her
        <lb/>Belly was not ſwelled, nor had ſhe any other external <lb/>Mark of Poiſon. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This Accident brought into Diſcourse another of <lb/>the like Nature which happened
        about four Years <lb/>ſince in the Town of <hi rend="italic">Kilkenny</hi>. A young Gentle-
        <lb/>man, Son to Mr. <hi rend="italic">— Evans</hi>, an Alderman of the <pb n="87"/>
        <lb/>Town, miſtook a Bottle of this <hi rend="italic">Laurel-Water</hi> for a <lb/>Bottle of
          <hi rend="italic">Ptiſan</hi>. What Quantity he drank is un- <lb/>certain, but he died in
        a few Minutes, complaining of <lb/>a violent Diſorder in his Stomach. This Affair was
        <lb/>not much regarded at that Time, becauſe he laboured <lb/>under a Diſtemper, to which,
        or to an improper Uſe <lb/>of Remedies, his Death was attributed by thoſe about <lb/>him. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To ſatisfy myſelf farther as to the Effects of this <lb/>Poiſon, I made ſome
        Experiments, in Conjunction <lb/>with a few of my Friends, an Account of which fol-
        <lb/>lows. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I. <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 3, 1728, We gave a large Setting-Dog <lb/>three
        Ounces of <hi rend="italic">Laurel-Water</hi> by the Mouth. In three <lb/>Minutes after he
        had taken it, he began to be ſtrongly <lb/>convulſed. His Convulſions continued about five
        <lb/>Minutes; after which I untied him. He then fell in- <lb/>to a moſt violent Difficulty
        of Breathing, which laſted <lb/>about eight Minutes, and abated gradually; upon <lb/>which
        he endeavoured to raiſe himſelf, but could <lb/>not. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I tied him down once again, and gave him an Ounce <lb/>and an half more, upon which he
        ſunk at once, and <lb/>without any Return of his Convulſions, or Difficulty <lb/>of
        Breathing, he expired in two Minutes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon opening the Stomach, I found in it the whole <lb/>Quantity of <hi rend="italic"
          >Water</hi> which he had taken; its Sur- <lb/>face was covered with Froth, but it was not
        other- <lb/>wiſe altered in its Colour, Conſiſtence, or Smell. <lb/>The Inſide of the
        Stomach was not at all inflamed, <lb/>nor was there any viſible Alteration in the <hi
          rend="italic">Tunica <lb/>Villoſa</hi>. </p>
      <pb n="88"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Veins of the Stomach, all the <hi rend="italic">Meſaraick</hi> Veins, <lb/>and
        likewiſe the <hi rend="italic">Vena Cava</hi>, were much diſtended <lb/>with Blood; the <hi
          rend="italic">Arteries</hi>, on the contrary, were re- <lb/>markably empty. The <hi
          rend="italic">Liver</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gall-Bladder</hi> were <lb/>no Way altered.
        The <hi rend="italic">Kidneys</hi> were unuſually full of <lb/>Blood, and appeared of a
        bluiſh Colour, almoſt as <lb/>deep as that of the Violet Plumb. Upon making an <lb/>Inciſion
        into one of the <hi rend="italic">Kidneys</hi>, the Blood flowed in <lb/>much greater
        Plenty, and was more fluid than uſual. <lb/>In the <hi rend="italic">Heart</hi> there
        appeared nothing præternatural. <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Brain</hi> was no way altered. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>II. <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 24, We gave an Ounce and an half of <lb/>the ſame
          <hi rend="italic">Water</hi> to a Bitch of a ſmaller Size. She was <lb/>immediately let
        looſe, and in two Minutes ſhe loſt the <lb/>Uſe of her Limbs. She attempted ſeveral Times to
        <lb/>raiſe herſelf, and walk, but ſhe ſtaggered and reeled <lb/>about, and then fell down.
        She repeated this with- <lb/>out ceaſing about five or ſix Minutes. At laſt ſhe was
        <lb/>violently convulſed, eſpecially in the Muſcles that ex- <lb/>tend the <hi rend="italic"
          >Head</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Spine</hi>. About the Space of a Minute <lb/>ſhe had that
        Sort of Convulſion called the <hi rend="italic">Opiſthotonos</hi>, <lb/>the Back of her <hi
          rend="italic">Head</hi> being drawn almoſt to her <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tail</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After this ſhe vomited plentifully, and her Convul- <lb/>ſions ceaſed. She then lay
        ſtill for ſeven or eight Mi- <lb/>nutes, labouring for Breath (though not ſo violently
        <lb/>as in the former Caſe) and foaming at the Mouth. <lb/>We gave her an Ounce more of the
          <hi rend="italic">Water</hi>; upon which <lb/>her Difficulty of breathing encreaſed, and
        ſhe died in <lb/>two Minutes. </p>
      <pb n="89"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon opening the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi> and
        the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Head</hi>, we found every thing in the ſame State as in the
        <lb/>former Inſtance. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>III. <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 25, We gave two Ounces of the <hi rend="italic">Wa-
          <lb/>ter</hi> to a Dog of the ſame Size with the former, which <lb/>produced the like
        Appearances as in the foregoing Caſe. <lb/>This Dog was dying half an Hour; for the Doſe was
        <lb/>not repeated, becauſe he did not vomit up what he <lb/>had taken. Upon opening him, we
        found every thing <lb/>in the ſame State as in the former Inſtance. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>IV. <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 26, We gave two Drams and an half <lb/>of the <hi
          rend="italic">Water</hi> to a Dog of a middle Size, and imme- <lb/>diately untied him. He
        then ran about the Room ve- <lb/>ry briskly for about a Minute, and ſeemed to be no <lb/>Way
        affected with it; yet he ſoon loſt the Uſe of his <lb/>Limbs. He often attempted to raiſe
        himſelf, and walk, <lb/>but ſtill fell down again before he had moved two Yards <lb/>from
        the Place. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After this he vomited plentifully, conſidering that <lb/>he had faſted 24 Hours, upon
        which he was ſeized <lb/>with a Convulſion more violent than any of the former <lb/>Dogs,
        eſpecially in the Muſcles that extend the <hi rend="italic">Head</hi>
        <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Spine</hi>. Theſe Convulſions continued about eight <lb/>or ten
        Minutes; upon their ceaſing, he lay ſtill, breath- <lb/>ing deeply, though regularly, and
        ſeemed to be aſleep. <lb/>In about ten Minutes he raiſed himſelf, took ſome <lb/>Food, and
        walked about tolerably well. We left <lb/>him, and returning after three Hours, we found him
        <lb/>perfectly recovered. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>V. <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 28, We injected an Ounce of the <hi rend="italic">Wa-
          <lb/>ter</hi> into the <hi rend="italic">Inteſtinum rectum</hi> of a ſtrong Spaniel
        <lb/>Dog, and let him looſe. In the Space of two Mi- <pb n="90"/>
        <lb/>nutes he began to loſe the Uſe of his Limbs, and to ſtag- <lb/>ger as the others had
        done. He was convulſed more vio- <lb/>lently than any of the reſt, and chiefly in the
        Muſcles <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Neck</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Spine</hi>. The
        Muſcles of his <hi rend="italic">Eyes</hi>
        <lb/>were ſtrongly convulſed, which Appearance was not <lb/>obſerved in the other Dogs. He
        foamed at the Mouth, <lb/>yelled frequently, and breathed with more Difficulty <lb/>than any
        of the reſt. His Convulſions continued twenty <lb/>Minutes; upon their ceaſing he lay quiet,
        as though <lb/>he ſlept, only that his Eyes were open. His Limbs <lb/>were now grown
        perfectly paralytick. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We raiſed him up ſeveral Times, and offered to ſet <lb/>him on his Legs, but he did not
        attempt to uſe them. <lb/>He continued in this Way about fifteen Minutes longer, <lb/>and
        then was ſeized with another violent Convulſion, <lb/>which in five Minutes put an End to
        his Life. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon opening the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, we found the Veins <lb/>of the <hi
          rend="italic">Stomach</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Guts</hi> very much diſtended with
        <lb/>Blood, as in all the former Inſtances. In the <hi rend="italic">Heart</hi>, <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Lungs</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Brain</hi>, there was no viſible
        Alteration. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>VI. <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 30, We injected an Ounce and an half <lb/>of the <hi
          rend="italic">Water</hi>, diluted with three Ounces of common <lb/>Water warmed, into the
          <hi rend="italic">Anus</hi> of a ſmall Bitch. Be- <lb/>fore we could untie her ſhe was
        ſeized with Convul- <lb/>ſions, and yelled much. She fell as ſoon as ſhe was <lb/>looſed,
        and never after endeavoured to riſe. She had <lb/>Convulſions, and great Difficulty of
        Breathing about <lb/>two Minutes. She then lay ſtill, with her Limbs ſtiff <lb/>and
        extended, about three Minutes; during which Time <lb/>her lower Jaw was convulſed, and
        pulled alternately <lb/>to and from the upper Jaw, with a very quick Mo- <lb/>tion. </p>
      <pb n="91"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After this her Limbs became paralytick, and ſhe gaſp- <lb/>ed for Breath about two
        Minutes longer. She was quite <lb/>dead in ſeven or eight Minutes from the Injection of the
        <lb/>Clyſter. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi> and <hi
          rend="italic">Brain</hi> every thing <lb/>appeared as uſual. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>VII. <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 2, We injected half an Ounce of <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">Water</hi>, diluted with three Ounces of common <lb/>Water warmed, into the
          <hi rend="italic">Anus</hi> of a ſmall Bitch. In <lb/>the Space of four Minutes ſhe began
        to breathe with <lb/>Difficulty. We let her looſe, but ſhe was not able to <lb/>ſtand, or
        walk without ſtumbling. The Muſcles that <lb/>extend the <hi rend="italic">Head</hi> were
        convulſed, and her Fore-legs <lb/>were affected for three of four Minutes with a <hi
          rend="italic">Tetanus</hi>, <lb/>but had no convulſive Motion. She vomited and purged
        <lb/>plentifully. She did not yell, nor ſeem to ſuffer much <lb/>Pain, nor did ſhe loſe her
        Senſes all the Time. In <lb/>half an Hour ſhe recovered. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>VIII. The next Day, we injected a Drachm of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Water</hi> into
        the external <hi rend="italic">Jugular</hi> of the ſame Bitch. <lb/>She was ſeized with
        Convulſions as violent as the for- <lb/>mer, before we could untie her. They laſted about
        <lb/>five Minutes; after which ſhe recovered gradually, and <lb/>continued well. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>IX. <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 20, We injected four Ounces of the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Water</hi> by the <hi rend="italic">Anus</hi>, without any Dilution, into a
        ſtrong <lb/>Dog of a middling Size. He was ſeized with Con- <lb/>vulſions and Difficulty of
        Breathing, in leſs than two <lb/>Minutes after the Injection. He fell to the Ground as
        <lb/>ſoon as his Convulſions began, and never once attempt- <lb/>ed to riſe; nor were his
        Convulſions in any Sort ſo vio- <lb/>lent, neither did they continue ſo long as in the for-
          <pb n="92"/>
        <lb/>mer Inſtances. He bled at the Noſe about four Spoon- <lb/>fuls. The Blood was of a very
        bright florid Colour, <lb/>His Convulſions laſted about four Minutes; after which <lb/>he
        became entirely paralytick, and died in three Mi- <lb/>nutes more. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We found the <hi rend="italic">Stomach</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Inteſtines</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">Liver</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> in <lb/>the ſame State as thoſe
        above-mentioned. Upon cut- <lb/>ting about an Inch from the lower Part of one of the
        <lb/>Lobes of the <hi rend="italic">Lungs</hi>, the Blood flowed from it in great
        <lb/>Plenty, and appeared more florid and fluid than uſual. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>X. <hi rend="italic">Decemb.</hi> 14, We gave five Ounces of <hi rend="italic">Laurel-
          <lb/>Water</hi> by a Clyſter to a Dog ſomewhat of the Size and <lb/>Shape of the <hi
          rend="italic">Italian</hi> Greyhound. He ſeemed at firſt <lb/>to be no Way affected with
        it, but in about five Mi- <lb/>nutes he began to droop, and loſe the Uſe of his <lb/>Limbs.
        He did not once yell, or ſtruggle as the others <lb/>had done, but ſunk gradually, till he
        became at laſt <lb/>entirely paralytick. He had not any Convulſion, ex- <lb/>cept a kind of
          <hi rend="italic">Spaſmus Cynicus</hi>, a few Minutes before <lb/>he died, which happened
        in half an Hour after the <lb/>Injection of the Clyſter. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon opening the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, we found the Veins <lb/>much diſtended
        with Blood, as were alſo the Veins <lb/>and Sinuſes of the <hi rend="italic">Brain</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>XI. <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 19, We gave three Ounces of the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Water</hi> in the ſame Manner to a Cur of the Lap-dog <lb/>Size. He died in
        ſeven Minutes, without any Con- <lb/>vulſion, except a <hi rend="italic">Tetanus</hi> in the
        Muſcles that extend <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Head</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Lauro Cerafus</hi> being an Ever-green, and aboun- <lb/>ding with
        a warm eſſential Oil, we imagined that other <pb n="93"/>
        <lb/>Ever-greens might partake of the ſame poiſonous <lb/>Quality. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Accordingly we made Trial of a <hi rend="italic">Water</hi> diſtilled in <lb/>an <hi
          rend="italic">Alembick</hi> from the Leaves of the <hi rend="italic">Yew-Tree</hi>, ſo
        much <lb/>talked of by the Ancients, and whoſe very Shade they <lb/>ſuppoſed to be fatal to
        thoſe who ſate or ſlept under <lb/>it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>XII. We gave three Ounces of this <hi rend="italic">Water</hi> by Cly- <lb/>ſter to a
        very ſmall Cur Dog, but he was not in the <lb/>leaſt affected with it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>XIII. We alſo gave, by the Mouth, two Ounces of <lb/>a <hi rend="italic">Water</hi>,
        diſtilled from the Leaves of the <hi rend="italic">Bay-Tree</hi>, <lb/>to a young Spaniel,
        without any Effect. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>XIV. We afterwards made an Experiment with the <lb/>diſtilled <hi rend="italic"
          >Water</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Box-Leaves</hi>, which had a very <lb/>ſtrong <hi
          rend="italic">Narcotick</hi> Smell. We injected five Ounces of <lb/>this <hi rend="italic"
          >Water</hi>, by the <hi rend="italic">Anus</hi>, into a ſmall Cur Dog, but <lb/>he was no
        Way affected with it, though we kept him <lb/>twelve Hours after the Operation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>XV. Being deſirous to know whether the Virulency <lb/>of <hi rend="italic"
          >Laurel-Water</hi> was owing to the Fire in Diſtilla- <lb/>tion, we poured warm Water upon
        ſome <hi rend="italic">Laurel-</hi>
        <lb/>Leaves bruiſed, and made a ſtrong Infuſion of them. <lb/>We poured an Ounce of it down
        a Dog's Throat, hald <lb/>of which was ſuppoſed to enter the Stomach, and five <lb/>Minutes
        after another Ounce was given in like Manner. <lb/>The Dog ſeemed to be ſomewhat ſick at his
        Stomach, <lb/>but was ſoon as lively as ever. A few Minutes after <lb/>this another Ounce
        was given to him by the Mouth, <lb/>of which we ſuppoſe a fourth Part to have been loſt.
        <lb/>He ſoon after ſtared, and trembled very much. In five <lb/>Minutes another Ounce was
        exhibited, upon which <pb n="94"/>
        <lb/>he trembled as before, but in a little Time he appear- <lb/>ed eaſy and lively. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Imagining that theſe ſmall Quantities loſt their Pow- <lb/>er, during the Intervals of
        giving them, in ten Minutes <lb/>after his taking the former Doſe, we poured down his
        <lb/>Throat two Ounces and a half at once. He immedi- <lb/>ately tumbled on his Back
        convulſed, and tumbled over <lb/>three or four times, but quickly returned to his Feet.
        <lb/>He ſtaggered, his Eyes ſtared, and he ſate down like <lb/>a Dog that is tired. At
        length he ſhut his Eyes, his <lb/>Neck became extended, and we apprehended he was
        <lb/>falling into Convulſions; but inſtead thereof he vomi- <lb/>ted a vaſt Quantity of
        indigeſted <hi rend="italic">Chyle</hi>, in which ap- <lb/>peared a great Portion of the
        Infuſion; after which he <lb/>ſeemed to be perfectly recovered. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>XVI. In about twenty-five Minutes after this we <lb/>gave the ſame Dog by the Mouth two
        Ounces of the <lb/>Juice expreſſed from <hi rend="italic">Laurel-</hi>Leaves, and in about
        <lb/>ten Minutes more another Ounce was given him in <lb/>the ſame Manner. In a few Minutes
        he began to loſe <lb/>the Uſe of his hinder Legs, but he quickly recovered <lb/>them. Upon
        his taking another Ounce ſoon after the <lb/>former, he fell into a great Difficulty of
        Breathing, <lb/>and yelled much. After this he was ſeized with very <lb/>ſtrong Convulſions,
        which affected his lower Jaw and <lb/>hinder Legs moſt remarkably. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In about the Space of five Minutes theſe Convulſions <lb/>were ſucceeded by an entire
        Reſolution of all the <lb/>Limbs. He breathed with great Difficulty, and very <lb/>ſlowly.
        No Appearance of Expiration. Sometimes <lb/>we obſerved two Attempts at Inſpiration without
        In- <lb/>termiſſion, or cloſing of the Mouth. At other <pb n="95"/>
        <lb/>times there was near the Space of a Minute between <lb/>two Inſpirations. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After this he was ſeized with a Trembling in his <lb/>Limbs, and in about three
        Quarters of an Hour from <lb/>his taking the laſt Ounce, he died without any Strug-
        <lb/>ling, with his Tail extended. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There were ſeveral other Experiments made of the <lb/>ſame kind, by ſome Gentlemen of
        the Profeſſion here, <lb/>which correſponded exactly with the foregoing, ex- <lb/>cepting
        this one Circumſtance, that they were of Opi- <lb/>nion, that this Poiſon occaſioned an
        Inflammation in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Stomach</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Guts</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Towards clearing this Diſpute, We, who thought <lb/>otherwiſe, put together the
        following Hints, from <lb/>which it appears that the Fact is not as they imagin- <lb/>ed,
        and that notwithſtanding we find, upon an Animal's <lb/>being killed by this Poiſon, the
        Veins greatly diſtend- <lb/>ed with Blood, yet there is not any Inflammation pro- <lb/>duced
        by it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I do not know any thing that will illuſtrate this <lb/>Matter better, than the Analogy
        which may be ob- <lb/>ſerved between the Convulſions occaſioned by the Epi- <lb/>lepſy, and
        thoſe which are the Effect of <hi rend="italic">Laurel- <lb/>Water</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For Inſtance, in the Epilepſy, the Body is univer- <lb/><choice>
          <corr>ſally</corr>
          <sic>verſally</sic>
        </choice> convulſed, eſpecially the Muſcles of the <hi rend="italic">Neck</hi>, <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">Tongue</hi>, the lower <hi rend="italic">Jaw</hi>, and thoſe of the <hi
          rend="italic">Arms</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Effect of theſe Convulſions is this: The <hi rend="italic">Heart</hi>
        <lb/>beats with unuſual Violence and Frequency, the ne- <lb/>ceſſary Conſequence of which
        is, that the Blood will <lb/>be thrown in greater Plenty from the Arteries into the
        <lb/>Veins. But becauſe the Muſcles do compreſs the Veins <pb n="96"/>
        <lb/>more than the Arteries (whoſe Syſtole does enable <lb/>them to overcome that Preſſure)
        therefore the Blood, <lb/>which is ſtill puſhed forward by the Syſtole of the <lb/>Heart
        into the Veins, will be retained there by the afore- <lb/>ſaid Preſſure of the Muſcles, and
        will return in a very <lb/>ſmall Quantity to the <hi rend="italic">Heart</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For Example, the <hi rend="italic">Abdominal</hi> Muſcles being con- <lb/>vulſed, preſs
        the <hi rend="italic">Stomach</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Inteſtines</hi> upon the <hi
          rend="italic">Vena <lb/>Cava aſcendens</hi>, and likewiſe upon the <hi rend="italic">Vena
          Portæ</hi>; <lb/>by which Means the Blood, returning from the lower <lb/>Extremities, is
        retained in thoſe Veſſels. Accordingly <lb/>we ſee the viſible and immediate Effects of this
        Preſ- <lb/>ſure are the forcing out the Excrements of the <hi rend="italic">Blad-
          <lb/>der</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Inteſtines</hi>, and very frequently the <hi
          rend="italic">Profluvi- <lb/>um Seminis</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In like Manner the Preſſure of the Muſcles of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Neck</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">Tongue</hi>, and lower <hi rend="italic">Jaw</hi> upon the <hi rend="italic"
          >Jugular</hi>
        <lb/>Veins and their Branches, will not ſuffer the Blood to <lb/>return to the <hi
          rend="italic">Heart</hi> by the <hi rend="italic">Vena Cava deſcendens</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To this we may add the Preſſure of the <hi rend="italic">Diaphragm</hi>
        <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Ribs</hi> upon the <hi rend="italic">Lungs</hi>, by which Means
        the Trunks <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Vena Cava aſcendens</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
          >deſcendens</hi> are com- <lb/>preſſed at their Inſertion into the <hi rend="italic"
          >Heart</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Hence follows that frightful Blackneſs of the Face <lb/>during the Paroxyſm, and the
        prodigious Swelling of <lb/>the Veins of the Head, eſpecially the Temporal. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The neceſſary Conſequence of all this muſt be, that if <lb/>the Convulſion laſts long
        enough the Man muſt die, on <lb/>Account of the Blood being thrown out of the Arteries
        <lb/>into the Veins, and not returning to the Heart. And I <lb/>make no Queſtion, that if
        ſuch a Perſon was opened <lb/>after Death, we ſhould find the <hi rend="italic">Vena
          Cava</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Vena </hi>
        <pb n="97"/>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Portæ</hi>, the Veins and Sinuſes of the <hi rend="italic"
        >Brain</hi>, together <lb/>with all their ſmalleſt Ramifications, very much di- <lb/>ſtended
        with Blood, and the Arteries on the contrary <lb/>almoſt empty. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But if the Epileptick Convulſion ceaſes before the Cir- <lb/>culation of the Blood is
        entirely ſtopped, then all becomes <lb/>calm again, the Preſſure is taken off the Veins, the
        <lb/>Blood returns to its uſual Courſe, and in a few Hours <lb/>the ſick Perſon is perfectly
        recovered. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And yet all this violent Convulſion of the Body, this <lb/>prodigious Diſtenſion of the
        Veins, and Interception of <lb/>the Courſe of the Blood paſſes without any Inflamma-
        <lb/>tion, as appears from the ſpeedy Recovery of the ſick <lb/>Perſon: For if the
        Convulſion had occaſioned an Inflam- <lb/>mation, a Fever muſt neceſſarily have enſued,
        which <lb/>would diſcover itſelf by manifeſt Tokens, and would re- <lb/>quire a much longer
        Time for its Abatement. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Let us now obſerve the Analogy between theſe Ap- <lb/>pearances, and thoſe produced by
          <hi rend="italic">Laurel-Water</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We find by Experiment, that an Ounce, or even two <lb/>Drachms and a half of <hi
          rend="italic">Laurel-Water</hi> will occaſion <lb/>more violent Convulſions than three
        Ounces, or even five <lb/>of it. <hi rend="italic">Exp.</hi> 4, 5 to 11. If therefore an
        Inflammation <lb/>was the neceſſary Conſequence of this <hi rend="italic">Water</hi> being
        ta- <lb/>ken into the <hi rend="italic">Stomach</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Guts</hi>, the
        more violent the Con- <lb/>vulſion is, the greater the Inflammation ought to be. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the contrary we find, that the more violent the Con- <lb/>vulſion is, the greater is
        the Probability that the Crea- <lb/>ture will recover. <hi rend="italic">Exp.</hi> 4 to 7.
        And when it ſo falls out, <lb/>the Manner is exactly the ſame as in the Recovery of an
        <lb/>Epileptick Perſon. In a few Minutes the Creature be- <lb/>comes as brisk as if no ſuch
        Thing had happened. </p>
      <pb n="98"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Now if an Inflammation was at all the neceſſary Con- <lb/>ſequence of this Poiſon,
        though the Creature recovers, <lb/>yet there muſt be ſome Inflammation, greater or leſs,
        pro- <lb/>duced, which muſt occaſion more violent and laſting <lb/>Symptoms. But ſince none
        ſuch appear, ſince the Recovery <lb/>is ſo ſudden and effectual, it is the ſtrongest and
        plaineſt <lb/>Argument, that there is not any Inflammation produced. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If the <hi rend="italic">Laurel-Water</hi> is adminiſtred to the Quantity <lb/>of an
        Ounce or more, the Creature unavoidably dies in a <lb/>few Minutes, and upon opening him the
        Appearances are <lb/>theſe. Both the Trunks of the <hi rend="italic">Vena Cava</hi>, and all
        the <lb/>Ramifications of the <hi rend="italic">Meſeraick</hi> Veins are greatly diſten-
        <lb/>ded with Blood. Theſe Veſſels are eaſily diſtinguiſhed <lb/>from the Arteries, not only
        by the Thinneſs of their <lb/>Coats, but alſo by the Colour which the Blood exhi- <lb/>bits
        to the Eye. Now I conceive that all Inflammati- <lb/>ons have their Beginning in the
        Arteries, and that they <lb/>are produced, becauſe there is no free Paſſage for the
        <lb/>Blood into the Veins. But if once this Paſſage becomes <lb/>free (as in this Caſe it
        ſurely is, for we find all the <lb/>Veins diſtended with Blood beyond their natural Di-
        <lb/>menſions) the Inflammation is then at an End, the Cauſe <lb/>which produced it being
        taken off. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Moreover, the Fact laid down, that the Veins are pre- <lb/>ternaturally diſtended with
        Blood, does neceſſarily con- <lb/>clude, that the Arteries are not diſtended with it, and
        <lb/>conſequently that there cannot be any Inflammation; <lb/>for if the Quantity of Blood
        is encreaſed in the Veins, <lb/>it muſt be proportionably diminiſhed in the Arteries. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To what has been ſaid, we may add the following <lb/>Obſervation; <hi rend="italic"
          >viz.</hi> that if there was any Inflammation <lb/>produced by this Poiſon, it ought to
        appear moſt re- <pb n="99"/>
        <lb/>markable on the Inſide of the <hi rend="italic">Stomach</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
          >Inteſtines</hi>, <lb/>becauſe of the immediate Contact it has with thoſe <lb/>Parts. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>All other Poiſons which occaſion Inflammations in <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >Stomach</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Guts</hi>, do firſt operate upon the Blood-
        <lb/>Veſſels, and corrode the Parts inflamed. They occaſion <lb/>Vomitings and Fluxes of
        Blood, which at length ter- <lb/>minate in Convulſions. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>One may very eaſily be deceived upon opening the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Stomach</hi> of
        a Dog, and may miſtake the Redneſs of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Tunica Villoſa</hi> for an
        Inflammation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The inner Coat of a Dog's Stomach is naturally of <lb/>a ruddy Fleſh-colour, and
        therefore of all domeſtick <lb/>Animals a Dog has the quickeſt and ſtrongeſt Digeſti-
        <lb/>on. Accordingly we ſee, that they ſwallow Bones, <lb/>and digeſt them perfectly well;
        and although they are <lb/>but half chewed when taken into the Stomach, yet <lb/>they are at
        laſt reduced to as ſoft a Conſiſtence as any <lb/>other Part of their Aliment. It is for
        this Reaſon <lb/>therefore, that the Stomachs of Dogs are more plenti- <lb/>fully ſupplied
        with Blood than thoſe of other Animals; <lb/>by which Means not only the muſcular Force of
        the <lb/>Stomach, but its Warmth alſo, which is the principal <lb/>Inſtrument of Digeſtion,
        is very much increaſed. </p>
      <p rend="indentall hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">N. B.</hi> The 15th and 16th <hi rend="italic">Experiments</hi> were
        com- <lb/>municated to me by Dr. <hi rend="italic">Stephens</hi>, a Fellow of <lb/>our
        College of Phyſicians. I am, </p>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <dateline rend="size(0.7) hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Dublin</hi>, <hi rend="italic">April</hi>
        <lb/>29, 1731. </dateline>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <salute rend="space italic align-center">
        <lb/>SIR, </salute>
      <signed rend="italic space">
        <lb/>Your moſt humble Servant, <lb/><hi rend="roman size(1.2)">T. M<hi rend="sc">adden</hi>.
        </hi>
      </signed>
      <pb n="100"/>
      <postscript rend="space italic">
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">D</hi>R. <hi rend="roman">John Rutty</hi> of <hi rend="roman"
            >Dublin</hi>, informed the Publiſher, <lb/>That whereas there were ſeveral other Experi-
          <lb/>ments made at the ſame Time by other Gentlemen, <lb/>as Dr. <hi rend="roman"
            >Madden</hi> mentions, which agreed with theſe, <lb/>ſome Perſons who were preſent at
          them propoſed ſe- <lb/>veral things to be tried as Antidotes to this Poiſon;
          <lb/>accordingly <hi rend="roman">Bole</hi>, <hi rend="roman">Vinegar</hi> and <hi
            rend="roman">Milk</hi> were given to a <lb/>Dog which had ſwallowed ſome of the <hi
            rend="roman">Laurel-Wa- <lb/>ter</hi>: The <hi rend="roman">Bole</hi> and <hi
            rend="roman">Vinegar</hi> were not obſerved to do <lb/>much good, but the Dog which
          drank the <hi rend="roman">Milk</hi> re- <lb/>covered without any bad Symptoms; but at
          that <lb/>Diſtance of Time the Doctor could not recollect the <lb/>Proportions that were
          given: He thinks a Pint of <lb/><hi rend="roman">Milk</hi>. The Publiſher hath tried
          ſeveral Experiments <lb/>in <hi rend="roman">Eſſex</hi> and in <hi rend="roman"
            >London</hi>, which correſpond with, and <lb/>confirm the above-related, and will be
          communi- <lb/>cated to the Publick in ſome other <hi rend="roman">Tranſaction</hi>. </p>
      </postscript>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
