<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Cockburn: A Discourse concerning the Difficulty of Curing
          Fluxes</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>William Cockburn</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Discourse concerning the Difficulty of Curing Fluxes, Writ Occasionally on
              Reading Dr. de Jussieu's Memoire in the History, &amp;c. of the Royal Academy of Sciences
              in Paris, for the Year 1729. By William Cockburn, M. D. F. R. S. and of the College of
              Physicians, London </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for W. Innys and R. Manby, Printers to the Royal Society, at the
                  West End of St. Paul's.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1731-1732</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">37</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">385-393</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111028653</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1731.0063</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT37_0385">
    <body>
      <pb n="385"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">III.</hi> A Diſcourſe concerning the <hi rend="roman">Difficulty of
          cu- <lb/>ring Fluxes</hi>, writ occaſionally on reading Dr. <hi rend="roman">de
          <lb/>Juſſieu</hi>'s <hi rend="roman">Memoire</hi> in the Hiſtory, <hi rend="roman"
          >&amp;c.</hi> of the <lb/>Royal Academy of Sciences in <hi rend="roman">Paris</hi>, for
        the Year <lb/>1729. By <hi rend="roman">William Cockburn</hi>, M. D. F. R. S. <lb/>and of
        the College of Phyſicians, <hi rend="roman">London</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N reading Dr. <hi rend="italic">de Juſſieu</hi>'s Memoire, about
        the pre- <lb/>ſent Diſgrace of <hi rend="italic">Ipecacuanha</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
          >France</hi>, and the <lb/>Method he propoſes for redreſſing its Defects by <hi
          rend="italic">Si- <lb/>marouba</hi>, a Root brought from <hi rend="italic">Cayen</hi> in
          <hi rend="italic">America</hi>, <lb/>I was ſurpriz'd to find a Remedy almoſt ador'd for
        <lb/>half a Century, to have fallen into the utmoſt Con- <lb/>tempt; a <hi rend="italic"
          >Specifick</hi>, a very ſhort and ſatisfactory Word, <lb/>totally neglected by its moſt
        zealous Votaries. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The learned Profeſſor alledges, that this great Re- <lb/>volution, in the Fame of <hi
          rend="italic">Ipecacuanha</hi>, proceeds from <lb/>its having been unſkilfully
        adminiſtred: Phyſicians <lb/>commonly conſidering the general Appearance of a <lb/>Looſeneſs
        only, without penetrating into the particu- <lb/>lar Cauſes which ſupport it, and that
        require, on that <lb/>Account, different Methods of curing it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Monſ. <hi rend="italic">de Juſſieu</hi>, avoiding all Extremes, is an <lb/>Enemy to the
        baniſhing <hi rend="italic">Ipecacuanha</hi> altogether out <lb/>of the Practice of Phyſick,
        as many of its diſappoint- <lb/>ed Adorers now do; because it is not the infallible Spe-
        <lb/>cifick they vainly imagined it to be. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This common Miſapplication of Medicines, or our <lb/>Ignorance of the particular
        Circumſtances of a Diſeaſe, <lb/>when it requires a different Method of Cure, is the
        <lb/>very Reaſon why great Numbers of excellent Medi- <pb n="386"/>
        <lb/>cines, among ancient Phyſicians, have been loſt, be- <lb/>cauſe they were not
        underſtood. Take a broken Shin <lb/>only, which has the Skin only rubb'd off, obſerve
        <lb/>the Difficulty the beſt and honeſteſt Surgeons have to <lb/>cure it. Go to <hi
          rend="italic">Aetius</hi>, and other, where you may <lb/>find a <hi rend="italic"
          >ſafe</hi>, <hi rend="italic">eaſy</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ſpeedy</hi> Cure; which, as
        the <lb/>ſame Author on another Occaſion obſerves, the Peo- <lb/>ple make Slight of, because
        they do not know the <lb/>Danger or Trouble that often attend it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A <hi rend="italic">Looſeneſs</hi> is more liable to be miſtaken than the <lb/>greateſt
        Number of other Diſeaſes; becauſe it is pro- <lb/>duced by two immediate Cauſes that are vey
        differ- <lb/>ent, when the reſt have one Cauſe only, however great <lb/>the Diverſity of
        particular Caſes may appear to be. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A Fever, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> has but one Cauſe, tho' the Variety <lb/>of
        Fevers, or the various Appearances of a Fever are <lb/>infinite, and never can be claſs'd by
        Obſervation, I <lb/>ſhall therefore conſider the different Circumſtances of a <lb/>Looſeneſs
        obſerved by Dr. <hi rend="italic">de Juſſieu</hi>, and that occaſi- <lb/>on the
        Miſapplication of <hi rend="italic">Ipecacuanha</hi>; but I ſhall <lb/>afterwards endeavour
        to make his Account more per- <lb/>fect; for thereby Phyſicians will be able to have
        <lb/>more perfect <hi rend="italic">Intentions</hi> and Views of Curing than <lb/>hitherto
        they have had. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="italic">When great Crudities, </q> ſays the Doctor, <q rend="italic"
         >and in- <lb/>digeſted Stuff in the firſt Paſſages, or an Obſtructi- <lb/>on in
          the Bowels of the lower Belly are the Cauſe of <lb/>a Looſeneſs, we may always expect the
          common <lb/>good Effects of the <hi rend="roman">Ipecacuanha</hi> for a Cure. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="italic">On the contrary, when <hi rend="roman">Ipecacuanha</hi> is given
          againſt <lb/>an Hepatick Dyſentery, or againſt a great Diſ- <lb/>charge of Blood upwards
          or downwards, often oc- <lb/>caſioned by a purging Medicine that was given for <pb n="387"/>
          <lb/>a Cure of the Looſeneſs, no Succeſs can reaſonably be <lb/>expected from the
          Specifick, far leſs have we any <lb/>Hopes, when <hi rend="roman">Ipecacuanha</hi> is
          given for the Cure of a <lb/>Looſeneſs that ſubſiſts on an Inflammation of the <lb/>lower
          Belly; or when ſharp and fix'd Pains give <lb/>us a Suſpicion that the Dyſentery has a
          cancerous <lb/>Ulcer for its Cauſe. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As there is no Difficulty that is peculiar to a <hi rend="italic">Dy-
        <lb/>ſentery</hi>, and is not common with the Dangers of a <lb/>Diarrhœa, the Terrour of
        Blood not expected, it <lb/>muſt be acknowledged that any <hi rend="italic">Vomit</hi> as
        well as <hi rend="italic">Ipe- <lb/>cacuanha</hi>, is a proper Cure againſt Indigeſtions and
        <lb/>Crudities in the Stomach, as <hi rend="italic">Hippocrates</hi> anciently
        <lb/>obſerved, and has been believed by all Phyſicians ſince <lb/>his Time: So that there is
        nothing in the <hi rend="italic">French</hi> Spe- <lb/>cifick that it not in <hi
          rend="italic">Salt</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Vitriol</hi>; which we find <lb/>held its
        Reputation, in curing <hi rend="italic">Dyſenteries</hi>, longer than <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Ipecacuanha</hi> is like to do. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is more wonderful that this Way of Curing a <lb/>Looſeneſs by <hi rend="italic"
          >Ipecacuanha</hi> was not ſooner determined. <lb/>Nothing beſides the lazy Talk of a
        Specifick, that ex- <lb/>cludes all Reaſoning and Reflection, could have made <lb/>Men eaſy
        under ſo groſs Ignorance. The very In- <lb/>ſtance given us by the late excellent Dr. <hi
          rend="italic">Tournefort</hi>, <lb/>in the Caſe of his Tutor <hi rend="italic">Petrus
          Sylvanus</hi>, is a ſuffi- <lb/>cient Proof that <hi rend="italic">Ipecacuanha</hi> is no
        Charm of a Spe- <lb/>cifick, but that it cures by its Evacuating: For, when <lb/>the
        Weakneſs of <hi rend="italic">Sylvanus</hi> made them cautious in ad- <lb/>miniſtring the
        Specifick, the Diſeaſe held its Ground <lb/>againſt the Charm, and its Adorers, 'till
        Deſpair drove <lb/>the Phyſician upon larger Doſes, the laſt Reſort of the <lb/>Vanquiſhed,
        and they produced Evacuations by <hi rend="italic">Vomit</hi>
        <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Stool</hi>, and thereby his <hi rend="italic">Health</hi> in one
        Night </p>
      <pb n="388"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It would be ſuperfluous to obſerve upon what is <lb/>ſaid about the <hi rend="italic"
          >Simarouba</hi>, and how far it may remedy <lb/>the Defects of <hi rend="italic"
          >Ipecacuanha</hi>, the Trials of it being few, <lb/>not ſufficient to determine the
        Univerſality of its Uſe. <lb/>Far leſs ſhall I enquire, whether the <hi rend="italic"
          >Weſt-India</hi> Plant <lb/>has any relation to the <hi rend="italic">Macir</hi> from the
          <hi rend="italic">Eaſt-Indies</hi>, <lb/>mentioned by <hi rend="italic">Pliny</hi>
        <note n="*" place="bottom">
          <p rend="align-center size(0.7)">
            <lb/>* Hiſt. Natur. lib. xii. </p>
        </note>; though I wiſh Dr. <hi rend="italic">de Juſſieu</hi>
        <lb/>had prepared the <hi rend="italic">Simarouba</hi> with <hi rend="italic">Honey</hi>,
        ſince the <lb/>great Cures, recorded by <hi rend="italic">Pliny</hi>, by the <hi
          rend="italic">Macir</hi> might <lb/>be aſſiſted by its being prepared in that Way. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I ſhall then proceed, and make the foregoing Account <lb/>more perfect, and more
        obvious, better fitted to fix the <lb/>Views of Phyſicians, in the Point they are to purſue.
        <lb/>For this Purpoſe, I ſhall give a plain Account of the ſe- <lb/>veral Species of a
        Looſeneſs, and in each of them apply <lb/>the different Kind of Remedies employ'd for the
        Cure <lb/>of them. Thus we ſhall perceive the proper Admi- <lb/>niſtration for every
        Looſeneſs, and how far any of <lb/>them is left without a Cure. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Anatomy of the Guts alone, informs us, that <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">immediate
          Cauſe of every Looſeneſs</hi>, whether it <lb/>by Symptomatick or Eſſential, muſt either
        be a <hi rend="italic">quicker <lb/>Conveyance of the common Quantity of concocted Food,
          <lb/>and of the Liquors that are commonly mixed with <lb/>it in the Guts. Or the Cauſe of
          a Looſeneſs is a <lb/>greater Secretion than ordinary, of a watry Sub- <lb/>ſtance from
          the Blood into the Guts, and brought in- <lb/>to them by the <hi rend="roman"
            >Pancreas</hi>, and various other <hi rend="roman">Glands</hi>. <lb/>In both which Caſes
          there muſt needs be a larger <lb/>Diſcharge of liquid Excrements, by Stool, than uſual,
          <lb/>or ther muſt be a Looſeneſs.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">A Looſeneſs</hi> produced by the firſt of theſe Cauſes, <lb/>admits
        of great Variety; both on the Account of the <pb n="389"/>
        <lb/>different <hi rend="italic">Stimuli</hi>, and even from the different Degrees <lb/>of
        the <hi rend="italic">Stimulus</hi> in each of them. The <hi rend="italic">Stimulus</hi>,
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> of indigeſted Food, Fruits, and the like, differs
        <lb/>very much from the <hi rend="italic">Stimulus</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Gall</hi>. The
        firſt Sort <lb/>is confined to the <hi rend="italic">Stomach</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
          >Inteſtines</hi>: In which <lb/>Caſe, the Diſeaſe is often a Cure to it ſelf; whereas the
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Stimulus</hi> of Gall is greater, and the Cauſe is more per-
        <lb/>manent and ſeldom carries off it ſelf. The Degree of the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Stimulus</hi> is occaſioned by the <hi rend="italic">Piles</hi>, an <hi rend="italic"
          >Ulcer</hi>, or a <lb/><hi rend="italic">Stricture</hi> in the Guts, it is vaſtly more
        Violent, and <lb/>much departs from the common Cure of a Looſeneſs, <lb/>whereby Phyſicians
        are often ſubjected to fatal Errors, <lb/>and groſs Miſapplications of their Medicines. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Watry Looſeneſs</hi> produced by the other im- <lb/>mediate
        Cauſe, is indeed deplorable; becauſe a Me- <lb/>thod of Curing it is not commonly known. It
        is not <lb/>only as a Principal, but it is a Second, in the Beginning, <lb/>at the Ending,
        and in the intermediate Times of all <lb/>other Diſeaſes, and even in old Age, when Nature
        is <lb/>ſubmitting to the Power of Death; when Phyſicians <lb/>call it a Colliquative
        Looſeneſs, becauſe it ſeems to <lb/>melt away the Fleſh of the Sick. <note n="*"
          place="bottom">
          <p rend="align-center size(0.7)">
            <lb/>* Pag. 188, 189, lib. de Peſte. </p>
        </note><hi rend="italic">Petrus Salius Di- <lb/>verſus</hi>, a moſt approved Phyſician,
        affirms it to be <lb/>vain for a Phyſician to attempt the Cure of it. <hi rend="italic">Ca-
          <lb/>rolus Piſo</hi>, who endeavours to explain it, and the moſt <lb/>ſagacious <hi
          rend="italic">Laz. Riverius</hi>, after trying all the common <lb/>Methods, give us no
        better Hopes of a Cure. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is now manifeſt why a Looſeneſs, that in all out- <lb/>war Appearance is one and the
        ſame thing, and pro- <lb/>miſes to ſubmit to the ſame Remedy, is vaſtly different <pb
          n="390"/>
        <lb/>in the manner of Curing it. Our Experience has contra- <lb/>dicted our Belief, and the
        Remedy that has proved <lb/>Effectual and Sufficient in one Caſe, has proved Inef-
        <lb/>fectual and Uſeleſs on other Occaſions; on which <lb/>Account Remedies are very liable
        to be miſapplied. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To prevent this Misfortune in a great Meaſure for <lb/>the Future, I ſhall conſider the
        Medicines commonly <lb/>made uſe of by Phyſicians for the Cure of a Looſe- <lb/>neſs; and
        next, how they may moſt properly be <lb/>adapted to that End: For thus we muſt perceive the
        <lb/>particular Caſes wherein they are like to be uſeful, and <lb/>when they are not like to
        be of any uſe at all. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Aſtringents</hi>, or binding Medicines, were the firſt <lb/>employed
        for the Cure of a Looſeneſs, as well as of <lb/>every other Evacuation: But <hi
          rend="italic">Hippocrates</hi> obſerving <lb/>that a Looſeneſs was often the eaſieſt cured
        when it <lb/>was attended with Vomiting, <hi rend="italic">Vomiting</hi> Medi- <lb/>cines
        were introduced on that Account. On a like <lb/>Conſideration, Purging Medicines were
        admitted by <lb/><hi rend="italic">Celſus</hi>, becauſe he found the <hi rend="italic"
          >Purging</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Cure</hi> of <lb/>itſelf; or that the Looſeneſs went
        off by going <lb/>to Stool for a few Days: But he adviſes Phyſi- <lb/>cians to take care
        that the Looſeneſs does not run <lb/>longer than ſeven Days, and that it is not attended
        <lb/>with a <hi rend="italic">Fever</hi>; for in that caſe the Looſeneſs is not <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Critical</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Salutary</hi>, but <hi rend="italic"
          >Symptomatical</hi>, and ha- <lb/>ſtens on the Ruin of the Sick. All theſe Obſerva-
        <lb/>tions have not been found univerſally true in many <lb/>other Countries; for <hi
          rend="italic">Cælius Aurelianus</hi>, a moſt ac- <lb/>curate Obſerver of Diſeaſes, <hi
          rend="italic">Rhaza</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Avicenna</hi>
        <lb/>blame this free Uſe of Purging and Vomiting, and may <lb/>be juſtified by what will be
        ſhewn in the Progreſs of <lb/>this Diſcourſe. </p>
      <pb n="391"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But, now that we may apply this Artillery of Phy- <lb/>ſicians againſt the two general
        Cauſes of all Looſeneſſes, <lb/>we ſhall begin with the moſt ancient of the mentioned
        <lb/>Methods, which was practiſed by <hi rend="italic">Prodicus Selym- <lb/>brianus</hi>,
        whoſe School was adorned by the divine <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hippocrates</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Binding Medicines, as I lately obſerved, were em- <lb/>ployed for the Cure of every
        Evacuation, and are ſtill <lb/>the Refuge of Phyſicians when all other Methods <lb/>have
        been baffled, under their own Conduct and <lb/>Direction; they tacitly have the Preference
        given <lb/>them to all other Medicines; for Inſtance, <hi rend="italic">Ipecacu-
          <lb/>anha</hi> is preferr'd to any other Vomit, and <hi rend="italic">Rhubarb</hi>
        <lb/>to any other Purge, becauſe they are more <hi rend="italic">aſtringent</hi>
        <lb/>than any other of the Tribe. So far do Phyſicians <lb/>extol the Power of <hi
          rend="italic">Aſtringents</hi>, that many of them <lb/>affirm, that by them any <hi
          rend="italic">Looſeneſs</hi> may be repreſs'd, if <lb/>they did not think it unſeaſonable
        or improper. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>However, it may ſtand with theſe Boaſters, it is <lb/>very certain, that theſe
        Medicines only affect a Looſe- <lb/>neſs occaſioned by a <hi rend="italic">Stimulus</hi>,
        and if this is ſmall, <lb/>the Looſeneſs may be cured by it; but if the Degree of <lb/>the
          <hi rend="italic">Stimulus</hi> is greater, the aſtringent Medicine is either <lb/>not
        able to put a Stop to it, or it will tear the Sick <lb/>with Gripes if it does. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is on the ſame Account of the <hi rend="italic">Stimulus</hi>, that a <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Vomit</hi> or a <hi rend="italic">Purge</hi> is properly premiſed to other
        Me- <lb/>dicines, if it conſiſts with the Strength of the Sick; <lb/>but after all, the
        Store-houſe of Phyſicians ſeems to <lb/>be exhauſted in curing a Looſeneſs that proceeds
        from <lb/>Indigeſtion, or Gall; but if the <hi rend="italic">Stimulus</hi> is from the
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Piles</hi>, an <hi rend="italic">Ulcer</hi>, or a <hi rend="italic"
          >Stricture</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Guts</hi>, Phyſi- <lb/>cians are loſt without any
        Remedy, and too frequent- <pb n="392"/>
        <lb/>ly have recourſe to the Omnipotent Aſtringent, with- <lb/>out any Succeſs. Here is a
        real Want, an Inability <lb/>and Unskilfulneſs in our Work, and leaves too much <lb/>room
        for miſapplying Medicines. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But if we turn theſe Engines of Vomiting, Purging <lb/>and Binding, upon the other
        general Cauſe of a Looſeneſs, <lb/>they either fall very ſhort, or like a little Water
        thrown <lb/>upon a great Fire, they rather inflame than extinguiſh it. <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Hippocrates</hi>
        <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Coac. Prænot. 134. Prædict. 81. </p>
        </note> indeed does not mention the <hi rend="italic">Watry <lb/>Looſeneſs</hi>, but he ſays
        many things that peculiarly con- <lb/>cern it; which <hi rend="italic">Foeſius</hi> not
        underſtanding, blamed him <lb/>for Obſcurity in this Place. <hi rend="italic">Piſo</hi>
        <note n="†" place="bottom" rend="align-right size(0.6)">† Sect. IV. cap. 1. Obſ. 54. </note>
        gives a very plain <lb/>Deſcription of this Looſeneſs, and his Obſervation is <lb/>admitted
        by every ſucceeding Phyſician. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The deſperate State of the Watry Looſeneſs was <lb/>formerly mentioned from the
        Conſeſſion of Authors <lb/>of the greateſt Knowledge and Veracity; and Phy- <lb/>ſicians
        ſhall for ever find that Looſeneſs to become <lb/>more violent the more you preſs it with
        Aſtringents, <lb/>Vomits, or purging Medicines. The boaſted Omni- <lb/>potency of putting a
        Stop to a Looſeneſs at Pleaſure, <lb/>muſt ſerve another uſe with the Sick, though it may
        <lb/>not be able to put the deſired Stop to his Purging. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There is even a Singularity in the Cure of this <lb/>Looſeneſs which I think has not
        hitherto been ob- <lb/>ſerved. In every other Kind of Looſeneſs the Stools <lb/>acquire a
        Conſiſtence, when they begin to be cured; <lb/>but in the Watry Looſeneſs, the Stools
        commonly leſ- <lb/>ſen in Quantity though not in their Looſeneſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I ſhould ſay ſomething of <hi rend="italic">Opium</hi>, a Medicine of- <lb/>ten made
        uſe of for the Cure of every Kind of Looſe- <pb n="393"/>
        <lb/>neſs, but as it neither acts as an Aſtringent, nor in a <lb/>Way obſerved by
        Phyſicians, it muſt ſtill remain <lb/>among other <hi rend="italic">Deſiderata</hi>. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
