<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Davis: Concerning Some Children Inoculated with the Small-Pox</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Evan Davis</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Letter from Mr. Evan Davis to Mr. John Eames, F. R. S. concerning Some Children
              Inoculated with the Small-Pox, at Haverford-West in Pembrokeshire</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for W. Innys and R. Manby, Printers to the Royal Society, at the
                  West End of St. Paul's.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1733-1734</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">38</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">121-126</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110529357</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1733.0025</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT38_0121">
    <body>
      <pb n="121"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">IX.</hi> A Letter from Mr. <hi rend="roman">Evan Davis</hi> to Mr.
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">John Eames</hi>, F. R. S. concerning ſome <hi rend="roman">Chil-
          <lb/>dren inoculated with the Small-Pox</hi>, at <lb/><hi rend="roman">Haverford-Weſt</hi>
        in <hi rend="roman">Pembrokeſhire</hi>. </head>
      <salute rend="space indent italic">
        <lb/>SIR, </salute>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">H</hi>AD I known in the Beginning of laſt Spring <lb/>that an Account
        of the Succeſs of Inoculation in <lb/>the Small-Pox, practis'd here about that time, would
        <lb/>be agreeable to you, as you ſignify in your laſt, I <pb n="122"/>
        <lb/>would not have delayed ſo long to communicate it. <lb/>If the Account had then been
        taken with a View of <lb/>ſending it abroad, it would probably have been more <lb/>full and
        particular in ſome Circumſtances relating to <lb/>the ſeveral Stages and Appearances of that
        Diſtemper <lb/>in the Caſes of thoſe who were inoculated with it, <lb/>than could now be
        recollected at this Diſtance of <lb/>time; yet I hope nothing material has been omitted,
        <lb/>that may be neceſſary for forming a Judgment on thoſe <lb/>Caſes which you have here
        related. The Meaſles in- <lb/>terfering with the inoculated Small-Pox, and prolong- <lb/>ing
        the time between the Inoculation and the Erup- <lb/>tion of this latter ſo much beyond what
        otherwiſe <lb/>was uſual, as you will obſerve below it did in every <lb/>one of the
        Inſtances mentioned, had, I thought, ſome- <lb/>thing in it that was peculiar and uncommon,
        and there- <lb/>fore what might deſerve your Notice. This was the <lb/>ſecond Opportunity
        that has been taken to practiſe <lb/>this Method of Inoculation in this Town and Neigh-
        <lb/>bourhood. It was firſt introduced here about ten <lb/>Years ago, by the ingenious and
        learned Dr. <hi rend="italic">Perrott <lb/>Williams</hi>, who then lived in this Town, and
        had <lb/>practis'd Phyſick for ſeveral Years in this Country with <lb/>eminent Succeſs; but
        is ſince removed to <hi rend="italic">London</hi>. <lb/>He had then his own Children
        inoculated among ſome <lb/>of the firſt on whom the Experiment was made, and <lb/>(if I
        forget not) ſent an Account of that Matter about <lb/>that time to your Society, which was
        afterwards <lb/>publiſhed by Dr. <hi rend="italic">Jurin</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Our Inoculators are two Surgeons of good Note and <lb/>repute in this Town (who alſo
        keep Apothecaries <lb/>Shops) and are the only Perſons that I hear of in theſe <lb/>Parts
        who are come into that Practice. Upon my re- <pb n="123"/>
        <lb/>questing it, I received from them this laſt Week the <lb/>Account following. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Some little time before laſt Chriſtmaſs the Small- <lb/>Pox appear'd in this Town,
        chiefly of the confluent <lb/>kind: Some had it with Purple-Spots, and other <lb/>violent
        Symptoms, whereof ſeveral died. Towards <lb/>the Spring, the Meaſles became more Epidemical,
        and <lb/>alſo more fatal, than the Small-Pox. Some of the <lb/>Subjects that had been
        viſited but a little time before <lb/>with the Small-Pox, and upon their Recovery had
        <lb/>their Bodies purged, yet died of the violent Cough <lb/>which attended and ſucceeded
        the Meaſles, which af- <lb/>terwards ſeized them. The Meaſles continued to rage <lb/>'till
        almoſt all the Subjects in this Place were viſited <lb/>with them, the Small-Pox continuing
        alſo during the <lb/>whole time, yet making but a ſlow Progreſs; and to <lb/>this time it
        has not left us. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About the End of <hi rend="italic">February</hi> laſt, Mr. <hi rend="italic">Francis
          Mey- <lb/>ler</hi> inoculated his own Son, near three Years old, <lb/>from a Child of
        about the ſame Age, who had the <lb/>diſtinct Sort of Small-Pox, but the Puſtules ſmall.
        <lb/>He made a ſlight Inciſion on both Legs, which took <lb/>only in one: After four Days a
        Puſtule appeared on <lb/>the Part wounded, but did not much inflame it, nor <lb/>make much
        Progreſs. On the 7th Day the Child grew <lb/>feveriſh, and on the 8th, or towards the 9th
        Day (in- <lb/>ſtead of the intended Small-Pox) the Meaſles appear'd <lb/>all over his Body,
        attended with a Cough; at which <lb/>time the feveriſh Diſorder abated, 'till the 11th or
        <lb/>12th Day: Then he grew feveriſh again, and to- <lb/>wards the 14th Day the Small-Pox
        appeared, a ſmall <lb/>diſtinct Sort, and few in Number. After the Eruption <lb/>was full,
        he grew hearty, and ſo continued, not being <pb n="124"/>
        <lb/>viſited with a ſecond Fever. After this Mr. <hi rend="italic">Meyler</hi>
        <lb/>inoculated two other Children from his own Son, by <lb/>applying the Matter, after a
        ſlight Inciſion, to both the <lb/>Legs of each of them, but it did not ſucceed. About
        <lb/>the ſame time he inoculated two other Children, a <lb/>little Way out of Town, from a
        Neighbour's Child, <lb/>but neither of them were infected. Its not ſucceed- <lb/>ing he
        knows not what to impute to; whether to the <lb/>Slightneſs of the Inciſion, or to the want
        of a Suffici- <lb/>ency of Matter to infect with, or to the want of a <lb/>Diſpoſition in
        the Subjects to be infected. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About the latter End of <hi rend="italic">March</hi> laſt Mr. <hi rend="italic">Richard
          <lb/>Wright</hi> inoculated a Daughter of <hi rend="italic">Tho. Kymer</hi>, Eſq; <lb/>of
        this Town, between 3 and 4 Years of Age, from <lb/>another Child of about the ſame Age, who
        had a di- <lb/>ſtinct kind. The Matter was applied to one of her <lb/>Arms, the Inciſion
        being made pretty deep. The <lb/>Inflammation thereof began about the 4th or 5th Day,
        <lb/>and afterwards appeared conſiderably great. She pro- <lb/>ceeded until the 7th Day in a
        very hearty and briſk <lb/>State, at which time ſhe began to grow heavy, ſick, <lb/>and very
        feveriſh. Then an Eruption of the Small- <lb/>Pox was expected; but her Fever increaſed, and
        the <lb/>next Day there were Eruptions ſeen all over her Body, <lb/>which proved to be the
        regular Meaſles. She was <lb/>treated accordingly, and grew well, excepting a pretty
        <lb/>ſevere Cough ſhe had, and this Cough continued <lb/>through the whole Courſe of the
        following Small- <lb/>Pox. About the 12th Day ſhe ſicken'd again, and <lb/>about the 14th
        the Small-Pox appeared, the diſtinct <lb/>ſort, and very favourable; they came out, fill'd,
        and <lb/>dry'd away very kindly, and were attended with very <lb/>little of a ſecond Fever.
        She went through the Di- <pb n="125"/>
        <lb/>ſtemper with a great deal of Chearfulneſs: She was <lb/>purged afterwards, and ſeemed
        very well; but in a <lb/>little time after, a Boil came on the lower Part of <lb/>the
        Shoulder-Blade of the ſame Arm wherein ſhe <lb/>was inoculated, which was brought to
        ſuppurate, and <lb/>was healed in a common Manner. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From this Subject laſt mentioned Mr. <hi rend="italic">Wright</hi> in- <lb/>oculated
        two Daughters and a Son of <hi rend="italic">Nicholas <lb/>Roch</hi>, Eſq; at his Seat,
        about five Miles diſtant from <lb/>this Town. Theſe three Children were aged from <lb/>3 to
        8 Years. The Inciſion was made in one Arm of each <lb/>Child; it produced the ſame Effect on
        every one of <lb/>them as it did on Miſs <hi rend="italic">Kymer</hi>; viz. the Meaſles on
        the <lb/>7th or 8th Day, and the Small-Pox of the diſtinct <lb/>ſort on the 14th Day. They
        went all three very <lb/>well through every Stage of the Diſtemper; the ſe- <lb/>condary
        Fever was but ſlight. One of theſe had them <lb/>ſomewhat thick, and the other two had a
        pretty many <lb/>of the Pox appearing over them likewiſe; but they <lb/>thoroughly recover'd
        all of them, and have all ſince <lb/>continued in a good State of Health. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thus, Sir, you have this Affair related by the Ino- <lb/>culators above named, in a
        faithful, and impartial Man- <lb/>ner. You may be aſſured, though perhaps not ſo large-
        <lb/>ly as you might expect, for the Reaſon before alledg- <lb/>ed: But if there ſhould be
        Occaſion for explaining <lb/>themſelves in any Particular, they will readily do it <lb/>when
        deſired. I know of nothing I have to add be- <lb/>fore I conclude, unleſs it be my good
        Wiſhes, that <lb/>wherever this Practice takes, it may be attended with <lb/>the ſame Safety
        and Succeſs that it has hitherto met <lb/>with here; which ſeems to me to recommend it as an
        <lb/>happy Expedient that Providence has kindly directed <pb n="126"/>
        <lb/>to, in order to guard againſt the Injuries and Dangers <lb/>of one of the moſt dreadful
        and deſtructive Diſeaſes in- <lb/>cident to Mankind. I have juſt Cauſe, I conceive, to
        <lb/>incline me to think very favourably of this Method, <lb/>from what I have myſelf
        obſerved of its Advantages. <lb/>In the Beginnings of this Year I loſt one Child out of
        <lb/>five I had, by the Small-Pox in the natural Way; and <lb/>I have ſeen what great
        Sickneſs and Miſery the other <lb/>four ſuffered, who all of them had the confluent ſort,
        <lb/>in Compariſon with what the Inoculated underwent. <lb/>One Boy of mine particularly,
        between 7 and 8 Years <lb/>of Age, had it ſo violently, that his Life firſt, then <lb/>his
        Limbs, Senſes, and Intellects were endangered by <lb/>it; and he is not yet fully recovered
        from the Effects <lb/>of it to his former good Health and Strength, though <lb/>he had it in
          <hi rend="italic">Dec.</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Jan.</hi> laſt, among thoſe who firſt
        <lb/>fell into it, when it came this laſt time to this Place. </p>
      <dateline rend="size(0.7)">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Aug.</hi> 18, 1732. </dateline>
      <postscript>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">P. S.</hi> Concerning the four Children above ment- <lb/>tioned, on
          whom the Operation did not ſucceed, <lb/>but remained uninfected after the variolous
          Matter <lb/>was applied in the uſual Way to them. They have <lb/>all of them ſince eſcaped
          the Meaſles, though moſt <lb/>other Children about them had 'em, and none of them
          <lb/>have yet had the Small-Pox, though it ſtill continues <lb/>in the Town. There are not
          many now that are <lb/>ſick of it, but it is of the bad confluent <lb/>kind, attended with
          Purple-Spots, and watery Blad- <lb/>ders that are mix'd with the Purples. It is obſerved,
          <lb/>that moſt of theſe who have of late been viſited with <lb/>it, have died thereof.
          This probably will incline <lb/>ſome to uſe Inoculation again, and to make that Prac-
          <lb/>tice, under Providence, their Refuge. </p>
      </postscript>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <dateline rend="space size(0.7)">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Oct.</hi> 25. 1732. </dateline>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <signed>
        <lb/>I am, Sir, Yours, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Evan Davis. </hi>
      </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
