<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Reynell: The Case of a Cataleptick Woman</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Richard Reynell</persName>
            </author>
            <title>The Case of a Cataleptick Woman: Communicated to the Royal Society by Richard
              Reynell, Apothecary, London</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for T. Woodward, at the Half-Moon, between the Two
                  Temple-Gates in Fleetstreet; and C. Davis, the Corner of Pater-Noster-Row, next
                  Warwick-lane; Printers to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1735-1736</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">39</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">49-53</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111029151</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1735.0012</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT39_0049">
    <body>
      <pb n="49"/>
      <head rend="hanging italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">IV.</hi> The Caſe of a <hi rend="roman">Cataleptick Woman</hi>: Com-
        <lb/>municated to the <hi rend="sc">Royal Society</hi> by <hi rend="roman">Richard
          <lb/>Reynell</hi>, Apothecary, <hi rend="roman">London</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="dc(1.5)">A</hi>NN Bullard</hi>, a Servant, about one and
        twenty <lb/>Years of Age, had been for ſome time irregular <lb/>in her <hi rend="italic"
          >Menſes</hi>, and very much afflicted for the Loſs <lb/>of a Friend. <hi rend="italic"
          >July</hi> the Tenth, 1730. ſhe complain- <lb/>ed of a Pain in her Head, Sickneſs in her
        Stomach, <pb n="50"/>
        <lb/>with a general Diſorder; and took <hi rend="italic">Gaſcoign</hi>'s Pow- <lb/>der for a
        Sweat: Next Morning, <hi rend="italic">July</hi> the Eleventh, <lb/>about Nine o'Clock, ſhe
        was found in Bed, ſenſe- <lb/>leſs, ſtiff, and void of Feeling, with her Eyes ſhut;
        <lb/>and, upon the firſt Surprize, it was thought ſhe was <lb/>dead. When I came, I found
        her in a true <hi rend="italic">Cata- <lb/>leptick Fit</hi>, ſenſeleſs, without Motion, her
        Limbs <lb/>very ſtiff, but warm, and not eaſy to be bent; but <lb/>in whatever Poſture any
        Limb was put, it continued <lb/>in the ſame, whether erect, or reclined: Her Reſpi-
        <lb/>ration was good, but her Pulſe low, and irregular; <lb/>ſhe had no Catchings, or
        convulſive Motions, but <lb/>could not, by any Means uſed, be brought to her- <lb/>ſelf (in
        any reſpect.) A Vein was opened in the <lb/>Arm, and twelve Ounces of Blood taken away;
        <lb/>ſhe bled freely, and came a little to herſelf, but <lb/>could not ſpeak. I then gave
        her this Draught: <lb/>℞ <hi rend="italic">Aq. Menth. Rutæ. Bryon. Co. ā.</hi> ʒvj. <hi
          rend="italic">Sal. volat. <lb/>Corn. C.</hi> ℈ß. <hi rend="italic">Sacchar. Albiſſ.</hi>
        ℈ij. <hi rend="italic">f. hauſt.</hi> and <lb/>five <choice>
          <corr>Spoonfuls</corr>
          <sic>Spoonfulls</sic>
        </choice> at pleaſure of the following Julep: <lb/>℞ <hi rend="italic">Aq. Puleg. Rutæ.
          Menth. ā.</hi> ℥ij. <hi rend="italic">Aq. Bryon. Co. <lb/>Nephrit. ā.</hi> ℥iß <hi
          rend="italic">Tinct. Caſtor.</hi> ʒij. <hi rend="italic">Sacchar. Albiſſ. <lb/>q. ſ. f.
          Julapium.</hi> In a few Hours ſhe came to <lb/>herſelf: I then asked her, whether ſhe knew
        how <lb/>ſhe was taken? She replied, that ſhe had been <lb/>reſtleſs and uneaſy till about
        Four o'Clock in the <lb/>Morning, when ſhe believed ſhe fell into the Diſ- <lb/>order ſhe
        was found in; but remember'd nothing <lb/>that had happened beſides. She complained of a
        <lb/>Dizzineſs in her Head, with a violent Pain in the <lb/>Fore-part of it, and Sickneſs in
        her Stomach, and <lb/>was a little feveriſh. I gave her the following Vomit <lb/>at Four
        o'Clock in the Afternoon: ℞ <hi rend="italic">Aq. Cardui </hi>
        <pb n="51"/>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">bened.</hi> ℥j. <hi rend="italic">Pulv. Ipecacuanh.</hi> ʒß. <hi
          rend="italic">Vitriol. alb. depurat.</hi>
        <lb/>gr. vj. <hi rend="italic">Oxym. Scillit.</hi> ʒiß <hi rend="italic">f. hauſt.</hi> The
        Vomit <lb/>work'd kindly, and ſhe ſeemed relieved by it: <lb/>About Six o'Clock in the
        Evening another Fit re- <lb/>turned, much in the ſame Manner as before; but <lb/>ſhe ſoon
        came out of it, and then took the Draught <lb/>with the Volatile Salt of Harts-horn, as
        before; and <lb/>I applied a large Bliſter to her Back, and two more <lb/>to her Arms: About
        Nine the ſame Evening ſhe <lb/>had a ſtrong Convulſion Fit, with Catchings, Grind- <lb/>ing
        of the Teeth, and a great Tremor, neither of <lb/>which ſhe had had before: ſhe had a Stool
        the <lb/>preceding Night, but none that Day. I gave her <lb/>the Draught as follows, at
        Night going to reſt: <lb/>℞ <hi rend="italic">Tinct. Hier. cum Vino fact</hi> ℥ij. <hi
          rend="italic">Aq. Menth.</hi> ʒvj. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Spt. Lavend. Co.</hi> ʒß <hi
          rend="italic">f. hauſt.</hi> and ſhe continued <lb/>taking the Draught, with the Volatile
        Salt, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        <lb/>every four Hours. <hi rend="italic">July</hi> the Twelfth, ſhe had been
        <lb/>light-headed all Night, with little or no Reſt; the <lb/>Bliſters were dreſſed, which
        diſcharged plentifully, <lb/>and the Tincture had given her three Stools in the <lb/>Night,
        which had made her a little faint; her Pulſe <lb/>was low, and her Water pale. I ſaw her in
        the <lb/>Evening, when ſhe had ſlept pretty well, with <lb/>which ſhe was refreſhed; the
        Pain in her Head but <lb/>little, her Stomach eaſy, and I found her in every <lb/>reſpect
        better. The Draughts were continued every <lb/>ſix Hours, and ſhe took of the Julep before
        men- <lb/>tioned, when faint or ill. <hi rend="italic">July</hi> the Thirteenth in <lb/>the
        Morning, I found her Head eaſy, her Water <lb/>higher coloured; ſhe was allowed Broth, and
        Food <lb/>of eaſy Digeſtion, which agreed very well with <lb/>her: She ſate up in the
        Afternoon, but was faint, <pb n="52"/>
        <lb/>and her Head giddy; but when in Bed, ſhe was <lb/>better: She had no Stool that Day. I
        gave her a <lb/>Draught with the Volatile Salt, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> at Night
        going <lb/>to reſt, and the following Purge the next Morning. <lb/>℞ <hi rend="italic"
          >Tinct. Hier. cum Vino fact.</hi> ℥iß <hi rend="italic">Syr. è Spinâ <lb/>Cerv. Aq. Puleg.
          ā.</hi> ʒvj <hi rend="italic">Spt. Lavend. Co.</hi> ʒj <hi rend="italic">f. <lb/>hauſt.
          cum regimine cap.</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">July</hi> the Fourteenth, the <lb/>Purge worked five times; ſhe eat a
        light Dinner, <lb/>and was eaſy; but upon walking about the Room, <lb/>her Head was giddy,
        and ſhe trembled very much, <lb/>but when in Bed, ſhe was better. I gave her the
        <lb/>following Draught at Night going to reſt: ℞ <hi rend="italic">Aq. <lb/>Rutæ Puleg.
          Bryon. Co. ā.</hi> ʒvj. <hi rend="italic">Spt. Corn. C. opt. <lb/>gutt.</hi> 40. <hi
          rend="italic">Tinct. Caſtor.</hi> ʒj. <hi rend="italic">Sacchar. Albiſs. paulu- <lb/>lum
          f. hauſt.</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">July</hi> the Fifteenth ſhe complained, <lb/>when up, of a Numbneſs in her
        Legs, and a Prick- <lb/>ing in them, like to what happens when the Legs <lb/>are what we
        commonly call aſleep: Her Appetite <lb/>was better, and ſhe was in every reſpect amended.
        <lb/>She took the following Medicines: ℞ <hi rend="italic">Pulv. rad. <lb/>Valerian
          Sylv.</hi> ℈ij. <hi rend="italic">P. Caſtor. Ruſſ.</hi> ℈j. <hi rend="italic"
          >Aſæfœtid.</hi> ʒj. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tinct. Caſtor. q. s. f. Maſſa Pilular. cujus
          formen- <lb/>tur Pilul. No. 40.</hi> of which ſhe took four twice <lb/>a day with a ſmall
        Draught of this Julep: ℞ <hi rend="italic">Aq. <lb/>Ceraſ. Nigr.</hi> ℥vj. <hi rend="italic"
          >Aq. Rutæ. Pæon. Co. ā.</hi> ℥ij. <hi rend="italic">Spt. <lb/>Lavend. Co.</hi> ʒvj. <hi
          rend="italic">Syrup. Caryoph. q. s. f. Julap.</hi>
        <lb/>of which ſhe took likewiſe five Spoonfuls at plea- <lb/>ſure. The Bliſters were kept
        running as long as we <lb/>could; and when they were dried up, <hi rend="italic">July</hi>
        the <lb/>Nineteenth, I gave her the ſame Purge as before. <hi rend="italic">July</hi>
        <lb/>the Twenty-ſecond, ſhe had continued very well, <lb/>without any Return of a Fit; but
        upon cutting an <lb/>Iſſue in her Arm, ſhe fell into a third Fit, in which <pb n="53"/>
        <lb/>ſhe continued near two Hours, but then came to <lb/>herſelf, and was well that Evening.
          <hi rend="italic">July</hi> the Twenty- <lb/>ninth the Purge was repeated. <hi
          rend="italic">August</hi> the Sixth ſhe <lb/>complained of a Pain in her Head, Sickneſs in
        her <lb/>Stomach, and ſome Days before, ſhe had a Shew of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >Menſes</hi>, and had vomited near a Pint of Blood, <lb/>and was coſtive: I then adviſed
        her to take two <lb/>Spoonfuls of <hi rend="italic">Tinctura Sacra</hi>, every or every
        other <lb/>Night going to Bed, as ſhe found it neceſſary, and <lb/>forty of the following
        Drops: ℞ <hi rend="italic">Spt. C. C. opt.</hi>
        <lb/>ʒiij. <hi rend="italic">Tinct. Helleb. Nigr.</hi> ʒv. to be taken twice a Day <lb/>in
        Chamomile-Tea. She took theſe Medicines about <lb/>three Weeks, which anſwered Expectation,
        and I <lb/>left her well. I ſaw her about twelve Months after, <lb/>and ſhe told me, ſhe had
        continued very well ever <lb/>ſince. </p>
      <p rend="indentall hanging space ">
        <q rend="diple">
          <lb/>Catalepſis tam rarus affectus eſt, ut credant in- <lb/>ter centum, imò Sexcentos, vix
          unum Medi- <lb/>cum reperiri, qui Catalepticum aliquem vi- <lb/>derit; ideóque Hiſtoriæ
          Catalepticorum, ſi <lb/>occurrant, diligenter annotandæ. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="align-right">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Sennertus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Med. Pract. lib. 1. c. 30. </hi>
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
