<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Amyand: Of an Inguinal Rupture, with a Pin in the Appendix Coeci,
          Incrusted with Stone</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Claudius Amyand</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Of an Inguinal Rupture, with a Pin in the Appendix Coeci, Incrusted with Stone;
              And Some Observations on Wounds in the Guts; By Claudius Amyand, Esq; Serjeant Surgeon
              to His Majesty, and F. R. S. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for T. Woodward, at the Half-Moon, between the Two
                  Temple-Gates in Fleetstreet; and C. Davis, the Corner of Pater-Noster-Row, next
                  Warwick-lane; Printers to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1735-1736</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">39</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">329-342</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111029151</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1735.0071</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT39_0329">
    <body>
      <pb n="329"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VIII.</hi> Of an <hi rend="roman">Inguinal Rupture</hi>, with a <hi
          rend="roman">Pin</hi>
        <lb/>in the <hi rend="roman">Appendix Cœci</hi>, incruſted with <lb/>Stone; and ſome
        Obſervations on <lb/><hi rend="roman">Wounds</hi> in the <hi rend="roman">Guts</hi>; by <hi
          rend="roman">Claudius <lb/>Amyand</hi>, Eſq; Serjeant Surgeon to His <lb/><hi rend="sc"
          >Majesty</hi>, and F. R. S. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="dc(1.5)">O</hi>Ctober</hi> 8, 1735. <hi rend="italic"
          >Hanvil Anderſon</hi>, a Boy, 11 <lb/>Years of Age, was admitted into St. <hi
          rend="italic">George</hi>'s <hi rend="italic">Ho- <lb/>ſpital</hi> near <hi rend="italic"
          >Hyde-Park</hi> Corner, for the Cure of a <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hernia Scrotalis</hi>,
        which he had had from his In- <lb/>fancy, and a Fiſtula between the Scrotum and Thigh
        <lb/>terminating into it, which for a Month laſt paſt had <lb/>diſcharged a great Quantity
        of an unkindly ſort of <lb/>Matter. The Rupture was ſmall, and not trouble- <lb/>ſome, and
        Part of it could be replaced, but as it ap- <lb/>peared that the Sinuous Ulcer ſprung from
        that Part <lb/>that could not; ſo 'twas evident that the Cure of the <lb/>Fiſtula depended
        upon the Cure of the Hernia, which <lb/>latter could be obtained by no other Operation than
        <lb/>that for the <hi rend="italic">Bubonocele</hi>, which was agreed to, and <lb/>performed
        the 6th Day of <hi rend="italic">December</hi> following. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This Operation proved the moſt complicated and <lb/>perplexing I ever met with, many
        unſuſpected Oddi- <lb/>ties and Events concurring to make it as intricate as <lb/>it proved
        laborious and difficult. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This Tumour, principally compoſed of the Omen- <lb/>tum, was about the Bigneſs of a
        ſmall Pippin: <lb/>In it was found the Appendix Cœci perforated by <lb/>a Pin incruſted with
        Stone towards the Head, the <lb/>Point of which having perforated that Gut, gave way <pb
          n="330"/>
        <lb/>to a Diſcharge of Fæces through the fiſtulous Open- <lb/>in therein, as the Portion of
        the Pin obturating the <lb/>Aperture in it ſhifted its Situation. The Abſceſs <lb/>formed in
        the Hernial Bag occaſionally, and the Sup- <lb/>puration for two Months laſt paſt from this
        Place out- <lb/>wardly, had knit and confounded, and, as it were, <lb/>inbodied together the
        Gut and Omentum with the <lb/>Hernial Bag, and theſe with the Spermatick Veſſels <lb/>and
        the Teſticule, ſo that it was difficult to diſtin- <lb/>quiſh them from each other, as it
        was to ſeparate <lb/>them without wounding them; this Pin, whoſe <lb/>Point was fixed in the
        Omentum, continually ſhifting <lb/>its Situation, and occaſioning a Diſcharge of Fæces.
        <lb/>The Pin frequently lying in the way of the Knife, <lb/>and ſtarting out of the wounded
        Gut, as a Shot out <lb/>of a Gun, the Inundation of Fæces upon this Occa- <lb/>ſion from a
        Gut we could not well diſtinguiſh, were <lb/>ſo many Difficulties in the way: But the
        greateſt yet <lb/>was, what to do with the Gut, which all this while <lb/>was unknown, and
        of which we could not come to <lb/>the Knowledge, till the Operation was over; for this
        <lb/>Appendix Cœci, which was the only Gut found in the <lb/>Rupture, was ſo contracted,
        carnous, duplicated, and <lb/>changed in its Figure and Subſtance, that it was im-
        <lb/>poſſible to determine what kind of Gut it was, or <lb/>to find out that it was only
        this Appendix elongated, <lb/>and in Diſguiſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We apprehended none of theſe Difficulties, when <lb/>we undertook this Operation, in
        which we proceeded <lb/>as uſual: The Omentum lying uppermoſt in the Her- <lb/>nial Bag was
        diſſected from the Parts it was knit to, <lb/>and particularly the Gut it was imbodied with,
        and <lb/>afterwards cut off cloſe to the Abdominal Muſcles <pb n="331"/>
        <lb/>without any previous Ligature, the Veſſels in it being <lb/>ſmall, and the Subſtance of
        it more like a Sweet- <lb/>bread than the Caul. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Much Time was ſpent in this Diſſection; we were <lb/>ſtreightened for Room, and greatly
        diſturbed by the <lb/>Diſcharge of the Fæces coming out of the Gut, upon <lb/>every motion
        the Pin lodged in it and the Omentum <lb/>ſuffered, upon the Separation of theſe from each
        <lb/>other. The Gut forming a double Tube, like a <lb/>double-jointed Syphon, continuing in
        the Curve as it <lb/>paſſed over the Teſticule and Spermaticks, was ſeparated <lb/>one part
        from the other and from the adjacent Parts, as <lb/>far as the Aperture in the Abdominal
        Muſcles, where <lb/>the unperforated End of it was ſeparated therefrom, and <lb/>thence
        ſtretched out and unfolded, which brought in <lb/>View the Aperture made in it by the Pin
        hitherto con- <lb/>cealed, through which that Part of it, which was in- <lb/>cruſted with
        Chalk, had juſt made its way out upon <lb/>an occaſional Preſſure, as a Cork out of a
        Bottle. It <lb/>was the Opinion of the Phyſicians and Surgeons pre- <lb/>ſent, to amputate
        this Gut: To which End a circular <lb/>Ligature was made about the ſound Part of it, two
        <lb/>Inches above the Aperture, and this being cut off an <lb/>Inch below the Ligature, was
        replaced in the Abdo- <lb/>men, in ſuch a Manner that an artificial Anus might <lb/>be made
        there, if the Patient's Caſe ſhould require it. <lb/>Afterwards ſo much of the Hernial Bag
        as had been <lb/>detached from the Skin, the Spermaticks, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> was
        <lb/>cut off, which, as they appeared in a ſound State, were <lb/>preſerved <hi
          rend="italic">in Situ</hi>. The Fiſtulous Opening adjoining <lb/>to the Thigh, and
        anſwering to the Aperture in the <lb/>Gut, was opened; ſome Angles of Skin in the way
        <lb/>removed; The Aperture in the Muſcles, which had <pb n="332"/>
        <lb/>been inlarged by Inciſion, was ſtopped up with a <lb/>Tent; and the reſt of the
        Dreſſings and the Situation <lb/>of the Patient ordered ſo, as to remove from the <lb/>Wound
        all ſuch Preſſure from within as might diſturb <lb/>the Cure. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>'Tis eaſy to conceive that this Operation was as <lb/>painful to the Patient as
        laborious to me: It was a <lb/>continued Diſſection, attended with Danger on Parts <lb/>not
        well diſtinguiſhed: It laſted near half an Hour, <lb/>and the Patient bore it with great
        Courage. During <lb/>it the Patient vomited largely, and had ſeveral Stools, <lb/>but was
        ſoon compoſed by half an Ounce of Diaco- <lb/>dium, and Emollient Embrocations and
        Fomentations, <lb/>frequently applied warm on the Belly: He was <lb/>blooded, and an
        Emollient Carminative oily Clyſter <lb/>was ordered to be applied in the Evening; but as he
        <lb/>was eaſy, and the Belly not Tenſe, that was omitted. <lb/>He was confined to a very
        ſparing Diet, and his Body <lb/>kept open by Clyſters, injected every 2d Day, when
        <lb/>Stools were wanted, to prevent ſtraining. When <lb/>dreſſed upon the 4th Day after the
        Operation, every <lb/>thing appeared well, and we had good Reaſon to <lb/>hope for a Cure,
        eſpecially as the Diſcharge by the <lb/>Anus was Natural. The Tent put into the Abdominal
        <lb/>Aperture was not removed till the 8th. Upon the 10th <lb/>the Ligature round the
        Appendix Cœci, where it had <lb/>been amputated, dropt off, and no Fæces followed it;
        <lb/>and as it was then plain they had taken the natural <lb/>Courſe, from that Time the
        Wound was treated like <lb/>an ordinary one, ſaving it was obſerved to keep a <lb/>ſtrong
        and conſtant Preſſure over the Abdominal Aper- <lb/>ture, as well to fence againſt the
        Intruſion of the Viſ- <lb/>cera into the Wound, as by a ſtrong Incarnation and <pb n="333"/>
        <lb/>Cicatrix, effectually to ſecure the Patient againſt a <lb/>Rupture. During the Time of
        the Cure he was con- <lb/>fined to his Bed, always kept to ſparing Diet, and or- <lb/>dered
        never to go to Stool but in a Bed-pan; by theſe <lb/>means the Wound was completely healed
        up in leſs <lb/>than a Month, and the Patient ſoon after diſcharged <lb/>with a Truſs, which
        he was ordered to wear ſome <lb/>Time, to confirm the Cure. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That the Appendix Cœci ſhould be the only Gut <lb/>found in this Rupture, is a Caſe
        ſingular in Practice: <lb/>This was full of Excrements, and occaſionally could <lb/>be
        diſtended with an additional Quantity, which up- <lb/>on Preſſure was returned into the
        Colon, with that <lb/>kind of Noiſe which Guts replaced generally give. <lb/>This had
        occaſioned a Diminution of the Tumour <lb/>when compreſſed, before the Operation was per-
        <lb/>formed, as the Patient was lying backwards with his <lb/>Head downwards, and an
        Increaſe of it as he ſtood <lb/>erect, when the Fæces from the Colon could get into <lb/>it
        again. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Patient does not remember, when he ſwal- <lb/>lowed the Pin which had perforated
        the Gut within <lb/>the Rupture. But as this Rupture was from his In- <lb/>fancy, fixed and
        unreducible, ſo it is likely the Pin <lb/>had then made its way into the Appendix Cœci pro-
        <lb/>lapſed; and that an Inflammation enſuing thereon, <lb/>had occaſioned an Adheſion,
        whereby the Increaſe of <lb/>the Tumour had been checked, and the Reduction of <lb/>the
        Parts prolapſed thereby, rendered impracticable. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Surgeons who conſtantly dreſſed the Patient <lb/>before the Operation, did obſerve
        then, as they have <lb/>ſince, that the Humour diſcharged formerly at the <lb/>Fiſtula, had
        frequently the Appearance, and as they <pb n="334"/>
        <lb/>thought, the Smell of Excrements, ſo that there is <lb/>no Doubt that the Cauſe of it
        was the Wound made <lb/>in the Gut, by the Pin giving way occaſionally to ſuch <lb/>a
        Diſcharge. The Patient alſo perfectly remembers, <lb/>that the Impoſtumation or Gathering
        preceding the <lb/>fiſtulous Diſcharge was attended with very little Pain, <lb/>or much leſs
        than generally attends Suppuration. <lb/>Which ſhews that the Extravaſation of the Excre-
        <lb/>ments from the Gut into the Hernial Bag, and the <lb/>burſting of this Bag, were the
        Cauſe of the fiſtulous <lb/>Diſcharge, and of the continuance of it outwardly. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As to the Pin found in the Rupture at the Time <lb/>of the Operation, it is obſervable,
        that two Thirds <lb/>of it, incruſted with a chalky Matter, were confined <lb/>and concealed
        within the Gut; the other Third next <lb/>the Point, had made its way through it, the Point
        <lb/>of which was ſo lodged in the Omentum wherein it was <lb/>fixed, as to leave a free
        Paſſage for the Excrement <lb/>from the perforated Gut outwardly, whenever the
        <lb/>Perforation in the Gut, upon ſhifting the Poſi- <lb/>tion of the incloſed Pin, could
        open, and afford a <lb/>Paſſage for the Diſcharge of the Fæces this way, <lb/>which was as
        oft as this conical or pyramidal Pin <lb/>did alter its Place, or did not exactly obturate
        the <lb/>Aperture in the Appendix Cœci, it exactly fitted. I <lb/>have already obſerved,
        that the Aperture made in the <lb/>Gut by the Pin, lay concealed, the Point being
        <lb/>lodged in the Omentum, lying parallel with the <lb/>Gut, which was here duplicated,
        where it was <lb/>ſo ſecured, that it ſeemed almoſt impoſſible it <lb/>could ever make its
        way out of this Place, and its <lb/>other Confinement in the Gut, as the Aperture was
        <lb/>callous, and ſo reſiſting that it was with ſome Vio- <pb n="335"/>
        <lb/>lence it was forced out of its Confinement through <lb/>an Aperture fitted for the
        Point only and ſo <lb/>ſtreight, that the Report upon its coming out was <lb/>like that of a
        Cork out of a Bottle; for though it <lb/>appeared the Opening had occaſionally been
        inlarged, <lb/>as the incruſted Part of the Pin was preſſed forward <lb/>into it, yet it is
        plain Nature's Attempts to get rid of <lb/>it had been fruitleſs, and might poſſibly have
        been <lb/>ſo during all the Patient's Life. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Sir <hi rend="italic">Hans Sloane</hi> has furniſhed the Curious with <lb/>Inſtances of
        Bodies incruſted in the Guts with Stone, <lb/>and of ſome making their way out, when there
        was <lb/>little Probability of it. Daily Experience ſhews how <lb/>far Nature will ſtruggle
        to free herſelf, ſo that it it <lb/>always moſt eligible to truſt them to her Care: This
        <lb/>may appear from the Difficulties that have attended <lb/>the Cure of this Caſe, which
        at laſt did not prove <lb/>ſo ſucceſsful as it was firſt hoped for; for the Pa- <lb/>tient
        having been remiſs in the wearing of his Truſs, <lb/>upon ſome Effort the Guts found a way
        into the <lb/>Inguen again, ſix Months after the healing of the <lb/>Wound. This Caſe alſo
        ſhews, that the beſt Ope- <lb/>ration, and the utmoſt Care, is no Security againſt <lb/>the
        Relapſe of a Rupture. This is the 3d or 4th <lb/>Inſtance I have met with, of the
        Inſufficiency of this <lb/>Operation to effectuate a Cure of Ruptures; and yet <lb/>it is
        plain, this is by far more likely to prove effec- <lb/>tual, than the Cauſtick or any other
        Method cried <lb/>up for the Cure of this Evil. In a growing <lb/>Age, a good Spring Truſs
        is an effectual Remedy; <lb/>and in an Adult, this ſhould be the ultimate one, <lb/>though
        it is no more than a Palliative Cure. </p>
      <pb n="336"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">N. B.</hi> The Omentum and the Gut amputated, with <lb/>the Pin
        perforating it, are in the Repoſitory of the <lb/>Royal Society. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>This Obſervation puts me in Mind of two I made <lb/>during the late War in <hi
          rend="italic">Flanders</hi>, and of two more <lb/>lately in <hi rend="italic">London</hi>. </p>
      <div>
        <head rend="sc space align-center">
          <lb/>Observation I. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Upon opening the Body of a Soldier who had la- <lb/>boured many Years with an
          Inguinal and Scrotal Rup- <lb/>ture, I found in a Segment of the Ilion, an Appendix
          <lb/>like a Cœcum, about ſix Inches long; ariſing from <lb/>that Gut, and nearly of the
          ſame Diameter with the <lb/>Gut itſelf, the Coats whereof were ſomewhat thinner <lb/>than
          thoſe of the Ilion this Cœcum did ariſe from, <lb/>whoſe Membranes and Dimenſions were
          Natural. <lb/>This Elongation of a Segment of the Ilion appeared <lb/>as if it had been
          lodged in the Rupture Bag it lay <lb/>near to, and into which it had been ſtretched along
          <lb/>the Vagina of the Spermatick Veſſels down to the <lb/>Teſticule, according to the
          Expanſion of the Rupture <lb/>Bag, which was of the ſame Dimenſion: This Pro- <lb/>duction
          of the Ilion, or <hi rend="italic">Appendix Ilii</hi>, was full of <lb/>Fæces, ſomewhat
          narrower at its Rife or Opening into <lb/>the Ilion than elſewhere, but nearly reſembling
          it, <lb/>and as ſound as that Gut it ſprung from. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="sc space align-center">
          <lb/>Observation II. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>A Soldier having been ſhot through the Belly, the <lb/>Ball was cut out upon the
          poſterior part of the Os <pb n="337"/>
          <lb/>Iliûm. Through both Wounds the Fæces were <lb/>chiefly diſcharged for ſeveral Months
          after, and at <lb/>Dreſſings a great Number of flat Worms, dead or <lb/>alive, were found
          upon the Plaiſter. The Fæces <lb/>having by degrees taken their Courſe through the
          <lb/>Anus, in five or ſix Months after, the two Wounds <lb/>being healed up, the Patient
          returned to his Duty as <lb/>a Soldier, and ſoon after was made Corporal, and <lb/>then
          Serjeant. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Eight Years after this, I had him again under my <lb/>Care at the Hospital, where he
          was brought with the <lb/>Head of the <hi rend="italic">Os Humeri</hi>, together with that
          of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Acromion</hi> and Clavicule, in the Articulation with the
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Scapula</hi>, fractured by a Cannon-ſhot, which thereby <lb/>was
          laid all open. The Limb was immediately cut <lb/>off in the Articulation with the <hi
            rend="italic">Scapula</hi>, having firſt <lb/>premiſed a Ligature about the Fleſh
          ſurrounding the <lb/>Veſſels, by thruſting cloſe to the Bone a Pack-Needle <lb/>armed with
          a ſtrong Packthread, there being no room <lb/>for the <hi rend="italic">Tourniquet</hi>
          <note place="bottom" n="*">
            <p rend="indent size(0.7)">
              <lb/>* Mr. <hi rend="italic">Le Dran</hi>, in his Chirurgical Obſervations, Vol. II.
              Obſerv. <lb/>43. 12<hi rend="sup">o.[unclear]</hi> 1731. has deſcribed the Manner of
              performing the Ampu- <lb/>tation of the Humerus in the Articulation with the Scapula,
              to which <lb/>the Reader is referred. </p>
          </note>: He loſt very little more Blood <lb/>in the Operation, than if a <hi rend="italic"
            >Tourniquet</hi> had been ap- <lb/>plied; but the great Diſcharge of Matter ſunk him,
          <lb/>and he died the 8th Day after. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Death of this Patient gave me an Opportunity <lb/>of examining how the former
          Wound in the Gut <lb/>had been cured. I had thought the Wound had been <lb/>in the Iliûm,
          from the Thinneſs of the Fæces diſcharged <lb/>through that Wound; but, upon Diſſection, I
          found <pb n="338"/>
          <lb/>it had been in the Colon in the broadeſt Part of it. This <lb/>was very much
          contracted, and made narrow in that <lb/>Part of it that had been ſhot through, where it
          ap- <lb/>peared purſed up, and inſeparably knit to the Iliûm <lb/>Bone. However, the
          Patient never had complained <lb/>of any Inconveniency therefrom, though the Narrow-
          <lb/>neſs of the Gut in this Place was ſuch, as ſeemed to <lb/>make the Deſcent of the
          Fæces difficult. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="sc space align-center">
          <lb/>Observation III. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>On the 19th of <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 1729, I attended Miſs— <lb/>aged 14, on
          account of a ſuppurated Tumour on the <lb/>Navel, whoſe Situation was under the <hi
            rend="italic">Muſculi Recti</hi>. <lb/>This Patient had had, what is truely called, a
          Starting <lb/>at the Navel in her Infancy; and of late had com- <lb/>plained, at Times, of
          a Swelling there, and alſo of <lb/>Colicks, Gripes, or Vomitings, that uſed to go off,
          <lb/>particularly as that Swelling diſappeared. As theſe <lb/>grew more troubleſome, ſhe
          lately had taken a Vomit, <lb/>from which Time ſhe had been greatly cauſtive, and <lb/>her
          Reachings, Vomitings, and Colicks, had proved <lb/>more conſtant, together with an
          increaſing Tenſion <lb/>and Pain in the Fore-part of the Belly, and a Tenderneſs <lb/>at
          the Navel, as Matter was gathering there. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Some Days before I was called in, Dr. <hi rend="italic">Campbell</hi>
          <lb/>had employed the propereſt Remedies to remove theſe <lb/>Complaints. Upon a
          Conſultation, we agreed to <lb/>diſcharge by Inciſion the Matter collected at the Na-
          <lb/>vel, being about a Spoonful of undigeſted Fluid, that <lb/>had made its way through
          the <hi rend="italic">Aponeuroſis</hi> of the Ab- <lb/>dominal Muſcles adjoining to the
          Navel Cicatrix: <lb/>Notwithſtanding which, the Tenſion of the Belly, <pb n="339"/>
          <lb/>the Cauſtiveneſs, the Reachings, and Vomitings, rather <lb/>increaſing, as in the <hi
            rend="italic">Miſerere Mei</hi>, and having thence <lb/>a Reaſon to apprehend a
          Strangulation and Suppuration <lb/>of ſome of the <hi rend="italic">Viſcera</hi> in the
          Neighbourhood of the <lb/>Navel, Dr. <hi rend="italic">Hollings</hi> being called in, it
          was agreed <lb/>to inlarge the Aperture made by the fore-mentioned <lb/>Matter in the <hi
            rend="italic">Linea Alba</hi>, with a View and Intent to <lb/>know the State the Parts
          were in, to reduce what we <lb/>found there, or at leaſt to procure a more free Diſ-
          <lb/>charge to the Matter collected under the <hi rend="italic">Aponeuroſis</hi>
          <lb/>of the Muſcles: For a Fortnight and more, every <lb/>Thing was done that could
          internally or externally <lb/>eaſe the Diſcharge, and open the Paſſage for the Fæces
          <lb/>downwards, but all in vain. The Patient was a whole <lb/>Fortnight without a Stool,
          all the Symptoms daily <lb/>increaſing, though towards the latter End ſhe vomited
          <lb/>rather more ſeldom: Yet, as ſhe was ſtill taking in, ſo <lb/>the Dimenſions of her
          Belly increaſed in Proportion, <lb/>and the more for that the Air confined and rarefied in
          <lb/>the Fæces pent in, added daily to the Tenſion; which <lb/>at laſt had-ſtretched the
          Skin to the utmoſt. There <lb/>was alſo a Suppreſſion of Urine, the Fundus of the
          <lb/>Bladder being ſtretched towards the Navel, at the ſame <lb/>Time that the Neck of it
          was compreſſed by the Fæces <lb/>bearing down in the Pelvis, and a Tumour ſprung up
          <lb/>about the Anus, as if they had been ſeeking a Paſſage <lb/>that way. It was propoſed
          to ſcoop them out, but <lb/>the Rectum was found empty, and the Obſtruction as <lb/>far
          beyond the Reach of any Chirurgical Operation, <lb/>as it had proved againſt all the Means
          hitherto em- <lb/>ployed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Patient was now reduced to the loweſt Ebb. <lb/>The Dejections were
          Excrementitious, her Pulſe de- <pb n="340"/>
          <lb/>preſſed, and extremely weak; ſhe had Rigors, clammy <lb/>Sweats, and all the Symptoms
          that denote an approach- <lb/>ing Death, from a Mortification in the Guts, when of <lb/>a
          ſudden the Fæces burſted the Gut, and forcing their <lb/>way through the Inciſion at the
          Navel, a Quantity equal <lb/>to two or three Quarts, intermixed with various kinds <lb/>of
          Fruits and Seeds, which ſhe had been taking during <lb/>her Illneſs, flowed out like a
          Torrent, with a ſurprizing <lb/>roaring Noiſe, which gave her immediate Relief. The
          <lb/>Diſcharge continued very great all that Day, but the <lb/>Aperture in the Hernial Bag
          was not anſwerable to that <lb/>in the Gut, ſo that the Diſcharge there was at Times
          <lb/>checked by Subſtances obturating it; this Aperture <lb/>therefore was inlarged by
          Inciſion, and thereby the <lb/>Patient releaſed from the Violence of the Vomiting <lb/>and
          Hickup. From this Time we began to entertain <lb/>ſome hopes of a Cure; for though the
          Patient was ex- <lb/>tremely reduced, and the Diſcharge continued exceed- <lb/>ingly great
          during ſeveral Days, with a Singultus and <lb/>Vomitings, yet ſhe was refreſhed with
          Sleep, and was <lb/>able to retain ſome Nouriſhment. The Tenſion of the <lb/>Belly
          ſubſiſted, though in a leſſer degree, until the <lb/>Fæces had made their way downwards,
          and ſo did the <lb/>Vomitings at Times, ſo long as the Inflammation con- <lb/>tinued. The
          Diet was ſuch as the Caſe required; <lb/>Clyſters were frequently applied, as well as
          Fomenta- <lb/>tions, and every Thing elſe that could determine or <lb/>invite the
          Diſcharge through the Anus, and reſtore the <lb/>diſtended Guts to their Tone; but from
          the Time the <lb/>Fæces burſted the Gut, it was 12 Days before any took <lb/>the natural
          Courſe; and then we were again brought <lb/>to the Brink of Ruin, for they then poured
          down ſo <lb/>faſt for a Day or two, that the Patient was like to have <pb n="341"/>
          <lb/>ſunk under them: However, this ſevere Evacuation <lb/>was timely conquered by
          Abſorbents and Diluents: It <lb/>took off the remaining Tenſion of the Belly, and all
          <lb/>Vomitings; and as from this Time the Fæces had a free <lb/>Diſcharge the natural way,
          and the Diſcharge through <lb/>the Wound decreaſed in proportion, ſo the Wound <lb/>in the
          Gut, and the external Wound in the Integuments <lb/>were healed up in about three Weeks,
          in ſuch Man- <lb/>ner that the Patient has ever ſince enjoyed a moſt per- <lb/>fect
          Health. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="sc space align-center">
          <lb/>Observation IV. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It happened that I was not a meer Stranger to the <lb/>principal Circumſtances of
          this Caſe, as in the Year <lb/>1716 I had attended ſuch another with the late Mr. <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Lafage</hi>, Surgeon, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> Miſs—a Girl about four
          <lb/>Years of Age, in whom the ſame Cauſe had produced <lb/>the like Effects; for upon a
          Suppuration of the Omen- <lb/>tum ſtrangulated in the Navel of this Patient, the
          <lb/>Fæces detained in the neighbouring Gut had in like <lb/>Manner forced their way
          through the Navel: The <lb/>Accident previous to the burſting, and ſubſequent up- <lb/>on
          it, having been nearly the ſame as in the former <lb/>Obſervation; only the Cure proved
          ſomewhat more <lb/>tedious, for the Wound was kept open by Currants- <lb/>ſeeds frequently
          working their way out at the Navel <lb/>for about 12 Months after; when it was made com-
          <lb/>plete: ſo that the Hardſhips the Patient has undergone <lb/>ſince in Child-bearing,
          and ſeveral hazardous Labours, <lb/>have not been able to diſturb it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Hence it appears, that the Parts inflamed and in Con- <lb/>tact have been coaleſced
          and knit together, ſo as to <pb n="342"/>
          <lb/>prevent any Extravaſation from the wounded or burſted <lb/>Gut into the Cavity of the
          Abdomen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>That the Cure in the two laſt Caſes has been owing <lb/>to a free Diſcharge of the
          Fæces through the Wound, <lb/>and conſequently that when in a Gut-Rupture the Part
          <lb/>prolapſed cannot be reduced, a Cure may be hoped <lb/>for by making ſuch an Opening
          in the Guts, before <lb/>they are intirely ſphacelated, as may procure a free Diſ-
          <lb/>charge to the Fæces pent in, and thereby ſecure the Pa- <lb/>tient's Life. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>That if this happens to the Colon or Cæcum, the <lb/>Tube of it will ſo far be
          preſerved as to open a free <lb/>Diſcharge for the Fæces the natural way; and if that
          <lb/>cannot be obtained in a Wound of the ſmall Gut, yet <lb/>the Diſcharge may be ſecured
          by making the Wound <lb/>an artificial Anus. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>That the readieſt way to obtain a Cure of a wound- <lb/>ed or burſted Gut, is to keep
          it in Contact with the <lb/>outward Wound, and the Patient in a very low Diet. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>That the Deligation of the Veſſels of the Omentum <lb/>previous to the Amputation of
          it, being liable to many <lb/>Exceptions, it is more eligible to forbear it, ſaving
          <lb/>when the Veſſels are large; for when reduced looſe <lb/>and floating, it is leſs
          liable to the Inflammations and <lb/>Suppurations that attend the Separation of the
          Ligature. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
