<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Madden: An Account of What Was Observ'd upon Opening the Corpse of a Person Who Had Taken
          Several Ounces of Crude Mercury Internally</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Dr. Madden</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of What Was Observ'd upon Opening the Corpse of a Person Who Had Taken
              Several Ounces of Crude Mercury Internally; And of a Plumb-Stone Lodg'd in the Coats
              of the Rectum. Communicated in a Letter from the Late Dr. Madden, Physician at Dublin,
              to Sir Hans Sloane, Bar. Pres. R. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for T. Woodward, at the Half-Moon, between the Two
                  Temple-Gates in Fleetstreet; and C. Davis, the Corner of Pater-Noster-Row, next
                  Warwick-lane; Printers to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1735-1736</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">39</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">291-294</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111029151</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1735.0061</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT39_0291">
    <body>
      <pb n="291"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">X.</hi> An <hi rend="roman">Account</hi> of what was obſerv'd
        <lb/>upon opening the Corpſe of a Perſon <lb/>who had taken ſeveral Ounces of <lb/><hi
          rend="roman">crude Mercury</hi> internally; and of a <lb/><hi rend="roman"
          >Plumb-Stone</hi> lodg'd in the Coats of the <lb/><hi rend="roman">Rectum</hi>.
        Communicated in a Letter <lb/>from the late Dr. <hi rend="roman">Madden</hi>, Phyſician
        <lb/>at <hi rend="roman">Dublin</hi>, to Sir <hi rend="roman">Hans Sloane</hi>, <choice>
          <corr>Bar<hi rend="sup">t.</hi></corr>
          <sic>Bar </sic>
        </choice>. <lb/>Preſ. R. S. </head>
      <salute rend="italic space indent">
        <lb/>SIR, </salute>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE Internal Uſe of <hi rend="italic">crude Mercury</hi> is be-
        <lb/>come ſo frequent of late, that I believe it <lb/>may produce ſome great Benefit to
        Mankind here- <lb/>after, if a careful Collection was made of all the <lb/>extraordinary
        Caſes relating to the good or bad Ef- <lb/>fects of this Practice. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There are ſome Circumſtances in the following <lb/>Caſe, which were not owing to the
        internal Uſe of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Mercury</hi>; yet there are many others which were
        <lb/>undoubtedly occaſioned by it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Some time ago I was preſent, with Dr. <hi rend="italic">Robinſon</hi>, <lb/>and Mr. <hi
          rend="italic">Nichols</hi>, our Surgeon-General, at the open- <lb/>ing the Body of a
        Gentleman of Note in this Town, <lb/>who, for ſeveral Years, had found great Difficulty
        <lb/>in going to Stool. This Diſorder increaſed upon <lb/>him towards the latter End of his
        Life, and he <lb/>was seized with a violent Diſtemper, of which <pb n="292"/>
        <lb/>I can give you no Deſcription, having never attended <lb/>him. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In order to procure a Paſſage downward (which <lb/>I ſuppoſe was a principal Complaint)
        he took, by <lb/>the Advice of a Phyſician, ſince dead, ſeveral Ounces <lb/>of <hi
          rend="italic">crude Mercury</hi>, at different times, without any <lb/>Relief, and at
        length died. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon opening the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, which was very <lb/>much diſtended,
        there burſt forth a great Quantity <lb/>of Wind, though the Guts and Stomach were not
        <lb/>wounded. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Stomach was empty; and upon opening it <lb/>we found the inner Coat very much
        inflamed from <lb/>one End to the other. We obſerved in ſeveral <lb/>Places of the ſmall
        Guts, ſome ſcatter'd Grains of <lb/><hi rend="italic">crude Mercury</hi>, and along with
        them we generally <lb/>found a black gritty Powder, very like <hi rend="italic">Æthiops
          <lb/>Mineral</hi>, which was, without doubt, the <hi rend="italic">Mercury</hi>
        <lb/>changed into that Conſiſtence. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Colon</hi> was diſtended, at its Origin, to <lb/>twice the
        Thickneſs that an ordinary Man's Arm <lb/>has about the Shoulder. This extraordinary Thick-
        <lb/>neſs extended itſelf about the Length of ten or <lb/>twelve Inches; from hence it
        gradually decrea- <lb/>ſed, and where it was attached to the Stomach, <lb/>it had not above
        a third Part of that Size. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It was much inflamed at its Origin, and con- <lb/>tained at leaſt ſix Quarts of liquid
        Excrement, in <lb/>which we obſerved <hi rend="italic">crude Mercury</hi>, and alſo ſome
        <lb/>of the black Powder mentioned above. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Colon</hi>, where it parted from the Stomach, <lb/>and diverged
        toward the left Kidney, adhered <pb n="293"/>
        <lb/>about the Space of three Inches to the <hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi>; <lb/>and upon
        ſeparating the Adheſion, we found an Ab- <lb/>ſceſs and Inflammation, which had communicated
        <lb/>itſelf to thoſe Parts of the <hi rend="italic">Ileon</hi>, which were con- <lb/>tiguous
        to the <hi rend="italic">Colon</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Colon</hi> had in this Place a Perforation about <lb/>three
        Quarters of an Inch in Diameter, and four <lb/>ſmaller Perforations, about the Size of a
        Gooſe's <lb/>Quill, through which ſome Excrement had paſſed <lb/>into the <hi rend="italic"
          >Abdomen</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Coats of the <hi rend="italic">Colon</hi>, as it approached the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Inteſtinum rectum</hi>, began to grow ſcirrhous, about <lb/>the Space of ſix
        Inches, and the Capacity became <lb/>gradually ſmaller. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Valves of the <hi rend="italic">Colon</hi>, about this Place, were <lb/>of a
        reddiſh Colour, and were more ſcirrhous <lb/>than the other Parts of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Inteſtine</hi>. The Coats <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Colon</hi>, where it was
        continued to the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Rectum</hi>, were at leaſt half an Inch thick, and
        its Ca- <lb/>pacity was not above the fourth Part of the natu- <lb/>ral Size<choice>
          <corr>.</corr>
          <sic/>
        </choice>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon cutting the Gut horizontally hereabout, <lb/>we perceived a Body which ſtopped the
        Paſ- <lb/>ſage, and ſeemed to the Touch almoſt of a car- <lb/>tilaginous Conſiſtence. Having
        opened the Gut <lb/>Lengthways, we found it was no more than two <lb/>of the <hi
          rend="italic">Valvulæ Conniventes Coli</hi>, which were <lb/>grown ſcirrhous, and were
        protruded downward <lb/>into the <hi rend="italic">Rectum</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We alſo found a ſmall <hi rend="italic">Plumb-Stone</hi> in this <lb/>Place, which was
        quite buried in the <hi rend="italic">Tunica Vil- <lb/>loſa</hi>, and had made <choice>
          <corr>itſelf</corr>
          <sic>tſelf</sic>
        </choice> a Bed between the Coats <pb n="294"/>
        <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Rectum</hi>. It had likewiſe formed a ſmall <lb/>Abſceſs,
        which diſcharged itſelf into the Cavity of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Pelvis</hi>, but had
        not any Communication with <lb/>the Cavity of the <hi rend="italic">Rectum</hi>. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
