<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Hartley, Sandys and Wollaston: Another Case of a Person Bit by a
          Mad-Dog</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>David Hartley</persName>
              <persName>Fr. Sandys</persName>
              <persName>Francis Wollaston</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Another Case of a Person Bit by a Mad-Dog, Drawn up by David Hartley, M. A. and
              Mr. Fr. Sandys, Communicated to the Royal Society by Francis Wollaston, Esq; F. R.
              S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for T. Woodward, at the Half-Moon, between the
                  Temple-Gates in Fleetstreet; and C. Davis, in Pater-Noster-Row; Printers to the
                  Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1737-1738</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">40</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">274-276</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111029613</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1737.0044</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT40_0274">
    <body>
      <pb n="274"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VI.</hi> Another Caſe of a Perſon bit by a <hi rend="roman">Mad-
          <lb/>Dog</hi>, drawn up by <hi rend="roman">David Hartley</hi>, M. A. <lb/>and Mr. <hi
          rend="roman">Fr. Sandys</hi>, communicated to the <lb/><hi rend="sc">Royal Society</hi> by
          <hi rend="roman">Francis Wollaſton</hi>, <lb/>Eſq; F. R. S. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>BOUT the latter End of <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 1732.
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Soame</hi>'s Groom was bit in the Hand by <lb/>a <hi
          rend="italic">Mad-Dog</hi>, ſo as to fetch Blood. It was not known <lb/>in the Family for
        three Days. On the 4th Day, when <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fr. Sandys</hi> firſt ſaw it, the
        Wound was healed; but <lb/>it was opened again by him, and kept ſo for ſome <lb/>time, but
        at laſt healed ſooner than was intended, by <lb/>the Neglect of the Servant. He was bled,
        took a <lb/>Purge, after that half an Ounce of <hi rend="italic">Pulvis Antilyſſus</hi>
        <lb/>every Morning for three Mornings, and was ordered <lb/>to go into cold Water every Day
        for ſome time; but <lb/>he neglected it after the 3d Day. Beſides this, <hi rend="italic"
          >Fr. <lb/>Sandys</hi> order'd him to forbear all Meats, and drink <lb/>nothing but Water.
        He continued in this Regimen <lb/>for about five Weeks, then finding himſelf well, would
        <lb/>confine himſelf no longer to it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On <hi rend="italic">Sunday, Jan. 7.</hi> following, he was ſeized with <lb/>a
        Sickneſs, Vertigo, and faultering in his Speech and <lb/>Memory; and at laſt his Vertigo
        increaſed to ſuch a <lb/>Degree, that he fell down twice in the Space of half <lb/>an Hour;
        and the laſt time did not recover his Senſes, <lb/>till he was put to Bed, and blooded by a
        Perſon in the <lb/>Neighbourhood, to the Quantity of 18 or 20 Ounces, <pb n="275"/>
        <lb/>by his Maſter's Order. <hi rend="italic">Fr. Sandys</hi> was ſent for, but <lb/>could
        not come. He continued all Night reſtleſs and <lb/>ſullen, and in the Morning was blooded
        again, to the <lb/>Quantity of 15 Ounces. <hi rend="italic">D. Hartley</hi> was ſent for,
        <lb/>and came about Eight at Night, and found him very <lb/>ſullen, thirſty, but averſe to
        drinking, and his Pulſe <lb/>quick and hard. He ordered him to be put into the <lb/>cold
        Bath; but he refuſed to comply with it, till he <lb/>ſaw that Force would be uſed. About
        Midnight his <lb/>Pulſe riſing, the Doctor ordered him to be blooded to <lb/>the Quantity of
        16 or 18 Ounces: He continued all <lb/>Night reſtleſs. About Eight in the Morning he went
        <lb/>into the cold Bath again: About 10 <hi rend="italic">D. Hartley</hi> went <lb/>away,
        leaving it as his Opinion, that the cold Bath and <lb/>Bleeding ſhould be freely repeated,
        as the Circum- <lb/>ſtances ſhould require. About Noon <hi rend="italic"><choice>
            <corr>Fr.</corr>
            <sic>D.</sic>
          </choice> Sandys</hi>, be- <lb/>ing hitherto detained by Buſineſs, came, and bled him
        <lb/>immediately, to the Quantity of 18 or 20 Ounces: <lb/>He continued all this Night
        reſtleſs. Upon <hi rend="italic">Fr. <lb/>Sandys</hi>'s asking him whether his Averſion to
        drinking <lb/>proceeded from any Pain in ſwallowing, or ſome <lb/>other Cauſe? he ſaid it
        was from a Pain in ſwallow- <lb/>ing. The next Morning his Strength not being at all
        <lb/>diminiſhed, and his Pulſe continuing full as vigorous <lb/>as ever, <hi rend="italic"
          >Fr. Sandys</hi> bled him again to the Quantity <lb/>of 15 or 16 Ounces; yet he ſtill
        remained the ſame, <lb/>and took the ſame Care of his Horſes as uſual. <hi rend="italic">Fr.
          <lb/>Sandys</hi> went away, leaving Orders that as long as theſe <lb/>Symptoms, <hi
          rend="italic">viz.</hi> Reſtleſſneſs, Strength, and Averſion <lb/>to drinking continued,
        he ſhould be blooded freely, <lb/>and put into the cold Bath. He was blooded twice <lb/>more
        within the Week, ſo that the whole Quantity <pb n="276"/>
        <lb/>which he loſt in that time was about 120 Ounces. <lb/>After the laſt bleeding his
        Symptoms diſappeared, and <lb/>he grew weak, low-ſpirited and ſleepy: Then he went
        <lb/>eight times into the cold Bath. He did not take any <lb/>Medicines during his whole
        Illneſs. </p>
      <signed rend="size(1.2) space">
        <cb n="1"/>
        <lb/>D. Hartley. <cb n="2"/>
        <lb/>F. Sandys. </signed>
      <cb n="1 2"/>
      <postscript>
        <p rend="hanging indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">N. B.</hi> This Perſon hath continued well ever ſince, <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Anno</hi> 1738. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>See <hi rend="italic">Dampier</hi>'s Powder, N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 237. and N<hi
            rend="sup">o</hi> 443. </p>
      </postscript>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
