<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Copping: Concerning the Caesarian Operation Performed by an Ignorant
          Butcher</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>John Copping</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Extracts of Two Letters from the Revd Dean Copping, F. R. S. to the President,
              concerning the Caesarian Operation Performed by an Ignorant Butcher; And concerning
              the Extraordinary Skeleton Mentioned in the Foregoing Article</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for T. Woodward, and C. Davis, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn; Printers to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1739-1741</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">41</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">814-819</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110112667</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1739.0147</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT41_0814">
    <body>
      <pb n="814"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XVII.</hi> Extracts of Two Letters from the Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
        <lb/>Dean <hi rend="roman">Copping, F. R. S.</hi> to the <hi rend="roman">Preſident</hi>,
        <lb/>concerning the <hi rend="roman">Cæſarian</hi> Operation performed <lb/>by an ignorant
        Butcher; and concerning the <lb/>extraordinary <hi rend="roman">Skeleton</hi> mentioned in
        the fore- <lb/>going Article. </head>
      <div>
        <salute rend="italic space indent">
          <lb/>SIR, </salute>
        <dateline rend="align-right"><hi rend="italic">Dublin, March</hi> 16. 1737-8. </dateline>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> Have tranſcribed a Caſe, which I received from a <lb/>young
          Clergyman, who ſome time ſtudied <lb/>Phyſic, and knows the Woman: I ſhall probably
          <lb/>ſee her at <hi rend="italic">Clogher</hi>, where ſhe now lives. The Caſe
          <lb/>happened within theſe Two Years, but I cannot <lb/>learn the exact Date at preſent. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Sarah M<hi rend="sup">c</hi> Kinna</hi>, who now lives at <hi
            rend="italic">Brentram</hi>, <lb/>Two Miles from the City of <hi rend="italic"
            >Clogher</hi>, in the County <pb n="815"/>
          <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Tyrone</hi>, was married at the Age of Sixteen Years.
          <lb/>—Before her Marriage ſhe never had the Appearance <lb/>peculiar to Women; but, in a
          Month after her Mar- <lb/>riage, thoſe Appearances ſhewed themſelves properly. <lb/>Ten
          Months after her Marriage, ſhe found the <lb/>Symptoms of Pregnancy, and bore a Child at
          the <lb/>Expiration of the uſual Time. Ten Months after, <lb/>ſhe was delivered of
          another; and each time had a <lb/>ſpeedy and eaſy Delivery. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Two Months after her ſecond Lying-in, Symptoms <lb/>of Pregnancy appeared again, and
          increaſed in Pro- <lb/>portion to the Time; but at the End of Nine Months <lb/>thoſe
          Symptoms began to dwindle, and in a little time <lb/>ſhe had no other Reaſon for thinking
          ſhe was with <lb/>Child, but an abſolute Stoppage of her <hi rend="italic">Catamenia</hi>:
          <lb/>Nor had ſhe, during the Space of Six Years and ſome <lb/>Months, any one Return of
          them; but for the <lb/>greateſt Part of that Time, eſpecially the Four firſt <lb/>Years,
          ſhe was perpetually afflicted with moſt violent <lb/>Pains in the middle Region of the <hi
            rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Some time in the Seventh Year after her laſt Pre- <lb/>gnancy, which ended in ſuch an
          unuſual Manner, a <lb/>Swelling in her Belly, and other Symptoms, made <lb/>her conclude
          ſhe was again pregnant. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>About Seven Months after this uncertain Account, <lb/>a Boil, as ſhe thought,
          appeared about an Inch and <lb/>an half higher than her Navel. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>During this time of her Pregnancy ſhe often found <lb/>the Symptoms of her being
          quick with Child, till <lb/>about Six Weeks before this Boil (as ſhe calls it)
          <lb/>appeared. It was attended with very great Pain. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>She ſent for one <hi rend="italic">Turlough [Terence] O Neill</hi>, a <lb/>Butcher,
          who then did, and does now live with Capt. <pb n="816"/>
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">George Gledſtanes</hi>, about a Mile from <hi rend="italic"
            >Clogher</hi>. This <lb/>Man came to her the <hi rend="italic">Sunday</hi> after her
          Meſſage, and <lb/>found her in an expiring Condition. By this time <lb/>the Impoſtumation
          (which ſhe apprehended to be a <lb/>Boil) had broken, and an Elbow of the Child had
          <lb/>forced itſelf through it, and appeared in View. At <lb/>the Request of herſelf and
          Friends, he undertook to <lb/>adminiſter Relief to her, and made ſo large an Inci-
          <lb/>ſion above and below the Navel, as enabled him, by <lb/>fixing his Fingers under the
          Jaw of the <hi rend="italic">Fœtus</hi>, to <lb/>extract it; in which Operation he met not
          with the <lb/>leaſt Impediment. He afterwards looked into her <lb/>Belly, and ſeeing
          ſomething black, he put in his <lb/>Hand, and extracted, by Pieces, a perfect Skeleton of
          <lb/>a Child, and ſeveral Pieces of black putrefied Fleſh. <lb/>After the Operation, he
          ſwathed her up; and in Six <lb/>Weeks ſhe purſued her domeſtic Buſineſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>She has been in good Health ever ſince this won- <lb/>derful Accident happened; only
          ſhe has a Navel- <lb/>rupture, owing to the Ignorance of the Man in not <lb/>applying a
          proper Bandage. I am, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <signed rend="align-right italic size(1.2)">
          <lb/>J. Copping. </signed>
      </div>
      <div>
        <dateline rend="align-right space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Clogher (Ireland) June</hi> 2. 1738. </dateline>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">—I</hi> Have ſeen the Woman, of whom I ſent you <lb/>the
          ſurpriſing Account, with her Husband, <lb/>and inquired more particularly into the Fact;
          but <lb/>hope to be ſtill a little more particular, when I ſee the <lb/>Man who extracted
          the Child. They are ſo ignorant, <lb/>that, with their bad Language, I could not make my-
          <lb/>ſelf quite Maſter of what they ſaid; but, if they ſpeak <lb/>true, there is ſomething
          more ſurpriſing than the <pb n="817"/>
          <lb/>former Account mentioned: For the ſeveral Parts of <lb/>the latter, or rather the
          former, <hi rend="italic">Fœtus</hi>, were ex- <lb/>tracting by Degrees, from <hi
            rend="italic">July</hi> to <hi rend="italic">Chriſtmas</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>She had, by their Account, been married about <lb/>Eight or Ten Years before her
          firſt Pregnancy. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As well as I could apprehend them, ſhe had a Mid- <lb/>wife at the proper Time, in
          her firſt Pregnancy, for <lb/>Eight Days, Day and Night: When the Symptoms
          <lb/>diſappeared, the Swelling decreaſed, and People con- <lb/>cluded there was no Child. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This Child was carried for Seven Years, till ſhe had <lb/>been again pregnant for
          Nine Months; about which <lb/>time there was a Swelling in her Navel about the
          <lb/>Bigneſs of a Gooſe-egg, which broke in a ſmall Ori- <lb/>fice, of itſelf, and
          diſcharged a watry Humour. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>She had a Midwife, and Three or Four Phyſicians, <lb/>who gave her over, and left her
          as a dying Woman. <lb/>From this Orifice ſtarted the Elbow of a Child, which <lb/>hung
          ſome Days by the Skin, viſible to abundance: <lb/>At length ſhe cut it off for her own
          Relief. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When <hi rend="italic"><sic>O Neile</sic></hi> came, (whom I have not yet ſeen,
          <lb/>but ſhall ſoon) ſhe begged him to help her. The <lb/>Man was frightened, and went to
          ſleep; but, when he <lb/>got up, gave her a large Draught of Sack, and, I ſup- <lb/>poſe,
          took one himſelf; when he opened the Place, <lb/>and made ſuch a Hole as the Man deſcribes
          to be as <lb/>large as his Hat. He put in his Hand, took hold of <lb/>the Second Bone of
          the Child, and, pulling it back- <lb/>ward and forward to looſen it, in a little time ex-
          <lb/>tracted the Child. After this, looking into the Hole, <lb/>and ſeeing ſomething
          black, he put in his Hand, and <lb/>extracted other Bones. Some Bones ſtill remained,
          <lb/>which, as I ſaid, were extracted at different times, it <pb n="818"/>
          <lb/>ſeems too in different ways; for ſome came by the <lb/>Navel, others from the Womb
          the Natural Way. She <lb/>had great Pain at each time. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The former Account ſays, ſhe purſued her do- <lb/>meſtic Buſineſs: She might be about
          the Houſe, but <lb/>ſhe was 15 Months confined to the Houſe. I have <lb/>examined the
          Rupture, and can put a Finger a pretty <lb/>Way up into the Body. Mr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Dobbs</hi>, I hear, an emi- <lb/>nent Surgeon at <hi rend="italic">Dublin</hi>, thinks
          there may be Relief, <lb/>and that the Rupture may be much helped, and the <lb/>Guts
          reduced. I queſtion whether he will think ſo, <lb/>when he ſees her. However, I have
          collected about <lb/>Four Pounds for her among the Gentlemen that viſit <lb/>my Lord
          Biſhop, ſhall buy her ſome Cloaths, and <lb/>ſend her to <hi rend="italic">Dublin</hi>
          about 10 Days hence, to the <lb/>Infirmary. She was fond of going, but her ignorant
          <lb/>Prieſt, and ſome other ignorant Neighbours, told her <lb/>they would keep her till
          ſhe dies: But, upon my <lb/>anſwering thoſe Difficulties, ſhe conſents to go; her
          <lb/>Husband will carry her; and they are ſo thankful to <lb/>me for entering ſo much into
          their Condition, that <lb/>they now ſay ſhe ſhall go to <hi rend="italic">London</hi>, or
          where-ever I <lb/>pleaſe. I am ſorry the ſeveral Bones extracted were <lb/>carried away by
          different Phyſicians, that I cannot <lb/>procure one to be ſent to you; which, with the
          <lb/>Account, might find a Place in your ſurpriſing Col- <lb/>lection. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I have wrote ſo long a Letter, that, by way of <lb/>Apology, and to make ſome Amends,
          I muſt make <lb/>it ſtill longer by another Account, which a worthy <lb/>Clergyman gave me
          by Strength of Memory, from the <lb/>Letter of a Phyſician to him. </p>
        <pb n="819"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">William Clark</hi>, a poor Man of the County of <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Corke</hi>, about 18 Years of Age, complained of a Stiff- <lb/>neſs in his
          Joints, which by Degrees increaſed till it <lb/>came to an univerſal <hi rend="italic"
            >Anchyloſis</hi>: That is, all his <lb/>Joints were immoveable or oſſified. He lived in
          <lb/>this Condition 38 Years, and Dr. <hi rend="italic">Barry</hi>, the Phy- <lb/>ſician
          at <hi rend="italic">Corke</hi>, has made a Skeleton of him; and his <lb/>Account of it is
          this [ſee <hi rend="sc">Tab. V.</hi> Fig. 1. 2.]: Not <lb/>one Bone in his Body has the
          natural Form; for all <lb/>his Joints are immoveable and oſſified: And ſuch a
          <lb/>luxuriant Diſpoſition had all the Humours of his Body <lb/>to turn into Bone, that
          many little Branches of Bone, <lb/>like Coral, ſpring from the Joints and ſeveral Parts
          <lb/>of the Body. The whole Spine is oſſified, and one <lb/>intire Arch of Bone there is
          from the <hi rend="italic">Occiput</hi> down <lb/>to the <hi rend="italic">Os Sacrum</hi>;
          out of which ariſes a very protu- <lb/>berant Bone, which ſerves as a fine Handle to the
          <lb/>Skeleton. A ſharp Horn, like a Cock's Spur, grew <lb/>out of his Heel every Year. The
          Extract concludes <lb/>thus: <q rend="diple quotes">It is as difficult to give a
            particular and exact <lb/>Deſcription of this curious <hi rend="italic">Memento
              mori</hi>, as of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Calypſo</hi>'s Grotto. </q> I am promiſed very
          ſoon a com- <lb/>plete Hiſtory of his Life, and I ſhall endeavour to <lb/>tranſmit <hi
            rend="italic">William Clark</hi>'s Name to future Ages. </p>
        <signed rend="align-right">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Signed, </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="size(1.2)">John Copping. </hi>
        </signed>
      </div>
      <figure>
        <head rend="align-center sc space">
          <lb/>Tab. V. </head>
        <p rend="italic">
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">Fig. 1.</hi> The Front of the Skeleton. </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of a skeleton, from the front, on a separate fold-out page.
        </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <p rend="italic indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">2.</hi> The Back-ſide of it. </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of a skeleton, from the back, on a separate fold-out page.
        </figDesc>
      </figure>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
