<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Cleland: A Description of a Catheter</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Archibald Cleland</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Description of a Catheter, Made to Remedy the Inconveniencies Which Occasioned
              the Leaving off the High Operation for the Stone; By Archibald Cleland, Surgeon to
              General Wade's Regiment of Horse</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for T. Woodward, and C. Davis, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn; Printers to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1739-1741</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">41</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">844-847</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110112667</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1739.0156</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT41_0844">
    <body>
      <pb n="844"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXVI.</hi> A Deſcription of a <hi rend="roman">Catheter</hi>, made to
        <lb/>remedy the Inconveniencies which occaſioned <lb/>the leaving off the <hi rend="roman"
          >High Operation</hi> for the <lb/><hi rend="roman">Stone</hi>; by <hi rend="roman"
          >Archibald Cleland</hi>, Surgeon to <lb/>General <hi rend="roman">Wade</hi>'s Regiment of
          <hi rend="roman">Horſe</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>S this Operation was left off very precipitately, <lb/>in order
        to introduce that Method now called <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Lateral Operation</hi>, which
        has been practiſed for <lb/>ſome time with good Succeſs; notwithſtanding, had <lb/>the
        Operators at that time had the Advantage of this <lb/>Inſtrument I here offer to this
        Honourable <hi rend="sc">Society</hi>, <lb/>I am perſuaded the Advantage would have been
        more <lb/>than equal in favour of this <hi rend="italic">High Operation</hi>, and pre-
        <lb/>ferable to any other Method yet practiſed: And I <lb/>humbly hope, that the
        Deſcription, and the Method <lb/>of uſing this <hi rend="italic">Catheter</hi>, will be a
        means of reviving <lb/>an Operation ſo happily begun, and calculated for <lb/>the Good of
        thoſe that are afflicted with the Stone in <lb/>the Bladder. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This <hi rend="italic">Catheter</hi> is made either of Silver or Steel, of
        <lb/>different Sizes, to ſuit different Ages; and has the <lb/>outward Appearance of a
        common <hi rend="italic">Catheter</hi> [<hi rend="sc">Tab. <lb/>VII.</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 1.], and will anſwer the ſame Uſes: But, in <lb/>reſpect to this
        Operation, it differs from the common <lb/>in this, that it is compoſed of Two Legs [<hi
          rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 2.], with <lb/>blunt Points, a long Tube, a Sliding bolt; and a
        Handle, <lb/>which ſerves to open and ſhut the Legs: The Bolt, <lb/>which is fixed to the
        Extremity of the Tube, goes <lb/>into Two Holes, fixed in the Plate of the Handle: The <pb
          n="845"/>
        <lb/>one ſerves to keep the Legs cloſe during the time it <lb/>is to be introduced into the
        Bladder, the other to <lb/>extend the Points at the Diſtance of an Inch or more, <lb/>during
        the time the Operation is performing. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Method of uſing this <hi rend="italic">Catheter</hi> is, firſt, (after <lb/>having
        taken the neceſſary Precautions, and filled the <lb/>Bladder) to introduce the <hi
          rend="italic">Catheter</hi> into the Bladder, <lb/>then unbolt it at the Handle, and by
        holding the Tube <lb/>in one Hand, and the Handle that moves the Legs in <lb/>the other,
        then turn or open the Legs, till the Bolt <lb/>becomes oppoſite to the Second Hole upon the
        Plate <lb/>into which the Bolt muſt be thruſt; then by preſſing <lb/>gently the Handle
        downwards betwixt the Patient's <lb/>Legs, the Two blunt Points will be eaſily felt above
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Os Pubis</hi>, in the Protuberance made by the In- <lb/>jection
        into the Bladder. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Advantages I propoſe by uſing this Inſtru- <lb/>ment, are theſe: Firſt, To be a
        Director for the Ope- <lb/>rator, in determining the Place where the Puncture <lb/>is to be
        made in the Bladder; it alſo ſerves as a Sup- <lb/>port to the Bladder, when the Water flows
        out; and <lb/>keeps it from ſubſiding during the Time of the Ope- <lb/>ration, and till the
        Stone is extracted: It ſerves like- <lb/>wiſe to reſiſt the Preſſure of the abdominal
        Muſcles <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Peritoneum</hi>, and alſo hinders the <hi rend="italic"
          >Inteſtines</hi> from <lb/>being forced down upon the Knife; and keeps the <lb/>Orifice
        open, till the Stone or Stones are brought <lb/>away. And, laſtly, by the Help of this
        Inſtrument it <lb/>may be diſcovered, whether the Bladder is indurated <lb/>or ſcirrhous. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Method of performing this Operation, with <lb/>Safety, is, after having introduced
        and fixed the <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="italic">Ca- <lb/>theter</hi></hi> with its Legs
        open, to feel for the Two Points <pb n="846"/>
        <lb/>above the <hi rend="italic">Os Pubis</hi>, and place the Finger and Thumb <lb/>gently
        upon them; then give the Handle to an Aſ- <lb/>ſiſtant, to keep it firm in that Poſition;
        then, with the <lb/>Knife in the Right Hand, make a Puncture at once <lb/>into the Bladder,
        exactly in the Middle betwixt the <lb/>Points; but, for the more Security, ſomewhat lower
        <lb/>nearer the <hi rend="italic">Os Pubis</hi>; and, without drawing out the <lb/>Knife,
        make a large Inciſion downwards, inclining <lb/>under the Arch of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Pubis</hi>, in proportion to the <lb/>Bigneſs of the Stone, taking care not to wound the
        <lb/>Cartilage that joins the Bones together, when the <lb/>Knife is withdrawn: The Bladder
        being thus ſup- <lb/>ported, the Stone may be extracted with the Fingers, <lb/>or with a
        ſmall Pair of Tenets, there being little <lb/>Danger of breaking it in this Method. When the
        <lb/>Operation is finiſhed, raiſe the Handle of the <hi rend="italic">Ca- <lb/>theter</hi>,
        and unbolt it; ſhut it cloſe and fix it ſo; then <lb/>withdraw the <hi rend="italic"
          >Catheter</hi>, and dreſs the Patient. </p>
      <dateline rend="size(0.7) indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 5. 1739. </dateline>
      <figure>
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>See <hi rend="sc">Tab. VII. </hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="italic hanging indentall">
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">Fig. 1.</hi> The <hi rend="roman">Catheter</hi>, as it is to be
          introduced into <lb/>the Bladder, the Two Legs <hi rend="roman">A</hi> and <hi
            rend="roman">B</hi> being <lb/>cloſed together. </p>
        <figDesc>An illustrations of the catheter, with its legs closed, on a separate fold-out
          page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <p rend="italic hanging indentall">
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">Fig. 2.</hi> The <hi rend="roman">Catheter</hi>, its Two Legs <hi
            rend="roman">A</hi>, <hi rend="roman">B</hi>, being open. <list rend="italic">
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">C, D,</hi> The Tube. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">E,</hi> The Sliding bolt. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">F,</hi> The Two Holes into which the Bolt is <lb/>to be ſlid. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">G,</hi> The Ears fixt to the Tube <hi rend="roman">C, D,</hi>
              which <lb/>is all of one Piece with the Leg <hi rend="roman">A</hi>. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">H,</hi> The Handle, which opens the Legs; <lb/>this Handle is
              all of one Piece with <pb n="847"/>
              <lb/>the Leg <hi rend="roman">B</hi>, which Leg <hi rend="roman">B</hi> is a Conti-
              <lb/>nuation of a Wire, that runs through <lb/>the Tube <hi rend="roman">C D,</hi> and
              is faſtened to the <lb/>Handle <hi rend="roman">H,</hi> and turns with it. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <figDesc>An illustrations of the catheter, with its legs open, on a separate fold-out page.
        </figDesc>
      </figure>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
