<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Huxham: Concerning an Extraordinary Hernia Inguinalis</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>John Huxham</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Letter from John Huxham, M. D. F. R. S. to C. Mortimer, M. D. Secr. R. S.
              concerning an Extraordinary Hernia Inguinalis; And an Observation of the Passage of
              Mercury Over the Sun, Oct. 31. 1738 </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for T. Woodward, and C. Davis, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn; Printers to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1739-1741</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">41</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">640-645</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110112667</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1739.0108</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT41_0640">
    <body>
      <pb n="640"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXII.</hi> A Letter from <hi rend="roman">John Huxham</hi>, M. D.
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">F. R. S.</hi> to <hi rend="roman">C. Mortimer</hi>, M. D. Secr. <hi
          rend="roman">R. S. </hi>
        <lb/>concerning an Extraordinary <hi rend="roman">Hernia Ingui- <lb/>nalis</hi>; and an
        Obſervation of the Paſſage of <lb/><hi rend="roman">Mercury</hi> over the <hi rend="roman"
          >Sun</hi>, <hi rend="roman">Oct. 31. 1738.</hi>
      </head>
      <salute rend="italic space indent">
        <lb/>Honoured SIR, </salute>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>S the frequent Diſſection of morbid Bodies <lb/>tends greatly to
        aſcertain the Diagnoſtic and <lb/>Prognoſtic of Diſeaſes, during my Studies, and for
        <lb/>the firſt Six or Eight Years of my Practice, I applied <lb/>myſelf to it with great
        Aſſiduity.—Some few of the <lb/>more remarkable Caſes, I have met with, I beg Leave <lb/>to
        ſend you from time to time; and, if any of them <lb/>appear to you worthy of that Honour,
        you may lay <lb/>them before the <hi rend="sc">Royal Society</hi>.—The following <pb n="641"/>
        <lb/>may be of ſome Uſe in Practice: Therefore I ſend it <lb/>firſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Burman</hi>, a Taylor of this Town, about 40, <lb/>had from his
        Childhood laboured under a ſmall in- <lb/>guinal Rupture on the Right Side; but about Six
        <lb/>Years before his Death, from a Blow received in his <lb/>Groin, the <hi rend="italic"
          >Hernia</hi> became very large, and the Gut <lb/>always remained down in the <hi
          rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>; for he wore <lb/>no Bag, Truſs, or the like, to ſupport
        it.—The Day <lb/>before his Death, he was following his Work, as <lb/>uſual, with his
        Preſſing-iron, without any violent <lb/>Jerk, or Straining; but, about 10 in the Morning,
        all <lb/>at once, he felt a very great Pain in his Right <hi rend="italic">Inguen</hi>;
        <lb/>which, continually increaſing, in Two or Three <lb/>Hours threw him into Vomitings,
        cold Sweats, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        <lb/>—His Apothecary, Mr. <hi rend="italic">Ellery</hi>, gave him Clyſter, <lb/>which
        brought off a ſmall matter of thin Stool; but <lb/>gave no Relief, though it had been
        formerly very <lb/>ſerviceable to him in the like Diſorder.—About <lb/>Eight in the Evening
        I was ſent for, and found him <lb/>in cold Sweats, with ſcarce any Pulſe: The <hi
          rend="italic">hernial</hi>
        <lb/>Tumour was prodigious large, and exceeding hard; the <lb/>Pains extremely violent,
        which cauſed exceſſive Lan- <lb/>guors.—I immediately ordered, that he ſhould be <lb/>placed
        in a proper Poſture, that a warm aromatic <lb/>emollient Fomentation ſhould be frequently
        and long <lb/>applied, and that a Reduction of the Inteſtine ſhould <lb/>be attempted; or,
        if that did not ſucceed, that the <lb/>Operation for the <hi rend="italic">Bubonocele</hi>
        ſhould be performed. <lb/>—The Fomentation was tried a long while, emol- <lb/>lient <hi
          rend="italic">Terebinthinate</hi> Clyſters injected, and the Re- <lb/>duction attempted,
        for an Hour or Two, by Mr. <hi rend="italic">John <lb/>Start</hi>, a skilful Surgeon, but in
        vain: Nay, the Swel- <pb n="642"/>
        <lb/>ling increaſed conſiderably during the Application; <lb/>and the Pain became (if
        poſſible) more aggravated <lb/>all over the <hi rend="italic">Hernia</hi>, which before was
        chiefly at, and <lb/>near, the Rings of the <hi rend="italic">Abdominal</hi> Muſcles; and
        this <lb/>too, though he took, with an eaſy Cordial, and mulled <lb/>Wine, <hi rend="italic"
          >Laudan. Solid. gr. <hi rend="roman">ij</hi> ʒiis Horis.</hi>—Early the <lb/>next Morning
        I was deſired to ſee him again; and, <lb/>finding that he had not ſlept a Moment, the Tumour
        <lb/>conſiderably increaſed, and exceſſive hard, though not <lb/>diſcoloured, and the
        Patient exceeding weak and <lb/>pained, I adviſed the Operation forthwith, as the <lb/>only
        poſſible Means of ſaving him: But he was un- <lb/>willing to admit of it, and we were all
        indeed dif- <lb/>fident of the Succeſs.—Whilſt a freſh Fomentation <lb/>was getting ready,
        the poor Man expired in Agonies. <lb/>—About an Hour or Two after, we opened the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>, which in ſo ſhort a Space of Time appeared <lb/>all livid, and
        the Blood-veſſels were extremely turgid <lb/>and varicoſe.—Upon cutting through the Tegu-
        <lb/>ments, Part of the <hi rend="italic">Colon</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Ilium</hi> thruſt
        out with <lb/>great Force; they were both prodigiouſly diſtended <lb/>with Wind, highly
        inflamed, and in ſeveral Places <lb/>very livid.—That Part of the Guts commonly called
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cæcum</hi>, was blown up into a kind of globular Figure, <lb/>as
        big as a Child's Head.—It was remarkable, whe- <lb/>ther in the original Conformation, or by
        the vaſt <lb/>Diſtention, I know not, that there was no manner <lb/>of Appearance of the <hi
          rend="italic">Appendix vermiformis</hi> to be <lb/>found, though we diligently examined:—
        And fur <lb/>ther, that the <hi rend="italic">Cæcum</hi> was vaſtly thicker ſet with
        <lb/>Glands, and they much larger, than I had ever ſeen <lb/>before in any Subject.—The
        Convolutions of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ilium</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Colon</hi> were
        ſo immenſly diſtended with <pb n="643"/>
        <lb/>Wind, that the valvular Corrugations in both almoſt <lb/>totally diſappeared.—Yet
        exactly at the <hi rend="italic">Valvula <lb/>Tulpii, alias Bauhini</hi>, there was a very
        great Con- <lb/>ſtriction of the inteſtinal Canal, as if tied ſtrongly <lb/>with a Cord;
        and, though we opened the <hi rend="italic">Colon</hi> about <lb/>a Hand's-breadth beyond
        the <hi rend="italic">Valve</hi>, and let out the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Flatus</hi>, we
        could not poſſibly preſs any Wind from <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Ilium</hi> into the <hi
          rend="italic">Colon</hi> through the <hi rend="italic">Valve</hi>.—I <lb/>ſuſpected
        indurated Excrement, as an Obſtacle; but, <lb/>on a careful Inquiry, only found the whole
        valvular <lb/>Production, and the End of the <hi rend="italic">Ilium</hi>, at its Inſertion
        <lb/>into the <hi rend="italic">Colon</hi>, highly inflamed, and quite ſhutting <lb/>up the
        Paſſage.—On dilating the Rings of the <lb/>oblique and tranſverſe Muſcles, the Wind rumbled
        <lb/>up out of the <hi rend="italic">Ilium</hi> into the Cavity of the Belly very
        <lb/>readily.—We found pretty much bloody <hi rend="italic">Sanies</hi> in <lb/>the Guts, on
        ſlitting them open, but little or no indu- <lb/>rated <hi rend="italic">Fæces</hi>: A
        manifeſt Proof, that the exceeding <lb/>Hardneſs of the Tumour was owing only to the ex-
        <lb/>ceſſive Flatulence, and great Inflammation; and ſhews <lb/>how much we may be deceived
        in our Conjecture <lb/>on like Occaſions.—The Tumour of the <hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>
        <lb/>was 28 Inches round.—I was much ſurpriſed to <lb/>find no Adheſion of the <hi
          rend="italic">Inteſtines</hi> to the containing <lb/>Parts, though he had ſo long laboured
        under the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hernia</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This unhappy Caſe gave me a ſevere Reflection, <lb/>and I cannot but think the Malady
        was much increaſed <lb/>by the repeated Application of the hot Fomenta- <lb/>tions; as it
        rarefied the Air greatly, and, by relaxing <lb/>the Parts, gave further Room to the vaſt
        Expanſion. <lb/>—At that time I had never ſeen <hi rend="italic">Belloſte</hi>'s Second
        <lb/>Part to his <hi rend="italic">Hoſpital-Surgeon</hi>, where he adviſes, in <pb n="644"/>
        <lb/>ſuch Caſes, the moſt cold aſtringent Fomentations. <lb/>—In this and the like, they
        might have been very <lb/>proper; eſpecially if a Portion of Spirit of Wine <lb/>camphorated
        had been added to prevent Mortifi- <lb/>cation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It ſometimes happens, that though the annular <lb/>Perforations of the abdominal
        Muſcles are dilated by <lb/>the Operation, yet the <hi rend="italic">Hernia</hi> cannot be
        reduced.— <lb/>I believe, as the Guts were diſtended to ſo enormous <lb/>a Bulk in this Man,
        it would have been impracti- <lb/>cable. In ſuch Caſes may it not be proper to prick
        <lb/>them with a Needle, to let out the <hi rend="italic">Flatus</hi>, as is com- <lb/>monly
        practiſed in ſmall Wounds of the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, <lb/>where the <hi
          rend="italic">Inteſtine</hi> thruſts out, and becomes ſo turgid <lb/>with Wind, that it
        cannot otherwiſe be returned?— <lb/>In ſome ventral Ruptures (as they are called) this
        <lb/>alſo may be neceſſary.—I find Mr. <hi rend="italic">Sharp</hi>, in his late
        <lb/>excellent Piece of Surgery, approves of this Method, <lb/>from an old <hi rend="italic"
          >Engliſh</hi> Practitioner, who had often uſed <lb/>it with Succeſs.—I am perſuaded,
        Punctures in this <lb/>Manner are much leſs dangerous than the Operation; <lb/>and believe,
        in ſuch Caſes, may be more effectual.— <lb/>It is a common thing with Graſiers and
        Cattle-Doc- <lb/>tors, to prick the Guts of their Sheep and Bullocks <lb/>with great
        Succeſs, when, by feeding on Clover, or <lb/>freſh young Graſs, their Guts become ſo vaſtly
        diſ- <lb/>tended with Wind, as would otherwiſe certainly <lb/>kill them.—May not a very
        ſmall hollow Needle <lb/>with Perforations, as in that uſed by ſome inſtead of <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">Trocar</hi> for a <hi rend="italic">Paracentheſis</hi>, be more proper than
        <lb/>a common Needle?—May not the hernial Tumour <lb/>be perceived to be chiefly flatulent
        by its being in <pb n="645"/>
        <lb/>ſome Degree tranſparent upon applying a Candle, <lb/>as uſed in the <hi rend="italic"
          >Hydrocele</hi>? And may not that direct <lb/>the proper Place for Punctures? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe are Conjectures; but I am, with great Truth, <lb/>and the higheſt Reſpect, </p>
      <salute rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>SIR, </salute>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <dateline rend="space size(0.7)">Plymouth, June 8. 1739. </dateline>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <signed rend="italic">
        <lb/>Your, moſt obliged, <lb/>and moſt obedient, <lb/>humble Servant, <lb/><hi
          rend="roman size(1.2)">J. Huxham. </hi>
      </signed>
      <cb n="1 2"/>
      <postscript rend="space">
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I have taken the Liberty to fill up this Letter with <lb/>a Scheme of the Phaſe of
          the Sun, <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 31ſt, <lb/>11<hi rend="sup">h</hi>. 5´. 12´´. as
          taken by my Teleſcope, which is a <lb/>very good one of 10 Feet; but as I had neither
          <lb/>Croſs-Hairs, Micrometer, or other exact Inſtruments, <lb/>the Obſervation may not be
          very exact: Beſides, I <lb/>had only a Glimpſe of the Sun for 7 or 8 Minutes. </p>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>An illustration showing the passage of the planet Mercury over the Sun.
          </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </postscript>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
