<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Ettrick: The Description and Draught of a Machine for Reducing
          Fractures</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Henry Ettrick</persName>
            </author>
            <title>The Description and Draught of a Machine for Reducing Fractures of the Thigh, by
              Mr. Henry Ettrick, Surgeon</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for T. Woodward, and C. Davis, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn; Printers to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1739-1741</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">41</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">562-568</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110112667</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1739.0091</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT41_0562">
    <body>
      <pb n="562"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">IV.</hi> The Deſcription and Draught of a <hi rend="roman">Ma-
          <lb/>chine</hi> for reducing <hi rend="roman">Fractures</hi> of the <hi rend="roman"
          >Thigh</hi>, <lb/>by Mr. <hi rend="roman">Henry Ettrick</hi>, Surgeon. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">H</hi>Aving frequently conſidered the many Incon- <lb/>veniences, and
        great Difficulties, attending the <lb/>common Methods of Reduction, I determined with
        <lb/>myſelf to attempt a Form more mechanical and cer- <lb/>tain. I immediately fixed on the
        Axle and Wheel, <lb/>as the moſt ſimple, and yet fully capable of taking <lb/>in and
        ingroſſing all and every Advantage neceſſary <pb n="563"/>
        <lb/>towards the well reducing of Fractures, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> It con-
        <lb/>ſiſts of no more than a Wheel and Pinion, with their <lb/>Axles; the Roch, or ſnagged
        Wheel, being herein <lb/>accounted as Part of the great Wheel, fixed in a light <lb/>Frame
        of about Two Feet long, [ſee Fig. 2. <hi rend="sc">Tab. II.</hi>] <lb/>the Whole not
        exceeding the Weight of 15 Pounds; <lb/>and when taken to Pieces, by unſcrewing the Frame-
        <lb/>pieces, may be packed up in a common Ruſh-Basket, <lb/>belted to the Side, and conveyed
        to any Diſtance. <lb/>Again, the Room it takes up in working is not a <lb/>full Yard, and
        may be ſet up and fixed for Uſe in a <lb/>few Minutes. In uſing this Machine, the Surgeon
        <lb/>need but one Aſſiſtant; whereas, in moſt other Me- <lb/>thods, their Number is moſt
        troubleſome and incon- <lb/>venient: The Buſineſs of this Aſſiſtant is no farther <lb/>than
        to mind the Surgeon's Orders, and move the <lb/>Winch according to his Direction. When the
        Ex- <lb/>tenſion is ſufficient, the Engine ſtays itſelf, and con- <lb/>tinues the Tenſion of
        the Limb, by the Aſſiſtance of <lb/>this Roch, or toothed Wheel, whoſe Teeth are cut fine
        <lb/>enough to ſtay the Engine at every Line of an Inch, <lb/>and which is fixed on the Back
        of the aforeſaid great <lb/>Wheel, both to the Croſs by the Help of Screws, <lb/>and on its
        Arbor by having its Centre ſquared out, <lb/>ſo as to fix tight thereon, and ſo near the
        Frame as <lb/>only to allow a bare clearidge: Its Teeth, ſtanding <lb/>counter to the
        former, admit the Spring or Catch <lb/>fixed on the Inſide of the Frame, to flip over the
        <lb/>Vertex thereof, without Interruption; but in a reverſe <lb/>Rotation, or when the
        Engine is about to come up, <lb/>flies into the Spaces thereof, and ſtays the ſame: The
        <lb/>upper Part thereof projects about an Inch from the <lb/>Frame, ſo that being preſſed
        upon by the Finger of <pb n="564"/>
        <lb/>one Hand, the inferior Part is elevated above the <lb/>Range of the Teeth, to admit the
        coming up of the <lb/>Engine, which is to be directed by the other Hand <lb/>being applied
        to the Winch in any Degree. This <lb/>Engine has its Power ſo commanded, that it may be
        <lb/>uſe without Reſtriction, from the moſt robuſt to <lb/>the moſt tender Frame, ſeeing it
        acts and exerts its <lb/>Power in proportion to the Reſiſtance made. Farther, <lb/>as hinted
        at before, it is enriched with all thoſe <lb/>Properties which Authors affirm neceſſary to a
        ſuc- <lb/>ceſsful Operation; for this Extenſion, according to <lb/>their Obſervation, is
        made deliberately, ſteady, <lb/>equally, and in one continued Line, without the <lb/>leaſt
        Variation. And further, in oblique Fractures of <lb/>the Thigh, where the Bones are apt to
        ride, (and <lb/>therefore, on that Account, require a continued Ex- <lb/>tenſion in a
        certain Degree, to prevent the Limbs <lb/>ſhortening after the Cure) ſuch a Machine muſt be
        <lb/>of excellent Service; having the Property of increaſ- <lb/>ing or decreaſing the
        Extenſion at Pleaſure, and to <lb/>be perfected without the leaſt Jar or Tremor. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The neceſſary Appendages are Bands, by which <lb/>the Engine extends the Limb; and
        deſerve the fol- <lb/>lowing Obſervations: Immediately from the Axle of <lb/>the great Wheel
        comes a Girt, at the other End of <lb/>which Girt is a Hook, which links into a Swivel-
        <lb/>Ring at the Bottom of a Sole-plate: This Sole-plate <lb/>anſwers the Shape of the Foot,
        and is made of well- <lb/>hammered Braſs, the Inſide of which is padded, to <lb/>ſit eaſy to
        the Foot: The upper Part hath a Strop fixed <lb/>thereto, which claſps over the upper Part
        of the Me- <lb/>tatarſal Bones; and to keep the Strops ending in the <lb/>Sole-plate from
        galling or preſſing the Sides of the <pb n="565"/>
        <lb/>Foot and Ancle, there project Two Arms from the <lb/>Sides of this Sole-plate, to which
        the Strops coming <lb/>from the Ancle-band are faſtened. That the whole <lb/>Limb may be
        kept in a Line with the Machine, the <lb/>Leg is ſuſpended by Bands, one of which is placed
        at <lb/>the Ancle, from the Sides of which paſs Two Strops, <lb/>to join the inferior
        Knee-band: From this Band paſs <lb/>Two Strops to the ſuperior Knee-band: All theſe
        <lb/>Strops are deſigned to divide the Extenſion, ſo that all <lb/>Parts may equally bear
        alike, and ſo to ſecure the <lb/>Joints of the Limb from the Violence of the Exten-
        <lb/>ſion. The Inſide of theſe Strops are lined; the Bands <lb/>incircling the Limb are
        contrived in the ſame Man- <lb/>ner as the Bow or Spring of a Truſs, having ſtrong
        <lb/>Claſps at the Ends, after the Manner of thoſe for <lb/>Pocket-books, to fit any
        Dimenſions. The Band <lb/>embracing the Part above the Fracture, and from <lb/>which paſs
        Two Strops to the Head of the Bed, to <lb/>make the Counter-extenſion, is of the ſame kind
        as <lb/>the former, and is to be kept on, the whole Time of <lb/>Decumbiture, to prevent the
        Patient's Body ſinking <lb/>on the Fracture, and thereby contracting the Limb. <lb/>The
        exterior of the Two laſt-mentioned Strops preſſes <lb/>juſt beneath the great <hi
          rend="italic">Trochanter</hi> on its Outſide; the <lb/>other comes from the anterior Part
        of the ſame Band, <lb/>and in ſuch a Scite as to give the Patient Liberty to <lb/>raiſe
        himſelf at Diſcretion. To preſerve the natural <lb/>Curvity of the Thigh, it would be
        neceſſary to have <lb/>a large broad Band ariſing from the Bedſide, to en- <lb/>compaſs the
        fractured Part, and keep it ſteady. </p>
      <pb n="566"/>
      <figure>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>Explanation of Figure 2. <hi rend="sc">Tab. II.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="italic space">
          <list rend="indentall">
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">A.A.</hi> Repreſents the Bed. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">B.</hi> The Patient. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">C.</hi> The Machine at the Feet of the Bed. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">D.D.</hi> The Frame. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">E.</hi> The great Wheel. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">F.</hi> The Roch-wheel, with a Catch and Spring, <lb/>to prevent
              the Wheel going back. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">G.</hi> The Pinion. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">H.</hi> The Winch. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">I.</hi> The Arbor of the great Wheel, whereon </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">K.</hi> the Girt <hi rend="roman">K</hi> is fixed: The Diameter
              of the <lb/>Barrel thereon is Two Inches. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">L.</hi> The End of the Girt fixed by </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">M.</hi> the Ring <hi rend="roman">M.</hi> to </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">N.</hi> the Sole-board <hi rend="roman">N.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">O.</hi> The Band which paſſes over the Inſtep. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">P.</hi> The Ancle-band. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">Q.</hi> The Strop which paſſes from the Sole-plate <lb/>to the
              Ancle. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">R.</hi> The Strop continued from the Ancle to the <lb/>Knee. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">S.</hi> The Knee-band. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">T.</hi> The ſuperior Knee-band, with the Strop con- <lb/>tinued,
              as before. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">V.</hi> The Band embracing the Part above the <lb/>Fracture. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">W.W.</hi> The Counter-ſtrops paſſing to the Bed's- <lb/>head. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">X.</hi> The lateral Band to preſerve the Curvity <lb/>of the
              Thigh-bone. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of the Machine described, on a separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <pb n="567"/>
      <postscript>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">P. S.</hi> I thought it would not be improper, if I <lb/>ſhould
          attempt to demonſtrate to what great Exact- <lb/>neſs Machines of this Nature may be made
          to <lb/>operate. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A Specimen of which I beg Leave to preſent as <lb/>follows: Admit the Barrel 4 Inches
          Diameter, the <lb/>Roch-wheel to be cut with 48 Teeth, the great <lb/>Wheel to have 32,
          anſwerable to a Pinion with 8. <lb/>The Reaſon of pitching on a Barrel of this Dimen-
          <lb/>ſion is, that it may be more preciſely judged what <lb/>Extenſion has been made; for
          repeated Revolutions <lb/>of the Girt upon the Cylinder, in extending, would, <lb/>by its
          uncertain Increaſe, ſubject the Judgment to err; <lb/>whereas the utmoſt Extenſion
          required comes within <lb/>one Revolution of this Barrel. The Teeth of the <lb/>Roch to be
          numbered at every Fourth, which will <lb/>be at every Inch, and equals in one Revolution
          the <lb/>Periphery of the Barrel; conſequently every Tooth <lb/>of this Roch will ſtretch
          the Limb One-fourth of an <lb/>Inch: So though the Spring or Catch to the ſaid Roch
          <lb/>ſhould paſs the capital Numbers, and ſtop in the <lb/>Interſpaces thereof, it is only
          counting from the laſt <lb/>capital Number to the Place where the Spring is, and <lb/>that
          gives the Parts of the Inch: By the ſame Rule <lb/>the Winch, every Turn it makes, will
          gain a Fourth <lb/>of this Wheel, which will be 3 Inches, or 12 Teeth; <lb/>and 4
          Revolutions thereof will anſwer to the Peri- <lb/>phery of the Barrel: So by meaſuring the
          ſound <lb/>Limb, and comparing the fractured therewith, the <lb/>Extenſion required may be
          nearly demonſtrated. <lb/>With the Uſe of this Machine, I ſhould recommend <lb/>the 18
          Tail Bandage to the circular Rollers of <hi rend="italic">Hip- <lb/>pocrates</hi>, ſince
          they are both leſs troubleſome to <pb n="568"/>
          <lb/>the Surgeon, and leſs painful to the Patient; nor yet <lb/>ſo liable to wreath the
          Muſcles, and diſtort the Ends <lb/>of the fractured Bones. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And to render this Machine of the like Service at <lb/>Sea, where we are in the
          greateſt need of Helps of <lb/>this Nature; I have deſigned a Bed to ſwing and <lb/>yield
          to the Ship's Motion, whereon the Patient is <lb/>to be laid, with the Engine thereto
          fixed, that the <lb/>frequent Diſcompoſure and Diſturbance given to the <lb/>fractured
          Part by the Ship's rolling and working at <lb/>Sea, may be prevented. </p>
      </postscript>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
