<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Watson: A Case Wherein Part of the Lungs Were Coughed up</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>William Watson</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Case Wherein Part of the Lungs Were Coughed up. Presented to the Royal Society
              by William Watson, F. R. S. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for T. Woodward, and C. Davis, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn; Printers to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1739-1741</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">41</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">623-624</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110112667</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1739.0100</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT41_0623">
    <body>
      <pb n="623"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XIII.</hi> A Caſe wherein Part of the <hi rend="roman">Lungs</hi>
        <lb/>were coughed up. Preſented to the <hi rend="sc">Royal <lb/>Society</hi> by <hi
          rend="roman">William Watſon, F. R. S.</hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="dc(1.5)">T</hi>Homas Halſey</hi>, aged about 70, of a ſhort
        Make, <lb/>and pretty fat, being in a tolerably good State of <lb/>Health, (unleſs, as for
        ſome Years paſt, troubled with <lb/>frequent coughing upon Motion) was ſeized <hi
          rend="italic">Sept.</hi>
        <lb/>23. 1740. with a violent Fit of Coughing, in which <lb/>he fell down, as the
        By-ſtanders thought, dead, and <lb/>diſcharged near a Quart of Blood at his Mouth, in a
        <lb/>very large Stream, mixed with many Portions of a <lb/>ſeemingly grumous Matter. His
        coughing Fit con- <lb/>tinued near Three Minutes. He revived upon bleed- <lb/>ing at the
        Arm, and, being put to-bed, recovered <lb/>his Senſes, and (as he ſaid) was perfectly eaſy,
        and <lb/>free from Pain, except upon Coughing, which as <lb/>often as he did, he ſpit Blood
        viſibly arterial from its <lb/>florid Colour. About Four Hours after the Firſt Fit, <lb/>he
        was taken with a Second, attended with the ſame <lb/>Symptoms as the Firſt; and expired in
        it. Upon <lb/>examining the Blood, which he brought up at his <lb/>Death, I found, in Pieces
        of different Sizes, near <lb/>Three Ounces of the Subſtance of the Lungs, not
        <lb/>ulcerated, or any ways diſtempered; and I have Rea- <lb/>ſon to believe there was near
        the ſame Quantity of <lb/>the Lungs thrown up during the Firſt Fit of Coughing. <lb/>The
        Pieces were eaſily diſtinguiſhable from grumous <lb/>Blood, by their connecting Membrane,
        the <hi rend="italic">Acini</hi> in <lb/>the internal Part, and their ſpecific Gravity. </p>
      <pb n="624"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon examining the Contents of the <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi>
        <lb/>after Death, the Right Lobes of the Lungs were ſound, <lb/>of a good Colour, and
        no-ways injured: In the Left <lb/>Cavity of the <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi>, there was a
        large Quantity of <lb/>extravaſated Blood; the inferior Left Lobe adhered <lb/>ſtrongly both
        to the <hi rend="italic">Pleura</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Mediaſtinum</hi>, and <lb/>was
        ſomewhat decayed; but of the ſuperior Left <lb/>Lobe, the upper Part next the <hi
          rend="italic">Trachea</hi> adhered <lb/>to the <hi rend="italic">Pleura</hi> for about Two
        Inches; and the Re- <lb/>mainder, where there had been no Adheſion, (as I <lb/>could
        perceive from the ſmooth Surface of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pleura</hi>) was torn away by
        Pieces, and diſcharged in <lb/>Coughing. As the greateſt Part of the Left Side of <lb/>the
        Lungs was tied down to the circumjacent <hi rend="italic">Mem- <lb/>branes</hi>, the Perſon
        being old, and the whole Force of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Parietes</hi> of the <hi
          rend="italic">Abdomen, Diaphragm, <hi rend="roman">&amp;c.</hi></hi> in <lb/>the Action of
        coughing, was unequally exerted upon <lb/>that Part that did not adhere, and which, by the
        <lb/>Violence of the Preſſure, was torn off from the reſt, <lb/>and diſcharged, as I juſt
        now mentioned; it is <lb/>worthy Obſervation, how ſmall the Degree of Senſi- <lb/>bility is
        in the Lungs; that a Perſon ſhould loſe ſo <lb/>much of their Subſtance, as in this
        Inſtance, upon the <lb/>Firſt Fit; and yet, upon Recovery of his Senſes, to <lb/>complain of
        little or no Pain from ſuch Dilaceration, <lb/>when even the Bite of an Inſect upon the
        Surface of <lb/>the Body is attended with ſo much. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Adheſion of this Man's Lungs explained like- <lb/>wiſe the Cauſe of his frequent
        Coughing for ſome <lb/>Years before his Death. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
