<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Powell and Sloane: Concerning a Gentlewoman Who Voided with Her Urine,
          Hairy Crustaceous Substances</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>John Powell</persName>
              <persName>Hans Sloane</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Letter from Mr. John Powell, to Sir Hans Sloane, Bart. Pr. R. S. &amp;c.
              concerning a Gentlewoman Who Voided with Her Urine, Hairy Crustaceous Substances: To
              Which is Annexed Sir Hans Sloane's Answer, Containing Several Observations of
              Extraordinary Substances Voided by the Urinary Passages</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for T. Woodward, and C. Davis, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn; Printers to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1739-1741</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">41</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">699-705</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110112667</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1739.0121</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT41_0699">
    <body>
      <pb n="699"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VIII.</hi> A Letter from Mr. <hi rend="roman">John Powell</hi>, to Sir
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">Hans Sloane</hi>, Bar<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> Pr. <hi rend="roman">R.
          S. <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi></hi> concern- <lb/>ing a Gentlewoman who voided with her
        <lb/>Urine, hairy cruſtaceous Subſtances: To <lb/>which is annexed Sir <hi rend="roman">Hans
          Sloane</hi>'s Anſwer, <lb/>containing ſeveral Obſervations of extraor- <lb/>dinary
        Subſtances voided by the Urinary <lb/>Paſſages. </head>
      <div>
        <salute rend="italic space indent">
          <lb/>Honoured SIR, </salute>
        <dateline rend="align-right"><hi rend="italic">Pembroke, July</hi> 16. 1733. </dateline>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">H</hi>Aving the Opportunity of ſending now to <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >London</hi> by a ſafe Hand, I make bold to ſend <lb/>you in a Box, ſome things that a
          worthy Divine's <lb/>Daughter of this Neighbourhood, whoſe Father has <lb/>been ſome Years
          dead, and her Husband now too, <lb/>has voided ever ſince <hi rend="italic"
            >Michaelmas</hi> laſt was Two <pb n="700"/>
          <lb/>Years, unleſs it were about Nine or Ten Weeks laſt <lb/>Summer. She is near 40 Years
          of Age, and has <lb/>been married about 17 Years, and had a Child about <lb/>12 Years ago,
          that lived about Nine Weeks. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>About <hi rend="italic">August</hi> laſt was Two Years, ſhe was ſeized <lb/>with a
          Stoppage in her Urine, a ſmall Pain in her <lb/>Bladder, and a great Pain in the Bottom of
          her Feet, <lb/>with the making of whitiſh Water like Whey; and <lb/>ſhe had then a great
          Weakneſs in her Limbs, and a <lb/>Pain in her Bowels; for which another Gentleman,
          <lb/>Six Miles off hence, ordered her to go into the cold <lb/>Bath, by which ſhe found
          great Benefit for the Pains <lb/>in her Limbs; but the Pain in her making Water
          <lb/>rather increaſed, and the her Urine began to grow <lb/>fetid; and about <hi
            rend="italic">Chriſtmas</hi> was Two Years, ſhe voided <lb/>the largeſt of the Things
          you find in the Box, without <lb/>any very great Pain then, being ſhe had taken a quiet-
          <lb/>ing Draught that Night to compoſe her; but, almoſt <lb/>ever ſince, they put her to
          moſt exquiſite Pain before <lb/>ſhe can get them off; and ſhe is commonly forced to
          <lb/>take the ſmall Part of the hairy Part between her <lb/>Fingers, before ſhe can get
          them off; and oftentimes <lb/>a good deal of Blood comes off with her plucking <lb/>them,
          which makes her very ſore inwardly. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Upon uſing gentle Evacuations laſt Spring was <lb/>Twelvemonth, ſhe grew much better;
          ſuch as Vo- <lb/>miting with the <hi rend="italic">Hypecacuanha</hi>, Purging with <hi
            rend="italic">Manna</hi>, <lb/>Oil of Sweet Almonds, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> and,
          taking ſometimes <lb/>Calomel the Nights before, and very often diuretic <lb/>and balſamic
          Pills, with and without <hi rend="italic">Trochiſc. Gor- <lb/>don.</hi> and emollient
          Decoctions and Emulſions of <lb/>ſeveral Kinds, the Fetor and Roapineſs in her Urine
          <lb/>abated, and ſhe was pretty hearty and brisk, ſo that <pb n="701"/>
          <lb/>ſhe undertook laſt <hi rend="italic">Auguſt</hi> a Journey into <hi rend="italic"
            >Hereford- <lb/>ſhire</hi>, and ſtaid there near Two Months, and, I fear, <lb/>ſhe might
          take ſome Cold in her Journey; for her <lb/>Pains grew worſe, and more troubleſome, after
          her <lb/>return home; and ſhe then voided great Quantities <lb/>of thoſe large Subſtances,
          as well as ſmall, that you <lb/>ſee, and her Urine grew extraordinary ropy and <lb/>fetid,
          notwithſtanding all the Endeavours of another <lb/>Gentleman and myſelf; and very often
          the Subſtance <lb/>ſhe voided would be ſo ſtiff and ropy, that we could <lb/>ſcarce
          ſeparate it from the Pot; at other times ſo <lb/>pliant, that you might take it up a great
          Height with <lb/>a Sprig of a Broom, or a Feather, and ſo fall down <lb/>again like a Lump
          into the Pot. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>She has for this conſiderable time voided one or <lb/>more of theſe hairy cruſtaceous
          Subſtances every Day <lb/>or Night; they looking, when they are firſt voided, <lb/>like
          Hair and Coralline; and her Pains are ſo very <lb/>exquiſite, that we are forced, every
          Third Night at <lb/>fartheſt, to give her an Anodyne to quiet her; and <lb/>that often
          cannot be done, her Pain being ſo very <lb/>great. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Continuance of this ſevere Pain has brought <lb/>her to a very conſiderable
          Weakneſs, and almoſt a <lb/>total Loſs of Fleſh; and, what is her great Misfortune,
          <lb/>(eſpecially at this Seaſon of the Year) that Milk will <lb/>by no means agree with
          her: She has often tried to <lb/>conquer it, but never could, it conſtantly making her
          <lb/>very ſick in her Stomach, and ſhe vomiting it up in <lb/>great large Lumps. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>We have uſed Injections of Two or Three Sorts, <lb/>but ſhe cannot well bear them;
          and ſhe has had her <lb/><hi rend="italic">Menſes</hi> very regularly, till within the Two
          or Three laſt <pb n="702"/>
          <lb/>Times; and for theſe 10 or 12 Days paſt, ſhe has <lb/>complained of a Swelling in her
          Belly, but none in <lb/>her Thighs nor Legs. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>One thing I had almoſt forgot to have told you, <lb/>that ſhe has often found a <hi
            rend="italic">Crepitus</hi>, or a breaking of <lb/>Wind, as it were, in her Bladder;
          which would make <lb/>one believe, that there is an Aperture from the <hi rend="italic"
            >In- <lb/>teſtinum Rectum</hi> to the Bladder. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Her Bladder has been ſearched, and the Surgeon <lb/>who did it, aſſures her, he can
          diſcover no Stone; and <lb/>he is a very ingenious Perſon in his Profeſſion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>She has for theſe Four or Five laſt Days complained, <lb/>at times, of aſthmatics
          Fits, which I muſt attribute to <lb/>the Heat of the Weather. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Voiding of theſe hairy cruſtaceous Subſtances <lb/>never occurred to me in my
          Practice before; though <lb/>I have above once had Perſons voided large Bladders,
          <lb/>like the <hi rend="italic">Hydatids</hi> in Fiſh, and large Quantities of them,
          <lb/>and cured them. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Theſe Subſtances therefore I beg Leave to ſend to <lb/>you, being, I reckon, there is
          ſcarce any thing that <lb/>eſcapes your Obſervation: But whether they have, or <lb/>have
          not, I deſire your Opinion of them; and beg <lb/>you will be pleaſed to inform me what
          Courſe you <lb/>judge moſt proper I ſhould take with her. </p>
        <salute rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>SIR, </salute>
        <signed rend="italic align-right">
          <lb/>Your moſt obliged, humble, <lb/>and obedient Servant, <lb/><hi rend="roman size(1.2)"
            >John Powell. </hi>
        </signed>
        <postscript>
          <label rend="space align-center italic">
            <lb/>P. S. </label>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>She drank the Hot-well-waters both at <hi rend="italic">Briſtol</hi> and <lb/>here,
            but with little Succeſs; has taken <hi rend="italic">Cantharides</hi>
            <pb n="703"/>
            <lb/>inwardly, as preſcribed by Dr. <hi rend="italic">Groenvelt</hi>, in Ulcers <lb/>of
            the Bladder, and all other things we could think <lb/>of. </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic space align-center">
          <lb/>Sir <hi rend="roman">Hans Sloane</hi>'s Anſwer to Mr. <hi rend="roman">Powell</hi>. </head>
        <salute rend="italic space indent">
          <lb/>SIR, </salute>
        <dateline rend="align-right"><hi rend="italic">London, July</hi> 26. 1733. </dateline>
        <p><hi rend="dc(1.5)">I</hi> Received yours of the 16th Two Days ſince, to- <lb/>gether with
          the Box, and Contents thereof; which <lb/>I have conſidered, and am ſatisfied, that the
          hairy <lb/>Excretions are generated moſt likely in her Kidneys. <lb/>I have ſeen, in my
          Practice, ſome Inſtances of the <lb/>like, and have by me what was brought off by Urine
          <lb/>from ſome of them. The firſt I remember, was from <lb/>a Gentleman near the <hi
            rend="italic">Exchange</hi>, who would fre- <lb/>quently, Forty Years ſince, void with
          his Urine long <lb/>Hairs, which were received on white Paper; and, the <lb/>Urine paſſing
          off, would remain there, and, by their <lb/>Tranſparency and Angles, yielded, on viewing
          by a <lb/>Microſcope, the fineſt Colours imaginable, ſuch as <lb/>we find by a Priſm. This
          Gentleman did not ſuffer <lb/>much, though he complained of a Sharpneſs of Urine. <lb/>The
          Perſon who was affected the moſt, and applied <lb/>to me for Help, was a Brewer, who had
          ſuch Hairs <lb/>matted or woven together, voided by Urine with <lb/>great Pain: But then
          there was no calculous Matter, <lb/>or very little, added to them. It is very likely, that
          <lb/>that Matter is added to thoſe of your Patient in the <lb/>Bladder, by being retained
          there. I have a Pin, that a <lb/>young Woman had ſwallowed, and was afterwards taken <pb
            n="704"/>
          <lb/>out of her Groin from an Apoſtem after a Tumour; <lb/>which Pin was covered or
          incruſted, as theſe hairy Sub- <lb/>ſtances, with ſuch calculous Matter, and got there
          <lb/>from the Urine in her Bladder, where in all likeli- <lb/>hood it had contracted that
          Cruſt. I have a ſilver Bod- <lb/>kin, the broad End of which is covereed with a pretty
          <lb/>large Stone. A poor Gentlewoman thought, by thruſt- <lb/>ing this Bodkin up the <hi
            rend="italic">Meatus urinarius</hi>, to remove a <lb/>Stone which preſſed upon the Neck
          of her Bladder, <lb/>and it ſlipt paſt Recovery into her Bladder; whence, <lb/>after Three
          Years, it was taken, and on which, as on <lb/>a Centre, was bred the Stone. I have other
          Inſtances <lb/>of the ſame, where an extraneous Body, paſſed into <lb/>the Bladder, hath
          proved as a Centre to attract or have <lb/>affixed to it ſuch Matter. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As to the Cure, Dilution ſeems to be the beſt. <lb/>The Brewer was cured by drinking
          plentifully of ſoft <lb/>Liquors, which he often poured down; and twice a <lb/>Week he
          took the purging Waters. You may gueſs <lb/>my Opinion to be, that the leſs is generated
          of this <lb/>Matter, and the leſs Time it remains in either Kid- <lb/>neys, <hi
            rend="italic">Ureters</hi>, or Bladder, the Diſeaſe will be miti- <lb/>gated, and, I
          hope, cured. I believe <hi rend="italic">Bath-waters</hi>
          <lb/>drank warm, Mallow-tea, Linſeed-tea, Oil of ſweet <lb/>Almonds, Syrup of
          Marſhmallows, little and often <lb/>taken, with Baths of emollient Herbs, may be of great
          <lb/>Uſe; and perhaps moderate Exerciſe may help them <lb/>off. Opiates, in exceſſive
          Pain, are neceſſary; and <lb/>now-and-then Bleeding, to take off the Inflamma- <lb/>tions
          that muſt of neceſſity attend ſuch a Diſtemper. <lb/>I alſo think, that ſome Balſamics,
          ſuch as <hi rend="italic">Locatelli</hi>'s <lb/><hi rend="italic">Balſam</hi>, may be
          uſeful; and perhaps, with the emol- <pb n="705"/>
          <lb/>lient Method, take off that Diſpoſition in the Kid- <lb/>neys, which produces this
          uncommon Diſtemper. <lb/>The Pains in her Feet, and about her, ſeem not to <lb/>have any
          relation to this Diſtemper; and I am of <lb/>Opinion, that violent Diuretics or Exerciſe
          will rather <lb/>hurt than help her. Thus you have my Thoughts on <lb/>this very
          extraordinary Caſe; and I ſhall be very glad <lb/>to hear of the Iſſue of it, and rejoice
          if I can be uſe- <lb/>ful to you in this or any thing elſe, leaving to you <lb/>the
          Determination of what you think reaſonable. I <lb/>beg Pardon for this haſty caſting
          together ſome things, <lb/>which, if I had more Time, ſhould be put into better <lb/>Order
          by </p>
        <signed rend="italic align-right">
          <lb/>Your moſt obedient, <lb/>and moſt humble Servant, <lb/><hi rend="roman size(1.2)"
            >Hans Sloane. </hi>
        </signed>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
