<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Chandler and Malfalguerat: The Case of Grace Lowdell, Aged about Sixty
          Years, Who Had an Extraordinary Tumour</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>John Chandler</persName>
              <persName>Mizael Malfalguerat</persName>
            </author>
            <title>The Case of Grace Lowdell, Aged about Sixty Years, Who Had an Extraordinary
              Tumour on Her Thigh; Communicated by John Chandler, F. R. S. from Mr. Mizael
              Malfalguerat, Surgeon, at St. Edmund's-Bury</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for T. Woodward, and C. Davis, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn; Printers to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1739-1741</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">41</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">365-367</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110112667</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1739.0064</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT41_0365">
    <body>
      <pb n="365"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXII.</hi> The Caſe of <hi rend="roman">Grace Lowdell</hi>, aged
        <lb/>about Sixty Years, who had an extraordinary <lb/><hi rend="roman">Tumour</hi> on her
        Thigh; communicated by <lb/><hi rend="roman">John Chandler, F. R. S.</hi> from Mr. <hi
          rend="roman">Mizael Mal- <lb/>falguerat</hi>, Surgeon, at <hi rend="roman">St.
          Edmund's-bury</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">G</hi><hi rend="italic">RACE Lowdell</hi>, a poor old Woman of the
        <lb/>Pariſh of <hi rend="italic">St. James</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Bury St. Edmund's,
          Suf- <lb/>folk</hi>, being naturally of a groſs, fat, and relaxed <lb/>Conſtitution, and
        conſtantly given to the drinking <lb/>of ſtrong Liquors; and conſequently labouring for
        <lb/>many Years under an ill Habit of Body, ſuch as the <lb/>Rheumatiſm, which had cauſed
        Contraction of ſome <lb/>of her Fingers, with ſome nervous Affections in her <lb/>Head,
        often cauſing ſome little Fits of Vertigo, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        <lb/>And though ſhe had formerly ſome Child-bearing <lb/>Weakneſs, <hi rend="italic"
          >viz.</hi> a <hi rend="italic">Procidentia Uteri</hi>, yet there could <lb/>not be found
        any other ſcrophulous Symptoms, than <lb/>that ſhe obſerved, when about Thirty Years of Age,
        <lb/>ſoon after her Delivery of a Son, a little hard Swell- <lb/>ing on the Muſcle <hi
          rend="italic">Biceps</hi>, and poſterior, inferior and <lb/>external lateral Part of the
        Thigh, a little above the <lb/>Ham, without her knowing any manifeſt Occaſion <lb/>for it;
        which at firſt went on ſlowly, but after pro- <lb/>ceeding more quickly, and the older it
        grew, it ſtill <lb/>came on the faſter, until it increaſed to the Bulk of <lb/>near a Foot
        in Circumference, being ſomewhat of a <lb/>globulous and a little longiſh Figure from its
        Baſis, <lb/>which was lax, like a Peduncle, or Stalk, and about <lb/>half the Circumference
        of the Tumour, like a Neck <lb/>to the Head of a Child hanging down. </p>
      <pb n="366"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From the firſt Appearance of this Tumour to the <lb/>Exciſion of it, there were more
        than Thirty Years: <lb/>She had exceſſive Pains and Uneaſineſs in it, and at <lb/>laſt its
        Bulk and Weight had in ſome meaſure inter- <lb/>cepted the Nouriſhment to it, ſo that an
        Ulcer had <lb/>affected the inferior Part of it, very putrid and ſinuous, <lb/>of about Six
        Months ſtanding. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This Excreſcence was of the natural Colour of the <lb/>Skin, and was for the moſt part
        of a pinquedinous <lb/>Subſtance; the Centre and Baſis being an <hi rend="italic"
          >Atheroma</hi>, <lb/>but more ſcirrhous than common. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This Excreſcence, having grown ſo big, was not <lb/>contained in a manifeſt <hi
          rend="italic">Cyſtis</hi>, but had ſome large <lb/>Circumvolutions of Fat adherent to its
        common Te- <lb/>guments, as was obſerved after the Exciſion of it, <lb/>when it was ſoon
        conveyed away; ſo that, through <lb/>Inadvertency, we did not weigh it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>My Deſign in this Caſe was to have made a total <lb/>Extirpation of this Excreſcence;
        but by reaſon of its <lb/>lying with large Veſſels, and amongſt the Tendons <lb/>of the
        Muſcles, I was content (as Dr. <hi rend="italic">Turner</hi> adviſes <lb/>in ſuch Caſes) <q
          rend="diple quotes">To level it, the beſt we can, by <lb/>Eſcharotics, ſtill repeated as
          the Sloughs throw off; <lb/>till we have conſumed as much of the Gland or <lb/>Subſtance,
          and gone as deep, as may be ſafely ad- <lb/>ventured; when probably ſome powerful Deſic-
          <lb/>cative may induce a <hi rend="italic">Cicatrix</hi>, which may ſo tie <lb/>the
          Remains, as to create no farther Trouble. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This Tumour had been ſhewn to moſt of the Phy- <lb/>ſicians and Surgeons hereabouts,
        ſome of no leſs <lb/>Skill than Note, who ſeemed to approve of the Ope- <lb/>ration:
        Therefore, <hi rend="italic">July</hi> the 7th 1735. I made a Li- <lb/>gature about the
        Baſis of it, with a Slip-knot, by <pb n="367"/>
        <lb/>which I gradually conſtringed it once or twice a Day, <lb/>as the Patient could ſuffer
        it, without cauſing any ill <lb/>Symptoms, till the 17th of the ſame Month, when <lb/>ſhe
        was taken with ſtrong Convulſions, a ſlow Fever, <lb/>Syncope, her Teeth ſet in her Head,
        and a Loſs of her <lb/>Senſes, which laſted that whole Day, and the Night <lb/>following;
        from which time I did no more con- <lb/>ſtringe the Tumour, preſcribed Cordials, volatile
        <lb/>Drops, a purging <hi rend="italic">Enema</hi>, and a paregoric Draught at <lb/>Night,
        which had ſo good an Effect, that by the next <lb/>Day ſhe was much recoverd, and came to
        her Senſes. <lb/>The Ligature began to make a Separation in the Neck <lb/>of this
        preternatural ſprouting Excreſcence; and on <lb/>the 20th, in the Preſence only of one in
        the Pro- <lb/>feſſion, having all my Apparatus before me, I extir- <lb/>pated the whole
        outward Tumour without any great <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hæmorrhage</hi>. I was induced to
        uſe the Ligature, in <lb/>order to prevent the too great Effuſion of Blood, <lb/>which might
        otherwiſe happen; thinking it not very <lb/>ſafe to make a Ligature of the Body of ſo large
        an <lb/>Artery as is in the Ham, for fear of intercepting after- <lb/>wards the Nouriſhment
        to the Leg, as happens often <lb/>after the Operation of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Aneuriſma</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Remains, though ſordid at firſt, by a peculiar <lb/>Method of Dreſſing, and proper
        Applications of ſtrong <lb/>Digeſtives, Deterſives, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> cleanſed,
        and the Ulcer <lb/>ſoon digeſted, the Subſtance came even to the Skin, <lb/>and, <hi
          rend="italic">September</hi> the 21ſt, it was all perfectly cured, <lb/>without any
        Hardneſs, or any Inconvenience to her <lb/>walking, and is like to remain always ſo. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
