<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Huxham: Concerning an Extraordinary Venereal Case</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>John Huxham</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Letter from John Huxham, M. D. F. R. S. to Thomas Stack, M. D. F. R. S.
              concerning an Extraordinary Venereal Case</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for T. Woodward, and C. Davis, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn; Printers to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1739-1741</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">41</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">667-672</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110112667</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1739.0115</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT41_0667">
    <body>
      <pb n="667"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">II.</hi> A Letter from <hi rend="roman">John Huxham</hi>, M. D.
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">F. R. S.</hi> to <hi rend="roman">Thomas Stack</hi>, M. D. <hi
          rend="roman">F. R. S.</hi>
        <lb/>concerning an Extraordinary <hi rend="roman">Venereal Caſe</hi>. </head>
      <salute rend="italic space indent">
        <lb/>Dear SIR, </salute>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> Have now ſent you the uncommon Venereal Caſe <lb/>I promiſed in
        my laſt, which, I think, hath ſome- <lb/>thing very remarkable in it, and ſeems very much to
        <lb/>confirm the Great <hi rend="italic">Boerhaave</hi>'s Opinion, that the Seat <lb/>of the
          <hi rend="italic">Lues Venerea</hi> is in the <hi rend="italic">Membrana adipoſa</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">R.B.</hi> aged about 27, of a bilious, dry Conſti- <lb/>tution,
        had, for ſome Years before his Death, contracted <lb/>a virulent <hi rend="italic"
          >Gonorrhœa</hi>, which was ſcarce well cured <lb/>before he got a Second, and at length a
        Third.— <lb/>To complete his Miſery, being in the Fleet at <hi rend="italic">Porto-
          <lb/>bello</hi>, he had frequent impure Converſation with <lb/>ſome of the <hi
          rend="italic">Negro</hi> Huſſies (who probably laboured <lb/>under the worſt Species of
          <hi rend="italic">Pox</hi>, called the <hi rend="italic">Yaws</hi>). </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He returned with a very troubleſome Itching all <lb/>over him, though no Puſtules
        appeared; was much <lb/>thinner than uſual, and had a horrible ſtinking Breath, <lb/>and
        ſpit frequently a foul, corrupt Matter.—As he <lb/>had no Running, Ulcer, <hi rend="italic"
          >Bubo</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Nodes</hi>, he thought <lb/>all ſafe.—But not many Days
        after his Arrival at <lb/><hi rend="italic">Portſmouth</hi>, <hi rend="italic">poſt impurum
          cum impurâ Coitum</hi>, a <lb/>violent Green-coloured <hi rend="italic">Gonorrhœa</hi>
        appears.—For <pb n="668"/>
        <lb/>this he put himſelf under the Care of a Surgeon, <lb/>who, after much Pain to no
        Purpoſe, endeavoured <lb/>to ſalivate him, but that alſo in vain.—The <hi rend="italic"
          >Gonor- <lb/>rhœa</hi> indeed was much abated, but a <hi rend="italic">Bubo</hi> was riſen
        <lb/>in his Left Groin, and ſome ſmall verrucoſe Eruptions <lb/>about the <hi rend="italic"
          >Anus</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In this Condition he returned here, and put himſelf <lb/>under the Hands of Mr. <hi
          rend="italic">St—</hi>, an ingenious Sur- <lb/>geon, who endeavoured to bring the <hi
          rend="italic">Bubo</hi> to Sup- <lb/>puration, but without Effect; for it ſoon receded,
        <lb/>and forthwith violent Pains ſeized him in and about <lb/>the Fundament, which ſoon
        produced an exceeding <lb/>painful <hi rend="italic">Phyma</hi> near the Verge of the <hi
          rend="italic">Anus </hi>on the <lb/>Left Side. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I was conſulted now, and adviſed to bring it to <lb/>Suppuration as ſoon as poſſible,
        which was done in <lb/>Two Days; from whence iſſued abundance of puru- <lb/>lent bloody
        Matter.—In a Day or two more, another <lb/>appeared on the other Side, which ſoon vented the
        like <lb/>Matter.—The <hi rend="italic">Verrucæ</hi> alſo now grew more nu- <lb/>merous and
        larger, and many puſtular and ſcaly Erup- <lb/>tion appeared all over him. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I ordered him to be fumigated with <hi rend="italic">Cinnabar</hi>, and <lb/>adviſed
        him to enter on a Salivation forthwith.— <lb/>But, antecedent to it, as his Humours were
        exceed- <lb/>ingly tough and acrid, I put him on a Courſe of very <lb/>plentiful Dilution;
        and this the rather, as he was natu- <lb/>rally of a dry and hot Conſtitution, and beſides
        had <lb/>lately been roaſted in the <hi rend="italic">Torrid Zone</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I began, as uſual, by giving him <hi rend="italic">Calomel</hi>; which, <lb/>though it
        neither purged or vomited him, yet, after <lb/>having taken Five Drachms, produced no Degree
        of <lb/>Salivation, nor did it make his Gums ſore.—How- <lb/>ever, it brought on his <hi
          rend="italic">Gonorrhœa</hi> again: I then <pb n="669"/>
        <lb/>ordered him once and again, Eight or Ten Grains of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Turbith
          mineral</hi>, which ſcarce puked him, and gave <lb/>him only Two or Three Stools.—I now
        found, <lb/>indeed, that <hi rend="italic">Mercury</hi> and he, as well as <hi rend="italic"
          >Venus</hi>, had <lb/>been old Acquaintance; ſo I greatly augmented the <lb/>Doſe of the
          <hi rend="italic">Mercurials</hi>, ordering immenſe Quan- <lb/>tities of thin watery
        Diluents: Notwithſtanding this, <lb/>there was very little Operation by Stool, and ſcarce
        <lb/>any by Salivation. Though his Gums and <hi rend="italic">Fauces</hi>
        <lb/>were very ſore and ſwoln, he ſcarce ſpit One Pint <lb/>in 24 Hours, and that
        exceſſively tough and fetid.— <lb/>Even under this ſtrong <hi rend="italic">Mercurial</hi>
        Courſe, the puſtular <lb/>and leprous Eruptions increaſed daily, ſo as to cover <lb/>almoſt
        his whole Body, nay his very Face. His Hands <lb/>and Feet were vaſtly ſwoln, as in an <hi
          rend="italic">Elephantiaſis</hi>, <lb/>with horrid Fiſſures, from whence iſſued a very
        ſtink- <lb/>ing ichoroſe Matter. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I was quite confounded at this dreadful Face of <lb/>Things, and ſeriouſly bethought me
        what further <lb/>Method could be taken againſt ſo terrible an Enemy. <lb/>—I had recourſe
        to a warm emollient Bath, in which <lb/>his whole Body was immerged; after which he was
        <lb/>well anointed with a ſtrong <hi rend="italic">Mercurial</hi> Ointment.— <lb/>This was
        done for Three Days ſucceſſively: Not- <lb/>withſtanding which, though his Chaps grew
        exceed- <lb/>ing ſore, and his Throat ſo much inflamed and pained, <lb/>that he ſwallowed
        with extreme Difficulty what he <lb/>ſucked through a Pipe or Quill, yet the Spitting was
        <lb/>very little increaſed, and as tough as ever: Nor did <lb/>the fiſtulous Ulcers ſeem in
        the leaſt diſpoſed to heal <lb/>up, but vented a vaſt Deal of ſtinking, oily, ſanious
        <lb/>Matter; nay, even new ones broke out under each <lb/><hi rend="italic">Axilla</hi>, and
        a very large <hi rend="italic">Phyma</hi> roſe on the <hi rend="italic">Coccyx</hi>, <pb
          n="670"/>
        <lb/>which ſoon diſcharged the ſame kind of virulent <lb/>Matter; though we found the Bone,
        and even the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Perioſteum</hi>, quite ſound and untouched. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Scales were now grown ſo hard and ſtiff, that <lb/>he could ſcarce bend a Limb, or
        Finger: Moreover, <lb/>Abundance of Ulcers, from whence flowed great <lb/>Quantities of
        greaſy, purulent, and ſomewhat bloody <lb/>Matter, were broke out in his Thighs and
        Buttocks. <lb/>—A very large Tumour was alſo riſen in his Right <lb/>Breaſt, and ſoon after
        on the Left, voiding prodi- <lb/>gious Quantities of the ſame kind of Matter. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It was obſervable, that where-ever any of theſe <lb/>Ulcers appeared, they ran only
        under the Skin, being <lb/>intirely ſeated in, and feeding on, the <hi rend="italic"
          >Membrana <lb/>adipoſa</hi>; ſo that the Muſcles and Tendons underneath <lb/>appeared as
        fair and florid as in the moſt healthy <lb/>Conſtitution. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I now unfortunately found, though too late, there <lb/>was nothing to be done by <hi
          rend="italic">Mercury</hi> in any Form; and <lb/>therefore determined to run it off, and
        try the <hi rend="italic">Guaia- <lb/>cum</hi> Method and Sweating, ſo much recommended
        <lb/>of old (and in ſome Caſes ſo juſtly) by Sir <hi rend="italic">Ulric <lb/>Hutton</hi>,
        and others; at the ſame time keeping up a <lb/>moſt plentiful Dilution, attempting withal to
        detach <lb/>the ſcaly <hi rend="italic">Cuticule</hi> by continued emollient Baths,
        <lb/>which at the ſame time alſo would partly act by <lb/>Dilution.—By this means the Scales
        came off apace, <lb/>juſt in the manner uſual in the confluent <hi rend="italic"
          >Small-pox</hi>; <lb/>only the <hi rend="italic">Exuviæ</hi> were here much larger,
        ſeveral <lb/>being above Four or Five Inches over.—In about a <lb/>Week's time, this Coat of
        Mail was pretty well <lb/>cleared off, and his Breath, from the moſt horribly <lb/>nauſeous
        I ever ſmelt, became as ſweet as that of an <pb n="671"/>
        <lb/>Infant. Nor was the Matter ſpit, though ſtill very <lb/>viſcid, any way fetid: For the
          <hi rend="italic">Mercury</hi> was pretty <lb/>well run down by lenient Cathartics, and
        the Sloughs <lb/>of his Mouth caſt off. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He was now become exceedingly emaciated: Where- <lb/>fore I ordered him plentiful
        liquid Nouriſhment <lb/>with Vipers, and large Dilution, avoiding every <lb/>thing that was
        in the leaſt groſs or fatty.—But with <lb/>all this he ſtill kept to his Three Pints of
        ſtrong <lb/>Decoction of <hi rend="italic">Guaiacum</hi> every 24 Hours, ſweating at
        <lb/>leaſt Two or Three of them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Under this Method I conceived ſome Hopes of his <lb/>Recovery, as he ſeemed now to gain
        ſome ſmall <lb/>Degree of Strength and Spirit; but ſtill his Ulcers <lb/>rather increaſed
        than abated, and continually diſ- <lb/>charged a vaſt Quantity of Matter, though by no
        <lb/>means ſo thick, putrid, or bloody;—and, in- <lb/>deed, in a moſt profuſe Manner from
        under each <lb/><hi rend="italic">Axilla</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But, what is vaſtly ſurpriſing, notwithſtanding all <lb/>the paſt Method and Medicines,
        Two very large <lb/>Chancres now appeared on the <hi rend="italic">Glans Penis</hi>, and a
        <lb/>very conſiderable <hi rend="italic">Bubo</hi> in the Left Groin.—A trou- <lb/>bleſome
        Cough ſoon alſo ſeized him, with Short- <lb/>neſs of Breath; and he began to expectorate a
        puru- <lb/>lent, and ſometimes bloody kind of Matter.—As <lb/>the whole <hi rend="italic"
          >Membrana adipoſa</hi> without, had been con- <lb/>ſumed by the Diſeaſe, it was now
        falling on that <lb/>Part of it that inveſted the more vital Parts.—But <lb/>Nature could
        ſupport no longer.—He died in the <lb/>extremeſt Degree of a pocky Conſumption.—But <lb/>not
        one ſingle Bone of any Part of his Body appeared <pb n="672"/>
        <lb/>to be touched, though he died with near 40 Ulcers <lb/>upon him. </p>
      <salute rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>Dear SIR, </salute>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <dateline rend="space size(0.7)">Plymouth, <lb/>Oct. 16. 1739. </dateline>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <signed rend="italic">Your humble Servant, <lb/><hi rend="roman size(1.2)">John Huxham. </hi>
      </signed>
      <cb n="1 2"/>
      <postscript rend="space">
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In another Letter dated at <hi rend="italic">Plymouth, Nov.</hi> 30. <lb/>1739. Dr.
            <hi rend="italic">Huxham</hi> ſays, <q rend="diple quotes">We have had a very
            <lb/>tempeſtuous Seaſon for ſeveral Days paſt, though <lb/>now fair; the <hi
              rend="italic">Mercury</hi> lower [28.1 Inches] than <lb/>I have known it for ſome
            Years, and the Tides <lb/>exceſſively high. </q>
        </p>
      </postscript>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
