<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - De Superville and Zollman: Some Reflections on Generation, and on
          Monsters</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Daniel De Superville</persName>
              <persName>Phil. Hen. Zollman</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Some Reflections on Generation, and on Monsters, With a Description of Some
              Particular Monsters: By Daniel de Superville, Privy Counsellor and Chief Physician to
              His Most Serene Highness the Margrave of Brandenburg-Bareith, President of the College
              of Physicians, Director of the Mines and of All Medicinal Affairs in the Margravite,
              Member of the Imperial Academy Naturae Curiosorum, and of the Royal Society of Berlin.
              Translated from the French by Phil. Hen. Zollman, F. R. S. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for T. Woodward, and C. Davis, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn; Printers to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1739-1741</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">41</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">294-307</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110112667</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1739.0044</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT41_0294">
    <body>
      <pb n="294"/>
      <head rend="hanging italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">II.</hi> Some Reflections on <hi rend="roman">Generation</hi>, and on
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">Monſters</hi>, with a Deſcription of ſome par- <lb/>ticular <hi
          rend="roman">Monſters</hi>: By <hi rend="roman">Daniel de Superville</hi>, <lb/>Privy
        Counſellor and chief Phyſician to his <lb/>moſt Serene Highneſs the Margrave of <lb/><hi
          rend="roman">Brandenburg-Bareith</hi>, Preſident of the Col- <lb/>lege of Phyſicians,
        Director of the Mines <lb/>and of all Medicinal Affairs in the Mar- <lb/>gravite, Member of
        the Imperial Academy <lb/><hi rend="roman">Naturæ Curioſorum</hi>, and of the Royal So-
        <lb/>ciety of <hi rend="roman">Berlin</hi>. Tranſlated from the <hi rend="roman">French</hi>
        <lb/>by <hi rend="roman">Phil. Hen. Zollman</hi>, F. R. S. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>T cannot be denied, that ſince the middle of laſt <lb/>Century
        to this Time, very important Diſcoveries <lb/>have been made in Natural Hiſtory: However,
        thoſe <lb/>Diſcoveries are very inſignificant, in compariſon to <lb/>what is ſtill concealed
        from us. We have ſome <pb n="295"/>
        <lb/>Knowledge of the coarſer ſort of Nature's Opera- <lb/>tions, but the Niceties, the
        Particulars of them, <lb/>eſcape us. If we endeavour to puſh our Knowledge <lb/>ſo far, we
        find ourſelves ſurrounded with Clouds, <lb/>we grope in the dark, and it is very difficult,
        if not <lb/>impoſſible, to catch Nature in the Fact. It even <lb/>ſeems, we have had better
        Succeſs in determining <lb/>what Nature does not do, or cannot do, than in <lb/>ſpecifying
        what ſhe actually does. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Human Body is a Compound of Springs, <lb/>which produce very regular Motions: Yet
        theſe <lb/>Springs themſelves we do not know but very ſuper- <lb/>ficially, and are far from
        knowing how thoſe Mo- <lb/>tions are produced. We know, that we are born, <lb/>that we
        exiſt; but how came we to this Exiſtence? <lb/>How were we produced? The Generation of Man-
        <lb/>kind and of Animals is one of thoſe <hi rend="italic">Phænomena</hi>, <lb/>where
        innumerable Experiments have not been of ſo <lb/>great Uſe, as they are elſe in other <hi
          rend="italic">Phænomena</hi> of <lb/>Natural Philoſophy, for diſcovering their moſt ſecret
        <lb/>Springs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is ſtill a Diſpute, whether the Male or the Fe- <lb/>male contributes moſt towards
        Generation. It is <lb/>certain, that for the Generation of Mankind there <lb/>muſt be a Male
        and a Female, and it is the ſame thing <lb/>with regard to that of Brutes. There is all the
        Rea- <lb/>ſon in the World to believe, that what is written <lb/>about Hermaphrodites, and
        about thoſe Animals <lb/>which, being endued with the Advantage of the two <lb/>Sexes,
        produce alone their Like, has not been exa- <lb/>mined with all the neceſſary Attention and
        Exactneſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Semen</hi> of Man, which is certainly a moſt <lb/>neceſſary Agent
        for Generation, becauſe it has been <pb n="296"/>
        <lb/>obſerved, that thoſe who have none, or do not eject <lb/>it according to certain
        requiſite Conditions, are not <lb/>fit for multiplying their own Species: This <hi
          rend="italic">Semen</hi>, <lb/>I ſay, is a Liquid full of ſmall Worms. It would <lb/>be
        abſurd to deny it: All exact Obſervators have taken <lb/>Notice of them, and offered to ſhew
        them to the <lb/>incredulous. I have obſerved theſe <hi rend="italic">Animalcula</hi> in
        <lb/>human <hi rend="italic">Semen</hi>, in that of ſeveral Quadrupedes, and <lb/>in that of
        ſome Birds. I have obſerved, that the <lb/>Figure of theſe <hi rend="italic"
        >Animalcula</hi>, as to Birds, was dif- <lb/>ferent from that of other Animals. I have
        preſerved <lb/><hi rend="italic">Animalcula</hi> in a proportionable Warmth alive for
        <lb/>ſeveral Hours; I have obſerved their Strength and <lb/>Livelineſs to leſſen by Degrees,
        and at laſt intirely <lb/>to ceaſe; and I have obſerved them dead, not ſwim- <lb/>ing any
        longer, but always ſinking to the Bottom. <lb/>I have obſerved in the <hi rend="italic"
          >Semen</hi> of Men, who had a <lb/>virulent <hi rend="italic">Gonorrhæa</hi> upon them,
        thoſe <hi rend="italic">Animalcula</hi> to <lb/>be without Motion, and like dead. I might
        inlarge <lb/>upon the Particulars of a greater Number of Obſer- <lb/>vations; they all prove
        the real and conſtant Exiſtence <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Animalcula</hi> in the <hi
          rend="italic">Semen</hi> of Males. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe Worms, according to ſome Natural Philo- <lb/>ſophers, are true <hi rend="italic"
          >Embryoes</hi>. As ſoon as an <hi rend="italic">Animal- <lb/>culum</hi> has entered into
        an Egg, the Female who <lb/>carries the Egg in her Body, has conceived; ſhe <lb/>harbours
        it, nouriſhes it, and contributes towards <lb/>the ſhaping of it, until it becomes an
        Animal, too <lb/>big to be any longer contained in ſo ſmall a Place, <lb/>and ſtrong enough
        to bear the Air. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>According to other Natural Philoſophers, the Eggs <lb/>that are in the <hi
          rend="italic">Ovaria</hi> of the Females, contain the <lb/>Image, the Type, the Picture of
        the <hi rend="italic">Embryo</hi>; and the <pb n="297"/>
        <lb/>ſubtile Vapour of the Male <hi rend="italic">Semen</hi>, or rather the <lb/>occult
        Quality of that Seed, impregnating one of <lb/>thoſe Eggs, immediately fixes that Image, and
        makes <lb/>a real <hi rend="italic">Embryo</hi> of it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe latter intirely deny the Exiſtence of <hi rend="italic">Ani- <lb/>malcula</hi> in
        the Seed, becauſe they have not ſeen <lb/>them; and if they are ſhewn them, they maintain
        <lb/>that they are foreign Beings; or, that they are a par- <lb/>ticular ſort of Worms, who
        form a ſeparate Claſs <lb/>among thoſe Inſects: That <hi rend="sc">God</hi> created them to
        exiſt <lb/>in the Seminal Liquid, that they keep in it as in their <lb/>Element, that they
        multiply there, and that they con- <lb/>tinue there and die, ſuch as we obſerve them by the
        <lb/>Microſcope. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I do not pretend to decide, that the former are <lb/>intirely in the Right; they
        maintain an Hypotheſis <lb/>founded on ſome Probabilities. Alas! who can <lb/>hope upon ſo
        dark and hidden a Subject to find a <lb/>demonſtrated Syſtem? The ſecond Opinion ſeems
        <lb/>to me unwarrantable: It is founded upon Words <lb/>which have no Reality. How can one
        form to him- <lb/>ſelf the Idea of a Vapour extremely ſubtile and active, <lb/>that ſhall
        have the Faculty of giving Life and Mo- <lb/>tion to an Image, to a Type, in ſhort, to a
        thing <lb/>that was not real? The Pre-exiſtence of the <hi rend="italic">Em- <lb/>bryo</hi>
        in the Egg can by no means be demonſtrated: <lb/>Even by the Help of the beſt Microſcopes,
        there is <lb/>never any thing found in thoſe Eggs, but a clear and <lb/>limpid Liquid. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I keep among my Curioſities ſix oſſified Eggs, <lb/>which I found in the <hi
          rend="italic">Ovaria</hi> of a Woman who <lb/>died at the Age of Sixty. They are not all
        of the <lb/>ſame Bigneſs. I broke two of them, and examined <pb n="298"/>
        <lb/>their internal Structure with all the Attention ima- <lb/>ginable; but found nothing
        there except oſſeous <lb/>Fibres, iſſuing from the Centre towards the Super- <lb/>ficies;
        there was not the leaſt Appearance of an <hi rend="italic">Embryo</hi>, <lb/>nor of its
        Image. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>One muſt have an Imagination extremely prepoſ- <lb/>ſeſſed to perſuade one's ſelf, that
        there is an organized <lb/>Body in the Liquid contained in thoſe Eggs: Or, it <lb/>requires
        a very particular Natural Philoſophy, to pre- <lb/>tend to demonſtrate, that a bare Vapour
        (more ſubtile <lb/>than any the moſt ſpirituous Vapours we know of) <lb/>could, by its
        ſimple Touch or Friction, produce an <lb/>organized Body, where there was none. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Generation of Mankind as well as of Brutes <lb/>by the means of the <hi
          rend="italic">Animalcula</hi>, which are obſerved <lb/>in the <hi rend="italic">Semen</hi>
        of Males, ſeems more analogous to all <lb/>that we ſee Nature do for the Production and
        Multi- <lb/>plication of the Vegetables. There needs no Imagin- <lb/>ation for forming to
        one's ſelf an Idea of it. Each <lb/><hi rend="italic">Animalculum</hi> is an <hi
          rend="italic">Embryo</hi>, is a ſmall Animal of the <lb/>ſame Species with that which
        harbours it: As ſoon as <lb/>it finds itſelf diſengaged from the Confinement in <lb/>which
        it was, and in a Place where it meets with a <lb/>Humour proper for its Vegetation and
        Expanſion, it <lb/>takes Root there, it ſwells like a Corn newly put <lb/>into the Earth, it
        ſpreads itſelf, its Members ſhape <lb/>themſelves, and by degrees take more Strength and
        <lb/>Conſiſtence, its Parts grow longer, and diſentangle <lb/>themſelves, as it were, from
        all thoſe Plaits and Folds <lb/>in which they were confined before, and the <hi
          rend="italic">Embryo</hi>
        <lb/>becomes a <hi rend="italic">Fœtus</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I own, that the immenſe Number of <hi rend="italic">Animalcula</hi>, <lb/>which are
        obſerved in the Seminal Liquid of Man, <pb n="299"/>
        <lb/>ſeems to oblige one to reject this Hypotheſis, and <lb/>particularly this Opinion, that
        every <hi rend="italic">Animalculum</hi>
        <lb/>is an <hi rend="italic">Embryo</hi>. For it is certain, that in every Man <lb/>there
        would be enough of them to people a vaſt <lb/>Country, and of all that immenſe Quantity
        there are <lb/>but a few that come to any thing. And ſo, there <lb/>you have Millions of
        little Men, created never to <lb/>exiſt; which ſeems directly contrary to the wiſe In-
        <lb/>tentions of the <hi rend="sc">Creator</hi>, who, in all Likelihood, <lb/>made nothing
        in vain. But <hi rend="italic">Teleology</hi> is one of thoſe <lb/>Parts of Philoſophy, in
        which there has been but <lb/>little Progreſs made, wherein one reaſons only by
        <lb/>Conjecture, nor can demonſtrate any thing other- <lb/>wiſe than <hi rend="italic">à
          poſteriori</hi>. Who dares preſume ſo far as <lb/>to pretend to penetrate into all the
        Deſigns of the <lb/><hi rend="sc">Almighty</hi>, and into the divers Ends He has pro-
        <lb/>poſed to Himſelf in the Creation of the Univerſe? <lb/>Beſides, it is certain, that
        half of Mankind periſh, <lb/>before they come to the Age of one Year, that is to <lb/>ſay,
        before they can know themſelves, before they <lb/>can anſwer the Ends <hi rend="sc">God</hi>
        propoſed to Himſelf when <lb/>He created them. Would one ſay therefore, that <lb/>their
        Exiſtence was uſeleſs? But moreover, this <lb/>ſeemingly uſeleſs Quantity of <hi
          rend="italic">Animalcula</hi> equally <lb/>affords an Argument againſt the Hypotheſis of
        thoſe, <lb/>who believe the <hi rend="italic">Embryo</hi> is in the Egg. One cannot
        <lb/>maintain, that all the Eggs in the <hi rend="italic">Ovaria</hi> are fruitful. <lb/>And
        ſo there we have equally an immenſe Quantity <lb/>of Types of <hi rend="italic"
          >Embryo's</hi> created for nothing, and abſo- <lb/>lutely uſeleſs; and it will follow from
        both Hypo- <lb/>theſes, that <hi rend="sc">God</hi> might have ſaved Himſelf the Trouble
        <lb/>of creating ſo prodigious a Quantity of Creatures in <lb/>order to precipitate them
        into nothing. But who <pb n="300"/>
        <lb/>dares ſay, that the creating ſo many Millions of <lb/>Creatures more has coſt Him any
        more Pains? And <lb/>by what could one prove, that all thoſe <hi rend="italic"
          >Animalcula</hi>, <lb/>which do not come to the State of a <hi rend="italic">Fœtus</hi>,
        are <lb/>annihilated? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Hypotheſis of the Generation by <hi rend="italic">Animalcula</hi>
        <lb/>in the Seminal Liquid of Man, appears ſupported <lb/>and confirmed by ſeveral
        Experiments. <hi rend="italic">Leewenhoek</hi>
        <lb/>has already obſerved, that a wild Male Rabbet, and a <lb/>tame and white Female,
        produce young ones intirely <lb/>reſembling the Father; and that it is a Cheat very
        <lb/>common in <hi rend="italic">Holland</hi> to ſell that ſort of Rabbets, for <lb/>wild
        ones, and that it is only by the Taſte one can <lb/>find out the Truth. There is among
        domeſtic Ani- <lb/>mals a ſort of Poultry without Tails, and another <lb/>ſort with the
        Feathers turned upwards; if a Cock <lb/>without a Tail is put among ordinary Hens, or a
        <lb/>Cock with the Feathers upwards, all the Chicks will <lb/>prove like the Cock: The ſame
        Experiment may be <lb/>made with Pigeons, with Canary-Birds, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>—
        A <lb/>Mule ſprung from an Aſs and a Mare, reſembles more <lb/>to the Aſs than to the Mare,
        whereas a Mule coming <lb/>from a Horſe and a She-Aſs, has more of the Horſe's <lb/>Nature.
        All this proves in ſome meaſure, that the <lb/>Male furniſhes the moſt eſſential Part in the
        Genera- <lb/>tion, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Embryo</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By the ſame Hypotheſis ſome <hi rend="italic">Phænomena</hi> obſerved <lb/>in
        Generation, may be more eaſily accounted for. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hippocrates</hi>
        believed that the Difference of the Sexes <lb/>depended on certain Diſpoſitions in the Seeds
        of the <lb/>Male and the Female; that when the Male was the <lb/>moſt vigorous in the
        Copulation, they begot Males; <lb/>but if the Seed of the Female prevailed, they pro- <pb
          n="301"/>
        <lb/>duced only Females. This Opinion, abſurd as it <lb/>is, has been followed and
        maintained by ſeveral cele- <lb/>brated Phyſicians. How can one believe, that a little
        <lb/>more of I do not know what, (for they do not <lb/>determine wherein the more or leſs of
        the Virtue in <lb/>the Seed muſt conſiſt) a little more Activity, a little <lb/>more
        Spirituouſneſs, ſhould compoſe, ſhould deter- <lb/>mine any Organization? It is more natural
        to be- <lb/>lieve, that every <hi rend="italic">Animalculum</hi> has already the Sex <lb/>it
        is to have when it comes into the World. It has <lb/>been diſputed Tooth and Nail, to
        determine the <lb/>Time when the <hi rend="italic">Fœtus</hi> becomes animated, and to
        <lb/>know from whence and how its Soul enters into its <lb/>Body. According to the moſt
        general Opinion, there <lb/>muſt be at every Conception a new Creation of a <lb/>Soul: Or,
        according to others, there is always a <lb/>Legion of created Souls fluttering about in the
        Air, <lb/>and watching the Minute for entering into a fruitful <lb/>Egg as ſoon as it is
        impregnated. What an Extra- <lb/>vagance is this! Would it be as abſurd to believe,
        <lb/>that every <hi rend="italic">Animalculum</hi> has already its Soul, which <lb/>waits
        only for the little Machine's unfolding itſelf in <lb/>order to exert its Function? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>According to the Hypotheſis of <hi rend="italic">Animalcula</hi>, one <lb/>may eaſily
        account for thoſe monſtrous Births, when <lb/>two <hi rend="italic">Fœtuſes</hi> are joined
        together, or Children and <lb/>Animals are double, in the Whole or in Part. I <lb/>keep in
        my Collection a Pig, that has eight Feet: <lb/>the two Bodies, that are ſeparated, reunite
        themſelves <lb/>by the <hi rend="italic">Spina Dorſi</hi> below the <hi rend="italic"
          >Diaphragma</hi>, and <lb/>have but one viſible Neck ſupporting a Head, bigger <lb/>than
        it ſhould be, on which there appear four Ears, <lb/>three Eyes, and the Snout ſeems double.
        I have alſo <pb n="302"/>
        <lb/>the Head of a Foal, which is double, and has three <lb/>Eyes. I have a <hi
          rend="italic">Turkiſh</hi> Duck, which is double, the <lb/>two Bodies are joined by the
        Breaſt; each Body has <lb/>two Wings, and two Legs; but they have only one <lb/>Neck with
        one Head. I keep a Chicken, which has <lb/>a ſecond Rump fixed to its Breaſt, with the two
        Legs, <lb/>and two Paws. I even have a Frog, which beſides <lb/>its four Paws, has a Fifth
        as well formed as the <lb/>others, which comes out at the Right Shoulder. The
        <lb/>Production of all theſe Monſters that are double, or <lb/>have ſuperfluous Members, may
        very well be occa- <lb/>ſioned by two <hi rend="italic">Animalcula</hi> entring into the
        ſame <lb/>Egg; they touch, they cloſe, they unite, they crowd <lb/>each other: The Parts of
        the weakeſt, being too <lb/>much crowded, cannot extend nor diſplay themſelves; <lb/>ſo they
        vaniſh, as it were, ſo much the eaſier as they <lb/>are extremely tender, and without any
        ſenſible Con- <lb/>ſiſtency. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is not more difficult to find plauſible Reaſons <lb/>for imperfect Monſters, or that
        have an odd Con- <lb/>formity, as to the Whole, or as to ſome of the Mem- <lb/>bers. I have
        the <hi rend="italic">Fœtus</hi> of a Sheep which has no <lb/>Noſe; the Part where the
        Noſtrils ſhould be, ſeems <lb/>to be flayed, and the two Eyes are there one by the <lb/>Side
        of the other. On the Forehead there is a ſmall <lb/>Trunk of about an Inch and a half long,
        and pierced <lb/>at the End by two Noſtrils. I have another, which <lb/>has but one Eye in
        the Middle of the Forehead. I <lb/>have a human <hi rend="italic">Fœtus</hi> of about ſeven
        Months, which <lb/>has no Mark of the Sex, and inſtead of the Legs <lb/>there is a Bag that
        runs to a Point, the Extremity <lb/>of which is cartilagineous: In that Bag there is a
        <lb/>Bone three Inches long, covered with a muſcular Fleſh; <pb n="303"/>
        <lb/>it is articulated with the <hi rend="italic">Os Sacrum</hi>; the <hi rend="italic">Oſſa
          inno- <lb/>minata</hi> are wanting, and below the <hi rend="italic">Anus</hi>, which is
        <lb/>upon the Middle of the <hi rend="italic">Os Sacrum</hi>, there is a ſmall <lb/>Tail
        like that of a Pig. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When I was at <hi rend="italic">Stetin</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Pomerania</hi>, about
        12 or <lb/>14 Years ago, a Midwife came to tell me, that a <lb/>Sergeant's Wife was
        delivered of three dead Children, <lb/>one of which had no Head. I immediately went,
        <lb/>and obſerved, that theſe <hi rend="italic">Fœtuſes</hi> had died at different
        <lb/>times. One began already to corrupt, and the <hi rend="italic">Epi- <lb/>dermis</hi>
        ſevered itſelf at the leaſt Touch. The Mon- <lb/>ſter without a Head was alſo already quite
        flabby, and <lb/>the third ſeemed to have died but a few Hours before. <lb/>I examined the
        Monſter; there was no Appearance <lb/>of any Head, and inſtead of the Navel there was a
        <lb/>ſmall Lump of ſpungy Fleſh of the Bigneſs of a large <lb/>Strawberry. About the <hi
          rend="italic">Secundines</hi> I found but two <lb/><hi rend="italic">Placentas</hi>, and
        two Coats; ſo that this Monſter muſt <lb/>abſolutely have been in one of thoſe Coats with
        <lb/>another <hi rend="italic">Fœtus</hi>. The Midwife was not skilful <lb/>enough to give
        me an Account of the Delivery: I <lb/>put Queſtions to the Mother, who aſſured me ſhe
        <lb/>felt one Child dying three Weeks before, and that <lb/>the laſt died the Evening
        before. I offered a good <lb/>Sum of Money to have all ſhe was delivered of, but <lb/>they
        would not let me have it. I ſtill offered Money <lb/>to have only Permiſſion to diſſect the
        Monſter, but <lb/>the impertinent Superſtition of the Parents deprived <lb/>me of that
        Satisfaction. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I ſtill preſerve in my Collection a monſtrous <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fœtus</hi>, which
        deſerves particular Attention. It is of <lb/>eight Months, without Head or Arms: The Figure
          <lb/>[<hi rend="italic">See</hi>
        <hi rend="sc">Tab I.</hi>. Fig. 1.] is here annexed, which out- <pb n="304"/>
        <lb/>wardly ſeems to be nothing elſe but the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>
        <lb/>with the Legs; theſe are well-ſhaped and propor- <lb/>tioned, with the Toes, and the
        Beginning of the <lb/>Nails; the Right Foot however is, as it were, crooked, <lb/>and
        bending inwards. Having opened it, I found <lb/>indeed but one Cavity, which in the upper
        Part <lb/>contains a ſmall Bladder. There is not in all the <lb/>Cavity any thing beſides a
        Bit of Inteſtine, the two <lb/>Kidneys, the Bladder, and the Right Teſticle, which <lb/>lay
        upon the Ring. The Fleſh was hard, and, as it <lb/>were, <hi rend="italic"
          >carcinomatoſe</hi>. The Navel-ſtring went in a <lb/>little higher than naturally, and a
        little towards the <lb/>Right Side, entering into the Inteſtine. There is a <lb/>ſlender
        Inteſtine of about 14 Lines in Length, pro- <lb/>ceeding from the ſame Place, where the
        Navel <lb/>entered into the Cavity; next comes the <hi rend="italic">Cœcum</hi>
        <lb/>with its vermicular Appendix, the <hi rend="italic">Colon</hi> and the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Rectum</hi>, the Whole together of the Length of about <lb/>two Feet. Theſe
        Inteſtines go from above to below <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">Zic-Zac</hi>, and are attached
        to the <hi rend="italic">Spina Dorſi</hi>. <lb/>There is no Footſtep of the Heart, the
        Lungs, the <lb/>Stomach, the Liver, the Spleen, the Pancreas, the <lb/>Meſentery; all that
        is wanting. The ſmall Bladder <lb/>I mentioned was fleſhy, and contained ſome Sero-
        <lb/>ſity; it is attached to the firſt of the <hi rend="italic">Vertebras</hi> of <lb/>the
        Neck. This Beginning of the <hi rend="italic">Spina</hi> is bent <lb/>forwards like a Bow,
        and forms the Monſter's Round- <lb/>neſs from above. The bended Extremity kept the
        <lb/>little Bladder, as it were, under, and ſhut up in the <lb/>Cavity cloſed up by the
        Ribs. This Cavity was to <lb/>form the <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi>, but the <hi
          rend="italic">Sternum</hi> was wanting as <lb/>well as the <hi rend="italic"
          >Diaphragm</hi>. </p>
      <pb n="305"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Deſcartes</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Lanciſci</hi> would in vain have
        looked <lb/>out here for the Seat of the Soul, and the <hi rend="italic">Punctum
          <lb/>Saliens</hi> would prove very hard to be determined in <lb/> this <hi rend="italic"
          >Fœtus</hi>. But I do not now intend to inlarge <lb/>upon it. The Buſineſs is to find ſome
        plauſible Rea- <lb/>ſons about the Origin of thoſe ſorts of Monſters I have <lb/>now
        deſcribed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Opinions of moſt of the Natural Philoſophers <lb/>on this head may, upon the main,
        be reduced to <lb/>theſe two Hypotheſes: 1. That Monſters are ori- <lb/>ginal, that is to
        ſay, that even in Conception the <lb/>Monſter is conceived. 2. That they are not pro-
        <lb/>duced but by Accident. One may conclude from <lb/>what I have ſaid about double
        Monſters, that I be- <lb/>lieved them accidental; and I believe, rigorouſly <lb/>ſpeaking,
        they are ſo, whatever they be: For ſup- <lb/>poſing every <hi rend="italic">Animalculum</hi>
        to be an <hi rend="italic">Embryo</hi> created, <lb/>I cannot imagine them to be created
        imperfect! <lb/>Their Imperfection, their Deformity, may proceed <lb/>from a thouſand
        Accidents, either in the <hi rend="italic">Reſervoirs</hi>
        <lb/>where they are contained, or in the different <lb/>Routs they are obliged to take going
        from Father to <lb/>Son. In this Caſe it may eaſily happen, that they <lb/>are Monſters,
        even in the Moment of Conception, <lb/>though they be ſuch by Accident. To how many
        <lb/>Accidents are they not ſubject afterwards in the <lb/>Venter of the Females? A Fall of
        the Mother, a <lb/>ſtrong Preſſure, a Contuſion, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> may diſorder
        the <lb/>nice and tender Structure of that little Creature ſo <lb/>far, that a great many of
        its Parts do not unfold <lb/>themſelves any longer, are deſtroyed, or have their <lb/>Order
        and natural Situation intirely changed. </p>
      <pb n="306"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The diſturbed and diſordered Imagination of the <lb/>Females ought alſo to be ranged
        among the acci- <lb/>dental Cauſes of Monſters. I have ſeen in a Sow juſt <lb/>ſlaughtered
        ſeven Pigs, which all had the bloody Mark <lb/>of the Knife about their Necks. About ſome
        twenty <lb/>Years ago, a Cloth-ſhearer in <hi rend="italic">Holland</hi> had the Miſ-
        <lb/>fortune to fall into the Hands of ſome drunken <lb/>young Fellows, who murdered him,
        and ſtabbed him <lb/>with more than twenty Wounds with their Swords. <lb/>He was to be
        married that very Week: His Sweat- <lb/>heart ſaw his Corpſe naked with all thoſe Wounds,
        <lb/>and was two Days after delivered of a dead Child, <lb/>which had the Marks of the
        Wounds in the ſame <lb/>Places of its Body, where the Mother had obſerved <lb/>them on her
        dead Lover. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I very well know, that theſe ſorts of Inſtances, <lb/>of which one might alledge ſome
        Hundreds, will <lb/>not go down with certain People, who deny the <lb/>Effect of the
        Mother's Imagination on the <hi rend="italic">Fœtus</hi>. <lb/>They lay Streſs on two
        principal Reaſons: 1<hi rend="italic">ſt</hi>, It is <lb/>pretended, that the <hi
          rend="italic">Fœtus</hi> has no immediate Con- <lb/>nexion with the Mother who carries it.
        But this is <lb/>ridiculous; for one cannot deny, that the <hi rend="italic">Secundines</hi>
        <lb/>are cloſely united to the <hi rend="italic">Matrix</hi>, and receive from <lb/>the
        Mother a Humour, or a Liquid, which by the <lb/>Navel-ſtring it remits to the <hi
          rend="italic">Fœtus</hi>. It is by that <lb/>way it receives its Nouriſhment, that is to
        ſay, the <lb/>Matter neceſſary for its Increaſe. Accordingly one <lb/>may ſay, that the <hi
          rend="italic">Fœtus</hi> owes part of its Being to the <lb/>Mother; and that the Liquid
        which runs in the Veſ- <lb/>ſels of the Mother, runs likewiſe in the Veſſels of the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Fœtus</hi>. 2<hi rend="italic">ndly</hi>, It is ſaid, that it is
        incomprehenſible <lb/>how the Soul of the Mother can have an Effect on <pb n="307"/>
        <lb/>the Child. I own I do not comprehend it neither. <lb/>It does not follow from thence,
        that we ought to <lb/>reject as falſe all that our Reaſon cannot penetrate <lb/>into. When
        once the Exiſtence and the Nature of <lb/>the Soul has been demonſtrated, when once we have
        <lb/>a perfect Knowledge of the Manner how an imma- <lb/>terial Being acts upon Matter, we
        ſhall then reaſon <lb/>in Conſequence about what the Soul can do, and <lb/>cannot do. Daily
        Obſervations demonſtrate to us, <lb/>that the diſordered and diſturbed Imagination of Wo-
        <lb/>men often hurts the Infants. And this is a Reaſon, <lb/>which I add to all the others,
        to think I have good <lb/>Grounds to conjecture, that all Monſters are acci- <lb/>dental;
        and to believe, that by the Hypotheſis of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Animalcula</hi> one may
        better explain the <hi rend="italic">Phænomena</hi>
        <lb/>which are obſerved in Generation, than by any other <lb/>Hypotheſis known as yet. </p>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>An illustration of the foetus with no head or arms, on a separate fold-out page.
          [The Royal Society website has misplaced this into the following article's PDF-file:
          http://rstl.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/41/452-461/308.full.pdf+html] </figDesc>
      </figure>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
