<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Milward: Concerning an Antidote to the Indian Poison in the
          West-Indies</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Edward Milward</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Letter from Edward Milward, M. D. to Martin Folkes, Esq; President of the Royal
              Society, concerning an Antidote to the Indian Poison in the West-Indies </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for T. Woodward, and C. Davis, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn; Printers to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1742-1743</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">42</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">2-10</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110356674</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1742.0003</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT42_0002">
    <body>
      <pb n="2"/>
      <head rend="hanging italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">II.</hi>A Letter from <hi rend="roman">Edward Milward</hi>, M. D.
        <lb/>to <hi rend="roman">Martin Folkes</hi>, Eſq; Preſident of the <lb/><hi rend="sc">Royal
          Society</hi>, concerning an <hi rend="roman">Antidote</hi>
        <lb/>to the <hi rend="roman">Indian Poiſon</hi> in the <hi rend="roman">Weſt-Indies</hi>. </head>
      <salute rend="italic space indent">
        <lb/>SIR, </salute>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="italic size(0.7)">Read <date rend="roman">Jan. 7. <lb/>1741-2.
          </date>
        </note>
        <hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>S the <hi rend="sc">Royal Society</hi>, over which <lb/>you ſo
        worthily preſide, was in- <lb/>ſtituted for the Advancement and Propagation of <lb/>Natural
        Knowledge, and as I am convinced, that every <lb/>the leaſt Step towards ſuch a Deſign
        cannot but be <lb/>agreeable; I ſhall do myſelf the Pleaſure of com- <lb/>municating to you,
        an extraordinary ſpecific Anti- <lb/>dote againſt the <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> or <hi
          rend="italic">Negro</hi> Poiſon; which, I <lb/>doubt not, will be the more acceptable, as
        this Poiſon <lb/>hath hitherto been eſteem'd the moſt deſtructive of <lb/>any. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Knowledge of this Remedy was firſt purchas'd <lb/>from a famous <hi rend="italic"
          >Negro</hi> Poiſoner, at a great Expence, <lb/>by one who ſtyles himſelf, <hi
          rend="italic">Iſaiah Burgeſs</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Doctor <lb/>of Phyſic</hi>; and the
        Secret devolv'd to myſelf, by <lb/>means of a Manuſcript of the Doctor's, which,
        <lb/>amongſt others, I have procur'd, for my <hi rend="italic">Hiſtory of <lb/>the Phyſical
          and Chirurgical Writers of this King- <lb/>dom</hi>. The Author intended this little
        Tract, which <lb/>contains <hi rend="italic">Obſervations on the moſt conſiderable Diſ-
          <lb/>tempers in</hi> America, ſhould be made public; he <lb/>wrote it, at the Requeſt of
        his Friends, about . . <lb/>. . . . . . when an Expedition was deſign'd <lb/>into <hi
          rend="italic">America</hi>; and particularly declares, that he pur- <pb n="3"/>
        <lb/>pos'd the Divulgation of this ſpecific Antidote, <hi rend="italic">that <lb/>ſuch as
          ſhould go to the <hi rend="roman">Weſt-Indies</hi>, amongſt the <lb/><hi rend="roman"
            >Spaniards</hi>, might meet with a Remedy in caſe of <lb/>Neceſſity</hi>. What prevented
        the Doctor from exe- <lb/>cuting this his laudable Deſign, I know not; but as <lb/>it was
        plainly his Intention it ſhould be made pub- <lb/>lic, and as the Knowledge of ſuch a Remedy
        may <lb/>be of the greateſt Benefit to Mankind, I ſhall lay it <lb/>before you, without any
        farther Preamble; that it <lb/>may, by means of your <hi rend="italic">Tranſactions</hi>, be
        communi- <lb/>cated to the World, provided you ſhall judge it <lb/>worthy of ſo
        diſtinguiſhing an Honour. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple">The <hi rend="italic">Negroes</hi>
        </q>, ſays he, <q rend="diple"> uſe a Poiſon of a ſtrange <lb/>and extraordinary
          Nature. The Doſe is very <lb/>ſmall, and it hath no ill Taſte; ſo that, mixt with
          <lb/>Meat or Drink, it is not perceivable. It cauſeth <lb/>divers Symptoms, and the Effect
          is various, accord- <lb/>ing as the Doſe is large or ſmall. It kills ſome- <lb/>times in
          very few Hours, ſometimes in ſome <lb/>Months, and at others in ſome Years. The Sym-
          <lb/>ptoms are according to the Quantity given: If <lb/>great, it cauſeth Evacuations
          upwards and down- <lb/>wards; of Excrements firſt, then of Humours, and <lb/>laſtly of
          Blood, with Fainting-Fits, and Sweatings. <lb/>Death follows in ſix or ſeven Hours. The
            <hi rend="italic">Ne- <lb/>groes</hi> turn white. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple">If the Doſe is but ſmall, the Sick looſeth his Ap- <lb/>petite,
          feels Pains in his Head, Arms and Limbs, <lb/>a Wearineſs all over, Soreneſs in his
          Breaſt, and Diffi- <lb/>culty of Breathing, (ſo that one appears as being <lb/>in a
          Conſumption) and at laſt dies languiſhing. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple">All Remedies yet publicly known, are of no <lb/>Force nor Virtue
          againſt this Poiſon; and the Pa- <pb n="4"/>
          <lb/>tient certainly dies. Nay, I queſtion whether the <lb/>beſt Cordial Remedies can put
          the leaſt Stop to <lb/>the Efficacy of its Venom, or retard Death, and <lb/>put it off,
          longer than the Intention of the <lb/>cunning Poiſoner had fixed it, in proportioning
          <lb/>the Doſe. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple">I know that the <hi rend="italic">Spaniards</hi> have Knowledge of
          <lb/>this very Poiſon, and am ſatisfied, that I have ſeen <lb/>ſeveral <hi rend="italic"
            >Bocaneers</hi> die of it, given them by <hi rend="italic">Spaniſh</hi>
          <lb/>Women. I am alſo perſuaded, that it is the ſame <lb/>Poiſon uſed in <hi rend="italic"
            >Spain</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi>. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple">This Poiſon hath but one ſpecific Antidote <lb/>yet known; the
          Knowledge of which coſt me very <lb/>dear: And it was with much Difficulty I could
          <lb/>perſuade a famous <hi rend="italic">Negro</hi> Poiſoner to part with <lb/>his Secret.
        </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple quotes">The Antidote is, the Root of the <hi rend="italic">Senſible
            Weed</hi>, <lb/>as it is commonly called, or <hi rend="italic">Herba Senſitiva</hi>. It
          <lb/>grows like a Shrub, has no Prickles, bloſſoms <lb/>yellow, and bears little Cods,
          full of ſmall black <lb/>pretty Seeds, of which the Women make Neck- <lb/>laces and
          Bracelets. Take none of the Root but <lb/>what is in the Ground; waſh it well, and ſplit
          it <lb/>in two. Take a good Handful of theſe Roots <lb/>ſo ſplit, and ſteep them in three
          Quarts of good <lb/>clear Water in an earthen glazed Pot, having a <lb/>Cover. Uſe but a
          moderate Fire, that it may boil <lb/>but very gently. The Decoction has no ill Taſte,
          <lb/>and you may either give it ſo, or add Sugar, as <lb/>you ſhall think beſt. Give to
          the Patient a good <lb/>Glaſs of this Decoction, as warm as he can drink <lb/>it; an Hour
          after give another, and ſo for ſome <lb/>time, as you ſhall think it neceſſary to make a
            <pb n="5"/>
          <lb/>perfect Cure. There is no Danger of giving too <lb/>much; it can do no Harm at all.
          Several People <lb/>have taken this Decoction, though they have not <lb/>been poiſoned,
          thinking it would do them good <lb/>in other Diſtempers; ſo that one who any ways
          <lb/>ſuſpects he has had ſome of that Poiſon given <lb/>him, may drink it very ſafely, and
          in what Quan- <lb/>tity he pleaſes. The reſt of the Plant is to be <lb/>rejected as bad
          and noxious. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Doctor enforces his Obſervations by remark- <lb/>ing, that he had been a
        Practitioner in thoſe Parts <lb/>for above Five-and-twenty Years. Many <hi rend="italic"
          >Negroes</hi>, <lb/>he ſays, were wonderfully preſerved and cured by <lb/>taking of this
        Antidote, though, for Brevity's ſake, <lb/>he gives but one Inſtance; which is, <q
          rend="diple quotes">of a ſtrong <lb/><hi rend="italic">Negro</hi> Man, about thirty Years
          of Age, and in <lb/>perfect Health, who being one Night at a Planta- <lb/>tion four Miles
          diſtant from that where he lived, <lb/>was invited to drink a Dram of Rum, by another
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Negro</hi>, who mixt Poiſon with it. The Fellow <lb/>drank it up,
          perceiving nothing to be in it; but <lb/>as he was taking Leave, on the other's bidding
          <lb/>him Farewel, and telling him he ſhould never ſee <lb/>him again, he ſuſpected he was
          poiſon'd; and put- <lb/>ting his Finger in his Mouth, vomited up great <lb/>part of the
          Poiſon, though there remain'd enough <lb/>of it to cauſe continual Evacuations in him up-
          <lb/>wards and downwards; of Excrements firſt, then <lb/>of Humours, and laſtly of Blood.
          As he was <lb/>coming home, he fainted away ſeveral times, and <lb/>calling at length to
          ſome Neighbour's <hi rend="italic">Negro</hi>
          <lb/>Houſes, was brought home extremely alter'r; turn'd <lb/>white, and was, as it was
          thought, expiring. The <pb n="6"/>
          <lb/>Root was immediately ſent for, and the Decoction <lb/>made, and given him in great
          Quantity. He con- <lb/>tinued taking it for three or four Days, and on <lb/>the Fifth went
          to work along with the reſt of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Negroes</hi>. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That the <hi rend="italic">Senſible Plant</hi> is endow'd with the Pro- <lb/>perty of
        reſiſting Poiſon, hath been, before this, <lb/>taken Notice of. For the Honourable Sir <hi
          rend="italic">Hans <lb/>Sloane</hi>, the late worthy Preſident of this <hi rend="sc"
          >Society</hi>, <lb/>whoſe Writings will always remain an Honour to his <lb/>Country, hath
        obſerv'd from <hi rend="italic">Piſo</hi>, that the <hi rend="italic">Root</hi> of <lb/>this
        Shrub is an Antidote againſt the <hi rend="italic">Shrub</hi> itſelf, <lb/>which is very
        poiſonous, and kills by Degrees, making <lb/>the unhappy Sufferers Cachectical,
        Short-winded, and <lb/>Melancholy, till they die <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.8)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>*Nat. Hiſt. of <hi rend="italic">Jamaica</hi>, Vol. II. <hi rend="italic">p</hi>.
            57. </p>
        </note>. This greatly corro- <lb/>borates what our Author has advanced; and it is
        <lb/>obſerveable, that he likewiſe directs all Parts of the <lb/>Plant, except that Part of
        the Root which is in the <lb/>Ground, <hi rend="italic">to be rejected, as bad and
          noxious</hi>: Though <lb/>whether this be exactly the ſame Plant with what <lb/>our Author
        mentions, I dare not determine; as Sir <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hans Sloane</hi> inquires
        whether it be not the <hi rend="italic">Æſ- <lb/>chynomene, ſeu Mimoſa arboreſcens
          Americana, <hi rend="roman">&amp;c.</hi>
          <lb/>flore albo</hi>; whereas Dr. <hi rend="italic">Burgeſs</hi> expreſly ſays, that it
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">flowers yellow</hi>: though this may, poſſibly, be a Miſ- <lb/>take
        in him. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I am ſensible it may be objected, that the <hi rend="italic">Negro</hi>
        <lb/>Poiſon is of various Kinds; and that therefore, though <lb/>this Remedy may be ſo
        extraordinary a Specific in <lb/>ſome Caſes, it may be unavailable in others. That <pb n="7"/>
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Negroes</hi> may have the Knowledge of different <lb/>Sorts of
        Poiſon, I deny not; but it would appear, <lb/>from the Univerſality of the Effects of this
        Medicine, <lb/>as the Doctor affirms <hi rend="italic">many have been wonderfully <lb/>cured
          and preſerved by it</hi>, and does not mention a <lb/>ſingle Inſtance of its Miſcarriage,
        as though the <hi rend="italic">Ne- <lb/>groes</hi> in the <hi rend="italic"
          >West-Indies</hi> uſed but <hi rend="italic">one</hi> Kind of Poiſon, <lb/>or, if
        different, yet ſuch as comes within the Power <lb/>of this Remedy. Beſides, as we cannot be
        aſſured, <lb/>but by the Conſequence, whether the Poiſon be of <lb/>that Sort, as to be
        within the Reach of this Remedy, <lb/>or not, I think there is all the Reaſon in the World
        <lb/>it ſhould be adminiſter'd under any Suſpicion of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Indian</hi>
        Poiſon: Eſpecially, as the Doctor aſſure us <lb/>of its great Innocence; and I believe every
        one will <lb/>readily agree with me, that it is no ſmall Recom- <lb/>mendation of a
        Medicine, <hi rend="italic">That let what will be- <lb/>come of its good Effects, it can do
          no Harm</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Dioſcorides</hi> hath rightly obſerv'd in his <hi rend="italic"
          >Alexi- <lb/>pharmics, that very different Poiſons produce the <lb/>ſame Effects upon
          Human Bodies; and that there- <lb/>fore they are, for the moſt part, curable by the ſame
          <lb/>Remedies. For though the Kinds of Poiſons are <lb/>various, yet the Effects which
          ariſe from them <lb/>are common, and but few</hi>
        <note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.8)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† Fere enim plurimorum Venenorum facultates in conſimiles <lb/>effectus Corpus
            tandem deducunt: quam ob cauſam pleriſque com- <lb/>munia conducunt Auxilia. Varia
            equidem ſunt Venenorum genera: <lb/>communes tamen, nec ita multi, qui ex iis oriuntur,
            affectus. </p>
        </note>. And that Ornament <lb/>of his Profeſſion, the learned and beneficent Dr. <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Mead</hi>, who hath given us a more rational Account <pb n="8"/>
        <lb/>of the Nature and properties of <hi rend="italic">Poiſons</hi>, and taught <lb/>us to
        reaſon with greater Certainty about ſuch abſ- <lb/>truſe Points, than any that ever came
        before him, <lb/>is of Opinion, <hi rend="italic">that though there be a great Variety
          <lb/>of internal Poiſons, as well Mineral as Vegetable, <lb/>yet they do all of them ſeem
          to agree in their pri- <lb/>mary Effects, and manner of Operation</hi>. Eff. III. <lb/>And
        in another Place, <hi rend="italic">That virulent Plants, al- <lb/>though they may be
          diſtinguiſh'd even from one another <lb/>by particular Virtues, do however kill by a like
          <lb/>Operation and Force</hi>. From whence it ſeems rea- <lb/>ſonable to infer, that
        although Poiſons may be vari- <lb/>ous in themſelves, yet it is not impoſſible they may
        <lb/>be cured by the ſame Remedy; as they produce like <lb/>Effects, and ſeem to kill by a
        like manner of Ope- <lb/>ration. And a very remarkable Inſtance of this we <lb/>have in all
        corroſive Poiſons, whether of the Mineral <lb/>or Vegetable Kingdom, which, however
        different in <lb/>themſelves, produce their Effects univerſally by erode- <lb/>ing the Coats
        of the <hi rend="italic">Stomach</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic">Primæ Viæ</hi>; <lb/>and
        which are all curable in like manner, by ſheath- <lb/>ing and blunting their acrimonious
        Particles, by <lb/>means of ſmooth, lubricating and oleaginous Me- <lb/>dicines. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But be this as it will, I think the Remedy deſerves, <lb/>at leaſt, a fair and
        impartial Trial, as the Author has <lb/>not indulged in any rhetorical Flouriſhes, or
        Theory, <lb/>but ſeemingly confin'd himſelf to Truth, and plain <lb/>matter of Fact. And,
        indeed, ſhould it be found <lb/>to ſucceed but <hi rend="italic">One</hi> time in <hi
          rend="italic">Twenty</hi>, in ſuch deplo- <lb/>rable Circumſtances, it cannot but be a
        Diſcovery <lb/>of the greateſt Conſequence; eſpecially as we are <lb/>ſufficiently aſſur'd
        beforehand, that all Cordial and <pb n="9"/>
        <lb/>Alexipharmic Medicines beſides, can be of no Ser- <lb/>vice at all. And this may ſerve
        as another Argu- <lb/>ment, why, under any Probability of a Perſon's being <lb/>injur'd by
        the <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Negro</hi> Poiſon, this Remedy
        <lb/>ſhould be adminiſter'd; even though we cannot poſi- <lb/>tively be aſſur'd, whether it
        be by this very Poiſon <lb/>or not: For in Caſes where all other Remedies are <lb/>likely,
        if not ſure, to prove unavailable, we may as <lb/>well adviſe this as any. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I cannot affirm, I ever knew any Effects from this <lb/>Remedy on my own Knowledge or
        Obſervation; <lb/>having never reſided in thoſe Places where this <lb/>Poiſon is frequent:
        But ſurely a Medicine which <lb/>promiſes ſuch great things for the Good of Man- <lb/>kind,
        deſerves to have a fair and candid <hi rend="italic">Examina- <lb/>tion</hi>; and ſhould it
        prove to be as ſerviceable as the <lb/>Author aſſures us it is, you cannot but receive the
        <lb/>highest Satisfaction, in being inſtrumental in divulg- <lb/>ing the Knowledge of a
        Remedy, from whence the <lb/>Public may receive ſuch unſpeakable Benefit. And <lb/>it would
        be doing the higheſt Service to their Fellow- <lb/>Creatures, if ſuch as have a proper
        Opportunity in <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">West-Indies</hi>, would adminiſter it, according
        to <lb/>the Directions here given, and report an exact Ac- <lb/>count of its Succeſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>One thing more I muſt beg leave to add, with <lb/>regard to the Trial of this Medicine;
        that it would <lb/>be neceſſary to obſerve, whether the ſame Root, <lb/>dried, would be of
        equal, or any Efficacy; that if <lb/>ſo, the Benefits of it may be extended to other Cli-
        <lb/>mates wherein this Herb does not naturally grow: <lb/>Particularly as the Author is
        convinced, that the <lb/>ſame ſort of Poiſon is uſed both in <hi rend="italic">Spain</hi>
        and <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi>. </p>
      <pb n="10"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I ſhall do myſelf the Honour, ſome other Oppor- <lb/>tunity, of laying before you the
        Conjectures of Au- <lb/>thors concerning this <hi rend="italic">Indian</hi> or <hi
          rend="italic">Negro</hi> Poiſon, with <lb/>the Remarks I have made thereon; and if the
        pre- <lb/>ſent Paper proves acceptable, ſhall communicate to <lb/>you the Doctor's others
        Obſervations concerning the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Bites of poiſonous Snakes</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">poiſonous Fiſh</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Wounds</hi>, <lb/>and <hi
          rend="italic">the moſt remarkable Diſtempers in the <hi rend="roman">Weſt-
            <lb/>Indies</hi></hi>; which cannot but be of great Service to ſuch <lb/>as reſide in
        thoſe Parts; eſpecially as he mentions <lb/>chiefly ſuch Medicines as are <hi rend="italic"
          >Natives</hi> of the Coun- <lb/>try he treats of, and which are therefore the more
        <lb/>eaſy to be procur'd. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I am, Sir, (with the greateſt Eſteem) </p>
      <signed rend="italic align-right">
        <lb/>Your, and the <hi rend="sc">Society's</hi>, <lb/>moſt Obedient, <lb/>and very humble
        Servant, <lb/><hi rend="roman size(1.2)">Edward Milward. </hi>
      </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
