<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Bell: An Account of the Case of William Payne, with What Appeared
          upon Examining His Kidneys and Bladder</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>George Bell</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of the Case of William Payne, with What Appeared upon Examining His
              Kidneys and Bladder, When His Body Was Opened</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for T. Woodward, and C. Davis, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn; Printers to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1742-1743</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">42</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">54-56</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110356674</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1742.0019</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT42_0054">
    <body>
      <pb n="54"/>
      <head rend="hanging italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XV.</hi> An Account of the Caſe of <hi rend="roman">William
        Payne</hi>, <lb/>with what appeared upon examining his <lb/><hi rend="roman">Kidneys</hi>
        and <hi rend="roman">Bladder</hi>, when his Body was <lb/>opened; by Mr. <hi rend="roman"
          >George Bell</hi>, Surgeon. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="italic size(0.7)">Read <date rend="roman">Feb. 4. <lb/>1741-2.
          </date>H This <lb/>ſhould have <lb/>been inſerted at <lb/><hi rend="roman">p. 27. Art.
            X.</hi>
        </note><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="dc(2)">W</hi>Illiam Payne</hi>, aged about 71, had
        <lb/>been afflicted with the Stone in his <lb/>Bladder, and other calculous Complaints,
        <lb/>for ſeveral Years: He had taken Mrs. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Stephens</hi>'s Medicines
        for 15 Months. <hi rend="italic">See <hi rend="roman">Hartley</hi>'s <lb/>View, <hi
            rend="roman">&amp;c. p.8. Caſe III</hi>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He was ſubject alſo to a ſcrotal Rupture on the <lb/>Left Side, from which however he
        ſuffered no great <lb/>Inconveniency, unleſs upon Neglect of his Truſs, which <lb/>he had
        been directed to wear; and even then, if the In- <lb/>teſtines came down, he uſed to return
        them with Eaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About the Beginning of <hi rend="italic">January</hi> laſt, he was at- <lb/>tacked with
        a ſevere Fit of the Stone, attended, upon <lb/>every Attempt to make Water, with a ſtrong
          <hi rend="italic">Teneſmus</hi>, <lb/>that forced into the <hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>
        a conſiderable Quantity <lb/>of the Inteſtines, which exceeding his Skill to reduce, <lb/>he
        ſent for me. I found the Tumour large and unequal, <lb/>but without much Tenſion or
        Inflammation; his Pulſe <lb/>low, with clammy Sweats; he complained of violent <lb/>Pains in
        his Back, propagated thro' the whole Length <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Ureters</hi>,
        accompanied with Nauſea and Vomit- <lb/>ings; he felt exquiſite Pain about the Neck of his
        Blad- <lb/>der and <hi rend="italic">Glans</hi>, with an unuſual Weight <hi rend="italic">in
          Perinæo</hi>; <lb/>he had frequent Inclinations to make Water, but ſel- <lb/>dom made
        above a Spoonful at once, and that Drop <pb n="55"/>
        <lb/>by Drop, with much Pain, and ſudden Stoppings: The <lb/>Urine was extremely fetid,
        ſometimes mixed with pu- <lb/>rulent Matter, at others tinged of a Coffee Colour. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He had received, juſt before I ſaw him, a Clyſter, <lb/>which produced two Stools, and
        encouraged me to <lb/>hope might facilitate the Reduction of his Rupture. I <lb/>attempted
        it by all neceſſary means poſſible, but with- <lb/>out Succeſs: For altho' the largeſt Part
        receded and <lb/>gave way, yet a conſiderable Portion remained, which <lb/>I could not
        poſſibly return. I therefore concluded, as <lb/>the Inteſtines performed their Office, and
        were free <lb/>from Tenſion, Inflammation, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> that the Parts ad-
        <lb/>hered; ſo left him, with Directions for a Bag-Truſs to <lb/>ſupport them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">January</hi> the 22d, being informed of his Death, I <lb/>applied for
        Leave to open him, which was granted. <lb/>In examining the Contents of the <hi
          rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, I found <lb/>the Left Kidney quite waſted, ſcarce any thing
        remain- <lb/>ing except the Coats, and thoſe filled with Blood and <lb/>purulent Matter; the
          <hi rend="italic">Ureter</hi> very much inlarged above <lb/>its natural Capacity, and full
        of the ſame. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Right Kidney was ulcerated in ſeveral Places, <lb/>and full of purulent Matter,
        mixed with Grit; ſeveral <lb/>Hydatids appeared upon its external Surface; the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Ureter</hi> was ſomewhat inlarged. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I next examined the Bladder, which was exceeding <lb/>large, and contained above three
        Pints of clear Urine; <lb/>upon opening it and introducing my Hand, I found <lb/>two ſmooth
        flattiſh Stones, ſomewhat larger than <lb/>common <hi rend="italic">Windſor Beans</hi>: I
        diſcovered a third in the <lb/>Neck of the Bladder, which probably had been forced
        <lb/>there during the Paroxyſm, and appeared to me to be <pb n="56"/>
        <lb/>the immediate Cauſe of his Death: It was about the <lb/>Size of a <hi rend="italic"
          >Filbert</hi>, and had quite corked up the Paſſage. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon diſſecting the Hernial Bag, the firſt Part that <lb/>preſented was a large Piece
        of Fat, about half a Pound; <lb/>and immediately underneath it lay a large Portion of
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Colon</hi>, in Length about 10 Inches; the internal <lb/>Surface
        of the <hi rend="italic">Peritoneum</hi> was ſtrongly attached to <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >Colon</hi> by ſeveral Filaments, and to the <hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi> by <lb/>its
        cellular Subſtance. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>All the other <hi rend="italic">Viſcera</hi> were in a natural State. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
