<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Banyer: Two Remarkable Medical Cases</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Henry Banyer</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Two Remarkable Medical Cases, One of an Extraordinary Haemorrhage, the Other an
              Ascites Cured by Tapping; Communicated by Henry Banyer, M. D. Extra-Licentiate of the
              College of Physicians, London, to C. Mortimer, M. D. Secr. R. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for T. Woodward, and C. Davis, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn; Printers to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1742-1743</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">42</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">628-633</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110356674</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1742.0100</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT42_0628">
    <body>
      <pb n="628"/>
      <head rend="hanging italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XV.</hi> Two remarkable <hi rend="roman">Medical Caſes</hi>, one of
        <lb/>an Extraordinary <hi rend="roman">Hæmorrhage</hi>, the other <lb/>an <hi rend="roman"
          >Aſcites</hi> cured by Tapping; communicated <lb/>by <hi rend="roman">Henry Banyer</hi>,
        M. D. Extra-Licentiate <lb/>of the <hi rend="roman">College of Phyſicians, London</hi>, to
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">C. Mortimer</hi>, M. D. Secr. <hi rend="roman">R. S.</hi>
      </head>
      <div>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/>
          <note place="inset" rend="italic size(0.7)">Read <date rend="roman">Dec. 22. <lb/>1743.
            </date>
          </note><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N the Month of <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 1729. <hi
            rend="italic">Da- <lb/>niel Goddard</hi>, a Gardener, about the <lb/>Age of Twenty-four
          Years, at <hi rend="italic">Wisbech</hi> in the Iſle of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ely,
            Cambridgeſhire</hi>, happened of a ſlight Puncture <lb/>from a ruſty Nail in the Sole of
          his Right Foot. And, <lb/>notwithſtanding there was not wounded any Tendon, <lb/>or
          Blood-veſſel, larger than ſmall Branches of Veins, <lb/>the whole Foot was immediately
          ſwelled to a very <lb/>unuſual Degree, without any Fever, or other apparent <lb/>Cauſe for
          it. It was alſo attended with great Pain, <lb/>and an extraordinary Pulſation upon the
          Part, as in <lb/>Wounds of Arteries; and ſo diſtended as if the Blood <lb/>would burſt out
          of its Veſſels. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Accordingly, after Two Days, upon opening a ſuper- <lb/>ficial Sinus, to inlarge the
          Wound, there ruſhed out <lb/>immediately ſuch an obſtinate Flux of Blood, as would
          <lb/>not yield to any ſtyptic Means, longer than the <lb/>Bandage was holden on by ſome
          ſtrong Hand. And, <lb/>although, by this Inciſion, no Veſſels were wounded, <lb/>but
          Capillary Veins; yet this <hi rend="italic">Hæmorrhage</hi> continued <lb/>to ſhew itſelf
          as violent as at firſt, for Six Days ſuc- <lb/>ceſſively, whenever the neceſſary Means
          were relaxed. <lb/>Upon which, for the ſake of <hi rend="italic">Revulſion</hi>, the
          Patient <pb n="629"/>
          <lb/>had a Vein opened on the Arm of the oppoſite Side; <lb/>and it had ſuch a ſudden and
          ſurpriſing Effect, that the <lb/>Flux of Blood in the Foot inſtantly ceaſed, and the
          <lb/>Wound healed very ſoon without any further Trouble; <lb/>but the Flux of Blood,
          conſequent upon Veneſection, <lb/>became equally as difficult to reſtrain, as that in the
          <lb/>Foot, for the Space of Four Days; all which time it <lb/>would have continued to flow
          moſt violently with- <lb/>out the ſtrictest Bandage, as the ſame Care of the <lb/>Hand, as
          before. Perhaps the Period of this <hi rend="italic">Hæmor- <lb/>rhage</hi> might have
          been much longer, if I had not <lb/>ſuffered the Ligature on the Arm to be looſened now-
          <lb/>and-then, as I judged the Redundancy of Blood re- <lb/>quired, for the ſake of ſome
          Evacuation, at each time. <lb/>After the Bleeding, he ſoon recovered his Strength, <lb/>ſo
          as to do his Buſineſs in the Gardens; and con- <lb/>tinued very well till the Month of <hi
            rend="italic">March</hi> 1730. <lb/>About the Middle of this Month, he complained of
          <lb/>Sleepineſs, and a particular Heavineſs all over his <lb/>Body; which was followed, in
          Three Days time, by <lb/>a violent <hi rend="italic"><choice>
              <corr>Hæmorrhage</corr>
              <sic>Hæmorhage</sic>
            </choice></hi> from the <hi rend="italic">Noſe</hi>. This Flux, in <lb/>ſpite of all
          Means being tried, except Veneſection, <lb/>continued Seven Days, and could never be
          totally <lb/>ſtopped, all this time, for one Hour together. He re- <lb/>covered again in a
          very ſhort time, and was able to <lb/>work in the Summer-ſeaſon, without any Complaints,
          <lb/>till <hi rend="italic">October</hi> following. Then the <hi rend="italic"
            >Hæmorrhage</hi> re- <lb/>turned again at the <hi rend="italic">Noſe</hi>, as before,
          with all the ſame <lb/>Circumſtances, and in Defiance of all Endeavours, <lb/>continued
          the Period of Seven Days. Thus it re- <lb/>turned in like manner of Bleeding, by <hi
            rend="italic">Stools</hi>, in the <lb/>Middle of <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 1731, and
          continued to diſcharge <lb/>this Way great Quantities of Blood, in one Motion, <pb n="630"/>
          <lb/>and ſometimes two Motions every Day for Seven Days <lb/>together, in Oppoſition to
          the moſt efficacious Reſtrin- <lb/>gents. Alſo it made its regular Return by vaſt Pro-
          <lb/>fuſions of Blood from the <hi rend="italic">Inteſtines</hi>, in the Begin- <lb/>ning
          of <hi rend="italic">October</hi> following, to the End of the firſt <lb/>Period of Seven
          Days, without Gripings, or any ſuch <lb/>uneaſy Senſations. Thus, again, it kept as
          orderly <lb/>Returns about the Vernal and Autumnal Equinoxes of <lb/>the Years 1732, 1733,
          with vaſt Profuſion of Blood by <lb/>Stool, for the uſual Term of Seven Days, agreeing in
          <lb/>all Circumſtances with the preceeding Years. Likewiſe <lb/>at, or very near theſe two
          grand Seaſons, in the Years <lb/>1734, 1735, this habitual <hi rend="italic"
            >Hæmorrhage</hi> broke away <lb/>by the <hi rend="italic">Kidneys and urinary
            Paſſage</hi>; and ſtill con- <lb/>ſtantly, for theſe Two Years, kept its old ſtated Time
          <lb/>of Seven Days, without any other Variation. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This young Man was ſeized in <hi rend="italic">Dec.</hi> 1735, with <lb/>the <hi
            rend="italic">Small-pox</hi>, of the Diſtinct Kind, which produced <lb/>ſuch a Change in
          his Conſtitution, that he eſcaped <lb/>thoſe periodical <hi rend="italic"
          >Hæmorrhages</hi>, or any other ſponta- <lb/>neous Evacuations equivalent thereto, for the
          Two <lb/>Seaſons of the Year 1736; and remained in very good <lb/>Health till <hi
            rend="italic">Chriſtmas</hi> following, being above Thirteen <lb/>Months free from any
          Symptoms of his old Eruption. <lb/>But, upon <hi rend="italic">December</hi> the 27th,
          without any previous <lb/>Notice of Heavineſs and Sleepineſs, the <hi rend="italic"
            >Hæmorrhage</hi>
          <lb/>returned by the <hi rend="italic">urinary Paſſages</hi>; but much more
          <lb/>favourably, and continued only Three Days. Again, <lb/>on <hi rend="italic">May</hi>
          the 13th following, 1737, he then felt the <lb/>previous Warnings, and bled again by Urine
          to the <lb/>20th of the ſame Month; with this Difference, that <lb/>for Three Days the
          Urine was only Coffee-coloured, <lb/>but afterwards, for Four Days longer, every Diſcharge
            <pb n="631"/>
          <lb/>reſembled an Effuſion of Blood from a Vein juſt <lb/>opened. He preſently recovered
          his Strength, even <lb/>although the Air was exceeding warm at this Time; <lb/>and I ſaw
          him Five Months after, very robuſt and <lb/>healthy, and, as he told me himſelf, was free
          from <lb/>all kinds of Tendency towards his old Complaint. <lb/>But he had always the
          Appearance of too much Ful- <lb/>neſs, though I am of Opinion, that his Conſtitution
          <lb/>did not ſuffer ſo much as might reaſonably be ima- <lb/>gined, from ſuch prodigious
            <hi rend="italic"><choice>
              <corr>Hæmorrhages</corr>
              <sic>Hæmorhages</sic>
            </choice></hi>. Of my <lb/>own Knowlege, he had no Return of his Bleeding, <lb/>or any
          thing like it, the enſuing Autumn; but re- <lb/>mained perfectly well all the following
          Winter Sea- <lb/>ſon. Afterwards I had no Opportunity of making <lb/>further perſonal
          Inquiries, but was informed by an <lb/>intelligent Man, that in <hi rend="italic"
            >March</hi> 1738 this unfortunate <lb/>Perſon got a ſlight Wound again, ſomewhere upon
          <lb/>one of his Legs, which proved equally as difficult, <lb/>with reſpect to the Flux of
          Blood, as the firſt Puncture <lb/>in his Foot. And, whether from too ſtrict as Reſtraint
          <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Hæmorrhage</hi>, or for want of Veneſection, he <lb/>fell
          into very violent Convulſions for Four or Five <lb/>Days, and died in a manner like
          Suffocation, from <lb/>too much Redundancy of Blood. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As this <hi rend="italic">Hæmorrhage</hi> never once depended upon <lb/>any other
          Diſtemper, or obſerved any regular Con- <lb/>currence with the Revolutions of the Moon, it
          ap- <lb/>pears to be a very extraordinary ſimple <hi rend="italic">Plethora</hi>.
          <lb/>During the Four Years that this Flux of Blood came <lb/>from the Noſe and Inteſtines,
          the Urine was never <lb/>of a higher Colour than Amber; nor was there any <lb/>Symptom of
          a Fever by the Pulſe, or otherways, for <lb/>the whole Term of the Diſorder. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="632"/>
      <div>
        <dateline rend="space align-right">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">January</hi> the 6th, 1743. </dateline>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">O</hi>N <hi rend="italic">March</hi> the 26th, 1739, the Wife of
          Mr. <hi rend="italic">Matth. <lb/>Wilkinſon</hi>, of <hi rend="italic">Long-Sutton</hi>,
          in <hi rend="italic">Lincolnſhire</hi>, was <lb/>tapped for an <hi rend="italic"
            >Aſcites</hi>, proceeding from frequent <hi rend="italic">Hæ- <lb/>morrhages</hi>, and a
          too liberal Uſe of ſmall Liquors. <lb/>She was between 30 and 40 Years old, of a very low
          <lb/>Stature, and always of a weak Conſtitution. The <lb/>Water was all taken away at one
          Time, and mea- <lb/>ſured Five Gallons. She was very faint immediately <lb/>after the
          Operation, and remained ſo for near Three <lb/>Weeks after. But, by great Abſtinence from
          Liquids, <lb/>excepting <hi rend="italic">Lower</hi>'s bitter Infuſion, and ſometimes a
          <lb/>Spoonful or Two of Cordial Julap, ſhe perfectly <lb/>recovered her Health again; and
          to a much better <lb/>Degree of it, than ſhe had enjoyed for many Years <lb/>before;
          without any Appearance at all of a Return <lb/>of the abdominal Tumour to this Day. The
          Water <lb/>was clear, and readily turned to a ſtrong Jelly upon <lb/>heating it; and I am
          very certain, there was unavoid- <lb/>ably left in the Abdomen a Quantity ſufficient to
          <lb/>prove the Exiſtence of abſorbent Veſſels. Perhaps <lb/>thoſe Patients, in this
          Diſtemper, whoſe Water turns <lb/>to a Jelly, have a better Chance to be cured by <hi
            rend="italic">Pa- <lb/>racenteſis</hi>, than others, whoſe Diſcharge is more like
          <lb/>Urine, and will never curdle by Heat. But Time, <lb/>and repeated Obſervation, muſt
          confirm this Opi- <lb/>nion. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="633"/>
      <postscript>
        <label rend="italic space align-center">
          <lb/>Poſtſcript againſt <hi rend="roman">Empiriciſm</hi>. </label>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">N</hi>Otwithſtanding the great Uſefulneſs and Ten- <lb/>dency of
          ſucceſsful Obſervations in Phyſic and <lb/>Surgery, to encourage Practitioners in a
          Perſeverance <lb/>in their Duty, even where the regular Prognoſtics <lb/>ſtand againſt
          them; yet I cannot forbear taking this <lb/>Opportunity to aſſert the Impoſſibility of any
          Per- <lb/>ſon's obtaining a competent Knowlege of the Art of <lb/>Healing, by Practice
          only; without a previous Know- <lb/>lege of Anatomy, and the Animal Oeconomy. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Hence have I met with an old Practitioner, of very <lb/>extenſive Buſineſs, who had
          never been educated in <lb/>this fundamental Qualification, and who, for want of <lb/>it,
          was treating his Patient with Cataplaſms and Fo- <lb/>mentations, to cure that Numbneſs in
          the Thigh <lb/>which is a certain Diagnoſtic of a <hi rend="italic">Nephritic Caſe</hi>.
          <lb/>And I have more than once ſeen a <hi rend="italic">Dyſuria</hi> under <lb/>the
          Treatment of a gravelly Caſe, when it has plainly <lb/>ariſen from the <hi rend="italic"
            >Venæ Hæmorrhoidales</hi> having been <lb/>too much ſwelled towards the urinary
          Paſſages. <lb/>Thus, where Men are not qualified to diſtinguiſh at <lb/>all upon the
          Symptoms of a Diſtemper, from ſome <lb/>true Knowlege of the Parts concerned, they muſt
          <lb/>neceſſarily be often miſtaking the Symptoms for Diſ- <lb/>tempers, and ſo <hi
            rend="italic">vice verſa</hi>, after this Manner; inſo- <lb/>much that their longeſt
          Practice will be little better <lb/>than a Multiplication of Blunders, without much
          <lb/>Chance to be wiſer by Time and Experience.—<hi rend="italic">Huic <lb/>Ratiocinationi
            adſtipulatur Experientia, qua ſine <lb/>vana omnis Theoria, bella ſit utcunque</hi>.
        </p>
      </postscript>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
