<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Burton: Two Histories of Internal Cancers</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>William Burton</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Two Histories of Internal Cancers, and of What Appeared upon Dissection, by
              William Burton, M. D.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for T. Woodward, and C. Davis, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn; Printers to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1742-1743</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">42</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">99-111</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110356674</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1742.0028</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT42_0099">
    <body>
      <pb n="99"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">II.</hi> Two Hiſtories of <hi rend="roman">Internal Cancers</hi>, and
        of <lb/>what appeared upon Diſſection, by <hi rend="roman">William <lb/>Burton</hi>, M. D. </head>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>I. </head>
        <dateline rend="align-right">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Windſor</hi>, <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 22. 1734. </dateline>
        <p rend="indent">
          <note place="inset" rend="italic size(0.7)">
            <lb/>Read <date rend="roman">May 13. <lb/>1742. </date>
          </note><hi rend="dc(2)">B</hi><hi rend="italic">Artholomew Collins</hi>, a Labourer in
          <lb/>the King's Works at <hi rend="italic">Windſor</hi>, of <lb/>low Stature, pale
          Complexion, ſlender and active, <lb/>aged about 36 Years, temperate in his manner of
          <lb/>Living, had, for ſome Years, been afflicted at dif- <lb/>ferent times with wandering
          arthritic, colic, and <lb/>nephritic Pains, none of which were periodical or
          <lb/>conſtant. During this Term, when in beſt Health, <lb/>he was uſually coſtive, and his
          Urine, as ſoon as made, <lb/>depoſited a <hi rend="italic">calculous</hi> Sediment. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 1733. he received a violent Blow by a <lb/>ponderous
          and obtuſe Inſtrument on his Loins, toge- <lb/>ther with the Spine of the <hi
            rend="italic">Os Innominatum</hi>, towards <lb/>the Left Side, which diſabled him for
          that Day; on <lb/>the next, the Pain abating, he continued ſo well for <lb/>Six Months
          after, as not even to recollect this Acci- <lb/>dent, till about a Month before his Death,
          although <lb/>he was often asked by the Phyſician, Whether that <lb/>Part had ever
          ſuffered a Contuſion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In <hi rend="italic">January</hi> following, he complained of an excru- <lb/>ciating
          Pain, extending from the aforeſaid Spine to <lb/>the ſpurious Ribs on the Left Side, which
          ſome- <lb/>times attacked alſo the Inteſtines; whence he became <lb/>continually reſtleſs,
          eſpecially in the Night, and, <lb/>toſſing the Bedcloaths off, frequently lay naked. <pb
            n="100"/>
          <lb/>He could not now lie upon his Back or Left, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
          <lb/>the affected Side, but lay always on his Right Side, <lb/>leaning on his Right Elbow.
          In <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 1734. his <lb/>Left Knee, from a Contraction of the
          Muſcles ele- <lb/>vating it, was always drawn up towards the <hi rend="italic">Abdo-
            <lb/>men</hi>, inſomuch that he could not ſtand upright. His <lb/>Left <hi rend="italic"
            >Teſticle</hi>, formerly leſs than the Right, was now <lb/>become ſcirrhous, and
          increaſed to double the Mag- <lb/>nitude of this, and the Left Spermatic Veſſels felt
          <lb/>like a knotty Chord. A ſort of Hectic Fever attended <lb/>him, the Exacerbation of
          which, as well as of his <lb/>Pains, was generally about Noon, and Six in the
          <lb/>Evening.—He had no Sleep of Nights without a Pare- <lb/>goric.—Though his Appetite
          failed him, he had no <lb/>Propenſity to vomit, nor complained of Thirſt. His
          <lb/>Reſpiration and Urine were not amiſs.—His Pains <lb/>were always exaſperated by the
          Uſe of heating Medi- <lb/>cines; and whenever the Pain ſeized the Inteſtines,
          <lb/>terebinthinate Clyſters increaſed them, whereas <lb/>emollient and refrigerating ones
          mitigated them; <lb/>by the Uſe of which he had daily one or two Stools. <lb/>—The Fœces
          were of a middling Conſiſtence, <lb/>lightly tinged with Bile.—The Blood frequently
          <lb/>taken away by <hi rend="italic">V. S.</hi> in ſmall Quantities, had always <lb/>a
          thick, tough, ſizy Buff-like pleuritic Coat; and at <lb/>firſt, from each ſeveral
          Bleeding, he found Relief. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 4. 1733-4. The Apothecary firſt admi- <lb/>niſtered to
          him, for the Colic, <hi rend="italic">Elect. Lenitiv. &amp; <lb/>Pulv. Diaſen. Ol.
            Junip.</hi> and emollient Clyſters. <lb/>Three Days after, Pains ſeizing his Left Side,
          and the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Sphincter Veſicæ</hi>, they were removed by repeated
          <lb/>Bleedings, and <hi rend="italic">Decoct. Hord. &amp; Lap. Prunel.</hi> and <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Syr. Althææ</hi>. On the 12th, he complained of a <pb n="101"/>
          <lb/>Heat about the <hi rend="italic">Regio Pubis</hi>, with Coſtiveneſs; but <lb/>by the
          Uſe of <hi rend="italic">Sal. Mirab. Glaub. Lap. Prunel. <lb/>Manna</hi>, emollient
          Decoctions with <hi rend="italic">Sp. Nitr. d. &amp; <lb/>Elect. Lenitiv. pro re
          nata</hi>, continued tolerably <lb/>eaſy till the 24th, when the erratic Pains returning,
          <lb/>and not yielding to the aforeſaid Apozems, on the <lb/>26th the Phyſician firſt
          conſulted gave him <hi rend="italic">Sperm. <lb/>Cet. Sal. C. C. &amp; pulv. e Chel.</hi>
          and <hi rend="italic">Sp. C. C.</hi> but <lb/>theſe not availing, the <hi rend="italic"
            >Lap. Prunel.</hi> was ſometimes <lb/>interpoſed, and a <hi rend="italic">Calomel</hi>
          Bolus, taken at Night, was <lb/>worked off by a Sena Potion next Day: This Me- <lb/>thod,
          and afterwards Powders of <hi rend="italic">Lap. Prunel.</hi> and <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Cinnab. Antim.</hi> taken in Honey, mitigated thoſe <lb/>Pains. But from <hi
            rend="italic">February</hi> 3. to <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 4. ſometimes
          <lb/>nephritic Pains, intermitting Fever, pleuritic Pains, and <lb/>Strangury,
          inordinately afflicted him, notwithſtand- <lb/>ing the Uſe, according to the ſaid
          Indications, of <lb/>carminative, terebinthinate and ſaponaceous Cly- <lb/>ſters, Purges,
            <hi rend="italic">Sal. Abſinth.</hi> Draughts, repeated Bleed- <lb/>ings, Veſicatories,
          the Powders and Electuary above- <lb/>mentioned, Opiates, <hi rend="italic">Cort.
            Peruv.</hi> in an Electuary, <lb/>and infuſed in Wine, <hi rend="italic">Lac Sulph.</hi>
          with Aſſes Milk, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cinnab. Antim. Millep. Gum Guaiac.</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">Pulv. e <lb/>Chel.</hi> with <hi rend="italic">Vinum Milleped.</hi> and
            <hi rend="italic">Sp. Nitr. d.</hi> On <lb/><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 20th, <hi
            rend="italic">Calomel.</hi> Gr. v. were given for Four <lb/>Nights ſucceſſively, and
          afterwards purged off with <lb/>a Sena Potion, and then continued again till the
          <lb/>28th, when he took another Potion.—Paregorics <lb/>were uſed now-and-then at Night,
          and <hi rend="italic">Ung. Opo- <lb/>deldoc</hi> was applied to the <hi rend="italic"
            >Teſticle</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 4th, I firſt attended him in Conſultation, <lb/>when he
          complained of an intolerable Pain, upon <lb/>any Preſſure about the Region of the Left
          Kidney; <pb n="102"/>
          <lb/>whereupon a maturating Cataplaſm was applied in <lb/>the Day time, and a Plaiſter at
          Night. Emulſions, <lb/>Whey, and ſuch-like, were the chief Internals he <lb/>uſed till <hi
            rend="italic">April</hi> 8th, when crude Mercury was recom- <lb/>mended to him, of which
          he took an Ounce Night <lb/>and Morning, which gave ſo much Relief as to en- <lb/>courage
          the Continuance of that Medicine only to <lb/>the 17th, when the Pains returning, he was
          bled <lb/>once in Two or Three Days, to Four or Five Ounces, <lb/>and treated with the
          ſubacid, cooling Regimen, and <lb/>Paregorics, till <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 29th,
          when he firſt mentioned <lb/>a ſcirrhous Tumour, as big as a Hen's Egg, ſituate on
          <lb/>the Left Maſtoid Muſcle of the Neck. Upon com- <lb/>paring this with the <hi
            rend="italic">Teſticle</hi>, (neither of which Tu- <lb/>mours were in the leaſt
          diminiſhed after Applications <lb/>for that Purpoſe) it was conjectured, that either the
          <lb/>Pancreas or Meſenteric Glands were cancerated. An <lb/>Emetic of <hi rend="italic"
            >Oxym. Scillit.</hi> farinaceous Decoctions <lb/>with Nitre, crude <hi rend="italic">Sal
            Armoniac, Oxym. Simp.</hi> and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Diacod.</hi> were of little or no
          Effect.—Afterwards <lb/>continuing the Uſe of Electuaries of <hi rend="italic">Conſ. Roſ.
            r. <lb/>Elect. Lenitiv. Balſ. Locatel. Æthiop. Min. Sperm. <lb/>Cet. Ol. Amygd. d.</hi>
          and the ſame with <hi rend="italic">Mercur. Al- <lb/>calizat.</hi> he became more and more
          emaciated, till <lb/><hi rend="italic">May</hi> 21ſt, the Day of his Death.— </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It was remarkable, that every new Medicine, ex- <lb/>cept it was very heating,
          afforded ſome Relief for <lb/>Two or Three Days. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">May</hi> 22d, On removing the Integuments of the <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Muſculi Recti</hi> appeared livid.—The
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi> was deſtitute of Fat.—The <hi rend="italic"
            >Inteſtine</hi> con- <lb/>tiguous to the Left <hi rend="italic">Os Innominatum</hi> was
          tinged with <lb/>Green.—Nothing beſides appeared morbid in the <pb n="103"/>
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Viſcera in Situ</hi> at firſt View.—The Situation of the <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Pylorus</hi> ſeemed lower than uſual. The Colour or <lb/>Texture of the
          Liver were not remarkably preter- <lb/>natural. The Spleen was of the largeſt Size, and
          <lb/>adhered in its hinder Part ſo ſtrongly to the <hi rend="italic">Peri-
            <lb/>tonæum</hi>, that it could not be ſeparated without La- <lb/>ceration.—Whereupon
          there remained in the Place <lb/>of Adheſion a thick, callous, and almoſt horny Mem-
          <lb/>brane, as big as an Half-crown.—The <hi rend="italic">Pancreas</hi>
          <lb/>was very ſmall, and ſeemed compoſed of ſmall <lb/><hi rend="italic">Scirrhi</hi>.—The
          Left Kidney was twice as big as the <lb/>Right, or as its own natural Magnitude: Its Sub-
          <lb/>ſtance about the <hi rend="italic">Pelvis</hi> was corroded by a ſemipu- <lb/>rulent
          cancerous <hi rend="italic">Sanies</hi>, that was in part collected <lb/>between the
          Surface of the Kidney and its containing <lb/>Bag. The internal Structure of it was not
          much <lb/>amiſs: But the <hi rend="italic">Fomes Morbi</hi>, the moſt ſingular and
          <lb/>ſurpriſing <hi rend="italic">Phænomenon</hi> in this Subject, was a Num- <lb/>ber of
          large conglobate, ſteatomatous, cancerated <lb/>Glands, reaching from the <hi
            rend="italic">Receptaculum Chyli</hi> to the <lb/>loweſt <hi rend="italic">Vertebræ</hi>
          of the Loins, ſo connected together <lb/>as to repreſent a <hi rend="italic">Pancreas</hi>
          affixed to the <hi rend="italic">Vertebræ</hi>
          <lb/>of the Loins, and upper anterior Part of the Left <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pſoas</hi>
          Muſcle: It was Four times as large as his <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pancreas</hi>, and as big
          as the Right or ſound Kidney. <lb/>—The <hi rend="italic">Aorta deſcendens</hi> pervaded
          the Middle of <lb/>this preternatural Subſtance Lengthways.—From <lb/>this Maſs, as a
          Fountain, flowed that cancerous Sa- <lb/>nies, which had made its Way to the Left Kidney,
          and <lb/>alſo corroded the ſuperior carneous Part of the Left <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pſoas
            major</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Iliacus internus</hi>, ſo that one might <lb/>eaſily
          rend their gangrened Fleſh like rotten Linen. <lb/>—Some of this green <hi rend="italic"
            >Ichor</hi> collected near the <hi rend="italic">Os </hi>
          <pb n="104"/>
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Innominatum</hi> had laid the Spine of it quite bare. <lb/>The Left
          ſpermatic Veſſels were knotty, tumefied, <lb/>and livid—The meſenteric Glands were
          ſcirrhous. <lb/>The deſcending Trunk of the <hi rend="italic">Aorta</hi> was ſmaller than
          <lb/>uſual; and, dividing it, we extracted a ſmall <hi rend="italic">Polypus</hi>.
          <lb/>—The Examination of the other Cavities was not <lb/>permitted.— </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>II. </head>
        <dateline rend="space align-right">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 11. 1735-6. </dateline>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Thomas Trinder</hi>, a Taylor, living at <hi rend="italic"
            >Windſor</hi>, <lb/>in his 29th Year, was of a pale Complexion, with <lb/>red Hair, of a
          middle Stature, and thin Habit, ad- <lb/>dicted to ſmoaking from Morning to Night, and
          now- <lb/>and-then to hard drinking. Eight Years before his <lb/>Death, he was thrown in
          Wreſtling, ſo as to pitch <lb/>the Small of his Back upon the Corner of a Chair, <lb/>by
          which at firſt he was much hurt in that Part; but <lb/>upon the Abatement of his Pain, he
          became from <lb/>that time ſubject to Fits of the Colic, in which he <lb/>ſaid his Bowels
          ſeemed to be drawn to his Back-bone, <lb/>and uſually received Eaſe by binding his Waiſt
          as <lb/>tight as he could.—He had alſo frequent recourſe <lb/>to Geneva and ſuch Liquors
          for Relief, but ſeldom <lb/>found any, till a Swelling, as big as a Hen's Egg, ap-
          <lb/>peared like a Rupture in his Right Groin. Theſe <lb/>Fits were not of above 24 Hours
          Duration, but the <lb/>inguinal Tumor laſted Two or Three Days. He was <lb/>often
          afflicted with Stitches under his Left Breaſt, <lb/>which were removed by Bleeding. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But in the Middle of <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 1735. his Colic <lb/>became ſo
          violent, that he could not lie in his Bed, <lb/>nor ſleep without Opiates.—<hi
            rend="italic">November</hi> 21. I found <pb n="105"/>
          <lb/>him in the Uſe of ſome carminative Pills ſent by an <lb/>Apothecary. He had frequent
          Reachings to vomit, <lb/>and was very coſtive. His Pains ſeemed confined to <lb/>the
          inteſtinal Region, and were moſt acute in the <lb/>Evening, continuing to haraſs him till
          Five or Six <lb/>in the Morning. His Pulſe beat ſeldom under an <lb/>Hundred in a Minute,
          at Night generally above. He <lb/>was not very hot, nor thirſty. His Urine at this
          <lb/>Time was rather defective in Quantity, than amiſs <lb/>in reſpect of Colour or
          Separation.—His Tongue was <lb/>foul towards the Root, but not very white.—Upon <lb/>his
          taking <hi rend="italic">Ipecacuan.</hi> ʒſs. and after its Operation a <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Sal. Abſinth.</hi> Draught, with <hi rend="italic">Syr.</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">Tinct. Rhabarb. <lb/>ā</hi> ʒij, and the plentiful Uſe of <hi
            rend="italic">Infuſ. Sem. Lini</hi>, <lb/>Barley-water, Broths, and Clyſters of Whey,
          Oil, and <lb/>Honey, his Reachings ceaſed, and the Pains de- <lb/>ſcended from the <hi
            rend="italic">Epigaſtrium</hi> to the <hi rend="italic">Hypogaſtrium</hi>. <lb/>On <hi
            rend="italic">November</hi> 24th, a Potion of <hi rend="italic">Tinct. Rhabarb. cum
            <lb/>Vino</hi> ℥iij. <hi rend="italic">Elix. pp. Helm. <hi rend="roman">ʒj.</hi> Sal.
            Abſinth. <hi rend="roman">℈ſs.</hi></hi> and <lb/>Two purgative Clyſters, one of which
          had <hi rend="italic">Terebinth <lb/><hi rend="roman">℥ſs</hi> cum Vitel. Ov.</hi> not
          procuring a Stool, he took a <lb/>Bolus of <hi rend="italic">Calomel <hi rend="roman"
              >ʒſs</hi> &amp; Camphor. <hi rend="roman">gr. xij.</hi> h. ſ.</hi> and <lb/>the Next
          Day his Pains continued, though he had <lb/>ſeveral Dejections from the Cathartic.
          Bleeding was <lb/>omitted hitherto, becauſe he had ℥x. of Blood taken <lb/>away a Week
          before this Paroxyſm; but now, upon <lb/>loſing ſo much Blood more, he found immediate
          <lb/>Relief. His Blood was very ſizy. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>After this, his Diſorder reſembled a Nephritic <lb/>one, his chief Complaint being of
          Pain about the <lb/>Region of the Kidneys, and along the Deſcent of <lb/>the Ureters. From
            <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 26th, upon the Uſe <lb/>of an oily <hi rend="italic"
            >Linctus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Manna</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Sal. Abſinth.</hi>
          Draughts <pb n="106"/>
          <lb/>and Nitre, Clyſters as well as Drinks of Whey and <lb/>Honey, with Paregorics, and
          repeated Bleeding, the <lb/>Pain, removing from the Loins, fixed itſelf at the <hi
            rend="italic">Os <lb/>Pubis</hi>, and in the Thighs, <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 29.
          but by the <lb/>Uſe of Emulſions with Gum Arabic and Nitre, the <lb/>Pain about the <hi
            rend="italic">Pubis</hi> abated, and moſtly afflicted the <lb/>Left Thigh and Hip. From
          this Time he generally <lb/>ſat up in his Bed, leaning forward to the Left, and <lb/>for
          the moſt part croſs-legged, finding himſelf eaſieſt <lb/>in this Poſture. He could not lie
          any time on his <lb/>Right Side.—The Quantity, Colour, and Sediment <lb/>of his Urine,
          were much the ſame now as when he <lb/>was in Health.—It was made without the Pain,
          <lb/>which, ſoon after the nephritic Symptoms com- <lb/>menced, he complained of at the
          Root of the <hi rend="italic">Penis</hi>. <lb/>And now his Diſorder reſembled the <hi
            rend="italic">Lumbago</hi> and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Sciatica</hi>, affecting the Left
          Side moſtly: Where- <lb/>upon, <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 2d, he was put in the Uſe
          of a <lb/>diuretic and aperient Electuary, with <hi rend="italic">Terebinthinate</hi>
          <lb/>Clyſters.—To this Time he had very few Stools <lb/>without Clyſters, and thoſe
          generally very ſmall and <lb/>fetid. <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 5th, the Fever and
          Pain in- <lb/>creaſing, a cooling aperient Apozem, with a pare- <lb/>goric Draught <hi
            rend="italic">pro re nata</hi>, were continued till <hi rend="italic">De-
            <lb/>cember</hi> 9th, when examining the Thigh where the <lb/>Pain now afflicted him
          moſt, I found ſome ſmall <lb/><hi rend="italic">Scirrhi</hi> in the Groin, which were
          ſenſible enough to <lb/>the Touch, though not to the Sight; and from that <lb/>Time,
          apprehending him of a ſcrophulous Habit, <lb/>preſcribed as follows: ℞ <hi rend="italic"
            >Myrrh. Milleped. Suc. <lb/>Glycyrrhiz. Terebinth. Venet. Pil. Matth. ā <hi rend="roman"
              >℈j.</hi> Balſ. <lb/>Gilead. <hi rend="roman">℈ſs</hi> Diacod. q. ſ. f. Pilulæ N<hi
              rend="sup">o</hi>
            <hi rend="roman">xx.</hi> Capiat <hi rend="roman">ij</hi>
            <lb/>tertiis horis cum Sero Lactis</hi>, which giving Relief, were <pb n="107"/>
          <lb/>repeated, only exchanging <hi rend="italic">Pil. Matth. gr. <hi rend="roman"
              >viij.</hi></hi> for <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ol. Aniſ. g<hi rend="sup">tt</hi>
            <hi rend="roman">v.</hi></hi> and continued to <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 12th,
          <lb/>when his Pains returned violently, and he coughed <lb/>up clotted Matter, not unlike
          the <hi rend="italic">Parenchyma</hi> of the <lb/>Lungs abraded, with a little Blood. His
          Breath be- <lb/>came fetid, his Reſpiration troubled, and he com- <lb/>plained of Thirſt.
          He uſed oily paregoric Draughts <lb/>to the 15th, about which Time he was ſeized with
          <lb/>ſo violent a pleuritic Pain, in the Middle of the <lb/>Night, that it was thought he
          muſt have expired, <lb/>had not about ℥x of Blood been taken away imme- <lb/>diately, upon
          which the Pain ſoon removed from <lb/>the Side, and attacked him there but for a few Mi-
          <lb/>nutes afterwards. The Blood continued as ſizy as <lb/>ever. In the Evenings, when his
          Pains were moſt <lb/>vehement, he had been ſometimes delirious. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">December</hi> 18th, he firſt told me of a Tumor he <lb/>had
          diſcovered near the Navel, ſince I ſaw him on <lb/>the 15th. It appeared not as he ſat,
          but when laid <lb/>on his Back, there was a Protuberance bigger than a <lb/>Turkey's Egg,
          Four Fingers Breadth on the Left Side <lb/>of the Navel, extending Two above it, and Four
          <lb/>below it. By its Situation, Reſiſtance to Preſſure, <lb/>and the Unevenneſs that from
          under the Skin was <lb/>communicated to the Touch, its diſappearing when <lb/>he was in an
          erect Poſture, and its not being dimi- <lb/>niſhed by diſcutient Fomentations, it was
          judged to <lb/>be a ſcirrhous Tumor, which had long exiſted there <lb/>unobſerved by the
          Patient, till it increaſed too much <lb/>to be longer undiſcovered.—The <hi rend="italic"
            >Emplaſt. de Ran. <lb/>&amp; cum Mercur.</hi> was applied outwardly; and conclu-
          <lb/>ding there was an internal Cancer, I was encouraged, <lb/>from the preceding Caſe, to
          order him <hi rend="italic">Hydrargyr. </hi>
          <pb n="108"/>
          <lb/>℥j every Morning.—Whereupon there was ſuch a <lb/>Remiſſion of his Pains, that during
          almoſt a Fort- <lb/>night, he got more Reſt without Opiates than before <lb/>with them;
          inſomuch that being greatly revived, and <lb/>regaining ſome Appetite, he got down Stairs
          Two or <lb/>Three times. Thinking the Plaiſter increaſed his <lb/>Pain, Indigo blue Linen
          was applied in its room. <lb/>The Mercury came away by Stool, and he had now <lb/>one
          almoſt every Day, and ſometimes twice a Day, <lb/>without a Clyſter.—His chief Drink was
          Milk and <lb/>warm Water.—His grand Complaint now was of <lb/>a moſt troubleſome <hi
            rend="italic">Cardialgia</hi>, eſpecially when he <lb/>lay down, which was ſomewhat
          mitigated by Pow- <lb/>ders of <hi rend="italic">Cret. Britan. cum pauxillo Sal.
            Abſinth</hi>. From <lb/>the firſt Uſe of the Mercury he ſeemed on the mend- <lb/>ing
          hand, till after about 12 Days, when omitting <lb/>it for a few Days, he relapſed into his
          former or a <lb/>worſe Condition; and though he was ſomewhat <lb/>eaſier on the Repetition
          of it, the good Effects laſted <lb/>not long.—He drooped daily from the 4th of <hi
            rend="italic">Ja- <lb/>nuary</hi>, and on the 13th died, emaciated and almoſt <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">exanguis</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Upon Diſſection, nothing preternatural appeared <lb/>in the Integuments, abdominal
          Muſcles, or <hi rend="italic">Perito- <lb/>neum</hi> immediately under them.—But under all
          <lb/>theſe, where the Protuberance had been obſerved, <lb/>and immediately under the <hi
            rend="italic">Omentum</hi>, (which was <lb/>deſtitute of Fat, and its lower Part was
          mortified) <lb/>there came in View an anomalous Subſtance <hi rend="italic">in Situ</hi>,
          <lb/>ſeemingly as big as a very large Potatoe; which, <lb/>when the circumambient <hi
            rend="italic">Viſcera</hi> were removed, was <lb/>found to be a ſcirrhous, fungous,
          cancerated Excre- <lb/>ſcence, rooted, as it were, to the Left Side of the <pb n="109"/>
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Vertebræ</hi>, quite from the <hi rend="italic">Diaphragm</hi> down
          to the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pelvis</hi>, of a monſtrous Bulk, occupying near one
          <lb/>half of the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, lying like a Tortoiſe with its <lb/>Head
          towards the <hi rend="italic">Pelvis</hi>, and its Back to the <hi rend="italic">Umbi-
            <lb/>licus</hi>. It was in the upper Part covered by and firmly <lb/>cohered with the
            <hi rend="italic">Colon</hi>, which in the whole Conti- <lb/>guity was black and
          mortified. It was ſtrongly at- <lb/>tached to the <hi rend="italic">Peritoneum</hi> on the
          Left Side of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Lumbal Vertebræ</hi>, having diſplaced the Left
          Kidney, <lb/>and brought it forwards to the Left Side of the <lb/>Navel, ſo that it came
          in View as ſoon as the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi> was removed. It likewiſe
          removed the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Aorta deſcendens</hi>, the Left Emulgent, and Meſeraic
          <lb/>Veſſels, quite out of their natural Situation; all of <lb/>which were found pervading
          the Centre, nearly, of <lb/>this Excreſcence, and ſmaller than natural.—It <lb/>adhered to
          the Kidney ſtrongly where the emulgent <lb/>Veſſels enter it, and it had detruded moſt of
          the <lb/>ſmall Guts into the <hi rend="italic">Pelvis</hi>.—Nothing was preter-
          <lb/>natural in the Stomach or Spleen, excepting that the <lb/>latter, as well as the Left
          Kidney, ſeemed paler than <lb/>uſual, and this Kidney alſo more flaccid: The Gall-
          <lb/>bladder was ſhrunk to the Size of a Nutmeg, and <lb/>empty.—The Liver had a
          preternatural Lobule, as <lb/>big as a Hazel-nut, adhering to it by a ſmall Pe-
          <lb/>dicle. But otherwiſe all theſe <hi rend="italic">Viſcera</hi>, as well as the
          <lb/>Right Kidney, Bladder, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> diſcovered nothing
          <lb/>morbid.— </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This cancerated Excreſcence could not be eradi- <lb/>cated without Laceration, and
          upon the Removal <lb/>of it, Two or Three large Trunks or Nerves appeared <lb/>naked,
          paſſing over the <hi rend="italic">Iliacus internus</hi> to the Thigh, <lb/>which had been
          compreſſed by this Tumor. The <pb n="110"/>
          <lb/>Weight of this Excreſcence was ℔iv┼℥xiv; and <lb/>allowing for what remained upon
          Laceration, and <lb/>the Effuſion upon cutting into it, it doubtleſs ex- <lb/>ceeded ℔v.
          Upon Biſection, it appeared to the <lb/>Depth of half an Inch from its Surface black and
          <lb/>gangrened, and, below that, it was all ſpongy, with <lb/>Cavities as large as thoſe
          of an Honeycomb; and <lb/>from it had iſſued a cancerous Sanies, draining to the <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Pelvis</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Upon opening the <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi>, the Right Lobe of the <lb/>Lungs was
          full of ſcirrhous cancerated Tubercles, <lb/>from whence a Sanies had flowed betwixt it
          and the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pleura</hi>: The Left Lobe was much ſmaller than the
          <lb/>Right, firmly attached to the <hi rend="italic">Pleura</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
            >Mediaſti- <lb/>num</hi>, and inſeparable without Dilaceration.—It had <lb/>ſome
          Tubercles alſo. The Heart appeared ſound, <lb/>but a large <hi rend="italic">Polypus</hi>
          was taken out of its Right Ven- <lb/>tricle, at the Orifice of the <hi rend="italic"
            >Arteria Pulmonalis</hi>.— </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Another Caſe occurred to me contemporary with <lb/>the firſt of theſe, and ſo like to
          both of them in the <lb/>antecedent Cauſe and Symptoms, that, could I have <lb/>obtained
          Leave to inſpect the Corpſe, I am perſuaded <lb/>ſome ſuch immediate Cauſe would have
          diſcovered <lb/>itſelf.—Crude Mercury was the only Medicine in <lb/>this Caſe alſo, that
          palliated for about Ten Days <lb/>ſucceſſively. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But to what Purpoſe ſo particular a Relation of <lb/>Caſes confeſſedly incurable? It
          is replied, That in <lb/>unſucceſsful Caſes an accurate Diagnoſtic tends not <lb/>a little
          to the Reputation of the Phyſician, and his <lb/>Science, although thereupon he pronounces
          the Caſe <lb/>incurable by all the known Methods of regular <lb/>Practitioners—Eſpecially
          as this Caſe is very likely <pb n="111"/>
          <lb/>to be miſtaken at firſt for an Arthritic Diſorder, or a <lb/>Nephritic one, either
          from Ulcer, <hi rend="italic">Calculus</hi>, or both, <lb/>or for an <hi rend="italic"
            >Iliac Paſſion</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Diagnoſtics therefore of a Cancer within the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>,
          deduced from the preceding Hiſtories, <lb/>ſeem to be as follows: </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A naturally ſlender Habit of Body, accompanied <lb/>with ſome ſcrophulous or
          ſcirrhous Tumor, together <lb/>with a pale Complexion, and coſtive Diſpoſition: If
          <lb/>ſuch an one, at an Age above Twenty, has received a <lb/>violent Contuſion on the
          Loins, and, neglecting all <lb/>Remedies, is ſome time afterwards attacked with
          <lb/>exceſſive Pains, afflicting now the <hi rend="italic">Colon</hi>, then the
          <lb/>urinary Paſſages, Spine of the <hi rend="italic">Os Innominatum</hi>, and <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Pubes</hi>, at various times, always inceaſed by all In- <lb/>ternals or
          Externals, by which the Heat of the Body is <lb/>increaſed, eſpecially <hi rend="italic"
            >Terebinthinate</hi> Clyſters; but <lb/>mitigated by ſome Singularity of Poſture, in
          which <lb/>the Patient conſtantly abides; if theſe be attended <lb/>with an Hectic Fever,
          without the uſual Degree of <lb/>Heat in the Skin, of Whiteneſs or Dryneſs of Tongue,
          <lb/>or Complaint of Thirſt, and alſo without Cough, <lb/>high-coloured Urine, or vitiated
          Reſpiration; if ac- <lb/>companied likewiſe with an Affection of the ſper- <lb/>matic
          Veſſels, of the Thighs, and frequent pleuritic <lb/>Pains; the Blood always abounding with
          tough Size: <lb/>if Opiates ſoon loſe their Effect, and only (as all other <lb/>new
          Remedies not heating) ſeem to give Relief for <lb/>Two or Three Days; if Cathartics take
          Place, and by <lb/>frequent Repetition do not produce a colliquative <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Diarrhœa</hi>, and the moſt palliative Remedies are nitrous <lb/>Salts and
          Mercurial; may it not be concluded with <lb/>much Probability, that ſuch a Caſe is owing
          to ſome <lb/>ſuch Cauſe? May it not be pronounced an internal <lb/>Cancer? </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
