<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: An Account of Margaret Cutting, a Young Woman</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of Margaret Cutting, a Young Woman, Now Living at Wickham Market in
              Suffolk, Who Speaks Readily and Intelligibly, Though She Has Lost Her Tongue</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for T. Woodward, and C. Davis, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn; Printers to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1742-1743</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">42</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">143-152</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110356674</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1742.0037</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT42_0143">
    <body>
      <pb n="143"/>
      <head rend="hanging italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XI.</hi> An Account of <hi rend="roman">Margaret Cutting</hi>, a young
        <lb/>Woman, now living at <hi rend="roman">Wickham Market</hi>
        <lb/>in <hi rend="roman">Suffolk</hi>, who ſpeaks readily and intel- <lb/>ligibly, though
        ſhe has loſt her Tongue. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="italic size(0.7)">Read <date rend="roman">July 1. <lb/>1742.
          </date>
        </note><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Brief Account of this young Wo- <lb/>man's Caſe, in a Letter
        from Mr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Benjamin Boddington</hi>, of <hi rend="italic">Ipſwich</hi>,
          <hi rend="italic">Turkey-Merchant</hi>, <lb/>to Mr. <hi rend="italic">Henry Baker</hi>, F.
        R. S. was communicated to <lb/>the <hi rend="sc">Royal Society</hi> in the Month of <hi
          rend="italic">February</hi>
        <lb/>laſt, and appeared ſo extraordinary, that Mr. <hi rend="italic">Baker</hi>
        <lb/>was deſired to make all poſſible Inquiries into the <lb/>Reality of the Fact, and lay
        before the <hi rend="sc">Society</hi> what <lb/>Information he ſhould receive in relation
        thereto. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In purſuance of this, he wrote to Mr. <hi rend="italic">Boddington</hi>, <lb/>and
        begged the Favour of him to make the ſtricteſt <lb/>and moſt critical Inquiry he was able
        into this Affair, <lb/>not only by viewing the young Woman's Mouth, and <lb/>examining her
        himſelf, but alſo by calling to his <lb/>Aſſiſtance ſome skilful Gentleman in the Phyſical
        <lb/>Way, and any other learned and judicious Perſon <lb/>whom he might judge moſt likely to
        contribute to- <lb/>wards diſcovering the real Truth, and detecting any <lb/>Error, Fallacy,
        or Impoſition. He likewiſe deſired <pb n="144"/>
        <lb/>they would heedfully obſerve her Manner of ſpeak- <lb/>ing and articulating the Sounds
        of thoſe Letters and <lb/>Syllables, in the Formation whereof the <hi rend="italic"
          >Apex</hi> of the <lb/>Tongue ſeems more particularly needful: And, in <lb/>order to
        render their Examination more eaſy, as well <lb/>as more ſatisfactory, he ſent a Liſt of
        Letters and <lb/>Sounds, together with ſeveral ſuch Sentences as he <lb/>imagined would be
        moſt difficult to be pronounced <lb/>without the Help of the Tongue. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Boddington</hi>, as ſoon after this as their Affairs <lb/>would
        give them Leave, prevailed upon Mr. <hi rend="italic">Notcutt</hi>, <lb/>a Miniſter, a
        learned and curious Gentleman, and <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Hammond</hi>, who perfectly
        underſtands Anatomy, <lb/>to accompany him to <hi rend="italic">Wickham Market</hi>, about
        Twelve <lb/>Miles from <hi rend="italic">Ipſwich</hi>, where the young Woman lives;
        <lb/>whoſe Caſe (after they had inſpected her Mouth, and <lb/>examined her in the ſtricteſt
        Manner) is ſet forth in <lb/>the following Certificate ſigned by them all. </p>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <dateline rend="space align-right">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ipſwich</hi>, <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 9. 1742. </dateline>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">W</hi>E have this Day been at <hi rend="italic">Wickham
              Market</hi>, to <lb/>ſatisfy our Curioſity concerning <hi rend="italic">Margaret
              <lb/>Cutting</hi>, a young Woman, who, we were informed, <lb/>could talk and diſcourſe
            without a Tongue. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>She informed us, that ſhe was now more than <lb/>Twenty Years of Age, born at <hi
              rend="italic">Turnſtal</hi>, a Village <lb/>within Four Miles of <hi rend="italic"
              >Wickham Market</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Suffolk</hi>, <lb/>where ſhe loſt her Tongue
            by a Cancer [being then <lb/>about Four Years old]. It firſt appeared like a ſmall
            <lb/>black Speck on the upper Superficies of the Tongue, <lb/>and ſoon eat its Way quite
            to the Root of it. She was <lb/>under the Care of Mr. <hi rend="italic">Scotchmore</hi>,
            a Surgeon of <hi rend="italic">Sax- <lb/>mundham</hi>, who ſoon pronounced the Caſe
            incurable: <pb n="145"/>
            <lb/>However, he continued uſing the beſt Means he could <lb/>for her Relief. One Day
            when he was Syringing of <lb/>it, the Tongue dropped out, and they received it into
            <lb/>a Plate, the Girl, to their Amazement, ſaying to her <lb/>Mother, <q
              rend="diple quotes">Don't be frighted, Mamma; 'twill grow <lb/>again. </q> It was near
            a Quarter of a Year after, before <lb/>it was quite cured. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>We proceeded to examine her Mouth with the <lb/>greateſt Exactneſs we could, but
            found not the leaſt <lb/>Appearance of any remaining Part of a Tongue, nor <lb/>was
            there any <hi rend="italic">Uvula</hi>. We obſerved a fleſhy Excre- <lb/>ſcence on the
            under Left Jaw, extending itſelf almoſt <lb/>to the place where the <hi rend="italic"
              >Uvula</hi> ſhould be, about a <lb/>Finger broad: This Excreſcence, ſhe ſaid, did not
            <lb/>begin to grow till ſome Years after the Cure: It is by <lb/>no means moveable, but
            quite fixed to the Parts <lb/>adjacent. The Paſſage down the Throat, at the Place
            <lb/>where the <hi rend="italic">Uvula</hi> ſhould be, or a little to the Right <lb/>of
            it, is a circular open Hole, large enough to admit <lb/>a ſmall Nutmeg. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Notwithſtanding the want of ſo neceſſary an Organ <lb/>as the Tongue was generally
            ſuppoſed to be, to form <lb/>a great Part of our Speech, and likewiſe to be aſſiſt-
            <lb/>ing in Deglutition, to our great Admiration, ſhe per- <lb/>formed the Office of
            Deglutition, both in ſwallowing <lb/>Solids and Fluids, as well as we could, and in the
            <lb/>ſame manner: And as to Speech, ſhe diſcourſed as <lb/>fluently and well as other
            Perſons do; though we <lb/>obſerved a ſmall Sound, like what is uſually called
            <lb/>ſpeaking through the Noſe; but, ſhe ſaid, ſhe had <lb/>then a great Cold, and ſhe
            believed that occaſioned <lb/>it. She pronounced Letters and Syllables very arti-
            <lb/>culately; the Vowels ſhe pronounced perfectly, as alſo <pb n="146"/>
            <lb/>thoſe Conſonants, Syllables, and Words, that ſeemed <lb/>necessary to require the
            Help of the Tongue, <lb/>as <note place="bottom" n="*">
              <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
                <lb/>* Theſe were the Letters, Sounds and Sentences mentioned by <lb/>Mr. <hi
                  rend="italic">Baker</hi>. </p>
            </note><hi rend="italic">d, l, t, n, r, at, al, ath, aſh, cha, la, ta, ja. The
              <lb/>little Dog did not eat Bread.—Touch the Tooth. <lb/>—Try to light the Candle.—
              Thrice Thirty- <lb/>three.— Let the large Cat ſcratch the little <lb/>Dog.— The
              Church.— doth.— Lilly.—</hi> All <lb/>theſe ſhe pronounced perfectly. She read to us
            in a <lb/>Book very diſtinctly and plain; only we obſerved, <lb/>that ſometimes ſhe
            pronounced words ending in <hi rend="italic">ath</hi>
            <lb/>as <hi rend="italic">et—</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">end</hi> as <hi rend="italic">emb—</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">ad</hi> as <hi rend="italic">eib—</hi>; but it required a <lb/>nice
            and ſtrict Attention to obſerve even this Differ- <lb/>ence of Sound. She ſings very
            prettily, and pro- <lb/>nounced her Words in Singing as is common. What <lb/>is ſtill
            very wonderful, notwithſtanding the Loſs of <lb/>this uſeful Organ the Tongue, which is
            generally <lb/>allowed by Anatomiſts, and Natural Philoſophers, to <lb/>be the chief, if
            not the ſole Organ of Taſte, ſhe diſtin- <lb/>guiſhes all Taſtes very nicely, and can
            tell the leaſt <lb/>perceivable Difference in either Smell or Taſte. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>We the Underwritten do atteſt the above to be a <lb/>true Account. </p>
          <signed rend="align-right">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Benjamin Boddington</hi>. <lb/><hi rend="italic">William
              Notcutt</hi>, Miniſter. <lb/><hi rend="italic">William Hammond</hi>, Apothecary.
          </signed>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <p rend="space indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Baker</hi> received along with the foregoing Cer- <lb/>tificate,
        by Letter from Mr. <hi rend="italic">Boddington</hi>, ſome farther <lb/>Particulars, which
        he ſuppoſed leſs material.—He <lb/>ſays, in her Perſon ſhe is a little thin Body, genteel
          <pb n="147"/>
        <lb/>enough, a pretty good Face, fair Complexion, with <lb/>light-brown Hair, of a weakly
        Conſtitution, lame on <lb/>one Side, through Weakneſs after a Fever and the <lb/>Small-pox,
        which ſhe had laſt Summer. She ſeems <lb/>a well-behaved Girl, and has nothing of a Country
        <lb/>Mien. She diſcourſes agreeably, very fluently and <lb/>pertinently, has every thing
        clean and neat about her, <lb/>gets her Livelihood by making Mantuas, and has an <lb/>Aunt
        in <hi rend="italic">London</hi>, named <hi rend="italic">Mary Cutting</hi>, who is Houſe-
        <lb/>keeper to the Dowager Lady <hi rend="italic">Rochford</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Bond-
          <lb/>ſtreet</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He ſays, if ſhe were among Twenty People in a <lb/>Room, he thinks it would be
        impoſſible for a Stranger <lb/>by any means to gueſs her being the Perſon without <lb/>a
        Tongue, for ſhe has no odd Motion of her Mouth <lb/>or Lips in Speaking: She ſings with an
        eaſy Air, and <lb/>modulates her Voice prettily.—He asked her, if <lb/>ſhe did not miſs her
        Tongue, or find any Inconve- <lb/>nience from the Want of it? She anſwered, No: Not <lb/>in
        the leaſt; nor could ſhe imagine what Advantage <lb/>he had in the Uſe of his. He inquired,
        how ſhe did <lb/>to guide her Food in her Mouth to eat: She replied, <lb/>very eaſily, ſhe
        could eat before, on one Side or the other <lb/>as ſhe pleaſed, but could not explain the
        Manner <lb/>how. He was very obſerving to ſee her eat, but <lb/>could diſcern no Difference
        from others in the moving <lb/>of her Jaws, or other Motions of her Face, nor in her
        <lb/>ſwallowing Food, or in drinking; ſhe did both very <lb/>neatly, and had exactly the
        ſame Motion in her <lb/>Throat as we have in its paſſing down. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He was apprehenſive the Excreſcence mentioned in <lb/>the Certificate, might, in ſome
        meaſure, ſupply the <lb/>Uſe of a Tongue; but ſhe aſſured him, it never <pb n="148"/>
        <lb/>moved in the leaſt, and that ſhe ſpoke as well before <lb/>it began to grow (which was
        ſeveral Years after the <lb/>Cure); and Mr. <hi rend="italic">Hammond</hi> convinced him, by
        trying <lb/>with their Fingers and a Spoon, that it was quite fixt <lb/>and immoveable.—He
        obſerves further, that ſhe is <lb/>no ways aſſiſted by a good Set of Teeth; for ſhe has
        <lb/>but few, thoſe bad, and ſcarce ſo high as her Gums.— <lb/>He asked her, in what Part of
        her Mouth her moſt <lb/>ſenſible Taſte lay? She ſaid, it was all over alike; and,
        <lb/>ſmiling, added, She was afraid ſhe was too nice in <lb/>that; for, if her Butter was
        not curious, ſhe eat dry <lb/>Bread. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Boddington</hi>, in another Letter to Mr. <hi rend="italic">James
          <lb/>Theobald</hi>, F. R. S. dated the 14th of <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 1742. after
        <lb/>giving an Account of this young Woman in the Man- <lb/>ner as before, adds, He can
        recollect nothing more, <lb/>except her telling him, that though ſhe was able to <lb/>ſpeak
        from the very firſt loſing of her Tongue, ſhe <lb/>was not ſo happy as to her Deglutition;
        for ſhe was <lb/>unable to ſwallow any thing ſolid for many Months <lb/>after, without its
        being minced very fine, and then <lb/>thruſt into her Throat by a Finger: But by degrees,
        <lb/>ſhe knows not how, ſhe became able to manage with- <lb/>out that Help, and could eat
        any thing in the ſame <lb/>manner as other Perſons can.—He adds, That, in his <lb/>own Mind,
        he thinks the fleſhy Excreſcence is of <lb/>great Service to her, though ſhe cannot make out
        in <lb/>what manner: That for his own part, he had for- <lb/>merly ſuppoſed it as impoſſible
        to ſpeak without a <lb/>Tongue, as to ſee without Eyes; and therefore expects <lb/>many, who
        ſhall hear this Account, will continue <lb/>Unbelievers, and think he and his Friends are
        all <lb/>miſtaken, that they do not know what they ſee, and <pb n="149"/>
        <lb/>that their Ignorance is the only Ground of their Ad- <lb/>miration. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>While Mr. <hi rend="italic">Baker</hi> was making his Inquiries, he was <lb/>informed,
        that Mr. <hi rend="italic">John Dennis</hi>, Tobacconiſt, in <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Alderſgate-ſtreet</hi>, could give him a full and ſatiſ- <lb/>factory Account of this
        Affair: He therefore applied <lb/>to Mr. <hi rend="italic">Dennis</hi>, who aſſured him in a
        very civil, <lb/>candid and intelligent Manner, that he was well ac- <lb/>quainted with <hi
          rend="italic">Margaret Cutting</hi>, having many Years <lb/>ago been carried by a
        Gentleman to ſee her as a Pro- <lb/>digy for being able to ſpeak without a Tongue: That
        <lb/>he had ſeen her ſeveral times ſince, commonly calling <lb/>on her when he travels that
        Way, and carrying ſome <lb/>Friend or other with him; and at all theſe times he <lb/>had
        inſpected her Mouth, and was ſure ſhe had no <lb/>Tongue: And that laſt Summer, in
        particular, he <lb/>and another went to ſee her: That he would declare <lb/>this under his
        Hand, and ſhould always be ready to <lb/>atteſt the Truth of it to any Body, or in any
        Manner. <lb/>He likewiſe gave an Account how ſhe loſt her Tongue, <lb/>as he had it from her
        Mother, who died ſome Years <lb/>ago, and it was exactly as above related; and ſaid he
        <lb/>had been told the ſame by an Apothecary alſo, who <lb/>had her in Hand along with Dr.
          <hi rend="italic">Scotchmore</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Teſtimony of Mr. <hi rend="italic">Dennis</hi>, and the Perſon who <lb/>ſaw her
        with him laſt Summer, is as follows: </p>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <dateline rend="space align-center">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 20. 1741. </dateline>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">W</hi>E the under-written ſaw <hi rend="italic">Margaret
              Cutting</hi>, at <lb/><hi rend="italic">Wickham Market</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
              >Suffolk</hi>, in or about <hi rend="italic">June</hi>
            <lb/>laſt; and, examining her Mouth, found ſhe had no <lb/>Tongue, and yet ſhe ſpeaks
            very intelligibly. </p>
          <signed rend="align-right">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">John Dennis</hi>. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Gabriel Daniells</hi>.
          </signed>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <floatingText><body>
        <pb n="150"/>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">M</hi>Yſelf ſaw her in about Two or Three Years after <lb/>her
          Tongue was loſt, had a full Account of it <lb/>from her Mother, heard her then ſpeak, and
          have <lb/>ſeen and heard her divers times ſince, and heard her <lb/>talk better and
          better. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>She was under the Care of Dr. <hi rend="italic">Scotchmore</hi> at <hi rend="italic"
            >Sax- <lb/>mundham, Suffolk</hi>. </p>
        <signed rend="align-right">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">John Dennis</hi>. </signed></body>
      </floatingText>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Dennis</hi> (upon Mr. <hi rend="italic">Baker</hi>'s Inquiry)
        wrote to <lb/>the young Woman herſelf, acquainting her, that <lb/>many People would not
        believe it poſſible for her to <lb/>ſpeak without a Tongue, and deſiring ſhe would not
        <lb/>be aſhamed to give an Account of herſelf under her <lb/>own Hand; in Anſwer to which he
        received the fol- <lb/>lowing Letter: </p>
      <floatingText><body>
        <head rend="italic space align-center">
          <lb/>To Mr. <hi rend="roman">John Dennis</hi>, in <hi rend="roman">Alderſgate-ſtreet</hi>. </head>
        <salute rend="italic space indent">
          <lb/>Sir, </salute>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">T</hi>HIS being the firſt Opportunity that I had to <lb/>anſwer
          your Letter, I aſſure you, that I have no <lb/>more Tongue in my Mouth than I had when you
          ſaw <lb/>me laſt, which is none, but, Thanks be to my <hi rend="sc">God</hi>, <lb/>I have
          had the Happineſs to ſpeak ever ſince it came <lb/>out, which was when I was about Four
          Years old. As <lb/>for my Age now, I cannot rightly tell, but I think I <lb/>am about
          Twenty-four Years old. I would have <lb/>none ſuſpect the Truth of it; for I have no
          Tongue, <lb/>and can ſpeak very well, and this is from my own <lb/>Hand. I was not aſhamed
          to write about myſelf, but <lb/>of my bad Writing. So no more, but I am </p>
        <signed rend="italic align-right">
          <lb/>Your humble Servant, <lb/><hi rend="roman">Margaret Cutting</hi>. </signed></body>
      </floatingText>
      <pb n="151"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Caſe of this young Woman is indeed extraor- <lb/>dinary <note n="*" place="bottom">
          <p rend="indent size(0.8)">
            <lb/>* <hi rend="italic">N. B. </hi>All the original Papers are in the Repoſitory of the
              <hi rend="italic">Royal <lb/>Society</hi>. </p>
        </note>; but there are ſeveral Examples of like Na- <lb/>ture to be met with in medical
        Writers, and thoſe of <lb/>the greateſt Authority; one of which, as it has the
        <lb/>Atteſtation of a whole Univerſity, cannot be im- <lb/>proper to mention here. <hi
          rend="italic">Monſieur Drelincourt</hi>, a <lb/>very noted Phyſician, tells us, in his
        Treatiſe on the <lb/>Small-pox, of a Child Eight Years of Age, who had <lb/>loſt his Tongue
        by that Diſtemper, and was yet able <lb/>to ſpeak, to the Aſtoniſhment of the Univerſity of
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Saumur</hi> in <hi rend="italic">France</hi>; and that the
        Univerſity (who <lb/>doubtleſs had firſt carefully examined into the Truth) <lb/>had
        atteſted it, by drawing up a particular Account <lb/>of the Fact, that Poſterity might have
        no room to <lb/>doubt concerning the Validity of it. The Account <lb/>is to be met with at
        large, in the Third Volume of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Ephemerides Germanicæ</hi>, under
        the Title of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Agloſſoſtomographia</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tulpius</hi> too makes mention of a Man who had the <lb/>Miſfortune
        to have his Tongue cut out by the <hi rend="italic">Turks</hi>, <lb/>and yet, after Three
        Years, could ſpeak very diſtinctly. <lb/>He ſays, he went himſelf to <hi rend="italic"
          >Weſop</hi>, a Town in <hi rend="italic">Hol- <lb/>land</hi>, to be ſatisfied of the Truth
        of it, and found it <lb/>to be as it was reported. Nay, he does not ſo much <lb/>as mention
        any Defect in his Speech, but aſſures us, <lb/>that he could pronounce thoſe Letters which
        depend <lb/>upon the <hi rend="italic">Apex</hi> of the Tongue, even the Conſonants,
        <lb/>very articulately. And this Caſe is ſtill the more <lb/>worthy Attention, becauſe the
        Patient could not <lb/>ſwallow even the leaſt Quantity of Food, unleſs he <lb/>thruſt it
        into the <hi rend="italic">Oeſophagus</hi> by means of his Finger. </p>
      <pb n="152"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If we go back to earlier Times, the Emperor <lb/><hi rend="italic">Juſtin</hi>, in <hi
          rend="italic">Cod. Tit. de Off. Præf. Præt. Af.</hi> ſays, he <lb/>had ſeen venerable Men,
          <hi rend="italic">qui abſciſſis <hi rend="roman">radicitus</hi> Linguis, <lb/>pœnas
          miſerabiliter <hi rend="roman">loquebantur</hi>, whoſe Tongues having <lb/>been cut out
            <hi rend="roman">by the Roots</hi>, they miſerably <hi rend="sc">spoke</hi></hi>, or
        <lb/>complained, of the <hi rend="italic">Puniſhments</hi> they had ſuffered. And
        <lb/>again, <hi rend="italic">Nonnullos alios, quibus <hi rend="roman">Honorichius</hi>
          Vanda- <lb/>lorum Rex Linguas <hi rend="roman">radicitus</hi> præciderat, <hi rend="roman"
            >loquelam <lb/>tamen habuiſſe integram</hi></hi>, that ſome others, whoſe <lb/>Tongues
          <hi rend="italic">Honorichius</hi>, King of the <hi rend="italic">Vandals</hi>, had cut
        <lb/>out by the Roots, <hi rend="italic">yet perfectly retained their Speech</hi>. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
