<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Fothergill: Recovering a Man Dead in Appearance, by Distending the
          Lungs with Air</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>John Fothergill</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Observations on a Case Published in the Last Volume of the Medical Essays,
              &amp;c. of Recovering a Man Dead in Appearance, by Distending the Lungs with Air.
              Printed at Edinburgh, 1744; by John Fothergill, Licent. Coll. Med. Lond.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for C. Davis, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn; Printer to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date/>
              <biblScope unit="vol">43</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">275-281</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110113631</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1744.0061</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT43_0275">
    <body>
      <pb n="275"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XI.</hi> Obſervations on a Caſe publiſhed in the laſt <lb/>Volume of
        the <hi rend="roman">Medical Eſſays</hi>, &amp;c. of <hi rend="roman">Reco- <lb/>vering</hi>
        a Man <hi rend="roman">Dead</hi> in Appearance, by diſ- <lb/>tending the <hi rend="roman"
          >Lungs</hi> with Air. Printed at <lb/><hi rend="roman">Edinburgh, 1744</hi>; by <hi
          rend="roman">John Fothergill</hi>, <lb/>Licent. Coll. Med. Lond. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="italic size(0.7)">Read <date rend="roman">Feb. 21. <lb/>1744-5.
          </date> Now <lb/>printed with <lb/>Additions. </note><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HERE are ſome
        Facts, which, in <lb/>themſelves, are of ſo great Im- <lb/>portance to Mankind, or which
        <lb/>may lead to ſuch uſeful Diſcoveries, that it would <lb/>ſeem to be the Duty of every
        one, under whoſe No- <lb/>tice they fall, to render them as extenſively public as <lb/>it is
        poſſible. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Caſe which gives Riſe to the following Re- <lb/>marks, I apprehend, is of this
        Nature: It is an Ac- <lb/>count of <hi rend="italic">
          <q rend="diple quotes">A Man, dead in Appearance, recovered by <lb/>diſtending the Lungs
            with Air; by Mr. <hi rend="roman">William <lb/>Toſſack</hi>, Surgeon in <hi rend="roman"
              >Alloa</hi>; </q></hi> printed in Part 2. p. 605. <lb/>Vol. V. of the <hi
          rend="italic">Medical Eſſays</hi>, publiſhed by a Society <lb/>of Gentlemen at <hi
          rend="italic">Edinburgh</hi>; an Abſtract of which <pb n="276"/>
        <lb/>will be ſufficient in this Place: Thoſe who deſire an <lb/>ampler Account may conſult
        the Article itſelf. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A Perſon ſuffocated by the <hi rend="italic">nauſeous Steam</hi> ariſing <lb/>from
        Coals ſet on Fire in the Pit, fell down as dead; he <lb/>lay in the Pit <hi rend="italic"
          >between half an Hour and three Quarters</hi>; <lb/>and was then dragg'd up; <hi
          rend="italic">his Eyes ſtaring and open, his <lb/>Mouth gaping wide, his Skin cold; not
          the leaſt <lb/>Pulſe in either Heart or Arteries, and not the leaſt <lb/>Breathing to be
          obſerved</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In theſe Circumſtances, the Surgeon, who relates <lb/>the Affair, <hi rend="italic"
          >applied his Mouth cloſe to the Patient's, <lb/>and, by blowing ſtrongly, holding the
          Noſtrils at the <lb/>ſame time, raiſed his Cheſt fully by his Breath</hi>. <lb/>The
        Surgeon <hi rend="italic">immediately felt ſix or ſeven very quick <lb/>Beats of the Heart;
          the Thorax continued to play, <lb/>and the Pulſe was ſoon after felt in the Arteries.
          <lb/>He then opened a Vein in his Arm; which, after <lb/>giving a ſmall Jet, ſent out the
          Blood in Drops <lb/>only for a Quarter of an Hour, and then he bled freely. <lb/>In the
          mean time he cauſed him to be pull'd, puſh'd, <lb/>and rubb'd, as much as he could. In one
          Hour the <lb/>Patient began to come to himſelf; within four Hours <lb/>he walked home; and
          in as many Days returned to <lb/>his Work.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There were many Hundred People, ſome of them <lb/>of Diſtinction, preſent at the Time. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This is the Subſtance of the Account; from whence <lb/>it naturally appears how much
        ought to be attributed <lb/>to the Sagacity of the Surgeon in the Recovery of <lb/>this
        Perſon. Anatomiſts, it is true, have long known, <lb/>that an artificial Inflation of the
        Lungs of a dead or <lb/>dying Animal will put the Heart in Motion, and <lb/>continue it ſo
        for ſome time; yet this is the firſt <pb n="277"/>
        <lb/>Inſtance I remember to have met with, wherein the <lb/>Experiment was applied to the
        happy Purpoſe of re- <lb/>ſcuing Life from ſuch imminent Danger. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Bleeding has hitherto been almoſt the only Refuge <lb/>upon theſe Occaſions: If this
        did not ſucceed, the <lb/>Patient was given up. By Bleeding, it was propoſed <lb/>to give
        Vent to the ſtagnating Blood in the Vein, in <lb/>order to make Way for that in the Arteries
          <hi rend="italic">à tergo</hi>, <lb/>that the Reſiſtance of the Heart being thus
        diminiſhed, <lb/>this Muſcle might again be put in Motion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But, in too many Inſtances, we every Day are in- <lb/>formed, that this Operation will
        not ſucceed, tho' the <lb/>Aperture is made with never ſo much Skill: Nor is <lb/>it likely,
        that it ſhould, when the Blood has loſt con- <lb/>ſiderably of its Fluidity, the Motion of
        the Heart, and <lb/>the contractile Force of the Solids, are at an End. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Chafing, Rubbing, Pulling, the Application of <lb/>Stimulants, are too often as
        ineffectual as Bleeding. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Method of diſtending the Lungs of Perſons, <lb/>dead in Appearance, having been
        try'd with ſuch Suc- <lb/>ceſs in one Inſtance, gives juſt Reaſon to expect, that <lb/>it
        may be uſeful to others. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It may be a proper Inquiry, In what Caſes, and <lb/>under what Circumſtances, there may
        be a Proſpect <lb/>of applying it with Succeſs? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It will at once be granted, That when the Juices <lb/>are corrupted, where they are
        rendered unfit for Cir- <lb/>culation by Diſeaſes, where they are exhauſted, or <lb/>where
        the Tone and Texture of the Solids is injured <lb/>or deſtroyed, it would be extreme Folly
        to think of <lb/>any Expedient to recover Life. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But where the Solids are whole, and their Tone <lb/>unimpair'd by Diſeaſes, the Juices
        not vitiated by <pb n="278"/>
        <lb/>any other Cauſe than a ſhort Stagnation; where <lb/>there is the leaſt Remains of
        animal Heat, it would <lb/>ſeem wrong not to attempt ſo eaſy an Experiment. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This Deſcription takes in a few Diſeaſes, but a <lb/>greater Number of Accidents.
        Amongſt the firſt are <lb/>many of thoſe which are called ſudden Deaths from <lb/>ſome
        inviſible Cauſe; Apoplexies, Fits of various Kinds, <lb/>as Hyſterics, <hi rend="italic"
          >Syncope's</hi>, and many other Diſorders, <lb/>wherein, without any obvious
        Præ-indiſpoſition, Per- <lb/>ſons in a Moment ſink down and expire. In many <lb/>of theſe
        Caſes it might be of Uſe to apply this Me- <lb/>thod; yet without neglecting any of thoſe
        other <lb/>Helps, which are uſually called in upon theſe melan- <lb/>choly Occaſions. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is not eaſy to enumerate all the various Caſual- <lb/>ties, in which this Method
        might be try'd not with- <lb/>out a Proſpect of Succeſs; ſome of them are the fol-
        <lb/>lowing: Suffocations from the ſulphureous Damps of <lb/>Mines, Coal-pits, <hi
          rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> the condenſed Air of long- <lb/>unopen'd Wells, or other
        ſubterraneous Caverns; <lb/>the noxious Vapours ariſing from fermenting Liquors
        <lb/>received from a narrow Vent; the Steam of burn- <lb/>ing Charcoal; ſulphureous mineral
        Acids; arſenical <lb/><hi rend="italic">Effluvia</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Perhaps thoſe, who, to Appearance, are ſtruck dead <lb/>by Lightning, or any violent
        Agitation of the Paſ- <lb/>ſions, as Joy, Fear, Surprize, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        might frequently <lb/>be recover'd by this ſimple Proceſs of ſtrongly blow- <lb/>ing into
        the Lungs, and by that means once more <lb/>communicating Motion to the vital Organs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Malefactors executed at the Gallows would afford <lb/>Opportunities of diſcovering how
        far this Method <lb/>might be ſucceſsful in relieving ſuch as may have <pb n="279"/>
        <lb/>unhappily become their own Executioners, by hang- <lb/>ing themſelves. It might at
        leaſt be try'd, if, after <lb/>the Criminals have hung the uſual Time, inflating the
        <lb/>Lungs, in the Manner propoſed, would not, ſome- <lb/>times, bring them to Life. The
        only ill Conſequence <lb/>that could accrue from a Diſcovery of this kind would <lb/>be
        eaſily obviated by prolonging the preſent allotted <lb/>Time of Suſpenſion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But this Method would ſeem to promiſe very much <lb/>in aſſiſting thoſe who have been
        ſuffocated in the <lb/>Water, under the above mentioned Circumſtances; <lb/>at leaſt it
        appears neceſſary to recommend a Trial of <lb/>it, after the Body has been diſcharged of the
        Water <lb/>admitted into it, by placing it in a proper Poſition, <lb/>the Head downwards,
        prone, and, if it can be, acroſs <lb/>a Barrel, Hogſhead, or ſome ſuch-like convex Support,
        <lb/>with the utmoſt Expedition. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It does not ſeem abſurd, to compare the animal <lb/>Machine to a Clock; let the wheels
        whereof be in <lb/>never ſo good Order, the Mechaniſhm complete in <lb/>every Part, and
        wound up to the full Pitch, yet, <lb/>without ſome Impulſe communicated to the <hi
          rend="italic">Pendu- <lb/>lum</hi>, the Whole continues motionleſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thus, in the Accidents deſcribed, the Solids are <lb/>ſuppoſed to be whole and elaſtic,
        the Juices in ſuf- <lb/>ficient Quantities, their Qualities no otherwiſe vi- <lb/>tiated
        than by a ſhort Stagnation, from the Qui- <lb/>eſcence of that <hi rend="italic">moving
          Something</hi> which enables Mat- <lb/>ter in animated Bodies to overcome the Reſiſtance
        <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Medium</hi> it acts in. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Inflating the Lungs, and, by this means, commu- <lb/>nicating Motion to the Heart, like
        giving the firſt <lb/>Vibration to a <hi rend="italic">Pendulum</hi>, may poſſibly, in many
          <pb n="280"/>
        <lb/>Caſes, enable this <hi rend="italic">Something</hi> to reſume the Govern- <lb/>ment of
        the Fabric, and actuate its Organs afreſh, till <lb/>another unavoidable Neceſſity puts a
        Stop to it in- <lb/>tirely. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It has been ſuggeſted to me by ſome of my Ac- <lb/>quaintance, that a Pair of Bellows
        might poſſibly <lb/>be applied with more Advantage in theſe Caſes, than <lb/>the Blaſt of a
        Man's Mouth; but, if any Perſon can <lb/>be got to try the charitable Experiment by blowing,
        <lb/>it would ſeem preferable to the other: 1<hi rend="italic">ſt.</hi> As the <lb/>Bellows
        may not be at hand: 2<hi rend="italic">dly</hi>, As the Lungs of <lb/>one Man may bear,
        without Injury, as great a Force <lb/>as thoſe of another Man can exert; which by the
        <lb/>Bellows cannot always be determin'd: 3<hi rend="italic">dly</hi>, The <lb/>Warmth and
        Moiſture of the Breath would be more <lb/>likely to promote the Circulation, than the
        chilling <lb/>Air forced out of a Pair of Bellows. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To conclude, as I apprehend, the Method above <lb/>deſcribed may conduce to the ſaving
        a great many <lb/>Lives, as it is practicable by every one who happens <lb/>to be preſent at
        the Accident, without Loſs of Time, <lb/>without Expence, with little Trouble, and leſs
        Skill, <lb/>and as it is, perhaps, the only Expedient of which it <lb/>can be juſtly ſaid,
        that it may poſſibly do <hi rend="italic">great Good</hi>, <lb/>but cannot do Harm, I
        thought it of ſo much Con- <lb/>ſequence to the Public, as to deſerve to be recom-
        <lb/>mended in this Manner to your Notice: For tho' it <lb/>is already publiſhed in a Work
        which is generally <lb/>read by the Faculty; yet, perhaps, it may be over- <lb/>looked by
        ſome, forgot by others, and perhaps, after <lb/>all the Care that can be taken, it may never
        come <pb n="281"/>
        <lb/>to the Knowledge of a Tenth of thoſe who ought <lb/>not to be ignorant of it. </p>
      <signed rend="size(1.2) align-right">
        <lb/>John Fothergill. </signed>
      <postscript>
        <p rend="hanging space">
          <lb/>
          <label rend="italic">P. S. </label> As the Repreſentation of an extraordinary <lb/>Fact
          may perhaps induce ſome to try the Experi- <lb/><choice>
            <corr>ment</corr>
            <sic>riment</sic>
          </choice>, when Occaſions like thoſe which are ſpe- <lb/>cified in the above Remarks
          occur, it is hoped, <lb/>that Humanity will prompt all ſuch to favour the <lb/>Public with
          an Account of their Succeſs, with the <lb/>principal Circumſtances that attended. And as
          <lb/>the Writer of theſe Remarks has embarked in the <lb/>Deſign of rendering this Fact
          diffuſively known, <lb/>he would be glad to have it in his Power to in- <lb/>form the
          Public, that numerous Experiments con- <lb/>firm what this Caſe ſuggeſts; <hi
            rend="italic">viz.</hi> the Poſſibility <lb/>of ſaving a great many Lives, without
          risking any <lb/>thing. </p>
      </postscript>
      <dateline rend="italic indentall hanging space size(0.7)">
        <lb/>White-Hart Court, Gracious-Street, <lb/>7ber, 1744. </dateline>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
