<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Rolli, Bianchini and Hilliard: Upon the Death of the Countess Cornelia
          Zangari &amp; Bandi, of Cesena</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Paul Rolli</persName>
              <persName>Joseph Bianchini</persName>
              <persName>John Hilliard</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Extract, by Mr. Paul Rolli, F. R. S. of an Italian Treatise, Written by the
              Reverend Joseph Bianchini, a Prebend in the City of Verona; Upon the Death of the
              Countess Cornelia Zangari &amp; Bandi, of Cesena. To Which are Subjoined Accounts of
              the Death of Jo. Hitchell, Who was Burned to Death by Lightning; And of Grace Pett at
              Ipswich, Whose Body was Consumed to a Coal</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for C. Davis, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn; Printer to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1744</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">43</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">447-465</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110113631</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1744.0088</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT43_0447">
    <body>
      <pb n="447"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XVI.</hi> An Extract, by Mr. <hi rend="roman">Paul Rolli</hi>, F. R.
        S. <lb/>of an <hi rend="roman">Italian</hi> Treatiſe, written by the Reve- <lb/>rend <hi
          rend="roman">Joſeph Bianchini</hi>, a Prebend in the <lb/>City of <hi rend="roman"
          >Verona</hi>; upon the Death of the <lb/>Counteſs <hi rend="roman">Cornelia Zangári &amp;
          Bandi</hi>, of <lb/><hi rend="roman">Ceſéna</hi>. To which are ſubjoined Accounts of
        <lb/>the Death of <hi rend="roman">Jo. Hitchell</hi>, who was burned to <lb/>Death by
        Lightning; and of <hi rend="roman">Grace Pett</hi> at <lb/><hi rend="roman">Ipſwich</hi>,
        whoſe Body was conſumed to a Coal. </head>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <epigraph rend="size(0.6)">
        <p rend="italic indent">
          <lb/>Satius eſt de re ipſa quærere, quam mirari. <hi rend="sc align-right">Seneca. </hi>
        </p>
      </epigraph>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <div>
        <dateline rend="space size(0.8) align-right">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ceſéna</hi>, <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 4. 1731. </dateline>
        <p>
          <lb/>
          <note rend="italic size(0.7)" place="inset">Read <date rend="roman">June 20. <lb/>1745.
            </date>
          </note><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE Counteſs <hi rend="italic">Cornelia Bandi</hi>, in
          <lb/>the 62d Year of her Age, was all <lb/>Day as well as ſhe uſed to be; but at Night was
          ob- <lb/>ſerved, when at Supper, dull and heavy. She re- <lb/>tired, was put to Bed, where
          ſhe paſſed three Hours <lb/>and more in familiar Diſcourſes with her Maid, and <lb/>in
          ſome Prayers; at laſt, falling aſleep, the Door <lb/>was ſhut. In the Morning, the Maid,
          taking notice <lb/>that her Miſtreſs did not awake at the uſual Hour, <lb/>went into the
          Bed-chamber, and called her; but not <lb/>being anſwer'd, doubting of ſome ill Accident,
          <lb/>open'd the Window, and ſaw the Corpſe of her Miſ- <lb/>treſs in this deplorable
          Condition. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Four Feet Diſtance from the Bed there was a Heap <lb/>of Aſhes, two Legs untouch'd,
          from the Foot to <lb/>the Knee, with their Stockings on; between them was <lb/>the Lady's
          Head; whoſe Brains, Half of the Back- <pb n="448"/>
          <lb/>part of the Scull, and the whole Chin, were <lb/>burnt to Aſhes; amongſt which were
          found three <lb/>Fingers blacken'd. All the reſt was Aſhes, which <lb/>had this particular
          Quality, that they left in the <lb/>Hand, when taken up, a greaſy and ſtinking
          <lb/>Moiſture. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Air in the Room was alſo obſerved cumber'd <lb/>with Soot floating in it: A ſmall
          Oil-Lamp on the <lb/>Floor was cover'd with Aſhes, but no Oil in it. <lb/>Two Candles in
          Candleſticks upon a Table ſtood up- <lb/>right; the Cotton was left in both, but the
          Tallow was <lb/>gone and vaniſhed. Somewhat of Moiſture was about <lb/>the Feet of the
          Candleſticks. The Bed receiv'd no <lb/>Damage; the Blankets and Sheets were only raiſed
          <lb/>on one Side, as when a Perſon riſes up from it, or <lb/>goes in: The whole Furniture,
          as well as the Bed, <lb/>was ſpread over with moiſt and aſh-colour Soot, <lb/>which had
          penetrated into the Cheſt-of-drawers, even <lb/>to foul the Linnens: Nay the Soot was alſo
          gone <lb/>into a neighbouring Kitchen, and hung on the Walls, <lb/>Moveables, and Utenſils
          of it. From the Pantry a <lb/>Piece of Bread cover'd with that Soot, and grown <lb/>black,
          was given to ſeveral Dogs, all which refuſed <lb/>to eat it. In the Room above it was
          moreover taken <lb/>notice, that from the lower Part of the Windows <lb/>trickled down a
          greaſy, loathſome, yellowiſh Liquor; <lb/>and thereabout they ſmelt a Stink, without
          knowing <lb/>of what; and ſaw the Soot fly around. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It was remarkable, that the Floor of the Chamber <lb/>was ſo thick ſmear'd with a
          gluiſh Moiſture, that it <lb/>could not be taken off; and the Stink ſpread more <lb/>and
          more through the other Chambers. </p>
        <pb n="449"/>
        <floatingText><body>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>REMARKS. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">I</hi>T is impoſſible, that, by any Accident, the Lamp
            <lb/>ſhould have cauſed ſuch a Conflagration. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>There is no Room to ſuppoſe any ſupernatural <lb/>Cauſe. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The likelieſt Cauſe then is a Flaſh of Lightning; which, <lb/>according to the moſt
            common Opinion, being put a <lb/>ſulphureous and nitrous Exhalation from the Earth,
            <lb/>having been kindled in the Air, did penetrate either thro' <lb/>the Chimney, or
            thro' the Chinks of the Windows, <lb/>and did the Operation. All the above mentioned
            <lb/>Effects prove the Aſſertion; for thoſe remaining foul <lb/>Particles are the
            groſſeſt Parts of the <hi rend="italic">Fulmen</hi>, either <lb/>burnt to Aſhes, or
            thickened into a viſcous bitu- <lb/>minous Matter. Hence no Wonder the Dogs would
            <lb/>not eat of the Bread, becauſe of the Bitterneſs of the <lb/>Soot, and Stink of the
            Sulphur that lodged on it. <lb/>The impalpable Aſhes of the Lady's Corpſe are alſo a
            <lb/>Demonſtration; for nothing but a <hi rend="italic">Fulmen</hi> could pro- <lb/>duce
            ſuch an Effect. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>They ſay that there was not any Noiſe; but may <lb/>be there was, and they heard it
            not, being in a ſound <lb/>Sleep: Beſides, there have been ſeen Lightnings and <lb/><hi
              rend="italic">Fulmina</hi> without Noiſe; as one may very often ob- <lb/>ſerve. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure></body>
        </floatingText>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>THIS is the whole <hi rend="italic">Narration</hi>; after which I think <lb/>proper
          to place what is ſaid in the Preface re- <lb/>lating to it. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>IN the <hi rend="italic">Acta Medica &amp; Philoſophica Hafnienſia</hi>,
          <lb/>publiſhed by the celebrated <hi rend="italic">Thomas Bartolin</hi>, 1673. <pb n="450"/>
          <lb/>Vol. II. p. 211. n. 118. one may ſee ſuch another <lb/>Accident related in theſe very
          Words. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>
          <q rend="diple quotes">A poor Woman at <hi rend="italic">Paris</hi> uſed to drink Spirit
            <lb/>of Wine plentifully for the Space of three Years, <lb/>ſo as to take nothing elſe.
            Her Body contracted <lb/>ſuch a combuſtible Diſpoſition, that one Night ſhe, <lb/>lying
            down on a Straw-Couch, was all burned to <lb/>Aſhes and Smoke, except the Scull, and the
            Extre- <lb/>mities of her Fingers. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">John Henry Cohauſen</hi> relates this Fact in a Book <lb/>printed
          at <hi rend="italic">Amſterdam</hi> 1717, intituled, <hi rend="italic">Lumen novum
            <lb/>Phoſphoris accenſum</hi>; and in the firſt Part, p. 92. <lb/>relates alſo, <q
            rend="diple quotes">That a <hi rend="italic">Poliſh</hi> Gentleman, in the Time <lb/>of
            the Queen <hi rend="italic">Bona Sforza</hi>, having drank two <lb/>Diſhes of a Liquor
            called Brandy-Wine, vomited <lb/>Flames, and was burnt by them. </q>
        </p>
        <floatingText><body>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>REMARKS. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">S</hi>UCH an Effect was not produced by the Light of <lb/>the
            Oil-Lamp, or of any Candles; becauſe common <lb/>Fire, even in a Pile, does not conſume
            a Body to <lb/>ſuch a Degree; and would have beſides ſpread itſelf <lb/>to the Goods of
            the Chamber, more combuſtible <lb/>than a human Body. It ſeems alſo, that it was not
            <lb/>what is commonly taken for a <hi rend="italic">Fulmen</hi>; for there <lb/>was not
            left in the Place any ſulphureous and nitrous <lb/>Smell: There did not appear any
            blackiſh Tracks <lb/>on the Walls; all Signs of the <hi rend="italic">Fulmina</hi>, as
            they have <lb/>been remarked by the exacteſt Obſerver of <hi rend="italic">Phæno-
              <lb/>mena</hi>, the celebrated Mr. <hi rend="italic">Boyle</hi>. But if it was not
            <lb/>a real <hi rend="italic">Fulmen</hi>, it was certainly of ſuch a Nature. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Some thought, that in the Ground under the Room <lb/>might have been a Mine of
            Sulphur: Which granted; <pb n="451"/>
            <lb/>what then? I know, by Experience, that in the very <lb/>Mines of Sulphur have
            periſhed ſome of the Miners, <lb/>but only by Suffocations cauſed by ſome ſudden co-
            <lb/>pious Exhalation of kindled Sulphur; and never by <lb/>having been burnt to Aſhes.
            The Miners have in- <lb/>formed me on the Spot, that thoſe of them who <lb/>periſhed,
            have been only choaked by a ſtrong nitrous <lb/>and ſulphureous <hi rend="italic"
              >Effluvium</hi>; but none of them by <lb/>having been ſet on Fire. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The Author relates, That, going once out of Cu- <lb/>rioſity into a Sulphur-Mine by
              <hi rend="italic">Montefiaſcone</hi>, when <lb/>near the Place from whence the Miners
            digg'd out <lb/>the Sulphur, he was adviſed by one of them, who <lb/>was carrying out
            his Load, not to go farther; for, <lb/>either the Smell, or ſome ſudden Exhalation,
            might <lb/>have done him great Injury; and when got again in the <lb/>open Air, told
            him, a few Days before three of his Fel- <lb/>low Miners fell ſtone-dead, while they
            were at Work, <lb/>by a violent Suffocation, cauſed by a ſtrong Exhala- <lb/>tion of
            bituminous Smoke, which burſt violently <lb/>from the Place where they were digging;
            which Miſ- <lb/>fortune was too frequent in ſuch Mines; but he <lb/>never heard nor ſaw,
            that any of them had been <lb/>burnt. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Thence it is concluded, that if the <hi rend="italic">Fulmina</hi> have <lb/>ſuch
            an Effect, the <hi rend="italic">Incendium</hi> proceeds originally <lb/>from their
            nitrous, and not from their ſulphureous <lb/>Parts; becauſe the Air, very cloſely
            impriſon'd in the <lb/>Nitre, and not in the Sulphur, either by its own <lb/>Elaſticity,
            or by ſome other Agent being put in Agi- <lb/>tation, produces the Flame of the <hi
              rend="italic">Fulmen</hi>, which <lb/>burns and conſumes any thing to Aſhes. </p>
          <pb n="452"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>I have, ſays he, ſeen the famous Sulphur-Spring, <lb/>a Mile diſtant from <hi
              rend="italic">Pozzoli</hi>, mentioned by <hi rend="italic">Petro- <lb/>nius
              Arbiter</hi>: At the lower End of the Plain there is <lb/>a Pit of liquid Sulphur,
            whoſe boiling Æſtuations <lb/>riſe ten or twelve Feet. Its liquid Matter conſumes
            <lb/>the Fleſh of any Corpſe, but does not affect the Bones <lb/>in the leaſt. In our
            Caſe the very Bones were burnt <lb/>to Aſhes; and ſtill the Pavement was not damaged.
            <lb/>No ſulphureous Smell remained in the Chamber. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>All this he advances, to oppoſe the Opinion of an <lb/>Academician at <hi
              rend="italic">Ravenna</hi>, who inſiſted, That under- <lb/>neath that Chamber muſt be
            a ſulphureous Mine. <lb/>Which Opinion he founds on this, That, in the very <lb/>Houſe,
            in a Room near that the Lady was burnt in, <lb/>there was ſet on Fire a good Quantity of
            Hemp, and <lb/>could not be found out by whom; as alſo, that, all <lb/>on a ſudden, Part
            of the Palace had fallen, and not <lb/>by any Earthquake; ſo that one might conjecture
            all <lb/>this to be Effects of the ſulphureous Mine under- <lb/>ground; Which is not
            proved by thoſe Aſſertions. <lb/>Nay, on the contrary, if there was a Mine of Sulphur,
            <lb/>one ſhould ſmell the Stink of it in thoſe dull Days, <lb/>when the nauſeous South
            Wind blows; the Sulphur <lb/>Mines then ſtinking at a great Diſtance: Beſides, the
            <lb/>Effects of Sulphur are not to reduce a Body into im- <lb/>palpable Aſhes. </p>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure></body>
        </floatingText>
        <floatingText><body>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Author</hi>'s Opinion. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">T</hi>HE Fire was cauſed in the Entrails of the Body by
            <lb/>inflamed <hi rend="italic">Effluvia</hi> of her Blood, by Juices and Fer-
            <lb/>mentations in the Stomach, by the many combuſtible <lb/>Matters which are abundant
            in living Bodies for the <lb/>Uſes of Life; and, finally, by the fiery Evaporations <pb
              n="453"/>
            <lb/>which exhale from the Settlings of Spirit of Wine, <lb/>Brandies, and other hot
            Liquors in the <hi rend="italic">Tunica vil- <lb/>loſa</hi> of the Stomach, and other
              <hi rend="italic">adipoſe</hi> or fat Mem- <lb/>branes; within which (as Chymiſts
            obſerve) thoſe <lb/>Spirits ingender a kind of Camphire; which, in the <lb/>Night-time,
            in Sleep, by a full Breathing and Reſpi- <lb/>ration, are put in a ſtronger Motion, and,
            conſe- <lb/>quently, more apt to be ſet afire. </p></body>
        </floatingText>
        <floatingText><body>
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>PROOFS. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>FAT is an oily Liquid ſeparated from the Blood by <lb/>the Glands of the <hi
              rend="italic">Membrana adipoſa</hi>; and it is of <lb/>an eaſily combuſtible Nature,
            as common Experience <lb/>ſhews. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Our Blood is of ſuch a Nature; as alſo our Lymph <lb/>and Bile: All which, when
            dry'd by Art, flame like <lb/>Spirit of Wine at the Approach of the leaſt Fire, <lb/>and
            burn away into Aſhes. [<hi rend="italic">Obſerv. <hi rend="roman">171.</hi> in the
                <lb/><hi rend="roman">Ephemeris</hi> of <hi rend="roman">Germany</hi>, <hi
                rend="roman">Anno X.</hi></hi>] </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Such a Drying-up of Matters may be cauſed in our <lb/>Body by drinking rectified
            Brandy, and ſtrong Wines; <lb/>as Monſieur <hi rend="italic">Litre</hi> obſerved in the
            Diſſection of a <lb/>Woman 45 Years old, in the Hiſtory of the <hi rend="italic">Royal
              <lb/>Academy of Sciences</hi>, 1706. p. 23. Which Effect <lb/>may oftener happen, if
            the Spirit of Wine has any <lb/>Mixture of Camphire: For that Liquor is but a ſub-
            <lb/>limated Oil, whoſe ſulphureous Particles, being atte- <lb/>nuated by the
            Fermentation, when ſeparated from <lb/>fixed and ſalt Matters, are eaſily put in Motion,
            and, <lb/>rolling thro' the Air, become Flame and Fire. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Beſides, altho' the Salts which are in living and <lb/>vegetable Creatures are not
            naturally inclined to kin- <pb n="454"/>
            <lb/>dle; nevertheleſs they often contribute to it, parti- <lb/>cularly, when there is
            join'd ſome ſtrong boiling <lb/>Fermentation. It is from ſuch a Cauſe, that we <lb/>know
            how the Mixture of two Liquors, altho' cold <lb/>to the Touch, produces a flaming Fire. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Becher</hi> was the firſt Diſcoverer of this marvel- <lb/>ous <hi
              rend="italic">Phænomenon</hi>, by mixing Oil of Vitriol with <lb/>that of Turpentine.
              <hi rend="italic">Borrichius</hi> afterwards did the <lb/>ſame, by mixing Oil of
            Turpentine with <hi rend="italic">Aquafortis</hi>; <lb/>and at laſt Monſieur <hi
              rend="italic">Tournefort</hi>, by joining Spirit of <lb/>Nitre with the Oil of <hi
              rend="italic">Saſſafras</hi>; and Monſieur <hi rend="italic">Hom- <lb/>berg</hi> with
            this acid Spirit, together with the Oil and <lb/>Quinteſſences of all the aromatic <hi
              rend="italic">Indian</hi> Herbs: Nay, <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Homberg</hi> aſſerts,
            that with a certain cold Water <lb/>Cannons were fired, <hi rend="italic">Anno</hi>
            1710. in the aboveſaid Hi- <lb/>ſtory of the <hi rend="italic">Academy of Sciences</hi>,
            p. 66. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is out of Queſtion, how, by a ſtrong Fermenta- <lb/>tion, Magazines of
            Gunpowder, Barns, Paper-Mills, <lb/>and Haycocks, have been ſet afire. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The acid Particles in our Bodies are much united <lb/>with the Fat and oily Parts;
            nay, all our Limbs <lb/>abound with Oil and Acid. What Wonder then, if <lb/>they may
            kindle? as Mr. <hi rend="italic">Homberg</hi> well obſerves, <lb/>in the aforeſaid
            Hiſtory, 1712. 1717. from p. 13. <lb/>to 31. where he takes notice, that all our Limbs
            have <lb/>abundance of fetid Oil, and volatile Salt, and there- <lb/>fore eaſily
            combuſtible. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>We ought not to omit how the Teeth are form'd <lb/>by ſo many ſhort Tubes, the
            Bones by long ones, <lb/>and eaſier therefore to be ſet on Fire. <hi rend="italic"
              >Malpighi</hi> ob- <lb/>ſerved alſo, that the Bones contain a fat oily Matter. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Beſides all this, we know that the <hi rend="italic">ſebaceous Glands</hi>
            <lb/>are ſpread all over the Body; and that an oily Moiſt- <pb n="455"/>
            <lb/>ure, with now-and-then a nitrous ſulphureous Smell, <lb/>perſpires from our Skin;
            to which Dr. <hi rend="italic">Blancard</hi>
            <lb/>aſcribes the whole Circulation. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Abundance of combuſtible Matter, ſhut up in a <lb/>great Number of Cells, lies in
            the <hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi>. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>There is further to be conſider'd the vaſt Quantity <lb/>of <hi rend="italic"
              >Effluvia</hi> that emanate from our Bodies. <hi rend="italic">Sanctorious</hi>
            <lb/>obſerved, that, of eight Pounds of Food and Drink <lb/>in a Day, there is an
            inſenſible Perſpiration of about <lb/>five; computing with them thoſe <hi rend="italic"
              >Effluvia</hi> which go <lb/>out of the Mouth by Breathing, and which might be
            <lb/>gathered in Drops on a Looking-glaſs [<hi rend="italic">Sect.</hi> 1. <lb/><hi
              rend="italic">Aphor.</hi> 6.]. As alſo, that, in the Space of one Night, <lb/>it is
            cuſtomary to diſcharge about 16 Ounces of Urine, <lb/>4 of concocted Excrements by
            Stool, and 40 and <lb/>more by Perſpiration [<hi rend="italic">Aphor.</hi> 59.]. He
            teaches alſo, <lb/>that Numbneſs is an Effect of too much internal Heat, <lb/>by which
            is prevented ſuch an inſenſible Tranſpiration; <lb/>as we will ſhew in this very Caſe. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>On this Suppoſition I ſay, that the <hi rend="italic">Effluvia</hi> of ſuch <lb/>an
            inſenſible Tranſpiration are an inflammable Mine, <lb/>eaſily apt to kindle, whenever a
            Friction, be it ever <lb/>ſo ſmall, puts them in quick Motion, and increaſes <lb/>their
            Velocity. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>We acknowledge the Diſcovery of this evident <lb/>Truth from Mr. <hi rend="italic"
              >Hauksbee, F. R. S.</hi> in the Experi- <lb/>ment ſo much known of the <hi
              rend="italic">Glaſs Globe</hi>, p. 30. <lb/>to which I refer the Reader. I ſaw this
            Experi- <lb/>ment at <hi rend="italic">Rome</hi>; and altho' it ſeems that the Light
            <lb/>be only <hi rend="italic">Phoſphorus</hi> produced by the <hi rend="italic"
              >Effluvia</hi> com- <lb/>ing out of the Hand, and of the Glaſs, it may never-
            <lb/>theleſs occaſion further Meditation on the preſent <lb/>Caſe. </p>
          <pb n="456"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The Friction of the Palms of our Hands, or of <lb/>any other Part of our Body, may
            produce thoſe <lb/>Fires commonly called <hi rend="italic">Ignes Lambentes</hi>. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>We learn of <hi rend="italic">Euſebius Nierembergius</hi>, that ſuch <lb/>was the
            Property of all the Limbs of the Father of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Theodoricus</hi>: ſuch
            were thoſe of <hi rend="italic">Charles Gonzaga</hi>, <lb/>Duke of <hi rend="italic"
              >Mantua</hi>, as the celebrated <hi rend="italic">Bartolin</hi> took <lb/>notice of.
            By the Teſtimony of <hi rend="italic">John Fabri, M. D.</hi>
            <lb/>a noted Philoſopher, who ſaw it, Sparkles of Light <lb/>flaſh'd out of the Head of
            a Woman, while ſhe <lb/>comb'd her Hair. <hi rend="italic">Scaliger</hi> relates the
            ſame of an- <lb/>other Woman. <hi rend="italic">Cardanus</hi>, of a <hi rend="italic"
              >Carmelite</hi> Monk, <lb/>whoſe Head continued 13 Years to flaſh out Sparkles,
            <lb/>every time he toſſed his Cowl on his Shoulders. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ezekiel à
              Caſtro, M. D.</hi> a famous <hi rend="italic">Jew</hi>, and after- <lb/>wards a <hi
              rend="italic">Chriſtian</hi>, wrote a little Treatiſe, intituled, <lb/><hi
              rend="italic">Ignis lambens</hi>; on the Occaſion that the Counteſs <lb/><hi
              rend="italic">Caſſandra Buri</hi>, of <hi rend="italic">Verona</hi>, when ſhe rubb'd
            her <lb/>Arms with a Cambrick Handkerchief, all the Skin <lb/>ſhined with a very bright
            Light. <hi rend="italic">Euſebius</hi> relates <lb/>the ſame of <hi rend="italic"
              >Maximus Aquilanus</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Licetus</hi> heard <lb/>ſay by his Father,
            that he ſaw the ſame Quality on <lb/><hi rend="italic">Francis Guido</hi>, a Civilian;
            and that he himſelf knew <lb/><hi rend="italic">Antony Cianfio</hi>, a Bookſeller in <hi
              rend="italic">Piſa</hi>, who, when <lb/>he ſhifted, ſhined all over with great
            Brightneſs. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Libavius</hi> relates the ſame of a Youth; and <hi
              rend="italic">Carda- <lb/>nus</hi> of a Friend of his; ſaying, that, when he ſhifted,
            <lb/>clear Sparkles of Fire ſhot forth of his Body. Father <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >Kircher</hi>, a Jeſuit, relates, how he, going in Com- <lb/>pany into a ſubterranean
            Grotto at <hi rend="italic">Rome</hi>, ſaw Sparkles <lb/>of Fire evaporate from the
            Heads of his Companions, <lb/>grown warm by walking. Father <hi rend="italic">Alphonſo
              d'Ovale</hi>
            <lb/>was Eye-witneſs on the higheſt Mountains of <hi rend="italic">Peru</hi>
            <pb n="457"/>
            <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Chili</hi>, how both Men and Beaſts there ſeem ſhining
            <lb/>with the brighteſt Light from Top to Toe. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Theſe Flames ſeem harmleſs, but it is only for <lb/>want of proper Fuel. <hi
              rend="italic">Peter Boviſteau</hi> aſſerts, that <lb/>ſuch Sparkles reduced to Aſhes
            the Hair of a young <lb/>Man. <hi rend="italic">John de Viana</hi>, in his Treatiſe
            intituled, <hi rend="italic">De <lb/>Peſte Malagenſi</hi>, p. 46. relates how the Wife
            of Doctor <lb/><hi rend="italic">Freilas</hi>, Phyſician to Cardinal <hi rend="italic"
              >de Royas</hi>, Archbiſhop <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Toledo</hi>, ſent forth
            naturally, by Perſpiration, a <lb/>fiery Matter, of ſuch a Nature, that if the Roller
            <lb/>that ſhe wore over her Shift was taken from her, and <lb/>expoſed to the cold Air,
            it immediately was kindled, <lb/>and ſhot forth like Grains of Gunpowder <note n="*"
              place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* <hi rend="italic">Pet. Borelli</hi> gives an Inſtance of ſuch <hi
                  rend="italic">Effluvia</hi> not only pro- <lb/>ducing Light, but likewiſe Fire.
                  <hi rend="italic">See</hi> his <hi rend="italic">Obſ. Cent. <hi rend="roman"
                    >II.</hi> Obſ. <hi rend="roman">75. <lb/>p. 174.</hi></hi> where he ſays, That
                there was a certain Peaſant, whoſe Li- <lb/>nen, hempen Thread, <hi rend="italic"
                  >&amp;c.</hi> if laid up in Boxes, tho' wet, or hung <lb/>upon Sticks in the Air,
                did ſoon take Fire; which hath been ſeen <lb/>by a great Number of Spectators. </p>
            </note>. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>After all this I ſay, that a feveriſh Fermentation, <lb/>or a very ſtrong Motion of
            combuſtible Matters, may <lb/>riſe in the Womb of a Woman, with ſuch an igne- <lb/>ous
            Strength that can reduce to Aſhes the Bones, and <lb/>burn the Fleſh. Two ſuch Caſes are
            known, one <lb/>in the <hi rend="italic">Acta Medica Philoſophica &amp; Hafnienſia</hi>,
              <hi rend="italic">Anno</hi>
            <lb/>1673. by the Obſervation of <hi rend="italic">Matt. Jacobei</hi>; and the
            <lb/>other in <hi rend="italic">M. Marcell. Donato, de Medic. Hiſt. Mirab. <lb/>lib. <hi
                rend="roman">IV.</hi> cap. <hi rend="roman">25, p. 248.</hi></hi> &amp; <hi
              rend="italic">lib. <hi rend="roman">VII.</hi> Coſmog. <hi rend="roman">c. 1.</hi></hi>
            of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cornel. Gemma.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>I ſay alſo, that the Bile, which is a neceſſary Juice <lb/>for our Digeſtion, was
            obſerved by <hi rend="italic">Peter Borelli</hi>, <lb/>that, being vomited up by a Man,
            it boiled like <lb/><hi rend="italic">Aqua fortis</hi>. [<hi rend="italic">Centur. <hi
                rend="roman">II.</hi> Obſ. <hi rend="roman">1. p. 109.</hi></hi>]. </p>
          <pb n="458"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Beſides, very ſtrong Fires may be kindled in our <lb/>Bodies, as well as in other
            Animals of an hot Tem- <lb/>perament, not only by Nature, but alſo by Art; <lb/>which,
            being able to kill, will ſerve for a better <lb/>Proof of my Argument. It is neceſſary,
            for clearer In- <lb/>ſtance thereof, to read the 77th Obſervation of <hi rend="italic"
              >John <lb/>Piſano</hi>, in the <hi rend="italic">German Ephemerides</hi>, printed in
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">Lipſia</hi> 1670. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Tie the upper Orifice of the Stomach of an Animal <lb/>with a String; tie alſo its
            lower Orifice; then cut it <lb/>out above and below the Ligatures, and preſs it with
            <lb/>both Hands, ſo that it ſwells up in one Side; which <lb/>done, let the left Hand
            keep it ſo that the ſwell'd <lb/>Part may not ſubſide; and, with the right, having
            <lb/>firſt, at an Inch Diſtance, placed a Candle, open it <lb/>quick with an anatomical
            Knife, and you will ſee a <lb/>Flame there conceiv'd, coming out in a few Seconds
            <lb/>of Time: And ſuch a Flame may, by the Curious, <lb/>be perceived not only in the
            Stomach, but alſo in <lb/>the Inteſtines. The firſt Diſcoverer of this was <hi
              rend="italic">An- <lb/>drew Vulparius</hi>, Anatomy-Profeſſor at <hi rend="italic"
              >Bologna</hi> in <lb/><hi rend="italic">Italy</hi> 1669. Thus you ſee, that a quick
            and vio- <lb/>lent Agitation of Spirits, or a Fermentation of Juices <lb/>in the
            Stomach, produces a viſible Flame. <hi rend="italic">Piſano</hi>
            <lb/>was an Eye-witneſs of the above-related Operation. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In the <hi rend="italic">German Ephemerides</hi>, <hi rend="italic">anno</hi> X. p.
            53. of the <lb/>Continuation by <hi rend="italic">John Chriſtopher Sturmius</hi>, one
            <lb/>may read, That often, in the Northmoſt Countries, <lb/>Flames evaporate from the
            Stomachs of thoſe who <lb/>drink ſtrong Liquors plentifully. About 17 Years <lb/>ago,
            ſays the Author, three Noblemen of <hi rend="italic">Curland</hi>, <lb/>whoſe Names, for
            Decency-ſake, I will not publiſh, <lb/>drank, by Emulation, ſtrong Liquors; and two of
              <pb n="459"/>
            <lb/>them died ſcorch'd and ſuffocated by a Flame forcing <lb/>itſelf from the Stomach. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The moſt celebrated <hi rend="italic">Borelli</hi> relates how he was <lb/>told,
            that a Woman vomited Flames in the Point <lb/>of Death: You may read, ſays he, in <hi
              rend="italic">Bartolinus de <lb/>Luce</hi>, and in <hi rend="italic">Euſebius
              Nierembergenſis</hi> his Hiſtory <lb/><hi rend="italic">Nat. peregrin.</hi> how ſuch
            Accidents did often happen <lb/>in great Drinkers of Wine and Brandy: Where is
            <lb/>related alſo, how Fire came out from the privy <lb/>Parts of a Woman. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>My Lord <hi rend="italic">Bacon</hi>, in his <hi rend="italic">Nat. Univ.
              Hiſt.</hi> aſſures, <lb/>he had ſeen a Woman's Belly ſparkling like Fire; <lb/>and
            truly ſuch Flames would often riſe in us, if the <lb/>natural Moiſture did not quench
            them; as <hi rend="italic">Lucretius</hi>
            <lb/>obſerves, from <hi rend="italic">Verſe</hi> 868. <hi rend="italic">Lib.</hi> IV.
            and <hi rend="italic">Verſe</hi> 1065. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Lib.</hi> VI. Moreover,
              <hi rend="italic">Marcellus Donatus</hi>, in his <lb/><hi rend="italic">Mirab. Hiſt.
              Medic. Lib. <hi rend="roman">VI.</hi> Cap. <hi rend="roman">4.</hi></hi> intituled,
              <hi rend="italic">Of <lb/>a new Diſtemper</hi>, ſays, <hi rend="italic">Albertus
              Krantzius</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Lib.</hi>
            <lb/>V. of his <hi rend="italic">Saxon</hi> Hiſtory, That, in the Time of <lb/><hi
              rend="italic">Godfrey</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Bologne</hi> his Chriſtian War, in the
            Terri- <lb/>tory of <hi rend="italic">Niverva</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Nivers</hi>,
            People were burning <lb/>of inviſible Fire in their Entrails, and ſome had cut <lb/>off
            a Foot or an Hand where the Burning began, <lb/>that it ſhould not go further. <hi
              rend="italic">Ezekiel de Caſtro</hi>, in <lb/>the aboveſaid Work of his, of <hi
              rend="italic">Lambent Fire</hi>, relates the <lb/>famous Inſtance of <hi rend="italic"
              >Alexandrinus Megetius</hi>, a Phy- <lb/>ſician, who, from the <hi rend="italic"
              >Vertebra</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Coxa</hi>, after <lb/>great Pain, relates how
            Fire came out, which burn'd <lb/>the Eyes, as <hi rend="italic">Simplicius</hi> and <hi
              rend="italic">Philaſeus</hi>, Eye-witneſſes, <lb/>did atteſt. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>After all theſe Inſtances, whan Wonder is there <lb/>in the Caſe of our old Lady?
            Her Dulneſs before <lb/>going to Bed was an Effect of too much Heat concen- <pb n="460"/>
            <lb/>trated in her Breaſt, which hindered the Perſpiration <lb/>through the Pores of her
            Body; which is calculated <lb/>to about 40 Ounces <hi rend="italic">per</hi> Night. Her
            Aſhes, found <lb/>at four Feet Diſtance from her Bed, are a plain Argu- <lb/>ment, that
            ſhe, by natural Inſtinct, roſe up to cool <lb/>her Heat, and perhaps was going to open a
            Win- <lb/>dow. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The learned Marquis <hi rend="italic">Scipio Maffei</hi> was told by <lb/>Count <hi
              rend="italic">Atimis</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Gorizia</hi>, who paſſed through <hi
              rend="italic">Ce- <lb/>ſena</hi> a few Days after the Accident, that he heard ſay
            <lb/>there, how the old Lady was uſed, when ſhe felt her- <lb/>ſelf indiſpoſed, to bathe
            all her Body with campho- <lb/>rated Spirit of Wine; and ſhe did it perhaps that very
            <lb/>Night. This is not a Circumſtance of any Moment; <lb/>for the beſt Opinion is that
            of the internal Heat and <lb/>Fire; which, by having been kindled in the Entrails,
            <lb/>naturally tended upwards; finding the Way eaſier, and <lb/>the Matter more unctuous
            and combuſtible, left the <lb/>Legs untouch'd; which may have been ſaved alſo, <lb/>by
            remaining cut off at the Combuſtion of the Ten- <lb/>dons, where they join with the
            Knees. The Thighs <lb/>were too near the Origin of the Fire, and therefore <lb/>were
            alſo burnt by it; which was certainly increaſed <lb/>by the Urine and Excrements, a very
            combuſtible <lb/>Matter, as one may ſee by its <hi rend="italic">Phoſphorus</hi>. <hi
              rend="italic">Galenus</hi>
            <lb/>(<hi rend="italic">Claſſ. <hi rend="roman">1.</hi> Lib. <hi rend="roman">III.</hi>
              de Temperam.</hi>) ſays, That the <lb/>Dung of a Dove was ſufficient to ſet Fire to a
            whole <lb/>Houſe: And the learned Father <hi rend="italic">Caſati</hi>, a Jeſuit, in
            <lb/>his <hi rend="italic">Phyſ. Diſſert. <hi rend="roman">Part 2. p. 48.</hi></hi>
            relates to have <lb/>heard a worthy Gentleman ſay, That, from great <lb/>Quantities of
            the Dung of Doves, Flights of which uſed, <lb/>for many Years, nay, Ages, to build under
            the Roof <lb/>of the great Church of <hi rend="italic">Piſa</hi>, ſprung originally the
            Fire <pb n="461"/>
            <lb/>which conſumed the ſaid Church <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* Which Effect is confirmed by <hi rend="italic">Galen</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                  >lib. <hi rend="roman">II.</hi> de Morb. Diſſ. <lb/>cap. <hi rend="roman"
                  >2.</hi></hi> where he ſays, That he hath ſeen Pigeons Dung take Fire, <lb/>when
                it was become rotten. </p>
            </note>. After all this, <lb/>the Author concludes, That to be ſure the Lady was
            <lb/>burnt to Aſhes ſtanding; drawing the Conſequence <lb/>from her Skull fallen
            perpendicular between her Legs; <lb/>and that the Back-part of her Head had been damaged
            <lb/>more than the Fore-part, was becauſe of her Hair, <lb/>and of the Nerves, whoſe
            principal Seat lies there: <lb/>and beſides, becauſe in the Face there were many
            <lb/>Places open, out of which the Flames might paſs; <lb/>as it happened in the Time of
            the <hi rend="italic">Roman</hi> Conſuls <hi rend="italic">T. <lb/>Gracchus</hi> and <hi
              rend="italic">M. Juventius</hi>, when a Flame came out <lb/>of a Bull's Mouth, without
            hurting the Beaſt, by not <lb/>finding any Reſiſtance to its Way. </p></body>
        </floatingText>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic hanging space">
          <lb/>Extract of a Pamphlet, intituled, <hi rend="roman">
            <q rend="quotes">Fire from <lb/>Heaven burning the Body of one <hi rend="italic">John
                <lb/>Hitchell</hi>, of <hi rend="italic">Holnehurſt</hi>, within the Pariſh <lb/>of
                <hi rend="italic">Chriſt-Church</hi>, in the County of <hi rend="italic">South-
                <lb/>ampton</hi>, the 26th of <hi rend="italic">June</hi>, 1613: </q></hi> By
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">John Hilliard</hi>. Printed at <hi rend="roman">London, 1613.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">—T</hi>HE Manner of the Accident is as followeth: <lb/>He (<hi
            rend="italic">John Hitchell</hi>), having been, on <hi rend="italic">Sa-
            <lb/>turday</hi> the 26th of <hi rend="italic">June</hi> laſt, at Work at the Houſe
          <lb/>of one <hi rend="italic">John Deane</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Parly Court</hi>, where
          he truly <pb n="462"/>
          <lb/>and painfully laboured at his Trade, being a Carpen- <lb/>ter, and having ended his
          Day's Work, went home <lb/>to his Houſe; and, after his coming home, betook <lb/>himſelf
          to his Reſt; and, being in Bed with his <lb/>Wife and Child, in the Deep of the Night, the
          Light- <lb/>ning came on ſo fiercely, that an old Woman, named <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Agnes Ruſſell</hi>, Mother to the Wife of the ſaid <hi rend="italic">John
            <lb/>Hitchell</hi>, having received a terrible Blow on her <lb/>Cheek (by what means I
          know not), was therewith <lb/>awakened, and cry'd to the ſaid <hi rend="italic">John
            Hitchell</hi> and <lb/>his Wife to help her: But they not anſwering, the <lb/>poor old
          Woman ſtarted out of her Bed, and went <lb/>unto the Bed where they lay, and awakened her
          <lb/>Daughter, who was, upon the ſudden, moſt lamenta- <lb/>bly burnt all on one Side of
          her, and her Husband and <lb/>Child dead by her Side. Yet nevertheleſs his poor <lb/>Wife,
          when ſhe ſaw her Husband and Child had thus <lb/>ſtrangely finiſhed their Days, ſhe (as it
          ſeemeth) thought <lb/>not ſo much of the Hurt ſhe had received herſelf, as <lb/>ſhe was
          careful to have preſerved the Life of her <lb/>Husband, if by any means poſſibly ſhe
          could; and <lb/>therefore (notwithſtanding all her grievous Wounds) <lb/>ſhe dragg'd him
          out of the Bed into the Street; and <lb/>there, by reaſon of the Vehemency of the Fire,
          ſhe <lb/>was inforced, to her no ſmall Grief, to forſake him; <lb/>where he lay burning
          upon the Ground for the Space <lb/>of three Days after, or thereabouts. Not that there
          <lb/>was any Appearance of Fire outwardly to be ſeen on <lb/>him, but only a kind of Smoke
          aſcending upwards <lb/>from his Carcaſe, until it was conſumed to Aſhes, <lb/>except only
          ſome ſmall Shew of Part of his Bones, <lb/>which were caſt into a Pit made by the Place.
        </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="463"/>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic hanging">
          <lb/>An Extract of the Minutes of the <hi rend="roman">Royal So- <lb/>ciety</hi>, of <hi
            rend="roman">Nov. 8.</hi> and <hi rend="roman">15.</hi>
          <hi rend="roman">1744.</hi> concern- <lb/>ing the Woman at <hi rend="roman">Ipſwich</hi>,
          who was found <lb/>burnt to Aſhes on <hi rend="roman">April 10.</hi> preceding. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE firſt Account of this extraordinary Acci- <lb/>dent was in
          a Letter from Mr. <hi rend="italic">R. Love</hi> to <lb/>his Brother Mr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Geo. Love</hi>, Apothecary at <hi rend="italic">Weſt- <lb/>minſter</hi>, dated <hi
            rend="italic">Ipſwich</hi>, <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 28. 1744. which was <lb/>laid
          before the <hi rend="italic">Society</hi> by the <hi rend="italic">Preſident</hi> on <hi
            rend="italic">Nov.</hi> 8. <lb/>following; wherein Mr. <hi rend="italic">Love</hi> ſays,
            <q rend="diple quotes">That it ap- <lb/>pear'd, upon the Coroner's Inqueſt concerning
            the <lb/>Death of this Woman (at which he attended), that <lb/>ſhe, having gone up
            ſtairs with her Daughter to <lb/>Bed, went down again from her, half undreſs'd; <lb/>and
            that, the next Morning early, hed Body was <lb/>found quite burnt, lying upon the
            Brick-Hearth in <lb/>the Kitchen, where no Fire had been, with the <lb/>Candleſtick
            ſtanding by her, and the Candle burnt <lb/>out, with which ſhe had lighted herſelf down;
            <lb/>and that the Daughter could aſſign no Reaſon for <lb/>her going down, unleſs it
            were to ſmoak a Pipe; <lb/>but ſaid ſhe was not addicted to drink <hi rend="italic"
              >Gin</hi>. The <lb/>Jury brought it in Accident Death. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Nov.</hi> 15. Dr. <hi rend="italic">Lobb</hi> communicated two
          Letters <lb/>concerning the ſame Woman; one from the Reve- <lb/>rend Mr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Notcutt</hi> at <hi rend="italic">Ipſwich</hi>, to the Reverend Mr. <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Gibbons</hi>; this dated <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 25. 1744. and the
          other <lb/>from the ſaid Mr. <hi rend="italic">Gibbons</hi> to a Friend, dated <hi
            rend="italic">Sept.</hi> 2. <lb/>following. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>They both agree in all the material Circumſtances <lb/>relating to the Fact; both
          giving their Relations <lb/>from the Mouths of the Eye-witneſſes, who viewed the <pb
            n="464"/>
          <lb/>Body when it was firſt found burning; particularly Mr. <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Gibbons</hi> from the Woman's own Daughter, and from 2 <lb/>other Perſons living in the
          ſame Houſe, whoſe Names <lb/>are <hi rend="italic">Boyden</hi>. The Caſe was this; One <hi
            rend="italic">Grace Pett</hi>, a <lb/>Fiſherman's Wife, of the Pariſh of <hi
            rend="italic">St. Clement</hi>'s in <hi rend="italic">Ipſ- <lb/>wich</hi>, aged about
          60, had a Cuſtom, for ſeveral Years <lb/>paſt, of going down ſtairs every Night, after ſhe
          was <lb/>half undreſs'd, to ſmoak a Pipe, or on ſome other <lb/>private Occaſion. The
          Daughter, who lay with her, <lb/>fell aſleep, and did not miſs her Mother, till ſhe
          <lb/>awaked early in the Morning, <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 10. 1744. when,
          <lb/>dreſſing herſelf, and going down-ſtairs, ſhe found her <lb/>Mother's Body lying on
          the right Side, with her Head <lb/>againſt the Grate, and extended over the Hearth, with
          <lb/>her Legs on the Deal-Floor, and appearing like a <lb/>Block of Wood burning with a
          glowing Fire with- <lb/>out Flame; upon which quenching it with two Bowls <lb/>of Water,
          the Smother and Stench thereof almoſt <lb/>ſtifled the Neighbours, whom her Cries had
          brought in; <lb/>the Trunk of the Body was in a manner burnt to <lb/>Aſhes, and appeared
          like an Heap of Charcoal cover'd <lb/>with white Aſhes; the Head, Arms, Legs and Thighs
          <lb/>were alſo very much burnt. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It was ſaid, that the Woman had drank very plen- <lb/>tifully of Gin over-night, on
          the Occaſion of a Merry- <lb/>making, on account of a Daughter who was lately come
          <lb/>home from <hi rend="italic">Gibraltar</hi>. But the Difficulty is to account <lb/>for
          the Fire by which ſhe was burnt; ſince there was <lb/>none in the Grate, and the Candle
          was burnt out in the <lb/>Socket of the Candleſtick, which ſtood by her; and <lb/>a
          Child's Cloaths on one Side of her, and a Paper <lb/>Screen on the other, were both
          untouch'd: And <lb/>altho' the melting of the Greaſe had ſo penetrated <lb/>into the
          Hearth, as not to be ſcour'd out, yet they <pb n="465"/>
          <lb/>obſerved, that the Deal-Floor was neither ſinged nor <lb/>diſcolour'd; and the Manner
          of the Fire burning in her <lb/>Body is deſcribed as the working of ſome inward Cauſe,
          <lb/>and not from the burning of her Cloaths, which were <lb/>only a Cotton Gown and upper
          Petticoat. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
