<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Warrick: An Improvement on the Practice of Tapping</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Christopher Warrick</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Improvement on the Practice of Tapping; Whereby That Operation, Instead of a
              Relief for Symptoms, Becomes an Absolute Cure for an Ascites, Exemplified in the Case
              of Jane Roman; And Recommended to the Consideration of the Royal Society, by
              Christopher Warrick, of Truro, Surgeon</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for C. Davis, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn; Printer to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1744</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">43</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">12-19</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110113631</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1744.0006</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT43_0012">
    <body>
      <pb n="12"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">III.</hi> An Improvement on the Practice of <hi rend="roman">Tap-
          <lb/>ping</hi>; whereby that Operation, inſtead of a <lb/>Relief for Symptoms, becomes an
          <hi rend="roman">abſolute <lb/>Cure</hi> for an <hi rend="roman">Aſcites</hi>, exemplified
        in the Caſe <lb/>of <hi rend="roman">Jane Roman</hi>; and recommended to the
        <lb/>Conſideration of the <hi rend="roman">Royal Society</hi>, by <hi rend="roman">Chri-
          <lb/>ſtopher Warrick</hi>, of <hi rend="roman">Truro</hi>, Surgeon. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="italic size(0.7)">Read <date rend="roman">Feb. 16. <lb/>1743-4.
          </date>
        </note><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>MONG all the Operations of Sur- <lb/>gery, perhaps there is
        not one, of <lb/>equal Importance, leſs oblig'd to Improvements, <lb/>than that of the <hi
          rend="italic">Paracenteſis</hi>; it being, at this time, <lb/>notwithſtanding the frequent
        Uſe thereof, in the <lb/>ſame State of Imperfection as when firſt introduced <lb/>among us;
        a mere palliative Remedy, or a Relief for <lb/>Symptoms. Mr. <hi rend="italic">Monro</hi>
        and Mr. <hi rend="italic">Garengeot</hi> have, <lb/>indeed, thrown ſome conſiderable Lights
        thereon; <lb/>the former, <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="italic size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Vide <hi rend="roman">Medical Eſſays, Vol. I. <hi rend="italic">Art.</hi>
              18.</hi>
          </p>
        </note> by ſubſtituting a Belt, inſtead of the <lb/>ordinary long Bandage for compreſſing
        the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, <lb/>and in aſcertaining the proper Place of Puncture;
        <lb/>the latter, in making the Evacuation at once, and in <lb/>rinſing the emptied Cavity,
        to remove the feculent <lb/>Part of the Waters; which, ſubſiding therein, and <lb/>being
        apt, by its Acrimony, to make rude Impreſ- <lb/>ſions on the Viſcera, he ſays, <note n="†"
          place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">† <hi rend="italic">Traité des Operations <lb/>de
            Chirurgie, <hi rend="roman">Chap. 6. Art. 6.</hi> de la Paracentheſe. </hi>
        </note> frequently occaſion <lb/>Mortifications thereof. Theſe are, I believe, the <lb/>only
        Improvements therein; at leaſt, that ſeem to <pb n="13"/>
        <lb/>have ſufficient Solidity in them to recommend them- <lb/>ſelves to our Practice. Its
        proper Object, an <hi rend="italic">Aſcites</hi>, <lb/>however, ſtill baffles our
        Endeavours, and renders <lb/>the Uſe of it contemptible and precarious; always aſ-
        <lb/>ſuring us of a Relapſe, by returning as conſtantly as ever <lb/>we put this Method
        alone in Practice to remove it; <lb/>ſo that, even in caſe of its being conſider'd as a pal-
        <lb/>liative Remedy, or a Relief of the Symptoms, by <lb/>repeating the Uſe of the <hi
          rend="italic">Trochar</hi>, we muſt ſuppoſe, at <lb/>the ſame time, an equal Certainty of
        Pain, conti- <lb/>nual Anxiety, and, perhaps, Death; which, at laſt, <lb/>muſt be the
        inevitable Conſequence of it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From theſe Conſiderations, and a ſincere Willing- <lb/>neſs to communicate to others
        what I think herein <lb/>has been of Service to myſelf, I am inclined to <lb/>believe the
        following Piece of Practice, conſidering <lb/>the Nature and Importance of it, may not be
        unac- <lb/>ceptable to the Public; not only as it tends to eſta- <lb/>bliſh an abſolute Cure
        for an <hi rend="italic">Aſcites</hi>, but likewiſe as <lb/>it may afford us ſome Light in
        the Treatment of an <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hydrocele</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Hydrops
          Pectoris</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Ovarii</hi>, and other Diſ- <lb/>eaſes incident to the
        human Fabric. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In 1742, among a great many Hydropics that fell <lb/>under my Care that Year, I was
        called to the Aſſiſt- <lb/>ance of one <hi rend="italic">Jane Roman</hi>. She was an Inha-
        <lb/>bitant of the Pariſh of <hi rend="italic">St. Agnes</hi>, near Fifty Years of <lb/>Age,
        and confined to her Bed, under that Species of <lb/>Dropſy called <hi rend="italic"
          >Aſcites</hi>, owing its Riſe, ſome Years <lb/>before, to the Severity of a lingering
        intermittent <lb/>Fever. The moſt remarkable of her Complaints <lb/>were, Loſs of Appetite,
        difficult Breathing, unquench- <lb/>able Thirſt, Suppreſſion of Urine, and a ſhort, im-
        <lb/>portunate, aſthmatic Cough, joined to that eſſential <pb n="14"/>
        <lb/>Symptom of the Diſeaſe, a large Quantity of extra- <lb/>vaſated Waters in the Cavity of
        the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, diſ- <lb/>tending it to an enormous Size, and
        perceptibly <lb/>fluctuating. Her more inferior Parts were likewiſe <lb/>ſwoln to an
        uncommon Magnitude, with livid Spots <lb/>and Veſications in divers Places. Under theſe
        Circum- <lb/>ſtances, and already ſatiated with tedious Courſes of <lb/>ineffectual
        Medicines, I drew from her (<hi rend="italic">Sept.</hi> 20th) <lb/>Thirty-ſix Pints of a
        greeniſh tranſparent Lymph, by <lb/>a <hi rend="italic">Paracenteſis</hi> made after the
        uſual Manner; whereby <lb/>her Complaints vaniſhed, and ſhe was ſoon re-eſta- <lb/>bliſhed
        on Foot again. With ſome Part of the ex- <lb/>tracted Lymph, which I had conveyed to my own
        <lb/>Houſe, on my Return thither, I made the following <lb/>Obſervations: </p>
      <floatingText><body>
        <head rend="sc align-center">
          <lb/>Obs. I. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Being as warm as it came from the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, with <lb/>one Pint
          of it I mixed the like Quantity of freſh <lb/><hi rend="italic">Briſtol</hi> Water; and
          immediately a ſlight <hi rend="italic">Coagulum</hi>
          <lb/>enſued. </p></body>
      </floatingText>
      <floatingText><body>
        <head rend="sc align-center">
          <lb/>Obs. II. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In mixing equal Parts of warmed Lymph and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cohore</hi> Claret
          together, the ſame Phænomenon <lb/>appeared; the <hi rend="italic">Coagulum</hi> ſubſided,
          and the Mixture <lb/>became milky. </p></body>
      </floatingText>
      <floatingText><body>
        <head rend="sc align-center">
          <lb/>Obs. III. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Being mixed with <hi rend="italic">Pyrmont</hi> Water, it manifeſted <lb/>little or
          no Change, only went turbid. </p></body>
      </floatingText>
      <floatingText><body>
        <head rend="sc align-center">
          <lb/>Obs. IV. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I mixed a Decoction of the <hi rend="italic">Cortex</hi> with the like <lb/>Quantity
          of warm Lymph, and it dropped a branny <lb/>Sediment. </p></body>
      </floatingText>
      <pb n="15"/>
      <floatingText><body>
        <head rend="sc align-center">
          <lb/>Obs. V. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Lymph <hi rend="italic">per ſe</hi>, boiled, became gelatinous; but, <lb/>being mixed
          with a ſtrong Solution of <hi rend="italic">Terra foliata <lb/>Tartari</hi>, it ſoon
          reſumed its former Fluidity. </p></body>
      </floatingText>
      <floatingText><body>
        <head rend="sc align-center">
          <lb/>Obs. VI. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In bringing the above Mixture to a State of boil- <lb/>ing, the Phænomenon of
          Coagulation appeared more <lb/>eminently in each of them; eſpecially that with Cla-
          <lb/>ret. <hi rend="italic">Eaton</hi>'s Styptic, Tormentil-roots, Pomegranate-
          <lb/>peels, and almoſt every Reſtringent, more or leſs <lb/>afforded the ſame Appearances
          of Coagulation. </p></body>
      </floatingText>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Notwithſtanding the Diſappearance of the Sym- <lb/>ptoms, and the favourable Proſpect
        that enſued the <lb/>Evacuation of the Waters, the Relief which ſhe had <lb/>thereby was
        only temporary, and of a ſhort Dura- <lb/>tion: For, </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Sept.</hi> 30. An Inundation again alarmed her, and <lb/>obliged her
        forthwith to remove the Bandage, for <lb/>Fear of Suffocation. Hence, to the latter End of
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">October</hi>, ſhe re-filled incredibly; and, notwith- <lb/>ſtanding
        any Method uſed to prevent it, within Forty <lb/>Days after the <hi rend="italic"
          >Paracenteſis</hi>, there was again col- <lb/>lected, in the <hi rend="italic"
          >Abdomen</hi>, and depending Parts, a <lb/>Quantity of Lymph, equal to, if not greater
        than, that <lb/>which I had but juſt before thence extracted. All her <lb/>former
        Complaints, eſpecially the <hi rend="italic">Dyſpnœa</hi>, likewiſe <lb/>returned, and
        oppreſſed her more violently than <lb/>ever. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Oct.</hi> 29. The Waters being ready to break their <lb/>Confines,
        and the Pain and Diſtention inſupportable <lb/>under them, ſhe again deſired my Aſſiſtance
        to re- <pb n="16"/>
        <lb/>lieve her. I had, by this time, drawn ſome Con- <lb/>cluſions from the above
        Obſervations on Lymph and <lb/>Reſtringents, and flattered myſelf, that ſome of them,
        <lb/>eſpecially thoſe of the warmeſt kind, applied imme- <lb/>diately to the Parts affected,
        (the ruptured Lympha- <lb/>tics) muſt, according to their known <hi rend="italic">Modus</hi>
        of Ope- <lb/>ration, cloſe up their Mouths, and prevent a further <lb/>Effuſion of their
        Contents, and, conſequently, a <lb/>Return of the Diſeaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In order then to obtain this deſirable End, I re- <lb/>ſolved to try their Efficacy, by
        way of Injection, on <lb/>the emptied Cavity: And, for this Purpoſe, the <lb/>Claret and <hi
          rend="italic">Briſtol</hi> Water ſeemed to claim the Su- <lb/>periority in my Eſteem; not
        only as they produced <lb/>the ſtrongeſt <hi rend="italic">Coagulum</hi> with Lymph, but
        likewiſe in <lb/>being the ſafeſt, and leaſt liable to create any uneaſy <lb/>Senſations on
        the <hi rend="italic">Viſcera</hi>. The Experiment, how- <lb/>ever, being of a pretty
        ſingular Nature, I communi- <lb/>cated my Sentiments thereof to Dr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Colwell</hi>, and Dr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ruſſell</hi>, Two eminent Phyſicians of our
        County, <lb/>and had the Pleaſure of finding them meet in their <lb/>Approbation: The
        latter, favouring me with his <lb/>Preſence, ſaw the Conduct of the whole Affair. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>My <hi rend="italic">Apparatus</hi> was, a large <hi rend="italic">Trois-quarts</hi>,
        made on <lb/>purpoſe, and dipped in Oil; an <hi rend="italic">Injector</hi>, capable of
        <lb/>containing Two or Three Pints, adapted thereto; <lb/>and Three or Four Gallons of
        blood-warm Injection, <lb/>compoſed of equal Parts of <hi rend="italic">Cohore</hi> Claret,
        and freſh <lb/><hi rend="italic">Briſtol</hi> Water; beſides Compreſs, Bandage, <hi
          rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> as <lb/>is uſual on theſe Occaſions. It was conducted pretty
        <lb/>near after the Manner following: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Being ſeated on her Bed-ſide, and proper Aſſiſtants <lb/>attending her, I plunged the
          <hi rend="italic">Trois-quart</hi> into the <pb n="17"/>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, about Five or Six Inches below, and as <lb/>much on the
        Left Side of the <hi rend="italic">Umbilicus</hi>; and thereby <lb/>ſoon diſcharged upwards
        of Twenty Pints of ſuch <lb/>clear briny Lymph as I had before; which Quantity <lb/>did not
        exceed Two Thirds of the Whole, though <lb/>as much as her Strength could well bear: The
        Cla- <lb/>ret and <hi rend="italic">Briſtol</hi> Water being then in Readineſs, I <lb/>began
        to repleniſh the empty Cavity therewith; but <lb/>I had ſcarce injected Ten or Twelve Pints
        of it, <lb/>before a <hi rend="italic">Syncope</hi>, a very material Obſtruction, made
        <lb/>ſome Advances, and would fain baffle my Deſign. <lb/>Here I perceived the great
        Expedition neceſſary in <lb/>conducting this Experiment; that Symptom being <lb/>more or
        leſs violent, as I happened to be dextrous, <lb/>or remiſs, therein; and was, for the moſt
        part, the <lb/>only one of Conſequence that attended it. Quicken- <lb/>ing therefore my Hand
        as faſt as I was able, and an <lb/>Aſſiſtant ſtopping the Mouth of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Cannula</hi> with his <lb/>Finger, to prevent a Return, I ſoon brought her up <lb/>to her
        former Magnitude, and had the Pleaſure thereby <lb/>of ſeeing the above Symptom ſuſpended. I
        had then <lb/>Time to ask her, what kind of Senſation this new <lb/>Piece of Practice
        excited within the Cavity? and <lb/>whether or not ſhe thought herſelf capable of under-
        <lb/>going it a ſecond time? She anſwered me in the <lb/>Affirmative; and ſaid, It ſeemed as
        it were entering <lb/>her Stomach. Notwithſtanding I had Reaſon to be- <lb/>lieve my
        Intentions already anſwered, as much as in <lb/>bringing thoſe Reſtringents in Contact with
        the Parts <lb/>affected, yet, as there was a great Quantity of Lymph <lb/>left behind in the
        Cavity undiſcharged, which, on <lb/>account of the <hi rend="italic">Syncope</hi>, I could
        not well prevent, <lb/>I imagined their Action, and full Efficacy, might <pb n="18"/>
        <lb/>thereby be, in ſome degree, interrupted. Every thing <lb/>therefore being in a
        favourable Way, I repeated the <lb/>Mixture for a ſecond Injection (the Claret being in
        <lb/>a double Proportion of the Water, to render it the <lb/>more efficacious for that
        Purpoſe); drew off the <lb/>whole Contents of the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi> to as much
        as would <lb/>flow through the <hi rend="italic">Cannula</hi>; repeated my Injections as
        <lb/>before; and once more, without the leaſt Interruption, <lb/>repleniſhed her therewith. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This total Diſcharge, however, made a great Al- <lb/>teration in the Face of Affairs;
        and her being full, <lb/>and under Diſtention, now, altered not, as it did at <lb/>firſt,
        the Caſe. A pungent Pain poſſeſſed her Breaſt, <lb/>frequently darting through all the <hi
          rend="italic">Viſcera</hi>; her <lb/>Breathing became extremely difficult; her Pulſe fal-
        <lb/>tered; the <hi rend="italic">Syncope</hi> returned; and ſhe became ſpeech- <lb/>leſs.
        Under theſe Circumſtances it was high time <lb/>to conclude my Deſign; and therefore, having
        <lb/>emptied the Cavity, as well as the Violence of them <lb/>would permit it, I withdrew
        the <hi rend="italic">Cannula</hi>, applied pro- <lb/>per Compreſs and Bandage, and finiſhed
        the Opera- <lb/>tion after the uſual Manner; which was the more <lb/>agreeable, as it ended
        with the perfect Recovery of <lb/>her Senſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Day following, (<hi rend="italic">Oct.</hi> 30.) on repeating my <lb/>Viſit, which
        I did for divers others ſucceſſively, I <lb/>had the Pleaſure of finding Things under a
        favour- <lb/>able Diſpoſition; a gentle <hi rend="italic">Diaphoreſis</hi>, from a liberal
        <lb/>Uſe of Cardiac Medicines, having totally removed <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >Syncope</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Dyſpnœa</hi>, and all other Complaints. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">November</hi> 12. I renewed my Bandage, and ſet her <lb/>on Foot
        again. </p>
      <pb n="19"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The 24th I waited on her again for the ſame Pur- <lb/>poſe; found the Swelling in the
        Extremities going <lb/>off, her Heart in a chearful Diſpoſition, her Appe- <lb/>tite ſtrong,
        and no Symptom of a Relapſe, as ſhe <lb/>formerly had long before that time approaching. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Dec.</hi> 1. the laſt Viſit I made her, ſhe told me, <lb/>That there
        was no further Occaſion for my Aſſiſt- <lb/>ance; and that the only Complaint ſhe had then,
        <lb/>was, in not having the good Luck to experience this <lb/>Remedy ſooner. Finding every
        thing therefore in a <lb/>favourable Way, her Appetite well, her Urine in <lb/>due Quantity,
        her Breathing clear, and the extreme <lb/>Parts of their natural Size, I left her in Purſuit
        of <lb/>that Health which ſhe ſoon acquired, and now enjoys <lb/>in as eminent a Degree as
        any other Perſon whatſo- <lb/>ever. To conclude; The Integuments, and other <lb/>Parts of
        the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, having not yet recovered their <lb/>former Tone; or, for
        aught I know, ſome of the In- <lb/>jection being coagulated therein; ſhe ſtill is, and ever
        <lb/>has been, ſince the Operation, ſomewhat above her <lb/>natural Bigneſs: However, it is
        ſo far from being an <lb/>Inconvenience to her, that ſhe made me a Viſit, on <lb/>a trifling
        Occaſion, a few Days ſince, on Foot; and <lb/>informed me, that ſhe had, of her own Choice,
        <lb/>walked Seven Miles that Morning for the Purpoſe. <lb/>Her Welfare now is upwards of a
        Twelvemonth's <lb/>Standing. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
