<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Myddleton: An Account of a Child Being Taken out of the
          Abdomen</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Starkey Myddleton</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of a Child Being Taken out of the Abdomen, after Having Lain There
              Upwards of 16 Years, during Which Time the Woman Had 4 Children, All Born Alive; By
              Starkey Myddleton M. D.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for C. Davis, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn; Printer to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1746</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">44</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">617-621</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110043561</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1746.0113</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT44_0617">
    <body>
      <pb n="617"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">X.</hi> An Account of a <hi rend="roman">Child</hi> being taken out
        <lb/>of the <hi rend="roman">Abdomen</hi>, after having lain there <lb/>upwards of 16 Years,
        during which time <lb/>the Woman had 4 Children, all born alive; <lb/>by <hi rend="roman"
          >Starkey Myddleton</hi> M. D. </head>
      <salute rend="italic indent">
        <lb/>Gentlemen, </salute>
      <p>
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="italic size(0.7)">Read <date rend="roman">Dec. 17. <lb/>1747.
          </date>
        </note><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE Records of your <hi rend="italic">Society</hi> furniſh
        <lb/>us with ſeveral Caſes of extra-ute- <lb/>rine Conceptions; one of which I communicated
        <lb/>to you <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 28. 1745. <note n="*" place="bottom"
          rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* See <hi rend="italic">Philoſ. Tranſ.</hi> N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 475. p. 336.
          </p>
        </note> nevertheleſs I could not <lb/>help flattering myſelf that this Caſe alſo might be
        <lb/>worthy your Notice. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>IN <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 1731. Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Ball</hi>, without <hi
          rend="italic">Biſhopſgate</hi>, <lb/>perceived (by the uſual Symptoms) that ſhe was preg-
        <lb/>nant; and in <hi rend="italic">October</hi> following, being then in the <lb/>ſixth
        Month of her Pregnancy, ſhe had a Child died <lb/>in her Lap of Convulſions, the Surprize of
        which <lb/>occaſion'd a great Fluttering within her, attended <lb/>with a ſenſible Motion of
        the Child, which Motion <lb/>continued, tho' gradually weaker and weaker, for <lb/>about 6
        or 7 Days, after which ſhe did not per- <lb/>ceive it to move any more; but from this time
        ſhe <lb/>had conſtant Pains attending her, which appear'd <lb/>like Labour-Pains. Her
        Midwife, for ſeveral Days, <lb/>expected a Miſcarriage; but finding herſelf diſap-
        <lb/>pointed, adviſed her to apply to Dr. <hi rend="italic">Bamber</hi>, whoſe <lb/>known
        Abilities in the ſeveral Branches of Phyſick, <lb/>joined to his great Experience and
        Judgment in <pb n="618"/>
        <lb/>Midwifry, made him unqueſtionably the moſt pro- <lb/>per Perſon to be conſulted, as the
        Caſe appear'd ſo <lb/>very uncommon in its Circumſtances, at the ſame <lb/>time that his
        great Humanity always gave the moſt <lb/>free Acceſs to the Poor in their Diſtreſſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Doctor (after a proper Examination) finding <lb/>ſufficient Indications of a dead
        Child, order'd her <lb/>ſome forcing Medicines; upon taking which about <lb/>three times ſhe
        diſcharg'd ſomething, which the Wo- <lb/>men ſuppos'd to be Part of an After-birth, accom-
        <lb/>panied with a ſmall Quantity of Water: In conſe- <lb/>quence of this Diſcharge her
        Pains ceaſed, but with- <lb/>out any viſible Diminution of her Belly. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After ſome time ſhe again apply'd herſelf to the <lb/>Doctor, who thought it moſt
        adviſeable to diſcon- <lb/>tinue her Medicines, and leave the Affair intirely to
        <lb/>Nature. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In this State ſhe continued for about 20 Months <lb/><hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> to <hi
          rend="italic">July</hi> 1733. which was 2 Years and 3 <lb/>Months from her firſt
        Reckoning, ſhe then again <lb/>apply'd herſelf to Dr. <hi rend="italic">Bamber</hi>,
        acquainting him, that <lb/>ſhe was not yet deliver'd of the Child ſhe ſo long <lb/>ſince
        came to conſult him about, and that her Pains <lb/>were lately return'd, and daily increaſed
        without any <lb/>Intermiſſion, upon the Doctor's examining her, he <lb/>thought it proper to
        ſend her home immediately, <lb/>directing her to promote her Pains, by frequently
        <lb/>ſupping ſome warm Caudle, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> by the Uſe of <lb/>which her
        Pains became more regular, and the next <lb/>Day the Doctor made her a Viſit, and was
        informed <lb/>ſhe had diſcharg'd two Waters, but nothing more: <lb/>He then carefully
        examined her again, and plainly <lb/>felt a Child through the Integuments of the <hi
          rend="italic">Abdo- <lb/>men</hi>, but could not give her any Aſſiſtance. </p>
      <pb n="619"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It was about this time that Dr. <hi rend="italic">Bamber</hi> firſt ac<choice>
          <corr>-</corr>
          <sic> </sic>
        </choice>
        <lb/>quainted me with the Caſe, and deſired that I would <lb/>attend her as often as
        Occaſion might require, and that I <lb/>would acquaint him, if any thing like Labour, or
        other <lb/>remarkable Alteration ſhould offer. Accordingly I <lb/>made her a Viſit, and
        after a proper Examination, <lb/>was convinc'd of the Certainty of the Doctor's Aſ-
        <lb/>ſertion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Her Pains now began to abate, and ſhe grew to- <lb/>lerably eaſy; but about the latter
        End of <hi rend="italic">January</hi>
        <lb/>1733-4. ſhe conceived again with Child, and was <lb/>deliver'd on the 28th of <hi
          rend="italic">October</hi> following by Dr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Bamber</hi>, who ſent
        for me to attend him in her <lb/>Labour: The Doctor ſoon deliver'd her of a fine <lb/>Boy,
        and after having brought away the <hi rend="italic">Placenta</hi>, <lb/>he ſearch'd for the
        other Child, which he had before <lb/>felt through the Integuments of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Abdomen</hi>, but <lb/>found it was lodg'd in the Cavity of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Abdomen</hi>, <lb/>and beyond the Reach of human Art to relieve her. <lb/>This Fact every
        one then preſent was made ſen- <lb/>ſible of. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">October</hi> 22. 1735. I was ſent for to her in her <lb/>Labour, but
        before my Arrival ſhe was deliver'd of <lb/>a Boy; but I brought away the <hi rend="italic"
          >Placenta</hi>, which <lb/>gave me an Opportunity of examining for the other <lb/>Child,
        and <choice>
          <corr>found</corr>
          <sic>fonnd</sic>
        </choice> it in the ſame Situation as for- <lb/>merly. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">October</hi> 9. 1738. I was again ſent for to her, when <lb/>in
        Labour, but ſhe was deliver'd of a Boy before I ar- <lb/>rived. Upon examining the Womb, and
        the State <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, the Child appear'd juſt as before,
        <lb/>without any Alteration. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 17, 1741. I was again ſent for in her La- <lb/>bour, but
        found her juſt deliver'd of a Girl; and <pb n="620"/>
        <lb/>upon examining the Parts, every thing appear'd as <lb/>before. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">October</hi> 14. 1747. being greatly emaciated by <lb/>conſtant
        Pains, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> ſhe was admitted a Patient in <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Guy</hi>'s <hi rend="italic">Hoſpital</hi>, where ſhe died the 7th of <hi rend="italic"
          >Novem- <lb/>ber</hi> following, after having labour'd under the Diſ- <lb/>treſſes and
        Uneaſineſs of carrying a dead Child <lb/>within her, in a manner looſe, in the Cavity of the
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi> upwards of 16 Years. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Day after her Death I open'd her, in the Pre- <lb/>ſence of Dr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Nesbit</hi>, Dr. <hi rend="italic">Nichols</hi>, and Dr. <hi rend="italic">Law-
          <lb/>rence</hi>, when the <hi rend="italic">Uterus</hi>, and the ſeveral other Con-
        <lb/>tents of the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi> appear'd (nearly) in their na- <lb/>tural
        State, but on the right Side within the <hi rend="italic">Os <lb/>Ilium</hi> a Child
        preſented itſelf, which was attach'd <lb/>to the <hi rend="italic">Ilium</hi> and
        neighbouring Membranes by a Por- <lb/>tion of the <hi rend="italic">Peritonæum</hi>, in
        which the <hi rend="italic">Fimbria</hi> and <lb/>Part of the right <hi rend="italic"
          >Fallopian</hi> Tube ſeem'd to loſe <lb/>itſelf. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Child ſeem'd no-ways putrid; but the Inte- <lb/>guments were become ſo callous, and
        chang'd from <lb/>their natural State, that the whole ſeem'd to reſem- <lb/>ble a
        cartilaginous Maſs, without Form or Diſtinc- <lb/>tion: The Legs indeed were
        diſtinguiſhable, though <lb/>they were much waſted and diſtorted. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon opening the callous Integuments of the <lb/>Head and Face of the Child, the Bones
        appear'd per- <lb/>fectly form'd, with a few Spots of tophous Concre- <lb/>tions on them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This Account may ſerve to convince thoſe who <lb/>are of Opinion that Boys are
        conceived on the <lb/>right Side, and the Girls on the left; as this Wo- <pb n="621"/>
        <lb/>man had three Boys, and one Girl, after the <hi rend="italic">Fallo- <lb/>pian</hi>
        Tube on the right Side had loſt its Action. <lb/>I am, </p>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <space dim="vertical" quantity="3" unit="lines"> </space>
      <dateline rend="hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Decem.</hi> 17. <lb/>1747. </dateline>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="4"> </space>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <signed rend="italic">
        <lb/>Gentlemen, <lb/><hi rend="space">With great Reſpect, </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="space">Your moſt obedient and </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="space">Moſt humble Servant, </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="roman size(1.2) space align-right">Starkey Myddleton. </hi>
      </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
