<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Amyand: Some Observations on the Spina, Ventosa</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Claudius Amyand</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Some Observations on the Spina, Ventosa; By the Late Claudius Amyand, Esq; F.R.S.
              and Serjeant-Surgeon to His Majesty</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for C. Davis, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn; Printer to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1746</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">44</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">193-211</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110043561</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1746.0040</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT44_0193">
    <body>
      <pb n="193"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">V.</hi> Some Obſervations on the <hi rend="roman">Spina ventoſa</hi>;
        <lb/>by the late <hi rend="roman">Claudius Amyand</hi>, Eſq; F. R. S. <lb/>and
        Serjeant-Surgeon to His <hi rend="roman">Majeſty</hi>. </head>
      <div>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/>
          <note place="inset" rend="italic size(0.7)">Read <date rend="roman">May 15. <lb/>1746
            </date>
          </note><hi rend="dc(2)">W</hi>HAT Practitioners generally under- <lb/>ſtand by the <hi
            rend="italic">Spina ventoſa</hi>, is a <lb/><hi rend="italic">Caries</hi> in the Bone,
          from the Extravaſation of ſome <lb/>ſharp Juices within it relaxing the Tone of the Fi-
          <lb/>bres, and ſwelling and increaſing its Bulk beyond the <lb/>natural Bounds. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In this Caſe, the Humour, or extravaſated Juices, <lb/>pent in the Bone, works <choice>
            <corr>its</corr>
            <sic>it</sic>
          </choice> Way out of it, through the <lb/>external <hi rend="italic">Cortex</hi>, or into
          the Joints, or both. By <lb/>Detention it acquires an Acrimony; and, like Vine- <lb/>gar,
          and other acrid Juices, it not only relaxes the <lb/>Tone of the bony Tubes, by mollifying
          them, but <lb/>alſo, like a Cauſtic, it tears and lacerates them. At <lb/>this time the
          Bone ſwells, tumefies, and ſpreads; and <lb/>the Sap flowing, running out through the
          lacerated <lb/>Tubes, overſpreads the Surface, and adds to the Tu- <lb/>mefaction, as the
          liquid Matter, forming a <hi rend="italic">Callus</hi>, is <lb/>indurated there. So that,
          when this happens at or <lb/>near the Joints, the Bones in Contact are knit toge-
          <lb/>ther, and the Carioſity is incruſted and cover'd with <lb/>an <hi rend="italic"
            >Exoſtoſis</hi>, in as many Places as the Matter con- <lb/>fined within the Bone, upon
          breaking the <hi rend="italic">Cortex</hi> of <pb n="194"/>
          <lb/>it, will work its Way out at. And thus this Diſtem- <lb/>per may be conſider'd
          differently, as it happens to <lb/>be in the different Stages of it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Alteration which the Bone ſuffers from the <lb/>extravaſated Matter lodged within
          the Subſtance or <lb/>Cavities of the Bone in the firſt Stage of a <hi rend="italic">Spina
            <lb/>ventoſa</hi>, becomes the Occaſion of ſome Exfoliation <lb/>or Detachment from it.
          As that Matter acquires a <lb/>greater Acrimony, the Texture of the Bone being
          <lb/>relaxed, and the <hi rend="italic">Lamellæ</hi> made ſoft and yielding, the <lb/>Bone
          is enlarged in its Dimenſions; and, in the laſt <lb/>Stage of it, wherein the Bone is
          carious, the corro- <lb/>ſive Matter deſtroys the Continuity, as it makes its <lb/>Way
          thro' the <hi rend="italic">Cortex</hi>, and into the Joints. At this <lb/>time
          Impoſtumations appear in as many Places as the <lb/>Matter can make its Way out at. The
          callous Mat- <lb/>ter lodged under the <hi rend="italic">Perioſtium</hi>, gradually
          oſſifying, <lb/>covers the Bone more or leſs with <hi rend="italic">Exoſtoſes</hi>; and
          <lb/>the Joints are ſtiffned, by the Extravaſation and In- <lb/>duration of the Sap
          flowing out of the Bone there. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Impoſtumations that happen in the Bone to- <lb/>wards the Centre of long Bones,
          are always attended <lb/>with additional Miſchief, as the working out of the <lb/>Matter
          there meets with a greater Reſiſtance from <lb/>their <hi rend="italic">Lamellæ</hi>,
          which lie cloſe, and are compact; <lb/>the Exfoliations made in the firſt Stage, and, as
          it <lb/>were, in the Beginning of the <hi rend="italic">Spina ventoſa</hi> there,
          <lb/>being frequently confined and locked in by the <hi rend="italic">Cor- <lb/>tex</hi>
          of the Bone, or ſome callous Expanſion on the <lb/>Surface of it. In the laſt Stage of
          this Diſtemper in <lb/>this Place, the Bone is uſually perforated with large <lb/>Holes,
          tubulous Cavities, and fiſtular Openings, and <lb/>the main Bone rotten, at a time that
          the Exfoliations <pb n="195"/>
          <lb/>incloſed preſerve their primitive State and Solidity. <lb/>The Patient then cannot
          ſurvive it long: For, as a <lb/>hectic Fever and <hi rend="italic">Diarrhœa</hi> are fed
          by the continual <lb/>Abſorption of ſome of the Matter into the Blood, ſo <lb/>the Body is
          drained by the large Diſcharge from ſuch <lb/>Wounds. The Amputation of the Limb is then
          the <lb/>uſual Remedy; but a better may be hoped for, be- <lb/>fore it comes to this Paſs,
          as will appear from the <lb/>following Obſervations. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="sc align-center space">
          <lb/>Observation I. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>One <hi rend="italic">Thomas Pentney</hi>, a Shepherd in <hi rend="italic"
            >Norfolk</hi>, <lb/>aged about 22, was admitted into <hi rend="italic">St. George</hi>'s
          Hoſ- <lb/>pital, towards the Beginning of <hi rend="italic">Auguſt</hi> 1739, and
          <lb/>committed to Mr. <hi rend="italic">Middleton</hi>'s Care. Five Years be- <lb/>fore,
          upon the Criſis of a Fever, he had felt a great <lb/>Pain in the <hi rend="italic">Os
            Humeri</hi> of his right Arm, which con- <lb/>tinued ſeveral Months; during which, the
          Dimen- <lb/>ſions of this Bone were ſo increaſed, that, towards <lb/>the End of the Year,
          it was half as big again as is <lb/>uſual in the natural State. About this time the Bone
          <lb/>impoſtumated; and the Matter being diſcharged by <lb/>the breaking of the Integuments
          on the Outſide of <lb/>the Arm, the Patient was eaſed, ſo as to have been <lb/>able to
          attend his Flock as before. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When he came to the Hoſpital four Years after <lb/>this, he had above twelve Holes
          thro' the Integu- <lb/>ments on the Outſide of the Arm, anſwering to, and
          <lb/>correſponding with, as many leading into the me- <lb/>dullary Cavity of the Bone;
          ſome of which were <lb/>large enough to admit the Finger. Theſe Impoſtu- <lb/>mations had
          been moſt vexatious of late. There was <lb/>an <hi rend="italic">Anchyloſis</hi> at the
          Elbow; and, for two Years laſt <pb n="196"/>
          <lb/>paſt, he neither could bend his Arm, nor uſe it in <lb/>Pronation and Supination. The
          whole Bone felt <lb/>thick and unequal up to the Shoulder, where the <lb/>Articulation was
          free. The Patient now did not <lb/>complain much. The Diſcharge from the Wounds <lb/>was
          moderate; his Reſt, Stomach, and Pulſe, as well <lb/>as could be expected; and therefore
          he was deter- <lb/>mined to forego any thing, rather than ſubmit to the <lb/>Amputation
          that was propoſed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In Conſultation with Mr. <hi rend="italic">Pawlet</hi>, Mr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Wilkie</hi>, Mr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Middleton</hi>, and Mr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Hawkins</hi>, we agreed to make an <lb/>Inciſion from the Deltoid Muſcle down to the
          Elbow, <lb/>thereby to lay the diſtemper'd Bone bare, ſo far as it <lb/>appear'd to be
          affected; and, with the exfoliative <lb/><hi rend="italic">Trepan</hi>, to make a fair
          Opening into the medullary <lb/>Cavity of the Bone, by taking off ſo much of it as
          <lb/>was perforated in the external Part of the Arm, and <lb/>ſo to make way for the
          Application of the actual <lb/>Cautery, if that was found neceſſary. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The two firſt Operations were performed with <lb/>Eaſe: For, as in the Inciſion the
            <hi rend="italic">Perioſteum</hi> was readily <lb/>detached from the Bone, ſo the Bone
          in View, being <lb/>nearly of a cartilaginous Nature, and making little <lb/>Reſiſtance,
          was ſoon removed, by the repeated Ap- <lb/>plication of the exfoliative <hi rend="italic"
            >Trepan</hi>. In the Courſe of <lb/>the Operation, Mr. <hi rend="italic">Middleton</hi>
          found a Bone looſe, <lb/>which hitherto had lain concealed under the <hi rend="italic"
            >Cortex</hi>
          <lb/>of the Bone; which, being taken out intire, mea- <lb/>ſured above ſeven Inches in
          Length, and more than <lb/>two in Circumference; the Centre forming a tubu- <lb/>lar
          Chanel, wherein the <hi rend="italic">Medulla</hi> of the Bone had <lb/>formerly been
          incloſed. This was an Exfoliation <lb/>fairly ſeparated from the Surface of all the
          medullary <pb n="197"/>
          <lb/>Cavity of the Bone, <choice>
            <corr>but</corr>
            <sic>bur</sic>
          </choice> improperly called an Exfo- <lb/>liation, as the Thickneſs of the Bone throughout
          was <lb/>as thick as a Shilling: It was more ſubſtantial in <lb/>ſome Places than in
          others, and open'd here and <lb/>there, ſo as not to be a complete Tube. But what,
          <lb/>perhaps, may be thought to deſerve more notice is, <lb/>that this looſe Bone, tho' it
          had for many Years been <lb/>ſoaking in the Matter lodged in the Bone (which, at
          <lb/>times, had worked its Way out, by perforating the <lb/>Surface of the <hi
            rend="italic">Os Humeri</hi> externally), yet this Ex- <lb/>foliation was in no-wiſe
          alter'd, or tainted with Ca- <lb/>rioſity, as the main Bone was; but in every reſpect
          <lb/>ſo ſound, as to give Ground to hope the poſterior <lb/>Part of the <hi rend="italic"
            >Os Humeri</hi> might be ſo; but it happen'd <lb/>otherwiſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Upon the Removal of this Exfoliation, the whole <lb/>internal Surface of the Bone was
          found of a Sub- <lb/>ſtance like a Cartilage: It was bare in ſome Places, <lb/>and cover'd
          with Fleſh in others. The Fleſh was fun- <lb/>gous in the lower Extremity of the Bone that
          was <lb/>carious; firmer towards its upper End, where it was <lb/>ſound; and callous
          towards the Middle, which was <lb/>degenerated into a cartilaginous Subſtance. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Removal of this Exfoliation having laid open <lb/>the whole Bone, in the inferior
          Part of it was found <lb/>a <hi rend="italic">Sinus</hi> leading into the Articulation
          with the Cubit, <lb/>and a Carioſity in the Bone there; and, in the upper <lb/>End, where
          the Bone appeared now ſound, but for- <lb/>merly was diſtemper'd, ſeveral <hi
            rend="italic">Foramina</hi>, which <lb/>were filled up with Fleſh, under Cover of the
          Del- <lb/><hi rend="italic">toid</hi> Muſcle. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>At this time the Surface of the Wound was very <lb/>large, and the Diſcharge from it
          greater than the <pb n="198"/>
          <lb/>Patient could ſupport. His Stomach hitherto had been <lb/>good; but that being
          defective, and a hectic Fever <lb/>with a <hi rend="italic">Diarrhœa</hi> attending, the
          Amputation of the <lb/>Limb was concluded on. It was taken off near the <lb/>Articulation
          with the <hi rend="italic">Scapula</hi>, where the Bone was <lb/>ſound. The Patient did
          not ſurvive it long; for the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Diarrhœa</hi> increaſing, he died
          ſpent, within four <lb/>Days after the Operation. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>In the Explanation of the annexed Figures, <hi rend="sc">Tab.</hi>
          <lb/>II. N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1. and N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 2. a further Account will
          be given <lb/>of the State of the Bones in the amputated Limb. <lb/>The <hi rend="italic"
            >Humerus</hi> next to the Shoulder-Joint did not, <lb/>after the Patient was dead,
          appear ſo ſound as it had <lb/>during Life: For the Matter proceeding from the <lb/>Bone,
          which was found, in two or three Places of it, <lb/>under the Deltoid and Pectoral
          Muſcles, ſhew'd, that <lb/>this Part of the Bone was not in that ſound State it
          <lb/>appeared in, when the Amputation was made. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="sc align-center space">
          <lb/>Observation II. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Upon the 5th of <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 1739. Mr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Johnſon</hi>, <lb/>about 26 Years of Age, having complained for 12 <lb/>Months laſt
          paſt, of a Swelling in the Bone of his <lb/>right Arm, which ſeemingly had been the Cauſe
          of <lb/>ſeveral Impoſtumations he had had thereabouts ſince, <lb/>then applied to me for
          Cure. He could aſſign no <lb/>Cauſe for this Swelling, ſaving his taking Cold, as <lb/>he
          imagines, after having exerciſed himſelf by fling- <lb/>ing heavy Stones at a great
          Diſtance: For that ſoon <lb/>after he was ſeized with a Fever, and a great Swell- <lb/>ing
          from the Neck to the Finger's End of this Arm; <lb/>which ſettling towards the Middle of
          the <hi rend="italic">Os Humeri</hi>, <pb n="199"/>
          <lb/>where ſeveral fiſtular Openings now were, and com- <lb/>ing to Suppuration thereabout
          in a ſhort time after, <lb/>a great Quantity of Matter was diſcharged by Inci- <lb/>ſion
          in <hi rend="italic">Nottingham</hi>; whereupon the Surgeon had <lb/>told him, that the
          Bone was bare; and ſoon after <lb/>had cut another Opening in the hind Part of his
          <lb/>Arm, where there was another Gathering, and the <lb/>Bone alſo laid bare, and dreſſed
          both Wounds, as <lb/>expecting the Bone to ſcale off; but that meeting <lb/>with no Cure,
          and, on the contrary, the Wounds <lb/>to break open as oft as they had been healed up, and
          <lb/>that Matter was ſtill gathering in new Places, and the <lb/>Swelling in the Bone to
          increaſe, had determined <lb/>him to look for a Cure in <hi rend="italic">London</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>At this time there were five or ſix fiſtular Openings <lb/>leading to the Bone
          diſtilling a ſanious Matter on the <lb/>Sides of the Tendon of the <hi rend="italic"
            >Deltoid</hi> Muſcle, and the <lb/>hind Part of the Arm, where the Bone was principally
          <lb/>enlarged; tho' it was very remarkably increaſed in Bulk <lb/>the whole Way down to
          the Elbow. I could not <lb/>with my Probe diſcover the State the Bone was in; <lb/>but,
          being ſatisfied it was carious, and that this Diſ- <lb/>temper was a <hi rend="italic"
            >Spina ventoſa</hi>, propoſed, for the Cure, <lb/>the laying open all the Bone in the
          anterior Part of <lb/>the Arm; which the Patient readily ſubmitted to. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This Diſtemper was found to be a <hi rend="italic">Spina ventoſa</hi>, <lb/>or
          Carioſity in the Body of the <hi rend="italic">Os Humeri</hi>, whereby <lb/>above four
          Inches of the ſolid Bone had been de- <lb/>ſtroyed; all which was caſed in by an <hi
            rend="italic">Exoſtoſis</hi>, or <lb/>callous Expanſion; ſaving in a few Places, where
          the <lb/>Matter flowing from the medullary Cavity of the <lb/>Bone had preſerved an
          Opening. </p>
        <pb n="200"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This <hi rend="italic">Spina ventoſa</hi> was treated nearly in the ſame <lb/>manner
          as the above-mention'd, and the Cure per- <lb/>formed as follows. It was enter'd upon <choice>
            <corr>the</corr>
            <sic>th</sic>
          </choice> 7th of <lb/><hi rend="italic">November</hi>, by making an Inciſion to the Bone
          upon <lb/>the external Part of the Arm, about ſix Inches long, <lb/>and one broad,
          beginning it above the Place in the <lb/>Bone where the <hi rend="italic">Deltoid</hi>
          Muſcle is inſerted; but, <lb/>on the Side of it, almoſt down to the <hi rend="italic"
            >Supinatores <lb/>Radii</hi>; and then, by deſtroying with the <hi rend="italic">Lapis
            in- <lb/>fernalis</hi> all the Fleſh growing on the <hi rend="italic">Exoſtoſis</hi> or
          <lb/>callous Expanſion incompaſſing round, and, as it <lb/>were, incaſing the carious
          Bone, which the next Day <lb/>being ſcraped off, the fiſtular Opening leading into
          <lb/>the medullary Cavity then came in View, and the <lb/>Probe going a great way therein,
          I immediately pro- <lb/>ceeded to the trepanning of the Bone, and inlarging <lb/>that
          fiſtular Opening into it with the exfoliative <hi rend="italic">Trepan</hi>,
          <lb/>perforating through the callous Expanſion or <hi rend="italic">Exoſ- <lb/>toſis</hi>,
          which was ſpread externally almoſt a Quarter <lb/>of an Inch upon it, quite into the
          medullary Cavity. <lb/>The next Day I applied this Intſtument above and be- <lb/>low the
          preceding Perforation; and, by cutting and <lb/>paring off the Angles betwixt them and the
          Sides of <lb/>the Perforations, with an Inſtrument the Engravers <lb/>make uſe of, then
          made a fair Opening into the me- <lb/>dullary Cavity of the Bone, and a convenient one
          <lb/>too; for the Diſcharge of the Matter hitherto con- <lb/>fin'd within it, which,
          whilſt pent in, had occaſion'd <lb/>the Carioſity, and the Progreſs of it, now found to
          <lb/>have deſtroyed above four Inches of its Body; and <lb/>alſo for the Removal of the
          Fragments and looſe <lb/>Bones confined in the medullary Cavity, and the Ap-
          <lb/>plication of the neceſſary means, as well to ſtop the <pb n="201"/>
          <lb/>Progreſs of the Evil, as the promoting the caſting off <lb/>of the morbid Bones. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But the Work was far from being finiſhed, as, <lb/>upon the Extraction of the
          foremention'd looſe Bones, <lb/>it appeared that we had a <hi rend="italic">Fungus</hi>
          ſprouting as well <lb/>from the Circumference of the medullary Cavity <lb/>above and below
          that Part of the Bone we had ope- <lb/>rated upon, as from the callous Expanſion over its
          <lb/>outward Surface occaſioning a greater Diſcharge of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Sanies</hi>
          than our Patient's Strength could ſupport; <lb/>that our Opening in that Cavity was not
          yet ſuf- <lb/>ficient to diſcharge all the Matter that was depoſited <lb/>in it, as well
          through a fiſtular Opening in the in- <lb/>ternal Part of the Bone anſwering to the <hi
            rend="italic">Axilla</hi>, as <lb/>another ſomewhat lower over the large Veſſels that
          <lb/>run upon the Surface of the Bone internally, that, <lb/>being ſhelter'd above and
          below, we could not come <lb/>at them without inlarging further the Opening we <lb/>had in
          the Bone externally. This laid us under the <lb/>Neceſſity of inlarging this Opening in
          its upper and <lb/>lower Part, ſo as to bring in View the fore-mention'd. <lb/>Theſe were
          inlarged with a <hi rend="italic">Terebellum</hi>, without any <lb/>Hazard of wounding the
          large Blood-veſſels, which <lb/>were ſhelter'd by the callous Expanſion lining the
          <lb/>carious Bone on this Side: And having thus render'd <lb/>eaſy the Diſcharge from all
          theſe Cavities, we had <lb/>nothing to ſtruggle with then but the Running; <lb/>which from
          this time became daily leſs; that from <lb/>the internal Part of the Arm, by the Matter
          having <lb/>a more eaſy Vent for itſelf; and that from the <hi rend="italic">Fun-
            <lb/>gus</hi> on the Bone by a Solution of the <hi rend="italic">Lapis infer-
            <lb/>nalis</hi> it was dreſſed with. Mr. <hi rend="italic">Singleton</hi>, Surgeon in
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Alderſgate-ſtreet</hi>, being conſulted upon the Caſe, <pb
            n="202"/>
          <lb/>the 18th from the firſt Operation, was of Opinion, <lb/>that the Amputation was
          hardly practicable; the <hi rend="italic">Sinus</hi>
          <lb/>into the medullary Cavity ſhewing that the Carioſity <lb/>was up to the Head of the
          Bone; but that, if it was <lb/>practicable, he thought the Patient had far better
          <lb/>chance for his Life, by purſuing the Cure in the Way <lb/>he was in. At this time we
          had but in part ſubdued <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Fungus</hi> that was continually
          ſprouting up from <lb/>the ſinuous Vacuity in the upper Part of the Bone, <lb/>where the
            <hi rend="italic">Medulla</hi> was all waſted, as well as from that <lb/>which was yet
          growing without the Bone from the <lb/>callous Expanſion the carious Bone was cover'd by:
          But <lb/>this was ſo effectually overcome and conquer'd by <lb/>the repeated Application
          of the actual Cautery, and <lb/>by it the Bone dried up ſo, that, in leſs than two
          <lb/>Months from its Uſe, all the morbid Bone did caſt <lb/>off. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Quantity of the morbid and carious Bone taken <lb/>out at divers times, being
          about 4 Inches of the ſo- <lb/>lid, was effectually repaired, by the Matter flowing as
          <lb/>well from the Circumferenece of the callous Expan- <lb/>ſion about it, which all
          along had ſteadied the Pa- <lb/>tient's Arm ſo, that he could pull his Stockings on
          <lb/>and off, as from the Matter flowing from the Ends <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Os
            Humeri</hi> into the Cavity formed round this <lb/>incaſing or incircling Bone. If we
          had been linger- <lb/>ing in our Proceedings, it is likely the great Diſ- <lb/>charge
          would have exhauſted the Strength that was <lb/>neceſſary to carry on this Cure, before we
          could have <lb/>got through ſo many that were unavoidable; and that <lb/>the Fleſh growing
          from the Edges of the external <lb/>Wound would have render'd more painful and dif-
          <lb/>ficult the ſeveral Operations on the Bone. By this <pb n="203"/>
          <lb/>Proceeding, this difficult Cure was aſcertained in leſs <lb/>than a Month, and
          intirely finiſhed in ſix; the Pa- <lb/>tient having now the Power of his Arm as complete
          <lb/>as ever. Nor is the Limb at all disfigured or ſhort- <lb/><choice>
            <corr>ened</corr>
            <sic>ended</sic>
          </choice>; the expanded incircling Bone attached to the <lb/>Ends of the <hi rend="italic"
            >Os Humeri</hi> preventing this; ſo that the <lb/>only appearing Defect is, that the
          Bone about the <lb/>Wound is thicker than uſual; but that ſtrengthens it, <lb/>and
          ſupplies a Defect in the anterior Part of the <lb/>Arm, where there is a conſiderable
          Hollowneſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In favour of the young Surgeons I ſhall cloſe this <lb/>Account with a few Remarks,
          by way of Infe- <lb/>rence; and deſcribe the Figures of ſome Bones, <lb/>which that expert
          Surgeon and Anatomiſt Mr. <hi rend="italic">Haw- <lb/>kins</hi>, Surgeon to His Royal
          Highneſs the Prince of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Wales</hi>, ſhew'd upon this Occaſion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>1º. That 'tis highly probable, a ſuppurated <hi rend="italic">Phleg- <lb/>mon</hi> in
          the Marrow, upon the Criſis of a Fever, <lb/>hath been the original Cauſe of the <hi
            rend="italic">Spina ventoſa</hi>
          <lb/>in the two Caſes before us; and that, if the Bone <lb/>had been denudated, and the
          Opening made thro' <lb/>it inlarged, when the Matter firſt made its Way <lb/>thro' the
          Integuments, that the Progreſs of the Evil <lb/>had been prevented in both, and the Cure
          brought <lb/>about in the laſt Caſe with a far greater Eaſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>2º. That a large Opening is always more advan- <lb/>tageous than many ſmaller,
          ſeemingly equal to it. <lb/>And this appears plain in the two Caſes mentioned,
          <lb/>inaſmuch as the Matter which was diſcharging thro' <lb/>the many large <hi
            rend="italic">Foramina</hi> in the Bones correſpond- <lb/>ing with the medullary Cavity
          in them, have not <lb/>prevented the Progreſs of the Evil; and therefore <lb/>we may
          conclude, that as a large Opening in the <pb n="204"/>
          <lb/>Bone, by giving a free Vent to the Matter, will af- <lb/>ford us the neareſt Proſpect
          of a Cure in the <hi rend="italic">Spina <lb/>ventoſa</hi> of all Bones, ſo that muſt be
          the Work of <lb/>the Surgeon, when that Diſtemper breaks out to- <lb/>wards the Centre of
          long Bones. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>3º. That, in the <hi rend="italic">Spina ventoſa</hi> affecting long <lb/>Bones
          towards their Centre, the Application of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Trepan</hi>, or of any
          other Inſtrument as ſhall take away <lb/>a conſiderable Portion of the Subſtance, is
          particularly <lb/>neceſſary, were it only to make way for the Removal <lb/>of ſuch
          Exfoliations as are detached from the inner <lb/>Cavity of the Bone in the firſt Stage of
          the Diſtemper; <lb/>which, in the two Caſes before us, were concealed <lb/>and ſhut in;
          and, in many others, may be wedged and <lb/>locked in by the Induration of the callous
          Matter <lb/>on the Surface of the Bone, as may appear in the Fi- <lb/>gures annexed, <hi
            rend="sc">Tab.</hi> II. <hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 3. <hi rend="italic">BB.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>4º. That, in a <hi rend="italic">Spina ventoſa</hi>, in the Centre of <lb/>long
          Bones, tho' the Diſcharge attending it is not <lb/>great, if any of their Joints are made
          ſtiff by an <lb/><hi rend="italic">Anchyloſis</hi>, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> by a
          callous Expanſion that ſhall ſol- <lb/>der together the Bones in Contact, the only
          Reſource <lb/>will be the immediate Amputation of the Limb; for- <lb/>aſmuch that, if that
          is delayed till the Patient labours <lb/>under a hectic Fever, colliquative Sweats, a <hi
            rend="italic">Diar- <lb/>rhœa</hi>, or ſuch Symptoms as denote a Reflux of the
          <lb/>Matter pent up in the Bone into the Maſs of Blood; <lb/>the Operation then will
          afford us very little Hopes <lb/>of Succeſs: Whereas the <hi rend="italic">Spina
            ventoſa</hi> that affects <lb/>the Extremities of long Bones only, and that which
          <lb/>appears in ſcrophulous Caſes in the Bones of the <hi rend="italic">Car- <lb/>pus</hi>
          and <hi rend="italic">Tarſus</hi>, when the Diſcharge is not great, <pb n="205"/>
          <lb/>are beſt cured by lenient Means, and the moſt paci- <lb/>fic Methods. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>5º. That, in that Stage of the <hi rend="italic">Spina ventoſa</hi>, <lb/>wherein the
          Bone is carnified, that is, turned into <lb/>Fleſh, with a painful <hi rend="italic"
            >Fungus</hi> ſhooting out, as well <lb/>from the callous Matter ſpread over the carious
          Bone <lb/>changed into Fleſh, as from the carious Bone itſelf <lb/>degenerated, that, in
          this Caſe, as there can be no <lb/>Hopes of reſtoring it to itſelf, the Removal of the
          <lb/>Bone ſo degenerated, is the only Method to be pur- <lb/>ſued; as that will make way
          for the Application of <lb/>the actual Cautery, wherein the Cure principally
          <lb/>conſiſts: And if this does not ſucceed, we muſt pro- <lb/>ceed to Amputation. This
          was the Caſe of Mr. <hi rend="italic">Co- <lb/>reho</hi> in <hi rend="italic">St. Mary
            Axe</hi>, whoſe Thumb Mr. <hi rend="italic">Sainthill</hi>
          <lb/>took off the 26th of <hi rend="italic">October</hi>, 1739, Mr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Ferne</hi> and <lb/>I being preſent: The laſt Bone of which, affected <lb/>with a <hi
            rend="italic">Spina ventoſa</hi> about 18 Years, was ſo ſwelled <lb/>out, and changed
          into Fleſh, that not the leaſt Part <lb/>of this Bone, as a Bone, was found, but only its
          car- <lb/>tilaginous Covering, in the Articulation with the ſe- <lb/>cond Internode; all
          the Bone itſelf being nothing elſe <lb/>but a Lump of Fleſh. </p>
      </div>
      <figure>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Explanation of the Figures in <hi rend="sc">Tab. II.</hi>
        </head>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 1 and 2. </head>
        <p rend="hanging">
          <lb/>Repreſent a <hi rend="italic">Spina ventoſa</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Os
            Humeri</hi> of the <lb/>right Arm, after an Operation performed upon it, <lb/>during
          Life, with the exfoliative <hi rend="italic">Trepan</hi>. The <lb/>Diſtemper in the Bone
          being complicated with an <lb/><hi rend="italic">Anchyloſis</hi> and Carioſity of the Head
          of the <hi rend="italic">Cubi- <lb/>tus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Radius</hi> in the
          Articulation of the Elbow, <pb n="206"/>
          <lb/>occaſioned by the nutritive Juice in the inner <lb/>Cavity of the Bone, where the <hi
            rend="italic">Medulla</hi> was waſted <lb/>by an Ulcer, running out thro' ſeveral Holes
          made <lb/>by it directly into this Joint. <hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 2. repreſents the
          <lb/>Exfoliation, which lay concealed within this Bone, <lb/>until the Time the Operation
          above-mentioned, it <lb/>was taken out by, was performed. This exfoliated <lb/>Bone being
          harder than the main Bone itſelf it was <lb/>incloſed in, and ſeemingly ſound, whilſt the
          latter <lb/>was carious: Notwithſtanding the caſt-off Bone <lb/>had been ſoaking longeſt
          in the Matter extravaſated <lb/>and pent up in the medullary Cavity, which was <lb/>the
          Original of the <hi rend="italic">Spina ventoſa</hi>, this Exfoliation, <lb/>which was the
          firſt Conſequence of the extrava- <lb/>ſated Matter within the Bone having, as it were,
          <lb/>been detached from the main Bone, which was <lb/>diſſolved by it, ſome time before it
          could poſſibly <lb/>reach the Body of the Bone itſelf. </p>
        <p rend="hanging">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 1. The <hi rend="italic">Os Humeri</hi> amputated near
          the Shoulder- <lb/>Joint <hi rend="italic">b</hi>, with the two Bones of the Fore-Arm
          <lb/>ſawed off in <hi rend="italic">E F</hi>. <hi rend="italic">a a a a</hi>, Several
          large Openings <lb/>in the Bone below and under the Deltoid Muſcle, <lb/>where the Bone
          had formerly been diſtemper'd and <lb/>affected by the <hi rend="italic">Spina
            ventoſa</hi>; this Part of the <lb/>Bone appearing ſound, and ſeemingly reſtored to
          <lb/>its natural State; whilſt all the reſt of it down- <lb/>wards is ſtrangely alter'd by
          the Humour occa- <lb/>ſioning it, and degenerating, as it were, into a <lb/>cartilaginous
          Subſtance, or ſuch a one as could <lb/>readily be cut with a Knife; the interior being
          <lb/>deſtroyed by a Carioſity, and the exterior, which <lb/>was ſpread out beyond its
          natural Dimenſions, in- <lb/>cruſted by a callous Expanſion ſticking to it, made <pb
            n="207"/>
          <lb/>ſolid, and forming a Body with it, ſaving where <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
            >Perioſtium</hi> was ſtrongly adhering, the <hi rend="italic">Cortex</hi>
          <lb/>of the Bone, after the <hi rend="italic">Exoſtoſis</hi>, or callous Shell <lb/>ſpread
          over it was taken off, being perforated with <lb/>many Blood-veſſels, which were larger,
          and more <lb/>in Number than uſual; theſe Veſſels perforating <lb/>it, as it was render'd
          ſoft and yielding, and the <lb/>indurated callous Matter ſticking to it, as well
          <lb/>within as without, was cover'd with a callous Fleſh <lb/>ſprouting from it. </p>
        <p rend="hanging">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">BB</hi>, A large Opening made in the external Part of <lb/>the Bone
          by the Trepan, wherewith the whole <lb/>medullary Cavity of it was laid open; this Open-
          <lb/>ing taking into its Scope 10 or 12 large Holes in <lb/>the Bone, all leading into
          that Cavity thro' which <lb/>the Matter pent in, and cauſing the <hi rend="italic">Spina
            ventoſa</hi>, <lb/>at times had worked its Way out by; which, when <lb/>laid into one by
          the Operation, favour'd the Ex- <lb/>traction of the tubular Exfoliation, <hi
            rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 2. which, <lb/>tho' it was intirely looſe in, and detached from
          <lb/>the Circumference of, the medullary Cavity, yet <lb/>was ſo concealed in it, by the
            <hi rend="italic">Fungus</hi>'s obturating <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Foramina</hi> in
          the Bone, as not to have been <lb/>diſcover'd before the Opening, it was taken out
          <lb/>by, was made in the Bone. </p>
        <p rend="hanging">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">C</hi>, A large Hole in the Place where the external <lb/>Proceſs
          of the <hi rend="italic">Humerus</hi> formerly ſtood; that hav- <lb/>ing been deſtroyed,
          by the Matter cauſing a great <lb/>Carioſity here; which alſo running out of the <lb/>Bone
          thro' the <hi rend="italic">Foramina</hi> made into the Joint, had <lb/>occaſioned the <hi
            rend="italic">Anchyloſis</hi>, and the Carioſity of all <lb/>the Bones there. </p>
        <pb n="208"/>
        <p rend="hanging">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">G</hi>, An <hi rend="italic">Exoſtoſis</hi>, or callous Expanſion
          on the exter- <lb/>nal Surface of the <hi rend="italic">Os Humeri</hi>, attached to it by
          <lb/>a cartilaginous Subſtance forming a Creſt there, <lb/>about two Inches long, and half
          an Inch high; <lb/>which, being wedged in between the Interſtices of <lb/>the Muſcles, by
          their Motion hath been kept in <lb/>ſome meaſure looſe upon it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is obſervable, that, during Life, the Subſtance of <lb/>this Bone had been
          render'd ſo ſoft, as to have yielded <lb/>when preſſed upon, if it had not been ſtiffened
          by the <lb/>indurated callous Shell, or <hi rend="italic">Exoſtoſis</hi>, ſpread over it,
          <lb/>wherewith it was incruſted from one End to the other: <lb/>And this indurated callous
          Subſtance, ſeemingly im- <lb/>bodied in the Bone internally, ending externally in <lb/>a
          griſly, fleſhy, and gelatinous Subſtance: All which, <lb/>ſticking to the Bone, added
          greatly to the apparent <lb/>Tumour of it; as doubtleſs, in time, that would have
          <lb/>been one with it; it appearing that all theſe Subſtances <lb/>would have acquired the
          Conſiſtency of it; tho', as yet, <lb/>they had only attained that of a <hi rend="italic"
            >Callus</hi> in its Infancy. </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of a disfigured humerus (upper arm bone) on a separate fold-out
          page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 2. </head>
        <p rend="hanging">
          <lb/>A tubular Exfoliation from all the Circumference <lb/>of the medullary Cavity of the
            <hi rend="italic">Os Humeri</hi>, ſe- <lb/>ven Inches in Length, and near two in Circum-
          <lb/>ference; which, lying looſe and detached from <lb/>the main Bone, was extracted whole
          thro' the <lb/>large Opening made in it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And thus, upon the Whole, it appears, that the In- <lb/>flammation, Suppuration, and
          Ulcer in the <hi rend="italic">Medulla</hi>, <lb/>in the firſt place, has brought about
          the Conſumption <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Medulla</hi> with the Bone; and, ſoon after,
          <lb/>ſuch an Alteration in it, as hath given Cauſe to the <pb n="209"/>
          <lb/>Exfoliation that hath happened: And that the Matter <lb/>confined, in time having
          acquired a greater Acri- <lb/>mony, hath gained the Power of ſoftening, diſſolving,
          <lb/>and deſtroying entirely the Bone, wherein the Cir- <lb/>culation of the Juices was
          preſerved excluſive of any <lb/>other Bone, that hath been laid out of the Way of
          <lb/>that Circulation, or hath happened to be detached <lb/>from it: Tho' this laſt
          evidently hath lain more under <lb/>the Power of the Matter than the main Bone itſelf was;
          <lb/>and to have been ſoaking longeſt in that very Matter, <lb/>which hath deſtroyed that
          Bone wherein that Circu- <lb/>lation of the Juices hath been preſerved; and there-
          <lb/>fore, that the Way to a ſpeedy Cure of the <hi rend="italic">Spina ven-
            <lb/>toſa</hi>, is, the making, as ſoon as poſſible, a fair Open- <lb/>ing into the
          medullary Cavity of the Bone that is <lb/>affected with it. </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of a hollow tube, its surface rough and pocked, on a separate
          fold-out page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 3. </head>
        <p rend="hanging">
          <lb/>Repreſents the anterior Surface of the left <hi rend="italic">Tibia</hi> of <lb/>a
          young Perſon affected with a <hi rend="italic">Spina ventoſa</hi>, in- <lb/>cloſing an
          Exfoliation detached from all the Cir- <lb/>cumference of the <hi rend="italic"
            >Medulla</hi>, about ſeven Inches <lb/>in Length; which is to be ſeen through a great
          <lb/>Number of Openings in the <hi rend="italic">Cortex</hi> of it. </p>
        <p>
          <list rend="hanging">
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">AA</hi>, An <hi rend="italic">Exoſtoſis</hi>, or Incruſtation
              in the Bone in- <lb/>larged, with an Opening in it four Inches long, <lb/>and one
              broad, through which the incloſed Exfo- <lb/>liation <hi rend="italic">BB</hi>
              appears; the <hi rend="italic">Caries</hi> of the Bone in the <lb/>Joint of the Knee,
              and nine large Openings in the <lb/>Body of it, having been made by the Matter diſ-
              <lb/>charging from the medullary Cavity, and cauſing <lb/>a Carioſity in the incloſing
              Bone only; whilſt the <lb/>exfoliated within is preſerved in its natural State. </item>
            <pb n="210"/>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">C</hi>, The Carioſity of the Bone in the Joint of the
              <lb/>Knee, communicated to the <hi rend="italic">Os Femoris</hi> where- <lb/>with it
              is anchyloſed in <hi rend="italic">D</hi>. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">D</hi>, The <hi rend="italic">Epiphyſis</hi> of the <hi
                rend="italic">Os Femoris</hi> in the Joint <lb/>of the Knee, deſtroyed by the
              Carioſity. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">E</hi>, The lower End of the Bone, as yet in a natural
              <lb/>State, with its <hi rend="italic">Epiphyſes</hi> forming the internal <lb/>Ankle.
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of a shinbone with a large opening in its middle on a separate
          fold-out page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 4. </head>
        <p rend="hanging">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">A A</hi>, The anterior and internal Surface of the left <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Tibia</hi>, cut off in <hi rend="italic">B</hi>, where the Bone was ſound:
          <lb/>The oppoſite End being carious, and perforated <lb/>with many large <hi rend="italic"
            >Foramina</hi> or Openings made by the <lb/>Matter flowing into the Joint of the Knee,
          from the <lb/>medullary Cavity in the Bone. The Exfoliation, <lb/><hi rend="italic">c c
            c</hi>, ſeemingly ſound, is detached from the Cavity; <lb/>but is locked and wedged in
          by the <hi rend="italic">Exoſtoſis</hi>, or cal- <lb/>lous Matter indurated on the
          Surface, in ſuch <lb/>manner that it cannot be taken out without cut- <lb/>ting off the
          Edges of it. </p>
        <p rend="hanging">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">dddd</hi>, The upper Part of the Bone, carious within <lb/>and
          without, made rough and unequal by the <hi rend="italic">Ex- <lb/>oſtoſis</hi>, or callous
          Expanſion render'd carious. </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of a shinbone with a large opening in its middle and one end badly
          decayed on a separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 5. </head>
        <p rend="hanging">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">A</hi>, Repreſents a Portion of the <hi rend="italic">Os
            Humeri</hi> ſawed off, <lb/>at the time of the Amputation of the Limb; which <lb/>is
          ſolder'd by an <hi rend="italic">Anchyloſis</hi> with the <hi rend="italic">Cubitus
          B</hi>, and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Radius C</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">D</hi>; <hi
            rend="italic">E</hi> being a large Exfoliation de- <lb/>tached from them, where thoſe
          Bones had been <lb/>ſhatter'd, which is wedged in by a callous Expan- <lb/>ſion, in ſuch
          manner that it could not be taken out. </p>
        <pb n="211"/>
        <p rend="hanging">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">E</hi>, The Exfoliation from the <hi rend="italic">Cubitus</hi>,
          three Inches <lb/>long, adhering to an Exfoliation from the <hi rend="italic">Radius</hi>
          <lb/>of the ſame Length, not ſeen; both which, being <lb/>almoſt of the Subſtance of the
          whole Bone, are <lb/>knit together by a <hi rend="italic">Callus</hi>: So that their
          Re-union <lb/>is prior to the Cauſe which has occaſioned the <lb/>Exfoliation. </p>
        <p rend="hanging">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">FFF</hi>, A callous Expanſion, incloſing the Bones which <lb/>are
          detached within, not hardened in the Middle <lb/><hi rend="italic">G</hi>; and partly
          cartilaginous there: So that, in <lb/>this Place, the Bones made up by the callous Ex-
          <lb/>panſion could play upon each other. </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of the two long forearm bones (ulna and radius), both badly
          disfigured, on a separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
