<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - le Cat and Zollman: An Observation of an Operation Made by the High
          Apparatus</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Claud. Nic. le Cat</persName>
              <persName>Philip Henry Zollman</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Observation of an Operation Made by the High Apparatus, According to M. le
              Cat's Method, in the Year 1743; by Claud. Nic. le Cat, M. D. F. R. S. Surgeon to the
              Hotel Dieu at Rouen, and Royal Demonstrator in Anatomy and Surgery; Translated from
              the French by Philip Henry Zollman, F. R. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for C. Davis, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn; Printer to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1746</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">44</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">175-184</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110043561</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1746.0036</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT44_0175">
    <body>
      <pb n="175"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">I.</hi> An Obſervation of an Operation made by <lb/>the <hi
          rend="roman">high Apparatus</hi>, according to M. <hi rend="roman">le <lb/>Cat</hi>'s
        Method, in the Year 1743; by <lb/><hi rend="roman">Claud. Nic. le Cat</hi>, M. D. F. R. S.
        Sur- <lb/>geon to the <hi rend="roman">Hotel Dieu</hi> at <hi rend="roman">Rouen</hi>, and
        <lb/>Royal Demonſtrator in Anatomy and Sur- <lb/>gery; tranſlated from the <hi rend="roman"
          >French</hi> by <hi rend="roman">Philip <lb/>Henry Zollman</hi>, F. R. S. </head>
      <div>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/>
          <note place="inset" rend="italic size(0.7)">Read <hi rend="roman">May 1. <lb/>1746.</hi>
          </note><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> HAVE given to the <note n="*" place="bottom"
            rend="size(0.7)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* See theſe <hi rend="italic">Tranſ.</hi> N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 476, <hi
                rend="italic">p.</hi> 391. </p>
          </note>
          <hi rend="italic">Royal Society</hi>
          <lb/>a Deſcription of a particular Method <lb/>of making the high <hi rend="italic"
            >Apparatus</hi>, and have proved its <lb/>Theory, by a Cure happily performed in
          practiſing <lb/>it. — The Spring of the Year 1743 furniſhed me <lb/>with a new Opportunity
          of confirming the Goodneſs <lb/>of this Method; which, by certain Circumſtances, <lb/>was
          put to ſuch a Trial, that I queſtion whether the <lb/>Stone could have been taken out by
          any other Man- <lb/>ner of Cutting. For this Reaſon I have thought this <lb/>Obſervation
          deſerved a Place, as a Supplement to the <lb/>Account which I have preſented to the <hi
            rend="italic">Society</hi> con- <lb/>cerning this Method. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Joſeph Bunel</hi>, of 12 Years of Age, a Native of <hi
            rend="italic">la <lb/>Bucaille</hi>, and living at <hi rend="italic">Vitry</hi> near <hi
            rend="italic">Andely</hi>, was af- <lb/>flicted with the Stone for 8 or 9 Years paſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Friday</hi> the 17th of <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 1743, being the
          Day <lb/>appointed to cut him, I prepared myſelf to do it by <pb n="176"/>
          <lb/>the lateral <hi rend="italic">Apparatus</hi>, which is the common Method. <lb/>At 5
          o' Clock in the Morning the Patient was placed <lb/>in the uſual Manner for the Operation;
          and I, en- <lb/>deavouring to enter the Probe, in order to cut him <lb/>laterally, found
          the Stone ſo big, or at leaſt ſo far <lb/>advanced in the Neck of the Bladder, that I had
          all <lb/>the Trouble in the World to make the Inſtrument <lb/>enter; nor could I effect
          it, otherwiſe than by thruſt- <lb/>ing it quite on the Side. I put my Finger into the
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Anus</hi>, and was convinced of the Reality of the Cir-
          <lb/>cumſtances which the Prboe had made appear: I <lb/>immediately thought that the
          Situation of this Stone <lb/>in the Neck of the Bladder would hinder me from <lb/>bringing
          the Inſtruments freely to it; that, as this <lb/>hard Body ſeem'd exactly to fill the
          Bladder, it would <lb/>be impoſſible to introduce a Pair of Pincers between <lb/>it and
          the Inſides of the Bladder; that, its Bulk <lb/>being too conſiderable, would cauſe a
          mortal Lacera- <lb/>tion by the low <hi rend="italic">Apparatus</hi>; and, laſtly, that
          the Pa- <lb/>tient was in ſuch a Caſe of Neceſſity, as required <lb/>to have recourſe to
          the high <hi rend="italic">Apparatus</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Not having ſuſpected all theſe particular Circum- <lb/>ſtances, and not being much
          inclined to make an <lb/>Operation in Town, which I had as yet made but <lb/>once, I had
          not brough my Inſtruments with me <lb/>for cutting by the high <hi rend="italic"
            >Apparatus</hi>; but, ſeeing it <lb/>would be a Raſhneſs in this Caſe, to perform the
          lateral <lb/>Operation, and not to prefer the high <hi rend="italic">Apparatus</hi>
          <lb/>to it, contrary to all my Experiments and Principles, <lb/>I put off the Operation to
          the next Day, and ſent to <lb/><hi rend="italic">Roüen</hi> for my Inſtruments for cutting
          by the high <lb/><hi rend="italic">Apparatus</hi>. </p>
        <pb n="177"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>That Day at Noon I gave the Patient a very light <lb/>Soup. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Saturday</hi> the 18th, I cut him by the high <hi rend="italic"
            >Appa- <lb/>ratus</hi> at 8 in the Morning. The Surgeon who was <lb/>gone to fetch the
          Inſtruments, brought Mr. <hi rend="italic">Graſſe</hi>, <lb/>a Surgeon from <hi
            rend="italic">Dublin</hi>, with him, who was come <lb/>to <hi rend="italic">Roüen</hi>,
          on the Part of Meſſieurs <hi rend="italic">Morand</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Ver-
            <lb/>dier</hi>, to ſee my Way of Cutting; and I had 10 or <lb/>12 young Surgeons with me
          who were come from <lb/><hi rend="italic">Roüen</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Patient was placed upon one of thoſe little <lb/>Beds which the Turners make for
          the Country Peo- <lb/>ple; the two Extremities of the Bed were rais'd, <lb/>eſpecially
          that which was to ſupport the Thighs, and <lb/>the Middle was hollow; the Whole covered
          with <lb/><hi rend="italic">Alaizes</hi>
          <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Theſe are Cloths folded ſeveral times, and laid under the Pa- <lb/>tients, to
              keep them cleanly. </p>
          </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Patient's Head was towards the Light; his <lb/>Hands and Feet were tied acroſs
          the Bed, in the Places <lb/>where they came to lie, when the Patient was laid on <lb/>his
          Back; his Legs were ſtretch'd and open; his Arms <lb/>brought down below his Hips; in a
          Word, he was in <lb/>a very convenient Poſture. I was on the right Side of <lb/>the
          Patient. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In this Manner I thruſted an <hi rend="italic">Algalie</hi> (or hollow <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Catheter</hi>) into the Bladder, introducing it on the <lb/>Side, as I had
          done the Day before. I injected a <lb/>Syringe-full of lukewarm Water into the Bladder;
          <lb/>which occaſion'd a Protuberance not immediately <lb/>above the <hi rend="italic"
            >Pubis</hi>, but three or four Fingers Breadth <pb n="178"/>
          <lb/>higher; which plainly proved, that the Stone took <lb/>up the whole exterior and
          inferior Region of the <lb/>Bladder. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I opened the Teguments, and thruſted my Inſtru- <lb/>ment into the Bladder cloſe to
          the <hi rend="italic">Pubis</hi>; but, find- <lb/>ing there only one Membrane, and the
          Stone, I was <lb/>obliged to bring the Edge of my Knife upwards, and <lb/>then the
          Inſtrument really enter'd, and Abundance <lb/>of Water and Urine came forth. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I turn'd again my Inſtrument, to ſupport the Blad- <lb/>der with the projecting Part,
          which is on the Back <lb/>of it <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* See the Figures in the preceding Account, <hi rend="italic">Tranſ.</hi> N<hi
                rend="sup">o</hi>. 476. </p>
          </note>. I ſlipt over it the ſtrait <hi rend="italic">Suſpenſor</hi> (a <hi rend="italic"
            >Catheter</hi>
          <lb/>that opens with a Bow), and dilated the Bladder with <lb/>the Inciſion Knife, towards
          the <hi rend="italic">Pubis</hi>, and intro- <lb/>duced the lateral <hi rend="italic"
            >Suſpenſors</hi>: I put my Finger into the <lb/>Bladder, and, having felt a Stone which
          was above <lb/>the firſt, I pull'd out this upper Stone with the <hi rend="italic">For-
            <lb/>ceps</hi>, which broke between the lateral <hi rend="italic">Suſpenſors</hi>.
          <lb/>I put my Finger in again, and felt another; which I <lb/>took hold of, and pull'd
          out, taking it for a third <lb/>Stone, though it was but a Fragment of the firſt,
          <lb/>which had eſcaped the <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This Fragment being taken out, I put my Finger <lb/>in again, and felt diſtinctly
          that the Bladder was parted <lb/>into two Chambers, like a Gourd. In the upper hin-
          <lb/>dermoſt Chamber, which I had open'd, the Injection <lb/>was lodg'd, and the Stone
          which I had taken out. <lb/>In the nethermoſt Chamber I felt the great Stone, <lb/>which
          went as far as the Neck of the Bladder, the <lb/>Top of which was ſurrounded by the
          Bladder like a <pb n="179"/>
          <lb/>Neck, the Opening of which did not admit more <lb/>than the Tip of one's Finger, with
          which I felt that <lb/>the Partitions of the Bladder were cloſely united, and <lb/>adhered
          to the Surface of this Stone. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Theſe melancholy Diſcoveries made me very un- <lb/>eaſy; this particular Structure of
          the Side of the Bot- <lb/>tom of the Bladder making me ſenſible of the ſame
          <lb/>Impoſſibility of introducing my Inſtruments, which I <lb/>had met with towards the
            <hi rend="italic">Perinæum</hi>. I try'd to <lb/>thruſt my Finger by Force between the
          Stone and <lb/>the Bladder, by ſetting the Nail ſtrongly againſt the <lb/>Stone, and
          looſening the Bladder from it, which <lb/>ſeem'd to adhere to it, dilating at the ſame
          time the <lb/>Bladder with all the Force my Finger was capable of. <lb/>I at laſt
          introduced my Finger to a certain Length, <lb/>with which I looſened the adherent Parts
          from the <lb/>Stone all along as far as my Finger could reach; then <lb/>I try'd to paſs
          in my <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi>, afterwards my different <lb/>Scoops, but all in
          vain. I was for an Inſtant believ- <lb/>ing that I could not get it out. This frightful
          Idea <lb/>made me redouble my Endeavours. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I begun to dilate again with the Forefinger of my <lb/>left Hand, and, with the ſame
          Finger, and the Thumb <lb/>of my right Hand in the <hi rend="italic">Anus</hi>, I
          violently thruſt the <lb/>Stone upwards towards the Belly, after a long and <lb/>painful
          Labour, both for the Patient and the Ope- <lb/>rator. I introduced upon my Finger, which
          was <lb/>between the Stone and the Bladder, the ſmall Scoop <lb/>of my double Crochet (ſee
            <hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 11. <hi rend="sc">Tab.</hi> IV. <hi rend="italic"
            >Tranſ.</hi>
          <lb/>476.): I advanced it quite beyond the Stone, and <lb/>then I began to pull, having
          wrapp'd ſome Linen <lb/>round the Inſtrument which hurt me; but the <hi rend="italic"
            >Pubis</hi>, <lb/>under which the Stone was, cauſed an Obſtacle, not <pb n="180"/>
          <lb/>to be overcome. I therefore ordered an Aſſiſtant to <lb/>puſh through the <hi
            rend="italic">Anus</hi> the Stone towards the Belly; <lb/>and I, on my Side, having
          diſcover'd the End of the <lb/>Stone under the <hi rend="italic">Pubis</hi>, put in the
          Fore-finger of <lb/>my right Hand, and preſs'd as hard as poſſible the <lb/>Stone with it
          towards the Spoon, which, at the ſame <lb/>time, I ſtrongly pull'd with my left Hand.
          Theſe <lb/>three Forces being united, made the Stone at laſt <lb/>give Way, and brought it
          forth to the Joy of the <lb/>Spectators, as well as the Patient. The upper Side <lb/>of
          the Stone, that is to ſay, that which anſwer'd to <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Pubis</hi>,
          was pretty even, and ſeem'd to give a Paſ- <lb/>ſage to the Urine; the nether or hindmoſt
          Side, <lb/>which lay towards the Proſtates and the Entrance of <lb/>the Bladder, kept the
          Shape of theſe Parts; its Sub- <lb/>ſtance was crumbling, of a reddiſh Colour, and like
          <lb/>the Membrane of the Bladder, having a fungous Poile <lb/>on it (ſee the <hi
            rend="italic">Figures</hi>, <hi rend="sc">Tab.</hi> I. of this <hi rend="italic"
            >Tranſaction</hi>), <lb/>with which it ſeem'd to have been incorporated, and <lb/>of
          which a ſort of Covering yet remain'd upon its Sur- <lb/>face; this Covering being taken
          off, and the Stone a <lb/>little dried, this whole appear'd to be pierced with Po-
          <lb/>roſities, which ſeem'd to have been the Receptacles <lb/>of the foreſaid Poile. There
          was no Mark on this <lb/>Side of any Urine having paſſed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A Pledget charged with Digeſtives, a Rag dipp'd <lb/>in an Embrocation, and an
          emollient Cataplaſm, were <lb/>laid upon the Wound; the Patient was laid upon <lb/>the
          Belly, his Breaſt being ſupported by one Bolſter, <lb/>and his Head by another. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Saturday</hi>, 1ſt Day. An Hour after he was let <lb/>Blood 3
          Porringers full. </p>
        <pb n="181"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>He found himſelf a little out of Order after Bleed- <lb/>ing, and had ſeveral <hi
            rend="italic">Nauſea's</hi>. I had a ſimple <lb/>Cordial made for him with five Ounces
          of Balm- <lb/>Water, one Ounce of Syrup of Barberries, and one <lb/>Ounce of Syrup of
          Clove-july flowers; of which he <lb/>took ſeveral Spoons-full a Day, when his Spirits
          <lb/>ſeem'd to fail him. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>He ſweated much all the Afternoon; which made <lb/>me defer bathing him till half an
          Hour after Seven; his <lb/>Pulſe was ſhort, quick, and ſtrong: The firſt Hour <lb/>he was
          in the Bath made no Alteration; he was ſick <lb/>at Heart, and ſpit up a white Froth; at
          laſt he fell <lb/>aſleep in the Bath for at leaſt an Hour: His Pulſe <lb/>ſeem'd to be
          ſlower, and, coming out of the Bath, he <lb/>found himſelf very well. He was dreſſed as
          before <lb/>at 10 o' Clock, and laid upon the Belly. He ſlept <lb/>beſt Part of the Night,
          which hindred his being <lb/>blooded at 3 or 4 o' Clock, as I had order'd. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">May</hi> 19th, <hi rend="italic">Sunday</hi>, 2d Day.] At 8 o'
          Clock in <lb/>the Morning I found him in a ſtrong Fever. I had <lb/>two Porringers of
          Blood taken from his Arm: The <lb/>Bleeding made his Pulſe ſhort, low, and quick, and
          <lb/>himſelf ſick at Heart. His Pulſe grew ſtrong again, <lb/>and the Fever came upon him.
          I deſigned to bathe <lb/>him yet that Morning; which ſhould have been done <lb/>if he had
          been blooded earlier; but it was late; and, <lb/>beſides, he had no Stool. I therefore
          thought <lb/>it neceſſary to give him an emollient and anodyne <lb/>Clyſter at 10 o'
          Clock. He was afterwards dreſs'd; <lb/>and I deferred his Bathing till 4 in the Afternoon:
          <lb/>But the Clyſter not being come from him, and the <lb/>Boy complaining of a Pain in
          his Stomach, I order'd <pb n="182"/>
          <lb/>him to be put in the Bath from half an Hour paſt <lb/>11, till half an Hour paſt 1. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>He found himſelf very well in the Bath; his <lb/>Clyſter there came from him, and he
          had a good <lb/>Stool. He was put to Bed again at a Quarter paſt 1: <lb/>There he had
          another Stool, and found himſelf very <lb/>well; nevertheleſs he was yet very feveriſh. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>He ſlept from half an Hour paſt 4 till half an Hour <lb/>paſt 6; after which his
          Fever was almoſt half gone. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>He was put into the Bath again at half an Hour <lb/>paſt 7 in the Evening. He deſired
          it himſelf; partly <lb/>on account of the Eaſe which it had hitherto given <lb/>him;
          partly becauſe the Situation of lying on his <lb/>Back, and ſitting in the Bath, was an
          agreeable <lb/>Change from that of lying on his Belly; which he <lb/>was oblig'd to do in
          his Bed. His Pulſe was very <lb/>well in the Bath; his Look and Eyes were more <lb/>clear
          than in the preceding Bathings; and indeed <lb/>he neither had any Pain in his Belly, nor
          at his Sto- <lb/>mach, nor in his Breaſt, nor in his Head; the Wound <lb/>only ſmarted
          now-and-then; he could not bear being <lb/>touch'd about it; however his Belly was very
          flat, and <lb/>he began to be hungry. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>He ſtaid an Hour and half in the Bath, and ſlept <lb/>good Part of the Night and
          Morning. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Monday</hi>, <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 20th, 3d Day.] He did not
          wake <lb/>till 8 o' Clock: He had hardly any Fever at all, and <lb/>he found himſelf much
          better than the Day before. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I order'd another Clyſter to be given him, on ac- <lb/>count of the Benefit which he
          had received from it <lb/>the Day before, and becauſe he had not been at Stool <lb/>ſince.
          It made him ſick at Stomach again, and did <lb/>not come from him. </p>
        <pb n="183"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I had him put into the Bath at 9 o' Clock. Part <lb/>of his Clyſter came from him
          there an Hour and half <lb/>after. At every Bathing I order'd a Spoonful of Cor- <lb/>dial
          to be given him at going in, and towards the <lb/>Middle of the Bath a Meſs of Broth, or 2
          half Meſſes. <lb/>He came out at the End of two Hours. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>After this fourth Bathing he found himſelf almoſt <lb/>without any Fever; and was ſo
          well, that he teiz'd <lb/>us and the Nurſes for ſomething to eat. This de- <lb/>termined
          me to let the Suppuration quietly fix itſelf; <lb/>which ſeem'd already to begin at the
          Wound of the <lb/>Teguments. He made Water this Day once or twice <lb/>through the <hi
            rend="italic">Penis</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tueſday</hi>, <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 21ſt, 4th Day.] In the
          Morning <lb/>he was without a Fever; and the Diſtemper which <lb/>he complain'd of moſt
          was Hunger. I then ſet out <lb/>for <hi rend="italic">Roüen</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Patient continued to grow better every Day. <lb/>I returned the 10th Day, to
          preſcribe him a leſs ſtrict <lb/>Diet. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Cicatrix</hi> of the Bladder had form'd itſelf on <lb/>the
          20th. That Day no Urine at all paſſed any more <lb/>through the Wound of the Belly, a
          large Bandage <lb/>was laid over the Wound, and he was ſometimes put <lb/>on his Back;
          eſpecially after he began to make Water <lb/>through the <hi rend="italic">Penis</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Wound of the Teguments was intirely cica- <lb/>trized on the 40th Day; and he was
          ſo well, that <lb/>he came to ſee me at <hi rend="italic">Roüen</hi> on the 50th Day. He
          <lb/>was grown ſo fat, that I hardly knew him again. </p>
        <figure>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>Explanation of the Figures. <hi rend="sc">Tab. II.</hi>
          </head>
          <p rend="hanging">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 1. repreſents the anterior and upper Side of the
            <lb/>Stone. </p>
          <figDesc>An illustration of a bladder stone, on a separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb n="184"/>
        <figure>
          <p rend="hanging">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 2. the poſterior and under Side, which reſted
            <lb/>partly upon the <hi rend="italic">Proſtatæ</hi>. This Side of the Stone <lb/>was
            attach'd to the Bladder. </p>
          <p rend="indentall indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">a.</hi> the Place where the Body of the Bladder was
            <lb/>contracted in Form of the Neck of a Gourd. </p>
          <p rend="indentall indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">b.</hi> the Extremity, which was lodged in the Be- <lb/>ginning
            of the <hi rend="italic">Urethra</hi>. </p>
          <p rend="indentall indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">c.</hi> the Impreſſion made by the Nail of the Fore- <lb/>finger
            of my left Hand, in paſſing it between the <lb/>Stone and the Inſide of the Bladder, in
            order to <lb/>detach them from each other, and to dilate the <lb/>Bladder ſufficiently
            to introduce the Crochet. </p>
          <figDesc>An illustration of a bladder stone, on a separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
