<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Glass: An Uncommon Dropsy from the Want of a Kidney</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Samuel Glass</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Uncommon Dropsy from the Want of a Kidney; And a Description of a Large Saccus
              That Contain'd the Water, by Samuel Glass, Surgeon, at Oxford; Sent to Dr.
              Mead</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for C. Davis, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn; Printer to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1746</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">44</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">337-343</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110043561</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1746.0061</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT44_0337">
    <body>
      <pb n="337"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">II.</hi> An uncommon <hi rend="roman">Dropſy</hi> from the Want of a
        <lb/>Kidney; and a Deſcription of a large <hi rend="roman">Saccus</hi>
        <lb/>that contain'd the Water, by <hi rend="roman">Samuel Glaſs</hi>, <lb/>Surgeon, at <hi
          rend="roman">Oxford</hi>; ſent to Dr. <hi rend="roman">Mead</hi>. </head>
      <dateline rend="size(0.7) align-right space">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">November</hi> 11, 1746. </dateline>
      <p>
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="size(0.7) italic">Read <date rend="roman">Jan. 8. <lb/>1746-7.
          </date>
        </note><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="dc(1.5)">M</hi>ARY Nix</hi>, who lived at <hi
          rend="italic">Hampton- <lb/>Poyle</hi>, a ſmall Village in <hi rend="italic">Oxford-
          <lb/>ſhire</hi>, had been remarkable all her Life for the pre- <lb/>ternatural Size of her
        Belly. After her Death, I had <lb/>the Curioſity, together with ſome learned Gentlemen
        <lb/>of the Univerſity, to inſpect her Body. Her Mother <lb/>was then preſent, and inform'd
        us, that this her <lb/>Daughter was born dropſical; that ſhe herſelf had <lb/>been ill of
        the ſame Diſeaſe for ſome time before, <lb/>and during, her Pregnancy; but, on the Birth of
        <lb/>this Child, ſhe was freed from that Diſorder. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Child, tho' born dropſical, prov'd otherwiſe <lb/>healthy; and, notwithſtanding the
        Diſeaſe continu- <lb/>ally increaſed as ſhe grew up, liv'd to be near twenty- <lb/>three
        Years of Age. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>She was a tall well-proportion'd Woman, except <lb/>with Regard to the enormous Size of
        her Belly; and, <lb/>for one of ſo unwieldy a Bulk, healthy, brisk, and <lb/>active. Her
        Appetite was always good, and ſhe was <lb/>never more than ordinarily thirſty; had no
        remarkable <lb/>Difficulty of Breathing, not even when ſhe lay ſu- <lb/>pine, nor did her
        Thighs or Legs ever ſwell. Her <lb/><hi rend="italic">Menſes</hi>, which appear'd at the
        uſual Time of Life, <lb/>continued regular, till within eight Months of her <lb/>Death. The
        only Complaint was now-and-then a <pb n="338"/>
        <lb/>Pain in making Water; and the Quantity ſhe made <lb/>was commonly about four or five
        Ounces. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon the Suppreſſion of her <hi rend="italic">Catamenia</hi>, there ſuc- <lb/>ceeded a
          <hi rend="italic">Dyſpnœa</hi>, Loſs of Appetite, Emaciation of <lb/>the ſuperior Parts,
        and a Tumefaction of one of her <lb/>Legs with Ulcerations. Theſe Symptoms gradually
        <lb/>increaſed till her Death. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon taking the Dimenſions of her Body before <lb/>Diſſection, we found the
        Circumference of her <hi rend="italic">Ab- <lb/>domen</hi> to be juſt ſix Feet four Inches,
        and from the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Xyphoid</hi> Cartilage to the <hi rend="italic">Os
          Pubis</hi> it meaſur'd four <lb/>Feet and half an Inch. The cutaneous Veſſels, diſ-
        <lb/>tributed upon the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, were remarkably large, <lb/>and
        diſtended with Blood, and the ſpurious Ribs <lb/>were preſſed greatly outwards and upwards. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After this general View of the external Parts, we <lb/>began the Diſſection, by
        dividing the Cartilages of <lb/>the ſix ſuperior Ribs, and raiſing the <hi rend="italic"
          >Sternum</hi>. The <lb/><hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi> being laid open, we obſerved that
        the Dia- <lb/>phragm was forcibly protruded into that Cavity. <lb/>The Baſe of the Heart lay
        under the right Clavicle, <lb/>and its <hi rend="italic">Apex</hi> upon the moſt convex Part
        of the Dia- <lb/>phragm; which Convexity advanced as high up as <lb/>the third ſuperior Rib.
        The Lungs were ſurpriſingly <lb/>ſmall, ſcarce exceeding in Magnitude thoſe of a new-
        <lb/>born Child. The right Lobe ſlightly adher'd to the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pleura</hi>,
        the left was free, and both were in a ſound <lb/>State. Within the <hi rend="italic"
          >Pericardium</hi> was found, as uſual, <lb/>a ſmall Quantity of Liquor, but none in the
        Cavity <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We next perforated the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi> in the moſt con- <lb/>venient
        depending Part, and evacuated from thence <lb/>a ſurpriſing Quantity of Water, which was
        lightly <pb n="339"/>
        <lb/>tinged of a Coffee-Colour, limpid as Urine, and not <lb/>in the leaſt fetid. This Water
        was carefully mea- <lb/>ſur'd, and found to be not above a Pint leſs than <lb/>thirty
        Gallons Wine Meaſure; which muſt weigh, <lb/>according to the common Calculation, near 240
          <hi rend="italic">l.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We afterwards made an Inciſion into the <hi rend="italic">Abdo- <lb/>men</hi> along the
          <hi rend="italic">Linea alba</hi>. The Integuments <lb/>upon the epigaſtric Region were
        very thin; the ab- <lb/>dominal Muſcles much extenuated; and above the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Umbilicus</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Tunica celluloſa</hi> contain'd no Fat;
        but <lb/>from the Navel to the <hi rend="italic">Os Pubis</hi>, the <hi rend="italic"
          >Panniculus <lb/>adipoſus</hi> was half an Inch thick. Upon dilating the <lb/>Inciſion,
        the large membranous Bag that contain'd <lb/>the Water preſented itſelf to View, adhering
        tranſ- <lb/>verſly about ten Inches to the anterior Part of the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Peritonæum</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This Adheſion being ſeparated, we had a full <lb/>View of this wonderful Reſervoir,
        which was of an <lb/>enormous Size, and had almoſt occupied the whole <lb/>Cavity of the <hi
          rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>. In Figure, Colour, Thick- <lb/>neſs, Number, Magnitude, and
        Diſtribution of Blood <lb/>veſſels, it very much reſembled the <hi rend="italic">Uterus</hi>
        of a <lb/>Cow at the End of Geſtation. The whole Inſide was <lb/>ſcabrous, and look'd as if
        parboil'd; and here and <lb/>there was obſerv'd a ſmall Quantity of a Coffee- <lb/>colour'd
        Sediment. On the left inferior Part was <lb/>diſcover'd the Orifice of a Duct, which open'd
        ob- <lb/>liquely into the Cavity of the <hi rend="italic">Saccus</hi>, and would <lb/>eaſily
        admit of a large Gooſe Quill. From this Open- <lb/>ing the Tube advanc'd about twelve Inches
        between <lb/>the Membranes of the Bag obliquely upwards, and <lb/>towards the right, from
        whence it was inflected <lb/>downwards, and paſs'd between the Duplicature of <pb n="340"/>
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Ligamentum latum Uteri</hi>, to be inſerted into <lb/>the Bladder
        of Urine. The <hi rend="italic">Saccus</hi> was connected to <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >Ligamentum ſuſpenſorium Hepatis</hi>, to a conſi- <lb/>derable Part of the <hi
          rend="italic">Meſocolon</hi>, to the <hi rend="italic">Peritonæum</hi>
        <lb/>on the right Side in two or three different Places, <lb/>to the ſame Membrane the whole
        Length of the <lb/>Spine, and to the <hi rend="italic">Ligamentum latum Uteri</hi> on the
        <lb/>right Side of the Body. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Liver was ſound, but leſs than in a natural <lb/>State; and its convex Part adher'd
        cloſely to the <lb/>Diaphragm. The Stomach, Spleen, <hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi>, ſmall
        <lb/>Inteſtines, and the upper Part of the <hi rend="italic">Colon</hi>, were <lb/>thruſt
        very high up into the left <hi rend="italic">Hypochondrium</hi>. <lb/>The Convolutions of
        the lower Part of the ſame <lb/>Inteſtine were intirely obliterated; and that, toge-
        <lb/>ther with the <hi rend="italic">Rectum</hi>, formed one continued ſtrait <lb/>Tube,
        from the left <hi rend="italic">Hypochondrium</hi> down to the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Anus</hi>. The left Kidney, with its emulgent Veſſels <lb/>and <hi rend="italic"
          >Ureter</hi>, were in their natural State and Situation. <lb/>The <hi rend="italic"
          >Uterus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Tuba Fallopiana</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Ovarium</hi>,
        on the <lb/>ſame Side, had nothing preternatural; but, on the <lb/>right Side, the <hi
          rend="italic">Fallopian</hi> Tube and Ovary were diſ- <lb/>pos'd in a very extraordinary
        Manner. The Tube, <lb/>by means of the Adheſion of the <hi rend="italic">Ligamentum latum
          <lb/>Uteri</hi> to the <hi rend="italic">Saccus</hi>, was extended to three times its
        <lb/>ordinary Length. The Ovary was likewiſe, by the ſame <lb/>Cauſe, render'd very
        preternatural, being no leſs <lb/>than five Inches three Quarters long, one Inch broad,
        <lb/>two Tenths of an Inch thick, and two Inches and <lb/>half diſtant from the <hi
          rend="italic">Uterus</hi>. The Bladder of Urine <lb/>was very ſmall, but appear'd to be
        ſound. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We then made an accurate Search for the right <lb/>Kidney; but, to our great Surprize,
        found no <pb n="341"/>
        <lb/>ſuch <hi rend="italic">Viſcus</hi>, nor any thing analogous to it, unleſs <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">Saccus</hi> that contain'd the Water already de- <lb/>ſcrib'd, may be
        eſteemed ſuch: And what ſeem'd to <lb/>favour this Opinion, was the Diſpoſition of the
        <lb/>emulgent Veſſels on the right Side, which were pro- <lb/>pagated from the <hi
          rend="italic">Aorta</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Vena cava</hi> to this <hi rend="italic"
          >Sac- <lb/>cus</hi>, in the ſame manner as to the Kidney on the <lb/>oppoſite Side; and,
        after having ran twelve or four- <lb/>teen Inches between the Membranes of the Bag with-
        <lb/>out any Ramifications, were diſtributed all over it <lb/>in the Manner
        before-mention'd. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From the foregoing Account the following Que- <lb/>ries are naturally ſuggeſted, which
        I leave to the <lb/>Determination of the Learned: </p>
      <p rend="space">
        <list rend="hanging">
          <item>
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Query</hi> 1. Was not the <hi rend="italic">Saccus</hi>
            originally a mis-ſhapen <lb/>Kidney, and the Duct a <hi rend="italic">Ureter</hi>? </item>
          <item>
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Query</hi> 2. Was not the Water contained in the <hi
              rend="italic">Sac- <lb/>cus</hi> prevented from growing putrid, by being con-
            <lb/>tinually drain'd off thro' the Duct into the Bladder <lb/>of Urine, and by being
            afreſh ſupplied by the <lb/>emulgent Artery; and more being ſecreted than <lb/>was
            evacuated, the Quantity thereby continually <lb/>increaſed? </item>
          <item>
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Query</hi> 3. Was not this the Reaſon why the Patient <lb/>had
            never any anaſarcous Swellings of her Thighs <lb/>or Legs, nor any Thirſt, or other
            Signs of a con- <lb/>firm'd Dropſy? </item>
          <item>
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Query</hi> 4. Were not the Lungs prevented from grow- <lb/>ing by
            the great Diminution of the Cavity of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi>, and the
            Preſſure they ſuſtain'd from the <lb/>diſtended <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>? And
            might not their never <lb/>having occupied a larger Space than they did at <lb/>Birth,
            be the Reaſon ſhe never labour'd under any <lb/>Difficulty of Breathing? </item>
          <pb n="342"/>
          <item>
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Query</hi> 5. Was not the Bladder of Urine likewiſe by <lb/>the
            ſuperincumbent Weight, prevented from di- <lb/>lating itſelf; and that the Reaſon why
            the Water <lb/>was often made, and always in ſo ſmall a <choice>
              <corr>Quan</corr>
              <sic>Qnan</sic>
            </choice>- <lb/>tity? </item>
        </list>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>In order to convey a more clear Idea of the ſeve- <lb/>ral Parts already deſcrib'd, to
        thoſe who may not <lb/>have an Opportunity of <unclear>inſpecting</unclear> them (they being
        <lb/>properly preſerved for that Purpoſe), and being ſen- <lb/>ſible of the great Difficulty
        of clearly repreſenting by <lb/>Words ſuch Things as are out of the ordinary Courſe <lb/>of
        Nature, I muſt beg Leave to refer the Reader to <lb/>the Figures hereto annex'd. </p>
      <figure>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>See <hi rend="sc">Tab. I.</hi>
        </head>
        <head rend="sc align-center space">
          <lb/>Fig. 1. </head>
        <p>
          <list rend="hanging">
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">aaaa</hi>, The great <hi rend="italic">Saccus</hi> that
              contain'd the Water. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">bb</hi>, The greater Diameter of the <hi rend="italic"
                >Saccus</hi>. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">cc</hi>, The leſſer Diameter. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">d</hi>, A prick'd Line ſhews the Entrance of the emul-
              <lb/>gent Veſſels. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">ef</hi>, Shews the Courſe of the Duct between the Mem-
              <lb/>branes of the <hi rend="italic">Saccus</hi>. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">f</hi>, The Orifice opening obliquely into the Cavity. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">eg</hi>, The inflected Part of the Duct, after its Egreſs
              <lb/>from the <hi rend="italic">Saccus</hi>, which paſſed between the <hi
                rend="italic">Liga- <lb/>mentum latum Uteri</hi> to the Bladder of Urine. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">g</hi>, The Duct, divided near the Bladder, where its
              <lb/>Cavity was ſo ſmall as only to admit of a com- <lb/>mon-ſiz'd Probe. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of a spherical, veined bag, on a separate fold-out page. Annexed is
          a scale, which shows the bag to be approximately two feet in diameter. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <pb n="343"/>
      <figure>
        <head rend="sc align-center space">
          <lb/>Fig. 2. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Repreſents the poſterior View of the <hi rend="italic">Uterus</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >Fal- <lb/>lopian</hi> Tubes, and Ovary. <list rend="space">
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">aa</hi>, The <hi rend="italic">Uterus</hi>. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">A</hi>, The <hi rend="italic">Os Tineæ</hi>. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">bc</hi>, The <hi rend="italic">Fallopian</hi> Tube in a natural
              State. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">c</hi>, The <hi rend="italic">Morſus Diaboli</hi>. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">d</hi>, The left Ovary in a natural State. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">ee</hi>, The <hi rend="italic">Ligamentum rotundum</hi>. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">fg</hi>, The right <hi rend="italic">Fallopian</hi> Tube. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">g</hi>, The <hi rend="italic">Morſus Diaboli</hi>. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">hh</hi>, The right Ovary. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">ii</hi>, The <hi rend="italic">Ligamentum rotundum</hi>. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">kkkk</hi>, The <hi rend="italic">Ligamentum latum Uteri</hi>. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">ll</hi>, Its Adheſion to the <hi rend="italic">Saccus</hi>.
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of the above-mentioned reproductive organs, the right side of which
          is disproportionately stretched, on a separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
