<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Cheselden: The Effects of the Lixivium saponis</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>William Cheselden</persName>
            </author>
            <title>The Effects of the Lixivium saponis, Taken Inwardly by a Man Aged 75 Years, Who
              Had the Stone, and in Whose Bladder, after His Decease, Were Found Two Hundred and
              Fourteen Stones: From William Cheselden, Esquire </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for C. Davis, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn; Printer to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1746</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">44</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">36-40</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110043561</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1746.0009</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT44_0036">
    <body>
      <pb n="36"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VII.</hi> The Effects of the <hi rend="roman">Lixivium Saponis</hi>,
        <lb/>taken inwardly by a Man aged 75 Years, <lb/>who had the Stone, and in whoſe Bladder,
        <lb/>after his Deceaſe, were found Two hundred <lb/>and fourteen Stones: From <hi
          rend="roman">William Che- <lb/>ſelden</hi>, Eſquire. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="italic size(0.7)">Read <date rend="roman">Jan. 13. <lb/>1745-6.
          </date>
        </note><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="dc(1.5)">M</hi>AY</hi> 21. 1739. <hi rend="italic"
          >Laurence Welch</hi>, aged <lb/>75, born in <hi rend="italic">Denmark</hi>, but at that
        <lb/>time a Penſioner in his Majeſty's Royal Hoſpital at <lb/><hi rend="italic"
        >Chelſea</hi>, after having had Symptoms of the Stone <lb/>for eight Years, but never known
        to void any in all <lb/>that time, began to take ten Drops of <hi rend="italic">Lixiv.
          Sapon.</hi>
        <lb/>in half a Pint of Water, three times a Day; and on <lb/>the 23d in the Evening voided
        ſeveral ſmall Scales of <lb/>Stone, with little or no Pain. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 24th the Doſe was increaſed to fifteen <lb/>Drops; but, making him very ſick,
        was reduced on <lb/>the 25th to ten. He complained of great Pain in his <lb/>Back this Day,
        and at Night paſs'd a whole Stone, <lb/>the Size of an Orange-kernel, and ſeveral little
        Bits. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 26th he complain'd of great Soreneſs in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Urethra</hi>
        when he made Water; for which a little <lb/>Oil was injected, and he took eight Ounces of a
        <lb/>Solution of Gum-Arabic inwardly, omitting this Day <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >Lixivium</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Being very eaſy on the 27th, he took the <hi rend="italic">Lixivium</hi>
        <lb/>as before: His Urine was thick and plentiful, but <lb/>had no Gravel or Sand in it. </p>
      <pb n="37"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 28th he took the <hi rend="italic">Lixivium</hi>, and about <lb/>four in the
        Afternoon voided ſeveral Bits of ſmall <lb/>Stone, of different Make and Texture, ſome as
        large <lb/>as Tares; which making the <hi rend="italic">Urethra</hi> very ſore, on <lb/>the
        29th he omitted the <hi rend="italic">Lixivium</hi>, and took a Solu- <lb/>tion of the Gum,
        and had the Oil injected as before. <lb/>Being ſearch'd this Afternoon, we perceived a great
        <lb/>Quantity of Stone in his Bladder. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 30th he took the <hi rend="italic">Lixivium</hi> again, was <lb/>very ſick, but
        eaſy. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The 31ſt, taking the <hi rend="italic">Lixivium</hi> after great Pain <lb/>in his Back,
        Belly, and <hi rend="italic">Penis</hi>, he paſs'd a large Piece <lb/>of Stone, with ſeveral
        ſmaller Bits. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 1. he took nothing, was very eaſy, and made <lb/>a great
        Quanity of thick turbid Urine. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He took the <hi rend="italic">Lixivium</hi> again the next Day, was <lb/>very eaſy, and
        continued ſo all the 3d; but on the <lb/>4th was in great Pain all Day and Night. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 5th, the Medicine having ſat well on his <lb/>Stomach theſe three Days, I
        ventur'd to give him fif- <lb/>teen Drops of the <hi rend="italic">Lixivium</hi>; and, after
        having great <lb/>Pain in his Loins and <hi rend="italic">Penis</hi>, at Night he voided ſe-
        <lb/>veral large Bits. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Early in the Morning, after very great Pain, on <lb/>the 6th, he voided three large
        Bits of Stone, and in <lb/>the Afternoon ſeveral more Pieces came away; one <lb/>of which
        was the largeſt yet voided. He took the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Solut. Gum. Arab.</hi> this
        Day, and no <hi rend="italic">Lixivium</hi>; and <lb/>at Night, being faint and fatigued
        with Pain and <lb/>Want of Reſt, he had an Opiate and cordial Julap. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On th 7th he likewiſe took no <hi rend="italic">Lixivium</hi>, hav- <lb/>ing great Pain
        and Sickneſs at his Stomach. His <lb/>Urine To-day appeared a little bloody, and had a <pb
          n="38"/>
        <lb/>tough <hi rend="italic">Mucus</hi> in it, which ſunk to the Bottom of the <lb/>Pot, and
        was very fetid. In the Afternoon a large <lb/>Piece of Stone ſtopt at the Extremity of the
          <hi rend="italic">Penis</hi>; <lb/>which, after endeavouring for two Hours to preſs
        <lb/>out with his Fingers in vain, was extracted, by en- <lb/>larging the Orifice. This
        Stone weigh'd but nine <lb/>Grains and a half, tho' near as large as a Die; and <lb/>two
        which he voided before, near as big, and of a <lb/>triangular Form, weigh'd, one, eight
        Grains, the <lb/>other, ſeven and three Quarters. This Day he took <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">Solut. Gum. Arab.</hi> and at Night had an Opiate <lb/>and cordial Julap, to
        take a little of now and then. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 8th he took nothing; and tho' he had a <lb/>great deal of Pain, and was very
        weak, had a better <lb/>Appetite than any Day ſince he began the Courſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He complain'd of Pain, in the Morning on the <lb/>9th; ſo took no Medicine; was very
        eaſy the reſt of <lb/>the Day, and paſs'd ſome very ſmall Scales. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 10th he took the <hi rend="italic">Lixivium</hi>, and was <lb/>pretty well. The
        11th had great Pain, and was very <lb/>ſick; and alſo on the 12th: Therefore he omitted
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Lixivium</hi> on the 13th; and, being very faint and <lb/>low,
        had a cordial Julep. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 14th he took the <hi rend="italic">Lixivium</hi>, and was very <lb/>eaſy every
        Day till the 20th, when he complain'd <lb/>his Water made him ſmart; and alſo the 21ſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The 22d he was very full of Pain, and ſick; there- <lb/>fore on the 23d he took only
        the <hi rend="italic">Solut. Gum. Arab.</hi>
        <lb/>was eaſy, and had a great deal of <hi rend="italic">Mucus</hi> come away <lb/>with
        ſeveral ſmall ſcaly Bits of Stone in his Urine; <lb/>and alſo on the 24th and 25th. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He complain'd of great Pain in the <hi rend="italic">Glans Penis</hi>
        <lb/>on the 26th; and his Belly ſwell'd, and pitted juſt <pb n="39"/>
        <lb/>above the <hi rend="italic">Os Pubis</hi>; and he voided ſome ſmall <lb/>Bits in a
        great Quantity of <hi rend="italic">Mucus</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 27th a few little Bits were voided, and he <lb/>had no Pain all Day. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The 28th he had great Pain, and made very little <lb/>Water; but on the 29th made a
        great deal of Water. <lb/>His Belly was ſwell'd, and he complain'd of great <lb/>Pain in his
        Loins.—He voided ſome ſmall Bits of <lb/>Stone on the 30th, which was the laſt Day he took
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Lixivium</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The 1ſt of <hi rend="italic">July</hi> he took the <hi rend="italic">Solut. Gum.
          Arab.</hi> and <lb/>was in great Pain. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 2d, being very faint, and wanting Reſt, <lb/>he had a cordial Julep and quieting
        Draught; and <lb/>the 3d and 4th; which Day he complain'd of great <lb/>Pain in his Limbs;
        and on the 5th had ſeveral looſe <lb/>Stools; which however ſtopt on the next Day. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He continued languiſhing, and in extreme Pain all <lb/>over his Body, even his Fingers
        and Toes, from this <lb/>Day to the 24th of <hi rend="italic">July</hi>, not being able to
        bear <lb/>being touch'd in any Part of his Body or Limbs, ſome <lb/>Days before his Death,
        which was on that Day, being <lb/>64 Days ſince the Commencement of this Courſe: <lb/>In
        which Time he took 81 Doſes of the <hi rend="italic">Lixivium</hi>, <lb/>being one Day with
        another (till he left off intirely, <lb/>which was 24 Days before he died) about 20 Drops
        <lb/>a Day. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>During the Courſe, his Water was generally thick <lb/>and muddy; tho' when in great
        Pain, ſometimes <lb/>clear and high colour'd. In about three Weeks after <lb/>he began,
        there was a great deal of that tough fetid <lb/><hi rend="italic">Mucus</hi> in his Urine,
        which continued till he left off <lb/>taking the <hi rend="italic">Lixivium</hi>, and then
        decreaſed conſiderably, <pb n="40"/>
        <lb/>till a Fortnight before his Death, when it intirely <lb/>diſappear'd, and his Urine had
        no Smell or Taſte, <lb/>and came away involuntarily. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On ſtraining and filtrating the Urine, I often found <lb/>little ſcaly Bits, very
        ſmall, which, when dry rubb'd, <lb/>became an impalpable Powder. After he left off the
        <lb/>Medicine, I could never find this in the Urine, tho' <lb/>I ſearch'd very carefully. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>His Diet the whole Time was chiefly Spoon-meat; <lb/>now<choice>
          <corr>-</corr>
          <sic> </sic>
        </choice>and-then a little Meat, but very ſeldom; and <lb/>he had but little Appetite when
        he began, and was <lb/>very weak. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On opening the Body I found his Kidneys very <lb/>ſound, and neither Stone nor Gravel
        in them: But <lb/>in his Bladder there were two Hundred and fourteen <lb/>Stones; the two
        biggeſt about the Size of Nutmegs, <lb/>the others gradually leſs, to the Bigneſs of a Pea,
        and <lb/>ſmaller, but each whole, not Pieces. They were of <lb/>a ſoft chalky Subſtance and
        Colour, and weigh'd <lb/>all together ſix Ounces <hi rend="italic">Averdup.</hi> two
        Scruples and <lb/>four Grains; beſides which there were ſeveral ſmall <lb/>Scales, ſuch as I
        found in his Urine. The other <lb/><hi rend="italic">Viſcera</hi> had nothing remarkable.
        The Quantity of <lb/>ſmall chalky and ſcaly Bits and Powder that I could <lb/>ſave out of
        the Urine, was about as much in 24 <lb/>Hours as would well cover a Shilling; and perhaps
        <lb/>there might be as much more loſt in his Urine, <lb/>when at Stool, and on the Sides of
        the Pot and <lb/>Urinal. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
