<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Aery: Containing the Particulars of the Cure of a Wound in the
          Cornea</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Thomas Aery</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Extract of a Letter from Tho. Aery M. D. to Cromwell Mortimer M. D. Secret. R. S.
              Containing the Particulars of the Cure of a Wound in the Cornea, and a Laceration of
              the Uvea in the Eye of a Woman </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for C. Davis, Printer to the Royal Society; over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1748</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">45</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">411-415</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110114449</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1748.0052</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT45_0411">
    <body>
      <pb n="411"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VIII.</hi> Extract of a Letter from <hi rend="roman">Tho. Aery</hi>
        <lb/>M. D. to <hi rend="roman">Cromwell Mortimer</hi> M. D. <lb/><hi rend="roman">Secret. R.
          S.</hi> containing the Particulars of <lb/>the Cure of a Wound in the <hi rend="roman"
          >Cornea</hi>, and a <lb/>Laceration of the <hi rend="roman">Uvea</hi> in the <hi
          rend="roman">Eye</hi> of a <lb/>Woman. </head>
      <dateline rend="size(0.7) space align-right">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Whitehaven</hi>, <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 14. 1748. </dateline>
      <div>
        <salute rend="italic indent">
          <lb/>SIR, </salute>
        <p>
          <lb/>
          <note place="inset" rend="italic size(0.7)">Read <date rend="roman">June 30. <lb/>1748.
            </date>
          </note><hi rend="dc(2)">Y</hi>OUR laudable Endeavours to pro- <lb/>mote the Art of
          Medicine, make <lb/>me willing to hope you will pardon the Freedom I <lb/>take of
          acquainting you with the following Caſe, <lb/>tho' I have not the Happineſs of your
          Acquaintance; <lb/>and I beg the Favour of you to lay it before the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Royal Society</hi>, to publiſh, if you approve of it; which <lb/>will oblige, Sir, </p>
        <signed rend="italic align-right">
          <lb/>Your humble Servant, <lb/><hi rend="roman space size(1.2)">Thomas Aery. </hi>
        </signed>
      </div>
      <pb n="412"/>
      <div>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> POOR Widow, aged 26 Years, of a pale <lb/>Complexion, was for
          ſeveral Years now-and- <lb/>then ſubject to the Colic. <hi rend="italic">Dec.</hi> 26.
          1744. ſhe re- <lb/>ceived a Wound in the <hi rend="italic">Cornea</hi> of her right Eye,
          by <lb/>the Spear of a common Fork, which alſo divided <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
            >Uvea</hi>. Part of the aqueous Humour was diſ- <lb/>charg'd, the Eye loſt its
          Tranſparency, had a violent <lb/>Pain in it, and ſhe could only diſtinguiſh Objects
          <lb/>when ſhe look'd down. I order'd her a <hi rend="italic">Collyrium</hi>
          <lb/>prepared of the <hi rend="italic">Balſ. Tolut. Camphor. ſolut. in Sp. <lb/>Vin. Aq.
            Plantag. cum pauxillo Tinct. Mart. <lb/>Mynſicht</hi>. A few Drops of this blood-warm
          was <lb/>to be uſed frequently; to bleed her largely in the <lb/>Arm, and her Diet was to
          conſiſt of Water-Gruel, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Aq. Hord.</hi> and freſh Broth. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Next Day ſhe had no Pain in the Eye, but com- <lb/>plain'd ſhe ſaw Motes floating
          before it: I order'd <lb/>her a Purge of <hi rend="italic">Infuſ. Sennæ</hi>, and an
          aſtringent Fo- <lb/>mentation to her Temples and Eyelids. The Day <lb/>following the Eye
          was inflamed, and the Lids tu- <lb/>mefied, and ſhe had a Pain in her Head. The <hi
            rend="italic">Col- <lb/>lyrium</hi> was changed to Roſe-water and Vinegar, <hi
            rend="italic">aa</hi>
          <lb/>℥ ſs. Roche-Alum <hi rend="italic">gr.</hi> v. 3 Drops twice a Day. The <lb/>29<hi
            rend="sup">th</hi> the Inflammation increaſing, the <hi rend="italic">Infuſ. Sennæ</hi>
          <lb/>and Bleeding were repeated, and the Parts were fo- <lb/>mented only with Spirit of
          Wine. The 31<hi rend="sup">ſt</hi> the <lb/>Inflammation continued to decreaſe, till after
          a <lb/>Fright. <hi rend="italic">Jan.</hi> 5. the Inflammation increaſing, the <lb/>Sides
          of the Wound became a little protuberant. <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Senna</hi> was
          repeated, and a Bliſter laid behind <lb/>the right Ear, and an emollient <hi rend="italic"
            >Collyrium</hi> was uſed: <pb n="413"/>
          <lb/>Next Day the Swelling of the Eyelids was gone: <lb/>The 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ſhe
          had a Shew of the <hi rend="italic">Menſes</hi>, and the <lb/>Wound appeared healed: From
          the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> to the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
          <lb/>the Inflammation continued to abate; only one Day <lb/>it increaſed by fretting and
          weeping much; but by <lb/>bleeding ſhe grew better, and ſo ſhe continued to <lb/>the 30<hi
            rend="sup">th</hi>; unleſs one Day, upon catching Cold, her <lb/>Eye became exceedingly
          inflamed, which was re- <lb/>lieved by bleeding. <hi rend="italic">Feb.</hi> 4. ſhe had a
          little Pain in <lb/>her Eye, and the <hi rend="italic">Tunica adnata</hi> looked a little
          red. <lb/>Soon after dropping in of 2 Drops of cold Water, <lb/>the Eyelids ſwelled, and a
          violent Inflammation of <lb/>the Eye enſued, with a Speck appearing; but theſe
          <lb/>Symptoms went off by repeated Applications of <lb/>Leeches and a mercurial Purge. The
            19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> a Ster- <lb/>nutatory of Hellebore and <hi rend="italic"
            >Euphorbium</hi> was order'd. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In a few Days after the Inflammation left her Eye; <lb/>when ſhe complained ſhe ſaw
          double; which Com- <lb/>plaints alſo ſoon left her. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Eye is myopical, and ſhe ſees the right Side <lb/>of Objects a little darkened;
          yet ſhe can read pretty <lb/>ſmall Characters. The <hi rend="italic">Uvea</hi> is not
          united where <lb/>it was divided, but ſtill retains its natural Power of <lb/>Contraction;
          the Tranſparency of the Humours and <lb/>Convexity of the <hi rend="italic">Cornea</hi>
          are the ſame as before; <lb/>there is no Scar upon the <hi rend="italic">Cornea</hi>; the
          Shape of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Pupil</hi> is much alter'd, as may be ſeen by the
          <lb/>Figure of the Eye, which I ſend herewith. See <hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi>
          <lb/>p. 415. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Upon catching Cold ſhe is ſubject to a ſlight Pain <lb/>in her Eye. At preſent there
          remains no other Al- <lb/>teration than what I have juſt mention'd, and what
          <lb/>neceſſarily follows from the Contraction of the <hi rend="italic">Pu- <lb/>pil</hi>,
          the not admitting a ſufficient Quantity of Rays <pb n="414"/>
          <lb/>to paſs to the <hi rend="italic">Retina</hi>, upon which Account ſhe is ſhort-
          <lb/>ſighted. Her ſeeing Objects darkened on one Side, <lb/>may proceed from the
          artificial Part of the <hi rend="italic">Pupil</hi>
          <lb/>being ſituate nigher to the great <hi rend="italic">Canthus</hi> of the Eye <lb/>than
          uſual in Nature; by which the Rays which <lb/>fall on the Side of the <hi rend="italic"
            >Cornea</hi> next to the little <hi rend="italic">Can- <lb/>thus</hi> of the Eye, being
          partly intercepted, muſt oc- <lb/>caſion a Defect in the Picture; from which Defect <lb/>a
          Darkneſs will be ſeen on one Side of the Object. <lb/>To the Weakneſs of the Veſſels of
          the Eye we may <lb/>attribute the Pain of the Eye upon catching Cold: It <lb/>oft-times
          happens to thoſe who have had a ſevere <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ophthalmia</hi>, that,
          during Life, the ſmall Veſſels are <lb/>too weak; and hence, from ſlight Cauſes being diſ-
          <lb/>tended, they will be painful, and frequently red. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>This Caſe is known to ſeveral in this Place, par- <lb/>ticularly to Mr. <hi
            rend="italic">Blencowe</hi>, an ingenious Surgeon <lb/>and Apothecary. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Some Remarks occur from this Caſe; <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
          <list rend="hanging">
            <item>
              <lb/>1. Her Cure would have been performed ſooner, if <lb/>her Circumſtances had
              allowed of her obſerving <lb/>an exact Regimen. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/>2. When her Eye had little or no Appearance of <lb/>Inflammation, I tried cold
              Water, but with rather <lb/>bad Succeſs. All cold Applications to inflamed <lb/>Eyes,
              Aſtringents or Repellents, require the utmoſt <lb/>Caution in applying them; for if
              they produce <lb/>not a good, they will produce a bad Effect. In <lb/>ſlight Caſes
              they oft have very happy Effects, but <lb/>where the obſtruent Matter is ſo fixt that
              it will <lb/>not ſuffer itſelf to be eaſily repell'd back, the<choice>
                <corr/>
                <sic>,</sic>
              </choice>
              <lb/>Veſſels being ſtraitened, the Fluids coagulated <pb n="415"/>
              <lb/>the Diſeaſe will be inceaſed; which happen'd in <lb/>this Caſe from the
              Application of cold Water. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/>3. The good Effects of Evacuations are very evi- <lb/>dent in abating the
              Inflammation. Wounds in <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Cornea</hi>, attended with a Wound
              of the <hi rend="italic">Uvea</hi>, <lb/>and a troubleſome Ophthalmy, heal without any
              <lb/>Scar. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><sic>5.</sic> An artificial <hi rend="italic">Pupil</hi>, made by ſlitting the
                <hi rend="italic">Uvea</hi>
              <lb/>in a different Method from that invented by the <lb/>ingenious Mr. <hi
                rend="italic">Cheſelden</hi>. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/>6. The Neceſſity of changing the Topics, according <lb/>to the State of the
              Diſtemper; which has been <lb/>remarked before by ſeveral celebrated Authors. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>An illustration of the eye, with the letter "A" next to it. A wide black line runs
          from the pupil to the outer edge of the iris. </figDesc>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">A</hi>, This Figure repreſents the Eye as it appears at
          <lb/>preſent. </p>
      </figure>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
