<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Mounsey and Baker: An Abstract of the Remarkable Case and Cure of a
          Woman, from Whom a Foetus Was Extracted</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>James Mounsey</persName>
              <persName>Henry Baker</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Abstract of the Remarkable Case and Cure of a Woman, from Whom a Foetus Was
              Extracted, That Had Been Lodged Thirteen Years in One of the Fallopian Tubes; Sent
              from Riga by Dr. James Mounsey, Physician to the Army of the Czarina, Together with
              the Bones of the Said Foetus, as a Present to the Royal Society of London, and
              Delivered Accordingly in His Name, by Henry Baker, F. R. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for C. Davis, Printer to the Royal Society; over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1748</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">45</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">131-137</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110114449</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1748.0009</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT45_0131">
    <body>
      <pb n="131"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">I.</hi> An Abſtract of the remarkable Caſe and <lb/>Cure of a Woman,
        from whom a <hi rend="roman">Fœtus</hi>
        <lb/>was extracted, that had been lodged thirteen <lb/>Years in one of the <hi rend="roman"
          >Fallopian Tubes</hi>; ſent <lb/>from <hi rend="roman">Riga</hi> by Dr. <hi rend="roman"
          >James Mounſey</hi>, Phy- <lb/>ſician to the Army of the <hi rend="roman">Czarina</hi>,
        together <lb/>with the Bones of the ſaid <hi rend="roman">Fœtus</hi>, as a Pre- <lb/>ſent to
        the <hi rend="roman">Royal Society</hi> of <hi rend="roman">London</hi>, and <lb/>delivered
        accordingly in his Name, by <lb/><hi rend="roman">Henry Baker</hi>, F. R. S. </head>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>
        <note rend="italic size(0.7)" place="inset">The Original read <lb/>at a Meeting of the
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">Royal Society</hi>, <date rend="roman">Feb. <lb/>4. 1747-8.
          </date>
        </note><hi rend="dc(4)">T</hi>HE Particulars of this extra- <lb/>ordinary Caſe are ſet forth
        <lb/>at large in <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* It is likewiſe printed in the <hi rend="italic">Swediſh</hi> Language, in the
            Acts <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Royal Academy</hi> at <hi rend="italic"
              >Stockholm</hi>. </p>
        </note>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Mounſey</hi>'s <lb/>Paper, the Subſtance where- <lb/>of is as
        follows: </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>A Soldier's Wife, of <hi rend="italic">Abo</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Finland</hi>, of a
        mid- <lb/>dling Stature, and who had been the Mother of two <lb/>Children, being pregnant a
        third time in the Year <lb/>1730. was afflicted with violent Pains and Twiſtings <lb/>in the
        Bowels, ſwooning Fits, Vomitings, and great <lb/>Diſorders in her Back and lower Belly.
        Theſe <lb/>Symptoms, and Complaints of ſeveral other kinds, <lb/>continued to make her
        uneaſy, till ſhe found her <pb n="132"/>
        <lb/>Burden increaſe, which fell from Side to Side as <lb/>ſhe changed the Poſture of her
        Body, and could be <lb/>preſſed by her Hand from one Place to another, but <lb/>rather choſe
        to remain on the right Side. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After Quickening her Health became better, ſhe <lb/>grew bigger belly'd than ordinary,
        and was ſuppoſed to <lb/>carry Twins. About the time her delivery was ex- <lb/>pected, ſhe
        was taken ill with violent Pains by Fits <lb/>acroſs her lower Belly; but had none in her
        Back, nor <lb/>any Forcings downwards; and the next Day theſe Pains <lb/>went off, which
        made her ſuppoſe ſhe had miſ- <lb/>reckon'd. But after his her Breaſts ſwell'd, and gave
        <lb/>Milk in plenty; and her Menſes came on, attended <lb/>with more violent Pains than ſhe
        had had before; <lb/>and ſuch large Diſcharges of Blood from time to <lb/>time, that ſhe
        could neither ſpeak nor move; and <lb/>even after the Floodings were ſtopp'd, her Blood
        <lb/>and Strength ſeem'd quite exhauſted: She often <lb/>fainted away, and was ſometimes
        thought to be dead. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>She continued very ſickly for ten Years afterwards; <lb/>during which Time her Burden
        was moveable, and <lb/>fell from Side to Side. But in the Month of <hi rend="italic">Sep-
          <lb/>tember</hi> 1741. ſhe felt a Pain beneath the Navel, <lb/>with a Swelling and
        Redneſs, which in about three <lb/>Weeks appear'd like a ſmall Boil. This ſhe pierced
        <lb/>with an Awl, and a yellow-colour'd Water ran <lb/>from it without any Smell, and
        continued ſo to do <lb/>for near three Weeks more, when it diſcharged a <lb/>purulent
        ſtinking Matter. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the Month of <hi rend="italic">June</hi> two ſmall Bones came <lb/>out, which were
        given to the Surgeon that viſited <lb/>her; who only applied a Piece of Plaiſter, perſuading
        <lb/>her that a Cure was impoſſible. Other ſmall Bones <pb n="133"/>
        <lb/>work'd themſelves out afterwards, till <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 1742. <lb/>when
        the Head-Quarters of the <hi rend="italic">Ruſſian</hi> Army being <lb/>at <hi rend="italic"
          >Abo</hi>, this unhappy Woman applied to Dr. <hi rend="italic">Moun- <lb/>ſey</hi>, who,
        after a careful Examination, undertook <lb/>to deliver her. And accordingly, deſiring the
        Aſ- <lb/>ſiſtance of Mr. <hi rend="italic">Geitle</hi>, Surgeon to the Regiment of <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Abo</hi>, a grooved Probe was thruſt into the <hi rend="italic"
        >Fiſtula</hi>, <lb/>and an Inciſion made with a Biſtory, upwards and <lb/>obliquely, from
        the <hi rend="italic">Linea alba</hi> into the Cavity of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >Abdomen</hi>; but ſhe being unruly, and the Ope- <lb/>ration not going on to the Doctor's
        Liking, he pro- <lb/>ceeded no farther till the next Day; only ſome looſe <lb/>Bones were
        extracted, and the Wound dreſſed with <lb/>Tents and Compreſſes, to hold in the <hi
          rend="italic">Omentum</hi>, <lb/>and keep the Wound open. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>At the next Operation the Inciſion was carried <lb/>downwards, and then another
        Inciſion continued <lb/>from the firſt was conducted upwards, and ſlanting <lb/>at a ſmall
        Diſtance from the firſt; taking care to keep <lb/>as near as poſſible the Direction where
        the Adheſion <lb/>of this Body to the <hi rend="italic">Peritonæum</hi> appeared to be, and
        <lb/>avoiding to make the external Wound larger than <lb/>abſolutely needful, leſt the <hi
          rend="italic">Omentum</hi> and Guts ſhould <lb/>fall out; and particularly leſt the
        Suppuration ſhould <lb/>exceed the Strength of Nature, which was here al- <lb/>ready nearly
        exhauſted. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A large Opening was now made, but the <hi rend="italic">Fœtus</hi>
        <lb/>being cloſely enveloped by its containing Sack, <lb/>the Doctor durſt not venture to
        draw it out by <lb/>Force, for fear ſome of the naked Bones might la- <lb/>cerate the
        internal Parts: Wherefore, dilating this <lb/>Sack with the Points of a Pair of
        Probe-Sciſſars, di- <lb/>rected by the Fingers of the left Hand, he pierced <pb n="134"/>
        <lb/>and cut in Pieces the Skull, which afterwards he ex- <lb/>tracted piece-meal. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Matter that firſt iſſued out had a very nauſe- <lb/>ous Smell, and conſiſted of
        Membranes, Fat, and <lb/>corrupted Fleſh. On opening the <hi rend="italic">Cranium</hi>, the
          <hi rend="italic">Ce- <lb/>rebrum</hi> appeared of its natural Colour. The Opera-
        <lb/>tion having been long, and the Woman fainting <lb/>away, the Wound was dreſſed, without
        attempting <lb/>to extract more at that time. In the Evening ſhe <lb/>was taken with
        Vomitings; but by proper internal <lb/>Medicines, and Flannel Stoups wrung out of hot
        <lb/>Wine, applied over the whole Belly, and often re- <lb/>new'd, ſhe found Eaſe, and grew
        better. — The <lb/>Loſs of Blood, during the whole Operation, was <lb/>inconſiderable<choice>
          <corr>.</corr>
          <sic>,</sic>
        </choice>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Next Day the Bones of the Trunk, and moſt of the <lb/>other large ones, with their
        Ligaments and rotten <lb/>Fleſh, were taken out. The Matter diſcharged for <lb/>ſeveral Days
        was of a dark-brown Colour, occaſion'd <lb/>by Blood iſſuing from the dilated Pores of the
        in- <lb/>ternal Surface of the Sack, which render'd the Mat- <lb/>ter at firſt of a deep-red
        Colour; but that changed <lb/>daily and gradually, till at laſt it became white. The
        <lb/>Doctor imagines this Diſcharge to reſemble the <hi rend="italic">Lo- <lb/>chia</hi>
        after Child-birth; for after the <hi rend="italic">Fœtus</hi> was ex- <lb/>tracted, the
        Woman's Breaſts ſwell'd, and gave Milk <lb/>in Plenty for two Months, in Quantity, Colour,
        <lb/>and Conſiſtence, as if after a Delivery at the proper <lb/>Time. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Doctor examined this Sack very diligently <lb/>with his Fingers, whilſt thin, and
        not contracted, but <lb/>formed into Wrinkles, through which he felt the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Rectum</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Veſica urinaria</hi>, and, as he thought,
          <pb n="135"/>
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Fundus Uteri</hi>. Many ſmall Bones lay in the <lb/>Folds; but,
        as ſhe complained not of Pain, they <lb/>were left till the Suppuration began, excepting
        thoſe <lb/>the Sack in contracting itſelf threw out. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Beſides Fomentations, Balſamics, proper Bandages, <lb/><hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        vulnerary detergent Injections were found very <lb/>uſeful, thrown in in large Quantities,
        both to waſh out <lb/>the putrid Fleſh, and bring away the Scales of Bones <lb/>which were
        ſtill concealed in the Folds of this <lb/>Sack. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Sack contracted itſelf daily, grew ſmooth and <lb/>white within, and narrower as it
        approached the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Uterus</hi>, which gave Reaſon to believe it one of
        the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fallopian</hi> Tubes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Wound was cured in about ſix Weeks, and <lb/>the Woman deliver'd from a long State
        of Miſery <lb/>grew fat and luſty, and now enjoys good Health. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Comparing theſe Circumſtances together, it ſeems <lb/>reaſonable to believe this Fruit
        never was in the <lb/>Cavity of the Womb, but that the impregnated <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Ovum</hi> was ſtopt in its Paſſage through one of the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Fallopian</hi> Tubes, where it grew, and was detained <lb/>ſo many Years; and that the
        Inflammation, which <lb/>happened below the Navel, was not owing to the <lb/>Rottenneſs of
        the <hi rend="italic">Fœtus</hi>, or to its bare Bones ſeek- <lb/>ing a Diſcharge, but
        rather to ſome accidental Fric- <lb/>tion of the containing Sack againſt the <hi
          rend="italic">Peritonæum</hi>, <lb/>thereby producing Adheſion, Obſtruction, Inflamma-
        <lb/>tion, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Fœtus</hi>, before this
        Accident, muſt <lb/>have remained all theſe Years intire, and without <lb/>perfect
        Corruption: For it took no leſs Time, after <lb/>its Communication with the common Air,
        before it <pb n="136"/>
        <lb/>ſhewed Marks of Putrefaction, than a freſh Subject, <lb/>kept in the ſame Degree of
        Heat, would have done. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Doctor's Obſervations of the Bones are: That <lb/>they have a full Proportion to
        thoſe of a Child at nine <lb/>Months, and that the Fibres are more compact, and their
        <lb/>Articulations ſtronger. The Sockets for the Teeth <lb/>are ſix on each Side of the
        Jaws; the <hi rend="italic">Dentes Inci- <lb/>ſores</hi> of the upper Jaw are high and
        large; the <hi rend="italic">Mo- <lb/>lares</hi> have almoſt all begun to oſſify in their
          <hi rend="italic">Al- <lb/>veoli</hi>; at leaſt the Crown, which is the cortical
        <lb/>Part, is form'd, and they are fill'd internally with a <lb/>cretaceous Subſtance. In
        new-born Children thoſe <lb/>Parts are ſeldom found ſo far advanc'd, which gives <lb/>Reaſon
        to believe this Child did not die within the <lb/>ordinary Time of Pregnancy, and that the
        different <lb/>Accidents, before-mention'd to have happen'd, were <lb/>chiefly owing to the
        preternatural Situation of the <lb/><hi rend="italic"><choice>
            <corr>Fœtus</corr>
            <sic>Fætus</sic>
          </choice></hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Some Places in the Skull appear to have been <lb/>carious, and corroded by ſome ſharp
        Humours; and <lb/>Nature, ſupplying its oſſifying Juices, has repaired <lb/>theſe Places,
        and render'd them more ſolid and <lb/>whiter than the reſt, but very uneven and ſcabrous,
        <lb/>from the different Times and Directions of the bony <lb/>Sproutings. There are likewiſe
          <hi rend="italic">Exoſtoſes</hi> on the <lb/>Ends of the Thigh-Bone, and ſome other Bones. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>'Tis very difficult to determine about what Time <lb/>the Growth of theſe Productions
        began or ended. <lb/>Suppoſing it from the Time of the Diſorders that <lb/>happened in the
        firſt Months of Pregnancy; would <lb/>not ſuch a Diſeaſe have cauſed Death to the <hi
          rend="italic">Fœtus</hi>, <lb/>before it had come thus to a full Growth? If it was
        <lb/>the Conſequence of the violent Accidents which <pb n="137"/>
        <lb/>happen'd about the Time of the natural Birth, the <lb/>Child then muſt have continued
        alive ſome conſi- <lb/>derable Time afterwards, during which theſe bony <lb/>Excreſcences
        were formed; there being a perfect <lb/>Oſſification, as performed by the Laws of Circula-
        <lb/>tion, and not by any vegetative or petrifying Power, <lb/>as in inanimate Bodies. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Two or three of the lateral Proceſſes of the Spine <lb/>were what firſt paſſed thro'
        the little Ulcer; the reſt of <lb/>the Bones (except a few that were loſt in cleanſing) were
        <lb/>preſented by the Doctor to the Muſeum of the <hi rend="italic">Royal <lb/>Society</hi>.
        They retain a very ſtrong and ſingular <lb/>Smell, though they were immediately cleanſed
        from <lb/>the rotten Fleſh, and well waſhed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Woman came by Sea to <hi rend="italic">Stockholm</hi> above a <lb/>Year after this
        Cure, and was preſented to the <hi rend="italic">Aca- <lb/>demy</hi> in good Health; and the
        Doctor believes ſhe <lb/>is ſtill alive and well. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
