<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Hales and Adee: An Examination of the Strength of Several of the
          Principal Purging Waters</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Stephen Hales</persName>
              <persName>Swithin Adee</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Examination of the Strength of Several of the Principal Purging Waters,
              Especially of That of Jessop's Well; By the Rev. Stephen Hales D. D. &amp; F. R. S.
              Communicated in a Letter to Cromwell Mortimer M. D. Secr. R. S. with a Letter from
              Swithin Adee M. D. F. R. S. to Dr. Hales, on the Virtues of the Said Well</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for C. Davis, Printer to the Royal Society, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1749</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">46</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">446-451</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111030968</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1749.0084</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT46_0446">
    <body>
      <pb n="446"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VII.</hi> An Examination of the Strength of ſeve- <lb/>ral of the <hi
          rend="roman">principal purging Waters</hi>, eſpe- <lb/>cially of that of <hi rend="roman"
          >Jeſſop</hi>'s <hi rend="roman">Well</hi>; by the Rev. <lb/><hi rend="roman">Stephen
          Hales</hi> D. D. &amp; F. R. S. commu- <lb/>nicated in a Letter to <hi rend="roman"
          >Cromwell Mortimer</hi>
        <lb/>M. D. Secr. R. S. with a Letter from <lb/><hi rend="roman">Swithin Adee</hi> M. D. F.
        R. S. to Dr. <hi rend="roman">Hales</hi>, <lb/>on the Virtues of the ſaid <hi rend="roman"
          >Well</hi>. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>An Account of the ſeveral Quantities of <hi rend="roman">Sediment</hi>
        <lb/>which were found in a Pound Averdupois of the <lb/>following <hi rend="roman">purging
          Waters</hi>, evaporated away to <lb/>Dryneſs, in <hi rend="roman">Florence</hi> Flasks,
        cut to a wide <lb/>Mouth; <hi rend="roman">viz.</hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="align-right size(0.7) space">
        <lb/>Grains </p>
      <p>
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="hanging italic size(0.7)">Read <date rend="roman">May 24.
            <lb/>1750. </date>
        </note>
        <list rend="hanging">
          <item>1. <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="dc(1.5)">M</hi>Arybon-Fields</hi> near <hi
              rend="italic">London</hi>
            <hi rend="align-right">24 </hi>
          </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>2. <hi rend="italic">Peterſtr. Brew-houſe Weſtm.</hi>
            <hi rend="align-right">27 </hi>
          </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>3. <hi rend="italic">Ebſham</hi>
            <hi rend="align-right">34 </hi>
          </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>4. <hi rend="italic">Scarborough</hi>, <hi rend="align-right">40 </hi>
            <lb/>And it was found nearly the ſame by Dr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Shaw</hi> and Dr.
              <hi rend="italic">Short</hi>: A little more or leſs, <pb n="447"/>
            <lb/>according to the Wetneſs or Dryneſs of the <lb/>Seaſons 1/3<unclear>.</unclear>2 of
            this in calcarious Matter; <lb/>the reſt, moſtly what is called nitrous Salts, <lb/>on
            account of the oblong Chryſtals which it <lb/>ſhoots into. </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>5. <hi rend="italic">Dog</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Duck</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
              >Lambeth</hi>
            <hi rend="align-right">40½ </hi>
          </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>6. <hi rend="italic">Kilburn</hi>, four Miles from <hi rend="italic">London</hi>,
            in the <lb/>Way to <hi rend="italic">Edgwar</hi>
            <hi rend="align-right">43 </hi>
          </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>7. <hi rend="italic">Acton</hi>
            <hi rend="align-right">44 </hi>
          </item>
          <item rend="hanging">
            <lb/>8. <hi rend="italic">Cheltenham, Glouceſterſhire</hi>, <hi rend="align-right">60 </hi>
            <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Short</hi> found the following Proportions <lb/>in <hi
              rend="italic">Cheltenham</hi> Water; <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
            <list rend="indentall">
              <item>
                <lb/><hi rend="italic">Sept.</hi> 1738. calcarious Sediment 1/10.6 of 74 </item>
              <item>
                <lb/><hi rend="italic">Dec.</hi> 1738. <hi rend="align-right">1/14 of 42 </hi>
              </item>
              <item>
                <lb/><hi rend="italic">July</hi> 1739. <hi rend="align-right">1/9.8 of 70 </hi>
              </item>
            </list>
            <lb/>He ſays it is the beſt and ſtrongeſt nitro-calca- <lb/>rious Water in <hi
              rend="italic">England</hi>, very bitter, hav- <lb/>ing only a little ſubtil impalpable
            Earth <lb/>mixed with its Salt. </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>9. <hi rend="italic">Cobham Well</hi>, a Mile South of <hi rend="italic">Church
              <lb/>Cobham, Surrey</hi>, once 68 Grains, another <lb/>time 60 Grains <hi
              rend="align-right">68 </hi>
          </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>10. <hi rend="italic">Jeſſop's Well</hi>, on <hi rend="italic">Stoke Common</hi>,
            in Mr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Vincent</hi>'s Manor, about three Miles South- <lb/>ward
            of <hi rend="italic">Claremont, Surrey</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Sept.</hi> 11, 1749.
            <lb/>after long dry Weather, 82 Grains in a Pound <lb/>of the Surface-Water <hi
              rend="align-right">82 </hi>
          </item>
        </list>
      </p>
      <p rend="hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">October</hi> 16, after a conſiderable Quantity of Rain , <lb/>the
        Surface-Water yielded but 60 Grains <hi rend="italic">Nov.</hi>
        <lb/>21, the Surface-Water yielded 65 Grains. </p>
      <pb n="448"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This great Inequality of the Strength of the Sur- <lb/>face-Water put me upon trying
        whether the Water <lb/>at the Bottom of the Well, near the Springs, were <lb/>ſtronger than
        the Surface-Water. And in order to <lb/>this, I procured, <hi rend="italic">Dec.</hi> 11, a
        Bottle of the Water <lb/>near the Bottom, which was ten Feet below the Sur- <lb/>face of the
        Water; which was done by tying an <lb/>empty Bottle to the End of a long Pole, with a Line
        <lb/>fixed to the Cork, to pull it out when at the Bottom, <lb/>for the Water to fill it:
        And I had at the ſame <lb/>time another Bottle full of the Surface-Water. The <lb/>lower
        Water yielded 82 Grains; the Surface-Water <lb/>but 48 Grains; and it was the ſame upon a
        ſecond <lb/>Evaporation of thoſe Waters. Hence we ſee how <lb/>much ſtronger the Water near
        the Bottom is, than <lb/>at the Surface; even when the preceding Rains have <lb/>been but
        moderate; for they had not as yet been <lb/>ſufficient to raiſe the Springs in this Country
        much. <lb/>Hence we ſee that the ſtronger lower Water may <lb/>eaſily be come at by means of
        a Pump; as alſo, that <lb/>the upper Land-Springs, ſoon after Rains, make the <lb/>Water
        near the Surface weaker: But, in long dry <lb/>Weather, when there are no Land-Springs, the
        Sur- <lb/>face-Water, and that at the Bottom, are nearly of <lb/>an equal Strength: For it
        requires Time for the ſa- <lb/>line mineral Virtue to be equally diffuſed thro' a <lb/>Maſs
        of that Depth of Water, whoſe upper Part is <lb/>inceſſantly weakened by a Land-Spring of
        freſh <lb/>Water. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Hence we ſee how adviſeable it is, in order to keep <lb/>out the Land-Springs, to dig a
        narrow Trench ſome <lb/>Feet Depth, round the Well, to be filled with ſtiff <lb/>Clay well
        rammed. </p>
      <pb n="449"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The mineral Virtue in this Water ſeems to be <lb/>much like that of <hi rend="italic"
          >Cheltenham</hi>, in its ſhooting into <lb/>very bitter, regular, oblong Chryſtals, which
        are, on <lb/>that account, called nitrous; tho' they are not a true <lb/>Nitre; for neither
        theſe, nor thoſe of <hi rend="italic">Cheltenham</hi>, <lb/>will deflagrate or flaſh in
        Touch-Paper, nor on burn- <lb/>ing Charcoal, as true Nitre will do; ſome of which <lb/>ſtill
        retain their Form and Firmneſs for 17 Months <lb/>ſince they were chryſtallized; whereas the
        chryſtal- <lb/>lized Salts of ſeveral other purging Waters have crum- <lb/>bled, and in a
        great meaſure waſted, away in much <lb/>leſs Time: A greater Proportion of the Salts of
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Jeſſop</hi>'s <hi rend="italic">Well</hi>, ſhoot into oblong
        Chryſtals than thoſe <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Cheltenham</hi>; and its Water alſo gives a
        ſtronger <lb/>green Tincture, with Violet flowers. The purging <lb/>Quality reſides chiefly
        in theſe chryſtalline Salts, and <lb/>a ſmall Proportion of common Salt; ſome of which
        <lb/>there is in all theſe mineral Waters. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Proportion alſo of its earthy calcarious Mat- <lb/>ter, is but 1/11 <gap
          reason="illegible"/>4 Part of it; which, like that of <hi rend="italic">Chel-
          <lb/>tenham</hi>, is but little, in compariſon of the much <lb/>greater Quantity of it in
        other purging Waters: It <lb/>is alſo ſoft and impalpable, like that of <hi rend="italic"
          >Cheltenham</hi>, <lb/>and not harſh and coarſe, as it is in ſome other purging
        <lb/>Waters. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And as the Quantity of purging Salt in this Water <lb/>is conſiderably greater than in
        any other, ſo it is found <lb/>by Experience, that, proportionably a leſs Quantity <lb/>of
        it ſuffices, which makes it fit the better on the <lb/>Stomach. It is alſo obſerved to
        exhilarate thoſe who <lb/>take it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It was obſervable of the Sediment of ſeveral of <lb/>theſe Waters, that, when dried,
        and while hot, <pb n="450"/>
        <lb/>there aſcended Plenty of inviſible volatile ſalt Fumes, <lb/>ſo pungent that the Noſe
        could not bear them. <lb/>Hence we may reaſonably conclude, that the Waters <lb/>which
        abound moſt with purging Salts, ſuch as thoſe <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Jeſſop's Well</hi>,
        ſhould be proportionably preferable <lb/>to weaker Waters, which are ſtrengthened by boiling
        <lb/>half away; whereby not only the more ſubtil active <lb/>Parts are evaporated; and thoſe
        that are left are de- <lb/>compounded, and formed into new groſſer Combi- <lb/>nations; as
        are alſo the calcarious Particles, which <lb/>are ſo fine as to paſs the Filter before
        Evaporation, <lb/>but not after it. This was the Reaſon which in- <lb/>duced me to examine,
        by various repeated Trials, <lb/>and to give an Account of the ſuperior Strength of <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Jeſſop</hi>'s <hi rend="italic">Well</hi> Water, above all others that I
        have <lb/>examined or heard of. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When <hi rend="italic">Jeſſop</hi>'s <hi rend="italic">Well</hi> was cleaned, <hi
          rend="italic">Oct.</hi> 16, 1749, <lb/>after a conſiderable Quantity of Rain, after about
        <lb/>half a Foot Depth of black muddy Filth was taken <lb/>out, then the natural fat
        ſandy-colour'd Clay-Bottom <lb/>appear'd; thro' ſeveral Parts of which the Water <lb/>ouzed
        up at the Rate of 160 Gallons in 24 Hours. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Water which then came freſh from the Spring <lb/>gave a weak Bluſh with Galls; but
        when put into <lb/>Bottles it did not do ſo next Day; a Sign that there <lb/>is ſome Degree
        of Steel in it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It was very obſervable, that the Man who ſtood <lb/>about three Hours bare-legg'd in
        this Well-Water <lb/>to clean it, was purged ſo ſeverely for a Week, <lb/>that he ſaid he
        would not venture, on any account, <lb/>thus to clean the Well again. And it was the ſame
        <lb/>with another Man, who cleaned the ſame Well about <lb/>twelve Years ſince. And I am
        credibly informed <pb n="451"/>
        <lb/>by a Merchant, that, being in a Warehouſe in <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ægypt</hi> to ſee
          <hi rend="italic">Senna</hi> baled up, it had the like pur- <lb/>gative Effect on him. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In order to get a ſatisfactory Account of the Ef- <lb/>ficacy of theſe Waters, I
        deſired Dr. <hi rend="italic">Adee</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Guilford</hi>, <lb/>who has
        long preſcribed them to his Patients, to <lb/>give me his Opinion of them; which he has done
        <lb/>in the following Letter; <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
      </p>
      <floatingText><body>
        <salute rend="italic indent space">
          <lb/>SIR, </salute>
        <dateline rend="align-right"><hi rend="italic">Guilford</hi>, <hi rend="italic">March</hi>
          14, 1749. </dateline>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> HAVE found very advantageous and uncommon <lb/>Effects from
          the Uſe of the Waters of <hi rend="italic">Jeſſop</hi>'s <lb/><hi rend="italic">Well</hi>.
          Some of my Patients who have drank them <lb/>ſteadily and cautiouſly have been cur'd of
          obſtinate <lb/>Scurvies. As I had a long time ago Reaſon to think <lb/>there was a fine
          volatile Spirit in them, I therefore <lb/>oblig'd ſome to drink them for a Courſe of Time
          at <lb/>the Well as an Alterative, with very happy Conſe- <lb/>quences. When I have
          order'd them as a Purge, <lb/>they have work'd very ſmartly, but have not diſpi-
          <lb/>rited. I am glad to have it in my Power to confirm <lb/>your Sentiments by my own
          Obſervations; and am <lb/>ſatisfied theſe Waters, if continued a proper Time, <lb/>and
          taken in a proper Manner, may be render'd <lb/>very beneficial to Mankind, according to
          the beſt <lb/>Opinion that can be formed by </p>
        <signed rend="italic align-right">
          <lb/>SIR, <lb/>Your moſt faithful humble Servant, <lb/><hi rend="roman space">Swithin
            Adee. </hi>
        </signed></body>
      </floatingText>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
