<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Heath and Mudge: A Proposal for Intirely Removing the Only Real Defect
          in the Lateral Operation</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Benj. Heath</persName>
              <persName>John Mudge</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Extract of a Letter from Benj. Heath Esq; to Peter Davall Esq; Secr. R. S.
              Inclosing a Proposal for Intirely Removing the Only Real Defect in the Lateral
              Operation for the Stone; By Mr. John Mudge Surgeon at Plymouth</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for C. Davis, Printer to the Royal Society, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1749</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">46</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">24-29</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111030968</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1749.0009</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT46_0024">
    <body>
      <pb n="24"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VIII.</hi> Extract of a Letter from <hi rend="roman">Benj. Heath</hi>
        <lb/>Eſq; to <hi rend="roman">Peter Davall</hi> Eſq; Secr. R. S. in- <lb/>cloſing a Propoſal
        for intirely removing the <lb/><hi rend="roman">only real Defect</hi> in the <hi
          rend="roman">lateral Operation</hi>
        <lb/>for the <hi rend="roman">Stone</hi>; by Mr. <hi rend="roman">John Mudge</hi> Sur-
        <lb/>geon at <hi rend="roman">Plymouth</hi>. </head>
      <div>
        <salute rend="italic indent space">
          <lb/>Dear Sir, </salute>
        <p>
          <lb/>
          <note place="inset" rend="italic size(0.7)">Read <date rend="roman">Feb. 2. <lb/>1748.
            </date>
          </note><hi rend="dc(2)">*** I</hi> TAKE the Freedom of con- <lb/>veying to you a Memoir
          writ- <lb/>ten by a very ingenious young Surgeon of my Ac- <lb/>quaintance propoſing an
          Improvement in the lateral <lb/>Method of cutting for the Stone. His View in put-
          <lb/>ting me on giving you this Trouble is, that it may <lb/>be laid before the <hi
            rend="italic">Society</hi>; and if it be thought to <lb/>deſerve it, it may be
          communicated to the Public <lb/>in their <hi rend="italic">Tranſactions</hi>. I am, </p>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <dateline rend="align-center space">
          <lb/><hi rend="size(0.7)"><hi rend="italic">Exeter</hi>, Jan. 16. </hi>
          <lb/>1748. </dateline>
        <cb n="2"/>
        <salute rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>SIR, </salute>
        <signed rend="italic space">
          <lb/>Your moſt humble Servant, <lb/><hi rend="roman size(1.2) space align-right">Benj.
            Heath. </hi>
        </signed>
      </div>
      <div>
        <space dim="vertical" quantity="2" unit="lines"> </space>
        <head rend="align-center italic">
          <lb/>A Propoſal for intirely removing the <hi rend="roman">only real <lb/>Defect</hi> in
          the <hi rend="roman">lateral Operation</hi> for the <hi rend="roman">Stone</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HO' the lateral Method of cutting for the <lb/>Stone is now
          almoſt univerſally allow'd to <lb/>have greatly the Advantage of any other hitherto diſ-
          <lb/>cover'd, yet it muſt be confeſs'd, that the Difficulty <pb n="25"/>
          <lb/>and Hazard attending the Extraction of large Stones <lb/>this Way, has really robb'd
          it of its Title to Per- <lb/>fection; for tho' the Inciſion be made to the Wiſh,
          <lb/>quite through the Proſtate, and carried on to the <lb/>Neck of the Bladder, if this
          be the Caſe (for it fre- <lb/>quently happens to the contrary) as the Bladder itſelf
          <lb/>in general is not, nor in all Probability can be, <lb/>wounded in this Way of
          operating, the real Aper- <lb/>ture after all for the Exit of a large Stone is ſo
          <lb/>ſmall, that the Parts muſt ſuffer moſt violent Lacera- <lb/>tions, and a Train of
          conſequent Evils. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The old Method indeed is greatly more obnoxious <lb/>to this Misfortune, becauſe the
          Parts are torn to Pieces <lb/>by downright Violence, without any previous Inciſion <lb/>of
          any Conſequence to prepare them for the Egreſs of <lb/>the Stone; and this Imperfection in
          the Operation is ſo <lb/>notoriouſly apparent, and ſo deſtructive in fact, that <lb/>this
          Method is deſervedly in Diſeſteem, and almoſt <lb/>univerſally diſcarded. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I wiſh it could be ſaid, that the lateral Method was <lb/>intirely free from this
          Imperfection; but I fear an <lb/>impartial Inquiry will make it clear, that three Fourths
          <lb/>of the Accidents which have attended this Operation, <lb/>may in truth be attributed
          to exceſſive Diſtenſions and <lb/>Lacerations of the Bladder, thoſe few Caſes, which
          <lb/>have miſcarried from (what may have been ſuppoſed) <lb/>a mere ſymptomatic Fever,
          will, I believe on a ſtrict <lb/>Diſquiſition, afford a ſhrewd Suſpicion, that this very
          <lb/>Fever itſelf aroſe from ſome Violence offer'd to the <lb/>Bladder, in the forcible
          Extraction of the Stone. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I will not enter into a ſtrict Examination of thoſe <lb/>fatal Symptoms which
          ſometimes ſucceed the Ope- <lb/>ration in grown Subjects, in order to prove that they <pb
            n="26"/>
          <lb/>in general proceed from the Bladder's being too <lb/>roughly dealt with, becauſe I
          take the Caſe to be <lb/>of itſelf very evident: Unleſs the Habit is remark- <lb/>ably
          bad, to what elſe ſhall we attribute violent Pain, <lb/>and the ſucceſſive Inflammation,
          Tumour, Suppreſ- <lb/>ſion of Urine, Mortification, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>? Theſe
          ſurely are <lb/>not the Attendants on a ſimple Inciſion only; for <lb/>conſtant Experience
          evinces, that the Bladder, tho' <lb/>an Organ of great Importance, and eſſentially neceſ-
          <lb/>ſary to the animal Oeconomy, may be wounded with <lb/>as little Danger of any of the
          above-mention'd Evils, <lb/>as any other membranous Part. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But I believe we ſhall not be at a Loſs for the true <lb/>Cauſe of all thoſe
          Miſchiefs, if the State of the Parts <lb/>in the Extraction of a large Stone be cloſely
          conſi- <lb/>der'd. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It may be obſerv'd, when a Stone is laid hold of <lb/>by the <hi rend="italic"
            >Forceps</hi>, that both together, Stone and <hi rend="italic">For- <lb/>ceps</hi>, from
          the Screw-pin to the former, form a com- <lb/>plete Wedge; inſomuch that a Perſon in a
          forcible <lb/>Extraction, can ſcarcely conceive the Power applied <lb/>to the Bladder, or
          the Force with which it is diſ- <lb/>tended. If the Diameter of the Stone be equal to
          <lb/>a third Part of the Length of the Chops of the <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi>, <lb/>a
          Force of ten Pounds applied to them will be to <lb/>the Wound of the Bladder, equal to
          thirty; but how <lb/>ſhocking muſt be the Caſe, when (either on account <lb/>of the
          Magnitude of the Stone, or Narrowneſs of the <lb/>Wound) a Man uſes his utmoſt Force, and
          many <lb/>ſuch Inſtances in adult Bodies I have ſeen. The Power <lb/>is then augmented by
          the Action of the Lever to <lb/>two or three hundred; a Force no doubt ſufficient <lb/>to
          reduce the Bladder and neighbouring Parts to Rags. <pb n="27"/>
          <lb/>This is ſcarce to be credited; but there is too much <lb/>Reaſon to believe, that the
          Want of Succeſs in Sub- <lb/>jects arriv'd at adult Age, where the Stones are almoſt
          <lb/>always large, is owing intirely to this very Circum- <lb/>ſtance. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When all this Violence is inſufficient, there is at <lb/>preſent no other eſtabliſh'd
          Method, than either to <lb/>attempt the making a ſecond Inciſion on the Stone, <lb/>as it
          is held in the <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi>, or to withdraw the lat- <lb/>ter, and to
          make it on the Bladder, in the flaccid <lb/>State it then lies, without any Guide at all. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As to the firſt Method, it is evident the <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi>, <lb/>Stone,
          and Bladder in Men are ſo much in the dark, <lb/>that the Inciſion muſt be made with the
          utmoſt Dif- <lb/>ficulty; indeed it is hardly poſſible to cut at all with <lb/>any
          Certainty. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The other Way of cutting on the Bladder when <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi>
          is withdrawn is much worſe; for if it <lb/>be remember'd, that the Bladder lieth upon, and
          is <lb/>contiguous with the <hi rend="italic">Rectum</hi>, and that they are both <lb/>in
          the ſame flabby State, it will appear impoſſible <lb/>to cut the one, without (at leaſt a
          very great Riſque <lb/>of) wounding the other. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This manifeſt Defect in the Operation would be <lb/>intirely removed, if there always
          was a Director for <lb/>the Knife left in the Bladder; and this is ſo eaſily <lb/>and
          completely to be done, that its great Simplicity <lb/>ſeems to be the Reaſon it has not
          been attended to. <lb/>If one Limb of the <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi>, from the Joint
          to its <lb/>Extremity, be converted into a Staff, by making a <lb/>deep Groove through its
          whole Length, it will bet- <lb/>ter anſwer the End deſired, than if it were poſſible
          <lb/>to ſuffer the Staff itſelf to remain in the Bladder <pb n="28"/>
          <lb/>during the Operation; for, when a large Stone is <lb/>laid hold of, and the <hi
            rend="italic">Forceps</hi> of courſe much diva- <lb/>ricated, inſomuch that the
          Extraction of the Stone <lb/>is found to be impracticable with Safety, without a
          <lb/>ſecond Inciſion on the Parts upon the Stretch; you <lb/>then ſlide the Point of a
          narrow Knife on the <lb/>Groove of the <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi> quite on into the
          Bladder, <lb/>and it will divide the very Part which needs it moſt; <lb/>whilſt the <hi
            rend="italic">Rectum</hi>, on account of its flaccid State, <lb/>will moſt certainly
          eſcape wounding. If the Wound <lb/>is deſired to be but little larger, the <hi
            rend="italic">Forceps</hi> muſt be <lb/>but gently drawn forward when the Inciſion is
          made; <lb/>but if, on the other hand, the Stone prove extremely <lb/>large, the <hi
            rend="italic">Forceps</hi> ſhould be then drawn forwards <lb/>with a Force ſufficient to
          put the Bladder upon the <lb/>Stretch; and by this Management the Dilatation <lb/>may be
          made as great or little as is required. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As the common Knife is not ſo proper for this <lb/>Purpoſe on account of its Breadth,
          I have got one <lb/>made of a more convenient Form, with a Gorget- <lb/>Handle and
          Button-Point, as in the <hi rend="italic">Bubonocele</hi> Knife. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This Method, as it removes all Occaſion for Vio- <lb/>lence to the Bladder, will
          reduce the Effects of the <lb/>Operation nearly to thoſe of a mere Inciſion only,
          <lb/>which might, as now, ſometimes prove fiſtulous, <lb/>but I believe ſcarcely ever
          mortal. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I would not be underſtood to mean that it ſhould <lb/>be uſed in common Caſes, and
          moderate ſized <lb/>Stones; no; Mr. <hi rend="italic">Cheſelden</hi> has ſufficiently
          demon- <lb/>ſtrated to the World, by Experiment, the Inconve- <lb/>nience of cutting
          beyond the Proſtate, when it can <lb/>be avoided. I only ſay this, that where a large
          Stone <lb/>offers, and the Circumſtances are ſuch, that the <lb/>Operator is under a
          Neceſſity of tearing the Parts to <pb n="29"/>
          <lb/>Pieces, unleſs divided by an Inciſion, the latter is <lb/>more ſafe and eligible. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The principal Advantages of this Contrivance are, <lb/>1. That the Degree of
          Dilatation is in the Operator's <lb/>Power, to the greateſt Exactneſs: 2. That it will in-
          <lb/>fallibly divide thoſe Parts only which are upon the <lb/>Stretch; and for this
          Reaſon, 3. The <hi rend="italic">Rectum</hi>, if it is <lb/>empty, and conſequently
          flaccid, muſt certainly <lb/>eſcape wounding. Its great Simplicity is another
          <lb/>Circumſtance much in its Favour; for it ſeems al- <lb/>low'd on all Hands, the leſs
          an Operation is incum- <lb/>ber'd with Inſtruments the better. In common Caſes, <lb/>where
          the Aſſiſtance of this Method is not wanted, <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi> is
          not the leaſt incommoded as to its ge- <lb/>neral Uſe; but if the Stone prove large (which
          can <lb/>never be certainly known till it is laid hold of), the <lb/>Remedy is at hand. </p>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <dateline rend="size(0.7) align-center space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Plimouth</hi>, Jan. 6. <lb/>1748-9. </dateline>
        <cb n="2"/>
        <signed rend="size(1.2) align-right space">
          <lb/>John Mudge. </signed>
        <cb n="1 2"/>
        <postscript>
          <label rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>P. S. </label>
          <p rend="hanging">
            <lb/>Theſe <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi> and Knife are repreſented in <hi rend="sc"
              >Tab.</hi>
            <lb/>I. <hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 3, 4, 5. </p>
          <figure>
            <p rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 3. The <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi>, with the
              Knife, <hi rend="italic">a b</hi>, applied <lb/>to one of the Cheeks of it. <hi
                rend="italic">c</hi>, the Button. <hi rend="italic">bfg</hi>, <lb/>the Handle. </p>
            <figDesc>An illustration of a forceps, with a knife attached to the backside of the left
              blade, on a separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
          <figure>
            <p rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 4. The Cheek of the <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi>
              with the Groove <lb/>in it <hi rend="italic">d e</hi>. </p>
            <figDesc>A close-up of the left blade from the back, showing a straight groove running
              through the length of it, on a separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
          <figure>
            <p rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 5. The Knife. The Blade <hi rend="italic">a b</hi>;
              the Button <hi rend="italic">c</hi>, <lb/>made to fit, and ſlide along the Groove <hi
                rend="italic">d e</hi>; <hi rend="italic">bfg</hi>
              <lb/>the Handle; <hi rend="italic">c a b</hi> the ſharp Edge; <hi rend="italic">c h
                f</hi> the Back <lb/>of the Knife, which muſt have the ſame Curve <lb/>as the Back
              of the Cheek of the <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi> or Groove <lb/>to which it is to be
              applied, as in <hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 3. </p>
            <figDesc>A close-up of the knife, the blade and handle of which are both curved, on a
              separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
