<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - le Cat and Zollman: Concerning the Cure of Dry Gangrenes</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Dr. le Cat</persName>
              <persName>Ph. H. Zollman</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Letter from Dr. le Cat F. R. S. to C. Mortimer M. D. Secret. R. S. concerning
              the Cure of Dry Gangrenes: Together with a Description of a New-Invented Instrument
              for the Extirpation of Tumours out of the Reach of the Surgeon's Fingers</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for C. Davis, Printer to the Royal Society, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1749</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">46</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">72-86</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111030968</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1749.0017</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT46_0072">
    <body>
      <pb n="72"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XVI.</hi> A Letter from Dr. <hi rend="roman">le Cat</hi> F. R. S. to
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">C. Mortimer</hi> M. D. Secret. R. S. concern- <lb/>ing the Cure of
          <hi rend="roman">Dry Gangrenes</hi>: together <lb/>with a Deſcription of a new-invented
        In- <lb/>ſtrument for the <hi rend="roman">Extirpation</hi> of <hi rend="roman">Tumours</hi>
        <lb/>out of the Reach of the Surgeon's Fingers. </head>
      <head rend="italic size(0.8)">
        <lb/><choice>
          <corr>Tranſlated</corr>
          <sic>Tranſſated</sic>
        </choice> from the <hi rend="roman">French</hi> by <hi rend="roman">Ph. H. Zollman</hi> Eſq;
        F. R. S. </head>
      <div>
        <salute rend="italic indent">
          <lb/>SIR, </salute>
        <p>
          <lb/>
          <note rend="italic size(0.7)" place="inset">Read <date rend="roman">March 9 <hi
                rend="italic">and</hi> 16. <lb/>1748-9. </date>
          </note><hi rend="dc(2)">F</hi>OR ſome Years paſt, in curing <lb/>the dry Gangrene, I have
          made <lb/>ſome Progreſs, of which I think I ought to inform <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
            >Royal Society</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>From the Year 1725 to the Year 1733, when I fre- <lb/>quented the Hoſpitals of <hi
            rend="italic">Paris</hi>, I ſaw that a great many <lb/>Perſons there died of a dry
          Gangrene, and even <lb/>that nothing was done to them. I knew that Ampu- <lb/>tation had
          been attempted in vain; but I did not ſee <lb/>any of the Practitioners endeavour to cure
          that Diſ- <lb/>temper by Remedies; nor did I think that Cure im- <lb/>poſſible. I
          ſuſpected, that the Cauſe of the dry Gan- <lb/>grene was the want of a Flow of the
          arterial Blood <lb/>and of the Spirits into the Part affected: And this <lb/>Want, as it
          accounts for the Deadneſs, which cannot <lb/>miſs befalling the Part, and the Dryneſs
          which at- <lb/>tends this ſort of Mortification; whereas in the hu- <lb/>mid Gangrene, it
          is chiefly the Return of the Blood <lb/>which is hindered, and thereby the Fluids are
          accu- <lb/>mulated, that ſwell and diſtend the Part. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Two Cauſes ſo oppoſite muſt demand alſo very <lb/>different Cures. The Diſtenſion
          which characterizes <lb/>the humid Gangrene ſhews the Neceſſity there is for <pb n="73"/>
          <lb/>Scarifications and Evacuations; as the Dryneſs of the <lb/>other Gangrene points out
          the Uſeleſsneſs of theſe <lb/>Operations in this ſort. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In the humid Gangrene the Solids are choaked up, <lb/>and overflowed with the
          accumulated Liquid; the <lb/>Nerves are there ſtupefied and benumbed: What can <lb/>be
          more proper then after Scarifications, which diſ- <lb/>gorge and relax thoſe Regions, than
          to apply ſtimu- <lb/>lating <hi rend="italic"><sic>Topics? Tonics</sic></hi>, which
          reſtore the Spring, the <lb/>Tone of the ſolid Parts; help them to expel thoſe
          <lb/>ſuperfluous Liquors, the Spirits of which are as it <lb/>were drowned and ſuffocated;
          and in ſhort the De- <lb/>fect being local, if thoſe Succours do not ſuffice, it <lb/>is
          very common to cut off a Limb; the Loſs of which <lb/>may bring on that of the whole
          Perſon. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On the contrary, in the dry Gangrene the Solids <lb/>are void of Fluids of all ſorts.
          The neighbouring <lb/>Regions, which begin to ſhare of that Want, are af- <lb/>fected with
          the moſt cruel Pains: If you attack thoſe <lb/>Parts with the cutting Inſtrument, you
          increaſe the <lb/>Irritation of the Solids, the Conſtriction of the Veſſels, <lb/>the Want
          of Fluids, the Exſiccation, and haſten Death. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On the contrary, the general Indication, which <lb/>this Diſtemper affords us is
          therefore to ſoften, to re- <lb/>lax the Veſſels, to draw thither the Liquors by To-
          <lb/>pics, whilſt inwardly all Remedies muſt be given <lb/>that are capable of bringing
          the Blood and the Spirits <lb/>from the Center to the Circumference. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If this Method is not ſucceſsful, Death is inevita- <lb/>ble; for even ſuppoſing that
          the Amputation was <lb/>not liable to the diſmal Conſequences juſt now ſpe- <lb/>cified,
          there is no Room for this Operation in an <lb/>internal Defect, which depends on the whole
            <pb n="74"/>
          <lb/>Habit, as the Caſe is with the dry Gangrene. And <lb/>ſuppoſing that there are dry
          Gangrenes purely local, <lb/>as the critical <hi rend="italic">Depoſitums</hi> of certain
          malignant Fevers, <lb/>you may aſſure yourſelf, that the very ſame Nature <lb/>which has
          cauſed this Criſis, if you aſſiſt her but a <lb/>little, will be alſo to ſeparate this
          Mortification <lb/>from the ſound Parts; and ſhe will do it more gently <lb/>and more
          dextrouſly than we. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Theſe were the Notions I had formed to myſelf <lb/>of theſe two ſorts of Gangrenes; I
          only waited for <lb/>Opportunities to make the Trials which this Theory <lb/>ſuggeſted to
          me. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I did not find any before 1738. in the Perſon of <lb/>a Wood-Merchant of our Town,
          called Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Four- <lb/>naiſe</hi>. She was then 65 Years of Age,
          extremely <lb/>corpulent; the Gangrene ſeized her at the Heel, by <lb/>a black and round
          Blotch, of two Inches Diameter, <lb/>without any Tumour, with ſome ſmall ſcorbutic
          <lb/>Spots, great Pains, and a little Fever. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Plethora</hi> made me begin with Bleeding and <lb/>Purging; the
          latter I repeated every 8 Days. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I applied all over the Foot and Part of the Leg, a <lb/>Pultis made of Herbs and <hi
            rend="italic">Farina's</hi>, emollient, re- <lb/>ſolving, and aromatic, the ſuppurative
          Ointment, and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Storax</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I gave inwardly diaphoretic Ptiſans: In the Morn- <lb/>ing, Broths of Vipers, of
          Crayfiſh prepared with pro- <lb/>per Herbs, and above all with Water-creſſes: In the
          <lb/>Evening a Bolus of <hi rend="italic">Theriaca</hi>. In ſhort, I followed
          <lb/>intirely the Theory I had formed to myſelf about <lb/>the dry Gangrene, and in 9 or
          10 Days I ſaw the <lb/>Suppuration formed; ſo that my Patient was per- <lb/>fectly cured
          in about 2 or 3 Months. </p>
        <pb n="75"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This Succeſs has been followed by many others, <lb/>both in our Town and in our
          Hoſpital. I have been <lb/>particularly ſucceſsful in the latter Place, becauſe I <lb/>am
          more Maſter there than any-where elſe, to ſee <lb/>my Method exactly followed, which I
          have ſtill im- <lb/>proved ſince 1738. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Report of theſe Cures having ſpread itſelf as <lb/>far as <hi rend="italic"
            >Paris</hi>, I was ſent for thither in <hi rend="italic">February</hi>
          <lb/>1746. to attend M. <hi rend="italic">Rondé</hi>, Treaſurer-General of the
          <lb/>Fortifications of <hi rend="italic">France</hi>, who was at the laſt Extre-
          <lb/>mity, by a dry Gangrene, which had ſphacelated his <lb/>Foot; the Cauſe of which had
          kept him in a lan- <lb/>guiſhing Way for 4 Years. M. <hi rend="italic">Rondé</hi> was in a
          <lb/>dreadful Condition, and I was vexed at having been <lb/>ſent for in ſo deſperate a
          Caſe: I declared it to his <lb/>Relations, and to the eminent Surgeons who at- <lb/>tended
          him: I therefore applied my Remedies to <lb/>the Patient, at the Requeſt of his Relations,
          only <lb/>by way of Trial, which I publicly declared to be <lb/>moſt doubtful. However,
          contrary to our Expecta- <lb/>tion, from the 3d Day there appeared plainly a Be-
          <lb/>ginning of Suppuration, and a Separation of the <lb/>Eſchars. On the 9th Day there
          was a complete <lb/>Suppuration, and the Regeneration of the Fleſh was <lb/>even ſo far
          advanced, that the Singularity of it raiſed <lb/>the Curioſity of ſome of the firſt
          Surgeons of <hi rend="italic">Paris</hi>. <lb/>At laſt, on the 15th Day my Patient found
          himſelf <lb/>in a more favourable Criſis; which, according to <lb/>the Teſtimony which M.
            <hi rend="italic">Morand</hi>, an aſſiduous <lb/>Spectator of my Cure, publicly gave of
          it, <q rend="italic">gave <lb/>Hopes of Recovery in a Caſe that had hitherto <lb/>been
            thought deſperate </q>. </p>
        <pb n="76"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Suppuration, the Separation of the Eſchars, <lb/>and Regeneration of the Fleſh,
          being all that a <lb/>Surgeon can deſire in a like Cure, I then thought <lb/>that my
          Miſſion was fulfilled, and that I might re- <lb/>turn home, whither I was called by more
          material <lb/>Affairs. I had Reaſon to repent of this Journey: <lb/>My Patient having
          naturally a very voracious Appe- <lb/>tite, I had confined him to a ſevere Diet; but he
          <lb/>could hold out no longer; and, by the Connivance <lb/>of his Nurſe, he took various
          Food, and that plenti- <lb/>fully too. This Conduct had ſoon ruined our Pro- <lb/>greſs. I
          returned to <hi rend="italic">Paris</hi>; my Repreſentations <lb/>were uſeleſs: The
          Patient had ſhaken off the Yoke <lb/>of the Faculty, and of Reaſon. Indigeſtions enſued
          <lb/>one upon another. The Looſeneſs, which never left <lb/>him after, totally ſuppreſſed
          the Suppuration, and <lb/>made him void the Matter quite crude by Stool, and <lb/>at laſt
          he died. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I was ſcarcely returned to <hi rend="italic">Rouen</hi>, when there came <lb/>to my
          Hoſpital a Patient ſeized with the dry Gan- <lb/>grene, and who ſo perfectly reſembled M.
            <hi rend="italic"><choice>
              <corr>Rondé</corr>
              <sic>Rondê</sic>
            </choice></hi>, <lb/>that we commonly called him <hi rend="italic">the Rondé of
            Rouen</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This Cure being extremely intereſting in all its <lb/>Circumſtances, I think, Sir, it
          is fit to tranſcribe for <lb/>you the Obſervation taken from a Letter which I <lb/>wrote
          on the 28th of <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 1746. to M. <hi rend="italic">Morand</hi>,
          <lb/>and which he has ſince made public. </p>
        <floatingText>
          <body>
            <p rend="space hanging">
              <lb/>
              <q rend="diple">As this Letter has been made public by Mr. <hi rend="italic"
                  >Morand</hi>, <lb/>I ſhall not fill up this <hi rend="italic">Tranſaction</hi>
                with a Tranſ- <lb/>lation of a long Letter already in Print, but <lb/>only give a
                ſhort Account of the Caſe. </q>
            </p>
            <signed rend="italic align-right">
              <lb/>
              <q rend="quotes">C. M. </q>
            </signed>
          </body>
        </floatingText>
        <pb n="77"/>
        <floatingText>
          <body>
            <p rend="space">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="dc(1.5)">T</hi>Homas le Monnier</hi>, a Carpenter,
              aged 66, was, <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 1744. ſeized with violent Pains
              in <lb/>his right Foot reſembling thoſe of the Gout, but with- <lb/>out ſwelling, and
              not preceded by any Sickneſs. He <lb/>had work'd hard at his Trade, and ſtill carried
              it on <lb/>in marſhy Places, and in bad and cold Weather, <lb/>when he was ſeized with
              this Pain. He took various <lb/>Remedies to no Effect. In <hi rend="italic"
                >November</hi> 1745. his <lb/>great Toe turned black; which Blackneſs gradually
              <lb/>ſpread to the other Toes, to the whole Foot, and at <lb/>laſt to the Ankle. He
              was ſent to the <hi rend="italic">Hotel Dieu</hi>
              <lb/>at <hi rend="italic">Roan</hi>
              <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 19. His Foot was intirely gangrened, <lb/>black and dry;
              his Pulſe was low, and a little fever- <lb/>iſh; he never ſlept but 2 Hours a Night,
              ſuffered <lb/>cruel Torments, was greatly emaciated, and of a yel- <lb/>low and
              leadiſh Complexion; his other Foot was <lb/>œdematous. <q rend="diple quotes">M. <hi
                  rend="italic">le Cat</hi> ſays, he would not attack <lb/>this Caſe Steel in Hand,
                by Scarifications or Am- <lb/>putation; cruel and murthering Methods! which
                <lb/>quite extinguiſh the Springs of Life in the nervous <lb/>Syſtem, which is
                already but too much ruffled. <lb/>A barbarous Surgery! which Prejudice, Ignorance,
                <lb/>and Unskilfulneſs alone can adopt, and by which I <lb/>have ſeen Patients die,
                when there were great Hopes <lb/>of their Recovery. </q> See <hi rend="italic">le
                Dran</hi>'s Operations, <lb/><hi rend="italic">p.</hi> 30. <hi rend="italic"
                >Saviard</hi>'s Obſervations, <hi rend="italic">p.</hi> 98. and <hi rend="italic">de
                la Motte</hi>
              <lb/>Obſ. 303. eſpecially <hi rend="italic">p.</hi> 371. <hi rend="italic">Tome</hi>
              III. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>As this Diſorder ariſes from internal Cauſes, its <lb/>Cure is chiefly to be
              attempted by internal Remedies; <lb/>and of theſe I give Cordials, Diaphoretics, and
              ſuch <lb/>as are capable of reviving the drooping Spirits, and <lb/>of quickening the
              Circulation even to the Extremities: <pb n="78"/>
              <lb/>To which ſhould be joined Medicines adapted to <lb/>the particular Habit of each
              Patient, whether it be <lb/>ſcorbutic, ſcrophulous, or any other, which may <lb/>have
              contributed to have brought on this particular <lb/>Species of Gangrene: At the ſame
              time emollient, <lb/>attractive, external Remedies, moderately warmed <lb/>with
              Spices, applied to the Part, concur to the ſame <lb/>Intention, by facilitating the
              Flow of Blood and Spi- <lb/>rits; the Interception of which makes the diſtinguiſh-
              <lb/>ing Characteriſtic of the dry Gangrene. Spirituous <lb/>and aqueous Topics,
              impregnated with Volatiles, <lb/>charged with ſaline, active, violently ſtimulating
              Par- <lb/>ticles, and others in Uſe in ordinary Gangrenes, are <lb/>to be avoided like
              deadly Poiſons; for ſuch Applica- <lb/>tions would rather contract and dry up the Part
              the <lb/>more, and increaſe the painful Irritations, and diſ- <lb/>poſe the contiguous
              Parts to a dry Gangrene. He <lb/>gives us Hopes of a Treatiſe expreſly on this Sub-
              <lb/>ject. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>But to return to the Caſe. The Suppuration began <lb/>to appear, and the <hi
                rend="italic">Eſchars</hi> diſtinguiſhed themſelves <lb/>from the live Fleſh the
              very firſt Days of the Cure; <lb/>and, after the Time uſual in the like Suppurations,
              <lb/>the Foot and lower Part of the Ankle ſeparated of <lb/>themſelves; and
              afterwards, healing over intirely, <lb/>left a Stump quite cover'd over with a
              Covering of <lb/>Fleſh, except ſome Points of Bone, which were not <lb/>eaſily to be
              ſeen, but might be felt, by paſſing the <lb/>Finger over this new Fleſh. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>After this Separation the Tendons of the Muſcles, <lb/>which lie along the Leg,
              formed Abſceſſes and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Sinus's</hi>. Some Practitioners would
              have laid open <lb/>theſe <hi rend="italic">Sinus's</hi> their whole Length; but ſuch
              large <pb n="79"/>
              <lb/>Inciſions would have ſo affected the Syſtem of the <lb/>Nerves, as to have
              brought back the gangrenous Diſ- <lb/>poſition into the internal Parts, and ſo have
              deſtroy'd <lb/>the Patient; as M. <hi rend="italic">le Cat</hi> ſays he has ſeen it
              very <lb/>lately happen by the like Practice: Wherefore he lets <lb/>the Matter gather
              in thoſe <hi rend="italic">Sinus's</hi>, till it forms a <lb/>Bag, and greatly thins
              the Skin, when he opens <lb/>them almoſt without Pain, in the Place only where
              <lb/>they point. Theſe Openings are ſufficient both for <lb/>the Diſcharge of the
              Matter, and for the coming <lb/>away of the Tendons; which no ſooner happens, <lb/>but
              the Integuments, whether open'd or not, unite <lb/>and cicatrize. Thus, at the End of
              6 or 7 Months, <lb/>the Stump itſelf cicatrized, and the Patient was quite
              <lb/>recover'd. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>So long a Cure could not but be liable to ſome <lb/>Accidents: The Patient was
              one who would indulge <lb/>in his Diet, and the Hoſpital is open for any one to
              <lb/>come in and viſit their Friends: He had ſeveral ſtrong <lb/>Acceſſes of an
              accidental Fever, and five or ſix vio- <lb/>lent Indigeſtions; one in <hi
                rend="italic">July</hi> kept him inſenſible <lb/>for 20 Hours, and was attended with
              a Defluxion <lb/>on the Lungs, accompanied with ſuch Expectora- <lb/>tions as gave the
              worſt Prognoſtications. Theſe were <lb/>Incidents which render'd his Recovery the more
              re- <lb/>markable. He has pick'd up his Fleſh, and promiſes <lb/>to enjoy a good Habit
              of Body; ſo that probably he <lb/>may live to a good old Age. Several that have been
              <lb/>cured by the Doctor of this Diſorder have lived to <lb/>upwards of 70. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Thus, ſays he, the common Opinion, that it is <lb/>impoſſible radically to cure
              the dry Gangrene, is as <lb/>falſe, as the ordinary Method of treating it is bad. <pb
                n="80"/>
              <lb/>He does not eſtabliſh his Method as infallible; but <lb/>aſſures us, that, in 8
              or 9 Years Practice it has not <lb/>failed curing any Perſons who exactly followed it,
              <lb/>and obſerved the Regimen preſcribed. </p>
          </body>
        </floatingText>
        <floatingText>
          <body>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>
              <q rend="quotes">We now return to Dr. <hi rend="italic">le Cat</hi>'s own Words. </q>
            </p>
          </body>
        </floatingText>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>I ſhall here ſubjoin the Deſcription of an Inſtru- <lb/>ment of Surgery, which I have
          lately invented. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">Forceps</hi> for the Extirpation of Tumours too remote <lb/>from the
          Surgeon's Fingers. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>When the Fingers can lay hold of an Excreſcency, <lb/>the Surgeon need not think of
          making uſe of Ma- <lb/>chines for it; he will never find any convenient <lb/>enough; but
          all Tumours that are to be extirpated <lb/>are not within the Reach of the Fingers: There
          are <lb/>even many of them which the Fingers can reach, <lb/>but where they cannot lay
          hold of them, nor work <lb/>as the Extirpation requires. Such are the Ex- <lb/>creſcences
          ſituated a little deep in the <hi rend="italic">Anus</hi>, in the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Vagina</hi>, in the Throat, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> For the like Extirpations
          <lb/>I have been obliged to invent the <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi> which I <lb/>am
          going to deſcribe. </p>
        <figure>
          <p rend="hanging space">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 1. The firſt Figure repreſents the <hi rend="italic"
              >Forceps</hi> ſhut, <lb/>as they are when the Inſtrument is cloſed, or when <lb/>it
            holds a ſmall Excreſcency. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">A C</hi> is the Extremity deſigned for laying hold of <lb/>the
            Excreſcency: It is of Silver, pliant as far as <hi rend="italic">a a</hi>, <lb/>in order
            to be able to give to theſe Cheeks the dif- <lb/>ferent Figures which thoſe of the
            Tumours to be <lb/>extirpated may require. The Inſide of theſe Branches <pb n="81"/>
            <lb/>is lined with a Slip of Buff-Skin, or cloſe Shamoys <lb/>(<hi rend="italic">K
              K</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 2. <hi rend="sc">Tab.</hi> III.) to prevent the
            Tumour's <lb/>ſlipping when once it has been laid hold of. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">B D</hi> is the Extremity of the <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi>,
            to be held <lb/>in the Hand of the Operator. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">E F</hi>, <hi rend="italic">G H</hi>, are the Pieces which
            connect the two <lb/>Parts of the Inſtrument, inſtead of the common Joints <lb/>or
            Rivets of the other <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi>, in a very advantageous <lb/>manner.
            Theſe Pieces make the principal Utility of <lb/>this Invention. </p>
          <figDesc>An illustration of the forceps on a separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <figure>
          <p rend="hanging space">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 2. <hi rend="sc">Tab.</hi> III. repreſents the Pincers
            taken to pieces <lb/>in two Parts. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>One eaſily ſees that the Piece <hi rend="italic">E</hi> is to go into the
            <lb/>Notch <hi rend="italic">gg</hi>, ſo that the Screw <hi rend="italic">f</hi> may
            paſs through its <lb/>Slit, and that the Nut <hi rend="italic">F</hi>, put on upon that
            Screw <lb/><hi rend="italic">f</hi>, is to keep the Whole together: But one thing
            <lb/>which the Figure cannot ſhew, is, that this Piece <hi rend="italic">E</hi> is
            <lb/>moveable in the Direction lengthways of the <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi>, <lb/>to
            anſwer the different Openings of the Cheeks. You <lb/>may obſerve in <hi rend="italic"
              >b</hi> the Pin upon which this Piece <lb/>turns. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The Piece <hi rend="italic">G</hi> likewiſe receives the Screw <hi rend="italic"
              >h</hi> into <lb/>its Slit; and the one and the other is ſtopped by the <lb/>Nut <hi
              rend="italic">H</hi>. But an eſſential Remark with regard to the <lb/>Piece <hi
              rend="italic">G</hi>, is, that it muſt have the Figure of an Arch <lb/>of a Circle,
            the <hi rend="italic">Radius</hi> whereof is the Inſtrument <lb/>itſelf; that is to ſay,
            it ought to be the Portion <lb/>of an Arch of a Circle, the Center of which is at the
            <lb/>Extremity of the Inſtrument; and this to the end <lb/>that in the ſmall Extremity
            of the Pincers, the Ends <lb/>of the Cheeks find themſelves over-againſt each other,
            <lb/>whatever Opening one may give to the larger Extre- <lb/>mity, or to the Handle <hi
              rend="italic">G H</hi>. </p>
          <figDesc>An illustration of the forceps, its two parts separated from each other, on a
            separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <p rend="indent">
          <choice>
            <corr>
              <pb n="82"/>
            </corr>
            <sic>
              <pb n="84"/>
            </sic>
          </choice>
          <lb/>To explain the Uſe of theſe <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi>: </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I ſuppoſe I am to extirpate an Excreſcence, a <hi rend="italic">Con-
          <lb/>dyloma</hi>, of two Inches Depth in the <hi rend="italic">Rectum</hi>. I can-
          <lb/>not lay hold of this Tumour with the Fingers, nor <lb/>make it come out; yet it is
          very troubleſome to the <lb/>Patient, and one is diſpoſed to ſlit or lay open the <hi
            rend="italic">Anus</hi>, <lb/>to make room for this Extirpation. With our <hi
            rend="italic">For- <lb/>ceps</hi> we ſhall avoid this cruel Preparative, and ſhall
          <lb/>with great Eaſe make the Extirpation. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Firſt, I introduce the Fore-finger of the left Hand <lb/>into the <hi rend="italic"
            >Rectum</hi> over the Tumour that is to be ex- <lb/>tirpated, to make myſelf ſure of the
          Situation: With <lb/>the right Hand, I take the Part of my <hi rend="italic">Forceps C
            D</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 2. and thruſt it into the <hi rend="italic"
            >Rectum</hi>, under the Fin- <lb/>ger which is already there, and make it ſlide along
          <lb/>the right Side of the Tumour, which to me is the <lb/>left Side. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>With the Fingers of the left Hand I ſupport this <lb/>Inſtrument in its Situation,
          whilſt with the right <lb/>Hand I introduce the other Part of the <hi rend="italic"
            >Forceps A B</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 2. and let it ſlide along the left
          Side of the <lb/>Tumour, which is over-againſt my right Hand. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Without taking the Fore<choice>
            <corr>-</corr>
            <sic> </sic>
          </choice>finger of my left Hand <lb/>out of the <hi rend="italic">Rectum</hi>, I put
          together the Parts of the <lb/>Inſtrument. I preſs between its Cheeks the Tumour <lb/>by
          its Root; after which I draw the Fore-finger out <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Rectum</hi>. I take with the left Hand the Han- <lb/>dle of the <hi rend="italic">Forceps
            B D</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 1.; I thruſt along the <lb/>right Side of their
          Cheeks underneath the Knife <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 3. the Button <hi
            rend="italic">A</hi> being turned againſt the Cheeks, <lb/>and the Back <hi
            rend="italic">C D</hi> towards the Inſide of the <hi rend="italic">Rectum</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I puſh this Inſtrument as far as beyond the Tumour <lb/>under the Extremity of the
          Cheeks of the <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi>, <choice>
            <corr>
              <pb n="83"/>
            </corr>
            <sic>
              <pb n="85"/>
            </sic>
          </choice>
          <lb/>of which I can make myſelf ſure with the Fore- <lb/>finger of the left Hand.— Then I
          raiſe towards the <lb/>upper Part the Cheeks of the <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi>, in
          order to <lb/>prolong as much as poſſible the Root of the Ex- <lb/>creſcence; and in this
          Condition I pull towards my- <lb/>ſelf, with the right Hand, the Knife; which does
          <lb/>not fail cutting the Tumour. </p>
        <figure>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>There are Caſes, in which the Inſtrument, <hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 4. <lb/>will
            be of more convenient Uſe. This cuts only by <lb/>its Creſcent <hi rend="italic">a
              b</hi>, puſh'd forward, and mov'd alter- <lb/>nately from one Side to the other, to
            aſſiſt its <lb/>Cutting. </p>
          <figDesc>An illustration of an instrument with a small concave blade on one end on a
            separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <figure>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>There are Circumſtances, wherein the Knife <hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 5. <lb/>may
            be preferable. </p>
          <figDesc>An illustration of a curved knife, with a pointed head, on a separate fold-out
            page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In fine, there are others, wherein all theſe Inſtru- <lb/>ments are of Service in one
          Operation, which hap- <lb/>pen'd to me in <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 1748. in the
          Extirpation of <lb/>a ſcirrhous <hi rend="italic">Polypus</hi> in our <hi rend="italic"
            >Hotel Dieu</hi>; in which <lb/>Operation I employ'd not only all the Inſtruments
          <lb/>above deſcribed, but alſo a cutting <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi>, which I <lb/>had
          contrived in 1735. for the Extirpation of <hi rend="italic">Fun- <lb/>gus's</hi> of the
          Bladders; and which alone was proper <lb/>to take off one Part of this Tumour, that was as
          <lb/>large as a Gooſe's Egg, and was falling into the <lb/>Throat. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I ſuffer the Wound to bleed a little, and then dreſs <lb/>it with all the Precautions
          uſually taken againſt Hæ- <lb/>morrhages in the Operation of the <hi rend="italic"
            >Fiſtula</hi> in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Anus</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="84"/>
      <div>
        <figure>
          <head rend="italic hanging space">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">Forceps</hi> for extracting Stones, and other foreign <lb/>Bodies,
            lodged in the Parts where the common <lb/><hi rend="roman">Forceps</hi> are of no Uſe.
              <hi rend="roman">Fig. 6. <hi rend="sc">Tab.</hi> III.</hi>
          </head>
          <figDesc>An illustration of the forceps on a separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The ſame Mechaniſm juſt now deſcribed in the fore- <lb/>going <hi rend="italic"
            >Forceps</hi>, may be applied with Advantage to the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi>
          with which the Stone is pulled out, and to <lb/>other Inſtruments deſigned for extracting
          Bullets, <lb/>Splinters of Grenadoes, Pieces of Iron, and other fo- <lb/>reign Bodies. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>There are ſeveral Caſes in the cutting for the Stone, <lb/>in which no Uſe can be
          made of the common <hi rend="italic">For- <lb/>ceps</hi>: The moſt frequent is this; when
          a Stone, laid <lb/>hold by the ordinary <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi>, eſcapes from the
          In- <lb/>ſtrument half-way, and ſo remains engaged in the <lb/>Inciſion. The Expedient
          commonly taken, is to puſh <lb/>the Stone back into the Bladder, in order to have
          <lb/>again the neceſſary Room for managing the <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi>; <lb/>But
          beſides the cruel Pain in thus puſhing back the <lb/>Stone into the Bladder, this foreign
          Body may enter <lb/>into the cellular Texture which ſurrounds the Blad- <lb/>der, and
          lodge itſelf there, and then the <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi>
          <lb/>not having any longer that Play which was endea- <lb/>voured to procure to them, the
          Stone will remain in <lb/>that fatal Lodgement, without Poſſibility of pulling <lb/>it
          out, and the Patient will die. This has been ſeen <lb/>many times. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Stone having ſtopp'd in the Paſſage of the <lb/>Inciſion, you ſlide along the
          Body of it one of <lb/>the Cheeks of our <hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >A</hi> or <hi rend="italic">C</hi>, well-oiled, <lb/>which will be done without much
          Trouble, as I <lb/>have experienced it; the other Cheek afterwards will <pb n="85"/>
          <lb/>paſs on the other Side; after which you join them, <lb/>as has been ſhewn above,
          taking care to preſs cloſe <lb/>the Extremity <hi rend="italic">AC</hi> upon the Stone,
          and to leave the <lb/>largeſt Opening on the Side of the Handle <hi rend="italic">BD</hi>,
          as <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 7. both to hinder the Stone from eſcaping, <lb/>and
          to widen its Paſſage; then, having well-ſecured <lb/>the Screw <hi rend="italic">G</hi>,
          you leave the Screw <hi rend="italic">F</hi> almoſt at Li- <lb/>berty. You graſp the
          Inſtrument with both Hands, <lb/>as near the Stone as you can, and you draw that <lb/>Body
          out, managing it as is uſual with the common <lb/><hi rend="italic">Forceps</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A ſecond Caſe of cutting for the Stone, where <lb/>theſe new <hi rend="italic"
            >Forceps</hi> will be of great Uſe, is this; <lb/>when the Stone is exactly embraced by
          the internal <lb/>Coat of the Bladder; be it that it completely fills <lb/>this whole
          Organ, or that it fills Part of it, which <lb/>may have cloſed itſelf upon the Stone; as
          has hap- <lb/>pen'd to <hi rend="italic">Joſeph Bunel</hi>, whom I cut at <hi
            rend="italic">Andelys</hi> in <lb/>1743. of which I have communicated the Obſervation
          <lb/>to the <hi rend="italic">Royal Society</hi>; or that the Stone has made <lb/>to
          itſelf a Lodgement or Bed in the inſide Coat of <lb/>the Bladder, prolonging itſelf
          towards the cellular <lb/>Texture, which ſurrounds a ſmall Part of thoſe in- <lb/>ſide
          Coats; as I ſaw it in the Bladder of M. <hi rend="italic">Pigache</hi>, <lb/>an eminent
          Counſellor of our City of <hi rend="italic">Rouen</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In ſhort, every foreign Body lodged in the Sub- <lb/>ſtance of any Part of the human
          Body, be it of what <lb/>Nature it will, becomes the Object of our Inſtru- <lb/>ment; and
          the Extraction of it will, in my Opinion, <lb/>become much more eaſy by the means of theſe
            <hi rend="italic">For- <lb/>ceps</hi>, than by the Bullet-drawers, and moſt of the
          <lb/>other Inſtruments invented for that Purpoſe; pro- <lb/>vided however one gets <hi
            rend="italic">Forceps</hi> made of all ſorts <choice>
            <corr>
              <pb n="86"/>
            </corr>
            <sic>
              <pb n="88"/>
            </sic>
          </choice>
          <lb/><choice>
            <corr/>
            <sic>of all ſorts </sic>
          </choice>of Lengths and Bigneſs, in ſhort, of all <lb/>the Shapes which the different
          Caſes may require. </p>
        <signed rend="indent">
          <lb/>I have the Honour to be, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </signed>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <dateline rend="size(0.7) hanging space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Rouen</hi>, May 20. <lb/>1748. <hi rend="italic">N. S.</hi>
        </dateline>
        <cb n="2"/>
        <signed rend="size(1.2) align-right space">
          <lb/>— Le Cat. </signed>
      </div>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>A horizontal line spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <postscript>
        <label rend="italic hanging">
          <lb/>Addition to the Deſcription of the <hi rend="roman">Glaſſes</hi> for pre-
          <lb/>ſerving things in <hi rend="roman">Spirit</hi> of <hi rend="roman">Wine</hi>, by Dr.
            <hi rend="roman">le Cat</hi>, <lb/>pag. 6. </label>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>In uſing the Bottle, of which I have given a De- <lb/>ſcription, I found that it was
          attended with one In- <lb/>convenience. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The circular Groove, the Edge of which was <lb/>turn'd up on the Inſide of the
          Bottle, retained a ſmall <lb/>Quantity of the Water, when I emptied and rinſed <lb/>it; ſo
          that it was impoſſible to do it thoroughly. </p>
        <figure>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Wherefore I cauſed this Veſſel to be made, as repre- <lb/>ſented in the annexed
            Figure, <hi rend="sc">Tab.</hi> I. <hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 1. which <lb/>is a
            Section of it; and where it appears that the Groove <lb/><hi rend="italic">AA</hi> is
            placed on the Outſide of the Edge of the Bot- <lb/>tle. By this means every Drop of the
            contain'd <lb/>Fluid can be pour'd out. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is eaſy to ſee that the circular Border <hi rend="italic">BB</hi> of <lb/>the
            Cover is to enter into theſe Grooves <hi rend="italic">AA</hi>, which <lb/>are fill'd
            with Oil or Quickſilver; and that the Hook <lb/><hi rend="italic">C</hi>, of the ſame
            Cover, is deſtined to ſuſpend in the <lb/>Liquor ſuch Pieces as are to be preſerved in
            it. </p>
          <figDesc>A cross-sectional illustration of a jar and its cover on a separate fold-out
            page. This page is not included in the pdf-file of this text, however it can be found in
            the pdf of the previous text in the corpus from the Philosophical Transactions,
            1749_pt46_0024.pdf. </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </postscript>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
