<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Le Cat and Stacke: Observations on Fungous Excrescences of the
          Bladder</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>M. Le Cat </persName>
              <persName>Tho. Stacke</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Observations on Fungous Excrescences of the Bladder; A Cutting Forceps for
              Extirpating These Excrescences; And Canula's for Treating These Diseases; By M. Le
              Cat, F. R. S. Translated from the French by Tho. Stacke, M. D. F. R. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for C. Davis, Printer to the Royal Society, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1751</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">47</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">292-301</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW109906897</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1751.0046</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT47_0292">
    <body>
      <pb n="292"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XLV<choice>
            <corr>.</corr>
            <sic/>
          </choice></hi> Obſervations on <hi rend="roman">fungous Excreſcences</hi>
        <lb/>of the <hi rend="roman">Bladder</hi>; a <hi rend="roman">cutting Forceps</hi> for ex-
        <lb/>tirpating theſe Exreſcences; and <hi rend="roman">Canula's</hi>
        <lb/>for treating theſe Diſeaſes; by M. <hi rend="roman">Le Cat</hi>, <lb/>F. R. S.
        Tranſlated from the <hi rend="roman">French</hi> by <lb/><hi rend="roman">Tho. Stacke</hi>,
        M. D. F. R. S. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="size(0.7) hanging">Read <date>Nov 14, <lb/>1751. </date>
        </note><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE widow Néel, a farmer at Plein- <lb/>boſc, in the pariſh of
        Etoutteville <lb/>near Yvetot, had, for ſome years, felt pain in the <lb/>ſmall of the back,
        thighs, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> In the year 1734, <lb/>ſhe had made bloody urine, and
        had one thigh and <lb/>leg œdematous. Theſe accidents having diſappear'd, <lb/>were
        ſucceeded by worſe ſymptoms. She had fre- <lb/>quent calls to make water, and did it often,
        a little <lb/>at a time, and with pain, which was violent, parti- <lb/>cularly after the
        urine was diſcharged: and this was <lb/>of a dull red colour, that is, a little tinged with
        <lb/>blood. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>All thoſe of the profeſſion, whom the patient con- <lb/>ſulted, aſſured her that ſhe
        had the ſtone; and I was <lb/>of the ſame opinion, but would not pronounce po-
        <lb/>ſitively, till I had ſearch'd her; which I did the 17 <lb/>of October 1735. As ſoon as
        the ſound was intro- <lb/>duced, blood came away, and in greater quantity, <lb/>the more I
        moved it about. The free play of the <lb/>ſound was obſtructed: I found no ſtone, but pretty
        <lb/>ſure ſigns of excreſcences in the obſtruction of the <lb/>ſound, and the iſſue of
        blood, which its motion oc- <lb/>caſioned. However, by dint of management I found <lb/>a
        ſituation of the ſound, in which, by giving a little <pb n="293"/>
        <lb/>jerk, I touch'd a hard body, the dull percuſſion of <lb/>which convey'd nothing but
        obſcurity to my hand or <lb/>judgment. In order to come at the knowledge of <lb/>this body,
        I paſſed the crooked ſound deſtined for <lb/>men, the bent of which I thought fitter to
        favour <lb/>my inquiries. I found the ſame body again, but <lb/>ſtill with the ſame
        obſcurity. I had extracted ſtones, <lb/>which did not afford plainer marks of their
        exiſtence; <lb/>wherefore I judged, that there might be a ſtone and <lb/>fungous
        excreſcences too in this bladder; and that <lb/>theſe excreſcences were the obſtacles that
        render'd <lb/>our ſearch difficult, and the ſtone doubtful. But the <lb/>dull reſiſtance
        which this hard body made, inclined <lb/>me to think, that it might as well be ſome
        ſcirrhous <lb/>tumour. Theſe doubts held us a long time in ſuſ- <lb/>penſe what party to
        take: but the extreme pain <lb/>which the patient ſuffer'd, and the frequent hæmor-
        <lb/>rhages, which muſt ſoon put an end to her life, made <lb/>us determine to perform the
        operation; that is, to <lb/>open the neck of the bladder, either to extract the <lb/>ſtone,
        if any, or remove and treat the fungus's, <lb/>which exiſted beyond all doubt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I cut this widow the 18 of October 1735, by <lb/>what I call the <hi rend="italic"
          >rural apparatus</hi>, that is, without <lb/>placing her upon the table uſed in our
        hoſpitals, <lb/>which could not well be carried to the country <lb/>where this woman dwelt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I placed her on the edge of her bed: a chair turn'd <lb/>upſide down ſupported her
        ſhoulders. Unknown to <lb/>the patient I cauſed a board to be put under the <lb/>firſt
        mattraſs of this edge of the bed: and when ſhe <lb/>was placed on it, under her backſide, or
        the <hi rend="italic">os ſacrum</hi>, <lb/>I laid another board, on which I put a ſtraw
        cuſhion <pb n="294"/>
        <lb/>made compact and cover'd with linen-cloth. Two <lb/>ſtraps tied to the ends of this
        board were paſſed into <lb/>the bars of the turn'd-up chair, which ſupported the
        <lb/>patient's body: and theſe pieces, to wit, the chair <lb/>and the board with the cuſhion
        were faſtened toge- <lb/>ther by buckles that were on the ſtraps. The aſ- <lb/>ſiſtants, who
        were on each ſide of the patient, had <lb/>each a ſtrong large ſwathing band folded double,
        and <lb/>paſs'd into this fold in a ſlip-knot: at preſent I uſe <lb/>one of thoſe ſtrong
        woollen ſaſhes or girdles, with <lb/>which couriers bind or ſwathe their body. This
        <lb/>ſlip-knot was paſſed on the patient's wriſts, who <lb/>had ſeen nothing of theſe
        preparations, and ſhe was <lb/>bound fast, almoſt before ſhe was aware of it. <lb/>Then I
        introduced a common grooved ſtaff, ſuch as <lb/>is uſed for abſceſſes of the bladder: I
        turn'd the <lb/>groove towards the patient's left thigh, and on this <lb/>groove I puſh'd my
        knife into the bladder; which <lb/>knife is the ſame that I ſtill uſe for women, but
        <lb/>made a little narrower. On that knife, which had <lb/>a groove, I ſlid the gorget and
        forceps in the uſual <lb/>manner. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I ſearched for the ſtone, but in vain, I found no- <lb/>thing but excreſcences, one of
        which was conſider- <lb/><choice>
          <corr>ably</corr>
          <sic>bly</sic>
        </choice> hard: I extracted ſeveral cluſters of them with <lb/>the forceps. Yet ſtill I was
        not very certain, but <lb/>that there might be a ſtone behind a rampart of ex-
        <lb/>creſcences which I felt; and I had not brought the <lb/>crooked forceps with me to
        ſearch behind this in- <lb/>trenchment. When I judged that the patient was <lb/>fatigued by
        my ſearchings, and the extirpations <lb/>which I made with the forceps; I had her put to
        <lb/>bed, after having put a canula into the wound, <pb n="295"/>
        <lb/>contrary to my uſual cuſtom; but this caſe required <lb/>it: theſe ſtrange bodies were
        to be removed, if poſ- <lb/>ſible; that organ muſt be injected, and conſequently <lb/>the
        canula was abſolutely neceſſary. The patient, <lb/>who bore the operation exceedingly well,
        was blooded <lb/>two hours after it: ſhe had a pretty good night, and <lb/>was blooded again
        the next morning. I left one of <lb/>my pupils with her, and return'd to Rouen. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The canula, which I left in the wound, was of <lb/>the common ſort, and therefore too
        narrow to admit <lb/>of ſearching in the diſeaſed part, and to give iſſue to <lb/>thoſe
        excreſcences, which we ought to endeavour to <lb/>diſengage and bring away in this
        treatment: beſides, <lb/>it is extremely difficult to make the canula remain <lb/>in the
        wound. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As ſoon as I got to Rouen, I order'd the canula <lb/>(Plate IV. Fig. 1.) to be made;
        the advantages of <lb/>which above the old one are: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>1. To afford a wider paſſage for the ſubſtances <lb/>that are to be evacuated and
        introduced. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2. To ſecure the inſtrument in the bladder, by <lb/>its own ſtructure chiefly, and
        particularly by the <lb/>ſwelling at <hi rend="italic">BB</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>3. The neck <hi rend="italic">AA</hi>, which is at the baſis of the <lb/>ſwelling, is
        embraced by the neck of the bladder; <lb/>whereby the ſurgeon may be ſure, how much of the
        <lb/>canula enters the bladder: and the openings <hi rend="italic">CC</hi>, <lb/>being
        immediately above the ſwelling <hi rend="italic">B</hi>, are fixed at <lb/>the loweſt part
        of the bladder. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Fig. 2, 3, 4, of the ſame plate repreſent the ſame <lb/>canula as above deſcribed, but
        with further im- <lb/>provements for caſes, which require the evacuation <lb/>of groſs
        ſubſtances, the paſſage for which cannot <pb n="296"/>
        <lb/>be too wide and direct. The deſcription of its parts, <lb/>which is in the explanation
        of the figures, ſuffices <lb/>to ſhew its uſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I return'd to the patient the next day; and found <lb/>her in a fever, with many
        colicky pains: but at <lb/>the end of the third day there was nothing extra- <lb/>ordinary. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I intended to make another ſearch, but I feared <lb/>renewing thoſe accidents:
        wherefore I contended my- <lb/>ſelf with injecting a liquid digeſtive; and deferr'd <lb/>any
        farther trials till after the ſuppuration was well <lb/>formed, which I expected about the
        8th or 9th day. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I re-viſited the patient on the 7th, and found her <lb/>a little feveriſh, but ſhe had
        a good night's reſt. <lb/>There was a ſmall diſcharge thro' the canula of tole- <lb/>rably
        white pus, but of an intolerable ſmell. The <lb/>canula ſeem'd to us to be much clogg'd with
        ſloughs; <lb/>and the ſtench made us ſuſpect a collection and <lb/>lodgment of theſe ſloughs
        behind the canula. We <lb/>reſolved to put in the canula above deſcribed; and <lb/>as there
        was a neceſſity of dilating, in order to intro- <lb/>duce it; we agreed to take the
        advantage of this di- <lb/>latation, to try to diſcover by the crooked forceps, <lb/>which I
        had brought with me, if there might not <lb/>be a ſtone to be extracted, or at leaſt ſome
        more of <lb/>theſe excreſcences, and to break or bruiſe ſuch as <lb/>we ſhould not be able
        to draw, that they may fall <lb/>off by ſuppuration. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I executed this trial on the 8th day. The dilata- <lb/>tion was made between two
        grooved ſounds, as it is <lb/>done in the greater apparatus between the male and <lb/>female
        conductors. I found no ſtone as yet, but <lb/>brought away cluſters of the tops of fungus's
        a ſpe- <pb n="297"/>
        <lb/>cimen of which appears in Plate I. Letter <hi rend="italic">F</hi>, I cruſhed <lb/>the
        reſt of the excreſcences, and placed the large <lb/>canula. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Experience has ſhewn me, that this bruiſing of <lb/>the fungus's of the bladder is more
        painful and dan- <lb/>gerous than poſſibly is imagined. They are far from <lb/>being of the
        ſame nature with the polypus of the <lb/>noſe, which is pull'd out with little or no pain,
        and <lb/>without any bad conſequence. The fungus's of the <lb/>bladder have more
        conſiſtence, more ſolidity, and <lb/>for that reaſon more ſenſibility. Accordingly, after
        <lb/>this laſt operation, the patient was ſeized with a vio- <lb/>lent fever, which carried
        her off in two days. I <lb/>open'd her body, and found the bladder in the con- <lb/>dition
        repreſented by the figures, and their expla- <lb/>nation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This obſervation made me think, that if I met <lb/>with a parallel caſe, that is, a
        patient with fungous <lb/>excreſcences in the bladder, diſtinctly characterized, <lb/>and
        accompanied with pains and exceſſive hæmor- <lb/>rhages, which render the palliative cure
        uſeleſs and <lb/>unſucceſsful; and if he had a conſtitution and cou- <lb/>rage proper to
        make me hope for ſucceſs from a great <lb/>operation; I would find a way to attack the
        excreſ- <lb/>cences with a cutting inſtrument, the operations of <lb/>which are much ſurer
        and leſs painful than any <lb/>other method. Practitioners adviſe to ſuppurate ſuch <lb/>of
        theſe excreſcences, as the fingers cannot reach, <lb/>that is, thoſe which can neither be
        tied not cut. <lb/>But how can one bring ſuch ſenſible parts to ſup- <lb/>puration? we have
        no ointment that can raiſe a ſup- <lb/>puration in a ſound part. Fungus's are a ſort of ve-
        <lb/>getation, which, tho' preternatural, are ſtill living, <pb n="298"/>
        <lb/>and, in ſome meaſure, ſound parts: how then are <lb/>they to be diſpoſed to ſuppurate?
        it muſt be either <lb/>by pulling them out, or by cruſhing them, as we <lb/>have done. But
        ſeeing this operation is dangerous, <lb/>an inſtrument ſhould be contrived, which might be
        <lb/>conveyed to the bottom of the bladder, like the for- <lb/>ceps; and which might at the
        ſame time be able to <lb/>cut theſe inacceſſible excreſcences, or the greateſt <lb/>part of
        them at leaſt; the remains of which being <lb/>cut open, would thereby acquire the neceſſary
        diſ- <lb/>poſitions to ſuppurate, which are indicated for the <lb/>cure. For this purpoſe it
        was, that about that time <lb/>I contrived the cutting forceps of Plate III. the uſe <lb/>of
        which will be ſufficiently declared in the expla- <lb/>nation of the figures. I did not
        intend to make this <lb/>inſtrument public, until I had uſed it on a living <lb/>body: but,
        as no opportunity has offer'd ſince the <lb/>year 1735, I thought I ought not to delay its
        publi- <lb/>cation any longer; to the end that, if ſome other <lb/>perſon met with this
        opportunity before me, he might <lb/>profit by the reflections, which the preceding obſer-
        <lb/>vation occaſioned me to make. </p>
      <figure>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Explanation of the Figures. </head>
        <p rend="space hanging">
          <lb/>Plate I. The bladder of the widow Néel, full of <lb/>excreſcences. </p>
        <p>
          <list rend="hanging">
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">AAA</hi>, The bladder. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">BB</hi>, Its neck. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">C</hi>, The inciſion of my lateral operation. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">DD</hi>, Thickneſs of the coats of the bladder. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">E</hi>, Remains of the excreſcences, which were not ex-
              <lb/>tirpated, and ſeem round or regular, becauſe their <pb n="299"/>
              <lb/>tops ending in cluſters were taken off by the <lb/>forceps. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">F</hi>, The ſhape of theſe tops of the excreſcences. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of the bladder cut open, showing the excreſcences inside it, on a
          separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>Plate II. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The ſame bladder, after removing the excreſcences, <lb/>in order to ſhew their common
          root <hi rend="italic">E</hi>. </p>
        <p>
          <list rend="hanging">
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">F</hi>, Very conſiderable fleſhy fibres, which ſurround
              <lb/>this baſis, and were confounded in the ſcirrhous <lb/>ſubſtance. It was this
              ſcirrhous baſis, that I had <lb/>touch'd with the ſtaff, and which I took for a
              <lb/>hard body. The difficulty of touching it aroſe <lb/>from the neceſſity of paſſing
              between two ex- <lb/>creſcences. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">DD</hi>, The great thickneſs of this bladder. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of the same bladder without the excreſcences on a separate fold-out
          page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>Plate III. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Cutting forceps or ſciſſars, to cut the excreſcences <lb/>of the bladder or <hi
            rend="italic">uterus</hi>, which are inacceſſible to <lb/>the fingers. </p>
        <p>
          <list rend="hanging">
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">A</hi>, The bend of this inſtrument on the flat of its
              <lb/>blades. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">B</hi>, Buttons, which terminate each blade, and are at
              <lb/>ſome little diſtance from one another, even when <lb/>the blades are cloſed
              together: that theſe ends <lb/>might neither prick nor pinch the coats of the
              <lb/>bladder. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of three pairs of scissors, slightly different in size but all
          having curved blades with buttoned tips, on a separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>Plate IV. </head>
        <figure>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>Fig. 1. The new canula. </head>
          <p>
            <list rend="hanging">
              <item>
                <lb/><hi rend="italic">A</hi>, The neck, which is to be embraced by the neck <lb/>of
                the bladder. </item>
              <item>
                <lb/><hi rend="italic">B</hi>, The ſwelling, which is to be within the neck of
                <lb/>the bladder. </item>
              <pb n="300"/>
              <item>
                <lb/><hi rend="italic">C</hi>, The head, which is to be in the cavity of this
                <lb/>organ, together with its wide openings. </item>
              <item>
                <lb/><hi rend="italic">D</hi>, The ſtyle or ſound of this canula. </item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <figDesc>An illustration of a curved cannula with a flame-shaped tip, and a similarly
            curved sound that is to be fitted through it, on a separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <figure>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>Fig. 2. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The ſame canula impoved, inaſmuch as its end <hi rend="italic">B</hi>, <lb/>which I
            name <hi rend="italic">introductor</hi>, is ſcrew'd on the canula <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >A</hi> at <hi rend="italic">C</hi>, and is unſcrew'd by means of the ſtructure of
            <lb/>this introductor. </p>
          <figDesc>An illustration of a straight cannula with a flame-shaped tip screwed on, on a
            separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <figure>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>Fig. 3. <lb/>The introductor ſeparated from the canula. </head>
          <p>
            <list rend="hanging">
              <item>
                <lb/><hi rend="italic">A</hi>, A wire or rod of ſteel, which ſupports the end of
                <lb/>the introductor, and ſerves to unſcrew it from the <lb/>canula. </item>
              <item>
                <lb/><hi rend="italic">B</hi>, The extremity of the introductor, which ought <lb/>to
                be made of ſilver. </item>
              <item>
                <lb/><hi rend="italic">CC</hi>, Elaſtic ſteel plates or blades. Theſe plates have
                <lb/>on the inſide of their edge a female ſcrew, which <lb/>enters on a male ſcrew
                of the outſide of the end <lb/>of the canula. Their ſpringineſs makes them
                <lb/>ſeparate when the introductor is mounted on the <lb/>canula; and by this
                widening aſunder they leave <lb/>the openings or eyes of <hi rend="italic">d</hi>,
                  <hi rend="italic">d</hi>, Fig. 1, 2. But when <lb/>they are unſcrew'd, they <choice>
                  <corr>cloſe</corr>
                  <sic>clofe</sic>
                </choice> together, as appears <lb/>in Fig. 3, whereby this end becomes ſlender
                enough <lb/>to paſs thro' the canula, thro' which this part of <lb/>the inſtrument
                is drawn out, when the canula is <lb/>placed in ſituation; which is the intent of
                this <lb/>ſtructure; for, by this means the outlet becomes <lb/>larger, and the
                excreſcences cannot be fretted. </item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <figDesc>An illustration of the flame-shaped tip, showing a long straight rod protruding
            from its base, on a separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <figure>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>Fig. 4. <lb/>The canula ſtripp'd of the part above deſcribed. </head>
          <p>
            <list rend="hanging">
              <item>
                <lb/><hi rend="italic">A</hi>, Its funnel or tube and wide ſtraight orifice: wherein
                  <pb n="301"/>
                <lb/>conſiſts the improvement of this laſt canula, which <lb/>I had principally in
                view in the rectification of the <lb/>firſt. </item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <figDesc>An illustration of the cannula without the tip on a separate fold-out page.
          </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </figure>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
