<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Debenham and Clubb: The Case of a Woman, from Whom the Bones of a
          Foetus Were Extracted</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Thomas Debenham</persName>
              <persName>J. Clubb</persName>
            </author>
            <title>The Case of a Woman, from Whom the Bones of a Foetus Were Extracted. By Mr.
              Thomas Debenham, Surgeon, at Debenham in Suffolk. Communicated by the Rev. Mr. J.
              Clubb, Vicar of That Parish, to William Battie M. D. F. R. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for C. Davis, Printer to the Royal Society, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1751</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">47</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">92-95</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW109906897</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1751.0014</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT47_0092">
    <body>
      <pb n="92"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XIII.</hi> The Caſe of a Woman, from whom the <lb/>Bones of a <hi
          rend="roman">Fœtus</hi> were extracted. By Mr. <lb/><hi rend="roman">Thomas Debenham</hi>,
        Surgeon, at <hi rend="roman">Deben- <lb/>ham</hi> in <hi rend="roman">Suffolk</hi>.
        Communicated by the Rev. <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="roman">J. Clubb</hi>, Vicar of that Pariſh, to
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">William Battie</hi> M. D. F. R. S. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="size(0.7) hanging">Read <date>Febr. 7. <lb/>1750. </date>
        </note><hi rend="dc(2)">O</hi>N the 25 of April 1749, the wife <lb/>of one Benjamin Laſt, a
        cooper, <lb/>in the pariſh of Debenham, in the county of Suf- <lb/>folk, aged about 34
        years, being pregnant of her <lb/>eighth child, had all the ſymptoms of a woman in <pb
          n="93"/>
        <lb/>labour. Accordingly, a midwife was ſent for; who, <lb/>from the violence of the pains,
        expected, that ſhe <lb/>would ſoon be delivered; but, to her great ſur- <lb/>prize, nothing
        enſued but a loſs of blood, and the <lb/>pains were conſiderably abated. A fever immedi-
        <lb/>ately came on, which caſt her into an exceſſive <lb/>faintneſs, and loſs of ſtrength,
        accompanied with a <lb/>nauſea. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 26 of May, I was deſired by her husband <lb/>to viſit her; and, by the account
        ſhe gave me, I <lb/>much ſuſpected, that ſhe muſt have miſcalculated <lb/>with regard to her
        time; and I propoſed to examine <lb/>her: but ſhe, out of a miſtaken modeſty, not com-
        <lb/>plying, I contented myſelf with cooling injections, <lb/>mild cathartics, and cordial
        powders, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>; by the <lb/>uſe of which medicines ſhe grew better;
        and, on the <lb/>26 of March following, undertook to walk a journey <lb/>of 15 miles. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I heard no more of her for the preſent; but, on the <lb/>27 of April 1750, the pains
        returned, very much like <lb/>thoſe of labour; which obliged her husband to call <lb/>me out
        of bed. I immediately gave her an ano- <lb/>dyne, which abated her pains, and compoſed her
        to <lb/>reſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 14 of May, ſhe felt a pricking pain in her <lb/>navel, with a ſwelling and
        redneſs, which, in a few <lb/>days, appear'd like a boil; when, being deſired to
        <lb/>inſpect the tumour, I applied an emollient cataplaſm. <lb/>The next morning, upon
        removing my dreſſings, a <lb/>fetid matter enſued; whereupon, dilating the ſmall <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">ſinus</hi> with my ſciſſars, the <hi rend="italic">ſcapula</hi> of a <hi
          rend="italic">fœtus</hi> pre- <lb/>ſented itſelf. On the 25 of July, by the direction <pb
          n="94"/>
        <lb/>of a phyſician, I undertook, by making a circular <lb/>inciſion round the navel, to
        enlarge the orifice into <lb/>the cavity of the <hi rend="italic">abdomen</hi>, in order to
        extract the <hi rend="italic"><choice>
            <corr>fœ</corr>
            <sic>fæ</sic>
          </choice>- <lb/>tus</hi> that way: but the woman being very weak, and <lb/>much emaciated,
        I could now only take off the <hi rend="italic">ſca- <lb/>pula</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The next day, I extracted one whole arm, ſome <lb/>ribs, part of the <hi rend="italic"
          >vertebræ</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> and, the day follow- <lb/>ing, the greateſt
        part of the remaining <hi rend="italic">fœtus</hi>, except <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >cranium</hi>, which ſeem'd to adhere to the inteſtines. <lb/>This determined me to
        proceed very cautiouſly, and <lb/>not to attempt the removal of it at once, but piece-
        <lb/>meal, and by degrees, as opportunity would give me <lb/>leave; which I did with my
        forceps: but, notwith- <lb/>ſtanding all my care, the ſharp edges of the broken <lb/>pieces
        of the <hi rend="italic">cranium</hi> tore the inteſtines, ſo that the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">fæces</hi> iſſued from the wound at every dreſſing for <lb/>ſeveral weeks
        together. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The wound was daily dreſs'd with dry lint, ſpi- <lb/>rituous fomentations, and
        cataplaſms. Injections, <lb/>made of ſack and warm water, were found of <lb/>great uſe,
        thrown in in large quantities; and (what <lb/>is well worth obſervation) ſeveral parts of
        the bones, <lb/>as the <hi rend="italic">tibia</hi>, <hi rend="italic">fibula</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> were diſcharg'd by the <lb/><hi rend="italic">vagina</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By the means above-mention'd, and proper band- <lb/>ages, the wound was thoroughly
        deterged, incarned, <lb/>and, by the uſe of epulotics, completely cicatrized; <lb/>and the
        woman is now perfectly recovered, and ſince <lb/>grown fat." </p>
      <pb n="95"/>
      <postscript>
        <p rend="hanging">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">N. B.</hi> After the diſcharge of the whole <hi rend="italic"
            >fœtus</hi>, the <lb/>patient had milk in her breaſts, as upon a natural <lb/>delivery.
        </p>
      </postscript>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <dateline rend="size(0.7) hanging space">
        <lb/>Debenham, Jan. 18. <lb/>1750-51. </dateline>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <signed rend="size(1.2) align-right space">
        <lb/>Tho. Debenham. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
