<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Stedman: The Effects of the Hyoscyamus albus, or White Henbane</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>John Stedman</persName>
            </author>
            <title>The Effects of the Hyoscyamus albus, or White Henbane; In a Letter to Dr. John
              Pringle, F. R. S. from Dr. John Stedman, Late Surgeon Major to the Regiment of the
              Royal Grey Dragoons</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for C. Davis, Printer to the Royal Society, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1751</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">47</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">194-197</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW109906897</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1751.0029</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT47_0194">
    <body>
      <pb n="194"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXVIII.</hi> The Effects of the <hi rend="roman">Hyoſcyamus al-
          <lb/>bus</hi>, or <hi rend="roman">white Henbane</hi>; in a Letter to <lb/>Dr. <hi
          rend="roman">John Pringle</hi>, F. R. S. from Dr. <hi rend="roman">John <lb/>Stedman</hi>,
        late Surgeon-Major to the Re- <lb/>giment of the Royal Grey Dragoons. </head>
      <div>
        <salute rend="indent space">
          <lb/>SIR, </salute>
        <dateline rend="size(0.7) align-right">Edinburgh, Octob. 2, 1750. </dateline>
        <p>
          <lb/>
          <note place="inset" rend="size(0.7) hanging">Read <date>May 16. <lb/>1751. </date>
          </note><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N the month of Auguſt 1748, whilſt <lb/>the Greys were
          cantoon'd in the vil- <lb/>lage of Vucht near Boiſleduc in Dutch Brabant, five <lb/>men
          and two women of that regiment having eaten <lb/>of the leaves of the <hi rend="italic"
            >hyoſcyamus albus</hi>, ſhred and boiled <lb/>in broth, were ſoon after ſeized with a
          giddineſs and <lb/>ſtupor, as if drunk. I ſaw them about three hours <lb/>after having eat
          of it; and then three of the men were <lb/>become quite inſenſible, did not know their
          com- <lb/>rades, talk'd incoherently, and were in as high a <lb/>delirium, as people in
          the rage of a fever. All of <lb/>them had low irregular pulſes, ſlaver'd, and fre-
          <lb/>quently chang'd colour: their eyes look'd fiery, and <lb/>they catch'd at whatever
          lay next them, calling out, <lb/>that it was going to fall. They complain'd of their
          <lb/>legs being powerleſs. I mix'd what ipecacuana I had <lb/>with me in warm water, and
          made them drink it; <lb/>and afterwards threw in as much warm water and <lb/>oil, as I
          could prevail with them to ſwallow. Thoſe, <lb/>who were not inſenſible, vomited freely,
          and were <lb/>relieved by it. Two of the three affected with de- <lb/>lirium, tho' they
          drank great quantities, did not vo- <lb/>mit, but had profuſe ſweats, and paſs'd plenty of
            <pb n="195"/>
          <lb/>urine, by which they were likewiſe ſomewhat re- <lb/>liev'd. The third of theſe was
          obſtinate, nor could <lb/>be prevail'd upon to do any thing. The ſymptoms <lb/>with him
          continued longer, and were more violent. <lb/>He was ſo reſtleſs, that, notwithſtanding he
          could <lb/>not walk, two of his comrades were not able to <lb/>keep him in a chair. Next
          morning they had no <lb/>other complaint than people commonly have after <lb/>great
          drinking; but afterwards (tho' the danger ſeem'd <lb/>over) ſome of them complain'd of
          feebleneſs and a <lb/>weight at their ſtomachs; others, of gripes, ſtitches, <lb/>headach;
          and all of them were vertiginous at times. <lb/>Theſe complaints continued above a month
          after the <lb/>accident. One of the women had her hands ſtiff <lb/>and ſwell'd; whether
          from the action of the vomit, <lb/>or the force of the poiſon, I know not. The man,
          <lb/>who pull'd theſe leaves in miſtake for another plant, <lb/>ſaid, that from the
          neareſt conjecture he could make, <lb/>there might be from fifteen to twenty leaves,
          boil'd <lb/>in about ten quarts of water. They did not eat one <lb/>half of that quantity,
          and the poiſon began to diſ- <lb/>cover itſelf with ſome of them in half an hour.
          <lb/>This ſeem'd to be the <hi rend="italic">hyoſcyamus major albus</hi> of Caſ- <lb/>par
          Bauhinus. It is eaſily known by its large duſkiſh <lb/>bell-flower; but if not in the
          flower, the remark- <lb/>able noiſome ſmell of the leaf, ſomewhat narcotic, <lb/>if once
          known, will ever after diſcover it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Some time before this accident, we had a proof of <lb/>the effect of the yew-tree
          upon ſome of our horſes: <lb/>they were put into an orchard, where they cropp'd <lb/>the
          branches of theſe trees, and about four hours <lb/>after, without any previous ſymptom of
          diſorder, <lb/>dropp'd down, and after a ſtruggle of a minute or <pb n="196"/>
          <lb/>two died. This was probably about the time, that <lb/>the juice enter'd the blood.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Remarks by Mr. <hi rend="roman">William Watſon</hi>, F. R. S. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Upon reading the above paper, Mr. Watſon obſerv'd, <lb/>that the effects therein
          mentioned could not ariſe <lb/>from the <hi rend="italic">hyoſcyamus albus</hi>, or white
          henbane, as Dr. <lb/>Stedman imagines; that plant, from the concurrent <lb/>teſtimony of
          the beſt botanical writers, not being <lb/>found ſo far north as Brabant: but the miſchief
          was <lb/>done by the <hi rend="italic">hyoſcyamus niger</hi>, or black henbane, <lb/>which
          grows plentifully there, as well as almoſt all <lb/>over Europe in uncultivated places,
          and by the ſides of <lb/>roads. The white on the contrary is ſown in gar- <lb/>dens, and
          not found ſpontaneous in higher latitudes <lb/>than the ſouthern parts of France. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Dr. Stedman's deſcription demonſtrates likewiſe <lb/>the above plant to be the <hi
            rend="italic">hyoſcyamus niger</hi>, as he <lb/>ſays, that <q rend="quotes">it is known
            by its duſkiſh bell-flower. </q>
          <lb/>The flower of black henbane is of that hue, being <lb/>of a yellow colour
          interſperſed with veins of purple; <lb/>whereas the flower of the white henbane is of a
          <lb/>pale-yellow colour. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This error ariſes from the improper denomination <lb/>impoſed upon many plants by the
          ancients, and <lb/>which has been preſerved even ſince the revival of <lb/>letters; which,
          to one not very well acquainted with <lb/>botany, is liable to miſlead. Thus, in the caſe
          be- <lb/>fore us, the leaves of the black henbane are very <lb/>little leſs white than
          thoſe of the white; but this <lb/>denomination took its riſe from the different colour
          <lb/>of their ſeeds. In ſuch caſes therefore, without <pb n="197"/>
          <lb/>being well acquainted with the ſpecifice difference of <lb/>each plant, before it
          ripens its ſeed, it is not a little <lb/>difficult to diſtinguiſh them one from the other.
          <lb/>This ſpecific difference will be beſt furniſhed by the <lb/>leaves. Thus in the
          henbane, the leaves of the white <lb/>are placed upon long footſtalks; thoſe of the black
          <lb/>have none, but the lower extremity of the leaf ſur- <lb/>rounds the ſtalk. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
