<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Pringle: A Remarkable Case of Fragility, Flexibility, and Dissolution,
          of the Bones</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>John Pringle</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Remarkable Case of Fragility, Flexibility, and Dissolution, of the Bones;
              Communicated by John Pringle, M. D. F. R. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for C. Davis, Printer to the Royal Society, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1753</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">48</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">297-301</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110357373</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1753.0044</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT48_0297">
    <body>
      <pb n="297"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XLIV.</hi> A remarkable Caſe of <hi rend="roman">Fragility</hi>, <hi
          rend="roman">Flexi- <lb/>bility</hi>, and <hi rend="roman">Diſſolution</hi>, of the <hi
          rend="roman">Bones</hi>; com- <lb/>municated by <hi rend="roman">John Pringle</hi>, M. D.
        F. R. S. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="size(0.7) hanging">Read <date>July 12, <lb/>1753. </date>
        </note><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>ARY Hayes, of Stoke-Holy-Croſs, <lb/>near Norwich in Norfolk,
        gave <lb/>the following Account, June 21, 1752: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That ſhe was born Jan. 11, 1718, and never mar- <lb/>ried, or was addicted to any kind
        of Intemperance: <lb/>That her father was unhealthy a great part of his life, <lb/>but ſhe
        knew not what diſeaſe he was ſubject to: That <lb/>her mother died when ſhe was a child; but
        ſhe did not <lb/>remember ſhe ever heard of her being unhealthy: <lb/>That ſhe herſelf was
        always look'd upon as an healthy <lb/>ſtrong girl, till about 15 years of age; then fell
        into <lb/>the green-ſickneſs, and took various medicines, to no <lb/>purpoſe: That this
        diſeaſe, as far as ſhe could recol- <lb/>lect, was all ſhe had to complain of; doing the or-
        <lb/>dinary work in a farmer's houſe, till October 1748: <lb/>Then was ſeiz'd with pain
        univerſally, attended with <lb/>feveriſh ſymptoms. Thus ſhe continued ſome weeks; <lb/>after
        which the pain was chiefly confined to her thighs <lb/>and legs, but not increaſed by
        external preſſure: <lb/>That, in September 1749, ſhe broke her leg, as ſhe <lb/>was walking
        from the bed to her chair, without fall- <lb/>ing down, and heard the bones ſnap. The
        fracture <lb/>was properly treated, and regard had to her indiſpo- <lb/>ſition; but no
        callus was generated; the bones growing <lb/>flexible from the knee to the ancle in a few
        months; <lb/>as did thoſe of her other leg. Soon after, thoſe of <lb/>her thighs were
        viſibly affected in the like manner. <pb n="298"/>
        <lb/>Both legs and thighs then became very œdematous, <lb/>and ſubject to excoriate,
        diſcharging a thin yellow <lb/>ichor. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The winter after breaking her leg, ſhe had ſym- <lb/>ptoms of the ſcurvy, and bled much
        at the gums. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Many eminent phyſicians, who were of opinion, <lb/>that this diſeaſe of the bones might
        ariſe from acidity <lb/>abounding in the blood, preſcribed for her, but with- <lb/>out
        effect: unleſs the regularity of her menſtruation <lb/>for the laſt eighteen months may be
        attributed to a <lb/>chalybeate medicine: tho' medicines of that nature <lb/>had no ſuch
        effect formerly, when ſhe was in a con- <lb/>dition to take exerciſe, and regularly
        perſiſted in the <lb/>uſe of them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For ſome conſiderable time paſt ſhe had found lit- <lb/>tle alteration in her
        complaints in general; thought <lb/>her appetite and digeſtion rather better, but that the
        <lb/>difficulty of breathing, which ſhe had long labour'd <lb/>under, gradually increaſed:
        and the thorax appeared <lb/>ſo much ſtraiten'd, as neceſſarily impeded the expan- <lb/>ſion
        of the lungs. Her ſpine became much diſ- <lb/>torted: any motion of the vertebræ of her
        loins gave <lb/>extreme pain; and her thighs and legs were become <lb/>intirely uſeleſs;
        which wholly confined her to her <lb/>bed, in a ſitting poſture: and the bones ſhe reſted
        <lb/>upon, having loſt their ſolidity, were much ſpread. <lb/>Alſo the ends of her fingers
        and thumbs, by frequent <lb/>endeavours to lift herſelf up for eaſe, became very <lb/>broad
        and flat. Then ſhe meaſured but four feet, <lb/>tho', before this diſeaſe came upon her, ſhe
        was about <lb/>five feet and a half high, and well-ſhaped. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This is the beſt information that could be obtained <lb/>from her own mouth, and what
        was obſerved in the <pb n="299"/>
        <lb/>caſe before, and at the firſt-mention'd time, when ſhe <lb/>readily conſented to the
        examination of her body, <lb/><hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> after death. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From that time to her death, which happened Feb. <lb/>6, 1753, the chief thing ſhe
        complain'd of, and what <lb/>the people about her obſerved, was a gradual increaſe <lb/>of
        difficulty of breathing; a waſting of her fleſh; a <lb/>ceſſation of her menſtruation for
        the laſt four months; <lb/>a tendency in her legs to mortify, which had long <lb/>been
        anaſarcous, and excoriated almoſt all over; ſhe <lb/>retaining her ſenſes perfectly to the
        laſt moment of <lb/>her life, and dying without ſhewing the leaſt ſigns of <lb/>the agonies
        of death. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Two days after death, her limbs being firſt well <lb/>ſtretched out, ſhe was exactly
        meaſured, and found <lb/>wanting of her natural ſtature more than two feet two <lb/>inches.
        Then the thorax and abdomen were opened, <lb/>the ſtrernum being intirely removed, with part
        of <lb/>the ribs, in order to gain at once a full view of thoſe <lb/>cavities, and diſcover
        how the viſcera therein con- <lb/>tained had obſtructed each other in their reſpective
        <lb/>functions. The heart and lungs were ſound, but flac- <lb/>cid, and much confined in
        their motion; to which <lb/>the enormous ſize of the liver contributed in ſome <lb/>meaſure,
        extending quite croſs the abdomen, and <lb/>bearing hard againſt the diaphragm. The lungs
        did <lb/>not adhere to the pleura; nor was the liver ſcirrhous, <lb/>but faulty only in its
        bulk. The meſentery was ſound, <lb/>except only one large ſcirrhous gland upon it. The
        <lb/>ſpleen extremely ſmall. Nothing elſe was found ob- <lb/>ſervable in thoſe cavities. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſcull was not opened, to examine the brain, <lb/>as intended, we wanting time; the
        miniſter waiting at <pb n="300"/>
        <lb/>church for interment, and the relations growing im- <lb/>patient; but we had no reaſon
        to ſuſpect any defect <lb/>there, from any previous complaint. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>All her bones were more or leſs affected, and <lb/>ſcarce any would reſiſt the knife:
        thoſe of the head, <lb/>thorax, ſpine, and pelvis, nearly to the ſame degree <lb/>of
        ſoftneſs: thoſe of the lower extremities much more <lb/>diſſolved than thoſe of the upper,
        or of any other part. <lb/>They were cut quite thro' their whole length, with- <lb/>out
        turning the edge of the knife, and much leſs re- <lb/>ſiſtance found, than firm muſcular
        fleſh would have <lb/>made; being changed into a kind of parenchymous <lb/>ſubſtance, like
        ſoft dark coloured liver, only meeting <lb/>here and there with bony <hi rend="italic"
          >laminæ</hi>, thin as an egg- <lb/>ſhell. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thoſe bones were moſt diſſolved, which, in their <lb/>natural ſtate, were moſt compact,
        and contained moſt <lb/>marrow in their cavities; and the heads of them were <lb/>leaſt
        diſſolved. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This, perhaps, is the more worthy obſervation, as <lb/>it held good throughout, and
        looks as if the wonder- <lb/>ful change they had undergone might be cauſed by <lb/>the
        marrow having acquired a diſſolving quality: <lb/>for it was evident the diſſolution began
        withinſide, <lb/>from the bony <hi rend="italic">laminæ</hi> remaining here and there on
        <lb/>the outſide, and no-where elſe, and the pain not be- <lb/>ing increaſed at firſt by
        external preſſure. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The perioſteum was thicker than ordinary: the car- <lb/>tilages rather thinner; but
        no-where in a ſtate of diſ- <lb/>ſolution like the bones. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The day after this examination, ſome of the whole <lb/>ſubſtance of the leg and
        thigh-bones, that was intirely <lb/>diſſolved into a kind of pulp, was ſent to an ingenious
          <pb n="301"/>
        <lb/>chemiſt; and, by the experiments which he made, <lb/>he ſaid he could diſcover neither
        acid nor alkali pre- <lb/>vailing in it. </p>
      <p rend="indentall hanging">
        <lb/>We, whoſe names are ſubſcribed, do atteſt the <lb/>truth of this relation. </p>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <dateline rend="size(0.7) space">
        <lb/>June 25, 1753. </dateline>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <signed rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">B. Dack</hi>, Phyſician. <lb/><hi rend="sc">Edward Cooper</hi>, <hi
          rend="dc(2)">}</hi>Surgeons. <lb/><hi rend="sc">B. Gooch</hi>, </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
