<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Sharp: A Description of a New Method of Opening the Cornea</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Samuel Sharp</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Description of a New Method of Opening the Cornea, in Order to Extract the
              Crystalline Humour; By Mr. Samuel Sharp, Surgeon to Guy's Hospital, and F. R.
              S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for C. Davis, Printer to the Royal Society, over-against
                  Gray's-Inn-Gate in Holbourn. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1753</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">48</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">161-163</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110357373</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1753.0024</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT48_0161">
    <body>
      <pb n="161"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXIV.</hi> A Deſcription of a new Method of <lb/>opening the <hi
          rend="roman">Cornea</hi>, in order to extract the <lb/><hi rend="roman">cryſtalline
          Humour</hi>; by Mr. <hi rend="roman">Samuel Sharp</hi>, <lb/>Surgeon to <hi rend="roman"
          >Guy's Hoſpital</hi>, and F. R. S. </head>
      <figure>
        <lb/>
        <figDesc>An illustration of an eye and a scalpel, its blade crossing the eyeball
          horizontally. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <p>
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="size(0.7) hanging">Read <date>April 12, <lb/>1753. </date>
        </note><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE operation of diſcharging the <lb/>cryſtalline humour from
        the eye, <lb/>for the cure of that ſpecies of blindneſs call'd a cata- <lb/>ract, was a few
        years ſince invented by Monſ. Daviel, <lb/>who has perform'd it on great numbers of
        patients, and <lb/>continues ſtill to practiſe it with remarkable ſucceſs, <lb/>as I have
        lately learned from unqueſtionable au- <lb/>thority <note n="*" place="bottom"
          rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Mr. Morand, perpetual Secretary of the Academy of Surgery <lb/>at Paris. </p>
        </note>. Suppoſing it therefore admitted, that the <lb/>extraction of the cryſtalline humour
        has been found <lb/>by experience to be a uſeful method of cure, I here <lb/>take the
        liberty of laying before the Society a new <lb/>manner of making the inciſion of the cornea,
        by <lb/><choice>
          <corr/>
          <sic>by </sic>
        </choice>which, I flatter myſelf, Monſ. Daviel's operation <lb/>will be very much ſhorten'd,
        the patient will ſuffer <lb/>leſs pain, and every ſkilful operator will be equal to <lb/>the
        undertaking. </p>
      <pb n="162"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Place the patient in the ſame ſituation as for couch- <lb/>ing, either opening the
        eyelids with your fore-finger <lb/>and thumb, or letting an aſſiſtant raiſe the upper eye-
        <lb/>lid, whilſt you yourſelf keep down the under eye- <lb/>lid. Then, with a ſmall knife,
        the figure of which is <lb/>here repreſented, holding its edge downwards, make <lb/>a
        puncture through the cornea near its circumference <lb/>into the anterior chamber of the
        eye, in ſuch a dire- <lb/>ction, as to carry it horizontally, and oppoſite to the
        <lb/>tranſverſe diameter of the pupil: after which you are <lb/>to paſs it towards the noſe,
        through the cornea from <lb/>within outwards, as near to its circumference, as in <lb/>the
        firſt puncture. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When you have made the ſecond puncture, puſh the <lb/>extremity of the blade one
        ſeventh of an inch beyond <lb/>the ſurface of the cornea, and immediately cut the
        <lb/>cornea downwards, drawing the knife towards you <lb/>as you make the inciſion. After
        this, you preſs <lb/>gently with your thumb againſt the inferior part of <lb/>the globe of
        the eye, in order to expel the cataract, <lb/>and the operation finiſhes, according to the
        different <lb/>circumſtances, as in the manner propoſed by Monſ. <lb/>Daviel. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>One extraordinary benefit ſeems to ariſe from the <lb/>uſe of this ſingle inſtrument,
        and perhaps from the <lb/>ſhape of its blade, which increaſes in breadth all the <lb/>way
        towards the handle: for, by this means, the <lb/>punctures are ſo exactly fill'd up by the
        blade, that <lb/>very little of the aqueous humour is diſcharged be- <lb/>fore you begin to
        make the inciſion, and conſe- <lb/>quently during this time, the cornea preſerves its
        <lb/>convexity; whereas by uſing one inſtrument to punc- <lb/>ture, and others to dilate,
        the cornea immediately <pb n="163"/>
        <lb/>becomes flaccid, upon the iſſue of the aqueous hu- <lb/>mour, and renders the operation
        tedious and embar- <lb/>raſſing, as I myſelf have found by experience in one <lb/>patient,
        on whom I performed the inciſion of the <lb/>cornea with a pair of ſciſſars, as recommended
        by <lb/>Monſ. Daviel. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
