<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Spry: A Remarkable Case of a Morbid Eye</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Edward Spry</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Remarkable Case of a Morbid Eye: By Mr. Edward Spry, Surgeon, at Plymouth, in
              Devonshire</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Printed for L. Davis and C. Reymers, Printers to the Royal Society,
                  against Gray's-Inn Gate, In Holbourn.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1755</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">49</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">18-21</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW109907535</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1755.0005</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT49_0018">
    <body>
      <pb n="18"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">IV.</hi> A remarkable Caſe of a morbid Eye: <lb/>By Mr. <hi
          rend="roman">Edward Spry</hi>, Surgeon, at <hi rend="roman">Ply- <lb/>mouth</hi>, in <hi
          rend="roman">Devonſhire</hi>. </head>
      <dateline rend="size(0.8) align-right">
        <lb/>June 1751. </dateline>
      <p>
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="size(0.7) hanging">Read <date>Jan. 9. <lb/>1755. </date>
        </note><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>ARY the wife of Thomas Smal- <lb/>dridge, a mariner of
        Plymouth, <lb/>complained to me of a violent pain in her left eye, <lb/>and ſometimes of
        very acute pains in the temple of <lb/>the ſame ſide, with ſome defect in her ſight. She
        alſo <lb/>imagined that her eye was bigger than ordinary; but, <lb/>upon inſpection, it
        appeared no bigger than the other. <pb n="19"/>
        <lb/>The Cornea however became leſs tranſparent, and <lb/>the pupil greatly dilated: but
        though the pain of <lb/>her eye was ſo great, yet the blood-veſſels of the <lb/>conjunctive
        were no way enlarged, nor in the leaſt <lb/>redder than that and the ſclerotic were before;
        and, <lb/>from its whiteneſs, it appeared no more morbid than <lb/>the other. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As to the cure: After having bled her plentifully <lb/>in the arm, I applied a
        bliſtering-plaiſter to her <lb/>neck, and a gentle repellent collyrium to waſh her <lb/>eye
        oftem; purging her every third of fourth day, as <lb/>her ſtrength permitted, with a bolus
        of about eight <lb/>grains of calomel, given night and morning, with a <lb/>ſolutive
        draught, purſuing this method for a month <lb/>or ſix weeks; in which time ſhe was bled
        three <lb/>times more; and cautiouſly obſerved my directions <lb/>in her diet. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But as this method proved of no effect, ſhe con- <lb/>ſulted Doctor Martyne, an eminent
        phyſician of this <lb/>town, who gave all the aſſiſtance he could, but with <lb/>as little
        ſucceſs, her pain increaſing rather than di- <lb/>miniſhing; and as the pupil was now
        enlarged, and <lb/>the cornea became more opake, with great inflam- <lb/>mation of the
        conjunctive and ſelerotica, and an <lb/>apparent prominence of the whole eye, when every
        <lb/>thing hitherto failed, I tried two or three draſtic <lb/>purges; but theſe diſagreeing
        very much, I was <lb/>forced to return to my former method. I then cut <lb/>a ſeton in her
        neck, which run very much; but all <lb/>to no purpoſe, and ſhe became ſtill more miſerable.
        <lb/>The conjunctive became greatly inflamed, with an <lb/>everſion of the upper lid,
        attended with great pain. <lb/>I often made inciſions with my lancet upon this coat,
        <lb/>which bled plentifully, and gave her eaſe for a day <pb n="20"/>
        <lb/>or two, and even took eight ounces of blood from <lb/>the temporal artery. But the eye
        being greatly en- <lb/>larged, and of ſo terrible an appearance, after all <lb/>our
        endeavours for eight or ten months, I judged her <lb/>diſeaſe to be a Carcinoma, and
        therefore propoſed <lb/>cutting out the whole eye as the only remedy. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Several ſkilful ſurgeons were conſulted, and it <lb/>was agreed to defer the operation,
        and truſt to na- <lb/>ture; though ſhe was in that miſerable condition; <lb/>but at length
        her eye becoming much greater, and <lb/>her pain being increaſed, I reſolved upon the opera-
        <lb/>tion, leſt the bones of the orbit might become ca- <lb/>rious. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thus, having called in that eminent and famous <lb/>phyſician Doctor Huxham, with ſome
        of the moſt <lb/>ſkilful ſurgeons of this place, I performed the ope- <lb/>ration in the
        following manner; <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> The tumor was <lb/>ſo very large, and the
        upper lid ſo diſtended, that I <lb/>was obliged firſt to divide the orbicular muſcle at
        <lb/>the inner Canthus; and there began my inciſion <lb/>round the upper part of the tumor,
        for the more <lb/>convenient uſe of my knife. I had not cut deep <lb/>when a great quantity
        of pus, like lymph, flow'd out <lb/>upon me, with great force, like a fountain, and the
        <lb/>tumor ſubſided a good deal: but purſuing the ope- <lb/>ration, I found a large ciſt,
        which filled the whole <lb/>orbit behind the eye; and ſo part of the ciſt was left <lb/>to
        ſlough off with the dreſſings. The whole eye <lb/>being cut out, I filled the wound with
        lint, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> and <lb/>in three days I removed the dreſſings,
        together with <lb/>a great quantity of ſanies, which were daily renew'd <lb/>and the part of
        the ciſt, which was left behind, <lb/>ſlough'd off the ſecond day. The cure went on with <pb
          n="21"/>
        <lb/>ſucceſs, and, in a month from the operation, was <lb/>completed; and ſhe remains free
        from pain from <lb/>that time to this. </p>
      <postscript>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">P. S.</hi> I muſt mention what ſeemed remarkable <lb/>upon the
          caſe: when the woman was put to bed, we <lb/>came to obſerve the ſtate of the eye, which
          appear'd <lb/>a little bigger than the other; and having cut through <lb/>it, we found the
          humours very much confuſed: the <lb/>aqueous humour was not ſo clear as uſual, the
          <lb/>cryſtalline leſs ſolid and tranſparent, and the vitreous <lb/>almoſt reduced to a
          liquid ſtate. The ciſt was very <lb/>ſtrong and elaſtic, and had a cavity large enough to
          <lb/>contain a large hen's egg. </p>
      </postscript>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
