<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Baker: A Supplement to the Account of a Distempered Skin</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Henry Baker</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Supplement to the Account of a Distempered Skin, Published in the 424th Number
              of the Philosophical Transactions. By Mr. Henry Baker, F. R. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Printed for L. Davis and C. Reymers, Printers to the Royal Society,
                  against Gray's-Inn Gate, In Holbourn.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1755</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">49</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">21-24</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW109907535</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1755.0006</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT49_0021">
    <body>
      <pb n="21"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">V.</hi> A Supplement to the Account of a diſtem- <lb/>pered Skin,
        publiſhed in the 424th Num- <lb/>ber of the <hi rend="roman">Philoſophical
        Tranſactions</hi>. By <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="roman">Henry Baker</hi>, F. R. S. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="size(0.7) hanging">Read <date>Jan. 23, <lb/>1755. </date>
        </note><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N the year 1731, a lad, fourteen years <lb/>of age, was
        brought by his father <lb/>from Euſton-Hall, in Suffolk, and ſhewn to the <lb/>Royal
        Society, on account of his having a cuticular <lb/>diſorder, of a different kind from any
        mentioned in <lb/>the hiſtories of diſeaſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The extraordinary caſe of this boy was drawn up <lb/>by Mr. John Machin, at that time
        one of the Secre- <lb/>taries of the Royal Society, and was publiſhed in <lb/>the
        Philoſophical Tranſactions, N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 42<choice>
          <corr>.</corr>
          <sic/>
        </choice>
      </p>
      <pb n="22"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As more than four and twenty years are now paſt <lb/>ſince this account was given, and
        the perſon therein <lb/>mentioned is ſtill alive, and was lately ſhewn at Lon- <lb/>don, by
        the name of the Porcupine-man, with a <lb/>boy in the like condition, both which I ſaw, and
        <lb/>examined; ſome farther knowledge of him may not, <lb/>I hope, be thought undeſerving
        the attention of this <lb/>Royal Society. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>His name is Edward Lambert. He is now forty <lb/>years of age; a good-looking,
        well-ſhaped man, of a <lb/>florid countenance; and, when his body and hands <lb/>are
        covered, ſeems nothing different from other <lb/>people. But except his head and face, the
        palms of <lb/>his hands, and bottoms of his feet, his ſkin is all <lb/>over covered in the
        ſame manner as in the year 1731, <lb/>which therefore I ſhall trouble you with no other
        <lb/>deſcription of, than what you will find in Mr. Ma- <lb/>chin's account above-mentioned;
        only begging leave <lb/>to obſerve, that this covering ſeemed to me moſt <lb/>nearly to
        reſemble an innumerable company of warts, <lb/>of a dark-brown colour, and a cylindric
        figure, riſing <lb/>to a like height, and growing as cloſe as poſſible to <lb/>one another;
        but ſo ſtiff and elaſtic, that, when the <lb/>hand is drawn over them, they make a <choice>
          <corr>rustling</corr>
          <sic>ruſting</sic>
        </choice> noiſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When I ſaw this man, in the month of September <lb/>laſt, they were ſhedding off in
        ſeveral places, and <lb/>young ones, of a paler brown, ſucceeding in their <lb/>room, which,
        he told me, happens annually in ſome of <lb/>the autumn or winter months: and then he
        commonly <lb/>is let blood, to prevent ſome little ſickneſs, which he <lb/>elſe is ſubject
        to whilſt they are falling off. At other <lb/>times he is <unclear>in</unclear>commoded by
        them no otherwiſe, than <lb/>by the fretting out his linen, which, he ſays, they <pb n="23"/>
        <lb/>do very quickly: and when they come to their full <lb/>growth, being then in many
        places near an inch in <lb/>height, the preſſure of his clothes is troubleſome. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He has had the ſmall-pox, and been twice ſalivated, <lb/>in hopes of getting rid of
        this diſagreeable covering; <lb/>during which diſorders the warting came off, and his
        <lb/>ſkin appeared white and ſmooth, like that of other <lb/>peole; but, on his recovery,
        ſoon became as it was <lb/>before. His health at other times has been very <lb/>good during
        his whole life. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But the moſt extraordinary circumſtance of this <lb/>man's ſtory, and indeed the only
        reaſon of my giving <lb/>you this trouble, is, that he has had ſix children, all <lb/>with
        the ſame rugged covering as himſelf: the firſt <lb/>appearance whereof in them, as well as
        in him, came <lb/>on in about nine weeks after the birth. Only one <lb/>of them is now
        living, a very pretty boy, eight years <lb/>of age, whom I ſaw, and examined, with his
        father, <lb/>and who is exactly in the ſame condition, which it <lb/>is needleſs to repeat.
        He alſo has had the ſmall- <lb/>pox, and during that time was free from this diſ-
        <lb/>order. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It appears therefore paſt all doubt, that a race of <lb/>people may be propagated by
        this man, having ſuch <lb/>rugged coats or coverings as himſelf: and, if this <lb/>ſhould
        ever happen, and the accidental original be <lb/>forgotten, 'tis not improbable they might
        be deemed <lb/>a different ſpecies of mankind: a conſideration, which <lb/>would almoſt lead
        one to imagine, that if mankind <lb/>were all produced from one and the ſame ſtock, the
        <lb/>black ſkins of the negroes, and many other differ- <lb/>ences of the like kind, might
        poſſibly have been ori- <lb/>ginally owing to ſome ſuch accidental <sic>4.</sic>uſe. </p>
      <pb n="24"/>
      <figure>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Mr. George Edwards, Librarian of the College of <lb/>Phyſicians, having lately drawn,
          and etched on a <lb/>copper-plate, the hand of this boy, in ſuch manner, <lb/>as to ſhew
          the palm free from theſe excreſcencies, <lb/>and its other parts covered with them; and
          alſo a <lb/>company of the excreſcencies, as they appear where <lb/>largeſt; a copy of the
          ſaid plate, which I was fa- <lb/>voured with by him, is now preſented with this ac-
          <lb/>count. </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of the hand holding a twig, and a close-up of a dozen columnar
          excrescencies, on a separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <dateline rend="size(0.7) indent">
        <lb/>January 23, 1755. </dateline>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
