<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Mounsey and Baker: The Strange Effects of Some Effervescent
          Mixtures</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>James Mounsey</persName>
              <persName>Mr. Baker</persName>
            </author>
            <title>The Strange Effects of Some Effervescent Mixtures; In a Letter from Dr. James
              Mounsey, Physician of the Russian Army, and F. R. S. to Mr. Henry Baker, F. R. S.
              Communicated by Mr. Baker </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Printed for L. Davis and C. Reymers, Printers to the Royal Society,
                  against Gray's-Inn Gate, In Holbourn.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1757</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">50</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">19-22</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111032290</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1757.0003</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT50_0019">
    <body>
      <pb n="19"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">II.</hi> The ſtrange Effects of ſome efferveſcent <lb/>Mixtures; in a
        Letter from Dr. <hi rend="roman">James <lb/>Mounſey</hi>, Phyſician of the <hi rend="roman"
          >Ruſſian</hi> Army, <lb/>and F. R. S. to Mr. <hi rend="roman">Henry Baker</hi>, F. R. S.
        <lb/>Communicated by Mr. <hi rend="roman">Baker</hi>. </head>
      <dateline rend="size(0.8) space align-right">
        <lb/>Moſcow, Sept. 20th, 1756. </dateline>
      <p>
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="size(0.7) hanging">Read <date>Jan. 20, <lb/>1757. </date>
        </note><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>R. Butler, a paper-ſtainer, trying to <lb/>make ſome
        diſcoveries for the bet- <lb/>ter fixing of colours, was put in great danger of his
        <lb/>life by the following experiments: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having put into one gallipot a quarter of an ounce <lb/>of verdegris, and into another
        pot two leaves of falſe- <lb/>gold leaf, to each he poured about a ſpoonful of
        <lb/>aqua-fortis. They began immediately to ferment, <lb/>eſpecially the gold-leaf. He was
        very aſſiduous in <lb/>ſtirring them, to make the ſolution perfect. Having <lb/>nothing elſe
        at hand, he did this with a pair of ſmall <lb/>ſciſſars, at arm's length, carefully turning
        away his <lb/>face, to prevent the fumes from entering his lungs. <lb/>He was called away,
        about other buſineſs, before he <lb/>had quite ended his proceſs; and ſoon after waſhed
        <lb/>and ſhifted himſelf: but had ſcarce finiſhed before <lb/>he felt a burning pain in the
        ring-finger of his right <lb/>hand, which he imputed to his having inadvertently
        <lb/>touched the aqua-fortis. This increaſed every mo- <lb/>ment, and affected the whole
        hand with burning pain <lb/>and ſwelling, which very ſoon ſubſided: but then it <lb/>flew
        into the left hand, and, a few minutes afterwards, <lb/>into the inſides of his legs, as if
        ſcalding water had <pb n="20"/>
        <lb/>been thrown on them. His ſtockings being imme- <lb/>diately pulled off, there appeared
        a great many red <lb/>ſpots, as large as ſix-pences, ſomething raiſed above <lb/>the ſkin,
        and all covered with very ſmall bliſters. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In about two hours after the accident, I firſt ſaw <lb/>him: he was very uneaſy,
        complaining of pain, and <lb/>great anxiety, at the pit of the ſtomach, as if a burn-
        <lb/>ing hot iron was laid on it: ſo he expreſſed himſelf. <lb/>His pulſe was regular, but
        ſlower and weaker than <lb/>natural: he had a nauſea, and complained of a very <lb/>coppery
        ſmell and taſte. I ordered ſome alcaline <lb/>volatile medicines, and to drink ſmall
        ſack-whey. <lb/>He vomited once, and had four or five ſtools, and <lb/>then his ſtomach grew
        eaſy. But the ſcene ſoon <lb/>began again with lancing pain in the left eye. He
        <lb/>continued the ſame medicines, drank plentifully of <lb/>the whey, and was kept in a
        breathing ſweat, by <lb/>which he found ſome eaſe at night: but whenever <lb/>the ſweating
        leſſened, the burning pains returned in <lb/>broad flakes, changing from one part of the
        body to <lb/>the other; ſometimes with ſhootings in his eye, and <lb/>ſometimes along the
        penis, but he had no heat of <lb/>urine. His pulſe continued regular, but weak; and <lb/>in
        ſeveral places of his body ſuch kind of ſpots ſtruck <lb/>out as thoſe on his legs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Monday, the third day, in the morning, after <lb/>ſleeping well, his pulſe was ſomewhat
        raiſed, and he <lb/>continued eaſy till about eleven o'clock, when the <lb/>burning pains
        returned, ſhooting from place to place; <lb/>but always ſo ſuperficial, that he could not
        diſtinguiſh <lb/>whether it was in or under the ſkin. Rubbing the <lb/>part affected with
        one's hand gave eaſe: but when <lb/>the ſweating went off, and the burnings and ſhoot- <pb
          n="21"/>
        <lb/>ings became inſufferable, I always put him into a <lb/>bath of hot water, with ſome
        wood aſhes, kept <lb/>ready in the room; which gave him great relief. <lb/>This afternoon he
        felt violent burning pain in his <lb/>great toes, and ſometimes in his left hand, with
        <lb/>ſhootings up to the ſhoulder. Once he cried out, <lb/>in great pain, that his ſhoulder
        was burſt; for the <lb/>felt ſomething fly out with a ſort of exploſion; but, <lb/>examining
        the part, I found nothing particular. He <lb/>obſerved, when the flaky burnings began, they
        were <lb/>as if they kindled from a point, and flaſhed like <lb/>lightning, as he termed it.
        He was very often tor- <lb/>mented with ſuch pains on the pit of the ſtomach; <lb/>and this
        evening had ſhootings thro' the back, with <lb/>a pain in the belly. He complained of a
        ſtrong ſul- <lb/>phurous ſmell, which, he ſaid, was like to ſuffocate <lb/>him; tho' his
        breathing ſeemed eaſy, and his lungs <lb/>no way affected. In the night he was ſeized with
        <lb/>great pain about the heart, and cried out violently, <lb/>that his heart was on fire:
        but after taking a doſe of <lb/>nervous medicines, and being put into the bath, he <lb/>was
        ſoon freed from this, and paſſed the reſt of the <lb/>night tolerably well. At the time of
        ſuch violent <lb/>attacks the pulſe continued regular, but ſtill ſlower <lb/>and ſofter than
        uſual. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Tueſday. He complained moſt of his toes, and <lb/>now and then burning pains in the
        forehead. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Wedneſday. This whole day it continued moſt <lb/>in the toes of the left foot; but in
        the evening the <lb/>pain on the ſtomach returned, which lanced to the <lb/>left ſide, with
        dartings inwardly. He became ſo un- <lb/>eaſy and reſtleſs, that I was obliged to add ſome
        opium <lb/>to the other medicines; which anſwered very well. </p>
      <pb n="22"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thurſday. The pains kept moſt in the toes of <lb/>the left foot. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Friday. Nothing particular, except his feeling, <lb/>with ſharp pain, a ſpark (as he
        called it) fly out of <lb/>his right cheek, in the ſame way, he ſaid, as that, <lb/>which
        burſt on his ſhoulder, but much leſs. He <lb/>perceived no pain in that part before this,
        nor any <lb/>thing after, beſides a ſoreneſs, which laſted for ſome <lb/>days. Hitherto he
        had been kept in a continual <lb/>ſweat: his appetite was greater than his allowance;
        <lb/>his digeſtion good; and his reſt indifferent. From <lb/>this time he was not attacked
        by any violent ſym- <lb/>ptoms; and could be quiet, tho' he did not ſweat. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On Sunday he began to get out of bed; but was <lb/>often ſeized with glowing pains,
        ſuddenly affecting <lb/>different parts of the body; which ſeldom continued <lb/>an hour in
        one part, but ſhifted from place to place: <lb/>theſe he was troubled with, in a leſs
        degree, even <lb/>long after he went abroad. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By care and watchfulneſs the violence of the ſym- <lb/>ptoms were kept under; and, by
        the uſe of antidotes <lb/>for poiſons of the nature of what he received this <lb/>from, the
        diſeaſe was overcome, and the patient <lb/>recovered his perfect health and ſtrength. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
