<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Warner: A Remarkable Instance of Four Rough Stones, That Were
          Discovered in an Human Urinary Bladder</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Joseph Warner</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A Remarkable Instance of Four Rough Stones, That Were Discovered in an Human
              Urinary Bladder, Contrary to the Received Opinion; And Successfully Extracted by the
              Lateral Method of Cutting for the Stone. By Mr. Joseph Warner, F. R. S. and Surgeon to
              Guy's-Hospital</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Printed for L. Davis and C. Reymers, Printers to the Royal Society,
                  against Gray's-Inn Gate, In Holbourn.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1757</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">50</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">579-585</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111032290</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1757.0077</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT50_0579">
    <body>
      <pb n="579"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">LXXVI.</hi> A remarkable Inſtance of Four <lb/>rough Stones, that were
        diſcovered in an <lb/>human urinary Bladder, contrary to the <lb/>received Opinion; and
        ſucceſsfully extract- <lb/>ed by the lateral Method of Cutting for <lb/>the Stone. By Mr.
          <hi rend="roman">Joſeph Warner</hi>, F. <lb/>R. S. and Surgeon to <hi rend="roman"
          >Guy's-Hoſpital</hi>. </head>
      <div>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/>
          <note place="inset" rend="size(0.7) hanging">Read <date>Feb. 23. <lb/>1758. </date>
          </note><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE favourable reception thoſe few <lb/>papers have met with
          from the <lb/>Royal Society, which I have done myſelf the ho- <lb/>nour of addreſſing to
          them, encourages me to take <lb/>the liberty of offering the following account to their
          <lb/>conſideration: and I am the more immediately in- <lb/>duced to ſubmit this paper to
          their peruſal, as the <lb/>fact hereafter related may poſſibly be not eſteemed a
          <lb/>matter of mere curioſity; ſince it is probable, that <lb/>the inferences deduced from
          the hiſtory of the ſub- <lb/>ſequent caſe, when attended to, may prove of the
          <lb/>greateſt conſequence to the future eaſe and welfare <lb/>of the patient, as well as
          be a means of preventing <lb/>the operator from falling into ſuch errors, as cannot
          <lb/>fail of drawing an imputation upon his character, in <lb/>the practice of one of the
          moſt capital and difficult <lb/>undertakings in his profeſſion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is a maxim laid down by the moſt judicious <lb/>and beſt received writers upon
          operations in ſurgery, <lb/>that when the ſurface of a ſtone, which has been
          <lb/>extracted from the bladder, appears to be totally <lb/>rough, it amounts to a proof
          of its having been <pb n="580"/>
          <lb/>there alone. But notwithſtanding I admit it is from <lb/>experience found, that the
          obſervation is in general <lb/>well grounded, it may nevertheleſs appear, from the
          <lb/>following caſe, that this rule is not unexceptionable: <lb/>for which reaſon perhaps
          it may be thought right, <lb/>that we ſhould not be determined from circumſtances
          <lb/>only; but, on the contrary, that it is neceſſary for <lb/>every ſurgeon to take ſuch
          methods during the opera- <lb/>tion, as will enable him to judge with that degree of
          <lb/>certainty, without which he cannot be enabled to <lb/>do ſo. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The methods I would recommend are theſe: That <lb/>after the extraction of a ſtone
          from the bladder, tho' <lb/>the whole of its ſurface be rough, the operator ſhould
          <lb/>nevertheleſs introduce the forefinger of his left or <lb/>right hand thro' the wound
          into the cavity of the <lb/>bladder; by which means, if the ſubject be under <lb/>twelve
          years of age, he will be enabled to come in <lb/>contact with every internal part of the
          bladder with <lb/>his finger: but if the ſubject be an adult, and of a <lb/>corpulent
          habit of body, the finger, under theſe cir- <lb/>cumſtances, not being found to be
          ſufficiently long <lb/>for the purpoſe, he muſt have recourſe to a female <lb/>catheter,
          or ſome other inſtrument that is nearly <lb/>ſtrait, quite ſmooth and poliſhed, and of
          about nine <lb/>or ten inches long; which will ſerve the purpoſe <lb/>equally well, if of
          a proper form and thickneſs. <lb/>This is the method I have made uſe of upon the <lb/>like
          occaſions of late years, without giving any great <lb/>degree of pain to the patient, or
          conſiderably retard- <lb/>ing the operation. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Since I have had the opportunity of making the <lb/>following obſervation, as well as
          a prior obſerva- <pb n="581"/>
          <lb/>tion ſomething ſimilar to this, where two rough <lb/>ſtones were extracted by me a
          few years ago from a <lb/>young man's bladder of 15 years of age, I cannot <lb/>help
          ſuſpecting, that there may have been inſtances <lb/>of one or more ſtones being left
          behind in the blad- <lb/>der at the time of operating, merely from the opera- <lb/>tor's
          putting too great a confidence in this general <lb/>rule. Which ſuſpicion I am led into
          from having <lb/>known people, who have undergone the operation <lb/>of cutting for the
          ſtone, relapſe into the like diſor- <lb/>der in a ſhort time after the healing of their
          wounds, <lb/>attended with ſuch ſymptoms, as have obliged them <lb/>to ſubmit to a ſecond
          operation; when the ſtone, <lb/>upon being extracted, has appeared of ſo conſide-
          <lb/>rable a ſize, as to make it ſuſpicious, that this ſtone <lb/>muſt probably have been
          of a much longer growth, <lb/>than the ſhort time betwixt the two operations could
          <lb/>admit of. The maxim laid down to us by authors, <lb/>of a ſmooth and poliſhed ſtone
          in the bladder being <lb/>never there alone, but always accompanied with one <lb/>or more
          ſtones of the ſame kind, I know no excep- <lb/>tion to. But if this phænomenon ſhould ever
          occur, <lb/>the ſtrict obſervance of that rule (delivered to us by <lb/>judicious writers
          in ſurgery) of always ſearching the <lb/>bladder under the like appearances, on
          preſumption <lb/>of one or more ſtones being left behind, cannot be <lb/>attended with any
          future miſchief to the patient, <lb/>when carefully executed by the methods recom-
          <lb/>mended above, and undoubtedly ſhould always be <lb/>ſtrictly attended to. The ſmooth
          and poliſhed ap- <lb/>pearances of the ſurfaces of human <hi rend="italic">calculi</hi>
          are uni- <lb/>verſally ſuppoſed to ariſe from their rubbing one <lb/>againſt the other;
          which may with reaſon be ſup- <pb n="582"/>
          <lb/>poſed to be the caſe: but I confeſs this inference is <lb/>not ſatisfactory to me;
          ſince it is probable, if this <lb/>was the ſole cauſe of their ſmoothneſs, the ſame ef-
          <lb/>fect would probably be always produced, when at- <lb/>tended with the ſame degree of
          friction. But as this <lb/>may be conſidered as a matter of mere ſpeculation, <lb/>I refer
          the deciſion of this point to thoſe of ſuperior <lb/>abilities. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>CASE. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Mr. William Woodhams, a gentleman farmer, of <lb/>a corpulent habit of body, in the
          46th year of his <lb/>age, now living in the pariſh of Udimore, within <lb/>three miles of
          Rye in Suſſex, was attacked about <lb/>eight years ago with ſevere complaints in his
          loins, <lb/>accompanied with an incapacity of voiding his urine <lb/>without the
          aſſiſtance of proper medicines, which <lb/>were adminiſtered to him by a neighbouring
          apothe- <lb/>cary for that purpoſe. Theſe medicines had the de- <lb/>ſired effect: they
          promoted a ſecretion, and an eva- <lb/>cuation of urine; which appeared to be loaded with
          <lb/>a conſiderable quantity of gravelly particles mixed <lb/>with a <hi rend="italic"
            >mucus</hi> of a whitiſh colour. In the ſpace of <lb/>three weeks he had perfectly
          recovered from this at- <lb/>tack, and continued well for near five years after-
          <lb/>wards, without any return of his complaint, except <lb/>when he rode hard on
          horſeback, or drank more <lb/>freely of ſtrong liquors than uſual. At the expira-
          <lb/>tion of five years he was ſeized with an acute fever, <lb/>of which he recovered in a
          few weeks. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Very ſoon after his recovery from this illneſs, he <lb/>began to complain of
          exceſſive pain in voiding his <lb/>urine, or upon going to ſtool; which ſymptoms <pb
            n="583"/>
          <lb/>were ſo greatly increaſed for many months before he<choice>
            <corr> </corr>
            <sic>-</sic>
          </choice>
          <lb/>ſubmitted to the operation, as to quite diſable him <lb/>from riding, from walking,
          or from uſing any kind <lb/>of exerciſe. His urine, of late, was continually and
          <lb/>involuntarily flowing from him in ſmall quantities. <lb/>He complained of great pain
          and ſoreneſs in his fun- <lb/>dament, attended with a <hi rend="italic">teneſmus</hi>.
          This account he <lb/>delivered to me on the ſecond day after the operation; <lb/>and at
          the ſame time he very feelingly told me, that <lb/>he had enjoyed but very few and ſhort
          intervals of <lb/>eaſe for the three laſt years, till ſince the operation. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On the 30th of January 1758, I cut him, at his <lb/>own houſe in Suſſex, having firſt
          prepared him <lb/>for the operation in the manner, that is uſual upon <lb/>the like
          occaſion. In the operation, I extracted <lb/>the four ſtones, which I now have the honour
          of <lb/>laying before the Royal Society. The whole ſur- <lb/>faces of theſe ſtones appear
          to be rough, not having <lb/>the leaſt marks of ever having rubbed againſt each <lb/>other
          during their confinement in the bladder: but <lb/>yet I conjecture this muſt frequently
          have been the <lb/>caſe, as there was no difficulty in embracing theſe <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">calculi</hi> with the forceps: for had they been con- <lb/>tained in
          different cells or pouches in the bladder, <lb/>which ſometimes have been obſerved from
          diſſections, <lb/>this circumſtances would, in all probability, have ren- <lb/>dered it
          impracticable for me to have ſo immediately <lb/>got at them, if at all. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The forceps was introduced only three times into <lb/>the bladder for effecting the
          extraction of the three <lb/>firſt ſtones, and only twice for the extraction of the
          <lb/>fourth ſtone. Beſides theſe four ſtones <figure>
            <figDesc>An illustration of the stones on a separate fold-out page, with the caption
              "This plate is an exact repreſentation of the sizes and external appearances of the
              four rough stones deſcribed in the preceeding paper". </figDesc>
          </figure>, which I have <lb/>preſented to the Society for their inſpection, I thought <pb
            n="584"/>
          <lb/>it not improper to produce, at the ſame time, ſome <lb/>other human <hi rend="italic"
            >calculi</hi>, for their further ſatisfaction, <lb/>each of which was found ſingle in
          the urinary blad- <lb/>ders of different ſubjects. The ſurfaces of theſe ſtones <lb/>may
          be obſerved to be much ſmoother than the ſur- <lb/>face of either of the four ſtones, that
          were extracted <lb/>from Mr. Woodhams's bladder in the operation I <lb/>have juſt now
          recited; and therefore it was more <lb/>reaſonable to expect to find each of theſe ſtones
          ac- <lb/>companied with one or more ſtones in the ſame <lb/>bladder (according to the
          received opinion), than it <lb/>was to find more ſtones than one in the caſe of Mr.
          <lb/>Woodhams's, which has given riſe to theſe obſerva- <lb/>tions. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But as the fact before us does of itſelf ſhew the <lb/>impropriety and danger of
          determining from the ſur- <lb/>faces of ſuch extraneous bodies, perhaps it may be
          <lb/>thought needleſs to enlarge upon this ſubject, to <lb/>ſtrengthen thoſe precautions
          ſo reaſonable to be ob- <lb/>ſerved in this operation. However, as I have al- <lb/>ready
          taken notice of the ſmooth and poliſhed ap- <lb/>pearances of the ſurfaces of ſuch ſtones,
          as are pro- <lb/>bably never found ſingle in the bladder; I have pro- <lb/>duced two
          ſtones of this kind, that were extracted <lb/>from the ſame bladder, to ſhew, that theſe
          ſtones <lb/>do no more reſemble thoſe ſtones of Mr. Wood- <lb/>hams's, than a piece of
          poliſhed marble can be ſaid <lb/>to reſemble a rough block of the ſame ſpecies. </p>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indentall hanging space">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">P. S.</hi> I am informed, by a letter from Suſſex, <lb/>dated the
            18th inſtant, that Mr. Woodhams is <lb/>perfectly well in health; that the whole of his
            <lb/>urine had paſſed through the urethra for the <pb n="585"/>
            <lb/>laſt five or ſix days; and that his wound will, <lb/>in all probability, be ſoon
            healed. </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <dateline rend="size(0.8) indent space">
        <lb/>Hatton-Garden, <lb/>February 22. 1758. </dateline>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <signed rend="size(1.2) align-right space">
        <lb/>Joſeph Warner. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
