<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Willis and Dashwood: An Account of an Extraordinary Case of a Lady,
          Who Swallowed Euphorbium</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Dr. Willis</persName>
              <persName>Francis Dashwood</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of an Extraordinary Case of a Lady, Who Swallowed Euphorbium. By Dr.
              Willis, of Lincoln: Communicated by Sir Francis Dashwood, Bart</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Printed for L. Davis and C. Reymers, Printers to the Royal Society,
                  against Gray's-Inn Gate, In Holbourn.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1759</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">51</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">662-669</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110115007</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1759.0065</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT51_0662">
    <body>
      <pb n="662"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">LXIII.</hi> An Account of an extraordinary Caſe <lb/>of a Lady, who
        ſwallowed Euphorbium. <lb/>By Dr. <hi rend="roman">Willis</hi>, of <hi rend="roman"
          >Lincoln</hi>: Communicated <lb/>by <hi rend="roman">Sir Francis Daſhwood</hi>, Bart. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="size(0.7) hanging">Read <date>Apr. 24, <lb/>1760. </date>
        </note><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N December 1758, Mrs. Willis of <lb/>Lincoln fell into a ſlow
        fever, occa- <lb/>ſioned by too ſmall a diſcharge of the lochia after <pb n="663"/>
        <lb/>lying-in, and a redundancy of milk, the conſequence <lb/>of her not ſuckling her child.
        On the 18th day <lb/>after her delivery, by the miſtake of her nurſe, ſhe <lb/>took, inſtead
        of a draught that was ordered for her, <lb/>two ounces of the tincture of euphorbium <note
          n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* The tincture was thus made, </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>℞ <hi rend="italic">Gum. Euphorb.</hi> ʒij. <hi rend="italic">Spt. Vin.
              rectif.</hi> ℥ij. <hi rend="italic">Sol. add. Camph.</hi> ʒij. <lb/>The camphor was
            ordered to weaken the cauſtic quality of the <lb/>tincture, which being applied to a
            horſe's leg without the camphor <lb/>had made a blemiſh. </p>
        </note>. The <lb/>ſhocking ſymptoms, which immediately enſued, vio- <lb/>lent ſuffocation,
        and an intolerable burning pain in <lb/>the mouth, throat, and ſtomach, ſoon diſcovered
        <lb/>the horrible miſtake. I was in the room in about <lb/>four or five minutes after the
        accident happened, <lb/>unappriſed of the nature of it, and therefore the <lb/>more ſhocked,
        when I found every body in tears of <lb/>deſpair, offering at no means of relief, as they
        had <lb/>no hopes of ſucceſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As ſoon as I was made acquainted with what had <lb/>happened, it occurred to me, that
        warm water and <lb/>oil were the likelieſt things to correct and expel the <lb/>poiſon. I
        imagined a large quantity of warm water <lb/>might probably make the patient vomit, and in
        ſome <lb/>meaſure help to diſcharge the cauſtic tincture. I was <lb/>ſure the water would at
        the ſame time mitigate its <lb/>violence, by diluting it, and by precipitating the acrid
        <lb/>gum from the ſpirit, whereby it would neceſſarily be <lb/>hindered from touching the
        membranes of the ſto- <lb/>mach and bowels in ſo many points, and from pene- <lb/>trating
        into their ſubſtance. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There was happily a large tea-kettle of water on <lb/>the fire, of which, being firſt
        qualified with a proper <pb n="664"/>
        <lb/>quantity of cold water, I immediately gave the pa- <lb/>tient a baſin lukewarm, and
        repeated it as faſt as poſ- <lb/>ſible, conjuring her to uſe her utmoſt reſolution to
        <lb/>ſwallow; which ſhe certainly did in a moſt ſurpriſing <lb/>manner. After the third
        baſin, ſhe vomited very <lb/>freely: what was brought up ſmelt very ſtrong of the
        <lb/>camphor, and ſeemed to contain a good deal of the <lb/>tincture, with the gum ſeparated
        from the ſpirit. <lb/>She ſtill drank on, but complained of exceſſive <lb/>burning and
        torture in her ſtomach, crying out con- <lb/>tinually, ſhe was burnt to death. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I had then recourſe to oil between whiles, in the <lb/>quantity of two or three ounces
        at a time; and <lb/>drenched her plentifully ſometimes with oil and <lb/>ſometimes with
        water. She vomited very copiouſly, <lb/>and I repeated the oil and water interchangeably,
        till <lb/>ſhe had taken, as well as I could gueſs by the veſ- <lb/>ſels, two gallons of
        water and a flaſk of oil in a very <lb/>ſhort time <note n="†" place="bottom"
          rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† Dr. Sydenham, being called to a man, who had taken <hi rend="italic">Mercur.
              <lb/>ſublim. corroſ.</hi> about an hour before the doctor ſaw him, the poiſon
            <lb/>having affected his lips, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> only ordered water to be
            taken in a <lb/>large quantity, and thrown up copiouſly in gliſters. But as the
            <lb/>corroſive ſublimate of mercury is to be conſidered as a poiſon, whoſe <lb/>cauſtic
            acrimony conſiſts in a ſaline principle, and water is the pro- <lb/>per ſolvent,
            diluent, and vehicle of all ſaline ſubſtances, the pro- <lb/>priety of Sydenham's
            ordering water alone is ſufficiently apparent. <lb/>Poiſons of a ſaline nature being
            diſſolved in the fluids of the ſtomach <lb/>and inteſtines, do not confine their ravages
            to theſe parts only, but <lb/>are apt to enter the abſorbent veſſels, and inſinuate
            themſelves into <lb/>the road of the circulation. Water is here a good antidote, as it
            di- <lb/>lutes ſuch ſubſtances, waſhes them off the ſenſible membranes, de- <lb/>ſtroys
            their acrimony, and readily paſſing through all ſorts of canals, <pb n="665"
              type="footnote"/>
            <lb/>ſoon carries them out of the body. But the caſe is otherwiſe with <lb/>gummy
            reſinous poiſons, ſuch as euphorbium. Theſe being indiſ- <lb/>ſoluble in water, are not
            ſo apt to enter the abſorbent veſſels, and paſs <lb/>into the blood, but, by their
            acrimony, ſhut up the orifcies of thoſe <lb/>canals, and preclude a paſſage. Therefore
            oil here ſhould be called <lb/>in to the aſſiſtance of water. For the cauſtic reſinous
            ſubſtance of <lb/>euphorbium being precipitated or ſeparated from the ſpirit, and
            <lb/>formed into clots by the water, would ſtill be apt to ſtick to the <lb/>tender
            nervous membranes of the ſtomach and bowels, and by its <lb/>intolerable acrimony cauſe
            violent vellications, inflammations, and <lb/>gangrene. But the oil contributes greatly
            to prevent theſe fatal ef- <lb/>fects, by ſheathing the corroſive acrimony of the
            poiſon, prevent- <lb/>ing its adheſion to the delicate lining membranes of theſe firſt
            paſ- <lb/>ſages, and defending them from the violence of its attacks; while <lb/>at the
            ſame time it promotes the diſcharge of their contents. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Theſe qualities of oil alſo render it very ſerviceable in other <lb/>ſpecies of
            poiſon. </p>
        </note>. </p>
      <pb n="665"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Imagining the deleterious draught had not had ſuf- <lb/>ficient time to bring on any
        violent inflammation or <lb/>excoriation, or to make its way into the blood, vo- <lb/>miting
        and purging, with plenty of diluents and <lb/>ſheathing ſubſtances, ſeemed the likelieſt
        means to <lb/>ſave the patient, if any thing could be hoped to ſuc- <lb/>ceed in ſo perilous
        a ſituation. I therefore ordered a <lb/>mild but operative emetic of <hi rend="italic">Pulv.
          Rad. Ipecacuan.</hi>
        <lb/>and a mixture with <hi rend="italic">Sperm. Ceti</hi> and oil to be taken
        <lb/>occaſionally; ſtill following up the patient with oil <lb/>and water. I had reaſon to
        except the emetic would <lb/>alſo purge as well as vomit, and not only clear the
        <lb/>ſtomach of the remains of the poiſonous draught, but <lb/>likewiſe carry downwards what
        portion of it might <lb/>have paſſed through the pylorus by the contraction <lb/>and
        agitation of the ventricle on the preceding vomit- <lb/>ing. The apothecary demurred at the
        emetic, and <pb n="666"/>
        <lb/>objected the danger of its aggravating the effects of <lb/>the poiſon by its ſtimulus
        and irritation. Though I <lb/>was not in the leaſt convinced by the objection, yet,
        <lb/>from an apprehenſion of the reflections, which might <lb/>probably be made after the
        tragical ſcene, which <lb/>ſeemd to be inevitable, I was ſtaggered in my pro- <lb/>ceeding,
        and wiſhed the objection had not been ſtart- <lb/>ed. My brother, obſerving my uneaſineſs,
        aſked <lb/>me, if ſhe ſhould ſend for Dr. Dymock. I gladly <lb/>accepted this offer, as it
        rid me of my perplexity, and <lb/>would give ſatisfaction to all concerned to have had
        <lb/>the beſt advice. In the mean time, I plied the pa- <lb/>tient with oil and water
        alternately, with which ſhe <lb/>vomited; but ſtill grievouſly complained of a burn-
        <lb/>ing heat in the ſtomach and bowels. Her breath and <lb/>all ſhe vomited ſmelt very
        ſtrong of the camphor. <lb/>Her pulſe was moderate, and not much quickened. <lb/>I had now
        given her about a gallon more of water, <lb/>and half a flaſk more of oil, when Dr. Dymock
        ar- <lb/>rived. Upon informing him of all the particulars of <lb/>the caſe, he, without
        heſitation, ordered an emetic <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Vin. Ipecacuan.</hi> ℥. which was
        immediately given: <lb/>but the patient complained more and more of an in- <lb/>ward burning
        heat, which made it neceſſary to ſup- <lb/>ply her with more water before the emetic oper-
        <lb/>ated. It had however in a ſhort time the deſired ef- <lb/>fect, and operated
        plentifully both by vomit and <lb/>ſtool, eſpecially the latter way. The ſtools, which
        <lb/>continued to be diſcharged for near an hour, without <lb/>any griping pain, very
        manifeſtly diſcovered both <lb/>camphor and oil being mixed with them. The <lb/>purging now
        began gradually to abate, and ſoon after <lb/>the burning heat in the region of the ſtomach
        became <pb n="667"/>
        <lb/>more tolerable, and inſenſibly grew better, the cam- <lb/>phor being no longer
        perceptible in the breath or <lb/>evacuations. Her drink now was water with the
        <lb/>addition of a little milk. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The patient's ſpirits, which, by means of the great <lb/>irritation and feveriſh tumult
        the cauſtic tincture had <lb/>excited, kept up ſurpriſingly, now began to fail her, <lb/>and
        ſhe was with difficulty got into bed: where, after <lb/>complaining for a ſhort time only of
        a ſoreneſs in <lb/>the firſt paſſages, ſhe lay ſweating profuſely for four <lb/>hours in a
        very low deſponding condition. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A gentle opiate was exhibited, which took effect; <lb/>and after a ſound ſleep of five
        hours the patient <lb/>waked very eaſy, took ſome of the ſperma ceti mix- <lb/>ture, and had
        another ſleep of three hours. She <lb/>now found herſelf free from all her complaints; the
        <lb/>previous ſlow fever, as well as the effects of the <lb/>poiſonous tincture, being
        entirely carried off. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is remarkable, that the patient found herſelf, <lb/>for four days ſucceſſively, in
        ſo happy a ſtate of eaſe <lb/>and tranquillity, as ſhe had never before experienced,
        <lb/>and to this day enjoys a perfect ſtate of health. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thus have I laid before you the true hiſtory of <lb/>this caſe; for the ſimple relation
        of which I flatter <lb/>myſelf I need make no apology, when I reflect, <lb/>that the
        practice of phyſic muſt derive much greater <lb/>advantages from plain hiſtories of matter
        of fact, and <lb/>juſt deductions drawn from them, than from the <lb/>moſt ingenious
        hypotheſes and ſpeculative theories. <lb/>Theſe were of baneful influence to the progreſs of
        <lb/>true knowledge, till your illuſtrious Society taught the <lb/>world the true method of
        inveſtigating the laws of <pb n="668"/>
        <lb/>nature, by obſervation of fact, experiment, and ra- <lb/>tional deduction. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The following obſervations, which this caſe natu- <lb/>rally ſuggeſts, ſeem to deſerve
        our attention. </p>
      <p rend="space">
        <list>
          <item rend="indent">
            <lb/>1<hi rend="italic">ſt</hi>, That in any ſimilar accidents of ſwallowing
            <lb/>corroſive poiſonous ſubſtances, a quick and reſolute <lb/>adminiſtration of theſe
            ſimple bodies, water and oil, <lb/>in a large quantity, ſeems to be the moſt effectual
            <lb/>method of preventing any bad conſequences, and far <lb/>preferable to the numerous
            boaſted antidotes, which <lb/>have been handed down to us. </item>
          <item rend="indent">
            <lb/>2<hi rend="italic">dly</hi>, That an emetic may be more ſafely and <lb/>effectually
            adminiſtered, and its operation waited for, <lb/>after the acrimony of the poiſon hath
            been ſheathed <lb/>and blunted, and the coats of the ſtomach defended <lb/>from its
            attacks, by a liberal uſe of water and oil, <lb/>than immediately after it is ſwallowed. </item>
          <item rend="indent">
            <lb/>3<hi rend="italic">dly</hi>, That as the ſlow fever and redundancy of <lb/>milk, as
            well as the poiſon, were carried off by the <lb/>copious diſcharge excited in the eaſy
            manner above- <lb/>mentioned; might we not often hope for ſucceſs in <lb/>fevers
            occaſioned by ſimilar cauſes, plenitude and <lb/>obſtruction, from plentiful
            evacuations, brought on <lb/>after the ſame manner, by ſimple, diluent, and ſheath-
            <lb/>ing medicines? </item>
          <item rend="indent">
            <lb/>4<hi rend="italic">thly</hi>, The camphor was undoubtedly of great <lb/>ſervice in
            curbing the deſtructive effects of the <lb/>euphorbium, by blunting its acrimony, and
            ſoothing <lb/>the nerves into an inſenſibility of irritation, and con- <lb/>ſequently an
            incapacity of ſpaſmodic affections. I <lb/>have tried the <hi rend="italic">tinct.
              euphorb. cum camphorâ</hi> on a <pb n="669"/>
            <lb/>horſe's leg ſeveral times, and find it not near ſo cauſtic <lb/>as without the
            camphor. And it is well known how <lb/>much camphor involves the ſpicula, corrects the
            acri- <lb/>mony, and mitigates the effects of cantharides, ſac- <lb/>charum Saturni, and
            rough, mercurial, and anti- <lb/>monial preparations. </item>
          <item rend="indent">
            <lb/>5<hi rend="italic">thly</hi>, To water and oil therefore we may juſtly <lb/>add
            camphor as a powerful corrector and expeller of <lb/>poiſons in general. This it
            probably effectuates, 1ſt, <lb/>by blunting the acrimony; 2dly, by calming the
            <lb/>nervous ſyſtem, and ſecuring it from ſpaſmodic tu- <lb/>mult and convulſion, which
            may be a conſequence <lb/>of its ſheathing quality; 3dly, by its extreme ſub- <lb/>tilty
            and volatility, whereby it freely penetrates the <lb/>ſmalleſt receſſes of the body, and
            powerfully pro- <lb/>motes a diaphoreſis. Some late inſtances of the ef- <lb/>fects of
            camphor in poiſonous caſes greatly confirm <lb/>this account. </item>
        </list>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Theſe three ſimple bodies then, water, oil, and <lb/>camphor, challenge the firſt place
        among the anti- <lb/>dotes hitherto diſcovered, both for internal and ex- <lb/>ternal uſe,
        and are much more to be depended upon <lb/>than any of the elaborate compoſitions calculated
        for <lb/>this purpoſe by the ancients, as the <hi rend="italic">Theriac. Androm.
          <lb/>Mithridat. Conf. Paulin. &amp;c.</hi>
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
