<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Nicholls: Observations concerning the Body of His Late Majesty</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Frank Nicholls</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Observations concerning the Body of His Late Majesty, October 26, 1760, by Frank
              Nicholls, M. D. F. R. S. Physician to His Late Majesty </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Printed for L. Davis and C. Reymers, Printers to the Royal Society,
                  against Gray's-Inn Gate, In Holbourn.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1761</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">52</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">265-275</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110357793</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1761.0052</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT52_0265">
    <body>
      <pb n="265"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">LI.</hi> Obſervations concerning the Body of his <lb/>late Majeſty,
          <date rend="roman">October 26, 1760 </date>, by <hi rend="roman">Frank <lb/>Nicholls</hi>,
        M. D. F. R. S. Phyſician to his <lb/>late Majeſty. </head>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>To the Right Honourable <hi rend="roman">George</hi> Earl of <hi rend="roman"
            >Macclesfield</hi>, <lb/>Preſident of the Royal Society. </head>
        <salute rend="indent space">
          <lb/>My Lord, </salute>
        <p>
          <lb/>
          <note place="inset" rend="size(0.7) hanging">Read <date>Nov. 26, <lb/>1761. </date>
          </note><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE incloſed papers have been laid <lb/>before the Lord
          Chamberlain, for <lb/>his Majeſty's inſpection; and his Majeſty's anſwer <lb/>was, That he
          ſaw no reaſon, why they may not be <lb/>made public. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The burſting the ventricle of the heart is a caſe <lb/>entirely unknown in phyſical
          writers; and muſt de- <lb/>pend on many circumſtances, which rarely coincide. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I have uſed my beſt endeavours, to give a clear <lb/>and ſatisfactory account of this
          very extraordinary <lb/>affair; and I hope I have ſucceeded: but, if any <pb n="266"/>
          <lb/>thing abſtruſe ſhould appear, I truſt, it will be attri- <lb/>buted rather to the
          nature of the caſe, than to any <lb/>want of conſideration or reſpect for your Lordſhip,
          or <lb/>the Society, in, </p>
        <signed rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>My Lord, <lb/>Your Lordſhip's <lb/>moſt obedient, <lb/>and moſt humble ſervant, </signed>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <dateline rend="size(0.8)">
          <lb/>October 20, 1761. </dateline>
        <cb n="2"/>
        <signed rend="size(1.2) space align-right">
          <lb/>Fran. Nicholls. </signed>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>To the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi rend="roman">Macclesfield</hi>,
          <lb/>Preſident of the Royal Society. </head>
        <salute rend="indent space">
          <lb/>My Lord, </salute>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">T</hi>HE circumſtances attending the death of the <lb/>late King
          being ſuch, as are not (I apprehend) <lb/>to be met with in any of the records of phyſical
          caſes, <lb/>and ſuch, as, from the nature of the parts concerned, <lb/>are not eaſily to
          be accounted for; I preſume it will <lb/>be agreeable to your Lordſhip, to the Society in
          <lb/>which you preſide, and to the learned world in ge- <lb/>neral, if I lay before your
          Lordſhip, and the Society, <lb/>a minute detail of what occurred on that remarkable
          <lb/>and melancholy occaſion; with ſuch explanations, as <lb/>ariſe from the circumſtances
          of the caſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>According to the report of the pages then in wait- <lb/>ing, about ſeven in the
          morning, Saturday, Octo- <lb/>ber 25th, a noiſe was ſomewhere heard, as if a large
          <lb/>billet had tumbled down; and, upon enquiry, his <pb n="267"/>
          <lb/>Majeſty was found fallen on the ground, ſpeechleſs <lb/>and motionleſs, with a ſlight
          contuſed wound on his <lb/>right temple. He appeared to have juſt come from <lb/>his
          neceſſary-ſtool, and as if going to open his eſcri- <lb/>toir. Mr. Andrews (at that time
          ſurgeon to the <lb/>houſhold) attempted to take away ſome blood; but <lb/>in vain, as no
          ſigns of ſenſe, or motion, were ob- <lb/>ſerved, from the time of his fall. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The next day, (Sunday, October the 26th) by <lb/>order of the Lord Chamberlain, I
          attended, with <lb/>the two ſerjeant-ſurgeons, who were directed to open <lb/>and embalm
          the Royal Body. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On opening the abdomen, all the parts therein <lb/>contained were found in a natural
          and healthy ſtate, <lb/>except that ſome hydatides (or watery bladders) were <lb/>found
          between the ſubſtance of each kidney, and its <lb/>internal coat. Theſe hydatides might,
          in time, have <lb/>proved fatal, either by compreſſing and deſtroying <lb/>the kidnies, ſo
          as to bring on an incurable ſuppreſſion <lb/>of urine; or, by diſcharging a lymph into the
          cavity <lb/>of the abdomen, might have formed a dropſy, not to <lb/>be removed by any
          medicines: but, in the preſent <lb/>caſe, theſe hydatides were of no conſequence, as none
          <lb/>of them exceeded the bulk of a common walnut. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On opening the head, the brain was found in a <lb/>healthy ſtate, no-ways loaded with
          blood, either in <lb/>its proper veſſels, or in the contiguous ſinuſes of the <lb/>dura
          mater. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Upon opening the cheſt, the lungs were in a na- <lb/>tural ſtate, free from every
          appearance of inflamma- <lb/>tion, or tubercle: but upon examining the heart, its
          <lb/>pericardium was found diſtended, with a quantity of <lb/>coagulated blood, nearly
          ſufficient to fill a pint cup; <pb n="268"/>
          <lb/>and, upon removing this blood, a round orifice ap- <lb/>peared in the middle of the
          upper ſide of the right <lb/>ventricle of the heart, large enough to admit the ex-
          <lb/>tremity of the little finger. Through this orifice, all <lb/>the blood brought to the
          right ventricle had been diſ- <lb/>charged into the cavity of the pericardium; and, by
          <lb/>that extravaſated blood, confined between the heart <lb/>and pericardium, the whole
          heart was very ſoon ne- <lb/>ceſſarily ſo compreſſed, as to prevent any blood con-
          <lb/>tained in the veins from being forced into the auricles; <lb/>which, therefore, with
          the ventricles, were found ab- <lb/>ſolutely void of blood, either in a fluid or
          coagulated <lb/>ſtate. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As, therefore, no blood could be tranſmitted <lb/>through the heart, from the inſant
          that the extrava- <lb/>ſation was completed, ſo the heart could deliver none <lb/>to the
          brain; and, in conſequence, all the animal <lb/>and vital motions, as they depend on the
          circulation <lb/>of the blood through the brain, muſt neceſſarily have <lb/>been ſtopped,
          from the ſame inſtant; and his Majeſty <lb/>muſt, therefore, have dropped down, and died
          in- <lb/>ſtantaneouſly: And as the heart is inſenſible of acute <lb/>and circumſcribed
          pain, his death muſt have been at- <lb/>tended with as little of that diſtreſs, which
          uſually ac- <lb/>companies the ſeparation of the ſoul and body, as was <lb/>poſſible,
          under any circumſtances whatſoever. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The above-mentioned appearances (as they ſhewed <lb/>the immediate cauſe of his
          Majeſty's death) were <lb/>thought ſufficient to form the report to his preſent
          <lb/>Majeſty, and his Council. But as the very eminent <lb/>and amiable character of his
          late Majeſty muſt make <lb/>the nature of his death the object of every one's atten-
          <lb/>tion and inquiry; and as the caſe was exceedingly <pb n="269"/>
          <lb/>ſingular and extraordinary in itſelf; and as the heart <lb/>muſt have been merely
          paſſive, and, conſequently, <lb/>there muſt have been ſome other concurrent circum-
          <lb/>ſtances neceſſary to produce ſuch an effect; I judged, <lb/>at the time, when the
          report was drawn, that a more <lb/>minute and exact detail would not only be expected
          <lb/>by the world, but would be highly proper, as our in- <lb/>quiry furniſhed ſufficient
          matter. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Two queſtions naturally ariſe upon the face of our <lb/>report; viz. by what means
          the right ſide of the <lb/>heart became ſo charged with blood, as to be under <lb/>a
          neceſſity of burſting? and how it could happen, <lb/>that, as the ventricle (when under
          great diſtenſions) <lb/>generally makes one continued cavity with the auricle, <lb/>and is
          much thicker and ſtronger than the auricle, <lb/>the blood ſhould, nevertheleſs, force its
          way, by <lb/>burſting the ventricle, rather than the auricle, ſeem- <lb/>ingly in
          contradiction to the known property of fluids, <lb/>to force their way, where the
          reſiſtance is leaſt? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Upon examining the parts, we found the two great <lb/>arteries, (the aorta and
          pulmonary artery, as far as <lb/>they are contained within the pericardium) and the
          <lb/>right ventricle of the heart ſtretched beyond their na- <lb/>tural ſtate; and, in the
          trunk of the aorta, we found <lb/>a tranſverſe fiſſure on its inner ſide, about an inch
          and <lb/>half long, through which ſome blood had recently <lb/>paſſed, under its external
          coat, and formed an elevated <lb/>echymoſis. This appearance ſhewed the true ſtate of
          <lb/>an incipient aneuriſm of the aorta; and confirmed <lb/>the doctrine, which I had the
          honour to illuſtrate, <lb/>by an experiment, to the ſatisfaction of the Society, <lb/>in
          the Year 1728; [See the Philoſophical Tranſ- <lb/>actions, N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 402.]
          viz. that the external coat of the <pb n="270"/>
          <lb/>artery may (and does) often controul an impetus of <lb/>the blood, capable of
          burſting the internal (or liga- <lb/>mentous, coat; although this laſt is by much the
          <lb/>thickeſt, and ſeemingly, the ſtrongeſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In regard to this diſtention of the aorta; as his <lb/>Majeſty had, for ſome years,
          complained of frequent <lb/>diſtreſſes and ſinkings about the region of the heart;
          <lb/>and as his pulſe was, of late years, obſerved to fall <lb/>very much upon bleeding;
          it is not doubted, but <lb/>that this diſtenſion of the aorta had been of long
          <lb/>ſtanding, at leaſt to ſome degree; and, as the pul- <lb/>monary artery was thereby
          neceſſarily compreſſed, <lb/>and a reſiſtance, greater than natural, thereby oppoſed
          <lb/>to the blood's diſcharge out of the right ventricle, it <lb/>is reaſonable to
          conclude, that a diſtenſion and con- <lb/>ſequent weakneſs of the pulmonary artery and
          right <lb/>ventricle, to ſome degree, were nearly coeval with <lb/>that of the aorta. But
          that the aorta had ſuffered a <lb/>more extraordinary and violent diſtenſion, immedi-
          <lb/>ately antecedent to the burſting of the ventricle, is evi- <lb/>dent, from the recent
          fiſſure of the aorta, and the <lb/>conſequent extravaſation of blood between its coats.
          <lb/>Now, as this increaſed and violent diſtenſion of the <lb/>aorta muſt have been
          attended with a proportionate <lb/>preſſure upon the pulmonary artery, and, conſe-
          <lb/>quently, an increaſed oppoſition to the paſſage of the <lb/>blood out of the right
          ventricle; ſo that diſtenſion of <lb/>the aorta muſt be conſidered, as the immediate cauſe
          <lb/>of the right ventricle's being ſurcharged with blood, <lb/>and conſequently of its
          burſting. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The immediate cauſe of this diſtenſion of the aorta, <lb/>as likewiſe of its being
          determined to that particular <lb/>time, are naturally explicable, from his Majeſty's <pb
            n="271"/>
          <lb/>having been at the neceſſary-ſtool; as the office then <lb/>required cannot be
          executed, but by ſuch a preſſure <lb/>on all the contents of the lower belly, and, conſe-
          <lb/>quently, on the great deſcending artery, as muſt, of <lb/>neceſſity, ſubject the
          trunk of the aorta, and all its <lb/>upper branches, to a ſurcharge with blood continually
          <lb/>increaſing, in proportion as the preſſure may happen <lb/>to be continued longer, or
          exerted with greater vio- <lb/>lence, in conſequence of a coſtive habit, or any other
          <lb/>reſiſtance. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As to the ſecond queſtion; viz. how it could <lb/>happen, that the blood ſhould force
          its way rather <lb/>through the ſide of the ventricle than of the auricle? <lb/>ſince it
          is well known, that when the ventricle is fully <lb/>diſtended with fluids, they will
          eaſily paſs back into <lb/>the auricle; ſo that under ſuch a diſtenſion, as the
          <lb/>ventricle muſt have ſuffered, before it burſt, it ſhould <lb/>ſeem to have made one
          continued cavity with the <lb/>auricle; of which cavity, the auricle, being by much
          <lb/>the weakeſt part, muſt have been the moſt liable to <lb/>a rupture. This certainly is
          the circumſtance, in <lb/>which the very great ſingularity of the caſe before us
          <lb/>conſiſts; and many difficulties offer againſt any ob- <lb/>vious explanation. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Two circumſtances, however, ſeem to throw ſome <lb/>light on this obſcure and
          difficult queſtion. The firſt <lb/>conſiſts in the texture, connexions, and capacity, of
          <lb/>the pericardium; the ſecond, in the order, in which <lb/>the ſeveral ſurcharges muſt
          have ariſen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The pericardium is a ſtrong tendinous membrane, <lb/>inelaſtic in every direction,
          containing the two auricles, <lb/>the two ventricles, and the two great arteries, as in a
          <lb/>purſe: it is fixed to its contents at the back of the <pb n="272"/>
          <lb/>two auricles, where, by its connexion, it ſurrounds <lb/>the two venæ cavæ: hence,
          paſſing along the arch <lb/>formed by the aorta, it deſcends to the pulmonary <lb/>artery,
          and continues round the orifices of the pul- <lb/>monary veins, firmly attached to theſe
          ſeveral parts <lb/>in its paſſage. By theſe connexions, theſe parts are <lb/>all fixed in
          their ſeveral ſtations, incapable of ſepa- <lb/>rating from each other, or ſhifting their
          ſituations, <lb/>however they may happen to be compreſſed. The <lb/>pericardium is
          generally ſaid to ſerve as a defence to <lb/>the heart; but that defence ſeems to conſiſt
          chiefly, <lb/>in preventing the right auricle from being ſtretched <lb/>by the depreſſions
          (or complanations) of the dia- <lb/>phragm, in hunger and inſpiration, and, by its bear-
          <lb/>ing firmly againſt the ſides of the auricles, to ſupport <lb/>and ſtrengthen them
          againſt too great diſtenſions: <lb/>for the cavity of the pericardium ſeems to be but
          little <lb/>more, than commenſurate to the bulk of its contents, <lb/>when one half of
          them are filled, and the other half <lb/>empty. This will appear, upon endeavouring to
          fill <lb/>the heart, with its auricles, and its two great arteries, <lb/>with wax, at the
          ſame time, while it is incloſed in <lb/>the pericardium; in which experiment, one or other
          <lb/>of theſe cavities will be found to have been ſo com- <lb/>preſſed by the pericardium,
          as to have refuſed a free <lb/>admittance to the wax, and will, therefore, be found
          <lb/>proportionally empty. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The inelaſtic texture, connexions, and capacity, of <lb/>the pericardium, being thus
          ſtated, let us now con- <lb/>ſider the order, in which the ſeveral diſtenſions muſt
          <lb/>have ariſen, in the two great arteries and cavities of <lb/>the heart, with the
          neceſſary effects of thoſe diſten- <pb n="273"/>
          <lb/>ſions on the pericardium, and the parts which it con- <lb/>tains. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The firſt diſtenſion (and this a great and violent <lb/>one) muſt have ariſen in the
          aorta; and the conſe- <lb/>quent preſſure on the pulmonary artery (by the aorta <lb/>ſo
          diſtended) muſt have been ſufficient (either by de- <lb/>grees or at once) to ſtop the
          blood's diſcharge out of <lb/>the right ventricle and pulmonary artery, and to di-
          <lb/>ſtend both thoſe cavities greatly beyond their natural <lb/>ſtate of repletion. So
          that, under theſe circumſtances, <lb/>the two great arteries, and the right ventricle,
          muſt <lb/>have been under an extraordinary and continued di- <lb/>ſtenſion (and,
          conſequently, an increaſe of bulk) at <lb/>the ſame time; whereas, in the natural ſtate of
          the <lb/>body, theſe three cavities are alternately dilated and <lb/>contracted, and the
          right ventricle is always propor- <lb/>tionally diminiſhed in bulk, as the pulmonary
          artery <lb/>in increaſed, and vice versâ. So that, with reſpect to <lb/>theſe three great
          cavities, (ſuppoſing that their ſeveral <lb/>diſtenſions had been no greater than natural)
          the pe- <lb/>ricardium muſt have been obliged to contain one third <lb/>more in
          proportion, than its capacity was formed to <lb/>receive. During this time, the blood
          being ſtopped in <lb/>its paſſage through the lungs, and its afflux to the left
          <lb/>auricle and ventricle muſt have remained in a con- <lb/>tracted ſtate; in conſequence
          of which, the right ven- <lb/>tricle had ample ſpace in the pericardium, to admit
          <lb/>that degree of diſtenſion, which was previouſly requi- <lb/>ſite for its burſting.
          But the right auricle (being fixed <lb/>to its ſtation by its connections with the left
          auricle <lb/>and the pericardium, and being firmly compreſſed <pb n="274"/>
          <lb/>againſt the pericardium, by the aorta, the pulmonary <lb/>artery, and the right
          ventricle, all which appear to <lb/>have been, at this time, greatly diſtended beyond
          their <lb/>natural bulk) muſt have been thereby deprived of the <lb/>ſpace in the
          pericardium, neceſſary to admit of its <lb/>being diſtended; and the whole ſurcharge and
          di- <lb/>ſtenſion muſt, by the preſſure of the pericardium on <lb/>the auricle,
          neceſſarily have been confined to the right <lb/>ventricle, till it burſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Had theſe ſurcharges ariſen in any other order, <lb/>their effects muſt have been
          greatly different: as for <lb/>inſtance, if the ſurcharge in the right ventricle had
          <lb/>ariſen from any other preſſure, than from a diſten- <lb/>ſion of the aorta, the
          extraordinary bulk of the <lb/>aorta, and its preſſure againſt the pulmonary artery,
          <lb/>would not have exiſted, and the right auricle, not <lb/>being then compreſſed againſt
          the pericardium, would <lb/>have been at liberty to diſtend, till the blood had <lb/>made
          its way through its ſides. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In confirmation of this power, here attributed to <lb/>the pericardium, of
          ſtrenghtening and ſupporting its <lb/>contained parts, let it be obſerved, that, in the
          caſe <lb/>under conſideration, the place of the fiſſure in the <lb/>aorta is preciſely
          where the preſſure of the pericardium <lb/>is kept off from the aorta, to a conſiderable
          degree, <lb/>by the ſituation of the right auricle and the pulmonary <lb/>artery. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>My Lord, in order to give a clear and diſtinct idea <lb/>of this very extraordinary
          caſe, I have here annexed <lb/>two prints; [<hi rend="italic">Vide Tab.</hi> XI. &amp;
          XII.] the firſt of <lb/>which ſhews the heart, as it appears when all its <lb/>cavities
          and blood-veſſels are filled with wax <figure>
            <figDesc>An illustration of the heart on a separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
          </figure>; the <lb/>other is the ſame print, having the orifice in the right <pb n="275"/>
          <lb/>ventricle, and the extravaſation covering the fiſſure in <lb/>the aorta, exactly
          marked, as they appeared to, <figure>
            <figDesc>An illustration of the heart, holes being evident in both the right ventricle
              and the aorta, on a separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <signed rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>My Lord, <lb/>Your Lordſhip's <lb/>moſt obedient <lb/>and moſt humble ſervant,
            <lb/><hi rend="size(1.2) space">Frank Nicholls. </hi>
        </signed>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
