<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Bones: Extract of a Second Letter from the Rev. Mr. Bones</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Mr. Bones</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Extract of a Second Letter from the Rev. Mr. Bones, to Dr. Baker</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Printed for L. Davis and C. Reymers, Printers to the Royal Society,
                  against Gray's-Inn Gate, In Holbourn.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1761</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">52</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">529-533</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110357793</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1761.0087</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT52_0529">
    <body>
      <pb n="529"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">LXXXV.</hi> Extract of a ſecond Letter from <lb/>the Rev. Mr. <hi
          rend="roman">Bones</hi>, to Dr. <hi rend="roman">Baker</hi>. </head>
      <p>
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="size(0.7) hanging">Read <date>May 6, <lb/>1762. </date>
        </note><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> Have taken all the pains I can to inform <lb/>myſelf of every
        circumſtance, which <lb/>may be deemed a probable cauſe of the diſeaſe, by <lb/>which the
        poor family in my pariſh has been afflicted. <lb/>But, I fear, I have diſcovered nothing,
        that will be <lb/>ſatisfactory to you. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The following is an anſwer to your queries. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Water.] This they have taken out of a ditch, or <lb/>pool of ſtanding-water, at their
        own door (as is com- <lb/>mon in this clay country.) We have no ſpring, or <lb/>well, in the
        pariſh. </p>
      <pb n="530"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Beer.] They have generally bought their beer at a <lb/>public-houſe. But, in Auguſt
        laſt, the poor man <lb/>brewed two buſhels of malt, in a large braſs kettle, <lb/>which is
        very commonly let out to the poor. It is an <lb/>old one, but belongs to a cleanly
        houſewife. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Bread.] We have no rye. This family have been <lb/>uſed to buy two buſhels of <hi
          rend="italic">clog-wheat</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">rivets</hi>, or <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >bearded-weat</hi>, (as it is variouſly called in this county) <lb/>every fortnight. Of
        this they have made their houſe- <lb/>hold bread. This wheat they have bought of the
        <lb/>farmer, whom I lodge with, who tells me, that laſt <lb/>year he had ſome wheat <hi
          rend="italic">laid</hi>, which he gathered, <lb/>and threſhed ſeparately, leſt it ſhould
        ſpoil his <hi rend="italic">ſamples</hi>. <lb/>Not that it was mildewed, or grown, but only
        diſ- <lb/>coloured, and ſmaller than the other. This damaged <lb/>wheat he treſhed laſt
        Chriſtmas; and then this poor <lb/>family uſed no bread, but what was made of it, as
        <lb/>likewiſe did the farmer's own family, and ſome others <lb/>in the neighbourhood. We
        obſerved, that it made <lb/>bad bread, and worſe puddings; but I do not find, <lb/>that it
        diſagreed with any body. A labouring man of <lb/>the pariſh, who had uſed this bread, was
        affected with <lb/>a numbneſs in both his hands, for about four weeks <lb/>from the ninth of
        January. His hands were con- <lb/>tinually cold, and his fingers ends peeled. One
        <lb/>thumb, he ſays, ſtill remains without any ſenſation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Kitchen utenſils.] They have two ſmall iron pots, <lb/>which have long been in uſe. In
        theſe they boiled <lb/>their pork, peaſe, &amp;c. They have likewiſe two <hi rend="italic"
          >braſs <lb/>ſkillets</hi>, rather old, in which they boiled milk, &amp;c. <lb/>The man
        tells me, they are in conſtant uſe, and never <lb/>were <hi rend="italic">cankered</hi>. </p>
      <pb n="531"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Peaſe.] They have now and then eaten peaſe and <lb/>peaſe-broth. Theſe they have always
        bought, as <lb/>others do, at the ſhop: and they have never diſagreed <lb/>with any of the
        family, except only on Sunday, Ja- <lb/>nuary 10. Three of the children were then ſick after
        <lb/>eating them; but became eaſy after they had vo- <lb/>mited. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Pork.] This, I find, they generally bought pickled, <lb/>of the farmer, whom I lodge
        with. The farmer's <lb/>family, and ſeveral others, have conſtantly eaten it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In this part of the country, there is a great deal of <lb/><hi rend="italic">old
          ewe-mutton</hi>, killed between the firſt of November <lb/>and January, ſome of which is
        very poor, and rotten, <lb/>and is uſually ſold at three halfpence, or perhaps one
        <lb/>penny, a pound. In December laſt, this family lived <lb/>for three weeks, at leaſt,
        upon this mutton, of which <lb/>they bought a quarter at a time, weighing ſeven or
        <lb/>eight pounds, for one ſhilling. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The man is ſo prepoſſeſſed with notions of witch- <lb/>craft, and is ſo obſtinate in
        his opinion, that I cannot <lb/>excite in him even a deſire of attributing this diſeaſe
        <lb/>to any other cauſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Since my laſt letter to you, Mary, (aged ſixteen) <lb/>who ſat for fourteen weeks in a
        great chair, and for <lb/>ſeven days without any feet, or fleſh on her leg-bones, <lb/>has
        conſented to have the bones taken off. She is <lb/>now in bed: the abſceſs is healing, and
        ſhe ſeems <lb/>likely to do well. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The father's fingers are almoſt healed. But he <lb/>every day feels ſevere darting
        pains in many parts of <lb/>his body. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The mother lies in bed, with her leg-bones bare, <lb/>which ſhe will not ſuffer to be
        taken off. Her hands <pb n="532"/>
        <lb/>are ſtill benumbed, but not <choice>
          <corr>black</corr>
          <sic>blaek</sic>
        </choice>. Her fingers are <lb/>contracted. The reſt of the family ſeem to be re-
        <lb/>covering perfect health. </p>
      <dateline rend="size(0.8) indent space">
        <lb/>Wattiſham, <lb/>April 30, 1762. </dateline>
      <postscript>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>There is, in <hi rend="italic">l'Hiſtoire de l'Academie Royale des
          <lb/>Sciences</hi>, for the year 1710, a paper, the title of <lb/>which is, <hi
            rend="italic">Sur le <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7) roman">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* Secale corniculatum nigrum, mentioned as a poiſon by <lb/>Hoffman. </p>
            </note> bled cornu appellé Ergot</hi>. Here it <lb/>is ſaid, that M. Noël, ſurgeon of
          the Hôtel-Dieu at <lb/>Orleans, had ſent an account to a member of the <lb/>academy, that,
          within about a year's time, he had <lb/>received into the hoſpital more than fifty
          patients af- <lb/>flicted <hi rend="italic">d'une gangrene ſeche, noire, et livide</hi>,
          which <lb/>began at the toes, and advanced more or leſs, being <lb/>ſometimes continued
          even to the thighs; and that he <lb/>had only ſeen one patient, who had been firſt ſeized
          <lb/>with it in the hand. He adds, that he obſerved, that <lb/>this diſeaſe affected the
          men only; and that, in ge- <lb/>neral, the females, except ſome very young girls,
          <lb/>were quite free from it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In the ſame paper is mentioned, as a fact well <lb/>known to the academy, the caſe of
          a peaſant, who <lb/>lived near Blois. In this patient, a gangrene, at its <lb/>firſt
          attack, deſtroyed all the toes of one foot, then <lb/>thoſe of the other, afterwards the
          remaining parts of <lb/>both feet; then the fleſh of both his legs, and that <lb/>of his
          thighs, rotted off ſucceſſively, and left nothing <lb/>but bare bones. </p>
        <pb n="533"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The gentlemen of the academy were of opinion, <lb/>that the diſeaſe (of which M. Noël
          had ſent an ac- <lb/>count) was produced by bad nouriſhment, particu- <lb/>larly by bread,
          in which there was a great quantity <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">ergot</hi>
          <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* This degenerated rye is called <hi rend="italic">ergot</hi>, from its
              reſemblance <lb/>to a cock's ſpur. </p>
          </note>. This ſubſtance is deſcribed by M. Fagon, <lb/>firſt phyſician to the King, and is
          ſaid by him to be <lb/>a kind of monſter in vegetation, which a particular <lb/>ſort of
          rye, ſown in March, is more apt to produce, <lb/>than what is ſown in the autumn, and
          which often <lb/>abounds in moiſt cold countries, and in wet ſeaſons. <lb/>How far it is
          true, that this ſubſtance was really the <lb/>cauſe of the French epidemical gangrene
          deſcribed, <lb/>I cannot determine. On compariſon, we find, that <lb/>the preſent diſeaſe
          at Wattiſham, and that recorded <lb/>by the French academy, do agree extremely in their
          <lb/>effects. However, it is now certain, that rye made <lb/>no part of the nouriſhment of
          the poor family at <lb/>Wattiſham. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Although we undoubtedly excel the antients in the <lb/>knowledge of poiſons, yet a
          great deal of that ſubject <lb/>ſtill remains unknown to us. It will, therefore, be
          <lb/>very difficult for us to diſcover, to what cauſe, or to <lb/>what combination of
          cauſes, ſo uncommon a malady <lb/>is to be attributed. </p>
      </postscript>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
