<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - White and Watson: An Account of a Case in Which the Upper Head of the
          Os Humeri Was Sawed off</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>C. White</persName>
              <persName>Mr. Watson</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of a Case in Which the Upper Head of the Os Humeri Was Sawed off, a
              Large Portion of the Bone Afterwards Exfoliated, and Yet the Entire Motion of the Limb
              Was Preserved. By Mr. White, Surgeon, at Manchester. Communicated by Mr. Watson, F. R.
              S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for Lockyer Davis, Printer to the Royal Society, near
                  Gray's-Inn Gate, in Holbourn. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1769</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">59</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">39-46</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110531012</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1769.0006</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT59_0039">
    <body>
      <pb n="39"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VI.</hi> An Account of a Caſe in which the upper <lb/>Head of the <hi
          rend="roman">Os Humeri</hi> was ſawed off, a <lb/>large Portion of the bone afterwards ex-
        <lb/>foliated, and yet the entire Motion of the <lb/>Limb was preſerved. By Mr. <hi
          rend="roman">White</hi>, <lb/>Surgeon, at <hi rend="roman">Mancheſter</hi>. Communicated
        <lb/>by Mr. <hi rend="roman">Watſon</hi>, F. R. S. </head>
      <div>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/>
          <note place="inset" rend="size(0.7) hanging">Read <date>February 9, <lb/>1769. </date>
          </note><hi rend="dc(2)">E</hi>DMUND POLLIT, of <lb/>Sterling, near Cockey Moor, in
          <lb/>this county, aged 16, of a ſcrophulous habit of body, <lb/>was admitted into the
          Mancheſter infirmary, April <lb/>6, 1768. The account I received with him was, <lb/>that
          he had been ſuddenly ſeized, about a fortnight <lb/>before, with a violent inflammation in
          his left ſhoul- <lb/>der, which threatened a mortification, but at laſt <lb/>terminated in
          a large abſceſs, which was opened with <lb/>a lancet a few days before his admiſſion. The
          ori- <lb/>fice was ſituated near the <hi rend="italic">axilla</hi>, upon the lower edge
          <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">pectoralis major</hi>; and through it, I could di-
          <lb/>ſtinctly feel the head of the <hi rend="italic">os humeri</hi> totally diveſted
          <lb/>of its burſal ligament. The matter, which was very <lb/>offenſive, and in great
          quantity, had made its way <lb/>down to the middle of the <hi rend="italic">humerus</hi>,
          and had likewiſe <lb/>burſt out at another orifice juſt below the <hi rend="italic"
            >proceſſus <lb/>acromion</hi>; through which the head of the <hi rend="italic">os
            humeri</hi>
          <lb/>might eaſily be ſeen. The whole arm and hand were <pb n="40"/>
          <lb/>ſwelled to twice their natural ſize, and were entirely <lb/>uſeleſs to him; he
          ſuffered much pain, and the ab- <lb/>ſorption of the matter had brought on hectic ſym-
          <lb/>ptoms, ſuch as, night-ſweats, <hi rend="italic">diarrhæa</hi>, quick pulſe, <lb/>and
          loſs of appetite, which had extremely emaciated <lb/>him. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Under theſe very dangerous circumſtances, there <lb/>ſeemed no reſource but from an
          operation. The <lb/>common one in theſe caſes, that of taking off the arm <lb/>at the
          articulation with the <hi rend="italic">ſcapula</hi>, appeared dreadful <lb/>both in the
          firſt inſtance and in its conſequences. I <lb/>therefore propoſed the following operation,
          from <lb/>which I expected many advantages; and performed <lb/>it on the 14th of the ſame
          month. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I began my inciſion at that orifice which was ſi- <lb/>tuated juſt below the <hi
            rend="italic">proceſſus acromion</hi>, and carried it <lb/>down to the middle of the <hi
            rend="italic">humerus</hi>, by which all the <lb/>ſubjacent bone was brought into view.
          I then took <lb/>hold of the patient's elbow, and eaſily forced the <lb/>head of the <hi
            rend="italic">humerus</hi> out of its ſocket, and brought it <lb/>ſo entirely out of the
          wound, that I readily graſped <lb/>the whole head in my left hand, and held it there till
          <lb/>I had ſawn it off (ſee Tab. I. Fig. 1.), with a com- <lb/>mon amputation-ſaw, having
          firſt applied a paſte- <lb/>board card betwixt the bones and the ſkin. I had <lb/>taken
          the precaution of placing an aſſiſtant on whom <lb/>I could depend, with a compreſs juſt
          above the cla- <lb/>vicle, to ſtop the circulation in the artery, if I ſhould <lb/>have
          the misfortune to cut or lacerate it; but no acci- <lb/>dent of any kind happened, and the
          patient did not <lb/>loſe more than two or three ounces of blood, only a <lb/>ſmall artery
          which partly ſurrounds the joint being <lb/>wounded, which was eaſily ſecured. </p>
        <pb n="41"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>He was remarkably eaſy after the operation, and <lb/>reſted well that night; the
          diſcharge diminiſhed <lb/>every day, the ſwelling gradually abated, his appetite
          <lb/>returned, and all his hectic ſymptoms vaniſhed. In <lb/>about five or ſix weeks, I
          perceived the parts, from <lb/>which the bone had been taken, had acquired a con-
          <lb/>ſiderable degree of firmneſs, and he was able to lift a <lb/>pretty large weight in
          his hand. At the end of two <lb/>months, I found that a large piece of the whole ſub-
          <lb/>ſtance of the bone, that had been denuded by the mat- <lb/>ter, and afterwards
          expoſed to the air, was now <lb/>ready to ſeparate from the ſound, and with a pair of
          <lb/>forceps I eaſily removed it (Fig. II.). After this ex- <lb/>foliation, the wound
          healed very faſt; and on Auguſt <lb/>15th he was diſcharged perfectly cured. On com-
          <lb/>paring this arm with the other, it was not quite an <lb/>inch ſhorter; he has the
          perfect uſe of it, and can not <lb/>only elevate his arm to any height, but can likewiſe
          <lb/>perform the rotatory motion as well as ever. The <lb/>figure of the arm is no ways
          altered; and from the <lb/>uſe he has of it, from its appearance to the eye, and <lb/>to
          the touch, I think I may ſafely ſay, the head, <lb/>neck, and part of the body of the <hi
            rend="italic">os humeri</hi> are ac- <lb/>tually regenerated. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I did not make uſe of any ſplints, machine, or <lb/>bandage, during the cure, to
          confine the limb ſtrictly <lb/>in one certain ſituation, nor was his arm ever dreſſed
          <lb/>in bed, but ſitting in a chair, and, as ſoon as he <lb/>could bear it, ſtanding up,
          with his body leaning for- <lb/>wards, to give room for applying the bandages, which
          <lb/>were no more than juſt neceſſary to retain the dreſ- <lb/>ſings; and to this method I
          attribute the preſervation <lb/>of the motion of the joint, which could not have <pb
            n="42"/>
          <lb/>been ſo well effected any other way; but the joint, <lb/>in all probability, would
          have remained ſtiff, and <lb/>formed an <hi rend="italic">anchyloſis</hi>, if it had not
          been allowed to play <lb/>about. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>REMARKS. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Though from this operation I hoped for many <lb/>advantages preferable to the
          amputation of the limb <lb/>at the <hi rend="italic">ſcapula</hi>, yet my moſt ſanguine
          expectations <lb/>fell greatly ſhort of the ſucceſs attending it. I did <lb/>not flatter
          myſelf with the hopes of a moveable joint, <lb/>or that the length of the limb would be ſo
          nearly <lb/>preſerved, when there was a loſs of above four inches <lb/>of the whole
          ſubſtance of the bone without any <lb/>other bone to ſupport it as in the leg and
          fore-arm; <lb/>and where the dreadful condition of the arm at the <lb/>time of the
          operation prevented me from making uſe <lb/>of any machine to keep it extended <note n="*"
            place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* After the extraction of three inches and ten lines of the <hi rend="italic">os
                <lb/>humeri</hi>, M. Le Cat made uſe of a machine to keep the upper <lb/>and lower
              pieces of the bone at their proper diſtances. He has <lb/>given a deſcription of the
              caſe, and a figure of the machine, in <lb/>vol. LVI. of the Philoſ. Tranſact. p. 270.
            </p>
          </note>. But I ſup- <lb/>poſe the weight of the arm was in this caſe in ſome <lb/>meaſure
          ſufficient to counterbalance the contractile <lb/>power of the muſcles, for his arm was
          only ſuſpended <lb/>by a common ſling, and the patient not at all con- <lb/>fined to his
          bed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I could not help being ſurprized to find ſo much <lb/>ſtrength and firmneſs in the
          parts as evidently ſhewed <lb/>a regeneration of the bone before the lower part had <pb
            n="43"/>
          <lb/>exfoliated, or even before it had begun to looſen. <lb/>This oſſeous matter could not
          proceed from the <hi rend="italic">ſca- <lb/>pula</hi>, the glenoid cavity of that bone
          not being di- <lb/>veſted of its cartilage; could it then poſſibly eſcape <lb/>from the
          end of the ſound bone, before the morbid <lb/>part had begun to ſeparate from it? or are
          there any <lb/>veſſels that could convey the bony matter, and depoſit <lb/>it in the place
          of what had been removed <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Mr. Gooch, in his volume of Caſes and Practical Remarks, <lb/>relating the caſe
              of a compound fracture of the leg, where a very <lb/>conſiderable portion of the <hi
                rend="italic">tibia</hi> was ſawed off, ſays, <q rend="diple quotes">In about
                <lb/>three weeks I was ſenſible, as were alſo ſeveral ſurgeons whom <lb/>curioſity
                led to ſee ſo uncommon a caſe, that the ſubſtance <lb/>which grew in the ſpace of
                five inches entirely void of bone, <lb/>had acquired in the middle only a greater
                degree of ſolidity <lb/>than fleſh; which circumſtance not agreeing with the general
                <lb/>received notion of the generation of <hi rend="italic">callus</hi>, we proved
                beyond <lb/>diſpute, with a ſharp pointed inſtrument, and we obſerved that <lb/>the
                oſſification was gradually formed from that central point, <lb/>which was
                conſiderably advanced before any exfoliation was <lb/>caſt off the ends of the
                divided bone. In leſs than four <lb/>months, the whole ſpace was ſo well ſupplied
                with the <hi rend="italic">callus</hi>, <lb/>or rather new bone, that he was able to
                raiſe his leg when the <lb/>bandage was off, without its bending. </q>
            </p>
            <p rend="align-right">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">Caſes and Remarks, new Edit.</hi> p. 287. </p>
          </note>? Theſe <lb/>are points that I will not pretend to decide abſolutely, <lb/>but I am
          much inclined to the latter opinion <note n="†" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>† In univerſum in ſanguine materies eſt apta producendo oſſi, <lb/>quæ adeo
              frequenter in celluloſum ſpatium intimum, interque <lb/>convexam ſuperficiem membranæ
              intimæ arteriarum, concavam- <lb/>que membranæ muſculoſæ extremitatem effunditur, et
              caſeoſa <lb/>primo, inde calloſa, quaſi coriacea, demum oſſeæ ſquamæ fit ſi-
              <lb/>millima. </p>
            <p rend="align-right">
              <lb/>Halleri Elem. Phyſiolog. tom. VIII. p. 316. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>— Calli in oſſibus non fracturas ſolas, ſed amiſſa integra <lb/>oſſa ſarcientes,
              fiunt ex liquido glutinoſo, pulſu proximarum ar- <lb/>teriarum compacto, &amp;c. <hi
                rend="align-right">Halleri Primæ Lineæ, p. 148. </hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>See further Haller's Pathological Obſervations, Obſ. xlvii. </p>
          </note>. </p>
        <pb n="44"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Is it not probable that there is a regeneration of the <lb/>cartilage as well as the
          bone? for it is well known to <lb/>every-body converſant in anatomy, that the ends of
          <lb/>ſome bones, which are joined to no others, are co- <lb/>vered with cartilages; but
          theſe are never wanting on <lb/>the ends, and in the cavities of ſuch bones as are de-
          <lb/>ſigned for motion; and I cannot ſee in this caſe how <lb/>the motion could be
          preſerved ſo complete without a <lb/>cartilage; and indeed without a burſal ligament, or
          <lb/>ſomething analogous to it, to contain the <hi rend="italic">ſynovia</hi>, and
          <lb/>keep the bone in its place. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As this is the firſt operation of the kind that has <lb/>been performed, or at leaſt
          made public, I thought <lb/>the relation of it might poſſibly conduce to the im-
          <lb/>provement of the art. That ingenious ſurgeon, Mr. <lb/>Gooch, has indeed related
          three inſtances of the heads <lb/>of bones being ſawed off in compound luxations. In
          <lb/>one of theſe caſes the lower heads of the <hi rend="italic">tibia</hi> and <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">fibula</hi> were ſawn off, in another that of the <hi rend="italic"
            >radius</hi>, <lb/>and in the third that of the ſecond bone of the thumb; <lb/>but theſe
          were, in many reſpects, different from the <lb/>preſent caſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I believe it will ſeldom happen that this operation <lb/>will not be greatly
          preferable to the amputation of the <lb/>arm at the <hi rend="italic">ſcapula</hi>, as
          this laſt is generally performed <lb/>for a <hi rend="italic">caries</hi> of the upper
          head of the <hi rend="italic">os humeri</hi>; and <lb/>as the preſervation of a limb is
          always of the utmoſt <lb/>conſequence, and what every ſurgeon of the leaſt hu- <lb/>manity
          would at all times wiſh for, but particularly <lb/>where (as in this caſe) the whole limb
          and its actions <lb/>are preſerved entire, the cure no ways protracted, and <lb/>the
          danger of the operation moſt undoubtedly leſs. <lb/>For though amputation is often
          indiſpenſably neceſ- <pb n="45"/>
          <lb/>ſary, and frequently attended with little danger or <lb/>inconvenience when only part
          of a limb is removed; <lb/>yet where the whole is loſt, the danger is greatly in-
          <lb/>creaſed, and the loſs irreparable. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I have frequently performed this operation on dead <lb/>ſubjects, and where the parts
          had not been diſeaſed, <lb/>and never found any difficulty; and from the diſſec- <lb/>tion
          of the parts had no reaſon to doubt of ſucceſs in <lb/>a living ſubject, where the
          ligaments and muſcles are <lb/>more ſupple, and the matter, by inſinuating itſelf be-
          <lb/>twixt the bone and integuments, has made leſs diſſec- <lb/>tion neceſſary. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I have likewiſe, in a dead ſubject, made an inciſion <lb/>on the external ſide of the
          hip joint, and continued the <lb/>inciſion down below the great <hi rend="italic"
            >trochanter</hi>, then cutting <lb/>through the burſal ligament, and bringing the knee
          <lb/>inwards, the upper head of the <hi rend="italic">os femoris</hi> was forced <lb/>out
          of its ſocket, and eaſily ſawed off; and I have no <lb/>doubt but this operation might be
          performed upon a <lb/>living ſubject with great proſpect of ſucceſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Royal Academy of Surgery at Paris propoſed <lb/>for a prize queſtion, Whether
          amputation of the <lb/>thigh at its articulation with the <hi rend="italic">os
            innominatum</hi> was <lb/>ever adviſeable: but was I under a neceſſity of per-
          <lb/>forming this operation, or that which I have been <lb/>deſcribing, I ſhould not
          heſitate a moment which to <lb/>prefer. </p>
        <signed rend="size(1.2) align-right">
          <lb/>C. White. </signed>
      </div>
      <figure>
        <figure>
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>TAB. I. FIG. I. </head>
          <p rend="indentall">
            <lb/>That part of the bone which was ſawed off. <lb/><hi rend="italic">a.</hi> The head
            of the bone corroded by the matter. </p>
          <figDesc>An illustration of a badly damaged upper extremity of the upper arm bone on a
            separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb n="46"/>
        <figure>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>FIG. II. </head>
          <p rend="indentall hanging">
            <lb/>The piece of bone which exfoliated. Both <lb/>pieces together were five inches in
            length, <lb/>four of which were of the whole ſubſtance. </p>
          <figDesc>An illustration of a piece of bone, broken on one end, on a separate fold-out
            page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <figure>
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>FIG. III. </head>
          <p rend="indentall">
            <list rend="hanging">
              <item>
                <lb/>The arm as it appeared after the wound was <lb/>healed. </item>
              <item>
                <lb/><hi rend="italic">a.</hi> The cicatrix of the firſt inciſion. </item>
              <item>
                <lb/><hi rend="italic">b.b.b.</hi> The cicatrix of the inciſion made to bring
                <lb/>out the head of the bone. </item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <figDesc>An illustration of the upper arm, with two long scars being clearly visible, on a
            separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>N. B. The drawings from which this plate was <lb/>engraved were made by Mr. Aikin, my
          pupil, who <lb/>attended at the operation, and during the whole cure. </p>
      </figure>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
