<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Price: Farther Proofs of the Insalubrity of Marshy Situations</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Richard Price</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Farther Proofs of the Insalubrity of Marshy Situations. In a Letter from the Rev.
              Dr. Price to the Rev. Dr. Horsley</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for Lockyer Davis, Printer to the Royal Society, in
                  Holbourn. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1774</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">64</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">96-98</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110532381</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1774.0009</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT64_0096">
    <body>
      <pb n="96"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">IX.</hi> Farther Proofs of the Inſalubrity of <lb/>marſhy situations.
        In a Letter from the <lb/>Rev. Dr. <hi rend="roman">Price </hi>to the Rev. Dr. <hi
          rend="roman">Horſley</hi>. </head>
      <salute rend="indent space sc">
        <lb/>dear sir, </salute>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="size(0.7) hanging">Redde, <date>Jan. 13, <lb/>1774. </date>
        </note><hi rend="dc(2)">D</hi>R. <hi rend="sc">priestley</hi>'s paper, on the <lb/>noxious
        effects of ſtagnant waters, <lb/>read laſt Thurſday to the Royal Society, brought <lb/>to my
        remembrance to a table; exhibiting the rate <lb/>of mortality in a pariſh ſituated among
        marſhes, <lb/>which I have ſeen in Mr. <hi rend="sc">Muret</hi>'s Obſervations,
        <lb/>publiſhed in the Memoirs of the Oeconomical So- <lb/>ciet at Bern, for 1766. I have
        ſince reviewed <lb/>this table, and found that it affords a full confir- <lb/>mation of Dr.
          <hi rend="sc">Priestley</hi>'s aſſertions. This pariſh <lb/>is a part of the diſtrict of
        Vaud, belonging to the <lb/>canton of Bern, in Switzerland; and contains <lb/>169 families,
        and 696 inhabitants. Mr. <hi rend="sc">Muret</hi>'s <lb/>table, of the rate of mortality in
        it, is formed from <lb/>a regiſter of the ages, at which all died in it for 15 <lb/>years.
        With this table he has alſo given tables, <lb/>from like regiſters, of the rates of
        mortality in <lb/>ſeven ſmall towns; in 36 country pariſhes and <lb/>villages; in 16
        pariſhes ſituated in the Alps; in <lb/>12 corn pariſhes, and in 18 vintage pariſhes.—
        <lb/>From comparing theſe tables, it appears, that <pb n="97"/>
        <lb/>the probabilities of life are higheſt in the most <lb/>hilly parts of the province, the
        loweſt in the <lb/>marſhy pariſh juſt mentioned. The difference is <lb/>indeed remarkable,
        as will appear from the follow- <lb/>ing particulars. One half, of all born in the moun-
        <lb/>tains, live to the age of 47. In the marſhy pariſh, <lb/>one half live only to the age
        of 25. In the hills <lb/>one in 20, of all that are born, live to 80. In the <lb/>marſhy
        pariſh, only one in 52 reaches this age. <lb/>In the hills, a perſon aged 40 has a chance,
        of 80 <lb/>to 1, fro living a year. In the marſhy pariſh, his <lb/>chance for living a year
        is not 30 to 1.— In the <lb/>hills, perſon aged 20, 30, and 40, have an even <lb/>chance for
        living 41, 33, and 25 years reſpec- <lb/>tively. The the fenny pariſh, perſons, at theſe
        ages, <lb/>have an even chance of living only 30, 23, and <lb/>15 years.— In ſhort, it
        appears, that, though the <lb/>probabilities of life, in all this country except this
        <lb/>once pariſh, are much higher than in London; <lb/>yet here, after 30, they are much
        lower. Before <lb/>the age of 30, they are indeed higher in this <lb/>pariſh; the reaſon of
        which muſt be, that the <lb/>London air and cuſtoms are particulary noxious <lb/>to
        children. </p>
      <note n="*" place="bottom">
        <p rend="size(0.7)">
          <lb/>* In London, one half of all that are born, die under 3 <lb/>years of age. But this
          is not peculiar to London. In Berlin <lb/>the ſame proportion dies under three; and at
          Vienna under two. </p></note>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I am ſenſible, that obſervations, for only 15 years, <lb/>in one ſmall pariſh, do not
        afford as deciſive and <lb/>ample an authority, in the preſent caſe, as there <lb/>is reaſon
        to wiſh for; and that, therefore, the per- <lb/>fect exacneſs of the particulars I have
        recited, <lb/>cannot be depended on.— They are, however, ſuf- <pb n="98"/>
        <lb/>ficiently near the truth to demonſtrate, in general, <lb/>the unhealthfulneſs of a
        marſhy ſituation, and as <lb/>the regiſter form whence they are derived is the <lb/>only
        one, in ſuch a ſituation, which I have ever <lb/>met with, and Dr. <hi rend="sc"
          >Alexander</hi>'s experiments may <lb/>lead ſome to very wrong concluſions on this
        <lb/>ſubject; I could not help thinking, that there would <lb/>be no impropriety, in fending
        you the account, I <lb/>have now given. If you think it of any impor- <lb/>tance, I ſhall be
        obliged to you for reading it to <lb/>the Royal Society. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I cannot help taking this opportunity to add <lb/>my wiſhes, that ſuch regiſters of
        mortality, as thoſe <lb/>publiſhed by Mr. <hi rend="sc">Muret</hi>, were eſtabliſhed in
        every <lb/>part of this kingdom. We might then determine <lb/>immediately every ſuch
        queſtion, as that which has <lb/>occaſioned this letter; and know certainly, what
        <lb/>influence different airs and different ſituations have <lb/>on the duration of life.
        Two ingenious phyſicians, <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="sc">Percival</hi> at Mancheſter, and Dr. <hi
          rend="sc">Haygarth</hi>
        <lb/>at Cheſter, have lately, with much zeal, promoted <lb/>inſtitutions of this kind; and a
        great deal of uſeful <lb/>information may be expected, from the accurate <lb/>and
        comprehenſive regiſters of mortality, which, <lb/>under their direction, have been
        eſtabliſhed in theſe <lb/>towns. But the inſtruction ariſing from theſe <lb/>eſtabliſhments
        cannot be complete, till they be- <lb/>come univerſal. </p>
      <signed rend="align-center">
        <lb/>I am, Sir, <lb/>Your moſt obedient <lb/>and humble Servant, </signed>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <lb/>
      <dateline rend="size(0.8)">Newington Green, <lb/>Dec. 21, 1773. </dateline>
      <cb n="2"/>
      <signed rend="size(1.2) align-right">RICHARD PRICE. </signed>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
