<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Cooper: An Account of an Extraordinary Acephalous Birth</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>W. Cooper</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of an Extraordinary Acephalous Birth. By W. Cooper, M. D. in a Letter
              to William Hunter, M. D. F. R. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by W. Bowyer and J. Nichols: For Lockyer Davis, In
                  Holbourn, Printer to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1775</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">65</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">311-321</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111050536</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1775.0032</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT65_0311">
    <body>
      <pb n="311"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXX.</hi> An Account of an extraordinary acephalous Birth. <lb/>By <hi
          rend="roman">W. Cooper</hi>, M. D. in a Letter to <hi rend="roman">William Hunter</hi>,
        <lb/>M. D. F. R. S. </head>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <salute rend="sc indent">
        <lb/>dear sir, </salute>
      <p>
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="size(0.7)">Redde, <date>April 27, <lb/>1775. </date>
        </note><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> TAKE the liberty to remit you an ac- <lb/>count of the
        delivery of a very curious <lb/>acephalous monſter, accompanied with a ſhort deſcrip-
        <lb/>tion of its anatomical ſtructure. If, after a peruſal of it, <lb/>you ſhould apprehend
        it may be acceptable to the Royal <lb/>Society, I beg that you will do me the honour to lay
        it <lb/>before them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mrs. <hi rend="sc">brackett</hi>, of Clerkenwell Cloſe, aged twenty- <lb/>three years,
        was, at the end of her firſt pregnancy, by <lb/>a natural labour, delivered a perfect female
        child, <lb/>on Friday the 8th of October, 1773, at ſeven o'clock in <lb/>the morning. The
        attending midwife, Mrs. <hi rend="sc">ayres</hi>, ſoon <lb/>perceived by the abdominal
        tumour that there was ano- <lb/>ther child. After waiting about three hours, a flooding
        <lb/>came on; but without pain, or any advancement of the <lb/>ſecond delivery. The <hi
          rend="italic">hæmorrhage</hi> producing faintneſs, <lb/>debility, and danger, the
        attendants and midwife were <lb/>alarmed, and I was ſent for. When I came, I found <lb/>her
        in the ſituation above deſcribed; and therefore <pb n="312"/>
        <lb/>thought it my duty to accompliſh the remaining part of <lb/>the labour, as ſoon as I
        could, conſiſtently with the ſafety <lb/>of the mother. Upon all occaſions, when the con-
        <lb/>comitant circumſtances render it neceſſary to turn a child <lb/><hi rend="italic">in
          utero</hi>, it is of the utmoſt conſequence, to underſtand, <lb/>as nearly as we can, its
        general ſituation, in order to de- <lb/>liver with greater eaſe, ſafety, and expedition. And
        <lb/>to an experienced <hi rend="italic">accoucheur</hi>, if the breech, knees, or
        <lb/>feet, do not immediately preſent themſelves, the head <lb/>and face of the child will,
        in moſt caſes, be a ſufficient <lb/>index to the poſition of the other parts of its body.
        This <lb/>circumſtance ariſes from the <hi rend="italic">fœtus</hi> commonly coiling it-
        <lb/>ſelf up into an oblong, oval, ſnug, compact figure, with <lb/>its knees towards its
        chin, in order to take up as little <lb/>room as poſſible, by being adapted to the cavity of
        the <lb/><hi rend="italic">uterus</hi>. In the preſent caſe, when the patient was
        <lb/>placed in a proper ſituation, having introduced my hand <lb/>as gently as poſſible
        through the <hi rend="italic">vagina</hi>, <hi rend="italic">cervix uteri</hi>, and
        <lb/>inveloping membranes, and no part of the inferior ex- <lb/>tremities, or breech,
        preſenting itſelf, I examined care- <lb/>fully for the head of the child, as uſual, but
        without <lb/>ſucceſs. This diſappointment ſomewhat embarraſſed me. <lb/>But as the woman's
        ſituation was become very ſerious by <lb/>the increaſing <hi rend="italic">uterine
          hæmorrhage</hi>, I attempted without <lb/>delay to get at the feet. I eaſily ſecured one
        of them; <lb/>but though I made uſe of very little force in bringing it <lb/>towards the <hi
          rend="italic">os externum</hi>, the ſtructure was ſo very tender <lb/>that the <hi
          rend="italic">tibia</hi> began to give way at its ſuperior <hi rend="italic"
          >epiphyſis</hi>. <lb/>On this account I was reduced to the diſagreeable neceſ- <pb n="313"/>
        <lb/>ſity of again introducing my hand into the <hi rend="italic">uterus</hi>; and <lb/>as
        one leg had thus unexpectedly failed me, I thought it <lb/>extremely futile to attempt any
        thing with the other. <lb/>The moſt eligible reſource which I apprehended I had <lb/>now
        left, was to fix a blunt hook upon one groin, and, <lb/>when it was brought low enough, to
        aſſiſt gently at the <lb/>other, with the two fore-fingers of my right hand. By <lb/>theſe
        means I happily accompliſhed the delivery of the <lb/>remaining <hi rend="italic"
        >fœtus</hi>, which proved to be a very ſingular kind <lb/>of monſter. And as the late
        ingenious Mr. <hi rend="sc">hewson</hi> in- <lb/>jected its blood veſſels, and diſſected it,
        I am enabled to <lb/>attempt a ſhort anatomical deſription of it, for the ſatiſ-
        <lb/>faction of the curious in philoſophy and phyſiology. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This extraordinary animal production is of the ſize <lb/>and appearance of a common
        twin child at its full time, <lb/>excepting the particularities now to be pointed out.
        <lb/>When firſt born it was very plump, but ſoft and flabby, <lb/>and the bones remarkably
        ſmall and tender. It has nei- <lb/>ther head, neck, hands, or arms. In the place where the
        <lb/>neck ſhould originate, is a little <hi rend="italic">mamilla</hi>, ſomewhat <lb/>larger
        than a woman's nipple, but quite ſoft. And on <lb/>each ſide, in the place where the arm
        ſhould begin, there <lb/>is a ſmall <hi rend="italic">papilla</hi>, about the bigneſs, and
        very much like <lb/>the extremity, of a common quill. The ſpine ſeems per- <lb/>fect, but
        ends abruptly at the upper <hi rend="italic">vertebræ colli</hi>. Be- <lb/>low the navel the
        parts are nearly intire, except the feet, <lb/>where the toes are of an irregular form and
        ſize, and <lb/>ſome of them united together. The external parts of <lb/>generation, which
        indicate it a female, are alſo perfect. <pb n="314"/>
        <lb/>Upon a careful inſpection internally, there is evidently <lb/>no brain nor ſpinal
        marrow. A few nerves, however, <lb/>are ſcattered about the <hi rend="italic">abdomen</hi>;
        but their origin, for <lb/>fear of deſtroying the preparation, is not traced. The <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">uterus</hi> is perfect; but only one <hi rend="italic">ovarium</hi> could be
        found. <lb/>There is alſo the appearance of a bladder; but it is ſo <lb/>contracted as to
        have no cavity. A large inteſtine <lb/>ariſes from the <hi rend="italic">anus</hi>; is a
        good deal convoluted when it <lb/>gets above the brim of the <hi rend="italic">pelvis</hi>,
        and ends in a blind <lb/>pouch or <hi rend="italic">cul de ſac</hi>, on the left ſide of the
          <hi rend="italic">abdomen</hi>. This <lb/><hi rend="italic">viſcus</hi> appears to be
        about ſix or ſeven inches in length, <lb/>varies its ſize in different parts, gradually
        becomes ſmal- <lb/>ler towards its ſuperior extremity, and ſeems fully diſ- <lb/>tended with
        a colourleſs <hi rend="italic">mucus</hi>
        <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)" n="(a)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">(a)</hi> Does not this circumſtance almoſt amount to a proof,
            that the <hi rend="italic">meconium</hi>, <lb/>univerſally found in the bowels of
            new-born children, is nothing more than the <lb/><hi rend="italic">mucus</hi> naturally
            ſecreted by the inteſtinal glands, mixed with bile, and perhaps a <lb/>ſmall portion of
            the <hi rend="italic">pancreatic</hi> juice? In the preſent inſtance, as there is no
            liver <lb/>there could be no bile, and conſequently the <hi rend="italic">meconium</hi>,
            if I may ſo call it, is <lb/>colourleſs. </p>
        </note>. All above the na- <lb/>vel is extremely defective. There is no heart, lungs,
        <lb/>diaphragm, ſtomach, liver, kidnies, ſpleen, <hi rend="italic">pancreas</hi>, nor
        <lb/>ſmall inteſtines. However, there are three ſmall glands <lb/>in the place of the <hi
          rend="italic">thymus</hi>, whoſe ſubſtance, when exa- <lb/>mined with a microſcope, Mr.
          <hi rend="sc">hewson</hi> remarked, exactly <lb/>reſembled that of the <hi rend="italic"
          >thymus</hi> itſelf. And on each ſide of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">vena cava</hi>, juſt
        under the navel, are two little glan- <lb/>dular ſubſtance, which ſeem to be ſomewhat like
          <hi rend="italic">cap- <lb/>ſulæ renales</hi>, only very ſmall to what are commonly <pb
          n="315"/>
        <lb/>found <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)" n="(b)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">(b)</hi> Mr. <hi rend="sc">hewson</hi>, ſome time before his
            death, ſeemed to be confirmed in <lb/>the opinion, that whenever children are born with
            little or no brain, the <hi rend="italic">cap- <lb/>ſulæ renales</hi> are always very
            much diminiſhed. This is certainly the caſe in one <lb/>or two almoſt brainleſs children
            which I have by me, and whoſe <hi rend="italic">renal capſulæ</hi> he <lb/>examined,
            with a view of being further ſatisfied upon this ſubject. </p>
        </note>. There is a large artery running upon the <lb/>ſpine, which may be called the <hi
          rend="italic">aorta</hi>. As this approaches <lb/>the upper extremity of the little
        animal, it is divided <lb/>into ſmaller and ſmaller branches; and in its courſe it
        <lb/>diſtributes lateral ones alſo to the contiguous parts of the <lb/>trunk. Below the
        navel it ſends off tow branches that <lb/>conſtitute the umbilical arteries, one of which is
        conſi- <lb/>derably larger than the other. And then below theſe, <lb/>two other branches
        deſcend to the inferior extremities. <lb/>A large umbilical vein comes in at the navel, and
        is im- <lb/>mediately divided into two conſiderable branches; one <lb/>aſcending, the other
        deſcending. Each of theſe is again <lb/>ſub-divided into ſmaller and ſmaller branches,
        which, <lb/>as they paſs upwards and downwards, ſeem to correſpond <lb/>with the different
        ramifications of the aſcending and de- <lb/>ſcending <hi rend="italic">aorta</hi>. The <hi
          rend="italic">funis umbilicalis</hi> was only about <lb/>two inches in length <note
          place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)" n="(c)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">(c)</hi> An exactly ſimilar circumſtance to this I took
            particular notice of, in the <lb/>delivery of another almoſt brainleſs monſter. </p>
        </note>, and ſo very tender alſo, that it <lb/>unavoidably ſeparated near the navel of the
        child during <lb/>the delivery. Whether, therefore, there was any pulſa- <lb/>tion in this
        ſhort <hi rend="italic">funis</hi> I am not able to determine. The <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >placenta</hi> was not particularly examined. </p>
      <pb n="316"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Here are evidently in this <hi rend="italic">fœtus</hi> two diſtinct ſyſtems of
        <lb/>veſſels, arteries and veins <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)" n="(d)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">(d)</hi> Mr. <hi rend="sc">hewson</hi> attempted to inject the
            whole blood veſſels by the umbili- <lb/>cal vein as uſual. To his great ſurprize, no
            part of the injection returned by <lb/>the umbilical arteries. He could not account for
            this ſingularity at that time: <lb/>but as only a part of the veſſels were filled, he
            injected afreſh by one of the <hi rend="italic">hypo- <lb/>gaſtric</hi> arteries. Upon
            diſſection afterwards, this myſtery was unravelled by the <lb/>heart's being totally
            abſent. It then appeared alſo, that by the firſt inſpection <lb/>he had filled the venal
            ſyſtem, and by the latter the arterial. </p>
        </note>, that carried red blood <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)" n="(e)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">(e)</hi> See a very curious caſe related by Monſ. <hi rend="sc"
              >winslow</hi>, in the Memoires de <lb/>L'Académie des Sciences for 1740, p. 586. and
            604. Among other remarkable <lb/>ſingularities in this little monſtrous abortion of ſix
            months, that excellent ana- <lb/>tomiſt particularly takes notice, that there was no
            appearance of one drop of red <lb/>blood in any of its veſſels, which were univerſally
            filled with a ſerous <sic>lympth</sic>; <lb/>and that there were no veſtiges of any
            veins at all. </p>
        </note>. It <lb/>is plain alſo, that the blood paſſed from the internal <hi rend="italic"
          >iliac</hi>
        <lb/>arteries, through the <hi rend="italic"><choice>
            <corr>hypogaſtrics</corr>
            <sic>hypograſtrics</sic>
          </choice></hi> and <hi rend="italic">umbilicals</hi> to the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >placenta</hi>, and was returned from it by the umbilical vein <lb/>to the navel, and
        thence diſtributed in the manner be- <lb/>fore obſerved. But as there is no heart, nor any
        thing <lb/>analagous to one, it becomes extremely difficult to aſcer- <lb/>tain the powers
        by which the circulation was carried on <lb/>through this curious phyſiological phænomenon.
        May <lb/>we not however venture to advance a conjecture, that <lb/>the periſtaltick, or
        living muſcular power of the arteries, <lb/>was principally ſubſervient to this important
        end? Many <lb/>examples are to be met with in the collections of the cu- <lb/>rious and
        learned in the different parts of Europe <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)" n="(f)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">(f)</hi>
            <hi rend="sc">f. licetus</hi>, de Monſtris, p. 300. et ſeq. <hi rend="sc">palfyn</hi>
            Traité des Monſtres, <lb/>p. 325. <hi rend="sc">cheselden</hi>'s Anatomy, 5th ed. p.
            379. Philoſophical Tranſactions, <lb/>1739-40. N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 456. p. 303. Ibid.
            1767, p. 1. L'Académie des Sciences, Hiſt. <pb n="317" type="footnote"/>
            <lb/>1720, p. 13. Ibid. Mem. 1720, p. 8. Ibid. 1740, p<choice>
              <corr>.</corr>
              <sic/>
            </choice> 586. and p. 592. Miſ- <lb/>cellania Curioſa Ephemeridum Germanicarum Ann. XIX.
            p. 258. Acta Eru- <lb/>ditorum Lipſiæ, Ann. 1724, p. 501. </p>
        </note>, <pb n="317"/>
        <lb/>which are ſomewhat ſimilar to that now related. When <lb/>carefully examined, however,
        excepting a very few in- <lb/>ſtances, they are generally found either eſſentially to
        <lb/>differ, or elſe their ſtructure has not been, with any to- <lb/>lerable preciſion,
        explained. The preſent hiſtory af- <lb/>fords alſo an exception to a frequent remark among
        au- <lb/>thors, <q rend="diple quotes">That brainleſs children are always very briſk
          <lb/>before they are born <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)" n="(g)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">(g)</hi> Philoſophical Tranſactions, 1674, N<hi rend="sup"
                >o</hi> XCIX. p. 6157. Ibid. 1767, <lb/>p. 18. </p>
          </note>; </q> for the mother has fre- <lb/>quently told me, <q rend="diple quotes">That
          ſhe felt no motion at all within <lb/>her after the firſt birth; and that ſhe had not the
          leaſt <lb/>ſuſpicion of there being a ſecond child till it was deli- <lb/>vered. </q> This
        circumſtance may however, perhaps, be <lb/>attributed to the <hi rend="italic">medulla
          ſpinalis</hi> being totally deficient, <lb/>as well as the <hi rend="italic">cerebrum</hi>
        and <hi rend="italic">cerebellum</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Phyſiologiſts and philoſophers have ſpent a great deal <lb/>of time in attempting to
        inveſtigate the cauſes of theſe <lb/>extraordinary phænomena. With this view many opi-
        <lb/>nions have been ſtarted; but moſt, if not all of them, as <lb/>far as I am able to
        judge, being built upon the tottering <lb/>baſis of conjecture only, afford, upon an
        attentive in- <lb/>ſpection, but little ſatisfaction to a diſpaſſionate enquirer <lb/>after
        truth. The particular hypotheſis, which has <lb/>been almoſt univerſally adopted, is, that
        monſtroſity and <lb/>marks in children depend upon the imagination and <pb n="318"/>
        <lb/>longing of the mother. Such pernicious a principle as this <lb/>ought to have very
        rational evidence, and the moſt ſtriking <lb/>facts to ſupport it. But is it not directly
        the contrary? <lb/>Indeed a great many ridiculous ſtories have been related <lb/>to the
        world <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)" n="(h)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">(h)</hi>
            <hi rend="sc">mauriceau</hi>, p. 53. Obſ. 64. Ibid. p. 63. Obſ. 118. <hi rend="sc"
              >smellie</hi>'s <lb/>Midwifry, vol. III. p. 402. Philoſophical Tranſactions, 1684,
              N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 160. p. 599. <lb/>Ibid. 1739-40, N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 456. p.
            303. and 306. </p>
        </note>, which, however, upon a little reflection <lb/>either obviate themſelves, or elſe
        are contradicted by <lb/>thoſe facts that occur. May we not exemplify this ob-
        <lb/>ſervation by the caſe of twins now related? One of the <lb/>children was perfect, and
        is ſtill living; the other proves <lb/>to be remarkably defective. Does not the queſtion na-
        <lb/>turally ariſe here, how could one child be affected by <lb/>the diſturbed imagination
        of the mother and not the <lb/>other? But the mother, upon repeated examination,
        <lb/>recollects no fright in particular while ſhe was preg- <lb/>nant. Neither, if ſhe did,
        would it all invalidate the <lb/>force of our argument upon this ſubject; for ſhe could
        <lb/>not poſſibly ſee any child wihout a head: and more eſ- <lb/>pecially, becauſe other
        parts, as the <hi rend="italic">viſcera</hi> and <hi rend="italic">medulla
          <lb/>ſpinalis</hi>, were equally defective, which are entirely out <lb/>of the reach of
        the eye or imagination of the mother <lb/>to form any idea about them. To elucidate this
        point <lb/>ſtill further, can any candid perſon poſſibly ſup- <lb/>poſe, that the caſual
        agitation of mind of a pregnant <lb/>woman, ſhould either produce or deſtroy a whole
        <lb/>ſyſtem of blood-veſſels, nerves, and fibres, which are <lb/>indiſpenſable conſtituents
        of almoſt every part of the <pb n="319"/>
        <lb/>body? And may we not adduce one proof more, in ſup- <lb/>port of our argument, from
        what happens to animals <lb/>and vegetables? Among theſe alſo, ſuch extraordinary
        <lb/>deviations from the general courſe of nature are by no <lb/>means uncommon: yet the
        former are poſſeſſed of a much <lb/>leſs ſhare of imagination than is generally allotted to
        the <lb/>human ſpecies; and the latter have none at all. Rea- <lb/>ſoning in the ſame manner
        upon ſeveral occaſions of this <lb/>kind in which I have been concerned, my concluſions
        <lb/>have always been ſimilar; <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> that the uſually aſſigned
        <lb/>cauſe of the mother's imagination is by no means equal <lb/>to the manifold effects
        produced. And on the other <lb/>hand, this injurious doctrine is pregnant with continual
        <lb/>miſchief to ſociety. It frequently makes women very <lb/>unhappy. And the fear of
        mutilating or marking their <lb/>infants often affects them ſo much, that they at laſt miſ-
        <lb/>carry. Having therefore indubitable facts to go upon, <lb/>and the cauſe of humanity ſo
        powerfully coinciding with <lb/>the truth, is it not right to affirm and maintain with con-
        <lb/>fidence, that neither the longing nor frighted imagi- <lb/>nation of the mother appears
        to have any power at all <lb/>to imprint marks or monſtroſity upon children? That <lb/>this
        is a very weak ſuppoſition, entirely void of founda- <lb/>tion, directly contrary to all
        philoſophy and experience, <lb/>and has nothing to ſupport it but a vulgar opinion, tranſ-
        <lb/>mitted to us from the ages of anatomical ignorance? <lb/>And is it not more reaſonable
        to conclude with you, <hi rend="sc">sir</hi>, <lb/>in your extenſively uſeful lectures, that
        whatever be the <lb/>defect or deformity in a monſtrous birth, it can never be <pb n="320"/>
        <lb/>occaſioned by accidents of any kind during pregnancy; <lb/>but probably has its
        exiſtence always originating, <hi rend="italic">cauſâ <lb/>adhuc incognitâ</hi>, in the
        firſt ſtamina of the embryo <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)" n="(i)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">(i)</hi> The great baron <hi rend="sc">haller</hi> is of opinion
            alſo, that this is evidently the <lb/>caſe in that ſpecies of monſters to which parts
            are added. Vide Opera Minora <lb/><hi rend="sc">halleri</hi>, tom. III. p. 148. </p>
        </note>? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thus, <hi rend="sc">sir</hi>, I have faithfully related the particulars of <lb/>this
        ſingular phænomenon among the human ſpecies, <lb/>which, to a demonſtration, confirms your
        opinion, that <lb/>the nouriſhment of the <hi rend="italic">fœtus in utero</hi> is
        principally by <lb/>means of the <hi rend="italic">funis umbilicalis</hi>. M. <hi rend="sc"
          >merry</hi> obſerves, that <lb/>defective monſters are more inſtructive than others that
        <lb/>have redundacies <note n="(k)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">(k)</hi> L' Académie des Sciences, Hiſt. 1720, p. 13. </p>
        </note>. If this be true, here is ſtill an <lb/>ample field for ſpeculation, notwithſtanding
        the few very <lb/>obvious remarks which I have already ventured to make. <lb/>In conformity
        to the general language of authors, I have <lb/>in this eſſay occaſionally adopted the uſe
        of the term <lb/><hi rend="italic">monſter</hi>. There is, however, ſomething in that word
        ex- <lb/>tremely repugnant to our common feelings, and very apt <lb/>to leave a terrifying
        impreſſion upon the mind. Why <lb/>may not the Author of Being ſometimes produce varia-
        <lb/>tions in the human ſpecies, as well as in the animal and <lb/>vegetable kingdom <note
          place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)" n="(l)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">(l)</hi> See <hi rend="sc">f. licetus</hi>. <hi rend="sc">j
              palfyn</hi> des Monſtres, &amp;c. in which are many in- <lb/>ſtances of each kind.
          </p>
        </note>, and equally exempt too from <lb/>ſuch frightful appellations? Would it not,
        therefore, <lb/>be more eligible in the preſent inſtance, and every ſimi- <lb/>lar one, to
        explode the common term, and call it ſimply <pb n="321"/>
        <lb/>a <hi rend="italic">luſus naturæ</hi>; or with <hi rend="sc">pliny</hi> to ſay, <hi
          rend="italic">
          <q rend="diple quotes">Hoc nobis mira- <lb/>culum, ſibi ludibrium, ingenioſa finxit
            natura. </q></hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The peculiar ſhare of your friendſhip, with which <lb/>you are pleaſed to honour me,
        makes me flatter myſelf <lb/>that you will give me credit for the truth of any facts
        <lb/>advanced in the courſe of the detail, that are not irre- <lb/>fragably evidenced by a
        recourſe to the preparation in its <lb/>preſent ſtate. </p>
      <signed rend="align-center space">
        <lb/>I am, &amp;c. </signed>
      <dateline rend="size(0.6)">
        <lb/>Norfolk-ſtreet, <lb/>June 6, 1774. </dateline>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
