<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Hamilton: An Account of a Suppression of Urine Cured by a Puncture
          Made in the Bladder</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Robert Hamilton</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of a Suppression of Urine Cured by a Puncture Made in the Bladder
              through the Anus; Being an Extract of a Letter from Dr. Robert Hamilton, Fellow of the
              Royal College of Physicians at Edinburgh, and Physician at King's-Lynn, in Norfolk, to
              Sir John Pringle, Bart. P. R. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by W. Bowyer and J. Nichols: For Lockyer Davis, In
                  Holbourn, Printer to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1776</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">66</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">578-586</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110532989</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1776.0040</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT66_0578">
    <body>
      <pb n="578"/>
      <head rend="hanging italic">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXXIX.</hi> An Account of a Suppreſſion of Urine cured by a
        <lb/>Puncture made in the Bladder through the <hi rend="roman">Anus</hi>; being <lb/>an
        Extract of a Letter from Dr. <hi rend="roman">Robert Hamilton</hi>, <lb/>Fellow of the Royal
        College of Phyſicians at <hi rend="roman">Edinburgh</hi>, <lb/>and Phyſician at <hi
          rend="roman">King's-Lynn</hi>, in <hi rend="roman">Norfolk</hi>, to Sir <hi rend="roman"
          >John <lb/>Pringle</hi>, Bart. P. R. S. </head>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <p>
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="size(0.7) hanging">R. <date>May 23, <lb/>1776. </date>
        </note><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> WAS ſent for on the 25th of March, 1774, <lb/>to viſit <hi
          rend="sc">james wilkinson</hi>, of about thirty- <lb/>one years of age, the ſon of a
        farrier in this town, who <lb/>had laboured under a ſuppreſſion of urine for three
        <lb/>days. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The account this man gave of himſelf was, that he <lb/>had been fourteen years a
        ſoldier in a regiment of foot, <lb/>but had been diſcharged the preceding year as unfit for
        <lb/>ſervice, on account of this diſorder, to which he had been <lb/>long ſubject, and which
        was ſuppoſed to originate from <lb/>a ſtone in the neck of his bladder; that, about twelve
        <lb/>years before his diſcharge, he had contracted a <hi rend="italic">gonor-
        <lb/>rhœa</hi>, which had been badly cured; that, from that pe- <lb/>riod, he had become
        afflicted with frequent ſuppreſſions <lb/>of urine, and that every return had ben of longer
        dura- <lb/>tion than the former; that when the ſuppreſſion had <lb/>continued ſome time, he
        had been uſed to go to the Regi- <lb/>mental Hoſpital, and to ſtay till it was removed; and
        that, <pb n="579"/>
        <lb/>bleeding, purging, and the warm-bath had been the <lb/>means uſed for his relieſ. He
        added, that the catheter <lb/>could never be introduced into his bladder from the firſt
        <lb/>attack; that the firſt ſigns of relief were a few involun- <lb/>tary drops of urine
        iſſuing from the <hi rend="italic">urethra</hi>, after which <lb/>followed a ſmall
        thread-like ſtream, which continued to <lb/>run until the bladder was a little more than
        half emp- <lb/>tied; for he did not think that his urine had at any time <lb/>been perfectly
        diſcharged, during the thirteen years he <lb/>had been afflicted with this painful diſorder.
        He con- <lb/>cluded with telling me, that in other reſpects he had <lb/>enjoyed good health;
        and that the preſent ſuppreſſion <lb/>had been brought on by hard riding on a journey he had
        <lb/>undertaken to go expreſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This man was in a very diſtreſſed condition. His <lb/>bladder was diſtended to an
        enormous ſize, reſembling <lb/>the gravid <hi rend="italic">uterus</hi> at that late period
        of geſtation, when <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">fundus</hi> reaches above the navel; to ſuch a
        degree was <lb/>it dilated by the repeated ſuppreſſions of urine for ſo <lb/>many years. His
        pulſe was ſmall and quick; he had <lb/>been troubled with a hiccup for many hours; and had
        <lb/>vomited every thing he had taken from the firſt day of <lb/>his illneſs. His head and
        face were emphyſematous from <lb/>ſtraining; and the cellular membrane was ſo much in-
        <lb/>flated, that he could not open his eye-lids. He was at- <lb/>tended by two ſurgeons,
        who had uſed bleeding, opiates, <lb/>clyſters, fomentations, and the warm-bath, without any
        <lb/>benefit; and they had repeatedly attempted to intro- <lb/>duce catheters of different
        ſizes, without ſucceſs; that <lb/>inſtrument, having paſſed without reſiſtance to the neck
          <pb n="580"/>
        <lb/>of the bladder, met there with an obſtruction not to be <lb/>overcome. Under ſuch
        preſſing circumstances no time <lb/>was to be loſt. The patient's life was in imminent dan-
        <lb/>ger, either from a rupture, or a gangrene of the bladder. <lb/>The approach of the
        latter was ſoon to be apprehended, <lb/>from the hiccup and ſmallneſs of the pulſe. There
        was <lb/>no alternative left; the bladder muſt be ſpeedily emptied <lb/>by an aperture
        ſomewhere, or the patient muſt periſh. <lb/>The ſurgeons, therefore, went to prepare thier
        inſtru- <lb/>ments for making an opening into the bladder. Re- <lb/>flecting, in their
        abſence, on the moſt eligible method <lb/>of performing the operation, I was in ſome degree
        of <lb/>perplexity; for I did not much approve of any of the <lb/>methods recommended by the
        beſt chirurgical writers; <lb/>either that of making a perforation above the <hi
          rend="italic">os pubis</hi>, <lb/>in the place where the higher operation of lithotomy
        <lb/>is performed; or that of the puncture <hi rend="italic">in perinæo</hi>. Whilſt <lb/>I
        was conſidering what was to be done, the mother of <lb/>the patient told me, that ſhe had
        ſeveral times that day <lb/>attempted to give him a cyſter, but had not been able to
        <lb/>introduce the pipe, by reaſon of a large ſubſtance low in <lb/>the gut near the
        fundament, which ſtopped up the paſ- <lb/>ſage. It immediately occured to me, that the
        obſtructing <lb/>body could be no other than the diſtended bladder, which, <lb/>having
        filled the <hi rend="italic">pelvis</hi>, preſſed downwards where there <lb/>was the leaſt
        reſiſtance towards the <hi rend="italic">anus</hi>, as well as up- <lb/>wards into the <hi
          rend="italic">abdomen</hi>. From this circumſtance I was led <lb/>to think, of diſcharging
        the urine by a puncture into the <lb/>bladder, with a trocar introduced by the <hi
          rend="italic">anus</hi>. I con- <lb/>ceived that this method would have advantages
        ſuperior <pb n="581"/>
        <lb/>to any other that I had heard of, for ſimplicity, eaſe, and <lb/>ſafety. The finger
        could guide the point of the inſtru- <lb/>ment to the very ſpot of the bladder to be
        pierced. The <lb/>coats of the <hi rend="italic">inteſtinum rectum</hi> and bladder, and the
        inter- <lb/>vening cellular membrane, were all that were to be per- <lb/>forated, and they
        were now preſſed ſo cloſely together, <lb/>that there could be no more art required than in
        piercing <lb/>any ſimple bag of water. When the ſurgeons returned, <lb/>I told them what had
        occured to me concerning the <lb/>deſcent of the diſtended bladder (for I had not yet exa-
        <lb/>mined it) and its preſſing the <hi rend="italic">rectum</hi> downwards; I re-
        <lb/>preſented to them the hazard and difficulty attending the <lb/>operation hitherto in
        uſe, and propoſed this method of <lb/>perforating the bladder with a trocar introduced by
        the <lb/><hi rend="italic">anus</hi>. They readily acknowledged the advantage of ſuch <lb/>a
        practice, and agreed to give it the preference. We <lb/>examined with a finger <hi
          rend="italic">in ano</hi>, and felt a large round <lb/>tumor, a very little way within the
        orifice, preſſing the <lb/>anterior ſide of the <hi rend="italic">rectum</hi> downwards, and
        puſhing the <lb/><hi rend="italic">anus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">perinæum</hi>
        conſiderably outwards. The gut itſelf <lb/>was looſe and empty; and through its relaxed
        ſides the <lb/>tumor,which was evidently the bladder, was diſtinctly <lb/>felt ſtretching
        every way, completely filling the <hi rend="italic">pelvis</hi>, <lb/>and feeling like the
        membranes which contain the wa- <lb/>ters of a woman in labour, thruſt into the dilated <hi
          rend="italic">vagina</hi>. <lb/>I deſcribed the manner in which I thought the punc-
        <lb/>ture ſhould be made; and, as I imagined that I could <lb/>better execute what I had
        myſelf conceived than another <lb/>perſon, I offered to do it; which being readily aſſented
        to <pb n="582"/>
        <lb/>the operation was performed in the following manner. <lb/>Having placed the patient on
        his back on a bed, with his <lb/>breech projecting a little over the ſide of it towards the
        <lb/>light, and his legs bent into the poſition they are placed <lb/>in for the operation of
        lithotomy, and held by two aſ- <lb/>ſiſtants, a trocar of the middle ſize, with its point
        <lb/>guarded by the extremity of the fore-finger well oiled, <lb/>was introduced into the
          <hi rend="italic">anus</hi>, until the tip of the finger <lb/>reached the anterior part of
        the tumor; when the finger <lb/>being a little withdrawn, and the point of the inſtrument
        <lb/>brought into contact with the tumor, it was plunged into <lb/>it, in a direction
        parallel to the axis of the bladder, in an <lb/>erect poſture; and the perforator being
        pulled out, the <lb/>water immediately followed. A ſtraight catheter was <lb/>quickly
        introduced through the canula into the bladder, <lb/>leſt, as it collapſed and ſhrunk
        upwards as the water was <lb/>diſcharged, the canula ſhould prove too ſhort, for its ſhell
        <lb/>was then cloſe to the <hi rend="italic">anus</hi>. The canula was then ſlipped <lb/>out
        of the aperture as far as the rings of the catheter, as <lb/>being no longer of uſe, and the
        catheter remained in <lb/>the bladder until the urine was all drawn off; during <lb/>which
        time, that inſtrument was moved different ways, <lb/>to ſearch for the ſtone which was
        ſuppoſed originally to <lb/>have occaſioned the diſorder; but none was to be found. <lb/>The
        water being diſcharged, the catherer was taken out, <lb/>and the patient put to bed. The
        parts were repeatedly <lb/>fomented; and a draught, with half a drachm of nitre <lb/>and 25
        drops of laudanum were given, and two more of <lb/>the ſame kind were ordered for the night. </p>
      <pb n="583"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>26th, He had had a very good night, and had made <lb/>water five or ſix times through
        the aperture made by the <lb/>trocar. He ſaid, that as ſoon as the bladder had collected
        <lb/>a certain quantity of urine, he had felt an inclination to <lb/>make water; that then
        ſitting on a chamber-pot or bed- <lb/>pan, and ſtraining in the uſual way, the urine had
        ruſhed <lb/>out at the aperture <hi rend="italic">per anum</hi> in a ſtream; and that none
        had <lb/>paſſed by the <hi rend="italic">urethra</hi>. Not contended with his account of
        <lb/>the matter, I deſired him to make water in my preſence, <lb/>and was witneſs to this
        curious and extraordinary power <lb/>of retention of the urine in a wounded bladder, and of
        <lb/>diſcharging it at pleaſure through an artificial paſſage. <lb/>The emphyſematous
        ſwelling of his head and face was al- <lb/>moſt gone. He was directed to drink the pectoral
        decoction <lb/>with the addition of ſome marſh-mallow root, ſweetened <lb/>with manna, and
        acidulated with orange or lemon-juice; <lb/>and the nitrous opiate was repeated. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>27th, He complained of a fulneſs of his belly, pro- <lb/>bably owing to his not having
        had a ſtool. He ſtill made <lb/>water through the trocar-aperture as before, and when-
        <lb/>ever he pleaſed; but now he began to perceive a little <lb/>urine come by the <hi
          rend="italic">urethra</hi> at the ſame time. We did not <lb/>chooſe to order a clyſter,
        leſt the gut ſhould be injured by <lb/>the pipe, but to wait the effect of the manna, which,
        <lb/>with the night-draught, was ſtill continued. The re- <lb/>ſolution of the inflammation
        being now begun, as was <lb/>conjectured by the urine finding its natural paſſage by
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">urethra</hi>, a bougie was introduced beyond the ſtricture
        <lb/>at the neck of the bladder, and to very good purpoſe. </p>
      <pb n="584"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>28th, He was much better, he had had ſome ſtools, <lb/>and had paſſed moſt of his urine
        by the <hi rend="italic">urethra</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>30th, No water had iſſued through the aperture either <lb/>this morning or the
        preceding day; the whole, though in <lb/>a ſmall ſtream, had flowed by the <hi rend="italic"
          >urethra</hi>. He complained <lb/>of a ſoreneſs <hi rend="italic">in ano</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>31st, This day he felt that ſoreneſs only when he went <lb/>to ſtool. The ſtream of
        urine by the <hi rend="italic">urethra</hi> was ſtill <lb/>ſmall. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>April 6th, The puncture through the <hi rend="italic">rectum</hi> and <lb/>bladder
        appeared to be quite healed. The urine was diſ- <lb/>charged in a tolerable ſtream, the
        paſſage being, as he <lb/>obſerved, much wider than it had been for thirteen years
        <lb/>before. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He continued the daily uſe of the bougies; and, <lb/>being ſenſible of the great
        benefit he had received from <lb/>them, willingly perſevered in their uſe, until the ſtric-
        <lb/>ture was ſo much leſſened, as to permit a free diſcharge <lb/>of his water, and by
        theſe means he obtained a complete <lb/>cure: for, in two months after, he left the town in
        every <lb/>reſpect well. It was remarkable, that, during the pro- <lb/>greſs of the cure, no
        urine was perceived to ooze invo- <lb/>luntarily through the opening; but it was always re-
        <lb/>tained until the patient, prompted by a fulneſs of the <lb/>bladder, made his water, as
        has been related. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having given as accurate an account of this caſe as I <lb/>am able, I muſt now, <hi
          rend="sc">sir</hi>, in juſtice to myſelf, beg leave <lb/>to aſſure you, that I had neither
        heard, nor read, of any <lb/>method of perforating the bladder, ſimilar to that which <lb/>I
        have related, before you kindly informed me in your <pb n="585"/>
        <lb/>laſt letter, that it was not a new operation; and that I <lb/>ſhould find an account of
        it in <hi rend="sc">pouteau</hi>'s <hi rend="italic">Melanges de <lb/>Chirurgie</hi>. I have
        procured the book, and have read the <lb/>paper with great ſatisfaction, and am much obliged
        to you <lb/>for your intelligence. I do not preſume to claim any <lb/>merit from a thing
        which took its riſe from mere acci- <lb/>dent. The obſtruction which the pipe met with when
        the <lb/>patient's mother attempted to give him the clyſter,ſug- <lb/>geſted the method of
        piercing the bladder by the <hi rend="italic">anus</hi>; and <lb/>I am perſwaded, that the
        ſame thought would have ariſen, <lb/>on a like occaſion, in the mind of any thinking man.
        <lb/>And I beg you would believe, that I have no ſmall ſatisfac- <lb/>tion in finding it
        occured to M. <hi rend="sc">flurant</hi>, the ingenious <lb/>author of the paper on that
        ſubject, in that publication, <lb/>from a circumſtance, which, though not exactly ſimilar,
        <lb/>amounted nearly to the ſame thing. This ſurgeon hav- <lb/>ing introduced his finger
        into the <hi rend="italic">anus</hi>, to examine the <lb/>ſtate of the bladder, in order to
        perform the puncture <hi rend="italic">in <lb/>perinæo</hi>, found it ſo round and tumid,
        and ſo much within <lb/>the reach of his inſtrument, that he thought he could <lb/>perforate
        it with ſafety in that place; and, from a little <lb/>reflection on the ſtructure of the
        parts, was convinced of <lb/>the expediency of operating in this manner, in preference
        <lb/>to any other. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Before I quit this ſubject, I think it proper to acquaint <lb/>you, that I have found a
        compoſition of calomel and opium, <lb/>in large doſes, the beſt internal remedy for
        ſuppreſſions <lb/>of urine, in general; and that I have repeatedly ſeen this <lb/>medicine
        ſucceed after the uſual means have failed. I am <pb n="586"/>
        <lb/>convinced, from theſe trials, that the principal or ſpecific <lb/>efficacy is in the
        calomel, as large doſes of opium alone, <lb/>or joined with camphire, have proved
        unſucceſsful. I <lb/>am ſo well ſatisfied of the advantages of this practice, <lb/>that, if
        called early in the diſorder, I direct ten grains of <lb/>calomel with two grains of ſolid
        opium, made into a bolus <lb/>with any conſerve, to be taken immediately, and re-
        <lb/>peated in ſix hours. I have ſeldom occaſion to order a <lb/>third doſe, the patient
        being generally relieved by the <lb/>ſecond, if the firſt has failed. I did not adminiſter
        it in <lb/>the caſe here related, becauſe the alarming ſituation the <lb/>patient was in
        when I came to him required the bladder <lb/>to be emptied without delay. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
