<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Darwin and Astle: A New Case in Squinting</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Erasmus Darwin</persName>
              <persName>Thomas Astle</persName>
            </author>
            <title>A New Case in Squinting, by Erasmus Darwin, M. D. F. R. S.; Communicated by
              Thomas Astle, Esq. F. R. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by J. Nichols, successor to Mr. Bowyer; For Lockyer Davis,
                  Printer to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1778</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">68</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">86-96</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111038263</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1778.0004</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT68_0086">
    <body>
      <pb n="86"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">IV.</hi> A new Caſe in Squinting, by <hi rend="roman">Eraſmus
          Darwin</hi>, <lb/>M. D. F. R. S.; communicated by <hi rend="roman">Thomas Aſtle</hi>, Eſq.
        <lb/>F. R. S. </head>
      <dateline rend="size(0.7) space align-right">Litchfield, March 10, 1777. </dateline>
      <p>
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="size(0.7) hanging">Read <date>Jan. 15, <lb/>1777. </date>
        </note><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE following caſe in ſquinting, as a <lb/>ſimilar one has not
        been recorded or <lb/>explained by others, may perhaps merit your attention <lb/>from its
        novelty. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About ſx years ago I was deſired to ſee a child of the <lb/>reverend Dr. <hi rend="sc"
          >sandford</hi>, in Shropſhire, to determine if <lb/>any method could be deviſed to cure
        him of ſquinting. <lb/>The child was then about five years old, and exceedingly
        <lb/>tractable and ſenſible, which enabled me to make the <lb/>following obſervations upon
        him with great accuracy <lb/>and frequent repetition. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I. He viewed every object which was preſented to <lb/>him with but one eye at a time. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2. If the object was preſented on his right-ſide, he <lb/>viewed it with his left eye;
        and if it was preſented on <lb/>his left-ſide, he viewed it with his right eye. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>3. He turned the pupil of that eye, which was on the <lb/>ſame ſide with the object, in
        ſuch a direction that the <pb n="87"/>
        <lb/>image of the object might fall on that part of the bot- <lb/>tom of the eye where the
        optic nerve enters it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>4. When an object was held directly before him, <lb/>he turned his head a little to one
        ſide, and obſerved it <lb/>with but one eye, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> with that moſt
        diſtant from the <lb/>object, turning away the other in the manner above de- <lb/>ſcribed;
        and when he became tired with obſerving it <lb/>with that eye, he turned his head the
        contrary way, and <lb/>obſerved it with the other eye alone, with equal facility; <lb/>but
        never turned the axes of both eyes on it at the ſame <lb/>time. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>5. He ſaw letters, which were written on bits of pa- <lb/>per, ſo as to name them with
        equal eaſe, and at equal <lb/>diſtances, with one eye as with the other. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>6. There was no perceptible difference in the diame- <lb/>ters of the iriſes, nor in
        the contractibility of them, after <lb/>having covered his eyes from the light. Theſe
        obſerva- <lb/>tions were carefully made by writing ſingle letters on <lb/>ſhreds of paper,
        and laying wagers with the child that <lb/>he could not read them when they were preſented
        at <lb/>certain diſtances and directions. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From theſe circumstances it appeared, that there was <lb/>no defect in either eye,
        which is the common cauſe of <lb/>ſquinting, ſo well obſerved by M. <hi rend="sc"
          >buffon</hi> and Dr. <hi rend="sc">reid</hi>; <lb/>and hence, that the diſeaſe was ſimply
        a depraved habit <lb/>of moving his eyes, and might probably be occaſioned <pb n="88"/>
        <lb/>by the form of a cap or head-dreſs, which might have <lb/>been too prominent on the
        ſides of his face, like bluffs <lb/>uſed on coach-horſes; and might thence, in early
        infancy, <lb/>have made it more convenient for the child to view ob- <lb/>jects placed
        obliquely with the oppoſite eye, till by habit <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">muſculi
          adductores</hi> were become ſtronger, and more <lb/>ready for motion than their
        antagoniſts. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A paper gnomon was made, and fixed to a cap; and <lb/>when this artificial noſe was
        placed over his real noſe, ſo <lb/>as to project an inch between his eyes, the child, rather
        <lb/>than turn his head ſo far to look at oblique objects, im- <lb/>mediately began to view
        them with that eye which was <lb/>next to them. But the death of Dr. <hi rend="sc"
          >sandford</hi>, which <lb/>happened ſoon after, occaſioned the removal of his fa-
        <lb/>mily; and the grief and cares of Mrs. <hi rend="sc">sandford</hi> pre- <lb/>vented
        this, and the other methods propoſed, from being <lb/>put in execution. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About a month ago I had again an opportunity of <lb/>ſeeing maſter <hi rend="sc">d.
          sandford</hi>, and obſerved all the circum- <lb/>ſtances of his mode of viſion to be
        exactly as they were <lb/>ſix years before, except that they ſeemed eſtabliſhed by
        <lb/>longer habit; ſo that I could not by any means induce <lb/>him to bend the axes of both
        his eyes on the ſame object, <lb/>not even for a moment. </p>
      <pb n="89"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A gnomon of thin braſs was made to ſtand over his <lb/>noſe, with a half circle of the
        ſame metal to go round <lb/>his temples; theſe were covered with black ſilk, and by
        <lb/>means of a buckle behind his head, and a croſs-piece <lb/>over the crown of his head,
        this gnomon was managed <lb/>ſo as to be worn without any inconvenience, and pro-
        <lb/>jected before his noſe about two inches and an half. By <lb/>the uſe of this gnomon he
        ſoon found it leſs inconve- <lb/>nient to view all oblique objects with the eye next to
        <lb/>them, inſtead of the eye oppoſite to them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After this habit was weakened by a week's uſe of the <lb/>gnomon, two bits of wood,
        about the ſize of a gooſe- <lb/>quill, were blackened all but a quarter of an inch at their
        <lb/>ſummits; theſe were frequently preſented for him to <lb/>look at, one being held on one
        ſide the extremity of his <lb/>black gnomon, and the other on the other ſide of it. As
        <lb/>he viewed theſe they were gradually brought forwards <lb/>beyond the gnomon, and then
        one was concealed behind <lb/>the other: by theſe means, in another week, he could <lb/>bend
        both his eyes on the ſame object for half a minute <lb/>together. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By the practice of this exerciſe before a glaſs, almoſt <lb/>every hour in the day, he
        became in another week able <lb/>to read for a minute together with his eyes both directed
        <lb/>on the ſame objects; and I have no doubt, if he has pa- <pb n="90"/>
        <lb/>tience enough to perſevere in theſe efforts, but he will <lb/>in the courſe of ſome
        months overcome this unſightly <lb/>habit. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I ſhall conclude the account of this caſe by adding, <lb/>that all the other ſquinting
        people I have had occaſion <lb/>to attend to, have had one eye much leſs perfect than the
        <lb/>other, according to the obſervations of Mr. <hi rend="sc">buffon</hi> and <lb/>Dr. <hi
          rend="sc">reid</hi>. Theſe patients, where the diſeaſed eye is not <lb/>too bad, are
        certainly curable by covering the beſt eye <lb/>many hours in a day; as, by a more frequent
        uſe of the <lb/>weak eye, it not only accquires a habit of turning to the <lb/>objects which
        the patient wiſhes to ſee, but gains at the <lb/>ſame time a more diſtinct viſion; and the
        better eye at <lb/>the ſame time ſeems to loſe ſomewhat in both theſe <lb/>reſpects, which
        alſo facilitates the cure. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This evinces are abſurdity of the practice of prohibit- <lb/>ing thoſe who have weak
        eyes from uſing them; ſince <lb/>the eye, as well as every other part of the body, acquires
        <lb/>ſtrength from that degree of exerciſe which is not ac- <lb/>companied with pain or
        fatigue; and I am induced to <lb/>believe, that the moſt general cauſe of ſquinting in chil-
        <lb/>dren originates from the cuſtom of covering the weak <lb/>eye, which has been diſeaſed
        by any accidental cauſe, <lb/>before the habit of obſerving objects with both eyes was
        <lb/>perfectly eſtabliſhed. </p>
      <pb n="91"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The facility with which maſter <hi rend="sc">sandford</hi> received <lb/>the images of
        oblique objects on the inſenſible part of <lb/>the retina of one eye, whilſt he viewed them
        with the <lb/>other, induced me to obſerve the ſize of this inſenſible <lb/>ſpot, and to
        endeavour to aſcertain the cauſe of it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There was formerly a diſpute among philoſophers, <lb/>whether the choroid coat of the
        eye or the retina was the <lb/>immediate organ of viſion, which has lately been re-
        <lb/>vived in ſome meaſure in Dr. <hi rend="sc">priestley</hi>'s valuable Hiſ- <lb/>tory of
        Light and Colours; and it was then thought by <lb/>one party in this diſpute, that the
        defect of the choroid <lb/>coat, where the optic nerve enters the eye, was the cauſe <lb/>of
        this want of viſion in that part. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But the following obſervation ſhews beyond a doubt <lb/>the fallacy of this
        ſuppoſition: the diameter of the optic <lb/>nerve, at its entrance into the eye, is about
        one-ſixth of <lb/>and inch, and the perforation of the choroid coat, through <lb/>which it
        paſſes, muſt of neceſſity be of the ſame diame- <lb/>ter: now the dark ſpot, which is ſeen
        in objects oppoſed <lb/>to the center of the optic nerve, if it was occaſioned by <lb/>the
        deficiency of the choroid coat, ſhould, at nine inches <lb/>diſtance from the eye, be
        fifty-four times the diameter <lb/>of this aperture, or nine inches in the diameter; whereas
        I <lb/>find, by experiment, that a paper of one inch in diameter <lb/>could not be totally
        concealed at nine inches diſtance <pb n="92"/>
        <lb/>from my eye; and M. <hi rend="sc">le cat</hi> by accurate obſervations <lb/>found, that
        the inſenſible part of his eye was but be- <lb/>tween the thirtieth and fortieth part of an
        inch in dia- <lb/>meter. This experiment is ſo eaſily made, that it can <lb/>be attended
        with no fallacy; and at the ſame time that <lb/>it ſhews that the inſenſible ſpot, where the
        optic nerve <lb/>enters the eye, is not owing to the deficiency of the cho- <lb/>roid coat,
        intirely ſubverts the opinion of the choroid <lb/>coat being the organ of viſion; for viſion
        exiſts where <lb/>the choroid coat is not. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Nor is the inſenſibility of the center of the optic <lb/>nerve owing to the ingreſs of
        the arteries along with it <lb/>into the eye; for a large branch of this artery runs along
        <lb/>the bottom of the eye, where viſion is moſt diſtinct, and <lb/>becauſe all this artery
        is covered with the expanſe of the <lb/>retina on the external ſide of it. Mr. <hi rend="sc"
          >savage</hi> made an <lb/>experiment for another purpoſe, which however ſhews, <lb/>that
        the optic artery, where it is branched under or <lb/>through the retina, does not much
        diſturb the power of <lb/>viſion. It is this: if you look on a white wall on a <lb/>luminous
        day, with the Sun ſhining on the wall <lb/>only by its reflected light, you will diſcern the
        parts of <lb/>the wall become darker and lighter at every pulſation of <lb/>the optic
        artery. This darker and lighter appearance is <lb/>like net-work, and not uniform like the
        wall itſelf; but <pb n="93"/>
        <lb/>the whole, though rather darker while the diaſtole of <lb/>the artery compreſſes the
        retina, is yet diſtinctly viſible. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The following circumſtance ſeems to give riſe to the <lb/>inſenſibility of the central
        part of the optic nerve at its <lb/>ingreſs into the eye, which I have obſerved in ſeveral
        <lb/>calves' eyes. The point of a pair of ſciſſars was intro- <lb/>duced behind the ciliary
        circle, and the whole of the <lb/>cornea, aqueous humour, iris, and cryſtalline, being re-
        <lb/>moved, the retina was beautifully ſeen through the vi- <lb/>treous humour ſomewhat
        magnified. On expoſing this <lb/>to the ſun-ſhine, and inſpecting it with nicety, a white
        <lb/>filament, about the tenth of an inch in length, ariſing <lb/>from the center of the
        optic nerve, was ſeen aſcending <lb/>ſtraight upwards into the vitreous humour, like a thin
        <lb/>white worm. The uſe of this may be to ſupply the vi- <lb/>treous humour or cryſtalline
        with nouriſhment, whe- <lb/>ther it be a nerve or an empty blood-veſſel; but this is
        <lb/>certain, that its riſing ſo high above the ſurface of the <lb/>retina muſt render it
        incapable of viſion: whence there <lb/>is just reaſon to conclude, that this conformation
        muſt <lb/>be the true cauſe of the inſenſibility of this part of the <lb/>eye. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I do not affirm, that the human eye, either during in- <lb/>fancy or in our riper
        years, is ſimilar in conformation to <lb/>that of a calf, nor have we ſufficient
        opportunities to ob- <pb n="94"/>
        <lb/>ſerve them; but I ſuſpect this veſſel may, after the growth <lb/>of the animal, be
        totally obliterated; and that, in ſome few <lb/>inſtances, the optic nerve may even in this
        part become <lb/>ſenſible to light. One inſtance I am certain I have <lb/>ſeen, as it was in
        a man capable of the moſt patient <lb/>and accurate obſervation, who on numberleſs repeated
        <lb/>trials, at different times, in my preſence, could never <lb/>loſe ſight of the ſmalleſt
        object withe either of his eyes. </p>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A long horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <postscript>
        <label rend="italic space align-center">
          <lb/>Supplement to the caſe in ſquinting. </label>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>IT ſince occured to me, that the unuſual mode of <lb/>ſquinting deſcribed in the
          above paper muſt have ariſen <lb/>from ſome original difference in the ſenſibility of ſome
          <lb/>parts of the eye, which might have rendered it more <lb/>eaſy for maſter <hi
            rend="sc">sandford</hi>, when a child, to obſerve ob- <lb/>jects with one eye only, and
          that with the eye moſt <lb/>diſtant from objects preſented obliquely to him. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Two circular papers, each of four inches diameter, <lb/>were ſtuck againſt the wall,
          their centers being exactly <lb/>at eight inches diſtance from each other. On cloſing
          <lb/>one eye, and viewing the central ſpot of one of theſe <lb/>papers with the eye
          furtheſt from it, and then retreating <pb n="95"/>
          <lb/>twenty-ſix inches from it, the other paper became invi- <lb/>ſible. This experiment
          was made on five people of <lb/>various ages, from ten years old to forty; and the paper
          <lb/>diſappeared to them all at about this diſtance, or an inch <lb/>or two more or leſs:
          but to maſter <hi rend="sc">sandford</hi> the paper <lb/>diſappeared at about thirteen
          inches diſtance from the <lb/>wall. Theſe papers were afterwards removed to twelve
          <lb/>inches, and then to four inches interval between them; <lb/>and by the niceſt
          obſervations on repeated trials I found, <lb/>that the paper, equally with one eye as with
          the other, <lb/>uniformly diſappeared to him at about half the diſtance <lb/>it did to
          five others. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Another curious circumſtance is, that as large a paper <lb/>diſappeared to him at
          half the diſtance as it did to others <lb/>at the whole diſtance; and hence the inſenſible
          part of <lb/>the center of the optic nerve in his eyes is, as near as can <lb/>be
          eſtimated, four times the area of the inſenſible part <lb/>of the eyes of other people, at
          the ſame time that the <lb/>angle made between the ingreſs of the optic nerve and <lb/>the
          bottom of the eye is twice as great as in others. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is eaſy to conceive that, in early infancy, when any <lb/>object which the child
          wiſhed to inſpect was preſented <lb/>obliquely to him, that on this firſt indiſtinct view
          of it, <lb/>before either eye could be turned towards it, it would <lb/>appear much more
          brilliant and diſtinct to the contrary <pb n="96"/>
          <lb/>eye, than to that neareſt the object, as ſo great a part of <lb/>it would now fall on
          the large inſenſible part of that eye. <lb/>This muſt naturally induce him to view it with
          the op- <lb/>poſite eye, to which it already appeared more brilliant <lb/>and diſtinct:
          and this to him would be ſo much eaſier to <lb/>accompliſh, as the inſenſible part of the
          neglected eye <lb/>was great enough to receive as large a part of an object <lb/>as is
          uſually viewed at once with accuracy, and hence <lb/>would not confuſe the viſion of the
          other. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I muſt beg leave to add, that by wearing the artificial <lb/>noſe he has greatly
          corrected the habit of viewing ob- <lb/>jects with the eye furtheſt from them; and has
          more <lb/>and more acquired the voluntary power of directing both <lb/>his eyes to the
          ſame object, particularly if the object be <lb/>not more than four or five feet from him;
          and will, I <lb/>believe, by reſolute perſeverance, intirely correct this <lb/>unſightly
          deformity. Nothing but the curioſity and no- <lb/>velty of the ſubject can excuſe the
          length of this paper. </p>
      </postscript>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
