<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Guthrie: Account of the Manner in Which the Russians Treat Persons
          Affected by the Fumes of Burning Charcoal</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Matthew Guthrie</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Account of the Manner in Which the Russians Treat Persons Affected by the Fumes
              of Burning Charcoal, and Other Effluvia of the Same Nature. In a Letter from Matthew
              Guthrie, M. D. to Joseph Priestley, LL. D. F. R. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by J. Nichols, successor to Mr. Bowyer; For Lockyer Davis,
                  Printer to the Royal Society.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1779</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">69</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">325-331</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110533706</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1779.0023</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT69_0325">
    <body>
      <pb n="325"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXII.</hi> Account of the Manner in which the <hi rend="roman"
          >Ruſſians</hi> treat <lb/>Perſons affected by the Fumes of burning Charcoal, and
        <lb/>other Effluvia of the ſame Nature. In a Letter from <lb/><hi rend="roman">Matthew
          Guthrie</hi>, M. D. to <hi rend="roman">Joſeph Prieſtley</hi>, LL. D. <lb/>F. R. S. </head>
      <head rend="size(0.7) align-center space">
        <lb/>Read <date>March 4, 1779. </date>
      </head>
      <salute rend="indent sc space">
        <lb/>dear sir, </salute>
      <dateline rend="size(0.7) align-right">St. Peterſburg, <lb/>October 12, 1778. </dateline>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> SHALL endeavour to recollect, according to your <lb/>deſire,
        the particulars of that part of my former let- <lb/>ter which related to the mode of
        recovering people in <lb/>Ruſſia, who are apparently deprived of life by the prin- <pb
          n="326"/>
        <lb/>ciple emitted from burning charcoal, or by the in- <lb/>cruſtation formed upon the
        inſides of the boors huts <lb/>when it thaws. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>People of condition in this country have double win- <lb/>dows to their houſes in
        winter; but the commoner ſort <lb/>have only ſingle ones, which is the reaſon that, during a
        <lb/>ſevere froſt, there is an incruſtation formed upon the in- <lb/>ſides on the glaſs
        windows. This ſeems to be compoſed <lb/>of condenſed breath, perſpiration, &amp;c. as a
        number of <lb/>people live and ſleep in the ſame ſmall room, eſpecially <lb/>in great
        cities. This excrementitious cruſt is farther im- <lb/>pregnated with the phlogiſton of
        candles, and of the <lb/>oven with which the chamber is heated. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When a thaw ſucceeds a hard froſt of long duration, <lb/>and this plate of ice is
        converted into water, there is a <lb/>principle ſet looſe, which produces all the terrible
        effects <lb/>upon the human body which the principle emitted from <lb/>charcoal is ſo well
        known to do in this country, where <lb/>people every day ſuffer from it. However, the
        Ruſſians <lb/>conſtantly lay the blame upon the oven, when they are <lb/>affected by the
        thawing of the cruſt, as the effects are <lb/>perfectly ſimilar, and they cannot bring
        themſelves to <lb/>believe, that the diſſolving of ſo ſmall a portion of ice <lb/>can be
        attended with any bad conſequence, when they <lb/>daily melt larger maſſes without danger:
        yet the oven <pb n="327"/>
        <lb/>does not at all account for the complaints brought on at <lb/>this period; for, upon
        examination, they generally find <lb/>every thing right there, and ſtill the <hi
          rend="italic">ugar</hi>, or hurtful <lb/>vapour, remaining in the room. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As the effects of both are ſimilar, as I have ſaid above, <lb/>and likewiſe the mode of
        recovery, I ſhall only give you <lb/>an account of the operation of the principle emitted by
        <lb/>burning charcoal, and of the method of bringing thoſe <lb/>people to life who have been
          <hi rend="italic">ſuffocated</hi> by it (as I think <lb/>it is erroneouſly termed); this
        will ſuperſede the neceſ- <lb/>ſity of giving the hiſtory of both, or rather it will be
        <lb/>giving both at the ſame time. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Ruſſian houſes are heated by the means of ovens; <lb/>and the manner of heating them is
        as follows. A num- <lb/>ber of billets of wood are placed in the peech of ſtove, <lb/>and
        allowed to burn till they fall in a maſs of bright red <lb/>cinders; then the vent above is
        ſhut up, and likewiſe the <lb/>door of the peech which opens into the room, in order to
        <lb/>concentrate the heat; this makes the tiles of which the <lb/>peech is compoſed as hot
        as you deſire, and ſufficiently <lb/>warms the apartment; but ſometimes a ſervant is ſo
        <lb/>negligent as to ſhut up the peech or oven before the <lb/>wood is ſufficiently burnt,
        for the red cinders ſhould be <lb/>turned over from time to time to ſee that no bit of wood
        <lb/>remains of a blackiſh colour, but that the whole maſs is <pb n="328"/>
        <lb/>of a uniform glare (as if almoſt tranſparent) before the <lb/>openings are ſhut, elſe
        the <hi rend="italic">ugar</hi> or vapour is ſure to <lb/>ſuceed to miſmanagement of this
        ſort, and its effects are <lb/>as follows. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If a perſon lays himſelf down to ſleep in the room ex- <lb/>poſed to the influence of
        this vapour, he falls into ſo <lb/>ſound a ſleep that it is difficult to awake him, but he
        feels <lb/>(or is ſenſible of) nothing. There is no ſpaſm excited in <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">trachea arteria</hi> or lungs to rouſe him, nor does the <lb/>breathing, by
        all accounts, ſeem to be particularly af- <lb/>fected: in ſhort, there is no one ſymptom of
        ſuffocation; <lb/>but towards the end of the cataſtrophe, a ſort of groan- <lb/>ing is heard
        by people in the next room, which brings <lb/>them ſometimes to the relief of the ſufferer.
        If a perſon <lb/>only ſits down in the room, without intention to ſleep, <lb/>he is, after
        ſome time, ſeized with a drowzineſs and in- <lb/>clination to vomit. However, this laſt
        ſymptom ſeldom <lb/>affects a Ruſſian, it is chiefly foreigners who are awaked <lb/>to their
        dangers by a <hi rend="italic">nauſea</hi>; but the natives, in common <lb/>with ſtrangers,
        perceive a dull pain in their heads, and if <lb/>they do not remove directly, which they are
        often too <lb/>ſleepy to do, are ſoon deprived of their ſenſes and power <lb/>of motion,
        inſomuch, that if no perſon fortunately diſco- <lb/>vers them within an hour after this
        worſt ſtage, they <lb/>are irrecoverably loſt; for the Ruſſians ſay, that they <pb n="329"/>
        <lb/>do not ſucceed in reſtoring to life thoſe who have lain <lb/>more than an hour in a
        ſtate of inſenſibility. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The recovery is always attempted, and often effected, <lb/>in this manner. They carry
        the patient immediately out <lb/>of doors, and lay him upon the ſnow, with nothing on
        <lb/>him but a ſhirt and linen drawers. His ſtomach amd tem- <lb/>ples are then well rubbed
        with ſnow, and cold water, or <lb/>milk is poured down his throat. This friction is conti-
        <lb/>nued with freſh ſnow until the livid hue, which the body <lb/>had when brought out, is
        changed to its natural colour, <lb/>and life renewed; then they cure the violent head-ach
        <lb/>which remains by binding on the forehead a cataplaſm <lb/>of black rye bread, and
        vinegar. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In this manner the unfortunate man is perfectly re- <lb/>ſtrored, without blowing up
        the lungs, as is neceſſary in <lb/>the caſe of drowned perſons; on the contrary, they be-
        <lb/>gin to play of themſelves ſo ſoon as the ſurcharge of <lb/>phlogiſton makes its eſcape
        from the body. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is well worthy of obſervation, how diametrically <lb/>oppoſite the modes are of
        reſtoring to life, those who <lb/>are deprived of it by water, and thoſe who have loſt it
        <lb/>by the fumes of charcoal: the one conſiſting in the inter- <lb/>nal and external
        application of heat, and the other in that <lb/>of cold. It may be alledged, that the
        ſtimulus of the cold <lb/>produces heat, and the fact ſeems to be confirmed by <lb/>the
        Ruſſian method of reſtoring circulation in a frozen <pb n="330"/>
        <lb/>limb by means of friction with ſnow. But what is ſin- <lb/>gular in the caſe of people
        apparently deprived of life in <lb/>the manner treated of is, that the body is much warmer
        <lb/>when brought out of the room than at the inſtant life is <lb/>reſtored, and that they
        awake cold and ſhivering. The <lb/>colour of the body is alſo changed from a livid red to
        its <lb/>natural complexion, which, together with ſome other <lb/>circumſtances, would
        almoſt lead one to ſuſpect, that <lb/>they are reſtored to life by the ſnow and cold water
        ſome <lb/>how or other freeing them from the load of phlogiſton <lb/>with which the ſyſtem
        ſeems to be replete; for although <lb/>the firſt application of cold water to the human body
        <lb/>produces heat, yet, if often repeated in a very cold at- <lb/>moſphere, it then cools
        inſtead of continuing to heat, <lb/>juſt as the cold bath does when a perſon remains too
        long <lb/>in it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In ſhort, I think it is altogether a curious ſubject, whe- <lb/>ther you take into
        conſideration the mode of action of <lb/>the principle emitted by burning charcoal, and our
        phlo- <lb/>giſticated cruſt; or the operation of the ſnow and cold <lb/>water. However, I
        ſhall by no means take upon me <lb/>to decide, whether the dangerous ſymptoms related
        <lb/>above are produced by the air in the room being ſo ſatu- <lb/>rated with phlogiſton as
        to be unable to take up the pro- <lb/>per quantity from the lungs, which occaſions a ſur-
        <lb/>charge in the ſyſtem, according to your theory, or whe- <pb n="331"/>
        <lb/>ther ſo ſubtle a fluid may ſomehow find its way into the <lb/>circulation, and thereby
        arreſt the vital powers; nor <lb/>ſhall I determine whether the livid hue of the body
        <lb/>when brought out is changed into a paler colour by the <lb/>atmoſphere ſomehow or other
        abſorbing and freeing the <lb/>blood from the colouring principle, as you have ſhewn <lb/>to
        be the caſe with blood out of the body: theſe are cu- <lb/>rious inquiries that I ſhall
        leave to your inveſtigation. I <lb/>have only endeavoured to collect facts from a number of
        <lb/>natives who have met with this accident themſelves, or <lb/>have aſſiſted in reſtoring
        others to life. It is ſo common <lb/>a caſe here that it is perfectly familiar to them, and
        they <lb/>never call in medical aſſiſtance. </p>
      <signed rend="align-center space">
        <lb/>I am, &amp;c. </signed>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>An illustration of what appears to be an obelisk and a trophy on a pedestal,
          surrounded by trees and shrubbery. </figDesc>
      </figure>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
