<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Hunter: An Experiment to Determine the Effect of Extirpating One
          Ovarium</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>John Hunter</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Experiment to Determine the Effect of Extirpating One Ovarium upon the Number
              of Young Produced. By John Hunter, Esq. F. R. S. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Sold by Lockyer Davis and Peter Elmsly, Printers to the Royal
                  Society</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1787</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">77</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">233-239</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111040592</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1787.0021</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT77_0233">
    <body>
      <pb n="233"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXI.</hi> An Experiment to determine the Effect of extirpating one
        <lb/>Ovarium upon the Number of Young produced. By <hi rend="roman">John <lb/>Hunter</hi>,
        Eſq. F. R. S. </head>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <dateline rend="align-center">
        <lb/>Read March 22, 1787. </dateline>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N all animals of diſtinct ſex, the females, thoſe of the bird
        <lb/>kind excepted, have, I believe, two ovaria, and of courſe <lb/>the oviducts are in
        pairs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By diſtinct ſex I mean when the parts deſtined to the <lb/>purpoſes of generation are
        of two kinds, each kind appro- <lb/>priated to an individual of each ſpecies, diſtinguiſhed
        by the <pb n="234"/>
        <lb/>appellation of male and female, and equally neceſſary to the <lb/>propagation of the
        animal; the teſticles, with their appen- <lb/>dages, conſtituting the male; the ovaria, and
        their appendages, <lb/>the female ſex. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As the ovaria are the organs which, on the part of the <lb/>female, furniſh what is
        neceſſary towards the production of <lb/>the third, or young animal; and as females appear
        to have a <lb/>limited portion of the middle ſtage of life allotted for that <lb/>purpoſe;
        it becomes a queſtion, whether thoſe organs are worn <lb/>out by repeated acts of
        propagation; or whether there is not a <lb/>natural and conſtitutional period to that power
        on their part, <lb/>even if ſuch power has never been exerted? If we conſider <lb/>this
        ſubject in every view, taking the human ſpecies as an <lb/>example, we ſhall diſcover that
        circumſtances, either local or <lb/>conſtitutional, may be capable of extinguiſhing in the
        female <lb/>the faculty of propagation. Thus we may obſerve when a <lb/>woman begins to
        breed at an early period, as at fifteen, and <lb/>has her children faſt, that ſhe ſeldom
        breeds longer than the <lb/>age of thirty or thirty-five; therefore we may ſuppoſe, either
        <lb/>that the parts are then worn out, or that the breeding conſti- <lb/>tution is over. If
        a woman begins later, as at twenty or <lb/>twenty-five, ſhe may continue to breed to the age
        of forty or <lb/>more; and there are, now and then, inſtances of women, who, <lb/>not having
        conceived before, have had children as late in life as <lb/>at fifty years or upwards. After
        that, few women breed, even <lb/>if they ſhould not have bred before; therefore, there muſt
        be a <lb/>natural period to the power of conception. A ſimilar ſtop to <lb/>propagation may
        likewiſe take place in many other claſſes of <lb/>animals, probably in the female of every
        claſs, the period <lb/>varying according to circumſtances; but ſtill we are not ena- <pb
          n="235"/>
        <lb/>bled to determine, how far it depends on any particular pro- <lb/>perty of the
        conſtitution, or of the ovarium alone. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As the female of moſt claſſes of animals has two ovaria, I <lb/>imagined, that by
        removing one it might be poſſible to deter- <lb/>mine how far their actions were
        reciprocally influenced by <lb/>each other, from the changes which by compariſon might be
        <lb/>obſerved to take place, either by the breeding period being <lb/>ſhortened, or perhaps,
        in thoſe animals whoſe nature it is to <lb/>bring forth more than one at a time, by the
        number produced <lb/>at each birth being diminiſhed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There are two views in which this ſubject may be conſidered. <lb/>The firſt, that the
        ovarium, when properly employed, may be <lb/>a body determined and unalterable reſpecting
        the number of <lb/>young to be produced. In that caſe we can readily imagine, that,
        <lb/>when one ovarium is removed, the other may produce its deter- <lb/>mined number in two
        different ways; one when the remaining <lb/>ovarium, not influenced by the loſs of the
        other, will produce <lb/>its allotted number, and in the ſame time; the other, when it
        <lb/>is affected by the loſs, yet the conſtitution demands the ſame <lb/>number of young
        each time of breeding, as if there were ſtill <lb/>two ovaria; conſequently it furniſhes
        double the number it <lb/>would have been required to ſupply, had both been allowed to
        <lb/>remain, but muſt ceaſe from the performance of its function in <lb/>half the time. The
        ſecond view of the ſubject is by ſuppoſing, <lb/>that there is not originally any fixed
        number which the ovarium <lb/>muſt produce; but that the number is increaſed or diminiſhed
        <lb/>according to circumſtances; that it is rather the conſtitution at <lb/>large that
        determines the number; and that, if one ovarium is <lb/>removed, the other will be called
        upon by the conſtitution to <lb/>perform the operations of both; by which means the animal
          <pb n="236"/>
        <lb/>ſhould produce, with one ovarium, the ſame number of young <lb/>as would have been
        produced if both had remained. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>With an intention to aſcertain thoſe points, as far as I could, <lb/>I was led to make
        the following experiment; and for that <lb/>purpoſe choſe pigs in preference to any other
        animal, becauſe <lb/>they are eaſily managed, and breed perfectly well under the
        <lb/>confinement neceſſary for experiments. Having ſelected two <lb/>female ones of the ſame
        colour and ſize, and likewiſe a boar <lb/>pig, all of the ſame farrow; after having removed
        one ova- <lb/>rium only from one of the females, and cut a ſlit in one of <lb/>its ears,
        that there might be no miſtake between it and the <lb/>other, I had them well fed and kept
        warm, that there might <lb/>be no impediment to their breeding; and whenever they far-
        <lb/>rowed, their pigs were taken away exactly at the ſame age. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About the beginning of the year 1779, they both took the <lb/>boar; but the one which
        had been ſpayed earlier than the per- <lb/>fect female. The diſtance of time, however, was
        not great, <lb/>and they continued breeding at nearly the ſame times. The <lb/>ſpayed animal
        continued to breed till September 1783, when <lb/>ſhe was ſix years old, which was a ſpace
        of more than four <lb/>years. In that time ſhe had eight farrows; but did not take <lb/>the
        boar afterwards, and had in all ſeventy-ſix pigs. The <lb/>perfect one continued breeding
        till December 1785, when ſhe <lb/>was about eight years old, a period of almoſt ſix years,
        in <lb/>which time ſhe had thirteen farrows, and had in all one hun- <lb/>dred and ſixty-two
        pigs; after this time ſhe did not breed: I <lb/>kept her till November 1786. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I have here annexed a table of the different times of each <lb/>farrow, with the number
        of pigs produced. </p>
      <pb n="237"/>
      <table rows="11" cols="3">
        <head rend="align-center space">Spayed Sow. </head>
        <row role="label" rend="size(0.7)">
          <cell>Farrows. </cell>
          <cell>Number of young. </cell>
          <cell rend="align-center">Time. </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell>1 </cell>
          <cell>6 </cell>
          <cell>Dec. 1779 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell>2 </cell>
          <cell>8 </cell>
          <cell>July 1780 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell>3 </cell>
          <cell>6 </cell>
          <cell>Jan. 1781 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell>4 </cell>
          <cell>10 </cell>
          <cell>Aug. 1781 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell>5 </cell>
          <cell>10 </cell>
          <cell>Mar. 1782 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell>6 </cell>
          <cell>9 </cell>
          <cell>Sept. 1782 </cell>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell>7 </cell>
          <cell>14 </cell>
          <cell>May 1783 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell>8 </cell>
          <cell>13 </cell>
          <cell>Sept. 1783 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell/>
          <cell>—</cell>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell/>
          <cell>76 </cell>
          <cell/>
        </row>
      </table>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>November following ſhe was put to the boar, but brought <lb/>no pigs. April 1784, ſhe
        was again put to the boar, without <lb/>effect, and never was obſerved to take the boar
        afterwards, <lb/>although often with him. November 1784, ſhe was killed. </p>
      <table rows="11" cols="3">
        <head rend="align-center space">Perfect Sow. </head>
        <row role="label" rend="size(0.7)">
          <cell>Farrows. </cell>
          <cell>Number of young. </cell>
          <cell rend="align-center">Time. </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell>1 </cell>
          <cell>9 </cell>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell>2 </cell>
          <cell>6 </cell>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell>3 </cell>
          <cell>8 </cell>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell>4 </cell>
          <cell>13 </cell>
          <cell>Dec. 1781 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell>5 </cell>
          <cell>10 </cell>
          <cell>June 1782 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell>6 </cell>
          <cell>16 </cell>
          <cell>Dec. 1782 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell>7 </cell>
          <cell>13 </cell>
          <cell>June 1783 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell>8 </cell>
          <cell>12 </cell>
          <cell>Oct. 1783 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell/>
          <cell>—</cell>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell/>
          <cell>87 </cell>
          <cell/>
        </row>
      </table>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Eleven pigs more than were produced by the ſpayed ſow in <lb/>her eight farrows. </p>
      <pb n="238"/>
      <table rows="8" cols="3" rend="space">
        <row role="label" rend="size(0.7)">
          <cell>Farrows. </cell>
          <cell>Number of young. </cell>
          <cell rend="align-center">Time. </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell>9 </cell>
          <cell>12 </cell>
          <cell>Feb. 1784 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell>10 </cell>
          <cell>16 </cell>
          <cell>June 1784 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell>11 </cell>
          <cell>12 </cell>
          <cell>Dec. 1784 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell>12 </cell>
          <cell>16 </cell>
          <cell>May 1785 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell>13 </cell>
          <cell>19 </cell>
          <cell>Dec. 1785 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell/>
          <cell>—</cell>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row rend="align-center">
          <cell/>
          <cell>75 </cell>
          <cell/>
        </row>
      </table>
      <p>
        <lb/>After which ſhe bred no more. </p>
      <table rows="7" cols="2" rend="space">
        <row>
          <cell>The firſt eight farrows were </cell>
          <cell rend="align-right">87 </cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>The laſt five farrows were </cell>
          <cell rend="align-right">75 </cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell/>
          <cell rend="align-right">—</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>Total </cell>
          <cell rend="align-right">162 </cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>The number from the ſpayed one </cell>
          <cell rend="align-right">76 </cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell/>
          <cell rend="align-right">—</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>More than farrowed by the imperfect animal </cell>
          <cell rend="align-right">86 </cell>
        </row>
      </table>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It is obſervable, that both ſows rather increaſed in their <lb/>number each time the
        older they grew, although not uni- <lb/>formly; the difference between the firſt and laſt in
        both ani- <lb/>mals being conſiderable. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From the above table we find, that the ſow with only one <lb/>ovarium bred till ſhe was
        ſix years old, from the latter end of <lb/>1779 till September 1783, about four years, and
        in that time <lb/>brought forth ſeventy-ſix pigs. The perfect animal bred till <lb/>ſhe was
        eight years of age. In the laſt, if conception depended <lb/>on the ovaria, it was to be
        expected, that ſhe would bring <lb/>forth double the number at each birth; or, if ſhe did
        not, that <lb/>ſhe would continue breeding for double the time. We indeed <lb/>find her
        producing ten more than double the number of the <lb/>imperfect animal, and continuing to
        breed much longer. </p>
      <pb n="239"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From a circumſtance mentioned in the courſe of this expe- <lb/>riment it appears, that
        the deſire for the male continues after <lb/>the power of breeding is exhauſted in the
        female; and there- <lb/>fore does not altogether depend on the powers of the ovaria to
        <lb/>propagate, although we muſt at the ſame time allow, that it <lb/>may be influenced by
        the exiſtence of ſuch parts. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If theſe obſervations ſhould be conſidered as depending on a <lb/>ſingle experiment,
        from which alone it is not juſtifiable to draw <lb/>concluſions, I have only to add, that
        the difference in the num- <lb/>ber of pigs produced by each was greater than can be juſtly
        <lb/>imputed to accident, and is a circumſtance certainly in favour <lb/>of the univerſality
        of the principle I wiſhed to aſcertain <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* It may be thought by ſome, that I ſhould have repeated this experiment; <lb/>but
            an annual expence of twenty pounds for ten years, and the neceſſary atten- <lb/>tion to
            make the experiment complete, will be a ſufficient reaſon for my not <lb/>having done
            it. </p>
        </note>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From this experiment it ſeems moſt probable, that the <lb/>ovaria are from the
        beginning deſtined to produce a fixed num- <lb/>ber, beyond which they cannot go, although
        circumſtances may <lb/>tend to diminiſh that number; that the conſtitution at large <lb/>has
        no power of giving to one ovarium the power of propa- <lb/>gating equal to two; for, in the
        preſent experiment, the ani- <lb/>mal with one ovarium produced ten pigs leſs than half the
        <lb/>number brought forth by the pig with both ovaria. But that <lb/>the conſtitution has ſo
        far a power of influencing one ovarium, <lb/>as to make it produce its number in a leſs time
        than would <lb/>probably have been the caſe if both ovaria had been preſerved, <lb/>is
        evident from the above recited experiment. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
