<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Baillie: An Account of a Remarkable Transposition of the
          Viscera</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Matthew Baillie</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of a Remarkable Transposition of the Viscera. By Matthew Baillie, M.
              D. In a Letter to John Hunter, Esq. F. R. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Sold by Lockyer Davis and Peter Elmsly, Printers to the Royal
                  Society</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1788</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">78</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">350-363</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111041132</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1788.0023</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT78_0350">
    <body>
      <pb n="350"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXI.</hi> An Account of a remarkable Tranſpoſition of the Viſcera.
        <lb/>By <hi rend="roman">Matthew Baillie</hi>, M. D. In a Letter to <hi rend="roman">John
          Hunter</hi>, <lb/>Eſq. F. R. S. </head>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>Read <date>May 8, 1788. </date>
      </head>
      <head rend="sc align-center space">
        <lb/>to john hunter, esq. f. r. s. </head>
      <div>
        <salute rend="sc indent space">
          <lb/>dear sir, </salute>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> VERY ſingular variety having occured lately in the
          <lb/>ſtructure of the human body, I beg leave to communi- <lb/>cate an account of it by
          your means to the Royal Society, <lb/>if you ſhould think it worthy of their notice. It
          happens <lb/>by a very uncommon concurrence of circumſtances, that <lb/>while I am
          naturally led by the ties of affinity to apply to <lb/>you upon this occaſion, I can
          gratify my pride by thinking it <lb/>is at the ſame time to the perſon who is poſſeſſed of
          the firſt <lb/>reputation for his unwearied reſearches in one of the moſt ex-
          <lb/>tenſive, as well as intereſting, parts of the ſyſtem of nature. </p>
        <signed rend="align-center space">I am, &amp;c. <lb/><hi rend="size(1.2) align-right space"
            >M. BAILLIE. </hi>
        </signed>
        <dateline rend="size(0.7) hanging space">
          <lb/>Great Windmill-ſtreet, <lb/>April 12, 1788. </dateline>
      </div>
      <pb n="351"/>
      <div>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>THERE is nothing which tends more to illuſtrate the <lb/>powers and the wiſdom of
          nature than the inveſtigation of the <lb/>ſtructure of animals. We there find a moſt
          wonderful deli- <lb/>cacy of mechaniſm, and exquiſitely adapted to a variety of
          <lb/>purpoſes. This, however, is not to be better ſeen by following <lb/>nature in her
          common tract than by obſerving her wanderings. <lb/>In theſe ſhe often ſhews more
          particularly the extent of her <lb/>powers, and throws light on her ordinary plans. It is
          ſuch <lb/>circumſtances which gave importance or value to the obſerva- <lb/>tion of
          ſingular phænomena. The variety in animal ſtructure, <lb/>an account of which I have the
          honour of preſenting to this <lb/>learned Society, is a complete tranſpoſition in the
          human ſub- <lb/>ject of the thoracic and abdominal viſcera to the oppoſite ſide <lb/>from
          what is natural. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is ſo extraordinary as ſcarcely to have been ſeen by any of <lb/>the moſt
          celebrated anatomiſts, and indeed has been but very <lb/>generally noticed at all. The
          circumſtance has been men- <lb/>tioned, but it has not been particularly deſcribed ſo as
          to make <lb/>it thoroughly known, or to eſtabliſh its certainty. It was <lb/>hanging in
          the minds of many as doubtful, whether ſuch a <lb/>variety did really exiſt. There is one
          circumſtance that attends <lb/>the account of the preſent caſe, which has not always hap-
          <lb/>pened in the record of ſingular phænomena, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> that is has
          <lb/>been examined by phyſicians and ſurgeons of the firſt reputa- <lb/>tion in this large
          town, and has been in ſome meaſure open to <lb/>the gratification of public curioſity.
          Such a circumſtance (were <lb/>it neceſſary) would give the ſtamp of authenticity to
          appear- <lb/>ances even much farther removed from the ordinary plans of <lb/>nature. </p>
        <pb n="352"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I have been at the pains to conſult many authors upon this <lb/>ſubject, but with
          very little ſatisfaction. I ſhall not enter into <lb/>a detail of what I have met with in
          the courſe of theſe re- <lb/>ſearches, but ſhall briefly notice, that when any luſus of
          this <lb/>ſort is mentioned, it is commonly in a ſingle ſentence or two, <lb/>and the
          tranſpoſition is not marked as univerſal, or it is a <lb/>change in the ſituation of ſome
          viſcus from diſeaſe. In ſhort, <lb/>I have only found this ſingular luſus naturæ deſcribed
          by <hi rend="sc">Cat- <lb/>tierius</hi>, <hi rend="sc">M. Mery</hi>, and <hi rend="sc">M.
            Daubenton</hi>; but by none of <lb/>them is it ſufficiently particular. Enough has been
          ſaid to <lb/>point out that they had exactly met with the ſame ſort of mon- <lb/>ſtroſity;
          but many circumſtances have been omitted, which I <lb/>hope will be ſupplied by the
          preſent account, which I proceed <lb/>immediately to lay before the Society. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The perſon who is the ſubject of this Paper was a male, <lb/>near forty years of age,
          ſomewhat above the middle ſtature, <lb/>and of a clean active ſhape. He was brought for
          diſſection in <lb/>the common way to Windmill-ſtreet. Upon opening the <lb/>cavity of the
          thorax and abdomen, the different ſituation of the <lb/>viſcera was ſo ſtriking as
          immediately to excite to the attention of <lb/>the pupils who were engaged in diſſecting
          it; and Mr. <hi rend="sc">Cruik- <lb/>shank</hi>, as well as myſelf, were very ſoon
          informed of the ſin- <lb/>gularity. We were much ſurprized as well as pleaſed with
          <lb/>the appearance, and I began immediately to examine every <lb/>part of the change with
          conſiderable attention: for this pur- <lb/>poſe, after deſiring a drawing to be made of
          the appearances <lb/>as they were found upon opening the body, I next day in- <lb/>jected
          it. The repeated diſſections have furniſhed various <lb/>views, which are repreſented
          faithfully by drawings, and <lb/>which I hope will enable me to give a tolerably diſtinct
          ac- <lb/>count of this ſingular luſus naturæ. I ſhall not enter in my <lb/>deſcription
          into unneceſſary minutiæ: this would render the <pb n="353"/>
          <lb/>Paper leſs ſuited to the Society, would not convey more infor- <lb/>mation to perſons
          thoroughly acquainted with anatomy, and <lb/>would rather tend to obſcure what is more
          important to thoſe <lb/>who have not given ſo much attention to ſubjects of this na-
          <lb/>ture. It may not be improper to obſerve, that, beſides the <lb/>tranſpoſition in the
          viſcera of this perſon, there are ſeveral <lb/>peculiarities which ſometimes occur. I have
          taken notice of <lb/>them in my deſcription, although they are entirely indepen- <lb/>dent
          of the tranſpoſition. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Deſcription of the thorax. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The mediaſtinum, or anterior duplicature of the pleura ſe- <lb/>parating the two
          cavities of the cheſt from each other, was <lb/>found to incline obliquely downwards to
          the right-ſide fully <lb/>as much as it does commonly to the left-ſide of the cheſt.
          <lb/>The pericardium too inclined obliquely to the right-ſide. On <lb/>preſſing it gently
          away from the lungs the phrenic nerves came <lb/>diſtinctly into view, in their common
          ſituation; but the right <lb/>phrenic nerve ran more obliquely, and was longer than the
          <lb/>left. The lung upon the right-ſide was divided by a ſingle <lb/>oblique fiſſure into
          two lobes, having at the same time a defi- <lb/>ciency oppoſite to the apex of the heart;
          and the lung on the <lb/>left-ſide was divided into three lobes, exactly contrary to what
          <lb/>is found in ordinary caſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On opening the pericardium the apex of the heart was found <lb/>to point to the
          right-ſide nearly oppoſite to the ſixth rib, and <lb/>its cavities as well as large
          veſſels were completely tranſpoſed. <lb/>What are commonly called the right auricle and
          ventricle were <lb/>ſituated on the left-ſide, and the left auricle and ventricle on <pb
            n="354"/>
          <lb/>the right. The pulmonary artery aſcended towards the right- <lb/>ſide of the cheſt.
          The aorta was alſo directing its arch to the <lb/>right; and the vena cava ſuperior, as
          well as inferior, were <lb/>ſeen opening into their auricle on the left-ſide of the ſpine.
          <lb/>There was nothing remarkable in the ſize or general figure of <lb/>the heart. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On the outſide of the pericardium the tranſpoſition of the <lb/>larger veſſels was
          very ſtriking. The longer ſub-clavian vein <lb/>was paſſing from the left-ſide obliquely
          to the right before the <lb/>branches which are ſent off from the arch of the aorta. The
          <lb/>left carotid and ſub-clavian arteries were found to ariſe from <lb/>the arch of the
          aorta by one common trunk; the right carotid <lb/>and ſub-clavian ſeparately. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In the duplicature of the pleura behind, or what may be <lb/>called the poſterior
          mediaſtinum, there was a change cor- <lb/>reſponding to what we have already deſcribed.
          The deſcend- <lb/>ing aorta was found paſſing on the right ſide of the ſpine. The
          <lb/>œſophagus was before it, inclining more and more to the right <lb/>towards its lower
          extremity, and it at length perforated the <lb/>diaphragm ſomewhat on the right-ſide of
          the ſpine <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* The vena azygos was on the left-ſide of the ſpine opening in the common
              <lb/>way into the vena cava ſuperior, which we formerly mentioned to be alſo
              <lb/>tranſpoſed in its ſituation. </p>
          </note>. The <lb/>thoracic duct was ſeen in the middle between the deſcending <lb/>aorta
          and the vena azygos in ſome places forming a plexus of <lb/>ſmall branches, in another
          dividing itſelf into two branches, <lb/>which afterwards re-united in a common trunk, and
          at length <lb/>climbing up to terminate in the angle between the jugular and
          <lb/>ſub-clavian veins on the right-ſide of the body. The recur- <lb/>rent nerve of the
          parvagum on the right-ſide paſſed round the <lb/>beginning of the deſcending aorta, and on
          the left paſſed round <pb n="355"/>
          <lb/>the common trunk of the carotid and ſub-clavian arteries. The <lb/>large intercoſtal
          nerves being exactly under the ſame circum- <lb/>ſtances on each ſide, it was impoſſible
          there could be any tranſ- <lb/>poſition in them. It appears then, from the foregoing
          deſcrip- <lb/>tion, that every thing admitting of ſuch a change was com- <lb/>pletely
          tranſpoſed in the thorax. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Of the abdomen. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The liver was ſituated in the left hypochondriac region, the <lb/>ſmall lobe being
          towards the right, and the great lobe in the <lb/>left-ſide. The ligaments uniting it to
          the diaphragm cor- <lb/>reſponded to this change, the right tranſverſe ligament being
          <lb/>longer, and the left being ſhorter, than uſual. The ſuſpen- <lb/>ſory ligament could
          undergo little change, except being puſhed <lb/>to the left-ſide along with the liver. On
          preſſing upwards the <lb/>liver, ſo as to exhibit its poſterior and under ſurface, the
          gall <lb/>bladder was ſeen on the left-ſide preſerving its proper relative <lb/>ſituation
          to the great lobe of the liver, and the veſſels of the <lb/>portæ were found upon
          diſſection to be tranſpoſed correſpond- <lb/>ing to the change of circumſtances. The
          hepatic artery was <lb/>found climbing up obliquely from the right towards the left,
          <lb/>before the lobulus ſpigelii, and entered at the portæ into the <lb/>ſubſtance of the
          liver by two or three branches on the right of <lb/>the other veſſels. The ductus communis
          cholidochus was on <lb/>the left of the other veſſels, being formed from the ductus
          <lb/>hepaticus and ductus cyſticus in the common way, and it paſſed <lb/>obliquely
          downwards on the left, to terminate in the duode- <lb/>num. What was moſt remarkable, of
          which indeed I never ſaw <lb/>or heard of any inſtance before, it terminated in the
          fore-part of <lb/>the duodenum. The vena portarum paſſed behind the hepatic <pb n="356"/>
          <lb/>artery and ductus communis cholidochus, aſcending obliquely <lb/>towards the
          left-ſide. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The ſpleen was ſituated in the right hypochondriac region, <lb/>adhering to the
          diaphragm in the common way. What was <lb/>very remarkable was, there being three ſpleens,
          nearly of the <lb/>ſize of a pullet's egg, found adhering to the larger ſpleen by
          <lb/>ſhort adheſions, beſides two other ſtill ſmaller ſpleens which <lb/>were involved in
          the epiploon at the great end of the ſtomach. <lb/>I never ſaw ſo many ſmall ſpleens in
          any one ſubject. The <lb/>pancreas was found on the right-ſide behind the ſtomach, run-
          <lb/>ning obliquely from the ſpleen to the curvature of the duo- <lb/>denum, and had its
          duct entering in common with the ductus <lb/>communis cholidochus into the cavity of that
          inteſtine. The <lb/>ſplenic veſſels were paſſing along the upper edge of the pan-
          <lb/>creas to the right-ſide, correſponding to the change of ſituation <lb/>in the
          pancreas and ſpleen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The stomach was ſituated on the right-ſide, partly hid by <lb/>the ſmall lobe of the
          liver paſſing to the left, and terminating <lb/>in the pylorus, rather on the left ſide of
          the ſpine. The duo- <lb/>denum took a moſt ſingular courſe; it firſt paſſed to the right-
          <lb/>ſide, behind the ſmall end of the ſtomach; it then turned <lb/>upon itſelf, towards
          the left-ſide; it afterwards took its proper <lb/>ſweep to the right-ſide, paſſing behind
          the ſuperior meſenteric <lb/>artery and meſaraica major vein. The meſentery began to be
          <lb/>formed on the right-ſide, inſtead of the left, as in ordinary <lb/>caſes. The ilium
          terminated in the great inteſtine on the left- <lb/>ſide, and there was in it a
          diverticulum of conſiderable ſize, a <lb/>luſus not unfrequently occurring. The cæcum was
          ſituated on <lb/>the left pſoas magnus and iliacus internus muſcels. The <lb/>tranſverſe
          arch of the colon paſſed from the left to the right- <pb n="357"/>
          <lb/>ſide of the body, and the ſigmoid flexure croſſed over the right <lb/>pſoas, to get
          into the cavity of the pelvis. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The kidnies had their veſſels tranſpoſed, as we ſhall remark <lb/>more particularly
          afterwards; the renal capſules had undergone <lb/>no change, as no variety could be
          produced by a tranſpoſition. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The aorta paſſed between the crura of the diaphragm into <lb/>the cavity of the
          abdomen, and adhered in its courſe to the <lb/>ſpine on the right-ſide of the vena cava
          inferior. Its branches <lb/>were directed in their courſe correſponding to the peculiar
          <lb/>ſituation of the viſcera. The ſplenic and coronary arteries <lb/>were paſſing to the
          right-ſide, and the hepatic artery obliquely <lb/>to the left. The ſuperior and inferior
          meſenteric arteries were <lb/>directed to the right-ſide. There was no change in the ſper-
          <lb/>matic arteries, any tranſpoſition in the teſticles (if ſuch a <lb/>thing could take
          place) not being capable of affecting them. <lb/>The lumbar arteries could alſo undergo
          little change, except <lb/>that the left lumbar arteries muſt neceſſarily, from the
          peculiar <lb/>ſituation of the aorta, be the longeſt. The vena cava inferior
          <lb/>perforated the tendinous portion of the diaphragm, and ad- <lb/>hered in its courſe
          to the ſpine on the left-ſide of the aorta. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The right emulgent vein was much longer than uſual, paſſing <lb/>from the right
          kidney before the aorta to terminate in the vena <lb/>cava ſuperior; and the left emulgent
          much ſhorter, paſſing from <lb/>the left kidney to the vena cava, which was ſituated on
          the left <lb/>ſide of the ſpine. The right ſpermatic vein was found to open <lb/>into the
          right emulgent, and the left into the vena cava infe- <lb/>rior, about an inch under the
          left emulgent. The vena por- <lb/>tarum was changed from its natural courſe, paſſing
          obliquely <lb/>upwards to the left-ſide, and its large branches, <hi rend="italic"
            >viz.</hi> the vena <lb/>ſplenica, meſaraica major and minor, were all directed towards
          <lb/>the right-ſide of the ſpine. </p>
        <pb n="358"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>There was no change in the intercoſtal nerve within the <lb/>cavity of the abdomen;
          nor does it ſeem to be capable of <lb/>being affected by any tranſpoſition of parts. We
          ſee then, <lb/>that there was a complete tranſpoſition of the abdominal viſ- <lb/>cera,
          each of them preſerving its proper relative ſituation to <lb/>the others. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I examined the brain, organs of ſenſe, of generation, the <lb/>muſcles and blood
          veſſels of the extremities, but found nothing <lb/>in them remarkable. Indeed, I had no
          expectation of it; for <lb/>all theſe parts perfectly independent of thoracic or abdo-
          <lb/>minal viſcera; but I did it to ſatisfy myſelf and the curioſity <lb/>of others, who
          might wiſh to put ſuch a queſtion, or have <lb/>ſuch a queſtion ariſing in their minds. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The perſon ſeems to have uſed his right-hand in preference <lb/>to his left, as is
          uſually the caſe, which was readily diſco- <lb/>vered by the greater bulk and hardneſs of
          that hand, as well <lb/>as the greater fleſhineſs of the arm. It was not to be ex-
          <lb/>pected he ſhould be left-handed; but I mentioned this circum- <lb/>ſtance too, with a
          view to ſatisfy a curioſity which I know <lb/>has been excited in many who have heard of
          this luſus. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I have been at conſiderable pains to learn ſomething of the <lb/>hiſtory of this
          perſon during life; but the particulars I have <lb/>heard are applicable only to the
          circumſtances of common men, <lb/>having no connection with ſingularity of ſtructure, and
          there- <lb/>fore, I think, it would be abuſing the time of the Society to <lb/>give any
          account of them. One thing it may be right to <lb/>mention is, that the perſon, while
          alive, was not conſcious of <lb/>any uncommon ſituation of his heart; and that his
          brother, <lb/>whom I have ſeen, has his heart pointing to the left-ſide as in
          <lb/>ordinary caſes. Indeed, there was little reaſon to expect that <lb/>we ſhould meet
          with any thing particular in the account of his <pb n="359"/>
          <lb/>life. His health could not be affected by ſuch a change of <lb/>ſituation in his
          viſcera; nor could there ariſe from it any pecu- <lb/>liar ſymptoms of diſeaſe. Still leſs
          could there be any con- <lb/>nection between ſuch a change and his diſpoſitions, or
          external <lb/>actions. He might have known that his heart was directed <lb/>towards the
          right-ſide; but if we conſider how little every <lb/>perſon, eſpecially thoſe of the lower
          claſs, are attentive to <lb/>circumſtances not very palpable, it was ſcarcely to be
          expected <lb/>he ſhould know of it. If I had met with any thing in his life <lb/>which was
          at all referable to the ſingularity of ſtructure, I <lb/>ſhould have been very glad to
          have gratified the public curioſity <lb/>by giving an account of it <note n="*"
            place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Since the above luſus has occurred, I have ſeen, in the poſſeſſion of Mr.
                <lb/><hi rend="sc">Payne</hi>, Surgeon, a fœtus at the full time, with the viſcera
              tranſpoſed. In the <lb/>Anatomical Collection of Chriſt Church, in Oxford, there is a
              heart tranſpoſed <lb/>that had belonged to a very ſmall fœtus; but the fœtus itſelf is
              not preſerved. </p>
          </note>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Every ſingular phænomenon in animal ſtructure is worth <lb/>remarking, even if it
          ſhould not lead immediately to any uſe- <lb/>ful obſervation; but it becomes more
          important if it ſhould <lb/>tend to throw any light upon the principles of nature in the
          <lb/>formation of animals. It is reaſonable to think, that nature <lb/>ſhould follow ſome
          general plan in her operations. There is <lb/>ſome effect which ſhe has in view, and ſhe
          will generally em- <lb/>ploy the ſame means to produce it. In the ſtructure of any
          <lb/>animal, her view is to form ſuch a combination of parts as to <lb/>render the animal
          fitted for certain purpoſes. She will com- <lb/>monly form the ſame combination where the
          ſame purpoſes <lb/>are to be ſerved; or, in other words, there will be the ſame
          <lb/>ſtructure in the ſame ſpecies of animals. The ſame effect <lb/>however may be
          produced, without a ſtrict adherence to the <lb/>employment of the ſame means, as we find
          to be the caſe <pb n="360"/>
          <lb/>in all human inventions, and therefore there is no reaſon why <lb/>nature ſhould not
          ſometimes deviate from her ordinary plans. <lb/>Accordingly we find there is much variety
          in animal ſtructure; <lb/>but this does not commonly affect the animal functions.
          <lb/>Under this reſtriction the variety is ſo great in the appearances <lb/>of every part
          of an animal, that it is almoſt impoſſible to exa- <lb/>mine any two animals of the ſame
          ſpecies without remarking <lb/>many differences. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In the bony compages of an animal we find little variety in <lb/>the extremities of
          bones where there is the apparatus of a joint, <lb/>becauſe a particular ſhape is beſt
          adapted to a particular kind or <lb/>latitude of motion. In other parts of the bones,
          where a <lb/>difference of features is not material, there is great variety, as <lb/>in
          the foramina, depreſſions, ridges, and ſutures of bones. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The ſame general rule will apply to variety in muſcles. The <lb/>principal object is
          a certain inſertion near a joint, ſo as to give <lb/>a determined direction of motion.
          With reſpect to ſuch in- <lb/>ſertions, there is, comparatively ſpeaking, little variety;
          but <lb/>there is a great difference in the bodies and connections of muſ- <lb/>cles,
          which have no ſhare in the regulation of the motion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>There is no part of an animal where there is a greater lati- <lb/>tude of variety
          than in the diſtribution of blood veſſels. The <lb/>reaſon of it is very obvious. The only
          object in the diſtribu- <lb/>tion of blood veſſels is, to carry blood to every part of the
          <lb/>body and bring it back to the heart. The parts of an animal, <lb/>in order to be
          ſupported, muſt be viſited by ſucceſſive changes <lb/>of freſh blood; but it ſurely cannot
          be an object of impor- <lb/>tance whether the blood paſſes by one rout or another. Hence
          <lb/>the variety in blood veſſels is extremely great. Still, however, <lb/>there is a
          method in the deviations of nature, ſo that they <pb n="361"/>
          <lb/>may be marked or noted, the ſame varieties occuring in dif- <lb/>ferent animals. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It cannot be at all important to the function of a viſcus, <lb/>whether it be in one
          maſs, or in ſeparate portions. The ſtruc- <lb/>ture being the ſame, the ſame action will
          take place. Hence <lb/>we often find the two kidnies joined together, forming one
          <lb/>maſs; and not unfrequently two or three ſpleens beſides the <lb/>common one. Neither
          can it be important, whether a viſcus <lb/>ſhould always be of the ſame ſhape, becauſe its
          functions do <lb/>not depend on ſhape, but on ſtructure: we find accordingly, <lb/>in this
          particular, much variety. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>There are many of the viſcera which are connected together <lb/>in their functions,
          or by the junction of large blood-veſſels, <lb/>in ſuch a way as to require nearly the
          ſame relative ſituation <lb/>among themſelves. This becomes alſo neceſſary in order to
          <lb/>preſerve the general ſhape of the animal. Accordingly we <lb/>find, that when any
          important viſcus is changed in its ſitua- <lb/>tion, it affects the ſituation of other
          viſcera, requiring in them <lb/>a ſimilar change. We ſaw in the perſon who is the ſubject
          <lb/>of this Paper, that a change in the ſituation of the heart and <lb/>liver was
          accompanied with a change of ſituation in the ſto- <lb/>mach, ſpleen, pancreas, and in
          ſhort the whole abdominal <lb/>viſcera. This, however, is a great deviation in nature; for
          <lb/>it is nothing leſs than changing almoſt the whole vital ſyſtem <lb/>in an animal, and
          therefore it rarely happens. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In ſuch a change it does not appear, that the functions can <lb/>be affected, as they
          depend on ſtructure and ſituation, which <lb/>are both preſerved. Hence the perſon who is
          the ſubject of <lb/>this Paper arrived at the age of maturity, and might have
          <lb/>continued to live to an extreme old age. </p>
        <pb n="362"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The human machine might have been conſtructed in this <lb/>way generally, and under
          ſuch circumſtances what is now <lb/>called the natural ſituation of parts would have been
          as ſingu- <lb/>lar as the preſent phænomenon. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>There appears to be leſs variety in the nervous ſyſtem of <lb/>animals of the ſame
          ſpecies than in moſt parts of the body. <lb/>There is ſcarcely any difference in the
          appearance of the brain, <lb/>and much leſs in the diſtribution of the nerves than of the
          <lb/>blood-veſſels. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>There is alſo little in variety in the organs of ſenſe: perhaps <lb/>the mechaniſm in
          both theſe is nicer, ſo that a conſiderable <lb/>deviation would interfere with their
          peculiar functions. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The moſt common great deviations which nature produces <lb/>in the ſtructure of an
          animal are various kinds of monſtroſity, <lb/>by which the animal becomes often unfit for
          continuing its <lb/>exiſtence. Why nature ſhould in its greater deviations fall <lb/>into
          a very imperfect formation, much below the ſtandard of <lb/>her common work, does not
          appear very obvious. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It ſeems that there might have been many varieties where <lb/>the functions could
          have been preſerved. Perhaps it is with a <lb/>view to check the propagation of great
          varieties, ſo as to pre- <lb/>ſerve an uniformity in the ſame ſpecies of animals. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It has been much agitated, whether monſtroſities depend on <lb/>the original
          formation, or are produced afterwards in the gra- <lb/>dual evolution of an animal. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This does not appear to be a queſtion of much importance; <lb/>nor perhaps can it be
          abſolutely determined. But upon the <lb/>whole it is more reaſonable to think, that the
          ſame plan of for- <lb/>mation is continued from the beginning, than that at any ſub-
          <lb/>ſequent period there is a change in that plan. </p>
        <pb n="363"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It may be obſerved, that it is exactly the ſame creative action <lb/>which produces
          the natural ſtructure, or any deviation from it; <lb/>for in caſes of deviation the action
          is either carried too far, <lb/>ceaſes too ſoon, or is diverted into uncommon channels.
          This <lb/>will explain the various kinds of monſtroſity from redundancy, <lb/>deficiency,
          or tranſpoſition of parts. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
