<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Home: An Account of a Child with a Double Head</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Everard Home</persName>
            </author>
            <title>An Account of a Child with a Double Head. In a Letter from Everard Home. Esq. F.
              R. S. to John Hunter, Esq. F. R. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Sold by Lockyer Davis and Peter Elmsly, Printers to the Royal
                  Society</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1790</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">80</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">296-305</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111041618</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1790.0020</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT80_0296">
    <body>
      <pb n="296"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XVI.</hi> An Account of a Child with a double Head. In a Letter
        <lb/>from <hi rend="roman">Everard Home</hi>, Eſq. F. R. S. to <hi rend="roman">John
          Hunter</hi>, Eſq. <lb/>F. R. S. </head>
      <space dim="vertical" quantity="2" unit="lines"> </space>
      <dateline rend="align-center">Read March 25, 1790. </dateline>
      <salute rend="sc space indent">
        <lb/>dear sir, </salute>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> FEEL a particular ſatisfaction in having been enabled,
        <lb/>through the kind attention of my Friend Captain <hi rend="sc">Bu- <lb/>chanan</hi>, to
        add to your invaluable collection the very uncom- <lb/>mon double ſkull of a monſtrous
        child, born in the Eaſt Indies, <lb/>which attracted the attention of all the curious in
        Calcutta, <lb/>where it was ſhewn alive; and, ſhould the following account <lb/>of it appear
        to you of ſufficient importance, I ſhall request <lb/>that you will do me the honour of
        laying it before the Royal <lb/>Society. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is much to be regretted, that the hiſtories of monſtrous <lb/>appearances in the
        ſtructure of the human body which are <lb/>to be found in the works of the older writers,
        and even of <lb/>many of the moderns, are ſo little to be depended upon. Few <lb/>authors
        have contented themſelves with giving a ſimple detail <lb/>of facts that were extraordinary;
        but, from an over anxiety to <lb/>make them ſtill more wonderful, or from having given an
        im- <lb/>plicit belief to the accounts received from the credulous and <lb/>ignorant, they
        have commonly added circumſtances too extra- <lb/>vagant to deſerve the attention of a
        reaſonable mind, which <pb n="297"/>
        <lb/>prevent the reader from giving credit to any part of the narra- <lb/>tion. This has
        been ſo general, that whenever the hiſtory of <lb/>any thing uncommon appears, the mind is
        impreſſed with a <lb/>doubt of its authenticity, and requires ſome ſtronger evidence <lb/>of
        the facts than the ſingle teſtimony of an individual in other <lb/>reſpects unimpeached in
        his veracity. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As the hiſtories of remarkable deviations from the common <lb/>courſe of nature in the
        formation of the human body already <lb/>regiſtered in the Philoſophical Tranſactions are
        very numerous, <lb/>I am deſirous of adding to them an account of one ſo truly
        <lb/>uncommon, that, I believe, no ſimilar inſtance is to be found <lb/>upon record. It is a
        ſpecies of <hi rend="italic">luſus naturæ</hi> ſo unaccountable, <lb/>that, although the
        facts are ſufficiently eſtabliſhed by the teſti- <lb/>monies of the moſt reſpectable
        witneſſes, I ſhould ſtill be dif- <lb/>fident in bringing them before the Royal Society,
        were I not <lb/>enabled at the ſame time to produce the double ſkull itſelf, in <lb/>which
        the appearances illuſtrate ſo clearly the different parts of <lb/>the hiſtory that is muſt
        be rendered perfectly ſatisfactory to <lb/>the minds of the moſt incredulous. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The following account of the child, when ſix months old, <lb/>I was favoured with from
        Sir <hi rend="sc">Joseph Banks</hi>; who, from the <lb/>hand-writing, and other
        circumſtances, believes that it was <lb/>written by the late Colonel <hi rend="sc"
          >Pierce</hi>. I have, however, been leſs <lb/>ſolicitous to aſcertain the author, as the
        obſervations contained in <lb/>this account agree ſo intirely with the remarks that were
        after- <lb/>wards made, and with the appearances of the ſkull, that they <lb/>require no
        name being annexed to them, in confirmation of <lb/>their having been made with accuracy and
        fidelity. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The child was born in May, 1783, of poor parents; the <lb/>mother was thirty years old,
        and named <hi rend="sc">Nooki</hi>; the father <pb n="298"/>
        <lb/>was called <hi rend="sc">Hannai</hi>, a farmer at Mandalgent near Bardawan, in
        <lb/>Bengal, and aged thirty-five. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>At the time of the child's birth, the woman who acted as <lb/>midwife, terrified at the
        ſtrange appearance of the double head, <lb/>endeavoured to deſtroy the infant by throwing it
        upon the fire, <lb/>where it lay a ſufficient time before it was removed to have one <lb/>of
        the eyes and ears conſiderably burnt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The body of the child was naturally formed, but the head <lb/>appeared double, there
        being, beſides the proper head of the <lb/>child, another of the ſame ſize, and to
        appearance almoſt <lb/>equally perfect, attached to its upper part. This upper head <lb/>was
        inverted, ſo that they ſeemed to be two ſeparate heads <lb/>united together by a firm
        adheſion between their crowns, but <lb/>without any indentation at their union, there being
        a ſmooth <lb/>continued ſurface from the one to the other. The face of the <lb/>upper head
        was not over that of the lower, but had an oblique <lb/>poſition, the center of it being
        immediately above the right eye. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the child was ſix months old, both of the heads were <lb/>covered with black hair,
        in nearly the ſame quantity. At this <lb/>period the ſkulls ſeemed to have been completely
        oſſified, ex- <lb/>cept a ſmall ſpace between the oſſa frontis of the upper one, <lb/>like a
        fontinelle. </p>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Obſervations on the ſuperior or inverted head. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>No pulſation could be felt in the ſituation of the temporal <lb/>arteries; but the
          ſuperficial veins were very evident. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The neck was about two inches long, and the upper part of <lb/>it terminated in a
          rounded ſoft tumor, like a ſmall peach. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>One of the eyes had been conſiderably hurt by the fire, but <lb/>the other appeared
          perfect, having its full quantity of motion; <lb/>but the eyelids were not thrown into
          action by any thing ſud- <lb/>denly approaching the eye; nor was the iris at thoſe times
          in <pb n="299"/>
          <lb/>the leaſt affected; but, when ſuddenly expoſed to a ſtrong <lb/>light, it contracted,
          although not ſo much as it uſually does. <lb/>The eyes did not correſpond in their motions
          with thoſe of the <lb/>lower head; but appeared often to be open when the child was
          <lb/>aſleep, and ſhut when it was awake. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The external ears were very imperfect, being only looſe folds <lb/>of ſkin; and one
          of them mutilated by having been burnt. <lb/>There did not appear to be any paſſage
          leading into the bone <lb/>which contains the organ of hearing. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The lower jaw was rather ſmaller than it naturally ſhould <lb/>be, but was capable of
          motion. The tongue was ſmall, flat, <lb/>and adhered firmly to the lower jaw, except for
          about half an <lb/>inch at the tip, which was looſe. The gums in both jaws <lb/>had the
          natural appearance; but no teeth were to be ſeen <lb/>either in this head or the other. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The internal ſurfaces of the noſe and mouth were lubri- <lb/>cated by the natural
          ſecretions, a conſiderable quantity of mu- <lb/>cus and ſaliva being occaſionally
          diſcharged from them. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The muſcles of the face were evidently poſſeſſed of powers <lb/>of action, and the
          whole head had a good deal of ſenſibility, <lb/>ſince violence to the ſkin produced the
          diſtortion expreſſive of <lb/>crying, and thruſting the finger into the mouth made it ſhew
          <lb/>ſtrong marks of pain. When the mother's nipple was applied <lb/>to the mouth, the
          lips attempted to ſuck. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The natural head had nothing uncommon in its appearance; <lb/>the eyes were attentive
          to objects, and its mouth ſucked the <lb/>breaſt vigorouſly. Its body was emaciated. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The parents of the child were poor, and carried it about the <lb/>ſtreets of Calcutta
          as a curioſity to be ſeen for money; and to <lb/>prevent its being expoſed to the
          populace, they kept it con- <lb/>ſtanly covered up, which was conſidered as the cauſe of
          its <lb/>being emaciated and unhealthy. </p>
        <pb n="300"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The attention of the curious was naturally attracted by ſo <lb/>uncommon a ſpecies of
          deformity; and Mr. <hi rend="sc">Stark</hi>, who re- <lb/>ſided in Bengal during this
          period, paid particular attention to <lb/>the appearances of the different parts of the
          double head, and <lb/>endeavoured to aſcertain the mode in which the two ſkulls <lb/>were
          united, as well as to diſcover the ſympathies which <lb/>exiſted between the two brains.
          Upon his return to <lb/>England, finding that I was in poſſeſſion of the ſkull, <lb/>and
          propoſed drawing up an account of the child, he very <lb/>obligingly favoured me with the
          following particulars, <lb/>and has likewiſe allowed me to have a ſketch taken <lb/>from a
          very exact painting, made under his own inſpection <lb/>from the child while alive, by Mr.
            <hi rend="sc">Smith</hi>, a portrait painter <lb/>then in India. From this drawing,
          which was annexed, and <lb/>two others, repreſenting the heads in the natural ſtate; and
          the <lb/>ſkulls, when all the other parts were removed, a much more <lb/>accurate idea
          will be given of the child's appearance than can <lb/>be conveyed by any deſcription. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>At the time Mr. <hi rend="sc">Stark</hi> ſaw the child, it muſt have been <lb/>nearly
          two years old <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* The dentes molares, or double teeth, which uſually appear at twenty months
              <lb/>or two years of age, were through the gum; and there was no reaſon to expect
              <lb/>them very early in this child. </p>
          </note>, as it was ſome months before its death, <lb/>which I have every reaſon to believe
          happened in the year 1785. <lb/>At this period the appearances differed in many reſpects
          from <lb/>thoſe taken notice of when only ſix months old. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The burnt ear had ſo much recovered itſelf as only to have <lb/>loſt about one fourth
          part of the looſe pendulous flap. The <lb/>openings leading from the external ear appeared
          as diſtinct as <lb/>in thoſe of the other head. The ſkin ſurrounding the injured eye,
          <lb/>which was on the ſame ſide with the mutilated ear, was in a <pb n="301"/>
          <lb/>ſlight degree affected, and the external canthus much con- <lb/>tracted, but the eye
          itſelf was perfect. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The eyelids of the ſuperior head were never completely <lb/>ſhut, remaining a little
          open, even when the child was aſleep, <lb/>and the eyeballs moved at random. When the
          child was <lb/>rouſed, the eyes of both heads moved at the ſame time; but <lb/>thoſe of
          the ſuperior head did not appear to be directed to the <lb/>ſame object, but wandered in
          different directions. The tears <lb/>flowed from the eyes of the ſuperior head almoſt
          conſtantly, <lb/>but never from the eyes of the other, except when crying. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The termination of the upper neck was very irregular, a <lb/>good deal reſembling the
          cicatrix of an old ſore. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The ſuperior head ſeemed to ſympathiſe with the child in <lb/>moſt of its natural
          actions. When the child cried, the features <lb/>of this head were affected in a ſimilar
          manner, and the tears <lb/>flowed plentifully. When it ſucked the mother, ſatisfaction
          <lb/>was expreſſed by the mouth of the ſuperior head, and the <lb/>ſaliva flowed more
          copiouſly than at any other time; for it <lb/>always flowed a little from it. When the
          child ſmiled, the <lb/>features of the ſuperior head ſympathiſed in that action. When
          <lb/>the ſkin of the ſuperior head was pinched, the child ſeemed to <lb/>feel little or no
          pain, at leaſt not in the ſame proportion as was <lb/>felt from a ſimilar violence being
          committed on its own head <lb/>or body. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When the child was about two years old, and in perfect <lb/>health, the mother went
          out to fetch ſome water; and, upon <lb/>her return, found it dead, from the bite of a <hi
            rend="italic">Cobra de ca- <lb/>pelo</hi>. The parents at this time lived upon the
          grounds of <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="sc">Dent</hi>, the honourable Eaſt India Company's Agent for
          <lb/>Salt at Tumloch, and the body was buried near the banks of <lb/>the Boopnorain river.
          It was afterwards dug up by Mr. <hi rend="sc">Dent</hi>
          <pb n="302"/>
          <lb/>and his European ſervant, the religious prejudices of the <lb/>parents not allowing
          them to diſpenſe with its being interred. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>My friend, Captain <hi rend="sc">Buchanan</hi>, late Commander of the <lb/>Ranger
          Packet, in the ſervice of the honourable the Eaſt India <lb/>Company, when at Bengal
          reſided a few days in Mr. <hi rend="sc">Dent</hi>'s <lb/>houſe. He was much ſtruck with
          the uncommon appearance <lb/>of the double ſkull, and expreſſed a wiſh that he might be
          <lb/>allowed to bring it to Europe, and preſent it to me; know- <lb/>ing, from the
          intereſt I have always taken in thoſe purſuits <lb/>which have ſo long and ſo deeply
          engaged your attention, it <lb/>would be a moſt acceptable preſent. His requeſt was no
          ſooner <lb/>communicated to Mr. <hi rend="sc">Dent</hi>, than it was complied with; that
          <lb/>gentleman having too much liberality to heſitate a moment in <lb/>ſending ſo rare a
          curioſity to Europe. I ſhould do both theſe <lb/>gentlemen injuſtice, were I not to
          attribute their readineſs upon <lb/>the preſent occaſion to oblige me, in a great meaſure
          to their <lb/>knowing that the double ſkull would be depoſited in your col- <lb/>lection,
          which muſt now be conſidered more as a national and <lb/>public repoſitory than a private
          cabinet. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The two ſkulls which compoſe this monſtrous head appear <lb/>to be nearly of the ſame
          ſize, and equally complete in their <lb/>oſſification, except a ſmall ſpace at the upper
          edge of the oſſa <lb/>frontis of the ſuperior ſkull, ſimilar to a fontinelle. The
          <lb/>mode in which the two are united is curious, as no portion of <lb/>bone is either
          added or diminiſhed for that purpoſe; but the <lb/>frontal and parietal bones of each
          ſkull, inſtead of being bent <lb/>inwards, ſo as to form the top of the head, are
          continued on; <lb/>and, from the oblique poſition of the two heads, the bones of <lb/>the
          one paſs a little way into the natural ſutures of the other, <lb/>forming a zig-zag line,
          or circular ſuture uniting them toge- <lb/>ther. </p>
        <pb n="303"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The two ſkulls appear to be almoſt equally perfect at their <lb/>union; but the
          ſuperior ſkull, as it recedes from the other, is <lb/>becoming more imperfect and
          deficient in many of its parts. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The meatus auditorius in the temporal bone is altogether <lb/>wanting. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The baſis of the ſkull is imperfect in ſeveral reſpects, par- <lb/>ticularly in ſuch
          parts as are to connect the ſkull with a body. <lb/>The foramen magnum occipitale is a
          ſmall irregular hole, <lb/>very inſufficient to give paſſage to a medulla ſpinalis; round
          <lb/>its margin are no condyles with articulating ſurfaces, as there <lb/>were no vertebræ
          of the neck to be attached to it. The fora- <lb/>men lacerum in baſi cranii is only to be
          ſeen on one ſide, and <lb/>even there too ſmall for the jugular vein to have paſſed
          through. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The oſſa palati are deficient at their poſterior part; the lower <lb/>jaw is too
          ſmall for the upper, and the condyle and coronoid <lb/>proceſs of one ſide are wholly
          wanting. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In moſt of the other reſpects, the two ſkulls are alike; the <lb/>number of teeth in
          both is the ſame, and is ſixteen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>From an examination of the internal ſtructure of the double <lb/>ſkull, the two
          brains have certainly been incloſed in one bony <lb/>caſe, there being no ſeptum of bone
          between them. How far <lb/>they were intirely diſtinct, and ſurrounded by their proper
          <lb/>membranes, cannot now be aſcertained; but from the ſympa- <lb/>thies which were taken
          notice of by Mr. <hi rend="sc">Stark</hi> between the <lb/>two heads, more particularly
          thoſe of the ſuperior with the <lb/>lower, or more perfect, I ſhould be inclined to
          believe, that <lb/>there was a more intimate connection between them than ſimply <lb/>by
          means of nerves, and therefore that the ſubſtance of the <lb/>brains was continued into
          one another. </p>
        <p rend="aling-right">
          <lb/>Had the child lived to a more advanced age, and given men <lb/>of obſervation
          opportunities of attending to the effects of this <pb n="304"/>
          <lb/>double brain, its influence upon the intellectual principle muſt <lb/>have afforded a
          curious and uſeful ſource of inquiry; but un- <lb/>fortunately the child only lived long
          enough to complete the <lb/>oſſification of the ſkull ſo as to retain its ſhape, by which
          means <lb/>we have been enabled to aſcertain and regiſter the fact, without <lb/>having
          enjoyed the ſatisfaction that would have reſulted from <lb/>an examination of the brain
          itſelf, and a more mature inveſti- <lb/>gation of the effects it would have produced. </p>
        <signed rend="align-center">
          <lb/>Yours, &amp;c. <lb/><hi rend="align-right space">E. HOME. </hi>
        </signed>
        <dateline rend="size(0.7) indentall">
          <lb/>Leiceſter ſquare, <lb/>May 22, 1790. </dateline>
      </div>
      <figure>
        <head rend="sc align-center space">
          <lb/>explanation of the plates. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Tab. XVII. The child is repreſented in this plate as it <lb/> appeared at the age of
          twenty months, and is copied from a <lb/>picture in the poſſeſſion of Mr. <hi rend="sc"
            >Stark</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The painting was taken from the child ſix months before its <lb/>death by Mr. <hi
            rend="sc">Smith</hi>, an ingenious artiſt, at that time reſiding <lb/>in Bengal. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It conveys a general idea of the appearance of this extraor- <lb/>dinary child, and
          the relative proportions between the double <lb/>head and the body. </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of the child on a separate fold-out page. The child, viewed from
          its right, is reclining on its back on a blanket, both heads supported by a pillow; the
          double head, however, rather than pointing upwards like the other one, faces the reader.
        </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Tab. XVIII. fig. 1. In this figure the double head is repreſented <lb/>exactly half
          the natural ſize. One of the eyes of the upper <lb/>face appears ſmaller or more
          contracted than the other; this <lb/>is in conſequence of the injury it received when the
          child was <lb/>thrown upon the fire. </p>
        <pb n="305"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The ſuperficial veins upon the forehead of the upper head <lb/>are very diſtinctly
          ſeen. </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration on a separate fold-out page, showing only the heads of the child:
          the upper, double head is upside down and faces the reader, while the lower one looks to
          the right. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Fig. 2. An exact repreſentation of the double ſkull, which <lb/>is now in Mr. <hi
            rend="sc">Hunter</hi>'s collection, upon the ſame ſcale as <lb/>fig. 1. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It ſhews the curious manner in which the two ſkulls are <lb/>united together, and the
          number of teeth formed before the <lb/>child's death; which circumſtance aſcertains, with
          tolerable <lb/>accuracy, its age. </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of the double skull on a separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
