<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Home: The Croonian Lecture on Muscular Motion</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Everard Home</persName>
            </author>
            <title>The Croonian Lecture on Muscular Motion. By Everard Home, Esq. F. R. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Sold by Peter Elmsly, Printer to the Royal Society</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1795</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">85</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">1-23</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111043554</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1795.0002</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT85_0001">
    <body>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">I.</hi> The <hi rend="roman">Croonian</hi> Lecture on Muscular Motion.
        By <hi rend="roman">Everard <lb/>Home</hi>, Esq. F.R.S. </head>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <dateline rend="align-center">
        <lb/>Read November 13, 1794. </dateline>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">W</hi><hi rend="sc">hen</hi> I had the honour last year of
        presenting an apology <lb/>for the unfinished state in which Mr. <hi rend="sc">Hunter</hi>
        left the <hi rend="sc">Croo- <lb/>nian </hi>lecture, I laid before this learned Society the
        plan upon <lb/>which he meant to proceed; but my mind was at that time <lb/>unfitted to
        prosecute so arduous an inquiry. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The progress Mr. <hi rend="sc">Hunter</hi> had made in this investigation <lb/>enabled
        him to prove the crystalline humour of the eye to be <lb/>laminated, and the laminæ to be
        composed of fibres; but the <lb/>use to which these fibres are applied in the œconomy of the
        <lb/>eye he had not ascertained, although several experiments were <lb/>instituted with that
        view: his opinion was certainly in favour <lb/>of their being muscular, for the purpose of
        adjusting the eye <lb/>to different distances by their contraction and relaxation. </p>
      <pb n="2"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Being unwilling that a subject on which Mr. <hi rend="sc">Hunter</hi> had <lb/>so
        publicly given his opinion should remain in an unfinished <lb/>state, I requested the
        President's permission to be allowed to <lb/>give the <hi rend="sc">Croonian</hi> lecture
        for the present year, as it would <lb/>afford me an opportunity of weighing with
        impartiality the <lb/>facts already ascertained, and of endeavouring by my own la-
        <lb/>bours to add to their number. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In prosecuting this inquiry, I consider myself to have been <lb/>particularly fortunate
        in having had the assistance of my friend <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="sc">Ramsden</hi>. It was a
        subject connected with his own pur- <lb/>suits, and one which had always engaged his
        attention; he <lb/>was therefore peculiarly fitted, both by his own ingenuity <lb/>and
        knowledge in optics, for such an investigation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In conversing upon the different uses of the crystalline hu- <lb/>mour, he made the
        following observations. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He said, that as the crystalline humour consists of a sub- <lb/>stance of different
        densities, the central parts being the most <lb/>compact, and from thence diminishing in
        density gradually in <lb/>every direction, approaching the vitreous humour on one side,
        <lb/>and the aqueous humour on the other, its refractive power be- <lb/>comes nearly the
        same with that of the two contiguous sub- <lb/>stances. That some philosophers have stated
        the use of the crys- <lb/>talline humour to be, for accommodating the eye to see objects
        <lb/>at different distances; but the firmness of the central part, and <lb/>the very small
        difference between its refractive power near the <lb/>circumference and that of the
        vitreous, or the aqueous humour, <lb/>seemed to render it unfit for that purpose; its
        principal use <lb/>rather appearing to be for correcting the aberration arising <lb/>from
        the spherical figure of the cornea, where the principal <lb/>part of the refraction takes
        place, producing the same effect <pb n="3"/>
        <lb/>that in an achromatic object glass we obtain in a less perfect <lb/>manner, by
        proportioning the radii of curvature of the different <lb/>lenses. In the eye, the
        correction seems perfect, which in the <lb/>object glass can only be an approximation, the
        contrary aber- <lb/>rations of the lenses not having the same ratio; so that if <lb/>this
        aberration be perfectly corrected at any given distance <lb/>from the centre, in every other
        it must be in some degree im- <lb/>perfect. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Pursuing the same comparison: In the achromatic object <lb/>glass, we may conceive how
        much an object must appear fainter <lb/>from the great quantity of light lost by reflection
        at the sur- <lb/>faces of the different lenses, there being as many primary re-
        <lb/>flections as there are surfaces; and it would be fortunate if <lb/>this reflected light
        was totally lost. Part of it is again reflected <lb/>towards the eye by the interior
        surfaces of the lenses, which <lb/>by diluting the image formed in the focus of the object
        glass, <lb/>makes that image appear far less bright than it would other- <lb/>wise have
        done, producing that milky appearance so often <lb/>complained of in viewing lucid objects
        through this sort of <lb/>telescope. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the eye the same properties that obviate this defect, <lb/>serve also to correct the
        errors from the spherical figure, by a <lb/>regular diminution of density from the centre of
        the crystal- <lb/>line outward. Every appearance shews the crystalline to con- <lb/>sist of
        laminæ of different densities; and if we examine the <lb/>junction of different media,
        having a very small difference of <lb/>refraction, we shall find that we may have a sensible
        refrac- <lb/>tion without reflection: now if the difference between the <lb/>contiguous
        media in the eye, or the laminæ in the crystal- <lb/>line, be very small, we shall have
        refraction without having <pb n="4"/>
        <lb/>reflection, and this appears to be the state of the eye; for al- <lb/>though we have
        two surfaces of the aqueous, two of the crys- <lb/>talline, and two of the vitreous humour,
        yet we have only one <lb/>reflected image, and that being from the anterior surface of the
        <lb/>cornea, there can be no surface to reflect it back, and dilute <lb/>an image on the
        retina. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This hypothesis may be put to the test, whenever accident <lb/>shall furnish us with a
        subject having the crystalline extracted <lb/>from one eye, the other remaining perfect in
        its natural state; <lb/>at the same time we may ascertain whether or no the crystal-
        <lb/>line is that part of the organ, which serves for viewing objects <lb/>at different
        distances distinctly. Seeing no reflection at the <lb/>surface of the crystalline, might
        lead some persons to infer <lb/>that its refractive power is very inconsiderable, but many
        cir- <lb/>cumstances shew the contrary; yet what it really is may be <lb/>readily
        ascertained, by having the focal length and distance <lb/>of a lens from the operated eye,
        that enables it to see objects <lb/>the most distinctly; also the focal length of a lens,
        and its dis- <lb/>tance from the perfect eye that enables it to see objects at the <lb/>same
        distance as the imperfect eye; these data will be suffi- <lb/>cient, whereby to calculate
        the refractive power of the crys- <lb/>talline with considerable precision. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Again, having the spherical aberration of the different hu- <lb/>mours of the eye, and
        having ascertained the refractive power <lb/>of the crystalline, we have data from whence to
        determine the <lb/>proportional increase of its density as it approaches the central
        <lb/>part, on a supposition that this property corrects the aber- <lb/>ration. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>These observations of Mr. <hi rend="sc">Ramsden</hi> respecting the use of the
        <lb/>crystalline lens, I was very desirous of bringing to the proof; <pb n="5"/>
        <lb/>and while my mind was strongly impressed by them, a favour- <lb/>able opportunity
        occurred. A young man came into St. George's <lb/>hospital with a cataract in the right eye:
        this proved to be a <lb/>fair case for an operation, to which the man very cheerfully
        <lb/>submitted, and was put under my care for that purpose. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In performing the operation, the crystalline lens was very <lb/>readily extracted, and
        the union of the wound in the cornea <lb/>took place unattended by inflammation, so that the
        eye suf- <lb/>fered the smallest degree of injury that can attend so severe an
        <lb/>operation; these circumstances it is proper to mention, as <lb/>they contributed to
        render the patient a more favourable sub- <lb/>ject for experiment. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The man's name was <hi rend="sc">Benjamin Clerk</hi>; he was a seafaring <lb/>man, 21
        years of age, and in perfect health. Both his eyes were <lb/>free from complaint till about
        the 11th of April, 1793, at which <lb/>time he was on a voyage home from the East Indies, a
        sud- <lb/>den mist or dimness appeared before his right eye; this in- <lb/>creased very
        rapidly, and on the 18th of the same month the <lb/>sight was entirely obscured. The
        crystalline humour was ex- <lb/>tracted on the 25th of November; and 27 days after the ope-
        <lb/>ration the eye was so far recovered as to admit of the fol- <lb/>lowing observations
        and experiments being made upon it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In this man we had all the circumstances combined, which <lb/>seemed to be required to
        determine how far the crystalline lens <lb/>was the principal agent in adjusting the eye.
        The man himself <lb/>was in health, young, intelligent, and his left eye perfect; the
        <lb/>other had been an uncommonly short time in a diseased state, <lb/>and appeared to be
        free from every other defect but the loss of <lb/>the crystalline lens. He very willingly
        allowed me to make <lb/>the following experiments on him; and remained in town, <pb n="6"/>
        <lb/>although inconvenient to himself, till they were completed; <lb/>the greater part of
        them were instituted by Mr. <hi rend="sc">Ramsden</hi>, and <lb/>all of them carried through
        under his direction. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The experiments were begun on the 22d of December, 1793, <lb/>at which time the
        following observations were made upon the <lb/>imperfect eye. The eye bore the light of the
        day very well; <lb/>but was fatigued by strong sunshine, or the glare of candle- <lb/>light.
        In weak lights objects were not seen at all by the im- <lb/>perfect eye, but in strong
        lights they presented a faint image, <lb/>which appeared at the same distance with that seen
        by the <lb/>perfect eye, and close to it, or nearly so, but always to the <lb/>left. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The imperfect eye, unassisted by glasses, could see objects, <lb/>but it was with a
        degree of indistinctness; and this indistinct <lb/>vision only took place at a distance
        between six and nine <lb/>inches. With a double convex glass, the radius of one sur-
        <lb/>face an inch and an half, of the other six inches, the flat side <lb/>towards the eye,
        having a focus of 2¼ inches, objects ap- <lb/>peared most distinct at 4½ inches, and the
        extremes were 2½ <lb/>inches, and 5½ inches. The different distances were ascertained
        <lb/>by placing one end of a foot rule against the man's fore- <lb/>head, and giving him the
        book in his own hand, desiring <lb/>him to carry it to the distance at which he saw best,
        and <lb/>afterwards to the two extremes of distinct vision, the upper <lb/>end of the book
        being always in contact with the rule; so <lb/>that the moment he adjusted the book, the
        distance was read <lb/>off from the scale. The accuracy with which he brought it <lb/>to the
        same point in repeating the experiments, proved his eye <lb/>to be uncommonly correct; for
        as he did not himself see the <lb/>scale, there could be no source of fallacy. </p>
      <pb n="7"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Making these experiments fatigued the eye considerably, <lb/>and repeating them after
        very short intervals made the eye <lb/>water, and gave a slight degree of pain; this,
        however, soon <lb/>went off. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In looking at objects through this glass, the image was free <lb/>from any tinge of
        colour, unless he directed his eye towards the <lb/>circumference of the glass, and then it
        had a considerable <lb/>tinge, which evidently arose from the prismatic figure of that
        <lb/>part of the glass. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A comparative experiment was made upon the perfect eye, <lb/>with a glass of 15 inches
        focus. Objects were found in one ex- <lb/>periment to appear most distinct at 8½ inches, the
        extremes <lb/>3 inches and 11 inches; in another, most distinct at 7 inches, <lb/>the
        extremes as before, 3 and 11 inches. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 29th of December, 34 days after the operation, the <lb/>following experiments
        were made by candle-light, about six <lb/>o'clock in the evening. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The experiment with the double convex glass was repeated, <lb/>the aperture being
        diminished to 3/20 of an inch; objects ap- <lb/>peared most distinct at 5 inches, the
        extremes 3 inches and <lb/>7¾ inches. The aperture was diminished to 3/40 of an inch, and
        <lb/>vision appeared most distinct at 5 inches, the extremes 3½ <lb/>inches and 7 inches.
        When the aperture was reduced to 1/20 of <lb/>an inch, the inflexion of the rays produced
        the appearance of <lb/>a speck, which obscured his vision. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By diminishing the aperture, spherical aberration was in a <lb/>great measure
        corrected, and vision rendered more distinct. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A plano-convex glass of 2⅞ inches focus, with the plane <lb/>towards the eye, was now
        applied, and the objects were most <lb/>distinct at 6 inches, but by no means well defined:
        the aper- <pb n="8"/>
        <lb/>ture was now reduced to 4/30 of an inch, and objects appeared <lb/>much more distinct
        at 5½ inches; when the glass was brought <lb/>within half an inch of the eye, objects were
        still more distinct, <lb/>and were seen at 5 inches. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The eye was less affected by these than the former experi- <lb/>ments, nor was it
        fatigued by the light of the candle. In strong <lb/>lights a faint image was seen by the
        imperfect eye, and always <lb/>to the left of the other. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The perfect eye, with a glass of 15 inches focus, saw objects <lb/>most distinctly at
        8½ inches, the extremes 3½ inches and 11¼ <lb/>inches. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As these experiments were made with a view to determine <lb/>whether the eye, when
        deprived of its crystalline humour, had <lb/>a power of adjusting itself to different
        distances; that being <lb/>ascertained, they were not prosecuted further, on account of
        <lb/>the tender state of the man's eye, who went into the country <lb/>as soon as they were
        completed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 4th of November, 1794, the man returned to Lon- <lb/>don, and submitted himself
        to be the subject of further experi- <lb/>ments. This afforded us an opportunity of
        ascertaining the <lb/>comparative adjustment of the two eyes, when by means of
        <lb/>different glasses they were brought to see distinctly at nearly <lb/>the same focal
        distance: an experiment we had been unable <lb/>to make before for want of proper glasses. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Sir <hi rend="sc">Henry Englefield</hi>, who will be found to have given <lb/>us his
        assistance in the subsequent part of this investigation, <lb/>was present at this
        experiment, and was much astonished, as <lb/>we had been in the former ones, at the accuracy
        with which <lb/>the man's eye was adjusted to the same distance in the re- <lb/>peated
        trials that were made with it. </p>
      <pb n="9"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The perfect eye, with a glass of 6½ inches focus, had dis- <lb/>tinct vision at 3
        inches; the near limit was 1⅞ inch, the distant <lb/>one less than 7 inches. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The imperfect eye, with a glass 2 2/10 inches focus, with an <lb/>aperture 3/40 of an
        inch, had distinct vision at 2⅞ inches, the near <lb/>limit 1⅞ inch, the distant one 7
        inches. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From the result of this experiment we find that the range <lb/>of adjustment of the
        imperfect eye, when the two eyes were <lb/>made to see at nearly the same focal distance,
        exceeded that <lb/>of the perfect eye. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>These experiments were made by Mr. <hi rend="sc">Ramsden</hi>, who took <lb/>particular
        care to avoid every thing that might be productive <lb/>of error or deception; and repeated
        them several times before <lb/>any conclusions were drawn from them. Several others were
        <lb/>made on the same subject, but as they only tended to confirm <lb/>those already
        mentioned, it would be taking up the time of <lb/>this learned Society unnecessarily to
        detail them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It may be proper to mention a reason which suggested it- <lb/>self to Mr. <hi rend="sc"
          >Ramsden</hi>, why the point of distinct vision of the <lb/>imperfect eye appeared to the
        man himself nearer than it was <lb/>in reality; it arose from his judging of distinctness by
        the <lb/>legibility of the letters, which were easier read when they sub- <lb/>tended a
        greater angle (from the imperfection of his eye) than <lb/>at his real point of distinct
        vision. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The result of these experiments convinced us that the in- <lb/>ternal power of the eye,
        by which it is adjusted to see at dif- <lb/>ferent distances, does not reside in the
        crystalline lens; we <lb/>were also satisfied by the facts and arguements adduced in Mr.
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Hunter</hi>'s letter on this subject, published in the first part
        <lb/>of the last volume of the Philosophical Transactions, that it <pb n="10"/>
        <lb/>does not arise from a change in the general form of the globe <lb/>of the eye; we
        therefore abandoned both of these theories. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It suggested itself that any change in the curve of the cornea <lb/>(could it be
        produced), would vary the refraction of the rays, <lb/>so as considerably to alter the focus
        of the eye; and upon con- <lb/>sidering this subject, Mr. <hi rend="sc">Ramsden</hi> made a
        rough calculation, <lb/>from which it appeared, that a very small alteration in that
        <lb/>part would vary the adjustment of the eye from parallel rays <lb/>to its shortest
        distance of distinct vision. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This opened to us a new field of inquiry, and I endea- <lb/>voured to ascertain how far
        the cornea admitted of such a <lb/>change, and if it did, how far that change operated in
        pro- <lb/>ducing this particular effect. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For the first of these purposes I made the following experi- <lb/>ments in the presence
        of Mr. <hi rend="sc">Ramsden</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A portion of the cornea ⅛ of an inch broad, and 11/20 of an <lb/>inch long, was removed
        from the eye of a person 40 years of <lb/>age, two days after death, with a part of the
        sclerotic coat on <lb/>each side attached to it. This was laid upon a piece of glass
        <lb/>immersed in water, under which was a scale divided into very <lb/>minute parts, these
        divisions being very readily seen through <lb/>the glass. One end of the cornea was made
        fast by fixing the <lb/>sclerotic coat, and a force was applied to the other; this power
        <lb/>was found capable of elongating the cornea 1/20 part of an inch; <lb/>and on removing
        it, the cornea recovered itself to its original <lb/>length. In different trials it varied
        in the quantity of elonga- <lb/>tion, but in all of them it was fully 1/11 part of the whole
        <lb/>length, or diameter of the cornea. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The elasticity of the cornea being thus ascertained, en- <lb/>couraged me to proceed in
        the anatomical investigation; and <pb n="11"/>
        <lb/>I was desirous of determining more exactly than had hitherto <lb/>been done, the
        precise insertion of the tendons of the four <lb/>straight muscles of the eye, so as to know
        whether their ac- <lb/>tion could be extended to the cornea or not. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In dissecting these muscles to their termination, I found <lb/>that they approached
        within ⅛ of an inch of the cornea, before <lb/>their tendons became attached to the
        sclerotic coat upon which <lb/>they lay; it was evident that they did not terminate at this
        <lb/>part, but were so united as to be difficultly separated by dis- <lb/>section; I
        therefore endeavoured by gentle force to pull them <lb/>asunder, as in that way the parts
        would separate in the direc- <lb/>tion of their fibres. In doing this, they not only
        admitted of <lb/>separation to the edge of the cornea, but brought away a lamina <lb/>of the
        cornea with them. I thought this would be better seen <lb/>in an eye after putrefaction had
        begun to take place, but found <lb/>that in that state it could scarcely be demonstrated;
        while <lb/>in the recent eye the whole of the external lamina of the cornea <lb/>could be
        brought away along with the four straight muscles, <lb/>leaving the surface underneath
        uniform, but without polish, <lb/>and upon the same plane with the sclerotic coat, of which
        it <lb/>was a continuation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As this was a new fact, and a very important one, shewing a <lb/>connection between
        these muscles and the cornea, I have dried <lb/>the parts, and preserved them in that state,
        to shew the mode <lb/>in which the tendons of the straight muscles are lost in the
        <lb/>cornea, giving it the appearance of a central tendon. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The cornea from this investigation is proved to be com- <lb/>posed of two laminæ, the
        external a continuation of the ten- <lb/>dons of the four straight muscles, the other a
        continuation of <lb/>the sclerotic coat, and the uniting medium between them is <lb/>not
        unlike very fine cellular membrane. </p>
      <pb n="12"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If the cornea is examined at its attachment to the sclerotic <lb/>coat and tendons of
        the straight muscles, it appears to be of <lb/>exactly the same thickness with those parts,
        but grows thicker <lb/>towards the centre; this increase of thickness is principally <lb/>in
        the external lamina, for when that is removed, the other <lb/>appears equally so through its
        whole extent. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To ascertain that the cornea is really thickest in the middle, <lb/>I made a transverse
        section of it, and Mr. <hi rend="sc">Ramsden</hi>, with se- <lb/>veral other gentlemen,
        examined the cut edge through a mag- <lb/>nifying glass, and all of them were satisfied with
        the fact of the <lb/>central part being evidently thicker than that which was nearer <lb/>to
        the circumference. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is necessary to mention, that in stretching the cornea <lb/>the central part yields
        most readily to the power applied; this <lb/>is so much the case, that if the cut edge of
        the cornea is <lb/>examined while it is several times drawn out and allowed to <lb/>contract
        again, the change in the centre will be found the <lb/>most distinct; the principal
        elasticity appearing to reside in <lb/>that part. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Before these experiments were made upon the cornea, Mr. <lb/><hi rend="sc">Ramsden</hi>
        had promised me that he would contrive an instru- <lb/>ment by which the cornea might be
        examined, while the eye <lb/>was adapting itself to different distances; so as to enable us
        <lb/>to decide whether any change took place at these times in its <lb/>external figure. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When I state to this learned Society, that seven months <lb/>elapsed before the
        apparatus for this experiment was com- <lb/>pleted, they will not attribute it to a want of
        solicitude on my <lb/>part, or a want of attention in Mr. <hi rend="sc">Ramsden</hi>; but to
        delays <lb/>which must necessarily occur to an artist so extensively em- <lb/>ployed in
        business, and at the same time so ready to engage <pb n="13"/>
        <lb/>both from inclination, and the urgent requests of his friends, <lb/>in promoting
        philosophical inquiries. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 31st of July, 1794, we were enabled to begin our ex- <lb/>periments, for which
        the following apparatus was constructed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A thick board was fixed to a strong upright support, di- <lb/>rectly opposite to the
        window of Mr. <hi rend="sc">Ramsden</hi>'s front room on <lb/>the first floor, which looks
        up Sackville-street, at the distance <lb/>of one foot from the window. In this board was a
        square hole, <lb/>large enough to admit a person's face, the forehead and chin <lb/>resting
        against the upper and lower bars, and the cheek against <lb/>either of the sides, so that
        when the face was protruded, the <lb/>head was steadily fixed by resting on three sides, and
        in this <lb/>position the left eye projected beyond the outer surface of the <lb/>board. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the outside of the board, or that next the window, <lb/>upon the left of the square
        hole, was fixed a microscope, so <lb/>placed as to take into its field the lateral part of
        the front of <lb/>the cornea, which projects beyond the eyelids. The micro- <lb/>scope had
        not only a movement directly forwards, but by <lb/>means of endless screws, had also a
        vertical and horizontal <lb/>motion, without which the experiments could not have been
        <lb/>made with any degree of precision. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From the upper part of the square hole an horizontal brass <lb/>beam projected towards
        the window, with joints, by which it <lb/>could be lengthened or shortened, and at the end
        of this a brass <lb/>plate was suspended, which admitted of being raised or de-
        <lb/>pressed, so as to bring a small hole that had been drilled through <lb/>it directly
        opposite to the eye. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>With this apparatus we began our experiments; and I con- <lb/>sider it as a fortunate
        circumstance that Sir <hi rend="sc">Henry Englefield</hi>
        <pb n="14"/>
        <lb/>arrived in town the night before they were made; he very <lb/>cheerfully gave us his
        assistance the moment I made the <lb/>request. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Sir <hi rend="sc">Henry</hi>, from his practical knowledge of mathematical
        <lb/>instruments, and the habit of making observations with them, <lb/>rendered us very
        material assistance in the course of our ex- <lb/>periments, and I feel myself obliged to
        him for remaining in <lb/>town till they were completed. To Mr. <hi rend="sc">Ramsden</hi>
        and my- <lb/>self it was a particular satisfaction to have an evidence who <lb/>had no
        presupposed opinion, therefore impartial; whose know- <lb/>ledge of the subject enabled him
        to form a judgment of the re- <lb/>sults, and to correct any error we might fall into in
        conducting <lb/>the experiments. This circumstance will also give to the ex- <lb/>periments
        an additional claim upon the notice of this learned <lb/>Society. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The first experiment was made at three o'clock, at which <lb/>were present Sir <hi
          rend="sc">Henry Englefield</hi>, Mr. <hi rend="sc">Ramsden</hi>, and <lb/>myself. It
        required some time, and considerable ability, in <lb/>which I can claim no part, to adjust
        the microscope, and bring <lb/>the cornea into its field; when this was done, the
        appearances <lb/>were so different from what were expected, that we had a dif- <lb/>ficulty
        in recognizing the objects; all that could be seen was 4 <lb/>curved lines, but even these
        were rendered confused by reflec- <lb/>tions from the cross bars of the sash of the window.
        Upon throw- <lb/>ing up the sash, the curved lines became very distinct, and that <lb/>which
        appeared the inner one in the microscope, was ascer- <lb/>tained to be the convex projecting
        surface of the cornea. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This being determined, the person whose eye was the object <lb/>of the experiment was
        desired to look at the corner of a chim- <lb/>ney at the upper end of Sackville-street, a
        distance of 235 <pb n="15"/>
        <lb/>yards, through the hole in the brass plate, and afterwards to <lb/>look at the edge of
        the small hole itself, which was only 6 <lb/>inches from the eye. In doing this several
        times, the curved <lb/>lines were seen to separate from each other; and the micro-
        <lb/>scope required being withdrawn from the object whenever the <lb/>person's eye was
        adjusted to the near distance; but the very <lb/>reverse took place when it was fixed on the
        distant one. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In making these experiments, the least motion of the head <lb/>carried the cornea out
        of the field of the microscope; it was <lb/>therefore necessary that the two objects should
        be exactly in <lb/>the same line respecting the eye, and that the person should <lb/>remain
        silent. When he complied with any request which <lb/>had been made, he signified by touching
        the knee of the ob- <lb/>server with his hand, that he had done so. This experiment <lb/>was
        made upon the eyes of all present, and the same appear- <lb/>ances were uniformly observed;
        and after several trials we be- <lb/>came so familiar with the appearances, that the
        observer only <lb/>required information of the adjustment having been changed, to
        <lb/>enable him to tell which of the objects the eye was fixed upon. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>August the 1st, about four o'clock, these experiments were <lb/>repeated, and after
        several attempts were made, without suc- <lb/>cess, to explain the cause of the curved
        lines, we found it neces- <lb/>sary to shade a part of the window, to take off the glare of
        <lb/>light which fatigued the eye, and rendered it unsteady; this <lb/>made the curved lines
        less distinct; and when the whole win- <lb/>dow was shaded they disappeared altogether,
        leaving a very <lb/>distinct view of the whole thickness of the cornea, with a well
        <lb/>defined line formed by its anterior projecting surface. This <lb/>discovery proved the
        curved lines to be reflections from the <lb/>sides of the window upon the cornea; but as it
        was not made <pb n="16"/>
        <lb/>till six o'clock, we were obliged to postpone any further obser- <lb/>vations upon it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>August the 3d, at seven o'clock in the morning, Mr. <hi rend="sc">Rams- <lb/>den</hi>
        and myself resumed our experiments, Sir <hi rend="sc">Henry Engle- <lb/>field</hi> being
        unable to attend at that hour. The eye of the <lb/>person under observation was shaded from
        the light by shut- <lb/>ting the half of the window-shutter directly before it, and to
        <lb/>direct the sight to pass through it, a hole was bored in the <lb/>shutter; the other
        half of the shutter was turned back, so as <lb/>to take off the side light, only letting in
        enough to illuminate <lb/>the cornea; in this state the cornea was very distinctly seen,
        <lb/>and the former experiments were repeated upon it, with a mi- <lb/>crometer wire in the
        focus of the eye-glass, so placed as ac- <lb/>curately to oppose the anterior edge of the
        cornea. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The motion of the cornea became now perfectly distinct; <lb/>its surface remained in a
        line with the wire when the eye was <lb/>adjusted to the distant object, but projected
        considerably be- <lb/>yond it when adapted to the near one; and the space through <lb/>which
        it moved was so great as readily to be measured by mag- <lb/>nifying the divisions upon a
        scale, and comparing them; in <lb/>this way we estimated it at the 800 part of an inch, a
        space <lb/>distinctly seen in a microscope magnifying 30 times. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It may not be improper, for the sake of accuracy, to mention <lb/>that the hole made in
        the window-shutter did not admit of see- <lb/>ing up Sackville-street, so that the distant
        object was now only <lb/>at 90 feet, which is rather less than is necessary for parallel
        rays; <lb/>a circumstance, so far as it can be considered, in favour of the <lb/>experiment,
        as a more distant object must have increased the ef- <lb/>fect upon the cornea. Having
        satisfied ourselves fully respect- <lb/>ing the result of this experiment, we desisted from
        further trials. </p>
      <pb n="17"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>At twelve o'clock of the same day, we prevailed on Sir <hi rend="sc">Henry
          <lb/>Englefield</hi> to make the experiment on my eye, without giv- <lb/>ing him any
        information of the observations that had been <lb/>made in the morning. He was very much
        struck with the dis- <lb/>tinctness of the cornea; and told me without difficulty the
        <lb/>different objects to which my eye was adjusted, and was as <lb/>fully satisfied as
        either Mr. <hi rend="sc">Ramsden</hi> or myself with the result <lb/>of the experiment. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="sc">Ramsden</hi> now made the same experiment on Sir <lb/><hi rend="sc"
          >Henry</hi>'s eye, but was unable to retain it in the field of the mi- <lb/>croscope; the
        motion of the cornea was always in one direc- <lb/>tion, and very irregular; after repeated
        trials, equally unsatisfac- <lb/>tory, the eye became so fatigued that he was obliged to
        desist. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>August the 4th, Mr. <hi rend="sc">Ramsden</hi> repeated the experiment on <lb/>Sir <hi
          rend="sc">Henry</hi>'s eye, to ascertain if possible the cause of his former <lb/>want of
        success, and found the same circumstances again take <lb/>place; the curve of the cornea
        moved always in the same direc- <lb/>tion, never returning to the wire. This could not be
        accounted <lb/>for, till it was accidentally discovered to arise from the motion <lb/>of his
        hand in touching the knee of the observer, for when that <lb/>was omitted, the experiment
        was followed by the same results <lb/>as those made on the rest of the company. I have been
        more <lb/>particular in mentioning this circumstance, as it shows that <lb/>the most
        trifling things may interfere with the result of the ex- <lb/>periment, and that it required
        a considerable degree of nicety <lb/>and management in adjusting the instrument, without
        which <lb/>the experiment could not have been made. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>August the 28th, the former experiments were repeated by <lb/>Sir <hi rend="sc">Henry
          Englefield</hi>, Mr. <hi rend="sc">Ramsden</hi>, and myself, upon the <lb/>eye of a young
        lad, and the result was similar to the others, the <pb n="18"/>
        <lb/>motion of the cornea was uncommonly distinct. Sir <hi rend="sc">Henry</hi>
        <lb/>now became the subject of the experiment, and changed the <lb/>adjustment of his eye
        from one distance to another in a very <lb/>irregular manner, without giving the smallest
        information, <lb/>with a view to embarrass Mr. <hi rend="sc">Ramsden</hi> who was the
        observer, <lb/>but without effect, for Mr. <hi rend="sc">Ramsden</hi> was able to tell every
        <lb/>change in distance he had made, without a single mistake; <lb/>this exceeded our
        expectation, and appeared to us so satisfac- <lb/>tory that we required no further proofs of
        the truth of our <lb/>former observations. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Before we concluded our experiments, every mode that <lb/>could be devised was put in
        practice to see how far there might <lb/>be any deception; the eye was moved upon its axis,
        and in <lb/>different directions, but these motions did not give at all simi- <lb/>lar
        appearances to those seen in the adjusting of the eye to <lb/>different distances. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From the different experiments which I have had the ho- <lb/>nour to lay before this
        learned Society, I shall consider the <lb/>following facts to have been ascertained. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>1st, That the eye has a power of adjusting itself to different <lb/>distances when
        deprived of the crystalline lens; and therefore <lb/>the fibrous and laminated structure of
        that lens is not in- <lb/>tended to alter its form, but to prevent reflections in the pas-
        <lb/>sage of the rays through the surfaces of media of different <lb/>densities, and to
        correct spherical aberration. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2d, That the cornea is made up of laminæ; that it is elas- <lb/>tic, and when
        stretched, is capable of being elongated 1/11 part <lb/>of its diameter, contracting to its
        former length immediately <lb/>upon being left to itself. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>3d, That the tendons of the four straight muscles of the eye <pb n="19"/>
        <lb/>are continued on to the edge of the cornea, and terminate, or <lb/>are inserted, in its
        external lamina; their action will therefore <lb/>extend to the edge of the cornea. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>4th, That in changing the focus of the eye from seeing with <lb/>parallel rays to a
        near distance, there is a visible alteration <lb/>produced in the figure of the cornea,
        rendering it more con- <lb/>vex; and when the eye is again adapted to parallel rays, the
        <lb/>alteration by which the cornea is brought back to its former <lb/>state is equally
        visible. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having supported these facts by the evidence of anatomical <lb/>structure, and absolute
        demonstration, I shall consider them to <lb/>be established; and make some observations upon
        the muscular <lb/>and elastic power by which so very curios an effect as the ad-
        <lb/>justment of the eye is produced. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The four straight muscles of the eye are attached to the bot- <lb/>tom of the bony
        orbit near the foramen opticum; they become <lb/>broader as they pass forward, and when
        arrived at the anterior <lb/>part of the eye-ball, are insensibly changed for tendons; these
        <lb/>adhere to the sclerotic coat, and terminate in the external <lb/>lamina of the cornea,
        which appears to be a continuation of <lb/>them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When we consider the situation of these muscles, it is evi- <lb/>dent that their action
        will produce three very different effects <lb/>upon the eye, according to circumstances.
        When they act se- <lb/>parately, they will move the eye in different directions; when
        <lb/>together, with only a small quantity of contraction, they will <lb/>steady the
        eye-ball; and when this is increased they will com- <lb/>press the lateral and posterior
        parts of the eye. This compres- <lb/>sion of the eye will force the aqueous humour forwards
        against <lb/>the centre of the cornea, while the circumference is steadied <pb n="20"/>
        <lb/>by the muscles, so that the radius of curvature of the cornea will <lb/>be rendered
        shorter, and its distance from the retina increased. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That the eye-ball cannot be made to recede in the orbit by <lb/>any of these actions,
        is sufficiently proved by its not having <lb/>done so in any of the experiments. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>These muscles are uncommonly large, and come much fur- <lb/>ther forward than appears
        necessary for the purposes generally <lb/>assigned to them; but when applied to so important
        an office <lb/>as that we have just stated, their size, and anterior insertion, <lb/>are
        easily explained. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It may be imagined that I have allotted to these muscles a <lb/>greater variety of uses
        than is compatible with the simplicity <lb/>of the general laws of the animal œconomy; but
        to prove this <lb/>not to be the case, I shall only bring the biceps flexor cubiti as
        <lb/>an instance of a similar kind. That muscle is attached to the <lb/>scapula by both its
        heads, one of which passes through the joint <lb/>of the shoulder, they afterwards unite,
        and their common ten- <lb/>don is inserted into the radius; when the muscle contracts, the
        <lb/>first effect will be to steady the joint of the shoulder; if the <lb/>contraction is
        increased, it will rotate the radius, and if still <lb/>more increased, bend the fore-arm. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There are many instances in animal bodies of elasticity be- <lb/>ing substituted for
        muscular action, but this in the eye is by <lb/>much the most beautiful of those
        applications. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the vascular system the arteries are composed of muscu- <lb/>lar fibres, and an
        elastic substance; in the natural easy state <lb/>of the circulation, the re-action in the
        larger vessels is princi- <lb/>pally the effect of elasticity, but when increased, it is the
        ef- <lb/>fect of muscular contraction. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The claws of the lion are drawn up, and supported from <pb n="21"/>
        <lb/>the ground, by means of elastic ligaments; but they are brought <lb/>down for use,
        which is an action not so often required, by <lb/>muscles. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the adjustment of the eye it is the same; the state fitted <lb/>for parallel rays is
        the effect of elasticity, but that for nearer <lb/>distances, which is less frequently
        wanted, is the effect of <lb/>muscular action. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In these different instances, the intention is uniformly to <lb/>avoid the expence of
        muscular action whenever the effect can <lb/>be produced in any other way, as muscular
        actions consume <lb/>a considerable quantity of blood, which is the nourishment of <lb/>the
        body. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That the adjusting the eye to near distances is the effect <lb/>of an action, nor
        exertion, was very evident to every gentleman <lb/>concerned in these experiments. In
        changing the focus of our <lb/>eyes, we were much astonished, particularly Sir <hi rend="sc"
          >Henry En- <lb/>glefield</hi>, at the exertion required to adjust the eye to the <lb/>near
        distances, and the facility with which it was adapted to <lb/>distant ones; the first was a
        strain upon the eye, the second <lb/>appeared a relief to it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the eye was intent upon the near object, it required <lb/>the attention to be
        constantly kept up, or the object became <lb/>indistinct; and if we looked at it beyond a
        certain time, the <lb/>eye was so much fatigued as to lose it at intervals. This cor-
        <lb/>responds with other muscular actions, for whenever muscles <lb/>are kept long in one
        state they begin to vibrate involuntarily. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>These circumstances explain what may be called a <hi rend="italic">coup
        <lb/>d'œil</hi>, or the distinctness with which an object is seen when <lb/>the eye is first
        fixed upon it. This arises from the nice ad- <lb/>justment produced by the muscles when
        first thrown into <pb n="22"/>
        <lb/>action, which they cannot keep up, being unable to remain long <lb/>in the same state;
        nor can they, after having been used for any <lb/>time, return to this adjustment with the
        same exactness. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The change that takes place in the eye at an advanced pe- <lb/>riod of life, by which
        it loses its adjustment to very near, and <lb/>very distant objects, does not arise from any
        defect in the <lb/>muscles, as might at first be imagined, since that would not <lb/>account
        for the eye being unable to see with parallel rays; <lb/>nor is there any obvious reason why
        these muscles should lose <lb/>their powers, while others, which are not apparently so
        strong, <lb/>if we may judge by their effects, retain their full action long <lb/>after the
        eye has undergone this change. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This defect in the eye I am led to believe is brought on by <lb/>the cornea losing its
        elasticity as we advance in life, neither <lb/>contracting nor being elongated to its usual
        extent, but re- <lb/>maining in a middle state. That elastic substances in the body <lb/>do
        undergo such a change may be well illustrated in the vas- <lb/>cular system. The aorta is
        composed almost entirely of elastic <lb/>substance, and there is probably no part of the
        body, at an ad- <lb/>vanced age, which is so often found to have lost its natural
        <lb/>action; it appears to undergo a change from age alone, be- <lb/>coming inelastic, and
        then taking on diseases of different kinds, <lb/>as being ossified, or becoming aneurismal;
        but in neither of <lb/>these diseases is it found to be contracted, although often the
        <lb/>reverse, and when disease has not supervened, the artery more <lb/>commonly remains in
        the middle state. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The cornea having similar properties must be liable to a <lb/>similar change, but its
        action being less constant, and the <lb/>power which it is to resist being weaker, the
        change will be <lb/>probably more gradual and less in degree, but sufficient to <pb n="23"/>
        <lb/>account for the alteration we find in the focus of the eyes of <lb/>old people. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There are many other circumstances respecting vision, and <lb/>many which occur in
        disease, that may be explained by a <lb/>knowledge of these facts; but as this lecture is
        only intended <lb/>to establish the facts themselves, in doing which I have already
        <lb/>taken up too much of the time of this learned Society, I shall <lb/>at some future
        period consider their application to the phæ- <lb/>nomena of vision in health, and disease. </p>
      <figure>
        <head rend="sc align-center space">
          <lb/>explanation of the plate. <hi rend="roman">(Tab. I.)</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Portions of the four straight muscles of the eye, with their <lb/>tendons insensibly
          lost in the external lamina of the cornea, <lb/>stretched out and dried. The tendons
          become broader as <lb/>they approach the cornea, and form a circle of which the cor-
          <lb/>nea appears to be a continuation. </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of the muscles of the eye and the cornea on a separate fold-out
          page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
