<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Heberden: Of the Influence of Cold upon the Health of the Inhabitants
          of London</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>William Heberden</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Of the Influence of Cold upon the Health of the Inhabitants of London. By William
              Heberden Jun. M. D. F. R. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Sold by Peter Elmsly, Printer to the Royal Society</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1796</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">86</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">279-284</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111044266</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1796.0013</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT86_0279">
    <body>
      <pb n="279"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XI.</hi> Of the Influence of Cold upon the Health of the Inhabitants
        of <lb/><hi rend="roman">London</hi>. By <hi rend="roman">William Heberden</hi> Jun. M. D.
        F. R. S. </head>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <dateline rend="align-center">
        <lb/>Read March 10, 1796. </dateline>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">T</hi><hi rend="sc">he</hi> extraordinary mildness of last
        January, compared with <lb/>the unusual severity of the January preceding, affords a pecu-
        <lb/>liarly favourable opportunity of observing the effect of each of <lb/>these seasons
        contrasted with each other. For of these two <lb/>successive winters, one has been the
        coldest, and the other <lb/>the warmest, of which any regular account has ever been kept
        <lb/>in this country. Nor is this by any means an idle speculation, <lb/>or matter of mere
        curiosity; for one of the first steps towards <lb/>preserving the health of our
        fellow-creatures, is to point out <lb/>the sources from which diseases are to be
        apprehended. And <lb/>what may make the present inquiry more particularly useful, <lb/>is
        that the result, as I hope clearly to make appear by the <lb/>following statements, is
        entirely contrary to the prejudices <lb/>usually entertained upon this subject. </p>
      <pb n="280"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>During last January, nothing was more common than to <lb/>hear expressions of the
        unseasonableness of the weather; and <lb/>fears lest the want of the usual degree of cold,
        should be pro- <lb/>ductive of putrid diseases, and I know not what other causes <lb/>of
        mortality. On the other hand, <q rend="quotes">a bracing cold </q> and <q rend="quotes">a
          <lb/>clear frost, </q> are familiar in the mouth of every Englishman; <lb/>and what he is
        taught to wish for, as among the greatest <lb/>promoters of health and vigour. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Whatever deference be due to received opinions, it appears to <lb/>me however from the
        strongest evidence, that the prejudices <lb/>of the world are upon this point at least
        unfounded. The <lb/>average degrees of heat upon <hi rend="sc">Fahrenheit</hi>'s thermometer
        <lb/>kept in London during the month of January 1795, was 23° in the <lb/>morning, and 29°.4
        in the afternoon. The average in January <lb/>1796, was 43°.5 in the morning, and 50°.1 in
        the afternoon. A <lb/>difference of above twenty degrees! And if we turn our atten-
        <lb/>tion from the comparative coldness of these months, to the <lb/>corresponding
        healthiness of each, collected from the weekly <lb/>bills of mortality, we shall find the
        result no less remarkable. <lb/>For in five weeks between the 31st of December 1794 and
        <lb/>the 3d of February 1795, the whole number of burials <lb/>amounted to 2823; and in an
        equal period of five weeks <lb/>between the 30th of December 1795 and the 2d of February
        <lb/>1796, to 1471. So that the excess of the mortality in January <lb/>1795 above that of
        January 1796, was less than of 1352 <lb/>persons. A number sufficient surely to awaken the
        attention <lb/>of the most prejudiced admirers of a frosty winter. And <lb/>though I have
        only stated the evidence of two years, the same <lb/>conclusion may universally be drawn; as
        I have learned from <lb/>a careful examination of the weekly bills of mortality for <pb
          n="281"/>
        <lb/>many years. These two seasons were choosen as being each of <lb/>them very remarkable,
        and in immediate succession one to the <lb/>other, and in every body's recollection. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It may not be impertinent to the objects of this Society, <lb/>without entering too
        much into the province of medicine, to <lb/>consider a little more particularly the several
        ways in which <lb/>this effect may be supposed to be produced; and to point out <lb/>some of
        the principal injuries which people are liable to sustain <lb/>in their health from a severe
        frost. And one of the first things <lb/>that must strike every mind engaged in this
        investigation, is <lb/>its effect on old people. It is curious to observe among those
        <lb/>who are said in the bills to die above 60 years of age, how re- <lb/>gularly the tide
        of mortality follows the influence of this pre- <lb/>vailing cause: so that a person used to
        such inquiries, may <lb/>form no contemptible judgment of the severity of any of our
        <lb/>winter months, merely by attending to this circumstance. <lb/>Thus their number last
        January was not much above 1/5th of <lb/>what it had been in the same month of the year
        before. The <lb/>article of asthma, as might be expected, is prodigiously in- <lb/>creased,
        and perhaps includes no inconsiderable part of the <lb/>mortality of the aged. After these
        come apoplexies and pal- <lb/>sies, fevers, consumptions, and dropsies. Under the two last
        <lb/>of which are contained a large proportion of the chronical <lb/>diseases of the
        country; all which seem to be hurried on to <lb/>a premature termination. The whole will
        most readily be <lb/>seen at one view in the following table. </p>
      <pb n="282"/>
      <table rend="boxed align-center" rows="8" cols="9">
        <head rend="align-center space">1795. </head>
        <row role="label" rend="size(0.6)">
          <cell>Week <lb/>ending </cell>
          <cell>Mean heat. </cell>
          <cell>Whole No. <lb/>of deaths. </cell>
          <cell>Aged above <lb/>60. </cell>
          <cell>Asthma. </cell>
          <cell>Apoplexy <lb/>and palsy. </cell>
          <cell>Fever. </cell>
          <cell>Consumption. </cell>
          <cell>Dropsy. </cell>
        </row>
        <row role="label" rend="size(0.6)">
          <cell/>
          <cell>Morn. Noon. </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row rend="size(0.7)">
          <cell>6 Jan. </cell>
          <cell>25° 29° </cell>
          <cell>244 </cell>
          <cell>51 </cell>
          <cell>13 </cell>
          <cell>4 </cell>
          <cell>20 </cell>
          <cell>73 </cell>
          <cell>7 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="size(0.7)">
          <cell>13 Jan. </cell>
          <cell>26° 32° </cell>
          <cell>532 </cell>
          <cell>139 </cell>
          <cell>26 </cell>
          <cell>13 </cell>
          <cell>49 </cell>
          <cell>158 </cell>
          <cell>20 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="size(0.7)">
          <cell>20 Jan. </cell>
          <cell>24° 30° </cell>
          <cell>637 </cell>
          <cell>145 </cell>
          <cell>51 </cell>
          <cell>11 </cell>
          <cell>81 </cell>
          <cell>164 </cell>
          <cell>37 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="size(0.7)">
          <cell>27 Jan. </cell>
          <cell>19° 27° </cell>
          <cell>543 </cell>
          <cell>143 </cell>
          <cell>64 </cell>
          <cell>11 </cell>
          <cell>42 </cell>
          <cell>157 </cell>
          <cell>17 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="size(0.7)">
          <cell>3 Feb. </cell>
          <cell>25° 37° </cell>
          <cell>867 </cell>
          <cell>239 </cell>
          <cell>95 </cell>
          <cell>13 </cell>
          <cell>66 </cell>
          <cell>273 </cell>
          <cell>45 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="size(0.7)">
          <cell>Result</cell>
          <cell>23° | 29°.4 </cell>
          <cell>2823 </cell>
          <cell>717 </cell>
          <cell>249 </cell>
          <cell>52 </cell>
          <cell>258 </cell>
          <cell>825 </cell>
          <cell>126 </cell>
        </row>
      </table>
      <table rend="boxed align-center" rows="8" cols="9">
        <head rend="align-center space">1796. </head>
        <row role="label" rend="size(0.6)">
          <cell>Week <lb/>ending </cell>
          <cell>Mean heat. </cell>
          <cell>Whole No. <lb/>of deaths. </cell>
          <cell>Aged above <lb/>60. </cell>
          <cell>Asthma. </cell>
          <cell>Apoplexy <lb/>and palsy. </cell>
          <cell>Fever. </cell>
          <cell>Consumption. </cell>
          <cell>Dropsy. </cell>
        </row>
        <row role="label" rend="size(0.6)">
          <cell/>
          <cell>Morn. Noon. </cell>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
          <cell/>
        </row>
        <row rend="size(0.7)">
          <cell>5 Jan. </cell>
          <cell>40° 46° </cell>
          <cell>300 </cell>
          <cell>35 </cell>
          <cell>5 </cell>
          <cell>7 </cell>
          <cell>34 </cell>
          <cell>79 </cell>
          <cell>13 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="size(0.7)">
          <cell>12 Jan. </cell>
          <cell>41° 49° </cell>
          <cell>273 </cell>
          <cell>37 </cell>
          <cell>9 </cell>
          <cell>5 </cell>
          <cell>25 </cell>
          <cell>53 </cell>
          <cell>19 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="size(0.7)">
          <cell>19 Jan. </cell>
          <cell>48° 53° </cell>
          <cell>313 </cell>
          <cell>29 </cell>
          <cell>2 </cell>
          <cell>4 </cell>
          <cell>29 </cell>
          <cell>77 </cell>
          <cell>11 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="size(0.7)">
          <cell>26 Jan. </cell>
          <cell>47° 52° </cell>
          <cell>257 </cell>
          <cell>20 </cell>
          <cell>7 </cell>
          <cell>9 </cell>
          <cell>23 </cell>
          <cell>47 </cell>
          <cell>11 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="size(0.7)">
          <cell>2 Feb. </cell>
          <cell>41° 49° </cell>
          <cell>328 </cell>
          <cell>32 </cell>
          <cell>6 </cell>
          <cell>6 </cell>
          <cell>23 </cell>
          <cell>86 </cell>
          <cell>16 </cell>
        </row>
        <row rend="size(0.7)">
          <cell>Result </cell>
          <cell>43°.5 | 50°.1 </cell>
          <cell>1471 </cell>
          <cell>153 </cell>
          <cell>29 </cell>
          <cell>31 </cell>
          <cell>134 </cell>
          <cell>342 </cell>
          <cell>70 </cell>
        </row>
      </table>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Notwithstanding the plague, the remittent fever, the dysen- <lb/>tery, and the scurvy,
        have so decreased, that their very name <lb/>is almost unknown in London; yet there has, I
        know not <lb/>how, arisen a prejudice concerning putrid diseases, which seems <lb/>to have
        made people more and more apprehensive of them, as <lb/>the danger has been growing less. It
        must in great measure <lb/>be attributed to this, that the consumption of Peruvian bark <pb
          n="283"/>
        <lb/>in this country has, within the last fifty years, increased from <lb/>14,000 to above
        100,000 pounds annually. And the same <lb/>cause has probably contributed, from a mistaken
        mode of rea- <lb/>soning, to prepossess people with the idea of the wholesome- <lb/>ness of
        a hard frost. But it has in another place <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Observations on the Jail Fever, by Dr. <hi rend="sc">Hunter</hi>, Med. Trans.
            Vol. III. </p>
        </note> been very <lb/>ably demonstrated that a long frost is eventually productive <lb/>of
        the worst putrid fevers that are at this time known in Lon- <lb/>don; and that heat does in
        fact prove a real preventive against <lb/>that disease. And although this may be said to be
        a very re- <lb/>mote effect of the cold, it is not therefore the less real in its
        <lb/>influence upon the mortality of London. Accordingly a com- <lb/>parison of the numbers
        in the foregoing table will shew that <lb/>very nearly twice as many persons died of fevers
        in January <lb/>1795, as did in the corresponding month of this year. I might <lb/>go on to
        observe that the true scurvy was last year generated <lb/>in the metropolis from the same
        causes extended to an unusual <lb/>length. But these are by no means the only ways, nor
        indeed <lb/>do they seem to be the principal ways, in which a frost ope- <lb/>rates to the
        destruction of great numbers of people. The <lb/>poor, as they are worse protected from the
        weather, so are <lb/>they of course the greatest sufferers by its inclemency. But <lb/>every
        physician in London, and every apothecary, can add <lb/>his testimony, that their business
        among all ranks of people <lb/>never fails to increase, and to decrease, with the frost. For
        <lb/>if there be any whose lungs are tender, any whose constitu- <lb/>tion has been impaired
        either by age, or by intemperance, or <lb/>by disease; he will be very liable to have all
        his complaints <lb/>increased, and all his infirmities aggravated by such a season. <lb/>Nor
        must the young and active think themselves quite secure, <pb n="284"/>
        <lb/>or fancy their health will be confirmed by imprudently ex- <lb/>posing themselves. The
        stoutest man may meet with impe- <lb/>diments to his recovery from accidents otherwise
        inconsider- <lb/>able; or may contract inflammations, or coughs, and lay the <lb/>foundation
        of the severest ills. In a country where the pre- <lb/>vailing complaints among all orders
        of people are colds, coughs, <lb/>consumptions, and rheumatisms, no prudent man can surely
        <lb/>suppose that unnecessary exposure to an inclement sky; that <lb/>priding oneself upon
        going without any additional clothing <lb/>in the severest winter; that inuring oneself to
        be hardy, at a <lb/>time that demands our cherishing the firmest constitution lest <lb/>it
        suffer; that braving the winds, and challenging the rudest <lb/>efforts of the season, can
        ever be generally useful to English- <lb/>men. But if generally, and upon the whole, it be
        inexpedient, <lb/>then ought every one for himself to take care that he be not <lb/>the
        sufferer. For many doctrines very importantly erroneous; <lb/>many remedies either vain, or
        even noxious, are daily imposed <lb/>upon the world for want of attention to this great
        truth; that <lb/>it is from general effects only, and those founded upon exten- <lb/>sive
        experience, that any maxim to which each individual may <lb/>with confidence defer, can
        possibly be established. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
