<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Wells: Observations and Experiments on the Colour of Blood</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>William Charles Wells</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Observations and Experiments on the Colour of Blood. By William Charles Wells, M. D. F. R. S.
            </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Sold by Peter Elmsly, Printer to the Royal Society</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1797</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">87</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">416-431</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111044859</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1797.0021</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT87_0416">
    <body>
      <pb n="416"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XIX.</hi> Observations and Experiments on the Colour of Blood. <lb/>By
          <hi rend="roman">William Charles Wells</hi>, M. D. F. R. S. </head>
      <dateline rend="align-center space">
        <lb/>Read July 6, 1797. </dateline>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">D</hi><hi rend="sc">r. Priestley</hi> is, I believe, the only
        person who has hi- <lb/>therto attempted to shew by what means common air brightens <lb/>the
        colour of blood, which has been for some time exposed to <lb/>it. <note n="*" place="bottom"
          rend="size(0.6)">
          <p rend="align-center">* Phil. Trans. for 1776. </p>
        </note> His opinion is, that the air produces this effect by de- <lb/>priving the blood of
        its phlogiston; for blood, according to the <lb/>same author, is wonderfully fitted both to
        imbibe and to part <lb/>with phlogiston, becoming black when charged with that
        <lb/>principle, but highly florid when freed from it. Various ar- <lb/>guments may be
        brought to prove that this opinion is erro- <lb/>neous, even upon the admission of such a
        principle of bodies <lb/>as phlogiston. It may be said, for instance, that it is contrary
        <lb/>to the laws of chemical affinity, that the same mass should, at <lb/>one time, convert
        pure into phlogisticated air, by giving out <lb/>its phlogiston, and immediately after
        reconvert phlogisticated <lb/>into pure air, by imbibing that principle; both which changes
        <lb/>are supposed by Dr. <hi rend="sc">Priestley</hi> to be induced by blood upon <lb/>those
        airs. Again; it may be urged, that, since the neutral <lb/>salts, and the different alkalis,
        when saturated with fixed air, <lb/>produce the same effect as common air upon the colour of
        <lb/>blood, if common air acts by attracting phlogiston, those other <lb/>bodies must have a
        similar operation. But surely it cannot be <pb n="417"/>
        <lb/>thought, that the mild volatile alkali, which has been supposed <lb/>by chemists to
        superabound with phlogiston, can yet attract it <lb/>from blood. It appears to me, however,
        unnecessary to bring <lb/>any further arguments of this kind against the opinion of Dr.
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Priestley</hi>, since the following experiments will, I expect, be
        <lb/>thought sufficient to shew, in opposition to what is taken for <lb/>granted by him in
        the whole of his inquiry, that the alteration <lb/>induced upon the colour of blood, both by
        common air and the <lb/>neutral salts, is altogether independent of any change effected
        <lb/>by them upon its colouring matter. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I infused a piece of black crassamentum of blood in dis- <lb/>tilled water, and
        immediately after covered the containing <lb/>vessel closely, to prevent the access of air.
        Having obtained <lb/>by this means a transparent solution of the red matter of blood,
        <lb/>nearly free from serum and coagulable lymph, I exposed a <lb/>quantity of it to the
        open air, in a shallow vessel, and poured <lb/>an equal quantity into a small phial, which
        was then well <lb/>closed. When the first portion of the solution had been ex- <lb/>posed to
        the air for several hours, I decanted it into a phial, of <lb/>the same size and shape as
        that which contained the second <lb/>portion, and having added to it as much distilled water
        as was <lb/>sufficient to compensate the loss it had suffered by evapo- <lb/>ration, I now
        compared the two together, with regard both to kind and <lb/>degree. I afterwards poured two
        other equal quantities of the <lb/>red solution into two phials of the same size and shape.
        To <lb/>one I added a little of a solution of nitre in water, and to the <lb/>other as much
        distilled water. Upon comparing the two mix- <lb/>tures together, I found that they also
        possessed precisely the <lb/>same colour. Lastly, I cut a quantity of dark crassamentum <pb
          n="418"/>
        <lb/>of blood into thin slices, and exposed them to common air. <lb/>When they became
        florid, I put them into a phial containing <lb/>distilled water. I then took as much of the
        same crassamen- <lb/>tum, which was still black, and infused it in an equal quantity <lb/>of
        distilled water, contained in a phial similar in size and shape <lb/>to the former. The two
        solutions which were thus obtained, <lb/>one from florid blood, the other from black blood,
        were, not- <lb/>withstanding, of precisely the same colour. These experiments <lb/>were
        frequently repeated, and were attended with the same <lb/>results, as often as I used
        certain precautions, which shall be <lb/>mentioned hereafter, as the reasons for them will
        then be more <lb/>readily understood than they can be at present. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Assuming therefore as proved, that neither common air, nor <lb/>the neutral salts (for
        all those I have tried are similar to nitre <lb/>in this respect) change the colour of the
        red matter of blood; <lb/>I shall now attempt to explain the manner in which those sub-
        <lb/>stances give, notwithstanding, to black blood a florid appear- <lb/>ance; premising,
        however, some observations upon the colours <lb/>of bodies in general. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It was the opinion of <hi rend="sc">Kepler</hi>, <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)"
          n="*">
          <p rend="align-center">
            <lb/>* <hi rend="italic">Paralipomena in <hi rend="sc">Vitellionem</hi></hi>, p. 23 et
            436. </p>
        </note> that light is reflected with- <lb/>out colour from the surfaces of bodies; which he
        says is easily <lb/>proved, by exposing to the sun's light a number of cups filled <lb/>with
        transparent liquors of different colours, and receiving the <lb/>reflexions from them upon a
        white ground in a dark place. <lb/><hi rend="sc">Zucchius</hi>, who was younger than <hi
          rend="sc">Kepler</hi>, but for some time his <lb/>cotemporary, taught more explicitly,
          <note n="†" place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)">
          <p rend="align-center">
            <lb/>† <hi rend="italic">Optica Philosophia, Pars <hi rend="roman">I. p. 278</hi> et
              seq.</hi>
          </p>
        </note> that the colours of bodies <lb/>depend, not upon the light which is reflected from
        their anterior <lb/>surfaces, but upon that portion of it which is received into their <pb
          n="419"/>
        <lb/>internal parts, and is thence sent back through those sur- <lb/>faces. The following
        are some of the experiments, upon which <lb/>he founded this doctrine. He exposed small
        round pieces of <lb/>transparent glass, tinged with various colours, to the light of
        <lb/>the sun, and received what was reflected from them upon white <lb/>paper, in a darkened
        part of his room. He then found, that <lb/>each glass produced two luminous circles, which,
        when the <lb/>paper was sufficiently remote, were entirely separate from each <lb/>other;
        and that the circle which proceeded from the upper <lb/>surface of the glass was altogether
        without colour, while that <lb/>which arose from the under surface, was of the same colour
        as <lb/>the glass exhibited, when held between the light and the eye. <lb/>From these
        experiments <hi rend="sc">Zucchius</hi> also concluded, first, that <lb/>every coloured body
        must be in some degree transparent, since <lb/>a body absolutely impenetrable to light,
        could only reflect the <lb/>colours of other bodies, but possess none of its own; and, se-
        <lb/>condly, that all bodies, which appear coloured when seen by <lb/>reflected light, must
        be in some measure opake; for as the <lb/>light which is reflected from their surfaces comes
        untinged to <lb/>the eye, if that part of it which penetrates their substance <lb/>were
        afterwards to proceed in it without impediment, no co- <lb/>lour could be exhibited by them.
          <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* The works of <hi rend="sc">Zucchius</hi> seem very little known, though they
            contain a consi- <lb/>derable number of original experiments, and though it is probable
            that he was the <lb/>inventor of the reflecting telescope. For he says (Pars 1. p. 126.)
            it had occurred to <lb/>him so early as 1616, that the same effect which is produced by
            the convex object- <lb/>glass of a telescope, might be obtained by reflexion from a
            concave mirror; and that, <lb/>after many attempts to construct telescopes with such
            mirrors, which proved fruitless <lb/>from imperfections in their figure, he at length
            procured a concave mirror very accu- <lb/>rately wrought, by means of which, and a <hi
              rend="italic">concave</hi> eye-glass, he was enabled to prove <lb/>his theory to be
            just. He does not mention at what precise time he constructed this <pb n="420"
              type="footnote"/>
            <lb/>telescope; but his book was printed in 1652, eleven years before the publication of
            the <lb/>
            <q rend="quotes"><hi rend="italic">Optica Promota</hi>
            </q> of <hi rend="sc">James Gregory</hi>. I have not met with any account of <hi
              rend="sc">Zuc- <lb/>chius</hi>, in <hi rend="sc">Montucla</hi>'s or <hi rend="sc"
              >Priestley</hi>'s histories; in the article <q rend="quotes">telescope, </q> in
            <lb/>the French Encyclopedia; or in any biographical dictionary which I have consulted.
          </p>
        </note>
      </p>
      <pb n="420"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When Sir <hi rend="sc">Isaac Newton</hi> began his experiments upon light <lb/>and
        colours, it was generally believed, that colours in opake <lb/>bodies arise from some
        modification given to light, by the <lb/>surfaces which reflect it. In opposition to one
        part of this <lb/>opinion, our great philosopher maintained, that such bodies are <lb/>seen
        coloured, from their acting differently upon the different <lb/>colorific rays, of which
        white light is composed; but having <lb/>established this point beyond dispute, he seems to
        have ad- <lb/>mitted, without inquiry, that colours are produced at the sur- <lb/>faces of
        the opake bodies to which they belong. For his expe- <lb/>riments do not necessarily lead to
        such a conclusion; on the <lb/>contrary, they are not more consistent with it, than they are
        <lb/>with the opinion of <hi rend="sc">Kepler</hi> and <hi rend="sc">Zucchius</hi>. This
        opinion, <lb/>indeed, he appears not to have known; since he has taken for <lb/>granted,
        what is contradicted by the experiments upon which <lb/>it is founded, that the tinging
        particles of transparent bodies <lb/>reflect coloured light. <note n="*" place="bottom"
          rend="size(0.6)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Optics, Book i. Part II. Prop. 10. </p>
        </note>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The very splendour of Sir <hi rend="sc">Isaac Newton</hi>'s discoveries in <lb/>optics,
        has probably done some injury to this branch of know- <lb/>ledge; for soon after they were
        made public, it became a <lb/>common opinion, that the subject of light and colours had
        <lb/>been exhausted by that great man, and that no writer upon it <lb/>before him, was now
        worthy of being read. The former part <lb/>of this opinion has long been generally
        acknowledged to be <lb/>unjust; but the latter part of it is still maintained by many, <pb
          n="421"/>
        <lb/>among whom may be placed the learned Mr. <hi rend="sc">Delaval</hi>. This
        <lb/>gentleman has lately published <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)">
          <p rend="align-center">
            <lb/>* Manchester Memoirs, Vol. II. </p>
        </note> a very elaborate treatise to <lb/>prove, that the colours of opake bodies do not
        arise from the <lb/>rays of light which they reflect from their anterior surfaces; <lb/>but
        from that portion of it, which, having penetrated their an- <lb/>terior surfaces, is
        reflected by the opake particles which are <lb/>diffused through their substance. But had
        the learned author <lb/>not believed, that no European writer upon colours, before Sir
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Isaac Newton</hi>, contained any valuable information upon that
        <lb/>subject, he would probably have discovered, that both <hi rend="sc">Kepler</hi>
        <lb/>and <hi rend="sc">Zucchius</hi> had long ago maintained the very opinion which <lb/>he
        now advances, and that they had built it upon experiments <lb/>similar to his own. The merit
        of the invention of this theory <lb/>belongs, therefore, to the great <hi rend="sc"
          >Kepler</hi>; but still much praise <lb/>is due to Mr. <hi rend="sc">Delaval</hi>, both
        for reviving and confirming it; <lb/>since, though it be not free from defects in some of
        its parts, it <lb/>affords solutions of several optical difficulties, which, as far as I
        <lb/>know, admit of an explanation from no other source. Among <lb/>these I regard the
        phænomenon which is the subject of the <lb/>present inquiry. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To shew then, from the theory of <hi rend="sc">Kepler</hi>, <hi rend="sc"
        >Zucchius</hi>, and <lb/><hi rend="sc">Delaval</hi>, how common air and the neutral salts
        may brighten <lb/>the appearance of blood, without producing any change upon <lb/>its
        colouring matter, I shall first suppose that all its parts have <lb/>the same reflective
        power. The consequence will be, that a <lb/>mass sufficiently thick to suffocate the whole
        of the light which <lb/>enters it, before it can proceed to the posterior surface, and be
        <lb/>thence returned through the first surface, must appear black; <pb n="422"/>
        <lb/>for the rays which are reflected from the first surface are without <lb/>colour, and,
        by hypothesis, none can be reflected from its inter- <lb/>nal parts. In the next place, let
        there be dispersed through this <lb/>black mass a small number of particles, differing from
        it in re- <lb/>flective power, and it will immediately appear slightly coloured; <lb/>for
        some of the rays, which have penetrated its surface, will <lb/>be reflected by those
        particles, and will come to the eye ob- <lb/>scurely tinged with the colour, which is
        exhibited by a thin <lb/>layer of blood, when placed between us and the light. Increase
        <lb/>now by degrees the number of those particles, and in the same <lb/>proportion as they
        are multiplied, must the colour of the mass <lb/>become both stronger and brighter. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having thus shewn that a black mass may become highly <lb/>coloured, merely by a
        considerable reflexion of light from its <lb/>internal parts; if I should now be able to
        prove, that both <lb/>common air and the neutral salts increase the reflexion of light
        <lb/>from the internal parts of blood, at the same time that they <lb/>brighten it, great
        progress would certainly be made in esta- <lb/>blishing the opinion, that the change of its
        appearance, which <lb/>is occasioned by them, depends upon that circumstance alone. <lb/>But
        the following observations seem to place this point beyond <lb/>doubt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I compared several pieces of crassamentum of blood, which <lb/>had been reddened by
        means of common air and the neutral <lb/>salts, with other pieces of the same crassamentum,
        which were <lb/>still black, or nearly so; upon which I found, that the red- <lb/>dened
        pieces manifestly reflected more light than the black. <lb/>One proof of this was, that the
        minute parts of the former <lb/>could be much more distinctly seen than those of the latter.
        <lb/>Now this increased reflection of light, in the reddened pieces, <pb n="423"/>
        <lb/>could not arise from any change in the reflective power of <lb/>their surfaces; for
        bodies reflect light from their surfaces in <lb/>proportion to their density and
        inflammability; and neither of <lb/>those qualities, in the reddened pieces of crassamentum,
        can <lb/>be supposed to have been augmented by common air, or a <lb/>solution of a neutral
        salt in water. The increased reflection <lb/>must, consequently, have arisen from some
        change in their <lb/>internal parts, by means of which much of the light which had
        <lb/>formerly been suffocated, was now sent back through their <lb/>anterior surfaces,
        tinged with the colour of the medium through <lb/>which it had passed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The precise nature of the change which is induced upon <lb/>blood by the neutral salts,
        is made manifest by the following <lb/>experiment. I poured upon a piece of printed card as
        much <lb/>serum, rendered very turbid with red globules, as barely al- <lb/>lowed the words
        to be legible through it. I next dropped upon <lb/>the card a little of a solution of nitre
        in water; when I obser- <lb/>ved, that, wherever the solution came in contact with the
        <lb/>turbid serum, a whitish cloud was immediately formed. The <lb/>two fluids were then
        stirred together; upon which the mixture <lb/>became so opake, that the printed letters upon
        the card could <lb/>no longer be seen. I have not hitherto been able to devise any
        <lb/>experiment, which shews the exact change induced by common <lb/>air; but it is evident
        that air must also, in some way, increase <lb/>the opacity of' blood, since it can, by no
        other means, increase <lb/>the reflection of light from the interior parts of that body. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This theory explains another fact respecting the colour of <lb/>blood, which might
        otherwise seem unaccountable. If a small <lb/>quantity of a concentrated mineral acid be
        applied to a piece of <lb/>dark crassamentum, the parts touched by it will for an instant
          <pb n="424"/>
        <lb/>appear florid; but the same acids, added to a solution of the red <lb/>matter in water,
        do nothing more than destroy its colour. <lb/>Upon examining the crassamentum, a reason for
        this difference <lb/>of effect is discovered; for the spots, upon which the acid was
        <lb/>dropped, are found covered with whitish films. From which it <lb/>seems evident, that
        the acid had occasioned an increase of opa- <lb/>city in the crassamentum, more quickly than
        it had destroyed <lb/>its colour; and that the red matter, from having been in con-
        <lb/>sequence seen by a greater quantity of light, had in that short <lb/>interval appeared
        more florid than formerly. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The change which, I think, I have proved to take place in <lb/>blood, when its colour
        is brightened by common air and the <lb/>neutral salts, is similar to that which occurs to
        cinnabar, in the <lb/>making of vermilion. This pigment, it is known, is formed <lb/>from
        cinnabar, merely by subjecting it to a minute mechanical <lb/>division. But the effect of
        this division is, to interpose among <lb/>its particles, an infinite number of molecules of
        air, which, now <lb/>acting as opake matter, increase the reflection of light from <lb/>the
        interior parts of the heap, and by this means occasion the <lb/>whole difference of
        appearance which is observed between those <lb/>two states of the same chemical body. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I expect, however, it will be said, in opposition to what I have <lb/>advanced, that,
        granting an increased reflection of light takes <lb/>place from the interior parts of blood,
        in consequence of the ap- <lb/>plication of common air and the neutral salts, still this is
        not a <lb/>sufficient cause for the production of the colour which they occa- <lb/>sion; for
        the colour of blood, after those substances have acted <lb/>upon it, is a scarlet, which,
        agreeably to the observation of a <lb/>learned and ingenious Fellow of this Society, Dr. <hi
          rend="sc">G. Fordyce</hi>, <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.6)">
          <p rend="align-center">
            <lb/>* Elements of the Practice of Physic, p. 13. </p>
        </note>
        <pb n="425"/>
        <lb/>differs not only in brightness, but also in kind, from the ordi- <lb/>nary colour of
        that fluid, which is a Modena red. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>My answer is, that there are examples, beside that to which <lb/>the objection is made,
        of dark blood appearing florid, merely <lb/>from its colouring matter being seen by means of
        an increased <lb/>quantity of light. One is afforded by rubbing a piece of the <lb/>darkest
        crassamentum with a proper quantity of serum; for a <lb/>mixture is thus formed, in a few
        seconds, possessing a colour <lb/>similar to that which is given to crassamentum by common
        air. <lb/>But here we certainly do nothing more, than interpose among <lb/>the red globules
        a number of the less dense particles of serum; <lb/>which, in their present situation, act
        as opake matter, and con- <lb/>sequently, increase the internal reflections. A second
        example <lb/>occurs, when we view, by transmitted light, the fine edges and <lb/>angles of a
        piece of crassamentum in water; for, in this si- <lb/>tuation, their colour appears to be a
        bright scarlet, though all <lb/>the other parts of the same mass are black. These facts seem
        <lb/>sufficient to prove, that the immediate cause I have assigned <lb/>for the production
        of the florid appearance in blood, which has <lb/>been exposed to the action of common air
        and neutral salts, is <lb/>adequate to the effect; but I shall advance a step further, and
        <lb/>shew how the Modena red is converted in to a scarlet. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Blood, as I have found by experiment, is one of those fluids <lb/>which Sir <hi
          rend="sc">Isaac Newton</hi> has observed appear yellow, <note place="bottom"
          rend="size(0.6)" n="*">
          <p rend="align-center">
            <lb/><choice>
              <corr>* </corr>
              <sic/>
            </choice>Book i. Part II. Prop. 10. </p>
        </note> if <lb/>viewed in very thin masses. When, therefore, a number of <lb/>opake
        particles are formed in it, by the action of common air <lb/>and the neutral salts, many of
        them must be situated imme- <lb/>diately beneath the surface. The light reflected by these
        will <lb/>consequently be yellow; and the whole effect of the newly- <pb n="426"/>
        <lb/>formed opake particles, upon the appearance of the mass, will <lb/>be the same, as if
        yellow had been added to its former colour, <lb/>a Modena red. But Modena red and yellow are
        the colours <lb/>which compose scarlet. <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)" n="*">
          <p rend="align-center">
            <lb/>* <hi rend="sc">Fordyce</hi>'s Elements of the Practice of Physic, p. 14. </p>
        </note>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I shall now relate the cautions to be observed in making the <lb/>experiments, which
        are described in the beginning of this <lb/>paper. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The first is, that the blood should be newly drawn, and the <lb/>weather cool. For as
        the solution of the red matter is not to <lb/>be filtred, but must become transparent by the
        gradual sub- <lb/>siding of whatever may render it turbid, if the blood be old, or <lb/>the
        weather warm, it will often assume, before it be clear, a <lb/>dark and purplish hue. When
        exposed in this state to the <lb/>atmosphere in a broad and shallow vessel, its colour
        changes <lb/>to a bright red, which, however, is not brighter than the pro- <lb/>per colour
        of the solution. The dark purplish hue seems owing <lb/>to some modification of sulphur; for
        the solution possessing it <lb/>smells like hepatic air, particularly when agitated, and
        tarnishes <lb/>silver which is held over it. Neutral salts produce no change <lb/>upon this
        colour. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The second caution is, that the neutral salts be not added <lb/>to the red solution,
        except when perfectly transparent; for if it <lb/>be not so, the salts will render it more
        turbid, and the mixture <lb/>will appear brighter, if seen by reflected light. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The last I shall note is, that the red solution ought to be <lb/>poured gently from the
        vessel in which it has been made. If <lb/>it be not, as it is a mucilaginous liquor, it is
        apt to entangle <lb/>small particles of air, which by acting as opake matter, will for
        <lb/>some time alter the appearance of the solution. </p>
      <pb n="427"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I proceed next to offer a few observations upon the cause of <lb/>the red colour of
        blood. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It has of late been very generally supposed, that blood derives <lb/>its colour from
        iron. As far as I know, however, no other argu- <lb/>ment has been given in support of this
        opinion, than that the <lb/>red matter is found to contain that metal. But there is
        certainly <lb/>no necessary connection between redness and iron; since this <lb/>metal
        exists in many bodies of other colours, and even in va- <lb/>rious parts of animals without
        colour, as bones and wool. <lb/>More direct reasons, however, may be given for rejecting
        this <lb/>opinion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>1. I know of no colour, arising from a metal, which can be <lb/>permanently destroyed
        by exposing its subject, in a close vessel, <lb/>to a heat less than that of boiling water.
        But this happens <lb/>with respect to the colour of blood. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2. If the colour from a metal, in any substance, be destroyed <lb/>by an alkali, it may
        be restored by the immediate addition of <lb/>an acid; and the like will happen from the
        addition of a proper <lb/>quantity of alkali, if the colour has been destroyed by an acid.
        <lb/>The colour of blood, on the contrary, when once destroyed, <lb/>either by an acid or an
        alkali, can never be brought back. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>3. If iron be the cause of the red colour of blood, it must <lb/>exist there in a
        saline state, since the red matter is soluble in <lb/>water. The substances, therefore,
        which detect almost the <lb/>smallest quantity of iron in such a state, ought likewise to
        <lb/>demonstrate its presence in blood; but upon adding Prussian <lb/>alkali, and an
        infusion of galls, to a very saturate solution of <lb/>the red matter, I could not observe,
        in the former case, the <lb/>slightest blue precipitate, or in the latter, that the mixture
        had <lb/>acquired the least blue, or purple tint. </p>
      <pb n="428"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon the whole it appears to me, that blood derives its <lb/>colour from the peculiar
        organization of the animal matter of <lb/>one of its parts; for whenever this is destroyed,
        the colour dis- <lb/>appears, and can never be made to return; which would not, <lb/>I
        think, be the case, if it depended upon the presence of any <lb/>foreign substance
        whatsoever. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I shall conclude this paper with relating several miscellaneous <lb/>facts respecting
        the colour of blood, and some conclusions <lb/>which may be formed from them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="sc">Priestley</hi> has mentioned, <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)"
          n="*">
          <p rend="align-center">
            <lb/>* Phil. Trans. for 1776, p. 246. </p>
        </note> that the only animal fluid, <lb/>beside serum, which he found to transmit the
        influence of <lb/>common air to blood, was milk. But I have observed, that the <lb/>white of
        an egg possesses the same property, notwithstanding <lb/>its great tenacity. Now as serum
        contains an animal substance <lb/>very similar to the white of eggs, it occurred to me as a
        ques- <lb/>tion, whether, in transmitting the influence of air to blood, it <lb/>acts by its
        salts only, or partly by means of the substance of <lb/>which I have just spoken. I took
        therefore a quantity of urine, <lb/>which is known to contain nearly the same salts as
        serum, and <lb/>having added to it as much distilled water as rendered its taste <lb/>of the
        same pungency as that of serum, I poured the mixture <lb/>upon a piece of dark crassamentum
        of blood. I then put to <lb/>another piece of the same crassamentum an equal quantity of
        <lb/>serum, and exposed both parcels to the atmosphere. The <lb/>result was, that the blood
        in the diluted urine did not become <lb/>nearly so florid as that in the serum. I have found
        also, that a <lb/>solution of sugar in water conveys the influence of air to blood;
        <lb/>from which it seems probable, that milk owes its similar pro- <lb/>perty to the
        saccharine matter which it contains. Black blood <pb n="429"/>
        <lb/>exposed to the atmosphere under mucilage of gum arabic, does <lb/>not become florid. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It has been said, <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)" n="*">
          <p rend="align-center">
            <lb/>* <hi rend="sc">Fordyce</hi>'s Elements of the Practice of Physic, p. 14. </p>
        </note> that neither serum, nor solutions of the <lb/>neutral salts, dissolve the red matter
        of blood. But this in- <lb/>duction has been made from too small a number of experi-
        <lb/>ments. For saturate solutions of all the neutral salts, which <lb/>I have tried, will
        extract, though slowly, red tinctures from <lb/>blood, some of which are very deep; and
        neither they, nor <lb/>serum, added in any proportion to a solution of the red matter
        <lb/>in water, alter its colour or transparency, except by diluting <lb/>it. The following
        experiments, however, will place this point <lb/>in a clearer light. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I added a drachm of distilled water to an ounce of serum, <lb/>and poured the mixture
        upon a small piece of crassamentum. <lb/>Upon an equal piece of crassamentum I poured a
        drachm of <lb/>water, and after some time added an ounce of serum. Each <lb/>parcel,
        therefore, contained the same quantity of crassamen- <lb/>tum, serum, and water; but the
        crassamentum upon which the <lb/>mixture of serum and water had been poured, communicated
        <lb/>no tinge to it; while the other piece, to which water had been <lb/>first applied, and
        afterwards serum, gave a deep colour to the <lb/>fluid above it. I made similar experiments
        with crassamentum, <lb/>water, and a dilute solution of a neutral salt, which were at-
        <lb/>tended with the same results. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Since then neither serum, nor a dilute solution of a neutral <lb/>salt, will extract
        colour from blood, though they are both ca- <lb/>pable of dissolving the red matter, when
        separated by water <lb/>from the other parts of the mass, it follows, in my opinion,
        <lb/>that what are called the red globules consist of two parts, one <pb n="430"/>
        <lb/>within the other, and that the outer, being insoluble in serum <lb/>or dilute solutions
        of neutral salts, defends the inner from the <lb/>action of those fluids. It is remarkable,
        that microscopical ob- <lb/>servations led Mr. <hi rend="sc">Hewson</hi> to the same
        conclusion, namely, <lb/>that the red globules consist of two parts, <note place="bottom"
          rend="size(0.6)" n="*">
          <p rend="align-center">
            <lb/>* <hi rend="sc">Hewson</hi>'s Works, Vol. III. p. 17. </p>
        </note> which, according <lb/>to him, are an exterior vesicle, and an interior solid sphere.
        <lb/>But the same writer, upon the authority of other microscopic <lb/>experiments, asserts
        that the vesicles are red. If they be so, <lb/>there must exist two red matters in the
        blood, possessing dif- <lb/>ferent chemical properties; which is certainly far from being
        <lb/>probable. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The exterior part of the globule appears to be that ingre- <lb/>dient of the blood upon
        which common air and the neutral salts <lb/>produce their immediate effect, when they render
        the whole <lb/>mass florid; for I have shewn they do not act upon the red <lb/>matter
        itself, and I have not found that they occasion any <lb/>change in coagulated lymph or
        serum. The only matter then <lb/>which remains to be operated upon, is that which I have
        men- <lb/>tioned. It seems evident also, from what has been just stated, <lb/>that there
        exists an animal matter in the blood, different from <lb/>the coagulable lymph, the
        coagulable part of the serum, the <lb/>putrescent mucilage, and the red particles, which, I
        believe, <lb/>are all the kinds it has hitherto been supposed to contain. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The microscopical observations of Mr. <hi rend="sc">Hewson</hi> appear like- <lb/>wise
        to furnish a reason, why both water, and a saturate solution <lb/>of a neutral salt, can
        extract colour from the red globules, <lb/>though a mixture of those fluids be incapable of
        the same <lb/>effect. For water applied to the red globules, separates the <lb/>exterior
        vesicles from the red particles, which are therefore now <pb n="431"/>
        <lb/>open to the action of any solvent. <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* <hi rend="sc">Hewson</hi>'s Works, Vol. III. p. 17. </p>
        </note> The addition, however, <lb/>of a small quantity of a neutral salt to the water
        enables the <lb/>vesicles to preserve their shape, and to retain the inner sphe- <lb/>rules.
          <note n="†" place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)">† Ibid. p. 40. </note> Upon the addition of a
        greater quantity of salt, the <lb/>vesicles contract, and apply themselves closely to the
        red par- <lb/>ticles within. <note n="‡" place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)">‡ Ibid. p. 31.
        </note> Thus far Mr. <hi rend="sc">Hewson</hi>'s observations extend. <lb/>Let it now be
        supposed that the vesicles contract still more, <lb/>from a further addition of salt to the
        water; the consequence <lb/>must be, that, as the internal particles are incompressible, the
        <lb/>sides of the vesicles will be rent, and their contents exposed to <lb/>the action of
        the surrounding fluid. Both water and a strong <lb/>solution of a neutral salt may,
        therefore, destroy the orga- <lb/>nization of the vesicles, though in different ways, and
        thus <lb/>agree in bringing the red matter in contact with a solvent; <lb/>while a mixture
        of those two fluids, namely, a dilute solution of <lb/>a neutral salt, will, by hardening
        the vesicles, increase the de- <lb/>fence of the red matter against the action of such
        substances <lb/>as are capable of dissolving it. But all reasoning founded upon
        <lb/>experiments with microscopes, ought perhaps to be regarded <lb/>as, in great measure,
        conjectural. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
