<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Home: The Croonian Lecture</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Everard Home</persName>
            </author>
            <title>The Croonian Lecture. On the Structure and Uses of the Membrana Tympani of the
              Ear. By Everard Home, Esq. F. R. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Philosophical Transactions. Giving Some Account of the Present Undertakings,
              Studies and Labours, of the Ingenious, in many Considerable Parts of the
              World.</title>
            <author>Royal Society</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed by W. Bulmer and Co. Cleveland-Row, St. James's; and sold
                  by Peter Elmsly, Printer to the Royal Society</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1800</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">90</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">1-21</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW111045480</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1098/rstl.1800.0001</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="PT90_0001">
    <body>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">I.</hi> The Croonian Lecture. On the Structure and Uses of the Mem-
        <lb/>brana Tympani of the Ear. By <hi rend="roman">Everard Home</hi>, Esq. F. R. S. </head>
      <dateline rend="align-center space">
        <lb/>Read November 7, 1799. </dateline>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">T</hi><hi rend="sc">he</hi> subject of inquiry appointed by the
        Croonian Institution, <lb/>has been greatly elucidated at different times by ingenious mem-
        <lb/>bers of this learned Society. A large field, however, still re- <lb/>mains open; and,
        respecting future investigations, I shall have <lb/>occasion to offer a fresh proof of the
        aid to be derived from <lb/>comparative anatomy, in ascertaining the structure of parts
        <lb/>which, from their minuteness and situation in the human body, <lb/>admit with much
        difficulty of being explored. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The principal object of the present lecture is to communicate <lb/>a discovery of the
        structure of the membrana tympani; which, <lb/>in some respects, affords a new and very
        curious instance of <lb/>the application of muscular action, and may conduce to account
        <lb/>for certain phænomena in the sense of hearing, in a more satis- <lb/>factory manner
        than has hitherto been proposed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The membrana tympani has always been considered as a <pb n="2"/>
        <lb/>common membrane, which, by means of muscles belonging to <lb/>the malleus being
        stretched or relaxed, became fitted, in its <lb/>various degrees of tension, to convey the
        vast variety of ex- <lb/>ternal sounds to the internal organ. Its shape, situation, and
        <lb/>office, have procured it the name of drum of the ear; and the <lb/>muscles of the
        malleus having been deemed sufficient for bra- <lb/>cing and unbracing it, less attention
        was bestowed on the struc- <lb/>ture of the membrane itself: to which may be added, that in
        <lb/>the human ear, and generally in the ear of quadrupeds, the <lb/>membrane is so
        extremely small and thin, and in its situation <lb/>so peculiarly confined, as not to be got
        at for inspection but with <lb/>much difficulty. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The case is different in the elephant, where this membrane <lb/>is so very large, that
        the parts of which it is composed are <lb/>readily distinguished: they are even conspicuous
        to the naked <lb/>eye; and muscular fibres are seen passing along the membrane, <lb/>in a
        radiated manner, from the bony rim which surrounds it, <lb/>towards the handle of the
        malleus, to which the central part of <lb/>the membrane is firmly attached. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This discovery in the elephant having led to that of a simi- <lb/>lar construction in
        the human membrana tympani, it may not <lb/>be improper to relate the circumstances by which
        I became <lb/>engaged in the investigation of the organ of hearing in that <lb/>animal. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Three different opportunities have occurred of dissecting the <lb/>elephant in London,
        by the deaths of those which had been <lb/>presented to his Majesty, and were kept at the
        King's stables <lb/>at Pimlico. One of them was given to the late Dr. <hi rend="sc"
          >Hunter</hi>; <lb/>one to his brother Mr. <hi rend="sc">J. Hunter</hi>; and the third to
        Sir <hi rend="sc">Ashton <lb/>Lever</hi>. </p>
      <pb n="3"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From my being connected with Mr. <hi rend="sc">John Hunter</hi>'s pursuits <lb/>in
        comparative anatomy, I was employed throughout the whole <lb/>of these dissections, and
        became extremely desirous of exami- <lb/>ning the internal parts of the ear, the structure
        of that organ in <lb/>the human body having at a very early period particulary en-
        <lb/>gaged my attention; <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* In the year 1776, I injected the cochlea and semicircular canals of the human ear
            <lb/>with a composition of wax and rosin. This was done by placing the temporal bone in
            <lb/>the receiver of an air pump, the upper part of which was in the form of a funnel,
            ren- <lb/>dered air-tight by a cork being fitted into its neck, and surrounded with
            bees' wax. <lb/>After the air had been exhausted, the hot injection, poured into the
            funnel, melted the <lb/>wax, and the cork was pulled out by means of a string previously
            attached to it; the <lb/>injection immediately rushed into the receiver, and was forced,
            by the pressure of the <lb/>atmosphere, into the cavities of the temporal bone. </p>
        </note> but neither Dr. <hi rend="sc">Hunter</hi> nor his brother <lb/>could be prevailed
        upon to sacrifice so large a portion of the <lb/>skull as was necessary for the purpose. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When Mr. <hi rend="sc">Corse</hi> arrived from Bengal, last year, and men- <lb/>tioned
        his having brought over a number of skulls of elephants, <lb/>in order to show the progress
        of the formation of their grind- <lb/>ing teeth, <note n="†" place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† On this subject, a very ingenious paper has been since published by him, in the
            <lb/>Philosophical Transactions for the year 1799. </p>
        </note> the desire to examine the organ of hearing in that <lb/>animal recurred to me so
        strongly, that I requested to have one <lb/>of the skulls for that purpose, and Mr. <hi
          rend="sc">Corse</hi> very readily and <lb/>obligingly complied with my request. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After having examined the organ in the dried skull, the want <lb/>of the membrana
        tympani, and of the small bones, made the <lb/>information thus received of a very
        unsatisfactory nature, and <lb/>increased the desire of seeing these parts in the recent
        head. In <lb/>considering how this could be done, I recollected a mutilated <lb/>elephant's
        head, preserved in spirits, which had been sent to <pb n="4"/>
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="sc">Hunter</hi>, but, from the multiplicity of his engagements, <lb/>had
        remained neglected in the cask at the time of his death, and <lb/>in the following year was
        dried, to show the proboscis, that it <lb/>might not be altogether spoiled. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon examining this dried head, the bones had been so much <lb/>broken, that one of the
        organs of hearing was altogether want- <lb/>ing: the other, however, was fortunately entire;
        and the mem- <lb/>brana tympani and small bones, having been little disturbed in <lb/>the
        drying of the parts, remained nearly in their natural situation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The membrana tympani, and every other part of the organ, <lb/>were found to be much
        larger in proportion than in other qua- <lb/>drupeds, or in man; differing in this respect
        from the eye of <lb/>the elephant, which is unusually small, when compared with <lb/>the
        enormous bulk of the animal. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The membrane was found of an oval form; the short dia- <lb/>meter of the oval rather
        more than an inch in length; the long <lb/>diameter an inch and 7/20ths. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the human ear, the membrana tympani is nearly circular; <lb/>the longest diameter is
        8/20ths of an inch; the shortest 7/20ths. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As the membrane in the elephant exceeds that of the human <lb/>ear in thickness as much
        as in extent, which is as the squares <lb/>of their diameters, or in the proportion of 135
        to 14, it is natu- <lb/>ral to conclude that the muscular fibres which are to stretch the
        <lb/>one, must greatly exceed in strength those capable of producing <lb/>the same degree of
        tension in the other. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From this statement, the muscular structure in the human <lb/>membrana tympani will
        necessarily be so much less distinct <lb/>than in the elephant, as scarcely to be visible to
        the naked eye, <lb/>and will easily be overlooked by the most attentive observer, <lb/>who
        is not directed by some previous information to examine <pb n="5"/>
        <lb/>it under the most favourable circumstances; but, when these <lb/>are attended to, it
        can be perceived without the aid of glasses. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If the membrana tympani of the human ear is completely <lb/>exposed on both sides, by
        removing the contiguous parts, and <lb/>the cuticular covering is carefully washed off from
        its external <lb/>surface, then, by placing it in a clear light, the radiated direc-
        <lb/>tion of its fibres may be easily detected. If a common magnify- <lb/>ing glass is used,
        they are rendered nearly as distinct as those <lb/>of the elephant appear to the naked eye;
        their course is exactly <lb/>the same; and they differ in nothing but in being formed upon
        <lb/>a smaller scale. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When viewed in a microscope magnifying 23 times, the <lb/>muscular fibres are
        beautifully conspicuous and appear uni- <lb/>formly the same throughout the whole surface,
        there being no <lb/>central tendons, as in the diaphragm; the muscular fibres ap- <lb/>pear
        only to form the internal layer of the membrane, and are <lb/>most distinctly seen when
        viewed on that side. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In examining this membrane in different subjects, the parts <lb/>were frequently found
        in a more or less morbid state. In one <lb/>instance, the membrane was found loaded with
        blood-vessels, <lb/>was less transparent than usual, and was united by close adhe- <lb/>sion
        to the point of the long process of the incus. In another <lb/>instance, there was a
        preternatural ossification adhering to it, at <lb/>a small distance from the end of the
        handle of the malleus. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As muscles in general are supplied with blood-vessels in pro- <lb/>portion to the
        frequency of their action, it is an object of im- <lb/>portance to determine the vascularity
        of the membrana tympani. <lb/>Upon this subject, my own want of information has been amply
        <lb/>supplied by Dr. <hi rend="sc">Baillie</hi>, who, in a communication upon this
        <lb/>subject, showed me a preparation of the membrane, in which <pb n="6"/>
        <lb/>the vessels had been most successfully injected with coloured <lb/>wax. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In this preparation, the most beautiful of the kind I ever saw, <lb/>the vessels in
        their distribution resembled those of the iris, and <lb/>were nearly half as numerous: they
        anastomosed with one an- <lb/>other in a similar manner, and their general direction was
        from <lb/>the circumference to the handle of the malleus; from near this <lb/>handle, a
        small trunk sent off branches, in a radiated manner, <lb/>which anastomosed with those which
        had an opposite course. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This correspondence, in the number and distribution of blood- <lb/>vessels, between the
        membrana tympani and the iris, is a strong <lb/>circumstance in confirmation of that
        membrane being endowed <lb/>with muscular action. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the horse, the membrana tympani is smaller than in man; <lb/>its long diameter is
        8/20ths of an inch; the short one 6/20ths; and <lb/>it is almost quite flat, while in man it
        is concave, which makes <lb/>the difference of extent considerably exceed the difference in
        the <lb/>diameters. In the horse, the fibrous structure is not visible to <lb/>the naked
        eye; it is even indistinctly seen when viewed through <lb/>a common magnifying glass; but in
        a microscope it is very <lb/>visible, and in every other respect agrees in structure with
        the <lb/>membrane in the human ear, and in that of the elephant. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In birds, the membrana tympani is larger in proportion than <lb/>in the quadruped, and
        more circular in its shape. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the goose, it is 6/20ths of an inch in its longest diameter, and <lb/>5/20ths in its
        shortest diameter. In the turkey, 7/20ths by 5/20ths. <lb/>It is thinner in its coats in
        birds than in the horse, and to the <lb/>naked eye has no appearance of fibres; but, when
        viewed in a <lb/>microscope, there is a visible radiated structure, not very unlike <lb/>the
        wire marks upon common writing paper. </p>
      <pb n="7"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In a former Lecture upon the Structure of Muscles, <note n="*" place="bottom"
          rend="size(0.6)">
          <p rend="align-center">* Philosophical Transactions for the year 1795. </p>
        </note> in <lb/>which a comprehensive view was taken of the subject, it was <lb/>stated,
        that the organization necessary for muscular contraction <lb/>could exist in an apparent
        membrane, and that a fasciculated <lb/>structure was only necessary when muscular action was
        to be <lb/>enabled to overcome resistance. The coats of the Tænia hydati- <lb/>gena were
        mentioned as an instance of the first; and the human <lb/>heart as the most complex of the
        second. In comparing the <lb/>membranæ tympani of different animals, they afford a beautiful
        <lb/>illustration of the truth of this position. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In birds, where from the smallness of its size the resist- <lb/>ance is very trifling,
        the membrane is very similar to the coat <lb/>of an hydatid, only still thinner. In the
        elephant, fibres form- <lb/>ing fasciculi are very distinct. The membrane of the horse,
        <lb/>and that of the human ear, form the intermediate gradations. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The knowledge of a muscular structure in the membrana <lb/>tympani, enables us to
        explain many phænomena in hearing, <lb/>which have not hitherto been accounted for in a
        satisfactory <lb/>manner. It is principally by means of this muscle that accu- <lb/>rate
        perceptions of sound are communicated to the internal or- <lb/>gan, and that the membrana
        tympani is enabled to vary the <lb/>state of its tension, so as to receive them in quick
        succession <lb/>in which they are conveyed to it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the human ear, and in that of birds, the radiated fibres of <lb/>the membrana
        tympani have their principal attachment to the <lb/>extremity of the handle of the malleus,
        which is nearly in the <lb/>centre of the membrane. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the membrane of the elephant, which is oval, the attach- <lb/>ment to the handle of
        the malleus is at some distance from the <pb n="8"/>
        <lb/>centre. In the horse, deer, and cat, which have the membrane <lb/>still more oval than
        the elephant, the handle of the malleus is <lb/>situated in the long axis of the membrane,
        with its extremity <lb/>extending beyond the centre, reaching nearer to the circumfe-
        <lb/>rence; and the fibres of the radiated muscle are not only at- <lb/>tached to its end,
        but also laterally to nearly the whole length <lb/>of its handle. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This oval form of the membrana tympani, in those quadrupeds, <lb/>and the very
        extensive attachment of the fibres of the radiated <lb/>muscle to the handle of the malleus,
        may be the reason why <lb/>their ears are not equally fitted to hear inarticulate sounds, as
        <lb/>the ears of birds and of man. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Should this radiated muscle of the membrana tympani (which <lb/>is probably the
        smallest in the body that has a distinct action) <lb/>be thought too insignificant to have
        an office of so much con- <lb/>sequence assigned to it, let it be remembered, that the size
        of <lb/>muscles is no indication of their importance, but only of the <lb/>resistance to be
        overcome by their action; and that the more <lb/>delicate actions are performed universally
        in the body by very <lb/>small muscles, of which the iris in the eye furnishes a very con-
        <lb/>spicuous example. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Before the mode in which the radiated muscle adapts the <lb/>membrana tympani to
        different sounds can be explained, it is <lb/>necessary that the more important parts of the
        organ should be <lb/>enumerated, and the use commonly assigned to each of them <lb/>pointed
        out. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In man and the more perfect quadrupeds, this organ consists <lb/>of the following
        parts: the membrana tympani, situated be- <lb/>tween the external passage and the cavity of
        the tympanum; <lb/>four small bones, which form a chain across the tympanum, <pb n="9"/>
        <lb/>connecting the membrana tympani with another membrane <lb/>lining the foramen ovale,
        which opens into the vestibulum, a <lb/>more internal part of the organ of hearing. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The bones are, the malleus, which is united to the membrana <lb/>tympani by a portion
        of its handle, and to the second bone or <lb/>incus by its head. The incus, which is
        connected to the mal- <lb/>leus by a capsular ligament, forming a regular joint, the sur-
        <lb/>faces of the bones being covered with cartilage, but they have <lb/>only a tremulous
        motion on one another. The incus is also <lb/>attached to the side of the cavity of the
        tympanum, where the <lb/>mastoid cells open, by a ligament on which it moves back-
        <lb/>wards and forwards: it is united by its long process to the <lb/>orbicular bone, which
        is the smallest in the body, and connects <lb/>the incus to the fourth bone or stapes, which
        has its base ap- <lb/>plied to the foramen ovale, or opening leading into the cavity of
        <lb/>the vestibulum. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The cavity of the tympanum, in which these bones are si- <lb/>tuated, communicates with
        the external air by means of the <lb/>Eustachian tube, so that there is always air behind
        the mem- <lb/>brana tympani. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The malleus has three muscles, by which it is moved; one <lb/>of them is called the
        tensor, from its pulling the malleus in- <lb/>wards, and tightening the membrana tympani:
        the other two <lb/>act in an opposite direction, and relax the membrane; the lar- <lb/>gest
        of these is called the obliquus, and is the antagonist of the <lb/>tensor muscle; the other
        is very small, and is called the laxator. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The stapes has one muscle, which acts upon it by bringing <lb/>its basis closer to the
        foramen ovale. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The vestibulum, which is completely separated from the <lb/>tympanum, by the membrane
        that lines the foramen ovale, com- <pb n="10"/>
        <lb/>municates freely with the cochlea and semicircular canals; but <lb/>these cavities are
        filled with a watery liquor, and have no com- <lb/>munication (as the tympanum has) with the
        external air. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This fact was ascertained in the horse, by the following ex- <lb/>periment, repeated
        several times. The organ of hearing was <lb/>separated from the skull immediately after
        death, and the ca- <lb/>vity of the tympanum exposed; the parts were then immersed <lb/>in
        water, and the stapes removed; by which means, the mem- <lb/>brane of the foramen ovale was
        destroyed, but no globule of <lb/>air was seen to escape through the water. <note
          place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)" n="*">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* This experiment was made by Mr. <hi rend="sc">Clift</hi>, who superintends Mr.
              <hi rend="sc">Hunter</hi>'s col- <lb/>lection, and who has afforded me material
            assistance in the different parts of this <lb/>investigation. </p>
        </note>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The following uses have generally been assigned to the parts <lb/>now mentioned. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The membrana tympani was supposed to be adapted to re- <lb/>ceive impressions, by the
        combined action of the tensor and <lb/>laxator muscles varying the degree of its tension, so
        as to bring <lb/>it in unison with different sounds: these impressions were con-
        <lb/>ducted, by the chain of bones, to the vestibulum, cochlea, and <lb/>semicircular
        canals; in which cavities, particulary the cochlea, <lb/>they were supposed to undergo some
        modification, before they <lb/>were impressed upon the nerves spread upon the linings of
        <lb/>these cavities. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The function of modifying impressions of sound was assign- <lb/>ed to the cochlea,
        partly from the delicacy of its internal struc- <lb/>ture, supposed to resemble a musical
        instrument, and partly <lb/>from there being no other part of the organ apparently suited
        <lb/>for repeating the variety of delicate sounds which pass into the <lb/>ear: the changes
        that could be produced upon the membrana <pb n="11"/>
        <lb/>tympani by the muscles of the malleus, being considered as in- <lb/>capable of
        answering that purpose. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This slight sketch of the organ of hearing, and of the uses, <lb/>as they are generally
        understood, of the different parts, will <lb/>enable me to point out, with more clearness,
        what parts of the <lb/>theory appear defective, and what improvements may be made <lb/>on
        it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is true that the membrana tympani is stretched and re- <lb/>laxed by the action of
        the muscles of the malleus, but not for <lb/>the purpose alleged in the commonly received
        theory. It is <lb/>stretched, in order to bring the radiated muscle of the membrane
        <lb/>itself into a state capable of acting, and of giving those diffe- <lb/>rent degrees of
        tension to the membrane which empower it to <lb/>correspond with the variety of external
        tremors: when the <lb/>membrane is relaxed, the radiated muscle cannot act with any
        <lb/>effect, and external tremors make less accurate impressions. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The membrana tympani, with its tensor and radiated muscles, <lb/>may not be unaptly
        compared to a monochord, of which the <lb/>membrana tympani is the string; the tensor muscle
        the screw, <lb/>giving the necessary tension to make the string perfrom its <lb/>proper
        scale of vibrations; and the radiated muscle acting upon <lb/>the membrane like the moveable
        bridge of the monochord, ad- <lb/>justing it to the vibrations required to be produced. The
        com- <lb/>bined effects of the action of these muscles give the perceptions <lb/>of grave
        and acute tones; and, in proportion as their original <lb/>conformation is more or less
        perfect, so will their actions be, <lb/>and, consequently, the perceptions of sound which
        they com- <lb/>municate. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This mode of subdividing the motions of the membrana <lb/>tympani between two sets of
        muscles, allotting a portion to <pb n="12"/>
        <lb/>each, is not peculiar to this part. A remarkable instance of it <lb/>appears in the
        rapid movements of the fingers, in performing <lb/>several actions, and particularly in
        playing on a musical instru- <lb/>ment. In all such rapid motions, the fingers are bent to a
        <lb/>certain degree by the long muscles that lie upon the fore-arm, <lb/>to the tendons of
        which a set of smaller muscles are attached, <lb/>called lumbricales. These last are unable
        to produce any effect <lb/>on the fingers, till elongated in consequence of the action of
        <lb/>the long muscles in bending the other joints; the lumbricales <lb/>then become capable
        of bending the fingers a little more, and <lb/>of acting with great rapidity. It is a
        curious circumstance, <lb/>that a similiar application of muscles should be employed to fit
        <lb/>the fingers to produce a quick succession of sounds, and to <lb/>enable the ear to be
        impressed by them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From the explanation given of the adjustment of the mem- <lb/>brana tympani, the
        difference between a musical ear and one <lb/>which is too imperfect to distinguish the
        different notes in <lb/>music, will appear to arise entirely from the greater or less nicety
        <lb/>with which the muscle of the malleus renders the membrane <lb/>capable of being truly
        adjusted. If the tension be perfect, all <lb/>the variations produced by the action of the
        radiated muscle <lb/>will be equally correct, and the ear truly musical; but, if the
        <lb/>first adjustment is imperfect, although the actions of the ra- <lb/>diated muscle may
        still produce infinite variations, none of them <lb/>will be correct: the effect, in this
        respect, will be similar to that <lb/>produced by playing upon a musical instrument which is
        not in <lb/>tune. The hearing of articulate sounds requires less nicety in <lb/>the
        adjustment, than of inarticulate or musical ones: an ear <lb/>may therefore be able to
        perceive the one, although it is not <lb/>fitted to receive distinct preceptions from the
        other. </p>
      <pb n="13"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The nicety or correctness of a musical ear being the result <lb/>of muscular action,
        renders it, in part, an acquirement; for, <lb/>although the original formation of these
        muscles in some ears <lb/>renders them more capable of arriving at this perfection in their
        <lb/>action, early cultivation is still necessary for that purpose; and <lb/>it is found
        that an ear, which upon the first trials seemed unfit <lb/>to receive accurate perceptions
        of sounds, shall, by early and <lb/>constant application, be rendered tolerably correct, but
        never <lb/>can attain excellence. There are organs of hearing in which <lb/>the parts are so
        nicely adjusted to one another, as to render <lb/>them capable of a degree of correctness in
        hearing sounds <lb/>which appears preternatural. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Children who during their infancy are much in the society <lb/>of musical performers,
        will be naturally induced to attend more <lb/>to inarticulate sounds than articulate ones,
        and by these means <lb/>acquire a correct ear, which, after listening for two or three
        <lb/>years to articulate sounds only, would have been attained with <lb/>more difficulty. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This mode of adapting the ear to different sounds, appears <lb/>to be one of the most
        beautiful applications of muscles in the <lb/>body; the mechanism is so simple, and the
        variety of effects so <lb/>great. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Several ways in which the correctness of hearing is affected <lb/>by the wrong actions
        of the muscles of the tympanum, that <lb/>appeared to be inexplicable, can be readily
        accounted for, now <lb/>that the means by which the membrane adjusts itself are un-
        <lb/>derstood. The following are instances of this kind. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Case 1</hi>. A gentleman thirty-three years of age, who possess- <lb/>ed
        a very correct ear, so as to be capable of singing in concert, <lb/>though he had never
        learned music, was suddenly seized with a <pb n="14"/>
        <lb/>giddiness in the head, and a slight degree of numbness in the right <lb/>side and arm.
        These feelings went off in a few hours, but on <lb/>the third day returned, and for several
        weeks he had returns of <lb/>the same sensations. It was soon discovered that he had lost
        <lb/>his musical ear; he could neither sing a note in tune, nor in the <lb/>smallest degree
        perceive harmony in the performance of others. <lb/>For some time he himself thought he had
        become a little deaf, <lb/>but his medical attendant was not sensible of that in conversa-
        <lb/>tion. Upon going into the country, he derived great benefit <lb/>from exercise and
        sea-bathing. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Twenty months after the first attack, he was capable of sing- <lb/>ing a Scotch air
        with tolerable exactness, though he could not <lb/>sing in concert. He continued to improve
        in his health, and <lb/>in the course of two or three years completely recovered his ear
        <lb/>for music. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In this case, there appeared to be some affection of the brain, <lb/>which had
        diminished the actions of the tensor muscles of the <lb/>membranæ tympani, through the
        medium of the nerves which <lb/>regulate their actions; this gradually went off, and the
        muscles <lb/>recovered their former action. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Case 2</hi>. A young lady was seized with a frenzy which last- <lb/>ed
        for several years. Previous to her derangement, she was <lb/>incapable of singing in tune,
        from the want of an ear for <lb/>music; but in the course of her madness she frequently, to
        the <lb/>astonishment of her relations, sung a tune with tolerable cor- <lb/>rectness. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This case is the reverse of the former; and, as it arose from a <lb/>directly contrary
        affection of the brain, may be considered as the <lb/>result of an unusual degree of action
        in the tensor muscles, giv- <lb/>ing the membrane a more correct adjustment than it had
        before. </p>
      <pb n="15"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Case 3</hi>. An eminent music master, after catching cold, found <lb/>a
        confusion of sounds in his ears. Upon strict attention, he dis- <lb/>covered that the pitch
        of one ear was half a note lower than that <lb/>of the other; and that the perception of a
        simple sound did not <lb/>reach both ears at the same instant, but seemed as two distinct
        <lb/>sounds, following each other in quick succession, the last being <lb/>the lowest and
        weakest. This complaint distressed him for <lb/>a long time, but he recovered from it
        without any medical <lb/>aid. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In this case, the whole defect appears to have been in the <lb/>action of the radiated
        muscle, exerted neither with the same <lb/>quickness nor force in one ear as in the other,
        so that the sound <lb/>was half a note too low, as well as later in being impressed
        <lb/>upon the organ. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This affection of the muscle of the membrana tympani is <lb/>very similar to an
        affection of the straight muscles of one of <lb/>the eyes, producing double vision, which I
        have noticed in a <lb/>former lecture, when treating of the wrong actions of that
        <lb/>organ. <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)" n="*">
          <p rend="align-center">* Vide Philosophical Transactions for the year 1797. </p>
        </note>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In endeavouring to explain the uses of the more internal parts <lb/>of the ear,
        considerable advantage may be derived from class- <lb/>ing them in two divisions; namely,
        those which are formed for <lb/>the purpose of receiving impressions conveyed through the
        me- <lb/>dium of liquid or of solid substances; and those adapted to re- <lb/>ceive
        impressions made by the impulses of an elastic fluid, as <lb/>the common air. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This can be done very correctly. Fish, which are formed to <lb/>hear in water, can have
        only the parts belonging to the first <lb/>division; while all the parts found in the ears
        of birds and <pb n="16"/>
        <lb/>quadrupeds, that are not met with in fish, must belong to the <lb/>second. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In fish, the organ consists of a vestibulum and three semi- <lb/>circular canals, and
        these are met with in all fish. In some <lb/>genera there is an external opening, and
        substances of a hard <lb/>nature are found lying loose in the vestibulum: these, how-
        <lb/>ever, cannot be considered as essential parts of the organ, from <lb/>their not being
        common to fish in general. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Birds have the vestibulum and semicircular canals in com- <lb/>mon with fish, but they
        have also a membrana tympani; a <lb/>slender bone connecting that membrane with the
        vestibulum; <lb/>and an Eustachian tube. In birds, the membrana tympani is <lb/>convex
        externally, being pushed forwards by the end of the <lb/>slender bone abovementioned. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In quadrupeds and man, besides the vestibulum and canals <lb/>met with in fish, the
        membrana tympani, the bone connecting <lb/>it with the vestibulum, and the Eustachian tube,
        found in birds, <lb/>there is a cochlea. The membrana tympani is either flat or <lb/>concave
        externally; the bony connection between it and the <lb/>vestibulum is made up of several
        bones, supplied with muscles <lb/>to move them in different directions. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The parts which compose the organ of hearing in fish, must <lb/>be intended for
        receiving impressions conveyed through water: <lb/>those additional parts met with in birds,
        and the still greater <lb/>additions which are found in the quadruped and man, must be
        <lb/>intended by nature for rendering more perfect the impressions <lb/>conveyed to the ear
        through the medium of the external air. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Fish, from the structure of the organ, can only hear sounds <lb/>which agitate the
        water immediately in contact with the head <lb/>of the fish; so that the impulse is
        conveyed, without inter- <pb n="17"/>
        <lb/>ruption, from the liquid in which they live, to the organ of <lb/>hearing. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Man is capable of hearing in a similar manner to fishes, when <lb/>a communication of
        solid parts is kept up between the sounding <lb/>body and the bones of the skull:
        experiments of this kind must <lb/>have been made by many members of this learned Society. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>One of the most common is, applying a watch to the fore- <lb/>head, and stopping the
        ears, which does not prevent the ticking <lb/>from being heard: the sound is still more
        distinct when the <lb/>watch is applied to the mastoid process. Here, as the sound <lb/>can
        neither pass through the meatus externus, nor by the Eus- <lb/>tachian tube, while the mouth
        is kept shut, it evidently must <lb/>be conducted through the bones of the skull. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the sound produced by boiling water is brought to the <lb/>ear, by one end of an
        iron rod resting upon the side of the kettle <lb/>and the other kept in contact with the
        teeth, the sound is con- <lb/>ducted in the same way, although in this case it has by some
        <lb/>been supposed to pass through the Eustachian tube. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In this mode of hearing, the vestibulum and semicircular <lb/>canals are probably the
        only parts of the organ which are ne- <lb/>cessary to convey the impression to the expansion
        of the audi- <lb/>tory nerve. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In hearing in air, the use of the membrana tympani in man <lb/>and quadrupeds has
        already been explained. Its office in <lb/>birds is precisely the same; but as in birds this
        membrane has <lb/>no tensor muscle to vary its adjustment, but is always kept <lb/>tense by
        the pressure of the end of the slender bone, the scale <lb/>in birds cannot descend so low
        as in the human ear; and the <lb/>intervals in their scale will be more minute, in
        consequence of <lb/>the slightest tremor communicated by the action of the radiated <pb
          n="18"/>
        <lb/>muscle to one end of the slender bone being immediately con- <lb/>ducted to the
        internal organ; while in the human ear it has to <lb/>pass from one bone to another, before
        it arrives at the vestibu- <lb/>lum. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The cochlea has been considered by all physiologists as one <lb/>of the most intricate
        and curious parts of the ear, and, on that <lb/>account had a most important office assigned
        to it. This, how- <lb/>ever, is now to be transferred to the membrana tympani; and,
        <lb/>upon attentive consideration of the subject, it will appear im- <lb/>possible for the
        cochlea to be of any use in modulating sounds, <lb/>since the ear is only intended to convey
        impressions received <lb/>from external bodies; hence, no impression can be communi-
        <lb/>cated to the cochlea, which has not been transmitted by the <lb/>membrana tympani. But,
        if all the varieties of sound are re- <lb/>peated by the membrana tympani, no modulation in
        the cochlea <lb/>is required; and, when it is considered that the cochlea contains
        <lb/>water, instead of air, the effect upon every part will be found to <lb/>be
        simultaneous. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That the cochlea is neither absolutely necessary to fit the <lb/>organ to be impressed
        by sounds communicated through air, <lb/>nor to render it what is termed a musical ear, is
        sufficiently <lb/>proved by that part being wanting in birds, whose organ is par-
        <lb/>ticulary adapted to inarticulate sounds. Some birds, particularly <lb/>bulfinches, can
        be taught to sing various airs, although it will <lb/>be always in high notes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If it should be found that birds hear less accurately than <lb/>quadrupeds, it will
        favour the idea that the great delicacy of <lb/>structure of the cochlea, is intended to
        render the nerves which <lb/>are spread upon it more readily impressed by weak tremors,
        <lb/>than those in either the vestibulum or semicircular canals. </p>
      <pb n="19"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The cochlea and semicircular canals must be considered as <lb/>two of the most
        important parts of the ear; their peculiar forms <lb/>are no doubt adapted to some essential
        purposes; but, what are <lb/>the precise advantages derived from their particular shape, is
        at <lb/>present unknown. There is, however, much ground to believe, <lb/>that a more
        extensive knowledge in comparative anatomy, join- <lb/>ed with future observations, may
        clear up this very curious and <lb/>obscure part of the physiology of the organ of hearing. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the elephant, the small bones, the cochlea, and semicircu- <lb/>lar canals, are
        larger than those in the human ear, nearly in the <lb/>same proportion with the increased
        size of the membrana tym- <lb/>pani. In that animal, there is a very remarkable peculiarity;
        <lb/>which is, a cellular structure occupying the upper and posterior <lb/>part of the
        skull, inclosed between the two tables, communi- <lb/>cating by a considerable aperture with
        the cavity of the tympa- <lb/>num, and lined by a similar membrane: the cells commu-
        <lb/>nicate freely with one another at their lower extremities, but <lb/>not near the upper,
        forming irregular cylinders, placed in a <lb/>converging direction, towards the cavity of
        the tympanum. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There is no middle bony septum, separating the cells of the <lb/>skull belonging to one
        ear from those which open into the <lb/>other, but a ready communication between them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the anterior part of the skull there is also a similar cel- <lb/>lular structure,
        only much smaller, which communicates with <lb/>the nose, but is entirely separate and
        distinct from that which <lb/>forms an appendage to the organ of hearing. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That the elephant hears better than other animals, is gene- <lb/>rally asserted by
        those who have had opportunities of making <lb/>observations on the subject. As this opinion
        has been ad- <lb/>vanced by men who had no knowledge in anatomy, and had <pb n="20"/>
        <lb/>no previous theory to bias their judgment, it is deserving of <lb/>credit. The organ of
        hearing being now found more perfect, <lb/>and formed upon a larger scale than in any other
        animal with <lb/>which we are acquainted, considerable weight is given to this <lb/>opinion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="sc">Corse</hi>, who resided many years at Tiperah, in Bengal, <lb/>and
        paid particular attention to the manners and habits of ele- <lb/>phants, concurs in the
        belief of their hearing being more acute <lb/>than that of man. The following circumstances
        are mentioned <lb/>by him in proof of it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A tame elephant, who was never reconciled to have a horse <lb/>moving behind him,
        although he expressed no uneasiness if the <lb/>horse was within his view, either before or
        on one side, could <lb/>distinguish the sound of a horse's foot at a distance, some time
        <lb/>before any person in company heard it: this was known by his <lb/>pricking up his ears,
        quickening his pace, and turning his head <lb/>from side to side. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A tame female elephant, who has a young one, was occa- <lb/>sionally sent out with
        other elephants for food, without the <lb/>young one being allowed to follow. She was not in
        the habit <lb/>of pining after her young one, unless she heard its voice; but
        <lb/>frequently, on the road home, when no one could distinguish <lb/>any sound whatever,
        she pricked up her ears, and made a noise <lb/>expressive of having heard the call of her
        young. This having <lb/>occured frequently, attracted Mr. <hi rend="sc">Corse</hi>'s notice,
        and made <lb/>him, at the time the female elephant used these expressions, <lb/>stop the
        party, and desire the gentlemen to listen; but they were <lb/>unable to hear any thing till
        they had approached nearer to the <lb/>place where the young one was kept. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The foregoing observations, the object of which has been to <pb n="21"/>
        <lb/>prove that the membrana tympani of the ear has a muscular <lb/>structure, have already
        exceeded the limits of a lecture, which <lb/>prevents us from going further at present into
        the considera- <lb/>tion of this very curious and important organ. The general <lb/>analogy
        between the uses of its different parts and those of the <lb/>organ of vision, and the
        similar variations of their actions when <lb/>under the influence of disease, furnish
        materials which, on <lb/>some future occasion, may be laid before this learned Society. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
