<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Cornaro: Sure and Certain Methods of Attaining a Long and Healthful
          Life</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Luigi Cornaro</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Sure and Certain Methods of Attaining a Long and Healthful Life with
              Means of Correcting a Bad Constitution, &amp;c. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T177748</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T177748"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for Tho. Leigh, and Dan. Midwinter, at the Rose and Crown
                  in St. Paul's Church-Yard, 1702.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1702</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="40"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="141"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="3"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">Bodleian Library, Oxford</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108840254</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Health guide"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="40"/>
    <body>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>The Sure Way of Attaining a <lb/>Long and Healthful Life. </head>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A horizontal line spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <div type="chapter">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>CHAP. I. </head>
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Of a Sober and Regular Life. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">N</hi>Othing is more certain, than <lb/>that Cuſtom becomes a ſe-
          <lb/>cond Nature, and has a great In- <lb/>fluence upon our Bodies. Nay, it <lb/>has too
          often more Power over <lb/>the Mind, than Reaſon it ſelf. <lb/>The honeſteſt Man alive, in
          keep- <lb/>ing company with Libertines, by <lb/>degrees forgets the Maxims of Pro-
          <lb/>bity, which he had imbibed from <lb/>the very Breaſt, and gives himſelf <lb/>the
          Looſe in thoſe Vices which he <lb/>ſees practis'd. If he be ſo happy <lb/>as to relinquiſh
          that bad Company, <lb/>and to meet with Better, Vertue <lb/>will triumph in its Turn; and
          he <pb n="2"/>
          <lb/>inſenſibly reſumes the Wiſdom <lb/>which he had abandoned. In a <lb/>word, all the
          Alterations which <lb/>we perceive in the Temper, Carri- <lb/>age, and Manners of moſt
          men, have <lb/>ſcarce any other Foundation, but the <lb/>force and prevalency of Cuſtom. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I have obſerv'd, that 'tis Cuſtom <lb/>which has given Riſe to two very
          <lb/>dangerous Evils within a little time <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi>; the firſt
          I reckon to be <lb/>Flattery and Ceremonies; and the <lb/>ſecond, Intemperance both in
          Eat- <lb/>ing and Drinking. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The firſt of theſe baniſhes out of <lb/>human Converſation, all Plain-deal- <lb/>ing,
          Frankneſs and Sincerity: And <lb/>againſt the latter I declare open war, <lb/>as being the
          moſt deſtructive of <lb/><hi rend="italic">health</hi>, and the greateſt Enemy it has. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>'Tis an Unhappineſs into which <lb/>the Men of this Age are fal'n, that <lb/>Variety
          of Diſhes is A-la-mode, <lb/>and become ſo far preferable to <lb/>Frugality. And yet the
          One is <pb n="3"/>
          <lb/>the Product of Temperance; whilſt <lb/>Pride and an unreſtrained Appetite <lb/>is the
          Parent of the Other. Notwith- <lb/>ſtanding the difference of their Ori- <lb/>gine, yet
          Prodigality is at preſent <lb/>ſtiled Magnificence, Generoſity, and <lb/>Grandeur, and is
          commonly eſteem- <lb/>ed of in the World; whilſt Frugality <lb/>paſſes for Avarice, and
          Sordidneſs <note place="margin">of </note>
          <lb/>Spirit in the Eyes of moſt Men. <lb/>Here is a viſible Error, which Cu- <lb/>ſtom and
          Habit have eſtabliſh'd. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This Error has ſo far ſeduced us, <lb/>that it has prevailed upon us to <lb/>renounce
          a frugal way of Living, <lb/>tho' taught us by Nature even <lb/>from the firſt Age of the
          World, <lb/>as being that which would prolong <lb/>our Days; and has caſt us into
          <lb/>thoſe Exceſſes, which ſerve only to <lb/>abridge the Number of them. We <lb/>become
          Old, before we have been <lb/>able to taſte the Pleaſure of being <lb/>Young; and the Time
          which <lb/>ought to be the Summer of our <pb n="4"/>
          <lb/>Lives, is often the beginning of <lb/>their Winter. We ſoon perceive <lb/>our
          Strength to fail, and Weakneſs <lb/>to come on apace, and decline even <lb/>before we come
          to perfection. On <lb/>the contrary, Sobriety maintains <lb/>us in the natural State
          wherein we <lb/>ought to be: Our Youth is laſt- <lb/>ing, and our Manhood attended
          <lb/>with a Vigor that does not begin <lb/>to decay till after a great many <lb/>Years. A
          whole Century muſt be <lb/>run out before Wrinkles can be for- <lb/>med on the Face, or
          gray Hairs grow <lb/>on the Head. This is ſo true, that <lb/>when Men were not addicted to
          <lb/>Voluptuouſneſs, they had more <lb/>Strength and Vivacity at fourſcore, <lb/>than we
          have at preſent at forty. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>O unhappy <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi>! Doſt thou <lb/>not perceive that Gluttony and
          <lb/>Exceſs robs Thee every Year of <lb/>more Inhabitants than Peſtilence, <lb/>War and
          Famine could have de- <lb/>ſtroyed? Thy true Plagues are thy <pb n="5"/>
          <lb/>frequent Feaſtings, which are ſo <lb/>extravagant, that no Tables can be <lb/>made
          large enough to hold that <lb/>Number of Diſhes which Prodiga- <lb/>lity lays upon them,
          but they are <lb/>forced to be heap'd upon one ano- <lb/>ther in Pyramids. What Madneſs,
          <lb/>what Fury is this? Regulate this <lb/>Diſorder, if not for God's ſake, <lb/>yet for
          thy own. I am ſure there <lb/>is no Sin, that diſpleaſes him <lb/>more, nor any
          Voluptuouſneſs that <lb/>can be more pernicious to thy ſelf. <lb/>Endeavour then to heal
          thy ſelf of <lb/>this as being one of thoſe Epide- <lb/>mical Diſtempers, from which
          <lb/>thou may'ſt be preferv'd by whole- <lb/>ſome Food, and by the Precautions <lb/>that
          may prevent them. 'Tis ve- <lb/>ry eaſie to avoid the Evils which <lb/>an Exceſs in Eating
          or Drinking <lb/>may bring upon us; nor is it any <lb/>hard Matter to find out a Sovereign
          <lb/>Remedy againſt Repletion, ſince <lb/>Nature it ſelf has taught us it. Let <pb n="6"/>
          <lb/>us only give it what it requires, <lb/>and not over-charge it; for a ſmall
          <lb/>Matter ſuffices Nature. The Rules <lb/>of Temperance are derived from <lb/>thoſe of
          Right Reaſon. Let us <lb/>accuſtom our ſelves to eat only to <lb/>ſupport Life; what is
          more than <lb/>neceſſary for our Nouriſhment <lb/>ſows the Seeds of Sickneſs and
          <lb/>Death; 'tis a Pleaſure for which <lb/>we muſt pay very dear, and <lb/>which can
          neither be innocent, nor <lb/>excuſable, ſince it may be ſo pre- <lb/>judicial to us. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>How many have I ſeen cut off <lb/>in the flower of their Days by the <lb/>unhappy
          Cuſtom of High-feeding? <lb/>How many excellent Friends has <lb/>Gluttony deprived me of,
          who <lb/>might have been ſtill an Orna- <lb/>ment to the World, an Honour <lb/>to their
          Country, and have occa- <lb/>ſioned me as much Satisfaction in <lb/>enjoying them, as now
          I have Sor- <lb/>row in loſing them? </p>
        <pb n="7"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>'Tis to put a ſtop to this ſpread- <lb/>ing Contagion that I have under- <lb/>taken
          to ſhew in this ſmall Tract, <lb/>that the Number and Variety of <lb/>Diſhes is a fatal
          Abuſe which ought <lb/>to be corrected, by living ſoberly, <lb/>as did the Patriarchs of
          Old. Se- <lb/>veral young Perſons, who for <lb/>their good Qualities, merit my
          <lb/>Eſteem, having loſt their Fathers <lb/>ſooner than they could have expe- <lb/>cted,
          have expreſs'd a great deſire <lb/>of being acquainted with my man- <lb/>ner of Living. I
          could not but <lb/>think their Curioſity very rea- <lb/>ſonable, ſince nothing is more
          rea- <lb/>ſonable than to wiſh for long Life. <lb/>The more we advance in Years, <lb/>the
          larger will our Experience be; <lb/>and if Nature, which aims only at <lb/>our Good,
          adviſes us to grow Old, <lb/>and concurs with us in that De- <lb/>ſign, 'tis becauſe ſhe
          is ſenſible that <lb/>the Body being weakned by Time, <lb/>which deſtroys all Things, the
            <pb n="8"/>
          <lb/>Mind, when diſingaged from the <lb/>Snares of Voluptuouſneſs, is more <lb/>at Leiſure
          to make uſe of its Rea- <lb/>ſon, and to taſte the Sweets of <lb/>Vertue. Hereupon I was
          willing <lb/>to ſatisfie thoſe Perſons, and at <lb/>the ſame time to do ſome Service
          <lb/>to the Publick, by declaring what <lb/>were the Motives that induced me <lb/>to
          renounce Intemperance, and <lb/>live a ſober Life; by ſhewing the <lb/>Method I obſerve,
          and what Be- <lb/>nefit I find thereby; and laſtly, by <lb/>demonſtrating that nothing can
          be <lb/>more beneficial to a Man, than to <lb/>obſerve a Regimen, that it is pra-
          <lb/>cticable and very neceſſary to be <lb/>followed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I ſay then that the Weakneſs of <lb/>my Conſtitution, which was con- <lb/>ſiderably
          increas'd by my way of <lb/>Living, caſt me into ſo deplorable <lb/>a Condition, that I
          was forced to <lb/>bid a final Adieu to all Feaſtings, <lb/>to which I had all my
          Life-long a <pb n="9"/>
          <lb/>violent Inclination. I was ſo often <lb/>engaged in Exceſſes of this kind, <lb/>that
          my tender Conſtitution could <lb/>not hold up under the Fatigues of <lb/>them. I fell into
          ſeveral Diſtem- <lb/>pers, ſuch as Pains of the Stomach, <lb/>the Cholick, and the Gout. I
          had <lb/>a lingring Fever, and an intolerable <lb/>Thirſt continually hanging upon
          <lb/>me. This made me deſpair of any <lb/>Cure, and tho' I was then not above <lb/>35 or
          40 Years old, yet I had no <lb/>hopes of finding any other end of <lb/>my Diſtempers, but
          what ſhould <lb/>end my Life too. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The beſt Phyſicians in <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi>
          <lb/>made uſe of all their Skill for my <lb/>Recovery, but without ſucceſs. At <lb/>laſt
          when they quite deſpair'd of <lb/>me, they told me that they knew <lb/>only of one Remedy
          that could <lb/>cure me, if I had Reſolution <lb/>enough to undertake and continue
          <lb/>it, to wit, a ſober and Regular <lb/>Life, which they exhorted me to <pb n="10"/>
          <lb/>live the remainder of my Days, <lb/>aſſuring me, that if Intemperance <lb/>had
          brought ſo many Diſtempers, <lb/>it was only Temperance that could <lb/>free me from them. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I reliſh'd this Propoſal; and per- <lb/>ceiv'd that notwithſtanding the
          <lb/>miſerable Condition to which my <lb/>Intemperance had reduced me, <lb/>yet I was not
          ſo incurable, but <lb/>the Contrary might recover or at <lb/>leaſt eaſe me. And I was the
          more <lb/>eaſily perſwaded to it, becauſe I <lb/>knew ſeveral Perſons of a great <lb/>Age,
          and a bad Conſtitution, who <lb/>only prolonged their Lives by Ob- <lb/>ſerving a Regimen,
          whilſt on the <lb/>other hand I knew others who <lb/>were born with a wonderful Con-
          <lb/>ſtitution, and yet broke it by their <lb/>Debaucheries. It ſeem'd very na- <lb/>tural
          to me, that a different Way <lb/>of living and acting produces dif- <lb/>ferent Effects;
          ſince Art may con- <lb/>duce to correct, perfect, weaken, <pb n="11"/>
          <lb/>or deſtroy Nature according to the <lb/>good or bad Uſe that is made of <lb/>it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Phyſicians beginning to find <lb/>me tractable, added to what they <lb/>had
          before told me, that I muſt <lb/>either chooſe a Regimen or Death; <lb/>that I could not
          live if I did <lb/>not follow their Advice, and that <lb/>if I defer'd much longer taking
          my <lb/>Reſolutions accordingly, it would <lb/>be too late to do it. This was <lb/>home; I
          was loth to die ſo ſoon, <lb/>and I could not tell how to bear <lb/>the Thoughts of it;
          beſides, I <lb/>was convinced of their Experience <lb/>and Ability. In ſhort, being mo-
          <lb/>rally certain, that my beſt way was <lb/>to believe them, I reſolved upon
          <lb/>putting into Practice this Courſe of <lb/>Life, how auſtere ſoever it ſeem'd <lb/>to
          me. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I intreated my Phyſicians to in- <lb/>form me exactly, after what man- <lb/>ner I
          ought to govern my ſelf. To <pb n="12"/>
          <lb/>this they reply'd, That I muſt al- <lb/>ways manage my ſelf as a ſick Per- <lb/>ſon,
          eat nothing but what was <lb/>good, and that in a ſmall Quantity. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>They had a long time before <lb/>preſcribed the ſame Thing to me; <lb/>but till then
          I made a Jeſt of it. <lb/>When I was cloy'd with the Diet <lb/>they order'd me, I did eat
          of all <lb/>thoſe Meats which they had for- <lb/>bidden, and perceiving my ſelf <lb/>hot
          and dry, I drank Wine in <lb/>abundance. However, I do not <lb/>boaſt of this my Conduct;
          I was <lb/>one of thoſe imprudent Patients, <lb/>who not being able to reſolve up- <lb/>on
          doing whatever is preſcribed <lb/>them for their Health, mind no- <lb/>thing elſe but
          deceiving their Phy- <lb/>ſicians, tho' they prove the greateſt <lb/>Cheats to themſelves
          at laſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As ſoon as I reſolv'd to believe <lb/>my Phyſicians, and thought that <lb/>it was a
          diſgrace not to have Cou- <lb/>rage enough to be Wiſe; I accu- <pb n="13"/>
          <lb/>ſtomed my ſelf ſo much to live ſo- <lb/>berly, that I contracted a Habit of <lb/>ſo
          doing, without any Trouble or <lb/>Violence offer'd to my ſelf. In a little <lb/>time I
          found relief, and (which <lb/>may ſeem to ſome incredible) at <lb/>the Year's end I found
          my ſelf not <lb/>only on the mending hand, but <lb/>I was perfectly cured of all my
          <lb/>Diſtempers. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When I ſaw I was recovered, <lb/>and began to taſte the Sweets of <lb/>this ſort of
          Reſurrection, I made <lb/>abundance of Reflections upon <lb/>the Uſefulneſs of a Regular
          <lb/>Life. I admir'd the Efficacy of <lb/>it, and perceiv'd that if it had <lb/>been ſo
          powerful as to cure me, it <lb/>would be capable enough of pre- <lb/>ſerving me from thoſe
          Diſtempers <lb/>to which I had been always ſub- <lb/>ject. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Experience I had thereof <lb/>removing all farther Scruple, I <lb/>began to ſtudy
          what Food was pro- <pb n="14"/>
          <lb/>per for me. I was minded to try <lb/>whether what pleaſed my Taſte <lb/>were
          Beneficial or Prejudicial to <lb/>my Health, and whether the Pro- <lb/>verb were true,
          which ſays, <hi rend="italic">That <lb/>what delights the Palate, cannot but <lb/>be good
            for the Heart</hi>. I found it to <lb/>be falſe; and that it only ſerves as an
          <lb/>Excuſe to the Senſualiſts, who are <lb/>for indulging themſelves in what- <lb/>ever
          might pleaſe their Appetites. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Formerly I could not drink my <lb/>Wine with Ice; I loved heady <lb/>Wines, Melons,
          all Sorts of raw <lb/>Fruits, Salads, ſalt Meats, high Sau- <lb/>ces and baked Meats,
          notwithſtand- <lb/>ing they were prejudicial to me. <lb/>Hereupon I made no account of the
          <lb/>Proverb, and being convinced of its <lb/>falſity , I made choice of ſuch Wines
          <lb/>and Meats as agreed with my Con- <lb/>ſtitution: I proportion'd the Quanti- <lb/>ty
          thereof according to the ſtrength <lb/>of my Stomach. I declin'd all <lb/>Diet that did
          not agree with <pb n="15"/>
          <lb/>me; and made it a Law to my <lb/>ſelf to lay a reſtraint upon my <lb/>Appetite, ſo
          that I always roſe <lb/>from Table with a Stomach to eat <lb/>more if I pleas'd. In a
          word, I <lb/>entirely renounced Intemperance, <lb/>and made a Vow to continue the
          <lb/>Remainder of my Life under the <lb/>ſame Regimen that I had obſerv'd: <lb/>A happy
          Reſolution this, the keep- <lb/>ing whereof has freed me from all <lb/>my Inſirmities,
          which without it <lb/>were incurable! I never before liv- <lb/>ed a Year together without
          falling <lb/>once at leaſt into ſome violent Di- <lb/>ſtemper; but this never happen'd
          <lb/>to me afterwards; on the contrary <lb/>I have been always Healthful ever <lb/>ſince I
          have been Temperate. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Nouriſhment which I take, <lb/>being in Quality and Quantity juſt <lb/>enough to
          ſuffice Nature, breeds <lb/>no ſuch corrupt Humours as ſpoil <lb/>the beſt Conſtitutions.
          'Tis true <lb/>indeed, that beſides this Precaution <pb n="16"/>
          <lb/>I made uſe of many others. For <lb/>inſtance, I took care to keep my <lb/>ſelf from
          Heats and Colds: I ab- <lb/>ſtain'd from all violent Exerciſes, <lb/>as alſo from ill
          Hours and Wo- <lb/>men. I no longer lived in Pla- <lb/>ces where was an unwholeſome
          <lb/>Air, and took ſpecial Care to <lb/>avoid the being expoſed to <lb/>violent Winds, or
          to the exceſſive <lb/>Heat of the Sun. All theſe Cau- <lb/>tions may ſeem morally
          impoſſible <lb/>to thoſe Men, who in their <lb/>Tranſactions in the World follow <lb/>no
          other Guides but their own <lb/>Paſſions; and yet they are not <lb/>hard to be practis'd,
          when a Man <lb/>can be ſo juſt to himſelf as to pre- <lb/>fer the Preſervation of his
          Health <lb/>to all the Pleaſures of Senſe and <lb/>the neceſſary Hurry of Buſineſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I likewiſe found it advantageous <lb/>to me not to abandon my ſelf to
          <lb/>Melancholy, by baniſhing out of my <lb/>Mind whatever might occaſion it: I <pb n="17"/>
          <lb/>made uſe of all the Powers of my <lb/>Reaſon to reſtrain the force of <lb/>thoſe
          Paſſions, whoſe Violence <lb/>does often break the Conſtitution <lb/>of the ſtrongeſt
          Bodies. 'Tis true <lb/>indeed, that I was not always ſo <lb/>much a Philoſopher, nor yet
          ſo Cau- <lb/>tious, but that ſometimes I fell <lb/>into thoſe Diſorders that I would
          <lb/>have avoided; but this rarely hap- <lb/>pen'd, and the Guard I kept over <lb/>my
          Appetite, which ought chiefly <lb/>to be minded, prevented all the <lb/>pernicious
          Conſequences which <lb/>might have ariſen from my petty <lb/>Irregularities. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This is certain, that the Paſſions <lb/>have leſs Influence, and cauſe leſs
          <lb/>Diſorder in a Body that is regular <lb/>in its Diet, than in another which <lb/>gives
          the looſe to the Cravings of <lb/>an inordinate Appetite. <hi rend="italic">Galen</hi>
          made <lb/>this Obſervation before me; and <lb/>I might produce ſeveral Authorities <lb/>to
          ſupport this Opinion, but I will <pb n="18"/>
          <lb/>go only upon mine own Experience. <lb/>It was impoſſible for me ſometimes <lb/>to
          abſtain from the Extreams of <lb/>Hot and Cold, and to get an en- <lb/>tire Maſtery over
          all the Occaſions <lb/>of Trouble which had cros'd my <lb/>whole Life; but yet theſe Emo-
          <lb/>tions made no alteration in the <lb/>State of my Health: And I met <lb/>with a great
          many Inſtances of <lb/>Perſons who ſunk under a leſs <lb/>Weight, both of Body and Mind. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>There was in our Family a con- <lb/>ſiderable Suit of Law depending <lb/>againſt ſome
          Perſons, whoſe Might <lb/>overcame our Right. One of my <lb/>Brothers, and ſome of my
          Relati- <lb/>ons, who having never ſmarted for <lb/>their Debauches, were the more free
          <lb/>to indulge them, could not conquer <lb/>that Concern which the Loſs of this <lb/>Suit
          of Law wrought in them, <lb/>and perfectly died of Grief. I was <lb/>as ſenſible as they
          were, of the In- <lb/>juſtice that was done us, but I did <pb n="19"/>
          <lb/>not die for it; and I attribute <lb/>their Loſs and my Welfare to the <lb/>Difference
          in our way of Living. <lb/>I was made amends for that Diſ- <lb/>grace by the Comfort I had
          of not <lb/>ſinking under it; and now make no <lb/>manner of Doubt, but that the Paſ-
          <lb/>ſions are leſs violent in a Man that <lb/>lives ſoberly, than in one that does
          <lb/>not. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>At ſeventy Years of Age I had <lb/>another Experiment of the Uſeful- <lb/>neſs of my
          Regimen. A Buſineſs <lb/>of an extraordinary Conſequence <lb/>drawing me into the Country,
          my <lb/>Coach-Horſes went faſter than I <lb/>would have them; being laſh'd <lb/>with the
          Whip, they got a head <lb/>and ran away with me. I was <lb/>over-thrown, and drag'd a long
          <lb/>way before they could ſtop the <lb/>Horſes. They took me out of the <lb/>Coach, with
          my Head broken, a <lb/>Leg and an Arm out of Joynt, and <lb/>in a word, in a very
          lamentable <pb n="20"/>
          <lb/>Condition. As ſoon as they <lb/>brought me Home again, they <lb/>ſent for the
          Phyſicians, who did <lb/>not expect I could live three <lb/>days to an end: However, they
          <lb/>reſolved upon letting me Blood to <lb/>prevent the coming of a Fever, <lb/>which
          uſually happens in ſuch <lb/>Caſes. I was ſo confident that <lb/>the regular Life which I
          had led, <lb/>had prevented the contracting of <lb/>any ill Humours which I might <lb/>be
          afraid of, that I oppos'd their <lb/>Preſcription. I order'd them to dreſs <lb/>my Head,
          to ſet my Leg and my <lb/>Arm, to rub me with ſome ſpeci- <lb/>fick Oils proper for
          Bruiſes, and <lb/>without any other Remedies I was <lb/>ſoon cured, to the great Aſtoniſh-
          <lb/>ment of the Phyſicians, and of all <lb/>thoſe who knew me. From hence <lb/>I infer,
          that a regular Life is an <lb/>excellent Preſervative againſt all <lb/>Natural Evils, and
          that Intempe- <lb/>rance produces quite contrary Ef- <lb/>fects. </p>
        <pb n="21"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>About four Years ago, I was over- <lb/>perſwaded to do a thing which had <lb/>like to
          have coſt me dear. My <lb/>Relations whom I love, and who <lb/>have a real Tenderneſs for
          me; <lb/>my Friends with whom I was wil- <lb/>ling to comply in any thing that <lb/>was
          reaſonable; laſtly, my Phyſi- <lb/>cians who were look'd upon as <lb/>the Oracles of
          Health, did all <lb/>agree, that I eat too little; <lb/>that the Nouriſhment I took
          <lb/>was not ſufficient for one of <lb/>my Years; that I ought not only <lb/>to ſupport
          Nature, but likewiſe to <lb/>increaſe the Vigour of it by eat- <lb/>ing a little more than
          I did. It <lb/>was in vain for me to repreſent to <lb/>them, that Nature is content with
          <lb/>a little; that this Little having <lb/>preſerved me ſo long in Health, <lb/>Cuſtom
          was become a ſecond Na- <lb/>ture to me: That it was more <lb/>reaſonable, ſince Natural
          Heat <lb/>abates in proportion as one grows <pb n="22"/>
          <lb/>older, that I ſhould likewiſe <lb/>abridge my Allowance in Diet. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>To add the greater force to my <lb/>Opinion, I mentioned to them the <lb/>Proverb
          which ſaith, <hi rend="italic">He that eats <lb/>little, eats much</hi>; that is, if a Man
          <lb/>is willing to live long in the en- <lb/>joyment of his Food, let him live
          <lb/>ſparingly. I likewiſe told them, <lb/>that what One leaves at a Meal <lb/>does one
          more good, than what <lb/>one has already eaten. But all <lb/>this could not prevail upon
          them; <lb/>and being wearied with their Im- <lb/>portunities, I was forced to ſub-
          <lb/>mit. Having thereſore before been <lb/>uſed to take twelve Ounces, in <lb/>Bread,
          Soops, Yolks of Eggs, and <lb/>Meat, I increas'd it to fourteen <lb/>Ounces a Day; and
          drinking <lb/>about fourteen Ounces of Wine, I <lb/>added Two Ounces more, and made
          <lb/>it ſixteen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This Augmentation of Diet <lb/>was ſo prejudicial to me, that as <pb n="23"/>
          <lb/>brisk as I was, I began to be ſad <lb/>and out of Humour; every thing <lb/>offended
          me, and upon the leaſt <lb/>Occaſion I broke out into a Paſ- <lb/>ſion, ſo that a Dog (as
          they ſay) <lb/>would not live with me. At <lb/>twelve days end I was taken <lb/>with a
          violent Fit of the Cho- <lb/>lick, and that followed by a <lb/>continual Fever, which
          torment- <lb/>ed me for Five and thirty days <lb/>together, and for the firſt fif-
          <lb/>teen days put me into ſuch an <lb/>Agony, that it was impoſſible for <lb/>me to take
          a quarter of an hours <lb/>ſleep at a time. There was no oc- <lb/>caſion to ask my Friends
          whether <lb/>they deſpair'd of my Life, and <lb/>whether they repented of the ad-
          <lb/>vice they had given me; for they <lb/>ſeveral times believed that I was <lb/>a dying
          Man, juſt giving up the <lb/>Ghoſt. However, I recovered, <lb/>tho' I was ſeventy eight
          Years of <lb/>Age, and tho' we had a harder Win- <pb n="24"/>
          <lb/>ter than is uſual in our Cli- <lb/>mate. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Nothing freed me from this <lb/>Danger, but the Regimen which I <lb/>had ſo long
          obſerv'd. It had pre- <lb/>vented me from contracting thoſe <lb/>ill Humours, with which
          they are <lb/>troubled in their old Age, who are <lb/>not ſo wife as to take care of
          <lb/>themſelves whilſt they are Young. <lb/>I did not perceive in me the old <lb/>Leaven
          of thoſe Humours, and <lb/>having nothing to ſtruggle with <lb/>but the new ones, which
          were oc- <lb/>caſioned by this ſmall Addition to <lb/>my Diet, I oppoſed and conquer'd
          <lb/>my Indiſpoſition, notwithſtanding <lb/>its force. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>From this Sickneſs, and my Re- <lb/>covery from it, we may diſcern, what <lb/>an
          Influence a Regimen has over <lb/>us, which preſerv'd me from <lb/>Death, and what a Power
          Reple- <lb/>tion has, which in ſo few days <lb/>brought me to the laſt Extremity. <pb
            n="25"/>
          <lb/>'Tis probable that Order being <lb/>neceſſary for the Conſervation of <lb/>the
          Univerſe, and our Bodily Life <lb/>being nothing elſe but a Harmony <lb/>and perfect
          Agreement between the <lb/>Elementary Qualities of which our <lb/>Bodies are compos'd, we
          cannot <lb/>live long in a diſorderly Courſe of <lb/>Life, of which nothing but Cor-
          <lb/>ruption can poſſibly come. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Order indeed is ſo exceeding Be- <lb/>neficial, that it cannot be too ſtrictly
          <lb/>obſerved in every thing. 'Tis by the <lb/>Means of this that we arrive to the
          <lb/>perfection of Arts, and an eaſy accom- <lb/>pliſhment in the Sciences. It renders
          <lb/>Armies Victorious, keeps up the Ci- <lb/>vil Policy of Cities, and Concord in
          <lb/>Families: It renders whole Nations <lb/>flouriſhing; in a word, it is the
          <lb/>ſupport and preſerver both of the <lb/>Civil and Natural Life; and the <lb/>beſt
          remedy that can be applied to <lb/>all Evils, whether Publick or Pri- <lb/>vate. </p>
        <pb n="26"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When a diſintereſted Phyſician <lb/>waits upon a Patient, let him re- <lb/>member to
          recommend to him his <lb/>Diet, and eſpecially a Regimen <lb/>therein in order to his
          Recovery. <lb/>This is certain, that if all Men <lb/>would live regularly and frugally,
          <lb/>there would be ſo few ſick Perſons, <lb/>that there would hardly be any oc-
          <lb/>caſion for Remedies; ev'ry one would <lb/>become his own <hi rend="italic"
            >Phyſician</hi>, and would <lb/>be convinced that he could never <lb/>meet with a
          better. It would be to <lb/>little purpoſe to ſtudy the Conſti- <lb/>tution of other Men;
          every one, if <lb/>he would but apply himſelf to it, <lb/>would always be better
          acquainted <lb/>with his own, than with that of <lb/>another; every one would be ca-
          <lb/>pable of making thoſe Experiments <lb/>for himſelf, which another could <lb/>not do
          for him, and would be the <lb/>beſt judge of the ſtrength of his <lb/>own Stomach, and the
          Food <lb/>which is agreeable thereto; for in <pb n="27"/>
          <lb/>one word, 'tis next to impoſſible to <lb/>know exactly the Conſtitution of
          <lb/>another, the Conſtitutions of Men <lb/>being as different from one another <lb/>as
          their Complexions. Who now for <lb/>inſtance, would imagine that Old <lb/>Wine ſhould be
          hurtful, and New <lb/>Wine wholeſome to me? That <lb/>things which are looked upon to be
          <lb/>hot by Nature ſhould refreſh and <lb/>ſtrengthen me? What Phyſician <lb/>could have
          obſerved in me thoſe <lb/>Effects, ſo uncommon in moſt Bo- <lb/>dies, and ſo contrary to
          the Notions <lb/>of Mankind, when I my ſelf was at <lb/>no ſmall pains in diſcovering the
          <lb/>Cauſes thereof after abundance of <lb/>Trials, which prove the difference of
          <lb/>Mens Conſtitutions? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Since no Man therefore can have <lb/>a better Phyſician than himſelf, nor <lb/>a more
          Sovereign Antidote than a <lb/>Regimen, every one ought to fol- <lb/>ow my Example; that
          is, to ſtudy <lb/>his own Conſtitution, and to Re- <pb n="28"/>
          <lb/>gulate his Life according to the <lb/>Rules of right Reaſon. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I own indeed that a Phyſician <lb/>may be ſometimes neceſſary; ſince <lb/>there are
          ſome Diſtempers which <lb/>all human Prudence cannot provide <lb/>againſt. There happen
          ſome un- <lb/>avoidable Accidents, which ſeiſe us <lb/>after ſuch a manner as to deprive
          <lb/>our Judgment of the Liberty it <lb/>ought to have to be a comfort to us. <lb/>It is
          fooliſhneſs then wholly to rely <lb/>upon Nature, it muſt have a ſup- <lb/>ply, and
          recourſe muſt be had to <lb/>ſome one or other for it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If the preſence of a <hi rend="italic">Friend</hi> who <lb/>comes <hi rend="italic"
            >to viſit a ſick Perſon</hi> and to teſti- <lb/>fie the Concern he has for his Illneſs,
          <lb/>be a Comfort and Refreſhment to <lb/>him; there is greater reaſon to be- <lb/>lieve
          that the Viſit of a Phyſician <lb/>muſt needs be more agreeable, being <lb/>a Friend upon
          whoſe Advice and <lb/>Care we may depend for a ſpeedy <lb/>Recovery of our Health; but for
            <pb n="29"/>
          <lb/>the Maintaining of that Health <lb/>there needs no other ſupport but a <lb/>Sober and
          Regular Life. 'Tis a <lb/>Speciſick and Natural Medicine, <lb/>which preſerves the Man,
          how ten- <lb/>der ſoever his Conſtitution be, and <lb/>prolongs his Life to above a Hun-
          <lb/>dred Years, ſpares him the Pain <lb/>of a violent Death, ſends him <lb/>quietly out
          of the World, when the <lb/>Radical Moiſture is quite ſpent, <lb/>and which, in ſhort, has
          all the <lb/>Properties that are fancied to be in <lb/><hi rend="italic">Aurum
            Potabile</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic">Elixir</hi> which <lb/>a great many Perſons
          have ſought <lb/>after in vain. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But alas! moſt Men ſuffer them- <lb/>ſelves to be ſeduced by the Charms <lb/>of a
          Voluptuous Life. They have <lb/>not courage enough to deny their <lb/>Appetites; and being
          over-ſwayed <lb/>by their prejudices ſo far, as to <lb/>think they cannot prevent the gra-
          <lb/>tification of them without abridg- <lb/>ing too much of their Pleaſures, <pb n="30"/>
          <lb/>they form Syſtems whereby to per- <lb/>ſuade themſelves, that it is more
          <lb/>eligible to live Ten Years leſs, than <lb/>to be upon the Reſtraint, and de-
          <lb/>prived of whatever may gratifie <lb/>the Cravings of their Appetites. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Alas! They know not the value <lb/>of Ten Years Healthful Life in an <lb/>Age when a
          Man may enjoy the <lb/>full uſe of his Reaſon and make an <lb/>advantage of all his
          Experiences: <lb/>In an Age wherein a Man may ap- <lb/>pear to be truly ſuch by his Wiſdom
          <lb/>and Conduct; laſtly, in a time <lb/>wherein he is in a condition of reap- <lb/>ing
          the fruits of his Studies and La- <lb/>bours. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>To inſtance only in the Sciences; <lb/>it is certain, that the beſt Books <lb/>which
          we have extant, were com- <lb/>poſed in thoſe laſt Ten Years which <lb/>the Intemperate
          deſpiſe; and that <lb/>Men's Minds growing to perfection <lb/>proportionably as their
          Bodies grow <lb/>old, Arts and Sciences would have <pb n="31"/>
          <lb/>loſt a great deal of their Perfection, <lb/>if all the Great Men who were
          <lb/>Profeſſors of them had lived Ten <lb/>Years ſhorter than they did. For <lb/>my part,
          I think it proper to <lb/>keep the fatal day of my Death as <lb/>far off as I can. If this
          had <lb/>not been my reſolution, I ſhould <lb/>not have finiſhed ſeveral Pieces,
          <lb/>which will be both pleaſing and <lb/>inſtructing to thoſe who come after <lb/>me. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Senſualiſts farther Object, <lb/>That it is impoſſible to live a Regu- <lb/>lar
          Life. To this I Reply; That <lb/><hi rend="italic">Galen</hi>, who was ſo Great a Man,
          <lb/>made choice of it, and adviſed <lb/>others to do the ſame, as being the <lb/>beſt
          Courſe they could take. <hi rend="italic">Plato</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cicero</hi>,
            <hi rend="italic">Iſocrates</hi>, and a great many <lb/>Famous Men of paſt Ages embra-
          <lb/>ced it; and in our Times, Pope <lb/><hi rend="italic">Paul Farneze</hi>, Cardinal <hi
            rend="italic">Bembo</hi>, and <lb/>Two of our Doges, <hi rend="italic">Lando</hi> and
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Donato</hi>, have practiſed it, and <pb n="32"/>
          <lb/>thereby arrived to an extreme Old <lb/>Age. I might inſtance in others <lb/>of a
          meaner Extract; but, having <lb/>followed this Rule my ſelf, I think <lb/>I cannot produce
          a more convincing <lb/>proof of its being practicable, and <lb/>that the greateſt trouble
          to be met <lb/>with therein is the firſt reſolving <lb/>and entring upon ſuch a Courſe
          <lb/>of Life. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>You will tell me that <hi rend="italic">Plato</hi>, as <lb/>Sober a Man as he was,
          yet affirm- <lb/>ed, That a Man devoted to the <lb/>Adminiſtration of the Government
          <lb/>in publick Affairs, can hardly lead <lb/>an Exact and Regular Life, being <lb/>often
          obliged in the Service of the <lb/>State, to be expoſed to the Badneſs <lb/>or Weather, to
          the Fatigues of <lb/>Travelling, and to Eat whatever <lb/>he can meet with. This cannot be
          <lb/>denied; but then I maintain, That <lb/>theſe things will never haſten a <lb/>Man's
          Death, provided he that is <lb/>in this Poſt, accuſtoms himſelf to a <pb n="33"/>
          <lb/>frugal way of Living. There is <lb/>no Man, in what condition ſo- <lb/>ever he is,
          but may prevent his <lb/>Over-eating; and cure himſelf of <lb/>thoſe Diſtempers that are
          cauſed by <lb/>Repletion. They who have the <lb/>charge of publick Affairs commit-
          <lb/>ted to their Truſt are more obliged <lb/>to it than any others: Where there is
          <lb/>no Glory to be got for their Coun- <lb/>try, they ought not to Sacrifice
          <lb/>themſelves: They ſhould preſerve <lb/>themſelves to ſerve it, and if they <lb/>purſue
          my Method, it is certain <lb/>they would ward off the Diſtem- <lb/>pers which Heat, and
          Cold, and <lb/>Fatigues might bring upon them; <lb/>or ſhould they be diſturbed with
          <lb/>them, it would be but very lightly. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It may likewiſe be Objected, <lb/>That if one who is Well is Dieted <lb/>like one
          that is Sick, he will be at a <lb/>loſs about the choice of his Diet <lb/>when any
          Diſtemper comes upon <pb n="34"/>
          <lb/>him. To this I ſay, That Nature <lb/>which preſerves all Beings as far as
          <lb/>poſſible, teaches us how we ought <lb/>to govern our ſelves in ſuch a caſe. <lb/>It
          begins by depriving us altogether <lb/>of our Appetite, that we can Eat <lb/>little or
          nothing at all. At that <lb/>time, whether the Sick Perſon has <lb/>been Sober or
          Intemperate, no <lb/>other Food ought to be made uſe of, <lb/>but ſuch as is proper for
          the con- <lb/>dition wherein he is; ſuch as Broth, <lb/>Jellies, Cordials, Barley-Water,
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">&amp;c</hi>. When his Recovery will per- <lb/>mit him to make uſe
          of a more ſolid <lb/>Nouriſhment, he muſt take leſs <lb/>than he was uſed to before his
          Sick- <lb/>neſs, and notwithſtanding the ea- <lb/>gerneſs of his Appetite, he muſt
          <lb/>take care of his Stomach till he has <lb/>a perfect Cure. Should he do o-
          <lb/>therwiſe, he would overburden Na- <lb/>ture,and infallibly relapſe into the
          <lb/>danger from whence he eſcaped. <lb/>But notwithſtanding this I dare to <pb n="35"/>
          <lb/>aver, That he who leads a Sober <lb/>and Regular Life will hardly ever <lb/>be Sick;
          or if he is, it will be but <lb/>ſeldom, and for a ſhort time. This <lb/>way of Living
          preſerves us from <lb/>thoſe Humours which occaſion our <lb/>Infirmities, and by
          conſequence <lb/>heals us of all thoſe Diſtempers <lb/>which they engender. The defect
          <lb/>of the Cauſe does Phyſically pre- <lb/>vent the production of the Effect, <lb/>and
          the Effect cannot be dangerous <lb/>and violent, when the Cauſe it ſelf <lb/>is but ſlight
          and weak. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Since then Sobriety lays a re- <lb/>ſtraint upon our Paſſions, preſerves <lb/>our
          Health, and is both Wholſome <lb/>and Beneficial to us, ought it not <lb/>to be followed
          and embraced by all <lb/>Men? Self-love if well underſtood <lb/>adviſes us to it: It is
          neither im- <lb/>poſſible nor difficult, and the me- <lb/>thod I take ought to diſcourage
          no <lb/>body from undertaking it. For I <lb/>do not pretend to perſuade every <pb n="36"/>
          <lb/>body to Eat as little as I do, or to <lb/>debar themſelves from the uſe of a
          <lb/>great many things from which I <lb/>refrain. I Eat but little, becauſe <lb/>my
          Stomach is nice, and I abſtain <lb/>from certain Diſhes becauſe they <lb/>are prejudicial
          to me. They who <lb/>are not offended by them, are not <lb/>obliged to refrain from them,
          but <lb/>are allowed the uſe of them; only <lb/>they ought to abſtain from eating <lb/>too
          much even of that which agrees <lb/>with them, becauſe it would be pre- <lb/>judicial to
          them, ſince an overcharg'd <lb/>Stomach cannot ſo eaſily digeſt it. In <lb/>ſhort, he that
          is offended at nothing <lb/>has no occaſion of enquiring into <lb/>the Quality of his
          Diet, he ought <lb/>only to be cautious of the Quantity <lb/>thereof. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It ſignifies nothing to tell me, <lb/>That there are ſeveral who denying
          <lb/>themſelves nothing, do yet live as <lb/>long without Infirmities, as they <pb n="37"/>
          <lb/>who are Sober. This is but rare, <lb/>uncertain, hazardous, and in a <lb/>manner
          Miraculous. The inſtan- <lb/>ces of this nature do not at all juſti- <lb/>fie the Conduct
          of thoſe Perſons, <lb/>who reckon it an extraordinary <lb/>Happineſs, and are commonly the
          <lb/>Betrayers of their good Conſtituti- <lb/>on. It is more certain, that an infirm
          <lb/>Old Man will live longer by obſer- <lb/>ving a ſtrict Regimen, than a <lb/>Young,
          Vigorous, and Healthful <lb/>Man will, that gives the looſe to <lb/>his Appetite. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>However, this is certain, That a <lb/>good Conſtitution, with the ſupport <lb/>of a
          Regular Life, will carry a Man <lb/>farther than a weak one, though <lb/>managed with an
          equal degree of <lb/>Care. God and Nature may form <lb/>bodies ſo ſtrong and robuſt, as to
          <lb/>be proof againſt all that is contrary <lb/>to us; as I have obſerved at <hi
            rend="italic">Venice</hi>
          <lb/>the Procurator <hi rend="italic">Thomas Matarini</hi>, <lb/>and at <hi rend="italic"
            >Padua</hi> the Chevalier <hi rend="italic">Antonio <pb n="38"/>
            <lb/>Capo di Vacca</hi>; but among a thou- <lb/>ſand one ſhall hardly meet with the
          <lb/>like. All others who are for a <lb/>Long and Healthful Life, who <lb/>would Die
          without an Agony and <lb/>only by a pure Diſſolution, who <lb/>would, laſtly, enjoy the
          Advanta- <lb/>ges of a happy Old Age, will ne- <lb/>ver come to what they aim at, with-
          <lb/>out Sobriety. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>'Tis Temperance alone which <lb/>ſupports our Conſtitution without <lb/>any
          Alteration; it creates nothing <lb/>but ſweet and wholſome Humours, <lb/>which ſending up
          no Vapours to <lb/>the Brain, leave the Mind in the <lb/>perfect uſe of the Organs, and
          are <lb/>no hindrance from raiſing its Con- <lb/>templation from the Wonders of <lb/>the
          World, to the Conſideration of <lb/>the Power of its Creator. A Man <lb/>can be never the
          better for thoſe <lb/>Reflections, when his Head is full <lb/>of the Vapours of Wine and
          Meat. <pb n="39"/>
          <lb/>But when once theſe Fumes are <lb/>gone, his Underſtanding is clear, <lb/>he obſerves
          and diſcerns a thouſand <lb/>agreeable things, which he would <lb/>not have known or
          comprehended <lb/>in another State. He can then di- <lb/>ſcern the falſity of thoſe
          pleaſures <lb/>which Voluptuouſneſs promiſes, <lb/>the Real Goods with which Vertue
          <lb/>loads us, and the Unhappineſs of <lb/>thoſe whom a fatal deluſion renders <lb/>Slaves
          to their Paſſions. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The three moſt dangerous are <lb/>the Pleaſure of the Taſte, the <lb/>hunting after
          Honours, and the <lb/>poſſeſſion of Riches. Theſe De- <lb/>ſires increaſe with the Age of
          <lb/>Old Men, who having always led <lb/>a diſorderly Life, have ſuffer'd their <lb/>Luſts
          to take Root in their Youth <lb/>and Manhood. A Wiſe Man does <lb/>not ſtay ſo long before
          he corrects <lb/>them; he declares betimes a War <lb/>againſt his Paſſions, of which he
            <pb n="40"/>
          <lb/>does not obtain the Maſtery till <lb/>after ſeveral ſtruggles, and then <lb/>Vertue
          in its turn Triumphs, and <lb/>crowns the Man with the Bleſſings <lb/>of Heaven and the
          Eſteem of all <lb/>the World. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Is he ready to pay the Tribute <lb/>that is due to Nature? Full of ac-
          <lb/>knowledgments for the favours al- <lb/>ready received from God, he throws
          <lb/>himſelf into the Arms of his future <lb/>Mercy. He is not afraid of thoſe
          <lb/>Everlaſting Puniſhments, which <lb/>they deſerve, who by their Intem- <lb/>perance
          offer violence to their own <lb/>Lives. He dies without complain- <lb/>ing, becauſe he was
          not to live for <lb/>ever; and his Reaſon ſweetens the <lb/>Bitterneſs of this Fatality:
          In a <lb/>word, he leaves the world gene- <lb/>rouſly, when in a long tract of <lb/>Happy
          years he has had time e- <lb/>nough to enjoy his Vertue and Re- <lb/>putation, and
          conſiders that not <pb n="41"/>
          <lb/>one in a thouſand who have lived <lb/>otherwiſe than he has done, has ar- <lb/>rived
          to ſuch an Age. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>He is comforted the more upon <lb/>conſidering that this Separation will <lb/>not be
          violent, painful or feveriſh. <lb/>His End is Calm, and he expires <lb/>like a Lamp when
          the Oil is ſpent, <lb/>no Delirium, no Convulſions attend- <lb/>ing him; and ſo he paſſes
          from this <lb/>Corruptible Life to that whoſe <lb/>Eternal Happineſs is the Reward of
          <lb/>the Virtuous. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>O Happy, bleſſed, and regular <lb/>Life, how worthy art thou of our <lb/>Eſteem, and
          how doſt thou deſerve <lb/>to be preferr'd before thy Contrary? <lb/>We need only reflect
          upon the dif- <lb/>ferent Effects of both to be ſenſible <lb/>of the Advantages that
          attend thee, <lb/>tho' thy name alone is ſufficient to <lb/>attract that Eſteem which thou
          De- <lb/>ſerveſt. </p>
        <pb n="42"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Having thus given the Reaſons <lb/>which made me abandon an Intem- <lb/>perate and
          take up with a ſober Life <lb/>as alſo the Method I obſerved in it, <lb/>and the Benefit
          which I reap'd from <lb/>it, and the Advantage which others <lb/>may receive from the
          practice there- <lb/>of, I ſhall now direct my Diſcourſe <lb/>to thoſe who ſuppoſe it to
          be no <lb/>benefit to grow Old, becauſe they <lb/>fancy that when a Man is paſt ſe-
          <lb/>venty his Life is nothing but Weak- <lb/>neſs, Infirmity and Miſery. In <lb/>the
          firſt place, I can aſſure them that <lb/>they are mightily miſtaken, and that <lb/>I find
          my ſelf, as Old as I am, <lb/>which is much beyond what they <lb/>ſpeak of, to be in the
          moſt pleaſant <lb/>and delightſom Stage of Life. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>To prove that I have reaſon for <lb/>what I ſay, they need only enquire <lb/>how I
          ſpend my time, what are my <lb/>uſual Pleaſures and Buſineſs, and <lb/>to hear the
          Teſtimony of all thoſe <pb n="43"/>
          <lb/>that know me. They will unani- <lb/>mouſly teſtifie that the Life I lead <lb/>is not
          a dead and languiſhing Life, <lb/>but as happy an one as can be <lb/>wiſh'd for in this
          World. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>They will tell you that I am <lb/>ſtill ſo ſtrong at fourſcore and three, <lb/>as to
          mount a Horſe without any <lb/>Help: That I can not only go <lb/>down Stairs without any
          concern, <lb/>but likewiſe deſcend a Hill all on <lb/>foot: That I am always merry,
          <lb/>always pleaſed, always in humour, <lb/>maintaining a happy peace in my <lb/>own Mind,
          the ſweetneſs and ſere- <lb/>nity whereof appear at all times in <lb/>my Countenance. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Beſides, they know that 'tis in <lb/>my Power to paſs away the time <lb/>very
          pleaſantly, having nothing to <lb/>hinder me from taſting all the plea- <lb/>ſures of an
          agreeable Society with <lb/>ſeveral perſons of parts and worth. <lb/>When I am willing to
          be alone, I <pb n="44"/>
          <lb/>read good Books, and ſometimes <lb/>fall to Writing, ſeeking always an <lb/>occaſion
          of being uſeful to the pub- <lb/>lick, and doing ſervice to private <lb/>perſons as far as
          poſſible. I do all <lb/>this without the leaſt trouble; and in <lb/>ſuch times as I ſet
          apart for theſe <lb/>Employments. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I dwell in a Houſe, which beſides <lb/>its being ſituated in the pleaſanteſt
          <lb/>part of <hi rend="italic">Padua</hi>, may be look'd upon <lb/>as the moſt convenient
          and moſt <lb/>agreeable Manſion of that City. I <lb/>there make me Apartments proper
          <lb/>for the Winter and Summer, which <lb/>ſerve as a ſhelter to defend me from <lb/>the
          Extreme Heat of the One, and <lb/>the Rigid Coldneſs of the other. <lb/>I walk out in my
          Gardens along <lb/>my Canals and Walks, where I <lb/>always meet with ſome little thing
          <lb/>or other to do, which at the ſame <lb/>time employs and diverts me. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I ſpend the Months of <hi rend="italic">April</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">May</hi>,
            <hi rend="italic">September</hi> and <hi rend="italic">October</hi> at my <pb n="45"/>
          <lb/>Country-Houſe, which is in the <lb/>fineſt Situation imaginable. The <lb/>Air of it
          is Good, the Avenues <lb/>Neat, the Gardens magnificent, <lb/>the Waters clear and
          plentiful; <lb/>and this Seat may well paſs for <lb/>an inchanted Palace. When I am
          <lb/>there, I ſometimes divert my ſelf <lb/>with a ſport that agrees moſt with <lb/>my Age
            <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> in going out with <lb/>a ſetting Dog or with Terriers. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Sometimes I take a walk to my <lb/><hi rend="italic">Villa</hi>, all whoſe Streets
          terminate <lb/>at a large Square, in the midſt of <lb/>which is a pretty neat Church, and
          <lb/>large enough for the bigneſs of <lb/>the Pariſh. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Through this <hi rend="italic">Villa</hi> runs a Rivu- <lb/>let, and the Country
          about is enrich'd <lb/>with fruitful and well cultivated <lb/>Fields, having at preſent a
          con- <lb/>ſiderable number of Inhabitants. <lb/>This was not ſo anciently; it was a
          <lb/>Marſhy Place, and the Air ſo bad, <pb n="46"/>
          <lb/>that it was more proper for Frogs <lb/>and Toads, than for Men to dwell <lb/>in. I
          thought it adviſable to drain the <lb/>the Mariſh-Lands, ſo that being dry, the <lb/>Air
          became more wholeſome: Seve- <lb/>ral Families have ſettled there and <lb/>rendred the
          place very populous, <lb/>where I may ſay that I have dedi- <lb/>cated to the Lord a
          Church, Altars, <lb/>and Hearts to Worſhip him; which <lb/>Reflection is a great Comfort
          to me <lb/>as often as I make it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Sometimes I pay a Viſit to my <lb/>Friends, of the Neighbouring <lb/>Towns, who
          procure me an ac- <lb/>quaintance with the Ingenious <lb/>Men of the place. I diſcourſe
          <lb/>with them about Architecture, <lb/>Painting, Sculpture, Mathematicks <lb/>and
          Agriculture; Sciences for <lb/>which I had all my Life long a <lb/>great fondneſs, and the
          rather, be- <lb/>cauſe they were very much in <lb/>eſteem in my Time. </p>
        <pb n="47"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I ſee with Curioſity the new <lb/>pieces of Workmanſhip; and it <lb/>was a new
          Pleaſure to me to take a <lb/>ſecond View of thoſe which I had <lb/>already ſeen; and I am
          always learn- <lb/>ing ſomething that I am pleaſed to <lb/>know. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>I viſit publick Buildings, Palaces, <lb/>Gardens, Antiquities, Squares,
          <lb/>Churches, and Fortifications, paſ- <lb/>ſing by no place that may gratifie <lb/>my
          Curioſity, or give me any new <lb/>Light into things. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/> That which charm'd me moſt <lb/>in the little Journeys I took, was <lb/>the Various
          Proſpects of Pla- <lb/>ces through which I went. The <lb/>Plains, the Hills, the Rivulets,
          <lb/>the Caſtles and the Villages, were <lb/>as ſo many Objects that offer'd
          <lb/>themſelves with pleaſure to my <lb/>Sight; and afforded a delightful <lb/>View. </p>
        <pb n="48"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In ſhort, the Pleaſures I take <lb/>are not imperfect upon the account <lb/>of the
          Weakneſs of my Organs. <lb/>I ſee and hear as well as ever I did <lb/>in my Life: All my
          Senſes are as <lb/>free and as perfect as ever, eſpeci- <lb/>ally my Taſte, which is
          better with <lb/>that little which I eat at preſent, <lb/>than when I was a Slave to my
          <lb/>Appetite. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Changing of Beds is no hinder- <lb/>ance to my repoſe, I ſleep very <lb/>ſoundly; and
          if I Dream, my <lb/>Dreams are pleaſant. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>'Tis with a great deal of ſatiſ- <lb/>faction that I ſee the End of a <lb/>Work of
          ſuch Importance to this <lb/>State, which has rendred ſo many <lb/>places fertile, that
          before were un- <lb/>cultivated and uſeleſs; a thing I <lb/>never expected to have ſeen
          com- <lb/>pleated, conſidering how many <lb/>States are loth to begin and wea- <lb/>ry of
          carrying on Undertakings of <lb/>ſo vaſt a Charge and ſo Difficult to <pb n="49"/>
          <lb/>be perform'd. I was upon the <lb/>places for two Months together <lb/>with the
          Commiſſaries that had <lb/>the overſight of theſe works, and <lb/>this during the greateſt
          Heat of <lb/>Summer; and yet, thanks to <lb/>my Regimen, the only preſerver <lb/>of my
          Health, neither the un- <lb/>wholeſome Air of the Fens, <lb/>nor the Fatigue did me any
          Injury. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Such as theſe are the Employ- <lb/>ments and Diverſions of my Old <lb/>Age, which is,
          bleſſed be God, <lb/>free from thoſe diſturbances of <lb/>Mind and Infirmities of Body,
          <lb/>under which ſo many poor Rheu- <lb/>matick and crazy Old Men, as <lb/>well as
          miſerable young Men la- <lb/>bour. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If in diſcourſing on ſuch a ſeri- <lb/>ous Subject as this, it be allowable <lb/>to
          ſpeak of Trifles, I might tell <lb/>you that at the Age of fourſcore <lb/>and three, a
          ſober Life had pre- <pb n="50"/>
          <lb/>ſerv'd me in that Sprightlineſs of <lb/>Thought, and Gaiety of Humour, as <lb/>to be
          able to compoſe a Play for the <lb/>uſe of the Stage, which was divert- <lb/>ing without
          ſhocking the Audience. <lb/>Comedy is uſually the product of <lb/>Youth, as Tragedy is of
          old Age, <lb/>The latter by the Gravity of its <lb/>compoſure ſuiting to Riper Years,
          <lb/>whilſt the former by its facetiouſ- <lb/>neſs is more agreeable to thoſe that
          <lb/>are Young. If Antiquity has ſo <lb/>far commended and admired a <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Greek</hi> Poet, for having in the ſe- <lb/>venty third Year of his Age
          com- <lb/>pos'd a Tragedy, which is a grave <lb/>and ſerious Poem, why ſhould I be
          <lb/>leſs admir'd and happy in having <lb/>compos'd a Comedy, which is di- <lb/>verting at
          my Age? For this I am <lb/>ſure of, that tho' that Author was <lb/>ten Years younger than
          I am, yet <lb/>he had not more health, nor a <lb/>brisker Genius. </p>
        <pb n="51"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>To conclude, as an Addition to <lb/>my Happineſs, I ſee my ſelf as it <lb/>were
          immortalized, and born a- <lb/>gain by the great Number of my <lb/>Deſcendants. I meet
          with not on- <lb/>ly two or three when I come home, <lb/>but eleven Grand-children, the
          <lb/>Eldeſt of which is Eighteen, and <lb/>the Youngeſt two Years Old, all <lb/>born of
          the ſame Father, and the <lb/>ſame Mother; all healthful, of good <lb/>parts, and of
          promiſing hopes. <lb/>I take a delight in playing with the <lb/>Youngſters; Children
          between <lb/>three and five Years of Age being <lb/>generally very merry and diverting
          <lb/>Company. Thoſe who are older <lb/>entertain me better: I often make <lb/>them ſing
          and play upon Muſi- <lb/>cal Inſtruments, and ſometimes I <lb/><unclear>joyn</unclear> in
          Conſort with them. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Call you this an infirm and crazy <lb/>Old Age, as they pretend, who ſay <lb/>that a
          Man is but half alive after <lb/>he is ſeventy? They may believe <pb n="52"/>
          <lb/>me if they pleaſe, but in reality I <lb/>would not change my Age and Life <lb/>for
          the moſt flouriſhing Youth <lb/>which lays no Reſtraint upon its <lb/>Senſes, being ſure
          that it is ſubject <lb/>to a great many Diſtempers which <lb/>may occaſion Death. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>I remember all the Follies that I <lb/>was Guilty of in my young Days <lb/>and am
          perfectly ſenſible of the <lb/>Danger and Imprudence of them. <lb/>I know with what
          Violence Young <lb/>Perſons are carri'd away by their Paſ- <lb/>ſions, and how much they
          preſume <lb/>upon their Strength, but would <lb/>think they had taken a ſure Leaſe <lb/>of
          their Life; they expoſe it <unclear>raſh-</unclear>
          <lb/>ly, as if it were chargeable to <unclear>them</unclear>
          <lb/>and they run headlong into <unclear>what-</unclear>
          <lb/>ſoever their Concupiſcence <unclear>prompts</unclear>
          <lb/>them to. They muſt gratifie <unclear>their</unclear>
          <lb/>Appetites whatever it coſts them, <lb/>without perceiving that they
            <unclear>feed</unclear>
          <lb/>thoſe ill Humours which will <unclear>render</unclear>
          <pb n="53"/>
          <lb/>their Lives miſerable, and haſten <lb/>the hour of their Death. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Of theſe two, the one is Cruel; <lb/>the other dreadſul and inſupport- <lb/>able by
          all ſenſual Men, eſpecially <lb/>young people, who ſuppoſe they <lb/>have a better Title
          to Life than <lb/>others, and Libertines who are not <lb/>ſo Blind as to flatter
          themſelves <lb/>that God will permit their ſin to <lb/>go unpuniſh'd. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As for my part, bleſſed be God, <lb/>I find my ſelf freed from thoſe juſt <lb/>fears
          which cannot but Alarm them <lb/>whenever they are capable of Re- <lb/>flexion. For in the
          firſt place I <lb/>am certain that I ſhall not fall Sick, <lb/>ſince I take care by a
          Regular Diet <lb/>to ward off Infirmities. And then <lb/>ſecondly, the Time of my Death
          <lb/>approaching teaches me to ſubmit <lb/>quietly to that which is Inevitable, <lb/>and
          from which no man could ever <lb/>ſecure himſelf. 'Tis folly to be a- <lb/>fraid of that
          which cannot be a- <pb n="54"/>
          <lb/>voided; but I hope whenever the <lb/>Time comes, the Merits of Jeſus <lb/>Chriſt will
          be available to me; and <lb/>tho I am ſenſible that I muſt die, <lb/>yet I am perſwaded it
          will be a <lb/>long time 'ere I ſhall, ſince this <lb/>Diſſolution cannot happen but by
          <lb/>the Conſumption of the Radical <lb/>Moiſture which is exhauſted by <lb/>Age. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Regular Life which I lead <lb/>has left Death this only way of de- <lb/>ſtroying
          me. The Humours of <lb/>my Body can do me more injury <lb/>than the Elementary Qualities
          <lb/>which prevail'd in my Nature ever <lb/>ſince my Birth. I am not ſo ſtupid <lb/>as not
          to perceive, that having had <lb/>a beginning, I muſt of neceſſity <lb/>have an End; but
          ſince we muſt <lb/>die, doubtleſs that Death is attend- <lb/>ed with leſs Terror which
          happens <lb/>by the Natural Diſſolution of the <lb/>parts of which we are compoſed.
          <lb/>Nature her ſelf having tyed the <pb n="55"/>
          <lb/>Bands of our Life, can likewiſe untie <lb/>them again without the leaſt pain,
          <lb/>and can ſtay longer before it executes <lb/>that Office than Sickneſses generally
          <lb/>do, which with Violence break the <lb/>Bands of our Life aſunder, and which
          <lb/>cannot happen to us but by foreign <lb/>Cauſes, ſince nothing is more con- <lb/>trary
          to Nature than that which <lb/>tends to our Deſtruction. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>When a Man draws near his <lb/>End, he perceives his Strength to <lb/>abate by
          Degrees; The Organs <lb/>and all the Faculties grow weak; <lb/>he can no longer Walk, and
          can <lb/>hardly Speak; His Judgment and <lb/>Memory fail him: He becomes <lb/>blind, deaf,
          and bowed together; <lb/>in fine, his whole frame is worn <lb/>out. Bleſſed be God, I am
          not as <lb/>yet in that Condition. On the <lb/>Contrary I promiſe my ſelf, that <lb/>my
          Soul finds its ſelf ſo well in my <lb/>Body, where ſhe meets with no- <pb n="56"/>
          <lb/>thing but Peace, Unity and Con- <lb/>cord (ſpite of all the different <lb/>Qualities
          of the Humours which <lb/>compoſe us, and the various In- <lb/>clinations that are
          produc'd by the <lb/>Senſes) that ſhe will be under no <lb/>temptation to wiſh a ſpeedy
          Sepa- <lb/>ration, and that it will be a long time <lb/>before ſhe can be brought to ſuch
          <lb/>a Reſolution. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>To conclude, I am aſſur'd that <lb/>I ſhall ſtill live ſeveral Years in <lb/>Health,
          and that I ſhall long enjoy <lb/>the pleaſure of being in the World, <lb/>which is
          certainly very comfort- <lb/>able, when a Man knows how to <lb/>make a right uſe of it. I
          hope to <lb/>reap a greater Satisfaction from <lb/>hence in the other Life, and I ſhall
          <lb/>lie under Obligations to the Virtues <lb/>of the Regimen, to which I am <lb/>indebted
          for the Victory I have ob- <lb/>tain'd over my Paſſions. Nor is <lb/>there any Man but
          what may hope <pb n="57"/>
          <lb/>for the ſame Happineſs, if he <lb/>would live as I have done. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>A ſober Life therefore being ſo <lb/>neceſſary, its Name ſo commend- <lb/>able, the
          Enjoyment of it ſo bene- <lb/>ficial, nothing remains after what <lb/>has been ſaid, but
          to conjure all Men <lb/>as they love themſelves to make the <lb/>beſt of life, and lay in
          a ſtock of that, <lb/>which being the moſt precious of <lb/>all, deſerves to be ſought
          after if <lb/>we have it not, and to be preſerved <lb/>if we have it. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>'Tis this Divine Sobriety which <lb/>is always pleaſing to God, and al- <lb/>ways the
          Friend of Nature; ſhe is <lb/>the Daughter of Reaſon, the Siſter <lb/>of all other
          Vertues, the Compa- <lb/>nion of Temperance; always <lb/>Chearſul, always Modeſt, always
          <lb/>Wiſe and Regular in in her Operati- <lb/>ons. She is the Root of Health, <lb/>of
          Induſtry, and of whatever be- <pb n="58"/>
          <lb/>comes a great Soul to be employ'd <lb/>about. She has the Laws of God and
          <lb/>Nature, both to juſtifie and enforce <lb/>her. When ſhe reigns, Repletions<choice>
            <corr>,</corr>
            <sic/>
          </choice> Diſ- <lb/>orders, Evil Habits, Superfluous Hu- <lb/>mours, Fevers, Aches, and
          the fears of <lb/>Death, do not diſreliſh or embitter <lb/>our Pleaſures. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The Happineſs of it ſhould in- <lb/>vite us, the Comelineſs of it ſhould <lb/>allure
          us to embrace it. She offers <lb/>to us the Duration of our mortal <lb/>Being: She is the
          faithful Guardi- <lb/>an of the Life of Man, whether he <lb/>be rich or poor, young or
          old, or of <lb/>what Sex ſoever. She teaches the <lb/>Rich not to abuſe his Wealth, the
          <lb/>poor to bear patiently the Inconve- <lb/>niences of his State; She teaches <lb/>the
          Man Wiſdom, the Woman <lb/>Chaſtity; Old Men the ſecret of <lb/>putting off their Death,
          and Young <lb/>Men the means of enjoying a long <lb/>Life. She files the Ruſt off of our
            <pb n="59"/>
          <lb/>Senſes, renders the Body Vigorous, <lb/>the Mind clear, the Soul lovely; <lb/>gives
          us a Happy Memory, free <lb/>Motions, and juſt Actions. 'Tis <lb/>by it that the Mind
          being diſen- <lb/>gaged from Matter enjoys a larger <lb/>Freedom, and the Blood runs
          <lb/>ſmoothly in our Veins without <lb/>meeting with any Obſtruction in <lb/>its
          Circulation. 'Tis laſtly by it <lb/>that all the Powers both of Soul <lb/>and Body are
          kept up in a perfect <lb/>Union, which nothing but the <lb/>Contrary Vice can diſturb. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>O Sacred and Healthful Sobri- <lb/>ety! The powerful ſupport of our <lb/>Nature! The
          true Phyſick of Body <lb/>and Mind! How ought Men to <lb/>praiſe thee and acknowledge thy
          <lb/>Benefits, ſince thou furniſheſt them <lb/>with the means of attaining Hea- <lb/>ven,
          and of preſerving Life and <lb/>Health here upon Earth! </p>
        <pb n="60"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But not deſigning to enlarge any <lb/>farther in commendation of this <lb/>Vertue, I
          ſhall conclude, keeping <lb/>within the bounds of Sobriety on <lb/>this Subject; not
          becauſe I have ſaid <lb/>enough of it, but that I may ſay <lb/>more of it another time. </p>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="8"> </space>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
      <pb n="61"/>
      <div type="chapter">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>CHAP. II. </head>
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>The Method of Correcting a bad <lb/>Conſtitution. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">S</hi>Everal Perſons, whoſe weak <lb/>Conſtitution requir'd great
          <lb/>Care in the Management of it, <lb/>having been well ſatisfied with <lb/>what I have
          written concerning <lb/>Sobriety, the Experience which <lb/>they have had of
            <unclear>the</unclear> Uſefulneſs of <lb/>my Counſels, and the acknowledg- <lb/>ments
          which they have made there- <lb/>of; encourage me to take up my <lb/>Pen again, that I may
          convince <lb/>thoſe, who meet with no Inconve- <lb/>nience from Intemperance, that
          <lb/>they are in the wrong in relying <lb/>ſo much on the ſtrength of their
          <lb/>Conſtitution. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Let it be never ſo well compos'd, <lb/>yet it holds not good but to ſuch <pb n="62"/>
          <lb/>an Age. Theſe perſons ſeldom <lb/>arrive to Sixty, but they decay all <lb/>of a
          ſudden, and perceive them- <lb/>ſelves loaded with a Complication <lb/>of Diſtempers. Some
          are Gouty, <lb/>Dropſical, and Rheumatical: <lb/>Others are Subject to Cholicks, <lb/>the
          Stone, and Piles; laſtly, to a- <lb/>bundance of Diſtempers which <lb/>would never have
          happened to <lb/>them, if they had been ſo wiſe as <lb/>to have taken care of themſelves
          <lb/>in their Youth. If they die infirm <lb/>at fourſcore Years of Age, they <lb/>might
          have lived in Health to an <lb/>hundred, and ſo have run out the <lb/>Term of Life which
          Nature has <lb/>left open to all Men. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It is to be ſuppoſed that this <lb/>Common Parent wiſhes that all her <lb/>Children
          might live at leaſt a Cen- <lb/>tury; and ſince ſome among them <lb/>have lived to a
          longer date, why <lb/>ſhould not others have a Right <pb n="63"/>
          <lb/>of Expecting the ſame Advan- <lb/>tage? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I do not diſagree but that we <lb/>are ſubject to the Stars which were
          <lb/>predominant at our Birth. Their <lb/>good or bad Aſpects enfeeble or <lb/>ſtrengthen
          the Springs of our Life; <lb/>but Man being endued with Judg- <lb/>ment and Reaſon ought
          to repair <lb/>by his prudent Conduct the harm <lb/>which his Planet may have done
          <lb/>him; he may prolong his Days by the <lb/>means of a ſober Life to as long a
          <lb/>period, as if he had been Born very <lb/>ſtrong and luſty. Prudence pre- <lb/>vents
          and corrects the Malignity of <lb/>the Planets; they give us certain <lb/>inclinations,
          they carry us out to <lb/>certain paſſions; but they lay no <lb/>violence upon us, we may
          reſiſt <lb/>them, and in this ſenſe a Wiſe <lb/>Man is above the Stars. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>I was born very cholerick and <lb/>haſty; I flew out into a paſſion for <pb n="64"/>
          <lb/>the leaſt trifle, I huff'd all Mankind, <lb/>and was ſo intolerable that a great
          <lb/>many Perſons of Repute avoided <lb/>my Company. I apprehended the <lb/>Injury which I
          did my ſelf; I <lb/>knew that Anger is a real Frenzy; <lb/>that it diſturbs our Judgment,
          that <lb/>it tranſports us beyond our ſelves, <lb/>and that the Difference be- <lb/>tween
          a Paſſionate and a Mad <lb/>Man is only this, that the latter <lb/>has loſt his Reaſon for
          ever, and <lb/>the former is only deprived of it <lb/>by Fits. A ſober Life cured me of
          <lb/>this Frenzy; by its Aſſiſtance I be- <lb/>came ſo Moderate and ſo much a <lb/>Maſter
          of my Paſſion, that no <lb/>Body could perceive that it was <lb/>born with me. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>A Man may likewiſe with Rea- <lb/>ſon and a Regular Life correct a <lb/>bad
          Conſtitution, and notwith- <lb/>ſtanding the Tenderneſs thereof <lb/>may live a long time
          in good health. <pb n="65"/>
          <lb/>I ſhould never have ſeen forty <lb/>Years, had I followed all my in- <lb/>clinations,
          and yet I am in the <lb/>Eighty ſixth Year of my Age. If <lb/>the long and dangerous
          Diſtempers <lb/>which I had in my Youth, had not <lb/>conſumed a great deal of the Ra-
          <lb/>dical Moiſture, the loſs of which is <lb/>irreparable, I might have promis'd <lb/>my
          ſelf to have lived a compleat <lb/>Century. But without flattering <lb/>my ſelf, I find it
          to be a great mat- <lb/>ter to have arrived to forty ſix <lb/>Years more than I ever
          expected, <lb/>and that in my Old Age my Con- <lb/>ſtitution is ſtill ſo good, that not
          <lb/>only my Teeth, my Voice, my <lb/>Memory and my Heart are in as <lb/>good a Condition
          as ever they were <lb/>in the briskeſt Days of my Youth; <lb/>but likewiſe my Judgment has
          loſt <lb/>nothing of its clearneſs and force. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>I am of the Opinion that this <lb/>proceeds from the Abridgment I <pb n="66"/>
          <lb/>make of my Food proportionably <lb/>to my growing into Years. Expe- <lb/>rience,
          which tells us that Infants <lb/>have a greater Appetite and are <lb/>more often hungry,
          than grown <lb/>Men, ought likewiſe to teach us, <lb/>that in Old Age we have leſs need
          <lb/>of Nouriſhment than in the begin- <lb/>ning of our Life. A Man who is <lb/>very Old
          can hardly eat, becauſe <lb/>he can ſcarce digeſt what he eats; <lb/>a little ſerves his
          turn, and the <lb/>Yolk of an Egg is a good Meal to <lb/>him. I ſhall be ſatisfied
          therewith <lb/>to the end of my Days, hoping by <lb/>this Conduct neither to dye with
          <lb/>violence nor with pain, not que- <lb/>ſtioning but that they who will <lb/>imitate
          me, will meet with as eaſie <lb/>an Exit, ſince we are all of the <lb/>ſame <hi
            rend="italic">Species</hi>, and made up of the <lb/>ſame Materials. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Since nothing then is more ad- <lb/>vantageous for a Man upon Earth <pb n="67"/>
          <lb/>than to live long; He is Obliged to <lb/>preſerve his Health as far as poſ-
          <lb/>ſible, and this he cannot do with- <lb/>out Sobriety. <choice>
            <corr>'</corr>
            <sic/>
          </choice>Tis true indeed, that <lb/>there are ſeveral who eat and drink <lb/>plentifully,
          and yet live to an hun- <lb/>dred Years of Age. 'Tis by their <lb/>Example that others
          flatter them- <lb/>ſelves with the hopes of attaining <lb/>to the ſame Age, without any
          oc- <lb/>caſion of laying a reſtraint upon <lb/>themſelves. But they are in the <lb/>wrong
          upon theſe two Accounts: <lb/>Firſt becauſe there is hardly one in <lb/>a thouſand, that
          has ſo ſtrong a <lb/>Conſtitution. Secondly, becauſe <lb/>ſuch Men do generally end their
          <lb/>Lives by ſuch Diſtempers as put <lb/>them into great Agonies by dying, <lb/>which
          would never happen to thoſe <lb/>that have the ſame Government of <lb/>themſelves that I
          have. A Man <lb/>runs the Riſque of not attaining to <lb/>fifty Years of Age for not
          daring <lb/>to undertake a Regular Courſe of <pb n="68"/>
          <lb/>Life, which is no impoſſible thing, <lb/>ſince 'tis what I and ſeveral others
          <lb/>have practiſed and do practiſe: <lb/>And a Man becomes inſenſibly a <lb/>Murderer of
          himſelf, becauſe he <lb/>cannot be perſwaded that notwith- <lb/>ſtanding the falſe Charms
          of a <lb/>Voluptuous Life, a Wiſe Man <lb/>ought not to look upon it as any <lb/>hardſhip
          to put in practice what his <lb/>Reaſon adviſes him. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Reaſon, if we hearken to it, <lb/>will tell us that a good Regimen <lb/>is neceſſary
          for the prolonging of <lb/>our days, and that it conſiſts in <lb/>two things: Firſt, in
          taking care of <lb/>the Quality; and Secondly, of the <lb/>Quantity, ſo as to eat and
          drink no- <lb/>thing that offends the Stomach<unclear>,</unclear>
          <lb/>nor any more than what we can <lb/>eaſily digeſt. Our Experience ought <lb/>to be our
          Guide in theſe two Prin- <lb/>ciples, when we are arrived to forty, <lb/>fifty, or
          threeſcore Years of Age. <pb n="69"/>
          <lb/>He who puts in practiſe that Know- <lb/>ledge which he has of what is good <lb/>for
          him, and goes on in a frugal way <lb/>of Living, keeps the Humours in a <lb/>juſt
          Temperature, and prevents <lb/>them from being altered, tho' he <lb/>ſuffer Heat and Cold,
          tho he be fati- <lb/>gued, tho his ſleep be broke, provided <lb/>there be no Exceſs in any
          of them. <lb/>This being ſo, what an Obligation <lb/>does a Man lie under of living ſo-
          <lb/>berly? And ought he not to free <lb/>himſelf from the fears of ſinking <lb/>under the
          leaſt Intemperature of the <lb/>Air, and under the leaſt Fatigue, <lb/>which make us ſick
          upon every <lb/>ſlight occaſion? </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>'Tis true indeed, the moſt ſo- <lb/>ber may ſometimes be indiſpoſed, <lb/>when they
          are unavoidably obliged <lb/>to <choice>
            <corr>tranſgreſs</corr>
            <sic>trangreſs</sic>
          </choice> the Rule which they <lb/>have been uſed to Obſerve; but <lb/>then they are
          certain that their In- <lb/>diſpoſition will not laſt above two <pb n="70"/>
          <lb/>or three days at moſt; nor can they <lb/>fall into a Fever. Wearineſs and
          <lb/>Faintneſs are eaſily remedied by <lb/>Reſt and good Diet. The Malig- <lb/>nancy of
          the Stars cannot put the <lb/>Malignant Humours in a ferment, <lb/>in Bodies which have
          them not: <lb/>Tho' Diſtempers which proceed <lb/>from Intemperance have an Internal
          <lb/>Cauſe, and may be dangerous; <lb/>thoſe which are derived from the <lb/>Influences of
          the Planets, affect us <lb/>only externally, and cannot produce <lb/>any great Diſorders. </p>
        <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="14"/>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="57"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
