<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Byfield: Directions tending to health and long life.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Timothy Byfield</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Directions tending to health and long life, &amp;c</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T27027</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T27027"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for the Author, 1717.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1717</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="32"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108268314</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Health guide"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic size(2.0)">Directions </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="space">Tending to </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(3.0)">HEALTH </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="space">AND </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">Long Life, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </hi>
      </head>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <div type="section">
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">B</hi>EING deſired (by Perſons of Qua- <lb/>lity) to preſcribe ſome
          Rules, in or- <lb/>der to promote <hi rend="italic">Health</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Long
            Life</hi>, <lb/>and not concern my ſelf about the SOUL: <lb/>But write like a meer
          Phiſitian. I readi- <lb/>ly comply'd, thinking it no harder a Task, <lb/>than the
          preſcribing Phyſic-Recipes to the <lb/>Sick. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But, when I ſat down, to attempt the <lb/>Deſign, I ſoon found my Mistake, and
          <lb/>that it was quite of another Nature, a <lb/>very difficult Thing; nay, not to be don,
          <lb/>without breaking the Bar, that was laid <lb/>in my way. So I reſolv'd to lay it
          <lb/>aſide. </p>
        <pb n="2"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But muſing awhile on the Diſappoint- <lb/>ment: It came into my mind, <hi
            rend="italic">that I ought <lb/>to be ready to every good Word and Work</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>I immediately obey'd the <hi rend="italic">Heavenly Di- <lb/>ctate</hi> and reaſſum'd
          my Pen and Ink. And <lb/>determin'd to make this fair Propoſal. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>That, if you will but lend me the in- <lb/>ferior part of the SOUL, with whom to
          <lb/>lodge my <hi rend="italic">Directions</hi>, and who muſt be <lb/>the Charioteer of
          the Body; and at the <lb/>ſame time take care, that the Superior <lb/>part be ſo nobly
          entertain'd with Religion; <lb/>ſo as to be ſatisfy'd; That He does not <lb/>break in, or
          filch upon, our ſober Me- <lb/>thod. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>I'll try, what I can do. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But why! ſo ſhie of a Soul? </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>What! afraid of your ſelf! </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Is not your ſpecific Order of Being a Rank <lb/>of Spirits? </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Only you are of Them, who are ap- <lb/>pointed to Dwell in Earthly Bodies a-
          <lb/>while: During which abode we ſtand re- <lb/>lated to this Kingdom of Matter; But, ſo
          <lb/>ſoon as order'd, obediently to lay them <pb n="3"/>
          <lb/>down and go, and give an Account of what <lb/>we have don in the Body. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>If the Question were put, wherefore did <lb/>God make Man? Who wou'd not be a-
          <lb/>ſham'd <hi rend="italic">SO</hi> to anſwer it: He made him to <lb/>Eat and Drink, and
          take his Pleaſure, to <lb/>gather up Wealth for he knows not who: <lb/>To uſe his
          Invention to become a talk and <lb/>wonder to others; And when He hath fetch't <lb/>a few
          turns upon the <hi rend="italic">Theater</hi>, and enter- <lb/>tain'd the Eyes of
          Beholders, Deſcend — <lb/>and never be heard of more. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But who ſees not, that the Nature of <lb/>Man is Capable of greater Things, than He
          <lb/>can here enjoy? </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The trueſt Notion we can yet have of <lb/>the Primitive Nature as Capacity of Man,
          <lb/>is by beholding it in its gradual Reſtitu- <lb/>tion. — </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>For it is Capable of a <hi rend="italic">Felicity</hi> that ſhall be <lb/>permanent
          and know no end. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But — my Order is, not to Preach — </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But write about <hi rend="italic">Meat, Drink, Airings, <lb/>Tranſpiration, <hi
              rend="roman">&amp;c.</hi></hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>I therefore here again compound, for the <pb n="4"/>
          <lb/>inferior Part of the <hi rend="italic">Soul</hi>: And for the Loan, <lb/>Promiſe to
          mend your Commons, which was <lb/>not my firſt Intention. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>For I had fixt my mind upon <hi rend="italic">Sanctori- <lb/>us's</hi> Chair, and the
            <hi rend="italic">Leſſian</hi> Diet, and tho't <lb/>to have put you into it. But as you
          are <lb/><hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi> Gentlemen, and abound with, and <lb/>are bred up
          to, Plenty. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>I chuſe the Man-like Mean, betwixt the <lb/>two Extreams. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>That of Foreign Authors, which in our <lb/>Country, wou'd be too rigid, and look like
          a <lb/>Method of Starving, rather than Living. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The other of guilty Exceſs and Careleſneſs, <lb/>which breed dangerous Diſeaſes, That
          either <lb/>cut off Life in the Prime of its Time; or con- <lb/>ſign to fixt Diſtempers
          and Decrepitneſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>And only beg the Conduct of a well govern'd <lb/>Mind, to which the Appetites ſhou'd
          be obe- <lb/>dient. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>By a temperate, ſober Diet, I mean, neither <lb/>eating nor drinking more at a time;
          nor oftner, <lb/>than the Conſtitution of the Body allows. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Now there cannot be one exact Meaſure <lb/><choice>
            <corr>for</corr>
            <sic>or</sic>
          </choice> all People, nor for the ſame Perſon, at all <pb n="5"/>
          <lb/>Seaſons: But muſt vary, according to the Di- <lb/>verſity of Conſtitutions, Ages,
          Seaſons of the <lb/>Year: Diſpoſition, or Indiſpoſition of the Sto- <lb/>mach, and other
          Infirmities or Circumſtances. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>So that, what is convenient for me, may <lb/>be too much for another, and too little
          for a <lb/>Third, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Here I muſt leave every one, who is ar- <lb/>rived to the Years of Diſcretion, to
          judge of <lb/>that temperate Proportion for himſelf, which <lb/>is needful; and who may
          very well gueſs, <lb/>when he exceeds thoſe Bounds. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>That Meaſure is to be obſerv'd, which the <lb/>Stomach can with appetite receive, and
          by it's <lb/>own Ability digeſt, without impediment to <lb/>Body or Mind. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>They then, who are indiſpos'd after Meals, <lb/>troubled with Fumes, Vapors,
          Heavineſs, <lb/>Drowſineſs, Yawnings, <hi rend="italic">Flatus</hi>, Oppreſſion, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
          <lb/>Or any of theſe. They have certainly tranſ- <lb/>greſt their due Meaſures. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>For Perſons after Meals ſhou'd be refreſht, <lb/>quick, apt and ready to the
          Exerciſes of Soul <lb/>or Body. But to bring things into an orderly <lb/>Method: I'll
          begin with the Day. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>And firſt, I muſt charge you to be careful, <pb n="6"/>
          <lb/>very careful of the better part: 'Tis but a lit- <lb/>tle thing I tell you, in
          compariſon. That if <lb/>he is not provided for to his Satisfaction, He'll <lb/>marr our
          bodily Health and Cheerfulneſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>When you riſe out of your warm Bed dont <lb/>enter immediately into a fluttering
          Night- <lb/>gown, Beau Cap and Slippers. — But keep <lb/>your Head and Neck a little
          Warmer, with <lb/>Additions to what you wore in the Night; <lb/>buckle up your Shoes
          quick, girt your Cloaths <lb/>tire about you, till your Pores are gradually <lb/>clos'd. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>After an Hour or two Waſh and Dreſs: Rub <lb/>your Teeth with a little fine Salt,
          waſh and <lb/>gargil your Mouth, with fair Water. This <lb/>preſerves your Teeth firm and
          ſound, and keeps <lb/>off Tooth-ach and Swelling. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>About nine o'clock, take ſome ſlight Break- <lb/>faſt, as Water-gruel, Barley-broath,
          Flumme- <lb/>ry, Milk, Milk-pottage, Barley-cream, Bo- <lb/>hea-Tea, or green Milk-Tea. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Milk-tea, with <hi rend="italic">Sal Volatile Oleoſum</hi> is my <lb/>own Breakfast,
          thro'out the Year. — I <lb/>put 3 Spoonfuls of cold, raw Milk into my <lb/>China Diſh, and
          ſweeten it to my Palate with <lb/>8<hi rend="sup">d</hi> or 9<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Sugar,
          then I put one Tea Spoonful of <lb/><hi rend="italic">S.V.O.</hi> which contains 30 or 40
          Drops, and <lb/>ſtir it in, and pour the Tea very hot, I ſtir <pb n="7"/>
          <lb/>it again and drink it. Thus ſeaſon'd, I drink <lb/>3 or 4 Diſhes in a Morning with
          Delight and <lb/>great Benefit. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>I chuſe green Tea-duſt, as preferable to <lb/>whole Tea in this Uſe: It yields its
          virtues <lb/>more free, and there follows and acerb or rough- <lb/>neſs, which Scours the
          fibres of the Stomach, <lb/>and enlivens the <hi rend="italic">Archaus</hi> 'tis the beſt
          Quali- <lb/>ty Breakfaſt that can be contriv'd: For it puts <lb/>whole Nature into
          pleaſant Activity, and <lb/>brightens the Enjoyments of all the day, when <lb/>as
          Chocolate is phlegmatic and dull, obſtru- <lb/>ctive and windy — the conſtant uſe of any
          <lb/>Nutts, eſpecially parch't or roaſted, are <lb/>clammy and heavy upon weak Stomachs,
          tho' <lb/>toothſome. Several have follow'd my Ex- <lb/>ample herein with great Benefit:
          Therefore <lb/>I mention it. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Now while ye are at the Tea-Table, 'tis <lb/>like ye will conſult, what's to be for
          Dinner. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Pray give theſe two Notes to your Caterer. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Firſt, to Buy ſuch Proviſions, as are in their <lb/>proper Seaſon. For many things
          are to be had <lb/> in great Plenty, which are not wholeſome <lb/>Nouriſhment, being out
          of Seaſon. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The other is, That the Females of all things <lb/>are the fineſt Food, and beſt
          Nouriſhment, <pb n="8"/>
          <lb/>while young: But when they come to <lb/>Breed, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> the
          Males are preferable, ex- <lb/>cept a very Fatt Old Hen in <hi rend="italic">January</hi>
          — </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Abhorr'd be ſtrong Beer, Ale, Wine, or a <lb/>Dram of the Bottle in a Morning. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>If any are ſo ill accuſtom'd, let'em im- <lb/>mediately conſult their Phyſitians;
          That their <lb/>vitiated Stomachs may be reſtor'd to their na- <lb/>tural Heat and
          Strength, and their inflam'd <lb/>Blood quieted down to a juſt Conſiſtence and
          <lb/>Temper. And if <hi rend="italic">S.V.O.</hi> be preſcrib'd in <lb/>this Caſe, the Dr.
          will have the Credit, and <lb/>the Patient the Benefit. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>About Twelve or One a Clock reſort to <lb/>the place of Dinner, where begin not too
          <lb/>eagerly, tho' Appetite preſſes forward. Eat <lb/>deliberately, chew well: For your
          Teeth <lb/>are to macerate your Food, and mix it <lb/>with a vivid <hi rend="italic"
            >Saliva</hi>, that ſprings forth in <lb/>the Action: And is of more Benefit to Fer-
          <lb/>mentation and Chylification, than moſt are <lb/>aware of. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Obſerve the Cravings of your Stomach, and <lb/>don't affect to force it by Wines,
          Pickles and <lb/>guſtful Sauces. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Don't eat a great deal haſtily, and drink at <lb/>the end of the Meal one or two
          great Draughts. <pb n="9"/>
          <lb/>But take it in moderate Proportions at ſeveral <lb/>times while you are eating, and
          drink the <lb/>oftener. 'Tis more wholeſome, and com- <lb/>plemental. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The firſt time you think you have pretty <lb/>well done, ſtop, beſure then, 'tis
          enough for <lb/>that meal. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Midling Beer, a little Hop't is of ſufficient <lb/>Strength for moſt Perſons. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Having thus temperately Din'd, don't pre- <lb/>ſently fall to Tea, Coffee, Fruit, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>If the Company ſee fit to continue toge- <lb/>ther a little, I think ſome profitable
          Diſ- <lb/>course the beſt Entertainment. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>And in your Converſation, pray take care <lb/>the Mind appears as decent as the Body,
          at <lb/>leaſt: So you'll not be reprov'd within, nor <lb/>without. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Abſtain 5 or 6 Hours, then the dilutive <lb/>Cup may be moderately taken, or a lit-
          <lb/> wholeſome Fruit, and proviſion made <lb/>for a moderate Supper, contriv'd of ſuch
          <lb/>things, as are leſs ſubſtantial than what <lb/>was for Dinner, and of a little
          ſtronger <lb/>Nouriſhment than what was mention'd for <pb n="10"/>
          <lb/>Breakfaſt. Every one's Invention is quick <lb/>enough for his Belly. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But on a Fiſh Day, or other ſlight Dining, <lb/>Exceedings at Supper may be allow'd,
          provi- <lb/>ded they be earlier taken, and not in ſo large <lb/>a Quantity as at Dinner. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>I can't but applaud the Wiſdom and <lb/>Care of our Anceſtors in Dieting young
          <lb/>Students, at Univerſities, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> Where they <lb/>are ſtinted
          to ſuch temperate Bounds, as <lb/>will preſerve their Health and Quicken 'em <lb/>for
          their Studies. And their Bodies being <lb/>inur'd to it, They gain a Habit of Tem-
          <lb/>perance and Sobriety. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Study is a Concern that draws the Spi- <lb/>rits to the Brain, and is apt to retain
          'em <lb/>too long for Health. Therefore exceſs with <lb/>Study will load the Head with
          Streams and <lb/>Vapours, that clog the Brain and hazard it <lb/>to many Diſeaſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Or by leaning the Head forward to read, <lb/>cloud the Senſes and obſtruct and foul
          the <lb/>Organs. Study and Exceſs together in ſome, <lb/>will bloat the Face, bottle the
          Noſe and <lb/>thicken the Lips. And in others cauſe Red- <lb/>neſs of Face, and Pimples,
          and run the <lb/>Body out of ſhape. </p>
        <pb n="11"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But the Schollar's Allowance is not a <lb/>meaſure for all People. For they that are
          <lb/>employ'd in Study, or other great Con- <lb/>cerns of Mind, ought to Eat and Drink
          <lb/>leſs than they, who Labour much with their <lb/>Bodies. Many work like Horſes, and
          there- <lb/>fore eat like 'em. To ſee this, I hope is no <lb/>Temptation to a refin'd
          Mind. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>To keep your Body in due Temper, <lb/>obſerve a temperate Diet. For a little
          <lb/>well digeſted and aſſimilated, preſerves the <lb/>Body ſtronger and more vigorous
          than Su- <lb/>perfluity. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Eat not, becauſe the cuſtomary Time for <lb/>it is arriv'd, unleſs your Appetite be
          ſo <lb/>too. For to charge the Stomach with a <lb/>new Supply upon a Semi-digeſtion of the
          <lb/>former Meal, cauſes Crudities, and a foul <lb/>Stomach, which muſt clog the Body, and
          <lb/>procure Diſeaſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Unequal Proportions of Meat to Drink, <lb/>and Drink to Meat are injurious. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>'Tis a very good <hi rend="italic">Italian</hi> Proverb, <hi rend="italic">He that
            <lb/>will eat much, let him eat little</hi>: For by eat- <lb/>ing little at a time, he
          prolongs his Life, and <lb/>ſo makes it up. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>An empty Stomach receives with Delight <pb n="12"/>
          <lb/>digeſts with Strength, and promotes a good <lb/>Concoction; which make Aſſimilation,
          Thri- <lb/>ving, and a wholeſome clean Body. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>'Tis better to Eat twice a Day with Mode- <lb/>ration, than to make one over-large
          Meal; <lb/>tho' you do abſtain above double the uſual <lb/>time, for Compenſation. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>However, if you have tranſgreſt at any <lb/>Meal, abſtain from the next; or let it be
          a <lb/>very thin one. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Have your Variety not at the ſame, but at <lb/>ſeveral Meals. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Forbear employ of Body or Mind, till half <lb/>an hour, or an hour after Dinner. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Sit not cloſe to the Fire, even in cold <lb/>Weather, preſently after Dinner: For it
          raiſes <lb/>Fumes, and hinders Digeſtion: A cool Air <lb/>will ſtrike the Heat inward, to
          help the <lb/>new Acceſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Neither eat nor drink preſently after Exer- <lb/>ciſe, or when you are Hot: Stay till
          Nature <lb/>has recall'd her diſſipated Spirits. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Canary, Sherry, White, or Rheniſh Wines <lb/>are not ſo fit at Meals (where Wine is
          al- <lb/>low'd) as Claret. The former over-heat and <pb n="13"/>
          <lb/>glut the Stomach; the other accelerate the <lb/>Food too ſoon, making it paſs crude,
          and ill di- <lb/>geſted, Claret corrugates the Stomach, ſtrength- <lb/>ens its tone,
          moderately warms; and ſo retains <lb/>the Food, and helps a good Concoction. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But young Perſons, whoſe Stomachs are <lb/>warm and ſtrong, need not this help. Nay,
          <lb/>Wine is hurtful for 'em. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The too early uſe of Wine and ſtrong Drinks <lb/>does ruin thouſands by devouring
          natural Heat, <lb/>and fir'ing the Blood into Feveriſh Frets and <lb/>Conſumptions. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The creating of falſe Appetites with Wine <lb/>and other ſtrong Liquors, in the firſt
          uſe of <lb/>'em, provoke to Gluttony, and after that <lb/>weaken and deſtroy the Stomach. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>For, beſides the preying on the Vital Fire <lb/>and radical moiſture; they relax the
          fibrous <lb/>Folds of the Stomach, and incline to a nauſcea, <lb/>and Reachings, next to
          ſpewing, and to <lb/>Diarrhæas, and Fluxes, and many naſty Di- <lb/>ſtempers. Now to
          remedy ſuch vitiated Sto- <lb/>machs, take my <hi rend="italic">S.V.O.</hi> in plenty. I
          know <lb/>nothing better. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>You may obſerve that cool, fat, moiſt Bo- <lb/>dies will bear hunger better than
          lean, dry, <lb/>cholerick, hot Bodies, which perſpire much: <pb n="14"/>
          <lb/> Yet for ſuch to omit, or lighten a Meal on <lb/>occaſion, 'twill ſharpen their
          Stomachs, con- <lb/>coct indigeſted Matter, and make the next <lb/>Meal reliſh the better. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>A ſtrong Body may bear for awhile, with <lb/>an irregular Courſe or Diet, better than
          a ten- <lb/>der Conſtitution, which is ſoon ſenſible of Diſ- <lb/>order. But at length he
          cuts ſhort his Days <lb/>to what they might be, while puleing Per- <lb/>ſon out lives him. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>I have often obſerv'd, for many Years, that <lb/>the Sickly and Infirm ſurvive the
          Robuſt and <lb/>Bold, who live at any or no Rate; while the <lb/>others live by ſome Rule. </p>
        <p rend="align-center italic">
          <lb/>Qui abſtinens eſt, adjiciet Vitæ. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>To come now to my other Directions, re- <lb/>lating to moderate Exerciſe or Labour:
          So as <lb/>to promote the neceſſary Laws of Perſpiration. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>A great part of Health ariſes from the due <lb/>Exerciſe of the Body. It ought then
          to be <lb/>ſo govern'd, that it may be refreſhing and <lb/>beneficial. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>All due Exerciſe makes the Body lightſom, <lb/>brisk and airy, increaſes
          natural-heat, pro- <lb/>motes a good concoction in the habit of the <lb/>Body and
          thriving: Beſides a convenient ex- <lb/>pulſion of Excrements. </p>
        <pb n="15"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And here take this Note, never bau'k Na- <lb/>tures firſt Motions to Evacuation. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Immoderate Exerciſe waſtes the Fleſh, <lb/>fires out natural Heat, frets the Blood,
          be- <lb/>gets the Scurvy (which looks like a Para- <lb/>dox) by chaſing the fixt Salts
          into ſuch an <lb/>Ebullition with the Spirits, that they tear <lb/>the balmy Texture of
          the Blood, and make <lb/>void its Continuity, which is the <hi rend="italic"
          >vinculum</hi>, <lb/>or tye of Life. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Perſons of a thinner habit of Body, are ve- <lb/>ry apt to be damag'd, by too long or
          too vio- <lb/>lent Exercise. Groſs and corpulent Bodies <lb/>will endure it with leſs
          hurt. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The Meaſures to be obſerved (as in Diet) <lb/>cannot be the ſame to all Bodies; nor
          to the <lb/>ſame Perſons, at all Seaſons. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>So much Exerciſe as promotes a full per- <lb/>ſpiration, without ſweating, is a
          convenient <lb/>mean: For it ſhould be <hi rend="italic">ad ruborem non ſu-
            <lb/>dorem</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Moderate Exerciſe rarifies and plumps the <lb/>Fleſh, dilates the minuteſt Paſſages,
          making <lb/>way for new Nouriſhment and Air to refreſh <lb/>and ventilate. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>In Reſpiration, we don't expire at Mouth <pb n="16"/>
          <lb/>and Noſe what we inſpire: But ſome part of <lb/>every draught of Air breaths thro'
          our Pores, <lb/>as is obvious, by laying your Finger on a bright <lb/>ſcour'd Diſh, you'll
          ſee the Effluviums Con- <lb/>denſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>And if ſuch <hi rend="italic">halitus</hi> continually paſs, where <lb/>the Skin is
          ſo thick: What think you evapo- <lb/>rate continually in the more lax parts, and
          <lb/>thro'out the whole? </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Now it may be of uſeful Conſideration <lb/>to ſickly and tender Bodies; That ſince ſo
          <lb/>much Air muſt paſs thro' 'em daily, to ex- <lb/>cite Curioſity and Enquiry, after the
          Nature <lb/>of Airs, and what wou'd beſt ſuit them. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>No doubt great Amendments may be made <lb/>by the right Application of Airs medici-
          <lb/>nally, and the frequent changing of 'em, <lb/>with Skill. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>I'm of the Opinion that there is room in <lb/>Science to form a Courſe of Airs. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>For the Air, which is Common to all <lb/>Things, is the great Source of undeter-
          <lb/>min'd Life, and the Univerſal Food of all <lb/>Living Creatures: Becauſe the three
          Prin- <lb/>ciples are here juſtly temper'd together, <lb/>and in their Firſt and higheſt
          Union and <lb/>Purity, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> in an illuminated Salt. </p>
        <pb n="17"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But not to digreſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>'Tis the right breathing of Air thro' all the <lb/>Pores of our Bodies, which are hot
          and per- <lb/>ſpirous, that I aim at. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>And this is to help't forward by moderate <lb/>Exerciſe, that enlivens the Spirits,
          concocts <lb/>crude Matter, and caſts off, what can't be <lb/>reduc'd to Aliment; by
          Stool, Urine, Tran- <lb/>ſpiration, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Uſe Exerciſe in the Forenoon, but give o- <lb/>ver half an Hour before Dinner. In the
          Even- <lb/>ing 'tis proper again. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Be not violent at it, nor continue it too <lb/>long, but deſiſt with Refreſhment and
          Plea- <lb/>ſure. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Let every one pleaſe his Fancy in innocent <lb/>Recreation, only ſecure a <hi
            rend="italic">Decorum</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Betwixt no Exerciſe and too much, I'll <lb/>leave you to exerciſe your Diſcretion. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Intend your Exerciſe gradually, and abate <lb/>ſo: Then you need no extraordinary
          Gar- <lb/>ment, when you come off from it, or fear <lb/>catching Cold. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>For from a ſuddain warmth to a ſuddain <pb n="18"/>
          <lb/>chilneſs, there's Danger, <hi rend="italic">Motibus oppoſitis <lb/>nibil
            pernicioſius</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>'Tis an healthful Sign, to feel lighter and <lb/>brisker at Exerciſe, than really one
          is. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The turgid Efferveſcence of the Spirits, <lb/>by Exerciſe expands the Pores,
          ventilates the <lb/>Blood, and throws off thoſe <hi rend="italic">effluviums</hi> which
          <lb/>endanger Fevers, by amaſſing, groſs, malig- <lb/>nant Humors. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But violent Exerciſe ſooner deſtroys the <lb/>Body, than the want of it. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Therefore conſumptive Bodies, and thoſe <lb/>that are hot, cholerick and lean, which
          re- <lb/>quire but little and mild Exerciſe, muſt be <lb/>caution'd againſt Exceſs in
          Recreation or Em- <lb/>ployment, as well as in Meat and Drink: <lb/>Leſt they break up
          their tender craſis of Blood, <lb/>and by firing the Spirits make 'em prey on <lb/>the
          pure Balſam of Life. They muſt reſt <lb/>much more than others, and often ſettle their
          <lb/>Spirits by Eaſe of Body and Mind. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>I'll venture to adviſe againſt two things <lb/>that conſume the Fleſh, and I'm ſure
          don't <lb/>profit the Spirit. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The Firſt is Gameing, which I acccount a <lb/>very ill Recreation: For beſides Incon-
            <pb n="19"/>
          <lb/>veniences (not now to take notice, that 'tis <lb/><hi rend="italic">malum in ſe</hi>)
          it diſturbs the Paſſions, makes <lb/>violent Commotions, within at leaſt; over- <lb/>heats
          the Blood, makes reſtleſs Nights, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
          <lb/>'Tis not properly call'd Play, and yet I don't <lb/>know what to call it, for 'tis
          not Work nei- <lb/>ther, tho' more Laborious to the whole Man <lb/>than either. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The ſecond is, unchriſtian Eagerneſs, <lb/>and diſtruſtful Carefulneſs after the
          things <lb/>of this Life. Oh! how it tears their <lb/>Fleſh and Blood Night and Day: Be-
          <lb/>ſides the Horrors of Mind. Yet they are <lb/>pleas'd to be tho't Chriſtians, in the
          Opi- <lb/>nion of others. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>They will have an Eſtate: But no ſooner <lb/>'tis got, the Man's gon, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Flannel Shifts I don't like. I think it <lb/>better to let 'em alone, while living.
          For <lb/>they widen the Pores, cauſe a great Diſpen- <lb/>dium of Spirits, diſpoſe to
          Sweat on ſlight <lb/>Occaſions, which ſhou'd not be: They <lb/>make your Perſpiration
          exceſſive, and your <lb/>Body ſo continually tender, that you can't <lb/>avoid catching
          cold. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>'Tis neceſſary to maintain a full Perſpirati- <lb/>on; but ſtill inviſible. </p>
        <pb n="20"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If the ambient Air is not warm enough, then <lb/>the Air of a Fire, more Cloths, or
          Exerciſe <lb/>muſt be ſought. In the Spring and Autumn <lb/>we are more ſubject to undue
          Perſpirations, be- <lb/>cauſe of ſudden Changes in the Air. For In- <lb/>ſtance, in <hi
            rend="italic">April</hi>, the Sun will ſhine ſtrong, and <lb/>warm the Air to a great
          Degree in the Day: <lb/>Whenas at Evening it ſhall be chil and cold: <lb/>So again in <hi
            rend="italic">September</hi>. While Summer has <lb/>a ſteady Heat, and Winter a ſetled
          Cold. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Now when great Quantity of Matter is <lb/>perſpiring, and a ſudden Check ariſes, the
          <lb/>obſtructed Effluviums ſtagnat, and a new Ac- <lb/>ceſs of Air preſſing in, the Body
          is preſently <lb/>ſurcharg'd: So that you are liable to a Fe- <lb/>ver; or at leaſt to
          have Matter depos'd on <lb/>the Brain or Lungs; or thrown into Fluxes, <lb/>Looſneſs, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Hence comes it to paſs, that Diſeaſes are <lb/>more rife in Spring and Fall, than in
          Summer <lb/>and Winter. By reaſon of the ſudden Altera- <lb/>tions of Weather from hot to
          cold, and cold <lb/>to hot in the ſame Day. The one promoting, <lb/>the other hindering
          convenient Tranſpiration, <lb/>which few minding are the ſooner entrapt. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Inſenſible Perſpiration is not to be rais'd to <lb/>a Sweat: Unleſs to divert a
          greater Inconve- <lb/>niency. </p>
        <pb n="21"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>A full Perſpiration rais'd by Art at ſeaſona- <lb/>ble Times, will more relieve the
          Body (in ſome <lb/>Caſes) than all other Evacuations combin'd. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>I have known weak Limbs and other De- <lb/>cays, thus reſtor'd, by Rarefactions only
          in <lb/>the Night time, without Sweat: And indeed <lb/>my <hi rend="italic">S.V.O.</hi>
          vaſtly excels here. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>You'll find Perſons wonder at the ſo ear- <lb/>ly Death of their Friends, becauſe
          they <lb/>have led a Temperate Sober Life. Alas! <lb/>the obſtructing of due Tranſpiration
          is as <lb/>equally deſtructive of the Body, as other <lb/>ill Government. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>To go to Stool, or make Water, more than <lb/>uſual, is a Sign you don't tranſpire
          well, and <lb/>that you are declining from Health. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>As ſoon as the Head ſhall but ake, or any <lb/>ſick Symptom ariſe, the Body perſpires
          leſs, <lb/>and begins to feel heavy and dull. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>I cou'd make appear, that moſt Fevers and <lb/>many other Diſeaſes ariſe from
          unſteady Per- <lb/>ſpiration. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But to come to a cloſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It ſeems then, that ſlender Diet, frequent, <lb/>tho' moderate Labour, and the ſeldom
          uſe of <pb n="22"/>
          <lb/>ſenſual Pleaſures, are productive of greater <lb/>Health and Serenity of Mind, than
          Satiety, <lb/>Idleneſs and Indulgence. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>For Temperance ſtrengthens the Faculties of <lb/>the Soul, as well as the Organs of
          the Body. <lb/>It preſerves Chaſtity and bridles the Paſſions. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Many erroneuſly think, they ſhou'd a- <lb/>bridge themſelves of the moſt ſubſtantial
          <lb/> Pleaſures of Life, if they ſhou'd abate the <lb/>Bottle, and the guſtful Aboundings
          of Food. <lb/>Whereas wou'd they experience the Change, <lb/>and bring the Body under a
          temperate Con- <lb/>duct, which wou'd wonderfully tend to the <lb/>Muſick of a clean Soul,
          the whole Man <lb/>wou'd be regal'd hereby, and you'd get Forty <lb/>Shillings a Week to
          boot, by ſaving. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>At firſt, to break off an ill Cuſtom with- <lb/>draw your ſelf from your extravagant
          Com- <lb/>pany; and from the Sight of Wine, Feaſts, <lb/>and tempting Baits: So your Fancy
          will not <lb/>conceive Delight, nor ſtir up your Senſual <lb/>Appetites. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>For 'tis Sight, Smell and Taſte that entice, <lb/>which if deny'd a little, you'll
          ſoon find the <lb/>Pleaſure of Conqueſt: a vaſt Reward. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>And to aſſiſt you in your Fortitude againſt <lb/>all Exceſs, obſerve theſe two Notes. </p>
        <pb n="23"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Firſt, Don't fancy your Happineſs lies in <lb/>any thing without you, as Company,
          ſenſu- <lb/>al Pleaſure, or Money: For if you want any <lb/>of theſe, take my Word for't,
          you'll be a <lb/>deviliſh Slave to other folks Luſts and Vices, <lb/>beſides your own. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The ſecond is, carry it with a prudent neg- <lb/>lect and diſ-eſteem of your outward
          ſelf and <lb/>of all things without you: Thus you'll find <lb/>many, who over-valuating
          them, will over- <lb/>look you, as a diſreputable Acquaintance. <lb/>But hereby you'l drop
          ſlender and non-im- <lb/>prov'd Intellects. Theſe Notes well digeſted <lb/>are very
          healthful to Soul and Body. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>If a Perſon of temperate Conduct ſhould <lb/>be indiſpos'd from any Surprize, he is
          ſoon- <lb/>er ſet right again, than a foul Body, which <lb/>generally falls into tedious
          and hazardous <lb/>Fits of Sickneſs: For beſides the preſent Miſ- <lb/>adventure, here's a
          foul Body to be cleans'd, <lb/><hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> And the hazard of Blunders
          in much <lb/>Phyſick. For the World abounds with Pre- <lb/>tenders. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>'Tis a hard Caſe, the immortal Eſſence <lb/>ſhou'd be only a Drudge in the Affairs of
          the <lb/>Body: and not at all regard its own great <lb/>Concerns. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It can't be tho't, ſuch noble intellectual <pb n="24"/>
          <lb/>Furniture ſhou'd be deſign'd, only to keep a- <lb/>live, and manage to the beſt
          Appearance a <lb/>Piece of well Figur'd Clay, for a while, and <lb/>then come to Nothing. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>A Temperate Life is a happy Neceſſity up- <lb/>on the Soul to look out for more
          ſuitable En- <lb/>joyments: Such as it may truly call ſo. <lb/>And a precious Remedy
          againſt Satan's <lb/>Devices. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>For Temperance, tho' it firſt deſigns the <lb/>ſingle Advantage of the Body: yet
          tends to, <lb/>and generally ends in the everlaſting Happi- <lb/>neſs of the whole Man. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But I muſt not Preach. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Then how pleaſant is the Temper of an <lb/>healthy ſound Body, expreſt in a lively
          active <lb/>Vigour. A ſprightly Strength poſſeſſing eve- <lb/>ry part, and actuating the
          whole. As tho' the <lb/>Man were all Body! </p>
      </div>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>So much for Rules. Now for Remedies. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>ND here I may very pertinently and <lb/>friendly introduce my
            <hi rend="italic">Sal Volatile Oleo- <lb/>ſum</hi>, which naturally tends to the raiſing
          of <lb/>ſuch a pitch of Health. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is not lying within the Sphere of Medicines; <pb n="25"/>
          <lb/>but of a ſublimer Original, The Element of <lb/>Air. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>For 'tis that alone can yield this Nitro- <lb/><unclear>aereal</unclear> Volatil
          Salt, enrich'd with Sulphurs and <lb/>Light, whereby it becomes the Root and Sup-
          <lb/>port of inferior Beings. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And foraſmuch as our Bodies neceſſarily <lb/>partake of Air and Aliment, for their
          continu- <lb/>ed Life, this noble Extract partaking of the <lb/>Form of Light in an
          inſeparable Union with <lb/>refin'd matter; It becomes a fit and proper <lb/>Medium to
          regulate Meat, Drink, Air, Tran- <lb/>ſpiration, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>You may obſerve, how it exhibits to view <lb/>ſome degree of that Splendor, which
          Vital <lb/>Sulphurs always ſhine with, as the choſen <lb/>matter, on which the Form of
          Light firſt <lb/>deſcends and unites with: Spiritualizing <lb/>and illuminating ſuch a
          Portion, as is ne- <lb/>ceſſary to every Individual, for its Vital <lb/>Ferment. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This impregnated radical Moiſture derives <lb/>both Heat and Influence thro'out the
          whole <lb/>Body. And as it receives freſh Supplies from <lb/>Air and Aliment, it refines
          the purer Portion, <lb/>for Support to the Stock of Life, and a gene- <lb/>ral good Habit
          of Body: Separating the im- <lb/>pure, thro' the various Paſſages deſign'd for <lb/>ſuch
          Purpoſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This Remedy naturally joins to the Life of <lb/>Beings, and maintains a pure and rich
          Foun- <pb n="26"/>
          <lb/>tain, whence very wholſome Streams are de- <lb/>rived thro' the groſs Corporeity. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But this ſort of Learning (in which Se- <lb/>cret lies) is ſo much above that, which
          gives <lb/>the general Qualification to Men, That 'twill <lb/>be to no Purpoſe to
          entertain you with it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And indeed a Perſon gets no Reputation <lb/>in this World, if he aims above outward
          <lb/>Forms of Things. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>For whatever Medicine tranſcends the Apo- <lb/>thecary's Skill, and can't be made out
          of <lb/>Shop-Goods, the Author is called a Quack, <lb/>the Alarum is given, all Mouths are
          open, <lb/>to cry down the Man and his Medicine. To <lb/>ſuch a Trade is Phyſick come. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Here I ſpeak feelingly. For ſuch Treat- <lb/>ment have I had ever ſince I became
          Profeſſor <lb/>of this <hi rend="italic">S.V.O<choice>
              <corr>.</corr>
              <sic/>
            </choice></hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But (I thank God) the Excellency and ve- <lb/>ry grat Uſefulneſs of this Bleſſing has
          main- <lb/>tain'd its own worth, and Me too, againſt all <lb/>Oppoſition. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>How many Diſeaſes are cur'd by it, is as <lb/>needleſs as laborious to enumerate.
          'Tis an <lb/>Antidote againſt all. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And proper for every Creature. Tho' this <lb/>ſounds ſtrange to ſhort Capacities. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But in particular, I adviſe it to weak and <lb/>ſickly Stomachs, to help good
          Chylification <lb/>and Digeſtion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It expels Wind, cures Gripes and Cholicks <lb/>of all ſorts. </p>
        <pb n="27"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>'Tis excellent againſt Melancholy, Hypo', <lb/>Vapours, and Fits of any kind. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It will encreaſe Breathing, cleanſe the re- <lb/>ſpiring Organs, and very good to
          cure Colds <lb/>and Foulneſs of the Cheſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It enlivens and invigorates the Brain, and <lb/>all the Senſes. And derives Strength
          and Acti- <lb/>vity to the Limbs. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It purifies and renews the Fountain of Life, <lb/>the Blood, and conſerves all the
          other Fluids <lb/>in juſt Proportions and a vivid State. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It preſerves the Body from decay and wi- <lb/>thering, and keeps it in Strength and
          Beauty. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">N.B.</hi> To ſuch as are lyable to the Scurvy, <lb/> Dropſie, Gout,
          Stone, Colick, Rheu- <lb/> matiſm, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> It ought to be their
          Con- <lb/> ſtant Companion, at Meals in their Drink, <lb/> and betwixt Meals, beſides. </p>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>The Uſe and Doſes. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N a quarter of a Pint of River, or other <lb/>Water, ſtir in
            70 or 80 Drops. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb rend="indent"/>In half a Pint of Table Beer or Ale, from <lb/>15 to 20 Drops. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In each Glaſs of Wine 7 or 8 Drops. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In a Glaſs of Cyder or Mead 15 to 16. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In a Glaſs of Mum 20. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In every Diſh of Milk-Tea, from 20 to 30. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In rough-Tea 20. In a Diſh of lac'd Cof- <lb/>fee 10 or 12. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Remember to ſtir them up very well in all <lb/>Liquors, before you Drink 'em. </p>
          <pb n="28"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/> Sick Folks and ſuch as have moſt need, <lb/>ſhould repeat the Doſe oftener. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Be ſure to avoid Pump-Waters, and ſuch <lb/>as cu<unclear>r</unclear>dle with theſe
            Drops, for all ſuch Wa- <lb/>ters are very pernicious. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In Fits of the Colick, take the Doſe every <lb/>half Hour in Water, for 3 or 4
            times. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The like do on any Surfeit of Meat or Drink. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Squeeze a drop or two in the Palm of your <lb/>Hand, and ſmell to it often. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In any affect of the Head, two or three <lb/>Drops lay'd on the Tongue, diffuſes a
            noble <lb/>gas to the Brain. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>With theſe Drops you may enrich all Li- <lb/>quors, obſerving a due Proportion. For
            they'll <lb/>recover all prickt, ſick Liquors: And give a <lb/>Body and Strength to
            thin, lean ones. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In Canary, White Wines, Cyder, and o- <lb/>ther ſpirituous Liquors; you'll ſee it
            lye at <lb/>the bottom of the Glaſs, and ſhew it ſelf red, <lb/>which is an excellent
            Mark of the true Me- <lb/>dicine, for that's a view of the internal Sul- <lb/>phur,
            rending to Fixation. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>But many being us'd to great Variety of <lb/>Medicines, can't underſtand how ſo
            much <lb/>Benefit may be receiv'd by one. Being ac- <lb/>cuſtomed to Vomiting, Purging,
            Sweating, <lb/> Bleeding, Bliſtering, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> But wholly un-
            <lb/>acquainted with what, ſo gratefully and in- <lb/>nocently, yet powerfully, joins
            with the Vital <lb/>Spirits. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="29"/>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>Another Excellent Remedy to pro- <lb/>mote Health and Long Life, is </head>
          <head rend="size(1.5) italic align-center space">
            <lb/>My Tincture of Rheubarb. </head>
          <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>His very wholſom and beneficial Drugg <lb/>is deſervendly
            reputed One of the beſt of <lb/>Vegetable Medicines, and has long obtain'd <lb/>an
            Univerſal Eſteem. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>'Tis a very mild and benign Purger of Cho- <lb/>ler, Phlegm, Viſcous and Tartarous
            matter <lb/>from the Stomach and Bowels. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>'Tis Specific to the Liver, and Opens the <lb/>Obſtructions of it, thinning the
            Gall, moving <lb/>it to a diſcharge. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This Root is Capable of great improvement <lb/>by Artful Preparation, if it be well
            choſen, <lb/>as to ſoundneſs and fulneſs of Tincture, <lb/>which is no difficulty to an
            Artiſt; tho' to <lb/>others 'tis not eaſie: For there is great Vari- <lb/>ety in this
            Subject: And often that which is <lb/>leaſt uſeful, goes at the beſt Price. The groſs
            <lb/>Earthy part is binding and heating, and too <lb/>hard and ſtiff upon the fibrous
            texture, apt <lb/>to force away the <hi rend="italic">mucus</hi> of the Guts, which
            <lb/>is a great Injury— </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Infuſions draw but in part its Tincture, <lb/>the greateſt skill in handling this
            noble Sub- <pb n="30"/>
            <lb/>ject lies in the <hi rend="italic">Menſtruum</hi>, which muſt be fu- <lb/>ſible,
            penetrating, and attractive. I a little <lb/>value my ſelf on this Attainment. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>For here, I not only get out all the rich <lb/>Tincture of the Drugg; but convey it
            too <lb/>(with Pleaſure thro' the Stomach, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>) into <lb/>the
            Blood and more diſtant parts of the Body, <lb/>whereby I diſtinguiſh Purity from
            Impurity, <lb/>and derive gradually foulneſs from remote <lb/>parts, and evacuate too,
            thro' cleanſing Or- <lb/>gands and Ducts.—'Tis a greater work to <lb/>Purify the Blood,
            than to Purge the Bowels: <lb/>And my Tincture has a direct Tendency to <lb/>the former. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>With the <hi rend="italic">Uſe</hi> of <hi rend="italic">This</hi> you may keep
            your <lb/>Blood Clean, Cool and Temperate, and your <lb/>skin from growing Tawney,
            Greeniſh, and Yel- <lb/>low— </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>'Tis an Excellent preſervative againſt <hi rend="italic">Drop- <lb/>ſies</hi>, <hi
              rend="italic">Jaundice</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Scurvy</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
              >Gout</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Aſthma</hi>, and foul <lb/>Lungs — And the Diſeaſes of
            the Brain. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It will cure the Cholick, and all windy, <lb/>weak Stomachs; it helps good Eating,
            Chy- <lb/>lification, and Digeſtion, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>— </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>I have long Obſerv'd the deplorable Caſe <lb/>of Infants; and that the likelieſt
            and ſtrongeſt <lb/>Children are ſooner cut off, than the Puling <lb/>and Sickly: Only
            becauſe their Stomachic <lb/>Ferment is ſtronger. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The right tempering down this predomi- <lb/>nant Acid early, wou'd ſave Thouſands.
            And <lb/>I offer this Tincture here in theſe Caſes, of <pb n="31"/>
            <lb/>meer Good Will: For the trifling advantage <lb/>to my ſelf in ſo dear and Laborious
            a Medi- <lb/>cine, is not worth while, at my Age. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>But becauſe I wou'd be clearly Underſtood, <lb/>pray obſerve — That Sour,
            Corroſive, con- <lb/>nate Leven, that lies pent up, and undiluted, <lb/>in the Stomachs
            of Infants, while in the <lb/>Womb, grows ſuch a potent and fiery Acid, <lb/>that ſo
            ſoon as Born, all that they be to re- <lb/>ceive at the Mouth is ſo corrupted hereby,
            <lb/>that Surfeits, Wind, Gripes, Belly-ach, and <lb/>Convulſion Fits, are the miſerable
            Conſe- <lb/>quences.—I wou'd have the firſt Thing <lb/>given to Infants new-born a
            little River-water <lb/>(by no means Pump-waters) ſweetned, and <lb/>3 or 4 drops of my
              <hi rend="italic">Sal Volatile Oleoſum</hi>, ſtirr'd <lb/>in 3 or 4 times a day — Or
            this Tincture of <lb/>Rheubarb — rather ſometimes One, and <lb/>other times the
            Other.—Let it be continu- <lb/>ed a Month for cleanſing and purifying. And <lb/>it wou'd
            contribute much, if the Wet-Nurſe, <lb/>as you call Her, drank a draught of Water and
            <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">S.V.O.</hi> in it, twice a day. N.B. Where <lb/>this firſt
            Cauſe of many Diſtempers is not <lb/>ſubdu'd in Infancy: In growing Years there
            <lb/>will be a predominant ſourneſs in the Stomach <lb/>always maintain'd by Meats and
            Drinks, that <lb/>will Cauſe Heart-burn, Head-ach, Colick, <lb/>Coſtiveneſs, <hi
              rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>—And an intemperating heat, <lb/>apt to break out into
            malignant Fevers, Mea- <lb/>ſles, Small-Pox, and other foul Eruptions <lb/>thro' the
            skin. </p>
          <pb n="32"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>But the liberal Uſe of this <hi rend="italic">Tincture of <lb/>Rheubarb</hi> to
            grown Perſons will prevent <lb/>many Diſeaſes, and promote Health and <lb/>Long Life. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The large Doſe is a Tea-ſpoonfull or 40 or <lb/>50 Drops in Tea, Water-gruel,
            Sage-Tea, <lb/>River-water, or Small-beer, and to be repeat- <lb/>ed thrice in
              <unclear>a</unclear> Morning: It may be repeated <lb/>again in the Evening about 5 or
            6 a Clock <lb/>with great benefit— </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Perſons inclin'd to Dropſies, <choice>
              <corr>Jaundices</corr>
              <sic>Jaundies</sic>
            </choice> or <lb/>both, ſhou'd take it very often and continue <lb/>it. And twice a Week
            take my Pills— </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>As for Children and Infants, from 10 to 20 <lb/>Drops, according to their Age: Here
            it muſt <lb/>be Diſpenſt at the Diſcretion of Others. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="subsection">
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The true <hi rend="italic">Sal Volatile Oleoſum</hi> is prepared <lb/>to the
            greateſt Perfection, at Dr. <hi rend="italic">Byfield's</hi> pre- <lb/>ſent Dwelling
            Houſe, in <hi rend="italic">Great Newſtreet</hi>, by <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >Fetter-lane</hi>, over againſt the <hi rend="italic">Three Tunns</hi>. As <lb/>is
            alſo his <hi rend="italic">Tincture of Rheubarb</hi>. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>They are Diſpenſt at 2 <hi rend="italic">s</hi> 6 <hi rend="italic">d</hi> each
            Vial. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Now, if any Gentlemen are pleas'd to <lb/>beſtow on their Friends this little Book
            of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Rules</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Remedies</hi>: They may have
            14 <lb/>to the Dozen at my Houſe, as above Dire- <lb/>cted. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
