<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Robinson: A treatise on the virtues and efficacy of a crust of
          bread</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Nicholas Robinson</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">A TREATISE ON THE VIRTUES and EFFICACY OF A CRUST of BREAD, Eat early
              in a Morning Fasting, To which are added Some particular Remarks concerning the great
              CURES accomplished by the SALIVA or FASTING SPITTLE, as well when externally applied,
              as when internally given, in the Scurvy, Gravel, Stone, Rheumatism, and divers other
              diseases, arising from Obstructions. With some critical Observations concerning the
              Recrements of the Blood; demonstrating, that when regularly secreted, they both
              contribute to preserve the Life of Animals and keep them in Health. </title>
            <edition n="2"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T59650</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T59650"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Dublin</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Dublin: printed by James Hoey, at the Mercury in Skinner-Row, next Door to
                  the Tholsel, M.DCC.LVII. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1757</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="3"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="32"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="2"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3308476125</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K052156.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Health guide"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>THE <lb/>INTRODUCTORY DISCOURSE, </head>
        <head type="sub" rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Diſcovering the great efficacy
            of the recrements of <lb/>the body, to the digeſtion of our food, the <w part="I"
              >cir-</w><lb/><w part="F">culation</w> of the blood, and the ſecretion of the
            <lb/>alimentary fluids. </hi></head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>Decorative frame around the letter "I".</figDesc>
          </figure>I AM ſenſible that few phyſicians have <w part="I">exa-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >mined</w> thoſe recrements of the body with <lb/>that attention, accuracy, and
          diligence, that <lb/>a point of ſo great importance requires; <lb/>and though they are
          many and divers, yet <lb/>they all contribute their ſhare to the maceration, <w part="I"
            >attenu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ation</w>, and digeſtion of our aliments in the mouth; to
          <lb/>the greater liquidation of the chyle in the ſtomach and <lb/>inteſtines; to the more
          perfect fuſion of the blood in the <lb/>veins and arteries; and the better ſecretion of
          the various <lb/>juices, ſeparated and collected in the different folliculi or
          <lb/>receptacles, ſituated in the various organs of the body, <lb/>and which are ordained
          by nature, to ſerve very great, <lb/>and important uſes in the animal œconomy. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe recrements are diſtinguiſhed from the <w part="I"
            >excremen-</w><lb/><w part="F">titious</w> diſcharges, as the latter are thrown out of
          the <lb/>body, and of no further uſe in ſupport of the ſeveral <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſpective</w> parts of the animal, and which therefore are <lb/>called the
          excrements: while the former ſerve many great <lb/>and neceſſary purpoſes in life; ſo that
          I queſtion whether <lb/>any animal circulation, ſecretion, or excretion, could be
          <lb/>carried on, without the aſſiſtance of theſe recrements; <lb/>for all the motions of
          the chyle, blood, and animal juices, <lb/>would ſtagnate and ſtand ſtill in an inſtant,
          were it not <lb/>for the ſaliva, bile, pancreatic juice, and divers other <lb/>fluids
          ſecreted from the arterial blood: And as theſe <w part="I">ſe-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >creted</w> fluids are the main principles that ſupport the life <pb xml:id="page_3"
            n="iv"/><lb/>of animals; ſo in the moſt noxious, venomous, and <w part="I"
            >poi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſonous</w> creatures, where the great miſchief is done by a
          <lb/>bite, and the infuſion of a poiſonous fluid into the wound, <lb/>as is done by the
          viper; then, upon reflection, we diſcover <lb/>that there muſt neceſſarily be a counter
          poiſon, generated <lb/>and ſecreted ſomewhere in the body itſelf, to preſerve this noxious
          animal from the force and deadly effects of <lb/>its own poiſon. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But of all the various ſeparations and ſecretions, I know <lb/>none of
          ſo much conſequence to the body, as that ſecreted <lb/>liquor, we call the ſaliva, or what
          is generally meant by <lb/>the faſting ſpittle, as will more clearly appear when we
          <lb/>come to ſpeak of its effects and conſequences upon the <lb/>bodies of rational
          animals; for without this ſecreted fluid, <lb/>we could neither chew our victuals, nor
          ſwallow our food <lb/>into the ſtomach, nor digeſt it, after it was there; ſo that
          <lb/>all the motions of the body will grow dry, ſtagnate, and <lb/>be at perpetual reſt,
          were not our ſeveral aliments mixed, <lb/>attenuated, and ſufficiently diluted in the
          mouth, by the<lb/>penetrating ſalts of the ſalival fluid, before they are <w part="I"
            >ſwal-</w><lb/><w part="F">lowed</w> down into the ſtomach. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And though of late, we have heard of mighty feats <lb/>being done by
          the virtues of crude mercury, tar-water, and<lb/>divers other quack medicines, ſold up and
          down this town, <lb/>with royal patents, and dignified titles; yet I queſtion,
          <lb/>whether in the gravel, ſtone, gout, and rheumatiſm, there <lb/>ever yet was, or at
          this time is; or in times to come <lb/>ſhall be diſcovered a medicine more valuable in the
            <w part="I">fore-</w><lb/><w part="F">going</w> diſeaſes, than what I now offer for the
          benefit of<lb/>mankind. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And the patient may aſſure himſelf, that, if theſe rules <lb/>and
          cautions, laid down in the following pages, are but <lb/>rightly purſued, and duly
          executed, they will mightily <lb/>contribute, not only to preſerve him in health, but alſo
          <lb/>prove extremely efficacious to reſtore that invaluable <w part="I">bleſ-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſing</w>, whenever over powered by the force of a diſeaſe. <lb/>And, in all
          theſe caſes, I find little occaſion for the uſe of<lb/>medicine, provided the patient eats
          his cruſt punctually in <lb/>a morning faſting, and is obſerving of the air, diet and
          <lb/>exerciſe I have ſet before him. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>

      <div n="1" type="section">
        <pb xml:id="page_4"/>
        <head rend="italic align-center"><lb/><hi rend="roman">SECT. I.</hi>
          <lb/>Of the Virtues of a Cruſt of Bread, eat early in a morning <lb/>faſting, with its
          force and efficacy in relieving the <lb/>ſcurvy, gravel, ſtone, gout, rheumatiſm, and
          various <lb/>other diſeaſes </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><figure>
            <figDesc>Decorative frame around the letter "I".</figDesc>
          </figure>I AM now going to ſpeak of a remedy ſecond to <lb/>none, in the cure and relief
          given in the <w part="I">forego-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> diſeaſes: It may indeed ſerve
          other intentions <lb/>and purpoſes as far as I know, but in the gravel, <lb/>ſtone, gout,
          and rheumatiſm, I know it to be the beſt <lb/>and ſureſt remedy hitherto diſcovered; and
          if you join <lb/>faſting to this noble medicine, I know none more <w part="I"
            >effica-</w><lb/><w part="F">cious</w>: Would you know this valuable ſecret, it is <w
            part="I">abſti-</w><lb/><w part="F">nence</w>: I ſay abſtinence;—but by the word
          abſtinence, I do <lb/>not mean a mere negative remedy, as if faſting was to <lb/>do all
          the work herſelf, by ſuffering nature, in due courſe <lb/>of time, to reſolve the
          obſtructions, and, at her leiſure, to <lb/>digeſt off the viſcid juices and corrupt
          humours; for <w part="I">ab-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtinence</w> is only neceſſary as an
          aſſiſtant, both to improve <lb/>the operation, and enable the Cruſt of Bread, eat early in
          <lb/>a morning faſting, to exert its virtues with more ſalutary <lb/>effects: For all
          medicines operate beſt upon an empty <lb/>ſtomach, and few purging medicines are adviſed,
          if they <lb/>are greatly efficacious but that they are preſcribed to be <lb/>taken in a
          morning early, and the firſt thing that the <w part="I">pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tient</w>
          does; and he is often adviſed not to eat till two or <lb/>three hours after. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I chuſe to expreſs myſelf, in the vulgar manner of <lb/>ſpeech,
          becauſe the viſible relief given in the gravel or <lb/>ſtone is uſually aſcribed to the
          Bread alone, and not to <lb/>any other aſſiſtant remedy mixed with it in the mouth, or
          <lb/>in its paſſage to the ſtomach, and ſo into the blood: For it <lb/>is a truth,
          eſtabliſhed by conſtant obſervation and <w part="I">expe-</w><lb/><w part="F">rience</w>,
          that divers perſons, by eating a Cruſt of Bread in <lb/>a morning early, and faſting two
          or three hours after it, <lb/>have received great relief in the gravel; others have <w
            part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">clared</w>, that under the ſtone their ſevereſt
          ſymptoms have <lb/>been mightily mitigated; and ſome again, under the moſt <lb/>painful
          ſymptoms of the gout and rheumatiſm, have found <lb/>their pains greatly relieved by
          adhering to this remedy, <lb/>and applying chewed bread, well moiſtened with the <pb
            xml:id="page_5" n="6"/><lb/>faſting ſaliva, warm to the gouty parts: And I do not
          <lb/>ſpeak theſe things of two or three people only, that have <lb/>accidentally been thus
          relieved, but of hundreds, nay, I <lb/>may ſay thouſands, that within my own knowledge,
          have <lb/>received great benefit from this invaluable and ſalutary <lb/>medicine. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now to examine the main point, and enquire upon what <lb/>principles
          this great relief is given; for if we conſider the <lb/>Bread itſelf, this concrete can
          have no efficacy, at one <lb/>time more than another; if the efficacy, I ſay, proceeds
          <lb/>from the intrinſical principles of the Bread; for then a <lb/>Cruſt eat at five or
          ſix in the afternoon, or at a proper <lb/>diſtance from our meals, muſt produce the ſame
          effects <lb/>upon the urinary paſſages; upon the obſtructions of the <lb/>joints and
          membranes of the muſcles, that it does, when<lb/> eat in a morning faſting; and therefore
          we are to conſider <lb/>whether this virtue and efficacy, ſuppoſed to be lodged in
          <lb/>the bread, may not more properly be owing to ſome other <lb/>aſſiſting cauſe, than to
          the piece of Bread itſelf; for we <lb/>know very well, that the matter of fact is ſo, <hi
            rend="italic">viz.</hi> That <lb/>a Cruſt of Bread, eat early in a morning faſting, does
            <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duce</w> theſe good effects in the aforeſaid
          diſeaſes; and if <lb/>we ſearch into the virtues of Bread, and conſider what
          <lb/>ingredients there is in a Cruſt, we ſhall not diſcover any <lb/>virtues in the Bread,
          more than to nouriſh the body; for <lb/>the pureſt wheat, when changed into never ſo many
            <w part="I">dif-</w><lb/><w part="F">ferent</w> forms, only produces a more elegant
          nouriſhment: <lb/>This is the prime law of its nature, and therefore we <w part="I"
            >can-</w><lb/><w part="F">not</w> ſuppoſe that the Bread itſelf can contain any powers
          <lb/>capable of producing theſe principles of diſſolution of the <lb/>gravel, attenuation
          of the phlegm, and mitigation of the <lb/>painful ſymptoms of the ſtone; and therefore I
          muſt <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">clude</w>, that the Bread itſelf does not
          contain any principles <lb/>powerful enough to accompliſh that great relief, that is
          <lb/>often received from eating a Cruſt of Bread in a morning <lb/>early; for then its
          great efficacy would ſenſibly appear, <lb/>from the great quantities we eat of this
          aliment, in our <lb/>ſeveral meals, at morning, noon, and night: And hence <lb/>I infer,
          that the good that is known to enſue from eating <lb/>the Bread, muſt be the reſult of
          ſomewhat that <w part="I">accom-</w><lb/><w part="F">panies</w> the Bread, and that we can
          conceive to be nothing <lb/>but the faſting ſaliva, which leads me to ſpeak of the
          <lb/>origin, ſecretion, and compoſition of this fluid, or what <pb xml:id="page_6" n="7"
          /><lb/>we vulgarly call the faſting ſpittle; as it is a fluid that <lb/>ſerves divers
          great and important purpoſes in the animal </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center"><lb/><hi rend="roman">SECT. II.</hi>
          <lb/>Of the origin, ſecretion, and compoſition of the Faſting <lb/>ſaliva, as the fluid
          that firſt mixes with the Bread, <lb/>in the mouth; in its paſſage through the gula; and
          in its <lb/>deſcent into the ſtomach, as the ſole cauſe of the <w part="I"
            >fore-</w><lb/><w part="F">going</w> ſalutary effects. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> Obſerved in the firſt ſection, that few
          phyſicians had<lb/>ſufficiently examined the recrements of the body; and <lb/>ſo far
          looked into the myſteries of nature, as to conſider <lb/>for what purpoſes and uſes in
          life, they were ſeperated and <lb/>ſecreted into their proper channels and receptacles;
          for <lb/>we daily perceive, that the ſaliva, the pancreatic juice, <lb/>and the bilioſe
          humours, are three liquors ſecreted from <lb/>their reſpective organs, that ſerve great
          and eminent <w part="I">pur-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſes</w> in the animal-oeconomy: and as
          the ſaliva, or what <lb/>we call the ſpittle, is the laſt and moſt conſiderable of the
          <lb/>ſecretions, ſo I think it will be proper to examine the nature, <lb/>properties, and
          conſtituent principles of a fluid, that is often <lb/>the cauſe of conſiderable changes
          and alterations in life. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now the three grand recrements of the body, <hi rend="italic"
            >viz.</hi> the <lb/>ſaliva, bile, and ſeed, are three principles, that not only
          <lb/>preſerve life and health in the individuum; but the laſt <w part="I">ſe-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">creted</w> fluid is that ſacred balſam, that has continued the <lb/>ſpecies
          from the beginning of the world to this time, and <lb/>which will ſo continue it, to the
          lateſt period of nature; <lb/>and therefore methinks they deſerve a more particular <w
            part="I">en-</w><lb/><w part="F">quiry</w>, than what I perceive phyſicians, hitherto,
          have been <lb/>pleaſed to beſtow upon them: however, I ſhall in this little <lb/>tract
          only proceed to examine the recrements of the <lb/>ſaliva, the principles of the juices
          ſecreted in the ſtomach, <lb/>and the properties of the bile, as ſubjects the moſt proper
          <lb/>at preſent for my enquiry; and ſhall poſtpone the laſt to a <lb/>more convenient
          opportunity. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>However, before we proceed to diſcover the powers, <lb/>efficacy, and
          operation of the Faſting Spittle, I judge it <lb/>highly neceſſary that, in the firſt
          place, we proceed to <lb/>examine the origin, ſecretion, and compoſition of this
          <lb/>noble fluid, as it is ſeperated from the arterial blood: becauſe <pb xml:id="page_7"
            n="8"/><lb/>upon theſe principles moſt of its active powers, in a great <lb/>meaſure,
          will be found to have their dependance. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The ſaliva, or what we call the faſting ſpittle, is <w part="I"
            >origi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nally</w> ſecreted from the arterial blood by two complex
          <lb/>glands, called the parotides, which, according to <hi rend="italic">Steno</hi>
          <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Nuck,</hi> two accompliſhed anatomiſts, lye at the root <lb/>of
          the ear, one on each ſide of the neck: Theſe glands <lb/>ſecern the groſſer ſaliva; and by
          means of a number of <lb/>little ſmall tubes, ariſing from the inner coat of theſe glands,
          <lb/>convey the ſecreted liquor into one common duct, which, <lb/>ne<unclear>##</unclear>
          the third upper grinder, opens into the mouth, <w part="I">where-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >by</w> the jaws, tongue, and all the inner parts of the lips, <lb/>are moiſtened with
          this viſcous, ſecreted ſpittle. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But, beſides theſe two large ſecretory glands, that <w part="I"
            >fur-</w><lb/><w part="F">niſh</w> out the groſſer ſecretions for moiſtening the mouth
          in <lb/>general, there are diſcovered by later anatomiſts divers <lb/>other minute,
          conglobate glands, that ſecrete a finer, <lb/>thinner, and more attenuated fluid: Theſe
          have their roots <lb/>in the polate, tongue, gums, and lips, all whoſe <w part="I"
            >mem-</w><lb/><w part="F">branes</w> are perforated with little ſmall tubuli, that let
          into <lb/>the mouth a fine, thin, volatile ſaliva, ſomewhat more <lb/>attenuated than the
          former: However, all theſe fountains <lb/>of the ſpittle are ſo commodiouſly ſituated,
          that they muſt <lb/>neceſſarily, upon cloſing of the lips, preſſure of the jaws, <lb/>and
          combining or compreſſing of the cheeks, ſqueeze out <lb/>a good quantity of their contents
          into the mouth, for the <lb/>ſeparating, moiſtening, and diſſolving of the aliments we
          <lb/>take for the ſupport of life. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And this is the reaſon, why theſe glands diſcharge the <lb/>greateſt
          quantities of their ſecreted liquors, during <w part="I">maſti-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cation</w>, or when we chew our food: becauſe then there is <lb/>not only the greateſt
          preſſure upon theſe organs, but, at <lb/>the ſame time, all the parts of the mouth are put
          into <lb/>greater motions and compreſſions, than at any other time <lb/>whatever, for to
          make the experiment if you pleaſe to <lb/>grind cloſe the teeth, and, at the ſame time,
          compreſs <lb/>your cheeks with the lips, you will readily perceive a <lb/>larger diſcharge
          of ſaliva to rouze from theſe reſpective <lb/>glands, than when the ſame lye ſtill, are at
          reſt, and under <lb/>no compreſſion. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But, of all remedies preſcribed, we ought not only to <w part="I"
            >at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tempt</w> to know their origin, nature, and production, but
          alſo <lb/>to endeavour to penetrate into the principles, powers, and <pb xml:id="page_8"
            n="9"/><lb/>properties they conſiſt of, whereby we ſhall be better <w part="I"
            >ena-</w><lb/><w part="F">bled</w> to diſcover their manner of action, and the different
          <lb/>efforts they exert upon the various organs of the animal <lb/>œconomy. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As to the ſaliva, when all the different ſecretions are <w part="I"
            >inti-</w><lb/><w part="F">mately</w> mixed in the mouth, and formed into one uniform,
          <lb/>attenuated, frothy humour; the mixture then appears from <lb/>experiments, to
          conſtitute a fine, thin, volatile, ſilver-<lb/>coloured fluid, and which is ſecreted from
          the arterial <lb/>blood in the caroted arteries, and called the ſaliva or <lb/>ſpittle. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Upon examination, it appears to be a compoſition of <lb/>ſalt, oil,
          and ſulphur, diſſolved in a pretty large quantity <lb/>of a ſine, thin, attenuated phlegm,
          very nearly reſembling <lb/>the conſiſtence of ſoap water, to which it is very nearly
          <lb/>related by the virtues of its qualities. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Under a ſound ſtate of health, it is without ſmell, <w part="I"
            >per-</w><lb/><w part="F">fectly</w> inſipid, or if it has any taſte, it may properly be
          ſaid <lb/>to reſemble the white of an egg: To the touch it is <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tremely</w> viſcid; eaſily mixes with oil, and therefore is <lb/>oleoſe; it
          readily evaporates with the leaſt force of fire, <lb/>and therefore contains a large
          portion of volatile parts; <lb/>and in its nature is mightily penetrant and abſterſive,
          and <lb/>therefore will deſtroy even the ſpericity of the mercurial <lb/>globles
          themſelves, whoſe round figures are ſo difficult <lb/>to deſtroy, unleſs you apply ſalts,
          fire, ſulphur, or ingredients <lb/>of an unctions, adheſive nature. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center"><lb/><hi rend="roman">SECT. III.</hi><lb/>Of the
          properties, virtues, and ſalutary effects of the <lb/>faſting ſaliva, when externally
          applied to old aches, <lb/>pains, recent cuts, wounds, old ulcers, corns, ſore eyes,
          <lb/>and gouty nodes. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>F we conſider the faſting ſaliva alone, and as
          it is <w part="I">ſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">creted</w> from the ſalival glands ſituated in
          the jaws and <lb/>mouth, we ſhall perceive divers great and remarkable <lb/>effects to
          ariſe from its application; for this ſaliva may <lb/>moſt properly be called the noble
          Balſam of Nature, as it <lb/>is a ſurer relief, in moſt caſes, where outwardly applied,
          <lb/>than what moſt people will eaſily be led to believe, that <lb/>have not themſelves
          tryed its efficacy: I do not deſire to <lb/>be too ſanguine upon the virtues of the
          faſting ſaliva; <pb xml:id="page_9" n="10"/><lb/>but ſhall only beg leave of the reader,
          to lay down what <lb/>I know to be matter of fact; and then ſhall proceed to <lb/>give a
          detail of divers very ſurprizing cures, that one <lb/>Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Beſtock,</hi>
          at <hi rend="italic">Nantwich</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Cheſhire,</hi> has done to
          vaſt<lb/>numbers of people, in that neighbourhood, by the outward <lb/>application of the
          faſting ſaliva, vulgarly called the faſting <lb/>ſpittle. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I am intimately acquainted with a gentleman, that <lb/>every ſpring
          and fall was accoſted with a very troubleſome <lb/>ſcorbutic tetter; he had taken mercury
          in all ſhapes, <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">viſed</w> with ſeveral phyſicians, and
          by their advice had <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">plied</w> mixtures, ointments, and
          waters, preſcribed for <lb/>tettery humours, but without ſucceſs: At laſt, he was <w
            part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">viſed</w> to apply the faſting ſaliva every morning,
          which, in <lb/>a fortnight's time, effectually cured him. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nor do I know a better medicine for troubleſome corns. <lb/>A perſon
          of ſome diſtinction had a corn on the off ſide of <lb/>his foot, that ſo ſhackled his
          limbs, as almoſt to reduce <lb/>him to the ſtate of a cripple: He employed the corn-cutter
          <lb/>without effect; for every time it was cut it both bled and <lb/>pained him very much:
          theſe are uſual accidents that <w part="I">hap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pened</w> from a nerve
          and vein, that entered into the <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſition</w> of the
          corn, and whoſe ſenſibility and cavity were <lb/>not totally deſtroyed by ſo hard a body
          He had made uſe <lb/>of plaiſters, balſams, ointments, lotions, and all manner <lb/>of
          applications, but to no manner of purpoſe: He then <lb/>accidentally asked a gentleman's
          opinion, and was adviſed <lb/>every night to ſoak his feet in warm water and bran, and
          <lb/>the next morning to apply chewed bread, well moiſtened <lb/>with the faſting ſpittle,
          by way of pultice, which, in a <lb/>little time, perfectly relieved him; for the corn, in
          leſs <lb/>than a week, tumbled out by the roots, and he has heard <lb/>no more of it
          ſince. The like happened to a gentleman <lb/>that was adviſed to apply the chewed bread,
          mixed with <lb/>the faſting ſpittle, to a gouty node, which mightily relieved <lb/>him,
          and has kept his feet eaſy ever ſince. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In thoſe hard excreſſences we call warts in the hands, <lb/>face, and
          divers other parts of the body, it is an infallible <lb/>cure, if conſtantly uſed. It alſo
          mightily aſſiſts in relieving <lb/>ſore eyes, eſpecially thoſe whoſe eye-lids from hard <w
            part="I">drink-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>, are red, angry, and inflamed: In theſe
          caſes, if you <lb/>do but lightly touch the parts affected, with this noble <lb/>balſam,
          every morning, you will find great relief. And <pb xml:id="page_10" n="11"/><lb/>we know,
          by certain experience, that in all cuts, recent <lb/>wounds, and accidental hurts, that
          the faſting ſaliva is a <lb/>ſovereign remedy: and its penetrant diſſolving abſterſive
          <lb/>qualities are ſo great, that if it be ſufficiently rubbed with <lb/>mercury, vulgarly
          called quick-ſilver, it will mortify that <lb/>mineral, and deſtroy the ſpericity of its
          globles, though <lb/>one of the moſt active bodies in nature. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But the great cures done by one <hi rend="italic">Bridget
            Boſtock,</hi> at <lb/><hi rend="italic">Nantwich</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
            >Cheſhire,</hi> by the external application of <lb/>faſting ſpittle, would ſurmount all
          credit, and ſcarce gain <lb/>belief, had we not ſufficient atteſtations, from ſeveral
          <lb/>authentic letters, that put the matters of fact above all <lb/>diſpute; for in a
          letter from a perſon of undoubted <w part="I">cha-</w><lb/><w part="F">racter</w>, he
          tells us; <q>"that this old woman, all her <w part="I">life-</w><lb/><w part="F">time</w>,
            made it her buſineſs to cure her neighbours, and <lb/>people that lived near her, of
            ſore legs, and other <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">orders</w>. But her reputation
            of late, ſeems ſo <w part="I">wonder-</w><lb/><w part="F">fully</w> encreaſed, that
            people come to her from all parts <lb/>far and near. A year ago ſhe had, as I remember,
            about <lb/>forty under her care: When I went to <hi rend="italic">London</hi> ſhe had
            <lb/>one hundred in the compaſs of a week; and they <w part="I">en-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >creaſed</w> ſo faſt, that, by the time I came back, which <lb/>was not above three
            weeks, ſhe had above eight ſcore: <lb/>and this day five weeks one hundred and ſixteen;
              <w part="I">Sun-</w><lb/><w part="F">day</w> ſe'ennight my wife and ſelf went to <hi
              rend="italic">Bridget</hi>'s houſe, <lb/>and were told by the perſons that kept the
            door, and <lb/>let the people in by fives and ſixes; that they had that <lb/>day told
            ſix hundred to whom ſhe had adminiſtred: <lb/>She at length grew ſo very faint, for ſhe
            never breaks <lb/>her faſt till ſhe has done, that at ſix of the clock in the
            <lb/>evening ſhe was obliged to give over her operations, <lb/>though then there were
            more than ſixty perſons to whom <lb/>ſhe had not adminiſtred. On Monday laſt ſhe had
            ſeven <lb/>hundred, and every day at preſent near that number.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes">She cures the blind, the deaf, and the lame of all
            <lb/>ſorts: Numbers of people have received great benefit, <lb/>in the rheumatiſm,
            king's-evil, hiſteric fits, falling <lb/>ſickneſs, and ſhortneſs of breath: She alſo
            mightily <lb/>relieves the dropſy, palſy, leproſy, cancers: and, in <lb/>ſhort, almoſt
            every diſeaſe mankind is ſubject to, except <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">French</hi> pox,
            which ſhe will not be prevailed by any <lb/>means to meddle with.</q>
        </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_11" n="12"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But here I muſt beg leave ſo far to interfere with this <lb/>old
          woman, as to declare, that in chancres, which is a <lb/>very ſtubborn ſpecies of the
          venereal diſeaſe, and which <lb/>often affects the glans penis, and baffles the utmoſt
          efforts <lb/>of the phyſician and ſurgeon, without a ſalivation: that <lb/>there is not a
          ſurer remedy, than every morning to touch <lb/>the part with the faſting ſaliva of a man
          or woman turned <lb/>of ſeventy or eighty years of age: And if you extinguiſh a
          <lb/>little crude mercury in the ſaliva, the efficacy will be ſo <lb/>much the more
          conſiderable and certain. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But to return from whence I digreſſed: <q rend="quotes">You will be
            <lb/>deſirous to know what medicines ſhe uſes to procure <lb/>ſuch mighty relief; and I
            muſt tell you, that all the <lb/>means ſhe uſes, are only to ſtroke the part with
            faſting <lb/>ſpittle, and praying for them; it is hardly credible to <lb/>think, what
            cures ſhe daily performs, and without you <lb/>were here to ſee them, it muſt appear
            romantic and <lb/>incredible: for ſome people grow well while in the <lb/>houſe; others
            while on the road, and all find themſelves <lb/>better after they are got home. She is
            about ſeventy <lb/>years of age, and takes no money for her cures, though <lb/>offered
            her; in ſhort, the rich, the lame, the blind, <lb/>and the deaf, all pray for her, and
            bleſs the great <lb/>good ſhe does; and the poor daily come to her in<lb/> cart-loads. I
            am, Sir, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi></q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This letter, I am well aſſured, comes from a perſon of <lb/>great
          veracity and integrity; and therefore I think deſerves <lb/>ſome animadverſions, as the
          cures the author ſpeaks of, <lb/>are many of them very ſurprizing, and divers out of the
          <lb/>common road of external applications: However, to make <lb/>ſuitable remarks on theſe
          cures, we muſt firſt obſerve, that <lb/><hi rend="italic">Bridget Boſtock</hi> is ſeventy
          years of age; that all was done <lb/>(beſides her prayers) by the force of the faſting
          ſpittle; as <lb/>to her prayers for a bleſſing upon her endeavours, I ſhall <lb/>not
          preſume to ſay any thing, becauſe we are aſſured in <lb/>holy writ, that perſons of leſs
          piety, virtue, and charity, <lb/>than this old woman ſeems to be miſtreſs of, have been
          <lb/>enabled to work miracles; and therefore we can never be <lb/>certain how far God
          Almighty interpoſes his finger in <w part="I">aſſiſt-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> the
          relief of divers diſeaſes: But in moſt of theſe caſes, <lb/>except the dropſy, I will be
          bold to ſay, that the means <lb/>this good woman uſed for the recovery of theſe people,
          <lb/>were equal to the effects that enſued; and in the dropſy <pb xml:id="page_12" n="13"
          /><lb/>there are two remedies may be uſed, that will infallibly <lb/>cure that diſeaſe,
          provided it does not ariſe from a rupture <lb/>of the lymphaticks, in which caſe there can
          no relief be <lb/>given, but by tapping the patient, and that only a <w part="I"
            >tran-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſient</w> relief, or the patient is not greatly advanced in
          years. <lb/>Thus far I could not but remark in caſes ſo particular in <lb/>their aſpect,
          and which were relieved by ſuch a ſimple <lb/>remedy as I am now treating of. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center"><lb/><hi rend="roman">SECT. IV.</hi>
          <lb/>Of the vehicle moſt proper to convey this ſovereign remedy <lb/>into the ſtomach, in
          order to facilitate its operation and <lb/>ſalutary effects, upon the various viſcera,
          organs, and <lb/>fluids of animal bodies. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">H</hi>ITHERTO we have conſidered the faſting ſaliva
          <lb/>alone, and as it is applied to the external parts of <lb/>the body; I am come now to
          ſpeak of its ſalutary effects, <lb/>when it is mixed, combined, and aſſociated with the
          fine <lb/>fluid ſecreted from the glands of the oeſophagus or gula, in <lb/>its deſcent
          into the ſtomach; when it is combined with <lb/>the ſtomachic juices ſecreted from the
          villous coat of that<lb/>important organ; and the improvements it acquires, as a
          <lb/>diſſolvent, after it is got out of the ſtomach into the <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">teſtines</w>, and there thoroughly mixed with the bile and <lb/>pancreatic
          juices. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And it plainly appears, from the obſervations we have <lb/>made in the
          firſt ſection, that the bread is little or nothing <lb/>concerned in producing theſe good
          effects, we ſo ſenſibly <lb/>perceive to enſue, upon eating a Cruſt of Bread, in a
          <lb/>morning faſting; nor can the virtues that follow, upon <lb/>eating that concrete, be
          properly aſcribed to the bread <lb/>itſelf; for it never could be ſwallowed, did not the
          faſting <lb/>ſaliva mix with it, and convert it to a pulpous ſubſtance, <lb/>and thereby
          fit it for digeſtion; for no dry aliments ever <lb/>could be ſwallowed, without a proper
          portion of the ſalival <lb/>fluid, nor do I conceive, that any other liquid menſtruum
          <lb/>would ſerve the intentions of nature ſo well as the ſaliva: <lb/>And this is the
          reaſon, why the greateſt number of ſalival <lb/>glands are placed in the mouth, and
          conſequently the <lb/>greateſt quantity of ſaliva ſeparated from theſe glandural
          <lb/>meſhes, during maſtication, or the time we are chewing <pb xml:id="page_13" n="14"
          /><lb/>of our food; for then there is not only the greateſt <w part="I">preſ-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſure</w> and motion in all the parts of the mouth, but the <lb/>muſcles of the
          jaws, cheeks, and lips, are more forcibly <lb/>compreſſed, contracted, and put into
          motion, than at any <lb/>other time: for theſe glandular bodies, the fountains of <lb/>the
          ſaliva, are ſo commodiouſly ſituated, that they muſt <lb/>neceſſarily, upon any preſſure
          of the cheeks, or cloſing of <lb/>the jaws, ſqueeze out their contents into the mouth;
          and, <lb/>to make the experiment, let any perſon grind cloſe his <lb/>gums and teeth, and
          at the ſame time, ſtraitly compreſs <lb/>the muſcleſs of his cheeks and jaws, and he will
          readily <lb/>perceive a larger diſcharge of ſaliva to flow into his mouth <lb/>from theſe
          compreſſions, than is uſual for the ſame glands, <lb/>at any other time; which plainly
          demonſtrates how much <lb/>the action of theſe muſcles contribute to influence the <w
            part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">charge</w> of theſe ſalival glands. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But if the relief given does not conſiſt in the virtues of <lb/>the
          bread itſelf, but in the ſecretion of the recrement, <lb/>called the Faſting Spittle, then
          you will ſay; to what end <lb/>and purpoſe ſerves a piece of bread, eat early in a
          morning<lb/>faſting: To this I anſwer; to very great and good <w part="I">pur-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">poſes</w> every way: For, in the firſt place, there is no other <lb/>ſubſtance
          we know of, that can ſo properly be eat in a <lb/>morning faſting, as a Cruſt of Bread, or
          that the ſtomach <lb/>will ſo readily receive and digeſt as that concrete: <w part="I"
            >Se-</w><lb/><w part="F">condly</w>, of all other aliments, it is the moſt proper
          vehicle <lb/>to imbibe and collect the Faſting Saliva; and therefore, <lb/>of all other
          vehicles, it is the fitteſt to be employed upon <lb/>theſe occaſions, as it beſt mixes
          with the ſaliva: Thirdly, <lb/>the force from the teeth, neceſſary to divide a Cruſt, and
          <lb/>break its coheſions, will more readily ſqueeze out the ſaliva <lb/>from the ſeveral
          falival glands. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe are the reaſons I offer in preference to a Cruſt of <lb/>Bread:
          and therefore I judge that no other concrete will <lb/>ſo readily ſerve the purpoſe, as a
          Cruſt of Bread, unleſs it <lb/>be what we call the captains biſcuits, which they carry to
          <lb/>ſea for their own eating: Theſe are ſtill preferable to bread, <lb/>as they are ſtill
          harder than a cruſt, and more deſtitute of <lb/>all foreign mixtures, as they are free
          both from leven and <lb/>yeſt. But as theſe ſometimes may be difficult to be had, <lb/>ſo
          I judge a piece of bread, in general, the beſt vehicle <lb/>we can ſubſtitute, in order to
          convey the faſting ſaliva into <lb/>the ſtomach. And hence it clearly appears, that the
          virtue <pb xml:id="page_14" n="15"/><lb/>and efficacy that reſults from eating a Cruſt of
          Bread, does not<lb/>ſo properly ariſe from the bread itſelf, as the chewing and
          <lb/>mixing it with the Faſting Spittle; and therefore, to <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">prove</w> this fine liquid, volatile ſoap, and exalt its virtues, <lb/>I adviſe
          you, having eat nothing over night for ſupper, <lb/>about five of the clock in the
          morning, to eat one ounce, <lb/>or an ounce and half, of either wheat or rye bread, which
          <lb/>in chewing, will take up full half an ounce of the faſting <lb/>ſaliva, to reduce it
          into a proper, ſoft, pulpoſe ſubſtance, <lb/>and which, when well chewed and moiſtened,
          will be <lb/>eaſily ſwallowed; and when you have got it down into <lb/>the ſtomach, then
          leave the reſt to nature, and, if you <lb/>can, go to ſleep. And it is adviſeable that you
          eat nothing <lb/>for two or three hours after: Which leads me to ſpeak a <lb/>few things
          of the conſequences of its being got into the <lb/>ſtomach, and of its mixture with divers
          of the ſecreted <lb/>juices, in the ſtomach and inteſtines. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now this courſe, if ſteadily purſued for a month or ſix <lb/>weeks,
          will prove of great efficacy in divers diſeaſes, that <lb/>have obſtructions and ſabulous
          concretions for their <lb/>parent, as the gravel, ſtone, gout, and rheumatiſm. Nor is it
          leſs <lb/>efficacious in tumours of the liver, ſpleen, and divers other <lb/>organs; in
          all which caſes, it is known to give great relief. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="5" type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center"><lb/><hi rend="roman">SECT. V.</hi>
          <lb/>Of the improvements the Faſting Saliva receives from its <lb/>mixing with the
          ſtomachic, the bilioſe, and pancreatic <lb/>juices in the ſtomach, inteſtines, and parts
          adjoining; <lb/>and in particular, of the nature, properties, and <w part="I"
            >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtituent</w> principles of the bile, as the greateſt <w
            part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſolvent</w> in nature. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">B</hi>UT after this ſine, thin, ſaponaceous fluid, we
          call <lb/>the ſaliva or ſpittle, has left the mouth, and before <lb/>it gets down into the
          ſtomach, it receives conſiderable <lb/>improvements from a fine, thin, attenuated,
          volatile fluid, <lb/>ſecreted from a number of glands, ſituated in the head of <lb/>the
          gula, which ſtill renders it more penetrant and <w part="I">abſter-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſive</w>: It ſtill acquires more force and energy from its <lb/>mixture with the
          ſtomach juices, diſcharged from the <lb/>various glands, whoſe orifices form the velvet
          coat of this <lb/>important organ: Theſe ſupply the ſtomach with a ſine, <pb
            xml:id="page_15" n="16"/><lb/>thin, clear, ſpumoſe fluid, that taſtes a little ſaline
          and <lb/>acid, but is very active and volatile in its properties. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This is ordained by nature to penetrate the foods, break <lb/>their
          coheſions, and help forward their digeſtion for the <lb/>nouriſhment of the body: And here
          a very fair opportunity <lb/>offers itſelf for me to ſpeak of the principles of digeſtion,
          <lb/>and to diſcover how theſe important changes are brought <lb/>about; that convert our
          aliments into nouriſhment, but <lb/>this would be foreign to my intention, and be a means
          of <lb/>rendering the diſcourſe tedious, as my avow'd deſign is <lb/>brevity, and only to
          take a view of the ſecreted fluids, as <lb/>far as, in their courſe, they join with the
          Faſting Saliva, <lb/>in order to exalt it into a fine, ſaponaceous liquor, proper <lb/>to
          relieve the body of its inſirmities. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Thus it appears how much the Faſting Saliva is improved <lb/>in its
          nature, properties, and action, from the lubricating <lb/>lymph of the gula, the ſtomachic
          juices, and the chylous <lb/>fluid, all continually digeſting in the ſtomach; continually
          <lb/>ſecreting from their reſpective glands, and continually <lb/>flowing over the pilorus
          into the duodenum, where they <lb/>mix and unite with the bilioſe and pancreatic juices,
          which <lb/>greatly improve this noble, active medicine, and by their <lb/>tumults,
          conſſicts, and conquaſſations, render it the moſt <lb/>penetrant, abſterſive, and
          diſſolving medicine we know of <lb/>in nature. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And becauſe I have mentioned the bilioſe juice as an <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">gredient</w> in this fine, volatile, diſſolvent medicine, you
          will<lb/>permit me here a little to examine into the nature, <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">perties</w>, and ſecretion of the bile, becauſe it is a liquor, <lb/>that will
          be found to have very conſiderable effect and <lb/>conſequences in the various organs of
          the animal œconomy. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The liver is the organ ordained by nature for the <w part="I"
            >ſepa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ration</w>, ſecretion, and ultimate perfection of the bilioſe
            <w part="I">hu-</w><lb/><w part="F">mour</w>; and I ſhould immediately proceed to
          examine the <lb/>principles and mechaniſm of this important organ, but that <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Malpigius,</hi> that accurate anatomiſt, and our learned <w part="I"
            >coun-</w><lb/><w part="F">tryman</w> Dr. <hi rend="italic">Gliſſon,</hi> have ſo fully
          exhauſted this ſubject, <lb/>that they have left but little, that is new, to be ſaid by
          <lb/>thoſe that come after them: And as I am only to obſerve <lb/>the nature of ſecretion,
          the principles of the bile, and the <lb/>uſes and purpoſes for which it is ordained to
          ſerve in life, <lb/>ſo I judge that the courſe of the veſſels, their various
          <lb/>ramifications, and their aptneſs for the ſecretion of this <pb xml:id="page_16"
            n="17"/><lb/>humour, will furniſh out every thing neceſſary to be <lb/>known upon this
          ſubject. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>However, I think proper here to obſerve, that the <lb/>modus of
          ſecretion of the bile in the liver, is different <lb/>from the humours ſecreted in all
          other parts of the body; <lb/>for in all other parts the ſecretions are uſually made from
          <lb/>an artery, but in the liver nature has inverted that order, <lb/>and makes uſe of a
          vein: and therefore the vena porta is <lb/>appointed for this important office: this vein
          receives <lb/>the blood from the ſpleen, from the meſenterick arteries, <lb/>and from
          almoſt all the organs ſituated in the lower <lb/>belly: this ſanguineous fluid moving much
          ſlower in <lb/>the vena porta, than it would have done in an artery of <lb/>the ſame
          ſtructure and mechaniſm, is the ſole cauſe why <lb/>the bilioſe ſalts are ſo readily
          diſpoſed to attract each <lb/>other, and form a fluid with that viſcidity, neceſſary to
          <lb/>give conſiſtence to the bile; and for this end and <w part="I">pur-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">poſe</w> the vena porta and biliary veſſels are incloſed in <lb/>one common
          ſheath or capſule: they enter the liver on t<lb/>he concave ſide, and are equally
          diſtributed through all <lb/>its ſubſtance; ſo that wherever there is a branch of the
          <lb/>one, there, upon good inſpection, you will be ſure to <lb/>diſcover a branch of the
          other: and therefore each lobe, <lb/>and each gland of that lobe, whether on the convex or
          <lb/>concave ſide, receives the ſame veſſels, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> A vein,
          <lb/>nerve and artery, called <hi rend="italic">arteria hepatica,</hi> to convey the
          <lb/>nouriſhment for the uſe of the liver. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The porta receives the blood from the neighbouring <lb/>parts, which
          is very ſharp, by reaſon of the cloſe union <lb/>of the bilious ſalts; for the lymph that
          kept them <w part="I">aſun-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w> is ſeparated from the blood by the
          glands of the <lb/>ſtomach, inteſtines, ancreas, and meſentery: and <w part="I"
            >there-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w>, if this ſharp, deterſive, ſaline bile, did
          continue <lb/>to circulate with the blood, it muſt frequently occaſion<lb/> vehement
          fevers, colliquative fluxes, heart-burnings, and <lb/>ſevere cholic pains, but theſe
          miſerable effects are often <lb/>prevented by a ſoft olious fluid, that tempers theſe
          ſharp, <lb/>keen ſalts, and blunts their acrimonious effects, both <lb/>upon the
          inteſtines and parts adjoining. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the ſecretion of the bile, we are to obſerve, that <lb/>the vena
          porta hepatica terminates in little ſmall <w part="I">glan-</w><lb/><w part="F">dular</w>
          folliculi, that ſecrete the bile from the blood; from <lb/>theſe ſmall glands the billous
          humour is received into the <pb xml:id="page_17" n="18"/><lb/>extremeties of the pori
          biliarii, as they inoſculate with <lb/>the extremeties of the vena porta, and which, by
          their <lb/>unions, form one trunk, called the ductus hepaticus: <lb/>this trunk empties
          part of the gall into the gall bladder: <lb/>from the gall bladder ariſes the ductus
          cyſticus, which <lb/>uniting with the ductus hepaticus, form one common <lb/>trunk, called
          the ductus communis cholidocus that <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">veys</w> the gall
          into the duodenum, near its curviture, that <lb/>forms the beginning of the jejunum; ſo
          that only part <lb/>of the gall flows into the veſica felea, by the cyſtick <lb/>duct,
          while the other part is conveyed into the <w part="I">inteſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">tines</w>
          by the ductus communis cholidocus, that opens <lb/>into that organ by an oblique
          inſertion. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The bile ſeems to be a groſs, thick, viſcid, oleous <lb/>phlegm well
          impregnated with ſalts of various kinds, as <lb/>ſweet, bitter, acerb, muriatic, and
          bitter ſweet; all <lb/>which are blended and intimately mixed in a ſmall <lb/>quantity of
          viſcid phlegm: in this fluid, more than any <lb/>other of the body, the oil and ſalts
          greatly predominate; <lb/>for an ounce of black gall contained in the fund of the
          <lb/>veſica fellea yields oil and ſalts, of each three drams; <lb/>of phlegm only two
          drams. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>If you examine the gall in the liver, in the pori <lb/>biliarii, and
          gall bladder, you will find it of a different <lb/>conſiſtence, colour and bitterneſs, in
          all theſe three <lb/>different ſituations; for the gall in the liver, or <w part="I"
            >glan-</w><lb/><w part="F">dular</w> folliculi, is of a pale green, more fluid, ſaltiſh,
          <lb/>and leſs bitter; that in the cyſtick duct more viſcid, leſs <lb/>bitter, but greatly
          partaking of ſacharine ſalts: that in <lb/>the gall bladder appears of a deep poracious
          green: and <lb/>laſtly, that in the fund, inclining to a blackiſh hue, and <lb/>which is
          more viſcid, leſs ſalt, but contains more of the <lb/>bitteriſh twang. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I could not but be thus particular upon the nature, <lb/>principles,
          and ſecretion of the bile, becauſe our great <lb/>maſter <hi rend="italic"
            >Hippocrates</hi> avers that the ingredients of bile <lb/>are generated with the firſt
          principles of life; and when <lb/>it happens to be viteous, redundant, or defective, fails
          <lb/>not to become the parent of moſt diſeaſes that any way <lb/>can affect the
          conſtitutions of animal bodies, eſpecially <lb/>thoſe that are hot, fiery, and
          inflammatory: and tho' <lb/>every conſtitution muſt neceſſarily generate bile, yet a
          <lb/>tenſe, ſpringy conſtitution, or a conſtitution with very <pb xml:id="page_18" n="19"
          /><lb/>elactic fibres, muſt neceſſarily have this humour in the <lb/>largeſt proportion,
          and theſe liable to generate much <lb/>bile, are very prone, ſpring and fall, to fall into
            <w part="I">looſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">neſſes</w>, fluxes, and the cholera morbus, which
          is what <lb/>we call a bilious vomiting, accompanied with a <w part="I">looſe-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ness</w>, where great quantities of yellow, green, black <lb/>ſtools are
          diſcharged. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="6" type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center"><lb/><hi rend="roman">SECT. VI.</hi>
          <lb/>Of ſome other ſovereign properties of the bile; as it <lb/>both promotes the
          digeſtion of our aliments, aſſiſts the <lb/>circulation of the blood, and helps forward
          the <w part="I">glan-</w><lb/><w part="F">dular</w> ſecretion in every part of the body. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">B</hi>UT I have not yet done with the bile: for it is
          a <lb/>ſecreted humour, of that vaſt ſervice and uſe in <lb/>the animal-oeconomy, that I
          very much queſtion <w part="I">whe-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> either health could
          ſubſiſt, or life itſelf be <w part="I">conti-</w><lb/><w part="F">nued</w> without its
          aſſiſtance; for this bile, I am ſpeaking <lb/>of is a ſecretion ſo univerſal, that I do
          not know one <lb/>ſingle ſpecies of animals deſtitute of this noble ſecretion; <lb/>for
          man, beaſt, reptiles, and the various claſſes of the <lb/>fiſh kind, all have bile; and,
          in all theſe different <w part="I">ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F">jects</w>, it is the bittereſt
          humour in the whole body; <lb/>which is a ſtrong argument with me of the neceſſity of
          <lb/>bitter medicines in divers caſes of diſeaſes, eſpecially <lb/>when they are properly
          applied. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now the bile is ſo copious a ſubject, and affords ſo <lb/>many
          experiments to enlarge upon, that I could write <lb/>a very large volume on the
          principles, nature, and <w part="I">vir-</w><lb/><w part="F">tues</w> of the bile alone,
          without exhauſting the ſubject: <lb/>and we find by experience, that all people of a hot,
          <lb/>choleric, dry conſtitution, are inordinately ſubject to be <lb/>hot, furious, and
          paſſionate, in proportion as they <w part="I">gene-</w><lb/><w part="F">rate</w> a greater
          or leſſer quantity of bile: however, I will <lb/>not ſay, that any one of the ſecreted
          liquors or <w part="I">recre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ments</w> are the ſole cauſe of life and
          health; yet this I <lb/>will aver, and am able to demonſtrate, that neither <lb/>health
          nor life can long ſubſiſt, where the recrements <lb/>of the ſaliva and bile are for any
          conſiderable time <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtructed</w>: and it is the
          obſervation of all naturaliſts, that <lb/>the bile greatly differs in its own nature; for
          in the <pb xml:id="page_19" n="20"/><lb/>larger animals it is leſs acid and ſharp, than in
          thoſe <lb/>that are little; in beaſts than in birds, and in birds than <lb/>in fiſhes, and
          in fiſhes, than the various tribes of inſects: <lb/>however, in man we diſcover the moſt
          tinging bitter <lb/>bile, that is in any animal whatſoever; for it is ſo <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">tenſely</w> bitter in this animal, that one drop will <w
            part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">municate</w> a bitteriſh twang to two ounces of water;
          and <lb/>the ſame quantity will tinge half a pint of the ſame fluid <lb/>with a fine,
          beautiful, paliſh green. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But to be a little more explicit, and particular upon <lb/>this
          ſubject: as it is a point of ſuch importance to the <lb/>health and lives of animals, I
          lay it down as a principle, <lb/>not to be conteſted, that life itſelf depends upon a <w
            part="I">regu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lar</w> and uninterrupted circulation of the blood
          and fluids<lb/> through the ſeveral organs of the animal-œconomy: this <lb/>conſtant and
          equal motion of the blood is kept up by the <lb/>circulation of the bile, that every where
          deſtroys the <lb/>tenacious, thick, viſcid particles of phlegm, that <w part="I"
            >ren-</w><lb/><w part="F">ders</w> the blood roapy, ſtagnant, and apt to furr up the
          <lb/>minuteſt arteries. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This bilious humour, from its inciding, penetrant, <lb/>and diſſolving
          qualities, not only aſſiſts the circulation, <lb/>but alſo is greatly concerned in
          promoting the ſeparation <lb/>of the chile from the fæces, or matter of our ſtools,
          <lb/>aſſiſts its paſſage into the lacteals, and then cuts, <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">vides</w>, and corrects the thick viſcid ſlime, that often <lb/>adheres to the
          coats of the ſtomach and inteſtines: <lb/>blocks up their ſecretions, and is a frequent
          cauſe of <lb/>very ſevere cholic pains. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But amongſt all the ſalts of the bile, which are both <lb/>volatile
          and fixed, there is a peculiar eſſential ſalt, <w part="I">en-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >dued</w> with a very ſweet property; theſe eſſential, <w part="I">ſacha-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">rine</w> ſalts, more readily join with the chyle in the <w part="I"
            >inteſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">tines</w> than any other; and this is that ſalt, that gives
          to <lb/>the chyle both its ſweetneſs and taſte, and that <w part="I">white-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ness</w> it obtains after it has paſſed the venæ lacteæ primi <lb/>geneſis:
          this ſacharine ſalt alſo gives to the urine of <lb/>thoſe that labour under the diabetes,
          that ſweet taſte <lb/>we often diſcover in thoſe that, for any conſiderable <lb/>time,
          have been ſubject to this diſeaſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>If we proceed farther in our enquiries, we ſhall <w part="I"
            >diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">cover</w> by experiments, that the bile of animals abſterges
          <lb/>like ſoap, and renders oils miſcible with water: as to <pb xml:id="page_20" n="21"
          /><lb/>its virtues, it penetrates, attenuates and reſolves all <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſtructions</w> in every part of the body, and affects roſins, <lb/>gums, and
          other tenacious bodies, by a diſſolution of <lb/>their texture; whereby they are brought
          to mix with <lb/>any fluid they are applied to: this bile or gall is neither
          <lb/>alcalious or acid, but ſeems a combination of various <lb/>ſalts, oils, and ſulphurs,
          diluted in a pretty large <w part="I">quan-</w><lb/><w part="F">tity</w> of phlegm; and
          there is no queſtion to be made, <lb/>but that the principal uſe of the bile is to
          ſeperate <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tenuate</w>, and ſheath the aſperities of the
          chyle by its <lb/>oils and ſulphurs; to blunt the acids by its oleous <lb/>corpuſcles, and
          to aſſiſt the circulation of the blood in <lb/>the veins and arteries, by its ſtimulating
          powers: It <lb/>alſo proves a ſtimulus to the inteſtines, and thereby <lb/>facilitates the
          deſcent of our excrements, and without <lb/>which we ſhould be perpetually coſtive and
          ſeldom go <lb/>to ſtool. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As the bile is the hotteſt and ſharpeſt of all other <w part="I"
            >hu-</w><lb/><w part="F">mours</w> in the body; ſo in its circulation, it every where
          <lb/>irritates the fibres of the veins, nerves, and arteries; <lb/>and thereby keeps up
          the circulation of the blood, and <lb/>frees the glands from obſtructions; ſo that without
          the circulation of the bile, and conſtant ſecretion of this <lb/>bilious humour, the
          circulation of the blood would be <lb/>languid, the ſecretion of the ſeveral humours ſtand
          ſtill, <lb/>and life itſelf be extinct; for there is no other power, <lb/>that we know of
          in nature, capable of keeping up the <lb/>blood's motion, ſave the bile: and therefore, in
          the <lb/>blood, theſe bilious ſalts are ſet at ſuch a diſtance from <lb/>each other, as
          only to irritate the veins and arteries to <lb/>a degree, as may keep the blood in motion,
          and help <lb/>forward the ſecretion of the ſeveral reſpective humours <lb/>to their
          deſtined ends and purpoſes of life; but as the <lb/>ſtomach and inteſtines are compoſed of
          more ſolid coats, <lb/>ſo, to make any ſuitable impreſſions upon their viſcid, <lb/>ſlimy
          ſecretions, there was a neceſſity for a more active, <lb/>volatile, inciding humour: and
          therefore, as the bile <lb/>came to be ſecreted into the vena porta of the liver, it
          <lb/>was deprived of its fluidity, that a greater quantity of <lb/>its various ſalts might
          be concentrated into a ſmaller <lb/>portion of phlegm; for by this means its ſalts are ſo
          <lb/>nearly collected, that they form a thick viſcid, ſaline, <lb/>bitter humour, whoſe
          office is to ſtimulate the inteſtines, <pb xml:id="page_21" n="22"/><lb/>keep up their
          periſtaltic motions, and help forwards the <lb/>deſcent of the excrements, and without
          which they <lb/>would be apt to ſtagnate in the inteſtines, and create <lb/>obſtinate
          coſtiveneſs and ſevere cholic pains; ſo that the <lb/>bilious ſalts ſerve ſeveral ends and
          purpoſes in life; for <lb/>as they exiſt in the blood, ſo they aſſiſt the circulation;
          <lb/>as they are ſecreted in the liver, and flow into the <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">teſtines</w>, the more fine parts help forwards the ſeparation <lb/>of the
          chyle, and its ſecretion into the lacteals, while <lb/>a groſſer portion of the bilious
          ſalts mix with the <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">crements</w>, and facilitate their
          deſcent; and without <lb/>which the animal itſelf neither could well ſubſiſt under <lb/>a
          ſound ſtate of health, or continue in life for any <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſiderable</w> time. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>After ſo much ſaid concerning our enquiries into the <lb/>nature,
          principles, and ſecretion of the bile, I ſhall only <lb/>obſerve on the fluid ſecreted
          from the pancreas, that it <lb/>is a fine, thin, lymphatic liquor, whoſe office, when
          <lb/>mixed and incorporated with the ſaliva, ſtomachic <lb/>juices, and bile, ſerves to
          dilute and attenuate the <lb/>chyle, and facilitate its motion into the lacteal veſſels;
          <lb/>which leads me to treat of the eſſicacy of the ſaliva, <lb/>when duly mixed, properly
          incorporated, and perfectly <lb/>united with the foregoing liquors, whereby they arrive
          <lb/>at the higheſt perfection their ſeveral natures are capable <lb/>of; and of whoſe
          effects and conſequences, in divers <lb/>diſeaſes, we ſhall treat in the following
          ſection. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="7" type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center"><lb/><hi rend="roman">SECT. VII.</hi>
          <lb/>Of the operation of the Faſting Saliva, when inwardly <lb/>taken, and mixed with the
          pancreatic and bilious <lb/>juices, in the ſcurvy, gravel, rheumatiſm, and <w part="I"
            >di-</w><lb/><w part="F">vers</w> other diſeaſes incident to obſtruct the blood, and
          <lb/>vitiate the ſecretions in the internal habit. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">W</hi>E have now ſeen in the fourth ſection what this
          <lb/>faſting ſpittle will do alone, and when outwardly <lb/>applied in divers external
          diſeaſes: I come now to <lb/>ſpeak of its effects and virtues, after it is mixed with
          <lb/>divers ſecreted liquors, in its paſſage from the mouth, <lb/>till it becomes a
          ſecreted liquor into the mouth again. <lb/>If the faſting ſpittle, after the bread has
          been well <pb xml:id="page_22" n="23"/><lb/>moiſtened with it in the mouth, is charged
          into the <lb/>ſtomach, it then, in its paſſage, meets with the <w part="I"
            >lubri-</w><lb/><w part="F">cating</w> lymph of the gula, which, from its ſpirituous,
          <lb/>active qualities, very much improves the faſting ſaliva: <lb/>and after its deſcent
          into the ſtomach, there the <w part="I">ſto-</w><lb/><w part="F">machic</w> juices are
          continually ſecreting from their <w part="I">reſpec-</w><lb/><w part="F">tive</w> glands;
          continually mixing with the ingeſted ſpittle <lb/>conveyed into the ſtomach with the meat
          we eat, till <lb/>digeſted into a thin, light, volatile ſpume or froth, they, <lb/>from
          their lightneſs and tenuity of parts, flow over the <lb/>pylorus into the inteſtines,
          where all theſe various fluids <lb/>of the ſaliva, of the ſecreted liquor iſſuing from the
          <lb/>glands of the œſophagus and ſtomach, are united in the <lb/>duodenum, and intimately
          combined with the bilious <lb/>and pancreatic juices, diſcharged from their reſpective
          <lb/>pipes, into one uniform maſs or ſoap. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And having brought the faſting ſaliva through a courſe <lb/>of
          digeſtions to mix with the bile, and pancreatic <lb/>juice in the inteſtines; it appears
          to me, from the very <lb/>nature and properties of the bilious humours thus
          new-<lb/>modelled, from the acceſs of the various ſecretions, <lb/>that we have generally
          confined the gall and pancreatic <lb/>juices to anſwer very imperfect purpoſes of life; as
          if <lb/>they were ſecreted for little elſe, but by their bitter <lb/>and acid ſalts, to
          diſſolve our aliments into the ſtomach <lb/>and inteſtines, to facilitate the deſcent of
          the foœces, <lb/>and give the depurated chyle a paſſage into the lacteals. <lb/>But upon a
          more attentive view of things, we ſhall <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceive</w>
          that the bilious humour ſerves very great and <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >portant</w> ends of life in the animal-œconomy; for were <lb/>this liquid, volatile,
          animal ſoap, of a very active, <lb/>cleanſing, penetrant and abſterſive nature, by the <w
            part="I">large-</w><lb/><w part="F">neſs</w> and union of ſalts of various natures, as
          of bitter, <lb/>ſweet, ſalt, acrid, alcalious, and muriatic, all <w part="I"
            >com-</w><lb/><w part="F">bined</w> into one ſubſtantial fluid; it will neceſſarily <w
            part="I">hap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pen</w>, that ſuch a uniform liquor will be able to
          diſſolve <lb/>all manner of viſcous humours, and ſabulous <w part="I">concre-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tions</w>, that furr up the mouths of the lacteals, obſtruct <lb/>the paſſage
          of the chyle, and diſpoſe all corrupt <w part="I">hu-</w><lb/><w part="F">mours</w> to
          diſcharge by ſtool, urine, and inſenſible <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſpiration</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This fluid the ſaliva, by the improvements it receives, <lb/>as above
          deſcribed, being admitted with the chyle into <pb xml:id="page_23" n="24"/><lb/>the
          lacteals, attenuates, diſſolves, and liquiſies any furr <lb/>or coaculum, that may ſtick
          or adhere to the coats of <lb/>the lacteals, or obſtruct in the veſſels of the
          receptaculum <lb/>chili, or ductus thoracicus: for the fine, thin, <w part="I"
            >depu-</w><lb/><w part="F">rated</w> chyle contains globles of a larger ſize, than any
          <lb/>to be found in the blood itſelf: and therefore are apter <lb/>to ſtagnate in theſe
          fine, white tubes, called venæ lacteæ <lb/>primi &amp; ſecundi generis, than in the
          veſſels of any other <lb/>parts of the body. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Therefore if it enters the lacteals, and gets into the <lb/>blood, it
          purifies that fluid, diſſolves all preternatural <lb/>lentours, ſcours the glands, and
          cleanſes their <w part="I">emuncto-</w><lb/><w part="F">ries</w>, whereby the veins,
          nerves, and arteries, are cleared <lb/>of all embarraſſing obſtructions, and the courſe of
          nature <lb/>carried on with the greateſt harmony and accord. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the kidnies, ureters, and bladder, it is known to <lb/>encreaſe the
          ſeparation and ſecretion of the fluids in the <lb/>urinary paſſages; ſo that a man may
          obſerve himſelf to <lb/>diſcharge more urine after he has eat his cruſt in a <w part="I"
            >morn-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> faſting, than at any other time of the day: again,
          <lb/>this noble fluid, by its oleous and balſamic qualities, <lb/>abates pain, and
          aſſwages the inflammation of the parts, <lb/>as is very uſual where either much gravel or
          large ſtones <lb/>have frequently paſſed theſe ſeveral organs: as this fine,
          <lb/>balſamic, liquid, compound ſoap is endued with ſoft, <lb/>oleous and balſamic
          properties, whereby it may ſheath <lb/>the aſperities of the acrimonious ſalts, and
          attemperate <lb/>all ſharp humours; ſo it abounds alſo with ſharp, acid, <lb/>inciding
          ſalts, both volatile, eſſential, and fixed; <w part="I">where-</w><lb/><w part="F">by</w>
          it attenuates, breaks, and diſſolves, all ſabulous <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cretions</w>, rectifies the intemperature of the blood, that <lb/>may intercept the
          motion of the fluids in every part, <lb/>and carries its virtues to the extremeſt organs
          of the body: <lb/>nor does it only contribute to deſtroy the moſt ſtubborn <lb/>diſeaſes,
          but alſo mightily ſerves to preſerve the body <lb/>in health; for where the circulation of
          the blood, the <lb/>ſecretion of the juices, and diſcharge of the <w part="I"
            >excrementi-</w><lb/><w part="F">tious</w> fœces and fluids are conſtant, regular, and
          uniform:<lb/>there the health is in the higheſt perfection a man can <lb/>poſſibly arrive
          at, in this imperfect ſtate of nature. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="8" type="section">
        <pb xml:id="page_24" n="25"/>
        <head rend="italic align-center"><lb/><hi rend="roman">SECT. VIII.</hi>
          <lb/>Of the force and efficacy of faſting and abſtinence, <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">der</w> the operation of this fine, penetrating, abſterſive, animal ſoap. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> Do not preſume here to treat theſe ſubjects of
          ſaſting <lb/>and abſtinence as a divine, who intends, by his <lb/>advice and counſel, to
          mortify the body or ſoul, and <lb/>better the conſcience; but as a phyſician, who is <w
            part="I">deſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">rous</w> to preſerve the ſtrength, health, and
          motions of <lb/>the body of his patient, ſteady, uniform, and regular. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Every one muſt be ſenſible, what great things have <lb/>been promiſed
          from quickſilver, tar-water, Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Stevens</hi>'s medicines, and divers
          other quack pills, powders, and <lb/>elixirs, in the gravel, gout, dropſy, and various
          other <lb/>diſeaſes: but I declare, that if the advice I offer for the <lb/>benefit of
          mankind, be but carefully obſerved, and <w part="I">punc-</w><lb/><w part="F">tually</w>
          put in practice, that many will not only receive <lb/>great relief, but an entire
          exemption, from the moſt <lb/>obſtinate and ſtubborn diſeaſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>For we ought ever to conſider, that nature is always <lb/>on the ſide
          of health, and continually ſtriving to reſtore <lb/>the conſtitution, whenever borne down
          by the force of <lb/>a diſeaſe; ſo that ſeldom can any-obſtructions happen <lb/>to the
          body, but that repletion or gorging more than <lb/>nature can digeſt, is the cauſe; and
          which, when often <lb/>repeated, brings on indigeſtions in the ſtomach, <w part="I"
            >windi-</w><lb/><w part="F">neſs</w> or flatulencies in the bowels and inteſtines; a <w
            part="I">cor-</w><lb/><w part="F">ruption</w> of humours in the blood, and various <w
            part="I">obſtruc-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w> in different organs of the habit: theſe
          are the <lb/>parents of moſt diſeaſes, that are incident to affect us in <lb/>life; for
          what is the ſcurvy, but a thick, viſcid, ropy <lb/>blood, unable to paſs the fineſt
          ſtrainers of the ſeveral <lb/>organs; and how comes it by theſe properties, but by
          <lb/>the indigeſtions of our aliments? The ſame we may <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſerve</w> of cholic pains, the aſthma, and dropſy; their <lb/>original cauſe
          undoubtedly ariſes from indigeſtions; nor <lb/>is the generation of gravel and ſtone leſs
          owing to the <lb/>ſame cauſes; for when our foods eſcape the force of the <lb/>ſtomach,
          not thoroughly digeſted, they never after <lb/>can receive the aſſimilating power from any
          after <w part="I">impreſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſions</w> the ſubſequent organs can lay upon
          them, but <w part="I">be-</w><pb xml:id="page_25" n="26"/><lb/><w part="F">come</w> the
          cauſe of various obſtructions in the ſmall <w part="I">or-</w><lb/><w part="F">gans</w> of
          the body: hence ariſe wind in the ſtomach, <lb/>pains in the inteſtines, rheumatiſms in
          the limbs, and <lb/>ſchirrous tumours in the liver, ſpleen, and divers other <lb/>parts. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now, under theſe circumſtances, to bring nature <lb/>home to herſelf,
          the firſt thing muſt be to preſcribe <w part="I">ab-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtinence</w> from
          all fleſh meats, for the compaſs of a week, <lb/>if the diſeaſe be recent; three weeks, or
          a month, if the <lb/>ſame has been of any long continuance: this will give <lb/>nature
          time to recover herſelf; what I mean by nature <lb/>recovering herſelf is that there are
          certain reſtitutive <lb/>powers in every organ and fibre of the body, whereby <lb/>nature,
          when any organ is obſtructed or oppreſſed, <lb/>ſtrives to recover its former tone. And
          this ſelf-reſtoring <lb/>power is partly the effects of the fluids, and partly <lb/>lodged
          in the organs themſelves, and the mechaniſm <lb/>that conſtitutes their powers of force
          and motion. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now in any great preſſure, from a load of foods <lb/>charged into the
          ſtomach, there is nothing that gives ſo <lb/>ſure a relief, as faſting and abſtinence; for
          theſe <w part="I">vacati-</w><lb/><w part="F">ons</w> from aliments, enables the fibres of
          the ſtomach, <lb/>vicera, and other organs, to reſolve the obſtructions, <lb/>to break the
          coneſions of the blood, and enables nature <lb/>to root out the moſt ſtubborn diſeaſes, by
          flinging their <lb/>cauſes off by either ſtool, urine, or inſenſible <w part="I"
            >preſpira-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, or ſometimes a profuſe ſweat: nor can there be
          <lb/>a more noble, ſafe, and efficacious remedy to rid us <lb/>of either ſtone, gravel, or
          gout, than what I now offer <lb/>for the relief of mankind; that is abſtinence, faſting,
          <lb/>and a Cruſt of Bread eat early in a morning faſting; or <lb/>rather the faſting
          ſaliva charged into the ſtomach, by <lb/>the aſſiſtance of a piece of bread: and in theſe
          caſes, it <lb/>is neceſſary that we take nothing of aliments for two <lb/>or three hours
          after. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Give me leave here to recapitulate, as briefly as I can, <lb/>the
          virtues of one of the greateſt diſſolvent medicines in <lb/>nature; and at the ſame time
          one of the ſafeſt, that ever <lb/>was communicated to mankind; a remedy that, if
          <lb/>ſteadily purſued, will cure both the gout, the gravel, <lb/>the ſtone, the aſthma,
          and dropſy. Would you know <lb/>this invaluable ſecret,—It is abſtinence.—I ſay <w
            part="I">ab-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtinence</w>; the moſt effectual cure in all diſeaſes:
          but by <pb xml:id="page_26" n="27"/><lb/>the word abſtinence, I do not mean a mere
          negative <lb/>remedy, as if faſting was to do all the work, by <w part="I"
            >ſuffer-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> nature, at her leiſure, to attenuate the fluids,
          reſolve <lb/>the obſtructions, and digeſt off the obſtructing matter: <lb/>nothing like
          it; for we have given you the form of this <lb/>medicine above, told you the ingredients,
          and whereof <lb/>this excellent remedy, ſo aſſiſting to nature, is <w part="I"
            >com-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſed</w>; and muſt leave yourſelf to judge of its efficacy
          <lb/>and operation. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>However to make ſome pertinent reflections upon this <lb/>ſubject, I
          beg leave to obſerve, that after the whole <lb/>quantity of chyle is digeſted into the
          ſtomach, and <lb/>conveyed into the inteſtines; thereupon the faſting ſaliva, <lb/>the
          lubricating lymph of the gula, the fluids ſecreted <lb/>from the fine velvet coat of the
          ſtomach, are all <w part="I">continu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ally</w> ſeparating from their
          reſpective glands; continually <lb/>digeſting in the ſtomach, and continually flowing over
          <lb/>the pylorus into the duodenum; there they are mixed, <lb/>united, and intimately
          combined with the pancreatic and <lb/>bilious juices, and which, by their conflicts,
          tumults, <lb/>and conquaſations, produce a moſt fine, thin, attenuated <lb/>fluid: this
          fluid being admitted into the lacteals, <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſolves</w> the
          obſtructions of the meſentery glands, every <lb/>where ſeated near the lacteals;
          attenuates, diſſolves, and <lb/>liquifies any furr or coagulum, that may adhere, or ſtick
          <lb/>to the ſides of the lacteals, and prevent its entrance <lb/>into the receptaculum
          chili, or ductus thoracicus. In <lb/>a word, this fine, volatile, ſaline fluid, from the
          various <lb/>ſecretions mixing with it, becomes a univerſal diſſolvent; <lb/>and is
          intended and ſeparated by nature, to break the <lb/>coheſions of the obſtruent matter,
          that may cleave to <lb/>the coats of the veſſels in every part of the body: and <lb/>from
          this natural obſervation, we may learn the great <lb/>benefit of frequent faſting, not
          only to preſerve the <lb/>body under a ſound ſtate of health, but alſo how <lb/>mightily
          ſerviceable it is in relieving divers diſeaſes; and <lb/>how efficacious it is in the
          gravel, ſtone, rheumatiſm, <lb/>and divers other diſeaſes, that have obſtructions for
          their <lb/>parent. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>You ſee now, that, after all, we diſcover this to be <lb/>no imaginary
          medicine, formed upon the negative <w part="I">prin-</w><lb/><w part="F">ciples</w> of
          faſting and abſtinence, as if they were to do <lb/>all the work themſelves, but on the
          ſolid grounds of <pb xml:id="page_27" n="28"/><lb/>the faſting ſaliva, combined and united
          with the liquors <lb/>ſecreted from almoſt every organ of the body, whereby <lb/>it is
          impowered to diſſolve all unfriendly coheſions in <lb/>the blood and animal juices; force
          open, break down, <lb/>and unbind thoſe ſtubborn obſtructions, that impede <lb/>the motion
          of the fluids, in their firſt paſſages; ſo that <lb/>there is ſcarce a nerve, vein,
          artery, or gland, in the <lb/>whole animal œconomy, but what muſt neceſſarily <w part="I"
            >re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceive</w> ſome benefit, from the daily operation of this fine,
          <lb/>liquid animal ſoap. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="9" type="section">
        <head rend="italic align-center"><lb/><hi rend="roman">SECT. IX.</hi>
          <lb/>Of the air, diet, exerciſe, and other requiſitorial rules, <lb/>neceſſary to be
          obſerved, in order to facilitate the <lb/>operation of this liquid ſoap, I eſteem a moſt
          <lb/>invaluable remedy. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HUS we have diſcovered the operation of this
          <lb/>noble and moſt ſovereign remedy in the ſcurvy, <lb/>gravel, rheumatiſm, and divers
          other diſeaſes; which <lb/>leads me to ſpeak a few things of the air, diet and <w part="I"
            >ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">erciſe</w>, neceſſary to be obſerved, in order to facilitate
          <lb/>the relief it gives in the moſt ſtubborn diſeaſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But before we can expect to accompliſh all theſe fine <lb/>effects,
          enumerated in the foregoing pages, I hold it <lb/>highly neceſſary that a proper air, a
          regular diet, and a <lb/>well adjuſted exerciſe, ſhould be enjoined the patient: as
          <lb/>to the air, which is the firſt thing we ought to <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſult</w> about, I judge it highly neceſſary, that the patient <lb/>ſhould ſojourn in a
          ſoft, free, open air, on a ground <lb/>rather riſing; in a place free from woods, ſens, or
          high <lb/>mountains, that may intercept the pure, balſamic <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">perties</w> of this healthful, enlivening fluid, the air. By <lb/>all means, if
          he is ſubject to either the gravel, aſthma <lb/>or rheumatiſm, let him avoid living in
          great cities, <lb/>which are pernicious to thoſe incident to the foregoing <lb/>diſeaſes;
          and therefore my advice is, that he take the <lb/>medicine in the country, if poſſible, as
          the goodneſs of <lb/>the air will aſſiſt its operation: but if his buſineſs calls <lb/>him
          to the city, and he cannot poſſibly ſtay in the <w part="I">coun-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >try</w>, he muſt not, by any means intermit the medicine, <lb/>but purſue its uſe a
          month or ſix weeks in the beſt <w part="I">man-</w><pb xml:id="page_28" n="29"/><lb/><w
            part="F">ner</w> he can, without intermiſſion; from which, in moſt <lb/>diſeaſes, that
          are lodged within the compaſs of the <w part="I">cir-</w><lb/><w part="F">culation</w>, he
          will receive conſiderable benefit. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Having done with the air, the next thing to be <w part="I"
            >ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerved</w>, is the patient's diet: and I chuſe to begin with
          <lb/>his diet in the morning, becauſe there are ſeveral nice <lb/>circumſtances, neceſſary
          to be adjuſted, in order to <lb/>facilitate the operation of this ſovereign remedy, we
          <lb/>call the faſting ſpittle. And therefore I adviſe the patient <lb/>to eat his
          breakfaſt about ten of the clock in the morning: <lb/>and, under a fit of the gravel, I
          would adviſe him to <lb/>drink three or four diſhes of tea, made either of mallow
          <lb/>flowers, or, if the ſeaſon does not permit them to be <lb/>had, let him uſe the
          mallow leaves, ſweetened with <lb/>honey, with a ſlice or two of bread and butter, as the
          <lb/>beſt breakfaſt he can have. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>An hour or two after breakfaſt, let him exerciſe; and <lb/>of all
          exerciſes, I prefer that on horſeback; but if the <lb/>weather happen to be hazy, and not
          promiſing, he may <lb/>then, for two or three hours, take the air in a chariot, <lb/>cloſe
          chaiſe, or coach. When I ſpeak of exerciſe, I <lb/>always ſuppoſe the patient is entirely
          free from any pains <lb/>of the gravel or ſtone. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>After his return, if he finds himſelf refreſhed, he may <lb/>take a
          walk in the garden, or about the houſe, or buſy <lb/>himſelf for the remainder of the time
          between that and <lb/>dinner, in his ſtudy: but above all things, let him take <lb/>care
          he does not habituate himſelf to drink wine, or <lb/>any thing that is ſtrong, in the
          morning, before dinner; <lb/>for many, by that means, have deſtroyed their appetite,
          <lb/>and for ever after ſpoiled a good digeſtion; ſo that <lb/>whatever they have eat at
          noon, has turned to wind <lb/>and crudities, and ſubjected them to ſevere cholic pains. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>When he ſits down to his great meal, or dinner, I <lb/>permit him to
          eat of every thing, ſo it be not too ſalt; <lb/>for ſalts, of all kinds, are undoubtedly
          ingredients of <lb/>both the gravel, ſtone, and rheumatiſm; and theſe <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">gredients</w> furniſh out the cauſe of frequent fits in theſe
          <lb/>diſeaſes: and therefore the young, of all animals, are <lb/>to be choſen, as they
          conſiſt of the lighteſt ſalts, and <lb/>ſuch as are eaſily diſſipable by urine, ſweat, and
            <w part="I">perſpi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ration</w>; and ſeldom concrete, as they are not
          endued <pb xml:id="page_29" n="30"/><lb/>with that degree of attraction as are the ſalts
          of older <lb/>animals. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Between dinner and ſupper, I would not adviſe him <lb/>to touch any
          thing, unleſs a diſh or two of tea or coffee, <lb/>with a ſlice of bread and butter; for
          the great point is <lb/>ſo to order the air, diet, and exerciſe, as to be able to
          <lb/>bring all the motions of the animal organs to a due <w part="I">tem-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">perature</w>, and then we ſhall greatly promote the <w part="I"
            >opera-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of this ſalutary remedy, and render its virtues
          <lb/>highly efficacious. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>His ſupper I would adviſe him to take about ſix or <lb/>ſeven in the
          evening, and by no means later; and as <lb/>milk is phlegmatic, ſo, if he pleaſes, he may
          take half <lb/>a pint, or more, of white wine whey, with a ſea biſcuit; <lb/>or, if it
          pleaſes him better, he may take a ſlice of new <lb/>cheeſe, and drink a few glaſſes of old
          port, or a pint <lb/>of fine, ſoft ale, with about ſix ounces of the cruſt of <lb/>a
          French role or minchet. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>After theſe things are done, I adviſe him not to eat <lb/>any thing
          till about ſix, ſeven, or eight of the clock the <lb/>next morning, which is the time of
          his taking the <lb/>grand medicine: this conſiſts of half an ounce or ſix <lb/>drachms of
          the faſting ſaliva, preſſed or ſqueeſed out <lb/>from the ſalival glands into the mouth,
          by the preſſure <lb/>of the jaws and teeth, in eating an ounce or ten drachms <lb/>of the
          cruſt or heel of a loaf made of the pureſt wheat; <lb/>for the cruſt occaſions ſo much the
          greater preſſure from <lb/>the teeth, whoſe greater force occaſions a greater <w part="I"
            >diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">charge</w> of this ſalival fluid, and which will anſwer all
          <lb/>the purpoſes we declared in the preceding ſections. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And, though of late years, we have heard of mighty <lb/>feats done by
          crude mercury, tar water, and other <lb/>quack medicines, ſold up and down the town, <w
            part="I">ſupport-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> by royal patents, and dignified titles: yet
          I queſtion, <lb/>whether in the gravel, ſtone, and rheumatiſm, there <lb/>ever yet was
          diſcovered, or at this time is diſcovered, <lb/>or any remedy, in future times, ſhall be
          diſcovered, that <lb/>in its virtues and efficacy, comes up to this invaluable
          <lb/>medicine, I now offer for the benefit of mankind: and <lb/>the patient may aſſure
          himſelf, that if theſe rules and <lb/>cautions and ſome others, that does not properly
          come <lb/>within the narrow compaſs, I here have ſet myſelf, are <pb xml:id="page_30"
            n="31"/><lb/>but rightly purſued, they will not only mightily <w part="I"
            >contri-</w><lb/><w part="F">bute</w> to preſerve him in health, but alſo be extremely
          <lb/>efficacious, to reſtore this invaluable bleſſing, whenever <lb/>overpowered by the
          force of a diſeaſe: and in all theſe <lb/>the patient will find little occaſion for taking
          of <w part="I">medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cines</w>, provided he is obſerving of theſe
          rules, and <w part="I">care-</w><lb/><w part="F">ful</w>, every day, to adjuſt his air,
          diet, and exerciſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now, though I will not pretend, like our modern <lb/>quacks, to cry up
          this medicine, as a univerſal catholicon, <lb/>and promiſe the world, that it will never
          fail to cure all <lb/>diſeaſes it is applied to; yet I will boldly venture to <lb/>declare
          a ſolemn truth, that no quack can, with juſtice, <lb/>affirm in favour of his medicine:
          that it never was known <lb/>to do any harm to man, woman, or child, <w part="I"
            >notwith-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtanding</w> the many thouſands of people, that have <w
            part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">perimentally</w> made uſe of it. </p>
        <trailer rend="italic align-center"><lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>Explanation of the abſtruſe Terms uſed in <lb/>the foregoing
          Treatiſe. </head>
        <list>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="dc(2)">R</hi>ECREMENT,</hi> a ſuperfluous matter in the
            blood <lb/>or body. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Secretion,</hi> the ſeparating one fluid from another. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Alimentary,</hi> nouriſhing. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Fluid,</hi> a ready flowing. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Maceration,</hi> the digeſtion of certain ingredients. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Attenuation,</hi> a thinning any thing. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Liquidation,</hi> making moiſt or clear. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Chyle,</hi> a whitiſh juice into which the food is converted
            <lb/>by digeſtion. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Fuſion,</hi> a melting or ſolution. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Folliculi,</hi> the gall-bladder. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Excrementitious,</hi> of the nature of excrements. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Excretion,</hi> a putting forth of the excrements. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Saliva,</hi> faſting ſpittle. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Bile,</hi> the gall. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Concrete,</hi> a body made up of different principles. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Urinary,</hi> ſomething belonging to the urine. </item>
          <pb xml:id="page_31" n="32"/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Gula,</hi> the throat. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Complex,</hi> compounded of many parts. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Tube,</hi> a long hollow pipe. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Viſcous,</hi> clammy. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Conglobated,</hi> heaped or gathered round together. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Perforation,</hi> an eroſion or eating of the bones through
            <lb/>them. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Maſtication,</hi> a breaking of food in one's mouth with <lb/>the
            teeth. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Oleoſe,</hi> oily. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Penetrant,</hi> ſharp. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Abſterſive,</hi> medicines uſed to clear the skin. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Unctious,</hi> greaſy. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Adheaſive,</hi> a ſticking cloſe together. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Œſophagus,</hi> the gullet. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Pulpous,</hi> full of ſubſtance. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Menſiruum,</hi> a diſſolving liquor. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Glandular,</hi> ſomething compounded of glands. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Coheſion,</hi> a ſticking together. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Stomachic,</hi> good for the ſtomach. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Spumoſe,</hi> full of froth. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Saline,</hi> briniſh. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Lubricating,</hi> ſmooth. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Lymph,</hi> a clear humour. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Duodenum,</hi> the firſt of the thin guts. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Conquaſſation,</hi> a daſhing or breaking to pieces. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Ramification,</hi> a collection of ſmall branches iſſuing out
            <lb/>of large ones. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Vena porta,</hi> the vein which enters the liver through two
            <lb/>eminences called <hi rend="italic">portæ,</hi> i. e. gates. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Meſentereck,</hi> belonging to a membranous part ſituate in
            <lb/>the middle of the belly. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Concave,</hi> hollow on the inſide. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Lobe,</hi> a body turned of a roundiſh ſhape. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Convex,</hi> bending down on every ſide. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Deterſive,</hi> of a cleanſing nature. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Colliquative,</hi> a profuſe ſweating. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Accrimonious,</hi> full of ſharpneſs. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Jejunum,</hi> the ſecond part of the inteſtines. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Inſertion,</hi> a grafting in. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Muriatick,</hi> briny. </item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
