<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Trusler: An Easy Way to Prolong Life</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>John Trusler</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">An Easy Way to Prolong Life, By a Little Attention to What we Eat and
              Drink: containing, A Chemical Analysis, or, an Enquiry into the Nature and Properties,
              of all Kinds of Food; how far they are wholesome, and agree with different
              Constitutions: with Some Directions respecting our Way of Living. Collected from the
              Authorities of some of our Ablest Physicians. By a Medical Gentleman.</title>
            <edition n="2"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T54922</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T54922"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for the author, and sold by J. Bell, near Exeter-Exchange,
                  in the Strand.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1775</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="3"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="79"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="3"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107367189</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Health guide"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="3"/>
    <body>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A horizontal triple line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <head rend="align-center space">
        <lb/>AN <lb/>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(2)">EAS Y WAY </hi>
        <lb/>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(0.5)">TO PROLONG</hi>
        <lb/>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">LIFE. </hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">H</hi>EALTH being the greateſt bleſſing <lb/>upon earth, it is natural
        to imagine, we <lb/>ſhould be ſtudious to preſerve it; and yet, if <lb/>we take a view of
        the actions and conduct of <lb/>mankind in general, we are led to ſuppoſe that <lb/>it is
        not the greateſt good. Inſtead of paying <lb/>any regard to it, we frequently indulge our
        <lb/>appetites, at the expence of our conſtitutions. <lb/>The human body is a piece of
        mechaniſm, that <lb/>requires care and attention. It may be com- <lb/>pared to clock-work,
        which, if not kept free <lb/>from duſt and other extraneous, injurious <lb/>ſubſtances, will
        preſently be out of order. <lb/>Life is, generally ſpeaking, ſhortened or pro- <lb/>longed,
        according to the care we take of it. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>In the firſt age of the world, the life of man <lb/>was nearly a thouſand years; but
        after the flood, <pb n="2"/>
        <lb/>it was abreviated to half its length. Three gene- <lb/>rations later, it was reduced to
        one fourth of its <lb/>original term, and man ſeldom lived above two <lb/>hundred years.
        About the time of Moſes, it <lb/>became ſhorter ſtill, commonly not exceeding <lb/>one
        hundred and twenty years, and now, it is <lb/>reduced to little more than half that period. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>But, though we find this gradual declenſion <lb/>in the ſeveral ages of the world; yet
        we muſt <lb/>underſtand, that it was not <hi rend="italic">equally</hi> ſo, in all
        <lb/>parts, at the ſame time; for difference of cli- <lb/>mate, and difference of living,
        cauſed a dif- <lb/>ference in the length of life. Hence, ſome of <lb/>the inhabitants of the
        earth lived three times <lb/>or four times as long as others. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Now, why the days of man ſhould be thus <lb/>ſhortened, and his term of life ſo much
        re- <lb/>duced, is an object worth our enquiry: and, if <lb/>we compare the manner of our
        living now, <lb/>with that of the firſt age of the world, we ſhall <lb/>ſee evident reaſons
        for it; every generation hav- <lb/>ing, more and more, impaired its conſtitution by <lb/>a
        degenerate courſe of living, incompatible <lb/>with the laws of nature. And as we muſt, of
        <lb/>neceſſity, admit of hereditary infirmities, we <lb/>have reaſon to expect, (unleſs by
        great refor- <lb/>mation of the injurious cuſtoms of later ages,) <lb/>that life in future
        will be ſhorter ſtill. </p>
      <pb n="3"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>'Tis true, there is another rational cauſe, <lb/>namely, that when the number of men
        upon <lb/>the earth was ſmall, it was neceſſary their life <lb/>ſhould be prolonged, for the
        purpoſes of popu- <lb/>lation; but as they increaſed, this became no <lb/>longer neceſſary,
        and the wiſdom of the Crea- <lb/>tor found it requiſite to ſhorten their days, <lb/>leſt the
        earth ſhould be overſtocked. For <lb/>were men to live nine hundred years now, <lb/>with the
        preſent encreaſe of the ſpecies, there <lb/>could not be proviſion for one tenth part of
        <lb/>their number. But, notwithſtanding this, it is <lb/>a matter of melancholy
        conſideration, to think, <lb/>how much longer a man might live, with tem- <lb/>perance, than
        he does, at preſent; and how <lb/>ſoon the gratification of a little momentary <lb/>pleaſure
        hurries him out of life, perhaps to the <lb/>deſtruction of his family, and the loſs of hap-
        <lb/>pineſs hereafter. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>In the infancy of the world, man ſought only <lb/>after the neceſſary requiſites of his
        being, and <lb/>was contented with that competent ſubſiſtence, <lb/>which nature required;
        but, in proceſs of time <lb/>he grew diſſatisfied with the bare neceſſaries of <lb/>life,
        (that wholeſome proviſion that would <lb/>have greatly prolonged it,) and hunted after
        <lb/>variety and exceſs, to pleaſe and gratify a <pb n="4"/>
        <lb/>ſenſual appetite. Thus, one age taught ano- <lb/>ther to be irregular and <hi
          rend="italic">diſordered</hi>, dictated new <lb/>inventions to ſucceeding generations, and
        tranſ- <lb/>mitted their ruined practices to the following <lb/>ages to imitate and
        compleat. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hinc illæ lachrymæ!</hi> — After this manner, <lb/>and by ſuch means,
        is the life of man beſet by <lb/>innumerable infirmities and diſeaſes: thus, is <lb/>he cut
        off, before he is well aware of it. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Now, as it is natural to man to covet length <lb/>of life, we have reaſon to ſuppoſe,
        he will be <lb/>glad to pay ſome attention to thoſe things, that <lb/>will either prolong or
        ſhorten it; and, as length of <lb/>life depends upon health, health is the principal
        <lb/>thing to be conſidered. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The practice of phyſic was anciently diſtri- <lb/>buted into three branches; the firſt
        of which was <lb/>confined to ſurgery; the ſecond, to the admini- <lb/>ſtration of internal
        remedies; the laſt, to a due re- <lb/>gulation of diet. The two former have, in no <lb/>age,
        received more uſeful improvement than in <lb/>the preſent. But, it is greatly to be doubted,
        <lb/>whether or not an attention has been paid to the <lb/>latter, in proportion to its
        dignity and impor- <lb/>tance. </p>
      <pb n="5"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Many are the cauſes of ill health, but the prin- <lb/>cipal one is the variety and
        exceſs of food. To <lb/>this then, at preſent, we ſhall turn our enquiries. <lb/>But, before
        we proceed, it may not be unneceſſary <lb/>to give the reader ſome little inſight into the
        na- <lb/>ture of digeſtion and the properties of food in <lb/>general. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>When food is thrown down into a healthy <lb/>ſtomach, it naturally diſſolves and
        ferments, it <lb/>being a natural property of the ſtomach to pro- <lb/>duce fermentation.
        The aliment being diſſolved <lb/>and fermented, is again rendered ſolid by the juices
        <lb/>of the ſtomach; and the nutritive fluid being ex- <lb/>pelled from the ſolid part, is
        paſſed into the inteſ- <lb/>tines, where it is abſorbed by certain veſſels that <lb/>open
        into them, and is converted into blood. The <lb/>remaining part of the food, being retained
        in the <lb/>ſtomach, during this proceſs, is afterwards eva- <lb/>cuated. But this
        fermentation in the body is not <lb/>exactly ſimilar to fermentations out of the body;
        <lb/>as, in fermentations out of the body, the air <lb/>contained in the ſubſtances
        fermenting is let <lb/>out, which may be found by experiment; but, <lb/>this is not the caſe
        in healthy perſons and in <lb/>proper food, within the body; fermentation <lb/>there takes
        place without any extrication of air. <lb/>In weak ſtomachs, indeed, and in the digeſting of
          <pb n="6"/>
        <lb/>ſome particular foods, extrication of air will often <lb/>ſo diſtend the ſtomach, as to
        occaſion flatulencies <lb/>and pain; but this is always irregular and un- <lb/>natural. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Now, if ſuch extrication of air ſhould happen, <lb/>or the food we take, be ſuch as
        will not, in the <lb/>ſtomach, readily diſſolve, ferment, become ſolid, <lb/>or re-diſſolve;
        or, in ſhort, if it be ſuch as ſhall, in <lb/>any way, reſiſt the powers of the ſtomach,
        digeſ- <lb/>tion will be imperfect, and the whole ſyſtem diſ- <lb/>ordered; it being only
        ſuch part of the food as is <lb/>digeſted, that nouriſhes the body. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>If the digeſtive powers of the ſtomach be weak, <lb/>natural fermentation will not take
        place, but ſuch <lb/>fermentation as we obſerve in flour, when mixt <lb/>with yeſt, that is,
        the air in the ſubſtances we eat, <lb/>will be extricated; and ſometimes to ſuch a degree
        <lb/>as to diſtend the ſtomach greatly, and bring on, <lb/>what is called wind, belchings
        and pain. In this <lb/>caſe vegetables will turn acid, and meat will pu- <lb/>trify, before
        either of them are paſſed from the ſto- <lb/>mach. This occaſions heart burn, a certain ſign
        <lb/>of indigeſtion; and, if this weakneſs of the ſto- <lb/>mach continues, and putrefaction
        runs to a great <lb/>height, ſickneſs, vomiting, and purging will be <lb/>the conſequence,
        and ſometimes fever. Now, <pb n="7"/>
        <lb/>ſhould any quantity of this putrid food be abſorbed <lb/>by the veſſels, and, in its
        paſſage thro' the body, be <lb/>carried into the blood, it will weaken the whole
        <lb/>ſyſtem, and, if not timely prevented, bring on <lb/>ſuch a general putrefaction of the
        blood, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> as to <lb/>prove fatal. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>If what we eat, be of hard digeſtion, that is, <lb/>ſuch as will not readily diſſolve,
        or break down, <lb/>or ferment in the ſtomach, either owing to the <lb/>nature of the food,
        its hard texture, or the weakneſs <lb/>of our digeſtive organs, it will remain too long,
        <lb/>before it be paſſed off, and produce a ſenſe of <lb/>weight, fullneſs, oppreſſion and
        cold; as is <lb/>the caſe with ſalted meats in weak ſtomachs. 'Tis <lb/>the ſame, if it will
        not re-diſſolve, after it is coa- <lb/>gulated or become ſolid. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>So again, if it be too eaſy of digeſtion; that is, <lb/>if it be ſuch as will not
        remain long enough in the <lb/>ſtomach, owing either to its want of tendency to <lb/>become
        ſolid again after it is diſſolved; or to the <lb/>ſtrength of the ſtomach preventing it, the
        nutri- <lb/>tive part will not have time to ſeparate, and the <lb/>body will not be
        nouriſhed. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Further, it muſt be obſerved that circulation is <lb/>carried on by a contraction of
        the heart, driving <lb/>the blood from its cavities into the blood-veſſels, <pb n="8"/>
        <lb/>which, immediately on receiving it, contract like- <lb/>wiſe, and impel it on, thro'
        the whole round of <lb/>the ſyſtem, to the heart again. Now, if the heart <lb/>and veſſels
        contract too quick, or with too much <lb/>force, it occaſions a ſtrong, quick pulſe and
        fever, <lb/>and will often throw the blood in ſuch quantities <lb/>upon the brain, which is
        a tender, delicate part, as <lb/>to bring on Stupor, Apoplexy, Delirium, and <lb/>Death:
        And, it is the property of ſome ſubſtances <lb/>to ſtimulate or encreaſe this action of the
        heart <lb/>and veſſels; and of others, to diminiſh it. Food <lb/>of a viſcid, clammy nature,
        glary, like the white of <lb/>an egg, will adhere to the ſides of the ſtomach, <lb/>and, by
        ſo doing, throw the blood, from other <lb/>parts of the body, in ſuch quantities upon the
        <lb/>brain as to oppreſs it, and ſometimes occaſion <lb/>Apoplexy. How this is brought
        about, is un- <lb/>known; but experience ſhews us that it is ſo. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Perſons have been ſo diſordered by eating <lb/>muſcles, which are of a viſcid nature,
        that, without <lb/>ſome timely aſſiſtance, they would have died. In <lb/>theſe caſes, the
        head ſwells, the face becomes of a <lb/>black red, the eyes are ready to ſtart from their
        <lb/>ſockets, and a Stupor ſucceeds; but by adminiſter- <lb/>ing a vomit, and making the
        ſtomach diſcharge <lb/>its contents, and by opening the jugular vein, the <lb/>patient has
        ſometimes recovered. </p>
      <pb n="9"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From hence it appears, that ſome kinds of <lb/>food are wholeſome, others unwholeſome,
        and <lb/>that there is none univerſally proper. It muſt be <lb/>adapted to the conſtitution. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Now, there is a period in the life of man, in <lb/>which the organs of digeſtion are
        weak, and yet, <lb/>at the ſame time, there is a neceſſity for much <lb/>nouriſhment. This
        period is infancy; for, as <lb/>at this time, the body encreaſes faſt, much nou-
        <lb/>riſhment is required to help and forward the <lb/>growth: milk being naturally
        provided, and <lb/>therefore probably adapted to it, we may ſup- <lb/>poſe it to be a food
        of eaſy digeſtion and conſi- <lb/>derable nouriſhment. Examining then the pro- <lb/>perties
        of milk, will give us ſome inſight into the <lb/>nature of food in general. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Milk is not a ſimple ſubſtance; it is a <lb/>mixture of three; namely, coagulable
        matter, <lb/>expreſſed oil, and ſugar. Coagulable matter is <lb/>that which will unite, and
        become ſolid, leaving <lb/>the reſt thinner and more fluid, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> the
        curd; and <lb/>expreſſed oil is ſuch as can be procured from any <lb/>ſubſtance by preſſing,
        as oil of almonds, olives, <lb/>and the like: by expreſſed oil, in milk, we un-
        <lb/>derſtand the cream. </p>
      <pb n="10"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The moſt ſimple food, then, does not appear <lb/>to be the eaſieſt of digeſtion; if it
        was, we ſhould <lb/>have expected that milk would have conſiſted of <lb/>one ſubſtance only. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>That the coagulable matter is capable of af- <lb/>fording conſiderable nouriſhment, may
        be gather- <lb/>ed from our experiencing that animal mucilage <lb/>nouriſhes the moſt;
        mucilage being that ſub- <lb/>ſtance which has ſufficient moiſture to keep it <lb/>together:
        as, for example,—ſound, good meat. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>This coagulable matter, in milk, is fluid indeed <lb/>when taken, but there is a juice
        peculiar to the <lb/>ſtomach, very different from an acid, that ren- <lb/>ders it ſolid. We
        find the ſtomach of a calf, <lb/>though cleared of every thing that is acid, to <lb/>have
        this property. An infuſion of a few grains <lb/>of the inner coat will coagulate or curdle
        ſeveral <lb/>quarts of milk. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>With reſpect to cheeſe, for I ſhall not have a <lb/>better opportunity to mention it,
        it has, in general, <lb/>a coſtive quality; but it differs, in proportion to <lb/>the
        quantity of oil, in the coagulable part. The <lb/>more rich, oily parts there are in cheeſe,
        the more <lb/>nutritive it is and ſoluble: that is, the readier it <lb/>will digeſt; the
        leaner the cheeſe, the more dif- <pb n="11"/>
        <lb/>ficultly it digeſts. Cheeſe is liable to become rank <lb/>and putrid, we muſt then
        conſider it as having <lb/>all the effects of animal food, when advanced to
        <lb/>putrefaction; at this time it ceaſes to be nutri- <lb/>tive, and can only be conſidered
        as an aſſiſtant to <lb/>digeſtion. Cheeſe, indeed, as food, is only fit <lb/>for the
        laborious and robuſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Having mentioned cheeſe, let me drop a word or <lb/>two upon butter. A quantity of pure
        cream eaten, is <lb/>undoubtedly unwholeſome; being, from its diſpo- <lb/>ſition to get acid
        and rancid, very difficult of digeſt- <lb/>ion; but, in the form of butter, it may be uſed
        <lb/>with advantage. 'Tis a ſtrong nutriment, fit to ac- <lb/>company our vegetable diet,
        eſpecially ſuch <lb/>vegetables as are naturally dry of themſelves; in <lb/>this caſe, it
        gives them the properties of rich, oily <lb/>ſubſtances.—But, to return. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It appears then that milk, and of courſe all <lb/>other food, muſt become ſolid in the
        ſtomach, and, <lb/>after that, undergo a freſh change, that is, be re- <lb/>diſſolved, for
        digeſtion; for which purpoſe, it muſt <lb/>remain ſome time there, before it be paſſed off. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Now, that the expreſſed oil, which is the cream, <lb/>helps digeſtion, is evident from
        milk's not digeſt- <lb/>ing ſo well when it has been ſkimmed, the <pb n="12"/>
        <lb/>curd being harder; for the cream and the ſugar, <lb/>being mixed with the curd,
        ſeparate the different <lb/>parts of it more from one another, ſo that the <lb/>natural
        fluid of the ſtomach will penetrate the <lb/>eaſier, and fermentation go on the better <note
          place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* If new milk is too rich or heavy for a child's ſtomach, <lb/>let it be diluted or
            mixed with water; it ſhould never be <lb/>ſkimmed. </p>
        </note>. And <lb/>as to ſugar, it, being from its nature more apt to <lb/>ferment, will of
        courſe facilitate digeſtion. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>That expreſſed oil affords <choice>
          <corr>much</corr>
          <sic>nuch</sic>
        </choice> nouriſhment, <lb/>we find from men and animals being able to live <lb/>a long time
        upon nuts, almonds, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> ſuch con- <lb/>taining a quantity of this
        oil. But, expreſſed oil <lb/>alone produces ſenſe of weight on the ſtomach, <lb/>owing to a
        relaxation it brings on, preventing the <lb/>ſtomach's contracting and expelling its load,
        and <lb/>if taken in quantities, it will bring on ſickneſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>That ſugar alſo affords great nouriſhment, is <lb/>evident from animals thriving on the
        ſhoots of <lb/>young plants, which contain a great deal of ſugar; <lb/>and from ſome negroes
        living wholly on the <lb/>ſugar-cane. But ſugar alone is viſcid, and, by ad- <lb/>hering to
        the ſides of the ſtomach, will ſtimulate <lb/>it and diſorder the ſyſtem, and if diluted
        with <lb/>any watery fluid, would be ſo thin as not to be <pb n="13"/>
        <lb/>retained in the ſtomach long enough for digeſtion, <lb/>but mixed with the coagulable
        part of the milk, it <lb/>is ſufficiently retained. Either of theſe ſubſtances <lb/>alone
        then, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> coagulable matter, expreſſed <lb/>oil, or ſugar, would be
          <hi rend="italic">hard</hi> of digeſtion; but <lb/>blended, as in milk, they are <hi
          rend="italic">eaſy</hi> of digeſtion. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Immediately after child-birth, when the milk <lb/>begins to flow in the mother's
        breaſts, it contains <lb/>a larger quantity of ſugar and water (for there <lb/>is always a
        ſmall quantity of water) in proportion <lb/>to the coagulable matter. Some months after
        <lb/>child birth, the coagulable matter encreaſes, and <lb/>the ſugar proportionably
        diminiſhes. For as the <lb/>infant-ſtomach is weak, the ſolid part of the milk <lb/>is, at
        firſt, leſs, ſo that a looſer maſs is formed, much <lb/>eaſier to be diſſolved. As the child
        grows ſtrong- <lb/>er, its ſtomach can bear more of this coagulable <lb/>matter, and digeſts
        it, if it be firmer. This <lb/>points out, that a young child, one of a month <lb/>old, will
        not thrive, in general, on breaſt-milk <lb/>eight or nine months old. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>We alſo learn from this, that weak ſtomachs <lb/>require food of eaſy digeſtion; ſtrong
        ſtomachs, <lb/>food of harder digeſtion. Thus, chicken, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        <lb/>will nouriſh people moſt, recovering from ſickneſs, <lb/>and bacon, <hi rend="italic"
          >&amp;c.</hi> will beſt recruit a labourer. </p>
      <pb n="14"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having thus far conſidered the properties of <lb/>milk, the food Nature has deſigned
        for the infant- <lb/>ſtomach, we ſhall be able to diſcover the whole- <lb/>ſomeneſs of other
        foods, by examining <hi rend="italic">their</hi>
        <lb/>different properties; and we will begin with <lb/>vegetables. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The vegetable ſubſtances capable of nouriſh- <lb/>ing are as follow: <list>
          <item rend="indent space">
            <lb/>1. Farrinaceous matter, or flour. This is ge- <lb/>nerally contained in grain; but
            ſometimes we <lb/>find it in the ſtems of plants, and ſometimes in <lb/>their roots. </item>
          <item rend="indent space">
            <lb/>2. Vegetable mucilage: as for example, gum- <lb/>arabic, <hi rend="italic"
              >&amp;c.</hi> That this is capable of nouriſhing, <lb/>is evident from whole caravans
            living on it, for a <lb/>long time, when they can procure no other food. </item>
          <item rend="indent space">
            <lb/>3. Sugar. </item>
          <item rend="indent space">
            <lb/>4. Expreſſed oils. And, </item>
          <item rend="indent space">
            <lb/>5. Native vegetable acid; or the juice of ſour <lb/>fruits, which tends to take off
            the putreſcency of <lb/>animal food: that is, to prevent meat from cor- <lb/>rupting,
            while it continues in the ſtomach. </item>
        </list>
      </p>
      <pb n="15"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For animal food, without a mixture of vege- <lb/>table, is apt to continue too long in
        the ſtomach, <lb/>before it ferments. In this caſe, it will ſome- <lb/>times begin to
        putrify before it be paſſed off, <lb/>which putrefaction getting into the blood, will
        <lb/>often bring on a putrefaction of all the fluids of <lb/>the body. This is a complete
        ſea-ſcurvy, which, <lb/>if not timely remedied, always terminates dread- <lb/>fully. Salting
        proviſions makes them harder of <lb/>digeſtion; and though it prevents meat from
        <lb/>corrupting ſoon out of the body; yet, as the <lb/>ſalt ſeldom if ever penetrates
        ſufficiently into the <lb/>ſubſtance of the meat, ſo as totally to ſecure it <lb/>againſt
        putrefaction, when in the body, if it is not <lb/>immediately made to ferment, by the
        addition of <lb/>vegetable food, or ſome vegetable acid thrown in <lb/>with it, it will be
        apt to putrify before it digeſts, <lb/>and contaminate the whole ſyſtem. Hence we <lb/>ſee,
        how liable mariners are, on a voyage, where <lb/>there is a ſcarcity of vegetables, to be
        afflicted <lb/>with the ſcurvy, and how ſoon they get rid of <lb/>that diſorder, when they
        once get on ſhore again, <lb/>to the free uſe of herbs and roots. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Now, theſe five vegetable ſubſtances, I have <lb/>mentioned, go naturally through
        fermentation, <lb/>and are converted into blood. </p>
      <pb n="16"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>With reſpect to the fibres, the ſolid part of <lb/>vegetables, we find them frequently
        paſs through <lb/>the body, without being altered. As for example, <lb/>peas and the ſkins
        of gooſeberries, currants, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        <lb/>Now, as the texture of the ſtrongeſt tendons of <lb/>animal food is conſtantly
        deſtroyed in their paſ- <lb/>ſage through the body, while ſuch parts of <lb/>vegetable food
        ſhall be evacuated as they were <lb/>taken in, it is a queſtion, whether theſe laſt were
        <lb/>digeſted? If any of them are, it muſt be ſuch <lb/>only as are young and tender. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>But, to return. Farrinaceous matter is con- <lb/>tained in the ſeeds of all vegetables;
        but in many, <lb/>it is ſo mixed with other ſubſtances, as to be unfit <lb/>for uſe. Thus,
        we find it in peas, beans, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        <lb/>but in too ſmall quantities for the purpoſes of <lb/>life. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>So again, we meet with it in nuts; as wal- <lb/>nuts, cheſnuts, almonds, filberds,
        common <lb/>nuts, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> But theſe contain too much oil to be
        <lb/>wholeſome for common food. Beſides, they <lb/>yield a bitteriſh, aſtringent matter,
        which adds to <lb/>their unwholeſomeneſs. Bitter almonds, acorns, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >&amp;c.</hi> which contain a great deal of this matter, <lb/>are more unwholeſome ſtill.
        The oil, contained <lb/>in nuts, will often give a ſenſe of weight in the <pb n="17"/>
        <lb/>ſtomach, and ſtimulate the ſyſtem during digeſ- <lb/>tion, eſpecially when eaten raw.
        Beſides, the <lb/>farrinaceous matter in them have a viſcidity that <lb/>renders them
        hurtful to the conſtitution; but <lb/>roaſting them will deſtroy this viſcidity, and then
        <lb/>they may be eaten ſafely, and will afford much <lb/>nouriſhment. They may be rendered
        eaſier of <lb/>digeſtion, by mixing them with flour. 'Tis the <lb/>cocoa-nut, mixed with
        flour, that forms cho- <lb/>colate. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Farrinaceous matter is found alſo in many <lb/>roots, as in potatoes, <hi rend="italic"
          >&amp;c.</hi> and ſometimes in the <lb/>pith of trees, as in the palm-tree. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>We uſe the pith of one tree, which we make <lb/>into ſago, by moiſtening it with water,
        beating it <lb/>up, ſo as to ſeparate it from the fibrous part of the <lb/>tree, drying it
        into a cake, and afterwards reduc- <lb/>ing it to powder. Thus, it becomes eaſy of
        <lb/>digeſtion, and does not ſtimulate; but, ſtill, as it <lb/>paſſes off too ſoon from the
        ſtomach, it does not <lb/>afford much nouriſhment. However, it is very <lb/>proper food for
        weak ſtomachs; as in fevers. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>In the Eaſt, they eat rice; in England, wheat; <lb/>in Germany, rye; in ſome parts,
        oats and <lb/>barley; and in Africa, Indian wheat. This is <pb n="18"/>
        <lb/>the grain commonly uſed for food, and it appears <lb/>to be well adapted to digeſtion. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Farrinaceous matter is, in its nature, ſolid, <lb/>capable of being diſſolved in water,
        and forming <lb/>a jelly. If, before we diſſolve it in water, we <lb/>expoſe it to heat, it
        coagulates or becomes ſolid; <lb/>thus, if we bake it, we convert it into bread; <lb/>after
        which, it will not ſo readily diſſolve. But <lb/>bread diſſolved by long boiling, is leſs
        viſcid than <lb/>a ſolution of flour would be; and conſequently <lb/>more wholeſome. Was
        flour uſed, with water, <lb/>raw, it would be ſo viſcid as to clog and cloy the
        <lb/>ſtomach; we therefore prepare it to take off this <lb/>viſcidity. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Flour is not apt to undergo that fermentation <lb/>in the ſtomach, ſo as ſufficiently
        to correct the <lb/>putreſcency of animal food; we therefore ferment <lb/>it firſt; that is,
        we make it into bread. Another <lb/>reaſon for our converting it into bread, is, that
        <lb/>in fermentation, extrication of air takes place, <lb/>which leaves a number of holes,
        making the <lb/>bread ſpungy; by which means, when eaten, <lb/>it ſoaks up the fluid of the
        ſtomach, and facilitates <lb/>digeſtion. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>In order to coagulate the flour, that is, make <pb n="19"/>
        <lb/>it into bread, and give it a whiteneſs, which is <lb/>the nature of all coagulants to
        do, bakers mix <lb/>with it a quantity of allum, which, if not ſo great <lb/>as to give the
        bread a taſte, can do no harm to <lb/>adults; but a ſmall quantity will do much miſ-
        <lb/>chief to infants. Panada, therefore, for children, <lb/>ſhould by no means be made of
        bread in which <lb/>any allum has been mixed. It is for this reaſon <lb/>phyſicians
        preſcribe biſcuit-powder. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Sometimes bakers uſe whites of eggs, and <lb/>ſometimes ſpirits of wine, to coagulate
        the flour, <lb/>as in French bread; the firſt is innocent, and the <lb/>laſt evaporates
        during the baking, and can <lb/>produce no ill effect. For if bread is not per- <lb/>fectly
        coagulated, it will ſometimes ferment a <lb/>ſecond time in the ſtomach, particularly if it
        <lb/>continues long, as in weak ſtomachs, and turn <lb/>ſour; but baking it a ſecond time
        will totally <lb/>prevent this. Thus, ruſks and toaſted bread are <lb/>often preſcribed for
        diſordered ſtomachs, as being <lb/>leaſt liable to do miſchief; for the leaſt extrication
        <lb/>of air in weak ſtomachs is injurious. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>But farrinaceous ſeeds and roots are not ſuffi- <lb/>cient to correct the putreſcency
        of meat; we <lb/>therefore make uſe of vegetables, that were not <pb n="20"/>
        <lb/>originally deſigned for food, namely, potherbs. <lb/>Of theſe, </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The one ſort are cabbages, colliflowers, bro- <lb/>coli, and all the varieties of this
        claſs of plants. <lb/>They contain naturally a ſtimulating oil, and a <lb/>bitter aſtringent
        juice, ſo as not to be fit for uſe; <lb/>but we find this only in wild cabbages, <hi
          rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> By <lb/>cultivation, this oil and bitter juice are deſtroyed,
        <lb/>and ſuch as grow in our gardens conſiſt of little <lb/>more than mucilage and ſugar;
        and, of courſe, <lb/>are fit for food. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The method taken to deſtroy theſe noxious <lb/>juices, is, to grow the plants in the
        dark, or, <lb/>with as little air as poſſible: this is done by <lb/>planting them in a rich
        ſoil, and thus making <lb/>them ſo luxuriant, that the leaves ſhall embrace <lb/>one
        another, by which means the body of the <lb/>plant grows in the dark, and with little or no
        air. <lb/>Hence the inner leaves become white, and are <lb/>free from thoſe hurtful juices.
        The outer leaves <lb/>may be eaten, but the inner ones are moſt whole- <lb/>ſome. So young
        plants are more wholeſome than <lb/>old ones, as whatever of theſe juices they con-
        <lb/>tain, they are not near ſo rank. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Another kind of plants we uſe, are parſley, <pb n="21"/>
        <lb/>fennel, thyme, mint, ſage, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> and ſome others <lb/>of the
        ſame kind. Theſe contain a ſtimulating <lb/>oil, that would be injurious to the
        conſtitution, <lb/>if eaten in any quantity; and on that account are <lb/>only uſed as
        condiments with a ſeaſoning to other <lb/>foods. Cellery is of the ſame kind; but by
        <lb/>earthing it up, and thus making it grow in the <lb/>dark, and with little or no air, we
        deſtroy its <lb/>noxious oil. Wild cellery, if eaten, would bliſter <lb/>the mouth. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The ſeveral ſpecies of onions, garlick, ſhalots, <lb/><hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        are of another claſs; we cannot deſtroy the <lb/>oil in theſe, but by boiling. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Lettuce, endive, dandelion, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> contain much <lb/>opium, and
        when wild are very bitter and diſ- <lb/>poſe to ſleep, conſequently are unfit for food;
        <lb/>but by cultivating them in rich ſoils, and covering <lb/>them from light and air, by
        tying them up, we <lb/>render them wholeſome. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Spinnage, beets and other plants of that kind, <lb/>when wild, contain alſo a very
        bitter oil, ſo as not <lb/>to be eatable; but by cultivation in rich ſoils they <lb/>loſe
        this oil. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>In the ſame manner, aſparagus contains oil ſo <pb n="22"/>
        <lb/>ſtimulating, that, if eaten wild, would bliſter the <lb/>tongue; but by cultivating it
        in rich ground <lb/>and making uſe only of the young ſhoots, we avoid <lb/>this
        inconvenience: but I ſhall take occaſion to <lb/>mention this and every other article more
        fully <lb/>hereafter. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>None of theſe plants alone afford much nou- <lb/>riſhment: we uſe them to correct the
        putreſcency <lb/>of animal food, and particularly in the ſummer, <lb/>as not ſtimulating. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>They are apt to ferment, and turn ſour in a <lb/>weak ſtomach, and in fermenting, will
        let looſe <lb/>the air contained in them, and occaſion wind: <lb/>when perſons find this,
        they ſhould refrain from <lb/>eating them, till their ſtomach grows ſtronger; <lb/>for by
        continuing to take down ſuch things as <lb/>diſagree with them, they not only diſorder them-
        <lb/>ſelves for the preſent, but will, in time, ſo injure <lb/>their digeſtive organs, as to
        be hereafter at- <lb/>tended with dreadful conſequences. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Peas, beans, kidney-beans, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> are more fla- <lb/>tulent or
        windy ſtill; eſpecially when eaten <lb/>unripe, as is always done: ſuch perſons there-
        <lb/>fore with whom they diſagree, ſhould by no <lb/>means eat them. </p>
      <pb n="23"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>With reſpect to eſculent roots; theſe contain <lb/>mucilage, ſugar and farrinaceous
        matter, that is, <lb/>flour. The two laſt afford much nouriſhment, <lb/>but the mucilage
        does little elſe than forward <lb/>fermentation. The more mucilaginous and watery <lb/>theſe
        roots are, the more apt they are to ferment <lb/>and correct the putreſcency of animal food,
        and <lb/>conſequently the fitter to be eaten in warm wea- <lb/>ther. But the more ſugar and
        flour they contain, <lb/>the more they nouriſh. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Turneps, radiſhes, onions, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> are equally as <lb/>liable to
        ferment and correct putreſcency, as the <lb/>herbs ſpringing from theſe roots; and as they
        <lb/>contain a greater quantity of ſugar than their re- <lb/>ſpective herbs, they are more
        nutritive. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Carrots, parſneps, artichokes, Jeruſalem arti- <lb/>chokes, <hi rend="italic"
          >&amp;c.</hi> contain much ſugar and farrinaceous <lb/>matter, but very little mucilage.
        Theſe are <lb/>wholeſome, nutritive, and eaſy of digeſtion. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The ſugar adds much to the nutritive quality of <lb/>the farrinaceous matter in all
        theſe ſubſtances. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Potatoes, yams, earth-nuts, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> contain flour <lb/>almoſt
        alone, with very little ſugar, but more <lb/>water than we find in farrinaceous ſeeds. How-
          <pb n="24"/>
        <lb/>ever, the farrinaceous matter is the ſame in both, <lb/>and is coagulable by heat. We
        boil them and <lb/>roaſt them, to deſtroy their viſcidity. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It was but lately that theſe roots were introduced <lb/>into Europe for food. They are
        as nutritive as <lb/>wheat flour, but cannot be ſo well made into <lb/>bread without a
        mixture of flour, as they will not <lb/>readily ferment without ſome ſuch mixture. One
        <lb/>reaſon for our not growing them ſo generally as <lb/>wheat, is, that they are more apt
        to fail in the <lb/>produce. The crop is not equally certain. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It is not yet determined, whether muſhrooms <lb/>are animals or vegetables. They have
        all the <lb/>properties of animal-food, and muſt be conſidered <lb/>as ſuch. </p>
      <div type="chapter">
        <head rend="size(1.25) align-center space">
          <lb/> FRUITS. </head>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">F</hi>RUITS contain ſugar, native vegetable <lb/>acid, and mucilage;
          and their ſkins contain <lb/>more or leſs an aſtringent juice; but ſo little of it,
          <lb/>as not to render them unwholeſome. Nay, it is <lb/>rather of ſervice, as it
          ſtimulates the ſtomach, <lb/>cauſes it to contract ſtrongly, and thus prevents <lb/>the
          fruit becoming acid and flatulent. The <pb n="25"/>
          <lb/>ſugar, acids and mucilage are capable of fer- <lb/>menting and being converted into
          blood. As <lb/>ſugar affords more nouriſhment than any other <lb/>ſubſtance, ſuch fruits
          as are ſweeteſt are the moſt <lb/>wholeſome, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> figs, grapes, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Sugar is even more nutritive than flour, but <lb/>it is ſeldom thoroughly digeſted;
          being ſo very <lb/>ſoluble, it paſſes off from the ſtomach before <lb/>any change can take
          place in it, but entangled <lb/>in the cells of fruit, it is retained longer in <lb/>the
          ſtomach, ſo as to yield ſome nouriſhment. <lb/>So again, it is not apt to ferment in the
          ſto- <lb/>mach alone, but mixed with the mucilage of <lb/>fruits, fermentation readily
          takes place. Beſides, <lb/>the acid of fruits helps to correct the <choice>
            <corr>putreſcency</corr>
            <sic>putrecency</sic>
          </choice>
          <lb/>of animal food. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The more diluted ſugar is, the more apt it <lb/>is to ferment. Hence, watry or
          mucilaginous <lb/>fruits, with little ſugar, as gooſberries, currants, <lb/>cherries, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> afford but little nouriſhment, but <lb/>then they tend more
          to correct putreſcency. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Such as contain much ſugar and leſs water <lb/>and mucilage, are not ſo apt to
          ferment, con- <lb/>ſequently are not ſo proper to correct <choice>
            <corr>putreſcency</corr>
            <sic>putrecency</sic>
          </choice>; <lb/>but then they are more nutritive than ſuch as <pb n="26"/>
          <lb/>contain more mucilage and water, and leſs ſugar. <lb/>They afford ſo much
          nouriſhment, that in many <lb/>countries they are uſed as food: thus, figs, dates,
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> in Portugal, are eaten as common food. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>By evaporating the water from fruits, that is <lb/>by drying them, we leſſen their
          diſpoſition to <lb/>ferment, conſequently, we make them leſs flatulent <lb/>and more
          nutritive. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The fermentation of ſome fruits in the ſto- <lb/>mach, have, by letting looſe the
          air, ſometimes <lb/>ſo diſtended it as to prove fatal; but we may <lb/>correct this by
          adding ſugar to them or ſpices. <lb/>However, ſuch as find they diſagree with them,
          <lb/>if they value their health, ſhould refrain from <lb/>eating them. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Fruits containing a great quantity of native <lb/>vegetable acid, afford ſo little
          nouriſhment, <lb/>(as lemons, oranges, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>) that we ſeldom uſe
          <lb/>them, but as a power acting on the ſtomach, to <lb/>correct the bad properties of
          other food; as will <lb/>be ſhewn hereafter. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Sour fruits, eaten in autumn, have been ac- <lb/>cuſed of bringing on violent
          continued purgings, <lb/>but without any reaſon. Indeed ſome ſour <pb n="27"/>
          <lb/>fruits will act as purgatives, and the purging ſhall <lb/>continue; but this muſt be
          owing to the ſtate of <lb/>the body, prediſpoſed to purge; for we find, <lb/>that when
          fruit purges a body, not prediſpoſed <lb/>to purge, no purging continues when the fruit
          <lb/>is evacuated. In hot ſummers, when there is <lb/>great plenty of fruit, dyſenteries
          or continued <lb/>purgings are apt to be general, but this is owing <lb/>to the heat of
          the weather; for perſons will be <lb/>afflicted with dyſentery, who eat no fruit. In
          <lb/>ſhort, in ſuch diſorders they counteract; and <lb/>thoſe who eat no fruit, are more
          apt to <lb/>purge, than ſuch as do. Nay, if large quantities <lb/>of fruit ſhould purge,
          it will not prove dan- <lb/>gerous; it will act no further than as a doſe of <lb/>phyſic. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>There is one ſpecies of fruit very different <lb/>from others, namely, cucumbers,
          melons, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
          <lb/>This fruit, either ripe or unripe, contains a great <lb/>deal of mucilage of a
          particular kind. Break <lb/>them in two, and you will ſee much of this muci- <lb/>lage
          ooze out, ſo as to glue the two parts firmly <lb/>together. Now, this mucilage prevents
          the other <lb/>parts of the fruit from fermenting, conſequently <lb/>cauſes indigeſtion,
          and brings on in the ſtomach <lb/>a ſenſe of weight, coldneſs and ſickneſs; for
          <lb/>though the ſubſtance be ſoft, it will not readily <pb n="28"/>
          <lb/>diſſolve. Cucumbers have been known to lie in <lb/>the ſtomach three days undigeſted.
          We are <lb/>led to uſe them in the ſummer as cooling food; <lb/>but they are very
          injurious to the conſtitution. <lb/>Beſides, they contain a quantity of eſſential oil,
          <lb/>(which no vegetable ſubſtance does) very diſa- <lb/>greeable and hurtful to a weak
          ſtomach. If they <lb/>are eaten, therefore, it ſhould be with oil and <lb/>pepper, as
          correctors of their noxious qualities. <lb/>There is a natural bitter in the ſkin of the
          cucum- <lb/>ber, which will ſerve to digeſt it, if eaten at the <lb/>ſame time; but this
          ſhould only be done when <lb/>the cucumber is young, as it afterwards becomes
          <lb/>injurious to the ſtomach. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Having now treated of the properties and <lb/>wholeſomeneſs of vegetable food, we
          will <lb/>proceed next to animal; and herein we will firſt conſider <lb/>the propriety of
          uſing it. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It has been given as a reaſon for not uſing <lb/>animal food, that it was
          inconſiſtent with <lb/>humanity. There can, however, be little diffi- <lb/>culty about
          this, as there are a great num- <lb/>ber of animals that muſt live on animal food
          <lb/>wholly, not being able to eat vegetable. It was <lb/>therefore the intention of the
          Creator, that ani- <lb/>mal food ſhould be eaten. All that is to be con- <pb n="29"/>
          <lb/>ſidered, is, whether man is that animal that <lb/>is deſtined to live upon animal
          food. The <lb/>Pythagorean doctrine, heightened by ſuperſti- <lb/>tion, has been a means
          of making numbers of <lb/>people, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> the whole of the Gentoos,
          the whole <lb/>empire of Hindoſtan, and part of China, larger <lb/>together than France,
          Spain, Italy, and Eng- <lb/>land, wholly abſtain from meat. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It is alſo to be obſerved, that the race of parti- <lb/>cular animals is ſeldom
          diminiſhed, tho' we deſtroy <lb/>many of them; the increaſe of animals being <lb/>much
          below what <hi rend="italic">might</hi> be propagated. One <lb/>man and one woman might,
          in the nature of <lb/>things, have thirty children; but, in general, <lb/>they may have
          ten, five boys and five girls. At <lb/>every generation, then, were men propagated to
          <lb/>the utmoſt, they could increaſe in number <lb/>five times; ſo that, in a very ſhort
          time, a nation <lb/>muſt become exceedingly populous. It is the <lb/>difficulty of
          procuring food, and obtaining the <lb/>neceſſaries and conveniencies of life that prevents
          <lb/>this propagation: A proof of the ſuperintendency <lb/>of Providence. Now as it is in
          man, ſo is it in <lb/>other animals. It is poſſible for a ſow to bring <lb/>forth ten pigs
          at every litter, ſo that were this <lb/>ſpecies propagated to the utmoſt, in a few
          <lb/>years, the increaſe would be prodigious. Ten- <pb n="30"/>
          <lb/>fold in one year, and a thouſand-fold in ten years. <lb/>Here alſo the difficulty of
          obtaining food prevents <lb/>increaſe; there being always a deſire of propa- <lb/>gation
          between the ſexes. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>This is more evident, if we obſerve the great <lb/>increaſe of rats in a granary,
          where they multiply, <lb/>in proportion to the quantity of corn there <lb/>lodged. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Theſe things conſidered, we may readily ſee, <lb/>that in deſtroying annually a
          number of any one <lb/>ſpecies of animals, ſo far from diminiſhing that <lb/>ſpecies, we
          ſhall rather increaſe it, as in ſuch a <lb/>caſe, we ſhall be anxious ſo to do. So, by
          ſending <lb/>a number of inhabitants out of a country, we do <lb/>not depopulate that
          country, unleſs we exceed a <lb/>certain bounds. Animals then living on one <lb/>another,
          is the means of increaſing animal life <lb/>conſiderably: there can be, therefore, no
          reaſon <lb/>why animal-food ſhould not be uſed. Let us <lb/>examine, then, whether this
          food be proper. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Moſt quadrupeds are confined naturally to par- <lb/>ticular climates, and moſt of
          them, in their or- <lb/>gans of digeſtion, fitted for animal and vegetable <lb/>food. Some
          have it only in their power to obtain <lb/>animal food, and ſome only vegetable; but man
            <pb n="31"/>
          <lb/>ſeems deſtined to cover the whole face of the <lb/>earth; no climate being yet
          diſcovered unfit for <lb/><hi rend="italic">his</hi> reſidence. His powers are fitted for
          animal <lb/>as well as vegetable food, and his digeſtive organs <lb/>equally adapted to
          both. And, if we conſider <lb/>mankind in their moſt ſimple ſtate, where they <lb/>are
          moſt guided by inſtinct, we find as many <lb/>ſhepherds and hunters living on animal food,
          as <lb/>huſbandmen living on vegetable. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Animals deſtined to live on animal food, have <lb/>their inteſtinal canal ſhorter
          than ſuch as live on <lb/>vegetable food. That is (in order to be under- <lb/>ſtood by
          ſuch as are unacquainted with phyſical <lb/>terms) have leſs length of gut. And as longer
          <lb/>retention in the ſtomach is required for animal <lb/>food than for vegetable, and
          man's digeſtive or- <lb/>gans are adapted to this, it appears that man is <lb/>deſtined to
          live equally on animal food, as vege- <lb/>table. Further, the teeth of man are a medium
          <lb/>between the teeth of carnivorous animals, and <lb/><choice>
            <corr/>
            <sic>and </sic>
          </choice>thoſe of grameniverous. Beſides, his health <lb/>is better ſupported by a mixture
          of the two, than <lb/>it would be, was he to live upon one. The Lap- <lb/>landers, indeed,
          live nine months on rein-deer, <lb/>and the Greenlander lives upon fiſh: it is poſſi-
          <lb/>ble, therefore, to live on animal food alone. How- <pb n="32"/>
          <lb/>ever, were we obliged to live upon one ſort wholly, <lb/>it would be beſt to live on
          vegetable; for animal <lb/>food alone, would frequently bring on diſeaſes; a <lb/>mixture
          therefore is beſt. In ſhort, man is endowed <lb/>with greater variety in his ſyſtem and
          conſtitution <lb/>than any other animal, he being deſtined to live <lb/>in all parts of
          the earth. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Let us next conſider the differences between <lb/>animal and vegetable food. Now, as
          we ſaid <lb/>before, fermentation which takes place in food, <lb/>within the ſtomach, is
          different from that which <lb/>takes place out of it. If the ſtomach then <lb/>be weak, ſo
          as not to bring on fermentation na- <lb/>tural to it, the fermentation that would take
          <lb/>place out of the ſtomach, will take place in it. <lb/>Hence it is, that in weak
          ſtomachs, food turns <lb/>acid and putrid. This firſt occaſions heart-burn, <lb/>a ſure
          ſign of a weak ſtomach; and if the putre- <lb/>faction ſhould run to a great height, the
          conſe- <lb/>quence is ſickneſs, vomiting, purging, and ſome- <lb/>times fever. And ſhould
          a ſmall quantity of ſuch <lb/>putrified matter, as was obſerved before, be ab- <lb/>ſorbed
          by the veſſels, in its paſſage through the <lb/>body, it will depreſs the ſtrength, and,
          without <lb/>a timely remedy, cauſe a general putrefaction of <lb/>the fluids through the
          whole ſyſtem. Thus the <pb n="33"/>
          <lb/>miſchiefs of animal food, putrifying, are greater <lb/>and more dangerous than ſuch
          as ariſe from <lb/>undigeſted vegetable food, as this turns ſour <lb/>only. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Another difference is this. Vegetable food, <lb/>during digeſtion, ſtimulates leſs.
          When the ſto- <lb/>mach is diſtended with food, the whole ſyſtem, <lb/>during digeſtion,
          is more or leſs ſtimulated; but <lb/>more ſo with animal food than with vegetable.
          <lb/>Now, the more our ſyſtem is ſtimulated, the <lb/>quicker is the circulation and the
          more feveriſh we <lb/>become. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>As animal food fills the blood-veſſels fuller <lb/>with blood than vegetable, it
          naturally encreaſes <lb/>our muſcular ſtrength; but then it loads the brain, <lb/>(every
          part being fuller of blood in proportion) <lb/>and occaſions heavineſs and ſtupor: whereas
          <lb/>vegetable food, from not loading the ſyſtem with <lb/>blood, rather diminiſhes
          muſcular ſtrength, but <lb/>enables the mind to act with greater force. Ve- <lb/>getable
          food, therefore, is fitter to give clearneſs <lb/>of ideas; and animal food is beſt
          adapted to <lb/>labour. A phyſical demonſtration might be <lb/>given of this; but to a
          general reader it would be <lb/>idle. However, habit has a great effect in this <lb/>caſe.
          Man accuſtomed to labour, and to eat ve- <pb n="34"/>
          <lb/>getable food, (as are the porters of Conſtantino- <lb/>ple) may be capable of great
          muſcular exertion; <lb/>but this does not prove the power of vegetable <lb/>food over
          animal. So a horſe fed on graſs, and <lb/>kept in exerciſe, will be better able to work,
          than <lb/>one fed on hay and corn for twelve months toge- <lb/>ther, without exerciſe: but
          this neither is any <lb/>proof. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The next thing to be conſidered is, a maxim <lb/>generally laid down by all authors
          on this ſubject; <lb/>namely, that ſimplicity of food is more conducive <lb/>to health
          than a variety: but experience teaches <lb/>us the contrary. Milk, as we before obſerved,
          <lb/>which affords great nouriſhment, is a mixture of <lb/>three nutritive ſubſtances; and
          we may venture to <lb/>affirm, that if an alderman was to eat as much of <lb/>beef-ſtakes,
          as he does of other things at a <lb/>city-feaſt, he would bring on ſickneſs and vomit-
          <lb/>ing. Put variety of grain before a hen, and ſhe <lb/>will eat of that ſhe likes beſt;
          but before the <lb/>day is out, ſhe will eat of the other. Inſtinct <lb/>leads her to
          this, as moſt conducive to her <lb/>health. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Almoſt all food contains oil, and the ſtomach <lb/>can better bear a variety of this
          oil, than a quan- <lb/>tity of one particular ſort. Beſides, animal and <pb n="35"/>
          <lb/>vegetable food correct the ill qualities of one <lb/>another. Animal food corrects
          the flatulency of <lb/>vegetable; and vegetable food, the putreſcency <lb/>of animal.
          Indeed, a mixture of ſome foods <lb/>will diſagree, as fiſh and milk; fiſh coagulating
          <lb/>milk too firmly for eaſy digeſtion; but there is <lb/>no rule without an exception. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The miſchief of variety of food is its tempt- <lb/>ing us to eat too much: but if we
          avoid <lb/>eating too much, variety is beſt, provided that <lb/>variety conſiſts of things
          eaſy of digeſtion. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But the moſt ſingular and curious circumſtance, <lb/>with reſpect to food, is this.
          The powers of di- <lb/>geſtion are adapted to the want of blood in the <lb/>blood-veſſels.
          If they are not ſufficiently full for the <lb/>purpoſes of health, the appetite is great,
          digeſtion <lb/>is ſtrong, and much blood is formed; but if they <lb/>are full enough,
          there is no appetite, digeſtion is <lb/>weak, and no blood is formed. For, let a man
          <lb/>ſwallow as much food as he can, without an appe- <lb/>tite, though he is able to
          digeſt it, it will not be <lb/>converted into blood. So watchful is Nature of <lb/>her
          health. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Eating too much food, in general, for a length <lb/>of time does harm. It weakens the
          organs of <pb n="36"/>
          <lb/>digeſtion, debilitates the conſtitution, and wears <lb/>it out. Hence ariſe gout,
          apoplexy, and all the <lb/>diſeaſes attendant on old age. In diſeaſe, men, <lb/>eating too
          much, never eſcape with impunity. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>We ſhall now proceed to the properties of the <lb/>different kinds of animal food.
          There are two <lb/>ſubſtances in meat capable of nouriſhing; muci- <lb/>lage and expreſſed
          oil. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Animal mucilages differ much from one ano- <lb/>ther; but conſidered as food, they do
          not. The <lb/>only difference of conſequence is, as far as de- <lb/>pends upon their
          texture. When the fibres of <lb/>an animal are large, they are not eaſily diſſolved;
          <lb/>of courſe, they are difficult of digeſtion. Beef is, <lb/>on this account, more
          difficult of digeſtion than <lb/>mutton; the fibres of the one being larger than
          <lb/>thoſe of the other. On the ſame principles, when <lb/>food is coagulated firmly, it
          is alſo difficult of <lb/>digeſtion. The firmer the coagulum, that is, the <lb/>leſs fluid
          it contains, the more difficult it will be <lb/>of digeſtion. Animal food, whoſe fibres
          have <lb/>but little fluid between them; that is, dry meat, <lb/>is more indigeſtible than
          moiſt. Thus, lean ani- <lb/>mals are harder of digeſtion than fat ones; and <lb/>the lean
          part of fat meat is eaſier of digeſtion than <lb/>the lean part of lean meat. By the ſame
          way of <pb n="37"/>
          <lb/>reaſoning, meat roaſted or boiled a great deal, is <lb/>not ſo digeſtible as when
          roaſted or boiled but <lb/>little; for when the fluids are expelled by heat, <lb/>the
          fibres approach cloſer to each other, and, <lb/>when in the ſtomach, will not admit the
          juice of <lb/>the ſtomach ſo readily to penetrate it, conſe- <lb/>quently, fermentation
          will not take place ſo <lb/>ſoon. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The readier animal food diſſolves in water, the <lb/>more digeſtible it is. A
          flounder boiled in an <lb/>equal quantity of water, is ſooner diſſolved than <lb/>mutton;
          therefore flounders are eaſier of digeſtion <lb/>than mutton; the juice of the ſtomach
          being <lb/>little elſe than warm water, helped by fermenta- <lb/>tion. But fiſh, though
          readily ſoluble in water, <lb/>has a property in it that renders it indigeſtible,
          <lb/>which is a certain glarineſs or viſcidity; but when <lb/>the ſtomach is ſtrong enough
          to digeſt it, it is <lb/>eaſier of digeſtion than either fleſh or fowl. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Meat apt to putrify, is ſooner digeſted, than <lb/>ſuch as is not. Pidgeon will
          putrify ſooner than <lb/>duck: of courſe, pidgeon is eaſier of digeſtion <lb/>than duck.
          Now, as the fluids in animal food <lb/>tend to haſten putrefaction; by depriving it of
          <lb/>thoſe fluids, by long boiling or roaſting, we ren- <lb/>der it harder of digeſtion.
          By boiling meat till <pb n="38"/>
          <lb/>it be free from gravy, we can keep it from cor- <lb/>rupting for ſix months. A
          further proof that <lb/>meat much dreſſed, is leſs wholeſome than ſuch <lb/>as is little
          dreſſed. Such meats, however, as <lb/>putrify the ſooneſt, are injurious to weak ſto-
          <lb/>machs, as this putreſcency ſtimulates during the <lb/>time of digeſtion. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It is with a view of rendering meat eaſier of <lb/>digeſtion, that we keep it ſome
          time after it is <lb/>killed before we eat it. As ſoon as meat is <lb/>killed, it begins
          to putrify; and putrefaction is <lb/>the moſt effectual breaker down of animal ſub-
          <lb/>ſtance, and a great aſſiſtant to ſolution, which is <lb/>the immediate forerunner of
          digeſtion. But the <lb/>length of time meat ought to be kept, ſhould <lb/>be proportioned
          to its tendency to putrify, <lb/>and the heat of the weather. It is eaten, <lb/>for
          example, much ſooner in ſummer than in <lb/>winter. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But the property in which meats differ moſt, is <lb/>their viſcidity or glarineſs.
          Such as are viſcid, <lb/>adhere to the ſides of the ſtomach, and ſtimulate <lb/>much. In
          quadrupeds, young animals have this <lb/>property, ſuch as veal, pig, fawn, and lamb; but
          <lb/>in a ſmaller degree. Young birds have the ſame <lb/>bad property, and all fiſh, in a
          great degree; par- <pb n="39"/>
          <lb/>ticularly ſhell-fiſh, which on this account, have <lb/>often proved poiſonous and
          fatal to many. When <lb/>theſe have proved fatal, it has been aſcribed to the <lb/>copper
          veſſel in which they were dreſſed; but <lb/>a little obſervation would ſhew the contrary.
          <lb/>When perſons loſe their lives by the ill effects of <lb/>copper; ſickneſs, vomiting,
          and purging take <lb/>place: but when poiſoned by ſhell-fiſh, the head <lb/>ſwells, the
          breaſt is oppreſſed, and ſtupor is the <lb/>conſequence. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Animal food diſſolved in water, forms a gela- <lb/>tinous ſolution or jelly, which is
          of a viſcid na- <lb/>ture, and in ſome degree, produces the ſame ef- <lb/>fect as viſcid
          foods. It ſtimulates, but does not <lb/>yield much nouriſhment. At the ſame time, it is
          <lb/>difficult of digeſtion, and of courſe, improper to <lb/>be taken by diſeaſed or weak
          ſtomachs. Jellies, <lb/>though long preſcribed to ſtrengthen the ſyſtem <lb/>after a
          fever, have lately been found prejudicial, <lb/>and the uſe of them are therefore
          exploded. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Eſſential oils, inherent in ſome animal food, <lb/>render it difficult of digeſtion.
          The eſſential oils <lb/>of vegetables are often agreeable to the ſtomach, <lb/>and
          ſtimulate it ſo as to forward digeſtion; but <lb/>thoſe of animal food, though agreeable
          to the <lb/>taſte, are injurious. Pork, geeſe, ducks, ſalmon, <pb n="40"/>
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> contain much of this oil; and are of courſe,
          <lb/>high-flavoured. They may be agreeable to the <lb/>taſte of ſtrong ſtomachs; but if
          eaten in too great <lb/>quantities, or if the ſtomach be too weak, they <lb/>will diſagree
          with it, and have the ſame effect <lb/>with viſcidity; that is, they will ſtimulate the
          <lb/>ſyſtem, and ſometimes bring on a fever. Animal <lb/>food then, that is viſcid, that
          contains much eſ- <lb/>ſential oil, or will not readily diſſolve, is apt to re- <lb/>main
          too long in the ſtomach, and do harm. But <lb/>that which will readily putrify and
          diſſolve, is re- <lb/>tained but a ſhort time in the ſtomach; and is, <lb/>of courſe,
          eaſily digeſted: for digeſtion depending <lb/>on the contraction of the ſtomach, if the
          ſtomach <lb/>be ſo diſordered as to loſe any of its contractile <lb/>powers, either by the
          oil or viſcidity of the food, <lb/>the food will be retained too long in it. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>We ſeldom uſe animal food without ſome pre- <lb/>paration. Thoſe preparations are
          either expoſing <lb/>them to ſuch heat as will coagulate the ſolids and <lb/>fluids, or
          after ſuch coagulation, diſſolving them <lb/>in water. By coagulating any animal ſolid, we
          <lb/>take off that viſcidity which almoſt all have when <lb/>raw, and the ſtomach
          conſequently bears it much <lb/>better. Thus we can digeſt twice the quantity of
          <lb/>oyſters roaſted, that we can raw. </p>
        <pb n="41"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In coagulating animal ſubſtances by heat, we <lb/>often expoſe them to great fire, as
          in roaſting; <lb/>which coagulates the outer parts, forming a cruſt, <lb/>as it were,
          round the inward fluids, and retaining <lb/>them. This gives them an empyreumatic oil,
          <lb/>offenſive to the ſmell. In boiling, we avoid <lb/>this empyreumatic, but then we take
          out the <lb/>eſſential oil. In frying, we retain both oils, <lb/>ſo that fried meat is
          more difficult of digeſtion <lb/>than either roaſted or boiled. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Chicken, partridges, veal, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> are more whole- <lb/>ſome
          when roaſted, than boiled. Mutton, beef, <lb/>pork, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> are
          eaſier digeſted when boiled. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>All quadrupeds that feed on vegetables are <lb/>uſed, ſomewhere or other, for food;
          ſuch as the <lb/>ox, the ſheep, the deer, the goat, the hog, the <lb/>hare, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> In ſome countries, horſes are eaten; <lb/>in others,
          ſquirrels, rats, and mice. Animals <lb/>that live on animal food alone, are ſeldom eaten;
          <lb/>as the lion, the cat, the tyger, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> Few make <lb/>uſe of
          dogs, or any animals of that claſs; thoſe <lb/>who do, feed them on vegetables. Such
          animals <lb/>as live on animal food alone, being, on account of <lb/>their putreſcency,
          and of the great quantity of <lb/>eſſential oil contained in them, both diſagreeable <lb/><choice>
            <corr>on</corr>
            <sic>o</sic>
          </choice> the ſtomach, and difficult of digeſtion. </p>
        <pb n="42"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Birds alſo are made uſe of for food, except birds <lb/>of prey; that is, ſuch as live
          on other birds; <lb/>and we except them for the ſame reaſons that we <lb/>do beaſts of
          prey. We prefer ſuch as live on <lb/>inſects to ſuch as feed on fiſh, becauſe they are
          <lb/>tenderer; ſuch as live on fiſh acquiring a tough- <lb/>neſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>All fiſh have been eaten, and all ſhell-fiſh <lb/>which have ſufficient muſcular
          fleſh to render them <lb/>worth eating. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Thoſe birds that are not very putreſcent in <lb/>their nature, and are moſt free from
          eſſential oil, <lb/>are the eaſieſt of digeſtion. As for example, <lb/>moor-game, poultry,
          partridges, pheaſants, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c</hi>; <lb/>and of quadrupeds, the deer,
          the ſheep, the ox, <lb/><hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> The older animals of this claſs are
          eaſier of <lb/>digeſtion than the young ones. Mutton, for in- <lb/>ſtance, is eaſier of
          digeſtion than lamb; beef <lb/>than veal; veniſon than fawn; and that on ac- <lb/>count of
          the viſcidity of the fleſh of young ani- <lb/>mals. Fiſh is more difficult of digeſtion
          than <lb/>fleſh, eſpecially in weak ſtomachs. And of fiſh, <lb/>thoſe that have leaſt
          flavour, that is, ſuch as have <lb/>leaſt eſſential oil in them, are white, and have ſome
          <lb/>degree of firmneſs, will digeſt much ſooner than <pb n="43"/>
          <lb/>ſuch as are of ſtronger flavour. Flounders, whitings, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >&amp;c.</hi> are eaſier of digeſtion than ſalmon, foals, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But ſtill, quadrupeds afford more nouriſhment <lb/>than either birds or fiſh; and
          thoſe animals of <lb/>ſtronger flavour, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> pork, geeſe, duck,
          ſalmon, <lb/><hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> afford more nouriſhment and are fitter for
          <lb/>ſuch as labour or take a great deal of exerciſe, <lb/>than animals of the ſame claſs,
          that are eaſier of <lb/>digeſtion. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Now, to correct the ill qualities of the different <lb/>kind of food, and to aſſiſt
          digeſtion, we make <lb/>uſe of a variety of things, ſuch as are called the
          <lb/>decoraments of the table; which in themſelves af- <lb/>ford little or no nouriſhment.
          Theſe are ſpices, <lb/>acids, ſalt, oil, and ſugar. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Spices act as ſtimulants. It muſt here be re- <lb/>collected, that digeſtion depends
          upon the con- <lb/>tracting power of the ſtomach, it being that <lb/>which prevents the
          food turning acid or putrid. <lb/>Now, if the action of the ſtomach be weak, that <lb/>is,
          not ſufficiently powerful, food will not be pro- <lb/>perly digeſted. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Spices then are powerful ſtimulants, that is, <lb/>they encreaſe the action of the
          ſtomach, and are <pb n="44"/>
          <lb/>agreeable to it; ſuch as the aromatic ſpices, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
          <lb/>cinnamon, cloves, nutmeg, mace, pimento, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
          <lb/>which are the produce of the warmer climates; <lb/>but they are, at the ſame time,
          inflammatory, <lb/>tending to encreaſe the circulation of the blood, <lb/>and bring on
          fever. We uſe muſtard, onions, <lb/>horſe-raddiſh, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> for the
          ſame purpoſe. Theſe <lb/>ſtimulate univerſally, but are not inflammatory; <lb/>becauſe
          their powers do not continue long; where- <lb/>as ſpices ſtimulate for a conſiderable
          length of <lb/>time. Mint, thyme, ſage, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> parſley, fennel,
          cele- <lb/>ry, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> are ſtimulants, but not ſo powerful as
          <lb/>muſtard, onions, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> nor are they inflammatory. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Spices ſeem adapted to different climates, and <lb/>different ſtomachs. In warm
          climates, and weak <lb/>ſtomachs, ſpices are more wholeſome than in <lb/>colder climates,
          and ſtronger ſtomachs. In warm <lb/>climates, the heat of the atmoſphere upon the ſkin
          <lb/>keeps up conſtant great circulation there. The <lb/>internal blood-veſſels are, of
          courſe, empty, and <lb/>the interior parts conſequently weaker, <hi rend="italic"
            >viz.</hi> the <lb/>ſtomach, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> It requires therefore more
          pow- <lb/>erful ſtimulants to aſſiſt digeſtion, and the natural <lb/>weakneſs of the
          ſtomach prevents their inflamma- <lb/>tory power. Hence, we may obſerve, that ſpices
          <lb/>are more wholeſome in ſummer than in winter; <lb/>and that perſons of luxurious life,
          who live with- <lb/>out exerciſe, whoſe ſtomachs are, of courſe, weak- <pb n="45"/>
          <lb/>ened and impaired, may eat them with greater <lb/>ſafety than ſuch as are ſtrong,
          laborious, and <lb/>healthful. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>In colder climates, and with temperate livers, <lb/>the ſtomach is naturally ſtrong:
          very little ſtimu- <lb/>lants, therefore, are required. Inflammatory ones <lb/>muſt, of
          courſe, do miſchief. If any, then, are <lb/>uſed, it ſhould be thoſe of the ſecond claſs,
            <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
          <lb/>muſtard, onions, horſe-raddiſh, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> Nature ſeems <lb/>here
          to have provided for herſelf; for we find <lb/>ſpices only in warm countries: none grow
          natu- <lb/>rally in cold ones. But the ſecond claſs are prin- <lb/>cipally natives of cold
          climates. If any of the <lb/>ſpices are made to grow in a cold climate, part of <lb/>their
          ſtimulus is loſt; and if the ſecond claſs of <lb/>ſtimulants are made to grow in a warm
          climate, <lb/>it is the ſame. Pepper grown here loſes its <lb/>ſtimulating powers; and an
          onion grown in Spain, <lb/>is not ſo ſtrong as one, the produce of England. <lb/>They ſeem
          deſtined then for particular climates. <lb/>In hot countries, therefore, ſpices are
          neceſſary; <lb/>but in colder ones, they are prejudicial. If the <lb/>ſtomach then be
          weak, which, in time, will diſor- <lb/>der the ſyſtem, it may be proper, to uſe ſpices,
          <lb/>but, if not weak, on no account to uſe them; for <lb/>they have ſometimes done ſo
          much harm, as to- <lb/>tally to deſtroy digeſtion, unleſs great quantities <lb/>have been
          conſtantly thrown in with the food. </p>
        <pb n="46"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A little ſpice, uſed with the more flatulent vege- <lb/>tables, is frequently
          ſerviceable, as by encreaſing <lb/>the action of the ſtomach, it brings on digeſtion,
          <lb/>before that fermentation takes place, which in <lb/>weak ſtomachs, would be attended
          with extrica- <lb/>tion of air. Thus, we uſe pepper with greens, <lb/>peas, &amp;c. to
          correct what is called their windi- <lb/>neſs; and we uſe pepper with broth, to coagulate
          <lb/>the fluid more firmly, and correct its putre- <lb/>ſcency, both which are brought
          about by the action <lb/>of the ſtomach. Lemon-juice, barley, <hi rend="italic"
            >&amp;c.</hi> is <lb/>often added to both, for the ſame purpoſe. So <lb/>we eat muſtard
          with ſalted pork and beef, ſalted <lb/>fiſh, &amp;c. in order to aſſiſt digeſtion, by
          encreaſing <lb/>the action of the ſtomach; ſalted proviſions being <lb/><choice>
            <corr/>
            <sic>being </sic>
          </choice>more difficult of digeſtion than ſuch as are <lb/>freſh. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The ſecond claſs of ſubſtances to aſſiſt digeſtion <lb/>are acids. None but the
          native vegetable acid, <lb/><hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> the juice of ſour fruits, is
          capable of afford- <lb/>ing nouriſhment; nor would this, if pure; it is <lb/>owing to the
          mucilage mixed with it, that it <lb/>nouriſhes. Acids then <hi rend="italic"
              ><unclear>aſſiſt</unclear></hi> digeſtion merely. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Acids produce many effects. In the firſt <lb/>place, they ſtimulate the glands of the
          ſtomach, <lb/>creating by their ſtimulus that ſenſation we call <pb n="47"/>
          <lb/>hunger. Digeſtion being conſiderably affected <lb/>by the appetite; if there is no
          appetite, though <lb/>the ſtomach be ſtrong, there will be no digeſtion<choice>
            <corr>.</corr>
            <sic/>
          </choice>
          <lb/>We frequently then employ acids, a little before <lb/>meals, to create an appetite.
          Thus, in hot <lb/>countries, where owing to an encreaſed circulation <lb/>of the ſkin, the
          internal circulation is diminiſhed, <lb/>and, of courſe, the ſtomach weakened, the in-
          <lb/>habitants accuſtom themſelves to the drinking of <lb/>beverage or lemonade before
          dinner, to encreaſe <lb/>their appetite. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Acids alſo promote ſecretion of the glands of <lb/>the ſtomach, ſo as to ſupply the
          food with a <lb/>watery menſtruum; that is, fluid proper and <lb/>ſufficient to promote
          fermentation. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>They act alſo as ſedatives or quieters of the <lb/>reſt of the ſyſtem, taking off
          that ſtimulus occa- <lb/>ſioned by digeſtion. Hence they are beneficial in <lb/>warm
          climates, and in weather where the heat <lb/>naturally ſtimulates the ſyſtem; and that
          ſtimulus <lb/>is liable to be encreaſed by digeſtion. Hence, as <lb/>was ſaid before,
          fruit is exceeding wholeſome in <lb/>the ſummer, and at certain times, if taken in
          <lb/>moderate quantities. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Acids tend likewiſe to coagulate animal ſolids, <pb n="48"/>
          <lb/>and fluids; and, aſſiſted by the coagulating fluids <lb/>of the ſtomach, they take
          off the viſcidity of food. <lb/>Thus we uſe lemon or vinegar with fiſh, particu-
          <lb/>larly ſhell-fiſh. Indeed, ſhell-fiſh ſhould never be <lb/>eaten without ſome acid;
          they being, as was be- <lb/>fore obſerved, in their nature ſo remarkably viſcid, <lb/>and,
          of courſe, ſo prejudicial to the conſtitution. <lb/>It is for the ſame reaſon, that we uſe
          acids with <lb/>veal, lamb, and all young animals; namely, to <lb/>correct their
          viſcidity. Of all acids, vinegar, <lb/>provided we attend to its quality, is the ſafeſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Acids check alſo vinous and acetous fermenta- <lb/>tion; that is, ſuch fermentation
          as ſhould by no <lb/>means take place in the ſtomach. It is for this <lb/>reaſon we uſe
          them with ſubſtances of looſe tex- <lb/>ture, that are apt to turn ſour in the ſtomach,
          and <lb/>become flatulent or windy. Thus we eat vinegar <lb/>with ſallad, and greens of
          all ſorts. So, in all weak <lb/>ſtomachs, where food is apt to turn ſour, and <lb/>cauſe
          heart-burn, the uſe of acids has been found <lb/>to correct and take it off. It is on this
          account, <lb/>that fruit has been introduced after meals. Acids <lb/>then are uſeful for
          many purpoſes in digeſtion; <lb/>but taken in too great quantities, they are hurt-
          <lb/>ful, as they will produce a diſpoſition to flatu- <lb/>lency, pain, and weakneſs, in
          the ſtomach and <pb n="49"/>
          <lb/>bowels, which is afterwards cured with dif- <lb/>ficulty. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The next ſubſtance, in general uſe with food, <lb/>is ſalt, which affords no kind of
          nouriſhment; <lb/>neither will it digeſt, but paſſes through the body <lb/>without any
          change. It is, however, univerſally <lb/>uſed where it can be got; nay, all animals prefer
          <lb/>food that is ſaltiſh to ſuch as is not. This gene- <lb/>ral inſtinct, we ſhould
          ſuppoſe, would not be <lb/>given, but to ſome purpoſe; yet it is difficult to ſay <lb/>of
          what uſe ſalt is, in digeſtion. It ſtimulates the <lb/>glands of the ſtomach, and promotes
          ſecretion of <lb/>the watery menſtruum; but of what other uſe it is, <lb/>we know not. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>We often preſerve food with ſalt; and thus <lb/>preſerved, it is conſiderably more
          difficult of di- <lb/>geſtion. The fibres are hardened, they are not <lb/>ſo readily
          diſſolved, and they go through the <lb/>proper fermentation of the ſtomach with
          difficulty. <lb/>Thus it is, that we cannot live ſo long on ſalted <lb/>proviſion as on
          freſh; for, as was before obſerved, <lb/>the ſalt does not penetrate thoroughly into all
          <lb/>parts of the meat; therefore, when in the ſto- <lb/>mach, before fermentation takes
          place in the outer <lb/>parts, the inner will putrify, and, by infecting the <lb/>fluids
          of the body, bring on the ſcurvy, as we ſee <pb n="50"/>
          <lb/>it does, in perſons upon a long voyage. And <lb/>yet ſalt may be uſed, in the
          greateſt quantity, <lb/>ſo as to prevent putrefaction of food, without <lb/>rendering it
          totally unfit for nouriſhment. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Oil is another ſubſtance that may be uſed to <lb/>help digeſtion, it taking off the
          viſcidity of food. <lb/>Hence it is, that we eat ſalad, with which oil has <lb/>been
          mixed, with the meat of young animals, as <lb/>with veal, lamb, <hi rend="italic"
            >&amp;c.</hi> and (with ſome kinds of fiſh) <lb/>which, from its glarineſs, tends much
          to diſturb <lb/>digeſtion. Oil alſo takes off the diſpoſition in <lb/>looſe vegetables to
          ferment improperly, and thus <lb/>prevents flatulency. It is for this reaſon, we uſe
          <lb/>it with ſallads, greens, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> But oil, in weak
          <lb/>ſtomachs diſpoſed to acidity, is apt to produce <lb/>ſourneſs in the ſtomach, and
          bring on heart-burn, <lb/>ſickneſs, vomiting, and purging. Why it ſhould <lb/>have theſe
          contrary effects, we cannot ſay; but ex- <lb/>perience ſhews it to be true. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Sugar is another aſſiſtant of digeſtion, by pre- <lb/>venting the bad effects of ſome
          food, and affords <lb/>conſiderable nouriſhment in itſelf. A diluted ſo- <lb/>lution
          ferments more readily than a more cen- <lb/>trated one; that is, the more water you put to
          <lb/>ſugar, provided you exceed not certain bounds, <lb/>the more readily it ferments.
          Sugar mixed with <pb n="51"/>
          <lb/>a certain quantity of water, preſently becomes vi- <lb/>negar. Now, the looſer
          vegetables and fruits, <lb/>ſuch as ſalad, currants, cherries, <hi rend="italic"
            >&amp;c.</hi> contain in <lb/>them a more diluted ſolution of ſugar than the <lb/>firmer
          vegetables, or the ſweeter fruits. It is on <lb/>this account, that we frequently eat
          ſugar with <lb/>them. Another reaſon why we eat ſugar with <lb/>ſuch vegetables, is to
          take off the aceſency and fla- <lb/>tulency which they are apt to run ſoon into, by
          <lb/>rendering them more difficult to ferment. Sugar <lb/>alſo corrects the putreſcency of
          animal food; but <lb/>not ſo much as vegetables do. For this purpoſe, <lb/>it was much
          uſed in England before kitchen- <lb/>gardens became general. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It is not above 150 years ſince greens, and <lb/>other vegetables were imported from
          Holland, <lb/>(a kitchen-garden being then a great curioſity.) <lb/>Salted meat at that
          time, was much eaten; <lb/>and the ſea-ſcurvy very general. Perſons were <lb/>then
          accuſtomed to eat ſugared mutton and ſu- <lb/>gared ham. At preſent, the cuſtom is not ſo
          much <lb/>aboliſhed, but that we eat ſweet ſauces with <lb/>various kinds of food. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Sugar has been ſaid to ſpoil the teeth. This <lb/>obſervation may, in ſome caſes, be
          juſt; as, where <lb/>the teeth may have a more than ordinary degree <pb n="52"/>
          <lb/>of ſenſibility; or it may, perhaps, by ſticking <lb/>about them, and turning acid,
          corrode them: but <lb/>faults of this kind are oftener imputed to it than <lb/>it
          deſerves. The finer the ſugar, the purer and <lb/>leſs noxious it is. Preſerves are far
          from unwhole- <lb/>ſome,—and pickles may be conſidered as ſpunges <lb/>filled with
          vinegar. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Having thus entered into the ſeveral properties <lb/>of eatables, let us now proceed
          to drinks. </p>
        <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="27"/>
      </div>
    </body>
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="3"/>
  </text>
</TEI>
