<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Lettsom: Of the improvement of medicine in London</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>John Coakley Lettsom</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Of the improvement of medicine in London on the basis of public
              good.</title>
            <edition n="2"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T7636</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T7636"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed by James Phillips, for E. and C. Dilly, MDCCLXXV. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1775</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="7"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="56"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">National Library of Medicine</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108126510</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Public welfare and institutional"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="7"/>
    <body>
      <pb n=""/>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>An ornamental horizontal column, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <head rend="sc align-center space">
        <lb/>of the <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">IMPROVEMENT </hi>
        <lb/>of <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">MEDICINE. </hi>
      </head>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>An ornamental horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
          <lb/>SECTION I. <lb/>Plan and Deſign of the General <lb/>Diſpenſary. </head>
        <p>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>Decorative frame around the letter I</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <hi rend="dc(4)">I</hi>T was the ſentiment of an <lb/>ancient Roman, that <q
            rend="diple quotes">no- <lb/>thing brings men nearer the <lb/>Deity, than giving health
            <lb/>to their fellow creatures. </q> The diſ- <lb/>poſition to the relief of diſtreſs
          that pre- <lb/>vails in this city, is a pleaſing example of <lb/>the influence of
          civilization, benevolence, <pb n="2"/>
          <lb/>and piety; and the many hoſpitals, and <lb/>other receptacles for almoſt every
          ſpecies <lb/>of miſery, are proofs of genuine huma- <lb/>nity, which no preceding age ever
          exhi- <lb/>bited. But objects of compaſſion muſt <lb/>ſtill prevail, as the human
          conſtitution is <lb/>ſtill liable to pain and diſeaſe; and when <lb/>pain and diſeaſe are
          united with poverty, <lb/>they form a picture of human woe, that <lb/>muſt naturally
          excite the pity, and en- <lb/>gage the protection of thoſe, who have <lb/>been exempted
          from ſuch accumulated <lb/>miſery. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Theſe conſiderations firſt gave riſe to <lb/>the <hi rend="sc">General
            Dispensary</hi>, as an auxi- <lb/>liary to the hoſpitals in this metropolis, <lb/>in
          order to adminiſter advice and medi- <lb/>cines to the poor, not only at the Diſ-
          <lb/>penſary, but alſo at their own habitations; <lb/>which latter circumſtance is an
          advantage <lb/>peculiar to this plan. And, notwithſtand- <lb/>ing the many excellent
          charities, already <lb/>ſubſiſting for relief of the ſick in and <lb/>about this great
          metropolis; yet, when it <pb n="3"/>
          <lb/>is conſidered how many poor, from the <lb/>nature of their circumſtances and diſor-
          <lb/>ders, are ſtill neceſſarily confined to their <lb/>wretched dwellings, and periſh
          through <lb/>want of proper aſſiſtance, the utility of <lb/>this inſtitution becomes
          obvious. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It is preſumed that this Charity will be <lb/>particularly ſerviceable to ſuch poor
          la- <lb/>bouring families, when viſited with ill- <lb/>neſs, as have not the ability to
          aſſiſt them- <lb/>ſelves, and yet are willing to exert their <lb/>utmoſt endeavours for
          ſupport in ſickneſs <lb/>as well as in health. What pleaſure muſt <lb/>it, therefore,
          afford the benevolent and hu- <lb/>mane, to ſtep in, at this critical time of
          <lb/>diſtreſs, to their aſſiſtance; and to be, <lb/>under Providence, the happy
          inſtruments <lb/>of relieving theſe poor objects from their <lb/>various afflictions! </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>This Charity extends alſo to the diſeaſes <lb/>of children; as it is too evident,
          that <lb/>many of theſe, under a variety of ſlight <lb/>maladies which affect their tender
          frames, <pb n="4"/>
          <lb/>are, by neglect or improper treatment, to- <lb/>tally loſt to the public; or, if they
          ſur- <lb/>vive, are rendered uſeleſs if not burthen- <lb/>ſome members of the community.
          It is <lb/>a melancholy truth, that near half the <lb/>number born in London die under two
          <lb/>years of age. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The ſubſcription is fixed low, with a <lb/>view to render the Charity more extenſive,
          <lb/>and give the induſtrious poor an eaſy op- <lb/>portunity of obtaining recommendations
          <lb/>from their benevolent neighbours, on the <lb/>earlieſt attack of ſickneſs; and
          thereby of <lb/>receiving immediate help, before their diſ- <lb/>eaſes have acquired that
          degree of violence, <lb/>which indigence and delay muſt neceſſari- <lb/>ly occaſion. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Under theſe peculiar advantages, the <lb/>poor have a phyſician at their bedſide on
          <lb/>the very day they apply for relief; inſtead <lb/>of being baniſhed from their
          habitations, <lb/>when languiſhing with ſickneſs, to bear <lb/>the controul of alien
          nurſes, they are con- <pb n="5"/>
          <lb/>tinued under the foſtering care of their <lb/>own relations, by which love and grati-
          <lb/>tude are mutually excited, and family con- <lb/>nexions more firmly eſtabliſhed; and
          while <lb/>domeſtic happineſs is thus cultivated, the <lb/>morals of ſo uſeful and
          numerous a claſs <lb/>of the community are preſerved unaſſailed <lb/>and untainted. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>As ſuch an extenſive plan could not be <lb/>immediately carried into execution in all
          <lb/>the adjoining parts of this great metropo- <lb/>lis, it was thought expedient to
          eſtabliſh <lb/>the firſt Diſpenſary in the city of London, <lb/>and to ſettle the limits
          of viſiting the ſick <lb/>at their own habitations, for the preſent, <lb/>within the
          liberties thereof. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The Diſpenſary is ſituated in Alderſgate- <lb/>ſtreet, where a phyſician attends at
          eleven <lb/>o'clock every day (Sundays excepted) to give <lb/>advice to ſuch out-patients
          as ſhall come <lb/>recommended, and to viſit the home-pa- <lb/>tients at the places of
          their abode, as the <lb/>caſe may require. — By out-patients are <pb n="6"/>
          <lb/>meant, ſuch as are able to attend the Diſ- <lb/>penſary; by home-patients, ſuch as
          are <lb/>not able to attend. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Though home-patients are, for the pre- <lb/>ſent, ſuch only as live within the city
          and <lb/>liberties of London; yet, out-patients are <lb/>relieved without any reſtriction
          as to place <lb/>of reſidence. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>An apothecary conſtantly reſides at the <lb/>Diſpenſary, to receive letters of
          recommen- <lb/>dation, and compound and deliver out the <lb/>medicines preſcribed by the
          phyſicians. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Chirurgical <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.75)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Since this piece was ſent to the preſs, the committee <lb/>have agreed to refer
              the admiſſion of ſurgery to the next <lb/>general meeting, in conſequence of a motion
              made for that <lb/>purpoſe by the author. </p>
          </note>, venereal, and lunatick caſes <lb/>are not admitted, being the peculiar ob-
          <lb/>jects of other charities. </p>
        <pb n="7"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But as there are medical caſes, wherein <lb/>chirurgical aſſiſtance is requiſite, a
          ſur- <lb/>geon attends on ſuch occaſions. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>No perſons are deemed objects of this <lb/>charity, but ſuch as are really
          neceſſitous. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Each patient is admitted by a printed <lb/>letter of recommendation, ſigned by a go-
          <lb/>vernor; and, when cured, returns thanks, <lb/>that ſuch governor may be informed of
          his <lb/>right to preſent another object. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>A general meeting is held on the ſecond <lb/>Wedneſday in March, June, September,
          <lb/>and December, in every year, at which <lb/>nine governors conſtitute a board. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>A committee of fifteen governors (three <lb/>of whom are a quorum) are choſen at the
          <lb/>general meetings in June and December, <lb/>and meet at the Diſpenſary on the laſt
          <lb/>Wedneſday in every month; which com- <lb/>mittee is open for any governors who pleaſe
          <lb/>to attend, and who are intitled to a vote <pb n="8"/>
          <lb/>equally with the gentlemen appointed <lb/>thereon. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>A medical committee is choſen annu- <lb/>ally, to inſpect the drugs uſed in the
          <lb/>Diſpenſary. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Perſons ſubſcribing one guinea annually <lb/>to the ſupport of this Charity, are
          gover- <lb/>nors during the continuance of their ſub- <lb/>ſcriptions, and intitled to
          have one patient <lb/>at a time upon the Diſpenſary liſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Governors ſubſcribing two guineas an- <lb/>nually are intitled to have two patients
          <lb/>upon the liſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>A benefaction of ten guineas conſtitutes <lb/>a governor for life, and admits two pa-
          <lb/>tients at a time upon the books. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Nobility, members of parliament, and <lb/>ladies, ſubſcribing as above, may vote at
          all <lb/>elections, by any governor appointed proxy <lb/>in writing for that purpoſe. </p>
        <pb n="9"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Annual ſubſcribers, deſirous of being <lb/>governors for life, may become ſuch, on
          <lb/>paying within the year a further ſum, to <lb/>make up not leſs than ten guineas in
          the <lb/>whole. </p>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A floral ornament. </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <pb n="10"/>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>SECTION II. </head>
        <head rend="hanging space">
          <lb/>Progreſs of the Diſpenſary, and <lb/>General Review of it's Plan and <lb/>Deſign. </head>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>T the commencement of the Diſ- <lb/>penſary, in the year 1770,
          it was <lb/>circumſcribed to admit certain objects and <lb/>diſeaſes only; but, in it's
          progreſs, the <lb/>acceſſion of ſubſcribers, and the conſe- <lb/>quent increaſe of it's
          income, have ren- <lb/>dered many of thoſe reſtrictions both un- <lb/>neceſſary and
          improper. The governors <lb/>have hitherto paid a laudable attention to <lb/>every
          propoſal of improvement; they have <lb/>lately admitted ſmall-pox patients, and do-
          <lb/>meſtic ſervants, when properly recom- <lb/>mended, to receive the benefits of their
          <lb/>contributions; they have elected a ſurgeon <lb/>to attend medical caſes, wherein
          chirurgi- <lb/>cal aſſiſtance is requiſite; and as they ſeem <lb/>thus diſpoſed to receive
          every repreſenta- <lb/>tion which tends to the convenience, in- <lb/>tereſts, and general
          good of the poor, I <pb n="11"/>
          <lb/>am induced to lay before them ſuch pro- <lb/>poſals, as, from an attentive
          conſideration <lb/>of the finances of the Charity, and the <lb/>miſeries of the poor,
          appeir moſt calcu- <lb/>lated to promote the great ends of the <lb/>inſtitution, Public
          Good. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The finances of the Diſpenſary, as well <lb/>as the applications of the ſick, have
          gra- <lb/>dually increaſed ſince it's firſt eſtabliſh- <lb/>ment, which has induced the
          governors <lb/>to inquire after a more ſpacious edifice <lb/>for the purpoſe of conducting
          the buſineſs <lb/>of it; the preſent, therefore, ſeems the <lb/>moſt eligible opportunity
          for addreſſing <lb/>them upon a ſubject now under their con- <lb/>templation, and upon the
          methods moſt <lb/>conducive to it's advantage and improve- <lb/>ment; and if it ſhould
          appear that open- <lb/>ing the Diſpenſary to ſurgery in general, <lb/>and to every
          diſeaſed object that may ap- <lb/>ply for relief, properly recommended by a
          <lb/>ſubſcriber, would form the broad baſis of <lb/>public good, I doubt not but this
          addreſs <lb/>will meet with that reception and ſupport, <pb n="12"/>
          <lb/>which has hitherto been manifeſted upon <lb/>other occaſions. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The governors at preſent do not amount <lb/>to 1000; but as the increaſe, though gra-
          <lb/>dual, has been great, there is the faireſt <lb/>reaſon to conclude, that the number
          will <lb/>ſoon be doubled. This, however, I ſhall <lb/>take for granted, and proceed in my
          cal- <lb/>culations upon ſuch a ſuppoſition; but <lb/>whatever number of ſubſcribers be
          admit- <lb/>ted, the proportional expences will near- <lb/>ly quadrate, and therefore no
          miſconſtruc- <lb/>tion can reſult from adopting two thouſand <lb/>inſtead of the preſent
          number. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Not two years ago the governors of the <lb/>Diſpenſary found the houſe firſt occupied
          <lb/>for conducting the buſineſs of it too ſmall, <lb/>they therefore took one more
          commodi- <lb/>ous; and this is now as much too little <lb/>as the former had been two
          years before: <lb/>hence it is hoped they will not pay too <lb/>ſcrupulous a regard to
          economy, when <lb/>they have found the public encourage- <lb/>ment ſo much ſurpaſs their
          moſt ſanguine <pb n="13"/>
          <lb/>expectations. For this reaſon I have of- <lb/>fered a plan of a Diſpenſary furniſhed
          with <lb/>baths, and proper apartments for every <lb/>uſeful contingency, with an eſtimate
          of all <lb/>the expences that are likely to accrue: and <lb/>as there are many old
          buildings in Alderſ- <lb/>gate-ſtreet, and in it's vicinity, the go- <lb/>vernors may
          execute whatever plan they <lb/>are pleaſed to adopt; and, with ſuch op- <lb/>portunities
          and advantages, we may hope <lb/>to ſee perſonal convenience, ſimple ele- <lb/>gance, and
          public utility, at once united. </p>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A floral ornament. </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
      <pb n="11"/>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center space">SECTION III. </head>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>Of the Finances of the Diſpenſary. </head>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N the year 1774 this Charity was en- <lb/>abled to purchaſe
          five hundred pounds <lb/>in the ſtocks, from the ſavings made in <lb/>that and the
          preceding years ſince it's eſta- <lb/>bliſhment. At the period abovemention- <lb/>ed, the
          gratuity to the two phyſicians was <lb/>particularly agitated; and many of the
          <lb/>governors were then of opinion, that their <lb/>ſubſcriptions would barely anſwer the
          nu- <lb/>merous applications of the ſick poor, which <lb/>had been of late conſiderably
          augmented <lb/>in proportion to the number of ſubſcri- <lb/>bers, from the Charity being
          more gene- <lb/>rally known among the lower claſs of <lb/>people; but, as the labor of the
          phyſicians <lb/>appeared to have been very great, it was <lb/>agreed to give each one
          hundred pounds <lb/>for their ſervices during the laſt year. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>In this city, where opulence is united <lb/>with benevolence, it was not probable <pb
            n="15"/>
          <lb/>that an an inſtitution ſo friendly to human nature, <lb/>would be leſs regarded by
          the public than <lb/>it had hitherto been; on the contrary, this <lb/>genteel emolument
          given to the faculty, <lb/>while it animated their application, ren- <lb/>dered the poſt
          of phyſician to the Diſpen- <lb/>ſary more conſpicuous, and more worthy <lb/>the attention
          of phyſicians of character <lb/>and reputation, and daily increaſed the <lb/>generous
          contributions of the public: the <lb/>applications of the ſick conſequently in-
          <lb/>creaſed, in proportion; and this rendered <lb/>it neceſſary to elect a third
          phyſician the <lb/>ſame year. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The expence which the Charity ſuſtain- <lb/>ed by ſo juſt an attention to the
          faculty, <lb/>ſeemed therefore amply compenſated by <lb/>the reputation and additional
          ſubſcriptions <lb/>procured by it; for in 1775 the governors <lb/>amounted to upwards of
          eight hundred, <lb/>and five hundred pounds more were laid <lb/>out in the funds; ſo that
          the capital a- <lb/>mounted to one thouſand pounds, beſides <lb/>upwards of one hundred in
          the treaſurer's <lb/>hands. </p>
        <pb n="16"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>From From this ſhort view it is evident, that <lb/>the General Diſpenſary will never
          fail for <lb/>want of ſubſcriptions, while the faculty <lb/>are treated in ſuch a manner
          as will en- <lb/>gage gentlemen of eminence to undertake <lb/>the laborious offices of
          phyſicians and ſur- <lb/>geons to it. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The progreſſive acceſſion of governors <lb/>muſt ſoon augment the number as high
          <lb/>as two thouſand. The Charity will then <lb/>require three phyſicians and as many ſur-
          <lb/>geons, whoſe ſalaries, with thoſe of the <lb/>apothecary and aſſiſtants, are rated in
          the <lb/>following eſtimate, which includes all <lb/>other contingent expences. </p>
        <table rend="space">
          <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell>£ </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Three phyſicians and three ſurgeons</cell>
            <cell>600 </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>One apothecary </cell>
            <cell>80 </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Two aſſiſtants, 40l. each </cell>
            <cell>80 </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Secretary </cell>
            <cell>40 </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Collector </cell>
            <cell>100 </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Drugs, &amp;c. </cell>
            <cell>500 </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Houſe-rent </cell>
            <cell>120 </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Miscellaneous expences, coals, candles, &amp;c. </cell>
            <cell>100 </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell>1620 </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>2000 governors, at 1l. 1s. per annum, is 2100</cell>
            <cell> </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Intereſt of 1000l. at 3 per cent. per ann. is 30 </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell> £ 2130</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <pb n="17"/>
        <p>
          <lb/>The expences deducted from the income <lb/>of the Charity will leave an annual
          ſurplus <lb/>of five hundred and ten pounds, which, in <lb/>a few years, muſt be
          ſufficient to enable <lb/>the governors to erect a new building, and <lb/>to extend the
          benefits of their inſtitution <lb/>to more diſtant limits. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It may be objected, that ſome of the <lb/>governors are ſubſcribers for life, and
          <lb/>therefore no future ſubſcription can ariſe <lb/>from them; but to balance this
          deficien- <lb/>cy, as many gentlemen at leaſt ſubſcribe <lb/>two guineas annually. To this
          we may <lb/>add donations by will, which will ſoon <lb/>augment the capital of this
          Diſpenſary, <lb/>and preclude every doubt of want of fi- <lb/>nances to anſwer it's future
          exigencies. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>With the revenue above-mentioned, the <lb/>General Diſpenſary will annually afford
          <lb/>relief to about twelve thouſand patients, <lb/>which is nearly double to ſome
          hoſpitals <lb/>in London, whoſe revenues are four times <lb/>greater. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="18"/>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>SECTION IV. </head>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>State of the Poor in the City of <lb/>London. </head>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE poor are a large, as well as uſe- <lb/>ful part of the
          community; they <lb/>ſupply both the neceſſary and ornamental <lb/>articles of life; they
          have, therefore, a <lb/>juſt claim to the protection of the rich, <lb/>whoſe intereſts
          muſt direct them to en- <lb/>courage the induſtrious in their employ- <lb/>ments, to frame
          laws for the mainte- <lb/>nance of their rights, and to ſuccour them <lb/>in the
          misfortunes to which they are un- <lb/>avoidably incident. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>This mutual obligation between the <lb/>rich and the poor, neither of whom could
          <lb/>long ſubſiſt without the aid of the other, <lb/>has in all ages formed the moſt
          natural <lb/>and permanent ground of intercourſe be- <lb/>tween the different degrees of
          the people; <lb/>the artizan always depending upon the af- <lb/>fluent for employment, and
          the ſucceſs of <lb/>the artizan being always neceſſary to the <lb/>eaſe and convenience of
          the affluent. </p>
        <pb n="19"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>In a country where many individuals <lb/>are enriched by commerce, and where all
          <lb/>people are poſſeſſed of civil liberty, and <lb/>the unreſtrained exerciſe of their
          faculties, <lb/>the ornamental and neceſſary arts muſt <lb/>unavoidably flouriſh: but,
          wherever many <lb/>perſons are employed, labor muſt be cheap; <lb/>the earnings,
          therefore, of the artizan, will <lb/>ſeldom exceed his expences; and as ma- <lb/>ny of
          theſe arts depend upon circum- <lb/>ſtances changeable in their nature, multi- <lb/>tudes
          muſt thereby be liable to ſuffer a tem- <lb/>porary poverty. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>However, whilſt health continues, the <lb/>reſources which daily open to the
          induſtri- <lb/>ous in a trading country, afford alſo a <lb/>temporary ſubſiſtance to their
          families: <lb/>but a long continuance of health is the <lb/>lot of few. The poor, from the
          occaſio- <lb/>nal want of employment and wholeſome <lb/>food, from expoſure to all changes
          of the <lb/>weather, and from various other cauſes, <lb/>are often viſited with ſickneſs,
          as well as <lb/>with poverty; one, indeed, is conſequent <pb n="20"/>
          <lb/>upon the other, and thereby they become <lb/>the immediate objects of aſſiſtance. It
          is <lb/>then peculiarly neceſſary that the hand of <lb/>pity ſhould be extended to ſoften
          the <lb/>pangs of a ſick bed, and to reſtore health <lb/>and eaſe to the poor in
          affliction. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But affecting as the picture of poverty <lb/>united with diſeaſe may appear, it
          ſerves <lb/>to heighten our approbation of the gene- <lb/>rous and benevolent ſpirit,
          which every <lb/>quarter of this city nobly exhibits; the <lb/>numerous hoſpitals, and
          other munificent <lb/>receptacles for our diſtreſſed fellow-crea- <lb/>tures, are
          undeniable proofs of the piety, <lb/>compaſſion, and liberality of the opulent, <lb/>which
          no preceding age ever afforded. <lb/>Greece had her exquiſite ſtatues, and Rome <lb/>her
          public baths and edifices; but Chriſtia- <lb/>nity hath raiſed monuments of compaſſion
          <lb/>and beneficence, unknown both to ancient <lb/>Greece and Rome. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>In a free country, where the manners of <lb/>the people are thus ſoftened and
          humanized, <pb n="21"/>
          <lb/>and amongſt whom mutual intereſts muſt <lb/>perpetually ſubſiſt, a ſpontaneous
          gratitude <lb/>will naturally ariſe in the poor towards <lb/>their benefactors, to repay
          by their induſ- <lb/>try thoſe obligations which their unavoid- <lb/>able ſickneſs had
          incurred; they not only <lb/>meet their families with pleaſure, but they <lb/>are animated
          to follow their daily labour <lb/>with redoubled chearſulneſs and vigor. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>I have been too intimately acquainted <lb/>with the condition and manners of the
          <lb/>poor, to want facts in ſupport of what I <lb/>advance; if I err, it will be in not
          doing <lb/>ſufficient juſtice to that induſtry and gra- <lb/>titude, which they exemplify
          in their ge- <lb/>neral deportment. Thoſe, who form their <lb/>judgment from a ſuperficial
          obſervation of <lb/>a few intoxicated objects, who are found <lb/>in the moſt frequented
          places, are much <lb/>miſtaken with reſpect to the body of the <lb/>laborious poor, who
          humbly ſeclude them- <lb/>ſelves in miſerable courts and allies. Vice <lb/>is barefaced,
          and boldly expoſes itſelf in <lb/>the open ſtreets; but modeſt worth ſteals <pb n="22"/>
          <lb/>from the public eye, and frequents the <lb/>moſt ſolitary avenues: one vicious man,
          <lb/>therefore, becomes more conſpicuous than <lb/>a thouſand good men; and our conclu-
          <lb/>ſions cannot be juſt without being formed <lb/>from the whole, both with reſpect to
          the <lb/>lower as well as higher ſtations of life. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>When I conſider the diſtreſſes of the in- <lb/>digent, I rather admire that the
          inſtances <lb/>of their miſconduct mould be ſo rare: <lb/>when they behold the affluence,
          eaſe, and <lb/>indulgence of their ſuperiors; when, in <lb/>ſpite of their utmoſt
          induſtry, they can <lb/>with difficulty ſupport their families; and <lb/>when ſickneſs and
          diſappointments ſuper- <lb/>vene, it is not to be wondered at, if ſome <lb/>expreſſions of
          diſcontent ſhould break forth <lb/>amongſt them. But ſuch only can pro- <lb/>perly judge
          of theſe repinings, who have <lb/>ſeen a whole family, that once experien- <lb/>ced better
          days, confined to one chamber, <lb/>and one ſolitary bed, with ſickneſs, with <lb/>want,
          and a total incapacity to raiſe one <lb/>penny; let ſuch try the experiment with- <pb
            n="23"/>
          <lb/>out murmuring, before they form a con- <lb/>cluſion to the diſadvantage of the
          ſufferers. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>During the laſt three years, I have at- <lb/>tended nearly ſix thouſand poor perſons,
          <lb/>into many of whoſe habitations I have <lb/>entered, and been converſant with their
          <lb/>ſufferings, and their reſignation under <lb/>them; in both of which they have ex-
          <lb/>ceeded many of their fellow-creatures, <lb/>whoſe lot has caſt them in a ſuperior
          ſta- <lb/>tion, and whoſe contentment under tem- <lb/>porary miſeries, ſhould ever be
          ſuſtained <lb/>by this comparative reflexion: </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <q rend="quotes">What myriads wiſh to be as bleſt as I! </q>
          <lb/><hi rend="align-right"><hi rend="sc">Shenſtone</hi>. </hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Great cities are like painted ſepulchres; <lb/>their public avenues, and ſtately
          edifices, <lb/>ſeem to preclude the very poſſibility of <lb/>diſtreſs and poverty: but if
          we paſs be- <lb/>yond this ſuperficial veil, the ſcene will <lb/>be reverſed; the pleaſing
          lights and ſhades <lb/>of the picture will be blended with, and <lb/>loſt in a dark
          back-ground. </p>
        <pb n="24"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>A man, converſant only with the com- <lb/>mon concerns of life, would infer, upon
          <lb/>the leaſt reflexion, that as families in the <lb/>middle ſtation, with the utmoſt
          circum- <lb/>ſpection, cannot reſtrain their expences <lb/>under conſiderable ſums a year;
          the la- <lb/>boring poor, and many ingenious artizans, <lb/>who cannot poſſibly acquire
          more than for- <lb/>ty or fifty pounds in the ſame time, muſt <lb/>be liable to ſuffer
          much diſtreſs either <lb/>when out of employment, or when viſited <lb/>with ſickneſs.
          Temperance and labor ren- <lb/>der them prolific; and to ſupport a nu- <lb/>merous family
          with all the neceſſaries of <lb/>life, by their ſmall earnings, is an invin- <lb/>cible
          proof of the economy and induſtry <lb/>that generally prevail among them. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Sometimes, indeed, by ſucceſſive attacks <lb/>of illneſs, they are incapable of
          procur- <lb/>ing the common neceſſaries of life; they <lb/>have literally wanted bread, as
          well as <lb/>cloaths; and, inſtead of a bed, an old <lb/>oil-cloth has been ſubſtituted,
          and the <lb/>whole furniture of it has been a worn-out <pb n="25"/>
          <lb/>blanket, inſufficient to hide what decency <lb/>requires. On ſuch a couch have been
          <lb/>found a huſband, a wife, and two or three <lb/>children, at once chained by diſeaſe,
          with- <lb/>out any reſources to procure a morſel of <lb/>bread; they have thus continued,
          till the <lb/>payment for their wretched dwellings be- <lb/>came due, when this diſmal
          confinement <lb/>has been changed for the horrible re- <lb/>ſtraint of a priſon, loaded
          with putridity <lb/>and poiſon. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It muſt be owned, indeed, that ſuch <lb/>examples of extreme diſtreſs do not very
          <lb/>often occur; they are, however, much more <lb/>frequent, than is uſually imagined by
          thoſe, <lb/>who conſider the amazing ſum which the <lb/>poor-rates annually amount to, and
          the <lb/>various other proviſions calculated to re- <lb/>lieve the indigent. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Though I wiſh not to accuſe individuals, <lb/>yet truth obliges me to ſay, that evils
          exiſt <lb/>ſomewhere, which require immediate re- <lb/>formation. I have reaſon to
          believe, that <lb/>the ſum annually raiſed, would ſupply all <pb n="26"/>
          <lb/>the neceſſities of the national poor, were <lb/>it timely and properly applied; and
          this <lb/>I can deduce from the conduct of a ſocie- <lb/>ty, whoſe poor are comfortably
          ſupported, <lb/>and their children clothed and educated, <lb/>and ſet forward in life,
          with no great ex- <lb/>pence to the individuals of the commu- <lb/>nity. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But from whatever cauſes the prevailing <lb/>diſtreſſes of the poor may originate,
          pre- <lb/>ſent miſery requires preſent aid; whereby <lb/>health, which is ſo neceſſary to
          their ſub- <lb/>ſiſtance, will be ſooner reſtored, famine <lb/>and a priſon avoided, the
          nation inriched <lb/>by induſtry, and a hardy race of uſeful <lb/>members preſerved to the
          community. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The occaſions of making ourſelves hap- <lb/>py by extending relief to the needy, are
          <lb/>numberleſs, and would ſeem adapted to <lb/>diffuſe happineſs more generally among
          <lb/>mankind. If affluence and independence <lb/>could univerſally prevail, the benevolent
          <lb/>would not experience the inexpreſſible <pb n="27"/>
          <lb/>pleaſure of relieving the diſtreſſed; nei- <lb/>ther could there exiſt that grateful
          ſa- <lb/>tisfaction, which modeſt indigence ever <lb/>feels from well-timed ſuccour. In
          this <lb/>city, however, there is no probability that <lb/>theſe cauſes of mutual pleaſure
          will ever <lb/>be removed; but, on the other hand, the <lb/>affluence of ſome riſes in
          proportion to <lb/>the neceſſities of others, whoſe wants ſi- <lb/>lently petition for
          their aſſiſtance. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>A little good, properly directed, is often <lb/>great in it's increaſe; the widow's
          mite was <lb/>not beſtowed in vain: no perſon, there- <lb/>fore, ſhould withhold his hand,
          from the <lb/>reflection that a little can produce no bene- <lb/>fit; but rather be
          animated to do good, <lb/>by obſerving that great effects have reſul- <lb/>ted from
          trifling cauſes; that the ſmalleſt <lb/>ſpring is the ſource of a mighty river <lb/>which
          waters numerous provinces; that the <lb/>loftieſt oak of the foreſt is germinated from
          <lb/>an acorn; and that the particle, that <lb/>ſeems loſt in the ocean, may become a
          <lb/>pearl of ineſtimable value. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="28"/>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>SECTION V. </head>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>Advantages of the Diſpenſary to <lb/>domeſtic ſervants. </head>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">S</hi>ICKNESS is the lot of humanity; <lb/>and this uſeful as well
          as numerous <lb/>part of ſhe community, who intereſt them- <lb/>ſelves in their different
          departments for <lb/>the profit and pleaſure of their maſters, <lb/>have a natural claim
          upon them for relief, <lb/>when rendered incapable of labour by the <lb/>attacks of
          ſickneſs. The female ſex, in <lb/>particular, conſtitute the majority of do- <lb/>meſtic
          ſervants in this city; they have <lb/>been accuſtomed to the plenty of their <lb/>maſter's
          table; and frequently receive in- <lb/>dulgencies to which the abject poor have <lb/>not
          been uſed: by this, and a continual <lb/>intercourſe with people of decent man- <lb/>ners,
          they acquire a degree of delicacy of <lb/>body, as well as ſenſibility of mind, that
          <lb/>renders them leſs able to undergo difficul- <lb/>ties, or expoſure to the wide world.
          Many <lb/>of them who are born with tender frames, <pb n="29"/>
          <lb/>and delicate conſtitutions, exert themſelves <lb/>ſo much in the diſcharge of their
          duty, as <lb/>renders them liable to numerous ailments; <lb/>and unwilling to complain for
          fear of in- <lb/>commoding a family, or incurring an ex- <lb/>pence which they themſelves
          are unable <lb/>to ſupport, they patiently linger on, till <lb/>diſeaſe becomes too deeply
          fixed to be era- <lb/>dicated. I have, indeed, been witneſs to the <lb/>moſt laudable
          inſtances of humanity in maſ- <lb/>ters and miſtreſſes of families, who, as ſoon <lb/>as
          they have diſcovered the ſickneſs of their <lb/>female ſervants, have evinced the
          tendereſt <lb/>care of them, engaging the advice of the <lb/>family phyſician or
          apothecary, and tak- <lb/>ing upon themſelves every expence that <lb/>might accrue: and
          where ſervants meet <lb/>with ſuch treatment the aid of the Diſ- <lb/>penſary is not
          requiſite. In ſome fami- <lb/>lies peculiar circumſtances may occur, and <lb/>ſervants may
          be ſeized with certain diſ- <lb/>eaſes, particularly of the infectious kind, <lb/>which
          may render it highly expedient to re- <lb/>move them to lodgings; but the humane in-
          <lb/>terference of maſters and miſtreſſes may ſtill <pb n="30"/>
          <lb/>be be conducted with no leſs advantage and ſe- <lb/>curity to ſervants than if they
          were at home. <lb/>There are, however, many heads of fami- <lb/>lies, whoſe humanity does
          not riſe to ſuch <lb/>complete efforts of genuine compaſſion. <lb/>The tender domeſtic,
          whoſe ſickneſs is of- <lb/>ten occaſioned by an anxious deſire to pleaſe <lb/>the family,
          is either left to diſcharge the <lb/>expences of it, or turned out of the houſe <lb/>at
          it's firſt commencement, for no other <lb/>reaſon, but becauſe ſhe is ſick, and may
          <lb/>poſſibly die in the family. If we are <lb/>made to aſſiſt and to do good to each
          other <lb/>in the daily and common occurrences of <lb/>life, how much more ſhould the
          tendereſt <lb/>emotions of ſympathy be excited, and the <lb/>moſt effectual relief be
          adminiſtered, in <lb/>ſuch affecting ſituations? If we ſerve our <lb/>fellow-creatures ſo
          far only as it creates us <lb/>no trouble, where is the prevalence of <lb/>Chriſtianity
          over ſelfiſhneſs? The removal <lb/>to ſtrange lodgings, the ideas of anxiety <lb/>thence
          excited, and the numerous fears <lb/>which are apt, in ſuch a perplexed ſtate, <lb/>to
          crowd in upon the mind of an inex- <pb n="31"/>
          <lb/>perienced girl, who may have laboured for <lb/>years without ſaving many ſhillings,
          all <lb/>contribute to augment the firſt malady, and <lb/>protract the cure. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Thus abandoned and out-caſt, what a <lb/>ſcene of woe do the firſt returns of health
          <lb/>exhibit? Perhaps far from her native home, <lb/>without one real friend, but
          ſurrounded <lb/>with many falſe ones of both ſexes, how <lb/>unexpectedly do the
          misfortunes of a frail <lb/>conſtitution, and the neglect of thoſe who <lb/>ſhould have
          ſuccoured her in diſtreſs, in- <lb/>troduce her into a ſcene of life, to which,
          <lb/>however ſhocking, neceſſity compels her to <lb/>ſubmit at firſt, and habit afterwards
          re- <lb/>conciles her beyond redemption. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>To ſervants, thus dangerouſly ſituated in <lb/>families, I know that the Diſpenſary
          has <lb/>been an uſeful and noble ſuccour. It has <lb/>induced maſters and miſtreſſes to
          admit <lb/>that relief, by which no expence is in- <lb/>curred; and, for the ſame reaſon,
          has en- <lb/>couraged ſervants to apply early for a cure, <lb/>before their diſorders were
          too deeply <lb/>rooted in the conſtitution. </p>
        <pb n="32"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Thus not only the health but the morals <lb/>of young people of both ſexes have been
          <lb/>preſerved, and that tie betwixt maſters and <lb/>ſervants which humanity and juſtice
          have <lb/>formed, has become firmly ſtrengthened; <lb/>and, as I have generally obſerved,
          every <lb/>kind aſſiſtance that domeſtics receive, is <lb/>amply repaid by their fidelity,
          economy, <lb/>and induſtry. </p>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A floral ornament. </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
      <pb n="33"/>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>SECTION VI. </head>
        <head rend="align-center ">
          <lb/>General Diſpenſary as it affects the <lb/>Faculty at large. </head>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">W</hi>HERE there are numbers of weal- <lb/>thy citizens, there muſt
          always <lb/>exiſt numbers of poor; the elegance and <lb/>eaſe of the former depend upon
          the inge- <lb/>nuity and labor of the latter; and the <lb/>opulent have abundantly
          teſtified their ſenſe <lb/>of this connexion, by many coſtly edifices <lb/>for the
          reception and relief of the diſeaſed <lb/>poor. Though this has undoubtedly leſſen-
          <lb/>ed the general practice of ſurgeons and <lb/>apothecaries, it has not leſſened their
          emo- <lb/>luments, as theſe receptacles are open only <lb/>to poverty and diſtreſs; it is,
          therefore, the <lb/>unprofitable buſineſs only that muſt be de- <lb/>ducted from the
          income of the faculty at <lb/>large: and, indeed, we find gentlemen of <lb/>the profeſſion
          ſo ſenſible of this, that ma- <lb/>ny of them have become benefactors to theſe <lb/>very
          inſtitutions. Hence, if hoſpitals do <lb/>not operate againſt the intereſts of the fa- <pb
            n="34"/>
          <lb/>culty, the Diſpenſary cannot injure them; <lb/>becauſe the ſubjects of it's relief
          are ſuch <lb/>only as are really neceſſitous; and from <lb/>ſuch I am ſure the faculty are
          too generous <lb/>and independent to demand the mite of <lb/>hard-earned labor. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The beſt plans have been abuſed, and, <lb/>probably, individuals in eaſy
          circumſtances <lb/>may have aſſumed the appearance of neceſ- <lb/>ſity, and thereby
          partaken of that charity <lb/>which was deſigned only for the indigent; <lb/>but ſuch
          inſtances muſt rarely, if ever, oc- <lb/>cur in the General Diſpenſary, becauſe a
          <lb/>committee of the governors attend daily, <lb/>to prevent impoſitions of this kind,
          and to <lb/>rectify every abuſe. </p>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A floral ornament. </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
      <pb n="35"/>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>SECTION VII. </head>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>Utility of admitting Surgery. </head>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> General Diſpenſary for relieving the <lb/>poor at their own
          habitations, is <lb/>but a modern inſtitution, different from <lb/>every other charity
          eſtabliſhed in this king- <lb/>dom; the governors, therefore, acted with <lb/>greater
          circumſpection, reſpecting the in- <lb/>diſcriminate admiſſion of patients, during
          <lb/>the infancy of ſo novel a plan. Perfec- <lb/>tion is not the production of a day; it
          is <lb/>experience that directs an accurate archi- <lb/>tect in raiſing a ſtupendous
          edifice upon a <lb/>well-laid foundation; and we have now <lb/>ſufficient ground to decide
          upon the pro- <lb/>priety of admitting chirurgical patients as <lb/>well as medical. The
          governors of the <lb/>Weſtminſter Diſpenfary, emboldened by the <lb/>ſucceſs of this prior
          eſtabliſhment in the <lb/>city of London, from the firſt ventured to <lb/>adminiſter
          relief to every malady to which <lb/>the human frame is liable; and the rapid
          <lb/>progreſs of this inſtitution of but the other <pb n="36"/>
          <lb/>day, is a proof of what the elder Chari- <lb/>ty, with a conſiderable capital in the
          <lb/>funds, is now able to accompliſh: it <lb/>ſhews that chirurgical caſes are not more
          <lb/>expenſive than medical; and, more than <lb/>this, it evinces, that the worſt
          operations <lb/>may be conducted at the houſes of the <lb/>patients with eaſe and with
          ſucceſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>We have, indeed, ſeen this happily <lb/>aſcertained, by the ſucceſs which hath at-
          <lb/>tended ſeveral operations conducted by the <lb/>ſurgeon to the General Diſpenſary,
          and <lb/>ſome of them in capital caſes, without one <lb/>example of fatality. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>There are frequent inſtances of patients <lb/>laboring under diſeaſes, equally
          demand- <lb/>ing the care of the ſurgeon as well as of <lb/>the phyſician; and moſt
          chirurgical caſes <lb/>require, likewiſe, medical aſſiſtance: a <lb/>ſtrong plea might
          hence be formed, for <lb/>admitting ſuch complicated caſes; and, <lb/>conſequently, for
          admitting ſurgery in ge- <lb/>neral. </p>
        <pb n="37"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The poor, whoſe circumſtances often <lb/>compel them to make uſe of the firſt means
          <lb/>of aid which ſpecious pretenders offer them, <lb/>frequently fall victims to
          ignorance and <lb/>quackery, and thereby for ever impair their <lb/>health, to the injury
          of their families, and <lb/><choice>
            <sic>and</sic>
            <corr/>
          </choice> loſs of the community. The Diſ- <lb/>penſary, however, has proved a noble
          <lb/>check to impoſtures in phyſic, and nearly <lb/>extirpated medical quacks out of the
          pre- <lb/>cincts of the city; but it's influence has <lb/>not yet been oppoſed to
          pretenders in ſur- <lb/>gery, by whom hundreds of our unhap- <lb/>py fellow creatures are
          annually ſacrificed <lb/>on Tower-hill and in Moorfields: per- <lb/>ſuaded I am, however,
          from the ſuppli- <lb/>cations of the poor, that theſe peſts of <lb/>ſociety would ſoon be
          compelled to quit <lb/>the city for want of bread, were chirur- <lb/>gical caſes admitted
          to partake of the be- <lb/>nefits of the Diſpenſary. Ignorance and <lb/>impudence would
          then no longer, in the <lb/>public walks, impoſe upon the unthinking <lb/>multitude the
          cures of ſlight ſcrophulas <lb/>for confirmed cancers, and of ſlight in- <pb n="38"/>
          <lb/>flammations of the eyes for the removal <lb/>of blindneſs the maladies of the poor
          <lb/>would then be timely checked, and effec- <lb/>tually eradicated, by the joint efforts
          of <lb/>medical and chirurgical experience, and the <lb/>life of many an uſeful member
          would be <lb/>redeemed to the community, their rela- <lb/>tions, and their friends. </p>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A floral ornament. </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
      <pb n="39"/>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>SECTION VIII. </head>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>Of conſulting, or extraordinary <lb/>Phyſicians. </head>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>S the Diſpenſary requires three times <lb/>as much attendance
          as the largeſt <lb/>hoſpital in London, though the ſmaller <lb/>hoſpitals have double the
          officers to do <lb/>the duty of them, it is natural to ſuppoſe, <lb/>that the labor of
          each of the Diſpenſary <lb/>phyſicians muſt be too great to allow them <lb/>to officiate
          one for another; and, at the <lb/>ſame time, their expoſure to infection in <lb/>viſiting
          the poor at their own habitations, <lb/>and frequently the priſoners in the comp-
          <lb/>ters, muſt render their health very precari- <lb/>ous; hence much inconvenience muſt
          ariſe, <lb/>for want of aſſiſtance during the indiſpo- <lb/>ſition of any of the
          phyſicians. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It appears neceſſary, therefore, to ap- <lb/>point conſulting phyſicians, to attend
          dur- <lb/>ing ſuch exigencies; and likewiſe to con- <lb/>ſult with the phyſicians in
          ordinary upon <pb n="40"/>
          <lb/>difficult and hazardous caſes. They might <lb/>be choſen out of thoſe phyſicians in
          ordi- <lb/>nary, who are diſpoſed to retire from that <lb/>laborious ſtation; and the poſt
          ſhould be <lb/>merely honorary, and have no ſalary an- <lb/>nexed to it. The governors, I
          dare ſay, <lb/>will not be under the neceſſity of waiting <lb/>long before they will have
          an opportunity <lb/>of ſhewing their approbation of former ſer- <lb/>vices, and, without
          any additional expence <lb/>to the charity, thus rewarding thoſe offi- <lb/>cers who have
          faithfully diſcharged their <lb/>duty. </p>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A floral ornament. </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
      <pb n="41"/>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>SECTION IX. </head>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>General Diſpenſary as a School of <lb/>Phyſic. </head>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">N</hi>EXT to the ſuccour and relief of <lb/>the poor, the promotion
          of medical <lb/>knowledge is of the utmoſt importance in <lb/>a medical inſtitution.
          Unfortunately for <lb/>ſtudents of phyſic and ſurgery, and for <lb/>mankind in general, no
          public plan has <lb/>been adopted in Europe for conveying in- <lb/>ſtruction in imitation
          of private practice; <lb/>and hence it is, that young gentlemen of <lb/>genius and
          application are ſo much at a <lb/>loſs at the commencement of their practice. <lb/>In
          places wherein a multitude of our ſpecies <lb/>are confined at one time, diſeaſes in
          general <lb/>put on a ſameneſs of appearance, and have <lb/>all more or leſs a putrid
          tendency; but a <lb/>plan like that of the General Diſpenſary, <lb/>where patients are
          viſited at their own <lb/>habitations, affords an opportunity for ſtu- <lb/>dents of the
          healing art to obſerve the <lb/>varieties in diſeaſes, as they uſually ariſe <pb n="42"/>
          <lb/>in private practice; they will ſee their <lb/>progreſs and determination more
          clearly, <lb/>and learn to diſtinguiſh and treat, more <lb/>judiciouſly, the ſymptoms they
          ſhall in <lb/>future have occaſion to preſcribe for. <lb/>Were theſe favourable
          opportunities of <lb/>information farther improved, by lectures <lb/>of the phyſicians and
          ſurgeons, adapted <lb/>to the reigning diſeaſes and circumſtances <lb/>of the patients, we
          need not heſitate to <lb/>declare, that this inſtitution might be ren- <lb/>dered of the
          utmoſt importance to ſtu- <lb/>dents, to the ſcience of medicine, and to <lb/>the public. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>There are many young gentlemen of <lb/>genius, application, and learning, whoſe
          <lb/>finances may have been much impaired in <lb/>acquiring only the rudiments of
          medicine; <lb/>and, therefore, as public good ſhould ever <lb/>be the motive of conduct
          with the facul- <lb/>ty, the admiſſion to the benefits of the <lb/>Diſpenſary ſhould be
          made as eaſy as <lb/>poſſible to the ſtudents, who, beſides the <lb/>uſual contingent
          expences requiſite to ac- <pb n="43"/>
          <lb/>quire medical knowledge, might not deem <lb/>ten guineas per ann. too large a
          gratuity for <lb/>the privilege not only of attending the prac- <lb/>tice of the
          phyſicians and ſurgeons, but <lb/>likewiſe of being admitted, during that <lb/>term, to
          all the lectures, and of ſeeing the <lb/>manner of compounding medicines, and <lb/>the
          forms uſed in preſcription. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The phyſicians and ſurgeons might each <lb/>give a public lecture, once every week,
          <lb/>on the following ſubjects: </p>
        <table rend="space size(0.75)">
          <row>
            <cell>The phyſician on Mondays, </cell>
            <cell><hi rend="dc(3)">{</hi> Clinical lectures on ſuch <lb/>caſes as the Diſpenſary
              <lb/>affords. </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>The phyſician on Tueſdays, </cell>
            <cell><hi rend="dc(2)">{</hi> Theory and practice of me- <lb/>dicine. </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>The phyſician on Wedneſdays, </cell>
            <cell><hi rend="dc(2)">{</hi> Materia medica, botany, <lb/>and chemiſtry. </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>The ſurgeon on Thurſdays, </cell>
            <cell><hi rend="dc(3)">{</hi> Practical lectures on the <lb/>chirurgical caſes in the
              <lb/>Diſpenſary. </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>The ſurgeon on Fridays, </cell>
            <cell><hi rend="dc(2)">{</hi> Syſtem of ſurgery, including <lb/>operations in general.
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>The ſurgeon on Saturdays, </cell>
            <cell><hi rend="dc(2)">{</hi> Anatomy, and chirurgical <lb/>obſervations in general.
            </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>This plan, indeed, may not be fully ex- <lb/>ecuted for ſome time; but though we can-
            <pb n="44"/>
          <lb/>not immediately attain perfection, the <lb/>nearer we approach towards it the better. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>By ſeeing a multitude of caſes in quick <lb/>ſucceſſion, without reflecting carefully
          on <lb/>each, the attention of the ſtudent is often be- <lb/>wildered; and the uſeful
          impreſſions which <lb/>one caſe affords, may be effaced by ſudden <lb/>ſubſequent ones: it
          is hence of conſequence <lb/>to digeſt one caſe before the attention is <lb/>engroſſed by
          another; and, to this end, <lb/>the ſtudents ſhould be allowed to viſit the
          <lb/>home-patients belonging to the Diſpenſary, <lb/>on ſuch days as the phyſicians
          attendance <lb/>may be diſpenſed with; and ſhould draw up <lb/>reports of the ſtate of the
          diſeaſe and the <lb/>preſent ſymptoms, as well as the indica- <lb/>tions of cure, and the
          remedies proper to <lb/>be adminiſtered: theſe reports ſhould be <lb/>preſented to the
          phyſicians under whom <lb/>the reſpective caſes were admitted, who <lb/>ſhould aſſign
          reaſons for confirming or re- <lb/>jecting the opinions of their pupils, and <lb/>then
          offer their own more mature judg- <lb/>ment upon the ſubject before them. </p>
        <pb n="45"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Every perſon of information is aware of <lb/>the ſanguine notions and theories which
          <lb/>ſtudents acquire by a mere college educa- <lb/>tion: it is a rational practice that
          muſt <lb/>confirm ſome of their opinions, and rectify <lb/>others; that muſt let them
          perceive that <lb/>many a diſeaſe, which theory has expelled <lb/>in a breath, remains
          obſtinate under the <lb/>care of the ableſt phyſicians. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Were ſuch a plan adopted, and that it <lb/>might eaſily be done I know by experi-
          <lb/>ence, young gentlemen, at their entrance <lb/>upon the anxious and arduous taſk of
          the <lb/>guardianſhip of life, would not be at a <lb/>loſs when called to the urgent
          relief of <lb/>the ſick, nor be tempted to adopt an <lb/>unſteady precarious method of
          treatment; <lb/>but, having carefully combined a ſyſtem of <lb/>practical and theoretical
          knowledge, they <lb/>would accurately inveſtigate ſymptoms, and <lb/>apply thoſe remedies
          that nature and the <lb/>diſeaſe require. </p>
        <pb n="46"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Though I have mentioned medicine in <lb/>a particular manner in this place, the ſame
          <lb/>plan might be adopted for ſurgery, and <lb/>ſimilar good effects would undoubtedly
          re- <lb/>ſult. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The faculty belonging to the Diſpenſa- <lb/>ry have long continued to meet together
          <lb/>once a week, to conſult upon all difficult <lb/>caſes, and to communicate their
          mutual <lb/>aſſiſtance to each other: and ſuch conſul- <lb/>tations, which tend to check
          the ſallies of <lb/>wild fancy, and bring theory to the teſt of <lb/>experience, muſt
          prove peculiarly inſtruc- <lb/>tive to the pupils, who would hear the <lb/>united
          obſervations of perſons experienced <lb/>in practice, ſee the inefficacy of certain
          <lb/>remedies in certain diſeaſes, and learn to <lb/>apply others better adapted to the
          urgent <lb/>ſymptoms, or peculiar conſtitution of the <lb/>patient. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>In ſuch a proceſs, ſtudents would find <lb/>the moſt ample means of perfecting them-
          <lb/>ſelves in the treatment of human maladies; <pb n="47"/>
          <lb/>and, while the healing art advanced to ma- <lb/>turity, the public muſt neceſſarily
          reap the <lb/>benefit, by always meeting with accom- <lb/>pliſhed guardians of health,
          under whoſe <lb/>protection they might ſafely repoſe that <lb/>deareſt of temporal
          bleſſings. </p>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A floral ornament. </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
      <pb n="48"/>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>SECTION X. </head>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>Influence of the Diſpenſary on the <lb/>Burials in London. </head>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">E</hi>VERY inſtitution which contributes <lb/>to the preſervation of
          health, or the <lb/>cure of diſeaſe, cannot fail to produce ſome <lb/>diminution in the
          bills of mortality; and <lb/>the General Diſpenſary, which, in the <lb/>ſpace of five
          years, has extended it's aſſiſt- <lb/>ance to about twelve thouſand diſeaſed <lb/>perſons,
          muſt have had a conſiderable ſhare <lb/>in redeeming victims from the grave, eſpe-
          <lb/>cially as many of them were too abject to <lb/>purchaſe the relief of medicine, or to
          pro- <lb/>cure a friend that had ſufficient influence to <lb/>open the lofty gates of an
          hoſpital. Many <lb/>of their diſeaſes were alſo too violent in their <lb/>ſymptoms, and
          too rapid in their progreſs, <lb/>to wait the ſlow return of the weekly day <lb/>of
          admiſſion; or of a tendency improper <lb/>for reception into one ward, previouſly
          <lb/>crowded with numbers of their diſeaſed <lb/>fellow-creatures. </p>
        <pb n="49"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It has been aſſerted, that <q rend="quotes diple">a third part <lb/>of all who die at
            Paris, die in hoſpitals. <lb/>In the Hotel Dieu, a great hoſpital ſi- <lb/>tuated in the
            middle of that city, we <lb/>behold a horrid ſcene of miſery; for the <lb/>beds being
            too few for the numbers <lb/>admitted, it is common to ſee four, ſix, <lb/>or even eight
            patients in a bed together, <lb/>lying four at one end, and four at the <lb/>other.
            Above a <hi rend="italic">fifth</hi> of all who are re- <lb/>ceived into this hoſpital,
            die; the an- <lb/>nual number admitted amounting to <lb/>near twenty-two thouſand. </q>
          Vid. Police <lb/>of France, p. 83. <q rend="diple quotes">In the two great hoſ-
            <lb/>pitals of London, St. Thomas's and St. <lb/>Bartholomew's, about ſix hundred die
            <lb/>annually, or one in <hi rend="italic">thirteen</hi> of all ad- <lb/>mitted as
            in-patients. </q> Vid. Price on the <lb/>Expectation of Lives, p. 216. <q
            rend="quotes diple">In the <lb/>Northampton Infirmary, <hi rend="italic">one</hi> in <hi
              rend="italic">nineteen</hi>
            <lb/>of the in-patients <hi rend="italic">(communibus annis)</hi>
            <lb/>die every year; and in that of Man- <lb/>cheſter, which is built in an airy ſitua-
            <lb/>tion, and tolerably well ventilated, <hi rend="italic">one</hi>
            <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">twenty-two</hi>. </q> Percival's Letter to <pb n="50"/>
          <lb/>Aikin on hoſpitals. In the Diſpenſary, the <lb/>deaths do not amount to <hi
            rend="italic">one</hi> in <hi rend="italic">thirty-three</hi>; <lb/>which, conſidering
          the many thouſands <lb/>of ſick perſons annually admitted to par- <lb/>take of it's
          relief, muſt contribute not a <lb/>little to the decreaſe of deaths in this me-
          <lb/>tropolis; and ſo indeed it appears to have <lb/>done by the bills of mortality, as
          the di- <lb/>minution in the burials has been nearly <lb/>progreſſive every year ſince
          it's eſtabliſh- <lb/>ment, except the year 1772, when the <lb/>ſmall-pox almoſt ſolely
          conſtituted this <lb/>difference, upwards of two thouſand dy- <lb/>ing that year of this
          diſeaſe more than in <lb/>the preceding year 1771. And it ſhould <lb/>be remarked, that
          ſmall-pox patients were <lb/>then not admitted to the benefits of the <lb/>Diſpenſary
            <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.75)" n="*">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* It muſt be grateful to every benevolent perſon to be in- <lb/>formed, that a
              Diſpenſary for inoculating the poor at their <lb/>own habitations, is now eſtabliſhed
              in London. </p>
          </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It is not merely by the relief which <lb/>the poor have immediately received from <pb
            n="51"/>
          <lb/>this inſtitution, that this happy diminu- <lb/>tion of burials in the bills of
          mortality <lb/>has been brought about: the uſeful in- <lb/>ſtructions which, in every part
          of London, <lb/>they have received from the phyſicians who <lb/>have attended them during
          their illneſs, <lb/>have greatly contributed to the preſerva- <lb/>tion of lives, that
          might have been ſacrified <lb/>to ignorance and quackery. In the ſpace <lb/>of a very few
          years I have obſerved a total <lb/>revolution in the conduct of the common <lb/>people
          reſpecting their diſeaſed friends; <lb/>they have learned, that moſt diſeaſes are mi-
          <lb/>tigated by a free admiſſion of air, by clean- <lb/>lineſs, and by promoting, inſtead
          of reſtrain- <lb/>ing, the indulgence and eaſe of the ſick. <lb/>Such inſtruction was new
          to the poor, though <lb/>important to their preſervation; and, when <lb/>we conſider how
          late they have acquired <lb/>this information, we muſt lament that ſo <lb/>many centuries
          have elapſed before an in- <lb/>ſtitution, like the General Diſpenſary, be- <lb/>came the
          object of public attention. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="52"/>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>SECTION XI. </head>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>Advantages of Baths. </head>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HOUGH ohſtructed perſpiration <lb/>may not now be conſidered
          as ſo <lb/>prolific and general a ſource of diſeaſe as <lb/>it was formerly, yet there is
          reaſon to con- <lb/>clude, that many diſeaſes either originate <lb/>from, or are increaſed
          by, a diminution of <lb/>this natural excretion; particularly amongſt <lb/>the poor, whoſe
          employments, and want <lb/>of cleanlineſs, tend to obſtruct the per- <lb/>ſpirable
          veſſels, and thereby induce the <lb/>diſorders dependent thereon. In ſuch <lb/>caſes a
          warm bath muſt prove peculiarly <lb/>ſerviceable, by cleanſing the ſurface of the
          <lb/>body, and reſtoring that perſpiration, by <lb/>the retention of which the diſeaſe had
          <lb/>either been acquired, or conſiderably aug- <lb/>mented. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The female poor more eſpecially, by <lb/>confinement in nurſing, miſmanagement
          <lb/>in lyings-in, laborious exertions above <pb n="53"/>
          <lb/>their ſtrength, poor diet, and other cir- <lb/>cumſtances of hardſhip, become
          enfeebled, <lb/>and acquire complaints wherein the cold <lb/>bath would prove more
          ſpeedily beneficial <lb/>than the continued uſe of internal re- <lb/>medies. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>There are likewiſe ſome ſudden and <lb/>painful diſeaſes, which require the imme-
          <lb/>diate uſe of a tepid bath, and without <lb/>which the uſual remedies would prove in-
          <lb/>effectual and uſeleſs; and it is known, that <lb/>the grateful warmth of water has
          ſoon <lb/>procured that eaſe and relief, which no- <lb/>thing elſe could give. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Amidſt the number of benevolent plans <lb/>in this metropolis, baths, for the uſe of
          <lb/>the poor, have never yet been conſtructed, <lb/>except in a few hoſpitals, where they
          are <lb/>open only to their own patients. The <lb/>Diſpenſary, therefore, which relieves
          thou- <lb/>ſands, who either cannot get admitted into <lb/>an hoſpital, or who do not
          chooſe to leave <lb/>their habitations and families, muſt re- <pb n="54"/>
          <lb/>main imperfect, till it is furniſhed both <lb/>with a warm and a cold bath; the
          expence <lb/>of which cannot be conſidered as burthen- <lb/>ſome to a Charity, whoſe
          finances are dai- <lb/>ly augmenting, and whoſe primary deſign <lb/>is the good of the
          poor. </p>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A floral ornament. </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
      <pb n="55"/>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>SECTION XII. </head>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>Deſcription of the Plan for a new <lb/>General Diſpenſary. </head>
        <p>
          <lb/>
          <hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE ingenious architects who oblig- <lb/>ingly preſented me with the
          annex- <lb/>ed plan and elevation of a new Diſpen- <lb/>ſary, have likewiſe generouſly
          intimat- <lb/>ed a diſpoſition to advance money below <lb/>the uſual rate of intereſt,
          were it neceſſa- <lb/>ry, in order to complete ſuch a ſtructure. <lb/>If this, however,
          ſhould not be accepted, <lb/>there is the utmoſt reaſon to ſuppoſe, that <lb/>the ſum
          requiſite for carrying this plan <lb/>into execution, might ſoon be raiſed by
          <lb/>voluntary ſubſcriptions among the opulent <lb/>and generous inhabitants of this city,
          who <lb/>have ſo often teſtified their readineſs to <lb/>promote the intereſts and welfare
          of the <lb/>indigent and diſtreſſed. </p>
        <pb n="56"/>
        <table>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/><hi rend="sc">Ground-Floor</hi>, twelve feet high, to <lb/>conſiſt of </head>
          <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell/>
            <cell>Feet </cell>
            <cell>Feet </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>A </cell>
            <cell>Phyſicians room </cell>
            <cell>13 by</cell>
            <cell>11</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>B </cell>
            <cell>Phyſicians room for patients, in- <lb/>cluding the apothecary's ſhop</cell>
            <cell><hi rend="dc(2)">}</hi>21 by</cell>
            <cell>14</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>C </cell>
            <cell>Surgeons room for patients, in- <lb/>cluding the ſurgery </cell>
            <cell><hi rend="dc(2)">}</hi> 21 by</cell>
            <cell>14 </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>D </cell>
            <cell>Surgeons room </cell>
            <cell>13 by </cell>
            <cell>11 </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>E </cell>
            <cell>Staircaſe </cell>
            <cell>14 by </cell>
            <cell>11 </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>F </cell>
            <cell>Hall </cell>
            <cell>10ft. wide</cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>G </cell>
            <cell>Portico</cell>
            <cell/>
            <cell/>
          </row>
        </table>
        <table>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Basement Story</hi> to contain </head>
          <row>
            <cell>A kitchen, ſcullery, beer and coal cellars. </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>A <hi rend="sc">Hot</hi> and <hi rend="sc">Cold Bath</hi>. </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <table>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/><hi rend="sc">One Pair Story</hi>, fifteen feet high, to <lb/>contain </head>
          <row>
            <cell/>
            <cell>Feet </cell>
            <cell>Feet </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>A committee room </cell>
            <cell>40 by </cell>
            <cell>21 </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Two rooms behind ditto, each </cell>
            <cell>13 by </cell>
            <cell>11 </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <table>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/><hi rend="sc">Two Pair Story</hi>, ten feet high, to <lb/>contain </head>
          <row>
            <cell>Four bedchambers. </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <trailer rend="space">FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
