<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Trusler: An Easy Way to Prolong Life, by a Little Attention to Our
          Manner of Living</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>John Trusler</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">AN EASY WAY TO PROLONG LIFE, By a Little Attention to Our Manner of
              Living. Containing many salutary observations, on Exercise, Rest, Sleep, Evacuations,
              &amp;c. Together with an Enquiry into the following points. Why some, who are very
              hungry and gave goot appetites, eat little, while others, having little appetites, eat
              much? Whence is it, that the accustomed hour of eating being passed, we often lose our
              appetite? Whether the losing of blood in the spring, be necessary for the preservation
              of health? Whether the occasional use of cordials; be prejudicial to the constitution?
              AND Some remarks on Drunkenness, Smoking, and on the utility of taking physic in the
              spring. </title>
            <edition n="4"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">N7173</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N7173"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for the author, and sold by J. Bell</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1780</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="4"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="39"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">Countway Library of Medicine</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3307602291</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K004313.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Health guide"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_1"/>
        <p rend="align-center">
          <lb/>AN <lb/><hi rend="size(2)">EASY WAY </hi>
          <lb/>TO <lb/><hi rend="size(3)">PROLONG LIFE</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="align-center">
          <lb/>By a Little ATTENTION to <lb/>Our way of LIVING. </p>
        <p rend="align-center">
          <lb/>[Price Eighteen Pence.] </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <head rend="dc(1.5) align-center">
          <lb/>ADVERTISEMENT. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE rapid ſale of the firſt part of this <lb/>work, and the
          general approbation the <lb/>Public hath beſtowed upon it, has induced <lb/>the author to
          complete his ſubject; and he <lb/>perſwades himſelf the obſervations in the <lb/>following
          pages, will be found no leſs impor- <lb/>tant that thoſe in the preceeding ones. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_4"/>
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Fifteen Rules neceſſary to be obſerved, in order to preſerve Health. </head>
        <list>
          <lb/>
          <item>1. Aërem purum ſuaveſque odores ſpirare. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>2. Cibum adverſante ſtomacho non ingerere. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>3. Cibaria ingrati &amp; extranei ſaporis vitare. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>4. Cruda, aut non bene cocta non guſtare. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>5. Cibos natura et coctione multum diſcrepantes eâdem <lb/>mensâ non aſſumere. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>6. Ad ſaturitatem nunquam edere et bibere. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>7. Cibos boni ſucci et facilis coctionis comedere. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>8. Cibis naturae et conſtitutioni convenientibus uti. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>9. Somnum moderatum &amp; tempeſtivum capere. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>10. Motum corporis moderatum non negligere. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>11. Ventrem modicè laxum habere. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>12. Veneris illecebras ejuſque uſum tanquam peſtem fugere. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>13. Melancholicos alioſque enormes animi affectus fugere. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>14. Corpus veris initio pharmaco convenienti purgare. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>15. Vitam probem et in corruptam degere. </item>
        </list>
        <p rend="align-center">
          <lb/>Hæc qui ſervabit corpus juvenile tenebit: </p>
        <p rend="align-center">
          <lb/>Hæ qui not ſervat, vitioſum corpus habebit. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_5" n="1"/>
      <head rend="align-center space">
        <lb/>AN <lb/><hi rend="size(2)">EASY WAY</hi>
        <lb/>TO PROLONG <lb/><hi rend="size(2)">LIFE</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">H</hi>AVING, in the firſt part of this work, gone <lb/>through the
        ſeveral properties of the va- <lb/>rious kinds of food, and ſhewn how far they <lb/>agree or
        diſagree with different conſtitutions, <lb/>we proceed now, according to our promiſe, in
        <lb/>order to complete this treatiſe upon health, to <lb/>conſider Exerciſe, Reſt,
        Excretions, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> for <lb/>let us ever be ſo obſervant of the
        former, unleſs <lb/>we pay a careful attention to theſe, we ſhall not <lb/>be able to keep
        ourſelves well. We ſhall treat <lb/>of them, therefore in their turns, and we will
        <lb/>begin with, </p>
      <div type="part">
        <pb xml:id="page_6" n="2"/>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>EXERCISE. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Now, in the human Syſtem, there is a <lb/>certain quantity only of living power that
          <lb/>can be produced for the health of the body; ſo <lb/>that if we exhauſt that power, we
          debilitate or <lb/>weaken the body. A man, for example, may <lb/>walk, till he can walk no
          longer: it is, therefore, <lb/>neceſſary to know how far Exerciſe is ſalutary; <lb/>but
          let us firſt conſider the great benefits procured <lb/>by it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Exerciſe encreaſes the natural heat of the body, <lb/>and thus excites and dilates
          the ſpirits, making <lb/>them far more vigorous and active. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It empties the ſtomach and promotes the ap- <lb/>petite for the next meal; for, as in
          ſedentary <lb/>habits, digeſtion does not quite clear the ſto- <lb/>mach, but leaves part
          of the food, which often <lb/>clogs and diſturbs it; exerciſe will excite this to
          <lb/>paſs away, and the ſtomach being thus diſcharged <lb/>of thoſe relicts, the appetite
          ſharpens and craves <lb/>food very ſtrongly. This naturally ſtrengthens <lb/>the powers of
          the ſtomach, and we digeſt our <lb/>next meal better. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_7" n="3"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It alſo excites an expulſion of excrements, not <lb/>ſuffering any ſuperfluous matter
          to lodge in the <lb/>body. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It likewiſe opens the pores, and gives a free <lb/>perſpiration, which too much reſt
          will ſhut up. <lb/>Nature has appointed theſe vents, and ſecret ways <lb/>of evacuation,
          to cleanſe the habit of the body; <lb/>which in a little time would be clogged and be-
          <lb/>come very foul and impure, by an accumulation <lb/>of ſuperfluous humours. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It, in the laſt place, promotes and adds greatly <lb/>to the nutrition of the body.
          We find by expe- <lb/>rience, that active, ſtirring people, have a freſher
          <lb/>countenance, a greater flow of ſpirits; nay <lb/>their fleſh is firmer and their
          limbs ſtronger, <lb/>than what is generally met with in perſons that <lb/>lead a
          ſedentary, idle and ſluggiſh life; for it is a <lb/>maxim univerſally known and received,
          that a fre- <lb/>quent exertion of the original powers, in any one <lb/>part of the body,
          tends to ſtrengthen that part. <lb/>For example, the legs of a dancer ſhall be <lb/>ſtrong
          and luſty, when his arms ſhall be weak and <lb/>ſmall, and the arms of a blackſmith or
          water- <lb/>man ſhall be muſcular and powerful, while their <lb/>legs ſhall fall away. The
          reaſon of this is very <lb/>evident: exerciſe circulates the blood and nutri- <pb
            xml:id="page_8" n="4"/>
          <lb/>tive juices, gives them a free paſſage to all parts <lb/>of the limbs ſo exerciſed,
          and drives off all ſu- <lb/>perfluous humours, that, without it, would be
          <lb/>deſtructive. But, </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Such exerciſe is to be choſen, as ſuits beſt with <lb/>the nature of each perſon's
          body, ſome requiring <lb/>exerciſe of the upper parts moſt, others of the <lb/>lower
          parts, and ſome equally of both; but that <lb/>is generally moſt advantageous, that
          exerciſes <lb/>every part, as dancing, fencing, riding, tennis, <lb/>ringing, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Now, whatever be our exerciſe, thoſe whom <lb/>good fortune has enabled to take it or
          not, would <lb/>do well to attend to the following obſervations. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Exerciſe ſhould be daily in the morning; al- <lb/>ways with an empty ſtomach; and, if
          poſſible, <lb/>after excremental evacuation; for the heat of the <lb/>body, opening the
          veſſels, may otherwiſe draw <lb/>foul humours into the blood and occaſion very
          <lb/>dangerous obſtructions. For this reaſon, it is not <lb/>ſo well to take any
          extraordinary exerciſe upon a <lb/>full ſtomach, or till the inteſtines are clear. <note
            place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Though any great exerciſe after meals is
            injurious, to <lb/>walk gently is exceedingly wholeſome, for, b<choice>
              <corr>y</corr>
              <sic>o</sic>
            </choice> this means, <lb/>our food will deſcend to the bottom of the ſtomach, the
            <lb/>natural heat of the body will be encreaſed, and digeſtion will <lb/>go on the
            better. Where perſons can retire after meals into the ſweet air, and ſuch delightful
            places as exhilerate the ſpi- <lb/>rits, tis right to do it. If the ſtate of the body be
            ſuch, as <lb/>that we cannot walk after meals, it will be right to ſtand up, <lb/>at
            leaſt, according to the old verſe, <lb/>
            <q rend="quotes">Poſt paſtum ſtabis, paſſu mollive meabis. </q>
            <lb/>That is, ſtand up after meals, or walk gently. </note>
        </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_9" n="5"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Exerciſe ſhould be varied according to your <lb/>conſtitution and the ſeaſon of the
          year. Young, <lb/>ſtrong, robuſt perſons, in cold weather, admit of <lb/>greater exerciſe;
          old, weak and thin perſons, in <lb/>hot weather, of leſs; for the fatter and groſſer
          <lb/>the body is, ſo much the more is the natural heat <lb/>diminiſhed, and exerciſe more
          neceſſary to diſ- <lb/>ſolve the ſuperfluous moiſture of the body, which <lb/>occaſions
          groſſneſs, and to encreaſe the circulation <lb/>of the blood. Circulation being naturally
          briſker <lb/>in the ſummer, exerciſe is leſs needful, but more <lb/>ſo in the winter, as
          the moiſture of the ſeaſon <lb/>will ſometimes occaſion obſtructions in the lungs <lb/>and
          breaſt, which ſtrong and laborious motion <lb/>will often remove. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Exerciſe, opening the pores, we ſhould be <lb/>careful not to uſe it in a damp air,
          leſt we take <lb/>in ſome of its noxious qualities, that may do us <pb xml:id="page_10"
            n="6"/>
          <lb/>harm; neither ſhould we expoſe the body, after <lb/>it, leſt we catch cold, but theſe
          things are ſo <lb/>well known, that they need not be further <lb/>explained. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Another neceſſary caution to be obſerved, is, <lb/>that exerciſe be not too violent,
          nor continued <lb/>longer than it is a pleaſure; but that we deſiſt <lb/>before we be
          weary, or ſweat too much. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Thoſe, who from age or infirmities are unable <lb/>to take exerciſe, ſhould rub their
          bodies, morning <lb/>and evening, with flannel or coarſe linen gloves. <lb/>All parts may
          be rubbed, except the ſtomach <lb/>and belly; rubbing theſe will diſturb digeſtion
          <lb/>and offend the head. We may apply a warm <lb/>cloth to them in the room of it. The
          loins of the <lb/>back likewiſe ſhould not be rubbed, unleſs we <lb/>feel them cold, and
          then but gently, leſt they <lb/>ſhould be over-heated and obſtructions in the uri-
          <lb/>nary paſſages ſhould enſue. In this operation we <lb/>ſhould begin ſoftly and eaſily,
          encreaſing the mo- <lb/>tion and weight of our hand, as the tenderneſs <lb/>of the skin
          will permit, till the fleſh, as it were, <lb/>ſwell and be ſomewhat ruddy, and then
          deſiſt; <lb/>for too much rubbing will bring on an inflamma- <lb/>tion. Was every perſon,
          well or ill, to rub them- <lb/>ſelves in this manner, once or twice a day, for a <pb
            xml:id="page_11" n="7"/>
          <lb/>little while, they would never omit it; for they <lb/>would find themſelves glow with
          a natural warmth, <lb/>their limbs would be active and their joints ſupple. <lb/>It is for
          this reaſon, that children are rubbed, <lb/>who can take no exerciſe; and experience
          teaches <lb/>us, that the currying and rubbing a horſe, not- <lb/>withſtanding his
          exerciſe, is a great addition to <lb/>his health. In cold and moiſt ſeaſons the head
          <lb/>alſo ſhould be rubbed with a coarſe linen cloth, <lb/>warmed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Thus having ſet out the times for exerciſe and <lb/>motion, let us proceed to
          conſider </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>REST. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Reſt is as neceſſary to preſerve health, and con- <lb/>tinue us in ſtrength and
          vigour, as exerciſe. When <lb/>the body is fatigued, reſt is refreſhing, and renews
          <lb/>its ſtrength; but when ſatiated with reſt it thirſts <lb/>again for motion and
          agreeable exerciſe. Reſt is a <lb/>burden, if forced upon nature longer than it re-
          <lb/>quires. <hi rend="italic">Interdum quies, inquieta eſt,</hi> ſays Seneca, <lb/>even
          reſt ſometimes is irkſome. For if exerciſe is <lb/>neceſſary for the preſervation of
          health, too much <lb/>inactivity muſt be prejudicial. <hi rend="italic">Ignavia corpus
            <lb/>hebetat, labor firmat.</hi> Sluggiſhneſs makes the mind <lb/>and body dull and
          heavy, whereas frequent mo- <lb/>tion ſtrengthens and invigorates them. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_12" n="8"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The life of man, converſant in change, ſpends <lb/>its whole courſe in ſleep and
          watching; the one <lb/>appointed for reſt and eaſe, the other for action <lb/>and labour.
          If he was conſtant in the firſt, his <lb/>life would be only the ſhadow of death; if in
          <lb/>the laſt, he would ſoon be exhauſted. Nature <lb/>therefore hath wiſely contrived,
          that man ſhould <lb/>not long continue in either, but wear out his life <lb/>between the
          two. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Sleep is a placid ſtate of body and mind, giv- <lb/>ing refreſhment and eaſe to both;
          for as an ex- <lb/>ertion of the faculties either of mind or body <lb/>exhauſts our
          powers, reſt will reſtore thoſe <lb/>powers. The powers of the mind are like a <lb/>ſmall
          current, which is ſufficient to keep up a <lb/>continual motion. If we want to give this
          wa- <lb/>ter greater power, we dam it up, and when the <lb/>water is run from the dam, if
          we wiſh to produce <lb/>a freſh power, equal to the firſt, we ſhut the <lb/>ſluices, and
          collect the water again: ſo it is with <lb/>the mind, in ſleep. In perfect ſleep, both the
          body <lb/>and mind are at reſt, excepting in thoſe particu- <lb/>lars, where an exertion
          is neceſſary to life; and <lb/>in ſleep, it is that the body receives a greater
          <lb/>degree of nutrition; it is then digeſtion takes <lb/>place in an extraordinary
          degree, and recruits <pb xml:id="page_13" n="9"/>
          <lb/>thoſe ſpirits that were exhauſted in the courſe of <lb/>the preceding day. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Now that ſleep may prove advantageous, an- <lb/>ſwering the intentions and deſigns of
          nature; let <lb/>us conſider four things concerning it. The time <lb/>when it ſhould be
          taken; the neceſſary limits, or <lb/>quantity of ſleep required; the ſalubrity of the
          <lb/>place, and the poſition of the body. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The time moſt proper for ſleep, is, according <lb/>to the appointment of nature, the
          night, when <lb/>creation, in general, take its reſt. At the <lb/>ſhutting up of the day,
          when the ſun gets below <lb/>the horizon; the ſpirits are not ſo active and <lb/>lively,
          but incline to a ceſſation. Tis then they <lb/>return to the centre of the body and apply
          <lb/>themſelves to what is called concoction; that is <lb/>they return to perform their
          vital operations, to <lb/>nouriſh and refreſh the ſyſtem. For during the <lb/>heat of the
          day, they are dilated and extended <lb/>to the external or circumferent parts. Hence, we
          <lb/>find, that, towards midnight, unleſs we are in <lb/>exerciſe, put on another garment,
          or encreaſe the <lb/>heat of the room, we always find ourſelves <lb/>chilly. In the
          morning again, at the riſing of <lb/>the ſun, our ſpirits are naturally freſh, brisk and
          <lb/>active. If we therefore, prevert the order of <pb xml:id="page_14" n="10"/>
          <lb/>nature, turn day into night, by keeping late <lb/>hours, and laying in bed, all the
          morning, we do <lb/>that which is greatly deſtructive to our conſtitu- <lb/>tion. For as
          ſleep naturally draws the animal <lb/>heat inwards, and the heat of the ſun counteracts
          <lb/>this power, by drawing it outwards; ſleeping <lb/>in the day is a reſiſting of
          nature, which muſt be <lb/>prejudicial to the health of the body. Sleeping <lb/>in the
          day, therefore, is a bad cuſtom, particu- <lb/>larly for fat, corpulent people; but if the
          <lb/>ſpirits be fatigued with care or buſineſs, or by <lb/>reaſon of old age, weakneſs of
          nature, extreme <lb/>hot weather, labour, or the like; then mo- <lb/>derate day-ſleep is a
          good refreſhment, but <lb/>take it rather ſitting than lying down, becauſe <lb/>the head
          will be leſs offended with the riſing <lb/>vapours. Neither ſhould it be taken immedi-
          <lb/>ately after dinner, but an hour or half an hour <lb/>after, at leaſt; and between
          dinner and our nap, <lb/>it would be prudent to walk a little. Thus <lb/>will our food
          deſcend better into the ſtomach and <lb/>be leſs liable to affect the head. Neither ſhould
          <lb/>this afternoon's nap be longer than half an hour, <lb/>or an hour at moſt, leſt the
          animal heat ſhould be <lb/>ſo collected from the outward parts, as to cauſe a
          <lb/>heavineſs in the head: neither ſhould it be taken <lb/>in a hot place, but in one
          cool rather, eſpecially in <lb/>ſummer time, as ſhall hereafter be ſhewn. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_15" n="11"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Sitting up late is one of the great deſtroyers <lb/>of the conſtitution; it tires and
          waſtes the animal <lb/>ſpirits, by keeping them too long upon duty; <lb/>weakens nature,
          haſtens on the effects of old age, <lb/>changes a freſh, florid countenance into a ſallow
          <lb/>one; heats and dries the body, breeds rheums <lb/>and bad humours and is particularly
          injurious to <lb/>thin people. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>By going early <hi rend="italic">to</hi> aſleep and early <hi rend="italic">from</hi>
          it, we <lb/>riſe refreſhed, lively and active. Sleeping late <lb/>in the morning, keeps
          that excrementitious <lb/>matter in the inteſtines which ought to be eva- <lb/>cuated and
          thus occaſions obſtructions and noi- <lb/>ſome vapours, which greatly offend the head,
          <lb/>dull the ſenſes and are very pernicious to the <lb/>whole body. If our neceſſities
          indeed oblige us to <lb/>ſit up late, our ſupper ſhould be little, and we <lb/>may make
          amends for it by laying an hour or two <lb/>longer in the morning; but let what will
          happen, <lb/>we ſhould always be up by nine o'clock. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In order that ſleep may be peaceable and re- <lb/>freſhing, we ſhould be careful to
          go to bed with <lb/>a free and quiet mind, and baniſh the thoughts <lb/>of all manner of
          care and buſineſs. How often <lb/>has a train of thinking diſturbed a man's reſt, and
          <lb/>kept him awake the whole night! The body <pb xml:id="page_16" n="12"/>
          <lb/>and the mind is recruited in proportion to the <lb/>ſoundneſs alſo of ſleep. The more
          we dream <lb/>the leſs are we refreſhed. Although reſt is not <lb/>complete at the
          beginning, it has a tendency to <lb/>become ſo, during this ſtate of the body; that is
          <lb/>to a quiet mind, ſleep becomes ſounder and <lb/>ſounder. When a man firſt falls
          a-ſleep, he dreams, <lb/>toſſes and tumbles about; gradually he becomes <lb/>more quiet,
          and were we awake him, he would <lb/>not recollect that he had been dreaming at all, or
          <lb/>he would tell us, he dreamed, but in a ſmall de- <lb/>gree. During ſleep the original
          power appears <lb/>to be ſo much accumulated, as to give a diſpo- <lb/>ſition to action,
          both to the mind and body, from <lb/>the ſlighteſt cauſe; ſleep then leaves us and we
          <lb/>awake: that is, when the powers are recruited, <lb/>the organs begin to be affected,
          and the man <lb/>dreams afreſh; at laſt, outward objects ſenſibly <lb/>affect him and he
          awakes. 'Tis then the mind is <lb/>fitteſt for action; the judgment is then ſtronger,
          <lb/>the imagination more lively and as the evening <lb/>comes on, theſe powers are
          gradually diminiſhed, <lb/>and require freſh ſleep to recruit them. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The next thing that falls under our conſidera- <lb/>tion, is the quantity of ſleep we
          take. This has <lb/>been in ſome meaſure noticed; but it may not be <lb/>unneceſſary to be
          a little more particular. It <pb xml:id="page_17" n="13"/>
          <lb/>cannot indeed be determined how long we may <lb/>ſleep; as in all other things, a
          mediocrity is beſt. <lb/>Our ſleep ſhould be proportioned to our health, <lb/>our age, the
          complexion and emptineſs or fulneſs <lb/>of the ſtomach. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As the nutrition of the body is particularly <lb/>aſſiſted by ſleep, we ſhould ſleep,
          in general, till <lb/>the food we take has performed its office; <lb/>that is, till what
          phyſicians call concoction is <lb/>completed. This may be diſcerned on our <lb/>awaking by
          the ſenſible lightneſs of the body, <lb/>eſpecially the head; the emptineſs of the ſto-
          <lb/>mach, and a certain deſire of evacuation, pro- <lb/>vided it is not unnaturally
          occaſioned. Heavi- <lb/>ness of the head and eyes, or a taſte of our <lb/>laſt meal,
          ſignify that we have not ſlept a ſuf- <lb/>ficient length of time. In ſhort, ſix, ſeven or
          <lb/>eight hours is long enough for young perſons in <lb/>health, but ſuch as are ſickly
          and weak require <lb/>longer reſt, nine, ten or eleven hours. Children <lb/>and old men
          require more ſleep, in general, <lb/>than young or middle-aged perſons; children,
          <lb/>that their growth may the better be promoted, <lb/>and old men, becauſe it leſſens
          the dryneſs of <lb/>their conſtitution. The ſame reaſon holds good <lb/>with lean people,
          to whom more ſleep is neceſ- <lb/>ſary than to ſuch as are fat; for ſleep moiſtens <pb
            xml:id="page_18" n="14"/>
          <lb/>and refreſhes the whole ſyſtem. In a word, as im- <lb/>moderate ſleep, or ſleep taken
          at improper times <lb/>weakens the natural heat, loads the head with <lb/>vapours, detains
          the excrements longer than is <lb/>wholeſome, makes men ſluggiſh and heavy- <lb/>headed,
          deſtroys the memory and ſubjects them <lb/>to the palſy, lethargy, &amp;c. ſo too little
          ſleep <lb/>dries up the conſtitution, dims the ſight, waſtes <lb/>the ſpirits and deſtroys
          all the powers and facul- <lb/>ties both of mind and body. It muſt be ob- <lb/>ſerved,
          that we ſhould not go to bed upon a full <lb/>ſtomach; that is, not go to reſt too ſoon
          after <lb/>ſupper; but continue up an hour or two, till <lb/>our food be half digeſted; if
          we are obliged to <lb/>ſup late, we ſhould eat the leſs: for, on account <lb/>of the
          natural heat of the body retiring inwards <lb/>during the time of ſleep, a full ſtomach
          will oc- <lb/>caſion a ſuperfluity of vapours, and greatly offend <lb/>the head. Beſides,
          great ſuppers are very apt <lb/>to occaſion heart-burn, which will of courſe de-
          <lb/>prive us of our reſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A matter occurs here; whether it be beneficial <lb/>or not to have our bed warmed?
          Perſons in years, <lb/>ſuch as are weak and thoſe who lead a tender and <lb/>delicate
          courſe of life, do right to warm their <lb/>beds, in cold and moiſt ſeaſons of the year;
          and <lb/>that for two reaſons; that the body, on putting <pb xml:id="page_19" n="15"/>
          <lb/>off our cloaths, may not be ſuddenly affected <lb/>with the external cold; and as the
          inward heat <lb/>of the body is much aſſiſted by the warmth of <lb/>the bed, concoction
          will be forwarded and the <lb/>ſuperfluous moiſture of the body be the better
          <lb/>conſumed. But this cuſtom is unwholeſome to <lb/>thoſe perſons who are healthful and
          ſtrong, be- <lb/>cauſe it will very much weaken them. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When we ariſe in the morning we ſhould find <lb/>it amply compenſate for our trouble,
          were we <lb/>gently to rub our breaſts and ſides downward with <lb/>our hands, and the
          reſt of our body more ſtrongly <lb/>with flannel or a hot linnen cloth, particularly our
          <lb/>joints. Doing this will quicken the blood, <lb/>ſtrengthen the parts and excite the
          natural heat. <lb/>When riſen, we ſhould ſtretch ourſelves out, that <lb/>the animal
          ſpirits may be dilated to the exterior <lb/>parts of the body, walk a little up and down,
          <lb/>that the remaining contents of the ſtomach may <lb/>more ſpeedily deſcend; this done,
          we ſhould pro- <lb/>ceed to cleanſe our noſe, by blowing it; to clear <lb/>our breaſt, by
          expectoration, and to make every <lb/>other neceſſary evacuation. We ſhould waſh and
          <lb/>and plunge our eyes in cold water, for this not <lb/>only clears away the filth, but
          ſtrengthens and <lb/>preſerves the ſight. The mouth ſhould be well <lb/>cleanſed with the
          ſame, and the teeth rubbed <pb xml:id="page_20" n="16"/>
          <lb/>with a dry coarſe cloth, after firſt ſcouring them <lb/>with a ſage leaf, dipped in
          vinegar. This will <lb/>purify the breath, and preſerve the teeth from <lb/>foulneſs and
          decay: and laſt of all the head <lb/>ſhould be combed, that the pores may be opened
          <lb/>to expel ſuch vapours, as were not conſumed by <lb/>ſleep. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The next thing to be mentioned is the ſalu- <lb/>briety of the place we ſleep in. A
          high room, <lb/>dry, ſweet and well-aired, free from ſmoke and <lb/>remote from noiſe, is
          the moſt wholeſome: nei- <lb/>ther ſhould our chamber be hot, for the ſpirits <lb/>and
          natural heat of the body, which is drawn in- <lb/>wardly by ſleep, as before-mentioned,
          will be <lb/>counteracted by any extraordinary heat in the <lb/>room; but it ſhould be
          moderately warm, and <lb/>free from damps, either natural or artificial, ariſ- <lb/>ing
          from new plaiſtered walls, waſhing the floor <lb/>or otherwiſe. It may not be amiſs here
          to men- <lb/>tion the danger of ſleeping in the open air or on <lb/>the ground, as many in
          the ſummer ſeaſon do. <lb/>Thoſe whoſe ſtations in life oblige them to it, <lb/>as
          ſoldiers, though for the preſent they eſcape <lb/>the miſchief, are frequently afterwards
          made ſen- <lb/>ſible of the injury, by aches, ſtiffneſs or weakneſs <lb/>of limbs, and
          many other infirmities that pro- <lb/>ceed from it. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_21" n="17"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Our beds may be ſoft, but ſhould not ſink in, <lb/>as that will ſuck from the body,
          exhauſt and im- <lb/>pair our ſtrength. A mattraſs upon a feather-bed <lb/>is both eaſy
          and wholeſome. As bedding receives <lb/>the vapours, and ſweaty moiſture of the body, we
          <lb/>ſhould be careful that it is always clean, ſweet <lb/>and well-aired; for if it is
          not purified by air or <lb/>fire, it will contract an ill ſcent and become un-
          <lb/>wholeſome. If every one ought to be thus care- <lb/>ful of the beds they conſtantly
          lie in themſelves, <lb/>we may ſee how neceſſary it is that travellers <lb/>ſhould be
          cautious how and where they ſleep. No <lb/>bed-chamber ſhould be waſhed in cold, wet or
          <lb/>foggy weather; ſweeping and bruſhing is ſuffici- <lb/>ent to keep it decent, and
          airing it in clear, dry <lb/>days, by opening the windows, will prevent its <lb/>becoming
          offenſive. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As to the nature of our covering at night, it <lb/>ſhould be according to the ſeaſon
          of the year. <lb/>The head ſhould be covered ſufficiently to pre- <lb/>vent its taking
          cold, but not too warm, leſt it <lb/>weaken it and haſten grey hairs; for if the va-
          <lb/>pours iſſuing from the brain are impeded in their <lb/>paſſage, it will cauſe the
          hair to turn grey, much <lb/>ſooner than it otherwiſe would. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>With reſpect to our manner of laying; we <pb xml:id="page_22" n="18"/>
          <lb/>may in a great meaſure conſult our own eaſe. <lb/>The head ſhould be higher than any
          other part <lb/>of the body; the bed from head to feet, ſhould <lb/>be ſmooth and even,
          without any fall below the <lb/>pillow, or hollow under the ſhoulders. Sleeping
          <lb/>generally on the back is unwholeſome, as the hu- <lb/>mours of the head naturally
          fall by this means <lb/>into the hinder part of the brain and may diſor- <lb/>der it, and
          the loins are thus more heated than <lb/>they would otherwiſe be, and of courſe the
          urinary <lb/>paſſages more ſubject to obſtructions. Perſons <lb/>afflicted with the ſtone
          ſhould by no means ſleep <lb/>on their backs. Sleeping with the back up- <lb/>wards may be
          occaſionally good for ſuch perſons <lb/>as are troubled with wind and have a weak di-
          <lb/>geſtion, the bowels being thus kept ſo much the <lb/>warmer; but to thoſe who have
          weak eyes it is <lb/>pernicious, as a defluxion of humours may thus <lb/>fall into them.
          The moſt wholeſome method of <lb/>ſleeping, is on the ſide, firſt on the left ſide, eſpe-
          <lb/>cially to thoſe who go to bed before they have <lb/>digeſted their ſupper, as the
          food will in this caſe <lb/>better deſcend to the bottom of the ſtomach; and <lb/>then on
          the right, that the motion of the heart <lb/>may be freeſt from preſſure. But the
          principal <lb/>thing to render ſleep comfortable, is, as was <lb/>hinted before, to
          compoſe the mind. If we lie <lb/>down with roving, troubled thoughts, they will <pb
            xml:id="page_23" n="19"/>
          <lb/>commonly calls us up, before it is fit to riſe, and <lb/>our ſleep will not be piacid
          or refreſhing. When <lb/>we lay by our cloaths, therefore, let us not lay <lb/>aſide our
          buſineſs, care and thoughts, and let not <lb/>a wandering fancy break our reſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It has been often doubted, whether it be good <lb/>to ſleep with the mouth a little
          open. Some <lb/>there are, that altogether deny it; but to ſleep <lb/>with the mouth open
          is certainly beneficial, <lb/>and that, for theſe three reaſons: becauſe the breath
          <lb/>paſſes more freely and the fuliginous fumes are <lb/>better ſent forth than
          diſcuſſed. Hence it is that <lb/>ſuch as ſleep with the mouth open, have a ſweet
          <lb/>breath, whereas thoſe that ſleep with it ſhut, have <lb/>generally an offenſive
          breath and foul teeth. The <lb/>ſecond is, becauſe ſome bad moiſture may in ſleep
          <lb/>paſs forth at the mouth, which if ſhut, would fall <lb/>upon the lungs and be
          prejudicial. The third rea- <lb/>ſon is, becauſe owing to the deſcent of rheumes <lb/>from
          the head, the free paſſage of the breath <lb/>through the noſe may be impeded, and
          ſnorings, <lb/>and offenſive routings enſue, that may diſturb us <lb/>of our reſt, and
          awaken us. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But becauſe the tongue, palate and gums of <lb/>ſuch as ſleep with their mouth open,
          are com- <lb/>monly afterwards very dry and covered with ſli- <pb xml:id="page_24" n="20"/>
          <lb/>my matter, though in fact, thoſe who ſleep with <lb/>their mouth ſhut are moſt
          ſubject to it, all perſons <lb/>in the morning, ſhould waſh their mouths and <lb/>teeth
          well and gargle their throats, and then eve- <lb/>ry inconvenience is removed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The only thing further to be enquired into, <lb/>upon this ſubject, is whether
          ſweating at night be <lb/>deſtructive to the conſtitution or not. Great ſweats <lb/>are
          undoubtedly weakening, but light ſweats are <lb/>a great benefit, for groſs humours are
          thereby diſ- <lb/>ſolved, wind is diſcuſſed, the blood is purified, <lb/>the ſpirits are
          refreſhed, the cramp, palſy, gout, <lb/>ſwelling of the joints and other parts, achs,
          <lb/>numbneſs and heavineſs of the limbs are prevent- <lb/>ed, and conſequently the whole
          body better pre- <lb/>ſerved, lively, and in health. But, this caution <lb/>muſt be
          obſerved, and the body be not ſuddenly a <lb/>fter it expoſed to the cold air. We will
          proceed <lb/>now to. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>EXCRETIONS or EVACUATIONS. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>All that the ſtomach receives is not fit to be <lb/>retained; our food, though
          ſtudiouſly choſen <lb/>and temperately uſed, is not all converted into <lb/>the ſubſtance
          of the body; but ſome part of it is, <pb xml:id="page_25" n="21"/>
          <lb/>to be ſeparated and ſent forth; the reſt is to ſup- <lb/>ply and nouriſh. This
          regular courſe being con- <lb/>tinued, the body thrives and is in good order; but <lb/>if
          that which ſhould be evacuated, be retained, <lb/>or that which ought to be retained, be
          injurioſly <lb/>paſſed off, the regular oeconomy is ſubverted <lb/>and the conſtitution
          ſuffers and decays. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The general excretions of the body are the <lb/>ſtool or <hi rend="italic"
            >faeces</hi> and the urine, and for eaſe and <lb/>health they ought to be daily
          evacuated. If our <lb/>habit be naturally lax, it is a happineſs, provided <lb/>that
          laxity be not immoderate; for ſuch perſons <lb/>as are continually coſtive, and have
          ſeldom the <lb/>benefit of nature, in the reſpect we are now talk- <lb/>ing of, are liable
          to many diſorders. The <hi rend="italic">fæces</hi>
          <lb/>retained longer than they ought, too often affect <lb/>the head, dim the ſight,
          occaſion heavineſs, dul- <lb/>neſs, and a degree of fever. Tis neceſſary there- <lb/>fore
          they ſhould be daily evacuated. If this cannot <lb/>naturally be obtained, the occaſional
          taking of a l <lb/>ittle lenitive electuary will be very neceſſary. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Seminal evacuations ought alſo to be mode- <lb/>rate. The ſperm is a ſubſtance full
          of ſpirit, and <lb/>if wilfully waſted, will hurt the conſtitution more <lb/>than the loſs
          of forty times the quantity of blood. <lb/> Immoderate venery is known to impair the <pb
            xml:id="page_26" n="22"/>
          <hi rend="italic">
            <lb/>ſtrength, hurt the ſight, conſume the ſpirits, and <lb/>haſten old age and death.
          </hi>
        </p>
        <q>
          <lb/>
          <l>Cibo vel potus repletis, ſuperfluè evacuatis, ſive <lb/>exercitatis, coitus
            interdicitur. </l>
          <lb/>
          <l>Tempus optimnm eſt manè &amp; poſt dormias. </l>
          <lb/>
          <l>Hyeme &amp; vere frequentius permittitur; æſtate <lb/>parciús. </l>
          <lb/>
          <l>Juvenes, ſanguinei &amp; pituitoſi liberalius, parcius mel<lb/>ancholici; parciſſimè
            bilioſi, ſenes emaciati. </l>
        </q>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Although it has been an old ſaying, as fooliſh <lb/>as common, <hi rend="italic">Qui
            medicè vivit, miſerè vivit;</hi> he <lb/> that lives by rule, lives miſerably; yet expe-
          <lb/>rience teaches us the contrary, and grounded <lb/>upon pure reaſon and the contents
          of theſe pages: <lb/>that he who pays no regard to the injunctions of <lb/>nature, both
          ſhortens his life and deſtroys the <lb/>comforts of it. In ſhort, would you ſee with-
          <lb/>out ſpectacles, go without crutches, or the help <lb/>of a ſtick; would you lie eaſy
          in your bed, not <lb/>telling the clock or wiſhing for day; would you <lb/>eat with an
          appetite and be <hi rend="italic">yonng</hi> in ſtrength <lb/>when you are <hi
            rend="italic">old</hi> in years: in fact, would you <lb/>enjoy yourſelf, and every thing
          about you, and <lb/>lengthen your life to the lateſt period; exerciſe <lb/>your reaſon and
          attend to the advice here given, <lb/>for <pb xml:id="page_27" n="23"/>
          <lb/>
          <q rend="italic align-center">Qui medicè vivit, ſine medicis diu vivet. </q>
          <lb/>He that lives by rule and wholeſome precepts, <lb/>is a phyſician to himſelf, and
          needs not the help <lb/>of others </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Whence it is that ſome who are very hungry and have good appetites, eat little; while
          others, hav-little appetites, each much? </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HIS proceeds from the difference of ſto- <lb/>machs. A man,
          with a ſmall ſtomach, <lb/>that will hold but little, will be ſatisfied with a <lb/>ſmall
          quantity of food; whereas one, with a large <lb/>ſtomach, though he ſeems not hungry, yet
          when <lb/>he comes to his meal, will eat plentifully. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A ſtomach naturally cold, will crave more than <lb/>it can digeſt. On the contrary, a
          hot ſtomach has <lb/>but little appetite, for heat deſtroys it. Hence <lb/>it appears,
          that a perſon, with a large capacious <lb/>ſtomach, naturally cold, will devour an immode-
          <lb/>rate quantity of food: while one, with a ſmall <lb/>ſtomach, naturally hot, will at
          his meals eat little <lb/>or nothing. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <pb xml:id="page_28" n="24"/>
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Whence it is, that the accuſtomed hour of eating be- <lb/>ing paſſed, we often loſe
          our appetite. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">B</hi>ECAUSE the ſtomach being empty and hun- <lb/>gry, draws up
          from the inteſtines putrid <lb/>vapours, which deſtroy the appetite. And as <lb/>theſe
          vapours not only annoy the ſtomach, but <lb/>the head and ſpirits, ſuch as are deſirous of
          health, <lb/>ſhould at their uſual hours of meals, if they find <lb/>a craving for food,
          always indulge it by eating a <lb/>little. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Cautions to be obſerved in the uſe of drinking. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HE neceſſity and uſe of drink is to preſerve <lb/>natural
          moiſture, and to make good a mix- <lb/>ture and diſtribution of meat, that it may digeſt
          <lb/>the better. For theſe reaſons it ſhould be mode- <lb/>rately taken at meals. Sundry
          little draughts <lb/>are more wholeſome than two or three large ones. <lb/> Large draughts
          at meals makes the food fluctuate <lb/>in the ſtomach. This with its weakening and
          <lb/>relaxing the coats of the ſtomach, deſtroys di- <lb/>geſtion. Great draughts alſo
          leſſen the natural <lb/>heat of the ſtomach, drives the food down too <lb/>haſtily, and
          corrups the whole body with too <lb/>great moiſture and crudity. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_29" n="25"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It will not be improper to mention here, that <lb/>ſuch perſons as accuſtom
          themſelves to taking <lb/>ſoup the firſt thing at a meal, would do well to <lb/>take it as
          hot as they can, as the heat will be <lb/>very comfortable to the ſtomach. Taken luke-
          <lb/>warm it would ſoon prove nauſeous, though <lb/>never ſo good. The drinking cold beer
          after hot <lb/>ſoup or broth is an abſurd and hurtful cuſtom, <lb/>for it counteracts the
          heat of the ſoup, deſtroys <lb/>the tone of the ſtomach, and does miſchief. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Drinking after meals, unleſs we are dry, is a <lb/>pernicious cuſtom, eſpecially if
          we drink during <lb/>digeſtion is taking place, as it deſtroys the na- <lb/>tural heat
          that is working in the ſtomach. But <lb/>after the food is paſſed off from the ſtomach,
          <lb/>that is, three or four hours after the meal, a few <lb/>glaſſes of wine, to a perſon
          in years, or of a cold <lb/>conſtitution is beneficial; as it will cleanſe the
          <lb/>ſtomach of the relicks of the food, and create a <lb/>readier diſtribution of the
          nutritive part of it, to <lb/>the different parts of the body. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <pb xml:id="page_30" n="26"/>
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>The utility of taking phyſic in the ſpring. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HE winter by its moiſture naturally fills the <lb/>body with
          crude and excrementitious hu- <lb/>mours, and by its coldneſs thickens and ſtagnates
          <lb/>the ſame; and the approaching ſpring working <lb/>on thoſe humours, rarifying and
          diſſolving them, <lb/>they are apt to fluctuate and putrify in the body, <lb/>which,
          unleſs by the force of nature, or the aſ- <lb/>ſiſtance of medicine, are often the cauſe
          of ſick- <lb/>neſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Beſides the uncertainty of the weather in ſpring, <lb/>its ſudden alterations from
          hot to cold, and from <lb/>dry to moiſt, will frequently produce feveriſh <lb/>diſorders,
          according to the diſpoſition of the <lb/>matter congealed as it were in the body during
          the <lb/>preceding winter. Hence it happens, that people <lb/>die more frequently in the
          ſpring than in any other <lb/>ſeaſon of the year. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Such perſons, therefore, as are deſirous to <lb/>prevent theſe ill effects, ſhould
          take a doſe or two <lb/>of purging phyſick; eſpecially thoſe who lead <lb/>a ſedentary
          life: and the beginning of the ſpring <lb/>is generally, the beſt time for this ſalutary
          pre- <lb/>caution. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_31" n="27"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is not neceſſary in general to take phyſic, by <lb/>way of prevention, in the fall
          or autumn of the <lb/>year. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Whether the loſing of blood in the ſpring, be neceſſary for the preſervation of the
          health? </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">F</hi>OR ſuch as are of a ſanguine conſtitution, <lb/>phlethoric and
          full of blood, it is benefical, <lb/>to prevent ſuch dangers as a too great fullneſs of
          <lb/>blood may occaſion; but it is far better to leſſen <lb/>their blood by a ſparing and
          cooling diet, than <lb/>by opening a vein. For blood being the very <lb/>eſſence of our
          life, diminiſhing its quantity fre- <lb/>quently, weakens the ſpirits and the conſtitu-
          <lb/>tion, and haſtens death. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Whether the occaſional uſe of cordials be prejudicial to the conſtitution? </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">W</hi>HEN uſed medicinally, in caſe of neceſſity, <lb/>as when the
          ſtomach is weak, or lapſed by <lb/>cold, a cordial may comfort and refreſh it. But
          <lb/>the immoderate, daily, or unſeaſonable uſe of <lb/>ſtrong liquors muſt be pernicious.
          Although <lb/>they may pleaſe the palate, and ſometimes not <pb xml:id="page_32" n="28"/>
          <lb/>offend, but warm and refreſh the ſtomach; yet, <lb/>in length of time, from daily
          uſe, and perhaps <lb/>in an improper ſeaſon, they muſt deſtroy the tem- <lb/>perature of
          the body, burn up the blood, and <lb/>produce very dangerous ſymptoms. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Some obſervations upon drunkenneſs. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">I</hi>T is a maxim eſtabliſhed upon good reaſon, <lb/>that <hi
            rend="italic">every thing exceeding its juſt bounds, is <lb/>hurtful to nature.</hi> The
          beſt of things are not ex- <lb/>cepted in this general rule. Even the neceſſary <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">ſupports</hi> of life, if not qualified and made whole- <lb/>ſome by this
          corrective, may prove the <hi rend="italic">procurers</hi>
          <lb/>of death. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Drink, when carried to exceſs, is no longer a <lb/>refreſhment, to moiſten or water
          the thirſty bo- <lb/>dy; nor a preſervative; but becomes an inunda- <lb/>tion, to drown
          and ſuffocate the vital powers, and <lb/>is the cauſe of ſickneſs. It puts a man out of a
          <lb/>ſtate of health, and diſorders him ſo much, that <lb/>we may conſider him as going to
          die. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It has been ſaid by ſome ancient phyſicians, <lb/>that to be drunk, once a month, is
          good phyſic <lb/>and wholeſome, as by overcharging the ſtomach <lb/>it provokes vomiting
          and ſo carries off what may <pb xml:id="page_33" n="29"/>
          <lb/>be there lodged, that would otherwiſe breed diſ- <lb/>eaſe; but this a poor plea for
          drunkenneſs; <lb/>that for the gaining one ſuppoſed benefit, (which <lb/>might be obtained
          by other means) we ſhould <lb/>run the risk of bringing on twenty diſorders. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Drunkenneſs is certainly a diſeaſe, for it has all <lb/>the requiſites to conſtitute
          a diſeaſe, and is far <lb/>diſtant from a ſtate of health. For if health be <lb/>the free
          and regular diſcharge of the functions <lb/>of the body and mind, and ſickneſs a weak and
          <lb/>imperfect diſcharge of thoſe functions; then <lb/>ebriety may properly be ſaid to be
          a diſeaſe or <lb/>ſickneſs; it having the ſymptoms of an acute <lb/>diſeaſe; for, during
          the time of drunkenneſs and <lb/>ſome time after, few of the faculties perform their
          <lb/>office righly. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If we examine the intellectual faculties, we <lb/>ſhall find the reaſon gone, the
          memory loſt or <lb/>bewildered, and the will ſtrangely perverted. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If we look into the ſenſitive faculties they are <lb/>alſo diſordered; their
          functions impeded, or very <lb/>defectively performed. The eyes do not ſee <lb/>well, the
          ears hear well, nor the palate reliſh, <lb/>&amp;c. The ſpeech falters and is imperfect;
          the <lb/>ſtomach throws up its contents, or nauſeates; <pb xml:id="page_34" n="30"/>
          <lb/>the legs fail, and the whole man is out of <lb/>order. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Now, according to theſe ſymptoms in other <lb/>diſeaſes, we ſhould judge the patient
          not likely <lb/>to live, or we ſhould deem his recovery very <lb/>difficult. Surely then
          drunkenneſs, for the time <lb/>it laſts, muſt be a very great diſeaſe. But be- <lb/>cauſe
          it does not in general prove mortal, or <lb/>continue long, it is thought little or
          nothing of, <lb/>and is conſidered as a trival matter, that will <lb/>cure itſelf. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But it may be asked, why drunkenneſs is not <lb/>uſually mortal, ſince the ſame
          ſymptoms in other <lb/>diſeaſes would be accounted ſo? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>To this we anſwer; all the hopes we have that <lb/>a drunken man ſhould live; is
          firſt, becauſe com- <lb/>mon experience ſhews that drunkenneſs is not <lb/>mortal;
          ſecondly, from the nature of the cauſe, <lb/>(ſtrong drink) which though it rage and
          ſtrangely <lb/>diſcompoſe the man for a time, yet it laſts not <lb/>long, nor is it
          commonly mortal. The inebriat- <lb/>ing ſpirits of the liquor, flowing in ſo faſt and
          <lb/>joining with the natural ſpirits of the man, oc- <lb/>caſions a tide, ſo high as to
          overflow all the <lb/>banks and bounds of order; but theſe adven- <pb xml:id="page_35"
            n="31"/>
          <lb/>titious ſpirits are ſo amicable and friendly to our <lb/>bodies, in their own nature,
          as not to be equally <lb/>deadly injurious, with that which is not ſo fami- <lb/>liar.
          Beſides, their being ſo very volatile, light, <lb/>and active nature, much ſooner recovers
          herſelf, <lb/>than if the morbific matter were more ſolid, <lb/>ponderous, and fixed. And,
          further, </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Thoſe bad ſymptoms in other diſeaſes are more <lb/>to be feared, becauſe they depend,
          perhaps, up- <lb/>on malignant cauſes; ſuch as, by time, may be <lb/>rooted in the
          conſtitution, or from the defection <lb/>of ſome principal part; but the ſtorm ariſing
          from <lb/>drunkenneſs, as it is ſuddenly raiſed, ſo common- <lb/>ly it ſoon abates. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But though drunkenneſs be not mortal, nor <lb/>the danger, perhaps, great for the
          preſent; yet <lb/>drunken bouts frequently repeated, their relicts <lb/>will accumulate,
          weaken nature, and lay the <lb/>foundation of many chronic diſeaſes. Nor can <lb/>it be
          expected otherwiſe; ſo that we may juſtly <lb/>conclude, from the manifeſt irregular
          actions <lb/>which appear to us externally, that the internal <lb/>functions and their
          motions are ſtrangely diſor- <lb/>dered: for outward madneſs proceeds from in- <lb/>ward
          impulſes and diſordered motions of the fa- <lb/>culties; which general diſturbance muſt of
          courſe <pb xml:id="page_36" n="32"/>
          <lb/>overturn the oeconomy of nature, and conſe- <lb/>quently ruin the whole ſyſtem. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The ill effects ariſing from intoxication, are a <lb/>changing of the natural tone of
          the ſtomach, a <lb/>deſtruction of its digeſtive powers, and degene- <lb/>ration of the
          nutritive part of our food. Com- <lb/>mon experience tells us, that, after a drunken
          <lb/>debauch, the ſtomach loſes its appetite, and <lb/>readineſs of digeſtion, and, of
          courſe, nauſea, <lb/>belching, and thirſt enſue. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Great drinkers generally acquire an unwhol- <lb/>ſome corpulency of body, or a lean
          confumptive <lb/>conſtitution; few of them eſcape. So great a <lb/>dependance is there
          upon the ſtomach, that other <lb/>parts cannot perform their duty, if this leading
          <lb/>principal part be perverted and debauched. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Now that different habits of body ſhould ariſe <lb/>from the ſame cauſe, is owing to
          the different <lb/>diſpoſition of parts: for in ſome perſons, although <lb/>the ſtomach be
          vitiated, yet the ſtrength of the <lb/>ſubſequent digeſtions is ſo great, from the vi-
          <lb/>gour of thoſe parts deſtined to ſuch offices, that <lb/>they act ſtrenouſly, though
          the matter on which <lb/>they act be tranſmitted to them imperfect and <lb/>degenerate,
          and do therefore keep the body <pb xml:id="page_37" n="33"/>
          <lb/>plump and full, although the juices be foul and <lb/>of a depraved nature. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Others, on the contrary; whoſe parts are not <lb/>ſo ſtrong, loſe the benefit of
          nutrition, and fall <lb/>away. Hence it is that by exceſſive drinking <lb/>one man ſhall
          puff up, fill, and grow dropſical; <lb/>while another pines away, and becomes conſump-
          <lb/>tive. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A third injury, and a common one ariſing <lb/>from intemperate drinking, is a
          weakneſs of <lb/>the nerves, brought on by diſorderly motions of <lb/>the animal ſpirits.
          Thus we ſee the inconve- <lb/>niences and miſchiefs attendant upon intempe- <lb/>rance. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Drinking together is the pledge of friendſhip, <lb/>and to be made drunk is the
          characteriſtic of a <lb/>generous and hearty entertainment: for, moſt <lb/>commonly,
          drinking concludes the feaſt. When <lb/>nature has been tempted with varieties, and per-
          <lb/>haps overcharged with them; the next folly is to <lb/>diſturb and inebriate the
          ſpirits, vitiate the fer- <lb/>mentation, and precipitate the food out of the <lb/>ſtomach
          by a flood of liquor, before digeſtion <lb/>be finiſhed; that if you have eſcaped a
          ſurfeit by <lb/>eating, you ſhall not go away without a miſchief <pb xml:id="page_38"
            n="34"/>
          <lb/>by drinking; thus your good dinner is ſpoiled, <lb/>and inſtead of being benefited by
          it, you are in- <lb/>jured, and your friends civility becomes your de- <lb/>ſtruction. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But to the neceſſary uſes of drink appointed <lb/>by nature, we have invented others,
          and made <lb/>it ſerve for pleaſure, for profit, for wantonneſs, <lb/>and debauchery. So
          that drink, which ſhould <lb/>help to ſupport, nouriſh, and maintain the ſtrength <lb/>and
          vigour of nature, is made an unhappy in- <lb/>ſtrument to abuſe and injure the
          conſtitution. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>However, as of drinking and drunkenneſs we <lb/>have enumerated the evils, let us not
          be ſo par- <lb/>tial as to ſmother the benefits. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Drinking advances the revenue of exciſe and <lb/>cuſtom. Makes barley bear a good
          price, and <lb/>helps the farmer to pay his rent. It keeps the <lb/>phyſician and
          apothecary in employ, and doubt- <lb/>less adds conſiderably to their buſineſs; and is
          <lb/>the ſupport of many a publican. But whether <lb/>drinking ought to be promoted, to
          forward theſe <lb/>advantages, with the deſtruction of health, the <lb/>ſhortening of
          life, and the debauchery of the <lb/>people: we leave the reader to judge. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <pb xml:id="page_39" n="35"/>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>OBSERVATIONS <lb/> ON THE <lb/>SMOAKING of TOBACCO. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>OBACCO is an herb of great antiquity and <lb/>reputation among
          the Indians of America. <lb/>It is alſo called <hi rend="italic">Nicotian;</hi> but the
          name, Tobacco, <lb/>was given it by the Spaniards, from an iſland on <lb/>which it
          plentifully grew, and that of Nicotian, by <lb/>the French, from one Nicot who firſt made
          them <lb/>acquainted with it. The Indians call it <hi rend="italic">Petun</hi> or <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Petum,</hi> which is indeed the beſt general name to <lb/>give it,
          deriving it from the Latin word <hi rend="italic">Peto,</hi> it <lb/>being far fetched and
          much ſought after. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is an herb, hot and dry in its nature, and, <lb/>we believe of a deſtructive or
          venomous quality, <lb/>for being taken any way into the body, it cauſes <lb/>ſuch a
          diſturbance as to occaſion violent vomiting <lb/>and purging, ſtupefying the ſenſes and
          benumb- <lb/>ing every part. Theſe effects do not proceed <lb/>from the temperature of the
          herb, but from the <lb/>very eſſence of it. Common experience con- <pb xml:id="page_40"
            n="36"/>
          <lb/>vinces us of its ſtupefying quality; for ſmoaking <lb/>to ſuch as are not uſed to it,
          will bring on a drun- <lb/>en-like lightneſs of the head and, if perſiſted in <lb/>for any
          length of time, will occaſion a ſleepineſs <lb/>of the whole ſyſtem. Now as the benumbing
          <lb/>effect of a plant generally ariſes from the cold- <lb/>neſs of its quality, and as
          Tobacco is of a hot <lb/>nature, it is evident that its ſleepy quality is not <lb/>owing
          to its temperature but its very ſubſtance. <lb/>However, there is in the juice of this
          herb a cleanſ- <lb/>ing and healing property, and it is very effectual <lb/>in the cure of
          any freſh wound, or old ſore. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If it be objected by thoſe who accuſtom them- <lb/>ſelves to ſmoke or chew tobacco,
          that they find <lb/>none of theſe injurious qualities I have menti- <lb/>oned, let it be
          conſidered, that it is owing to ha- <lb/>bit, for by a conſtant uſe of it, they in time
          ren- <lb/>der themſelves inſenſible to its effects, in the ſame <lb/>manner as the Turks
          do, with reſpect to their <lb/>chewing opium. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Indians, from whom we learned the man- <lb/>ner of ſmoaking, accuſtomed
          themſelves to uſe to- <lb/>bacco, only when they were much fatigued with <lb/>labour or
          exerciſe, or when the wiſhed to foretell <lb/>things to come. For the ſmoke's lulling them
          to <pb xml:id="page_41" n="37"/>
          <lb/>ſleep and creating ſundry dreams; on their awak- <lb/>ing, they found themſelves
          refreſhed, and from <lb/>their wandering thoughts during their inſenſibi- <lb/>lity, they
          fondly conceived, they could progno- <lb/>ſticate the event of any buſineſs they took in
          <lb/>hand or any matter of importance they wiſhed to <lb/>know. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Their method of uſing it was this. Having <lb/>dried the leaves, they caſt them on
          the coals, <lb/>and with a cane received the ſmoke of them by <lb/>the mouth and noſtrills
          till they fell into a <lb/>drunken trance or ſleep, in which they continued <lb/>three or
          four hours, according to the quantity <lb/>of ſmoke they had taken in. After which they
          <lb/>found themſelves lightened and refreſhed, and <lb/>were able to return to their
          labour or exerciſe as <lb/>before. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But we ſmoke tobacco for no ſuch purpoſe; <lb/>where one perſon takes a pipe
          medicinally, a <lb/>hundred do it for pleaſure to paſs away the time. <lb/>And as this is
          done indiſcriminately at all times <lb/>and by all ages and conſtitutions, very often to
          <lb/>the injury of health, a few obſervations upon this <lb/>ſubject, can be no leſs
          profitable than pleaſing. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_42" n="38"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Notwithanding there is ſomething injurious in <lb/>the nature of tobacco, and it
          leaves a diſagreea- <lb/>ble ſmell and ſavour behind it; yet it is beneficial <lb/>to ſuch
          perſons as are of a cold, moiſt conſtitu- <lb/>tion, and troubled with rheums, eſpecially
          in <lb/>cold, damp weather, and when uſed moderately; <lb/>for it will expel wind,
          diſſolve and diſſipate cold <lb/>humours, raiſe the ſpirits, eaſe pains in the teeth,
          <lb/>ſwellings of the gums and aches of the joints; <lb/>and if the ſmoke be ſwallowed, it
          will ſpeedily <lb/>cure a ſurfeit, by cauſing a ſudden evacuation <lb/>both upwards and
          downwards. But to ſuch as are <lb/>not of a cold and moiſt conſtitution, nor affected
          <lb/>with rheums, tho' it be only taken in at the mouth <lb/>and immediately ejected, it
          is unwholeſome, as <lb/>its heat will greatly affect the brain and diſturb the <lb/>animal
          ſpirits. As to ſwallowing the ſmoke, un- <lb/>less medicinally, or by way of phyſic, it is
          abſo- <lb/>lutely pernicious both to the ſtomach and the <lb/>lungs, for it diſturbs
          digeſtion and tends to dry <lb/>up the ſoft and ſpungy ſubſtance of the lungs. <lb/>If any
          one therefore has habituated himſelf to this <lb/>idle practice, let him inſtantly leave
          it off, for <lb/>though he may find no great inconveniencies <lb/>ariſing from it, while
          he is young and ſtrong, <lb/>yet he may be aſſured, when it is too late to re- <lb/>pair
          the injury, he will diſcover that it has ruined <lb/>his conſtitution. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_43" n="39"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>There are two or three cautions to be obſerved <lb/>by thoſe who accuſtom themſelves
          to ſmoaking, <lb/>which ſhall conclude the whole; one is, that in <lb/>drawing the ſmoke,
          they take care that they <lb/>ſuck it not ſuddenly into their throat or windpipe, <lb/>as
          in ſuch caſe it will much offend and diſturb <lb/>both the lungs and the mouh of the
          ſtomach. <lb/>Another caution is in returning the ſmoke from <lb/>the mouth, to take care
          it does not outwardly <lb/>affect the eyes, for it will do them a great deal <lb/>of
          injury. A third caution, not to go abroad <lb/>into the air for half an hour after they
          quit their <lb/>pipe, eſpecially if the ſeaſon be cold or damp, <lb/>for the tobacco will
          open the pores of the head, <lb/>and the ſudden acceſs of the cold air may do <lb/>a great
          deal of miſchief. Hence we may ſee how <lb/>idle and fooliſh ſuch perſons act, who walk or
          <lb/>travel with a pipe in their mouths. In the laſt <lb/>place, ſuch as are of a dry,
          lean conſtitution, <lb/>ſhould ſhun the uſe of tobacco totally, for its dry- <lb/>ing
          nature muſt be deſtructive to ſuch habits. </p>
      </div>
      <trailer rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_44"/>
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>This Day is publiſhed by <hi rend="roman">J. BELL,</hi> in the <hi rend="italic"
            >Strand.</hi> Price <hi rend="italic">1s. 6d.</hi> with a beautiful Frontiſpiece, and
          with very conſiderable Additions and Improvements, a new Edi- <lb/>dition, being the
          Seventh, of </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>RUSLER's Chronology; or the <lb/>HISTORIAN's VADE MECUM:
          wherein e- <lb/>very remark the Occurrence in our own Hiſtory, from the <lb/>Deſcent of
          Julius Caeſar, to the preſent time; as well as <lb/>mort of the principal Events of
          ancient Hiſtory, are accu- <lb/>rately and alphabetically recorded, with the Dates
          affixed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>For ther with a full and exact Chronology of the moſt <lb/>eminent Men, in all Ages
          of the World: with ſeveral <lb/>uſeful Liſts; ſuch as the Kings of every Country, the Ro-
          <lb/>man Emperors, and when they reigned, the Lord Lieute- <lb/>nants of Ireland, the
          Chancellors of Oxford and Cambridge, <lb/>and all the Biſhops, &amp;c &amp;c. for many
          Years back. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This Book is printed in ſuch Manner as to lie in a <lb/>Pecker Book, being deſigned
          to ſet People right in Con- <lb/>verſation, when talking of hiſtorical Matters, and is of
          <lb/>ſuch uſe, that when we are in doubt of the time when any <lb/>Occurrence happened, or
          when any celebrated Perſon was <lb/>born, or died, the perciſe Day may inſtantly be found.
          <lb/>Though of ſo ſmall a Size, it contains upwards of five <lb/>thouſand Articles. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>N. B. It anſwers all the Purpoſes of Blair's Chronology, <lb/>a Book that ſills for
          five Pounds.—It is done in the Man- <lb/>ner of the <hi rend="italic">Bries
            Chonology,</hi> that may be ſeen in every com- <lb/>mon Sheet Almanack. </p>
        <div type="part">
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Specimen of the Work. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>African Company eſtabliſhed 1695. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Alderman firſt appointed 882. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Baronets firſt created 1611. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Benefices, Church, came in Uſe, about 500. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Cheſs, the game of, invented 608 before Chriſt. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Doctor, the degree of, firſt given in England 1207. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Epiſcopacy aboliſhed in Scotland 1638. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>N. B. As there are ſome incorrect, ſimilar publica- <lb/>tions, pleaſe to ask for
              <hi rend="italic">Truſter's Chronology,</hi> that with Dr. <lb/>Truſier's name on the
            frontiſpiece. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
