<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Lettson: History of some of the effects of hard drinking</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>John Coakley Lettsom</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">History of some of the effects of hard drinking.</title>
            <edition n="6"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">N33225</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N33225"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed by W. Darton and Co. No. 55, Gracechurch-Street; and sold
                  by C. Dilly, in the Poultry, M.DCC.XCI.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1791</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="3"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="12"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">Harvard University Libraries</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3308436127</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K016530.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Health guide"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <head rend="dc(2) align-center">
          <lb/>PREFACE. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N the firſt volume of the "Memoirs of the Medical Society
          <lb/>of London," I deſcribed ſome of the unhappy effects of <lb/>the too free indulgence
          of ſtrong liquors. My opinions have <lb/>been diſſeminated by inſertion into many public
          prints, both <lb/>at home and abroad; and I have reaſon to conclude, have <lb/>been
          productive of eſſential benefit to the community. To <lb/>render this benefit ſtill more
          extenſive, I have reprinted that <lb/>part of the original eſſay, more immediately
          applicable to <lb/>the pernicious uſe of theſe liquors, to which I have added <lb/>ſome
          farther cautions; and likewiſe a moral and phyſical <pb xml:id="page_3" n="ii"/>
          <lb/>Thermometer, the hint of which was ſuggeſted by a friend <lb/>abroad. It is formed to
          convey, by a glance of the eye, the <lb/>ſentiments I wiſh to impreſs upon the reader. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>LONDON, April 1789. </p>
        <p rend="align-right">
          <lb/>JOHN COAKLEY LETTSOM. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">This little Performance was originally printed to give away; but
            the Demands be- <lb/>coming very numerous, I have applied it to the Benefit of the</hi>
          <hi rend="sc">Philanthropic <lb/>Society</hi>, <hi rend="italic">inſtitued "for the
            Prevention of Crimes, and for a Reform in the <lb/>Manners of the riſing Poor."</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The general Outlines of the Plan adopted by the Society, are to take miſerable and
          <lb/>deſtitute Children from poor depraved Parents, and from the reſorts of wicked
          <lb/>People, to cloath, feed, and educate them as Orphans; and thus by a total ſe-
          <lb/>paration from their abominable connections, and a redemption from the loweſt
          <lb/>depths of diſtreſs, to reſtore them to civil community, to which they were either
          <lb/>loſt, or known only as its burthens, nuiſances, and plunderers. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Although</hi> this Society has been but a few months eſtabliſhed, there
          are already <lb/>placed under the care of proper perſons, in hired houſes, conveniently
          ſituated at <lb/><hi rend="sc">Hackney</hi>, ſeveral Children of both ſexes, who a few
          weeks ſince were inhabi- <lb/>tants of the moſt miſerable abodes of vice and want; but are
          now enjoying the <lb/>bleſſings of a new life, heightened by the proſpects of acquiring an
          honourable <lb/>ſupport by their own induſtry. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_4"/>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>HISTORY <lb/>OF <lb/>SOME OF THE EFFECTS <lb/>OF <lb/>HARD DRINKING. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>FTER introducing the want of appetite for food <lb/>ariſing
          from the indulgence of drinking ſtrong <lb/>liquors, I cannot well diſmiſs the ſubject,
          without adverting <lb/>more fully to its painful influence upon the conſtitution,
          <lb/>which I have obſerved with more anxiety, as the ſufferers <lb/>are often thoſe of the
          more delicate part of the female ſex, <lb/>whoſe habits of intemperance are not
          unfrequently intro- <lb/>duced by thoſe who ſhould have been the guardians of their
          <lb/>health. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> miſeries entailed by theſe indulgences, differ <lb/>much as to
          their progreſs and violence, and even the <pb xml:id="page_5" n="2"/>
          <lb/>ſymptoms vary ſo much, as to admit of obvious diſ- <lb/>tinctions. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">firſt</hi> I ſhall notice, as being generally leſs painful, <lb/>though
          equally permanent, are the ſymptoms more eſpecial- <lb/>ly attendant on perſons who have,
          early in life, habituated <lb/>themſelves to drink freely of wine of various kinds, and
          from <lb/>their ſituations in life, undergone a change of climate, as from <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Europe</hi> to the <hi rend="italic">Indies,</hi> &amp;c. Punch-drinkers,
          likewiſe, <lb/>have been liable to ſimilar complaints. The firſt appear- <lb/>ance of
          diſeaſe is loſs of appetite, which at length is ſo <lb/>weakened and vitiated,, that after
          taking food, before the <lb/>return of the next meal, a kind of heavy pain of the ſto-
          <lb/>mach, with a conſtriction of the muſcles of the abdomen, <lb/>come on, and with a
          ſlight effort, a ſweetiſh, brackiſh, or <lb/>acid fluid, is thrown up, and the pain and
          conſtriction for a <lb/>ſhort time ſubſide. For ſeveral years in this unhappy ſtate,
          <lb/>the patient drags on a life, rendered now and then more <lb/>ſupportable, either by
          renewed potations, or exputations, till <lb/>at length the bodily and mental powers become
          impaired: <lb/>the object grows emaciated, the whole body ſhrinks; nei- <lb/>ther ſwelling
          nor dropſy appear, though the countenance <lb/>looks ſallow; the region of the liver is
          not enlarged, and the <lb/>liver itſelf ſeems leſs than natural: the urine is not very
          <lb/>high coloured; the <hi rend="italic">fæces</hi> are hard and dark-coloured; <lb/>the
          ſtomach will take and retain food, but after receiving it, <pb xml:id="page_6" n="3"/>
          <lb/>it is oppreſſed, and feels tightened or contracted in its <lb/>dimenſions; the
          patient expreſſes it, as if it were tied by a <lb/>ſtraight bandage; the ſame ſenſation
          affects the inteſtines, <lb/>and the abdomen ſuffers ſuch irregular conſtrictions, as
          <lb/>become evident to the external touch, the muſcles being <lb/>drawn into irregular
          action, the ſurface of the belly is di- <lb/>verſified with protuberances and cavities:
          ſometimes the <lb/>ſpaſmodic ſtrictures run tranſverſely, and raiſe this ſurface <lb/>like
          waves of the ſea. The pain continues increaſing to <lb/>ſuch exceſs, that the miſerable
          ſufferer is obliged to preſs <lb/>againſt a table or ſome hard body, to mitigate his
          diſtreſs, <lb/>till vomiting brings a reſpite; or he haſtens this operation, <lb/>by
          thruſting his finger into the throat; and thus relieves <lb/>himſelf till the next
          reception of nouriſhment, when the ſame <lb/>tragedy is repeated. The matter diſcharged is
          thin, acrid, <lb/>ſour, ſweet, or brackiſh. Sometimes, inſtead of conſtipa- <lb/>tion, an
          occaſional purging enſues, and mitigates the pain, <lb/>whilſt it ſubdues the
          conſtitution; and after years of miſery, <lb/>the victim ſlides into a fatal decay; but
          long before this, <lb/>the powers of the mind have been debilitated, and its recol-
          <lb/>lection and actions impaired. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">ſecond</hi> train of diſtreſſful ſymptoms which I ſhall <lb/>relate,
          more generally ſucceed the free uſe of ſpirits, or of <lb/>wines with the admixture of
          ſpirits, as Madeira; and eſpe- <pb xml:id="page_7" n="4"/>
          <lb/>cially where late hours and illicit amours have been <lb/>ſuperadded. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> early ſymptoms of complaint are, a pain and oppreſ- <lb/>ſion
          about the pit of the ſtomach after eating, or diſtenſion <lb/>from fluids; this pain
          extends to the breaſt and ſhoulders; <lb/>there are frequent eructations of wind, which
          ſeem to burn <lb/>the throat as they aſcend; theſe ſymptoms, which are uſual <lb/>in
          affections of the liver, and particularly in bilious effuſions, <lb/>are at firſt ſo
          trivial, as ſeldom to alarm the fears of the <lb/>patient, or he ſlightly mentions them as
          ſymptoms of the <lb/>gout, whilſt he attempts to avert the preſent ſuffering, by
          <lb/>indulging more freely in the very cauſe of the miſchief, till <lb/>repeated fillips
          of raw ſpirits, or a dilution of the poiſon, <lb/>render exiſtence miſerable. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> appetite now totally fails, but an inſatiable thirſt con-
          <lb/>tinues, and if it be not ſupplied with an exhilarating cordial, <lb/>the vital
          ſpirits inſtantly flag, and ſuch horrors take place as <lb/>are dreadful even to a
          bye-ſtander; the poor victim is ſo de- <lb/>preſſed, as to fancy a thouſand imaginary
          evils; he expects <lb/>momentarily to expire, and ſtarts up ſuddenly from his <lb/>ſeat;
          walks wildly about the room; breathes ſhort, and <lb/>ſeems to ſtruggle for breath; if
          theſe horrors ſeize him in <lb/>bed, when waking from ſlumber, he ſprings up like an
          elaſtic <lb/>body, with a ſenſe of ſuffocation, and the horrors of fright- <pb
            xml:id="page_8" n="5"/>
          <lb/>ful objects around him; at the ſame time the pain of the <lb/>ſtomach continues and
          augments; the fight of wholeſome <lb/>plain food gives diſguſt, inſtead of appetite; drink
          is his <lb/>cry; or if hunger is excited, it is after high-ſeaſoned, ſalt, <lb/>or acrid
          nouriſhment. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">At</hi> this time, if a dropſy, or fatal jaundice, do not
          <lb/>terminate exiſtence, the legs ſhrink, are ſwarthy-coloured like <lb/>the reſt of the
          body, and ſometimes purple ſpots appear and <lb/>diſappear for many months; the
          extremities feel ſore to the <lb/>touch, and upon ſcratching them, exude blood: the thighs
          <lb/>likewiſe ſhrink; but the body, and particularly about the re- <lb/>gion of the liver,
          enlarges, and the hardneſs of the liver may <lb/>be frequently traced: the face is nearly
          copper-coloured, is <lb/>emaciated, ſometimes with little ſuppurations, which dry <lb/>and
          turn ſcaly; the breath ſmells like rotten apples, and the <lb/><hi rend="italic">morbus
            niger,</hi> or vomitings of a fluid like that of coffee-grounds, ſnatch the patient from
          complicated miſery. Some- <lb/>times a purging, or bloody diſcharges, haſten the cata-
          <lb/>ſtrophe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">third</hi> train of ſymptoms to be deſcribed, is not con- <lb/>ſined to
          age or ſex, but is in general more frequently the <lb/>attendant of the female ſex. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> perſons liable to the ſymptoms, have been thoſe of <pb
            xml:id="page_9" n="6"/>
          <lb/>delicate habits, who have endeavoured to overcome the <lb/>nervous debility, by the
          aid of ſpirits: many of theſe have <lb/>begun the uſe of theſe poiſons from perſuaſion of
          their utili- <lb/>ty, rather than from the love of them: the relief, however, <lb/>being
          temporary, to keep up their effects, frequent acceſs <lb/>is had to the ſame deluſion,
          till at length what was taken by <lb/>compulſion, gains attachment, and a little drop of
          brandy, <lb/>or gin and water, becomes as neceſſary as food; the female <lb/>ſex, from
          natural delicacy, acquire this cuſtom by ſlow de- <lb/>grees, and the poiſon being
          admitted in ſmall doſes, is ſlow <lb/>in its operations, but not leſs painful in its
          effects. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> ſoberer claſs of tradeſmen, alſo, who occaſionally in-
          <lb/>dulge in their ſixpenny-worth of brandy and water, gradually <lb/>ſlide into the ſame
          unhappy habits, and entail upon their <lb/>conſtitutions the ſame miſery, which I ſhall
          now introduce. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> firſt appearance of indiſpoſition very much reſembles
          <lb/>what has been laſt deſcribed; and under the deception of <lb/>the gout, the fuel is
          heaped upon the fire, till the deluſion has <lb/>been too long maintained to admit of
          retreat: in general, at <lb/>leaſt, the attachment to the uſe of ſpirituous drinks, be-
          <lb/>comes ſo predominant, that neither threats nor perſuaſions <lb/>are powerful enough
          to overcome it. The miſerable ſufferer <lb/>is ſo infatuated, as, in ſpite of locks and
          keys, to bribe by high <lb/>rewards the dependent nurſe, privately to procure it. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_10" n="7"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> the concluding ſymptoms are very different from <lb/>either of
          the foregoing hiſtories: frequently, indeed, the <lb/>appetite for food vaniſhes, but
          ſometimes continues vora- <lb/>cious; and, at the ſame time, whilſt the body is coſtive,
          and <lb/>no vomiting enſues, the lower extremities grow more and <lb/>more emaciated; the
          legs become as ſmooth as poliſhed ivory, <lb/>and the ſoles of the feet even glaſſy and
          ſhining, and at the <lb/>ſame time ſo tender, that the weight of the finger excites
          <lb/>ſhrieks and moaning; and yet I have known, that in a mo- <lb/>ment's time, heavy
          preſſure has given no uneaſineſs. The <lb/>legs, and the whole lower extremities, loſe all
          power of ac- <lb/>tion; wherever they are placed, there they remain till <lb/>moved again
          by the attendant; the arms and hands acquire <lb/>the ſame palſied ſtate, and the patients
          are rendered incapable <lb/>of feeding themſelves. Thus for years they exiſt, with no
          <lb/>material alteration in the ſize of the body, or aſpect of the <lb/>countenance. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Whether</hi> they really undergo the agonies they appear <lb/>to
          ſuffer, I much doubt, as at this period their minds appear <lb/>idiotiſh: they often
          ſhriek out with a vehemence that may <lb/>be heard at a conſiderable diſtance, but upon
          enquiring <lb/>about the ſeat of pain, they have been vague and indeciſive <lb/>in their
          anſwers. When a cramp comes on the lower ex- <lb/>tremities, involuntary motions draw up
          the legs, and produce <lb/>the moſt piercing ſhrieks: and the features of the face, al-
            <pb xml:id="page_11" n="8"/>
          <lb/>tered by convulſive twitchings, excite pain in a ſpectator. <lb/>For ſome months
          before they die, theſe ſhrieks are more in- <lb/>ceſſant, and as violent as the ſtrength
          will admit. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">They</hi> talk freely in the intervals of mitigation, but of
          <lb/>things that do not exiſt; they deſcribe the preſence of their <lb/>friends, as if
          they ſaw realities, and reaſon tolerably clear <lb/>upon falſe premiſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Mostly</hi> before they die, they take leſs food; ſometimes <lb/>a
          purging ſucceeds, of a thin ſubſtance, and of a dark green <lb/>colour; ſometimes a
          vomiting of black matter; but moſt <lb/>generally they gradually ſink from the
          accumulation of pain <lb/>and debility. There is rarely any fever. They do not, as <lb/>in
          the preceding ſtate, fall into dropſies, but uſually become <lb/>paralytic: the breath is
          not offenſive, nor is there the ſame <lb/>difficulty of breathing, or horror of
          ſuffocation: whether <lb/>the imperceptible and gradual augmentation in the uſe of
          <lb/>ſpirits, is the cauſe of this difference, I am not certain; but <lb/>the difference
          is conſiderable, as muſt appear from their <lb/>hiſtories, which I have drawn from actual
          obſervation. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">would</hi> not, however, infer, that every ſpirit-drinker
          <lb/>acquires the ſymptoms of diſeaſe above related, or that other <pb xml:id="page_12"
            n="9"/>
          <lb/>diſeaſes do not more frequently ſucceed this dangerous habit: <lb/>liver diſeaſes, of
          various kinds, it is well known, uſually <lb/>reſult from intemperance, and dropſies often
          ſucceed; but <lb/>from ſome circumſtances in the conſtitution, or from the <lb/>mode of
          indulgence in liquors, the ſymptoms I have de- <lb/>ſcribed have ſeverally occurred where
          no dropſical affec- <lb/>tions have ſupervened. There is ſomething in ſprituous
          <lb/>liquors, ſo injurious to the human frame, that too much at- <lb/>tention cannot be
          paid in diſcouraging the uſe of them. <lb/>Many of the unhappy victims I have attended,
          aſcribe their <lb/>ſufferings to the unguarded advice of ſome medical practi- <lb/>tioner,
          who has, under the idea of wine turning ſour on the <lb/>ſtomach, permitted a little drop
          of brandy and water to be ſubſtituted; ſeldom, indeed, a day paſſes without introducing
          <lb/>me to the ſick bed of ſome deluded object of miſery; and it <lb/>is from the moſt
          decided conviction of the injury, that I <lb/>would guard every perſon from beginning with
          even a little <lb/>drop of this faſcinating poiſon, which once admitted, is ſeldom,
          <lb/>if ever, afterwards overcome. Whenever I hear the patient <lb/>plead for ſome
          ſubſtitute for beer or wine, under the ſuppo- <lb/>ſition of their turning ſour, my fears
          are alarmed, and my <lb/>endeavours excited, to pluck the unſuſpicious patient from
          <lb/>the brink of deſtruction; this plea is never made, till the <lb/>exhilarating
          influence of ſpirit has been experienced; and <lb/>not a moment ſhould be loſt, in warning
          ſuch objects of <lb/>their danger. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_13" n="10"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Some</hi>, who avoid brandy, have been induced to take rum, <lb/>from a
          vulgar opinion, that it is more oily and balſamic; <lb/>the argument is erroneous, for
          what balſamic qualities can <lb/>empyreumatic oil contain? Others, who condemn both
          <lb/>brandy and rum, make no objection to gin, becauſe they <lb/>think it diuretic; but ſo
          far from it, that half the dropſies <lb/>among the lower claſſes of the people originate,
          or, at leaſt, <lb/>are confirmed by the uſe of this ſpirit; they are all poiſons, <lb/>and
          are nearly alike deleterious. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">When</hi> the effects of ſpirits on the conſtitution, have not
          <lb/>greatly contaminated it, beyond the frequent recurrence of <lb/>ſickneſs and
          vomiting; after interdicting ſpirits altogether, <lb/>the patient ſhould be allowed to fix
          upon ſome one ſpecies <lb/>of nutriment; and, whatever it is, ſhould be confined to it
          <lb/>alone, and that in the ſmalleſt quantities poſſible, and at re- <lb/>gular ſtated
          diſtances, that the preceding portion may be <lb/>properly digeſted, before any addition
          be allowed: when <lb/>the ſtomach has thus acquired more tone, either ſome new, <lb/>or an
          increaſe of the former nutriment, may be admitted. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">once</hi> attended a lady, who could not retain any food <lb/>on the
          ſtomach above an hour or two. I requeſted her to <lb/>fix upon ſome light nouriſhment that
          ſhe could palate, and ſhe <lb/>mentioned milk: I then reſtrained her to four
          table-ſpoonfuls <lb/>of it every ſix hours, and afterwards increaſed the quantity <pb
            xml:id="page_14" n="11"/>
          <lb/>as the ſtomach could bear it. From this ſhe went to broth, <lb/>and thus gradually
          acquired ſuch a ſtate of the ſtomach, as <lb/>to bear the uſual food of the family; and
          for four years paſt <lb/>ſhe has enjoyed good health, with the moderate uſe of a
          <lb/>glaſs of wine, or beer, but not one drop of ſpirits. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> in ſome caſes, where the habit of drams has been long
          <lb/>continued, the total and ſudden omiſſion of them, has ſunk <lb/>the perſon into
          irretrievable debility. Here this pernicious <lb/>cuſtom muſt be left off gradually. A man
          who uſually <lb/>drank twelve drams a day, being convinced of his approach- <lb/>ing
          miſery, took the reſolution to wean himſelf from this <lb/>poiſon; he always drank out of
          one glaſs, into this he daily <lb/>dropped a drop of ſealing-wax; by this means he had
          <lb/>twelve drops leſs of ſpirit every day, till, at length, his glaſs <lb/>being filled
          with wax, his habit was cured. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> ſame advantage has been obtained, by taking the <lb/>dram, or
          glaſs of cordial, out of a quart bottle, which is to <lb/>be repleniſhed each time with as
          much water, and by this <lb/>means gradually diluting the remaining liquor, till its
          <lb/>ſtrength becomes wholly ſubdued, and little more than the <lb/>ſubſtituted water
          remains. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Painful</hi> indeed is this truth, that when the indulgence <lb/>in
          ſpirituous liquors is rendered habitual, it is extremely dif- <pb xml:id="page_15" n="12"/>
          <lb/>ficult to overcome. Although the miſerable object is per- <lb/>ſuaded, that it clouds
          his reaſon, debilitates his mental as well <lb/>as corporeal faculties, debars him of all
          the cheerful gratifi- <lb/>cations annexed to health and virtue; yet ſo exceſſive are
          <lb/>the debility and tremors of the body—and ſo horrid is the <lb/>deſpondency of the
          mind after the exhilarating effects of <lb/>theſe liquors have ſubſided, that without a
          perſeverance in <lb/>determined efforts to vanquiſh this habit, a repetition of the
          <lb/>deluſive poiſon will be indulged, till reſolution is too tran- <lb/>ſient and weak to
          enable the victim to ſtop at the precipice, <lb/>which terminates his painful exiſtence. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">May</hi> ſuch, however, as have ſtrength of reſolution to re-
          <lb/>flect upon their danger, be encouraged, by an aſſurance, <lb/>that however great the
          debility may feel, and ſtrong the idea <lb/>of diſſolution may appear, yet from mere
          debility alone, <lb/>life is not in danger; and this is a certain fact, that the lon-
          <lb/>ger and more frequently the evil habit is reſiſted, that habit <lb/>becomes leſs
          powerful, whilſt the ſtrength of the conſtitution <lb/>proportionally augments, and
          thereby renders the victory <lb/>leſs difficult than might at firſt appear; and what
          exertions <lb/>are more intereſting and worthy of a rational being, than <lb/>thoſe which
          ſubſtitute vigour and health of body, for agita- <lb/>tion, tremor, and pain; and ſerenity
          and cheerfulneſs of <lb/>mind, for horror, deſpondency, and ſuicide? </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_16"/>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>A <lb/>MORAL AND PHYSICAL THERMOMETER; <lb/>OR, <lb/>A SCALE of the Progreſs of
          TEMPERANCE and INTEMPERANCE. </head>
        <head type="sub" rend="align-center">
          <lb/>LIQUORS, with their EFFECTS, in their uſual Order. </head>
        <figure>
          <lb/>
          <figDesc>ſcale of the effects of temperance and intemperance depicted as a thermometer
          </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>   TEMPERANCE <lb/>70 WATER; <lb/>60 Milk and Water; <lb/>50 Small Beer; <list>
            <lb/>
            <item>Health, Wealth, </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Serenity of Mind, </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Reputation, long Life, and </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Happineſs. </item>
          </list>
          <lb/> 40 Cyder and Perry; <lb/> 30 Wine; <lb/> 20 Porter; <lb/>10 Strong Beer: <list>
            <lb/>
            <item>Cheerfulneſs, </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Strength and, </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Nouriſhment, when taken <lb/>only at meals, and in moderate <lb/>Quantities.
            </item>
          </list>  <lb/> INTEMPERANCE <lb/>0   <lb/>10 Punch <lb/> 20 Toddy &amp; Crank; <list>
            <lb/>
            <item>30 </item>
            <item>Grog, </item>
            <item>and <lb/>Brandy </item>
            <item>and <lb/>Water; </item>
          </list>
          <lb/>40 Flip and Shrub; <lb/>50 <list>
            <lb/>
            <item>Bitters infuſed <lb/>in Spirits; </item>
            <item>Uſquebaugh; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Hyſteric Water; </item>
          </list>
          <lb/>60 <list>
            <lb/>
            <item>Gin, </item>
            <item>Anni- <lb/>ſeed, </item>
            <item>Brandy, </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Rum, </item>
            <item>and <lb/>Whisky in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Morning.</hi>
            </item>
          </list>
          <lb/> 70 Do. during the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Day</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Night.</hi>
          <lb/>VICES. <list>
            <lb/>
            <item>Idleneſs; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Peeviſhneſs; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Quarrelling; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Fighting; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Lying; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Swearing </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Obſcenity; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Swindling; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Perjury; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Burglary; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Murder; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Suicide. </item>
          </list>
          <lb/>DISEASES. <list>
            <lb/>
            <item>Sickneſs; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Puking, and </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Tremors of the <lb/>Hands in the <lb/>Morning; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Bloatedneſs; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Inflamed Eyes; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Red Noſe &amp; Face; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Sore and ſwelled <lb/>Legs; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Jaundice; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Pains in the Limbs, <lb/>and burning in <lb/>the Palms of the <lb/>Hands, &amp;
              Soles <lb/>of the Feet; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Dropſy; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Epilepſy; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Melancholy; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Madneſs; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Palſy; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Apoplexy; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item><hi rend="sc">Death.</hi>
            </item>
          </list>
          <lb/>PUNISHMENTS. <list>
            <lb/>
            <item>Debt; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Black-Eyes; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Rags; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Hunger; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Hoſpital; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Poor-houſe; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Jail; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Whipping; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>The Hulks; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Botany Bay; </item>
            <lb/>
            <item><hi rend="sc">Gallows.</hi>
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
