<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Garnett: A Lecture on the Preservation of Health.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Thomas Garnett</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">A lecture on the preservation of health.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T37696</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T37696"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Liverpool</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Liverpool: printed by J. M'creery, and sold by Cadell and Davies, London,
                  1797.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1797</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="72"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107318694</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Health guide"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="1"/>
      <pb n="5"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>A LECTURE, &amp;c. </head>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>A ſhort horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(1.75)">T</hi>HE greateſt bleſſing we enjoy is health, <lb/>without it,
        wealth, honors, and every <lb/>other conſideration, would be inſipid, and <lb/>even irkſome;
        the preſervation of this <lb/>ſtate therefore, naturally concerns us all. <lb/>In this
        lecture, I ſhall not attempt to teach <lb/>you to become your own phyſicians, for <lb/>when
        the barriers of health are once bro- <lb/>ken down, and diſeaſe has eſtabliſhed <lb/>itſelf,
        it requires the deepeſt attention, <lb/>and an accurate acquaintance with the <lb/>extenſive
        ſcience of medicine, to combat <lb/>it; to attain this knowledge demands <lb/>the labour of
        years. But, a majority of <pb n="6"/>
        <lb/>the diſeafes to which we are ſubject, are <lb/>the effects of our own ignorance or im-
        <lb/>prudence, and it is often very eaſy to <lb/>prevent them; mere precepts however,
        <lb/>have ſeldom much effect, unleſs the rea- <lb/>ſoning upon them be rendered evident;
        <lb/>on this account, I ſhall firſt endeavour, in <lb/>as plain and eaſy a manner as
        poſſible, <lb/>to explain to you the laws by which life <lb/>is governed; and when we ſee in
        what <lb/>health conſiſts, we ſhall be better enabled <lb/>to take ſuch methods as may
        preſerve it. <lb/>Health is the eaſy and pleaſant exerciſe <lb/>of all the functions of the
        body and mind; <lb/>and diſeaſe conſiſts in the uneaſy and <lb/>diſproportioned exerciſe of
        all, or ſome <lb/>of the functions. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>When dead matter acts upon dead <lb/>matter, the only effects we perceive are
        <lb/>mechanical, or chemical; for though <lb/>there may appear to be other kinds of at-
        <lb/>traction, or repulſion, ſuch as electric and <lb/>magnetic, yet theſe come under the
        <lb/>head of mechanical attraction, as pro- <pb n="7"/>
        <lb/>ducing motion; we may therefore lay <lb/>it down as a law, that when dead, or
        <lb/>inanimate bodies act upon each other, no <lb/>other than mechanical, or chemical ef-
        <lb/>fects are produced; that is, either mo- <lb/>tion, or the decompoſition, and new
        <lb/>combination of their parts. If one ball <lb/>ſtrike another, it communicates to it a
        <lb/>certain quantity of motion, this is called <lb/>mechanical action; and if a quantity of
        <lb/>ſalt, or ſugar, be put into water, the par- <lb/>ticles of the ſalt or ſugar will
        ſeparate <lb/>from each other, and join themſelves to <lb/>the particles of the water; the
        ſalt and <lb/>water in theſe inſtances, are ſaid to act <lb/>on each other chemically; and
        in all <lb/>caſes whatever, in which inanimate, or <lb/>dead bodies act on each other, the
        effects <lb/>produced are, motion, or chemical at- <lb/>traction. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>But, when dead matter acts on thoſe <lb/>bodies which we call living, the effects
        <lb/>are much different; let us take for ex- <lb/>ample a very ſimple inſtance.—Snakes, <pb
          n="8"/>
        <lb/>at leaſt ſome ſpecies of them, paſs the <lb/>winter in a torpid ſtate, which has all
        <lb/>the appearance of death; now heat, if <lb/>applied to dead matter, will only pro-
        <lb/>duce motion, or chemical combination; <lb/>but if it be applied to the ſnake, let us
        <lb/>ſee what will be the conſequence; the <lb/>reptile firſt begins to move, and opens
        <lb/>its eyes and mouth; when the heat has <lb/>been applied for ſome time, it crawls a-
        <lb/>bout in ſearch of food, and performs all <lb/>the functions of life. Here then, dead
        <lb/>matter, when applied to a living body, <lb/>produces living functions; for if the heat
        <lb/>had not been applied, the ſnake would <lb/>have continued ſenſeleſs, and apparent-
        <lb/>ly lifeleſs. In more perfect animals, the <lb/>effects produced by the action of dead
        <lb/>matter on them, are more numerous, <lb/>and are different in different living ſyſ-
        <lb/>tems, but are in general the following— <lb/>ſenſe and motion in almoſt all animals,
        <lb/>and in many the power of thinking, and <lb/>other affections of the mind. The pow-
        <lb/>ers, or dead matters, which are applied, <pb n="9"/>
        <lb/>and which produce theſe functions, are <lb/>chiefly, heat, food, and air. The proof
        <lb/>that theſe powers do produce the living <lb/>functions, is in my opinion a very con-
        <lb/>vincing one, namely, that when their <lb/>actions are ſuſpended, the living func-
        <lb/>tions ceaſe; take away, for inſtance, <lb/>heat, air, and food from animals, and
        <lb/>they ſoon become dead matter; and it is <lb/>not neceſſary that an animal ſhould be
        <lb/>deprived of all thoſe to put a ſtop to the <lb/>living functions; if any one of them be
        <lb/>taken away, the body ſooner or later <lb/>becomes dead matter: it is found by ex-
        <lb/>perience, that if a man be deprived of <lb/>air, he dies in about three or four mi-
        <lb/>nutes; for inſtance, if he be immerſed <lb/>under water, if he be deprived of heat,
        <lb/>or in other words, expoſed to a very ſe- <lb/>vere degree of cold, he likewife ſoon
        <lb/>dies; or if he be deprived of food, his <lb/>death is equally certain, though more
        <lb/>ſlow. It is ſufficiently evident then, <lb/>that the living functions are owing to
        <lb/>the action of theſe external powers upon <pb n="10"/>
        <lb/>the body. What I have here ſaid, is <lb/>not confined to animals, but the living
        <lb/>functions of vegetables are likewiſe cauſ- <lb/>ed by the action of dead matter upon
        <lb/>them. The dead matters, which by their <lb/>action produce theſe functions, are prin-
        <lb/>cipally heat, moiſture, light, and air. It <lb/>clearly follows therefore, from what I
        <lb/>have ſaid, that living bodies muſt have <lb/>ſome property different from dead matter,
        <lb/>which renders them capable of being <lb/>acted upon by theſe external powers, ſo
        <lb/>as to produce the living functions; for if <lb/>they had not, the only effects which
        theſe <lb/>powers could produce, would be mecha- <lb/>nical, or chemical. Though we know
        <lb/>not exactly in what this property con- <lb/>ſiſts, or in what manner it is acted on,
        <lb/>yet we ſee, that when bodies are poſſeſſed <lb/>of it, they become capable of being
        acted <lb/>upon by external powers, and thus the <lb/>living functions are produced; we
        ſhall <lb/>therefore call this property <hi rend="italic">excitability</hi>, <lb/>and in
        uſing this term it is neceſſary to <lb/>mention, that I mean only to expreſs a <pb n="11"/>
        <lb/>fact, without the leaſt intention of point- <lb/>ing out the nature of that property
        <lb/>which diſtinguiſhes living from dead <lb/>matter, and in this we have the example
        <lb/>of the great Newton, who called the <lb/>property which cauſes bodies in certain
        <lb/>ſituations to approach each other, <hi rend="italic">gravi- <lb/>tation</hi>, without
        in the leaſt hinting at <lb/>its nature; yet, though he knew not <lb/>what gravitation was,
        he inveſtigated <lb/>the laws by which bodies were acted on <lb/>by it; in the ſame manner,
        though we <lb/>are ignorant of excitability, or the nature <lb/>of that property which
        diſtinguiſhes liv- <lb/>ing from dead matter, we can inveſti- <lb/>gate the laws by which
        dead matter acts <lb/>on living bodies through this medium. <lb/>We know not what magnetic
        attraction <lb/>is, and yet we can inveſtigate its laws; <lb/>the ſame holds good with
        regard to elec- <lb/>tricity; if we ever ſhould attain a know- <lb/>ledge of the nature of
        this property, it <lb/>would make no alteration in the laws <lb/>which we had before
        diſcovered. </p>
      <pb n="12"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I ſhall now proceed to the inveſtiga- <lb/>tion of the laws by which the excitability
        <lb/>is acted on; but I muſt firſt define ſome <lb/>terms which it will be neceſſary to uſe,
        <lb/>to avoid circumlocution, and at the ſame <lb/>time to give us more diſtinct ideas on
        the <lb/>ſubject. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>When the excitability is in ſuch a ſtate <lb/>as to be very ſuſceptible of the action
        of <lb/>external powers, I ſhall call it <hi rend="italic">abun- <lb/>dant</hi>, or <hi
          rend="italic">accumulated</hi>; but when it is <lb/>found not very capable of receiving
        their <lb/>action, I ſhall ſay, it is <hi rend="italic">deficient</hi>, or <hi rend="italic"
          >ex- <lb/>hauſted</hi>. I would not wiſh however, to <lb/>have it thought, that by theſe
        terms I <lb/>mean in the leaſt to hint at the <hi rend="italic">nature</hi> of
        <lb/>excitability, nor that it is <hi rend="italic">really</hi> one <lb/>while increaſed,
        and at another dimi- <lb/>niſhed in quantity, for the abſtract queſ- <lb/>tion is in no
        ſhape conſidered; we know <lb/>not whether the excitability, or the vi- <lb/>tal principle,
        depends on a particular ar- <lb/>rangement of matter, or from whatever <lb/>cauſe it may
        originate; by the terms <pb n="13"/>
        <lb/>here uſed, I mean only to ſay, that the <lb/>excitability is eaſily acted on when I
        call <lb/>it abundant, or accumulated; at other <lb/>times the living body is with more
        diffi- <lb/>culty excited, and then I ſay, the vital <lb/>principle is deficient, or
        exhauſted. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The laws by which external powers <lb/>act on living bodies, will, on a careful
        <lb/>examination, be found to be the follow- <lb/>ing— </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Firſt, when the powerful action of <lb/>the exciting powers ceaſes for ſome time,
        <lb/>the excitability accumulates, or becomes <lb/>more capable of receiving their action,
        <lb/>and is more powerfully affected by them. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>If we examine ſeparately the differ- <lb/>ent exciting powers, which act on the
        <lb/>body, we ſhall find abundant confirma- <lb/>tion of this law. Let us firſt conſider
        <lb/>Light; if a perſon be kept in darkneſs <lb/>for ſome time, and be then brought into
        <lb/>a room in which there is only an ordi- <pb n="14"/>
        <lb/>nary degree of light, it will be almoſt <lb/>too oppreſſive for him, and appear exceſ-
        <lb/>ſively bright; and if he have been kept for <lb/>a conſiderable time in a very dark
        place, <lb/>the ſenſation will be very painful. In <lb/>this caſe, while the retina, or
        optic <lb/>nerve, was deprived of light, its excita- <lb/>bility accumulated, or became more
        ea- <lb/>ſily affected by light; for if a perſon <lb/>goes out of one room, into another
        <lb/>which has an equal degree of light, he <lb/>will feel no effect. You may convince
        <lb/>yourſelves of this law by a very ſimple <lb/>experiment—ſhut your eyes, and cover
        <lb/>them for a minute or two with your <lb/>hand, and endeavour not to think of the
        <lb/>light, or of what you are doing; then <lb/>open them, and the day-light will for a
        <lb/>ſhort time appear brighter. If you look <lb/>attentively at a window, for about two
        <lb/>minutes, and then caſt your eyes upon <lb/>a ſheet of white paper, the ſhape of the
        <lb/>window-frames will be perfectly viſible <lb/>upon the paper; thoſe parts which ex-
        <lb/>preſs the wood-work, appearing brighter <pb n="15"/>
        <lb/>than the other parts. The parts of the <lb/>optic nerve on which the image of the
        <lb/>frame falls, are covered by the wood- <lb/>work from the action of the light; <lb/>the
        excitability of theſe parts of the <lb/>nerve will therefore accumulate, and <lb/>the parts
        of the paper which fall upon <lb/>them, muſt of courſe appear brighter. <lb/>If a perſon be
        brought out of a dark <lb/>room where he has been confined, into <lb/>a field covered with,
        ſnow, when the <lb/>ſun ſhines, it has been known to affect <lb/>him ſo much, as to deprive
        him of ſight <lb/>altogether. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Let us next conſider what happens <lb/>with reſpect to heat; if heat be for ſome
        <lb/>time abſtracted, the excitability accu- <lb/>mulates, or in other words, if the body
        <lb/>be for ſome time expoſed to cold, it is <lb/>more liable to be affected by heat, after-
        <lb/>wards applied; of this alſo you may be <lb/>convinced by an eaſy experiment—put
        <lb/>one of your hands into cold water, and <lb/>then put both into water which is conſi-
          <pb n="16"/>
        <lb/>derably warm; the hand which has <lb/>been in cold water, will feel much <lb/>warmer
        than the other. If you handle <lb/>ſome ſnow with one hand, while you <lb/>keep the other in
        your boſom, that it <lb/>may be of the ſame heat as the body, <lb/>then bring both within
        the ſame diſ- <lb/>tance of the fire, the heat will affect <lb/>the cold hand infinitely
        more than the <lb/>warm one. This is a circumſtance of <lb/>the utmoſt importance, and ought
        al- <lb/>ways to be carefully attended to. When <lb/>a perſon has been expoſed to a ſevere
        de- <lb/>gree of cold for ſome time, he ought to <lb/>be cautious how he comes near a fire,
        <lb/>for his excitability will be ſo much <lb/>accumulated, that the heat will act
        <lb/>violently; often producing a great de- <lb/>gree of inflammation, and even ſome-
        <lb/>times mortification. We may by the <lb/>way obſerve, that this is a very com- <lb/>mon
        cauſe of chilblains, and other in- <lb/>flammations. When the hands, or any <lb/>other parts
        of the body have been ex- <lb/>poſed to violent cold, they ought firſt <pb n="17"/>
        <lb/>to be put into cold water, or even rubbed <lb/>with the ſnow, and expoſed to warmth
        <lb/>in the gentleſt manner poſſible. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Exactly the ſame takes place with <lb/>reſpect to food, if a perſon have for ſome
        <lb/>time been deprived of food, or have taken <lb/>it in ſmall quantity, whether it be meat
        <lb/>or drink; or if he have taken it of a leſs <lb/>ſtimulating quality, he will find, that
        <lb/>when he returns to his ordinary mode of <lb/>living, it will have more effect upon him
        <lb/>than before he lived abſtemiouſly. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Perſons who have been ſhut up in a <lb/>coal-work from the falling in of the pit,
        <lb/>and have had nothing to eat for two or <lb/>three days, have been as much intoxi-
        <lb/>cated by a baſon of broth, as a perſon in <lb/>common circumſtances with two or three
        <lb/>bottles of wine; and we all know that <lb/>ſpirituous, or vinous liquors affect the
        <lb/>head more in the morning, than after <lb/>dinner. </p>
      <pb n="18"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This <choice>
          <corr>circumſtance</corr>
          <sic>circnmſtance</sic>
        </choice> was particularly <lb/>evident among the poor ſailors who were <lb/>in the boat
        with Captain Bligh after <lb/>the mutiny. The Captain was ſent by <lb/>government to convey
        ſome plants of <lb/>the bread-fruit tree from Otaheite, to the <lb/>Weſt Indies; ſoon after
        he left Otaheite, <lb/>the crew mutinied, and put the captain <lb/>and moſt of the officers,
        with ſome of <lb/>the men, on board the ſhip's boat, with <lb/>a very ſhort allowance of
        proviſions, and <lb/>particularly of liquors, for they had <lb/>only ſix quarts of rum, and
        ſix bottles <lb/>of wine, for nineteen people, who were <lb/>driven by ſtorms about the
        ſouth-ſea, ex- <lb/>poſed to wet and cold all the time, for <lb/>nearly a month; each man
        was allowed <lb/>only a tea-ſpoon full of rum a day, but <lb/>this tea-ſpoon full refreſhed
        the poor <lb/>men, benumbed as they were with <lb/>cold, and faint with hunger, more than
        <lb/>twenty times the quantity would have <lb/>done thoſe who were warm, and well <lb/>fed;
        and had it not been for the ſpirit <lb/>having ſuch power to act upon men in <pb n="19"/>
        <lb/>their condition, they never could have <lb/>outlived the hardſhips they experienced.
        <lb/>All theſe facts, and many others which <lb/>might be brought, eſtabliſh beyond a
        <lb/>doubt the truth of the law I have men- <lb/>tioned, namely, that when the powerful
        <lb/>action of the exciting powers ceaſes for <lb/>ſome time, the excitability accumulates,
        <lb/>or becomes more capable of receiving <lb/>their actions. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The ſecond law is, that when the ex- <lb/>citing powers have acted with violence,
        <lb/>or for a conſiderable time, the excitabi- <lb/>lity becomes exhauſted, or leſs fit to
        be <lb/>acted on, and this we ſhall be able to <lb/>prove by a ſimilar induction. Let us
        <lb/>take the effects of light upon the eye; <lb/>when it has acted violently for ſome time
        <lb/>upon the optic nerve, it diminiſhes the <lb/>excitability of that nerve, and renders
        <lb/>it incapable of being affected by a quan- <lb/>tity of light that would at other times
        <lb/>affect it. When you have been walk- <lb/>ing out in the ſnow, if you come into <pb
          n="20"/>
        <lb/>your room, you will be ſcarcely able to ſee <lb/>any thing for ſome minutes. Look
        <lb/>ſtedfaſtly at a candle for a minute or <lb/>two, and you will with difficulty diſcern
        <lb/>the letters of a book, which you were <lb/>before reading diſtinctly; and if you hap-
        <lb/>pen to caſt your eyes upon the ſun, you <lb/>will not ſee any thing diſtinctly for ſome
        <lb/>time afterwards. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Let us next conſider the matter of <lb/>heat: ſuppoſe water to be heated luke-
        <lb/>warm, if you put one hand into it, it <lb/>will feel warm; if you now put the
        <lb/>other hand into water, heated for inſtance <lb/>to 120° or 130°, and keep it there ſome
        <lb/>time, we will ſay, two minutes, if <lb/>then you take it out, and put it into the
        <lb/>luke-warm water, that water will feel <lb/>cold, though ſtill it will ſeem warm <lb/>to
        the other hand; for, the hand which <lb/>had been in the heated water, has had its
        <lb/>excitability exhauſted by the application <lb/>of heat. Before you go into a warm
        <lb/>bath, the temperature of the air may <pb n="21"/>
        <lb/>ſeem warm and agreeable to you, but <lb/>after you have remained for ſome time <lb/>in
        a bath that is rather hot, when you <lb/>come out, you feel the air uncommonly <lb/>cool and
        chilling. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Let us now examine the effects of <lb/>ſubſtances taken into the ſtomach; and <lb/>as
        the effects of ſpirituous, and vinous li- <lb/>quors, are a little more remarkable than
        <lb/>food, we ſhall make our obſervations <lb/>upon them. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>A perſon who is unaccuſtomed to <lb/>drink theſe liquors, will be intoxicated <lb/>by a
        quantity that will produce no effect <lb/>upon one who has been ſome time ac- <lb/>cuſtomed
        to take them; and when a <lb/>perſon has uſed himſelf to theſe ſtimu- <lb/>lants for ſome
        time, the ordinary pow- <lb/>ers which in common ſupport life, will <lb/>not have their
        proper effects upon him, <lb/>becauſe his excitability has been in ſome <lb/>meaſure
        exhauſted by the ſtimulants. </p>
      <pb n="22"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſame holds good with reſpect to <lb/>tobacco and opium; a perſon accuſtom- <lb/>ed
        to take opium will not be affected by <lb/>a quantity that would completely intoxi-
        <lb/>cate one not uſed to it; becauſe the <lb/>excitability has been ſo far exhauſted
        <lb/>by the uſe of that drug, that it cannot <lb/>be acted on by a ſmall quantity. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Theſe facts, with innumerable others, <lb/>which will eaſily ſuggeſt themſelves to
        <lb/>you, prove the truth of our ſecond pro- <lb/>poſition, namely, that when the exciting
        <lb/>powers have acted violently, or for a <lb/>conſiderable time, the excitability is ex-
        <lb/>hauſted, or leſs fit to be acted on. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>This exhauſtion of the excitability, <lb/>may, however, be either finite, or tem-
        <lb/>porary; we ſee animals, while the ex- <lb/>citing powers continue to act, at firſt
        <lb/>appear in their greateſt vigour, then <lb/>gradually decay, and at laſt come into
        <lb/>that ſtate, in which, from the long <lb/>continued action of the exciting powers, <pb
          n="23"/>
        <lb/>the excitability is entirely exhauſted, and <lb/>death takes place. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>We likewiſe ſee plants in the ſpring, <lb/>while the exciting powers have acted on
        <lb/>them, moderately, and for a ſhort time, <lb/>arrayed in their verdant robes, and
        adorned <lb/>with flowers of <q rend="quotes">many mingling hues; </q>
        <lb/>but, as the exciting powers which ſupport <lb/>the life of the plant, continue to be
        ap- <lb/>plied, and ſome of them, for inſtance heat, <lb/>as the ſummer advances become
        increaſ- <lb/>ed, they firſt looſe their verdure, then <lb/>grow brown, and at the end of
        ſummer <lb/>ceaſe to live; becauſe their excitability <lb/>is exhauſted by the long
        continued action <lb/>of the exciting powers; and this does <lb/>not happen merely in
        conſequence of the <lb/>heat of ſummer decreaſing, for they <lb/>grow brown and die, even in
        a greater <lb/>degree of heat than that which in ſpring <lb/>made them grow luxuriantly. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Theſe are examples of the finite, or <lb/>irreparable exhauſtion of the excitability;
          <pb n="24"/>
        <lb/>but we find alſo, that it may be ex- <lb/>hauſted for a time, and accumulated a-
        <lb/>gain. Though the eye has been ſo daz- <lb/>zled by the ſplendour of light, that it
        <lb/>cannot ſee an object moderately illumi- <lb/>nated, yet, if it be ſhut for ſome time,
        <lb/>the excitability of the optic nerve accu- <lb/>mulates again, and we are again capable
        <lb/>of ſeeing with an ordinary light. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>We find, that we are not always equal- <lb/>ly capable of performing the functions
        <lb/>of life. When we have been engaged in <lb/>any exertion, either mental or corporeal,
        <lb/>for ſome hours only, we find ourſelves <lb/>fatigued, and unfit to purſue our labours
        <lb/>much longer; if in this ſtate, ſeveral <lb/>of the exciting powers, particularly
        <lb/>light and noiſe, be withdrawn; and if <lb/>we are laid in a poſture which does not
        <lb/>require much muſcular exertion, we <lb/>ſoon fall into that ſtate which nature
        <lb/>intended for the accumulation of the ex- <lb/>citability, and which we call ſleep. In
        <lb/>this ſtate, many of the exciting powers <pb n="25"/>
        <lb/>cannot act upon us, unleſs applied with <lb/>ſome violence, for we are inſenſible to
        <lb/>their moderate action. A moderate <lb/>light, or a moderate noiſe, does not af-
        <lb/>fect us, and the power of thinking, <lb/>which exhauſts the excitability very
        <lb/>much, is in a great meaſure ſuſpended. <lb/>When the action of theſe powers has
        <lb/>been ſuſpended for ſix or eight hours, <lb/>the excitability is again capable of being
        <lb/>acted on, and we riſe freſh, and vigor- <lb/>ous, and fit to engage in our occupa-
        <lb/>tions. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Sleep then, is the method which na- <lb/>ture has provided to repair the exhauſ-
        <lb/>ted conſtitution, and reſtore the vital <lb/>energy; without its refreſhing aid, our
        <lb/>worn out habits would ſcarcely be able <lb/>to drag on a few days, or at moſt a few
        <lb/>weeks, before the vital ſpring was quite <lb/>run down; how properly therefore has
        <lb/>the great poet of nature called ſleep the <lb/>chief nouriſher in life's feaſt.— </p>
      <pb n="26"/>
      <p rend="size(0.5)">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple quotes">Sleep, that knits up the ravell'd ſleeve of care, <lb/>the death of
          each day's life, ſore labour's bath, <lb/>balm of hurt minds, great Nature's ſecond
          courſe, <lb/>chief nouriſher in life's feaſt. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>From the internal ſenſations often ex- <lb/>cited, it is natural to conclude that the
        <lb/>nerves of ſenſe are not torpid during <lb/>ſleep; but that they are only precluded
        <lb/>from the perception of external objects, <lb/>by the external organs being rendered
        <lb/>unfit to tranſmit to them the impulſes <lb/>of bodies, during the ſuſpenſion of the
        <lb/>power of volition; thus, the eye-lids <lb/>are cloſed in ſleep, to prevent the im-
        <lb/>pulſe of the light from acting on the op- <lb/>tic nerve; and it is very probable that
        <lb/>the drum of the ear is not ſtretched; <lb/>it is likewiſe probable that ſomething
        <lb/>ſimilar happens to the external appara- <lb/>tus of all our organs of ſenſe, which
        <lb/>may make them unfit for their office of <lb/>perception during ſleep. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The more violently the exciting pow- <lb/>ers have acted, the ſooner is ſleep brought
          <pb n="27"/>
        <lb/>on; becauſe the excitability is ſooner <lb/>exhauſted, and therefore, ſooner re-
        <lb/>quires the means of renewing it; and <lb/>on the contrary, the more weakly the
        <lb/>exciting powers have acted, the leſs is a <lb/>perſon inclined to ſleep. Inſtances of
        <lb/>the firſt are, exceſs of exerciſe, ſtrong <lb/>liquors, or ſtudy; and of the latter, an
        <lb/>under proportion of theſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>A perſon who has been daily accuſ- <lb/>tomed to much exerciſe, whether men- <lb/>tal
        or corporeal, if he omit it, will <lb/>find little or no inclination to ſleep; he <lb/>may
        however be made to ſleep by <lb/>taking a little diffuſible ſtimulus; for <lb/>inſtance, a
        little warm punch, or opium; <lb/>which act entirely by exhauſting the <lb/>excitability to
        that degree which is com- <lb/>patible with ſleep; and when the ſtimu- <lb/>lant effect of
        theſe ſubſtances is over, <lb/>the perſon ſoon falls into that ſtate. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>But though the excitability may have <pb n="28"/>
        <lb/>been ſufficiently exhauſted, and the ac- <lb/>tion of the external powers conſiderably
        <lb/>moderated, yet there are ſome things <lb/>within ourſelves, which ſtimulate vio-
        <lb/>lently, and prevent ſleep, ſuch as pain, <lb/>thirſt, and ſtrong paſſions and emo-
        <lb/>tions of the mind. Theſe all tend to <lb/>drive away ſleep, but it may be induced,
        <lb/>by withdrawing the mind from theſe <lb/>impreſſions; particularly from uneaſy
        <lb/>emotions, and employing it on ſomething <lb/>which makes a leſs impreſſion; ſleep,
        <lb/>in ſuch caſes, is frequently brought on <lb/>by liſtening to the humming of bees, or
        <lb/>the murmuring of a rivulet; by em- <lb/>ploying the mind on ſubjects which do <lb/>not
        require much exertion, nor produce <lb/>too much commotion; ſuch as count- <lb/>ing to a
        thouſand, or counting drops of <lb/>water which fall ſlowly. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It ſometimes happens, as has been <lb/>well obſerved by Dr. Franklin, that an
        <lb/>uneaſy heat of the ſkin, from a want of <lb/>perſpiration, occaſioned by the heat of
          <pb n="29"/>
        <lb/>the bed-cloaths, will prevent ſleep; in <lb/>this caſe, he recommends a method,
        <lb/>which I believe will often ſucceed— <lb/>namely, to get up and walk about the <lb/>room
        'till you are conſiderably cooled; <lb/>when you get into bed again, the heat <lb/>of the
        ſkin will be diminiſhed, and perſ- <lb/>piration become more free, and you <lb/>will
        probably ſleep in a very few mi- <lb/>nutes. <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* May not the heat, and want of perſpiration, de- <lb/>pend on an exhauſted
            irritability of the ſubcutaneous <lb/>veſſels, which will be accumulated by the method
            here <lb/>recommended? </p>
        </note>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>By induction we have diſcovered two <lb/>of the principal laws by which living
        <lb/>bodies are governed; the firſt is, that <lb/>when the ordinary powers which ſup-
        <lb/>port life have been ſuſpended, or their <lb/>action leſſened for a time, the
        excitability, <lb/>or vital principle accumulates, or becomes <lb/>more fit to receive their
        actions; and <lb/>ſecondly, when theſe powers have been <pb n="30"/>
        <lb/>acted upon violently, or for a conſidera- <lb/>ble time, the excitability is exhauſted,
        <lb/>or becomes leſs fit to receive their ac- <lb/>tions. There are therefore three ſtates
        <lb/>in which living bodies exiſt.— </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Firſt, a ſtate of accumulated excita- <lb/>bility. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Second, a ſtate of exhauſted excitabi- <lb/>lity. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Third, when it is in ſuch a ſtate as to <lb/>produce the ſtrongeſt and moſt healthy
        <lb/>actions, when acted upon by the exter- <lb/>nal powers. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>From what I have ſaid, it muſt ap- <lb/>pear, that life is a forced ſtate, depend-
        <lb/>ing on the action of external powers <lb/>upon the excitability; and that, by their
        <lb/>continued action, if they are properly <lb/>regulated, the excitability will be gra-
        <lb/>dually and inſenſibly exhauſted; and <lb/>life will be reſigned into the hands of <pb
          n="31"/>
        <lb/>him who gave it, without a ſtruggle, <lb/>and without a groan. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>We ſee then, that that nature operates <lb/>in ſupporting the living part of the crea-
        <lb/>tion, by laws as ſimple and beautiful as <lb/>thoſe by which the inanimate world is
        <lb/>governed. In the latter we ſee the or- <lb/>der and harmony which is obſerved by
        <lb/>the planets, and their ſatellities, in their <lb/>revolution round the great ſource of
        heat <lb/>and light. </p>
      <p rend="size(0.5) indent space">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple quotes">All combin'd <lb/>and ruled unerring, by that ſingle power <lb/>which
          draws the ſtone projected, to the ground. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>In the animated part of the creation, <lb/>we obſerve thoſe beautiful phenomena,
        <lb/>which are exhibited by an almoſt infinite <lb/>variety of individuals, all depending
        up- <lb/>on one ſimple law, the action of the <lb/>exciting powers on the excitability. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>I cannot expreſs my admiration of the <pb n="32"/>
        <lb/>wiſdom of the creator better than in the <lb/>words of Thompſon. </p>
      <p rend="size(0.5) space">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple quotes">O unprofuſe magnificence divine! <lb/>O wiſdom truly perfect ! thus
          to call <lb/>from a few cauſes, ſuch a ſcheme of things; <lb/>effects ſo various,
          beautiful, and great. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Life then, or thoſe functions which <lb/>we call living, are the effects of certain
        <lb/>exciting powers, acting on the excita- <lb/>bility, or property diſtinguiſhing living
        <lb/>from dead matter. When thoſe effects, <lb/>namely, the functions, flow eaſily, plea-
        <lb/>ſantly, and compleatly, from the action <lb/>of the exciting powers, they indicate
        <lb/>that ſtate which we call Health. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>I have detained you a long time on <lb/>this ſubject, but it is of importance to
        <lb/>make you acquainted with theſe laws; <lb/>for it is from a knowledge of them, <lb/>that
        the rules for preſerving health muſt <lb/>be deduced; and having rendered them, <lb/>as I
        hope, intelligible to you, I ſhall pro- <lb/>ceed to point out ſuch neceſſary cautions
        <lb/>for our conduct, as are eaſily deduced <pb n="33"/>
        <lb/>from them; and which, experience con- <lb/>firms; and I ſhall follow an arrange-
        <lb/>ment in the conſideration of the ſubject, <lb/>which naturally preſents itſelf to us.
        <lb/>The chief exciting powers which act <lb/>upon us are, air and food; theſe I ſhall
        <lb/>reſpectively conſider, and afterwards <lb/>make a few remarks on exerciſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The air is the main-ſpring in the a- <lb/>nimal machine; the ſource of heat and
        <lb/>activity, without which our blood would <lb/>ſoon become a black and ſtagnant maſs,
        <lb/>and life would ſoon ſtop. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It is now known, that only a part of <lb/>atmoſpheric air, is neceſſary for reſpira-
        <lb/>tion: the atmoſphere near the ſurface of <lb/>the earth, conſiſts of two kinds of air;
        <lb/>one, which is highly proper for reſpira- <lb/>tion, and combuſtion, and in which, an
        <lb/>animal immerſed, will live much longer <lb/>than in the ſame quantity of common
        <lb/>air; and one, which is perfectly impro- <pb n="34"/>
        <lb/>per for ſupporting reſpiration, or com- <lb/>buſtion for an inſtant. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The firſt of theſe airs, has been called <lb/>vital air, from its property of
        ſupporting <lb/>life, and conſtitutes about one fourth of <lb/>the atmoſphere. <note
          rend="size(0.5)" place="bottom" n="*">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Oxygen gas, according to the new Nomenclature. </p>
        </note> The other, from its <lb/>property of deſtroying life, is called <lb/>azote, and
        forms of courſe the remain- <lb/>ing three fourths of the atmoſphere. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Theſe two airs may be ſeparated from <lb/>each other by various methods. If a
        <lb/>candle be incloſed in a given quantity of <lb/>atmoſpheric air, it will burn only for a
        <lb/>certain time, and then be extinguiſhed; <lb/>and from the riſing up of the water in
        <lb/>the veſſel in which it is incloſed, it is <lb/>evident that a quantity of air has been
        <lb/>abſorbed. What has been abſorbed is <lb/>the vital air, and what remains, the a-
        <lb/>zote; which is incapable of ſupporting <pb n="35"/>
        <lb/>flame. If an animal be immerſed in a <lb/>given quantity of common air, it will
        <lb/>only live a certain time; at the end of <lb/>this time, the air will be found <choice>
          <corr>diminiſh</corr>
          <sic>diminſh</sic>
        </choice>- <lb/>ed, about one fourth being extracted <lb/>from it, and the remainder will
        neither <lb/>ſupport flame nor animal life; this expe- <lb/>riment might eaſily be made, but
        it <lb/>ſeems a piece of unneceſſary cruelty. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>By ſimilar experiments to thoſe I have <lb/>mentioned, we get the azote pure; here
        <lb/>is ſome, in which a candle has burnt <lb/>out, and in which nothing but azote, <lb/>or
        the impure part of the atmoſphere is <lb/>left <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* The fixed air, or carbonic acid gas, formed dur- <lb/>ing the combuſtion, having
            been ſeparated by agitation <lb/>in contact with lime water. </p>
        </note>. I ſhall plunge a lighted match <lb/>into it, and you ſee it is inſtantly extin-
        <lb/>guiſhed. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Many metals, and particularly man- <lb/>ganeſe, when expoſed to the atmoſ- <pb n="36"/>
        <lb/>phere, attract the vital air from it, <lb/>without touching the azote; and it may
        <lb/>be procured from theſe metals by the <lb/>application of heat, in very great purity.
        <lb/>Here is a bottle of that kind of air, <lb/>which I have expelled by heat from
        <lb/>manganeſe; I ſhall plunge a taper into it, <lb/>and you will perceive that it burns
        with <lb/>great brilliancy. An animal ſhut up in <lb/>it, would live about four times as
        long <lb/>as if ſhut up in an equal quantity of at- <lb/>moſpheric air. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>If I take three parts of azote, and one <lb/>of vital air, I ſhall form a compound
        <lb/>which is ſimilar to the atmoſphere, and <lb/>which is the mixture beft ſuited to ſup-
        <lb/>port the health of the body; for if there <lb/>were a much greater proportion of vital
        <lb/>air, it would act too powerfully upon <lb/>the ſyſtem, and bring on inflammatory
        <lb/>diſeaſes; it would likewiſe by its ſtimu- <lb/>lus exhauſt the excitability, and bring
        <lb/>us ſooner to death; and in the ſame <lb/>manner that a candle burns brighter in <pb
          n="37"/>
        <lb/>vital air, and would therefore be ſooner <lb/>extinguiſhed, ſo would the flame of life
        <lb/>be ſooner burnt out. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>On the contrary, if the atmoſphere <lb/>contained a much leſs proportion of vital
        <lb/>air, it would not ſtimulate the body ſuf- <lb/>ficiently; the excitability would mor-
        <lb/>bidly accumulate, and diſeaſes of debility <lb/>would occur. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Combuſtion, putrefaction, and the <lb/>breathing of animals, are proceſſes which
        <lb/>are continually diminiſhing the quantity <lb/>of vital air contained in the atmoſphere;
        <lb/>and if the all-wiſe author of nature had <lb/>not provided for its continual re-produc-
        <lb/>tion, the atmoſphere would in all proba- <lb/>bility have long ſince become too impure
        <lb/>to ſupport life; but this is guarded a- <lb/>gainſt in a moſt beautiful manner. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Water is not a ſimple element, as has <lb/>been ſuppoſed, but is compoſed of vital
        <lb/>air, and a particular kind of air which <pb n="38"/>
        <lb/>is called inflammable; the ſame that <lb/>is uſed to fill balloons. It has been
        <lb/>found by experiment, than one hundred <lb/>pounds of water, are compoſed of eighty-
        <lb/>five pounds of vital-air, and fifteen of <lb/>inflammable air. <note n="*"
          place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Strictly ſpeaking, water is compoſed of the baſes <lb/>of theſe airs, the
            greateſt part of the caloric being <lb/>given out on their union. </p>
        </note>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Water may be decompounded by a <lb/>variety of means, and its component <lb/>parts
        ſeparated from each other. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Vegetables effect this decompoſition; <lb/>they abſorb water, and decompoſe it in
        <lb/>their glands; and taking the inflamma- <lb/>ble air for their nouriſhment, breathe
        <lb/>out the vital air in a ſtate of very great <lb/>purity; this may be aſcertained by a
        ve- <lb/>ry eaſy experiment. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>This vital air is received by animals <lb/>into their lungs, gives them their <pb
          n="39"/>
        <lb/>heat, and communicates a red colour to <lb/>their blood; when animals die for want
        <lb/>of vital air, their blood is always found <lb/>black. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>From what I have ſaid, it is evident, <lb/>that in large and populous towns, where
        <lb/>combuſtion and reſpiration are continu- <lb/>ally performed on a large ſcale, the air
        <lb/>muſt be much leſs pure than in the <lb/>country, where there are few of theſe
        <lb/>cauſes to contaminate the atmoſphere, <lb/>and where vegetables are continually
        <lb/>tending to render it more pure; and if <lb/>it was not for the winds which agitate
        <lb/>this element, and continually occaſion <lb/>its change of place; the air of large
        <lb/>towns would probably ſoon become unfit <lb/>for reſpiration. Winds bring us the
        <lb/>pure air of the country, and take away <lb/>that from which the vital air has been
        <lb/>in a great meaſure extracted; but ſtill, <lb/>from the immenſe quantity of fuel which
        <lb/>is daily burnt, and the number of people <pb n="40"/>
        <lb/>breathing in large towns, the air very <lb/>ſoon becomes impure. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>From the greater purity of the air in <lb/>the country, proceeds the roſy bloom
        <lb/>found in the rural cottage, which we in <lb/>vain look for in the ſtately palace, or
        the <lb/>ſplendid drawing room. Here then are <lb/>reaſons for preferring the country,
        <lb/>which no one will diſpute; and when- <lb/>ever it can be done, ſuch a ſituation
        <lb/>ought always to be choſen in preference <lb/>to a large town; this cannot be better
        <lb/>enforced than in the words of Dr. Arm- <lb/>ſtrong.— </p>
      <p rend="size(0.5) space">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple">Ye, who amid the feveriſh world would wear <lb/>a body free of pain, of
          cares a mind; <lb/>fly the rank city, ſhun its turbid air; <lb/>breathe not the chaos of
          eternal ſmoke, <lb/>and volatile corruption, from the dead, <lb/>the dying, ſick'ning, and
          the living world <lb/>exhaled, to ſully heaven's tranſparent dome <lb/>with dim mortality.
        </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent size(0.5) space">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple quotes">While yet you breathe, away; the rural wilds <lb/>invite; the
          mountains call you, and the vales; <lb/>the woods, the ſtreams, and each ambroſial breeze
          <lb/>that fans the ever undulating ſky. </q>
      </p>
      <pb n="41"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But there are many whoſe occupations <lb/>oblige them to reſide in large towns;
        <lb/>they, therefore ſhould make frequent <lb/>excurſions into the country, or to ſuch
        <lb/>ſituations as will enable them to enjoy, <lb/>and to breathe air of a little more
        purity. <lb/>I ſay <hi rend="italic">enjoy</hi>, for who that has been for <lb/>ſome time
        ſhut up in the town, without <lb/>breathing the pure air of the country, <lb/>does not feel
        his ſpirits revived the mo- <lb/>ment he emerges from the azote of the <lb/>town. Let not
        therefore, if poſſible, a <lb/>ſingle day paſs, without enjoying, if <lb/>but for an hour,
        the pure air of the coun- <lb/>try. Doing this, only for a ſhort time <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >every</hi> day, would be much more effec- <lb/>tual than ſpending whole days, or even
        <lb/>weeks in the country, and then return- <lb/>ing into the corrupt atmoſphere of the
        <lb/>town; for when you have for a long <lb/>time breathed an impure air, the excita-
        <lb/>bility becomes ſo morbidly accumulated, <lb/>from the want of the ſtimulus of pure
        <lb/>air, that the air of the country will have <lb/>too great an effect upon you; it will
        fre- <pb n="42"/>
        <lb/>quently, in the courſe of a day or two, <lb/>bring on an inflammatory fever, attend-
        <lb/>ed with ſtuffing of the noſe, hoarſeneſs, <lb/>a great degree of heat, and dryneſs of
        the <lb/>ſkin, with other ſymptoms of a violent <lb/>cold. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Large towns are the graves of the hu- <lb/>man ſpecies; they would periſh in a <lb/>few
        generations, if not conſtantly re- <lb/>cruited from the country. The confin- <lb/>ed,
        putrid air, which moſt of their inha- <lb/>bitants breathe, their want of natural
        <lb/>exerciſe, but above all their diſſipation, <lb/>ſhorten their lives, and ruin their
        conſti- <lb/>tutions. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Children particularly, require a pure <lb/>air, every circumſtance points out the
        <lb/>country as the proper place for the edu- <lb/>cation of children; the purity of the
        <lb/>air, the variety of ruſtic ſports, the <lb/>plainneſs of diet, the ſimplicity and in-
        <lb/>nocence of manners, all concur to re- <lb/>commend it. It is a melancholy fact, <pb
          n="43"/>
        <lb/>that above half the children born in Lon- <lb/>don, die before they are two years old. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>To ſhew how indiſpenſable freſh air <lb/>is to children, I ſhall mention one ex-
        <lb/>ample which ſets the fact in the cleareſt <lb/>light. In the lying-in hoſpital at Dub-
        <lb/>lin, 2944 infants, out of 7650, died in <lb/>the year 1782, within the firſt fortnight
        <lb/>after their birth, which is nearly every <lb/>third child; they almoſt all died in con-
        <lb/>vulſions ; many of them foamed at the <lb/>mouth, their thumbs were drawn into <lb/>the
        palms of their hands, their jaws <lb/>were locked, the face was ſwelled and <lb/>looked
        blue, as though they were choak- <lb/>ed. This laſt circumſtance led the phy- <lb/>ſicians
        to conclude that the rooms in the <lb/>hoſpital were too cloſe, and hence, that <lb/>the
        infants had not a ſufficient quantity <lb/>of good air to breathe; they therefore <lb/>ſet
        about ventilating them better, which <lb/>was done very compleatly. The con- <lb/>ſequence
        has been, that not one child <lb/>dies now where three uſed to die. </p>
      <pb n="44"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Fewer children indeed die convulſed <lb/>now, than formerly; this is becauſe the
        <lb/>rich learn, either from books, or con- <lb/>verſation with phyſicians, how neceſſa-
        <lb/>ry freſh air is to life and health; hence <lb/>they keep their houſes well aired; but
        <lb/>the poor, and ſervants, are not made to <lb/>comprehend this matter properly; and
        <lb/>therefore from neglecting to open their <lb/>windows, and breathing a foul, tainted
        <lb/>air, the greateſt part of their time, many <lb/>diſorders are brought on, and others
        <lb/>rendered worſe than they naturally <lb/>would be. <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)"
          n="*">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Where manufactures are carried on to a great ex- <lb/>tent, the air is rendered
            ſtill worſe, and every precau- <lb/>tion ought to be uſed to preſerve the health of the
            in- <lb/>habitants. Places where manufactures are carried on, <lb/>ought, therefore, to
            be conſtructed in ſuch a manner <lb/>as to be very lofty, and capable of being eaſily
            venti- <lb/>lated. Night working is undoubtedly a perverſion of <lb/>the laws of nature,
            renders the conſtitution feeble, and <lb/>lays a foundation for bad health and diſeaſe:
            for it not <lb/>only gives no time for ventilation, and in conſequence <lb/>the quantity
            of oxygen becomes more and more ex- <lb/>hauſted, but the number of candles uſed,
            contributes <pb n="45" type="footnote"/>
            <lb/>very much to contaminate the air. It has been found <lb/>by experiment that a
            candle contaminates more air than <lb/>a man. By perſons who are intereſted in the
            welfare of <lb/>the ſucceeding generation, night-work will never be <lb/>urged, and it
            will be right to ventilate the manufac- <lb/>tories every night, as well as during
            breakfaſt and <lb/>dinner. </p>
        </note>
      </p>
      <pb n="45"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having conſidered the purity of the <lb/>air, let us next take a view of the changes
        <lb/>in temperature which it undergoes, and <lb/>the effects which theſe have upon the
        <lb/>conſtitution. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>We find the air ſometimes conſiderably <lb/>below the freezing point; nay, even ſo
        <lb/>much as 20 or 30 degrees; it is then <lb/>intenſely cold; and on the other hand,
        <lb/>it ſometimes riſes to a great degree of <lb/>heat. We then find ourſelves much re-
        <lb/>laxed, and our conſtitutions exhauſted. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>To underſtand how this happens, let <lb/>us conſider for a moment the nature of
        <lb/>heat, and cold.—Heat is one of thoſe <lb/>ſtimuli which act upon the excitability, <pb
          n="46"/>
        <lb/>and ſupport life: for if it was totally <lb/>withdrawn, we ſhould not be able to exiſt
        <lb/>even a few minutes; and cold, is only <lb/>a diminution of heat. When heat is pre-
        <lb/>ſent, in a proper degree, or the atmoſ- <lb/>phere is about that degree of heat which
        <lb/>we call temperate, it juſt gives ſuch a <lb/>degree of ſtimulus, and keeps the excita-
        <lb/>bility exhauſted to ſuch a degree, as to <lb/>preſerve the body in health; but if it
        <lb/>continue for a conſiderable time to be <lb/>much warmer than this temperature, the
        <lb/>conſequence muſt be, from the laws al- <lb/>ready laid down, an exhauſtion of the
        <lb/>excitability, and a conſequent relaxation <lb/>and debility; for, when the excitability
        <lb/>has been exhauſted by the violent applica- <lb/>tion of heat, long continued, the com-
        <lb/>mon ſtimulant powers which ſupport <lb/>life, cannot produce a ſufficient effect
        <lb/>upon it, to give to the body that tone <lb/>which is compatible with health. On
        <lb/>the contrary, when the heat of the air <lb/>falls below what we call temperate, or
        <lb/>when cold is applied to the body, from <pb n="47"/>
        <lb/>the accuſtomed ſtimulus of heat being <lb/>diminiſhed, the excitability muſt accu-
        <lb/>mulate, or become more liable to be af- <lb/>fected by the action of the external
        <lb/>powers. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>This, however, very ſeldom produces <lb/>bad effects, unleſs the exciting powers be
        <lb/>improperly or quickly applied; for we <lb/>can bear a conſiderable diminution of heat
        <lb/>without any bad conſequences; and in all <lb/>caſes I hope I ſhall be able to make it
        ap- <lb/>pear, that much more miſchief ariſes from <lb/>the too great action of heat, than
        from the <lb/>diminution of it. Nature never made any <lb/>country too cold for its
        inhabitants. In <lb/>cold climates, ſhe has made exerciſe, and <lb/>even fatigue habitual to
        them, not only <lb/>from the neceſſity of their ſituation, but <lb/>from choice, their
        natural diverſions be- <lb/>ing all of the athletic or violent kind. <lb/>But the ſoftneſs
        and effeminacy of mo- <lb/>dern manners, has both deprived us of <lb/>our natural defence
        againſt the diſeaſes <lb/>moſt incident to our climate, and ſub- <pb n="48"/>
        <lb/>jected us to all the inconveniencics of a <lb/>warm one. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>People are afraid of going out into the <lb/>cold air; but if they conduct themſelves
        <lb/>properly afterwards, they will never be <lb/>in the leaſt danger from it. Indeed the
        <lb/>action of cold, unleſs it be exceſſive, <lb/>never produces any bad effects. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Many of you will, no doubt, think <lb/>me here in an error; but I hope you <lb/>will
        not long entertain that opinion. You <lb/>will ſay that you have had frequent ex-
        <lb/>perience to the contrary; that you have <lb/>often gone out into the cold air, and
        <lb/>have caught dreadful colds. That this <lb/>is owing to the action of cold, I will
        <lb/>deny; nay, I will aſſert, that if a per- <lb/>ſon go out into air which is very cold,
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">and remain in it</hi> for a very long time, he <lb/>will never
        perceive any ſymptoms of <lb/>what is called a cold ſo long as he re- <lb/>mains there. </p>
      <pb n="49"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A common cold is attended with a <lb/>running of the noſe, hoarſeneſs, and <lb/>cough,
        with a conſiderable degree of fe- <lb/>veriſh heat, and dryneſs of the ſkin.— <lb/>Now it is
        univerſally agreed, that this <lb/>diſorder is an inflammation, or is of an
        <lb/>inflammatory nature; it is an inflamma- <lb/>tion of the ſmooth, moiſt ſkin which
        <lb/>lines the noſtrils, and goes down the <lb/>wind-pipe into the lungs; but as cold
        <lb/>is only a diminution of heat, or a dimi- <lb/>nution of a ſtimulus acting upon the bo-
        <lb/>dy, it is impoſſible that ſuch a diminu- <lb/>tion can cauſe a greater action or
        excite- <lb/>ment; we might as well expect to fill a <lb/>veſſel by taking water out of it.
        But <lb/>let us ſee how a cold, as it is commonly <lb/>called, is uſually produced. When a
        <lb/>perſon in cold weather goes out into the <lb/>air, every time he draws in his breath,
        <lb/>the cold air paſſes through his noſtrils <lb/>and windpipe into the lungs, and in
        <lb/>thus diminiſhing the heat of the parts, allows <lb/>their excitability to accumulate,
        and <lb/>renders them more liable to be affected by <pb n="50"/>
        <lb/>the ſucceeding heat. So long as that <lb/>perſon continues in the cold air, he feels
        <lb/>no bad effects; but if he come into a <lb/>warm room, he firſt perceives a glow
        <lb/>within his noſtrils and breaſt, as well as <lb/>all over the ſurface of the body. Soon
        <lb/>afterwards, a diſagreeable dryneſs and <lb/>huſkineſs will be felt in the noſtrils and
        <lb/>breaſt. By and by a ſhort, dry, tickling <lb/>cough comes on. He feels a ſhivering,
        <lb/>which makes him draw nearer to the fire, <lb/>but all to no purpoſe; the more he tries
        <lb/>to heat himſelf, the more chill he be- <lb/>comes. All the miſchief is here cauſed
        <lb/>by the violent action of the heat on the <lb/>accumulated excitability. For want of
        <lb/>a knowledge of this law, theſe diſagree- <lb/>able, and often dangerous complaints are
        <lb/>brought on; when they might be avoid- <lb/>ed with the greateſt eaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>When you take a ride into the coun- <lb/>try on a cold day, you find yourſelves
        <lb/>very cold; as ſoon as you go into a houſe, <lb/>you are invited to come to the fire,
        and <pb n="51"/>
        <lb/>warm yourſelves; and what is ſtill <lb/>worſe, to drink ſomething warm and
        <lb/>comfortable, to keep out the cold, as the <lb/>ſaying is. The inevitable conſequence
        <lb/>of this, is, to bring on the complaints <lb/>which I have juſt deſcribed, which might
        <lb/>with more propriety, be called heats <lb/>than colds. But how eaſily might theſe
        <lb/>complaints have been avoided! When <lb/>you come out of a very cold atmoſphere,
        <lb/>you ſhould not at firſt go into a room <lb/>that has a fire in it, or if you cannot
        <lb/>avoid that, you ſhould keep for a conſi- <lb/>derable time at as great a diſtance from
        <lb/>the fire as poſſible, that the accumulated <lb/>excitability may be gradually
        exhauſted, <lb/>by the moderate and gentle action of <lb/>heat; and then you may bear the
        heat <lb/>of the fire without any danger: but, <lb/>above all, refrain from taking warm or
        <lb/>ſtrong liquors while you are cold. If a <lb/>perſon have his hands or feet expoſed to
        <lb/>a very ſevere cold, the excitability of <lb/>thoſe parts will be ſo much accumulated,
        <lb/>that if they ſhould be brought ſuddenly <pb n="52"/>
        <lb/>near the fire, a violent inflammation, <lb/><choice>
          <corr>and</corr>
          <sic>aud</sic>
        </choice> even a mortification will take place, <lb/>which has often happened; or, at any
        <lb/>rate, that inflammation called Chilblains <lb/>will be produced, from the violent ac-
        <lb/>tion of the heat upon the accumulated ex- <lb/>citability of thoſe parts; but, if a
        perſon <lb/>ſo circumſtanced, was to put his hands or <lb/>feet into cold water, very little
        warmer <lb/>than the atmoſphere to which he had <lb/>been expoſed, or rub them with ſnow,
        <lb/>which is not often colder than 32 or 30 <lb/>degrees, the morbid excitability will be
        <lb/>gradually exhauſted, and no bad conſe- <lb/>quences will enſue. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>When a part of the body only has been <lb/>expoſed to the action of cold, and the reſt
        <lb/>kept heated, if, for inſtance, a perſon <lb/>in a warm room ſits ſo that a current of
        <lb/>air coming through a broken pane, ſhould <lb/>fall upon any part of the body, that part
        <lb/>would be ſoon affected with an inflam- <lb/>mation, which is uſually called a rheuma-
        <lb/>tic inflammation. </p>
      <pb n="53"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From what has been ſaid, it will be <lb/>eaſy to account for this circumſtance.
        <lb/>The excitability of the part is accumu- <lb/>lated by the diminution of its heat; but
        <lb/>at the ſame time, the reſt of the body <lb/>and blood is warm; and this warm blood
        <lb/>acting upon a part where the excitability <lb/>is accumulated, will cauſe an inflamma-
        <lb/>tion; to which, the more you apply heat, <lb/>the worſe you make it.—From theſe
        <lb/>conſiderations, we may lay it down as a <lb/>fact, and experience ſupports us in ſo
        <lb/>doing, that you may in general go out of <lb/>warm into cold air without much dan-
        <lb/>ger; but, that you can never return <lb/>ſuddenly from the cold into the warm air
        <lb/>with perfect impunity. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Hence, we may lay down the follow- <lb/>ing rule, which, if ſtrictly obſerved,
        <lb/>would prevent the frequent colds we <lb/>meet with in winter. <hi rend="italic">When
          the whole <lb/>body, or any part of it, is chilled, bring <lb/>it to its natural feeling
          and warmth by <lb/>degrees. </hi>
      </p>
      <pb n="54"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But if, for want of obſerving this ne- <lb/>ceſſary caution, a cold, as it is called,
        <lb/>ſhould have ſeized a perſon, let us con- <lb/>ſider what is proper to be done. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It will, from the preceding reaſoning, <lb/>appear very improper to make the room
        <lb/>where you ſit warmer than uſual, to en- <lb/>creaſe the quantity of bed-cloaths, to
        <lb/>wrap yourſelf up in flannel, or particu- <lb/>larly to drink a large quantity of
        barley- <lb/>water, gruel, or tea, almoſt boiling hot, <lb/>by way of diluting, as it is
        called, and <lb/>forcing a perſpiration; this will infalliably <lb/>make the diſorder worſe,
        in the ſame <lb/>manner as confining inoculated perſons <lb/>in warm rooms would make their
        ſmall- <lb/>pox more violent. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Perhaps there would be ſcarcely ſuch <lb/>a thing as a bad cold, if people, when
        <lb/>they found it coming on, were to keep <lb/>cool, and avoid wine and ſtrong liquors,
        <lb/>and confine themſelves for a ſhort time <lb/>to a ſimple diet of vegetable food, drink-
          <pb n="55"/>
        <lb/>ing only toaſt and water. Inſtances are <lb/>by no means uncommon, where a heat <lb/>of
        the noſtrils, difficulty of breathing, <lb/>a ſhort, tickling cough, and other ſymp-
        <lb/>toms, threatening a violent cold, have <lb/>gone off entirely in conſequence of this
        <lb/>plan being purſued. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Colds would be much leſs frequent, <lb/>were we to take more pains to accom-
        <lb/>modate our dreſs to the ſeaſon: if we <lb/>were warmly cloathed in cold weather,
        <lb/>our excitability would not be accumu- <lb/>lated by the action of the cold. If a
        greater <lb/>proportion of females fall victims to this <lb/>diſeaſe, is it not becauſe,
        loſing ſight, <lb/>more than men, of its primary purpoſe, <lb/>they regulate their dreſs
        ſolely by fan- <lb/>taſtic ideas of elegance? If happily, as is <lb/>obſerved by Dr.
        Beddoes, our regret <lb/>ſhould recall the age of chivalry, to break <lb/>the ſpell of
        faſhion would be an atchieve- <lb/>ment worthy the moſt gallant of our fu- <lb/>ture
        Knights. Common ſenſe has al- <lb/>ways failed in the adventure; and our <pb n="56"/>
        <lb/>ladies, alas! are ftill compelled, when- <lb/>ever the enchantreſs waves her wand, to
        <lb/>expoſe themſelves half undreſſed, to the <lb/>fogs and froſts of our iſland. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Beſides the effects of the air, we ought <lb/>by no means to be indifferent with regard
        <lb/>to what we take into the ſtomach as food <lb/>and drink; ſince theſe have even a
        <lb/>greater influence on our health, than the <lb/>circumſtances I have already mentioned.
        <lb/>Among the cauſes which excite the body, <lb/>and ſupport life, I have formerly menti-
        <lb/>oned food, or the matters taken into the <lb/>ſtomach. It is from theſe matters that
        <lb/>all the animal ſolids and fluids are formed; <lb/>theſe are ſtimuli, which if totally
        with- <lb/>drawn, we could not exiſt many days. <lb/>Theſe ſtimuli are ſubject to the ſame
        laws <lb/>with all the others which act upon the <lb/>body. When they act properly in con-
        <lb/>cert with the other powers, they produce <lb/>the healthy ſtate; but if they act in an
        <lb/>undue degree, whether that action be too <lb/>great or too little, diſeaſe will be the
          <pb n="57"/>
        <lb/>conſequence. When they act too feebly, <lb/>the excitability will accumulate; and diſ-
        <lb/>eaſes of debility, attended with a very <lb/>great degree of irritability, will take
        <lb/>place: this has been inſtanced in thoſe <lb/>who have been without food for ſome
        <lb/>time. Perſons who have been ſhut up <lb/>in a coal-work by the falling-in of the
        <lb/>pit, and have conſequently been without <lb/>food for ſome days, have had their ex-
        <lb/>citability ſo much accumulated, as to be <lb/>toxicated with a baſon of broth. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>To this ſource we may attribute many <lb/>of the diſeaſes with which the poor are
        <lb/>afflicted; but they are by no means ſo <lb/>common as diſeaſes of an oppoſite nature,
        <lb/>which ariſe from a too free uſe of food. <lb/>I ſhall confine myſelf here to the conſi-
        <lb/>deration of what is more ſtrictly called <lb/>food, and afterwards conſider the effects
        <lb/>of ſtrong liquors. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>When we take food in too great quan- <lb/>tity, or of too nouriſhing a quality, it <pb
          n="58"/>
        <lb/>will either produce inflammatory diſeaſes, <lb/>ſuch as pleuriſy, or by exhauſting the
        <lb/>excitability, it will bring on ſtomach <lb/>complaints, gout, and all the ſymptoms
        <lb/>of premature old age. This follows ſo <lb/>evidently from the laws we have inveſti-
        <lb/>gated, that it is ſcarcely neceſſary to ſay <lb/>more on the ſubject; and I am ſure
        there <lb/>are few who have not ſeen examples <lb/>of it. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Be therefore temperate in eating, and <lb/>eat only of ſuch foods as are the plaineſt;
        <lb/>and let a proper quantity of vegetable <lb/>food be mixed with animal. If you
        <lb/>value the preſervation of health, never <lb/>ſatiate yourſelves with eating; but let
        <lb/>it be a rule from which you ought never <lb/>to depart, always to riſe from table with
        <lb/>ſome remains of appetite: for, when the <lb/>ſtomach is loaded with more food than
        <lb/>it can eaſily digeſt, a crude and unaſſi- <lb/>milated chyle is taken into the blood,
        <lb/>pregnant with diſeaſes. Nor is the quan- <lb/>tity the only object of attention; the
          <pb n="59"/>
        <lb/>quality of the food is to be carefully ſtu- <lb/>died; made diſhes, enriched with hot
        <lb/>ſauces, ſtimulate infinitely more than <lb/>plain food, and therefore exhauſt the ex-
        <lb/>citability, bringing on diſeaſes of indirect <lb/>debility; ſuch as the worſt kind of
        gout, <lb/>apoplexy, and paralytic complaints. <q rend="quotes">For <lb/>my part, </q> ſays
        an elegant writer, <q rend="quotes">when <lb/>I behold a faſhionable table ſet out in all
          <lb/>its magnificence, I fancy that I ſee gouts <lb/>and dropſies, fevers and lethargies,
          with <lb/>other innumerable diſtempers, lying in <lb/>ambuſcade among the diſhes. </q> Let
        it be <lb/>therefore laid down as a rule by thoſe <lb/>who wiſh to preſerve their health,
        and I <lb/>have nothing to ſay to thoſe who are in- <lb/>different on that head, to make
        their <lb/>chief repaſt on one plain diſh, and trifle <lb/>with the reſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It is by no means uncommon for a <lb/>medical man to have patients, chiefly <lb/>among
        people of faſhion and fortune, <lb/>who complain of being hot and reſtleſs <lb/>all night,
        and having a foul taſte in the <pb n="60"/>
        <lb/>mouth every morning: on examination <lb/>it is found, that in nineteen caſes out of
        <lb/>twenty, it has ariſen from their having <lb/>overloaded their ſtomachs, and at the
        <lb/>ſame time neglected to take proper exer- <lb/>ciſe; for it muſt always be obſerved,
        <lb/>that more may be eaten with ſafety, <lb/>nay, more is even neceſſary, when a
        <lb/>perſon takes a good deal of exerciſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>When people take little exerciſe, and <lb/>overload their ſtomachs, there lies within
        <lb/>them a fermenting maſs of undigeſted <lb/>aliment; and it is not ſurprizing that
        <lb/>this ſhould irritate and heat the body <lb/>during the night. This is likewiſe the
        <lb/>foundation of ſtomach complaints, flatu- <lb/>lencies, and all other ſymptoms of indi-
        <lb/>geſtion; which more frequently proceed <lb/>from intemperance in eating and drink-
        <lb/>ing than any other cauſe. The benefits <lb/>ariſing from temperance are ſet in a
        <lb/>ſtriking light in the following allegory, <lb/>which may be found in the adventurer. </p>
      <pb n="61"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Eſculapius, after his deification or ad- <lb/>mittance among the Gods, having re-
        <lb/>viſited his native country, and being one <lb/>day (as curioſity led him a rambling,)
        in <lb/>danger of being benighted, made the beſt <lb/>of his way to a houſe he ſaw at ſome
        <lb/>diſtance, where he was hoſpitably re- <lb/>ceived by the maſter's of it. Cremes, for
        <lb/>that was the maſter's name, though but <lb/>a young man, was infirm and ſickly. <lb/>Of
        ſeveral diſhes ſerved up to ſupper, <lb/>Cremes obſerved that his gueſt ate but <lb/>of one,
        and that the moſt ſimple; nor <lb/>could all his intreaties prevail upon him <lb/>to do
        otherwiſe. He was, notwith- <lb/>ſtanding, highly delighted with Eſcula- <lb/>pius's
        converſation, in which he obſerved <lb/>a cheerfulneſs and knowledge ſuperior to <lb/>any
        thing he had hitherto met with. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The next morning, Eſculapius took <lb/>his leave, but not till he had engaged his
        <lb/>good-natured hoſt to pay him a viſit at a <lb/>ſmall villa, a few miles from thence.
        <lb/>Cremes came accordingly, and was moſt <pb n="62"/>
        <lb/>kindly received; but how great was his <lb/>amazement when ſupper was ſerved up,
        <lb/>to ſee nothing but milk, honey, and a <lb/>few roots, dreſſed in the plaineſt, but
        <lb/>neateſt manner, to which hunger, cheer- <lb/>fulneſs, and good ſenſe, were the only
        <lb/>ſauces. Eſculapius ſeemed to eat with <lb/>pleaſure, while Cremes ſcarcely taſted of
        <lb/>them. On which a repaſt was ordered <lb/>more ſuitable to the taſte of our gueſt. Im-
        <lb/>mediately there ſucceeded a banquet com- <lb/>poſed of the moſt artful diſhes that
        luxury <lb/>could invent, with great plenty and va- <lb/>riety of the richeſt and moſt
        intoxicating <lb/>wines. Theſe too were accompanied by <lb/>damſels of the moſt bewitching
        beauty. <lb/>Cremes now gave a looſe to his appetites, <lb/>and every thing he taſted raiſed
        exſtaſies <lb/>beyond what he had ever known. <lb/>During the repaſt, the damſels ſung and
        <lb/>danced to entertain them; their charms <lb/>enchanted the enraptured gueſt, already
        <lb/>fluſhed with what he had drank; his <lb/>ſenſes were loſt in exſtatic confuſion.
        <lb/>Every thing around him ſeemed Elyſium, <pb n="63"/>
        <lb/>and he was on the point of indulging the <lb/>moſt boundleſs freedoms, when on a
        <lb/>ſudden their beauty, which was but a <lb/>vizard, fell off, and diſcovered forms
        <lb/>the moſt hideous and forbidding imagi- <lb/>nable. Luſt, revenge, folly, murder,
        <lb/>meagre poverty, and deſpair, now ap- <lb/>peared in the moſt odious ſhapes, and
        <lb/>the place inſtantly became a moſt dire <lb/>ſcene of miſery and confuſion. How
        <lb/>often did Cremes wiſh himſelf far diſtant <lb/>from ſuch a diabolical company, and
        <lb/>now dreaded the fatal conſequence which <lb/>threatened him. His blood ran chill at
        <lb/>his heart, and joy and rapture were per- <lb/>verted to amazement and horror!—
        <lb/>When Eſculapius perceived it had made <lb/>a ſufficient impreſſion on his gueſt, he
        <lb/>thus addreſſed him: <q rend="quotes">Know, Cremes, <lb/>it is Eſculapius who has thus
          entertained <lb/>you, and what you have beheld is a true <lb/>image of the deceitfulneſs
          and miſery <lb/>inſeparable from luxury and intempe- <lb/>rance. Would you be happy, be
          tem- <lb/>perate: temperance is the parent of <pb n="64"/>
          <lb/>health, virtue, wiſdom, plenty, and <lb/>every thing that can make you happy in
          <lb/>this or the world to come. It is indeed <lb/>the true luxury of life, for without it
          <lb/>life cannot be enjoyed. </q> This ſaid, he <lb/>diſappeared, and left Cremes (inſtead
        of <lb/>an elegant apartment) in an open plain, <lb/>full of ideas quite different from
        thoſe he <lb/>had brought with him. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>On his return home, from the moſt <lb/>luxurious, he became one of the moſt
        <lb/>temperate men, by which wiſe method <lb/>he ſoon regained health. Frugality pro-
        <lb/>duced riches, and from an infirm and <lb/>crazy conſtitution, and almoſt ruined
        <lb/>eſtate, by virtue of this infallible elixir, <lb/>he became one of the happieſt men
        <lb/>breathing, and lived to a healthy old age, <lb/>revered as an oracle for his wiſdom
        <lb/>throughout all Greece. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>If temperance be neceſſary with re- <lb/>gard to food, it is ſtill more ſo with re-
        <lb/>ſpect to ſtrong liquors; theſe diffuſible <pb n="65"/>
        <lb/>ſtimuli by quickly exhauſting the exci- <lb/>tability, ſoon blaſt the vigour, and ſap
        <lb/>the foundation of the ſtrongeſt conſtitu- <lb/>tion. Their immediate effects you
        <lb/>know are ſtimulant; they raiſe the ani- <lb/>mal ſpirits, produce a cheerful ſtate of
        <lb/>mind, and if taken in greater quantity, <lb/>cauſe intoxication, or that temporary de-
        <lb/>rangement of the thinking powers which <lb/>ariſes from too great a degree of excite-
        <lb/>ment: but let us ſee what happens the <lb/>next day; the animal ſpirits are ex-
        <lb/>hauſted, and the perſon thus ſituated, <lb/>finds himſelf languid and enervated to a
        <lb/>great degree; for it ſeems a law of the <lb/>human body, that the ſpirits are never
        <lb/>artificially raiſed, without being after- <lb/>wards proportionably depreſſed; and to
        <lb/>ſhew clearly that in this ſtate the exci- <lb/>tability is exhauſted, the ordinary pow-
        <lb/>ers which in general ſupport life, will <lb/>not have their due effect; and a perſon
        <lb/>thus ſituated finds moſt relief the next <lb/>day, from taking ſome of the ſame
        <lb/>ſtimulus which occaſioned the exhauſ- <pb n="66"/>
        <lb/>tion; becauſe the common exciting <lb/>powers can ſcarcely act upon his ex-
        <lb/>hauſted excitability. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>But though the excitability be in this <lb/>way exhauſted, it will in the courſe of
        <lb/>a day or two be again accumulated, and <lb/>it may, perhaps, be ſuſpected that this
        <lb/>exhauſtion can do no harm at all to the <lb/>conſtitution; but this is a premature
        <lb/>concluſion, and quite contrary to fact <lb/>and experience, as well as to reaſon;
        <lb/>for, juſt in the ſame manner that a pen- <lb/>dulum, made to vibrate in the arc of a
        <lb/>circle, will never return exactly to the <lb/>ſame height, but fall a little ſhort of
        it <lb/>every time; ſo, though the excitability <lb/>may be again accumulated, it never can
        <lb/>be brought back to what it was before; <lb/>and every freſh debauch will ſhorten life,
        <lb/>probably two or three weeks at leaſt, <lb/>beſides debilitating the body, and bring-
        <lb/>ing on a variety of diſeaſes, with pre- <lb/>mature old age. </p>
      <pb n="67"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Thoſe who drink only a moderate <lb/>quantity of wine, ſo as to make them
        <lb/>cheerful, as they call it, but not abſo- <lb/>lutely to intoxicate, may imagine that
        <lb/>it will do them no harm. The ſtrong <lb/>and robuſt may enjoy the pleaſures of <lb/>the
        bottle and table with ſeeming impu- <lb/>nity, and ſometimes for many years, <lb/>may not
        find any bad effects from them; <lb/>but depend upon it, if a full diet of ani- <lb/>mal
        food be every day indulged in, with <lb/>only a moderate portion of wine, its <lb/>baneful
        influence will blaſt the vigour of <lb/>the ſtrongeſt conſtitution. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>While we are eating, water is the beſt <lb/>beverage. The cuſtom of drinking fer-
        <lb/>mented liquors, and particularly wine, <lb/>during dinner, is a very pernicious one.
        <lb/>The idea that it aſſiſts digeſtion, is falſe; <lb/>thoſe who are acquainted with
        chemiſtry <lb/>know, that food is hardened, and ren- <lb/>dered leſs digeſtible by theſe
        means, and <lb/>the ſtimulus which wine gives to the <lb/>ſtomach is not neceſſary,
        excepting to <pb n="68"/>
        <lb/>thoſe who have exhauſted the excitabi- <lb/>lity of that organ by the exceſſive uſe of
        <lb/>ſtrong liquors. In theſe, the ſtomach <lb/>can ſcarcely be excited to any action
        <lb/>without the aſſiſtance of ſuch a ſtimulus. <lb/>If food wants diluting, water is the
        beſt <lb/>diluent, and will prevent the riſing, as <lb/>it is called, of ſtrong food, much
        better <lb/>than wine or ſpirits. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Before I finiſh this ſubject, I ſhall ſay <lb/>a few words on the pernicious cuſtom of
        <lb/>ſuffering children to drink wine, or <lb/>other fermented liquors. Nothing is <lb/>more
        common than to ſee, even very <lb/>young children come to the table after <lb/>dinner, to
        drink a glaſs of wine. The leaſt <lb/>quantity produces violent effects on their
        <lb/>accumulated excitability, and by quick- <lb/>ly exhauſting it, ruins their
        conſtitutions <lb/>through life, and often renders them ha- <lb/>bitual drinkers. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>I can ſcarcely help attributing in ſome <lb/>degree the many ſtomach complaints we <pb
          n="69"/>
        <lb/>meet with, among young people in the <lb/>preſent age, and which were unknown <lb/>to
        our forefathers, to the abominable <lb/>practice of ſuffering children to drink
        <lb/>fermented, or ſpirituous liquors. You <lb/>muſt all have obſerved how ſoon chil-
        <lb/>dren are intoxicated and inflamed by ſpi- <lb/>rituous liquors; you may judge then,
        <lb/>that if theſe liquors be only a ſlow poiſon <lb/>to us, they are a very quick one to
        <lb/>them. A glaſs of wine, on account of <lb/>the accumulated excitability of children,
        <lb/>will have more effect upon them, than <lb/>a bottle will have upon an adult accuſ-
        <lb/>tomed to drink wine. If therefore, the <lb/>health of a child, and its happineſs
        <lb/>through life be an object, never ſuffer it <lb/>to taſte fermented, or ſpirituous
        liquors, <lb/>till it be fifteen or ſixteen years of age, <lb/>unleſs a little wine be
        neceſſary as a me- <lb/>dicine. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It now only remains for me to take <lb/>ſome notice of exerciſe. Of all the va-
        <lb/>rious methods of preſerving health, and <pb n="70"/>
        <lb/>of preventing diſeaſes, which nature has <lb/>ſuggeſted, there is none more efficacious
        <lb/>than exerciſe, it puts the fluids all in <lb/>motion, ſtrengthens the ſolids, promotes
        <lb/>perſpiration, and occaſions the decompo- <lb/>ſition of a larger quantity of
        atmoſpheric <lb/>air in the lungs. Hence, in order to <lb/>preſerve the health of the body,
        the au- <lb/>thor of nature has made exerciſe abſo- <lb/>lutely neceſſary to the greater
        part of <lb/>mankind for obtaining the means of ex- <lb/>iſtence.—Had not exerciſe been
        abſo- <lb/>lutely neceſſary for our well-being ſays <lb/>the elegant Addiſon, nature would
        not <lb/>have made the body ſo proper for it, <lb/>by giving ſuch an activity to the limbs,
        <lb/>and ſuch a pliancy to every part, as ne- <lb/>ceſſarily produce thoſe compreſſions, ex-
        <lb/>tenſions, contortions, dilatations, and all <lb/>other kinds of motions that are
        neceſſary <lb/>for the preſervation of ſuch a ſyſtem of <lb/>tubes and glands.—And that we
        might <lb/>not want inducement to engage us in <lb/>ſuch exerciſe of the body as is proper
        for <lb/>its welfare, it is ſo ordered, that nothing <pb n="71"/>
        <lb/>valuable can be procured without it. <lb/>Not to mention riches and honors, even
        <lb/>food and raiment are not to be come at <lb/>without the toil of the hands and ſweat
        <lb/>of the brow. Providence furniſhes ma- <lb/>terials, but expects that we ſhould work
        <lb/>them up ourſelves. The earth muſt be <lb/>laboured before it gives its increaſe, and
        <lb/>when it is forced into its ſeveral pro- <lb/>ducts, how many hands muſt they paſs
        <lb/>through before they are fit for uſe? Ma- <lb/>nufactures, trade, and agriculture, natu-
        <lb/>rally employ more than nineteen parts of <lb/>the ſpecies out of twenty; and as for
        <lb/>thoſe who are not obliged to labour by <lb/>the condition in which they are born,
        <lb/>they are more miſerable than the reſt of <lb/>mankind, unleſs they indulge themſelves
        <lb/>in that voluntary labour which goes by <lb/>the name of exerciſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Of all the different kinds of exerciſe, <lb/>there is none that conduces ſo much to
        <lb/>health as riding; it is not attended with <lb/>the fatigue of walking, and the free air
          <pb n="72"/>
        <lb/>is more enjoyed in this way than by any <lb/>other mode of exerciſe. Where it can-
        <lb/>not be uſed, walking, or exerciſe in a <lb/>carriage, ought to be ſubſtituted. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The beſt time for taking exerciſe is <lb/>before dinner, for the body is then more
        <lb/>vigorous and alert, and the mind more <lb/>cheerful, and better diſpoſed to enjoy
        <lb/>the pleaſure of a ride or walk. Exerciſe <lb/>after a full meal diſturbs digeſtion, and
        <lb/>cauſes painful ſenſations in the ſtomach <lb/>and bowels, with heart burn, and acid
        <lb/>eructations. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>But whatever mode of exerciſe you <lb/>uſe, it ought not at firſt to be too violent.
        <lb/>Dr. Armſtrong has given us an excellent <lb/>rule— </p>
      <p rend="size(0.5) space">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple quotes">Begin with gentle toils, and as your nerves <lb/>grow firm, to
          hardier, by juſt ſteps aſpire. <lb/>The prudent, even in every moderate walk, <lb/>at
          firſt but ſaunter, and by flow degrees <lb/>increaſe their pace. </q>
      </p>
      <trailer rend="sc space align-center">
        <lb/>the end. </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
