<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Douglas: Lithotomia Douglassiana: or, an account of a new method of
          making the high operation</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>John Douglas</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Lithotomia Douglassiana: OR, An Account of a New METHOD of making the
              High Operation, in order to extract the Stone out of the Bladder. Which is much easier
              to the Patient, much sooner done by the Operator, and the Cure much more certain, than
              after any of the other Methods now in Use. By which also, several of the most dismal
              Consequences of the common Operations are entirely prevented, such as Incontinency of
              Urine, Impotency, Fistula's, &amp;c.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T41092</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T41092"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for Tho. Woodward, next Door but one to Temple-Bar,
                  MDCCXX. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1720</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="28"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="3"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3306948141</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K040667.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Surgical or anatominal work"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_2" n="3"/>
      <head rend="hanging"><lb/><hi rend="italic dc(2)">Lithotomia Douglaſſiana:</hi>
        <lb/> OR, <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">An Account of a <hi rend="sc">New Method</hi></hi>
        <lb/>of making the <hi rend="sc">High Operation</hi>, <lb/>in order to extract the Stone out
        of <lb/>the Bladder, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space"><lb/>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>Decorative frame around the letter "I".</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N this new Operation, I cut on <lb/>the lower Part of the Belly. In
        <lb/>the common Operations, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
        <lb/>Cutting on the <hi rend="italic">Staffe,</hi> and <w part="I">cut-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ting</w> on the <hi rend="italic">Gripe,</hi> they cut on <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >Perinæum, i. e.</hi> between the Teſticles and <lb/>Fundament. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_3" n="4"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>This Section is call'd by Authors, <hi rend="italic">The High
          <lb/>Operation,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Hypogaſtrick Section.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I have hitherto only met with three, that <lb/>ever pretended to have
        made it: The firſt <lb/>of whom is <hi rend="italic">Peter de Franco</hi> of <hi
          rend="italic">Turriers</hi> in <lb/><hi rend="italic">France,</hi> of which he gives the
        following <lb/>Account in his Treatiſe of <hi rend="italic">Hernio</hi>'s, (at the <lb/>End
        of the 33d Chapter, Page 139) publiſh'd <lb/>at <hi rend="italic">Lyons</hi> in the Year
        1561, in theſe Words: <q rend="italic indent diple"><lb/>"Hiſtoire, <lb/>Je reciteray ce que
          une fois m'eſt advenu <lb/>voulant tirer une pierre a un enfant de deux <lb/>ans ou
          environ: auquel ayant trouué la pierre <lb/>de la Groſſeur d'um æuf de poulle, ou peu
          pres, <lb/>je fey tout ce que je peu pour la mener bas: &amp; <lb/>voyant que je ne
          pounoye rien avancer par-<lb/>tous mes efforts, avec ce, que le patient eſtoit
          <lb/>merueillcuſement tormenté, &amp; auſſi les Parens <lb/>deſirans qu'il mouruſt
          pluſtoſt que de viure en-<lb/>tel travail: Joint auſſi, que je ne vouloye pas <lb/>quil me
          fut Reproché de ne l'avoir ſeu tirer, <lb/>(qui eſtoit à moy grand folie) je deliberay
          <lb/>avec l'importunité du pere, Mere, &amp; amis, de <lb/>Copper le dit enfant par deſſus
          l'os Pubis, <w part="I">d'au-</w><lb/><w part="F">tant</w> que la Pierre ne voulut
          deſcendre bas, <lb/>&amp; fut Coppé ſur le Penil, un peu a Coſtè &amp; <lb/>ſur la Pierre.
          Car je leuoys icelle avec mes <lb/>doigts, qui eſtoyèt au fondment, &amp; d'autre
          <lb/>Coſté en la tenant ſubiette avec les mains <lb/>d'un Serviteur qui comprimoit le
          petit ventre <pb xml:id="page_4" n="5"/><lb/>au deſſus de la pierre, Dont elle fut tirée
          hors <lb/>par ce moyen, &amp; puis apres le patient fut <lb/>guary, (non obſtant qu'il en
          fut bien malade) <lb/>&amp; la playe conſolidée: Combien que je ne <lb/>conſeille a
            <unclear>#</unclear>omine d'ainſi faire. Ains <w part="I">pluſt-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >oſt</w> uſer du moyen par nous ino<unclear>#</unclear>nt<unclear>#</unclear> du quel
          <lb/>nous venons de parler. "</q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>This is (in his own Words) all that he <lb/>ſays about it: Which, for
        the Benefit of <lb/>thoſe that don't underſtand <hi rend="italic">French,</hi> I ſhall
        <lb/>tranſlate into <hi rend="italic">Engliſh,</hi> thus: </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>"He ſays, he had a Child about two <lb/>Years old, who had a Stone in
        the Bladder <lb/>as big as a Hen's Egg, brought to him to <lb/>cut: He uſed all his
        Dexterity to force the <lb/>Stone down to the Neck of the Bladder, <lb/>but found it
        impoſſible to be done: The <lb/>Child was in that Torture and Miſery, <lb/>that the Parents
        wiſhed him rather dead, <lb/>than he ſhould live longer in ſo doleful a <lb/>Condition. <hi
          rend="italic">De Franco,</hi> on the other Hand, <lb/>thinking it would tend to his
        Diſhonour <lb/>not to take away the Stone, at laſt <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſolv'd</w> to make Tryal, whether he could <lb/>not bring it to the very Groin, which he
        <lb/>did, by putting his Fingers into the <w part="I">Fun-</w><lb/><w part="F">dament</w>,
        and raiſing up the Stone, he caus'd <lb/>his Servant, on the other Side oppoſite to
        <lb/>him, to preſs it down to the Place <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">tended</w> for
        Inciſion; which he made, took <lb/>out the Stone, and, tho' the Child was <pb
          xml:id="page_5" n="6"/><lb/>very weak, recover'd him, and heal'd the <lb/>Wound: But he
        adviſes others not to <w part="I">fol-</w><lb/><w part="F">low</w> his Example; and, inſtead
        of it, <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">commends</w> the Operation which he calls
        <lb/>his own Invention, and has deſcrib'd, in <lb/>the foregoing Part of the ſame Chapter." </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The next to him, that's ſaid to have <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">form'd</w> it, is one <hi rend="italic">Bonnet,</hi> of whom Monſ. <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Tollet,</hi> in the 5th Edition of his <hi rend="italic">Lithotomy,</hi>
        <lb/>publiſh'd at <hi rend="italic">Paris</hi> 1708, gives the following <lb/>Account, Page
        139. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes"><hi rend="italic">Feu M.</hi> Jonnot <hi rend="italic"
            >m'a dit autrefois que <lb/>M.</hi> Bonnet <hi rend="italic">Chirurgien, qui prætiquoit
            il ya <lb/>tres-long-temps la Lithotomie dans l'</hi> Hôtel <lb/>Dieu <hi rend="italic"
            >de</hi> Paris, <hi rend="italic">l'avoit aſſuré d'en avoir taillé <lb/>de cette façon.
            M.</hi> Petit, <hi rend="italic">Maitre Chirurgien <lb/>façon de cet Hoſpital mà dit
            l'avoir vu pratique <lb/>ſur une Petite fille par le même M.</hi> Bonnet.</q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes">Mr. <hi rend="italic">Tollet</hi> ſays, that the late
          Mr. <hi rend="italic">Jonnot</hi>
          <lb/>(who was alſo a famous <hi rend="italic">Lithotomiſt</hi>) told <lb/>him formerly,
          that Mr. <hi rend="italic">Bonnet,</hi> a Surgeon, <lb/>who practis'd <hi rend="italic"
            >Lithotomy</hi> a conſiderable <lb/>Time ago in the <hi rend="italic">Hotel Dieu</hi> at
            <hi rend="italic">Paris,</hi> aſſur'd <lb/>him, (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> Mr. <hi
            rend="italic">Jonnot</hi>) that he had cut <lb/>after that Manner. Mr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Petit,</hi>
          <w part="I">Maſter-Sur-</w><lb/><w part="F">geon</w> of that Hoſpital, alſo told our <w
            part="I">Au-</w><lb/><w part="F">thor</w>, that he had ſeen it practiſed by the
          <lb/>ſame <hi rend="italic">Bonnet</hi> on a young Girl.</q>
      </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_6" n="7"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Mons. <hi rend="italic">Dionis,</hi> in the 2d Edition of his <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Courſe of Chirurgical Operations,</hi> publiſh'd at <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Paris</hi> 1714, Page 139, gives the following <lb/>Account of the ſame Man, <hi
          rend="italic">viz.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes"><hi rend="italic">On nous aſſure que Monſieur</hi>
          Bonnet <lb/><hi rend="italic">a pratiqué ſovent cette Operation à l'</hi>Hôtel <lb/>Dieu
            <hi rend="italic">de</hi> Paris <hi rend="italic">avec une heureux ſuccés, &amp;
            <lb/>que même Monſieur Petit luy a vû faire.</hi></q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes">We are aſſur'd, that Mons. <hi rend="italic"
            >Bonnet,</hi>
          <w part="I">fre-</w><lb/><w part="F">quently</w> and with good Succeſs, perform'd
          <lb/>this Operation at the <hi rend="italic">Hotel Dieu</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
            >Paris;</hi>
          <lb/>and that Mons. <hi rend="italic">Petit</hi> has ſeen him perform <lb/>it.</q> This is
        all the Account that I have <lb/>met with of this <hi rend="italic">Bonnet.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>After him, Dr. <hi rend="italic">Groenevelt</hi> was the next <lb/>that
        perform'd it, of which he gives the <w part="I">fol-</w><lb/><w part="F">lowing</w> Account
        in the <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi> Edition of <lb/>his <hi rend="italic">Lithotomy,</hi>
        publiſh'd at <hi rend="italic">London</hi> in 1710. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes">I once had a Patient in <hi rend="italic">Long Lane, <w
              part="I">Moor-</w><lb/><w part="F">fields</w>,</hi> upon whom I was oblig'd to <w
            part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">form</w> this High Operation; and very <w part="I"
            >ſuc-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceſſfully</w> extracted the Stone, by making <lb/>Inciſion
          near the Groin, the Patient ſoon <lb/>recovering; which ſhews, that Wounds in <lb/>the
          fibrous Part of the Bladder are not <lb/>always mortal.</q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Thoſe are the only Three that I have met <lb/>with, that ever pretended
        to have cut above <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Os Pubis, i. e.</hi> into the Belly. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_7" n="8"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Franco</hi> cut ſo firſt, becauſe he had a <w part="I"
          >Pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tient</w> that he could not cut his own Way, <lb/>tho', at the
        ſame Time, he had the <w part="I">Cha-</w><lb/><w part="F">racter</w> of one of the beſt <hi
          rend="italic">Lithotomiſts</hi> of his <lb/>Age. But tho' he ſucceeded, yet, it ſeems,
        <lb/>he found ſuch Difficulties in it, that he <lb/>would never do't again, and charges us
        never <lb/>to follow his Example; which one would <lb/>have expected that he ſhould have
        explain'd <lb/>in his Account of it, the better to deter <lb/>others from the like Practice. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Bonnet</hi> is ſaid to have done it ſeveral Times
        <lb/>with Succeſs; yet he don't recommend it to <lb/>others as a Rule of Practice, nor was
        ever <lb/>imitated by any of his Contemporaries. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Groenevelt</hi> did it but once, and ſays, he <lb/>was
        oblig'd to do it: I ſuppoſe, in ſome <w part="I">ſuch-</w><lb/><w part="F">like</w> Caſe as
          <hi rend="italic">De Franco</hi>'s; and though he <lb/>alſo ſucceeded, yet, inſtead of
        recommending <lb/>it, he only draws this Conſequence from <lb/>it, <hi rend="italic"
          >viz.</hi> That Wounds of the fibrous Part <lb/>of the Bladder are not always mortal. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Franco</hi> cut on the Hair above the <hi
          rend="italic">Pubis,</hi>
        <lb/>a little on one Side; <hi rend="italic">Groenevelt</hi> near the <lb/>Groin: But not
        one of them tells us what <lb/>luſtruments they uſed, or which Way they <lb/>uſed them;
        whether they made a croſs, <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">lique</w>, or longitudinal
        Inciſion; whether <lb/>they made the Inciſion at once, or at ſeveral <lb/>Times, or what
        Poſition they put their <w part="I">Pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tient</w> in; all which, and
        many more <w part="I">Cir-</w><lb/><w part="F">cumſtances</w>, ought to have been exactly <w
          part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſcrib'd</w>, before any one could be ſaid to have <pb
          xml:id="page_8" n="9"/><lb/>follow'd their Method; from whence I <lb/>may very ſafely
        infer, that it will be no <lb/>eaſy matter to tell which Way any of them <lb/>made their
        Operations, and yet it's commonly <lb/>aſſerted with the greateſt Aſſurance (not with
        <lb/>any Deſign to raiſe <hi rend="italic">De Franco</hi>'s Reputation, but <lb/>to leſſen
        mine) that I made this Operation <lb/>after <hi rend="italic">De Franco</hi>'s Method,
        though he has told <lb/>but very little of his Story, and I have told <lb/>none of mine. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Upon the Whole, I muſt ſay, that it's a <w part="I">Mi-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">racle</w> to me, that after ſo much Succeſs, either <lb/>they, or thoſe that ſaw
        them do it, did not <w part="I">ei-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> continue the Practice of
        it, or give us more <lb/>ſubſtantial Reaſons why they diſapprov'd of it; <lb/>ſo far from
        that, they have not given us one <lb/>Inſtance of a Patient's dying after this Section. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>This Operation is alſo recommended as a <lb/>very probable Way by <hi
          rend="italic">Rouſſecus, Dionis,</hi> &amp;c. <lb/>yet not one of them was ever ſo far <w
          part="I">perſwa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ded</w> of it as to make the Experiment, <w part="I"
          >how-</w><lb/><w part="F">ever</w> ſeveral of them have undertaken (which <lb/>none that
        ever made the Operation thought <lb/>fit to do) to deſcribe the Method how it may <lb/>be
        done, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> to teach others to perform <lb/>what they can't do
        themſelves; (which, in my <lb/>Opinion is the greateſt Abſurdity in Nature;) <lb/>but to
        what Purpoſe, he that makes the <w part="I">Ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">periment</w> will ſee. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Having thus recited all the Inſtances that I <lb/>have met with of the
        Stone in the Bladder, <lb/>being extracted through the Belly, in the <lb/>Words of the
        Authors, That every one may <pb xml:id="page_9" n="10"/><lb/>be a Judge of the Encouragement
        I had to <lb/>undertake this Operation from what has been <lb/>done this Way before. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I ſhall next give an Account of the <w part="I">Ob-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >jections</w> made againſt the fore-mention'd <w part="I">Gen-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tlemens</w> Operations, by ſome of the moſt <w part="I">au-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >thentick</w> Authors that have mention'd them. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Firſt,</hi> Some ſay that the Urine from the
        <lb/>Bladder, and the Diſcharge from the Wound, <lb/>will flow into the Cavity of the <hi
          rend="italic">Abdomen</hi> or <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pelvis,</hi> where Corrupting, will
        occaſion ſeveral <lb/>grievous and incurable Symptoms, amongſt <lb/>whom is Dr. <hi
          rend="italic">Drelincount,</hi> &amp;c. who expreſſes <lb/>himſelf thus: </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes"><hi rend="italic">Operatio Franconiana ut inventa eſt
            ſic <lb/>exolevit, quia dum perfunderetur Veſicæ <w part="I">fun-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >dum</w> Urina Effluebat in Abdominis Cavum &amp; <lb/>Mortem inducit,</hi> i. e.</q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes">The <hi rend="italic">Franconian</hi> Section, <hi
            rend="italic">viz.</hi> the high <lb/>Operation, died aſſoon as it was invented;
          <lb/>becauſe when the Fund of the Bladder is <lb/>perforated, the Urine flows into the
          Cavity <lb/>of the Belly and cauſes Death.</q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Secondly,</hi> Others ſay that the Wound being
        <lb/>made in the membranous Part of the Bladder, <lb/>won't heal again, amongſt whom is <hi
          rend="italic">Bar-<lb/>bett,</hi> &amp;c. who has theſe Words: </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_10" n="11"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes"><hi rend="italic">Periculoſa interim &amp; in ſe
            moleſta Operatio <lb/>eſt, &amp; quod ſi Labia Vulneris in Veſia facti <lb/>haud
            uniantur Muſculis Abdominis, exulceratio <lb/>veſicæ ſequitur, magis dolorifica minus <w
              part="I">cura-</w><lb/><w part="F">bilis</w> ipſo Calculo, quæ etiam incommoda <w
              part="I">effe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cerunt</w> quod minus Operationibus aliis haberi
            <lb/>cœperit à practicis veris,</hi> i. e.</q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes">It's a dangerous and in it ſelf a <w part="I"
            >trouble-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſome</w> Operation; and if the Lips of the <lb/>Wound made
          in the Bladder don't unite <lb/>to the Muſcles of the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen,</hi> an
            <w part="I">Ulcera-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of the Bladder will follow, more <w
            part="I">pain-</w><lb/><w part="F">ful</w> and leſs curable than the Stone it ſelf,
          <lb/>which Inconveniencies have made it leſs <lb/>eſteem'd than the other Operations by
          true <lb/>Practitioners.</q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Thirdly,</hi> Mons. <hi rend="italic">Thevinin,</hi> a
        very eminent <lb/>Surgeon, in his Book of Chirurgical <w part="I">Obſer-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >vations</w>, publiſh'd at <hi rend="italic">Paris</hi> in the Year 1669, <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Pag.</hi> 68. gives this Account of it, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes"><hi rend="italic">L'hault appareil qui a eſte
            premierement <w part="I">prati-</w><lb/><w part="F">qué</w> par de Franco n'eſt point en
            uſage à preſent, <lb/>à Cauſe de l'inciſion qui'l oblige de faire au <lb/>fonds &amp;
            corps inferieur de la veſſic qui apporte <lb/>de grand accidens,</hi> i. e.</q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes">The high Operation, firſt practiſd by <hi rend="italic"
            >de <lb/>Franco,</hi> is no more in Uſe, becauſe the <w part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ciſion</w> being made in the Fund and Body <lb/>of the Bladder cauſes great
          Accidents.</q>
      </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_11" n="12"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Fourthly,</hi> Others ſay that the Guts will
        <lb/>burſt out at the Wound, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Thomas Fienus,</hi> in the 70th Page of his Book, <hi
          rend="italic">De præcipuis Artis Chirurgicæ controverſis,</hi> Edit. 1602. gives his
        Opinion of this high Operation, in theſe Words: </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes"><hi rend="italic">Præter hactenus uſitatam Sectionem
            exorcus eſt, Franciſus Rouſettus, qui in Libro ſuo de <lb/>Partu Cæſario ſcribit, videri
            longe <w part="I">ſecurio-</w><lb/><w part="F">rem</w> &amp; faciliorem ſectionis
            rationem futuram, <lb/>ſi Venter aut Abdomen a Latere ſub umbilico <lb/>aperiantur,
            &amp; impoſita per foramen manu <lb/>veſicæ corpus vulneretur &amp; inde calculus <w
              part="I">exi-</w><lb/><w part="F">matur</w>. Sed illa ratio non valet: veſicæ enim
            <lb/>vulnus lethale eſt, &amp; non poteſt conſolidari, &amp; <lb/>quamvis aliquando
            legatur conſolidatum, eſt <lb/>tamen rara avis, &amp; temerarium nimis foret, <lb/>&amp;
            quia illam rationem nemo ſecutus eſt, <lb/>de ea non agimus,</hi> i. e.</q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes">Beſides the common Ways of Cutting, <lb/>there's one
            <hi rend="italic">Fr. Rouſettus,</hi> who affirms in <lb/>his Book of the <hi
            rend="italic">Cæſarian</hi> Birth, that the <lb/>Operation would be ſafer and eaſier, if
          <lb/>we cut through the Belly (a little below <lb/>the Navel, and on one Side) and into
          the <lb/>Bladder, and then extracted the Stone <lb/>through the Wound. But that can't be,
          <lb/>becauſe Wounds of the Bladder are <w part="I">mor-</w><lb/><w part="F">tal</w>, and
          cannot be conſolidated; altho' <lb/>we have ſome Hiſtories of their being cur'd, <pb
            xml:id="page_12" n="13"/><lb/>it's a great Rarity, and therefore it's too <lb/>raſh an
          Undertaking; and becauſe no Body <lb/>practiſes it, I'll ſay no more on't.</q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Anſwer to all which (not to deſcend <lb/>to Particulars) is the
        happy Succeſs of my <lb/>Operation. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The next Queſtion that naturally follows, <lb/>is, What could incite or
        encourage me to <lb/>undertake this high Operation, which thoſe <lb/>that had done it, had
        ſuch an indifferent <w part="I">Opi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nion</w> of, which thoſe eminent
        Authors (juſt <lb/>quoted, and almoſt every one elſe that have <lb/>mention'd it) exclaim'd
        ſo warmly againſt, <lb/>and which, by the common Conſent of <w part="I">Man-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">kind</w>, was deem'd impracticable? </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>To which I anſwer: That it was, firſt, <lb/>becauſe I was fully
        perſwaded that the great <lb/>Danger, Tediouſneſs, and frequent bad <w part="I"
          >Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſequences</w> of the common Operations, were <lb/>entirely owing
        to the Structure of the Parts <lb/>concern'd, which the beſt Operator could <lb/>not avoid,
        if the Stone was of any <w part="I">conſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">derable</w> Bigneſs, or of a
        rugged irregular <lb/>Figure. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Secondly,</hi> Becauſe I was as firmly <w part="I"
          >per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſwaded</w>, that all the Objections made againſt <lb/>the fore
        mention'd Gentlemens Operations, <lb/>(ſo far as they concern mine) were very ill
        <lb/>grounded; which is prov'd by the Succeſs. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_13" n="14"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Two Operations that are only in Uſe <lb/>now amongſt us are, <hi
          rend="italic">Firſt,</hi> That which <w part="I">Sur-</w><lb/><w part="F">geons</w> call
        Cutting on the Staffe, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> When <lb/>a furrow'd Probe is paſs'd
        into the Bladder, <lb/>upon which they afterwards Cut. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The other is call'd cutting on the Gripe, <lb/><hi rend="italic">i.
          e.</hi> When they paſs their Fingers into the <lb/>Fundament, and preſs the Stone
        outwards, <lb/>and then cut upon it. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>In order to explain what I have juſt now <lb/>aſſerted, <hi
          rend="italic">viz.</hi> That the Danger, <w part="I">Tediouſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
        >ness</w>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> of the common Operations, are <lb/>entirely owing
        to the Structure of the Parts <lb/>concern'd. I ſhall firſt deſcribe the Parts
        <lb/>concern'd in each, and then make ſuch <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">cluſions</w>
        as naturally follow therefrom. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Cutting on the Staffe is moſt in Uſe, and <lb/>therefore I ſhall begin
        with it. </p>
      <p rend="italic align-center"><lb/>Parts concern'd in Cutting on the Staffe, or <lb/>Great
        Apparatus. </p>
      <p rend="italic"><lb/>Parts Cut: </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>They cut firſt through the Skin, on one <lb/>ſide of the <hi
          rend="italic">Rapha</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Perinæum.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="2"><lb/>2<hi rend="italic">dly,</hi> Through the <hi rend="italic"
          >Accelerator Muſcle.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="3"><lb/>3<hi rend="italic">dly,</hi> Through the Bulb of the <hi
          rend="italic">Urethra.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="align-center italic"><lb/>Parts that are dilated. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Inciſion being made, opens a Paſſage <lb/>into the membranous Part
        of the <hi rend="italic">Uretha,</hi> at <lb/>the upper-end of which is the <hi
          rend="italic">Sphincter</hi> of <lb/>the Bladder, through both which the <w part="I"
          >Inſtru-</w><pb xml:id="page_14" n="15"/><lb/><w part="F">ments</w> muſt paſs into the
        Bladder, and the <lb/>Stone, tho' enlarg'd by the Thickneſs of the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Forceps,</hi> muſt paſs out. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>They are both apt to be too much dilated <lb/>by a large, and lacerated
        by a rugged Stone. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The membranous <hi rend="italic">Urethra,</hi> is about Two <lb/>Inches
        long, more or leſs, according to the <lb/>Bigneſs of the Perſon. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It's about as big (in a middle-ſiz'd Man) as <lb/>to admit of a Gooſe
        Quill. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It's much longer, and not ſo thick and <lb/>ſtrong, as the <hi
          rend="italic">Urethra</hi> in Women, and <w part="I">conſe-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >quently</w> more liable to be injur'd. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Sphincter</hi> is a few circular Fibres;
        <lb/>which keep the Bladder ſhut, and ſo prevents <lb/>the involuntary Diſcharge of the
        Urine. </p>
      <p rend="italic indent hanging"><lb/>The Genital Parts, which by the Nearneſs of their
        <lb/>Situation are liable to be injur'd, next after the <lb/>foremention'd, are: </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Firſt,</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Veſiculæ
          Seminales,</hi> i. e. the <w part="I">Re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſervatories</w> of the Seed:
        They are ſituate <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F">mediately</w> behind the <hi
          rend="italic">Sphincter,</hi> between the <lb/>Bladder and <hi rend="italic">Rectum,</hi>
        i. e. the ſtraight Gut. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Secondly,</hi> Their <hi rend="italic">Ducts;</hi>
        which paſs from <lb/>them, and open about the Middle of the <lb/>membranous Part of the <hi
          rend="italic">Urethra,</hi> by Two <lb/>Orifices, which are cover'd by a ſort of a
        <lb/>Caruncle, call'd, <hi rend="italic">Caput Gallinaginis,</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
          >Veru-<lb/>montanum;</hi> which ſerves inſtead of <hi rend="italic">Valves,</hi> to
        <lb/>hinder the involuntary emiſſion of the Seed. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_15" n="16"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Thirdly,</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Proſtatæ;</hi>
        which are ſituated a <lb/>Little below the <hi rend="italic">Veſiculæ Seminoles,</hi>
        between <lb/>the membranous <hi rend="italic">Urethra</hi> and ſtraight Gut. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Structure and Situation of the Parts <lb/>being thus ſtated, it will
        not be difficult to <lb/>deduce all die foremention'd Inconveniencies <lb/>from them, <hi
          rend="italic">viz.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Firſt,</hi> The Danger of this Operation (to <lb/>ſay
        no more) will appear from a <w part="I">Computati-</w><lb/><w part="F">on</w> of the Number
        of thoſe that do and do <lb/>not eſcape after it; which is (in general) <w part="I"
          >oc-</w><lb/><w part="F">caſion'd</w> by the Length and Streightneſs of the <lb/>Paſſage
        before deſcrib'd, Figure and Bigneſs <lb/>of the Stones, Force requir'd to extract
        <lb/>them, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> Whence the foremention'd Parts, <hi rend="italic"
          >&amp;c.</hi>
        <lb/>are lacerated and contuſed to too great a Degree, <lb/>and thence exceſſive Pain,
        Hemorrhagy, Loſs <lb/>of Strength, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> too great to be maſter'd. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Secondly,</hi> Every one that has made, or ſeen
        <lb/>any Number of theſe Operations perform'd, <lb/>cannot but be ſenſible of the
        Tediouſneſs of <lb/>them (and conſequently of the Pain the <w part="I">Pa-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">tient</w> muſt needs ſuffer) which is owing to the <lb/>Length and Streightneſs
        of the Paſſage (which <lb/>cannot be alter'd, as is commonly ſuppos'd, <lb/>by enlarging the
        External Orifice,) <w part="I">Num-</w><lb/><w part="F">ber</w>, and Neceſſary Largeneſs of
        the <w part="I">Inſtru-</w><lb/><w part="F">ments</w> uſed; Number, Bigneſs, and Figure of
        <lb/>the Stones, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Thirdly,</hi> The bad Conſequences that <w part="I"
          >fre-</w><lb/><w part="F">quently</w> follow this Operation (in thoſe that <pb
          xml:id="page_16" n="17"/><lb/>eſcape with Life) are, <hi rend="italic">Incontinency of
          Urine, <lb/>Impotency, Fiſtula's, &amp;c.</hi> which every one <lb/>muſt be ſatisfy'd of,
        that have ſeen any <lb/>Number of them: In ſome of whom you'll <lb/>obſerve an <hi
          rend="italic">Incontinency of Urine,</hi> in others <lb/><hi rend="italic">Impotency,</hi>
        in others <hi rend="italic">Fiſtula'</hi>s, in others all of <lb/>them; any one of which is
        very little better <lb/>than the Stone itſelf. </p>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center italic size(1.7)"><lb/>Cauſe of the Incontinency of <lb/>Urine. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It's cauſed when the Sphincter of the <w part="I">Blad-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">der</w> is over-ſtretched by the Bigneſs, or <w part="I">lace-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">rated</w> by the Aſperitys of the Stone; becauſe <lb/>it can never afterwards
          do its Office as before; <lb/>And ſo the Urine flows involuntarily Day <lb/>and Night;
          which keeps them always wet, <lb/>from whence none of the moſt agreeable <lb/>Scents
          ariſe. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center size(1.7) italic"><lb/>Cauſe of the Impotency. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It's occaſion'd by the Laceration of the <lb/>Ducts of the <hi
            rend="italic">Veſiculæ Seminales,</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">Veru-<lb/>montanum;</hi>
          and that by the Bigneſs or <w part="I">Aſpe-</w><lb/><w part="F">ritys</w> of the Stone,
          as before: So when <lb/>the Wound heals, the Ducts, or <hi rend="italic"
            >Verumonta-<lb/>num;</hi> are ſtopp'd by the <hi rend="italic">Callous,</hi> ſo that the
          <lb/>Seed can no more flow into the <hi rend="italic">Urethra.</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <pb xml:id="page_17" n="18"/>
        <head rend="align-center size(1.7) italic"><lb/>Cauſe of Fiſtula's. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe Parts are Membranous, Nervous, or <lb/>Spermatick, as Authors
          call them, and, of <lb/>Courſe, very unapt to heal when wounded, <lb/>lacerated, or
          contuſed; which is alſo <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">creas'd</w> by the conſtant
          Paſſage of the Urine, <lb/>Gravel, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> thro' the Wound, and ſo
          they <lb/>turn fiſtulous; and then all or a great Part <lb/>of the Urine, which ſhould
          paſs thro' the <lb/>Yard, paſſes thro' the Fiſtula left in the <lb/>Wound; whence People
          are made nauſeous <lb/>to themſelves and others. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Great <hi rend="italic">Hildanus, pag.</hi> 733, expreſſes the
          <lb/>Danger of this Operation in theſe Words: </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes"><hi rend="italic">Ingens ac magnus Calculus ut per
              Collum <lb/>Veſicæ extrabatur, propter ejus anguſtiam <lb/>longum requirit tempus,
              interim æger <w part="I">ingen-</w><lb/><w part="F">tibus</w> affligitur Doloribus,
              Veſica, ipſiuſque <lb/>Fibræ dilacerantur, Sanguis copiosè profluit, <lb/>vires
              diſſolvuntur, maximoque cum Cruciatu <lb/>æger vel in ipſa Operatione aut paulò poſt
              <lb/>extinguitur,</hi> i. e.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes">When a large Stone is extracted through <lb/>the Neck
            of the Bladder, becauſe of its <lb/>Streightneſs, it takes up a long Time: In <lb/>the
            mean Time, the Patient ſuffers <w part="I">intole-</w><lb/><w part="F">rable</w> Pain,
            the Bladder and its Fibres are <pb xml:id="page_18" n="19"/><lb/>tore, there's a great
            Flux of Blood, Loſs <lb/>of Strength, and the Patient, by reaſon <lb/>of the great
            Torture, dies, either in or <lb/>ſoon after the Operation.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The late Mr. <hi rend="italic">Couper,</hi> in his Comment upon
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Bidloo,</hi> has the following Obſervations on <lb/>the Accidents
          which happen from the <w part="I">Stru-</w><lb/><w part="F">cture</w> of the Parts. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes">This Part of the <hi rend="italic">Urethra, viz.</hi>
            that <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">tween</w> the <hi rend="italic">Proſtatæ</hi>
            and the <hi rend="italic">Bulb,</hi> is liable <lb/>to be wounded, and ſometimes
            perforated, <lb/>by too haſtily introducing the Conductor <lb/>into the Bladder, after
            an Inciſion is made <lb/>in the <hi rend="italic">Perinæum</hi> in Cutting for the
            Stone; <lb/>whereby the Operator afterwards thruſts <lb/>his <hi rend="italic"
              >Forceps</hi> between the Bladder and <hi rend="italic">Re-<lb/>ctum.</hi></q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes">This Inadvertency, I'm perſuaded, is <lb/>very often
            practiſed by the Pretenders to <lb/><hi rend="italic">Lithotomy,</hi> and frequently
            proves fatal to <lb/>the Patient: One would think it hardly <lb/>poſſible, that a Man in
            his Senſes, and <lb/>but tolerably acquainted with Anatomy, <lb/>could commit ſuch
            Errors; yet, of this I <lb/>have met with more than one Inſtance, <lb/>when being called
            to diſſect the Deceaſed, <lb/>in whom ſuch Operators have been ſo <w part="I"
              >un-</w><lb/><w part="F">fortunate</w> as to leave the Stone ſtill in the
            <lb/>Bladder.</q>
        </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_19" n="20"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>So much to ſhew the unavoidable Danger, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >&amp;c.</hi> of Cutting on the <hi rend="italic">Staffe.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The other Operation in uſe is Cutting on <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
            >Gripe.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Parts cut. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>They cut (farther off of the <hi rend="italic">Rapha</hi> of the
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Perinæum</hi> than in the foregoing Operation) <lb/>1. Through
          the Skin: 2. The Fat: 3. Part <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Erector Penis:</hi> 4. Some
          confiderable <lb/>Blood-Veſſels: 5. A Part of the <hi rend="italic">Levator Ani:</hi>
          <lb/>6. Into the Body of the Bladder above the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Sphincter.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This Operation can't always be practis'd, <lb/>becauſe our Fingers are
          not long enough to <lb/>bring down and keep the Stone faſt againſt <lb/>the <hi
            rend="italic">Perinæum</hi> in grown People. Though, <lb/>when it can be done, </p>
        <p rend="italic align-center"><lb/>The Inconveniencies of it are, </p>
        <list rend="indent">
          <lb/>
          <item>1. When the Stone is rough, it's <w part="I">trouble-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſome</w>,
            painful, and tedious, to make the <w part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F">ciſion</w> on it. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>2. The Arteries, which are cut, are often <lb/>very large. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>3. When the Stone is rough, it pricks, and <lb/>contuſes the Bladder in ſeveral
            Places, by <lb/>being preſſed hard againſt the <hi rend="italic">Perinæum;</hi>
            <lb/>whence ſeveral dangerous and deadly <w part="I">Symp-</w><lb/><w part="F">toms</w>
            enſue. </item>
          <pb xml:id="page_20" n="21"/>
          <lb/>
          <item>4. The Wound in the Bladder being <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">pending</w>,
            is hinder'd from aglutinating, by <lb/>the Gravel and Urine paſſing thro' it, <hi
              rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
          </item>
        </list>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>From all which, I think 'tis evident, that <lb/>the rare Succeſs of
          theſe Operations, even <lb/>in the beſt of Hands, (not to mention the <lb/>Havock that is
          often made by Pretenders) is <lb/>entirely owing to the Structure of the Parts
          <lb/>concern'd; which is what I undertook to <lb/>prove. </p>
        <p rend="italic align-center"><lb/>Advantages of this new Operation. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Whereas, in the other Operations, the <lb/>Danger, <hi rend="italic"
            >&amp;c.</hi> are owing to the Structure of <lb/>the Parts; in my Operation, by reaſon
          of <lb/>the Structure of the Parts, they are <w part="I">ſucceſſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >fully</w> prevented. <hi rend="italic">E. G.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="1"><lb/>1. There can be no Impotency cauſed by <lb/>it, becauſe there's
          none of the Genital Parts <lb/>can be injur'd in doing it. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="2"><lb/>2. There can be no Incontinency of Urine <lb/>caus'd by it,
          becauſe the <hi rend="italic">Sphincter</hi> of the <lb/>Bladder cannot be hurt in making
          it. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="3"><lb/>3. There can be no Fiſtula after it, if <w part="I"
            >pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">per</w> Care is taken of the Wound. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="4"><lb/>4. There can be no ſuch Force requir'd to <lb/>extract the
          Stone, as will contuſe and <w part="I">lace-</w><lb/><w part="F">rate</w> the Parts,
          which, in the other <w part="I">Opera-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w>, are the Cauſe of
          Symptoms too hard <lb/>to be govern'd) becauſe the Wound may be <pb xml:id="page_21"
            n="22"/><lb/>made as large as you pleaſe, which can't be <lb/>done in them. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="5"><lb/>5. There can't be any Flux of Blood, <lb/>becauſe there's no
          Occaſion to cut any of <lb/>the great Veſſels, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> Thus the
          Defects of <lb/>the others are ſupply'd by this. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>My Patient was between ſixteen and <w part="I">ſe-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >venteen</w> Years of Age, and was cut two <lb/>Days before laſt <hi rend="italic"
            >Chriſtmas,</hi> and in a Month's <lb/>Time the Wound was perfectly cicatriz'd, <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">i.e.</hi> healed. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Operation was over in one Minute, <lb/>and I believe will never be
          above two. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>He now performs all his natural Faculties <lb/>as well as he had never
          been troubled with <lb/>the Stone. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>There were two Phyſicians, two Surgeons, <lb/>and an Apothecary,
          preſent at the <w part="I">Opera-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>: But to ſave them the
          Trouble of <w part="I">an-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſwering</w> every little Prig's impertinent
            <w part="I">Que-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtions</w>, I don't think it's proper to mention
          <lb/>them. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Stone was of the Bigneſs and Figure <lb/>expreſs'd in the Plate
          following. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_22" n="23"/>
        <figure>
          <lb/>
          <figDesc>a bladder stone</figDesc>
          <head rend="align-center italic"><lb/>The Natural Figure &amp; Bigneſs of ye ſtone </head>
        </figure>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Some ſay that I have robb'd the Dead of <lb/>their Right, and
          endeavour'd to impoſe on <lb/>the Living, by putting my own Name to <lb/>another Man's
          Work, and pretending that <lb/>it's a new Operation, though, at the ſame <lb/>Time, it was
          practis'd by its firſt Inventor, <lb/><hi rend="italic">De Franco,</hi> above 150 Years
          ago. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_23" n="24"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">De Franco</hi> (whoſe Memory I reverence,
          <lb/>becauſe he was certainly an excellent <w part="I">Sur-</w><lb/><w part="F">geon</w>,
          and one of the beſt <hi rend="italic">Lithotomiſts</hi> in his <lb/>Time) is ſo far from
          valuing himſelf upon <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">High Operation,</hi> which he was once
          forc'd <lb/>to make, that he owns himſelf to be very <lb/>much to blame for doing of it;
          and deſires <lb/>no Man afterwards to follow his Example; <lb/>and in the Room of that, in
          the preceding <lb/>Part of that very ſame Chapter, <w part="I">recom-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >mends</w> another which is made on the <hi rend="italic">Peri-<lb/>næum,</hi> which he
          aſſumes, and, with a great <lb/>deal of Pleaſure, calls his own Invention. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Hildanus</hi> is alſo of the ſame Opinion, and
          <lb/>expreſſes himſelf thus, <hi rend="italic">Pag.</hi> 730. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes"><hi rend="italic">De quarto operandi modo, in</hi>
            Lithotomia <lb/><hi rend="italic">uſitato, qui merito</hi> Lithotomia Franconiana
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">appellari poteſt.</hi></q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And ſo he goes on to deſcribe and <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >commend</w> that Operation, which <hi rend="italic">De Franco</hi>
          <lb/>owns in the 33d Chapter of his Book, to be <lb/>his proper Invention: But it's not
          the <hi rend="italic">High,</hi>
          <lb/>but an Operation in the <hi rend="italic">Perinæum,</hi> that's <w part="I"
            >aſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſum'd</w> by the one, and commended by the <lb/>other. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In Page 732, he has theſe Words: </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes">Franciſcus Rouſettus <hi rend="italic">Lib. de
              partu</hi>
            <w part="I">Cæſa-</w><lb/><w part="F">rio</w>
            <hi rend="italic">concludere voluit, ſemper calculum eo in <pb xml:id="page_24" n="25"
              /><lb/>Loco exſecandum eſſe, illudque minori cum <w part="I">pe-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >riculo</w> fieri poſſe.</hi> Lithotomiam <hi rend="italic">proinde illam</hi>
            <lb/>Franconianam <hi rend="italic">vocat, cum tamen D.</hi> Franc. <lb/><hi
              rend="italic">eam minimè ad Imitationem præſcripſerit, <lb/>ſed expressè in Libro ſuo,
              ſe ſtolide egiſſe <lb/>fateatur, adeoque unumquemque, ne ipſum hac <lb/>in parte
              imitetur, ſed precedentem operandi <lb/>modum amplectatur, Hortetur.</hi></q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes"><hi rend="italic">Franciſcus Rouſettus,</hi> in his
            Book on the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cæſarian</hi> Birth, aſſerts, that we ought <w
              part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">ways</w> to cut for the Stone through the <lb/>lower
            Part of the Belly, becauſe it can be <lb/>done with a great deal leſs Danger; and
            <lb/>then calls it <hi rend="italic">De Franco</hi>'s Method, <w part="I"
              >notwith-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtanding</w>
            <hi rend="italic">De Franco</hi> never preſcrib'd it as a <lb/>Rule; ſo far from which,
            he confeſſes in <lb/>his own Book, that he acted fooliſhly in <lb/>doing it; and
            therefore adviſes us never <lb/>to imitate him in it, but in the Operation <lb/>juſt
            before deſcrib'd.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>He concludes his Story thus: </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes"><hi rend="italic">Cum dicto igitur D.</hi> Franco,
              <hi rend="italic">fideli atque <lb/>induſtrio cuivis Chirurgo periculoſæ hujus</hi>
            <lb/>Lithotomiæ <hi rend="italic">Adminiſtrationem iterum atque <lb/>iterum
              diſſuadeo.</hi></q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><q rend="quotes">Therefore, with the foremention'd <hi rend="italic"
              >De <lb/>Franco,</hi> I again and again diſſuade every <lb/>faithful and induſtrious
            Surgeon from <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">forming</w> this dangerous
            Operation.</q>
        </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_25" n="26"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>From all which I conclude, that inſtead of <lb/>being an Honour to <hi
            rend="italic">De Franco,</hi> to have had <lb/>his Name put to it, it would have been a
          <lb/>real Injury to the Memory of the Dead, to <lb/>have made him the Author of an
          Operation, <lb/>that he blam'd himſelf for doing when <lb/>alive. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nay, I'm ſo far from having an Opinion <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">De
            Franco</hi>'s Operation, as he has deſcrib'd <lb/>it, that I think it's fully as
          inconſiſtent and <lb/>impracticable as <hi rend="italic">Talicotius</hi>'s Project of <w
            part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtoring</w> loſt Noſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>All the Analogy between his and mine, <lb/>is, that they are both made
          in the Belly. <lb/>But his was made in one Place of the <lb/>Belly, and mine in another:
          His, with his <lb/>own Inſtruments, (which he has not <w part="I">men-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tion'd)</w> mine with mine: His were uſed <w part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w>
          one Manner, mine after another: And <lb/>thoſe, I think, are the moſt material <w part="I"
            >Diffe-</w><lb/><w part="F">rences</w> betwixt any two Operations, <hi rend="italic"
            >viz.</hi> The <lb/>Variation of the Place upon which the <w part="I">Ope-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ration</w> is made, of the Number, Figure, and <lb/>Size of the Inſtruments,
          and of the Method <lb/>of uſing them. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The two foremention'd Operations, call'd, <lb/>Cutting on the <hi
            rend="italic">Staffe,</hi> and Cutting on the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Gripe,</hi> are
          both made on the <hi rend="italic">Perinæum:</hi> The <lb/>Deſign of both is the ſame, <hi
            rend="italic">viz.</hi> To extract <pb xml:id="page_26" n="27"/><lb/>the Stone out of
          the Bladder; yet no Man <lb/>ever was ſo abſurd as to call them both the <lb/>ſame
          Operations, for the Reaſons <w part="I">before-</w><lb/><w part="F">mention'd</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The late famous Mr. <hi rend="italic">Rau,</hi> Profeſſor of
          <lb/>Phyſick and Surgery at <hi rend="italic">Leyden,</hi> and the <w part="I"
            >fore-</w><lb/><w part="F">mention'd</w>
          <hi rend="italic">De Franco,</hi> and ſeveral others, as <lb/><hi rend="italic">Celſus,
            Guido, Marianus, &amp;c.</hi> had each a <w part="I">par-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ticular</w> Method of Cutting on the <hi rend="italic">Perinæum,</hi>
          <lb/>to which every one gave his own Name, <lb/>and why ſhould not I be allow'd the ſame
          <lb/>Liberty. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But ſuppoſing that my Operation was, in <lb/>every Tittle, the ſame as
            <hi rend="italic">De Franco</hi>'s; yet, <lb/>if it's found to be a ſafer and eaſier Way
          of <lb/>relieving the Miſerable, it's nevertheleſs <lb/>new; for that Operation was as
          much dead, <lb/>before mine, and thought as much <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >practicable</w>, (which the general Opinion <lb/>of the Town on this Occaſion
          abundantly <lb/>proves) as it was 150 Years before <hi rend="italic">De Franco</hi>
          <lb/>was born. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I readily grant, that one Operation, tho' <lb/>ſucceſſfully perform'd,
          is not enough to <w part="I">ſa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tisfy</w> the Publick that it's the
          ſafeſt Method; <lb/>but it's enough to me, who, before the <w part="I">Ope-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ration</w>, thought myſelf very ſure of Succeſs, <lb/>elſe I had never
          attempted it. But now I <lb/>have perform'd it, and ſeen the whole <w part="I"
            >Pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">cess</w> of the Cure, I'm in no manner of Pain <pb
            xml:id="page_27" n="28"/><lb/>about the future Succeſs of if; nay, I dare <lb/>venture
          to prophecy, that not one in ten will <lb/>die, nor one in fifty want a perfect Cure, that
          <lb/>do after the common Methods; and there <lb/>fore do (what never any did before) <w
            part="I">recom-</w><lb/><w part="F">mend</w> it as the moſt eaſy ſafe, and ſpeedy
          <lb/>Method of extracting the Stone, (excluſive <lb/>of all others) in Males, and when the
          Stone <lb/>is large, in Females. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I have had a great many vile, malicious <lb/>and ſalfe Reflections
          caſt upon me, on this <lb/>Occaſion, by a Set of <hi rend="italic">Scioli,</hi> who
          (becauſe <lb/>they never did anything out of the common <lb/>Road themſelves) envy every
          Man elſe that <lb/>does. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Imputation of Novelty (ſays the great <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Lock</hi>) is a terrible Charge among thoſe <lb/>who judge of Mens Heads, as they do of
          <lb/>their Perukes, by the Faſhion, and can allow <lb/>none to be right but the receiv'd
          Doctrines. <lb/>Truth ſcarce ever carry'd it by Vote any <lb/>where at its firſt
          Appearance: New <w part="I">Opi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nions</w> are always ſuſpected, and
          uſually <w part="I">op-</w><lb/><w part="F">pos'd</w>, without any other Reaſon, but <w
            part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">cauſe</w> they are not already common: But <lb/>Truth,
          like Gold, is not the leſs ſo, for <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> newly
          brought out of the Mine. </p>
        <lb/>
        <q rend="italic align-center">Magna eſt Veritas, &amp; prevalebit.</q>
      </div>
      <trailer rend="italic align-center size(1.7)"><lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_28"/>
        <head rend="dc(2) align-center"><lb/>INDEX. </head>
        <list rend="indent hanging italic">
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="dc(2)">P</hi>LACE where this new Operation is <lb/>made <hi rend="roman"
              >Page 3</hi>
          </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>An Account of three Surgeons that have <lb/>made the <hi rend="roman">High Operation
              P.4</hi>
          </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>The Opinions of ſome of the moſt eminent <lb/>Authors about it <hi rend="roman">P.
              10</hi>
          </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>Remarks on the two Operations now in Uſe, <lb/><hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> Cutting
            on the <hi rend="roman">Staffe,</hi> and Cutting on <lb/>the <hi rend="roman"
              >Gripe;</hi> whereby their Inconveniencies <lb/>are explain'd <hi rend="roman">P.
              14</hi>
          </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>The Advantages of the New Way explain'd <hi rend="roman">P. 21</hi>
          </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>The common Objection, <hi rend="roman">viz.</hi> That this is not <lb/>mine but <hi
              rend="roman">De Franco</hi>'s Operation, fully <lb/>anſwer'd, <hi rend="roman">&amp;c.
              &amp;c. P. 23</hi>
          </item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic size(1.7) align-center"><lb/>Advertiſement. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N a ſhort Time will be publiſh'd, <hi
            rend="italic">Anato-<lb/>mia Chirurgo Neceſſaria:</hi> Or, a Deſcription <lb/>of all
          thoſe Parts of Anatomy, that are <w part="I">abſo-</w><lb/><w part="F">lutely</w>
          neceſſary to be well underſtood by <w part="I">Sur-</w><lb/><w part="F">geons</w>, with
          their practical Uſes, as mention'd <lb/>in my printed <hi rend="italic">Syllabus.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>For the Uſe of Students of Surgery. </p>
        <lb/>
        <q rend="italic">Qui fructuoſa non qui multa ſoit ſapit.</q>
        <p rend="align-center"><lb/>Printed for <hi rend="italic">Tho. Woodward.</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_29"/>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">BOOKS printed for</hi> Tho. Woodward
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">near</hi> Temple Bar. </head>
        <p rend="indent" n="1"><lb/>1. <hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">Syllabus</hi> of what is to be perform'd in <lb/>a Courſe of Anatomy,
          Chirurgical <w part="I">O-</w><lb/><w part="F">perations</w> and Bandages. By <hi
            rend="italic">John Douglas,</hi>
          <lb/>Surgeon. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="2"><lb/>2. General Obſervations and Preſcriptions <lb/>in the Practice
          of Phyſick, on ſeveral Perſons <lb/>of Quality, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> by an
          eminent <hi rend="italic">London</hi>
          <w part="I">Phy-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſician</w>, who was Contemporary with Dr. <hi
            rend="italic">Gif-<lb/>ford,</hi> Dr. <hi rend="italic">Ridgley,</hi> Dr. <hi
            rend="italic">Meveral,</hi> Dr. <hi rend="italic">Andrews,</hi>
          <lb/>and Sir <hi rend="italic">Theodore Mayerne,</hi> Phyſicians in <w part="I"
            >Or-</w><lb/><w part="F">dinary</w> to King <hi rend="italic">James,</hi> and King <hi
            rend="italic">Charles the <lb/>Firſt.</hi> Inſcrib'd to Sir <hi rend="italic">Samuel
            Garth,</hi> Kt. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="3"><lb/>3. A. ſhort and eaſy Method to underſtand <lb/>Geography;
          wherein are deſcrib'd, the Form <lb/>of Government of each Country, its <w part="I"
            >Qua-</w><lb/><w part="F">lities</w>, the Manners of its Inhabitants, and
          <lb/>whatſoever is moſt remarkable in it. To <lb/>which are added, Obſervations upon thoſe
          <lb/>Things of Importance that have happen'd <lb/>in each State. With an Abridgement of
          the <lb/>Sphere, and the Uſe of Geographical Maps. <lb/>Made <hi rend="italic"
            >Engliſh</hi> by a Gentleman of <hi rend="italic">Cambridge,</hi>
          <lb/>from the <hi rend="italic">French</hi> of Mr. <hi rend="italic">A.D. Fer,</hi>
          <w part="I">Geogra-</w><lb/><w part="F">pher</w> to the <hi rend="italic">French</hi>
          King. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_30"/>
        <p rend="indent" n="4"><lb/>4. Mathematical Elements of Phyſicks <lb/>prov'd by Experiments;
          being an <w part="I">Intro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duction</w> to Sir <hi rend="italic">Iſaac
            Newton</hi>'s Philoſophy. <lb/>By Dr. <hi rend="italic">William James Graveſande,</hi>
          <w part="I">Profeſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſor</w> of Mathematicks and Aſtronomy in the
          <lb/>Univerſity of <hi rend="italic">Leyden,</hi> and Fellow of the <lb/>Royal Society of
            <hi rend="italic">London.</hi> Made <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi> and <lb/>illuſtrated
          with 33 Copper Plates, revis'd <lb/>and corrected by Dr. <hi rend="italic">John Keil,
            F.R.S.</hi>
          <w part="I">Pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">feſſor</w> of Aſtronomy in <hi rend="italic"
            >Oxford.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="5"><lb/>5. <hi rend="italic">Chriſtiani Hugenii Libellus de Ratiociniis
            <lb/>in Ludo Aleæ:</hi> Or, the Value of all Chances <lb/>in Games of Fortune, Cards,
          Dice, Wagers, <lb/>Lotteries, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> Mathematically demonſtrated.
          <lb/>Price 1 <hi rend="italic">s.</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
    </back>



  </text>
</TEI>
