<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title> LMEMT Corpus - Sharp: A treatise on the operations of surgery</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Compiler</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="IT">
                        <forename>Irma</forename>
                        <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="TH">
                        <forename>Turo</forename>
                        <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ALe">
                        <forename>Anu</forename>
                        <surname>Lehto</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="VM">
                        <forename>Ville</forename>
                        <surname>Marttila</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="RO">
                        <forename>Raisa</forename>
                        <surname>Oinonen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="PP">
                        <forename>Päivi</forename>
                        <surname>Pahta</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="MR">
                        <forename>Maura</forename>
                        <surname>Ratia</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="CS">
                        <forename>Carla</forename>
                        <surname>Suhr</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="JT">
                        <forename>Jukka</forename>
                        <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="WA">
                        <forename>Wilma</forename>
                        <surname>Andersson</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="EC">
                        <forename>Emanuela</forename>
                        <surname>Costea</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="DV">
                        <forename>Diana</forename>
                        <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="SK">
                        <forename>Sami</forename>
                        <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="MK">
                        <forename>Mirella</forename>
                        <surname>Klinga</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="SKo">
                        <forename>Sami</forename>
                        <surname>Koskinen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ALi">
                        <forename>Aatu</forename>
                        <surname>Liimatta</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="HR">
                        <forename>Heikki</forename>
                        <surname>Rajala</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="JR">
                        <forename>Jenni</forename>
                        <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="AW">
                        <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
                        <surname>Walraff</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>
                    <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
                </sponsor>
                <funder>
                    <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
                    <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
                </funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                <date>forthcoming</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName>Samuel Sharp</persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">A treatise on the operations of surgery, with a
                            description and representation of the instruments used in performing
                            them: To which is Prefix'd an Introduction on the Nature and Treatment
                            of Wounds, Abscesses and Ulcers. By Samuel Sharp, Surgeon to Guy's
                            Hospital.</title>
                        <edition n=""/>
                        <idno type="ESTC">T101089</idno>
                        <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T101089"/>
                        <imprint>
                            <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName>London</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>
                                <persName>London: printed by J. Watts: and sold by J. Roberts in
                                    Warwick-Lane, and J. Brotherton in Cornhill,
                                    MDCCXXXIX.</persName>
                            </publisher>
                            <date>1739</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <extent>
                            <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
                            <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="69"/>
                            <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="224"/>
                            <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
                        </extent>
                    </monogr>
                    <note type="source_copy">
                        <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
                        <idno type="ECCO">CW108168868</idno>
                    </note>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef n="Surgical or anatominal work"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
        <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="69"/>
        <body>
            <pb/>
            <figure>
                <lb/>
                <figDesc>A rectangular decorative figure, six lines in height.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <lb/>
            <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"/>
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">TREATISE</hi>
                <lb/><space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"/>
                <lb/><hi rend="size(0.75)">OF THE</hi>
                <lb/><space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"/>
                <lb/><hi rend="size(1.75)">Operations <hi rend="italic">of SURGERY</hi></hi>. </head>
            <figure rend="space">
                <lb/>
                <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head rend="space align-center size(1.25)"><lb/>CHAP. I. <lb/><space dim="vertical"
                        unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
                    <lb/><hi rend="italic">Of SUTURES</hi>. </head>
                <p rend="space"><lb/><figure>
                        <figDesc>A decorative frame around the letter "W", five lines in
                            height.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <hi rend="dc(5)">W</hi>HEN a Wound is recent, <lb/>and the Parts of it are <w
                        part="I">divid-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> by a ſharp Inſtrument,
                    <lb/>without any farther Violence, <lb/>and in ſuch a manner that they <lb/>may
                    be made to approach <lb/>each other, by being returned with the Hands <lb/>they
                    will, if held in cloſe Contact for ſome <lb/>time, re-unite by Inoſculation, and
                    cement <pb n="2"/><lb/>like one Branch of a Tree ingrafted on another. <lb/>To
                    maintain them in this ſituation, ſeveral <lb/>ſorts of Sutures have been
                    invented, and <w part="I">for-</w><lb/><w part="F">merly</w> practis'd, but the
                    number of them has of <lb/>late been very much reduced. Thoſe now <w part="I"
                        >chief-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> deſcribed, are the Interrupted, the
                    Glover's, <lb/>the quill'd, the twiſted, and the dry <lb/>Sutures, but the
                    interrupted and twiſted, are almoſt the <lb/>only uſeful one's; for the quill'd
                    Suture is never <lb/>preferable to the interrupted; the dry Suture <lb/>is
                    ridiculous in terms, ſince it is only a piece <lb/>of Plaiſter apply'd in many
                    different ways to <lb/>re-unite the Lips of a Wound; and the Glover's, <lb/>or
                    uninterrupted Stitch, which is recommended <lb/>in ſuperficial Wounds to prevent
                    the <w part="I">defor-</w><lb/><w part="F">mity</w> of a Scar, does rather by
                    the frequency <lb/>of the Stitches occaſion it, and is therefore to <lb/>be
                    rejected in favour of a Compreſs and <w part="I">ſtick</w><lb/><w part="F"
                        >ing</w> Plaiſter; the only Inſtance where I would <lb/>recommend it, is in
                    a Wound of the Inteſtine: <lb/>the manner of making this Suture I ſhall <w
                        part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="I">ſcribe</w> in the Chapter of the
                    Gaſtroraphy.</p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">From</hi> the Deſcription I have given of the
                    <lb/>ſtate of a Wound proper to be ſewed up, it <lb/>may be readily conceived,
                    that Wounds are <lb/>not fit ſubjects for Suture when there is either <lb/>a
                    Contuſion, Laceration, loſs of Subſtance, great <lb/>Inflammation, difficulty of
                    bringing the Lips <pb n="3"/><lb/>into appoſition, or ſome extraneous Body <w
                        part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſinuated</w> into them; though ſometimes a
                        <w part="I">lace-</w><lb/><w part="F">rated</w> Wound may be aſſiſted with
                    one or <lb/>two Stitches. It has formerly been forbidden to <lb/>ſew up Wounds
                    of the Head; but this Rule is <lb/>very little regarded by the Moderns, though
                    <lb/>the ill effects I have frequently ſeen from <lb/>Matter pent up under the
                    Scalp, and the great <lb/>convenience there is of uſing Bandage on the
                    <lb/>Head, have convinc'd me that much leſs <lb/>harm would be done, if Sutures
                    were us'd in <lb/>this Part with more caution.</p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">If</hi> we ſtitch up a Wound that has none of
                    <lb/>theſe Obſtacles, we always employ the <w part="I">inter-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">rupted</w> Suture, paſſing the Needle two, three, <lb/>or four
                    times, in proportion to the length of <lb/>it, though there can ſeldom be more
                    than <lb/>three Stitches required.</p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> method of doing it is this, the Wound
                    <lb/>being emptied of the grumous Blood, and <lb/>your Aſſiſtant having brought
                    the Lips of it <lb/>together, that they may lie quite even; you <lb/>carefully
                    carry your Needle from without, <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">wards</w> to
                    the bottom, and ſo on from within, <lb/>outwards; uſing the Caution of making
                    the <lb/>Puncture far enough from the edge of the <lb/>Wound, leſt the Ligature
                    ſhould tear quite <lb/>through the Skin and Flesh; this diſtance may <pb n="4"
                    /><lb/>be three or four tenths of an Inch: as many <lb/>more Stitches as you
                    ſhall make, will be only <lb/>repetitions of the same Proceſs. The Threads
                    <lb/>being all paſſed, you begin tying them in the <lb/>Middle of the Wound,
                    though if the Lips are <lb/>held carefully together all the while, as they
                    <lb/>ſhould be, it will be of no great conſequence <lb/>which is done firſt. The
                    moſt uſeful kind of <lb/>Knot in large Wounds is a ſingle one firſt, <lb/>over
                    this a little linnen Compreſs, on which is <lb/>to be made another ſingle Knot,
                    and then a <lb/>Slip-knot, which may be looſened upon any <lb/>Inflammation; but
                    in ſmall Wounds there is <lb/>no danger from the double Knot alone, <w part="I"
                        >with-</w><lb/><w part="F">out</w> any Compreſs to tie it upon, and this is
                    <lb/>moſt generally practis'd. If an Inflammation <lb/>ſhould ſucceed to any
                    degree, looſening the <lb/>Ligature only will not ſuffice, it muſt be cut
                    <lb/>through and drawn away, and the Wound be <lb/>treated afterwards without
                    any farther Suture. <lb/>When the Wound is ſmall, the leſs it is <w part="I"
                        >di-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſturbed</w> by dreſſing, the better, but in large
                    <lb/>ones there will ſometimes be a conſiderable <lb/>Diſcharge, and if the
                    Threads are not <w part="I">cauti-</w><lb/><w part="F">ouſly</w> carried through
                    the bottom of it, <w part="I">Ab-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſceſſes</w> will
                    frequently enſue from the Matter <lb/>being pent up underneath, and not finding
                    <lb/>iſſue. If no accident happens you muſt, after <pb n="5"/><lb/>the Lips are
                    firmly agglutinated, take away <lb/>the Ligatures, and dreſs the Orifices they
                    <lb/>leave, ſuperficially. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> mſst be remembered that during the Cure,
                    the Suture must be always assisted by the Application of <lb/>Cure, the Suture
                    muſt be alwyas aſſiſted by the <lb/>application of of Bandage if poſſible, which
                    is <lb/>frequently of the greateſt Importance, and <lb/>that ſort of Bandage
                    with two Heads, and a <lb/>ſlit in the middle, which is by much the beſt,
                    <lb/>will in moſt caſes be found practicable. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> twiſted Suture being principally <w
                        part="I">em-</w><lb/><w part="F">ployed</w> in the Hare-lip, I ſhall reſerve
                    its <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſcription</w> for the Chapter on that
                    Head. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <figure rend="space">
                    <lb/>
                    <figDesc>A decorative horizontal line, spanning the whole page.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <head rend="space align-center size(1.25)"><lb/>CHAP. II. <lb/><space dim="vertical"
                        unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
                    <lb/><hi rend="italic">Of the <hi rend="roman sc">Suture</hi> of <hi
                            rend="roman sc">Tendonds</hi></hi>. </head>
                <p rend="space"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">W</hi>OUNDS of the Tendons are not only
                    <lb/>known to heal again, but even to admit of <lb/>ſewing up like thoſe of the
                    fleſhy parts, though <lb/>they do not re-unite altogether in ſo ſhort a
                    <lb/>time. When a Tendon is partly divided, it is <lb/>generally attended with
                    an exceſſive Pain, <w part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F">flammation</w>, <hi
                        rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> in conſequence of the <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">maining</w> Fibres being ſtretch'd and forced by <lb/>the action of
                    the Muſcle, which neceſſarily <pb n="6"/><lb/>will contract more, when ſome of
                    its <w part="I">reſiſt-</w><lb/><w part="F">ance</w> is taken away: To obviate
                    this miſchief, <lb/>it has been hitherto an indiſputable Maxim in <lb/>Surgery,
                    to cut the Tendon quite through, <lb/>and immediately afterwards perform the <w
                        part="I">Su-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w>; but I do not think this Practice
                        <w part="I">adviſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">able</w>; for though the diviſion of
                    the Tendon <lb/>affords preſent eaſe, yet the Flexion only of <lb/>the Joint
                    will have the ſame effect, if it be a <lb/>Wound of a Flexor Tendon: Beſides, in
                        <w part="I">or-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w> to ſew up the extremities of the
                    Tendon <lb/>when divided, we are obliged to put the Limb <lb/>in ſuch a
                    ſituation, that they may lap one <lb/>over the other, and even to ſuſtain it in
                    that <lb/>posture to the finiſhing of the Cure: If then <lb/>the poſture will
                    lay the Tendon in this <w part="I">poſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, we can
                    likewiſe keep it ſo without uſing <lb/>the Suture, and are more ſure of its not
                        <w part="I">ſlip-</w><lb/><w part="F">ping</w> away, which ſometimes happens
                    from any <lb/>careleſs motion of the Joint, when the Stitches <lb/>have almoſt
                    wore through the Lips of the <lb/>Wound; on which account I would by all
                    <lb/>means adviſe in this caſe, to forbear the <w part="I">Su-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">ture</w>, and only favour the ſituation of the <w part="I"
                        >ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">tremities</w> of the Tendon. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">If</hi> it ſhould be ſuggested that for want of
                    <lb/>a farther ſeparation, there will not be <w part="I">Inflam-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">mation</w> enough to produce an Adheſion of <pb n="7"/><lb/>the
                    ſeveral parts of the Wound, which is <lb/>particularly mention'd as the Property
                    of this <lb/>ſort of Cicatrix, though it is likewiſe of all <lb/>others: I ſay,
                    that the Inflammation will be <lb/>in proportion to the Wound, and a ſmall
                    <lb/>Wound is certainly more likely to recover than <lb/>a large one. If it
                    ſhould be objected that <lb/>keeping the Limb in one poſture the whole <lb/>time
                    of the Cure, will bring on a Contraction <lb/>of the Joint, the Objection is as
                    ſtrong againſt <lb/>the Suture; and now I am upon this Subject, <lb/>I would
                    adviſe Surgeons to be leſs <w part="I">apprehen-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſive</w> of
                    Contractions after Inflammations of <lb/>the Tendons, than Practice ſhews they
                    are: <lb/>For perhaps there is hardly any one Rule has <lb/>done more miſchief
                    than that of guarding <lb/>againſt this Conſequence, and I would lay it
                    <lb/>down as a method to be purſued at all <lb/>times, to favour the Joint in
                    theſe <w part="I">Diſor-</w><lb/><w part="F">ders</w>, and keep it in that
                    poſture we find <lb/>moſt eaſy for the Patient. The riſque of an <lb/>immoveable
                    Contraction in ſix weeks is very <lb/>little, but the endeavour to avoid it has
                    been <lb/>the loſs of many a Limb in half the time. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> when the Tendon is quite ſeparated,
                    <lb/>and the ends are withdrawn from one another, <lb/>having brought them
                    together with your <w part="I">Fin-</w><lb/><w part="F">gers</w>, you may ſew
                    them with a ſtrait <w part="I">trian-</w><pb n="8"/><lb/><w part="F">gular</w>
                    pointed Needle, paſſing it from without <lb/>inwards, and from within outwards,
                    in a <lb/>ſmall Tendon, about three tenths of an Inch <lb/>from their
                    extremities, and in the <hi rend="italic">Tendo <w part="I">Achil-</w><lb/><w
                            part="F">lis</w></hi> near half an Inch. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Some</hi> Surgeons, for fear the Muſcle ſhould
                    <lb/>contract a little, notwithſtanding all our care, <lb/>adviſe not to bring
                    the ends of the Tendon <lb/>into an exact Appoſition, but to lay one a <w
                        part="I">lit-</w><lb/><w part="F">tle</w> over the other, which allowing for
                    the <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">traction</w> that always enſues in ſome
                    degree, <lb/>the Tendon will become a ſtrait Line, and <lb/>not be ſhorten'd in
                    its length. As the Wound <lb/>of the Skin will be nearly tranverſe I would
                    <lb/>not have it rais'd to expoſe more of the <w part="I">Ten-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">don</w>, but rather ſew'd up with it, which will <lb/>conduce to
                    the ſtrength of the Suture. The <lb/>Knot of the Ligature is to be made as in
                    <lb/>other Wounds, and the Dreſſings the ſame: <lb/>There is a ſort of thin
                    crooked Needle that <lb/>cuts on its concave and convex ſides, which <lb/>is
                    very handy in the Suture of large Tendons, <lb/>and to be preferr'd to the
                    ſtrait one. During <lb/>the Cure the Dreſſings muſt be ſuperficial, and <lb/>the
                    parts kept ſteady with Paſte-board and <lb/>Bandage: The ſmall Tendons re-unite
                    in three <lb/>weeks, but the <hi rend="italic">Tendo Achillis</hi> requires ſix
                    at <lb/>leaſt. </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="9"/>
            <div type="chapter">
                <figure rend="space">
                    <lb/>
                    <figDesc>A decorative horizontal line, spanning the whole page.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <head rend="space align-center size(1.25)"><lb/>CHAP. III. <lb/><space
                        dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
                    <lb/><hi rend="italic">Of the GASTRORAPHY</hi>. </head>
                <p rend="space"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE Account of this Operation has <w
                        part="I">em-</w><lb/><w part="F">ploy'd</w> the Ingenuity of many Surgical
                    <lb/>Writers, and occaſioned much debate about <lb/>the proper Rules for
                    performing it, and yet <lb/>what makes the greateſt part of the <w part="I"
                        >deſcrip-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> can hardly ever happen in Practice,
                    and <lb/>the reſt but very ſeldom. I have been told <lb/>that <hi rend="italic"
                        >Du Verney</hi>, who was the moſt eminent <lb/>Surgeon in the <hi
                        rend="italic">French</hi> Army a great many <lb/>years during the Wars, and
                    faſhion of <w part="I">Duel-</w><lb/><w part="F">ling</w>, declar'd he never had
                    once an <w part="I">opportu-</w><lb/><w part="F">nity</w> of practiſing the
                    Gaſtroraphy, as that <lb/>Operation is generally deſcribed; for though <lb/>the
                    word in ſtrictneſs of etymology, ſignifies <lb/>no more than ſewing up any Wound
                    of the <lb/>Belly, yet in common acceptation it implies <lb/>that the Wound of
                    the Belly is complicated <lb/>with another of the Inteſtine. Now the
                    <lb/>ſymptoms laid down for diſtinguiſhing when <lb/>the Inteſtine is wounded,
                    do not with any <lb/>certainty determine it to be wounded only in <lb/>one
                    place, which want of information, makes <pb n="10"/><lb/>it abſurd to open the
                        <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi> in order to <lb/>come at it; if ſo, the
                    Operation of ſtitching <lb/>the Bowels can only take place, where they <lb/>fall
                    out of the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, and we can ſee where <lb/>the Wound
                    is, or how many Wounds there <lb/>are: If it happens that the Inteſtines fall
                    out <lb/>unwounded, the Buſineſs of the Surgeon is to <lb/>return them
                    immediately without waiting for <lb/>ſpirituous, or emollient Fomentations; and
                    in <lb/>caſe they puff up ſo, as to prevent their <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">duction</w> by the ſame Orifice, you may with a <lb/>Knife or
                    Probe-Sciſſars dilate it ſufficient for <lb/>that purpoſe, or even prick them to
                    let out <lb/>the wind, laying it down for a Rule in this, <lb/>and all
                    Operations where the <hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi>
                    <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">trudes</w>, to cut off ſo much as ſhall be
                        <w part="I">morti-</w><lb/><w part="F">fied</w> before you replace it. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Upon</hi> the ſuppoſition of the Inteſtine being
                    <lb/>wounded in ſuch a manner as to require the <lb/>Operation, for in ſmall
                    Punctures it is not <w part="I">ne-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceſſary</w>; the method
                    of doing it may be this: <lb/>Taking a ſtrait Needle with a ſmall Thread, you
                    lay hold of the Bowel with your left <lb/>hand, and ſew up the Wound by the
                    Glover's <lb/>Stitch, that is, by paſſing the Needle through <lb/>the Lips of
                    the Wound, from within outwards <lb/>all the way, ſo as to leave a length of
                    Thread <lb/>at both ends, which are to hang out of the <pb n="11"/><lb/>Inciſion
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>; then carefully <w part="I"
                        >mak-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> the interrupted Suture of the external
                    <lb/>Wound, you pull the Bowel by the ſmall <lb/>Threads into Contact with the
                        <hi rend="italic"><w part="I">Peritonæ-</w><lb/><w part="F">um</w></hi>, for
                    the more readily uniting afterwards <lb/> by Adheſion with it; though I think it
                    <lb/>would be more ſecure to paſs the Threads <lb/>with the ſtrait Needle
                    through the lower <lb/>edges of the Wound of the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>,
                    which <lb/>would more certainly hold the Inteſtine in <lb/>that ſituation. In
                    about ſix days it is ſaid the <lb/>Ligature of the Inteſtine will be looſe
                    enough <lb/>to draw away, which muſt be done without <lb/>great force; in the
                    interim the Wound is to <lb/>be treated with ſuperficial Dreſſings, and the
                    <lb/>Patient to be kept very ſtill and low. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <figure rend="space">
                    <lb/>
                    <figDesc>A decorative horizontal line, spanning the whole page.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <head rend="space align-center size(1.25)"><lb/>CHAP. IV. <lb/><space dim="vertical"
                        unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
                    <lb/><hi rend="italic">Of the BUBONOCELE</hi>. </head>
                <p rend="space"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">W</hi>HEN the Inteſtine or <hi rend="italic"
                        >Omentum</hi> falls <lb/>out of the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi> into any
                    Part, the <lb/>Tumour in general is known by the Name of <lb/><hi rend="italic"
                        >Hernia</hi>, which is farther ſpecified either from <lb/>the difference of
                    Situation, or the nature of its <lb/>Contents. When the Inteſtine or <hi
                        rend="italic">Omentum</hi> falls <pb n="12"/><lb/>through the Navel, 'tis
                    call'd a <hi rend="italic">Hernia <w part="I">Umbili-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                            >calis</w></hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Exomphalos</hi>; when through the
                    Rings <lb/>of the Abdominal Muſcles into the Groin, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
                        >Hernia Inguinalis</hi>; or if into the <hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic"><w part="I">Scro-</w><lb/><w part="F">talis</w></hi>: Thſe two
                    laſt, though the firſt only is <lb/>properly so call'd, are known by the Name of
                        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Bubonocele</hi>. when they fall under the <hi
                        rend="italic"><w part="I">Ligamen-</w><lb/><w part="F">tum</w>
                    Fallopii</hi>, through the ſame Paſſage that the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
                        >Iliac</hi> Veſſels creep into the Thigh, 'tis call'd <hi rend="italic"><w
                            part="I">Her-</w><lb/><w part="F">nia</w> Cruralis</hi>. With regard to
                    the Contents <w part="I">cha-</w><lb/><w part="F">racteriſing</w> the Swelling,
                    it is thus <w part="I">diſtinguiſh-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>: If the Inteſtine
                    only is fallen, it becomes <lb/>an <hi rend="italic">Enterocele</hi>; if the <hi
                        rend="italic">Omentum (Epiploon) <w part="I">Epi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                            >plocele</w></hi>; and if both, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Entero-Epiplocele</hi>. There <lb/>is beſides theſe another kind of <hi
                        rend="italic">Hernia</hi>
                    <w part="I">men-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion'd</w> and deſcrib'd by the Moderns,
                    when the <lb/>Inteſtine or <hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi> is inſinuated between
                    the <lb/>Interſtices of the Muſcles, in different Parts <lb/>of the Belly: This
                        <hi rend="italic">Hernia</hi> has derived its <lb/>name from the Place
                    affected, and is call'd the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hernia Ventralis</hi>. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">All</hi> the Kinds of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Hernia</hi>'s of the Inteſtines <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi>,
                    are owing to a preternatural <w part="I">Di-</w><lb/><w part="F">latation</w> of
                    the particular Orifices through <lb/>which they paſs, and not to a Laceration of
                    <lb/>them, which laſt Opinion however has <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                        >vailed</w> ſo much, as by way of eminence, to <lb/>give name to the
                    Diſorder, which is known <pb n="13"/><lb/>more by that of Rupture, than any of
                    thoſe <lb/>I have mentioned; on which account I ſhall beg leave to make uſe of
                    it myſelf. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Rupture of the Groin, or <hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>,
                    is <lb/>the moſt common Species of <hi rend="italic">Hernia</hi>, and in
                    <lb/>young Children is very frequent, but it rarely <lb/>happens in Infancy that
                    any miſchiefs ariſe <lb/>from it. For the moſt part, the Inteſtine <w part="I"
                        >re-</w><lb/><w part="F">turns</w> of it ſelf into the Cavity of the <hi
                        rend="italic"><w part="I">Abdo-</w><lb/><w part="F">men</w></hi>, whenever
                    the Perſon lies down, at leaſt <lb/>a ſmall degree of Compreſſion will make it.
                    To <lb/>ſecure the Inteſtine when returned into its <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">per</w> place, there are Steel Truſſes now ſo artfully <lb/>made,
                    that by being accommodated exactly to <lb/>the Part, they perform the Office of
                    a Bolſter, <lb/>without galling, or even ſitting uneasy on the <lb/>Patient.
                    Theſe Inſtruments are of ſo great <lb/>ſervice, that were people who are ſubject
                    to <lb/>Ruptures always to wear them, I believe very <lb/>few would die of this
                    Diſtemper, ſince it <w part="I">of-</w><lb/><w part="F">ten</w> appears, upon
                    enquiry, when we perform <lb/>the Operation for the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Bubonocele</hi>, that the <w part="I">ne-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceſſity</w>
                    of the Operation is owing to the neglect <lb/>of wearing a Truſs. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> the Application of a Truſs to theſe
                    kinds <lb/>of Swellings, a great deal of judgment is <w part="I"
                        >ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F">times</w> neceſſary, and for want of it we daily
                    <lb/>ſee Truſſes put even on <hi rend="I">Bubo</hi>'s, indurated <pb n="14"
                    /><lb/>Teſticles, <hi rend="italic">Hydrocele</hi>'s, <hi rend="italic"
                        >&amp;c.</hi> But for the <hi rend="italic"><w part="I">Her-</w><lb/><w
                            part="F">nia</w></hi>'s I have deſcribed, I ſhall endeavor to lay
                    <lb/>down two or three Rules, in order to guide <lb/>more poſitively to the
                    Propriety of applying <lb/>or forbearing them. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">If</hi> there is a Rupture of the Inteſtine
                    only, <lb/>it is eaſily, when return'd into the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>,
                    <lb/>ſupported by an Inſtrument; but if of the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
                        >Omentum</hi>, notwithſtanding it may be return'd, <lb/>yet I have never
                    found the Reduction to be of <lb/>much Relief; for the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Omentum</hi> will lie uneaſy in <lb/>a lump at the bottom of the Belly, and
                    upon <lb/>removal of the Inſtrument drop down again <lb/>immediately; upon which
                    account, ſeeing the <lb/>little Danger and Pain there is in this kind of
                        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hernia</hi>, I never recommend any thing but a
                    <lb/>Bag-Truſs, to ſuſpend the <hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>, and <w part="I"
                        >pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">vent</w> poſſibly by that means the increaſe of
                    <lb/>the Tumour. The difference of theſe <w part="I">Tu-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                        >mours</w> will be diſtinguished by the Feel; that <lb/>of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Omentum</hi> feeling flaccid and rumpled, <lb/>the other more
                    even, flatulent, and ſpringy. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Sometimes</hi> in a Rupture of both the <w
                        part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F">teſtine</w> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Omentum</hi>, the Gut may be reduced, <lb/>but the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Omentum</hi> will ſtill remain in the <hi rend="italic"><w part="I"
                            >Scro-</w><lb/><w part="F">tum</w></hi>, and when thus circumſtanced,
                    moſt <w part="I">Sur-</w><lb/><w part="F">geons</w> adviſe a Bag-Truſs only,
                    upon a <w part="I">Suppo-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſition</w> that the Preſſure of a
                    Steel one, by <w part="I">ſtop-</w><pb n="15"/><lb/><w part="F">ping</w> the
                    Circulation of the Blood in the <w part="I">Veſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſels</w> of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi>, would bring on a <w part="I"
                        >Morti-</w><lb/><w part="F">fication</w>: but I have learnt, from a
                    multitude <lb/>of theſe Caſes, that if the Inſtrument be <w part="I"
                        >nice-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> fitted to the Part, it will be a Compreſs
                    <lb/>ſufficient to ſuſtain the Bowel, and at the <lb/>ſame time not hard enough
                    to injure the <hi rend="italic"><w part="I">Omen-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                        >tum</w></hi>; ſo that, when a great quantity of <w part="I"
                        >Inte-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtine</w> falls down, though it is complicated
                    with <lb/>a Deſcent of the <hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi>, the Rupture will
                    <lb/>conveniently and ſafely admit of this <w part="I">Re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                        >medy</w>. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">There</hi> are some Surgeons who, to prevent
                    <lb/>the trouble of wearing a Truſs, when the <w part="I">In-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">teſtine</w> is reduced, deſtroy the Skin over the <lb/>Rings of the
                    Abdominal Muſcles with a <lb/>Cauſtick of the ſize of a half Crown-piece,
                    <lb/>and keep their Patients in Bed till the Cure of <lb/>the Wound is finiſh'd;
                    propoſinging by the <lb/>Stricture of the Cicatrix to ſupport it in the <lb/><hi
                        rend="italic">Abdomen</hi> for the future: But by what I have <lb/>ſeen of
                    this Practice, the event, though often <lb/>ſucceſsful, is not anſwerable to the
                    Pain and <lb/>Confinement; for if after this Operation the <lb/>Inteſtine ſhould
                    again fall down, which <w part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F">times</w> happens,
                    there would be much more <lb/>danger of a Strangulation than before the Scar
                    <lb/>was made. </p>
                <pb n="16"/>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">I have</hi> as yet conſidered the Rupture as
                    <lb/>moveable; but it happens frequently that the <lb/>Inteſtine, after it has
                    paſs'd the Rings of the <lb/>Muſcles, becomes inflam'd, which inlarging <lb/>the
                    Tumour, prevents the Return of it into <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>,
                    and becoming every moment <lb/>more and more ſtrangled, it ſoon tends to a
                    <lb/>Mortification, unleſs we dilate the Paſſages <lb/>through which it is
                    fallen, with ſome <w part="I">Inſtru-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w>, to make room
                    for its return, which <w part="I">Di-</w><lb/><w part="F">latation</w> is the
                    Operation for the <hi rend="italic">Bubonocele</hi>. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/>It rarely happens that Patients ſubmit to this <lb/>Inciſion
                    before the Gut is mortified, and it is <lb/>too late to do ſervice; not but that
                    there are <lb/>Inſtances of People ſurviving ſmall Gangrenes, <lb/>and even
                    perfectly recovering afterwards. I <lb/>my ſelf have been an Eye-witneſs of the
                    Cure <lb/>of two Patients who ſome time after the <w part="I">Ope-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">ration</w>, when the Eſchar ſeparated, diſcharged <lb/>their Fæces
                    through the Wound, and <w part="I">conti-</w><lb/><w part="F">nued</w> to do ſo
                    for a few Weeks in ſmall <w part="I">quan-</w><lb/><w part="F">tities</w>, when
                    at length the Inteſtine adhered <lb/>fairly to the external Wound, and then was
                    <lb/>eaſily healed. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> Mortifications of the Bowels, when <w
                        part="I">fal-</w><lb/><w part="F">len</w> out of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Abdomen</hi> into the Navel, it is <lb/>not very uncommon for the whole
                    gangren'd <lb/>Inteſtine to ſeparate from the ſound one, ſo <pb n="17"
                    /><lb/>that the Excrement muſt neceſſarily ever after <lb/>be diſcharged at that
                    Orifice: There are <w part="I">like-</w><lb/><w part="F">wiſe</w> a few
                    Inſtances, where the Rupture of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi> has
                    mortified and become the <hi rend="italic">Anus</hi>, <lb/>the Patient doing
                    well in every other reſpect. <lb/>Theſe Caſes however are only mentioned to <w
                        part="I">fur-</w><lb/><w part="F">niſh</w> Surgeons with the knowledge of
                    the <w part="I">poſſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">bility</w> of ſuch Events, and not to
                    miſlead them <lb/>ſo far as to make favourable Inferences with <lb/>regard to
                    Gangrenes of the Bowels, which <w part="I">ge-</w><lb/><w part="F">nerally</w>
                    are mortal. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Before</hi> the Performance of the Operation
                    <lb/>for the <hi rend="italic">Bubonocele</hi>, which is always to be done
                    <lb/>in wxtremity of Danger, the milder Methods <lb/>are to be tried; theſe are,
                    ſuch as will <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">duce</w> to ſooth the
                    Inflammation; for as to the <lb/>other Intent of ſoftening the Excrements, I
                    <lb/>believe it is much to be queſtioned, whether <lb/>there can be any of that
                    degree of Hardneſs <lb/>in the <hi rend="italic">Ilium</hi>, which is the Bowel
                    diſeaſed, as <lb/>to form the Obſtruction; and in fact, thoſe <lb/>Operators who
                    have unluckily wounded the <lb/>Inteſtine, have proved, by the thin Diſcharge
                    <lb/>of Fæces which has follow'd upon the <w part="I">Inci-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                        >ſion</w>, that the Induration we feel is the <w part="I">Ten-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">ſion</w> of the Parts, and not the hardened Lumps <lb/>of
                    Excrement. </p>
                <pb n="18"/>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Perhaps</hi>, except the Pleuriſy, no Diſorder
                    <lb/>is more immediately relieved by plentiful <lb/>Bleeding than this; Clyſters
                    repeated one <w part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> another three or four
                    times, if the firſt or <lb/>ſecond are either retained too long, or <w part="I"
                        >imme-</w><lb/><w part="F">diately</w> return'd, prove very efficacious;
                    theſe <lb/>are ſerviceable, not only as they empty the <lb/>great Inteſtines of
                    their Excrements and <w part="I">Fla-</w><lb/><w part="F">tulencies</w>, which
                    laſt are very dangerous, but <lb/>they likewiſe prove a comfortable <w part="I"
                        >Fomenta-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, by paſſing through the Colon all
                    around <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >Scrotum</hi> and Groin muſt, <lb/>during the ſtay of the Clyſter, be bath'd
                    with <lb/>warm Stoops wrung out of a Fomentation, <lb/>and with theſe on the
                    Part you muſt attempt to <lb/>reduce the Rupture: For this purpoſe let your
                    <lb/>Patient be laid on his Back, ſo that his <w part="I">But-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">tocks</w> may be conſiderably above his Head; the <lb/>Bowels will
                    then retire towards the <w part="I">Dia-</w><lb/><w part="F">phragm</w>, and
                    give way to thoſe which are to <lb/>be puſh'd in. If after endeavouring two or
                    <lb/>three Minutes, you do not find Succeſs, you <lb/>may ſtill repeat the
                    Trial: I have ſometimes, <lb/>at the end of a Quarter of an Hour returned
                    <lb/>ſuch as I thought deſperate, and which did <lb/>not ſeem to give way in the
                    leaſt, till the <lb/>moment they went up; however this muſt be <lb/>practis'd
                    with caution, for too much rough <lb/>handling will be pernicious. </p>
                <pb n="19"/>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">If</hi>, notwithſtanding theſe means, the <w
                        part="I">Pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tient</w> continues in very great torture,
                    though <lb/>not ſo bad as to threaten an immediate <w part="I">Mor-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">tification</w>, we muſt apply ſome ſort of <w part="I"
                        >Pul-</w><lb/><w part="F">tice</w> to the <hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>;
                    that which I uſe in this <lb/>Caſe is, equal parts of Oil and Vinegar made
                    <lb/>into a proper conſiſtence with Oatmeal: <w part="I">Af-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                        >ter</w> ſome few hours the Fomentation is to be <lb/>repeated, and the
                    other Directions put in <w part="I">prac-</w><lb/><w part="F">tice</w>. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/>After all, ſhould the Pain and Tenſeneſs of <lb/>the Part
                    continue, and Hiccoughs and <w part="I">Vomit-</w><lb/><w part="F">ings</w> of
                    the Excrements ſucceed, the Operation <lb/>muſt take place; for if you wait till
                    a languid <lb/>Pulſe, cold Sweats, ſubſiding of the Tumour, <lb/>and
                    Emphyſematous Feel come on, it will be <lb/>moſt likely too late, as they are
                    pretty ſure <lb/>ſymptoms of a Mortification. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">To</hi> conceive rightly of the Occurrences in
                    <lb/>this Operation, it muſt be remembered that in <lb/>every Species of Rupture
                    the <hi rend="italic">Peritonæum</hi> falls <lb/>down with whatever makes the
                        <hi rend="italic">Hernia</hi>, for <lb/>the contents of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Abdomen</hi> being <w part="I">immediate-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                        >ly</w> envelop'd in this Membrane, they cannot <lb/> puſh though any
                    Orifice, but they muſt <w part="I">like-</w><lb/><w part="F">wiſe</w> carry a
                    part of it along with them: So that <lb/> in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Bubonocele</hi>, the Situation of tht Tumour <pb n="20"/><lb/>will be in
                    the Cavity of the <hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>, upon <lb/>the <hi
                        rend="italic">Tunica Vaginalis</hi> and Spermatic Cord. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> beſt way of laying your Patient will
                    <lb/>be on a Table of about three Foot four Inches <lb/>high, letting his Legs
                    hang down; then <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">perly</w> ſecuring him, you
                    begin your Inciſion <lb/>above the Rings of the Muſcles, beyond the
                    <lb/>extremity of the Tumour, and bring it down <lb/>about half the length of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>, through <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Membrana
                        adipoſa</hi>, which will require <w part="I">ve-</w><lb/><w part="F">ry</w>
                    little trouble to ſeparate from the <hi rend="italic"><w part="I"
                            >Perito-</w><lb/><w part="F">næum</w></hi> (call'd <hi rend="italic">the
                        Sac of the Hernia</hi>) and <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                        >ſequently</w> will expoſe the Rupture for the <w part="I">far-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">ther</w> Proceſſes of the Operation; but I cannot <lb/>help once
                    more recommending it as a thing of <lb/>great conſequence, to begin the external
                    Inciſion <lb/>high enough above the Rings, ſince there is no <lb/>danger in that
                    part of the Wound: and for <lb/>want of the room this Inciſion allows, the
                    <lb/>moſt expert Operators are ſometimes tedious <lb/>in making the Dilatation.
                    If a large Veſſel be <lb/>open'd by the Inciſion, it muſt be taken up
                    <lb/>before you proceed further. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">When</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Peritonæum</hi>
                    is laid bare, you <lb/>muſt cut though it carefully to avoid <w part="I"
                        >prick-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> the Inteſtines; though, to ſay the
                    truth, <lb/>there is not quite ſo much danger of this <pb n="21"/><lb/>Accident
                    as is repreſented, for generally <w part="I">ſpeak-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>
                    the quantity of Water ſeparated in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Sac <hi
                            rend="roman">of the</hi> Peritonæum</hi>, raiſes it from the <w part="I"
                        >In-</w><lb/><w part="F">teſtine</w>, and prevents any ſuch miſchief. This
                    <lb/>diſcharge of Water which follows upon <w part="I">wound-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">ing</w> the <hi rend="italic">Peritonæum</hi>, and the Ignorance of
                    the <lb/>Structure of the <hi rend="italic">Tunica Vaginalis</hi>, have made
                    <lb/> it ſo generally thought that Ruptures were <lb/>received into the Cavity
                    of that Tunick. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> has lately been conſider'd by ſome as
                    <lb/>an Improvement in the Operation, to forbear <lb/>wounding the <hi
                        rend="italic">Peritonæum</hi>, and to return the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
                        >Sac</hi> intire into the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, thinking by this
                    <lb/>means to make a firmer Cicatrix, and more <lb/>ſurely to prevent a Relapſe
                    for the future; <lb/>but beſides that this Practice is not <w part="I"
                        >found-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> on Reaſon in the very particular it is <w
                        part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">commended</w> for, the ſeeming neceſſity
                    there <lb/>is of letting out the Waters that are <w part="I">fre-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">quently</w> fœtid, of taking away the mortified <lb/>Part of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi>, which we cannot come <lb/>at without the
                    Inciſion, and laſtly to leave <lb/>an Opening for the iſſue of the Excrements
                    <lb/>out of the Wound, in caſe an Eſchar ſhould <lb/>drop from the Inteſtine,
                    put out of <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">pute</w>, in my opinion, the
                    Impropriety of this <lb/>new Method. </p>
                <pb n="22"/>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Peritonæum</hi> being cut through, we <lb/>arrive to its
                    Contents, the nature of which <lb/>will determine the next Proceſs; for if they
                    <lb/>be Inteſtine only, it muſt directly be reduced, <lb/>but if there be any
                    mortify'd <hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi>, it <lb/>muſt be cut off; in order to
                    which it is <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">viſed</w> to make a Ligature
                    above the Part <lb/>wounded, to prevent an Hæmorrhage, but it <lb/>is quite
                    needleſs, and in ſome meaſure <w part="I">perni-</w><lb/><w part="F">cious</w>,
                    as it puckers up the Inteſtine, and <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                        >orders</w> its ſituation, if made cloſe to it: For <lb/>my part I am very
                    jealous that Wounds of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi> are dangerous, on
                    which account I <lb/>cannot paſs over this part of the Operation, <lb/>without
                    cautioning againſt cutting any of it <lb/>away, unleſs it is certainly
                    gangrened; and <lb/>when that happens, I think it adviſeable to <lb/>cut off
                    only ſome of the mortify'd Part, and <lb/>leave the reſt to ſeparate in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, <lb/>which may be done with as much ſafety, as
                    <lb/>leaving the ſame quantity below a Ligature. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">When</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi> is
                    remov'd, we next <lb/>dilate the Wound, to do which with ſafety, an infinite
                    number of Inſtruments have been <lb/>invented; but in my opinion, there is none
                    we <lb/>can uſe in this caſe with ſo good m <w part="I">manage-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">ment</w> as a Knife; and I have found my Finger <lb/>in the
                    Operation a much better defence againſt <pb n="23"/><lb/>pricking the Bowels,
                    than a Director which <lb/>I intended to employ: The Knife muſt be <lb/>a little
                    crooked and blunt at its extremity, <lb/>like the end of a Probe. Some Surgeons
                        <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">haps</w> may not be ſteady enough to
                    cut <w part="I">dex-</w><lb/><w part="F">terouſly</w> with a Knife, and may
                    therefore <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">form</w> the Inciſion with
                    Probe-Sciſſars, <w part="I">care-</w><lb/><w part="F">fully</w> introducing one
                    Blade between the <w part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F">teſtine</w> and
                    circumference of the Rings, and <lb/>dilating upwards. When the Finger and Knife
                    <lb/>only are employ'd, the manner of doing the <lb/>Operation will be by
                    preſſing the Gut down <lb/>with the fore Finger, and carrying the Knife
                    <lb/>between it and the Muſcles, ſo as to dilate <lb/>upwards about an Inch,
                    which will be a <lb/>Wound large enough. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> Opening being made, the Inteſtine is
                    <lb/>gradually to be puſh'd into the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, and
                    <lb/>the Wound to be ſtitch'd up; for this purpoſe <lb/>ſome adviſe the quill'd,
                    and others the <w part="I">inter-</w><lb/><w part="F">rupted</w> Suture, but as
                    there is very little danger <lb/>of the Bowels falling out when a Dreſſing
                    <lb/>and Bandage are applied, and the Patient all <lb/>the while kept upon his
                    Back, I would by all <lb/>means uſe but a ſlight Stitch through the <lb/>Skin
                    only, ſince the ſtricture of a Ligature in <lb/>the tendinous Parts cannot but
                    be <w part="I">dange-</w><lb/><w part="F">rous</w>, and I could wiſh the
                    Operation was <pb n="24"/><lb/>practis'd without ſewing up afterwards at
                    <lb/>all. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Hitherto</hi>, in the deſcription of the <hi
                        rend="italic"><w part="I">Bubo-</w><lb/><w part="F">nocele</w></hi> I have
                    ſuppos'd it looſe, or ſeparate in <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Sac</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>, but it happens ſometimes <lb/>in an Operation,
                    that we find not only an <lb/>Adheſion of the outſide of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Peritonæum</hi> to <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Tunica Vaginalis</hi>, and
                    ſpermatic Veſſels, <lb/>but likewiſe of ſome part of the Inteſtines to <lb/>its
                    internal Surface; and in this caſe there is <lb/>ſo much confuſion that the
                    Operator is often <lb/>obliged to extirpate the Teſticle, in order to diſſect
                    away and diſintangle the Gut, tho' if <lb/>it can be done without Caſtration it
                    ought: <lb/>I believe however, this Accident happens <lb/>rarely, except in
                    thoſe Ruptures that have <lb/>been a long time in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Scrotum</hi> without <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">turning</w>; in
                    which caſe the difficulty and <lb/>hazard of the Operation are ſo great, that <w
                        part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">leſs</w> urged by the ſymptoms of an
                    inflamed <lb/>Inteſtine, I would not have it undertaken. <lb/>I have known two
                    Inſtances of Perſons ſo <lb/>uneaſy under the circumſtance of ſuch a load
                    <lb/>in their <hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>, tho' not otherwiſe in pain,
                    <lb/>as to deſire the Operation, but the Event in <lb/>both proved fatal; which
                    I think ſhould make <lb/>us cautious how we expoſe a Life for the <lb/>ſake of a
                    convenience only, and teach our <pb n="25"/><lb/>Patients to content themſelves
                    with a <w part="I">Bag-</w><lb/><w part="F">Truſs</w>, when in this condition. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> dreſſing of the Wound firſt of all
                    <lb/>may be with dry Lint, and afterwards as <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                        >rected</w> in the Introduction. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> Operation of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Bubonocele</hi> in <w part="I">Wo-</w><lb/><w part="F">men</w> ſo exactly
                    reſembles that perform'd on <lb/>Men, that it requires no particular
                    deſcription, <lb/>only in them the Rupture is form'd by the <w part="I"
                        >ln-</w><lb/><w part="F">teſtine</w> or <hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi>
                    falling down through the <lb/>Paſſage of the <hi rend="italic">Ligamentum
                        Rotundum</hi> into the <lb/>Groin, or one of the <hi rend="italic">Labia
                        Pudendi</hi>; where <lb/>cauſing the ſame ſymptoms as when obſtructed
                    <lb/>in the <hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>, it is to be return'd by the <w
                        part="I">Di-</w><lb/><w part="F">latation</w> of that Paſſage. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <figure rend="space">
                    <lb/>
                    <figDesc>A decorative horizontal line, spanning the whole page.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <head rend="align-center space size(1.25)"><lb/>CHAP. V. <lb/><space dim="vertical"
                        unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
                    <lb/><hi rend="italic">Of the EPIPLOCELE</hi>. </head>
                <p rend="space"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>here have been a few Inſtances where
                    <lb/>ſo great a quantity of the <hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi> has <lb/>fallen
                    into the <hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>, that by drawing the <lb/>Stomach and
                    Bowels downwards, it has <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">cited</w>
                    Vomitings, Inflammation, and the ſame <lb/>train of Symptoms as happen in a <hi
                        rend="italic">Bubonocele</hi>; in <lb/>which caſe the Operation of opening
                    the <hi rend="italic"><w part="I">Scro-</w><pb n="26"/><lb/><w part="F"
                        >tum</w></hi> is neceſſary: The Inciſion muſt be made <lb/>in the manner of
                    that for the Rupture of <lb/>the Inteſtine, and the ſame Rules obſerved
                    <lb/>with regard to the <hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi>, that are laid <lb/>down
                    in the laſt Chapter. It is neceſſary alſo <lb/>the Rings of the Muſcles ſhould
                    be dilated, <lb/>or otherwiſe, though you have taken away <lb/>ſome of the
                    mortify'd part of the <hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi>, the reſt that is out of
                    its place, and ſtrangled <lb/>in the Perforation will gangrene alſo. The
                    <lb/>Wound is to be treated in the ſame manner <lb/>as that after the Operation
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Bubonocele</hi>. <lb/>What I have here deſcribed as an
                    Inducement <lb/>to the Operation, ſhould, by the Experience <lb/>I have had, be
                    the only one. There are a <lb/>great many People who are ſo uneaſy with
                    <lb/>Ruptures, though they are not painful, that <lb/>a little encouragement
                    from Surgeons of <w part="I">Cha-</w><lb/><w part="F">racter</w> will make them
                    ſubmit to any means <lb/>of Cure; but as I have ſeen two or three <w part="I"
                        >Pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tients</w>, who were in every reſpect hale and
                    <lb/>ſtrong, die a very few days after the <w part="I">Opera-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">tion</w>, the event, though very ſurpriſing, ſhould <lb/>be a
                    Leſſon never to recommend this method <lb/>of treating an <hi rend="italic"
                        >Epiplocele</hi>, unleſs it is attended <lb/>with Inflammation, <hi
                        rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="27"/>
            <div type="chapter">
                <figure rend="space">
                    <lb/>
                    <figDesc>A decorative horizontal line, spanning the whole page.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <head rend="space align-center size(1.25)"><lb/>CHAP. VI. <lb/><space dim="vertical"
                        unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
                    <lb/><hi rend="italic">Of the <hi rend="roman sc">Hernia Cruralis</hi></hi>. </head>
                <p rend="space"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HIS Species of Rupture is the ſame in
                    <lb/>both Sexes, and form'd by the falling of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Omentum</hi> or Inteſtine, or both of them, <lb/>into the inſide of the
                    Thigh, through the <lb/>Arch made by the <hi rend="italic">Os Pubis</hi>, and
                        <hi rend="italic"><w part="I">Ligamen-</w><lb/><w part="F">tum</w>
                        Fallopii</hi>, where the Iliac Veſſels and <w part="I">Ten-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">dons</w> of the <hi rend="italic">Pſoas</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Iliacus Internus</hi>
                    <w part="I">Muſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">cles</w> paſs from the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Abdomen</hi>. It is very <w part="I">ne-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceſſary</w>,
                    Surgeons ſhould be aware of this <w part="I">Diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">order</w>,
                    which creates the ſame Symptoms as <lb/>other Ruptures, and muſt firſt of all be
                        <w part="I">treat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> by the ſame methods: The
                    manner of <lb/>operating in the Reduction is alſo ſo nearly <lb/>the ſame, with
                    the difference only of <w part="I">dilat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> the
                    Ligament inſtead of the Rings of the <lb/>Muſcles, that it would be a mere
                    repetition <lb/>of the Operation for the <hi rend="italic">Bubonocele</hi> to
                    give any <lb/>deſcription of it. </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="28"/>
            <div type="chapter">
                <figure rend="space">
                    <lb/>
                    <figDesc>A decorative horizontal line, spanning the whole page.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <head rend="space align-center size(1.25)"><lb/>CHAP. VII. <lb/><space
                        dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
                    <lb/><hi rend="italic">Of the EXOMPHALOS</hi>. </head>
                <p rend="space"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HIS Rupture is owing to a Protruſion
                    <lb/>of the Inteſtine, or <hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi>, or both of <lb/>them,
                    at the Navel, and rarely happens to be <lb/>the ſubject of an Operation; for
                    though the <lb/>caſe is common, yet moſt of them are <w part="I">gra-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">dually</w> form'd from very ſmall beginnings, <lb/>and if they do
                    not return into the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>
                    <lb/>upon lying down, in all probability they <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">here</w> without any great inconvenience to the <lb/>Patient, till
                    ſome time or other an <w part="I">Inflam-</w><lb/><w part="F">mation</w> falls
                    upon the Inteſtines, which ſoon <lb/>brings on a Mortification, and Death,
                    unleſs <lb/>by great chance the mortified Part ſeparates <lb/>from the ſound
                    one, leaving its Extremity <lb/>to perform the office of an <hi rend="italic"
                        >Anus</hi>: in this <lb/>Emergency however I think it adviſeable to
                    <lb/>attempt the Reduction, if call'd in at the <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">ginning</w>, though the univerſal Adheſion of <lb/>the <hi
                        rend="italic">Sac</hi> and its Contents, are a great obſtacle <lb/>to the
                    ſucceſs: The Inſtance in which it is <lb/>moſt likely to anſwer, is, when the
                    Rupture <lb/>is owing to any Strain, or ſudden Jerk, and <pb n="29"/><lb/>is
                    attended with thoſe Diſorders that follow <lb/>upon the Strangulation of a Gut. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> this Caſe, having tried all other means,
                    <lb/>in vain, the Operation is abſolutely neceſſary, <lb/>which may be thus
                    performed: Make the <w part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F">ciſion</w> ſomewhat
                    above the Tumour, on the <lb/>left ſide of the Navel, through the <hi
                        rend="italic">Membrana <lb/>Adipoſa</hi>, and then emptying the <hi
                        rend="italic">Sac</hi> of its <lb/>Water, or mortified <hi rend="italic"
                        >Omentum</hi>, dilate the Ring <lb/>with the ſame crooked Knife, conducted
                    on <lb/>your Finger, as in the Operation for the <hi rend="italic"><w part="I"
                            >Bu-</w><lb/><w part="F">bonocele</w></hi>; after this, return the
                    Inteſtines and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi> into the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Abdomen</hi>, and dreſs the <lb/>Wound without making any Ligature. </p>
                <lb/>
                <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="5"/>
                <figure>
                    <lb/>
                    <figDesc>A small decorative figure in the middle of the page.</figDesc>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <pb n="30"/>
            <div type="chapter">
                <figure rend="space">
                    <lb/>
                    <figDesc>A decorative horizontal line, spanning the whole page.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <head rend="space align-center size(1.25)"><lb/>CHAP. VIII. <lb/><space
                        dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
                    <lb/><hi rend="italic">Of the <hi rend="roman sc">Hernia Ventralis</hi></hi>. </head>
                <p rend="space"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>his Tumour is ſeldom larger than a
                    <lb/>Walnut, and is a Diſeaſe not ſo common <lb/>as to have been obſerved by
                    many, but there <lb/>are Caſes enough known to put a Surgeon <lb/>upon enquiry
                    after it, when the Patient is <lb/>ſuddenly taken with all the Symptoms of a
                    <lb/>Rupture, without any appearance of one in <lb/>the Navel, Scrotum, or
                    Thigh: I have before <lb/>defined this <hi rend="italic">Hernia</hi> to be a
                    Strangulation of <lb/>the Gut, between ſome of the Interſtices of <lb/>the
                    Muſcles of the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>: The manner of <lb/>dilating it
                    will be as above directed in the <lb/>other <hi rend="italic">Hernia</hi>'s:
                    After the Operation in this, <lb/>and all <hi rend="italic">Hernia</hi>'s where
                    the Inteſtines have <lb/>been reduced, 'twill be convenient to wear a
                    <lb/>Truſs, ſince the Cicatrix is not always firm <lb/>enough in any of them, to
                    prevent a Relapſe, <lb/>as I have had ſeveral opportunities to inform <lb/> my
                    ſelf. </p>
                <pb/>
                <pb n="31"/>
                <figure>
                    <head rend="space align-center"><lb/>>PLATE II. <lb/><space dim="vertical"
                            unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
                        <lb/><hi rend="italic">The <hi rend="roman sc">Explanation</hi></hi>.</head>
                    <p rend="space indent"><lb/><label rend="italic">A.</label> The round-edged
                        Knife, of a <w part="I">conve-</w><lb/><w part="F">nient</w> ſize for almoſt
                        all Operations where <lb/>a Knife is uſed; the Make of it will be better
                        <lb/>underſtood by the Figure than any other <w part="I">De-</w><lb/><w
                            part="F">ſcription</w>; only it may be remark'd, that the <lb/>Handle is
                        made of a light Wood, as indeed <lb/>the Handles of all Inſtruments ſhould
                        be, that <lb/>the Reſiſtance to the Blades may be better felt <lb/>by the
                        Surgeon. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><label rend="italic">B.</label> A Pair of Probe-Sciſſars,
                        which require <lb/>nothing very particular in their Form, but <lb/>that the
                        lower Blade ſhould be made as ſmall <lb/>as poſſible, ſo that it is ſtrong
                        and has a good <lb/>Edge, becauſe being chiefly us'd in Fiſtula's <lb/>in
                            <hi rend="italic">Ano</hi>, the Introduction of a thick Blade <w
                            part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">to</w> the Sinus, which is generally
                        narrow, <lb/>would be very painful to the Patient. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><label rend="italic">C.</label> The crooked Knife with the
                        Point <lb/>blunted, us'd in the Operation of the <hi rend="italic"><w
                                part="I">Bubo-</w><lb/><w part="F">nocele</w></hi>. </p>
                    <figDesc>Illustrations of the three instruments on the previous page.</figDesc>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <pb n="32"/>
            <div type="chapter">
                <figure rend="space">
                    <lb/>
                    <figDesc>A decorative horizontal line, spanning the whole page.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <head rend="space align-center size(1.25)"><lb/>CHAP. IX. <lb/><space dim="vertical"
                        unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
                    <lb/><hi rend="italic">Of the HYDROCELE</hi>. </head>
                <p rend="space"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE <hi rend="italic">Hydrocele</hi>,
                    called alſo <hi rend="italic">Hernia Aquoſa</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hydrops
                        Scroti</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Hydrops Teſtis</hi>, is a <lb/><choice>
                        <sic>watry</sic>
                        <corr>watery</corr>
                    </choice> Tumour of the <hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>; which <w part="I"
                        >not-</w><lb/><w part="F">withſtanding</w> the multiplicity of diſtinctions
                    <lb/>uſed by Writers, is but of two kinds: The <lb/>one, when the Water is
                    contain'd in the <hi rend="italic"><w part="I">Tu-</w><lb/><w part="F">nica</w>
                        Vaginalis</hi>, and the other when in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Membrana
                        Cellularis Scroti</hi>: This laſt is <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                        >moſt</w> always complicated with an <hi rend="italic">Anaſarca</hi>,
                    <lb/>which ſpecies of Dropſy is an Extravaſation of <lb/>Water lodged in the
                    Cells of the <hi rend="italic">Membrana <lb/>Adipoſa</hi>; and when thus
                    circumſtanced will <lb/>not be difficult to be diſtinguish'd; beſides that
                    <lb/>it is ſufficiently characteris'd by the ſhining <lb/>and ſoftneſs of the
                    Skin, which gives way to <lb/>the leaſt Impreſſion, and remains pitted for
                    <lb/>ſome time. The <hi rend="italic">Penis</hi> is likewiſe ſometimes
                    <lb/>enormously inlarged, by the Inſinuation of the <lb/><choice>
                        <sic>the</sic>
                        <corr/>
                    </choice> Fluids into the <hi rend="italic">Membrana Cellularis</hi>, all
                    <lb/>which Symptoms are abſolutely wanting in <lb/>the Dropſy of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Tunica Vaginalis</hi>. </p>
                <pb n="33"/>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> the Dropſy of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Membrana Cellularis <lb/>Scroti</hi>, the Puncture with the Trocar is <w
                        part="I">recom-</w><lb/><w part="F">mended</w> by ſome, and little Orifices
                    made here <lb/>and there with the point of a Lancet by others, <lb/>or a ſmall
                    Skane of Silk paſs'd by a Needle <lb/>through the Skin, and out again at the
                    diſtance <lb/>of two or three Inches, to be kept in the <w part="I"
                        >man-</w><lb/><w part="F">ner</w> of a Seton, till the Waters are quite
                    <lb/>drained: But the two firſt Methods avail <lb/>very little, as they open but
                    few Cells; <lb/>and the laſt cannot be ſo efficacious in <lb/>that reſpect as
                    Inciſions, and will be much <lb/>more apt to become troubleſome, and even to
                    <lb/>gangrene. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Indeed</hi> it is not often proper to perform
                    <lb/>any Operation at all upon this Part, ſince the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
                        >Membrana Cellularis Scroti</hi>, being a <w part="I">continua-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">tion</w> of the <hi rend="italic">Membrana Adipoſa</hi>,
                    Scarifications <lb/>made through the Skin in the ſmall of the <lb/>Legs will
                    effectually empty the <hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>, as I have many Times
                    experienced; and this <lb/>Place ought rather to be pitch'd upon than <lb/>the
                    other, as being more likely to anſwer <lb/>the purpoſe by reaſon of its
                    Dependency: <lb/>However it ſometimes happens that the <w part="I"
                        >Wa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ters</w> fall in ſo great quantities into the <hi
                        rend="italic"><w part="I">Scro-</w><lb/><w part="F">tum</w></hi>, as by
                    diſtending it, to occaſion great Pain, <lb/>and threaten a Mortification: The
                    Prepuce of <pb n="34"/><lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Penis</hi> alſo becomes very
                    often exceſſively <lb/>dilated, and ſo twiſted that the Patient <w part="I"
                        >can-</w><lb/><w part="F">not</w> void his Urine. In theſe two Inſtances I
                    <lb/>would propoſe an Inciſion of three Inches <lb/>long to be made on each ſide
                    of the <hi rend="italic"><w part="I">Scro-</w><lb/><w part="F">tum</w></hi>,
                    quite through the Skin into the Cells <lb/>containing the Water, and two or
                    three, of <lb/>Half an Inch long in any part of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Penis</hi>, <lb/>with a Lancet or Knife; all which may be <lb/>done with great
                    ſafety, and ſometimes with <lb/>the ſucceſs of carrying off the Diſeaſe of the
                    <lb/>whole Body. This I can poſitively ſay, that <lb/>though I have done it upon
                    Perſons in a very <lb/>languid Condition, yet, by making the Wound <lb/>with a
                    ſharp Inſtrument, and treating it <w part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                        >terwards</w> with Fomentations and ſoft <w part="I">Digeſ-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">tives</w>, I have never ſeen any Inſtance of a <lb/>Gangrene, which
                    is generally ſo much <w part="I">appre-</w><lb/><w part="F">hended</w> in this
                    caſe. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> Dropſy of the <hi rend="italic">Tunica
                        Vaginalis</hi> is <lb/>owing to a preternatural Diſcharge of that <lb/>Water
                    which is continually ſeparating in a <lb/>ſmall quantity on the internal Surface
                    of the <lb/>Tunick, for the moiſtening or lubricating the <lb/>Teſticle, and
                    which collecting too faſt, heaps <lb/>up and forms in time a Swelling of great
                    <lb/>magnitude: This is what I take to be the <lb/>other Species of <hi
                        rend="italic">Hydrocele</hi>, and the only one <pb n="35"/><lb/>beſides;
                    though from the time of <hi rend="italic">Celſus</hi>
                    <lb/>down to our own Days, the Writers on this <w part="I">Sub-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">ject</w> make two kinds, one on the inſide of the <lb/><hi
                        rend="italic">Tunica Vaginalis</hi>, and another between the <lb/><hi
                        rend="italic">Scrotum</hi> and outſide of it, and among the <lb/>Cauſes
                    aſſigned for this Diſtemper, the <w part="I">prin-</w><lb/><w part="F">cipal</w>
                    one is the Derivation of Water from the <lb/>Aſcites, which Opinion though
                    univerſally <lb/>received, is abſurd in Anatomy: For beſides <lb/>that People
                    afflicted with a <hi rend="italic">Hydrocele</hi> are very <lb/>ſeldom otherwiſe
                    dropſical, and on the <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">trary</w>, thoſe with
                    an Aſcites have no <hi rend="italic"><w part="I">Hydro-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                            >cele</w></hi>; the <hi rend="italic">Tunica Vaginalis</hi> is like a
                    Purſe <w part="I">to-</w><lb/><w part="F">tally</w> ſhut up on the outſide of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, ſo that no Water from any Part can <w
                        part="I">inſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nuate</w> into it; and with reſpect to
                    the <w part="I">No-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of Water falling from the <hi
                        rend="italic">Abdomen</hi> into <lb/>the Interſtice of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Tunica Vaginalis</hi> and <hi rend="italic"><w part="I">Scro-</w><lb/><w
                            part="F">tum</w></hi>, it is equally impoſſible; for though in <lb/>the
                        <hi rend="italic">Hernia Inteſtinalis</hi>, the Gut falls into this
                    <lb/>Part, yet in that caſe the <hi rend="italic">Peritonæum</hi> (which
                    <lb/>would hinder the Egreſs of the Water) falls <lb/>down too, which the
                    Ancients did not know, <lb/>and the Moderns have omitted to reflect on <lb/>in
                    relation to this Subject. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Hydrocele <hi rend="roman">of the</hi> Tunica Vaginalis</hi>
                    <lb/>is very eaſily to be diſtinguished from the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
                        >Hydrocele <hi rend="roman">of the</hi> Membrana Cellularis</hi>, by <pb
                        n="36"/><lb/>the preceding deſcription of that Species of <lb/>Dropſy: I
                    ſhall now explain how it differs <lb/>from the other Tumours of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> the <hi
                        rend="italic">Bubonocele</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Epiplocele</hi>, and
                    enlarg'd <lb/>Teſticle: In the firſt place, it is ſeldom or <lb/>never attended
                    with Pain in the beginning, and <lb/>is very rarely to be imputed to any <w
                        part="I">Acci-</w><lb/><w part="F">dent</w>, as the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Hernia<hi rend="roman">'s of the</hi> Omentum</hi> and <w part="I"
                        >In-</w><lb/><w part="F">teſtine</w> are: from the time it firſt makes
                    <lb/>its appearance it hardly is ever known to <lb/>diminiſh, <lb/>but generally
                    continues to increaſe, <lb/>though in ſome much faſter than in others; <lb/>in
                    one Perſon growing to a very painful <w part="I">Di-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                        >ſtenſion</w> in a few Months, whilſt in another <lb/>it ſhall not be
                    troubleſome in many Years; <lb/>nay, ſhall ceaſe to ſwell at a certain Period,
                    <lb/>and ever after continue in that ſtate <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                        >out</w> any notable diſadvantage; though this laſt <lb/>Caſe very rarely
                    happens: In proportion as <lb/>it enlarges it becomes more tenſe, and then
                    <lb/>is ſaid to be tranſparent, indeed the <w part="I">Tranſ-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">parency</w> is made the chief Criterion of the <lb/>Diſtemper, it
                    being conſtantly advis'd to hold <lb/>a Candle on one ſide of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>, which <lb/>it is ſaid will ſhine through to the
                    other, if <lb/>there be Water: but this Experiment does <lb/>not always anſwer,
                    becauſe ſometimes the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi> is very much
                    thicken'd, and the <pb n="37"/><lb/>Water it ſelf not tranſparent; ſo that to
                    <lb/>judge poſitively if there be a Fluid, we muſt <lb/>be guided by feeling a
                    Fluctuation; and tho' <lb/>ſometimes we do not perhaps evidently <w part="I"
                        >per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceive</w> it, yet we may be perſuaded there is
                    <lb/>a Fluid of ſome kind, if we are once aſſur'd <lb/>that the Diſtenſion of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Tunica Vaginalis</hi>
                    <lb/>makes the Tumour, which is to be <w part="I">diſtin-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                        >guiſh'd</w> in the following manner. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">If</hi> the Inteſtine, or <hi rend="italic"
                        >Omentum</hi>, form the <lb/>Swelling, they will be ſoft and pliable, (<w
                        part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">leſs</w> inflamed) uneven in their Surface,
                        <w part="I">particu-</w><lb/><w part="F">larly</w> the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Omentum</hi>, and both of them extend <lb/>themſelves up from the <hi
                        rend="italic">Scrotum</hi> quite into the <lb/>very <hi rend="italic"
                        >Abdomen</hi>; whereas in the <hi rend="italic">Hydrocele</hi>, the
                    <lb/>Tumour is tenſe and ſmooth, and ceaſes before <lb/>or at its arrival to the
                    Rings of the Abdominal <lb/>Muſcles; becauſe the upper extremity of the <lb/><hi
                        rend="italic">Tunica Vaginalis</hi> terminates at ſome diſtance <lb/>from
                    the Surface of the Belly. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">When</hi> the Teſticle is increas'd in its Size,
                    <lb/>the Tumour is rounder, and, if not attended <lb/>with an Inlargement of the
                    Spermatic <w part="I">Veſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſels</w>, the Cord may be eaſily
                    diſtinguiſh'd <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">tween</w> the Swelling and <hi
                        rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>; but <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                        >out</w> this Rule of diſtinction, either the Pain <lb/>or the very great
                    Hardneſs, will diſcover it to <lb/>be a Diſeaſe of the Teſticle. </p>
                <pb n="38"/>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">As</hi> to the Cure of this Diſtemper by <w
                        part="I">exter-</w><lb/><w part="F">nal</w> Applications, or internal Means,
                    after <w part="I">hav-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> tried upon a great variety of
                    Subjects, <lb/>moſt of the Medicines invented to that end, I <lb/>have found but
                    very little Satisfaction in the <lb/>Event; for if by chance any one has mended
                    <lb/>under a Phyſical Regimen, it muſt be <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                        >feſs'd</w> too, that there are ſome Inſtances of <lb/>People recovering,
                    who have ſo abſolutely <lb/>neglected themſelves as not even to wear a <w
                        part="I">Bag-</w><lb/><w part="F">Truſs</w>; on which account, I ſhould
                    judge it <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">viſable</w> to wait with patience
                    till the Tumour <lb/>becomes troubleſome, and then to tap it with <lb/>a Lancet,
                    which is rather leſs offenſive to the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tunica
                        Vaginalis</hi> than the Trocar. In <w part="I">open-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                        >ing</w> with a Lancet it may poſſibly happen, the <lb/>Orifice of the Skin
                    ſhall ſlip away from that <lb/>of the Tunick, and prevent the Egreſs of the
                    <lb/>Water; to obviate which Inconvenience you <lb/>may introduce a Probe, and
                    by that means <w part="I">ſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cure</w> the exact Situation
                    of the Wound. It is <lb/>ſpoken of as an eaſy thing to hold the Teſticle
                    <lb/>with the left Hand, while we make the <w part="I">Punc-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                        >ture</w> with the right, but when the <hi rend="italic">Tunica
                        <lb/>Vaginalis</hi> is very tenſe it cannot well be <w part="I"
                        >diſtin-</w><lb/><w part="F">guiſh'd</w>, however I think there is no Danger
                    of <lb/>wounding it, if you open the inferior part of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Scrotum</hi>, and not with too long a Lancet. <pb n="39"/><lb/>During the
                    Evacuation, the <hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi> muſt be <lb/>regularly preſs'd;
                    and after the Operation a <lb/>little piece of dry Lint and ſticking Plaiſter
                    are <lb/>ſufficient. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> Method of Tapping is call'd <hi
                        rend="italic">The <w part="I">Pal-</w><lb/><w part="F">liative</w>
                    Cure</hi>; not but that it does now and then <lb/>prove an absſlute one. To
                    prevent the <w part="I">Re-</w><lb/><w part="F">lapſe</w> of this Diſeaſe,
                    Surgeons preſcribe the <lb/>making a large Wound, either by Inciſion or
                    <lb/>Cauſtick, that upon healing it afterwards, the <lb/>Firmneſs and
                    Contraction of the Cicatrix may <lb/>bind up the relaxed lymphatic Veſſels, and
                    <lb/>obſtruct the further preternatural Effuſion of <lb/>their Contents: But by
                    what I have ſeen of <lb/>this Practice, it is attended with ſo much <w part="I"
                        >dan-</w><lb/><w part="F">er</w>, that, notwithſtanding its succeſs in the
                    <lb/>end, I believe whoever reads the following <lb/>Caſes will be apt to
                    diſcard the Method, and <lb/>abide rather by the Palliative Cure. </p>
                <div type="section">
                    <head rend="space align-center"><lb/>CASE I.</head>
                    <p rend="space indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">A. B.</hi> aged 44, a ſtrong Man,
                        never in his <lb/>Life having been ſubject to any other <w part="I"
                            >Infirmi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ty</w>, put himſelf under my care for the
                        Relief <lb/>of a <hi rend="italic">Hydrocele</hi> on the left ſide of the
                            <hi rend="italic"><w part="I">Scro-</w><lb/><w part="F">tum</w></hi>. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">December 3</hi>, 1733, I diſcharged the
                        Water, <lb/>by making an Inciſion through the Teguments <pb n="40"
                        /><lb/>about four Inches long. Towards Night he <lb/>grew feveriſh, got no
                        reſt; the <hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi> and <lb/>Teſticle on that ſide
                        beginning to inflame, and <lb/>the capillary Arteries (dilating) to bleed
                        freely. <lb/>He was ſeized too with a violent Pain in his <lb/>Back, which
                        was in a great meaſure remov'd <lb/>by ſuſpending the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Scrotum</hi> with a Bag-Truſs. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">From</hi> the 3d to the 7th, continued in a
                        mſst <lb/>dangerous condition, when the Fever tended <lb/>to a Criſis, by
                        the Suppuration of both Wound <lb/>and Teſticle. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">From</hi> the 7th to the 24th, he daily
                        acquired <lb/>Strength; but the Diſcharge from the Teſticle <lb/>increaſing,
                        and the Sinus penetrating now very <lb/>deep towards the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Septum Scroti</hi>, I opened the <lb/>Body of the Teſticle the whole
                        length of the <lb/>Abſceſs. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">From</hi> the 24th, the Diſcharge leſſen'd
                            <w part="I">ſur-</w><lb/><w part="F">priſingly</w>, ſo that in ſix days,
                        the Surface of the <lb/>greateſt part of the Teſticle united with the
                            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>, and there remain'd only a
                        ſuperficial <lb/>Wound, which was intirely cicatris'd on <hi rend="italic"
                            >Jan. <lb/>10</hi>, 1733-4. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">March 31</hi>, 1737, he continued in
                        perfect <lb/>Health.</p>
                </div>
                <pb n="41"/>
                <div type="section">
                    <head rend="space align-center"><lb/>CASE II.</head>
                    <p rend="space indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> the Year 1733, I made an
                        Inciſion thro' <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                            >Tunica Vaginalis</hi> of a Boy <w part="I">a-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                            >bout</w> eight years of age, who narrowly <w part="I">eſca-</w><lb/><w
                            part="F">ped</w> with his Life: but the Symptomatick <w part="I"
                            >Fe-</w><lb/><w part="F">ver</w> terminating at laſt in an Abſceſs of
                        the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>, it prov'd his Cure, though with
                        ſome <lb/>trouble, in a few Weeks.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head rend="space align-center"><lb/>CASE III.</head>
                    <p rend="space indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">A. C.</hi> aged 37, of a very hale
                        habit of <w part="I">Bo-</w><lb/><w part="F">dy</w>, had complained of a
                        Tumour on one ſide <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>, which
                        continuing to enlarge <lb/>for ſix Years, he apply'd to a Surgeon, who
                        <lb/>laid a ſmall Cauſtick on the upper part of it, <lb/>and opening the
                        Eſchar, empty'd near three <lb/>Pints of Water; but he relapſing ſoon after
                        <lb/>this, I undertook the abſolute Cure. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">December 15</hi>, 1736, I laid on the
                        anterior <lb/>and upper part of the <hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>, a
                        Cauſtick <w part="I">a-</w><lb/><w part="F">bout</w> ſix Inches long, and
                        one broad. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">December 16</hi>, by a ſmall Puncture
                        through <lb/>the Eſchar, I emptied above a Quart of <lb/>Water. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">From</hi> the 17th to the 24th, he continued
                        <lb/>in a great deal of Pain, not only in the Part, <lb/>but in his Back and
                        Loins, and had very little <pb n="42"/><lb/>rest; the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Scrotum</hi> on that ſide became <w part="I">exceed-</w><lb/><w
                            part="F">ingly</w> inflam'd and thicken'd, the <w part="I"
                            >ſymptoma-</w><lb/><w part="F">tic</w> Fever running very high, without
                        any <lb/>ſigns of the Digeſtion of the Wound. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">On</hi> the 24th at night he grew a little
                            <w part="I">ea-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſier</w>, and continued ſo till the
                        29th, when the <lb/>Slough ſeparated; but the Wound retained <lb/>ſtill a
                        bad Aſpect, no Granulations appearing <lb/>on its Surface. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">From</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Decemb. 29</hi>, to <hi rend="italic">Jan. 5</hi>, he
                        remain'd <lb/>in the ſame ſtate. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">From</hi> the 5th to the 13th, the <w
                            part="I">Swel-</w><lb/><w part="F">ling</w> and Pain rather increas'd,
                        and that night <lb/>he was ſeized with an Ague Fit, which <w part="I"
                            >re-</w><lb/><w part="F">turn'd</w> every other day twice more. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">From</hi> the 17th to the 26th, the Ague <w
                            part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> ſtopt, he began to alter much
                        for the <w part="I">bet-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w>, a couple of
                        Impoſthumations on the <hi rend="italic"><w part="I">Scro-</w><lb/><w
                                part="F">tum</w></hi> being in this interim opened. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">By</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Feb. 2</hi>, the Pain was quite gone, the <lb/>Tumour very
                        much ſunk, and the Induration <lb/>ſoftened. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> a very few days after, the Wound <w
                            part="I">cica-</w><lb/><w part="F">tris'd</w>, and on <hi rend="italic"
                            >Feb. 24</hi>, I left him in perfect <lb/>Health, and free from any
                        complaint. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Having</hi> in the preceding Caſes been <w
                            part="I">threat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ened</w> with the Death of the
                        Patients, I tried <lb/>the following Experiment, upon the <w part="I"
                            >reputa-</w><pb n="43"/><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of its having been
                        done with Succeſs by <lb/>others.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head rend="space align-center"><lb/>CASE IV.</head>
                    <p rend="space indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">A.D.</hi> aged Forty-two, had for
                        near four <lb/>years been troubled with a <hi rend="italic">Hydrocele</hi>
                        on one <lb/>ſide, for which I had tapp'd him about <w part="I"
                            >do-</w><lb/><w part="F">zen</w> times, taking away near a Pint of clear
                        <lb/>Water each Operation. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Jan. 3</hi>, 1736-7, after having
                        emptied the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tunica Vaginalis</hi>, I injected an
                        Ounce of <w part="I">Spi-</w><lb/><w part="F">rit</w> of Wine; in the
                        inſtant he complained of <lb/>great Pain, which continued to increaſe, and
                        <lb/>the next day the Teguments were very much <lb/>augmented in their bulk
                        and thickneſs. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Jan. 7</hi>, the Tenſion became
                        violently <lb/>painful, and perceiving a Fluctuation, I made <lb/>a
                        Puncture, and he voided about half a Pint <lb/>of Water, very deeply tinged
                        with Blood, but <lb/>without any flavour of the Spirits to be <w part="I"
                            >diſtin-</w><lb/><w part="F">guiſh'd</w> by the ſmell: This gave him
                        ſome <lb/>eaſe, but the Inflammation and Thickneſs <w part="I"
                            >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tinued</w> a whole month, and then terminated
                        in <lb/>a couple of Abſceſſes on the forepart of the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
                            >Scrotum</hi>, which I open'd the 7th of <hi rend="italic">February</hi>
                        <lb/>following, and on their Diſcharge the whole <lb/>Tumour ſubſided,
                        leaving a firm Cicatrix and <lb/>abſolute Cure of that Diſorder. </p>
                    <pb n="44"/>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Something</hi> ſimilar to the Circumſtance
                        of <lb/><hi rend="italic">A. D</hi>'s bloody Water is the Caſe of another
                        <lb/>Perſon who was under my care: He had at <lb/>conſiderable intervals of
                        time been often tapp'd, <lb/>diſcharging that ſort of ſerous Water the <hi
                            rend="italic"><w part="I">Tu-</w><lb/><w part="F">nica</w>
                            Vaginalis</hi> for the moſt part yields; at laſt <lb/>it became tinged
                        with Blood, and every time <lb/>grew more bloody than the other: The fourth
                        <lb/>Diſcharge of this kind was attended with a <lb/>remarkable Hæmorrhage,
                        and terminated in an <lb/>abſolute Cure; no ſigns of a Relapſe <w part="I"
                            >appear-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> ſome Months after, as I had an <w
                            part="I">opportuni-</w><lb/><w part="F">ty</w> to inform myſelf. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">To</hi> the Caſes above recited I could add
                        ſtill <lb/>more that have fallen within my know]edge <lb/>ſince the time I
                        made theſe Obſervations; <w part="I">par-</w><lb/><w part="F">ticularly</w>
                        two, attended with Inflammation and <lb/>Abſceſs, from the mere Puncture of
                        the <w part="I">Lan-</w><lb/><w part="F">cet</w>; both of which terminated
                        in an abſolute <lb/>Cure. It may be remark'd however of theſe <lb/>two, that
                        one was attended with a thickened <lb/>Tunick, and the Water bloody; and in
                        the <lb/>other, the Coat was thickened, and the <hi rend="italic"><w
                                part="I">Epidi-</w><lb/><w part="F">dymis</w></hi> inlarged and
                        indurated from a former <w part="I">Go-</w><lb/><w part="F">norrhœa</w>. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">I would</hi> not however be underſtood from
                        <lb/>this Catalogue of Miſfortunes, that the <w part="I">Opera-</w><lb/><w
                            part="F">tion</w> is never performed with Safety; a few <pb n="45"
                        /><lb/>Examples I have known in its favour, but by <lb/>no means enough to
                        balance the bad Effects <lb/>of it. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">'Tis</hi> worth obſerving, that upon <w
                            part="I">examina-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of the ſeveral <hi
                            rend="italic">Hydrocele</hi>'s after their Cure, <lb/>it appeared
                        evidently it was wrought by an <lb/>univerſal Adheſion of the Teſticle to
                        the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tunica Vaginalis</hi>, and again of that Coat to
                        <lb/>the Parts enveloping it; from which <w part="I">Obſerva-</w><lb/><w
                            part="F">tion</w> it will not be difficult to conceive how it
                        <lb/>happens, that Diſcharges of bloody Water work <lb/>a Cure; ſince
                        Inflammations of Membranes <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">moſt</w>
                        perpetually produce Adheſions of the <lb/>neighbouring Parts, and theſe
                        Diſcharges are <lb/>no other than a mixture of Blood with the <lb/>Water
                        from the ruptur'd Veſſels of the <w part="I">infla-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                            >med</w> Tunick. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> has been ſuggeſted that probably the
                            <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſing</w> the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Tunica Vaginalis</hi> to the Air, might <lb/>occaſion the
                        abovemention'd Diſorders; but <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſides</w>
                        that the Caſe of the injected <hi rend="italic">Sp. Vin.</hi> the <lb/>Caſe
                        of the Cauſtick and the two Punctures, <lb/>are ſufficient Anſwers to that
                        Opinion, the <w part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtances</w> I have ſeen of
                        the whole <hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>
                        <w part="I">ſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">parating</w> in a Gangrene from the <hi
                            rend="italic">Tunica <w part="I">Vagi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                            >nalis</w></hi>, and leaving it naked a great many days <lb/>without any
                        ill effect, put it out of diſpute <lb/>that 'tis the mere Inflammation of
                        the Tunick <pb n="46"/><lb/>produces the Danger. I have caſtrated two
                        <lb/>Men, whoſe ſcirrhous Teſticles were <w part="I">accom-</w><lb/><w
                            part="F">panied</w> with a <hi rend="italic">Hydrocele</hi>, but the
                        whole <w part="I">Tuni-</w><lb/><w part="F">ca Vaginalis</w> being carried
                        off by the <w part="I">Opera-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, they both
                        recover'd without any bad <lb/>Symptoms. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">I shall</hi> finiſh this Chapter with a
                        further <lb/>Remark on the ſuppoſed variety of <hi rend="italic"><w part="I"
                                >Hydroce-</w><lb/><w part="F">le</w></hi>'s. Beſides the imaginary
                        one already <w part="I">ſpeci-</w><lb/><w part="F">fied</w> between the <hi
                            rend="italic">Scrotum</hi> and inferior <w part="I">Mem-</w><lb/><w
                            part="F">branes</w>, there is mention made of a Species of <lb/>Dropſy
                        between the <hi rend="italic">Cremaster Muſcle</hi> and <hi rend="italic"><w
                                part="I">Tu-</w><lb/><w part="F">nica</w> Vaginalis</hi>, call'd the
                            <hi rend="italic">Encryſted Hydrocele</hi>: <lb/>But I judge it more
                        likely to be within-ſide the <lb/>Coat, which adhering in different Places
                        to the <lb/>Spermatick Cord, may form a Cyſt or two <w part="I"
                            >be-</w><lb/><w part="F">tween</w> the Adheſions, of which an inſtance
                        has <lb/>fallen under my own Examination. Indeed if we <lb/>reflect on the
                        Cauſe of a Dropſy of this Part, <lb/>we muſt neceſſarily confine it to the
                        Inſide of <lb/>the Membrane, where only is that order of <w part="I"
                            >Veſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſels</w> which are the Subject of the Diſeaſe.
                        The <lb/>Dropſy of the <hi rend="italic">Teſtis</hi> itſelf is the laſt
                        ſuppos'd <lb/>Species, but it's what I have never ſeen; and <lb/>from the
                        Analogy of the <hi rend="italic">Teſtis</hi> to the Structure <lb/>of other
                        Glands, that are not pretended to <lb/>become Dropſical, I am ſuſpicious
                        there is no <lb/>ſuch Diſtemper. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <pb n="47"/>
            <div type="chapter">
                <figure rend="space">
                    <lb/>
                    <figDesc>A decorative horizontal line, spanning the whole page.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <head rend="space align-center size(1.25)"><lb/>CHAP. X. <lb/><space dim="vertical"
                        unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
                    <lb/><hi rend="italic">Of CASTRATION</hi>. </head>
                <p rend="space"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HIS is one of the moſt melancholy <w
                        part="I">Ope-</w><lb/><w part="F">rations</w> in the Practice of Surgery,
                    ſince <lb/>it ſeldom takes place but in Diſorders into <lb/>which the Patient is
                    very apt to relapſe, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
                    <lb/>thoſe of a Schirrhus, or Cancer, for under moſt <lb/>of the Symptoms
                    deſcribed as rendering it <w part="I">ne-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceſſary</w>, it is
                    abſolutely improper; ſuch as a <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hydrocele</hi>, Abſceſs of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Teſtis</hi>, an increaſing <lb/>Mortification, or what is
                    ſometimes underſtood <lb/>by a <hi rend="italic">Sarcocele</hi>; of which laſt
                    it may not be <lb/>amiſs to ſay a Word. In the utmoſt latitude <lb/>of the
                    meaning of this Term, 'tis receiv'd as <lb/>a fleſhy Swelling of the Teſticle
                    itſelf, call'd <lb/>likewiſe <hi rend="italic">Hernia Carnoſa</hi>; or in ſome
                        <w part="I">Inlarge-</w><lb/><w part="F">ments</w>, ſuch as in a Clap, more
                    frequently <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hernia Humoralis</hi>; but generally ſpeaking
                    is <lb/>conſider'd as a fleſhy Excreſcence form'd on <lb/>the Body of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Teſtis</hi>, which becoming <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">ceeding</w> hard and tumefied, for the moſt part <lb/>is ſuppos'd
                    to demand Extirpation, either by <lb/>burning away the Induration, or amputating
                    <lb/>the Teſticle: But this Maxim too <w part="I">precipitate-</w><pb n="48"
                        /><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> receiv'd, has, I apprehend, very much <w part="I"
                        >miſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">guided</w> the Practitioners of Surgery. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> order to conceive better of the <w
                        part="I">Diſtinc-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> I'm going to make, it muſt be
                        <w part="I">remem-</w><lb/><w part="F">bred</w>, that what is call'd the
                    Teſticle, is <w part="I">real-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> compos'd of two
                    different parts; one <w part="I">Glan-</w><lb/><w part="F">dular</w>, which is
                    the Body of the <hi rend="italic">Teſtis</hi> itſelf; <lb/>and one Vaſcular or
                    Membranous, known by <lb/>the name of <hi rend="italic">Epididymis</hi>, which
                    is the <w part="I">begin-</w><lb/><w part="F">ning</w> of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Vas Deferens</hi>, or the Collection of <lb/>the excretory Ducts of the
                    Gland. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Now</hi> it ſometimes happens that this Part is
                    <lb/>tumefied, independent of the Teſticle, and <lb/>feeling like a large
                    adventitious Excreſcence, <lb/>anſwers very well to the Idea moſt Surgeons
                    <lb/>form of a <hi rend="italic">Sarcocele</hi>; but not being aware of <lb/>the
                    different Nature and Texture of the <hi rend="italic"><w part="I"
                            >Epi-</w><lb/><w part="F">didymis</w></hi>, they have frequently
                    confounded its <lb/>Diſorders with thoſe of the Teſticle itſelf, and
                    <lb/>equally recommended Extirpation in the <w part="I">Indu-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">ration</w> of one or the other. But without <w part="I"
                        >ti-</w><lb/><w part="F">ring</w> the Reader with particular Hiſtories of
                    <lb/>Caſes relating to this Subject, I ſhall only ſay, <lb/>That from diligent
                    enquiry I have collected, <lb/>that all Indurations of the glandular Part of
                    <lb/>the Teſticle not tending to Inflammation and <lb/>Abſceſs, generally, if
                    not always, lead on to <lb/>Scirrhus and Cancer; whereas thoſe of the <pb n="49"
                        /><lb/><hi rend="italic">Epididymis</hi> ſeldom or never do. It is true, in
                    <lb/>ſpite of internal or external Means, theſe laſt <lb/>often retain their
                    Hardneſs, and ſometimes <lb/>ſuppurate, but however without much danger <lb/>in
                    either Caſe. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">'Twill</hi> not be hard to account for this <w
                        part="I">dif-</w><lb/><w part="F">ference</w> of Conſequences from Tumours
                    of <lb/>ſeemingly one and the ſame Body, when we <lb/>reflect how much it is the
                    nature of cancerous <lb/>Poiſons to fix upon Glands, and how different <lb/>the
                        <hi rend="italic">Epididymis</hi> is from a Gland, though ſo <lb/>nearly in
                    the neighbourhood of one. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">I would</hi> not have it ſuppoſed from what I
                    <lb/>have ſaid, that the <hi rend="italic">Epididymis</hi> never becomes
                    <lb/>Cancerous; I confeſs it may, ſo may <lb/>every part of the human Body: But
                    I <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">vance</w>, that it rarely or never is ſo,
                    but from <lb/>an Affection of the Glandular Part of the <lb/>Teſticle firſt,
                    which indeed ſeldom fails to <lb/>taint, and by degrees to confound it in ſuch
                    <lb/>manner as to make one Maſs of the two. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Before</hi> we caſtrate, it is laid down as a
                    <lb/>Rule to inquire whether the Patient has any <lb/>Pain in his Back, and in
                    that Caſe to reject <lb/>the Operation, upon the reaſonable <w part="I"
                        >Preſump-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of the Spermatick Veſſels being
                    likewiſe <lb/>diſeaſed; but we are not to be too haſty in <lb/>this
                    Determination; for the mere weight of <pb n="50"/><lb/>the Tumour ſtretching the
                    Cord, will <w part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F">times</w> create the Complaint.
                    To learn the <lb/>Cauſe then of this Pain in the Back, when the <lb/>Spermatick
                    Cord is not thickened, let your <w part="I">Pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tient</w> be
                    kept in bed, and ſuſpend his <hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>
                    <lb/>in a Bag-Truſs, which will relieve him if <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w
                        part="F">ordered</w> by the weight only; but if the <w part="I"
                        >Sper-</w><lb/><w part="F">matick</w> Cord is thickened or indurated, which
                    <lb/>Diſeaſe, when attended with a Dilatation of <lb/>the Veſſels of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>, is deſcribed by the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
                        >Latins</hi> under the name of <hi rend="italic">Ramex</hi>, (though it
                    <lb/>is more now known by the <hi rend="italic">Greek</hi> Appellations <lb/><hi
                        rend="italic">Circocele</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Varicocele</hi>) the Caſe
                    is deſperate <lb/>and not to be undertaken. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> ſuppoſing no obſtacle in the way to
                    <lb/>the Operation, the Method of doing it may <lb/>be this: Lay your Patient on
                    a ſquare Table <lb/>of about three foot four Inches high, letting <lb/>his Legs
                    hang down, which, as well as the <lb/>reſt of his Body, muſt be held firm by the
                    <lb/>Aſſiſtants. Then with a Knife begin your <lb/>Wound above the Rings of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Abdominal</hi>
                    <lb/>Muſcles, that you may have room afterwards <lb/>to tie the Veſſels, ſince
                    for want of this <w part="I">Cau-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> Operators will
                    neceſſarily be puzzled in <lb/>making the Ligature: then carrying it through
                    <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Membrana Adipoſa</hi>, it muſt be continued
                    <lb/>downward, the length of it to be in <w part="I">propor-</w><pb n="51"
                        /><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> to the ſize of the Teſticle. If it is very
                    <lb/>ſmall, it may be diſſected away without taking <lb/>off any part of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>; but I am not <lb/>very fond of this Method,
                    becauſe ſo much <lb/>looſe flabby Skin is apt to form Abſceſſes <w part="I"
                        >af-</w><lb/><w part="F">terwards</w>, and very frequently grow callous.
                    <lb/>If the Teſticle, for Inſtance, weighs twenty <lb/>Ounces; having made one
                    Inciſion about five <lb/>inches long, a little circularly, begin a ſecond
                    <lb/>in the ſame Point as the firſt, bringing it <lb/>with an oppoſite Sweep to
                    meet the other in <lb/>the inferior Part, in ſuch a manner as to cut <lb/>out
                    the ſhape of an Oval, whoſe <w part="I">ſmal-</w><lb/><w part="F">leſt</w>
                    Diameter ſhall be two inches: After <lb/>this, diſſect the body of the Tumour,
                    with <lb/>the piece of Skin on it from the <hi rend="italic">Scrotum</hi>, firſt
                    <lb/>taking up ſome of the Blood-Veſſels if the <lb/>Hæmorrhage is dangerous.
                    Then paſs a <lb/>Ligature round the Cord, pretty near the <hi rend="italic"><w
                            part="I">Ab-</w><lb/><w part="F">domen</w></hi>, and if you have ſpace
                    between the <w part="I">Li-</w><lb/><w part="F">gature</w> and Teſticle, a
                    ſecond about half an inch <lb/>lower, to make the ſtoppage of Blood ſtill
                    <lb/>more ſecure. The Ligatures may be tied with <lb/>what is call'd the <hi
                        rend="italic">Surgeon<hi rend="roman">'s</hi> Knot</hi>, where the
                    <lb/>Thread is paſs'd through the Ring twice. This <lb/>done, cut off the
                    Teſticle a little underneath <lb/>the ſecond Ligature, and treat your Patient as
                    <lb/>in other freſh Wounds. </p>
                <pb n="52"/>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">I once</hi> caſtrated a Man whoſe Teſticle
                    <lb/>weighed above three Pounds, where ſome of <lb/>the Veſſels were ſo
                    exceeding varicous and <lb/>dilated as nearly to equal the ſize of the
                    <lb/>Humeral Artery; however, I took up two <lb/>or three of the moſt
                    conſiderable, and <lb/>purſued the Operation, cutting away near <lb/>three
                    fourths of the Skin, by which means I <lb/>avoided a dangerous Effuſion, as by
                    dividing <lb/>the Veſſels before they were much ramified, <lb/>I had fewer
                    Ligatures to make: The Succeſs <lb/>anſwer'd the Deſign, and the Patient
                    ſurviv'd <lb/>the Operation and healing of the Wound, <lb/>but the cancerous
                    Humour falling on his <lb/>Liver ſome time after, deſtroy'd him. In <lb/>large
                    Tumours, ſuch as the laſt I have <w part="I">men-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                    >tion'd</w>, it is very much to be advis'd to cut <lb/>away great part of the
                    Skin; for beſides that <lb/>the Hæmorrhage will be much leſs in this <lb/>caſe,
                    and the Operation greatly ſhorten'd; <lb/>the Skin by the great Diſtenſion
                    having been <lb/>render'd very thin, will great part of it, if not <lb/>taken
                    away, ſphacelate, and the reſt be more <lb/>prone to degenerate into a cancerous
                    Ulcer. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> may be obſerv'd, I do not, in order to
                    <lb/>avoid wounding the Spermatick Veſſels, <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                        >commend</w> pinching up the Skin before the <lb/>Inciſion, and afterwards
                    thruſting the Fingers <pb n="53"/><lb/>between the <hi rend="italic">Membrana
                        Adipoſa</hi> and the <w part="I">Teſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ticle</w>, to tear
                    the one from the other; the <lb/>firſt is not dextrous, and the other is cruel,
                    <lb/>and both of them, in my opinion, are <w part="I">calcu-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                        >lated</w> to prevent what there is little or no <lb/>danger of. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <figure rend="space">
                    <lb/>
                    <figDesc>A decorative horizontal line, spanning the whole page.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <head rend="space align-center size(1.25)"><lb/>CHAP. XI. <lb/><space dim="vertical"
                        unit="lines" quantity="1"/>
                    <lb/><hi rend="italic">Of the PHYMOSIS</hi>.</head>
                <p rend="space"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE <hi rend="italic">Phymoſis</hi>
                    ſignifies no more than <lb/>ſuch a ſtraightneſs of the Prepuce, that <lb/>the
                    Glans cannot be denuded, which if it <lb/>becomes troubleſome ſo as to prevent
                    the <lb/>Egreſs of the Urine, or conceal under it <lb/>Chancres, or foul Ulcers,
                    quite out of the <lb/>reach of Application, is to be cut open. It <lb/>ſometimes
                    happens that Children are born <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                    >perforate</w>, in which caſe a ſmall Puncture, <lb/>dreſs'd afterwards with a
                    Tent, effects a Cure: <lb/>But this Operation is chiefly practis'd in <w
                        part="I">ve-</w><lb/><w part="F">nereal</w> Caſes, in order to expoſe
                    Chancres <lb/>either on the Glans or withinſide the Prepuce <lb/>it ſelf: And
                    here, if the Prepuce is not very <lb/>callous and thick, a mere Inciſion will <w
                        part="I">an-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſwer</w>, which may be made either with the
                        <pb n="54"/><lb/>Sciſſars, or by ſlipping a Knife between the <lb/>Skin and
                    Glans to the very extremity, and <lb/>cutting it up: This laſt Method is more
                    <lb/>eaſy than that of the Sciſſars, but it is <lb/>much ſafer to make the Wound
                    on one <lb/>ſide the Prepuce than upon the upper part, <lb/>for I have ſometimes
                    ſeen the great Veſſels <lb/>on the <hi rend="italic">Dorsum Penis</hi> afford a
                    terrible <w part="I">Hæ-</w><lb/><w part="F">morrhage</w>, which may be avoided
                    by <w part="I">follow-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> this Rule. </p>
                <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">If</hi> the Prepuce be very large and indurated,
                    <lb/>the Opening alone will not ſuffice, and it is more <lb/>adviſeable to take
                    away the Calloſity by <w part="I">Cir-</w><lb/><w part="F">cumciſion</w>, which
                    muſt be performed with a <lb/>Knife; and if the Artery bleeds much, it <lb/>muſt
                    be taken up with a ſmall Needle and <lb/>Ligature. </p>
            </div>
            <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="54"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
