<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Kirkland: An essay on the methods of suppressing hæmorrhages from
          divided arteries</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Thomas Kirkland</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">An ESSAY on the Methods of suppressing HÆMORRHAGES from Divided
              Arteries. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T53266</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T53266"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London : printed for R. and J. Dodsley, in Pall-Mall,
                  MDCCLXIII.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1763</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="6"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="53"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3306950477</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K047937.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Surgical or anatominal work"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2" n="v"/>
        <head rend="align-center size(1.5)"><lb/>ADVERTISEMENT. </head>
        <p rend="italic"><lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">N</hi>Otwithſtanding much has been <lb/>lately wrote
          upon this ſubject, <lb/>yet no one ſeems to have conſidered it <lb/>thoroughly. The author
          therefore begs <lb/>leave to offer the reſult of his enquiries <lb/>concerning this
          matter, imagining, if <lb/>he has gone farther than other writers, <lb/>that he is doing
          ſome ſervice to the Art <lb/>of Surgery, though this Eſſay ſhould <lb/>(as it probably
          will) fall ſhort of <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">fection</w>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_3" n="vii"/>
        <head rend="align-center size(1.7)"><lb/>INTRODUCTION. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(4)">W</hi>HOEVER takes a view of <lb/>the late
          well-intended <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tempts</w> to recommend a leſs
          <lb/>painful method of ſuppreſſing the <w part="I">hæ-</w><lb/><w part="F">morrhage</w>
          from divided arteries, than <lb/>is generally practiſed, will find that <lb/>theſe writers
          have omitted to aſcertain <lb/>by proper experiments the principles <lb/>on which the
          ſuppreſſion depends; <lb/>and upon enquiry the different <w part="I">theo-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ries</w> which have been invented by other <lb/>writers will appear to be
          greatly <w part="I">defi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cient</w>, and deſtitute of any fact or <w
            part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">periment</w> ſufficient to evince their truth. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_4" n="viii"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Indeed Mr. Gooch<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Caſes,
            p. 140. London 1758. </note> has conſidered <lb/>this affair nearly in its true light;
          but <lb/>as what he ſays is only conjectural, it <lb/>ſeems not to have gained preference
          <lb/>to the other hypotheſes which have <lb/>been advanced; a very ingenious <w part="I"
            >ſur-</w><lb/><w part="F">geon</w> at this time adopting the opinion <lb/>of
            Pouteau<note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† Mr. White on Spunge. </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In fact, this part of practice has <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ways</w> been defective, by not learning <lb/>from nature the true intentions to be
          <lb/>anſwered. Hence, from not acting <lb/>upon right principles, remedies have <lb/>been
          applied at random; and nature <lb/>has often effected a cure, in <w part="I"
            >oppoſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> to the moſt barbarous and <w part="I">im-</w><pb
            xml:id="page_5" n="ix"/><lb/><w part="F">proper</w> applications. The different
          <lb/>ſpecifics which have been cried up <lb/>and in vogue, and the multiplicity of
          <lb/>remedies, ſufficiently point out the <lb/>uncertainty with which this ſubject
          <lb/>has been treated; for had the <w part="I">princi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ples</w> on
          which we were to proceed <lb/>been aſcertained, the moſt effectual <lb/>applications would
          eaſily have been <lb/>diſcovered, and the reſt diſcarded as <lb/>uſeleſs. And though ſince
          the needle <lb/>and ligature were introduced, we have <lb/>been more ſteady in our
          practice, yet <lb/>I apprehend we have, even in this <lb/>particular, been not quite free
          from <lb/>imperfection.—And were we not ſo <lb/>unſettled, as to be near giving it up
          <lb/>for remedies recommended with only <lb/>ſuppoſed advantages? </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_6" n="x"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The following eſſay is therefore <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tended</w> to ſupply theſe defects; and I <lb/>hope, by proper experiments, and
          <lb/>giving a new light to ſeveral facts, I <lb/>have both aſcertained the principles
          <lb/>on which a ſuppreſſion of the flux <lb/>from divided arteries depends, and <lb/>what
          method moſt ſafely and <w part="I">effec-</w><lb/><w part="F">tually</w>, under different
          circumſtances, <lb/>anſwers this purpoſe. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_7"/>
      <head rend="align-center"><lb/></head>
      <p rend="align-center"><lb/>AN <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">ESSAY</hi>
        <lb/>ON THE <lb/><hi rend="sc size(1.5)">Methods of Suppressing </hi><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)"
          >HÆMORRHAGES</hi>
        <lb/>FROM <lb/><hi rend="sc dc(2)">Divided Arteries</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="align-center"/>
      <div n="1" type="chapter">
        <head rend="align-center italic"><lb/><hi rend="roman size(1.5)">CHAP. I.</hi>
          <lb/>Of the natural or ſpontaneous ſuppreſſion of <lb/>Hæmorrhages from divided arteries. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(4)">W</hi>HEN agaric of the oak was firſt <lb/>introduced
          in England, for <w part="I">ſup-</w><lb/><w part="F">preſſing</w> the hæmorrhage from
          <lb/>divided arteries, I made ſeveral <lb/>experiments to try in what manner it <w
            part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duced</w> its effects; and I was ſoon convinced,
          <lb/>that it had no other property than that of <w part="I">ad-</w><pb xml:id="page_8"
            n="2"/><lb/><w part="F">hering</w> cloſe to the mouth of the veſſel: this
          <lb/>circumſtance, together with conſidering how <lb/>often the ſmaller arteries cloſe
          themſelves by <lb/>their own natural contraction, and that it was <lb/>common for very
          conſiderable arteries to be <lb/>cloſed in the ſame manner, when the impulſe <lb/>of the
          blood was abated by the ſwooning <lb/>of the patient<note place="bottom" n="*"
            rend="size(0.5)">* See Baron Van Swieten's Comm. vol. ii, p. 34. and <lb/>Phil. Trans.
            No 449. p. 313. </note>, led me to imagine that the <lb/>ſame thing muſt of courſe
          happen in the large <lb/>arteries, provided the paſſage of the blood <lb/>through them be
          firſt intercepted for a time, <lb/>and that the cloſe contraction which was <w part="I"
            >ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerved</w> in thoſe arteries<note place="bottom" n="†"
            rend="size(0.5)">† Warner's Caſes, p. 136. </note> to which the agaric <lb/>had been
          applied, was intirely owing to the <lb/>courſe of the blood being impeded by <w part="I"
            >block-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> up the end of the veſſel. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Every day's experience confirmed me in <lb/>this opinion; for I found
          that the flux from <lb/>very conſiderable arteries was eaſily and <w part="I"
            >ef-</w><lb/><w part="F">fectually</w> ſuppreſſed by only making a <w part="I"
            >per-</w><lb/><w part="F">pendicular</w> preſſure a few minutes upon the <lb/>end of the
          veſſel.—But, in order to be more <pb xml:id="page_9" n="3"/><lb/>certain about this
          matter, in the latter end of <lb/>the year 1755 I made the following <w part="I"
            >experi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>After tying a large horſe down, Mr. Peale <lb/>of Maidſtone, then with
          me, took off one of <lb/>his hind legs about the middle of the thigh: <lb/>immediately
          upon the bone being divided, <lb/>the horſe drew the ſtump towards his body, <lb/>at which
          time the tourniquet ſlipt off, and five <lb/>arteries, the leaſt of them about the ſize of
          a <lb/>wheat-ſtraw, ſome near as large as a <w part="I">gooſe-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >quill</w>, and one much larger, poured out with <lb/>great vehemence; but an immediate
          ſtop was <lb/>put to the flux by a perſon preſſing with both <lb/>hands upon the wound;
          and by continuing <lb/>this preſſure fifteen minutes, the veſſels <w part="I"
            >be-</w><lb/><w part="F">came</w> ſo firmly cloſed as not to diſcharge the <lb/>leaſt
          drop of blood. However I paſſed a <lb/>needle and thread round one of the largeſt,
          <lb/>intending to make an experiment with the <lb/>ligature. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The pulſation at firſt was very plainly ſeen <lb/>at their
          extremities; but after ſome time it <lb/>became leſs perceptible, and the wound was <pb
            xml:id="page_10" n="4"/><lb/>covered with tow, which was kept on with <lb/>very ſlight
          bandage. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The horſe was kept alive forty-eight hours <lb/>after the operation;
          and though he tumbled <lb/>about and ſtruggled much in attempting to <lb/>raiſe himſelf
          up, yet there was not any return <lb/>of the hæmorrhage, nor did there appear the
          <lb/>leaſt pulſation. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>After he was killed we diſſected the thigh, <lb/>and found that the
          bleeding was not <w part="I">ſup-</w><lb/><w part="F">preſſed</w> by congealed blood, but
          by all the <lb/>veſſels being quite cloſe contracted for near an <lb/>inch or more from
          their extremity. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>After this I made more experiments of the <lb/>ſame kind upon brutes
          with the ſame ſucceſs, <lb/>and always found, upon diſſection, the ends <lb/>of the
          veſſels cloſe contracted for a <w part="I">conſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">derable</w> way: by
          removing my fingers from <lb/>time to time, while I preſſed upon the veſſel, <lb/>it was
          eaſy to diſcover this contraction taking <lb/>place by a gradual decreaſe of the ſtream of
          <lb/>blood; but in Auguſt 1757 the following caſe <lb/>gave a further light to this
          matter. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_11" n="5"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Jos. Ayre of Caudwell, about twenty years <lb/>of age, in being bled
          had the misfortune to <lb/>have the humeral artery opened along with <lb/>the baſilic
          vein, and the operator with much <lb/>difficulty ſuppreſſed the hæmorrhage by <w part="I"
            >ban-</w><lb/><w part="F">dage</w>: however a tumor with great pulſation <lb/>ſoon began
          to ariſe in the part wounded, <lb/>which in ſix or ſeven weeks increaſed to the <lb/>ſize
          of a pullet's egg. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The nature of the tumor was at once <w part="I">evi-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">dent</w>, and an eſchar on the upper part of it <lb/>being upon the point of
          ſeparation, <w part="I">deter-</w><lb/><w part="F">mined</w> me to perform the operation
          for the <lb/>aneuriſm. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The impulſe of the blood againſt the <w part="I">liga-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ture</w> at the time of the operation was very <lb/>great; and as part of the
          artery (whoſe <w part="I">dia-</w><lb/><w part="F">meter</w> was conſiderably enlarged)
          was expoſed, <lb/>its pulſation was remarkably viſible: but upon <lb/>removing the
          dreſſings the third day <w part="I">after-</w><lb/><w part="F">wards</w>, the pulſation
          could neither be ſeen nor <lb/>felt nearer to the ligature than an inch and <lb/>half;
          whence I was led to conclude, that the <lb/>artery had collapſed and gradually cloſed
          itſelf <pb xml:id="page_12" n="6"/><lb/>up to the neareſt lateral branches, as the <w
            part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſiſtance</w> towards the ligature abated from the
          <lb/>blood paſſing through thoſe veſſels.—And it <lb/>appeared to me ſelf-evident that
          nature always <lb/>took this ſtep to ſuppreſs the hæmorrhage <lb/>from divided arteries,
          when I reflected that <lb/>the ſame circumſtance conſtantly happens, <lb/>when the
          umbilical veſſels are divided at the <lb/>birth of the foetus. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>However, as I did not look for the lateral <lb/>branches in the
          experiments mentioned, I cut <lb/>off another horſe's tail near his body, and <w part="I"
            >ſup-</w><lb/><w part="F">preſſed</w> the hæmorrhage by preſſing a few <w part="I"
            >mi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nutes</w> with my fingers; and by a careful <w part="I"
            >diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſection</w> the next day after he was killed, I <lb/>found
          that the concluſion I had drawn was <lb/>(in this ſubject at leaſt) perfectly right. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Is it not owing to this cauſe that an <w part="I">hæ-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">morrhage</w> does not follow thoſe mortifications, <lb/>where the greateſt part
          of the limb is <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtroyed</w> and ſeparates? For if the
          great veſſels <lb/>were cloſed no farther than where the <w part="I">morti-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">fication</w> ends, a flux of blood muſt of courſe <lb/>enſue upon the coming
          away of the dead <pb xml:id="page_13" n="7"/><lb/>parts. Is not this evinced in a caſe
          lately <w part="I">pub-</w><lb/><w part="F">liſhed</w> by Mr. Antrobus<note place="bottom"
            n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Med. Obſerv. &amp; Inq. vol. ii. p. 152. </note>? where, though
          <lb/>the mortification ſtopped only two inches <lb/>above the ancle, yet it is probable
          that the <lb/>large arteries cloſed themſelves as far at leaſt <lb/>as where the femoral
          artery divides below <lb/>the knee; becauſe neither pulſation nor <w part="I"
            >hæ-</w><lb/><w part="F">morrhage</w> appeared when the leg was taken <lb/>off. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It will not, I imagine, appear at all <w part="I">ſur-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">priſing</w>, that the cloſing of the end of the <lb/>veſſel an inch only, or
          perhaps leſs, ſhould be <lb/>ſufficient to reſiſt the force of the circulation, <lb/>when
          it is conſidered, that this impulſe againſt <lb/>the end of the artery immediately becomes
          <lb/>leſs, and ſoon intirely ceaſes, from the blood <lb/>upon meeting with reſiſtance
          dilating and <lb/>paſſing through the neareſt lateral branches; <lb/>as is fully evident
          from the gradual decreaſe, <lb/>and at length the total diſappearance, of <w part="I"
            >pul-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſation</w>. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_14" n="8"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nor is this contraction of the artery and <lb/>the alteration in the
          courſe of the blood long <lb/>in taking place, as appears from the <w part="I"
            >experi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ments</w> mentioned: and beſides theſe, in many
          <lb/>inſtances I have obſerved, that arteries as large <lb/>as thoſe we commonly meet with
          in cutting <lb/>for the ſtone, or in taking off ſchirrous breaſts, <lb/>&amp;c. will for
          the moſt part, if they are wholly <lb/>divided, be effectually cloſed by preſſure in
          <lb/>three or four minutes. And if in taking off <lb/>a leg, we intercept the courſe of
          the blood <lb/>longer than is uſually done, moſt of the <w part="I">ar-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">teries</w> will often be cloſed, if the patient is in <lb/>a tolerable good
          habit, as I have learnt by <lb/>tying the large veſſels without looſening the
          <lb/>tourniquet. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I took off a woman's leg near the middle <lb/>of her thigh, and tied
          the large artery <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w part="F">out</w> looſening the tourniquet;
          upon ſetting it <lb/>at liberty, we obſerved ſome blood draining <lb/>down the muſcles
          from one artery only, and <lb/>though it had contracted itſelf ſo much as <lb/>ſcarce to
          admit the paſſage of any blood, yet <lb/>by the pulſation it appeared to be a very <w
            part="I">con-</w><pb xml:id="page_15" n="9"/><lb/><w part="F">ſiderable</w> veſſel, and
          on this account the <w part="I">li-</w><lb/><w part="F">gature</w> was uſed. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Several more, which did not bleed, were <lb/>diſcovered by a ſtrong
          pulſation at their <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">tremities</w>; and therefore,
          inſtead of <w part="I">immedi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ately</w> dreſſing the patient, we
          waited ten or <lb/>fifteen minutes, and gave her wine to raiſe <lb/>her ſpirits, ſo that
          we might ſee whether they <lb/>would bleed or not, and thereby prevent our <lb/>being
          alarmed with a freſh hæmorrhage after <lb/>ſhe was put to bed: but during this time the
          <lb/>pulſation gradually diſappeared, and the <w part="I">bleed-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ing</w> was effectually ſtopped. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Indeed, ſince I have attended to this <w part="I">cir-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">cumſtance</w> I have ſeen it ſo often happen, that <lb/>I am well convinced in
          amputations larger <lb/>veſſels have been truſted with lint and flour <lb/>than has
          generally been imagined; and that <lb/>when a freſh hæmorrhage returns ſome hours
          <lb/>after an operation, it is not from ſmall <w part="I">arte-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >teries</w> being dilated by an increaſed motion in <lb/>the blood, as has generally
          been thought, but <lb/>to the principal lateral branches which had <lb/>cloſed themſelves
          being again forced open. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_16" n="10"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>That the large arteries are alſo cloſed in a <lb/>very little time,
          does not only appear from the <lb/>experiment made upon the horſe's leg, but <lb/>likewiſe
          in ſeveral of thoſe caſes where the <lb/>courſe of the blood was intercepted, either by
          <lb/>the application of agaric or other fungous <w part="I">ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſtances</w>, eſpecially a caſe related by Mr. War-<lb/>ner<note place="bottom" n="*"
            rend="size(0.5)">* Caſes, p. 147, 148. </note>, where, <q rend="quotes">in an hour after
            the <w part="I">opera-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, the mouths of the veſſels were
            found <lb/>totally contracted, ſo as to reſiſt the whole <lb/>force of the
            circulation;</q> after which they <lb/>probably, like the umbilical veſſels, ſhrink
          <lb/>into a perfect cord, and become impervious.— <lb/>And does not nature ſeem to point
          out, that <lb/>intercepting the paſſage of the blood for a <lb/>while, is all that is
          required from art; as <lb/>ſome animals by inſtinct, in ſeparating their <lb/>young from
          the placenta, lacerate the cord <lb/>with their teeth, whence probably the ragged
          <lb/>fibres ſtop up the end of the veſſel by <w part="I">col-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >lapſing</w> over each other? </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Seeing then that nature ſuppreſſes the <w part="I">hæ-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">morrhage</w> from divided arteries by the natural <pb xml:id="page_17" n="11"
          /><lb/>contraction of their circular fibres, when the <lb/>impediment to this contraction
          is removed, <lb/>by intercepting the impulſe of the blood, let <lb/>us fairly enquire what
          method beſt anſwers <lb/>this purpoſe, beginning with the ligature, on <lb/>account of its
          having been long in general <lb/>uſe. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="chapter">
        <pb xml:id="page_18" n="12"/>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">CHAP. II.</hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Of the Ligature.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HE ſucceſs which has hitherto in <w part="I"
            >ge-</w><lb/><w part="F">neral</w> attended the ligature, is a full <lb/>proof of its
          efficacy; and it is evident <w part="I">no-</w><lb/><w part="F">thing</w> can more
          powerfully intercept the courſe <lb/>of the blood, provided it can be properly <w part="I"
            >ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">plied</w>: and though it ſeems to have been a <lb/>general
          opinion, that the veſſel only unites in <lb/>that part where the ſtricture is made, and
          <lb/>preference has on that account been lately <lb/>given to other remedies<note
            place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Philos. Trans. vol. xlvii. art. 94. </note>; yet
          I imagine, <lb/>from what has been ſaid, it will readily be <lb/>conceived that it is alſo
          in this caſe cloſed by <lb/>its own natural contraction, and which will <lb/>be found
          true, if the end of the artery can be <lb/>diſcovered. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But this is often difficult, it being at firſt <lb/>commonly covered
          with the ſwelled muſcles, <pb xml:id="page_19" n="13"/><lb/>and after ſome time ſends out
          (like all other <lb/>parts) new fleſh, and cannot be diſtinguiſhed: <lb/>therefore as a
          proof, I ſhall obſerve that the <lb/>artery which was tied in the horſe's leg, was
          <lb/>net only cloſed below, but alſo at leaſt half <lb/>an inch above the ligature; ſo
          that every <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">vantage</w> poſſible, in regard to ſtopping
          the <lb/>blood, is obtained, provided the end of the <lb/>veſſel does not ſeparate and
          come away with <lb/>the ligature; for though no inconvenience <lb/>will follow, if the
          ſtricture is made ſome <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">tance</w> from the lateral
          branches; yet, if it <lb/>happens to be very near, a freſh flux of blood <lb/>muſt enſue,
          which is probably one reaſon <lb/>why there are ſome few inſtances to be met <lb/>with of
          the arteries bleeding again ſome time <lb/>after they have been tied. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But, from attending ſeveral years to this <lb/>particular, I find that
          the end of the veſſel <lb/>does not ſo often come away as is imagined, <lb/>and that a
          ſeparation may be generally avoided, <lb/>as it only happens when the ligature is thin,
          <lb/>and very little ſubſtance is compriſed along <lb/>with the veſſel in the nooſe;
          whereas when <lb/>we take in a proper quantity of the <w part="I">circum-</w><pb
            xml:id="page_20" n="14"/><lb/><w part="F">jacent</w> parts to defend it, and the
          ligature is <lb/>of a proper ſize, upon digeſtion coming on it <lb/>becomes looſe and
          ſlips off, leaving the veſſel <lb/>firmly cloſed and intire. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>However, that we may avoid with as much <lb/>certainty as poſſible the
          ſeparation of the end <lb/>of the veſſel, I would adviſe that the ligature <lb/>ſhould be
          made of long twelve-penny flax, <lb/>without either being the leaſt twiſted or waxed
          <lb/>further than juſt the end, to make it paſs thro' <lb/>the eye of the needle; and if
          it is rubbed <lb/>over with ſome ſoft digeſtive, it will ſlip <w part="I">ea-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſily</w> through the fleſh. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This will be found ſufficiently ſtrong for <lb/>the purpoſe for which
          it is wanted, without <lb/>the leaſt danger of its injuring the veſſel; nor <lb/>need the
          compreſſure be greater than is juſt <lb/>neceſſary to intercept the paſſage of the blood,
          <lb/>which will ſtill add to the ſecurity in this <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſpect</w>, and at the ſame time produce other <lb/>advantages, as will be obſerved in
          their proper <lb/>place. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_21" n="15"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And further, if the ligature can be <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">perly</w> applied, it is equally effectual, whether <lb/>the artery be only in
          part or intirely divided; <lb/>whether it is at liberty to retract itſelf, or <w part="I"
            >ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">heres</w> to an undivided muſcle or the bone. <lb/>And if the
          needle can be paſſed a proper <lb/>depth into the adjacent parts, no accident <lb/>can
          remove it, if they are ſound, till the ſtate <lb/>of contraction and inflammation is over;
          <lb/>when, in general, all will have been done <lb/>that is neceſſary, the preſſure of the
          ſwelled <lb/>muſcles moſt effectually aſſiſting the cloſing <lb/>of the veſſels. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nevertheleſs, along with theſe advantages <lb/>it muſt be confeſſed,
          that great pain often <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">companies</w> the uſe of the
          ligature; which, where <lb/>it cannot be avoided, would make us prefer <lb/>any other
          remedy that is equally ſafe and <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">attended</w> with this
          inconvenience. But it very <lb/>fortunately happens, that where the ligature <lb/>is moſt
          wanted, it may be applied with very <lb/>little or no pain, if properly managed; for
          <lb/>the large arteries are commonly ſurrounded <lb/>with a conſiderable quantity of
          cellular <w part="I">mem-</w><pb xml:id="page_22" n="16"/><lb/><w part="F">brane</w>; and
          if we only take in with the veſſel <lb/>this nearly inſenſible ſubſtance, the patient
          <lb/>ſeems undiſturbed during the operation<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">*
            See Monro, Ed. Med. Eſs. vol. iv. p. 264. </note>: <lb/>and upon enquiring of ſeveral at
          the time of <lb/>tying the veſſel, whether they felt much pain, <lb/>I have always been
          anſwered in the negative; <lb/>and though the nerve which accompanies the <lb/>artery is
          incloſed in the nooſe, it makes no <lb/>difference in regard to this circumſtance. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Perhaps it may ſeem ſtrange to thoſe who <lb/>have not conſidered this
          matter, that great <lb/>pain ſhould not ariſe upon a nerve, which is <lb/>an organ of
          ſenſation, being compreſſed; but <lb/>there are ſeveral inſtances in the practice of
          <lb/>ſurgery, beſides this, which lead us to <w part="I">ima-</w><lb/><w part="F">gine</w>
          that the nerves are incapable of being <lb/>irritated, till they are diveſted of their <w
            part="I">cover-</w><lb/><w part="F">ings</w>, unleſs you penetrate through their coats
          <lb/>down to the medullary ſubſtance<note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† In
            performing the operation upon an aneuriſm ſome <lb/>time ſince, I accidentally had an
            opportunity of obſerving <lb/>the difference betwixt pricking and tying a nerve. <p
              rend="indent"><lb/>In paſſing the needle under the artery it penetrated the
              <lb/>nerve, upon which the patient inſtantly cried out of great <lb/>pain all down his
              arm, which ceaſed when the needle was <lb/>withdrawn. But though the ſame nerve was
              afterwards <lb/>incloſed in the ligature along with the artery, the patient <lb/>told
              me he only felt a prickling and numbneſs, which <lb/>ſoon went off. </p>
          </note>
          <w part="I">conſe-</w><pb xml:id="page_23" n="17"/><lb/><w part="F">quently</w>, when they
          are alſo defended by the <lb/>artery, fat, and cellular membrane, they will <lb/>ſtill be
          leſs liable to be affected. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This may be illuſtrated by reflecting on the <lb/>ſituation of the
          nerves in the bones, tendons, <lb/>membranes, and the like; where they ſeem <lb/>to be
          rendered inſenſible and incapable of <lb/>being irritated by the compactneſs of the
          <lb/>parts which inveſt them<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* It does not
            hence follow, that <q rend="quotes">wounds of the <w part="I">ten-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >dons</w> are the moſt eaſily cured of all others only by the <lb/>help of nature,
              without any trouble or bad ſymptom,</q>
            <lb/>as an author of eminence has aſſerted: and as it will <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">plain</w> part of what is hereafter ſaid about convulſions, we <lb/>ſhall
            juſt obſerve, that though the tendons in their <w part="I">natu-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ral</w> ſtate are void of ſenſibility, yet, when they become <lb/>ſwelled and tenſe,
            more painful and troubleſome <w part="I">ſymp-</w><lb/><w part="F">toms</w> generally
            ariſe in theſe than in other wounds; <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">bably</w> from
            the particular ſtructure of the part, by which <lb/>the obſtruction riſes higher and is
            long in terminating, <lb/>and the nerves during this ſtate are put more upon the
            <lb/>ſtretch than in any other part of the body. <lb/>But this does not hold good when a
            tendon is much <lb/>lacerated, or a large wound is made in any other <w part="I"
              >tendi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nous</w> part; for then they remain inſenſible, and give
            no <lb/>other diſturbance than from the length of time they take <lb/>to ſeparate; very
            likely from the obſtructed fluids being <lb/>freely diſcharged, and the nerves being in
            a ſtate of <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">laxation</w>. </note>, as appears from
            <pb xml:id="page_24" n="18"/><lb/>the new fleſh which follows their being <lb/>wounded,
          being ſenſible, and again loſing its <lb/>ſenſibility, as the part acquires its natural <w
            part="I">tex-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>With this we may obſerve that numbneſs, <lb/>the uſual conſequence of
          compreſſing a nerve, <lb/>cannot here give any uneaſineſs, becauſe the <lb/>parts to which
          the nerves were diſtributed are <lb/>removed. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>However, when the veſſels are ſo ſituated <lb/>that muſcular fibres
          muſt of courſe be <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">cloſed</w>, the ligature will
          unavoidably be <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tended</w> with conſiderable pain;
          owing <w part="I">proba-</w><lb/><w part="F">bly</w> to the nerves being diveſted of their
            <w part="I">cover-</w><lb/><w part="F">ings</w>, and their medullary ſubſtance alone <w
            part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">panded</w> over every fibre of a muſcle; not, I
          <lb/>imagine, in the form of papillæ, but in the <pb xml:id="page_25" n="19"/><lb/>ſame
          manner, though much thinner, as the <lb/>retina in the bottom of the eye<note
            place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* If I am not much miſtaken, in tracing the nerves
            <lb/>through the muſcles I have ſeen them become a perfect <lb/>mucus in this manner;
            and whoever will compare, by the <lb/>help of a proper glaſs, the medullary part of the
            brain or <lb/>a nerve cut open, with muſcular fibres, which are not <lb/>dried by being
            expoſed to the air, will find that they are <lb/>covered with a kind of pulp that has
            exactly the ſame <lb/>appearance. And does not an obſervation of Haller's <lb/>(Senſib.
            &amp; Irritab. p. 59.) ſeem to confirm this opinion; <lb/>for in attempting to prove
            that irritability reſides in the <lb/>glutinous mucus, he ſays, <q rend="quotes">the
              moſt irritable parts are <lb/>deprived of that quality only by robbing them of this
              <lb/>mucus by drying;</q> which is eaſily explained, if <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ſtead</w> of mere gluten, this proves to be the medullary part <lb/>of the
            nerve. <p rend="indent"><lb/>Hence too we may eaſily ſee, how every part of the
              <lb/>body (except thoſe which are ſecured by a particular <lb/>ſtructure) is liable to
              be affected by the point of the <lb/>fineſt needle. And how pain is carried by conſent
              of <lb/>parts all over the body, neither of which can be well <w part="I"
                >ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">counted</w> for, if the nerves are ſuppoſed to continue <w
                part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">tinct</w> cords to their extremities. </p>
          </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But this pain is only momentary, becauſe <lb/>whatever is incloſed
          becomes nearly inſenſible <lb/>upon the ſtricture being made. If the <w part="I"
            >liga-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w> recommended is uſed, the parts will be <pb
            xml:id="page_26" n="20"/><lb/>leſs irritated; and whether the abſolute <w part="I"
            >ſecu-</w><lb/><w part="F">rity</w> againſt a future hæmorrhage does not fully
          <lb/>compenſate for the uneaſineſs the patient feels <lb/>on this account, may be gathered
          from what <lb/>follows. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But it is thought, <q rend="quotes">that the ligature, by
            <lb/>compreſſing the adjacent nerve, is <w part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F">times</w>
            productive of convulſions.</q> Now as <lb/>no facts are brought to ſupport this opinion,
          <lb/>and as I have never yet ſeen any accident of <lb/>this kind happen, though I have
          always, <lb/>without regarding the nerve, freely uſed the <lb/>needle and ligature; nor,
          upon ſtrict enquiry, <lb/>found one inſtance of its happening amongſt <lb/>an extenſive
          chirurgical acquaintance, I am <lb/>induced to think with Mr. Sharp<note place="bottom"
            n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Crit. Inq. p. 291. </note>, that the <lb/>doctrine of
          convulſions being cauſed by the <lb/>tying of a nerve is merely ſpeculative, and
          <lb/>ſeems, though the theory is changed, to have <lb/>taken its riſe from the arguments
          brought <lb/>againſt Parey, when he firſt introduced the <lb/>practice of tying the
          arteries, and ſince to <lb/>have been copied from one to another by <w part="I"
            >ſuc-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceeding</w> writers. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_27" n="21"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But is it not probable that in this inſtance, <lb/>as well as many
          others in ſurgery, by quite <lb/>altering the meaning of the word <hi rend="sc"
            >nervus</hi> we <lb/>have made thoſe ſymptoms follow the tying <lb/>of a nerve, which
          ſhould have been <w part="I">conſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">dered</w> only as the conſequence
          of pricking a <lb/>tendon? for long after Parey's time <hi rend="sc">nervus</hi>
          <lb/>was uſed to ſignify <hi rend="sc">tendon</hi>, and by <q rend="quotes">ner-<lb/>voſam
            aliquam partem, vel nervum<note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† Nam ſi acu
              nervoſam aliquam partem, vel nervum <lb/>ipſum pupugerit, dum ita novo &amp; inuſitato
              modo venam <lb/>abſurde conatur conſtringere, nova inflammatio neceſſario
              <lb/>conſequetur, à quo convulſio, &amp; à convulſione cita mors. <lb/>See Parey's
              Surgery, p. 1133. </note>,</q> &amp;c. <lb/>there is great reaſon to think Parey's <w
            part="I">adver-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſary</w> meant a tendon or any tendinous part;
          <lb/>eſpecially as he ſupports his opinion by <w part="I">ſhew-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ing</w>, that for fear of the accidents deſcribed, <lb/>Galen durſt not ſtitch
          tranſverſe wounds till <lb/>he had firſt diſcovered the <hi rend="italic">aponeuroſis of
            the <lb/>muſcles.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>However, we will conſider this matter in <lb/>the light it now ſtands;
          and for this purpoſe <lb/>we may obſerve, that the ligature ſeems only <pb
            xml:id="page_28" n="22"/><lb/>capable of irritating and of totally obſtructing <lb/>the
          nerves. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now as the nerves upon the muſcular fibres <lb/>are very eaſily
          irritated, a theory plauſible <lb/>enough may be invented to ſhew, that in <w part="I"
            >cer-</w><lb/><w part="F">tain</w> habits convulſions will come on upon <lb/>their being
          tied; but then this would moſt <lb/>probably happen at the very time they were
            <lb/>irritated<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* See Sharp's Crit. Inq. p.
            292. </note>: ſo far from this, no one that I <lb/>know of has even pretended to ſay,
          that he <lb/>has ſeen any patient fall into convulſions at <lb/>the time the ſtricture was
          made. It is true <lb/>there are inſtances where convulſions have <lb/>inſtantly been
          brought on by irritation<note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† See Van Swieten's
            Comm. vol. ii. p. 47. </note>; but <lb/>they ſeem not to have any analogy with the
          <lb/>caſe in hand: for the parts were diſeaſed, <lb/>and in all probability had a more
          acute <w part="I">feel-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> than ever happens to the nerves in
          their <lb/>natural ſtate, and conſequently different effects <lb/>would ariſe.—May not the
          pain in this caſe, <lb/>as it is ſmart and of ſhort duration only, <lb/>ſomewhat in the
          manner of volatiles applied <pb xml:id="page_29" n="23"/><lb/>to the noſe, rather enliven
          the ſpirits than <lb/>bring on convulſions? </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>On the other hand, if convulſions aroſe in <lb/>conſequence of the
          nerve being obſtructed, <lb/>inſtead of being a ſymptom that but very <lb/>rarely happens,
          they would either in a greater <lb/>or leſs degree appear almoſt every time a large
          <lb/>one was tied; for if theſe are, as is generally <lb/>believed, diſtinct cords from
          their origin, the <lb/>obſtruction and its effects would be always <lb/>nearly the ſame.
          But ſo far from this, <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">vulſions</w> of any kind are
          not more frequent <lb/>where the large nerves are incloſed in the <w part="I"
            >li-</w><lb/><w part="F">gature</w>, than in ſlight injuries where it is not <lb/>uſed. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Lately Le Dran<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Op.
            Surgery, p. 428. </note> ſeems to have biaſſed the <lb/>minds of people<note
            place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† Mr. Warner's Caſes, p. 146. </note> in favour of
          this doctrine; <lb/>but unfortunately his practice immediately <lb/>contradicts his
          theory: for ſpeaking of thoſe <lb/>who, in performing the operation for the <lb/>aneuriſm,
          incloſe the adjacent fleſh within <pb xml:id="page_30" n="24"/><lb/>the ligature, he
            ſays<note place="bottom" n="{horizontal ‡}" rend="size(0.5)">{horizontal ‡} Loc. cit. p.
            409. </note>, <q rend="quotes">though by this <w part="I">me-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >thod</w> they tie the nerve together with the <lb/>artery, yet it is very ſeldom any
            ill <w part="I">conſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">quences</w> enſue from thence, as the
            quantity <lb/>of fleſh included by the ligature prevents the <lb/>nerve from being much
            compreſſed.</q> And <lb/>does not the ſame reaſoning hold good, as is <lb/>already ſhewn
          in amputations, where as great <lb/>a quantity of the neighbouring parts is <w part="I"
            >com-</w><lb/><w part="F">monly</w> incloſed? Beſides, when he tells us, <lb/><q
            rend="quotes">that tying the nerve along with the veſſel, <lb/>ſometimes brings on
            convulſions ſome days <lb/>after the ligature is made.</q> He alſo <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">forms</w> us, <q rend="quotes">that there will not be any
            danger <lb/>of this happening, if we apply a button of <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >vitriol</hi> when the dreſſings are firſt <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >moved</w>;</q> which, he ſays, <q rend="quotes">gradually forms <lb/>an eſchar that
            includes the ligature, and <lb/>renders it uſeleſs.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now in a few days the ligature becomes <lb/>looſe ſpontaneouſly, and
          is no longer capable <lb/>of doing injury. The parts being now <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">flamed</w> and more ſenſible, <hi rend="italic">vitriol</hi> will act with <pb
            xml:id="page_31" n="25"/><lb/>great violence upon the nerves; ſo that if no <lb/>ill
          effects aroſe from this complicated <w part="I">treat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w>, much
          leſs could they ariſe from the <w part="I">li-</w><lb/><w part="F">gature</w> alone. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>If the convulſions then were not the <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſequence</w> of the dying ſtate of the patient<note place="bottom" n="*"
            rend="size(0.5)">* Sharp's Crit. Inq. p. 292. </note>, <lb/>is it not probable they were
          owing to the <lb/>nerves being irritated, either with acrid <w part="I">mat-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ter</w> or ſome other cauſe? for it is well known <lb/>after the inflammation
          comes on the nerves <lb/>become tenſe, and acquire a more acute <w part="I"
            >feel-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>, and ſometimes, where the fluids are very <lb/>acrid,
          in few days are rendered ſo extremely <lb/>ſenſible, as to bring on convulſions upon the
          <lb/>ſlighteſt touch: and this ſeems to hold equally <lb/>good in regard to the locked
          jaw, which within <lb/>theſe few years has been ſaid, <q rend="quotes">ſometimes <lb/>to
            come on in conſequence of the ſtricture <lb/>made upon the arteries and their <w
              part="I">neigh-</w><lb/><w part="F">bouring</w> parts by ligatures;</q> for in all the
          <lb/>caſes of this kind which have come to my <lb/>knowledge, it appears not to have
          happened <lb/>till the injured part has been inflamed and <lb/>painful. In wounds it has
          often come on, <pb xml:id="page_32" n="26"/><lb/>when there has been the greateſt reaſon
          to <lb/>believe that the habit was become bad<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">*
            Dr. Clephane ſays, <q rend="quotes">In all the caſes of the locked <lb/>jaw I ever ſaw,
              the blood appeared of a looſe texture, <lb/>never ſizey.</q> Med. Ob. &amp; Inq. vol.
            i. p. 59. </note>, and <lb/>the parts extremely ſenſible from a long <w part="I"
            >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tinued</w> flux of acrid matter falling upon them. <lb/>But it
          ſeems moſt frequently to have occurred <lb/>in wounds of the joints and other
            mem-<lb/>branes<note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† See Hippoc. de Morb.
            Popular. lib. v. p. 334. ver. 9. <lb/>and p. 339. ver. 405 and 412. Cornarii Verſione.
            Parey, <lb/>lib. xii. p. 464. Baron Van Swieten's Comm. Boerha. <lb/>vol. iv. p. 182.
            Ranby on Gun-ſhot Wounds, p. 70 &amp; <lb/>ſeq. Warner's Caſes, caſe 13. Neal on Agaric,
            p. 32. <lb/>Med. Inq. vol. i. caſe 1 and 7. and vol. 2. caſe 24. </note>, where the
          nerves <lb/>being put more <lb/>upon the ſtretch are more liable to produce this
          <lb/>terrible ſymptom, which ſeems only to differ <lb/>from other convulſions in its
          degree of <w part="I">vio-</w><lb/><w part="F">lence</w>, and affects thoſe, probably,
          where the <lb/>whole nervous ſyſtem is in a moſt extreme <lb/>degree of irritability, as
          appears by the large <lb/>and repeated doſes of opium neceſſary to quiet <lb/>the ſpaſms. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>From the whole then of what has been <lb/>ſaid, there is reaſon to
          acquit the ligature of <pb xml:id="page_33" n="27"/><lb/>being productive of thoſe
          convulſions which <lb/>ſometimes have happened to attend a wound <lb/>wherein it has been
          uſed. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Another kind of ſpaſms, that are partial <lb/>and attended with pain,
          are ſaid conſtantly to <lb/>attend the uſe of the needle and ligature; and <lb/>it muſt be
          confeſſed, that while the needle is <lb/>piercing a muſcle a ſpaſm is often produced:
          <lb/>but it may with equal truth be obſerved, that <lb/>it immediately ceaſes when the
          parts incloſed <lb/>are numbed with the ligature. And it ſeems <lb/>more likely that thoſe
          ſpaſms, which <w part="I">conti-</w><lb/><w part="F">nue</w> more or leſs for ſome time
          after the <w part="I">ope-</w><lb/><w part="F">ration</w>, ariſe from the nerves being
          irritated <lb/>by the knife, by the air, and by the <w part="I">dreſſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ings</w>; for whoever attends to this <w part="I">circum-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſtance</w> will find, that the ſpaſms which <w part="I">fol-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >low</w>, for inſtance, an amputation of the leg, <lb/>immediately ſeize the muſcles
          upon their <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> divided before any needle can be
          uſed. <lb/>And we know by experience they will <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tinue</w> ſome time after the irritating cauſe is <lb/>removed, in proportion as the
          nerves were <lb/>more or leſs affected<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* See
            Whytt on vital and invol. Mot. p. 20 and 242. </note>. That a ſimilar effect <pb
            xml:id="page_34" n="28"/><lb/>will be produced by the other cauſes aſſigned, <lb/>there
          is reaſon to conclude from obſerving, <lb/>that even the muſcles of animals, <w part="I"
            >immedi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ately</w> after death, are thrown into ſpaſms by <lb/>being
          expoſed to the cold air; and ſpaſms are <lb/>alſo often brought on by touching naked
          <lb/>wounds with dry lint. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Beſides, ſpaſms follow thoſe amputations <lb/>juſt in the ſame manner,
          where the veſſels <lb/>are not tied<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Phil.
            Trans. vol. xlviii. part 2. p. 591. </note>; nor can the abſence of this <lb/>ſymptom
          with juſtice be aſcribed to the <w part="I">omiſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſion</w> of the
          ligature in amputations of the <lb/>breaſts<note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">†
            Ibid. p. 596. </note>, becauſe in this caſe the muſcles, <lb/>which are the ſeat of
          ſpaſms, are ſeldom <lb/>touched with the needle; the cellular and <lb/>adipoſe membrane
          only being taken in with <lb/>the veſſel, and which, from their ſmall <w part="I"
            >de-</w><lb/><w part="F">gree</w> of ſenſibility, give but little uneaſineſs: <lb/>and
          out of many inſtances I do not remember <lb/>any patient attended with <hi rend="italic"
            >troubleſome</hi> ſpaſms <lb/>after this operation, though the needle and <lb/>ligature
          were always uſed. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_35" n="29"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Another objection to the ligature is, <q rend="quotes">that <lb/>it
            increaſes the ſymptomatic fever, becauſe <lb/>its application gives violent pain:</q>
          but <lb/>though it often gives ſmart pain for an <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſtant</w>, it does not follow that it aggravates the <lb/>ſymptomatic fever, for the
          pain is only <w part="I">mo-</w><lb/><w part="F">mentary</w>, and whatever is included in
          the <w part="I">li-</w><lb/><w part="F">gature</w> immediately becomes ſo inſenſible, as
          <lb/>to give no future diſturbance. It is true, an <lb/>inflammation will take place above
          the <w part="I">ſtric-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w>; but as an inflammation of equal
          degree <lb/>would probably have occurred, though the <lb/>ligature was not uſed, very
          little difference of <lb/>pain can ariſe from this cauſe, as is evinced <lb/>by the
          ſymptoms following an operation <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> much the ſame,
          whether we uſe many <lb/>ligatures or few. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But the ſymptomatic fever ſeems not to <lb/>ariſe from the pain which
          accompanies or <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F">mediately</w> follows any part of the
          operation, <lb/>but to the diſtenſion which is cauſed by the <lb/>obſtruction and
          inflammation that comes on <lb/>ſome time after in conſequence of the diviſion <lb/>of the
          parts; for that pain which ariſes from <lb/>the nerves being irritated and diſordered in
            <pb xml:id="page_36" n="30"/><lb/>the operation, preſently goes off, the irritating
          <lb/>cauſe being inſtantly removed. And does not <lb/>the ſymptomatic fever gradually come
          on, a <lb/>few hours after the operation, as the parts <lb/>about the wound begin to
          ſwell, and again <lb/>decline as the diſtenſion abates, from the <lb/>lymphatic veſſels
          freely tranſmitting their con-<lb/>tents? </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Beſides, from the account given us of the <lb/>ſymptomatic fever
          following an amputation <lb/>of the leg, where the ligature was omitted, <lb/>we ſee<note
            place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Phil. Trans. vol. xlviii. part 2. p. 591. or Mr.
            <lb/>Warner's Caſes, caſe 29. </note> it came on about the uſual time, and <lb/>ſeems to
          have been nearly the ſame as when <lb/>it is uſed. And though the ſymptomatic <w part="I"
            >fe-</w><lb/><w part="F">ver</w> has been ſlight in amputations of the <lb/>breaſts<note
            place="bottom" n="†">† Ibid. </note>, where the veſſels were not tied, <lb/>yet it does
          not appear to be a proof that it is <lb/>increaſed by the uſe of the ligature, becauſe
          <lb/>in this operation the ſymptomatic fever is for <lb/>the moſt part, if not always,
          ſlight; for the <lb/>fat in the cellular membrane eaſily melts <lb/>down, and the
          reticular or membranous part <pb xml:id="page_37" n="31"/><lb/>ſends out new fleſh without
          giving much <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">turbance</w>, and in this caſe theſe,
          with the <lb/>ſkin, are the only parts wounded; for even <lb/>when a ſchirrus adheres, it
          is ſeparated from <lb/>the pectoral muſcle without doing much <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">jury</w>, as this operation, I imagine, is never <lb/>practiſed when the
          adheſion is otherwiſe than <lb/>ſlight. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>With this we ſhould remember, that the <lb/>ſymptomatic fever is
          always ſlight where the <lb/>ſolids are relaxed and weak, in conſequence <lb/>of the ſmall
          degree of force with which the <lb/>blood is carried againſt the obſtructed veſſels.
          <lb/>And is it not therefore more likely owing to <lb/>this cauſe than to the omiſſion of
          the <w part="I">liga-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w>, that a ſlight fever only followed in
          thoſe <lb/>whoſe legs were amputated by Mr. Warner<note place="bottom" n="*"
            rend="size(0.5)">* Loc. cite. </note>, <lb/>as all theſe patients were much reduced <w
            part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">vious</w> to the operation? And is not, in ſuch
          <lb/>habits, the ſymptomatic fever conſtantly ſlight, <lb/>though the ligature is uſed. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is alſo ſaid that abſceſſes are the <w part="I">conſe-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">quence</w> of uſing the ligature, and that it <w part="I">ſome-</w>
          <pb xml:id="page_38" n="32"/><lb/><w part="F">times</w> remains fixed to the laſt, ſo as
          to retard <lb/>the healing of the wound; but theſe <w part="I">incon-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >veniencies</w> only happen when the needle is <lb/>paſſed very deep, and may therefore
          be <w part="I">avoid-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> by a contrary practice: nor is paſſing
          the <lb/>needle deep at all neceſſary (if the parts are <lb/>ſound) as a ſmall quantity of
          fleſh or cellular <lb/>membrane below the ſtricture will ſufficiently <lb/>prevent the
          ligature being puſhed off by the <lb/>impulſe of the blood. However I would <w part="I"
            >cau-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> againſt extremes; for with paſſing the <lb/>needle
          but a very little way the veſſel <w part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F">times</w> may not
          be tied, and cauſe unneceſſary <lb/>trouble; if we therefore paſs the needle only <lb/>a
          moderate depth, the ligature will always <lb/>come away in due time without <w part="I"
            >inconveni-</w><lb/><w part="F">ence</w>, or at leaſt it may be taken away long
          <lb/>before the wound is healed, without any <w part="I">dan-</w><lb/><w part="F">ger</w>
          of bringing on a freſh hæmorrhage: for <lb/>as ſoon as digeſtion is complete, and the new
          <lb/>fleſh begins to riſe, the ligature makes not any <lb/>preſſure upon the veſſel; and
          though new <lb/>fleſh may have covered the nooſe, yet if we <lb/>take the advice long
          ſince given by Monro<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Ed. Med. Eſs. vol. iv.
            p. 275. </note>, <pb xml:id="page_39" n="33"/><lb/>it may be removed without any hazard
          of <lb/>cutting the artery. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This is the light in which I have been led <lb/>to conſider the uſe
          and abuſe of the needle <lb/>and ligature in tying the blood veſſels, and <lb/>ſhall now
          proceed to enquire into the method <lb/>of ſuppreſſing the hæmorrhage by fungous
          <lb/>ſubſtances; which, like the ligature, will <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >pear</w> to have their advantage and <w part="I">inconve-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >nience</w>. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="chapter">
        <pb xml:id="page_40" n="34"/>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">CHAP. III.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="italic indent hanging"><lb/>Of ſuppreſſing the hæmorrhage by the <w part="I"
            >applica-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of fungous ſubſtances, by coagulated <lb/>blood,
          by aſtringents, and by perpendicular <lb/>preſſure. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HE late ſucceſs which has attended the
          <lb/>application of fungous ſubſtances is a <lb/>full proof that an hæmorrhage from large
            <w part="I">ar-</w><lb/><w part="F">teries</w> may often be effectually ſuppreſſed by
          <lb/>their uſe; and it at the ſame time points out <lb/>the truth of the doctrine
          advanced, and what <lb/>little aſſiſtance in this caſe is wanting. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But the manner of applying funguſes makes <lb/>a material difference
          in regard to ſucceſs; for <lb/>if they are preſſed cloſe againſt the end of the
          <lb/>veſſel, they intercept the paſſage of the blood; <lb/>and the artery cloſes itſelf up
          in the manner <lb/>deſcribed: whereas, when this circumſtance is <lb/>not obſerved, and
          they are only laid near to <lb/>the orifice, in the manner Cheſelden<note place="bottom"
            n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Phil. Trans. No 478. p. 33. </note> uſed <pb xml:id="page_41"
            n="35"/><lb/>ſpunge, they ſuppreſs the hæmorrhage by <lb/>choaking up the mouth of the
          veſſel with <lb/>coagulated blood, which hinders its being <lb/>cloſed; and though it
          ſtops the bleeding at <lb/>preſent, yet it may be the ſource of a future <lb/>hæmorrhage. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This is evident from the experiments made <lb/>by La Foss<note
            place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Philos. Trans. vol. xlix. part. art. 10 &amp;
            11. </note>, where the coagulated blood, <lb/>which filled the end of the artery, was
          formed <lb/>into a cone with its apex towards the heart; <lb/>conſequently, if the plug
          happens to extend <lb/>to the next collateral branch, a freſh flux of <lb/>blood muſt
          enſue upon its coming away; for <lb/>it does not unite with the veſſel, as ſome <lb/>have
          imagined. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I know there are inſtances, where an <w part="I">ori-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">fice</w> made in an artery has been ſtopped with <lb/>a clot of ſolid blood,
          which adhering firmly <lb/>to the cicatrix of the integuments, produced <lb/>a
          conſiderable calloſity, and which ſeems to <lb/>have given riſe to this opinion. But it
          muſt <lb/>be obſerved in theſe caſes, the wound was <pb xml:id="page_42" n="34"/>
          <pb xml:id="page_43" n="35"/>
          <pb xml:id="page_44" n="36"/><lb/>cured without coming to ſuppuration; whereas <lb/>when
          the air has free acceſs, we well know a <lb/>putrefaction of the coagulated blood, as well
          <lb/>as digeſtion, is always the conſequence; and <lb/>I make no doubt but the ſeparation
          of <w part="I">coa-</w><lb/><w part="F">gulated</w> blood is one cauſe why a freſh <w
            part="I">bleed-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> has ſometimes come on after the <w part="I"
            >inflam-</w><lb/><w part="F">mation</w> was abated, and matter began to be <lb/>freely
          diſcharged. In a very late inſtance, <lb/>where the bleeding from a divided artery had
          <lb/>been ſuppreſſed by coagulated blood, I ſaw it <lb/>renewed again next day by taking
          this blood <lb/>away; the artery bleeding in the ſame manner <lb/>as when it was firſt
          opened; but upon preſſing <lb/>it betwixt my fingers it was ſoon effectually <lb/>cloſed.
          Hence we may obſerve, that the <w part="I">prac-</w><lb/><w part="F">tice</w> of laying
          allum, or any thing elſe, at <lb/>the end of the artery to coagulate the blood, <lb/>is
          very improper, as every impediment to the <lb/>contraction of the veſſel ſhould on the <w
            part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">trary</w> be removed. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This leads me to take notice of Petit's <w part="I">opi-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">nion</w>, who imagined that the hæmorrhage <lb/>from divided arteries was
          always ſuppreſſed <lb/>by plugs of blood within the veſſel; becauſe <pb xml:id="page_45"/>
          <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="2"/>
          <pb xml:id="page_48" n="37"/><lb/>he found in ſome of them, after the death of <lb/>the
          patient, coagulated blood, which extended <lb/>itſelf upwards a conſiderable way. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But notwithſtanding this, it is very <w part="I">proba-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ble</w> that the hæmorrhage was ſtopped by the <lb/>natural contraction of the
          veſſel; for we find <lb/>in the two waggoners mentioned by Monſ. <lb/>Fagot<note
            place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Philos. Trans. for 1753; or Mr. Warner's Caſes,
            <lb/>p. 136. </note> where, after death, coagulated blood <lb/>was found in the ſame
          manner, <q rend="quotes">their <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">tremities</w> were
            contracted and ſtraitened, as <lb/>if they had been tied.</q> And in the many
          <lb/>experiments I have made on this occaſion, I <lb/>never found coagulated blood but
          once; and <lb/>then the extremity of the artery was cloſe <lb/>contracted<note
            place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† It was in the artery of a large dog which was <w
              part="I">ſtran-</w><lb/><w part="F">gled</w>.—The horſes, &amp;c. were killed by being
            bled to death <lb/>in the uſual manner, which ſeems to prove that the <w part="I"
              >co-</w><lb/><w part="F">agula</w> are not formed while the blood circulates
            regularly, <lb/>but when the animal is near dying, or immediately after death. </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Pouteau<note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† Melanges des
            Chirurg. p. 314. </note> opened ſeveral arteries, and <w part="I">ne-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ver</w> found any coagulum; nor is there any <pb xml:id="page_49" n="38"
          /><lb/>coagulum found in the umbilical veſſels of <lb/>children after death: from all
          which may we <lb/>not conclude, that this circumſtance is merely <lb/>accidental, and no
          ſtep taken by nature, who <lb/>is always uniform, if no impediment, is in <lb/>the way?
          Indeed, I think with ſome other <lb/>writers,<note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">†
            Gouch, Pouteau. </note> that it is of the ſame kind, and <lb/>produced in the ſame
          manner as the fibrous <lb/>blood we often find in the great arteries near <lb/>the heart:
          that which I ſaw had exactly the <lb/>ſame appearance; nor did it ſeem ſufficient <lb/>to
          have blocked up the veſſel. What is <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">ready</w> ſaid
          about coagulated blood preventing <lb/>the contraction of the veſſel, here alſo takes
          <lb/>place; and was it extended to the extremity <lb/>of the artery, putrefaction and its
          conſequences <lb/>muſt of courſe enſue, from its being in <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tact</w> with the air. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It follows then, that whatever fungus is <lb/>uſed, it ſhould be
          preſſed cloſe to the end of <lb/>the veſſel; and that kind which adheres <w part="I"
            >clo-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſeſt</w> ſhould be choſen. Mr. White ſays<note place="bottom"
            n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† Loc. cit. </note> that <lb/>ſpunge is on this account
          preferable; and if <pb xml:id="page_50" n="39"/><lb/>his directions, in regard to the
          choice, <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">paration</w>, and manner of applying it, be
            <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerved</w>, I believe he ſays true; but even this
          <lb/>ſticks the faſteſt when it is leaſt wanted; for <lb/>though after a while it adheres
          ſo firm, that <lb/>it is removed with difficulty, yet, till the parts <lb/>begin to ſwell
          and become moiſt, the <w part="I">adhe-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſion</w> is very ſlight. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Bandage therefore muſt be carefully applied <lb/>to preſerve it in its
          proper ſituation; and if <lb/>this circumſtance had been duly attended to, <lb/>inſtead of
          relying upon a ſpecific property in <lb/>agaric, better ſucceſs would probably have <w
            part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tended</w> it when in vogue; for where agaric
          <lb/>itſelf proved ineffectual, tight bandage and <lb/>common dreſſings ſuppreſſed the
          hæmorrhage. <lb/>And we might produce innumerable inſtances <lb/>which prove, that
          whatever is kept firm upon <lb/>the end of the veſſel is ſufficient for the <w part="I"
            >pur-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſe</w>. —However, if what is ſaid about tying <lb/>the great
          arteries be true, moſt ſurgeons, I <lb/>imagine, will ſtill ſecure them with the <w
            part="I">liga-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w>; for no ſort of bandage can with ſafety
          <lb/>in amputations be ſo applied, but the fungus <lb/>may ſometimes be diſplaced by
          ſpaſms, <w part="I">cough-</w><pb xml:id="page_51" n="40"/><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>,
          vomiting, or the like: and ſhould an <w part="I">hæ-</w><lb/><w part="F">morrhage</w>
          return from theſe veſſels, we know <lb/>death may enſue from the loſs of no very large
          <lb/>quantity of blood. Mr. Sharp's<note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† Phil.
            Trans. vol. xlviii. part 2. art. 78. </note>
          <w part="I">pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tient</w>, in whom the veſſels burſt open three
          <lb/>hours and half after he had applied agaric, <lb/>died in about twenty minutes with
          the loſs of<lb/> leſs than thirty ounces of blood, including <lb/>what was loſt in the
          operation: nor could <w part="I">aſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſiſtance</w> be ſpeedy enough to
          prevent this <w part="I">ca-</w><lb/><w part="F">taſtrophe</w>, though it was upon the
          ſpot when <lb/>the hæmorrhage returned; and how much <lb/>more likely is this to be the
          caſe in private <lb/>practice, eſpecially in the country, where the <lb/>perſon obliged to
          be intruſted with our <w part="I">pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tient</w> is often an intire
          ſtranger to chirurgical <lb/>operations? </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But ſuppoſe our aſſiſtant ſhould be ſo lucky <lb/>as to compreſs the
          tourniquet time enough to <lb/>ſave the patient's life, yet it is probable a <lb/>quantity
          of blood will often be loſt, that may <lb/>be injurious to him; for though the loſs of
          <lb/>ſome blood from this accident may be <w part="I">ſer-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >viceable</w>, when the patient is not much <w part="I">re-</w><pb xml:id="page_52"
            n="41"/><lb/><w part="F">duced</w> by the diſeaſe<note place="bottom" n="†"
            rend="size(0.5)">† See Mr. Warner's Caſes, caſe 44. </note>; on the other hand, <lb/>the
          loſs of a few ounces, when he is become <lb/>weak, will be very improper, and very likely
          <lb/>retard the recovery of his health: and we <lb/>may obſerve, even in ſtrong habits,
          that the <lb/>diſcharge of blood ought not to be <w part="I">commit-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ted</w> to chance, but intirely directed by the <lb/>judgment of the ſurgeon. And
          though it <lb/>ſhould happen that very little blood is loſt, <lb/>the patient may not only
          undergo great pain <lb/>from the compreſſure, till the ſurgeon can be <lb/>called, perhaps
          from a conſiderable diſtance, <lb/>but the parts may be much injured by the <lb/>fluids
          being ſo long in a ſtate of ſtagnation. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But this inconvenience will for the moſt <lb/>part attend the uſe of
          this remedy in <w part="I">ampu-</w><lb/><w part="F">tation</w> of the limbs; for all
          agree that it is <lb/>neceſſary to keep the limb compreſſed a <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſiderable</w> time with the tourniquet, and which <lb/>will alſo in all
          probability overbalance the pain <lb/>cauſed in uſing the needle and ligature. Nor
          <lb/>can we help thinking but ſome miſtake <w part="I">hap-</w><pb xml:id="page_53" n="42"
            /><lb/><w part="F">pened</w> in deſcribing thoſe caſes, where we <lb/>are told, though
          the tourniquet was kept <lb/>compreſſed for half an hour, that the <w part="I"
            >pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tient</w> was remarkably eaſy during that time. <lb/>Mr.
            Sharp's<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Phil. Trans. vol. xlviii. part 2.
            art. 78. </note> patient, when he uſed agaric, <lb/>complained <hi rend="italic"
            >grievouſly</hi> of pain ariſing from the <lb/>tourniquet; and my patients tell me, it
          is <lb/>the worſt part of the operation: beſides, I <lb/>have obſerved when a piece of
          fungus <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">heres</w> cloſe, it gives very conſiderable
          pain in <lb/>being removed; ſo that upon the whole, this <lb/>method of ſecuring the great
          veſſels is attended <lb/>with more pain and leſs ſafety, than the <w part="I"
            >liga-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w> when properly applied. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This reaſoning alſo holds good in regard <lb/>to the leſſer arteries,
          when they are ſurrounded <lb/>with the cellular or adipoſe membrane only; <lb/>though it
          cannot be extended to the tying <lb/>of thoſe which are ſituated amongſt the muſcles,
          <lb/>becauſe, as is already obſerved, the ligature is <lb/>here attended with conſiderable
          pain; nor is <lb/>the tourniquet in this caſe wanted; and I <lb/>make no doubt, but theſe
          veſſels may in <w part="I">ge-</w><pb xml:id="page_54" n="43"/><lb/><w part="F">neral</w>
          be truſted with ſpunge, or any thing <lb/>elſe that adheres cloſe to their extremities:
          <lb/>but the ſpunge ſhould be removed the firſt or <lb/>ſecond dreſſing, otherwiſe the new
          fleſh <w part="I">grow-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> into its pores will cauſe an increaſe
          of <lb/>pain in the removal. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>On the other hand, if the bleeding ſhould <lb/>happen to return,
          though on account of the <lb/>ſize of the veſſels it might not be dangerous, <lb/>yet even
          here more blood might be diſcharged <lb/>than it would be prudent to loſe; a freſh <w
            part="I">hæ-</w><lb/><w part="F">morrhage</w> is always alarming to the patient;
          <lb/>and as momentary pain ſeems to be the only <lb/>inconvenience, perhaps many ſurgeons
          will <lb/>think it beſt to leave their patients in perfect <lb/>ſecurity: and we may juſt
          obſerve, that in <lb/>many operations the ligature muſt of courſe <lb/>be uſed upon all
          the veſſels, as it will be <w part="I">ne-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceſſary</w> to ſtop the
          bleeding as we go on. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nevertheleſs, when the fleſh is become <w part="I">ten-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">der</w>, and gives way to the ligature, ſpunge <lb/>ſeems to be the beſt
          remedy; for though the <lb/>large veſſels might be pulled out, and tied in <pb
            xml:id="page_55" n="44"/><lb/>the manner Dionis<note place="bottom" n="*"
            rend="size(0.5)">* He deſcribes different methods, but that is here <w part="I"
              >re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ferred</w> to, where the thread is paſſed through the end of
            <lb/>the veſſel to prevent its being puſhed off by the impulſe <lb/>of the blood. See
            chap. on Amputation. </note> deſcribes, yet, being <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >defended</w>, the end would commonly ſeparate; <lb/>and unleſs the ligature was placed
          near its <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">tremity</w>, ſometimes bring on a freſh <w
            part="I">hæmor-</w><lb/><w part="F">rhage</w> in the manner already obſerved. And
          <lb/>this was moſt probably the reaſon why Parey <lb/>had more certain ſucceſs, when he
          took in, <lb/>along with the veſſel, ſome of the adjacent <lb/>parts, than when he
          incloſed it alone in the <lb/>ligature. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Where the veſſels are ſo deeply ſituated as <lb/>not to be come at
          with the needle, the ſame <lb/>kind of application muſt have preference, if <lb/>it can be
          laid cloſe to the mouth of the <w part="I">ar-</w><lb/><w part="F">tery</w>; and it
          ſucceeds better in this caſe, as <lb/>the ſides of the wound aſſiſt in keeping it in
          <lb/>its proper ſituation: but before it is applied, <lb/>it ſeems neceſſary to examine
          whether the <w part="I">ar-</w><lb/><w part="F">tery</w> is wholly divided; for without
          this <w part="I">cau-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> we may ſometimes be diſappointed in
          <lb/>our expectation, and aſcribe inſufficiency to <pb xml:id="page_56" n="45"/><lb/>this
          method, as was done to the agaric<note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† See Neal on
            Agaric, p. 35. </note>, <lb/>when the want of ſucceſs was owing to the <lb/>veſſel being
          in part divided, whence it was <lb/>incapable of intercepting the paſſage of the
          <lb/>blood. Nor ſhould we forget, that in wounds <lb/>which admit of cure by an immediate
          union <lb/>of their divided parts, fungous ſubſtances are <lb/>unneceſſary, as the common
          method of <w part="I">dreſſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> effectually ſuppreſſes the
          bleeding, though <lb/>it is from conſiderable arteries. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>However, if the artery is large, and any <lb/>difficulty occurs, if
          the part will admit of the <lb/>practice of dilating the wound, perhaps it <lb/>may ſeem
          more proper by that means to uſe <lb/>the ligature, eſpecially if it adheres to an <w
            part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">divided</w> muſcle or the bone, and bandage <w part="I"
            >can-</w><lb/><w part="F">not</w> be conveniently applied; and where the <lb/>principal
          trunk of a large artery is wounded <lb/>in a longitudinal direction, Mr. Lambert's<note
            place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† Med. Inq. vol. ii. p. 360. </note>
          <lb/>method of ſewing it up ſhould, I think, be <lb/>tried. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_57" n="46"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>When an hæmorrhage ariſes from a thin <lb/>ſtate of the blood, and the
          diſcharge is from <lb/>the whole ſurface of the wound, <hi rend="italic">puff ball</hi>
          <lb/>ſeems preferable to ſpunge, or the like, as the <lb/>blood would probably eſcape
          through its pores. <lb/>In this caſe, with tight bandage it has <w part="I">an-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſwered</w> my purpoſe, till internal medicines <lb/>had their proper effect:
          and if upon trial it <lb/>ſhould prove ſucceſſful under the like <w part="I"
            >circum-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtances</w>, will it not be more proper than <hi
            rend="italic">ſtyp-<lb/>tics</hi> or <hi rend="italic">aſtringents,</hi> &amp;c. as
          theſe harden the <w part="I">fi-</w><lb/><w part="F">bres</w>, and prevent digeſtion, from
          which <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">convenience</w> this remedy is free? Nor do I
          <lb/>apprehend the bandage will be ſo unartfully <lb/>applied, as to bring on a flux of
          blood by <lb/>compreſſing the veins, as I imagine in general <lb/>this obvious cauſe of an
          hæmorrhage is well <lb/>underſtood, being pointed out by ſeveral <w part="I"
            >wri-</w><lb/><w part="F">ters</w> on ſurgery, and clearly demonſtrated by
            <lb/>Monro<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Ed. Med. Eſs. vol. iv. p. 271.
          </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Perhaps ſome will think that ſtyptics and <lb/>aſtringents will
          forward the contraction of <lb/>the veſſels: but we may learn how little they <pb
            xml:id="page_58" n="47"/><lb/>are wanted, from the artery in the young <w part="I"
            >fel-</w><lb/><w part="F">low's</w> arm, which was evidently relaxed and <lb/>weak,
          cloſing itſelf without any aſſiſtance; <lb/>and I am perſuaded, from ſome experiments
          <lb/>I have made, that theſe applications, inſtead <lb/>of aſſiſting, would, if they were
          not hindered <lb/>by mixing with the blood in wounds, rather <lb/>prevent the collapſing
          of the veſſel by <w part="I">hard-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> its fibres. And however
          contrary this <w part="I">doc-</w><lb/><w part="F">trine</w> may be to the generally
          received <w part="I">opi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nion</w>, experience is certainly in its
          favour; <lb/>for though by coagulating the blood, they <lb/>might ſucceed upon very ſmall
          arteries, yet, <lb/>being applied to thoſe which were large, they <lb/>were always found
          inſufficient to ſuppreſs the <lb/>bleeding, unleſs tight bandage was at the ſame <lb/>time
          uſed, and to which I think it is clear the <lb/>ſucceſs was owing: for many of theſe <w
            part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſitions</w>, which were thought to be <w part="I"
            >aſtrin-</w><lb/><w part="F">gents</w>, had certainly no other property as
          blood-<lb/>ſtaunchers than that of choaking up the mouths <lb/>of the veſſels<note
            place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* See Parey, p. 328. Hildanus, p. 812. Clow's <w
              part="I">Sur-</w><lb/><w part="F">gery</w>, p. 27. </note>. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_59" n="48"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is obvious that the fungus, when uſed, <lb/>muſt be kept in its
          proper ſituation by <w part="I">ban-</w><lb/><w part="F">dage</w> differently applied,
          according to the part <lb/>wounded; and in this matter every ſurgeon's <lb/>own judgment
          will beſt direct him. <w part="I">How-</w><lb/><w part="F">ever</w> we may juſt obſerve,
          that in amputations <lb/>good ſlicking plaiſter, as adviſed by Mr. <lb/>White<note
            place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Eſſay on Spunge. </note>, and keeping the hand
          preſſed harder <lb/>againſt the part for a few hours, may often <lb/>be ſuffcient; though
          the machine <w part="I">recom-</w><lb/><w part="F">mended</w> by Mr. Gooch<note
            place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† Caſes, p. 131 and 141. </note> will, probably,
          be <lb/>more certain; and when this is not at hand, <lb/>a circular piece of leather may
          be made to <lb/>anſwer nearly the ſame purpoſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This piece of leather muſt be large enough <lb/>to cover the end of
          the ſtump, and near its <lb/>edge muſt be cut four ſlits in oppoſite <w part="I"
            >direc-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w>, that will admit each a fillet.—Suppoſing <lb/>a
          leg taken off below the knee, two fillets <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>
          paſſed through theſe ſlits croſſways, and <lb/>under a roller or a piece of cloth that
          goes <lb/>round the thigh, above the knee, muſt be <pb xml:id="page_60" n="49"
          /><lb/>brought back again, and tied upon the end <lb/>of the ſtump, by which means the
          dreſſings <lb/>will be fixed, and any degree of preſſure may <lb/>be made: and this
          bandage, if it is kept from <lb/>ſlipping down, by being faſtened with filleting <lb/>to a
          roller round the waiſt, ſerves equally well <lb/>when we amputate above the knee. Nor do
          <lb/>I recommend this method without experience; <lb/>for having amputated a leg, where
          the blood <lb/>was extremely poor, and the fleſh very tender, <lb/>the ligatures were
          forced off the veſſels a few <lb/>hours after the operation, by a fit of <w part="I"
            >cough-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> and vomiting; I immediately applied the <lb/>bandage
          above-mentioned, with bolſters of <lb/>dry lint, which effectually anſwered the <w
            part="I">pur-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſe</w>: for, though the patient vomited and
          <lb/>coughed ſeveral times afterwards, the <w part="I">hæmor-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >rhage</w> did not return. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Indeed bandage ſeems hitherto to have <lb/>proved leſs ſerviceable
          than it might have <lb/>been, merely from imagining it would be <lb/>uſeleſs, unleſs the
          ſides of the veſſels were <lb/>brought together in cloſe contact; whereas, had <lb/>the
          preſſure been made only upon the end of <lb/>the veſſel, and juſt ſufficient to reſiſt;
          the <w part="I">im-</w><pb xml:id="page_61" n="50"/><lb/><w part="F">pulſe</w> of the
          blood, it might much oftener <lb/>have been uſed without inconvenience, and <lb/>with
          better ſucceſs, as there is reaſon to think <lb/>from many inſtances. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>We have only further to add on this head, <lb/>that where the wounded
          artery cannot be come <lb/>at, preſſure is ſtill the only remedy; and <lb/>where things
          are ſo circumſtanced that we <lb/>are obliged to choak up the mouths of the <lb/>veſſels
          with coagulated blood, it ſeems <w part="I">neceſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſary</w>, for
          reaſons already given, to make a <lb/>preſſure, if it can be done, againſt the end of
          <lb/>the artery, that the contraction beyond the <lb/>plug may more certainly take place. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_62"/>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="chapter">
        <pb xml:id="page_63" n="51"/>
        <head rend="italic align-center"><lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">CHAP. IV.</hi>
          <lb/>Of ſuppreſſing hæmorrhages by cauteries, <w part="I">cau-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſtics</w> &amp;c. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">B</hi>ESIDES the methods above-mentioned, <lb/>Mr.
            Warner<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Caſes, p. 38. </note> has ſhewn,
          that when an <lb/>artery is opened in the roof of the mouth, the <lb/>actual cautery is
          ſometimes neceſſary to ſtop <lb/>the bleeding: and many years ago, after <w part="I"
            >ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">tirpating</w> a tumor from this part, I was obliged, <lb/>for
          the ſame reaſons, to have recourſe to the <lb/>ſame remedy; but the iron was no hotter
          than <lb/>juſt ſufficient to form the neighbouring parts <lb/>into an eſchar upon the end
          of the artery; by <lb/>which means the courſe of the blood was <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tercepted</w>, and the veſſel left at liberty to cloſe <lb/>itſelf up; whereas
          when the cautery is very <lb/>hot, it not only burns the end of the artery <lb/>a
          conſiderable way, but hardening its fibres <lb/>beyond the eſchar, renders it incapable of
            <w part="I">col-</w><lb/><w part="F">lapſing</w>; ſo that it is no wonder an <w part="I"
            >hæmor-</w><pb xml:id="page_64" n="52"/><lb/><w part="F">rhage</w> ſhould ſo often enſue
          upon the <w part="I">ſepira-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of the dead parts. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>However, the cautery is at all times a cruel <lb/>application, and
          ſhould be avoided, if <w part="I">poſſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w>: nor do I now call to
          mind any other <lb/>part where its uſe can be wanted. But if this <lb/>is cruel, the
          potential cautery is more ſo, as <lb/>it ſpreads itſelf further into the neighbouring
          <lb/>parts; and yet it is not very uncommon for <lb/>ſurgeons in performing operations to
          apply <lb/>lint ſoaked in ſcalding oil of turpentine, where <lb/>the artery, though not
          very large, cannot be <lb/>readily come at: and this piece of cruelty is <lb/>ſtill
          aggravated, when we conſider that a few <lb/>minutes preſſure would, in all probability,
          <lb/>have alone been ſuffcient for the purpoſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Cauſtics, &amp;c. are, I believe, in general, <lb/>laid aſide in
          ſupperſſing hæmorrhages; and <lb/>therefore we need only obſerve, that, though <lb/>they
          do not, by hardening the ſides of the <lb/>artery, render it incapable of collapſing above
          <lb/>the part deſtroyed, yet, by cauſing its end to <lb/><unclear>#####</unclear>
            thei<unclear>#</unclear>
          <unclear>#####</unclear> is <unclear>#####</unclear>
          <unclear>####</unclear>rary to right <lb/><unclear>##### #####</unclear> adviſe ill, <pb
            xml:id="page_65" n="53"/><lb/>who give up every advantage gained by the <lb/>ligature,
          in afterwards applying a piece of <lb/>vitriol. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But all theſe errors in the choice of <w part="I">reme-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">dies</w>, or their application, have aroſe from the <lb/>true principles of
          ſupperſſing hæmorrhages <lb/>not being previouſly inveſtigated; it will <lb/>therefore
          give great pleaſure to the author of <lb/>this little eſſay, if it appears that he has ſet
          <lb/>in its proper light this important, though <lb/>common operation. </p>
        <trailer rend="align-center"><lb/>THE END. </trailer>
      </div>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
