<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Brand: The true method of reducing ruptures</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Robert Brand</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">THE TRUE METHOD of REDUCING RUPTURES; and Retaining Them in the
              Abdomen, and in the Navel: together with TESTIMONIES to the Merits of Mr. Brand's
              ELASTIC TRUSS; and several Authenticated Cases of the most Extraordinary Cures. To
              which is added, a POSTSCRIPT.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">N27762</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N27762"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for the author, and sold by him. Sold also by S. Bladon;
                  and Messrs. Richardson and Urquart, 1771.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1771</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="3"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="47"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">National Library of Medicine</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3308675338</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K015319.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Surgical or anatominal work"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>TO <lb/><hi rend="size(2)">Mr. HUNTER</hi>. </head>
        <lb/>
        <salute rend="indent size(1.75)">SIR, </salute>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">S</hi>INCE it is principally to you I am <lb/>obliged for my
          knowledge in the re- <lb/>duction of Ruptures, I cannot with ſo <lb/>great propriety
          dedicate the following <lb/>Sheets to any other perſon. Added to this, <lb/>the
          conſideration of that generous friend- <lb/>lineſs, (ſo predominating in men of frank
          <lb/>natures) which you have, on many occa- <lb/>ſions, exerciſed towards me, prompts me
          <lb/>to ſnatch the opportunity of confeſſing my <lb/>gratitude. At the ſame time, I am
          happy <lb/>that not the moſt cenſorious caviller can <lb/>pretend this addreſs is founded
          on <hi rend="italic">intereſted</hi>
          <pb xml:id="page_3"/>
          <lb/>motives.—I have nothing to ask of the <lb/>World but <hi rend="italic"
          >Candor:</hi>—from <hi rend="sc">you</hi>, Sir, I am <lb/>aſſured of meeting with it in
          the moſt re- <lb/>fined ſenſe. </p>
        <signed rend="indent hanging">
          <lb/>I am, Sir, <lb/>With the moſt unfeigned Reſpect, <lb/>Your much obliged, and
          <lb/>Very obedient Servant, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Long Acre.</hi> ROBERT BRAND. </signed>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body rend="indent">
      <pb xml:id="page_4"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>THE <lb/><hi rend="size(1.75)">TRUE METHOD</hi>
        <lb/><hi>OF</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">REDUCING RUPTURES, &amp;c. </hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <figure>
          <figDesc>Decorative frame around the letter "M".</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">M</hi>Y Truſs is only intended for the <lb/>benefit of ſuch Ruptures in
        the <lb/>Groin and Scrotum as there is a poſ- <lb/>ſibility of returning again into the
        Abdomen; <lb/>tho' I make others of a different conſtruction, <lb/>according to the
        ſituation of the part from <lb/>whence it proceeds, and other circumſtances <lb/>that may
        attend it; and in particular a new in- <lb/>vented Elaſtic Bandage for a Rupture in the
        <lb/>Navel; for the invention of which I am in part <lb/>obliged to Dr. <hi rend="sc"
          >Allen</hi>, of <hi rend="italic">Dalwich College.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Before</hi> I give any directions how to apply <lb/>my Truſs, it may be
        proper to ſay ſomething <pb xml:id="page_5" n="2"/>
        <lb/>with regard to the ſafeſt and eaſieſt manner <lb/>of reducing the Inteſtine, when
        fallen <lb/>down; and the following is the method I <lb/>have always practiſed with great
        ſucceſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">must</hi> too premiſe, that I have ſome hopes <lb/>my Readers will not
        entertain a leſs favoura- <lb/>ble Opinion of me, if I avoid the pompoſity <lb/>of ſome
        perſons who have wrote on this ſub- <lb/>ject; if I do not endeavour to raiſe my merit
        <lb/>on the ſound of a word, and torture <lb/>language for new-fangled and varying names,
        <lb/>merely becauſe the ſymptoms of the diſorder <lb/>are triflingly different. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">If</hi> the Rupture then be much enlarged, or <lb/>painful, it will be of
        great ſervice to the Pa- <lb/>tient, before the reduction is attempted, to <lb/>take a
        gentle cooling purgative, ſuch as a de- <lb/>coction of Tamarinds with Sena, or a ſolution
        <lb/>of Salts and Manna; and if he is of a plethoric <lb/>or full habit of body, to let a
        moderate quan- <lb/>tity of blood will be proper; and at the ſame <lb/>time the parts ſhould
        be fomented with a piece <lb/>of flannel wrung out of a warm decoction of <lb/>emollient
        herbs, ſuch as Chamomile Flowers, <lb/>Mallows, &amp;c. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_6" n="3"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">After</hi> theſe preparations, you ſhould pro- <lb/>ceed in the following
        manner: Lay the Pa- <lb/>tient upon his back in ſuch a poſture that his <lb/>Buttocks may be
        conſiderably higher than his <lb/>Head, as by that means the Bowels that are <lb/>within the
        Belly will fall more towards the <lb/>Breaſt, and not only give way to what is to <lb/>be
        returned, but be of ſome aſſiſtance to the <lb/>reduction. Then you muſt examine care-
        <lb/>fully as to the ſituation of the Teſticles; and <lb/>if you find they are forced up
        towards the <lb/>ſides of the Scrotum by the ſize of the Rup- <lb/>ture, you muſt be very
        cautious not to <lb/>ſqueeze them in your attempt. If you find <lb/>them compreſſed at the
        bottom of the Scro- <lb/>tum, you muſt with the fore-finger and <lb/>thumb of one hand
        ſeparate them from the <lb/>ruptured part, and with the ſame fingers of <lb/>the other hand
        take hold of the upper part <lb/>that is next the Ring of the Muſcles, or place <lb/>from
        whence the Rupture comes out, and <lb/>work it gently in, in the ſame manner as you
        <lb/>obſerve Women do with a cow's teats <lb/>when they milk her. By obſerving this me-
        <lb/>thod you will never be apt to ſtrain the <lb/>Rings of the Muſcles, nor hurt the
        Inteſtine, <lb/>ſo as to occaſion an inflammation of any of <lb/>theſe parts. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_7" n="4"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As to the application of the Truſs, it <lb/>will be more convenient to put it ſlack
        round <lb/>the Patient's Body before he is laid down, as <lb/>by his getting up after the
        reduction there <lb/>might be ſome riſque of the Bowel falling <lb/>down again. Take hold of
        each end of the <lb/>ſpring, and open it wide enough to receive his <lb/>Body ſide-ways; and
        after you have got the <lb/>Bowel fairly reduced, apply the Cuſhion of <lb/>the Truſs upon
        the Rings or Orifice from <lb/>whence the Bowel came out. It muſt have a <lb/>gentle hold of
        the upper part of the Os Pubis <lb/>or Sharebone; but take care it is not placed <lb/>too
        high or too low: The Spring will be a <lb/>direction, which ſhould come round the Os
        <lb/>Ilium, and cloſe to the juncture of the Thigh- <lb/>bones, and touch the Rump juſt
        where the clift <lb/>of the Buttocks begins; which parts are called <lb/>by the Anatomiſts,
        the Great Trochanter of <lb/>the Thigh-bones, and the middle of the Os <lb/>Sacrum. The
        Truſs muſt be made ſo tight <lb/>as to make it ſit cloſe, otherwiſe it will neither <lb/>do
        its office, nor be eaſy to the wearer. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Always</hi> keep under the Cuſhion four <lb/>fold of old coarſe linnen,
        which will keep the <lb/>part cool and eaſy, and prevent the Cuſhion <lb/>from being ſpoiled
        by the moiſture of the <pb xml:id="page_8" n="5"/>
        <lb/>Skin. It will be a great addition to the Truſs, <lb/>if for ſix or ſeven weeks, or
        longer (that is to <lb/>ſay, till the Patient has compleated his cure, <lb/>which, if he has
        youth on his ſide, may poſſi- <lb/>bly be in two months; of which, indeed, I have <lb/>ſeen
        ſome inſtances, but then the Patient has <lb/>been very obſervant of the rules preſcribed
        <lb/>him) the parts are bathed with very cold wa- <lb/>ter every night and morning, which
        may be <lb/>done conveniently in the following manner: <lb/>Take a piece of large linen
        cloth, fold it up <lb/>pretty thick ſo as to be about ſix or ſeven in- <lb/>ches ſquare, a
        few ſtitches may be put into it to <lb/>keep the folds together; dip it into a baſon of
        <lb/>cold water, (but, that you may not wet the <lb/>Truſs, looſe it, and lay the Pad or
        Cuſhion <lb/>that was in the Groin up to the Navel out of the <lb/>way of the water) then
        ſqueeze and apply it to <lb/>the Scrotum and Groin, and as it loſes its cold- <lb/>ness dip
        it in the water again and again, which <lb/>ſhould be continued for half an hour at a time:
        <lb/>It is moſt convenient this cold bathing ſhould <lb/>be performed when the Patient is
        naked in <lb/>bed. It is neceſſary that the Patient's breeches <lb/>ſhould be very long in
        the Thighs, ſo as to al- <lb/>low the waiſtband to come high up on the Pel- <lb/>vices above
        the Truſs, for if it bear thereon it <pb xml:id="page_9" n="6"/>
        <lb/>will add ſo much to the preſſure, which will <lb/>make it very uneaſy. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">must</hi> here adviſe my Reader, that in ex- <lb/>amining any thing
        like a Rupture, he does not <lb/>miſtake a Swelling of the Spermatic Chord, <lb/>or in the
        Groin, for one; as by handling any <lb/>thing of that kind roughly, he may not only
        <lb/>give the Patient an exquiſite deal of pain, but <lb/>do great miſchief. If it is really
        a Rupture, <lb/>gentle means, without being in too great a <lb/>hurry, will anſwer beſt. A
        very gentle preſ- <lb/>ſure of the Fingers in an erect poſture will <lb/>ſometimes cauſe it
        to diſappear: But if this <lb/>ſhold fail, lay your Patient on his Back; then <lb/>rub your
        Fingers upwards and downwards ob- <lb/>liquely from the Os Ilium to the Os Pubis. <lb/>This
        is to be continued for a conſiderable <lb/>time; but if it ſhould not remove it, and it
        <lb/>ſtill continues to the touch as at firſt, the Pa- <lb/>tient muſt continue in the ſame
        ſituation, and <lb/>have the part fomented, and the above opera- <lb/>tion again performed:
        After which, ſhould it <lb/>ſtill continue hard, it is certainly no Rupture <note
          place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* When a Surgeon meaſures a Patient for a Truſs, he
          is <lb/>to take it round very cloſe to the juncture of the Thigh- <lb/>bone to the Os
          Ilium, which is the proper place for <lb/>the Truſs to be wore; then ſending the number of
          in- <lb/>ches that the meaſure contains to the Truſs-maker, he <lb/>never can make an
          error; but he muſt, too, be in- <lb/>formed on which ſide the Rupture is; whether it is
          <lb/>double, or whether it is only in the Groin, or in both <lb/>Groins, ſo as to deſcend
          as low on one ſide as the Teſti- <lb/>cles. </note>. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_10" n="7"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">have</hi> been frequently ſhocked at the <lb/>cruelty with which I have
        ſeen Surgeons uſe <lb/>their Patients, merely by miſtaking a Swel- <lb/>ling for a
        Rupture.—On theſe occaſions I <lb/>have remonſtrated;—but as I was not bred a <lb/>Surgeon,
        my counſel was treated with con- <lb/>tempt, altho' they quickly found their at- <lb/>tempts
        in that way were in vain. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> may not here be improper to obſerve, <lb/>that my knowledge in
        theſe matters took its <lb/>firſt riſe from being afflicted with a Rupture <lb/>myſelf. I
        tried all the different kinds of Truſſes <lb/>that have been uſed and recommended by
        <lb/>Surgeons for many years back, but found the <lb/>beſt of them ſubject to ſome
        inconveniency. <lb/>However, as I was originally a Mechanic, I <lb/>went to work with an
        intention to avoid the <lb/>inconveniencies of thoſe I had uſed; and after <lb/>trying
        ſeveral different new forms, I at laſt hit <lb/>upon that which I now offer to the Public,
        <lb/>and has given ſo much ſatisfaction to all who <lb/>have uſed it. As to any farther
        knowledge <pb xml:id="page_11" n="8"/>
        <lb/>I have of Ruptures, I am obliged to ſome Gen- <lb/>tlemen of the Faculty, particularly
        Dr. Hun- <lb/>ter and Dr. Livingſton; alſo to Dr. Barry, for <lb/>the books he recommended
        to my peruſal. <lb/>When put you in mind how ridiculous the <lb/>Surgeons of former times
        appear in this <lb/>more enlightened age, in having rejected <lb/><hi rend="italic">Frere
          Jaques</hi>'s new method of Cutting for the <lb/>Stone, for no other reaſon but becauſe he
        was <lb/>not a regular bred Surgeon, I hope no Gen- <lb/>tleman of the Faculty will condemn
        my Truſs, <lb/>till he can prove its having any deficiency, <lb/>and has compared it very
        narrowly with others <lb/>that continue in uſe. The recommendation of <lb/>thoſe who have
        experienced its benefit (which <lb/>ſome thouſands in the dominions of Britain, <lb/>France,
        Italy, Germany, Holland, and Por- <lb/>tugal, have done) would perhaps be ſuffi- <lb/>cient,
        but that many people who are ſubject <lb/>to any diſorder of that kind are fond of con-
        <lb/>cealing it, and conſequently will never mention <lb/>any thing of my Truſs. However, in
        my be- <lb/>ing conſtituted Truſs-Maker to his Majeſty's <lb/>Royal Hoſpital at Greenwich;
        even when Mr. <lb/>Alexander Reid, firſt Surgeon's Mate of Chel- <lb/>ſea Hoſpital; Mr.
        William Blackey, of the <lb/>College of Surgeons at Paris; and Mr. Ed- <lb/>diſon, <hi
          rend="italic">Bedſtead-Maker,</hi> of Hanover-Street, <pb xml:id="page_12" n="9"/>
        <lb/>Long-Acre, with a letter of recommenda- <lb/>tion ſigned by a great number of <hi
          rend="italic">regular-bred</hi>
        <lb/>Surgeons, (amongſt whom I wiſh Mr. Haw- <lb/>kins had not been one) ſome of them too
        the <lb/>moſt eminent in the profeſſion in Truſſes in Lon- <lb/>don; were candidates in
        oppoſition to me, can- <lb/>not fail to give the Public a juſt idea ofits merit. <lb/>Theſe
        gentlemen, it is well known, did ſtand a <lb/>fair trial with me every day, almoſt for two
        <lb/>months, before the Phyſicians and Surgeons of <lb/>the Royal Hoſpital made their report
        of the <lb/>candidates different merits; on which I was ap- <lb/>pointed Elaſtic Truſs-maker
        by the Honorable <lb/>Board of Directors of his Majeſty's Royal <lb/>Hoſpital. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">think</hi> it would be here an unpardonable <lb/>offence to poſterity,
        not to inform my Read- <lb/>ers, that to this day a Surgeon of the greateſt <lb/>eminence
        recommends a <hi rend="italic">Shoemaker.</hi> to all his <lb/>Ruptured Patients to make the
        Truſſes for <lb/>them, though I am very certain he does not <lb/>know iron from ſteel, when
        it is made out of <lb/>the common ſizes of the bars thereof. This I <lb/>have from
        jobbing-ſmiths, ſome of whom the <lb/>ſeller has employed ever ſince he was con- <lb/>verted
        from a <hi rend="italic">Shoemaker</hi> into a Truſs-maker. <lb/>It is this <hi
          rend="italic">eminent Surgeon</hi> and this <hi rend="italic">Shoemaker</hi>
        <lb/>that Counſellor Brand, at May's Hill, Green- <pb xml:id="page_13" n="10"/>
        <lb/>wich, means in his letter therefrom to me, <lb/>which is hereafter inſerted for the uſe
        of the <lb/>public, amongſt others ſent me, together with <lb/>Certificates of the Efficacy
        of my Truſſes above <lb/>all others made uſe of. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Shortly</hi> after I had invented my Elaſtic <lb/>Truſs, I had an
        opportunity of ſending ſome <lb/>of them to Mr. Ranby, Principal Serjeant- <lb/>Surgeon to
        his Majeſty; in conſequence of <lb/>which I received the following letter. </p>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">To</hi>
          <hi rend="sc">Robert Brand</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Cutler, in</hi> Aberdeen. </head>
        <lb/>
        <salute>"SIR, </salute>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Some</hi> time ago, I believe about the time <lb/>you mention, a
          Soldier left two Truſſes at <lb/>my houſe, and in a day or two afterwards <lb/>took them
          away. I underſtood from my <lb/>ſervant that he was the maker of them. <lb/>They appeared
          to me to vary a little from <lb/>the common ones: However, when you <lb/>come up in June,
          bring ſome with you, <lb/>which if upon trial anſwer better than <lb/>thoſe uſed now, you
          will certainly meet <lb/>with encouragement. </p>
        <signed rend="indent hanging">
          <lb/>I am <lb/>Your moſt obedient Servant, <lb/>J. RANBY." </signed>
        <lb/>
        <dateline><hi rend="italic">Chelſea College,</hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 10, 1764. </dateline>
      </div>
      <pb xml:id="page_14" n="11"/>
      <div>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>"<hi rend="sc">That</hi> I bought one of theſe Truſſes from <lb/>the bearer, Robert
          Brand, Cutler, and <lb/>that it has done better with me than one I <lb/>had from England,
          or one I had made in <lb/>this place; is in juſtice and gratitude to <lb/>his merit </p>
        <lb/>
        <dateline rend="indent">Atteſted, at Aberdeen, May 30th, <lb/>1764, by </dateline>
        <signed rend="align-right">
          <lb/>J. <hi rend="sc">Ogleby</hi>, <lb/>Miniſter, at Aberdeen." </signed>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>"I <hi rend="sc">shall</hi> only add (which is indeed truth) <lb/>that this Truſs is
          ſo very convenient, <lb/>that I can walk and do every thing elſe <lb/>as freely with it as
          if I had no ailment at <lb/>all. </p>
        <signed rend="align-right">
          <lb/>J. O." </signed>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>"<hi rend="sc">In</hi> juſtice and gratitude to Robert Brand, <lb/>Truſſ-maker, in
          Aberdeen, I acknowledge <lb/>that I have had a Rupture for theſe five <lb/>years; that
          about that time I was an inva- <lb/>lid, doing garriſon duty at the Iſland of
          <lb/>Guernſey, I had a Truſs purchaſed at Lon- <lb/>don for me by Mr. Roſe, the King's Re-
            <pb xml:id="page_15" n="12"/>
          <lb/>ceiver in the iſland; which I wore, but with <lb/>great pain, for the ſpace of four
          years. I <lb/>then got a Truſs which came from Chel- <lb/>ſea Hoſpital, but with no better
          ſucceſs; <lb/>until about a month ago, I purchaſed one <lb/>from Mr. Brand, being a ſingle
          Truſs and <lb/>fitted for the right ſide, which has anſwer- <lb/>ed the intent, by giving
          me no pain in my <lb/>walking, keeps up the Rupture, and with- <lb/>out the incumbrance of
          a Thigh-ſtrap: <lb/>Is atteſted to be truth by me, this 30th day <lb/>of May, 1764. </p>
        <signed rend="align-right">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Alexander Forbes</hi>." </signed>
      </div>
      <lb/>
      <div>
        <dateline rend="italic">Aberdeen. </dateline>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>"<hi rend="sc">The</hi> above declaration is atteſted by me, <lb/>John Dye, of
          Tilligrieg, one of his Ma- <lb/>jeſty's Juſtices of the Peace for the County <lb/>of
          Aberdeen, </p>
        <signed rend="align-right">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">John Dye</hi>, J. P." </signed>
      </div>
      <lb/>
      <div>
        <dateline><hi rend="italic">Aberdeen,</hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">May</hi> 30, 1764. </dateline>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>"I Doctor Thomas Livingſton, Phyſician <lb/>to the Infirmary at Aberdeen, do hereby
          <lb/>certify, that Robert Brand, Cutler, in this <lb/>City, has beſtowed great pains and
          atten- <pb xml:id="page_16" n="13"/>
          <lb/>tion in contriving a new conſtruction of <lb/>Rupture-truſſes, which, for eaſe as
          well as <lb/>prevention of the diſeaſe, ſeems to anſwer <lb/>better than the ordinary
          Truſſes formerly in <lb/>uſe; and it conſiſts with my particular know- <lb/>ledge, that
          many people have uſed them <lb/>with great benefit and ſatisfaction. </p>
        <signed rend="align-right">
          <lb/>Atteſted by <hi rend="sc">Thomas Livingston</hi>." </signed>
        <lb/>
        <dateline><hi rend="italic">Aberdeen,</hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 2, 1764. </dateline>
      </div><div>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> January, 1765, the following Memorial <lb/>was preſented to the
          <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Society for the <lb/>Encouragement of Arts, &amp;c.</hi> by
        Mr. Barclay, <lb/>their Secretary. </p>
        <lb/></div><div>
      <salute rend="indent">"My <hi rend="sc">Lords</hi> and <hi rend="sc">Gentlemen</hi>, </salute>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">humbly</hi> beg leave to repreſent to you, <lb/>that Ruptures are
        unfortunately too com- <lb/>mon: Perhaps the fourth part of mankind <lb/>labour under them
        in old age; and as to <lb/>women who have had children, if half of <lb/>them eſcape
        accidents of this kind, it is a <lb/>miracle. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_17" n="14"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Being</hi> originally <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* When
          I ſay <hi rend="italic">originally,</hi> I would be underſtood that it <lb/>was the firſt
          trade I followed: and I am not, I ought <lb/>not to be aſhamed of ſaying, though I
          practiſed it ſome <lb/>years with great ſuceſs, I was not regularly bred even to <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">that,</hi> nor any other trade whatever. </note> a Cutler and Surgeon's
        <lb/>Inſtrument-maker, and having been for ma- <lb/>ny years afflicted with a Rupture which
        great- <lb/>ly incommoded me in the neceſſary functi- <lb/>ons of life, I had recourſe to
        the various <lb/>Truſſes and Bandages made uſe of for re- <lb/>lieving that misfortune, both
        from London <lb/>and Paris; but finding them very incom- <lb/>modious as well as
        ineffectual, I applied <lb/>myſelf with great attention to the improve- <lb/>ment of thoſe
        neceſſary contrivances; and, <lb/>after many years repeated trials and many <lb/>years
        experience have at laſt happily ſucceed- <lb/>ed, and ſo greatly improved the Steel Truſs,
        <lb/>as to make it anſwer every deſireable purpoſe <lb/>for the curing as well as palliating
        that trou- <lb/>bleſome diſorder; which numbers as well <lb/>as myſelf have experienced,
        both here and in <lb/>London; to authenticate which aſſertion, <lb/>letters, ſhould it be
        thought neceſſary, can <lb/>be produced from Patients reſident at both <lb/>places. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_18" n="15"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> great advantages which my Truſſes <lb/>have, in conſequence of
        this Improvement, <lb/>above others, are as follow: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">First</hi>, by an Elaſtic Spring, peculiar <lb/>to themſelves, they are
        accommodated <lb/>equally well to perſons of every Age and <lb/>Size; ſo that two different
        Sizes is the only <lb/>requiſite for making them fit every perſon <lb/>of above two years of
        age; and the ſame <lb/>circumſtance likewiſe makes them more <lb/>proper for exportation
        than any hitherto <lb/>invented. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Secondly</hi>, They do not require that <lb/>troubleſome and incommodious
        appendage <lb/>a Thigh-ſtrap, ſo commonly uſed in other <lb/>Bandages. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Thirdly</hi>, They by the Elaſticity above- <lb/>mentioned maintain a
        conſtant, equal, and <lb/>uniform preſſure on the part only affected, <lb/>and imitate the
        kind preſſure of the Hand <lb/>in all its degrees, in all the different atti- <lb/>tudes of
        the Body; whereby the parts mak- <lb/>ing the Rupture are ſo conſtantly kept from
        <lb/>coming down, that an opportunity is given <lb/>to the relaxed and ruptured parts
        through <pb xml:id="page_19" n="16"/>
        <lb/>which they deſcend to recover their former <lb/>ſtate, and thereby prove to the Patient
        a <lb/>radical Cure. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Fourthly</hi>, I can afford to ſell the above- <lb/>mentioned Truſſes at
        as low a price as the <lb/>other Truſſ-makers in Britain ſell their Iron <lb/>Truſſes,
        without any other property to them <lb/>than dignifying them with the names of Steel
        <lb/>and Spring Truſſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">These</hi>, and other advantages, too te- <lb/>dious to mention, convince
        me that this im- <lb/>provement, when generally known, will <lb/>prove a very great benefit
        to a very great <lb/>part of mankind: And therefore I perſuade <lb/>myſelf that ſhould it
        meet with your appro- <lb/>bation, I ſhall not fail of ſharing that encou- <lb/>ragement and
        generoſity which ſo highly dig- <lb/>nifies your honourable Society. </p>
      <signed rend="align-right size(0.5)">
        <lb/>I am, <lb/>My Lords and Gentlemen, <lb/>with the moſt profound reſpect, <lb/>your moſt
        obedient Servant, <lb/>ROBERT BRAND." </signed>
      <dateline rend="size(0.5)">[TRUE COPY.] <lb/><hi rend="italic">Aberdeen,</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Jun.</hi> 28, 1765. </dateline></div>
      <pb xml:id="page_20" n="17"/><div>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> conſequence of the preſentation of the <lb/>foregoing memorial I
        received the following <lb/>letter: </p></div><div>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">To</hi>
        <hi rend="sc">Robert Brand</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Cutler,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
          >Truſs-Ma- <lb/>ker,</hi> in Aberdeen: </head>
      <lb/>
      <salute>SIR, </salute>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">You</hi> here have the report Dr. Monro gives <lb/>the Society of Arts,
        on the back of your me- <lb/>morial, which I returned this day to Mr. <lb/>Barclay, who ſaid
        it would make nothing as to <lb/>premium. After his reſpectful compliments <lb/>to the
        honourable Society, Dr. Monro ſays, <lb/>"The Truſſes Mr. Brand preſents is no new
        <lb/>invention, as there is of the ſame kind and <lb/>ſame materials uſed by moſt Surgeons
        in <lb/>Europe for many years paſt: The only eſ- <lb/>ſential circumſtance is, the circular
        Steel <lb/>Spring is more ſtrict than thoſe in common <lb/>uſe, which makes them ſit eaſier
        on the Pati- <lb/>ent, and better fit perſons of different ſizes." <lb/>He adds, "that this
        laſt is ſcarce worth obſer- <lb/>vation, as each perſon ought to have his <pb
          xml:id="page_21" n="18"/>
        <lb/>meaſure taken in the moſt accurate man- <lb/>ner. <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 6th,
        1765." </p>
      <signed rend="align-right">
        <lb/>Your moſt obedient Servant, <lb/>JOHN PIRRIE. </signed>
      <lb/>
      <dateline><hi rend="italic">Edinburgh,</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 7th, 1765. </dateline></div><div>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple quotes">"P. S. A few days after I delivered your <lb/>memorial to Mr. Barclay he called
          at my <lb/>houſe, and told me the Society had pitched on <lb/>Dr. Monro to examine into
          the merits of your <lb/>Truſſes; which the Doctor very readily aſ- <lb/>ſented to, and
          that I muſt carry them to him <lb/>directly; which I accordingly did. On <lb/>opening the
          box, taking them out, and ſhew- <lb/>ing them to the Doctor, he ſaid they were <lb/>made
          in the ſame manner as Mr. Auchinlec <lb/>here makes them. I ſaid there was a <hi
            rend="italic">great</hi>
          <lb/>difference. But ſtill the Doctor inſiſted there <lb/>was <hi rend="italic">none.</hi>
          On this, his ſon ſtept into another <lb/>room, and brought one of Auchinlec's mak-
          <lb/>ing out, and on comparing them together, he <lb/>confeſſed there <hi rend="italic"
            >was</hi> a difference.—Had he <lb/>ſuffered as much pain with Truſſes as I have
          <lb/>done, he would ſooner have ſeen it. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">When</hi> perſons of confined ideas, and who <lb/>have not the advantages
        of education, fall into <pb xml:id="page_22" n="19"/>
        <lb/>an error, there is an excuſe ready for them: <lb/>The groſs miſtakes of a man of
        letters are un- <lb/>pardonable. Dr. Monro's miſapprehenſion in- <lb/>deed ſeems <hi
          rend="sc">Wilful</hi>. Could any thing be more <lb/>uncandid than his declaration that my
        Truſſes <lb/>and Mr. Auchinlec's were alike?—Could <lb/>any thing be more mean than the
        hard-ſtrain'd <lb/>acknowledgement, that <q rend="quotes">there was <hi rend="italic">ſome
            dif- <lb/>ference?</hi>
        </q> In his report he ſays, <q rend="quotes">that my <lb/>Truſs differs from others, only in
          the circular <lb/>Steel Spring being more ſtrict than thoſe in <lb/>common uſe; which
          makes them ſit <hi rend="italic">eaſier,</hi>
          <lb/>and better fit perſons of <hi rend="italic">different ſizes;</hi>
        </q> but <lb/>this <hi rend="italic">eaſe</hi> and this <hi rend="italic">convenience,</hi>
        it ſeems, are not <lb/>worth thinking of, becauſe <q rend="quotes">each perſon ought <lb/>to
          have his meaſure taken in the moſt ac- <lb/>curate manner. </q>—Here is philoſophy!
        <lb/>—I frequently ſend Truſſes to the Eaſt and <lb/>Weſt Indies—Were Dr. Monro living, I
        <lb/>would ask him, if I ſhould make a voyage <lb/>every time I receive an order.— </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Here</hi> follow ſeveral teſtimonies to the <lb/>merits of my Truſs,
        which, without further <lb/>ceremony, the Reader will, I believe, accept. </p></div><div>
      <pb xml:id="page_23" n="20"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">To</hi> Mr. <hi rend="sc">Brand</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Great
          Peter's Street,</hi>
        <lb/>Weſtminſter. </head>
      <lb/>
      <salute>SIR, </salute>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>"<hi rend="sc">The</hi> Machine you laſt left with me does <lb/>its office very well,
        and ſits eaſy. </p>
      <signed rend="align-right">
        <lb/>Your humble Servant, <lb/>J. B." </signed>
      <lb/>
      <dateline><hi rend="italic">Greenwich,</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Auguſt 7th,</hi> 1765. </dateline></div><div>
      <head rend="align-cneter">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">To</hi> Mr. <hi rend="sc">Brand</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Great
          Peter's Street,</hi>
        <lb/>Weſtminſter. </head>
      <lb/>
      <salute>Mr. <hi rend="sc">Brand</hi>, </salute>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>"<hi rend="sc">After</hi> a variety of Truſſes I have made <lb/>uſe of from different
        perſons recommended to <lb/>me by a Surgeon of great character in Town, <lb/>which did not
        do their office; yours that I <lb/>have now on, and have worn conſtantly nine <lb/>or ten
        weeks, not only fully anſwers its <lb/>purpoſe of keeping the Gut up, but ſits very
        <lb/>eaſy, and is attended with little or no trou- <lb/>ble. </p>
      <signed rend="align-right">
        <lb/>J. BRAND, <lb/>Counſellor at Law." </signed>
      <lb/>
      <dateline><hi rend="italic">Greenwich,</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Sept. 11th,</hi> 1765. </dateline></div><div>
      <pb xml:id="page_24" n="21"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>"<hi rend="sc">On</hi> the recommendation of Dr. Hunter, <lb/>I made uſe of Mr. Brand's
        Elaſtic Truſs, <lb/>to a youth about ſeven years of age, who <lb/>had been afflicted with a
        Scrotal Rupture <lb/>for two or three years. I had uſed in the <lb/>courſe of that time
        ſeveral ineffectual means <lb/>without ſucceſs: Yours he wore with great <lb/>eaſe, and
        intirely prevented any return of the <lb/>diſorder. </p>
      <lb/>
      <dateline>Witneſs my Hand this 27th Day of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Feb.</hi> 1766. </dateline>
      <signed rend="align-right">
        <lb/>W. TAYLER, <lb/>Late Surgeon of the Dock-Yard <lb/>at <hi rend="italic">Woolwich,</hi>
        a new Surgeon <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Greenwich Hoſpital."</hi>
      </signed></div><div>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>"<hi rend="sc">These</hi> are to certify that I have ſeen <lb/>Mr. Brand's Bandages for
        Ruptures, and <lb/>that from the ſeveral opportunities I have <lb/>had for them, find they
        anſwer better than <lb/>any other I have had occaſion to uſe. </p>
      <signed rend="align-right">
        <lb/>W. NORTON, <lb/>Navy Surgeon." </signed>
      <lb/>
      <dateline><hi rend="italic">Strand,</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">June 2d,</hi> 1766. </dateline></div><div>
      <pb xml:id="page_25" n="22"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>"<hi rend="sc">This</hi> is to certify, that I have frequently <lb/>recommended Mr.
        Robert Brand, Truſs- <lb/>Maker, whoſe Bandages always gave great <lb/>ſatisfaction to my
        Patients, and to me. </p>
      <signed rend="align-right">
        <lb/>R. BROMFIELD, M. D." </signed>
      <lb/>
      <dateline><hi rend="italic">Gerard-Street,</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">July 18th,</hi> 1766. </dateline></div><div>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>"<hi rend="sc">These</hi> are to certify, that I have ſeen <lb/>and carefully examined
        the Elaſtic Bandages <lb/>for Ruptures, made by Mr. Robert Brand, <lb/>of Peter-Street
        Weſtminſter, Truſs-Maker; <lb/>and am of opinion, that they are neat and <lb/>ſtrong in
        their conſtruction, very ingenious <lb/>in their contrivance, and more peculiarly
        <lb/>adapted to ſeveral purpoſes of a Truſs <lb/>than any other Bandage I have ever ſeen. </p>
      <lb/>
      <dateline>Given under my Hand, this 18th Day of <lb/><hi rend="italic">July,</hi> 1766. </dateline>
      <signed rend="align-right">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">St. Martin's-Lane.</hi>
        <lb/>C. KELLY, M. D." </signed></div><div>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>"<hi rend="sc">Having</hi> made uſe of the Truſſes made <lb/>by Mr. Brand, on ſome
        Patients afflicted <lb/>with Ruptures, I think it no more than a <lb/>piece of juſtice due
        to his ingenuity, to ac- <lb/>knowledge, that they have ſucceeded very <pb xml:id="page_26"
          n="23"/>
        <lb/>well in fulfilling the intention for which <lb/>they were applied; nor have I ever ſeen
        <lb/>any Truſſes which I ſhould prefer to them. </p>
      <signed rend="align-right">
        <lb/>W. HEWSON, <lb/>Surgeon." </signed>
      <lb/>
      <dateline>Now in <hi rend="italic">Argyle Buildings, <lb/>Oxford Road,</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 17, 1766. </dateline></div><div>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>"<hi rend="sc">These</hi> are humbly to certify the Go- <lb/>vernors of the Royal
        Hoſpital at Green- <lb/>wich, that I have ſeen ſeveral inſtances of <lb/>Ruptures, where the
        Patients have unſuc- <lb/>ceſſfully made uſe of ſeveral Operators <lb/>Truſſes, which were
        painful and uneaſy to <lb/>them; and afterwards being adviſed to uſe <lb/>Mr. Brand's
        Elaſtic ones, they found <lb/>ſpeedy eaſe, and no pain therefrom; <lb/>and for that reaſon,
        in my opinion, his <lb/>deſerves the preference of all other Truſſes. </p>
      <signed rend="align-right">
        <lb/>T. POOLE, <lb/>Surgeon of the Royal Navy." </signed>
      <lb/>
      <dateline><hi rend="italic">Savoy,</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">Auguſt,</hi> 29, 1766. </dateline></div><div>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>"I <hi rend="sc">have</hi> ſeen ſome inſtances where Mr. <pb xml:id="page_27" n="24"/>
        <lb/>Brand's Elaſtic Truſſes have been ſucceſſ- <lb/>ful, where others have failed. </p>
      <signed rend="align-right">
        <lb/>E. BARRY, M. D." </signed>
      <lb/>
      <dateline>Now in <hi rend="italic">Bath,</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Auguſt 20th,</hi> 1766. </dateline></div><div>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>"I <hi rend="sc">have</hi> ſeen ſome inſtances where Mr. <lb/>Brand's Elaſtic Truſſes
        have been ſucceſſ- <lb/>ful, where others have failed; therefore I <lb/>think they deſerve
        peculiar notice. </p>
      <signed rend="align-right">
        <lb/>F. PINKSTON, <lb/>Surgeon." </signed>
      <lb/>
      <dateline><hi rend="italic">St. Alban's-Street</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Auguſt 29th,</hi> 1766. </dateline></div><div>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>"<hi rend="sc">These</hi> are to certify that I recommended a <lb/>Patient to Mr.
        Brand, who had been afflicted <lb/>from his infancy with an inguinal Rupture, <lb/>and had
        tried all means for a cure, with the <lb/>different ſorts of Truſſes, without ſucceſs, giv-
        <lb/>ing him great pain in wearing them, ſo that <lb/>he was often obliged to leave them
        off, and <lb/>his Rupture would as often come down; <lb/>but after applying Mr. Brand's
        Truſs, he <lb/>found to his great ſatisfaction that he could <lb/>wear it with great eaſe,
        and declared himſelf <lb/>much obliged to the ingenious Author <pb xml:id="page_28" n="25"/>
        <lb/>of ſuch a Truſs, from which he had found <lb/>ſo much relief. </p>
      <signed rend="align-center">
        <lb/>As witneſs my Hand, <lb/>HUGH CRAWFORD, M. D." </signed>
      <lb/>
      <dateline><hi rend="italic">Leiceſter-Fields,</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Auguſt 25th,</hi> 1766. </dateline></div><div>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> the caſe referred to by this Gentleman, <lb/>on reducing the
        Rupture, if great care was not <lb/>taken to divide the Teſticle from it, the latter
        <lb/>would follow the former into the Belly. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>"<hi rend="sc">This</hi> is to certify that I have often ex- <lb/>amined, and ſeen
        applied, Mr. Brand's Steel <lb/>Truſſes, and I do imagine that they are bet- <lb/>ter
        adapted for the cure of Ruptures than any <lb/>I have ſeen. </p>
      <signed rend="align-right">
        <lb/>JOHN HUNTER, <lb/>Surgeon." </signed>
      <lb/>
      <dateline>Now in <hi rend="italic">Jermyn Street,</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Auguſt</hi> 24, 1766. </dateline></div><div>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>"I Hereby certify, that after having recom- <lb/>mended various ſorts of Truſſes to my
        Pa- <lb/>tients, I can find none ſo eaſy to the wearers, <lb/>or ſo well adapted to the
        relief of their diſ- <pb xml:id="page_29" n="26"/>
        <lb/>orders, as the Elaſtic Truſſes made by <lb/>Mr. Brand, of Peter-Sreet, Weſtminſter. </p>
      <signed rend="align-right">
        <lb/>C. HALE, <lb/>Surgeon." </signed>
      <lb/>
      <dateline><hi rend="italic">Parliament-Street,</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Auguſt</hi> 25, 1766. </dateline></div><div>
      <head rend="italic indent hanging">
        <lb/>To <hi rend="roman">Mr. ROBERT BRAND</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="sc">Truss-Maker</hi> to his
        Majeſty's Royal Hoſpital <lb/>at Greenwich: At his Houſe in St. Martin's- <lb/>Lane, near
        Charing-Croſs, London. </head>
      <lb/>
      <salute>SIR, </salute>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>"<hi rend="sc">The</hi> generoſity and humanity with which <lb/>you treated me demand
        the moſt grateful <lb/>acknowledgments, and nothing gives me <lb/>more concern than to think
        that neceſſity <lb/>ſhould oblige me to leave London without <lb/>being able to pay you, as
        my friend was not <lb/>in town, and the ſhip going away. There- <lb/>fore I muſt intreat you
        to be patient for a <lb/>ſhort time, and you ſhall have no cauſe to <lb/>complain. In the
        interim I ſend you my <lb/>Note for 2l. 10s. payable in ſix months af- <lb/>ter date, tho'
        the ſum I owe you is only <lb/>2l. 2s. And as I ſhall make a remittance <pb xml:id="page_30"
          n="27"/>
        <lb/>by the return of the ſhip from South Caro- <lb/>lina, to Mr. Edward Upton, in
        Paternoſter- <lb/>Row, I ſhall deſire him at the ſame time to <lb/>take up the Note. Permit
        me to aſſure you, <lb/>Sir, that I ſhall ſpare no pains to recommend <lb/>your Truſſes in
        South Carolina: And in the <lb/>mean time pleaſe to pay my compliments to <lb/>your good
        ſpouſe and ſon. </p>
      <signed rend="indent hanging">
        <lb/>SIR, <lb/>I am, with the greateſt reſpect, <lb/>Your much obliged humble Servant,
        <lb/>G. SPENCER." </signed>
      <lb/>
      <dateline><hi rend="italic">Deal,</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">July 30th,</hi> 1767. </dateline></div><div>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Mr</hi>. Spencer was a gentleman of the <lb/>clergy, and had a living in
        North America. <lb/>Being afflicted with a very large Femoral <lb/>Rupture, he applied to
        ſeveral for relief <lb/>without any ſucceſs; among whom was the <lb/>ingenious Mr. Blackey,
        of Paris, who ap- <lb/>plied a Truſs that was adapted for a Groin <lb/>Rupture on his
        Femoral Rupture; how- <lb/>ever, I made a proper Truſs for him, and ap- <lb/>plied it; which
        I had no ſooner done, and <lb/>he finding that it would do its office, than he <lb/>deſired
        me to take it off. I asked him why? <pb xml:id="page_31" n="28"/>
        <lb/>He ſaid becauſe he had not money ſufficient <lb/>about him to pay for it, and that his
        friend <lb/>was not in town. I told him I had no doubt <lb/>of the money, for I believed him
        a gentle- <lb/>man. On which we parted; and I never <lb/>faw, nor heard from him, till I
        received the <lb/>letter inſerted. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">He</hi> faithfully remitted the money, and I <lb/>received it. </p></div><div>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">To</hi> Mr. ROBERT BRAND. </head>
      <lb/>
      <salute>SIR, </salute>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>"A <hi rend="sc">short</hi> time ſince, I deſired my brother <lb/>to call on you for an
        Elaſtic Steel Truſs, <lb/>for a Patient I have here. During the time <lb/>he has uſed it,
        has found the greateſt be- <lb/>nefit. Have reaſon to think he will get a per- <lb/>fect
        cure, by perſevering in the uſe of it. <lb/>This morning, as he was applying it as uſual,
        <lb/>the part broke as you ſee, which beg you <lb/>to get mended, and ſend to the bearer for
        <lb/>conveyance to, </p>
      <signed rend="indent hanging">
        <lb/>"SIR, <lb/>Your moſt humble Servant, <lb/>WILLIAM ROBBINS." </signed>
      <lb/>
      <dateline><hi rend="italic">Axminſter,</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 11, 1771. </dateline></div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_32"/>
        <head rend="align-center dc(2)">
          <lb/>POSTSCRIPT. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">H</hi>AVING received ſeveral letters <lb/>containing the moſt
          illiberal abuſe, <lb/>in conſequence of the publication of the preced- <lb/>ing pages,
          ſome of which I have reaſon to ſup- <lb/>poſe were written by Counſellor Brand's <note
            place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* See Page 20. </note>
          <hi rend="italic">Surgeon <lb/>of Character;</hi> I think it neceſſary to declare,
          <lb/>that I never intended, nor, indeed, could I <lb/>form an idea, that the Treatiſe in
          queſtion <lb/>ſhould give the ſmalleſt offence to any Gentle- <lb/>man of the Faculty. My
          ſole object was—the <lb/>relief of my fellow-creatures, and the inſtruc- <lb/>tion of the
          ignorant in that which it is neceſ- <lb/>ſary they ſhould know.—Beſides improv- <lb/>ing
          their practice, I have a right to the thanks <lb/>of the Faculty, for pointing out the
          moſt ef- <lb/>ficacious cure of a Malady, from which <hi rend="italic">they</hi>
          <lb/>are by no means exempt—and which the moſt <lb/>eminent of them have had no little
          trouble to <lb/>remove.—And I ſincerely wiſh I could not <lb/>ſay with truth, that numbers
          have, within theſe <lb/>few years, loſt their lives, after having paid <lb/>very
          conſiderable ſums for pretended aſſiſ- <lb/>tance, and ineffectual advice. It is intereſt,
            <pb xml:id="page_33" n="30"/>
          <lb/>then, alone that prevents theſe cavillers from <lb/>doing juſtice to my performances,
          and which <lb/>prompts them to cheat the diſordered of aſ- <lb/>ſiſtance. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">am</hi> acquainted with Surgeons who have <lb/>been many years in
          practice, and who have aſ- <lb/>ſured me they never had an opportunity of <lb/>reducing a
          Rupture, or of applying a Truſs. <lb/>—A midwife, too, who has been up- <lb/>wards of
          twenty years in practice, lately de- <lb/>clared to me, that, to her knowledge, ſhe ne-
          <lb/>ver had delivered a woman that had a Rup- <lb/>ture either in the Groin or Navel.—Yet
          have <lb/>I applied Bandages on a variety of both.— </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Notwithstanding</hi> the <hi rend="italic">true method</hi> of ap-
          <lb/>plying Truſſes, or <hi rend="italic">reducing Ruptures,</hi> is a mat- <lb/>ter of
          the utmoſt importance in the treatment <lb/>of that malady, and in the higheſt degree con-
          <lb/>ducive to the eaſe of the Patient, I am bold to <lb/>ſay, that in all the treatiſes I
          have peruſed, both <lb/>antient and modern (and they are not a few), <lb/>I never met with
          any thing like a clear inſtruc- <lb/>tion to that purpoſe.—Something <hi rend="italic"
            >curious,</hi>
          <lb/>tho' by no means advantageous, may be col- <lb/>lected from a book lately
          publiſhed.—(The <lb/>Author, I think, dignifies his name with, <pb xml:id="page_34" n="31"/>
          <lb/>
          <q rend="diple">Maſter of Arts and Surgery, Member of <lb/>the Royal Academy of Surgery at
            Paris, <lb/>Demonſtrator in the School of St. Come, <lb/>Surgeon for Ruptures of the
            Hoſpitals of <lb/>Hotel Dieu, the Invalids and Incurables, <lb/>of the City of Paris,
            and of all the military <lb/>Hoſpitals in France.) </q> A proceſs is there <lb/>adviſed
          for making an ointment of a ſolution <lb/>of Gold Pearls, to be uſed for aſſiſting the
          <lb/>reduction of ſtrangulated Ruptures.— <lb/>When this ingenious and moſt expenſive pre-
          <lb/>paration is compleated, it will probably be as <lb/>efficacious as the ſame quantity
          of clay, in the <lb/>ſame manner applied. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">hoped</hi> in the treatiſes above hinted at, to <lb/>have found
          ſomething that would, at leaſt, <lb/>have been capable of improvement in the true
          <lb/>method of applying Truſſes, and the reducing <lb/>Ruptures:—On the contrary, they
          contain <lb/>merely long and unſatisfactory details of the <lb/>manner in which the
          antient Surgeons com- <lb/>monly burnt the Ruptures of their Patients, <lb/>and deſtroyed
          the fleſh of thoſe parts to the <lb/>Bone, with a view of avoiding the more ne-
          <lb/>ceſſary application of Truſſes.—This is one <lb/>proof, among many, that Surgeons
          never en- <lb/>couraged Truſſes, altho' it is univerſally ac- <pb xml:id="page_35" n="32"/>
          <lb/>knowledged that it is impoſſible a cure can be <lb/>perfectly obtained without ſuch
          an aſſiſtant.— <lb/>The pain attending the wearing of ſome <lb/>Truſſes, it muſt be
          acknowledged, has pre- <lb/>vented many perſons from adhering to the <lb/>moſt ſalutary
          method of cure; but ſuch neg- <lb/>lect is often attended with the moſt dreadful
          <lb/>conſequences; it being no uncommon thing <lb/>to meet perſons in the ſtreet, whoſe
          Guts <lb/>partly falling into their breeches, exhibit a <lb/>deplorable and pitiable
          ſpectacle. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">And</hi> here it may not be improper to inform <lb/>the Reader of the
          encouragement I received <lb/>from the Faculty on my arrival in London, <lb/>which was in
          June, 1764. Mr. Ranby being <lb/>the only gentleman of the profeſſion I had <lb/>the
          honour of knowing, I waited upon him; <lb/>and, by his deſire, afterwards attended the
          <lb/>Gentlemen of St. George's Hoſpital. With <lb/>the countenance of ſuch a Gentleman as
          Mr. <lb/>Ranby, whoſe name and letter to me at <lb/>Aberdeen I had the liberty to uſe, I
          could not <lb/>but form the moſt pleaſing hopes of convin- <lb/>cing ſome of the firſt
          Surgeons in England of <lb/>the merit and utility of my Truſſes.—But <lb/>I was
          diſappointed: I found, tho' they were <lb/>men of learning, they were not men of can- <pb
            xml:id="page_36" n="33"/>
          <lb/>dor. —Mr. Bromfield ſaid, <q rend="quotes">he believed they <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >might do.</hi>
          </q> Mr. Gataker ſaid, <q rend="quotes">he could <lb/>ſee nothing more in <hi
              rend="italic">my</hi> Truſſes than in <hi rend="italic">any</hi>
            <lb/><hi rend="italic"> other.</hi>
          </q> However, while I was one day at- <lb/>tending a perſon, then under the care of Mr.
          <lb/>Hawkins, he informed me that he had long <lb/>been an Out-patient of that Hoſpital,
          and had <lb/>Truſſes from every Truſſ-maker in Town, <lb/>but that none of them would keep
          his Rup- <lb/>ture up; and that ſince he had been under Mr. <lb/>Hawkins's care, he had
          procured him a Truſs <lb/>from a perſon in Bartholomew Cloſe, which <lb/>would by no means
          keep up his Rupture, tho' <lb/>he had been to the maker twenty times to have <lb/>it
          altered, who told him his Rupture would <lb/>never be well 'till he had it cut. I looked
          <lb/>upon this as an opportunity, offered me by <lb/>Providence, of at once doing a
          ſervice to a fel- <lb/>low-creature, and bringing conviction of the <lb/>uſe of my Elaſtic
          Truſſes to thoſe who had <lb/>ignorantly or intereſtedly denied their merits. <lb/>I
          brought the youth to my lodgings, and there <lb/>applied a Truſs on him; my honeſt endea-
          <lb/>vours had the deſired effect; and in about <lb/>three months, he obtained a compleat
          cure. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Lest</hi> any of my Readers ſhould doubt <lb/>the truth of this
          relation, I deſire to inform <pb xml:id="page_37" n="34"/>
          <lb/>them that the name of the above-mentioned <lb/>youth is John Pellerſt, whoſe uncle,
          of the <lb/>ſame name, lives in Downe-ſtreet, near Hyde- <lb/>Park Corner; and I believe
          that ſomething <lb/>relative to this affair will be found in the books <lb/>of St.
          George's Hoſpital, from the beginning <lb/>of April 1764, to the end of Auguſt in the
          <lb/>ſame year.—To this caſe I have only <lb/>to add, that notwithſtanding this ample
          proof <lb/>of the merits of my Truſs, I cannot charge Mr. <lb/>Hawkins with recommending a
          ſingle Patient <lb/>to me, tho' he has often confeſſed my Truſſes <lb/>were more
          efficacious than thoſe of any other <lb/>perſon he had knowledge of. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> Mr. Pott's Treatiſe on Ruptures, ſecond <lb/>Edition, Sec. 1.
          Page 29, that gentleman ſays, <lb/>
          <q rend="quotes">The cure of a Rupture is either perfect (called <lb/>alſo radical) or
            imperfect, which is called <lb/>palliative. This diſtinction, which, he ſays, <lb/>is
            juſt and true, and founded both on reaſon <lb/>and experience, has frequently been
            miſun- <lb/>derſtood by the generality of mankind, <lb/>and has therefore been the cauſe
            of much <lb/>undeſerving cenſure on the practitioners of <lb/>Surgery. </q> He adds, <q
            rend="quotes">the truth is, that <lb/>tho' the events are extremely different, yet
            <lb/>the chirurgical means which are made uſe <pb xml:id="page_38" n="35"/>
            <lb/>of in either caſe are exactly the ſame, viz. <lb/>the reduction of the protruded
            parts, and re- <lb/>tention of them when ſo reduced by proper <lb/>Bandages. </q>—I wiſh
          Mr. Pott had given <lb/>the addreſs of his <hi rend="italic">proper Bandage-maker,</hi>
          <lb/>as Dr. Smellie did of his proper Midwifery In- <lb/>ſtrument-maker. I could never
          find thoſe <lb/>Bandages at the <hi rend="italic">Shoemaker</hi>'s, nor at the <hi
            rend="sc"> Rup- <lb/>ture-Curer's</hi>, who has his name diſtinguiſhed <lb/>in the Court
          and City Regiſter for 1771.— <lb/>Convinced at leaſt of their politeneſs in thus
          <lb/>dignifying a man who has little pretenſion to <lb/>public favour, I had no doubt but
          that the com- <lb/>pilers, or compilers directors had compli- <lb/>mented me with a
          ſimilar appellation;—but <lb/>I was again miſtaken: I found (in Page 142) <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">my</hi> deſert would procure me barely the title of <lb/>plain <hi
            rend="italic">Truſſ-maker.</hi>—I wiſh ſome of thoſe perſons <lb/>whom this <hi
            rend="sc">Rupture-Curer</hi> has aſſiſted, would <lb/>perſuade me out of a notion that
          it is death <lb/>which generally performs the cure for this <lb/>worthy gentleman. I am
          aſſured that thoſe <lb/>Truſſes ſaid to be of his making are too painful <lb/>even for a
          horſe to wear. He prides himſelf, <lb/>I am told, on employing the ſame perſons who
          <lb/>did buſineſs for my Predeceſſor.—As <lb/>a proof of the abſurdity of building on
          another's <lb/>ſuppoſed reputation, when I was appointed <pb xml:id="page_39" n="36"/>
          <lb/>Truſs-maker to Greenwich Hoſpital, I could <lb/>not find one in twenty of the
          ruptured men in <lb/>that place, who could wear the Truſſes made <lb/>by my predoceſſor;
          and thoſe who did wear <lb/>them were ſo miſerably fretted and galled on <lb/>their Hips
          and Loins, that they were obliged <lb/>to attend the Surgeon every morning to have
          <lb/>their Wounds dreſſed: So that by my ap- <lb/>pointment, I had the pleaſure not only
          of re- <lb/>lieving the diſeaſed men from the miſery they <lb/>ſuffered by the iron
          Truſſes before made uſe <lb/>of, but prevented the ſurgeons from being <lb/>troubled with
          the like complaints, and ſaved <lb/>the expences of the houſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Being</hi>, about twenty-eight years ſince, af- <lb/>flicted with a
          Rupture, I conſented to become <lb/>a Patient to Meſſrs. Woodward and Hunt; <lb/>and from
          a ſtrict attention to their method, I <lb/>am enabled to give the Reader ſome idea of it.
          <lb/>The firſt object then with them was, to ex- <lb/>amine the Patient—with reſpect to
          his circum- <lb/>ſtances. If he would part freely with his mo- <lb/>ney, they firſt
          applied a linen Bandage; and <lb/>ſhortly after informed him, that was not ſuffi-
          <lb/>cient of itſelf to perform the cure, and that <lb/>they muſt call in the aſſiſtance
          of proper Me- <pb xml:id="page_40" n="37"/>
          <lb/>dicines, with which they would furniſh him at <lb/>one Guinea per Month.—And in this
          way <lb/>did they cajole me out of Fourteen Guineas; <lb/>and my Rupture was greatly worſe
          at the year's <lb/>end than when firſt I became their Patient. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">am</hi> here induced to relate a Story which <lb/>cannot be
          contradicted, and which will ſerve <lb/>ſufficiently to expoſe the fallacy of trifling and
          <lb/>vain pretenders. A gentleman of 70 years of <lb/>age, who has been afflicted many
          years with <lb/>a Rupture, and who has worn a Truſs of my <lb/>making for upwards of theſe
          five years, which <lb/>rendered his Rupture, tho' by no means cura- <lb/>ble, of little
          trouble to him, was very lately <lb/>perſuaded to apply to Mr. L. a Surgeon, for <lb/>a
          complete cure. He accordingly waited on <lb/>that gentleman, to know if he would take his
          <lb/>caſe in hand, and what the expence would be. <lb/>Mr. L. told him he had no doubt of
          effecting <lb/>a cure, even if he was eighty years old; and <lb/>as he was only a
          Tradeſman, he believed he <lb/>could do it for about 30 Guineas; but that <lb/>the Patient
          muſt wait on him every morning. <lb/>This, the gentleman informed him, was a <lb/>thing he
          could not do; and the Surgeon, <lb/>therefore, conſented to call upon him.—Next <pb
            xml:id="page_41" n="38"/>
          <lb/>morning Mr. L. dreſſed in a ſuit of black vel- <lb/>vet, drove in his chariot to his
          Patient's. The <lb/>tradſeman, reflecting that this appearance of <lb/>grandeur was not
          kept up at a ſmall expence, <lb/>determined to make a ſure bargain, and ac- <lb/>cordingly
          told the Surgeon,— <q rend="quotes">Sir, before we <lb/>proceed to buſineſs, let me know
            exactly what <lb/>the expence of this cure will be; and if no <lb/>cure—no pay. </q>—At
          this the Surgeon <lb/>"ſtarted like a <hi rend="italic">guilty thing,"</hi> and turning on
          <lb/>his heel, whipp'd into his chariot, and drove <lb/>home,—no doubt ſufficiently
          mortified at the <lb/>diſappointment.—I have only to remark, <lb/>that if every afflicted
          perſon would endeavour <lb/>to make as certain a bargain as my Patient in- <lb/>tended to
          do with the above-mentioned im- <lb/>pudent aſſertor, the velvet ſuits of ſuch pet-
          <lb/>tifoggers in genius would ſoon be ruſty, and <lb/>their Chariots without a wheel. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">am</hi> acquainted with many perſons of both <lb/>ſexes who have been
          Patients to Mr. L. and <lb/>they all agree that the following is his method <lb/>of
          operation: Firſt, he applies a Bandage, <lb/>as Woodward and Hunt uſed to do. The Pati-
          <lb/>ent muſt then attend on him once a day for <lb/>ſo many times as he ſhall appoint,
          and at <lb/>theſe times he applies a bruſh dipt in ſome- <pb xml:id="page_42" n="39"/>
          <lb/>thing which he calls an Aſtringent. When he <lb/>is tired of bruſhing, he pronounces
          a com- <lb/>plete cure; which ſhould the Patient preſume <lb/>to doubt, he is capable of
          behaving in the <lb/>moſt inſolent manner, which he juſtifies by the <lb/>affront offered
          to his knowledge:—and ſhould <lb/>their ſpirit on the occaſion equal his impu- <lb/>dence
          (which is barely poſſible), he will even <lb/>go ſo far as to threaten a proſecution for
          defa- <lb/>mation. To corroborate this fact, it is well <lb/>known that, about ſeven years
          ago, this ſame <lb/>Mr. L. obtained a verdict of eighty pounds <lb/>from a Surgeon of
          eminence, and another of <lb/>an hundred pounds from a Gentleman in the <lb/>ſame
          profeſſion equally reſpectable, for a pre- <lb/>tended defamation; and has ſince been at
          the <lb/>point of being pilloried for his mal-practices <lb/>on his Ruptured Patients. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">must</hi> here beg leave to introduce a paſſage <lb/>from Mr. Pott's
          Treatiſe on Ruptures, p. 169. <lb/>
          <q rend="quotes">The hiſtories of Prior, Cabriere, Bowles, <lb/>Sir Thomas Renton, Dr.
            Littlejohn, &amp;c. <lb/>&amp;c. to be found in Dionis, Houſton, and <lb/>other writers,
            will furniſh to the Reader an <lb/>idea of the practice and performances of <lb/>ſome
            who have ſtood at the head of thoſe bold <lb/>promiſers. </q>— <q rend="quotes">This is
            a ſubject in which <pb xml:id="page_43" n="40"/>
            <lb/>mankind are much intereſted, and on which <lb/>a good deal might be ſaid; but as an
            ho- <lb/>neſt endeavour to ſave the afflicted from <lb/>the hands of thoſe who have no
            character to <lb/>loſe, and whoſe only point is money, might <lb/>from one of the
            profeſſion be miſconſtrued <lb/>into malevolence and craft, I will not enter <lb/>into
            it; but ſhall conclude by wiſhing, that they <lb/>who have capacity to judge of theſe
            matters <lb/>(which are as much the object of common- <lb/>ſenſe as any other kind of
            knowledge) <lb/>would not ſuffer themſelves to be deluded by <lb/>the impudent
            aſſertions of any Charlatan <lb/>whatever; but determine in this, as they <lb/>do in
            many other things, that is, by the <lb/>event. </q>—There is a ſentence in ſacred
          <lb/>writ which naturally ſtrikes me on the preſent <lb/>occaſion— <q rend="quotes">Out of
              <hi rend="italic">thy own</hi> mouth will I <hi rend="italic">con- <lb/>demn</hi>
            thee. </q>—Let the Reader join the <lb/>above quotations, and think for himſelf.—I
          <lb/>ſnall only ſay, that I ſincerely wiſh Counſel- <lb/>lor Brand's <hi rend="italic"
            >Surgeon of character</hi> would reflect <lb/>on the very <hi rend="italic"
            >excellent</hi> opinion of Mr. Pott, be- <lb/>fore he receives his fee merely for
          approving <lb/>what the <hi rend="italic">Shoemaker</hi> has done, or preparing <lb/>the
          way for what he is to do. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_44" n="41"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">With</hi> reſpect to myſelf, without a vain pre- <lb/>tence to a
          thorough knowledge of Surgery, <lb/>it is my boaſt that a ſtudious application, long
          <lb/>experience, and, above all, a ſtrict adherence to <lb/>the principles of <note
            place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* My Readers, I hope, will not accuſe me of
            oſtenta- <lb/>tion when I remark, that from the 7th of November, <lb/>1770, to the 31ſt
            of January, 1771, I have given away <lb/>Truſſes to perſons who were incapable of
            purchaſing <lb/>them, to the amount of 23l. 2s.—Atteſtations of <lb/>the truth of which
            from the Overſeers, &amp;c. of the dif- <lb/>ferent pariſhes to which they belong, are
            ready to be pro- <lb/>duced to thoſe who ſhall deſire to ſee them: A greater <lb/>ſum, I
            believe, than is diſpenſed to the poor afflicted with <lb/>Ruptures from all the
            Hoſpitals, except Greenwich and <lb/>Chelſea, in the ſame period of time. </note>
          Humanity, have fixed me <lb/>in the midſt of a moſt extenſive practice. That <lb/>there
          are perſons who bear me illw-ill, I have <lb/>no doubt; but I have the conſolation, that,
          in <lb/>this caſe, thoſe who are <hi rend="italic">my</hi> enemies are the <lb/>enemies of
          Society.—I deſpiſe the reflections <lb/>thrown out againſt me on account of my <lb/>former
          profeſſions: Such reflections are at <lb/>once a proof of ill manners and ill principles.
          <lb/>The good and the ſenſible will acknowledge, <lb/>that it is as poſſible for a ſoldier
          to attain a <lb/>knowledge of the true method of reducing <pb xml:id="page_45" n="42"/>
          <lb/>Ruptures and applying Truſſes, as it was for <lb/>Frere Jacques to diſcover the
          proper manner of <lb/>cutting for the ſtone; for a friar to inſtruct the <lb/>world in the
          uſe of Gun-powder; or a ſoldier <lb/>to invent the important and uſeful art of
          <lb/>Printing. From a conviction that the Pupils <lb/>in the different Hoſpitals in town
          ſeldom had <lb/>an opportunity of ſeeing a Rupture, and from <lb/>a deſire to render a
          knowledge of its proper <lb/>treatment more general; I very lately gave <lb/>them a public
          invitation to ſee me perform <lb/>the operation of reducing Ruptures, and the
          <lb/>retention of them when ſo reduced by apply- <lb/>ing Truſſes, which is the only
          remedy, at all <lb/>ages, and in all ſtates, of reducible Ruptures. <lb/>At the ſame time,
          I provided a number of <lb/>caſes, ſome of which were acknowledged by <lb/>Mr. Hunter to
          be the moſt ſingular he re- <lb/>membered to have met with.—However, <lb/>this good
          diſpoſition in me could not eſcape <lb/>cenſure;—an undiſtinguiſhing haughtineſs con-
          <lb/>ſtrued it an affront—and I was informed, that <lb/>if I perſiſted in that practice,
          it would greatly <lb/>offend the Faculty. To exculpate myſelf from <lb/>a deſign to give
          offence, I ſhall only refer to <lb/>the feelings of every candid Reader, and ſay, <pb
            xml:id="page_46" n="43"/>
          <lb/>that I meant a ſervice to the world. In conclu- <lb/>ſion, I ſhall ſubjoin a few
          Caſes, and for the <lb/>preſent take my leave,—wiſhing thoſe who <lb/>condemn from
          ignorance, more know- <lb/>ledge;—thoſe who aſperſe from malevolence, <lb/>more
          good-nature. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_47"/>
        <head rend="align-center dc(2)">
          <lb/>CASES. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">O</hi>N the 20th of January, one of the In- <lb/>penſioners of
          Greenwich Hoſpital ap- <lb/>plied to me, in the Surgery of that place, for a <lb/>Truſs
          for a double Rupture. Upon examining <lb/>him, I ſound the Rupture ſingle only, and in
          <lb/>the right Groin; in the left Groin the Teſticle <lb/>lying in an oval figure, acroſs
          the orifice, where <lb/>a Rupture generally deſcends, and no appear- <lb/>ance of the
          Scrotum on the left ſide of the <lb/>Penis. This moſt extraordinary ſituation was
          <lb/>occaſioned, he informed me, by a fall acroſs <lb/>the gunnel of a boat about twelve
          months ago. <lb/>When the Truſs was properly applied, the <lb/>Bandage did not in the
          ſmalleſt degree com- <lb/>press the Teſticle oppoſite to the Rupture; <lb/>and I have the
          ſatisfaction to ſay, that there <lb/>is now the greateſt probability of a palliative
          <lb/>cure being effected. Thoſe who doubt the <lb/>authenticity of this relation are
          intreated to <lb/>refer to the cheque book, which is kept in the <lb/>Surgery of the
          above-mentioned Hoſpital. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">On</hi> the 7th of November laſt, a poor man, <lb/>recommended by Mr.
          Benjamin Morris, <lb/>Overſeer of the Poor of St. Luke, Middleſex, <pb xml:id="page_48"
            n="45"/>
          <lb/>came to me for aſſiſtance. He ſaid, that about <lb/>ten Months before that time, he
          felt ſomething <lb/>in his Groin which was not then attended <lb/>with any pain: However,
          it by degrees in- <lb/>creaſed, and increaſing grew very painful, and <lb/>much larger;
          and that very often it made him <lb/>ſo ſick, that it would occaſion him to throw <lb/>up
          what he had eaten, and was often incapa- <lb/>ble of working for his bread;—for that when
          <lb/>he was in an upright poſture his Rupture <lb/>would ſometimes fall down with that
          violence <lb/>as to burſt open the codpiece of his breeches. <lb/>I applied a Truſs; and
          the laſt time I ſaw <lb/>him, which was the 14th of January laſt, he <lb/>informed me,
          that ever ſince I applied the <lb/>Truſs to his Rupture, it had not fallen down <lb/>once,
          nor had he loſt a day's work. Any per- <lb/>ſon who ſhall doubt this, may be ſatisfied of
          the <lb/>truth of the caſe by applying to Mr. Morris <lb/>above-mentioned, or at my houſe,
          where they <lb/>will be ſhewn a letter of thanks from the Pa- <lb/>tient himſelf, whoſe
          deſire it is the ſame may <lb/>be publicly ſeen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Thomas</hi> Weſt, a young man about twenty, <lb/>applied to me on the
          24th of December laſt, <lb/>for relief in the caſe of a Rupture, which he <pb
            xml:id="page_49" n="46"/>
          <lb/>had had ever ſince he was fourteen years of age. <lb/>It was, at the time mentioned,
          increaſed to the <lb/>ſize of eight inches circumference from the <lb/>Teſticle above the
          Os Pubis. I reduced it <lb/>all, and applied a Truſs thereon, at the ſame <lb/>time
          informing him in what manner he ſhould <lb/>proceed to obtain a perfect cure. In about
          <lb/>ten days he came to me again, ſaid he had <lb/>been very punctual in the obſervation
          of my <lb/>directions, and that he was completely cured, <lb/>notwithſtanding he had uſed
          all manner of <lb/>common exerciſes. He then pulled off his <lb/>Truſs, coughed and blowed
          his noſe in a vio- <lb/>lent manner, and ſaid there was no occaſion <lb/>for wearing the
          Truſs any longer. I asked him <lb/>if wearing it gave him any pain; he replied <lb/>no;
          and I ordered him not to leave it off for <lb/>a few months.—This extraordinary caſe
          <lb/>will be authenticated by applying to Mr. <lb/>Weſt, Lighterman, in King-Street,
          Deptford, <lb/>who is the Patient's Brother. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">About</hi> two years and a half ago, a lad of <lb/>twelve years of age
          was brought to me by <lb/>Mr. Macguire, Peruke-maker, of Hedge- <lb/>lane, for the cure of
          a Rupture. When I ex- <lb/>amined him, I found the Rupture, which was <pb xml:id="page_50"
            n="47"/>
          <lb/>in the right Groin, prodigiouſly large, with <lb/>the Teſticle at the lower extremity
          of it: The <lb/>left Teſticle was confined in the abdomen, and <lb/>had been ſo ever ſince
          he could remember. <lb/>By the proper application of my Elaſtic Truſs, <lb/>he obtained a
          radical cure in about nine <lb/>months; the right Teſticle at that time re- <lb/>maining
          in its proper and natural ſtate in the <lb/>Scrotum. I then told him he might lay the
          <lb/>Truſs aſide. In a few months after, Mr. Mac- <lb/>guire brought the boy to me again;
          ſaid his <lb/>Rupture was extremely bad, and that he muſt <lb/>have another Truſs.—On
          examining him, <lb/>ſo far from having a Rupture, his right Teſti- <lb/>cle had followed
          the Rupture into the abdo- <lb/>men, and, with the left, remains in that ſtate <lb/>to
          this day; and what is ſtill more remarka- <lb/>ble, there is not the ſmalleſt appearance
          of the <lb/>Scrotum, altho' the Penis remains in its na- <lb/>tural ſtate. </p>
        <trailer rend="align-center">
          <lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
