<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Kirkland: Animadversions on a late treatise on the kink-cough</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Thomas Kirkland</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Animadversions on a late treatise on the kink-cough. To which is
              annexed, An essay on that disorder.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T21905</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T53266"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for R. Baldwin, and J. Bew, in Pater-Noster Row,
                  MDCCLXXIV. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1774</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="11"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="55"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3307240393</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K030744.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Surgical or anatominal work"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_1"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>ANIMADVERSIONS ON A LATE TREATISE ON THE KINK-COUGH. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>[Price One Shilling and Six-pence.] </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <head ><lb/>ERRATA. </head>
        <list>
          <item>Preface, p. v. line 6, <hi rend="italic">after</hi> it, <hi rend="italic">add</hi>
            ever. </item>
          <item>Page 2, line 19, <hi rend="italic">for</hi> taffis, <hi rend="italic">read</hi>
            tuffis. </item>
          <item>Page 7, — <hi rend="italic">for</hi> AVICENNA, <hi rend="italic">read</hi>
            AVICENNAE. </item>
          <item>Page 14, line laſt, <hi rend="italic">after</hi> an, <hi rend="italic">read</hi>
            external. </item>
          <item>Page 18, line 27, <hi rend="italic">for</hi> taffim, <hi rend="italic">read</hi>
            tuffim. penult. <hi rend="italic">for</hi> Avicenna,<hi rend="italic">read</hi>
            AVICENNAE. </item>
          <item>Page 22, line 16, <hi rend="italic">after</hi> wou'd, <hi rend="italic">add</hi>
            often. </item>
          <item>Page 23, line 19, <hi rend="italic">for</hi> the, <hi rend="italic">read</hi>
            though. line 20, <hi rend="italic">after</hi> given, <hi rend="italic">put a, inſtead of
                <unclear>##### #####</unclear></hi>
          </item>
          <item>Page 33, line 6, <hi rend="italic">for</hi> n, <hi rend="italic">read</hi> In. </item>
          <item>Page 39, line 3, <hi rend="italic">for</hi> con, <hi rend="italic">read</hi>
            conſult. </item>
          <item>Page 46, line 12, <hi rend="italic">for</hi> irritated, <hi rend="italic">read</hi>
            irritating. </item>
          <item>Page 47, line 8, <hi rend="italic">after</hi> in, <hi rend="italic">add</hi> the.
            line 18, <hi rend="italic">read</hi> Syr. e mecon. </item>
          <item>Page 53, line 28, <hi rend="italic">for</hi> when, <hi rend="italic">read</hi>
            whence. </item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_4"/>
        <head ><lb/>PREFACE. </head>
        <q >AUDI ALTERAM PARTEM.</q>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>IT is now well known with what little truth hemlock was recommended as
          a cure for cancers, Dr. De Haen of Vienna, phyſician in the ſame hoſpital with Dr. Storck,
          having given us a fair account of this matter. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In a letter to a phyſician in England, publiſhed in the third volume
          of the Medical Muſeum, he ſays, ſpeaking of the Cicuta, <q rend="diple quotes"><p
              rend="indent"><lb/>I am now able to <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">plain</w> this
              matter to you, from the many experiments I have made in <pb xml:id="page_5" n="ii"
              />conſequence of an order received from high authority. The firſt thirty <w part="I"
                >pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tients</w> it abſolutely failed me, but confiding in the
              good faith of others, that they might happen to be ſuch only as were incurable, I
              advanced to make further trials, as well publicly in the hoſpital, as privately in the
              city and ſuburbs, to the <w part="I">num-</w><lb/><w part="F">ber</w> of one hundred
              and twenty; but, unhappily for me, after ſo much trouble, the reſult was, that not one
              perſon was cured or relieved by it; that many grew worſe, and that ſeven unhappy women
              with cancers in their breaſts periſhed <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w> my
              hands, of whom I could have ſaved ſome of them by the knife, and in all probability
              others might have been preſerved a long time by the palliative methods. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>I muſt own, ſir, I am aſhamed of this affair. How did I intreat
                <pb xml:id="page_6" n="iii"/>thoſe to whom it belonged to uſe more precaution, and
              at leaſt to <w part="I">ſuſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">pend</w> for ſome time the printing
              of thoſe books that praiſe the Cicuta, till repeated trials had been made, and by
              ſeveral hands, leſt the <w part="I">pub-</w><lb/><w part="F">lic</w> faith ſhould be
              abuſed by a premature publication, and the <w part="I">au-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >thor</w> rendered ridiculous in the face of the univerſe. But my <w part="I"
                >re-</w><lb/><w part="F">monſtrances</w> were fruitleſs; and, to my great concern,
              my beſt friends abruptly fell out with me, and I have incurred the diſgrace of the
              beſt of ſovereigns. </p></q> Wherefore, three years after, in 1766, he <w part="I"
            >pub-</w><lb/><w part="F">liſhed</w> his <hi rend="italic">Epiſtola de Cicuta,</hi>
          wherein he denies the cures which Dr. Storck ſaid he had accompliſhed by this remedy, and
          maintains it, <q rend="quotes">that many, or moſt of thoſe very <w part="I">pa-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">tients</w> Dr. Storck aſſerts to have been perfectly cured, died while they
            were taking this medicine; <pb xml:id="page_7" n="iv"/>and that there was proved in
            reality, on a candid enquiry, no more than one that could be ſaid to be cured by
            hemlock; that <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">though</w> five hundred pounds weight
            of Dr. Storck's extract of Cicuta had been ſent to different places abroad, yet there
            has not been received one authentic account of a real cure of a true cancer having been
            ever yet performed by it in any inſtance where it was uſed.</q> Which <w part="I"
            >per-</w><lb/><w part="F">fectly</w> agrees with general experience; and indeed it is
          amazing, that it ſhould ever have been received as a ſpecific in this diſorder, when we
          reflect, that upon enquiry, by <w part="I">diſſec-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, into the
          nature of a confirmed ſchirrhus, the veſſels ate found to be perfectly deſtroyed and
          obliterated, and the whole to be one confuſed maſs; wherefore, any medicine <w part="I"
            >cap-</w><lb/><w part="F">able</w> of reſtoring a part thus diſeaſed, muſt have a power
          of creating a new <pb xml:id="page_8" n="v"/>ſet of veſſels, and of making a new gland of
          the old one; and we may as well believe that it has a power of <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">moving</w> any inconvenience from <w part="I">am-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >putation</w>, by creating a new limb, as that it cured a true ſchirrhus<note
            place="bottom" n="*">* Thoſe who will take the trouble of examining ſchirri with a good
            microſcope, will look with <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">dignation</w> upon the
            accounts he meets with in Dr. Storck's books, and will be convinced, that unleſs we can
            diſcover a medicine that will penetrate into, correct the cancerous virus, and diſſolve
            all the <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">eaſed</w> parts into matter, we muſt ſtill
            continue to remove cancers in time by the knife, or what is more tedious and painful,
            the cauſtic, if we think of curing the patient. </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But when we reflect how <w part="I">deſti-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tute</w> we were of any medicine <w part="I">cap-</w><lb/><w part="F">able</w> of
          curing a cancer, we ſhall ſee the reaſon why phyſicians and <w part="I">ſur-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">geons</w> ſhould ſeek with avidity after a medicine recommended for this
          purpoſe by a phyſician of eminence <pb xml:id="page_9" n="vi"/>and character; and finding
          it give eaſe in ſome inſtances, its uſe has been continued, not conſidering that it is an
          opiate, and that the ſame <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">vantage</w> might have been
          received from ſmall doſes of opium; and that both opium and hemlock lull the <w part="I"
            >pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tient</w> into a fatal ſecurity, while the neceſſary and proper
          methods are <w part="I">ne-</w><lb/><w part="F">glected</w>, and the diſeaſe makes an <w
            part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">curable</w> progreſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nevertheleſs, the writer of the Eſſay on the Kinkcough is a true
          diſciple of Dr. Storck; and if this publication is well received, we have reaſon given to
          expect a more extenſive account of the virtues of hemlock; wherefore it muſt be a thankful
          office to <w part="I">en-</w><lb/><w part="F">quire</w>, how far what is already ſaid by
          this writer merits attention, and whether, as he aſſerts, <q rend="quotes">it is a <w
              part="I">ſpe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cific</w> in the kinkcough, according to the moſt
            proper interpretation of <pb xml:id="page_10" n="vii"/>that word,</q> to prevent our
          being again haſtily led, in giving preference to a medicine, perhaps no ways <w part="I"
            >en-</w><lb/><w part="F">titled</w> to the encomiums beſtowed on it. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Although by ſhewing that the caſes Dr, B— has given are <w part="I"
            >inſuffici-</w><lb/><w part="F">ent</w> to recommend hemlock, and that he himſelf does
          not believe what he has ſaid in favour of this medicine to be true, we might anſwer all
          the ends propoſed; yet, as theory is apt to affect practice, it will be proper to examine
          his doctrine previous to his caſes, and more eſpecially as it will ſhew this imitator of
            THESSALUS<note place="bottom" n="*">* The reader who is not acquainted with medical
            hiſtory, muſt be informed, that THESSALUS lived in the time of NERO, and with madneſs
            railed in open invectives againſt all phyſicians. He even had the vanity to direct, that
            the word IATRONICES ſhould be written upon his tomb-ſtone, in hopes of having it <w
              part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">lieved</w>, that he was ſuperior in his profeſſion to
            any phyſician that ever lived. Plin. Hiſt.Nat. lib. xxix. cap. 1. </note>, <pb
            xml:id="page_11" n="viii"/>that he, like other men, is not quite free from imperfection;
          that there muſt be a great amendment to make, as he <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >pects</w> his name greater in the next century than any man that ever lived; and
          knowing himſelf, he may ſee the neceſſity of ſtill improving. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_12"/>
        <head ><lb/>ANIMADVERSIONS ON A LATE TREATISE on the KINKCOUGH. </head>
        <div type="part">
          <head ><lb/>To Dr. B*****. </head>
          <salute>SIR, </salute>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>I HAVE read your Treatiſe on the <w part="I">Kink-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">cough</w>, and willingly point out to you ſome overſights in this work, in
            hopes of improving your medical knowledge, and thereby enabling you better to ſupport
            the character you have ſo long aſſumed, of being "ſecond in the profeſſion to no man." </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Indeed, ſir, your ſtricture upon DOCTOR <w part="I">FO-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">THERGILL</w>, in the beginning of your Preface, ſeems not only to be
            unneceſſary, but a little unlucky to yourſelf; becauſe, I dare ſay, you might have gone
            on in your ſyſtem-building quietly, and <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w part="F">out</w>
            notice; whereas, from what you have there ſaid, people will naturally be led to make a
              <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">pariſon</w> between the two writers that cannot
            poſſibly turn out to your advantage. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_13" n="2"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>They will at once plainly ſee that you have <w part="I"
              >ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſcured</w> and perplexed your ſubject, by treading in the
            path he has avoided. Thoſe converſant with medical books will diſcover, that you have
            ſerved your HEMLOCK up in a haſh of old materials; and that you have not advanced one
            new obſervation, or even one new thought, except ſome new errors, which it was quite
            unneceſſary to add to the theory and practice of phyſic. Beſides, I apprehend, your book
            will be thought to border a little upon quackery; while it muſt be confeſſed, that the
            DOCTOR has written like a man of ſcience. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Whoever looks over the 30th article, in the third volume of the
            Medical Obſervations and <w part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F">quiries</w>, will find that
            he recommends, from the ſucceſs of himſelf and many of his medical <w part="I"
              >ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">quaintance</w>, a powder compoſed of crabs claws and emetic
            tartar, as a very uſeful medicine in the taſſis convulſiva, and in preference of oxymel
            of ſquills and ipecacuanha, which have ſo often afforded moſt relief, by emptying the
            ſtomach of its contents; and he has mentioned the manner of giving it, and the diet he
            has found moſt uſeful on this occaſion. And, ſurely, there can be no impropriety in his
            confirming, by the experience of himſelf and many phyſicians, the uſefulneſs of a
            medicine which has been adviſed by preceding writers. And why is his giving directions
            about the manner of its being taken, and laying down rules for diet, unworthy of him,
            when ſo great a man as yourſelf has imitated him in theſe particulars<note
              place="bottom" n="*">* Treatiſe on the Kinkcough, p. 169. </note>? </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_14" n="3"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>But he ſays, the remedy he recommends is not a certain cure in all
            caſes; he would not be underſtood to ſuppoſe, that it will alone complete the cure of
            the whooping-cough; ſays he, <q rend="quotes">I know it will not; and that this, as well
              as any other medicine, is uſeful or otherwiſe, juſt as it is <w part="I"
                >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">dicated</w>:</q> whereas you happen not to trouble your
            head about indications, but recommend <w part="I">hem-</w><lb/><w part="F">lock</w>
            <hi rend="italic">as a ſpecific</hi> in the diſorder under conſideration. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>A ſpecific in the whooping-cough is a deſireable remedy, if it could
            be obtained; but whether that you have adviſed is better than the <hi rend="italic"
              >fleſh of fryed mice,</hi> which has been in vogue as a ſpecific for the ſame purpoſe;
            may be much doubted; for ſuch is the difference of conſtitutions, the variations in the
            ſame diſeaſe, and in the combinations of diſeaſes; that no one remedy has hitherto been
            found out, capable of invariably curing any one diſorder. Quacks, therefore, only talk
            of curing diſeaſes under various circumſtances by a ſpecific: they, indeed, from a
            poverty of knowledge, recommend one remedy in all ſorts of complaints, and bring
            teſtimony of their uſe from every recovery which happens where they are given. You, in
            like <w part="I">man-</w><lb/><w part="F">ner</w>, have, for ſeveral years, been
            preſcribing <w part="I">hem-</w><lb/><w part="F">lock</w> in almoſt all the caſes which
            have come <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w> you, and now aſcribe effects to
            it of which there is no evidence. I will point out an inſtance, which may ſerve for the
            preſent. You ſay, it may be given in the ſmall-pox <hi rend="italic">with
              advantage,</hi> becauſe it was taken by an healthy boy and girl, in the <w part="I"
              >be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ginning</w> of the eruptive fever of this diſeaſe, after
            emptying their bowels by ſenna tea, and the ſmall-pox <pb xml:id="page_15" n="4"/>turned
            out a very diſtinct good ſort. Now, if there had never before been a very diſtinct good
            ſort of ſmall-pox, in an healthy boy and girl, <w part="I">eſpe-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >cially</w> after purging, the hemlock might have <w part="I">gain-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ed</w> ſome credit; but if, upon enquiry, it ſhould be diſcovered, that a
            diſtinct good ſort of ſmall-pox is not unfrequent where hemlock is not given, I rather
            think, no other concluſion can be drawn from theſe inſtances than that, like a chip in
            pottage, it <w part="I">nei-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> did good nor harm. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nor can Dr. STORCK ſhelter you, I am fearful, from the appearance of
            having made a random <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">periment</w>, if even what he
            ſays be true; for, <w part="I">ſup-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſing</w>
            <hi rend="italic">hemlock,</hi> in ſome inſtances, to have promoted a kindly ſuppuration
            where the Peruvian bark failed; yet it does not follow, that it will promote a kindly
            ſuppuration in the ſmall-pox; becauſe different kinds of acrid matter require different
            correctives: though we no way accuſe you of making a random experiment by deſign, but <w
              part="I">inno-</w><lb/><w part="F">cently</w>, without knowing that matter in ſores
            and the matter in the ſmall-pox may require different remedies. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>However, though you have been a little out in theſe things, yet your
            declaration of not being <w part="I">an-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſwerable</w> for other
            peoples experiments with <w part="I">hem-</w><lb/><w part="F">lock</w>, unleſs made with
            the very preparation you always uſe<note place="bottom" n="*">* No one will doubt,
              though Dr. B— has publiſhed his methods of preparing hemlock, that he means, by this
              caveat, the preparation made by his own apothecary, when they know that he is provided
              with a ſufficient quantity to ſerve the whole kingdom. </note>, may ſcreen you from
            reproach where <pb xml:id="page_16" n="5"/>you are not known, in caſe it is not found ſo
              <w part="I">ſuc-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceſſful</w> in curing the kinkcough as you have
              <w part="I">repre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſented</w> it to be; for, in juſtification of
            yourſelf, you may have recourſe to your old practice, and ſay, that the blockhead of a
            compounder ſcorched the herb in drying, that he ſtirred the juice with a wooden skewer
            inſtead of a bit of hemlock ſtalk, or that there was certainly an ebullition while it
            was over the fire; which, if you are as ſucceſſful as you have been with no better
            arguments, may <w part="I">ef-</w><lb/><w part="F">fectually</w> ſtop any clamour. And
            who can ſay, though they took the utmoſt care, that two or three bubbles did not ariſe?
            which would be ſufficient for your purpoſe; or you may further inſiſt upon it, that no
            one can ſo exactly perform the method you have deſcribed, of making experiments upon
            people that are ill, as yourſelf. Nor will the <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ſcriptions</w> being written in Engliſh, hinder your forcing a trade and carrying on
            buſineſs, as they will be underſtood by every good woman, who will not have any thing to
            do, but, as they have already experienced, to conſult you, pay their fee, and <w
              part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceive</w>, with directions, in a pot ſealed up, your
              <q rend="quotes"><hi rend="italic">agreeable, certain, and expeditious cure for the
                kinkcough.</hi></q>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>ARNAUD wrote a book, to prove that GOULARD'S extract of lead is the
            beſt and moſt univerſal topic in ſurgery, and may very properly be ſubſtituted in the
            place of all others preſcribed; that it could only be made by GOULARD himſelf; and that
            he, ARNAUD, was the only perſon in England intruſted with the ſale of this preparation;
            in hopes, no doubt, of getting the whole trade in chirurgical <pb xml:id="page_17" n="6"
            />applications to himſelf. You, in imitation, have written a book, to prove that hemlock
            is a remedy againſt almoſt all diſeaſes; that it may properly be ſubſtituted for all
            others generally preſcribed for the kinkcough; and that they muſt have the very
            preparation you uſe. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>An anonymous writer lately attempted to <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">plode</w>, by chemical inveſtigation, all the febrifuge powders hitherto
            invented, in hopes of <w part="I">recom-</w><lb/><w part="F">mending</w> the ſale of his
            own medicine for the cure of fevers. You have endeavoured to decry, for the ſame
            purpoſe, the practice recommended by other phyſicians, and as much as lay in your power,
            by patching together <unclear>#</unclear>hreds from different authors, have dreſſed out
            your performance with a ſcientifical air, in hopes, no doubt, of ſeeing your doctrine
            and medicines more greedily ſwallowed. And if, by theſe means, you can perſuade the <w
              part="I">pub-</w><lb/><w part="F">lic</w> to believe, that whatever has been written
            upon the ſubject is erroneous, you may, perhaps, drive a great trade, and we ſhall then,
            without doubt, have the whole of your experience of hemlock as a medicine. Nevertheleſs,
            we will now ſee whether your book and liſt of cures will ſtand the teſt of inquiry; and
            the following are the heads of the chapters in which we ſhall diſcuſs this matter. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>

      <div>
        <head ><lb/>CONTENTS. </head>
        <list>
          <item>CHAP. I. Of the ſynonyma, deſcription, and prognoſtics of the kinkcough. </item>
          <item>CHAP. II. Of the nature of the kinkcough. </item>
          <pb xml:id="page_18" n="7"/>
          <item>CHAP. III. Of the ſeat of the kinkcough. </item>
          <item>CHAP. IV. Of the cauſes of the kinkcough. </item>
          <item>CHAP. V. Of the hiſtory of hemlock, as a cure for the kinkcough. </item>
          <item>CHAP. VI. Of the cure of the kinkcough, both ſimple and <w part="I"
              >compli-</w><lb/><w part="F">cated</w>, ſupported by your own reaſon. </item>
          <item>CHAP. VII. On hemlock, and its preparations. </item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div n="1" type="chapter">
        <head ><lb/><hi rend="italic">CHAP. I.</hi> Of the ſynonyma, deſcription, and
          prognoſtics of the kinkcough. </head>
        <div type="part">
          <head ><lb/>Of the ſynonyma. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The different names by which a diſeaſe is <w part="I"
              >diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">tinguiſhed</w> being placed in one view is undoubtedly
            uſeful; but your <hi rend="italic">ſynonymes,</hi> ſir, would have been much more
            perfect, if you had looked back to an earlier period, and informed us by what name the
            Greeks and Arabians diſtinguiſhed what the <w part="I">Eng-</w><lb/><w part="F">liſh</w>
            call the Whooping-cough; for both <w part="I">HIPPO-</w><lb/><w part="F">CRATES</w> and
            AVICENNA gave it a name. And beſides, there are ſeveral other ſynonyma<note
              place="bottom" n="*">* <foreign xml:lang="el">###Greek omitted###</foreign>, tuſſis
              perennis, <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">fantum</w>, ſuffocativa, puerile;
              chink-cough, chine-cough, king's cough, and many others. </note>, which ought to have
            been taken into the catalogue to have made it complete; ſo that, upon the whole, the
            firſt is a very ſuperficial ſection. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="part">
          <pb xml:id="page_19" n="8"/>
          <head ><lb/>Of the deſcription. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nor is your deſcription of the diſeaſe, and of the manner of its
            terminating, as we ſhall preſently ſhew, leſs imperfect, as the moſt alarming and
            dangerous ſtage of it is unnoticed, and ſeems <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >tirely</w> to be unknown to you. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="part">
          <head ><lb/>Of the prognoſtics, </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Which have been again and again publiſhed, and now eked out by the
            ſagacious information, <q rend="quotes">that a pulmonary haemorrhage may terminate in a
              conſumption, &amp;c. and that the kinkcough, when complicated with another diſorder,
              is more <w part="I">ha-</w><lb/><w part="F">zardous</w> than when ſingle and by
              itſelf.</q>
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="chapter">
        <head ><lb/><hi rend="italic">CHAP. II.</hi> Of the nature of the kinkcough. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It ſeems as unneceſſary <hi rend="italic">to prove,</hi> that this may
          be complicated with other diſorders, as that light and darkneſs exiſt; and the reader will
            <w part="I">there-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w> readily believe, that, perchance, you
          may have ſeen it conjoined with the meaſles, <w part="I">peripneu-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >monic</w> ſymptoms, &amp;c. but if he pays any regard to your book, he cannot coincide
          with you in opinion, that theſe varieties merit the moſt <w part="I">atten-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tive</w> conſideration of phyſicians; becauſe, <w part="I">hem-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">lock</w> it is ſaid is a ſpecific againſt the kinkcough, both when ſimple and
          when complicated with the diſeaſes ſpecified; but you will have wonderful ſatisfaction, in
          reading former writers upon this <pb xml:id="page_20" n="9"/>ſubject, becauſe you will
          find yourſelf ſupported by their authority concerning your opinion, that it is contagious;
          that a fever is not eſſential to it; that it is not an inflammatory diſeaſe, and the like:
          and the only misfortune in this chapter is, that, according to your own account, you have
          drawn a very erroneous concluſion from theſe <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >miſes</w>, for you do not heſitate to pronounce, that the kinkcough is a nervous
          ſpaſmodic diſeaſe<note place="bottom" n="*">* Dr. Hillary has been before you, and called
            it a nervous cough and convulſive ſpaſms. </note>. That a morbid irritability is the
          primary, and the ſpaſms only a ſecondary affection; and yet afterwards you ſay, <q
            rend="quotes">under certain circumſtances of the air, &amp;c. the various humours <w
              part="I">compoſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> the inteſtinal contents, may undergo an
              <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">common</w> degree of fermentation. The <w part="I"
              >ferment-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> maſs, by its unnatural ſtimulus, will <w
              part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duce</w> a vitiated ſecretion into that bowel. And
            this additional mixture will probably render the whole more and more active and exalted,
            till at length there are generated particles of a deleterious nature, operating on the
            mucous glands of the inteſtines in particular, whereby that ſecretion is increaſed and
            vitiated, and ſo the kinkcough is produced<note place="bottom" n="†">† Inſtead of miaſma
              being generated in the guts, Dr. <w part="I">Hil-</w><lb/><w part="F">lary</w>, with
              more reaſon, thought, that ſome peculiar diſpoſition in the air generated miaſma, that
              were recived into and <w part="I">infect-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> the habit.
            </note>.</q> From all which it follows: </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_21" n="10"/>
        <list>
          <item>1ſt, That <hi rend="italic">the air under certain circumſtances,</hi> is the primary
            cauſe of the diſeaſe. </item>
          <item>2dly, That the various humours compoſing the inteſtinal contents, are primarily
            affected. </item>
          <item>3dly, That the affection of the mucous glands, is not a primary but a ſecondary
            affection, from deleterious particles operating upon them. </item>
          <item>4thly, That the kinkcough happens in <w part="I">conſe-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >quence</w> of a diſeaſe thus brought on. </item>
        </list>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And laſtly, That the kinkcough is not a <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">eaſe</w>, but the ſymptom of a diſeaſe; of all which together with the ſtory of
          fermentation, we ſhall take notice of, in their proper place; and ſhall only now obſerve,
          that if you had been ſo lucky, as to conſider the kinkcough as a ſymptom, inſtead of a
          diſeaſe, your wonderful penetration in <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">covering</w>
          it to be nervous and ſpaſmodic, could not have been diſputed; becauſe coughs of all kinds,
          whether with or without a kink, are ſymptoms ariſing from nervous irritation and ſpaſms;
          and whether by this formal declaration you have not diſcovered that you are not well
          verſed in the nature of coughs in general, the reader will readily determine. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="chapter">
        <head ><lb/><hi rend="italic">CHAP. III.</hi> Of the ſeat of the kinkcough. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Though you aſſert that arguments are <w part="I">fal-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">lacious</w>, yet you are ſo deſtitute of plain proof, that you have not
          produced one fact in ſupport <pb xml:id="page_22" n="11"/>of your opinion, that the
          inteſtinal canal is the primary ſeat of the diſeaſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>That particular diſeaſes affect particular parts, is known to every
          one; but you will find it a <w part="I">dif-</w><lb/><w part="F">ficult</w> matter to
          prove, <q rend="quotes">the meaſles <hi rend="italic">chiefly</hi> affect the membrane
            inveſting the lungs, the ſmall-pox that of the ſtomach, and agues that of the
            duodenum.</q>—That the inteſtines of children are more irritable than the other parts of
          the body, will be equally difficult to prove. Dentition <w part="I">ren-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ders</w> all the nerves in the body praeternaturally irritable; and the
          colic-pains, and the like, do not ſeem to ariſe from the nerves of the inteſtines being
          more irritable, but from their being more irritated, by an acid firſt generated in the
          ſtomach. Nor has Dr. Harris <hi rend="italic">proved,</hi> that almoſt all the diſeaſes of
          children depend on an affection of the firſt paſſages; or who would believe that the CROUP
          for inſtance, had its ſeat in the inteſtines, becauſe <hi rend="italic">he</hi> ſaid the
          complaints of infants ſpring from an acid, their common ſource; and though it be allowed
          that a diſeaſe in the inteſtines can <w part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F">fect</w> the
          whole, or any part of the nervous ſyſtem, and that worms lodging in the inteſtines can <w
            part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duce</w> a cough, yet it does not follow, that all
          coughs happening to children have their primary ſeat in the ſame place: we could
          inconteſtably prove, that a violent cough took its riſe from an inflammatory tumour in the
          hand; but, are we therefore to conclude, that the kinkcough ever had its primary ſeat in
          this member of the body? </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_23" n="12"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Vomits being more ſerviceable, when they render the body ſoluble, only
          ſeems to prove, that the diſeaſe is not confined to the ſtomach; and if it be true, that
          ſuch patients bear the action of vomits better than purges, the only concluſion that can
          be drawn is, that purges weaken by making a general drain from the whole body, <w part="I"
            >where-</w><lb/><w part="F">as</w> vomits do not cauſe ſo great an <w part="I"
            >evacua-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nor is the king's evil, and rickets, being the conſequence of <hi
            rend="italic">an obſtinate</hi> kinkcough, any more to your purpoſe. You acknowledge the
          king's-evil to have its ſeat in the conglobate glands; and ſuppoſing, (though it is far
          from being certain) that thoſe of the meſentery are firſt affected, yet this is no clear
          proof in your favour, this diſeaſe being in another bowel. And can the <w part="I"
            >kink-</w><lb/><w part="F">cough</w>
          <hi rend="italic">ſimply conſidered,</hi> any more produce the king's-evil, than the
          king's-evil the kinkcough? The rickets have followed the ſmall-pox, which you ſay is a
          diſeaſe of the ſtomach; and any <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">order</w> at a
          certain period in life, that greatly weakens and relaxes the fibres of children, <w
            part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">diſpoſed</w> to the rickets, will bring them on. You
          confeſs, that both theſe diſorders are in <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſequence</w> of the kinkcough's continuing a long time, and to the inteſtines thereby
          loſing their contractile power. And we alſo think, as theſe diſorders never follow the
          kinkcough, till it has long continued, that they are brought on by its obſtinacy cauſing a
          general weakneſs and <w part="I">relaxa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, in habits
          previouſly diſpoſed to theſe <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">plaints</w>, <pb
            xml:id="page_24" n="13"/>and not to its primary ſeat being in the inteſtines. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But ſurely you are much miſtaken about your fourth, and what you think
          your moſt powerful argument, p. 25. For if we are to conclude from the periodical returns,
          that the kinkcough and <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">termitting</w> fevers have both
          their ſeat in the ſame place, you prove that inſtead of the inteſtines, the kinkcough may
          have its primary ſeat in the eyes, or in one of the teeth, becauſe you have given us a
          clear inſtance of an intermittent thus ſituated; for the black ſtools we imagine were
          owing to their being tinctured with extract of bark; and we ſhould have received equal
          information about the nature of the diſeaſe, if we had been told that the patient had
          black ſtools after eating bilberries. If you did not think the ſeat of this intermittent
          to be in the tooth, why did you direct it to be drawn? and are not local intermittents
          common? We believe that intermitting fevers have often their ſeat in the abdomen, yet we
          think the <w part="I">opi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nion</w> of their proximate cauſe being in
          the liver, meſentery, &amp;c. more probable than that it lodges ſolely in the guts; nor do
          your two caſes prove the contrary. You have before ſaid, p. 23. that an enlarged belly and
          colic are the ſymptoms of obſtructed glands in the meſentery; and might not the pain in
          the firſt boy's belly, p. 26. ariſe from a ſimilar cauſe, and the cure chiefly to be owing
          to the fomentation removing the <w part="I">obſtruc-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, becauſe
          his colic was cured before the worms were entirely eradicated? Might not the cure of <pb
            xml:id="page_25" n="14"/>the ſecond boy be accompliſhed by the purges producing the ſame
          effect; and would the belly have been large <hi rend="italic">and hard,</hi> if the
          inteſtines only had been diſeaſed? </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In regard to the inteſtines being the moſt likely place for generating
          an infectious diſeaſe, we muſt obſerve, that however plauſible the arguments in favour of
          this opinion may appear, they are very far from being concluſive; and though the <w
            part="I">dyſen-</w><lb/><w part="F">tery</w> and putrid fever, &amp;c. ſpread by
          contagion, yet it is not a clear point, that the miaſmata bring on the ſucceeding diſeaſe
          by firſt affecting the <w part="I">ali-</w><lb/><w part="F">mentary</w> canal. The
          viperine poiſon, though deadly when infuſed into a wound, taken by the mouth produces no
          bad effect; nor will the <w part="I">va-</w><lb/><w part="F">riolous</w> matter create a
          diſeaſe ſwallowed in the ſame manner, provided in its paſſage it touches not an excoriated
          part, though even a ſingle atom is fully ſufficient for the purpoſe when the cuticle is
          removed, and it comes in contact with the <w part="I">ab-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſorbent</w>
          veſſels, ſeated on the ſurface of the body. A poor lad had a large tumour in his mouth, <w
            part="I">ariſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> from the upper jaw, which was very foul, and
          from which a large quantity of very offenſive <w part="I">pu-</w><lb/><w part="F">trid</w>
          matter was ſwallowed in the night-time, when he was aſleep. It purged him gently, and, at
          the end of three weeks or a month, his blood ſeemed to be diſſolved by the vibices which
          appeared in the skin; yet he never had the leaſt fever, though he lived at leaſt ſix or
          eight weeks, and at laſt died of extreme weakneſs; whereas, had the ſame <w part="I"
            >quan-</w><lb/><w part="F">tity</w> of matter been abſorbed from an ulcer, a <w part="I"
            >col-</w><lb/><w part="F">liquative</w>
          <pb xml:id="page_26" n="15"/>fever would ſoon have been the <w part="I">conſe-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">quence</w>. From all which we would infer, that the juices in the primae viae
          correct and reader leſs active infectious matter; and that this does not ſeem to be the
          only way by which infection is <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">municated</w>. The
          opinion that the miaſms which propagate infection, enter the habit by the <w part="I"
            >lym-</w><lb/><w part="F">phatics</w> in the lungs, and other abſorbents, ſeems more
          likely to be true; for in this way, by ſuch time as the diſeaſe makes its appearance<note
            place="bottom" n="*">* When we inoculate for the ſmall-pox, it is evident that the
            variolous matter enters the inteſtines before any fever comes on, by its deſtroying
            worms. See the following eſſay. </note>, they will in all probability have contaminated
          the bile, and the variety of humours blended in the <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >teſtines</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But to return to the reſemblance betwixt the kinkcough and
          intermitting fevers, which ſeem to ariſe from an accumulation and diſcharge of phlegm; for
          when the ſtomach is unloaded by coughing and vomiting, the patient becomes eaſy till a
          freſh quantity of phlegm is collected in the ſtomach ſufficient to excite another fit of
            <w part="I">cough-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>; which, ſurely, notwithſtanding your <w
            part="I">argu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ments</w> to the contrary, is a full proof, that this
          bowel is immediately affected, and that unloading it is the cauſe of the intermiſſion. You
          indeed think differently; but may we not ſuppoſe, that in intermitting fevers obſcure
          intermiſſions are rendered diſtinct, by thoſe medicines which remove the offending cauſe
          from the affected part? And <pb xml:id="page_27" n="16"/>why then are we not to believe a
          diſorder, that has periodical returns, to be ſeated in the ſtomach, becauſe vomiting
          affords relief?—Why truly, ſay you, <q rend="quotes">It would ſeem that the interfering
            cauſe, a foulneſs of ſtomach, being thus removed, the pure inteſtinal ſymptom of
            intermiſſion becomes evident and diſtinct:</q> which is a moſt futile argument, becauſe
          you have not in one inſtance proved, that intermittents are ſeated in the <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">teſtines</w>; and we may therefore conclude, that WALDSCHMID,
          when he ſaid this cough <w part="I">proceed-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> from the ſtomach,
          was guided by <w part="I">common-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſenſe</w>, which you, ſir, have
          deſerted; and through the whole of this chapter have had recourſe to mere conjecture and
          hypotheſis. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="chapter">
        <head ><lb/><hi rend="italic">CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the cauſes of the kinkcough. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>How full and true your deſcription of the <w part="I">kink-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">cough</w> is, we have already obſerved, and ſhall farther make appear; and how
          far your <w part="I">obſerva-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w> have eſtabliſhed the true ſeat
          of the diſeaſe, let every man judge. However, you have given us a clear inſtance, that you
          remember what you learnt at lecture, in ſo very learnedly explaining what is the
          prediſpoſing, and what the proximate cauſe of a diſeaſe; and to be ſure it required a
          maſterly hand to point out that a diſeaſe is preſent, while its cauſe is preſent: but we
          do inſiſt upon it, that a diſeaſe often remains after its proximate cauſe is removed. But
          wonderful information <pb xml:id="page_28" n="17"/>muſt accrue to the public from their
          now being ſhewn the neceſſity and uſe of being acquainted with the cauſe of a diſeaſe; we
          may add, when it can be accompliſhed; <q rend="quotes">but ſo great are the difficulties
            of tracing out the hidden cauſes of the evils to which this frame of ours is ſubject,
            that the moſt candid of the profeſſion have ever <w part="I">allow-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ed</w> and lamented how unavoidably they are in the dark;</q> and the abortiveneſs of
          your <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tempt</w> in this reſpect, is one clear proof how
          juſtly they have reaſoned. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Few or none will think with you in regard to the kinkcough being
          peculiar to childhood, <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">cauſe</w> it ſometimes ſeizes
          grown people; and it may with truth be affirmed, that the ſtory about the irritability of
          children, both in health and when diſeaſed, has been long known and applied; and certain
          it is, that this diſorder more commonly affects children, without being preceded by any
          other diſeaſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>You ſay, <q rend="quotes">an enumeration of the effects of the
            ſpecific miaſms, which produce the <w part="I">kink-</w><lb/><w part="F">cough</w>, will
            ſufficiently point out their true <w part="I">na-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w>;</q> but
          not ſuch a perplexed enumeration as you have given us. In one place you aſſert, p. 51.
          that they act upon the nervous powers, and increaſe the irritability of the ſyſtem, a few
          lines after, <q rend="quotes">that as far as your ſenſes can <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">cover</w>, they act chiefly on the mucus;</q> and then again, a few lines
          below, you ſay, <q rend="quotes">it <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pears</w> that the
            kinkcough anſwers to the <w part="I">defini-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of
            peſtilential diſorders, &amp;c. ſince its <pb xml:id="page_29" n="18"/>miaſms are
            contagious, and act chiefly on the nerves;</q> and laſtly, after this confuſed <w
            part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">count</w>, <q rend="quotes">you hope you have
            ſufficiently cleared up the nature of the contagious particles.</q> But in what manner?
          For do not miaſms, as different in their <hi rend="italic">nature</hi> as poſſible, act
          upon the nervous power, and increaſe the irritability of the ſyſtem, of which the miaſms
          producing the ſmall-pox, meaſles, &amp;c. are an inſtance? or why do they produce
          different diſeaſes? Suppoſe what you have ſaid to be true, it only proves that they have
          an irritating property, which is far from <w part="I">explor-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>
          their <hi rend="italic">nature:</hi> but all theſe little miſtakes every conſiderate man
          will excuſe, when he reflects that you do not pretend to go deeper into this matter than
          the limits of your underſtanding will permit. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But to have been conſiſtent with yourſelf, you ſhould have omitted
          enquiring into the origin of the contagious particles which give riſe to the kinkcough, as
          this is certainly wading out of your depth. Indeed in this inquiry you ſet out very
          aukwardly; for not having examined into the <w part="I">mat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w>
          yourſelf, you are led into a miſtake by <w part="I">copy-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> a
          former writer, in regard to our not having any very early account about this diſorder; for
          Hippocrates preſcribed <hi rend="italic">ad taſſim pueri</hi><note place="bottom" n="*">*
              <foreign xml:lang="el">###Greek omitted###</foreign> nota finem lib. Morb. Mulier.
          </note>, and Avicenna deſcribes, according to the Latin <w part="I">tranſ-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">lation</w>, the method of curing the <hi rend="italic">tuſſis
            infantum</hi><note place="bottom" n="†">† De Aegritudinibus quae infantibus accidunt,
            cap. iii. lib. i. Fien. Dort. 1. p. 157. vol. i. </note>. <pb xml:id="page_30" n="19"
          />No concluſion, therefore, can be drawn as to the place of the growth of theſe particles,
          except it be true that they are bred in people's guts; and they then may be natives of
          Europe, and every other quarter of the globe. Even when they reviſited <w part="I"
            >Bar-</w><lb/><w part="F">badoes</w>. According to your account they muſt eſcape from
          the guts, and we may readily ſuppoſe that ſome paſſenger carried a belly-full over, and
          letting fly as ſoon as he landed, infected the whole iſland. Indeed Dr. Hillary obſerves,
          that the hooping-cough appeared in Barbadoes in the month of July 1753, after a good deal
          of rain, often with thunder and lightning, though the <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >termediate</w> days were hot and dry; and he could not find upon the ſtricteſt enquiry,
          that any child or elder perſon brought it thither, which you may conclude is in favour of
          your doctrine; but you muſt be told, that fermentation deſtroys the <w part="I"
            >co-</w><lb/><w part="F">heſion</w> of all bodies upon which it acts. That tough viſcid
          phlegm is always diſcharged in the firſt ſtage of the kinkcough; that there is, <w
            part="I">there-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w>, no fermentation in the caſe, and that the
          whole of what you have ſaid about creating <w part="I">dele-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >terious</w> particles in the guts is of courſe <w part="I">chimeri-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cal</w>, and ſeems to be no better ſupported than the opinion that Spaniſh mares become
          pregnant by aſcending high mountains, and ſwallowing with open mouth the weſtern wind. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>If ſo, the remainder of what you have ſaid in this chapter, except its
          being ſometimes <w part="I">propa-</w><lb/><w part="F">gated</w> by contagion, falls to
          the ground, and <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">quires</w> no farther comment; though,
          I muſt <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">fess</w>, <pb xml:id="page_31" n="20"/>I much
          admire your arguments againſt the removal of children in this diſorder; becauſe, if they
          were removed from Derby, and its environs, the writing of your book might not anſwer the
          end deſigned; and yet it may be difficult to <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >prove</w> the truth of the opinion, that pure air aſſiſts in recovering the patient.
          For, if <q rend="quotes">the air under certain circumſtances is the primary cauſe of this
            diſorder,</q> how comes it to paſs that the kinkcough does not depend upon the ſtate of
          the atmoſphere, like many epidemic diſeaſes? Will not an air capable of producing the
          kinkcough be a conſtant <hi rend="italic">fomes morbi?</hi> and, conſequently, <w part="I"
            >remov-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> the patient to a place where the air is pure muſt be
          rational at leaſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And, though you have not only <hi rend="italic">a priori,</hi> but
          likewiſe <hi rend="italic">a poſteriori,</hi> come to the ſame <w part="I"
            >determina-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, yet I queſtion whether you have <w part="I"
            >ſatisfactori-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> cleared up this matter; for the mucous glands
          of the ſtomach, and thoſe of the inteſtines, are both of the ſame kind; and will it be
          believed that the air <hi rend="italic">under certain circumſtances,</hi> when taken in by
          the mouth, can paſs through the ſtomach without affecting it; and is not the ſtomach <w
            part="I">load-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> with phlegm from the beginning? So that you
          have no way of maintaining your ground in regard to the <hi rend="italic">guts</hi> being
          the <hi rend="italic">primary ſeat</hi> of this diſeaſe, unleſs you give up your <hi
            rend="italic">prior,</hi> and adhere to your <hi rend="italic">poſterior</hi> arguments,
          by proving that the <hi rend="italic">fomes morbi</hi> doth not enter by the mouth but <hi
            rend="italic">per partes poſteriores.</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="5" type="chapter">
        <pb xml:id="page_32" n="21"/>
        <head ><lb/><hi rend="italic">CHAP. V.</hi> Of the hiſtory of hemlock, as a cure for
          the kinkcough. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>What you ſay, ſir, has been aſſerted about the cure of the kinkcough,
          may with equal truth be aſſerted of every diſorder known, as we have not <hi rend="italic"
            >a certain</hi> cure for any of them. Where there it a multiplicity of indications in
          diſeaſes (for methods of cure are not indications), it is impoſſible for them all to give
          way to ſpecific treatment; for various circumſtances will always require a combination of
          various remedies. Nor is the unſucceſſful treatment of the kinkcough the reaſon why Dr.
          Willis's obſervation, <q rend="quotes">that old women are oftner conſulted in this
            diſorder than phyſicians,</q> holds true in our own times; for people ſeldom apply to
          phyſicians, on account of the expence, as they do not apprehend danger, and they know the
          diſeaſe will commonly get well of itſelf in time. Nevertheleſs, if you can make people
          believe that we have as yet no certain and effectual cure for the kinkcough, nor any one
          medicine that ought to be uſed in many caſes that occur, that every method hitherto
          followed is at beſt but a palliative, and that hemlock is a ſpecific in every caſe that
          can happen, your buſineſs is done. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But whether your being convinced that the diſeaſe is ſpaſmodic, and
          that hemlock is one of the beſt antiſpaſmodics, will aſſiſt in <w part="I"
            >recommend-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> it to the notice of practitioners in medicine,
            <pb xml:id="page_33" n="22"/>may be much doubted; becauſe, as we have <w part="I"
            >al-</w><lb/><w part="F">ready</w> obſerved, what you have ſaid tends to <w part="I"
            >per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſuade</w> other people, that the diſeaſe is not <w part="I"
            >ſpaſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">modic</w>, but a morbid alteration of the inteſtinal
          contents; and it will eaſily be diſcovered whether medicines that clear the <hi
            rend="italic">primae viae,</hi> and leſſen <w part="I">irri-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tability</w>, or a medicine which acts as an <w part="I">antiſpaſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >modic</w> only, are moſt likely to prove palliatives. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>However, though your reaſoning may have perplexed this matter, and
          though you may be miſtaken about the nature and the ſeat of the <w part="I"
            >dif-</w><lb/><w part="F">order</w> in queſtion, yet it does not follow that you have
          not found out a remedy that will cure it, the uſe of medicine being often diſcovered by <w
            part="I">acci-</w><lb/><w part="F">dent</w>. The Indian who diſcovered that the bark
          would cure an intermitting fever, knew nothing probably of the nature of the diſeaſe; and
            <hi rend="italic">as you have confined your practice in almoſt all diſeaſes to the uſe
            of hemlock,</hi> you may by chance have found out a cure for the kinkcough, and we muſt,
            <w part="I">there-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w>, ſee whether the evidence you produce
          will ſupuort the character you give it. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>A ſpecific ſhould be able to cure the diſeaſe to which it is
          appropriated without any aſſiſtance; and, in order to have a clear proof of the efficacy
          of any medicine, it ſhould be given ſimply and alone; and it is therefore impoſſible to
          ſay how far hemlock, and how far the other remedies might contribute to the cure in your
          firſt and fifth caſes. Cantharides have always been found of great <w part="I"
            >effi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cacy</w> in the hooping-cough, whether taken <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">wardly</w>, or outwardly applied; nor have purging <pb
            xml:id="page_34" n="23"/>medicines, eſpecially emetic tartar, &amp;c. by <w part="I"
            >clear-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> the <hi rend="italic">primae viae,</hi> been found
          leſs ſerviceable. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Who can, therefore, ſay in Mrs. Hodgkinſon's caſe, that the bliſter
          and emetic tartar did not <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tenuate</w> and remove the
          viſcid phlegm, which was manifeſtly the cauſe of the cough? Hemlock might then be
          ſerviceable, by acting as an opiate, and allaying that increaſed irritability, which the
          cauſe of every cough in a greater or leſs degree produces, and which often will occaſion
          frequent coughing for ſome time after the primary diſeaſe is removed. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>A. B. was better from the application of the firſt bliſter, and the
          effects of his purging <w part="I">mix-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w>, which brought away
          ſlime, before hemlock was given. Lancing the gum too would leſſen the increaſed
          irritability of the whole habit, <w part="I">eſpe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cially</w> the
          ſecond operation, which let out three teeth at once, and yet the hemlock was <w part="I"
            >conſtant-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> given: we find he coughed a good deal till a
          ſecond bliſter was applied, <hi rend="italic">and then</hi> the fits were much milder, and
          returned ſcarcely once in two hours. Beſides, the bowels were unloaded of ſlime <hi
            rend="italic">daily,</hi> either with ſyrup of roſes or manna; he was vomited with
          oxymel of ſquills, which rendered his breathing free; and after five weeks and four days
          had elapſed, in which time ſix teeth were bred, (and I ſuppoſe came to light) the patient
          was well. And it may be asked, with what pretenſions could it be ſaid in the third <w
            part="I">corol-</w><lb/><w part="F">lary</w>, that <q rend="quotes">that hemlock
            certainly prevented ſpaſms, and probably convulſions, in this child?</q>
          <pb xml:id="page_35" n="24"/>Muſt not there be a ſtrange partiality in favour of hemlock
          to make ſuch a concluſion; and will not corollaries thus drawn lead to error? </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But to go back to your writing to your friend in Scotland, p. 63. we
          may obſerve, that it was unlucky that the children were got well before your letter of
          advice arrived, otherwiſe hemlock might have got the whole credit of the cure; and, though
          this anecdote does not throw great light upon the ſubject, yet perhaps it may foreſtall
          any claim a pretender may make to hints given; and you will thereby avoid that cenſure you
          have <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w> experienced<note place="bottom" n="*">*
            In the Reviews. </note>, in publiſhing as your own a method of curing the ſtone by
          injection, when the hint came from Dr. Whytt. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The ſecond caſe not being inſiſted on as <w part="I">evi-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">dence</w>, I paſs it over; and the third does not ſeem much to your purpoſe,
          becauſe hemlock was not given by itſelf; and who will be hardy enough to ſay, that lemon
          juice, ſalt of tartar, and ſyrup of ſugar, did not alter the properties of this remedy?
          and that the good effects were not produced by the manna, and a medicine very <w part="I"
            >dif-</w><lb/><w part="F">ferent</w> from hemlock when given alone? But the complete
          recovery ſeems to have been <w part="I">accom-</w><lb/><w part="F">pliſhed</w>, as often
          happens in this diſeaſe, by time, as nine or ten weeks elapſed before the patient was in
          perfect health. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Indeed, you inform us, that ſhe was in a <w part="I">man-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ner</w> well in a much ſhorter time; but this we <pb xml:id="page_36" n="25"
          />imagine was nothing more than the natural <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">cline</w>
          of the cough, which always happens after a certain period. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>You ſay, <q rend="quotes">a fever is not eſſential to the <w part="I"
              >kink-</w><lb/><w part="F">cough</w>;</q> but in the cough following the meaſles, a
          fever, with a white tongue, quick pulſe, and ſediment in the urine, is a common attendant:
          and are not this fever and cough <w part="I">fre-</w><lb/><w part="F">quently</w>
          increaſed and renewed by eating things of hard digeſtion, or upon taking a ſlight cold?
          whence there is reaſon to imagine, that a great part of this child's illneſs was owing to
          acrid <w part="I">mat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> remaining after the meaſles, upon, and
            <w part="I">irritat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> the lungs. It is common for ſaline
          medicines, without the aſſiſtance of hemlock, to make the phlegm looſer in the cough thus
          produced; and this hectic fever and cough have often been cured by the ſame remedies, and
          gentle purging, in a ſhort ſpace of time: ſo that, upon the whole, you may ſee this is not
          ſo clear a caſe in your favour as you have imagined. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The fourth caſe too, communicated to you by Mr. Smith, is liable to
          the ſame objections, as not hemlock alone, but a medicine of a very different nature was
          given; and from a ſerious peruſal of the firſt five caſes, the reader will judge, whether
          you had any good reaſon to be <hi rend="italic">perfectly</hi> convinced that you had
          diſcovered <q rend="quotes">an agreeable, certain, and expeditious cure for the
            kinkcough:</q> when, not having patients enow of your own, you wrote to Mr. Yorke to
          furniſh you with ſome for your purpoſe. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_37" n="26"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But the firſt of theſe caſes will do you very little ſervice; for,
          upon enquiry, the child did not take the medicine except a few days. The <w part="I"
            >mo-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> not dreading the event of the diſorder, did not chuſe
          to give it her by force, though it was regularly brought every evening about ſix o'clock,
          to be taken next day, but it was conſtantly thrown away. The mother ſays <q rend="quotes"
            >the ſmell of the <hi rend="italic">hum∣lucks</hi> ſcented the whole houſe, and was ſo
            very diſagreeable, that the child could not bear it; and, ſhe believes, it would have
            thrown her daughter into fits if ſhe had perſiſted in the uſe of this medicine.</q> She,
          therefore, bought manna<note place="bottom" n="*">* The mother ſays, <q rend="quotes"
              >thoſe days ſhe was purged with manna ſhe was much better than when ſhe took the
              humlucks.</q>
          </note> at different places, with which ſhe kept her bowels open, and the diſorder
          terminated, as often happens, in the ſpace of ſix weeks. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is very common for the lower claſs of people to omit taking
          medicines, even when they are to pay for them, becauſe they are unpalatable; and, I have
          ſo often diſcovered, that the medicines during a whole illneſs have been ſecreted, and not
          taken, that I am very cautious in aſcribing effects to them, unleſs I am very certain they
          have been given. The parents of theſe children had not thought of calling in any
          aſſiſtance, but were ſent to, and deſired to make trial of ſome medicine that ſhould be
          given them; and common civility obliged them not to refuſe the offer; but when we <w
            part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">flect</w>, that giving medicines to children is always
            <pb xml:id="page_38" n="27"/>troubleſome, and requires great reſolution to <w part="I"
            >ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">compliſh</w>; that the common people do not look upon this
          diſorder as dangerous, and that they have no doubt of it in general going off of its own
          accord, it is reaſonable to imagine, that they would not be equally vigorous with the
          preſcriber in purſuing his method of cure, otherwiſe the <w part="I">pa-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">rents</w> of HELE<note place="bottom" n="*">* See Treatiſe on the Kinkcough, p.
            159. </note> would not have diſuſed the bark ſhift which was given her; and, in my
          opinion, I think none of theſe caſes are to be depended upon, where either the preſcriber
          or apothecary did not ſee the medicines given. However, ſuppoſing them to be taken, the
          caſe of ELIZABETH and JOHN PAGE are exceptionable, becauſe lemon-juice and ſalt of tartar
          were joined with hemlock; beſides, ELIZABETH PAGE had the diſorder from firſt to laſt near
          ſeven weeks; and does not it <w part="I">of-</w><lb/><w part="F">ten</w> terminate of
          itſelf in this time? We may <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">clude</w>, that JOHN PAGE
          had the diſorder very ſlightly, otherwiſe he would have kinked oftener than twice in the
          night. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Mary Green was not cured. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Mr. Smith, for all that we know, joined juice of lemon and ſalt of
          tartar with hemlock, in the manner he had before done; and his caſes, as they at preſent
          ſtand, are therefore no evidence. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Thomas Newdale, who had the diſorder near ſeven weeks, had ſal
          polychreſt and magneſia given to aſſiſt the cure. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_39" n="28"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Magneſia and ſal polychreſt were alſo given in MARY HELE'S caſe, but
          ſhe had no permanent relief till ſhe wore a bark ſhift; and after taking hemlock a month,
          a violent diarrhea, with <w part="I">puru-</w><lb/><w part="F">lent</w> ſtools ſtreaked
          with blood, and a teneſmus came on, and ſhe was very reſtleſs, and vomited up her food;
            <hi rend="italic">but, upon the hemlock mixture being omitted,</hi> and three drops of
          laudanum being given, and repeated every night and morning, her looſeneſs was abated and
          cured, ſhe had good nights, and <hi rend="italic">her cough, which the hemlock could not
            ſubdue,</hi> was intirely removed; and, we are told, ſhe got well: but of this
          hereafter. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>WILLIAM TOPLIS had a variety of medicines joined to hemlock,
          notwithſtanding which he died, though, it is ſaid, his kinkcough was cured a few days
          before his death, and at a time when he appears to have been very ill; but in the <w
            part="I">fol-</w><lb/><w part="F">lowing</w> Eſſay we ſhall have occaſion to take notice
          of hemlock, and we ſhall then review this caſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Mary Langley had the diſorder in all ſeven weeks, and magneſia and
          nitre were joined with hemlock; and, upon the whole we may obſerve, that there are only
          ſeven caſes out of the twenty, in which hemlock can poſſibly have all the credit of the
          cure, becauſe other medicines were joined along with it; and if it was imagined they would
          give no aſſiſtance, why were they preſcribed? And even in all theſe ſeven caſes, will not
          the ſugar of ſugar-candy rob the hemlock of its honour and <pb xml:id="page_40" n="29"
          />glory, becauſe ſugar, vegetable juice, and water will ferment? I know that this hemlock
          mixture will, in a few hours become ropy, and afterwards a fermentation enſues, and it
          becomes vinous; and, though it may, like cowſlip wine, retain ſomething of its narcotic
          quality, yet it will be greatly altered. Perhaps it may be ſaid, that the mixture being to
          be taken in the ſpace of twenty-four hours, it has not time to ferment; but in the heat of
          May and June, when theſe children were ill, every body knows that this alteration will
          take place in a very few hours. Beſides, ANNE ARCHER and ROBERT TRUSSEL were ill five
          weeks. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>SAMUEL ARCHER one month. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>ANCOR SARAH WADDLE and ELIZABETH TRUSSEL about two months. And you
          yourſelf are ſo well ſatisfied that theſe caſes are not <w part="I">ſatiſ-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">factory</w>, that you think it neceſſary to explain ſome circumſtances in ſome
          of them: </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>We join you in opinion, p. 157, that the fifth caſe may be as
          remarkable as any of the reſt, and yet not very remarkable in favour of hemlock. Any man
          muſt be ſtrangely biaſſed in favour of this medicine, who could conclude, when ſo many
          other medicines had given relief, that it ſaved this patient's life; and from what has
          been ſaid, it is plain you were miſtaken in aſcribing the cure <hi rend="italic">of
            all</hi> the ſix patients to hemlock. But you ſeem to be eaſily convinced, otherwiſe you
          would not have attempted to perſuade others it was effectual where the diſeaſe was not
          cured; for you have <pb xml:id="page_41" n="30"/>artfully numbered Mary Green among thoſe
          made well by this remedy, though her caſe proves the contrary; and her mother ſays, ſhe
          did not get well of at leaſt ſix months after ſhe had quite done taking this medicine. You
          ſay, <q rend="quotes">I ſaw all the four patients cured by Mr. Yorke (Mary Green being one
            of them), and ſome of them before they were well; and I enquired very minutely into
            their ſeveral ſymptoms, and this was only that I might have every poſſible <w part="I"
              >teſti-</w><lb/><w part="F">mony</w> for facts, which I deſired to deliver to the
            world with the utmoſt conſciouſneſs of their reality.</q> Surely this is ſtraining a
          point, to ſay no worſe of it, to give credit to hemlock; and how are we to believe you,
          when you thus ſolemnly attempt to impoſe upon us? </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Curing Thomas Newdale twice in a fortnight was really extravagant;
          once well done would have been quite ſufficient, as the diſorder ſeizes a perſon but once
          in his life. But notwithſtanding what may have been ſaid to the contrary, (ſee caſe 17)
          HELE does not ſeem to have been cured once. Poor child! She indeed ſuffered much hardſhip,
          ſeemingly from being trifled with, when the uſe of the bark was ſo early indicated<note
            place="bottom" n="*">* You knew an ague had been cured by the bark when complicated with
            the kinkcough, (ſee Treat. Kink. p. 172.) why then was the uſe of this medicine deferred
            near ſeven weeks? and was not giving hemlock in this inſtance <w part="I"
              >experi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w> making? becauſe an <hi rend="italic">approved
              remedy</hi> was at hand. See Home Princip. Med. p. 122. </note>, and if this <w
            part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">medy</w> had been ſooner given, ſhe now probably <pb
            xml:id="page_42" n="31"/>might have been numbered among the living <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtead</w> of the dead, as her conſtitution might not have been
          ruined, and ſhe might have been able to bear a blaſt of wind. But you were conſiſtent with
          yourſelf in adhering to your opinion, that hemlock does not only cure the kinkcough, but
          the ague alſo; and the conſequence was, that ſhe together with TOPLIS are in heaven; and,
          it may be inſiſted on, that hemlock did good ſervice in theſe inſtances, by ſtanding in
          the place of <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">per</w> remedies, and ſuffering the
          diſorder to carry theſe infants into happineſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>You ſee, ſir, how willing I am to help you out at a dead lift; and in
          the Eſſay annexed, the <w part="I">looſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w> which probably
          aſſiſted in carrying HELE to her grave, will be accounted for, without having recourſe to
          conjecture, and the neceſſity of killing and deſtroying worms for the purpoſe; though I
          admire your ingenious theory of theſe vermin, <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>
          obliged by uncommon heat to ſeek their way out of the body by a voluntary effort, in the
          ſame manner. I ſuppoſe, as people make a voluntary effort to get out of a window, or a
          back door, when a houſe is on fire. But there is another way of <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">plaining</w> this matter; and the reader will <w part="I">preſent-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ly</w> judge whether it ought not to have been known to one who is a fellow of
          a royal college of <w part="I">phy-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſicians</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But after all, I find you have been <w part="I">endeavour-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ing</w> to make us give credit to what you yourſelf do not believe; for, if you
          had been perfectly convinced, that in hemlock you had diſcovered a <pb xml:id="page_43"
            n="32"/>certain and expeditious cure for the kinkcough, you would not in the laſt caſe
          but one, <q rend="quotes">have been perpetually wavering between the <w part="I"
              >influ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ence</w> of a great name, and the ſuggeſtion of your own
            reaſon and experience.</q> From this declaration it is evident, you wanted <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ward</w> conviction from plain proof; for a man muſt be an
          errant fool indeed, who gives up a plain matter of fact, of which he is perfectly <w
            part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">vinced</w>, to the influence of any name how great
          ſoever. And we ask the opinion of thoſe <w part="I">uncon-</w><lb/><w part="F">cerned</w>
          in this matter, whether they think you were perfectly convinced or not? </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Your laying the death of HELE to the <w part="I">miſcon-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">duct</w> of her parents, and excuſing the want of ſpeedy ſucceſs to a ſmoaky
          houſe, &amp;c. in <w part="I">TOP-</w><lb/><w part="F">LIS'S</w>, LANGLEY'S<note
            place="bottom" n="*">* This is a curious excuſe, it being confeſſed, that they were not
            confined within doors, p. 161. </note>, and WADLEY'S caſes, will avail but little in
          favour of your remedy, when it is called to mind, that you have long inſenſibly fallen
          into this way of excuſing yourſelf by the moſt trifling evaſions, when, having promiſed a
          recovery, death, by victory, has ſhewn the <w part="I">feeble-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ness</w> of the weapons by which you endeavoured to keep him at a diſtance. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>From the whole it muſt appear to every <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">biaſſed</w> reader, that hemlock has not always been ſucceſſful in the
          kinkcough; that other <w part="I">me-</w><lb/><w part="F">dicines</w> were required, both
          when it was ſimple and when the diſeaſe was complicated, and that <pb xml:id="page_44"
            n="33"/>you have ſaid more in the praiſe of this remedy than is true. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="6" type="chapter">
        <head ><lb/><hi rend="italic">CHAP. VI.</hi> Of the cure of the kinkcough, both when
          ſimple and <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">plicated</w>, ſupported by your own
          reaſons. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><unclear>#</unclear>n this chapter it was reaſonable to expect, that
          the different indications in all the varities ariſing from complication with other
          diſorders would have been pointed out; but if we except the meaſles, in which you have
          never given this <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">medy</w>, and lancing the gums in
          dentition, <w part="I">how-</w><lb/><w part="F">ever</w> complicated the diſorder, there
          is but one <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">dication</w> which is to give hemlock; and
            <hi rend="italic">giving</hi>
          <w part="I">hem-</w><lb/><w part="F">lock</w>, we imagine, is no indication at all, but we
          gueſs what you mean. And this principle, I <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerve</w>,
          you firſt lay down when you ſpeak </p>
        <div type="part">
          <head ><lb/>Of the ſimple kinkcough. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>And yet, two pages, after you forget yourſelf, and recommend a
            variety of purging medicines to be taken, if the patient has not two ſtools a day; ſo
            that the contents of the bowels being retained is another indication: and what is very
            curious, it ſeems very immaterial with you whether the <w part="I">pa-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">tient</w> takes hemlock in a mixture, or in powder, bolus, or pills; and yet,
            if what we have ſaid about ſugar, vegetable juice, and water <w part="I"
              >ferment-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> be true, the mixture and the powder, &amp;c. may
            be as different medicines as nitre and ſalt of <pb xml:id="page_45" n="34"/>wormwood;
            and this will be looked upon as one inſtance, how well you conſider what effect <w
              part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">bination</w> may have upon the medicines you
            preſcribe. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="part">
          <head ><lb/>Of the cure of the kinkcough with worms. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The very ſame means is recommended in this complication as for the
            ſimple kinkcough; <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">cauſe</w> a child who uſed to part
            with a great <w part="I">num-</w><lb/><w part="F">ber</w> of round worms, had ſome come
            away while it was taking this medicine (ſee caſe 11.) and, for this reaſon, we are to
            believe, that hemlock will, in ſuch caſes, often ſuperſede the uſe not only of
            laxatives, but of any other medicines whatever in the cure of both diſorders. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="part">
          <head ><lb/>Of the cure of the kinkcough with a dyſentery. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Hemlock is here the beſt remedy, becauſe <hi rend="italic"
              >opium</hi> ſaved a child's life under theſe <w part="I">circum-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ſtances</w>, when the ſtools had acquired a pretty <w part="I">na-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">tural</w> appearance from the uſe of gentle vomits, laxatives, bliſters, the
            Peruvian bark, &amp;c. But we will ask the advice of thoſe skilled in medicine, whether,
            notwithſtanding the idle theory about the hemlock removing clotty feculent accumulations
            lurking in the guts, either it or opium can be given with ſafety, without previous
            evacuations, or purging medicines joined along with them? <w part="I">Hem-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">lock</w> is allowed to act the part of an aſtringent in diarrhoeas; and will
            it not, if the advice here given is purſued, confine the <hi rend="italic">fomes
              morbi</hi> in the <pb xml:id="page_46" n="35"/>inteſtines, and for the moſt part be
            the death of the patient? </p>
        </div>
        <div type="part">
          <head ><lb/>The cure of the kinkcough with dentition. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>In this variety too hemlock is to be depended upon, becauſe, if both
            diſeaſes are urgent, by lancing the gum you relieve the patient. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="part">
          <head ><lb/>The cure of the kinkcough with an ague. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Again, hemlock is the <hi rend="italic">fac totum,</hi> becauſe <q
              rend="quotes">it does not appear that the bark was more <w part="I">effica-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">cious</w> than hemlock in poor HELE's caſe</q> (17); only that the bark
            ſhift intirely removed the ague, which was not cured while the hemlock was <w part="I"
              >de-</w><lb/><w part="F">pended</w> on as a febrifuge. Indeed, on the ninth of March
            it appears from the caſe, that ſhe had neither ague nor fever, but on the tenth it <w
              part="I">return-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>; and on the twelfth, things were in ſuch a
            ſtate, that recourſe was immediately had to the bark ſhift, and opium, with a good
            effect. But <w part="I">ſuppoſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> the ague fit to be removed
            for a little time previous to the uſe of the bark, why is this to be attributed to
            hemlock? The child's belly was hard and full at the onſet of the diſeaſe; magneſia and
            ſal polychreſt were joined with hemlock, and purged the patient: and have not agues thus
              <w part="I">cir-</w><lb/><w part="F">cumſtanced</w> been cured by purging medicines?
            There is ſcarce a practitioner living who has not cured the ague, accompanied with a big
            belly in children, with a few doſes of calomel and jalap; and ſo powerful a medicine is
            ſal polychreſt and rhubarb in this very caſe, that Dr. William <pb xml:id="page_47"
              n="36"/>Fordyce is of opinion, he might have made a <w part="I">for-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">tune</w> by uſing it as a noſtrum; and I am <w part="I">aſtoniſh-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ed</w> that any man ſhould have his head ſo turned, as to draw a concluſion
            in favour of hemlock from ſuch premiſes; and what is worſe, poor HELE is dead, perhaps
            becauſe earlier recourſe was not had to the bark. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Of the kinkcough with the ſmall-pox;</hi> which we
            have already taken notice of. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="part">
          <head ><lb/>Of the cure of the kinkcough with the meaſles, </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Which you have never treated, and therefore your recommendation of
            hemlock in this caſe does not require any comment. And we ſhall <w part="I"
              >hereaf-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> mention a plain fact, which may perhaps <w
              part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">termine</w> whether it or other medicines ought to
            have the preference in caſes of pregnancy<note place="bottom" n="*">* See page 37
              forward. </note>. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The corrollaries we ſhall hereafter have occaſion to refer to; and
            as to the preparations of <w part="I">hem-</w><lb/><w part="F">lock</w> we think them
            unneceſſary, becauſe we have already much ſafer and better medicines of the ſame claſs.
            Indeed it may be much queſtioned, whether your ſtewing this medicine over the fire does
            not render it nea<unclear>##</unclear>y effete<note place="bottom" n="†">† People in
              Derby ſay, the ſmell ariſing from the Cicuta while it is over the fire is ſo
              offenſive, as to be a common nuiſance. Muſt not then its moſt volatile parts fly off?
              and does not the chief effect of the hemlock pill ariſe from the powder of hemlock,
              which happily for the patient is only one fifth of the whole? See caſe in the Eſſay
              where the patient took powdered hemlock. </note>; for a ſurgeon <pb xml:id="page_48"
              n="37"/>gave ſome of the extract a conſiderable time <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">out</w> the leaſt alteration in the patient, but a few ſpoonfuls of the juice
            of hemlock, being taken had a moſt violent and dangerous effect; and, though you are
            willing to have it believed, that you have availed yourſelf of the rule given by CELSUS,
            yet you have not proved that hemlock cures the kinkcough ſafely, certainly, <w part="I"
              >expeditiouſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w>, and pleaſantly, or even that it cures it at
            all. I ſhall, therefore, take the liberty of inſtructing you in the uſe and abuſe of
            this medicine; and if a mind which cannot bear contradiction, ſhould <w part="I"
              >be-</w><lb/><w part="F">come</w> boiſterous upon this occaſion, we will, as time and
            opportunity permit, explain and amend any repreſentations in theſe animadverſions that
            may diſpleaſe you; and, perhaps, we may be able to preſent you with a dialogue from the
            dead <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">twixt</w> SOCRATES, HELE, and TOPLIS, who all
            had, while living, ſufficient experience of the medicine you ſo earneſtly recommend, and
            who went out of the world nearly in the ſame manner. </p>
          <signed>I am, Sir, Your moſt humble ſervant, The AUTHOR. </signed>
          <dateline>Dec. 31ſt, 1773.</dateline>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_49"/>
        <head ><lb/>AN ESSAY ON THE HOOPING-COUGH. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>WHOEVER has a mind to ſee what has been ſaid by former writers upon
          this <w part="I">ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F">ject</w>, a few of the ancients excepted, may
          con-Dr. MILLAR's late obſervations on the <w part="I">hooping-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cough</w>, where they will find that phyſicians <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >fore</w> the days of Dr. B—, had employed <w part="I">ſuc-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ceſſfully</w> ſome of their thoughts on the nature and cure of this diſorder; and the
          following ſhort Eſſay is intended to ſhew whether the method and medicines they recommend,
          or that adviſed by Dr. B—, is moſt likely to relieve the <w part="I">pa-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tient</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>For this purpoſe, we will begin by taking an abſtract from notes made
          in 1749, when the hooping-cough prevailed in this place and <w part="I">neigh-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">bourhood</w>; and we chuſe to relate the ſymptoms <pb xml:id="page_50" n="40"
          />attending thoſe children where the diſorder took its courſe without help from medicine,
          as from hence we ſhall learn its regular progreſs, and theſe we had many opportunities of
          ſeeing, as the common people knowing that the diſorder <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">monly</w> wears off of itſelf in time, were not <w part="I">ſoli-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">citous</w> about medical aſſiſtance, but relied on ſuch trifling remedies as
          themſelves thought moſt proper. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Early in the ſpring, which was moiſt and very cold, many children in
          the ſpace of four or five miles round this place were ſeized with the <w part="I"
            >hoop-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing-cough</w>, about the ſame time, which firſt <w part="I"
            >be-</w><lb/><w part="F">gan</w> with a little dry cough, and ſometimes the ſame kind of
          indiſpoſition as accompanies taking cold, but ſoon after ropy phlegm was coughed up. After
          this the lungs and ſtomach were daily loaded with a larger quantity of phlegm, which in
          ſome became immoderate. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>After ſome, or all of this phlegm was <w part="I">diſcharg-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ed</w> by a fit of coughing and vomiting, the child became eaſy till a
          ſufficient quantity was again <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">cumulated</w> to excite
          another fit of coughing, &amp;c. during which, ſtrong children often bled at the noſe, and
          were black in the face: the phlegm <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">charged</w> was
          ſometimes ſtreaked with blood, and the countenance in a little while acquired a <w
            part="I">luco-</w><lb/><w part="F">phlegmatic</w> appearance. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Thoſe children who had ſenſe enough to ſpit out the phlegm at the time
          of coughing, got ſafely over the diſorder; ſometimes, where it was not very troubleſome,
          in about ſix weeks; where more <pb xml:id="page_51" n="41"/>violent, in about two months,
          and ſometimes it was three months, or longer, before it <w part="I">terminat-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ed</w>. But ſome younger children fared not ſo well, for inſtead of throwing
          the phlegm out of their mouth they ſwallowed it; a griping and looſe ſtools followed, and
          all the parts about the anus were excoriated. At this time they became dry, had a quick
          ſmall pulſe, and all the other <w part="I">ſymp-</w><lb/><w part="F">toms</w> accompanying
          a fever. They now daily got weaker, their legs and body became more or leſs oedematous,
          the cough gradually ceaſed, the difficulty of breathing became more urgent, <w part="I"
            >ſleepi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w>, &amp;c. came on; and when the parents thought
          their children getting better, death convinced them of their miſtake, by cloſing the ſcene
          with all the ſymptoms of a <hi rend="italic">ſpurious <w part="I">peripneu-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">mony</w>.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>During the progreſs of this diſeaſe it often <w part="I"
            >hap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pened</w> in different parts of the neighbourhood, that the
          cough was better for two or three days<note place="bottom" n="*">* <q rend="diple">It is
              worthy of remark, that the convulſive cough in Edinburgh, after being milder in
              January 1735, ſuddenly became much worſe in the firſt week in February, and <w
                part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tinued</w> ſo the greater part of that month,
              gradually <w part="I">decreaſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> afterwards as the ſpring
              and ſummer advanced. Ed. Med. Eſs. vol. iv.</q>
          </note>, and then returned again with its uſual violence, but towards the latter part of
          ſummer it wholly diſappeared. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe ſymptoms give us every reaſon to <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">clude</w>, with other writers, that the diſorder is cauſed by ſome morbid
          diſpoſition of the air, <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">cauſe</w>
          <pb xml:id="page_52" n="42"/>not only one, but many children ſeveral miles aſunder were
          ſeized nearly at the ſame time. Nor can we account for the ſudden abatement and return of
          the cough, but from ſudden alterations in this element. Perhaps it becomes replete with
          miaſma, which render the ſerous and lymphatic juices acrid; whence a larger quantity of
          them than ordinary is ſecreted in conſequence of their irritating the veſſels which
          ſecrete them; or <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">haps</w> the air may have the power
          of weakening the muſcular fibres, and of rendering the fluids viſcid and ropy. But Dr. B—
          ſays, miaſms irritate the mucous glands alone, and cauſe a greater ſecretion of viſcous
          matter. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In ſupport of the firſt of theſe opinions, it may be ſaid, that
          whenever the ſerous or lymphatic juices are extravaſated, and depoſited in any <w part="I"
            >ca-</w><lb/><w part="F">vity</w> in the body, they become viſcid and ropy, witneſs the
          lymph which ſtagnates in the noſe; and why, therefore, will not lymph become ropy in the
          ſame manner, when a greater quantity than ordinary is depoſited upon the lungs in the
          ſtomach and in the inteſtines? </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In ſupport of the ſecond opinion, it may be ſaid, that we know a
          particular ſtate of the air under a lax habit, and ſuch are children, will render the
          lymph ropy, witneſs the ſpurious <w part="I">pe-</w><lb/><w part="F">ripneumony</w> which
          children we ſee in this diſorder fall into when the offending matter is not expelled in
          coughing. And in favour of both theſe <w part="I">opi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nions</w> it
          may be ſaid, the diſeaſe is not confined to the lungs, or to the alimentary canal, but
          that <pb xml:id="page_53" n="43"/>it is extended to the whole body; the fibres in <w
            part="I">ge-</w><lb/><w part="F">neral</w> being relaxed, and an oedematous <w part="I"
            >appear-</w><lb/><w part="F">ance</w> evinces, that the lymph in general has <w part="I"
            >ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">quired</w> a pituitous diſpoſition<note place="bottom" n="*">*
            Some writers have aſſerted, that the juices never acquire this diſpoſition; they ſhould
            have added while they were <w part="I">circu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lating</w> in the
            veſſels; for upon diſſecting an oedematous leg, I found the fluids which had ſtagnated
            in the cellular membrane gla<unclear>##</unclear>y and reſembling the white of an egg.
          </note>; and, beſides, it does not appear that mucus but thickened lymph is diſcharged. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In ſupport of the laſt opinion, nothing can be ſaid till we are
          certain that it is mucus alone which is diſcharged in the fit of coughing, and then there
          could be no doubt but in this diſeaſe the mucous glands are chiefly firſt affected. Theſe
          different opinions we mention to ſhew what <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >certainty</w> there is in fixing the manner in which the immediate cauſe of this
          diſorder acts, and what parts of the body are firſt affected; and, therefore, all the
          plain truth we can collect is, that in <w part="I">conſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">quence</w>
          of a particular ſtate in the air, the <w part="I">ſto-</w><lb/><w part="F">mach</w> and
          lungs are loaded with a tough viſcid phlegm, and that there is a weakneſs and a <w
            part="I">gene-</w><lb/><w part="F">ral</w> tendency to relaxation in the fibres, and to
          a ropy diſpoſition of the lymph and ſerum; that an affection of the ſtomach and lungs is
          the <w part="I">imme-</w><lb/><w part="F">diate</w> cauſe of the cough, becauſe the
          patient <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F">mediately</w> becomes eaſy by vomiting and <w
            part="I">expecto-</w><lb/><w part="F">ration</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>That the lungs and ſtomach are chiefly, and more immediately affected
          in the firſt ſtage of the <pb xml:id="page_54" n="44"/>diſeaſe than the inteſtines, ſeems
          to be plain, <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">cauſe</w> the phlegm does not wholly paſs
          off by ſtool, but is diſcharged by the mouth. Beſides, when it is not evacuated upwards, a
          new train of ſymptoms will ariſe; for accumulating in the ſtomach, it paſſes into the
          inteſtines, putrifies, and becomes very acrid; and the queſtion is, whether if the
          inteſtines were the primary ſeat of the <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">eaſe</w>,
          this putrefaction and a conſequent diarrhaea would not always take place, and whether the
          phlegm would not all paſs downward inſtead of upward? Whereas the truth is, unload the <w
            part="I">ſto-</w><lb/><w part="F">mach</w> and lungs as of ten as an accumulation of
          viſcid phlegm takes place, and the bowels will not ſeem to be much affected. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>However, it is not matter of much <w part="I">conſe-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">quence</w> in practice, whether phlegm firſt reſides in the ſtomach or
          inteſtines, as the whole <w part="I">ali-</w><lb/><w part="F">mentary</w> canal from its
          connection muſt be more or leſs affected with phlegm <hi rend="italic">during</hi> the
          progreſs of the diſeaſe; and ſeeing that the patient becomes eaſy upon its being
          diſcharged, and that a general weakneſs and viſcidity prevails, the true intentions of the
          cure muſt be, to clear repeatedly the lungs and <hi rend="italic">prime viae,</hi> to
          attenuate viſcid phlegm, to <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">vigorate</w> the blood,
          and to preſerve the ſtrength of the ſolids; and, by taking a view of preceding writers, we
          ſhall find, that the medicines which have anſwered theſe ends, have been found moſt
          ſerviceable in curing this diſorder<note place="bottom" n="*">* If this hereafter appears
            to be true, thoſe who inſiſt on hemlock's being a ſpecific, becauſe it is antiſpaſmodic,
            do not ſeem to have ſeen this matter in its true light. </note>. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_55" n="45"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Vomits and purges, and medicines which both vomit and purge, have been
          recommended as principal remedies; and can there be any doubt of theſe medicines relieving
          the patient, as they take away the immediate cauſe of the cough? General conſent evinces,
          that bliſters, or cantharides taken inwardly, have here been remarkably ſerviceable; and
          the cure of the hooping-cough, by <w part="I">inocula-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> for
          the ſmall-pox, alſo ſhew that attenuants are proper aſſiſtants in the cure. And do not all
          agree, that the bark is in this caſe a moſt uſeful medicine? </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nevertheleſs, particular ſymptoms require <w part="I">far-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ther</w> aſſiſtance, till theſe medicines have had time to act upon and remove
          the diſeaſe itſelf, the <w part="I">prin-</w><lb/><w part="F">cipal</w> of which is the
          COUGH; and this Dr. B— has, with great deliberation, declared to be <w part="I"
            >ner-</w><lb/><w part="F">vous</w> and ſpaſmodic. We ſhall, therefore, for the
          information of this gentleman, obſerve, that there is an increaſed degree of irritability
          in the nerves in every cough, though but of ſhort ſtanding; that all coughs are brought on
          by the nerves of particular parts being irritated; and that, in <w part="I"
            >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſequence</w>, a ſpaſm of the diaphragm, and other muſcles
          ſubſervient to reſpiration, follow to ſhake off and expel the irritating matter, by an
          increaſed force of the air which paſſes out of the lungs in reſpiration<note
            place="bottom" n="*">* Thoſe who have read Hoffman, &amp;c. are well acquainted with
            this doctrine; but they will pleaſe to remember, that I am not attempting to inſtruct
            thoſe who have enquired properly into the nature of coughs. </note>. So that every cough
          is a <w part="I">convul-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſive</w>
          <pb xml:id="page_56" n="46"/>cough, and only differs from the hooping-cough in its degree
          of violence; for, though in this laſt there is a vomiting and coughing mixed, yet when we
          reflect upon the action of coughing, and the parts concerned, we ſhall diſcover it to be a
          minor vomiting, and that of courſe a deeper <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſpiration</w> and greater force in coughing will enſue, when the cauſe is ſeated in the
          ſtomach than when it only reſides about the lungs. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nevertheleſs, there is a difference in the nature of the cauſe of
          coughs, ſome being entirely the conſequence of irritated matter, while others ariſe from a
          diſeaſe in the nerves themſelves, which <w part="I">ren-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w> them
          ſo very irritable that a fit of coughing comes on from any ſlight accident that may <w
            part="I">hap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pen</w> to effect the nerves of the lungs<note
            place="bottom" n="*">* This kind of cough is cured by removing the cauſe of the diſeaſe
            in the nerves, and by medicines which have a power of taking off increaſed irritability,
            ſuch as myrrh, gum <w part="I">ammo-</w><lb/><w part="F">niacum</w>, opium, camphire,
            bark, and the like. </note>; but the cough of which we are now treating, is <w part="I"
            >acknow-</w><lb/><w part="F">ledged</w> to ariſe from the former of theſe cauſes. Nor
          could it ever be cured by irritating medicines if it was entirely nervous; and we ſhall,
          therefore, proceed to obſerve, that every cough is an effort of nature to expel the
          irritating matter, and though, when violent, it may always be mitigated with <w part="I"
            >ſafe-</w><lb/><w part="F">ty</w> and advantage, yet wherever it is accompanied with an
          accumulation of phlegm, or the like, it ought never to be ſuppreſſed intirely, unleſs we
          can alſo at the ſame time remove this <w part="I">preterna-</w><lb/><w part="F">tural</w>
          flux. <q rend="quotes">Opiates rather did hurt in the <pb xml:id="page_57" n="47"
            />hooping-cough which raged at Edinburgh in 1734,</q> probably becauſe they were given
          in the uſual dole, and cauſed a retention of that phlegm which would have been diſcharged,
          if the coughing had not been much ſuppreſſed. Poor TOPLISS<note place="bottom" n="*">* See
            caſe xviii. p. 131. </note> had his cough ſuppreſſed by hemlock, which is an opiate; and
          he died of his other <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">plaints</w>, in ſame manner
          probably as thoſe <w part="I">chil-</w><lb/><w part="F">dren</w> we have taken notice of,
          where the cough was ſuppreſſed by weakneſs <hi rend="italic">and an overload of
            phlegm.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nevertheleſs, when we give only one, two, of three drops of laudanum
          in a day, without entirely ſuppreſſing the cough, it ſufficiently leſſens the <w part="I"
            >ir-</w><lb/><w part="F">ritability</w> of the whole habit, and gives the <w part="I"
            >pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tient</w> relief, by preventing the nerves from being ſo
          violently affected. Dr. Hillary ſays, <q rend="quotes">a little ſyr. mecon. or elix.
            paregoric.</q> (joined with other medicines), ſeldom fails to render the diſeaſe more
          moderate, and in time takes it off: and the only deficiency I can ſee in the practice of
          phyſicians in general is, that they have omitted to join <hi rend="italic">very ſmall
            doſes</hi> of opium along with the <w part="I">me-</w><lb/><w part="F">dicines</w> they
          have given to remove the cauſe of the diſeaſe. Whereas Dr. B— gives an opiate joined to
          purges; for we ſhall preſently ſhew, that hemlock, by his manner of mixing it, may be
          converted into a purge; and when this does not happen, he joins other purges along with
          it, ſo that while he is crying up hemlock as a ſpecific, <pb xml:id="page_58" n="48"/>he
          is in a great meaſure carrying off the diſeaſe by medicines recommended by former writers. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>We have already obſerved the neceſſity of <w part="I">keep-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ing</w> the <hi rend="italic">primae viae</hi> and lungs clear of phlegm, and
          this we are not to expect from hemlock, unleſs by accident, for though it ſometimes
          purges, <q rend="quotes">yet it often does not ſenſibly affect any ſecretion;</q> and,
          therefore, is not in this caſe to be ſolely <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">pended</w>
          upon. When it is juſt mixed with ſugar and water, or given in extract or powder, it, like
          other opiates, ſtops immediate ſecretion, and <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >motes</w> ſweat; but when the hemlock mixture has ſtood till it ferments, it opens the
          bowels in the ſame manner as ſugar-candy and the juice of penny-royal when they have ſtood
          together ſome time, ſo that this purgative quality is not inherent in hemlock, but ariſes
          from its being in a ſtate of fermentation; nor does it any way appear that it has an
          attenuating property, or that it is capable of invigorating the blood and ſolids, or of <w
            part="I">unload-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> the lungs when they are overcharged with
          phlegm; whence, though hemlock like opium may ſuppreſs the cough and vomiting, yet the <hi
            rend="italic">dis∣order</hi> is long in terminating under its uſe<note place="bottom"
            n="*">* The patients would probably have been well in the ſame time if they had not
            taken any medicines at all. </note>, becauſe it is deſtitute of other properties which
          are <w part="I">neceſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſary</w> to complete a cure. Peripneumonic <w
            part="I">ſymp-</w><lb/><w part="F">toms</w>, bleeding at the noſe and eyes, and the
          phlegm being ſtreaked with blood, are ſurely ſymptoms which ſometimes require the uſe of
          the <pb xml:id="page_59" n="49"/>lancet, admitting it to protract the diſeaſe, for as
          hemlock, by Dr. B—'s own account, is a week at leaſt in making a cure, may not in this
          time a rupture of a veſſel in the lungs or brain happen, and deſtroy the patient? It is
          confeſſed, that <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">cidental</w> bleedings have ſometimes
          done good; and is it not amazing, that a man who has ſeen <w part="I">pe-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ripneumonic</w> ſymptoms complicated with the <w part="I">hoop-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ing-cough)</w> ſhould in all caſes truſt the life of the patient entirely to a
          favourite antiſpaſmodic? </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It muſt evidently appear from what has been ſaid, that various
          remedies will here ever be <w part="I">neceſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſary</w>; and as an
          opiate of ſome kind or other will in this cough always be a uſeful ingredient, it <w
            part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">mains</w> for us to enquire, whether ſmall doſes of
          laudanum or hemlock ought to have the <w part="I">prefer-</w><lb/><w part="F">ence</w>.
          For this purpoſe we will relate a caſe or two, which have fallen under our own inſpection,
          and the reader himſelf may judge which is the ſafeſt and beſt remedy to cure the cough by
            <w part="I">leſſen-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> irritability. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>A gentlewoman having an incurable ſchirrus, took, by the advice of two
          eminent phyſicians, ſeven grains of hemlock twice a day, which in a little time brought on
          an itching of the whole body. This was ſucceeded by innumerable ſmall bliſters, attended
          by a very angry kind of <w part="I">inflam-</w><lb/><w part="F">mation</w>, pain, and
          ſoreneſs; but upon leaving off this medicine theſe ſymptoms entirely <w part="I"
            >diſap-</w><lb/><w part="F">peared</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Another lady took fourteen grains of the leaves of hemlock made into a
          powder twice a day, and <pb xml:id="page_60" n="50"/>a poultice of the ſame herb was
          applied to an <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">dolent</w> tumour, occaſioned by milk
          ſtagnating in the upper part of her breaſt; the ſame kind of itching and bliſters we have
          mentioned followed accompanied by an inflammation reſembling a malignant eryſipelas, which
          ſwelled her more or leſs all over, but in particular her head; her eyes were affected; ſhe
          ſometimes complained of a <w part="I">ver-</w><lb/><w part="F">tigo</w>; the breaſt, upon
          which the poultice was laid, was ſpread over with fiery eruptions, and indeed her whole
          body ſeemed to be poiſoned. She was full of pain, had reſtleſs nights, and a fever; but
          upon leaving off this dangerous remedy, and <w part="I">tak-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>
          proper remedies, ſhe narrowly eſcaped death, and was reſtored to perfect health. I have
          ſeen other ſimilar caſes; but, perhaps it may be ſaid, it does not often produce theſe
          effects, which muſt be owing to ſome idioſyncraſy in theſe patients. Be it ſo; but may not
          this idioſyncraſy happen in a child, the darling of a tender mother; and would not a
          premature death thus brought on be inex∣cuſeable<note place="bottom" n="*">* Can this
            medicine then be given always with ſafety in pregnant women? </note>, when a drop or two
          of laudanum; or a few drops of the elixir paregoricum, will <w part="I"
            >effectu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ally</w> eaſe the cough, by leſſening increaſed <w
            part="I">irritabi-</w><lb/><w part="F">lity</w>, without the leaſt degree of hazard or
          incon∣venience? </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Dr. BURTON, in order attenuate and diſſolve the phlegm, to corroborate
          and ſtrengthen the fibres, and to prevent any farther viſcidity, after <pb
            xml:id="page_61" n="51"/>clearing the <hi rend="italic">primae viae</hi> with oxymel of
          ſquills and deterſive purges, gave a medicine compoſed of <hi rend="italic">cantharides,
            camphire,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">extract of bark.</hi>
          <q rend="diple quotes">By this medicine, ſays he, I performed the cures very ſoon, ſome in
            five or ſix days, as I can produce many vouchers to witness<note place="bottom" n="*">*
              Dr. B— has only two to vouch for him, here are many. </note>; <w part="I"
              >particu-</w><lb/><w part="F">larly</w> Mr. Dent, apothecary in Selby, who has uſed it
            in the preſent epidemic chincough, <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">cording</w> to my
            preſcription;</q> which is in a much ſhorter time than Dr. B—r pretends to have cured by
          his method; and I can eaſily <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">lieve</w> what Dr. Burton
          ſays to be true, becauſe <hi rend="italic">tincture of cantharides</hi> alone has cured
          this diſorder. Becauſe camphire, which the doctor added to <w part="I">cor-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">rect</w> the cantharides, leſſens increaſed irritability; and becauſe I have
          ſeen bark and attenuants <w part="I">equal-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> ſucceſſful in a
          more advanced period. For my own part, I have in ſome meaſure followed Dr. Burton's method
          in the firſt ſtage of the diſeaſe, except, that inſtead of cantharides I have choſen
          antimony as an attenuant, and I have given <w part="I">lau-</w><lb/><w part="F">danum</w>
          in very ſmall doſes<note place="bottom" n="†">† The rule is to give as much laudanum as
            will leſſen the cough without ſuppreſſing of it intirely; one drop I find it <w part="I"
              >com-</w><lb/><w part="F">monly</w> enough for the purpoſe, taken in the ſpace of
            twenty-four hours in a child of half a year old; two drops in one of a year old; three
            drops, two or three years old; four drops, four years old, &amp;c. but it is not
            neceſſary to continue increaſing the doſe according to the age of the patient, a leſs
            quantity, in proportion, being ſufficient, which is probably owing to the very irritable
            ſtate of young children. </note> for the purpoſe already mentioned. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_62" n="52"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>If the child is plethoric and bleeds at the noſe, or if the phlegm
          diſcharged is ſtreaked with blood, I take ſome blood away from the arm to prevent any
          farther rupture of the veſſels. But I agree with Dr. Burton and others, that blood muſt be
          taken away with great caution; for, as we ſee this diſorder renders the fibres weak, and
          the juices ropy, ſo bleeding, by ſtill weakening them, will increaſe the complaint, and
          therefore, too large a diſcharge of blood will be greatly injurious. <w part="I"
            >On-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> ſo much blood muſt be then taken away as is ſufficient
          to prevent a rupture of the veſſels, and this muſt be judged from the violence of the
          cough, together with the ſtrength of the patient. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Where the ſtomach, &amp;c. are much loaded, I give a vomit of oxymel
          of ſquills, or rather ſome of the preparation of antimony; afterwards the child is purged
          gently every day with rhubarb and ſal polychreſt; and, at the ſame time, is taken three or
          four times a day, a doſe proportioned to the ſtrength and age of the patient, of a
          medicine compoſed of the bark decoction, eſſence of <w part="I">anti-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >mony</w>, ſyrup of pennyroyal, and laudanum, which very ſoon leſſens, and ſhortly
          intirely removes the whole of this complaint. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Where the child is very young, a medicine <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">poſed</w> of ſyrup of pennyroyal, eſſence of antimony, and laudanum, will be
          more readily got down; and provided the ſyrup is made of expreſſed juice without boiling,
          and given while it is in a <w part="I">ferment-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> ſtate, it will
          purge ſufficiently; and, I will <w part="I">ven-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w> to affirm,
          ſooner relieve the patient than the <pb xml:id="page_63" n="53"/>poiſon with which the
          malefactors of the <w part="I">Atheni-</w><lb/><w part="F">ans</w> were deſtroyed; and if
          the child wears at the ſame time a bark ſhift, a complete cure will ſoon be the
          conſequence; though it may be ſometimes requiſite to add oxymel to this mixture, where a
          quantity of phlegm upon the lungs makes its uſe neceſſary. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Hitherto then we have only conſidered the cure of the firſt ſtage of
          the diſeaſe, and ſhall now <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceed</w> to the ſecond,
          which generally ariſes from neglect in not clearing the <hi rend="italic">primae viae</hi>
          by art, when the efforts of nature to expel the offending matter by the mouth are not
          accompliſhed. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In this ſtage we have full evidence, that the lungs, the ſtomach, and
          the inteſtines are all affected, <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">cauſe</w> a ſpurious
          peripneumony invades the little patient, at the ſame time that the phlegm, which paſſes
          from the ſtomach into the inteſtines, brings on a diarrhoea that may end in a dyſentery,
          if the child happens to live. Nevertheleſs, this <w part="I">ſymp-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tom</w> is not without its advantages, where the child happens to be troubled with
          worms, for the <w part="I">mat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> which cauſes it is a, moſt
          powerful vermifuge. The mucus with which children's bowels are lined, is a proper nidus
          for the breeding and increaſe of theſe vermin, and there is not any thing more powerfully
          diſſolves and deſtroys this aſylum than putrid matter, when they are expelled along with
          the faeces. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The coming away of worms is often the <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſequence</w> of inoculation, when the variolous <w part="I">mat-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ter</w> has contaminated the whole maſs of humours, <pb xml:id="page_64" n="54"
          />and part of it enters the inteſtines. A boy <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cidentally</w> broke a penknife blade in the nates, where part of it remained ſome
          time, and <w part="I">form-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> a ſinous ulcer, which collected and
          retained a conſiderable quantity of matter, that became putrid by ſtagnation. The more
          active parts of this matter being abſorbed, brought on a diarrhoea, in which an incredible
          number of worms both dead and living came away, and thus entirely cured the lad of a
          diſeaſe under which he had long laboured. I could indeed produce many ſimilar inſtances,
          but theſe are ſufficient to ſhew thoſe unacquainted with theſe things, that the, ſlimy
          matter which comes away in fevers is not the skins of dead worms; nor are we to believe,
          without farther evidence, that the child has the worms, but that it is the mucus of the
          inteſtines ſet at liberty by putrid matter, and then <w part="I">diſcharg-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ed</w> in the common manner. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>However, though we look upon putrid <w part="I">mat-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ter</w> in the inteſtines as a remedy in ſome caſes, we are not to forget that
          it is a diſeaſe; and, therefore, rhubarb and ſpermaceti ſhould be given as often as
          neceſſary, to clear the bowels, which may <w part="I">after-</w><lb/><w part="F">wards</w>
          be defended from acrid matter, and healed by taking ſtarch, mutton ſuet diſſolved in milk,
          or the pulv. c. chele. e. and ſpermaceti mixed; and the common ſaline julep, with eſſence
          of antimony in it, will be found ſerviceable in abating the fever: but above all things,
          bliſters are moſt <w part="I">uſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">ful</w>, for when the load of
          phlegm upon the lungs has been exceſſive great, the cough ceaſed, and <pb xml:id="page_65"
            n="55"/>an oedema has appeared all over the body, I have frequently ſeen, after they
          have <w part="I">diſcharg-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> a little, the cough return with a
          large <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">pectoration</w> of phlegm, and the little
          patient <w part="I">there-</w><lb/><w part="F">by</w> ſnatched from the jaws of death.
          Nevertheleſs, medicines proper for the ſpurious peripneumony may, if needful, here take
          place; and when the fever is abated, and the difficulty of breathing <w part="I"
            >re-</w><lb/><w part="F">moved</w>, the blood and fibres muſt be invigorated, by having
          recourſe to the bark, to which bees wax or ſpermaceti may be added, if an excoration of
          the bowels ſtill require their uſe. But if the hooping-cough does depend upon ſome
          peculiar diſpoſition in the air, ſurely the child ſhould be <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">moved</w> into an air where this diſpoſition does not prevail, any thing ſaid
          to the contrary <w part="I">not-</w><lb/><w part="F">withſtanding</w>. </p>
        <trailer rend="italic align-center"><lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
