<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Bell: A system of surgery</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Benjamin Bell</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">A system of surgery. By Benjamin Bell, Member of the Royal College of
              Surgeons of Edinburgh, and one of the Surgeons to the Royal Infirmary of that City.
              Illustrated with Copperplates. ...</title>
            <edition n=""/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T99545</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T99545"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: printed by Macfarquhar and Elliot for Charles Elliot,
                  Edinburgh; and G. Robinson, London, M,DCCLXXXIII.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1783</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="15"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="549"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="2"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3307124348</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Surgical or anatominal work"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="15"/>
    <body>
      <pb n=""/>
      <head rend="sc align-center space">
        <lb/>A <lb/><hi rend="size(1.25)">TREATISE </hi>
        <lb/>on the <lb/>THEORY and PRACTICE <lb/>of <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">SURGERY. </hi>
      </head>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A horizontal double-line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <div type="chapter">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>CHAPTER I. </head>
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Of <hi rend="sc">Sutures</hi>. </head>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>SECTION I. </head>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Of Sutures in general. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>S ſutures of one kind or another are <lb/>found neceſſary,
            not only in every <lb/>large wound, but in almoſt every opera- <lb/>tion of importance,
            the conſideration of <pb n="2"/>
            <lb/>this ſubject ſeems firſt to require our at- <lb/>tention. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>A variety of ſutures have been practiſed <lb/>by ſurgeons, each of which has from
            long <lb/>experience been applied to a particular <lb/>purpoſe, <hi rend="italic"
              >viz.</hi> the interrupted ſuture; the <lb/>quilled ſuture; the glover's, and the
            twiſted <lb/>ſuture. Many others are enumerated by <lb/>ancient writers; but the four
            now men- <lb/>tioned are the only ſpecies of ſutures at <lb/>preſent in ordinary uſe;
            and even of theſe, <lb/>ſome, we think, might with propriety be <lb/>omitted. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The intention of every ſuture, is to <lb/>unite parts, which either by accident or
            <lb/>deſign have been divided. Another mode <lb/>of effecting this, is through the
            interven- <lb/>tion of adheſive plaſters; and this by ſur- <lb/>geons has been termed
            the falſe or dry <lb/>ſuture; in oppoſition to the others per- <lb/>formed by the
            needle, which are denomi- <lb/>nated the true or bloody ſuture.—But as <lb/>the
            conſideration of this ſubject, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> the uſe <lb/>of adheſive
            plaſters in wounds, will be <lb/>more properly introduced in a ſubſequent <pb n="3"/>
            <lb/>part of this work, we ſhall not in this <lb/>place enter upon its diſcuſlioni </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>SECTION II. </head>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Of the Interrupted Suture. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N deep wounds, when a reunion of the <lb/>divided paſts is
            intended, this is the ſu- <lb/>ture to which we generally have recourſe; <lb/>but from
            what will be afterwards more <lb/>fully explained when treating of wounds, <lb/>and from
            what will preſently farther appear, <lb/>it does not ſeem to be ſo well adapted to
            <lb/>this purpoſe as the twiſted ſuture. When <lb/>it is determined, however, to make
            trial of <lb/>the interrupted ſuture, the following is <lb/>the eaſieſt mode of doing
            it. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In every Wound where ſutures are found <lb/>neceſſary for the retention of parts,
            it has <lb/>commonly been conſidered as good prac- <lb/>tice, to carry the needle and
            ligature to <lb/>the bottom of the ſore, ſo as to afford as <lb/>little chance as
            poſſible of matter collecting <lb/>underneath; and the uſual mode of effect- <lb/>ing
            this, is by introducing the needle from <pb n="4"/>
            <lb/>without inwards, and again from the <lb/>bottom of the wound to the ſame diſtance
            <lb/>on the oppoſite ſide. But this ſuture, it <lb/>may be remarked, is much more
            neatly, <lb/>and at the ſame time more eaſily performed, <lb/>by paſſing both ends of
            the thread from <lb/>within outwards; which is readily done <lb/>by uſing two needles
            upon each thread, <lb/>inſtead of one. A needle being put upon <lb/>each end of the fame
            thread, and each <lb/>needle being inſerted at the bottom of the <lb/>ſore, and puſhed
            outwardly ſo as to paſs <lb/>out at a proper diſtance from the edge of <lb/>the wound,
            the needles are then to be taken <lb/>off, and the threads allowed to remain till
            <lb/>all the ligatures are paſſed which the ex- <lb/>tent of ſore ſeems to require. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The number of ligatures neceſſary for <lb/>any wound, muſt in a great meaſure de-
            <lb/>pend upon the extent of divided parts. By <lb/>authors in general it has been laid
            down <lb/>as an eſtabliſhed rule, that one ſuture is <lb/>fully ſufficient for every
            inch of wound. <lb/>It will frequently indeed happen, that this <lb/>number is found
            ſufficient; but in ſome in- <pb n="5"/>
            <lb/>ſtances, particularly where muſcular parts <lb/>are deeply cut tranſverſely, and
            where con- <lb/>ſequently a great degree of retraction oc- <lb/>curs, a greater number
            of ſtitches are ne- <lb/>ceſſary: Whenever a number of angles, too, <lb/>occur in a
            wound, more ligatures are re- <lb/>quired than in a ſtraight wound of the <lb/>ſame
            extent; for, at every angle, however <lb/>inconſiderable it may be, there ought to be
            <lb/>a ſuture. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In paſting the ligatures, great care is <lb/>neceſſary to pierce the ſkin at a
            ſufficient <lb/>diſtance from the edge of the wound; for, <lb/>if they do not comprehend
            a thickneſs of <lb/>parts in ſome meaſure proportioned to the <lb/>depth of the wound,
            and to the extent of <lb/>retraction to be expected, they will very <lb/>readily cut
            through the parts entirely.— <lb/>By ſome authors we are directed to paſs <lb/>the
            ligatures, at nearly the ſame diſtance <lb/>from the edges of the ſore, as the wound is
            <lb/>of depth. This rule, however, will by no <lb/>means be found to anſwer in practice.
            <lb/>Thus, in a very deep wound, for inſtance <lb/>of three inches or ſo, no neceſſity,
            can oc- <pb n="6"/>
            <lb/>cur for carrying the ligatures three inches <lb/>from, the edges of the ſore; and
            again, in <lb/>very ſuperficial cuts, it ſometimes happens <lb/>that the ligature ought
            to be paſſed out at <lb/>a greater diſtance from the edges of the <lb/>wound than the
            ſore is of depth. It ought <lb/>not, in almoſt any caſe, to be leſs than half <lb/>an
            inch from the edge of the ſore; and it <lb/>will ſeldom happen, even in the largeſt
            <lb/>wounds, that an inch is not found to be a <lb/>ſufficient diſtance. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It will be readily underſtood, that the <lb/>ſtrength of the ligature and ſize of
            needle <lb/>ought always to be proportioned to the <lb/>depth of the ſore and retraction
            of parts. <lb/>The ſeveral ſizes of needles, as repreſen- <lb/>ted in Plate I. are of
            the various di- <lb/>menſions found neceſſary in practice; <lb/>and the ligatures to be
            uſed along with <lb/>them ought to be ſuch as nearly, though <lb/>not entirely, to fill
            the eyes of the diffe- <lb/>rent needles. In order to make the liga- <lb/>tures paſs
            more eaſily, to render them <lb/>more durable, and at the ſame time to <lb/>make them
            more ſuſceptible of a flattened <pb n="7"/>
            <lb/>form, which does not ſo readily cut thro' <lb/>the contained parts as a round one,
            they <lb/>ought all to be well covered with fine bees- <lb/>wax. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>So ſoon as the threads are all paſſed, the <lb/>lips of the wound ought to be
            preſſed to- <lb/>gether and ſupported by an aſſiſtant till all <lb/>the ligatures are
            firmly tied; beginning <lb/>either in the middle of the wound, or at <lb/>one end, as
            the operator inclines. In ty- <lb/>ing the knots, it is uſual to paſs the ends <lb/>of
            the threads twice through the firſt nooſe, <lb/>in order to prevent their yielding; and
            <lb/>when this is done, it is alleged by ſome <lb/>that there is no neceſſity for more
            than <lb/>one knot upon each ligature; but as two <lb/>knots are very eaſily made, and
            as every <lb/>chance of their yielding is thereby effec- <lb/>tually prevented, this
            precaution ought <lb/>never to be omitted. It is a practice with <lb/>ſome ſurgeons to
            inſert a piece of lint be- <lb/>tween the firſt and ſecond knots, or be- <lb/>tween the
            firſt knot and the ſkin below, in <lb/>order to ſave the parts underneath from the
            <lb/>preſſure of the knots; but as in reality all <pb n="8"/>
            <lb/>ſuch means of protection afford no advan- <lb/>tage of importance, and as they
            prevent the <lb/>knots from being made with exactneſs, they <lb/>ought therefore to be
            laid entirely aſide. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>By ſome writers on this ſubject, we are <lb/>deſired not to bring the knots of
            ligatures <lb/>immediately upon the edges of the wound, <lb/>but rather to carry them to
            one ſide, over <lb/>upon the ſound teguments: but whoever <lb/>has tried both methods,
            will at once be <lb/>ſenſible, that this is by no means an im- <lb/>provement; for in no
            other way can both <lb/>ſides of the ſore be equally ſupported, but <lb/>by the knots
            being paſſed immediately <lb/>above the lips of the divided parts. </p>
          <figure>
            <head>
              <lb/>Explanation of Plate I. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(|. . .. , Fig. i. A form of hook, commonly ter- <lb/>med a tenaculum, for the
              purpoſe of pul- <lb/>ling out bleeding veſſels to be tied by liga- <lb/>tures. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Fig. 2. and 3. Two needles of a different <lb/>curve from thoſe in ordinary uſe.
              The cur- <lb/>vatures being altogether on their fore-parts, <lb/>and the handles
              perfectly ſtraight, they are <lb/>thereby more eaſily managed than the <lb/>others,
              particularly in deep wounds. Fig. 5. <lb/>and 6. repreſent two needles of the uſual
              <lb/>form; but neither theſe nor the other two <lb/>have an edge on their concave
              parts. They <lb/>are made ſomewhat round like a lancet, <lb/>both on their convex and
              concave ſides; <pb n=""/>
              <lb/>which adds to their ſtrength, and makes <lb/>them enter with more eaſe than the
              others. <lb/>I have long made uſe of thoſe needles, and <lb/>whoever employs them will
              find them pre- <lb/>ferable in every reſpect to the others. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Fig. 4. and 7. Two ſtraight needles for <lb/>ſutures of the inteſtines and other
              delicate <lb/>membranous parts. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>All theſe needles are repreſented of the <lb/>full ſize. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>A number of inſtruments have been <lb/>contrived for holding the needles when
              <lb/>they are to be employed in deep wounds. <lb/>The Port-aiguille repreſented in
              Plate II. <lb/>will anſwer this purpoſe as well as any <lb/>other; but inſtruments of
              this kind can- <lb/>not be often needed. </p>
            <figDesc> </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>SECTION III. </head>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Of the Quilled Suture. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>S the quilled ſuture is ſtill retained by <lb/>ſome
            practitioners, it is here thought <lb/>neceſſary to deſcribe the. mode of perform-
            <lb/>ing it. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In deep wounds attended with much re- <lb/>traction, it, is always a neceſſary
            precau- <pb n="9"/>
            <lb/>tion, to aſſiſt the operation of the liga- <lb/>tures, by means of bandages ſo
            applied as <lb/>to afford as much ſupport as poſſible to the <lb/>divided parts: But,
            even with every aſſiſt- <lb/>ance of this nature, it now and then hap- <lb/>pens, that
            the divided parts cannot be kept <lb/>together, retraction occurs to a greater or
            <lb/>leſſer degree, and the ligatures of courſe <lb/>cut aſunder the ſoft parts they
            were at <lb/>firſt made to ſurround. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>With a view to prevent this receding of <lb/>the teguments and other parts, it was
            long <lb/>ago propoſed to add to the interrupted ſu- <lb/>ture what was ſuppoſed would
            afford an ad- <lb/>ditional ſupport; <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> quills, or pieces of
            <lb/>plaſter rolled up into the form of quills, <lb/>one of which being placed on each
            fide of <lb/>the wound, the double of the ligature is <lb/>made to include the one, and
            the knot to <lb/>preſs directly upon the other, inſtead of <lb/>being made immediately
            on the edges of <lb/>the ſore as was directed for interrupted <lb/>ſutures. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is at once evident, however, that the <lb/>ligatures muſt here make the ſame
            degree <pb n="10"/>
            <lb/>of preſſure on the parts through which <lb/>they paſs, as they do in the
            interrupted <lb/>ſuture; and this being the caſe, it is equal- <lb/>ly obvious, that the
            interpoſition of theſe <lb/>ſubſtances cannot be of any uſe. This <lb/>ſuture is
            accordingly now very rarely prac- <lb/>tiſed, and it is probable that it will be
            <lb/>ſoon laid entirely aſide. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>SECTION IV. </head>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Of the Glover's Suture. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HIS ſuture is termed the Glover's from <lb/>being the one in
            common uſe among <lb/>that ſet of people. As it is exceedingly <lb/>ſimple, and very
            univerſally known, it does <lb/>not here merit much deſcription: We ſhall <lb/>therefore
            juſt ſhortly obſerve, that it con- <lb/>ſiſts in a ſeries of ſtitches all connected with
            <lb/>one another, and continued in an oblique <lb/>ſpiral direction along the courſe of
            the di- <lb/>vided parts intended by it to be kept to- <lb/>gether. </p>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/>This ſuture has hitherto been univer- <lb/>ſally employed for reuniting ſuch parts
            of <pb n="11"/>
            <lb/>the inteſtines as have been divided by <lb/>wounds: but, when treating of accidents
            <lb/>of this kind, I ſhall endeavour to ſhow, <lb/>that the ſame end may be more
            perfectly <lb/>attained, and probably with leſs danger, <lb/>by means of the interrupted
            ſuture; ſo <lb/>that as this ſuture has almoſt never been <lb/>applied to any other
            purpoſe, it will like- <lb/>wiſe in all probability ſoon fall into diſ- <lb/>uſe. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center space">
            <lb/>SECTION V. </head>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Of the Twiſted Sutura. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">B</hi>Y the term twiſted ſuture is meant, that <lb/>ſpecies of
            ligature, by which, parts <lb/>either naturally or artificially ſeparated, <lb/>are
            united together, by means of ſtrong <lb/>threads properly twiſted round pins or
            <lb/>needles puſhed through the edges of the <lb/>divided parts. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This ſuture is commonly employed for <lb/>the purpoſe of uniting the parts in caſes
            of <lb/>hare-lip; and this indeed is almoſt the only <lb/>uſe to which it has been
            hitherto applied: <pb n="12"/>
            <lb/>But we may here remark, that it may with <lb/>great advantage be put in practice in
            a va- <lb/>riety of other caſes, particularly in all arti- <lb/>ficial or accidental
            diviſions either of the <lb/>lips or cheeks; and, in every wound in <lb/>other parts
            that does not run deep and in <lb/>which ſutures are neceſſary, this ſuture is
            <lb/>preferable to the interrupted or any other. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In very deep wounds, for inſtance in all <lb/>wounds extending to a greater depth
            than <lb/>an inch and half, the interrupted ſuture is <lb/>the only one that is
            admiſſible; for, in <lb/>all ſuch deep cuts, the pins neceſſary in the <lb/>twiſted
            ſuture cannot with propriety be <lb/>employed, as they cannot be introduced <lb/>to ſuch
            a depth, and afterwards ſo twiſted <lb/>with ligatures as to reunite the divided
            <lb/>parts, but with great pain to the patient. <lb/>In ſuch wounds, therefore, we muſt
            of ne- <lb/>ceſſity have recourſe to the interrupted ſu- <lb/>ture: But it may be here
            remarked, that <lb/>wounds of this depth requiring the aid of <lb/>ſutures, are very
            rarely met with; ſo that, <lb/>in by much the greateſt proportion of <lb/>wounds where
            ſutures are adviſable, the <pb n="13"/>
            <lb/>twiſted ſuture will be found practica- <lb/>ble; and whenever it is ſo, it ought
            cer- <lb/>tainly to be preferred to every other, as <lb/>being obviouſly better
            calculated, even than <lb/>the interrupted ſuture, for the retention of <lb/>divided
            parts. The pins made uſe of for <lb/>twiſting the threads upon, ought to be <lb/>made of
            a flat form, ſo as not to cut the <lb/>parts through which they paſs, ſo readily <lb/>as
            the ligatures employed in the interrupted <lb/>ſuture: And thus one great objection to
            <lb/>the latter is very effectually obviated; for, <lb/>every practitioner muſt be
            ſenſible of this <lb/>being the moſt faulty part of the interrup- <lb/>ted ſuture, that
            when muſcular parts are <lb/>divided, ſo as to produce much retraction, <lb/>the
            ligatures employed for retaining them, <lb/>almoſt conſtantly cut them thro' before a
            <lb/>reunion is accompliſhed; whereas, the flat- <lb/>neſs of the pins uſed in the
            twiſted ſuture, <lb/>and upon which, it may be remarked, the <lb/>whole preſſure
            produced by the ligatures <lb/>is made to reſt, proves in general a very <lb/>effectual
            preventative againſt all ſuch oc- <lb/>currences. </p>
          <pb n="14"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The The pins uſed in this operation, have <lb/>commonly been made of ſilver; and,
            in <lb/>order to make them paſs with greater eaſe, <lb/>ſteel points have been added to
            them. As <lb/>gold pins, however, are capable of receiv- <lb/>ing a ſufficient degree of
            ſharpneſs, which <lb/>renders the intervention of ſteel points quite <lb/>unneceſſary;
            and as gold is fully more <lb/>cleanly than ſilver, from its not acquiring <lb/>ſo
            readily that kind of cruſt which immer- <lb/>ſion in fluids is apt to produce upon the
            <lb/>other, pins of this metal are therefore pre- <lb/>ferable. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The form and ſize of pins as repre- <lb/>ſented in Plate II. is what from
            experience <lb/>has been found to be the moſt uſeful for <lb/>every ordinary purpoſe;
            but, for parti- <lb/>cular uſes, the ſize muſt no doubt be ſub- <lb/>ject to variations. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The manner of performing this opera- <lb/>tion is as follows. The divided parts in-
            <lb/>tended to be reunited, muſt by the hands <lb/>of an aſſiſtant be brought nearly
            into con- <lb/>tact; leaving juſt as much ſpace between <lb/>the edges of the ſore, as
            to allow the ſur- <pb n="15"/>
            <lb/>geon to ſee that the pins are carried to a <lb/>proper depth. This being done, one
            of the <lb/>pins muſt be introduced through both ſides <lb/>of the wound, by entering it
            on one ſide <lb/>externally, puſhing it forwards and in- <lb/>wards to within a little
            of the bottom of <lb/>the wound, and afterwards carrying it <lb/>outwardly through the
            oppoſite ſide, to the <lb/>ſame diſtance from the edge of the ſore <lb/>that it was made
            to enter at on the <lb/>other. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The diſtance at which the needle ought <lb/>to enter from the edge of the ſore,
            muſt be <lb/>determined by the depth of the wound, <lb/>and by the degree of retraction
            produced <lb/>in the divided parts. In general, however, <lb/>it is a proper regulation
            in deep wounds, to <lb/>carry the pins nearly to the ſame diſtance <lb/>from the ſide of
            the ſore, as they are made <lb/>to penetrate in depth: And it may be alſo <lb/>remarked,
            that, whatever the deepneſs of <lb/>the wound may be, the pins ought to paſs <lb/>within
            a very little of its bottom; other- <lb/>wife the parts which lie deep will run a
            <lb/>riſk of not being united, a circumſtance <pb n="16"/>
            <lb/>which muſt always give riſe to troubleſome <lb/>collections of matter. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In paſſing the pins through the different <lb/>ſides of the wound, if the ſkin and
            other <lb/>teguments are not more firm than ordi- <lb/>nary, it may commonly be done by
            the <lb/>fingers alone, and particularly if the pins <lb/>are made with ſmall heads or
            knobs for the <lb/>fingers to preſs upon; but when, from <lb/>firmneſs of parts and
            other circumſtances, <lb/>much difficulty is expected to the entrance <lb/>of the pins,
            the inſtrument termed Porte- <lb/>aiguille very effectually removes this in-
            <lb/>convenience.—In Plate II. is repreſented <lb/>the moſt convenient form of this
            inſtru- <lb/>ment that has yet been invented. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The firſt pin being paſſed in this man- <lb/>ner very near to one end of the ſore,
            <lb/>and the parts being ſtill ſupported by an <lb/>aſſiſtant, the ſurgeon, by means of
            a firm <lb/>waxed ligature, paſſed three or four times <lb/>round and acroſs the pin, ſo
            as nearly to <lb/>deſcribe the figure of 8, is to draw the parts <lb/>through which it
            has paſſed, into immediate <lb/>and cloſe contact: and the thread being <pb n="17"/>
            <lb/>now ſecured with a looſe knot, another pin <lb/>muſt be introduced in the ſame
            manner at <lb/>a proper diſtance from the former; and <lb/>the thread with which the
            other was <lb/>fixed, being looſed, and in the ſame man- <lb/>ner carried round this
            pin, others muſt be <lb/>introduced at proper diſtances along the <lb/>whole courſe of
            the wound, and the ſame <lb/>ligature ought to be of a ſufficient length <lb/>for
            ſecuring the whole. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The number of pins to be uſed, muſt <lb/>be determined entirely by the extent of
            the <lb/>wound. Whenever this ſuture, however, is <lb/>practiſed, whether the wound be
            large or <lb/>of very ſmall extent, a pin ought to be in- <lb/>troduced very near to
            each end of it, other- <lb/>wiſe the extremities of the ſore are apt to <lb/>ſeparate ſo
            as not to be afterwards eaſily <lb/>reunited. In large wounds, if the pins <lb/>are
            introduced at the diſtance of three <lb/>quarters of an inch from one another, it
            <lb/>will in general be found ſufficient; but, in <lb/>cuts of ſmaller extent, a greater
            number of <lb/>pins become neceſſary in proportion to the <lb/>dimenſions of the ſores. </p>
          <pb n="18"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Thus, in a wound of an inch and half <lb/>in length, three pins are abſolutely
            requi- <lb/>ſite; one near to each end, and another in <lb/>the middle of the ſore:
            Whereas, five pins <lb/>will always be found fully ſufficient for a <lb/>wound of three
            inches and a half in extent, <lb/>allowing one to be within a quarter of an <lb/>inch of
            each extremity of the wound, and <lb/>the others to be placed along the courſe of
            <lb/>the ſore at the diſtance of three quarters of <lb/>an inch from one another. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The pins being all introduced and ſe- <lb/>cured in the manner directed, nothing
            re- <lb/>mains to be done, but to apply a piece of <lb/>lint wet with mucilage, all
            along the courſe <lb/>of the wound, with a view to exclude as <lb/>effectually as
            poſſible every acceſs to the ex- <lb/>ternal air. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In order to prevent the ends of the pins <lb/>from preſſing upon and hurting the
            ſkin <lb/>below, it is uſual to apply a ſmall bolſter <lb/>of finen or charpie under
            each of them; <lb/>but as this always does miſchief, by tend- <lb/>ing to preſs upon the
            pins, ſo as to force <lb/>them to act upon the ſoft parts thro' which <pb n="19"/>
            <lb/>they have paſſed, every thing of this kind <lb/>ought to be omitted. When, however,
            the <lb/>patient happens to complain of being hurt <lb/>by the ends of the pins, this
            may be eaſily <lb/>prevented, by introducing between them <lb/>and the ſkin pieces of
            thin linen ſpread with <lb/>any adheſive plaſter. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In order to give every chance of ſucceſs <lb/>to this operation, it has been
            commonly <lb/>adviſed, immediately after the pins are ſe- <lb/>cured, to apply the
            uniting bandage over <lb/>the whole, ſo as to afford as much ſupport <lb/>as poſſible to
            the contiguous parts. The <lb/>leaſt reflection, however, renders it evident, <lb/>that
            every degree of preſſure made in this <lb/>manner muſt do mifqhief; for, the bandage
            <lb/>being made to reſt immediately upon the <lb/>pins, a conſiderable degree of pain
            and con- <lb/>ſequent inflammation muſt of courſe be pro- <lb/>duced by it: And in fact
            this is ſo much the <lb/>caſe, that, in every inſtance in which I have <lb/>ſeen this
            bandage applied, it either did harm, <lb/>by exciting inflammation in conſequence
            <lb/>of too much preſſure upon the pins; or, if <lb/>that effect was not produced, no
            advantage <pb n="20"/>
            <lb/>was received from it, from the bandage <lb/>not being applied with ſuch tightneſs
            as <lb/>to afford any ſupport whatever to the parts <lb/>below. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The next point to be determined, is, the <lb/>time the pins ſhould be allowed to
            re- <lb/>main. When they remain long, they gene- <lb/>rally do harm, by the unneceſſary
            irritation <lb/>and conſequent retraction of parts with <lb/>which they are always
            attended; and again, <lb/>if they are not continued for a ſufficient <lb/>length of
            time, that degree of adheſion is not <lb/>produced between the divided parts that is
            <lb/>neceſſary for their future retention, ſo that <lb/>the effect of the operation
            comes to be in <lb/>a great meaſure, if not entirely, loſt. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In wounds of no great depth, for in- <lb/>ſtance of three quarters of an inch or
            ſo, a <lb/>ſufficient degree of adheſion always takes <lb/>place in the ſpace of five
            days; and ſix, or <lb/>at moſt ſeven days, will generally be found <lb/>ſufficient for
            wounds of the greateſt depth. <lb/>But with reſpect to this circumſtance, it <lb/>muſt
            always be underſtood, that the pa- <lb/>tient's ſtate of health muſt have a conſider-
              <pb n="21"/>
            <lb/>able influence on the time neceſſary for <lb/>producing adheſion between divided
            parts. <lb/>In ſpecifying the time neceſſary for this pur- <lb/>poſe, the operation is
            ſuppoſed to have been <lb/>done on a conſtitution in a ſtate of perfect <lb/>health.
            When the patient labours under <lb/>ſcurvy, or any diſorder which affects the
            <lb/>general ſyſtem, it is impoſſible to aſcertain <lb/>this circumſtance with
            preciſion: In ſuch <lb/>caſes we muſt be determined by the nature <lb/>and ſtate of the
            diſeaſe preſent at the time. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>So ſoon as the pins are withdrawn, the <lb/>uniting bandage may be then applied
            with <lb/>great advantage in order to ſerve as a ſupport <lb/>to the parts newly united;
            but, as flips of <lb/>leather ſpread with ordinary glue, when ap- <lb/>plied to each
            ſide of the cicatrix, may, by <lb/>means of ligatures properly connected with <lb/>them,
            be made to anſwer this purpoſe in a <lb/>more effectual manner, this mode of ſup-
            <lb/>porting the parts ought of courſe to be <lb/>preferred <note place="bottom" n="*"
              rend="size(0.75)">*Figures of parts united in this manner, will be re- <lb/>preſented
              when we come to treat of the Hare-Lip. </note>. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>As the twiſted ſuture when properly <pb n="22"/>
            <lb/>performed is a very neat operation, as its <lb/>conſequences are in general of
            importance, <lb/>and as it may with much advantage be made <lb/>to ſuperſede the uſe of
            almoſt every ſu- <lb/>ture, a few inſtances only excepted, I there- <lb/>fore thought it
            proper to conſider it with <lb/>more attention than has hitherto been com- <lb/>monly
            beſtowed upon it. </p>
          <figure>
            <head>Explanation <hi rend="italic">of</hi> Plate II. </head>
            <figDesc> </figDesc>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Fig. 1. A Porte-aiguille mentioned inp. 16. <list rend="indentall">
                <lb/>
                <item>A. A. The handles of the inſtrument. </item>
                <lb/>
                <item>B. A groove for receiving the pins uſed in the twiſted ſuture. </item>
              </list>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>This inſtrument is commonly made with <lb/>a ſlider for fixing the handles after
              the pins <pb n="24"/>
              <lb/>are inſerted into the groove; but as this al- <lb/>ways proves troubleſome to the
              operator, <lb/>and is not in any degree neceſſary, it is here <lb/>purpoſely omitted. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Fig. 2.3. and 4. are different ſizes of pins <lb/>uſed in the twiſted ſuture
              deſcribed p. 13. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>And fig. 5. is a flat needle ſometimes <lb/>found uſeful in ſtitching
              blood-veſſels that <lb/>lie between contiguous bones. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>All the inſtruments in this plate are re- <lb/>preſented of their full ſize. </p>
          </figure>
          <figure>
            <figDesc> </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter">
        <head rend="align-center space">CHAP. II. </head>
        <head rend="hanging space italic">
          <lb/>Of the <hi rend="sc">LIGATURE</hi> of <hi rend="sc">ARTERIES</hi>, and other
          <lb/>means employed by art for putting a ſtop to <lb/><hi rend="sc">HÆMORRHAGIES</hi>. </head>
        <div type="section">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N every ſpecies of wound, whether ac- <lb/>cidentally
            produced, or effected by the <lb/>hands of a ſurgeon, the firſt circumſtance to <lb/>be
            attended to, is the degree of hæmorrhagy <lb/>that takes place. In all ſuch occurrences,
              <pb n="25"/>
            <lb/>the blood is diſcharged, either from one or <lb/>more large arteries; or, is
            produced by a <lb/>general oozing from the ſmaller veſſels over <lb/>the ſurface of the
            ſore: To the former of <lb/>theſe cauſes we ſhall firſt attend, and ſhall
            <lb/>afterwards proceed to the conſideration of <lb/>the latter. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>A ſurgeon being called to a perſon loſing <lb/>much blood from the diviſion of any
            of the <lb/>larger veſſels, the firſt ſtep to be taken, is, by <lb/>means of ſtrong
            compreſſion, to effect a tem- <lb/>porary ſtoppage of the diſcharge, till by the
            <lb/>application of ligatures a more effectual re- <lb/>medy is obtained. In the head,
            as well as in <lb/>the trunk of the body, the eaſieſt method of <lb/>applying preſſure
            of this kind, is, by means <lb/>of doſſilſof linen or charpie, held firmly up- <lb/>on
            the mouths of the bleeding veſſels, either <lb/>by the hands of an aſſiſtant, or by the
            uſe of <lb/>a proper bandage: Or, when preſſure can be <lb/>effectually applied to the
            ſuperior part of the <lb/>artery, it anſwers better; as it not only ſe- <lb/>cures the
            veſſel equally well, but admits of <lb/>the neceſſary ligature being applied with
            <lb/>greater freedom. </p>
          <pb n="26"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When, again, accidents of this nature <lb/>occur in any of the extremities, and
            where <lb/>preſſure can be made with eaſe on the ſupe- <lb/>rior parts of arteries, for
            ſuch caſes we are <lb/>in poſſeſſion of a remedy, which, when ſkill- <lb/>fully applied,
            never fails of producing an <lb/>immediate ſtop to all farther loſs of blood. <lb/>What
            is here meant, is, the Tourniquet. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Till the invention of this inſtrument, <lb/>which was not known till laſt century,
            Sur- <lb/>gery remained in a deplorable ſtate indeed. <lb/>No operation of importance
            could be un- <lb/>dertaken on any of the extremities but with <lb/>great hazard to the
            patient; and the effects <lb/>of large wounds muſt frequently have pro- <lb/>ved mortal,
            from the want of this aſſiſt- <lb/>ance, which otherwiſe might not have been <lb/>in any
            degree hazardous. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>As the invention of the tourniquet is <lb/>claimed by different people, and even by
            <lb/>different nations, we ſhall not here pretend <lb/>to ſay from whence it originally
            came: <lb/>but whoever had the merit of it, the firſt inſtru- <lb/>ment of this kind
            with which the world <lb/>was made acquainted, was exceedingly <pb n="27"/>
            <lb/>ſimple; ſo much-ſo, indeed, that we now <lb/>reflect with aſtoniſhment at the
            diſcovery <lb/>having been reſerved to ſuch a very late pe- <lb/>riod. A ſmall cuſhion
            being placed upon the <lb/>courſe of the principal artery of a limb, a <lb/>circular
            rope or bandage was made to paſs <lb/>twice round it; and a ſmall timber handle
            <lb/>being then introduced between one of the <lb/>folds of the bandage, for the purpoſe
            of <lb/>twiſting it, the cuſhion by theſe means was <lb/>preſſed with ſo much force upon
            the artery, <lb/>as to put an effectual ſtop to the courſe of <lb/>the blood through the
            under part of the <lb/>limb. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Mr Petit, an eminent ſurgeon of Paris, was <lb/>the firſt who propoſed a
            conſiderable im- <lb/>provement on this inſtrument, by connec- <lb/>ting the circular
            bandage with a ſcrew, <lb/>which was ſo contrived as to produce the <lb/>preſſure
            chiefly on the principal arteries, <lb/>without materially affecting the reſt of the
            <lb/>limb. It had this advantage over the other <lb/>inſtrument, that the operator
            himſelf could <lb/>manage it, without being under the neceſ- <lb/>ſity of employing an
            aſſiſtant; but it was <pb n="28"/>
            <lb/>liable to one great inconvenience from <lb/>the very circumſtance which by the
            inven- <lb/>tor was conſidered as an improvement. <lb/>This inſtrument of Mr Petit being
            made <lb/>to act upon the principal arteries only, <lb/>the ſmaller veſſels
            communicating with <lb/>theſe, by not being properly compreſſed, <lb/>diſcharge blood
            freely from the inſtant they <lb/>are cut; and as this proves a very trouble- <lb/>ſome
            circumſtance in the courſe of ope- <lb/>rations, different improvements have of
            <lb/>late been made upon it. The pattern in <lb/>Plate III. is the reſult of all of
            theſe. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>By means of this inſtrument in its now <lb/>improved ſtate, the blood in arty limb
            is <lb/>very eaſily and effectually commanded; and <lb/>as it graſps the whole member
            equally, all <lb/>the collateral branches as well as the prin- <lb/>cipal arteries are
            equally compreſſed by it. <lb/>It has this material advantage, too, over <lb/>every
            other inſtrument of this kind, that, <lb/>when properly applied, a ſingle turn, or
            <lb/>even half a turn of the ſcrew, is ſufficient <lb/>for producing either a flow of
            blood, or <pb n="29"/>
            <lb/>for putting a total ſtop to it.—The manner <lb/>of uſing it is this. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Let a cuſhion of three inches in length <lb/>by one inch and half in diameter be
            pre- <lb/>pared of a linen roller, and be made tole- <lb/>rably firm but yet not ſo hard
            as to ren- <lb/>der preſſure produced by it very pain- <lb/>ful: This being placed upon
            the courſe of <lb/>the principal artery of the limb, is to be <lb/>firmly ſecured in
            that ſituation by one or <lb/>two turns of a circular roller, of the ſame <lb/>breadth
            with the cuſhion itſelf. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The inſtrument A, with the ſtrap con- <lb/>nected with it, being now placed upon
            the <lb/>limb, with the handle of the ſcrew B on <lb/>the oppoſite ſide of the member to
            the <lb/>cuſhion upon the artery, the ſtrap C is to be <lb/>carried round the limb
            directly over the <lb/>cuſhion, and to be firmly connected on the <lb/>other ſide to the
            buckle D. In thus connec- <lb/>ting the ſtrap and buckle together, parti- <lb/>cular
            attention is neceſſary in doing it with <lb/>great firmneſs, ſo as that the ſcrew may
            <lb/>afterwards operate with as much advantage <lb/>as poſſible, in producing a
            ſufficient degree <pb n="30"/>
            <lb/>of preſſure. When proper attention is paid <lb/>to this circumſtance, a ſingle turn
            of the <lb/>ſcrew, as we have ſaid, proves ſufficient <lb/>for putting an entire ſtop to
            the circulation <lb/>of blood in the limb; but when the ſtrap <lb/>has not originally
            been made very tight, <lb/>ſeveral turns of the ſcrew become neceſ- <lb/>ſary; an
            occurrence which may be always <lb/>very eaſily prevented, and which, when not
            <lb/>attended to, frequently proves very em- <lb/>barraſſing in the courſe of an
            operation. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Whenever it is determined, therefore, <lb/>that any farther loſs of blood from a
            divi- <lb/>ded artery is to be prevented, preſſure on <lb/>the ſuperior part of the
            veſſel ought to be <lb/>immediately had recourſe to; by the hands <lb/>of an aſſiſtant,
            or a proper bandage, when <lb/>the cut is on the head or trunk of the <lb/>body; and by
            means of the tourniquet, <lb/>when any of the extremities are wound- <lb/>ed. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The patient being in this manner ſecured <lb/>from immediate danger, the
            practitioner <lb/>muſt now proceed to the eaſieſt and moſt <lb/>effectual mode of
            preventing a return of <pb n="31"/>
            <lb/>hæmorrhagy on the removal of the tourni- <lb/>quet. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The ancients, as we have ſeen, were ig- <lb/>norant of the uſe and application of
            the <lb/>tourniquet, and they were equally deficient <lb/>in the employment of means for
            giving a <lb/>permanent ſecurity againſt the flow of <lb/>blood from divided veſſels: It
            will there- <lb/>fore readily occur to every modern prac- <lb/>titioner, that in this
            imperfect ſtate of <lb/>Chirurgical knowledge, when any capital <lb/>operations were
            attempted, they muſt have <lb/>run a much greater riſk of doing miſchief, <lb/>than of
            procuring any advantage to their <lb/>patients. To the ſmaller veſſels they ap-
            <lb/>plied doſſils of linen covered with aſtringent <lb/>powders; and for the larger
            arteries, ſear- <lb/>ing with hot irons was their only re- <lb/>ſource. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Even this laſt remedy however, although <lb/>it commands a temporary ſtoppage of
            the <lb/>blood in every caſe of hæmorrhage, its <lb/>effects are by no means to be
            depended on: <lb/>for, in general, the pulſation of the larger <lb/>arteries very ſoon
            overcomes all the reſiſt- <pb n="32"/>
            <lb/>ance produced by the application of the <lb/>cautery. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In ancient times, however, when this <lb/>was the moſt effectual remedy with which
            <lb/>the world was acquainted, practitioners <lb/>were under the neceſſity of having
            recourſe <lb/>to it; and, at that period, it is not ſurpri- <lb/>ſing to find them
            exerciſing their genius in <lb/>inventing a variety of ſtyptic applications: <lb/>But
            ſince ſurgery became enriched with <lb/>that material improvement of ſecuring the
            <lb/>larger arteries by means of ligatures, a <lb/>practice eaſily effected, and with
            very little <lb/>pain to the patient, it is ſurpriſing to find <lb/>that remedies of
            this kind are ſtill ſearched <lb/>after. If the uſe of ligatures was in itſelf at-
            <lb/>tended with much difficulty, if by experi- <lb/>ence it had been found to be
            productive of <lb/>many bad conſequences, or, if it had been <lb/>frequently known to
            fail in anſwering as a <lb/>full ſecurity againſt the hæmorrhagies of <lb/>the larger
            arteries; in any of theſe events, <lb/>it ought to be the buſineſs of practitioners
            <lb/>to endeavour to procure a more effectual <lb/>remedy. But, as the ligature of
            arteries is <pb n="33"/>
            <lb/>very ſimple in its nature; as the pain ari- <lb/>ſing from it is trifling; as few
            inſtances <lb/>occur of any thing bad being produced by <lb/>it; and eſpecially, as,
            when properly per- <lb/>formed, it never fails of proving a ſure <lb/>preventative
            againſt all loſs of blood from <lb/>the larger arteries; there can therefore be <lb/>no
            good reaſon for anxiouſly ſeeking after <lb/>other remedies inſtead of it. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Agaric and other fungous ſubſtances <lb/>have been much extolled for their ſtyptic
            <lb/>powers; and chalybeate ſolutions, as well <lb/>as all the variety of mineral acids,
            have <lb/>in different forms been held forth to the <lb/>public as effectual remedies of
            this nature; <lb/>not only as noſtrums by thoſe of leſs liberal <lb/>principles, but,
            what is more ſurpriſing, in <lb/>ſome inſtances by practitioners of character. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>With the former claſs of men this hap- <lb/>pens as a common occurrence in the
            courſe <lb/>of their profeſſion, and is therefore to be <lb/>expected; but, a
            perſeverance in queſt of <lb/>any new remedy of this kind on the part <lb/>of Surgeons
            of reputation, who are already <lb/>well acquainted with the effects of liga- <pb n="34"/>
            <lb/>tures in caſes of hæmorrhagy, and who <lb/>alſo know that the practice is ſeldom
            at- <lb/>tended with bad conſequences, muſt pro- <lb/>ceed from a degree of nicety and
            refine- <lb/>ment, which may create much trouble to <lb/>themſelves, but which in all
            probability <lb/>can never be productive of any practical <lb/>advantage. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>We ſhall therefore venture to lay it down <lb/>as an eſtabliſhed maxim in ſurgery,
            That in <lb/>every caſe of hæmorrhagy from any of the <lb/>larger arteries, no ſtyptic
            application what- <lb/>ever ought to be truſted to, the ligature <lb/>being the only
            remedy to be depended on. <lb/>We now proceed therefore to the conſidera- <lb/>tion of
            the eaſieſt and moſt effectual mode <lb/>of carrying this application into execution. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Various methods have been invented for <lb/>ſecuring arteries by means of
            ligatures. <lb/>The practice now in ordinary uſe, is, by <lb/>means of a curved needle,
            to paſs a ligature <lb/>of ſufficient ſtrength round the mouth of <lb/>the bleeding
            veſſel, including a quarter of <lb/>an inch all round of the ſurrounding parts <note
              place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.75)">* Sharp's Surgery—On Amputation. </note>, <pb
              n="35"/>
            <lb/>and afterwards to form a knot of a proper <lb/>tightneſs upon the veſſel and other
            parts <lb/>comprehended in the nooſe. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>One great objection, however, to this <lb/>method, is, that the nerves accompanying
            <lb/>the blood-veſſels, together with a conſider- <lb/>able portion of the muſcular
            ſubſtance <lb/>through which they paſs, muſt always be <lb/>ſurrounded with every
            ligature formed in <lb/>this manner. From this circumſtance <lb/>much more pain is
            produced than is neceſ- <lb/>ſary, by the nerves and other parts be- <lb/>ing at the
            ſame time compreſſed with the <lb/>arteries; and, on ſome occaſions, the ſame <lb/>cauſe
            has evidently given riſe to violent <lb/>convulſive affections, not only of the part
            <lb/>chiefly affected, but of the whole ſyſtem. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Spaſmodic twitches are frequently found <lb/>to occur after the amputation of
            limbs, and <lb/>are often the ſource of much diſtreſs. In <lb/>ſome inſtances they are
            no doubt to be <lb/>conſidered as the effect of other cauſes; <lb/>but in various caſes
            it has happened, that <lb/>demonſtrative proof has been obtained of <lb/>their ariſing
            from the ligatures of ar- <pb n="36"/>
            <lb/>teries having been applied in ah improper <lb/>manner. When ſuch convulſive
            affections <lb/>occur after amputations, and the uſual <lb/>means of preventing them
            being found to <lb/>fail, effectual relief may be frequently ob- <lb/>tained by
            deſtroying the ligatures altoge- <lb/>ther, ſo as to remove the compreſſion upon
            <lb/>the nerves; care being taken at the ſame <lb/>time to renew the ligatures upon the
            arte- <lb/>ries immediately, without comprehending <lb/>any of the contiguous parts. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Thus, it is not the ſimple ligature of <lb/>veſſels to which any bad ſymptoms
            occur- <lb/>ring in ſuch caſes are to be attributed; but <lb/>to the operation being
            done in an im- <lb/>proper manner, by including nerves and <lb/>other parts, inſtead of
            tying the arteries by <lb/>themſelves. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Practitioners have commonly been afraid <lb/>of tying up blood-veſſels by
            themſelves <lb/>without the intervention of ſome of the <lb/>ſurrounding parts, on the
            ſuppoſition of <lb/>the coats of arteries not being of a ſuffi- <lb/>cient firmneſs for
            bearing that degree of <pb n="37"/>
            <lb/>compreſſion neceſſary for the prevention <lb/>of hæmorrhagy. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This, however, originates from an idea <lb/>of the coats of arteries not being ſo
            ſtrong <lb/>as they really are, and of a great degree of <lb/>force being neceſſary for
            compreſſing the <lb/>ſides of arteries into cloſe contact with one <lb/>another. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>But it is now well known, that even <lb/>very ſmall arteries are poſſeſſed of much
            <lb/>firmneſs; and it is alſo certain, that even <lb/>in the largeſt arteries of the arm
            or thigh, <lb/>a very ſlight degree of compreſſion is fully <lb/>ſufficient, not only
            for reſtraining hæmor- <lb/>rhagy, but for ſecuring the ligature on the <lb/>very ſpot
            to which it is firſt applied: And <lb/>in ſmall veſſels the force neceſſary for this
            <lb/>purpoſe is trifling indeed; being far leſs <lb/>than is commonly practiſed. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Although the circumſtance we are now <lb/>inſiſting upon may not at firſt ſight
            ſeem <lb/>to be of much importance, yet in fact it <lb/>merits very particular
            attention. Even of <lb/>itſelf it is a matter of no ſmall conſe- <lb/>quence, but it is
            the more material when <pb n="38"/>
            <lb/>we conſider it as'connected in many in- <lb/>ſtances with circumſtances on which
            the <lb/>life of a patient may in a great meaſure <lb/>depend; and we know well too,
            that ſuc- <lb/>ceſs in ſurgical operations depends more <lb/>on a minute attention to
            every circum- <lb/>ſtance relating to them, than on particular <lb/>dexterity in any one
            part of them. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It has alſo been objected to this mode of <lb/>ſecuring blood-veſſels by
            themſelves, that <lb/>the ligatures, although they ſhould not <lb/>cut the arteries
            through, yet are more <lb/>apt to ſlip than when ſome of the ſur- <lb/>rounding parts
            are comprehended along <lb/>with them; and, in ſome inſtances, it is <lb/>ſaid that
            arteries retract ſo far, that they <lb/>cannot in any other way be laid hold of,
            <lb/>than by means of the crooked needle in <lb/>the ordinary method. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Long and repeated experience, however, <lb/>of a few individuals, of this mode of
            ta- <lb/>king up arteries by themſelves, has put <lb/>the fact beyond a doubt, that it
            is equal- <lb/>ly ſecure as any other yet invented <note place="bottom" n="*"
              rend="size(0.75)">* See an eſſay upon this ſubject, by Mr Aitken,
                <lb/><unclear>an</unclear> ingenious ſurgeon of Warrington. </note>.— <pb n="39"/>
            <lb/>Fatal hæmorrhagies after capital opera- <lb/>tions, either from inattention, or
            ſome <lb/>other cauſe, do now and then indeed hap- <lb/>pen in the hands of the moſt
            able practi- <lb/>tioners; but occurrences of this nature <lb/>have as frequently
            happened when the <lb/>curved needle was employed, as when the <lb/>blood-veſſels were
            ſecured by themſelves <lb/>without any of the contiguous parts being <lb/>included. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>From the reſult of my own experience, <lb/>indeed, I mould be induced even from
            <lb/>this conſideration, to draw a concluſion <lb/>in favour of the method we have been
            en- <lb/>deavouring to inculcate. For, in the courſe <lb/>of practice, both among
            hoſpital patients <lb/>and in private, I have known different deaths <lb/>occur from the
            bleeding of ſtumps after <lb/>the amputation of members: Whether this <lb/>proceeded
            from the ligatures having ſlip- <lb/>ped from ſome of the arteries; or that <lb/>ſome of
            the veſſels, from not appearing <lb/>during the operation, had been of courſe
            <lb/>paſſed over without being obſerved and <lb/>had afterwards burſt out, I ſhall not
            pre- <pb n="40"/>
            <lb/>tend to determine; but in all of theſe, <hi rend="italic">the <lb/>crooked needle
              only</hi> had been uſed during <lb/>the operation; and it has ſo happened, <lb/>that I
            never met with a ſingle inſtance of <lb/>a ſimilar occurrence where the arteries
            <lb/>were ſecured by themſelves by means of <lb/><hi rend="italic">the tenaculum</hi>,
            an inſtrument to be after- <lb/>wards taken notice of. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In a few inſtances it may happen, that <lb/>a bleeding veſſel, from lying at the
            bottom <lb/>of a deep wound, cannot be laid hold of <lb/>in any other manner than by the
            curved <lb/>needle being made to paſs round it. Such <lb/>occurrences, however, are
            exceedingly rare; <lb/>inſomuch that I have ſeldom known an <lb/>inſtance in which
            hæmorrhagy could not <lb/>be as effectually reſtrained by the mode <lb/>now to be
            pointed out, as by the uſe of <lb/>the crooked needle. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In all operations whatever, to ſave <hi rend="italic">unne- <lb/>ceſſary</hi> pain
            ought to be a very capital ob- <lb/>ject. In every buſineſs of this kind, the
            <lb/>object in view ought no doubt to be at- <lb/>tained in the moſt complete manner;
            but <lb/>that mode by which we perform an ope- <pb n="41"/>
            <lb/>ration equally well with any other, at the <lb/>ſame time that we ſave a good deal
            of pain <lb/>to the patient, is undoubtedly in every in- <lb/>ſtance to be preferred.
            Now, with reſpect <lb/>to the point in queſtion, as we have al- <lb/>ready clearly
            ſhown, that arteries may be <lb/>tied with as much ſafety in every reſpect, <lb/>by
            themſelves, as when connected with <lb/>any of the neighbouring parts, the <hi
              rend="italic">diffe- <lb/>rence of pain</hi> produced by the two modes <lb/>of
            operating, ought at once to determine <lb/>in favour of the former. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When any of the contiguous parts, par- <lb/>ticularly when the nerves which
            generally <lb/>accompany the blood-veſſels, are included <lb/>in the ſame ligature with
            an artery, and <lb/>which when the curved needle is em- <lb/>ployed is a circumſtance
            ſcarcely to be <lb/>avoided, every practitioner knows that <lb/>tying the knot in this
            manner is fre- <lb/>quently complained of by the patient in <lb/>very ſevere terms. I
            have on many occa- <lb/>ſions known patients, who have bore the <lb/>amputation of
            limbs, and of cancerous <lb/>breaſts, without ſhrinking, complain bit- <pb n="42"/>
            <lb/>terly of the ſevere pain produced by the <lb/>method of ſecuring arteries by means
            of <lb/>the crooked needle. And on the con- <lb/>trary, the pain attending the method
            now <lb/>propoſed, is ſo trifling, that, when pro- <lb/>perly done, even the moſt timid
            patients <lb/>very ſeldom complain of it. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>For ſome time after I firſt began to <lb/>uſe the tenaculum, curioſity induced me,
            <lb/>on different occaſions, to put the matter <lb/>under conſideration to the teſt of
            experi- <lb/>ment: And to render the trial as fair and <lb/>deciſive as poſſible, it was
            always made <lb/>upon the ſame ſubject, under the ſame ope- <lb/>ration. Different
            veſſels were ſecured in <lb/>the ordinary manner by the crooked needle; <lb/>whilſt
            others were laid hold of by the tena- <lb/>culum: But ſo great was the difference in
            <lb/>point of pain, that the one was uniformly <lb/>allowed to give very little
            uneaſineſs; <lb/>whereas it frequently happened, that the <lb/>other was complained of
            as the moſt pain- <lb/>ful part of the whole operation. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Among other advantages which the ty- <lb/>ing of arteries by means of the tenaculum
              <pb n="43"/>
            <lb/>has over the old mode of operating, there <lb/>is ſtill one we have not yet taken
            notice of. <lb/>It often happens after amputations, and <lb/>other operations where the
            larger arteries <lb/>have been tied, that the ligatures do not <lb/>come eaſily away,
            from being made to run <lb/>ſo deep as with the curved needle is com- <lb/>monly
            neceſſary. In ſome inſtances much <lb/>pain and trouble has occurred from this
            <lb/>circumſtance, the ligature remaining quite <lb/>immoveable for a great many weeks:
            And <lb/>after all, I have ſeen it neceſſary for the ſur- <lb/>geon, to put the patient
            to a great deal of <lb/>pain, by being obliged to cutout the threads <lb/>with a
            ſcalpel. But when the tenaculum <lb/>is uſed, every riſk of this kind is effec-
            <lb/>tually avoided, from the ligatures generally <lb/>falling off of their own accord,
            in the <lb/>gourſe of the third or fourth dreſſing of <lb/>the ſore. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>From what has been ſaid, therefore, we <lb/>ſhall conſider it as a practice that
            ought to <lb/>be eſtabliſhed, that in forming the ligature <lb/>of arteries, the <hi
              rend="italic">nerves</hi> and <hi rend="italic">other contiguous <lb/>parts</hi>
            ſhould be carefully avoided. </p>
          <pb n="44"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>For the purpoſe of effecting this with <lb/>eaſe and ſafety, forceps of various
            kinds <lb/>have been invented; with theſe, the arte- <lb/>ries of a ſore are laid hold
            of and pulled <lb/>out, ſo as to admit of the application of <lb/>ligatures. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>For the larger blood-veſſels, the forceps <lb/>have been found to anſwer
            conveniently <lb/>enough; but, in the ſmaller arteries, they <lb/>are by no means ſo fit
            for the purpoſe as <lb/>the curved hook commonly termed a te- <lb/>naculum, as
            repreſented in Plate I. And as <lb/>a hook of this form anſwers equally well <lb/>in the
            larger arteries likewiſe, the uſe of <lb/>the forceps may therefore be laid entirely
            <lb/>aſide. The manner of uſing the tenacu- <lb/>lum is this. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In order to detect the arteries to be <lb/>tied, the tourniquet with which they are
            <lb/>ſecured, muſt be ſlackened a little by a <lb/>turn or two of the ſcrew; and the
            moment <lb/>the largeſt artery of the ſore is diſcovered, <lb/>the ſurgeon fixes his eye
            upon it, and im- <lb/>mediately reſtrains the blood again by <lb/>means of the
            tourniquet. An aſſiſtant <pb n="45"/>
            <lb/>now forms a nooſe on the ligature to be <lb/>made uſe of; and this nooſe being
            placed <lb/>immediately over the end of the artery, <lb/>ſo as to include it with
            certainty, the <lb/>operator then puſhes the ſharp point of <lb/>the tenaculum through
            the ſides of the <lb/>veſſel, and at the ſame time pulls ſo much <lb/>of it out, over
            the ſurface of the ſurround- <lb/>ing parts, as he thinks is ſufficient to be
            <lb/>included in the knot which the aſſiſtant is <lb/>now to make. In forming this
            ligature, <lb/>the ſurgeon's knot, as it is termed, which <lb/>conſiſts in paſſing the
            thread twice thro' <lb/>the firſt nooſe, is certainly preferable to <lb/>every other,
            from its being leſs liable to <lb/>yield or flip. And as ſome additional ſe- <lb/>curity
            is obtained by forming a ſecond knot <lb/>above the firſt, this precaution ought never
            <lb/>to be omitted. It is eaſily done; and on <lb/>ſecurity in this point, the patient's
            life may <lb/>in a great meaſure depend. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The degree of ſtrength of the ligature <lb/>muſt always be proportioned to the ſize
            of <lb/>the veſſels; but this is a circumſtance to be <lb/>at all times determined by
            the judgment <pb n="46"/>
            <lb/>of the practitioner, as muſt alſo the force <lb/>to be employed in forming the
            knots. To <lb/>what was already ſaid upon this point I <lb/>ſhall juſt add, that a very
            ſmall force is fully <lb/>ſufficient for ſecuring even the largeſt ar- <lb/>teries 5 and
            that, after ſuch a force has been <lb/>applied as evidently reſtrains the farther loſs
            <lb/>of blood, a very trifling additional compreſ- <lb/>ſion is all that is in any
            degree neceſſary. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The principal artery being in this man- <lb/>ner ſecured, all the veſſels of the
            part <lb/>muſt one after another be taken up in the <lb/>fame manner, by firſt looſening
            the tour- <lb/>niquet in order to diſcover them, and <lb/>afterwards applying the
            ligature to each in <lb/>the manner directed. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It often happens, however, that the loſs <lb/>of blood the patient has ſuſtained, a
            ten- <lb/>dency to deliquium which may take place <lb/>for the time, the fear he labours
            under, and <lb/>the degree of cold to which the ſore is ex- <lb/>poſed, have all
            together ſuch an effect upon <lb/>the ſmaller arteries, as to prevent them for <lb/>the
            time from diſcharging their contents, <lb/>and as arteries left in ſuch a ſtate without
              <pb n="47"/>
            <lb/>being ſecured, generally burſt out on the <lb/>removal of theſe cauſes, a
            circumſtance <lb/>which always occaſions much trouble to <lb/>the practitioner, as well
            as a great deal of <lb/>pain to the patient, every ſurgeon there- <lb/>fore ought to pay
            the niceſt attention to <lb/>this point. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The tourniquet ſhould be made perfect- <lb/>ly looſe; any coagulated blood on the
            ſur- <lb/>face of the ſore, ought to be carefully waſh- <lb/>ed off with a ſpunge and
            warm water; and <lb/>the patient, if faintiſh, ought to get a <lb/>glaſs of wine, or
            ſome other cordial; and <lb/>after all, the ſurgeon ought to examine, <lb/>with the moſt
            minute attention, the uſual <lb/>courſe which the veſſels of the part are <lb/>known to
            take. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This being done, every artery of the part, <lb/>even the ſmalleſt that can be
            diſtinguiſhed, <lb/>ought to be ſecured with a ligature: For <lb/>ſuch veſſels as appear
            exceedingly trifling <lb/>while the part is yet expoſed to the air, <lb/>after the
            patient becomes warm in bed, <lb/>when of courſe the ſolids become relaxed, <lb/>and the
            fluids expand, even the ſmalleſt <pb n="48"/>
            <lb/>branches of arteries that happen to be <lb/>neglected, will now be capable of
            produ- <lb/>cing much miſchief, by diſcharging very <lb/>conſiderable quantities of
            blood; and, as <lb/>little or no injury can ever occur by the <lb/>proper application of
            ligatures to all the <lb/>arteries that preſent themſelves, the greateſt <lb/>attention
            ought at all times to be paid to <lb/>this circumſtance. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>I have inſiſted the more on this, from <lb/>having frequently obſerved much un-
            <lb/>eaſineſs and diſtreſs produced by a want <lb/>of proper attention to this part of
            an ope- <lb/>ration. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When the principal arteries of a ſtump <lb/>have been taken up, and a little blood
            <lb/>continues to be diſcharged, but appears to <lb/>come from ſundry ſmall veſſels
            only, the <lb/>ſurgeon, unleſs he is much accuſtomed to <lb/>this kind of buſineſs, is
            induced to think, <lb/>that as they are very trifling to appear- <lb/>ance, ſo he need
            not be at the trouble of <lb/>tying them, as the neceſſary compreſſion <lb/>of the
            bandages proper for the wound will <lb/>in all probability effect a total ſtoppage of
              <pb n="49"/>
            <lb/>the hæmorrhagy. In a general oozing of a <lb/>ſmall quantity of blood from the
            whole <lb/>ſurface of a ſore, and when no particular <lb/>veſſel can be diſtinguiſhed,
            there is a neceſ- <lb/>ſity for truſting to this remedy; but, when- <lb/>ever an artery
            can be diſcovered, of what- <lb/>ever ſize it may be, it ought unqueſtionably <lb/>to be
            ſecured by a ligature. It very rarely <lb/>happens that any inconvenience occurs
            <lb/>from ligatures when properly applied; but <lb/>many lives have been loſt from a
            remiſſneſs <lb/>in this article. I have known different in- <lb/>ſtances of this, and
            the ſame muſt have oc- <lb/>curred to others. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When, from the deepneſs of a wound, or <lb/>from any other cauſe, ſome particular
            ar- <lb/>tery cannot be properly ſecured by the <lb/>tenaculum, in this caſe we are
            under the <lb/>neceſſity of employing the crooked needle, <lb/>and the following is the
            mode of uſing it. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The operator ought to be provided with <lb/>needles of various ſizes, and of
            different <lb/>forms. The needles in ordinary uſe, are <lb/>for many purpoſes quite too
            much crooked; <lb/>for, in general, they are mope eaſily ma- <pb n="50"/>
            <lb/>naged when their curvatures are not ſo <lb/>conſiderable. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The ſame kinds of needles as are found <lb/>neceſſary for the interrupted ſuture,
            as re- <lb/>preſented in Plate I. anſwer equally well <lb/>for the ligature of arteries. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The needles in common uſe are made <lb/>triangular, with three different edges, one
            <lb/>on each ſide, and a third on the concave <lb/>part of the needle. There is no real
            ne- <lb/>ceſſity, however, for more than two: In- <lb/>deed the needle enters fully more
            eaſily <lb/>with two than with three edges; and as the <lb/>third edge on the concave
            ſide, renders <lb/>them more liable to injure arteries and <lb/>other parts in the
            courſe of their introduc- <lb/>tion, this addition ought therefore to be <lb/>omitted. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>A needle of this ſhape, armed with a li- <lb/>gature of a ſize proportioned to
            itſelf and <lb/>to the veſſel to be taken up, is to be intro- <lb/>duced at the diſtance
            of a ſixth or eighth <lb/>part of an inch from the artery, and puſhed <lb/>to a depth
            ſufficient for retaining it, at the <lb/>ſame time that it is carried fully one- <pb
              n="51"/>
            <lb/>half round the blood-veſſel. It muſt now <lb/>be drawn out; and being again puſhed
            <lb/>forward till it has completely encircled <lb/>the mouth of the artery, it is then
            to be <lb/>pulled out, and a knot to be tied of a ſuffi- <lb/>cient firmneſs, as was
            already directed when <lb/>the tenaculum is uſed. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In this manner, either by the uſe of the <lb/>crooked needle, or of the tenaculum,
            every <lb/>hæmorrhagy depending upon a diviſion of <lb/>one or more large arteries, may
            in general <lb/>be very eaſily reſtrained; but it frequently <lb/>happens, that
            conſiderable quantities of <lb/>blood are diſcharged, not from any parti- <lb/>cular
            veſſel, but from all the ſmall arteries <lb/>over the ſurface of the ſore. In wounds of
            <lb/>great extent, particularly after the extir- <lb/>pation of cancerous breaſts, and
            in other <lb/>operations where extenſive ſores are left, <lb/>this ſpecies of hæmorrhagy
            often proves <lb/>very troubleſome by being exceedingly dif- <lb/>ficult to ſuppreſs. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Bleedings of this kind ſeem evidently to <lb/>proceed from two very different and
            oppo- <lb/>ſite cauſes; a circumſtance which, in the <pb n="52"/>
            <lb/>treatment of them, is a matter of much <lb/>importance to attend to. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sc">Firſt</hi>, We now and then find effuſions of <lb/>this nature
            occurring in ſtrong robuſt people, <lb/>where they evidently proceed, either from
            <lb/>too great a quantity of blood contained in <lb/>the veſſels, or from an over degree
            of tone <lb/>in the veſſels themſelves; or, perhaps, from <lb/>a combination of both
            theſe cauſes. But, <lb/><hi rend="sc">Secondly</hi>, Such evacuations undoubtedly
            <lb/>happen moſt frequently in conſtitutions <lb/>quite the reverſe of the former, viz.
            in ſuch <lb/>as are very relaxed and debilitated; either <lb/>from a putrid diſſolved
            ſtate of the blood, <lb/>or from a want of tone in the containing <lb/>veſſels, or in
            ſome inſtances from a con- <lb/>currence of both. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In conſtitutions perfectly healthy, when <lb/>the fluids are not tainted with any
            degree <lb/>of putreſcency, and the ſolids are poſſeſſed <lb/>of their natural tonic
            powers, on the oc- <lb/>currence of wounds even of the moſt ex- <lb/>tenſive nature, ſo
            ſoon as the larger arteries <lb/>are ſecured, all the ſmall veſſels that have <lb/>been
            divided, in conſequence of that con- <pb n="53"/>
            <lb/>tractile power with which in a ſtate of <lb/>health they are endowed, and from the
            ſti- <lb/>mulus of the external air to which they are <lb/>now expoſed, are diminiſhed
            not only in <lb/>their diameters, but alſo in their length; in <lb/>conſequence of
            which, they recede conſi- <lb/>derably within the ſurface of the ſurround- <lb/>ing
            parts. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This cauſe of itſelf would probably in <lb/>the greateſt number of inſtances prove
            ſuf- <lb/>ficient for reſtraining all loſs of blood <lb/>from the ſmaller arteries; but,
            in the ſound <lb/>ſtate of conſtitution of which we have now <lb/>been ſpeaking, another
            very powerful agent <lb/>is provided by nature for producing the <lb/>fame effect. From
            the extremities of the <lb/>divided veſſels which at firſt diſcharged <lb/>red blood
            only, there now, in their con- <lb/>tracted ſtate, oozes out a more thin, though
            <lb/>viſcid fluid, containing a great proportion <lb/>of the coagulable parts of the
            blood; and <lb/>this being equally diſtributed over the ſur- <lb/>face of the wound, by
            its balſamic agglu- <lb/>tinating powers, has undoubtedly a very <pb n="54"/>
            <lb/>conſiderable influence in reſtraining all ſuch <lb/>hæmorrhagies. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In conſtitutions altogether healthy, where <lb/>neither of the ſtates of diſeaſe we
            have al- <lb/>luded to preponderates over the other, we <lb/>find, that, ſo ſoon as the
            larger arteries of <lb/>wounds are ſecured, nature, in the manner <lb/>already
            deſcribed, generally puts a ſtop to <lb/>all farther diſcharge. So that, whenever the
            <lb/>contrary happens, by a tedious oozing con- <lb/>tinuing from the ſurface of the
            ſore, we <lb/>ought then to pay particular attention to <lb/>the habit of body with
            which it is connec- <lb/>ted. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When ſuch an occurrence happens in a <lb/>patient, young and vigorous, and where
            <lb/>the tone of the muſcular fibres is evident- <lb/>ly great, the moſt effectual means
            of putting <lb/>a ſtop to the diſcharge, is to relax the <lb/>vaſcular ſyſtem, either by
            opening a vein <lb/>in ſome other part, or, what gives ſtill more <lb/>immediate relief,
            by untying the ligature <lb/>on one of the principal arteries of the part, <lb/>ſo as to
            allow it to bleed freely: Thoſe vio- <lb/>lent ſpaſmodic twitchings too, ſo frequent <pb
              n="55"/>
            <lb/>after operations on any of the extremities, <lb/>when they do not depend on a nerve
            being <lb/>included in the ligature with the artery, <lb/>are in this manner more
            effectually re- <lb/>lieved than by any other means. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>By the ſame means, the patient, from <lb/>being in a febrile heat and much
            confuſed, <lb/>ſoon becomes very tranquil: The violent <lb/>pulſation of the heart and
            larger arteries <lb/>abates, and, the blood not being pro- <lb/>pelled with ſuch
            impetuoſity into the <lb/>ſmaller veſſels of the part, they are thereby <lb/>left at
            more liberty to retract; and as in <lb/>this ſtate they do not pour forth red blood
            <lb/>ſo freely, they are the more readily covered <lb/>with that viſcid glutinous fluid
            which we <lb/>have already ſhown to be one of the moſt <lb/>important means intended by
            nature for <lb/>the prevention of ſuch hæmorrhagies. At <lb/>the ſame time that by the
            means recom- <lb/>mended we endeavour to allay the com- <lb/>motion produced in the
            ſyſtem, the patient <lb/>ought to be kept exceedingly cool; wine <lb/>and other cordials
            ſhould be rigidly avoid- <lb/>ed; cold water, acidulated either with the <pb n="56"/>
            <lb/>mineral or vegetable acids, ought to be the <lb/>only drink; motion of every kind,
            par- <lb/>ticularly of the part affected, ſhould be <lb/>guarded againſt; and the wound
            being <lb/>gently covered with ſoft charpie, ought <lb/>to be tied up with a bandage ſo
            applied <lb/>as to produce a moderate degree of preſ- <lb/>ſure on the extremities of
            the divided <lb/>parts. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In every extenſive wound attended with <lb/>hæmorrhagies of this kind, and
            particularly <lb/>when violent ſpaſmodic affections of the <lb/>muſcles ſupervene,
            together with the means <lb/>already recommended, large doſes of opi- <lb/>ates are
            found highly beneficial; for what- <lb/>ever hurtful effects may have been appre-
            <lb/>hended from opiates in ſome inflamma- <lb/>tory affections, every practitioner who
            has <lb/>ventured on a free uſe of them muſt ad- <lb/>mit, that in all occurrences of
            this nature <lb/>their influence far ſurpaſſes that of any <lb/>other remedy. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>So ſoon therefore as a ſufficient quantity of <lb/>blood has been diſcharged, and
            the wound <lb/>being dreſſed and the patient laid to reſt, <pb n="57"/>
            <lb/>a doſe of opium proportioned to the vio- <lb/>lence of the ſymptoms ought to be
            imme- <lb/>diately exhibited. It ought to be remark- <lb/>ed however, that, in all ſuch
            circumſtan- <lb/>ces, much larger doſes of the remedy <lb/>are neceſſary, than in
            ordinary caſes re- <lb/>quiring the uſe of opiates. Small doſes, <lb/>inſtead of
            anſwering any good purpoſe, <lb/>ſeem frequently rather to aggravate the <lb/>various
            ſymptoms; ſo that, whenever they <lb/>are here had recourſe to, they ought always
            <lb/>to be given in quantities ſufficient for the <lb/>intended effect. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Although hæmmorrhagies of this nature <lb/>do now and then occur in firm vigorous
            <lb/>conſtitutions; yet they undoubtedly happen <lb/>much more frequently in relaxed
            enfeebled <lb/>habits, where the ſolids have loſt part of their <lb/>natural firmneſs,
            and the fluids have acqui- <lb/>red ſome degree of putreſcency. As the <lb/>veſſels in
            this ſituation of matters are ſup- <lb/>poſed to have been deprived of that degree
            <lb/>of tone of which we wiſh them to be poſſeſ- <lb/>ſed, inſtead of reſtraining the
            patient from <lb/>the uſe of cordials, as is done uſually <hi rend="italic">in <pb
                n="58"/>
              <lb/>every caſe of hamorrhagy</hi>, a moderate uſe <lb/>of generous wine ought to be
            immediately <lb/>preſcribed; for nothing, it may be obſer- <lb/>ved, tends ſo much in
            ſuch circumſtances <lb/>to reſtrain hæmorrhagies, as a well-directed <lb/>uſe of proper
            cordials. By tending to in- <lb/>vigorate and brace the ſolids, they thereby <lb/>enable
            the arterial ſyſtem to give a due <lb/>reſiſtance to the contained fluids; and the
            <lb/>ſame cauſe, it may be obſerved, has a conſi- <lb/>derable influence in reſtoring to
            the fluids <lb/>that viſcidity of texture, of which in all ſuch <lb/>inſtances we
            ſuppoſe them to be deprived. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Whenever, therefore, ſuch tedious hæmor- <lb/>rhagies occur in relaxed debilitated
            habits, <lb/>a free uſe of Port, Madeira, or any other <lb/>wine whoſe ſtrength and
            goodneſs can be <lb/>depended on, ought to be immediately <lb/>allowed; a nouriſhing
            diet alſo becomes <lb/>proper; the patient ought to be kept cool; <lb/>and the mineral
            acids, from their known <lb/>utility in every ſpecies of hæmorrhagy, <lb/>ought alſo to,
            be preſcribed. Reſt of body <lb/>is here proper too; and opiates, when in- <lb/>dicated,
            either by pain or ſpaſmodic affec- <pb n="59"/>
            <lb/>tions of the muſcles, ought never to be <lb/>omitted. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Together with theſe remedies adapted <lb/>to the general ſyſtem, particular
            dreſſings, <lb/>appropriated to the ſtate of the parts to <lb/>which they are to be
            applied, have been <lb/>found very beneficial. We have already <lb/>remarked, that in
            firm healthy conſtitu- <lb/>tions, ſo ſoon as the diſcharge of blood <lb/>which
            naturally occurs in every large <lb/>wound is over, the parts come ſoon to be
            <lb/>covered with a viſcid coagulable effuſion <lb/>from the mouths of the now retracted
            ar- <lb/>teries; but in conſtitutions of an oppoſite <lb/>nature, where the ſolids are
            much relaxed, <lb/>the blood in general is found in ſuch a <lb/>diſſolved ſtate as to
            afford no ſecretion of <lb/>this nature. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In order therefore to ſupply as much as <lb/>poſſible the deficiency of this
            natural bal- <lb/>ſam, different artificial applications have <lb/>been invented.
            Duſting the parts with <lb/>ſtarch or wheat flour, has ſometimes been <lb/>found of uſe;
            and I have known gum <pb n="60"/>
            <lb/>arabic in fine powder to anſwer when <lb/>theſe have failed. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Applications of this kind, indeed, have <lb/>been uſed with ſucceſs in all ſuch
            hæmor- <lb/>rhagies, with whatever habit of body they <lb/>happen to be connected; but
            they have al- <lb/>ways proved more particularly ſerviceable <lb/>in relaxed
            conſtitutions, attended with a <lb/>diſſolved ſtate of the blood and an enfeebled
            <lb/>muſcular ſyſtem. We may here uſe with <lb/>freedom too, a remedy which in ſuch cir-
            <lb/>cumſtances generally proves ſerviceable, <lb/>but which in conſtitutions of an
            oppoſite <lb/>nature ought never to be employed. The <lb/>remedy alluded to is alcohol,
            or any other <lb/>ardent ſpirits, impregnated with as great a <lb/>quantity as they can
            diſſolve of myrrh or <lb/>any other of the heating viſcid gums. The <lb/>balſamum
            traumaticum of the ſhops, a reme- <lb/>dy of this nature, has long been famous for
            <lb/>its influence in ſuch caſes, but that indiſcri- <lb/>minate uſe of this and ſimilar
            applications <lb/>which has long prevailed with ſome prac- <lb/>titioners, I am
            confident has done much <lb/>harm; for, as they are all poſſeſſed of very <pb n="61"/>
            <lb/>ſtimulating powers, they of courſe tend to <lb/>aggravate every ſymptom in wounds
            con- <lb/>nected with a tenſe ſtate of fibres, when much <lb/>pain, and eſpecially when
            ſpaſmodic muſcu- <lb/>lar affections, prevail. But, in conſtitutions <lb/>of an oppoſite
            nature, where the blood ap- <lb/>pears to be in a diſſolved ſtate, and where <lb/>the
            arterial ſyſtem ſeems evidently to re- <lb/>quire a ſtimulus, remedies of this claſs
            come <lb/>to be very uſeful: Inſomuch that, in every <lb/>conſtitution of this kind
            where hæmor- <lb/>rhagies prove troubleſome, no application <lb/>whatever is found to
            anſwer better, than <lb/>charpie immerſed in an agglutinating <lb/>ſpirituous balſam of
            this nature. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>By a due perſeverance in one or other of <lb/>the plans here pointed out, it will
            ſeldom <lb/>happen that hæmorrhagies of this nature <lb/>are not at laſt put a ſtop to:
            But when <lb/>the contrary does occur; when, notwith- <lb/>ſtanding the uſe of the
            remedies recom- <lb/>mended, a diſcharge of blood ſtill conti- <lb/>nues; together with
            the means already ad- <lb/>viſed, an equal moderate preſſure ought to <lb/>be applied
            over the whole ſurface of the <pb n="62"/>
            <lb/>ſore, to be continued ſo long as the neceſſity <lb/>of the caſe ſeems to indicate. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In finiſhing the dreſſings of ſuch wounds, <lb/>after the charpie and compreſſes
            have been <lb/>applied, a bandage properly adapted to <lb/>the part ought to conclude
            the whole, and <lb/>in ſuch a manner as to produce as equal <lb/>a degree of preſſure
            over the ſurface of the <lb/>ſore as poſſible. But it now and then hap- <lb/>pens, that
            no bandage whatever can be ſo <lb/>applied, as to produce the deſired effect; <lb/>and
            in ſuch caſes, the hand of an aſſiſtant <lb/>is the only reſource. In ſuch inſtances, a
            <lb/>perſon's hand being firmly applied over the <lb/>dreſſings, ſo as to produce a very
            equal <lb/>degree of preſſure, will commonly ſucceed <lb/>when no other remedy is found
            to have <lb/>much influence. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Having thus endeavoured to point out <lb/>the moſt effectual means of putting a
            ſtop <lb/>to morbid hæmorrhagies, we ſhall now <lb/>proceed to conſider the different
            modes <lb/>employed by art, for effecting a diſcharge <lb/>of blood when indicated by
            the preſence of <lb/>ſome diſorder in the conſtitution. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="497"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
