<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Cruikshank: The Anatomy of the Absorbing Vessels of the Human
          Body.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>William Cruikshank</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">The anatomy of the absorbing vessels of the human body.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T63442</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T63442"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for G. Nicol, Bookseller to His Majesty, in the Strand,
                  M.DCC.LXXXVI. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1786</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="13"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="192"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="8"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107888178</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Surgical or anatominal work"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="13"/>
      <pb n=""/>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="sc align-center space">
          <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">PART II. </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="space">containing </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="space">A DESCRIPTION OF THE SITUATION AND NUMBER OF <lb/>THE ABSORBENT
            GLANDS, </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="space">and of the </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="space">PARTICULAR DISTRIBUTION OF THE ABSORBING VESSELS <lb/>THEMSELVES, </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="space">IN THE HUMAN BODY. </hi>
        </head>
        <pb n="117"/>
        <div type="chapter" subtype="introduction">
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal double-line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
          <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="3"> </space>
          <head rend="sc size(1.5) align-center">
            <lb/>INTRODUCTION to PART II. </head>
          <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE blood-veſſels of the human body have been frequently and
            <lb/>accurately deſcribed by authors. The anatomiſts who have de- <lb/>ſcribed parts of
            the abſorbent ſyſtem are alſo neither few nor obſcure; <lb/>but the ſubject is really
            difficult; they have not hit on the proper <lb/>methods of inveſtigation; they had not
            the advantages of proper ſub- <lb/>jects, and proper inſtruments; they were not
            ſufficiently maſters of <lb/>their own time; they did not live to accompliſh what they
            had begun; <lb/>or they laid before the public the produce of a fertile imagination, in
            the <lb/>place of a true deſcription. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>I have, in another part of this treatiſe, already mentioned the firſt <lb/>writers
            on the abſorbents; and the' reader is ſuppoſed to be acquainted <lb/>with Aſellius,
            Veflingius, Rudbeck, and Bartholine. Their united la- <lb/>bours amounted to little more
            than the diſcovery of the lacteals, ſome <lb/>lymphatics of the liver and teſticle, with
            the thoracic duct. Nor does <lb/>any body appear, for a long time after, to have added
            any thing to their <lb/>ſtock of knowledge. If I afterwards make it appear, that ſome
            other <lb/>parts of this ſyſtem were known, yet, as this knowledge was not ge-
            <lb/>neral, but confined to private ſocieties or perſons, and formed what <lb/>Haller
            would call crepuſculæ lymphaticorum, it will not invalidate <lb/>the general aſſertion I
            have now made. Haller knew all theſe facts I <lb/>allude to; yet he ſays, <q
              rend="quotes">Poſt ea tempora, diu nihil acceſſit, &amp; multum <lb/>hæc hiſtoria
              etiam nunc a perfectione abeſt, neque in omnibus parti- <lb/>bus corporis animalis hæc
              vaſa demonſtrata ſunt, neque ſyſtema ab- <lb/>ſolutum eſt, quale ad arterias corporis
              humani poſſidemus. Multæ <lb/>enim partes corporis ſunt, in quibus vaſa lymphatica
              nemo vidit, aliæ <lb/>ubi &amp; raro quiſquam, &amp; cum dubio aliquo. Ad alia enim
              inciſores <pb n="118"/>
              <lb/>ſe converterunt, eorumque labores rei difficultas vicit. </q> — We have,
            <lb/>indeed, been informed, that Nuck had traced the abſorbents over the <lb/>whole
            body; that he had engraved the appearances, and was going to <lb/>publiſh them, when he
            was prematurely cut off. <q rend="quotes">Plura promiſerat <lb/>Antonius Nuck, &amp;
              poterat de ejus viri induſtria magna inciſorum <lb/>expectatio eſſe. Integrum enim
              vaſorum lymphaticorum ſyſtema amal- <lb/>gamate repletum ſiccaverat, fed pertinacem in
              eo labore virum, &amp; <lb/>per plura animalia ſua vaſcula perſequentem, mors ante
              diem abſtulit. <lb/>Ad ea quæ edidit, utique brutis animalibus uſum eſſe conſtat, vel
              cordis <lb/>exemplo. Non ideo tamen vir. cl. aut J. Henrici Schulzii acerbam
              <lb/>accuſationem meritus eſt, aut Laurentii Heiſteri cenſuram, qui tabulas <lb/>hujus
              viri pro fictitiis habent. Ipſe enim teſtimonium pro Nuckio <lb/>dixit Hermannus
              Boerhaave, tabulaſque vaſorum lymphaticorum vidit, <lb/>quæ argento vivo repleta vir
              induſtrius continuata ſiccaverat. </q>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>I ſhould be exceedingly ſorry to detract from the reputation of any
            <lb/>induſtrious anatomiſt; but the appearances he has cauſed to be engraved <lb/>are
            not like what I have ſeen. It is very evident, that he ſometimes <lb/>deſcribed from the
            quadruped; it is to me alſo very evident, that he <lb/>deſcribes from his own
            imagination. He is right in deſcribing the ab- <lb/>ſorbent glands as cellular; but
            neither his engravings of thoſe glands, <lb/>nor ſome others that I have ſeen, very much
            reſembling them, are ac- <lb/>cording to nature. Haller, indeed, ſays of him, <q
              rend="quotes">Pari facilitate vaſa <lb/>lymphatica oſtendebat ut alii rubra, </q> and
            that he injected theſe in <lb/>vacuo: <q rend="quotes">Antlia pneumatica ad eum ſcopum
              uſum fuiſſe. </q> — He alſo <lb/>informs us, that he made uſe of an amalgam of
            quickſilver. This does <lb/>not correſpond, however, with what he afterwards ſays: <q
              rend="quotes">Nuckium <lb/>adipe aliquo argentum vivum coegiſſe. </q> This mixture
            would not paſs <lb/>into the abſorbent veſſels readily, in the way we now inject: I
            cannot <lb/>ſay what might happen, if the veſſels were injected in vacuo; but I
            <lb/>have a great many doubts on this ſubject. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Some attempts have ſince that period been made, and ſome things have <lb/>been
            added to the hiſtory of the abſorbents, by Mekel, Hewſon, and <lb/>Haller; but the
            deſcription is ſtill incomplete, as Haller himſelf con- <lb/>feſſes: <q rend="quotes"
              >III. Meckelius paſſim ad eorum hiſtoriam aliqua addidit,. tum <lb/>Alexander Monro
              fil. &amp; potiſſimum Guil. Hewſon, qui multas novas <lb/>ex humano corpore tabulas
              dedit, etiam in artubus, &amp; in his non ſola <pb n="119"/>
              <lb/>cuti vicina vaſa, fed etiam profunda, neque prius dicta. Sparſim &amp; <lb/>ego,
              &amp; in hominum cadaveribus, &amp; in vivis animalibus, vaſa lym- <lb/>phatica &amp;
              vidi, &amp; perſecutus ſum. Plurima tamen ubique deſunt, neque <lb/>in artubus, aut
              dorſo, aut interiori capite ea vaſcula hactenus ſatis <lb/>certo viſa ſunt, neaque
              conſtitutæ radices aut extremi termini. </q>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/> The deſcription of the abſorbent ſyſtem I am about to give, is in moſt <lb/>things
            the ſame with that which I gave at lectures twelve or thirteen <lb/>years ago, as I
            formerly obſerved, particularly that of the abſorbents of <lb/>the liver, and of the
            lungs, and pancreas, which were not known to <lb/>Dr. Hunter himſelf; the laſt,
            particularly, neither to Haller nor Mr. <lb/>Hewfon. Every year I added ſuch varieties
            as I had diſcovered. Moſt of <lb/>the pupils at Windmill Street took notes; and copies
            of my deſcription <lb/>are in the hands of a vaſt number of ſtudents. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>I have uſed, in the Firſt Part of this treatiſe, the terms <hi rend="italic"
              >lacteals</hi> and <lb/><hi rend="italic">lymphatics</hi>, inſtead of <hi
              rend="italic">abſorbents</hi>, in order to avoid all ambiguity con- <lb/>cerning the
            veſſels meant; but, having there diſproved abſorption by red <lb/>veins, I cannot now be
            miſapprehended, and ſhall in future employ the <lb/>term <hi rend="italic"
              >abſorbents</hi>, to ſignify <hi rend="italic">lacteals</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
              >lymphatics</hi>; and ſhall write <hi rend="italic">glands of <lb/>the abſorbents</hi>
            inſtead of <hi rend="italic">lymphatic glands</hi>. I muſt alſo remark, that neither
            <lb/>the glands of the abſorbents, nor their veſſels, are ſo conſtant in their ſitua-
            <lb/>tion and diſtribution as the arteries; in which reſpect they reſemble the <lb/>red
            veins. I have here deſcribed them as I found them moſt frequently. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Another general obſervation I wiſh alſo to premiſe is, that, indepen- <lb/>dent of
            thoſe abſorbents which accompany the arteries, and which are <lb/>uſually one on each
            ſide, there is on the extremities a ſet of cutaneous <lb/>abſorbents, accompanying the
            larger trunks of the cutaneous veins, as <lb/>the ſaphena major and minor, in the lower
            extremity; the baſilic and <lb/>cephalic veins, in the upper extremity. There is alſo on
            the viſcera <lb/>commonly a ſuperficial and a deep-ſeated ſet; the firſt run by
            themſelves, <lb/>on the ſurfaces of the viſcera; the ſecond accompany the principal
            blood- <lb/>veſſels of the viſcera, and ramify in the ſame manner. This diſtinction
            <lb/>takes place even amongſt the abſorbents of the inteſtines themſelves. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Previous to the deſcription of the veſſels, I have thought proper to <lb/>deſcribe
            the number and ſituation of the glands of the abſorbents, as they <lb/>are more eaſily
            diſcovered. By this means I ſhall give an outline of the <pb n="120"/>
            <lb/>ſyſtem, which will facilitate afterwards the deſcription of the veſſels
            <lb/>themſelves. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Many of theſe glands, from their bulk, may be diſcovered under <lb/>the
            integuments, both by the eye and by the touch. When they are <lb/>ſwelled or indurated,
            they are ſtill more eaſily diſcovered; and in the <lb/>dead body, diſſection, with the
            utmoſt facility, diſcovers them in all <lb/>the other parts where they exiſt. Both in
            the deſcription of the glands <lb/>and of the veſſels, I ſhall begin at the greateſt
            diſtance from the termi- <lb/>nations of the ſyſtem; viz. the angles of the jugular and
            ſubclavian <lb/>veins, and follow the courſe of the abſorbed fluids moving in their
            <lb/>veſſels: conſequently, I begin with the lower extremity. I have quoted <lb/>Haller
            very often, not only becauſe I conſider him as the beſt anatomi- <lb/>cal author, on the
            whole, that we have, but alſo becauſe I find the <lb/>anatomical knowledge of all his
            predeceſſors collected in his writings. <lb/>He does not appear to have done much in
            this ſyſtem himſelf; but he <lb/>knows every thing that has been done by his
            predeceſſors and cotem- <lb/>poraries. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="121"/>
        <div type="chapter">
          <figure>
            <figDesc>A horizontal double-line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
          <head rend="sc align-center space">
            <lb/>A <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">DESCRIPTION </hi>
            <lb/>of the situation and number of the <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">GLANDS of the
              ABSORBENTS. </hi>
          </head>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>A long horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
          <div type="section">
            <head rend="sc size(1.25) align-center">
              <lb/>THE POPLITEAL GLANDS. </head>
            <p rend="space">
              <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> Have not ſeen any glands in the lower extremity, below
              the ham. <lb/>Haller makes a ſimilar obſervation: <q rend="quotes">Senſim rariores
                factæ in <lb/>poplite fere deſinunt, cum in tibia, fibula, pedeque nullæ mihi un-
                <lb/>quam occurrerint. </q> — Mr. Hewſon deſcribes and delineates one very
              <lb/>ſmall gland a little below the middle of the tibia, on the fore part of <lb/>that
              bone, between it and the external integuments; but I have never <lb/>once met with it;
              and would therefore conſider it as a kind of luſus <lb/>naturæ. Dr. Hunter once found
              the glands even of the ham wanting. <lb/>This circumſtance alſo I never met with.
              There are ſeldom more than <lb/>three; they lie cloſe upon the popliteal artery; and,
              though ſmall, are <lb/>by no means, as Haller ſays, <q rend="quotes">uti ultimæ
                conglobatarum, ita minimæ. </q>
              <lb/>There are many on the meſocolon, and in a variety of other places, <lb/>much
              ſmaller than they are. They ſwell from ſores on the outſide of <lb/>the foot, in the
              ſole of the foot, and from ſores of the integuments on <lb/>the calf of the leg. Dr.
              Hunter mentioned a caſe of a patient who was <lb/>bit by a mad dog in the calf of the
              leg: the ſore healed at firſt, but <lb/>ſome weeks after broke out again. Red lines
              were perceived running <lb/>upward from the ſore, with the ſaphena minor, which dipt
              down in the <lb/>ham, and were loſt. They were inflamed lymphatics going to thoſe
              <lb/>glands. </p>
          </div>
          <pb n="122"/>
          <div type="section">
            <head rend="align-center">
              <lb/>THE INGUINAL GLANDS. </head>
            <p rend="space indent">
              <lb/>THE glands of the groin are of an uncertain number, from eight, <lb/>ten, or
              twelve, to twenty or more. Haller makes them only four. <lb/>
              <q rend="quotes">Illas cum plures eſſe credidiſſem, accuratius numerans, quatuor in-
                <lb/>veni; octo faciebat Whartonus. </q> They are ſituated, principally, above
              <lb/>the faſcia of the thigh, though ſeveral of them lie under it. Theſe laſt are
              <lb/>placed on the iliacus internus muſcle, between the triceps and ſartorius.
              <lb/>Sometimes ſeveral of theſe glands are collected into one large one, which
              <lb/>lies on the upper ſide of the inguinal artery. Thoſe which are neareſt <lb/>the
              ſymphyſis pubis belong to the abſorbents of the parts of generation <lb/>in both
              ſexes, and become, in the venereal diſeaſe, the ſeat of buboes. <lb/>In ſome obſtinate
              venereal ulcerations of theſe glands, the coats of the <lb/>ſubjacent inguinal artery
              have been ſo eroded, that from ſtraining <lb/>the artery has burſt, and the patient
              inſtantly expired. A caſe of <lb/>this kind was related by Dr. Hunter, as having
              happened in a ſol- <lb/>dier of the guards. — Thoſe on the outſide of theſe
              laſt-mentioned <lb/>are more apt to inflame and enlarge, from ſerophulous or other
              ſores <lb/>on the inſide or top of the foot, from ſores on the inſide of the
              <lb/>knee, or any where in the courſe of the ſaphena major. They may <lb/>ſwell from
              ſores any where on the inſide or fore part of the leg <lb/>and thigh. I have known
              them ſwell from wounds of the buttocks, <lb/>and even from the inflamed and bleeding
              piles about the verge of the <lb/>anus. When plaſters, producing ulcers in the
              integuments, have been <lb/>applied to the ſkin, near the ſpine of the ilium, I have
              alſo repeatedly <lb/>ſeen theſe glands ſwell. They ſometimes ſwell, and even
              ſuppurate, <lb/>from ſympathy with an inflamed teſticle, though there is no connec-
              <lb/>tion between them by lymphatic veſſels. Haller and Nuck make <lb/>theſe glands
              extend ſometimes to the middle of the ſartorius muſcle: <lb/>
              <q rend="quotes">Aliquouſque cum magnis vaſorum truncis ad medium fere ſartorium
                <lb/>deſcendunt, a quo muſculo, <hi rend="italic">ſartoriarum</hi> nomen, Nuckius
                ſumſit, ab <lb/>arteria, vero, crurales dixit. </q> I have ſeldom ſeen any glands
              between <lb/>the popliteal and inguinal glands, neither with the cutaneous nor deep-
              <lb/>ſeated lymphatics. </p>
          </div>
          <pb n="123"/>
          <div type="section">
            <head rend="align-center">
              <lb/>THE EXTERNAL ILIAC GLANDS. </head>
            <p rend="space indent">
              <lb/>THESE alſo are of an uncertain number, from ſix to eight or ten, <lb/>or even
              more, and are ſituated both above and below the external iliac <lb/>artery and vein:
                <q rend="quotes">A magnis vaſis, eædem (glandulæ) cum eorum iliacis <lb/>ramis
                cognomines, ad femora tendunt. </q> Though the venereal poiſon <lb/>muſt paſs
              through theſe glands, in its way to the blood, I know of no <lb/>inſtance of their
              ever forming buboes; and it is very fortunate they do <lb/>not; for if theſe, like the
              inguinal glands, ſuppurated, they could not <lb/>be opened by the lancet, they muſt be
              left to themſelves — might burſt; <lb/>the pus might fall into the cavity of the
              abdomen; might produce pe- <lb/>ritoneal inflammation, and might probably deſtroy the
              patient. It <lb/>is very difficult to aſſign any reaſon for this, as cancerous matter
              <lb/>not only affects the firſt glands it enters, but all the glands that <lb/>lie
              between the fore and the thoracic duct. Some have aſſigned, as a <lb/>reaſon for the
              venereal virus not affecting the ſecond glands as <lb/>well as the firſt, that the
              poiſon was diluted by being mixed with the lymph in <lb/>the firſt gland. This is by
              no means ſatisfactory; ſince, even after it <lb/>has been mixed with the whole maſs of
              blood, it is capable of producing <lb/>ulcers in the throat, blotches on the whole
              ſurface of the body, and <lb/>caries in the bones. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="section">
            <head rend="align-center">
              <lb/>THE INTERNAL ILIAC GLANDS. </head>
            <p rend="space indent">
              <lb/>THESE alſo have been noticed by Haller. — Speaking of the former <lb/>claſs, or
              external iliac glands, he ſays, <q rend="quotes">Ab eo agmine alter faſciculus <lb/>in
                pelvim deſcendit cum vena hypogaſtrica ramoque ejus obturatorio. </q>
              <lb/>Their number is alſo uncertain; generally, however, more numerous <lb/>than the
              former. They are apt to form large indurated maſſes, from <lb/>diſeaſes, about the
              rectum, uterus, or bladder, which in many inſtances <lb/>have proved fatal. A caſe of
              this kind Dr. Hunter attended. A woman <lb/>was in labour, and could not be delivered
              in the natural way, from a <lb/>tumor on the ſide of the pelvis preventing the child's
              head from coming <pb n="124"/>
              <lb/>down. After ſhe was compleatly exhauſted, and the pains gone, he was <lb/>obliged
              to deliver by the crotchet. The child, of courſe, was loſt; the <lb/>mother fell into
              a fever, and died. Haller, ſpeaking of the ſame glands, <lb/>ſays, <q rend="quotes"
                >Funeſtis ſchirris obnoxiæ! </q>
            </p>
          </div>
          <div type="section">
            <head rend="align-center">
              <lb/>THE SACRAL GLANDS. </head>
            <p rend="space indent">
              <lb/>HALLER blends theſe with the former claſs. They are connected <lb/>with them,
              undoubtedly; but, lying more in the hollow of the ſacrum, <lb/>and behind the rectum,
              I have conſidered them apart. Some of theſe <lb/>are a continuation of the glands of
              the meſocolon, and belong to the <lb/>rectum; others to the vagina, bladder, and
              glutæi muſcles. <q rend="quotes">In <lb/>pelvi ultimas meſentericarum quæ rectum
                inteſtinum poſteriores co- <lb/>mitantur, hæ ſacræ iterum adtingunt. </q> Theſe, as
              well as the former, <lb/>are liable to ſchirrus; and have ſometimes ſo compreſſed the
              rectum, as <lb/>almoſt entirely to prevent the extruſion of the fæces: the patient has
              <lb/>been wore out, and deſtroyed. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="section">
            <head rend="align-center">
              <lb/>THE LUMBAR GLANDS. </head>
            <p rend="space indent">
              <lb/>THE bodies of the lumbar vertebræ, the lower part of the aorta, <lb/>and cava
              inferior, are covered with a plexus of lymphatic glands, more <lb/>numerous than any
              of the former claſſes. Under theſe the thoracic duct <lb/>takes its origin; ſo that I
              am not ſurprized at Bartholin's conſidering <lb/>them to be the real receptacle of the
              chyle in man. Haller ſays, <q rend="quotes">Cum <lb/>vena cava, porro, anteriores
                glandulæ deſcendunt, per lumborum ver- <lb/>tebras, lumbalium nomine; celebres
                toties Bartholino laudatæ, quas <lb/>vir cl. ob numeroſa immiſta vaſa lymphatica,
                omnino pro vero in <lb/>homine chyli receptaculo, habuit. </q> Theſe, in cancers,
              and ſcrophulous <lb/>affections of the teſticles and ovaria, are frequently enlarged
              and diſeaſed. <lb/>
              <q rend="quotes">Grandes ſunt, &amp; frequenter intumeſcunt. </q> In the dead body of
              a man, <lb/>whoſe left teſticle had formerly been extirpated on account of its being
              <lb/>cancerous, I found the lumbar glands enlarged to the ſize of a child's head
              <lb/>at birth, and encloſing the vena cava inferior, and aorta deſcendens, <lb/>for
              ſome way. </p>
          </div>
          <pb n="125"/>
          <div type="section">
            <head rend="align-center">
              <lb/>THE MESENTERIC GLANDS. </head>
            <p rend="space indent">
              <lb/>THEIR number is from between 130 to 140 or 150. — Ruyſch <lb/>makes them vaſtly
              more numerous than I do; and ſays, that he has <lb/>counted ſeventy glands in a
              portion of the meſentery not broader than <lb/>the palm of his hand. — Haller does not
              ſay how many glands there <lb/>are in the meſentery, but uſes the term plurima. <q
                rend="quotes">In adipe circa <lb/>vaſorum inteſtinalium diviſiones, plurimæ glandulæ
                ſedent, ovatæ, <lb/>compreſſæ, molles, tenera membrana obductæ, conglobati generis,
                cellu- <lb/>loſæ &amp; ipſæ; in meſenterio quidem potiſſimum, tamen etiam in
                meſocolo <lb/>tranſverſo, inque aliis meſocolis, etiam pone rectum inteſtinum. Iis
                <lb/>glandulis cum thymo commune eſt, fucco lacteolo in fetu adbundare,
                <lb/>vaſculiſque innumerabilibus, deinde ea ætate ſucculentas eſſe, &amp; in ſe-
                <lb/>nibus demum diminui, &amp; fere evaneſcere. </q> This variety depends on this
              <lb/>circumſtance — the inteſtinal canal is longer in ſome human bodies than <lb/>in
              others; ſo much ſo, that it is ſometimes ſeven or eight times the length <lb/>of the
              whole body; at other times not more than three times that length. <lb/>The number of
              the glands, and the breadth of the meſentery, are almoſt <lb/>always in proportion to
              the length of the inteſtinal tube, and of courſe to <lb/>the number of the abſorbent
              veſſels. As the abſorbents are more nu- <lb/>merous upon the jejunum, or ſuperior part
              of the inteſtinal tube, their <lb/>glands are not only more numerous, but larger, on
              that part of the <lb/>meſentery which correſponds to that inteſtine. Moſt of them are
              <lb/>ſituated on the convex or left ſide of the ſuperior meſenteric artery. In
              <lb/>the healthy ſtate of the body, even in the adult, the largeſt glands on <lb/>the
              meſentery ſeldom exceed the ſize of an almond. It is very ſeldom <lb/>that they are
              ſituate nearer the edge of the inteſtine than one or two <lb/>inches. They are
              commonly ſcattered at a little diſtance from each <lb/>other. Sometimes they are
              cluſtered, or accumulated; and in many <lb/>quadrupeds they are only to be found in
              this cluſtered form, at the root <lb/>of the meſentery. Aſellius found them ſo in the
              dogs; and, from their <lb/>forming a line of ſome length at that place, as well as
              from other cir- <lb/>cumſtances, ſuppoſed them to be the pancreas. Although ſucceeding
              <lb/>anatomiſts diſcovered his error, they ſtill continued to call this conglo- <pb
                n="126"/>
              <lb/>meration of the lymphatic glands, in thoſe animals, by the name of the
              <lb/>Pancreas of Aſcllius. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>I have ſaid, that the glands of the abſorbents on the lower part of the
              <lb/>meſentery, and towards the right ſide, are ſmaller and leſs numerous than
              <lb/>thoſe toward the upper and left ſide; but the chyle from the lower <lb/>part of
              the ilium, if it paſſes at firſt apparently through fewer and ſmaller <lb/>glands,
              paſſes afterwards through a greater number, and even through <lb/>the large glands at
              the root of the meſentery; ſo that what is not <lb/>ſtrictly true reſpecting the
              veſſel, though aſſerted by Haller, is certainly <lb/>true reſpecting the chyle
              abſorbed from the ilium. <q rend="quotes">Idem vas lacteum, <lb/>quod mihi ſelegerim,
                ad quintam uſque glandulam, in ſuperficie meſenterii proſecutus ſum. </q>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Theſe glands often become enlarged and indurated; this enlargement
              <lb/>frequently depends upon a ſpecies of dyſentery and ulceration of the in-
              <lb/>teſtines. The abſorbents ariſing out of the. ulcers carry the inflamma- <lb/>tion
              to the meſenteric glands, and become the cauſe of their enlarge- <lb/>ment. The glands
              of the meſentery alſo enlarge from ſcrophula, without <lb/>any inflammation or
              ulceration of the inteſtines: and, as children liable <lb/>to this complaint are
              generally very much emaciated, and ſoon after die, <lb/>their emaciation and death has
              been attributed to the obſtruction in the <lb/>glands preventing the chyle from
              entering into the blood; and the <lb/>diſeaſe has been called tabes meſenterica, as I
              have already ſaid. <lb/>Haller ſays, <q rend="quotes">Non alibi, in corpore humano
                frequentior ſchirro <lb/>locus eſt &amp; ſteatomatibus etiam lapideis
                cducretionibus, ut omnino <lb/>dudum earum tumor &amp; ſchirrus pro cauſa peculiaris
                atrophiæ infan- <lb/>tilis habiti ſunt. </q> After which he exhibits a long liſt of
              indurations <lb/>and enlargements of theſe glands: — <q rend="quotes">Schirrus enormis
                librarum decem — <lb/>In atrophia meſenterium totum lapidoſum — Glandulæ meſenterii
                tumi- <lb/>diſſimæ, intus tartaro fetæ. </q> — Diemerbroeck appears to have miſtaken
              the <lb/>ſcrophulous ſuppuration of theſe glands for the ſtagnation and coagulation
              <lb/>of the chyle in them: <q rend="quotes">In atrophia glandulæ meſentericæ tumidæ
                ca- <lb/>ſeoſo chylo plenæ. </q> De Haen mentions a caſe where the meſentery, from
              <lb/>the diſeaſed glands, weighed thirty pounds: <q rend="quotes">Tumor meſenterii cum
                <lb/>hydatidibus, etiam cartilagineis partibus, triginta librarum pondere. </q>
            </p>
          </div>
          <pb n="127"/>
          <div type="section">
            <head rend="align-center sc">
              <lb/>The GLANDS of the MESOCOLON. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THE glands of the meſocolon are neither ſo large nor ſo numerous <lb/>as thoſe of
              the meſentery. They are among the ſmalleſt in the body; and <lb/>their number ſeldom
              exceeds twenty or thirty. They are ſituated nearer <lb/>the edge of the inteſtine; but
              are alſo ſcattered not only along what is <lb/>called the meſocolon, but on that fixt
              production of the peritoneum <lb/>which belongs to the caput coli, and alſo to the
              ſigmoide flexure of <lb/>the colon. They are alſo found on what Haller calls the
              meſocolon in- <lb/>ferior, in the hollow of the ſacrum, what Dr. Hunter uſed to call
              the <lb/>meſorectum. Haller ſays little or nothing of theſe glands: <q rend="quotes"
                >Nume- <lb/>roſiſſimis illis meſenterii &amp; meſocoli glandulis conjungitur. </q>
              The me- <lb/>ſenteric glands, at the time of the abſorption of the chyle, are of a
              pure <lb/>white colour; but 1 never ſaw this happen to the glands of the meſo-
              <lb/>colon. Winſlow ſays, that he demonſtrated, to the Academy of Sciences, <lb/>chyle
              in the lacteals of the great inteſtines. This I formerly obſerved I <lb/>never ſaw.
              The chyle is principally found in the jejunum; and the con- <lb/>tents of the ilium,
              towards its lower end, approach very much to the nature <lb/>of fæces. In the great
              inteſtine I have never found any thing but fæces. <lb/>The circumſtance of the glands
              being more numerous in the meſentery, <lb/>along which almoſt all the chyle is
              carried, and being ſmaller and leſs nu- <lb/>merous on the meſocolon, through which
              hardly any paſſes, looks as if the <lb/>glands were intended to produce ſome
              remarkable change on the chyle. <lb/>Theſe glands are not ſo liable to ſchirrus as
              thoſe on the meſentery; but <lb/>are ſometimes enlarged, from cancers and lchirri in
              the great inteſtines, <lb/>which occur there more frequently than in the ſmall. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="section">
            <head rend="space align-center sc">
              <lb/>The GLANDS of the OMENTUM and STOMACH. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>IT is ſeldom that any glands are found on the omentum till you come <lb/>near the
              great arch of the ſtomach; they are about three or four in num- <lb/>ber, in the
              courſe of the gaſtrica dextra and ſmiſtra; and, though they <lb/>belong to the omentum
              as much as to the ſtomach, have been conſidered <lb/>by ſome anatomiſts as belonging
              to the ſtomach only, and been termed <pb n="128"/>
              <lb/>glandulæ ventriculi inferiores. There are ſome ſmall glands alſo on the edge
              <lb/>of the little epiploon, where it adheres to the ſmall arch of the ſtomach;
              <lb/>theſe, from their ſituation, have been termed glandulæ ventriculi ſu-
              <lb/>periors. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="section">
            <head rend="space sc align-center">
              <lb/>The GLANDS of the LIVER, PANCREAS, and SPLEEN. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THE trunk of the vena portarum, near its entrance into the <lb/>liver, is beſet
              with abſorbent glands; theſe I have ſeen diſeaſed, and <lb/>diſtended to an enormous
              ſize, and compreſſing both the ductus <lb/>communis choledochus, and the pancreatic
              duct, at the place of their <lb/>inſertion into the duodenum: and this plexus is
              connected with another, <lb/>which runs in the courſe of the ſplenic artery and vein,
              and belongs <lb/>to the ſtomach, pancreas, and ſpleen. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="section">
            <head rend="space align-center sc">
              <lb/>The THORACIC GLANDS of the ABSORBENTS. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>FROM the cavity of the abdomen we now go to the cavity of the tho- <lb/>rax. The
              firſt glands we meet with in the cavity of the thorax, on the fore <lb/>part of the
              pericardium, and upper ſurface of the diaphragm, are three or <lb/>four in number;
              they are of a moderate ſize, and belong commonly to the <lb/>abſorbents of the liver,
              ſometimes only to the diaphragm. There are <lb/>others between the laminæ of the
              anterior mediaſtinum, three, four, or <lb/>five; neither of theſe have I, on any
              occaſion, ſeen diſeaſed. On the op- <lb/>poſite ſide of the pericardium, between the
              lamina of the poſterior me- <lb/>diaſtinum, there are abſorbent glands, which lie upon
              the œſophagus; <lb/>a continuation of which are found, in moſt ſubjects, ſcattered on
              the <lb/>external ſurface of that canal, throughout its whole length. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Along with the internal mammary arteries a number of ſmall glands <lb/>are
              commonly found, under the cartilages of the true ribs, from ſix to eight <lb/>or ten.
              — Sometimes, but rarely, the glands of the abſorbents are found <lb/>within the
              ſubſtance of the lungs. They are conſtantly found, however, <lb/>at the root of the
              lungs, both before and behind the bifurcation of the <lb/>trachea, in the two
              bronchia. Haller ſays, <q rend="quotes">Quæ cum arteria aſpera <pb n="129"/>
                <lb/>deſcendunt, eæ utrumque pariter cjus ramum comitantur, &amp; pulmonis
                <lb/>grandia vaſa circumſtant, &amp; anteriores &amp; poſteriores. </q> Theſe glands
              belong <lb/>to the abſorbents of the lungs, and may be termed the bronchial glands of
              <lb/>the abſorbents; ſome of them frequently blend with others which lie <lb/>upon the
              arch of the aorta, not unfrequently between the origins of the <lb/>carotids, which
              may be termed the cardiac glands. The former glands <lb/>are commonly of a blue,
              ſometimes of a black colour. When they are of <lb/>the latter colour, their internal
              ſubſtance appears as it were broke down <lb/>or diſſolved; and when cut into, reſemble
              ſo many little bags of ink; at <lb/>other times are full of oſſifications, which
              ſometimes have ulcerated their <lb/>way into the trachea, and bits of bone have been
              coughed up, to the aſto- <lb/>niſhment of the practitioner, as well as of the patient.
              Bone may be <lb/>coughed up from other cauſes, however. Dr. Hunter uſed to relate a
              <lb/>caſe, and ſhew the baſis of the cricoid cartilage converted into bone,
              <lb/>which, dying from ſome cauſe in the part itſelf, exfoliated, and was at <lb/>laſt
              coughed up. The patient, for ſeveral months, coughed up blood and <lb/>pus, though in
              ſmall quantities; was ſuppoſed to be in a conſumption; <lb/>but on the bone's
              ſeparating, and being coughed up, he recovered. — <lb/>Some glands are alſo continued
              from theſe, on the fore part of the trachea, <lb/>all the way to the upper edge of the
              ſternum. I once knew an inſtance <lb/>of theſe glands becoming ſchirrous, and forming
              a conſiderable maſs, <lb/>which being prevented by the ſternum from puſhing forwards,
              preſſed <lb/>backwards upon the trachea, and compreſſed it in ſuch a manner, that
              <lb/>its cavity was gradually obliterating. The man was for ſome time inca- <lb/>pable
              of the leaſt exertion or motion, without running immediate riſk <lb/>of ſuffocation;
              and actually died one morning ſuddenly, as he was putting <lb/>on his cloaths. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The ſides of the vertebræ of the back have a ſmall chain of glands <lb/>continued
              as it were from the lumbar glands, through their whole <lb/>length. Theſe glands are
              almoſt always to be found, and are commonly <lb/>very ſmall; they belong to the
              abſorbents of the intercoſtal ſpaces, and <lb/>ſeem to be ſo many guards on the
              thoracic duct, that no abſorbent may <lb/>enter it, which has not previouſly paſſed
              through a gland. </p>
          </div>
          <pb n="130"/>
          <div type="section">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/>The GLANDS Of The ABSORBENTS Of The NECK. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THE glands of the neck are almoſt as numerous as thoſe of the meſentery;
              <lb/>they are ſituated chiefly on the ſides of the neck; ſome of them lie imme-
              <lb/>diately under the ſkin, and accompany the external jugular veins; but by <lb/>far
              the greater number accompany the internal jugular veins and carotid <lb/>arteries. <q
                rend="quotes">Porro hæc glandularum ſeries cum pharynge continuatur &amp; <lb/>ad
                latus &amp; ad poſteriorem ejus faciem, ſecundum iter jugularis venæ <lb/>&amp;
                carotidis arteriæ — Verum agmen illud jugulare dextrum cum vena <lb/>cava, utriuſque
                vero lateris cum aſpera arteria continuatur. </q> Haller. <lb/>Theſe glands
              frequently ſwell in children, from inflammations of the <lb/>gums and alveolar
              proceſſes in teething, and recover after the teething <lb/>is over. They frequently
              ſwell and enlarge from ſuppurations and <lb/>ulcerations of the integuments on the top
              of the head; and they fre- <lb/>quently inflame and enlarge from ſcrophulous
              diſpoſition alone. I have <lb/>known them ſwell to an enormous ſize; and, though
              commonly ac- <lb/>companied with little pain, I have known the inflammation changed
              <lb/>from indolent to active; and the pain and irritation of the parts, together
              <lb/>with the affection of the mind, have worn out and deſtroyed the pa- <lb/>tient.
              Commonly, however, the ſcrophulous affection of thoſe glands is <lb/>more offenſive to
              the eye of ſpectators, and troubleſome to the patient, than <lb/>dangerous. As they
              are ſituated in parts which are not uſually covered, <lb/>they are expoſed to every
              body's view, and almoſt conſtantly excite the <lb/>idea of ſcrophula, and of the
              blood's being tainted with an hereditary <lb/>diſeaſe, which may be communicated to
              the offſpring of the perſon. The <lb/>inflammation of thoſe glands not unfrequently
              terminates in ſuppura- <lb/>tion. They burſt of themſelves, continue diſcharging for
              months or <lb/>years, or alternately heal and break out again, till the age of
              fourteen or <lb/>ſixteen; when the increaſed vigor of the conſtitution, and the
              changes <lb/>that take place reſpecting the organs of generation, put a ſtop to the
              <lb/>diſeaſe, the patient for the remainder of his life ſhews no more ſymptoms <lb/>of
              ſcrophula, or at leaſt not till towards the end of life, when the vigor <lb/>of the
              body declining, permits this diſpoſition again to ſhew itſelf. <pb n="131"/>
              <lb/>Theſe glands not only enlarge from particular affections of the teeth and
              <lb/>jaws, and of the integuments on the outſide of the head, but from affec-
              <lb/>tions of the brain and its coverings; a proof not only of there being ab-
              <lb/>ſorbents in the brain, but of the courſe which theſe abſorbents take. <lb/>Theſe
              glands alſo ſwell from ulcerations of the integuments in the nape <lb/>of the neck.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div type="section">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/>The GLANDS of the ABSORBENTS in the AXILLÆ. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THESE glands blend in with another plexus, ſituated under <lb/>the clavicles and
              in the axillæ; theſe are not ſo numerous as <lb/>thoſe of the neck, though in general
              they are larger. They belong <lb/>to the abſorbents of the arms, of the breaſts, and
              of the integuments <lb/>behind the ſcapulæ; and inflame and enlarge in particular
              affections <lb/>of thoſe parts. They even receive abſorbents from the cavity of the
              <lb/>cheſt; and I have known them ſwell from pleuriſy, peripneumony, and
              <lb/>pulmonary conſumption. A nerve from the ſecond dorſal perforates <lb/>the
              intercoſtal muſcles, and alſo goes to the axilla, at the ſame place <lb/>with theſe
              abſorbents. Theſe glands, particularly, ſwell in cancerous <lb/>affections of the
              breaſts of women. It is ſometimes poſſible to extirpate <lb/>them with the diſeaſed
              breaſts themſelves, but more frequently their <lb/>ſwelling on theſe occaſions is a
              mark of the diſeaſe being incurable; <lb/>and I have known them form a ſchirrous maſs,
              and ſurround the axillary <lb/>artery in ſuch a manner, that it was impoſſible to
              extirpate them, with- <lb/>out extirpating that part of the artery too. In moſt of the
              caſes of <lb/>cancer in the breaſt, where theſe glands have been extirpated, the
              diſeaſe <lb/>returns, becauſe it is almoſt impoſſible to find out or extirpate all the
              <lb/>infected glands; or the arm ſome time after becomes œdematous, becauſe <lb/>the
              trunks of the abſorbents have been cut through, and afterwards in- <lb/>cluded in the
              cicatrix. </p>
          </div>
          <pb n="132"/>
          <div type="section">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/>GLANDS of the ARM. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THESE alſo are of an uncertain number, from three to ſix or ſeven in <lb/>each
              arm, and placed in no certain order: they occupy the inſide of the <lb/>arm, from the
              axilla to the internal condyle of the humerus, where there <lb/>is almoſt conſtantly
              one gland, in each arm, to be found on the anterior ſur- <lb/>face of that condyle.
              They run principally with the brachial artery. I <lb/>have known the laſt-mentioned
              glands die, and ſlough out in ſcrophula, <lb/>without any great inconvenience. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="section">
            <head rend="sc align-center space">
              <lb/>GLANDS of the FACE. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THERE are ſome ſmall glands belonging to the abſorbents on the <lb/>ſides of the
              face; the uppermoſt of theſe are immediately under the zygo- <lb/>matic proceſſes of
              the temporal bones, others lie on the external ſurfaces <lb/>of the parotid glands, as
              well as on the buccinator muſcles. There may <lb/>be four, five, or ſix of each ſide;
              ſometimes there are none. There are <lb/>alſo ſeveral glands about the angles of the
              lower jaw, and on its baſe, <lb/>between theſe angles and its ſymphyſis. There are
              conſtantly two be- <lb/>hind and upon the mammillary proceſſes of the temporal bones,
              but theſe <lb/>are rather to be conſidered as the uppermoſt of the neck than belonging
              <lb/>to the head. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="section">
            <head rend="align-center space sc">
              <lb/>Where there are no GLANDS of the ABSORBENTS. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>HAVING thus pointed out in what parts of the body the abſorbent <lb/>glands are
              chiefly to be found, it will naturally be aſked, Are there no <lb/>glands to be met
              with in the other parts of the body? I do not ſay that <lb/>they are never found any
              where elſe. Anatomiſts may yet find them in <lb/>parts where I have not ſeen them. We
              are every day finding ſome luſus <lb/>naturæ in the arteries, veins, and nerves; and,
              as the abſorbent ſyſtem <lb/>allows of a ſtill greater variety, other glands may yet
              be ſeen than thoſe <pb n="133"/>
              <lb/>which I have deſcribed. But I have ſeen no glands on the feet, none on <lb/>the
              legs below the ham, none between the integuments of the thigh <lb/>and the muſcles,
              different from thoſe deſcribed. Others have ſeen thoſe <lb/>that ſometimes, as it
              would appear, accompany the femoral artery in the <lb/>middle of the thigh; I have
              ſeen none between the ham and the groin. <lb/>I never ſaw any either under the
              integuments of among the muſcles of <lb/>the nates. I have met with none, on the
              poſterior part of the trunk of <lb/>the body, different from thoſe I have already
              deſcribed; nor on the ante- <lb/>rior part, except ſome ſmall ones on the breaſts of
              women, ſituated be- <lb/>tween the nipple and the axilla. There are none on the hands.
              I <lb/>never ſaw any in the fore-arm. There are none on the outſide of the
              <lb/>cranium; none on the inſide, either in the coverings or in the ſubſtance <lb/>of
              the brain. The pituitary gland has ſome reſemblance to the glands <lb/>of the
              abſorbents; but when cut into, it evidently conſiſts of two ſub- <lb/>ſtances; in
              which reſpect it reſembles the renal capſula of quadrupeds: <lb/>one upon the outſide,
              which may be called cortical; and another on the <lb/>inſide, which, were we to
              compare it to the ſubſtance of the brain, may <lb/>be called medullary. There is
              nothing of this appearance in the glands <lb/>of the abſorbents of the human body. No
              abſorbent vefiels have been <lb/>yet traced into it; we therefore do not know whether
              it is or is not a gland belonging to the abſorbents. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <pb n="134"/>
        <div type="chapter">
          <head rend="sc align-center space">
            <lb/>of the <lb/>PARTICULAR DISTRIBUTION <lb/>of the <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">ABSORBENT
              VESSELS</hi> themſelves, <lb/>in the different parts of the body. </head>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A long horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
          <div>
            <head rend="align-center space">
              <lb/>ABSORBENTS of the <hi rend="sc">Lower Extremity</hi>. </head>
            <p rend="space">
              <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> Have, in a former part of this work, demonſtrated that
              the trunks <lb/>of the abſorbents are at leaſt double the number of the larger ar-
              <lb/>teries. Some have imagined that this ſuperiority in number did not <lb/>extend to
              the minute branches; but the annexed engraving of the deep- <lb/>ſeated lacteals will
              ſufficiently demonſtrate that this ſuperiority in num- <lb/>ber is kept up there alſo.
              I have occaſionally ſeen, immediately under <lb/>the common integuments on the top of
              the foot, innumerable ramifica- <lb/>tions of the abſorbents, and exactly the fame
              appearance as in the ramification of arteries themſelves. Bartholin and Steno appear
              firſt to have <lb/>ſeen ſomething of theſe veſſels in quadrupeds; but Van Horne was
              the <lb/>firſt who ſaw them in the human ſubject. This I take on the authority <lb/>of
              Haller: <q rend="quotes">Ea vero in humano crure oſtendit Johannes Van Horne. </q>
              <lb/>The larger abſorbents of the lower extremity are formed into two ſets,
              <lb/>ſuperficial, and deep-ſeated; the ſuperficial ſet accompany chiefly the
              <lb/>cutaneous veins, and the deep-ſeated accompany the arteries. The cu- <pb n="135"/>
              <lb/>taneous veins of the lower extremity form two principal trunks; one <lb/>of theſe
              is named ſaphena major, and the other ſaphena minor. The <lb/>greater number of the
              cutaneous abſorbents accompany the ſaphena <lb/>major; and I have long diſtinguiſhed
              them by the name of <hi rend="italic">vaſa lymphatica <lb/>venam ſaphenam majorem
                comitantia</hi>. Some abſorbents ariſe from the ſides <lb/>of the toes, in the ſame
              manner as the arteries, two and two. But, be- <lb/>ſides theſe, there is a net-work of
              abſorbents compleatly ſurrounding the <lb/>toes. The two lateral abſorbents accompany
              the deep-ſeated arteries; <lb/>the net-work upon the outſide belong to thoſe which
              accompany the <lb/>cutaneous veins. They form four great diviſions; the firſt ariſes
              from <lb/>between the great toe and the one on its outſide, where the ſaphena
              <lb/>major commences, and conſiſts of ſix or ſeven veſſels; they run over the <lb/>top
              of the foot, with that vein, towards the fore part of the inner ancle; <lb/>from
              thence they run, in company with the vein, towards the inſide of <lb/>the knee, where
              they are joined by others, preſently to be deſcribed. <lb/>The ſecond diviſion, which
              I have ſeen conſiſting ſometimes of eight <lb/>or ten veſſels, ariſe about the middle
              of the inner edge of the foot, <lb/>paſs behind the inner ancle, and, running over the
              inſide of the calf of <lb/>the leg, join the laſt-deſcribed veſſels on the inſide of
              the knee. The third <lb/>diviſion, conſiſting of five or ſix veſſels, ariſe near the
              little toe, run over <lb/>the outer and upper ſide of the foot, in the direction of
              the outer ancle; <lb/>when they come near it, they divide into two; one part croſs
              over the <lb/>anterior part of the tibia, and go likewiſe to the inſide of the knee,
              where <lb/>they join the two former diviſions. — It happened once, that when I was
              <lb/>injecting this plexus with quickſilver, I injected a portion of the ſkin <lb/>to
              great minuteneſs, the mercury having run contrary to the valves, <lb/>into exceeding
              fine extremities of the abſorbents. The part where this <lb/>happened, as well as the
              veſſels from whence it was injected, are ſeen <lb/>in the largeſt annexed figure. —
              From the union of theſe three diviſions, a <lb/>grand plexus is formed, conſiſting of
              fourteen, ſixteen, or twenty trunks <lb/>of the abſorbents, which ſtill continue to
              accompany the ſaphena major; <lb/>that is, to run obliquely from the inſide of the
              knee to the middle of <lb/>the groin; there they commonly go into the different
              inguinal glands <lb/>already deſcribed. But, in the moſt ſucceſsful injection that I
              ever <lb/>made of theſe veſſels, they terminated in one gland, as will be ſeen in <pb
                n="136"/>
              <lb/>the annexed figure. It frequently happens, that two or three of theſe <lb/>trunks
              paſs by the glands of the groin, and are not inſerted into any gland <lb/>till they
              have paſſed under Paupart's ligament. Part of the laſt diviſion, <lb/>viz. that coming
              from the little toe, join another which ariſes from the <lb/>middle of the outer edge
              of the foot, where the ſaphena minor commences, <lb/>and accompanying that vein, paſs
              behind the outer ancle; from thence run <lb/>on the outſide of the tendo achilles, go
              afterwards between the bellies of <lb/>the gaſtroenemeus muſcle, and, dipping down
              between its heads, near the <lb/>place where they are inſerted into the condyles of
              the os femoris, terminate <lb/>in the glands of the ham, already deſcribed. Theſe I
              have long diſtinguiſhed <lb/>by the name of <hi rend="italic">vaſa lymphatica venam
                ſaphenam minorem comitantia</hi>. Theſe <lb/>are not above one fifth ſo numerous as
              the former. The deep-ſeated ab- <lb/>ſorbents ariſe, as I have ſaid, from the ſides of
              the toes, along with the <lb/>arteries, two on each ſide, as the deep-ſeated veins.
              Part of theſe accom- <lb/>pany the anterior tibial artery, on the top of the foot; and
              I have long <lb/>diſtinguiſhed them by the name of <hi rend="italic">vaſa lymphatica
                arteriam tibialem an- <lb/>ticam comitantia</hi>; they accompany it through its
              whole courſe, with it, <lb/>perforate the interoſſial ligament, between the tibia and
              fibula, and ter- <lb/>minate in the glands of the ham: but the principal part
              accompany the <lb/>arteries plantaris externa &amp; interna, in the ſole of the foot,
              and afterwards <lb/>the poſterior tibial artery through its whole courſe, and
              terminate alſo <lb/>in the glands of the ham; theſe I have long named <hi
                rend="italic">vaſa lymphatica ar- <lb/>teriam tibialem poſticam comitantia</hi>. I
              have once or twice alſo ſeen the ab- <lb/>ſorbents accompanying, in the fame manner,
              the peroneil artery. Though <lb/>I have not injected them with quickſilver, I have
              inflated them with air, <lb/>and have no doubt but that they terminate in the ſame
              glands. From the <lb/>glands of the ham, two grand trunks emerge, as vaſa efferentia
              principally <lb/>to the deep-ſeated abſorbents now deſcribed, but alſo to the
              cutaneous <lb/>abſorbents which accompanied the ſaphena minor; theſe run one on each
              <lb/>ſide of the femoral artery: I have uſually called them <hi rend="italic">arteriæ
                cruralis <lb/>comites</hi>. Theſe frequently communicate with one another by croſs
              canals, <lb/>and their branches ſometimes form circles which compleatly ſurround
              <lb/>the artery. In one caſe they both terminated in the ſame gland in which <lb/>the
              greater number of the cutaneous abſorbents had terminated; but <lb/>more frequently
              they terminate in three or four of the larger glands, <pb n="137"/>
              <lb/>which lie on the upper or under ſide of the inguinal artery. The glands <lb/>and
              the veſſels together I have uſually named <hi rend="italic">lymphaticorum plexus
                inguina- <lb/>lis</hi>. From theſe glands ſeveral trunks emerge. I have occaſionally
              ſeen <lb/>two; ſometimes four; and, the very laſt time that I injected them, which
              <lb/>was laſt ſummer, there were ſix: theſe I have been uſed to name <hi rend="italic"
                >effe- <lb/>rentia inguinis</hi>. The principal trunk lies under the faſcia of the
              thigh, <lb/>immediately in contact with the upper ſide of the inguinal artery, and
              <lb/>a little above that paſſes under Paupart's ligament, where it immediately
              <lb/>enters into the glands that are upon the ſides of the external iliac ar-
              <lb/>tery; and, being joined with other ſmaller trunks from the thigh, forms <lb/>a
              very elegant plexus of veſſels and glands, all the way to the lowermoſt <lb/>vertebra
              of the loins; which I have uſually diſtinguiſhed by the name <lb/>of <hi rend="italic"
                >lymphaticorum plexus iliacus externus</hi>: ſometimes the principal trunk,
              <lb/>without entering any gland, accompanies the iliac artery till it is loſt in
              <lb/>the lumbar glands. I have ſometimes found it paſſing along theſe, with- <lb/>out
              entering any of them, and going immediately into the beginning of <lb/>the thoracic
              duct, where, joined by a ſimilar trunk from the oppoſite <lb/>ſide, they might be
              ſaid, as it were, to form the two crura of the thoracic <lb/>duct. Some of the ſmaller
              vaſa efferentia of the groin lie above the faſcia <lb/>of the thigh, and, before they
              paſs under Paupart's ligament, are obliged <lb/>to perforate the faſcia in ſo many
              different places. When the abſorbents <lb/>of the thigh form one large trunk, lying on
              the upper ſide of the ingui- <lb/>nal artery, I have diſtinguiſhed it by the name of
                <hi rend="italic">efferens inguinis maxi- <lb/>mum</hi>. If the operation for the
              inguinal aneuriſm was to be performed <lb/>in ſuch a caſe, this trunk muſt be tied up
              with the artery, the leg muſt <lb/>become œdematous, and there would be a ſtagnation
              of lymph in almoſt <lb/>all the abſorbents of the lower extremity. About two years ago
              I in- <lb/>jected the trunks accompanying the femoral artery: — a little above the
              <lb/>middle of the thigh they ſplit into four branches; theſe ſubdividing, <lb/>formed
              about ſeven or eight; ſome of theſe were inſerted into glands on <lb/>the inſide of
              the inguinal artery, but the principal veſſels went with it <lb/>under Paupart's
              ligament, into the cavity of the abdomen, and were in- <lb/>ſerted into the external
              iliac glands. </p>
          </div>
          <pb n="138"/>
          <div>
            <head rend="align-center space">
              <lb/>The ABSORBENTS of the <hi rend="sc">Penis</hi>. </head>
            <p rend="space indent">
              <lb/>THESE likewiſe may be divided into a ſuperficial and deep-ſeated <lb/>ſet. The
              ſuperficial abſorbents ariſe from the prepuce, in three divi- <lb/>ſions; one on the
              right ſide of the frænum, another on the left, and the <lb/>third directly in the
              middle, on the ſuperior ſide. Thoſe from the <lb/>under ſide make a ſemicircular turn,
              from the under to the upper ſide of <lb/>the penis; whilſt that on the ſuperior part
              of the prepuce runs on the <lb/>middle of the dorſum penis, exactly in the direction
              of the ſymphyſis <lb/>pubis. At a little diſtance from the ſymphyſis, the three
              diviſions unite <lb/>into one common trunk, which almoſt immediately ſeparates again
              into <lb/>two. One of theſe trunks goes to the right groin, accompanies thoſe
              <lb/>veins which go to the inguinal vein, and terminates near it in thoſe
              <lb/>inguinal glands which are neareſt the ſymphyſis pubis. The other trunk <lb/>goes
              to the left groin, and terminates exactly in the ſame manner as the <lb/>former. I
              have uſually named theſe <hi rend="italic">penis lymphatica cutanea</hi>. It is from
              <lb/>this circumſtance, that when venereal matter is abſorbed from a chancre <lb/>on
              the prepuce, red lines are ſometimes ſeen running on the body of the <lb/>penis, and
              terminating in the groin: theſe are the abſorbent veſſels in- <lb/>flamed by the
              irritation of the poiſon. This inflammation ſeldom laſts <lb/>above a day or two. At
              other times they put on the appearance, and <lb/>have the feel of ſmall cords: theſe
              alſo go off in a few days. At other <lb/>times the veſſels not only inflame, and form
              indurations, but alſo ſup- <lb/>purate in different places, and form what has been
              called buboes of <lb/>the penis. The deep-ſeated ones accompany the arteries, and paſs
              <lb/>with them on the inſide of the tuberoſities of the iſchia, or under <lb/>the
              angle of the pubis. If the venereal virus forms a chancre on the <lb/>prepuce, a buboe
              is frequently the conſequence, in one of the glands <lb/>of the groin; but if the
              chancre is formed on the glans penis, there is <lb/>ſeldom a buboe in the groin, and
              yet the conſtitution is infected as <lb/>certainly as in the former caſe. The inguinal
              glands ſometimes inflame <lb/>and ſuppurate merely from ſympathy with the urethra,
              though no vene- <lb/>real matter be paſſing through them: this we ſee ſometimes in go-
              <lb/>norrheas cured without mercury; where, notwithſtanding, ſymptoms <lb/>of the lues
              venerea in the conſtitution appeared afterwards. The <pb n="139"/>
              <lb/>ſame thing frequently happens when bougies have been introduced, <lb/>with a view
              to the cure of a ſtricture in the urethra. Theſe abſorbents <lb/>may be termed <hi
                rend="italic">lymphatica penis profundiora</hi>. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="space align-center">
              <lb/>The ABSORBENTS <lb/><hi rend="sc">OF THE EXTERNAL PARTS OF GENERATION IN
                WOMEN</hi>. </head>
            <p rend="space indent">
              <lb/>THE abſorbents from the clitoris, and beginning of the vagina, <lb/>alſo form two
              diviſions; one of theſe, as in the male, goes to the in- <lb/>guinal glands of each
              ſide; the other runs up with the round liga- <lb/>ments towards the rings of the
              external oblique muſcles of the abdo- <lb/>men, and may either paſs into the glands on
              the inſide of Paupart's <lb/>ligament, or, blending with the abſorbents of the uterus,
              moſt probably <lb/>terminate in the lumbar glands. This arrangement of theſe veſſels
              will <lb/>explain what we commonly fee taking place, as the conſequence of
              <lb/>chancres in women — If the chancre is near the meatus urinæ, the red <lb/>lines,
              which mark the inflamed abſorbents, are ſometimes ſeen run- <lb/>ning in the courſe of
              the round ligament; and ſuppurations, ſimilar <lb/>to the buboes of the penis in men,
              alſo ſometimes take place; but if <lb/>the chancre be ſituated any where near the
              perineum, the red lines are <lb/>ſeen running in the direction of the groin, and the
              buboe has the <lb/>ſame ſituation that it uſually has in men. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="align-center space">
              <lb/>Some other ABSORBENTS, <lb/><hi rend="sc">TERMINATING IN THE GLANDS OF THE
                GROIN</hi>. </head>
            <p rend="space indent">
              <lb/>I HAVE ſeen abſorbents injected with quickſilver, which aroſe <lb/>from the
              buttocks and poſterior part of the thigh, and which, paſſing <lb/>between the
              integuments and muſcles of the outſide of the thigh, were <lb/>inſerted into thoſe
              inguinal glands which are neareſt the ſpine of the <lb/>ilium. The following
              appearances ſhew, that the abſorbents about the <lb/>verge of the anus, as well as the
              abſorbents of the lateral part of the <lb/>abdomen, are inſerted in the glands of the
              groin. Where the piles <lb/>have been very much inflamed or ſuppurated, I have
              repeatedly ſeen <lb/>the inguinal glands ſwell; and where ulcerations have been
              produced <pb n="140"/>
              <lb/>in the integuments which cover the poſterior edge of the obliquuſ <lb/>externus,
              the abſorbent glands of the groin have alſo ſwelled. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="align-center">
              <lb/>The ABSORBENTS of the <hi rend="sc">Testicle</hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="space indent">
              <lb/>MAY be divided into four claſſes: thoſe of its coats, thoſe of the body <lb/>of
              the teſticle, thoſe of the rete teſtis, and thoſe of the epididymis. <lb/>The firſt I
              have uſually diſtinguiſhed by the name of <hi rend="italic">lymphatica tunicæ
                <lb/>vaginalis</hi>; the ſecond, by the name of <hi rend="italic">lymphatica teſtis
                profundiora</hi>; the <lb/>third, <hi rend="italic">lymphatica rete teſtis</hi>; and
              the fourth, by the name of <hi rend="italic">lympha- <lb/>tica epididymidis</hi>. The
              abſorbents of the tunica vaginalis are eaſily diſ- <lb/>covered, lying between the
              reflection of that coat and the tunica albu- <lb/>ginea. Though they are thus
              ſituated, I know that they belong equally <lb/>to the body of the teſticle: they are
              in great numbers, and I have <lb/>ſometimes covered the albuginea with abſorbents
              injected with quick- <lb/>ſilver; perhaps there is not any part of the human body
              where the ab- <lb/>ſorbents are larger or more numerous, in proportion to the part,
              than <lb/>here. They ſoon leave the albuginea, and get upon the cord, where <lb/>they
              are joined by others, to be deſcribed preſently; but the tunica va- <lb/>ginalis has
              alſo other abſorbents, upon the anterior and lateral parts, which <lb/>have not the
              leaſt connection with the body of the teſticle, nor with the <lb/>albuginea, and which
              alſo ſoon blend with the former, on the beginning <lb/>of the cord. The abſorbents
              which ariſe out of the rete teſtis are ex- <lb/>ceedingly large, and appear to have no
              connection with its coats. A very <lb/>beautiful preparation of theſe veſſels I made
              at Windmill Street, at leaſt <lb/>ten years ago: I injected the vas deferens with
              quickſilver, and <lb/>had in view not only the filling of the epididymis, but the
              tubuli <lb/>teſtis themſelves. I had forced the mercury along the epididymis, and
              <lb/>was delighted to ſee it get into the body of the teſticle; the mercury
              <lb/>continued to deſcend very quickly through the glaſs injecting tube, <lb/>but I
              ſoon found that it was not running into the tubuli teſtis, but <lb/>into ſome veſſels
              which mounted along the cord; theſe I ſoon perceived <lb/>were abſorbents. The
              preparation was dried, afterwards put into oil of <lb/>turpentine; the abſorbents were
              then, and are now, diſtinctly ſeen riſing <lb/>out of the rete teſtis. I have alſo
              injected them from every part of <lb/>the epididymis, from its ſuperior extremity,
              from the middle, and from <pb n="141"/>
              <lb/>the lower end. The vaſculum aberrens Halleri is not an abſorbent veſ- <lb/>ſel,
              and cannot poſſibly return the ſemen to the blood; it is a luſus <lb/>naturæ, and
              either forms a cul de ſac, or, after many convolutions, <lb/>returns back again upon
              itſelf, and terminates where it began. It ſome- <lb/>times mounts four inches upon the
              cord, and then terminates in a <lb/>cæcum or blind pouch. Sometimes it is not a
              quarter of an inch in <lb/>length. I have ſeen it convolute like the epididymis
              itſelf; from <lb/>which it could not be diſtinguiſhed, till by maceration and
              diſſection <lb/>the cellular membrane had been removed. It may be compared with the
              <lb/>diverticulum ilii, ſo frequently met with in the human inteſtines. The
              <lb/>abſorbents having reached the cord, form from ſix to twelve trunks, <lb/>or more;
              ſome of theſe are ſometimes larger than a crow-quill: they do <lb/>not appear to
              anaſtomoſe with one another as they paſs along the cord; <lb/>at firſt they run
              ſtraight upwards, in the direction of the ring of the <lb/>external oblique muſcle;
              after which they are bent upon themſelves, and <lb/>paſs a little way in the direction
              of the ſpine of the ilium; after which <lb/>they are bent as it were a ſecond time
              upon themſelves, and run over <lb/>the anterior ſurface of the pſoas muſcle, and
              terminate at laſt in the <lb/>lumbar glands. The reaſon of their termination, ſo
              diſtant from their <lb/>origin, will eaſily occur to thoſe who reflect that the
              original ſituation <lb/>of the teſticle was at this place, and that it was natural for
              it, like the <lb/>other viſcera, to receive its blood-veſſels and nerves from the
              neareſt <lb/>trunks, and to return its abſorbents to the neareſt glands. I have al-
              <lb/>ready ſaid, that, in ſchirrus or cancer of the teſticle, theſe glands <lb/>were
              ſometimes infected, and enlarged to an immenſe ſize. Nuck <lb/>appears to have been
              the firſt who ſaw the lymphatics of the <lb/>teſticle. Haller ſays, <q rend="quotes"
                >Olim Cl. Nuckius flatu per venas ſperma- <lb/>ticas impulſo hæc vaſa diſtenderat,
                &amp; ad quadraginta vaſa lymphatica ex <lb/>albuginea tunica naſci, in quinque
                ramos confluere, ſuamque lympham <lb/>in ciſternam chyli deponere docuerat: aliud
                vero vaſculum cum ductu <lb/>deferente ad ureteram tendere, pariterque prope renes
                in ciſternam finiri. <lb/>Ligatis vaſis ſpermaticis, Graafius utebatur, &amp; ejus
                præceptor Sylvius. </q>
              <lb/>There is a circumſtance in this deſcription which renders it ſuſpicious;
              <lb/>that is, his aſſerting that they terminated immediately in the receptacle <lb/>of
              the chyle. In all my injections of thoſe veſſels, they have con- <lb/>ſtantly
              terminated in the lumbar glands. Dr. Joliffe appears to have <pb n="142"/>
              <lb/>been the firſt who ſaw thoſe veſſels on the ſpermatic cord of the living
              <lb/>human ſubject, as I have formerly obſerved. Haller appears alſo to <lb/>have ſeen
              them, but, with his uſual candor and modeſty, confeſſes that <lb/>he knew very little
              either of their origin or termination. <q rend="quotes">In homine <lb/>aliquoties vidi
                majuſcula, non tamen valde numeroſa, in funiculo <lb/>ſeminali cum venis
                adſcendentia, valvuloſa, ut tamen neque originem, <lb/>neque finem ſatis accurate
                viderem. </q>
            </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="space align-center">
              <lb/>The ABSORBENTS of the <hi rend="sc">Uterus</hi>. </head>
            <p rend="space indent">
              <lb/>AS the uterus has two ſets of arteries and veins, it has alſo two ſets <lb/>of
              abſorbent veſſels: one of theſe is the largeſt, and accompanies the <lb/>hypogaſtric
              arteries and veins; I have uſually named them <hi rend="italic">lymphatica
                <lb/>hypogaſtrica</hi>. The other is ſmaller, and accompanies the ſpermatic ar-
              <lb/>teries and veins; and which I have uſually diſtinguiſhed by the name of <lb/><hi
                rend="italic">ovarii lymphatica ſpermatica</hi>. In the gravid uterus, the trunks of
              the <lb/>hypogaſtric abſorbents are as large as a gooſe-quill, and the veſſels
              <lb/>themſelves ſo numerous, that, when they only were injected with quick-
              <lb/>ſilver, one would have been almoſt tempted to ſuppoſe that the uterus
              <lb/>conſiſted of abſorbents only. In the unimpregnated uterus they are <lb/>not ſo
              eaſily detected; but, when that viſcus has been injected by the <lb/>arteries and the
              veins, and has afterwards been macerated in water <lb/>for ſome days, the air then
              produced in the cellular membrane, by pu- <lb/>trefaction, gets into the abſorbent
              veſſels, and makes them per- <lb/>fectly diſtinct. The hypogaſtric plexus paſs from
              above downwards, <lb/>into glands which are ſituated on the ſides of the vagina; which
              en- <lb/>large, as the veſſels themſelves do, in the impregnated ſtate, though they
              <lb/>are almoſt inviſible in the unimpregnated ſtate: from theſe glands the
              <lb/>trunks of theſe veſſels paſs to other glands, ſurrounding the internal iliac
              <lb/>artery and vein, and which have been already deſcribed; the glands and
              <lb/>veſſels together I have diſtinguiſhed by the name of <hi rend="italic"
                >lymphaticorum <lb/>plexus iliacus internus</hi>: from theſe they paſs into the
              lumbar glands, <lb/>and there blending with the trunks from the lower extremities,
              they paſs <lb/>into the thoracic duct. On the internal ſurface of the gravid uterus,
              at <lb/>that part where the placenta had formerly adhered, I have ſeen the quick- <pb
                n="143"/>
              <lb/>ſilver, which I had thrown into theſe veſſels from the external ſurface of
              <lb/>the uterus, eſcaping at torn extremities of veſſels which had been paſſing
              <lb/>into the placenta, even contrary to the valves. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The abſorbents which accompany the ſpermatic artery and vein are <lb/>neither ſo
              large nor ſo numerous as the former; they belong chiefly to <lb/>the ovarium,
              fallopian tube, and the round ligament; they anaſtomoſe <lb/>with the former in ſuch a
              manner that they are frequently injected <lb/>from them; this cannot happen in any
              other way than contrary to the <lb/>valves. They run up on the ſpermatic cord, without
              paſſing through <lb/>any gland, till they come to the fame place where the abſorbents
              of <lb/>the teſticle terminate in the male; there they alſo terminate, in glands
              <lb/>ſituated on the ſides of the vertebræ of the loins: from theſe glands <lb/>they
              paſs out, and blending with the lumbar plexus, get into the thoracic <lb/>duct. In
              quadrupeds the abſorbent veſſels of the uterus are very eaſily <lb/>diſtinguiſhed, and
              they ramify exactly as the arteries and veins. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The abſorbent veſſels of the human uterus were firſt ſeen by Mery,
              <lb/>afterwards by Morgagni and Winſlow. Haller ſays, <q rend="quotes">Vidit in
                <lb/>humano utero Johannes Mery, in omnibus ad inſtrumentum genitale
                <lb/>pertinentibus partibus; tum I. B. Morgagnus in puerpera, turgida, ſub
                <lb/>membrana externa uteri repentia; &amp; I. B. Winſlow. </q>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>He himſelf appears never to have ſeen them: <q rend="quotes">Etſi in homine
                <lb/>ea vaſa nunquam mihi contigit vidiſſe, vidi tamen in majoribus beſtiis
                <lb/>etiam manifeſtiſſima. </q>
            </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="space align-center">
              <lb/>The ABSORBENTS of the <hi rend="sc">Bladder</hi>. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>THESE, in both ſexes, accompany the principal veins on the <lb/>bladder, and at
              the bottom, on the right and left ſide, paſs into the <lb/>glands ſurrounding the
              internal iliac artery and vein, but previous to <lb/>this they frequently paſs into
              ſmall glands ſituated on the ſides of the <lb/>bladder itſelf. Zellerus has given a
              deſcription of thoſe veſſels, in a <lb/>treatiſe, which I have not ſeen. Haller ſays
                <q rend="quotes">Zellerus vaſa lym- <lb/>phatica (veſicæ) injecto vinculo
                confirmavit; </q> and, though Haller had <lb/>not ſeen the abſorbents themſelves, he
              had ſeen the ſmall glands which <pb n="144"/>
              <lb/>I have mentioned, and for that reaſon has no doubts of Zellerus's de-
              <lb/>ſcription. He ſays, <q rend="quotes">In veſica quidem non vidi, ſunt tamen in
                cellu- <lb/>loſa tela, ei circumpoſta glandulæ conglobatæ, quæ rei fidem faciunt.
              </q>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>I have uſually diſtinguiſhed theſe by the name of <hi rend="italic">veſicæ
                lymphatica</hi>. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="align-center space">
              <lb/>The ABSORBENTS of the <hi rend="sc">Rectum</hi>. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>AS the blood-veſſels of the rectum are in proportion larger than in <lb/>moſt
              parts of the great inteſtines, ſo are its abſorbents. It is alſo ſur- <lb/>rounded
              with abſorbent glands. Mr. Hewſon ſays, <q rend="quotes">The lymphatic veſ- <lb/>ſels
                ariſe even from the rectum, as can be ſeen in quadrupeds that are <lb/>opened
                immediately after death, or in fiſh when a coloured injection is <lb/>thrown into
                their lymphatic ſyſtem. </q> He ſeems to me to have had no <lb/>adequate idea of the
              abſorbent ſyſtem: I could as eaſily conceive a part <lb/>to be without arteries and
              veins as without abſorbents. Haller ſays, <lb/>
              <q rend="quotes">Qui negaverunt craſſis inteſtinis lactea data eſſe, ii non ſatis ad
                <lb/>difficultatem negationis univerſalis adtenderunt. </q> Mr. Hewſon ſhould
              <lb/>have known, that the abſorbents of the rectum were the firſt diſcovered
              <lb/>after thoſe of the liver, by Rudbeck; and, from the authority <lb/>I laſt
              mentioned it appears, <q rend="quotes">Prima etiam lymphatica vaſa, quæ <lb/>præter
                hepar in hbmine viſa ſunt, ea in recto inteſtino adparuerunt. </q>
              <lb/>Auerbach alſo aſſerts, that he had ſeen the abſorbents of the rectum <lb/>with
              his naked eye; <q rend="quotes">Sibi nudo oculo in elapſo inteſtino viſa eſſe. </q>
              <lb/>Haller is here obliged to reject the exiſtence of the ampullula; and the
              <lb/>reaſon he gives us is, that there are no villi formed on the internal ſur-
              <lb/>face of the rectum. He ſays, <q rend="quotes">Cum villi hic nulli ſint, neceſſe
                <lb/>eſt, etiam alio modo &amp; abſque ampullula, chylum de inteſtino poſſe
                <lb/>ſorberi. </q> The lymphatics of the rectum, having paſſed the glands that
              <lb/>lie upon it, terminate at laſt in the lumbar glands, where, blending <lb/>with
              the larger trunks of the abſorbents, already deſcribed, the fluids <lb/>they have
              abſorbed are carried to the thoracic duct. Thoſe I have uſually <lb/>called <hi
                rend="italic">lymphatica hæmorrhoidea interna</hi>. </p>
          </div>
          <pb n="145"/>
          <div>
            <head rend="space align-center">
              <lb/>The ABSORBENTS of the <hi rend="sc">Hips</hi>. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>THESE I have uſually diſtinguiſhed by the name of <hi rend="italic">lymphatica
                <lb/>ſciatica</hi>. Some of theſe, I have already ſaid, go round by the great tro-
              <lb/>chanter of the thigh to the glands of the groin; or paſs on the inſide <lb/>of
              the thigh, between it and the ſcrotum, to the ſame glands: but by <lb/>far the greater
              number go in at the ſciatic notch, with the arteries <lb/>glutea and ſciatica, and
              terminate in the glands ſurrounding the internal <lb/>iliac artery and vein; and when
              they have paſſed through thoſe glands, <lb/>they terminate at laſt in the lumbar
              glands, from whence their fluids go <lb/>into the thoracic duct. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="align-center space">
              <lb/>The ABSORBENTS of the <hi rend="sc">Kidnies</hi>. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THE abſorbents of the viſcera are commonly found in two ſets; one <lb/>which runs
              on the external ſurface of the viſcus, and another deep ſeated, <lb/>which accompanies
              the larger blood-veſſels. In the ſound ſtate of the <lb/>kidney, I have very ſeldom
              ſeen the ſuperficial abſorbents; but in caſes <lb/>where the kidnies were diſeaſed,
              and formed into large hydatids, thoſe <lb/>veſſels, which, in the ſound ſtate of the
              viſcus, from their minuteneſs <lb/>are with great difficulty ſeen, having enlarged
              with the diſeaſed parts, <lb/>become perfectly diſtinct. They run from the outer edge
              of the kidney <lb/>towards the inner, where they either blend in with the
              deeper-ſeated ſet, <lb/>or go ſeparately to be inſerted into the lumbar glands,
              already deſcribed. <lb/>Nuck's engravings of theſe veſſels appear to me highly
              ſuſpicious. Theſe <lb/>I have uſually diſtinguiſhed by the name of <hi rend="italic"
                >lymphatica renis exteriora</hi>. In a <lb/>diſeaſed kidney, where its ſubſtance, in
              conſequence of ſtones being con- <lb/>tained in the pelvis, had ſhrunk, and left the
              principal branches of the veins <lb/>and arteries naked, I injected nine abſorbents
              with quickſilver; which run <lb/>upon the outſide of the blood-veſſels, and ramified
              as they did. When <lb/>they came near the trunks of the emulgent artery and vein, they
              were <lb/>more cloſely collected into a plexus, and, running nearly parallel to each
              <lb/>other, terminated at laſt in the lumbar glands, a little to the outſide of the
                <pb n="146"/>
              <lb/>origin of the emulgent artery. Thoſe I have uſually diſtinguiſhed by the
              <lb/>name of <hi rend="italic">lymphatica renis profundiora</hi>. By making a ligature
              upon the emul- <lb/>gent vein, and compreſſing the ſubſtance of the kidney, whilſt it
              was in ſitu, <lb/>I have forced the blood, which had tranſuded into the cellular
              ſubſtance <lb/>of that viſcus, into the mouths of the abſorbents, and thence into
              their <lb/>branches; they have then ſhewn themſelves to have been exceedingly
              <lb/>numerous, at leaſt equal to the blood-veſſels. It is in this ſtate I have
              <lb/>repreſented them, in the ſubſtance of the kidney, in the large figure an-
              <lb/>nexed. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="46"/>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
