<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Hale: Case of a Fracture of the Sternum</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>John Hale</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Case of a Fracture of the Sternum, by John Hale, Surgeon to the New
              Finsbury Dispensary</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">N4680</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N4680"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed In The Year MDCCLXXXVII.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1787</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="5"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="28"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="2"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">National Library of Medicine</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3308205189</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K002999.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Surgical or anatominal work"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <pb xml:id="page_3" n="iii"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">A</hi>LTHO' Fractures of the <w part="I"
            >Ster-</w><lb/><w part="F">num</w> are deſcribed by every <lb/>writer on the accidents
          to which the <lb/>bones are ſubject, yet they appear to <lb/>have ſeldom occurred, even to
          the <lb/>oldeſt practitioner. All thoſe authors <lb/>whom I have had an opportunity of
          <lb/>conſulting, very fully deſcribe in <lb/>what manner this accident may <w part="I"
            >hap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pen</w>, and as fully preſcribe the rules <lb/>to be obſerved
          in the treatment of it. <lb/>They ſeem, however, to have copied <lb/>from each other,
          without adducing <lb/>any proofs to corroborate their <w part="I">aſſer-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tions</w>. <hi rend="sc">Du Verney</hi>, in his excellent <lb/>Treatiſe on the
          Diſeaſes of the Bones, <pb xml:id="page_4" n="iv"/><lb/>is the only writer (that I have
          met <lb/>with) who enters fully and <w part="I">circum-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtantially</w>
          into Fractures of this part, <lb/>he mentions three caſes which had <lb/>occurred to him,
          two of which proved <lb/>inſtantly fatal; and the third <w part="I">recover-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ed</w>, but the patient remained an <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >valid</w> during the reſt of his life. He <lb/>likewiſe aſſerts, that all Fractures of
          <lb/>the Sternum are to be regarded as <lb/>mortal; <q rend="quotes">tho' there have been
              <w part="I">pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tients</w> whoſe conſtitutions have held <lb/>out,
            and have been cured.</q> I can <lb/>only regret that he gives no <w part="I"
            >informa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> where thoſe caſes are recorded. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The ſingularity of the following <lb/>caſe, the unexpected favourable
            <w part="I">ter-</w><pb xml:id="page_5" n="v"/><lb/><w part="F">mination</w> of it,
          together with the <lb/>ſolicitations of my friends, are the <lb/>motives which induce me
          to have a <lb/>few copies printed for their peruſal. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>My particular thanks are due to my <lb/>worthy Friend and Colleague
            <hi rend="sc">Dr. <lb/>Skeete</hi>, and to <hi rend="sc">Mr. Haighton</hi>, for
          <lb/>their kind advice and aſſiſtance during <lb/>the progreſs of the cure. They who
          <lb/>are acquainted with the profeſſional <lb/>abilities of thoſe Gentlemen, will
          <lb/>rather approve my ſilence, than <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">mend</w> me for
          any further eulogium <lb/>on their merits. </p>
        <lb/>
        <dateline><hi rend="italic">October,</hi> 1787. </dateline>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_6"/>
      <head rend="align-center space"><lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)">CASE</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(0.5)">OF A </hi><lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">FRACTURED STERNUM</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">J</hi>OHN OATES, aged 38, by trade <lb/>a
        cabinet-maker, being in company <lb/>with ſome friends at a Tavern, and <w part="I"
          >drink-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> freely, a diſpute aroſe, which <w part="I"
          >termi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nated</w> in blows, and he was unfortunately <lb/>thrown down
        with ſuch violence on the edge <lb/>of a chair, as to cauſe a fracture of the <lb/>Sternum,
        about four inches above the <lb/>enſiform cartilage. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_7" n="8"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Being carried home, a neighbouring <lb/>Apothecary was ſent for, who
        ordered ſome <lb/>draughts to be taken, and a volatile liniment <lb/>to embrocate the part.
        Symptoms, <w part="I">how-</w><lb/><w part="F">ever</w>, ſoon became alarming, great pain
        <lb/>and difficulty in reſpiration, cough, and <lb/>oppreſſion on the lungs. Theſe
        complaints <lb/>were ſuffered to increaſe, without any means <lb/>being uſed to alleviate
        them, for the ſpace <lb/>of one week. He often ſpoke with <w part="I">cer-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">tainty</w> of his breaſt being broken, and ſaid <lb/>he could <q rend="quotes"
          >feel the bones jar againſt each <lb/>other.</q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Obtaining no relief, and being poſitively <lb/>told that his complaint
        was only a bruiſe, <lb/>he diſmiſſed his Apothecary, and applied <lb/>to the <hi rend="sc"
          >New Finsbury Dispensary</hi>, on <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tueſday,</hi> the 23d <hi
          rend="italic">January,</hi> 1787. He <lb/>was immediately viſited by <hi rend="sc">Dr.
          Skeete</hi>
        <pb xml:id="page_8" n="9"/><lb/>and myſelf, with <hi rend="sc">Mr. Haighton</hi>, who
        <lb/>happened to call on me that morning. On <lb/>examination, we perceived that a fracture
        <lb/>had taken place as deſcribed above, but <lb/>how much of the bone was depreſſed, or
        <lb/>how deep the depreſſion might be, we could <lb/>not readily aſcertain, owing to an <w
          part="I">inflam-</w><lb/><w part="F">mation</w> which occupied the inferior and
        <lb/>middle part of the Sternum, and which <lb/>ſeemed haſtily advancing to ſuppuration.
        <lb/>His pulſe was hard and full, the cough <lb/>frequent, and attended with ſuch diſtreſs
        <lb/>and anxiety to the patient, that he ſaid he <lb/>ſhould be perfectly well if the cough
        could <lb/>be ſtopped; for at that time he could plainly <lb/>feel the broken edges of the
        bone grate on <lb/>each other, the irritation of which was <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">moſt</w> inſupportable, and prevented his taking <lb/>any reſt. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_9" n="10"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>He was immediately blooded to the <lb/>quantity of ſixteen ounces, which
        was much <lb/>inflamed, a laxative mixture ordered to be <lb/>taken occaſionally, an
        emulſion of Sperm. <lb/>Ceti, cum Sal. Nitri, and Tinct. Thebaic. <lb/>every three hours;
        and every other means <lb/>uſed to obviate the effects which we imagined <lb/>would be the
        conſequences of ſuch an <w part="I">acci-</w><lb/><w part="F">dent</w>. On the day
        following, the pulſe <lb/>was rather ſofter, and the reſpiration not <lb/>quite ſo
        laborious; ten ounces more of <lb/>blood were taken from him, which had the <lb/>ſame
        inflammatory appearance; the <w part="I">inflam-</w><lb/><w part="F">mation</w> on the
        Sternum was more <w part="I">circum-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſcribed</w>, and evidently ſhewed
        that ſome <lb/>pus was already formed. The laxative <lb/>medicine was ordered to be
        repeated, and <lb/>thirty drops of Tinct. Thebaic to be taken <lb/>at night. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_10" n="11"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Symptoms continued much the ſame till <lb/>Saturday, the 27th of
        January, when Mr. <lb/><hi rend="sc">Cooper</hi>, Surgeon to Guy's Hoſpital, <w part="I"
          >fa-</w><lb/><w part="F">voured</w> me with his company, and was of <lb/>opinion that the
        abſceſs on the Sternum <lb/>ſhould be immediately opened. About ſix <lb/>ounces of pus were
        diſcharged. On paſſing <lb/>my finger to the bottom of the wound, I <lb/>expected to have
        diſcovered the broken <lb/>portion of bone, but did not, probably <lb/>owing to the parts
        having become thickened <lb/>in conſequence of the preceding <w part="I"
          >inflamma-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>. The fracture, however, was evident <lb/>to one
        ſenſe, though not to the other; for <lb/>on the patient deſiring us to place our ear <lb/>on
        the wound, we could hear the edges of <lb/>the bone grate on each other at every <w part="I"
          >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſpiration</w>. The pulſe being ſtill full, it was <lb/>thought
        neceſſary to draw ſix ounces more <lb/>of blood. He had no reſt this night, the <pb
          xml:id="page_11" n="12"/><lb/>cough being inceſſant. On Sunday, the <lb/>28th, the
        countenance appeared much <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">jected</w>, the ſkin hot, but
        the pulſe calm; <lb/>I ordered the opiate to be increaſed to <lb/>ſeventy drops of Tinct.
        Thebaic, and <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">plied</w> a bandage, or rather a girt,
        (ſuch as <lb/>I uſe in fractures of the ribs, and which is <lb/>made to buckle to what
        degree of <w part="I">tight-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w> may be requiſite) in hopes of
        being <lb/>able to confine the motion of the Sternum, <lb/>and thereby prevent the
        irritation which the <lb/>fracture produced. I intended to have <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">plied</w> this bandage when I firſt viſited him, <lb/>but it was thought that if
        much preſſure <lb/>was thrown on the ribs, it might probably <lb/>cauſe the inferior broken
        part of the bone <lb/>to protrude through the inflamed <w part="I">integu-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ments</w>, and be productive of much danger; <lb/>the bandage was therefore
        deferred till the <lb/>abſceſs was opened, and the bone not being <pb xml:id="page_12"
          n="13"/><lb/>evident to the touch, we had leſs to fear <lb/>from the application of a
        moderate preſſure. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>He experienced much relief in <w part="I">conſe-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >quence</w> of the bandage being applied, the <lb/>cough was greatly abated, the opiate <w
          part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">cured</w> a ſound ſleep, and the bone was not
        <lb/>troubleſome in inſpiration; the pulſe was <lb/>perfectly calm, and the wound diſcharged
        <lb/>a healthy pus. He was now ordered ſome <lb/>mutton broth, having hitherto been confined
        <lb/>to water-gruel. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>From this time to Monday the ſixth of <lb/>February, the ſymptoms
        indicated much <lb/>danger; he ſweated profuſely, coughed <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ceſſantly</w>, and what he expectorated was <lb/>often tinged with blood. He took
        liberally <lb/>of a decoction of Bark with Elixir of <lb/>Vitriol, drank warm milk every
        morning, <lb/>and uſed ſuch nouriſhing articles of diet as <pb xml:id="page_13" n="14"
        /><lb/>were directed by <hi rend="sc">Dr. Skeete</hi>. This plan <lb/>ſeemed to ſucceed, for
        from the 6th to <lb/>12th of February, the ſweats were much <lb/>diminiſhed, and the cough
        leſs frequent; <lb/>but the wound diſcharged a fœtid ichor in <lb/>great abundance, which
        proceeded from a <lb/>ſinus extending above, and for ſome ſpace <lb/>round the ſuperior part
        of the wound. We <lb/>were now of opinion that this ichorous <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">charge</w> might proceed from the edges of <lb/>the broken bone, if ſo, it became
          <w part="I">adviſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">able</w> to make a further opening, to <w part="I"
          >endea-</w><lb/><w part="F">vour</w> to reach the foundation of the <w part="I"
          >miſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">chief</w>, and then purſue ſuch a courſe as <lb/>might be
        indicated from examining the <lb/>condition of the parts. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>This, however, was delayed till Saturday, <lb/>the 17th of February, as
        for ſome days we <lb/>pleaſed ourſelves with the idea that the <pb xml:id="page_14" n="15"
        /><lb/>parts would unite independent of our <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >terference</w>, eſpecially as the diſcharge from <lb/>the wound became thicker; (<hi
          rend="sc">Dr. Skeete</hi>
        <lb/>having added Gum Myrrh to the decoction <lb/>of Bark) but we were unhappily <w part="I"
          >diſap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pointed</w> in our expectations; and as no <lb/>time was to be
        loſt, I informed him of the <lb/>plan which (on conſultation) we intended <lb/>to follow,
        viz. to make an inciſion down <lb/>to the bone, to examine its condition, and, <lb/>if
        neceſſary, to remove whatever part of it <lb/>might, in our opinion, be an obſtacle to a
        <lb/>perfect union. He readily aſſented to <w part="I">what-</w><lb/><w part="F">ever</w>
        might be judged expedient for his <lb/>relief; not on his own account, having <lb/>ſuffered
        ſo much that life was become a <lb/>burden, but for the ſake of his wife and <lb/>five
        infant children, whoſe ſubſiſtence <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">pended</w> ſolely on
        his labour. I made an <lb/>inciſion from about an inch above the edge <pb xml:id="page_15"
          n="16"/><lb/>of the old wound, and continued it to the <lb/>bottom, the knife grated on
        the bone, and <lb/>the inferior part became evident to the <lb/>touch, tho' covered
        externally with a ſmooth <lb/>granulation. It now appeared that the <lb/>fracture was not
        immediately on the centre <lb/>of the Sternum, but more inclined to the <lb/>right ſide of
        it; that portion to which the <lb/>ribs are united was firmly attached to them, <lb/>and in
        conſequence of the inciſion, the <lb/>fractured part had ſeparated from its <w part="I"
          >ſitua-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, and expoſed the cavity of the <w part="I"
          >mediaſti-</w><lb/><w part="F">num</w>. I paſſed my finger into the cavity, and <lb/>felt
        the parts <hi rend="italic">apparently</hi> carious on each ſide. <lb/>We now could only
        conjecture that a large <lb/>exfoliation would enſue; but, in all <w part="I"
          >proba-</w><lb/><w part="F">bility</w>, the conſequence of this operation <lb/>might prove
        fatal, either by the pus lodging <lb/>in the cavity of the mediaſtinum, or by <lb/>cauſing
        that irritation often conſequent to <pb xml:id="page_16" n="17"/><lb/>the expoſure of
        cavities. Theory certainly <lb/>juſtified us in theſe concluſions, but practice <lb/>has
        happily convinced us that <w part="I">notwith-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtanding</w> theſe
        diſcouragements, there was <lb/>ſtill a method left to prevent what we had <lb/>ſo much
        reaſon to fear. The bone, tho' <lb/>broken, was not denuded, both the ſuperior <lb/>and
        inferior portions were covered with <lb/>granulations; it then became an object to
        <lb/>endeavour to promote a union of thoſe parts <lb/>by incarnation, ſimilar to what occurs
        in <lb/>compound fractures, in which light it might <lb/>now certainly be conſidered. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I muſt here obſerve, that on the day <w part="I">fol-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">lowing</w>, I found him much better, he <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >came</w> eaſier after the operation, coughed <lb/>but little, and ſlept the greateſt part
        of the <lb/>night without taking the opiate; this was <lb/>the firſt natural ſleep he had
        enjoyed ſince <pb xml:id="page_17" n="18"/><lb/>the accident happened, for the opiates only
        <lb/>ſerved to palliate the cough, without <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">curing</w>
        any refreſhing ſleep, altho' he <w part="I">gene-</w><lb/><w part="F">rally</w> took one
        hundred drops of Tinct. <lb/>Thebaic; the expectoration alſo appeared <lb/>more frothy, and
        he had no difficulty in <lb/>diſcharging it from the lungs. This <w part="I"
          >amend-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w> was but temporary, for from the 17th <lb/>to the 24th
        of February, the opiates were <lb/>again obliged to be given. Our attempts <lb/>to procure a
        union of the parts proved <lb/>abortive, and the inferior edge of the bone <lb/>protruded
        through the wound at every <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſpiration</w>, and
        conſequently expoſed the <lb/>cavity of the mediaſtinum. There ſeemed <lb/>no proſpect of
        any exfoliation, I therefore <lb/>omitted the former bandage, as it appeared <lb/>to have no
        power to anſwer the intention we <lb/>had in view, and paſſed a common roller <lb/>round the
        inferior part of the Sternum; <pb xml:id="page_18" n="19"/><lb/>the preſſure of this brought
        the lower <w part="I">por-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> in contact with the upper, and we
        had <lb/>the pleaſure of ſeeing a union effected in <lb/>a few days. The ſweats from this
        time <lb/>totally ceaſed, and the cough was not <lb/>troubleſome. I removed him to
        Iſlington, <lb/>for the benefit of the air, there the cough <lb/>entirely left him, and he
        ſlept without taking <lb/>the opiate. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>When he attempted a deep inſpiration, <lb/>he felt a ſmall preſſure on
        the fractured <lb/>part, and alſo on the right ſide of the <lb/>wound; which ſide was
        evidently enlarged, <lb/>and felt as if the cartilages of the ribs had <lb/>received ſome
        injury from the fall. He <lb/>complained that the air was too ſharp for <lb/>him, and (to
        uſe his own expreſſion) <q rend="quotes">felt <lb/>like vinegar in his noſtrils;</q> indeed
        this <lb/>was ſo much the caſe, that if he ſtood at the <pb xml:id="page_19" n="20"
        /><lb/>window when open, or attempted to walk <lb/>out, the air inſtantly cauſed him to
        ſneeze <lb/>violently, which gave great pain to the <lb/>fractured part. I was therefore
        obliged to <lb/>remove him from Iſlington, where he only <lb/>continued four days; and for
        two or three <lb/>nights after he returned home, the cough <lb/>again became violent, ſo
        that I was under <lb/>the neceſſity of repeating the opiates. As <lb/>the wound healed, the
        cough abated, and <lb/>his only complaint was that of great <w part="I">weak-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ness</w>, and a total inability to uſe his arms <lb/>with any freedom of motion.
        He could <lb/>ſtoop to buckle his ſhoe, could take up any <lb/>weight, but was utterly
        unable to perform <lb/>any <hi rend="italic">lateral motion.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>March. During this month, he was <lb/>perfectly free from complaint; had
        taken <lb/>Pulv. Cort. Peruv. 3. ter die. The <pb xml:id="page_20" n="21"/><lb/>enlargement
        related to have been on the <lb/>right ſide of the wound was much leſſened, <lb/>but an
        abſceſs formed on that ſide <w part="I">imme-</w><lb/><w part="F">diately</w> on the breaſt,
        which broke on <lb/>Friday, the 30th of March. It appeared <lb/>quite ſuperficial, and to
        have had no <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">nection</w> with the original injury. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>April. The wound on the Sternum was <lb/>now healed to about the ſize of
        a ſix-pence, <lb/>and from this a vaſt diſcharge was daily <lb/>evacuated; ſuſpecting ſome
        ſinus, I paſſed <lb/>the probe, and found one, which extended <lb/>about two inches on the
        right ſide between <lb/>the two inferior cartilages, directly above <lb/>that enlargement
        already mentioned. This <lb/>ſinus was laid open, and continued <w part="I"
          >diſcharg-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> till the beginning of Auguſt, when it <lb/>was
        propoſed to apply a cauſtic on the <lb/>part; the action of which laid bare the <pb
          xml:id="page_21" n="22"/><lb/>fractured portions of the bone, the ſuperior <lb/>edge
        greatly depreſſed, and the intermediate <lb/>ſpace filled with a kind of membranous
        <lb/>ſubſtance, which had prevented an oſſific <lb/>union of the parts. It was now curious
        to <lb/>obſerve the proceſs which nature was daily <lb/>executing, in order to fill up the
        vacuity; <lb/>at every dreſſing ſome new excitement <lb/>was perceived; increaſed
          vaſcularity<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* In order more fully to comprehend
          what I mean by <lb/>an "increaſed vaſcularity," it is neceſſary to obſerve, <lb/>that when
          the ſlough (which the action of the cauſtic <lb/>had produced) was ſeparated from the
          Sternum, a very <lb/>large portion of the inferior part of the bone <hi rend="italic"
            >appeared</hi>
          <lb/>to be entirely deprived of the living principle; but <lb/>fortunately this was not
          the caſe; every day's inſpection <lb/>fully proved it, by that portion becoming more and
          <lb/>more florid, and by the aſſiſtance of a glaſs, we could <lb/>plainly diſcover new
          veſſels ſhooting in a tranſverſe <lb/>direction through the oſſeous fibres. I therefore
          truſt <lb/>that the term of "increaſed vaſcularity," is not <w part="I">miſ-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">applied</w>, and I am at a loſs for any other to expreſs my <lb/>meaning more
          intelligibly. </note> in the <lb/>living portions of bone, by which the carious <pb
          xml:id="page_22" n="23"/><lb/>part became more ſeparated, and <w part="I"
          >granu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lations</w> ariſing from the ſurrounding ſoft <lb/>parts. On
        the 10th of October, the <w part="I">exfo-</w><lb/><w part="F">liation</w> from the inferior
        part took place, <lb/>the portion of bone was but ſmall, healthy <lb/>granulations being
        ſubſtituted in its place. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>We now aſſiſted him with an elaſtic truſs, <lb/>which proved of ſo much
        ſervice as to <lb/>enable him again to follow his buſineſs of <lb/>a cabinet-maker. This
        truſs makes an <lb/>equal preſſure on each ſide of the breaſt, <lb/>and ſupports the ſternum
        in ſuch a manner, <lb/>that if he takes it off, he ſays, he feels <q rend="quotes">as
          <lb/>if his inſide was falling in pieces.</q>
        <w part="I">With-</w><lb/><w part="F">out</w> it, he is incapable of performing any
        <lb/>lateral motion. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The wound now healed, without any <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >terruption</w>, and was perfectly cicatrized on <lb/>the 23d of October. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_23" n="24"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The following obſervations are ſuch as <lb/>will naturally ſuggeſt
        themſelves on an <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tentive</w> conſideration of the above
        facts. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Firſt, That the caſe was attended with <lb/>conſiderable danger,
        throughout the greater <lb/>part of its progreſs; but from very different, <lb/>and even
        oppoſite circumſtances, at different <lb/>periods. In the beginning, the ſymptoms <lb/>of
        inflammation in the Thorax ſeemed to <lb/>be ſo general and violent, that without the
        <lb/>free uſe of the lancet, aſſiſted by dilution <lb/>and the antiphlogiſtic regimen, it is
          <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">bable</w> that a fatal termination would ſpeedily
        <lb/>have enſued; but the only method by which <lb/>this could be prevented, doubtleſs
        aſſiſted <lb/>in inducing that ſtate of debility and hectic <lb/>under which the patient was
        afterwards in <lb/>danger of ſinking, and which required the <lb/>liberal exhibition of
        Bark, Elixir of Vitriol, <pb xml:id="page_24" n="25"/><lb/>Myrrh, and ſuch nouriſhing
        articles of diet <lb/>as were judiciouſly preſcribed by Dr. Skeete. <lb/>The ſame thing
        happens in many caſes of <lb/>diſeaſe which fall under the care of the <lb/>Surgeon; and the
        preſent inſtance is a ſtrong <lb/>illuſtration of the neceſſity of a particular
        <lb/>attention being required to the ſtate of the <lb/>conſtitution, as well as to the
        condition of <lb/>the diſeaſed part. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Secondly, It may appear extraordinary, <lb/>that notwithſtanding the
        frequent expoſure <lb/>of the cavity of the Mediaſtinum, which <lb/>ſeemed to take place
        when the broken edges <lb/>of the bone were ſeparated, during the <lb/>alternate motions of
        inſpiration and <w part="I">expi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ration</w>, that this expoſure was not
        followed <lb/>by any repeated attack of inflammation, or <lb/>by any effuſion of pus into
        the cavities of <lb/>the Thorax, tho' we had more than once <lb/>ſufficient reaſons to
        apprehend ſuch effects, <pb xml:id="page_25" n="26"/><lb/>eſpecially when the expectoration
        aſſumed <lb/>a purulent and bloody appearance, with <lb/>ſymptoms of hectic. The event
        therefore <lb/>ſeems to prove that ſuch adheſions muſt <lb/>have taken place between the
        Lungs and <lb/>Pleura in the neighbourhood of the injured <lb/>part, as compleatly to have
        prevented any <lb/>ſuch effect. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Thirdly, After ſome months, the treatment <lb/>was almoſt entirely
        confined to the part; <lb/>the healing of the wound being prevented <lb/>by the ſtate of the
        bone underneath, as <lb/>has been already mentioned. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Fourthly, That the loſs of ſubſtance <lb/>which the Sternum has
        ſuſtained, is at <lb/>preſent ſupplied by granulation only; and <lb/>whether nature will in
        this caſe, as in many <lb/>others, reſtore the part to its original ſtate, <lb/>by a bony
        depoſition, time alone will be <lb/>able to diſcover. </p>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_26" n="27"/>
        <head rend="align-center size(1.5)"><lb/>POSTSCRIPT. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">S</hi>INCE the foregoing ſheets came from <lb/>the
          preſs, I have read an account of a <lb/>Fractured Sternum, in the <hi rend="sc">Edinburgh
            Medical <lb/>Commentaries</hi>, Vol. IV. p. 185, <lb/>by Mr. George Borthwick, Surgeon
          to the <lb/>14th regiment of Dragoons. In many <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſtances</w> the ſymptoms agreed with thoſe <lb/>mentioned in my caſe, particularly the
          <lb/>grating noiſe in the time of reſpiration. <lb/>Mr. Borthwick being immediately called
          in, <lb/>prevented that train of dangerous ſymptoms <lb/>which unfortunately befel my
          patient. The <lb/>account being drawn up with great preciſion, <lb/>I refer my reader to
          the book itſelf for <lb/>further information. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_27" n="28"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The addition of this Poſtſcript affords <lb/>me an opportunity of
          ſaying, that my <w part="I">pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tient</w> called on me at the
          Diſpenſary, on the <lb/>30th ult. and informed me that he had <lb/>gained ſo much ſtrength
          within a few days, <lb/>as to be enabled to perform the moſt <w part="I">la-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">borious</w> part of his work, without the <lb/>aſſiſtance of the truſs. </p>
        <lb/>
        <dateline><hi rend="italic">November,</hi> 1787. </dateline>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
