<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Blane: A Lecture on Muscular Motion</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Gilbert Blane</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">A Lecture on Muscular Motion: Read at the Royal Society, the 13th and
              20th of November, 1788. By Gilbert Blane, M.D. F.R.S.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T104111</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T104111"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed by Joseph Cooper; and sold by J. Murray, No. 32, Fleet
                  Street; J. Johnson, No. 71, St. Paul's Church Yard; and J. Stockdale, Opposite
                  Burlington House, Piccadilly.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1788</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="57"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3308300482</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K083729.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Surgical or anatominal work"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front> </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="size(0.5)">A</hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)">LECTURE </hi><lb/><hi rend="size(0.5)">ON</hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">MUSCULAR MOTION</hi>. </head> 
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend= "size(0.5)"> Importance of the
            ſubject. </note><hi rend="sc"><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>his </hi>Lecture was founded by Dr.
          Croone, who was one of the <lb/>original Fellows of this Society, having been previouſly a
          member of <lb/>thoſe private meetings which laid the foundation of this inſtitution.
          <lb/>He was not only a phyſician of learning and eminence, but his <w part="I"
            >cha-</w><lb/><w part="F">racter</w> for taſte, as well as for mathematical and natural
          knowledge, <lb/>was ſo diſtinguiſhed, that he was elected Profeſſor of Rhetoric in Greſham
            College<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* See Ward's Lives of the Greſham
            Profeſſors. </note>, and was appointed a member of the firſt council <lb/>of the Royal
          Society. What prompted him to perpetuate and keep <lb/>alive an attention to this ſubject
          was, no doubt, an opinion of its <lb/>importance and difficulty. There are certain
          branches of <w part="I">know-</w>
          <pb xml:id="page_3" n="2"/><lb/><w part="F">ledge</w> which, being conſidered as belonging
          to particular profeſſions, <lb/>appear leſs intereſting to men who entertain a taſte for
          general ſcience; <lb/>and this has in ſome meaſure been the caſe with inquiries
          <lb/>relating to the animal œconomy. But when we conſider the rank <lb/>which animated
          beings hold in the ſcale of Nature, and that <w part="I">Muſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cular</w> Motion involves ſome of the moſt important circumſtances <lb/>relating to
          them, it cannot be denied that this is a ſubject highly <lb/>intereſting, as a branch of
          natural knowledge in general, <w part="I">indepen-</w><lb/><w part="F">dent</w> of its
          utility as ſubſervient to medicine. For though ſenſitive <lb/>beings bear no aſſignable
          proportion to the great volume of the <w part="I">ma-</w><lb/><w part="F">terial</w>
          world, yet as man belongs to this claſs of exiſtence, and as <lb/>all other exiſtence
          would ſeem to be created in vain, unleſs there <lb/>were beings capable of perception and
          enjoyment, the inveſtigation <lb/>of animal nature appears to be of the utmoſt importance,
          not only <lb/>as the grounds of a uſeful art, but as an object of philoſophical
          <lb/>curioſity. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> Extenſive <w part="I"
              >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">fluence</w> of <w part="I">muſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">cular</w>
            power in the animal œconomy. </note>Muſcular motion is juſtly deemed an important and a
          characteriſtic <lb/>attribute of animated beings, not only as conferring that <w part="I"
            >loco-mo-</w><lb/><w part="F">tive</w> faculty peculiar to animals, and that power by
          which they are <lb/>enabled to exerciſe a command over external objects, but alſo as it
          <lb/>conſtitutes that energy by which the motion of the fluids and all <lb/>the internal
          functions of the body are carried on. For we are to <lb/>conſider as muſcles not only
          thoſe large maſſes of fleſh which <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſe</w> ſo great a
          proportion of the whole bulk of the body, but <w part="I">like-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >wiſe</w> all the minuter organs ſubſervient to circulation, nutrition, <lb/>and
          ſecretion; ſince not only the heart itſelf, but the whole <w part="I">vaſcu-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">lar</w> ſyſtem and the inteſtines, owe their action to certain powers of
          <lb/>irritability and contractility peculiar to muſcular fibres. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_4" n="3"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In inveſtigating this ſubject, it ſeems moſt natural to begin by
          <lb/>comparing the muſcles, and the motion belonging to them, to other <lb/>modifications
          of matter and motion that occur in nature. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> Properties of a Muſcle in its
            dead ſtate. </note>A muſcle, even in ſo far as its ſtructure is an object of our ſenſes
          <lb/>in its dead ſtate, has characters which diſtinguiſh it from every <lb/>other
          ſubſtance in nature. The moſt ſtriking of theſe, is its <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">gular</w> organization of parallel fibres. The fibrous ſtructure is, <w
            part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">deed</w>, found in other parts of the body, ſuch as the
          tendons and <lb/>ligaments, and alſo in vegetables, ſome of which are even <lb/>poſſeſſed
          of viſible irritability; and a ſimilar conformation is manifeſt in ſome <lb/>minerals,
          ſuch as the <hi rend="italic">asbeſtos;</hi> but there is a certain degree of <w part="I"
            >tena-</w><lb/><w part="F">city</w>, elaſticity, and moiſture, which, joined to its
          fibrous <w part="I">organi-</w><lb/><w part="F">zation</w>, diſtinguiſh it from every
          other form of matter. With <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">gard</w> to the minute
          ſtructure of muſcles, though ſome have fancied <lb/>they have ſeen, by the help of
          glaſſes, the ultimate fibres, and <lb/>theſe conſiſting either of hollow tubes, or ſtrings
          of veſicles, or <w part="I">rhom-</w><lb/><w part="F">boidal</w> articulations, according
          to the reſpective theory with which <lb/>the mind of the obſerver was prepoſſeſſed, it
          appears, from the beſt <lb/>microſcopical obſervations, that the fibres are diviſible
          beyond what <lb/>the powers of the beſt aſſiſted ſight can trace, and that they are to
          <lb/>all appearance uniform. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This regular fibrous ſtructure of muſcles, may be compared to <lb/>the
          cryſtalliſation of ſalts, and other regular forms which inanimate <lb/>bodies aſſume, when
          paſſing to a ſolid form from a ſtate of ſolution <lb/>or fuſion. Every ſpecies of matter
          has a mode of aggregation <w part="I">pe-</w><lb/><w part="F">culiar</w> to itſelf, when
          its particles are at liberty to attract each other <lb/>according to that tendency which
          has been called their <hi rend="italic">polarity.</hi>
          <lb/>Thoſe who firſt conceived this idea, ſeemed to have proceeded on <pb xml:id="page_5"
            n="4"/><lb/>the ſuppoſition of the ultimate particles of matter being ſolid <w part="I"
            >bo-</w><lb/><w part="F">dies</w>, infinitely hard, having their different ſides endowed
          with <lb/>different powers of attraction and repulſion, ſo as to give various
          <lb/>configurations to the parts of matter, when concreting into a ſolid <lb/>form. There
          is another and later idea<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* See Dr. Blagden's
            Experiments on the cooling of Water below its freezing point. <lb/>Phil. Trans. Vol.
            LXXVIII. page 143. </note> of polarity, founded on the <lb/>hypotheſis of the ultimate
          particles of matter being combinations <lb/>of attracting and repelling points, which when
          brought much within <lb/>the natural limits of theſe powers, produce unequal degrees of <w
            part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">traction</w> and repulſion at equal diſtances from
          their common centre, <lb/>thereby defining what may be called the ſhape of the particles,
          and <lb/>conſtituting polarity. In whatever manner we conceive this to take <lb/>place,
          ſome ſuch circumſtance ſeems univerſal, and perhaps <w part="I">neceſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſary</w> to all the varieties of ſolid matter; and there is in ſome <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtances</w> a difference in the appearance and other properties
          of the <lb/>ſame ſubſtance, after paſſing from a fluid to a ſolid form, according <lb/>as
          its particles have been at liberty to follow more or leſs freely the <lb/>tendency of
          their polarity in the act of concretion. This may be <lb/>illuſtrated by the freezing of
          water, and the cryſtalliſation of ſalts, <lb/>which are more or leſs regular or confuſed,
          according to the <w part="I">cir-</w><lb/><w part="F">cumſtances</w> in which they have
          taken place. The ſame may be <lb/>exemplified in metals and other ſubſtances; for it is
          well known, <lb/>that the properties of iron and glaſs, in point of coheſion and <w
            part="I">elaſti-</w><lb/><w part="F">city</w>, are very much affected by the quickneſs
          or ſlowneſs with <lb/>which they paſs from a ſtate of fuſion to a ſtate of ſolidity. It is
          <lb/>probably in ſome circumſtance of this kind that muſcles differ from <lb/>other ſoft
          animal matter. We cannot trace by inſpection the <w part="I">man-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ner</w> in which the fluid nutritious matter is <hi rend="italic">applied</hi> in
          forming ſolid <lb/>parts; but as muſcles are compoſed of parts ſo regularly figured <pb
            xml:id="page_6" n="5"/><lb/>and endowed with contractility, it ſeems probable that there
          is <lb/>ſome proviſion made by Nature, whereby the particles follow the <lb/>exact impulſe
          of their polarity, and conſtitute a more exquiſite <lb/>ſtructure than in other parts of
          the body. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>So far with regard to the character of a Muſcle, conſidered in its
          <lb/>dead ſtate. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> Muſcular <w part="I"
              >Mo-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> conſidered in relation to other motions. </note>The
          firſt circumſtance that meets the attention in conſidering its <lb/>living ſtate, is that
          contractile power or motion, which is properly <lb/>the ſubject of this Lecture; and in
          order to inveſtigate its nature, <lb/>it will be neceſſary to compare it with that which
          takes place in <lb/>inanimate bodies, by conſidering the nature of motion in general. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> Motion an <w part="I"
              >ori-</w><lb/><w part="F">ginal</w> and <w part="I">na-</w><lb/><w part="F">tural</w>
            property of all matter. </note>So far as we know, either from actual obſervation, or
          from <w part="I">ana-</w><lb/><w part="F">logy</w>, there does not exiſt in nature any
          ſuch thing as abſolute <hi rend="italic">reſt:</hi>
          <lb/>for when we contemplate the motions of the earth and heavenly <lb/>bodies, the
          various complications of the planetary revolutions in <lb/>their rotation round their own
          axes, and in the paths of their orbits, <lb/>in the irregularities ariſing from the
          diſturbances of their mutual <lb/>gravitation, and from the preceſſion of the equinoxes,
          not to mention <lb/>the influence of the innumerable ſiderial ſyſtems upon each
            other<lb/><note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* See Dr. Herſchel's paper on the
            conſtruction of the Heavens. Phil. Trans. Vol. LXXV. page 231. </note>, <lb/>it may be
          affirmed, on inconteſtible principles, that no particle of <w part="I">mat-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ter</w> ever was, or will be, for two inſtants of time, in the ſame place,
          <lb/>and that no particle of it ever has returned, or will return, to any one <lb/>point
          of abſolute ſpace which it has ever formerly occupied. <w part="I">Whe-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ther</w> motion, therefore, can ſtrictly be called an <hi rend="italic"
            >eſſential</hi> property of <lb/>matter or not, it is, certainly, by the actual
          conſtitution of nature, <lb/>originally and indefeaſibly impreſſed upon it; and as reſt
          does not <pb xml:id="page_7" n="6"/><lb/>exiſt in nature, but may be conſidered, in a
          vulgar ſenſe, as a <w part="I">fal-</w><lb/><w part="F">lacy</w> of the ſenſes, and in a
          philoſophical ſenſe, as an abſtraction of <lb/>the mind, it follows, that what is called
          the <hi rend="italic">vis inertiæ</hi> of matter, <lb/>is not a reſiſtance to a change
          from reſt to motion, or from motion <lb/>to reſt, but a reſiſtance to acceleration or
          retardation, or to change <lb/>of direction. If it ſhould be alledged, that any given
          particle or <lb/>portion of matter is carried along by virtue of the motion of the
          <lb/>planet to which it belongs, it may be anſwered, that the earth or <lb/>any other
          planet is nothing more than a congeries of ſuch particles, <lb/>each of which muſt poſſeſs
          a ſhare of the ſame energy which <w part="I">ani-</w><lb/><w part="F">mates</w> the whole
          maſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> Farther proof of the active
            nature of <w part="I">mat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w>. </note>The active nature of
          matter is farther proved by thoſe attractions <lb/>and repulſions which univerſally take
          place among its parts, <w part="I">how-</w><lb/><w part="F">ever</w> near or remote; and
          every inſtance of motion within the <w part="I">cog-</w><lb/><w part="F">niſance</w> of
          our ſenſes, in the bodies around us, is referrible, either in <lb/>itſelf or its cauſe, to
          ſome mode of attraction or repulſion.<lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> Mechanical
            impulſe cannot be a primary cauſe of <w part="I">mo-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>. </note>
          <w part="I">Me-</w><lb/><w part="F">chanical</w> impulſe being the moil familiar cauſe of
          motion in the <lb/>ordinary events of life, is apt to be conſidered as the moſt ſimple
          <lb/>and original cauſe of it; but it is obvious, upon reflection, that it <lb/>cannot
          originate in itſelf, and that all colliſions are produced either <lb/>by the efficiency of
          living animals, that is, by muſcular action, or <lb/>by means of ſome operation of nature,
          depending on attraction or <lb/>repulſion. Of the firſt kind, all the mechanical
          operations of art <lb/>are examples; and with regard to the others, they may, if <w
            part="I">care-</w><lb/><w part="F">fully</w> inveſtigated, be referred in every
          inſtance, either immediately <lb/>or remotely, to the above-mentioned inherent energies of
          matter. <lb/>The natural agitation of air or water, for inſtance, may produce <w part="I"
            >mo-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> by impulſe, or may bring two ſolid bodies to impinge
          upon <lb/>each other; but it is evident that theſe motions in the atmoſphere <pb
            xml:id="page_8" n="7"/><lb/>or the ocean, could not take place without gravitation,
          which is <lb/>one of the attractive powers of matter. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> Hypotheſis of attraction and
            repulſion <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtituting</w> the <w part="I"
              >eſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſence</w> of matter. </note>Attraction and repulſion may be
          conſidered as one principle, <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">aſmuch</w> as they are
          both expreſſive of that active ſtate originally <lb/>inherent in matter, and becauſe any
          two particles, having affinity <lb/>with each other, either attract or repel, according to
          their diſtance, <lb/>their common temperature, and other circumſtances; and it is ſo
          <lb/>univerſal an agent in nature, that ſome modern philoſophers have <lb/>made it abſorb,
          as it were, every other power and property of <w part="I">mat-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ter</w>. The late Father Boſcovich<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="italic size(0.5)">*
              <hi rend="roman">See this doctrine fully explained, in a work entitled,</hi> Theoria
            nova Philoſophiæ <lb/>naturalis redacta ad unicam legem, &amp;c. Auctore Rogerio
            Boſcovich. Venetiis, <hi rend="italic">1763.</hi>
          </note>, of Milan, about forty years ago, <lb/>advanced a very bold doctrine to this
          effect, alledging, with great <lb/>ſtrength of argument, illuſtrated by geometrical
          reaſoning, that <lb/>there does not exiſt in nature any ſuch thing as impenetrable <w
            part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">tended</w> particles; and he deduces all the phænomena
          of the <w part="I">mate-</w><lb/><w part="F">rial</w> world from one principle, which
          ſuppoſes it conſtituted of <lb/>points having ſeveral ſpheres of attraction and repulſion,
          which <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> variouſly arranged and combined, produce
          the different forms and <lb/>properties of matter, and its ſeveral powers, ſuch as
          chemical <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">traction</w>, coheſion, and gravitation.
          Whether this hypotheſis is <lb/>founded in truth or not, it would appear from the
          reaſonings made <lb/>uſe of, that all the relative properties of matter may be accounted
          <lb/>for, though we abſtract from every other conſideration but <w part="I"
            >attrac-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> and repulſion. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> Muſcular <w part="I"
              >mo-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> cannot <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">pend</w>
            on any mechanical cauſe; </note>It is evident, therefore, that whatever may be the cauſe
          of <w part="I">muſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">cular</w> motion, it is not referrible to
          mechaniſm, which is itſelf only <pb xml:id="page_9" n="8"/><lb/>a ſecondary principle.
          Some theories have had recourſe to the <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">veyance</w> of
          a fluid into the fibres of muſcles, by which they were <lb/>ſwelled, and thereby
          ſhortened. One of the moſt plauſible of <lb/>theſe hypotheſes ſuppoſes this fluid to be
          the blood; but this is <lb/>plainly a <hi rend="italic">petitio principii;</hi> for, in
          order to give motion to the blood, <lb/>the very power in queſtion is neceſſary. Other
          fluids have been <lb/>ſuppoſed to have this effect, but even the exiſtence of theſe has
          not <lb/>been proved. I will not detain this learned audience with a recital <lb/>of the
          numerous theories of this kind that have been invented by <lb/>fanciful and ingenious men,
          only <hi rend="italic">one</hi> of which can be true, and <lb/>the moſt ſolid objections
          could be urged againſt them all. Other <lb/>arguments, derived from the nature of
          irritability and ſenſibility, <lb/>could, if neceſſary, be brought to prove that Muſcular
          Motion <w part="I">can-</w><lb/><w part="F">not</w> depend on any mechanical cauſe: but
          this part of the ſubject was <lb/>fully treated of by the ingenious Gentleman who
          delivered the <lb/>Croonian Lecture laſt year. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> But an <w part="I"
              >origi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nal</w> law of <w part="I">Na-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ture</w>. </note>As it has been proved that all matter is in a ſtate of perpetual
          <lb/>motion, originally impreſſed upon it by Nature, alſo that attraction <lb/>and
          repulſion are eſſential to it, and the ultimate cauſes of all new <lb/>motions that can
          ariſe in the univerſe, mechanical action being <lb/>only a ſecondary cauſe, it ſeems moſt
          agreeable to the analogy of <lb/>nature, to refer Muſcular Motion to an original law of
          animated <lb/>matter, whereby its particles are endowed with an attractive power <lb/>for
          which no cauſe can be aſſigned, any more than for gravitation, <lb/>coheſion, or chemical
          affinity. If I underſtand it right, this was <lb/>the doctrine laid down and illuſtrated
          laſt year by Doctor Fordyce, <lb/>and to which I am endeavouring to contribute ſome
          additional proofs <lb/>and illuſtrations, from a conviction that it is the only rational
          and <lb/>philoſophical light in which this ſubject has hitherto been viewed. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_10" n="9"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> A proof of this from the <w
              part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">creaſe</w> power of coheſion. </note>If the
          ſhortening of a muſcular fibre depends on this increaſed <lb/>power of attraction between
          its particles, the effect of it will be to <lb/>add to the power of coheſion in the fibre,
          and if this ſhall be found <lb/>in fact to be the caſe, it will be a farther proof of the
          doctrine juſt <lb/>now advanced.<note place="marg"> Experiment. </note> In order to decide
          this, I made the following <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">periment</w> upon the
          flexor muſcle of the thumb of a man, five hours <lb/>after death, while the parts were yet
          warm and flexible. All the <lb/>parts of the joint having been ſeparated, except the
          tendon, a weight <lb/>was hung to it, ſo as to act in the natural direction, and was <w
            part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">creaſed</w> gradually till the muſcle broke, which
          happened when <lb/>twenty-ſix pounds had been appended. I found that a man of the
          <lb/>ſame age, and the ſame apparent ſize and Strength, with the <w part="I"
            >ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F">ject</w> of the preceding experiment, could with eaſe lift
          thirty-<lb/>eight pounds by the voluntary exertion of the ſame muſcle. It is <w part="I"
            >far-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> in proof of this fact, that in the caſe of a violent
          ſtrain from <lb/>muſcular contraction in the living body, it is the tendon that gives
          <lb/>way, whereas we have ſeen, in the experiment juſt now related, <lb/>that in the dead
          body, the muſcle is the weaker of the two. It is <lb/>alſo well known, that in caſes of
          over-exertion, the muſcular <lb/>fibres themſelves do not give way, though the ſtrongeſt
          tendons, <lb/>ſuch as the <hi rend="italic">tendo Achillis,</hi> and even bones, ſuch as
          the knee-pan, <lb/>are broke by their living force<note place="bottom" n="*"
            rend="size(0.5)">* There is a caſe related in the Philoſophical Tranſactions, by Mr.
            Amyand, <lb/>wherein the <hi rend="italic">os humeri</hi> was broken by an exertion of
            the muſcles. See Phil. Tranſ.<lb/>Vol. XLIII. page 252. Every one has obſerved or heard
            of fractures happening <lb/>from very ſlight accidents. Theſe occur moſt probably from a
            jerk of the muſcles <lb/>concurring with the external violence. </note>, which, in ſuch
          inſtances, muſt be<lb/>many times greater than the ſtrength of the dead fibres. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_11" n="10"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> Proof from the increaſed
            hardneſs. </note>The ſenſible increaſe of hardneſs in a muſcle, when in a ſtate of
          <lb/>contraction, may alſo be conſidered as a proof of an increaſed <w part="I"
            >attrac-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of its particles to each other at that time. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> Whether <w part="I"
              >muſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">cular</w> contrac-<lb/>tion produces a change of denſity.
          </note>In inveſtigating this ſubject farther, it is of importance to <w part="I"
            >de-</w><lb/><w part="F">termine</w>, whether or not a muſcle, when in a ſtate of
          contraction, <lb/>undergoes any change of denſity. A compariſon of it in this <w part="I"
            >re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſpect</w> with dead matter, may throw ſome light on the nature
          of <lb/>muſcular action. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Every homogeneous body poſſeſſes a certain degree of denſity,
          <lb/>determined by the diſtance of its integrant particles. The moſt <lb/>common means in
          nature, by which the denſity of ſuch bodies is <lb/>altered, are heat and cold; the one
          univerſally producing <w part="I">expan-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſion</w>, the other
          condenſation. Whether mechanical force has the <lb/>ſame effects is a point in natural
          philoſophy not ſo well aſcertained; <lb/>for though tenſion and colliſion produce in ſolid
          elaſtic bodies a <lb/>change of figure, which they immediately reſume when the force
          <lb/>is withdrawn, it has not been enquired, ſo far as I know, whether in <lb/>ſuch caſes,
          a change of denſity takes place while the body is in <lb/>the ſtate of elongation or
          compreſſion. Two elaſtic balls, in the act of <lb/>colliſion, undergo a momentary change
          of figure, ſo that there muſt <lb/>be an approximation of particles in the direction in
          which they are <lb/>flattened; and in the elongation of an elaſtic chord by tenſion, there
          <lb/>muſt be an increaſed diſtance of the particles in one direction, but <lb/>while theſe
          changes take place in one dimenſion of the reſpective <lb/>bodies, they may be compenſated
          by contrary changes in the other <lb/>dimenſions; ſo that the ſeveral bodies may preſerve,
          upon the <lb/>whole, the ſame ſolid contents. In order to aſcertain this in the <pb
            xml:id="page_12" n="11"/><lb/>caſe of tenſion, which is the only caſe bearing analogy to
          Muſcular <lb/>Motion, I made the following experiment:<note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)">
            Experiment. </note> I took a piece of the <lb/>elaſtic gum, or <hi rend="italic"
            >kahoutchouck,</hi> three inches ſquare, and about the <lb/>eighth of an inch in
          thickneſs; I procured a piece of ſheet-tin, <lb/>three inches broad, and ſix inches long,
          cut into ſharp teeth at each <lb/>end. The gum was firſt weighed in air, and found to be
          380.25 <lb/>grains. It was then weighed in water, along with the tin, to <lb/>which it was
          looſely attached, and the weight of both was then <lb/>758,75 grains. The gum was then
          ſtretched upon the tin, by <lb/>means of the teeth at each end, to a ſurface of about five
          inches <lb/>ſquare, the tin being bent ſo as to leave a free ſpace between it and <lb/>the
          gum, in order that when immerſed in the water, no air <w part="I">bub-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >bles</w> might be entangled. In this ſituation, the weight of both in <lb/>water was
          found to be 746,75 grains. Here was a difference of twelve <lb/>grains, which could be
          owing only to a diminution of ſpecific <w part="I">gravi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ty</w>; and
          in order to be ſure that there was no fallacy nor inaccuracy <lb/>in the experiment, the
          gum was immediately afterwards diſengaged <lb/>from one end of the tin, ſo as to allow it
          to ſhrink, and being again <lb/>weighed in this ſtate in the water, it was found to have
          recovered <lb/>exactly its former weight. This, as well as the ſubſequent ſtatical
          <lb/>experiments, was performed by means of the exquiſite balance <lb/>lately invented and
          conſtructed by Mr. Ramſden, and belonging to <lb/>Sir Joſeph Banks, who politely allowed
          me the uſe of it. I was <lb/>alſo aſſiſted by Mr. Gilpin, clerk of this ſociety, who is
          extremely <lb/>accurate and expert in all operations of this kind. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> Experiments to determine whether
            the denſity of a Muſcle is <w part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F">fected</w> by <w part="I"
              >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">traction</w>. </note>Now, does the ſtate of relaxation and
          contraction make in like <lb/>manner a temporary difference in the denſity of muſcles?
          When the <lb/>circumſtance of <hi rend="italic">decurtation</hi> only is conſidered, we
          ſhould be tempted <lb/>to think that there muſt be an approximation of the particles of
          the <pb xml:id="page_13" n="12"/><lb/>fibre; but there is at the ſame time a lateral
          ſwelling of the muſcle, <lb/>which may compenſate for what is loſt in the other dimenſion.
          <lb/>This point cannot be decided but by an experimental examination. <lb/>It might be
          determined whether a muſcle occupies moſt ſpace when <lb/>relaxed or when contracted, by
          finding its ſpecific gravity in each <lb/>of theſe ſtates by means of the hydroſtatical
          balance. But this <lb/>would be found extremely difficult; for the ſtate of contraction is
          <lb/>very tranſitory, and the motion itſelf would produce ſuch a <w part="I"
            >diſtur-</w><lb/><w part="F">bance</w>, as would render the reſult unſatisfactory. As
          there is this <lb/>obſtacle to the experiment on a living muſcle, it occurred to me
          <lb/>that it might be performed on the muſcles of a fiſh, which had <lb/>undergone the
          operation of <hi rend="italic">crimping,</hi> as it is called; for, in <w part="I"
            >conſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">quence</w> of dividing the muſcles, by cutting them when
          alive, they <lb/>undergo a contraction, which continues after death<note place="bottom"
            n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* It has been made a queſtion, whether life and its actions may
            not affect the <hi rend="italic">ab-<lb/>ſolute</hi> gravity of bodies? Though this
            doubt has not ariſen upon any aſſignable grounds <lb/>that I know of, unleſs it be that
            one unknown principle may affect another equally <lb/>unknown, I thought it might be
            worth while to determine it by experiment. The <lb/>firſt trials were with animals of
            warm blood incloſed in oil ſkin, and cloſe tin veſſels, <lb/>but not being ſatisfied
            with the accuracy of theſe, from the difficulty of cutting off <lb/>all communication
            with the external air, ſo as to prevent moiſture from exhaling, I <lb/>incloſed live
            eels in flasks, and ſealed them hermetically; and, in this ſituation, <lb/>their weight
            when alive being compared with their weight when dead, there did not <lb/>appear any
            reaſon to ſuſpect that the mere circumſtance of life made any difference <lb/>in regard
            to gravity. </note>; and upon <lb/>comparing, by the hydroſtatic balance, portions of
          muſcle which <lb/>had been crimpt, with thoſe of the oppoſite ſide of the ſame fiſh,
          <lb/>which had on purpoſe been ſaved from this operation, it did not <lb/>appear that
          there was any difference in the ſpecific gravity. Two <pb xml:id="page_14" n="13"
          /><lb/>trials were made, one with the maſſeter muſcles of a skate, the <lb/>other with the
          ſides of a large trout. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The following experiment was alſo made, in order to decide the
          <lb/>comparative denſity of a contracted and relaxed muſcle. I took a <lb/>glaſs flask,
          into which one half of a living eel was introduced. <lb/>The mouth was immediately
          afterwards fuſed by a blow-pipe, and <lb/>drawn into a tube like the ſtem of a
          thermometer. The flask and <lb/>tube were then filled with water, in order to ſee whether
          the <w part="I">mo-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of the animal would make the fluid rife
          or fall. It had neither <lb/>the one effect nor the other, though there were at times
          ſtrong <lb/>convulſions, and if the muſcles had at any one time occupied <lb/>either more
          ſpace or leſs than at another, a ſenſible fluctuation would have <lb/>been produced,
          eſpecially when the column of fluid was rendered <lb/>very fine, by the introduction of a
          ſteel wire to irritate the parts. <lb/>That part of the eel from the <hi rend="italic"
            >anus</hi> to the tail was made uſe of for <lb/>this experiment, as the other diviſion,
          containing the organs of <lb/>reſpiration and the air-bladder, might have occaſioned a
          fallacy, <lb/>from the expanſion or condenſation of an elaſtic fluid, by <w part="I"
            >acciden-</w><lb/><w part="F">tal</w> changes of temperature, or compreſſion. This was
          repeated <lb/>three times, with the ſame reſult. In one of the trials, the <w part="I"
            >above-</w><lb/><w part="F">mentioned</w> portion of two eels was introduced, and though
          they <lb/>were at times both in convulſions at once, not the leaſt motion of <lb/>the
          fluid in the tube could be perceived. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> Contraction produces no change of
              <w part="I">den-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſity</w>; </note>I was the more deſirous to be
          accurate in this and the preceding<lb/> experiments, as the reſult of them was different
          from my own <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſſeſſion</w> at the time, and
          different, I believe, from the opinion of <lb/>moſt modern phyſiologiſts. It may ſafely be
          inferred from them, <lb/>that the contraction of a muſcle produces no change in its
          denſity, <pb xml:id="page_15" n="14"/><lb/>and that animal life differs from inanimate
          matter in this reſpect, as <lb/>well as in moſt of its other properties and laws. One
          purpoſe in <w part="I">na-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w> for muſcles always preſerving the
          ſame denſity may be, that <lb/>as ſome of them act in confined cavities, inconvenience
          might ariſe <lb/>from their occupying more ſpace at one time than another. In <lb/>the
          extremities of cruſtaceous animals, for inſtance, which are filled <lb/>with muſcles, a
          change of denſity would be apt to burſt them. <lb/>This may alſo be conſidered as a proof
          of the fact itſelf. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> Nor of <w part="I"
              >tempe-</w><lb/><w part="F">rature</w>. </note>Another circumſtance in which the
          contractions of muſcles differs <lb/>from ſimple elaſticity is, that the former, however
          frequent and <lb/>violent, does not produce any heat as colliſion and tenſion are
          <lb/>known to do. This may admit of ſome cavil with regard to <w part="I">ani-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">mals</w> of warm blood; for, one of the theories with regard to <w part="I"
            >ani-</w><lb/><w part="F">mal</w> heat is, that it ariſes from the perpetual vibration
          of muſcular <lb/>fibres, particularly thoſe of the vaſcular ſyſtem; but this will not
          <lb/>hold with reſpect to animals of cold blood, in which the actions of <lb/>life are
          equally vigorous. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> Recapitula-<lb/>tion and <w
              part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">pariſon</w> of facts. </note>The principal
          phænomena, therefore, of Muſcular Motion, are <lb/>the ſhortening of the fibres, the
          lateral ſwell, the increaſe of <w part="I">cohe-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſion</w> and
          hardneſs, and the unchanged denſity and temperature. <lb/>It would appear, from the two
          laſt circumſtances, that the intimate <lb/>motions of the particles in relation to each
          other, muſt be different <lb/>from what take place in the ſeveral inſtances of contraction
          and <lb/>expanſion in dead bodies. In the expanſion ariſing from the action <lb/>of heat,
          and the contraction from cold, the change of denſity ſhews <lb/>that in the one caſe, the
          ultimate particles muſt recede from each <lb/>other; and in the other caſe, that they muſt
          approach. The ſame <lb/>may be ſaid of elaſticity. But as there is no alteration of the <w
            part="I">den-</w><pb xml:id="page_16" n="15"/><lb/><w part="F">ſity</w> of a muſcle in
          paſſing from relaxation to contraction, this <lb/>change cannot conſiſt in the
          approximation of the integrant parts <lb/>of the fibres, but muſt depend on ſome other
          circumſtance in the <lb/>intimate diſpoſition of the particles. In attempting to conceive
          in <lb/>what this conſiſts, the following explanation may be offered:—<lb/><note
            place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> A Theory of Muſcular <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >traction</w>. </note> It was formerly mentioned that the regular ſtructure of ſolid
          bodies <lb/>depended on the polarity and ſhape of their integrant parts. Now <lb/>all
          bodies, except ſuch as are ſphærical, muſt have a long and a <lb/>ſhort axis; and let us
          imagine the fibres of muſcles to be compoſed <lb/>of ſphæroidal particles; we may then
          conceive relaxation to conſiſt <lb/>in their being diſpoſed with their long axis in the
          line of the fibres,<lb/>and contraction to conſiſt in their ſhort axis being diſpoſed more
          or <lb/>leſs in that direction. This will not only account for the <w part="I"
            >de-</w><lb/><w part="F">curtation</w>, and uniform denſity, but for the lateral ſwell,
          and <lb/>alſo for the increaſed hardneſs and coheſion; for though the <lb/>particles do
          not approach or recede, as in bodies ſimply elaſtic, <lb/>yet their power of attraction
          will be increaſed by their <w part="I">cen-</w><lb/><w part="F">tres</w> being brought
          nearer, and by being applied<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* By being
            applied, I do not mean that they are actually in <hi rend="italic">contact;</hi> for it
            is <w part="I">evi-</w><lb/><w part="F">dent</w>, from the effect of heat in expanding
            bodies, and of cold in condenſing them<lb/>that there can be no ſuch thing as contact of
            the ultimate particles of matter, even <lb/>on the ſuppoſition that theſe conſiſt of
            impenetrable bodies infinitely hard. </note> to each other <lb/>by more oblate ſurfaces.
          This hypotheſis accords with what <lb/>has been before proved, concerning the unchangeable
          denſity; <lb/>for what is loſt in one dimenſion, is gained in another; and the <lb/>cauſe
          for there being no increaſe of temperature, depends <w part="I">proba-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >bly</w> on the ſame circumſtance by which the denſity is preſerved <lb/>unaltered. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_17" n="16"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> This account of Muſcular Motion
            does not account for the operation of <hi rend="italic">ſtimuli.</hi>
          </note>WHAT has been hitherto advanced on this ſubject, has tended <lb/>only to explain
          that ſtate of a muſcular fibre which renders it <w part="I">ſuſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ceptible</w> of contraction, and to aſcertain the nature of that change <lb/>which
          takes place in paſſing from the ſtate of relaxation to that of <lb/>contraction. It ſtill
          remains a queſtion by what efficient power <lb/>this contraction is excited. We have,
          indeed, referred the cauſe <lb/>to attraction; but of attractions ſome are perpetual, ſuch
          as <w part="I">gra-</w><lb/><w part="F">vitation</w>, which exerts an equal and
          unremitting <hi rend="italic">niſus</hi> upon every <lb/>particle of matter, which is the
          ſubject of its action; and there are<lb/>others fugitive and occaſional, ſuch as
          electricity and magnetiſm, <lb/>and we may add muſcular contraction. With regard to the
          firſt <lb/>kind, as it is always uniform, it ſeems ſufficient to ſay, that it <lb/>exiſts
          as a part of the invariable conſtitution of nature; but with <lb/>regard to that which is
          fluctuating, it ſeems incumbent on thoſe <lb/>who ſearch into the laws of nature, to ſay
          by what mode of <w part="I">ef-</w><lb/><w part="F">ficiency</w> the attraction is
          performed, ſo that its action ſhould take <lb/>place at one time, and not at another. In
          order to anſwer this <lb/>queſtion, with regard to Muſcular Motion, we ought to be able to
          <lb/>ſpecify by what mode of operation a <hi rend="italic">ſtimulus</hi> excites
          contraction. <lb/>Thoſe theories which account for the contraction of muſcles, by <lb/>the
          ſwelling of the fibres, in conſequence of a conveyance of <w part="I">mat-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ter</w>, profeſſed to account for the operation of <hi rend="italic"
            >ſtimuli;</hi> but upon the <lb/>principles I have adopted in this Lecture, I am obliged
          to confeſs <lb/>my entire ignorance on this ſubject. Perhaps it is inſcrutable.
          <lb/>Perhaps the ſtate of human knowledge is not ripe for ſuch an <lb/>inquiry; for we are
          ſtill in the dark with regard to moſt of thoſe <lb/>properties of matter which bear any
          analogy to this, and the <lb/>knowledge of which might tend to throw light upon it. We
          know <lb/>that electric attraction depends on the accumulation of a ſubtle <pb
            xml:id="page_18" n="17"/><lb/>fluid, but we are ignorant of the nature of magnetiſm.
          With <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">gard</w> to heat, which is univerſally a cauſe of
          repulſion, and the moſt <lb/>general, powerful, and active, as well as the moſt uſeful and
            <w part="I">fa-</w><lb/><w part="F">miliar</w> agent in nature, it is hardly decided as
          yet whether it is a <lb/>matter or a quality; and with regard to light, though it is
          itſelf <lb/>the medium by which we become acquainted with the moſt <w part="I"
            >re-</w><lb/><w part="F">mote</w> objects, it is ſo obſcure in its own nature, that it
          is ſtill a <lb/>queſtion whether it conſiſts in the tranſmiſſion or vibration of a
          <lb/>ſubtle fluid. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As I am unable, therefore, to explain the <hi rend="italic">operation
            of ſtimuli,</hi> I <lb/>ſhall content myſelf with endeavouring to <hi rend="italic"
            >enumerate</hi> them. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> Enumeration of Stimuli.
          </note>Every natural cauſe exciting the contraction of a muſcular fibre, <lb/>is called a
            <hi rend="italic">ſtimulus.</hi> They may be divided into internal and <w part="I"
            >exter-</w><lb/><w part="F">nal</w>.<note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> 1. Internal <w
              part="I">ſti-</w><lb/><w part="F">muli</w>. </note> As an example of the former, the
          circulation of the blood <lb/>may be mentioned; as this is kept up by an exciting
          influence of <lb/>the blood upon the heart and veſſels which contain and impel it.
          <lb/>The earlieſt perceivable inſtance of Muſcular motion, is the beating <lb/>of the
          heart, as it is ſeen in the firſt rudiments of the embryo in <lb/>an egg, and called the
            <hi rend="italic">punctum ſaliens.</hi> There ſeems to be <w part="I"
            >eſtabliſh-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> by nature, a certain <hi rend="italic"
            >habitude</hi> of action between the veſſels and <lb/>their fluids, whereby the former
          are duly ſtimulated to propel the <lb/>latter. This does not depend merely on the acrimony
          of the <lb/>fluids; for if a fluid even more mild than the blood, ſuch as milk, <lb/>be
          injected into the circulation, it will produce great diſturbance; <lb/>and if the blood,
          by being deprived of the influence of reſpirable air, <lb/>becomes deſtitute of a certain
          property which it would naturally <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">quire</w> in the act
          of reſpiration, it does not prove a <hi rend="italic">ſtimulus</hi> to the <lb/>heart. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_19" n="18"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> All the <w part="I"
              >func-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w> of the body are <w part="I">car-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ried</w> on by <w part="I">ſpe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cific</w>
            <hi rend="italic">ſtimuli.</hi>
          </note>The irritability of all die containing parts, is in like manner <w part="I"
            >ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">commodated</w> to the nature of their reſpective contents. The
            <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">teſtines</w> are ſo calculated, as to have proper
          motions excited in them <lb/>by the aliment, and the ſecretions which are mixed with it;
          and <lb/>there are bodies which, though perfectly mild, ſuch as alimentary<lb/> ſubſtances
          of difficult digeſtion, yet excite more violent <w part="I">commo-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tions</w> in the ſtomach than other ſubſtances which are very <w part="I"
            >acri-</w><lb/><w part="F">monious</w>. The various effects of poiſons in different
          parts of the <lb/>body, may alſo be mentioned as an illuſtration of the peculiar <w
            part="I">ſuſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceptibility</w> of the ſeveral organs of the body. The
          poiſon of a <lb/>viper, for inſtance, is perfectly innocent, not only in the <w part="I"
            >recep-</w><lb/><w part="F">tacles</w> of the animal which produces it, but it may be
          taken into the <lb/>ſtomach of any animal without the leaſt bad effect, and only exerts
          <lb/>its deleterious power when brought in contact with a wounded part. <lb/>Some
          vegetable poiſons, on the contrary, ſuch as that of laurel water<note place="bottom" n="*"
            rend="size(0.5)">* See Experiments on Poiſons, by Abbé Fontana. </note>, prove deadly,
          when taken into the mouth, or applied to <lb/>any part of the alimentary canal, but are
          innocent when injected <lb/>into the veins. The ſame principle might be illuſtrated by the
            <w part="I">opera-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of various medicines, ſome of which act
          upon one ſet of organs, <lb/>and ſome upon another. But it is meant here more particularly
          to <lb/>elucidate the natural internal actions of the body; and it may be <w part="I"
            >re-</w><lb/><w part="F">marked</w>, that the receptacles of the ſeveral ſecreted
          fluids, ſuch as the <lb/>gall bladder, and bladder of urine, are ſo adapted to their
          natural <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tents</w>, by a due meaſure of irritability,
          as to bear their accumulation <lb/>to a certain degree, and then to expel them. We have
          here alſo a <lb/>proof that irritability is not in proportion to ſenſibility; for both
          <lb/>theſe receptacles are extremely ſenſible to pain and irritation, from <lb/>extraneous
          acrimony, though ſo moderately ſenſible to the acrimony <lb/>of their natural contents.
          This diſpoſition in the ſeveral organs to <pb xml:id="page_20" n="19"/><lb/>perform their
          natural functions, in conſequence of the <hi rend="italic">ſtimulus</hi> of <lb/>the
          reſpective fluids they contain, has aptly enough been called the <lb/>natural <hi
            rend="italic">perception</hi> of theſe organs<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)"
            >* This idea is well illuſtrated by Mr. Hunter in his lectures; alſo by Mr. Mudge,
            <lb/>in a diſſertation on the <hi rend="italic">vis vitæ,</hi> ſubjoined to a tract,
            entitled, "A radical and <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">peditious</w> cure for a
            catarrhous cough." </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It follows from this, that the application of chemical and <w part="I"
            >me-</w><lb/><w part="F">chanical</w>
          <hi rend="italic">ſtimuli</hi> to irritable parts, is not a mode of experiment likely
          <lb/>to be productive of uſeful knowledge, ſince the internal organs are <lb/>calculated
          to perform their actions in conſequence of peculiar and <lb/>ſpecific <hi rend="italic"
            >ſtimuli,</hi> provided by nature;<note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> Application of
            this in <w part="I">ſuggeſt-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> the means of reſtoring life in
            caſe of ſtrangulation, &amp;c. </note> and this conſideration may ſerve <lb/>to ſuggeſt
          the moſt likely means of reſtoring loſt irritability <lb/>and action to the vital
          functions, when ſuſpended by ſuffocation, <lb/>ſtrangulation, or ſubmerſion. The action of
          the heart depends on <lb/>the action of the lungs and the inſpiration of atmoſpheric air;
          and <lb/>I have found, from repeated experiments on animals, that in ſuch <lb/>caſes, all
          other means of reſtoring circulation and life, are of little <lb/>or no avail, in
          compariſon of inflating the lungs with atmoſpheric <lb/>air, and by ſtroking and preſſing
          the ribs, ſo as to imitate the <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of
          reſpiration. Neither mechanical friction, nor any other <lb/>external <hi rend="italic"
            >ſtimulus,</hi> nor ſtimulating clyſters, ſeemed to have any <lb/>ſenſible effect in
          recalling life. The only other means, beſides <lb/>thoſe above mentioned, that ſeem
          material in attempting to reſtore <lb/>ſuſpended animation, is a due attention to the
          external temperature. <lb/>In the caſe of drowning in cold water, for inſtance, it is of
          the <w part="I">ut-</w><lb/><w part="F">moſt</w> conſequence to reſtore the natural
          warmth, either by the <lb/>cautious uſe of artificial heat, or the application of living
          bedies. <lb/>In the caſe of thoſe who have been ſuffocated by foul air, it is, on <lb/>the
          contrary, adviſeable to expoſe them to cool air. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_21" n="20"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> And to <w part="I"
              >patho-</w><lb/><w part="F">logy</w>. </note>From what has been before advanced,
          concerning that habitude <lb/>or mutual influence of the ſolids and fluids, it would
          appear that <lb/>they are ſpecifically appropriated to each other, in order to carry
          <lb/>on not only the circulation, but the important functions of <w part="I"
            >digeſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, abſorption, ſecretion, and excretion; and as the
          healthy <lb/>condition of an animal conſiſts in the maintenance of that natural
          <lb/>harmony, ſo muſt the ſtate of diſeaſe depend on the derangement <lb/>of thoſe
          delicate impreſſions and nice ſenſibilities, or rather <hi rend="italic"
            >irritabi-<lb/>lities,</hi> in which the functions of the ſeveral organs conſiſt; and as
          the <lb/>affections of the ſolids and fluids are reciprocal, diſeaſe may depend
          <lb/>either on ſome deviation of the former, from their healthy and natural
          <lb/>perceptions, or from ſome acrimony or vitiation of the latter, or <w part="I"
            >per-</w><lb/><w part="F">haps</w> more commonly from the concurrence of both, in
          conſequence <lb/>of their mutual influence. When the fluids only are morbidly <w part="I"
            >af-</w><lb/><w part="F">fected</w>, nature alone is poſſeſſed of reſources of cure; for
          if the <lb/>containing ſolids retain their natural irritability, they will be <w part="I"
            >ſti-</w><lb/><w part="F">mulated</w> to expel what is extraneous or vitiated. A
          depraved ſtate <lb/>of the ſolids is therefore likely to prove a more frequent cauſe of
          <lb/>morbid derangement; and as they differ from the fluids, by <w part="I"
            >poſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſeſſing</w> an inherent activity, it is the object of medicine
          to incite,<lb/> reſtrain, or alter their diſeaſed actions, according to the nature of
          <lb/>the morbid affection. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is evident, that this doctrine will admit of a much more
          <lb/>extenſive application in pathology, than there is time here <lb/>to follow out; and I
          ſhall confine myſelf to the illuſtration <lb/>of it,<note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)">
            Exemplified in the <w part="I">abſor-</w><lb/><w part="F">bents</w>. </note> in the caſe
          of the abſorbent veſſels. Theſe evidently <lb/>poſſeſs a power of abſorbing certain
          ſubſtances, and rejecting <lb/>others. The lacteals, for inſtance, in a ſtate of health,
          take up <pb xml:id="page_22" n="21"/><lb/>only the nutritious part of the alimentary maſs;
          for there is in the <lb/>fecal part ſubſtances equally ſoluble as the chyle. The inner <w
            part="I">ſur-</w><lb/><w part="F">face</w> of the gall bladder is beſet with abſorbents,
          which, however, <lb/>do not abſorb bile in the ordinary ſtate of health, and only <w
            part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">centrate</w> it by taking up the fluid with which it
          is diluted. But <lb/>when in conſequence of the obſtruction of the gall ducts, the <w
            part="I">blad-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w> becomes over diſtended, or when the ſpecific
          perception of the <lb/>abſorbents is depraved by diſeaſe, in theſe caſes the bile is
          abſorbed <lb/>and thrown into the circulation. Sometimes, ſuch unuſual actions <lb/>of the
          abſorbents are excited as a reſource of nature, either to cure <lb/>diſeaſe, or to carry
          on growth; for it has been ſhewn by Mr. Hunter, <lb/>that not only ſoft and fluid parts,
          but bone, can be removed by <w part="I">abſorp-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>. At other
          times, diſeaſe conſiſts in affections of theſe veſſels, <lb/>either by their action being
          too much retarded, as in the caſe of <lb/>dropſy, or where the matter of an ulcer, or in
          the puſtules of the <lb/>ſmall pox, is prematurely abſorbed, in conſequence of the
          depraved <lb/>action of fever. It is ſufficiently demonſtrable, that the whole <w part="I"
            >ſur-</w><lb/><w part="F">face</w> of the ſkin and <hi rend="italic">bronchiæ</hi> is
          beſet with inhaling veſſels, which <lb/>abſorb the fluids diſſolved in the atmoſphere; and
          it would be <lb/>contrary to the analogy of the reſt of the body, to ſuppoſe that
          <lb/>theſe are not poſſeſſed of ſome elective power, whereby they prefer <lb/>or reject
          ſuch fluids as are preſented to them, according to their <lb/>ſeveral qualities, and that
          this power ſhould not be various, <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">cording</w> to the
          ſtate of health or diſeaſe. But, independent of <w part="I">ana-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >logy</w>, the variable ſtate of the human body, in reſpect to its <w part="I"
            >ſuſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceptibility</w> of contagious diſeaſes, ſeems to be a direct
          proof of this. <lb/>It is a well-known fact, that a perſon who has never had the ſmall
          <lb/>pox, will at one time be cloſely expoſed to their infection, and <pb xml:id="page_23"
            n="22"/><lb/>yet eſcape the diſeaſe, and at another time will be affected by the
          <lb/>ſlighteſt degree of it. If it ſhould be ſaid, that the poiſon is <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">haled</w> in the one caſe as well as the other, but that the
          internal <lb/>ſtate of the body is in one caſe diſpoſed to be affected, and in the
          <lb/>other not, it may be anſwered, that any method by which it can <lb/>certainly be
          introduced, as by inoculation, will almoſt infallibly <lb/>produce this diſeaſe in
          conſtitutions that have never before <w part="I">under-</w><lb/><w part="F">gone</w>
            it.<note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> The ſuperior ſafety of <w part="I"
              >ino-</w><lb/><w part="F">culation</w> ac-<lb/>counted for. </note> And this ſeems to
          afford a ſolution of a much agitated <lb/>queſtion, On what does the ſuperior ſafety of
          the inoculated ſmall <lb/>pox depend? For, in a conſtitution already morbidly diſpoſed,
          the <lb/>powers of life will be more apt to give way to any diſturbance that <lb/>may be
          excited; and the ſame derangement of nature, which, in <lb/>this caſe, makes the inhalant
          veſſels admit the noxious effluvia of <lb/>diſeaſe, will render the body leſs capable of
          counteracting it when <lb/>admitted. In the caſe of inoculation, the poiſon is not taken
          <lb/>into the circulation by any natural operation of the body; but <lb/>being obtruded by
          art, there is no particular propenſity in the <lb/>conſtitution to give way to it, unleſs
          the time of inoculation ſhould <lb/>accidentally coincide with thoſe moments in which the
          body is <w part="I">na-</w><lb/><w part="F">turally</w> ſuſceptible; and as this muſt
          ſometimes happen, it is <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">cordingly</w> obſerved, that
          one caſe in a great number of inoculated <lb/>ſmall pox, is equally malignant as any caſe
          of the natural ſort. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> Analogy <w part="I"
              >be-</w><lb/><w part="F">tween</w> motion and ſenſation. </note>The ſpecific
          irritability of muſcular fibres, in conſequence of the <lb/>peculiar action of <hi
            rend="italic">ſtimuli,</hi> has been called <hi rend="italic">perception,</hi> as was <w
            part="I">men-</w><lb/><w part="F">tioned</w> before. This term is not to be taken in a
          ſenſe ſtrictly <w part="I">lite-</w><lb/><w part="F">ral</w>, but as a metaphor, borrowed
          from ſenſation, and applied to <lb/>motion. In like manner as the ſenſes are fitted to
          convey <w part="I">pecu-</w><lb/><w part="F">liar</w> ideas, in conſequence of their
          reſpective organs being adapted <lb/>to their correſponding external impreſſions, ſo are
          the various organs <pb xml:id="page_24" n="23"/><lb/>of motion by nature made ſuſceptible
          of excitement from peculiar <lb/>impreſſions, either internal or external. This analogy is
          the more <lb/>exact, that the nerves ſeem to be the inſtruments of both; for <lb/>not only
          the organs of ſenſation and voluntary motion, but thoſe <lb/>of involuntary motion, are
          ſupplied with nerves, and dependant <lb/>upon them; for if the influence of the nerves
          leading to the heart <lb/>or inteſtines is interrupted, by cutting ligature or palſy, the
            <w part="I">func-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of theſe parts is thereby deſtroyed.
          Thus, as there is a <w part="I">pecu-</w><lb/><w part="F">liar</w> ſenſibility belonging
          to the ſeveral ſenſes, ſo is there a peculiar <lb/>irritability belonging to the ſeveral
          organs of motion. The <w part="I">inten-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of Nature,
          therefore, in diſtributing nerves to every muſcular <lb/>organ, was probably in order to
          conſtitute thoſe peculiar <w part="I">percep-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w> on which the
          various vital and natural functions depend. But <lb/>I give this only as a conjecture; and
          though the nervous influence <lb/>may thus <hi rend="italic">modify</hi> irritability,
          there is reaſon to think that it does not <lb/><hi rend="italic">beſtow</hi> it. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> Whether <w part="I"
              >vita-</w><lb/><w part="F">lity</w> is <w part="I">depen-</w><lb/><w part="F">dant</w>
            on the nervous ſyſtem </note>This leads us to conſider how far vitality is dependant on
          the <lb/>nerves. It has been the opinion of ſome phyſiologiſts, who have <lb/>been
          ſuppoſed to entertain very rational ideas of the animal <w part="I">œco-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">nomy</w>, that all muſcular irritability depended on a ſentient
            prin-<lb/>ciple<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* See Whytt on the vital and
            involuntary motions. </note>; and ſome have even maintained, that there is an <w
            part="I">intelli-</w><lb/><w part="F">gent</w> principle<note place="bottom" n="†"
            rend="size(0.5)">† Vide Opera Stahlii &amp; Prelectio de anima medica, Auct. Doct. <hi
              rend="italic">Nicholls.</hi>
          </note> reſiding in animal bodies, in order to guide their <lb/>functions and operations.
          From the preceding facts and reaſoning, <lb/>and from its being well atteſted that there
          have been ſeveral <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtances</w> of the production of
          fœtuſes, without the brain<note place="bottom" n="‡" rend="size(0.5)">‡ See Phil. Trans.
            Vol. XIX. and XXI. </note>, there ſeems <pb xml:id="page_25" n="24"/><lb/>no occaſion to
          have recourſe to ſo violent a hypotheſis. This, <w part="I">how-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ever</w>, is not the queſtion here intended to be diſcuſſed; but it is meant <lb/>to
          enquire, whether or not there is a foundation in nature for an <lb/>opinion broached by
          Mr. Hunter, that there is a living principle, <lb/>diſtinct from the nervous ſyſtem, and
          independent of ſenſation and <lb/>conſciouſneſs. The principal fact in ſupport of this
          opinion, is <lb/>the exiſtence of animals without brain and nerves. That there are
          <lb/>ſuch, was, I believe, firſt obſerved by Haller<note place="bottom" n="*"
            rend="size(0.5)">* Vide Primas Lincas Phyſiologiæ, <hi rend="italic">ccccii.</hi>
          </note>, and has been <lb/>confirmed by Mr. Hunter; who maintains farther, that the <w
            part="I">ſto-</w><lb/><w part="F">mach</w> is a centre, or ſeat of life, more eſſential
          to it than the brain. <lb/>That the ſtomach ſhould be an organ of ſo much conſequence,
          <lb/>ſeems natural enough, from the importance of its function, <lb/>which is that of
          aſſimilation; and life can be more <w part="I">imme-</w><lb/><w part="F">diately</w> and
          completely extinguiſhed by an injury to it, ſuch <lb/>as a blow, than by the ſame violence
          to any other part <lb/>of the body. It is alſo well known, that the muſcular fibres
          <lb/>of animals, endowed with a nervous ſyſtem, will retain their <lb/>irritability for
          ſome time after their ſeparation from the brain <lb/>and nerves. It is evident, likewiſe,
          from the <hi rend="italic">phænomena</hi> of <w part="I">ve-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >getation</w>, that irritability may exiſt in nature, without ſenſation,
          <lb/>conſciouſneſs, or any ſuſpicion of the exiſtence of a nervous ſyſtem. <lb/>The facts
          I allude to, are not only the perceptible motions of the <lb/>ſenſitive plant, but more
          particularly thoſe motions which muſt <lb/>neceſſarily take place in all plants, in
          carrying on their growth; <lb/>for there is no accounting for the accretion of ſolid
          parts, in <lb/>conſequence of the conveyance of nutrition by the propulſion <lb/>of the
          ſap, but by admitting ſome power, acting by laws <lb/>different from thoſe of dead matter.
          In favour of this opinion, <lb/>it is farther obſervable, that thoſe animals which are
          deſtitute <pb xml:id="page_26" n="25"/><lb/>of brain and nerves, are of the claſs <hi
            rend="italic">vermes,</hi> the moſt ſimple in <lb/>nature, having only one function, to
          wit, that of <hi rend="italic">aſſimilation,</hi> and <lb/>therefore not requiring that
          variety of action, and thoſe peculiar <lb/>perceptions which are neceſſary to more complex
          animals. Laſtly, <lb/>the ſtate of an egg before incubation, and the condition of thoſe
          <lb/>animals which become torpid from cold, and afterwards revive, <w part="I"
            >af-</w><lb/><w part="F">ford</w> facts which favour this opinion; as they ſhew that
          there is a <lb/>certain principle of ſelf-preſervation, independent not only of the
          <lb/>operation of the nervous ſyſtem, but even of the circulation; for, <lb/>in this
          quieſcent ſtate, theſe portions of animal matter are preſerved <lb/>for a great length of
          time from that corruption to which they <lb/>would otherwiſe be liable, and their fluids
          are prevented from <lb/>freezing in a degree of cold, which would congeal them, were they
          <lb/>deſtitute of every principle of life. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> The mutual dependance of ſimple
            life and nervous <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">fluence</w>. </note>But though
          ſimple life may be conſidered as diſtinct from the <lb/>nervous ſyſtem, which is only an
          acceſſary appendage to it, yet in <lb/>thoſe animals in which they are conjoined, the
          purpoſes of nature <lb/>render them dependant on each other. The functions of the
          <lb/>brain, for inſtance, cannot go on without the action of the heart; <lb/>for whenever
          the circulation of the blood is interrupted, <w part="I">conſciouſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >neſs</w> and ſenſation are deſtroyed, as is evident in the caſe of a ſwoon, <lb/>and in
          the effects of ſtrangulation. On the other hand, as has been <lb/>before obſerved, the
          action of the heart has a dependance on the <lb/>influence of the nerves, as connected
          with the brain. There are <lb/>alſo inconteſtible proofs of the extreme veſſels being
          affected by the <lb/>influence of the brain; for we know that a thought in the mind
          <lb/>will produce partial determinations of the circulating fluids, as in <lb/>the caſe of
          bluſhing, and the fullneſs of the veſſels in the organs <lb/>of generation, in conſequence
          of certain paſſions. It does not, <pb xml:id="page_27" n="26"/><lb/>however, follow, from
          all this, that irritability depends on the <lb/>nerves; the influence of which may be
          conſidered as modifying <lb/>general irritability, in the manner already mentioned; or it
          may <lb/>be conſidered rather as a <hi rend="italic">ſtimulus</hi> to the muſcular fibres,
          than as <w part="I">en-</w><lb/><w part="F">dowing</w> them with irritability, as in the
          inſtances laſt adduced: and <lb/>though the organs eſſential to life, ſuch as the heart,
          cannot exert the <lb/>action neceſſary to life, without the influence of the nerves, yet
          the<lb/> veſſels of the extremities can exert their uſual action independent <lb/>of it;
          for there are caſes in which the natural heat and circulation <lb/>continue in the limbs,
          after a total deprivation both of voluntary <lb/>motion and ſenſation<note place="bottom"
            n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* This fact is aſcertained, both by the experiment of cutting the
            crural nerve of <lb/>a living animal, and by the circumſtances attending certain
            diſeaſes. I lately met <lb/>with two caſes of palſy, in which there was a total loſs
            both of ſenſation and <w part="I">volun-</w><lb/><w part="F">tary</w> motion in the
            lower extremities, and yet the natural warmth and circulation <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">mained</w>. In one of theſe caſes, excoriations were produced on the feet by
            ſinapiſms; <lb/>and in the other, bliſters roſe on the knees, but without exciting any
            ſenſation, and <lb/>the parts healed as in a healthy perſon. The firſt, was that of a
            gentleman advanced <lb/>in life, in whom this affection came on after the gout in the
            ſtomach, and he died <lb/>in conſequence of the palſy extending to the bladder and other
              <hi rend="italic">viſcera.</hi> The other <lb/>was that of a young woman in St.
            Thomas's Hoſpital, who had been ſubject to <lb/>violent hyſterical convulſions. After a
            tedious illneſs, ſhe entirely recovered the uſe <lb/>and feeling of her limbs. </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> Eſſential <w part="I"
              >pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">perties</w> of ſimple life. </note>It may here be obſerved,
          that beſide muſcular irritability, the <lb/>principal, if not the only, powers of ſimple
          life, are the aſſimilation <lb/>of aliment, and that power in the living body, by which it
          preſerves <lb/>itſelf from putrefaction; and it is ſtrongly in proof of vitality being
          <lb/>independent of nervous power, that when the trunk of a nerve is <lb/>cut through, the
          limb to which it leads, though deprived of all <w part="I">ſen-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſation</w> and voluntary motion, not only continues free from <w part="I"
            >ſponta-</w><pb xml:id="page_28" n="27"/><lb/><w part="F">neous</w> putrefaction, but
          the warmth and circulation continue, even <lb/>though the nerve ſhould not be
            regenerated<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* It appears, from ſome
            experiments of Mr. Cruikſhank, that there is a proceſs <lb/>in nature, whereby nerves
            can be regenerated after being cut through. </note>. The only viſible <lb/>change
          produced in a limb by this operation, is, that after ſome <lb/>time it begins to waſte. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> The influence of the nervous
            ſyſtem <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">friendly</w> to ſimple life. </note>But there
          are circumſtances that would ſeem to prove, that the <lb/>nervous ſyſtem is not only a
          mere appendage to life, but that it <lb/>tends to impede its operation, and ſhorten its
          exiſtence. Simple <lb/>life will not only ſurvive ſenſation, but will ſurvive it longer,
          if <lb/>the animal is killed, by deſtroying the nervous ſyſtem, than if it <lb/>had been
          deſtroyed by hæmorrhage, ſuffocation, or other violence.<note place="marg"
            rend="size(0.5)"> This <w part="I">illuſtrat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> by <w part="I"
              >obſerva-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w> on fiſh, </note> It is a curious and well
          aſcertained fact, that if a fiſh, immediately <lb/>upon being taken out of the water, is
          ſtunned by a violent blow on <lb/>the head, or by having the head cruſhed, the
          irritability and <w part="I">ſweet-</w><lb/><w part="F">neſs</w> of the muſcles will be
          preſerved much longer, than if it had <lb/>been allowed to die with the organs of ſenſe
          entire. This is ſo <lb/>well known to fiſhermen, that they put it in practice, in order to
          <lb/>make them longer ſuſceptible of the operation called <hi rend="italic">crimping.</hi>
          A <lb/>ſalmon is one of the fiſh leaſt tenacious of life, inſomuch, that it <lb/>will loſe
          all ſigns of life in leſs than half an hour after it is taken <lb/>out of the water, if
          ſuffered to die without any farther injury; but if, <lb/>immediately after being caught,
          it receives a violent blow on the <lb/>head, the muſcles will ſhew viſible irritability
          for more than twelve <lb/>hours afterwards. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> On <w part="I">quadru-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">peds</w>, </note>There is a circumſtance obſerved with regard to animals of
          warm <lb/>blood, which ſeems to depend on the ſame principle. An exceſſive <lb/>exertion
          of voluntary motion, immediately before death, prevents <lb/>the muſcles from becoming
          rigid when cold, and renders them <pb xml:id="page_29" n="28"/><lb/>more prone to
          putrefaction. Thus, if an ox is killed immediately <lb/>after being overdrove, the carcaſe
          will not become ſtiff when it <lb/>grows cold, nor is it capable of being preſerved by
          means of ſalt. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> And diſeaſes of the human
            ſpecies. </note>In illuſtration of the ſame principle, it may be remarked, that
          <lb/>there is a ſymptom in certain diſeaſes of the human ſpecies, <w part="I"
            >ſhew-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> that digeſtion, which is one of the principal
          functions of ſimple <lb/>life, will ſometimes go on better, in conſequence of leſions of
          the <lb/>brain; for in thoſe diſorders in which the exerciſe of the ſenſes is <lb/>in a
          great meaſure deſtroyed, or ſuſpended, as in the <w part="I">hydrocepha-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">lus</w> and apoplectic palſy, it happens not uncommonly that the <w part="I"
            >ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">petite</w> and digeſtion are better than in health. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> Every exerciſe of the brain
            produces <w part="I">fa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tigue</w>. </note>From theſe facts we may
          infer, with Mr. Hunter, that the <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">erciſe</w> of
          ſenſation is inimical to life, and that a ſort of fatigue is<lb/>induced by this, as well
          as by voluntary motion: ſo that all that <lb/>intercourſe carried on through the nerves,
          whether <hi rend="italic">towards</hi> the <lb/>brain, in the caſe of ſenſation, or <hi
            rend="italic">from</hi> the brain, in acts of volition, <lb/>tends to wea rout the
          animal powers<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* There are ſome ingenious
            remarks on the analogy of ſenſation and motion, in <lb/>a paper on the ocular <hi
              rend="italic">ſpectra</hi> of light and colours, by Dr. Robert Waring Darwin,
            <lb/>Phil. Trans. Vol. LXXVI. This diſſertation abounds with reſined and well <w
              part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">duced</w> obſervations on the ſubject he treats
            of.</note>. And as intenſe and long-<lb/>continued thought, though not terminating in
          any outward action,<lb/>tends alſo to produce an inability for farther exertions, it would
          <lb/>appear that the brain, or ſenſorium, is more particularly the organ <lb/>which is
          ſubject to that ſpecies of ſufferance called fatigue.<note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)">
            Hence the <w part="I">ne-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceſſity</w> of ſleep, </note> From
          <lb/>theſe facts, we perceive the neceſſity of ſleep, which conſiſts in a <pb
            xml:id="page_30" n="29"/><lb/>temporary ſuſpenſion of ſenſation, volition, and thought,
          and is a <lb/>reſource of nature, whereby the powers of life recover themſelves <lb/>after
          ſatiety and fatigue, which are provided as guards to warn us <lb/>when nature is in danger
          of being ſtrained, either by repletion or <lb/>over exertion; and it is evident that ſuch
          barriers were abſolutely <lb/>neceſſary, in order to ſet bounds to operations which are
          only <w part="I">oc-</w><lb/><w part="F">cationally</w> requiſite, and which would
          otherwiſe depend on the <lb/>caprices of the will. The exerciſe of ſenſation and voluntary
            <w part="I">mo-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, in a moderate degree, is conformable to
          the intention of <w part="I">na-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w>, and therefore ſalutary; and
          it is only when they are exceſſive, <lb/>that they tend to wear out the powers of life,
          and more <lb/>eſpecially if theſe are not duly recruited by ſleep.<note place="marg"
            rend="size(0.5)"> And the bad effect of <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F">moderate</w>
            la∣bour and <w part="I">ſen-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſuality</w>. </note> Immoderate labour,
            <w part="I">there-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w>, and watching, alſo ſpaſms and
          convulſions of every kind, are <lb/>unfriendly to health and long life: in like manner,
          ſenſations, <lb/>when too frequent or intenſe, eſpecially thoſe which conſiſt in <lb/>the
          gratification of the ſenſes, tend to wear out the animal <lb/>powers; and hence we
          perceive why a life of ſenſuality is <lb/>productive of certain diſeaſes, independent
          either of the <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">pletion</w> or evacuation which attend
          them. The gout, but more <lb/>certainly the palſy, ſeems to proceed merely from the <w
            part="I">indul-</w><lb/><w part="F">gence</w> of the ſenſes; for the latter commonly
          enough occurs in the <lb/>moſt ſpare and emaciated conſtitutions, and in thoſe who have
          <lb/>been accuſtomed to exhauſting pleaſures, as well as thoſe of a full <lb/>habit, who
          have indulged in the exceſſes of the table. A <w part="I">turge-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſcence</w> of the veſſels in the brain will certainly be more apt to <w part="I"
            >pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duce</w> that rupture of them in which apoplectic palſy
          conſiſts, when <lb/>theſe veſſels have been relaxed, as we conceive them to be, by <w
            part="I">fre-</w><lb/><w part="F">quent</w> and intenſe ſenſations. But in thoſe who are
          the reverſe of <lb/>being plethoric, and who fall victims to this diſeaſe, in conſequence
          <lb/>of too tree indulgence in venereal pleaſures, in the decline of life, <pb
            xml:id="page_31" n="30"/><lb/>(as every one who has much obſervation of the world, or
          experience <lb/>in phyſic, knows to be a frequent caſe) it muſt ariſe from a <w part="I"
            >pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ternatural</w> weakneſs in the brain, induced by the mere
          circumſtance <lb/>of ſenſation. This accounts for what has been reckoned a <w part="I"
            >diffi-</w><lb/><w part="F">culty</w> in reaſoning on the cauſe of apoplexy and palſy,
          to wit, that <lb/>the ſame effect ſhould be produced by thoſe gratifications which
          <lb/>produce repletion, as by thoſe which produce evacuation. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> And the good effects of <w
              part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">moving</w> irri-<lb/>tation in <w part="I"
              >cer-</w><lb/><w part="F">tain</w> diſeaſes. </note>It follows, from the ſame
          principle, that when life is threatened <lb/>by certain diſeaſes, of which the chief
          ſymptom is irritation, any <lb/>means by which ſenſation, whether natural or morbid, and
            <w part="I">muſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">cular</w> motion, whether voluntary or involuntary,
          convulſive or <lb/>ſpaſmodic, can be ſoothed or ſuſpended, will prove ſalutary, by
          <lb/>allowing the powers of life to rally, as it were, and recover <w part="I"
            >them-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſelves</w>. In this conſiſts the operation of narcotic
          medicines, ſuch <lb/>as opium, which, in complaints both of a general and local nature,
          <lb/>proves uſeful not merely as a palliative, by the removal of <w part="I"
            >tem-</w><lb/><w part="F">porary</w> pain or ſpaſm, or by procuring ſleep, but as a
          principal <lb/>inſtrument of recovery, by allowing the powers of life to exert <lb/>their
          natural action, in conſequence of the removal of irritation<lb/><note place="bottom" n="*"
            rend="size(0.5) ">* As an example of the general affections of the conſtitution in which
            opium is a <lb/>uſeful remedy, we may mention thoſe low fevers in which the principal
            ſymptoms <lb/>are tremors, <hi rend="italic">pervigilum,</hi> and low <hi rend="italic"
              >delirium.</hi> And as an inſtance of local affections, <lb/>in which it has been
            found highly ſerviceable, we may mention ill-conditioned <w part="I">ul-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">cers</w> of all kinds, but particularly thoſe which occur in the venereal
            diſeas. One of <lb/>the principal difficulties in the cure of this diſeaſe, is that
            irritability of conſtitution <lb/>whereby ulcers are ſo exaſperated, by the uſe of
            mercury, as not to bear a ſuffcient <lb/>quantity of it to produce a cure. This is
            obviated by a free uſe of opium, which <lb/>ſeems more efficacious in ſuch caſes, than
            even Peruvian bark, or any other remedy; <lb/>and this is one of the principal modern
            improvements in the treatment of this diſeaſe. </note>. <pb xml:id="page_32" n="31"
          /><lb/>It is but juſt to own, that this is an idea which was firſt ſuggeſted <lb/>to me by
          a learned and eminent phyſician<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Dr. Warren.
          </note> of this place, when in <lb/>conſultation with him a few years ago. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)"> Comparative effects of <w
              part="I">opi-</w><lb/><w part="F">um</w> upon <w part="I">ſen-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ſitive</w> and ſimple life. </note>It would be curious, as well as uſeful, to
          diſtinguiſh the <w part="I">ope-</w><lb/><w part="F">ration</w> of medicine, as they
          affect ſimple or ſenſitive life. I <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tempted</w> a
          compariſon of this kind with opium, which, though it <lb/>chiefly affects ſenſation, has
          alſo a powerful effect on ſimple life, <lb/>as I found by trying its effects upon leeches,
          which are a ſpecies of <lb/>animals without brain or nerves. In order to diſcern the power
          of<lb/>this drug, as affecting the different principles of animals poſſeſſing <lb/>both
          ſorts of life, I took a ſolution of it in water, into one portion<lb/>of which I put ſome
          ſound living eels, and into another ſome eels<lb/>alſo alive, but having their heads
          bruiſed, chuſing the former, as <lb/>nearly as I could, of the ſame vigor with the latter,
          before their <lb/>heads were bruiſed. It was found, in a number of trials, that the
          <lb/>ſound eels generally died ſooner than the others. The opium had <lb/>a double effect
          on the former, as it acted both upon the ſenſes and <lb/>upon the principle of ſimple
          life, and the effect upon the ſenſes <lb/>was more than equivalent to the external injury
          of the latter, upon <lb/>which the opium acted only upon one principle, the ſenſes being
          <lb/>locked up by the deſtruction of their organs. In order to make <lb/>this operation
          ſucceed, the ſolution ſhould be of a certain degree <lb/>of ſtrength, ſo as to act as a
          poiſon. There ſhould be at leaſt half a <lb/>grain of opium to an ounce of water. When the
          trial was made <lb/>with a ſolution of half this ſtrength, the ſound eels lived much
          <lb/>longer; for the time was then protracted to that period in which <pb xml:id="page_33"
            n="32"/><lb/>the wounded eels would have died merely of their injury. It may <lb/>be
          mentioned, that thoſe which had their heads bruiſed, and were <lb/>put into a ſolution of
          opium, died conſiderably ſooner than thoſe <lb/>which had ſuffered the ſame injury, and
          were put into plain water <lb/>for a ſtandard. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><note place="marg" rend="size(0.5)">
            <hi rend="italic">Stimuli</hi>
            <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">nected</w> with conſciouſneſs. </note>Having
          conſidered the various qualities of the fluids exciting the <lb/>correſponding
          irritability of the reſpective veſſels, as a leading <w part="I">prin-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ciple</w> in carrying on ſome of the moſt important functions of the <lb/>body, and
          ſerving to account for many of the vital and involuntary <lb/>motions, the only other
          internal <hi rend="italic">ſtimuli</hi> that remain to be <w part="I">enume-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">rated</w>, are thoſe connected with conſciouſneſs. The great maſſes <lb/>of
          muſcle in the trunk and extremities of the body, are the <w part="I">inſtru-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ments</w> of the mind in acting upon external bodies; and we may,
          <lb/>therefore, reckon in the liſt of <hi rend="italic">ſtimuli,</hi> the nervous power by
          which <lb/>the will and the paſſions excite external motions. This is a <w part="I"
            >func-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> ſufficiently important for the nerves, without
          admitting them <lb/>as the principle upon which irritability depends. This queſtion has
          <lb/>been already diſcuſſed; but it may be farther obſerved, that the <w part="I"
            >ner-</w><lb/><w part="F">vous</w> power, being a ſtimulus acting upon an irritable
          principle in <lb/>the muſcular fibres, affords a preſumption that they are different from
          <lb/>each other; for, the matter being conſidered abſtractedly, where any <lb/>effect is
          the reſult of the concurrence of two bodies, as, for inſtance, <lb/>in the combinations of
          chemiſtry, theſe two bodies muſt be different, <lb/>in order to produce any given effect.
          It is otherwiſe, indeed, when <lb/>the effect depends on mere <hi rend="italic"
            >communication,</hi> as in the caſe of <w part="I">mecha-</w><lb/><w part="F">nical</w>
          impulſe, where the ſame motion that is loſt by one body is <lb/>acquired by another. But
          it will not be ſaid, that there is any <w part="I">ſimi-</w><pb xml:id="page_34" n="33"
            /><lb/><w part="F">larity</w> between what takes place in a nerve, and what takes place
          in <lb/>a muſcular fibre in the act of voluntary contraction. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I have already acknowledged my ignorance of the manner in <lb/>which
            <hi rend="italic">ſtimuli</hi> in general operate, and that this muſt be admitted as
          <lb/>an ultimate fact in nature. But the operation of the will through <lb/>the nerves,
          ſeems involved in double obſcurity; for as it depends<lb/>on the nature of thought, it
          cannot be made a ſubject; of <w part="I">experi-</w><lb/><w part="F">mental</w>
          inveſtigation. For this reaſon I ſhall decline the inquiry, <lb/>as not being adapted to
          the ends of this Society; and it ſeems <lb/>impoſſible for human ſagacity to penetrate the
          connection of matter <lb/>with ſenſation and volition, except by inferences more or leſs
            <w part="I">hy-</w><lb/><w part="F">pothetical</w>. The properties of different bodies,
          in relation to each <lb/>other, appear to be the only proper ſubjects of experimental <w
            part="I">rea-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſoning</w>; for, in their relation to the mind, they
          are only the <w part="I">ef-</w><lb/><w part="F">fects</w>, perhaps the remote effects, of
          their intimate nature upon the <lb/>ſenſes; ſo that we may venture to affirm that human
          reaſon can no <lb/>more fathom the connection of thought with the correſponding
          <lb/>changes in the corporeal organs, than the eye can ſee itſelf. </p>
        <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="24"/>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
