<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title> LMEMT Corpus - Hunter: A treatise on the blood, inflammation, and gun-shot
                    wounds</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Compiler</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="IT">
                        <forename>Irma</forename>
                        <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="TH">
                        <forename>Turo</forename>
                        <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ALe">
                        <forename>Anu</forename>
                        <surname>Lehto</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="VM">
                        <forename>Ville</forename>
                        <surname>Marttila</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="RO">
                        <forename>Raisa</forename>
                        <surname>Oinonen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="PP">
                        <forename>Päivi</forename>
                        <surname>Pahta</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="MR">
                        <forename>Maura</forename>
                        <surname>Ratia</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="CS">
                        <forename>Carla</forename>
                        <surname>Suhr</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="JT">
                        <forename>Jukka</forename>
                        <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="WA">
                        <forename>Wilma</forename>
                        <surname>Andersson</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="EC">
                        <forename>Emanuela</forename>
                        <surname>Costea</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="DV">
                        <forename>Diana</forename>
                        <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="SK">
                        <forename>Sami</forename>
                        <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="MK">
                        <forename>Mirella</forename>
                        <surname>Klinga</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="SKo">
                        <forename>Sami</forename>
                        <surname>Koskinen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ALi">
                        <forename>Aatu</forename>
                        <surname>Liimatta</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="HR">
                        <forename>Heikki</forename>
                        <surname>Rajala</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="JR">
                        <forename>Jenni</forename>
                        <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName xml:id="AW">
                        <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
                        <surname>Walraff</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>
                    <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
                </sponsor>
                <funder>
                    <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
                    <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
                </funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                <date>forthcoming</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName>John Hunter</persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">A treatise on the blood, inflammation, and gun-shot
                            wounds, by the late John Hunter. To which is prefixed, A short account
                            of the author's life, by his brother-in-law, Everard Home.</title>
                        <edition n=""/>
                        <idno type="ESTC">T055638</idno>
                        <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T055638"/>
                        <imprint>
                            <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName>London</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>
                                <persName>London: printed by John Richardson, for George Nicol,
                                    Bookseller to His Majesty, Pall-Mall, 1794.</persName>
                            </publisher>
                            <date>1794</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <extent>
                            <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
                            <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="10"/>
                            <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="565"/>
                            <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="16"/>
                        </extent>
                    </monogr>
                    <note type="source_copy">
                        <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
                        <idno type="ECCO">CW108342200</idno>
                    </note>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef n=""/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
        <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="77"/>
        <body>
            <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="178"/>
            <div type="part">
                <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="88"/>
                <pb n="277"/>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head rend="align-center space size(1.25)"><lb/>CHAPTER III. </head>
                    <head rend="align-center space size(1.25) italic"><lb/>THE ADHESIVE
                        INFLAMMATION.</head>
                    <figure rend="space">
                        <lb/>
                        <figDesc>A horizontal double-line in the middle of the page.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <p rend="space"><lb/><hi rend="sc">I shall</hi> begin by treating of the nature
                        and effects of what I have called <lb/>the adhesive inflammation, as well as
                        giving a proper idea of it. I shall <lb/>also open the way to a clear
                        understanding of the many phænomena <lb/>which attend the suppurative
                        inflammation; but as inflammation does not <lb/>produce one effect only, but
                        several, and as most of them take place about <lb/>the same time, it is
                        difficult to determine in the mind, which to describe <lb/>first. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/>Inflammation in most cases appears to begin at a point;
                        for at the very <lb/>first commencement, all the local symptoms are within a
                        very small <lb/>compass, and they afterwards spread according to the
                        violence of the <lb/>cause; the disposition in the parts for inflammation,
                        and the nature of the <lb/>surrounding parts themselves, which
                        susceptibility in the surrounding parts <lb/>may be either constitutional or
                        local. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/>This is so much the case, that inflammation shall come on
                        at once in <lb/>a fixed point, giving great pain, and which shall be soon
                        followed by <lb/>tumefaction. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/>This is also the case with those inflammations which arise
                        from <w part="I">acci-</w><lb/><w part="F">dent</w>, for all accidents are
                        confined to fixed and determined limits, but the <lb/>inflammation which
                        follows is not; it spreads over a large extent, yet <lb/>the inflammation is
                        always the greater, the nearer it is to the first fixed <lb/>point; and
                        gradually becomes less and less in the surrounding parts, till <lb/>at last
                        it is insensibly lost in them. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/>This spreading of the inflammation is owing to continued
                        sympathy, <lb/>the surrounding parts sympathising with the point of
                        irritation; and in <pb n="278"/><lb/>proportion to the health of the
                        surrounding parts and constitution, this <lb/>sympathy is less; for we find
                        in many states of parts, and many <w part="I">consti-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                            >tutions</w>, that there is a disposition to this sympathy, and in such,
                        the <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">flammation</w> spreads in
                        proportion. </p>
                    <figure rend="space">
                        <lb/>
                        <figDesc>A horizontal double-line in the middle of the page.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <div type="section">
                        <head rend="align-center space"><lb/>I. ACTION OF THE VESSELS IN
                            INFLAMMATION. </head>
                        <p rend="indent space"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> act of inflammation would
                            appear to be an increased action of the <lb/>vessels <note
                                place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.75)">
                                <p rend="indent"><lb/>* It may be here remarked, that the action of
                                    vessels is commonly supposed to be <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
                                        part="F">traction</w>, either by their elastic or muscular
                                    coats; but I have shewn that their elastic power <lb/>also
                                    dilated them; and I have reason to believe their muscular power
                                    has a similar effect. </p>
                            </note>, but whatever action it is, it takes place, most probably in the
                            <lb/>smaller vessels, for it may be confined almost to a point where
                            nothing <lb/>but the smallest vessels exist. The larger vessels may be
                            considered as <lb/>only the conveyers of the materials, for the smaller
                            to act upon and dispose <lb/>of according to the different intentions;
                            however, inflammation in a part, <lb/>is not only an action of the
                            smaller vessels in the part itself, but in the <lb/>larger vessels
                            leading to it. This is proved by a whitlow taking place on <lb/>the end
                            of a finger; for although the inflammation itself shall be confined
                            <lb/>to the end of a finger, and the inflammatory sensation or throbbing
                            be <lb/>situated in this part, yet we can feel by our hands, when we
                            grasp the <lb/>finger, a strong pulsation in the two arteries leading to
                            the inflamed part, <lb/>while no such pulsation can be felt in the other
                            fingers; and if the <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">flammation</w>
                            is very considerable, the artery, as high as the wrist, will be
                            <lb/>sensibly affected, which proves that the arterial system is at that
                            time <lb/>dilating itself, and allowing a much larger quantity of blood
                            to pass than <lb/>is usual. This is probably by continued sympathy. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Where the inflammation affects the constitution, the
                            vessels of the <lb/>system rather contract, and keep as it were
                            stationary, which stationary <lb/>contraction is more or less according
                            to the state of the constitution; in <lb/>strong healthy constitutions
                            whose powers are equal to the necessary actions, <pb n="279"/><lb/>or in
                            parts that affect the constitution less, this contraction is less and
                            less <lb/>stationary. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The very first act of the vessels when the stimulus
                            which excites <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">flammation</w> is
                            applied, is, I believe, exactly similar to a blush. It is, I
                            <lb/>believe, simply an increase or distension beyond their natural
                            size. This <lb/>effect we see takes place upon many occasions, gentle
                            friction on the skin <lb/>produces it; gently stimulating medicines have
                            the same effect, a warm <lb/>glow is the consequence, similar to that of
                            the cheek in a blush; and if <lb/>either of these be increased or
                            continued, real inflammation will be the <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
                                part="F">sequence</w>, as well as excoriation, suppuration, and
                            ulceration. This effect we <lb/>often see, even where considerable
                            mischief has been done; and I believe <lb/>it is what always terminates
                            the boundaries of the true inflammation. A <lb/>musket-ball shall pass a
                            considerable way under the skin, perhaps half <lb/>way round the body,
                            which shall be discovered and traced by a red band <lb/>in the skin, not
                            in the least hard, only a little tender to the touch; and it <lb/>shall
                            subside without extending farther. This appearance I shall term a
                            <lb/>blush; for although this may be reckoned the first act of
                            inflammation, <lb/>yet I would not call it inflammation, having produced
                            a laſting effect; I <lb/>should rather say, that inflammation sets out
                            from this point, and that <lb/>afterwards a new action begins, which is
                            probably first a separation of the <lb/>coagulating lymph, and the
                            throwing it out of the vessels. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The parts inflamed appear to become more vascular; but
                            how far they <lb/>are really so, I am not certain, for this appearance
                            does (at least in part) <lb/>arise from the dilatation of the vessels,
                            which allows the red part of the <lb/>blood to go into vessels where
                            only serum and coagulating lymph could <lb/>pass when they were in a
                            natural state, and till the newly extravasated <lb/>substances become
                            vascular; the effect is most probably owing wholly to <lb/>the above
                            cause. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This incipient enlargement of the vessels upon the
                            first excitement of <lb/>inflammation is satisfactorily seen in the
                            following manner. Make an <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">cision</w>
                            through the skin on the inside of the upper part of a dog's thigh,
                            <lb/>three inches long; by pulling the cut edges asunder, and observing
                            the ex-<lb/>posed surface, we shall see the blush or ash-coloured
                            cellular membrane <lb/>covering the different parts underneath, with a
                            few arteries passing through <pb n="280"/><lb/>it to the neighbouring
                            parts; but in a little time we shall see these vessels <lb/>increasing
                            in size, and also smaller vessels going off from them that were <lb/>not
                            before observable, as if newly formed or forming; the number and
                            <lb/>size shall increase till the whole surface shall become extremely
                            vascular, <lb/>and at last the red blood shall be thrown out in small
                            dots on the <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">posed</w> surface,
                            probably, through the cut ends of the arteries that only <lb/>carried
                            the lymph before. This surface will become in time more opaque, <lb/>and
                            less ductile. Parts inflamed, when compared with similar parts not
                            <lb/>inflamed, shew a considerable difference in the size of the
                            vessels, and <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">bably</w> from this
                            cause bring an increased number to view. I froze the <lb/>ear of a
                            rabbit and thawed it again; this excited a considerable <w part="I"
                                >inflam-</w><lb/><w part="F">mation</w>, and increased heat, and a
                            considerable thickening of the part. This <lb/>rabbit was killed when
                            the ear was in the height of inflammation, and the <lb/>head being
                            injected, the two ears were removed and dried. The uninflamed <lb/>ear
                            dried clear and transparent, the vessels were distinctly seen ramifying
                            <lb/>through the substance; but the inflamed ear dried thicker and more
                            <lb/>opaque, and its arteries were considerably larger. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In inflammation of the eye, which is commonly of the
                            tunica <w part="I">conjunc-</w><lb/><w part="F">tiva</w>, the progress
                            of inflammation may, in part, be accurately observed, <lb/>although not
                            so progressively as in a wound. The contrast between the <lb/>red vessel
                            and the white of the eye, under this coat is very conspicuous, <lb/>and
                            although we do not see the vessels enlarging in this coat, yet we see
                            <lb/>the progress they have made, the white appears as if it was
                            becoming <lb/>more vascular, and these vessels larger, till at last the
                            whole tunica <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">junctiva</w> shall
                            appear as one mass of blood, looking more like extravasated <lb/>blood <choice>
                                <corr>than</corr>
                                <sic>then</sic>
                            </choice> a congeries of vessels, although I believe it is commonly the
                            <lb/>last. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>From these circumstances it must appear, that a much
                            larger <w part="I">quan-</w><lb/><w part="F">tity</w> of blood passes
                            through parts when inflamed than when in a natural <lb/>state, which is
                            according to the common rules of the animal œconomy; <lb/>for, whenever
                            a part has more to do than simply to support itself, the <lb/>blood is
                            there collected in larger quantity; this we find to take place <w
                                part="I">uni-</w><lb/>
                            <w part="F">versally</w> in those parts whose powers are called up to
                            action by some <lb/>necessary operation to be performed, whether natural
                            or diseased. </p>
                        <pb n="281"/>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As the vessels become larger, and the part becomes
                            more of the colour <lb/>of the blood, it is to be supposed there is more
                            blood in the part; and as <lb/>the true inflammatory colour is scarlet,
                            or that colour which the blood <lb/>has when in the arteries, one would
                            from hence conclude, either that the <lb/>arteries were principally
                            dilated, or at least, if the veins are equally <w part="I"
                                >dis-</w><lb/><w part="F">ended</w>, that the blood undergoes no
                            change in such inflammation in its <lb/>passage from the arteries into
                            the veins, which I think is most probably <lb/>the case; and this may
                            arise from the quickness of its passage through <lb/>those vessels. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>When inflammation takes place in parts that have a
                            degree of <w part="I">trans-</w><lb/><w part="F">parency</w>, that
                            transparency is lessened. This is, probably, best seen in
                            <lb/>membranes, such as those membranes which line cavities, or cover
                            bodies <lb/>in those cavities, such as the pia-mater, where, in a
                            natural state, we may <lb/>observe the blood-vessels to be very
                            distinct. But when we see the <w part="I">blood-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                                >vessels</w> fuller than common, yet distinct in such membranes, we
                            are not <lb/>to call that inflammation, although it may be the first
                            step, as we find to <lb/>be the case in the first action of the vessels
                            in consequence of such <w part="I">irri-</w><lb/><w part="F">tation</w>
                            as will end in inflammation. As it may not, however, be the first
                            <lb/>step, there must be other attending circumstances to determine it
                            to be the <lb/>very first action of the vessels in inflammation, for as
                            that appearance <lb/>may either belong to a briskness in the circulation
                            in the part at the time, <lb/>or the very first step in inflammation,
                            their causes are to be discriminated <lb/>by some other symptom; they
                            are both a kind of blush, or an exertion of <lb/>the action of the
                            vessels; but when it is an effect of an inflammatory cause, <lb/>it is
                            then only that the inflammation has not yet produced any change in
                            <lb/>the natural structure of the parts, but which it will soon do <note
                                place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.75)">
                                <p rend="indent"><lb/>* When this appearance is seen any where after
                                    death, it should not be called <w part="I">inflam-</w><lb/><w
                                        part="F">mation</w>, even although we knew it was the first
                                    action of inflammation; for as we are then <lb/>only looking out
                                    for the causes of death, or the symptoms prior to death, we are
                                    only to look <lb/>out for such as can be a cause, and not lay
                                    hold of those that cannot possibly be a cause, <lb/>which those
                                    first actions cannot be. </p>
                            </note>. What the <lb/>action is, or in what it differs from the common
                            action of the vessels, is <lb/>not easily ascertained, since we are more
                            able to judge of the effects <lb/>than the immediate cause. However, it
                            is probably an action of the <pb n="282"/><lb/>vessels, which we can
                            better observe than any diseased action in the body, <lb/>for we can
                            observe the state in which the arteries are, with their general
                            <lb/>effects; we feel, also, a different temperature respecting heat,
                            yet the <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F">mediate</w> cause may not be
                            ascertainable. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The vessels, both arteries and veins, in the inflamed
                            part are enlarged, <lb/>and the part becomes visibly more vascular, from
                            which we should <w part="I">sus-</w><lb/><w part="F">pect</w>, that
                            instead of an increased contraction, there was rather what would
                            <lb/>appear an increased relaxation of their muscular powers, being, as
                            we might <lb/>suppose, left to the elasticity entirely. This would be
                            reducing them to a <lb/>state of paralysis simply; but the power of
                            muscular contraction would <lb/>seem to give way in inflammation, for
                            they certainly dilate more in <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                                >flammation</w> than the extent of the elastic power would allow;
                            and it must <lb/>also be supposed, that the elastic power of the artery
                            must be dilated <lb/>in the same proportion. The contents of the
                            circulation being <lb/>thrown out upon such occasions, would, from
                            considering it in those <lb/>lights, rather confirm us in that opinion;
                            and when we consider the whole <lb/>of this as a necessary operation of
                            nature, we must suppose it something <lb/>more than simply a common
                            relaxation; we must suppose it an action in <lb/>the parts to produce an
                            increase of size to answer particular purposes; and <lb/>this I should
                            call the action of dilatation, as we see the uterus increase <lb/>in
                            size in the time of uterine-gestation, as well as the os tincæ in the
                            time <lb/>of labour, the consequence of the preceding actions, and
                            necessary for <lb/>the completion of those which are to follow. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The force of the circulation would seem to have same
                            share in this <lb/>effect, but only as a secondary cause; for I could
                            conceive a part to <lb/>inflame, or be in a state of inflammation,
                            although no blood were to pass. <lb/>As a proof of this, we may observe,
                            that by lessening either the action <lb/>of the heart, or the column of
                            blood, inflammation is lessened; and I may <lb/>also observe, that we
                            have an increased pain in the inflamed part in the <lb/>diastole of the
                            artery, and a part inflamed by being gently pressed is made <lb/>easier.
                            Thus, a person with an inflammation in the fingers will find relief
                            <lb/>by gently pressing it in the other hand. These are strong proofs
                            that it <lb/>is not a contractile action of the vascular coat of the
                            vessel; for in such a <lb/>sensible state of vessels if they contracted
                            by their muscular power, the <pb n="283"/><lb/>pain would be in their
                            systole; for we find in all muscles which are in a <lb/>state of great
                            sensibility, from whatever cause, that they cannot act <lb/>without
                            giving great pain. Thus an inflamed bladder becomes extremely
                            <lb/>painful when expelling its contents, an inflamed intestine in the
                            same <lb/>manner; I should say, therefore, that in inflammations the
                            muscular coats <lb/>of the arteries do not contract. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Whatever purpose this increase of the size of the
                            vessels may answer, <lb/>we must suppose it allows a greater quantity of
                            blood to pass through the <lb/>inflamed part than in the natural state,
                            which supposition is supported by <lb/>many other observations. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The part inflamed, I have already observed, becomes to
                            appearance <lb/>more vascular than when in the natural state, and it is
                            probable that it is <lb/>really so, both from new vessels being set up
                            in the inflamed part, as well <lb/>as the new and adventitious uniting
                            substance becoming vascular. Besides, <lb/>the vessels of the parts are
                            enlarged, so that the red blood passes further <lb/>than common, which
                            increases those appearances. But the brain appears <lb/>to be an
                            exception to these general rules; for in all diseases of the brain,
                            <lb/>where the effects were such as are commonly the consequence of <w
                                part="I">inflam-</w><lb/><w part="F">mation</w>, such as suppuration
                            from accidents, I never could find the above <lb/>appearances; the brain
                            may, perhaps, go directly into suppuration, as <lb/>sometimes the
                            peritoneum does; but its slowness of going into suppuration <lb/>after
                            the accident, would make us supppose, apriori, that there was <w
                                part="I">suf-</w><lb/><w part="F">ficient</w> time for adhesions to
                            form. </p>
                        <figure rend="space">
                            <lb/>
                            <figDesc>A horizontal double-line in the middle of the page.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                    <div type="section">
                        <head rend="align-center space"><lb/>II. OF THE COLOUR, SWELLING, AND PAIN
                            OF INFLAMED PARTS. </head>
                        <p rend="indent space"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> colour of an inflamed
                            part is visibly changed from the natural, <lb/>whatever it was, to a
                            red. This red is of various hues, according to the <lb/>nature of the
                            inflammation; if healthy, it is a pale red; if less healthy, <lb/>the
                            colour will be darker, more of a purple, and so on till it shall be a
                            <lb/>blueish purple, which I took notice of in the short sketch of the
                            peculiar <pb n="284"/><lb/>inflammations; but the parts inflamed will in
                            every constitution be more <lb/>of the healthy red when the parts
                            inflamed are near to the source of the <lb/>circulation, than when far
                            from it. This increase of red appears to arise <lb/>from two causes; the
                            first is a dilatation of the vessels, whereby a greater <lb/>quantity of
                            blood is allowed to pass into those vessels which only admitted
                            <lb/>serum or lymph before<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.75)">
                                <p rend="indent"><lb/>The tunica conjunctiva of the eye when <choice>
                                        <corr>inflamed</corr>
                                        <sic>inflammed</sic>
                                    </choice>, is a striking instance of this; but the <lb/>visible
                                    progress of inflammation I have already described in the
                                    experiment on the dog. </p>
                            </note>. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The second is owing probably to new veſſels being set
                            up in the <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">travasated</w> uniting
                            coagulating lymph. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This colour is gradually lost in the surrounding part
                            if the inflammation <lb/>is of the healthy kind, but in many others it
                            has a determined edge, as in <lb/>the true erysepelatous, and in some
                            specific diseases, as in the small-pox, <lb/>where its quick termination
                            is a sign of health. </p>
                        <p rend="indent space"><lb/>From the account I have given of the immediate
                            effects of inflammation <lb/>of the cellular membrane, in which I
                            include the larger cavities, the <lb/>volume of the part inflamed must
                            be increased. This, when a common <lb/>consequence of inflammation, is
                            not circumscribed, but rather diffused, as <lb/>the inflammation,
                            however, begins in a circumscribed part, which is at <lb/>least the case
                            with that arising from violence; the inflammation I just now
                            <lb/>observed is always the greatest nearest to that point, and is
                            gradually lost <lb/>in the surrounding parts, the swelling of course is
                            the greatest at, or nearest <lb/>to this point, and it is also lost in
                            the surrounding sound parts. This <lb/>takes place, more or less,
                            according to the constitution, or the situation of <lb/>the
                            inflammation; for if the constitution be strong and healthy, the <w
                                part="I">sur-</w><lb/><w part="F">rounding</w> parts will sympathize
                            less with the point of irritation, so that <lb/>inflammation and its
                            consequences, viz. extravasation will be less diffused. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>There will be less of the serum, and of course a purer
                            coagulating lymph, <lb/>so that the swelled parts will be firmer; but in
                            some specific disease or <lb/>dissimilar part, as a gland, it has a more
                            determined edge, the surrounding <lb/>parts not so readily taking on
                            specific diseased action as in other cases. In <lb/>this both the colour
                            and swelling correspond very much, since they both <lb/>depend on the
                            same principle. </p>
                        <pb n="285"/>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This increase of volume is owing to the extravasation
                            of the coagulating <lb/>lymph, and some serum; in proportion to the
                            inflammation, the degree of <lb/>which depends on the causes
                            abovementioned, this effect is more or less, <lb/>and therefore is
                            greatest at the point of inflammation, becoming less and <lb/>less as it
                            extends into the surrounding parts, till it is insensibly lost in
                            <lb/>them. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The extravasation of the serum along with the
                            coagulating lymph is, <lb/>probably, not a separation of itself, as in a
                            dropsy, but a part of it being <lb/>separated from the lymph in the
                            coagulation of that fluid, is squeezed into <lb/>the surrounding
                            cellular membrane, where there is but little extravasation, <lb/>and
                            where the cells are not united by it. Thus the circumference of such
                            <lb/>swelling is a little œdamatous; but the whole of the serum, if
                            there be a <lb/>depending part, will move thither, and distend it
                            considerably, as in the <lb/>foot in consequence of an inflammation in
                            the leg. But in most cases <lb/>there is a continued extravasation of
                            serum, long after the extravasation of <lb/>the coagulating lymph is at
                            an end; so that depending parts will continue <lb/>œdematous, while the
                            inflammation is resolving, or while suppuration, or <lb/>even healing is
                            going on. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The whole swelling looks like a part of the body only
                            a little changed, <lb/>without any appearance of containing extraneous
                            matter; and indeed it is <lb/>simply formed by an extravasation of
                            fluids without their having <w part="I">under-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                                >gone</w> any visible or material change, except coagulation. </p>
                        <p rend="indent space"><lb/>As few uncommon operations can go on in an
                            animal body without <lb/>affecting the sensations, and as the first
                            principle of sensation arises from <lb/>some uncommon action, or
                            alteration being made in the natural position <lb/>or arrangement of the
                            parts, we should naturally suppose that the sensation <lb/>would be in
                            some degree according to those effects, and the sensibility of <lb/>the
                            parts. One can easily form an idea of an alteration in the structure
                            <lb/>of parts giving sensation which may even be carried to pain, but
                            that the <lb/>simple action of parts should produce sensations and even
                            violent pain is <lb/>but little known, or at least has been, I believe,
                            but little attended to; all <pb n="286"/><lb/>these effects, I think,
                            may justly be included under the term spasm<note place="bottom" n="*"
                                rend="size(0.75)">
                                <p rend="indent"><lb/><choice>
                                        <corr>*</corr>
                                        <sic>†</sic>
                                    </choice> How far a nerve from a part, or how far the materia
                                    vitæ of a part, can act so as to <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
                                        part="F">vey</w> sensation I do not know; but we all know
                                    that an involuntary action of a voluntary<lb/>muscle, or the
                                    spontaneous action of an involuntary muscle will produce it.
                                </p>
                            </note>; at <lb/>least we are led by analogy to suppose that they belong
                            to that class. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>By spasm I should understand a contraction of a
                            muscle, without the <lb/>leading and natural causes. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Thus the contraction of a muscle of the leg, called
                            the cramp, gives <lb/>considerable pain, often violent, as also the
                            tetanus, and when in a less <lb/>degree, as in the twinkling of the
                            eye-lid, it gives only sensation, whereas <lb/>if the muscles were to
                            act by the will, no sensation would be produced. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>We find that those sensations are more or less acute,
                            according to the <lb/>quickness or slowness of the progress of these
                            causes, from whence we are <lb/>naturally led to assign two causes which
                            must always attend one another; <lb/>for when both do not take place at
                            the same time, the mind then remains <lb/>insensible to the alteration.
                            This is its being produced in a given time, <lb/>for the alteration in
                            the position of the parts may be produced so slowly, <lb/>as not to keep
                            pace with sensation, which is the case with many indolent <lb/>tumors,
                            ascites, etc. on the other hand this alteration in the natural <w
                                part="I">posi-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of parts may be so quick
                            as to exceed sensation, and therefore there is <lb/>a certain medium,
                            which produces the greatest pain. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The actions I have been describing being pretty quick
                            in their effects, <lb/>we cannot fail to see why the pain from the
                            inflammation must be <w part="I">consi-</w><lb/><w part="F">derable</w>;
                            however the pain is not the same in all the different stages. In the
                            <lb/>adhesive state of the inflammation it is generally but very
                            inconsiderable, <lb/>especially if it is to go no further, and is
                            perhaps more of a heavy than an <lb/>acute pain; when it happens on the
                            skin it often begins with an itching; <lb/>but as the inflammation is
                            passing from the adhesive to the suppurative, <lb/>the parts then
                            undergo a greater change than before, and the pain grows <lb/>more and
                            more acute, till it become very considerable. The nerves also
                            <lb/>acquire at that time a degree of sensibility, which renders them
                            much more <lb/>susceptible of impressionn than when they are in their
                            natural state; thus <lb/>an inflamed part is not only painful in itself,
                            but it communicates <w part="I">im-</w><pb n="287"/><lb/><w part="F"
                                >pressions</w> to the mind independent of pain, which do not arise
                            from a <w part="I">na-</w><lb/><w part="F">tural</w> sound part. This
                            pain increases every time the arteries are dilated, <lb/>whence it would
                            appear that the arteries do not contract by their muscular <lb/>power,
                            in their systole, for if they did, we might expect a considerable pain
                            <lb/>in that action which would be at the full of the pulse. Whether
                            this <lb/>pain arises from the distention of the artery by the force of
                            the heart, or <lb/>whether it arises from the action of distention from
                            the force of the artery <lb/>itself, is not easily determined. We know
                            that diseased muscles give much <lb/>pain in their contraction, perhaps
                            more than they do when stretched<note place="bottom" n="*"
                                rend="size(0.75)">
                                <p rend="indent"><lb/>* This is very evident in the bladder of urine
                                    when inflamed, for in the contraction of that <lb/>viscus to
                                    expel the urine, there is more pain than in the dilatation;
                                    indeed, the distention <lb/>is gradual, and when the urine is
                                    wholly evacuated, the irritation produced by the contraction
                                    <lb/>still continues, which produces a continuance of the
                                    straining. </p>
                            </note>. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>That the degree of inflammation which becomes the
                            cause of adhesions <lb/>gives but little pain, is proved from
                            dissections of dead bodies; for we <lb/>seldom or never find a body in
                            dissection which has not adhesions in some <lb/>of the larger cavities;
                            and yet it may reasonably be supposed, that many <lb/>of these persons
                            never had any acute symptoms, or violent pain in those <lb/>parts;
                            indeed, we find many strong adhesions upon the opening of dead
                            <lb/>bodies, in parts which the friends of these persons never heard
                            mentioned, <lb/>during life, as the subject of a single complaint. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>That adhesions can be produced from very slight
                            inflammation, is <lb/>proved in ruptures in consequence of wearing a
                            truss; for we find the <lb/>slight pressure of a truss exciting such
                            action as to thicken parts, by <lb/>which means the two sides of the
                            sack are united, though there be hardly <lb/>any sensation in the part;
                            we also see, in cases where this inflammation <lb/>arises from violence,
                            it gives little or no pain. A man shall be shot <lb/>through the cavity
                            of the abdomen, and if none of the contained parts are <lb/>materially
                            hurt, the adhesive inflammation shall take place in all the <w part="I"
                                >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ternal</w> parts contiguous to the wound
                            made by the ball, and yet no great <lb/>degree of pain shall be felt.
                            This assertion is still proved by the little pain <lb/>suffered after
                            many bruises, where there is evident inflammation; and in <lb/>simple
                            fractures, the pain from <choice>
                                <corr/>
                                <sic>the</sic>
                            </choice> the inflammation is very trifling, <w part="I"
                                >what-</w><lb/><w part="F">ever</w> it may be from the laceration of
                            the parts. But this will be <w part="I">ac-</w><pb n="288"/><lb/><w
                                part="F">cording</w> to the degree of inflammation, what stage it is
                            in, and what parts <lb/>are inflamed, as will be fully explained
                            hereafter. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>We find it a common principle in the animal machine,
                            that every part <lb/>increases in some degree according to the action
                            required. Thus we find <lb/>muscles increase in size when much
                            exercised; vessels become larger in <lb/>proportion to the necessity of
                            supply, as for instance, in the gravid uterus; <lb/>the external
                            carotids in the stag, also, when his horns are growing, are <lb/>much
                            larger than at any other time; and I have observed, that in <w part="I"
                                >inflam-</w><lb/><w part="F">mation</w>, the vessels become larger,
                            more blood passes, and there appear to <lb/>be more actions taking
                            place; but the nerves do not seem to undergo any <lb/>change. The nerves
                            of the gravid uterus are the same as when it is in <lb/>the natural
                            state; neither do the branches of the fifth and seventh pair of
                            <lb/>nerves in the stag become larger; and in inflammation of the
                            nerves, their <lb/>blood-vessels are enlarged, and have coagulating
                            lymph thrown into their <lb/>intestines, but the nerve itself is not
                            increased so as to bring the part to <lb/>the state of a natural part,
                            fitted for acute sensation, which shews that the <lb/>motions of the
                            nerves have nothing to do with the œconomy of the part, <lb/>they are
                            only the messengers of intelligence and orders. It appears that
                            <lb/>only the actions of the materia vitæ in the inflamed parts is
                            increased, and <lb/>this increase of action in the inflamed part is
                            continued along the nerve <lb/>which is not inflamed, to the mind, so
                            that the impression on the <w part="I">senso-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                                >rum</w> is, probably, equal to the action of the inflamed materia
                            vitæ. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The quantity of natural sensibility is, I believe,
                            proportioned to the <lb/>quantity of nerves, under any given
                            circumstance; but I apprehend, the <lb/>diseased sensibility does not
                            take place at all in this proportion, but <lb/>in proportion to the
                            diseased action of the materia vitæ. Thus a tendon <lb/>has very little
                            sensation when injured in a natural state; but let that <w part="I"
                                >ten-</w><lb/><w part="F">don</w> become inflamed, or otherwise
                            diseased, and the sensation shall be <lb/>very acute. </p>
                        <p rend="indent space"><lb/>It may not be improper to observe, that many
                            parts of the body in <lb/>a natural state, give peculiar sensations when
                            impressed; and when those <lb/>parts are injured, they give, likewise,
                            pain peculiar to themselves; it <lb/>is this latter effect, which I am
                            to consider. I may also observe, that the <pb n="289"/><lb/>same mode of
                            impression shall give a peculiar sensation to one part, while <lb/>it
                            shall give pain to another. Thus, what will produce sickness in the
                            <lb/>stomach, will produce pain in the colon. When the sensation of pain
                            is <lb/>in a vital part, it is somewhat different from most of those
                            pains that are <lb/>common. Thus, when the pain arises from an injury
                            done to the head, <lb/>the sensation is a heavy stupifying pain,
                            rendering the person affected <lb/>unfit to pay attention to other
                            sensations, and is often attended with <w part="I">sick-</w><lb/><w
                                part="F">ness</w>, from the stomach sympathizing with it. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>When the pain is in the heart or lungs, it is more
                            acute, and is very <lb/>much confined to the part diseased. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>When in the stomach and intestines, especially the
                            upper part of them, <lb/>it is a heavy oppressive sickly pain, but more
                            or less, attended with <w part="I">sick-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w>,
                            according to its pressure or proximity to the stomach; for when
                            <lb/>situated in the colon, it is more acute, and less attended with
                            sickness. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>We cannot give a better illustration of this, than by
                            taking notice of <lb/>the effects of a purge. If we take such a purge as
                            will produce both <w part="I">sick-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w> and
                            griping, we can easily trace the progress of the medicine in the
                            <lb/>canal; when in the stomach it makes us sick, but we soon find the
                                <w part="I">sick-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w> becoming more faint,
                            by which we can judge that it has proceeded <lb/>to the duodenum, and
                            then a kind of uneasiness, approaching to pain, <w part="I"
                                >suc-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceeds</w>; when this the case, we may be
                            certain that the medicine is passing <lb/>along the jejunum; it then
                            begins to give a sickish griping pain, which I <lb/>conceive belongs to
                            the ilium; and when in the colon it is a sharp pain, <lb/>soon after
                            which a motion takes place. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The liver, testicles, and uterus, are subject nearly
                            to the same kind of <lb/>pain as the stomach. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>A tendon, ligament, and bone, give something of the
                            same kind of pain, <lb/>though not so oppressive; namely, a dull and
                            heavy pain, often attended <lb/>with some little sickness, the stomach
                            generally sympathizing in such <lb/>cases. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But the skin, muscles, and the cellular membrane, in
                            common, give an <lb/>acute pain, which rather rouses than oppresses, if
                            not too great. All of <lb/>this will be further mentioned when we treat
                            of each part. </p>
                        <pb n="290"/>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>One cause of this variety of sensations, according as
                            the parts inflamed, <lb/>are vital or not vital, seems to consist in the
                            different systems of materia vitæ <lb/>with which those parts are
                            supplied, having, probably, nerves peculiarly <lb/>constructed for this
                            purpose; for all the parts which are supplied with <lb/>branches from
                            the par vagum and intercostals, affect the patient with <w part="I"
                                >low-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w> of spirits from the very first
                            attack of the inflammation: the actions <lb/>of those parts are
                            involuntary, and therefore are more immediately <w part="I"
                                >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">nected</w> with the living principle, and
                            consequently that principle is affected <lb/>whenever any thing affects
                            these nerves. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The other system of the materia vitæ, when affected by
                            this <w part="I">inflamma-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, rather rouses
                            at first the constitution, which shows signs of strength, <lb/>unless
                            the parts have rather weak powers of recovery, such as tendon,
                            <lb/>bone, etc. or are far from the heart, in which cases the signs of
                            weakness, <lb/>sooner or later, appear: hence it would seem that this
                            difference in the <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">stitution</w>,
                            arising from the difference in parts and their situation, arises from
                            <lb/>the constitution having a disease which it cannot so easily manage,
                            as it <lb/>can in those parts which are not vital, and in parts that are
                            near to the <lb/>heart, which circumstances alone become a cause of
                            irritation in the <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">stitution</w>. </p>
                        <figure rend="space">
                            <lb/>
                            <figDesc>A horizontal double-line in the middle of the page.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="80"/>
                </div>
                <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="138"/>
            </div>
            <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="12"/>
            <pb n="521"/>
            <div type="part">
                <head rend="size(2.0) align-center space"><lb/>PART IV. </head>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head rend="align-center space size(1.25)"><lb/>CHAPTER I. </head>
                    <head rend="italic align-center space size(1.25)"><lb/>OF GUN-SHOT WOUNDS. </head>
                    <figure rend="space">
                        <lb/>
                        <figDesc>A long horizontal double-line in the middle of the page.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <p rend="space"><lb/><hi rend="seíze(2.0)">G</hi><hi rend="sc">un-shot</hi>
                        wounds may be said to be an effect of ainodern <w part="I"
                            >improve-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w> in offence and defence, unknown
                        in the former mode of war, which <lb/>is still practised where European
                        improvements are not known; and it is <lb/>curious to observe that fire-arms
                        and spirits are the first of our <w part="I">refine-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                            >ments</w> that are adopted in uncivilized countries; and, indeed, for
                        ages they <lb/>have been the only objects that have been at all noticed or
                        sought after <lb/>by rude nations. It was not till the fourteenth century
                        that gunpowder <lb/>was made, or rather compounded; but it was not, till
                        afterwards, applied <lb/>to the purpose of projecting bodies. But even now,
                        the wounds received <lb/>in war are not all gun-shot wounds: some,
                        therefore, are similar in many <lb/>respects to those received in former
                        times. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/>The knowledge of the effect of gunpowder, and its
                        application to the <lb/>art of war, or the projection of bodies for the
                        destruction of men, has been <lb/>in some degree accompanied by improvements
                        in the arts and sciences <lb/>in general, and among others, that of surgery,
                        in which art, the <w part="I">heal-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> of wounds so
                        produced, makes a material part. In France, more <lb/>especially, the study
                        of both were carried to considerable lengths; but <lb/>though the art of
                        destruction has been there improved and illustrated by <lb/>writings, it is
                        rather surprising that the art of healing should not have <lb/>been equally
                        illustrated in the same manner. Little has been written on <lb/>this
                        subject, although, perhaps, when we take every circumftance into <pb n="522"
                        /><lb/>consideration, it requires particular discussionn; and what has been
                        written <lb/>is so superficial, that it deserves but little attention.
                        Practice, not <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">cept</w>, seemed to be
                        the guide of all who studied in this branch; and, if we <lb/>observe the
                        practice hitherto pursued, we shall find it very confined, being <lb/>hardly
                        reduced to the common rules of surgery, and therefore it was hardly
                        <lb/>necessary for a man to be a surgeon to practice in the army. </p>
                    <div type="section">
                        <figure rend="space">
                            <lb/>
                            <figDesc>A horizontal double-line in the middle of the page.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <head rend="space align-center"><lb/>I. THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN GUN-SHOT
                            WOUNDS AND COMMON <lb/>WOUNDS. </head>
                        <p rend="space indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Gun-shot</hi> wounds are named, as
                            is evident, from the manner in which <lb/>they are produced. From the
                            frequency of their happening in the time <lb/>of battle to a set of men
                            appropriated for war, both by sea and land : and <lb/>from the
                            appointment of particular surgeons for their cure, they have been
                            <lb/>considered apart from other wounds, and are now become almost a <w
                                part="I">dis-</w><lb/><w part="F">tinct</w> branch of surgery. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Gun-shot wounds are made by the projection of hard
                            obtuse bodies, the <lb/>greatest number of which are musket-balls; for
                            cannon-balls, pieces of <lb/>shells and stones from ramparts in sieges,
                            or splinters of wood, etc. when <lb/>on board of a ship in an engagement
                            at sea, can hardly have their effects <lb/>ranked among gun-shot wounds,
                            they will come in more properly with <lb/>wounds in general. As the
                            wounds themselves made by those very <w part="I">dif-</w><lb/><w
                                part="F">ferent</w> modes will in general differ very considerably;
                            any peculiarity that <lb/>may be necessary in the treatment of gun-shot
                            wounds, from those made <lb/>by cannon-balls, shells, etc. or even
                            common wounds, will generally <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                                >long</w> to those made by musket-balls. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The whole of gun-shot wounds will come within the
                            definition of <w part="I">ac</w><lb/><w part="F">cidents</w>. They are a
                            recent violence committed on the body; but they <lb/>often become the
                            cause of, or degenerate into a thousand complaints, <lb/>which are the
                            objects of surgery or physic, many of which are common to <lb/>accidents
                            in general, and to many other diseases; of this kind are abscesses,
                            <lb/>ulcerating bones, fistulæ; but some are peculiar to gun-shot
                            wounds, as <pb n="523"/><lb/>calculi in the bladder from the ball
                            entering that viscus, consumption <lb/>from wounds in the lungs, which I
                            believe rarely happens; for I cannot <lb/>say I ever faw a case where
                            such an effect took place. But it is the recent <lb/>state in which they
                            are distinguished, and in which they are to be <w part="I"
                                >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">sidered</w> as a distinct object of
                            treatment. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Wounds of this kind vary from one another, which will
                            happen <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">cording</w> to circumstances;
                            these variations will be in general according to <lb/>the kind of body
                            projected, the velocity of the body, with the nature and
                            <lb/>peculiarities of the parts injured. The kind of body projected, I
                            have <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">served</w>, is principally
                            musket-balls, sometimes cannon-balls, sometimes <lb/>pieces of broken
                            shells, and very often on board of ship, splinters of <lb/>wood. Indeed,
                            the effects of cannon- balls on different parts of the ship, <lb/>either
                            the containing parts, as the hull of the ship itself, or the contained,
                            <lb/>are the principal causes of wounds in the sailor; for a cannon-ball
                            must <lb/>go through the timbers of the ship before it can do more
                            execution than <lb/>simply as a ball, (which makes it a spent ball) and
                            which splinters the <lb/>inside of the ship very considerably, and moves
                            other bodies in the ship, <lb/>neither of which it would do if moving
                            with sufficient velocity; musket <lb/>or cannon-balls seldom doing
                            immediate injury to those of that profession. <lb/>The wounds produced
                            by the three last bodies will be more like many <lb/>common and violent
                            accidents, attended with much contusion and <w part="I">lace-</w><lb/><w
                                part="F">ration</w> of parts. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Gun-shot wounds, from whatever cause, whether from a
                            musket-ball, <lb/>cannon-ball, or shell, etc. are in general contused
                            wounds, from which <lb/>contusion there is most commonly a part of the
                            solids surrounding the <lb/>wound deadened, as the projecting body
                            forced its way through these solids, <lb/>which is afterwards thrown off
                            in form of a slough, and which prevents <lb/>such wounds from healing by
                            the first intention, or by means of the <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w
                                part="F">hesive</w> inflammation, from which circumstance most of
                            them must be <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">lowed</w> to suppurate.
                            This does not always take place equally in every <lb/>gun-shot wound,
                            nor in every part of the same wound; and the difference <lb/>commonly
                            arises from the variety in the velocity of the body projected; for
                            <lb/>we find in many cases, where the ball has passed with little
                            velocity, <lb/>which is often the case with balls, even at their
                            entrance, but most <w part="I">com-</w><pb n="524"/><lb/><w part="F"
                                >monly</w> at the part last wounded by the ball, that the wounds are
                            often <lb/>healed by the first intention. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Gun-shot wounds, from the circumstance of commonly
                            having a part <lb/>killed, in general do not inflame so readily as those
                            from other accidents; <lb/>this backwardness to inflame will be in the
                            proportion that the quantity of <lb/>deadened parts bear to the extent
                            of the wound; from which <w part="I">circum-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                                >stance</w> the inflammation is later in coming on, more especially
                            when a <lb/>ball passes through a fleshy part with great velocity;
                            because there will <lb/>be a great deal deadened, in proportion to the
                            size of the wound; <w part="I">there-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w>
                            inflammation in gun-shot wounds is less than in wounds in general,
                            <lb/>where the same quantity of mischief has been done; and this, also,
                            is in <lb/>an inverse proportion to the quantity of the parts deadened,
                            as I have <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">ready</w> explained in my
                            introduction to inflammation, viz. that <w part="I">inflamma-</w><lb/><w
                                part="F">tion</w> is less, where parts are to slough, than where
                            parts have been destroyed <lb/>by other means. On the other hand, where
                            the ball has fractured some <lb/>bone, which fracture in the bone has
                            done considerable mischief to the <lb/>soft parts, independent of the
                            ball, then there will be nearly as quick <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w
                                part="F">flammation</w> as in a compound fracture of the same bone,
                            because the <lb/>deadened part bears no proportion to the laceration or
                            wound in general. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>From this circumstance, of a part being often
                            deadened, a gun-shot <lb/>wound is often not completely understood at
                            first; for it is at first, in <lb/>many cases, impossible to know what
                            parts are killed, whether bone, <w part="I">ten-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                                >don</w>, or soft part, till the deadened part has separated, which
                            often makes <lb/>it a much more complicated wound than at first was
                            known or imagined; <lb/>for it very often happens, that some viscus, or
                            a part of some viscus, or a <lb/>part of a large artery, or even a bone,
                            has been killed by the blow, which <lb/>does not show itself till the
                            slough comes away. If, for instance, it is a <lb/>part of an intestine
                            that has received a contusion, so as to kill it, and which <lb/>is to
                            slough, a new symptom will most probably appear from the sloughs
                            <lb/>being separated, the contents of the intestine will most probably
                            come <lb/>through the wound; and probably the same thing will happen
                            when any <lb/>other containing viscus is in part deadened; but those
                            cases will not be so <lb/>dangerous, as if the same loss had been
                            produced at first, for by this time all <lb/>communication will be cut
                            off between the containing and contained parts; <pb n="525"/><lb/>nor
                            will it be so dangerous as when a considerable blood-vessel is deadened;
                            <lb/>for in this case, when the slough comes off, the blood, getting a
                            free <lb/>passage into the wound, as also out of it, probably death will
                                <w part="I">immedi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ately</w> follow. If this
                            artery is internal, nothing can be done; if in an <w part="I"
                                >ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">tremity</w>, the vessel may be either taken
                            up, or probably amputation may <lb/>be necessary to save the person's
                            life; therefore an early attention should <lb/>be paid to accidents,
                            where such an event is possible. In case of a bone <lb/>being deadened,
                            an exfoliation takes place. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Gun-shot wounds are often such as do much mischief to
                            vital parts, the <lb/>effects of which will be according to the nature
                            of the parts wounded, <lb/>and the violence of the wound; and also to
                            parts, the soundness of which <lb/>are essential either to the health of
                            the whole, or to the uses of the parts <lb/>wounded; such as some
                            viscus, whose contents are voided through the <lb/>opening, or joints,
                            the disposition of which is slow to heal, and whose <lb/>uses are
                            impeded when healed. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Gun-shot wounds often admit of being classed with the
                            small and deep <lb/>seated wounds, which are always of a particular kind
                            respecting the cure. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The variety of circumstances attending gun-shot wounds
                            is almost <w part="I">end-</w><lb/><w part="F">less</w>; the following
                            case may be given as an example. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>An officer in the navy was wounded by a pistol-ball,
                            in the right side, <lb/>about the last rib; it entered about five inches
                            from the navel, and <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">peared</w> on
                            the inside of the skin about two inches from the spinal process,
                            <lb/>having passed, I believe, in among the abdominal muscles. The only
                                <w part="I">re-</w>
                            <lb/><w part="F"><choice>
                                    <corr>markable</corr>
                                    <sic>remarkable</sic>
                                </choice></w> thing that occured was, that the cellular membrane for
                            some <lb/>way about the passage of the ball was œdematous, and when I
                            cut out the <lb/>ball, air came out with it. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="section">
                        <figure rend="space">
                            <lb/>
                            <figDesc>A long horizontal double-line in the middle of the
                                page.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <head rend="space align-center"><lb/>II. OF THE DIFFERENT EFFECTS ARISING
                            FROM THE DIFFERENCE <lb/>IN THE VELOCITY OF THE BALL. </head>
                        <p rend="space indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Many</hi> of the varieties between
                            one gun-shot wound and another, arise <lb/>from the difference in the
                            velocity of the body projected; and they are <lb/>principally the
                            following. </p>
                        <pb n="526"/>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>If the velocity of the ball is small, then the
                            mischief is less in all of <lb/>them; there is not so great a chance of
                            their being compounded with <w part="I">frac-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                                >tures</w> of the bones, etc. but if the velocity is sufficient to
                            break the bone <lb/>it hits, the bone will be much more splintered than
                            if the velocity had <lb/>been very considerable; for where the velocity
                            is very great, the ball, as it <lb/>were, takes a piece out; however,
                            all this will also vary according to the <lb/>hardness of the bone. In a
                            hard bone the splinters will be the most <w part="I">fre-</w><lb/><w
                                part="F">quent</w>. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>When the velocity is small, the direction of the wound
                            produced by <lb/>the ball, will, in common, not be so strait, therefore
                            its direction not so <lb/>readily ascertained, arising from the easy
                            turn of the ball. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>When the velocity is small, the deadened part or
                            slough is always less; <lb/>for with a small velocity, a ball would seem
                            only to divide parts, while <lb/>when the velocity is great, the
                            contrary must happen; from this <w part="I">circum-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                                >stance</w> it is, that the slough is larger at that orifice where
                            the ball enters <lb/>than where it comes out; and if the ball meets with
                            a great deal of <w part="I">resist-</w><lb/><w part="F">ance</w> in its
                            paſſage through, there will very probably be no slough at all <lb/>at
                            its exit, which will be therefore only a lacerated wound. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The greater the velocity of the ball, the cleaner it
                            wounds the parts, <lb/>so much so as almost to be similar to a cut with
                            a ſharp instrument; from <lb/>which circumstance it might be imagined,
                            that there should be a smaller <lb/>slough; but I suspect, that a
                            certain velocity given to the best cutting <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w
                                part="F">strument</w>, would produce a slough on the cut edges of
                            the divided parts; <lb/>for the divided parts not giving way equally to
                            the velocity of the dividing <lb/>body, must of course be proportionally
                            bruised. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Gun-shot wounds are attended with less bleeding than
                            most others; <lb/>however, some will be attended with this symptom more
                            than others, <lb/>even in the same part; this arises from the manner in
                            which the wound is <lb/>produced: bleeding arises from a vessel being
                            cut or broken; but the <w part="I">free-</w><lb/><w part="F">dom</w> of
                            bleeding arises from the manner in which this is done: if the <w
                                part="I">ar-</w><lb/><w part="F">tery</w> is cut directiy across,
                            and it is done by a ball passing with a <w part="I">consider-</w><lb/><w
                                part="F">able</w> velocity, it will bleed pretty freely; if bruised,
                            and in some degree <lb/>torn, then it will bleed less. When the velocity
                            of the ball is small, the <lb/>vessel will be principally torn, for they
                            will have time to stretch before <pb n="527"/><lb/>the continuity of
                            their parts gives way; but if it is great, they will bleed <lb/>more
                            freely, because velocity will make up for want of sharpness. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>According to the velocity of the ball so is the
                            direction. When the <w part="I">ve-</w><lb/><w part="F">locity</w> is
                            great, the direction of the ball will be in general more in a strait
                            <lb/>line than when it is small; for under such circumstances the ball
                            more <lb/>easily overcomes obstructions, and therefore passes on in its
                            first <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F">rection</w>. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Velocity in the ball makes parts less capable of
                            healing, than when it <lb/>moves with a small velocity; therefore
                            gun-shot wounds in pretty thick <lb/>parts are in general later of
                            healing at the orifice where the ball enters, <lb/>than at the orifice
                            where it passes out; because it becomes in some degree <lb/>a spent
                            ball, the part having less slough, being only torn, which will often
                            <lb/>admit of being healed by the first intention. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In cases where the ball passes through, and in such a
                            direction as to have <lb/>one orifice more depending than the other, I
                            have always found that the <lb/>depending orifice healed soonest, and
                            more certainly so is the ball came <lb/>out that way, and also if the
                            ball had been pretty much spent in its <w part="I">pas-</w><lb/><w
                                part="F">sage</w>; therefore it will require art to keep the
                            depending orifice open, if <lb/>thought necessary; but this circumstance
                            of its being a spent ball, will not <lb/>always happen, because if the
                            person is near the gun when fired, the <w part="I">velo-</w><lb/><w
                                part="F">city</w> of the ball will be very little diminished in its
                            progress through the soft <lb/>parts; and therefore it will have nearly
                            the same velocity on both sides. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This fact of the lower orifice healing soonest, is
                            common to all wounds, <lb/>and I believe is owing to the tumefaction
                            which generally arises from the <lb/>extravasated fluid always
                            descending to the lower part, and being retarded <lb/>at the lower
                            orifice, it is as it were stopped there, and presses the sides <lb/>of
                            the wound together, obliging it to heal, if the parts have not been
                            <lb/>deadened; this is evidently the case after the introduction of the
                            seaton in <lb/>the hydrocele, especially if the two orifices of the
                            seaton are at some <lb/>distance; but in the hydrocele there is a more
                            striking reason for it; for <lb/>in this disease, the extravasated
                            fluids are wholly detained about the lower <lb/>orifice, as there is no
                            depending part for the fluid to descend to. </p>
                    </div>
                    <pb n="528"/>
                    <div type="section">
                        <head rend="space align-center"><lb/>III. OF THE DIFFERENT KINDS OF GUN-SHOT
                            WOUNDS. </head>
                        <p rend="space indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Gun-shot</hi> wounds may be
                            divided into the simple, and the <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                                >pound</w>. Simple, when the ball passes into, or through the soft
                            parts only: <lb/>the compound will be according to the other parts
                            wounded. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The first species of compound, are those attended with
                            fractures of the <lb/>bones, or with the wound of some large artery. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The second species of compound wounds is, where the
                            ball penetrates <lb/>into some of the larger circumscribed cavities.
                            This last, or penetrating <lb/>wound, may be doubly complicated, or may
                            be divided into two. First, <lb/>simply penetrating; and, secondly,
                            where some viscus or contained part, <lb/>as the brain, lungs, heart,
                            abdominal <choice>
                                <corr>viscera</corr>
                                <sic>visera</sic>
                            </choice>, etc. is injured; all which <lb/>cases will be taken notice of
                            in their proper places. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <pb n="529"/>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head rend="align-center space size(1.25)"><lb/>CHAPTER II. </head>
                    <head rend="italic space align-center size(1.25)"><lb/>OF THE TREATMENT OF
                        GUN-SHOT WOUNDS. </head>
                    <figure>
                        <lb/>
                        <figDesc>A horizontal double-line in the middle of the page.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <p rend="space"><lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">I</hi><hi rend="sc">t</hi> has been
                        hitherto recommended, and universally practised by almost <lb/>every
                        surgeon, to open immediately upon their being received, or as soon <lb/>as
                        possible, the external orifice of all gun-shot wounds made by <w part="I"
                            >musket-</w><lb/><w part="F">balls</w>; so much has this practice been
                        recommended, that they have made <lb/>no discrimination between one gun-shot
                        wound and another; this would <lb/>appear to have arisen, and to be still
                        continued, from an opinion that <lb/>gun-shot wounds have a something
                        peculiar to them, and of -course are <lb/>different from all other wounds,
                        and that this peculiarity is removed by <lb/>the opening; I own that I do
                        not see any peculiarity. The most <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                            >bable</w> way of accounting for the first introduction of this
                        practice, is from <lb/>the wound in general being small, and nearly of a
                        size from one end to <lb/>the other; also the frequency of extraneous bodies
                        being forced into <lb/>these wounds by the ball, or the ball itself
                        remaining there; for the way <lb/>in which these wounds are made, is by the
                        introduction of an <w part="I">extrane-</w><lb/><w part="F">ous</w> body
                        which is left there, if it has not made its way through, so that <lb/>the
                        immediate cause of the wound makes a lodgment for itself; often <w part="I"
                            >car-</w><lb/><w part="F">rying</w> before it cloathes, and even the
                        parts of the body wounded, such as the <lb/>skin, etc. from hence it would
                        naturally appear at first view, that there was <lb/>an immediate necessity
                        to search after those extraneous bodies, which very <lb/>probably led the
                        surgeon to do it; and in general the impossibility of <w part="I"
                            >find-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> them, and even of extracting them
                        when found, without dilatation, gave <lb/>the first idea of opening the
                        mouths of the wounds; but, from experience, <lb/>they altered this practice
                        in part, and became not so desirous of searching <lb/>after these extraneous
                        bodies; for they found that it was oftener impossible<w part="I"
                            >impossi</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w> to find them than could at first
                        have been imagined, and when found that <pb n="530"/><lb/>it was not
                        possible to extract them, and that afterwards these bodies <lb/>were brought
                        to the skin by the parts themselves, and those that could <lb/>not be
                        brought to the external surface in this way, were such as gave <lb/>little
                        or no trouble afterwards, such as balls; yet they altered this <w part="I"
                            >prac-</w><lb/><w part="F">tice</w> only so far as respected the attempt
                        to extract extraneous bodies, for <lb/>when they found from experience, that
                        it was not necessary nor possible <lb/>to extract these immediately, yet
                        they did not see that it therefore was not <lb/>necessary to take the
                        previous or leading steps towards it. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/>The circumstance I have mentioned, of gun-shot wounds
                        being <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tused</w>, obliges most of them
                        to suppurate, because in such cases there is <lb/>more or less of a slough
                        to be thrown off, especially at the orifice made <lb/>by the entrance of the
                        ball; there is, therefore, a freer passage for the <lb/>matter, or any other
                        extraneous substance, than the same sized wound <lb/>would have, if made by
                        a clean cutting instrument, even if not allowed to <lb/>heal by the first
                        intention. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/>From all which, if there is no peculiarity in a gun-shot
                        wound, I <lb/>think this of dilating them as a general practice should be
                        rejected at <lb/>once, even were it only for this reason, that few gun-shot
                        wounds are <lb/>alike, and therefore the same practice cannot apply to all. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/>This treatment of gun-shot wounds is diametrically
                        opposite to a <w part="I">prin-</w><lb/><w part="F">ciple</w> which is
                        generally adopted in other cases, although not understood <lb/>as a general
                        rule, which is, that very few wounds of any kind require <w part="I"
                            >sur-</w><lb/><w part="F">gical</w> treatment at their commencement,
                        excepting with an opposite view <lb/>from the above, viz. to heal them by
                        the first intention. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is contrary to all the rules of surgery founded on our
                        knowledge of <lb/>the animal œconomy to enlarge wounds simply as wounds; no
                        wound, <lb/>let it be ever so small, should be made larger, excepting when
                        preparatory <lb/>to something else, which will imply a complicated wound,
                        and which is <lb/>to be treated accordingly; it should not be opened because
                        it is a wound, <lb/>but because there is something necessary to be done,
                        which cannot be <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">ecuted</w> unless the
                        wound is enlarged. </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/>This is common surgery, and ought also to be military
                        surgery <w part="I">respect-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> gun-shot wounds. </p>
                    <pb n="531"/>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/>As a proof of the inutility of opening gun-shot wounds as
                        a general <lb/>practice, I shall mention the cases of four Frenchmen, and a
                        British <w part="I">sol-</w><lb/><w part="F">dier</w>, wounded on the day of
                        the landing of our army on the island of <w part="I">Bel-</w><lb/><w
                            part="F">lisle</w>; and as this neglect rather arose from accident than
                        design, there is no <lb/>merit claimed from the mode of treatment. </p>
                    <list>
                        <item rend="indent"><lb/><label>Case I.</label> A. B. was wounded in the
                            thigh by two balls, one went <lb/>quite through, the other lodged
                            somewhere in the thigh, and was not <lb/>found while he was under our
                            care. </item>
                        <item rend="indent"><lb/><label>II.</label> B. C. was shot through the
                            chest; he spit blood for some little <lb/>time. </item>
                        <item rend="indent"><lb/><label>III.</label> C. D. was shot through the
                            joint of the knee: the ball entered at <lb/>the outer edge of the
                            patella, crossed the joint under that bone, and came <lb/>out through
                            the inner condyle of the os femoris. </item>
                        <item rend="indent"><lb/><label>IV.</label> D. E. was shot in the arm: the
                            ball entered at the inside of the <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                                >sertion</w> of the deltoid muscle, passed towards the head of the
                            os humeris, <lb/>then between the scapula and ribs, and lodged between
                            the basis of the <lb/>scapula and spinal processes, and was afterwards
                            extracted. The man's <lb/>arm was extented horizontally when the ball
                            entered, which accounts for <lb/>this direction. </item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/>These four men had not any thing done to their wounds for
                        four days <lb/>after receiving them, as they had hid themselves in a
                        farm-house all that <lb/>time after we had taken possession of the island;
                        and when they were <lb/>brought to the hospital, their wounds were only
                        dressed superficially, and <lb/>they all got well, </p>
                    <p rend="indent"><lb/>A grenadier of the 30th regiment was shot through the arm,
                        the ball <lb/>seemed to pass between the biceps muscle and the bone; he was
                        taken <lb/>prisoner by the French. The arm swelled considerably, they
                        fomented <lb/>it freely, and a superficial dressing only was applied. About
                        a <w part="I">fort-</w><lb/><w part="F">night</w> after the accident he made
                        his escape, and came to our hospital; but <lb/>by that time the swelling had
                        quite subsided, and the wounds healed; <lb/>there only remained a stiffness
                        in the joint of the elbow, which went off <lb/>by moving it. </p>
                    <pb n="532"/>
                    <div type="section">
                        <head rend="space align-center"><lb/>I. OF THE PROPRIETY OF DILATING
                            GUN-SHOT WOUNDS. </head>
                        <p rend="space indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> would be absurd for any
                            one to suppose that there is never occasion <lb/>to dilate gun-shot
                            wounds at all; but it is certain there are very few in <lb/>which it is
                            necessary. It will be impossible to determine by any general
                            <lb/>description what those are that ought to be opened, and what those
                            are <lb/>that ought not, that must be left in a great measure to the
                            discretion of <lb/>the surgeon, when once he is master of the arguments
                            on both sides. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Some general rules may be given with regard to the
                            more simple cases; <lb/>but with regard to the more complicated, the
                            particular circumftances of <lb/>each case are the only guide; and they
                            must be treated according to the <lb/>general principles of surgery. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Let us first give an idea of the wound that would
                            appear to receive no <lb/>benefit from being dilated; and first of the
                            most simple wounds. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>If a ball passes through a fleshy part where it can
                            hurt no bone in its <lb/>way, such as the thick of the thigh, I own, in
                            such a simple wound, I <lb/>see no reason for opening it; because I see
                            no purpose that can be <w part="I">an-</w><lb/><w part="F">swered</w> by
                            it, except the shortening of the depth of the wound made by <lb/>the
                            ball, which can be productive of no benefit. If the ball does not pass
                            <lb/>through, and is not to be found, opening can be of as little
                            service. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>If the opening in the skin should be objected to, as
                            being too small, <lb/>and thereby forming an obstruction to the exit of
                            the slough, etc. I <lb/>think that in general it is not; for the skin is
                            kept open by its own <w part="I">elas-</w><lb/><w part="F">ticity</w>,
                            as we see in all wounds; this elasticity, muscles and many other
                            <lb/>parts have not; and in general the opening made by a ball is much
                            <lb/>larger than those made by pointed instruments; for I have already
                                <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">served</w>, that there is often
                            a piece of the skin carried in before the ball, <lb/>especially if it
                            passed with considerable velocity, besides the circular slough; <lb/>so
                            that there is really in such cases a greater loss of substance; <w
                                part="I">there-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w>, whatever matter or
                            extraneous body there is, when it comes to the <lb/>skin, it will find a
                            free passage out. Nor does the wound in the skin in <pb n="533"
                            /><lb/>general heal sooner than the bottom; and, indeed, in many cases
                            not so <lb/>soon, because the skin is generally the part that has
                            suffered most. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>However, this is not an absolute rule, for the skin
                            sometimes heals first; <lb/>but I have found this to be the case as
                            often where openings had been <lb/>made, as in those where they had not;
                            and this will depend upon <w part="I">cir-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                                >cumstances</w> or peculiarities; such as the bottom being at a
                            considerable <lb/>distance, with extraneous bodies, and having no
                            disposition to heal, <w part="I">tend-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> to a
                            fistula; and I have observed in those cases, that the wound or
                            <lb/>opening made by the surgeon generally skinned to a small hole
                            before the <lb/>bottom of the wound was closed, which brings it to the
                            state it would <lb/>have been in, if it had not been dilated at all,
                            especially if there are <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">traneous</w>
                            bodies still remaining; for an extraneous body causes and keeps <lb/>up
                            the secretion of matter, or rather keeps up the disease at the bottom of
                            <lb/>the wound, by which means the healing disposition of its mouth is
                            in <lb/>some degree destroyed. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Let me state a case of this last description. Suppose
                            a wound made <lb/>with a ball; that wound (from circumftances) is not to
                            heal in six <lb/>months, because the extraneous bodies, etc. cannot be
                            extracted, or <choice>
                                <corr>worked</corr>
                                <sic>work</sic>
                            </choice><lb/> out sooner, or some other circumstance prevents the cure
                            in a shorter time; <lb/>open that wound as freely as may be thought
                            necessary, I will engage <lb/>that it will be in a month's time in the
                            same state with a similar wound <lb/>that has not been opened, so that
                            the whole advantage (if there is any) <lb/>must be before it comes to
                            this state; but it is very seldom that any thing <lb/>of consequence can
                            be done in that time, because the extraneous bodies <lb/>do not come out
                            at first so readily as they do at last, for the <w part="I"
                                >inflamma-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> and tumefaction, which
                            extends beyond that very opening, <w part="I">gene-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                                >rally</w> keeps them in; and if the wound is opened on their
                            account at first, <lb/>it ought to be continued to the very last. Upon
                            the same principle, <w part="I">open-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> on
                            account of extraneous bodies at first cannot be of so much service
                            <lb/>as opening some time after; for the suppuration, with its leading
                            causes, <lb/>viz. inflammation and sloughing, all along the passage of
                            the ball, makes <lb/>the passage itself much more determined and more
                            easily followed; for <lb/>the want of which, few extraneous bodies are
                            ever extracted at the <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ginning</w>,
                            excepting whit are superficial, small, and loose. </p>
                        <pb n="534"/>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>If the extraneous bodies are broken bones, it seldom
                            happens that they <lb/>are entirely detached, and therefore must loosen
                            before they can come <lb/>away; also the bones in many cases are
                            rendered dead, either by the blow <lb/>or by being exposed, which must
                            exfoliate, and this requires some time; <lb/>for in gun-shot wounds,
                            where bones are either bruised or broke, there is <lb/>most commonly an
                            exfoliation, because some part of the bone is deadened, <lb/>similar to
                            the slough in the soft parts. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>A reason given for opening gun-shot wounds is, that it
                            takes off the <lb/>tention arising from the inflammation, and gives the
                            part liberty; this <lb/>would be very good practice if tention or
                            inflammation were not a <w part="I">conse-</w><lb/><w part="F"><choice>
                                    <corr>quence</corr>
                                    <sic>sequence</sic>
                                </choice></w> of wounds; or it would be very good practice, if they
                            could <lb/>prove that the effects from dilating a part that was already
                            wounded were <lb/>very different, if not quite the reverse of those of
                            the first wound; but as <lb/>this must always be considered as an
                            extention of the first mischief, we <lb/>must suppose it to produce an
                            increase of the effects arising from that <lb/>mischief; therefore this
                            practice is contradiaory to common sense and <lb/>common observation. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>They are principally the compound wounds that require
                            surgical <w part="I">ope-</w><lb/><w part="F">rations</w>, and certain
                            precautions are necessary with regard to them, which <lb/>I shall here
                            lay down. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As the dilatation of gun-shot wounds is a violence, it
                            will be necessary <lb/>to consider well what relief can be given to the
                            parts or patient by such an <lb/>operation; and whether without it more
                            mischief would ensue; it should <lb/>also be considered what is the
                            proper time for dilating. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But it will be almost impossible to state what wound
                            ought, and what <lb/>ought not be opened; this must always be determined
                            by the surgeon, <lb/>after he is acquainted with the true state of the
                            case and the general <w part="I">prin-</w><lb/><w part="F">ciples</w>;
                            but from what has been already said, we may in some measure <lb/>judge
                            what those wounds are that should be opened, in order to produce
                            <lb/>either immediate relief, or to assist in the cure: we must have
                            some other <lb/>views than those objected to, we must see plainly
                            something to be done <lb/>for the relief of the patient by this opening,
                            which cannot be procured <lb/>without it, and if not procured, that the
                            part cannot heal, or that the <lb/>patient most probably must loose his
                            life. </p>
                        <pb n="535"/>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The practice to be recommended here will be exactly
                            similar to the <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">mon</w> practice of
                            surgery, without paying any attention to the cause as a <lb/>gun-shot
                            wound. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>One of the principal points of practice will be to
                            determine at what <w part="I">pe-</w><lb/><w part="F">riod</w> of time
                            the dilatation should be made. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>First, if the wound should be a slight one, and should
                            require opening, it <lb/>will be better to do it at the beginning,
                            before inflammation comes on; <lb/>for the inflammation, in consequence
                            of both, will be slight; but in slight <lb/>cases dilatation will never
                            be necessary, except to allow of the extraction of <lb/>some extraneous
                            body that is near. But if the wound is a considerable one, <lb/>and it
                            should appear upon consideration, that you cannot relieve <w part="I"
                                >imme-</w><lb/><w part="F">diately</w> any particular part, or the
                            constitution, then you can gain <w part="I">no-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                                >thing</w> by opening immediately, but will only increase the
                            inflammation, <lb/>and in some cases the inflammation arising from the
                            accident and opening <lb/>together, may be too much for the patient;
                            under this last circumstance, it <lb/>would be more advisable to wait
                            till the first inflammation ceases, by which <lb/>means the patient will
                            stand a much better chance of a cure, if not of his <lb/>life; therefore
                            it is much better to divide the inflammations; however, it <lb/>is
                            possible that the inflammation may arise from some circumstance in the
                            <lb/>wound, which could be removed by opening it; for instance, a bill,
                            or <lb/>broken bone pressing upon some part whose actions are either
                            essential to <lb/>the life of the part or the whole, as some large
                            artery, nerve, or vital part; <lb/>in such the case will determine for
                            itself. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>On the other hand, it may, in many cases be better to
                            remove the whole <lb/>by an operation, when in such parts as will admit
                            of it, which will be <lb/>taken notice of. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Secondly, if an artery is wounded, where the patient
                            is likely to become <lb/>either too weak, or to loose his life from the
                            loss of blood; then, certainly <lb/>the vessel is to be tied, and most
                            probably this cannot be done without <lb/>previously opening the
                            external parts, and often freely. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Or thirdly, in a wound of the head, where there is
                            reason to suspect a <lb/>fracture of the scull, it is necessary to open
                            the scalp, as in any other <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">mon</w>
                            injury done to the head where there was reason to suspect a fracture,
                                <pb n="536"/>
                            <lb/>and when opened, if a fracture is found, it is to be treated as any
                            other <lb/>fractured scull. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Fourthly, where there are fractured bones in any part
                            of the body that <lb/>can be immediately extracted with advantage, and
                            which would do much <lb/>mischief if left, this becomes a compound
                            fracture wherever it is, and it <lb/>makes no difference in the
                            treatment, whether the wound in the skin was <lb/>made by a ball, or the
                            bone itself, at least where the compound fracture is <lb/>allowed to
                            suppurate; for there is often a possibility of treating a <w part="I"
                                >com-</w><lb/><w part="F">pound</w> fracture as a simple one, which
                            gun-shot fractures, if I may be <lb/>allowed the expression, seldom will
                            allow of; but where the compound <lb/>fracture must suppurate, there
                            they are very similar. However, there <lb/>have been instances where a
                            fracture of the thigh-bone made by a ball <lb/>has healed in the same
                            way as a compound simple fracture. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Fifthly, where there is some extraneous body which can
                            with very <lb/>little trouble be extracted, and where the mischief by
                            delay will probably <lb/>be greater than that arising from the
                            dilatation. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Sixthly, where some internal part is misplaced, which
                            can be replaced <lb/>immediately in its former position, such as in
                            wounds in the belly, where <lb/>some of the viscera are protruded, and
                            it becomes necessary to perform <lb/>the operation of gastroraphia;
                            which is to be done in this case in the <lb/>same manner as if the
                            accident arose from any other cause; but the <lb/>treatment should be
                            different; for gun-shot cases cannot heal by the first <lb/>intention,
                            on account of the slough that is to ensue. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Or, seventhly, when some vital part is pressed, so
                            that its functions are <lb/>lost or much impaired, such as will often
                            happen from fractures of the <lb/>scull, fractures of the ribs, sternum,
                            etc. in short, when any thing can be <lb/>done to the part after the
                            opening is made for the present relief of the <lb/>patient, or the
                            future good arising from it. If none of these circumstances <lb/>has
                            happened, then I think we should be very quiet. Balls that enter any
                            <lb/>of the larger cavities, such as the abdomen or thorax, need not
                            have their <lb/>wounds dilated, except something else is necessary to be
                            done to the <lb/>contained parts, for it is impossible to follow the
                            ball; therefore they are <lb/>commonly not opened, and yet we find them
                            do very well. </p>
                        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Balls that enter any part where they cannot be
                            followed, such as into <pb n="537"/><lb/>the bones of the face need not
                            have the wound in the skin in the least <lb/>enlarged, as it can give no
                            assistance to the other part of the wound, which <lb/>is a bony canal.
                            The following cases are strongly in proof of this, being
                            <lb/>respectively instances of both modes of practice. </p>
                        <div>
                            <head rend="space align-center sc"><lb/>case first.</head>
                            <p rend="indent"><lb/>I was sent for to an officer who was wounded in
                                the cheek by a ball, <lb/>and who had all the symptoms of an injured
                                brain; upon examining the <lb/>parts, I found that the ball had
                                passed directiy backwards through the <lb/>cheek-bone; therefore,
                                from the symptoms and from the direction of the <lb/>wound, I
                                suspected that the ball had gone through the basis of the scull
                                <lb/>into the brain, or at lead had produced a depression of the
                                scull there: I <lb/>enlarged the external wound, and with my fingers
                                could feel the coronoid <lb/>process of the lower jaw; I found that
                                the ball had not entered the scull, <lb/>but had struck againd about
                                the temporal process of the sphenoid bone, <lb/>which it had broke,
                                and afterwards passed down on the inside of the lower <lb/>jaw. With
                                small forceps I extracted all I could of the loose pieces of
                                <lb/>bone; he soon recovered from his stupor, and also from his
                                wound. <lb/>The ball afterwards caused an inflammation at the angle
                                of the lower jaw, <lb/>and was extracted. The good which I proposed
                                by opening and <w part="I">search-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> for
                                extraneous bodies and loose pieces of bone was the relieving of the
                                <lb/>brain; but as the ball had not entered the scull, and as none
                                of the bones <lb/>had been driven into the brain, it is most
                                probable that I did no good by <lb/>my opening; but that I could not
                                foresee. </p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head rend="space align-center sc"><lb/>case second.</head>
                            <p rend="indent"><lb/>An officer received a wound by a ball in the
                                cheek, (which in this case <lb/>was on the opposite side) the wound
                                led backwards, as in the other; by <lb/>putting my finger into the
                                wound I felt the coronoid process of the lower <lb/>jaw, as in the
                                former; but he had no symptoms of an injured brain; I <lb/>therefore
                                advised not to open it, because the reason for opening in the <w
                                    part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceding</w> case did not exist
                                here; my advice was complied with, and the <lb/>wound did well, and
                                rather better than the former, by healing sooner. <lb/>The ball was
                                never found, so far as I know. </p>
                            <pb n="538"/>
                            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The present practice is not to regard the balls
                                themselves, and seldom <lb/>or ever to dilate upon their account,
                                nor even to search much after them <lb/>when the wound is dilated,
                                which shews that opening is not necessary, or <lb/>at least not made
                                upon account of extraneous bodies. </p>
                            <p rend="indent"><lb/>This practice has arisen from experience; for it
                                was found that balls, <lb/>when obliged to be left, seldom or ever
                                did any harm when at rest, and <lb/>when not in a vital part; for
                                balls have been known to lie in the body for <lb/>years, and and are
                                often never found at all, and yet the person has found no
                                <lb/>inconvenience. </p>
                            <p rend="indent"><lb/>This knowledge of the want of power in balls to
                                promote <w part="I">inflam-</w><lb/><w part="F">mation</w> when left
                                in the body, arose from the difficulty of finding them, <lb/>or
                                extracting them when found; and therefore in many cases they were
                                <lb/>obliged to leave them. </p>
                            <p rend="indent"><lb/>One reason for not readily finding the ball at
                                first is, because the parts <lb/>are only torn and divided, without
                                any loss of substance, (till the slough <lb/>comes off) by which
                                means the parts collapse and fall into their places <lb/>again,
                                which makes it difficult to pass any thing in the direction of the
                                <lb/>ball, or even to know its direction. The different courses they
                                take, by <lb/>being turned aside by some resisting body, add also to
                                the difficulty; as will <lb/>be explained. </p>
                            <p rend="indent"><lb/>But the course of a ball, if not perpendicular,
                                but passing obliquely and <lb/>not very deep a little way under the
                                skin, probably an inch or more, is <lb/>easy to be traced through
                                its whole course, for the skin over the whole <lb/>passage of the
                                ball generally is marked by a reddish line. I have seen <lb/>this
                                redness, even when the ball has gone pretty deep; it has none of the
                                <lb/>appearances of inflammation, nor of extravasation, for
                                extravasation is of <lb/>a darker colour, and what it is owing to, I
                                have not been able to discover<w part="I">dis-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                                    >cover</w>. I can conceive it to be something similar to a
                                blush; only the <lb/>small vessels allowing the red particles of the
                                blood to flow more easily. </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="27"/>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
