<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Hicks: A compleat treatise of urines</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>T. Hicks</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">A Compleat TREATISE OF URINES, Shewing the right Method of Urinal
              Prognostication, Far different From the Common Practice OF Quacks and
              Mountebanks.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T61971</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T61971"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for Henry Bonwicke, at the Red Lyon in St. Paul's Church-Yard, 1703.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1703</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="11"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="88"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3307213523</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K053821.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: method"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="11"/>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_12" n="1"/>
      <head rend="align-center space"><lb/>OF <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">URINE</hi>. </head>
      <div n="1" type="chapter">
        <head rend="align-center space"><lb/>CHAP. I. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Of the Principles and
            chief Accidents of</hi> Urine. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="dc(3)">U</hi>RINE</hi> new made, or after
            <w part="I">putrefacti-</w><lb/><w part="F">on</w> by long digeſtion, may be <w part="I"
            >Chymi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cally</w> reſolv'd into theſe Principles. <lb/>By
          Diſtillation, 1ſt, A ſmall Spirit, <lb/>like that of Wine diluted with Water, aſcends;
          <lb/>but in ſo little a quantity, that 'tis not eaſily <w part="I">ta-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſted</w>: This is ſucceeded by a watery Liquor <lb/>conſiderable in quantity,
          intermix'd with ſome <lb/>looſer particles of <hi rend="italic">Salt,</hi> and principally
            <hi rend="italic">Sulphur:</hi>
          <lb/>3dly, A very penetrative Water is exhal'd, <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >monly</w> call'd <hi rend="italic">Spiritus Urinæ,</hi> which has but <w part="I"
            >lit-</w><lb/><w part="F">tle</w> of the Wine-like Spirit, being generally only <lb/>a
          Phlegm very much ſharpen'd with <hi rend="italic">Salt;</hi>
          <w part="I">where-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w>, as in Vinegar diſtill'd, it aſcends laſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But becauſe the <hi rend="italic">Salt</hi> of <hi rend="italic"
            >Urine</hi> is volatile, and <lb/>of Vinegar fluid, therefore the diſtill'd Liquor
          <lb/>impregnated with the particles of this, is very <lb/>Acid; but what's incorporated
          with the ſaline <lb/>particles of the other, is very ſharp and <w part="I"
            >pungi-</w><lb/><w part="F">tive</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>'Tis hence evident, That the <hi rend="italic">Spiritus Urine</hi>
          <pb xml:id="page_13" n="2"/><lb/>(commonly ſo call'd) owes its ſharpneſs <w part="I"
            >eſpecial-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> to <hi rend="italic">Salt;</hi> becauſe tho' moſt
          ſubtile, it takes not <lb/>flame; but extinguiſheth it, if preſented to it. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>After Diſtillation, and the remaining moiſture <lb/>being wholly
          evaporated, another portion of <hi rend="italic">Salt</hi>
          <lb/>with a little Earth remains in the bottom of the <lb/>Matraſs, out of which by a
          ſtronger heat, a <hi rend="italic">Volatile <lb/>Salt</hi> may be ſublim'd, leaving the
          earthy Dregs behind. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This Anatomy of <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi> plainly ſhews, That
          <lb/>the Principles whereof it conſiſts, are moſt <hi rend="italic">Wa-<lb/>ter</hi> and
            <hi rend="italic">Salt,</hi> a little <hi rend="italic">Sulphur</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">Earth,</hi> and very <lb/>little <hi rend="italic">Spirit.</hi> We may
          diſcern the Saltneſs of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Urines</hi> by Taſte and Touch; in Taſte it
          comes <lb/>neareſt a Nitrous Salt, and proceeds from the <lb/>ſalt Particles of what we
          eat, which by <w part="I">Conco-</w><lb/><w part="F">ction</w> in the Veſſels, is for the
          moſt part <w part="I">elabo-</w><lb/><w part="F">rated</w> into a Volatile Salt, <hi
            rend="italic">i. e.</hi> a <hi rend="italic">Salt</hi> and <w part="I">cer-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tain</w> Spirit, which by their long and mutual <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">bination</w> are knit together in the cloſeſt tye: <lb/>hence Salt it ſelf
          otherwiſe fix'd, is volatiliz'd, <lb/>and (as 'twere by the Wing of another) becomes
          <lb/>not unfit for motion. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>From the different Diſpoſitions of our Bodies, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Urines</hi> contain more or leſs <hi rend="italic">Salt,</hi> and that <w part="I"
            >(ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">cording</w> to the Accidents) more volatile or fix'd, <lb/>and
          therefore are different in Colour and <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſiſtence</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>That there's <hi rend="italic">Sulphur</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
            >Urines,</hi> their ſpeedy <lb/>putrefaction and ſtink ſufficiently prove; and it
          <lb/>proceeds from the ſaline-ſulphureous Particles of <lb/>Nouriſhment. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Of this Sulphur there's leſs than in Blood, the <lb/>Horns of Animals,
          or Soot; (and therefore in the <pb xml:id="page_14" n="3"/><lb/>Diſtillation of <hi
            rend="italic">Urine,</hi> nothing almoſt Oily or <lb/>Fat aſcends) for while the Blood
          circulates, the <w part="I">ſpi-</w><lb/><w part="F">rituous</w> and ſulphureous Bodies
          which depart from <lb/>it, for the moſt part evaporate: In the interim, the <lb/>ſaline
          and watery reliques make up the <hi rend="italic">Urine.</hi> Yet <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Urines</hi> always have ſome <hi rend="italic">Sulphur,</hi> but the <w part="I"
            >quan-</w><lb/><w part="F">tities</w> and proportion are diverſly altered, <w part="I"
            >accord-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> to the different degrees of Concoction and
          <lb/>Crudity; hence proceed the changes of heat and <lb/>conſiſtence in <hi rend="italic"
            >Urines.</hi> That the wine-like <w part="I">Spi-</w><lb/><w part="F">rits</w> of <hi
            rend="italic">Urine</hi> are but few, 'tis evident from the <lb/>defect in the Liquor
          firſt Diſtill'd, as alſo from <lb/>the ſudden putrefaction of <hi rend="italic"
            >Urine;</hi> but the <w part="I">inte-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtine</w> motion of the
          Particles in <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi> conclude <lb/>ſome; <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
          the ſeparation of Thin from Thick, <lb/>and the ſpontaneous diviſion of ſome parts from
          <lb/>others, and the collection of that <hi rend="italic">Hypoſtaſis,</hi> or <lb/>thick
          ſubſtance which generally ſubſides, at the <lb/>bottom of <hi rend="italic">Urine;</hi>
          beſides, the ſaline Particles <w part="I">(in-</w><lb/><w part="F">aſmuch</w> as they
          become volatile) are cloſely <w part="I">wed-</w><lb/><w part="F">ded</w> to the
          ſpirituous, and therefore become more <lb/>brisk in motion and quick of energy. Yet <w
            part="I">accord-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> to the different plenty and prevalency of
          Spirits <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">Urines,</hi> there are divers modes of thoſe <hi
            rend="italic">Nubeculæ,</hi>
          <lb/>or Urine-clouds, and alſo of the Sediments, and <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
            >Urines</hi> themſelves, have a more quick or <lb/>ſlow putrefaction. The watry-part in
            <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi> far <lb/>exceeds the reſt in quantity, as being almoſt ſix
          <lb/>times more than the other: And by Diſtillation <lb/>'tis not ſo clearly ſeparated,
          but that ſome <w part="I">vola-</w><lb/><w part="F">tile</w> parts of <hi rend="italic"
            >Salt</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sulphur</hi> aſcend together <lb/>with it, which
          tincture it with an ingrateful ſent. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This has its original from a plentiful ingeſtion <lb/>of Liquids with
          Food, which yet of what kind <pb xml:id="page_15" n="4"/><lb/>ſoever they be, loſe their
          proper Qualities, and <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">quire</w> others, before their
          change into <hi rend="italic">Urine;</hi> for <lb/>nothing almoſt ſincere of that Liquor
          we drink, <lb/>beſides moiſture, barely remains in the Piſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The diſtillation and evaporation of <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi>
          <lb/>plainly demonſtrate, that there's ſome portion of <lb/>Earth, as well as ſlimy-muddy
          Dreggs in it; for <lb/>when all the liquid parts are exhal'd, the Earth, <lb/>as a <hi
            rend="italic">Caput mortuum,</hi> remains in the bottom in a <lb/>moderate quantity. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>For in the Nutritive Juice, beſides the active <lb/>Principles of <hi
            rend="italic">Salt, Sulphur</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Spirit,</hi> is requir'd
          <lb/>ſomething ſolid, whence Bodies have their bulk <lb/>and magnitude. The Recrements and
          earthy <lb/>Dreggs of this, are plentifully diſſolv'd in the <lb/>ſerous part, making the
          contents of a more thick <lb/>conſiſtence; but this is different according to the
          <lb/>variable State of Concoction and Crudity. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe are the Principles which make up the <lb/>Body of <hi
            rend="italic">Urine,</hi> into which, by Chymiſtry 'tis <lb/>eaſily reſolvable. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>From the combinations and various <w part="I">admix-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tures</w> of theſe, the other Accidents of <hi rend="italic">Urine, viz.</hi>
          <lb/>Quantity, Colour and Conſiſtence, which are <w part="I">ſen-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſibly</w> the moſt obſervable in it, and from hence <lb/>the eſpecial Objects of
          Urine-judgment, do ariſe; <lb/>for when almoſt nothing beſides is diſcernible in <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Urine,</hi> thoſe make the firſt <hi rend="italic">Phænomenons,</hi> in
          the <lb/>right ſolution of which, the whole <w part="I">Hypothe-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſis</w> of this Science conſiſts. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Wherefore in the next place, I ſhall Treat of <lb/>theſe; and firſt,
          concerning the <hi rend="italic">Urines</hi> of ſound <lb/>Men, what is their Quantity,
          Colour, Conſiſtence <lb/>and Contents; as alſo I ſhall endeavour to <w part="I">de-</w><pb
            xml:id="page_16" n="5"/><lb/><w part="F">clare</w> upon what mixture of Elements, what
            <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">coction</w> of the Bowels and Veſſels, every one of
          <lb/>theſe depend, </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the next place it ſhall be ſhew'd, how far <lb/>the <hi
            rend="italic">Urines</hi> of ſick Perſons, differ from the Rule <lb/>and Standard of
          thoſe who are ſound. And I <lb/>ſhall endeavour to aſſign the proper Cauſes of <lb/>their
          change to each of theſe Differences; and <lb/>what I have ſaid hitherto, ſhall finiſh the
          firſt <lb/>ſcope of my Diſcourſe, to wit, the Anatomy of <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Urine.</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="chapter">
        <head rend="align-center space"><lb/>CHAP. II. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Concerning the
            Quantity and Colour in Sound <lb/>Mens</hi> Urine. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HE quantity of <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> in
          Sound Men, <lb/>ought to be a little leſs, than the Liquids <lb/>dayly ingeſted; for what
          is potable and moiſt <lb/>that is daily taken, is the very matter of which <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Urines</hi> primarily conſiſt. But theſe (when <w part="I">hun-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ger</w> and thirſt urge) are more plentifully requir'd, <lb/>that they may
          ſufficiently dilute the Maſs of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Chyle,</hi> for its right
          Fermentation in the Bowels; <lb/>as alſo that it may ſerve for a Vehicle, both to
          <lb/>convey it into the Maſs of Blood, that the Blood it <lb/>ſelf may circulate in the
          Veſſels without <w part="I">Stagnati-</w><lb/><w part="F">on</w>, and to the Nervous
          Juice, that it may actuate <lb/>and moiſten the Organs of ſenſe and motion. <lb/>Thus the
          ſerous part having almoſt contributed <lb/>whatever <hi rend="italic">Spirit</hi> or <hi
            rend="italic">Sulphur</hi> it had, gives place <lb/>to a new Nutritive Humor, and it
          ſelf then, as <pb xml:id="page_17" n="6"/><lb/>unprofitable, is carry'd off from the
          Blood, by <lb/>the ſecluſive help of the <hi rend="italic">Kidneys.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Nouriſhing Liquor, which at laſt is chang'd <lb/>unto <hi
            rend="italic">Urine,</hi> is different in its own nature; <w part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">times</w> wateriſh, ſometimes inpregnated with <w part="I">Spi-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">rits</w>, ſometimes with <hi rend="italic">Salt</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
            >Sulphur;</hi> and <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">cording</w> to the different
          prevalency of this or that <lb/>Element in it, many Variations happen: but no <lb/>liquids
          wholly and unchanged paſs our Bodies, <lb/>but in diverſe parts, undergo their mutations
          and <lb/>looſe ſome portion of their quantities, before <lb/>they be ultimated into Piſs.
          For the Liquor to be <lb/>turn'd into <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi> being firſt receiv'd
          into the <w part="I">Sto-</w><lb/><w part="F">mach</w>, and ſtaying there till Concocted,
          is alſo <lb/>Impregnated with <hi rend="italic">Salt</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
            >Sulphur</hi> of its own <lb/>or other diſſolv'd particles, from ſome more <lb/>ſolid
          nouriſhment; after this, much of it, <w part="I">toge-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> with
          the Nutritive Juice is mixt with the <lb/>Blood, with which after long Circulation, and
          then <lb/>according to the various temper of the Blood, and <lb/>its accenſion in the
          Heart, it receives a further <w part="I">tin-</w><lb/><w part="F">cture</w> of <hi
            rend="italic">Salt</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sulphur;</hi> hence ſome portion of
          <lb/>it, is deriv'd into the Brain and Nerves, and there <lb/>being render'd weak and
          non-Nutritive 'tis <w part="I">final-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> again reduc'd into the
          maſs of Blood. After <lb/>that, the more generous part of the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>
          is ſpent <lb/>upon the Blood and the Nervous juice, a great <lb/>part alſo by Sweat and
          other Emunctories, the <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">mainder</w>, while the Blood
          continually paſſeth <lb/>the Reins, is there ſeparated from it, either by
          <lb/>Percolation, or the Force of ſome Fermentation, <lb/>by way of precipitation, paſſing
          the Ureters, <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">to</w> the Bladder, whence 'tis ejected. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>From the Original and view of this ſerous <pb xml:id="page_18" n="7"
          /><lb/>part now diſcrib'd, 'tis evident and that clearly, <lb/>that the <hi rend="italic"
            >Urine</hi> ought to anſwer the quantity of <lb/>Liquids ingeſted in a proportion
          ſomewhat leſs, <lb/>perhaps about a third, which plainly ſhews the <lb/>complextion and
          ſtrength of the Bowels, whoſe <lb/>Office is Concoction, and likewiſe of the Blood <lb/>it
          ſelf, as alſo in ſome ſort, the temper and <lb/>diſtribution of the <hi rend="italic"
            >Succus Nervoſus:</hi> Moreover <lb/>it carries with it the ſigns of the affects of the
          <lb/>urinary Paſſages. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The quantity of the Urine does not always hit <lb/>this Rule, but
          ſometimes exceeds, ſometimes <lb/>comes ſhort, and for a little time, may <lb/>conſiſt
          with a State, not much out of tune; <lb/>but the long continuance of ſuch different
          <lb/>Accidents argues a ſickly condition: Concerning <lb/>theſe, I ſhall ſpeak amongſt the
            <hi rend="italic">Phænomenons</hi>
          <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> in a craſy Body. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the next place, I conſider the Colour of a <lb/>ſound <hi
            rend="italic">Urine.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> that is made, after a perfect <w
            part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">coction</w> in the whole Body, is of a Citron-colour
          <lb/>like a <hi rend="italic">Lixivium</hi> indifferently boil'd, which <lb/>without doubt
          proceeds from the Salt and Sulphur <lb/>of the Nutritive Juice and Blood, diſſolv'd by <w
            part="I">e-</w><lb/><w part="F">bullition</w> in the <hi rend="italic">Serum.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This Colour ariſes not from <hi rend="italic">Salt</hi> only, (as ſome
          <lb/>contend) for any Liquor that is impregnated with <lb/>Salt (except it be evaporated
          to a certain <w part="I">thik-</w><lb/><w part="F">neſs)</w> doth not at all grow Yellow:
          And truly <lb/>the Salt of <hi rend="italic">Tartar</hi> diſſolv'd by liquation, yet <w
            part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">mains</w> clear. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>To what's objected concerning a <hi rend="italic">lixivium</hi> of <w
            part="I">A-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſhes</w>; I anſwer, the whole quantity of <hi
            rend="italic">Sulphur</hi> is not <pb xml:id="page_19" n="8"/><lb/>ſpent by burning, but
          the citron colour ariſes from <lb/>ſome Salt and other aduſt Sulphureous particles
          <lb/>cleaving to the aſhes, infus'd and incocted in the <lb/>Liquor. Nor has ſound <hi
            rend="italic">Urine</hi> this tincture from <lb/><hi rend="italic">Sulphur</hi> only;
          for Sulphur in a Wateriſh <hi rend="italic">Men-<lb/>ſtruum,</hi> cannot be diſſolv'd
          without the addition <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Salt;</hi> neither parts with any of its
          tincture <lb/>without ſuch addition: and therefore if you digeſt <lb/>Salt of <hi
            rend="italic">Tartar</hi> and common <hi rend="italic">Sulphur</hi> together in
          <lb/>Water, or boil Antimony in a Salt <hi rend="italic">Menſtrum,</hi>
          <lb/>both liquors, Urine like, grow Yellow from <lb/>thence; even ſo the Salt and
          Sulphureous <w part="I">parti-</w><lb/><w part="F">cles</w> of Nouriſhment, by digeſtion
          in the Stomach <lb/>and Inteſtines, and by circulation with the Blood <lb/>in the Arteries
          and Veins, being minutely <w part="I">divid-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> and througly
          incocted with the <hi rend="italic">Serum,</hi> make <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi>
          of a Citron-colour. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The diſſolution of Salt and Sulphur in manner <lb/>aforemention'd, by
          which <hi rend="italic">Urines</hi> become <w part="I">Citron-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >colour'd</w>, is firſt begun in the Bowels, afterwards <lb/>perfected in the other
          Veſſels, much depending <w part="I">up-</w><lb/><w part="F">on</w> the Concoction of the
          Stomach and Inteſtines. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>For here by the help of Heat, and <w part="I">Fermentati-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">on</w>, the Nouriſhments ingeſted are eſpecially <w part="I">fer-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">mented</w>. The tye of mixture being looſed, the <lb/>Sulphureous and Saline
          particles minutely <w part="I">brok-</w><lb/><w part="F">en</w>, are advanc'd into <hi
            rend="italic">Chyle,</hi> and then the <hi rend="italic">Se-<lb/>rum,</hi> which is the
          remainder from the <w part="I">concocti-</w><lb/><w part="F">on</w> and diſtribution of
          that Milkie Juice, becomes <lb/>citron colour'd; as when Salt of <hi rend="italic"
            >Tartar</hi> and <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">mon</w>
          <hi rend="italic">Sulphur</hi> are diſſolv'd together in any Liquor, <lb/>and ſome <hi
            rend="italic">Acid</hi> pour'd upon it, it preſently <lb/>turns milkie, and ſoon after,
          the contents being <w part="I">ſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">parated</w>
          <hi rend="italic">per Sabſidentiam,</hi> the remainder of the <lb/>Liquor grows yellow
          like a <hi rend="italic">Lixivium.</hi>
        </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_20" n="9"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But if the Nouriſhment, through ſome <w part="I">indiſ-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">poſition</w> of the Stomach, be not rightly digeſted <lb/>in the firſt
          Concoction, as it often happens in a <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pica, Dropſie,</hi> and other
          Diſtemperatures of the <lb/>Bowels, the <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> then becomes crude,
          clear <lb/>and almoſt inſipid like Fountain Water. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But by reaſon of the too exalted, or otherwiſe <lb/>deprav'd Ferments
          of the Bowels; as in the <hi rend="italic">Scur-<lb/>vy, Hypocondriack Melancholy,</hi> or
          in a <hi rend="italic">Feaveriſh</hi>
          <lb/>conſtitution, the particles of nouriſhment being <lb/>too much diſſolv'd in the firſt
          Region, the <hi rend="italic">Urines</hi>
          <lb/>become red and thick. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Serum,</hi> which in the firſt Concoction, as is
          <lb/>ſaid, had got a tincture like <hi rend="italic">Lie,</hi> being mixt with <lb/>the
          Blood, as long as it circulates with it, is yet <lb/>further concocted and gets a deeper
          colour; for <lb/>tho' the throughly concocted particles of Blood <lb/>are generally
          ſeparated into the <hi rend="italic">Veſicula fellis,</hi> yet <lb/>partly their incoction
          in the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> enhances 'its <lb/>tincture. Hence <hi rend="italic"
            >Urine</hi> firſt made after <w part="I">Conco-</w><lb/><w part="F">ction</w> is moſt
          pale; the next made ſomewhat red; <lb/>and after long faſting, yet more deep. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Where the Blood is more cold, as in a <hi rend="italic"
            >Ca-<lb/>chexia,</hi> the colour of <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> is below its juſt
          <lb/>ſtate; but where the Blood is accended and <lb/>as 'twere boil'd by a Feaveriſh Heat,
          'tis of a high Red. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>'Tis worthy obſervation, that ſome <hi rend="italic">Urines,</hi> and
          <lb/>thoſe ſound, made after large drinking, are not <lb/>colour'd, but pale and wateriſh. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Concerning which, the enquiry is, how the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Serum</hi> ſo ſuddenly paſſes the Stomach, (contrary <lb/>to common belief) and running
          through firſt the <lb/>Chylie-paſſages, then the Veins, Arteries, the <lb/>Ventricles of
          the Heart, the turnings and <w part="I">wind-</w>
          <pb xml:id="page_21" n="10"/><lb/><w part="F">ings</w> of the Reins and Ureters, in ſo
          ſhort a <lb/>ſpace is ſent out of the Body; and beſides, <lb/>otherwiſe than in moſt other
          caſes, borrows no <lb/>colour in its paſſages, but loſes its own. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>'Tis probable, beſides the long circuit of the <w part="I"
            >Nu-</w><lb/><w part="F">tritive</w> juice, wherein after ſome ſtay in the <w part="I"
            >Sto-</w><lb/><w part="F">mach</w>, it glides down the Inteſtines, and thence <lb/>is
          carry'd through the <hi rend="italic">lacteal</hi>-Veſſels into new <lb/>paſſages, and
          thence into the Veins; (a circuit <lb/>not to be run in a trice, therefore) 'tis probable,
          I <lb/>ſay, that there's another more proper paſſage of <lb/>the ſame Nutritive Juice, by
          which 'tis <w part="I">preſent-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> convey'd to the Maſs of Blood
          and perhaps to <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Succus Nervoſus.</hi> Wherefore after long <w
            part="I">hun-</w><lb/><w part="F">ger</w>, immediately upon Eating, but eſpecially <w
            part="I">up-</w><lb/><w part="F">on</w> Drinking, we find a ſudden refreſhment, which
          <lb/>cannot be ſuppos'd to proceed but from Spirits or <lb/>Vapours; becauſe immediately
          after ſuch drinking <lb/>follows piſſing, and that ſooner than the Maſs of <lb/>Chyle can
          be thought to be ſent out of the <w part="I">Sto-</w><lb/><w part="F">mach</w>. Therefore
          it ſeems not improbable, that <lb/>forthwith a thinner part of the Nouriſhing Liquor
          <lb/>(that's receiv'd into the Stomach) conſiſting of <lb/>ſome Spirit and eſpeially
          Water, is imbib'd by <lb/>its Membranes, like a Spunge, and thence <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtill'd</w> into the Mouths of the Veins, and is <w part="I"
            >preſent-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> mixt with the Blood in its return to the Heart.
          <lb/>For many are of this opinion, that the Chyle in <lb/>ſome meaſure is immediately
          deriv'd from the <lb/>Stomach and Inteſtines, through the branches of <lb/>the <hi
            rend="italic">Vena porta</hi> into the Maſs of Blood. And <lb/>as the lacteal paſſages
          carry it about in a long <lb/>Circuit, by which 'tis ſent into the deſcending <lb/>Branch
          of the <hi rend="italic">Vena cava,</hi> ſo by a nearer way, <pb xml:id="page_22" n="11"
          /><lb/>through theſe Veſſels, may it be carry'd into the <lb/>aſcending branch of the ſame
          Vein; for the<lb/> Blood, being in ſome meaſure impoveriſht with <lb/>its Circulation,
          returning both ways, ought to be <lb/>refreſhed with a new Juice, before it enters the
          H<lb/>eart, to enliven the Ferment there. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now ſince the far greater part of Blood is <w part="I">car-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ry'd</w> upward, it ſeems certainly Reaſonable, that<lb/>ſome part of the
          Nutritive Juice ſhould as 'twere <lb/>fewel for a new accenſion in the Heart) be <w
            part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">veyed</w> into the Blood already ſpent and grown
          <lb/>feeble. Many arguments make for this, which <lb/>to recite, were too large a
          digreſſion from my <lb/>preſent ſcope; wherefore I think 'tis in ſome <w part="I"
            >mea-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſure</w> after the manner aforeſaid, that we piſs ſuch <lb/>a
          pale wateriſh <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi> ſo ſoon after drinking. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>That Liquor, which from Nouriſhment is ſo <w part="I">ſpee-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">dily</w> convey'd into the Maſs of Blood, not paſſing <lb/>through ſo many
          windings, as the membranes <lb/>of the Bowells, (as if drawn by diſtillation, the
          <lb/>groſſer part rejected) in a manner, is only <w part="I">Wa-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ter</w> and Spirit, whereby it may refreſh the <w part="I">Vi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tal</w> Spirits and dilute the Blood. In which task, <lb/>the ſpirituous part being
          ſpent, the wateriſh <lb/>part, being weighty and troubleſome by reaſon of <lb/>its plenty,
          is continually ſent out by the Kidneys; <lb/>and ſince it comes from the Stomach, not as
          yet <lb/>embrewed with <hi rend="italic">Salt</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sulphur,</hi> nor
          is not ſo <lb/>long circulated with the blood, as to acquire <lb/>from thence, a lixivious
          tincture, tis piſs'd out <lb/>thin and clear. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="chapter">
        <pb xml:id="page_23" n="12"/>
        <head rend="align-center space"><lb/>CHAP. III. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Concerning the
            Conſiſtence and Contents of the</hi> Urine <hi rend="italic">of the ſound</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">H</hi>Itherto have we diſcours'd of the <w part="I"
            >Quan-</w><lb/><w part="F">tity</w> and Colour of <hi rend="italic">Urines</hi> in ſound
            <w part="I">Bo-</w><lb/><w part="F">dies</w>; but as to the Contents, there ought to be
          <lb/>nothing in ſound <hi rend="italic">Urines,</hi> beſides the <hi rend="italic"
            >Nubecula</hi>
          <lb/>or <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi>-ſloud; and what this is, and how it <lb/>is form'd,
          in the next place remains to be <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">plain'd</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>While the maſs of Blood is commixt with <hi rend="italic"
            >ſe-<lb/>rum</hi> and the Nutritive humour, 'tis continually <lb/>circulated in the
          Veſſels; from hence a certain <lb/>Nutritive Juice, by perpetual digeſtion is <w part="I"
            >elabo-</w><lb/><w part="F">rated</w>, which becomes a Nutriment at laſt, <w part="I"
            >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tinually</w> ſupplying the ſolid Parts. This at firſt <lb/>is
          concocted into a glutinous Humour, not much <lb/>unlike the white of an Egg; after that,
          into <w part="I">ſlen-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w> Filaments, which being interwoven in
          the pores <lb/>and little ſpaces of the ſolid Parts, ſupply them <lb/>with an augmentation
          always of new Subſtance. <lb/>And while the <hi rend="italic">Serum,</hi> that is mixt
          with the <lb/>Blood, waſhes over all the regions of the Body, <lb/>it ſwallows up in it
          ſelf a ſuperfluous part of this <lb/>laſt Nouriſhment, deſign'd for the <w part="I"
            >Augmentati-</w><lb/><w part="F">on</w> of the ſolid Parts, and carries out with it,
          <lb/>that which makes the <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi>-cloud. When this <lb/>appears
          (becauſe it ſignifies Concoction and <w part="I">Nu-</w><lb/><w part="F">trition</w> in
          ſome meaſure) 'tis accounted a <w part="I">lauda-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w> ſign; but if
          no ſuch <hi rend="italic">Phænomenon</hi> be viſible, <pb xml:id="page_24" n="13"
          /><lb/>'tis a ſign of Crudity, as in a <hi rend="italic">Cachexia</hi> and <w part="I"
            >Dyſcra-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſie</w> in <hi rend="italic">Feavers.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It conſiſts of ſlender Filaments (as aforeſaid) <lb/>and is diſperſt
          thro' the whole body of the <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi>
          <lb/>and then is gather'd together into one Cloud, <lb/>Thus; the Filaments are long and
          ſomewhat <lb/>ſmooth, having ſome aſperities, bramble-like, ſo <lb/>that being mov'd to
          and fro, they eaſily take hold <lb/>one of another, and are complicated in themſelves;
          <lb/>as if we ſhou'd caſt many Hairs into a Veſſel full <lb/>of Water, and there by often
          ſhaking, and toſſing <lb/>the Veſſel about, the Hairs, which at firſt Swim <lb/>on the
          top, here and there, ſhortly after <w part="I">Mutual-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> embrace,
          and knit in one knot. After the <lb/>ſame manner, ('tis probable) the Filaments which
          <lb/>make up the <hi rend="italic">Nubecula</hi> or Urine-cloud, being <lb/>toſt too and
          fro by the innate heat and Spirits of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi> do concur and
          knit together, till by <lb/>a mutual complex of each other they Concenter <lb/>into one
          little Cloud; and becauſe thoſe <w part="I">Fila-</w><lb/><w part="F">ments</w> are more
          compact and firm, than the reſt <lb/>of the Contents of the Urine, by reaſon of their
          <lb/>Gravity, they fall to the bottom. 'Tis highly <lb/>probable, that ſuch Filaments, in
          ſome Perſons <lb/>make up the Urine-cloud; becauſe the Blood in <lb/>a good State, and
          conſequently diſpoſed for <lb/>Nouriſhment, is interwoven with many Fibres <lb/>or white
          threads, which any body may diſcover <lb/>by phlebotomy, when the Blood is receiv'd <w
            part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">to</w> hot Water; therefore 'tis probable that ſome
          <lb/>divided ſlender parts of thoſe threads, being <lb/>ſnatch'd along with the <hi
            rend="italic">Serum,</hi> are the matter <lb/>of that Wool-like Subſidence in the Urine:
          <lb/>Wherefore in a <hi rend="italic">Cachexia,</hi> the blood being <w part="I"
            >water-</w>
          <pb xml:id="page_25" n="14"/><lb/><w part="F">iſh</w> through Crudities, and unfit for
          Nouriſhment, <lb/>is diſtitute of thoſe Elaborated ſmall fibrous <lb/>threads; as likewiſe
          in great Dyſcraſies, when by <lb/>an over ebullition of the Blood, the Nutritive
          <lb/>Juice is not rightly concocted into ſuch like <lb/>threads, the <hi rend="italic"
            >Hypoſtaſis</hi> or thick Sediment of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> is either
          utterly wanting, or very much <lb/>confus'd and troubled. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>A good and laudable Urine-cloud is white, <lb/>round and equal,
          falling towards the bottom; <lb/>and to this is requir'd, firſt, that the <w part="I"
            >Nouriſh-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w> be rightly elaborated, whereby the <w part="I"
            >Fila-</w><lb/><w part="F">ments</w> may become ſomewhat ſmooth, round <lb/>and firm,
          like ſlender threads. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="2"><lb/><hi rend="italic">2dly.</hi> That the <hi rend="italic"
            >Urine</hi> be ſufficiently <w part="I">Impreg-</w><lb/><w part="F">nated</w> with
          Spirits, which (as 'tis evident in the <lb/>Fermentation of new Wine) may drive and <w
            part="I">exa-</w><lb/><w part="F">gitate</w> the parts to and fro. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="3"><lb/><hi rend="italic">3dly.</hi> That the Liquor be not too thick,
          nor <lb/>its pores prepoſſeſs'd with other little bodies, <lb/>whereby it may happen, that
          the motion of the <lb/>Contents may be hindred; wherefore there ought <lb/>to be an ample
          ſpace left, to agitate and hurry <lb/>about ſuch Particles. If the Urine-cloud be red,
          <lb/>'tis a Sign that the laſt nouriſhment is render'd <lb/>aduſt, and over concocted by
          too much Heat; <lb/>therefore ſuch a Sediment for the moſt part, is <lb/>in the beginning
          of <hi rend="italic">Feavers,</hi> while the <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >coction</w> of the Bowells and Veſſels is not <w part="I">whol-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ly</w> preverted. If the <hi rend="italic">Hypoſtaſis</hi> be broken and <lb/>unequal,
          'tis a ſign, that the Nutriment <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſign'd</w> for the
          ſolid Parts, is not rightly and <w part="I">e-</w><lb/><w part="F">qually</w> concocted,
          that its particles are not <w part="I">alto-</w><lb/><w part="F">gether</w> Congenerous,
            <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> of the ſame kind, and <lb/>of <pb xml:id="page_26" n="15"
          /><lb/>the ſame Nature, and therefore the Filaments <lb/>hang not together Uniformly, but
          as 'twere <w part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> a Separate and confus'd manner of <w
            part="I">Implicati-</w><lb/><w part="F">on</w>; hence ſome that are more craſs, fall to
          the <lb/>bottom; others more rare, hang higher. When <lb/>the ſubſtance, of which the <hi
            rend="italic">Hypoſtaſis</hi> is made, <lb/>doth not altogether fall, but wholly hangs
            <w part="I">ei-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> in the top or middle Region, it happens
          <lb/>thus, either becauſe 'tis made of Filaments not <lb/>perfectly Elaborated, firm and
          compact, but more <lb/>thin and Spungy, or becauſe the Liquor is more <lb/>than ordinary
          Impregnated with <hi rend="italic">Salt</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sul-<lb/>phur,</hi> and
          therefore like a ſtrong <hi rend="italic">Lixivium,</hi> bears <lb/>up that weighty
          matter, which otherwiſe wou'd <lb/>fall to the bottom. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Some times the <hi rend="italic">Nubecula</hi> or Urine-cloud is
          <lb/>wholly wanting in ſound Bodies, after long <lb/>Hunger, immoderate Labours or
          extraordinary <lb/>Sweats, the matter being either wholly ſpent <lb/>in Nutriment; or
          evaporated by Sweat: And. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In <hi rend="italic">Feavers,</hi> becauſe the mixture of the Blood
          <lb/>is greatly Deprav'd: in the longing and deprav'd <lb/>Appetites of Child bearing
          Women; in a <hi rend="italic">Ca-<lb/>chexia</hi> or an ill habit of body, and other ſuch
          <lb/>like Affects, by reaſon of the Predominant <w part="I">Cru-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >dity</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Concerning the Conſiſtence of ſound <hi rend="italic">Urines,</hi>
          <lb/>not many things worthy obſervation occur. <lb/>'Tis commonly like Middle Ale well
          purify'd <lb/>by Fermentation, or a <hi rend="italic">Lixivium</hi> indifferently
          <lb/>boil'd: <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> The aqueous part of the <hi rend="italic"
            >Urine,</hi>
          <lb/>ought to contain within its pores and ſpaces <lb/>many particles of <hi rend="italic"
            >Salt</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sulphur</hi> broke and <lb/>diſolv'd very ſmall, as
          alſo a little Earth diſjoin'd <pb xml:id="page_27" n="16"/><lb/>into the leaſt atomes, and
          diſperſt throughout the <lb/>whole body of the <hi rend="italic">Urine.</hi> If the
          Conſiſtence be <lb/>thinner, than it ought to be, as 'tis ſeen in clear <lb/>and wateriſh.
            <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi> 'tis a Sign of Indigeſtion <lb/>and Crudity, that the
          aliment is not fully <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">cocted</w>: but if the <hi
            rend="italic">Urine</hi> be more craſs and thick <lb/>than it ought to be, 'tis a Sign
          the body of the <lb/>Liquor is clogg'd with Preternatural Contents; <lb/>but of theſe
          elſewhere, when we treat of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Urines</hi> of ſick Perſons.
          Hitherto have we <w part="I">ſpok-</w><lb/><w part="F">en</w> of <hi rend="italic"
            >Urine</hi> in a ſound Body, both as the <w part="I">Excre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w>
          and Sign of Concoction rightly perform'd <lb/>in the Bowells and other Veſſels. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>We muſt take the meaſures of its Quantity <lb/>from what we drink; its
          Citron-colour, from <hi rend="italic">Salt</hi>
          <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Sulphur</hi> diſſolv'd and incocted in the <hi rend="italic"
            >Serum.</hi>
          <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Hypoſtaſis</hi> or Contents depend upon the <w part="I"
            >fi-</w><lb/><w part="F">laments</w> elaborated in the maſs of Blood, for <lb/>the
          nouriſhment of the ſolid parts. Its <w part="I">Conſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtance</w> is
          from <hi rend="italic">Salt</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sulphur,</hi> together with
          <lb/>ſome particles of Earth, filling up the pores and <lb/>ſpaces of the ſerous Part. It
          remains next, that <lb/>we treat of the <hi rend="italic">Urines</hi> of ſick Perſons, in
          which <lb/>likewiſe the Quantity, Colour, Contents and <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſiſtence</w>, as alſo ſome other accidents, offer <w part="I">them-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſelves</w> to our conſideration. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="chapter">
        <head rend="align-center space"><lb/>CHAP. IIII. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Of the Quantity and
            Colour of the </hi>Urines <hi rend="italic">of Sick <lb/>Perſons</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">I</hi>N a deſeaſe or ſickly State of Body, the
          Quan-<lb/>tity of <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> frequently anſwers not the <w part="I"
            >ne-</w>
          <pb xml:id="page_28" n="17"/><lb/><w part="F">ceſſary</w> proportion of ingeſted Liquids;
          for ſometimes <lb/>there's a Defect, (ſometimes an Exceſs) in the <lb/>juſt Meaſure, when
          the <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> is far leſs than the <lb/>ingeſted Liquors. The reaſon of
          the Defect is, <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">cauſe</w> the ſerous part Stagnates
          ſomewhere in the <lb/>Body, or is diverted ſome other way, than that of <lb/>the <hi
            rend="italic">Urinary</hi> excretion; For 'tis either <hi rend="italic">1ſt,</hi> lodg'd
            <w part="I">a-</w><lb/><w part="F">about</w> the Bowels and their cavities, and
          ſometimes <lb/>alſo ſtays longer, than it ought, in the Stomach, <lb/>by which means 'tis
          ſomewhat diſtended, cauſing <lb/>troubleſome Spitting: but more frequently it is
          <lb/>lodg'd in the hollow of the Paunch, ſometimes in <lb/>the cavity of the Breaſt or
          Head, and there <w part="I">uſual-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> produces <hi rend="italic"
            >Dropſical</hi> Diſeaſes: or <hi rend="italic">2dly.</hi> the <hi rend="italic"
            >ſerum</hi>
          <lb/>Stagnates in the Veſſels, and thereby <w part="I">augmen-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ting</w> the Maſs of Blood and Nervous Liquor, <lb/>greatly perverts their motion: or
            <hi rend="italic">3dly.</hi> that <w part="I">wa-</w><lb/><w part="F">teriſh</w> Humour
          is thrown upon the habit of the <w part="I">Bo-</w><lb/><w part="F">dy</w> and ſo creates
          a ſwelling of the whole or ſome <lb/>parts: or <hi rend="italic">4thly</hi> and laſtly
          'tis obſtructed in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Urinary</hi> paſſages, by a Stone or ſome
          Viſcous <lb/>matter creating Pain and Convulſions in thoſe <lb/>parts, and a Superfluity
          of <hi rend="italic">ſerum</hi> in the whole <lb/>Body. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But when the <hi rend="italic">ſerum</hi> is diverted otherways, it
          <lb/>often diſpoſes the Sick to frequent and <w part="I">trouble-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſome</w> Sweats, or almoſt a continual Flux. The <lb/>Affects therefore which the
          deficient Quantity of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> indicates, are Swellings and
          aqueous <w part="I">colle-</w><lb/><w part="F">ctions</w> of ſome Bowels, alſo ſometimes
            <w part="I">Rheuma-</w><lb/><w part="F">tick</w> Pains, ſometimes an ill Diſpoſition of
          the <lb/><hi rend="italic">genus nervoſum,</hi> ſometimes an univerſal <hi rend="italic"
            >Dropſy</hi>
          <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">phlegmatick</hi> Tumours, and ſometimes the <pb
            xml:id="page_29" n="18"/><lb/>Stone in the Reins and Bladder; ſometimes alſo <lb/>the
          penury of <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> is the effect and ſign of <lb/>ſome other
          præternatural Evacuation, to wit, of <lb/>Sweat, a <hi rend="italic">Diarrhœa,</hi> or
          ſome other immoderate <w part="I">Ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">cretion</w>. To deſcribe every
          cauſe and mode of <lb/>the office of the <hi rend="italic">Serum,</hi> either as it is in
          the <w part="I">Bo-</w><lb/><w part="F">dy</w>, or as it is excern'd thence, were in a
          manner <lb/>to bring over hither, the whole matter of all the <lb/>Affects; for many and
          diverſe are the Occaſions <lb/>and Circumſtances, by reaſon of which the <hi rend="italic"
            >ſerum</hi>
          <lb/>is lodg'd in this or that Part, and by ſtaying in <lb/>the Body, leſſens the quantity
          of <hi rend="italic">Urine.</hi>
          <w part="I">Not-</w><lb/><w part="F">withſtanding</w>, the principal and moſt frequent
          <lb/>cauſe of this, is not ſo much the Vice of the <w part="I">Li-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ver</w>, Spleen or Reins, as that of the Blood it ſ<lb/>elf. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Free and plentiful Piſſing, as likewiſe its <w part="I"
            >tar-</w><lb/><w part="F">rying</w> in the Body and penurious Excretion, <w part="I"
            >de-</w><lb/><w part="F">pend</w> eſpecially upon the temper of the Blood <lb/>and its
          Accenſion or Fermentation in the Heart: <lb/>For, if the Blood be impregnated with active
          <lb/>principles, (<hi rend="italic">viz. Spirit, Sulphur</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
            >Salt</hi>) <lb/>rightly exalted, and have a lively Ferment in the <lb/>Veſſels, ſo that
          the well looſened complex of <lb/>the Liquor be rightly accended by the Ferment of
          <lb/>the Heart, it all in a manner Spiritualizeth, and <lb/>by its Heat and rapid Motion
          Tranſmits it ſelf, <lb/>without obſtruction, through every Part; <w part="I"
            >what-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſoever</w> is ſuperfluous and volatile evaporates, and
          <lb/>while the Blood that is rarify'd and as 'twere <lb/>boyling with Heat, paſſeth the
          Reins, that which <lb/>is the ſerous part, either by reaſon only, the <w part="I"
            >Kid-</w><lb/><w part="F">neys</w>, is as 'twere its Strainer, or having in them <pb
            xml:id="page_30" n="19"/><lb/>ſome Coagulated matter, is eaſily ſeparated and <lb/>as
          'twere Precipitated from the reſt of the Maſs <lb/>of Blood. Tis the ſame in a manner with
          the Maſs <lb/>of Blood, what we obſerve in Milke; <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
          <lb/>while it grows Hot and almoſt Boyling, it <w part="I">ea-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſily</w> Curds or Coagulates, and its <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> or Whey <lb/>ſoon
          ſeparates by pouring in a little Runnet or <lb/>any ſharp ſour Liquor; but if it be Cold,
          though <lb/>you pour in ſtronger Ferments and a conſiderable <lb/>quantity of any Acid,
          ſcarce any Precipitation <lb/>follows. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Therefore if the Blood become more Cold and <lb/>Watery from an ill
          conſtitution of Diet, ſo that <lb/>being leſs impregnated with active Particles, its
          <lb/>Ebullition is more ſlow, 'tis accended as 'twere <lb/>piece-meal in the Heart, and
          circulates very <w part="I">ſlow-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> and with difficulty in the
          Veſſels, and <w part="I">run-</w><lb/><w part="F">ning</w> the courſe of the pores and
          paſſages in the <lb/>Fleſh and Bowels, ſticks by degrees, leaving <lb/>ſomething of it
          ſelf behind it: whence <w part="I">Obſtructi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ons</w> and Tumours
          every where accrue. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>By this means alſo, the Blood being Feeble <lb/>and Viſcous, is
          conſequently leſs ſit for <w part="I">Precipi-</w><lb/><w part="F">tation</w> or
          Percolation, and doth not ſo readily <lb/>convey its ſerous Excrements into the Kidneys,
          <lb/>but leaves them every where diſpers'd in the <lb/>whole Body, by reaſon of the
          Settlement of <lb/>ſome Humour and Difficulty of Circulation. <lb/>Wherefore in this
          State, thoſe things which <lb/>much exagitate the Blood, as Exerciſe, ſwift and
          <lb/>frequent Motion; or as thoſe things which like <lb/>Rennet infus'd do precipitate, as
          Acids and Salt <lb/>Preparations do, provoke <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> more <w part="I"
            >plentiful-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w>. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_31" n="20"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Sometimes ſick Perſons Piſs very copiouſly, ſo <lb/>that in the ſpace
          of twenty four hours, they <w part="I">e-</w><lb/><w part="F">vacuate</w> twice or thrice
          as much <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> as they <lb/>have taken Liquids. The cauſe of which
          Effect is <lb/>divers, and the Signification much different. If <w part="I">af-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ter</w> the diminution' of its quantity, or ſuppreſſion of <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Urine;</hi> if in <hi rend="italic">dropſical</hi> affects, <hi
            rend="italic">Rheumatiſms</hi> or other <lb/>nervous Paſſions, or the <hi rend="italic"
            >criſis</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Feavers,</hi> plenty <lb/>of <hi rend="italic"
            >Urine</hi> naturally, or by the uſe of <hi rend="italic">Diureticks,</hi>
          <lb/>freely enſue, for the moſt part it preſages the <lb/>diſcontinuance of the Diſeaſe
          and Preternatural <lb/>Indiſpoſition; or at leaſt, its declenſion. But <lb/>if (as I have
          often obſerv'd, without theſe <w part="I">fore-</w><lb/><w part="F">going</w> and
          premention'd effects) the <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> far <lb/>exceeds the ingeſted
          Liquids, and thence enſue a <lb/>remarkable Debility, this indeed portends an ill
          <lb/>State, an inclination to an <hi rend="italic">Atrophy</hi> or <w part="I"
            >Conſumpti-</w><lb/><w part="F">on</w>. I have known ſome Women of a ſlender <lb/>thin
          habit of Body, who ſometimes being <w part="I">indiſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">pos'd</w> for
          many days together, were wont to make <lb/>in great plenty (above what Liquids they took)
          a <lb/>thin Watery <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi> without Contents or <hi rend="italic"
            >Urine</hi>-<lb/>cloud, at which time, they complain'd of their <lb/>ſtrength
          languiſhing, difficulty of Breathing, and <lb/>an inability to Motion. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I ſuppoſe in this caſe, the Blood and <hi rend="italic">Succus
            <lb/>Nervoſus,</hi> by an exalted and fluid <hi rend="italic">Salt,</hi> became <lb/>too
          acid, and conſequently unapt to be in the leaſt <lb/>diſſolv'd in their mixture, and were
          too much <lb/>diſpos'd to Seroſities; for 'tis obſervable, that <lb/>whatever Liquids,
          tho' thick and clammy, if <lb/>kept till ſour, they preſently become more thinn <lb/>and
          wateriſh. Further, 'tis manifeſt, that thoſe <pb xml:id="page_32" n="21"/><lb/>accidental
          overflowings of <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> ariſe from <lb/>ſuch a diſpoſition of the
          Blood and Humours; <lb/>for the <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> has a Vinegar Smack: and ſuch
          <lb/>affects (as aforemention'd) are ordinarily cur'd <lb/>by <hi rend="italic"
            >Chalybeat</hi> Medicines, and not always by <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >mon</w> Aſtringents and Thickners. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now as to the Colour of the <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> of the Sick,
          <lb/>that of ſound Perſons muſt be the rule and <w part="I">Stand-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ard</w>, by which all the reſt ought to be try'd and <lb/>judg'd. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Since then the Colour of theirs who are Sound, <lb/>ought to be
          Citron; the <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> of thoſe that are <lb/>ſick, will either be more
          Pale than Citron, and ſo <lb/>white like common Water; or more <w part="I"
            >deep-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> tinctur'd, and then generally 'twil be either of
          <lb/>a Flame or Saffron-colour, Red, Green or Black. <lb/>In ſhort, I'le endeavour to
          appropriate the <w part="I">Cau-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſes</w>, from which each of theſe
          Alterations proceed, <lb/>and what Affects or preparations of Diſeaſes they <lb/>uſually
          indicate. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> is clear like Water, when by <w
            part="I">rea-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſon</w> of the indigeſtive faculty of the Stomach,
          <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Saline</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sulphureous</hi> particles of
          our Meat <lb/>are not ſo well concocted and minutely broke, <lb/>that they can be
          volatiliz'd and diſſolv'd in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> to tincture it ſo deep,
          as that after all its <lb/>windings and paſſages it can beſpeak its <w part="I"
            >Origi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nals</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>For Liquids, that are to be chang'd into <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi>
          <lb/>by reaſon they are preſs'd and driven through <lb/>ſecret and very narrow Paſſages,
          as 'twere by <lb/>Diſtillation, thereby looſe their Colour and <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſiſtence</w> which they had when ingeſted, and <w part="I">im-</w><pb
            xml:id="page_33" n="22"/><lb/><w part="F">bibe</w> nothing from the Chyle (whoſe vehicle
          they <lb/>are) but what is volatile. Wherefore if by <w part="I">rea-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſon</w> of eminent Crudity, <hi rend="italic">Salt</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
            >Sulphur</hi> and <w part="I">o-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> Contents be not firſt
          volatiliz'd in the <w part="I">Bow-</w><lb/><w part="F">els</w>, nor after, diſſolv'd in
          the Veſſels ſo far, as <lb/>to run the ſame courſe with the <hi rend="italic">Serum,</hi>
          this at <lb/>laſt, in a manner diveſted of all, is ſent out like <lb/>clear Water. And
          that ſuch <hi rend="italic">Urines</hi> generally <lb/>want their active Principles, 'tis
          evident, becauſe <lb/>they are longeſt preſerv'd from Putrifaction. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Such <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> in Virgins generally ſignifies a <hi
            rend="italic">Chlo-<lb/>roſis</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">Green-Sickneſs,</hi> in moſt
          an ill habit <lb/>of Body or a <hi rend="italic">Dropſie;</hi> in ſome 'tis a ſign of
          great <lb/>crudity and the want of Concoction; and <w part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >times</w> alſo, in thoſe who are ſubject to the <hi rend="italic">Stone,</hi>
          <lb/>it Preindicates an approaching Fit, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> while the <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Serum</hi> in the Kidneys is coagulated by an acid <lb/>fermenting Juice,
          its Contents being condens'd <lb/>into a Tartarous matter, a thin wateriſh part <lb/>is
          only excern'd. They who for a time, (let the <lb/>Diſeaſe be what it will) Piſs thin and
          wateriſh, <lb/>have very often theſe Symptoms; difficult and <lb/>frequent Breathing after
          motion, Diſtenſion about <lb/>the region of the Stomach, and as 'twere a <w part="I"
            >Swel-</w><lb/><w part="F">ling</w> or Puffing up, after Meat. The reaſon of <lb/>which
          wholly depends upon want of <w part="I">Volatiliza-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> in the
          Blood: For, becauſe its Liquor is <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtitute</w> of
          active particles rightly exalted, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> (<hi rend="italic"
            >Spi-<lb/>rit, Sulphur</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Salt</hi>) therefore 'tis not <w
            part="I">ſuffici-</w><lb/><w part="F">ently</w> accended by the ferment of the Heart, <w
            part="I">where-</w><lb/><w part="F">by</w> the whole ſhould preſently ſally and as
          'twere <lb/>break forth into a Flame; but fermenting with <lb/>difficulty, and apt to
          Stagnate, or for the moſt part <pb xml:id="page_34" n="23"/><lb/>to ſettle in the Heart,
          'tis much oppreſs'd by it; <lb/>wherefore, if the Blood thus diſpos'd, be haſten'd
          <lb/>thro' the Ventricles of the Heart, by a motion more <lb/>quick than ordinary, becauſe
          it has not free <w part="I">Rare-</w><lb/><w part="F">faction</w>, it preſently ſallies
          out, in a manner all <lb/>at once; therefore there is need of a greater <w part="I"
            >En-</w><lb/><w part="F">deavour</w>, and more frequent Agitation of the <lb/>Lungs to
          pump it. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Wateriſh <hi rend="italic">Urines</hi> therefore, fore-tell ſuch like
          <lb/>Crudities in the Blood; becauſe if they have <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ceived</w>, in a manner, no tincture from the <hi rend="italic">Salt</hi>
          <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Sulphur,</hi> 'tis a ſign their particles are leſs
          <lb/>diſſolv'd, or leſs volatiliz'd, in the Maſs of Blood. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As to the Diſtention of the Stomach, of which <lb/>clear <hi
            rend="italic">Urines</hi> are both an effect and ſign; I ſay, <lb/>for want of a due
          Fermentation, the Chyle is not <lb/>all changed into a volatile white Subſtance, but
          <lb/>(like Bread not fermented) is alter'd and <w part="I">tranſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >muted</w> into a heavy ponderous Maſs, which is <lb/>ſlowly, and not without a Viſcous
          Phlegme <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">companying</w> it, ſent from the Stomach,
          whoſe <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">liques</w> being fixt to the foldings and
          membranes <lb/>of the Stomach, obſtruct all its Pores and <w part="I">Paſſa-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ges</w>, ſo that nothing can evaporate, and what is <lb/>more Thin and
          Spirituous, cannot be carry'd to the <lb/>Blood forthwith through ſecret Paſſages as it
          <lb/>ought. Hence plenty of Flatulencies or <w part="I">Windi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ness</w> is engender'd; which ſpeedily ſtretches the <lb/>Stomach, blowing it up beyond
          its proportion. <lb/>And ſince thoſe dreggs, by long reſidence in the <lb/>Stomach, abound
          with a fixt <hi rend="italic">Salt,</hi> they ſometimes <lb/>degenerate into an Acid,
          ſometimes into a <w part="I">Vitri-</w><lb/><w part="F">oline</w> or other baſe
          Heterogeneous matter, whence <pb xml:id="page_35" n="24"/><lb/>Violent pains in the
          Stomach, deprav'd Appetite, <lb/>violent heat with frequent Thirſt, ſometimes <w part="I"
            >vi-</w><lb/><w part="F">olent</w> Vomitings and other very grievous <w part="I"
            >Sym-</w><lb/><w part="F">ptoms</w> ariſe. Some of which, tho' they argue <lb/>heat, and
          that in a great degree, lurke and lye <lb/>hid within: yet thoſe who are thus affected for
          <lb/>want of Concoction, often make Crude and <w part="I">Wa-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >teriſh</w>
          <hi rend="italic">Urine.</hi> We have thus now largely <w part="I">treat-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ed</w> of clear <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi> becauſe the reaſons of the reſt,
          <lb/>may be had hence, which are Pale and thin <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >out</w> Colour or Conſiſtence, in thoſe who are Sound. <lb/>For the <hi rend="italic"
            >Phænomenons</hi> of Pale ſtraw-colour'd or <lb/>other Colours below Citron, ariſe, and
          may be <lb/>explicated after the ſame manner we have <w part="I">alrea-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">dy</w> ſaid of the Water-like, clear <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi> from
          <lb/>the greater or leſs Diſſolution and Concoction of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Salt</hi>
          and <hi rend="italic">Sulphur</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Serum.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Another kind of <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi> more Pale than Citron,
          <lb/>yet remains, not at all Thin but Thick, of a ſullied <lb/>whitiſh Colour, which is
          commonly obſerv'd, <lb/>Children make, when their Bowels are much <lb/>troubled with
          Wormes; the reaſon of which ſeems <lb/>to be, becauſe the matter of which Wormes <lb/>are
          ingender'd, is a viſcous Phlegm through <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">digeſtion</w>
          of Chyle and want of Volatilization, <lb/>heapt up in the Bowels, which doth not readily
          <lb/>tranſmit any tincture to the <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi> becauſe the <lb/>matter is
          fixt; after that, the ſame matter <w part="I">putrid-</w><lb/><w part="F">fying</w>, is
          exalted and volatiliz'd in a manner, and <lb/>then partly by Heat and Spirit is form'd
          into <lb/>Wormes, and that phlegmatick matter, being <lb/>unfit for nouriſhment, 'tis
          ſeparated from the <lb/>Blood with the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> and mixt with the <hi
            rend="italic">Urine;</hi>
          <pb xml:id="page_36" n="25"/><lb/>hence that white Colour and whitiſh Sediment. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Sometimes in <hi rend="italic">Feavers,</hi> eſpecially the <hi
            rend="italic">Urines</hi>
          <lb/>of Children grow white; the reaſon of which <lb/>is, becauſe the ſupply of Nutritive
          Juice coming <lb/>from the Chyle to the Maſs of Blood, is not <lb/>rightly aſſimilated,
          but degenerates into an <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">crementitious</w> Humour, a
          part of which being <lb/>incocted in the <hi rend="italic">Serum,</hi> gives it a more
          thick <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſiſtence</w> and milkie-colour, otherwiſe than
          in <hi rend="italic">Fea-<lb/>vers</hi> of the Adult, where when the Heat is more
          <lb/>ſtrong and vigorous, the mixture of ſuch Juice <lb/>tinctures the <hi rend="italic"
            >Serum</hi> with a deep Red. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Sometimes alſo <hi rend="italic">Urines</hi> appear white, from a
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Gonorrhæa, Flour albus, Ulcers</hi> of the Kidneys, <lb/>Ureters,
          or Urinary paſſage, by reaſon of the <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">mixture</w> of
          Matter or corrupted Seed. <w part="I">Howe-</w><lb/><w part="F">ver</w> it be, the white
          colour of the <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi> is <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >duc'd</w> by its Contents, which falling to the <w part="I">bot-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tom</w>, the Liquor for the moſt part becomes of a <lb/>yelowiſh-pale Colour, like as
          'tis ſeen in the <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">paration</w> of <hi rend="italic"
            >Lac Sulphuris,</hi> where the Milkie <w part="I">ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtance</w>
          falling to the bottom, the Liquor <w part="I">ſwim-</w><lb/><w part="F">ming</w> above, is
          commonly of a Citron colour. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Urines</hi> whoſe Colour is more Intenſe, than
          <lb/>Citron, owe not their appearances only to the <lb/>more than ordinary diſſolution of
            <hi rend="italic">Salt</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sul-<lb/>phur,</hi> but in ſome
          meaſure, to the more craſs <lb/>Contents in the Liquor. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The plentiful diſſolution of <hi rend="italic">Salt</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">Sulphur</hi> is <lb/>perform'd in the Veſſels containing the very Maſs
          <lb/>of Blood, and thence is the Tincture deriv'd <w part="I">up-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >on</w> the <hi rend="italic">Serum,</hi> and this for the moſt part, comes <lb/>to paſs
          two ways. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_37" n="26"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Firſt,</hi> either by reaſon of a Feaveriſh Heat, in
          <lb/>as much as the Blood boyling in the Veſſels, and <lb/>being more accended in the
          Heart, is much <w part="I">weak-</w><lb/><w part="F">ned</w> in its mixture; and therefore
          the particles of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Salt</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sulphur,</hi>
          which are ſeparated by <w part="I">Ebulli-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, plentifully
          impregnate the <hi rend="italic">Serum.</hi> Or <lb/><hi rend="italic">Secondly,</hi>
          without a <hi rend="italic">Feaver,</hi> when ſuch like <w part="I">Sul-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">phureous</w> and Saline little Bodies, which were <lb/>wont to be ſent out at
          other Emunctories, are <lb/>detain'd; therefore being heapt up, by little and <lb/>little
          in the Blood, they are commixt with the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Serum:</hi> Of which, there
          are two particular <lb/>Caſes or Modes for either the <w part="I">Excre-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ments</w> of Blood, which eſpecially partake <lb/>of an aduſt <hi rend="italic"
            >Sulphur,</hi> and ought to be ſent <lb/>forth by the <hi rend="italic">Veſicula
            Fellis,</hi> are retain'd and ſo <lb/>mixing with the <hi rend="italic">Serum,</hi>
          tincture it with a <w part="I">yel-</w><lb/><w part="F">low</w>: Or the <hi rend="italic"
            >Effluviums</hi> which are eſpecially of a <lb/>Saline nature, and were wont to
          evaporate by <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſenſible</w> Tranſpiration are retain'd,
          and by them is <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> tinctur'd, like a <hi rend="italic"
            >Lixivium</hi> or with a <lb/>Lye-like colour. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>All Perſons in the <hi rend="italic">Jaundiſe</hi> have <hi
            rend="italic">Urine</hi> of the <lb/>friſt ſort; but that of the latter, is familiar to
          <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Scurvy;</hi> for in a Scorhutick Habit, the <hi rend="italic"
            >Sa-<lb/>line</hi> Particles of Blood fall ſhort of <w part="I">Volatilizati-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">on</w>, and become fluid, wherefore by reaſon of <lb/>fixation, they evaporate
          leſs, and being <w part="I">plenti-</w><lb/><w part="F">fully</w> heap'd up in the Maſs of
          Blood, they <w part="I">great-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> prevent its Mixture, and
          eſpecially <w part="I">impre-</w><lb/><w part="F">gnate</w> the <hi rend="italic"
            >Serum</hi> with <hi rend="italic">Salt.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Contents which augment the colour of <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Urine</hi> are of two ſorts, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> Either the aduſt <pb
            xml:id="page_38" n="27"/><lb/>Recrements, which are the reliques of the Blood's
          <lb/>Inflammation: Or the Particles of the Nutritive <lb/>Juice, degenerated into an
          unknown Matter; of <lb/>which, in their proper place hereafter: Our <w part="I"
            >pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſent</w> Task is, a particular decyphering every <w part="I"
            >Co-</w><lb/><w part="F">lour</w>, that is above Citron. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the firſt place, The Flame-colour'd <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi>
          <lb/>appears like the yellowiſh red Vapours in the <w part="I">Di-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſtillation</w> of <hi rend="italic">Spiritus Nitri,</hi> and this is very often
          <lb/>found in <hi rend="italic">Intermitting Feavers,</hi> frequently in <hi rend="italic"
            >Ter-<lb/>tians.</hi> This Colour ariſes from a ſmall portion <lb/>of thin yellow <hi
            rend="italic">Choler,</hi> mix'd with the <hi rend="italic">Serum,</hi>
          <lb/>while 'tis in motion; for in this <hi rend="italic">Feaver</hi> there is <lb/>a ſharp
          and hot Diſtemperature of the Blood, <lb/>which burnes and in a manner torrifies all the
          <lb/>Humours, and therefore plentifully produceth <lb/><hi rend="italic">Choler.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And tho' this for the moſt part, is ſent out <lb/>by the <hi
            rend="italic">Ductus bilarius;</hi> notwithſtanding, ſince <lb/>it abounds in the
          Veſſels, part of it, or (what's <lb/>equivalent) the aduſt Particles of Blood and <w
            part="I">Hu-</w><lb/><w part="F">mours</w> being incocted in the <hi rend="italic"
            >Serum,</hi> tincture it <lb/>with a deep yellowiſh-red. This <hi rend="italic"
            >Urine</hi> is Thin <lb/>and Shining, becauſe in this Diſeaſe, almoſt a <lb/>continual
          Sweat forces out the Excrements of <lb/>the Nutritive Juice and the more groſs part of
          <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Serum,</hi> to the circumference of the Body. The
          <lb/>Saffron-colour'd <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi> which dies Linnen-<lb/>cloth with the
          ſame colour, is an undoubted <lb/>Sign of the <hi rend="italic">Jaundiſe;</hi> and 'tis
          thus tinctur'd <lb/>from yellow Choler, or <hi rend="italic">Salt</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">Sulphur</hi> aduſt <lb/>and plentifully mix'd with the <hi rend="italic"
            >Serum,</hi> For that <lb/>Yellow is neceſſarily produc'd by the more than <pb
            xml:id="page_39" n="28"/><lb/>ordinary continual motion and over-heat of the <lb/>Blood:
          And Nature has deſign'd the <hi rend="italic">Veſicula <lb/>Fellis</hi> and its paſſages
          which are radicated in the <lb/>Liver, for diſcharging the Choler from the Maſs <lb/>of
          Blood. But if this Office of the <hi rend="italic">Ductus <w part="I">Bila-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">rius</w>,</hi> in conveying the Gall, be any ways <w part="I">hin-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">der'd</w>, that Humour ſtagnating in the Blood and <lb/>plentifully heap't up
          there, dies the Skin, Blood, and <lb/>Urine eſpecially, with a yellow Tincture. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>A Safftron-colour'd, differs from a <w part="I">Flame-co-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">lour'd</w>
          <hi rend="italic">Urine;</hi> becauſe in the laſt, only ſome <lb/>part of the thinner, in
          the firſt, a more craſs <lb/>and plentiful part of the <hi rend="italic">Gall</hi> is
          incorporated <lb/>with the <hi rend="italic">Urine:</hi> Farther, in yellow <hi
            rend="italic">Choler, <lb/>Sulphur</hi> being long circulated with an <w part="I"
            >ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">companying</w>
          <hi rend="italic">Salt,</hi> is fully diſſolv'd by it, and <lb/>becomes like Paint,
          colouring any Subject with <lb/>a Saffron tincture, like as when common <hi rend="italic"
            >Sul-<lb/>phur</hi> and the Oil of <hi rend="italic">Tartar</hi> are diſſolv'd together. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But that Redneſs which is in <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi> without
          <lb/>the ſtagnation of <hi rend="italic">Choler,</hi> happens after the ſame <lb/>manner,
          as in a <hi rend="italic">Lixivium</hi> or Lie of Aſhes, <lb/>where the Particles of <hi
            rend="italic">Sulphur</hi> without any <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >diſpoſition</w>, from thoſe of <hi rend="italic">Salt,</hi> together with them <lb/>are
          imbib'd in the Liquor. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the next place, we will Treat of Red <hi rend="italic">Urines,</hi>
          <lb/>which are of a different Nature, depend upon <lb/>different Cauſes, and many times
          ſignify <w part="I">differ-</w><lb/><w part="F">rent</w> kinds of Affects; the chief of
          which, and <lb/>their proper ſignifications we'll briefly deſcribe. <lb/>Firſt of all, the
          Liquor grows red of it ſelf, <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">mains</w> in the ſame
          Condition, neither is the <w part="I">Co-</w><lb/><w part="F">lour</w> of any part of it
          alter'd by Subſidence. Or, <pb xml:id="page_40" n="29"/><lb/><hi rend="italic">2dly,</hi>
          the deep dye of <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> proceeds eſpecially <lb/>from what's
          contain'd in it; and after its <w part="I">reſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">dence</w> to the
          bottom, it becomes Yellowiſh, or <lb/>leſs Red than before. The Affects which ſuch
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Urines</hi> are wont to ſignify, are eſpecially, <hi
            rend="italic">Fea-<lb/>vers, Scurvy,</hi> and a confirm'd <hi rend="italic"
            >Conſumption.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Let's conſider the Reaſons of each. When <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
            >Urine</hi> which is made Red, continues ſo. 'Tis <lb/>either <hi rend="italic"
            >1ſt,</hi> of an indifferent Conſiſtence and <w part="I">Tran-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſparent</w>, and then it owes its Colour to <hi rend="italic">Salt</hi> and <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Sulphur</hi> more than ordinarily aduſt and <w part="I">there-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">fore</w> plentifully incocted in the <hi rend="italic">Serum.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Or, <hi rend="italic">2dly,</hi> Such an <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi>
          is Red, as alſo Dark <lb/>and Muddy and beſides what particles of <hi rend="italic"
            >Salt</hi>
          <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Sulphur</hi> it hath, ſome earthy Particles are <lb/>emboyl'd
          in it, which ſticking in the Pores and <lb/>Paſſages of the <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi>
          do not all precipitate; <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">cauſe</w> the Liquor of the
            <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> diveſted of its fit <lb/>Spirits, which wou'd ſeparate and
          precipitate all <lb/>parts of a different diſpoſition, as it uſually happens <lb/>in Wine
          that hath loſt its Head, or been ſower'd by <lb/>Thunder; in which Caſe, the Liquor is <w
            part="I">impre-</w><lb/><w part="F">gnated</w> with thick and muddy Dreggs, and for
          <lb/>want of due Spirits cannot finally clarify and <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >come</w> limpid as before. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Hence ſuch <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> is the worſt of ſigns in <hi
            rend="italic">Fea-<lb/>vers;</hi> becauſe it ſignifies ſuch a confuſion of <w part="I"
            >a-</w><lb/><w part="F">duſt</w> matter in the Blood, that ought to be <w part="I"
            >ſepa-</w><lb/><w part="F">rated</w>, and yet the Vital Spirits cannot bring it <w
            part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w> and overcome it. The <hi rend="italic"
            >Urine</hi> is ſometimes <lb/>made Red, becauſe of its Contents, which falling <lb/>to
          the bottom, the Liquor becomes of another <lb/>Colour </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_41" n="30"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now this, as 'tis ſaid above, is two-fold, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
          <lb/>ſometimes thin, which is the matter or <w part="I">remaind-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >er</w> of the aduſt Recrements from the deflagration of <lb/>the Blood: Sometimes
          thick, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> from the <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >generate</w> Particles of the Nutritive Juice; both <lb/>theſe being torrify'd by the
          Blood's Ebullition <lb/>and being ſeparated, are partly ſent out by Sweat, <lb/>and partly
          mix'd with the <hi rend="italic">Serum,</hi> whoſe <w part="I">Conſi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſtence</w> they thicken, and enhance its Colour, to <lb/>wit, as long as thoſe Contents
          are held up, <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> enclos'd in the Pores and
          Paſſages of the <w part="I">Li-</w><lb/><w part="F">quor</w>, the Colour appears more
          deep, and the <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſiſtence</w> more thick; but theſe
          being fallen to the <lb/>bottom, the Redneſs and Thickneſs of the Liquor <lb/>are abated:
          The reaſon of both which ſhall be <lb/>aſſign'd hereafter, when we aſſert the Cauſes of
          <lb/>Clearneſs, Darkneſs, and other Colours of <hi rend="italic">Urines.</hi>
          <lb/>Now let's enquire What's the Reaſon of the <w part="I">dif-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ference</w>, that Red <hi rend="italic">Urines</hi> are wont to be made
            <lb/><unclear>#####</unclear>
          <hi rend="italic">Feavers,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Scurvy, Conſumptions,</hi> and
          per-<lb/>haps in other Affects. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="1"><lb/><hi rend="italic">1ſt.</hi> In <hi rend="italic">Feavers</hi>
          the Liquor of <hi rend="italic">Urines</hi> is of a <lb/>deep Red, through the plentiful
          diſſolution of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Salt</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sulphur,</hi> whoſe
          Particles are plentifully <lb/><unclear>#</unclear>ncocted in the <hi rend="italic"
            >Serum;</hi> for while the Blood and <lb/>Humours are in Ebullition from a Febrifick
          Cauſe, <lb/>by reaſon of great Heat, highly inflam'd, the little <lb/>bodies of <hi
            rend="italic">Salt</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sulphur</hi> being torrefy'd and
            <lb/><unclear>#</unclear>duſt are more diſſolv'd, and by incoction in the <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Serum,</hi> tincture it more deeply; as a <hi rend="italic">Lixivium,</hi>
          <lb/>or Lie of Aſhes boyl'd on the Fire, becomes far <lb/>more red, than if we only
          proceed by way of In-<lb/>fuſion. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_42" n="31"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As likewiſe in <hi rend="italic">Feavers,</hi> the Contents of <hi
            rend="italic">Urine</hi>
          <lb/>often advance its Colour, that is, by <w part="I">rea-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſon</w> of
          the Intemperature and Deflagration of the <lb/>Blood; for then both the degenerate
          Particles of <lb/>the Nutritive Juice, as alſo another matter (like <lb/>Aſhes remaining
          from the Calcination of Blood) <lb/>are burnt, as 'twere into a red <hi rend="italic"
            >Calx,</hi> which <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> ſhut up in the Pores of
          the <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi> render <lb/>its Colour higher; and afterwards falling to
          the <lb/>bottom, becomes a red Sediment, like Painter's <lb/><hi rend="italic">Oaker</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="2"><lb/><hi rend="italic">2dly,</hi> In an inveterate <hi rend="italic"
            >Scurvy,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> is <lb/>often ſo high colour'd, that 'tis
          not exceeded in a <lb/>violent burning <hi rend="italic">Feaver,</hi> which (if evaporated
          or <lb/>diſtill'd) yields plenty of <hi rend="italic">Salt</hi> with ſlimy Dreggs,
          <lb/>wherefore it ſeems evident by this Experiment. <lb/>that this high Colour, owes its
          original to <hi rend="italic">Salt</hi>
          <lb/>Principles, as was hinted before; becauſe in <lb/><hi rend="italic">Scorbutick</hi>
          Caſes, thoſe <hi rend="italic">Salt</hi> Particles, which <lb/>ought to be Volatiliz'd,
          and ſent forth by a <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtant</w> Tranſpiration, are
          fix'd and reſtrain'd from <lb/>their uſual Motion, and therefore are more <w part="I"
            >plen-</w><lb/><w part="F">tifully</w> heap'd up in the affected Body. This <hi
            rend="italic">Salt</hi>
          <lb/>(afore-ſaid) remaining within, with <hi rend="italic">Sulphur</hi>
          <lb/>and Earth, is diverſly coagulated, and then <w part="I">plen-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tifully</w> reſolv'd. And from this different <w part="I">Coagu-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >lation</w> and Re-diſſolution, follows wonderful <lb/>Symptoms of this Diſeaſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Likewiſe from theſe <hi rend="italic">Saline</hi> Particles, <w
            part="I">plenti-</w><lb/><w part="F">fully</w> diſſolv'd with ſome <hi rend="italic"
            >Tartarous</hi> Dreggs, and <lb/>diluted with the <hi rend="italic">Serum, Urines</hi>
          become <w part="I">tin-</w><lb/><w part="F">ctur'd</w> with adeep and high Red. Beſides in
          this <lb/>Affect, when inveterate, the courſe and <w part="I">paſ-</w><pb xml:id="page_43"
            n="32"/><lb/><w part="F">ſages</w> of the Liver and <hi rend="italic">Veſicula
            Fellis</hi> being <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtructed</w> and deprav'd, they
          perform their <w part="I">Of-</w><lb/><w part="F">fice</w> worſe, in ſeparating the aduſt
          Particles of <lb/>Blood from the reſt of the Maſs, which being <lb/>plentifully loaded
          with it, and diſſolv'd in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Serum,</hi> do the more dye it with a
          Lie-like <w part="I">Tin-</w><lb/><w part="F">cure</w>. And if thoſe Particles of aduſt
            <hi rend="italic">Sulphur,</hi>
          <lb/>over-ballance thoſe of a fix'd and <hi rend="italic">Scorbutick</hi>
          <lb/>Salt, the <hi rend="italic">Jaundiſe</hi> is in complication with the <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Scurvy,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> then dyes Linnen with a
          <lb/>Saffron-colour. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But if they be exceeded by the <hi rend="italic">Saline</hi>
          Particles,<lb/>only a <hi rend="italic">Scorbutick</hi> Affect is produc'd, in which the
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> is highly red; but yet will not make yellow
          <lb/>Linnen. That 'tis thus, it is highly probable; for, <lb/>in Diſſecting many of thoſe,
          who had frequently <lb/>made red <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> and dy'd of the <hi
            rend="italic">Scurvy,</hi> it has <lb/>has been obſerv'd, that their Liver or the <hi
            rend="italic">Veſicu-<lb/>la Fellis</hi> was greatly in fault: In ſome, the <w part="I"
            >Li-</w><lb/><w part="F">ver</w> hath appear'd wholly bloodleſs and dry'd <lb/>like a
          Cow's Udder: In others, the <hi rend="italic">Veſicula Fel-<lb/>lis</hi> was quite empty:
          In ſome obſtructed with <lb/>little Stones: In others again, fill'd with <w part="I"
            >Mo-</w><lb/><w part="F">thery</w> Dreggs, nor at all bitter: but in all thoſe <lb/>that
          were ſo affected, a ſeparation of the Gall <lb/>was hinder'd. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="3"><lb/><hi rend="italic">3dly,</hi> by reaſon of <hi rend="italic"
            >Salt</hi> ſo diſſolv'd, the <hi rend="italic">Urines</hi>
          <lb/>are ſometimes Red in <hi rend="italic">Gouty</hi> Diſeaſes for beſides <lb/>the <hi
            rend="italic">Arthritik</hi> Fits (in which ſuch <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> is <w
            part="I">of-</w><lb/><w part="F">ten</w> made) I have obſerv'd, in ſome very <w part="I"
            >pain-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſal</w> Affects, imitating, in a manner, a <hi rend="italic"
            >Feaver,</hi>
          <lb/>with a deep red <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi> wandring Pains, <w part="I"
            >ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F">times</w> raging in this, ſometimes in that Part; ſo <pb
            xml:id="page_44" n="33"/><lb/>that the afficted Patient could ſcarce ſtand upon <lb/>his
          Feet, or move a Member; troubled alſo <lb/>with Watchings and frequent Sweats, and <w
            part="I">like-</w><lb/><w part="F">wiſe</w> with Thirſt, great dryneſs of the Jaws, the
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> very red, with a plentiful Sediment; yet <lb/>in the
          interim, 'twas not evident, that there was <lb/>any great Ebullition in the Blood, that
          the <w part="I">Pati-</w><lb/><w part="F">ent</w> was under any great Languor of Spirits,
          or <lb/><hi rend="italic">Head-ach,</hi> whereupon I ſuſpected this Affect was
          <lb/>eſpecially from the <hi rend="italic">genus Nervoſum,</hi> chiefly <w part="I"
            >de-</w><lb/><w part="F">pending</w> upon the Exorbitances of a Saline, rather <lb/>than
          a Sulphureous Principle. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="4"><lb/><hi rend="italic">4ly,</hi> Likewiſe the <hi rend="italic"
            >Urine</hi> is Red in a confirm'd <lb/><hi rend="italic">Conſumption,</hi> eſpecially if
          a <hi rend="italic">Hectick</hi> (as 'tis <w part="I">ge-</w><lb/><w part="F">nerally)</w>
          be join'd with it. The reaſon of which <lb/>is, if at any time an <hi rend="italic"
            >Ulcer</hi> has ſeiz'd the <hi rend="italic">Lungs;</hi>
          <lb/>from thence, a putrid Matter being mix'd with <lb/>the Blood in it's Circulation,
          cauſes almoſt a <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tinual</w> Ebullition; whereby the
            <hi rend="italic">Sulphureous</hi> and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Saline</hi> Particles,
          being more plentifully diſſolv'd <lb/>and incocted in the <hi rend="italic">Serum,</hi>
          render its Liquor <lb/>Red: Beſides, by reaſon the Blood is thus <w part="I"
            >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">taminated</w>, almoſt all the Nutritive Juice <w part="I"
            >dege-</w><lb/><w part="F">nerates</w> into Putrefaction, and with thoſe <w part="I"
            >Recre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ments</w> the <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> being
          impregnated, grows more <lb/>Red, and is plentifully ſtuſs d with its Contents. <lb/>An
          evidence of which is, that <hi rend="italic">Conſumptive</hi>
          <w part="I">Per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſons</w> are for the moſt part, hot after Meat, their
          <lb/>whole Body being put into a <hi rend="italic">Feaveriſh</hi>-heat, <lb/>which is
          ſucceeded by <hi rend="italic">Nocturnal</hi> Sweats. <w part="I">More-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">over</w>, there is in the <hi rend="italic">Urines</hi> a thick and <w part="I"
            >plenti-</w><lb/><w part="F">ful</w> Sediment, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Nutritive Juice being mix'd with the <pb xml:id="page_45" n="34"
          /><lb/>Blood, and not rightly aſſimilated, cauſeth an <lb/>Ebullition in it, and
          degenerating into ſome <lb/>ſtrange Matter, is partly driven through the Skin, <lb/>partly
          tranſmitted by <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi> and partly <w part="I">aug-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ments</w> its Colour and Conſiſtence. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Hitherto have we Treated of Red <hi rend="italic">Urines;</hi> and
          <lb/>every kind of 'em now hinted at, have many <w part="I">De-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >grees</w> of intenſion and remiſſion; for as the Cauſes <lb/>change in them, ſo in the
          Colour and <w part="I">Conſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtence</w> they are either weaker or
          ſtronger. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As for Green or Black <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi> I confeſs, I <w
            part="I">ne-</w><lb/><w part="F">ver</w> ſaw any that was either exactly green as
          <lb/>Leeks, or black as Ink. But I think, from a <lb/>very high yellow, with a dark or
          ſomewhat Inky <lb/>mixture, the appearances of greeniſh or blackiſh <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Urine</hi> may ariſe, which Authors uſually call <lb/>green or black <hi rend="italic"
            >Urine.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But thoſe <hi rend="italic">Urines</hi> which are thus colour'd, do
          <lb/>either conſtantly remain in the ſame ſtate for <lb/>ſome time, and are ſigns of the
            <hi rend="italic">Black-Jaundiſe,</hi>
          <lb/>or the Blood affected with ſome Virulency; or <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Urines</hi>
          are occaſionally diverſly chang'd, and <lb/>are ſometimes of that, and ſometimes preſently
          <lb/>of another Colour; ſo that I have known <hi rend="italic">Hypo-<lb/>condriacal</hi>
          Perſons wont firſt to make ſuch <hi rend="italic">Urines,</hi>
          <lb/>and then a little after, like thoſe of ſound <w part="I">Per-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſons</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As to the former, when the <hi rend="italic">Jaundiſe</hi>
          <lb/>grows very high, ſo that the aduſt portion of <hi rend="italic">Sulphur</hi>
          <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Salt</hi> have a longer continuance in the Maſs <lb/>of Blood,
          theſe ſame by long incoction, acquire <lb/>a Colour more deep than yellow; <hi
            rend="italic">viz.</hi> at firſt <lb/>Greeniſh, and then afterwards ſomewhat Black, <pb
            xml:id="page_46" n="35"/><lb/>with which the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> is in like
          manner <w part="I">tin-</w><lb/><w part="F">ctur'd</w>. For if yellow Gall be taken out of
          the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Veſicula Fellis,</hi> and put into a Bolt-head, and
          <lb/>expos'd to the gentle heat of a warm Bath, it <lb/>waxes ſhortly green, and
          afterwards by <w part="I">continu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ance</w> will appear almoſt as
          black as Ink. <w part="I">Where-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w> in the <hi rend="italic"
            >Black-Jaundiſe,</hi> which is only the <lb/>Yellow, by longer continuance advanc'd into
          a <lb/>greater degeneracy, there's nothing more uſual <lb/>than an Inky-<hi rend="italic"
            >Urine.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Further, ſuch <hi rend="italic">Urines</hi> ſometimes appear in a
          <lb/>malignant <hi rend="italic">Feaver</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Plague,</hi> as
          alſo <w part="I">fre-</w><lb/><w part="F">quently</w> after the drinking of Poyſon, and in
          <lb/>theſe Caſes, are commonly a deadly Sign; <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cauſe</w> they argue the Blood much corrupted, and <lb/>as 'twere mortify'd, the
          Spirits being vanquiſh'd, <lb/>and the bond of mixture loos'd, juſt as when a <lb/>part in
          our Bodies is Ulcerated, and afterwards <lb/>perverted into a <hi rend="italic"
            >Gangrene</hi> or Mortification, <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſently</w> the
          Piſs, which before was wateriſh, <lb/>white or yellow, becomes black. Wherefore <lb/>in
          the aforeſaid Affects, when the <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> grows <lb/>black, the <hi
            rend="italic">Serum</hi> and Blood being wholly <w part="I">vitia-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ted</w>, the outward Skin is likewiſe darkned with <lb/>ſuch a Colour. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Urines</hi> that are tinctur'd with a greeniſh, or
          <lb/>eſpecially a black Colour, at certain times <lb/>which often happens to <hi
            rend="italic">Hypocondriacks</hi>) very <lb/>likely proceed from the Dregs of the <hi
            rend="italic">Bilis atra,</hi>
          <lb/>or the black Choler entreaſur'd in the <hi rend="italic">Spleen;</hi>
          <lb/>and then through too plentiful congeſtion, <w part="I">over-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >flowing</w> at ſometimes, mix with the Maſs of <lb/>Blood: For ſuch Matter being often
          effunded <w part="I">in-</w><pb xml:id="page_47" n="36"/><lb/><w part="F">to</w> the
          Stomachs of ſome Men, produces greeniſh <lb/>or inky Vomits: As likewiſe in others, the
          ſame <lb/>Matter being ſuck'd up by the Blood, in its <w part="I">Cir-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >culation</w>, may tincture the <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> with ſuch like
          <lb/>Colours. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Hitherto have we ſpoken of the Colours of <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Urines:</hi> Thoſe that are Pale, proceed from too <lb/>much Crudity; almoſt all thoſe
          that are <w part="I">High-</w><lb/><w part="F">colour'd</w>, ariſe either from <hi
            rend="italic">Salt</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Sulphur</hi> too <lb/>plentifully
          diſſolv'd, and ſometimes, from the <lb/>aduſt Recrements throughly incocted in the <hi
            rend="italic">Se-<lb/>rum;</hi> or from the more craſs Contents of the <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Urine,</hi> whether they be the very <hi rend="italic">Calx</hi> and <w
            part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">mainder</w> of the Aliment degenerated in <w part="I"
            >Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">coction</w>, or the Liquations and mouldrings of the
          <lb/>Conſumptive Body, or ſome ill-affected Part <lb/>thereof; which expreſſions will be
          better <w part="I">under-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtood</w>, if we explain the manner, how
          ſuch-like <lb/>Diſſolutions and Contents may diverſly change <lb/>the Colour of <hi
            rend="italic">Urine.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Cauſes of different Appearances and <lb/>changeable Colours, as
          alſo of Darkneſs and <lb/>Tranſparency in <hi rend="italic">Urines</hi> (as in other
          Liquors) <lb/>depend wholly on the different immiſſion and <lb/>emmiſſion of the Rays of
          Light. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>For, if the body of the Liquor be thin, with <lb/>open Pores and
          Paſſages, that the Rays of Light <lb/>may be eaſily tranſmitted, 'tis then <w part="I"
            >Tranſpa-</w><lb/><w part="F">rent</w> and Clear, like Fountain-water: But if the
          <lb/>Pores of the Liquor be ſtuff'd with Contents, or <lb/>little Bodies ſwimming in it,
          ſo that the <w part="I">illu-</w><lb/><w part="F">minating</w> Rays be refracted and
          broken in the <lb/>tranſmiſſion, at laſt when they appear <w part="I">accord-</w><pb
            xml:id="page_48" n="37"/><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> to the different Modes of Refraction
          and <w part="I">Re-</w><lb/><w part="F">flection</w>, in the (as yet) diaphanous Liquor,
          the <lb/>Colour will appear either Citron, Saffron, or Red. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But if the ſpaces of the Pores, be yet more <w part="I"
            >poſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſeſs'd</w>, ſo that the Light be not at all <w part="I"
            >tranſmit-</w><lb/><w part="F">ted</w>, from thence Darkneſs will proceed: But <lb/>then
          if the Rays once receiv'd, be but little or <lb/>not at all reflected, the Liquor will
          appear of a <lb/>dusky or blackiſh Colour. But if they be <w part="I">Re-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">flected</w> according to the different modes of <w part="I">Re-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">flection</w>, the appearance will be White, <w part="I">Aſhe-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">colour'd</w>, or of another kind; upon this <w part="I">Suppo-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſition</w>, that as the Liquor of the <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> is <w
            part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F">times</w> in a manner, almoſt devoid of <hi
            rend="italic">Salt, <w part="I">Sul-</w><lb/><w part="F">phur</w>,</hi> and other
          Diſſolvables, it eaſily tranſmits <lb/>the Light. Sometimes being moderately, or much
          <lb/>ſtuft'd with ſuch-like Contents, it either diſtorts <lb/>the incident Rays in their
          paſſage, or wholly <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F">bibes</w> them, or laſtly reflects
          them: So that from <lb/>hence, 'tis eaſy to unfold all the <hi rend="italic"
            >Phænomenons</hi>
          <lb/>of Colours and Conſiſtence in <hi rend="italic">Urines.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It happens frequently, that the Colour of the <lb/>ſame <hi
            rend="italic">Urine</hi> is much chang'd; for that which is <lb/>made Red, being expos'd
          to the Air, becomes <lb/>White or of a Darkiſh-colour, and then a <w part="I"
            >lit-</w><lb/><w part="F">tle</w> time after of a Citron colour; the reaſon of
          <lb/>which appearance ſeems to be this: </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi> when made is red, becauſe the
          <lb/>Pores of the Liquor are much poſſeſs'd with the <lb/>Contents: Yet as long as thoſe
          Pores are kept <lb/>open by Heat, they tranſmit the Rays of Light<lb/>in ſuch manner (tho'
          diverſly diſtorted) that they <lb/>by way of Reflection, rebound again. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_49" n="38"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But this <hi rend="italic">Urine,</hi> is no ſooner expos'd to the
          <lb/>cold Air, but the Pores being ſhut up, the <w part="I">poſi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tion</w> of Parts are chang'd in the Contents, and <lb/>therefore the tranſmiſſion of
          the Rays of Light is <lb/>hinder'd, wherefore the Liquor becomes preſently <lb/>dark, and
          as thoſe Rays are reflected this or that <lb/>way, the Colour becomes white, dusky, or
          ſome <lb/>other Colour. But at laſt the Contents, by their <lb/>weight, falling to the
          bottom, the Pores being <lb/>freed, eaſily tranſmit the Rays of Light, and do <lb/>leſs
          diſtort them; wherefore the Colour appears <lb/>not high, but Citron. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>From what has been ſaid concerning the <w part="I">Co-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">lour</w> of <hi rend="italic">Urines,</hi> it may appear what's the Cauſes
          <lb/>of the different Conſiſtence of <hi rend="italic">Urines:</hi> For as <lb/>the
          Particles of <hi rend="italic">Salt, Sulphur,</hi> or aduſt Matter, <lb/>or the Nutritive
          Juice depriv'd of a right <w part="I">Aſſimi-</w><lb/><w part="F">lation</w>, are more or
          leſs incocted in the <hi rend="italic">Se-<lb/>rum,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Urines</hi>
          become more or leſs Thick or <lb/>Thin in their Conſiſtence. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the next place it remains, we ſpeak of the <lb/>Preternatural
          Contents in <hi rend="italic">Urine.</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="50"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
