<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Marten: A Treatise of All the Degrees and Symptoms of the Venereal
          Disease</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>John Marten</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">A TREATISE Of All the Degrees and Symptoms of the Venereal Disease,
              In both SEXES; Explicating Naturally and Mechanically, its Causes, Kinds, various Ways
              of Infecting; The Nature of Hereditary Infection; Certainty of knowing whether
              Infected or not; Infallible way to prevent Infection; Easiness of Cure when Infected;
              Reasons why so many miss of Cure; How to know when, and when not, in Skilful Hands for
              Cure, and the Use and Abuse of Mercury in the Cure. Necessary to be Read and Observ'd
              by All Persons that either Now have, Ever had, (many other Diseases being occasion'd
              by the Venereal Taint and Mercury) or at any time May have, the Misfortune of that
              Distemper, in order to prevent their being Ruin'd by Ignorant Pretenders, Quacks,
              Mountebanks, Impostors, &amp;c.whose Notorious Practices are clearly evinc'd. To which
              is added, An Account of the Cause and Cure of Old Venereal and other Gleets,
              Introductory to which, the Genital Parts in both SEXES, their Use and Abuse, are
              briefly describ'd, and why Gleets (as sometimes they do) hinder procreation, causing
              Impotency, &amp;c.in Men, and Sterility, &amp;c.in Women. With some remarkable Cases
              of that kind incerted. The whole Interspers'd With peculiar Prescriptions, many
              pertinent Observations, Histories, and Letters of very remarkable Cures. The like, for
              general Advantage, never Publish'd by any Author, Ancient or Modern, since the Disease
              came first to be known in the World. </title>
            <edition n="5"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T204466</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T204466"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for, and sold by S. Crouch in Cornhil, N. Crouch in the
                  poultry, J. Knapton in St. Paul's Church-yard, W. Hawes in Ludgate-street, P.
                  Varenne at Seneca's Head in the Strand, C. King, Westminster-hall, and J. Isted
                  against St. Dunstan's Church Fleetstreet, Booksellers.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1707</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="41"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="503"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="47"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">Trinity College Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CB128014557</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: disease"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="41"/>
    <body>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>A <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">TREATISE </hi>
        <lb/>OF THE <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">Venereal Diſeaſe. </hi>
      </head>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <div type="chapter">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>CHAP. I. </head>
        <head rend="italic hanging">
          <lb/>The Nature, Cauſes, and Signs of the Ve- <lb/>nereal Diſeaſe, the various Ways of In-
          <lb/>fecting, with the difference and degrees <lb/>thereof; the certainty of knowing
          whether <lb/>Infected or not, and how to prevent, or <lb/>hinder Infection. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">I</hi> Shall not trouble my ſelf, or the Reader, <lb/>in this ſmall
          Tract, with the many dif- <lb/>ferent and indeterminate Notions of the <lb/>Natural Cauſe
          of this Diſtemper, as to its <lb/><hi rend="italic">Original Production</hi>, whether it
          be (as ſome <lb/>have undertaken to make out) meerly the <lb/>effects of Divine Wrath and
          Judgment, in- <lb/>flicted on Mankind as a Scourge for their <pb n="2"/>
          <lb/>wanton and luſtful Debaucheries; or whether <lb/>(as others ſtrenuouſly aſſert) it
          was contract- <lb/>ed by the carnal Conjunction of ſome <hi rend="italic">Scabby</hi>,
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Leprous</hi>, or other ſort of unclean Perſons; or <lb/>whether
          deriv'd to us from the <hi rend="italic">Spaniards</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Neapolitans</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Italians</hi> or <hi rend="italic">French</hi>; I
          ſay, I ſhall <lb/>not ſpend time about thoſe Definitions which <lb/>are only ſpeculative,
          and tend more to ſa- <lb/>tisfie the Curious, than to edifie the Neceſ- <lb/>ſitous; and
          it being what I ſhall amply and par- <lb/>ticularly diſcourſe on in my general Treatiſe,
          <lb/>intended ſhortly to be Publiſh'd, I purpoſely, <lb/>for brevity ſake, paſs them by. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Neither is it pertinent to my preſent De- <lb/>ſign, to relate here, <hi
            rend="italic">Where</hi>, or from <hi rend="italic">What</hi>
          <lb/>this Diſtemper owes its Original, or <hi rend="italic">How</hi>, or <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">When</hi> it came to be ſpread over the greateſt <lb/>part of the World,
          it being ſufficient, and <lb/>too notorious, that we know it to be a com- <lb/>mon
          Diſeaſe, which, tho' it may ariſe by ma- <lb/>ny Ways and Accidents, yet now a-days is
          <lb/>gotten for the moſt part, by the impure and <lb/>carnal Embrace of an infected
          Perſon, and <lb/>the Child of an unclean Parent may bring <lb/>the Diſtemper into the
          World with it, and <lb/>that Child infect the Nurſe that Suckles it, <lb/>and the Nurſe
          her Husband, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Or the Nurſe infected, may infect the Child <lb/>that is ſound, Children whoſe Fleſh
          is more <lb/>lax, and Pores more open than grown Perſons <lb/>are, being much ſooner
          liable and apt to receive <lb/>the Infection, and that not only by <hi rend="italic"
            >Sucking</hi> a <lb/>polluted Nurſe, but alſo by the <hi rend="italic">Slaver</hi>, in
          <lb/>being kiſs'd by thoſe foul <hi rend="italic">Sluts</hi> that have Ve- <pb n="3"/>
          <lb/>nereal Ulcers in their Throats, or Mouths, <lb/>as too many miſerable Inſtances have
          made <lb/>manifeſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I ſay, it is ſufficient that we know it to be a <lb/>Diſtemper daily gotten, and
          indeed ſo very <lb/>frequently now, that as certain Author <lb/>takes notice, it is
          undeniable that the <hi rend="italic">Pox</hi> in <lb/>this looſe and diſſolute Age, is
          more propa- <lb/>gated in one Day, than an hundred Years ago <lb/>it was in a Month, and
          the number of Vene- <lb/>real Patients conſequently multiplied. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And indeed ſo univerſal is the Diſtemper <lb/>now become, that it is almoſt as much a
          won- <lb/>der to hear of many Perſons that never had it, <lb/>or that never had taken the
          way to get it, as <lb/>it was formerly a wonder to hear of any in- <lb/>fected; and ſo
          obnoxious were the People in <lb/>thoſe Days that had the Pox, that I have <lb/>ſomewhere
          read, they were oblig'd, when it <lb/>came to be known, under a ſevere Penalty, to
          <lb/>withdraw themſelves from the City, or Town, <lb/>where they dwelt, to a certain Place
          appoint- <lb/>ed (as are our Hoſpitals) for their Reception <lb/>and Cure, and there to be
          kept cloſe confin'd, <lb/>left their Society and Converſation ſhould <lb/>infect others,
          the Diſtemper then being thought <lb/>by moſt as equally infectious as the <hi
            rend="italic">Plague</hi>, <lb/>and the People were altogether as equally a- <lb/>fraid
          of it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And <hi rend="italic">Sennertus</hi> tells us, that <hi rend="italic">Jul.
            Palmarius</hi>
          <lb/>writes in his Book <hi rend="italic">de Lue Vener. cap. 5.</hi> That <lb/>the Pox at
          its firſt riſe, was reported to be ſo <lb/>filthy, that that which reigns now is ſcarce
          <lb/>thought to be of the ſame kind; for then <pb n="4"/>
          <lb/>thoſe infected, had innumerable Ulcers, rough <lb/>and bunching out in the figure and
          bulk of <lb/>Acorns, from which flowed a filthy Humour, <lb/>of ſuch a ſtinking
          exhalation, or ſmell, that the <lb/>Noſes of thoſe that ſmelt it, were believ'd to <lb/>be
          preſently infected. The colour of thoſe filthy <lb/>Puſtles was between black and green,
          the <lb/>ſight of which was much tormented and terrified <lb/>the Patient, as did their
          grievous Pain. There- <lb/>fore all People did ſhun the ſight of them, <lb/>and more
          avoided touching them, than any <lb/>thing belonging to any Diſeaſe beſides. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And that in <hi rend="italic">China</hi>, as I have been told by <lb/>a Gentleman now
          my Patient, who for a <lb/>conſiderable time liv'd there, the Venereal <lb/>Infection is
          call'd the <hi rend="italic">Lazarus</hi>, and affects <lb/>thoſe that have it with a
          contraction of the <lb/>Fingers, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> and breakings out in the
          Body, <lb/>particularly with thick Scabs all down the <lb/>Thighs and Legs, like the
          Diſtemper call'd <lb/>the Farcy in Horſes, and that they are very <lb/>unſightly, painful
          and loathſome, and are <lb/>ſeldom, if ever, Cured, if the Infection be <lb/>great, or
          arives to its height of inveteracy. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This infectious Evil, ſays an Author, raged <lb/>by Wholeſale in the <hi
            rend="italic">American</hi> Iſlands, and <lb/>(tho' I thought not to mention theſe
          matters <lb/>here, as before hinted) was brought from <lb/>thence into <hi rend="italic"
            >Europe</hi> by the <hi rend="italic">Spaniards</hi> there, <lb/>but from whence it came
          ſo as to infect the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Americans</hi>, that is, from whence this
          Diſeaſe <lb/>ſprung <hi rend="italic">ab Origine</hi>, or had its firſt beginning, <lb/>is
          the great Queſtion in diſpute. </p>
        <pb n="5"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Martin Liſter</hi> ſays, it is to be believ'd, <lb/>that it
          proceeded at firſt, either from the Bi- <lb/>ting of ſome Venomous Animal, or from ſome
          <lb/>Food certainly Poyſonous; it being very well <lb/>known that the <hi rend="italic"
            >Americans</hi> freely eat certain <lb/>Serpents, (of which innumerable new Species or
          <lb/>Kinds are amongſt the <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> unknown to us) <lb/>and ſo
          either from the Poyſonous Nature of <lb/>that their impure Diet, or the Bitings of thoſe
          <lb/>Poyſonous Serpents, (as from the Biting of a <lb/>Mad-Dog, an <hi rend="italic"
            >Hydrophoby</hi> is occaſion'd) either <lb/>ſays he, from that external or internal
          Cauſe <lb/>was the Venereal Diſeaſe certainly bred, <lb/>which when once begotten,
          infected afterwards <lb/>with a Contagion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And he tells us, that <hi rend="italic">Conſalvus Oviedus</hi> a No- <lb/>ble <hi
            rend="italic">Spaniard</hi>, makes the ſame Obſervation, who <lb/>among all the <hi
            rend="italic">Spaniards</hi> was the moſt faithful <lb/>Hiſtorian of the Nature of
          Things, and was <lb/>for many Years one of the chief Governours <lb/>of thoſe Iſlands; of
          him there are ſome Books <lb/>extant, although many written by him are <lb/>loſt; and was
          a Man as <hi rend="italic">Cardan</hi> allows, to be <lb/>compared with Ancient Writers;
          and among <lb/>the other Animals, which he mentions to be <lb/>in <hi rend="italic"
            >Weſt-India</hi>, he exactly deſcribes the <hi rend="italic">Ingu- <lb/>anas</hi> to be
          no mean little Beaſt of the kind <lb/>of four footed Serpents, upon which the <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Indians</hi> fed greedily, accounting them a <lb/>Dainty; therefore the
            <hi rend="italic">Spaniſh</hi> Men after <lb/>their example, put them into their Food
          alſo, <lb/>their taſte being not in the leaſt diſpleaſing, <lb/>but on the contrary, more
          ſavoury than the <lb/>Fleſh of Rabits; and ſays, that the eating of <pb n="6"/>
          <lb/>them hurted no Body, unleſs ſuch who had <lb/>been infected with the Venereal <hi
            rend="italic">Lues</hi>, and <lb/>thoſe, although they had long before been <lb/>Cured
          thereof, it preſently offended, and at <lb/>length did ſtir up and renew the Diſeaſe, as
          <lb/>if the ſame had lain only dormant; and this, <lb/>ſays he, our Men experienc'd by
          innumerable <lb/>examples. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And for that reaſon, ſays Dr. <hi rend="italic">Liſter</hi>, 'tis <lb/>not ſo abſurd
          to believe, that this <hi rend="italic">Lues</hi> had <lb/>its Original from the like, if
          not from the <lb/>ſelf-ſame Cauſes, when ſurely by the eating <lb/>of them, forthwith the
          Malady revives, dead <lb/>as it were long before. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And the more, ſays he, am I confirm'd, <lb/>becauſe the ſecret Parts of either Sex
          in- <lb/>fected with this Diſeaſe, even when other <lb/>Symptoms are wanting a great
          while, are be- <lb/>ſet with certain <hi rend="italic">Tufts</hi>, thick-Tooth'd, like
          <lb/>Cocks-combs, juſt like thoſe in the Serpent <lb/><hi rend="italic">Inguanas</hi>,
          whoſe Body commonly is all over- <lb/>laid with Creſts of that ſort; certainly a pro-
          <lb/>per repreſentation from what Animal that <lb/>Diſtemper deriv'd its being. But thoſe
          creſted <lb/>Maladies, perhaps are reckoned by others, a- <lb/>mongſt the ſwelling
          Inflammations of the Fun- <lb/>dament and Hæmorrhoids, becauſe thoſe are <lb/>commonly
          viſible without any pain or cer- <lb/>tain tenuity of the Membrane. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is common, ſays he, that Poyſonous Ani- <lb/>mals alſo imprint proper and peculiar
          Cha- <lb/>racters of their Contagion; for Example, a <lb/>Barking in <hi rend="italic"
            >Hydrophobia</hi>, caus'd by the Biting <lb/>of a Mad-Dog, alſo a Dog-like voracity of
            <pb n="7"/>
          <lb/>ſwallowing, with an aptitude of licking, rather <lb/>than drinking, by a continual
          putting out of <lb/>the Tongue. Alſo by the biting of a Flea, like <lb/>a Spider call'd
            <hi rend="italic">Tarantula</hi>, is caus'd a conſtant <lb/>deſire of leaping; neither
          is the goings of thoſe <lb/>Spider-like things, other than after the man- <lb/>ner of
          Fleas, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> a skipping from one place <lb/>to another. I am not
          Ignorant indeed that <lb/>this may be accounted a Fable by ſome, even <lb/>Learned Men;
          but certainly, ſays he, not ſo <lb/>by me, to whom the cuſtoms of Spiders, are <lb/>a
          little more diligently conſider'd than others; <lb/>yea, that kind of Spiders may be
          afforded in <lb/>hot Countries, as <hi rend="italic">Calabria</hi>, by which moſt
          <lb/>pernicious bitings may be inflicted: indeed <lb/>the Hiſtory of the Nature of thoſe
          things is <lb/>only begun, and therefore, ſays he, I wonder <lb/>not ſo much that that,
          and innumerable <hi rend="italic">Phæ- <lb/>nomena's</hi> of that ſort, are hid from us,
          and <lb/>juſtly ſuſpected. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Moreover, ſays he, they who have eaten <lb/>a Sea <hi rend="italic">Lepus</hi>, (that
          is a kind of naked Sea-Hare, <lb/>of a purple Colour, found even in our Sea) <lb/>make a
          purple colour'd Urine; and in their <lb/>ſleep, ever and anon ſeem to hear the Waves
          <lb/>of the beaten Shores, and their Bodies be- <lb/>come livid; this Fiſh is reckon'd to
          be Poyſon <lb/>to Man, and Man to him, as <hi rend="italic">Scribonius</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">Dioſ- <lb/>corides</hi> and others, ſay. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Thus does this Author ſay of thoſe men- <lb/>tion'd, and other Poyſons, how that they
          im- <lb/>print the like upon the Perſon, that has either <lb/>been bitten by them, or has
          eaten of them; <lb/>to ſhew how the poſſibility of the Venereal <pb n="8"/>
          <lb/>Infection, from thoſe Poyſonous Animals, may <lb/>be infus'd, and that it might be
          propagated <lb/>at firſt from Beaſt to Man, and ſo transferr'd <lb/>from Man to Woman, or
          Woman to Man, <lb/>to what we daily find it to be now; and thus <lb/>he ſtates the
          Original of the Venereal <hi rend="italic">Lues</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Firovanti</hi> will not allow that this Diſeaſe <lb/>was brought
          from the <hi rend="italic">Weſt-Indies</hi>, but on the <lb/>contrary affirms, that the
            <hi rend="italic">French</hi> firſt got it <lb/>at the Siege of <hi rend="italic"
            >Naples</hi>, by feeding upon dead <lb/>Mens Carkaſſes, which Diet they were forc'd
          <lb/>to take up with, being almoſt famiſh'd; and <lb/>as a proof thereof, ſays he, feed
          but a Sow <lb/>with Sows Fleſh, or an Owl or a Whelp with <lb/>the Fleſh of their own
          Kind, and they will be <lb/>mark'd, as he has try'd and found, with <lb/>Blotches, Spots
          and Pimples, even like thoſe <lb/>of the Pox. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Paracelſus</hi> ſays, the Diſeaſe was bred be- <lb/>tween a <hi
            rend="italic">French</hi> Leper, and a <hi rend="italic">Neapolitan</hi> Whore,
          <lb/>when ſhe had her Courſes upon her. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Others again report, that a <hi rend="italic">Leper</hi> of <hi rend="italic"
            >Valentia, <lb/>Hiſpania Tarraconenſi</hi>, was the firſt that gave this <lb/>Diſeaſe,
          and that it was to a Noble Whore, of <lb/>whom he purchas'd a Nights Lodging for Fifty
          <lb/>pieces of Gold, and that ſhe ſince had diſpers'd <lb/>it among many others. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And ſome (as Dr. <hi rend="italic">Harvey</hi>, &amp;c. from others) <lb/>ſay. that
          it was firſt caus'd by <hi rend="italic">Greek</hi> Wine, daſh'd <lb/>with <hi
            rend="italic">Lepers</hi> Blood, which the <hi rend="italic">French</hi> drank, being
          <lb/>purpoſely left them at <hi rend="italic">Suma</hi> by the <hi rend="italic"
            >Spaniards</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But Divines, eſpecially ſome of them, im- <lb/>pute the riſe of it to God Almighty's
          Judgment <lb/>upon Adulterers, Fornicators, and other ſin- <lb/><unclear>f</unclear>ul
          Criminals. </p>
        <pb n="9"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The moſt Learned <hi rend="italic">Leonicenus</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Fracaſ-
            <lb/>torius</hi>, and certain others, were of the Opini- <lb/>on, that the riſe of the
          Venereal Diſeaſe was <lb/>Epidemical, and proceeded from a common <lb/>Cauſe, for that at
          its firſt beginning, Boys, <lb/>Men, Old-Folks, Girls and Women, were in- <lb/>fected,
          without any Communication or Here- <lb/>ditary Diſpoſition: and that the ſaid <hi
            rend="italic">Fracaſ- <lb/>torius</hi> writes in his Book, <hi rend="italic">de Morbo
            Gallic. <lb/>cap. 7.</hi> that tho' the greateſt part of Man- <lb/>kind, in his Time,
          had contracted the Diſ- <lb/>eaſe by Contagion, yet it had been obſerved, <lb/>that
          Numbers of others were infected Epi- <lb/>demically, without recieving it, or contracting
          <lb/>it, from any one. And thinks it impoſſible, <lb/>that in ſo ſmall a time, the
          Contagion (which, <lb/>ſays he, of it ſelf is ſlow and not eaſily re- <lb/>ceiv'd) could
          ſpread it ſelf over ſo many <lb/>Lands, when at firſt it was brought but by <lb/>one Fleet
          of the <hi rend="italic">Spaniards</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But if it was ſo, that it was at firſt <lb/>brought to us from <hi rend="italic"
            >America</hi> upon the diſ- <lb/>covery and conqueſt of that part of the <lb/>World, and
          that it was not known in <hi rend="italic">Eu- <lb/>rope</hi> before, as it has happen'd,
          it has prov'd <lb/>to us an untoward Conqueſt in that reſpect, <lb/>as Mr. <hi
            rend="italic">Tate</hi> in his Epiſtle to Dr. <hi rend="italic">Thomas <lb/>Hobbs</hi>,
          before his Poetical Tranſlation of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Syphilis</hi>, or the French
          Diſeaſe (written in <lb/>Latin by that Famous Poet and Phyſician <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Fracaſtorius</hi>) well obſerves, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>
          <q rend="italic">Dear was the Conqueſt of a <hi rend="roman">New</hi> found World,
            <lb/>Whoſe Plague e'er ſince thro' all the <hi rend="roman">Old</hi> is hurl'd. <pb
              n="10"/>
            <lb/>
            <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.75) roman">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* <hi rend="italic">Tranſlation</hi>. page 4. </p>
            </note>If then by Traffick thence this Plague was brought, <lb/>How dearly dearly was
            that Traffick bought! </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Others impute its Original riſe to the <lb/>Stars; others to the inundation, or over-
          <lb/>flowing of the River <hi rend="italic">Tyber</hi>, the Air being in- <lb/>fected by
          the Corruption of ſeveral Creatures, <lb/>which the Waters had caſt up and left upon the
          <lb/>Shore, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> And thus we ſee <hi rend="italic">Tot Homines
            quot <lb/>Sententia</hi>, many Men many Minds, for that thoſe <lb/>that lived about the
          time of the firſt beginning <lb/>of the Diſeaſe, cannot agree in their Judgments
          <lb/>about the true riſe thereof; and if they could <lb/>not then, what muſt we do now,
          that live more <lb/>than 2 Ages after them? As therefore it would <lb/>take up a great
          deal of Time and no ſmall <lb/>Pains, to enquire into the Validity or Proba- <lb/>bility
          of thoſe ſeveral Conjectures, (which I <lb/>cannot ſtand here to do, and conſequently
          <lb/>give my own Sentiments about) ſhall defer <lb/>it till a proper opportunity, which
          will be, <lb/>as before hinted, in my other Book promis'd, <lb/>only ſhall obſerve what a
          Gentleman in his <lb/>Commendatory Verſes upon the aforeſaid <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Tate</hi>, upon his Tranſlation of <hi rend="italic">Syphilis</hi>, <lb/>ſays, <hi
            rend="italic">viz.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>
          <q rend="italic">Blame not the Stars; 'tis plain it neither fell, <lb/>From the
            Diſtemper'd Heavens, nor roſe from Hell. <lb/>Nor need we to the diſtant <hi
              rend="roman">Indies</hi> rome; <lb/>The Curſt <hi rend="roman">Originals</hi> are
            nearer Home. <pb n="11"/>
            <lb/>Whence ſhould that foul infectious Torment flow, <lb/>But from the baneful Source
            of all our wo? <lb/>That <hi rend="roman">wheedling, Charming Sex</hi>, that draws us
            in, <lb/>To every Puniſhment, and every Sin. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Some ſay it is a Diſtemper very Malignant, <lb/>Poyſonous and Contagious, others
          differ ſo <lb/>much from that Opinion, as to ſay, the high- <lb/>eſt degree of Infection
          has no Malignity in it <lb/>at all, and that whenever they meet with a <lb/>Patient that
          has a <hi rend="italic">Clap</hi>, do, as faſt as poſſible, <lb/>adminiſter Medicines to
          ſtop the Running, <lb/>without any regard to what other Symptoms <lb/>occur, for that when
          the Running once ceaſes, <lb/>all the other Symptoms, (which, as they alledge, <lb/>ever
          ſpring only from the Running) go off in <lb/>courſe, without any detriment to the Patient.
          <lb/>But let thoſe that believe ſo, do ſo if they will, I <lb/>am ſatisfy'd, and too many
          unfortunate Peo- <lb/>ple can very readily agree with me, that it is <lb/>the only ſure
          way to Pox the Patient, and <lb/>when once that is done, the Symptoms and
          <lb/>Conſequences, will ſpeak too plainly how far <lb/>they have been in the wrong, and
          what in- <lb/>jury they have done the poor Patient. Seve- <lb/>ral Inſtances of which
          kind, the Reader will <lb/>obſerve, before he gets to the end of this Book. <lb/>But this
          by the way. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Perſons in Years may alſo be infected by <lb/>the immodeſt open-Mouth'd, laſcivious
          Kiſ- <lb/>ſings of Venereal People, eſpecially thoſe of <lb/>them that have Ulcers in
          their Mouths or <lb/>Throats, and where at the ſame time they <lb/>dwell as it were upon
          their Lips and Mouths, <pb n="12"/>
          <lb/>reiterating wanton, unſeemly Kiſſes, thereby <lb/>conveying their ſlimy, infectious
            <hi rend="italic">Slaver</hi>, to <lb/>ſuch; I ſay, grown Perſons by that means
          <lb/>may, and frequently have gotten the Vene- <lb/>real Diſtemper, but then generally
          they have <lb/>been obſerv'd to complain of their Throats <lb/>firſt, it ſeizing them
          after the ſame manner, <lb/>as if ſome Cold had been taken, the <hi rend="italic"
            >Saliva</hi> of <lb/>the Pocky Perſon communicating its infectious <lb/>Steams no
          farther at firſt, than about the <hi rend="italic">Glan- <lb/>dules</hi> in thoſe Parts,
          and which if not ſpeedily <lb/>minded, <hi rend="italic">Inflames</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >Ulcerates</hi>, and ſpreads its <lb/>Infection to the no ſmall damage of the Patient. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>To this way of Infection, alſo a certain <lb/>Learned Author aſſents, who ſays, that
          if it be <lb/>received only by Kiſſing of the Lips, it Bloſ- <lb/>ſoms there firſt, and
          appears with Scabby Erup- <lb/>tions, and a ſore Mouth or Throat; but if it <lb/>be gotten
          by the <hi rend="italic">Tail</hi>, 'tis not preſently Cha- <lb/>ractered in the Face or
          other Parts, but ſtays <lb/>ſome time in the lower parts, the place of its <lb/>Conception
          and Birth, and afterwards upon <lb/>neglect or ill management, or both, Travels in-
          <lb/>to other Regions of the Body, and appears here <lb/>and there, with variety of ugly
          Shapes, and un- <lb/>wholſome Salutes to its new Quarters, ſuch <lb/>as <hi rend="italic"
            >Pains</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Pimples</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Itch</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">Spots</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Scurf</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Scabs</hi>,
          &amp;c. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But Infections this way, that is, by Kiſſing, <lb/>are ſoon cured, if taken in time;
          indeed in <lb/>Children much more difficultly, what with <lb/>their not being ſuſpected by
          the Parent or <lb/>Attendant, of having any ſuch Infection, and <lb/>alſo not being
          capable of complaining, and <lb/>their tenderneſs (as obſerv'd before) much <pb n="13"/>
          <lb/>ſooner attracting the Taint, it is the more <lb/>eaſily diffus'd and radicated, than
          in grown <lb/>Perſons, which with their incapacity of going <lb/>thro' a Method that is
          proper, renders them <lb/>conſequently much harder of Cure, as the fol- <lb/>lowing
          Inſtance will demonſtrate. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A Child that I had in hand, ſome Years ſince, <lb/>upon ſucking a Wet-Nurſe, to whom
          it <lb/>was put out in the Country, grew ill, ac- <lb/>companied with breakings out all
          over the <lb/>Head and Face, (the Child being perfectly <lb/>well when it went from Home)
          I going one <lb/>Day to ſee it, and taking notice of the Nurſe, <lb/>obſerv'd ſhe had a
          ſore Eye; upon a narrow <lb/>inſpection of it, I had ſufficient cauſe of ſuſ- <lb/>picion,
          whereupon I examin'd her concerning <lb/>it, and tax'd her with having the Diſtemper,
          <lb/>which at firſt ſhe denied, but afterwards when <lb/>I had told her I was poſitive it
          was ſo, and de- <lb/>clared to her my Reaſons for it, (other Symp- <lb/>toms concurring)
          and at the ſame time urg- <lb/>ing her to acknowledge it; ſhe, with ſome <lb/>Reluctancy
          and Shame confeſſed the whole <lb/>matter, ſaying, ſhe got it from her Husband, <lb/>who
          (by the Character I afterwards heard of <lb/>him) I do believe was only in the Fault, not
          <lb/>but that the Nurſe was exceedingly to blame, <lb/>and indeed very indiſcreet and baſe
          to take the <lb/>Child to Suckle, when (whatever Excuſes ſhe <lb/>made to the contrary)
          ſhe could not but before- <lb/>hand be ſenſible of her Condition; but notwith-
          <lb/>ſtanding all the prudent endeavours, and ne- <lb/>ceſſary means that could be uſed,
          as well by the <lb/>Preſcripions, of an Eminent Phyſician, as my <pb n="14"/>
          <lb/>own, to ſave the poor Infant, it daily <lb/>grew worſe and worſe, and ſoon after died
          in <lb/>a moſt miſerable condition, to the no ſmall <lb/>trouble of the tender and honeſt
          Parents, <lb/>whoſe Grief, as may eaſily be ſuppos'd, was <lb/>ſo much the more
          aggravated, as the manner <lb/>of its Death was woful and unexpected. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This ſingle inſtance, without enumerating <lb/>others of the like kind, which have
          occurr'd in <lb/>my Practice, may ſerve for a Caution to Pa- <lb/>rents to be wary and
          careful what Wet-Nurſes <lb/>they chooſe, and alſo to wholeſome Nurſes <lb/>what Children
          they take to Suckle, the dan- <lb/>ger being almoſt equal both to the one and <lb/>the
          other, ſince many Children that are Born <lb/>of Venereal Parents, bringing the Diſtemper
          <lb/>into the World with them, do, upon being <lb/>put out to Nurſes to Suckle, very often
          con- <lb/>vey the Infection; as was the condition of a <lb/>Nurſe that I lately Cured, who
          by giving Suck <lb/>to a Pocky Child, of about two Months Old, <lb/>had her Breaſts all
          over ſpread with a Humour, <lb/>beginning firſt at the Nipples, which ſwell'd <lb/>the
          Glands, and Tumified, before ſhe ſo much <lb/>as imagin'd what ſhould be the Cauſe
          thereof; <lb/>till upon growing worſe, with breakings out, <lb/>Inflammation and Pain, ſhe
          ſought for help, and <lb/>was told it was Venereal; and making appli- <lb/>cation to me,
          by the recommendation of ano- <lb/>ther, I ſoon recover'd her to her Health, which
          <lb/>ſhe now enjoys. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Likewiſe a good ſober Woman, who had Suck- <lb/>led ſeveral Gentlemen's Children, to
          their great <lb/>ſatisfaction, as good a Nurſe perhaps as can be, <pb n="15"/>
          <lb/>upon giving Suck to a Child, ſeemingly <lb/>as ſhe thought, very Healthy, (only had
          ſome <lb/>breakings out about it, which the Mother <lb/>ſaid was only Heat and ſharp
          Humours) was ex- <lb/>ceedingly infected with the Pox, all her Nip- <lb/>ples breaking
          out, her Throat ſore, with Ul- <lb/>cers, a Hoarſneſs and Pains about her, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
          <lb/>at firſt ſhe did not mind it, not in the leaſt <lb/>ſuſpecting any harm; but when it
          invaded her <lb/>Throat, cauſing Hoarſneſs, as alſo Pains in her <lb/>Limbs, and breakings
          out on the Privy Parts, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
          <lb/>ſhe began to fear, and came for my Advice; <lb/>for her Cure I advis'd to a
          Salivation, which <lb/>ſhe is now preparing for, and will go into <lb/>as ſoon as the
          Ulcers in her Throat are ſo <lb/>well amended as to give leave. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Alſo divers others of the like Infections <lb/>have happen'd in my Practice, to the
          Diſad- <lb/>vantage, and ſometimes Ruin, both of Nurſes <lb/>and Children, the ſmalleſt
          Species of the <lb/>Diſeaſe being ſufficient many times, eſpeci- <lb/>ally in Children,
          and other tender Conſtitu- <lb/>tions to infect either, by which means many <lb/>Families
          have been undone, who not knowing <lb/>for a long time what has ail'd them, and lit-
          <lb/>tle dreaming of ſuch a Diſtemper, or the poſ- <lb/>ſibility of getting it that way,
          have been <lb/>drill'd along in a miſtaken Courſe, till (when <lb/>too late perhaps) it
          has been diſcover'd that <lb/>their Diſtempers were Venereal. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And 'tis not to be doubted, but that num- <lb/>bers of Perſons, more eſpecially
          Children, are <lb/>yearly deſtroy'd in this City, by means of <lb/>that Diſeaſe,
          notwithſtanding they paſs in the <pb n="16"/>
          <lb/>Bills of Mortality for <hi rend="italic">Fevers</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >Convulſions</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Con- <lb/>ſumptions</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >Gripings in the Guts</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Rickets</hi>, <hi rend="italic">King's-
            <lb/>Evil</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Teeth</hi>, and the
          like; tho' at the <lb/>ſame time it might be, that they died of <lb/>thoſe Diſtempers, but
          then too often cauſed <lb/>by, and complicated with, the Venereal In- <lb/>fection, ſo as
          juſtly enough to be term'd <hi rend="italic">Pocky <lb/>Conſumptions</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">Pocky King's-Evil</hi>, &amp;c. and indeed <lb/>it is great pity poor
          innocent Babes, (they al- <lb/>ways faring the worſe under ſuch a Diſaſter) <lb/>ſhould be
          (as they too frequently are) depriv'd <lb/>of their Lives, and at the beſt of their
          Healths, <lb/>by the barbarous Treatment of their polluted <lb/>Attendants; who, tho' they
          too well know <lb/>before-hand what Diſtempers they have upon <lb/>them, will for the
          lucre of a little Money run <lb/>the hazard of the Childrens Lives. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And not only do Children become Sufferers <lb/>by Wet-Nurſes, but alſo by
          Nurſery-Maids, <lb/>many of whom, however paſſing for modeſt <lb/>Perſons, have ſecret
          Venereal Infirmities <lb/>upon them, which they too often communi- <lb/>cate to the
          Children they lie with, whoſe <lb/>open Pores by Sweating, do attract thoſe in-
          <lb/>fectious Steams, and which has ſoon after ap- <lb/>pear'd, as I have obſerv'd in
          ſeveral Children, <lb/>either by breakings out about the Body, Sore- <lb/>Eyes, Swellings,
          or after ſome other manner <lb/>diſcovering it ſelf, ſo as not to be doubted <lb/>but that
          it is Venereal, and which for ſome <lb/>time perhaps has not been in the leaſt ſuſpec-
          <lb/>ted by the Parents, to be what it has proved; <lb/>for which reaſon Parents can never
          be too <lb/>careful what Servants they take to Bed with, <pb n="17"/>
          <lb/>and bring up their Children, ſince ſo many <lb/>Miſchiefs by means thereof, have too
          demon- <lb/>ſtrably accrued; among ſeveral of which that <lb/>I could recollect, I ſhall
          take notice only of <lb/>one, that happen'd but very lately, and is as <lb/>follows, <hi
            rend="italic">viz.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A Nurſery-Maid that had the Care of the <lb/>two youngeſt Children of an eminent
          Shop- <lb/>keeper in this City, committed to her, was <lb/>one Day obſerv'd by ſome of the
          Family, to <lb/>have divers Medicines in her Trunk, as <hi rend="italic">Pills</hi>,
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Electuaries</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Powders</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">Balſams</hi>, &amp;c. and being <lb/>ask'd what ſhe did with them? ſhe
          anſwer'd, <lb/>that ſhe always kept ſuch by her, in caſe any <lb/>illneſs ſhould happen to
          her, pretending that <lb/>ſhe had great skill in Diſtempers; ſome ſhort <lb/>time after
          this, the two Children ſhe attend- <lb/>ed grew ill, with loſs of Stomach, being <lb/>hot
          and feveriſh, and upon one of them aroſe <lb/>a Swelling under the Ear, and in one of the
          <lb/>Arm-pits, which render'd it very froward; <lb/>the other had Sore-Eyes and
          Breakings-out in <lb/>many places of the Head, Face and Body, <lb/>attended with a violent
          hot, ſharp Humour <lb/>upon the lower Parts; in ſhort, both of them <lb/>were ſo bad, that
          notwithſtanding the en- <lb/>deavours of an Apothecary that was employ'd <lb/>to
          adminiſter to them, they grew worſe and <lb/>worſe, upon which he advis'd them to a Sur-
          <lb/>geon, and mentioning me, I was ſent for; <lb/>when I was there, after inquiring into
          their <lb/>Conditions, ask'd what they had taken? <lb/>which, when I had been inform'd,
          and being <lb/>what was proper, told the Parents, I wonder'd <pb n="18"/>
          <lb/>thoſe attempts ſhould prove fruitleſs, and <lb/>that their Caſes muſt needs be
          rebellious to <lb/>reſiſt thoſe Medicines; beſides it was ſome- <lb/>thing unaccountable
          that two Children (who, <lb/>as I was told, were ever till then very heal- <lb/>thy)
          ſhould fall ill, almoſt all of a ſudden, <lb/>and after ſuch a manner, and wiſh'd it was
          <lb/>no hurt; upon which they ask'd me what I <lb/>meant by ſaying ſo? I preſently
          enquir'd for <lb/>the Perſon that attended them; and ſhe that <lb/>lay with them being in
          the Room, I ask'd <lb/>her how ſhe did, for that I ſuppos'd ſhe was <lb/>their Bed-fellow,
          and whether ſhe had any <lb/>Breakings out? ſhe immediately anſwer'd no, <lb/>and that ſhe
          lay with them, but for her part <lb/>was as well as ever ſhe was in her Life: ſo I
          <lb/>ſaid no more, but after ordering what they <lb/>ſhould do at home for them, and
          telling the <lb/>Parents I would ſend what was neceſſary, <lb/>went away. After I was
          gone, the Parents <lb/>were uneaſie at my Expreſſions, not knowing <lb/>what I meant,
          which the Servant that had <lb/>ſeen the Medicines in the Nurſery-Maids <lb/>Trunk,
          obſerving, told her Miſtreſs thereof, <lb/>and ſaid, ſhe fear'd the Nurſery-Maid had
          <lb/>given the children ſome Phyſick that had <lb/>done them harm; upon this, they immedi-
          <lb/>ately calls and asks her, but ſhe poſitively <lb/>denyed it; but ſuſpecting ſomething
          of the <lb/>Matter, would needs ſee her Trunk, where- <lb/>in among many Boxes and Pots,
            <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> they <lb/>found a written Paper of Directions for the
          <lb/>taking her Medicines, and dreſſing her Sores <lb/>in the Groins and other Parts; and
          they re- <pb n="19"/>
          <lb/>membring my Words, ask'd her what Diſ- <lb/>temper ſhe had? and ſent immediately away
          <lb/>for me. When I came, I found them all a- <lb/>larm'd, and after telling me what had
          oc- <lb/>curr'd, ask'd my Opinion, upon which, I told <lb/>them plainly, I believ'd their
          Children had <lb/>got the foul Diſeaſe, but how they came by <lb/>it I knew not, unleſs by
          lying with the Nur- <lb/>ſery-Maid. It was thereupon agreed that I <lb/>ſhould examine
          her, which accordingly I did, <lb/>but ſhe with a great deal of Confidence de- <lb/>nied
          it, and not only ſo, but that ſhe would <lb/>make me prove my Words; but however, the
          <lb/>more ſhe denied it, the more I aſſerted it, and <lb/>what with urging her, threatning
          her, and tell- <lb/>ing her I was ſure what I ſaid was true; ſhe began <lb/>to relent, and
          at laſt told me her Condition, and <lb/>how ſhe came by the Infection, but ſtill upon my
          <lb/>promiſe of Secrecy, and that I would inter- <lb/>cede with her Maſter and Miſtreſs
          for her, <lb/>which I did, who after ſome exclamations and <lb/>ſharp reprimands,
          diſcharged her of their <lb/>Service. This Creature had a Sore, Scabby <lb/>Head, which
          run much, had an Ulcer in each <lb/>Groin, and ſeveral Sores beſides, attended <lb/>with
          malignant Eruptions in ſeveral other <lb/>parts of her Body, which by lying between
          <lb/>the two Children, one of them about two, <lb/>the other above three Years old, and
          Sweat- <lb/>ing often with Medicines which ſhe ſaid ſhe <lb/>took, muſt needs have
          convey'd the Infection <lb/>to them, and which, under God, I ſet them <lb/>free from, tho'
          not without a great deal of <lb/>difficulty, and no ſmall time; but ſo deplo- <pb n="20"/>
          <lb/>rable were their conditions, that I often <lb/>fear'd the Succeſs, they for a long
          time ap- <lb/>pearing to all, eſpecially one of them, more <lb/>likely to die, than to
          live. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A Child alſo of an Apothecary that was <lb/>infected by the naſty Slavering of a
          Pocky <lb/>Servant-Maid that attended it, it appearing <lb/>in the Child's Mouth, which
          was grievous <lb/>Sore, I Cured; as alſo the Wenches ulcera- <lb/>ted Throat and
          Hoarſneſs, which ſhe at firſt <lb/>call'd a Cold: But I ſhall not enumerate In-
          <lb/>ſtances here, intending to enlarge further <lb/>concerning thoſe Matters in my
          general Trea- <lb/>tiſe aforemention'd, which I have now made <lb/>ſuch a Progreſs in, as
          that it will ſoon be <lb/>ready for the Preſs, the Title-Page and Con- <lb/>tents of which
          is (for the ſatisfaction of <lb/>ſome that may be deſirous to know in <lb/>what Method I
          treat thereon) affixed at the <lb/>end of this Tract: In which Treatiſe I ſhall <lb/>alſo
          for the benefit of the Publick, ſhew the <lb/>Methods I generally purſue, and preſcribe
          <lb/>the Medicines I uſually adminiſter in the <lb/>Cure of this Diſeaſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Many are the ways aſſign'd by Authors of <lb/>the Propagation of the Venereal
          Diſtemper, <lb/>ſeveral of which, (as I ſhall by and by men- <lb/>tion) ſeem very abſurd
          and irrational, and <lb/>which I ſhould particularly here enlarge upon <lb/>and ſhew the
          fallacy of, but for brevity ſake, <lb/>I having never in all my Practice, (which has
          <lb/>been none of the leaſt) obſerv'd any one <lb/>Perſon really to have gotten the
          Diſeaſe thoſe <lb/>ways, tho' I have made the moſt exact En- <pb n="21"/>
          <lb/>quiry into ſeveral Patients, who (to ſcreen <lb/>their Guilt) have endeavour'd to
          amuſe me <lb/>therewith, tho' afterwards confeſs'd the con- <lb/>trary: Thoſe Authors
          aſſerting that the Di- <lb/>ſtemper is to be gotten by barely lying in <lb/>the ſame Bed
          with an infected Perſon, (of <lb/>which I ſhall anon say more) or after ſuch in <lb/>the
          ſame <hi rend="italic">Sheets</hi>, or by wearing their <hi rend="italic">Cloaths</hi>,
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Gloves</hi>, &amp;c, or by ſitting preſently after <lb/>them on
          the ſame <hi rend="italic">Cloſe-ſtool</hi>, or by Drink- <lb/>ing out of the ſame <hi
            rend="italic">Pot</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Glaſs</hi> immediate- <lb/>ly after them, or
          by receiving the <hi rend="italic">Breath</hi> of <lb/>infected Perſons, by talking with
          them, or <lb/>the like, which tho' nothing be more com- <lb/>mon, than that the Patient to
          avoid the <lb/>Shame and Diſgrace of having gotten it by <lb/>Copulation, will pretend,
          and work ſome <lb/>(eſpecially over-credulous or ignorant Peo- <lb/>ple) into the belief
          of, and at the ſame time <lb/>pleaſe themſelves to ſee them impos'd upon, <lb/>(as certain
          Matrons which <hi rend="italic">Gabriel Fallopius</hi>
          <lb/>in his Book <hi rend="italic">De Morbo Gallico</hi>, cap. 10. takes <lb/>notice of
          Scoffingly, who having the Vene- <lb/>real Diſtemper, and willing to be accounted
          <lb/>chaſt, would have it believed by their Phy- <lb/>ſicians, <hi rend="italic"
            >&amp;c.</hi> that they got it by ſprinkling <lb/>themſelves with Holy-Water, which ſome
          <lb/>Pocky Perſons had polluted) yet is what Men <lb/>skill'd in the Diſtemper can quickly
          ſee thro' <lb/>and detect; and indeed are ſuch ridiculous <lb/>Fancies, that I have often
          wonder'd any <lb/>ſhould take up with and believe them; for <lb/>beſides my own
          Obſervations, I never by all <lb/>the Enquiries I have made of Men of Buſi- <pb n="22"/>
          <lb/>neſs, could learn that any of them ever met <lb/>with one that really was infected
          thoſe ways; <lb/>and the more I have improv'd in the Know- <lb/>ledge of the Venereal
          Diſeaſe, the more I <lb/>have been convinc'd of the impoſſibility there- <lb/>of; for were
          ſuch a thing poſſible, how uni- <lb/>verſally would the Diſtemper be ſpread? how <lb/>many
          hundreds, I may ſay thouſands, would <lb/>be daily in danger of getting it? and how
          <lb/>few by this time would have eſcaped it, I <lb/>leave all Perſons to judge? but the
          Reaſons <lb/>thoſe Authors aſſign to maintain their Opini- <lb/>on, are no other than what
          are eaſie to be <lb/>confuted, and indeed ſo weak and groundleſs, <lb/>as not worth Time
          and Pains to take notice <lb/>of. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The ſame Authors likewiſe aſſert that the <lb/>Diſtemper may be, and frequently is
          gotten <lb/>in Coition, between a ſound Man and a ſound <lb/>Woman, by their too much
          forcing the <hi rend="italic">Sper- <lb/>matick Veſſels</hi>, and over-heating the Parts,
          <lb/>eſpecially the <hi rend="italic">Proſtate Glandules</hi>; but this al- <lb/>ſo is
          without the leaſt colour or ſhew of Rea- <lb/>ſon: indeed a <hi rend="italic"
            >Gonorrhæa</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Running</hi>, may <lb/>be procured thereby, and is
          what very often <lb/>happens by the weakning of the <hi rend="italic">Spermatick Veſ-
            <lb/>ſels</hi>, and diſpoſing them to receive ſharp Hu- <lb/>mors, but yet is ever
          attended with diffe- <lb/>rent Symptoms, than uſually appears when <lb/>the Caſe is
          Venereal; for the Seeds of one Man <lb/>and one Woman in Coition that are Sound, <lb/>can
          never degenerate into a Contagious or <lb/>Venereal Ferment; the Laws of Nature be- <pb
            n="23"/>
          <lb/>ing always uniform, and which (as one ob- <lb/>ſerves) are no ways capable of
          alteration, <lb/>otherwiſe than for the generating a Natural <lb/>Birth, or ſome other
          Production; or if it <lb/>happens that ſome diſpoſition be wanting for <lb/>ſuch a
          generation, thoſe Seeds then are on- <lb/>ly loſt, but never produce any Bodily harm,
          <lb/>at leaſt no Contagious or Venereal Diſtem- <lb/>per, as many Authors fancy, and
          Patients <lb/>that have got it otherwiſe, would, to pre- <lb/>ſerve their Reputation, have
          to be ſo, ſome- <lb/>what elſe being neceſſarily required to make <lb/>the Seed degenerate
          into a Ferment that is <lb/>Venereal, and altogether contrary to Na- <lb/>ture; for the
          the Pox proving Infectious upon <lb/>Copulation, is becauſe its engender'd out of
          <lb/>very infectious Diſeaſes, aud conveyed by <lb/>the Seed, which as it is the Spirits
          contract- <lb/>ed, and Flower of all the Juices in the Body, <lb/>ſo muſt it likewiſe
          conſiſt of the Spirits con- <lb/>tracted, and Flower of all the Infection, or
          <lb/>infected Juices of the whole Body. But I <lb/>ſhall not expatiate upon thoſe Matters
          here, <lb/>the narrow compaſs I am confin'd to prevent- <lb/>ing; and beſides, that I
          intend in my other <lb/>Book, particularly to enlarge thereon. I ſhall <lb/>therefore, as
          pertinent to the purpoſe afore- <lb/>ſaid, only relate the Caſes of a Gentleman <lb/>and
          his Wife lately under my Care, that were <lb/>Venereal, (tho' they would have it that it
          <lb/>was only from Weakneſs) and conclude this <lb/>Head; which Caſes will demonſtrate how
          ea- <lb/>ſily ignorant Practitioners may be impos'd up- <lb/>on in this reſpect, and what
          ways ſome Pa- <pb n="24"/>
          <lb/>tients take, and Stories they invent to hide <lb/>their Guilt, tho' manifeſtly to
          their own hurt: <lb/>the Caſe is this. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A Gentleman and his Wife, (who were <lb/>but newly Marry'd,) came to me together,
          <lb/>and told me a melancholly Story of a great <lb/>weakneſs that attended them,
          contracted as <lb/>he ſaid by over-indulging themſelves in their <lb/>conjugal Enjoyments,
          and that it appeared <lb/>upon them with a Running, Sharpneſs and <lb/>ſtoppage of Urine,
            <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> In ſhort, upon enqui- <lb/>ry, I found they had nothing
          leſs than the ap- <lb/>parent Symptoms of a Clap; they had been, <lb/>as they told me, in
          the Hands of a Doctor, <lb/>who for ſome time together had adminiſtred <lb/>ſtrengthning
          Medicines, but to ſo little pur- <lb/>poſe, that they grew worſe, (as no wonder <lb/>but
          they ſhould) upon which he advis'd them <lb/>to live abſtemious, and haſten down to the
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Bath</hi>, which he ſaid would Cure them; even <lb/>the ſame,
          ſaid I, as <hi rend="italic">the old Womans Plaiſter <lb/>did the Bone out of Joynt, which
            ſhe ſaid would <lb/>draw it in again</hi>; however upon his meeting <lb/>with my Book,
          they came as before-ſaid to <lb/>conſult me, and I telling them they might <lb/>be cured,
          gave them ſuch encouragement, <lb/>that put a ſtop to their <hi rend="italic"
          >Bath</hi>-journey, but <lb/>finding his Wife Ignorant as to the real Cauſe <lb/>of their
          Indiſpoſitions, and believing it to <lb/>be his fault; I enquir'd not ſo ſtrictly, nor
          <lb/>told them what my Opinion was as to their <lb/>Diſtemper, when they were with me
          together, <lb/>leſt it ſhould ſtir up difference between them; <lb/>but the next Day when
          he came for the Me- <pb n="25"/>
          <lb/>dicines, I plainly told him their Caſes were <lb/>Venereal; but he (for fear, I
          ſuppoſe, that <lb/>his Wife ſhould know it) poſitively denied <lb/>it, and ſeem'd
          diſpleas'd at me for telling <lb/>him ſo, and ſaid if it had been Venereal, his <lb/>other
          Doctor would have diſcover'd it; but <lb/>inſtead thereof, always aſſur'd them it was
          <lb/>nothing but weakneſs. I told him his Doc- <lb/>tor was certainly miſtaken, and that I
          was <lb/>ſorry I had any Reaſon to tell him ſo; but <lb/>if he himſelf was ſure he never
          deſerv'd for <lb/>the Diſtemper, and alſo (as he ſaid) could <lb/>engage for his Wifes
          Honeſty, he had better <lb/>employ ſome Body elſe, for as 'twas my Opi- <lb/>nion their
          Caſes were Venereal, ſo I ſhould <lb/>not pretend to Cure them any otherwiſe <lb/>than by
          Anti-Venereals, which if their Di- <lb/>ſtempers were not ſo, would do them an In-
          <lb/>jury; upon which, he reply'd, if they had <lb/>the Diſtemper, it was gotten by only
          too <lb/>violent Coition; but I telling him that could <lb/>not be, he at laſt, upon
          engaging my Secre- <lb/>ſie, acknowledg'd the Matter, and told me, <lb/>that a few Months
          before he was Married, he <lb/>got a Clap, but thought that he had been as well <lb/>from
          it, as ever he was in his Life, but now <lb/>as it appear'd otherwiſe he begg'd Pardon for
          <lb/>his denying it, and entreated my aſſiſtance, <lb/>which I readily gave him, and with
          ſuch <lb/>Succeſs that both of them were well Cured in <lb/>a very ſhort time; and to this
          Day his Wife <lb/>knows no otherwiſe than that it proceeded, <lb/>as at firſt repreſented;
          and there being no <lb/>ſuſpicion nor cauſe for it, they live very lov- <pb n="26"/>
          <lb/>ingly together. This Gentleman, as an ac- <lb/>knowledgement of my Care, over and
          above <lb/>what I requir'd and was paid for their Cures, <lb/>has ſince made me a very
          generous Preſent. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I promis'd a little before to take further <lb/>Notice about getting the Diſtemper by
          bare- <lb/>ly lying in the ſame Bed with an Infected <lb/>Perſon, and obſerv'd that I had
          never met <lb/>with any that receiv'd the Taint that way; <lb/>but at the ſame time it is
          to be underſtood <lb/>that 'tis dangerous Sweating in a Bed with <lb/>one that hath the
          Pox, ſo as to be wet with <lb/>the Sweat, eſpecially for young People, whoſe
          <lb/>Conſtitutions are tender, Fleſh more lax, and <lb/>Pores more open, and readier to
          receive the <lb/>Infection than thoſe of Years, and ſuch have <lb/>been known to be
          infected thereby, witneſs <lb/>the two Children infected by the Nurſery- <lb/>Maid, which
          I a little before Related; but <lb/>yet it is not very commonly known; and to <lb/>hear of
          grown People ſo infected, is very rare, <lb/>eſpecially robuſt, hardy Conſtitutions, who
          <lb/>are ſcarce ever infected, tho' in the moſt <lb/>Danger that way imaginable; an
          Inſtance of <lb/>which was a Woman, whoſe Husband I had <lb/>in Cure for the Pox, that lay
          with him con- <lb/>tinually in the ſame Bed, wherein he was <lb/>frequently Sweated, (they
          not having the <lb/>conveniency of lying apart) and yet receiv'd <lb/>not the leaſt
          Injury, notwithſtanding the diſ- <lb/>advantage ſhe was under, of being very ill <lb/>at
          the ſame time of another Diſtemper, and <lb/>her Husband too in a moſt miſerable Condi-
          <lb/>tion, labouring under as radicated a Pox as <lb/>moſt that I have known. </p>
        <pb n="27"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Alſo a late Patient I cured that had a thorow <lb/>Pox upon him, with Breakings out
          in many pla- <lb/>ces of his Body, who lay for many Weeks to- <lb/>gether in the ſame Bed
          with his own Brother, <lb/>a ſound freſh-colour'd young Man, lately <lb/>come out of the
          Country, not letting him <lb/>know what ail'd him, tho' he frequently com- <lb/>plain'd
          that he ſmell'd ſo ſtrong, he could <lb/>ſcarcely lye with him, yet never receiv'd the
          <lb/>leaſt Infection; notwithſtanding he told me, <lb/>(when he came to know what his
          Brothers <lb/>Diſtemper was) that ſome Nights when he <lb/>awak'd, he found himſelf to
          Sweat and ſtick <lb/>to his Brothers Sores, and was in ſuch fear <lb/>concerning himſelf,
          that he could hardly be <lb/>perſwaded but that he had gotten the Infec- <lb/>tion. Nay
          further than this, I have read <lb/>that a certain noble Man of <hi rend="italic"
            >Padua</hi>, that had <lb/>the Venereal Diſeaſe, for which he had uſed <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Guaiacum</hi> for Cure almoſt twenty times, and <lb/>was thrice anointed
          with <hi rend="italic">Quickſilver</hi>, yet the <lb/>Diſtemper was ſo ſtubborn, as that
          he could <lb/>not be cured; this Man, tho' infected, lay <lb/>with ſeveral Virgins, and
          yet never gave to <lb/>either of them the Diſeaſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And <hi rend="italic">Antonius Muſa</hi>, relates one whoſe <lb/>Wife had the
          Venereal Diſeaſe about her <lb/>Breaſt, and tho' he continually lay with her, <lb/>yet
          never contracted the Diſeaſe. The Cauſe <lb/>of which muſt be, that the Diſeaſe had taken
          <lb/>its ſeat in remote Parts and was not carried <lb/>to the Genitals, elſe would
          certainly have <lb/>proved Contagious, excepting for what we allow <lb/>as to the
          diſpoſition of ſome Bodies, as we ſhall <pb n="28"/>
          <lb/><choice>
            <corr>particularly</corr>
            <sic>ticularly</sic>
          </choice> mention by and by, in which there <lb/>is not an aptitude to receive it at all
          times, <lb/>as we daily obſerve, by ſeveral Mens lying <lb/>with one and the ſame infected
          Woman, <lb/>and yet ſome of them ſhall be tainted, and <lb/>others go free, as <hi
            rend="italic">Gabriel Fallopius de Morbo <lb/>Gallico</hi> cap. 22. makes mention; and
          that of <lb/>12 Schollars that had to do at one time, with <lb/>one and the ſame Whore,
          that had the Pox, <lb/>one after another, only three of the twelve <lb/>got the Infection,
          the reſt eſcaped clear. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And <hi rend="italic">Euſtachius Rudius</hi> writes, <hi rend="italic">lib. 5. de
            Mor- <lb/>bo occult.</hi> cap. 9. That he hath obſerved a <lb/>thouſand times, that many
          young Men have <lb/>on the ſame day Copulated with one and the <lb/>ſame Whore, and yet
          not all of them Infect- <lb/>ed, and thoſe that were infected, not infected <lb/>alike. It
          appearing in one with a Running <lb/>of the Reins, in another with a Bubo, in a-
          <lb/>nother with Rottenneſs, another with Pain <lb/>in the Head, another with falling off
          of the <lb/>Hair, and in others with other different pre- <lb/>ternatural effects; which
          doubtleſs, ſays he, <lb/>happens by Reaſon of the various diſpoſiti- <lb/>ons of the
          Bodies, weakneſs of the Parts, and <lb/>variety of the Humours; for Weak parts, do
          <lb/>more eaſily receive Vitious Humours than <lb/>the ſtrong; and ſtrong Bodies
          oftentimes re- <lb/>ſiſt Vitious Humours when weak ones can't; <lb/>again one Body is more
          clean, another more <lb/>foul, one abounds with one ſort of Humours, <lb/>another with
          others, which when they are <lb/>corrupted with the Venereal or Poyſonous <lb/>Matter, do
          cauſe this, or that Symptom, <pb n="29"/>
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Secundum Corporis habitudo</hi>; by which is indi- <lb/>cated both
          the Certainty, Degree and Nature <lb/>of the Infection. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>An tho', as I have ſaid before, that by <lb/>the laſcivious Kiſſings of impure or
          Infected <lb/>Perſons whoſe Lips are Ulcerated, or that <lb/>have Ulcers in their Mouths
          or Throats, the <lb/>Diſtemper is in like manner convey'd and at- <lb/>tracted, yet it is
          not to be underſtood, that <lb/>it can be gotten by the common modeſt way <lb/>of Kiſſing,
          or being Kiſs'd by ſuch Perſons; <lb/>for were it ſo, what numbers of People would <lb/>be
          daily infected with the Pox? and what <lb/>Danger would Thouſands be in of getting
          <lb/>it, that never gave occaſion for it? beſides <lb/>if the thing were poſſible, Kiſſing
          for that <lb/>very reaſon would be ſoon out of uſe, many <lb/>Women diſeas'd being perhaps
          Kiſs'd by <lb/>twenty, when not lain with by one Man, <lb/>and the ſame by a Man ſo
          Diſtemper'd; and <lb/>after all, it is very rare that the Diſeaſe got- <lb/>ten this way,
          ſhould only ſeize the Throat <lb/>without any other Symptom attending, tho' <lb/>I have
          obſerv'd it ſo, yet more commonly <lb/>with other Concomitants, but then perhaps <lb/>more
          through neglect of taking it in time, <lb/>or other Irregularities either in themſelves,
          <lb/>or ill management of the Practitioner, or both; <lb/>it being very eaſie for the
          Patient, and too <lb/>often for the Practicer, to be miſtaken as to <lb/>its Cauſe, and
          look upon it only as a Sore <lb/>Throat from Cold, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> which
          miſtake proves <lb/>too frequently to the Danger, if not De- <lb/>ſtruction, of the
          Patient; ſeveral ſuch un- <pb n="30"/>
          <lb/>happy People having come within my Know- <lb/>ledge, that would ſcarcely be perſwaded
          it <lb/>could proceed from a Venereal Cauſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is likewiſe by ſome Authors mightily af- <lb/>firm'd for Truth, that if a Woman
          that is <lb/>perfectly Sound, ſhould keep Company with <lb/>half a dozen young Fellows as
          ſound as her <lb/>ſelf, and be Debauch'd by them ſeverally, <lb/>time after time, ſome one
          or other of them <lb/>ſhall quickly receive a Venereal Taint, and <lb/>that 'tis rare but
          all of them, by a repetition <lb/>of the Venereal Act, ſhall at laſt be infected, <lb/>by
          the corrupt Ferment of mixt Seeds; but <lb/>it is an aſſertion that I never could Credit,
          <lb/>for were ſuch a thing poſſible, as there has <lb/>been <hi rend="italic">Whores</hi>
          from the Creation that drove a <lb/>common Trade, ſo we ſhould conſequently <lb/>have had
          the Pox among us long before it <lb/>had a beginning; it never, as the generality <lb/>of
          Authors aſſure us, being known in any <lb/>part of the World till the Year 1493. and
          <lb/>that was at <hi rend="italic">Naples</hi>, from Cauſes quite different <lb/>to any
          thing of that kind; and beſides by <lb/>the many Enquiries I have made in my own
          <lb/>Practice, and the opportunities had of inform- <lb/>ing my ſelf among others, and
          ſome of them <lb/>the moſt curious, I could never find or hear <lb/>of any one ſo
          infected. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And the better to demonſtrate the contra- <lb/>ry, I will relate what I was told by a
          young <lb/>Fellow who was the ſeventh that lay with a <lb/>certain Servant-Maid that was
          clean, one af- <lb/>ter another, as faſt as they could, and yet <lb/>neither of them, nor
          the Female as he poſi- <pb n="31"/>
          <lb/>tively aſſured me, got the leaſt harm; and the <lb/>more to convince me that what he
          ſaid was <lb/>true, he further declar'd, that they ſeven be- <lb/>ing Intimates, and in
          League one with another, <lb/>did frequently make uſe of her afterwards, for a
          <lb/>conſiderable length of Time, and that it was <lb/>rare but one, two, or three of them
          lay with her <lb/>every Day, they allowing her a competency <lb/>for the freedom, whereby
          ſhe became a Pro- <lb/>ſtitute to their Service, and no Bodies elſe; <lb/>and indeed in my
          Opinion ſhe needed no more. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Thus plainly appears the unlikelineſs, or <lb/>rather impoſſibility of getting the
          Diſtemper <lb/>that way, which the better to ſtrengthen my <lb/>Opinion, and confute thoſe
          Practicers that <lb/>believe the contrary, ſhall curſorily relate <lb/>what a certain
          Author has obſerved concern- <lb/>ing the like Matter. The Story is this. A <lb/>Woman
          came on Board a Ship, of which he <lb/>was the Surgeon, and was familiarly and fre-
          <lb/>quently made uſe of for ſome Hours together <lb/>by the greateſt part of the Ship's
          Crew, they <lb/>taking her by turns, and yet all of them <lb/>came off clear without the
          leaſt Venereal <lb/>Taint, and poſitively affirms that the Wo- <lb/>man was likewiſe the
          ſame. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The ſame Author alſo gives an Account of <lb/>another Woman that had been Drinking
          all <lb/>Night, with ſome Officers belonging to a Gar- <lb/>riſon, with whom they had all
          the freedom <lb/>of her Body they could deſire, and ſhe go- <lb/>ing Home afterwards in a
          reeling Poſture, <lb/>was taken aſide by ſome Soldiers, who made <lb/>the like uſe of her,
          to the number of thirty <pb n="32"/>
          <lb/>of them, one after another, yet notwith- <lb/>ſtanding all this mighty Heat of
          Action, nei- <lb/>ther the Woman, nor the Men, upon the <lb/>ſtricteſt Enquiry and
          Obſervation that could <lb/>be made, received the leaſt Hurt or Injury. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Theſe Inſtances one would think are ſuffi- <lb/>cient to confute thoſe that believe
          the Vene- <lb/>real Ferment is produced by the Corruption <lb/>of many Seeds, received
          into the Matrix of <lb/>the ſame Woman, and not only do ſuch Au- <lb/>thors contend that
          it does, but alſo aſſert, <lb/>that after thoſe mixt Seeds have bred the Pox <lb/>in her
          Womb, another freſh Man that is <lb/>Sound converſing with her, ſhall carry off <lb/>with
          his Yard that Venereal Ferment, and <lb/>abſolutely free the Woman from the ſame. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>'Tis from this, I ſuppoſe that the Liber- <lb/>tines have a Notion, that when they
          have got <lb/>the Diſtemper, their converſing with a Sound <lb/>Perſon clears them from
          the Diſeaſe; as a <lb/>young Fellow that I Cured of a Clap about <lb/>12 Years ago, or
          more, who being ſent in <lb/>the time of his Cure by his Maſter, to carry <lb/>ſome Goods
          to an Inn with a Country Girl, <lb/><hi rend="italic">a Virgin</hi>, that had bought them
          of him, told <lb/>me himſelf, that he prevail'd with her as they <lb/>went along to go
          into a Houſe to Drink with <lb/>him, and afterwards to let him Debauch her, <lb/>which he
          ſaid he did, and for no other Rea- <lb/>ſon, as he alledg'd, but becauſe he had heard
          <lb/>it would clear him of the Diſtemper; which <lb/>yet was ſo far from having ſuch an
          Effect, <lb/>that it render'd his condition worſe. </p>
        <pb n="33"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Neither is it poſſible (tho' many perſwade <lb/>themſelves to the contrary) to get
          the Ve- <lb/>nereal Diſtemper, by lying with a Woman <lb/>when ſhe has her Monthly Viſits
          upon her, <lb/>for were that likely, how many hundreds of <lb/>Men ſhould we have every
          Day infected? <lb/>there being many that are of ſo hot and un- <lb/>governable a Temper,
          as not to ſpare their <lb/>Wives, even in that, the moſt forbidden <lb/>Seaſon, although
          they may have hear'd (it <lb/>being what ſome Phyſicians and Mid-wives <lb/>aſſert) that
          Children begotten at that Junc- <lb/>ture, moſt commonly are Born either Weak- <lb/>ly, or
          Diſtemper'd; and as ſome ſay (tho' <lb/>without the leaſt parity of Reaſon) Red-
          <lb/>Hair'd. But at thoſe times alſo, as well as at <lb/>other Times and Seaſons, even in
          the moſt <lb/>Amorous Embrace, can it poſſibly procure <lb/>to either of them the foul
          Diſeaſe, (pro- <lb/>vided the Parties be ſound) for the Reaſons <lb/>already alledg'd,
          however ſome others may be <lb/> of a contrary Opinion; an Inſtance of which <lb/>was a
          Man that I not long ſince had in Cure <lb/>for a Clap, who to excuſe his Folly of Ramb-
          <lb/>ling abroad, poſſeſt his Wife, and endeav- <lb/>our'd alſo to amuſe me, that he got
          it by con- <lb/>verſing with her at that Juncture, which the <lb/>poor Credulous Woman
          believ'd, and had no- <lb/>thing more to ſay, but that he might e'en thank <lb/>himſelf,
          it being his own Fault, which was <lb/>indeed too true, tho' ſhe poor Woman at <lb/>the
          ſame time was under a great miſtake. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But tho' neither of theſe laſt mention'd <lb/>ways can produce that Diſeaſe, there is
          yet a <pb n="34"/>
          <lb/>certain way of becoming infected, without <lb/>Carnal Copulation, or attracting it by
          any <lb/>external Means, and that is, by Heredita- <lb/>ry Succeſſion, the Parents Maſs of
          Blood, <lb/>and conſequently Seed's being infected with <lb/>the Venereal Taint at the
          time of the beget- <lb/>ting the Birth, and being connatural with <lb/>the Seminal and
          Sanguine Principles of the <lb/>Body, makes the deepeſt Stain and Tincture, <lb/>and is
          moſt difficult to be fetch out; many <lb/>of which Born with the Diſeaſe upon them <lb/>I
          have had in Cure, and which has prov'd <lb/>very ſtubborn and obdurate, when arriv'd to
          <lb/>the height of Infection; One that juſt now <lb/>occurs to my Memory, among the many
          o- <lb/>thers that I could recollect is as follows. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A young Perſon born of impure Parents, whoſe <lb/>Cure not being look'd after, or
          endeavour'd in <lb/>its Minority, (tho' if it had, might very proba- <lb/>bly have been
          difficultly cured) was, when grown <lb/>up, ſo confirm'd, and the whole Maſs of <lb/>Blood
          and Juices ſo contaminated and ſpoil'd, <lb/>that all the Efforts of Curing were but
          fruit- <lb/>leſly attempted, inſomuch that the Life it <lb/>led, which was to 15 or 16
          Years of Age, <lb/>was a Life of Miſery and Pain, it rotting <lb/>away, as it were, by
          peace-meal; ſome part <lb/>of the Noſe, Cheek and Jaw, beſides the Pa- <lb/>late, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> being conſumed, before it approach- <lb/>ed to the time of
          its deplorable Death: So <lb/>that we may ſee, that the Hereditary Vene- <lb/>real Diſeaſe
          is the worſt to be endured, hardeſt <lb/>to be cured, and is what generally proves the
          <lb/>moſt fatal to the Patient, the malignant Ve- <pb n="35"/>
          <lb/>nom being eſſentially implanted into the very <lb/>nature of the Birth, and is very
          difficulty in <lb/>all, if ever perfectly in any, eradicated and <lb/>cured; and it's to
          be obſerv'd generally, that <lb/>as ſuch hereditary Poxes are harder of Cure, <lb/>ſo the
          Infection in Children born with it, is <lb/>the ſooner and eaſier communicated to the
          <lb/>Nurſes that give them ſuck, and ſtill the <lb/>ſooner convey'd to others that they
          converſe <lb/>with. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I remember I have read ſomewhere of a <lb/>Child that was born thus Diſeaſes, that
          In- <lb/>fected the Nurſe that ſuckl'd it; ſhe not <lb/>knowing any thing of the Matter,
          infected <lb/>her Husband and two Children more that ſhe <lb/>gave ſuck to; thoſe Children
          were no ſoon- <lb/>er taken home, but infected their Mothers, <lb/>their Mothers their
          Husbands; and ſo in <lb/>ſhort no leſs than nine ſeveral Perſons by <lb/>means thereof,
          were infected in the ſpace of <lb/>one Month's time. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But it may objected here by ſome, that <lb/>notwithſtanding the Parents may have the
          <lb/>Diſeaſe upon them, yet Children have been <lb/>begotten and Born ſound and clear from
          any <lb/>Infection or Symptoms thereof; which, may <lb/>be true, as to outward appearance
          at leaſt, <lb/>yet as the Learned and moſt Ingenious Dr. <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Baynard</hi> ſays, the Infection has lain ſmother'd <lb/>in their Bloods; and either
          ſuch Children, <lb/>when grown up have prov'd Sickly and Weak, <lb/>or their Children been
            <hi rend="italic">Rickety</hi>, <hi rend="italic">King's-Evil'd</hi>, <lb/>or <hi
            rend="italic">Conſumptive</hi>; for the <hi rend="italic">Shakes</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">Girds</hi> ſtrong <lb/>Phyſick gives the human Fabrick, [which the <pb
            n="36"/>
          <lb/>Parent under that circumſtance muſt of Ne- <lb/>ceſſity have taken,] cannot but
          looſen ſome <lb/><hi rend="italic">Rivets</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Pins</hi>, as I may
          ſay, that ſhould go to <lb/>the faſtening of the Foundation of his Fami- <lb/>ly. And
          quotes that true ſaying of <hi rend="italic">Galen</hi>, <hi rend="italic">lib: <lb/>de
            ſectis prope finem</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>
          <q rend="italic">Neque impune poſſe adminiſtrari remedia, cum <lb/>omnia præter naturam
            ſint, ob idque naturales fa- <lb/>cultates infestent, nec poſſint adeo morboſas Cau-
            <lb/>ſas reſcindere, q<unclear>u</unclear>in una illis aliquid etiam benig- <lb/>næ
            ſubſtantiæ rapiant. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>Which is in Engliſh <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Neither can thoſe Remedies be adminiſtred <lb/>without harm, ſeeing all things are
          preter- <lb/>natural and for that Reaſon may infeſt the na- <lb/>tural Faculties, nor can
          they ſo reſcind or cut <lb/>off the Morbifick Cauſes, but at the ſame <lb/>time much
          ſnatch away or raviſh along <lb/>with them ſomething of the benign or kind <lb/>Subſtance.
          And this is that, ſays he, which <lb/>cauſes no good Texture in our <hi rend="italic"
            >Off-Spring</hi>. <lb/>Hence the complaints of <hi rend="italic">Mala ſtamina Vitæ</hi>,
          <lb/>when the <hi rend="italic">Web</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Woof</hi> are not well
          <lb/>ſtruck together. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>How many Children, ſays he, have I heard <lb/>(from their bitterneſs of Soul) Curſe
          their <lb/>Parents for begetting them, the wretched <lb/>Heirs apparent to <hi
            rend="italic">Pills</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Potions</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Poſſet-
            <lb/>drink</hi>, dwindling out the ſputtering <hi rend="italic">Snuff</hi> of <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Life</hi>, in Pain and Miſery, and ſpending their <lb/>little Subſtance
          among Phyſick-<hi rend="italic">Harpies</hi>, and <lb/>their ravenous Attendants, <hi
            rend="italic">Nurſes</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Quacks</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Apothecaries</hi>, &amp;c. </p>
        <pb n="37"/>
        <p>
          <lb/>Were I, ſays he, a young <hi rend="italic">Woman</hi>, I think I <lb/>ſhou'd very
          well be acquainted with my Man, <lb/>and his <hi rend="italic">Manners too</hi>, e'er I
          ventur'd on the <lb/>Voyage-Life, in the Ship Matrimony; and <lb/><hi rend="italic">é
            contrario</hi>, the Man ſometimes has been <lb/>Ship-Wreck'd on as <hi rend="italic"
            >Rotten a Bottom <hi rend="roman">&amp;c.</hi></hi> for <lb/><hi rend="italic">Non
            ſemper Inferius, ſicut ſuperius</hi>. </p>
        <lg rend="italic  space">
          <l rend="indent"><lb/>One may look <hi rend="roman">Brisk</hi>, with <hi rend="roman"
              >Cherry-Cheek</hi>, </l>
          <l><lb/>And yet below-<hi rend="roman">Stairs</hi> very Weak. </l>
          <l><lb/>That Woman's in a doubtful Caſe </l>
          <l><lb/>That builds her hopes upon a <hi rend="roman">Face</hi>; </l>
          <l><lb/>As One was cheated when ſhe Choſe </l>
          <l><lb/>A <hi rend="roman">Husband</hi> by the length of's <hi rend="roman">Noſe</hi>.
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>But I go on. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>There is yet another way of getting the <lb/>Infection, without carnal Copulation, or
          by <lb/>hereditary communication, and which has <lb/>been but very little taken notice of
          by Au- <lb/>thors, by ſome indeed judg'd unlikely; but <lb/>the Account I am going to give
          will make the <lb/>contrary manifeſt; the way I mean is by on- <lb/>ly a ſuperficial
          contact or meer touch with <lb/>the Privities, the Man no more than placing <lb/>the
          erected <hi rend="italic">Yard</hi> to the Womans <hi rend="italic">Labia</hi>,
          <lb/>without the leaſt entrance into her Body, <lb/>which wanton and luſtful Dalliance,
          have not- <lb/>withſtanding their imagin'd Safety, prov'd <lb/>of bad preſage to numbers;
          the Pocky Steams <lb/>of the diſeaſed Woman having by means <lb/>thereof, as effectually
          imprinted their malig- <lb/>nant Miaſms on the Genitals of thoſe Wary <lb/>Gentlemen, as
          if they had purſued a cloſe <lb/>Engagement, ſome Inſtances of which I have <pb n="38"/>
          <lb/>met with, and could divertingly enough relate; <lb/>but they being too tedious to be
          particu- <lb/>lariz'd in this place, ſhall only take notice <lb/>of two or three which
          happen'd very lately, <lb/>and reſerve the remainder for the Treatiſe <lb/>intended. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>An Apprentice that had the Venereal Di- <lb/>ſtemper, importun'd the Servant-Maid in
          <lb/>the Houſe, (who was a Virgin) upon the <lb/>promiſe of Marriage to let him lie with
          her, <lb/>he aſſuring her that by what he had learnt <lb/>by reading ſome Phyſick Books,
          he could ſo <lb/>order the Matter as that it ſhould be great <lb/>pleaſure to them both,
          and yet he would <lb/>not get her with Child, (a great Belly being <lb/>moſt ſhe fear'd)
          to which at length ſhe con- <lb/>ſented, not in the leaſt imagining him to <lb/>have the
          Diſtemper; but how far the <lb/>Thuoghts of his Condition might reſtrain <lb/>him from a
          cloſe Engagement I know not, <lb/>but when ſhe came to me to be cured of a <lb/>ſore
          Throat, which ſhe ſaid ſhe had gotten <lb/>by Cold, obſerving her to be Hoarſe, and
          <lb/>finding upon Inſpection there were foul Ul- <lb/>cers upon the <hi rend="italic"
            >Uvula</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tonſils</hi>, I ſuſpected <lb/>her Condition, and
          charg'd her with having <lb/>the Diſtemper, which, after ſome denial, ſhe <lb/>confeſs'd,
          and related the whole Story. But <lb/>that which ſeem'd very much to pleaſe and
          <lb/>comfort her under this melancholly Diſaſter, <lb/>was, that ſhe neither was with
          Child, nor <lb/>ſo much as had parted with her Virginity, <lb/>ſhe declaring that he was
          ſo far from eject- <lb/>ing any Seed into her Body, that he did <pb n="39"/>
          <lb/>not enter her any farther than the <hi rend="italic">Labia</hi>, <lb/>which upon ſome
          Queſtions that I ask'd her, <lb/>and further Aſſurances ſhe gave me, I was <lb/>almoſt
          ready to believe; but when I again <lb/>conſider'd the unlikelineſs thereof, I could
          <lb/>not but be of a contrary Mind, and con- <lb/>cluded that he might either emit Seed
          in- <lb/>to the <hi rend="italic">Uterus</hi> and not get her with Child, <lb/>or not emit
          into her, and ſo eſcape, notwith- <lb/>ſtanding by either of which means he might
          <lb/>give her the Diſeaſe; but otherwiſe I <lb/>cannot believe, nor that ſhe retains her
          <lb/>Virginity whatever ſhe may fancy; for a <lb/>ſmall Running and heat of Urine ſhe told
          <lb/>me ſhe had, and the Ulcers in her Throat <lb/>as aforeſaid were viſible, ſo that ſhe
          was <lb/>both Poxt and Clapt together, and without <lb/>doubt no Virgin. This Perſon I
          cured, and <lb/>ſhe remains now in as good a ſtate of Health <lb/>as any one can enjoy. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Another that I think neceſſary to take <lb/>notice of, was a Man that upon going to
          <lb/>converſe with a Woman, that he had pickt <lb/>up in the Street, found her Body wet,
          and <lb/>fearing the harm, retreated, after he had <lb/>juſt toucht her with his Yard, and
          contented <lb/>himſelf with the accommodation ſhe was <lb/>capable of affording him by her
          Hand, and <lb/>diſmiſs'd her; the next Morning when he <lb/>aroſe, he found a great pain
          in his Back, <lb/>and ſoon after in his Yard, with a redneſs; <lb/>upon which he applies
          to a Surgeon, who <lb/>in the ſpace of three Weeks or a Month <lb/>left him as he found
          him, or rather worſe: <pb n="40"/>
          <lb/>He goes then to another Surgeon, who in <lb/>about the ſame compaſs of time, afforded
          <lb/>him likewiſe no Relief; and finding he could <lb/>not cure him, told him at laſt he
          ail'd no- <lb/>thing, and that he was ſure there was no- <lb/>thing in it, and that he had
          not the Diſtem- <lb/>per; but meeting with my Book he comes <lb/>from him to me: I told
          him by his Complaints <lb/>he certainly was infected, and put him into a <lb/>method of
          Cure; upon taking of the Medi- <lb/>cines other Symptoms appear'd, which the <lb/>more
          confirmed me that his condition was as <lb/>I ſaid, which to be ſure it was, and of which
          <lb/>in ſome time after I cured him, and he re- <lb/>mains now as perfectly well as ever
          in his <lb/>Life. </p>
        <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="55"/>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="408"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
