<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: The virtues and excellency of the American tobacco
          plant</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">The virtues and excellency of the American tobacco plant, for cure of
              diseases, and preservation of health: and the noxious qualities of the tobacco growing
              in Northern countries</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T96718</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T96718"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for R. Parker, at the Unicorn under the Royal-Exchange;
                  and sold by J. Morphew near Stationers-Hall. 1712. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1712</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="15"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3308704520</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K077880.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: medicine"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front> </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_2" n="3"/>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>Two horizontal lines, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>THE <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">VIRTUES</hi>
        <lb/>AND <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">EXCELLENCY</hi>
        <lb/>OF THE <lb/><hi rend="italic">American</hi> Tobacco Plant. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HE Diſcovery and Con- <lb/>queſt of <hi rend="italic"
          >America</hi> by the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Spaniards</hi>, enrich'd <hi rend="italic"
          >Europe</hi>
        <lb/>with not only vaſt Treaſures of <lb/>Gold and Silver, but alſo diſco- <lb/>ver'd and
        furniſh'd us with (per- <lb/>
        <pb xml:id="page_3" n="4"/>
        <lb/>haps) much more uſeful and valu- <lb/>able things; to wit, many excel- <lb/>lent
        Specific Remedies, for the <lb/>Cure of Diſeaſes, and Preſervation <lb/>of Health. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Nature had been ſo kind to the <lb/>poor ignorant Natives of that Coun- <lb/>try, as to
        direct them to, and Ex- <lb/>perience taught them, the peculiar <lb/>Virtues of many Herbs,
        Roots, <lb/>Plants, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> growing amongſt them, <lb/>and how to
        apply them. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The Learned Phyſicians in no <lb/>Age had ever the Knowledge of a <lb/>more celebrated
        Specific Remedy <lb/>for any Diſtemper, than we in this <lb/>laſt have found the <hi
          rend="italic">Peruvian</hi> Bark <lb/>to be, for a never failing and ſud- <lb/>den Cure of
        Intermitting Fevers <lb/>and Agues: And to which alone, <lb/>ſince it has been generally
        us'd, <pb xml:id="page_4" n="5"/>
        <lb/>more Lives have been owing, than <lb/>to any other Medicine whatſoever. <lb/>So
        wonderful is it in its Operation, <lb/>that it looks almoſt like a Charm. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>But above all, their Tobacco <lb/>Plant deſerves to be plac'd in the <lb/>firſt Rank,
        for its many amicable <lb/>Qualities and Uſefulneſs to Human <lb/>Bodies, for the Cure of
        ſeveral <lb/>Diſtempers, Preſervation of Health, <lb/>and Prolongation of Life. Beſides
        <lb/>the agreeable Diverſion and Enter- <lb/>tainment it affords to thoſe that <lb/>uſe it.
        The <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> by their plen- <lb/>tiful Smoaking and Chawing it,
        <lb/>find great Relief for their inward <lb/>Diſeaſes: And in caſe of Wounds <lb/>or Ulcers,
          <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> they apply the <lb/>Leaf, which eats away the proud
        <lb/>Fleſh, and inclines the Sore to <lb/>heal. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_5" n="6"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It is an Opiat to thoſe that are <lb/>in Pain, makes the Poor forget <lb/>their
        Neceſſities, ſupplies Food to <lb/>the Hungry, making them bear <lb/>the Want of it eaſily.
        It is well <lb/>known how Armies have been en- <lb/>abled to undergo tedious Marches,
        <lb/>and Seamen long Voyages, with <lb/>hardly any other Proviſion, when <lb/>well ſupply'd
        with this. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It is endued with a Salutiferous <lb/>Sulphur, and hath alſo a Narcotic <lb/>compoſing
        Quality, which gives <lb/>Eaſe, Refreſhment, and Tranqui- <lb/>lity both to the Body and
        Mind <lb/>Inſomuch that it may ſeem to re- <lb/>ſemble the Famous Herb mention- <lb/>ed by
          <hi rend="italic">Homer</hi>, that had the Power to <lb/>turn Sadneſs into Joy. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_6" n="7"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The frequent Smoaking of To- <lb/>bacco diſcharges Phlegm and other <lb/>watry peccant
        Humours out of the <lb/>Glands. It removes Obſtructions <lb/>in the Veſſels, by diſſolving
        the <lb/>coagulated Juices: It promotes a <lb/>due Circulation of the Blood, and <lb/>a free
        Perſpiration, thro' the Pores <lb/>of the whole Body, ſo neceſſary to <lb/>Health. It not
        only purges the <lb/>Head, but with very many, ope- <lb/>rates downwards, rendring the
        <lb/>Bowels ſoluble, whereby coſtive <lb/>Conſtitutions find great Benefit. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It deſtroys Worms in Human <lb/>Bodies, and is likewiſe by Experi- <lb/>ence found to
        be a Remedy againſt <lb/>Leproſies, Scurvy and Itch. To <lb/>which the Poor (heretofore)
        inha- <lb/>biting the Sea-Coaſt of this Iſland, <lb/>were by their Eating too much Fiſh <pb
          xml:id="page_7" n="8"/>
        <lb/>very much ſubject: But ſince the <lb/>ſmoaking of Tobacco came to be <lb/>much in Uſe
        among them, they <lb/>have been totally free from. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Chawing Tobacco is by many <lb/>prefer'd to Smoaking it, as being a <lb/>greater Drain,
        and communicating <lb/>its Virtues and Warmth more effe- <lb/>ctually to the Stomach and
        Brain; <lb/>preſerving the Teeth, killing the <lb/>Worms, and altering the Juices <lb/>that
        occaſion Pain and Rottenneſs <lb/>in them<choice>
          <sic> </sic>
          <corr>.</corr>
        </choice>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>By the Chawing it, the Glands <lb/>of the Jaws, Throat and Veſſels <lb/>being
        continually mov'd and com- <lb/>preſs'd, diſmiſs or ſpue out great <lb/>Quantities of Rheum,
        the Cauſe <lb/>of Defluctions, Coughs, Catarrhs <lb/>and Conſumptions. It communi-
        <lb/>cates alſo a certain Impulſe to the <pb xml:id="page_8" n="9"/>
        <lb/>Membranes of the Lungs, which <lb/>helps their Diſcharge of vicious <lb/>Phlegm and
        other Matter, apt to <lb/>breed Ulcers, Aſtma's, and other <lb/>Diſtempers. It's obſerv'd by
        many, <lb/>That thoſe who from their Youth <lb/>have been accuſtom'd to chaw To- <lb/>bacco,
        are never afflicted (or at <lb/>leaſt very rarely) with Gout, Rheu- <lb/>matiſms, Scurvy, or
        Tooth-ach, <lb/>which proceeds from an Acrimony <lb/>in the Blood or Juices, that this
        <lb/>Plant wonderfully helps to correct <lb/>and ſweeten. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>As Smoaking and Chawing of <lb/>Tobacco, by Experience, is found <lb/>to have theſe
        good Effects; ſo the <lb/>uſing it by way of Snuff is bene- <lb/>ficial, as well as
        diverting, to many <lb/>Perſons, (eſpecially to ſuch as have <lb/>weak Eyes, affected with
        too <lb/>much Moiſture.) By its gently <pb xml:id="page_9" n="10"/>
        <lb/>pricking and ſtimulating the Mem- <lb/>branes, it cauſes Sneezing or Con-
        <lb/>tractions, whereby the Glands and <lb/>Channels, like ſo many ſqueez'd <lb/>Sponges,
        diſmiſs their Seroſities <lb/>and Filth. And as it ſerves for a <lb/>Drain to exceſſive
        Moiſture in the <lb/>Eyes or Head; ſo when a ſufficient <lb/>Moiſture is wanting, its quick
        and <lb/>noble Spirit opens the Veſſels that <lb/>afford Supplies thereto; and pure
        <lb/>Snuff put into the Corners of the <lb/>Eyes is found to alter and deſtroy <lb/>the
        ſharp Humours that occaſion <lb/>Bloodſhot, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> So beneficial is
        this <lb/>Powder for the Preſervation of that <lb/>moſt dear and valuable of all our
        <lb/>Senſes, the Sight. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>But Care ought to be taken, <lb/>That the Snuff made uſe of in all <lb/>theſe Caſes be
        made of only pure <lb/>clean Tobacco Leaves, without <pb xml:id="page_10" n="11"/>
        <lb/>any Mixture of Stiptic Earths, or <lb/>Rotten Wood, which Common <lb/>Snuff-makers put
        thereto to dea- <lb/>den, colour, or elſe encreaſe the <lb/>Quantity. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Tobacco alſo is often a Remedy <lb/>for Deafneſs, by putting a Drop <lb/>of its Oyl
        into the Ear with Cotton <lb/>Wool. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>But its moſt uſeful and excellent <lb/>Quality is ſtill to be mention'd; <lb/>to wit,
        That it is the moſt ſove- <lb/>reign Antidote and greateſt Preſer- <lb/>vative againſt the
        Plague, or other <lb/>peſtilential Diſeaſes; the Small- <lb/>Pox, or other Infection. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Turks</hi> and others, among <lb/>whom the Plague often rages,
        have <lb/>recourſe to nothing more effectual to <lb/>avoid it, than conſtant Smoaking of <pb
          xml:id="page_11" n="12"/>
        <lb/>Tobacco, Chawing, Snuffing, and <lb/>burning it in their Rooms and <lb/>Streets; and
        when the Peſti- <lb/>lence is among them, many ſtuff <lb/>their Bedding and Pillows with it.
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> where it grows hang <lb/>it about their Necks, and
        are ſel- <lb/>dom ſeen without a Pipe in their <lb/>Hand. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>When the Plague raged ſo vio- <lb/>lently in <hi rend="italic">London,</hi> in the Year
        1665. <lb/>it's well known to many now living, <lb/>how very few it ſeized of thoſe that
        <lb/>were conſtant Smoakers and Chaw- <lb/>ers of Tobacco: And what was <lb/>more
        remarkable, not any of thoſe <lb/>poor People, whoſe Employment <lb/>was to manufacture,
        roll, or cut <lb/>Tobacco, of which there were many <lb/>Hundreds at work in ſeveral
        <lb/>Houſes within this City, were in- <lb/>fected. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_12" n="13"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>By theſe and many other Inſtan- <lb/>ces which might be given, it is <lb/>evident, that
        Tobacco wonderfully <lb/>helps to purify the Air, and pre- <lb/>vent Infection; ſo that it
        were <lb/>very much to be wiſh'd, that in <lb/>time of Peſtilence and other infe-
        <lb/>ctious Diſtempers, the Rich would <lb/>be ſo charitable, as to ſupply the <lb/>Poor
        with great Stores of this moſt <lb/>uſeful Drug, and ſovereign Anti- <lb/>dote in ſuch
        Caſes; which may be <lb/>a Means to put a ſtop to the raging <lb/>of ſuch Diſtempers, and
        preſerve <lb/>whole Families. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>But it is to be noted, there are <lb/>many ſorts and degrees of Tobacco <lb/>Plants;
        and thoſe highly prefera- <lb/>ble, which grow in Climates and <lb/>Soils natural to them,
        having a <pb xml:id="page_13" n="14"/>
        <lb/>light Earth and warm Sun, which <lb/>gives that noble Flavour, Strength <lb/>and Virtue
        to that Tobacco produc'd <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">Brazil, New-Spain, Virginia</hi> and
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Mary-land</hi>: Whereas that Plant <lb/>raiſed in Northern Regions
        (where <lb/>Tobacco-Plantations have of late <lb/>mightily increaſed) has not only a
        <lb/>faint, earthy Taſte and Smell, but <lb/>is alſo very unwholſom and perni- <lb/>cious to
        thoſe that uſe it. Inſtead <lb/>of preſerving, it deſtroys Health; <lb/>which though not ſo
        immediately <lb/>and ſenſibly felt by poor People of <lb/>ſtrong and robuſt Conſtitutions,
        yet <lb/>it is certainly ſo much Poiſon ſuck'd <lb/>into their Veins, which by Degrees
        <lb/>conſumes the Body, and often im- <lb/>mediately cauſes Vomitings, Ver- <lb/>tigo's and
        Convulſions. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_14" n="15"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>To conclude, All Perſons who <lb/>love long Life and Health, will <lb/>daily have
        Recourſe to the <hi rend="italic">Ameri- <lb/>can</hi> Tobacco, as a noble Remedy; <lb/>and
        ſhun that of the <hi rend="italic">European</hi>
        <lb/>Growth, as Poiſon. </p>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <trailer rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
