<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - M. M.: A short historical account of the several kinds of worms
          breeding in human bodies</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>M. M.</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">A short historical account of the several kinds of worms breeding in
              human bodies: extracted from the writings of the most eminent authors. With a
              particular description of their symptoms, and the most approved remedies for their
              expulsion.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">N22775</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N22775"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed by B. Mills, and sold by J. Baker, and T. Warner, at the
                  Black-Boy in Pater-Noster-Row, 1716.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1716</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="63"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">National Library of Medicine</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3308121860</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K013252.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: disease"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front> </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2" n="3"/>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal floral ornament, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>A SHORT <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">Hiſtorical Account</hi>
          <lb/>Of the ſeveral Kinds of <lb/><hi rend="size(3.0)">WORMS</hi>
          <lb/>Breeding in <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">Human Bodies, <hi rend="italic"
            >&amp;c.</hi></hi>
        </head>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <div n="1" type="chapter">
          <head rend="space align-center italic">
            <lb/><hi rend="sc">Chap</hi>. <hi rend="roman">I.</hi>
            <lb/>Of the Breeding of <hi rend="roman">Worms</hi> in <lb/>Human Bodies. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HAT our Bodies ſhould become <lb/>the Prey of <hi
              rend="italic">Worms,</hi> when they are <lb/>returning to their Original Duſt,
            <lb/>might be ſubmitted to without Regret; but <lb/>to be ſeiz'd on before that time,
            and even <pb xml:id="page_3" n="4"/>
            <lb/>upon our very Entrance on Life, that In- <lb/>fant Innocence ſhould ſuſtain the
            Fate of the <lb/>Profane <hi rend="italic">Prometheus,</hi> in having their tender
            <lb/>Bowels corroded by theſe Inteſtine Vultures, <lb/>is a Condition exceedingly
            deplorable, and <lb/>yet ſo very frequent, that 'tis almoſt always <lb/>ſuſpected in
            Children on every Diſorder, <lb/>and not unjuſtly; ſince, as <hi rend="italic"
              >Platerus</hi> obſerves, <lb/>few Perſons are free from <hi rend="italic">Worms;</hi>
            and Ex- <lb/>perience verifies the Obſervation in the Diſ- <lb/>ſection of Dead Bodies. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hippocrates</hi> has aſſur'd us, That unborn <lb/>Infants are
            invaded by them; and <hi rend="italic">Dolæus</hi> in <lb/>Diſſecting an Infant, which
            dy'd as ſoon as <lb/>born, tells us, he found a Cluſter of <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>
            <lb/>in its Bowels. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The Phyſicians and Philoſophers of former <lb/>Ages, had a very ſhort and eaſy Way
            of <lb/>Accounting for the Generation of Inſects, by <lb/>ſuppoſing them bred of
            themſelves, out of <lb/>ſome putrefying Matter, by the Aſſiſtance <lb/>of Heat or
            Motion. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>But this Account is now juſtly rejected, <lb/>as extreamly Abſurd and Unreaſonable,
            by <lb/>thoſe, who have been the leaſt acquainted <lb/>with the great and ſurprizing
            Diſcoveries of <lb/>the Modern Philoſophers; who, by the Aſ- <lb/>ſiſtance of
            Microſcopes (an Advantage un- <pb xml:id="page_4" n="5"/>
            <lb/>known to former Ages) have found, that <lb/>the minuteſt Inſects are furniſh'd with
            all <lb/>the Parts that are neceſſary, not only for <lb/>Life, but alſo for the
            Propagation of their <lb/>ſeveral Kinds, as perfect as in larger Ani- <lb/>mals; and
            conſequently, are not produc'd <lb/>at Random; but are the regular Off-ſpring <lb/>of
            Parents of the ſame Kind, no leſs than <lb/>others. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>It's obſervable, that Nature's wiſe Au- <lb/>thor has given ſuch a Propenſion to
            thoſe <lb/>Creatures, who cannot bring up their Pro- <lb/>geny, to lay their Eggs in
            Places proper to <lb/>breed them. Thus Flies commonly drop <lb/>theirs in <hi
              rend="italic">dead Bodies</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Puſtles</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
              >Ulcers</hi>, &amp;c. <lb/>becauſe in ſuch tender Parts their Eggs may <lb/>lie eaſy,
            and find Warmth ſufficient to <lb/>hatch them; and afterwards, Humidity and <lb/>Food
            for the Nouriſhment of the Animal. <lb/>An Inſtance of this is related by Mr. <hi
              rend="italic">de la <lb/>Croſs</hi>, in his <hi rend="italic">Memoirs, p.</hi> 229. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>A <hi rend="italic">Dutch</hi> Woman had her Leg ſwoln and <lb/>glandulous, about a
            Span from the Knee; <lb/>the Chyrurgion, who had it in Cure, to <lb/>know the Cauſe of
            the Diſeaſe, took off <lb/>this glandulous Body to the Bigneſs of a <lb/>Nail, waſh'd it
            in Brandy, cut it, and per- <lb/>ceiv'd therein a great many little <hi rend="italic"
              >Worms</hi>; <lb/>whereupon, having conſulted Mr. <hi rend="italic">Leeuwen- <pb
                xml:id="page_5" n="6"/>
              <lb/>hoeck</hi>, he affirm'd, they were come from <lb/>the Eggs, which a Fly had lain
            in the mor- <lb/>tify'd Part, as he prov'd in the following <lb/>Manner; He put theſe
              <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> into a Box, <lb/>with a Piece of raw Beef, which was ſoon
            <lb/>conſum'd by them, as well as the glandu- <lb/>lous Body, wherein they were hatch'd;
            He <lb/>fed them three ſeveral times, and five Days <lb/>after, <hi rend="italic">viz.
              July</hi> 31, he found his Box empty; <lb/>but having look'd carefully about the Room,
            <lb/>he recover'd ſome of theſe <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>, that <lb/>would eat no
            more, and were already grown <lb/>to the length of ones Nail: He put them <lb/>on a
            Paper, cover'd with a large Glaſs; <lb/>and the next Day, in the Morning, he ob-
            <lb/>ſerv'd one of theſe <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> ſhortned, but <lb/>encreas'd a
            third Part in Bulk, ſo that it <lb/>had ſomething of the ſhape of a Tun: In <lb/>the
            Evening, he perceiv'd four others in <lb/>the ſame Poſture, which from White became
            <lb/>Red. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Aug.</hi> 11. The Cods of theſe <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> were
            <lb/>all black, he open'd one of them, whence <lb/>he took out a perfect Fly, that was
            yet wet <lb/>and motionleſs: He obſerv'd, that beſides <lb/>the Cod, this Inſect was
            wrap'd up in a <lb/>very thin Membrane. He open'd this un- <lb/>timely Fly, and found a
            great quantity of <lb/>Eggs in its Body. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_6" n="7"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Aug.</hi> 15. All the Flies inclos'd in the Glaſs <lb/>were
            hatch'd, and at the ſame time he per- <lb/>ceiv'd other Flies againſt the Glaſs-Windows
            <lb/>of his Chamber, which he had ſuppos'd to <lb/>have come from thoſe <hi
              rend="italic">Worms</hi>, which he had <lb/>not retriev'd. In feeding theſe Infects,
            moſt <lb/>part dy'd, or fled away: So that, <hi rend="italic">Sept.</hi> 7. he <lb/>had
            but Two left, that were probably Male <lb/>and Female, for they laid 145 Eggs; ſome
            <lb/>of which he caus'd to be hatch'd in leſs than <lb/>24 Hours, by carrying them in
            his Pocket, <lb/>ſhut up in a Box. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The Learn'd <hi rend="italic">Baglivi,</hi> Phyſician at <hi rend="italic"
              >Rome,</hi>
            <lb/>in a Letter to Mr. <hi rend="italic">Andry</hi> at <hi rend="italic">Paris,</hi>
            writes thus <lb/>concerning the Breeding of <hi rend="italic">Worms.</hi> The
            <lb/>Beginning and Original of all Animals and <lb/>Vegetables is from an Egg; for what
            elſe <lb/>are the Seeds of Plants but Eggs, in which <lb/>all the Rudiments of the
            future Plant are <lb/>contracted, as it were, into a ſhort Compen- <lb/>dium? And thoſe,
            by Virtue of the Fermen- <lb/>tation of the Nutritive Juice, by the Ela- <lb/>ſtick
            Power of the Air, and the double <lb/>Warmth, one of the Sun, and the other of <lb/>the
            central Warmth of the Earth, the great <lb/>Mother of all, are uncover'd by little and
            <lb/>little; and their Fetters being as it were <lb/>loos'd, they grow, and arrive in
            due time <lb/>to ſuch a Bulk, as great as is allotted to every <lb/>ſort of Plant by the
            Laws of Nature. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_7" n="8"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If all Philoſophers and Phyſicians think <lb/>thus concerning Vegetables, much more
            <lb/>muſt they think ſo of living Creatures, not <lb/>only of thoſe that are call'd
            Perfect, but of <lb/>the Imperfect alſo, which are commonly <lb/>call'd Inſects. For
            beſides, that there is the <lb/>ſame equal Order in all Things, and that <lb/>all come
            from one Principle, and after a cer- <lb/>tain general Circuit, end all in one again;
            <lb/>Inſects, by an admirable Connexion and <lb/>Conſtruction of Parts, and by a more
            no- <lb/>ble Exerciſe of vital Operations, do not only, <lb/>in no wiſe, give place to
            Plants, but far excel <lb/>them. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Wherefore, ſince no Man ſays that Plants <lb/>riſe from Putrefaction, they ought
            not in <lb/>Reaſon to deduce the Original of Inſects, <lb/>and other baſer Animals from
            thence. For <lb/>'tis a ſhame to Philoſophers and Phyſicians, <lb/>in this moſt happy
            Age of Sciences, where- <lb/>in the Cauſes of Things are illuſtrated by
            <lb/>Experiments, and ſolid Precepts of the Ma- <lb/>thematicks, to aſcribe to the
            fortuitous <lb/>Chance of Putrefaction, that which the con- <lb/>ſtant and perpetual Law
            of Nature, remain- <lb/>ing in its Seeds, rules and directs. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>For 'tis not Putrefaction that produces im- <lb/>perfect living Creatures, but the
            Heat and <lb/>Fermentation of the Things putrefying, that <pb xml:id="page_8" n="9"/>
            <lb/>makes fruitful the Seeds of Things ſpread <lb/>all over the World, if I may be
            allow'd ſo <lb/>to ſpeak; or rather, it ſtirs up, and revives <lb/>the imperceptible
            Parts of the future living <lb/>Creature in the Egg; and, as it were, in- <lb/>ſpires
            'em with the firſt Life, in the ſame <lb/>manner with the Heat of the Sun, or that
            <lb/>of brooding Hens. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>What we have ſaid of Inſects in gene- <lb/>ral, may be aptly apply'd to the <hi
              rend="italic">Worms</hi>
            <lb/>bred in Human Bodies, ſeeing they are not <lb/>generated by putrefying Humours; but
            the <lb/>Worms Eggs lying hid in the Inteſtines, are <lb/>enliven'd, and brought forth
            by the ſame <lb/>Means. </p>
        </div>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <div n="2" type="chapter">
          <head rend="align-center sc space">
            <lb/>Chap. II. </head>
          <head rend="space align-center italic">
            <lb/>Of the ſeveral Kinds of <hi rend="roman">Worms</hi>
            <lb/>bred in Human Bodies. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HESE pernicious Animals differ <lb/>greatly, not only among
            themſelves, <lb/>as to Shape, and other Circumſtances; but <lb/>alſo in reſpect of the
            ſeveral Parts of the <pb xml:id="page_9" n="10"/>
            <lb/>Body they poſſeſs, and whence they receive <lb/>their Denomination. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Thus the <hi rend="italic">Cephalick</hi> breed in the Head, <lb/>where they
            occaſion violent Pains, Diſtra- <lb/>ctions, and ſometimes contagious Diſtem- <lb/>pers;
              <hi rend="italic">Sennertus</hi> mentions a Perſon afflicted <lb/>with an Head-Ach
            violent to Diſtraction; <lb/>when after ſeven Days Continuance, and the <lb/>Patient
            almoſt dead with the Pain, a <hi rend="italic">Worm</hi>
            <lb/>came out of his right Noſtril, above a Span <lb/>long, after which he ſoon
            recover'd. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Andry</hi> ſays, he knew a Man, who <lb/>being cur'd of a <hi
              rend="italic">Venereal Diſeaſe,</hi> complain'd <lb/>afterwards of an unſufferable
            Pain in his <lb/>Head; for which his Skull was trepan'd, <lb/>and a little ſhort <hi
              rend="italic">Worm</hi> was found upon the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Dura-mater;</hi>
            which being taken out, the Pa- <lb/>tient recover'd a perſect Health. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Such another Caſe is related by <hi rend="italic">Foreſtus</hi>, <lb/>only the <hi
              rend="italic">Worm</hi> he ſpeaks of was Black. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hild-ſheim</hi> tells of a Perſon, who voided <lb/>Thirteen long
              <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> alive, and Woolly <lb/>like a <hi rend="italic"
              >Caterpiller</hi> from his Noſtrils, Ears and <lb/>Mouth. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">C. Gemma</hi> reports of a Matron dying of a <lb/>Peſtilential
            Fever, whoſe Head being open'd, <pb xml:id="page_10" n="11"/>
            <lb/>there appear'd abundance of <hi rend="italic">Worms,</hi> both <lb/>in the
            Subſtance of the Brain, and between <lb/>the Coverings, and alſo Swarms of Inſects
            <lb/>like <hi rend="italic">Bugs</hi>. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>But the Account which <hi rend="italic">F. Angelinus</hi> ſent <lb/>his Friend is
            wonderful, concerning a Perſon <lb/>who had an Epidemical Fever, and was <lb/>reſtleſs
            eight Nights; when, upon his Re- <lb/>covery, he was troubled with an Itching in
            <lb/>his right Noſtril; and ſoon after there came <lb/>out of it a <hi rend="italic"
              >Worm</hi> as long as ones little Fin- <lb/>ger, its Body thick and red, its Head
            black <lb/>and hard, with two ſharp Arms like thoſe <lb/>of a <hi rend="italic"
              >Scorpion</hi>; ſix Feet towards the Head, <lb/>and ſome ſmall ones towards the Tail,
            on <lb/>which it walk'd very briskly; it liv'd four <lb/>Days without Food. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Kerckingius</hi> in his Anatomical Obſervations, <lb/>gives us
            the Figure of an Hairy horn'd <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worm,</hi> which came out of the
            Noſtril of a <lb/>Woman at <hi rend="italic">Amſterdam</hi>, on the 21ſt of <hi
              rend="italic">Sept.</hi>
            <lb/>1688. which he kept alive 'till the 3d of <lb/><hi rend="italic">October,</hi>
            without giving it any Food: And <lb/>which is very Remarkable, it brought forth
            <lb/>another <hi rend="italic">Worm</hi> before it dy'd. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>A Peſtilential Fever rag'd at <hi rend="italic">Beneventum</hi>, <lb/>and ſwept off
            abundance of People; at length <lb/>the Phyſicians opening the Head of one that <pb
              xml:id="page_11" n="12"/>
            <lb/>dy'd of it, found a little live <hi rend="italic">Worm</hi> very <lb/>ſhort, and
            all over red; and having try'd <lb/>ſeveral Things to kill it, found nothing ef-
            <lb/>fectual but the Decoction of <hi rend="italic">Radiſhes</hi> in <lb/><hi
              rend="italic">Malmſey</hi> Wine, which was no ſooner pour'd <lb/>on the <hi
              rend="italic">Worm</hi> but it dy'd; after which they <lb/>adminiſtred the ſame Remedy
            to all their <lb/>Patients, and almoſt all recover'd. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Schenckius</hi> alſo relates, That in the Year <lb/>1571. an
            Epidemical Fever rag'd in <hi rend="italic">Ancona</hi>, <lb/>which caus'd a furious
            Giddineſs, and Death <lb/>on the third or fourth Day. All the Phyſi- <lb/>cians of the
            Place confeſs'd they did not <lb/>underſtand the Diſeaſe, and conſequently <lb/>knew not
            how to cure it. A rich young <lb/>Man finding a Periodical Pain beginning in <lb/>his
            Head, became apprehenſive of being <lb/>ſeiz'd with the Diſtemper; and being fright-
            <lb/>ed by the ingenuous Acknowledgment of <lb/>the Phyſicians, left the Country, and
            went <lb/>to <hi rend="italic">Venice</hi>; where calling for a Conſultation <lb/>of the
            moſt Learned Phyſicians, one of them <lb/>aſſerted, that a <hi rend="italic">Worm</hi>
            in the Brain was the <lb/>occaſion of thoſe Periodical Pains, which <lb/>were ſo violent
            in the Paroxyſm, without <lb/>diſturbing his Reaſon or Memory, that it <lb/>ſeem'd as if
            his Head had been bored with <lb/>an Iron. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_12" n="13"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>They adminiſtred ſeveral Things without <lb/>Effect, ſo that he dy'd in three Days
            time <lb/>after his Arrival. They open'd his Head, <lb/>and found on the Right ſide,
            under the <hi rend="italic"> Pia- <lb/>mater</hi> the Head of a <hi rend="italic"
              >Worm,</hi> which by Rea- <lb/>ſon of the cold Air, immediately retir'd in- <lb/>to
            the Subſtance of the Brain. They then <lb/>cut open the Ventricles of the Brain, and
            <lb/>trac'd out the <hi rend="italic">Worm,</hi> which was all over <lb/>Red, as long as
            one's Fore-finger; the <lb/>Head black and pointed, and the Neck <lb/>Hairy. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Amatus Luſit.</hi> took a <hi rend="italic">Worm</hi> out of the
            in- <lb/>ner Corner of a Girl's Eye; 'twas half a <lb/>Span long, white, and alive when
            taken <lb/>out. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Sometimes <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> are found in the Ear, <lb/>as in a Girl of
            Ten Years old, who was <lb/>afflicted with the Evil, and had a violent <lb/>Pain in the
            Right Ear, which ſuppurated <lb/>from time to time, and ſometimes ſhe be- <lb/>came
            Deaf. Mr. <hi rend="italic">Andry</hi>, after a fruitleſs Ap- <lb/>plication of ſeveral
            Remedies, ſuſpected <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worms,</hi> and apply'd an Ointment for that
            <lb/>Purpoſe; whereupon abundance of ſmall <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> came forth,
            they were yellow, long, <lb/>and very ſlender. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_13" n="14"/>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Kerkingius</hi> gives an Account of five <hi rend="italic"
              >Worms,</hi>
            <lb/>which came from a Man's Ear in the Year <lb/>1663. very much like Hog-Lice. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>There are <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> which breed under a <lb/>Cruſt, that covers
            the ſurface of the Teeth. <lb/>They are very ſmall, and have a round Head, <lb/>mark'd
            with a black Point, the other Part <lb/>of their Body being long and ſlender. Theſe
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> corrode the Teeth by degrees, and <lb/>occaſion a
            Stink, but no violent Pain. They <lb/>are call'd <hi rend="italic">Dentarii.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Even the Liver has been obſerv'd to en- <lb/>tertain theſe Inſects, ſo <hi
              rend="italic">Caſper Bauhinus</hi> re- <lb/>lates, That in <hi rend="italic"
              >October</hi> 1578. ſeveral ſmall <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> were found in the
            Liver of a Child <lb/>of two Years of Age, that dy'd of the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >Small-Pox:</hi> They were red, round, ſome- <lb/>what long and ſoft; it ſeem'd
            ſtrange to <lb/>ſeveral Phyſicians, who were preſent at the <lb/>opening: But it may be
            conſider'd, that <lb/>there may be ſeveral Accidents, wherein <lb/>the Gall in the Liver
            may be ſo much al- <lb/>ter'd, as to loſe very much of its Bitter- <lb/>ness, and
            thereby permit the Ingendring of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worms.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>They ſometimes breed in the Heart, oc- <lb/>caſioning violent Pains, Swoonings and
            ſud- <pb xml:id="page_14" n="15"/>
            <lb/>den Death. Thus <hi rend="italic">Sphererius</hi> writes, That <lb/>a <hi
              rend="italic">Florentine</hi> Gentleman diſcourſing one Day <lb/>with a Stranger, in
            the Great Duke of <hi rend="italic"> Tuſ- <lb/>cany</hi>'s Court, drop'd down dead, on a
            ſud- <lb/>den; and his Body being open'd on Suſpi- <lb/>cion of Poiſon, a live <hi
              rend="italic">Worm</hi> was found in the <lb/>Heart. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Pleuriſy</hi> has been often obſerv'd to be <lb/>occaſion'd
            by <hi rend="italic">Worms. Gabucinus</hi> viſited a <lb/>Maid, ſeiz'd with a <hi
              rend="italic">Pleuriſy,</hi> and obſerving <lb/>her cold and hot reciprocally, and in
            her hot <lb/>Fits one of her Cheeks very red, the other <lb/>continuing pale, ſuſpecting
              <hi rend="italic">Worms,</hi> he pre- <lb/>ſcrib'd her a Medicine for that purpoſe,
            <lb/>which brought away a great Number of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worms,</hi> and
            thereupon the <hi rend="italic">Pleuriſy</hi> left <lb/>her. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Several ancient Men, as <hi rend="italic">Quercitan</hi> teſtifies, <lb/>defunct of
              <hi rend="italic">Pleuriſies</hi>, had their Inteſtines full <lb/>of large <hi
              rend="italic">Worms,</hi> which he concluded the <lb/>Cauſe of that Diſtemper. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Loſs,</hi> in his <hi rend="italic">Obſervations,</hi>
            relates ſuch <lb/>a Caſe of a Youth about Fourteen Years of <lb/>Age, of a thin and
            bilious Conſtitution, <lb/>who in a very ſharp Winter, having got- <lb/>ten Cold, was
            ſeiz'd with a true <hi rend="italic">Pleuriſy</hi>, <lb/>attended with a continual
              Fever<unclear>;</unclear> a prick- <lb/>ing Pain in his leſt Breaſt, reaching to his
              <pb xml:id="page_15" n="16"/>
            <lb/>Throat, a difficulty in Breathing, a violent <lb/>Cough, and Spitting of Blood; his
            Body <lb/>was by Intervals cold and hot, with a Red- <lb/>ness in his Cheeks, and a
            great Reſtleſſneſs. <lb/>About the fifth Day of the Diſeaſe, being <lb/>Coſtive, a
            Gliſter of Milk was injected, <lb/>which brought away five <hi rend="italic">Worms,</hi>
            which <lb/>were <hi rend="italic">Teretes;</hi> wherefore with ſome Alte- <lb/>ration of
            the Medicines, which were before <lb/>preſcrib'd, the following Powder was ex-
            <lb/>hibited. </p>
          <p rend="indent italic">
            <lb/>℞ Scord. card. ben. a ℈j Corallin. ℈ij C.C.C.ʒj <lb/>Rhabarb. ℈4 Sal Centuar. ℈j
              <hi rend="roman">Doſe</hi> ʒſs. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>After which <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> came away daily, in <lb/>all above Thirty,
            and he recover'd. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Andry</hi> had ſo remarkable a Caſe of this <lb/>ſort, that
            it put him upon Writing an en- <lb/>tire Book on the Subject of <hi rend="italic"
              >Worms.</hi> The <lb/>Caſe was this, On the 4th of <hi rend="italic">June,</hi> 1698.
            <lb/>a young Man, about Thirty Years of Age, <lb/>was ſeiz'd with a Fever, great Pain in
            his <lb/>Side, Spitting of Blood, and Difficulty of <lb/>Breathing. He began the Cure by
            Opening <lb/>a Vein, and repeated the ſame the next Day, <lb/>on the 3d he ſweated, on
            the 4th he ſeem'd <lb/>to be much better; but from thence to the <lb/>5th he had a <hi
              rend="italic">Delirium</hi>, which went off the <lb/>next Morning. The <hi
              rend="italic">Delirium</hi> not being <pb xml:id="page_16" n="17"/>
            <lb/>preceded by the uſual Signs, occaſion'd a <lb/>Suſpicion of <hi rend="italic"
              >Worms,</hi> and finding withal a <lb/>great many in his Excrements by Stool, <lb/>he
            preſcrib'd a purging Medicine the next <lb/>Morning (which has been very ſucceſsful
            <lb/>in that Caſe) an Hour after the taking it, <lb/>the Patient found ſomething ſtir in
            his Bo- <lb/>dy, which Motion continu'd two Hours, <lb/>and determin'd in the Iſſuing
            forth of a <lb/>live <hi rend="italic">Worm</hi>, or rather Link of <hi rend="italic"
              >Worms,</hi> four <lb/>Ells three Inches in Length, being the <hi rend="italic"> Cu-
              <lb/>curbitini,</hi> which are particularly deſcrib'd, <lb/><hi rend="italic">p.</hi>
            34. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Sometimes we meet with 'em in the <lb/>Blood, where they obſtruct the Orifice in
            <lb/>Bleeding; ſo a Chirurgion at <hi rend="italic">Paris,</hi> whilſt <lb/>he was
            Bleeding a Patient, found the Blood <lb/>ſtop on a ſudden; and turning up the Arm
            <lb/>to find the Cauſe, he ſaw an horned <hi rend="italic">Worm</hi>
            <lb/>as long as an <hi rend="italic">Earwig,</hi> which burſt out with <lb/>Violence
            along with the Blood. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Such another Accident is related by Mr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">de la Croſe,</hi> in
            his <hi rend="italic">Memoirs,</hi> of Mr. <hi rend="italic">du Puy</hi>, <lb/>a <hi
              rend="italic">French</hi> Phyſician; who being preſent at <lb/>the Bleeding of a Lady,
            his Patient, the <lb/>Blood, after it had ſprung out above two <lb/>Ounces, ſtop'd on a
            ſudden; and as he <lb/>was looking for the Cauſe of it, he per- <lb/>ceiv'd an <hi
              rend="italic">Heterogeneous</hi> Body that ſtop'd <pb xml:id="page_17" n="18"/>
            <lb/>the Orifice; whereupon taking the Chirur- <lb/>gion's Forceps, he drew out a <hi
              rend="italic">Worm</hi> as big <lb/>as could come out of the Inciſion. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>He accounts for its coming there in the <lb/>following Manner: The Egg of ſome fly-
            <lb/>ing Inſect had been ſwallow'd by the Pa- <lb/>tient in her Food, and being
            deſcended in- <lb/>to the ſmall Guts, went with the Chile <lb/>into the Milky Veins,
            through all the Pores <lb/>of the filtrating Glandules, the Heart, <lb/>Lungs, Aorta,
            'till arriving at laſt to the <lb/>Extremities or the Fingers, it remain'd <lb/>there
            among their ſmall Arteries and Veins, <lb/>and was hatch'd out by the moſt conve-
            <lb/>nient and natural Heat of the Blood and <lb/>Fleſh. Having thus gotten the Life and
            <lb/>Motion of a <hi rend="italic">Worm,</hi> it ſwam for greater <lb/>Eaſe and Room
            into the Arm; and follow- <lb/>ing ſtill the cheriſhing Liquor, wherein it <lb/>was
            bred, it came at length to the Inci- <lb/>ſion of the Vein, whence Mr. <hi rend="italic"
              >du Pay</hi> ex- <lb/>tracted it. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>They have been often ſeen in the Urine, <lb/>and of various Kinds; ſome like
            Hog-Lice, <lb/>others like Mites in Cheeſe, ſome like <lb/>Leeches, others like
            Graſſ-Hoppers; of <lb/>which laſt ſort was that voided by Count <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >Mansfield,</hi> when he lay ill of a continual <lb/>Fever. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_18" n="19"/>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Vidius</hi> writes of one, who after tedious <lb/>Pains in the
            Kidnies, diſcharg'd a ſmall <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worm</hi> by Urine; its Head was
            ſharp and <lb/>horned, its Back and Belly broad, and <lb/>cover'd with an hard Shell
            like a <hi rend="italic">Tortoiſe</hi>, <lb/>its Colour black, but reddiſh on the Bel-
            <lb/>ly. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Sennertus</hi> ſays, he ſaw the whole Sub- <lb/>ſtance of the
            Kidnies of a Dog waſted, and <lb/>only the outward Skin left, which was full <lb/>of <hi
              rend="italic">Worms</hi> like <hi rend="italic">Earth-worms.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Turberville,</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Philos. Trans.
              No.</hi>
            <lb/>167. <hi rend="italic">p.</hi> 839. gives an Account of a Gentle- <lb/>woman, who
            was much troubled with the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Falling-Sickneſs,</hi> and diſcharg'd
            by Urine a <lb/>great Number of ſhort <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> like <hi
              rend="italic"> Milli- <lb/>pedes</hi>; two or three Purges were preſcrib'd <lb/>her,
            and ſtill in every Water that was <lb/>brought the Phyſician, he found, Eight, <lb/>Ten,
            or more of thoſe <hi rend="italic">Worms;</hi> they ap- <lb/>pear'd lively, and full of
            Motion, and the <lb/>Fits continu'd daily; at laſt he gave her <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >Oxymel Helleboratum</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Tanſy</hi>-Water, which <lb/>wrought
            well, and was ſucceſsful; ſo that <lb/>ſhe had a compleat Cure. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>In the <hi rend="italic">Philos. Trans.</hi> there is an Account <lb/>of one Mr.
              <hi rend="italic">Thomas Dent</hi>, who being af- <pb xml:id="page_19" n="20"/>
            <lb/>flicted with <hi rend="italic">Tumours</hi> on his Tongue, ap- <lb/>ply'd himſelf
            to one Mrs. <hi rend="italic">French</hi> at <hi rend="italic"> Lei- <lb/>ceſter;</hi>
            who (in the Preſence of Two Al- <lb/>dermen of that Town, Mr. <hi rend="italic"
              >Gibbs,</hi> Chap- <lb/>lain to the Earl of <hi rend="italic">Derby,</hi> and others)
            <lb/>pierc'd the Parts tumify'd with a Lancet, <lb/>and drew ſome Blood; and ſoon after
            with <lb/>a ſmall <hi rend="italic">Spatula,</hi> and another Inſtrument, <lb/>wherewith
            ſhe open'd the Orifices, ſhe <lb/>pick'd out five or ſix <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> at
            a time. <lb/>She plainly ſhew'd them to the Spectators, <lb/>as they came out of the
            Fleſh; they were <lb/>all alive, and mov'd their Heads, ſome- <lb/>what leſſer than
            ordinary <hi rend="italic">Maggots:</hi> In leſs <lb/>than eight Days ſhe took out of
            the Tongue <lb/>more than an hundred <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>, almoſt all <lb/>of
            the ſame Bigneſs, except two very large <lb/>ones, which ſhe ſaid were of a Cancerous
            <lb/>Production. She took more than Thirty <lb/>out of the Gums, which laſt Operation
            was <lb/>her ordinary Practice. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">de la Croſe</hi> in his <hi rend="italic">Memoirs, p.</hi>
            223. <lb/>gives an Account of one <hi rend="italic">Sarah Haſtings</hi>, <lb/>who
            follow'd the ſame Practice at <hi rend="italic">Holm</hi>, <lb/>in <hi rend="italic"
              >Huntingdon-ſhire</hi>; and had attain'd to <lb/>ſo great Skill, as to diſcern at
            firſt Sight, <lb/>whether any Perſon had <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> great or
            <lb/>ſmall in his Gums, Tongue or Face: Theſe <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> ſhe
            affirm'd to be the Cauſe of Rot- <lb/>tenness of the Teeth, of <hi rend="italic"
              >Puſtules,</hi> and ma- <pb xml:id="page_20" n="21"/>
            <lb/>ny other Putrefactions; ſhe drew them <lb/>out of any Part in three or four
            Minutes, <lb/>with a Gooſe-Quill, cut like a Pen; ſhe <lb/>pierc'd the Part ſo
            Dexterouſly, that the <lb/>Pain was almoſt inſenſible; then ſhe threw <lb/>the extracted
              <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> into a Glaſs of clean <lb/>Water, where they appeared to
            have a <lb/>round and red Head, the reſt of the Body <lb/>being white. He there relates
            ſeveral ex- <lb/>traordinary Cures of that Sort, too large to <lb/>inſert here. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>But of all the Parts, the Stomach and <lb/>Guts are the moſt uſually infeſted with
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worms,</hi> eſpecially in Children: However, <lb/>before we
            enter upon a particular Deſcrip- <lb/>tion of thoſe, which properly belong to <lb/>theſe
            Parts, it may be convenient to en- <lb/>tertain the Reader with ſome Hiſtories of
            <lb/>very ſtrange Animals, excluded the Sto- <lb/>mach by Vomiting. The Accounts are
            <lb/>taken out of the <hi rend="italic">Philos. Tranſactions.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The firſt is Dr. <hi rend="italic">Liſter</hi>'s, of a Baker at <lb/><hi
              rend="italic">York,</hi> who in <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 168<formula
              notation="fraction">1/2</formula>. vomited up a <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worm</hi> of a
            very ſtrange Figure; I found <lb/>it (<hi rend="italic">ſays the Doctor</hi>) in the
            Blood, which <lb/>came up with it; having caus'd it to be <lb/>waſh'd, for the more
            careful Examination <lb/>of it; much of the Blood being Clods of <lb/>a kind of skinny
            and fleſhy Subſtance. Of <pb xml:id="page_21" n="22"/>
            <lb/>this kind of Blood there was about two <lb/>Pounds ſav'd in the Waſhing, and this
            <lb/>odd Animal amongſt it: It was of a dark, <lb/>green Colour, like an Horſe-Leech,
            and <lb/>ſpotted, not unlike ſome of them. I could <lb/>not perceive, when I found it,
            any Life <lb/>or Motion in it. The Girl, who waſh'd <lb/>it, had beaten off almoſt a
            Fin, and part <lb/>of one of the Forks of the Tail, and burſt <lb/>its Belly; yet it was
            regularly and curi- <lb/>ouſly ſhap'd in all its Members. The <lb/>Man imagin'd he drank
            it the Summer <lb/>before in Pond-Water, whereof he was <lb/>us'd to drink after ſore
            Labour in his Cal- <lb/>ling. This is certain, he had about his <lb/>Stomach, and right
            Side, a moſt exqui- <lb/>ſite and tormenting Pain for at leaſt four <lb/>Months, which
            many times threw him <lb/>into Horrors and Chilneſs, Ague like; and <lb/>indeed, when he
            vomited this up, he was <lb/>the ſickeſt Man I ever ſaw, not to die: <lb/>He alſo voided
            Blood by Stool ſeveral <lb/>Days. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>I am at a loſs where to place this Ani- <lb/>mal, it not being like any thing I
            ever <lb/>ſaw in Nature. It was about four Inches <lb/>long, and in the thickeſt Part
            three Inches <lb/>about; it had three Fins on a ſide, all near <lb/>the Head, and all of
            them were thick and <lb/>fleſhy; but the forked Tail was finny and <pb xml:id="page_22"
              n="23"/>
            <lb/>tranſparent, and to be extended. It was <lb/>plac'd Horrizantally, not as that of
            moſt <lb/>(if not all) ſmall Fiſh, and even <hi rend="italic">Newts</hi>
            <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Tadpoles,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Frogs</hi> in Diſguiſe,
            in which <lb/>Particular it differs from all, as well as in <lb/>the Fleſhineſs of the
            Fins. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Beſides this odd Animal, I found the <lb/>Head of another of a different Shape; but
            <lb/>the like dark green Colour. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>I'm apt to think, we often eat and drink <lb/>what is alive; and 'tis certain, ſome
            <lb/>Things will live on in our Stomachs in <lb/>ſpight of Concoction, as <hi
              rend="italic">Gut-Worms</hi> bred <lb/>in us, and perhaps in ſome Children be-
            <lb/>fore they are born. And yet I am of the <lb/>Mind, that what was accidentally ſwal-
            <lb/>low'd by us alive, and that ſhall have the <lb/>Power to live on within us
            (eſpecially if <lb/>it be young and tender) and yet growing, <lb/>may have its Shape and
            deſign'd Form ſo <lb/>monſtrouſly perverted, as to appear to us <lb/>quite another Thing
            than naturally it is; <lb/>and this I take to be the Caſe of this odd <lb/>Creature,
            which might have been the <lb/>Spawn, or Embrio of a <hi rend="italic">Toad</hi> or <hi
              rend="italic">Newt</hi>. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The skinny Lumps of Blood vomited up <lb/>with it, I think, may be eaſily accounted
            <lb/>for. For this Spawn, or Embrio of a <hi rend="italic">Toad</hi>
            <pb xml:id="page_23" n="24"/>
            <lb/>or <hi rend="italic">Newt,</hi> might well envenom the Sto- <lb/>mach or Gut, in
            which Part or Wrinckle <lb/>ſoever it chanc'd to reſt or ſtick firſt, and <lb/>cauſe an
            Inflamation there, and have it <lb/>ſwell'd or clos'd up within a Tumour of <lb/>its own
            making; which in Proceſs of Time <lb/>might gather to this Bigneſs, and at <lb/>length
            burſting in Pieces, come up toge- <lb/>ther. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Familiar Inſtances of this Nature we ſee <lb/>in Fruits or Wens, which Inſects
            raiſe <lb/>upon Vegetables; who by natural Inſtinct <lb/>know how to envenom a Plant,
            and com- <lb/>pendiouſly provide both Food and Houſing <lb/>for their Young. <hi
              rend="italic">So far Dr.</hi> Liſter. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The next is, <hi rend="italic">No.</hi> 117. <hi rend="italic">p.</hi> 395. Of a
            Girl <lb/>at <hi rend="italic">Sheffield,</hi> about eight Months old, who <lb/>was
            ſeiz'd with violent Fits of Vomiting, <lb/>which held her about a Week; and Mr. <lb/><hi
              rend="italic">Fiſher</hi> being ſent for, and happening to ſay, <lb/>that <hi
              rend="italic">Wormwood</hi> was good for the Stomach, <lb/>whilſt he was gone to fetch
            ſome Things <lb/>proper for that Occaſion, they in the mean <lb/>Time offer'd the Child
            ſome <hi rend="italic">Wormwood</hi> Ale, <lb/>which ſhe took ſo greedily, that ſhe
            ſwal- <lb/>low'd down a Pint of it; and at his Re- <lb/>turn, ſhe vomited up in his
            Preſence three <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hexapodes</hi> (i. e. <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>
            with ſix Feet) all <lb/>very active and nimble; and the Child <pb xml:id="page_24"
              n="25"/>
            <lb/>ſoon recover'd. Mr. <hi rend="italic">Fiſher</hi> carry'd them <lb/>the ſame Day to
            Mr. <hi rend="italic">Jeſſop</hi> (who ſent the <lb/>Account) they kill'd one of them in
            try- <lb/>ing Experiments upon it, but gave each of <lb/>the other Two, the Head of a
            ſhining <hi rend="italic"> A- <lb/>tricapella</hi> (a Bird with black Feathers on
            <lb/>its Head) which in about five Week's <lb/>Time they eat up, Bones, Feathers and
            all, <lb/>except the Extremities of the Feathers and <lb/>Beaks. Then they gave them a
            Piece of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Larus</hi> (a <hi rend="italic">Sea-Cob</hi>) but that
            it ſeems did <lb/>not agree ſo well with them, for they dy'd <lb/>within two Days after. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The laſt Account is Dr. <hi rend="italic">Liſter</hi>'s, the Son <lb/>of one not
            far from <hi rend="italic">Rippon,</hi> about 9 Years <lb/>of Age, in <hi rend="italic"
              >Feb.</hi> 1674. was afflicted with <lb/>a great Pain in his Stomach, and continual
            <lb/>Vomitings; a Powder was given him, <lb/>wherein was a ſmall Quantity of <hi
              rend="italic">Mercurius <lb/>Dulcis;</hi> he thereupon vomited up ſeveral <lb/>ſtrange
              <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>, two of which were brought <lb/>the Doctor at <hi
              rend="italic">York</hi>, one dead, the other <lb/>alive, 'till he put it into Spirit
            of Wine, <lb/>to preſerve it in its true Shape. Theſe <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>
            were very <hi rend="italic">Caterpillers,</hi> with fourteen <lb/>Legs, <hi
              rend="italic">viz.</hi> ſix ſmall pointed, the eight <lb/>middle Stumps, and the two
            hind ones <lb/>Claſpers. They were ſomething more than <lb/>an Inch long, of the
            thickneſs of a Duck's- <lb/>Quill, thin hair'd, or rather naked, with <pb
              xml:id="page_25" n="26"/>
            <lb/>brown <hi rend="italic">Annuli,</hi> and black Heads; the <lb/>ſame for kind, that
            is often ſeen on Plants. <lb/>Theſe, no doubt, would in due time, if <lb/>the Place had
            not hindred, have ſhrunk <lb/>into <hi rend="italic">Chryſalis's</hi>, and chang'd into
              <hi rend="italic">Moths</hi>; <lb/>as alſo thoſe mention'd by Mr. <hi rend="italic"
              >Jeſſop</hi>, in <lb/>the preceeding Hiſtory, would have chang'd <lb/>into <hi
              rend="italic">Beetles.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The proper Inhabitants of theſe dark <lb/>Regions, are of four Sorts; <hi
              rend="italic">viz.</hi> The <lb/><hi rend="italic">Teres,</hi> the <hi rend="italic"
              >Cucurbitini,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Tænia,</hi> and the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >Aſcarides</hi>. </p>
          <p rend="indent space" n="1">
            <lb/>1. Of the <hi rend="italic">Teres,</hi> or common long and <lb/>round <hi
              rend="italic">Worm,</hi> Dr. <hi rend="italic">Tyſon</hi> has given a very
            <lb/>curious Anatomical Deſcription in the <hi rend="italic"> Phi- <lb/>los. Trans.
              No.</hi> 147. <hi rend="italic">p.</hi> 154. from whence I <lb/>ſhall borrow a few
            Obſervations. Tho' we <lb/>are gravell'd <hi rend="italic">(ſays the Doctor)</hi> in
            Aſſign- <lb/>ing how theſe Sorts of <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> ſhould come <lb/>firſt
            into the Body; yet being once there, <lb/>nothing is more plain, than that they are
            <lb/>propagated by an univocal Generation; <lb/>there being in this Sort, ſo perfect a
            Di- <lb/>ſtinction or Sexes, Male and Female; and <lb/>the Organs of each ſo curiouſly
            contriv'd, <lb/>ſo conſpicuous and plain, as ſhew how ſo- <lb/>licitous Nature is in
            preſerving, and propa- <lb/>gating the meaneſt Species. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_26" n="27"/>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>This <hi rend="italic">Worm,</hi> which Children are uſually <lb/>troubled with, is
            uſually a Foot long, the <lb/>Male generally leſs than the Female; its <lb/>thickneſs
            about that of a Wheat Straw, or <lb/>Gooſe-Quill, at both Extreams, they grow
            <lb/>narrow, the Mouth conſiſts of three Lips, <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Anus</hi> of a
            tranſverſe Slit, a little before <lb/>the extream Point of the Tail. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>In Cutting thro' the Muſcles under the <lb/>Skin, there iſſu'd out a copious <hi
              rend="italic">Ichor</hi>, which <lb/>is naturally diſcharg'd by ſome Pores in the
            <lb/>Skin, and makes a Covering to the Body, <lb/>which is often caſt off, and obſerv'd
            as a <lb/>mucous Matter in the Stools of thoſe, who <lb/>are troubled with them. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>In Opening the <hi rend="italic">Cornua Uteri</hi> of the Fe- <lb/>male <hi
              rend="italic">Worm,</hi> they were found turgid with <lb/>a Milky Juice, a little of
            which being <lb/>plac'd on a ſmall <hi rend="italic">Microſcope,</hi> was found to
            <lb/>be nothing elſe but an infinite Number of <lb/>Eggs, tho' to the naked Eye, it
            appear'd <lb/>only as a fluid Body. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>By Comparing that ſmall Quantity, I did <lb/>obſerve, and in which I could
            diſtinguiſh <lb/>ſo many Eggs, with the whole Quantity <lb/>contain'd, in both the <hi
              rend="italic">Cornua,</hi> I cannot <lb/>gueſs there could be fewer than Ten Thou- <pb
              xml:id="page_27" n="28"/>
            <lb/>ſand in each Female <hi rend="italic">Worm,</hi> which ſuffici- <lb/>ently accounts
            for that prodigious Number <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>, ſometimes obſerv'd to
            be bred <lb/>in Animal Bodies; and were it not that <lb/>the greateſt Part of the Litter
            of this <hi rend="italic">Worm</hi>
            <lb/>is uſually carry'd forth by the <hi rend="italic">Fæces</hi>, it <lb/>could not be
            avoided, but we ſhould be de- <lb/>vour'd by ſuch a multiparous Enemy, bred <lb/>in our
            own Bowels; of whoſe pernicious <lb/>Effects, ſome of the following Inſtances are
            <lb/>fatal Proofs. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Preſton,</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Philos. Trans. p.</hi>
            326. <lb/><hi rend="italic">No.</hi> 224. relates, That in Diſſecting a Boy <lb/>of Nine
            Years of Age, who dy'd ſuddenly, <lb/>being ſeiz'd with a Fit of Vomiting; be-
            <lb/>ſides, a great many other Diſorders of all <lb/>the Bowels, they found a <hi
              rend="italic">Worm</hi> in the Sto- <lb/>mach about nine Inches long, and a Line
            <lb/>and a half broad. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">James Burrows</hi> reports, in the <hi rend="italic">Philos.
              <lb/>Trans. No.</hi> 264. <hi rend="italic">p.</hi> 598. That in <hi rend="italic"
              >May</hi> or <lb/><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 1700. a Labouring Man of middle <lb/>Age
            at <hi rend="italic">Stanton</hi>, ſeven Miles from <hi rend="italic">Bury</hi>,
            <lb/>had for many Days together ſo inordinate <lb/>an Appetite, that he eat up an
            ordinary <lb/>Leg of Veal roaſted at a Meal. He would <lb/>eat Sow-Thiſtles, and divers
            other Herbs, <lb/>as greedily, during the time his <hi rend="italic">Bulimia</hi>
            <lb/>laſted, as the Beaſts that uſe ſuch Food; <pb xml:id="page_28" n="29"/>
            <lb/>and all he could get was little enough to <lb/>ſatisfy his Hunger, 'till at length
            he voided <lb/>divers <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>, as long, and as big about <lb/>as a
            Tobacco-Pipe; after which, his Ap- <lb/>petite declin'd by degrees, 'till it came to
            <lb/>the common Rate of others. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>We have alſo an Account, in the ſame <lb/>Place, of a Diſſection perform'd by the
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">Sieur Soye</hi>, in an Hoſpital, on the Body of <lb/>a Servant
            Maid, about twenty ſix Years of <lb/>Age, who was from time to time ſeiz'd <lb/>with a
              <hi rend="italic">Bloody-Flux.</hi> He found the <hi rend="italic">Colon</hi>,
            <lb/>and part of the <hi rend="italic">Meſentery</hi> ulcerated, the <lb/>Mouth of which
              <hi rend="italic">Ulcer</hi> was ſo large, that <lb/>one might eaſily thruſt in his
            Fiſt at it, and <lb/>'twas ſtop'd with a Clew of <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> greater
            <lb/>than it. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Loſs,</hi> in his Book of <hi rend="italic">Obſervations</hi>
            <lb/>writes, That the Son of Sir <hi rend="italic">Lewis Dive</hi>, a <lb/>Child of a
            good Conſtitution of Body, af- <lb/>ter an Indiſpoſition of two or three Days,
            <lb/>attended with a dry Cough, and a reſtleſs <lb/>Condition, eſpecially in the Night,
            with <lb/>continual Cryings, was at length ſeiz'd <lb/>with violent and continual <hi
              rend="italic">Convulſions</hi>, <lb/>whereof in three Days he dy'd. In cut- <lb/>ting
            open the Body to diſcover the Cauſe, <lb/>they were ſoon ſatisfy'd, when they found
            <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Duodenum</hi> quite eaten thro' by a <hi rend="italic"
              >Teres</hi>, <pb xml:id="page_29" n="30"/>
            <lb/>or long <hi rend="italic">Worm,</hi> which was taken out a- <lb/>live. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Willis,</hi> in his Book of <hi rend="italic">Fevers</hi>
            tells us, <lb/>He knew one in an acute <hi rend="italic">Fever</hi>, who was
            <lb/>moleſted with continual Swoonings, 'till he <lb/>vomited up a long round <hi
              rend="italic">Worm</hi>; and there- <lb/>upon his Swoonings left him. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Examples of this Kind are very nume- <lb/>rous, and 'tis no wonder to meet with
            this <lb/>Species in their proper Soil; but the Ac- <lb/>count which Dr. <hi
              rend="italic">Liſter</hi> has publiſh'd in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Philos.
              Trans.</hi> is very ſurprizing; <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> In <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >April</hi> 1673. a Chyrurgion at <hi rend="italic">York</hi> brought <lb/>him about
            twenty <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>, which he had <lb/>juſt taken out of an ulcerated
            Ancle of a <lb/>Girl about eight Years of Age; ſhe had <lb/>been in great Miſery ſome
            Months, and <lb/>had been ſent up to <hi rend="italic">London,</hi> where ſhe was
            <lb/>touch'd and dreſs'd for the <hi rend="italic">Evil;</hi> ſome- <lb/>time after her
            Return, her Pain <choice>
              <sic>contiuu-</sic>
              <corr>continu-</corr>
            </choice>
            <lb/>ing, a young Puppy was open'd, and ap- <lb/>ply'd to the Sore. The Chyrurgion, who
            <lb/>took off the Puppy, found it to his great <lb/>Surprize full of <hi rend="italic"
              >Worms,</hi> at leaſt ſixty in <lb/>Number, of the Species of the <hi rend="italic"
              >Teretes,</hi> which <lb/>Children familiarly void from the Guts. <lb/>They were
            between three and four Inches <lb/>long, all about an equal Bigneſs, as of one
            <lb/>Brood, ſomething thicker than a <hi rend="italic">Duck's-</hi>
            <pb xml:id="page_30" n="31"/>
            <lb/>Quill, very ſharp at both Ends; ſtiff, and <lb/>exactly round, and yet could move,
            and <lb/>twiſt themſelves viſibly enough. The Leg <lb/>was ſound, all but the Ancle,
            which was <lb/>vaſtly ſwell'd, and the Girl otherwiſe hear- <lb/>ty, and well colour'd. </p>
          <p rend="indent space" n="2">
            <lb/>2. The <hi rend="italic">Taenia,</hi> or Tape <hi rend="italic">Worm,</hi> ſo
            call'd <lb/>from its Reſemblance to a Tape or Rib- <lb/>bon, is broad and flat, and
            white; its <lb/>Thinneſs renders it diaphanous, its Length <lb/>is very uncertain,
            becauſe its Subſtance be- <lb/>ing very ſoft and tender; it uſually breaks <lb/>off when
            it comes away, ſo that 'tis very <lb/>rare to find it entire; the whole is proba-
            <lb/>bly the Length of all the Bowels, that is, <lb/>ſeven times the Length of the Man;
            but <lb/>lying very much folded together, takes up <lb/>but little Room; it uſually
            comes away <lb/>Piece-meal, ſeven or eight Foot long, ſome- <lb/>times nineteen, twenty
            three, thirty; forty <lb/>five Foot of it has been found broke off at <lb/>a time; it
            grows gradually ſmaller towards <lb/>the Tail, which terminates in a very ſmall <lb/>and
            long Part like an Hair; in its wideſt <lb/>Part, its Breadth is about that of one's
            Fore- <lb/>finger. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Spigelius</hi> tells us of a Woman, who void- <lb/>ed at ſeveral
            times ſeveral Pieces of this <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worm</hi>, whereof two were
            extraordinary <pb xml:id="page_31" n="32"/>
            <lb/>long. The firſt that came away, was two <lb/>Yards and a half long, containing the
            Tail <lb/>Part of the <hi rend="italic">Worm,</hi> but wanting the ex- <lb/>tream Part
            of the Tail, perhaps unknow- <lb/>ingly broke off by the Patient before, part <lb/>of it
            hanging out of the <hi rend="italic">Anus;</hi> her Siſter <lb/>drew it forth ſo far,
            but tir'd with its pro- <lb/>digious Length, ſhe broke it off with her <lb/>Nails; this
            Piece, in that Part where it <lb/>was freſh broke off, was as broad as ones <lb/>little
            Finger, and became narrower gradu- <lb/>ally as it approach'd the Tail; its Sub-
            <lb/>ſtance was ſoft, throughout white, blood- <lb/>less like a Membrane of the Guts.
            Ano- <lb/>ther Piece that came away about a Year <lb/>after, was eight Foot long, and
            the breadth <lb/>of ones Middle-Finger; the Joints were <lb/>larger and thicker, the
            Inciſures wider, and <lb/>the Sides more jagged. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fabricius</hi> gives a Deſcription of the like <lb/>Sort of <hi
              rend="italic">Worm,</hi> which a Woman of twenty <lb/>Years of Age voided, upon taking
            a Purg- <lb/>ing Medicine, which was twenty Spans <lb/>long; one of the Extreams was as
            ſlender <lb/>as a Thread, the other broad. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The ſame Author relates the following <lb/>Hiſtory. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_32" n="33"/>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>A Lady at <hi rend="italic">Lauſanne,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">France,</hi> very
            <lb/>ſubject in her Youth to Palpitations of the <lb/>Heart; and after a ſort of Purge
            ſhe us'd <lb/>to take, ſhe voided ſometimes very long <lb/>Pieces of <hi rend="italic"
              >Worms.</hi> After ſhe was marry'd, <lb/>and began to have Children, her Palpita-
            <lb/>tions left her, only ſhe was troubled with a <lb/><hi rend="italic">Lienteria;</hi>
            during which, ſhe voided down- <lb/>wards ſeveral Pieces of <hi rend="italic"
              >Worms;</hi> ſome ſix, <lb/>ſome nine, others ten Spans long. Every <lb/>time ſhe
            voided theſe Pieces, ſhe felt the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> break in her Bowels;
            one Day, af- <lb/>ter taking her Remedy, ſhe voided a Piece <lb/>of <hi rend="italic"
              >Worm</hi> ſeven Ells long; and a few Days <lb/>after, another Piece, without perceiv-
            <lb/>ing as before that any thing broke; from <lb/>which time ſhe became perfectly well.
            All <lb/>the Pieces put together, would make above <lb/>twenty Ells. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Olaus Borrhicius</hi> tells us, That a Patient <lb/>of his has
            voided eight hundred Foot of <lb/>this <hi rend="italic">Worm</hi> in ſeveral Pieces;
            and that hi- <lb/>therto, he has not met with the Head; for <lb/>the Patient declar'd,
            that always in the <lb/>Voiding, he perceiv'd it break off. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>A Sucking-Child (by the Relation of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Caſp. Wolphius</hi>)
            brought forth a broad <hi rend="italic">Worm</hi>, <lb/>at leaſt three Ells long. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_33" n="34"/>
          <p rend="indent space" n="3">
            <lb/>3. The <hi rend="italic">Cucurbitinj,</hi> or ſpurious jointed <lb/>Tape <hi
              rend="italic">Worm; Valliſnerius,</hi> an <hi rend="italic">Italian</hi> Phyſi-
            <lb/>cian, has publiſh'd a very large and accu- <lb/>rate Deſcription of this Species of
              <hi rend="italic"> Gut- <lb/>Worms,</hi> the Reſult of his indefatigable In-
            <lb/>duſtry, from whom I have taken this Ac- <lb/>count following. <hi rend="italic"
              >Anno</hi> 1706. viſiting a <lb/><hi rend="italic">Jeweſs,</hi> twenty five Years of
            Age, three <lb/>Months gone with Child (who, like many <lb/>of that Nation, was incident
            to broad <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worms,</hi> which in her third or fourth Month,
            <lb/>uſually occaſion'd her to Miſcarry; but <lb/>when ſhe was not with Child, they
            never <lb/>gave her any Diſturbance. She often void- <lb/>ed, by Vomiting and Stool,
            many of theſe <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worms,</hi> as well ſingly as link'd together,
            <lb/>in the manner of a Chain:) She had juſt <lb/>diſcharg'd a very long Chain of theſe
              <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>, <lb/>beſides ſeveral ſingly. He ſeparated with- <lb/>out
            much Pains, many of theſe from each <lb/>other in that Part which was largeſt; but
            <lb/>obſerv'd, they were very ſtrictly joyn'd to- <lb/>gether. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Every one of theſe conſiſted of a Mem- <lb/>branous, ſoft, white, ſhining, flexible
            and <lb/>ſlippery Matter; the upper Part ſmaller <lb/>than the lower. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_34" n="35"/>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>In the upper Side of each there ariſe two <lb/>very ſmall Prominences, which, when
            <lb/>preſs'd with the Fingers, feel like little <lb/>Horns, or crooked Thorns, and are
            con- <lb/>ſpicuous by the <hi rend="italic">Microſcope.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>By theſe they adhere firmly to the hin- <lb/>der Part of the preceding <hi
              rend="italic">Worm,</hi> in whoſe <lb/>poſtick Part are Cavities fitted to receive
            <lb/>theſe Prominences. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The lateral Parts of theſe <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> are rug- <lb/>ged, and out
            of their Middle riſes a kind <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Tet,</hi> whoſe Center is
            perforated with a <lb/>very conſpicuous Opening, and pours out <lb/>ſometimes a quantity
            of <hi rend="italic">Chyle,</hi> ſometimes <lb/>clear Water, ſometimes a yellow <hi
              rend="italic">Serum.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Their Mouth is in the narrower and up- <lb/>per Side, between the two <hi
              rend="italic">Protuberances</hi>; <lb/>If it be objected, that if the Mouth be in
            <lb/>this Part, they cannot receive Nouriſhment <lb/>by it adhering ſo cloſely to the
            preceding <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worm.</hi> 'Tis anſwer'd, they being fed with <lb/>a
            fluid Matter <hi rend="italic">Chyle,</hi> which penetrating e- <lb/>very where, eaſily
            enters that Chink where <lb/>the Mouth is, ſince the middle Part is not <lb/>ſo cloſe as
            the Jettings. Beſides, that when <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> adhere ſo cloſe,
            'tis to preſerve <lb/>themſelves when in danger of Expulſion; <pb xml:id="page_35"
              n="36"/>
            <lb/>at other times they are more cloſely con- <lb/>nected. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Theſe flat <hi rend="italic">Worms,</hi> when ſingle, very <lb/>much reſemble in
            Bigneſs and Shape the <lb/>Seed of a <hi rend="italic">Gourd,</hi> which in <hi
              rend="italic">Latin</hi> is call'd <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cucurbita,</hi> whence they
            are call'd <hi rend="italic"> Cucur- <lb/>bitini;</hi> and being very numerous, and ad-
            <lb/>hering to each other ſo firmly in the man- <lb/>ner aforeſaid, do form a Chain of a
            ſur- <lb/>prizing Length, which has been miſtaken <lb/>by ſeveral very eminent Authors
            for an en- <lb/>tire <hi rend="italic">Worm;</hi> in particular, the Ingenious <lb/>Dr.
              <hi rend="italic">Tyſon,</hi> and Mr. <hi rend="italic">Andry</hi> of <hi
              rend="italic">France,</hi> the <lb/>former having given a very particular and
            <lb/>large Account of it in the <hi rend="italic">Philos. Trans. No.</hi>
            <lb/>146. <hi rend="italic">p.</hi> 113. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Andry,</hi> in Examining theſe <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>
            <lb/>very diligently with a <hi rend="italic">Microſcope,</hi> after cut- <lb/>ting them
            open, perceiv'd them full of <lb/>ſmall globular Bodies, reſembling that Clu- <lb/>ſter
            of Eggs, uſually found in <hi rend="italic">Carps:</hi> Theſe <lb/>Eggs are ſo numerous,
            that the Quantity <lb/>taken up with the Point of a Pin, tho' <lb/>no bigger than a
            Grain of Duſt, would ap- <lb/>pear, under a <hi rend="italic">Microſcope,</hi> an
            incredible Pile <lb/>of ſmall Eggs; which ſufficiently accounts <lb/>for the vaſt Number
            of theſe Inſects. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_36" n="37"/>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>They are found in Perſons of all Ages. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">George Francus</hi> ſaw a Child one Year <lb/>three Months
            old, in the Year 1686. in <lb/>good Health, and Fleſhy; who, tho' it <lb/>ſuck'd, us'd
            to drink Beer and Water, after <lb/>he had voided ſeveral ſmall <hi rend="italic"
              >Worms</hi> upwards <lb/>and downwards; at length, brought away <lb/>a Chain of <hi
              rend="italic">Cucurbitini</hi> three Ells long; which <lb/>would have been much
            longer, if the frighted <lb/>Nurſe had not broke it off, inſtead of draw- <lb/>ing it
            all out. <hi rend="italic">Miſcel. Curios.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Wagner</hi> relates of a Soldier, who was <lb/>freed of ſuch a
            Chain of <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> ſix Ells <lb/>long; and ſoon after of another
            longer than <lb/>the former. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Examples of theſe <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> are innumera- <lb/>ble, tho' many
            Authors have ſet them <lb/>down ſo confuſedly, that 'tis not poſſible <lb/>to
            diſtinguiſh whether they are the genuine <lb/><hi rend="italic">Taenia,</hi> deſcrib'd
            in the ſecond Article, which <lb/>is but one entire <hi rend="italic">Worm,</hi> or this
            ſpurious <lb/>Sort, conſiſting of a Chain of <hi rend="italic">Cucurbitini.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Tyſon</hi> mentions a Perſon in <hi rend="italic"
            >London</hi>, <lb/>who has voided vaſt Quantities of theſe <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >Worms</hi> for ſeveral Years together; but in <lb/>ſeveral Pieces, two, three, four,
            ſix, or <pb xml:id="page_37" n="38"/>
            <lb/>more Yards long; and ſays, he had a Piece <lb/>by him of a great Length, voided by
            a <lb/>young Man, upon the Uſe of an Emul- <lb/>ſion of the cold Seeds. It was twenty
            four <lb/>Foot long, and conſiſted of five hundred <lb/>and ſeven <hi rend="italic"
              >Joints</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Worms,</hi> in Thickneſs a- <lb/>bout that of an
            Half-Crown. The Perſon <lb/>drag'd it from himſelf, not without fright- <lb/>ful
            Apprehenſions, that Guts, and all were <lb/>coming out. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Theſe Chains of <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> lye convoluted in <lb/>ſeveral Places,
            and are ſometimes as long <lb/>as all the Guts, and ſometimes vaſtly ex- <lb/>ceed that
            Length. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Theſe <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> have been found ſometimes <lb/>included in a
            Bag; which has been miſta- <lb/>ken by ſeveral for a large <hi rend="italic">Worm.</hi>
            The <lb/><hi rend="italic">Jeweſs,</hi> before-mention'd, upon a Time <lb/>imagining a
            large Piece of her Bowels <lb/>coming from her, tho' ſhe felt no Pain, <lb/>being
            frighted at it, ſhe ſent for her Phy- <lb/>ſician, who was himſelf at firſt ſurpriz'd
            <lb/>at it. This Subſtance was like a doubl'd <lb/>Rowler, cloſe in every Part, compos'd
            of a <lb/>thick, ſmooth, ſhining, tranſparent and <lb/>mucilaginous Membrane, two Thumbs
            <lb/>broad, above a Yard long; it was hol- <lb/>low, and contain'd within it a
            numberleſs <lb/>Quantity of <hi rend="italic">Cucurbitini,</hi> not link'd toge- <pb
              xml:id="page_38" n="39"/>
            <lb/>ther; but every one ſeparate, their Bigneſs <lb/>was various, they were all alive,
            and mov'd <lb/>freely. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>This Bag ſeems to be form'd moſtly of <lb/>a concreſſible Humour in the Inteſtines,
            af- <lb/>ter the ſame manner as <hi rend="italic">Polypus's</hi> in the <lb/>Heart and
            Arteries, and is encreas'd by a <lb/>glewy Matter, caſt out by theſe <hi rend="italic"
              >Worms</hi>
            <lb/>from their lateral Orifices. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Teretes</hi> alſo, or long and round <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >Worms,</hi> are ſometimes found involv'd in <lb/>ſuch a Bag. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="4">
            <lb/>4. The laſt Species of <hi rend="italic">Worms,</hi> uſually <lb/>found in the
            Inteſtines, are the <hi rend="italic">Aſcarides</hi>; <lb/>they are very ſmall and
            round, full of Vi- <lb/>vacity and Motion. Their Habitation is in <lb/>the loweſt Part
            of the Inteſtines, where <lb/>they provoke a continual Itching; and oc- <lb/>caſion
            ſometimes moſt direful Symptoms. <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Curteis,</hi> in his <hi
              rend="italic">Treatiſe</hi> on the Recovery <lb/>of Health, gives us the following
            Exam- <lb/>ple. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>A Boy, about twelve Years of Age, was <lb/>ſo extreamly afflicted with ſuch
            formidable <lb/>Symptoms, as were imputed to the Effect <lb/>of Witchcraft: What gave
            Birth to ſo ge- <lb/>neral a Conjecture, were the extraordinary <pb xml:id="page_39"
              n="40"/>
            <lb/>Convulſions, Rolling, Screaming, violent <lb/>Beating himſelf, <hi rend="italic"
              >&amp;c.</hi> by frequent <hi rend="italic">Paroxiſms</hi>; <lb/>all which ſoon
            diſappear'd, and the My- <lb/>ſtery was at an end, upon his liberally <lb/>taking the
              <hi rend="italic">Æthiops</hi>, Mineral and Purging; <lb/>and thereupon voiding an
            almoſt incredible <lb/>Number of <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> of different Sizes, and
            <lb/>eſpecially of theſe <hi rend="italic">Aſcarides;</hi> whereupon <lb/>the Patient
            was reſcu'd from his imagin'd <lb/>Witchcraft, and a very poor old Woman <lb/>from worſe
            than Hanging, who was ſuſpect- <lb/>ed of being the Occaſion. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Several Examples of this Sort of <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>
            <lb/>might be produc'd out of Authors; but this <lb/>is ſufficient for a Specimen. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc rend="space">A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="chapter">
          <pb xml:id="page_40" n="41"/>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
          <head rend="align-center sc size(1.25) space">
            <lb/>Chap. III. </head>
          <head rend="align-center italic size(1.25) space">
            <lb/>The Signs of <hi rend="roman">Worms</hi> from <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="roman">Andry.</hi>
          </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE Signs of <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> are Common or
            <lb/>Particular. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The common Signs ſhew the Genius, and <lb/>the Particular the Species; that is,
            when <lb/>the Common meet, we ſay, there are <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worms;</hi> and when
            we find particular Signs, <lb/>we may ſay, not only that there are <hi rend="italic"
              >Worms</hi>
            <lb/>in general, but that thoſe <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> are of <lb/>ſuch a
            particular Sort. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The common Signs are fiery ſparkling <lb/>Eyes, livid Cheeks, cold Sweats in the
            <lb/>Nights, Abundance of Spittle drivelling <lb/>from the Mouth in Sleep, great Drowth
            <lb/>in the Day-time, Dryneſs of the Tongue <lb/>and Lips, a Stinking-Breath, Grating of
            <lb/>the Teeth in Sleep, a conſtant Looſeneſs, <lb/>with whitiſh Excrements, frothy
            Urine, <lb/>ſometimes White, ſometimes Obſcure, but <lb/>for the moſt part Thick and
            Muddy. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_41" n="42"/>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Frequent Vomitings, and Convulſion-Fits <lb/>are ſometimes Signs of <hi
              rend="italic">Worms</hi>; that is, <lb/>when the Vomitings throw up nothing but
            <lb/>what has been eaten, and the Convulſions <lb/>are without Foaming at the Mouth. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Sometimes they riſe in their Sleep, and <lb/>move their Lips as if they were
            eating: To <lb/>know if theſe Symptoms are from <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>,
            <lb/>obſerve, if they are eas'd by Abſtinence; <lb/>for they that have <hi rend="italic"
              >Worms</hi>, cannot faſt with- <lb/>out finding themſelves tormented; not by
            <lb/>Hunger, for many times they have no Ap- <lb/>petite; but by Twitchings and
            Tearings, <lb/>caus'd by the various Motions of the <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>
            <lb/>in ſearch of Food. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>A dry Cough is very often a Sign of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>; by this <hi
              rend="italic">Foreſtus</hi> knew, that a lit- <lb/>tle Girl, who had been ſix Months
            ill of a <lb/><hi rend="italic">Quartan-Ague</hi>, was troubl'd with <hi rend="italic"
              >Worms</hi>; <lb/>he preſcrib'd her Medicines accordingly, <lb/>which brought away
            five <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>, and her <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ague</hi> thereupon
            left her. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>A Stinking-Breath is very often a Sign; <lb/>ſo <hi rend="italic">Braſſavolus,</hi>
            viſiting an old Man eighty <lb/>Years of Age, who ſeem'd to lye a dying, <lb/>knew by
            his Breath that he was troubl'd <lb/>with <hi rend="italic">Worms;</hi> he thereupon
            directed him <pb xml:id="page_42" n="43"/>
            <lb/>ſome <hi rend="italic">Vermifuges,</hi> which ſcour'd away five <lb/>hundred <hi
              rend="italic">Worms,</hi> and cur'd him. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Raging Hunger many times proceeds <lb/>from <hi rend="italic">Worms,</hi> when 'tis
            accompany'd with <lb/>extream Leanneſs, tho' the Party eat much; <lb/>thus a Boy, about
            twelve Years of Age <lb/>(<hi rend="italic">ſays</hi> Foreſtus) had kept his Bed for
            ſeve- <lb/>ral Months, and was dry'd almoſt to a <hi rend="italic"> Ske-
            <lb/>leton</hi>, without feeling any other Illneſs than <lb/>a ſlight Pain in his Belly,
            near his Navel: <lb/>The Phyſician was at firſt a little at a ſtand <lb/>to find out the
            Diſtemper, the Cauſe of <lb/>which he could not imagine; for the Child <lb/>eat very
            well, tho' to no Purpoſe; his <lb/>Urine was of a good Conſiſtency and Co- <lb/>lour,
            tho' ſomewhat Crude and Wateriſh; <lb/>but the Pain of his Belly, together with his
            <lb/>extraordinary Hunger, caus'd him to ſuſpect <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>:
            Therefore, for ſeveral Days, twice <lb/>a Day, he order'd a Glaſs of the Decoc-
            <lb/>tion of <hi rend="italic">Hyſſop</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Marjoram</hi>, <hi
              rend="italic">Fennel</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Fumitory</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >Centaury</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Wormwood</hi>, with <hi rend="italic"
            >Oxymel</hi>, Sy- <lb/>rup of <hi rend="italic">Fumitory</hi>, and Honey of <hi
              rend="italic">Roſes.</hi> This <lb/>Medicine, every time he took it, caus'd <lb/>him
            to void a great Number of <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>, <lb/>and perfectly cur'd him. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The particular Signs differ according to <lb/>the Species of <hi rend="italic"
              >Worms.</hi>
          </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_43" n="44"/>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The Signs of Long and Round <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>, <lb/>are Tenſions of the
            Belly, with Hardneſs <lb/>and Pain, Itching of the Noſe, Corroſion <lb/>of the Guts,
            Hiccoughs, a Palpitation in <lb/>Sleep, Waking with ſudden Startings, or <lb/>Shrieks,
            an unequal Pulſe, intermitting <lb/>Fevers, of which the Party will have three <lb/>or
            four Fits, without any certain Order; <lb/>the Eyes hollow, and ſometimes red; the
            <lb/>Cheeks ſometimes glowing red, and ſome- <lb/>times of a Lead Colour; ſometimes they
            <lb/>want a Stomach, and vomit after Eating; <lb/>they have Fevers, accompany'd with
            Cold <lb/>in the extream Parts of the Body: Theſe <lb/>Signs never meet altogether, but
            ſome- <lb/>times one, ſometimes another. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The Signs of <hi rend="italic">Aſcarides</hi> are a continual <lb/>Itching in the
            Fundament, cauſing Faint- <lb/>ings, and ſometimes Swoonings; the Itch- <lb/>ing
            proceeds from the Motion of theſe <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worms,</hi> and the quick Senſe
            of the Part <lb/>where they lye. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The Signs of the <hi rend="italic">Tænia,</hi> or Tape <hi rend="italic">Worm</hi>,
            <lb/>are Laſſitude, and Faintings after Meat; <lb/>frequent Numbneſs and Dulneſs in the
            Day- <lb/>time, which cauſe an Heavineſs above the <lb/>Navel, tho' theſe may proceed
            from other <lb/>Cauſes. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_44" n="45"/>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The Signs of the <hi rend="italic">Cucurbitini</hi> are little <lb/>Bodies, like
            the Seeds of <hi rend="italic">Cucumers</hi> or <lb/><hi rend="italic">Melons,</hi>
            found in the Excrements; I ſup- <lb/>poſe they are the young Brood not yet <lb/>link'd
            together. Both <hi rend="italic">Hippocrates</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> Ari-
              <lb/>ſtotle</hi> mention theſe as certain Signs; to <lb/>which may be added ſhifting
            Pains of the <lb/>Liver, accompany'd with great Fluxes of <lb/>Spittle; Pains in the
            Stomach ſucceed <lb/>thoſe of the Liver by Intervals, and ſome- <lb/>times attended with
            tedious Pains in the <lb/>Back. </p>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
              <lb/>Some Obſervations from <hi rend="roman">Baglivi</hi>. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>When Children are obſerv'd to rub their <lb/>Bellies very much, 'tis a Sign of
                <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>; <lb/>eſpecially if they are often grip'd. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Very often it happens, that Perſons are <lb/>ſuddenly, and without any apparent
              Cauſe <lb/>or Signs of any other Diſtemper, reduc'd <lb/>to the extreameſt Danger,
              like the Aſſault <lb/>of an <hi rend="italic">Apoplexy</hi>, with Coldneſs of the ex-
              <lb/>tream Parts, a creeping Pulſe (which is <lb/>moſt commonly a Sign of <hi
                rend="italic">Worms,</hi> as is alſo <lb/>the Hiccough) Swooning, and ſometimes
              <lb/>a ſudden Madneſs; in ſuch a Caſe we <lb/>ought to ſuſpect <hi rend="italic"
                >Worms,</hi> and to preſcribe <lb/>accordingly. </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_45" n="46"/>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Bleeding by Drops, in continual Fevers, <lb/>from the Noſtrils, is ſometimes a
              Sign of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worms,</hi> as very Judicious Authors have aſ-
              <lb/>ſerted. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Whenever there is the leaſt Cauſe to <lb/>ſuſpect <hi rend="italic">Worms,</hi>
              by no Means defer the Ad- <lb/>miniſtration of Remedies; for they often <lb/>occaſion
              ſudden Death to grown Perſons, <lb/>as well as to Children or Infants. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Whatever Diſtemper Children are trou- <lb/>bled with, <hi rend="italic"
                >Worms,</hi> are always to be ſuſpect- <lb/>ed; for either they immediately encreaſe
              <lb/>the Diſeaſe, or by Reaſon of its Continu- <lb/>ance, the Seeds of <hi
                rend="italic">Worms</hi> are hatch'd into <lb/>Life, and fill the Bowels with that
              peſtife- <lb/>rous Vermine. </p>
            <figure rend="space">
              <figDesc rend="space">A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
            </figure>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="chapter">
          <pb xml:id="page_46" n="47"/>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc rend="space">A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
          <head rend="align-center space sc size(1.25)">
            <lb/>Chap. IV. </head>
          <head rend="italic align-center space size(1.25)">
            <lb/>Of the Remedies for the Deſtroy- <lb/>ing of <hi rend="roman">Worms</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="align-center">
            <lb/>And they are, </p>
          <p rend="indent space" n="1">
            <lb/>1. <hi rend="dc(2)">E</hi>Xternal Applications, as <hi rend="italic"> Fomenta-
              <lb/>tions</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Cataplaſms</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Ointments</hi>,
              <hi rend="italic"> Pla- <lb/>ſters</hi>, all which are not a little beneficial;
            <lb/>For as Dr. <hi rend="italic">Fuller</hi> obſerves, <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> do
            ſo <lb/>ſecurely burrow, and intrench themſelves <lb/>in the Foldings and Cavities of
            the Bowels, <lb/>as to eſcape and elude the Impreſſion of <lb/>Purging, or other
            Medicines; for which <lb/>Reaſon outward Applications are very uſe- <lb/>ful to diſturb
            them from their lurking Pla- <lb/>ces, and ſo expoſe them to the Attacks of
            <lb/>Internals, which may deſtroy, and expel <lb/>them. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_47" n="48"/>
          <p rend="indent space" n="2">
            <lb/>2. Internal Adminiſtrations, which by a <lb/>ſpecifick Quality, diſturb and kill
            them; <lb/>the Forms of theſe are various as <hi rend="italic">Liquors</hi>, <lb/><hi
              rend="italic">Syrups</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Powders</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
              >Boluſſes</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Pills</hi>, &amp;c. where- <lb/>of ſome are
            Purgative, others not; in the <lb/>Uſe of which Dr. <hi rend="italic">Andry</hi>
            recommends the <lb/>following Obſervations. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>That the beſt Time to take them is in <lb/>the Wain of the Moon; he confeſſes, he
            <lb/>look'd upon this at firſt as an idle Fancy, <lb/>but that his Experience convinc'd
            him of <lb/>his Miſtake. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>That in the Adminiſtration of Reme- <lb/>dies for the <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>,
            there ought to be due <lb/>Intermiſſions; leſt being too vigorouſly <lb/>attack'd, they
            ſhou'd retire into the Ca- <lb/>vity of the <hi rend="italic">Gut-Colon,</hi> where they
            wou'd <lb/>be very much out of the reach of Medi- <lb/>cines. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>As for <hi rend="italic">Gliſters,</hi> they are obſerv'd to be <lb/>very uſeful,
            and they are of two general <lb/>Kinds; Sweet and Bitter. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The Latter are of great Efficacy againſt <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Aſcarides;</hi>
            which (as Dr. <hi rend="italic">Fuller</hi> ob- <pb xml:id="page_48" n="49"/>
            <lb/>ſerves) are a ſmall, but an almoſt invin- <lb/>cible Nation; for tho' you ſhou'd
            waſh <lb/>away all by one <hi rend="italic">Gliſter,</hi> yet a new and <lb/>numberleſs
            Off-ſpring will quickly diſco- <lb/>ver themſelves, being produc'd of the Seed <lb/>of
            the former, depoſited in the <hi rend="italic">Rectum</hi>; <lb/>ſo that 'twill not be
            ſufficient to have ex- <lb/>pell'd the Parents, unleſs their Poſterity <lb/>be alſo
            vigorouſly proſecuted and deſtroy'd; <lb/>this may be done, if after the <hi
              rend="italic">Aſcarides</hi> diſ- <lb/>appear, we do not preſently deſiſt, but re-
            <lb/>peat theſe bitter Injections for ſome time, <lb/>once in two or three Days at
            firſt, and af- <lb/>terwards once a Week. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>But for the <hi rend="italic">Teretes,</hi> or long and round <lb/><hi
              rend="italic">Worms,</hi> theſe bitter Injections are by no <lb/>Means proper, ſo long
            as they are brisk, <lb/>lively and agile, and inclin'd to get up <lb/>into the Stomach,
            or ſmall Guts, leſt be- <lb/>ing driven upon thoſe Parts, they ſhou'd <lb/>occaſion a
            great deal of Miſchief there; <lb/>but after the Uſe of other Medicines, which <lb/>have
            made them Sickly, and thruſt them <lb/>down, the Exhibition of ſuch <hi rend="italic"
              >Gliſters</hi>
            <lb/>may be very ſeaſonable and ſucceſſ- <lb/>ful. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The ſweet <hi rend="italic">Gliſters</hi> made of Milk, Su- <lb/>gar, <hi
              rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> are convenient before the Uſe <pb xml:id="page_49" n="50"/>
            <lb/>of the Bibber ones, when the <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> are <lb/>lurking in the
            ſmall Guts, where, by gnaw- <lb/>ing and tearing the Bowels, they excite <lb/>violent
            Pains in the Belly; for the <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>
            <lb/>take to the Milk, being pleaſant and agree- <lb/>able to them, and ſo leave off
            preying on <lb/>the Bowels, and are alſo entic'd out of <lb/>their Burrows, and
            following the agree- <lb/>able Liquor, are diſpos'd to come away by <lb/>Stool. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc rend="space">A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
          <div type="part">
            <head rend="italic align-center size(1.25) space">
              <lb/>A View of ſome of the moſt <lb/>celebrated Remedies. </head>
            <p rend="hanging space">
              <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Simon Pauli</hi>'s Worm Powder, which <lb/>expell'd a great
              Number of the <hi rend="italic"> Cucur- <lb/>bitini.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText>
              <body>
              <p rend="italic indentall hanging space">
                <lb/>℞ C. C. rad filic. a ʒij Corallin. ſem <lb/>ſancton. a ʒj Myrrh lig. Al. fl.
                Sulph. <lb/>a ʒſſ. Nitri. ʒiij M. f. Pulvis doſ. <lb/>ʒj. </p></body>
            </floatingText>
            <p rend="hanging space">
              <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Nic. Andry</hi>'s Powder, which brought <lb/>away that
              large Chain of <hi rend="italic">Cucurbitini,</hi>
              <lb/>and cur'd the Patient of a <hi rend="italic">Pleuriſy</hi>, men- <lb/>tion'd <hi
                rend="italic">Page</hi> 16. </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_50" n="51"/>
            <floatingText>
              <body>
              <p rend="italic indentall hanging">
                <lb/>℞ Diagryd. Crem. Tart. Diaphor. Miner. <lb/>Rhab. rad. filicis fæmin. a ʒſs
                Tana- <lb/>cet fol. &amp; fl. p. i. Cort. rad Mori. <lb/>ʒj M. f. Pulv. in juſculo
                pingui <lb/>mane, jejuno Ventriculo exhiben- <lb/>dus. </p></body>
            </floatingText>
            <p rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Electuarium Vermifugum. </p>
            <floatingText> <body>
              <p rend="italic indentall hanging space">
                <lb/>℞ Succ. Menth. &amp; Trifol. fibrin a ℥ij <lb/>Rutæ &amp; Marrhubij albi a ℥j
                coq. <lb/>leviter cum Sacch. alb. ℔j &amp; deſ- <lb/>pumentur tum adde Corallin.
                &amp; ſ. <lb/>Tanacet ac ſancton a ℥ſs Cinnam &amp; <lb/>Cardamom min. a ℥ij Cort.
                Citr. <lb/>condit. ℔ſs &amp; f. Elect. </p></body>
            </floatingText>
            <p rend="hanging space">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">Scharff</hi>'s Eſſence for <hi rend="italic">Worms,</hi> which
              expell'd <lb/>a <hi rend="italic">Worm</hi> of a very great Thickneſs. </p>
            <floatingText><body>
              <p rend="italic indentall hanging space">
                <lb/>℞ Herb. Abrotan, Scordij Tanacet a <lb/>Mj. Rad dictam filicis Zedoar. a
                <lb/>℔ſs fl Centuar Mj. Perſicor p. ij Co- <lb/>rallin ℥iſs. ſ. Sancton. Coriand. a
                ʒvj <lb/>Bacc. Junip. ℥ij Myrrh. Theriac. a <lb/>℥ſs. Conciſ. Contuſ. infunde in S.
                q. <lb/>Sp. Juniper rectif. Tinctum quod eſt <lb/>ſeparetur; Novus Sp. affundatur;
                <lb/>conjunctis liquoribus addendo Sp. <lb/>C. C. ſale volatili impregnati ℥ij. f.
                <lb/>Eſſentia. </p></body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb xml:id="page_51" n="52"/>
            <p rend="align-center">
              <lb/>A Fomentation by Dr. <hi rend="italic">Fuller</hi>. </p>
            <floatingText><body>
              <p rend="italic indentall hanging space">
                <lb/>℞ Rad Ariſtoloch. rot. ℥j Herb. Abſ. <lb/>vulg. Abrotan. fæm. Tanacet Sabin.
                <lb/>a Mj. Helleborast. Mſs. Pulp. Colo- <lb/>cynth. Aloes. a ʒj f Dec. in aq ℔iij
                <lb/>ad ℔ij col. pro fotu ope ſtupharum <lb/>Abdominis regioni calide uſurpan-
                <lb/>do. </p></body>
            </floatingText>
            <p rend="hanging space">
              <lb/>After uſing this <hi rend="italic">Stupe</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                >Fomentation,</hi> the <lb/>following <hi rend="italic">Pultice</hi> may be laid on
              the <lb/>Navel. </p>
            <floatingText><body>
              <p rend="italic indentall hanging space">
                <lb/>℞ Ther. Ven. Farin. Lupin. a ʒiij ſem <lb/>Sancton ʒiſs hier picr. ʒſs Ol. Ab-
                <lb/>ſinth. Still. gt. xvj ſucc. Tanacet. qſ. <lb/>F. Cataplaſma </p></body>
            </floatingText>
            <p rend="align-center space">
              <lb/>Or this Plaiſter. </p>
            <floatingText><body>
              <p rend="italic indentall hanging space">
                <lb/>℞ Aloes ℥ij Ol. Abſ. chym. gt. viij-cum <lb/>fell. bov. qſ. F. Maſſa quæ ſuper
                Alu- <lb/>tam ducta Umbilico applicetur. </p></body>
            </floatingText>
            <p rend="hanging space">
              <lb/>A Bitter Gliſter to expel and kill the <hi rend="italic"> Aſca- <lb/>rides</hi>,
              from Dr. <hi rend="italic">Fuller.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText><body>
              <p rend="italic indentall hanging space">
                <lb/>℞ Rad. ſerp. V. ʒj Colocynth. ℈j Herb <lb/>Tanacet Sabinæ a Mſſ. f. decoctio in
                  <pb xml:id="page_52" n="53"/>
                <lb/>aq. F. qſ. col. ℥vj adde Ol. Hyperic. <lb/>℥ſſ. Ol. Abſ. Chym. ʒſſ. ſp. Hier
                <lb/>picr. ℈ſſ. M. </p></body>
            </floatingText>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>The ſame may be us'd for the other Sorts <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Worms,</hi>
              but then others made of Milk <lb/>ought to preceed, for Reaſons before-men-
              <lb/>tion'd. Dr. <hi rend="italic">Fuller</hi> gives the following for <lb/>this
              Purpoſe. </p>
            <floatingText><body>
              <p rend="italic indentall hanging space">
                <lb/>℞ Lact. Vaccin. rec. ℥vj Theriac Ja- <lb/>nuenſ. ℥ij M. </p></body>
            </floatingText>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>The Honourable Mr. <hi rend="italic">Boyle,</hi> in his Trea- <lb/>tiſe of <hi
                rend="italic">Specifick Medicines,</hi> commends <hi rend="italic">Small
                <lb/>Beer</hi> frequently ſhaken with good <hi rend="italic"> Quick-
                <lb/>ſilver</hi>, as an excellent Remedy to kill <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>;
              <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Quickſilver</hi> communicating its Virtue, <lb/>without
              changing the Colour or Taſte of <lb/>the Liquor. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Æthiops Minerable</hi> has been gene- <lb/>rally obſerv'd
              to have very happy Effects; <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Harris</hi>, in his Treatiſe of
              Children's <lb/>Diſeaſes, relates an extraordinary Cure per- <lb/>form'd by that
              Medicine, as follows. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">J. P.</hi> A Boy of Thirteen Years of Age, <lb/>was ſo pin'd
              away with a <hi rend="italic">Conſumption</hi> by <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worms,</hi>
              as it prov'd, that he was more like <lb/>a <hi rend="italic">Skelaton,</hi> than a
              living Perſon; his Eyes <pb xml:id="page_53" n="54"/>
              <lb/>hollow, his Noſe ſharp, and his Bones only <lb/>cover'd with Skin; he became
              ſenſeleſs, <lb/>and ſo weak, that he could ſcarce crawl <lb/>from one Side of the Room
              to the other <lb/>with the Swiftneſs of a <hi rend="italic">Snail</hi>; all his Ex-
              <lb/>crements by Urine and Stool, fell involun- <lb/>tarily from him. By taking the
              foreſaid <lb/><hi rend="italic">Medicine</hi> twice a Day for ſome Time, and
              <lb/>gently Purging every fourth Day without <lb/><hi rend="italic">Rhubarb,</hi> he
              voided a great many <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>, <lb/>and recover'd perfectly well. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Such, whoſe Curioſity leads them to en- <lb/>quire more fully after Inſtances of
              this Na- <lb/>ture, may conſult the elaborate Works of <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic"
                >Nicholas Andry,</hi> and Dr. <hi rend="italic">Daniel Clerc,</hi>
              <lb/>who have treated very largely on this Sub- <lb/>ject. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_54" n="55"/>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal floral ornament, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>AN <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">APPENDIX</hi>
        </head>
        <head rend="italic align-center space size(1.25)">
          <lb/>Concerning the firſt Original of <lb/><hi rend="roman">Worms</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">I</hi>T has been already obſerv'd in the <lb/>preceeding Treatiſe,
          that even unborn <lb/><hi rend="italic">Infants</hi> are not always free from <hi
            rend="italic">Worms</hi>, <lb/>which <hi rend="italic">Valliſneri</hi>, an <hi
            rend="italic">Italian</hi> Phyſician, en- <lb/>deavours to Account for in the following
          <lb/>Manner. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Chyle (ſays he)</hi> appointed for the <lb/>Nouriſhment of the
            <hi rend="italic">Infant</hi>, is firſt pre- <lb/>par'd in the Stomach of the Mother,
          and <lb/>render'd more perfect and pure by the Di- <lb/>geſtions and Glands of the Bowels.
          Now, <lb/>ſince the <hi rend="italic">Inteſtines</hi> are the general Seat of <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Worms</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic">Fetus</hi> is for ſeveral Months
          <lb/>nouriſh'd by this <hi rend="italic">Chyle</hi>, the Seeds of <hi rend="italic"
            >Worms</hi>, <pb xml:id="page_55" n="56"/>
          <lb/>which are in the Mother's Bowels, mixing <lb/>with the Flower of the <hi
            rend="italic">Chyle</hi>, are, by the <lb/>uſual Paſſages, carry'd along to the <hi
            rend="italic"> Mem- <lb/>branes,</hi> which involve the <hi rend="italic">Fetus</hi>: By
          this <lb/>Means it may be eaſily gueſs'd how the <hi rend="italic"> In- <lb/>fant</hi> may
          receive this Verminous Progeny <lb/>into its own Bowels. But if it happen, <lb/>that the
          Mother be either entirely free, or <lb/>having <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>, they ſhou'd
          not happen to <lb/>ſpawn during the Time of her being <lb/>pregnant, then, indeed, the <hi
            rend="italic">Infant</hi> will <lb/>not be infeſted with them in this Manner; <lb/>but
          if this <hi rend="italic">Infant</hi> ſhou'd happen to be <lb/>ſuckl'd by another Woman,
          who has <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>, her Milk may furniſh the Child <lb/>with a
          Colony of theſe Inſects, ſince Milk <lb/>differs not from <hi rend="italic">Chyle</hi>,
          and is convey'd from <lb/>the Bowels to the Breaſts. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But whence (it may be demanded) have <lb/>this Mother or Nurſe theſe <hi
            rend="italic">Worms</hi>, which <lb/>they thus communicate to the Child? 'Tis
          <lb/>anſwer'd, they have alſo receiv'd them in <lb/>the Manner aforeſaid; and that they
          have <lb/>been ſo convey'd down through all Ages, <lb/>from the Beginning of the World,
          and the <lb/>firſt Parents of Mankind. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>And, indeed, ſince the Seeds of Things, <lb/>none excepted, were created at the
          Begin- <lb/>ning of the World, all Sorts of Inſects, <pb xml:id="page_56"/>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>An illustration of a type of worm. </figDesc>
            <head rend="italic">
              <lb/>Fig. 1. </head>
          </figure>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>An illustration of worm eggs. </figDesc>
            <head rend="italic">
              <lb/>Fig. 2. </head>
          </figure>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>An illustration of a type of tapeworm. </figDesc>
            <head rend="italic">
              <lb/>Fig. 3. </head>
          </figure>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>An illustration of a part of a worm. </figDesc>
            <head rend="italic">
              <lb/>Fig. 4. </head>
          </figure>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>An illustration of a section of a worm. </figDesc>
            <head rend="italic">
              <lb/>Fig. 5. </head>
          </figure>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>An illustration of a section of a worm. </figDesc>
            <head rend="italic">
              <lb/>Fig. 6. </head>
          </figure>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>An illustration of a section of a worm. </figDesc>
            <head rend="italic">
              <lb/>Fig. 7. </head>
          </figure>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>An illustration of a section of a worm. </figDesc>
            <head rend="italic">
              <lb/>Fig. 8. </head>
          </figure>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>An illustration of ten smaller worms. </figDesc>
            <head rend="italic">
              <lb/>Fig. 9. </head>
          </figure>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>An illustration of three hookworms. </figDesc>
            <head rend="italic">
              <lb/>Fig. 10. </head>
          </figure>
          <pb xml:id="page_57" n="57"/>
          <lb/>may vie with Man himſelf for the Anti- <lb/>quity of their Original; and foraſmuch as
          <lb/>thoſe <hi rend="italic">Worms,</hi> which inhabit the Bowels of <lb/>Mankind, are
          never found elſewhere; it <lb/>muſt be inferr'd, that their Seeds were ori- <lb/>ginally
          implanted in the Body of the firſt <lb/>Man, or Woman. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>At this Rate, 'twill be objected, all Per- <lb/>ſons muſt neceſſarily be poſſeſs'd
          with theſe <lb/>Inſects, or elſe their Succeſſion might fail. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>'Tis ſuppos'd, that the Seeds or Eggs of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> may lye a
          long Time within every <lb/>Man's Body; and theſe, ſometime or other, <lb/>as Occaſion
          offers, be produc'd into Life, <lb/>which, without ſuch Occaſion, wou'd have <lb/>remain'd
          unchang'd: Thus, in a certain <lb/>ancient Perſon, the Eggs of the <hi rend="italic"
            >Tape-Worm</hi>
          <lb/>were hatch'd not 'till after the fifty fifth <lb/>Year of his Age, at which Time he
          began <lb/>to be moleſted with that kind of <hi rend="italic">Worm</hi>; <lb/>either
          becauſe the Juices of his Bowels had <lb/>never before gotten that Quality, which was
          <lb/>requiſite to vivify thoſe Eggs; or becauſe <lb/>the Place was not rightly diſpos'd
          for that <lb/>Purpoſe. But thoſe that in this Man were <lb/>ſo ſlowly excluded, may be
          much ſooner <lb/>in another, even before his Birth, or in his <lb/>Childhood, or Youth,
          according as Cir- <lb/>cumſtances may favour their Production. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_58" n="58"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Again, in many Perſons they may be <lb/>never animated; becauſe there may be al-
          <lb/>ways wanting a ſuitable Diſpoſition of the <lb/>Humours, or Place to produce them,
          juſt <lb/>as the Eggs of the <hi rend="italic">Vermis Africanus</hi>; for <lb/>Example,
          tho' they may be lodg'd in the <lb/>Skin or Fleſh of every Many, yet this In- <lb/>ſect
          troubles none but <hi rend="italic">Africans</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> and
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Arabians</hi>; not the Inhabitants of the <hi rend="italic"> Nor-
            <lb/>thern</hi> Climates, becauſe the Heat of <hi rend="italic">Africa</hi>, <lb/>or <hi
            rend="italic">India,</hi> promotes the Vivification of theſe <lb/>Eggs, which cannot be
          animated in colder <lb/>Countries; as on the other hand the Seeds <lb/>of the <hi
            rend="italic">Taenia,</hi> by Reaſon of the Moiſture of <lb/>the Climate, are render'd
          fruitful amongſt <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Hollanders</hi>, which in <hi rend="italic"
            >India</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Africa</hi>, <lb/>becauſe of the extream Drineſs of
          thoſe <lb/>Regions, are unprolifick. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>This Notion is confirm'd by the Obſer- <lb/>vation of <hi rend="italic"
            >Hemmerſam</hi>, who ſpeaking of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Vermis Africanus</hi>, ſays,
          'tis worth noting, <lb/>that thoſe, who only ſail by <hi rend="italic">Guiney</hi>, feel
          <lb/>an Itching in the Skin, chiefly in that of <lb/>the Arms and Legs; but moſt commonly
          <lb/>in the Thighs: This Itching certainly indi- <lb/>cates the beginning Motion of the
            <hi rend="italic">Vermis <lb/>Africanus,</hi> excited by the Heat of that <lb/>Country. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_59" n="59"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Every one knows, how much Heat, and <lb/>the Fermentation of Juices, conduces to the
          <lb/>Production of Animals. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Neither is the ſeeming Uſeleſsneſs of ſo <lb/>many Seeds, conſequent upon this
          Notion, <lb/>any juſt Objection, when the ſame may be <lb/>ſaid of many other Seeds,
          whereof the <lb/>much greater Part is often loſt; and that <lb/>Loſs not to be accounted
          of, if we conſider <lb/>their infinite Number. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Nor, laſtly, ought we to object the of- <lb/>ten long Continuance of theſe Eggs in
          the <lb/>Body, before they are vivify'd; for as <lb/>much as the Seeds of ſeveral Plants
          kept <lb/>many Years, and afterwards committed to <lb/>the Earth, do germinate as readily
          as if <lb/>they had been freſh; and the <hi rend="italic">Ova</hi> of Wo- <lb/>men
          advanc'd in Years, are often equally <lb/>prolifick with thoſe of younger Women. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Theſe <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>, then (may the Objector <lb/>further argue) were
          created by God in the <lb/>Body of <hi rend="italic">Adam</hi>, either before his Fall, or
          <lb/>afterwards; but if we conſider Man as he <lb/>was firſt created, perfectly Innocent,
          it <lb/>ſeems not probable, that the juſt and good <lb/>God would implant ſuch foul
          Vermine in <lb/>his immaculate Body. And beſides, as <pb xml:id="page_60" n="60"/>
          <lb/>that State of Innocence was entirely free <lb/>from all manner of Diſeaſes, and
          poſſeſs'd <lb/>of a perfect Happineſs, undiſturb'd by any <lb/>Diſorder of Body, it were
          impoſſible he <lb/>ſhould have any <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> in his Bowels; <lb/>which
          we find, by daily Experience, are the <lb/>Cauſes of innumerable Diſorders; and even
          <lb/>of Death it ſelf. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Nor can it eaſily be imagin'd, how this <lb/>filthy Inſect, hatch'd, and nouriſh'd in
          Pu- <lb/>trefaction, could ſuit with that ſweet man- <lb/>ner of Living, directed by the
          Light of <lb/>pure Reaſon, void of all Intemperance, <lb/>and its Conſequences; which
          produce that <lb/>putrid Humour, proper to receive, and pro- <lb/>duce the Eggs of <hi
            rend="italic">Worms.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>To have Recourſe to the Divine Preſci- <lb/>ence in this Caſe, <hi rend="italic"
            >viz.</hi> That God foreſee- <lb/>ing the Apoſtacy of his Creature, prepar'd <lb/>for
          his Puniſhment, would be very unrea- <lb/>ſonable, ſince the Suffering ſhould by no
          <lb/>means preceed the Offence. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>If on the other hand we ſay, that theſe <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> were form'd
          after the Alteration of <lb/>his Nature, by his Diſobedience to the Di- <lb/>vine Command,
          the Difficulty will be yet <lb/>greater; for then 'twill follow, that God <lb/>began a new
          Creation, which is contrary <pb xml:id="page_61" n="61"/>
          <lb/>to the Tenour of the ſacred Scriptures, <lb/>which inform us that God, before he
          crea- <lb/>ted Man, produc'd all other Creatures; not <lb/>excepting Inſects. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>To remove theſe Objections, 'tis aſſerted, <lb/>That before Man's Formation, all
          other <lb/>Animals, Plants, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> were created; and <lb/>that Man
          was laſt form'd out of the <lb/>Mud. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>That in this Mud, thoſe <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>, which <lb/>were a little before
          created, were implant- <lb/>ed, and ſo enter'd in the Compoſition of his <lb/>Body, being
          probably deſign'd by Provi- <lb/>dence, whilſt he continu'd Innocent, to be <lb/>very
          uſeful to him, and to contribute to the <lb/>Perfection of his Body; and, ſhould he af-
          <lb/>ter lapſe from his Integrity, become a Pu- <lb/>niſhment to him. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Now, tho' this may ſeem ſtrange, that <lb/><hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> ſhould any
          way conduce to the Be- <lb/>nefit and Perfection of our Bodies, yet let <lb/>us conſider. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>That thoſe <hi rend="italic">Machines,</hi> which are ſelf- <lb/>moving, as Watches,
            <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> are always e- <lb/>ſteem'd more Perfect and Surprizing,
          the <lb/>more they comprehend other <hi rend="italic">Machines</hi>, e- <lb/>qually
          Curious, within their Structure. And <pb xml:id="page_62" n="62"/>
          <lb/>is not the World accounted more Perfect, <lb/>by containing ſuch an infinite Variety
          of <lb/>Animals, great and ſmall, honourable and <lb/>baſe, as they are call'd; if any of
          its <lb/>Countries prove deſtitute of Inhabitants, <lb/>are they not accounted unhappy,
          and deſ- <lb/>picable? Why ſhould not, then, our little <lb/>World be eſteem'd more
          compleat, by <lb/>being furniſh'd with its proper Inhabi- <lb/>tants? </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Nor would it be any Injury to our firſt <lb/>Parent, to ſuppoſe his Body the Recepta-
          <lb/>cle of various and wonderful Inſects, which, <lb/>whilſt he continu'd Innocent, were
          ſo far <lb/>from being Pernicious to him, that they <lb/>render'd him more Perfect, and
          redounded <lb/>to his Honour. They liv'd quietly, and <lb/>amicably with him, and ſed on
          the Super- <lb/>fluities of indigeſted Food only; they ex- <lb/>ceeded not their juſt
          Limits, they abſtain'd <lb/>from preying on the Bowels, and did no <lb/>Injury to the
          Walls of their Incloſures, but <lb/>gently licking and cleanſing their Man- <lb/>ſions;
          they gratefully requited the Bene- <lb/>fit of their Reception: Moreover, if the
          <lb/>Fibres of the Bowels were at any time <lb/>become torpid, or oppreſs'd with too copi-
          <lb/>ous, or excrementitious Juices, which might <lb/>be detrimental to the Body; theſe
          might <lb/>excite them to the brisker Diſcharge of <pb xml:id="page_63" n="63"/>
          <lb/>their Functions; in ſhort, they might be <lb/>no ways Noxious, but very Beneficial. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But this Felicity of <hi rend="italic">Adam</hi> prov'd but <lb/>ſhort; for by
          Rebelling againſt his Maker, <lb/>the Natures of all Things were ſoon chang'd; <lb/>and
          then theſe <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi> alſo became the Mi- <lb/>niſters of Divine
          Vengeance, as well as <lb/><hi rend="italic">Lyons</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Tigers</hi>,
            <hi rend="italic">Serpents</hi>, and other deſtructive <lb/>Animals. </p>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <trailer rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
