<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: An account of the vertues, use, dose, and wonderful manner
          of operation of the pilulæ polychrestæ</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">AN ACCOUNT OF THE Vertues, Use, Dose, and wonderful manner of
              Operation OF THE Pilulæ Polychrestæ. Which Speedily and Safely extirpate those
              Opprobria's of Physicians, the Gout, Madness and Melancholy of all Sorts, Stone and
              Gravel in the Kidneys, &amp;c. herein specified.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T18455</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T18455"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed in the year, MDCCXIX.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1719</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="15"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107227139</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K029243.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: medicine"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>AN <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">ACCOUNT </hi><lb/>OF THE <lb/><hi
            rend="dc(2)">Virtues, Uſe, Doſe, and <w part="I">won-</w><lb/><w part="F">derful</w>
            manner of Operation </hi><lb/>OF THE <lb/><hi rend="italic dc(2)">Pilulæ
            Polychreſtæ.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="space"><lb/>
            <figure>
              <figDesc>Decorative frame around the letter "A".</figDesc>
            </figure> 
          <hi rend="dc(4)">A</hi>S there ſeems no Neceſſity to <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >dicate</w> to the Reader the Signs <lb/>and Cauſes of thoſe dangerous <lb/>Diſeaſes
          that are moſt certainly <lb/>and ſafely cured by the <hi rend="italic">Pilulæ
            <lb/>Polychreſtæ,</hi> (for <hi rend="italic">Non Eloquentiâ <lb/>ſed remediis curantur
            morbi,</hi> ſaid <hi rend="italic">Celſus,</hi> that <w part="I">Pri-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">vy-Councellor</w> to Nature) ſo we thought it <pb xml:id="page_3" n="4"
          /><lb/>better to be potent in Fact than only to <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >pear</w> puiſſant in Words, (as do the Generality <lb/>of our modern Doctors) and to
          relieve Perſons <lb/>under exquiſite Pain, than to divert our <w part="I">Rea-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">der</w> with Concluſions drawn from Topicks <lb/>grounded on fundamental Truths
          or eſſential <lb/>Verities: Expect not therefore to meet with <lb/>many profound
          Philoſophical Hypotheſis's, or <lb/>that I ſhould prove the abſtruce Principles, or
          <lb/>real Grounds of Sympathy, or concupiſcible <w part="I">At-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >traction</w> and Coition; nor with Mathematical <lb/>Demonſtrations, which I mention
          laſt, becauſe <lb/>I think the leaſt neceſſary in Phyſick. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is enough, (at leaſt for a time) that we <lb/>have made known (for
          univerſal Good) ſuch a <lb/><hi rend="italic">Polichreſtick,</hi> or Sovereign Medicine,
          as one <w part="I">o-</w><lb/><w part="F">perating</w> Conſimilar to it can't be produced
          by <lb/>any Doctor, Chymiſt, or Apothecary in <hi rend="italic">Great <lb/>Britain:</hi>
          Yea, and ſuch a one as will extirpate <lb/>thoſe Hydra's of Diſeaſes undermentioned,
          <lb/>which have for ſo many Ages bid Defiance to <lb/>the moſt eminent and ſage
          Phyſicians. Let <lb/>not this ſeem a bold and emperical Aſſertion, <lb/>but ſuſpend your
          Verdict till you have peruſed <lb/>the following Account; which before we <w part="I"
            >pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceed</w> to give, it will be requiſite to tell you, <lb/>that
          the Author has uſed them with admirable <lb/>yea almoſt incredible Succeſs, above theſe <w
            part="I">Thir-</w><lb/><w part="F">ty</w> Three Years, not only in this Metropolis,
          <lb/>but in moſt Parts of <hi rend="italic">Great Britain;</hi> and tho' he <lb/>ſeldom
          adminiſtred them to any but ſuch as <lb/>were (by the ableſt Phyſicians) pronounced <w
            part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">curable</w>, and had languiſhed under their <w part="I"
            >Miſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">fortunes</w>, ſome Three, ſome Seven, ſome Ten <lb/>and ſome
          Twenty Years, yet there were none, <pb xml:id="page_4" n="5"/><lb/>tho' their Caſes were
          never ſo complicated, or <lb/>of never ſo long Continuance, but were in the <lb/>Space of
          one Month (at moſt) reſtored (by the <lb/>help of theſe Pills) to a perfect State of
          Health. <lb/>And tho' I could nominate above a hundred <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >traordinary</w> and almoſt incredible Cures <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >formed</w> by them, (to many of which ſome of <lb/>our eminent Doctors now in being are
          no <w part="I">Stran-</w><lb/><w part="F">gers)</w> yet I decline it, and refer the Matter
          <lb/>to Experience, which is the only true Examen <lb/>or <hi rend="italic">Lydian</hi>
          Touch-ſtone, to diſtinguiſh Truth <lb/>from Falſity, and matter of Fact from ſpurious
          <lb/>and odible Impoſture. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_5" n="6"/>
      <head rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">The Vertues of theſe</hi>
        <lb/>PILULÆ POLYCHRESTÆ. </head>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Firſt,</hi> THEY Cure all <hi rend="italic"
          >Manias</hi> or Madneſs <lb/>in either Sex, but ſooner in Men <lb/>than Women, by reaſon
        of the <hi rend="italic">Furer Uterinus,</hi>
        <lb/>which is commonly either the primary or <w part="I">ſecon-</w><lb/><w part="F">dary</w>
        Cauſe; concerning which Diſeaſe, and <lb/>the miſtaken Notions both of its Cauſe and Cure,
        <lb/>I propoſe at a convenient Time to treat. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="2"><lb/><hi rend="italic">2dly</hi>. Melancholly of all Sorts whteher <w
          part="I">Sple-</w><lb/><w part="F">netic</w>, Hypocondriac, or Hyſteric, which is
        <lb/>commonly called Vapours, tho' of ever ſo long <lb/>Duration. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="3"><lb/><hi rend="italic">3dly</hi>. Pains in the Head, chiefly <w
          part="I">Sympathe-</w><lb/><w part="F">tic</w>, that is, which proceed from ſome <w
          part="I">Indiſpo-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſition</w> of the Hypochonders, Spleen, Womb, <hi
          rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="4"><lb/><hi rend="italic">4thly</hi>. All wandering Pains, whether <w
          part="I">Rheu-</w><lb/><w part="F">matic</w>, or Scorbutic, in any part of the Body. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="5"><lb/><hi rend="italic">5thly</hi>, Pains in the Stomach, whether from
        <lb/>Wind pent up in Viſcid Slime, or from ſome <lb/>pungent, acid, or acrid Humour,
        pricking, and <lb/><unclear>##</unclear>l<unclear>##</unclear>cating the Veſſels. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="6"><lb/><hi rend="italic">6thly</hi>. The Cholic, from what Cauſe ſoever. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="7"><lb/><hi rend="italic">7thly.</hi> The Stone and Gravel in the Kidneys. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_6" n="7"/>
      <p rend="indent" n="8"><lb/><hi rend="italic">8thly</hi>. Suppreſſion of Urine, either from
        <lb/>Stones, Gravel, Sand, Wind, or ſlimy Matter, <lb/>whence Stones, <hi rend="italic"
          >&amp;c.</hi> are commonly generated. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="9"><lb/>9thly. Obſtructions in the Liver and Spleen, <lb/>and <hi
          rend="italic">Ductus Biliarius,</hi> or Gall Paſſage. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="10"><lb/>10thly. Heat and Hardneſs of the Liver, <lb/>which uſually cauſes
        the Jaundies, both yellow <lb/>and black, and a ſchirrhus or ſtony Hardneſs <lb/>of the
        Liver, generally thought incurable; and <lb/>indeed if the Patient hath been a hard Drinker
        <lb/>and in Years; if likewiſe the Diſtemper has <lb/>been of long Continuance, it may be
        concluded <lb/>ſo; but if none of theſe Three Circumſtances <lb/>occur, theſe Pills have
        been found <w part="I">experimen-</w><lb/><w part="F">tally</w> to reſtore the Liver to its
        proper Function. <lb/>They alſo perfectly cure the black and yellow <lb/>Jaundies. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="11"><lb/><hi rend="italic">11thly</hi>. Dropſies of all Sorts, whether
        Aſcites, <lb/>Anaſarcites, or Tympanities, which is a <w part="I">Drop-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſy</w> of the Womb, or that Diſeaſe which in <w part="I">out-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ward</w> Appearance Symboliſeth with it, the <lb/>Tumor of the Ovarium, (as ſome Doctors
        call it) <lb/>whether from Wind or Water, or both: But <lb/>as the Tympany of the Womb,
        always <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceeds</w> from Wind, 'tis impoſſible to cure it
        by <lb/>Purges, the more you exhibit the worſe they <lb/>are; neither by Tapping, after
        which I don't <lb/>remember one to have lived above 14 Days. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="12"><lb/>12thly. The Gout, provided it be neither <lb/>Nodoſe nor
        Cretaceous, that is, if it be <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">companied</w> with neither
        Knots, nor Chalky <lb/>Concretions in the Joynts: And one Doſe taken <lb/>Spring and Fall
        perfectly prevents its returning <pb xml:id="page_7" n="8"/><lb/>under any Form or Symptom
        whatever, in any <lb/>Part of the Body. What Affinity there is <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">tween</w> the Chalky Concretions lodged in the <lb/>Joynts of Gouty People, and
        the Stone <w part="I">gene-</w><lb/><w part="F">rated</w> in the Kidneys, ſhall one time or
        other <lb/>be farther conſider'd. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="13"><lb/><hi rend="italic">13thly.</hi> The Pleuriſie, and all Pains in
        the <lb/>Sides, or in any other Part of the Body, <w part="I">whe-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ther</w> wandering or fixed, tho' of the longeſt <lb/>Continuance, without Bleeding,
        Cupping, or <lb/>bliſtering. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="14"><lb/><hi rend="italic">14thly,</hi>The Palſy, whether of any <w
          part="I">particu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lar</w> Part or Member of the Body, or <w part="I"
          >univer-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſal</w> all over; whether with a Tremor or <w part="I"
          >trem-</w><lb/><w part="F">bling</w>, or numb or dead, (as it is called): <w part="I"
          >pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">vided</w> they have been neither Vomited, <w part="I"
          >Pur-</w><lb/><w part="F">ged</w>, nor Clyſtered; much leſs Blooded, <w part="I"
          >Bliſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">tered</w>, or Cupped. Provided alſo that the <w part="I"
          >Pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tient</w> be of a Plethoric, or full habit of Body, <lb/>not
        Thin, Meagre, or Lean, Old, or <w part="I">Super-</w><lb/><w part="F">annuated</w>; or that
        the Palſy hath not <w part="I">ſu-</w><lb/><w part="F">pervened</w> ſome preceding
        Diſtemper, as a <lb/>Fever, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> then theſe Pills will certainly
        <lb/>reſtore the Members to their Priſtine Strength, <lb/>and the Patient to perfect Health. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="15"><lb/><hi rend="italic">15thly,</hi> All hardneſs with Extenſion or <w
          part="I">ſwel-</w><lb/><w part="F">ling</w> of the Peritonæum, and Belly, not only <w
          part="I">a-</w><lb/><w part="F">bout</w> the Navel, but between that and the Pit <lb/>of
        the Stomach, accompany'd with pain and <lb/>difficulty of bending the Body downwards:
        <lb/>Which in Men, hath by many Doctors been <lb/>taken for a Dropſy, (as they do a Tympany
        of <lb/>the Womb) and handled with the like Succeſs. <pb xml:id="page_8" n="9"/><lb/>Several
        other Caſes I could mention, ſurpaſſing <lb/>belief, attended with ſuch Symptoms as the
        <lb/>Doctors could neither tell what to call, nor <lb/>how to manage; which perhaps we may
        take <lb/>occaſion to inſert in the next Edition of theſe <lb/>Directions. This only will I
        add, as a general <lb/>Rule, that in all Cronic and Complicated Caſes, <lb/>if the Party
        hath ſtore of Fluids, theſe Pills <lb/>are never given without the deſired Succeſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I have by by this time ('tis ſuppos'd) a little <lb/>ſtartled you, by
        citing ſuch a Scroll or <w part="I">Cata-</w><lb/><w part="F">logue</w> of direful Diſeaſes,
        and the Gout it ſelf, <lb/>which for many Ages hath withſtood the force <lb/>of all
        Medicines that could be oppoſed, by the <lb/>moſt learned Academicks; I ſay, no doubt but
        <lb/>you'll wonder, that they ſhould be eradicated <lb/>by a Doſe or Two, of one only
        Medicine; <lb/>but we boldly and openly bid defiance to all <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >Æſculapian</hi> Tribe in <hi rend="italic">Great Britain,</hi> to <w part="I"
          >pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duce</w> a Medicine operating like this, the <w part="I"
          >ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſequent</w> Account of which will probably put <lb/>the matter
        out of all Diſpute, and to your <w part="I">en-</w><lb/><w part="F">tire</w> Satisfaction. </p>
      <div type="part">
        <pb xml:id="page_9" n="10"/>
        <head rend="italic align-center"><lb/>Their manner of Operation, and <lb/>the Method of
          ordering the <lb/>Patient. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>A Convenient Room with a Fire in it, <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ing</w> provided, and Two Perſons to <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tend</w>, let the Patient go into a warmed Bed, <lb/>at Eight a Clock in the Evening
          (or any <w part="I">o-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> time in caſe of Neceſſity) put at the
          ſame <lb/>time a blade or two of Mace and an upper <lb/>Cruſt of Bread, into a Pint of
          Ale, and cover <lb/>it up cloſe: Which done, give him the Pills in <lb/>the Pulp of a
          roaſted Apple, (which is the beſt) <lb/>or a Wafer moiſtened with Water or Canary,
          <lb/>drinking nothing either with, or after them; <lb/>then compoſing himſelf, he will
          preſently be a <lb/>Sleep, and continue ſo Four Hours, and no <lb/>longer; during which
          time he will ſweat moſt <lb/>powerfully, and care muſt be had neither to <lb/>wipe the
          Sweat off his Face, nor do any thing <lb/>elſe to diſturb him. The Four Hours being
          <lb/>expired, and the Patient awake, let two <w part="I">Peo-</w><lb/><w part="F">ple</w>
          rub him dry with hot Cloaths, and put on <lb/>him a clean hot Shirt and Gown; then bring
          <lb/>him to the Fire, and let him eat a Morſel of <lb/>the Bread, and ſip ſome of the Mace
          Ale made <lb/>very hot, and well ſweetned with ſingle <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >fined</w> Loaf-Sugar; when he hath done this, <lb/>and drank the remaining part of the
          Ale, <lb/>Sweating will immediately ceaſe, which is <hi rend="italic">è
            <lb/>diametro,</hi> or directly contrary to all the <w part="I">Su-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >dorifics</w> or Sweating Medicines now in uſe. <pb xml:id="page_10" n="11"
          /><lb/>Preſently after they work plentifully by Urine, <lb/>(which when cold, in ſome
          Caſes and <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtitutions</w> may be cut with a Knife as
          Size.) <lb/>To ſee the Contents of which, a clean White-<lb/>Ware Chamber-Pot muſt be in a
          readineſs, for <lb/>they cleanſe the Kidnies and Ureters of <w part="I">a-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">bundance</w> of Stones, Sand, Slime, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> if any
          <lb/>be lodged there: When he has been up <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">twixt</w> a
          quarter and half an Hour, let him <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">pair</w> to Bed
          again, it being turned and well w<lb/>armed, or another well ſeaſoned put in its
          <lb/>place, the Sheets and Blankets likewiſe being <lb/>changed, and others well heated
          put on; then <lb/>the Pills begin to work ſtrongly, by breaking <lb/>Wind downwards, to
          his own and the <w part="I">by-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtanders</w> great ſurprize. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Patient muſt neither eat nor drink <lb/>any thing till Dinner, if
          he can faſt ſo long; <lb/>if he can't, a Morſel of Bread, and a quarter <lb/>of a Pint of
          hot Ale, ſweetened with ſingle <lb/>refined Loaf-Sugar may be taken. Let his <lb/>Dinner
          be hot, but neither of baked, fryed, <lb/>nor frigofy'd Meat, his drink alſo muſt be
          <lb/>hot, and I forbid Wines of all ſort, during the <lb/>whole courſe of theſe
          Operations, and 24 <lb/>Hours after they all ceaſe, and it would be <lb/>better if
          neceſſity would permit to forbear <lb/>Wine for 24 Hours before the Pills are taken. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>About two Hours after Dinner they begin <lb/>to work downwards by
          Stool, except the <w part="I">Pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tient</w> has Obſtructions in the
          Liver, Kidneys, <lb/>Lacteals, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> or a Tympany of the Womb, or
          <lb/>that Diſtemper which the Doctors call a <w part="I">Tu-</w><lb/><w part="F">mor</w>
          of the <hi rend="italic">Ovarium;</hi> in all which caſes, and <pb xml:id="page_11" n="12"
          /><lb/>ſome others, the working by Stool is <w part="I">intro-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >duced</w> by one large but eaſy Vomit; without <lb/>any previous Nauſea, or Sickneſs
          which brings <lb/>up none of the Meat with it. During the <lb/>time they Purge, which is
          without any <w part="I">Sick-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w> or Gripes, the Patient muſt by
          no means <lb/>ſtop a Motion, or expoſe himſelf to any cold <lb/>or damp Air, or place;
          neither (except in <lb/>Caſes of extream Thirſt, which I never knew <lb/>to happen) muſt
          he drink any thing; but if <lb/>Thirſtineſs urge, a little Tea, made of good
          <lb/>Juniper-berries, and ſweetned with ſingle <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >fined</w> Loaf-Sugar, may be drank. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>About an Hour and half, or two Hours at <lb/>moſt, after Supper (which
          muſt be hot,) the <lb/>Patient muſt go to a well warmed Bed; and <lb/>the Pills taken the
          Night before, will repeat <lb/>their Operations ſucceſſively as at firſt, but in <lb/>a
          much weaker degree: So that ſometimes <lb/>there is no occaſion either to rub the Party or
          <lb/>change his Linnen. In ſome Caſes and <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſtitutions</w>, the firſt Doſe will work 2 or 3 <lb/>Nights and Days, and the ſecond
          Doſe 3 or 4, <lb/>eſpecially in hot Weather, or Summer Time; <lb/>and then there muſt be
          an Intermiſſion of 2 <lb/>or 3 Days before the Third Doſe be taken; <lb/>but two Doſes
          commonly perform the Cure, <lb/>be the Caſe never ſo Chronic and Complicated: <lb/>In all
          my 33 Years Practice and upward, I <w part="I">ne-</w><lb/><w part="F">ver</w> knew but
          one Patient that had Occaſion <lb/>for the Third Doſe; whoſe Caſe and many <lb/>others
          very wonderful, ſhall in another Eſſay <lb/>be fully related. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_12" n="13"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Indeed their manner of Operation is ſo <lb/>particular and
          extraordinary, that I almoſt <lb/>think it hath ſcarce been parallell'd in any <lb/>Age;
          for tho' they work moſt powerfully <lb/>by all the Emunctories, yet they are ſo gentle
          <lb/>and agreeable to Nature, that ſhe is not only <lb/>exceedingly refreſh'd by them
          afterwards; <lb/>but even pleaſs'd with the ſeeming <w part="I">Diſtur-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">bance</w> they give her. Hence 'tis no wonder <lb/>that theſe <hi rend="italic"
            >Pilulæ Polychreſtæ,</hi> ſhould extirpate ſo <lb/>many dreadful Diſeaſes in ſo ſhort a
          time. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <pb xml:id="page_13" n="14"/>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">The</hi> DOSE </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">O</hi>F theſe Pills is firſt Four, then Five,
          <lb/>laſtly Six, taken as above: But if the <lb/>Patient labours under any acute and
          painful <lb/>Diſeaſe, as the Gout, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> let him begin with
          <lb/>Five, increaſing one the next Doſe. After the <lb/>Cure of any Chronic Diſtemper,
          'tis requiſite <lb/>to take one Doſe every Spring and Fall, which <lb/>muſt be as large as
          the laſt Doſe that was taken <lb/>before, and this will be ſufficient to carry off
          <lb/>whatever peccant Matter may be collected ſince <lb/>the laſt Time of taking. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe Pills are ſealed up in little Thumb <lb/>Bottles, by which means
          their Vertues will <lb/>be preſerved Twenty Years in all Regions; but <lb/>obſerve that in
          all hot Climates, the Doſe muſt <lb/>be leſs than in <hi rend="italic">England</hi> or a
          colder Climate. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Sold only at Mr. <hi rend="italic">Winſtone</hi>'s at the <hi
            rend="italic">Black Boy</hi>
          <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Comb,</hi> near <hi rend="italic">Fleet Bridge</hi> in <hi
            rend="italic">Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> at <lb/>One Guinea <hi rend="italic">per</hi> Bottle,
          containing Three Doſes, <lb/>two of which is commonly ſufficient to cure <lb/>many of the
          aboveſaid Diſeaſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Where this Book is gave away gratis, to any <lb/>one that will ask for
          it. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>For the Encouragement of the Buyers, and <lb/><unclear>##</unclear>at
          they may not in the leaſt ſuſpect being <lb/><unclear>###</unclear>pos'd upon, any Perſons
          agreeing to the <pb xml:id="page_14" n="15"/><lb/>Propoſals made at the Place of Sale, may
          be <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tended</w>, and no Money received till the Cure
          <lb/>be perfected. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">N. B.</hi> No Woman with Child muſt take <lb/>theſe
          Pills, nor any one that hath an <hi rend="italic">Eryſipelas,</hi>
          <lb/>(which is the St <hi rend="italic">Anthony</hi>'s Fire) <hi rend="italic"
            >Elephantiaſis,</hi> or <lb/><hi rend="italic">Noli me Tangere.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Above all things great Care muſt be taken, <lb/>that no ſort of Liquor
          be drank, either <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſently</w> before, with, or after
          theſe Pills; even <lb/>not ſo much as one Drop to moiſten the Mouth <lb/>or waſh them
          down, otherwiſe they will be of <lb/>no Effect. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Secondly,</hi> Obſerve that while the Patient
          ſweats, <lb/>no more Cloaths be put upon him than uſual. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Laſtly,</hi> All the Directions given in this Paper,
          <lb/>are to be exactly and punctually obſerved, if <lb/>you intend to receive Benefit by
          them, or elſe <lb/>you muſt blame your ſelf and not me. </p>
      </div>
      <trailer rend="italic align-center"><lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
