<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Smith: The curiosities of common water</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>John Smith</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">THE CURIOSITIES OF Common Water: OR The Advantages thereof in
              Preventing and Curing many Distempers. Gather'd from the Writings of several Eminent
              Physicians, and also from more than Forty Years Experience. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">N2997</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N2997"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Roberts, in Warwick-Lane; A. Dodd, without
                  Temple-Bar; and J. Fox, in Westminster-Hall, M.DCC.XXIII. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1723</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="76"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">National Library of Medicine</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3308104482</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K001932.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: method"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2" n="3"/>
        <head rend="align-center space"><lb/>THE <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">CURIOSITIES</hi>
          <lb/>OF <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">Common Water.</hi></head>
        <p rend="space"><lb/>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>Decorative frame around the letter "F".</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <hi rend="dc(4)">F</hi>OR the Benefit of Mankind <lb/>in general, I have taken <lb/>pains
          to give the World an <lb/>Account of what I have <lb/>found written in the Works of
          <lb/>the moſt eminent Phyſicians <lb/>concerning the Good that Mankind may <lb/>receive
          from the Uſe of Common Water, <lb/>and of the Informations I have had <w part="I"
            >con-</w><pb xml:id="page_3" n="4"/><lb/><w part="F">cerning</w> the Benefits thereof
          from others <lb/>by word of mouth; and of what I have <lb/>diſcover'd by my own Experience
          from <lb/>frequent Tryals during a time that hath <lb/>intervened from that of thirty to
          ſeventy <lb/>four Years of Age: which is ſufficient to <lb/>confirm the ſtupendous Effects
          thereof in <lb/>many Particulars, that ſhall be mentioned <lb/>as my own Diſcovery with
          reſpect to this <lb/>excellent Remedy, which will perform <lb/>Cures with very little
          Trouble, and <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w part="F">out</w> any Charge, and is alſo to be
          had <lb/>wherever there are any Habitations, which <lb/>is what can hardly be ſaid of any
            <w part="I">o-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> thing: ſo that in ſome ſenſe, Water <lb/>may
          truly be ſtiled <hi rend="italic">An Univerſal <w part="I">Reme-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >dy</w>,</hi> ſince the Diſeaſes it either prevents or <lb/>cures may have this Remedy
          applied to all <lb/>Perſons, and in all Places where Men do <lb/>inhabit. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The firſt Commendation of Common <lb/>Water that I ſhall mention, is
          that which <lb/>is written concerning it by Dr. <hi rend="italic">Manwa-<lb/>ring,</hi> in
          his <hi rend="italic">Method and Means of <w part="I">enjoy-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>
            Health;</hi> wherein he ſaith, that <w part="I">Wa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> is a
          wholeſome Drink, or rather the <lb/>moſt wholeſome—being appointed for <lb/>Man in his
          beſt State: which doth <w part="I">ſtrong-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> argue that Drink to
          be the moſt <w part="I">ſuit-</w><lb/><w part="F">able</w> for human Nature—anſwering all
          <lb/>the Intentions of common Drinks, for it <pb xml:id="page_4" n="5"/><lb/>cools,
          moiſtens and quencheth Thirſt; 'tis <lb/>clear, thin, and fit to convey the <w part="I"
            >Nouriſh-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w> through the ſmalleſt Veſſels of the <lb/>Body—and
          is a Drink that is a Rule to <lb/>itſelf, and requires little Caution in the <lb/>Uſe of
          it, ſince none will be tempted to <lb/>drink of it more than needs: And that <lb/>in the
          Primitive Ages of the World, <w part="I">Wa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter-Drinkers</w>, he
          ſays, were the longeſt <lb/>Livers by ſome Hundreds of Years— <lb/>nor ſo often ſick and
          complaining, as we <lb/>are. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Keill,</hi> when he treats concerning <lb/>the
          Stomach, in his <hi rend="italic">Abridgment of the <lb/>Anatomy of Human Bodies,</hi>
          ſaith, that <lb/>Water ſeems the fitteſt to promote <w part="I">Di-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >geſtion</w> of the Food which we eat; all <lb/>ſpirituous Liquors having a Property by
          <lb/>which they hurt, rather than help <w part="I">Di-</w><lb/><w part="F">geſtion</w>;
          the ſad Effects of which they <lb/>are ſenſible of, he ſaith, who by a long <lb/>uſe
          thereof have loſt their Appetite, <w part="I">hard-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> ever to be
          reſtored without drinking <lb/>Water, which ſeldom faileth of procuring <lb/>a good
          Appetite and a ſtrong Digeſtion. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Prat,</hi> in his <hi rend="italic">Treatiſe of
            Mineral <lb/>Water,</hi> ſhews it to be his Judgment, that <lb/>if People would accuſtom
          themſelves to <lb/>drink Water, they would be more free <lb/>from many Diſeaſes; ſuch as
            <hi rend="italic">Tremblings, <pb xml:id="page_5" n="6"/><lb/>Palſies, Apoplexies,
            Giddineſs, Pains in <lb/>the Head, Gout, Stone, Dropſy, <w part="I">Rheuma-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">tiſm</w>, Piles, and ſuch like:</hi> Which <w part="I">Diſ-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">eaſes</w> are moſt common among them that <lb/>drink ſtrong Drinks, and which
          Water <lb/>generally would prevent. Moreover, he <lb/>alſo ſaith, that Water plentifully
          drank <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſtrengthens the Stomach, cauſeth an <w part="I"
              >Ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">petite</w>, preſerves the Sight, maketh the <lb/>Senſes
            lively, and cleanſeth all the <w part="I">Paſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſages</w> of the
            Body,</hi> eſpecially thoſe of the <lb/>Kidneys and Bladder. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>'Tis ſaid alſo by Dr. <hi rend="italic">Duncan,</hi> in his <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Treatiſe of hot Liquors,</hi> that when Men <lb/>contented themſelves with
          Water, they <lb/>had more Health and Strength; and that <lb/>at this day thoſe who drink
          nothing but <lb/>Water, are more healthy, and live longer <lb/>than thoſe who drink ſtrong
          Liquors, <lb/><hi rend="italic">which raiſes the Heat of the Stomach to <lb/>Exceſs,
            whereas Water keeps it in a due <lb/>Temper.</hi> And he adds in another part of
          <lb/>the Book, that by hot Liquors the Blood <lb/>is inflamed; and ſuch whoſe Blood is <w
            part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">flamed</w>, live not ſo long as thoſe who are <lb/>of a
          cooler Temper: <hi rend="italic">a hot Blood being <lb/>commonly the Cauſe of Fluxes,
            Rheums, <lb/>ill Digeſtion, Pains in the Limbs, <w part="I">Head-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ach</w>, Dimneſs of Sight,</hi> and eſpecially of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hyſteric
            Vapours.</hi> He alſo imputes the <lb/>Cauſe of Ulcers to a hot Blood, and <w part="I"
            >de-</w><pb xml:id="page_6" n="7"/><lb/><w part="F">clares</w>, that if Men kept their
          Blood cool <lb/>and ſweet, <hi rend="italic">by a moderate cooling Diet,</hi>
          <lb/>they would never be troubled with <w part="I">Ul-</w><lb/><w part="F">cers</w>, or
          other Breakings out. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Sir <hi rend="italic">John Floyer</hi> alſo, in the Preface to
          <lb/>his <hi rend="italic">Treatiſe of Cold Baths,</hi> does affirm, <lb/>that Vapours
          both in Men and Women <lb/>are cauſed by hot things, and that <hi rend="italic">by
            <lb/>leaving off ſtrong Liquors and a hot Diet, <lb/>and by drinking Water,</hi> he had
          procured <lb/>to himſelf a better Health, and more <lb/>Hardineſs, than he had enjoyed for
          many <lb/>Years. And in the Body of that Book <lb/>he affirmeth, that drinking of Water in
          <lb/>the Morning, <hi rend="italic">cools the Blood, prevents <lb/>Defluxions, and waſhes
            off the bilious <lb/>and ſalt Recrements by Urine;</hi> and that <lb/>drinking Water
          after Dinner, <hi rend="italic">cools and <lb/>ſtops the too high Fermentation of the
            <lb/>Stomach,</hi> which is the Cauſe of breeding <lb/>Wind or Belching after Meat: to
          the <lb/>Truth of which, the Author of this <w part="I">Ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">count</w>
          can bear a full Teſtimony, who <lb/>being for many Years afflicted with this <lb/>belching
          up of Wind after Meat, did at <lb/>length prevent the ſame, by drinking <lb/>Water after
          eating, inſtead of other Drink, <lb/>which in time did cool that <hi rend="italic"
            >Hypochon-<lb/>driack Heat,</hi> from whence thoſe Belchings <lb/>did proceed. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_7" n="8"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Having read over an old Book written <lb/>by one Sir <hi rend="italic"
            >Tho. Eliot,</hi> entitled, <hi rend="italic">The <w part="I">Ca-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ſtle</w> of Health,</hi> he there declared from his <lb/>own Experience, that in the
          County of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cornwall,</hi> tho it was a very cold <w part="I"
            >Quar-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w>, the Poorer Sort, which in his time <lb/>did never,
          or but very ſeldom drink any <lb/>other Drinks but Water, were ſtrong of <lb/>Body, and
          lived to a very great Age; to <lb/>which Relation that of Sir <hi rend="italic">Henry
            Blount</hi>
          <lb/>is very agreeable who affirmed, in his <lb/><hi rend="italic">Book of Travels into
            the</hi> Levant, (where <lb/>under the <hi rend="italic">Turkiſh</hi> Government the Uſe
          <lb/>of Wine was forbid, <hi rend="italic">and where the <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">mon</w> Drink is Water</hi>) that he then had a <lb/>better Stomach to his
          Food, and digeſted <lb/>it more kindly than he ever did before <lb/>or ſince. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And in the Treatiſe of the <hi rend="italic">Vanity of
            <lb/>Philoſophy,</hi> written by Dr. <hi rend="italic">Gideon <w part="I"
              >Har-</w><lb/><w part="F">vey</w>,</hi> it is affirmed by him, that it is not
          <lb/>Heat that cauſeth a good Digeſtion, <hi rend="italic">but <lb/>a proper Ferment or
            Liquor provided by <lb/>Nature,</hi> to diſſolve the Food into a <w part="I"
            >Sub-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtance</w> like unto Pap made with fine <lb/>Flower: which
          Diſſolvent, he ſaith, is <lb/>much depraved by hot ſpirituous Liquors, <lb/>and therefore
          he commends Water above <lb/>all other Drinks to promote Digeſtion. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_8" n="9"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Water-drinking is alſo ſaid by Dr. <hi rend="italic">Al-<lb/>len</hi>
          to be good to prevent two deplorable <lb/>Diſtempers, <hi rend="italic">the Gout and the
              <w part="I">Hypochon-</w><lb/><w part="F">driack</w> Melancholy;</hi> for, ſays he,
          the Gout <lb/>is generally cauſed by the too great <w part="I">drink-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ing</w> of fermented Liquors, <hi rend="italic">and is never <lb/>ſaid to have
            aſſaulted any Drinker of <lb/>Water;</hi> and he ſaith alſo, that <hi rend="italic"
            >Melan-<lb/>choly Hypochondriack</hi> is kept off longeſt <lb/>by drinking Water inſtead
          of ſtrong <lb/>Drink. To which let me add, that I once <lb/>knew a gouty Gentleman, who,
          to avoid <lb/>his drinking Companions in <hi rend="italic">London,</hi>
          <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">tired</w> to <hi rend="italic">New Brentford,</hi>
          where I then <lb/>lived; in which Town, by a very <w part="I">tempe-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >rate</w> Diet of one Meal a day, and <w part="I">drink-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>
          only Water, he lived two whole Years <lb/>free from Pain: but being viſited by one
          <lb/>who came that way, and invited to drink <lb/>but one Bottle of Claret between them,
          <lb/>he fell next day into a terrible Fit of the <lb/>Gout, which held above a Month
          after; <lb/>of which being recover'd, he by the ſame <lb/>Courſe continued well till I
          left the Place, <lb/>which was about a Year and a half after. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The good Properties of Water are <w part="I">fur-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ther</w> manifeſted in preventing the <w part="I">breed-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> of
          Gravel in the Kidneys; for <hi rend="italic">Zechias,</hi>
          <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">Conſult.</hi> 17. as he is quoted by <hi rend="italic"
            >Salmon,</hi>
          <lb/>affirms, that nothing doth ſo much abate <pb xml:id="page_9" n="10"/><lb/>the Heat of
          the Kidneys, and free them <lb/>from thoſe Recrements which cauſe Pain <lb/>in the Back,
            <hi rend="italic">one great ſign of Gravel,</hi> as <lb/>Water does: but he adviſeth to
          drink it <lb/>warm, by the Uſe of which, he ſaith, the <lb/>unnatural Heat in time will be
          ſo <w part="I">extin-</w><lb/><w part="F">guiſhed</w>, that no more of that Matter
          <lb/>cauſing Gravel will be produced in the <lb/>Body. Which Aſſertion, by Experience
          <lb/>I have found to be true: for <w part="I">obſerv-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> much
          Gravel to be voided by me, as <lb/>alſo abundance of Matter floating in the <lb/>Urine
          like Bran, with a great number of <lb/>Recrements like Cuttings of Hair, ſome <lb/>above
          an Inch long; <hi rend="italic">which Subſtances <lb/>were found in all the Water I made
            in <lb/>above twelve Months;</hi> for which I could <lb/>get no Remedy: I was adviſed to
          <lb/>drink Water, which in about half a Year <lb/>did entirely free me from thoſe <w
            part="I">Symp-</w><lb/><w part="F">toms</w> which ſome imputed to Witchcraft <lb/>out of
          Ignorance; ſo that from that time <lb/>to this preſent I never have been troubled
          <lb/>with it. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Water alſo is commended as efficacious <lb/>to prevent the breeding of
          the Stone in <lb/>the Bladder, for it hath been obſerved, <lb/>that in ſome who have been
          cut for the <lb/>Stone, that new Stones have been <w part="I">ingen-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >der'd</w>, ſo that ſome young Perſons have <lb/>been cut ſeveral times. Now to prevent
            <pb xml:id="page_10" n="11"/><lb/>this, the drinking Water hath been <w part="I"
            >ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">viſed</w> with Succeſs; for by this that <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">temperate</w> Heat in the Body was abated, <lb/>which did
          occaſion the Diſtemper. Some <lb/>have adviſed to drink it warm, and others <lb/>cold, and
          in particular <hi rend="italic">Van Heydon,</hi> a <lb/>Phyſician of <hi rend="italic"
            >Ghent</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Flanders,</hi> in his <lb/>Book, entitled, <hi
            rend="italic">Help for the Rich and <lb/>Poor;</hi> which he ſaith, in <hi rend="italic"
            >p.</hi> 49. is <w part="I">ſuffi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ciently</w> inſinuated by <hi
            rend="italic">Piſo</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Alexander,</hi>
          <lb/>who do aſſure us, that the taking a <lb/>Draught of cold Water in the Morning,
          <lb/>hath done ſo much good, that ſeveral <w part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> the
          voiding of a Stone never had any <lb/>more Stones grow in them. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Which Experiment may give light to <lb/>the Diſcovery of a way to cure
          the Stone <lb/>without cutting; for if the growing of <lb/>new Stones can be prevented by
          drinking <lb/>Water, let it be hot or cold, <hi rend="italic">it may <w part="I"
              >pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">vent</w> a Stone from growing bigger when <lb/>begun;</hi>
          and if the aiding Matter to <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">creaſe</w> a Stone new
          begun, can be <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">vented</w>, Nature in time may waſte
          that <lb/>which is begun, eſpecially if ſome Drops <lb/>of ſweet Spirit of Nitre be added
          to all the <lb/>Water drank, which will powerfully <lb/>help to cool, and is known to be
          an <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">mirable</w> Mover or Provoker of Urine, and
          <lb/>will waſte a Stone, and make it crumble <lb/>like Fullers Earth, if applied to a
          Stone <pb xml:id="page_11" n="12"/><lb/>taken from the Body. Or the Water may <lb/>be
          ſweeten'd with Honey, which is now <lb/>much in uſe among the Gentry, as I am
          <lb/>informed by an ingenious Apothecary; <lb/>who told me, that among them at preſent
          <lb/>Pump-Water and Honey was in great <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">pute</w> to
          give eaſe in Gravel: and there is <lb/>ſo near an Affinity between Gravel and <lb/>the
          Stone, that what is proper for one, <lb/>will be ſuitable to both, and will prevent
          <lb/>the growing of both. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Water is alſo ſtiled in <hi rend="italic">Sennertus</hi>'s <hi
            rend="italic">Works</hi>
          <lb/>the Balſam of Children, the drinking of <lb/>it by the Mother being one of thoſe
          things <lb/>whereby Children may be ſtrengthen'd <lb/>in the Womb, and will prevent thoſe
            <w part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F">juries</w> that are done them by drinking
          <lb/>ſtrong Liquors; which <hi rend="italic">Sampſon</hi>'s Mother <lb/>was not allowed to
          do, for ſhe was <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">manded</w>
          <hi rend="italic">not to drink Wine or ſtrong <lb/>Drink,</hi> Judg. 13.4. But I will not
          ſay, <lb/>if all Women ſhould do this, their <w part="I">Chil-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >dren</w> ſhall be as ſtrong as <hi rend="italic">Sampſon</hi> was; <lb/>yet this I will
          ſay, if they would do this, <lb/>they would find their Children more free <lb/>from
          Diſtemper and Frowardneſs, and ſo <lb/>much more eaſy to nurſe and bring up, <lb/>and be
          leſs liable to an immature Death; <lb/>the want of which Abſtinence from ſtrong
          <lb/>Drinks is the Cauſe why ſo many rich <lb/>People find it hard to bring up Children,
            <pb xml:id="page_12" n="13"/><lb/>in compariſon to what is done by the <lb/>Poor: for
          theſe laſt are born of Mothers, <lb/>who not only are prevented from being <lb/>Gluttons
          by their want of <hi rend="italic">Dainties, <lb/>which are deceitful Meat,</hi> Prov.
          23.3. <lb/>but they ſeldom taſte Wine or ſtrong <lb/>Drink: whereas the Rich not only feed
          <lb/>high, and ſo engender foul Blood, but <lb/>they alſo drink ſtrong Drinks, which in
          <lb/>moſt Conſtitutions do over-heat the <w part="I">Hu-</w><lb/><w part="F">mours</w> of
          the Body, and that Blood by <lb/>which their Children are nouriſhed <w part="I"
            >du-</w><lb/><w part="F">ring</w> their Pregnancy. Which Injury to <lb/>unborn Infants
          would be prevented, if <lb/>the Mother would be temperate in Diet, <lb/>and drink Water,
          eſpecially at Meals, by <lb/>which the Blood of the Mother would <lb/>be kept cool and
          clean; which muſt needs <lb/>communicate a healthful Subſtance to the <lb/>Child within
          her, and prevent all thoſe <lb/>Diſtempers which Infants do bring with <lb/>them into the
          World. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And here it may be proper to add, <lb/><hi rend="italic">what by
            divers Experiments hath been <lb/>found to be true,</hi> that the drinking Water <lb/>by
          Nurſes while they give ſuck to <w part="I">Chil-</w><lb/><w part="F">dren</w>, will
          wonderfully increaſe Milk in <lb/>thoſe that want it, <hi rend="italic">as every one will
            find,</hi>
          <lb/>who can be perſuaded to make uſe <w part="I">there-</w><lb/><w part="F">of</w>. I
          have adviſed many to make uſe of <lb/>it, who have found that by drinking a <pb
            xml:id="page_13" n="14"/><lb/>large Draught of Water at Bed-time, <lb/>they have been
          ſupplied with Milk <w part="I">ſuf-</w><lb/><w part="F">ficient</w> for that Night, when
          before they <lb/>wanted it, and could not be ſupplied by <lb/>any other means: And
          beſides, they who <lb/>have found their Children reſtleſs by reaſon <lb/>of too much Heat
          in their Milk, do find <lb/>them much more quiet after their Milk <lb/>is cooled by
          Water-drinking. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>By drinking Water alſo, the want of <lb/>Food for a time may be
          ſuffered without <lb/>ſtarving; for I have been informed by a <lb/>credible Friend, who
          was an Officer at <lb/>Sea, that being ſent down to <hi rend="italic">Stafford</hi> to
          <lb/>take care to ſee ſome Men conveyed on <lb/>Ship-board, that had deen preſs'd by Act
          <lb/>of Parliament for the Sea-Service; he <lb/>found in the Priſon, <hi rend="italic"
            >where they were <lb/>kept,</hi> a luſty Fellow, who had declared <lb/>he would ſtarve
          himſelf rather than go to <lb/>Sea, and taking particular notice <w part="I"
            >there-</w><lb/><w part="F">of</w>, he found upon due Enquiry, that for <lb/>twenty days
          he had refuſed to eat any <lb/>manner of Food, <hi rend="italic">only he drank each day
            <lb/>about three Pints or two Quarts of <w part="I">Wa-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ter</w>,</hi> hoping thereby to get himſelf <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >charged</w>: but when he found his <w part="I">Preten-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſions</w> to
          be in vain, and that in about two <lb/>days they ſhould all march for <hi rend="italic"
            >London,</hi>
          <lb/>he condeſcended to eat ſome Food, <w part="I">begin-</w><lb/><w part="F">ning</w>
          with a little, and in the March he <pb xml:id="page_14" n="15"/><lb/>was obſerved to
          travel as well as the beſt <lb/>Man. I find alſo an Account in Dr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Car</hi>'s <lb/><hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi> of a certain crack-brain'd Man,
          <lb/>who, at <hi rend="italic">Leyden,</hi> when the Doctor reſided <lb/>in that
          Univerſity, pretended he could <lb/>faſt as long as Chriſt did; and it was <lb/>found that
          he held out the time of forty <lb/>Days without eating any Food, only he <lb/>drank Water
          and ſmoak'd Tobacco. And <lb/>I once had a ſad Complaint from a poor <lb/>old Woman of the
          Greatneſs of her Want, <lb/>affirming that oftentimes ſhe had not <w part="I"
            >ea-</w><lb/><w part="F">ten</w> any Food for two or three days; upon <lb/>which I asked
          her, if ſhe did not then <lb/>ſuffer much Uneaſineſs in her Stomach: <lb/>ſhe ſaid ſhe
          did, but found a way at laſt <lb/>to aſſuage her Hunger, by drinking <w part="I"
            >Wa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w>, which did ſatisfy her Appetite. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Water is alſo of great uſe to ſtrengthen <lb/>weak Children, for we
          are informed by <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Joſeph Browne,</hi> in his Treatiſe of <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Cures performed by Cold Baths,</hi> that the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Welſh</hi> Women do preſerve their Children <lb/>from the Rickets, by waſhing them
          <lb/>Night and Morning in cold Water, till <lb/>they are three quarters of a Year old,
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">p.</hi> 79. And 'tis ſaid by Sir <hi rend="italic">John
            Floyer,</hi>
          <lb/>in his <hi rend="italic">Treatiſe of Cold Baths,</hi> that a <w part="I"
            >La-</w><lb/><w part="F">dy</w> in <hi rend="italic">Scotland,</hi> who had loſt ſeveral
            <w part="I">Chil-</w><lb/><w part="F">dren</w> through Weakneſs, <hi rend="italic">did
            by the <w part="I">Ad-</w><pb xml:id="page_15" n="16"/><lb/><w part="F">vice</w> of a
            Highland Beggar-Woman</hi>
          <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerve</w> thoſe ſhe had afterwards, by <w part="I"
            >waſh-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> them daily in cold Water. And I <w part="I"
            >my-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſelf</w> did adviſe a Neighbour, whoſe Child <lb/>began to be
          ricketty, to treat the Child <lb/>in the ſame manner; but ſhe, inſtead of <lb/>waſhing,
          dipt it over head and ears every <lb/>Morning, <hi rend="italic">it being then in the <w
              part="I">Summer-</w><lb/><w part="F">time</w>:</hi> the Event of which was, the Child
          <lb/>became ſtrong, and had a good <w part="I">Counte-</w><lb/><w part="F">nance</w>, tho
          before it was in the Face very <lb/>pale and wan. Which ſhews how great <lb/>the Power of
          Water is, when uſed <w part="I">out-</w><lb/><w part="F">wardly</w>, to invigorate the
          Spirits, and <lb/>ſtrengthen Nature. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is alſo a known Cuſtom, to prevent <lb/>the Swellings that follow
          Bruiſes in the <lb/>Faces of Children, by immediately <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >plying</w> thereunto a Linnen Cloth four or <lb/>ſix times double, dipt in cold Water,
          and <lb/>new dipping it as it begins to grow warm; <lb/>for the Cold repels or prevents
          the <w part="I">flow-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> of Humours to the Part, which <w
            part="I">other-</w><lb/><w part="F">wiſe</w> would cauſe great Swelling, and after
          <lb/>turn blackiſh: and if upon neglecting to <lb/>do ſo, a Swelling ſhould ſucceed, it
          may be <lb/>diſcuſſed by fomenting Night and <w part="I">Morn-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ing</w>, for an hour at a time, with Water <lb/>as hot as can be endured; for that will
          <lb/>give vent to the Humours to tranſpire <pb xml:id="page_16" n="17"/><lb/>through the
          Skin, or diſſolve them, ſo as <lb/>to make them capable of returning back. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Moreover, by means of Water all <lb/>Sickneſs at the Stomach may be
          cured, <lb/>which is done thus: Take four Quarts <lb/>of Water, make it as hot over the
          Fire as <lb/>you can drink it; of which Water let a <lb/>Quart be taken down at ſeveral
          Draughts; <lb/><hi rend="italic">then wrap a Rag round a ſmall Piece <lb/>of a Stick, till
            it is about the Bigneſs of a <lb/>Man's Thumb,</hi> tie it faſt with ſome Thread;
          <lb/>and with this, by endeavouring gently to <lb/>put it a little way down your Throat,
          <lb/>provoke yourſelf to vomit up again moſt <lb/>of the Water: then drink another Quart,
          <lb/>and vomit up that, and repeat the ſame <lb/>the third and fourth time. You may <w
            part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſo</w> provoke Vomiting by tickling your <lb/>Throat
          with your Finger, or the Feather-<lb/>End of a Gooſe-Quill; <hi rend="italic">but the
            Cloth <lb/>round a Skuer maketh one vomit with <lb/>moſt eaſe,</hi> which is done with
          no <w part="I">Trou-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w> when the Stomach is full. And by
          <lb/>this way of Vomiting, <hi rend="italic">which will be all <lb/>performed in an hour's
            time,</hi> that vitious <lb/>and ropy Phlegm in the Stomach, which <lb/>cauſeth the
          Sickneſs, will be caſt up, ſo <lb/>that the Party in that time will be free <lb/>from all
          that inward Diſturbance, <hi rend="italic">if you <lb/>uſe the Remedy at the firſt;</hi>
          but if the <lb/>Sickneſs hath continued for a time, it <pb xml:id="page_17" n="18"
          /><lb/>will require the ſame Courſe once or <lb/>twice more, which may be done in three
          <lb/>or four Hours, one after another, <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w part="F">out</w> any
          other Inconvenience, <hi rend="italic">beſides that <lb/>of being a little ſore in the
            Breaſt the <lb/>next Day,</hi> which will ſoon go off by <lb/>the Force of Nature. Which
          Remedy, <lb/>by forty Years Experience, I look upon <lb/>to be infallible <hi
            rend="italic">in all Sickneſs at the <w part="I">Sto-</w><lb/><w part="F">mach</w> from
            what Cauſe ſoever, and for <lb/>all Pains in the Belly which ſeem to be <lb/>above the
            Navel;</hi> for theſe are all in the <lb/>Stomach, as by long Experience I have
          <lb/>found: which Pains are generally counted <lb/>the Cholick; <hi rend="italic">but it
            is not ſo,</hi> for true <lb/>Cholicks are always below the Navel, in <lb/>the <hi
            rend="italic">Gut, Colon.</hi> And by this means I have <lb/>eaſed very great Pains
          cauſed by eating <lb/>Muſſels that were poiſonous; and it is <lb/>alſo a certain Cure for
          all Surfeits or <w part="I">Diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">orders</w> that follow after much
          eating; ſo <lb/>that the Lives of Multitudes might be <lb/>ſaved by this means, who for
          want of <lb/>expelling what offends, do often die in <lb/>Miſery: For by thus cleanſing
          the <w part="I">Sto-</w><lb/><w part="F">mach</w> at the firſt, the Root of Diſeaſes
          <lb/>proceeding from Surfeiting, unwholeſome <lb/>Food, or any viſcous Humours from a
          <lb/>bad Digeſtion, are prevented; <hi rend="italic">the <w part="I">Sto-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">mach</w> being the Place in which all <w part="I">Diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >tempers</w> do at firſt begin.</hi> No Man was <lb/>more ſubject to Sickneſs than
          myſelf <w part="I">be-</w><pb xml:id="page_18" n="19"/><lb/><w part="F">fore</w> thirty
          Years of Age; but ſince I found <lb/>out the way of vomiting with Water, <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">which is now above forty Years,</hi> I never <lb/>have been ſick for two
          Days together: <lb/>for when I find myſelf ill to any great <lb/>degree, I betake myſelf
          to this way of <lb/>vomiting, <hi rend="italic">which in an hour's time <w part="I"
              >re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtores</w> me to Eaſe, and perfectly removes <lb/>my
            Illneſs;</hi> and the ſame Benefit all my <lb/>Family find in it, as do others alſo whom
          <lb/>I can perſuade to try the Experiment; <lb/>which is ſuch, <hi rend="italic">that no
            Phyſician <w part="I">what-</w><lb/><w part="F">ever</w> can adviſe a better to the King
            <lb/>himſelf, ſhould he fall ſick.</hi> For, in the <lb/>firſt place, 'tis not a
          nauſeous Remedy, it <lb/>does not make the Patient ſick, as the <lb/>beſt of all other
          Vomits do; and then <lb/>'tis a Vomit which is at our own <w part="I">Com-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">mand</w>, ſince we can leave off when we <lb/>pleaſe: and it infallibly works a
          Cure to <lb/>all ſick Stomachs. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Some few indeed pretend they are not <lb/>able to vomit by this means;
          now if <lb/>they cannot vomit, let them take a Pint <lb/>of Water when they find
          themſelves ill <lb/>from eating, and do ſo every three or <lb/>four Hours, eating no more
          till they are <lb/>hungry; and they will find the Water <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">geſt</w> and carry off what was offenſive. <lb/>The ingenious Dr. <hi
            rend="italic">Cheyne,</hi> in his <hi rend="italic">Trea-<lb/>tiſe of the Gout,</hi>
          doth affirm that warm <pb xml:id="page_19" n="20"/><lb/>Water drank freely in a Morning
          faſting, <lb/>and at Meals, (<hi rend="italic">and I ſay cold Water is as <lb/>good</hi>)
          hath been a ſovereign Remedy <hi rend="italic">for <lb/>reſtoring loſt Appetites, and <w
              part="I">ſtrengthen-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> weak Digeſtions, when other more
            <lb/>pompous Medicines have failed.</hi> And <lb/>he adviſeth Gouty Perſons, after
          Exceſs <lb/>either in Meat or Drink, <hi rend="italic">to ſwill down <lb/>as much fair
            Water as their Stomach <lb/>will bear,</hi> before they go to bed, <w part="I"
            >where-</w><lb/><w part="F">by</w> they will reap theſe Advantages, <hi rend="italic"
            >ei-<lb/>ther the Contents of the Stomach will be <lb/>thrown up,</hi> or both Meat and
          Drink will <lb/>be much diluted, and the Labour and <w part="I">Ex-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >pence</w> of Spirits in Digeſtion much ſaved. <lb/>And indeed I have found by long <w
            part="I">Expe-</w><lb/><w part="F">rience</w>, that nothing cauſeth ſo good a <w
            part="I">Di-</w><lb/><w part="F">geſtion</w> as fair Water; but this requires <lb/>time
          to free us from the Uneaſineſs that <lb/>an ill Digeſtion cauſeth, whereas Vomiting
          <lb/>is an immediate Remedy, and frees a <lb/>Man from it upon the ſpot. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>We are told by Sir <hi rend="italic">John Floyer,</hi> in his <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Treatiſe of Bath and Mineral Springs,</hi>
          <lb/>that Vomiting with Water is very uſeful <hi rend="italic"><lb/>in the Gout, Sciatica,
            Wind, Shortneſs of <lb/>Breath, Hypochondriack Melancholy, and
            <lb/>Falling-Sickneſs;</hi> which Diſtempers are <lb/>generally derived from evil Matter
            <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tained</w> in the Stomach, as is likewiſe <hi
            rend="italic">Gid-<lb/>dineſs in the Head and Apoplexies,</hi> with <pb xml:id="page_20"
            n="21"/><lb/>which myſelf once ſeemed to be <w part="I">threat-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ned</w>; for after eating a plentiful Dinner, <lb/>I was ſeized with Giddineſs, and the
          Sight <lb/>of my Eyes became ſo depraved, that <lb/>things ſeemed double, which was <w
            part="I">accom-</w><lb/><w part="F">panied</w> with a ſtrange Conſternation of
          <lb/>Spirit; and having read, <hi rend="italic">that Apoplexies <lb/>generally ſeize after
            eating,</hi> I <w part="I">immediate-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> called for Water, and
          not daring to <lb/>ſtay till it was warmed, I drank it cold, <lb/>and by the help of my
          Finger provoked <lb/>Vomiting: upon which I did <w part="I">immediate-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ly</w> overcome the Evils I was threatned <lb/>with, the Symptoms before mentioned
          <lb/>being the ſame as did precede the Fit of <lb/>an Apoplexy in another Perſon, as
          himſelf <lb/>afterwards told me, who died of it the <lb/>third Fit. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As for People who are troubled with <lb/>Shortneſs of Breath, 'tis
          certain from <w part="I">Ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">perience</w>, that Vomiting with warm <w
            part="I">Wa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> three or four times will afford certain
          <lb/>Relief. And the ſame may be prevented <lb/>by drinking nothing but Water <w part="I"
            >after-</w><lb/><w part="F">wards</w>, either cold, or warmed with a <lb/>Toaſt: for
          upon doing this, the Difficulty <lb/>of Breathing will apparently abate; which <lb/>Water,
          if you pleaſe, may be boiled with <lb/>Honey. And I knew one, who by this <lb/>means, <hi
            rend="italic">as he was adviſed by me,</hi> lived <lb/>comfortably in this City two or
          three <pb xml:id="page_21" n="22"/><lb/>Winters, but having undertaken Buſineſs <lb/>which
          did occaſion drinking ſtrong Drinks, <lb/>was the next Winter carried off by the
          <lb/>Diſtemper: Wine, Ale, or Brandy, being <lb/>as bad as Poiſon to People troubled with
          <lb/>Shortneſs of Breath. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Some People are taken with <hi rend="italic">violent <w part="I"
              >Vo-</w><lb/><w part="F">miting</w>,</hi> and the Exceſs thereof in ſome <lb/>hath
          been ſo great, as to endanger their <lb/>Lives, yea, cauſe Death: in which Caſe <lb/>Water
          will be very helpful; for if a Pint <lb/>of it warmed be drank after every <w part="I"
            >Vo-</w><lb/><w part="F">mit</w>, it will prevent that violent Straining, <lb/>wherein
          lieth the Danger of all Vomiting, <lb/>becauſe to ſtrain violently when but little
          <lb/>will come up, does endanger the <w part="I">break-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> of
          ſome inward Veſſel. And beſides <lb/>this, the offending Matter will be ſooner
          <lb/>looſen'd from the internal Part of that <lb/>Bowel, <hi rend="italic">the
            Stomach,</hi> and caſt out, upon <lb/>which the Vomiting will ſooner ceaſe: <lb/>For
          after this manner the famous <hi rend="italic">Syden-<lb/>ham,</hi> a moſt honeſt Writer,
          did overcome <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Cholera Morbus,</hi> or Vomiting and
          <lb/>Looſeneſs, ſo common in his Time, and <lb/>was found by the weekly Bill to kill more
          <lb/>than now die of Convulſions; for his way <lb/>was to boil a Chicken in four Gallons
          of <lb/>Water, which made a Broth not much <lb/>differing from Water, of which he order'd
          <lb/>large Draughts to be given, and ſome of <pb xml:id="page_22" n="23"/><lb/>it to be
          taken by Clyſter, till the whole <lb/>Quantity was ſpent, <hi rend="italic">if the
            Vomiting did <lb/>not ſtop before;</hi> which did ſo take off the <lb/>Sharpneſs of the
          Matter offending, and <lb/>waſh it out, that the Party in a little <lb/>time became well.
          And the ſame was <lb/>the Practice of <hi rend="italic">Sigiſmundus Graſius,</hi>
          <lb/>who commends pure Water in a <w part="I">Vomit-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> and
          Looſeneſs to be drank in large <lb/>Quantities; for thereby, he ſaith, the <lb/>corroſive
          or ſharp Humours will be ſo <lb/>weaken'd, that they will no more offend: <lb/>and he
          faith it may be drank cold, if the <lb/>Patient be ſtrong, otherwiſe let it be
          <lb/>warmed. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And in <hi rend="italic">Common Fluxes</hi> without <w part="I"
            >Vomit-</w><lb/><w part="F">ings</w> a Quart or more of warm Water <lb/>drank, will ſo
          weaken the Sharpneſs <lb/>whereby the Diſtemper is cauſed, that it <lb/>will ſoon be
          overcome, and the Gripings <lb/>eaſed; and in the <hi rend="italic">Bloody Flux,</hi>
          which is <lb/>the moſt dangerous of all Fluxes, the <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >genious</w>
          <hi rend="italic">Cornelius Celſus</hi> adviſeth a large <lb/>Drinking of cold Water as
          the beſt of <lb/>Remedies: but then no other Subſtance <lb/>muſt be taken till the Diſeaſe
          is cured. <lb/>And another great Phyſician, by Name <lb/><hi rend="italic">Luſitanus,</hi>
          affirms, <hi rend="italic">Cent.</hi> 1. <hi rend="italic">Obſer.</hi> 46. <lb/>that he
          knew one, who, being in the <lb/>Summer-time afflicted with this bloody <lb/>Flux, did
          drink a large quantity of cold <pb xml:id="page_23" n="24"/><lb/>Water, and did thereby
          recover. This <lb/>large quantity therefore of Water in theſe <lb/>Fluxes, doth ſo correct
          the Sharpneſs of <lb/>the Humour offending, that it can have <lb/>no power to cauſe Pain,
          or corrode the <lb/>Veſſels, and cauſe bloody Digeſtions or <lb/>Stools. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Water alſo is a Drink that conduceth <lb/>above all things to cure <hi
            rend="italic">Conſumptive <lb/>People,</hi> for the Digeſtion being weaken'd, <lb/>is
          the Cauſe of producing a hot, fretting <lb/>Nouriſhment; which is injurious to the
          <lb/>tender Subſtance of the Lungs, and which <lb/>conſtringes and ſtops up the Lymphatick
          <lb/>Veſſels, thro which the Nouriſhment is <lb/>to paſs to all the Parts; ſo that by <w
            part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">grees</w>
          <hi rend="italic">the Body for want of due Supplies <lb/>conſumes:</hi> which
          Obſtructions, and that <lb/>Acrimony that cauſeth them, will be <w part="I">o-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">pen'd</w> and ſweeten'd by the plentiful Uſe <lb/>of Water; <hi rend="italic"
            >if taken before the Lungs <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">come</w> ulcerous.</hi>
          Which Cure of <w part="I">Conſump-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w> by Water is recommended
          in the <lb/>Writings of Dr. <hi rend="italic">Couch,</hi> who in his <hi rend="italic"
            >Praxis <lb/>Catholica</hi> tells us, that he knew a Man <lb/>cured very ſoon of a
          Conſumption by <lb/>drinking pure Water. And 'tis ſaid by <lb/>another, that ſome have
          been cured of <lb/>Conſumptions by drinking no other <lb/>Drink but Water, <hi
            rend="italic">avoiding all Malt <w part="I">Li-</w><lb/><w part="F">quors</w> and ſharp
            Wines:</hi> for Wine or <pb xml:id="page_24" n="25"/><lb/>any other ſtrong Liquor is
          pernicious in <lb/>this Diſtemper. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Some there are who are much troubled <lb/>with <hi rend="italic"
            >fluſhing Heat</hi> in their Face, and <w part="I">o-</w><lb/><w part="F">thers</w>
          <hi rend="italic">with a Heat in the Back;</hi> in both <lb/>which Caſes, Water, uſed as
          common <lb/>Drink, is the beſt Remedy, with a ſpare <lb/>cooling Diet: and 'tis alſo
          excellent for <lb/>ſuch as have <hi rend="italic">red Blotches in their Face,</hi>
          <lb/>which proceeds from a hot fretting Blood, <lb/>which, by Water-drinking, and a <w
            part="I">mode-</w><lb/><w part="F">rate</w> Diet, will be kept under: for as Dr.
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Duncan,</hi> before quoted, doth affirm, <lb/>thoſe who keep
          their Blood cool and clean, <lb/>are never troubled with Breakings out, <lb/>like many
          others, who may be known to <lb/>be Drinkers of hot Drinks, and uſe a hot <lb/>full Diet,
          by their Faces. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Water is alſo commended by the <w part="I">Lear-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ned</w> for the Cholick; thus <hi rend="italic">Riverius</hi>
          <w part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F">firms</w>, that in the Cholick large drinking <lb/>of
          Water hath been found to be an <w part="I">excel-</w><lb/><w part="F">lent</w> Remedy; and
          'tis ſaid by <hi rend="italic">Fortis,</hi> that <lb/>when he practiſed at <hi
            rend="italic">Venice,</hi> he often <lb/>gave cold Water in the Cholick with <lb/>good
          Succeſs. With whom an <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi>
          <lb/>Phyſician, Dr. <hi rend="italic">Wainwright,</hi> in his <hi rend="italic"
            >Me-<lb/>chanical Account of the ſix <w part="I">Non-natu-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >rals</w>,</hi> concurs; for he ſaith that Water-<lb/>Drinkers are never troubled with
          the <pb xml:id="page_25" n="26"/><lb/>Cholick, and that many thereby have <lb/>been cured
          when all other Remedies <lb/>failed. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And in the <hi rend="italic">Small-Pox,</hi> Water hath alſo <lb/>been
          proved to be an excellent Drink. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Salmon,</hi> in his <hi
            rend="italic">Synopſis Medicinæ,</hi> ſaith, <lb/>that in this Diſtemper you may ſafely
          give <lb/>the Sick fair Water, of which, <hi rend="italic">ſays he,</hi>
          <lb/>they may drink liberally to quench Thirſt; <lb/>the want of which plenty of Drink
          hath <lb/>been the Death of many a Patient. <lb/>Which Opinion of his was right, as by
          <lb/>Experience I have found in two of my <lb/>own Children, when ſick of this <w part="I"
            >Diſtem-</w><lb/><w part="F">per</w>; to whom, after I had given a gentle <lb/>Vomit of
          Emetick Tartar, I gave no other <lb/>Drink but Water, and they both <w part="I"
            >recove-</w><lb/><w part="F">red</w> ſafely, and were not in the leaſt
          light-<lb/>headed, as two others before were in the <lb/>ſame Diſtemper, when treated
          otherwiſe: <lb/>and I remember that one Dr. <hi rend="italic">Betts</hi> being
          <lb/>conſulted in a Caſe where the Eruptions <lb/>did not come out kindly, did order two
          <lb/>Quarts of cold Water to be drank as <lb/>ſoon as could be, upon which they came
          <lb/>out according to expectation, and the <lb/>Party did well. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>'Tis alſo certain, that in what we call <lb/>burning Fevers, Water is
          found to be a <lb/>ſafe and effectual Remedy. It is ſaid by <pb xml:id="page_26" n="27"
          /><lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Primroſe,</hi> in his <hi rend="italic">Popular Errors,</hi>
          that <lb/>many great Phyſicians <hi rend="italic">have commended <lb/>the drinking cold
            Water in Diſeaſes, and <lb/>they attribute to it the chief Place in <lb/>Fevers,</hi>
          where the Sick muſt drink <w part="I">large-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w>; for thus taken,
            <hi rend="italic">it will quench all <lb/>Heat,</hi> pag. 374. And <hi rend="italic"
            >Galen</hi> is ſaid, by an <lb/><hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi> Author, to reprove <hi
            rend="italic">Craſiſtratus</hi>
          <lb/>for denying cold Water in burning <w part="I">Fe-</w><lb/><w part="F">vers</w>; and
          ſays, that this is a Remedy for <lb/>any Fever, <hi rend="italic">provided it be drank in
            <lb/>great abundance:</hi> with which Opinion I <lb/>find Dr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Oliver</hi> to agree, who, in his <hi rend="italic">Eſ-<lb/>ſay on Fevers,</hi> ſays,
          That in Fevers we <lb/>muſt drink oftner than Thirſt calls for it, <lb/>and ſuch Draughts
          as are plentiful; and the <lb/>Drink he preſcribes, is either cold Water <lb/>or
          Barley-Water. Dr. <hi rend="italic">Wainwright</hi>
          <w part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F">firms</w> alſo, that Water is proper in <w part="I"
            >Fe-</w><lb/><w part="F">vers</w>, <hi rend="italic">and that the Antients gave as
            <lb/>much of it as the Patient could drink.</hi>
          <lb/>And by another 'tis ſaid, that if you give <lb/>the Patient nothing but Water for
          three <lb/>Days, that in the third Day the Fever <lb/>will be cured generally; but if it
          is not, <lb/>give for Food a little Barley-Broth, and <lb/>the Fever will not exceed the
          ſeventh <lb/>Day. And by another we are informed, <lb/>how one in a Fever, <hi
            rend="italic">that was paſt Hope,</hi>
          <lb/>being forbidden to drink Water, which <lb/>he greatly deſired, did find means, in
          <lb/>the Abſence of his Nurſe, to get a large <pb xml:id="page_27" n="28"/><lb/>Pot-full,
          which he drank off, and lay down <lb/>again, being well cooled; after which he <lb/>fell
          into a Sweat, and ſo was cured. And <lb/>I find that Dr. <hi rend="italic">Cook</hi> of
            <hi rend="italic">Warwick,</hi> in his <lb/><hi rend="italic">Book of Obſervations
            on</hi> Engliſh <hi rend="italic">Bodies,</hi>
          <lb/>does preſcribe, for the Cure of Fevers, <lb/>firſt a Vomit, and afterwards as much
          <lb/>cold Water as the Patient can drink; and <lb/>he ſaith, that if he ſweat upon it, the
          <lb/>Sweat muſt he continued as long as can <lb/>be. And 'tis ſaid by another, that 'tis
          an <lb/>excellent Remedy in Fevers to drink a <lb/>Quart of hot Water, and ſweat upon it,
          <lb/>being covered warm. There is alſo one <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Quinton,</hi> who,
          in his <hi rend="italic">Book of <w part="I">Obſer-</w><lb/><w part="F">vations</w>,</hi>
          writes, That to one in a <w part="I">malig-</w><lb/><w part="F">nant</w> Fever, whoſe
          Pulſe was ſo low it <lb/>could ſcarcely be felt, there was three <lb/>Quarts of Water
          given, at ſeveral Draughts, <lb/>to make him vomit; but it did not <w part="I"
            >ope-</w><lb/><w part="F">rate</w> that way, yet the Event was this, <lb/>that it did
          refreſh him, much raiſed his <lb/>Pulſe, brought him into a breathing <lb/>Sweat, and
          paſſed off by Urine: which <lb/>Lowneſs of the Pulſe my own Experience <lb/>hath often
          found to be raiſed by drinking <lb/>Water plentifully. And I know a Woman, <lb/>who tho'
          ſhe in a Fever had the Advice <lb/>of two Doctors, yet became diſtracted: <lb/>I bid the
          Nurſe give her a Pint of cold <lb/>Water, which ſhe drank up, and in three <lb/>or four
          Minutes came to her right Senſes; <pb xml:id="page_28" n="29"/><lb/>and deſiring to drink
          more, ſhe recovered. <lb/>And I have obſerved, that when, in <w part="I">Fe-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">vers</w>, the Patient can reliſh no other Drink, <lb/>yet Water is always drank
          with pleaſure, <lb/>as it alſo will always be after the eating <lb/>ſweet things, that
          ſpoil the Reliſh of <w part="I">o-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> Drinks; which is one
          Excellence <w part="I">pe-</w><lb/><w part="F">culiar</w> to Water, and ſhews it to be
          moſt <lb/>agreeable to the Nature of Mankind, tho' <lb/>now ſo much ſlighted. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And as for the <hi rend="italic">Gout,</hi> which Dr. <hi
            rend="italic">Harris</hi>
          <lb/>ſaith, in his <hi rend="italic">Anti-Empirice,</hi> is gotten <w part="I"
            >ei-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> by high feeding, or drinking much <lb/>Wine, or other
          ſtrong Drink; it may be <lb/>cured, as that Author doth affirm, by a <lb/>very ſpare Diet,
          and drinking Water: <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">cording</w> to what is ſaid alſo
          by Sir <hi rend="italic">Theo-<lb/>dore Mayhern,</hi> who, in his <hi rend="italic"
            >Medicinal <lb/>Counſels,</hi> adviſeth to leave off all ſtrong <lb/>Drinks in this
          Diſeaſe, and drink only <lb/>Water. And <hi rend="italic">Van Heydon</hi> ſaith alſo, in
          <lb/>his Treatiſe of <hi rend="italic">Help for the Rich and <lb/>Poor,</hi> that there is
          not any greater <w part="I">Reme-</w><lb/><w part="F">dy</w> for the Gout <hi
            rend="italic">than drinking Water,</hi>
          <lb/>not only by young but old Men; many of <lb/>whom, he ſaith, have drank cold Water
          <lb/>for many Weeks, <hi rend="italic">which hath ſucceeded <lb/>ſo well, though they were
            far gone in <lb/>Years,</hi> that they found great Eaſe <w part="I">there-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">by</w>, without that Offence to the Stomach, <lb/>or Hindrance of Digeſtion,
          which ſome <pb xml:id="page_29" n="30"/><lb/>did ſeem to fear. And he alſo commends
          <lb/>the large drinking of Water in the <w part="I">Scia-</w><lb/><w part="F">tica</w>, or
          Hip-Gout, he having often cured <lb/>this Diſtemper, by this means, in leſs time <lb/>than
          could reaſonably be expected; and <lb/>the ſame myſelf have found to be <w part="I"
            >effec-</w><lb/><w part="F">tual</w> in a like Pain in the Shoulder, which <lb/>had
          continued very bad for three Months. <lb/>For, being taken with a Fever, I drank <lb/>in
          one Day about four Quarts of Water; <lb/>which though it did not make me ſweat,
          <lb/>becauſe I lay not in my Bed, yet it cured <lb/>me ſo that I ſlept well that Night;
          and <lb/>in the Morning, when I roſe, I did find <lb/>that the Pain in my Shoulder was not
          <lb/>felt, neither did it ever return. And the <lb/>ſame Succeſs I have had in the Pains
          of <lb/>other Parts, whereby I judge, that in all <lb/>Pains whatever the drinking of
          Water is <lb/>proper, as well as in the Gout; and <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cordingly</w> I find cold Water adviſed to be <lb/>drank largely for the Cure of the <w
            part="I">Head-</w><lb/><w part="F">ach</w> from hard Drinking; that Pain <w part="I"
            >pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceeding</w> from the ſame Cauſe the Gout <lb/>does, namely
          from Heat, as all Pains do. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is ſaid alſo by Dr. <hi rend="italic">Wainwright,</hi> that <lb/>in
          the <hi rend="italic">Itch, Scurvy, Leproſy,</hi> and in all <lb/>hot <hi rend="italic"
            >inflammatory Diſtempers,</hi> ſuch as <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pleuriſies,
            Rheumatiſms,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">St. <w part="I">Antho-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ny's</w>. Fire,</hi> Water is a proper Remedy; <lb/>but he adviſeth to drink it hot
          in ſome <w part="I">Ca-</w><pb xml:id="page_30" n="31"/><lb/><w part="F">ſes</w>, as
          doubtleſs ought to be done in <hi rend="italic">Pleuri-<lb/>ſies.</hi> He alſo ſaith, that
          Water is proper in <lb/><hi rend="italic">Head-aches, Catarrhs, Vapours,
            Falling-<lb/>Sickneſs, Dullneſs of Sight, Melancholy, <lb/>Shortneſs of Breath, Scurvey
            in the <lb/>Mouth,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Windineſs in the Stomach:</hi>
          <lb/>And, for Wind in the Stomach, I, by long <lb/>Experience, have found it the beſt <w
            part="I">Reme-</w><lb/><w part="F">dy</w>, who, in the former part of my Life,
          <lb/>through a diſorderly Diet, and drinking <lb/>ſtrong Drink <hi rend="italic">like
            others,</hi> was never free <lb/>from windy Belchings, and ſometimes <w part="I"
            >ve-</w><lb/><w part="F">ry</w> ſickiſh Qualms after Meals; from which <lb/>at length I
          was delivered, by drinking <lb/>only Water at Meals, ſo that for above <lb/>forty Years I
          have been ſeldom troubled: <lb/>and if I find myſelf troubled, a Pint or <lb/>more of cold
          Water, in leſs than half an <lb/>Hour, will ſet me free, by drinking of it. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And that Water is the beſt Remedy for <lb/>the Miſchiefs that come by
            <hi rend="italic">Hard <w part="I">Drink-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>,</hi> Experience
          teacheth; there being <w part="I">no-</w><lb/><w part="F">thing</w> that ſo effectually
          frees from thoſe <lb/>nauſeating and reaching Qualms the next <lb/>Morning, as the
          drinking a Pint or more <lb/>of fair Water; which effectually allays the <lb/>Inflammation
          of the Bowels, occaſioned <lb/>by ſtrong or hot Drink, which ſpoils the <lb/>Strength of
          the Stomach, as it doth the <lb/>Strength of all other Parts; nothing being <lb/>a greater
          Enemy to the Vigour of the <pb xml:id="page_31" n="32"/><lb/>Nerves and Sinews, <hi
            rend="italic">ſince by much <w part="I">drink-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>, Men make
            themſelves unable to <lb/>ſtand or go:</hi> Which Effect would never <lb/>follow, if
          Liquors, that abound with <w part="I">Spi-</w><lb/><w part="F">rits</w>, were
          ſtrengthening; and if they were <lb/>ſtrengthening, the Fibres of the Stomach <lb/>would
          not be ſo weakened, after drinking <lb/>ſtrong Drinks, as to make Men ſick: which
          <lb/>Sickneſs will ſoon be recovered by the <lb/>drinking cold Water, this being alſo the
          <lb/>beſt Remedy, if taken largely, for that <lb/>Heat of Urine which is often occaſioned
          <lb/>by Hard-drinking. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In <hi rend="italic">Colds,</hi> Water is the beſt of all Drinks
          <lb/>to prevent Floods of Rheum from the <lb/>Noſe and Mouth, as my long Experience
          <lb/>teſtifies, and the drinking thereof will <lb/><hi rend="italic">prevent Coughs;</hi>
          for a Cough will ſeldom <lb/>ſucceed a Cold, if Water is uſed from the <lb/>firſt as
          common Drink: and if, through <lb/>Neglect, a Cough ſhould become <w part="I"
            >trou-</w><lb/><w part="F">bleſome</w>, the Uſe of Water, <hi rend="italic">avoiding all
            <lb/>Wine and ſtrong Drink,</hi> will contribute <lb/>much to the Cure. Some order the
            <w part="I">Wa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> to be drank warm, but others ſay that
          <lb/>to drink it cold vaſtly excells the uſing of <lb/>it hot in a Cough. 'Tis ſaid by <hi
            rend="italic">Van <w part="I">Hey-</w><lb/><w part="F">don</w>,</hi> that ſome may think
          it ſtrange to <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">viſe</w> Water in ſuch Diſeaſes, which
          moſt <lb/>do account to proceed from Crudity or <lb/>Indigeſtion; but, he ſays, that in
          any <w part="I">Diſ-</w><pb xml:id="page_32" n="33"/><lb/><w part="F">eaſe</w> where the
          Caſe is dangerous, <hi rend="italic">the <lb/>Uſe of Water is the only Friend to <w
              part="I">Na-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w>;</hi> cold Water being a Preventer <w
            part="I">ra-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> than a Cauſe of Crudity, ſince, by <lb/>all
          Experience, it is proved to be a <w part="I">Pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">moter</w> of a good
          Digeſtion: And at this <lb/>time I know a Woman, 78 Years of Age, <lb/>who for this ten
          Years hath had a great <lb/>Cough, and ſpits much tough Phlegm, <lb/>that hath this
          preſent Winter 1722, been <lb/>perſuaded to leave off all ſtrong and ſmall <lb/>fermented
          Liquor, and drink only <w part="I">Wa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> at Meals, and ſometimes
          a Diſh or <lb/>two of Tea; and hath found herſelf much <lb/>leſs ſubject to cough than
          before, and <lb/>ſcarce coughs at all in Bed. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is the general Opinion of moſt <w part="I">Phyſi-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">cians</w>, that Wine and Strong-Drinks are <lb/>not proper for Children, and
          that the <lb/>ſmaller and cooler their Drink is, the <w part="I">bet-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ter</w> it will be with them; and that <w part="I">no-</w><lb/><w part="F">thing</w>
          conduceth more to the Health of <lb/>Children than drinking Water, which <lb/>will prevent
          the Foundation of thoſe <lb/>Diſeaſes that are cauſed in many by <lb/>Strong-Drink, and do
          ſhew themſelves in <lb/>their more advanced Age, wherein <w part="I">ma-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ny</w> alſo do ſuffer much by the ill Cuſtom <lb/>of making them Gluttons, by
          conſtantly <lb/>cramming their Stomachs with Food, <lb/>many being thereby deſtroyed among
          the <pb xml:id="page_33" n="34"/><lb/>Children of the Rich before they come <lb/>to the
          Years of Maturity; when the <w part="I">Chil-</w><lb/><w part="F">dren</w> of poor Country
          People, who fare <lb/>hard, and very often drink Water, ſtand <lb/>their Ground till full
          grown: for fewer <lb/>Children die in the Country than in great <lb/>Cities, where Luxury
          in Diet doth more <lb/>abound; which is one Reaſon <hi rend="italic">why ſo few
            <lb/>Houſekeepers in</hi> London <hi rend="italic">were born in it,</hi>
          <lb/>the great Supply of Inhabitants being <lb/>from the Country, Children being brought
          <lb/>up more hardy there than in <hi rend="italic">London,</hi>
          <lb/>where great Numbers are killed by over-<lb/>pleaſing their Palates. Which Miſchief
          <lb/>would be, in a great meaſure, prevented <lb/>by their being accuſtomed to drink <w
            part="I">Wa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w>; which, by Experience, is found to <lb/>make
          young Children free from that <w part="I">Frow-</w><lb/><w part="F">ardness</w> which is
          commonly cauſed by a <lb/>ſharp, and hot, or feveriſh Blood, which <lb/>ingendereth Wind,
          and cauſeth Pain and <lb/>Gripes: for there is no Pain but is the <lb/>Conſequence of
          Heat, if it is not cauſed <lb/>by Blows and Bruiſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Water, I have found, by long <w part="I">Experi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ence</w>, to be of excellent uſe <hi rend="italic">in Burns and <lb/>Scalds;</hi> for
          in all Burns and Scalds that <lb/>are ſlight, if the Part is plunged <w part="I"
            >imme-</w><lb/><w part="F">diately</w> into cold Water, <hi rend="italic">the colder the
            <lb/>better,</hi> the Pain will inſtantly be <w part="I">ta-</w><lb/><w part="F">ken</w>
          off; and it will fetch out the Fire, if <pb xml:id="page_34" n="35"/><lb/>continued ſo
          long, as will be required to <lb/>do it by any other Remedy. And if the <lb/>Burn be ſo
          conſiderable, that other <w part="I">Reme-</w><lb/><w part="F">dies</w> muſt be applied,
          none of which will <lb/>take off the Smart of themſelves <hi rend="italic">in leſs
            <lb/>than two or three Hours;</hi> yet if you <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ply</w> cold Water preſently, after other <w part="I">Ap-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >plications</w> are made to the Part, the <lb/>Pain immediately will ceaſe, till the <w
            part="I">Re-</w><lb/><w part="F">medy</w> becomes effectual: ſo that the Eaſe <lb/>Water
          will give in ſuch Caſes, makes it <lb/>of good Uſe. Which Remedy, <hi rend="italic">as it
            hath <lb/>not been diſcovered till now,</hi> appears to <lb/>tranſcend all other
          Remedies in this Caſe; <lb/>becauſe, in a moment, the great Smart <lb/>will be eaſed, if
          the Water is cold, and <lb/>will be felt no more if the Part afflicted be <lb/>kept
          immerſed in it till the Fire is <w part="I">extin-</w><lb/><w part="F">guiſhed</w>, either
          by the Water, or the <w part="I">Me-</w><lb/><w part="F">dicine</w> applied. <hi
            rend="italic">Beſides, it is a Remedy <lb/>every where ready at hand,</hi> which <w
            part="I">can-</w><lb/><w part="F">not</w> be ſaid of any other; which generally
          <lb/>requires ſo much time to get it ready, <lb/>that much Pain will be endured, if <w
            part="I">Bli-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſters</w> do not ariſe, which do much increaſe
          <lb/>the Trouble. <hi rend="italic">If the Part burnt, or <lb/>ſcalded, cannot be dipt in
            Water,</hi> you <lb/>may apply Water to it, with double <w part="I">Lin-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">nen</w> Cloths dipped therein, and new dipt <lb/>as they grow warm; by which
          means I <lb/>have cured Burns and Scalds in the Face <pb xml:id="page_35" n="36"
          /><lb/>without bliſtering, when applied <w part="I">imme-</w><lb/><w part="F">diately</w>
          before Bliſters did ariſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I once knew a large Ulcer in the Foot, <lb/>made by the running of
          melted Braſs <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">to</w> the Shoe, that was kept in hand by
          a <lb/>Surgeon nine Weeks, without any <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">bability</w>
          of healing, <hi rend="italic">becauſe of the great <lb/>Inflammation that attended
            it;</hi> but the <lb/>Party being a Lover of Angling, was <lb/>perſuaded to go with ſome
          others to <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hackney River:</hi> ſome of them went <w part="I"
            >bare-</w><lb/><w part="F">legg'd</w> into the Water, to come at a <w part="I"
            >cer-</w><lb/><w part="F">tain</w> Hole where much Fiſh was <w part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">times</w> found. The Sport was ſo good that <lb/>the lame Man, having pulled
          off his <w part="I">Stock-</w><lb/><w part="F">ings</w> and Plaiſters, went in alſo, where
          he <lb/>ſtaid above two Hours, and coming out <lb/>again he found the Ulcer, which <w
            part="I">appear-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> very red and angry when he went in, <lb/>did
          look pale; <hi rend="italic">he put on his Dreſſings,</hi>
          <lb/>and came home, and in leſe than a <w part="I">Fort-</w><lb/><w part="F">night</w> his
          Ulcer healed up: which <w part="I">doubt-</w><lb/><w part="F">less</w> was occaſioned by
          the abating of <lb/>the Inflammation by the Coldneſs of the <lb/>Water. And I have had an
          Account alſo <lb/>from an Acquaintance, that was Surgeon <lb/>to a Merchant Ship, that
          their Gunner, <lb/>at a time when the Captain treated ſome <lb/>Friends on board, going to
          charge a Gun <lb/>that juſt before had been fired off, the <w part="I">Car-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tridge</w> he was ramming down took fire, <pb xml:id="page_36" n="37"
          /><lb/>whereby he was blown into the Water, <lb/>and had ſome of his Fingers torn off, and
          <lb/>it was about an Hour before a Boat could <lb/>be got to take him up: but they found
          <lb/>that the Coldneſs of the Water had <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">moſt</w> ſtopt
          the Bleeding, and the Cure was <lb/>effected ſo ſpeedily, that other Surgeons
          <lb/>wondered at it; which he imputed to the <lb/>Water, which kept back the Humours, by
          <lb/>its Coldneſs, from flowing to the Part at <lb/>the firſt: ſo that there was no <w
            part="I">Impedi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w>, from Inflammation, to hinder <w part="I"
            >heal-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>; for the chief Impediment to healing, <lb/>is
          Inflammation in Wounds or Ulcers. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And as for <hi rend="italic">Strains and Sprains</hi> in the
          <lb/>Joints, cold Water affords the beſt and <lb/>moſt ſpeedy Remedy, as <hi rend="italic"
            >Van Heydon</hi>
          <w part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F">firms</w>; who ſaith, That by bathing in <lb/>cold
          Water all harm ſo received may, by <lb/>this Remedy, be cured more ſafely and <lb/>more
          ſpeedily than by any other, <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w part="F">out</w> Loſs of Time,
          Coſt, or Trouble; for <lb/>no more is to be done, than, as ſoon as <lb/>can be, <hi
            rend="italic">to put the Part into a Tub of <lb/>cold Water for about two Hours,</hi>
          which <lb/>will prevent all Swelling and Pain, by <lb/>repelling or keeping back the
          Humours <lb/>that otherwiſe would flow to the Part. <lb/>And if it ſhould be the Shoulder,
          or any <lb/>other Part, which is ſo hurt, that cannot <lb/>well be immerſed in Water after
          this <pb xml:id="page_37" n="38"/><lb/>manner, Water may be applied, by <w part="I"
            >dip-</w><lb/><w part="F">ping</w> Towels folded up into it, and <w part="I"
            >lay-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> them to the Part, as is done, in effect, <lb/>to the
          wrenched Joints of Horſes; about <lb/>which, if you wind oftentimes a thick <lb/>Rope made
          of Hairs, and then caſt upon <lb/>it divers times a Pail of cold Water, the <lb/>Wrench
          will be cured; which <w part="I">Experi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w> is now commonly
          practiſed by thoſe <lb/>concerned about Horſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Bathing in cold Water hath alſo been <lb/>found to be a good Remedy
            <hi rend="italic">to ſtrengthen <lb/>Weakneſs in the Joints,</hi> as Sir <hi
            rend="italic">John <lb/>Floyer,</hi> in his Treatiſe of <hi rend="italic">Cold
            Bathing,</hi>
          <lb/>hath ſhewed; and which by Experience <lb/>I found to be true in a certain Woman,
          <lb/>who complained of great Weakneſs and <lb/>Pain in her Ankles: I adviſed her to dip
          <lb/>the Part in cold Water every Morning for <lb/>about a quarter of an Hour, and to do
          <lb/>the ſame at Night; and in about twenty <lb/>Days ſhe became as ſtrong in that Part
          <lb/>as ſhe was in the other. And Sir <hi rend="italic">John</hi>
          <lb/>tells us of a Boy who could not ſtand, his <lb/>Limbs were ſo weak, that by bathing
          in <lb/>cold Water, perfectly recover'd his Strength <lb/>in a little time. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Great <hi rend="italic">Pain in the Head</hi> hath been alſo
          <lb/>cured by this means; for we are told by <lb/><hi rend="italic">Van Heydon,</hi> that
          one Sir <hi rend="italic">Toby Mathews</hi>
          <pb xml:id="page_38" n="39"/><lb/>had for twenty Years been troubled with <lb/>great Pain
          in one ſide of his Head, and <lb/>a great Defluxion of Rheum from his <lb/>Noſe; but he at
          laſt was cured, by <w part="I">apply-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> cold Water to the Part
          every day for <lb/>about a quarter of an hour: upon <w part="I">read-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ing</w> of which, I tried the Experiment <w part="I">up-</w><lb/><w part="F">on</w>
          myſelf, who for a long time had been <lb/>trouble with the running of much clear
          <lb/>Water from my Noſe, with great ſpitting <lb/>of thin Rheum: for I let a Water-Cock
          <lb/>run upon the Mould of my Head every <lb/>Morning, by which, in about ſix Weeks
          <lb/>time, I was eaſed of my Trouble. And <lb/>ſince that I had a credible Information
          <lb/>of a certain Servant-Maid, who was <w part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F">flicted</w>
          greatly with a Rheumatiſm and <lb/>an intolerable Pain in the Head, who <w part="I"
            >be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> put into <hi rend="italic">St. Thomas's Hoſpital,</hi>
          her <lb/>Nurſe was order'd by the Doctor to <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">ply</w> to
          her Head Towels four times <w part="I">dou-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w>, dipt in cold
          Water, changing them <lb/>as they became warm, which ſhe was to <lb/>continue doing four
          or five Hours; in <lb/>which time ſhe was freed from that Pain <lb/>in the Head, and was
          afterwards cured of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Rheumatiſm</hi> by other Means. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Want of Sleep in Fevers</hi> may be <lb/>cured
          likewiſe by the Application of cold <lb/>Water: for to a near Relation, who could <lb/>not
          ſleep for three Days and three Nights, <pb xml:id="page_39" n="40"/><lb/>I order'd a Towel
          to be ſeveral times <lb/>folded up, then to be dipt in Water, and <lb/>a little wrung out
          and ſo laid upon her <lb/>Forehead, and to be new dipt as it grew <lb/>hot; which in about
          two Hours time ſo <lb/>cooled her Head, that ſhe fell into a Sleep, <lb/>and continued in
          it five Hours: and I <w part="I">or-</w><lb/><w part="F">der'd</w> the farce to be done
          the next Night, <lb/>with the same effect. And we find that <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Cockburn,</hi> in his Treatiſe of <hi rend="italic">Sea <w part="I">Diſ-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">eaſes</w>,</hi> d<unclear>#</unclear>d order for the want of Sleep in
          <lb/>Fevers, to dip a Towel, four times <w part="I">dou-</w><lb/><w part="F">bled</w>, in
            <hi rend="italic">Oxycrat,</hi> which is ſix parts <w part="I">Wa-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ter</w>, and one part Vinegar, to be bound <lb/>about the Head and Temples; which, he
          <lb/>ſaith, will cauſe Sleep with wonderful <lb/>Succeſs: but Water only will have the
          <lb/>ſame effect, as I often have proved. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And that the Uſe of cold Water <hi rend="italic">in
            <lb/>Swoonings</hi> is of great effect, common <w part="I">Ex-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >perience</w> teacheth; for if a Diſh or Cup <lb/>of cold Water is thrown ſtrongly upon
          the <lb/>Face, the Perſon in an inſtant will recover <lb/>his Senſes, tho for a time he
          ſeemeth <lb/>dead, and perhaps might not have <w part="I">reco-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ver'd</w> in ſome caſes, if cold Water had <lb/>not been ſo applied: ſuch Faintings
          being <lb/>ſometimes deadly, which proceed from <w part="I">poſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſonous</w> Vapours aſcending up to the Brain <lb/>from a foul Stomach; for ſuch Effects
          <lb/>there are, as I have found by Experience, <pb xml:id="page_40" n="41"/><lb/>who, in
          my young Days, did ſwoon away <lb/>twice; at both which times I was <w part="I"
            >ſenſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w> of a Collection of Wind in my <w part="I"
            >Sto-</w><lb/><w part="F">mach</w>, from whence I plainly felt a Fume <lb/>or Vapour
          aſcend to the Head, that in an <lb/>inſtant deprived me of all Senſe: but <w part="I"
            >be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> both times in the Company of a <w part="I"
            >Per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſon</w> who had ſeen the thing tried, he <lb/>daſh'd ſome cold
          Water againſt my Face, <lb/>which I remember made me ſtart, as if <lb/>I had been ſuddenly
          a waked. And I am <lb/>apt to think, that ſome die in ſuch a Fit, <lb/>when none are near
          to help them; and <lb/>eſpecially when ſo taken in their Sleep, <lb/>which, I believe,
          none need fear who live <lb/>temperately, or that eat no Suppers: none <lb/>who have
          refrained from Suppers, having <lb/>been ever found to die in Sleep. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Dangerous <hi rend="italic">Bleedings at the Noſe</hi> have <lb/>alſo
          been cured with cold Water largely <lb/>drank, ſyringing cold Water up their
          <lb/>Noſtrils, and applying Towels round their <lb/>Necks dipt in cold Water, changing
          them <lb/>as they grow warm; for 'tis ſaid by a <lb/>good Writer, that this will ſo cool
          the <lb/>Heat of the Blood, and by the Coldneſs <lb/>of the Water ſyringed up the Noſe, ſo
          <lb/>contract the Mouths of the burſted Veins <lb/>which bleed, that it will put a ſtop to
          <lb/>the Bleeding. Such Bleedings have alſo <lb/>been ſtopt by daſhing cold Water often
            <pb xml:id="page_41" n="42"/><lb/>into the Face, as a <hi rend="italic">French</hi>
          Writer hath <lb/>affirmed, whoſe Name was <hi rend="italic">Flamand;</hi>
          <lb/>and the ſame alſo is affirmed by <hi rend="italic">Cook,</hi> in <lb/>his <hi
            rend="italic">Marrow of Surgery.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Cold Water is an abſolute Cure for all <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſmall
            Cuts in the Fingers or other Parts;</hi>
          <lb/>for if when cut, you cloſe the Cut up <lb/>with the Thumb of your other Hand,
          <lb/>keeping it ſo cloſed for a quarter or half <lb/>an Hour, this will infallibly ſtop
          the <lb/>Bleeding: after which, if you double up <lb/>a Linnen Rag five or ſix times, dip
          it in <lb/>cold Water, and apply it to the Part, <lb/>binding it on faſt. This, by
          preventing <lb/>Inflammation and a Flux of Humours, <lb/>will give Nature time ſoon to
          heal it <lb/>without any other Application, as is ſeen <lb/>in the common Practice of
          Surgeons <lb/>when they let a Man blood; for all the <w part="I">Appli-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">cation</w> they make to the Vein ſo cut, is a <lb/>Pledget of Linnen dipt in
          cold Water, and <lb/>bound on with a Fillet: for all Wounds <lb/>without loſs of Subſtance
          will heal of <lb/>themſelves, if Inflammation is prevented, <lb/>and the Lips of the Wound
          are kept cloſe <lb/>together. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>We alſo are told by <hi rend="italic">Van Heydon,</hi> that <lb/>in
          his time ſome were of an opinion, that <lb/>a Perſon bit by a mad Dog might be <w part="I"
            >pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerved</w> from that Symptom, call'd, <hi rend="italic">The
              <pb xml:id="page_42" n="43"/><lb/>Fear of Water,</hi> which generally follows <lb/>and
          proves ſo mortal, by applying cold <lb/>Water to the Place bitten: And this, he <lb/>ſays,
          they conceive to be no unlikely thing, <lb/>if there is any credit to be given to what
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cornelius Celſus</hi> writes, who ſaith, that <lb/>the only
          Remedy in this caſe is to throw <lb/>the Party who is in this Condition, or <lb/>hath <hi
            rend="italic">the Fear of Water</hi> upon him, into a <lb/>Pond or River, and when
          plunged over <lb/>Head and Ears, to keep him in the <w part="I">Wa-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ter</w> till filled with it, whether he will <lb/>or no; and by this means both his
          Thirſt <lb/>and Dread of Water will be cured. For if <lb/>this Immerſion be of uſe when
          the Party <lb/>is ſo far gone, why ſhould it not be of <lb/>greater force in preſerving
          from it, if <w part="I">ſpee-</w><lb/><w part="F">dily</w> applied and repeated? Now tho
          this <lb/>is mention'd by him as a probable <w part="I">Opi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nion</w>,
          yet Experience in our days ſhews, <lb/><hi rend="italic">That the plunging the Patient
            into the <lb/>ſalt Water either of the River of</hi> Thames, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >about</hi> Graveſend, <hi rend="italic">or in the ſalt Springs <lb/>in</hi> Cheſhire,
          is an infallible means to <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">vent</w> any Evil
          ſucceeding the Bite of a <lb/>mad Dog; they muſt indeed be dipt ſo <lb/>often, as to be
          almoſt drown'd before the <lb/>Danger is over; but 'tis a queſtion <w part="I"
            >whe-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> the Saltneſs of the Water contributes <lb/>any thing
          to this Cure, ſince <hi rend="italic">Boerhave,</hi> the <lb/>preſent Profeſſor at <hi
            rend="italic">Leyden,</hi> affirms, That <lb/>when Men bitten by a mad Dog are <pb
            xml:id="page_43" n="44"/><lb/>arrived to the Fear of Water, call'd an <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Hydrophobia,</hi> they may be cured, by <w part="I">blind-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ing</w> the Patient's Eyes, and throwing of <lb/>him into a Pond of Water
          often, till he <lb/>ſeems not to be afraid of it, or but very <lb/>little, and then force
          him to drink large <lb/>Quantities. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And we are told by Dr. <hi rend="italic">Browne,</hi> that <lb/>a
          Perſon troubled with the <hi rend="italic">Falling <w part="I">Sick-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ness</w>,</hi> by happening to fall into a cold <lb/>Spring, <hi rend="italic">(I
            ſuppoſe it was in the time of <lb/>his Fit)</hi> was freed from his Diſtemper all
          <lb/>his Life after: and he ſaith there is no <lb/>need of preparing the Body for it in
          this, <lb/>as in ſome other Caſes. But the Patient, <lb/>when plunged into a cold Bath,
          ought to <lb/>continue in the Bath each time about <lb/>three or four Minutes: for in
          plunging <lb/>over head and ears at his firſt Entrance <lb/>into a cold Bath, the Brain
          will be ſo <w part="I">ſen-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſibly</w> affected, as to be relieved from
          the <lb/>Diſtemper, which is a kind of <w part="I">Convul-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſion</w>
          proceeding from an Inflammation, or <lb/>ſome other Cauſe; <hi rend="italic">but we want
            more <lb/>Experiments to confirm this Notion:</hi>
          <lb/>Which Notion may be worth noting, that <lb/>the thing may be tried in others, to ſee
          <lb/>whether it will ſucceed as it did in this <lb/>Perſon. For 'tis ſaid by the ingenious
          <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Pitcairn,</hi> a <hi rend="italic">Scotchman,</hi> ſome time
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Profeſſor</hi> at <hi rend="italic">Leyden,</hi> that there is no
          ſuch <pb xml:id="page_44" n="45"/><lb/>thing as the Art of Phyſick, but <w part="I"
            >Reme-</w><lb/><w part="F">dies</w> were found out by chance, <hi rend="italic">p.</hi>
          264. of <lb/>his Works; for if Phyſick were an Art as <lb/>certain in its Rules, as the
          Rules are that <lb/>belong to Muſick, or to Watch-making, <lb/>Phyſicians would as ſeldom
          be miſtaken in <lb/>their Preſcriptions, as the others are in their <lb/>Deſigns. But when
          Remedies happen to <lb/>be diſcover'd, and prove often to be <w part="I">ef-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">fectual</w>, the remembring that Remedy, <lb/>to apply it in a like caſe, often
          brings <lb/>Reputation to the Preſcriber; and if it <lb/>fails, ſome other Experiment muſt
          be <lb/>tried, which, were Phyſick an Art, need <lb/>not be done. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>'Tis alſo ſaid by the ſame Dr. <hi rend="italic">Browne,</hi>
          <lb/>that Madneſs and Melancholy, with all <lb/>their Retinue, may find better Effects
          <lb/>from the Uſe of bathing in cold Water, <lb/>than from other violent Methods, with
          <lb/>which People ſo afflicted are now treated; <lb/>for, ſays he, <hi rend="italic">that
            which will make a <lb/>drunken Man ſober in a minute, will <lb/>certainly go a great way
            towards the <lb/>Cure of a Madman in a month.</hi> Now <lb/>'tis moſt certain, to my own
          Knowledge, <lb/>that if a drunken Man be plunged over <lb/>head and ears in cold Water, he
          will come <lb/>out of it perfectly ſober: And ſome I <lb/>have known, that in ſuch caſes
          have been <lb/>recover'd by barely waſhing their Heads <pb xml:id="page_45" n="46"
          /><lb/>in cold Water. And the forementioned <lb/>Opinion of Dr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Browne</hi> is confirmed by <lb/>the Practice of Dr. <hi rend="italic">Blair,</hi> who,
          in a <w part="I">Let-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> to Dr. <hi rend="italic">Baynard,</hi>
          declares, That he <w part="I">cu-</w><lb/><w part="F">red</w> a Man raving mad, who being
          bound <lb/>in a Cart, ſtript of his Clothes, and <w part="I">blind-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >folded</w>, that the Surprize might be the <lb/>greater; he on a ſudden had a great
          Fall <lb/>of Water let down upon him from the <lb/>height of twenty foot, <hi
            rend="italic">under which he <lb/>continued ſo long as his Strength would
            <lb/>permit:</hi> and after his Return home, he <lb/>fell into a Sleep, and ſlept
          twenty-nine <lb/>Hours, and awaked in as quiet a State of <lb/>Mind as ever, and ſo had
          continued to <lb/>the time of the writing that Letter, which <lb/>was twelve Months. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Which Relation ſeems to make that a <lb/>more probable Truth, which
          was related <lb/>in a Letter from Sir <hi rend="italic">John Floyer</hi> to Dr. <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Browne,</hi> and printed by that Doctor; <lb/>wherein it is ſaid, that in
            <hi rend="italic">Normandy</hi> they <lb/>immerſe Fools, or dip them in cold <w part="I"
            >Wa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w>, to cure them: a hot Brain being the <lb/>Cauſe,
          perhaps, of ſeveral Diſorders in the <lb/>Underſtanding, and is in great part found
          <lb/>to be true, in the ridiculous Behaviour of <lb/>ſome drunken Men, which, when their
          <lb/>Heads are become cool, abhor what they <lb/>before did do or ſay. Now if ſuch Dipping
          <lb/>would cure Fools among us, great <w part="I">Num-</w><pb xml:id="page_46" n="47"
            /><lb/><w part="F">bers</w> might be made more happy than <lb/>they are. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Browne,</hi> in his Diſcourſe <hi rend="italic"
            >of Cold <lb/>Baths,</hi> affirms likewiſe, that to bathe in <lb/>cold Water hath been
          found to be the <lb/>quickeſt, ſafeſt, and pleaſanteſt Cure for <lb/>the King's Evil; and
          he tells us, in <hi rend="italic">p.</hi> 85. <lb/>of a <hi rend="italic">Yorkſhire</hi>
          Gentleman, who was <lb/>grievouſly afflicted with this Diſtemper, <lb/>having great Ulcers
          in the Glands of his <lb/>Neck, which were ſo much inflamed, as to <lb/>bring him very
          low; but being adviſed <lb/>by Dr. <hi rend="italic">Baynard</hi> to bathe in the Cold
          <lb/>Bath, he in a Month's time was perfectly <lb/>cured, his Ulcers being healed up, <w
            part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">trary</w> to the Opinion of the moſt learned
          <lb/>Phyſicians. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>We alſo find mention, in the Deſcription <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic"
            >Scottiſh</hi> Iſlands, of an odd Remedy <lb/>commonly made uſe of there for the Cure
          <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Jaundice;</hi> which is this: They <lb/>ſtrip the Party
          naked, lay him upon the <lb/>Ground on his Belly, and pour unawares <lb/>upon his Back a
          Pail of cold Water. And <lb/>alſo Pains in the Joints, as Dr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Curtis</hi>
          <lb/>tells us, will be cured, by holding the <lb/>Part under the Stream of a Pump or
          <lb/>Cock; and fomenting with cold Water is <lb/>commended as good to aſſuage hot <w
            part="I">Swel-</w><lb/><w part="F">lings</w>. And I know a Perſon who had <pb
            xml:id="page_47" n="48"/><lb/>often been ſubject to blood-ſhot or <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">flamed</w> Eyes, who afterwards, upon the <lb/>beginning of the
          ſame Diſtemper, took, <lb/>by Advice, a Ball of linnen Rags, dipt <lb/>them in cold Water,
          and applied them to <lb/>the Part, cooling them by new dipping <lb/>as oft as they grew
          hot: which <w part="I">Applica-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> was continued three Hours, in
          which <lb/>time the Humour was ſo repelled, as to <lb/>be troubleſome no more; for the
          Party, <lb/>to my knowledge, hath had no ſign of <lb/>that Diſtemper ſince, tho the ſame
          had <lb/>been very troubleſome many times <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is alſo adviſed by Dr. <hi rend="italic">Gideon <w part="I"
              >Har-</w><lb/><w part="F">vey</w>,</hi> to waſh the Eyes well twice a day in <lb/>cold
          Water, as the beſt Remedy to prevent <lb/>Defluxions on them, and preſerve the
          <lb/>Eye-ſight, which it greatly comforts. And <lb/>this I have found true for many Years,
          <lb/>my Eyes being often apt to be dim and <lb/>ſtiff on a ſudden, ſo that I could ſcarce
          <lb/>open my Eye-lids; which, upon waſhing <lb/>for a minute with fair Water, hath been
          <lb/>felt no more till a good while after. <w part="I">Be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſides</w>
          which Benefit to the Eyes, Authors <lb/>ſay it is alſo good to preſerve the <w part="I"
            >Memo-</w><lb/><w part="F">ry</w>, if the whole Forehead be waſhed <lb/>twice a day;
          which is a certain Cure for <lb/>itching in the Eyes, as Authors tell us. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_48" n="49"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Some People are troubled with a <hi rend="italic"
            >Callo-<lb/>ſity,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Hardneſs of the Bottoms of their
            <lb/>Feet,</hi> which is ſo troubleſome, as to be a <lb/>hindrance to their eaſy
          walking; for <lb/>which a Cure is preſcribed by Dr. <hi rend="italic">Cook,</hi>
          <lb/>that is, to ſoak them well in warm <w part="I">Wa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w>, till
          the Hardneſs is ſoften'd, and then <lb/>ſcrape it off with the Edge of a Knife: <lb/>and
          if the Feet burn with any unnatural <lb/>Heat, the bathing often in hot Water <lb/>will
          cool them, by giving vent to what <lb/>offends. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And the plentiful drinking of Water <lb/>is commended in the Scurvey,
          by Dr. <hi rend="italic">Pit-<lb/>cairn,</hi> to diſſolve the Scorbutick Salts, and
          <lb/>carry them out by Urine, whether they <lb/>are Acids or Alkalies; and myſelf having
          <lb/>formerly been extremely troubled with <lb/>the Scurvey, which often made me faint
          <lb/>and weak, and my Pulſe ſo low as <w part="I">ſcarce-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> to be
          felt, I found at laſt that the <lb/>Pulſe would infallibly riſe upon drinking <lb/>a Pint
          or more of cold Water, and in a <lb/>little time I ſhould become brisk and <lb/>ſtrong:
          For I have often found that upon <lb/>a Diſorder of the Stomach, the Strength <lb/>of the
          bodily Members ſoon would fail, and <lb/>would eaſily be recovered when the <w part="I"
            >Diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">order</w> of the Stomach was removed; <lb/>and have, by long
          Experience, found that <pb xml:id="page_49" n="50"/><lb/>nothing conduceth ſo much to
          bodily <lb/>Strength as a Stomach in right Order, <lb/>which requires Temperance and
          cooling <lb/>Drink. </p>
        <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="16"/>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="10"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
