<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Boulton: Some thoughts concerning the unusual qualities of the
          air.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Richard Boulton</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Some thoughts concerning The Unusual Qualities of the air. Containing
              Some Cautions necessary to prevent Malignant and Pestilential or Contagious
              Distempers. As also Proper Medicines to prevent the ill Effects of Malignancy and
              Contagious Infection, either in Respect of Malignant Fevers, the Small-Pox; or
              Intermitting Fevers or Agues, especially where Endemical or Epidemical, as in Kent and
              Essex. By Richard Boulto, sometime of Brazen-Nose Colledge in Oxford. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T49403</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T49403"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for John Hooke, at the Flower de Luce, over against St.
                  Dunstan's Church in Fleet-Street, MDCCXXIV.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1724</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="5"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="47"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3307209566</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K045775.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: disease"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>TO THE Illuſtrious Prince <hi rend="italic">JOHN,</hi> Duke of <hi rend="italic"
            >Montagu.</hi>
        </head>
        <salute>May it pleaſe your Grace, </salute>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>YOUR Noble Anceſ- <lb/>tors, have continued ſo Illuſtrious a Cha- <lb/>racter to
          Poſterity; that it is a great Happineſs to find the <pb xml:id="page_3"/>
          <lb/>ſame, equally ſhining in your Grace: A Character, ſo wor- <lb/>thy of its Noble
          Origin, ex- <lb/>celling both in Learning Vir- <lb/>tue and Loyalty, that I ſhould be vain
          to endeavour to draw that, which lyes out of the Power of my ſlender Pen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I ſhall therefore forbear to attempt, according to the u- <lb/>ſual Methods of
          Dedications, what I am not able to do Juſtice to, and ſhall only humbly beg the Favour to
          lay this Trifle at your Feet. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A Trifle, not in reſpect of the Subject, being of the higheſt concern and worthy our
          Conſideration, but only <pb xml:id="page_4"/>
          <lb/>as it contains ſome brief Thoughts, ſufficient to guard us from Dangerous Effects:
          for my Intention here was not to write a thorough or com- <lb/>pleat Tract, but to propoſe
          juſt and neceſſary Cautions, againſt ſuch Evils, which I choſe to do in as few words as I
          could. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Honour your Grace hath been pleaſed to do the Faculty of Phyſick, in being a
          Fellow of the College, encourages me to hope that any thing that may ſeem Rea-
          <lb/>ſonable that way, may meet with your Graces favourable Acceptance and Patronage. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_5"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If this Trifle ſhall ſeem ſo to your Grace, it will be the greateſt Satisfaction and
          En- <lb/>couragement to </p>
        <signed>Your Graces Moſt Humble and Obedient Servant <hi rend="italic">RICHARD BOULTON.</hi>
        </signed>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_6" n="1"/>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A rectangular floral ornament. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>SOME <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">THOUGHTS</hi>
          <lb/>CONCERNING <lb/><hi rend="size(1.25)">The Unuſual Qualities</hi>
          <lb/>OF THE <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">AIR, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi></hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(4)">S</hi>INCE all Creatures <lb/>who have the Faculty <lb/>of
          Reſpiration, and live <lb/>upon the Superficies of <lb/>this Terreſtrial Globe, and inha-
          <lb/>bit the ſeveral Climates of the known <pb xml:id="page_7" n="2"/>
          <lb/>World, are obliged to breathe the <lb/>Common Air or Atmoſphere they <lb/>live in;
          and ſince not only thoſe, <lb/>but Mankind, whoſe Lives are more <lb/>particularly
          valuable, as a Creature <lb/>of the moſt Noble and firſt Rank, <lb/>are ſubject to be
          altered and vari- <lb/>ouſly affected, according to the dif- <lb/>ferent Qualities of that
          Air; and <lb/>to receive different Impreſſions, ac- <lb/>cordingly as that is impregnated,
          <lb/>and endowed with ſeveral various <lb/>Extraneous Bodies, Vapours or Ef-
          <lb/>fluſions; and ſince theſe are not only <lb/>likely to affect human Bodies ex-
          <lb/>ternally through the Pores of the <lb/>Skin, but internally, when ſucked <lb/>into
          the Lungs, into more tender <lb/>and rarify'd Veſſels, containing hu- <lb/>mours more
          exquiſitely rarify'd and <lb/>expanded; and conſequently are <lb/>liable to be altered and
          depraved ac- <lb/>cording to the various Diſpoſitions <lb/>of that Air we breathe, which
          may <lb/>lay the foundations of Diſorders and <lb/>Diſtempers, pernicious and deſtructive
            <pb xml:id="page_8" n="3"/>
          <lb/>to human Bodies, as thoſe extraneous <lb/>Bodies, Vapours, or Effluviums are
          <lb/>more or leſs unwholſome and of a <lb/>different Nature; I ſay, ſince Hu- <lb/>man
          Bodies are thus diſpoſed and <lb/>liable to be ill affected and diſordered <lb/>by the
          various Qualities of the Air <lb/>we breathe, it is not only neceſſary <lb/>but requiſite
          we ſhould conſider, the <lb/>different Qualities of that Air, and <lb/>what Extraneous
          Bodies, Vapours, <lb/>or Effluviums it may be impregnated <lb/>and endowed with; and what
          alte- <lb/>rations or ill Effects theſe may occa- <lb/>ſion and produce, either at the
          pre- <lb/>ſent, or for the future; and how far <lb/>they may be prejudicial and perni-
          <lb/>tious to Mankind. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>To determine and enable us to judge <lb/>of the different Qualities of the Air,
          <lb/>and what Extraneous Bodies or Va- <lb/>pours it may be Impregnated and <lb/>Endowed
          with, we are to conſider, <lb/>how many Ways it may be furniſhed <lb/>with ſuch Vapours or
          Effluviums; <pb xml:id="page_9" n="4"/>
          <lb/>which muſt be, either from foreign <lb/>Globes, far diſtant from the Earth <lb/>we
          live in, and from the Superficies <lb/>of our Atmoſphere; from extrane- <lb/>ous Bodies,
          or Vapours emitted or <lb/>riſing from Bodies on the Superficies <lb/>of our Globe; or
          from Vapours <lb/>and Effluviums tranſuding and aſ- <lb/>cending out of the Bowels of the
          <lb/>Earth. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>As for thoſe Globes which are vaſt- <lb/>ly diſtant from the Earth we live in,
          <lb/>and far remote from the Superficies <lb/>of our Atmoſphere, theſe are either <lb/>the
          Stars, the Moon or the Sun. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The Stars are ſo many Thouſand <lb/>Miles diſtant from us, and ſeparated <lb/>by ſuch
          a ſpacious and boundleſs <lb/>Aether or Medium, that we can but <lb/>juſt perceive the
          Glimmering rays <lb/>of thoſe Celeſtial Bodies, which are <lb/>ſufficient to convince us
          that there <lb/>are ſuch Stupendious Effects of an <lb/>Infinite Power; but they are ſo
          ſmall, <pb xml:id="page_10" n="5"/>
          <lb/>that they can have but little Effects <lb/>in altering the Qualities of the <lb/>Air
          we Breathe; much leſs are they <lb/>able to inform us, of the Nature of <lb/>thoſe
          diſtarit Globes; and conſe- <lb/>quently cannot afford us any know- <lb/>ledge what
          Alterations ſuch can pro- <lb/>duce; only we may conclude, that <lb/>where the Cauſes are
          ſmall and ſcarce <lb/>perceivable, the Effects muſt be in- <lb/>conſiderable; and
          therefore can do <lb/>little good, except as Luminaries, <lb/>or produce not much ill; and
          con- <lb/>ſequently cannot contribute much <lb/>to pervert it or deprave the Diſpo-
          <lb/>ſition of our Air or Atmoſphere. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>As for the Moon, though that is <lb/>much nearer than any of the Stars, <lb/>yet it
          is alſo placed at a great di- <lb/>ſtance from the Superficies of the <lb/>Earth, and
          ſeparated by a vaſt ex- <lb/>tent of fine Æther, which interpoſes <lb/>betwixt that Globe
          and ours, <lb/>and prevents it from any im- <lb/>mediate Effects upon the Air we live <pb
            xml:id="page_11" n="6"/>
          <lb/>in; and though ſeveral Effects are <lb/>attributed to it, becauſe the Periods
          <lb/>ſeem to keep time with its different <lb/>Poſitions, yet it is contrary to all
          <lb/>known Laws Statical or Hydroſtatical, <lb/>that it ſhould have any Effect upon
          <lb/>any Bodies contained within our At- <lb/>moſphere, as having no immediate
          <lb/>contact with terrene Bodies, but <lb/>only upon that Aether, which equally
          <lb/>encompaſſes and compreſſes the Su- <lb/>perficies of our Vortex, and the ut-
          <lb/>moſt Extent of the Globe we live <lb/>and breathe upon or in; for the Air <lb/>or
          Atmoſphere may be properly ſaid <lb/>to be a part of our Globe though <lb/>the moſt fluid
          and rarify'd Superficial <lb/>covering of Earth and Water, and <lb/>though Lunaticks, or
          thoſe Diſtem- <lb/>pers which grow worſe at certain <lb/>periods, ſeem to be equal in
          diſtance <lb/>with the ſeveral Poſitions of the <lb/>Moon, yet it cannot be demon-
          <lb/>ſtrated, that thoſe Effects are owing <lb/>to it as a Cauſe, ſince other periodi-
          <lb/>cal Diſtempers keep an equal diſtance <pb xml:id="page_12" n="7"/>
          <lb/>betwixt their Periods, which depend <lb/>upon Cauſes contained within the <lb/>Limits
          of our own Bodies; and as <lb/>for the Ebbing and Flowing of the <lb/>Sea, that muſt
          proceed from ſome o- <lb/>ther Cauſe, both Statical and Hy- <lb/>droſtatical Rules
          excluding it any <lb/>ſhare in theſe different Motions of <lb/>that fluid Element; but not
          to en- <lb/>ter upon Diſputes of that Nature, <lb/>which are foreign to our preſent pur-
          <lb/>poſe, we ſhall only obſerve, that <lb/>the Beams of the Moon, which illu- <lb/>minate
          our Globe; are only reflected <lb/>Beams of the Sun tranſmitted into <lb/>our Atmoſphere,
          and not the proper <lb/>Emanations or Effluviums of that <lb/>Globe; and for as much as
          the Beams <lb/>of the Sun reflected from other Sub- <lb/>ſtances within our Globe, do not
          <lb/>tranſmit to us the Nature of thoſe <lb/>Bodies they are reflected from, but <lb/>are
          only variouſly modifyd and re- <lb/>fracted in the Superficies of thoſe <lb/>Bodies, which
          different refractions <lb/>variouſly affect our Senſory, or the <pb xml:id="page_13" n="8"/>
          <lb/>Organ of Sights, and produce the <lb/>Senſation of different Colours or
          <lb/>Refractions, and which only affect <lb/>the Senſe of Seeing, as they are
          <lb/>ſtronger or weaker: Conſequently <lb/>we cannot expect, that the Beams of <lb/>the
          Sun, reflected from the Super- <lb/>ficies of the Moon, ſhould convey <lb/>to us the
          Qualities of that Body or <lb/>Globe, eſpecially ſince they are like- <lb/>wiſe convey'd
          through ſo fine a Strai- <lb/>ner as the interpoſed Aether, and re- <lb/>fracted and
          altered alſo in paſſing <lb/>through the great and lofty expanded <lb/>part of our
          Atmoſphere, which is <lb/>reckoned, or computed, to be Seven <lb/>Miles perpendicular in
          height, boying <lb/>up a Pillar of Quickſilver in a Wea- <lb/>ther-Glass, ſuch a
          conſiderable height, <lb/>till it amounts to an Aequilibrium, or <lb/>equal Weight of a
          Pillar of Air, of <lb/>the ſame Diameter and thickneſs, <lb/>preſſing upon the Baſis, or
          Bottom <lb/>of that Pipe the Mercury or Quick- <lb/>ſilver is contained in. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_14" n="9"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>As for the Sun, it is evident, that <lb/>it acts upon all Bodies within our
          <lb/>Atmoſphere by Virtue of its Heat, <lb/>ſince in the Summer time, when it is <lb/>near
          enough, it rarifies, expands and <lb/>digeſts the Superficial Juices of the <lb/>Earth, as
          well thoſe in our Bodies, <lb/>which when fermented, attenuated <lb/>and rarify'd, are
          preſſed by the force <lb/>of the incumbent Atmoſphere in- <lb/>to the Roots of Plants and
          Trees, <lb/>and riſe higher, as further rarify'd, <lb/>preſs'd and expanded in the Veſſels
          <lb/>of each Plant, which being variouſly <lb/>fermented and ſtrained through dif-
          <lb/>ferent Veſſels along with Specifick <lb/>Juices, are aſſimilated and converted
          <lb/>into the proper Juices of thoſe Plants. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The Sun Beams alſo affect other <lb/>Bodies on the Superficies of the <lb/>Earth, and
          by their active Parts, put <lb/>the Parts of other Subſtances in Mo- <lb/>tion, and cauſes
          them to emit Va- <lb/>pours and Effluviums, which, ac- <lb/>cording to their different
          Natures <pb xml:id="page_15" n="10"/>
          <lb/>variouſly alter and affect the Air we <lb/>breathe, and render it more or leſs
          <lb/>wholeſome and pernicious, Healthful <lb/>or Deſtructive: But though the <lb/>Sun hath
          ſuch conſiderable Effects <lb/>upon this Globe, when near us, yet <lb/>when but a little
          further off in the <lb/>Winter, we ſee that it hath little or <lb/>no apparent Effects
          upon the Climate <lb/>we live in; and if ſo ſmall a dif- <lb/>ference can extinguiſh the
          obvious <lb/>Effects of ſo bright a Body as the <lb/>Sun, we can ſcarce imagin, that the
          <lb/>Moon or Stars which are much fur- <lb/>ther off and Shine but faintly, ſhould
          <lb/>have any conſiderable Effects, or <lb/>indeed any at all, eſpecially ſince they
          <lb/>cannot be perceived. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It appearing hence, in a great Mea- <lb/>ſure, how the Air we breathe may <lb/>be
          altered by Foreign Globes far <lb/>diſtant from our Earth, we are next <lb/>to conſider
          how the Air we breathe <lb/>in may be altered and depraved by <lb/>Vapours and Effluviums
          emitted, <pb xml:id="page_16" n="11"/>
          <lb/>and ariſing from the Superficies of <lb/>the Globe we inhabit, which appears
          <lb/>from the vaſt variety of different <lb/>Subſtances which may be obſerved <lb/>on the
          Superficies of the Globe we <lb/>live upon, which deprave the Natural <lb/>Temper and
          Diſpoſition of the Air, <lb/>and conſequently variouſly affect the <lb/>Maſs of Humours
          circulating through <lb/>the minute and ſmall Veſſels con- <lb/>tained in and diſperſed
          through the <lb/>Subſtance of the Lungs, ſuch as pu- <lb/>trify'd Bodies, and the conſtant
          E- <lb/>manation of Vapours occaſioned by <lb/>ſtanding Waters, and the unwhole- <lb/>ſome
          Stenches which naturally flow <lb/>from the products of Art, as well <lb/>as Nature, which
          more particularly <lb/>affect thoſe Perſons employed in <lb/>ſuch Arts, and more
          immediately <lb/>exerciſed about them; thus we ſee <lb/>the ſtrange decay in thoſe Perſons
          <lb/>which work in Pot-houſes, Chymi- <lb/>cal Elaboratories, and other employ-
          <lb/>ments, where they are expoſed to <lb/>unwholeſome Vapours and preternar- <pb
            xml:id="page_17" n="12"/>
          <lb/>tural Fumes. And theſe are further <lb/>improved to an ill purpoſe, and <lb/>grow
          more pernicious and unwhole- <lb/>ſome, and deprave the wholeſome <lb/>Diſpoſiton of the
          Air, when more <lb/>forceably put in Action by the united <lb/>force and heat of the Sun
          Beams. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But the greateſt and moſt con- <lb/>ſiderable Alteration which the Air <lb/>receives
          from the Extraneous mix- <lb/>ture of Vapours and Effluviums, <lb/>ſeems to be from ſuch
          as tranſude <lb/>and aſcend out of the Bowels of the <lb/>Earth, whether of a Mineral kind
          or <lb/>of any other Nature. And as ſuch <lb/>ſort of Vapours and Effluviums are <lb/>moſt
          likely to produce great and ex- <lb/>traordinary Alterations, ſo coneſ- <lb/>quently thoſe
          Alterations are pro- <lb/>bably moſt pernicious, and of the <lb/>worſt conſequence, and
          apteſt to oc- <lb/>caſion the worſt of Accidents in hu- <lb/>man Bodies. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_18" n="13"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>From ſuch kind of Vapours dif- <lb/>fervently agitated and put in Action <lb/>by the
          nearer approach, or greater <lb/>diſtance of the Sun, ſeems to ariſe <lb/>that great
          variety of Climates, not <lb/>only in the ſame Latitude, but ſe- <lb/>veral Parts of the
          Terreſtrial Globe; <lb/>for accordingly as the Air is variouſly <lb/>affected with ſuch
          Effluviums of dif- <lb/>ferent kinds, theſe Vapours being <lb/>put in Action by the heat
          of the Sun <lb/>Beams produce different Effects, and <lb/>render the Air in ſuch Climates
          <lb/>more or leſs wholeſome, pernicious <lb/>and depraved: Thus Agues are <lb/>more
          frequent in <hi rend="italic">Kent</hi>, and other Di- <lb/>ſtempers more common and
          cuſtom- <lb/>mary in different Parts of the World. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>When by the Conſtant and Cuſto- <lb/>mary tranſmiſſion of particular Va- <lb/>pours
          and Effluviums, any Country <lb/>is frequently or conſtantly ſubject to <lb/>ſuch
          Diſeaſes; theſe Diſtempers are <lb/>ſaid to be Endemical or proper to <lb/>that particular
          Climate; but when <pb xml:id="page_19" n="14"/>
          <lb/>Contagious or Malignant Diſtempers <lb/>happen to rage more than commonly <lb/>or
          accidentally in any Place, ſuch <lb/>Diſorders are called Epidemical, or <lb/>ſpreading at
          ſome particular Times, <lb/>ariſing from the accidental Diſcharge <lb/>and Aſcenſion of
          particular Vapours <lb/>out of the Bowels of the Earth at <lb/>that Time. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The Temper of the Air in dif- <lb/>ferent Climates is alſo altered dif- <lb/>ferently
          according to the Quantity <lb/>as well as Quality of ſuch Vapours, <lb/>and as the Air is
          more plentifully or <lb/>ſparingly impregnated with ſuch pre- <lb/>ternatural Vapours,
          which alſo in the <lb/>ſame Climates exert themſelves more <lb/>or leſs vigorouſly
          according to the <lb/>different Seaſons of the Year. Thus <lb/>in Summer time Contagious
          or Ma- <lb/>lignant Diſtempers rage more vigo- <lb/>rouſly and univerſally and are leſs
          Epi- <lb/>demical in the Winter. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_20" n="15"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>And as the Temper and Diſpoſition <lb/>of the Air varies according to dif-
          <lb/>ferent Climates, the various quan- <lb/>tities of Mineral Effluviums, and the
          <lb/>different Seaſons of the Year; ſo we <lb/>find a vaſt difference according to the
          <lb/>Nature and Qualities of ſuch Mineral <lb/>Vapours. Some Minerals afford very
          <lb/>wholeſome and Salutiferous Steams, <lb/>whilſt others are dangerous and per-
          <lb/>nicious. Thus the Mines in <hi rend="italic">Cornwall</hi>
          <lb/>make the Country wholeſome and <lb/>healthful, whilſt others produce Con-
          <lb/>tagious and Peſtilential Qualities, <lb/>which render ſuch Countries frequent-
          <lb/>ly ſubject to ſuch Diſtempers. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Thoſe Mineral Effluviums or Va- <lb/>pours which produce Peſtilential Diſ-
          <lb/>eaſes, are of a moſt pernicious <lb/>kind, and are attended with very <lb/>violent
          and moſt fatal Symptoms, <lb/>and ſuch are eſteemed, by that moſt <lb/>Worthy and profound
          Judge of the <lb/>Works of Nature, the Honourable <lb/><hi rend="italic">Robert
          Boyle</hi>, to be of an Arſenical <pb xml:id="page_21" n="16"/>
          <lb/>kind, producing Effects of the moſt <lb/>Malignant and Poiſonous Nature, <lb/>being
          moſt offenſive and deſtructive <lb/>to Human Bodies. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It appearing then from what we <lb/>have ſaid, that the Temper of the <lb/>Air, and
          its moſt Unuſual Qualities, <lb/>which are likewiſe moſt deſtructive <lb/>and dangerous,
          chiefly depend on <lb/>the Effluviums or Vapours riſing out <lb/>of the Bowels of the
          Earth, when- <lb/>ever we find the Temper and Diſpo- <lb/>ſition of any Climate to vary
          and <lb/>differ from what it commonly does <lb/>in ſuch Climates, we have good rea-
          <lb/>ſon to conclude, that the Air is Im- <lb/>pregnated with ſome unuſual Efflu-
          <lb/>viums out of the Bowels of this Ter- <lb/>reſtrial Globe, which being mixed <lb/>with
          and diſperſed through the Air <lb/>produce that uncommon Indiſpo- <lb/>ſition. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>And ſince we are conſtantly obli- <lb/>ged to breathe the Air we live in, and <pb
            xml:id="page_22" n="17"/>
          <lb/>to impregnate our Blood with ſuch <lb/>Heterogeneous and offenſive Particles,
          <lb/>which perverting the Courſe of Na- <lb/>ture may produce ill Effects in human
          <lb/>Bodies, we ought to be very careful <lb/>to guard our ſelves againſt ſuch Ac-
          <lb/>cidents as may be Deſtructive, and <lb/>ſo prejudicial to Mankind, and to <lb/>make
          uſe of neceſſary precautions to <lb/>prevent ſuch ill Accidents, as ſuch
          <lb/>Inconveniencies may render us liable <lb/>to. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It cannot be out of our Memory <lb/>what fatal Conſequences have lately <lb/>happened
          Abroad, eſpecially in the <lb/>South Parts of <hi rend="italic">France</hi>; and how
          <lb/>many Thouſands have been deſtroy- <lb/>ed by the fatal Effects of an ill diſ-
          <lb/>poſed Temper of the Air, ſo Mor- <lb/>tal and Epidemical. And as other <lb/>Parts of
          the World may be likely to <lb/>ſuffer by Accidents, and may be <lb/>liable to the ſame
          approaching Dan- <lb/>gers, by hidden Vapours and Efflu- <lb/>viums tranſmitted from the
          inward <pb xml:id="page_23" n="18"/>
          <lb/>Parts of the Earth, and by Mineral <lb/>Effluviums of a Malignant kind; <lb/>whenever
          we find any unuſual Quality <lb/>in the Air, we have a great deal of <lb/>Reaſon to be
          afraid of ſome unuſual <lb/>Accidents, and to make uſe of all <lb/>neceſſary precautions
          to prevent <lb/>them. If ſuch ill and Malignant <lb/>Qualities ſhould be convey'd from
          <lb/>the inward Parts of the Earth into <lb/>our Atmoſphere, ſuch cautionary
          <lb/>Preparations would arm us the bet- <lb/>ter againſt their ill Effects; and tho'
          <lb/>no ſuch danger, as we might juſtly <lb/>fear, ſhould happen, yet at leaſt we
          <lb/>ſhould reap this advantage by our <lb/>jealous ſurmiſes, that we ſhould free <lb/>our
          Bodies of ill diſpoſed Humours, <lb/>and put our ſelves in a better State <lb/>and
          Condition of Health; ſo that <lb/>our Labour would not be ill beſtow- <lb/>ed and
          fruitleſs, nor our Pains ill re- <lb/>warded; the juſt Cautions to arm <lb/>our ſelves
          againſt the greateſt of <lb/>Dangers, would at leaſt ſecure us <lb/>againſt leſs Evils. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_24" n="19"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/> And that at the preſent, we have <lb/>very probable Grounds and ſubſtan- <lb/>tial
          Reaſons to fear ſome impending <lb/>Evil, and future Danger, which may <lb/>too ſuddenly
          happen in our Climate, <lb/>and conſequently we ought to make <lb/>uſe of proper Methods
          to prevent <lb/>ſuch Events, will in a great meaſure <lb/>appear, if we conſider the Steps
          arid <lb/>Progreſs of Malignant or Peſtilen- <lb/>tial Diſtempers in former Times, and
          <lb/>alſo the Intemperies of our Climate <lb/>for ſome time paſt, and at the preſent
          <lb/>time; which may give us ſufficient <lb/>grounds to ſuſpect the conſequential
          <lb/>Intemperature of the Air for the fu- <lb/>ture, or time to come. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>As for the Steps and Progreſs of <lb/>Malignant or Peſtilential Diſtempers,
          <lb/>formerly it hath been obſerved, that <lb/>the Peſtilence took its Courſe ſuc-
          <lb/>ceſſively through ſeveral Parts of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Europe,</hi> beginning
          firſt in <hi rend="italic">Aſia,</hi> and <lb/>then runing through <hi rend="italic"
            >Italy, Germany, <lb/>Denmark, Sweden, England,</hi> &amp;c. In <pb xml:id="page_25"
            n="20"/>
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Turkey</hi> it is Endemical, and con- <lb/>ſtantly appears every
          Year; but this <lb/>in a great meaſure depends on the <lb/>exceſſive Heats of the Climate,
          and <lb/>their way of living; their Blood be- <lb/>ing too much phlegmated to ſupport
          <lb/>and ſupply a ſufficient Diaphoreſis or <lb/>Sweat, in the Time of exceſſive
          <lb/>Heat, and this is, in a great meaſure, <lb/>occaſioned by their Abſtinence, ac-
          <lb/>cording to <hi rend="italic">Mahomet</hi>'s Laws, from <lb/>Spiritous Liquors, which
          might ſuf- <lb/>ficiently attenuate the Serum of the <lb/>Blood, and render it apt for
          Tran- <lb/>ſpiration, ſo that when the Maſs of <lb/>Humours begin to be fermented with
          <lb/>Heat, the phlegmatick Parts of <lb/>the whole are too great in Quanti- <lb/>ty, and
          too groſs in Quality to be <lb/>diſcharged according to the ordinary <lb/>Courſe of
          Nature. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But it appear'd lately in <hi rend="italic">France</hi>
          <lb/>without any Mask or Excuſe to hide <lb/>the Evident Cauſe of its Malignancy, <lb/>it
          plainly appearing to proceed from <pb xml:id="page_26" n="21"/>
          <lb/>Contagious Parts of Matter diſperſed <lb/>through the Air, which, from what <lb/>hath
          been ſaid, appear to be ſupply'd <lb/>by Subterraneous Mineral Effluviums, <lb/>or
          Vapours, proceeding out of the <lb/>Bowels of the Earth, Which God Al- <lb/>mighty
          preſerve us from! </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But it is too much to be feared, <lb/>that ſome Heterogeneous Particles, or
          <lb/>Malignant Vapours and Effluviums <lb/>have, and are, too much diſperſed <lb/>through
          our Atmoſphere, or the Air <lb/>which we now breathe in our Cli- <lb/>mate; and this will
          appear too likely, <lb/>if we obſerve, that near the whole <lb/>Twelve Months laſt paſt,
          the Nitrous <lb/>Parts of the Air have almoſt been to- <lb/>tally overpower'd, and
          hindered from <lb/>producing their Natural Effects as <lb/>uſual in this Climate: For we
          may <lb/>obſerve, that moſt of the laſt Sum- <lb/>mer was not only hot and dry, but
          <lb/>that moſt of the laſt Winter ap- <lb/>peared more like Summer than <lb/>Winter
          Weather, there being little <pb xml:id="page_27" n="22"/>
          <lb/>appearance of either Froſt or Snow, <lb/>to what is uſual in this Climate; <lb/>and
          we at the preſent find, that the <lb/>Heat of the Weather hath ſome time <lb/>exceeded
          what it hath for ſeveral Years <lb/>laſt paſt, which if it ſhould encreaſe
          <lb/>proportionally, as the Sun ap- <lb/>proaches, it muſt render the hotteſt <lb/>Seaſon
          of the Year exceſſively ſo; <lb/>and conſequently muſt produce ex- <lb/>ceeding Malignant
          Diſtempers, if not <lb/>Peſtilential. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>And that we may reaſonably con- <lb/>clude, that ſuch Intemperatures of the <lb/>Air
          proceed from Subterraneous Va- <lb/>pours, or Effluviums, which not only <lb/>over-power
          the Nitrous Parts of the <lb/>Air, but are put and excited into a <lb/>preternatural
          Fermentation by the <lb/>heat of the Sun; I ſay, we may <lb/>reaſonably deduce this
          Concluſion, <lb/>ſince the Sun would have its conſtant <lb/>and certain effect at the ſame
          Diſtance, <lb/>and conſequently, that the Differen- <lb/>ces muſt proceed from ſome
          Hetero- <pb xml:id="page_28" n="23"/>
          <lb/>geneous Particles, which concur <lb/>to produce ſuch Alterations and <lb/>Differences
          in the Natural Diſpoſition <lb/>of the Air in one Climate. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>And that the Air is too much Im- <lb/>pregnated with ſome Heterogeneous <lb/>Vapours,
          is evident from the Mala- <lb/>dies which have lately afflicted ſeveral <lb/>Perſons, as
          particular Feveriſh Heats <lb/>and Indiſpoſitions, attended with <lb/>Pains in the Head
          and dizzineſs, and <lb/>other Symptoms much different from <lb/>thoſe which appear in
          Phthiſis or any <lb/>uſual Diſtempers. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>If then, as we may well conclude, <lb/>or, at leaſt ſuſpect, the Air we breathe,
          <lb/>is impregnated with Heterogeneous <lb/>Particles, as it ſeems to appear, not
          <lb/>only from what we have mentioned, <lb/>but the ſudden and ſurpriſing Death <lb/>of
          ſeveral Perſons, eſpecially of late, <lb/>ſince we continually ſuck in, and <lb/>imbibe
          theſe Heterogeneous Particles <lb/>into our Blood in Reſpiration, it <pb xml:id="page_29"
            n="24"/>
          <lb/>ſeems worth our while to conſider <lb/>what Methods are proper to prevent <lb/>their
          ill Effects, if either it ſhould <lb/>happen, that the Air ſhould be more <lb/>plentifully
          impregnated with ſuch <lb/>Particles, or by long breathing them <lb/>into our Lungs, the
          Maſs of Blood <lb/>ſhould be more ſtrongly impregnated <lb/>with them, ſo as to enable
          them to <lb/>produce their ill Effects more vigo- <lb/>rouſly. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>In order to aſſign proper Methods <lb/>to this purpoſe, it will be requiſite <lb/>to
          conſider, what Cauſes commonly <lb/>concur to produce Malignant Peſti- <lb/>lential
          Diſtempers, front whence it <lb/>will appear, what Methods may be <lb/>proper and moſt
          expedient to prevent <lb/>ſuch Maladies, and to ſecure Man- <lb/>kind from ſuch Dangers as
          may hap- <lb/>pen, without the over-ruling hand of <lb/>Providence to divert ſuch
          pernicious <lb/>Qualities which may be more plen- <lb/>tifully emitted out of the Bowels
          of <pb xml:id="page_30" n="25"/>
          <lb/>the Earth, and diſperſed through <lb/>the infected Air we breathe in. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>And, firſt, From what hath been <lb/>ſaid, it appears ſufficiently, that the
          <lb/>Antecedent Cauſe of Malignant or <lb/>Peſtilential Diſtempers depends on, <lb/>and is
          compoſed of extraneous ma- <lb/>lignant Mineral Vapours, or Exhala- <lb/>tions riſing out
          of the Bowels of the <lb/>Earth and Impregnating the Air we <lb/>breathe with pernicious
          Particles. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Theſe Mineral Effluviums or Va- <lb/>pours, Firſt and Primarily affect Hu- <lb/>man
          Bodies, and being ſucked into <lb/>the Lungs in Breathing gradually im- <lb/>pregnate the
          whole Maſs of Blood <lb/>with their Poiſonous Steams. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Theſe Poiſonous Particles of Mi- <lb/>neral Vapours, at the firſt are ſo <lb/>ſmall
          in quantity, that they are not <lb/>able to produce any ill Effects, be- <lb/>ing lodged
          and harboured amongſt <lb/>the more Phlegmatick and groſs Parts <pb xml:id="page_31"
            n="26"/>
          <lb/>of the Animal Humours; but being <lb/>gradually collected to a greater quan-
          <lb/>tity they exert themſelves more <lb/>powerfully, and the groſs Parts of <lb/>the
          Blood being attenuated and ſub- <lb/>tiliſed by their corroſive Qualities, or <lb/>at
          leaſt ſome part of them, they are <lb/>no longer able to cloak and skreen <lb/>them from
          ſhewing their corroſive <lb/>Qualities. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The Maſs of Blood being thus <lb/>gradually more ſtrongly impregnated <lb/>with theſe
          depraved and Heteroge- <lb/>neous Particles, and ſome Parts of <lb/>the Maſs of Humours
          attenuated by <lb/>their corroſive Qualities, they begin <lb/>to diſcover thoſe Qualities;
          run them <lb/>into a more fluid form by their cor- <lb/>roſive Faculty, and ſeparating
          them <lb/>from the reſt, the perfect Mixture of <lb/>the Maſs of Humours is by this
          <lb/>means broke, and made an imper- <lb/>fected Mixture, the groſſer Parts be- <lb/>ing
          caſt off and ſeparated from the <lb/>thinner, and by this means rendered <pb
            xml:id="page_32" n="27"/>
          <lb/>unapt and unfit for Circulation; the <lb/>groſſer Parts occaſion Obſtructions <lb/>in
          the ſmall and minuteſt Veſſels, <lb/>whilſt the more thin and corroſive <lb/>corrode and
          deſtroy the continuity <lb/>of the Veſſels, whoſe joint Effects <lb/>make ſuch a ſad
          Cataſtrophe in hu- <lb/>man Bodies, and putting the whole <lb/>fabrick into diſorder,
          produce thoſe <lb/>ill Symptoms in Peſtilential and Ma- <lb/>lignat Diſtempers; as
          Tumours, <lb/>Ulcers, Inflammations, Deliriums, <lb/>Mortifications and Death: In the
          <lb/>Glandulous Parts they produce <lb/>Buboes, in the fleſhy Pares Car- <lb/>buncles and
          Blotches, in the Nervous <lb/>Parts, eſpecially the Membranes of <lb/>the Brain,
          Inflammation, Delirium <lb/>and Phrenſy, in the Glandulous <lb/>Parts of the Brain, and
          other noble <lb/>Parts, violent Symptoms and ſud- <lb/>den Death. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Theſe Malignant and Peſtilential <lb/>Diſtempers being thus formed, and <lb/>the
          Blood ſtrongly Impregnated with <pb xml:id="page_33" n="28"/>
          <lb/>deſtructive Vapours as well as the <lb/>Air, the Diſtemper begins to be <lb/>more
          contagious and ſpreading; the <lb/>ill Effluviums heaped up in human <lb/>Bodies now
          exerting themſelves <lb/>powerfully, and breaking out of <lb/>thoſe Repoſitories, unite
          with thoſe <lb/>contained in the Air, and more <lb/>ſtrongly affect thoſe Perſons about
          <lb/>them; and thus the Infection is ſpread <lb/>and promoted Secondarily, theſe
          <lb/>Effluviums from human Bodies u- <lb/>niting with thoſe contained in the <lb/>Air, and
          thoſe already collected in <lb/>the Maſs of Blood. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But beſides theſe Primary and <lb/>Secundary Antecedent Cauſes to pro- <lb/>duce
          Malignant and Peſtilential Di- <lb/>ſtempers, there are other acceſſory <lb/>and
          Concurring Cauſes requiſite; <lb/>for ſince all are not equally ſubject <lb/>to them, but
          ſeveral continue a long <lb/>time amongſt ſuch Perſons without <lb/>prejudice, till at the
          laſt their Conſti- <lb/>tutions are gradually depraved and <pb xml:id="page_34" n="29"/>
          <lb/>more ſtrongly affected with the Ve- <lb/>nemous Exhalations. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>This Acceſſory concurring Cauſe, <lb/>muſt be a particular Diſpoſition in <lb/>the
          Blood, to retain, and be affected <lb/>by theſe Infectious Vapours or Efflu- <lb/>viums of
          the Earth, and human <lb/>Bodies; otherwiſe all People would <lb/>be equally ſubject to be
          Infected at <lb/>the ſame time. To diſcover this <lb/>Diſpoſition, we are to conſider,
          that <lb/>whatever is contained in the Maſs of <lb/>Blood, as long as it is thin enough
          <lb/>to circulate through the Veſſels, there <lb/>is no danger of Obſtruction, and con-
          <lb/>ſequently there can no damage <lb/>happen, except it be too thin, and <lb/>corroſive,
          and opening the Extremi- <lb/>ties, or otherwiſe corroding and de- <lb/>ſtroying the
          Continuity of the Veſ- <lb/>ſels occaſions an Extravaſation; but <lb/>even to produce that
          Effect, the Hu- <lb/>mours muſt be very ſharp before they <lb/>can break the Veſſels, as
          long as they <lb/>circulate freely, ſince they ſtay not <pb xml:id="page_35" n="30"/>
          <lb/>long enough in any Part to produce <lb/>that Effect, and therefore we may <lb/>well
          conclude that there muſt be <lb/>Viſcocity alſo in the Blood, and that <lb/>thoſe viſcous
          Parts being either too <lb/>thick to circulate, or ſeparate from <lb/>the reſt, firſt
          cauſe an Obſtruction <lb/>and detain theſe corroſive Humours, <lb/>the perfect Mixture of
          the Blood be- <lb/>ing firſt broke and deſtroy'd by thoſe <lb/>Contagious Parts. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Indeed when the Veſſels are too <lb/>much crouded and extended with <lb/>Humours, as
          in Plethorick Bodies, <lb/>Corroſive Particles crouded and im- <lb/>pelled by the force of
          Circulation <lb/>into the ſmall Pores of the Veſſels, <lb/>may too much extend them and
          con- <lb/>tribute to ſeparate and divide the <lb/>continuity of their Parts; but ſince
          <lb/>there is Naturally a Viſcocity in the <lb/>Blood and Serum, and this may be, <lb/>and
          frequently is too great; this u- <lb/>nited with thoſe Corroſive Qualities, <lb/>and
          retaining them, will give them <pb xml:id="page_36" n="31"/>
          <lb/>a greater opportunity of Corroſion. <lb/>Thus a Viſcous Phlegm retaining a <lb/>ſharp
          Humour upon the Top of the <lb/>Stomach or Ventricle, where there <lb/>is a plentiful
          Diſtribution of Nerves, <lb/>cauſes a corroding Pain at the Sto- <lb/>mach, called
          Heart-burn; and <lb/>in the Membranes, about the <lb/>Muſculous Parts, occaſions Rheu-
          <lb/>matick Pains, eſpecially where they <lb/>are moſt Senſible and incapable of
          <lb/>Extenſion; and the Membranes of the <lb/>Joints corroded with a ſharp or Au-
          <lb/>ſtere Viſcous Matter produce thoſe <lb/>exceſſive Pains of the Gout, where <lb/>the
          Obſtruction ſo much retains thoſe <lb/>ſharp Humours that they corrode <lb/>the Veſſels in
          pieces, and occaſion <lb/>ſuch an extravaſation of this Viſcous <lb/>Matter as to produce
          and form <lb/>Nodes. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>From hence it plainly appearing <lb/>that a prediſpoſition in the Blood is <lb/>an
          acceſſory concurring Cauſe, and <lb/>that this prediſpoſed Humour, is a <pb
            xml:id="page_37" n="32"/>
          <lb/>Viſcous groſs Humour, which retains <lb/>and heaps up the Contagious Par- <lb/>ticles
          of the Air we imbibe, and <lb/>draw in with our Breath, it con- <lb/>ſequently follows,
          that the Conjunct <lb/>Cauſe, or Matter of the Diſeaſe is, <lb/>Contagious Particles
          lodged firſt in <lb/>a Viſcous Humour, which was an <lb/>acceſſory Antecedent Cauſe, and
          <lb/>diſengaged or ſeparated from the <lb/>ſharp Humour, and cauſing Ob- <lb/>ſtructions,
          becomes along with that <lb/>ſharp Contagious Humour, a Con- <lb/>junct Cauſe, and both
          together make <lb/>up the Material Cauſe, or the Mor- <lb/>bifick Matter of the Diſorder
          and <lb/>Diſtemper, which according to the <lb/>Degrees, produces more Malignant
          <lb/>Diſeaſes, and when abounding in an <lb/>extraordinary degree, even the Peſti-
          <lb/>lence, which is ſo obnoxious and fa- <lb/>tal to Mankind. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>And that a Viſcous Matter, along <lb/>with the Contagious Particles, is the
          <lb/>Conjunct Cauſe, and produces Ma- <pb xml:id="page_38" n="33"/>
          <lb/>lignant and Peſtilential Diſtempers, <lb/>is evident from hence, ſince all Peo-
          <lb/>ple are not equally ſubject to ſuch <lb/>Diſtempers, and ſome never have <lb/>any at
          all, though they live in a <lb/>Contagious Air, and amongſt In- <lb/>fected Perſons; and
          that a Viſcous <lb/>prediſpoſition of Blood is neceſſary <lb/>as a concurring Cauſe is
          manifeſt; <lb/>for as long as the Humours are ſuf- <lb/>ficiently attenuated, though ſharp
          <lb/>corroſive Particles are imbibed into <lb/>the Blood, and mixed with it in
          <lb/>Reſpiration, they are ſoon diſcharged <lb/>and ſeparated from it again, by the
          <lb/>common Emunctories and diſcharges <lb/>of Nature, as by Sweat, Tranſpi- <lb/>ration,
          Urine or Stool, before they <lb/>can have any time or power to alter <lb/>and corrupt the
          Blood by deſtroying <lb/>its Texture and Mixture, for the <lb/>conſtant Agitation and
          Circulation <lb/>of the Blood preſerves its Mixture <lb/>along time when kept in perpetual
          <lb/>Motion; but when the Blood is <lb/>too thick it retains a greater Quan- <pb
            xml:id="page_39" n="34"/>
          <lb/>tity, hinders the Natural Diſcharge, <lb/>and conſequently tends to heap up
          <lb/>Infectious Particles. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Beſides, when the Blood abounds <lb/>with Viſcous Parts, it produces a <lb/>larger
          Diſcharge or Separation of <lb/>Phlegmatick Parts, when its Texture <lb/>and Mixture is
          imperfect, which oc- <lb/>caſion Obſtructions, and concur to <lb/>produce Malignant
          Symptoms, when <lb/>thrown Critically upon the minute <lb/>Veſſels or Glands of any Part. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>When any ſuch Critical Diſcharge <lb/>is made, and a Malignant or Peſti- <lb/>lential
          Diſtemper is formed, and <lb/>properly in <hi rend="italic">eſſe</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
            >factu</hi>, that is, per- <lb/>fectly formed, the Antecedent, con- <lb/>junct and
          Acceſſory Cauſes along <lb/>with the Symptoms produced, make <lb/>up the formal Cauſe,
          which is the <lb/>Diſeaſe and its Symptoms. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But to compleat this, there is one <lb/>Cauſe acceſſory, which is the Proca- <pb
            xml:id="page_40" n="35"/>
          <lb/>tartick Cauſe, or that which puts <lb/>the Antecedent Cauſes in Action; <lb/>as any
          ſudden Paſſion of the Mind, <lb/>and the ill uſe of Non-Naturals, or <lb/>the force of
          Imagination; but that <lb/>which is chiefly ſo and External, is <lb/>the approaching Heat
          and Activity <lb/>of the Sun Beams, which put thoſe <lb/>Contagious Effluviums, Vapours or
          <lb/>Exhalations, in Action more briskly, <lb/>by encreaſing the Degrees of Fer-
          <lb/>mentation or Digeſtion, the Conſe- <lb/>quence of which we may juſtly <lb/>fear and
          dread; for if ſuch Conta- <lb/>gious Effluviums are in the Air, and <lb/>ſhould encreaſe,
          it may reaſonably <lb/>be feared, that Contagious Diſtem- <lb/>pers may happen more or
          leſs Ma- <lb/>lignant, if not Peſtilential, accord- <lb/>ing to the Degrees of the Primary
          <lb/>Antecedent Cauſe, <hi rend="italic">Viz.</hi> Extraneous <lb/>Mineral Exhalations,
          Vapours or <lb/>Effluviums, from which God Al- <lb/>mighty, or Art, muſt preſerve us, if
          <lb/>they ſhould by the courſe of Natu- <lb/>ral Cauſes break forth. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_41" n="36"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>From what hath been ſaid, it <lb/>appears what juſt cauſe we have <lb/>to dread the
          ill Conſequences of <lb/>Contagious Vapours, which we <lb/>may too reaſonably ſuſpect. It
          <lb/>may therefore be requiſite to con- <lb/>ſider, what Methods are moſt <lb/>proper to
          prevent and avert the E- <lb/>vent, and Conſequences of ſuch <lb/>dreadful Cauſes; which
          may eaſily <lb/>be deduced from what hath been <lb/>ſaid: For if Contagious Vapours
          <lb/>are retained by a Viſcous Indiſpo- <lb/>ſition of Blood, and ſharp Cor- <lb/>roſive
          Humours or Vapours, col- <lb/>lected and run into a Fluor, deſtroy <lb/>the Texture and
          Mixture of the <lb/>Blood, and by this Means produce <lb/>the Symptoms of Malignant or
          Peſti- <lb/>lential Diſtempers, the proper In- <lb/>tentions to prevent ſuch Accidents,
          <lb/>muſt be to Correct and Diſcharge <lb/>that Viſcous Matter which retains
          <lb/>Contagious Vapours, as well as to <lb/>correct and prevent the ill Effects of
          <lb/>thoſe Infectious Effluviums; it being <pb xml:id="page_42" n="37"/>
          <lb/>impoſſible either to prevent Mineral <lb/>Exhalations, which is the Primary
          <lb/>Antecedent Cauſe, or to hinder and <lb/>obſtruct the Sun's approach, which <lb/>is
          the Principal Procatartick Cauſe, <lb/>though ſometimes the Antecedent <lb/>Cauſe, when
          encreaſed to a great <lb/>Degree, and plentifully heaped up, <lb/>may alſo be a
          Procatartick Cauſe, <lb/>and put it ſelf in Action. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Since then the Principal Intentions <lb/>to prevent Malignant or Peſtilential
          <lb/>Diſtempers are to remove the Na- <lb/>tural Indiſpoſition, which retains
          <lb/>Contagious Vapours, and to correct <lb/>thoſe Vapours, or Malignant Par- <lb/>ticles
          which deſtroy the Texture of <lb/>the Blood, and produce ſuch fatal <lb/>Conſequences, we
          are to conſider <lb/>what is moſt reaſonable to be done. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>As for the Air, it is of ſuch vaſt <lb/>Extent, and the Superficies of the <lb/>Earth
          ſo large, that it will be hard <lb/>to deal with ſo extenſive a Subject <pb
            xml:id="page_43" n="38"/>
          <lb/>Phyſically, but in the Compaſs of a <lb/>human Body we may be more likely <lb/>to
          deal with them. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>As for the Prediſpoſition of the <lb/>Blood which renders human Bodies <lb/>moſt
          likely to retain them, and <lb/>to heap up Contagious Particles, <lb/>ſince that is a
          Viſcous Humour, it <lb/>is obvious to thoſe who have taken <lb/>Pains in Phyſick, what
          Intentions <lb/>are requiſite to that purpoſe; as <lb/>Bleeding and Purging, for Bleeding
          <lb/>emptying the Veſſels makes room <lb/>for Fluids to dilute and thin the reſt, <lb/>and
          Purging diſcharges a groſſer Hu- <lb/>mour than paſſes off by any other <lb/>Natural way,
          which Nature makes <lb/>uſe of. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>And to correct thoſe Contagious <lb/>Vapours which may already be <lb/>heaped up in
          the Blood, or may <lb/>hereafter be contracted, ſince they <lb/>wou<unclear>l</unclear>d
          paſs off, if nothing was in <lb/>the Way to obſt<unclear>r</unclear>uct them, without <pb
            xml:id="page_44" n="39"/>
          <lb/>deſtroying the Texture of the Blood, <lb/>ſince thin Humours flow beſt off by
          <lb/>Diaphoreſis, or through the Pores of <lb/>the Skin, when the groſs Humours <lb/>are
          removed by Bleeding and Purge- <lb/>ing Alexipharmick Diaphoreticks, <lb/>ſeem moſt proper
          for that purpoſe, <lb/>which may correct thoſe Malignant <lb/>Vapours and diſcharge them,
          and <lb/>conſequently preſerve the Texture <lb/>and due Mixture of the Blood, and
          <lb/>prevent thoſe Malignant and fatal <lb/>Conſequences. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>As for particular forms for this <lb/>purpoſe, I need not direct Phyſicians,
          <lb/>they being able to preſcribe for <lb/>themſelves; but every Body not <lb/>being
          Phyſicians, or able, or willing <lb/>to employ them, as too expenſive, <lb/>I ſhall
          recommend ſome Medicines <lb/>convenient for that purpoſe, to the <lb/>uſe of thoſe who
          think it worth <lb/>their while to preſerve their Health, <lb/>and guard themſelves from
          future ill <lb/>Conſequences. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_45" n="40"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>And, as I ſaid before, it may not <lb/>be amiſs to purſue ſuch meaſures, for
          <lb/>they will at leaſt have this advantage, <lb/>that if Peſtilential Diſtempers hap-
          <lb/>pen not; they will ſtill guard them- <lb/>ſelves from the Dangers of Malig- <lb/>nant
          Diſtempers, which will be worth <lb/>their while, and reward their Care <lb/>of their
          Health, and preſeve a good <lb/>Conſtitution. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Indeed for the ſake of thoſe who <lb/>cannot afford to imploy a Phyſician <lb/>I
          ſhould have laid down forms for <lb/>their uſe, that they might apply <lb/>themſelves to
          Apothecaries, but <lb/>ſome of them are too apt to adulte- <lb/>rate Medicines, and leave
          out any <lb/>Ingredients that are dear, though <lb/>moſt uſeful and neceſſary; beſides in
          <lb/>the ſeveral Books I have already <lb/>writ, I have been ſo free that way, <lb/>that
          ſeveral, though they have made <lb/>uſe of them to their Advantage, yet <lb/>they have not
          had the Civility to <lb/>acknowledge the freedom, in a way <pb xml:id="page_46" n="41"/>
          <lb/>cuſtomary to thoſe who have been <lb/>educated in Phyſick, though it hath <lb/>been
          the whole buſineſs and ſtudy of <lb/>my Life, ſince I left School Edu- <lb/>cation. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If therefore any one ſhall think it <lb/>worth their while to take care of <lb/>their
          Health, and guard themſelves <lb/>from future ill Conſequences, after <lb/>Bleeding to
          attenuate the Humours, <lb/>to diſcharge the Viſcous Humour, <lb/>though I hate any thing
          that looks <lb/>like common Quackery, not- <lb/>withſtanding the Art of Phyſick <lb/>was
          built upon it, I ſhall recom- <lb/>mend particular Medicines for that <lb/>purpoſe already
          prepared, with Di- <lb/>rections for their Uſe. Yet if any <lb/>ſhall apply themſelves to
          me for <lb/>Adviſe, I ſhall not ſcruple to pre- <lb/>ſcribe, let them make uſe of who
          <lb/>they pleaſe. But to proceed from <lb/>this accidental Digreſſion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The propereſt Purge which I <lb/>ſhould recommend upon this occa- <lb/>ſion, is Dr.
            <hi rend="italic">Sagittary</hi>'s Elixir, a Me- <pb xml:id="page_47" n="42"/>
          <lb/>dicine of Excellent Uſe, and diſ- <lb/>charging obnoxious Humours with a <lb/>great
          deal of Safety. This ought <lb/>to be taken once or twice a Week, <lb/>working gently, and
          by making a <lb/>gradual diſcharge without too much <lb/>force upon Nature, and therefore
          <lb/>moſt agreeable to human Bodies; <lb/>I have no Intereſt in recommending <lb/>this
          Excellent Medicine, but only <lb/>the good of Mankind. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Thoſe Days which are free from <lb/>Purging, they may take an <hi rend="italic">
            Anti-ma- <lb/>lignant</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Antipeſtilential Tincture</hi>,
          <lb/>which will correct thoſe Contagious <lb/>Vapours, and expel them out of <lb/>the
          Blood, gently through the Pores <lb/>of the Skin, without the trouble or <lb/>force of
          immoderate Sweat, or any <lb/>ſenſible ſweating at all, taking <lb/>a Spoonful every
          Morning, and <lb/>at Night going to Bed, in a Glaſs <lb/>of Wine and Water, or Wine only,
          <lb/>or in Beer, if any ſhall like it ra- <lb/>ther. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_48" n="43"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It alſo preſerves the due Mixture <lb/>and Craſis of the Maſs of Blood <lb/>and
          Humours, preſerving human <lb/>Bodies from Contagious Infection, <lb/>whether from thoſe
          more Malignant <lb/>or Peſtilential Effluviums, or Va- <lb/>pours diſperſed through the
          Air, <lb/>from the Superficial or Subter- <lb/>raneous Parts of the Earth, or from
          <lb/>the Bodies of Infected Perſons. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It alſo preſerves human Bodies in <lb/>ſuch a perfect ſtate of Health,
            tha<unclear>t</unclear>
          <lb/>it prevents and guards them from the <lb/>ill Effects of ſuch leſs Indiſpoſitions
          <lb/>and Intemperatures as occaſion and <lb/>render Mens Bodies liable to
            Agu<unclear>es</unclear>
          <lb/>or Intermitting Fevers, as in <hi rend="italic">Ke<unclear>nt</unclear></hi>
          <lb/>or <hi rend="italic">Eſſex</hi>; where it will be of ſingu- <lb/>lar and univerſal
          Uſe, if frequentl<unclear>y</unclear>
          <lb/>made uſe of in thoſe Climates. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It will likewiſe, if frequently mad<unclear>e</unclear>
          <lb/>uſe of, contribute to prevent the <lb/>ſpreading of that Contagious and
          <lb/>Infectious Diſtemper the Small-Pox, <lb/>or at leaſt render the
          B<unclear>l</unclear>ood of ſo <lb/>wholeſome a Diſpoſition, by clean- <pb
            xml:id="page_49" n="44"/>
          <lb/>ſing it of its Impurities, that if it <lb/>does not totally prevent them, yet <lb/>it
          will render them leſs virulent, or <lb/>much milder and leſs dangerous, and <lb/>prevent
          the unneceſſary hazard and <lb/>danger of Inoculation, a new con- <lb/>trived Practiſe
          which only foreſtalls <lb/>future by preſent Sickneſs, and ha- <lb/>ſtens on that
          Inconveniency which <lb/>would be effected or happen at a <lb/>greater diſtance of Time,
          or perhaps <lb/>not at all. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And that the Small-Pox depends <lb/>on a particular Diſpoſition of the <lb/>Air,
          which deſtroys the due mixture <lb/>of the Maſs of Blood, and makes <lb/>an Alteration in
          its Texture is very <lb/>evident, ſince we ſee, that this Diſ- <lb/>eaſe is often times
          Epidemical, and <lb/>rages more univerſally at one time <lb/>than another. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And that the Diſpoſition of the <lb/>Air, in this Caſe, deſtroys the Tex- <lb/>ture
          of the Blood, appears from the <lb/>Symptoms of it, for we ſee, that the <lb/>groſſer
          Particles of the Blood, in <pb xml:id="page_50" n="45"/>
          <lb/>that Diſeaſe, are not only ſeparated <lb/>from the reſt, but that they are cri-
          <lb/>tically caſt off in the Glands of the <lb/>Skin; which evidently appears, ſince
          <lb/>as the Air is impregnated with par- <lb/>ticular Vapours, milder, or more <lb/>ſharp
          and biteing, the Pox are of a <lb/>benign kind, or Corroſive, and oc- <lb/>caſion Pits, or
          Exulcerations which <lb/>leave disfiguring Marks behind them. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But in this Diſtemper there is not <lb/>only a depraved Indiſpoſition in the
          <lb/>Air, but likewiſe a Prediſpoſition in <lb/>the Maſs of Humours is requiſite
          <lb/>which from the Symptoms appears <lb/>to be Viſcous, and to depend per- <lb/>haps on
          the faults of Digeſtion, and <lb/>Crudities thus congeſted in their <lb/>Infancy, but this
          we have not time <lb/>or room to conſider thoroughly. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I ſhall only add, that to prevent <lb/>this Diſtemper the Purgeing Elixir <lb/>may be
          uſed once a Week, and the <lb/>Tincture before-mentioned thoſe <lb/>Days that are free
          from Purgeing, and <lb/>for ſome time after, which are alſo <pb xml:id="page_51" n="46"/>
          <lb/>frequently to be repeated; the Quan- <lb/>tity to be proportioned according to
          <lb/>the Perſon's Age, Directions for which <lb/>will be given along with that Tincture. </p>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>Of the Differences of Contagious Vapours. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Since in the foregoing Sheets we <lb/>have taken Notice, that Malignant and
            <lb/>Contagious Diſtempers depend on, and <lb/>are occaſioned by pernicious Vapours
            <lb/>and Exhalations riſing out of the <lb/>Bowels or the Superficial Parts of the
            <lb/>Earth, impregnating the Air we <lb/>breathe, and acting upon Bodies pre-
            <lb/>indiſpoſed, and furniſhed with Viti- <lb/>ous depraved Humours; we ſhall
            <lb/>briefly add ſomething of the differ- <lb/>ences of thoſe Contagious Vapours
            <lb/>and Exhalations which produce theſe <lb/>different Effects; the Effects varying,
            <lb/>as we before took notice, according <lb/>to the variety of the Cauſes. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>And firſt Watry Exhalations ren- <lb/>der the Air thick and moiſt, and ob-
            <lb/>noxious to Athmatick Perſons, and <lb/>thoſe that have moiſt Lungs; theſe <pb
              xml:id="page_52" n="47"/>
            <lb/>with Nitrous acid Effluviums occaſi- <lb/>on Agues, The Famous Mr. <hi
              rend="italic">Boyle</hi>
            <lb/>Obſerving that a particular Acid mix- <lb/>ed with a Volatile, produces a Cold
            <lb/>Effervency; In the Small-Pox, the <lb/>Mixture of the Blood is Broke by
            <lb/>Vitriolick Vapours or Effluviums, <lb/>which appears from the Curdling
            <lb/>Effects, which produce Tumours in <lb/>the Skin, and alſo from the Nauſeous
            <lb/>Smell attending that Diſeaſe. Malig- <lb/>nant Fevers depend on a higher degree
            <lb/>of corroſive Mineral Salts, producing <lb/>a higher degree of Crudities, and
            <lb/>much more than Nature can digeſt, <lb/>throw off or diſcharge. In Peſtilen-
            <lb/>tial Diſtempers the Effluviums are of <lb/>a more Malignant kind, and rather of
            <lb/>an Arſenical Nature, producing <lb/>Symptoms of a proportionable De- <lb/>gree of
            Malignancy and more per- <lb/>nicious. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>How theſe Malignant Effects may <lb/>be prevented, we have already obſer- <lb/>ved,
            and where this Tincture may be <lb/>had, I ſhall annex by way of Adver- <lb/>ment. </p>
        </div>
        <trailer rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_53"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">N. B.</hi> THis Cordial, Anti-Malignant Tincture, will be Sold at
          Mr. <hi rend="italic">Osborns,</hi> at the <hi rend="italic">Golden-Lyon,</hi> at St. <hi
            rend="italic">Margarets-Hill, Southwark;</hi> Mr. <hi rend="italic">Scaggs</hi>'s an
          Inſtrument Makers at <hi rend="italic">Wapping-New-Stairs, Wapping;</hi> Mr. <hi
            rend="italic">Dyſons,</hi> at die <hi rend="italic">Wool∣pack</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
            >Burchin-Lane,</hi> near the <hi rend="italic">Royal-Exchange;</hi> Mr. <hi
            rend="italic">Tredwells,</hi> a Toy-Shop, at the Corner of St. <hi rend="italic"
            >Martins-Le-Grand, Newgate-Street;</hi> Mr. <hi rend="italic">Hookes,</hi> Bookſeller,
          oppoſite to St. <hi rend="italic">Dunſtan</hi>'s-Church, near <hi rend="italic"
            >Temple-Barr;</hi> Mr. <hi rend="italic">Hargraves,</hi> at St. <hi rend="italic"
            >Anns</hi> Coffee-Houſe, over againſt the Church; Mr. <hi rend="italic">Oakey,</hi>
          Grocer, at the <hi rend="italic">Golden-Sugar-L<unclear>##</unclear>f,</hi> in <hi
            rend="italic">Old Bonſtreet,</hi> near <hi rend="italic">Piccadilly;</hi> Mr. <hi
            rend="italic">Ewens,</hi> a <unclear>#</unclear>oy-Shop, at the <hi rend="italic">Seven
            Stars,</hi> near <hi rend="italic">York Buildings</hi> in the <hi rend="italic"
            >Strand.</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>BOOKS Writ and Publiſhed by the Author. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A Treatiſe of the Reaſon of Muſcular Mo- <lb/>tion, or the Efficient Cauſes of the
          con- <lb/>traction o<unclear>#</unclear> a Muſcle. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A Treatiſe of the Reaſon of the Heat of the Blood, and of the Uſe of the Lungs. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>An Epitomy of Mr. <hi rend="italic">Boyles</hi> Philoſophical Works, in Four Volumes.
            <hi rend="italic">Octavo.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>An Epitomy of Mr. <hi rend="italic">Boyles</hi> Theological Works, in Three Volumes,
          with his Life prefixed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A Syſtem of Rational and Practical Surgery. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A Treatiſe of the <hi rend="italic">Gout, King's-Evil, Lues Ve- <lb/>nerea,</hi> with
          an Eſſay of the Reaſon of Intermit- <lb/>ting Fevers, and the Effects of the <hi
            rend="italic">Cortex Peru.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A Compleat Hiſtory of Witchcraft, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> in Two Volumes. <hi
            rend="italic">Octavo.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A Vindication of the ſame againſt Reflections of Dr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Hutchinſons,</hi> now Biſhop of <hi rend="italic">Down an Connor.</hi> To which is
          added, an Eſſay on the Nature of Material and Immaterial Subſtances. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>An Eſſay on the Plague printed at <hi rend="italic">Dublin.</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
