<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Jurin: An account of the success of inoculating the small pox in
          Great Britain</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>James Jurin</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main"> AN ACCOUNT Of the SUCCESS of INOCULATING THE SMALL POX In GREAT
              BRITAIN. WITH A Comparison between the Miscarriages in that Practice, and the
              Mortality of the Natural Small-Pox. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T18700</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T18700"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Peele, at Locke's Head in Pater-Noster Row,
                  1724.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1724</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="5"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="39"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="3"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3306815660</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K029453.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: method"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <head rend="align-center space"><lb/>TO <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">Her Royal Highneſs
          </hi><lb/>THE <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">Princeſs of WALES</hi>. </head>
        <lb rend="indent"/>
        <salute>MADAM, </salute>
        <p rend="space"><lb/>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>Decorative frame around the letter "T".</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <hi rend="dc(4)">T</hi>HE great and <w part="I">undeſerv-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>
          Honour you have <lb/>been pleas'd to grant<lb/> me, of laying theſe <w part="I"
            >Pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">pers</w> at the Feet of your <lb/><hi rend="sc">Royal
            Highness</hi>, juſtly demands <pb xml:id="page_3"/><lb/>the moſt thankful
          Acknowledgement: <lb/>Inaſmuch, as it muſt be a Means of <lb/>preſerving me from the
          Cenſures, or <lb/>Suſpicions of thoſe, whom my own <lb/>Character, little known in the
          World, <lb/>may not ſatisfy of the Impartiality <lb/>and Regard to Truth, which I have
          <lb/>obſerv'd therein. For it will not <lb/>ſurely be imagin'd, that I ſhould <lb/>preſume
          to offer to ſo Great, ſo <lb/>Good, and ſo diſcerning a <hi rend="sc">Princess</hi>,
          <lb/>any Account of a Matter of ſo much <lb/>Conſequence to Mankind, but what <lb/>is in
          all Reſpects juſt and true, to the <lb/>beſt of my Knowledge. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is, <hi rend="sc">Madam</hi>, by ſuch an <w part="I">Ac-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">count</w>, that the Practice of <w part="I">Inocu-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >lation</w> muſt ſtand, or fall. If upon <lb/>a fair and exact Balance of the <pb
            xml:id="page_4"/><lb/>good and ill Succeſs of it, it appear <lb/>in the main to be
          beneficial to <w part="I">Man-</w><lb/><w part="F">kind</w>; it will in Time, in deſpite
          of <lb/>Clamour and unreaſonable <w part="I">Oppoſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, be
          reckon'd among the many <lb/>Bleſſings, for which theſe Nations, <lb/>under the Divine
          Providence, are <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">debted</w> to the Illuſtrious Houſe of
            <lb/><hi rend="sc">Brunswick</hi>: And if it prove the <lb/>contrary, I need not ſay,
          that <w part="I">nei-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> the Name and powerful <w part="I"
            >Patro-</w><lb/><w part="F">nage</w> of your <hi rend="sc">Royal Highness</hi>, nor
          <lb/>the happy Succeſs it has been <w part="I">attend-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> with on
          the growing Hopes of <lb/><hi rend="sc">Britain</hi>, will be able to protect it. <lb/>For
          if this ſhould be the Caſe, I am <lb/>well aſſured, that the ſame Noble <lb/>and God-like
          Motive of doing Good, <lb/>which has hitherto prompted you to <lb/>countenance this
          Practice, will then <lb/>no leſs powerfully induce you to <pb xml:id="page_5"
          /><lb/>abandon and diſcourage it. I am, <lb/>with the greateſt Submiſſion, <w part="I"
            >Re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſpect</w>, and Duty, </p>
        <salute><hi rend="sc">Madam,</hi></salute>
        <signed rend="indent hanging space"><lb/>Your <hi rend="sc">Royal Highness</hi>'s <lb/>Moſt
          obedient, <lb/>Moſt faithful, and <lb/>Moſt devoted Servant, <lb/>J. JURIN. </signed>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_6" n="1"/>
      <head rend="align-center"><lb/>AN <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">ACCOUNT</hi>
        <lb/>OF <hi rend="dc(2)"><lb/>The Succeſs of <w part="I">Inocula-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ting</w> the <hi rend="sc">Small Pox</hi>
          <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">Great Britain, &amp;c.</hi></hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space"><lb/>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>Decorative frame around the letter "T".</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <hi rend="dc(4)">T</hi>HE Diſputes about the <w part="I">Pra-</w><lb/><w part="F">ctice</w>
        of Inoculating the <lb/><hi rend="sc">Small Pox</hi>, like many of <lb/>our other
        Differences, have <lb/>been carry'd to ſo great a <lb/>Height, that it is difficult <lb/>for
        any one to write upon <lb/>this Subject, without being drawn into <w part="I"
          >Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">troverſy</w>, even tho' he delivers only Matter <lb/>of Fact, or
        the undeniable Conſequences drawn <lb/>from it, and that with the greateſt <w part="I"
          >Impartia-</w><lb/><w part="F">lity</w>, and the ſtricteſt Regard to Truth. <pb
          xml:id="page_7" n="2"/><lb/>Tho' ſuch a Procedure, one would imagine, <lb/>ſhould ſo far
        entitle the Writer to the good <lb/>Nature and Protection of the World, as to <w part="I"
          >ſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cure</w> him from the Attacks of either Party; <lb/>eſpecially as
        in acting thus, he cannot favour <lb/>or prejudice either of them, any otherwiſe than
        <lb/>as the Facts themſelves declare for, or againſt <lb/>them. At leaſt, thoſe who contend
        only for <lb/>Truth, ought never to be out of Humour with <lb/>him, who indifferently
        furniſhes either Side <lb/>with the proper Materials for the Support of <lb/>their Opinion,
        or the Conviction of its being <lb/>not to be maintain'd. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>With this Deſign I laid before the World a <lb/>little <note
          place="bottom" n="*">* <hi rend="italic">Letter to Dr.</hi> Coteſworth. </note> Piece the
        laſt Year, and intend, God <lb/>willing, to continue ſo doing, from Year to <lb/>Year, 'till
        the Practice of Inoculation ſhall <w part="I">ei-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> be
        eſtabliſh'd on a firm and laſting Foot, <lb/>or ſhall be juſtly exploded; the Fate thereof
        <lb/>being, as I conceive, only to be determin'd <lb/>by Matter of Fact and Experience
        faithfully <lb/>related. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>In Order to be able to do which, I have <lb/>uſed my beſt Endeavours,
        with the Aſſiſtance <lb/>of my Friends, to procure the moſt <w part="I">Authen-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">tick</w> Accounts I was able; and I ſhall be <lb/>thankful to all Perſons, who at
        any Time <lb/>hereafter, will be pleaſed to ſend me well <lb/>atteſted Relations of any
        Particulars relating <lb/>to the Succeſs of this Practice, bad as well as <lb/>good; all
        which, they may be aſſured, ſhall <lb/>be juſtly repreſented. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>To impoſe upon the World in any <w part="I">Particu-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >lar</w>, is diſingenuous and baſe; but to deceive <lb/>them in an Affair ſo nearly
        concerning the <pb xml:id="page_8" n="3"/><lb/>Lives of Mankind, is a Wickedneſs worthy
        <lb/>of the utmoſt Abhorrence and Deteſtation. <lb/>I hope none, that know me, will think me
        <lb/>capable of any Thing ſo criminal; and as for <lb/>others, I beg they will not too
        eaſily give <lb/>Credit to flying Reports, with which the <lb/>World is too often amuſed,
        without any juſt <lb/>Foundation; but that, in Caſe of Doubt <lb/>about any Thing which I
        ſhall here deliver, <lb/>they will be pleaſed to give themſelves the <lb/>Trouble of
        peruſing the Materials in my <lb/>Hands, which I ſhall carefully preſerve, and <lb/>be ready
        to ſhew them for their Satisfaction, <lb/>as Vouchers of my Fidelity. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>This Controverſy, though drawn out into <lb/>many Particulars, ſeems
        principally to turn <lb/>upon the two following Points. </p>
      <list>
        <lb/>
        <item>1. Whether the Diſtemper given by <w part="I">Inocu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lation</w> be
          an effectual Security to the <lb/>Patient, againſt his having the Small <lb/>Pox
          afterwards in the natural Way? </item>
        <lb/>
        <item>2. Whether the Hazard of Inoculation be <lb/>conſiderably leſs than that of the <w
            part="I">natu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ral</w> Small Pox? </item>
      </list>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>If theſe two Points were effectually ſettled, <lb/>there would, I
        ſuppoſe, be an End of the <lb/>Diſpute, at leaſt among Phyſicians. For, if <lb/>either of
        them be fairly determin'd in the <lb/>Negative, the Practice of Inoculation muſt <lb/>on all
        Hands be given up. And on the other <lb/>Hand, if the Teſt of Experience ſhould plainly <pb
          xml:id="page_9" n="4"/><lb/>declare for the affirmative Side of both theſe <lb/>Queſtions,
        I doubt not but that every <w part="I">Gen-</w><lb/><w part="F">tleman</w>, who has the
        Honour to ſerve his <lb/>Country in the Capacity of a Phyſician, will <lb/>have Integrity
        and Humanity enough to <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">clare</w> himſelf honeſtly and
        openly in Favour <lb/>of the Practice. At leaſt, he will conſider, <lb/>whether it will be
        for his Reputation, when <lb/>his Friend and his Patient ſhall put his Life, <lb/>or the
        Lives of his Children, into his Hands, <lb/>to amuſe himſelf with Theological Diſputes
        <lb/>and Scruples, whether it be lawful to ſave <lb/>them. For if the Practice of
        Inoculation be <lb/>really found to be a Means of preſerving <lb/>Life, it will not be eaſy
        to make the World <lb/>believe, that it is criminal to uſe it. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>As to the firſt, therefore, of theſe Queſtions, <lb/>though it will
        require a conſiderable Length <lb/>of Time, and a much greater Number of <w part="I"
          >Ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">periments</w> than have yet been made, before <lb/>it can be
        abſolutely determin'd; yet thus <lb/>much may at preſent be ſaid, that our <w part="I"
          >Expe-</w><lb/><w part="F">rience</w>, as far as it goes, has hitherto ſtrongly
        <lb/>favour'd the affirmative Side. For tho' many <lb/>Trials have been purpoſely made by <w
          part="I">Phyſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cians</w> and others, both upon Children and
        <lb/>grown Perſons, who have had the Small Pox <lb/>by Inoculation, in cauſing them not only
        <lb/>to converſe with, but to handle, to nurſe, and <lb/>to lie in the ſame Bed with others
        ſick of the <lb/>natural Small Pox; yet there is no Inſtance, <lb/>as far as I have been
        able to learn, of any one <lb/>Perſon either in <hi rend="italic">Turky, New-England,</hi>
        or here at <lb/>Home, who has receiv'd the Small Pox by <w part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >oculation</w>, that has afterwards had it in the <w part="I">na-</w><pb xml:id="page_10"
          n="5"/><lb/><w part="F">tural</w> Way. If any ſuch Caſe ſhall hereafter <lb/>come to my
        Knowledge, I ſhall not fail to lay <lb/>it faithfully before the World; tho' it is to be
        <lb/>obſerv'd, that a ſingle Inſtance or two of this <lb/>Kind, out of a very great Number
        of Perſons <lb/>inoculated, ought not in Reaſon to overthrow <lb/>the Practice. For it
        cannot be expected, that <lb/>a Perſon who receives the Small Pox by <w part="I"
          >Ino-</w><lb/><w part="F">culation</w>, ſhould be ſafer from having it again, <lb/>than
        one that has undergone it in the natural <lb/>Way; and we are not certain, that the Small
        <lb/>Pox does never, tho' perhaps exceeding <w part="I">rare-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w>,
        happen twice naturally to the ſame <w part="I">Per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſon</w>. For my own
        Part, I have never known <lb/>it: But my ingenious Friend, Mr. <hi rend="italic">Iſaac <w
            part="I">Maſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſey</w>,</hi> Apothecary, whom I the rather name,
        <lb/>becauſe he is known to be no Friend to <w part="I">Ino-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >culation</w>, has aſſur'd me, that he ſaw the ſame <lb/>Perſon twice undergo the natural
        Small Pox. <lb/>This, however, undoubtedly happens very <lb/>ſeldom; but if it does happen
        in the natural <lb/>Way, it may happen likewiſe after <w part="I">Inocula-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">tion</w>; and conſequently, a Perſon who has <lb/>receiv'd the Diſtemper by this
        Means, muſt <lb/>content himſelf with no greater a Degree of <lb/>Security, than if he had
        undergone it <w part="I">natu-</w><lb/><w part="F">rally</w>. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>But if the Perſon inoculated does not <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ceive</w> the Diſtemper in any Degree from that <lb/>Operation, as ſometimes
        falls out; in ſuch <lb/>a Caſe we have no Reaſon to be ſurpriz'd, <lb/>if he afterwards
        happen to be taken with <lb/>it in the natural Way. Inoculation, like all <lb/>other
        Applications in Phyſick or Surgery, <lb/>will not always produce the intended Effect. <pb
          xml:id="page_11" n="6"/><lb/>And no Wonder. We know from a <w part="I">thou-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſand</w> Inſtances, that of ſeveral Perſons, <w part="I">equal-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ly</w> expoſed to the ſame contagious Diſeaſe, <lb/>Part ſhall eſcape, and Part
        be infected; and <lb/>the ſame Perſon, expoſing himſelf in the <lb/>ſame Manner, at
        different Times, to the <lb/>ſame Danger, ſhall eſcape at one Time, and <lb/>be ſeiz'd at
        another. The ſame has happen'd <lb/>twice in the Caſe of Inoculation: Two <w part="I"
          >Chil-</w><lb/><w part="F">dren</w>, who had been inoculated without any <lb/>Manner of
        Effect, as is atteſted, not only by <lb/>the Phyſician, Dr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Nettleton,</hi> but by the <w part="I">Cer-</w><lb/><w part="F">tificates</w> of the
        Parents themſelves, were <w part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F">terwards</w> ſeiz'd with the
        Small Pox, when it <lb/>raged epidemically where they were; they <lb/>had it favourably, and
        recover'd. The <w part="I">Re-</w><lb/><w part="F">lation</w> ſent up to me, with the
        Certificates, <lb/>by Dr. <hi rend="italic">Nettleton,</hi> was publiſh'd ſome Months
        <lb/>ago in the <hi rend="italic">Daily Journal,</hi> and is reprinted at <lb/>the End of
        this Paper, the Originals being <lb/>ſtill in my Hands. And theſe are all the <lb/>Caſes of
        this Kind that are come to my <w part="I">Know-</w><lb/><w part="F">ledge</w>, except a like
        Caſe of Mr. <hi rend="italic">De Grave</hi> the <lb/>Surgeon's Daughter; an Account of
        which, <lb/>under the Father's own Hand, has been <w part="I">pub-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >liſh'd</w> by Mr. <hi rend="italic">Maitland.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>In Order to come to ſome Determination <lb/>of the ſecond Queſtion, <hi
          rend="italic">viz.</hi> Whether the <lb/>Hazard of Inoculation be conſiderably leſs
        <lb/>than that of the natural Small Pox? It is <w part="I">ne-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ceſſary</w> in the firſt Place, to know what is the <lb/>Proportion between the Numbers
        of thoſe that <lb/>undergo the Small Pox in the natural Way, <lb/>and thoſe that die of
        them. With this View, <pb xml:id="page_12" n="7"/><lb/>I have prov'd in my Piece <note
          place="bottom" n="*">* <hi rend="italic">Letter to Dr.</hi> Coteſworth. </note> publiſh'd
        laſt Year, <lb/>that at leaſt a fourteenth Part of Mankind <lb/>die of the natural Small
        Pox; and I have, <lb/>I think, render'd it probable, that, of <w part="I">Per-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſons</w> of all Ages undergoing that Diſtemper, <lb/>there die at leaſt two in
        ſeventeen. Theſe <lb/>Deductions are drawn from the Conſideration <lb/>of the Bills of
        Mortality for 42 Years paſt: <lb/>And from an actual Account of a great <w part="I"
          >Num-</w><lb/><w part="F">ber</w> of Perſons that underwent that Diſeaſe, <lb/>as taken in
        ſeveral Places, by a careful <w part="I">En-</w><lb/><w part="F">quiry</w> from Houſe to
        Houſe, I have there <lb/>ſhown, that there died one in between five or <lb/>ſix, or about
        two in eleven. I ſhall now <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">peat</w> that Account with
        ſeveral others, which <lb/>have ſince been communicated to me by <w part="I">Per-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſons</w> of Credit, in the following Table. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><table>
          <row>
            <cell role="label" rows="1" cols="1"> </cell>
            <cell rend="italic" role="label" rows="1" cols="1">Sick of the Small Pox. </cell>
            <cell rend="italic" role="label" rows="1" cols="1">Died </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">In <hi rend="italic">Halifax</hi></cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">276</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">43</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">In a Part of the Pariſh of <hi rend="italic">Hali-<lb/>fax,</hi>
              ſtretching towards <hi rend="italic">Brad-<lb/>ford</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">297</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">59</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">In another Part of the ſame <lb/>Pariſh—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">268</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">28</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">In <hi rend="italic">Barſland, Ripponden, Sorby,</hi>
              <lb/>and another Part of <hi rend="italic">Halifax</hi>
              <lb/>Pariſh, about four Miles from <lb/>the Town—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">230</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">38</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">In <hi rend="italic">Bradford</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">129</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">36</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">In <hi rend="italic">Leeds</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">792</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">189</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">In <hi rend="italic">Wakefield</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">418</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">57</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">In <hi rend="italic">Rochdale</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">177</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">38</cell>
          </row>
          <pb xml:id="page_13" n="8"/>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">In <hi rend="italic">Asbton under Line,</hi> a ſmall <lb/>Market
              Town in <hi rend="italic">Lancaſhire,</hi>
              <lb/>including two neighbouring <lb/>Villages—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">279</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">56</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">In <hi rend="italic">Bolton, Lancaſhire</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">406</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">89</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">In <hi rend="italic">Macclesfield</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">302</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">37</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">In <hi rend="italic">Stockport</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">287</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">73</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">In <hi rend="italic">Hatherfield</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">180</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">20</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rend="italic" rows="1" cols="1">Ware —</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">612</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">72</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rend="italic" rows="1" cols="1">Salisbury— </cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">1244</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">165</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1"><hi rend="italic">Rumſy</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
              >Hampſhire</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">913</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">143</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1"><hi rend="italic">Boſton</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
                >New-England</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">5742</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">841</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rend="italic" rows="1" cols="1">Chicheſter —</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">994</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">168</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1"><hi rend="italic">Haverford Weſt</hi> in <hi rend="italic">South
                Wales</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">227</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">52</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rend="italic" rows="1" cols="1">Bedford —</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">786</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">147</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rend="italic" rows="1" cols="1">Total </cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">14559</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">2351</cell>
          </row>
        </table></p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Reſult is, that as far as theſe Accounts <lb/>can inform us, there
        dies nearly one out of <lb/>ſix Perſons ſick of the Small Pox in the <w part="I"
          >na-</w><lb/><w part="F">tural</w> Way, or (more accurately) five out of <lb/>thirty one:
        Which Proportion we muſt <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tent</w> our ſelves with for
        the preſent; 'till by <lb/>obtaining Accounts from more Places, we may <lb/>by the Largeneſs
        of the Numbers, come <w part="I">near-</w><lb/><w part="F">er</w> to the true Proportion. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Such therefore being the Hazard of dying <lb/>of the Small Pox in the
        natural Way; we <lb/>come now to conſider what is the Hazard of <lb/>dying of the Inoculated
        Small Pox; in Order <lb/>to which, we offer the following Liſts of <w part="I"
          >Per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſons</w> inoculated; which we hope may be <w part="I"
          >de-</w><lb/><w part="F">pended</w>
        <pb xml:id="page_14" n="9"/><lb/>upon, as having taken all poſſible <lb/>Care to obtain the
        beſt Accounts that we <lb/>could. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The firſt contains the Number of Perſons <lb/>inoculated to the End of
        the Year 1723, <lb/>with the Names of the Perſons that perform'd, <lb/>or directed the
        Operation, and the Places <lb/>where it was done. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><table>
          <head rend="align-center"><hi rend="italic">Perſons inoculated in the Years</hi> 1721,
            <lb/>1722, 1723.</head>
          <row>
            <cell cols="2" rows="1" rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic ">In and about</hi>
              London,</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1"><hi rend="dc(3)">B</hi>Y <hi rend="italic">Claudius Amyand,</hi>
              Eſq; Principal <lb/>and Serjeant Surgeon in Ordinary to <lb/>his Majeſty—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">62</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">By Mr. <hi rend="italic">Maitland,</hi> Surgeon—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">85</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">By Mr. <hi rend="italic">Alexander Geekie,</hi> Surgeon—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Mr. <hi rend="italic">Geekie,</hi> Jun. Surgeon—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">1</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Mr. <hi rend="italic">Weymiſh,</hi> Surgeon—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">5</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Mr. <hi rend="italic">Dover,</hi> M. L.—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">5</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">The Reverend Dr. <hi rend="italic">Johnſon</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">3</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell cols="2" rows="1" rend="align-center"><lb/>In <hi rend="italic">Yorkſhire,</hi>
              and the County of <hi rend="italic">Durham, &amp;c.</hi></cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">By <hi rend="italic">Ditto</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">8</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Dr. <hi rend="italic">Nettleton</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">80</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell cols="2" rows="1" rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">In and about</hi>
              Norwich.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">By the Direction of Sir <hi rend="italic">Benjamin
              Wrench</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">6</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Dr. <hi rend="italic">Bohun</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">4</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Dr. <hi rend="italic">Offley</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">6</cell>
          </row>
          <pb xml:id="page_15" n="10"/>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">By Mr. <hi rend="italic">Johnſon,</hi> Apothecary—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">1</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Mr. <hi rend="italic">Brady,</hi> Apothecary—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell cols="2" rows="1" rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">At</hi>
              Stamford.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">By Mr. <hi rend="italic">Hepburn,</hi> Surgeon—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell cols="2" rows="1" rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">In and near</hi>
              Portſmouth.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">By the Direction of Dr. <hi rend="italic">Brady,</hi> Phyſician
              <lb/>to the Garriſon there—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">6</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Mr. <hi rend="italic">Waller.</hi> Apothecary—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">14</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Mr. <hi rend="italic">Robert Barkham,</hi> Apothecary—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">6</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Mr. <hi rend="italic">Rowe,</hi> Surgeon, at <hi rend="italic"
                >Fareham</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">5</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell cols="2" rows="1" rend="align-center"><hi rend="italic">At</hi> Chicheſter.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">By Mr. <hi rend="italic">Smith,</hi> Surgeon—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">11</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Mr. <hi rend="italic">Dymer,</hi> Surgeon—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">4</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Mr. <hi rend="italic">Robert Baker,</hi> Surgeon in <hi
                rend="italic">London,</hi> by <lb/>the Direction of Dr. <hi rend="italic"
                >Whitaker</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">1</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell cols="2" rows="1"><hi rend="italic">At</hi> Steyning <hi rend="italic">in</hi>
              Suſſex.—</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">By Mr. <hi rend="italic">William Hill,</hi> Surgeon—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell cols="2" rows="1" rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">At</hi>
              Havant.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">By Mr. <hi rend="italic">Millard,</hi> Surgeon, by the <w
                part="I">Di-</w><lb/><w part="F">rection</w> of Dr. <hi rend="italic">Edward
                Bayly</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell cols="2" rows="1" rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">At</hi>
              Wincheſter.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">By Mr. <hi rend="italic">Baconneau,</hi> Surgeon—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Mr. <hi rend="italic">Godwin,</hi> Apothecary—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">15</cell>
          </row>
          <pb xml:id="page_16" n="11"/>
          <row>
            <cell cols="2" rows="1" rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">At</hi> Rumſey <hi
                rend="italic">in</hi> Wiltſhire.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">By Mr. <hi rend="italic">Oliver,</hi> Apothecary—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">3</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell cols="2" rows="1" rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">At</hi>
              Salisbury.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">By Mr. <hi rend="italic">James Elderton,</hi> M. L.—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">35</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Mr. <hi rend="italic">Geldwyer,</hi> Surgeon—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">51</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Mr. <hi rend="italic">Foulks,</hi> Surgeon—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">13</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell cols="2" rows="1" rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">At</hi>
              Shaftsbury.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">By Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Dorothy Ringe</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">4</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell cols="2" rows="1" rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">At</hi>
              Haverford-Weſt, South Wales.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">By Dr. <hi rend="italic">Williams</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">7</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell cols="2" rows="1" rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Near</hi>
              Leiceſter.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">By Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Roberts</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">5</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell cols="2" rows="1" rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">In and about</hi>
              Bedford.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">By Mr. <hi rend="italic">Daniel,</hi> Surgeon—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">10</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Mr. <hi rend="italic">Fleming,</hi> Apothecary—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">1</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell cols="2" rows="1" rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">At</hi>
              Briſtol.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">By Dr. <hi rend="italic">French</hi>—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">1</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell cols="2" rows="1" rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">At</hi>
              Cambridge.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">By Mr. <hi rend="italic">Warren,</hi> Surgeon—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">4</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rend="italic" rows="1" cols="1">Total </cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">474</cell>
          </row>
        </table></p>
      <pb xml:id="page_17" n="12"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The ſecond Table contains the Number of <lb/>Perſons of every ſeveral
        Age there expreſs'd, <lb/>that were inoculated, with the Effect of the <lb/>Operation </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>In Order to make which the better <w part="I">under-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſtood</w>, as well as for the Information of thoſe <lb/>Readers, who may have Occaſion to
        make <lb/>Uſe of this Practice, I ſhall here give ſome <lb/>Account of what is to be done,
        and what is <lb/>uſually obſerv'd in Inoculation, as I have <lb/>extracted it from a careful
        Examination and <lb/>Compariſon of the ſeveral Relations <w part="I">tranſ-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">mitted</w> to me, with Regard, 1ſt, To the <w part="I">Sub-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ject</w> to be inoculated: 2d, The Preparation: <lb/>3d, The Choice of the infectious
        Matter: 4th, <lb/>The Operation: 5th, The Sickening, or the <lb/>Symptons preceding the
        Eruption: 6th, The <lb/>Eruption: 7th, The Running of the Inciſions. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="1"><lb/>1. Great Care ought to be taken to <w part="I">inocu-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">late</w> none but Perſons of a good Habit of <lb/>Body, and free, not only from
        any <w part="I">appa-</w><lb/><w part="F">rent</w>, but, as far as can be judg'd, from
        <lb/>any latent Diſeaſe; for which Reaſon, every <lb/>prudent Perſon will, in this Caſe,
        have the <lb/>Advice and Opinion of his own Phyſician, <lb/>whether the Subject to be
        inoculated, be in a <lb/>fit Condition to undergo the ſmall Pox; that <lb/>ſo he may not
        have that Diſtemper, and <lb/>a bad Conſtitution, or perhaps another <w part="I"
          >Di-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſeaſe</w>, to ſtruggle with at the ſame Time; of <lb/>which there
        have been ſeveral fatal Inſtances, <lb/>thro' the Neglect of this Caution. In ſome
        <lb/>Caſes indeed it has fallen out, that the Perſon <lb/>inoculated, has by this Means got
        free of <w part="I">an-</w><lb/><w part="F">other</w> Diſeaſe, under which he labour'd <w
          part="I">be-</w><pb xml:id="page_18" n="13"/><lb/><w part="F">fore</w>; as ſometimes
        happens likewiſe in the <lb/>natural Way, though the contrary is much <lb/>more frequent. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="2"><lb/>2. The Body, eſpecially if Plethorick, <lb/>ought to be prepared
        by proper Evacuations, <lb/>as bleeding, purging, vomiting, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        tho' in <lb/>many Caſes there will be Occaſion for very <lb/>little or none of theſe, it
        being ſufficient to <lb/>enjoyn a temperate Diet, and proper <w part="I">Regi-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">men</w>: But this muſt be left to the Judgment <lb/>of the Phyſician. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="3"><lb/>3. The utmoſt Caution ought to be uſed in <lb/>the Choice of
        proper Matter to communicate <lb/>the Infection. It ſhould be taken from a <lb/>young
        Subject, otherwiſe perfectly ſound and <lb/>healthful, who has the Small Pox in the
        <lb/>moſt favourable Manner. When the Puſtules <lb/>are perfectly, maturated, and juſt upon
        the <lb/>Turn, or ſoon after, two or three of them <lb/>ſhould be ripp'd with a Glover's
        Needle, or <lb/>ſmall Lancet, and a couple of ſmall Pledgets <lb/>of Lint, or Cotton, are to
        be well moiſtned <lb/>with the Matter, and immediately put into <lb/>a little Vial, or Box,
        and carry'd in the warm <lb/>Hand, or Boſom of the Operator, to the <lb/>Houſe of the Perſon
        to be inoculated. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="4"><lb/>4. The Inciſions are uſually made with a <lb/>ſmall Lancet in the
        brawny Part of both <lb/>Arms, or in one Arm and the oppoſite Leg, <lb/>cutting juſt into,
        or at moſt thro' the Cutis, <lb/>or true Skin, for the Length of a Quarter of <lb/>an Inch,
        half an Inch, or at moſt an Inch. <lb/>This being done, one of the Pledgets moiſtned
        <lb/>with the infectious Matter, is to be laid upon <lb/>each Inciſion, and to be kept on by
        Means of <pb xml:id="page_19" n="14"/><lb/>a Bit of ſticking Plaiſter laid over it, for
        <lb/>about four and twenty Hours; after which, <lb/>all may be taken off, and the Inciſions
        dreſt <lb/>with common <hi rend="italic">Diachylon,</hi> or with only warm <lb/>Cabbage or
        Colewort Leaves, once a Day <lb/>at firſt; and afterwards, when the Diſcharge <lb/>is
        conſiderable, twice a Day 'till they heal; <lb/>or only with a Linnen Roller, to defend
        <lb/>them from the Air. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="5"><lb/>5. The Perſon inoculated, ſometimes <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ceives</w> the Small Pox without any previous <lb/>Sickneſs, as often happens in
        the moſt <w part="I">favou-</w><lb/><w part="F">rable</w> Sort in the natural Way. But the
          <w part="I">great-</w><lb/><w part="F">er</w> Part begin to be a little feveriſh, and have
        <lb/>more or leſs of the uſual Symptoms preceding <lb/>the natural Small Pox, moſt commonly
        upon <lb/>the eighth Day from Inoculation, tho' pretty <lb/>often upon the ſeventh, and very
        rarely a <lb/>Day or two ſooner or later. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="6"><lb/>6. The Patients are ſometimes taken with <lb/>fluſhing Heats,
        which diſappear again in a <w part="I">lit-</w><lb/><w part="F">tle</w> Time, about the 4th
        or 5th Day; but the <lb/>Eruption of the Puſtules happens generally <lb/>within a Day, or
        ſometimes two or three, <lb/>after the ſickening, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> moſt commonly
        on <lb/>the ninth Day, leſs frequently on the 10th, <lb/>and ſtill leſs on the 8th or 11th;
        in a few <lb/>Caſes it has appear'd on the 7th or 12th, in <lb/>one Caſe on the 18th, in one
        on the 24th, in <lb/>one on the 6th, and in another on the 3d. <lb/>The laſt Patient but one
        had the confluent <lb/>Sort, and dy'd: The laſt was very full of the <lb/>diſtinct Kind, and
        recover'd. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="7"><lb/>7. The Inciſions begin to grow ſore and <lb/>painful about the 4th
        or 5th Day, and about <pb xml:id="page_20" n="15"/><lb/>the 6th, 7th, or 8th, they begin to
        digeſt, <lb/>and run with a thick purulent Matter, which <lb/>gradually encreaſes 'till
        about the Turn of <lb/>the Diſtemper, during which Time the <lb/>Wounds grow wide and deep;
        afterwards the <lb/>Running gradually abates, and they uſually <lb/>heal up in about a
        Month, ſometimes in <lb/>three Weeks, though in ſome they continue <lb/>running five or ſix
        Weeks, or ſomething <w part="I">lon-</w><lb/><w part="F">ger</w>. The greater the Diſcharge
        is by the <w part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F">ciſions</w>, the more favourable the Diſtemper
        <lb/>is found in other Reſpects. When the <w part="I">Ino-</w><lb/><w part="F">culation</w>
        does not take Effect, the Inciſions <lb/>heal up in a few Days, like a common Cut.
        <lb/>Where Children happen to have Iſſues before <lb/>Inoculation, they begin in a few Days
        to <lb/>run in a much greater Quantity than uſual, <lb/>and continue ſo doing, in the ſame
        Manner <lb/>as the Inciſions, during the State of the <w part="I">Di-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſtemper</w>, after which, they return to their <lb/>ordinary Courſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>In this Table, by having an imperfect <lb/>Small Pox, is meant, the
        having ſome <w part="I">ſligh-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> Eruption, of but a few Days
        continuance, <lb/>but this attended with an Inflammation and <lb/>Running of the Inciſions
        for the uſual Time, <lb/>and generally preceded by ſome of the <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">mon</w> Symptoms of the Small Pox; this <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ing</w> eſteem'd, by the Accounts from <hi rend="italic">Turkey,</hi>
        <lb/>and our own Experience at Home, as far as it <lb/>goes, to be an effectual Security
        againſt <w part="I">ha-</w><lb/><w part="F">ving</w> the Small Pox afterwards in the natural
        <lb/>Way. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Under the Article of <hi rend="italic">No Effect,</hi> are <w part="I"
          >com-</w><lb/><w part="F">prehended</w>, not only all thoſe Perſons upon <pb
          xml:id="page_21" n="16"/><lb/>whom the Operation produced no Effect of <lb/>any Kind, but
        alſo thoſe upon whom the <w part="I">E-</w><lb/><w part="F">ruption</w> was ſo ſlight, and
        the Running of <lb/>the Inciſions ſo little in Quantity, or of ſo <lb/>ſhort a Duration, as
        to render it juſtly <w part="I">doubt-</w><lb/><w part="F">ful</w> whether it would amount
        to a Security, <lb/>or no. Two of theſe were known to have <lb/>had the Small Pox before,
        and were <w part="I">inocula-</w><lb/><w part="F">ted</w> only for Experiment Sake, and
        ſeveral of <lb/>the reſt underwent the Operation upon a Doubt <lb/>whether they had had the
        Small Pox before <lb/>or no, the Diſtemper which they had <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">dergone</w> in the natural Way, having been ſo <lb/>ſlight and ſo favourable, as
        to make their <w part="I">Pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">rents</w>, themſelves, or their
        Phyſicians, to <lb/>ſuſpect that it was not the true Small Pox. <lb/>But there were ſome,
        upon whom <w part="I">Inocula-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> did not produce the Diſtemper,
        tho' there <lb/>was no Suſpicion of their having had it <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >fore</w>. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Under the Head of dying after <w part="I">Inocula-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tion</w> is compriz'd every Perſon, as far as I <lb/>have been been able to learn, that
        has either <lb/>by the Friends, or Adverſaries, to this <w part="I">Pra-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ctice</w>, been ſuſpected to have dy'd of <w part="I">Inocula-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tion</w>. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_22" n="17"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><table>
          <row>
            <cell role="label" rows="1" cols="1">Ages.</cell>
            <cell role="label" rows="1" cols="1">Perſons <w part="I">inocu-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >lated</w>.</cell>
            <cell role="label" rows="1" cols="1">Had the Small Pox by <w part="I">Inocu-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">lation</w>.</cell>
            <cell role="label" rows="1" cols="1">Had an <w part="I">imper-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >fect</w> Small Pox by <w part="I">Inocu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lation</w>.</cell>
            <cell role="label" rows="1" cols="1">No Effect.</cell>
            <cell role="label" rows="1" cols="1">Suſpect-<lb/>ed to have died of <w part="I"
                >Inocu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lation</w>.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell cols="2" rows="1">Und. <lb/>1 Year</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">11</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">11</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">00</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">00</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">00</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell cols="2" rows="1">1 Year to 2</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">15</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">14</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">00</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">01</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">02</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">2</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">3</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">31</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">31</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">00</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">00</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">01</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">3</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">4</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">41</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">38</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">00</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">03</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">01</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">4</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">5</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">33</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">31</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">00</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">02</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">01</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">5</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">10</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">140</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">137</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">01</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">02</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">02</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">10</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">15</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">82</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">76</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">00</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">06</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">00</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">15</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">20</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">56</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">50</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">01</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">05</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">02</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">20</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">52</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">62</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">50</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">03</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">09</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">00</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell cols="2" rows="1">Age <lb/>unknown.</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">03</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">02</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">00</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">01</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">00</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell cols="2" rows="1">Total</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">474</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">440</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">05</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">29</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">09</cell>
          </row>
        </table></p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>From this Table it appears, </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="1"><lb/>1. That of 474 Perſons inoculated, 440<lb/> have receiv'd the
        Small Pox from that <w part="I">Opera-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>; to which if it be
        thought proper to <lb/>add the five, who had an imperfect Small Pox <lb/>by Inoculation, the
        whole Number will be <lb/>445. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="2"><lb/>2. That the Operation has of ner fail'd of <lb/>taking Effect upon
        thoſe of more advanc'd <lb/>Ages, than upon young Children, as was <lb/>naturally to be
        expected from the Reaſons <lb/>mention'd above; it being more likely that <lb/>Perſons of
        ſuch Ages have had the Small Pox <lb/>before, than Children. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="3"><lb/>3. That however more favourable the <w part="I">na-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">tural</w> Small Pox generally is to Children than <lb/>grown Perſons, yet
        Inoculation has been <w part="I">at-</w><pb xml:id="page_23" n="18"/><lb/>with better
        Succeſs in the latter than <lb/>in the former; and in particular, that out <lb/>of 50 or 53
        Perſons of 20 Years of Age and <lb/>upwards, that have had the Small Pox by
        <lb/>Inoculation, not one has miſcarry'd. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="4"><lb/>4. That 9 is the Number of Perſons, who <lb/>have been ſuſpected
        to have died of <w part="I">Inocula-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>; ſo that, if this
        Operation was really <lb/>the Cauſe of all their Deaths, the Hazard of <lb/>dying of the
        inoculated Small Pox muſt be <lb/>that of 9 in 440, or 445, that is, of one in <lb/>49, or
        50. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>But the curious Reader will doubtleſs <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">pect</w>, that I ſhould give him ſome farther <w part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >formation</w>, in Order to enable him to judge, <lb/>whether, or no, all theſe Perſons
        really died <lb/>of Inoculation. This I ſhall endeavour to <lb/>do with all the Fidelity,
        that a Caſe of ſo <lb/>much Importance requires, and with ſuch <w part="I">Im-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">partiality</w>, as to give no juſt Cauſe of Offence <lb/>to either of the
        contending Parties. With <lb/>this View I ſhall here ſet down the Name of <lb/>every Perſon,
        that has been ſuſpected by the <lb/>one Side to have died of Inoculation; and <lb/>on the
        other Hand, I ſhall communicate the <lb/>Accounts of thoſe Caſes, as they have been
        <lb/>tranſmitted to me by the Gentlemen <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">cern'd</w> in
        inoculating thoſe Perſons, <w part="I">ſubjoin-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> every one's Name
        to his own Account. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="1"><lb/>1. The firſt is the Caſe of the Honourable <lb/>Mr. <hi
          rend="italic">William Spencer,</hi> aged about three Years, <lb/>who was inoculated in
        Town, <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 2d, 1722, <lb/>and died on the 21ſt of the ſame Month.
        <lb/>The Eruption appear'd on the 9th Day; he <lb/>had a fair and full Eruption of Puſtules
        of <pb xml:id="page_24" n="19"/><lb/>different Sorts, obſerving the common Periods <lb/>and
        Symptoms of Inoculation; and after <lb/>the greateſt Part of the Puſtules were dry'd
        <lb/>off, he was ſeiz'd, on a ſudden, on the 21ſt <lb/>Day, of a convulſive Fit, of which he
        died. <lb/>The Occaſion of his Death may be farther <lb/>enquir'd into, from the printed
        Account. Mr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Maitland. Vid. Maitland</hi>'s Anſwer to Dr. <hi
          rend="italic">Wagg-<lb/>ſtaffe.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="2"><lb/>2. Miſs <hi rend="italic">Rigby,</hi> aged a Year and ſix Months,
        <lb/>was inoculated in <hi rend="italic">London, April</hi> 29, 1722. She <lb/>had a fair
        Eruption of Puſtules, appearing on <lb/>the eighth Day, and a much more <w part="I"
          >favoura-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w> Diſeaſe than her Siſter, who recover'd: <lb/>But one
        of her Arms ſwell'd and <w part="I">impoſthuma-</w><lb/><w part="F">ted</w>, (as is uſual
        ſometimes in the natural Small <lb/>Pox) and whether it was by that, or breeding <lb/>her
        Teeth (for ſhe cut ſome Teeth about that <lb/>Time) is uncertain; however ſhe continu'd
        <lb/>ſickly, feveriſh and hectick, and died about <lb/>8 Weeks after the Inoculation. <hi
          rend="italic">N. B.</hi> Mr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Maitland</hi> declin'd the inoculating
        her with <lb/>her Siſter; but the Father having had a <w part="I">fa-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >vourable</w> Account of this Practice from the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Turkey</hi>
        Merchants, would have it done; and <lb/>there was another unlucky Circumſtance in <lb/>this
        Affair; Mr. <hi rend="italic">Maitland</hi> was ſeiz'd with a <lb/>violent Fever for the
        Space of three Weeks, <lb/>from the Day ſhe was inoculated, which, he <lb/>thinks, might in
        ſome Meaſure have <w part="I">occa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſion'd</w> the Soreneſs of her Arm,
        no ſuch <lb/>Thing having happen'd where he has been <lb/>able to attend. Mr. <hi
          rend="italic">Maitland.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="3"><lb/>3. Lord <hi rend="italic">Bathurſt</hi>'s Servant, aged 19, was
        <lb/>inoculated in <hi rend="italic">London, April</hi> 30, 1722. He <pb xml:id="page_25"
          n="20"/><lb/>was lately come from the Country into my <lb/>Lord's Houſe, where five of his
        Lordſhip's <lb/>Children were then ſick of the Small Pox: <lb/>He was ill for ſome few Days
        before he was <lb/>inoculated, and his Complaints were ſuch, <lb/>that 'twas apprehended
        'twould be the Small <lb/>Pox. Therefore he was remov'd to a Nurſe's <lb/>in <hi
          rend="italic">Swallow-Street, Piccadilly,</hi> who provides for <lb/>Perſons in that Way.
        By Mr. <hi rend="italic">Mead</hi>'s <w part="I">Di-</w><lb/><w part="F">rections</w> he was
        blooded, and vomited, and <lb/>took ſeveral cordial Powders; whereby being <lb/>reſtor'd to
        Health it was thought proper to <lb/>inoculate him. The Small Pox appear'd on <lb/>him the
        9th Day after Inoculation, of the <lb/>favourable diſtinct Kind, whereby his <w part="I"
          >Com-</w><lb/><w part="F">plaints</w> were allay'd; but returning the next <lb/>Day with
        bilious Vomitings frequent Stools, <lb/>and a <hi rend="italic">Delirium,</hi> a great many
        of the fluxed <lb/>Kind then appear'd. Theſe continu'd more <lb/>or leſs upon him,
        notwithſtanding all the <lb/>Medicines which Dr. <hi rend="italic">Arbutbnot,</hi> and <w
          part="I">after-</w><lb/><w part="F">wards</w> Dr. <hi rend="italic">Mead</hi> in
        Conjunction with him did <lb/>preſcribe. He died on the 7th Day from the <lb/>Eruption. His
        Lungs were found inflam'd <lb/>and mortify'd. Serjeant <hi rend="italic">Amyand.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="4"><lb/>4. Miſs <hi rend="italic">Rolt,</hi> aged between 9 and 10 Years,
        <lb/>was inoculated in <hi rend="italic">London,</hi> together with a <lb/>Child of between
        2 and 3 Years of Age, <lb/>both with the ſame Matter, <hi rend="italic">Sept.</hi> 25, 1723.
        <lb/>Then both began to ſicken on the eighth <lb/>Day from Inoculation, and on the 10th the
        <lb/>Small Pox appear'd on both of the diſtinct <lb/>Kind. The Boy recover'd. Miſs <hi
          rend="italic">Rolt,</hi> the Day <lb/>before the Eruption, complain'd of great <lb/>Pains
        in her Shoulders, Elbows and Knees, <pb xml:id="page_26" n="21"/><lb/>and the Fever
        continuing, the Small Pox <w part="I">flux-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> upon her the 3d Day
        from the Eruption. <lb/>Sir <hi rend="italic">Hans Sloane</hi> and Dr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Arbuthnot</hi> attended her. <lb/>She went thro' the Diſtemper with Eaſe; the <lb/>Small
        Pox began to turn on her the 7th <lb/>Day; but 'twas not dry'd all over 'till the <lb/>14th.
        The Fever, that aroſe then, <w part="I">occa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſion'd</w> her being
        blooded, and ſoon after <lb/>ſeveral Tumours appear'd in the <w part="I"
          >Neighbour-</w><lb/><w part="F">hood</w> of ſeveral Joints, which were open'd. <lb/>The
        Fever ſtill continu'd, and more <w part="I">ſuppu-</w><lb/><w part="F">rated</w> Tumours
        were daily appearing, which <lb/>were diſcharg'd as ſoon as poſſible. <w part="I"
          >Some-</w><lb/><w part="F">times</w> ſhe was troubled with a <hi rend="italic"
          >Diarrhœa,</hi>
        <lb/>whereby, as well as by the Suppuration of <lb/>20 or 30 Boils that were open'd, ſhe was
        <lb/>ſpent, ſo that ſhe dy'd the 27th of <hi rend="italic">November</hi>
        <lb/>following, that is 9 Weeks after the <w part="I">Inocu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lation</w>.
        Her Inciſions continu'd running to <lb/>the laſt. By all Accounts, ſhe had a bad <lb/>Habit
        of Body; ſhe ſtruggled with the <w part="I">Jaun-</w><lb/><w part="F">dice</w> the Year
        before, during ſix Months; it <lb/>ſhew'd its Head again in the Spring, but was <lb/>ſoon
        conquer'd; and as I have been inform'd <lb/>of late, ſhe recover'd of the Meaſles but 10
        <lb/>Weeks before ſhe was inoculated. Had I been <lb/>inform'd of this before, as well as of
        her <w part="I">ir-</w><lb/><w part="F">regular</w> Life, no Ways ſuited to one of her
        <lb/>Years, I would hardly have adventur'd the <lb/>Inoculation on her; tho' all that Time,
        ſhe <lb/>ſeem'd to me in a perfect State of Health, and <lb/>perfectly recover'd of the
        Meaſles, which ſhe <lb/>had had in the moſt favourable Manner: <lb/>Serjeant <hi
          rend="italic">Amyand.</hi>
      </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_27" n="22"/>
      <p rend="indent" n="5"><lb/>5. Miſs <hi rend="italic">Brooksbank,</hi> aged 15 Months, was
        <lb/>inoculated at <hi rend="italic">Ealand</hi> near <hi rend="italic">Halifax,</hi> in <hi
          rend="italic">June</hi>
        <lb/>1723. She dy'd ſuddenly on the 11th Day <lb/>from the Eruption. <hi rend="italic"
          >Vid.</hi> Dr. <hi rend="italic">Nettleton</hi>'s, and <lb/>the Parent's Account at the
        End of this Paper. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="6"><lb/>6. Miſs <hi rend="italic">Betty a Court</hi> 4 Years of Age, <w
          part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">oculated</w> at <hi rend="italic">Ivy-Church</hi> near
          <hi rend="italic">Salisbury, Sept.</hi> 20, <lb/>1723. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>She may very well be ſaid to be born an <lb/>infirm Child, for it is
        notoriouſly known, <lb/>that her Mother was ſo ill almoſt all the <lb/>Time of going with
        her, that her Midwife <lb/>often deſpair'd of her Life, as believing ſhe <lb/>would not go
        out her Time. The Child, two <lb/>or three Months after ſhe was born, was <lb/>ſeiz'd with
        an <hi rend="italic">Ophthalmia</hi> in both Eyes, <lb/>and after that ſhe had a Humour to a
        great <lb/>Degree, which broke out under her Chin, <lb/>her Throat being very raw from Ear
        to Ear, <lb/>which by purging, cutting an Iſſue, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> went
        <lb/>off. But ſtill at Spring and Fall ſhe was <lb/>ſubject to theſe Humours, but to a leſs
          <w part="I">De-</w><lb/><w part="F">gree</w> than at firſt. Her Iſſue by the <w part="I"
          >Negli-</w><lb/><w part="F">gence</w> of the Nurſe, was dry'd up ſome <w part="I"
          >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſiderable</w> Time before the Child was <w part="I"
          >inocu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lated</w>, as Mr. <hi rend="italic">a Court</hi> himſelf told
        me; and <lb/>that the Child had ſomething of theſe <w part="I">Hu-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >mours</w> broke out upon her, not above 3 Weeks <lb/>before the Operation was perform'd,
        I was <lb/>aſſur'd by the Servants in the Houſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>She was inoculated with her four <w part="I">Bro-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >thers</w> and a Servant Maid, all with the ſame <lb/>Matter, from a Boy about 8 or 9
        Years old, <lb/>that had a kind Sort. I heard nothing of <lb/>any of their Complaints 'till
        the eighth Day, <pb xml:id="page_28" n="23"/><lb/>and then one had a Pain in his Head, <w
          part="I">ano-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> in his Back, one was taken with a <w part="I"
          >Shi-</w><lb/><w part="F">vering</w>, another with a Vomiting, and in <lb/>ſhort every one
        of them had ſomething or <lb/>other of the Symptoms of the Small Pox, <lb/>except the Maid
        Servant. Miſs's Complaint <lb/>was chiefly in her Head and Back; the next <lb/>Day, after
        the Symptoms came on, ſhe was <lb/>fluſh'd in her Face rather like an <hi rend="italic"
          >Eryſipelas</hi>
        <lb/>than the Small Pox, and in 24 Hours after <lb/>that the Puſtules appear'd very thick in
        her <lb/>Face, her right Arm and right Thigh, and <lb/>ſeem'd to come on pretty well. They
        were as <lb/>full on her Breaſt, the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi> and Inſide <lb/>of the
        Thighs; yet they continu'd always <lb/>flat and languiſhing, without coming to <w part="I"
          >Ma-</w><lb/><w part="F">turity</w>, notwithſtanding all the Doctor could <lb/>do to raiſe
        them. The Fever encreas'd on <lb/>her every Day, and ſhe grew more and more <lb/>reſtleſs,
        tho' her Inciſions diſcharg'd after a <lb/>wonderful Manner. For all round each Arm,
        <lb/>from her Shoulders to her Elbows, they ran <lb/>like large Bliſters, being as thick of
        Puſtules <lb/>as they could ſtand under the Dreſſings, <lb/>which gave us ſome faint Hopes
        ſhe might <lb/>get over it, 'till a Day or two before ſhe <lb/>died. The Puſtules on her
        Face, her right <lb/>Arm and Thigh, turn'd the 7th and 8th Day; <lb/>but then the ſecond
        Fever came on, and it <lb/>getting Ground every Day, ſhe continu'd in <lb/>a languid State,
        and grew weaker and <lb/>weaker, 'till ſhe expir'd, which was the 22d <lb/>Day from the
        Inciſions. Mr. <hi rend="italic">Goldwyer.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>A Daughter of Mr. <hi rend="italic">a Court</hi>'s, 4 Years of <lb/>Age,
        was inoculated under a very ill Habit <pb xml:id="page_29" n="24"/><lb/>of Body, and ſubject
        to inflammatory <w part="I">cuta-</w><lb/><w part="F">neous</w> Eruptions from its Birth.
        Perſecuted <lb/>always by a hectick Heat, the Child was <lb/>thin and weak, too weak,
        indeed, to withſtand <lb/>the Malignity of the confluent Kind ſhe <w part="I">la-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">bour'd</w> under. But the four Sons inoculated <lb/>at the ſame Time, with Matter
        taken from <lb/>the ſame Perſon, had Diſeaſes of the diſtinct <lb/>Kind, and are recover'd,
        though not the <lb/>moſt proper Perſons for this Operation. Dr. <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Hele,</hi> Phyſician in <hi rend="italic">Salisbury.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="6"><lb/>6. <hi rend="italic">Francis Bacon,</hi> Eſq; 17 Years of Age,
        <lb/>was inoculated at <hi rend="italic">Earlbam</hi> near <hi rend="italic">Norwich,</hi>
        <lb/>with his Siſter, <hi rend="italic">Sept.</hi> 11th, 1723. The <w part="I"
          >In-</w><lb/><w part="F">ciſions</w> did not inflame, but healed in about <lb/>10 Days,
        like a common Cut: No Fever, <lb/>nor any Sort of Eruption follow'd; he was <lb/>kept in
        breathing Sweats in Bed the 9th and <lb/>10th Day; a Day or two after he was purged,
        <lb/>and ſo a 2d, and a 3d Time. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>On the 1ſt of <hi rend="italic">October,</hi> a ſecond Attempt <lb/>was
        made with Matter taken from his Siſter; <lb/>the Succeſs was the ſame; he was purged
        <lb/>again as before, and releas'd from his <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >finement</w>. During this whole Proceeding, he <lb/>ſlept very well, had a very good
        Appetite, <lb/>and made not the leaſt Complaint, 'till <w part="I">up-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >on</w> taking the Air in a very ſharp Day, <w part="I">to-</w><lb/><w part="F">wards</w>
        the latter End of <hi rend="italic">October,</hi> he grew <lb/>feveriſh that Night, with
        Pains in his Head <lb/>and Limbs; his Pulſe was ſtrong, his Urine <lb/>high colour'd, with a
        good Sediment; he was <lb/>not very hot, nor thirſty, but inclinable to <lb/>ſweat; the
        greateſt Uneaſineſs he felt, was <lb/>from a decay'd Tooth, which he was forc'd <pb
          xml:id="page_30" n="25"/><lb/>to have drawn. This Diſorder went off in 3 <lb/>Days by
        natural Sweats: All that was given <lb/>him, was 3 or 4 Papers of <hi rend="italic">Pulv. e
          Chel. Cancr. <lb/>comp.</hi> with <hi rend="italic">Caſtor, &amp;c.</hi> he being
        ſometimes a <w part="I">lit-</w><lb/><w part="F">tle</w> low ſpirited. A Faintneſs remain'd
          <w part="I">up-</w><lb/><w part="F">on</w> him, four or five Days after the Fever
        <lb/>went off, with want of Appetite: But upon <lb/>taking a little Rhubarb once or twice,
        he <lb/>ſoon recover'd his Stomach, and ſeem'd <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >fectly</w> well, when he return'd to <hi rend="italic">Cambridge,</hi>
        <lb/>about the Middle of <hi rend="italic">November.</hi> The only <lb/>Difference I
        obſerv'd in him, was, that he <lb/>was paler than uſual, which I imputed to <lb/>a long
        tedious Confinement and a ſpare Diet, <lb/>together with ſome little Anxiety from the
        <lb/>Diſappointment he had met with. What <lb/>happen'd at <hi rend="italic">Cambridge,</hi>
        I ſhall ſay nothing to, <lb/>leaving that Part to the Phyſician that <w part="I"
          >at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tended</w> him; I ſhall only obſerve, that this <lb/>young
        Gentleman has been very ſubject to <lb/>Fevers, attended with nervous Symptoms; <lb/>and
        that a Perſon nearly related to him, <lb/>who ſaw him in both Caſes, told me, that <lb/>this
        laſt Illneſs differ'd in nothing, except in <lb/>the Violence of the Symptoms, from a <w
          part="I">Fe-</w><lb/><w part="F">ver</w> he was ſeiz'd with about three Years ago.
        <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Offley.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>This young Gentleman was taken ill of <lb/>a nervous Fever, ſuch as he
        had been ill <lb/>of ſeveral Times before, about <hi rend="italic">Chriſtmas</hi> laſt,
        <lb/>and dy'd on the 5th of <hi rend="italic">Jannary.</hi> No Spot, nor <lb/>Eruption of
        any Kind appear'd upon him; <lb/>but a little before his Death, a great <w part="I"
          >Quan-</w><lb/><w part="F">tity</w> of Blood and Matter guſh'd out at his <pb
          xml:id="page_31" n="26"/>Noſtrils. Mrs <hi rend="italic">Bacon,</hi> Mr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Profeſſor Green,</hi><lb/>
        Dr. <hi rend="italic">Aſhenhurſt.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="8"><lb/>8. <hi rend="italic">Mary Waller,</hi> five Years and a half old,
        <lb/>was inoculated near <hi rend="italic">Goſport, Oct.</hi> 18, 1723; <lb/>together with
        two other Children, all with <lb/>the ſame Matter. The other two ſicken'd on <lb/>the 7th
        Day, the Small Pox appear'd on the <lb/>9th, and they did very well: But this Child
        <lb/>ſicken'd at the Completion of the 4th Day, <lb/>and the Eruption appear'd on the ſixth.
        She <lb/>had the confluent Kind all over her, with <lb/>many Purples, and died on the 18th
        Day <lb/>after ſhe was inoculated. From the <note place="bottom" n="*">* Vid. <hi
            rend="italic">pag.</hi> 14. </note>
        <w part="I">Ear-</w><lb/><w part="F">liness</w> of her Sickening, and the Eruption, it
        <lb/>is not improbable, that ſhe had taken the <lb/>Infection the ordinary Way before. This
        <lb/>Opinion is farther ſtrengthen'd by the <w part="I">fol-</w><lb/><w part="F">lowing</w>
        Circumſtance. A Maid was <w part="I">violent-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> ſeiz'd with the
        Small Pox in the common <lb/>Way, a little before the Operation, and <w part="I"
          >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tinu'd</w> there two Days in a narrow Room, her <lb/>Breath
        ſmelling ſtrong of the Infection, and <lb/>the Child was ſometimes with her. To what <lb/>is
        ſaid, may be added, that the Child was <lb/>leprous. Mr. <hi rend="italic">Waller.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="9"><lb/>9. Miſs <hi rend="italic">Brailsford,</hi> aged 2 Years, died the
        <lb/>26th Day after Inoculation, of a Worm <w part="I">Fe-</w><lb/><w part="F">ver</w>. The
        Small Pox were all ſhal'd and <lb/>gone off. Dr. <hi rend="italic">Dover.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>From the Facts here laid down, I am <w part="I">ſen-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſible</w> the Inoculators will raiſe ſeveral <w part="I">Ob-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >jections</w> againſt the Eſtimate of the Hazard <lb/>of Inoculation, which I have given
        above, <lb/>and to do them Juſtice, I am obliged to lay <pb xml:id="page_32" n="27"
        /><lb/>what are, or may be their Arguments, <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w> the
        World. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="1"><lb/>1. They will maintain that the 4th, 6th, <lb/>and 8th Caſes ought
        to be left out of the <lb/>Computation, becauſe the Patients were <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">healthy</w> Subjects, and therefore no Argument <lb/>can be drawn from their
        dying, to increaſe <lb/>the Hazard of thoſe who ſhall be <w part="I">inocula-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ted</w> in perfect Health, purſuant to the <w part="I">Cau-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tion</w> above given; and conſequently, that the <lb/>Hazard to heathful Perſons, can at
        moſt be <lb/>reckon'd to be no more than that of ſix in <lb/>440, or 445, that is of one in
        73, or 74. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="2"><lb/>2. They may object, that the ſeventh Caſe <lb/>is intirely out of
        the Queſtion, the Perſon <w part="I">hav-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> been well ſo long
        after the Operation, <lb/>and in his laſt Illneſs, which happen'd near <lb/>three Months
        after the ſecond Inoculation, <lb/>having had no Manner of Appearance of the <lb/>Small Pox,
        nor any other Symptons, (as <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pears</w> by the
        Acknowledgement of his <w part="I">near-</w><lb/><w part="F">eſt</w> Relations and others,)
        but what he had <lb/>had more than once in former Fevers; <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">cept</w> only the Eruption of Blood and Matter <lb/>from his Noſtrils, a little
        before his Death; <lb/>which often happening in other Caſes, ſeems <lb/>not to be juſtly
        chargeable upon Inoculation, <lb/>eſpecially at ſo great a Diſtance of Time <lb/>from that
        Operation. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="3"><lb/>3. They may juſtly plead, that in a <w part="I">Com-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">pariſon</w> between the Hazard of the natural <lb/>and inoculated Small Pox,
        either only ſuch, <lb/>as die in the Courſe of the Diſtemper, ought <lb/>to be ſet down on
        both Sides; or that, if <lb/>in the Caſe of Inoculation, I will charge the <pb
          xml:id="page_33" n="28"/><lb/>Conſequences of the Operation, in <w part="I"
          >occaſion-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> other Diſeaſes, of which, the Patients <lb/>happen
        to die after the Small Pox are <w part="I">en-</w><lb/><w part="F">tirely</w> gone off, that
        I ought to do the ſame <lb/>in the Caſe of the natural Small Pox, it <lb/>being notorious,
        that this Diſtemper <w part="I">frequent-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> occaſions other
        Diſeaſes, of which the <lb/>Patients die a conſiderable Time after: And <lb/>if I cannot do
        this in the natural Way, <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">cauſe</w> the Death of the
        Patient is, in this <lb/>Caſe, ſet down in the weekly Bills, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        to <lb/>the other apparent Diſeaſe, then I ought to <lb/>omit all ſuch Caſes in the Way of
          <w part="I">Inocula-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, and conſequently the 2d, as likewiſe,
        <lb/>the 4th and 7th for this Reaſon, beſides the <lb/>others before given, ought to be left
        out of <lb/>the Eſtimate. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="4"><lb/>4. They may likewiſe object to the 1ſt, <lb/>3d, and 5th
        Inſtances, from the <w part="I">Circumſtan-</w><lb/><w part="F">ces</w> mention'd in the
        Account of thoſe Caſes, <lb/>and conſequently will not allow of more than <lb/>one Caſe,
        where the Patient can be juſtly <lb/>ſaid to have died of Inoculation: And <w part="I"
          >per-</w><lb/><w part="F">haps</w> even that will be diſputed. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>How far theſe ſeveral Objections are of <lb/>Weight, is ſubmited to the
        Determination of <lb/>thoſe, who muſt and will judge for <w part="I">them-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſelves</w>, that is, to every intelligent Reader, <lb/>who being thus appriz'd of
        the Facts, may <lb/>eaſily, by ſtriking off ſuch of the Inſtances <lb/>given above, as he
        thinks reaſonable, form <lb/>to himſelf a Judgment of the Hazard of Life <lb/>in this
        Operation: And to ſuch therefore I <lb/>leave it But to ſave him ſome little <w part="I"
          >Trou-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w>, I ſhall only obſerve, that if upon the <pb
          xml:id="page_34" n="29"/><lb/>Reaſons here mention'd, he ſees Cauſe to <w part="I"
          >ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">cept</w> one Perſon out of the Number of thoſe <lb/>that are
        ſuſpected to have died of <w part="I">Inocula-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, the Hazard muſt
        then be eſtimated to <lb/>be that of one in 55, or 56. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><table>
          <row>
            <cell role="label" rows="1" cols="1">If he except—</cell>
            <cell role="label" rows="1" cols="1">The Hazard will be</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Two—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">One in 63, or 64</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Three—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">One in 73, or 74</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Four—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">One in 88, or 89</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Five—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">One in 110, or 111</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Six—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">One in 147, or 148</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Seven—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">One in 220, or 222</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">Eight—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">One in 440, or 445.</cell>
          </row>
        </table></p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It may perhaps be expected from me by <lb/>ſome Perſons, that in giving
        Account of the <lb/>Miſcarriages of Inoculation, I ſhould not <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">fine</w> my ſelf barely to Loſs of Life; but that <lb/>I ſhould likewiſe relate
        all the leſſer <w part="I">Acci-</w><lb/><w part="F">dents</w>, as the breaking out of
        Boils, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> that <lb/>have follow'd upon that Practice, where the
        <lb/>Patient has eſcap'd with his Life. But to <lb/>ſuch I muſt reply, that in a Deſign to
        make <lb/>a Compariſon between the Hazard of the <w part="I">Di-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſtemper</w> in the natural Way, and when given <lb/>by Inoculation, it would be improper
        and <lb/>uſeleſs to inſert ſuch an Account, if it could <lb/>be obtain'd, on the one Side,
        unleſs it were <lb/>done likewiſe on the other. And every <w part="I">Phyſi-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">cian</w> knows, that ſuch like Accidents <w part="I">frequent-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ly</w> happen upon having the natural Small Pox, <lb/>which it would be next to
        impoſſible to <lb/>make a perfect Collection of, and as <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >practicable</w> to ſet that Collection in ſuch a <pb xml:id="page_35" n="30"/><lb/>Light,
        as would be requiſite, in Order to make <lb/>a Compariſon between it and the Accidents
        <lb/>owing to Inoculation. For this Reaſon, I <lb/>limit my Compariſon to the Hazard of Life
        <lb/>itſelf, and ſee no Reaſon to doubt, but that <lb/>ſuch Way of having the Diſeaſe as
        leſs <w part="I">en-</w><lb/><w part="F">dangers</w> Life, muſt be likewiſe more <w part="I"
          >favour-</w><lb/><w part="F">able</w> in all other Particulars. This is affirm'd <lb/>by
        the Practiſers of Inoculation, and their <lb/>Adverſaries, I think, do not offer to deny it. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Before I conclude, it may not be <w part="I">impro-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >per</w>, to take ſome little Notice of an Article <lb/>lately inſerted in one of our
        publick Papers. <lb/>that in the Year 1722, there died of the Small <lb/>Pox, within the
        Bills of Mortality, 2167 <w part="I">Per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſons</w>, and that in the Year
        1723, <hi rend="italic">the Year <lb/>of Inoculation,</hi> there died 3271, exceeding
        <lb/>the former Number by 1104. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>With what View this was publiſh'd, is beſt <lb/>known to the Authors of
        that, and ſome other <lb/>ſuch like Articles: But the Uſe that I have heard <lb/>made of it
        in Converſation, is, that <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">oculating</w> the Small Pox,
        contributed very <lb/>much to the ſpreading of the Diſtemper, and <lb/>conſequently to the
        great Increaſe of the <lb/>Mortality above-mention'd. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>To obviate, which, I muſt take Notice in <lb/>the firſt Place, that by
        the Accounts now <lb/>lying before me, it appears, that in the Year <lb/>1722, there were 63
        Perſons inoculated <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w part="F">in</w> the Bills of Mortality, and
        in the Year <lb/>1723, which this Writer calls <hi rend="italic">the Year of
          <lb/>Inoculation.</hi> the Number inoculated was 68, <lb/>juſt five more than the Year
        before. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_36" n="31"/>
      <p rend="indent" n="2"><lb/>2. That as there died of the natural Pox, <lb/>3271 Perſons in the
        Year 1723, the whole <lb/>Number ſick of the ſame Diſeaſe that Year, <lb/>muſt have been, by
        the Proportion laid down <lb/>before, of ſix and ſomething more to one, <lb/>about 20000
        Perſons, and conſequently the <lb/>ſpreading of the Diſtemper by Means of <w part="I"
          >Ino-</w><lb/><w part="F">culation</w>, could bear no greater a Proportion <lb/>to the
        natural Propagation of it, than that <lb/>of 68 to 20000, or of one to 300. For it will
        <lb/>not, I ſuppoſe, be pretended, that the Small <lb/>Pox given by Inoculation, is more
        infectious <lb/>than the natural Sort. I believe every <w part="I">Per-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſon</w>, who has been acquainted with both, <lb/>will think it leſs ſo, in Proportion, as
        it is <lb/>more favourable. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Laſtly, if I have not already taken up <lb/>more of the Reader's Time
        upon this Head, <lb/>than the Thing is worth, I would deſire <lb/>him to caſt his Eye upon
        the following <lb/>Account of the Mortality of the Small <lb/>Pox, for ſeveral Years before
        Inoculation <lb/>was introduc'd among us, in ſome of which, <lb/>he will find it greater,
        and in others, nearly <lb/>equalito the laſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Out of every thouſand Perſons that were <lb/>bury'd, there died of the
        Small Pox, </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><table>
          <row>
            <cell role="label" cols="2" rows="1">In the Year</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">1668—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">115</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">1674—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">118</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">1681—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">125</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">1683—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">102</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">1685—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">107</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">1710—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">127</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">1714—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">106</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">1719—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">114</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">1723—</cell>
            <cell rows="1" cols="1">112</cell>
          </row>
        </table></p>
      <pb xml:id="page_37" n="32"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Conſideration of the Bills of <w part="I">Mortali-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ty</w> puts into my Head another Remark, <lb/>which I muſt beg leave to make. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>For theſe ten Years laſt paſt, there have died <lb/>of the Small Pox,
        within the Bills of Mortality, <lb/>at a <hi rend="italic">Medium,</hi> 2287 Souls <hi
          rend="italic">per Annum.</hi> Let us <lb/>now conſider a little, what may be the <w
          part="I">Conſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">quence</w>, in Caſe Inoculation ſhould hereafter
        <lb/>become a general Practice. If we allow all <lb/>the Oppoſers of Inoculation contend
        for, we <lb/>ſhall find but one in 49 to die of Inoculation, <lb/>and in the natural Way, we
        have ſhown it to <lb/>be one in ſix: It follows, that if we <w part="I">ſubſti-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">tute</w> Inoculation for the natural Way, the <lb/>Number of the Dead would be
        reduc'd ſeven <lb/>Parts in eight, and conſequently 2000 <w part="I">Per-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſons</w>, that are yearly cut off, within the Bills <lb/>of Mortality alone, and
        thoſe generally in <lb/>the Beginning, or Prime of Life, might be <lb/>preſerv'd to their
        King and Country. Let <lb/>the warm Oppoſers of Inoculation, lay their <lb/>Hands upon their
        Hearts, and conſider, <w part="I">whe-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> the ſaving of ſo many
        Lives, be <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">trary</w> to any Precept of Law, or Goſpel.
        We <lb/>have been told indeed, and from the Pulpit <lb/>too, that this Practice came from
        the Devil: <lb/>But if it prove thus beneficial and ſalutary to <lb/>Mankind, I, for my
        part, ſhall make no <lb/>Scruple of aſcribing it to a greater and a <w part="I"
          >bet-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> Author; and undoubtedly, all ſober and <lb/>thinking
        Perſons will judge and believe, that <lb/>the making known to the World, a Method <lb/>of
        preſerving their Lives from one of the <lb/>moſt terrible Diſeaſes in Nature, can be <w
          part="I">ow-</w><pb xml:id="page_38" n="33"/><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> to no other, than
        the kind and tender <w part="I">Pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">vidence</w> of the great Creator
        and Preſerver <lb/>of Mankind. </p>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Part of a Letter from Dr.</hi> Nettleton
            <hi rend="italic">to <lb/>Dr.</hi> Jurin. </head>
        <dateline><hi rend="italic">Halifax, Oct.</hi> 28, 1723. </dateline>
      
      <lb/>
      <salute rend="italic">SIR, </salute>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> Was very much ſurpriz'd to find it <w part="I"
          >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerted</w> in ſeveral of the News Papers of <lb/>the laſt Poſt,
        as a current Report, that I had <lb/>been lately call'd to a Patient, who was <w part="I"
          >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">oculated</w> about a Year ago, and who is ſince <lb/>dead of the
        natural Small Pox; and I cou'd <lb/>not omit this firſt Opportunity to aſſure you, <lb/>that
        the ſaid Report is entirely falſe, none <lb/>who have been inoculated, having died of
        <lb/>the natural Small Pox afterwards, neither <lb/>have we any Reaſon to think worſe of the
        <lb/>Practice here, than when I writ to you laſt, <lb/>tho' we were far from expecting that
        any <lb/>Thing, in this World, ſhould be ſo compleat, <lb/>as to be free from all
        Inconveniencies and <lb/>Misfortunes. The Method has not been <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">tended</w> with any Diſaſter in theſe Parts, <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >cepting</w> only one, which, I ſuppoſe, gave Riſe <lb/>to theſe Reports in the publick
        Papers, and <lb/>of which, I ſhall give you a very particular <lb/>Relation; for I ſhou'd be
        highly blameable, <lb/>if I did either conceal, or miſrepreſent any <lb/>Circumſtance
        relating to a Matter of ſo great <lb/>Conſequence to Mankind. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_39" n="34"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>About four Months ago, Mr. <hi rend="italic">Brooksbank</hi>
        <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Ealand,</hi> deſir'd me to inoculate the Small <lb/>Pox upon a
        Daughter of his, aged about 14 <lb/>Months, the Diſtemper being then in the
        <lb/>Neighbourhood, and ſeveral having died in <lb/>the natural Way; it was accordingly
        done, <lb/>and alſo upon ſome others, at the ſame <lb/>Time, who did very well; but in this
        Child, <lb/>the Symptoms were very ſevere, and when <lb/>the Puſtules appear'd, they were
        very <w part="I">nume-</w><lb/><w part="F">rous</w>, tho' diſtinct, and not ſo kindly as we
        <lb/>cou'd have wiſh'd, but rather of the crystaline <lb/>Sort; however, ſhe went on as well
        as we<lb/>cou'd expect to the eleventh Day, the <w part="I">Pu-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſtules</w> cruſted, and were many of them gone, <lb/>and the Child was very cheerful and
        brisk, <lb/>and play'd about the Room, inſomuch, that <lb/>we all concluded the Danger to be
        over: <choice>
          <corr>but</corr>
          <sic>ut</sic>
        </choice>
        <lb/>ſhe died ſuddenly in the Night, without any <lb/>Notice of her being worſe; whether her
        <lb/>Death was from the Small Pox, or ſome <w part="I">o-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w>
        Cauſe, occaſioning ſome ſudden <w part="I">Convul-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſion</w> or
        Suffocation, I will not preſume to <lb/>determine. </p></div>
      <div>
      <head rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic ">A ſecond Letter from the ſame <w part="I"
            >Gentle-</w><lb/><w part="F">man</w> to Dr.</hi> Jurin. </head>
      <dateline><hi rend="italic">Halifax, Nov.</hi> 11, 1723. </dateline>
      <lb/>
      <salute rend="italic">SIR, </salute>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HERE have been ſome Occurrences <lb/>here, in the
        Method of Inoculation, <lb/>which have been miſrepreſented, of which <lb/>it is neceſſary
        the Publick ſhould have a true <pb xml:id="page_40" n="35"/><lb/>and impartial Account. It
        was altogether a <lb/>Miſtake to affirm, that one who had been <lb/>inoculated a Year ago,
        was lately dead <lb/>of the natural Small Pox: But it is very <lb/>true, that one who had
        the Small Pox by <w part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F">oculation</w> did die; and alſo, that
        two others, <lb/>whom we attempted to inoculate, but <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >out</w> Effect, had the Diſtemper afterwards in <lb/>the natural Way. The Facts are
        contain'd in <lb/>the following Certificates, which will be <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">teſted</w> upon Oath, by the Parties concern'd, <lb/>whenever it ſhall be
        requir'd. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>We have Reaſon to believe, that the Death <lb/>of the Child hereafter
        mention'd, was owing <lb/>to ſome other Cauſe beſides the Small Pox; <lb/>but if, to avoid
        Diſpute, we yield that Point, <lb/>it muſt then be acknowledged, that out of <lb/>Seventy
        four, who had the Small Pox by <w part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F">oculation</w> hereabouts,
        one has died; all the <lb/>reſt are at this Time alive, and in good <lb/>Health. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>We have been told by all thoſe, who have <lb/>writ upon the Subject of
        Inoculation, that it <lb/>may ſometimes fail, and produce nothing at <lb/>all; in which
        Caſe, it can be no more <w part="I">Secu-</w><lb/><w part="F">rity</w> againſt the
        Diſtemper, than if nothing <lb/>had been done. Moſt of thoſe who have <lb/>been inoculated
        here, have been as much <lb/>expos'd, as theſe two Children who have taken <lb/>the
        Infection ſince; but we have not yet <lb/>found, that any, who had the Small Pox by
        <lb/>this Method, tho' in the loweſt Degree, ever <lb/>had it again in the natural Way. If
        any ſuch <lb/>Thing ſhould happen, I ſhall not fail to <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >viſe</w> you of it. There has nothing occurr'd <pb xml:id="page_41" n="36"/><lb/>here, ſo
        far as I know, that can poſſibly be <lb/>repreſented to the Diſadvantage of the <w part="I"
          >Pra-</w><lb/><w part="F">ctice</w>, beſides what is contain'd in the <w part="I"
          >enclo-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſed</w> Papers. </p>
      <signed rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">I am, SIR, <lb/>Your moſt obedient humble
          Servant,</hi>
        <lb/>Thomas Nettleton. </signed></div>
      <div>
      <dateline><hi rend="italic">Ealand,</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">Nov.</hi> 8, 1723. </dateline>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe may certify, that in <hi rend="italic">February,</hi> 1721/2,
        <lb/>the Small Pox was inoculated upon two of <lb/>our Daughters, the one about five, and
        the <lb/>other four Years of Age, who had, as far as <lb/>we could judge, the true Small
        Pox, through <lb/>which Diſtemper they got with very great <lb/>Eaſe. Some time after, the
        ſame Operation <lb/>was perform'd upon a Boy of ours, aged about <lb/>three Years, but
        without any Effect: The <lb/>Child was not in the leaſt diſorder'd, had no <lb/>Appearances
        upon his Skin, neither did the <lb/>Places of Inciſion ſwell or inflame as in the <lb/>other
        Children, ſo that we then concluded it <lb/>would avail him nothing. About five Months
        <lb/>ago, the Diſtemper being then in the <w part="I">Neigh-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >bourhood</w>, and ſeveral having dy'd of it in <lb/>the natural Way; we had the Small Pox
          <w part="I">ino-</w><lb/><w part="F">culated</w> upon a Daughter of ours, aged about
        <lb/>15 Months; with this Child the Diſtemper <lb/>was more ſevere than uſual; ſhe was very
        <lb/>full, tho' the Puſtules were diſtinct. She <lb/>went on as well as we cou'd expect, and
        on <lb/>the eleventh Day, was very chearful and <lb/>brisk, free from Heat or Thirſt, and
        the <lb/>Small Pox were many of them cruſted and <pb xml:id="page_42" n="37"/><lb/>gone off,
        inſomuch, that we thought her out <lb/>of Danger: However, that Night ſhe died
        <lb/>ſuddenly, even before any Alteration for the <lb/>worſe was perceiv'd by thoſe that
        attended <lb/>her. This unhappy Event may poſſibly <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >poſe</w> us to the Cenſure of the World; but the <lb/>Conſciouſneſs of having done our
        Duty in <lb/>uſing the moſt likely Means, to preſerve Life <lb/>in a Time of common Danger,
        makes us <w part="I">ea-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſy</w> and content. About ten Days after this,
        <lb/>our Son abovemention'd, upon whom the <lb/>Inoculation had no Effect, was ſeized in the
        <lb/>natural Way, had a very kindly Sort, and <lb/>recover'd very well. The Diſtemper was,
        at <lb/>that Time, very rife in two or three <w part="I">neigh-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >bouring</w> Families, inſomuch, that none <w part="I">eſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">cap'd</w>,
        who had not had it before; amongſt <lb/>theſe, there were ſix Perſons who had the <lb/>Small
        Pox by Inoculation, ſome of which <lb/>were conſtantly, and the reſt frequently, in
        <lb/>Company with thoſe that were ſick of the <lb/>natural Sort, without being any Way
        affected. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>To the Truth of the above, we ſubſcribe. </p>
      <lb/>
      <salute rend="size(0.5)">To the above written <w part="I">Par-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ticulars</w>, atteſt the Nurſe <lb/>and Maid, who attended <lb/>the Children, during
        <lb/>their Illneſs. </salute>
      <signed>
        <list>
          <lb/>
          <item rend="italic">Joſeph Brooksbank, </item>
          <lb/>
          <item rend="italic">Eliza. Brooksbank. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Eliza.</hi> I <hi rend="italic">Brooksbank,</hi>
          </item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italic">Eliza.</hi> X <hi rend="italic">Mellar.</hi>
          </item>
        </list>
      </signed></div>
      <pb xml:id="page_43" n="38"/>
      <lb/>
      <div>
      <dateline><hi rend="italic">Halifax,</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">Nov.</hi> 5, 1723. </dateline>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe may certify, that at our Requeſt in <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >February</hi> 1721/2, the Small Pox was <w part="I">inocula-</w><lb/><w part="F">ted</w>
        upon two of our Children, the one a Boy <lb/>aged about 5 Years, the other a Girl, about
        <lb/>3 Years old. The Girl, in a Week's Time, <lb/>began to be very feveriſh and ill, and
        after <lb/>2 or 3 Days the Small Pox appear'd: They <lb/>roſe very round and large, tho' but
        few in <lb/>Number, and ſhe ſoon recover'd. The Boy was <lb/>no Ways affected, had no Manner
        of Illneſs <lb/>that we could perceive, nothing appear'd <w part="I">up-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >on</w> his Skin, neither did the Places that were <lb/>cut, look red and angry, as they
        did in the <lb/>Girl: But about a Week or ten Days after <lb/>his Siſter recover'd, he fell
        ill of the Small <lb/>Pox, had more in Number, and was much <lb/>worſe than ſhe was, but
        after ſome Time <lb/>recover'd very well. </p>
      <signed><lb/>As Witneſs our Hands, <list>
          <lb/>
          <item>Teſt. </item>
          <item rend="italic">Martha Micheli, </item>
          <lb/>
          <item rend="italic">Thomas Thorp. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item rend="italic">William Clark, </item>
          <lb/>
          <item rend="italic">Phebe Clark. </item>
        </list>
      </signed></div>
      <div>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">P. S.</hi> It is to be obſerv'd, that theſe two
        <lb/>Children were not inoculated with the ſame <lb/>Matter. The Girl was from one, that had
        <lb/>a very favourable Kind in the natural Way. <lb/>The Boy was from one that was
        inoculated; <lb/>but I had the Misfortune to come too late; <lb/>the Puſtules were wither'd,
        and almoſt gone, <lb/>and the Matter was chiefly taken from the <lb/>Inciſion in the Arm. I
        did not think <w part="I">neceſſa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ry</w> to mention this Particular, in
        the <w part="I">Ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">count</w> I gave of this Boy formerly, becauſe <pb
          xml:id="page_44" n="39"/><lb/>I could not conclude from one Tryal, any <lb/>Thing
        certainly. It is now very well known, <lb/>that the Matter taken from the Puſtules of
        <lb/>the inoculated Small Pox, will convey the <lb/>Diſtemper, as well as the natural; but I
          <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">lieve</w>, that which runs from the Inciſions will
        <lb/>not. I can give no Account how the <w part="I">Opera-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>
        happen'd to fail in Mr. <hi rend="italic">Brooksbank</hi>'s Boy; <lb/>for two other Children
        were inoculated at <lb/>the ſame Time, with the ſame Matter, in <lb/>whom it ſucceeded very
        well. </p></div>
    </body>
    <back> </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
