<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Douglas: A short account of the state of midwifery in London,
          Westminster</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>John Douglas</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Lithotomia Douglassiana: OR, An Account of a New METHOD of making the
              High Operation, in order to extract the Stone out of the Bladder. Which is much easier
              to the Patient, much sooner done by the Operator, and the Cure much more certain, than
              after any of the other Methods now in Use. By which also, several of the most dismal
              Consequences of the common Operations are entirely prevented, such as Incontinency of
              Urine, Impotency, Fistula's, &amp;c.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T62746</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T41092"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for and sold only by the author in Lad-Lane, near
                  Guild-Hall, M.DCC.XXXVI. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1736</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="3"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="75"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="2"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library"/>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3308018378</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K054348.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Surgical or anatominal work"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_1"/>
        <p rend="align-center space"><lb/>A <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">SHORT ACCOUNT</hi>
          <lb/>OF THE <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">STATE of MIDWIFERY</hi><lb/>IN <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)"><hi
              rend="italic">London, Weſtminſter,</hi> &amp;c. </hi></p>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="3"/>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_6"/>
      <head rend="align-center space"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)"><hi rend="sc">The <lb/>State of
            Midwifery.</hi></hi></head>
      <p rend="space"><lb/>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>Decorative frame around the letter "I".</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <hi rend="dc(4)">I</hi>S it not very ſurpriſing, nay and <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >accountable</w>, that tho' almoſt all the <lb/>other parts of Surgery have been <w
          part="I">cul-</w><lb/><w part="F">tivated</w> with great aſſiduity, by the <lb/>moſt
        knowing Men, ever ſince <w part="I">Hip-</w><lb/><w part="F">pocrates</w>, nay and before
        him, yet ('till about the <lb/>middle of the laſt century) the operations neceſſary for
        <lb/>the ſafety of women in labour, and their children; <lb/>operations of more conſequence
        to mankind than <lb/>almoſt all the reſt; operations ſo often wanted, ſo <lb/>difficult many
        times to perform, and upon which <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">ways</w> two, and
        ſometimes more lives depend, ſeem <lb/>to have been entirely left to a parcel of ignorant
        <lb/>women, or to Men little better qualified than they, <lb/>who upon any extraordinary
        difficulty (as too many <lb/>ſtill do) took hooks or knives, and carved the <w part="I"
          >chil-</w><lb/><w part="F">dren</w> to pieces; and often alſo deſtroyed the Mother? </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Surgeons at Paris, &amp;c. to remedy this evil, <lb/>have for many
        years paſt, obliged all the <w part="I">Midwo-</w><lb/><w part="F">men</w> to be examined
        and approved of at their hall, <lb/>before ever they dare ſet up for practice: An <w
          part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">ample</w> moſt worthy of imitation! But how, or by
        <lb/>what infatuation, our <hi rend="italic">Dom. fac. totum</hi> ſuffered theſe <pb
          xml:id="page_7" n="2"/><lb/>operations to drop through their fingers, (as if they
        <lb/>were no part of their profeſſion, as if they were not <lb/>manual operations, or were
        of little or no <w part="I">conſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">quence</w> to mankind,) into the
        hands of Doctors, <lb/><hi rend="italic">inferioris ſortis medici,</hi> (as a certain
        Gentleman <lb/>calls them,) Apothecaries, and the loweſt claſs of <lb/>their own Fraternity!
        (ſome of whom have been, <lb/>and are, as illiterate, of as low capacities, and as little
        <lb/>acquainted with the other great operations of Surgery, <lb/>as almoſt any of the women)
        and have and do allow <lb/>every ſilly woman, who takes it in her head, with <lb/>very
        little or no inſtruction, to practice <hi rend="italic">impunè</hi>
        <lb/>among his Majeſty's ſubjects, without any the leaſt <lb/>examination or licence! are
        queſtions I ſhall not <lb/>now take upon me to anſwer. But to proceed: </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> firſt rational account we ever had of <w part="I"
          >deli-</w><lb/><w part="F">vering</w> women in labour, was publiſhed at Paris <lb/>by Mr.
        Mauriceau, in 1668. In his dedication, <lb/>he gives the following honeſt account of his
        deſign: <lb/><q >I have the rather undertaken this work, that <lb/>Midwives might
          find therein what they ought to <lb/>know, the better to exerciſe their art, and <w
            part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">dergo</w> the examination they are obliged to at
          <lb/>Surgeons-Hall, before they are admitted to <lb/>practice.</q> In his preface, he
        ſays, <q >I have <lb/>not run out into ſuperfluous diſcourſe</q> (i. e. he <lb/>had
        avoided all puzzling and unintelligible <lb/>Theories and Hypotheſes, about generation,
        <lb/>nutrition, ſuperfoetation, and ſuch ſort of <w part="I">jar-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >gon</w>,) <q >that I might be more ſerviceable both <lb/>to Surgeons and
          Midwives.</q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> plain practical work, would <w part="I"
          >undoubted-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> have had a much better effect upon our <w part="I"
          >Mid-</w><lb/><w part="F">women</w>, <pb xml:id="page_8" n="3"/><lb/>had they not been
        puzzled and <w part="I">confound-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>, (inſtead of being inſtructed)
        by the artful <w part="I">inſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nuations</w> of the tranſlator, in his
        preface and <w part="I">mar-</w><lb/><w part="F">ginal</w> notes, publiſhed in 1672. as will
        appear by <lb/>the following quotations. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Dr.</hi> Chamberlen, in his preface, ſays, <q 
          >Hav-<lb/>ing long obſerved the great want of neceſſary <lb/>directions how to govern
          women with child, <lb/>and in child-bed, &amp;c. I deſign'd a ſmall <w part="I"
            >ma-</w><lb/><w part="F">nual</w> to that purpoſe; but meeting ſome time <lb/>after in
          France with this treatiſe of Mauriceau, <lb/>which in my opinion exceeds all former <w
            part="I">Au-</w><lb/><w part="F">thors</w>, I changed my reſolution into that of
          <lb/>tranſlating him; whom I need not much <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">mend</w>,
          becauſe he is fortified with the <w part="I">approba-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of the
          wardens of the Surgeons company of <lb/>Paris.</q> Pray would the Doctor have thought he
        <lb/>had been ſo well fortified, if he had had the <w part="I">approba-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tion</w> of the then wardens of the Surgeons company of <lb/>London? or the approbation
        of the college of <w part="I">phy-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſicians</w> at Paris? <q >I
          have carefully rendered his <lb/>book into Engliſh, for the benefit of our <w part="I"
            >Mid-</w><lb/><w part="F">wives</w>.</q> This is certainly a very fair and honeſt
        <lb/>Exordium, a worthy and laudablc Deſign; but pray <lb/>mark the end on't: <q >Of
          whom many may yet very <lb/>well admit of an additional knowledge.</q> This <lb/>cannot be
        denied, but pray where are they to go <lb/>look for this additional knowledge, if he means,
        in <lb/>their profeſſion? Is it to be found in his preface and <lb/>marginal notes upon
        Mauriceau's work? No! they <lb/>rather darken, than explain, the Author's meaning. <lb/>But
        the additional knowledge the Doctor means, and <lb/>has taken ſuch pains to inculcate,
        through the <pb xml:id="page_9" n="4"/><lb/>whole of his preface and notes, is to inform
        them <lb/>the He and his family can aſſiſt them better than any <lb/>other Men; that they
        have no buſineſs to meddle <lb/>with any child, except thoſe who juſt drop into <lb/>their
        hands, and that whenever the leaſt difficulty <lb/>appears, to ſend for him, or ſome or the
          <w part="I">Noſtrum-</w><lb/><w part="F">mongers</w>; as will appear evidently from the
        tenure <lb/>of the whole. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Then</hi> he goes on, <q >The principal thing <w
            part="I">wor-</w><lb/><w part="F">thy</w> the obſervation of Midwives in this book,
          <lb/>is accurately to diſcover what is properly their <lb/>work, and when it is neceſſary
          to ſend for <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">vice</w> and aſſiſtance, that ſo, <hi
            rend="italic">many women and <lb/>children may be preſerved, that now periſh for
            <lb/>want of ſeaſonable help.</hi></q> i. e. ſhall victims <lb/>to the ignorance of
        Midwomen. <q >And that <lb/>Midwife's skill is certainly the greateſt, and <lb/>ſhe
          deſerves moſt commendation, who can <lb/>ſooneſt diſcover the ſucceſs of the labour,
          <lb/>and accordingly either wait with patience, or <lb/>timely ſend for advice and
          help.</q> Pray is not <lb/>that <choice>
            <sic>Midwwoman's</sic>
            <corr>Midwoman's</corr>

        </choice> skill ſtill greater? and does ſhe <lb/>not deſerve much more commendation? who can
        <lb/>ſooneſt diſcover what obſtructs the delivery, and <lb/>then removes the obſtruction
        herſelf, and thereby <lb/>ſaves the woman the fright, trouble, and expence, <lb/>of ſending
        for any farther help or advice? <q >Nor <lb/>can it be ſo great a diſcredit to a
          Midwife (let <lb/>ſome of them imagine what they pleaſe) to have <lb/>a woman or child
          ſaved by a man's aſſiſtance, as <lb/>to ſuffer either to die under her own hand, tho'
          <lb/>delivered: For that Midwife miſtakes her office, <lb/>that thinks ſhe hath performed
          it, by only laying <pb xml:id="page_10" n="5"/><lb/>the woman; becauſe her principal duty
          is to <lb/>take care that ſhe and her child be well, with <lb/>ſafety and convenient ſpeed
          parted;</q> who <lb/>don't know that? <q >and, if this be impoſſible for <lb/>her,
          it will juſtify her better to wave her <w part="I">imagi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nary</w>
          reputation, and ſend for help.</q> No doubt <lb/>of it. But would it not have been much
        better if <lb/>they had been taught to do their office themſelves? </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Thus</hi> you ſee Mr. Mauriceau's deſign in <w part="I"
          >pub-</w><lb/><w part="F">liſhing</w> his book, was to inſtruct the Midwomen <lb/>how to
        perform their office better; but Dr. <w part="I">Cham-</w><lb/><w part="F">berlen</w>
        perverts that deſign, and ſeems to have the <lb/>Intereſt of the Midmen, and not that of the
          <w part="I">Mid-</w><lb/><w part="F">women</w>, or — principally at heart, as is <w
          part="I">evi-</w><lb/><w part="F">dent</w> from the foregoing quotations, &amp;c. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Notwithſtanding all theſe coaxes and threats, <lb/>which he plays off ſo
        briskly upon the town <w part="I">Mid-</w><lb/><w part="F">women</w>, (who are undoubtedly
        much better <w part="I">qualifi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>, than thoſe in the country) in
        caſe they don't ſend <lb/>for him, &amp;c. on every trifling difficulty, he goes on,
        <lb/>and ſays, <q >Yet in countries and places where help <lb/>and good advice is not
          ſeaſonably to be had, <lb/>Midwives are compelled to do their beſt, as <lb/>God ſhall
          enable them.</q> Pray has God any <lb/>where promiſed to give more aſſiſtance to a country
        <lb/>than a town Midwoman? Thus the poor country <lb/>Midwomen are to act as God ſhall
        enable them; <lb/>but the town Midwomen, as the Doctor &amp;c. ſhall <lb/>direct, <hi
          rend="italic">Utrum horum!</hi> Pray has God Almighty given <lb/>us the leaſt ground to
        expect, that he will <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſpire</w> us in an inſtant, even
        upon the moſt urgent <lb/>occaſion, with the perfect knowledge of any <w part="I"
          >uſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">ful</w> art, only becauſe it would juſt then be of <w part="I"
          >ſer-</w><pb xml:id="page_11" n="6"/><lb/><w part="F">vice</w> to us? No. But he has told
        us, that, if we <lb/>want to acquire the knowledge of any uſeful art, <lb/>we muſt
        diligently and aſſiduouſly apply ourſelves <lb/>to the ſtudy of it in the moſt proper manner
        we <lb/>can. <hi rend="italic">Dii laborantibus omnia vendunt!</hi><q >Which <w
            part="I">dan-</w><lb/><w part="F">gerous</w> and uncertain trials in doth not become
          <lb/>them to put in practice upon women, where <lb/>no timely aſſiſtance need be
          wanting.</q> Thus <lb/>you ſee, the Doctor thinks dangerous and <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">certain</w> trials may lawfully be put in practice <lb/>on women in the country,
        tho' not upon thoſe in <lb/>town, where he and the reſt of the <w part="I"
          >Noſtrum-</w><lb/><w part="F">mongers</w> may be had. But, pray, might not <lb/>many of
        theſe uncertain and dangerous trials, <lb/>both in town and country, have been prevented, if
        <lb/>he had endeavoured as much to inſtruct them how <lb/>to give better aſſiſtance
        themſelves, as he has done <lb/>to let them know when to ſend for him, &amp;c. <lb/>Are not
        the women's lives in the country as <w part="I">va-</w><lb/><w part="F">luable</w> as thoſe
        in town? </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Then</hi> he goes on to tell them in what <w part="I"
          >particu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lar</w> caſes they ought to ſend for him, &amp;c. viz.
        <lb/>"1. In moſt wrong births, with or without pain." <lb/>(alias with or without danger or
        difficulty) <q >2. All <lb/>floodings with clods, tho' little or no pain,
          <lb/>whether at full time or not. 3. All convulſions. <lb/>4. Many firſt labours. 5. And
          ſome others;</q>
        <lb/>(i. e. every other caſe, when the People are <w part="I">ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſtantial</w>,) viz. <q >tho' the child be right, if little or <lb/>no pain, after
          the breaking of the waters, and <lb/>the child's not following them in ſome ſix or
          <lb/>ten hours after, require the good advice of, and, <lb/>peradventure, ſpeedy delivery
          by expert <w part="I">phyſi-</w><pb xml:id="page_12" n="7"/><lb/><w part="F">cians</w>
          clans in this practice.</q> Pray would not expert <w part="I">Sur-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >geons</w> in this practice do as well? Is it not evident <lb/>from the Doctor's liſt of
        caſes, that very few <w part="I">wo-</w><lb/><w part="F">men</w> (except thoſe in the
        country, or who are very <lb/>poor) could eſcape thoſe expert Phyſicians? viz. He, <lb/>his
        father, and two brothers. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> leaſt the charge he has given to the <w part="I"
          >Mid-</w><lb/><w part="F">women</w> (of ſending for him, &amp;c. upon every <w part="I"
          >tri-</w><lb/><w part="F">fling</w> occaſion) ſhould not have weight enough, <lb/>he alſo
        threatens the poor ſuffering women with <lb/>what may happen to them, in caſe they don't
        oblige <lb/>their Midwomen to ſend for them. <q >Let me <lb/>therefore adviſe the
          good women, not ſo readily <lb/>to blame thoſe Midwives who are not backward <lb/>in
          dangerous caſes," <hi rend="italic">(or not dangerous caſes,)</hi>
          <lb/>to deſire advice, leaſt it coſt them dear;" (pray <lb/>don't it always coſt them dear
          when they do?) <lb/>by diſcouraging and forcing them to preſume <lb/>beyond their
          knowledge and ſtrength,</q> As for <lb/>their want of knowledge, I take it to be more
        their <lb/>misfortune than their fault, becauſe they have <lb/>not yet had ſuch proper
        opportunities of informing <lb/>themſelves, as they ought to have; but as to <lb/>ſtrength,
        I'm ſatisfied moſt of them have enough, <lb/>did they know how to make a proper uſe of it.
        <lb/>eſpecially when too many are over confident." <lb/>For this compliment the Midwomen are
        as much <lb/>obliged to him, as for many others he paſſes upon <lb/>them. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>In another place he ſays, <q >If therefore the <lb/>uſe of hooks
          by Phyſicians</q> (pray what buſineſs <lb/>have phyſicians with hooks? Are not pen, ink,
        <lb/>and paper, their proper inſtruments? What right <pb xml:id="page_13" n="8"/><lb/>have
        they then to encroach upon us? Don't they <lb/>make a ſad outcry, are not they alarmed as if
        <lb/>their craft was in danger, when we uſe pen <lb/>and ink? except in Pauper caſes. <q
          >and <w part="I">Sur-</w><lb/><w part="F">geons</w>, be condemned, (without thereto
            <w part="I">neceſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſitated</w> by ſome monſtrous birth, &amp;c.)</q>
        Now <lb/>you ſee he is obliged to own, notwithſtanding all <lb/>he ſays to the contrary,
        that hooks are <w part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F">times</w> abſolutely neceſſary. <q
          >We can much leſs <lb/>approve of a Midwife's uſing them, as ſome here <lb/>in
          England boaſt they do; which raſh <w part="I">preſump-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, in
          France, would call them in queſtion for <lb/>their lives.</q> The Doctor allows, pag. 5.
        country <lb/>Midwives are compelled to do their beſt as <lb/>God ſhall direct; them: Now
        ſuppoſing that God <lb/>ſhould direct one of them to make uſe of a <w part="I"
          >croch-</w><lb/><w part="F">et</w>, in a fit caſe, and after a proper manner, <lb/>muſt
        ſhe be tried for her life for it? Is not this a <lb/>very hard charge upon the poor
        Midwomen, <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w part="F">out</w> any proof? I muſt diffent ſo far
        from the <w part="I">Doc-</w><lb/><w part="F">tor's</w> opinion, that I believe the hardieſt
          <w part="I">Mid-</w><lb/><w part="F">woman</w> in London, would tremble at the very
        <lb/>thought of it, unleſs they were fully inſtructed how <lb/>to uſe it, as—; but for what
        they may do <lb/>in the country, according to the Doctor's advice, <lb/>above recited, I
        cannot anſwer. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Mr. Mauriceau (pag. 179.) ſays, <q >A Midwife <lb/>vaunted ſhe
          was more skilful in her art than any <lb/>Surgeon.</q> Upon which Dr. Chamberlen remarks,
        <lb/>that, <q >It ſeems Midwives in other countries, as <lb/>well as England, have
          that pernicious vanity.</q>
        <lb/>But, pray were there no Midmen then in <w part="I">Eng-</w><lb/><w part="F">land</w>,
        who had vaunted they could perform what <pb xml:id="page_14" n="9"/><lb/>they really could
        not? Vid. Mr. Mauriceau's 26th <lb/>obſervation, quoted below. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>MR. Mauriceau, pag. 203. <q >If the arm be <w part="I"
            >ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">vanced</w> as far as the ſhoulder, &amp;c. Dr. Chamberlen
          <lb/>remarks, which ſeldom is, unleſs an Ignorant <lb/>Midwife tamper with it.</q> Are not
        theſe pretty <lb/>compliments? but where is the inſtruction? Are <lb/>not all practitioners,
        of the very leaſt experience, <lb/>ſenſible it often happens without any tampering. <lb/>But
        notwithſtanding he has been ſo laviſh in <lb/>theſe, and many other places, in cenſuring
        <lb/>thoſe good women, yet he winds up his preface <lb/>with a ſalvo for all, viz. <q
          >I hope no good <lb/>Midwives will blame me for reprehending the <lb/>faults of Bad
          ones, who are only aimed at, and <lb/>admoniſhed in this work; and I'm confident <lb/>none
          but the Guilty will be concerned, and take <lb/>it to themſelves, which I deſire they may,
          and <lb/>amend.</q> Is not this cobweb eaſily ſeen through? <lb/>Is not this the firſt
        time he has mentioned good <lb/>Midwives? </p>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>Dr. Chamberlen's account of his ſecret. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">H</hi>E is not content with amuſiing, <w part="I"
            >confound-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>, nay, and abuſing the Midwomen, at <lb/>the ſame
          time he makes a ſhew of teaching them, <lb/>but alſo ſerves the Midmen the ſame ſauce; by
          <lb/>telling them he has a ſecret, which will do <w part="I">won-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ders</w>, i. e. It will ſave many children's lives, <lb/>which, they who do not know
          it, <hi rend="italic">(or ſomething <lb/>as good,)</hi> muſt deſtroy; but cannot in honour
          <lb/>(notwithſtanding it might ſave thouſands of lives) <pb xml:id="page_15" n="10"
          /><lb/>diſcover it even to them, becauſe it might <w part="I">preju-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >dice</w> the perſonal intereſt of his father and two <lb/>brothers, who only, in all
          Europe, know it: But <lb/>what they may do in Africa, Aſia, &amp;c. this <lb/>deponent
          ſayeth not. His own ſtory is as <w part="I">fol-</w><lb/><w part="F">lows</w>: <q 
            >My Author, lib. ii. cap. 17. juſtifies <lb/>the faſtening hooks in the head of a child
            that <lb/>comes right, and yet becauſe of ſome difficulty <lb/>or diſproportion, cannot
            paſs; which I confeſs <lb/>has been, and is yet the practice of the moſt <lb/>expert
            artiſts in Midwifery, not only in <w part="I">Eng-</w><lb/><w part="F">land</w>, but
            throughout Europe. But I can neither <lb/>approve of that practice, nor thoſe
            delays;</q>
          <lb/>(Pray obſerve how long he was in attempting to <lb/>deliver that woman at Paris, vid.
          M. M. obs. 26. <lb/>quoted below; <q >becauſe my father, brothers, <lb/>and
            ſelf,</q> (tho' none elſe in Europe as I know,) <lb/>Pray had not Sir David Hamilton
          more buſineſs, <lb/>and as good, if not better ſucceſs, in the <lb/>practice of Midwifery
          than he? May we not then <lb/>reaſonably ſuppoſe, that he either knew his ſecret, <lb/>or
          had one of his own, tho' he never made any <lb/>noiſe about it, which anſwered as well? <q
            >have, <lb/>by God's bleſſing, and our iuduſtry, attained to, <lb/>and long
            practiſed a way to deliver women in <lb/>this caſe, without any prejudice to them or
            their <lb/>infants; tho' all others (being obliged, for want <lb/>of ſuch an expedient,
            to uſe the common way) <lb/>do, and muſt endanger, if not deſtroy one or <lb/>both with
            hooks.</q> Pray would it not have <lb/>been a grateful return, for God's bleſſing them
          <lb/>with ſo uſeful a ſecret, to have communicated it to <lb/>the reſt of the Midmen,
          whereby the deſtruction <pb xml:id="page_16" n="11"/><lb/>of ſo many women and children,
          might have been <lb/>prevented? <q >By this manual operation a labour may <lb/>be
            diſpatched, (on the leaſt difficulty)</q> ſo that <lb/>on the leaſt difficulty, either
          to Midwomen or <lb/>Midmen, we muſt immediately run for one of the <lb/>Noſtrum-mongers.
            <q >with fewer pains, and <w part="I">ſoon-</w><lb/><w part="F">er</w>, to the
            great advantage, and without danger <lb/>both of woman and child.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">He</hi> is not content with having thus acquainted
          <lb/>us with the great value of his ſecret, and who <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſides</w> himſelf are poſſeſſed of it, in his epiſtle, but <lb/>alſo mentions and
          recommends it over and over, <lb/><hi rend="italic">ad nauſeam uſque,</hi> through the
          whole of his remarks <lb/>on this work, for fear the Midwomen ſhould <w part="I"
            >at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tend</w> Mr. Mauriceau ſo much, that they ſhould <w part="I"
            >for-</w><lb/><w part="F">get</w> his <hi rend="italic">Noſtrum,</hi> E. G. Mr.
          Mauriceau, pag. 176. <lb/><q >If there be any caſe, wherein a Surgeon <lb/>ought to
            make the greateſt reflection, and uſe <lb/>moſt precaution in his art, it is this; to
            know <lb/>whether the infant be alive or dead?</q> Dr. <w part="I">Cham-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">berlen</w> remarks, <q >This caution is not ſo neceſſary <lb/>to thoſe
            practitoners which can fetch a child <lb/>coming right, or with the Arm, without hooks
            <lb/>or ſharp inſtruments, as the tranſlator of <lb/>this book, and his father, and his
            brothers can.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Mr.</hi> Chapman in his eſſay on Midwifery, 1733.
          <lb/>ſays, Dr. Chamberlen's ſecret was the Forceps. <lb/>Then makes the following quaint
          obſervation on <lb/>the fore-mentioned remark: <q >Here is <w part="I"
              >ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F">thing</w> very odd methinks, in applying this <lb/>ſecret
            to both theſe caſes, as equally <w part="I">ſervice-</w><lb/><w part="F">able</w> to
            either, the caſes differing ſo very <pb xml:id="page_17" n="12"/><lb/>widely, and
            requiring a quite different method: <lb/>For the head preſenting, and far advanced, is
            <lb/>to be taken hold of by the Forceps, and <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >tracled</w>; when a child which preſents an arm, <lb/>is to be turned, and ſo brought
            away by its <lb/>feet;</q> i. e. without either hooks or ſharp <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtruments</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Whence</hi> its evident, Mr. Chapman did not
          <lb/>apprehend the Doctor's view in applying his ſecret <lb/>to the arm as well as the
          head. It was <w part="I">undoubted-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> the better to puzzle the
          cauſe, the better to <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceal</w> his Noſtrum, that he
          applies it to two caſes, <lb/>between which there is not the leaſt analogy. He <lb/>might
          as well have ſaid, it would be of great uſe in <lb/>extracting the ſtone, or in drawing
          teeth. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>MR. Mauriceau, pag. 204. <q >The arm <lb/>is to be twiſted off,
            if the child be dead.</q>
          <lb/>Dr. Chamberlen, <q >Good if the child be dead; <lb/>but it may be always done
            without.</q>
          <w part="I">Undoubt-</w><lb/><w part="F">edly</w> it may be often done without twiſting it
          <lb/>off, but not with his Forceps. Mr. Mauriceau, ibid. <lb/><q >Before you uſe
            the Crotchet, be ſure the child is <lb/>dead.</q> Dr. Chamberlen, <q >this caveat
            is <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">neceſſary</w> to thoſe who underſtand the art
            aright.</q>
          <lb/>i. e. only the Noſtrum-mongers. Dr. <w part="I">Chamber-</w><lb/><w part="F">len</w>,
            <q >The uſe of the crotchet may be <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">nived</w>
            at when the child is dead; but becauſe <lb/>the moſt careful may often times be
            miſtaken, <lb/>it cannot be approved of; as appears in the <lb/>tranſlator's epiſtle to
            the reader.</q> Dr. Chamberlen, <lb/>pag. 226. <q >Tho' the Crotchet cannot hurt
            a dead <lb/>child, yet it may endanger the woman by ſlipping:</q>
          <lb/>So may a Lancet, Traphine, or any other <w part="I">inſtru-</w><pb xml:id="page_18"
            n="13"/><lb/><w part="F">ment</w> in the hands of thoſe who don't know how <lb/>to uſe
          them.) <q >Wherefore the tranſlator of this <lb/>treatiſe cannot approve of it,
            having an eaſier <lb/>and ſafer way to do this operation, as he <w part="I"
              >men-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w> in his preface to this book.</q> Dr. <w part="I"
            >Chamber-</w><lb/><w part="F">len</w>, pag. 227. <q >All this <hi rend="italic"
              >(viz. the uſe of the <lb/>Crotchet)</hi> were to no purpoſe, if others had the
            <lb/>art to do it, as the tranſlator can, and mentions <lb/>in his preface to this
            book.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>DR. Chamberlen, pag. 229. <q >Thoſe <w part="I"
              >inſtru-</w><lb/><w part="F">ments</w> are very unſafe for the woman;</q>
          <w part="I">(un-</w><lb/><w part="F">doubtedly</w>, when in unexperienced hands, <w
            part="I">other-</w><lb/><w part="F">wiſe</w> they are not at all dangerous;) <q 
            >and having <lb/>a better way, I cannot paſs them without <w part="I">mani-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">feſting</w> my diſlike.</q> Mr. Mauriceau, pag. 194. <lb/><q >It's a
            great queſtion, whether a living child <lb/>ought to be deſtroyed to ſave the
            mother?</q>
          <lb/>Dr. Chamberlen, <q >This queſtion is out of doors, <lb/>for the reaſon given
            in the foreſaid preface.</q>
          <lb/>I'm afraid this will prove but a very bad reaſon in <lb/>ſome caſes, notwithſtanding
          it's laid down with <lb/>ſuch a magiſterial and dictatorial air, as I ſhall <lb/>prove at
          a more proper time. Mr. Mauriceau, <lb/>pag. 195. ſays, <q >It is always better of
            two evils <lb/>to chooſe the leaſt, ſo we ought always to <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">fer</w> the mother's life before the child's.</q> Dr. <lb/>Chamberlen, <q
            >This chapter might be very well <lb/>ſpared, if every practitioner had the art
            the <lb/>tranſlator profeſſeth in his epiſtle, of fetching a <lb/>child, when it comes
            right, without hooks, or <lb/>turning it.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>IF turning will do, there is never any occaſion <lb/>for hooks, or for
          his ſecret either. Thus you ſee <pb xml:id="page_19" n="14"/><lb/>with what fulſome
          repetitions, what nauſeous <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">commendations</w> of his
          Noſtrum, he has ſtuffed his <lb/>remarks; but has not made one remark, that can <lb/>be of
          any advantage to our Midwomen; and ſeems <lb/>to have had nothing elfſe in view through
          the <lb/>whole, but to tell them when they ought to ſend <lb/>for him, and to let them
          know, that he, &amp;c. <lb/>could ſerve them better than any body elſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>OUR tranſlator, like all the reſt of the <w part="I"
            >Secret-</w><lb/><w part="F">mongers</w>, has given a better character of his <w
            part="I">No-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtrum</w>, than I fancy it deſerves. E. G. He has
          <lb/>taken a great deal of pains, and uſed all his art to <lb/>perſuade us, that he,
          &amp;c. can fetch a child, which <lb/>preſents right, at all times, and in all
          circumſtances, <lb/>without hooks, or turning, &amp;c. but how this <w part="I"
            >qua-</w><lb/><w part="F">drates</w> with the two following caſes, (one of which <lb/>is
          tranſlated by the Doctor himſelf, and the other <lb/>is recorded in Mr. Mauriceau's 26th
          obſervation,) <lb/>I leave the reader to judge. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>MR. Mauriceau, pag, 198. tells us, that <q >in the year 1660,
            while he practiſed Midwifery in <lb/>the Hotel Dieu, one of the Deputies had a <w
              part="I">wo-</w><lb/><w part="F">man</w> whoſe Child ſhe could not poſibly bring
            <lb/>forth further than its head; therefore called the <lb/>head Midwife to her aid; who
            likewiſe uſed her <lb/>utmoſt skill but in vain: And when they had <lb/>both thus tir'd
            themſelves in pulling the head, <lb/>I came in accidentally, and they deſired me to
            <lb/>examine, and find the cauſe why the child could <lb/>not be drawn forth with all
            their ſtrength, <lb/>which was ſufficient to have drawn forth the <lb/>ſhoulders, if
            they had been as big again as they <lb/>were; which having conſidered, I immediately <pb
              xml:id="page_20" n="15"/><lb/>conceived the difficulty to proceed from <w part="I"
              >ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F">thing</w> elſe: I then put my hand into the womb, <lb/>up
            to the child's ſhoulders, which ſeemed ſmall <lb/>enough to paſs with eaſe, therefore I
            concluded <lb/>that the hindrance was not there.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><q >After that, I put my hand farther up <w part="I"
              >to-</w><lb/><w part="F">wards</w> it's belly, which I found very much <w part="I"
              >ſwel-</w><lb/><w part="F">led</w> by a dropſy. I therefore told them that it <lb/>was
            impoſſible ever to deliver the woman, until <lb/>the water was emptied by piercing the
            belly: <lb/>But not having a Crotchet in my pocket, I ſent <lb/>to another Surgeon of
            the ſame hoſpital, and <lb/>told him the ſtory, adding withal that the child <lb/>could
            not be born, unleſs an orifice was made <lb/>to empty the belly: but he would not take
            my <lb/>advice, imagining he could extract it with his <lb/>hands; but he ſoon ſeparated
            the head from <lb/>the ſhoulders, the Midwives having almoſt done <lb/>it before.
            Afterwards he fell to work with his <lb/>Crotchet, and in about three quarters of an
            hour <lb/>brought away both arms, ſeveral ribs, heart, <lb/>and lungs, and tired himſelf
            heartily, yet in all <lb/>this time, he had never opened the Diaphragma, <lb/>nor
            Abdomen, which I adviſed him to do every <lb/>moment, without which it was impoſſible to
            <lb/>draw forth the reſt of the body. Then he gave <lb/>me the Crotchet, telling me I
            might weary <w part="I">my-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſelf</w> as well as he had done; which I
            willingly <lb/>accepted, knowing very well, that inſtead of <lb/>amuſing myſelf, as they
            had done, by pulling it, <lb/>I ought only to pierce the infant's belly to let out
            <lb/>the waters, after which all the reſt would eaſily <lb/>follow. I then introduced my
            left hand as far <pb xml:id="page_21" n="16"/><lb/>as the ſide of the infant's belly,
            and then with <lb/>my right guided the Crotchet upon it, to the <lb/>ſame place, then
            turned its point, and ſtruck it <lb/>into the infant's belly, ſo that I made a hole big
            <lb/>enough to receive the ends of my two fingers, <lb/>with which I ſtretched the
            orifice, and the <w part="I">wa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ters</w> guſhed out, ſo that with
            one hand I eaſily <lb/>drew out the reſt of the body, to the <w part="I"
              >aſtoniſh-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w> of this Surgeon, whom I could never
            <lb/>perſuade that the infant was ſo full of the dropſy. <lb/>I filled the belly
            afterwards, through the hole I <lb/>had made, and it held about five quarts. I <lb/>have
            ſet down this ſtory, that other Surgeons <lb/>may know how to behave on the like <w
              part="I">occa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſions</w>.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Pray</hi> what could Dr. Chamberlen have done <lb/>with
          his Forceps in this caſe? But the following <lb/>ſtory will more clearly ſhew, that he
          himſelf has <lb/>been foiled, <hi rend="sc">Secret and all</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>Mr. Mauriceau's obſervation xxvi. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><q >Of a woman who died with her child in her <lb/>womb, which
            could not be extracted by an <lb/>Engliſh Phyſician who undertook to deliver
            <lb/>her.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><q ><hi rend="dc(3)">O</hi>N the 19th of Auguſt, 1670. I
            viſited a <lb/>little woman, about thirty-eight years of <lb/>age, who had been in
            labour of her firſt child <lb/>for four days, the membranes being broke the firſt
            <lb/>day of her illneſs, and yet there was hardly any <lb/>dilatation of the mouth of
            the womb. I ordered <pb xml:id="page_22" n="17"/><lb/>her to be blooded, and in caſe
            that did not <lb/>encreaſe her pains, to give her a decoction of <lb/>Senna, in order to
            excite them; which <w part="I">ſucceed-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> ſo well, that next
            day the womb was <w part="I">ſuffi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ciently</w> dilated.
            Nevertheleſs, it was nor <w part="I">poſſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w> to deliver her.
            The infant preſented it's <lb/>head, but could not advance into the paſſage,
            <lb/>becauſe of the ſtraitneſs and bad formation of <lb/>the bones of the Pelvis, which
            made it <w part="I">impoſſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w> for me to introduce my hand
            tho' I have a <lb/>very ſmall one, or any other inſtrument <w part="I">where-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">with</w> I could deliver her. I therefore declared <lb/>to the good women,
            that it was not poſſible to <lb/>deliver her at all, except by the Caeſarian ſection,
            <lb/>which I did not care to meddle with, &amp;c. But <lb/>ſoon after I left her, there
            was an Engliſh <w part="I">Phy-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſician</w>, named <hi rend="sc"
              >Chamberlen</hi>, recommended by <lb/>ſomebody to viſit her.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><q ><hi rend="sc">When</hi> he came and heard how it was, and
            <lb/>what had paſſed, he ſeemed exceedingly <w part="I">ſur-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >prized</w> that a Man of ſo much experience, as I was <lb/>reputed to have, could not
            deliver her; yet, for all <lb/>that, he aſſured them, that he would deliver her in
            <lb/>leſs than half a quarter of an hour, let the <w part="I">diffi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >culty</w> be what it would: Accordingly he ſet <w part="I">a-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >bout</w> the work, but inſtead of finiſhing it in half <lb/>a quarter of an hour, as
            he had promiſed, he <lb/>worked above three hours, (<hi rend="sc">Secret and all</hi>)
            <lb/>without any intermiſſion, except to breath a <lb/>little now and then. And at laſt,
            having <lb/>ſpent, to no purpoſe both his ſtrength and art, <lb/>and ſeeing the poor
            woman ready to expire in <lb/>his hands, he was obliged to give it up, and <pb
              xml:id="page_23" n="18"/><lb/>declared alſo, that it was not poſſible to deliver
            <lb/>her. The poor woman died with her child in <lb/>her belly about twenty-four hours
            after he <lb/>left her: Upon opening the body, I found <lb/>the womb pierced and tore in
            ſeveral places, <lb/>by the inſtruments that Phyſician had <w part="I">blind-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ly</w> uſed without the guidance of his hand, <lb/>which being much larger
            than mine could <lb/>not be introduced. Nevertheleſs this <w part="I">Phyſi-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">cian</w> had come from England to Paris, about <lb/>ſix months before, in
            hopes of making his <w part="I">for-</w><lb/><w part="F">tune</w>. He gave it out that
            he had a particular <lb/>ſecret for delivering children when the head <w part="I"
              >pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſented</w>; and bragg'd that he could lay the moſt
            <lb/>troubleſome and dangerous in half a quarter of <lb/>an hour. Nay, he had even
            propoſed to the <lb/>king's firſt phyſician, that if he would give <lb/>him 10000.
            crowns he would diſcover his <w part="I">ſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cret</w>. But the bad
            ſucceſs of the fore-mentioned <lb/>caſe put him ſo much out of humour, that he
            <lb/>returned a few days afterwards to England.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Does</hi> not this ſtory ſhew how little dependance
          <lb/>there is upon ſecrets, tho' never ſo poſitively <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >commended?</w> Does not this ſhew how cautious <lb/>people ought to be in believing of
          them? Does <lb/>not this ſhew, that, tho' they may be really <w part="I">uſe-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ful</w> in ſome caſes, yet they are not ſo in all, as <lb/>they commonly
          pretend? </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Preface</hi>. <q >I ſhall now take leave to offer
            <lb/>an apology for not publiſhing the ſecret I <w part="I">men-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >tion</w> we have to extract children without hooks, <lb/>where other artiſts uſe
            them, viz. there being <lb/>my father and two brothers living, that practiſe <pb
              xml:id="page_24" n="19"/><lb/>this art, I cannot eſteem it my own to diſpoſe
            <lb/>of,</q>
          <hi rend="italic">(a pretty and reaſonable excuſe indeed!)</hi>
          <lb/>"nor publiſh it without injury to them; <hi rend="italic">(but there <lb/>was not a
            word of this when he was bargaining with the <lb/>French king's firſt Phyſician,)</hi><q
            >and think I have <lb/>not been unſerviceable to my country, altho' I <lb/>do but
            inform them that the fore-mentioned <lb/>three perſons of our family, and myſelf, can
            <lb/>ſerve them in theſe extremities, with greater <lb/>ſafety than others.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">If</hi> Ward's Pill, or any other quack medicine,
          <lb/>was found by experience, to be generally of uſe in <lb/>this, that, or t'other
          diſeaſe, it may be ſent with <lb/>proper directions, to all parts of the kingdom; ſo
          <lb/>that the moſt diſtant inhabitants would have almoſt <lb/>the ſame benefit of it, with
          thoſe among whom <lb/>Mr. Ward lived; and conſequently Mr. Ward <lb/>might very juſtly
          ſay, that (notwithſtanding he <lb/>would not diſcover what his medicine was <w part="I"
            >com-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſed</w> of, becauſe it would be worth ſo much <w part="I"
            >year-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> to him and his ſucceſſors,) yet his country was
          <lb/>obliged to him, for telling them where they might <lb/>purchaſe ſo beneficial a
          remedy. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> how few in the whole community could <lb/>be
          the better for all the manual operations in <w part="I">Mid-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >wifery</w>, four Men could perform? Can four Men <lb/>deliver all the good women in
          England, who want <lb/>their aſſiſtance, ſuppoſing they were to ride poſt <lb/>night and
          day after them? Is there any proportion <lb/>between the benefit the publick would receive
          from <lb/>the quack medicines, and the ſecret manual <w part="I">opera-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tions</w> of four Men? What ſervice is it then to the <lb/>country in general,
          for the Doctor to tell them, <pb xml:id="page_25" n="20"/><lb/>that he and three others
          can ſerve them with <w part="I">great-</w><lb/><w part="F">er</w> ſafety than other Men? </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Nevertheless</hi> I'm far from thinking, that <lb/>the
          publick has any right to expect, that every <lb/>private Man (who, at a conſiderable
          expence, and <lb/>aſſiduous ſtudy, makes any conſiderable diſcovery <lb/>in manual
          operations, which cannot be made <w part="I">uni-</w><lb/><w part="F">verſally</w> uſeful,
          as medicines may, and really are, <lb/>except they are fully and diſtinctly explained,)
          <lb/>ſhould always communicate <hi rend="italic">Gratis</hi> the fruits of his <lb/>labour
          and expence. No! they ought to be <w part="I">hand-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſomely</w>
          rewarded, not only for the real ſervice they <lb/>have done, but to encourage induſtry in
          others. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> the Doctor offered to diſcover this ſecret
          <lb/>to the French for ten thouſand crowns; pray why <lb/>did he not make the ſame offer
          to his country? <lb/>Had not his country better have given each of them <lb/>ten thouſand
          crowns, than expoſed ſo many <w part="I">thou-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſands</w> of beautiful
          women, and innocent children, <lb/>to the danger of hooks, ſharp inſtruments, &amp;c.
          <lb/>the Doctor exclaims ſo much againſt? Surely yes. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Dr. Chamberlen. pag. 221. ſays, <q >The Author, <lb/>viz.
            Mauriceau,) you ſee was only a Surgeon.</q>
          <lb/>Pray what would he have him be? a Doctor, an <lb/>Apothecary, or what? Are not theſe
          operations <lb/>merely chirurgical? who then can be ſo fit to <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">form</w> them as Surgeons? Are not the <hi rend="italic">Superioris <lb/>ſortis
              <unclear>#</unclear>i,</hi> who never delivered one of them, as <lb/>capable of
          directing for them, both before and after <lb/>delivery, as any Doctor or Apothecary who
          had <lb/>laid ſeveral? No doubt of it! they are much more <lb/>capable! and it's very
          ſurprizing they don't aſſert <lb/>their own right, and ours? What then can <pb
            xml:id="page_26" n="21"/><lb/>Dr. Chamberlen mean by this ſneer, this ſarcaſm?
          <lb/>Eſpecially when Mr. Mauriceau is then talking as <lb/>much to the purpoſe, as ever
          he, or any body elſe <lb/>did, on that ſubject, viz. that when a woman has <lb/>a violent
          flooding, &amp;c. the beſt way to ſerve her, <lb/>is to deliver her as ſoon as poſſible,
          whether at full <lb/>time or no? Prove the contrary who can. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> pag. 172. he explains himſelf a little more
          <lb/>plainly. Mr. Mauriceau ſays, <q >A Surgeon <lb/>ought always to endeavour to
            bring the <w part="I">chil-</w><lb/><w part="F">dren</w> alive.</q> Upon which the
          Doctor makes the <lb/>following moſt inſolent remark, <q >And therefore
            <lb/>undertake what he can ſafely perform, and <lb/>what he cannot, leave to others that
            may,</q>
          <lb/>(pray who be they, Doctors, Apothecaries, <w part="I">Sha-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >vers</w>, or Noſtrum-Mongers?) <q >for life is not to <lb/>be played with.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Is</hi> not the good which Surgeons do their patients
          <lb/>as evident as the Sun? E. G. When they cut for the <lb/>ſtone, when they perforate
          the ſcull, reduce a <w part="I">luxa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, &amp;c. neither of
          which can be affected only by the <lb/>ſtrength of nature. But as the learned and honeſt
            <lb/><hi rend="sc">Baglivi</hi> frankly owns, <q >It's often doubtful whether
            <lb/>the cure, ſuppoſed to be performed even by <w part="I">Phyſi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >cians</w> of the firſt rank, was moſtly owing to <w part="I">na-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ture</w>, or the medicines, &amp;c. which they directed.</q>
          <lb/>E.G. "In fevers, ſmall pox, conſumptions, &amp;c." <lb/>What ground had he then to
          charge the Surgeons with <lb/>playing with life? The Doctor owns, pag. 14. <q >That
            <lb/>Surgeons only practiſe Midwiſery in France;</q>
          <lb/>and ſo they do, or ought to do, every where elſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> how far the Doctor went out of his own
          <lb/>ken, when he talked to Surgeons in ſuch a <w part="I">magi-</w><pb xml:id="page_27"
            n="22"/><lb/><w part="F">ſterial</w> and dictatorial way, in matters merely <w part="I"
            >chi-</w><lb/><w part="F">rurgical</w>, the three following caſes will evidently
          <lb/>demonſtrate. Caſe 1. Mr. Mauriceau, pag. 344. <lb/>ſays, <q >That children's
            gums ought to be cut <lb/>with a Lancet, tho' Nurſes ſometimes do it with <lb/>their
            Nails.</q> Yet our commentator ſays, <q >A <lb/>thin groat <hi rend="italic">(a
              ſmall piece of ſilver)</hi> is as good or <lb/>better than either.</q> Whence it's
          evident, our <lb/>tranſlator was only a Doctor. Notwithſtanding he <lb/>takes upon him to
          direct the Surgeons in ſuch an <lb/>imperious and dictatorial way; yet in this <w part="I"
            >obſerva-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, he betrays himſelf, and plainly ſhews, he
          <lb/>did not underſtand this very little part of Surgery, <lb/>even ſo well as the very
          Nurſes. The method he <lb/>propoſes is ſo far from being better than <w part="I"
            >Mauri-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceau's</w>, he takes upon him ſo freely and publickly
          <lb/>to correct, that it is worſe than that uſed by the <lb/>old women, as will appear at
          ſight, to every <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">per</w> judge. Caſe 2. Mr. Mauriceau,
          pag. 227. <lb/>ſays, When by the firſt faſtning of the Crotchet, <lb/><q >the head
            is drawn a little lower, you may looſen <lb/>it out of the firſt place, to faſten it
            further up, <lb/>that ſtronger hold may be taken and ſo <w part="I">ſuc-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ceſſively</w> removing and faſtening of it till the head <lb/>is quite born,
            &amp;c. Dr. Chamberlen, "This is <lb/>needleſs and dangerous, in caſe Crotchets be uſed,
            <lb/>unleſs they loſe their hold.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Can</hi> any thing expoſe a Man's judgment more
          <lb/>than finding fault in the wrong place? Would not <lb/>this remark convince any Man
          that he had never uſed <lb/>a Crotchet, nay, that he did not know how to uſe <lb/>it? The
          Doctor himſelf allows, that Crotchets are <lb/>abſolutely neceſſary in ſome caſes, and
          conſidering <pb xml:id="page_28" n="23"/><lb/>his large ſhare of practice, it's impoſſible
          but <lb/>ſome of theſe very caſes muſt fall in his way. <lb/>Pray what did he do then? Did
          he uſe the Crotchet <lb/>himſelf? or did he ſend for a Surgeon to uſe it for <lb/>him?
          Caſe 3. Of a violent Flooding. Mr. <w part="I">Mauri-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceau</w>, pag.
          89. <q >The woman being put into a <lb/>proper poſture, the Surgeon having well
            greaſed <lb/>his hand, introduces the end of his fingers into <lb/>the mouth of the
            womb, then opens them <w part="I">gent-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> to dilate it,</q> (i.
          e. by little and little, <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w part="F">out</w> either great
          violence or hurry,) <q >wide enough <lb/>to admit his whole hand; then, if the <w
              part="I">mem-</w><lb/><w part="F">branes</w> are not broke, let him break them; then,
            <lb/>tho' the Head preſents, let him ſearch for the feet, <lb/>and draw it forth by
            them, becauſe there is <w part="I">bet-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> hold, and more eaſy
            to deliver by them, <lb/>than by the head, or any other part of the <lb/>body.</q> Dr.
          Chamberlen, <q >Without it could <lb/>be done without hooks, as mentioned in the
            <lb/>preface of the tranſlator.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>IF this is not puzzling the cauſe, if this is <lb/>not amuſing and
          confounding people inſtead of <lb/>inſtructing them, pray what can be called <lb/>ſo? Is
          not bringing the child out by the feet, as <lb/>Mr. Mauriceau directs, bringing it out
          without <lb/>hooks? Beſides, don't every body know, that it <lb/>may be quicker brought
          away by the feet than by <lb/>the head; and that the ſooner the woman is <w part="I"
            >deli-</w><lb/><w part="F">vered</w>, the ſooner the flooding will ſtop? Is not
          <lb/>this making good, bad? Is not this finding fault <lb/>where there is none? Don't this
          prove that <lb/>Mr. Mauriceau was a good and faithful Surgeon, <lb/>and that Chamberlen
          was only a — Doctor. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_29" n="24"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Thus</hi>, upon the whole, I think it's evident,
          <lb/>that Dr. Chamberlen's main deſign, in his preface, <lb/>and notes upon Mr.
          Mauriceau's book, was to <w part="I">puz-</w><lb/><w part="F">zle</w>, rather than
          inſtruct the Midwomen or <w part="I">Mid-</w><lb/><w part="F">men</w>, to perſuade them,
          that he, and the reſt of <lb/>the Noſtrum-mongers, could ſerve them better <lb/>than any
          other artiſts; and to repreſent Phyſicians, <lb/>tho' unacquainted with almoſt every other
          part of <lb/>Surgery, as fitter perſons to deliver women in <w part="I">la-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">bour</w> than Surgeons, &amp;c. </p>
        <p rend="indent hanging"><lb/>In 1734. Dr. HODY publiſhed 225 Caſes in <w part="I"
            >Mid-</w><lb/><w part="F">wifery</w>, written ſome years before by the late <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">genious</w> and experienced Mr. <hi rend="sc">William <w
              part="I">Gif-</w><lb/><w part="F">fard</w></hi>, Surgeon and Man-midwife. In which he
          <lb/>has given the following account of the <hi rend="sc"><w part="I">Igno-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">rance</w></hi> of the Midwomen, and its fatal <w part="I">conſe-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">quences</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case I.</hi>
          <q ><hi rend="dc(3)">I</hi> Was fetched to the wife of a <w part="I"
              >chair-</w><lb/><w part="F">man</w>, and found one arm of the <lb/>child ſunk down
            without the outer orifice, and <lb/>the ſhoulder and ſide ſo engaged, and ſunk <lb/>ſo
            low, that I could neither return the arm, nor <lb/>with all my ſtrength move the other
            parts to <lb/>fetch it by the feet. Another Man-midwife<lb/> — had been there before me,
            who at firſt <lb/>would not attempt any thing without a ſum of <lb/>money was laid down;
              <hi rend="italic">(a great piece of <w part="I">inhu-</w><lb/><w part="F">manity</w>
              too many are guilty of,)</hi> but upon <w part="I">aſſu-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >rances</w> that he ſhould be paid, he worked upon <lb/>the poor woman, and left her
            in a worſe <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">dition</w> than he found her. (Thus you
            ſee <w part="I">Mid-</w><pb xml:id="page_30" n="25"/><lb/><w part="F">men</w> are not
            all witches any more than the <lb/>Midwomen.) However this was the ſtate I <lb/>found
            her in, which gave me occaſion to <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">primand</w> the
            Midwife, telling her ſhe had not <lb/>ſent for help in time, and not till ſhe had <w
              part="I">work-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> upon her, which had occaſioned thoſe parts
            <lb/>to be funk ſo low, and ſo ſtrongly engaged, <lb/>that I could neither return the
            arm, nor paſs <lb/>my hand (the whole paſſage being ſtopped up <lb/>on every ſide) to
            fetch it by the feet; which <lb/>might have been very eaſily done had I been <lb/>ſent
            for in time. The caſe being ſo deſperate <lb/>at firſt, I was at a loſs where to begin:
            Her <lb/>pulſe was very languid and low, and ſhe was in <lb/>cold ſweats, ſo that I
            fear'd ſhe would die <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w> the fatigue and pain
            ſhe muſt of neceſſity <lb/>undergo. Then he twiſted off the arm, and <lb/>with great
            difficulty extracted the reſt, of the <lb/>infant with his Crotchet; yet after all this
            <lb/>woman recovered.</q> Q. 1. Whether one in <lb/>fifty recovers after ſuch a job? Q.
          2. Whether <lb/>this bad poſture of the child, the great <w part="I">ſuffer-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ing</w> and danger of the mother, might not have <lb/>been prevented, nay, and
          the child's life ſaved, <lb/>had a skilful Midwoman attended? </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case II.</hi>
          <q >The child was born dead, which <lb/>is generally the fate of thoſe children
            whoſe <lb/>Placenta offers firſt,</q> (Madam du Tertre, head <lb/>Midwoman in the Hôtel
          Dieu at <hi rend="sc">Paris</hi>, and <w part="I">Au-</w><lb/><w part="F">thor</w> of one
          of the beſt books on this ſubject, <w part="I">pub-</w><lb/><w part="F">liſhed</w> in
          1677. ſays, the Placenta offering before <lb/>the child, is the moſt certain ſign of its
          being <pb xml:id="page_31" n="26"/><lb/>dead,<note place="bottom" n="*">* <q
              rend="size(0.5)">Entre les ſignes qui nous font connoiſtre que l'enfant eſt <lb/>mort,
              le plus certain eſt lorſque l'arriere-fais eſt ſorty avant <lb/>luy. <bibl
                rend="italic">Inſtruction familiere, &amp;c. </bibl></q>
          </note>) <q >if a proper perſon be not at hand to <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">liver</w> them immediately.</q> Who can be ſo <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">per</w>, who is ſo likely to be in the way as a <w part="I">skil-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ful</w> Midwoman? But as long as they want skill to <lb/>perform it, the child
          muſt die before a Midman <lb/>can be brought. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case III</hi>. <q >The Midwife informed me, that
            <lb/>the navel-ſtring was thruſt into the Vagina, <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >yond</w> the Os internum, but could not inform <lb/>me what other part preſented.
            Many <w part="I">Mid-</w><lb/><w part="F">wives</w> are ignorant of the method of <hi
              rend="sc">touching</hi>, <lb/>which oftentimes occaſions very great <w part="I"
              >misfor-</w><lb/><w part="F">tunes</w> both to mother and infant, and ſometimes
            <lb/>is the death of both, but moſt commonly of <lb/>the child <hi rend="italic">(Is not
              deſtroying one bad enough?)</hi>
            <lb/>which being for ſome time engaged in a wrong <lb/>poſture, and the waters gone off,
            the Uterus is <lb/>ſo collapſed, it gives great trouble to the <w part="I"
              >opera-</w><lb/><w part="F">tor</w>, much more pain to the mother, and very
            <lb/>often, as I ſaid before, occaſions the death of <lb/>the infant; all which may be
            prevented if a <lb/>skilful operator is ſent for in time.</q> But much <lb/>better, if a
          skilful operatrix attended. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case IV</hi>. <q >I viſited a woman who had been
            <lb/>ſome days in labour, and the Midwife affirmed <lb/>that the waters run off the
            preceding day, and <lb/>that ſhe thought a foot preſented, but upon my <lb/>touching I
            found it to be the hand bent <w part="I">back-</w><pb xml:id="page_32" n="27"/><lb/><w
              part="F">wards</w> in the paſſage, and protruded out of the <lb/>inner orifice up to
            the ſhoulder.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case V</hi>. <q >The Midwife told me that one
            <lb/>hand and the arm was ſliped down into the <w part="I">Va-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >gina</w>, and that it had laid ſo for ſome hours, <lb/>and the waters, ſhe ſaid, were
            gone of ſeveral <lb/>hours before the hand was protruded. I <w part="I"
              >rebuk-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> her (as he very well might) for not ſending
            <lb/>ſooner; ſhe alledged, for excuſe, that her labour <lb/>might have ſucceeded in
            time: Then I told her <lb/>that it was impoſſible, in the poſture the child
            <lb/>preſented, it could ever be born.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case VI.</hi>
          <q >The Midwife told me, that one <lb/>child had been born, and another remained <w
              part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">hind</w>, that the membranes, with the waters, <w
              part="I">preſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſed</w> forwards, and were very tight at every
            <lb/>pain; but the woman having flooded very much <lb/>after the birth of the firſt
            child, the Midwife <lb/>could not tell me what part of the ſecond <w part="I"
              >pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſented</w>. I Blamed the Midwife for not ſending <lb/>for me
            ſooner, &amp;c. Whereupon I paſſed up my <lb/>hand, and found the membranes much <w
              part="I">extend-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> with the waters, and the legs of the
            infant <lb/>(which the Midwife knew nothing of, not <lb/>knowing how to touch) preſſed
            forward into <lb/>the Vagina.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case VII.</hi>
          <q >Upon examining the Midwife, <lb/>at my firſt coming, how the child preſented,
            ſhe <lb/>anſwer'd, &amp;c. This convinced me of the <w part="I">Mid-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >wife's</w> ignorance in the method and knowledge <lb/>of touching, and I could wiſh
            it was not too <lb/>common. I have generally found them <w part="I">igno-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">rant</w> in this point, which often occaſions the <pb xml:id="page_33" n="28"
            /><lb/>death both of Mother and infant,</q> (Why did <lb/>not he do his endeavour to
          amend this great evil? <lb/>What ſignifies finding fault with them in every <lb/>page
          without attempting a remedy?) <q >and gives <lb/>a great deal of pain to the
            Man-midwife.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case VIII.</hi>
          <q >I was ſent for to a woman, <lb/>whoſe child was brought out to the ſhoulders,
            <lb/>where it had ſtuck for about three hours; the <lb/>Midwife not knowing how to draw
            out the <lb/>arms and the head. They had alſo ſent for <w part="I">ano-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ther</w> Midwife before I got there, but ſhe knew <lb/>not how to extricate
            the child out of this ſnare. <lb/>Then I extracted it, but the child was dead,
            <lb/>which could not otherwiſe be expected, ſince it <lb/>had been ſo long held in that
            poſture.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case IX.</hi>
          <q >I firſt enquired of the Midwife, <lb/>how matters ſtood in general, but ſhe
            giving me <lb/>no ſatisfactory account, I deſcended to <w part="I">particu-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">lars</w>. I then asked her if the membranes were <lb/>broke, and if ſo, how
            long before; to which ſhe <lb/>could not give a ready anſwer, ſo that I found <lb/>her
            thoroughly Ignorant. I next enquired how <lb/>long the navel-ſtring had been fallen
            down; <lb/>Her anſwer was, ſeveral hours. I told her, <lb/>i. e. rebuked her,
            &amp;c.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case X. </hi>I was ſent for to a perſon, whoſe<q 
            ><lb/>child was born, and the Placenta left behind. <lb/>Upon my coming there, the
            Midwife told me <lb/>that ſhe had attempted, by all methods ſhe was <lb/>miſtreſs of, to
            fetch it, but could not ſucceed: <lb/>Wherefore, conſidering the length of time, from
            <lb/>the bringing of the Foetus to my coming, I thought <lb/>no more time ought to be
            loſt; and <w part="I">immediate-</w><pb xml:id="page_34" n="29"/><lb/><w part="F">ly</w>
            put up my hand, and found the inner orifice <lb/>ſo much contracted, that at firſt I
            could ſcarce <lb/>paſs up the ends of my two fore-fingers, but <w part="I"
              >af-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> ſome time I dilated it ſo much, that I was <lb/>able
            to paſs my hand, &amp;c.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><q ><hi rend="sc">This</hi> Caſe will ſhew us, what
            difficulties <lb/>people often fall into from the Ignorance of the <lb/>Midwife, in not
            knowing how to paſs their <lb/>hands as ſoon as the Foetus is protruded.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XI</hi><q >I found the Scalp was extended
            <lb/>and ſeparated from the Cranium. This I judged <lb/>to have proceeded from the
            Midwife's top rudely <lb/>handling the head.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XII. </hi><q >The Midwife being very <w
              part="I">igno-</w><lb/><w part="F">norant</w>, was not able to give me a ſatisfatory
            <lb/>account of the caſe. I found the Labia Pudendi <lb/>very much ſwell'd, &amp;c.
            wherefore Irebuked the <lb/>Midwife, telling her, that when ſhe had done <lb/>all the
            miſchief ſhe could, then ſhe perſuaded <lb/>them to ſend for me: This is a common fault
            <lb/>amongſt them, not being willing to have <lb/>further help, 'till matters are come
            to the laſt <lb/>extremity.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XIII.</hi>
          <q >I thereupon paſſed up my hand <lb/>into the Vagina, and found the parts
            ſomewhat <lb/>ſwell'd, by the Midwife's too rudely handling <lb/>them.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XIV.</hi>
          <q >Upon paſſing my hand, I <lb/>found the Midwife had been too buſy, for <lb/>the
            arm was ſunk low, and much ſwell'd; not <lb/>knowing better, ſhe had endeavoured to
            bring <lb/>it away in the poſture it preſented; whereupon <lb/>I Rebuked her, telling
            her, that by her ſo doing <pb xml:id="page_35" n="30"/><lb/>ſhe had made bad work, and
            ſhew'd her, that <lb/>it was almoſt <hi rend="italic">(he might have ſaid
              altogether)</hi>
            <lb/>impoſſible to bring it away in the poſture it <lb/>came in. </q></p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XV.</hi>
          <q >This caſe ſhould be a caution to <lb/>Midwives to ſend for help in time, when a
            child <lb/>comes Footling, and not to venture (unleſs <lb/>they are very skilful) to
            bring it forwards.</q>
          <lb/>But whoſe fault is it they are not all very skilful? <lb/>Why are they ſuffered to
          practiſe, who are not <lb/>very skilful? Would not Madam du Tertre have <lb/>laughed at
          any Man, who ſhould have told her, <lb/>ſhe muſt not venture to bring a child forwards
          <lb/>when the feet preſents? Are not our women as <w part="I">ca-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >pable</w> of being taught as the French women? </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XVI.</hi>
          <q >I came, and the Midwife <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> a Novice in
            her profeſſion, was not capable <lb/>of giving proper directions. She ſhould have
            <lb/>adviſed the labouring woman to have, kept <lb/>back, as much as poſſible, her
            throws, and not <lb/>forced downwards, and ſhe ought to have paſſed <lb/>her hand up,
            and preſſed againſt the child's <lb/>buttocks, to retain it from ſlipping down, <w
              part="I">when-</w><lb/><w part="F">ever</w> the pains preſſed forwards;</q> (<hi
            rend="italic">or, which <lb/>would have been much more to the purpoſe, put up <lb/>her
            hand, laid hold of the feet, and brought it <w part="I">a-</w><lb/><w part="F">way</w>
            by them;</hi>) <q >but the Midwife neglecting to <lb/>give this advice, or to act
            in this manner, I <lb/>found the hip of the infant, with the Scrotum, <lb/>ſunk low into
            the Vagina, and ſtrongly engaged <lb/>between the bones of the Pelvis, ſo that I could
            <lb/>not move it by any means.</q>
        </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_36" n="31"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XVII.</hi>
          <q >I found things very bad, which <lb/>in a great meaſure proceded from the
            Ignorance <lb/>of the Midwife; I therefore rebuked her for her <lb/>careleſſneſs,
            &amp;c.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XVIII.</hi>
          <q >I enquired of the Midwife, <lb/>if the waters were broke, how long they had
            <lb/>been gone off, and what part preſented; She <lb/>told me that the waters had been
            run off ſome <lb/>hours, but what part preſented ſhe knew not. I <lb/>ſoon perceived her
            Ignorance; for upon paſſing <lb/>my ſingers, I found the membranes protruded <lb/>by the
            waters beyond the Os internum, into <lb/>the Vagina, about the bigneſs os a pig's <w
              part="I">blad-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w>, ſo that the waters were not gone off, as
            <lb/>ſhe ſaid, for ſome hours, and being Ignorant of <lb/>the method of touching, it was
            impoſſible ſhe <lb/>could tell what part preſented.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XIX.</hi>
          <q >I was call'd about ſix in the <lb/>morning, and the Midwife told me, that the
            <lb/>Membranes were broke, and the waters flowed <lb/>off about twelve o'clock at night,
            and that the <lb/>firſt part which preſented was the elbow. I <w part="I">Re-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">buked</w> her for ſtaying ſo long before ſhe ſent <lb/>for help, and I ſoon
            diſcovered her Ignorance; <lb/>for ſhe told me that ſhe had delivered ſeveral
            <lb/>children where the arm came firſt, in the ſame <lb/>poſture, and ſome were born
            alive, &amp;c. The <lb/>child was born dead, which I imagined to <w part="I"
              >pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceed</w> from its lying ſo long in the poſture I <lb/>found
            it, and the Midwife's too rudely pulling <lb/>the arm when it firſt fell into the
            paſſage, in <lb/>hopes, as ſhe thought, to have brought away <lb/>the child in the
            poſture it preſented. By her <pb xml:id="page_37" n="32"/><lb/>violent pulling ſhe had
            almoſt ſeparated the arm <lb/>from the ſhoulder.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><q ><hi rend="sc">This</hi> is one amongſt the Many <w part="I"
              >inconve-</w><lb/><w part="F">niences</w> that occur from the ignorance of <w part="I"
              >Mid-</w><lb/><w part="F">wives</w>: Had I been ſent for as ſoon as the <w part="I"
              >mem-</w><lb/><w part="F">branes</w> were broke, and before the ſhoulder, by
            <lb/>reiterated pains, was ſo ſtrongly locked between <lb/>the bones of the Pelvis, moſt
            of my trouble, <lb/>and the child's life might have been ſaved.</q>
          <lb/>Undoubtedly! or if ſhe had had skill enough to <lb/>have done it herſelf. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XX.</hi>
          <q >When I came I found the child <lb/>protruded to the hips, which hung out beyond
            <lb/>the Labia Pudendi, the Midwife told me that <lb/>the waters run off about an hour
            before; that <lb/>the child preſented with the feet firſt, and that <lb/>when ſhe had
            brought it to the buttocks, it ſtuck <lb/>there, nor could ſhe bring it any further. I
              <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">buked</w> her for not ſending at firſt, when ſhe
            <lb/>found it to preſent in a wrong poſture; but <lb/>ſhe in excuſe, as is uſual amongſt
            them, told me, <lb/>that ſhe had brought out many children offering <lb/>in that
            poſture.</q> (<hi rend="italic">She muſt indeed have been a <lb/>very ordinary Midwife
            if ſhe had not.</hi>) <q >The child <lb/>from its having lain ſome time ſo
            preſſed, was <lb/>dead, which, I told her, was very probably <w part="I">ow-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ing</w> to her neglect, in not ſending ſooner, when <lb/>ſhe was ſatisfied
            the child preſented wrong.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XXI.</hi>
          <q >Upon examination of the child's <lb/>head, I found a Tumour, about the bigneſs
            of <lb/>a pigeon's egg, on its upper part, ariſing, as I <lb/>judged, from the Midwife's
            too rudely <w part="I">hand-</w><lb/><w part="F">ling</w> it, or (<hi rend="italic"
              >which is much more probable</hi>) it's <pb xml:id="page_38" n="33"/><lb/>lying ſo
            long locked between the bones.</q> But <lb/>it's their way to haul the Midwomen in, head
          and <lb/>ſhoulders, guilty or not guilty. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XXII.</hi>
          <q >I Rebuked the Midwife for <lb/>not ſending ſooner, telling her the danger ſhe
            <lb/>had expoſed the poor woman to by her delay: <lb/>She in excuſe, anſwered me, that
            ſhe had never <lb/>had ſuch an accident before, altho' ſhe had been <lb/>a Midwife above
            eleven years; however I found <lb/>ſhe was very ignorant.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XXIII.</hi>
          <q >This caſe (viz. the Placenta <lb/>being leſt behind, occaſioned a flooding)
            ſhould <lb/>be a caution to all Midwives not to delay <w part="I">ſend-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ing</w> early, and not depend too far on their own <lb/>skill and experience;
            for it's plain this poor <lb/>woman died a Martyr to either the Midwife's
            <lb/>Ignorance, or vain Opinion of her own Self-<lb/>ſufficiency, which too much
            prevails amongſt <lb/>them.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XXIV.</hi>
          <q >Paſſing my hand into the <lb/>Vagina, I found the arm bent and broke, <lb/>by
            the Midwife's too rudely handling it. The <lb/>child was born dead, which proceeded, as
            I <lb/>judged, from its long lying in ſo uneaſy a <lb/>poſture, and from the Midwife's
            Ignorance, in <lb/>not knowing how to keep up the arm, &amp;c.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XXV.</hi>
          <q >Men-midwives frequently find <lb/>great difficulty in paſſing their hand into
            the <lb/>womb, when, from the Ignorance of the <w part="I">Mid-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >wife</w>, they are obliged to fetch the Placenta after <lb/>the child has been born
            ſome time, the Os <w part="I">inter-</w><lb/><w part="F">num</w> being upon theſe
            occaſions generally very <pb xml:id="page_39" n="34"/><lb/>much contracted.</q> Pray is
          not a Midwoman's <lb/>hand eaſier paſſed at firſt, than a Midman's at laſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XXVI.</hi>
          <q >One foot preſented; but the <lb/>Midwife (thinking herſelf capable of
            delivering <lb/>the woman, being in her own opinion very Self-<lb/>ſufficient, altho'
            ſhe was very ignorant,) would <lb/>not at firſt ſend for aſſiſtance, &amp;c.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XXVII.</hi>
          <q >As ſoon as the Midwife found <lb/>that the hands preſented, ſhe ſent for me.
            This <lb/>is what Midwives ſeldom do;</q> (<hi rend="italic">a black ſwan
            <lb/>indeed!</hi>) <q >truſting too much to, and depending upon <lb/>their own
            Sufficiency, which very often <w part="I">occa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſions</w> the loſs
            of the child, and ſometimes of the <lb/>mother.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XXVIII.</hi>
          <q >The Midwife's Ignorance, <lb/>in not knowing how to paſs her hand, occaſion'd
            <lb/>this uneaſineſs.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XXIX.</hi>
          <q >This is one among the many <lb/>misfortunes that attend a Man-midwife, when he
            <lb/>he is ſent for too late, proceeding from the <w part="I">neg-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ligence</w>, ſupineneſs, ignorance, or ſelf-ſufficiency <lb/>of the Midwife; which
            laſt prevails in moſt of <lb/>them, and is very often the occaſion of the loſs
            <lb/>either of the mother or child, or ſometimes <lb/>both.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XXX.</hi>
          <q >The Ignorance of the Midwife, <lb/>in not knowing how to keep up the womb from
            <lb/>being forced before the head ſo low into the <w part="I">Va-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >gina</w>, was what added ſo much to my difficulty <lb/>in delivering this woman.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XXXI</hi>. <q >When I came, I found all
            <lb/>but the head was protruded beyond the Labia <lb/>Pudendi, but that ſtuck above,
            altho' the <w part="I">Mid-</w><pb xml:id="page_40" n="35"/><lb/><w part="F">wife</w>
            had pulled ſo ſtrongly, that ſhe had near <lb/>ſeparated the body from the head. The <w
              part="I">Mid-</w><lb/><w part="F">wife</w>, being Ignorant, did not take care to turn
            <lb/>the child's face towards the Spine of the mother <lb/>as the body advanced.
            However, I brought it <lb/>out in a minute's time, this ſurprized all that <lb/>were
            preſent, becauſe the Midwife had been <lb/>working above an hour, without making any
            <lb/>advance. Had I been there early, I might very <lb/>probably have ſaved the life of
            the child, but <lb/>Self-ſufficiency, join'd with an idle Notion that <lb/>they ſuffer
            in their character if they ſend for a <lb/>Man's aſſiſtance, generally prevents moſt <w
              part="I">Mid-</w><lb/><w part="F">wives</w> from ſending early, by which they too
            <lb/>often endanger the lives of both mothers and <lb/>children, and give no ſmall
            trouble to the <w part="I">Man-</w><lb/><w part="F">midwife</w>.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XXXII.</hi>
          <q >The Midwife could not fetch <lb/>the Placenta, for as ſhe was ignorant in the
              <w part="I">me-</w><lb/><w part="F">thod</w> of paſſing her hand into the Uterus, up
            to <lb/>the body of the Placenta, to examine whether it <lb/>adhered to it, ſhe had only
            pulled by the end of <lb/>the ſtring which hung out, and ſo had very <lb/>near broke it
            cloſe to the Placenta; ſhe had <lb/>made no Ligature upon the end of the ſtring,
            <lb/>therefore a Hemorrhage had enſued, and the <lb/>woman had loſt a great quantity of
            blood. <w part="I">Mid-</w><lb/><w part="F">wives</w> very often depend too much upon
            their <lb/>own judgment, and think themſelves <w part="I">Self-ſuffi-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">cient</w>, ſo that they poſtpone ſending for help in <lb/>time, whereby the
            poor women become Victims <lb/>to their Ignorance or Self-conceit.</q>
        </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_41" n="36"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XXXIII</hi>
          <q >The Child's arm preſented <lb/>ſeveral hours before I was ſent for; upon which
            <lb/>I rebuked the Midwife for not ſending ſooner; <lb/>but ſhe, to juſtify herſelf, had
            the Aſſurance to <lb/>to tell me, that ſhe had brought out ſeveral <lb/>children
            preſenting in that manner; whereupon I <lb/>ſhewed her the impoſſibility of it, and
            adviſed<lb/>her for the future always to ſend for help, as <lb/>ſoon as ſhe ſhould find
            the hand to preſent firſt, <lb/>and not, by pulling the hand, draw it further <lb/>down,
            and engage the ſhoulder in the paſſage, <lb/>as ſhe had now done.</q> Pray would it not
          have <lb/>been much more ſeaſonable advice to have ſhewn <lb/>her how to paſs her hand,
          and get hold of the <lb/>feet, &amp;c. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XXXIV.</hi>
          <q >The Nurſe came and told <lb/>me the child was born, but the Midwife was
            <lb/>ſoiled in her attempts to fetch away the Placenta. <lb/>I went, and found the
            Midwife was both <w part="I">igno-</w><lb/><w part="F">rant</w> of the cauſe of its
            being retained, and the <lb/>method of paſſing the hand to extract it; yet <lb/>I
            brought it away whole in leſs than half a <w part="I">mi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nute's</w>
            time, which much ſurprized both the <w part="I">wo-</w><lb/><w part="F">man</w> and the
            by-ſtanders, the Midwife having <lb/>ſpent ſo much time without being able to effect
            <lb/>it.</q> Sometimes a Man gets more credit by <w part="I">do-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ing</w> nothing than by a difficult operation! </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XXXV.</hi>
          <q >The Man-midwife's being <lb/>ſent for ſo late, too often proceeds from the <w
              part="I">Igno-</w><lb/><w part="F">rance</w> or Self-ſufficiency of the Midwife, (<hi
              rend="italic">but <lb/>oftener from the modeſty of the women, covetouſneſs, <lb/>or
              real poverty of the men, &amp;c.</hi>) who either <lb/>not knowing how to behave in
            difficult caſes, <pb xml:id="page_42" n="37"/><lb/>or fearing ſhe ſhould ſuffer in her
            character <lb/>ſhould ſhe deſire aſſiſtance, puts off the calling <lb/>in of a
            Man-midwife to the laſt extremity, ſo <lb/>that the mother and child too often become <w
              part="I">vic-</w><lb/><w part="F">tims</w> either to her negligence or ignorance.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XXXVI.</hi>
          <q >The Midwife depending <lb/>upon her own Sufficiency, (altho' ſhe was very
            <lb/>ignorant) had let the child advance too far, <lb/>without taking care to turn and
            bring the face <lb/>backwards towards the Os Sacrum, and had for <lb/>ſome time
            endeavoured to bring out the head, <lb/>but to no purpoſe; wherefore I was at laſt ſent
            <lb/>for, and found the parts very dry, and <w part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >what</w> ſwelled, by the rude Handling of the <lb/>Midwife.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XXXVII.</hi>
          <q >The woman had been in <lb/>labour forty-eight hours; the Midwife being
            <lb/>very Ignorant, could neither tell me how the <lb/>Child preſented, nor at what time
            the <w part="I">mem-</w><lb/><w part="F">branes</w> broke, but anſwered me, according to
            <lb/>her dialect, that it was a dry labour.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XXXVIII.</hi>
          <q >The child was brought <lb/>into the world all but the head, where it had
            <lb/>ſtuck two or three hours before I came; the <lb/>Midwife being very Ignorant, was
            not able to do <lb/>the buſineſs herſelf, nor would ſhe ſend for <w part="I"
              >aſſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtance</w> in time, ſo that the child was loſt, and
            <lb/>the mother narrowly eſcaped.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XXXIX.</hi>
          <q >The Midwife, in <w part="I">attempt-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> to bring away
            the Placenta, had inverted <lb/>the Uterus, for I found the whole body of the
            <lb/>Uterus, with the Placenta, adhering to it's <w part="I">Fun-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >dus</w>, hanging out beyond the Labia Pudendi; <pb xml:id="page_43" n="38"/><lb/>I
            Rebuked the Midwife for not ſending <lb/>ſooner, and told her, that ſhe, thro' her <w
              part="I">Igno-</w><lb/><w part="F">rance</w>, was the immediate cauſe of this woman's
            <lb/>death. Before I examined her, the Midwife <lb/>told me, that the Placenta was
            partly brought <lb/>out, being ignorant that ſhe had alſo pulled out <lb/>the womb,
            &amp;c.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>CASE XL. <q >But the Midwife by pulling the <lb/>Navel-ſtring
            too rudely, had broke it off near <lb/>the Placenta, which was left in the womb. <lb/>As
            ſoon as I came, I paſſed up my hand, where <lb/>I found the Placenta entirely ſeparated
            from the <lb/>Uterus, and partly protruded into the Vagina, <lb/>ſo that I readily
            brought it away, and in ſo ſhort <lb/>a time, that the people that were preſent were
            <lb/>greatly ſurprized. Had the Midwife <w part="I">under-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtood</w>
            how to have paſſed her hand, ſhe might <lb/>eaſily have brought away the burden before;
            <lb/>and for want of this knowledge, ſome women <lb/>fall into violent floodings, whence
            faintings, <lb/>convulſions, and death.</q> A wonderful <w part="I">opera-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tion</w> indeed! But does ſhe deſerve the Name of a <lb/>Midwoman who could not
          have extracted it as <lb/>quick as he? </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XLI.</hi>
          <q >Had I been ſent for before the <lb/>membranes were broke, the waters paſſed
            off, <lb/>the arm ſlipped down, and the back part of the <lb/>ſhoulder ſo rivetted, I
            might not only have <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerved</w> the Child, but
            prevented the Mother's <lb/>ſuffering ſo much pain, and have likewiſe ſaved <lb/>myſelf
            much fatigue and trouble.</q> Without <lb/>doubt! </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_44" n="39"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It's</hi> too true, that many Midwives are <w part="I"
            >Igno-</w><lb/><w part="F">rant</w> "of the method of touching," (<hi rend="italic">and
            it's as true <lb/>they might with very little trouble be taught;</hi>) <q >and
            <lb/>therefore are incapable of judging in what <w part="I">man-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ner</w> the Child preſents, until an arm, or ſome <lb/>other part is protruded into
            the Vagina, which <lb/>is often ſo locked between the bones of the <w part="I"
              >Pel-</w><lb/><w part="F">vis</w>, that it is ſcarce poſſible to remove it; and
            <lb/>too often they depend ſo much upon their own <lb/>ſufficiency, and delay ſending
            for aſſiſtance in <lb/>time, that both the mother and child, but more <lb/>frequently
            the latter, die martyrs to their <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſumption</w>.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XLII. </hi><q >I was ſent for about two in
            <lb/>the morning, the Midwife had delivered the <lb/>Child about ſix the evening before,
            but not <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> able, notwithſtanding all her
            endeavours, to <lb/>bring away the Placenta, ſhe at laſt left the <lb/>woman, telling
            her, that it would in time come <lb/>away, and that ſhe had known it retained <w
              part="I">four-</w><lb/><w part="F">teen</w> days without any inconveniency; but as
            <lb/>this was a doctrine I was a ſtranger to, and <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ing</w> on the contrary well ſatisfied that <w part="I">inconve-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >niencies</w> might attend, ſhould it not be ſpeedily <lb/>drawn away; therefore
            —.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Case XLIII.</hi>
          <q >The child's arm was ſlipped <lb/>out into the Vagina, which, as ſoon as the <w
              part="I">Mid-</w><lb/><w part="F">wife</w> obſerved, who was firſt ſent for, ſhe <w
              part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſed</w> that a Man-midwife ſhould be ſent for,
            <lb/>telling thoſe that were preſent, that it was not a <lb/>Midwife's buſineſs;
            whereupon another Midwife <lb/>was ſent for, who pretended to do the work of a
            <lb/>Man-midwife, and at firſt gave them aſſurances <pb xml:id="page_45" n="40"
            /><lb/>that ſhe would deliver her, but after ſhe had <lb/>worked upon her for half an
            hour, or longer, <lb/>puting her into ſeveral poſtures, as kneeling, <lb/>ſtanding,
            &amp;c. ſhe left her in a much worſe <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">dition</w>
            than ſhe found her; for being ignorant of <lb/>the method of delivery, when a child
            offered in <lb/>the manner this did, ſhe truly had endeavoured <lb/>to draw the child
            forward in the ſame poſture it <lb/>preſented, whereby ſhe had drawn the hand out,
            <lb/>and part of the arm, beyond the Labia Pudendi, <lb/>and almoſt ſeparated it at the
            ſhoulder. The <lb/>temerity, joined to the ignorance of this <w part="I">Mid-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">wife</w>, very much encreaſed the difficulty of <w part="I">lay-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ing</w> her. If I had been ſent for in time, I might <lb/>with much more eaſe
            have delivered the woman, <lb/>and withal have ſaved the Child. I have meet <lb/>with
            ſome Midwives, who have had the <w part="I">igno-</w><lb/><w part="F">rance</w> and
            aſſurance to tell me, that they have <lb/>deliver'd children thus preſenting, without <w
              part="I">turn-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> and bringing them by the feet.</q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="35"/>
    </body>
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="1"/>
  </text>
</TEI>
