<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Hartley: An account of the contribution for making Mrs. Stephens's
          medicines public</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>David Hartley</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">An Account of the CONTRIBUTION for making Mrs. Stephens's Medicines
              public; with some Reasons for it, and Answers to the most Remarkable Objections made
              against it. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">N14987</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N14987"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName/>
              </publisher>
              <date>1738</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">2⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="4"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">National Library of Medicine</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3308586020</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K009425.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: medicine"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_1"/>
      <head rend="italic indent hanging"><lb/>An <hi rend="roman">ACCOUNT</hi> of the <hi
          rend="roman">CONTRIBUTION</hi> for making Mrs. <hi rend="roman">Stephens</hi>'s <lb/><hi
          rend="sc"><hi rend="roman">Medicines</hi></hi> public; with ſome <hi rend="sc"><hi
            rend="roman">Reasons</hi></hi> for it, and <hi rend="sc"><hi rend="roman"
          >Answers</hi></hi> to the <lb/>moſt Remarkable <hi rend="roman">Objections</hi> made
        againſt it. </head>
      <p rend="space"><lb/>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>Decorative frame around the letter "T".</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE falſe Pretences to Methods <lb/>of diſſolving Stones in the <w
          part="I">Uri-</w><lb/><w part="F">nary</w> Paſſages have been ſo many, <lb/>and ſome of
        them ſo pernicious, <lb/>that Phyſicians of Character and <lb/>Experience ſeem for ſome time
        <lb/>to have left off enquiring into the <lb/>Nature and Efficacy of Medicines ſaid to
        diſſolve <lb/>Stones; contenting themſelves with preſcribing <lb/>opiate and lenient
        Remedies, where the Stones <lb/>were ſuppoſed too large to paſs; or adviſing the
        <lb/>Operation for thoſe in the Bladder, if the Age, <lb/>Strength and other Circumſtances
        of the Patient <lb/>made it proper to be attempted. But ſtill the <lb/>thing is not
        impoſſible; the active Principles <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">covered</w> in Stones
        have always afforded ſome <lb/>Hopes to the careful Enquirers into Nature, that <lb/>a ſafe
        Diſſolvent might at laſt be found; and, what <lb/>is above all, Matters of Fact may juſtly
        claim a <lb/>fair Hearing, eſpecially in a Caſe of great <w part="I">Import-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ance</w>. In order to obtain this for Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Stephens</hi>'s
        <lb/>Medicines, I ſome time ago publiſhed a Pamphlet, <lb/>entituled, <hi rend="italic">Ten
          Caſes of Perſons who have taken <lb/>Mrs.</hi> Stephens<hi rend="italic">'s Medicines for
          the Stone; with an <lb/>Abſtract of ſome Experiments, tending to illuſtrate theſe
          <lb/>Caſes.</hi> Since this a Contribution has been begun, <lb/>and is now carried on at
        Mr. <hi rend="italic">Drummond</hi>'s, Banker <lb/>at <hi rend="italic">Charing-croſs,</hi>
        for the raiſing 5000<hi rend="italic">l.</hi> in order to <lb/>purchaſe the Secret from Mrs.
          <hi rend="italic">Stephens;</hi> and his <lb/>Grace the Lord Archbiſhop of <hi
          rend="italic">Canterbury;</hi> the <lb/>Right Honourable the Earl of <hi rend="italic"
          >Godolphin,</hi> Lord <lb/>Privy Seal; his Grace the Duke of <hi rend="italic"
          >Richmond</hi> and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Lenox;</hi> his Grace the Duke of <hi
          rend="italic">Montague;</hi> the <lb/>Right Honourable the Earl of <hi rend="italic"
          >Pembroke;</hi> the <lb/>Right Honourable the Earl of <hi rend="italic">Scarborough;</hi>
        the <lb/>Right Honourable the Lord Viſcount <hi rend="italic">Lonſdale;</hi>
        <lb/>the Right Reverend the Lord Biſhop of <hi rend="italic">Glouceſter;</hi>
        <lb/>the Right Reverend the Lord Biſhop of <hi rend="italic">Oxford;</hi>
        <lb/>the Right Honourable the Lord <hi rend="italic">Baltimore;</hi> the <lb/>Right
        Honourable <hi rend="italic">Arthur Onſlow,</hi> Eſq; Speaker <lb/>of the Houſe of Commons;
        the Right <w part="I">Honour-</w><lb/><w part="F">able</w>
        <hi rend="italic">Stephen Poyntz,</hi> Eſq; and the Honourable <lb/><hi rend="italic">Thomas
          Townſhend,</hi> Eſq; have conſented to become <lb/>Truſtees and Judges between the Public
        and <lb/>Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Stephens,</hi> and have taken Dr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Shaw</hi> and <lb/>Myſelf into their Number. Every 1000<hi rend="italic">l.</hi> as it
        <lb/>ariſes, is to be veſted in <hi rend="italic">South Sea</hi> Annuities, in <lb/>the
        Names of the Truſtees, and when the 5000<hi rend="italic">l.</hi>
        <lb/>is completed, Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Stephens</hi> will diſcover her <w part="I"
          >Me-</w><lb/><w part="F">dicines</w>. They will then be made public, and tried <lb/>in the
        Hoſpitals, in the moſt ſtrict and authentic <lb/>manner, upon Perſons who are to be examined
        by <lb/>the Catheter both before and after taking them. She <lb/>is to have the Intereſt of
        the 5000<hi rend="italic">l.</hi> from the time <lb/>of diſcovering her Medicines, in
        Conſideration of the <lb/>great Profits which ſhe forfeits by diſcovering them; <lb/>and the
        Principal itſelf, whenever it ſhall appear <lb/>to the Truſtees, or a Majority of them, that
        her <lb/>Medicines are able to diſſolve Stones in the <w part="I">Blad-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >der</w>; but if this does not appear, the Principal will <lb/>be returned to the
        Contributors. Theſe are the <lb/>Propoſals which appeared moſt reaſonable and
        <lb/>practicable to the Gentlemen whom I conſulted in <lb/>this Affair; and I beg Leave to
        aſſure the Public, <lb/>that had I known a better Scheme, I ſhould have <lb/>embraced it
        with ſtill more Readineſs; but I hope, <lb/>ſmall Difficulties and Objections will be <w
          part="I">over-</w><lb/><w part="F">looked</w>, and I ſhall now endeavour, in the beſt
        <lb/>manner I can, to remove all ſuch conſiderable <lb/>ones as I have heard mentioned,
        giving firſt ſome <lb/>Reaſons, which ſeem to me to render the preſent <lb/>Propoſals worthy
        of the Encouragement of all <lb/>generous Minds. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It has been a prevailing Notion, that Stones of <lb/>the urinary
        Paſſages cannot be diſſolved by any <lb/>Liquid, except ſuch as is too acrimonious for
        <lb/>the Paſſages themſelves. But this is plainly a Miſtake. <lb/>For Monſieur <hi
          rend="italic">Littre,</hi> a Member of the Royal <w part="I">Aca-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >demy</w> of Sciences at <hi rend="italic">Paris,</hi> found, that the <w part="I"
          >com-</w><lb/><w part="F">mon</w> Waters of <hi rend="italic">Paris,</hi> one of which
        leaves great <lb/>Incruſtations upon the Pipes thro' which it runs, <lb/>diſſolved Stones,
        even without Heat; and there is <lb/>an Account of his Experiments in the Memoirs of
        <lb/>that Academy for the Year 1720. Dr. <hi rend="italic">Hales</hi> alſo <lb/>waſted
        ſeveral Gravel-ſtones both in warm and <lb/>cold Water, and found, that <q rend="quotes"
          >thoſe in warm <lb/>Water diſſolved much ſooner than the other.</q>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hoemaſtaticks,</hi> p. 216. And it appears by the <w part="I"
          >Ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">periments</w> which I have publiſhed, that <hi rend="italic"
          >Thames</hi>
        <lb/>Water, <hi rend="italic">New River</hi> Water, and <hi rend="italic">Pump</hi> Water
        are <lb/>all able to diſſolve a great Variety of Stones, by <lb/>barely ſuffering the Stones
        to lie in them, in a Heat <lb/>equal to that of Urine in the Bladder. The Stones <lb/>I made
        uſe of were taken from the human Bladder, <lb/>ſome of them were exremely hard, they were of
        <lb/>different Sizes, the biggeſt weighing about half <lb/>an Ounce, and waſted away
        entirely. There ſeem <lb/>therefore to be in Stones themſelves ſome <w part="I"
          >Prin-</w><lb/><w part="F">ciples</w>, which have a great Tendency to <w part="I"
          >Putre-</w><lb/><w part="F">faction</w> and Diſſolution, ſince theſe Effects are <w
          part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duced</w> upon them by mere Water only, either cold
        <lb/>or moderately warm. And to ſay that an <w part="I">acrimo-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >nious</w> Liquid is neceſſary for this Purpoſe, is a <lb/>haſty Aſſertion, contrary to
        the plaineſt and moſt <lb/>obvious Experiments. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>However, this does not come home to the <lb/>Point. Tho' a Rill of warm
        Water paſſing thro' <lb/>the urinary Paſſages would indeed waſte all the <lb/>Stones lying
        in them by Degrees, yet this is what <lb/>no Art can procure. The great Queſtion is, <w
          part="I">Whe-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> Urine, which naturally increaſes Stones, as
        <lb/>appears by the daily Experience of thoſe unhappy <lb/>Perſons who are afflicted with
        the Stone, can be ſo <lb/>changed by any Medicines, as to diſſolve Stones <lb/>in the ſame
        manner as common Water has been <lb/>ſhewn to do. In order to determine this Point, I
        <lb/>tried what Effect my own Urine, altered by taking <lb/>the Medicines, would have upon a
        Variety of <lb/>Stones taken from the human Bladder, in a Heat <lb/>equal to that of Urine
        in the Bladder; and found, <lb/>that they were diſſolved entirely by lying in it, <lb/>much
        in the ſame manner as the correſponding <lb/>Pieces in common Water; and at the ſame time
        <lb/>that other correſponding Pieces were increaſed by <lb/>lying in common Urine with the
        ſame Heat. <w part="I">Af-</w><lb/><w part="F">terwards</w> I tried the Urine of another
        Perſon who <lb/>took Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Stephens</hi>'s Medicines, and found that it
        <lb/>had the ſame diſſolving Power as mine, or rather, <lb/>as I gueſſed, one ſomething
        greater; ſo that thoſe <lb/>who take Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Stephens</hi>'s Medicines have
        evidently <lb/>a Liquid running thro' the urinary Paſſages, which <lb/>is a Solvent for
        Stones in a Heat no greater than <lb/>that of thoſe Paſſages. And this is ſuch a <w part="I"
          >Pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſumption</w> in Favour of Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Stephens</hi>'s
        Medicines, <lb/>as few others can pretend to from Theory. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It will probably afford ſome Satisfaction to <lb/>mention what
        Alterations the Urine receives from <lb/>theſe Medicines. Theſe are a volatile putrid Smell;
          <pb xml:id="page_2" n="2"/><lb/>a turbid and milky Appearance at the time of <lb/>making;
        a copious white Sediment, by the falling <lb/>of which the Urine becomes clear, and which
        may <lb/>be dried into a chalky Subſtance; and an alkaline <lb/>Quality, as appears by
        Trials both with the <w part="I">mi-</w><lb/><w part="F">neral</w> and vegetable Acids, and
        alſo with Syrup of <lb/>Violets. Now it is not at all improbable, that <lb/>Urine with theſe
        Properties ſhould firſt loſe its <w part="I">ce-</w><lb/><w part="F">menting</w>, accreting
        Power, and then render the <lb/>Stones, which lie in it, rotten by Degrees. For <lb/>common
        Urine, when it putrefies, diſſolves its own <lb/>Gravel; Wine in corrupting diſſolves its
        own <lb/>Tartar; and the mineral Waters, as Dr. <hi rend="italic">Hales</hi>
        <lb/>has aſſured me, take up their own Sediment, after <lb/>they have been putrefied for
        ſome time. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>But what will and ought to weigh moſt with <lb/>every Body is, that many
        Perſons, who have had <lb/>all the Symptoms of Stones in the Kidneys and <lb/>Bladder, have
        taken theſe Medicines, voided much <lb/>Grit, with many plain Scales and Pieces of Stone,
        <lb/>have become free from all their Complaints, and <lb/>continued ſo. Now tho' it happens,
        that many <lb/>Perſons who have the Stone void Pieces without <lb/>taking any Medicines, yet
        theſe Pieces are <w part="I">gene-</w><lb/><w part="F">rally</w> few in Number, hard when
        voided, and the <lb/>Perſons themſelves continue to have the ſame <lb/>Complaints, becauſe
        the main Body of the Stone <lb/>ſtill remains; whereas the greateſt Part of thoſe <lb/>who
        take Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Stephens</hi>'s Medicines regularly, <w part="I">hav-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ing</w> the true Symptoms of the Stone, void either <lb/>Grit, or Scales, or
        Fragments of Stone, or all, in <lb/>great Quantities, and continue to do ſo, till they
        <lb/>are freed from their Symptoms; that is, as one <lb/>may reaſonably ſuppoſe, from the
        great Quantities <lb/>voided, till the Stone be quite waſted. This is a <lb/>conſtant
        regular Effect, like thoſe of the principal <lb/>Medicines uſed in Phyſic, all which fail
        ſometimes <lb/>thro' the Irregularity or particular Conſtitution of <lb/>the Patient, and
        always require a different Doſe, <lb/>a different Time for taking Effect, or a peculiar
        <lb/>Accommodation, according to the Nature of the <lb/>Caſe. Let theſe common equitable
        Allowances be <lb/>made to Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Stephens</hi>'s Medicines, and the Caſes
        <lb/>of thoſe who have taken them will prove their <lb/>diſſolving Power as ſtrongly, as the
        Virtue of any <lb/>other Medicine can be proved by a like Number <lb/>of Caſes, taken with
        the ſame Advantages and <lb/>Diſadvantages; and without doubt this diſſolving <lb/>Power in
        them will be no more queſtioned ſome <lb/>Years hence, than the anodyne Quality of Opium
        <lb/>is now. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I publiſhed Ten Caſes, but there are many <lb/>more of the ſame kind,
        which I have either ſeen, <lb/>or been well informed about. Each of theſe, ſingly
        <lb/>taken, favours the diſſolving Power of the <w part="I">Medi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >cines</w>; Three or Four taken together become a <lb/>ſtrong Preſumption; but the united
        Force of the <lb/>whole cannot be thought leſs than a full Proof, by <lb/>thoſe who know
        them accurately. It muſt not be <lb/>expected, that theſe Medicines ſhould cure every
        <lb/>one who takes them; ſome cannot take them <w part="I">regu-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >larly</w>, ſome are negligent, and ſome have their <lb/>Kidneys in great meaſure
        deſtroyed, or labour <lb/>under incurable Diſtempers of another kind; and <lb/>beſides this,
        ſome Stones may perhaps be too hard <lb/>to be affected by them; but if they will diſſolve
        <lb/>only the greateſt Part of the Stones of the Kidneys <lb/>and Bladder, they are worthy
        of all <w part="I">Encourage-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w>; and the Evidence for this is as
        great as can <lb/>any way be expected. A Medicine which did <lb/>really diſſolve far the
        greateſt Part of the Stones of <lb/>the Kidneys and Bladder, need not have given
        <lb/>greater Proofs of it in the ſame Number of Trials. <lb/>Nothing more could be expected
        from ſuch a <w part="I">Me-</w><lb/><w part="F">dicine</w>, but that Scales and broken
        Pieces of Stone <lb/>of various Shapes and Sizes, ſhould be voided after <lb/>taking it, in
        ſo ſoft or rotten a State, as to ſhew <lb/>plain Marks of Diſſolution, till at laſt the
        Patient <lb/>was freed from his Complaints. And this is the <w part="I">ge-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">neral</w> Caſe here. The Scales and Pieces voided are <lb/>of all Sizes capable
        of paſſing the <hi rend="italic">Urethra,</hi> every <lb/>way irregular in their Shapes, for
        the moſt part <lb/>ſoft, or at leaſt ſo rotten, as to crumble eaſily, <lb/>have their
        Surfaces white, and often honey-comb'd; <lb/>and, in ſhort, all Appearances anſwer to the <w
          part="I">Expe-</w><lb/><w part="F">riments</w> made upon the Stones with my Urine, and
        <lb/>that of the other Perſon who took the Medicines. <lb/>And beſides this, there is one
        Evidence from the <lb/>Examination by the Catheter, as ſtrong as a ſingle <lb/>one can well
        be. Mr. <hi rend="italic">Holland,</hi> Warder of the <lb/>Tower, had the Symptoms of a
        Stone in the <w part="I">Blad-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w> for Three Years, and was examined
        in <hi rend="italic">No-<lb/>vember</hi> laſt by Mr. <hi rend="italic">Hawkins;</hi>
        Governor <hi rend="italic">William-<lb/>ſon,</hi> Dr. <hi rend="italic">Sandys,</hi> and
        myſelf being preſent. We all <lb/>felt a Stone. He took the Medicines, voided <lb/>many
        Scales and Pieces of Stone, with an entire <lb/>one, as large as could well paſs, and grew
        free from <lb/>all his Complaints, tho' he was driven over the <lb/>Stones in a Hackney
        Coach with the utmoſt <w part="I">Vio-</w><lb/><w part="F">lence</w>. On the 19th of laſt
        Month he was <w part="I">exa-</w><lb/><w part="F">mined</w> again by Mr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Hawkins,</hi> in the Preſence of <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Sandys,</hi> Dr. <hi
          rend="italic">Shaw,</hi> and Mr. <hi rend="italic">Roberts,</hi> when a <lb/>Catheter was
        introduced three different times, and <lb/>he was put into different Poſtures, but no Stone
        <lb/>could be found. And there are ſeveral others, who <lb/>having been found to have Stones
        in the Bladder <lb/>by the Catheter, take the Medicines, void Pieces, <lb/>and are expected
        to be well ſhortly. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>This is in general the Evidence for the <w part="I">diſſolv-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ing</w> Power of theſe Medicines, and I cannot ſee <lb/>what is to be ſaid
        againſt it; but indeed I do not <lb/>know that any thing is ſaid againſt it by thoſe who
        <lb/>are well informed of the Facts. However, it is not <lb/>intended to do more by this
        Evidence, than ſo far <lb/>to engage the Attention and Favour of the World, <lb/>as to raiſe
        the 5000<hi rend="italic">l.</hi> and have the Medicines made <lb/>public. This is deſirable
        without doubt, becauſe <lb/>they have plainly done moſt eminent Service in <lb/>many
        terrible Kidney and Bladder Caſes, where <lb/>the common Practice could do nothing, whether
        <lb/>they diſſolve Stones or no. But Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Stephens</hi> is <lb/>ſo well
        aſſured of their diſſolving Power, that ſhe <lb/>puts all upon that Foundation, and
        particularly <lb/>upon their diſſolving Stones in the Bladder, ſince <lb/>this admits of the
        moſt unqueſtionable Evidence; <lb/>ſhe is content to be entirely without the Reward, if
        <lb/>this Fact be not proved to a Majority of the <w part="I">Tru-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſtees</w>: She is willing and deſirous, that as many <w part="I">Pa-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tients</w> as the Truſtees ſhall think fit, be put into any <lb/>or all of the Hoſpitals,
        that they be examined by <lb/>the Catheter in the ſtricteſt and moſt public <w part="I"
          >man-</w><lb/><w part="F">ner</w>; and if this Evidence does not anſwer, ſhe <lb/>gives up
        all Title to the Reward, and each <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tributor</w> will
        have his Contribution returned. Now <lb/>upon theſe Conditions, eſpecially where there are
        <lb/>ſuch unqueſtionable Judges, a ſlender Probability <lb/>ſeems ſufficient Foundation for
        a Contribution; nay, <lb/>it would not be very improper, if there were no <lb/>Probability
        at all; for this would at leaſt be a <lb/>means of detecting a Pretence which has impoſed
        <lb/>upon many Gentlemen of Worth and Knowledge <lb/>in other Matters; and if there be no
        Remedy but <lb/>the Operation, it is better that this be had early, <lb/>while the Parts are
        ſound, and the Strength entire. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I will now conſider the moſt remarkable <w part="I">Difficul-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ties</w> and Objections which I have heard mentioned. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is ſaid, That a Trial of theſe Medicines by <lb/>the Catheter ought
        to have been made in the <w part="I">Ho-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſpitals</w> before the
        Contribution was propoſed. But <lb/>there are ſeveral Inconveniencies attending this
        <lb/>Method of proceeding. Firſt, Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Stephens</hi> has <lb/>already more
        Perſons who take her Medicines than <lb/>ſhe can make up for conſiſtently with her own
        <lb/>Health, and it would be very hard to leave any of <pb xml:id="page_3" n="3"
        /><lb/>theſe, in order to make up for the Hoſpitals, as <lb/>every body would think in their
        own Caſe. <w part="I">Se-</w><lb/><w part="F">condly</w>, When it was proved in this way,
        that <lb/>Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Stephens</hi>'s Medicines were able to diſſolve <lb/>Stones
        in the Bladder, there would be a Neceſſity <lb/>for another Trial, to know, whether ſhe <w
          part="I">commu-</w><lb/><w part="F">nicated</w> theſe Medicines faithfully; whereas, <w
          part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">cording</w> to the preſent Propoſals, ſhe will have no
        <lb/>Reward unleſs ſhe communicates a Medicine able <lb/>to diſſolve Stones in the Bladder.
        Thirdly, There <lb/>are in all Parts of the World many unhappy <w part="I">Per-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſons</w>, either dying or living in Pain, thro' the <w part="I">Cru-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">elty</w> of this Diſtemper, whoſe Miſery calls for the <lb/>moſt ſpeedy Relief;
        ſo that if theſe Medicines <lb/>ſhould be effectual, their Publication ought not to <lb/>be
        deferred a Moment longer than neceſſary. But <lb/>it would be a conſiderable Time before the
        few <lb/>Trials to be made of theſe Medicines, while kept <lb/>ſecret, could determine
        either way; and this was <lb/>the principal Reaſon for contriving a Method, <lb/>which
        admitted of an immediate Publication. <lb/>Laſtly, The greater Number of Trials made
        <lb/>when the Medicines are known to the World, <lb/>will render the Judgment formed upon
        them <lb/>much more ſatisfactory. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is ſaid, That there is no Streſs to be laid upon <lb/>what is voided,
        becauſe any one would do the ſame <lb/>upon taking the Medicines, whether he had a Stone
        <lb/>or no. But this Objection will vaniſh upon a due <lb/>Attention to the Facts. For the
        Perſons who take <lb/>Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Stephens</hi>'s Medicines void Pieces of Stone,
        <lb/>as evidently ſuch, as if a Stone was broke in a <w part="I">Mor-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tar</w> into Pieces of all Sizes capable of paſſing the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Urethra.</hi> As to the Sediment which falls to the <lb/>Bottom of the Urine, it may
        perhaps be in great<lb/>meaſure the Effect of the Medicines, but there is <lb/>no Evidence
        that it does not alſo contain Stone, <lb/>becauſe no body cares to take the Medicines
        without <lb/>firſt being apprehenſive at leaſt that he has a Stone. <lb/>On the contrary, it
        is probable, that ſome Part of <lb/>this Sediment is Stone in an impalpable Form; for
        <lb/>if the Stone come away in large Pieces, it may much <lb/>rather be voided in an
        impalpable Powder from the <lb/>ſame Cauſe, whatever it be; and many of the <lb/>Stones in
        my Experiments had a white powdery <lb/>Subſtance upon their Surfaces, that might be
        <lb/>rubbed off with the Finger; which has alſo been <lb/>the Caſe with ſome Pieces of Stone
        that have been <lb/>voided. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is ſaid, That theſe Medicines are nothing <lb/>more than Soap. That
        Soap is one Part is very <lb/>plain, but it is as plain, that there is another Part
        <lb/>which is not Soap. Beſides, Soap will not diſſolve <lb/>Stones, and if it would, this
        would be the <w part="I">Inven-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of Mrs. <hi rend="italic"
          >Stephens,</hi> for which ſhe deſerves the <lb/>ſame Reward as for inventing any other
        Solvent. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is ſaid, That theſe Medicines may probably <lb/>force Grit and Gravel
        from the Kidneys, and <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">vent</w> the Growth of Stones,
        but cannot diſſolve <lb/>Stones in the Bladder. But this Objection will alſo <lb/>vaniſh
        upon a due Attention to the Facts. Moſt of <lb/>the Perſons whoſe Caſes I publiſhed, had the
          <w part="I">plain-</w><lb/><w part="F">eſt</w> Symptoms of Stones in the Bladder. And <w
          part="I">ſeve-</w><lb/><w part="F">ral</w> of theſe, with many others, have voided Pieces
        <lb/>too large to paſs the <hi rend="italic">Ureters</hi> without Pain, and <lb/>which
        accordingly have given Pain in paſſing the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Urethra,</hi> who yet had
        no previous Pains in the <lb/>Region of the Kidneys or Ureters. The <w part="I"
          >Medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cines</w> are indeed Diuretic, but not more ſo than <lb/>many
        others in common Uſe, and therefore their <lb/>good Effects muſt ariſe from ſome other
        Property. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is ſaid, That the Medicines are certainly <lb/>good in Bladder Caſes,
        and have done much <w part="I">Ser-</w><lb/><w part="F">vice</w>, but that their diſſolving
        Power may ſtill be <lb/>queſtioned. Be it ſo. However, ſince they have <lb/>done much
        Service in Bladder Caſes, where large <lb/>Pieces of Stone have been voided, as was ſaid in
        <lb/>the laſt Paragraph, theſe Bladder Caſes muſt <lb/>have been Stones in the Bladder; and
        a Medicine <lb/>which does Service in Stones of the Bladder, by <lb/>making the Perſon void
        Pieces, and grow free <lb/>from his Complaints at laſt, bids fair for a Solvent. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is ſaid, That the Medicines are nauſeous, <w part="I">oc-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">caſion</w> great Pains, and are attended with Danger. <lb/>That they are very
        nauſeous is certain; the <w part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F">creaſe</w> of Pain is alſo
        ſometimes very conſiderable, <lb/>but then it is generally of ſhort Continuance; and
        <lb/>they may be, and I believe are, dangerous, <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >out</w> proper Care and due Regulations; yet with <lb/>theſe I ſee no Danger. And the
        Public may be <w part="I">aſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſured</w>, that I, who have taken them
        conſtantly for <lb/>a Year, cannot but have enquired very ſtrictly <w part="I"
          >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">to</w> this Matter. The ſame Objections may be <lb/>made to many
        of the beſt Medicines in daily Uſe; <lb/>which would be unanſwerable, did not the Care
        <lb/>and Skill of Phyſicians remove them, or the Pain <lb/>and Danger attending Diſtempers
        over-rule them. <lb/>And in the preſent Caſe one may eaſily ſuppoſe, <lb/>that Phyſicians
        will make great Improvements in <lb/>the manner of giving theſe Medicines; and if they
        <lb/>do not, the Medicines, upon the worſt Suppoſition, <lb/>are ſtill far preferable either
        to the Stone, or the <lb/>Operation of Cutting. I ought however to <w part="I"
          >ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerve</w>, in Juſtice to Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Stephens,</hi>
        that her manner <lb/>of proceeding is in general very careful and <w part="I"
          >ratio-</w><lb/><w part="F">nal</w>, and that ſhe ſuffers much from the <w part="I"
          >Negli-</w><lb/><w part="F">gence</w> and Irregularity of thoſe who take her <w part="I"
          >Me-</w><lb/><w part="F">dicines</w>; which Phyſicians know to be often their <lb/>own
        Caſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is ſaid, That many Perſons who have the <lb/>Stone, grow eaſy without
        any viſible Reaſon. <lb/>However, this is very rare; and theſe Medicines, <lb/>which are
        Diuretic, and occaſion Pain at firſt, are <lb/>very unlikely to be Palliatives, or even to
        permit <lb/>a Perſon to be eaſy till the Cauſe be removed. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is ſaid, That the Sum of 5000<hi rend="italic">l.</hi> is too large.
        <lb/>But by what Rule of Eſtimation ſhall one <w part="I">deter-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >mine</w> this Matter? If we ſpeak ſtrictly, and <w part="I">accord-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ing</w> to the Obligations which we are all under to <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſult</w> public Happineſs at all Events, I ſuppoſe <w part="I">nei-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ther</w> Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Stephens</hi> nor any one elſe is ſo generous <lb/>and
        diſintereſted as theſe Obligations require. <lb/>However, in common Language, Mrs. <hi
          rend="italic">Stephens</hi>
        <lb/>has a Right to her own Secret, and may ſet what <lb/>Price ſhe pleaſes upon it,
        eſpecially if it be no <lb/>more than what ſhe may reaſonably hope to make <lb/>of it in
        another way. And the thing itſelf, if it be <lb/>a Solvent for the Stone, is ſurely of more
          <w part="I">Import-</w><lb/><w part="F">ance</w> to Mankind than 5000<hi rend="italic"
          >l.</hi> can be of to the <lb/>Contributors. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is ſaid, That this will encourage Quacks. <lb/>I believe not. There
        are few Quacks who will <lb/>venture to appeal to ſuch Judges, and to ſuch a <lb/>Method of
        Examination. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is ſaid, That the moſt eminent Gentlemen <lb/>of the Faculty ought to
        have been made Judges. <lb/>This is very true; and one of the firſt Steps which <lb/>I took
        was, to deſire thoſe to whom I had the <w part="I">Ho-</w><lb/><w part="F">nour</w> to be
        beſt known, to become Judges in the <lb/>Affair; but they declined it. However, I beg of
        <lb/>them once more to attend to the Facts; and, if <lb/>they pleaſe, to contribute, becauſe
        this would ſoon <lb/>bring the Matter to a Trial. And I need not ſay, <lb/>that their
        Judgment will have the greateſt Weight <lb/>as well with the Truſtees, as with every body
        elſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is ſaid, That I ought to have publiſhed all <lb/>the Failures and ill
        Accidents as well as the Ten <lb/>Caſes, which favour the diſſolving Power of the
        <lb/>Medicines. But I have met with nothing of this <lb/>kind ſufficient to render the
        Medicines ſuſpected <lb/>either of being ineffectual or pernicious. And the <lb/>full
        Hiſtory of theſe Medicines, with all their <lb/>Uſes, Defects and Cautions, is more than I
        have <lb/>had Opportunity to obtain, but may eaſily be <pb xml:id="page_4" n="4"
        /><lb/>procured from the Trials which will be made of <lb/>them in the Hoſpitals and other
        Places before the <lb/>Reward be aſſigned. I have omitted many more <lb/>Caſes in Favour of
        the Medicines than I have <lb/>given, and it is a ſufficient Reaſon for a farther <lb/>Trial
        of them, that ſo many Perſons have received <lb/>Benefit from them, and ſo few Harm. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is ſaid, That I myſelf have received no <w part="I">Be-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">nefit</w>. My Caſe is in ſhort this: I have the <lb/>Symptoms of a Stone or
        Gravel in both Kidneys, <lb/>and of a Stone in the Bladder, having Pain in <lb/>both Sides
        now and then; Pain at the Neck of the <lb/>Bladder, in the <hi rend="italic">Urethra</hi>
        and <hi rend="italic">Glans;</hi> Pain and <lb/>Difficulty in making Water; a ſudden
        Stoppage <lb/>frequently; and I make bloody Water upon <w part="I">Mo-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tion</w>. I have been examined twice, but no Stone <lb/>could be found. However, ſince my
        taking theſe <lb/>Medicines I have voided, and do ſtill void, little <lb/>angular Bits of
        Stone very frequently; and in ſo <lb/>ſoft a State as to crumble eaſily. And as I had no
        <lb/>conſiderable Pain before I began the Medicines, <lb/>except upon Motion, ſo I ſtill am
        eaſy while at <lb/>Reſt. The Medicines agree extremely well with <lb/>my general Health; and
        as it ſeems to me, both <lb/>that I have a Quantity of Stone ſomewhere in the <lb/>Paſſages,
        and alſo that this is coming away <w part="I">gradu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ally</w>, tho' very
        ſlowly, I go on with the Medicines, <lb/>hoping that they will at laſt be effectual, and not
        <lb/>knowing what elſe to do. And it would be very <lb/>unreaſonable in me to conceal a
        Medicine of great <lb/>Importance to Mankind, becauſe I myſelf have as <lb/>yet received no
        Benefit from it. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I ſhall conclude with begging the Favour of all <lb/>thoſe who have a
        compaſſionate Senſe of the <w part="I">Mi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſery</w> of others, to be ſo
        good as to pay in their <lb/>Contributions of themſelves, and without Delay. <lb/>This may
        be done in the Country by ſending them <lb/>to the Poſtmaſter of any neighbouring Town, who
        <lb/>will remit them, with the Names of each <w part="I">Contri-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >butor</w>, to Mr. <hi rend="italic">Drummond.</hi> It may be done in <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">London,</hi> by ſending a Servant to Mr. <hi rend="italic">Drummond</hi>'s
        <lb/>at <hi rend="italic">Charing-croſs;</hi> and Care will be taken to have <lb/>Liſts of
        the Contributors printed from time to <lb/>time, for the Satisfaction of the Public. There
        <lb/>is now upwards of 900<hi rend="italic">l.</hi> paid in, and in a great <lb/>Variety of
        Sums, from 5<hi rend="italic">s.</hi> to 100<hi rend="italic">l.</hi>
      </p>
      <dateline>June 5, 1738. </dateline>
      <signed rend="align-right"><lb/>D. HARTLEY. </signed>
      <postscript>
      <p rend="indent size(0.5)"><lb/>P.S. <hi rend="italic">Mr.</hi> Binford, <hi rend="italic"
          >whoſe Caſe is related</hi> No. 2. <hi rend="italic">in a Pamphlet intitled,</hi> Ten
        Caſes of Perſons who have <lb/>taken Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Stephens</hi>'s Medicines, <hi
          rend="italic">&amp;c. and who was found to have a large Stone in the Bladder, by Mr.</hi>
        <lb/>Patch, <hi rend="italic">a Surgeon at</hi> Exeter, <hi rend="italic">upon Examination
          with the Finger in the</hi> Anus, <hi rend="italic">has continued perfectly well <lb/>ever
          ſince he left off the Medicines; and has been examined again by the ſame Gentleman in the
          ſame Manner, <lb/>but no Stone could be found.</hi>
      </p></postscript>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
