<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: A treatise of the gravel and stone</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">A treatise of the gravel and stone, shewing, I. Their nature, causes,
              difference, and symptoms. II. The method of curing them. III. How to ease and remove
              the fits when present. And, IV. To prevent them for the future. With their proper
              remedies prescrib'd; and easily to be prepared, by the patients themselves. Writen,
              ... by a late learned and eminent physicain [sic] ... </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T10657</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T10657"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Torbuck; and E. Torbuck, 1738.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1738</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="7"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="63"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3307863683</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K025215.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: disease"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="7"/>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_8" n="1"/>
      <div n="1" type="chapter">
        <head rend="italic indent hanging"><lb/><hi rend="roman">I.</hi>
          <lb/>Of the Nature, Cauſes, Difference, <lb/>and Symptoms of the <hi rend="roman"
            >Gravel</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Stone.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(4)">T</hi>HE Diſeaſe of the Stone, either in <lb/>the
          Kidneys or the Bladder, and <lb/>that of the Gout, which are nearly <lb/>related, are two
          of the moſt cruel <lb/>and inexorable Tyrants that perſecute the <lb/>Race of Mankind: So
          great is their <w part="I">Vio-</w><lb/><w part="F">lence</w>, and ſo unextinguiſhed their
          Fury, that <lb/>they afflict the unhappy Patients with ſuch <lb/>frequent and inſufferable
          Tortures, as make <lb/>Life an undeſirable Poſſeſſion, and rather a <lb/>Burthen too hard
          to bear, than a State of <lb/>Satisfaction and Enjoyment. And had not <lb/>the All-wiſe
          Divine Author, planted in our <lb/>Nature, ſo ſtrong an Averſion to Death and
          <lb/>Diſſolution, it is highly probable that many, <lb/>grown utterly impatient of
          undergoing ſuch <pb xml:id="page_9" n="2"/><lb/>a Weight of Miſery, would lay Hands upon
          <lb/>themſelves, and ſoon put an End to their <lb/>Calamities and their Lives together,
          the <lb/>Grievance or the firſt to much over-balancing <lb/>the Pleaſure of the laſt.
          Some, it is true, of <lb/>theſe forlorn Creatures, have endeavoured to <lb/>eaſe
          themſelves by adventuring on theſe <w part="I">tra-</w><lb/><w part="F">gical</w>
          Expedients, and, no doubt, Multitudes <lb/>more would follow their Example, did not <lb/>a
          Principle of Religion among Chriſtians, <lb/>and a powerful Inſtinct of Self-Preſervation
          <lb/>among all Men, controul their Impatience, <lb/>and prevent Self-execution: Nor is it
          a Won-<lb/>der they ſhould prefer the Shades and <w part="I">Tran-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >quility</w> or the Grave, to the Heats and <w part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >quietudes</w> of ſuch acute Diſeaſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But it muſt be allowed, that of this Pair <lb/>ſo near y allied, the
          Stone and the Gout, the <lb/>firſt is the moſt terrible, and diſtinguiſhed <lb/>for its
          Fierceneſs and Cruelty. This Lictor <lb/>and Miniſter of Death, inflicts, above all
          <lb/>others, the ſharpeſt and moſt inſufferable <lb/>Tortures: What a melancholy Scene!
          What <lb/>a moving Spectacle of mortal Nature is it, <lb/>to ſee the unhappy Patient
          extended on the <lb/>Rack, groaning and crying out in Agonies <lb/>of Diſtreſs and
          unſpeakable Torment: E'er <lb/>Night is half ſpent, he wiſhes for Day; when <lb/>Day
          appears, he longs for Night; Diſtracted <pb xml:id="page_10" n="3"/><lb/>with his
          Sufferings, he lies wakeful, <w part="I">count-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> the Hours, any
          one of which, when <lb/>protracted and multiplied by raging Miſery, <lb/>ſeems a numerous
          Train, ſo ſluggiſh and <lb/>unprogreſſive does Time grow under <w part="I"
            >griev-</w><lb/><w part="F">ous</w> Sufferings. He changes his Pillow, but <lb/>not his
          Pain; new-makes his Bed, but keeps <lb/>his old Inquietudes, and though he often
          <lb/>turns from Side to Side, he never leaves his <lb/>Agonies behind: They, hapleſs
          State! know <lb/>no Ceſſation or Interruption: If they <w part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">times</w> remit and abate their Violence, they <lb/>ſoon recover their
          Strength, rekindle their <lb/>Rage, and inſult the Patient with as great <lb/>Fury as
          before. It muſt therefore be a <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">mendable</w> Action,
          and becoming an <hi rend="italic">Æſcu-<lb/>lapian</hi> worthy to endeavour, with all his
          <lb/>Might, to repel or diſable this Plague that <lb/>ſo much infeſts Mankind; and
          therefore <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">cordingly</w> I have undertaken to aſſiſt
          thoſe <lb/>who have already attacked this Peſt with <lb/>Skill and Vigour: For this is not
          the Work <lb/>of a ſingle Aggreſſor, but as in hunting down <lb/>a Foreſt Beaſt, or that
          enormous Bird the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Oſtrich,</hi> many Champions unite their Power,
          <lb/>armed with various Inſtruments of Death, <lb/>Cutlaſſes, Lances, Hooks, and Javelins,
          that <lb/>with different Weapons and mutual <w part="I">Aſſiſt-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ance</w> they may ſubdue the Enemy, or at leaſt <pb xml:id="page_11" n="4"/><lb/>oblige
          him to retreat; ſo, as a ready Auxiliary, <lb/>I bring my Forces, ſuch as they are, to
          join <lb/>thoſe of abler Combatants, in order to quell <lb/>this formidable Enemy, at
          leaſt to diminiſh <lb/>his Strength and reſtrain his Fury. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As to the Nature of the Diſeaſe, there are <lb/>ſcarce any Part of the
          Body privileged from <lb/>breeding Stones in their larger Cavities, or <lb/>more minute
          Interſtices, which are, in ſome <lb/>meaſure diverſified, according to the Nature <lb/>of
          the Bowels or Organs where they are <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duced</w>. They
          are found ſometimes in the <lb/>external Muſcles of the Body, as well as in <lb/>the
          Lungs, the Stomach, the Liver, the Gall- <lb/>Bladder, the Bowels or Contents of the
          <lb/>Abdomen, as well as in the Tongue, the <lb/>Brain, and even the Blood it ſelf: For <w
            part="I">ſeve-</w><lb/><w part="F">ral</w> credible Authors have affirm'd, that upon
          <lb/>opening a Vein, ſmall Stones, together with <lb/>the ſpouting Blood have ruſh'd into
          the <w part="I">Re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceiver</w>. In all which Neſt, the petrifying <w
            part="I">Prin-</w><lb/><w part="F">ciples</w>, meeting and embracing each other,
          <lb/>produce a ſingle Stone, or a Quarry of them <lb/>But this Diſcourſe is confin'd to
          the Stone in <lb/>the Kidneys, and that in the Bladder, which <lb/>in this Diſſertation I
          ſhall conſider as the ſame, <lb/>and not as the Diſeaſe of a diſtinct Species <lb/>When it
          is formed and ſettled in either <w part="I">Kid-</w><lb/><w part="F">ney</w>, it is
          accompanied with various Symptoms <pb xml:id="page_12" n="5"/><lb/>according as it is
          large or ſmall, ſmooth or <lb/>rugged, fixed or looſe, cloſely or ſlightly <w part="I"
            >co-</w><lb/><w part="F">herent</w>, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> hard and ſolid, or
          friable and <lb/>porous. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Of the minute Stone, that is, the Grit and <lb/>Gravel, formed of
          ſandy Rudiments in the <lb/>Kidneys or Bladder, which however are <w part="I"
            >per-</w><lb/><w part="F">fect</w> Stones, there are three Sorts diſtinguiſhed <lb/>by
          their Colour, that is, White, Yellow, and <lb/>Red. White is the native Complexion of
          <lb/>theſe little Bodies, Atoms indeed, in reſpect <lb/>of thoſe of the largeſt Dimenſion,
          as are the <lb/>Sands on the Shore, when compared with <lb/>the Rock at whoſe Feet they
          lie: Theſe <w part="I">pri-</w><lb/><w part="F">mitive</w> Stones are, however, ſo cloſe
          and <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">porous</w>, that the Coheſion of their Parts, are
          <lb/>not to be unclaſped and diſſolved, but with <lb/>great Difficulty, inſomuch that they
          imitate <lb/>the Hardneſs of the Diamond, and will <w part="I">po-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >liſh</w> Glaſs, like the Duſt of that Jewel, as <lb/>celebrated Authors aſſert; and it
          facilitates <lb/>our Belief of the indiſſoluble Structure of <lb/>this Grit, when we
          reflect on the like <w part="I">Qua-</w><lb/><w part="F">lity</w> in that called
          Hour-Glaſs Sand, which <lb/>is found, by Experience, to be leſs porous, <lb/>or more ſolid
          than Flint; and therefore the <lb/>Operators in Glaſs have laid aſide the firſt, <lb/>and
          now employ the laſt, as Materials for <lb/>their fineſt Works. But theſe minute white <pb
            xml:id="page_13" n="6"/><lb/>Stones, cannot, as I conceive, give <w part="I"
            >nephri-</w><lb/><w part="F">tick</w> Pains, or a Fit of the Stone, unleſs a
          <lb/>Collection or Congeries of them, are <w part="I">involv-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>
          or united by ſome adventitious, mucous, <lb/>ſlimy, or other anomalous Matter, ſo as to
          <lb/>form a Moles or Bulk, large enough to <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtruct</w>
          the Mouths or Channels of the <w part="I">Uri-</w><lb/><w part="F">nary</w> Paſſages, and
          that, it is true, may <w part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F">times</w> happen; but,
          generally ſpeaking, ſince <lb/>the minute pale Stones are ſo ſmooth and <lb/>ſmall, that
          they may enter with Eaſe the <w part="I">Ori-</w><lb/><w part="F">fices</w> of the Urinary
          Aquaeducts, and paſſing <lb/>through thoſe Conveyances, may, without <lb/>creating Pain or
          Trouble, be excluded with <lb/>the common Stream; and though there <lb/>ſhould be a great
          Quantity of that ſmall <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">coherent</w> Sand, it may,
          however, without <lb/>Difficulty, flow through the Ureters into the <lb/>Bladder with the
          ſerous Current, and <w part="I">toge-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> with it be diſcharged. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As to the Yellow Gravel, it is evident that <lb/>the minute Particles
          that compoſe it, are <lb/>ſtained with that Colour, by the alkalizate or <lb/>lixivial
          Salts of the Urine, which abounds <lb/>with ſuch Contents: And this Mixture in <lb/>the
          ſmall Yellow Stones, is the Reaſon why <lb/>they are leſs ſolid, and more diſſoluble than
          <lb/>the White of a purer Compoſition; which is <lb/>likewiſe obſerv'd, and from the ſame
          Reaſon, <pb xml:id="page_14" n="7"/><lb/>in the Stones generated in the Receptacle of
          <lb/>the Gall, whoſe Parts have not that ſtrict <lb/>Connexion and cloſe Structure as the
          White. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Red Gravel receives that Complexion, <lb/>from being infected with
          a little Drop of <lb/>Blood iſſuing from ſome lacerated Vein <lb/>where the Gravel lay. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>All theſe, if they are ragged and uneven, <lb/>may, by pricking,
          vellicating, or wounding <lb/>the tender Membranes that include them, <lb/>cauſe either
          duller and heavier, or more <w part="I">a-</w><lb/><w part="F">cute</w> Pains, according
          as they are arm'd with <lb/>more or leſs pointed Angles whilſt they lie <lb/>in the <hi
            rend="italic">Pelvis</hi> or Baſin of the Kidneys, and <lb/>there rouſed and diſturbed
          by the Motion <lb/>of the Body on Foot or Horſeback, rub <w part="I">up-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">on</w> and fret the neighbouring Membranes; <lb/>and ſo nephritick Sufferings
          may ariſe from <lb/>Gravel, which conſiſts in real and perfect <lb/>Stones, as before
          obſerved, though called <lb/>Sand, or a friable, gritty Matter, by Reaſon <lb/>of their
          ſmall Dimenſion. This is the firſt <lb/>nephritick Symptom before a larger Stone is
          <lb/>formed, which, however, is vexatious, and <lb/>often attended not only with Pain, but
          <lb/>much Inquietude, Sickneſs of the Stomach, <lb/>and a general Diſorder of the whole <w
            part="I">Oeco-</w><lb/><w part="F">nomy</w>, while the ſandy Atoms, that lie <w part="I"
            >heap-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> up in the Kidneys, are worked and <w part="I"
            >agi-</w><lb/><w part="F">tated</w>
          <pb xml:id="page_15" n="8"/><lb/>by the Motion of the Back or Loins, <lb/>irritate and
          gaul their Membranes of <w part="I">exqui-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſite</w> Senſe during their
          Confinement in thoſe <lb/>Lodgings. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It ought to be obſerved, that there are <lb/>often ſound in the Urine
          of Perſons in good <lb/>Health, or at leaſt not much diſtempered, a <lb/>Red Gravel or
          Sand, that ſticks to the Sides <lb/>of the Urinal or Chamber-pot that receives <lb/>it;
          but this is not the genuine Gravel, that <lb/>cauſes nephritick Sufferings, but the <w
            part="I">Produc-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of the Blood in Perſons of a ſcorbutick
          <lb/>Diſpoſition, or a warm Temperament, and <lb/>is diſtinguiſhed from the true Gravel in
          this, <lb/>that the laſt falls down, immediately after <lb/>the Urine is rendered, to the
          Bottom of the <lb/>Receiver, whereas the ſpurious Kind does <lb/>not break off from its
          Mixture and Union <lb/>with the Urine, till after ſome Hours ſtanding <lb/>in that Veſſel,
          when it is at length looſed <lb/>from its Embraces, precipitated and thruſt <lb/>down by
          the Cold of the Air, and afterwards, <lb/>if the Urine be gradually heated again, it
          <lb/>will recover its former Connexion with it, <lb/>which is not the Caſe of the genuine
            <w part="I">nephri-</w><lb/><w part="F">tick</w> Gravel: Beſides, there is often
          obſerved<lb/> in Perſons of ſuch a Conſtitution, a thin <w part="I">Sub-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſtance</w> floating on the Surface of their Urine, <lb/>imitating melted Fat or
          Greaſe, but when it <pb xml:id="page_16" n="9"/><lb/>is skimmed off, and dried upon a
          Paper <lb/>placed in the Sun, it diſcovers it ſelf to <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſiſt</w> of gritty ſaline Concretions, united <w part="I">to-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >gether</w> by ſome viſcous or ſlimy Bonds. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>If the Stones are of a larger Size than thoſe <lb/>called Sand or
          Gravel, they affect Humane <lb/>Bodies with yet more painful and afflictive <lb/>Symptoms,
          and ſuppoſing that their Figure <lb/>is unequal, and varied with many Angles; <lb/>then
          their Points, eſpecially upon bodily <lb/>Motion, vex and vellicate the Repoſitories
          <lb/>where they are neſted, and as ſo many ſharp <lb/>Thorns in the Sides of the <hi
            rend="italic">Pelvis,</hi> continually <lb/>grieve, prick, or wound their Membranes;
          <lb/>whence ariſes the frequent Diſcharge of <lb/>bloody Urine, a common Symptom of this
          <lb/>cruel Diſeaſe, which, if freſh, and newly let <lb/>out of the Veins, gives the Urine
          a red <w part="I">Co-</w><lb/><w part="F">lour</w>, and the Blood is diſcernable to the
          <lb/>Sight; but if it has lain, for ſome Time, <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >travaſate</w> in the Bladder, or if but a few <lb/>Drops ſtay in that manner in the
          Kidneys, <lb/>by turning to grumous and coagulated Clots, <lb/>they impart a dark and
          blackiſh Tincture to <lb/>the Urine, not unlike to that of Coffee; this <lb/>is a Symptom
          likewiſe that often <w part="I">accompa-</w><lb/><w part="F">nies</w> this Diſtemper: It
          is true alſo, that pale <lb/>limpid Water ſometimes attends the <w part="I">Pa-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">roxyſms</w> of the Stone, like that obſerved in <pb xml:id="page_17" n="10"
          /><lb/>Convulſive, Hypocondriacal, and Hyſterick <lb/>Paſſions, and from the ſame Cauſe,
          that is, <lb/>the Spaſmodick Diſorder or Contraction of <lb/>the Syſtem of the Nerves
          during the Fit. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Another Symptom, that accompanies the <lb/>Stones laſt deſcribed, is
          great Sickneſs of the <lb/>Stomach, Nauſea, and frequent Vomitings, <lb/>or Strainings to
          Vomit; for while the Fibres <lb/>in the Kidneys are grieved, and lacerated by <lb/>the
          rough Stone or Stones bred and confined <lb/>there, the Suffering is propagated to the <w
            part="I">Sto-</w><lb/><w part="F">mach</w> by a Conſent of Parts, or <w part="I"
            >Communi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cation</w> of Nerves, from one of thoſe Bowels <lb/>to the
          other; and this is ſo diſtinguiſhing a <lb/>Symptom of this Diſeaſe in the Kidneys, that
          <lb/>other Symptoms without this, are not <w part="I">ſuffi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cient</w>
          to induce the Phyſician to pronounce <lb/>the Diſtemper the Stone. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>If the Stone in the Kidneys be ſome Degree <lb/>larger, and likewiſe
          jagged, it creates <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſufferable</w> Pains, while it
          remains in the Pelvis <lb/>or Baſin of the Kidneys, grating and <w part="I"
            >lacera-</w><lb/><w part="F">ting</w> the encloſing Membrane, or while it <lb/>ſtrives
          through the Ureters, and wounds the <lb/>Fibres as they make their Way. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>When the Stone formed in the Kidneys is <lb/>grown yet larger, and ſo
          diſproportioned to <lb/>the Mouth of the Ureter, that it cannot enter, <lb/>even though
          its Superficies is ſmooth and <pb xml:id="page_18" n="11"/><lb/>equal, it will obſtruct
          the Orifice of that Tube, <lb/>while it attempts to paſs into it, or will ſtick <lb/>in
          the Channel of it; and while it continues <lb/>fixed there, as it ſtops the Current of the
            <w part="I">Wa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> through the Pipe, ſo it creates exquſite and
          <lb/>enormous Miſery, by diſtending the ſenſible <lb/>Membranes; and if it be unequal and
          ragged, <lb/>it will produce the moſt afflictive Tortures, <lb/>till it is protruded by
          Art or Nature through <lb/>the Ureter, and excluded into the Bladder. <lb/>This happens as
          often as the Stone grows to <lb/>a greater Size than is ſuitable to the Inlet and
          <lb/>Paſſage of that Tube: And the Effect is the <lb/>ſame if the Stone, though not of a
            <w part="I">diſpropor-</w><lb/><w part="F">tinate</w> Bulk to paſs the Ureter, ſhould <w
            part="I">how-</w><lb/><w part="F">ever</w> lye a-croſs the Orifice, for then it will
          <lb/>obſtruct the Deſcent of the Urine, and create <lb/>great Diſorder, till it find a
          proper Poſition, <lb/>and its Figure is adapted to the Inlet, and then <lb/>it enters and
          is at laſt diſcharged. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>After the Stone has made its Paſſage through <lb/>the Ureters for ſome
          Years, by ſtretching and <lb/>enlarging the Road ſo often, it becomes <w part="I"
            >ca-</w><lb/><w part="F">pacious</w> enough to receive much larger Stones <lb/>than the
          firſt, and to let them through into <lb/>the Bladder; ſo that the Cavity of the Ureter,
          <lb/>through which they have paſſed ſo long, is <lb/>by Degrees ſometimes extended to a
          Finger's <lb/>Breadth, as unqueſtionable Authors aſſure us. <pb xml:id="page_19" n="12"
          /><lb/>The Stone of the Kidneys is likewiſe <w part="I">conſi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >dered</w> as looſe or fixed; if as looſe and <w part="I">float-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ing</w>, or not adherent to any part of that <lb/>Bowel, but is always attempting to
          paſs the <lb/>Ureters to the Bladder, it produces the <w part="I">pain-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ful</w> Symptoms before deſcribed; but if it is <lb/>fixed, it then Neſts
          itſelf and ſettles in the <w part="I">Sub-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtance</w> of the Kidneys,
          where it grows by <w part="I">Ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">cretion</w> of Parts, and ſpreads
          like branching <lb/>Coral through the Body of the Kidney; and <lb/>while it lodges there
          in this quiet and inactive <lb/>State, the Patient may ſometimes feel <w part="I"
            >Heavi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w>, or a Weight in the Back, which however <lb/>is but
          an inconſiderable Suffering; and ſome in <lb/>this Condition have felt no Symptom at
          <lb/>all, and dyed of other Diſtempers; and when <lb/>they were, after Death, diſſected by
          the Sur-<lb/>geon, a conſiderable Stone has been diſcovered, <lb/>propagated through the
          Kidney, of which <lb/>however the Patient never complained. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And this was the Caſe, as I have been <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">formed</w> of the late Lord <hi rend="italic">Mohun</hi>'s Father, who
          <lb/>being open'd after he dyed of a Wound <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceived</w>
          in a Duel, a large Stone was diſcovered <lb/>ſpreading through the Kidney, of which <w
            part="I">not-</w><lb/><w part="F">withſtanding</w> in his Life Time he was entirely
          <lb/>unconſcious. I likewiſe knew an eminent <lb/>Divine, of a very Lean and Unmuſcular <w
            part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtitution</w>, who told me in Converſation, that <pb
            xml:id="page_20" n="13"/><lb/>ſuſpecting he had a Stone in the Kidneys, tryed <lb/>one
          Night in Bed, if he could not feel it, and <lb/>by preſſing his Loins, much emaciated with
          <lb/>his long Fingers, he aſſured me he felt the <lb/>Stone, and then, ſaid he, I
          reflected it muſt <lb/>be a large one propagated through that <w part="I">Bow-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">el</w>, and therefore that no Medicinal Methods <lb/>ſhould be attempted to
          break it, leſt the <w part="I">Frag-</w><lb/><w part="F">ments</w> falling into the <hi
            rend="italic">Pelvis,</hi> ſhould ſtop the <lb/>Paſſage of the Ureters, and create great
          Fits <lb/>of the Stone; upon this, ſaid he, I fell aſleep, <lb/>and during many Years,
          thought of it no more, <lb/>till of late ſome Incident, which he named, <lb/>and I have
          forgotten, brought again to his <lb/>Mind this Obſervation, and when he (ſome <lb/>Years
          afterwards) Died and was Diſſected, <lb/>a large Stone was found in his Kidney, which
          <lb/>though he felt, as ſaid before, yet lying <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >diſturbed</w> and quiet in its Neſt, it gave him <lb/>little Uneaſineſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Stone we are diſcourſing of is either <lb/>lighter or heavier, or
          which is the ſame thing, <lb/>more porus and friable, or more cloſe and <w part="I"
            >ſo-</w><lb/><w part="F">lid</w>. The Particles that compoſe the firſt, hang
          <lb/>together by a ſlight Connexion, which is eaſily <lb/>broken and diſſolved, like
          Flocks of frozen <lb/>Snow, the Sides of a Spunge, or the unſolid <lb/>and porus Subſtance
          of the Pumice-Stone, <lb/>and theſe by any internal or external Violence, <pb
            xml:id="page_21" n="14"/><lb/>or milder Motion, are often ſeparated and <lb/>crumbled
          into Parts, that drop into the Ureters <lb/>and paſs into the Bladder, to be diſcharged,
          <lb/>and theſe Fragments, like the ſmall ſandy and <lb/>gritty Stones ſpoken of before,
          produce the <lb/>ſame troubleſome Effects. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I have accounted for the Stones, that owe <lb/>their Production to the
          Kidneys, and ſhall now <lb/>purſue their Progreſs and follow their Courſe <lb/>to the
          Bladder. When the Stone generated in <lb/>the Urinary Strainer is diſcharged by the <w
            part="I">Ure-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> into the common Receiver, it too often
          <lb/>happens, that it acquires ſo large a Dimenſion, <lb/>that the Outlet of the Bladder
          is not wide <w part="I">e-</w><lb/><w part="F">nough</w> to let it through, and therefore
          of <w part="I">Ne-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceſſity</w> it muſt remain impriſoned there, where
          <lb/>by the Acceſſion of new petrifying Particles, <lb/>and gritty Matter continually
          deſcending from <lb/>the Kidneys, and adhering to it, its Size is <w part="I"
            >gra-</w><lb/><w part="F">dually</w> augmented, till it is yet more incapable <lb/>of
          being excluded, where if it is looſe and <w part="I">float-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>,
          it produces many grievous Symptoms; <lb/>for though it be only ſmooth and equal, and
          <lb/>ſo does not lacerate the Bladder, yet it will <lb/>often, as it plays againſt the
          Neck of it, and <lb/>attempts to paſs through, ſtop the Mouth of <lb/>the Aquaeduct, that
          conveys away the Urine, <lb/>and by ſo doing, produces very great Torment, <lb/>while the
          Bladder is exceſſively diſtended, and <pb xml:id="page_22" n="15"/><lb/>unable to
          diſcharge the encloſed Deluge; and <lb/>if the Stone be uneven and rugged, it will by
          <lb/>goading and wounding the encompaſſing <lb/>Membranes, create exquiſite Pain and
          bloody <lb/>Urine, and by long repeated Cruelties of this <lb/>Kind, it frequently forms
          an Ulcer in the <w part="I">lace-</w><lb/><w part="F">rated</w> Part, which is diſcovered
          by the <w part="I">Secre-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of putrid Matter mingled with the
          Urine; <lb/>for when it has ſtood ſome Hours, a pale ſlimy <lb/>Sediment is precipitated
          to the Bottom of the <lb/>Receiver, like the Excrement of the Noſe, or <lb/>the Whites of
          Eggs, and is diſtinguiſhed, from <lb/>the like Matter that deſcends to the Bladder,
          <lb/>from an Ulcer in the Kidneys, by the Odour, <lb/>which is ſtrong and faetid, if the
          purulent Mat<lb/>ter comes from an Ulcer in the Bladder, but <lb/>that derived from one in
          the Kidneys has no <lb/>ſuch offenſive Smell, as ſaid above. And the <lb/>Caſe is the ſame
          when an Ulcer ariſes in the <lb/>Kidneys or the Neck of the Bladder, not from <lb/>the
          Stone but from other Cauſes, ſuch as <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duce</w> Ulcers
          in the Lungs, in the Inteſtines, or <lb/>other internal Parts, that is, the Impurities
          <lb/>and incongruous Particles, which by Reaſon <lb/>of their diſproportionate Size and
          Figure, <w part="I">can-</w><lb/><w part="F">not</w> ſlide through the ſtrait Paſſages of
          the <lb/>Glands, but ſtick in them, till more of the like <lb/>Nature entangled there,
          encreaſe the <w part="I">Obſtruc-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> and ſwell the Parts, whence
          by Degrees <pb xml:id="page_23" n="16"/><lb/>they are inflamed, putrify, and by their <w
            part="I">Diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ruption</w>, form an Ulcer; and when this Diſeaſe
          <lb/>is produced in the Kidneys or the Bladder, the <lb/>putrid Contents iſſuing from
          them, and <w part="I">toge-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> with the Urine excluded into the
            <w part="I">Re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceiver</w>, ſhew themſelves, as I have ſaid, by
          <lb/>their viſcous and ropy Quality, and are <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >verſified</w> by their faetid or inoffenſive Smell: <lb/>And it ſhould be obſerved,
          that their mucous <lb/>and ſlimy Nature, diſtinguiſhes theſe Contents <lb/>from others,
          that proceed from a ſcorbutick <lb/>or unhealthful Habit of Body, when much <lb/>white,
          mealy, and light Matter appears in the <lb/>Sediment, and which being without <w part="I"
            >Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">nexion</w>, upon ſhaking the Glaſs will riſe and <lb/>float
          incoherent in the Urine, but unſlimy, as <lb/>well as without Faetor: This therefore, as I
          <lb/>have ſaid, does not proceed from any internal <lb/>Ulcer, but is a Defect ariſing
          from ſome <w part="I">irre-</w><lb/><w part="F">gular</w> and depraved State of the Blood,
          that <lb/>communicates with its Serum ſuch Matter <lb/>to the Kidneys. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Suppreſſion of Urine, occaſioned by a <lb/>Stone too large to paſs
          the <hi rend="italic">Urethra,</hi> is not <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tended</w>
          with Sickneſs and Vomiting, as when <lb/>a Stone ſticks in its Paſſage through the <w
            part="I">Ure-</w><lb/><w part="F">ters</w>, there being no Communication of Nerves
          <lb/>between the Bladder and the Stomach, to <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">vey</w>
          the Senſations from one to the other. But <pb xml:id="page_24" n="17"/><lb/>exquiſite and
          grievous Pains however attend it <lb/>from the Diſtention of the Bladder, as I have
          <lb/>ſaid, and ſometimes a ſmaller Stone, that has <lb/>entered the Mouth of the <hi
            rend="italic">Urethra,</hi> yet being <lb/>too great to ſlide through, ſtops near the <w
            part="I">En-</w><lb/><w part="F">trance</w>, or in the Middle, and creates a total
          <lb/>Suppreſſion of Urine, as well as great Torment. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I have now accounted for the Nature, <w part="I">Pro-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">perties</w>, and Symptoms of this Diſeaſe, and have <lb/>likewiſe in carrying
          on my Diſcourſe, <w part="I">inter-</w><lb/><w part="F">mixed</w> an Ennumeration of its
          various Kinds, <lb/>diſcriminated by the Receptacles, where the <lb/>Stone is contained,
          or by its different Colour <lb/>or various Shape and Figure; and now I ſhall <lb/>proceed
          to ſearch into the Cauſes of it. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The remote, antecedent Cauſe of the Stone, <lb/>is a defect in the
          digeſtive Faculty of the <lb/>Stomach, or that of the Blood, or nervous <lb/>Juices,
          whence ſuch Impurities and feculent <lb/>Portions remain, as produce the Coagulations
          <lb/>and Concreſcencies, that become the <w part="I">Founda-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>
          of the Stone, whoſe Rudiments and <w part="I">pri-</w><lb/><w part="F">mitive</w>
          Materials, conſiſt in a cloſe <w part="I">Combina-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of a
          volatile in a ſuperior, and acid Salt <lb/>in an inferiour Proportion. That theſe two
          <lb/>are the petrifying Principles, is known by <lb/>Experience, that ſhews us that this
          is the Effect <lb/>of Acids and Alkalies meeting together; as for <lb/>Example, <hi
            rend="italic">Juice of Lemon, and Salt of Tartar;</hi>
          <pb xml:id="page_25" n="18"/><lb/>Let it be ſuppoſed then, that from the <w part="I"
            >inordi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nate</w> and depraved Concoctions before-named, <lb/>ſuch
          hard Coalitions, ſlimy Coagulations, or <lb/>cretaceous Confederacies ſhould be left <w
            part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">hind</w>, and it is eaſy to conceive how, when <lb/>yet
          more hardened and prepared in the Blood, <lb/>they may by the Power of the urinous Salts
          <lb/>in the Kidneys, be ſoon converted into gritty, <lb/>ſandy Atoms, which, cluſtring
          together, and <lb/>cohering, form at length a Stone of the loweſt <lb/>Size; that by the
          daily Acceſſion of new <w part="I">ſimi-</w><lb/><w part="F">lar</w> Particles, acquires a
          far greater Dimenſion <lb/>in the Kidneys, and yet a greater after its <lb/>Deſcent from
          that Bowel to the Bladder; for <lb/>while it is detained, from being too large to be
          <lb/>excluded, it has more Room to receive <w part="I">Aug-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >mentation</w>, whilſt conſtantly fed by the ſandy <lb/>Rivulets, that empty themſelves
          through the <lb/>Outlets of the Ureters into that Ciſtern, where <lb/>it grows by ſuch
          Accretion, till ſometimes it <lb/>becomes exceeding large: Thus petrified <w part="I"
            >Foſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſils</w> and Flints in the Earth, as well as rotten,
          <lb/>Sticks and Pieces of Wood turned to Stone, <lb/>owe their Growth, as well as
          Production, to <lb/>lapideſcent or ſtony Particles, that continually <lb/>accede to, and
          ſtrictly embrace the former <w part="I">col-</w><lb/><w part="F">lected</w> Materials; But
          as to the intrinſick <w part="I">Na-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w> of
          <unclear>#</unclear>he Stone bred in living Creatures, and <lb/>thoſe laſt named, that is,
          Minerals and <w part="I">Vege-</w>
          <pb xml:id="page_26" n="19"/><lb/>there is a vaſt Difference; for the greateſt <lb/>Part
          of the firſt are formed of volatile Salts, or <lb/>Animal Alkalies, but the other are not
            <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſed</w> of any ſuch Ingredients. It is truly <w
            part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">marked</w>, that thoſe who are obnoxious to the
          <lb/>Stone, are generally of a hot Conſtitution, as <lb/>it is likewiſe obſerved of gouty
          Patients, by <lb/>which means their Blood is more inclined to <lb/>breed cretaceous, hard,
          and gritty <w part="I">Combina-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w>, which by a certain Degree
          of Heat, <lb/>are ſoon advanced into proper Materials for <lb/>the Gout and Stone,
          Diſeaſes ſo nearly related, <lb/>that they are eaſily convertible into each other.
          <lb/>But of theſe Subjects I have diſcourſed at <lb/>large in my Treatiſe of the Gout, to
          which <lb/>I refer the Reader. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>When the Seeds or Principles of the Stone, <lb/>that is, the viſcous,
          tough or ſandy <w part="I">Concre-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w>, not to be diſſolved and
          ſeparated from <lb/>the Blood, bearing however a Figure and <w part="I">Di-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">menſion</w> proper to enter the papillary Glands, <lb/>the Strainers in the
          Kidneys, they are there yet <lb/>more indurated, and acquire a gritty and <w part="I"
            >ſabu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lous</w> Conſtitution; though even in the Blood <lb/>itſelf,
          before the Serum is ſeparated from it by <lb/>the ſecretory Glands, ſmall Stones are often
          <lb/>formed, as they are in all the Parts of the <lb/>Body, as before obſerved. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_27" n="20"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is remarkable that thoſe Countries, that <lb/>lye upon the River
            <hi rend="italic">Rhine</hi> and the Northern <lb/>Parts of <hi rend="italic"
            >France,</hi> who drink a thin, ſharp, <lb/>pale Wine, which is more repleniſhed with
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tarcar</hi> than other Fruits of the Vine, <w part="I"
            >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">cocted</w> by a hotter Sun, are moſt obnoxious <lb/>to the
          Stone in the Kidneys: For ſuch Wines <lb/>convey to the Blood in great Plenty, a Sort of
          <lb/>petrifying Fluid, whoſe redundant acid <w part="I">Parti-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cles</w>, before their Nature is changed to an <hi rend="italic">Al-<lb/>kali</hi> by
          the active Principles of the Blood, <lb/>meeting and combining with the volatile Salts
          <lb/>there, the Reſult is a hard and tartarous <w part="I">Pro-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >duction</w>, eaſily formed into a Stone. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The voluptuous Life of thoſe that eat and <lb/>drink deliciouſly every
          Day, cannot but <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">miniſter</w> to the Blood, the Seeds
          and Principles <lb/>of the Stone, in Conſtitutions diſpoſed and <lb/>prepared for that
          Diſtemper: For theſe coſtly <lb/>and luxurious Meats and Drinks, exceſſively <lb/>and
          conſtantly ingeſted, being unequal to the <lb/>digeſt ve Power of the Stomach, fill it
          with a <lb/>Load of Crudities and unconcocted Foods; <lb/>which tranſmitted by the
          Miniſtry of the <lb/>lacteal Paſſages to the Veins, communicate to <lb/>the Blood, not
          only great Plenty of noxious <lb/>Impurities, but likewiſe a rich Chyle, <w part="I"
            >abun-</w><lb/><w part="F">dant</w> in volatile Salts, with ſuch a Proportion <lb/>of
          Acids, as are apt to create this Diſtemper. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_28" n="21"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>A ſedentary and inactive Life, eſpecially <lb/>when the Perſons are of
          a vigorous and hot <lb/>Complexion, much promotes the Production <lb/>of the Stone; for
          while the Blood runs lazy and <lb/>unagitated in its Channels, for want of due <lb/>Labour
          and Exerciſe of the Limbs to puſh on <lb/>its Streams with due Celerity, it is eaſy to
          <lb/>conceive how the crude and impure Parts run <lb/>into various Concreſcencies and
          Coagulations. <lb/>On the contrary, when due Activity, either by <lb/>the Labour of the
          Hands, or by riding, or <w part="I">o-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> Exerciſes of the Body,
          the Motion of the <lb/>Blood is accelerated, it is obvious to <w part="I"
            >appre-</w><lb/><w part="F">hend</w>, that by the Rencounters and mutual <w part="I"
            >Col-</w><lb/><w part="F">liſions</w> of the Parts daſhing and rubbing upon <lb/>each
          other, they are broken, divided and <w part="I">atte-</w><lb/><w part="F">nuated</w>, till
          they become ſo minute and ſo well <lb/>mixed, that the tough, ſlimy, and yet harder
          <lb/>Combinations are unlocked and diſſolved, by <lb/>which means the Seeds and Rudiments
          of the <lb/>Stone are prevented, and the Cauſe removed: <lb/>And therefore in this Caſe,
          as in the Gout, <lb/>the ſedentary Lawyer; the over-thoughtful <lb/>Perſon; the hard
          Student; and the inactive, <lb/>indolent, and voluptuous Gentleman, are <w part="I"
            >ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">noxious</w> to this grievous Diſtemper, as are <lb/>likewiſe
          Men of covetous Tempers; while the <lb/>laborious Husbandman, and Mechanick, the
          <lb/>daily Traveller, and indefatigable Sportſman, <pb xml:id="page_29" n="22"/><lb/>are
          ſeldom attacked and tortured by it: For <lb/>theſe keep the Body in a Healthful State,
          <lb/>while their repeated Exerciſe helps their <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >geſtive</w> Faculties to do their Duty, and refine <lb/>the Blood, by a conſtant
          Expulſion of <w part="I">inordi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nate</w> and incongruous Humours.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="chapter">
        <head rend="italic align-center dc(2)"><lb/><hi rend="roman">II.</hi>
          <lb/>The Method of Curing the <lb/><hi rend="roman">Gravel</hi> and <hi rend="roman"
            >Stone.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(4)">F</hi>IRST, of the loweſt Degree of this <w part="I"
            >Diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">eaſe</w>, that is, the ſmall Sand-like
          Gri<unclear>#</unclear>t, <lb/>either White, Red, or Yellow, which though <lb/>very
          minute, yet are true Stones, and diſtinct <lb/>from the ſcorbutick Red Matter, that does
          <lb/>not ſeparate and fall down from the Urine, <lb/>till after ſome Hours ſtanding, and
          then is <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">cipitated</w> by the Impreſſion of the Cold
          from <lb/>the Ambient Air, as above deſcribed. The <lb/>Cure of this Diſtemper, conſiſts
          in the carrying <lb/>off the ſabulous and ſandy Atoms, and <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">venting</w> the Generation of more, and ſo <w part="I">cut-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ting</w> off the Supplies, that uſe to fill the Room <lb/>of the forther, that are
          diſcharged with the <pb xml:id="page_30" n="23"/><lb/>Urine: And it is highly neceſſary to
          attempt <lb/>this, leſt otherwiſe the ſmall Stones, <w part="I">continu-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ing</w> undiſturbed, ſhould unite and adhere to <lb/>each other, and receiving
          gradual <w part="I">Augmenta-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, from new Particles daily
          arriving, ſhould <lb/>grow to a Stone of great Bulk, and become <lb/>incapable of paſſing
          the Ureters, or at leaſt <lb/>without great Difficulty and Pain; and when <lb/>they ſlide
          through and drop into the Bladder, <lb/>ſhould contract there a large Size as before <w
            part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſcribed</w>. For it is highly probable, that the
          <lb/>Stone is very ſeldom originally generated in <lb/>that Receptacle, and that all, or
          at leaſt the <lb/>far greateſt Part found there, deſcend thither <lb/>from the Kidneys,
          and receive their Encreaſe <lb/>from the ſandy and gritty Supplies, tranſmitted <lb/>to it
          through the Ureters. It has therefore <lb/>been an unhappy Neglect, committed by ſome
          <lb/>Patients, that though they have long perceived <lb/>a conſiderable Quatity of Gravel
          diſcharged <lb/>with their Urine, and have felt the Trouble <lb/>and Uneaſineſs of it in
          their Kidneys, have <lb/>however, taken little Care to clear them of <lb/>theſe gritty
          Materials, and prevent the <w part="I">breed-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> of more; from
          which Omiſſion, at length, <lb/>Stones of a bigger Bulk, always painful and <lb/>often
          fatal, have been produced. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is therefore evidently the Intereſt of all <lb/>Perſons, when they
          obſerve that a Quantity of <pb xml:id="page_31" n="24"/><lb/>ſuch Sand and Gravel, the
          Rudiments and <w part="I">Mo-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> of bigger Stones, is excluded
          with the <lb/>Urine from the Bladder, to endeavour, by <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">per</w> Means, to free the Kidneys from theſe <w part="I">noxi-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ous</w> Inhabitants, and prevent the Generation <lb/>of new Supplies; and in
          the firſt Place, it is <lb/>requiſite to convey away the Gravel, that is <lb/>already
          bred, for which Purpoſe the following <lb/>Method is moſt efficacious. </p>
        <p rend="align-center"><lb/>Firſt Purgatives. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic hanging"><lb/>Take over Night, going to Bed, of Elixir <lb/> Salutis,
          three Spoonfuls; and the next <lb/>Morning, drink a Quart or three Pints <lb/>of purging
          Mineral Waters, ſuch as thoſe <lb/>of <hi rend="roman">Epſom, Dulledge, Acton,
            Northal</hi>, &amp;c. <lb/> And at Night going to Bed, </p>
        <p rend="indent italic hanging"><lb/>Take of Milk-Water, two Ounces; <w part="I"
            >com-</w><lb/><w part="F">pound</w> Water of Horſe-radiſh, half an <lb/>Ounce; twelve
          Drops of liquid <w part="I">Lauda-</w><lb/><w part="F">num</w>, and three Drachms of
          Diacodium; <lb/>make it a Draught: repeat both <w part="I">Medi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cines</w> every other Day and Night, for <lb/>three Times. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>After an Interval of three Weeks do the <lb/>ſame, and ſooner, if the
          Symptoms of the <lb/>Gravel call for it. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_32" n="25"/>
        <p rend="indent hanging"><lb/>Or, <hi rend="italic">Drink alone, two Quarts of ſuch <w
              part="I">purg-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> Waters ſeveral Days, and then reſt.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Reaſon why theſe Waters are very <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">neficial</w> for the Purpoſe intended, is, that a <lb/>conſiderable Part of
          them paſs by Urine, and <lb/>in their Paſſage through the Kidneys, waſh <lb/>away in their
          Current the Sand and Gravel, <lb/>and ſuffer them not to lodge there, till they <lb/>grow
          to a Stone of a large Size: And 'tis the <lb/>ſame in reſpect of the Bladder; for the ſame
          <lb/>Flood that ruſhes down through the Ureters, <lb/>carries off the Gritt from the
          Receiver, and <lb/>expels it with the Urine. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Diureticks, to be employed in the Intervals <lb/>of purging, for the
          ſame Purpoſe, are ſuch <lb/>as follow. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic hanging"><lb/>Take of Roots of Chervil, Stone Parſley, <lb/>Eringo,
          Fennel, Sorrel, each half an <lb/>Ounce; of Seeds of Burdock, Aniſe, and <lb/>ſweet
          Fennel, each a Drachm; of <w part="I">Juni-</w><lb/><w part="F">per</w> Berries, three
          Drachms; boil theſe <lb/>Ingredients, in three Pints of Spring-<lb/>Water, to a Quart; add
          to it, a Drachm <lb/>of purified Nitre; ſtrain it, and add a <lb/>Pint of Rheniſh Wine:
          Drink a <w part="I">Quar-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> of a Pint Morning and Evening. </p>
        <p rend="indent hanging"><lb/>Or, <hi rend="italic">Take Millepedes alive and waſhed,
            <lb/>fifty, bruiſe them in a Mortar, with a <pb xml:id="page_33" n="26"/><lb/>Quarter of
            a Pint of Rheniſh Wine, and <lb/>four Ounces of compound Horſe-radiſh <lb/>Water; make a
            ſtrong Expreſſion for a <lb/>Draught, to be taken twice a Day.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But the moſt effectual Diuretick for <w part="I">carry-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ing</w> off Gravel, and clearing the Parts afflicted <lb/>with it, are mineral
          unpurging Waters, ſuch <lb/>as thoſe of the <hi rend="italic">Bath, Tunbridge,</hi> the
            <hi rend="italic">Spaw,</hi>
          <lb/>and other Chalybeate Springs: For theſe, <lb/>ruſhing with a plentiful Tide through
          the <w part="I">uri-</w><lb/><w part="F">nary</w> Organs where the Gravel is lodged as
          <lb/>well as generated, diſturbs its ſeveral Neſts, <lb/>and rolls along in its Stream,
          the Sand-beds it <lb/>meets in its Way, till at length they are <w part="I"
            >diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">charged</w> in the Urine. But this is not the only
          <lb/>Advantage, that attends the drinking <w part="I">co-</w><lb/><w part="F">piouſly</w>
          Chalybeate Waters; for beſides this, it <lb/>very much contributes the laying the Axe to
          <lb/>the Root of the Diſeaſe, and preventing the <lb/>Generation of ſuch petrifying Seeds,
          as ſhall <lb/>be ſhewn afterwards. There are other <w part="I">diure-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tick</w> Remedies uſeful in this Diſtemper; as a <lb/>Mixture of Water, <hi
            rend="italic">French</hi> Brandy, and Juice <lb/>of Lemon, called Punch, if made ſmall,
          and <lb/>not intoxicating, though taken in a <w part="I">conſide-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >rable</w> Quantity. <hi rend="italic">Juice or Syrup of Lemons; <lb/>Syrup of
            Marſh-mallows; and freſh Oil of <lb/>Sweet Almonds;</hi> of each an equal Portion, <pb
            xml:id="page_34" n="27"/><lb/>mixed and beat together, with as much Sugar <lb/>as is
          ſufficient to give them a Conſiſtency, <lb/>taken to a Spoonful or two often in a Day, is
          <lb/>very beneficial; ſo is a Spoonful or two of <lb/><hi rend="italic">compound
            Juniper-Water of</hi> Cologne, <hi rend="italic">or</hi>
          <lb/>Holland, <hi rend="italic">drank now and then in a Glaſs of <lb/>White-wine;</hi> add
          to theſe Remedies, the <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">erciſe</w> of the Body, by
          riding ſometimes on a <lb/>hard trotting Horſe, ſometimes by hurrying <lb/>in a Coach over
          paved Stones, or other rugged <lb/>and uneven Ground, (if the Patient can bear <lb/>it)
          which by the repeated working and <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">cuſſion</w> of the
          Back, move and diſlodge the <lb/>Gravel in the Kidneys, and force it thence <lb/>into the
          Bladder, whence it is excluded with <lb/>the Water. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now to prevent the Production of little <lb/>Stones or Gravel, all
          thoſe Remedies are <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">quired</w> as moſt effectual, that
          have an <w part="I">opera-</w><lb/><w part="F">tive</w> Vertue, to looſe and diſengage all
          viſcous <lb/>and tough Coagulations, and diſſolve the <w part="I">Co-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >heſion</w> and Structure of cretaceous and gritty <lb/>Coalitions, whence ſmall Stones
          and Gravel <lb/>are created, ſome in the Blood, and others in <lb/>the urinary Strainers.
          This is indeed a Matter <lb/>of the greateſt Importance in this Caſe; for if <lb/>this is
          effected, the formidable and pernicious <lb/>Diſeaſe will be cruſhed in Embrio, and not <w
            part="I">ſuf-</w><lb/><w part="F">fered</w> to arrive at a mature State. I ſhall <w
            part="I">there-</w><pb xml:id="page_35" n="28"/><lb/>ſet down the Medicines, endowed
          with <lb/>the greateſt Force, for procuring this End. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is eaſy to ſee that thoſe Remedies, that <lb/>reſtore the Blood
          when depraved, to its native <lb/>Temperament, and keep it in that juſt and <w part="I"
            >ſa-</w><lb/><w part="F">lutary</w> Conſtitution, which ſpecifially belongs <lb/>to this
          Animal Fluid, are in general to be <w part="I">cho-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſen</w>; and in
          this Caſe in particular, thoſe are <lb/>to be inſiſted on, that are moſt capable of <w
            part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">joyning</w> and ſeparating the aſſociated, viſcous,
          <lb/>and ſandy Particles, that conſpire to the <w part="I">For-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >mation</w> of a Stone, and ſo to attenuate and <lb/>refine them, that they may eaſily
          incorporate <lb/>with the Blood, and produce an uniform and <lb/>equal Mixture. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And for this Purpoſe, Chalybe<unclear>#</unclear>te Medicines,
          <lb/>prepared by Art or Nature, are the moſt <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ferable</w>: And ſince Patients afflicted with this <lb/>Diſeaſe, are commonly of a
          hotter <w part="I">Conſtitu-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> than others, thoſe Preparations
          that have <lb/>the leaſt Sulphur left in their Compoſition, are <lb/>moſt beneficial to
          them; ſuch as the <hi rend="italic">Salt of <lb/>Steel,</hi> or the Tincture of it in
          Wine: But <w part="I">a-</w><lb/><w part="F">bove</w> all, mineral Waters, impregnated
          with <lb/>Steel in Embrio, are in this Caſe moſt <w part="I">cele-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >brated</w>, which not only dilute and attemper <lb/>the Blood, and carry off in their
          Current the <lb/>ſandy and petrifying Materials, as before <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">plained</w>, but likewiſe by their active Vertue, <pb xml:id="page_36" n="29"
          /><lb/>animate, ferment, and exalt the Blood, break <lb/>the Coheſion of the knotty and
          cretaceous <lb/>Seeds of the Stone, and by wreſting the <w part="I">Parti-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">cles</w> from each others Embraces, prevent the <lb/>engendering of this
          Diſeaſe, by the <w part="I">Confede-</w><lb/><w part="F">racy</w> of ſuch Impurities. So
          that theſe <w part="I">ſalu-</w><lb/><w part="F">tary</w> Springs, are not only highly
          uſeful in <w part="I">free-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> the Veins from immiſcible and
          hurtful <lb/>Matter, cleanſing the Urinary Channels, and <lb/>rolling away in their Flood,
          the Gravel lodged <lb/>in the Cavities, through which their Waters <lb/>make their Way,
          but they likewiſe very much <lb/>contribute to the Recovery of a juſt Craſis, or
          <lb/>Conſtitution of Blood, by deſtroying the <w part="I">Prin-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ciples</w> and Rudiments of this Diſeaſe, 'ere yet <lb/>they combine in a Stone of
          large Size, and <lb/>reach a mature State, which they effect in the <lb/>Manner deſcribed. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But if hard and gravelly Materials, aſſociate <lb/>and unite in the
          Kidneys, by a ſlight Structure, <lb/>and are rather entangled one with another, and
          <lb/>hang together like a piece of Spunge, Hoar-<lb/>Froſt, or a Flake of Snow, than
          ſtrictly <w part="I">co-</w><lb/><w part="F">here</w>, whence they become very porus and
          <lb/>friable; or if when more cloſely complicated <lb/>and connected, they grow to a
          greater Bulk, <lb/>and create great Pain either in the Kidneys or <lb/>the Ureters, by
          grating the Membranes with <lb/>their unequal and ragged Figure in their <w part="I"
            >Paſ-</w><pb xml:id="page_37" n="30"/><lb/><w part="F">ſage</w>, or by their too large
          and diſproportionate <lb/>Size, ſtop at the Entrance, or in their Way <lb/>through theſe
          Tubes, in ſuch Caſes, the proper <lb/>Remedies do remove them from the Kidneys, <lb/>and
          oblige them to paſs the Uteters into the <lb/>Bladder, are ſuch as theſe. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="chapter">
        <head rend="align-center dc(2)"><lb/>III. <lb/>How to remove a Fit of the <lb/><hi rend="sc"
            >Gravel</hi>, or <hi rend="sc">Stone</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent italic hanging"><lb/>Take three or four Spoonfuls of Elixir <w part="I"
            >Sa-</w><lb/><w part="F">lutis</w>, or of the Tincture or Infuſion of <lb/>Sena and
          Rhubarb and Anniſeeds, over <lb/>Night, and a Quart of purging Mineral-<lb/>Water the next
          Morning, and the Night <lb/>following take this Draught, </p>
        <p rend="indent italic hanging"><lb/>Of Milk-Water, two Ounces; of compound
          <lb/>Horſe-radiſh-Water, three Drachms; of <lb/>crude Opium colated, a Grain and half;
          <lb/>Syrup of Marſh-mallows, half an Ounce; <lb/>make it a Draught: And if the Stone or
          <lb/>Gravel, be not removed, but the Fit <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tinues</w>,
          take the next Morning, two <lb/>Quarts of the ſame purging Waters, <lb/>either <hi
            rend="italic">Epſom, Dulledge, Acton,</hi> &amp;c. and <lb/>the Night following, the
          ſame compoſing <pb xml:id="page_38" n="31"/><lb/>Draught, and ſo the next Morning and
          <lb/>Night, for three Times, during the Fit; <lb/>and if notwithſtanding, the Paroxyſm
          <lb/>is ſtill prolonged, then let the Patient <lb/>take the following Draught, going to
          <lb/>Bed, every Night, if the Pains are <w part="I">vio-</w><lb/><w part="F">lent</w>, or
          otherwiſe every other Night. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic hanging"><lb/>Take of Oil of Sweet-Almonds, and Ounce; <lb/>of the
          pectoral Decoction, a Quarter of <lb/>a Pint; of Syrup of Meconium, ten <lb/>Drachms; make
          a Draught. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic hanging"><lb/>Take alſo ſuch oily and diuretick Medicines <lb/>as
          follow. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic hanging"><lb/>Take of Oil of Sweet-Almonds, and <w part="I"
            >Lin-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſeed</w>, drawn without Fire, each an <lb/>Ounce; of Syrup of
          Lemons and Marſh-<lb/>mallows, each ten Drachms; of Saffron, <lb/>a Scruple; of fine
          Sugar, as much as is <lb/>ſufficient; let it all be well mixed in a <lb/>marble Mortar,
          and made a Linctus. <lb/>Let the Patient take a Spoonful or two <lb/>often in a Day and
          Night. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Small Punch likewiſe, eſpecially if made <lb/>with <hi rend="italic"
            >Spaw</hi>-Water, is uſeful to puſh on the <lb/>Stone, or Gravel, when either of them
          ſticks <lb/>in the Ureters, and to clear the Kidneys of <lb/>the Beds of Sand collected
          there. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_39" n="32"/>
        <p rend="indent italic hanging"><lb/>Juniper-Water, eſpecially that of <hi rend="roman"
            >Cologne,</hi>
          <lb/>or <hi rend="roman">Holland,</hi> and the diuretick Apozem, <lb/>above ſet down, are
          beneficial. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>To be more particular, let the Patient in <lb/>the Paroxyſm, that
          eludes the Force of the <lb/>forementioned Remedies, take the following. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic hanging"><lb/>Take of Flowers of Camomile, two <w part="I"
            >Hand-</w><lb/><w part="F">fuls</w>; Roots of Marſh-mallows, ſix <lb/>Drachms; of wild
          Carrot-Seed, half an <lb/>Ounce; of Venice Turpentine, diſſolved <lb/>with the White of an
          Egg, three Drachms; <lb/>of the Electuary of Hiera cum Agarick, <lb/>ſix Drachms; make it
          a Clyſter. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic hanging"><lb/><hi rend="roman">Or,</hi> Take of the common emollient
            <w part="I">Decocti-</w><lb/><w part="F">on</w>, twelve Ounces; adding to the <w
            part="I">Ingre-</w><lb/><w part="F">dients</w> Juniper-Berries, ſix Drachms; <lb/>Seeds
          of the wild Carrot, three Drachms; <lb/>diſſolve in it of Lenitive Electuary, ten
          <lb/>Drachms; uſe it for a Clyſter. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic hanging"><lb/>Let one of theſe Clyſters be given every <lb/>Day, for
          three or four Times. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>For eaſing the Paroxyſm, it will likewiſe be <lb/>very Advantagious,
          for the Patient to ſit up <lb/>to the Waſte, in a Bath of Lukewarm Water, <lb/>and repeat
          it two or three Times, or in a <lb/>medicated Bath, which may be made thus.</p>
        <pb xml:id="page_40" n="33"/>
        <p rend="indent italic hanging"><lb/>Take of the Leaves of Mallows, Marſh-<lb/>mallows,
          Pellitory of the Wall, each <lb/>three Handfuls; Flowers of Camomile, <lb/>Melilot, and
          Elder, each two Handfuls; <lb/>Tops of Camomile, two Handfuls; <w part="I"
            >Juni-</w><lb/><w part="F">per-Berries</w>, ſix Ounces; of Linſeed, and
          <lb/>Fenugreek-Seed, each two Ounces; boil <lb/>all in a ſufficient Quantity of
          Spring-<lb/>Water, and let the Patient ſit in it <lb/>Lukewarm, up to the Waſte, in a <w
            part="I">Ba-</w><lb/><w part="F">thing</w> Tub. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In this Caſe alſo, there are vaſt Varieties of <lb/>Remedies,
          preſcribed by celebrated Authors, <lb/>as Fomentations, Liniments, Plaiſters, &amp;c.
          <lb/>to be externally applied, which <w part="I">notwithſtand-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ing</w>, are little availing for removing a Fit of <lb/>the Stone, or Gravel: The moſt
          effectual, are <lb/>certainly the Uſe of purging Mineral Waters, <lb/>three or four Times,
          and taking at Night, <w part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> their Operation, a Grain
          and half of <hi rend="italic">Opium</hi>, <lb/>as before-mentioned, or an equivalent <w
            part="I">Quan-</w><lb/><w part="F">tity</w> of <hi rend="italic">liquid Laudanum</hi>,
          that is, about <lb/>thirty Drops.</p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But in Caſe that Method ſhould not <w part="I">ſuc-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ceed</w>, the next moſt valuable Medicines are <lb/>Pills made of
          Venice-Turpentine, or rather <lb/>Chios, taken to the Quantity of a Scruple, alone,
          <lb/>or mixed with an equal Part of Rhubarb. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_41" n="34"/>
        <p rend="indent hanging"><lb/>Or, Thus,—<hi rend="italic">Take of Venice, or <w part="I"
              >Chios-Tur-</w><lb/><w part="F">pentine</w>, four Scruples; of Rhubarb, a <lb/>Drachm;
            of Salt of Tartar, half a <lb/>Drachm; Cinnamon, half a Scruple; of <lb/>Balſamick
            Syrap, as much as will make <lb/>a Maſs, to be formed into Pills of <w part="I"
              >ordi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nary</w> Size; take four every other Day, <lb/>at Bed
            Time.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>For the ſame End, Emulſions are <w part="I">condu-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cive</w>, ſuch as theſe, </p>
        <p rend="indent italic hanging"><lb/>Of Sweet-Almonds blanched, number <w part="I"
            >fif-</w><lb/><w part="F">teen</w>; of Seeds of Melons, Pumpions, <lb/>Violets, each two
          Drachms; bruiſe them <lb/>together in a marble Mortar, pouring <lb/>on them, gradually, a
          Quart of Barley-<lb/>Water; ſtrain it for uſe; drink often of <lb/>it, a Quarter of a
          Pint, or ſix Ounces, <lb/>Day or Night. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic hanging"><lb/><hi rend="roman">Or,</hi> Take of Seeds of Violets,
          three <lb/>Drachms; of Seeds of Pumpions, <w part="I">Me-</w><lb/><w part="F">lons</w>,
          white Poppies, each two Drachms; <lb/>eight blanched Sweet-Almonds; bruiſe <lb/>them
          together in a Mortar, and pour <lb/>upon them, Milk-Water, and Corn <lb/>Poppy-Water, each
          a Pint, ſtrain it, <lb/>and make it an Emulſion to be drank as <lb/>the others </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_42" n="35"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Oily Medicines, are likewiſe very uſeful, as <lb/>they envelop and
          ſoften the acid and <w part="I">acrimo-</w><lb/><w part="F">nious</w> Juices, and promote
          the Expulſion of <lb/>the Stone, as thus, </p>
        <p rend="italic indent hanging"><lb/>Take two Spoonfuls of Linſeed-Oil, newly <lb/>drawn,
          without Fire, twice a Day. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic hanging"><lb/><hi rend="roman">Or,</hi> Take new Oil of
          Sweet-Almonds, and <lb/>Linſeed-Oil, drawn without Fire, each <lb/>an Ounce; of Syrup of
          Marſh-mallows, <lb/>and Violets, of each ſix Drachms; of <lb/>Syrup of Lemons, half an
          Ounce; of <lb/>Saffron, rubbd fine, half a Scruple; mix <lb/>them well to make a Linctus:
          Take a <lb/>Spoonful often, ſhaking it well. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic hanging"><lb/><hi rend="roman">Or,</hi> Take an Ounce of freſh Oil of
          Sweet-<lb/>Almonds, in a Quarter of a Pint of the <lb/>Decoction for the Syrup of <w
            part="I">Marſh-mal-</w><lb/><w part="F">lows</w>, and repeat it frequently. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Riding in a Coach, or on Horſeback, in <lb/>rough unequal Ground, or
          our paved Streets, <lb/>conduces much to the Diſcharge of the Stone, <lb/>or Gravel, when
          either one or t'other ſticks <lb/>in the Ureter, or <hi rend="italic">Pelvis,</hi> if the
          Patient can <lb/>endure it. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And while theſe Remedies are made Uſe of, <lb/>opiate Medicines muſt
          be given, mingled with <lb/>them, or alone, to abate the ſpaſmodick <w part="I">Con-</w>
          <pb xml:id="page_43" n="36"/><lb/><w part="F">traction</w> of the tender Membranes, and
          give <lb/>Eaſe to the diſordered and afflicted Spirits, that <lb/>they being lulled to
          Reſt and Quiet, may ceaſe <lb/>their convulſive Graſps, and the mean Time <lb/>the Stone,
          or Gravel, ſollicited by city ſmooth <lb/>Remedies, ſlippery and gentle Diureticks, may
          <lb/>ſlide through the Ureters, and drop, or paſs, <lb/>into the Bladder without
          Reſiſtance. </p>
        <p rend="italic indent hanging"><lb/>Take of crude Opium, diſſolved and ſtrained, <lb/>a
          Grain and half, or two Graine; of the <lb/>pectoral Decoction, a Quarter of a Pint;
          <lb/>Syrup of Lemons, three Drachms; make <lb/>it a Draught, to be taken at Night, or
          <lb/>at any Time when the Pain is violent, <lb/>and repeat it as the Symptoms ſhall <w
            part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">quire</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic hanging"><lb/><hi rend="roman">Or,</hi> Take of Cinnabar of Antimony,
          half a <lb/>Scruple; Crabbs-Eyes and Coral, of each <lb/>ſix Grains; Laudanum Opiatum, a
          Grain <lb/>and half; make it a Powder, to be taken <lb/>at the Draught now preſcribed. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>If the Patient is diſpoſed to Vomiting, or <lb/>ſtraining to Vomit,
          let him take two <w part="I">Spoon-</w><lb/><w part="F">fuls</w> of the following Mixture,
          and repeat it <lb/>four or five times, once in four Hours. </p>
        <p rend="italic indent hanging"><lb/>Take of Mint-Water, or Barley Cinnamon-<lb/>Water, two
          Ounces; of Juice of Lemons, <pb xml:id="page_44" n="37"/><lb/>two Ounces; of Salt of
          Wormwood, <lb/>a Drachm and half; of Laudanum, a <lb/>Grain and half; make a Mixture. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>For eaſing the Pain, and facilitating the <lb/>Paſſage of the Stone,
          or Gravel, various <w part="I">diu-</w><lb/><w part="F">retick</w> Remedies are
          recommended, by <w part="I">emi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nent</w> Phyſicians, the following
          Decoction of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Forreſtus,</hi> is for this Purpoſe, much cried up. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic hanging"><lb/>Take of Seeds of Mallows, <w part="I"
            >Marſh-mal-</w><lb/><w part="F">lows</w>, each two Drachms and half; of <lb/>fat lenten
          Figgs, cut and ſliced, <w part="I">num-</w><lb/><w part="F">ber</w> nine; Sebeſtens in
          number ſeven; <lb/>boil theſe Ingredients in three Quarts <lb/>of Water, to three Pints:
          This ſoft <lb/>and ſlippery Decoction, like that for <lb/>making Syrup of Marſh-mallows,
          or <lb/>the pectoral Decoction, in the <hi rend="roman">London</hi>
          <lb/>Diſpenſatory, may be improved by <w part="I">o-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w>
          diurclick Ingredients, <hi rend="roman">(viz.)</hi> Seeds <lb/>of Burdock, Roots of
          Fennel, Violets, <lb/>Eringo, wild Carrots, Juniper-<lb/>Berries, &amp;c. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_45" n="38"/>
        <p rend="italic indent hanging"><lb/>In a Fit of the Stone likewiſe, the <w part="I"
            >De-</w><lb/><w part="F">coction</w> of the Flowers of Camomile, is <lb/>much applauded
          by ſome worthy <w part="I">Phy-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſicians</w>; and that of the
          Water-Lilly; <lb/>and if ſome Drops of ſweet Spirit of <lb/>Salt, or Vitriol, were added
          to each <lb/>Draught of ſuch diuretick Apozems, <lb/>their Force would be ſtill improved.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="chapter">
        <head rend="italic indent hanging size(1.7)"><lb/><hi rend="roman">IV.</hi>
          <lb/>To preſerve from, or prevent the <lb/>return of Fits of the <hi rend="roman"
            >Stone,</hi> or <lb/><hi rend="roman">Gravel,</hi> when the <w part="I">Pa-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">roxyſms</w> ceaſe. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc"><hi rend="dc(4)">G</hi>entle</hi> Purgatives of <hi
            rend="italic">Sena, Rhubarb, <lb/>Elixir Salutis,</hi> &amp;c. taken once in a
          <lb/>Month or ſix Weeks, are beneficial, as they <lb/>cleanſe the Stomach, and their
          appending <lb/>Roads from their Impurities, and the crude <lb/>and unconcocted Remains of
          the Foods <w part="I">ingeſt-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>; but the beſt Way is frequently
          to uſe <w part="I">purg-</w><pb xml:id="page_46" n="39"/><lb/>Mineral Waters; and in the
          Intervals, <w part="I">diu-</w><lb/><w part="F">retick</w> and alterative Remedies, ſhould
          be <lb/>taken, ſuch as theſe that follow. </p>
        <p rend="italic indent hanging"><lb/>Take of the Pulp of candied Citron-Peel, <lb/>and of
          the Root of Marſh-mallows, each <lb/>an Ounce; of Species Dialthaeae, and <w part="I"
            >Di-</w><lb/><w part="F">atragacanth</w> frigid, each a Drachm and <lb/>half; of
          Crabbs-Eyes, two Drachms; of <lb/>the Seeds of Purſlain, and white <w part="I"
            >Pop-</w><lb/><w part="F">pies</w>, each a Drachm; of the Fruit of <lb/>Alkakengi, two
          Scruples; of Gumm <w part="I">Ara-</w><lb/><w part="F">bick</w>, two Drachms; Syrup of <w
            part="I">Marſh-</w><lb/><w part="F">mallows</w>, as much as will make an <w part="I"
            >Elec-</w><lb/><w part="F">tuary</w>; take the Quantity of a large <lb/>Nutmeg, or ſmall
          Cheſnut, twice a Day, <lb/>Drinking after it, a Quarter of a Pint <lb/>of the Decoction
          for the Syrup of <w part="I">Marſh-</w><lb/><w part="F">mallows</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But for cleanſing the Kidneys, and <w part="I">carry-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ing</w> off the Sand and gritty Concreſcences, <lb/>leſt by daily Augmentation,
          they ſhould at <lb/>laſt form a larger Stone, ſlippery and oily <w part="I">Re-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">medies</w>, and Turpentine, ſuch as mentioned <lb/>above, Whey, and above all,
          unpurging <w part="I">Mi-</w><lb/><w part="F">neral</w> Waters of all Kinds, but chiefly
          the <w part="I">Cha-</w><lb/><w part="F">ybeate</w>, ſuch as <hi rend="italic"
            >Tunbridge,</hi> muſt be relied <lb/>upon; or the <hi rend="italic">Iſlington</hi>
          Waters, call'd <hi rend="italic">New-</hi><pb xml:id="page_47" n="40"/><hi rend="italic"
            ><lb/>Tunbridge</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Millepedes</hi>, are alſo a good <w part="I"
            >Diu-</w><lb/><w part="F">retick</w> in this Caſe: But I have above treated <lb/>on this
          Subject, where I have diſcourſed on the <lb/>Gravel, and ſmall ſandy Concretions, which
          <lb/>are the minuteſt real Stones, and the Seeds <lb/>and Rudiments, that by their
          Conſluence <lb/>and Coherence, produce thoſe of a greater <w part="I">Dimen-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſion</w>, and to that Diſcourſe I refer the Reader; <lb/>for the true Method of
          preſerving the Patient <lb/>from the Return of his Paroxyſms, is to <w part="I"
            >pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">vent</w> the Generation of ſuch fabulous <w part="I"
            >Mate-</w><lb/><w part="F">rials</w>, out of which the Stone is made, or to <lb/>carry
          them off before they have formed ſuch <lb/>large Bodies. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is very uſeful in a Paroxyſm of the Stone, <lb/>to go into a <hi
            rend="italic">Bath</hi> of Spring-Water moderately <lb/>warm, which by ſtopping Sweat
          and <w part="I">Perſpi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ration</w>, and ſoothing the Spirits, relaxing
          and <lb/>dilating the Fibres, promotes Urine, and <lb/>therefore the Protruſion and
          Expulſion of the <lb/>Stones, that hang or ſtick in the Ureters <lb/>which after they have
          acquired a conſiderable <lb/>Magnitude, will notwithſtanding ſtrive and <lb/>make their
          Way for a while through thoſe <lb/>Tubes, which are much ſtretched and enlarged <lb/>by
          being the beaten Road for Stones to paſs <lb/>from the Kidneys to the Bladder; yet at
          length <lb/>they encreaſe to ſuch a Size, that when they <lb/>have entered the Orifice of
          the Ureter, and <pb xml:id="page_48" n="41"/><lb/>are incapable of proceeding farther,
          they plug <lb/>up the Paſſage, and ſtop the Current of the <lb/>Urine; and if afterwards
          another Stone of ſuch <lb/>a diſproportionate Size, ſhould fall from the <lb/>Kidney into
          the Mouth of the other Tube, a <lb/>total Suppreſſion of Urine and Death in a <lb/>ſhort
          Time, that is, in ten or eleven Days, are <lb/>the Conſequence; for a total and
          deſtructive <lb/>Stoppage of the Urine, cannot ariſe from the <lb/>Obſtruction of one
          Ureter; for Nature that has <lb/>framed ſo many double Organs for other <w part="I"
            >Func-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w>, two Eyes, two Ears, two Jugular Veins, <lb/>two
          Lobes of the Lungs, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> that if one of <lb/>theſe Inſtruments
          ſhould be loſt or become <lb/>defective, the other, at leaſt in a great Meaſure,
          <lb/>might perform the Office of both; ſo it has <lb/>evidently for the more certain and
          effectual <lb/>Secretion of the Urine, provided a pair of <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">veyances</w>, one in each Kidney, that if one be <lb/>entirely diſabled and
          ſtopped up, the other <lb/>may do double Duty, and diſcharge the <w part="I"
            >Por-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of Serum, that uſed to run through the <lb/>other
          Aquaeduct. It is therefore evident to a <lb/>Demonſtration, that no total Suppreſſion of
          <lb/>the Urine can happen, where both the Ureters <lb/>are not entirely ſtopped; and it is
          hard to <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceive</w> how at any Time two Stones ſhould
          at <lb/>once fall down, one from each Kidney, and <lb/>ſtop in the ſame Inſtant, each of
          thoſe Organs <pb xml:id="page_49" n="42"/><lb/>of Separation: If therefore a full Stoppage
          of <lb/>Water happens, and neither of the Ureters was <lb/>before that Time obſtructed, it
          is moſt <w part="I">agree-</w><lb/><w part="F">able</w> to Reaſon, that we ſhould aſſign
          another <lb/>Cauſe of that Event, that is, a paralytick <w part="I">Im-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">potence</w> of the ſecretory ſmall Tubes and <w part="I">pa-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">pillary</w> Glands, which ſtrain the Serum from <lb/>the Blood, through the
          Kidneys and Ureters, <lb/>into the Bladder; for if theſe ſecretory Tubes <lb/>by a <hi
            rend="italic">Paralyſis</hi> affecting the Spirits reſiding in <lb/>them, quite loſe
          their Tenſion and falling flat <lb/>together cloſe up their <hi rend="italic"
            >Foramina,</hi> or Paſſages, <lb/>no Serum can be longer ſeparated from the <lb/>Blood,
          or conveyed into the Receptacle of <lb/>the Urine; and this will prove as effectual and
          <lb/>adaequate a Cauſe of a total Obſtruction of <lb/>Urine, as if both the Ureters were
          compleatly <lb/>ſtopped by the falling of two Stones of <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">proportionate</w> Size into their Mouths. And <lb/>this was the Caſe of an
          illuſtrious Perſon, one <lb/>of the firſt Rank of the <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi>
          Nobility, who <lb/>having for ſeveral Years been afflicted with <lb/>the Gout, one Day
          felt a ſevere Pain in one of <lb/>his Shoulders, which after ſome Time ceaſed <lb/>to
          afflict him; but he had not been long at <lb/>Eaſe, when the Flow of his Urine was
          entirely <lb/>interrupted, and continued ſo to the eleventh <lb/>Day, when the noble
          Patient expired, <w part="I">not-</w><lb/><w part="F">withſtanding</w> all the Means and
          Methods that <pb xml:id="page_50" n="43"/><lb/>his Phyſicians, of whom I had the Honour to
          <lb/>be one, could direct for his Recovery. Upon <lb/>opening the dead Body there
          appeared, when <lb/>the K<unclear>#</unclear>dneys were divided, ſome ſmall Stones <lb/>in
          the <hi rend="italic">Pelvis,</hi> and others entangled in the <lb/>Fibres or Strings of
          the Kidneys, but no Stone <lb/>in the Mouth or Channel of either Ureter; ſo <lb/>nothing
          can be more certain, nor more <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">vious</w> to the meaneſt
          Capacity than this, that <lb/>the Stone could not be the Cauſe of hindring <lb/>the Water
          from deſcending into the Bladder, <lb/>no Stone being found in the Ureters, nor in
          <lb/>the Kidneys, of a Size capable of ſtopping the <lb/>Tubes before-named; and had there
          been bred <lb/>in the Kidneys, any Stones of a ſufficient <w part="I">Big-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ness</w>, to have compleatly ſtopped the Ureters, <lb/>yet it muſt be ſuppoſed,
          as before ſuggeſted, <lb/>that two Stones of ſuch a Magnitude fell at <lb/>the ſame
          Inſtant, one into the Orifice of each <lb/>Ureter, elſe a total Suppreſſion of Urine could
          <lb/>not have followed; and this muſt be ſuppoſed <lb/>ſcarce ever to have happened, and
          is but <w part="I">bare-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> poſſible. But <hi rend="italic">de
            facio,</hi> there were no ſuch <lb/>Stoppage found in either Ureter. Yet <w part="I"
            >not-</w><lb/><w part="F">withſtanding</w> one of the Phyſicians declared <lb/>his
          Opinion, and obſtinately perſevered in it, <lb/>that the Suppreſſion of Urine, of which
          the <lb/>Patient dyed, proceeded from the Stone in <lb/>The Kidneys. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_51" n="44"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe are the beſt preſervatory Means <lb/>againſt the Return of this
          formidable Diſeaſe, <lb/>ſince the true and effectual Way, as mentioned <lb/>above, is
          either to enable the active <w part="I">Princi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ples</w> of the Blood
          to keep the Maſs in ſuch an <lb/>equal, regular, and juſt Mixture, and to refine <lb/>and
          exalt it to ſuch an healthful State, as may <lb/>prevent the Generation of hard and gritty
            <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">creſcences</w>, that as they are the Foundation of
          <lb/>the Stone, ſo they adminiſter Materials for <lb/>the Superſtructure; and for
          procuring this <lb/>End, the Remedies already enumerated are <lb/>moſt availing, in as
          much as they animate <lb/>and enliven the Spirits, refine and elevate the <lb/>Maſs of
          Blood, and diſſolve and ſever <w part="I">creta-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceous</w> or ſandy
          Coalitions, by maintaining its <lb/>Circulation with a due Celerity. To theſe <lb/>may be
          added ſuch Medicines as ſubdue the <lb/>acid and acrimonious Quality of the Juices, by
          <lb/>blunting and ſmoothing their ſharp Points and <lb/>Angles, ſuch as <hi rend="italic"
            >Coral, Crabbs-Eyes, Crabbs-<lb/>Claws, Oyſter-ſhells,</hi> and other teſtaceous, <w
            part="I">ab-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſorbing</w> and correcting Powders, given with <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Aſſes-Milk,</hi> or mixed with other Ingredients <lb/>in Pius or
          Electuaries; and likewiſe thoſe, that <lb/>are proper to aſſiſt the digeſtive Faculty of
          the <lb/>Stomach, to concoct the Foods and Liquors <lb/>it receives, into a wholeſome
          well-laboured <lb/>and duly mixed Maſs of Chyle, that the <w part="I">un-</w><pb
            xml:id="page_52" n="45"/><lb/>and fæculent Parts, the firſt Seeds <lb/>and Principles
          which by their Union and <lb/>Coacervation produce the Stone, may be <lb/>prevented. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Forms of ſuch Medicines that <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >mote</w> Digeſtion in the Stomach, are ſuch <lb/>as theſe. </p>
        <p rend="italic indent hanging"><lb/>Take of Conſerve of Roman Wormwood, of <lb/>candied
          Citron Peel, or the outward <lb/>yellow Rind of the Orange, each an <lb/>Ounce; of Coral,
          Crabbs-Eyes, and Pearl, <lb/>each a Drachm; of candied Nutmegs, a <lb/>Drachm and half; of
          Salt of Wormwood <lb/>and Tartar, each two Scruples; of <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">pound</w> Powder of Wake-Robin, and the <lb/>Leaves of Chamaepitys, each a
          Drachm <lb/>and half; of the Syrup from candied <w part="I">Nut-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >meg</w>, as much as will make an Electuary. <lb/>Take the quantity of a large Nutmeg,
          <lb/>every Morning and Evening, <w part="I">drink-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> after it, a
          Glaſs of Wormwood-wine, <lb/>or the Infuſion of the Root of Gentian, <lb/>or Twenty Drops
          of the Tincture of <w part="I">Gen-</w><lb/><w part="F">tian</w> in a Glaſs of White-wine. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic hanging"><lb/><hi rend="roman">Or,</hi> Take of the Tops of Roman <w
            part="I">Worm-</w><lb/><w part="F">wood</w>, and the leſſer Centaury, each half a
          <lb/>Pugil; of the Root of Gentian, and <w part="I">Vir-</w><pb xml:id="page_53" n="46"
          /><lb/>ginian Snake-root, each a Drachm; of <lb/>Cardamom Seeds, two Scruples; of <w
            part="I">Cori-</w><lb/><w part="F">ander</w> Seeds, two Drachms and half; of <lb/>Salt
          of Tartar a Drachm; infuſe all in a <lb/>ſufficient Quantity of Spring-Water to <lb/>a
          Quart; ſtrain it, and add to it, of <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">pound</w>
          Wormwood, and compound <w part="I">Gen-</w><lb/><w part="F">tian</w> Water, each an Ounce
          and half; take <lb/>a Quarter of a Pint each Morning <w part="I">faſt-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ing</w>, and alſo in the Afternoon, about <lb/>three Hours after Dinner. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic roman"><lb/><hi rend="roman">Sometimes</hi> Take of Elixir Propriet
          at is <w part="I">tar-</w><lb/><w part="F">tariſed</w>, five and twenty, or thirty Drops
          <lb/>in a Glaſs of Mountain White-wine, <lb/>twice a Day, viz. <hi rend="italic">at about
            Eleven and <lb/>Four.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Beſides theſe Remedies, moderate Exerciſe, <lb/>pure and well
          ventilated Air, Regularity and <lb/>Temperance, in Eating and Drinking, muſt be
          <lb/>carefully obſerved, without which the beſt <lb/>Methods of Phyſick may be unavailing. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As to thoſe Medicines called by the <hi rend="italic">Greek</hi>
          <lb/>Phyſicians <hi rend="italic">Lithontriptica,</hi> that is, ſuch as <lb/>break and
          diſſolve the Stone, either in the <lb/>Kidneys or Bladder, and to which many <w part="I"
            >Em-</w><lb/><w part="F">piricks</w> have pretended, aſſuring us that they
          <lb/>gradually wear and crumble it away, and <w part="I">re-</w><pb xml:id="page_54"
            n="47"/><lb/><w part="F">duce</w> it to ſuch minute Fragments, that they <lb/>eaſily
          paſs the Ureters into the Bladder, and <lb/>with the ſame eaſe ſlide through, and are <w
            part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">cluded</w> thence together with the Urine: I <w
            part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">knowledge</w> I am incapable of conceiving how <lb/>a
          Medicine ingeſted by the Mouth can produce <lb/>this Effect. It is true, that the
          celebrated <hi rend="italic">Car-<lb/>thaginian</hi> General <hi rend="italic"
            >Hannibal,</hi> as Hiſtorians <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">port</w>, found means
          by Vinegar, or ſome <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">vented</w> ſharp and acid Liquor,
          to diſſolve the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Alpine</hi> Rocks, and ſo to eat his Way through
          <lb/>thoſe Mountains into <hi rend="italic">Italy.</hi> But if any <w part="I"
            >Pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tient</w>, afflicted with the Stone, ſhould ſwallow <lb/>a
          proper Quantity of this powerful Fluid, were <lb/>it to be had, or any other of like
          Vertue, ſince <lb/>it muſt firſt undergo a great Alteration by the <lb/>Ferment and
          digeſtive Faculty of the Stomach, <lb/>and then a farther by mixing with the bilious
          <lb/>Humours deſcending from the Gall-Bladder, <lb/>and afterwards with the acid Juices
          iſſuing <lb/>from the <hi rend="italic">Pancreas,</hi> and then another by <w part="I"
            >paſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſing</w> the lacteal Strainers, and mingling its <lb/>Stores
          with the Lympha brought by numerous <lb/>Water-Pipes into the common Receptacles;
          <lb/>then another by its Admiſſion into the Veins, <lb/>where during repeated Circulations
          with great <lb/>Celerity, the Parts by innumerable Attritions, <lb/>Reverberations, and
          Glances from their violent <lb/><unclear>##</unclear>ſhing and beating one upon another,
          receive <pb xml:id="page_55" n="48"/><lb/>great Comminution, and are attenuated, <w
            part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">alted</w>, and ſmoothed, till they acquire a <w
            part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">fined</w> volatile State; and at laſt of all, ſince
          they <lb/>muſt receive another Alteration by entering <lb/>and paſſing the urinary
          Strainers in the <w part="I">Kid-</w><lb/><w part="F">neys</w>: Let, I ſay, all theſe
          Changes be <w part="I">contem-</w><lb/><w part="F">plated</w>, and will not, do you think,
          the <w part="I">Medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cine</w> ingeſted be unedged and diſarmed of its
          <lb/>ſharp Points and Angles, and loſe all its <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſolving</w> or Stone-cutting Quality? For no acid <lb/>Juices, not Vinegar itſelf,
          continue acid after <lb/>they have mingled and circulated with the <lb/>Blood, and have
          felt for ſome Time, the <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F">geſtive</w> Power of its
          active Principles. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Thoſe bold Perſons therefore that pretend <lb/>to be Maſters of
          Remedies, which given by the <lb/>Mouth, will break or diſſolve the Stone in the
          <lb/>Kidneys, or the Bladder, impoſe upon <w part="I">Man-</w><lb/><w part="F">kind</w>,
          not only becauſe the Medicine loſes its <lb/>peculiar Qualities, by undergoing ſuch a <w
            part="I">Va-</w><lb/><w part="F">riety</w> of Changes and Alterations, as have been
          <lb/>enumerated, but likewiſe by mingling and <lb/>being diluted with above Twenty Pound
          of <lb/>Blood, (for few Men have leſs) and <w part="I">frequent-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ly</w> running its Circuit with it, by which means <lb/>it becomes quite another Thing,
          before it <lb/>reaches the Stone it was deſigned to diſſolve <lb/>or crumble to pieces. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_56" n="49"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It muſt be obſerved, that as <w part="I">above-menti-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">oned</w>, there are ſome porus, light, and friable <lb/>Stones, whoſe
          Conſtructure is ſo ſlight, that <lb/>they will by a little Shock or Colliſion, <w part="I"
            >crum-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w>, and be divided into ſmall Fragments, while <lb/>the
          Parts of others ſo ſtrictly cohere, that they <lb/>are ſcarcely capable of Separation; and
          it is <lb/>of theſe harder and more ſolid Stones that I <lb/>ſpeak, when I ſay they cannot
          be broken, or <lb/>cut in pieces, by Remedies given at the Mouth, <lb/>but they defy the
          Edge of the keeneſt <hi rend="italic">Lithon-<lb/>triptick</hi> Weapon in all the Arſenals
          of <hi rend="italic">Greece.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>When therefore Stones or Gravel are at any <lb/>Time removed from the
          Kidneys, and <w part="I">exclu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ded</w> with the Urine, it is not by
          Vertue of any <lb/>Stone-breaking Medicine, acting upon them, <lb/>but by the Operation of
          its diuretick Quality, <lb/>exciting a great Separation of Serum, which <lb/>ruſhing in a
          ſwift Current through the <w part="I">Kid-</w><lb/><w part="F">neys</w>, waſhes away in
          its Streams the Gravel <lb/>and Stones lodged there, that by their <w part="I"
            >propor-</w><lb/><w part="F">tionate</w> Magnitude are capable of paſſing the
          <lb/>Ureters, as a ſudden Storm or ſharp Shower of <lb/>Rain, rolls down the Streets in
          its Torrent, <lb/>the Sand and looſe Stones, as well as other <lb/>promiſcuous Impurities
          to be carried off by <lb/>the common Drain: Though it is very <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">bable</w> that ſometimes this Flood of Serum, <pb xml:id="page_57" n="50"
          /><lb/>tranſmitted from the Veins by its immoderate <lb/>Quantity, as well as the Strength
          of its Tide, <lb/>in its Paſſage through the Kidneys, may <w part="I">like-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">wiſe</w> diſunite, and ſhatter to Pieces ſome <lb/>ſmaller friable Stones,
          whoſe Parts hang <w part="I">toge-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> by a very ſlight
          Connexion. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But if Nature or Art can afford any <w part="I">Medi-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">cines</w>, that are capable of breaking a hard <lb/>large Stone in the Bladder,
          the moſt probable <lb/>Way of making them effectual, would be to <lb/>inject them directly
          into the Bladder; for then, <lb/>having undergone none of thoſe various <w part="I"
            >Al-</w><lb/><w part="F">terations</w> above enumerated, which thoſe <w part="I"
            >Re-</w><lb/><w part="F">medies</w> muſt do that are taken by the Mouth, <lb/>they would
          exert their Stone-diſſolving <w part="I">Ver-</w><lb/><w part="F">tue</w>, if they have
          any, entire and <w part="I">undiminiſh-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>, and would have the
          great Advantage of <lb/>acting upon it by immediate Contact, by <lb/>which means the Stone
          in the Bladder, if it <lb/>could be effected by Medicines, would be <lb/>waſted and
          moulder away. But Experience <lb/>ſhews that this is not found practicable; for <lb/>were
          ſuch a Medicine diſcovered, it would <lb/>prevent the Tortures and Miſery of many <w
            part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">happy</w> Patients, and make the uſeful Art of
          <lb/>Cutting for the Stone unneceſſary, of which <lb/>I ſhall ſpeak afterwards. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_58" n="51"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>When large Stones are bred in the Kidneys, <lb/>or ſuch as cannot
          paſs, but with great Pain and <lb/>Difficulty, all forcing diuretick Medicines <lb/>muſt,
          be forborn, and only ſuch as are ſmooth, <lb/>oily, and ſlippery ſhould be employed; leſt
          <lb/>ſuch as powerfully provoke Urine, ſhould <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >turb</w> and puſh forward the bigger, that lay <lb/>quiet in the Kidneys, into the
          Ureters, where <lb/>they will either ſtop at the Entrance, or ſtick <lb/>in the Paſſage,
          and by that Means either ſhut <lb/>up the Mouth, or create a violent Fit of Pain,
          <lb/>together with bloody Urine, if their Surface <lb/>be rough and ragged; and therefore
          in ſuch <lb/>Caſes, ſlimy, ſoft, and mucilaginous Remedies, <lb/>are chiefly to be
          depended on, to promote the <lb/>ſlipping of the Stone into the Bladder: And <lb/>if
          active Diureticks, have been employed in <lb/>vain to puſh on the Stone, which often <w
            part="I">hap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pens</w> in a violent Paroxyſm, opiate Medicines
          <lb/>of good Force ſhould be given, that the Fibres <lb/>of the encloſing Membranes,
          whilſt <w part="I">ſtimu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lated</w> by the Torture of the Stone, and
          urged <lb/>by the Medicine deſigned to expel it, being <lb/>eaſed and lulled by their
          narcotick Vertue, <lb/>may ceaſe to contract themſelves and claſp <lb/>the Stone ſo
          cloſely, and by dilating and <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">laxing</w> themſelves
          while at Eaſe, may make <lb/>Way for it to ſlide through into the Bladder. <pb
            xml:id="page_59" n="52"/><lb/>But if the Stone in the Kidneys is large, ſolid, <lb/>and
          branches through their Subſtance, no <lb/>Means at all ſhould be uſed for its Cure; for
          <lb/>if there are any Remedies that have Power to <lb/>break and diſlodge its Fragments,
          which I <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">lieve</w>, as I have ſaid, there are not, what
          <lb/>would that be, but to ſend them down to ſtop <lb/>the Ureters, or to give
          unſufferable Torments, <lb/>by ſticking in their Channels! </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As to the Stone in the Bladder, which, as <lb/>ſaid above, is no more
          than a Stone firſt <lb/>bred in the Kidney, and thence conveyed <lb/>through the Ureters;
          where it receives its <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">long</w> Figure, into the
          Bladder, and gains there <lb/>ſuch a Magnitude, that it becomes incapable <lb/>of being
          expelled with the Urine, being fed <lb/>and augmented continually with new Gritt <lb/>and
          ſandy Materials waſhed from the Kidneys <lb/>and falling down into the Bladder; when it
          <lb/>firſt deſcends into that Receptacle, and its Size <lb/>does not exceed a due
          Proportion, while it <lb/>floats in the Urine, it often plays, aims, and <lb/>offers at
          the Orifice of the Urethra, but its <w part="I">Fi-</w><lb/><w part="F">gure</w> or
          Poſition not being accommodated to <lb/>it, cannot paſs through that urinary Channel;
          <lb/>and then it not only creates great Uneaſineſs, <lb/>by lying croſs its Mouth, but
          likewiſe often by <lb/>interrupting the Streams of Urine, and <w part="I">ſome-</w><pb
            xml:id="page_60" n="53"/><lb/><w part="F">times</w> by totally obſtructing the Paſſage.
          When <lb/>the Gravel, or Stone, or Stones, are yet ſmall <lb/>enough to enter and paſs the
          Urethra, to <w part="I">faci-</w><lb/><w part="F">litate</w> their Diſcharge, the Veins
          ſhould be <lb/>filled with ſuch diuretick Liquors, as I have <lb/>before ſet down, that
          they may communicate <lb/>a conſtant Flow of Urine to the Bladder, <lb/>which being
          commonly kept full, will be the <lb/>more apt to eject the Stone, together with the
          <lb/>Flood that diſtends it. But if it grows ſo <lb/>great, that it becomes unable to make
          its Way, <lb/>by Reaſon of its diſproportionate Size, it will <lb/>be daily augmented by
          the Accretion or <w part="I">Ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">dition</w> of new Gritt or Gravel,
          carried from <lb/>the Kidneys, through the Ureters, by the <lb/>Streams of Urine, as Sand
          and ſmall Stones, <lb/>are rolled along from a riſing Ground, by Rills <lb/>of Water, that
          flow down its Sides. Now theſe <lb/>Sands or minute Concretions, as I have <w part="I"
            >ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">plained</w> above, are the Seeds, or Mother of the <lb/>Stone,
          that is, the Principles or firſt Materials, <lb/>that combine for the Formation of it in
          the <lb/>Kidneys, and afterwards to its Augmentation <lb/>in the Bladder; and to hinder
          its encreaſing <lb/>there to a great Magnitude, thoſe Remedies <lb/>are to be uſed which
          were enumerated before, <lb/>for cutting off the Generation of Gravel, and <lb/>ſuch ſandy
          and fabulous Combinations; to <lb/>which I refer the Reader. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_61" n="54"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But if through Neglect, or the Inability of <lb/>Methods and Medicines
          to prevent the <w part="I">breed-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> of Sand and Gravel in the
          Kidneys, which <lb/>waſhed away by the Urine into the Bladder, <lb/>conſtantly feed and
          amplify the Stones <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">fined</w> there, which grow not
          like Animals and <lb/>Vegetables, by Nouriſhment admitted by the <lb/>Mouth or the Root,
          and conveyed and <w part="I">diſtri-</w><lb/><w part="F">buted</w> to the outward Parts
          from the inward, <lb/>but by the daily Acceſs, Accumulation, and <lb/>Adheſion, of hard,
          ſandy Particles to the <w part="I">Sur-</w><lb/><w part="F">face</w> of the Stone; if, I
          ſay, the Stone, by the <lb/>Arrival and Complication of new petrifying <lb/>Principles,
          becomes large and ponderous, and <lb/>being attended with a terrible Train of <w part="I"
            >Symp-</w><lb/><w part="F">toms</w>, that render the Patient a great Object of
          <lb/>Compaſſion, while Death is more eligible <lb/>than Life, and no effectual Means can
          be <w part="I">ſug-</w><lb/><w part="F">geſted</w>, how it may be cut, diſſolved, or <w
            part="I">crum-</w><lb/><w part="F">bled</w> to pieces, as I have before demonſtrated,
          <lb/>all that can be done by Medicine, is to quiet <lb/>or reduce the enormous Pains and
          Torments, <lb/>inflicted by this cruel Diſeaſe; and for the <w part="I">ef-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">fecting</w> of this, only <hi rend="italic">crude Opium,</hi> or its <w
            part="I">Pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">parations</w>, the Gift of Divine Benignity to <w
            part="I">mi-</w><lb/><w part="F">tigate</w> the Tortures, and alleviate the extream
          <lb/>Miſeries of Mankind, can be depended on. <lb/>This is the Patient's Refuge, and the
          only <w part="I">Con-</w><pb xml:id="page_62" n="55"/><lb/><w part="F">ſolation</w> to
          allay his Agonies, and reſtrain the <lb/>Rage of his Sufferings. And therefore in this
          <lb/>Caſe, let him take the following Pills. </p>
        <p rend="italic indent hanging"><lb/>Take of Saffron, beat ſmall, three Grains; <lb/>of
          Extract of Gentian, ſix Grains; of <lb/>crude Opium diſſolved and ſtrained, a <lb/>Grain
          and half; Balſamick Syrup, <lb/>enough to make it into Pills, for one <lb/>Doſe, to be
          taken in violent Pains, and <lb/>repeated when the Force of the firſt is <lb/>worn off, if
          the Torments continue. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But if the Quantity of <hi rend="italic">Opium</hi> preſcribed, is
          <lb/>not ſufficient to remove the Pain, it may <w part="I">gra-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >dually</w> be encreaſed, by adding a Quarter of a <lb/>Grain; and if that likewiſe
          ſhould be <w part="I">ineffec-</w><lb/><w part="F">tual</w>, add half a Grain, and ſo on,
          till the <w part="I">Pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tient</w> has found what is the juſt Quantity
          that <lb/>will relieve him, and when he has taken his <lb/>Meaſure, and ſettled the
          Proportion, he will <lb/>be obliged to take it as often as his Agonies <lb/>ſhall make it
          abſolutely neceſſary. All <lb/>ſmooth, ſoft, and ſlippery Meats and Drinks, <lb/>as well
          as Medicines muſt be choſen; for <lb/>thoſe of an oppoſite Nature will irritate and
          <lb/>enrage the Paroxyſm, eſpecially if an Ulcer <pb xml:id="page_63" n="56"/><lb/>attends
          the Stone, which is an incurable <w part="I">Diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">eaſe</w>: And as
          Ulcers produced either in the <lb/>Kidneys, or the Neck of the Bladder, from <lb/>other
          Cauſes beſides the Stone, elude the <lb/>Force of all Remedies, which is likewiſe the
          <lb/>Caſe of all other internal Ulcers in the Lungs, <lb/>Liver, <hi rend="italic"
            >&amp;c.</hi> ſo thoſe, that ariſe from the <w part="I">Fret-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ting</w> and Laceration of the Membranes in the <lb/>Kidneys or the Bladder, by Stones
          of a rough <lb/>and ragged Superficies, can never be healed, <lb/>at leaſt while the Stone
          continuing there, is <lb/>always wearing and wounding the Part where <lb/>it lodges: And
          therefore all that can be done, <lb/>is to drink plentifully of ſmooth, and ſoft <w
            part="I">Li-</w><lb/><w part="F">quors</w>, beſides taking ſlippery and oily <w part="I"
            >Reme-</w><lb/><w part="F">dies</w>, that may conſtantly dilute and waſh <w part="I"
            >a-</w><lb/><w part="F">way</w> the ulcerous Matter, leſt gathering <w part="I"
            >to-</w><lb/><w part="F">gether</w> in too great a Quantity, it ſhould ſtop <lb/>the
          Paſſage of the Urine; which Obſtruction <lb/>is ſometimes ſo great, that the Surgeon's
          Hand <lb/>is neceſſarily required to paſs his Catheter <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >to</w> the Bladder, for the Relief of the Patient, <lb/>through which the impriſoned
          Urine may <lb/>flow freely out; and the Patient is obliged to <lb/>fly to this Refuge for
          Eaſe, as often as Clyſters <lb/>and other Medicines ingeſted by the Mouth <lb/>are
          ineffectual. The ſoft and ſmooth Liquors <lb/>that may aſſiſt the Patient, by diluting the
            <pb xml:id="page_64" n="57"/><lb/>corrupt Matter, and making it fit to flow, are
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Mead,</hi> or other Liquors made of <hi rend="italic">Honey;</hi>
          alſo <lb/>Decoctions of <hi rend="italic">Barley, Liquoriſh, <w part="I"
              >Marſh-mal-</w><lb/><w part="F">lows</w>, dryed Figgs, and Raiſins of the Sun,
            <lb/>ſtoned;</hi> or rather, the following Apozem. </p>
        <p rend="italic indent hanging"><lb/>Take of Flowers of Mallows, an handful; <lb/>of Root of
          Marſh-mallows, half an Ounce; <lb/>of ſweet Fennel-Root, an Ounce; of <lb/>Leaves of
          Violet, Parietaria, each a <lb/>Pugil; of Aniſe and Carraway Seeds, <lb/>each a Drachm and
          half; boil all in <lb/>three Pints of Spring-Water, to a Quart, <lb/>ſtrain it, and add of
          Syrup of Marſh-<lb/>mallows, three Ounces; and ſix Drachms <lb/>of the Tincture of
          Saffron, made with <lb/>Treacle-Water; drink half a Pint, or ſix <lb/>Ounces of it, three
          Times a Day. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The ſmootheſt and ſofteſt Spring-Water, <lb/>ſhould be choſen for
          common Drink, ſuch as <lb/>that of <hi rend="italic">Briſtol,</hi> or any other, that
          riſes from <lb/>Chalk-Hills: A good Draught likewiſe of <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >White-wine,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">new Ale,</hi> [mind this] now <lb/>and then
          repeated, is uſeful to diſlodge and <lb/>carry off the noxious and impure Matter, <w
            part="I">iſſu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> from an Ulcer in the Kidneys or Bladder;
          <lb/>and the Sediment of each of them is <w part="I">diſtin-</w><pb xml:id="page_65"
            n="58"/><lb/><w part="F">guiſhed</w> by their ſlimy, glutinous and ropy <lb/>Quality,
          from the white, mealy and light <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tents</w>, found
          often in the Urine, from <w part="I">ſcor-</w><lb/><w part="F">butick</w> Cauſes, as above
          ſuggeſted, that by <lb/>ſhaking the Glaſs, will preſently riſe and float <lb/>in the Boſom
          of it, which however has no <lb/>weight, nor viſcous, nor gritty Quality, but <lb/>ſwims
          in pale, diſcontinued, and incoherent <lb/>Matter, communicated to the Urine from the
          <lb/>Blood, abounding with ſuch Impurities. And <lb/>they are diſcriminated from one
          another, by <lb/>a fætid and offenſive Smell, proper to the <w part="I">Mat-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ter</w> diſcharged from an Ulcer in the Bladder, <lb/>and contracted from long
          mixing with the <lb/>Urine, which is not found in thoſe ſlimy <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tents</w> that flow down from the Kidneys, and <lb/>are excluded with the
          ſerous Streams, as I have <lb/>above explained. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>After all, when notwithſtanding the due <lb/>Care and Obſervance of
          the beſt Rules to <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">vent</w> it, the Stone in the
          Bladder grows very <lb/>large, and the Pains are greater than Humane <lb/>Patience can
          bear, the laſt Refuge from this <lb/>dreadful Tormentor, is manual Operation, <lb/>when
          Inciſion is made into the Bladder, and <lb/>the Stone extracted through the Wound. So
          <lb/>ſtrong is the Principle of Self-Preſervation, <lb/>and ſo terrible the Idea and
          Apprehenſion of <pb xml:id="page_66" n="59"/><lb/>Death, that to continue a little longer
          in <w part="I">Be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>, Men ſubmit, not only to a great Variety
          <lb/>of lingering Sufferings and Calamities, but <lb/>likewiſe to the acuteſt Fains, or
          which their <lb/>yeilding to this Method of curing the Stone, <lb/>is a moſt convincing
          Evidence. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Though the Cutting for the Stone is a <w part="I">pain-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ful</w> Operation, and attended with the Hazard <lb/>of Life, yet many Patients
          have been relieved <lb/>by it, and continued well after it for many <lb/>Years, eſpecially
          thoſe, that were Cut in their <lb/>Youth. Yet it muſt be acknowledged, that <lb/>many alſo
          have miſcarried, either from the <lb/>Nature of the Stone, their ill Habit of Body,
          <lb/>the Unskilfulneſs of the Operator, or his want <lb/>or ſufficient knowledge in
          Surgery to heal the <lb/>Wound. And this Misfortune often happens <lb/>likewiſe from the
          Patient's deferring the <w part="I">Ope-</w><lb/><w part="F">ration</w> too long, out of
          an Abhorrence of the <lb/>Violence of the Cure, or from flattering Hopes <lb/>that the
          Diſeaſe will not ariſe to that <w part="I">Extre-</w><lb/><w part="F">mity</w>, and
          torment them with ſuch <w part="I">inſuffer-</w><lb/><w part="F">able</w> Symptoms. It is
          therefore the Intereſt <lb/>of Perſons afflicted with it, to undergo the <lb/>Operation,
          by which the Stone is extracted, <lb/>when as yet it is of a moderate Size, and <w
            part="I">there-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w> more Eaſily to be drawn through the
          <lb/>Wound, and before their Strength is <w part="I">ex-</w><pb xml:id="page_67" n="60"
            /><lb/><w part="F">hauſted</w> by long Sufferings, and repeated <w part="I"
            >Pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">roxyſms</w> of Torture, and before the Ulcer <lb/>that is often
          formed by it, becomes deep and <lb/>inveterate; and then, while their Vigour is
          <lb/>unwaſted, and their Conſtitution otherwiſe <lb/>hail, and the Stone not of an
          extraordinary <lb/>Magnitude, the Operation is likely to be <w part="I">ſuc-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ceſſful</w>: And if theſe Rules were obſerved, the <lb/>Lives of many of theſe
          unhappy Patients <lb/>might be ſaved, that are loſt for want of a <lb/>timely Submiſſion
          to this Method of Cure. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>When the Stone, lapſed from the Kidneys <lb/>into the Bladder, are not
          augmented there to <lb/>that Proportion, as makes them incapable of <lb/>entering into the
          Mouth of the <hi rend="italic">Urethra,</hi> yet <lb/>ſometimes after it has entered, it
          is however <lb/>too large to make its Way through that <w part="I">Aquæ-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">duct</w>, and therefore ſtops in the Road, where <lb/>it not only creates great
          Pain, but likewiſe <lb/>obſtructs the Current of the Water, till at <lb/>length there is
          no Remedy left but the <w part="I">Sur-</w><lb/><w part="F">geon's</w> Art, who in this
          Caſe eaſily relieves <lb/>the Sufferer, by cutting upon the Stone where <lb/>he feels it
          lodged, and thruſting it forth <lb/>through the Orifice of the Wound: And this <lb/>is the
          moſt practicable and leaſt dangerous <lb/>Inſtance of Cutting for the Stone. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_68" n="61"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As for Cutting into the Bladder, and <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tracting</w> the Stone thence, various Methods <lb/>have been invented, of
          which a diſtinct and <lb/>accurate Hiſtory is not the Buſineſs of this <lb/>Diſſertation:
          It is enough for me in this Place <lb/>to mention the moſt Practicable and ſafeſt
          <lb/>Way, and this, as I am informed, is that of <lb/>cutting into the Bladder, in the
          Region above <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Os Pubis,</hi> lately brought into Uſe. <w
            part="I">Whe-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> there occur any dark and obſcure Hints
          <lb/>of this Practice in ancient or modern Authors, <lb/>or whether the firſt Invention
          does Honour <lb/>to the ingenious Surgeon Mr. <hi rend="italic">Douglaſs,</hi> it is
          <lb/>certain, that either as Reviver or Inventor of <lb/>this new Method, he has deſeryed
          well of <lb/>Mankind, and merited the Thanks and <w part="I">Eſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >teem</w> of all the Faculty, ſince all Ways of <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >forming</w> this Operation known before, were <lb/>accompanied with more difficulty,
          more <w part="I">ſuf-</w><lb/><w part="F">fering</w>, and greater Hazard of Life. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Before the Patient conſents to undergo this <lb/>Method of Cure, great
          Care and Caution <lb/>ſhould be uſed, that the Operator may be ſure <lb/>himſelf, and ſo
          able to ſatisfy the Patient, <lb/>that there is a Stone in the Bladder, the Cauſe <lb/>of
          all his painful Symptoms, and fit to be <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">tracted</w>.
          For there have been other Diſeaſes <lb/>of the Bladder, that have ſo perfectly imitated
            <pb xml:id="page_69" n="62"/><lb/>the Stone in all its Symptoms, and have <w part="I"
            >im-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſed</w> upon Surgeons, eminent in their Art, <lb/>who after
          ſtrict Search have pronounced the <lb/>Caſe to be the Stone, yet when they have cut
          <lb/>the Patient to relieve him, no Stone has been <lb/>found, and upon opening the dead
          Body, <w part="I">ei-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> a <hi rend="italic">Fungus,</hi> or
          ſome Excreſcency, grown <lb/>to a great Bigneſs in the Neck of the Bladder, <lb/>or ſome
          other Diſeaſe, or Errour of Nature <lb/>in the Bladder, appeared to be the only <lb/>Cauſe
          of all the Nephretick-like Symptoms, <lb/>that afflicted the Patient: And therefore, I
          <lb/>ſay, the Undertaker, before he attempts the <lb/>Operation, ought with the greateſt
            <w part="I">Delibera-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, and moſt careful Scrutiny, to get
          the <lb/>fulleſt Conviction in himſelf, of the real <lb/>Exiſtence of the Stone in the
          Place he expects to <lb/>find it. </p>
        <trailer rend=" center"><lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="1"/>
  </text>
</TEI>
