<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Wintringham: An enquiry into the exility of the vessels in a human
          body</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Clifton Wintringham</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">An enquiry into the exility of the vessels in a human body: wherein
              animal identity is Explained, and shewn Incommunicable to any Individual throughout
              the whole Species.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T59012</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T59012"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for Thomas Osborne in Gray's-Inn, sold by M. Coopers,
                  MDCCXLIII.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1743</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="6"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="44"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3309035161</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K051654.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: midwifery"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_1"/>
        <p rend="align-center space"><lb/>AN <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">ENQUIRY</hi>
          <lb/>Into the <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">EXILITY of the VESSELS</hi>
          <lb/>In a <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">Human Body, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
          </hi></p>
        <p rend="align-center"><lb/>Sold by <hi rend="sc">M. Cooper</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
            >Pater-noſter Row.</hi>
          <lb/>Price 1 <hi rend="italic">s.</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_3"/>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="sc">To</hi>
          <lb/>Edward Wilmot, M.D. <lb/>Phyſician in Ordinary to His <lb/>Moſt Sacred <hi rend="sc"
            >Majesty</hi> the <lb/><hi rend="sc">King</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Great Britain,</hi>
          and <lb/>to his Royal Highneſs the <lb/>Prince of <hi rend="italic">Wales;</hi> Fellow of
          <lb/>the College of Phyſicians in <lb/><hi rend="italic">London,</hi> and of the <hi
            rend="italic">Royal <lb/>Society.</hi>
        </head>
        <lb/>
        <salute>SIR, </salute>
        <p rend="space"><lb/>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>Decorative frame around the letter "T".</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HE following Enquiry <lb/>containing ſeveral <w part="I"
            >Par-</w><lb/><w part="F">ticulars</w>, which, tho' <lb/>they have not been hitherto <pb
            xml:id="page_4" n="ii"/><lb/>either regarded, or perhaps <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">derſtood</w> by vulgar Anatomiſts, <lb/>may not on thoſe Accounts at <lb/>all
          the leſs tend to illuſtrate the <lb/>ſurprizing Structure of Animal <lb/>Bodies, requires
          the Protection <lb/>of One, whoſe known Abilities <lb/>in every Branch of Phyſick,
          <lb/>may ſilence the Cavils of thoſe, <lb/>whoſe Penetration ends with <lb/>the Edge of
          their Knife, or the <lb/>Flowing of an Injection. This <lb/>Conſideration alone, had I no
          <lb/>other, is a ſufficient Warrant <lb/>for my Application to you. <lb/>But if the
          ſpontaneous <w part="I">confer-</w><lb/><w part="F">ring</w> of Favours on ſuch, as <pb
            xml:id="page_5" n="iii"/><lb/>had no Claim to them, but the <lb/>mere Benevolence of the
            <w part="I">Do-</w><lb/><w part="F">nor</w>, demands a publick <w part="I"
            >Ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">knowledgment</w>; I ſhould be <lb/>wholly unpardonable, did I
          not <lb/>take this Opportunity of <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">turning</w> you my
          Thanks for <lb/>thoſe ſingular Lights you was <lb/>pleaſed to afford me during <lb/>my
          Attendance at St. <hi rend="italic">Thomas</hi>'s <lb/>Hoſpital, where I had not only
          <lb/>my own Doubts reſolved, but <lb/>new Steps pointed out, by <lb/>that uncommon
          Sagacity, which <lb/>has raiſed you to the higheſt <lb/>Pitch of the Profeſſion, and
          <lb/>rendered you ſo juſtly eſteemed <pb xml:id="page_6" n="iv"/><lb/>by all, who have the
          Honour <lb/>of your Acquaintance. As <lb/>theſe, Sir, were the Motives <lb/>of this my
          Application to you, <lb/>I thought myſelf excuſable in <lb/>not acquainting you with it,
          <lb/>leſt you ſhould prevent me <lb/>from thus acknowledging the <lb/>Obligations I lie
          under, as well <lb/>as declaring how much I am, </p>
        <signed><lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your moſt obliged <lb/>humble Servant,<lb/><hi rend="italic">C.
            Wintringham.</hi>
        </signed>
        <lb/>
        <dateline rend="size(0.5)">Feb. 3. 1742. <lb/>Bennet-Street, <lb/>St. James's. </dateline>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>

      <pb xml:id="page_7"/>
      <head rend="align-center space"><lb/>AN <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">ENQUIRY</hi>
        <lb/>Into the <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">EXILITY</hi> of the <hi rend="dc(2)">VESSELS</hi>
        <lb/>In a <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">Human Body, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi></hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space"><lb/>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>Decorative frame around the letter "T".</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HE Structure of the <w part="I">Ani-</w><lb/><w part="F">mal</w>
        Body, whether we <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſider</w> the Size, Situation and
        <lb/>Uſes of its larger and more complex <lb/>Parts, with relation to each other, and
        <lb/>their Subſervience to the whole, or <lb/>by diving deeper into the ſecret and <pb
          xml:id="page_8"/><lb/>more myſterious Parts of Nature, we <lb/>ſcrutinize the ſeveral
        Parts of which <lb/>theſe are compoſed, exhibits to our <lb/>View ſuch an amazing Scene of
          <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">bounded</w> Power and Wiſdom, as <w part="I"
          >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">finitely</w> exceeds all the Contrivance <lb/>of the reſt of the
        viſible Creation, <lb/>how great the Bodies, or aſtoniſhing <lb/>ſoever their Motions and
        Revolutions <lb/>may upon a ſtrict Enquiry appear <lb/>to us. </p>
      <lb/>
      <q><foreign xml:lang="el">###Greek omitted###</foreign>
        <note place="bottom" n="(a)">(a) Ariſt. Ethic. lib. 5. cap. 1. </note>.</q>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>But tho' this Poſition is ſufficiently <lb/>evident from the Structure
        of every <lb/>Organ in the Animal Body, yet it is <lb/>in no Part ſo ſingularly aſtoniſhing,
        <lb/>as in the Growth of Animals, from <lb/>their firſt original Stamina in the <w part="I"
          >Ani-</w><pb xml:id="page_9" n="3"/><lb/><w part="F">malcule</w>, till they arrive at
        their <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pointed</w> Size. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>That every Veſſel and Fibre in the <lb/>Body is contained in Miniature
        in an <lb/>Animalcule, few, I believe, will <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">pute</w>,
        it being abſolutely impoſſible, <lb/>that mere Matter and Motion, <w part="I"
          >with-</w><lb/><w part="F">out</w> its being conducted by the Veſſels <lb/>proper to an
        Animal, ſhould produce <lb/>an Animal at all; and ſtill more <w part="I">ab-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſurd</w>, if there can be Degrees in <w part="I">Ab-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſurdity</w>, to ſuppoſe ſuch a Cauſe <w part="I">ca-</w><lb/><w part="F">pable</w> of
        producing that Variety of <lb/>Species, in their regular Order, which, <lb/>we ſee, is
        conſtantly kept up thro' ſo <lb/>great a Series of Years and <w part="I">Genera-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">tions</w>; but that inſtead of a Calf, a <lb/>Cow might as naturally produce a
        <lb/>Lion, Camel, or any other Creature, <pb xml:id="page_10" n="4"/><lb/>as frequently as
        its own proper <w part="I">Spe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cies</w>. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Beſides, could the Parts or Limbs, <lb/>or even the moſt minute Organ be
        <lb/>produced by the Motion of the Fluids, <lb/>without their being conducted by <lb/>the
        Veſſels of the Organ itſelf already <lb/>latent in the Stamina, what ſhould <lb/>hinder, why
        any Part taken away <lb/>by Amputation ſhould not again be <lb/>perfectly formed and
        reſtored, ſince <lb/>all the adductory Veſſels continue in <lb/>their former State, and are
        capable <lb/>of ſupplying the ſame Fluids as <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore?</w>
        Conſequently ſince the moſt <lb/>minute Organ cannot be ſupplied by <lb/>any other than the
        forementioned <lb/>Method, can any thing be ſo abſurd, <lb/>as to ſuppoſe that all the
        regular <w part="I">Or-</w><pb xml:id="page_11" n="5"/><lb/><w part="F">der</w> of Veſſels
        neceſſary to compoſe the <lb/>whole Bodily Machine ſhould be <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">duced</w> by ſuch a Cauſe, as is utterly <lb/>incapable of forming the leaſt Part
        <lb/>imaginable in a regular Manner? This <lb/>is no leſs exemplified in the Seeds or
        <lb/>proper Embryos of Plants. Thus <lb/>the Seed of the Fir-tree, whoſe Bulk <lb/>with all
        its Integuments ſcarce equals <lb/>the Head of the ſmalleſt Pin, has its <lb/>Fibres and
        Veſſels ſo enlarged by the <lb/>Addition of freſh Particles, as to grow <lb/>to an enormous
        Size, without ever <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">viating</w> (in whatever Soil it
        grows) <lb/>from its own Species into any other <lb/>kind of Tree. Which can be owing
        <lb/>to no other Cauſe than the original <lb/>Stamina latent in its Seed; which not
        <lb/>only ſeparate, but conduct the <w part="I">Parti-</w><lb/><w part="F">cles</w> proper
        for its Nouriſhment, each <pb xml:id="page_12" n="6"/><lb/>to its proper Place in a manner
          <w part="I">pecu-</w><lb/><w part="F">liar</w> to itſelf, thereby diſtinguiſhing <lb/>it
        from all other Vegetables of what <lb/>kind ſoever. But a Branch once <w part="I"
          >lop-</w><lb/><w part="F">ped</w> off can no more be reſtored by <lb/>the Gardener's Art,
        than an <w part="I">amputa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ted</w> Limb by the Surgeon's: 'Tis true,
        <lb/>indeed, new Buds may be thruſt forth <lb/>by the redundant Nouriſhment, both <lb/>in
        the adjacent and more remote Parts, <lb/>to compenſate in ſome meaſure <lb/>this Defect: but
        whether this <w part="I">Mutila-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of the Plant be of its Summit,
        or <lb/>of a lateral Branch, the Extremity <lb/>muſt ſhrivel and dry up, and will bud
        <lb/>and bloſſom no more. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>If therefore mere Matter, altho' <lb/>ſuppoſed to be in Motion, muſt be
        <lb/>thus conducted by the Veſſels of an <pb xml:id="page_13" n="7"/><lb/>Animal, it muſt be
        conducted by the <lb/>Animal itſelf, no Application of <w part="I">dif-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ferent</w> Forces <hi rend="italic">ab extra</hi> to the Veſſels <lb/>(was there any ſuch
        thing, as it is <w part="I">evi-</w><lb/><w part="F">dent</w> from the Structure of the
        Uterus, <lb/>there is not) being capable of <w part="I">regula-</w><lb/><w part="F">ting</w>
        and directing ſuch an <w part="I">innumera-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w> Variety of Motions,
        or indeed of <lb/>contributing to its Operations, any <lb/>farther than ſupplying it with a
          <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">per</w> Nidus, and furniſhing it with <lb/>Materials
        ready prepared for the <w part="I">Pur-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſe</w>, as ſufficiently
        appears, not only <lb/>from the Obſervations of the accurate <lb/>Malpighi, Bellini, Redi,
        Merian and <lb/>others, but diſcovers itſelf to our <w part="I">Sen-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſes</w>, in the Generation of innumerable <lb/>other Species of Animals, ſome <w part="I"
          >depo-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſiting</w> their Eggs on Vegetables, or in <lb/>the Earth, to
        be brought to Light by <pb xml:id="page_14" n="8"/><lb/>the genial Warmth of the Sun, others
        <lb/>in Dunghills, and other putrefying <lb/>Subſtances, and others in Streams of
        <lb/>Water, where it is impoſſible for any <lb/>ſuch Force to be applied. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Hence then Nutrition muſt conſiſt <lb/>not only in the mere Diſtenſion,
        but <lb/>in the Appoſition of new Particles <lb/>into ſuch Parts of the Animal Body, <lb/>as
        by the Enlargement of the Pores, <lb/>and Vacuities in the Solids, are fitted <lb/>to
        receive them, as I have elſewhere <lb/>ſhewn by Experiment <note place="bottom" n="(a)">(a)
          See Sect. 7. Exp. 11. of an Experimental Enquiry on ſome Parts of the Animal Structure.
        </note>: And, <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">deed</w>, was it otherwiſe, the Animal
        <lb/>would have a Power of making its <lb/>own Fibres and Veſſels, and <w part="I"
          >conſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">quently</w> of producing itſelf; nay the <pb xml:id="page_15"
          n="9"/><lb/>Circulation of the Fluids muſt be <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >formed</w> in Veſſels, before the Veſſels <lb/>themſelves, thro' which it is to be
        <lb/>conveyed, have a Being; which are <lb/>ſuch Abſurdities, as I ſhall not give
        <lb/>myſelf the Trouble of confuting. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>That theſe new Particles by <w part="I">adhe-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ring</w> firmly to the original Stamina <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">creaſe</w>
        the Bulk of the Animal, till <lb/>ſuch time as it arrives at the <w part="I"
          >Perfec-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> its Structure is capable of, needs <lb/>no Proof;
        but that the Strength of <lb/>the original Animal owes its gradual <lb/>Improvement to the
        ſame Cauſe, is <lb/>likewiſe evident from the common <lb/>Practice of ſeveral of our
        mechanic <lb/>Workmen, who by ſteeping and <w part="I">ſatu-</w><lb/><w part="F">rating</w>
        porous Woods, or the like light <lb/>and brittle Subſtances in glutinous <pb
          xml:id="page_16" n="10"/><lb/>Decoctions, vaſtly increaſe their <w part="I">na-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">tural</w> Strength, without any Addition <lb/>to their external Bulk, which would
        <lb/>be ſtill farther increaſed, was that alſo <lb/>enlarged by a regular Diſtenſion of
        <lb/>Parts, as in the Caſe of Animal Bodies. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Hence then it will follow, that <lb/>theſe adventitious Particles, which
        by <lb/>their Coheſion with the original <w part="I">Sta-</w><lb/><w part="F">mina</w>,
        increaſe the Bulk and Strength <lb/>of the Body, and thereby enable it to <lb/>perform the
        proper Offices, for which <lb/>it was created, are not really any Part <lb/>of the Body
        itſelf, but extraneous to <lb/>it, actuated and regulated intirely by <lb/>it, and
        conſequently contribute no <lb/>farther to its exerciſing the Powers, <lb/>it is deſigned to
        exert when perfect, <lb/>than would be performed by a ſtrong <pb xml:id="page_17" n="11"
        /><lb/>Lever acting with ſuch a Power, as <lb/>would be impoſſible for a weak one <lb/>to
        ſuſtain, tho' in all other Reſpects <lb/>the Caſe might be exactly parallel. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nor is this leſs true with regard <lb/>to the Senſations, than Strength
        of <lb/>the Body. A proper Tenſion in the <lb/>nervous Fibres being as requiſite in
        <lb/>this Caſe, as Strength in thoſe <w part="I">deſign-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> for
        Muſcular Motion, as appears <lb/>from the pernicious Effects of too great <lb/>Laxity, as
        well as Rigidity, in ſeveral <lb/>Diſeaſes, the one rendering the <w part="I"
          >Sen-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſations</w> ſo languid and ſlow thro' their <lb/>weak
        Vibrations, as not to affect the <lb/>Animal with ſufficient Force and <w part="I"
          >Vi-</w><lb/><w part="F">vacity</w>; whilſt the other, thro' too <lb/>great Stiffneſs and
        Inflexibility, ſcarce <lb/>allows them to vibrate at all, as is the <pb xml:id="page_18"
          n="12"/><lb/>Caſe in old Age; or laſtly by being <lb/>too ſpringy and elaſtic, and thence
        <lb/>exciting too ſtrong and frequent <w part="I">Vi-</w><lb/><w part="F">brations</w> in
        ſuch as are younger, <w part="I">ei-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> renders their Senſations
        painful <lb/>and uneaſy, or ſo quick in their <w part="I">Suc-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ceſſions</w> to each other, as to prove <lb/>uſeleſs, nay often prejudicial to the
        <lb/>Animal, as is the Caſe in Phrenſies, <lb/>Maniacal Perſons, and the like. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>How far the Strength of the Body <lb/>depends upon the adventitious <w
          part="I">Parti-</w><lb/><w part="F">cles</w> derived to it by Nutrition has <lb/>been
        explained above, and it is hence <lb/>no leſs evident, that they cannot <w part="I"
          >poſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſibly</w> contribute farther to its <w part="I"
          >Senſa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w>, than as they add ſuch a Degree <lb/>of Firmneſs, as
        may prevent any <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">ternal</w> Species from acting upon the
          <pb xml:id="page_19" n="13"/><lb/>nervous Fibrils ſo forcibly, as to <w part="I"
          >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">jure</w> them; whilſt at the ſame time <lb/>by their intimate
        Adheſion with the <lb/>original ſenſitive Organs, they cannot <lb/>act upon the one, without
        exciting a <lb/>proper Degree of Motion in the other; <lb/>and conſequently the real
        Senſitive <lb/>Part of an Animal can contain no <lb/>greater Quantity of Matter, than is
        <lb/>included in the Nervous Parts of the <lb/>Animalcule. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>This then being the State of an <lb/>Animal when arrived at its
        Perfection, <lb/>how amazing muſt it be to conſider, <lb/>how ſmall and weak Organs do
        really <lb/>actuate the whole Machine! But that <lb/>this may more fully appear, and alſo
        <lb/>afford us ſome determinate Idea of <lb/>their extream Tenuity, I ſhall <w part="I"
          >endea-</w><pb xml:id="page_20" n="14"/><lb/><w part="F">vour</w> to reduce ſuch
        Microſcopical <w part="I">Ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſervations</w> as are of beſt Credit to a
          <w part="I">cer-</w><lb/><w part="F">tain</w> Standard; that by comparing <lb/>them with
        each other, and reducing <lb/>them to Numbers, our Notions of them <lb/>may not be
        altogether ſo vague and <lb/>indeterminate as at preſent they are. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Leeuwenhoek,</hi> that curious and <w part="I"
          >di-</w><lb/><w part="F">ligent</w> Inquirer into thoſe Works of <lb/>Nature, which till
        his Time had by <lb/>their Minuteneſs eſcaped all <w part="I">Diſcove-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ry</w>, has by his repeated Microſcopical <lb/>Obſervations on the <hi rend="italic"
          >Semen Maſculi-<lb/>num</hi> of Animals, not only ſhewn, that <lb/>it abounds with
        Animalcula proper <lb/>to each Species, but that, according <lb/>to his Judgment, a thouſand
        of them <lb/>would ſcarce be equal in Thickneſs <pb xml:id="page_21" n="15"/><lb/>to a Grain
        of Sand <note place="bottom" n="(a)">(a) <hi rend="italic">Leeuwenhoek</hi> Epiſt. 41. Tom.
          IV. </note>; and <w part="I">conſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">quently</w> that a cubical Inch
        would <lb/>contain a thouſand Millions of <w part="I">Mil-</w><lb/><w part="F">lions</w> of
        theſe little Beings. Profeſſor <lb/><hi rend="italic">Keil</hi> indeed, in his elegant
        Inquiry <lb/>into the actual Diviſibility of the <lb/>Particles of Matter, has from a
        <lb/>Principle of Dioptrics computed <lb/>their Magnitude to be ſomewhat <lb/>greater than
        that juſt now <w part="I">mention-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>; but he has however <w
          part="I">demon-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtrably</w> ſhewn, that the Length of <lb/>a ſingle
        Animalculum cannot <w part="I">poſſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">bly</w> exceed the 3/100000th Part
        of an <lb/>Inch <note place="bottom" n="(b)">(b) <hi rend="italic">Introductio ad veram
            Phyſicam,</hi> p. 48. </note>. That our preſent Enquiry <lb/>may therefore be wholly
        confined <lb/>within the Limits of Truth, rather <lb/>than proceed upon probable <w part="I"
          >Conjec-</w><pb xml:id="page_22" n="16"/><lb/><w part="F">ture</w>, we will make Choice of
        this <lb/>latter Eſtimate, and for the further <lb/>Conveniency of Calculation, take it
        <lb/>for granted, that when the Foot is <lb/>decimally divided, even ſuch a <w part="I"
          >Cubi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cal</w> Inch will exceed the Bulk of a <lb/>ſingle Animalculum,
        in no greater a <lb/>Proportion, than that of a thouſand <lb/>Millions of Millions to 27. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now the ſpecific Weight of the <lb/>various Parts of an Animal Body <w
          part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">duced</w> to a Medium amounts to a <w part="I"
          >lit-</w><lb/><w part="F">tle</w> more than the Weight of an equal <lb/>Bulk of Water; if
        therefore we ſuppoſe <lb/>one of theſe Animalcula to be to <w part="I">Wa-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ter</w>, as the other Parts of young <w part="I">Ani-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >mals</w> are, (and greater it cannot be, <lb/>as appears from what I have elſewhere
        <lb/>demonſtrated with relation to the <w part="I">in-</w><pb xml:id="page_23" n="17"
          /><lb/><w part="F">creaſed</w> ſpecific Gravity in the <w part="I">Arte-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ries</w> of aged Animals <note place="bottom" n="(a)">(a) Sect. 5. Exp. 11. of an
          Experimental Enquiry on ſome Parts of the Animal Structure. </note>, it follows, <lb/>that
        as a Cubical Inch of Water is <lb/>equivalent to 0.5271 parts of an <lb/>Ounce Troy, the
        Weight of a ſingle <lb/>Animalcule will be equal to the <lb/>1/140391450739th part of a
        Grain nearly. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>But by the Experiments of the <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >genious</w> Dr. <hi rend="italic">Keil</hi> it appears, that in a <lb/>Man of 12
        Stone-weight, the Fluids <lb/>are to the Solids when taken at a <w part="I">Me-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">dium</w>, at the leaſt in the Proportion <lb/>of 8 to 3 <note place="bottom"
          n="(b)">(b) <hi rend="italic">Eſſays on ſeveral Parts of the Animal OEconomy,</hi> p. 38.
            <hi rend="italic">to</hi> 63. </note>, excluſive of thoſe, which <lb/>by the Help of
        Fire and a Chymical <lb/>Proceſs may be extracted without the <lb/>Deſtruction of a ſingle
        Fibre, which <lb/>amounts to no ſmall Quantity. It has <pb xml:id="page_24" n="18"
        /><lb/>alſo been farther ſhewn by <w part="I">Experi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w>, that the
        Veſſels in young <w part="I">Ani-</w><lb/><w part="F">mals</w> bear a much leſs Proportion
        to <lb/>their Cavities, than the like Veſſels <lb/>in old ones of the ſame Species bear
        <lb/>to theirs <note place="bottom" n="(a)">(a) Sect. 3. Exp. 11 <hi rend="italic">of the
            Experimental Enquiry,</hi> &amp;c. </note>; conſequently, ſince the <lb/>Denſity of any
        Body is as the Weight <lb/>of the Body directly, and its <w part="I">Magni-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">tude</w> inverſely, we ſhall find, by <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >paring</w> the foregoing Proportions of <lb/>the Fluids and Solids together in each
        <lb/>different State of the Animal, as well <lb/>before its Birth, as after it has arrived
        <lb/>at full Maturity, that all the Stamina, <lb/>from which ſo noble a Being as Man
        <lb/>himſelf was at firſt derived, could not <lb/>contain ſo much ſolid Matter as would
        <lb/>be equal in Bulk, to that of a <w part="I">Quan-</w><lb/><w part="F">tity</w> of Water,
        of no greater a Weight <pb xml:id="page_25" n="19"/><lb/>than the
        1/92408129934910602442073752000th <lb/>part of a Grain. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>If the preceding Exility of the <lb/>Solids in general be ſo ſurpizingly
        <lb/>ſmall, That of the Senſitive Parts <lb/>alone, could their Relation to the reſt <lb/>be
        once adjuſted, would doubtleſs, to <lb/>ſpeak in the Language of the <w part="I"
          >Mathe-</w><lb/><w part="F">maticians</w>, appear a mere Infiniteſimal. <lb/>For even <hi
          rend="italic">Leeuwenhoek</hi> has declared in <lb/>expreſs Words, that <q rend="quotes"
            ><hi rend="italic">Hæ Cerebri <lb/>Fibrillæ, tenuibus puto amiciuntur <lb/>Membranulis,
            quæ ob inſignem <lb/>Exilitatem nunquam ſeſe <w part="I">nuda-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >bunt</w> conſpectui noſtro: Quod niſi <lb/>ſtatuamus, quo pacto Fibrillarum
            <lb/>Diſparationem vel Diſtinctionem <lb/>Oculis aſſequeremur?</hi>
          <note place="bottom" n="(a)">(a) <hi rend="italic">Leeuwenhoek</hi> Epiſt. 34. Tom. IV.
          </note></q> To <pb xml:id="page_26" n="20"/><lb/>which he might have added our <w part="I"
          >Intel-</w><lb/><w part="F">lectual</w> Faculties alſo, it being ſcarce <lb/>poſſible to
        conceive Fibres always <lb/>growing and encreaſing in Bulk, <lb/>ſhould be kept ſeparate,
        and perform <lb/>their various Operations, but muſt <lb/>ſoon prove immoveable, without <w
          part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> divided from each other by theſe <lb/>ſlender
        Partitions. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>This is not only evident from the <lb/>Nature of the Fibres, but <w
          part="I">demonſtra-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w> from Fact in the larger Parts even <lb/>of
        full-grown Animals; which, when <lb/>contiguous and deprived of their <lb/>proper
        Integuments, never fail to <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">here</w> and unite firmly to
        each other, <lb/>as is ſufficiently known to the <w part="I">Prac-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >titioners</w> in Surgery. How much <lb/>ſooner then would this Adhæſion be <pb
          xml:id="page_27" n="21"/><lb/>produced in growing Animals, where <lb/>the Fibres are not
        only more ſupple, <lb/>and thence more eaſily united, but if <lb/>deprived of theſe
        Membranes, would <lb/>daily as they increaſe in Bulk, preſs <lb/>more ſtrongly againſt each
        other? </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Writers in Geometry have laid <lb/>it down as an eſtabliſhed Maxim,
        <lb/>that <hi rend="italic">ubicunque deficit Modulus, in <lb/>æternum latebit Menſura;</hi>
        on which <lb/>account, tho' we may reſt ſatisfied, <lb/>that the Subtility of the ſenſitive
        <lb/>Parts in an Animal Body muſt <w part="I">neceſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſarily</w> ſo far
        ſurpaſs the Extent of <w part="I">hu-</w><lb/><w part="F">man</w> Abilities, as to put their
        Bulk <lb/>beyond a Poſſibility of being ever <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >termined</w> to a Mathematical <w part="I">Exact-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w>; yet even
        the Nerves themſelves, <lb/>thoſe delicate Inſtruments of all our <pb xml:id="page_28"
          n="22"/><lb/>Knowledge, may be brought under <lb/>ſuch an Examination, as to afford us
        <lb/>a much clearer Idea of their <w part="I">exqui-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſite</w>
        Minuteneſs, than what can be <lb/>obtained from thoſe conjectural <w part="I">De-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſcriptions</w>, the Anatomiſts have <w part="I">hi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >therto</w> given us concerning it. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>For it is evident, that all the <w part="I">Mem-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >branes</w> of an Animal Body have <w part="I">Muſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">cular</w> Fibres,
        and that even the <w part="I">great-</w><lb/><w part="F">eſt</w> Number of them are
        principally <lb/>made up of ſuch; conſequently we <lb/>could not err very far from the
        Truth, <lb/>were we to eſtimate the Bulk of the <lb/>Membranous Fibres in the ſame <w
          part="I">Pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">portion</w> with the Muſcular ones. But <lb/>we ſhall
        examine the Bulk and <w part="I">Pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">portion</w> they bear to each
        other a <w part="I">lit-</w><lb/><w part="F">tle</w> more diſtinctly. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_29" n="23"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now <hi rend="italic">Leeuwenhoek</hi> in his <w part="I"
          >Obſerva-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w> on the Muſcular Fibres has <lb/>ſhewn, that ſome
        of them were equal <lb/>to the 1/9th, others to the 1/16th part of a <lb/>Hair <note
          place="bottom" n="(a)">(a) <hi rend="italic">Leeuwenhoek,</hi> Epiſt. 6. Tom. IV. </note>;
        conſequently ſuppoſing each <lb/>Fibre to be the Length of a Decimal <lb/>Inch, there will
        be contained in ſuch <lb/>a Cubic Inch ſeven Millions two <lb/>hundred ninety thouſand of
        the <w part="I">for-</w><lb/><w part="F">mer</w>, and twenty-three Millions forty
        <lb/>thouſand of the latter Kind. But <lb/>theſe Muſcular Fibres are by later
        <lb/>Obſervations found to be really ſmall <lb/>Muſcles, conſiſting of Parts ſimilar <lb/>to
        the large one, which they <w part="I">conſti-</w><lb/><w part="F">tute</w>, and terminating
        in Tendons <lb/>after the ſame Manner as the former; <lb/>and conſequently the Fibres, of
        which <pb xml:id="page_30" n="24"/><lb/>the more lax and cavernous Parts of <lb/>the Muſcle
        are compoſed, muſt be <lb/>much ſmaller than the muſcular <w part="I">Fi-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">bres</w> rendered viſible by his Glaſſes. <lb/>Whether theſe be the ſame
        individual <lb/>Fibres, which conſtitute the Tendon, <lb/>by being more cloſely compacted in
        <lb/>their Parts, I ſhall not undertake to <lb/>determine; but this we learn from <lb/>the
        forecited Author, that a hundred <lb/>of theſe exceed not the Bulk of a <lb/>Hair <note
          place="bottom" n="(a)">(a) <hi rend="italic">Leeuwenhoek</hi> Epiſt. 14. Tom. IV. </note>,
        and conſequently nine <w part="I">hun-</w><lb/><w part="F">dred</w> Millions of them will be
          <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tained</w> in the forementioned Cubic <lb/>Inch. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>But theſe are far from being the <lb/>ſmalleſt Fibres in the Body. For
        <lb/>that the pellucid Membranes conſiſt <pb xml:id="page_31" n="25"/><lb/>of Fibres of
        ſtill ſmaller Dimenſions, <lb/>decreaſing probably to the 1/300th part <lb/>of a Hair, or
        upwards, is evident from <lb/>the Structure of thoſe fine Capillary <lb/>Arteries, which are
        deſtined to <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">vey</w> a Fluid to them. For the whole
        <lb/>Diameter of ſuch an extream Artery <lb/>does not exceed the 1/1620th part of an
        <lb/>Inch <note place="bottom" n="(a)">(a) <hi rend="italic">Hale's Haemaeſt.</hi> Exp. 9.
        </note> that is, the 1/5th of a Hair <lb/>nearly, and yet the Coat of this <w part="I"
          >Veſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſel</w> is made up of at leaſt three diſtinct <lb/>Species of
        Membranes, each of them <lb/>furniſhed with Veſſels peculiar to <w part="I">it-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſelf</w>. And farther, if we conſider, <lb/>that the tranſverſe Section of every
        <lb/>Veſſel is of a circular Form, we muſt <lb/>neceſſarily allow, that the <w part="I"
          >Longitudi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nal</w> Fibres muſt be much ſmaller than <lb/>any of thoſe
        abovementioned; <w part="I">other-</w><pb xml:id="page_32" n="26"/><lb/>inſtead of a Circle,
        a Polygon <lb/>would be produced, as is evident from <lb/>Geometry. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now even theſe are bulky <w part="I">Sub-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſtances</w>, when compared with the <lb/>nervous Fibrils deſtined to Senſation, <lb/>as
        appears from thoſe which form <lb/>the Retina. For theſe Fibres were <lb/>manifeſtly before
        their Expanſion into <lb/>this Membrane collected within the <lb/>Bulk of what is ſtyled by
        Anatomiſts <lb/>the Optic Nerve, and are, as the <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >genious</w> Profeſſor <hi rend="italic">Monro</hi> aſſures us, <lb/>ſo extreamly ſmall,
        that it is <w part="I">demon-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtrable</w>, they cannot exceed the <w
          part="I">Thick-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w> of the 1{diviſor}32400th part of a Hair <note
          place="bottom" n="(a)">(a) <lb/><hi rend="italic">Monro</hi>'s Anatomy of the Human Bones
          and Nerves, p. 3. </note>. <lb/>If therefore we reject the odd four <lb/>hundred in the
        foregoing Fraction, <pb xml:id="page_33" n="27"/><lb/>and ſuppoſe, that no more than 32000
        <lb/>of theſe Nervous Fibrils are neceſſary <lb/>to make up a Thickneſs equal to that
        <lb/>abovementioned, and alſo ſet the <lb/>Muſcular, Tendinous, and <w part="I"
          >Membra-</w><lb/><w part="F">nous</w> Fibres to be at a Medium, of <lb/>no greater a
        Thickneſs than the 1/200th <lb/>Part of a Hair, (which, from what <lb/>has been juſt now
        explained above, <lb/>is apparently a very large Allowance <lb/>with reſpect to the
        Subtility of the <lb/>Fibres in general) it will then follow, <lb/>that the Thickneſs of one
        of theſe <lb/>Fibrils in the Retina will be to that <lb/>of ſuch Fibres, as conſtitute the
        other <lb/>Membranes and Organs of the Body, <lb/>in the proportion of 1 to 160. But <lb/>we
        have already ſhewn, that all the <w part="I">Sta-</w><lb/><w part="F">mina</w> in an
        Animalcule could not <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tain</w> ſo much ſolid Matter, as
        is equal <pb xml:id="page_34" n="28"/><lb/>in Bulk to a Particle of Water <w part="I"
          >weigh-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> the 1/92408129934910602442073752000th <lb/>part of a
        Grain; conſequently, if we <lb/>ſuppoſe, that a Nervous Fibril does <lb/>accompany every
        individual Fibre in <lb/>the Animal Syſtem, and compare <lb/>the Proportions they bear to
        each <lb/>other as given above, we ſhall find, <lb/>that the whole ſenſitive Parts in the
        <lb/>Animalcule taken together could not <lb/>amount to a greater Bulk than that <lb/>of the
        1/3764060396563654679984851840619241th <lb/>part of a cubical Inch, or that all the
        <lb/>ſolid Matter of the Nerves, by which <lb/>the Senſations in the human Syſtem <lb/>are
        actually communicated to the <lb/>Mind, cannot poſſibly weigh the
        1/14877708919520606993173874072000th part of <lb/>a Grain. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_35" n="29"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>That the ſtupendous Expanſion <lb/>and Action of the Fibres and Veſſels
        <lb/>of an Animalcule up to that of a <lb/>full grown Man ſhould be owing to <lb/>an Entity
        like this, a mere fluxionary <lb/>Increment with reſpect to Quantity <lb/>and Magnitude,
        will, I doubt not, to <lb/>many appear impoſſible, to all <w part="I">incom-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">prehenſible</w>; but are not all other of <lb/>the Creator's Works equally ſo? Or
        <lb/>is this more than infinite Power <w part="I">act-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> on Matter
        infinitely diviſible is <lb/>capable of, whoſe Particles muſt be <lb/>ſtill higher
        ſubtiliſed, and ſpun into <lb/>Fibres inconceivably more minute in <lb/>the Bodies of
        Inſects, than is here <w part="I">ſpe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cified</w> of the human, as they
        are all <lb/>furniſhed with Arteries, Veins, Nerves, <lb/>Muſcles, Bones, and Tendons
        ſuitable <pb xml:id="page_36" n="30"/><lb/>to their various Structures, and <w part="I"
          >Man-</w><lb/><w part="F">ner</w> of ſubſiſting. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The incomparable Mr. <hi rend="italic">Locke,</hi>
        <lb/>ſpeaking of the Identity of the ſame <lb/>Perſon, reſolves it wholly into its <w
          part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſciouſness</w>, even though the whole <lb/>Subſtance,
        material or immaterial, <lb/>ſhould be intirely changed. Many <lb/>Phyſicians have alſo been
        of opinion, <lb/>and ſome even laid it down as a <lb/>Maxim, that the whole Subſtance of
        <lb/>the Body, during the Length of an <lb/>ordinary Life, is ſeveral times ſo <w part="I"
          >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">tirely</w> changed, as to conſiſt wholly <lb/>of new Particles,
        of the ſame Nature <lb/>and Kind as the preceeding. How <lb/>far theſe Opinions may agree
        with <lb/>what is taught by Divine Revelation, <lb/>where this very Sameneſs, in its <pb
          xml:id="page_37" n="31"/><lb/>ſtricteſt Acceptation, ſeems to be <w part="I"
          >ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">preſſly</w> declared, is not my province <lb/>to determine. But
        this we may <lb/>plainly deduce from what has been <lb/>premiſed, that the whole Subſtance
        <lb/>of the Body, except theſe original <lb/>Stamina of the Animalcule, may be <lb/>many
        times changed, and yet the real <lb/>Body continue the ſame, and be <w part="I"
          >poſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſeſſed</w> of the ſame perſonal Identity, <lb/>with regard both
        to Body and Mind, <lb/>at the End of the longeſt Life, as it <lb/>was at the inſtant of its
        Birth; nay <lb/>even in the Animalcule itſelf. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>That theſe original Stamina ſhould <lb/>all remain unhurt, and fit to
        perform <lb/>their ſeveral Functions to the End of <lb/>Life, is a Poſition not to be
        admitted; <lb/>but that without a competent <w part="I">Num-</w><pb xml:id="page_38" n="32"
          /><lb/><w part="F">ber</w> of them ſo remaining, the Animal <lb/>will decline both in its
        vital and <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">tellectual</w> Faculties, notwithſtanding
        <lb/>the Body be repleniſhed with a <w part="I">ſuf-</w><lb/><w part="F">ficient</w> Number
        of homogeneous <w part="I">Par-</w><lb/><w part="F">ticles</w> to ſupply the Place of ſuch
        Parts <lb/>as are abraded and worn away, or <lb/>otherwiſe hindered from performing
        <lb/>their natural Functions, ſeems equally <lb/>certain; both from the Decay of our
        <lb/>intellectual Faculties, and the gradual <lb/>Loſs of Vigour in the Body, even
        <lb/>whilſt the Force of the vital Organs <lb/>ſeems no ways impaired. <w part="I"
          >Conſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">quently</w> ſomething more muſt be <w part="I">ne-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ceſſary</w>, than the mere Application of <lb/>homogeneous Matter to ſupply this
        <lb/>Demand. But that can be no other, <lb/>than that particular Texture, with <lb/>which
        they were originally formed, <pb xml:id="page_39" n="33"/><lb/>and by which they become
        capable <lb/>of tranſmitting the Effects of <w part="I">exter-</w><lb/><w part="F">nal</w>
        Agents to the Mind. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It may poſſibly be objected, that <lb/>all Matter being equally
        incapable of <lb/>Senſation, no Reaſon can poſſibly be <lb/>aſſigned, why ſuch homogeneous
        <lb/>Matter, as ſupplies the conſtant Loſs, <lb/>the Body ſuſtains by the Attrition of
        <lb/>its Parts on each other, and ſerves for <lb/>its Accretion, Strength, and <w part="I"
          >Nutri-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, may not be equally capable of <lb/>conveying our
        Senſations to the Mind, <lb/>as the original Stamina above <w part="I">men-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">tioned</w>. But if we may reaſon from <lb/>what enſues in the larger Parts, which
        <lb/>are compounded of theſe very <w part="I">Sta-</w><lb/><w part="F">mina</w>, upon their
        being wounded, or <lb/>broken with Loſs of Subſtance, 'tis <pb xml:id="page_40" n="34"
        /><lb/>evident, that though by the <w part="I">Addi-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of
        homogeneous Matter to the <lb/>different Species of Veſſels, the Body <lb/>to Appearance,
        may have received no <lb/>great Detriment, and be ſufficient <lb/>for the principal Purpoſes
        of Life; <lb/>yet are ſuch Parts of very dull and <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſcure</w> Senſation, if they may be ſaid <lb/>to enjoy it in any other manner, than
        <lb/>by their Union with the original <w part="I">Sta-</w><lb/><w part="F">mina</w>. So that
        could we ſuppoſe theſe <lb/>Stamina quite deſtroyed, and the Body <lb/>ſo far changed, as to
        conſiſt only of <lb/>ſuch homogeneous Matter, though <lb/>with Veſſels in Form and Bulk <w
          part="I">ſimi-</w><lb/><w part="F">lar</w> to the former, yet theſe united by <lb/>a
        Texture different from that of the <lb/>original Fibres; 'tis evident from <lb/>what enſues
        upon a like Change in <lb/>the Fibres conſtituting the larger <pb xml:id="page_41" n="35"
        /><lb/>Parts, that ſuch a Perſon, if he had <lb/>either Senſitive or Intellectual <w
          part="I">Facul-</w><lb/><w part="F">ties</w> at all, muſt have them in a <w part="I"
          >man-</w><lb/><w part="F">ner</w> vaſtly different from thoſe of the <lb/>former. And
        conſequently this <w part="I">Same-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w> or Identity muſt remain in
        a great <lb/>Meaſure fixed and unalterable in the <lb/>Body from its Birth to its
        Diſſolution. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nor is this Difference in the <w part="I">ori-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ginal</w> Stamina confined in its Effects <lb/>to the fibrous Parts of the Body only,
        <lb/>but communicates them to the <w part="I">circu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lating</w> Juices
        themſelves, <w part="I">diſtinguiſh-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> thereby the different Kinds
        of <lb/>Fleſh of each Species of Animals from <lb/>each other, even where they are <w
          part="I">ſu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtained</w> by the ſame Kind of Food. <lb/>Otherwiſe it
        would happen in Caſes <lb/>of this Kind, that the Taſte, <w part="I">Com-</w><pb
          xml:id="page_42" n="36"/><lb/><w part="F">plexion</w>, Odour, and Coheſion of the
        <lb/>Fleſh would of Neceſſity be nearly <lb/>the ſame in all. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The ſame would be the <w part="I">Conſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">quence</w>
        with regard to the Glands of <lb/>the ſame Body, which would <w part="I">ſepa-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">rate</w> nearly the ſame Kind of Juice, <lb/>and conſequently be uſeleſs, or <w
          part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">haps</w> prejudicial, was it not prevented <lb/>by the
        different Structure both of the <lb/>Strainer itſelf, and the Preparatory <lb/>Veſſels. For
        howſoever we may <lb/>imagine the Juice to be ſeparated <lb/>from the circulating Maſs, we
        cannot <lb/>with any Colour of Reaſon ſuppoſe <lb/>ſuch a various and exquiſite <w part="I"
          >Contri-</w><lb/><w part="F">vance</w>, as is diſcovered not only in the <lb/>Formation of
        the Gland itſelf, but <lb/>alſo in that of the Veſſels leading to <pb xml:id="page_43"
          n="37"/><lb/>and from it, ſo widely differing <lb/>among themſelves in their Structure,
        <lb/>Texture, and Capacity <note place="bottom" n="(a)">(a) Sect. 6. Exp. 47. of the
          Experimental Inquiry on, &amp;c. </note>, ſhould <lb/>ever be deſigned only to perform
        <lb/>what any one Species of them was <lb/>capable of. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Hence then it muſt follow, that <lb/>the principal Differences in Animal
        <lb/>Bodies are owing to the different <lb/>Structure of the original Stamina, <lb/>with
        regard not only to their exterior <lb/>Shape and Actions, but that even the <lb/>Fluids
        themſelves, and that ſolid <lb/>Part called the Fleſh, derive their <lb/>chief and principal
        Difference from <lb/>this Source; and conſequently, that <lb/>there is a real Identity of
        Animal <pb xml:id="page_44" n="38"/><lb/>Bodies incommunicable to any other, <lb/>depending
        on this very Cauſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nor is this relating to the Fluids <lb/>a mere Conjecture, but a real
        Fact, <lb/>as appears from thoſe morbid Caſes, <lb/>where either the Glands, Preparatory
        <lb/>Veſſels, or even the fleſhy Parts are <lb/>vitiated and depraved; which never <lb/>fail
        to ſeparate unnatural Juices, tho' <lb/>derived from the moſt healthful Blood. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Analogous to this we ſee in the <lb/>Vegetable World, that it is not the
        <lb/>Root, or even Trunk of the Tree, <lb/>tho' all the Juices are thereby <w part="I"
          >ſup-</w><lb/><w part="F">plied</w>, but the Bud or Scion only, <lb/>which governs the
        whole, and <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duces</w> the Species of Bloſſoms and <pb
          xml:id="page_45" n="39"/><lb/>Fruit peculiar to itſelf. In like <lb/>manner the Veſſels of
        the Animalcule, <lb/>of what Species ſoever it be, convert <lb/>the Juices deſigned for its
          <w part="I">Nouriſh-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w>, each, into ſuch as are ſuitable <lb/>to
        their different Structures; and <lb/>thence keep up an infinite Variety in <lb/>Animals,
        tho' ſupplied by the ſame <lb/>kind of Food, according to the <w part="I">dif-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ferent</w> Veſſels by whoſe means it is <lb/>elaborated and perfected, being in
        <lb/>ſome highly volatiliſed and <w part="I">attenuat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>, which
        gives the high Taſte; in <lb/>others more viſcous and inactive, <lb/>which produces the
        oppoſite, and <lb/>are therefore leſs pleaſing to a <w part="I">volup-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tuous</w> Appetite. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I am not here ſuppoſing, that the <lb/>Qualities of the circulating
        Juices of <pb xml:id="page_46" n="40"/><lb/>Animals depend ſo intirely upon the
        <lb/>Structure of the Solids, that the <w part="I">Di-</w><lb/><w part="F">verſity</w> of
        Food is herein of no <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſequence</w>, daily Experience
        ſufficiently <lb/>confuting ſo abſurd an Opinion. But <lb/>only that in thoſe of a different
          <w part="I">Spe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cies</w>, the Taſte, Odour, and other <lb/>Qualities
        of their Juices, are <w part="I">princi-</w><lb/><w part="F">pally</w> owing to this
        different <w part="I">Struc-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w>; as is manifeſt from hence, <hi
          rend="italic">viz.</hi>
        <lb/>that the Qualities of the Juices of <lb/>differing Animals, though ſuſtained <lb/>with
        the ſame Kind of Food, are <lb/>more diſſonant to each other, than <lb/>are thoſe of the
        ſame Species, though <lb/>ſuſtained with Food of a very <w part="I">differ-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ent</w> Nature; and conſequently, this <lb/>Identity in the various Species of
        <lb/>Animals, muſt principally conſiſt in <lb/>the Structure of the Solids, or, in <pb
          xml:id="page_47" n="41"/><lb/>other Words, in the original Stamina <lb/>of each individual
        Species. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Thus has our Reaſoning at length <lb/>led us to the Diſcovery and <w
          part="I">Demon-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtration</w> of a Truth, which at firſt <lb/>Sight
        muſt appear beyond all <w part="I">Proba-</w><lb/><w part="F">bility</w>, and we can now
        with <w part="I">Cer-</w><lb/><w part="F">tainty</w> affirm, that from ſo ſimple a
        <lb/>Cauſe as the different Modification <lb/>of the ſame Matter, the wiſe Author <lb/>of
        Nature has produced not only one <lb/>kind of Fleſh of Men, another of <lb/>Beaſts, another
        of Fiſhes, and another <lb/>of Birds; but theſe alſo infinitely <w part="I">dif-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ferent</w> in the different Species of <lb/>each. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Hence we may ſee, why ſome <w part="I">Ani-</w><lb/><w part="F">mals</w>
        ſhall neceſſarily require ſuch a <pb xml:id="page_48" n="42"/><lb/>Degree of Warmth, to
        preſerve their <lb/>Juices ſufficiently exalted and <w part="I">attenu-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ated</w> for their comfortable Subſiſtence, <lb/>as others cannot ſuſtain without <w
          part="I">Pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">judice</w>, even ſcarcely without a <w part="I"
          >Diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſolution</w>; and <hi rend="italic">vice verſa,</hi> why ſuch
        <lb/>a Degree of Cold, as is only <w part="I">agree-</w><lb/><w part="F">able</w>, or
        perhaps neceſſary to the <lb/>Health of theſe, ſhould prove ſo far <lb/>deſtructive of
        others, as on the leaſt <lb/>Condenſation of the Fluids from that <lb/>Cauſe, to render them
        torpid, <w part="I">mo-</w><lb/><w part="F">tionless</w>, and ſeemingly dead, till <w
          part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtored</w> by the kindly Influence of the
        <lb/>approaching Summer. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Hence alſo it is obvious, why the <lb/>Blood and Juices of ſome
        particular <lb/>Species of Animals ſhall be affected <lb/>with Diſeaſes of a Peſtilential
        Nature <pb xml:id="page_49" n="43"/><lb/>with regard to them, from ſuch <lb/>Cauſes, as
        ſhall produce very few <w part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F">conveniences</w> to many other
        Kinds. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Hence alſo we may ſee the Reaſon, <lb/>why each individual Perſon has
        ſome <lb/>Particularities in his Conſtitution <w part="I">pe-</w><lb/><w part="F">culiar</w>
        to himſelf, not to be found in <lb/>the Generality of the Species, nor <w part="I"
          >de-</w><lb/><w part="F">pending</w> on his Manner of Life, by <lb/>which he is as it were
        diſtinguiſhed <lb/>from the reſt: Which alſo probably <lb/>may ſometimes be the Caſe in
        Brutes, <lb/>tho' more rarely than in Men, could <lb/>we equally arrive at the Knowledge
        <lb/>of it, as is manifeſt from the different <lb/>Sprightlineſs, Vigour, and Activity
        <lb/>of ſome compared with others of the <lb/>ſame Species. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_50" n="44"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Laſtly, hence we may ſee, why <lb/>an intire Change of the Conſtitution
        <lb/>ſhould be attended with almoſt <w part="I">inſu-</w><lb/><w part="F">perable</w>
        Difficulties: Why great <w part="I">Al-</w><lb/><w part="F">terations</w> require a long and
        gradual <lb/>Proceſs, nor are to be attempted by <lb/>haſty Methods, leſt the Patient, <w
          part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtead</w> of Relief, meet with certain <lb/>Ruin and
        Deſtruction. </p>
      <trailer rend="italic align-center"><lb/>FINIS. </trailer>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
