<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Berkeley: SIRIS: A Chain of Philosophical Reflexions and
          Inquiries</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>George Berkeley</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">SIRIS: A Chain of Philosophical Reflexions and Inquiries Concerning
              the Virtues of Tar Water, And divers other Subjects connected together and arising one
              from another.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T72826</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T72826"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Dublin</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Dublin: printed by Margt. Rhames, for R. Gunne, Bookseller in
                  Capel-Street, MDCCXLIV. 1744.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1744</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="2"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="261"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107132115</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: medicine"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="2"/>
      <pb n="3"/>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>An ornamental horizontal column, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/><hi rend="size(4.0)">SIRIS: </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">A Chain of </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">Philoſophical Reflexions </hi>
        <lb/>AND <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">INQUIRIES, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc"><hi rend="dc(4)">F</hi>or Introduction</hi> to the following <lb/>piece I
        aſſure the reader, that no- <lb/>thing could, in my preſent ſituation, <lb/>have induced me
        to be at the pains <lb/>of writing it, but a firm belief that it would <lb/>prove a valuable
        preſent to the Public. <lb/>What entertainment ſoever the reaſoning <lb/>or notional part
        may afford the mind, I will <lb/>venture to ſay, the other part ſeemeth ſo <lb/>ſurely
        calculated to do good to the Body, that <pb n="4"/>
        <lb/>both muſt be gainers. For if the lute be not <lb/>well tuned, the muſician fails of his
        har- <lb/>mony. And in our preſent ſtate, the opera- <lb/>tions of the mind, ſo far depend
        on the right <lb/>tone or good condition of it's inſtrument, <lb/>that any thing which
        greatly contributes to <lb/>preſerve or recover the health of the body, is <lb/>well worth
        the attention of the mind. Theſe <lb/>conſiderations have moved me to communi- <lb/>cate to
        the Public the ſalutary virtues of Tar <lb/>water; to which I thought my ſelf indiſpen-
        <lb/>ſibly obliged, by the duty every man owes <lb/>to mankind. And, as effects are linked
        with <lb/>their cauſes, my thoughts on this low but <lb/>uſeful theme led to farther
        inquiries, and thoſe <lb/>on to others remote, perhaps, and ſpeculative <lb/>but, I hope,
        not altogether uſeleſs or unen- <lb/>tertaining. </p>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/>1. <hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N certain parts of America, Tar water <lb/>is made by putting
        a quart of cold wa- <lb/>ter to a quart of tar, and ſtirring them well <lb/>together in a
        veſſel, which is left ſtanding till <lb/>the tar ſinks to the bottom. A glaſs of clear
        <lb/>water being poured off for a draught is repla- <lb/>ced by the ſame quantity of freſh
        water, the <lb/>veſſel being ſhaken and left to ſtand as before. <lb/>And this is repeated
        for every glaſs; ſo long <lb/>as the tar continues to impregnate the water <pb n="5"/>
        <lb/>ſufficiently, which will appear by the ſmell <lb/>and taſte. But as this method
        produceth tar <lb/>water of different degrees of ſtrength, I chuſe <lb/>to make it in the
        following manner. Pour a <lb/>gallon of cold water on a quart of tar, and <lb/>ſtir and mix
        them thoroughly with a ladle or <lb/>flat ſtick <choice>
          <corr>for</corr>
          <sic>far</sic>
        </choice> the ſpace of three or four minutes, <lb/>after which the veſſel muſt ſtand eight
        and for- <lb/>ty hours that the tar may have time to ſub- <lb/>ſide, when the clear water is
        to be poured off <lb/>and kept for uſe, no more being made from <lb/>the ſame tar, which may
        ſtill ſerve for com- <lb/>mon purpoſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>2. <hi rend="sc">This</hi> cold infuſion of tar hath been uſed <lb/>in ſome of our
        colonies, as a preſervative or <lb/>preparative againſt the ſmall-pox, which fo- <lb/>reign
        practice induced me to try it in my own <lb/>neighbourhood, when the ſmall-pox raged
        <lb/>with great violence. And the tryal fully an- <lb/>ſwered my expectation: all thoſe,
        within my <lb/>knowledge, who took the tar water having <lb/>either eſcaped that diſtemper,
        or had it very <lb/>favourably. In one family there was a re- <lb/><choice>
          <corr>markable</corr>
          <sic>emarkable</sic>
        </choice> inſtance of ſeven children, who <lb/>came all very well through the ſmall pox, ex-
        <lb/>cept one young child which cou'd not be <lb/>brought to drink tar water as the reſt had
        <lb/>done. </p>
      <pb n="6"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>3. <hi rend="sc">Several</hi> were preſerved from taking <lb/>the ſmall pox by the uſe
        of this liquor: <lb/>others had it in the mildeſt manner, and others <lb/>that they might be
        able to take the infection <lb/>were obliged to intermit drinking the tar-water. <lb/>I have
        found it may be drunk with great ſafe- <lb/>ty and ſucceſs for any length of time, and this
        <lb/>not only before, but alſo during the diſtemper. <lb/>The general rule for taking it is,
        about half <lb/>a pint night and morning on an empty ſtomach, <lb/>which quantity may be
        varied, according to <lb/>the caſe and age of the patient, provided it <lb/>be always taken
        on an empty ſtomach, and <lb/>about two hours before or after a meal. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>4. <hi rend="sc">It</hi> ſeemed probable, that a medicine of <lb/>ſuch efficacy in a
        diſtemper attended with ſo <lb/>many purulent ulcers, might be alſo uſeful in <lb/>other
        foulneſſes of the blood, accordingly I <lb/>tried it on ſeveral perſons infected with cuta-
        <lb/>neous eruptions and ulcers, who were ſoon re- <lb/>lieved, and ſoon after cured.
        Encouraged by <lb/>theſe Succeſſes I ventured to adviſe it in the <lb/>fouleſt diſtempers,
        wherein it proved much <lb/>more ſucceſsful than Salivations and wood <lb/>drinks had done. </p>
      <pb n="7"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>5. <hi rend="sc">Having</hi> tried it in a great variety of <lb/>caſes, I found it
        ſucceed beyond my hopes; <lb/>in a tedious and painful ulceration of the bow- <lb/>els, in a
        conſumptive cough and (as appeared <lb/>by expectorated pus) an ulcer in the lungs; <lb/>in
        a pleuriſy and peripneumony. And when <lb/>a perſon, who for ſome years had been ſub-
        <lb/>ject to eryſipelatous fevers, perceived the uſu- <lb/>al fore-running ſymptoms to come
        on, I ad- <lb/>viſed her to drink tar water which prevented <lb/>the eryſipelas. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>6. <hi rend="sc">I never</hi> knew any thing ſo good for <lb/>the ſtomach as tar water:
        it cures indigeſtion <lb/>and gives a good appetite. It is an excellent <lb/>medicine in an
        aſthma. It imparts a kindly <lb/>warmth and quick circulation to the juices <lb/>without
        heating, and is therefore uſeful, not <lb/>only as a pectoral and balſamic, but alſo as
        <lb/>a powerful and ſafe deobſtruent in cachectic <lb/>and hyſteric caſes. As it is both
        healing and <lb/>diuretic, it is very good for the gravel. I be- <lb/>lieve it to be of
        great uſe in a dropſy, having <lb/>known it cure a very bad anaſarca in a per- <lb/>ſon
        whoſe thirſt, though very extraordinary, <lb/>was in a ſhort time removed by the drink-
        <lb/>ing of tar water. </p>
      <pb n="8"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>7. <hi rend="sc">The</hi> uſefulneſs of this medicine in <lb/>inflammatory caſes is
        evident, from what <lb/>has been already obſerved <note n="(a)" place="bottom"
          rend="size(0.75) align-center">(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>). <hi rend="italic">Sect.</hi> 5.
        </note>. And yet <lb/>ſome perhaps may ſuſpect that, as the tar it <lb/>ſelf is ſulphureous,
        tar water muſt be of a hot <lb/>and inflaming nature. But it is to be noted <lb/>that all
        balſams contain an acid ſpirit, which <lb/>is in truth a volatile ſalt. Water is a men-
        <lb/>ſtruum that diſſolves all ſorts of ſalts, and <lb/>draws them from their ſubjects. Tar,
        there- <lb/>fore, being a balſam, it's ſalutary acid is ex- <lb/>tracted by water, which yet
        is incapable of <lb/>diſſolving it's groſs reſinous parts, whoſe <lb/>proper menſtruum is
        ſpirit of wine. There- <lb/>fore tar water, not being impregnated with <lb/>reſin, may be
        ſafely uſed in inflammatory <lb/>caſes: and in fact it hath been found an ad- <lb/>mirable
        febrifuge, at once the ſafest cooler and <lb/>cordial. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>8. <hi rend="sc">The</hi> volatile ſalts ſeparated by in- <lb/>fuſion from tar, may be
        ſuppoſed to contain <lb/>it's ſpecific vertues. Mr. Boyle and other <lb/>later Chymiſts are
        agreed, that fixed ſalts are <lb/>much the ſame in all bodies. But it is well <lb/>known
        that volatile ſalts do greatly differ, <lb/>and the eaſier they are ſeparated from the <pb
          n="9"/>
        <lb/>ſubject, the more do they poſſeſs of its ſpe- <lb/>cific qualities. Now the moſt eaſy
        ſepara- <lb/>tion is by infuſion of tar in cold water, which <lb/>to ſmell and taſte ſhewing
        it ſelf well impreg- <lb/>nated, may be preſumed to extract and re- <lb/>tain the moſt pure
        volatile and active par- <lb/>ticles of that vegetable balſam. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>9. <hi rend="sc">Tar</hi> was by the ancients eſteemed <lb/>good againſt poiſons,
        ulcers, the bites of ve- <lb/>nomous creatures, alſo for pthiſical, ſcrophu- <lb/>lous,
        paralitic and aſthmatic perſons. But the <lb/>method of rendering it an inoffenſive medicine
        <lb/>and agreeable to the ſtomach, by extracting <lb/>it's virtues in cold water, was
        unknown to <lb/>them. The leaves and tender tops of pine <lb/>and fir are in our times uſed
        for diet drinks, <lb/>and allowed to be antiſcorbutic and diuretic. <lb/>But the moſt
        elaborate juice, ſalt, and ſpirit <lb/>of thoſe evergreens are to be found in tar;
        <lb/>whoſe virtues extend not to animals alone, <lb/>but alſo to vegetables. Mr. Evelyn in
        his <lb/>treatiſe on Foreſt trees obſerves with wonder, <lb/>that ſtems of trees, ſmeared
        over with tar, <lb/>are preſerved thereby from being hurt by the <lb/>invenomed teeth of
        goats and other injuries, <lb/>while every other thing of an unctuous na- <lb/>ture is
        highly prejudicial to them. </p>
      <pb n="10"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>10. <hi rend="sc">It</hi> ſeems that tar and turpentine may <lb/>be had more or leſs,
        from all ſorts of pines <lb/>and firs whatſoever; and that the native <lb/>ſpirits and
        eſſential ſalts of thoſe vegetables <lb/>are the ſame in turpentine and common tar. <lb/>In
        effect this vulgar tar, which cheapneſs and <lb/>plenty may have rendered contemptible, ap-
        <lb/>pears to be an excellent balſam, containing <lb/>the virtues of moſt other balſams,
        which it <lb/>eaſily imparts to water, and by that means <lb/>readily and inoffenſively
        inſinuates them into <lb/>the habit of the body. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>11. <hi rend="sc">The</hi> reſinous exſudations of pines and <lb/>firs are an important
        branch of the materia <lb/>medica, and not only uſeful in the preſcrip- <lb/>tions of
        phyſicians, but have been alſo <lb/>thought otherwiſe conducive to health. Pliny <lb/>tells
        us, that wines in the time of the old <lb/>Romans were medicated with pitch and reſin;
        <lb/>and Jonſtonus in his Dendrographia obſerves <lb/>that it is wholeſome to walk in groves
        of <lb/>pine trees, which impregnate the air with <lb/>balſamic particles. That all
        turpentines and <lb/>reſins are good for the lungs, againſt gravel <lb/>alſo and
        obſtructions, is no ſecret. And that <lb/>the medicinal properties of thoſe drugs are
        <lb/>found in Tar water, without heating the <pb n="11"/>
        <lb/>blood, or diſordering the ſtomach, is con- <lb/>firmed by experience: and particularly
        that <lb/>pthiſical and aſthmatic perſons receive ſpeedy <lb/>and great relief from the uſe
        of it. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>12. <hi rend="sc">Balsams</hi>, as all unctuous and oily <lb/>medicines, create a
        nauſeating in the ſtomach. <lb/>They cannot therefore be taken in ſubſtance, <lb/>ſo much or
        ſo long, as to produce all thoſe <lb/>ſalutary effects, which, if thoroughly mixed <lb/>with
        the blood and juices, they wou'd be <lb/>capable of producing. It muſt therefore be a
        <lb/>thing of great benefit, to be able to introduce <lb/>any requiſite quantity of their
        volatile parts <lb/>into the fineſt ducts and capillaries, ſo as not <lb/>to offend the
        ſtomach, but, on the contrary, <lb/>to comfort and ſtrengthen it in a great degree. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>13. <hi rend="sc">According</hi> to Pliny, liquid pitch <lb/>(as he calls it) or Tar
        was obtained by ſet- <lb/>ting fire to billets of old fat pines or firs. <lb/>The firſt
        running was tar, the later or <lb/>thicker running was pitch. Theophraſtus is <lb/>more
        particular: he tells us the Macedoni- <lb/>ans made huge heaps of the cloven trunks of
        <lb/>thoſe trees, wherein the billets were placed <lb/>erect beſide each other. That ſuch
        heaps or <lb/>piles of wood were ſometimes a hundred and <lb/>eighty cubits round, and ſixty
        or even a <pb n="12"/>
        <lb/>hundred high: and that having covered them <lb/>with ſods of earth to prevent the flame
        from <lb/>burſting forth (in which caſe the tar was loſt) <lb/>they ſet on fire thoſe huge
        heaps of pine or fir, <lb/>letting the tar and pitch run out in a channel. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>14. <hi rend="sc">Pliny</hi> ſaith, it was cuſtomary for <lb/>the antients, to hold
        fleeces of wooll over <lb/>the ſteam of boiling tar, and ſqueeze the <lb/>moiſture from
        them, which watery ſubſtance <lb/>was called piſſinum. Ray will have this to <lb/>be the
        ſame with the piſſelæum of the anci- <lb/>ents; but Harduin in his Notes on Pliny,
        <lb/>thinks the piſſelæum to have been produced <lb/>from the cones of cedars. What uſe they
        <lb/>made of theſe liquors anciently I know not: <lb/>But it may be preſumed they were uſed
        in <lb/>medicine, though at preſent, for ought I can <lb/>find, they are not uſed at all. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>15. <hi rend="sc">From</hi> the manner of procuring <lb/>tar <note n="(b)"
          place="bottom" rend="size(0.75) align-center">(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) <hi rend="italic"
            >Sect.</hi> 13. </note> it plainly appears to be a natural <lb/>production, lodged in
        the veſſels of the tree, <lb/>whence it is only freed and let looſe (not <lb/>made) by
        burning. If we may believe <lb/>Pliny, the firſt running or tar was called ce- <lb/>drium,
        and was of ſuch efficacy to preſerve <lb/>from putrefaction, that in Ægypt they em-
        <lb/>balmed dead bodies with it. And to this he <pb n="13"/>
        <lb/>aſcribes their mummies continuing uncur- <lb/>rupted for ſo many ages. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>16. <hi rend="sc">Some</hi> modern writers inform us that <lb/>tar flows from the
        trunks of pines and firs, <lb/>when they are very old, through inciſions <lb/>made in the
        bark near the root. Pitch is tar <lb/>inſpiſſated: and both are the oyl of the tree
        <lb/>grown thick and black with age and ſun. <lb/>The trees like old men being unable to
        per- <lb/>ſpire, and their ſecretory ducts obſtructed, they <lb/>are, as one may ſay,
        choaked and ſtuffed with <lb/>their own juice. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>17. <hi rend="sc">The</hi> method uſed by our colonies in <lb/>America, for making tar
        and pitch, is in effect <lb/>the ſame with that of the ancient Macedoni- <lb/>ans; as
        appears from the account given in the <lb/>philoſophical tranſactions. And the relation
        <lb/>of Leo Africanus who deſcribes, as an eye <lb/>witneſs, the making of tar on Mount
        Atlas, <lb/>agrees in ſubſtance, with the methods uſed by <lb/>the Macedonians of old, and
        the people of <lb/>New England at this day. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>18. <hi rend="sc">Jonstonus</hi> in his Dendrogra- <lb/>phia, is of opinion, that pitch
        was anciently <lb/>made of cedar, as well as of the pine and fir <lb/>grown old and oily. It
        ſhould ſeem indeed that <pb n="14"/>
        <lb/>one and the ſame word was uſed by the an- <lb/>cients in a large ſenſe, ſo as to
        comprehend the <lb/>juices iſſuing from all thoſe trees. Tar and <lb/>all ſorts of
        exſudations from evergreens are, <lb/>in a general acceptation, included under the <lb/>name
        reſin. Hard coarſe reſin or dry pitch is <lb/>made from tar, by letting it blaze till the
        moiſ- <lb/>ture is ſpent. Liquid reſin is properly an oily <lb/>viſcid juice oozing from the
        bark of ever- <lb/>green trees, either ſpontaneouſly or by inciſion. <lb/>It is thought to
        be the oyl of the bark inſpi- <lb/>ſiated by the ſun. As, it iſſues from the tree <lb/>it is
        liquid, but becomes dry and hard being <lb/>condenſed by the ſun or by fire. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>19. <hi rend="sc">According</hi> to Theophraſtus, reſin <lb/>was obtained by ſtriping
        off the bark from <lb/>pines, and by inciſions made in the ſilver fir <lb/>and the pitch
        pine. The inhabitants of Mount <lb/>Ida, he tells us, ſtriped the trunk of the <lb/>pine on
        the ſunny ſide two or three cubits <lb/>from the ground. He obſerves that a good <lb/>pine
        might be made to yield reſin every year; an <lb/>indifferent every other year, and the
        weaker <lb/>trees once in three years; and that three run- <lb/><choice>
          <corr>nings</corr>
          <sic>ings</sic>
        </choice> were as much as a tree cou'd bear. It is <lb/>remarked by the ſame author, that a
        pine <lb/>doth not at once produce fruit and reſin, but <lb/>the former only in its youth,
        the later in its <lb/>old age. </p>
      <pb n="15"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>20. <hi rend="sc">Turpentine</hi> is a fine reſin. Four <lb/>kinds of this are in uſe.
        The turpentine of <lb/>Chios or Cyprus which flows from the Tur- <lb/>pentine tree; the
        Venice turpentine which <lb/>is got by piercing the Larch tree; the Strars- <lb/>burgh
        Turpentine which Mr. Ray informs <lb/>us is procured from the knots of the ſilver <lb/>fir;
        it is fragrant and grows yellow with <lb/>age; the fourth kind is common turpen- <lb/>tine
        neither tranſparent, nor ſo liquid as <lb/>the former; and this Mr. Ray taketh to flow
        <lb/>from the mountain pine. All theſe turpentines <lb/>are uſeful in the ſame intentions.
        Theophraſ- <lb/>tus ſaith the beſt reſin or turpentine is got from <lb/>the Terebinthus
        growing in Syria and ſome of <lb/>the Greek iſlands. The next beſt from the <lb/>ſilver fir
        and pitch pine. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>21. <hi rend="sc">Turpentine</hi> is on all hands al- <lb/>lowed to have great
        medicinal virtues. Tar <lb/>and it's infuſion contain thoſe virtues. Tar <lb/>water is
        extremely pectoral and reſtorative, <lb/>and if I may judge, from what experience I
        <lb/>have had, it poſſeſſeth the moſt valuable qua- <lb/>lities aſcribed to the ſeveral
        balſams of Peru, <lb/>of Tolu, of Capivi and even to the balm of <lb/>Gilead, ſuch is it's
        virtue in aſthmas and <lb/>pleuriſies, in obſtructions and ulcerous eroſi- <pb n="16"/>
        <lb/>ons of the inward parts. Balſams as hath <lb/>been already obſerved are apt to offend
        the <lb/>ſtomach. But tar water may be taken with- <lb/>out offending the ſtomach. For the
        ſtrength- <lb/>ening whereof it is the beſt medicine I have <lb/>ever tried. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>22. <hi rend="sc">The</hi> folly of man rateth things by <lb/>their ſcarceneſs, but
        Providence hath made <lb/>the moſt uſeful things moſt common. <lb/>Among thoſe liquid oily
        extracts from trees <lb/>and ſhrubs, which are termed Balſams, and <lb/>valued for medicinal
        virtues, Tar may hold it's <lb/>place as a moſt valuable balſam. It's fra- <lb/>grancy
        ſheweth, that it is poſſeſſed of ac- <lb/>tive qualities, and it's oilyneſs, that it is
        <lb/>fitted to retain them. This excellent balſam <lb/>may be purchaſed for a penny a pound,
        <lb/>whereas the balſam of Judæa, when moſt <lb/>plenty, was ſold on the very ſpot that pro-
        <lb/>duced it, for double its weight in ſilver, if <lb/>we may credit Pliny; who alſo
        informs us <lb/>that the beſt balſam of Judæa flowed only <lb/>from the bark, and that it
        was adulterated <lb/>with reſin and oyle of turpentine. Now <lb/>comparing the vertues I
        have experienced in <lb/>Tar, with thoſe I find aſcribed to the pre- <lb/>cious balm of
        Judæa, of Gilead, or of Mecha <lb/>(as it is diverſly called) I am of opinion, that <pb
          n="17"/>
        <lb/>the later is not a medicine of more value or <lb/>efficacy than the former. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>23. <hi rend="sc">Pliny</hi> ſuppoſed amber to be a <lb/>reſin, and to diſtill from
        ſome ſpecies of pine, <lb/>which he gathered from it's ſmell. Never- <lb/>theleſs it's being
        dug out of the earth ſhews it <lb/>to be a foſſil, though of a very different kind <lb/>from
        other foſſils. But thus much is certain, <lb/>that the medicinal virtues of amber are to
        <lb/>be found in the balſamic juices of pines and <lb/>firs. Particularly the virtues of the
        moſt <lb/>valuable preparation, I mean ſalt of amber, <lb/>are in a great degree anſwered by
        Tar water, <lb/>as a detergent, diaphoretic, and diuretic. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>24. <hi rend="sc">There</hi> is, as hath been already <lb/>obſerved, more or leſs oyl
        and balſam in all <lb/>evergreen trees, which retains the acid ſpirit, <lb/>that principle
        of life and verdure; the not <lb/>retaining whereof in ſufficient quantity, <lb/>cauſeth
        other plants to droop and wither. <lb/>Of theſe evergreen trees productive of reſin,
        <lb/>pitch, and tar, Pliny enumerates ſix kinds in <lb/>Europe; Jonſtonus reckons up thrice
        that <lb/>number of the pine and fir family. And, in- <lb/>deed, their number, their
        variety, and their <lb/>likeneſs makes it difficult to be exact. </p>
      <pb n="18"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>25. <hi rend="sc">It</hi> is remarked both by Theo- <lb/>phraſtus and Jonſtonus, that
        trees growing <lb/>in low and ſhady places do not yield ſo good <lb/>tar, as thoſe which
        grow in higher and more <lb/>expoſed ſituations. And Theophraſtus fur- <lb/>ther obſerves,
        that the inhabitants of mount <lb/>Ida in Aſia, who diſtinguiſh the Idæan pine <lb/>from the
        maritime, affirm, that the tar flow- <lb/>ing from the former is in greater plenty, as
        <lb/>well as more fragrant than the other. Hence <lb/>it ſhou'd ſeem, the pines or firs in
        the moun- <lb/>tains of Scotland, might be employ'd that <lb/>way, and rendered valuable;
        even where <lb/>the timber, by it's remoteneſs from water- <lb/>carriage, is of ſmall value.
        What we call <lb/>the Scotch fir is falſly ſo called, being in <lb/>truth a wild foreſt
        pine, and (as Mr. Ray <lb/><choice>
          <corr>informs</corr>
          <sic>inſorms</sic>
        </choice> us) agreeing much with the deſcrip- <lb/>tion of a pine growing on mount Olympus
        in <lb/>Phrygia, probably the only place where <lb/>it is found out of theſe iſlands; in
        which of <lb/>late years it is ſo much planted and culti- <lb/>vated with ſo little
        advantage, while the <lb/>cedar of Lebanon might perhaps be raiſed, <lb/>with little more
        trouble, and much more <lb/>profit and ornament. </p>
      <pb n="19"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>26. <hi rend="sc">The</hi> pines, which differ from the <lb/>firs in the length and
        diſpoſition of their <lb/>leaves and hardneſs of the wood, do not in <lb/>Pliny's account,
        yield ſo much reſin as the fir <lb/>trees. Several ſpecies of both are accurately
        <lb/>deſcribed and delineated by the naturaliſts. <lb/>But they all agree ſo far as to ſeem
        related. <lb/>Theophraſtus gives the preference to that <lb/>reſin which is got from the
        ſilver fir and pitch <lb/>tree (έλάτη and πίτυς) before that yielded by <lb/>the pine, which
        yet he ſaith is in greater <lb/>plenty. Pliny, on the contrary, affirms that <lb/>the pine
        produceth the ſmalleſt quantity. It <lb/>ſhou'd ſeem therefore that the interpreter of
        <lb/>Theophraſtus might have been miſtaken, in <lb/>rendering πέυκη by pinus, as well as
        Jon- <lb/>ſtonus, who likewiſe takes the pine for the <lb/>πεύκη of Theophraſtus. Hardouin
        will have <lb/>the pinus of Pliny to have been by others <lb/>called πέυκη, but by
        Theophraſtus πίτυς. <lb/>Ray thinks the common fir, or picea of the <lb/>Latins to be the
        male fir of Theophraſtus. <lb/>This was probably the ſpruce fir; for the <lb/>picea
        according to Pliny, yields much reſin, <lb/>loves a cold and mountainous ſituation, and
        <lb/>is diſtinguiſhed, tonſili facilitate, by its fitneſs <lb/>to be ſhorn, which agrees
        with the ſpruce fir, <lb/>whereof I have ſeen cloſe ſhorn hedges. </p>
      <pb n="20"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>27. <hi rend="sc">There</hi> ſeems to have been ſome con- <lb/>fuſion in the naming of
        theſe trees, as well <lb/>among the ancients as the moderns. The <lb/>ancient Greek and
        Latin names are by later <lb/>authors applied very differently. Pliny him- <lb/>ſelf
        acknowledgeth, it is not eaſy even for the <lb/>skilful to diſtinguiſh the trees by their
        leaves, <lb/>and know their ſexes and kinds: and that <lb/>difficulty is ſince much
        increaſed, by the diſ- <lb/>covery of many new ſpecies of that ever- <lb/>green tribe,
        growing in various parts of the <lb/>globe. But deſcriptions are not ſo eaſily
        <lb/>miſapplied as names. Theophraſtus tells us, <lb/>that πιτυς differeth from πεύκη, among
        other <lb/>things, in that it is neither ſo tall nor ſo <lb/>ſtreight, nor hath ſo large a
        leaf. The fir <lb/>he diſtinguiſheth into male and female: the <lb/>later is ſofter timber
        than the male, it is alſo <lb/>a taller and fairer tree, and this is probably <lb/>the
        ſilver fir. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>28. <hi rend="sc">To</hi> ſay no more on this obſcure <lb/>buſineſs which I leave to
        the Criticks, I ſhall <lb/>obſerve that according to Theophraſtus not on- <lb/>ly the
        turpentine trees, the pines, and the firs <lb/>yield reſin or tar, but alſo the cedars and
        palm <lb/>trees; and the words pix and reſina are taken <lb/>by Pliny in ſo large a ſenſe as
        to include the <pb n="21"/>
        <lb/>weepings of the Lentiſcus and Cypreſs, and <lb/>the balms of Arabia and Judæa; all
        which <lb/>perhaps are near of kin, and in their moſt uſe- <lb/>ful qualities concur with
        common tar, eſpeci- <lb/>ally the Norwegian, which is the moſt liquid <lb/>and beſt for
        medicinal uſes of any that I have <lb/>experienced. Thoſe trees that grow on <lb/>mountains,
        expoſed to the ſun or the North <lb/>wind, are reckoned by Theophraſtus to produce <lb/>the
        beſt and pureſt Tar: And the Idæan pines <lb/>were <choice>
          <corr>diſtinguiſhed</corr>
          <sic>diſtingniſhed</sic>
        </choice> from thoſe growing on the <lb/>plain, as yielding a thinner, ſweeter, and better
        <lb/>ſcented tar, all which differences I think I have <lb/>obſerved, between the tar that
        comes from <lb/>Norway, and that which comes from low <lb/>and ſwampy countries. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>29. Agreeably to the old obſervation <lb/>of the Peripatetics, that heat gathereth
        homo- <lb/>geneous things and diſperſeth ſuch as are he- <lb/>terogeneous, we find chymiſtry
        is fitted for <lb/>the analyſis of bodies. But the chymiſtry of <lb/>nature is much more
        perfect than that of human <lb/>art, inaſmuch as it joineth to the power of <lb/>heat that
        of the moſt exquiſite mechaniſm. <lb/>Thoſe who have examined the ſtructure of <lb/>trees
        and plants by microſcopes, have diſco- <lb/>vered an admirable variety of fine capillary
        <lb/>tubes and veſſels, fitted for ſeveral purpoſes, <pb n="22"/>
        <lb/>as the imbibing or attracting of proper nou- <lb/>riſhment, the diſtributing thereof
        through all <lb/>parts of the vegetable, the diſcharge of ſu- <lb/>perfluities, the
        ſecretion of particular juices. <lb/>They are found to have ducts anſwering to <lb/>the
        tracheæ in animals, for the conveying of <lb/>air; they have others anſwering to lacteals,
        <lb/>arteries and veins. They feed, digeſt, reſpire, <lb/>perſpire and generate their kind,
        and are pro- <lb/>vided with organs nicely fitted for all thoſe <lb/>uſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>30. <hi rend="sc">The</hi> ſap veſſels are obſerved to be fine <lb/>tubes running up
        through the trunk from the <lb/>root. Secretory veſſels are found in the bark, <lb/>buds,
        leaves, and flowers. Exhaling veſſels, <lb/>for carrying off excrementitious parts, are diſ-
        <lb/>covered throughout the whole ſurface of the <lb/>vegetable. And (though this point be
        not ſo <lb/>well agreed) doctor Grew in his anatomy of <lb/>plants, thinks there appears a
        circulation of the <lb/>ſap, moving downwards in the root, and feed- <lb/>ing the trunk
        upwards. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>31. <hi rend="sc">Some</hi> difference indeed there is be- <lb/>tween learned men,
        concerning the proper uſe <lb/>of certain parts of vegetables. But, whether <lb/>the
        diſcoverers have rightly gueſſed at all their <lb/>uſes or no, thus much is certain, that
        there <pb n="23"/>
        <lb/>are innumerable fine and curious parts in a <lb/>vegetable body, and a wonderful
        ſimilitude or <lb/>analogy between the mechaniſm of plants and <lb/>animals. And perhaps
        ſome will think it not <lb/>unreaſonable, to ſuppoſe the mechaniſm of <lb/>plants more
        curious than even that of animals, <lb/>if we conſider not only the ſeveral juices ſe-
        <lb/>creted by different parts of the ſame plant, <lb/>but alſo, the endleſs variety of
        juices drawn <lb/>and formed out of the ſame ſoil, by various <lb/>ſpecies of vegetables;
        which muſt therefore <lb/>differ in an endleſs variety, as to the texture <lb/>of their
        abſorbent veſſels and ſecretory <lb/>ducts. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>32. <hi rend="sc">A Body</hi>, therefore, either animal or <lb/>vegetable may be
        conſidered, as an organiſed <lb/>ſyſtem of tubes and veſſels, containing ſeveral <lb/>ſorts
        of fluids. And as fluids are moved <lb/>through the veſſels of animal bodies, by the
        <lb/>ſyſtole and diaſtole of the heart, the alter- <lb/>nate expanſion and condenſation of
        the air, <lb/>and the oſcillations in the membranes and <lb/>tunicks of the veſſels; even ſo
        by means of air <lb/>expanded and contracted in the tracheæ or <lb/>veſſels made up of
        elaſtic fibres, the ſap is <lb/>propelled through the arterial tubes of a plant, <lb/>and
        the vegetable juices, as they are rarefied <lb/>by heat or condenſed by cold, will either
        aſ- <pb n="24"/>
        <lb/>cend and evaporate into air, or deſcend in <lb/>the form of a groſs liquor. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>33. <hi rend="sc">Juices</hi> therefore, firſt purified by <lb/>ſtraining through the
        fine pores of the root, <lb/>are afterwards exalted by the action of the air <lb/>and
        veſſels of the plant, but, above all, by <lb/>the action of the ſun's light; which at the
        <lb/>ſame time that it heats, doth wonderfully ra- <lb/>refy and raiſe the ſap; till it
        perſpires and <lb/>forms an atmoſphære, like the effluvia of ani- <lb/>mal bodies. And
        though the leaves are <lb/>ſuppoſed to perform principally the office of <lb/>lungs,
        breathing out excrementitious va- <lb/>pours and drawing in alimentary; yet it <lb/>ſeems
        probable, that the reciprocal actions of <lb/>repulſion and attraction, are performed all
        <lb/>over the ſurface of vegetables, as well as <lb/>animals. In which reciprocation,
        Hippocra- <lb/>tes ſuppoſeth the manner of nature's acting, for <lb/>the nouriſhment and
        health of animal bodies <lb/>chiefly to conſiſt. And, indeed, what ſhare <lb/>of a plant's
        nouriſhment is drawn through <lb/>the leaves and bark, from that ambient hetero-
        <lb/>geneous fluid called air, is not eaſy to ſay. <lb/>It ſeems very conſiderable and
        altogether ne- <lb/>ceſſary, as well to vegetable as animal <lb/>life. </p>
      <pb n="25"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>34. <hi rend="sc">It</hi> is an opinion received by many, that <lb/>the ſap circulates
        in plants as the blood in <lb/>animals: that it aſcends through capillary ar- <lb/>teries in
        the trunk, into which are inoſculated <lb/>other veſſels of the bark anſwering to veins,
        <lb/>which bring back to the root the remainder of <lb/>the ſap, over and above what had
        been depo- <lb/>ſited, during it's aſcent by the arterial veſſels, <lb/>and ſecreted for the
        ſeveral uſes of the vege- <lb/>table throughout all it's parts, ſtem, branches<choice>
          <corr>,</corr>
          <sic/>
        </choice>
        <lb/>leaves, flowers, and fruit. Others deny this <lb/>circulation, and affirm that the ſap
        doth not <lb/>return through the bark veſſels. It is never- <lb/>theleſs agreed by all that
        there are aſcending <lb/>and deſcending juices; while ſome will <lb/>have the aſcent and
        deſcent to be a circula- <lb/>tion of the ſame juices through different veſ- <lb/>ſels:
        others will have the aſcending juice to <lb/>be one ſort attracted by the root, and the de-
        <lb/>ſcending another imbibed by the leaves, or <lb/>extremities of the branches: laſtly,
        others <lb/>think that the ſame juice, as it is rarefied or <lb/>condenſed by heat or cold,
        riſes and ſubſides <lb/>in the ſame tube. I ſhall not take upon me <lb/>to decide this
        controverſy. Only I cannot <lb/>help obſerving, that the vulgar argument from <lb/>analogy
        between plants and animals loſeth <lb/>much of it's force, if it be conſidered, that <pb
          n="26"/>
        <lb/>the ſuppoſed circulating of the ſap, from the <lb/>root or lacteals through the
        arteries, and <lb/>thence returning, by inoſculations, through <lb/>the veins or bark
        veſſels to the root or lacteals <lb/>again, is in no ſort conformable or analogous <lb/>to
        the circulation of the blood. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>35. <hi rend="sc">It</hi> is ſufficient to obſerve, what all <lb/>muſt acknowledge,
        that a plant or tree is a <lb/>very nice and complicated machine <note n="(g)"
          place="bottom" rend="size(0.75) align-center">(<hi rend="italic">g</hi>) 30, 31 </note>;
        by <lb/>the ſeveral parts and motions whereof, the <lb/>crude juices admitted through the
        abſorbent <lb/>veſſels, whether of the root, trunk, or <lb/>branches, are variouſly mixed,
        ſeparated, al- <lb/>tered, digeſted, and exalted in a very wond- <lb/>derful manner. The
        juice as it paſſeth in and <lb/>out, up and down, through tubes of different <lb/>textures,
        ſhapes, and ſizes, and is affected by <lb/>the alternate compreſſion and expanſion of
        <lb/>elaſtic veſſels, by the viciſſitudes of ſeaſons, <lb/>the changes of weather, and the
        various ac- <lb/>tion of the ſolar light, grows ſtill more and <lb/>more elaborate. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>36. <hi rend="sc">There</hi> is therefore no chymiſtry like <lb/>that of nature, which
        addeth to the force of <lb/>fire the moſt delicate, various and artificial <lb/>percolation
          <note n="(d)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.75) align-center">(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) 29.
        </note>. The inceſſant action of the <pb n="27"/>
        <lb/>ſun upon the elements of air, earth, and <lb/>water, and on all ſorts of mixed bodies,
        ani- <lb/>mal, vegetable and foſſil, is ſuppoſed to <lb/>perform all ſorts of chymical
        operations. <lb/>Whence it ſhould follow, that the air con- <lb/>tains all ſorts of chymic
        productions, the va- <lb/>pours, fumes, oyls, ſalts, and ſpirits of all <lb/>the bodies we
        know: From which general <lb/>aggregate or maſs, thoſe that are proper be- <lb/>ing drawn
        in, through the fine veſſels of the <lb/>leaves, branches, and ſtem of the tree, under-
        <lb/>go in it's various organs, new alterations, <lb/>ſecretions, and digeſtions, till ſuch
        time as <lb/>they aſſume the moſt elaborate form. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>37. <hi rend="sc">Nor</hi> is it to be wondered, that the <lb/>peculiar texture of each
        plant or tree, coope- <lb/>rating with the ſolar fire and preexiſting juices, <lb/>ſhould ſo
        alter the fine nouriſhment drawn <lb/>from earth and air, <note n="(f)" place="bottom"
          rend="size(0.75) indent">(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>) 33. </note> as to produce vari-
        <lb/>ous ſpecific qualities of great efficacy in me- <lb/>dicine; eſpecially if it be
        conſidered that in <lb/>the opinion of learned men, there is an in- <lb/>fluence on plants
        derived from the ſun, beſides <lb/>it's mere heat. Certainly doctor Grew, that <lb/>curious
        anatomiſt of plants, holds the ſolar <lb/>influence to differ from that of a mere culinary
          <pb n="28"/>
        <lb/>fire, otherwiſe than by being only a more <lb/>temperate and equal heat. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>38. <hi rend="sc">The</hi> alimentary juice taken into the <lb/>lacteals, whether of
        animals or vegetables, <lb/>conſiſts of oily, aqueous, and ſaline particles, <lb/>which
        being diſſolved, volatiliſed, and di- <lb/>verſly agitated, part thereof is ſpent and exha-
        <lb/>led into the air; and that part which remains <lb/>is by the œconomy of the plant, and
        action <lb/>of the ſun, ſtrained, purified, concocted, and <lb/>ripened into an inſpiſſated
        oyl or balſam, <lb/>and depoſited in certain cells placed chiefly <lb/>in the bark, which is
        thought to anſwer the <lb/>panniculus adipoſus in animals, defending <lb/>trees from the
        weather, and, when in ſuffici- <lb/>ent quantity, rendering them evergreen. This
        <lb/>balſam, weeping or ſweating through the <lb/>bark, hardens into reſin; <choice>
          <corr>and</corr>
          <sic>aud</sic>
        </choice> this moſt copi- <lb/>ouſly in the ſeveral ſpecies of pines and firs, <lb/>whoſe
        oyl being in greater quantity, and <lb/>more tenacious of the acid ſpirit or vegetable
        <lb/>ſoul (as perhaps it may not improperly be <lb/>called) abides the action of the ſun,
        and at- <lb/>tracting the ſun beams, is thereby exalted and <lb/>enriched, ſo as to become a
        moſt noble medi- <lb/>cine; ſuch is the laſt product of a tree, per- <lb/>fectly maturated
        by time and ſun. </p>
      <pb n="29"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>39. <hi rend="sc">It</hi> is remarked by Theophraſtus, that <lb/>all plants and trees
        while they put forth have <lb/>moſt humour, but when they have ceaſed to <lb/>germinate and
        bear, then the humour is <lb/>ſtrongeſt and moſt ſheweth the nature of the <lb/>plant, and
        that, therefore, trees yielding re- <lb/>ſin ſhould be cut after germination. It ſeems
        <lb/>alſo very reaſonable to ſuppoſe the juice of <lb/>old trees, whoſe organs bring no new
        ſap, <lb/>ſhould be better ripened than that of others. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>40. <hi rend="sc">The</hi> aromatic flavours of vegetables <lb/>ſeem to depend upon the
        ſun's light, as much <lb/>as colours. As in the production of the later, <lb/>the reflecting
        powers of the object, ſo in that <lb/>of the former, the attractive and organical
        <lb/>powers of the plant cooperate with the <lb/>ſun <note n="(h)" place="bottom"
          rend="size(0.75) align-center">(<hi rend="italic">h</hi>) 36, 37. </note>. And as from ſir
        Iſaac Newton's <lb/>experiments it appears, that all colours are <lb/>virtually in the white
        light of the ſun, and <lb/>ſhew themſelves when the raies are ſepa- <lb/>rated by the
        attracting and repelling powers <lb/>of objects, even ſo the ſpecific qualities of <lb/>the
        elaborate juices of plants ſeem to be <lb/>virtually or eminently contained in the ſolar
        <lb/>light, and are actually exhibited upon the <lb/>ſeparation of the raies, by the
        peculiar powers <pb n="30"/>
        <lb/>of the capillary organs in vegetables, attract- <lb/>ing and imbibing certain raies,
        which produce <lb/>certain flavours and qualities, in like manner <lb/>as certain raies
        being reflected, produce cer- <lb/>tain colours. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>41. <hi rend="sc">It</hi> hath been obſerved by ſome curious <lb/>anatomiſts, that the
        ſecretory veſſels in the <lb/>glands of animal bodies are lined with a fine <lb/>down, which
        in different glands is of diffe- <lb/>rent colours. And it is thought, that each
        <lb/>particular down, being originally imbued <lb/>with it's own proper juice, attracts none
        but <lb/>that ſort; by which means ſo many various <lb/>juices are ſecreted in different
        parts of the <lb/>body. And perhaps there may be ſomething <lb/>analogous to this, in the
        fine abſorbent veſ- <lb/>ſels of plants, which may cooperate towards <lb/>producing that
        endleſs variety of juices, ela- <lb/>borated in plants from the ſame earth and <lb/>air. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>42. <hi rend="sc">The</hi> balſam or eſſential oyl of vegetables <lb/>contains a
        ſpirit, wherein conſiſt the ſpecific <lb/>qualities, the ſmell and taſte of the plant.
        <lb/>Boerhaave holds the native preſiding ſpirit to be <lb/>neither, oyl, ſalt, earth, or
        water; but ſome- <lb/>what too fine and ſubtile to be caught alone <lb/>and rendered viſible
        to the eye. This when <pb n="31"/>
        <lb/>ſuffered to fly off, for inſtance, from the oyl <lb/>of roſemary, leaves it deſtitute
        of all flavour<choice>
          <corr>.</corr>
          <sic/>
        </choice>
        <lb/>This ſpark of life, this ſpirit or ſoul, if we <lb/>may ſo ſay, of the vegetable
        departs without <lb/>any ſenſible diminution of the oyl or water <lb/>wherein it was lodged. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>43. <hi rend="sc">It</hi> ſhould ſeem that the forms, ſouls, <lb/>or principles of
        vegetable life, ſubſiſt in <lb/>the light or ſolar emanation <note n="(m)" place="bottom"
          rend="size(0.75) align-center">(<hi rend="italic">m</hi>) 40. </note>, which <lb/>in
        reſpect of the macrocoſm is what the <lb/>animal ſpirit is to the microcoſm; the
        <lb/>interior tegument, the ſubtile inſtrument <lb/>and vehicle of power. No wonder then
        that <lb/>the ens primum or ſcintilla ſpirituoſa, as it is <lb/>called, of plants ſhould be
        a thing ſo fine and <lb/>fugacious as to eſcape our niceſt ſearch. It is <lb/>evident that
        nature at the ſun's approach ve- <lb/>getates; and languiſhes at his receſs; this ter-
        <lb/>reſtrial globe ſeeming only a matrix diſpoſed <lb/>and prepared to receive life from
        his light; <lb/>whence Homer in his hymns ſtyleth earth <lb/>the wife of heaven,
          <unclear>άλοχ, όυραν <gap reason="illegible"/> άςερόεντος</unclear>. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>44. <hi rend="sc">The</hi> luminous ſpirit which is the form <lb/>or life of a plant,
        from whence it's differences <lb/>and properties flow, is ſomewhat extremely <pb n="32"/>
        <lb/>volatile. It is not the oyl, but a thing more <lb/>ſubtile whereof oyl is the vehicle,
        which re- <lb/>tains it from flying off, and is lodged in ſeve- <lb/>ral parts of the plant,
        particularly in the cells <lb/>of the bark and in the ſeeds. This oyl pu- <lb/>rified and
        exalted by the organical powers of <lb/>the plant, and agitated by warmth, becomes <lb/>a
        proper receptacle of the ſpirit; part of <lb/>which ſpirit exhales through the leaves and
        <lb/>flowers, and part is arreſted by this unctuous <lb/>humour that detains it in the
        plant. It is to <lb/>be noted this eſſential oyl animated, as one <lb/>may ſay, with the
        flavour of the plant is very <lb/>different from any ſpirit, that can be procur- <lb/>ed
        from the ſame plant by fermentation. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>45. <hi rend="sc">Light</hi> impregnates air, <note n="(n)" place="bottom"
          rend="size(0.75) align-center">(<hi rend="italic">n</hi>) 37, 43. </note> air im-
        <lb/>pregnates vapour; and this becomes a watery <lb/>juice by deſtillation having riſen
        firſt in the <lb/>cold ſtill with a kindly gentle heat. This <lb/>fragrant vegetable water
        is poſſeſſed of the <lb/>ſpecific odour and taſte of the plant. It is re- <lb/>marked that
        deſtilled oyls added to water <lb/>for counterfeiting the vegetable water can <lb/>never
        equal it, artificial chymiſtry falling <lb/>ſhort of the natural. </p>
      <pb n="33"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>46. <hi rend="sc">The</hi> leſs violence is uſed to nature <lb/>the better it's
        produce. The juice of olives <lb/>or grapes iſſuing by the lighteſt preſ- <lb/>ſure is beſt.
        Reſins that drop from the <lb/>branches ſpontaneouſly, or ooze upon the <lb/>ſlighteſt
        inſicion, are the fineſt and moſt fra- <lb/>grant. And infuſions are obſerved to act
        <lb/>more ſtrongly than decoctions of plants, tho <lb/>more ſubtile and volatile ſalts and
        ſpirits <lb/>which might be loſt or corrupted by the <lb/>later, being obtained in their
        natural ſtate <lb/>by the former. It is alſo obſerved that the <lb/>fineſt, pureſt, and moſt
        volatile part is that <lb/>which firſt aſcends in deſtillation. And, in- <lb/>deed, it
        ſhould ſeem the lighteſt and moſt ac- <lb/>tive particles required leaſt force to diſengage
        <lb/>them from the ſubject. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>47. <hi rend="sc">The</hi> ſalts, therefore, and more active <lb/>ſpirits of the tar
        are got by infuſion in cold <lb/>water: but the reſinous part is not to be diſ- <lb/>ſolved
        thereby: <note n="(p)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.75) indent">(<hi rend="italic">p</hi>)
            <hi rend="italic">Sect.</hi> 7. </note> Hence the prejudice <lb/>which ſome perhaps may
        entertain againſt <lb/>Tar water, as a medicine, the uſe whereof <lb/>might inflame the
        blood by it's ſulphur and <lb/>reſin, appears to be not well grounded; <lb/>it being indeed
        impregnated with a fine acid <pb n="34"/>
        <lb/>ſpirit, balſamic, cooling, diuretic, and poſſeſ- <lb/>ſed of many other virtues <note
          n="(q)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.75) align-center">(<hi rend="italic">q</hi>) <hi
            rend="italic">Sect.</hi> 42, 44. </note>. Spirits are <lb/>ſuppoſed to conſiſt of ſalts
        and phlegme, pro- <lb/>bably too ſomewhat of a fine oily nature, <lb/>differing from oyl in
        that it mixeth with <lb/>water, and agreeing with oyl, in that it <lb/>runneth in rivulets
        by deſtillation. Thus <lb/>much is allowed, that the water, earth, and <lb/>fixed ſalt are
        the ſame in all plants; that, <lb/>therefore, which differenceth a plant or makes <lb/>it
        what it is, the native ſpark or form, in the <lb/>language of the chymiſts or ſchools, is
        none <lb/>of thoſe things, nor yet the fineſt oyl, <lb/>which ſeemeth only it's receptacle
        or vehicle. <lb/>It is obſerved by chymiſts, that all ſorts of <lb/>balſamic wood afford an
        acid ſpirit, which is <lb/>the volatile oily ſalt of the vegetable: Here- <lb/>in is chiefly
        contained their medicinal virtues, <lb/>and by the tryals I have made it appears, <lb/>that
        the acid ſpirit in tar water, poſſeſſeth the <lb/>virtues, in an eminent degree, of that of
        guai- <lb/>acum, and other medicinal woods. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>48. <hi rend="sc">Qualities</hi> in a degree too ſtrong for <lb/>human nature to
        ſubdue, and aſſimilate to it <lb/>ſelf, muſt hurt the conſtitution. All acids,
        <lb/>therefore, may not be uſeful or innocent. But <lb/>this ſeemeth an acid ſo thoroughly
        concocted, <pb n="35"/>
        <lb/>ſo gentle, bland, and temperate, and withal <lb/>a ſpirit ſo fine and volatile, as
        readily to enter <lb/>the ſmalleſt veſſels, and be aſſimilated with the <lb/><choice>
          <corr/>
          <sic>the </sic>
        </choice>utmoſt eaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>49. <hi rend="sc">If</hi> any one were minded to diſſolve <lb/>ſome of the reſin,
        together with the ſalt or <lb/>ſpirit, he need only mix ſome ſpirit of wine <lb/>with the
        water. But ſuch an intire ſolution <lb/>of reſins and gums, as to qualify them for
        <lb/>entering and pervading the animal ſyſtem, <lb/>like the fine acid ſpirit that firſt
        flies off from <lb/>the ſubject, is perhaps impoſſible to obtain. <lb/>It is an apothegme of
        the chymiſts, derived <lb/>from Helmont, that whoever can make <lb/>myrrh ſoluble by the
        human body, has the <lb/>ſecret of prolonging his days: and Boer- <lb/>haave owns that there
        ſeems to be truth in <lb/>this, from it's reſiſting putrefaction. Now <lb/>this quality is
        as remarkable in Tar, with <lb/>which the ancients embalmed and preſerved <lb/>dead bodies.
        And though Boerhaave him- <lb/>ſelf, and other chymiſts before him, have <lb/>given methods
        for making ſolutions of myrrh, <lb/>yet it is by means of alcohol which extracts <lb/>only
        the inflammable parts. And it doth <lb/>not ſeem that any ſolution of myrrh is im-
        <lb/>pregnated with it's ſalt or acid ſpirit. It may <pb n="36"/>
        <lb/>not, therefore, ſeem ſtrange if this water <lb/>ſhou'd be found more beneficial for
        procuring <lb/>health and long life, than any ſolution of <lb/>myrrh whatſoever. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>50. <hi rend="sc">Certainly</hi> divers reſins and gums <lb/>may have virtues, and yet
        not be able for their <lb/>groſſneſs to paſs the lacteals and other finer <lb/>veſſels, nor
        yet, perhaps, readily impart <lb/>thoſe virtues to a menſtruum, that may with <lb/>ſafety
        and ſpeed convey them throughout the <lb/>human body. Upon all which accounts, I
        <lb/>believe tar water will be found to have ſin- <lb/>gular <choice>
          <corr>advantages</corr>
          <sic>advangages</sic>
        </choice>. It is obſerved that acid <lb/>ſpirits prove the ſtronger, by how much the
        <lb/>greater degree of heat is required to raiſe <lb/>them. And indeed, there ſeemeth to be
        no <lb/>acid more gentle than this, obtained by the <lb/>ſimple affuſion of cold water;
        which carries <lb/>off from the ſubject the more light and ſub- <lb/>tile parts, and, if one
        may ſo ſpeak, the very <lb/>flower of it's ſpecific qualities. And here it <lb/>is to be
        noted, that the volatile ſalt and <lb/>ſpirit of vegetables do, by gently ſtimulat- <lb/>ing
        the ſolids, attenuate the fluids contained <lb/>in them, and promote ſecretions, and that
        <lb/>they are penetrating and active, contrary to <lb/>the general nature of other acids. </p>
      <pb n="37"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>51. <hi rend="sc">It</hi> is a great maxim for health, that <lb/>the juices of the body
        be kept fluid in a due <lb/>proportion. Therefore, the acid volatile ſpi- <lb/>rit in tar
        water, at once attenuating and <lb/>cooling in a moderate degree, muſt greatly <lb/>conduce
        to health, as a mild ſalutary deob- <lb/>ſtruent, quickening the circulation of the
        <lb/>fluids without wounding the ſolids, thereby <lb/>gently removing or preventing thoſe
        obſtruc- <lb/>tions, which are the great and general cauſe <lb/>of moſt chronical diſeaſes;
        in this manner an- <lb/>ſwering to the antihyſterics, aſſa fœtida, gal- <lb/>banum, myrrh,
        amber, and in general, to all <lb/>the reſins and gums of trees or ſhrubs uſeful <lb/>in
        nervous caſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>52. <hi rend="sc">Warm</hi> water is it ſelf a deobſtru- <lb/>ent. Therefore the
        infuſion of tar drunk <lb/>warm, is eaſier inſinuated into all the nice <lb/>capillary
        veſſels, and acts, not only by virtue <lb/>of the balſam, but alſo by that of the ve-
        <lb/>hicle. It's taſte, it's diuretic quality, its be- <lb/>ing ſo great a cordial, ſhew the
        activity of <lb/>this medicine. And at the ſame time that it <lb/>quickens the ſluggiſh
        blood of the hyſterical, <lb/>its balſamic oily nature abates the too rapid <lb/>motion of
        the ſharp thin blood in thoſe who <lb/>are hectic. There is a lentour and ſmooth- <lb/>neſs
        in the blood of healthy ſtrong people, on <pb n="38"/>
        <lb/>the contrary, there is often an acrimony and <lb/>ſolution in that of weakly morbid
        perſons. <lb/>The fine particles of Tar are not only warm <lb/>and active, they are alſo
        balſamic and emol- <lb/>lient, ſoftening and enriching the ſharp and <lb/>vapid blood, and
        healing the eroſions occa- <lb/>ſioned thereby in the blood veſſels and <lb/>glands. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>53. <hi rend="sc">Tar</hi> water poſſeſſeth the ſtomachic <lb/>and cardiac qualities of
        elixir proprietatis, <lb/>Stoughton's drops, and many ſuch tinctures <lb/>and extracts, with
        this difference, that it <lb/>worketh it's effect more ſafely, as it hath no- <lb/>thing of
        that ſpirit of wine, which, however <lb/>mixed and diſguiſed, may yet be well ac-
        <lb/>counted a poiſon in ſome degree. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>54. <hi rend="sc">Such</hi> medicines are ſuppoſed to be <lb/>diaphoretic, which being
        of an active and <lb/>ſubtile nature, paſs through the whole <lb/>ſyſtem, and work their
        effect in the fineſt ca- <lb/>pillaries and perſpiratory ducts, which they <lb/>gently
        cleanſe and open. Tar water is ex- <lb/>tremely well fitted to work by ſuch an inſen-
        <lb/>ſible diaphoreſis, by the fineneſs and activity <lb/>of it's acid volatile ſpirit. And
        ſurely thoſe <lb/>parts ought to be very fine, which can ſcour <lb/>the perſpiratory ducts,
        under the ſcarf ſkin or <pb n="39"/>
        <lb/>cuticle, if it be true that one grain of ſand, <lb/>wou'd cover the mouths of more than
        a <lb/>hundred thouſand. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>55. <hi rend="sc">Another</hi> way wherein tar water <lb/>operates, is by urine, than
        which perhaps <lb/>none is more ſafe and effectual, for cleanſing <lb/>the blood and
        carrying off it's ſalts. But it <lb/>ſeems to produce it's principal effect as an
        <lb/>alterative, ſure and eaſy, much ſafer than <lb/>thoſe vehement purgative, emetic, and
        ſali- <lb/>vating medicines, which do violence to na- <lb/>ture. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>56. <hi rend="sc">An</hi> obſtruction of ſome veſſels cauſeth <lb/>the blood to move
        more ſwiftly in other <lb/>veſſels, which are not obſtructed. Hence <lb/>manifold diſorders.
        A liquour that dilutes <lb/>and attenuates reſolves the concretions which <lb/>obſtruct. Tar
        water is ſuch a liquour. It <lb/>may be ſaid, indeed, of common water, that <lb/>it
        attenuates, alſo of mercurial preparations <lb/>that they attenuate. But it ſhou'd be con-
        <lb/>ſidered that mere water only diſtends the <lb/>veſſels and thereby weakens their tone;
        and <lb/>that Mercury by it's great momentum may <lb/>juſtly be ſuſpected of hurting the
        fine capil- <lb/>laries, which two deobſtruents therefore <lb/>might eaſily overact their
        parts, and (by leſ- <pb n="40"/>
        <lb/>ſening the force of the elaſtic veſſels) remotely <lb/>produce thoſe concretions they
        are intended <lb/>to remove. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>57. <hi rend="sc">Weak</hi> and rigid fibres are looked on <lb/>by the moſt able
        phyſicians, as ſources of two <lb/>different claſſes of diſtempers: a ſluggiſh mo- <lb/>tion
        of the liquids occaſions weak fibres: there- <lb/>fore tar water is good to ſtrengthen them
        as it <lb/>gently accelerates their contents. On the <lb/>other hand, being an unctuous
        bland fluid it <lb/>moiſtens and ſoftens the dry and ſtiff fibres: <lb/>and ſo proves a
        remedy for both extremes. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>58. <hi rend="sc">Common</hi> ſoaps are compoſitions of <lb/>lixivial ſalt and oyl. The
        corroſive acrimo- <lb/>ny of the ſaline particles, being ſoftened by <lb/>the mixture of an
        unctuous ſubſtance they in- <lb/>ſinuate themſelves into the ſmall ducts with <lb/>leſs
        difficulty and danger. The combination <lb/>of theſe different ſubſtances makes up a very
        <lb/>ſubtile and active medicine, fitted for mixing <lb/>with all humours, and reſolving all
        obſtructi- <lb/>ons. Soap therefore is juſtly eſteemed a moſt <lb/>efficacious medicine in
        many diſtempers. Al- <lb/>caline ſoap is allowed to be cleanſing, attenu- <lb/>ating,
        opening, reſolving, ſweetening; it is <lb/>pectoral, vulnerary, diuretic, and hath other
        <lb/>good qualities which are alſo to be found in <pb n="41"/>
        <lb/>tar water. It is granted, that oyl and acid <lb/>ſalts combined together exiſt in
        vegetables, <lb/>and that conſequently there are acid ſoaps as <lb/>well as alcaline. And
        the ſaponaceous nature <lb/>of the acid vegetable ſpirits, is what renders <lb/>them ſo
        diuretic, ſudorific, penetrating, ab- <lb/>ſterſive and reſolving. Such, for inſtance, is
        <lb/>the acid ſpirit of Guaiacum. And all theſe <lb/>ſame virtues ſeem to be in tar water in
        a mild <lb/>and ſalutary degree. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>59. <hi rend="sc">It</hi> is the general opinion that all acids <lb/>coagulate the
        blood. Boerhaave excepts vi- <lb/>negar which he holds to be a ſoap, inaſmuch <lb/>as it is
        found to contain an oyl as well as an <lb/>acid ſpirit. Hence it is both unctuous and
        <lb/>penetrating, a powerful antiphlogiſtic, and <lb/>preſervative againſt corruption and
        infection. <lb/>Now it ſeems evident that tar water is a ſoap <lb/>as well as vinegar. For
        though it be the <lb/>character of reſin, which is an inſpiſſated groſs <lb/>oyl, not to
        diſſolve in water <note n="(a)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.75) indent">(<hi rend="italic"
            >a</hi>) <hi rend="italic">Sect.</hi> 47. </note>, yet the ſalts <lb/>attract ſome fine
        particles of eſſential oyl: <lb/>which fine oyl ſerves as a vehicle for the acid <lb/>ſalts,
        and ſhews it ſelf in the colour of the <lb/>tar water: for all pure ſalts are colourleſs.
        <lb/>And though the reſin will not diſſolve in wa- <lb/>ter, yet the ſubtile oyl, in which
        the vegeta- <pb n="42"/>
        <lb/>ble ſalts are lodged, may as well mix with <lb/>water as vinegar doth, which contains
        both <lb/>oyl and ſalt. And as the oyl in tar water diſ- <lb/>covers it ſelf to the eye, ſo
        the acid ſalts do <lb/>manifeſt themſelves to the taſte. Tar water <lb/>therefore is a ſoap
        and as ſuch hath the me- <lb/>dicinal qualities of ſoaps. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>60. It operates more gently as the acid <lb/>ſalts loſe their acrimony being ſheathed
        in <lb/>oyl, and thereby approaching the nature of <lb/>neutral ſalts, are more benign and
        friendly to <lb/>the animal ſyſtem: and more effectually, as <lb/>by the help of a volatile
        ſmooth inſinuating <lb/>oyl, thoſe ſame ſalts are more eaſily introduc- <lb/>ed into the
        capillary ducts. Therefore in fe- <lb/>vers and epidemical diſtempers it is (and I <lb/>have
        found it ſo) as well as in chronical di- <lb/>ſeaſes, a moſt ſafe and efficacious medicine,
        <lb/>being good againſt too great fluidity as a <lb/>balſamic, and good againſt viſcidity as
        a ſoap. <lb/>There is ſomething in the fiery corroſive na- <lb/>ture of lixivial ſalts,
        which makes alcaline <lb/>ſoap a dangerous remedy in all caſes where an <lb/>inflammation is
        apprehended. And as in- <lb/>flammations are often occaſioned by obſtruc- <lb/>tions, it
        ſhou'd ſeem an acid ſoap was much <lb/>the ſafer deobſtruent. </p>
      <pb n="43"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>61. <hi rend="sc">Even</hi> the beſt turpentines, however <lb/>famous for their
        vulnerary and detergent qua- <lb/>lities, have yet been obſerved by their warmth <lb/>to
        diſpoſe to inflammatory tumours. But the <lb/>acid ſpirit <note n="(e)" place="bottom"
          rend="size(0.75) indent">(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) <hi rend="italic">Sect.</hi> 7, 8.
        </note> being in ſo great proportion in <lb/>tar water renders it a cooler and ſafer medi-
        <lb/>cine. And the ætherial oyl of turpentine <lb/>though an admirable dryer, healer, and
        ano- <lb/>dyne, when outwardly applied to wounds <lb/>and ulcers, and not leſs uſeful in
        cleanſing the <lb/>urinary paſſages and healing their ulcerations, <lb/>yet is known to be
        of a nature ſo very relax- <lb/>ing as ſometimes to do much miſchief. Tar <lb/>water is not
        attended with the ſame ill effects, <lb/>which I believe are owing in a great meaſure
        <lb/>to the ætherial oyls being deprived of the acid <lb/>ſpirit in diſtillation, which
        vellicating and con- <lb/>tracting as a ſtimulus might have proved a <lb/>counterpoiſe to
        the exceſſive lubricating and <lb/>relaxing qualities of the oyl. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>62. <hi rend="sc">Woods</hi> in decoction do not ſeem to <lb/>yield ſo ripe and
        elaborate a juice, as that <lb/>which is depoſited in the cells or loculi tere-
        <lb/>binthiaci, and ſpontaneouſly oozes from them. <lb/>And indeed though the balſam of Peru
        obtain- <lb/>ed by boiling wood and ſcumming the decoc- <lb/>tion, be a very valuable
        medicine and of <pb n="44"/>
        <lb/>great account in divers caſes, particularly <lb/>aſthmas, nephritic pains, nervous
        colics and <lb/>obſtructions, yet I do verily think (and I do <lb/>not ſay this without
        experience) that Tar wa- <lb/>ter is a more efficacious remedy in all thoſe <lb/>caſes than
        even that coſtly drug. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>63. <hi rend="sc">It</hi> hath been already obſerved that <lb/>the reſtorative pectoral
        antihyſterical virtues <lb/>of the moſt precious balſams and gums are <lb/>poſſeſſed in a
        high degree by tar water <note n="(d)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.75) align-center">(<hi
            rend="italic">d</hi>) <hi rend="italic">Sect.</hi> 9, 21, 22, 23. </note>. <lb/>And I do
        not know any purpoſe anſwered by <lb/>the wood drinks, for which tar water may <lb/>not be
        uſed with at leaſt equal ſucceſs. It con- <lb/>tains the virtues even of Guaiacum which
        <lb/>ſeems the moſt efficacious of all the woods, <lb/>warming, and ſweetening the humours,
        dia- <lb/>phoretic and uſeful in gouts, dropſies and <lb/>rheums, as well as in the foul
        diſeaſe. Nor <lb/>ſhou'd it ſeem ſtrange, if the virtues obtain- <lb/>ed by boiling an old
        dry wood prove inferior <lb/>to thoſe extracted from a balſam. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>64. There is a fine volatile ſpirit in the <lb/>waters of Geronſter, the moſt eſteemed
        of all <lb/>the fountains about Spa, but whoſe waters do <lb/>not bear tranſporting. The
        ſtomachic, cardiac <lb/>and diuretic qualities of this fountain ſome- <pb n="45"/>
        <lb/>what reſemble thoſe of tar water, which, if I <lb/>am not greatly miſtaken, contains
        the virtues <lb/>of the beſt chalybeat and ſulphureous waters; <lb/>with this difference
        that thoſe waters are apt <lb/>to affect the head in taking, which tar water <lb/>is not.
        Beſides, there is a regimen of diet to be <lb/>obſerved, eſpecially with chalybeat waters,
        <lb/>which I never found neceſſary with this. Tar <lb/>water layeth under no reſtraint
        either as to <lb/>diet, hours, or employment. A man may <lb/>ſtudy or exerciſe or repoſe,
        keep his own <lb/>hours, paſs his time either within or without, <lb/>and take wholeſome
        nouriſhment of any kind. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>65. <hi rend="sc">The</hi> uſe of chalybeat waters, however <lb/>excellent for the
        nerves and ſtomach, is often <lb/>ſuſpended by colds and inflammatory diſor- <lb/>ders; in
        which they are acknowledged to be <lb/>very dangerous. Whereas tar water is ſo far <lb/>from
        hurting in thoſe caſes, or being diſcon- <lb/>tinued on that account, that it greatly
        contri- <lb/>butes to their cure <note n="(f.)" place="bottom"
          rend="size(0.75) align-center">(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>) <hi rend="italic">Sect.</hi> 7.
        </note>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>66. <hi rend="sc">Cordials</hi>, vulgarly ſo called, act im- <lb/>mediately on the
        ſtomach, and by conſent of <lb/>nerves on the head. But medicines of an <lb/>operation too
        fine and light to produce a ſen- <lb/>ſible effect in the primæ viæ, may, never- <pb n="46"/>
        <lb/>theleſs, in their paſſage through the capilla- <lb/>ries, operate on the ſides of thoſe
        ſmall veſ- <lb/>ſels, in ſuch manner as to quicken their oſ- <lb/>cillations, and
        conſequently the motion of <lb/>their contents, producing in iſſue and effect, <lb/>all the
        benefits of a cordial much more laſting <lb/>and ſalutary than thoſe of fermented ſpirits,
        <lb/>which by their cauſtic and coagulating qua- <lb/>lities do incomparably more miſchief
        than <lb/>good. Such a cardiac medicine is tar water. <lb/>The tranſient fits of mirth,
        produced from <lb/>fermented liquors, are attended with propor- <lb/>tionable depreſſions of
        ſpirit in their intervals. <lb/>But the calm chearfulneſs ariſing from this <lb/>water of
        health (as it may be juſtly called) <lb/>is permanent. In which it emulates the vir-
        <lb/>tues of that famous plant Gen Seng, ſo much <lb/>valued in China as the only cordial
        that raiſeth <lb/>the ſpirits without depreſſing them. Tar water <lb/>is ſo far from hurting
        the nerves as common <lb/>cordials do, that it is highly uſeful in cramps, <lb/>ſpaſms of
        the viſcera, and paralytic numb- <lb/>neſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>67. <hi rend="sc">Emetics</hi> are on certain occaſions ad- <lb/>miniſtred with great
        ſucceſs. But the over- <lb/>ſtraining and weakening of nature may be <lb/>very juſtly
        apprehended from a courſe of eme- <lb/>tics. They are nevertheleſs preſcribed and <pb n="47"/>
        <lb/>ſubſtituted for exerciſe. But it is well remark- <lb/>ed in Plato's Timæus that vomits
        and purges <lb/>are the worſt exerciſe in the world. There is <lb/>ſomething in the mild
        operation of tar water, <lb/>that ſeems more friendly to the œconomy, and <lb/>forwards the
        digeſtions and ſecretions in a <lb/>way more natural and benign, the mildneſs of <lb/>this
        medicine being ſuch that I have known <lb/>children take it, for above ſix months toge-
        <lb/>ther, with great benefit, and without any in- <lb/>convenience; and after long and
        repeated ex- <lb/>perience I do eſteem it a moſt excellent diet <lb/>drink fitted to all
        ſeaſons and ages. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>68. <hi rend="sc">It</hi> is I think allowed that the origine of <lb/>the gout lies in
        a faulty digeſtion. And it is re- <lb/>marked by the ableſt phyſicians, that the <lb/>gout
        is ſo difficult to cure, becauſe heating <lb/>medicines aggravate it's immediate, and cool-
        <lb/>ing it's remote cauſe. But tar water, although <lb/>it contain active principles that
        ſtrengthen <lb/>the digeſtion beyond any thing I know, and <lb/>conſequently muſt be highly
        uſeful, either to <lb/>prevent or leſſen the following fit, or by invi- <lb/>gorating the
        blood to caſt it upon the extre- <lb/>mities, yet it is not of ſo heating a nature as
        <lb/>to do harm even in the fit. Nothing is more <lb/>difficult or diſagreeable than to
        argue men <lb/>out of their prejudices, I ſhall not therefore <pb n="48"/>
        <lb/>enter into controverſies on this ſubject, but if <lb/>men diſpute and object, ſhall
        leave the deci- <lb/>ſion to time and tryal. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>69. <hi rend="sc">In</hi> the modern practice, ſoap, opium, <lb/>and mercury bid
        faireſt for univerſal medi- <lb/>cines. The firſt of theſe is highly ſpoken of. <lb/>But
        then thoſe who magnify it moſt, except <lb/>againſt the uſe of it in ſuch caſes where the
        <lb/>obſtruction is attended with a putrefactive <lb/>alkali, or where an inflammatory
        diſpoſition <lb/>appears. It is acknowledged to be very dan- <lb/>gerous in a pthiſis,
        fever, and ſome other <lb/>caſes in which Tar water is not only ſafe but <lb/>uſeful. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>70. <hi rend="sc">Opium</hi> though a medicine of great <lb/>extent and efficacy, yet
        is frequently known <lb/>to produce grievous diſorders in hyſterical or <lb/>hypochondriacal
        perſons, who make a great <lb/>part, perhaps the greateſt, of thoſe who lead <lb/>ſedentary
        lives in theſe iſlands. Beſides, upon <lb/>all conſtitutions dangerous errours may be
        <lb/>committed in the uſe of opium. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>71. <hi rend="sc">Mercury</hi> hath of late years become <lb/>a medicine of very
        general uſe. The extreme <lb/>minuteneſs, mobility, and momentum of its <lb/>parts,
        rendering it a moſt powerful cleanſer of <pb n="49"/>
        <lb/>all obſtructions, even in the moſt minute ca- <lb/>pillaries. But then we ſhould be
        cautious in <lb/>the uſe of it, if we conſider, that the very <lb/>thing which gives it
        power of doing good <lb/>above other deobſtruents, doth alſo diſpoſe it <lb/>to do miſchief.
        I mean it's great momentum, <lb/>the weight of it being about ten times that of <lb/>blood,
        and the momentum being the joint <lb/>product of the weight and velocity, it muſt <lb/>needs
        operate with great force; and may it <lb/>not be juſtly feared, that ſo great a force en-
        <lb/>tering the minuteſt veſſels, and breaking the <lb/>obſtructed matter, might alſo break
        or wound <lb/>the fine tender coats of thoſe ſmall veſſels, <lb/>and ſo bring on the
        untimely effects of old <lb/>age, producing more, perhaps, and worſe ob- <lb/>ſtructions
        than thoſe it removed? Similar <lb/>conſequences may juſtly be apprehended from <lb/>other
        mineral and ponderous medicines. There- <lb/>fore, upon the whole, there will not perhaps
        <lb/>be found any medicine, more general in it's <lb/>uſe, or more ſalutary in it's effects
        than tar <lb/>water. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>72. <hi rend="sc">To</hi> ſuppoſe that all diſtempers ariſing <lb/>from very different,
        and it may be from con- <lb/>trary cauſes, can be cured by one and the <lb/>ſame medicine
        muſt ſeem chimærical. But it <lb/>may with truth be affirmed, that the virtue <pb n="50"/>
        <lb/>of tar water extends to a ſurpriſing variety of <lb/>caſes very diſtant and unlike
          <note n="(h)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.75) indent">(<hi rend="italic">h</hi>) <hi
            rend="italic">Sect.</hi> 3, 4, 5, 6, 21, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </note>. This I have <lb/>experienced in my neighbours, my family, <lb/>and my ſelf. And as
        I live in a remote cor- <lb/>ner among poor neighbours, who <choice>
          <corr>for</corr>
          <sic>ſor</sic>
        </choice> want of <lb/>a regular phyſician have often recourſe to me, <lb/>I have had
        frequent opportunities of tryal, <lb/>which convince me it is of ſo juſt a tempera-
        <lb/>ment as to be an enemy to all extremes. I <lb/>have known it do great good in a cold
        wate- <lb/>ry conſtitution, as a cardiac and ſtomachic; <lb/>and at the ſame time allay heat
        and feveriſh <lb/>thirſt in another. I have known it correct <lb/>coſtive habits in ſome,
        and the contrary ha- <lb/>bit in others. Nor will this ſeem incredible <lb/>if it be
        conſidered that middle qualities natu- <lb/>rally reduce the extreme. Warm water, for
        <lb/>inſtance, mixed with hot and cold will leſſen <lb/>the heat in that, and the cold in
        this. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>73. <hi rend="sc">They</hi> who know the great virtues of <lb/>common ſoap, whoſe
        coarſe lixivial ſalts are <lb/>the product of culinary fire, will not think it
        <lb/>incredible, that virtues of mighty force and <lb/>extent ſhould be found in a fine acid
        ſoap <note n="(g)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.75)">(<hi rend="italic">g</hi>) 58. </note>,
        <lb/>the ſalts and oyl whereof, are a moſt elabo- <lb/><choice>
          <corr>rate</corr>
          <sic>borate</sic>
        </choice> product of nature and the ſolar <lb/>light. </p>
      <pb n="51"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>74. <hi rend="sc">It</hi> is certain tar water warms, and <lb/>therefore ſome may
        perhaps ſtill think it can- <lb/>not cool. The more effectually to remove <lb/>this
        prejudice, let it be farther conſidered, <lb/>that as on the one hand, oppoſite cauſes do
        <lb/>ſometimes produce the ſame effect, for in- <lb/>ſtance, heat by rarefaction and cold by
        con- <lb/>denſation do both increaſe the air's elaſticity: <lb/>ſo on the other hand, the
        ſame cauſe ſhall <lb/>ſometime produce oppoſite effects: heat for <lb/>inſtance in one
        degree thins, in another coa- <lb/>gulates the blood. It is not therefore ſtrange <lb/>that
        tar water ſhou'd warm one habit, and <lb/>cool another, have one good effect on a cold
        <lb/>conſtitution, and another good effect on an <lb/>inflamed one; nor, if this be ſo, that
        it ſhou'd <lb/>cure oppoſite diſorders. All which juſtifies <lb/>to reaſon, what I have
        often found true in <lb/>fact. The ſalts, the ſpirits, the heat of tar <lb/>water are of a
        temperature congenial to the <lb/>conſtitution of a man which receives from it <lb/>a kindly
        warmth, but no inflaming heat. It <lb/>was remarkable that two children in my
        <lb/>neighbourhood, being in a courſe of tar wa- <lb/>ter, upon an intermiſſion of it, never
        failed to <lb/>have their iſſues inflamed by an humour much <lb/>more hot and ſharp than at
        other times. But <lb/>it's great uſe in the ſmall-pox, pleuriſies, and fe- <pb n="52"/>
        <lb/>vers, is a ſufficient proof that tar water is not <lb/>of an inflaming nature. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>75. <hi rend="sc">I have</hi> dwelt the longer on this head, <lb/>becauſe ſome
        gentlemen of the faculty have <lb/>thought fit to declare that tar water muſt en-
        <lb/>flame, and that they would never viſit any <lb/>patient in a fever, who had been a
        drinker of <lb/>it. But I will venture to affirm, that it is ſo <lb/>far from increaſing a
        feveriſh inflammation, that <lb/>it is on the contrary a moſt ready means to <lb/>allay and
        extinguiſh it. It is of admirable <lb/>uſe in fevers, being at the ſame time the ſur-
        <lb/>eſt ſafest and moſt effectual both paregoric and <lb/>cordial; for the truth of which,
        I appeal to <lb/>any perſon's experience, who ſhall take a <lb/>large draught of it milk
        warm in the pa- <lb/>roxyſm of a fever, even when plain water or <lb/>herb teas ſhall be
        found to have little or no <lb/>effect. To me it ſeems that it's ſingular and
        <lb/>ſurprizing uſe in fevers of all kinds, were <lb/>there nothing elſe, would be alone
        ſufficient <lb/>to recommend it to the public. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>76. The beſt phyſicians make the idea of a <lb/>fever to conſiſt in a too great
        velocity of the <lb/>heart's motion, and too great reſiſtance at the <lb/>capillaries. Tar
        water, as it ſoftens and gent- <lb/>ly ſtimulates thoſe nice veſſels, helps to pro- <pb
          n="53"/>
        <lb/>pel their contents, and ſo contributes to re- <lb/>move the later part of the diſorder.
        And for <lb/>the former, the irritating acrimony which ac- <lb/>celerates the motion of the
        heart is diluted <lb/>by watery, corrected by acid, and ſoftened by <lb/>balſamic remedies,
        all which intentions are an- <lb/>ſwered by this aqueous acid balſamic medi- <lb/>cine.
        Beſides, the viſcid juices coagulated by <lb/>the febrile heat are reſolved by tar water as
        <lb/>a ſoap, and not too far reſolved, as it is a <lb/>gentle acid ſoap; to which we may
        add, that <lb/>the peccant humours and ſalts are carried off <lb/>by it's diaphoretic and
        diuretic qualities. </p>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="208"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
