<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Heberden: Antitheriaka</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>William Heberden</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Antitheriaka. An essay on mithridatium and theriaca. By W. Heberden,
              M.D.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T22200</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T22200"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>MDCCXLV</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1745</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="19"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107078319</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: medicine"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="1"/>
    <body>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <head rend="align-center space">
        <lb/>AN <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">ESSAY </hi>
        <lb/>ON <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)"><hi rend="italic">MITHRIDATIUM</hi>, &amp;c. </hi>
      </head>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>ITHRIDATES, the famous King of <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Pontus</hi>, had a ſtrange affectation of ſuperior <lb/>ſkill in the powers of Simples.
        His Courtiers, <lb/>we may imagine, flattered him upon it, and he <lb/>has accordingly been
        delivered down to us as a <lb/>ſecond <hi rend="italic">Solomon</hi>. Whereas if we conſider
        the little <lb/>leiſure, that he had for his own enquiries into <lb/>this part of nature; or
        the little helps, that he <lb/>could have from the people about him; we muſt <lb/>conclude
        that his knowledge was very inconſi- <lb/>derable. However, <hi rend="italic">Pompey</hi>
        ſeems to have been <lb/>poſſeſſed with the vulgar opinion, and, after he <lb/>had conquered
        this King, took uncommon care to <lb/>ſecure his writings, in hopes of ſome mighty
        <lb/>treaſures of natural knowledge. He was ſoon con- <lb/>vinced of what he might eaſily
        have foreſeen, <lb/>and is repreſented as laughing at the diſappoint- <lb/>ment of his own
        credulity, when, inſtead of thoſe <pb n="2"/>
        <lb/>great arcana, he only found one or two trifling <lb/>receipts. <note place="bottom"
          n="a" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">a</hi> Q. Serenus Samonicus de Venen. prohib. </p>
        </note>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There were probably ſome artful people at <lb/>this time, who were not diſpoſed to part
        ſo eaſily <lb/>with the great expectations that had been raiſed, <lb/>nor to loſe this fair
        opportunity of enriching them- <lb/>ſelves by a plauſible impoſture: which has ſince,
        <lb/>been ſeveral times repeated and is frequently <lb/>practiced amongſt us at this day.
        For ſoon after, <lb/>there was publiſhed in <hi rend="italic">Rome</hi> a moſt pompous
        <lb/>medicine with the name of <hi rend="italic">Antidotum Mithrida- <lb/>tium</hi>, which
        was pretended to have been found <lb/>among his papers: though <hi rend="italic"
          >Plutarch</hi>
        <note place="bottom" n="b" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">b</hi> In Vit. Pomp. </p>
        </note> who <lb/>gives a minute detail of them (mentioning the <lb/>Love-letters and ſeveral
        interpretations of Dreams) <lb/>ſays not one word of this famous medicine; <lb/>which one
        can hardly think that he would have <lb/>omitted, if he had found the tradition ſupported
        <lb/>by any proper teſtimonies. The authority of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Q. Serenus
          Samonieus</hi> is more poſitive, who ſays <lb/>that, notwithſtanding the many receipts of
          <hi rend="italic">Mi- <lb/>thridatium</hi> that were handed about, the true me-
        <lb/>dicine found in the cabinet of <hi rend="italic">Mithridates</hi>, was <lb/>only that
        trivial one conſiſting of twenty leaves <lb/>of rue, one grain of ſalt, two nuts, and two
        dried <lb/>ſigs. <note place="bottom" n="c" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">c</hi> De Venen. Prohib. </p>
        </note> So that there is ſome reaſon to ſuſpect <pb n="3"/>
        <lb/>that <hi rend="italic">Mithridates</hi> was as much a ſtranger to his <lb/>own
        antidote, as ſeveral eminent Phyſicians have <lb/>ſince been to the medicines that are daily
        adver- <lb/>tiſed under their names. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Publiſhers were not content with father- <lb/>ing this compoſition upon ſo great a
        name, but <lb/>were likewiſe very extravagant in their com- <lb/>mendations of it's virtues:
        The principal of which <lb/>was made to conſiſt in it's being a moſt powerful
        <lb/>preſervative from all kinds of venom. Whoever <lb/>took a proper quantity in a morning,
        was inſured <lb/>from being poiſoned during that whole day. <note place="bottom" n="a"
          rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><choice>
              <corr><hi rend="sup">a</hi>
              </corr>
              <sic> </sic>
            </choice>Galen de Antid. L. 1. </p>
        </note>
        <lb/>This was confirmed by the example <note place="bottom" n="b" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">b</hi> Celſus. L. 5. c. 23. </p>
        </note> of it's ſup- <lb/>poſed Inventor; who was farther ſaid, by uſing <lb/>it in this
        manner, to have been at laſt ſo forti- <lb/>fied againſt all baneful Simples, that none
        would <lb/>have any effect, when he wanted their aſſiſtance <lb/>to diſpatch himſelf. <note
          place="bottom" n="c" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">c</hi> Celſus et Appian. </p>
        </note>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By theſe arts it gained ſo great a reputation, <lb/>that ſome of the Roman Emperors
        prepared it <lb/>for themſelves with their own hands; ſeveral <lb/>Phyſicians among the
        Antients employed their <lb/>ſtudies upon it in order to render it more perfect; <lb/>and it
        has been the ſubject of many volumes, as <lb/>well as the occaſion of many unaccountable
        <lb/>medicines made in emulation of it, among the <pb n="4"/>
        <lb/>Moderns. In particular, <hi rend="italic">Andromachus</hi>, who was <lb/>phyſician to
          <hi rend="italic">Nero</hi>, made conſiderable alterations <lb/>in it; among other things
        leaving out the Scink, <lb/>adding Vipers, and increaſing the proportion of <lb/>Opium. He
        likewiſe changed the name of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Mithridatium</hi> thus reformed to
        Γαλήνη, but in <lb/><hi rend="italic">Trajan</hi>'s time it obtained that of <hi
          rend="italic">Theriaca</hi>, either <lb/>from the Vipers in it, or from it's good effects
        <lb/>in curing the bites of venomous beaſts; <note place="bottom" n="a" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">a</hi> Galen L. 1. de Antid. et de Theriac. ad Piſon. </p>
        </note> and by <lb/>this name it is known and uſed at this day. But, <lb/>notwithſtanding
        this happy improvement by <lb/><hi rend="italic">Andromachus</hi>, the original <hi
          rend="italic">Mithridatium</hi> has all <lb/>along been continued as well as this
        reformation <lb/>of it, and is ſtill prepared by our Apothecaries <lb/>according to a
        receipt of <hi rend="italic">Damocrates</hi> in Greek <lb/>Iambics, which has been preſerved
        by <hi rend="italic">Galen</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Now whether <hi rend="italic">Mithridates</hi> was or was not the <lb/>author of this
        celebrated compoſition, it was <lb/>manifeſtly founded in error, ſince it was chiefly
        <lb/>intended as a counterpoiſon: for nothing can be <lb/>more falſe than the notions which
        have generally <lb/>prevailed about the force and number of Poiſons, <lb/>and conſequently
        of Antidotes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the ruder ages of the world, before experi- <lb/>ence had furniſhed mankind with any
        conſiderable <lb/>knowledge of nature, they ſeem to have been under <lb/>perpetual alarms
        from an apprehenſion of poiſons: <lb/>They had probably ſeen the ill effect of ſome <pb
          n="5"/>
        <lb/>few ſubſtances on the human body, and, like peo- <lb/>ple in the dark, immediately made
        their dangers <lb/>more and greater than they were; hence came <lb/>that great number of
        Antidotes, which we meet <lb/>with in the writings of the old Phyſicians, <lb/>whoſe chief
        uſe was againſt poiſons. <note place="bottom" n="a" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">a</hi> Celſus L. 5. c. 23. </p>
        </note> What ig- <lb/>norance or an immoderate fondneſs for life had <lb/>thus begun, was
        carried to a much greater height <lb/>by that ſtrong paſſion which the Vulgar have ever
        <lb/>ſhewn for prodigies and miraculous ſtories. This <lb/>was a ſufficient warrant for
        Poets and other dealers <lb/>in ſiction to make a plentiful uſe of poiſons upon <lb/>all
        occaſions; by which the original error has <lb/>been much confirmed and improved. Not to
        <lb/>mention any thing of the ſuſpicions which have <lb/>attended Mothers-in-law, immediate
        Succeſſors <lb/>and other perſons intereſted in the deaths of ſuch <lb/>as were taken off
        with any unuſual ſymptoms. <lb/>Politicians ſeem likewiſe to have given authority <lb/>to
        theſe groundleſs ſuppoſitions, by laying the <lb/>the deaths of many, whom they diſpatched,
        upon <lb/>poiſons which the parties themſelves, as was given <lb/>out, always carried about
        with them and had <lb/>ſecretly taken; by this contrivance the matter <lb/>was huſhed up and
        all the odium of the murder <lb/>avoided. The death of <hi rend="italic">Demoſthenes</hi>
        was, I think, <lb/>of this ſort; who was probably killed by ſome <lb/>truſty Aſſaſſin that
          <hi rend="italic">Antipater</hi>'s party ſent into <pb n="6"/>
        <lb/>the temple to him, but it was too unpopular an <lb/>action among the Athenians to be
        openly avowed. <lb/>This, though not hitherto ſuſpected that I know <lb/>of, appears not
        unlikely from the variety of ac- <lb/>counts about his poiſoning himſelf, and becauſe
        <lb/>there was no poiſon then known that could effect <lb/>it according to any of theſe
        accounts. The ſame <lb/>perhaps may be ſaid of <hi rend="italic">Hannibal</hi> and of
        ſeveral <lb/>others. By all theſe means the number and fame <lb/>of reputed poiſons has been
        perpetually increaſing; <lb/>and Antidotes have increaſed in proportion; for <lb/>if a
        perſon did not dye who had taken an inef- <lb/>fectual poiſon, it was of courſe attributed
        to the <lb/>virtue of ſome inſignificant Antidote. After all <lb/>theſe rumours of poiſons
        and tragical relations of <lb/>their effects in all hiſtories, it is ſurprizing to find
        <lb/>that the Antients knew of none except the Cicuta, <lb/>Aconitum, and thoſe of venomous
        beaſts; <note place="bottom" n="a" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">a</hi> Hoffman. Syſt. Med. Rat. T. 11. p. 183. </p>
        </note> and <lb/>knew of no antidote whatever to theſe poiſons. <lb/>The many intrigues
        mentioned in antient hiſtory <lb/>to have been carried on by means of others and <lb/>far
        more ſubtil ones, eſpecially in the Perſian <lb/>court, will at once come into my learned
        Reader's <lb/>mind in prejudice of my aſſertion. To obviate <lb/>which I only deſire him to
        conſider that all the <lb/>old Naturaliſts and Phyſicians, though ſome of <lb/>them
        profeſſedly treat of poiſons, appear to have <lb/>known no real ones but thoſe
        abovementioned: <pb n="7"/>
        <lb/>their catalogue is indeed much larger by having <lb/>in it, Quickſilver, Orpiment,
        Bull's Blood, Dia- <lb/>monds with many other innocent things: And <lb/>is it poſſible that
        Women and Eunuchs ſhut up <lb/>in an eaſtern palace ſhould have a greater inſight <lb/>into
        the powers of nature, than thoſe Philoſophers <lb/>who ſpent their whole lives and travelled
        the <lb/>known world over in queſt of natural knowledge? <lb/>Indeed the common ſtories have
        all the marks of <lb/>forgery and falſhood; in particular, it is pleaſant <lb/>to obſerve
        how theſe fantoms have fled before the <lb/>approach of light and learning. The firſt
        account <lb/>of ſubtil poiſons that might be concealed under <lb/>the ſtone of a ſeal or
        ring began in <hi rend="italic">Greece</hi>; and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Theophraſtus</hi>
        mentions a ſort of them that might <lb/>be proportioned ſo as to exert their effects after
        <lb/>any given time. <note place="bottom" n="a" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">a</hi> Hiſt. Plant. L. 9. c. 16. </p>
        </note> When this ſtory could no longer <lb/>maintain its ground in <hi rend="italic"
          >Europe</hi>, it took ſanctuary <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">Africa</hi>, for in <hi
          rend="italic">A. Gellius</hi>'s time <note place="bottom" n="b" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">b</hi> A. Gell. L. 6. c. 4. </p>
        </note> ſuch an one <lb/>was reported to have been given there to <hi rend="italic"
          >Regulus</hi>, <lb/>before they permitted his going to <hi rend="italic">Rome</hi>, that,
        <lb/>whatever happened, they might be ſure of de- <lb/>ſtroying him. From <hi rend="italic"
          >Africa</hi> it fled into <hi rend="italic">Aſia</hi>
        <lb/>among the <hi rend="italic">Turks</hi>, who, as <hi rend="italic">Matthiolus</hi>
        <note place="bottom" n="c" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">c</hi> In Dioſcor. p. 972. </p>
        </note> ſuſpected, <lb/>were in poſſeſſion of theſe fatal ſecrets. It has <lb/>been driven
        from the Turks into the remoteſt <pb n="8"/>
        <lb/>Eaft-Indies, <note place="bottom" n="d" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">d</hi> Purchas, Pilgr. L. 10. c. 8. </p>
        </note> and upon our coming nearer theſe <lb/>countries by an eſtabliſhed commerce, this
        ignis <lb/>fatuus retreated into the Weſt-Indies, the firſt <lb/>accounts <note
          place="bottom" n="e" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">e</hi> G. Piſo Hiſt. Nat. Braſil. L. 3. </p>
        </note> of which give us the old ſtory with <lb/>all the pretended airs of truth and
        novelty, as if it <lb/>had not been long before exploded out of every <lb/>other part of the
        World. I would not be under- <lb/>ſtood to deny the poſſibility of poiſoning by ſuch
        <lb/>very ſmall quantities, by the vapors ariſing from <lb/>perfumed gloves and letters, or
        that a poiſon may <lb/>lye concealed in the blood for a conſiderable time <lb/>before it
        exerts itſelf. It is plain that there are <lb/>ſuch things in nature, from the terrible
        effects of <lb/>that very little liquor inſtilled by the bite of a <lb/>viper; from the
        vapors of charcoal; and the poiſon <lb/>of a mad-dog lurking, as ſome ſay, for twenty
        <lb/>years: however the gout and leproſy and madneſs <lb/>will certainly lye in the blood
        unactive for a <lb/>whole generation. But I think I may venture to <lb/>aſſert, there never
        was any thing yet diſcovered <lb/>that we can apply with ſuch effects. Now if this <lb/>is a
        true account of the ſtate of poiſons among <lb/>the Antients, what are we to think of their
        <lb/>Antidotes? Would it not be as ſtrange to make <lb/>uſe of them, as of the charms and
        amulets which <lb/>are delivered down to us as preſervatives from <pb n="9"/>
        <lb/>witchcraft, an evil eye, or the power of any <lb/>malicious Demons? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>What has here been ſaid may be objected to <lb/>every ſingle alexipharmac drug: but
        much more <lb/>may be ſaid againſt them when united together <lb/>as in the <hi
          rend="italic">Mithridatium</hi>; which has by many <lb/>been called a piece of mere jumble
        and chance- <lb/>work without any footſteps of order, proportion <lb/>or deſign, without any
        regard to the known <lb/>virtues of Simples or to any rules of artful com- <lb/>poſition. I
        forbear to mention the unreaſonable <lb/>number of ingredients, their contradictory effects
        <lb/>even according to the Antients themſelves, the <lb/>inconſiderable portion of many of
        them in the <lb/>quantity of a doſe, with ſeveral other particulars <lb/>of the ſame kind
        that have been ſo often objected <lb/>to it. The moſt zealous patron that ever defended
        <lb/>it will hardly aſſert that it's Inventor had ſuch an <lb/>inſight into the powers of
        the Materia medica, as <lb/>to ſee any reaſon a priori for the number and pro- <lb/>portions
        that he has uſed: Experience alone can <lb/>be called in to vouch for it's character, and no
        <lb/>better voucher can be deſired; but experience is <lb/>clearly againſt it; this once
        all-powerful medicine <lb/>that reſiſted every poiſon and malignant diſeaſe, <lb/>that
        procured long life, quickneſs of ſenſes, ſta- <lb/>bility of health, that not only cured
        preſent but <lb/>prevented future diſeaſes, (all which and much <pb n="10"/>
        <lb/>more is affirmed of the reformed Mithridate or <lb/><hi rend="italic">Theriaca</hi> by
          <hi rend="italic">Galen</hi>
        <note place="bottom" n="a" rend="size(0.75)">
          <cb n="1" type="footnote"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">a</hi> In Libb. citatis. </p>
        </note>) is at preſent ſcarce ever <lb/>made uſe of for any of theſe purpoſes; but deſti-
        <lb/>tute of all it's celebrated virtues is forced to take <lb/>refuge in that of a
        Diaphoretic, which is com- <lb/>monly the virtue of a medicine that has none. <lb/>And there
        cannot ſurely be a ſtronger proof of <lb/>any medicine's inſignificancy, than it's loſing
        <lb/>ground ſo remarkably after a tryal of near two <lb/>thouſand years with a conſtant
        prepoſſeſſion in <lb/>it's favour. We have no particular accounts of <lb/>any ſervice that
        it ever did; but we are told that <lb/>the conſtant uſe of it hurt that excellent Emperor
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Antoninus</hi> by throwing him into a lethargic diſ- <lb/>order:
          <note place="bottom" n="b" rend="size(0.75)">
          <cb n="2" type="footnote"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">b</hi> ibid. </p>
        </note> and it did <hi rend="italic">Mithridates</hi> no good, ſup- <lb/>poſing that he ever
        knew and uſed it; for his not <lb/>being able to diſpatch himſelf was probably leſs
        <lb/>owing to the ſtrength of his antidote than to the <lb/>weakneſs of his poiſon. In
        particular it's antidote <lb/>virtue is utterly loſt; we know of many more <lb/>poiſons than
        the Antients, yet there is not one <lb/>which the Mithridate will at all counteract any
        <lb/>farther than plain Opium will do it: Whoever <lb/>was to depend upon it would
        infallibly meet with <lb/>the fate of that unfortunate Quack mentioned <lb/>by <hi
          rend="italic">Wepfer</hi>
        <note place="bottom" n="c" rend="size(0.75)">
          <cb n="1 2" type="footnote"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">c</hi> De Cicuta Aquatica p. 322. </p>
        </note> who offered to ſale a medicine made <pb n="11"/>
        <lb/>upon the plan of the old Antidotes, that was to <lb/>ſecure people from all poiſons: he
        was raſh <lb/>enough to make the experiment upon himſelf <lb/>by taking Arſenic, and ſoon
        died, notwithſtand- <lb/>ing his Antidote, in a miſerable manner. But if <lb/>we are forced
        to give up the original alexipharmac <lb/>virtue, there is a ſtrong preſumption againſt it's
        <lb/>being good for any thing elſe; for if medicines <lb/>ſo elaborately contrived will not
        anſwer their firſt <lb/>purpoſe, it is a great chance if they can be applied <lb/>to any
        other for which they were not intended, <lb/>without having great defects and ſuperfluities
        in <lb/>this new application. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But let us even ſuppoſe that undeſigning chance <lb/>did hit upon a mixture, for which
        experience <lb/>has found out uſes in as full a manner as the <lb/>Antients ever pretended;
        yet what foundation <lb/>will this be to us for expecting the like advantages? <lb/>What if
        Fortune has for once out of a medley <lb/>of inconſiſtent drugs produced an uſeful medicine,
        <lb/>can we therefore hope that any other fortuitous <lb/>concourſe of them will have the
        ſame effect? <lb/>But this we muſt hope, if we have any confidence <lb/>in what is at
        preſent called <hi rend="italic">Mithridatium</hi> or <lb/><hi rend="italic">Theriaca</hi>.
        For I believe that it has ſcarce ever <lb/>continued the ſame for a hundred years together.
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Celſus</hi> is the firſt that deſcribes this medicine, and <lb/>in
        him it conſiſts of thirty eight Simples. Before <pb n="12"/>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Nero</hi>'s time, five of theſe were ſtruck out, and <lb/>twenty
        others added. Soon after, <hi rend="italic">Andromachus</hi>
        <lb/>leaving out ſix and adding twenty-eight ingredi- <lb/>ents, increaſed the ſum total to
        ſeventy-five, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Aëtius</hi> in the V<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Century and
          <hi rend="italic">Myrepſus</hi> in the <lb/>XII<hi rend="sup">th</hi> give us very
        different deſcriptions of <hi rend="italic">Mithri- <lb/>datium</hi>: and ſince that time it
        has been in a ſtate <lb/>of perpetual fluctuation; the alterations, that it <lb/>has
        undergone by accident, being as great as thoſe <lb/>that have been deſignedly made in it.
        For of the <lb/>Simples that antiently compoſed it, ſeveral are <lb/>utterly unknown, <note
          place="bottom" n="a" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">a</hi> See Manard. Epiſt. Lib. 6. ep. 3. et Jo. Bapt. Theodos.
            <lb/>Epiſt. 11. </p>
        </note> others only gueſsed at with <lb/>great uncertainty, and ſome very erroneouſly, as
        <lb/>eaſily be ſhewn, and were ſo even in <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pliny</hi>'s <note
          place="bottom" n="b" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">b</hi> Nat. Hiſt. L. 29. c. 1. </p>
        </note> time. From the different ſubſtitutes <lb/>for the unknown parts, and the various
        gueſſes <lb/>at the uncertain parts, with the difficulty of get- <lb/>ting many of the
        ingredients, being never uſed <lb/>but in this compoſition, it happens that not only
        <lb/>all the Moderns differ from the Antients, but <lb/>almoſt all our ſhops differ from one
        another in <lb/>their manner of preparing it. Many are the diſ- <lb/>putes, which have been
        occaſioned among Phy- <lb/>ſicians, about it's true drugs. There was one <lb/>carried ſo
        high, about a hundred years ago, con- <pb n="13"/>
        <lb/>cerning Balſam of Gilead, that at laſt the Diſputants <lb/>appealed to the Pope; but
        the Pope, not chuſing <lb/>to aſſert his infallibility in matters of Phyſic, <lb/>wiſely
        referred the cauſe to <hi rend="italic">Petrus Caſtellus</hi>, a <lb/>learned Phyſician of
          <hi rend="italic">Rome</hi>, who has publiſhed an <lb/>account of this notable
        controverſy. Now in caſes <lb/>where we can reaſon upon the effects of a <lb/>medicine, many
        alterations may be made and <lb/>yet the virtues continue the ſame; but as here <lb/>we muſt
        wholly depend upon experience, how <lb/>can any one be ſure that theſe alterations <lb/>have
        not utterly ſpoiled it, ſince no one knows <lb/>where it's virtues lye? and <note
          place="bottom" n="c" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">c</hi> De Theriaca. ad Piſon. c. 12. If it be <hi rend="italic"
              >Galen</hi>'s. </p>
        </note>Galen has told us that <lb/>the badneſs of any one ingredient will often ſpoil
        <lb/>the whole compoſition. Beſides, which of all the <lb/>antient deſcriptions are we to
        take? for the <lb/>ſeveral receipts <note place="bottom" n="d" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">d</hi> Galen in Libb. citat. </p>
        </note> under the names of the elder <lb/>and younger <hi rend="italic">Andromachus</hi>,
          <hi rend="italic">Damocrates</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Crito</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Magnus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Xenocrates</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Demetrius</hi> all
        vary from <lb/>one another. This objection will farther be <lb/>ſtrengthened by conſidering
        that even in <hi rend="italic">Galen</hi>'s <lb/>time there were great faults in the copies
        that <lb/>were handed about, <note place="bottom" n="a" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">a</hi> Galen Lib. 1. de Antidot. </p>
        </note> and if many new ones <lb/>have not been ſince added, they muſt have had <lb/>better
        fortune than any other kind of writing; <pb n="14"/>
        <lb/>but the firſt elements of criticiſm will teach us <lb/>that they are of all the moſt
        corrupt, as they con- <lb/>ſiſt of arbitrary marks for quantities and uncon- <lb/>nected
        names of Simples, where the context is <lb/>of no ſervice to direct the copyiſts: and that
        this <lb/>has happened in fact to theſe medicines appears <lb/>from the various readings
        belonging to their de- <lb/>ſcriptions in <hi rend="italic">Celſus</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Galen</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Aëtius</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Myrepſus</hi>; <lb/>and
        likewiſe from all theſe authors differing from <lb/>one another in their directions how they
        are to <lb/>be prepared. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If our objections ſtopped here, and theſe grand <lb/>antidotes were only good for
        nothing; it would <lb/>hardly be worth while to cenſure or take any <lb/>notice of them: but
        we may juſtly fear that their <lb/>uſe is attended with a good deal of danger. As <lb/>many
        people buſy themſelves with the practice of <lb/>Phyſic, who are unqualified to know what
        they <lb/>are doing; it may be adviſable, for the ſake of <lb/>ſuch as fall into their
        hands, to diſcountenance <lb/>a medicine, which, upon the tradition of it's <lb/>ſovereign
        virtues, or as a ſudorific, is often applied <lb/>at random, and, by means of the Opium,
        does <lb/>much miſchief. But it's uſe may be of ill conſe- <lb/>quence not only in the hands
        of the vulgar, but <lb/>even of a ſkillful Phyſician; for Opium or any <lb/>powerful drug,
        mixed up into an electuary with <lb/>any other things, is againſt all rules of phar- <pb
          n="15"/>
        <lb/>macy; the preſcriber lies too much at the mercy <lb/>of the perſon who mixes the
        ingredients, whether <lb/>what he gives for an ordinary doſe ſhall not con- <lb/>tain a
        dangerous or fatal quantity of opium: and <lb/>indeed it is hardly to be expected, in ſuch a
        <lb/>multiplicity of ingredients, that the uſual doſe <lb/>will contain a juſt proportion of
        all of them, and <lb/>of courſe the Phyſician will be greatly in the dark, <lb/>whenever he
        preſcribes it. There are not wanting <lb/>inſtances of ſuch ill effects from the <hi
          rend="italic">Mithridatium</hi>
        <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Theriaca</hi>, as muſt have been owing to the <lb/>patient's
        having more than his ſhare of Opium. <lb/>It is very probable that this was long ago experi-
        <lb/>enced, which gave occaſion to the commendations <lb/>beſtowed upon <hi rend="italic"
          >Old Theriaca</hi>; for <hi rend="italic">Galen</hi> tells us <note place="bottom" n="a"
          rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">a</hi> L. 1. de Antid. </p>
        </note>
        <lb/>that the uſe of keeping it for ſome time is to <lb/>mitigate the ſtrength of the Opium:
        (which, <lb/>however, keeping will not do to any purpoſe <note place="bottom" n="b"
          rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">b</hi> Edinb. Eſſays. Vol. 5. art. 12. </p>
        </note>) <lb/>another reaſon has been ſince found out, namely, <lb/>that age reſolves the
        ſeveral parts into one uni- <lb/>form maſs: upon theſe two accounts the practice <lb/>of
        preferring ſuch as has been laid up till it is <lb/>thirty or forty years old, prevails to
        this day. <note place="bottom" n="c" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">c</hi> Vid. Aq. Theriacal. Pharm. Lond. </p>
        </note>
        <lb/>This ſurely lies extremely open to cenſure; for <lb/>would it not have been better to
        have put leſs <pb n="16"/>
        <lb/>Opium in it at firſt? Did it enter there, only that <lb/>it might go out again?
        Beſides, together with the <lb/>ſtrength of the Opium, the virtues of the Aro- <lb/>matics
        will exhale and leave the maſs, if not quite <lb/>ſpiritleſs and unactive, at leaſt much
        altered from <lb/>what it was at firſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Laſtly, this <hi rend="italic">farrago</hi> is very apt to ferment; <lb/>which
        fermentation, while it laſts, is ſaid to <lb/>exalt <note place="bottom" n="d"
          rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">d</hi> Juncker. Chem. Tab. 72. </p>
        </note> the power of the Opium to a degree of <lb/>ſtrength three or four times as great as
        it had <lb/>before; and a common doſe may by theſe means <lb/>be ſo much ſtronger than was
        intended; which <lb/>is a danger not commonly thought of nor eaſily <lb/>avoided, and cannot
        be balanced by any real vir- <lb/>tues belonging to theſe medicines. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Why then ſhould we retain them any longer <lb/>in our ſhops? Can we not do every thing,
        that <lb/>they can reaſonably pretend to, in a much art- <lb/>fuller, ſafer and more ſimple
        manner? I think <lb/>that they are now chiefly given as Opiates and <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Aromatics</hi>; which intentions would ſurely be <lb/>much better anſwered by mixing two
        or three <lb/>of our many ſpices, in which we ſo far excell <lb/>the Antients, with as much
        Opium added to <lb/>every doſe as was thought proper; without load- <lb/>ing a ſick man's
        ſtomach with ſo many other uſe- <lb/>leſs things, that muſt accompany them, when <pb n="17"/>
        <lb/>given in the <hi rend="italic">Mithridatium</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Theriaca</hi>. I
        own it <lb/>is hard to ſay, that theſe are their chief virtues, <lb/>or what their chief
        virtues are; for there are as <lb/>many friendly and hoſtile qualities blended to-
        <lb/>gether, as in that well-known caſe, where the <lb/>Poet forbids us <hi rend="italic"
          >incerta hæc ratione certa facere</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I might now proceed to ſupport my objections <lb/>by authorities, which perhaps would
        be the pro- <lb/>pereſt method of attacking what is ſupported only <lb/>by authority. For I
        muſt do that juſtice to Phy- <lb/>ſicians as to own that there have not been want- <lb/>ing
        ſeveral in all ages who have born witneſs againſt <lb/>this complicated error, and that it's
        triumph has <lb/>been conſtantly attended with many juſt cenſures <lb/>and reproaches.
        However I ſhall content myſelf <lb/>with quoting only the opinion of <hi rend="italic"
          >Pliny</hi> who is almoſt <lb/>as old as the <hi rend="italic">Theriaca</hi>, and that of
        a Writer of our <lb/>own times; ſince if what has been ſaid is of any <lb/>weight, it will
        make it an unneceſſary taſk to col- <lb/>lect all that has been diſputed for and againſt it
        <lb/>by the intervening Writers. The latter of theſe <lb/>Authors <note place="bottom" n="a"
          rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">a</hi> Theriaca, Mithridatium, Philonium et alia confuſa <lb/>magis,
            quam compoſita remedia, plus ſane damni, quam <lb/>auxilii adferunt. Hinc ad juſta Dei
            judicia referendum vide- <lb/>tur, quod falſæ de his remediis traditiones univerſo ſere
            terra- <lb/>rum orbi impoſuerint. Junck. Med. Pract. 587. </p>
        </note> aſſerts that <hi rend="italic">Mithridatium</hi> and ſuch <lb/>other medicines have
        done more miſchief in <pb n="18"/>
        <lb/>the world than good: The former declaims with <lb/>great vehemence againſt the
        injudiciouſneſs, the <lb/>oſtentation and wantonneſs of this heap of Drugs. <note
          place="bottom" n="a" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="sup">a</hi> Theriaca vocatur excogitata compoſitio luxuriæ; fit ex
            <lb/>rebus externis, cum tot remedia dederit Natura, quæ ſingula <lb/>ſufficerent.
            Mithridatium Antidotum ex rebus <hi rend="sc">liv</hi> com- <lb/>ponitur, interim nullo
            pondere æquali, et quarundam rerum <lb/>ſexageſima denarii unius imperata. Quo Deorum
            perfidiam <lb/>iſtam [al. per fidem iſta] monſtrante? Hominum enim <lb/>ſubtilitas tanta
            eſſe non potuit. Oſtentatio artis et porten- <lb/>toſa ſcientiæ venditatio manifeſta
            eſt. Plin. N. H. L. 29. c. 1. </p>
        </note>
        <lb/>Both of them ſeem, oddly enough, to agree in <lb/>referring the invention of it to the
        juſt judgment <lb/>of heaven; as if the deluſion was too ſtrong <lb/>and unaccountable to
        proceed from mere human <lb/>artifice and contrivance. But notwithſtanding <lb/>what theſe
        and others have ſaid againſt it, it <lb/>ſtill goes on to be prepared in the old manner,
        <lb/>as near as may be, in all the great cities of <lb/>Europe. It's power indeed and fame
        has of late <lb/>been manifeſtly declining; and we may hope <lb/>that it's reign will not
        laſt much longer. Enough <lb/>ſurely has been given to Antiquity: let not <lb/>length of
        time, which has ever been the fatal <lb/>enemy of falſhood and impoſture, be made in
        <lb/>this inſtance to ſupport and protect them. Perhaps <lb/>the glory of it's firſt
        expulſion from a public <lb/>Diſpenſatory was reſerved to theſe times and <pb n="19"/>
        <lb/>to the Engliſh Nation; in which all parts of <lb/>Philoſophy have been ſo much aſſiſted
        in aſſerting <lb/>their freedom from antient fable and ſuperſtition; <lb/>and whoſe College
        of Phyſicians, in particular, <lb/>hath deſervedly had the firſt reputation in their
        <lb/>profeſſion. Among the many eminent ſervices, <lb/>which the authority of this learned
        and judicious <lb/>Body hath done to the practice of Phyſic, it might <lb/>not be the leaſt
        that it had driven out this medley <lb/>of diſcordant Simples; which, perhaps, has no
        <lb/>better title to the name of <hi rend="italic">Mithridates</hi>, than as <lb/>it ſo well
        reſembles the numerous, undiſciplined <lb/>forces of a barbarous King, made up of a diſ-
        <lb/>ſonant crowd collected from different countries, <lb/>mighty in appearance, but in
        reality, an ineffec- <lb/>tive multitude, that only hinder one another. </p>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="7"> </space>
      <trailer rend="align-center">
        <lb/>THE END. </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
