<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Dod: Several cases in physick</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Peirce Dod</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Several cases in physick: and one in particular, giving an account of
              a person who was inoculated for the small-pox, and had the small-pox upon the
              inoculation, and yet had it again. ... To which is added, a letter to Dr. Lee, giving
              him an account of a letter of Dr. Freind's [sic] ... Together with the said letter. By
              Peirce Dod, ... </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T3138</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T3138"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for C. Davis, printer to the Royal Society,
                  1746.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1746</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="5"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="58"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="2"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3307514032</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K021932.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: disease"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>THE <lb/><hi rend="size(2)">PREFACE</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(4)">T</hi><hi rend="italic">HE three firſt of the following <lb/>Caſes
            have already, in ſome mea- <lb/>ſure, been communicated to the <lb/>Publick, through the
            Candour of <lb/>the <hi rend="roman">Learned Gentleman</hi> to whom <lb/>they are
            addreſs'd. </hi>
        </p>

        <p rend="indent">
          <hi rend="italic">
            <lb/>It may be ſeemingly unneceſſary therefore <lb/>perhaps to publiſh them again: But
            as there is <lb/>ſomething in each of them which is very re- <lb/>markable, and One of
            them in particular, <lb/>ſeems to clear up a Point of conſiderable Conſe- <lb/>quence
            with reſpect to <hi rend="roman">Inoculation,</hi> it cannot <lb/>be amiſs, I think, to
            give them a Chance at <lb/>leaſt, of being, if poſſible, a little more pub- <lb/>lick:
            Beſides, there are ſeveral Additions to <lb/>the two laſt of them ſince they were ſent
            to the <lb/><hi rend="roman">Royal Society.</hi></hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Moſt of the other Caſes are taken from ſome <lb/><hi rend="italic">Adverſaria,</hi>
          or Manuſcript Notes, which I <lb/>have, as well as an Account of ſeveral Diſeaſes,
          <lb/>both Acute and Chronical, in Manuſcript like- <lb/>wiſe, <pb xml:id="page_3"/>
          <lb/>of Dr. <hi rend="roman">Browne</hi>'s, Son of the famous <note place="bottom" n="*">*
              <hi rend="roman">Author of the Religio <lb/>Medici.</hi>
            <q>Nec ſatis eſt vulgaſſe Fidem — </q>
            <hi rend="roman">but <lb/>the Author likewiſe of Pſeudodoxia Epidemica,and of ſeveral
              <lb/>other valuable Treatiſes.</hi>
          </note> Sir <hi rend="roman">Thomas Browne,</hi> and who was himſelf <lb/>likewiſe a
          Perſon of great Learning and Emi- <lb/>nence, and <hi rend="roman">Phyſician</hi> to St.
            <hi rend="roman">Bartholomew</hi>'s <lb/><hi rend="roman">Hoſpital</hi> for upwards of
          ſix and twenty Years, <lb/>and ſucceeded therein by Dr. <hi rend="roman">Cade,</hi> in <hi
            rend="roman">October, <lb/>Anno Domini, 1708.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The firſt of them was communicated to him <lb/>by one <hi rend="roman">R. G.</hi> an
            <hi rend="roman">Apothecary</hi> at the <hi rend="roman">Bath,</hi> and <lb/>the Minutes
          of it are ſaid to have been taken <lb/>from Mr. <hi rend="roman">Long</hi>'s own Mouth, as
          may be ſeen <lb/>by the ſaid <hi rend="roman">R. G</hi>'s Letter, dated <hi rend="roman"
            >July 11, 1692,</hi>
          <lb/>and is by no means an inaccurate Relation. <lb/>The three others, <hi rend="roman"
            >viz.</hi> Mr. <hi rend="roman">Dormer</hi>'s, Mr. <lb/><hi rend="roman">Hales</hi>'s,
          and the Marquis of <hi rend="roman">Dorcheſter</hi>'s, <lb/>came directly within his own
          Obſervation, and <lb/>have ſomething in them which is very well <lb/>worth Notice, as well
          as that brief Account <lb/>of the <hi rend="roman">Small-Pox,</hi> which is chiefly
          likewiſe <lb/>taken from his Manuſcript Papers. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>There are but two Caſes beſides; One of them, <lb/>of the ſame kind with That in the
          firſt <hi rend="roman">Letter</hi>
          <lb/>to Mr. <hi rend="roman">Folkes,</hi> tho' not of the ſame fortunate <lb/>Event: The
          other, taken from <hi rend="roman">Tulpius,</hi> which <lb/>I hope there is no occaſion to
          make any Apology <lb/>for, eſpecially conſidering how appoſite it ſeems <lb/>to be to ſome
          of thoſe Obſervations, which oc- <pb xml:id="page_4"/>
          <lb/>curr'd to me upon Mr. <hi rend="roman">Hales</hi>'s Caſe, and to <lb/><hi
            rend="roman">another Caſe of the Stone</hi> which has lately <lb/>made a great deal of
          Noiſe in the World. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>That <hi rend="roman">Letter</hi> of Dr. <hi rend="roman">Freind</hi>'s to Dr. <hi
            rend="roman">Cock- <lb/>burne,</hi> which is added after theſe Caſes, is ac-
          <lb/>counted for in <hi rend="roman">the Epiſtle</hi> that precedes it: I <lb/>have
          nothing further therefore, I think, to <lb/>trouble the World with at preſent, </p>
        <p rend="align-center">
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">Parvâ perfunctus Opellâ.</hi>
        </p>

      </div>
      <div>
        <head>
          <lb/>ERRATA. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Page 5. l. 18. after Syrup, read <hi rend="italic">and</hi> — Page 8. l. 26. inſtead
          <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">affluente,</hi> read <hi rend="italic">effluente</hi> — Page 24.
          l. 28. inſtead of <hi rend="italic">Country,</hi>
          <lb/>read <hi rend="italic">Courſe</hi> — Page 37. l. 22. inſtead of <hi rend="italic"
            >Julep,</hi> read <hi rend="italic">Jalap</hi> — <lb/>Page 41. l. 3. after Age, add <hi
            rend="italic">when</hi> — In <hi rend="italic">Epiſtolâ ad Doctorem <lb/>Lee,</hi> Page
          ult. l. 11. inſtead of ejuſvis, read cujuſvis — In <hi rend="italic">Epi- <lb/>ſtolâ
            Doctoris Freind,</hi> Page 51. l. 1. inſtead of <hi rend="italic">litteras,</hi> read
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Literas.</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div n="1" type="part">
        <pb xml:id="page_6"/>
        <head rend="align-center size(1.5)">
          <lb/>CASE <hi rend="italic">the</hi> FIRST. </head>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>AN <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5) space">ACCOUNT</hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="space">OF A</hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="space">Perſon who made <hi rend="italic">Bloody Water</hi> in the Courſe
            <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Small-Pox</hi>, and yet recover'd: </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="space">In a LETTER to</hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="space size(1.25)"><hi rend="italic">MARTIN FOLKES,</hi> Eſq; </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="space"><hi rend="sc">President</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Royal
              Society.</hi>
          </hi>
        </head>
        <salute rend="italic">SIR, </salute>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(5)">M</hi>AKING Bloody Water is uni- <lb/>verſally eſteem'd as terrible
          a Symp- <lb/>tom as any that can happen in the <lb/>Small-Pox, and all who have wrote
          <lb/>concerning that Diſtemper do una- <lb/>nimouſly agree, that it is a certain
          Forerunner <lb/>of approaching Death. Dr. <hi rend="italic">Cade</hi> indeed ſays, <lb/>in
          his Letter to Dr. <hi rend="italic">Friend</hi> concerning Purg- <lb/>ing in that
          Diſtemper, that he has ſometimes <lb/>cur'd this Symptom by the help of Camphire, <pb
            xml:id="page_7" n="2"/>
          <lb/>and a copious Quantity of Acids; but then he <lb/>adds, that this Relief was only
          temporary, and <lb/>that, to confeſs the Truth, he never knew <lb/>any Body that made that
          ſort of Water, who <lb/>ever ſurviv'd the 16th Day from the Eruption, <lb/>and <hi
            rend="italic">there is no Body whom I know of</hi>, that has <lb/>been converſant in
          this Diſtemper, but has <lb/>conſtantly experienc'd, ſooner or later, the like
          <lb/>Fatality in conſequence of it: I mean, when <lb/>this ſort of Urine has plainly
          proceeded from <lb/>a broken Craſis or Contexture, or as it were a <lb/>thorough
          Diſſolution of the whole Maſs of <lb/>Blood: For I know very well you ſhall now <lb/>and
          then have ſeveral Streaks, and ſometimes <lb/>larger Quantities of Blood, in the Urine,
          from <lb/>the Acrimony of the Salts that are in <hi rend="italic">Spaniſh</hi>
          <lb/>Flies, upon the Application of Bliſters, which <lb/>are frequently ordered, and <hi
            rend="italic">moſtly likewiſe</hi> ne- <lb/>ceſſary, in one or other of the <hi
            rend="italic">Stadia</hi> of this <lb/>Diſtemper, and yet the Patient ſhall do well.
          <lb/>And Dr. <hi rend="italic">Browne</hi>, who was a very worthy <lb/>Predeceſſor of mine
          in St. <hi rend="italic">Bartholomew</hi>'s Hoſ- <lb/>pital, gives an Account of a
          Gentlewoman <lb/>that liv'd in <hi rend="italic">Dean's Yard</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >Weſtminſter</hi>, who <lb/>made bloody Urine in the Small-Pox, for four <lb/>or five
          Days together, and that Dr. <hi rend="italic">Needham</hi>, <lb/>who attended her <hi
            rend="italic">along</hi> with him, did, upon <lb/>that account, forſake her, and yet ſhe
          did well; <lb/>but that they found afterwards, that this bloody <lb/>Urine was not
          occaſion'd by the Malignancy <pb xml:id="page_8" n="3"/>
          <lb/>of the Diſtemper, but by a ſharp Stone which <lb/>was at that time deſcending from
          one of the <lb/>Kidneys, through the Ureters, into the Blad- <lb/>der, and which ſhe
          afterwards voided. This <lb/>I have from ſome <hi rend="italic">Adverſaria</hi> of his, a
          good <lb/>number of which I have had the fortune to be <lb/>in poſſeſſion of ſeveral
          Years, and among <lb/>which there are likewiſe ſeveral other re- <lb/>markable Caſes that
          occurr'd to him during <lb/>the courſe of a very long and extenſive, as well <lb/>as
          ſucceſſful Practice. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But to return to my Subject. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It cannot but be a Satisfaction therefore, to <lb/>a Perſon of your Humanity and
          Goodneſs, to <lb/>hear of an Inſtance in which this frightful <lb/>Symptom was not
          attended with its uſual Fa- <lb/>tality; and it was in the Caſe of a young <lb/>Gentleman
          of about 16 Years of Age, Son <lb/>to one Colonel <hi rend="italic">Ellitſon</hi>, a
          Gentleman of very <lb/>conſiderable Fortune and Worth in <hi rend="italic">Jamaica.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>He was taken with a Fever and great Pain <lb/>in his Head on <hi rend="italic"
            >April</hi> the 20th laſt, and had <lb/>the Small-Pox come out upon him the Day fol-
          <lb/>lowing, notwithſtanding which the ſame Symp- <lb/>toms ſtill continued, and <hi
            rend="italic">nothing almoſt</hi> would <lb/>ſtay in his Stomach, and his Head likewiſe
          was <lb/>very delirious: <hi rend="italic">He was oblig'd therefore to be</hi>
          <pb xml:id="page_9" n="4"/>
          <lb/>blooded, and had Bliſters applied to his Neck <lb/>and to his Arms, which, together
          with a pro- <lb/>per Quantity of <hi rend="italic">Pulvis e chelis Cancror. comp.</hi>
          <lb/>and Nitre, were the firſt Things that I had <lb/>an Opportunity of ordering for him. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The next Day every thing was more quiet, <lb/>and ſo again the third Day from the
          Eruption; <lb/>but the Small-Pox were very numerous all over <lb/>him, and of a rank angry
          Sort, as they gene- <lb/>rally are, I think, in moſt of your <hi rend="italic"
            >Weſt-India</hi>
          <lb/>Conſtitutions; but this young Gentleman had <lb/>beſides overheated himſelf a little
          before, upon <lb/>acting his Part among the reſt of his School- <lb/>Fellows, at the <hi
            rend="italic">Montum</hi> near <hi rend="italic">Eaton.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Things continued in the ſame State the <lb/>fourth Day, but towards the Evening there
          <lb/>were a few Streaks of Blood mix'd with, and <lb/>ſubſiding in his Water, which did
          not much <lb/>alarm me, becauſe I did not know but it might <lb/>be caus'd by the
          Bliſters. I had but one Rea- <lb/>ſon to doubt the contrary, and that was, he <lb/>had
          little or no Strangury; but ſome Perſons <lb/>did aſſure me that they had known ſuch, or
          <lb/>even a more bloody ſort of Water occaſion'd <lb/>by Bliſters, even tho' there was no
          Strangury. <lb/>I was willing therefore to hope the beſt, and <lb/>ſo made no other
          Alteration in my Proceſs than <lb/>to direct a plentiful Uſe of Spirit of Vitriol. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>What was order'd happen'd to ſucceed: We <lb/>had no more of that ſort of Water,
          either <pb xml:id="page_10" n="5"/>
          <lb/>that Night, or the next Day, or the Morning <lb/>following: But I was ſent for in a
          great hurry <lb/>that Day, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> the 6th in the Afternoon, and
          <lb/>found his Friends in the utmoſt Conſternation, <lb/>not only becauſe it return'd, but
          becauſe it <lb/>began to increaſe upon them, and was pouring <lb/>off in a very free
          manner; <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* No Notice was taken of this, either to the Society, or in <lb/>the Account
              which is given of this Affair in the <hi rend="italic">Tranſactions</hi>, <lb/>the
              Reaſons for which you will ſee towards the Beginning of <lb/>the ſubſequent Letter.
            </p>
          </note> a Specimen of <lb/>which I herewith ſend you. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It was neceſſary therefore to proceed in ano- <lb/>ther Method, and I accordingly
          preſcrib'd him <lb/><hi rend="italic">Gum. Arabic. Oliban. &amp; Pulv. Amyl. ana</hi>
          <unclear>℈</unclear>ſs. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Alumin. nup. gr.</hi> iv. to be taken <hi
            rend="italic">ſextis horis</hi>, <lb/>in 3 or 4 Spoonfuls of a Mixture, <hi
            rend="italic">ex Aqua. <lb/>Cinnamom. ten. Ciras. nigr. ana.</hi> ℥iii. <hi
            rend="italic">Theriacal.</hi>
          <lb/>℥iſs. <hi rend="italic">Terr. Japonic.</hi> ʒſs. <hi rend="italic">Tinct.
            Antiphthiſic.</hi> ʒiſs. <lb/><hi rend="italic">&amp; Syrup de Mecon.</hi> ℥ſs. Which,
          with <hi rend="italic">Tinct. <lb/>Roſar. rubrar.</hi> ſtrongly acidulated with <hi
            rend="italic">Spirit <lb/>of Vitriol</hi>, ſweeten'd with the above <hi rend="italic"
            >Syrup. <lb/>Aqua Cinnamom. tem. Fort. ana.</hi> ℥ii. to be <lb/>us'd <hi rend="italic"
            >ad libit</hi>, had the deſired Effect, and <lb/>the Bloodineſs of the Urine began to
          abate in <lb/>about 10 or 12 Hours, and in 10 or 12 Hours <lb/>more to go thoroughly off,
          ſo that by the next <lb/>Day in the Evening the Urine was return'd to <lb/>its natural
          State and Colour. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_11" n="6"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>There was nothing farther obſervable in the <lb/>courſe of this Caſe, except that the
          Diſtem- <lb/>per was of the Coherent Kind, and according- <lb/>ly attended with many other
          dubious Symp- <lb/>toms likewiſe: For tho' it is generally thought <lb/>that the Coherent
          Sort is not ſo formidable as <lb/>the Confluent, yet, as Dr. <hi rend="italic">Friend</hi>
          has judi- <lb/>ciouſly obſerv'd, and Dr. <hi rend="italic">Moreton</hi> before him,
          <lb/>there is not ſo much difference between them, <lb/>but they are almoſt always
          attended with <lb/>much the ſame Appearances, and the ſame <lb/>Fevers plainly, at the
          time of Maturation; for <lb/>that the Danger does not ariſe ſo much from <lb/>the Sort, as
          from the Number of the Puſtules, <lb/>which if it be great, there is the like Reaſon
          <lb/>to be fearful of the Event, whether they flux, <lb/>or whether they only cohere: All
          which not- <lb/>withſtanding this young Gentleman had the <lb/>good Fortune to eſcape. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>I have nothing farther to detain you with at <lb/>preſent but one ſhort Requeſt, and
          that is, <lb/>that you will be ſo good as to believe me <lb/>with all the Reſpect and
          Eſteem imagin- <lb/>able, </p>
        <signed rend="align-right"><hi rend="italic">SIR, <lb/>Your moſt Obedient, <lb/>Faithful
            Servant,</hi>
          <lb/>P. D. </signed>
        <dateline>June 23, 1745. </dateline>
      </div>
      <div n="2-3" type="part">
        <pb xml:id="page_12"/>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>CASE <hi rend="italic">the</hi> SECOND <hi rend="italic">and</hi> THIRD. </head>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>A SECOND LETTER to <lb/><hi rend="italic">MARTIN FOLKES</hi>, Eſq; <lb/><hi rend="sc"
            >President</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Royal Society</hi>. </head>
        <head type="sub" rend="align-center">
          <lb/>In Vindication of the foregoing CASE. <lb/><hi rend="size(0.5)">Together with</hi>
          <lb/>Two other very remarkable <hi rend="italic">Small-Pox</hi> Caſes. </head>
        <div type="section">
          <salute rend="space italic">SIR, </salute>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi>
              <figure rend="dc(5)">
                <figDesc>A decorative frame around the letter. </figDesc>
                <p>I</p>
              </figure>
            </hi> DID myſelf the Pleaſure, ſome <lb/>time ſince, to ſend you an Ac- <lb/>count of a
            young Gentleman <lb/>who made Bloody Water in the <lb/>Courſe of the Small-Pox, and yet
            <lb/>recover'd, and you were ſo obliging as to <lb/>give it a Place in a ſubſequent <hi
              rend="italic">Tranſaction.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>There is one Thing however which I <lb/>could wiſh had not been omitted, and <hi
              rend="italic">that</hi> is, <lb/>that I ſent you likewiſe a Sample of that Wa- <pb
              xml:id="page_13" n="8"/>
            <lb/>ter, by which you might ſee whether it was, <lb/>or was not, of that formidable
            Sort which I <lb/>took it to be; but Dr. <hi rend="italic">Mortimer</hi> tells me,
            <lb/>there were ſeveral Gentlemen at the Society <lb/>who had never had the Small-Pox,
            and that <lb/>ſome of them might probably be very much <lb/>afraid of it, and that it
            was not therefore <lb/>thought adviſeable that the ſaid Sample ſhou'd <lb/>be produc'd,
            and that it not having been pro- <lb/>duc'd before the Society he, through Inadver-
            <lb/>tency, did forget to take any Notice of it in <lb/>the Publication. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The Caſe muſt therefore reſt upon the bare <lb/>Relation, as it does: All that I
            ſhall ſay far- <lb/>ther in relation to it is, That it was a more <lb/>thorough bloody
            Urine, and in a larger <lb/>Quantity, than is ever occaſion'd by Bliſters, <lb/>and
            entirely of that kind as ſeldom ever fails <lb/>to be fatal: <hi rend="italic">Et
              quamvis Remedia propoſita <lb/>ſint vulgaria, hic Caſus tamen obſervationem
              <lb/>meruit propter Eventum non vulgarem, ex <lb/>omnibus enim Variolis laborantibus
              quos mihi <lb/>totâ vitâ videre contigit, hic unicus fuit qui <lb/>ex Fluxu ſanguineo
              evaſerit, ſed in cæteris <lb/>certum Mortis præſagium fuit, magnâ præ- <lb/>ſertim
              ſanguinis copiâ affluente</hi>; as <hi rend="italic">Riverius</hi>
            <lb/>had the Good-fortune to be able to ſay <lb/>before me, in a parallel Caſe which
            came <lb/>before him, <hi rend="italic">Centur. primâ Obſervation</hi>:, —
            <lb/>Obſervat. lxxi. — I call it a parallel Caſe, <pb xml:id="page_14" n="9"/>
            <lb/>tho' This was a <hi rend="italic">Fluxus Alvei</hi>, becauſe the <lb/>Prognoſtick
            is the ſame, whether the Effuſion <lb/>of Blood be <hi rend="italic">per Alveum, vel per
              Veſicam.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>What I have to offer to you now is a Caſe <lb/>of a different Nature, but an
            Inſtance like- <lb/>wiſe of the Recovery of a Gentleman who <lb/>had this Diſtemper in
            as terrible a manner as <lb/>can well be conceiv'd, and that by a Regimen
            <lb/>altogether as extraordinary. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>It was one Mr. <hi rend="italic">Prouſe</hi>, Grandſon to the <lb/>learned and good
            Dr. <hi rend="italic">Hooper</hi>, at that time <lb/>Biſhop of <hi rend="italic">Bath
              and Wells</hi>, and the preſent <lb/>worthy and ſteady Repreſentative of his
            <lb/>Country for the County of <hi rend="italic">Somerſet</hi>, and is <lb/>taken from a
            Letter which was ſent to a <lb/>Friend of mine, from one of the neareſt Re- <lb/>lations
            that Mr. <hi rend="italic">Prouſe</hi> had, and who was <lb/>with him during the whole
            time, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> his <lb/>Mother, dated <hi rend="italic">October</hi>
            31, 1719. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>He had the Small-Pox came out upon him <lb/><hi rend="italic">October</hi> 15,
            1719, and on the 17th, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> the <lb/>third Day, at Night, was
            ſeiz'd with a vio- <lb/>lent Shortneſs of Breath, which increas'd <lb/>upon him the 18th
            in the Morning, ſo that <lb/>he was in danger of being what they call <lb/>throttled,
            had the Hiccups, rattled in his <lb/>Throat, fetch'd his Breath double, grew
            <lb/>ſenſeleſs, look'd black and blue, was convuls'd <lb/>all over, and loſt one Pulſe
            in four. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_15" n="10"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This till Eight at Night, during which <lb/>time they pour'd in as much Wine,
            Brandy, <lb/>and Spirits, as they cou'd, every Quarter of <lb/>an Hour, but about that
            time he began to be <lb/>in ſuch a State as they cou'd not get in any <lb/>more, and he
            fell into a ſort of Slumber, out <lb/>of which he wak'd in a very little time, and
            <lb/>was ſomething better: So from thence they <lb/>continued him in the ſame Courſe,
            drinking <lb/>nothing weaker than Strong Beer, and that <lb/>with at leaſt two or three
            Spoonfuls of <lb/>Brandy, or Spirits, in every Draught of it, <lb/>once every Hour, to
            the 27th, or the 13th <lb/>after the Eruption: And what is very re- <lb/>markable, if
            they let him lie any time an Hour <lb/>or two extraordinary without theſe Liquors,
            <lb/>he would grow light-headed, hot, and ſick, <lb/>but upon returning to them would
            grow cool <lb/>and eaſy. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The Night between the 27th and the 28th <lb/>was a very bad one, inſomuch that it
            was as <lb/>much as three Perſons cou'd do to hold him <lb/>in his Bed, but about Seven
            in the Morning <lb/>he came entirely to himſelf, and was from <lb/>that time thoroughly
            out of Danger; but <lb/>during the Courſe that he was in before, <lb/>which was from the
            18th to the Morning of <lb/>the 28th, beſides his other Potables, which <lb/>were all
            heighten'd and made ſtrong with <lb/>Drops or Spirits, he drank ſix and twenty <pb
              xml:id="page_16" n="11"/>
            <lb/>Quarts and one Pint of Liquor, the ſmalleſt <lb/>of which was Strong Beer, and the
            greateſt <lb/>part the ſtrongeſt Wine that cou'd be got, <lb/>beſides a full Quart of
            Brandy. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>All this while he did not know that it was <lb/>the Small-Pox, but fancied it was a
            Surfeit <lb/>which he had got by his having eaten too <lb/>heartily of Pork, and was
            about 12 Years old <lb/>when this happen'd. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The Eclat of this Recovery did a great deal <lb/>of Credit to old Dr. <hi
              rend="italic">Bettenſon,</hi> under whoſe <lb/>Care he was at the <hi rend="italic"
              >Bath</hi>, who, as he was a <lb/>very eminent and good Phyſician, did every
            <lb/>thing incumbent upon a Perſon of Skill and <lb/>Integrity in a regular manner,
            previous to theſe <lb/>terrible Appearances, but found himſelf, as he <lb/>thought then,
            oblig'd to go a good deal out of <lb/>the way, in order to ſupport him, if poſſible,
            <lb/>under the Violence of them, and was after- <lb/>wards in a manner neceſſitated to
            go on with it <lb/>by what is above related: And his Succeſs in <lb/>this Caſe, if I am
            rightly inform'd, encourag'd <lb/>him to treat ſome of his future Small-Pox Pa-
            <lb/>tients, more particularly the preſent Earl <hi rend="italic"> Pow- <lb/>let</hi>,
            and a Brother or two of his, in much the <lb/>ſame manner, and that without any ſiniſter
            <lb/>Event; but not being Maſter of thoſe Caſes, I <lb/>can't ſay any thing more as to
            them. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_17" n="12"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Give me leave only to remark, That the <lb/>Gentlemen of that County have, for the
            moſt <lb/>part, good <hi rend="italic">Stamina</hi>, and that it happens like- <lb/>wiſe
            very fortunately, eſpecially in Caſes of <lb/>ſuch extreme Danger as that of Mr. <hi
              rend="italic">Prouſe</hi>
            <lb/>was, <hi rend="italic">ut &amp; ſint</hi>, as <hi rend="italic">Horace</hi>
            expreſſes it, <hi rend="italic">dura <lb/>Ilia, &amp; ut, quicquid Veneni ſæviat in
              præcor- <lb/>diis, Medici ſint, qui iis auxiliatricem expor- <lb/>rigant manum.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>I did not think to trouble you with any <lb/>thing more at preſent, but another
            Small-Pox <lb/>Caſe being lately come to my Hands, I was <lb/>not willing to loſe the
            Opportunity of com- <lb/>municating it. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is the Caſe of a little Boy, Son to <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Richards</hi>,
            Member of Parliament for <lb/><hi rend="italic">Bridport</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
              >Dorſetſhire.</hi> He was inoculated <lb/>about three Years ago, at the Age of about
            3, <lb/>and had the Small-Pox come out upon him to <lb/>the number of 50 or 60, and they
            matura- <lb/>ted and ſcabb'd, and went off in the ſame <lb/>manner that that ſort of
            Pock, which was a <lb/>regular and diſtinct one, generally does: But <lb/>about two
            Years afterwards, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> about a <lb/>Year ago, he had the
            Small-Pox again, and <lb/>there came out between 2 and 300, which <lb/>maturated and
            ſcabb'd likewiſe, and went <lb/>through the ſame Stages, and in the ſame <lb/>manner
            that the former did, only he was <pb xml:id="page_18" n="13"/>
            <lb/>worſe before the Eruption, but when that <lb/>was compleated had no manner of
            Diſorder <lb/>except too much of an Appetite, as is uſual <lb/>every now and then, in
            and after the Small-Pox. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This is authenticated to me by a Letter <lb/>which I have from a learned and
            experienced <lb/>Phyſician in thoſe Parts, Dr. <hi rend="italic">Brodrepp</hi>, who
            <lb/>is likewiſe Grandfather to the Child, and <lb/>attended him upon both Occaſions:
            And, <lb/>whatever may be ſaid in evaſion of other <lb/>Caſes, in which Perſons that
            have been inocu- <lb/>lated have had the Small-Pox afterwards, as <lb/>That the
            Inoculation did not take place, There <lb/>was no Eruption, at leaſt no Variolous one,
            <lb/>and the like, is certainly an Inſtance that All <lb/>is not to be depended upon
            that is given out <lb/>in favour of, or is expected from Inoculation, <lb/>and that it
            is, by no means, an effectual Se- <lb/>curity from one's having the Small-Pox again. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>
            <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.75)">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>** What is between theſe two <hi rend="italic">Aſterisks,</hi> added now upon
                <lb/>the Printing. </p>
            </note> But, as it has been obſerved long ſince <lb/>by the inimitable Author of <hi
              rend="italic">Hudibraſs</hi>, <q rend="italic space align-center">
              <lb/>Surely the Pleaſure is as great <lb/>In being Cheated, as to Cheat. </q>
            <lb/><hi rend="space">or elſe it is impoſſible that Inoculation ſhou'd <lb/>triumph ſo
              much as it is ſaid <note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.75)">
                <p>† Appendix to Dr. <hi rend="italic">Jurin</hi>'s Caſe, p. 28. </p>
              </note> that it does over all its Oppoſers? </hi>
            <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.75)"><hi>
                <lb/>** What is between theſe two <hi rend="italic">Aſterisks,</hi> added now upon
                <lb/>the Printing. </hi>
            </note>
          </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_19" n="14"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Addreſſes of this kind likewiſe ought not to <lb/>be too long, I ſhall therefore
            ſay no more with <lb/>relation to this Point at preſent, but haſten to <lb/>a
            Concluſion, for fear that mine ſhould not <lb/>only be thought, but prove ſo, and am,
            with <lb/>great Reſpect, </p>
          <signed rend="align-right"><hi rend="italic">SIR, <lb/>Your moſt Obedient, <lb/>humble
              Servant,</hi>
            <lb/>P. D. </signed>
          <dateline>June, 1743. </dateline>
        </div>
        <div>
          <pb xml:id="page_20" n="15"/>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/><hi rend="sc">Postscript</hi> to the above Letter. </head>
          <p rend="indent sapce">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">S</hi>INCE I wrote this, I have likewiſe had <lb/>an Opportunity
            of being afreſh ſatisfied <lb/>of what is above related with reſpect to <lb/>Mr. <hi
              rend="italic">Prouſe</hi>, with theſe further Particulars, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>That he was at firſt treated in the ſame <lb/>manner that other People uſually are,
            and <lb/>put into a very temperate, if not too cool a <lb/>Regimen. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>That the Small-Pox, thereupon, did not <lb/>come on, or rather ſtruck in, and that
            in <lb/>conſequence thereof, he was brought into the <lb/>Straits in which he was upon
            the third and <lb/>fourth Days. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>That, upon this, Dr. <hi rend="italic">Bettenſon</hi> told Mr. <lb/><hi
              rend="italic">Prouſe</hi>'s Relations, of the good Effects which <lb/>he had ſometimes
            ſeen from a free Uſe of <lb/>Strong and Spirituous Liquors, in his Practice <lb/>among
            People in the Country, but did not <lb/>care to venture upon it in a Perſon of ſuch
            <lb/>tender Years, and of ſuch conſequence as <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Prouſe</hi>
            was; but that it was inſiſted upon <lb/>that he ſhou'd do it, it being apparently a de-
            <lb/>ſperate Caſe, and there being nothing elſe <lb/>ſeemingly to be done. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_21" n="16"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>That they accordingly enter'd upon it, and <lb/>went on with it, but more
            frequently than as <lb/>it is above mention'd, being never able to <lb/>diſcontinue the
            pouring in of them by as <lb/>much as he cou'd take, for a Quarter of <lb/>an Hour,
            without a ſenſible Detriment to <lb/>him. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>That the Strong Beer which he drank was <lb/>ſome that his Grandfather had brewed
            when <lb/>he was Dean of <hi rend="italic">Canterbury</hi>, and brought <lb/>with him
            from thence, which was then a <lb/>matter of ſixteen Years before, and of the <lb/>Black
            or Noggiſh ſort, of near 20 Buſhels to <lb/>the Hogſhead. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>That the good Event of this Proceſs occa- <lb/>ſion'd a pretty general Run into a
            like one, in <lb/>thoſe Parts, during the time that the Small- <lb/>Pox was ſo rife, and
            of ſo malignant a Sort, <lb/>as it was that Winter and the Spring following, <lb/>and
            that the Failure of it in ſome Inſtances <lb/>was thought to be owing to too negligent
            an <lb/>Attendance to it, or the not plying them duly <lb/>and ſufficiently with
            ſuch-like Liquors. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>And laſtly, That it had been generally <lb/>thought that Mr. <hi rend="italic"
              >Prouſe</hi>'s Cure, extraordinary <lb/>as it was, could not well be aſcrib'd to any
            <lb/>thing elſe, but that <hi rend="italic">a Phyſician of the firſt <pb
                xml:id="page_22" n="17"/>
              <lb/>Rank,</hi> who, has been concern'd in his Family, <lb/>ſeem'd to make light of
            it, and very frankly <lb/>told them that he wou'd have done every whit <lb/>as well if
            old <hi rend="italic">Bettenſon</hi> had order'd him to <lb/>have been dragg'd through a
            Horſe-pond: At <lb/>which, I perceive, they were ſomewhat ſur- <lb/>priz'd, and which is
            more indeed than I ſhou'd <lb/>have thought, had it come from <hi rend="italic">One of
              leſs <lb/>Eminence in the Profeſſion, or leſs critical <lb/>upon the Practice of
              others than himſelf</hi>: But <lb/>preſume that he took it from a very good <hi
              rend="italic">Way</hi>
            <lb/>that they have <hi rend="italic">of curing Fevers among the <lb/>Tartars</hi>
            <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.75)">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* Dum quis Febre corripitur, tunc comprehensâ Comâ ip- <lb/>ſum aliquantiſper
                exagitantes, &amp; circumrotantes in Aquam pro- <lb/>fluentem projiciunt, hocque
                modo Humores &amp; Spiritus alterando <lb/>procurant Febrifugum. — <hi rend="italic"
                  >Obſervationes Medicinales circa Mor- <lb/>bos in regionibus Septentrionalibus per
                  Philippum</hi> Lloyd, <hi rend="italic">M. D. in <lb/>Actis Philoſophicis,</hi> N°
                256. pag. <unclear>3</unclear>10. </p>
            </note>, and that is, <q rend="diple quotes">When any one is <lb/>ſeiz'd with a Fever,
              they take him by the <lb/>Hair of the Head and ſhake him well for <lb/>a little while,
              and ſwing him round and <lb/>round, and then throw him into the Water; <lb/>by which
              means a Turn is given to the <lb/>Blood, and the Humours and Spirits are <lb/>alter'd,
              and ſo the Fever is cur'd. </q>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>And thus much for this memorable Caſe. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="part">
        <pb xml:id="page_23"/>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal ornamental line. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center size(1.5)">
          <lb/>CASE <hi rend="italic">the</hi> FOURTH. </head>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)"><hi rend="sc">Bloody Urine</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">in the</hi>
            <hi rend="sc">Small-Pox</hi></hi>, <lb/><hi rend="space">And the Patient liv'd to the
            20th Day.</hi>
        </head>
        <head type="sub" rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>Together with a ſhort Account of the <hi rend="italic"> Small- <lb/>Pox</hi> in
          general. </head>
        <div n="1" type="section">
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/>
            <figure rend="dc(5)">
              <figDesc>A decorative frame around the letter. </figDesc>
              <p>S</p>
            </figure>INCE I wrote the foregoing Let- <lb/>ters, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> I
            have met with a Caſe <lb/>of the ſame Nature with the Firſt, <lb/>in which there was
            Reaſon, as I <lb/>thought, to hope for the ſame for- <lb/>tunate Event, and of which I
            will likewiſe <lb/>give a brief Account, notwithſtanding I was <lb/>diſappointed. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It was in a Servant of my own, a Lad of <lb/>about 19 Years old, who was ſeiz'd
            with a <lb/><hi rend="italic">violent Pain in his Back,</hi> which he imputed <lb/>to
            his having help'd the Brewer's Servants in <lb/>carrying down Drink; but which
            continuing, <lb/>notwithſtanding he was blooded and had a <lb/>Plaiſter put upon it, and
            being attended like- <lb/>wiſe with a Pain in his Head (tho' not a great <lb/>one) the
            Day following, I immediately appre- <lb/>hended that it was the Forerunner of the
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">Small-Pox,</hi> and that of a bad Sort; I ſay of a <pb
              xml:id="page_24" n="19"/>
            <lb/>bad Sort, becauſe I have ſcarce ever known <lb/>that Symptom to have preceded and
            to perſiſt, <lb/>but the <hi rend="italic">Small-Pox</hi> has proved of a very dan-
            <lb/>gerous Sort, and almoſt conſtantly fatal: <lb/>Which is more than I remember to
            have been <lb/>obſerv'd by any body that has hitherto treated <lb/>concerning this
            Diſtemper. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The Eruption enſued, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> began to ſhew <lb/>itſelf, on the
            third Day, and <hi rend="italic">Bloody Water</hi>
            <lb/>upon the fourth from that, or the ſeventh <lb/>from the Invaſion, and continued
            that and the <lb/>next Day, and great part of the Day follow- <lb/>ing; and there were
            other Symptoms, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> a <lb/><hi rend="italic">Delirium</hi> and
              <hi rend="italic">Diarrhoea</hi>, <hi rend="italic">and great Reſtleſneſs <lb/>and
              Inquietude</hi>, which attended him likewiſe <lb/>from juſt before the Eruption to
            almoſt that <lb/>time, notwithſtanding he had been Blooded <lb/>again, and had a Bliſter
              <hi rend="italic">inter Scapulas</hi>, and <lb/>taken all proper temperate
            Reſtringents the <lb/>whole while. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>What was farther remarkable in this Caſe <lb/>is, that he went on pretty tolerably
            for Num- <lb/>ber and Sort, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> after this until the
            fifteenth <lb/>Day, but was then ſeiz'd with a ſudden <hi rend="italic"> De-
              <lb/>liquium</hi>, and in ſuch a State that it was almoſt <lb/>impracticable to get
            any thing down, and he <lb/>was ſeemingly expiring. They made a ſhift <lb/>however to
            get down, every now and then, a <lb/>Spoonful or two of <hi rend="italic">Lac
              Ammoniac</hi> and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tinctura Croci</hi>, with ſome <hi
              rend="italic">Serpentaria</hi> in it, <pb xml:id="page_25" n="20"/>
            <lb/>and a couple of Bliſters were applied <hi rend="italic">infra Cu- <lb/>bitos</hi>,
            by means of which he came to himſelf, <lb/>and was likely enough to live the next Morn-
            <lb/>ing; and continuing ſo that Day, which was <lb/>the Sixteenth from the Eruption,
            and which <lb/>has been obſerv'd <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.75)">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* <hi rend="italic">Vide</hi> Caſe I. Page 2. </p>
            </note> to be the lateſt that any <lb/>One has been known to ſurvive who ever made
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſuch dreadful Water</hi>; and continuing ſo like- <lb/>wiſe
            with not much of a Fever, and ſome- <lb/>thing of an Appetite, and two or three Stools
            <lb/>a Day, and good Apprehenſions for himſelf, for <lb/>two Days more, I cannot but
            think there was <lb/>Reaſon to hope he might have done well: But <lb/>unluckily for him,
              <hi rend="italic">the Fever roſe upon him</hi>
            <lb/>again <hi rend="italic">the third time</hi>, to a very high degree, <lb/>the next
            Day in the Evening, and threw every <lb/>thing into Confuſion, and he died upon the
            <lb/>19th Day of <hi rend="italic">December</hi> laſt, having had the <lb/><hi
              rend="italic">Small-Pox</hi> come out upon him the 30th of the <lb/>Month before. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="section">
          <pb xml:id="page_26" n="21"/>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>SECT. II. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>S I am upon <hi rend="italic">Small-Pox</hi> Caſes, it will
            not <lb/>be unacceptable, I hope, if I add ſome- <lb/>thing concerning that Diſtemper in
            general, <lb/>eſpecially as it is partly taken from the <hi rend="italic"> Ad-
              <lb/>verſaria</hi> of that <hi rend="italic">Learned Gentleman</hi> who is
            <lb/>mention'd in the Preface, and to whom the <lb/>Reader will be further oblig'd in
            moſt of the <lb/>ſubſequent Caſes. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Small-Pox</hi> is a contagious Diſtemper, <lb/>and as
            terrible as any of them, very many dy- <lb/>ing of it, more particularly when it is
            accom- <lb/>panied, as it generally is, with a Fever of a <lb/>dangerous Kind. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This, when they are many, or of the Flux, <lb/>or Confluent Sort; on the contrary,
            when the <lb/>Patient has but a few, and the Fever ceaſes <lb/>upon the Eruption, no
            Diſeaſe is more fa- <lb/>vourable, and you may ſometimes meet them <lb/>walking about
            their Affairs, with the <hi rend="italic">Small- <lb/>Pox</hi> in their Faces, in the
            open Streets of <lb/><hi rend="italic">London.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>No Diſeaſe likewiſe in which there is more <lb/>of a Criſis than in the <hi
              rend="italic">Small-Pox</hi>; for by the <lb/>fourth Day, at furtheſt, after the
            Invaſion, the <lb/>Eruption is evident; by the ſeventh it is per- <lb/>fected, or all
            are come out; by the eleventh <lb/>they dry away, or turn into Scabs; and by <pb
              xml:id="page_27" n="22"/>
            <lb/>the fourteenth they fall off; tho' in the Flux <lb/>Sort they are often ſlower, and
            ſome die after <lb/>the fourteenth, nay on the ſeventeenth, and <lb/>twentieth Days,
            altho' few have Strength <lb/>enough to hold out ſo long. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>A <hi rend="italic">Fever</hi>, as has been ſaid, generally joined <lb/>with the
              <hi rend="italic">Small-Pox</hi>, and when it ceaſes not <lb/>upon the Eruption, apt
            however for ſome <lb/>Days after it to be more remiſs: but on the <lb/>ſeventh from the
            Eruption it increaſes again, <lb/>and returns with ſome Violence; and this is <lb/>what
            is generally called the <hi rend="italic">Second Fever</hi>, and <lb/>occaſions the
            Danger, which continues for ſome <lb/>Days: Nay in the Flux Sort ſome are ſo un-
            <lb/>fortunate as to have <hi rend="italic">a third Fever</hi> ſeven Days <lb/>after the
            ſecond, in which Caſe very few <lb/>eſcape. </p>

          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Small-Pox</hi> favourable, </p>
          <p rend="italic space">
            <lb/>Quæ cito maturæ, quæ erumpunt Febre remissâ, <lb/>Rubræ, albæ, paucæ, nullæ nigrore
            notatæ; </p>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/>Et ubi </p>
          <p rend="indent italic space">
            <lb/>Libera vox, facilis ſpiratio, non ſitis ingens; </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Thoſe on the contrary unfavourable, and <lb/>for the moſt part mortal where there
            is </p>
          <p rend="indent italic space">
            <lb/>Mictus ſanguineus, fluxuſve, Angina, Phrenitis; </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_28" n="23"/>
          <p rend="indent italic">
            <lb/>Qui Variolis pereunt vel Anginâ fauces oc- <lb/>cludente, vel Peripneumoniâ aut
            Reſpiratione <lb/>ſuffocatoriâ, vel Syncope vires dejiciente, vel <lb/>Febre, vel demùm
            Diarrhoeâ aut Dyſenteriâ, <lb/>fatis ut plurimùm cedunt. </p>

          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The greateſt Danger, as has been ſaid be- <lb/>fore, moſtly from the Fever, upon
            which <lb/>account Dr. <hi rend="italic">Browne</hi> is of Opinion, that if <lb/>that
            cou'd be reſpited there wou'd not near <lb/>ſo many die of this Diſeaſe, and was con-
            <lb/>firm'd in this Opinion from his own Expe- <lb/>rience, upon trying of the Bark,
            both in the <lb/>firſt Fever which brings them out, and in the <lb/>ſecond when they
            begin to dry and ſhou'd go <lb/>away, and gives us ſome of the Inſtances, one <lb/>of
            which, relating to its Efficacy in the Secon- <lb/>dary Fever, I ſhall here ſet down,
            and may <lb/>be called, <hi rend="italic">The Fifth Caſe</hi>. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Dormer,</hi> who lodg'd then in <hi rend="italic"> Pall-
              <lb/>Mall,</hi> had a very ill Sort of <hi rend="italic">Small-Pox</hi>, <lb/>which
            ran all together, and covered moſt of <lb/>the Superficies of his Skin, both in Face and
            <lb/>Body, and was in danger from the Beginning. <lb/>When the time came that they
            ſhou'd dry <lb/>away, and the <hi rend="italic">ſecond Fever</hi> increas'd upon
            <lb/>him, they ſtood <hi rend="italic">like a Quagmire</hi> all about <lb/>him, and
            wou'd advance no further, notwith- <lb/>ſtanding many powerful Remedies were given <pb
              xml:id="page_29" n="24"/>
            <lb/>him. In this difficult Caſe <hi rend="italic">the Doctor</hi> delayed <lb/>no
            longer, but gave him <hi rend="italic">a Drachm of the <lb/>Bark</hi> in Subſtance, and
            repeated it every ſix <lb/>Hours at furtheſt, till he had taken about <hi rend="italic"
              >an <lb/>Ounce and an half of it.</hi> His Nights were ſo <lb/>bad before,
            notwithſtanding many quieting <lb/>Remedies which he had taken, that each of <lb/>them,
            as it was fear'd, wou'd be his laſt; but <lb/>the firſt Night after he began with the
              <hi rend="italic">Bark</hi> was <lb/>quieter, and the <hi rend="italic">Small-Pox</hi>
            on both Sides of <lb/>his Face began to dry; the ſecond Night his <lb/>Face was all
            dried, and ſome of his Body ad- <lb/>vanc'd very much, and after the third Night
            <lb/>all the Symptoms abated, and he ſeem'd to be <lb/>in great Safety, and very
            ſuddenly recover'd to <lb/>the great Joy of all his numerous Friends. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">The Doctor</hi>'s general <hi rend="italic">Process</hi> as to
            this <lb/>Diſtemper upon other Occaſions, much the <lb/>ſame as has been ever ſince, <hi
              rend="italic">except as to <lb/>Bleeding</hi>, which he reſtrains to a Plethoric
            <lb/>Habit, and the Time before the Eruption; <lb/>tho' at the ſame time he informs us,
            that at <lb/><hi rend="italic">Paris</hi> they let them Blood any Day after the
            <lb/>Appearance, but ſays this is not practis'd here <lb/>in <hi rend="italic"
              >England</hi>; <hi rend="italic">and</hi> excepting likewiſe <hi rend="italic">as to
              Bliſ- <lb/>ters</hi>, which he does not ſo much as adviſe the <lb/>Uſe of, or make any
            mention of in the whole <lb/>Country, or in any State of the Diſeaſe, and <lb/>which I
            am the more ſurprized at, becauſe <pb xml:id="page_30" n="25"/>
            <lb/>he takes great Notice of them, and adviſes <lb/>one at leaſt to be kept continually
            open and <lb/>running during the whole courſe of the ma- <lb/>lady, in Malignant and
            Peſtilential Fevers, and <lb/>ſays that the great Uſe of them came firſt to <lb/>be
            known during the <hi rend="italic">Peſtilential Conſtitution</hi>, <lb/>which was <hi
              rend="italic">Anno</hi> 1664 and 1665, and had <lb/>continued ever ſince. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The reſt of his Proceſs, <hi rend="italic">Pectoral Drinks, <lb/>Lambatives, and
              Poſſet-Drink, with Tares</hi> in <lb/>it in caſe that the Lungs, and <hi rend="italic"
              >Gargles and <lb/>Mucilages</hi> in caſe that the Throat is affected, <lb/>together
            with <hi rend="italic">Diaſcordium, Theriaca,</hi> or <hi rend="italic"> Phi-
              <lb/>lonium,</hi> in caſe of a Looſeneſs, <hi rend="italic">and an Ounce <lb/>of
              Diacodium</hi> every Night in caſe of Inquie- <lb/>tude; and, if the <hi rend="italic"
              >Small-Pox</hi> prove long laſt- <lb/>ing, ſome temperate Cordial, and to ſupply
            <lb/>the Spirits often with a Draught of it, in caſe <lb/>of Faintneſs, and <hi
              rend="italic">thorough Purging</hi> when the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Small-Pox</hi> is
            well off, and the Patient fit <lb/>for it. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>There is one thing further which the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Doctor</hi> takes
            notice of, and that is, that many <lb/>Waters, Oils and Unguents, or Liniments, <lb/>are
            frequently made uſe of, in order to pre- <lb/>ſerve the Face, after the <hi
              rend="italic">Small-Pox</hi>; all which <lb/>he thinks altogether uſeleſs, if not
            hurtful; <lb/>and that a little Flower, or white Starch, <lb/>well dried, and ſhaken
            upon the Face, is <lb/>preferable to them all. Nay, if you let no- <pb xml:id="page_31"
              n="26"/>
            <lb/>thing that is moiſt, or greaſy, touch the Face <lb/>for fifteen Days, the Face, he
            ſays, will ſcarce <lb/>be red, at leaſt not ſo red as it will otherwiſe <lb/>be; and if
            for a long while after you forbear <lb/>to waſh it, it will be the better, and the moſt
            <lb/>that you need to do is to breathe upon a warm <lb/>Handkerchief, and to wipe your
            Face with it. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A floral ornament. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <div n="6" type="part">
        <pb xml:id="page_32"/>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>An ornamental, horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center space size(1.5)">
          <lb/>CASE <hi rend="italic">the</hi> SIXTH. </head>
        <head rend="align-center space italic size(1.5)">
          <lb/>A general Decrepitacy from the <hi rend="sc">Gout</hi>. </head>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>Cur'd by <hi rend="italic">Bathing</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Drinking</hi> of the
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Bath-Waters</hi>. </head>
        <head rend="align-center space italic">
          <lb/>Anno Domini 1691 and 1692. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(5)">M</hi>R.<hi rend="italic">Long,</hi> of <hi rend="italic"
            >Downeſide</hi>, in the <hi rend="italic"> Pa- <lb/>riſh</hi> of <hi rend="italic"
            >Shepton Mallet,</hi> in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">County</hi> of <hi rend="italic"
            >Somerſet</hi>, of about 49 <lb/>Years of Age, was ſeiz'd with the <lb/>Gout about 14
          Years before, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi>
          <lb/>before the Year 91, and for the three Years <lb/>immediately preceding, was never
          without great <lb/>Pains a Month together in the whole Year, <lb/>the Pains rambling from
          Part to Part, and <lb/>upon Abatement leaving a Numbneſs over <lb/>the whole Body. In
          conſequence of this <lb/>likewiſe, the <hi rend="italic">Joints of his Fingers</hi> became
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">crooked</hi> and inflexible; the <hi rend="italic">Patella</hi>
          of his right <lb/>Knee <hi rend="italic">fix'd</hi>; his <hi rend="italic">Poſture</hi>
          decrepit, and <hi rend="italic">quite <lb/>double</hi>, with extreme Pain in his Hips
          <lb/>and Small of the Back; the <hi rend="italic">Muſcles</hi> and <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Joints</hi> of his <hi rend="italic">Thighs, Legs, Ancles</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
            >Feet, <lb/>motionleſs</hi>, ſo that he was carried about from <lb/>Place to Place, not
          able to put the leaſt <pb xml:id="page_33" n="28"/>
          <lb/>Streſs upon the Ground; his Stomach, loſt; <lb/>his thirſt, unquenchable; his Face
          meagre, <lb/>pale and yellow; the <hi rend="italic">Hair of his Head, gray,</hi>
          <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">the whole Habit of his Body, emaciated</hi>
          <lb/>to Skin and Bones. To theſe Afflictions <lb/>were frequently added, <hi rend="italic"
            >terrible Fits of the <lb/>Stone,</hi> to which ſort of Concretions the En- <lb/>trails
          of his Body were ſo much diſpos'd, <lb/>that after ſix Weeks uſe of the <hi rend="italic"
            >Bath Waters</hi>, <lb/>leaving his Waters, by chance, for ſeven <lb/>Days, the <hi
            rend="italic">Urinal</hi> was <hi rend="italic">cruſted all over</hi> with <lb/>a
          perfect hard Stone <hi rend="italic">like a Pumice,</hi> thicker <lb/>than a Crown-piece. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This was his Caſe when he began to drink <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Bath Waters</hi>
          at the End of <hi rend="italic">April,</hi> 1691; <lb/>and he drank them hot in the
          Morning, and <lb/>cold at Meals; and in a little time was recon- <lb/>ciled to them for
          his conſtant Drink, without <lb/>Deſire of any other. In a Week's time his <lb/>Stomach
          came, and his Thirſt abated; and <lb/>after a Month's conſtantly Drinking, and <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Bathing every other Day</hi> a little while, only <lb/>to ſtretch his
          Joints, it gave him perfect Eaſe <lb/>from Pain. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The 28th of <hi rend="italic">May</hi> he return'd home, and <lb/>carried ſome of the
          Waters along with him, <lb/>and ſent for them conſtantly once a Week, <lb/>uſing them for
          his ordinary Drink, and ſome- <lb/>times drinking them warm in the Morning <lb/>for a
          Stool or two, as Occaſion required, and <pb xml:id="page_34" n="29"/>
          <lb/>they paſs'd very well, but not ſo effectually <lb/>as upon the Place. This Courſe
          continued till <lb/>the End of <hi rend="italic">Auguſt</hi> 1691, when he came to the
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Bath</hi> again, Drinking and <hi rend="italic">Bathing</hi> as
          at the <lb/>firſt, till the Middle of <hi rend="italic">October</hi>, with increaſ-
          <lb/>ing Succeſs; but towards that time he went <lb/>home again, and ſent and continued to
          uſe the <lb/>Waters as before. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Between <hi rend="italic">Allhallowtide</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Chriſtmas</hi> the
          <lb/>Gray Hairs began to fall off, and new ones <lb/>ſucceeded; and by <hi rend="italic"
            >Candlemas</hi> they were all <lb/>gone, and a brown, curling Hair came in <lb/>their
          place, ſuch as he had when he was about <lb/>20, growing ſo faſt, that he was oblig'd to
          <lb/>cut above an Inch a Month, and ſtill growing <lb/>thicker and freſher, ſo that he had
          a Head <lb/>of Hair like a Wig, without a gray one <lb/>in it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This encourag'd him to quit his own <lb/>Houſe, and come and take a Houſe at the
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Bath</hi>, and to renew and purſue the above Me- <lb/>thod very
          diligently, and it was accordingly <lb/>attended with daily Amendment, inſomuch <lb/>that
          in the <hi rend="italic">Summer</hi>, 1692, <hi rend="italic">his Toe-Nails</hi>,
          <lb/>which before were hard, rugged, and ſcaly, <lb/>were thruſt off by ſome that were <hi
            rend="italic">new</hi>, freſh, <lb/>and ſmooth; his Arms were ſtrengthen'd; his
          <lb/>Legs plump'd out, and his Feet cou'd bear a <lb/>ſtrait pair of Shoes; and he that
          before cou'd <lb/>not lay the leaſt Streſs upon them, cou'd then <pb xml:id="page_35"
            n="30"/>
          <lb/>bear to ſtamp upon the Ground, and that <lb/>forcibly, and without the leaſt Regret,
          and <lb/>found his Strength, as he had done his Decay, <lb/>ſtill increaſing upwards, ſo
          that he could ſtand <lb/>almoſt upright without any Pain. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>He acquired likewiſe a fleſhy Habit of <lb/>Body, and a ruddy and plump Face, and a
          <lb/>lively vigorous Eye, and cou'd bend his Knees, <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">did not
            want other Effects or Powers of <lb/>Youth:</hi> Nor had he any Fit of the Gout to
          <lb/>lay him up, nor the leaſt Touch of the Stone, <lb/>or any Sharpneſs of Urine, after
          he was once <lb/>well enter'd into drinking of the <hi rend="italic">Bath-Waters.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">This Caſe</hi> is related, among a great many <lb/>others, by Dr.
            <hi rend="italic">Peirce</hi> in <hi rend="italic">his Memoirs of</hi> the <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Bath</hi>, Page 334, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> but neither ſo
          clearly, <lb/>nor ſo fully as above; upon which account I <lb/>take the liberty to publiſh
          it, and think that it <lb/>is ſo remarkable and <hi rend="italic">well-told a Caſe</hi>
          that it <lb/>very well deſerves the Notice which is taken <lb/>of it; and there is thus
          much farther remark- <lb/>able in it, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> that the Cure ſeems to
          be, in <lb/>a great meaſure, owing to the <hi rend="italic">Bathing</hi>, as <lb/>well as
          Drinking of the Waters, tho' it is now <lb/>thought to be extremely prejudicial, and con-
          <lb/>ſequently prohibited to all who are in any man- <lb/>ner afflicted with the <hi
            rend="sc">Gout</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="7" type="part">
        <pb xml:id="page_36"/>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>An ornamental, horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center space size(1.25)">
          <lb/>CASE <hi rend="italic">the</hi> SEVENTH. </head>
        <head rend="align-center space italic size(1.25)">
          <lb/>The Caſe of the Marquis of <hi rend="roman">Dorcheſter</hi>. </head>
        <head type="sub" rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>A large Quantity of <hi rend="italic">Opium</hi> taken through <lb/>a Miſtake. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(5)">H</hi>ENRY, <hi rend="italic">Marquis</hi> of <hi rend="italic"
            >Dorcheſter</hi>, <lb/>Son to the Earl of <hi rend="italic">Kingſton</hi>, Lieu-
          <lb/>tenant-General of his Majeſty King <lb/><hi rend="italic">Charles</hi> I. his Forces,
          within the <lb/>Counties of <hi rend="italic">Lincoln</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Rutland</hi>, &amp;c. <lb/><hi rend="italic">a great Lover of Learning, and a great
            <lb/>Lover of learned Men,</hi> (and to whom the <hi rend="italic"> Col- <lb/>lege of
            Phyſicians</hi> is oblig'd for a valuable Col- <lb/>lection of Books, which he purchas'd
          at the <lb/>Expence of ſome thouſand Pounds, and gave <lb/>to the College) had a Cabinet
          of Choice Re- <lb/>medies, as was uſual with Great Perſons, and <lb/>in all great Families
          at that time, and among <lb/>the reſt <hi rend="italic">a Metalline Subſtance</hi>, which
          look'd <lb/>like <hi rend="italic">Regulus of Antimony</hi>, but being in Wine, <lb/>or
          any other Liquor, was <hi rend="italic">not Vomitive but <lb/>Sudorifick.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>He had likewiſe <hi rend="italic">a</hi> well-compounded <hi rend="italic"> Cor-
            <lb/>dial Electuary,</hi> of which he us'd to take <lb/>about the Quantity of a Walnut
          every Morn- <lb/>ing, and likewiſe always kept a celebrated <pb xml:id="page_37" n="32"/>
          <lb/>Extract, then much in uſe, and call'd <hi rend="italic"> Ex- <lb/>tractum Cardiac.
            Magiſtrale</hi>, the ſeventh Part <lb/>of which was Extract of, or purified <hi
            rend="italic">Opium</hi>, <lb/>and of which he us'd alſo to give his Servants, <lb/>or
          others that wanted it, every now and then, <lb/>a few Grains. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>One Morning, as a Servant of his was paſ- <lb/>ſing through, his Bed-chamber, he
          call'd to <lb/>her to reach him the Gallypot in which the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cordial
            Electuary</hi> was, out of his Cloſet, but <lb/>ſhe through miſtake brought him the <hi
            rend="italic">Pot of <lb/>the Extract</hi>, and of which, as it happen'd, <lb/>there
          were four Ounces, and he immediately <lb/>took ſix Drachms of it, as appear'd upon
          <lb/>weighing of what remained afterwards; ſo <lb/>that what he took contain'd about <hi
            rend="italic">two Scru- <lb/>ples and an half, or fifty Grains of</hi> pure <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Opium.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>After this he ſlept four Hours, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> from <lb/>Eight to
          Twelve, before his Servants perceived <lb/>any thing of the Miſtake, or attempted to
          <lb/>wake him; but then they could not, tho' <lb/>they did what they could, and therefore
          ſent <lb/>immediately from <hi rend="italic">Highgate</hi>, where his Lord- <lb/>ſhip then
          was, to Dr. <hi rend="italic">Browne</hi> and Sir <hi rend="italic">John
            <lb/>Micklethwaite</hi> to come and attend him. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Sir <hi rend="italic">John Micklethwaite</hi> being abroad, Dr. <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Browne</hi> preſcrib'd divers Things, and had <lb/>them made up ready, and
          a little while after- <lb/>wards they met with Sir <hi rend="italic">John,</hi> and by
          Five <pb xml:id="page_38" n="33"/>
          <lb/>in the Evening they were both of them with <lb/><hi rend="italic">my Lord,</hi> at
          his Houſe in <hi rend="italic">Highgate.</hi> His Ser- <lb/>vants in the mean time had
          been able to take <lb/>him up, and put on his Cloaths, and to ſup- <lb/>port and aſſiſt
          him to walk about his Cham- <lb/>ber, and he was ſometimes able to open his <lb/>Eyes, and
          to anſwer to what was ſpoken, but <lb/>fell aſleep again preſently, and they were not
          <lb/>able to keep him awake a Quarter of a Mi- <lb/>nute with all their Striving, calling
          upon him, <lb/><hi rend="italic">giving him provoking Language</hi>, nor any thing
          <lb/>elſe that they cou'd do. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>He was therefore <hi rend="italic">let Blood</hi> directly, and that
          <lb/>plentifully, and then took <hi rend="italic">Infuſion. Croci Me- <lb/>tallor.</hi>
          ℥iſs, and after that <hi rend="italic">Vitrioli albi</hi> ʒi, twice, <lb/>but cou'd not
          vomit, neither did he ever vo- <lb/>mit in the whole courſe of his Life: How- <lb/>ever
          the Medicines work'd downwards, and <lb/>he had a Stool in about an Hour's time, and
          <lb/>they then proceeded to give him a <hi rend="italic">Draught</hi> of <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Decoct. Senn.</hi> ℥iv, with <hi rend="italic">two Ounces of Syrupus
            <lb/>de Spinâ</hi>, and repeated the ſame ſort of Me- <lb/>dicines every two or three
          Hours afterwards, <lb/>and Sir <hi rend="italic">John Micklethwait</hi> ſeeing little or
          no <lb/>Alteration for the better, return'd to <hi rend="italic">London</hi>
          <lb/>about Nine at Night, bewailing the apparent <lb/>Loſs of ſo great a Man, ſo good a
          Friend, and <lb/>ſo kind a Maſter; but Dr. <hi rend="italic">Browne</hi> continued
          <lb/>with him, and ſtill to give what Aſſiſtance he <lb/>cou'd, and about Midnight order'd
            <hi rend="italic">my Lord</hi>
          <pb xml:id="page_39" n="34"/>
          <lb/>to be put to Bed, and to be ſuffered to ſleep <lb/>without thoſe frequent
          Interruptions which <lb/>had been hitherto given him. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Purging Draughts</hi> continued to work <lb/>plentifully, and
          as ſoon as the Day began to <lb/>appear, <hi rend="italic">the Doctor</hi> walk'd down
          into the <lb/>Garden to refreſh himſelf with the cool Air <lb/>of the Morning, giving
          Orders to be call'd in <lb/>half an Hour, or upon any Alteration which <lb/>might happen
          to his Lordſhip, and about that <lb/>time Notice was brought him that <hi rend="italic">my
            Lord</hi>
          <lb/>ſeem'd to be more ſenſible, and was awake; <lb/>upon which <hi rend="italic">the
            Doctor</hi> went in again, and <lb/>found his Pulſe not quite ſo high as it had been
          <lb/>before, and gave him a <hi rend="italic">Cordial Draught</hi>, with <lb/>15 <hi
            rend="italic">Drops of Spiritus Salis Armoniaci</hi> in it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">My Lord</hi> being now not ſo deſirous of <lb/>Sleep as before,
          call'd for <hi rend="italic">his Chaplain</hi> to read <lb/>to him, and in half an Hour
          more his Head <lb/>was clear, and he ſeem'd to be totally reco- <lb/>ver'd, and deſired to
          ſee what had been or- <lb/>der'd for him, and ſpoke of <hi rend="italic">the
            Præſcriptions</hi>
          <lb/>with a great deal of Candour and Reaſon, <lb/>and Skill and Judgment. And thus, in
          the <lb/>ſpace of leſs than twenty-four Hours from <lb/>the Time of the taking it, <hi
            rend="italic">the Narcotick</hi>, or <lb/>whatever <hi rend="italic">other noxious
            Quality</hi> there may be <lb/>in too large a Quantity of <hi rend="italic">Opium</hi>,
          was maſter'd <lb/>and totally remedied. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_40" n="35"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This Caſe is without a Date, but what I <lb/>have likewiſe among Dr. <hi
            rend="italic">Browne</hi>'s <hi rend="italic"> Adverſa- <lb/>ria</hi>, and a clear
          Inſtance of his Abilities, and <lb/>of the Juſtice with which my <hi rend="italic">Lord
            Marquis</hi>
          <lb/>was pleas'd to ſpeak of him in his Profeſſion, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Bleeding</hi>,
            <hi rend="italic">Vomiting</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Purging</hi>, or one, or
          <lb/>more, if not All of them, being certainly the <lb/>moſt effectual, if not the <hi
            rend="italic">unicè neceſſaria</hi> upon <lb/>all ſuch Occaſions: Upon which account I
          <lb/>have often wonder'd that ſo general a Notice <lb/>only is taken of them, that <hi
            rend="italic">Acid Medicines</hi>
          <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Lixivial Salts</hi> are put upon an equal foot <lb/>of Efficacy
          with them, in a <hi rend="italic">celebrated Trea- <lb/>tiſe upon the Subject of
            Poiſons</hi>, with which <lb/>the World has been long oblig'd, and lately
          <lb/>reoblig'd. But multiplicity of Buſineſs, greater <lb/>Concerns, and a <hi
            rend="italic">Non vacat pro rebus exiguis</hi>, <lb/>cannot but prevent <hi
            rend="italic">Perſons of Eminence</hi> from <lb/>being ſo particularly inſtructive as
          they might <lb/>otherwiſe be, and what is ſaid in relation to <lb/>it, <hi rend="italic"
            >in each of the Editions</hi>
          <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.75)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* A Mechanical Account of <hi rend="italic">Poiſons, London,</hi> 1702 &amp;
              1745, <lb/>Page 147 of the Firſt Edition, and 267 of the Third. </p>
          </note>, ſeems to be in- <lb/>tended rather for Hints of all that is proper in
          <lb/>general, than to point out what may be more <lb/>particularly neceſſary, and is
          principally to be <lb/>depended upon on ſuch Occaſions. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The ſaid <hi rend="italic">Marquis</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Dorcheſter</hi> was edu-
          <lb/>cated at <hi rend="italic">Emanuel-College</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Cambridge</hi>,
          and <pb xml:id="page_41" n="36"/>
          <lb/>became afterwards <hi rend="italic">a hard Student</hi>, ſtudying, <lb/>as it is
          ſaid, for the moſt part, ten or twelve <lb/>Hours a Day, and applying himſelf to the
          <lb/>Study of the Fathers, and Schoolmen, and <lb/>Caſuiſts, and of the Canon and Civil
          Law; as <lb/>likewiſe of the Common Law, and was ac- <lb/>cordingly admitted a <hi
            rend="italic">Bencher</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Grays-Inn, <lb/>Anno Dom.</hi> 1642, but
          about ſeven Years af- <lb/>terwards, when he was about 43 Years old, <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">viz.</hi> in the Year 1649, he <hi rend="italic">betook himſelf to
            <lb/>the Study of Phyſick and Anatomy,</hi> and was <lb/>admitted to be a <hi
            rend="italic">Fellow of the College of Phy- <lb/>ſicians</hi> in 1658, and became a
          Credit and Or- <lb/>nament to it, or, as <hi rend="italic">Tony Wood</hi>
          <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.75)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* <hi rend="italic">Athenæ Oxonienſes, Faſti</hi>, Vol. II. Page 22. </p>
          </note> expreſſes it, <lb/>their <hi rend="italic">Pride and Glory</hi>, and was a great
          Lover <lb/>of the whole Society, and more particularly <lb/>of Dr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Browne,</hi> who was the Perſon whom <lb/>he conſulted principally, and intruſted
          likewiſe <lb/>as to the Purchaſe of ſuch Books as were ne- <lb/>ceſſary for compleating of
          his Library, for the <lb/>future Service and Benefit of the College. He <lb/>was born <hi
            rend="italic">Anno Dom.</hi> 1606, and died at his <lb/>own Houſe in <hi rend="italic"
            >Charter-Houſe Yard, Decemb.</hi> 8, <lb/>1680, aged 74 Years. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="8" type="part">
        <pb xml:id="page_42"/>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>An ornamental, horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center size(1.25)">
          <lb/>CASE <hi rend="italic">the</hi> EIGHTH. </head>
        <head rend="align-center space italic size(1.25)">
          <lb/>A Suppreſſion of Urine, from the <hi rend="roman">Stone</hi>
          <lb/>in the <hi rend="roman">Kidneys</hi>, </head>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>Cur'd by a large Quantity of <hi rend="italic">Soap</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(5)">M</hi>R. <hi rend="italic">Hales</hi>, Brother to Sir <hi
            rend="italic">Edward <lb/>Hales</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Kent</hi>, had <hi
            rend="italic">Stones in both <lb/>Kidneys</hi>, and it ſo happen'd, that <lb/>the Stones
          on each ſide deſcended <lb/>together, and ſtopp'd, or plugg'd <lb/>up both the Ureters in
          ſuch a manner, that he <lb/>labour'd under a <hi rend="italic">total Suppreſſion of Urine
            for</hi>
          <lb/>twenty Days together. Dr. <hi rend="italic">Browne</hi> viſited <lb/>him from the
          Beginning of it, and gave him <lb/><hi rend="italic">Glyſters</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
            >Purges</hi>, and order'd him to be <lb/><hi rend="italic">blooded</hi> ſeveral times,
          and as often as he could <lb/>bear it for the Pain, to go from his Brother's <lb/>Chambers
          in the <hi rend="italic">Temple</hi>, where he lodg'd, as <lb/>far as to <hi rend="italic"
            >Hyde-Park</hi> in a Coach: He gave him <lb/><hi rend="italic">Vomits</hi> likewiſe,
          eſpecially if ever he began to <lb/>be drowſy, which frequently happen'd, and <lb/>they
          were of <hi rend="italic">Vitriol. alb. Oxymel of Squills</hi>, <lb/>and <hi rend="italic"
            >Vin. Benedictum</hi>, as his <hi rend="italic">Purges</hi> were of <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Decoct. Sennæ &amp; Mannæ,</hi> with <hi rend="italic">Syrup of
            <lb/>Buckthorn</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Julep</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Reſin of
            Julep</hi>, and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Aloes</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Scammony</hi>,
          which the Doctor gave <pb xml:id="page_43" n="38"/>
          <lb/>chiefly becauſe he hop'd they wou'd prove <hi rend="italic"> Hy- <lb/>dragogues</hi>,
          and help to carry off the Serous <lb/>Parts of the Blood, leſt they ſhou'd otherwiſe
          <lb/>break in upon, and drown the Brain. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Theſe and other Medicines</hi> were <hi rend="italic">given</hi>,
          <lb/>ſcarce any thing being omitted that cou'd any <lb/>ways contribute either to the
          Support of him, <lb/>or to the ſuppling of the Paſſages, or the <lb/>making a Diſcharge of
          the Stone, in all re- <lb/>ſpects, more eaſy; notwithſtanding which <lb/>there was no
          Relief, only that he was kept ſtill <lb/>alive. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>At length <hi rend="italic">the Doctor</hi> thought of <hi rend="italic">Caſtile
            <lb/>Soap</hi>, and gave him not a little, but from two <lb/>or three Drachms <hi
            rend="italic">to an Ounce</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">an Ounce <lb/>and an half</hi>,
          and to <hi rend="italic">two and more Ounces</hi> at a <lb/>time, diſſolv'd in Water,
          'till he had taken <lb/>two Pounds of it, and at laſt there came away <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">a Stuff</hi>, and ſome Water followed. — This Stuff <lb/>was ſeparated, as
            <hi rend="italic">the Doctor</hi> imagines, from <lb/>the Inſide of the Ureter, and
          there came away <lb/><hi rend="italic">a</hi> large <hi rend="italic">Stone</hi> along
          with it, and wrapt up in <lb/>it, beſides ſeveral other ſmall ones, and Dirt <lb/>and
          Skin, and the gangren'd Membrane, <hi rend="italic">and</hi>
          <lb/>after that a <hi rend="italic">foul and naſty Urine,</hi> and then, <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">viz.</hi> the next Day in the Morning, a great <lb/>Quantity of Water. —
          What he took afterwards <lb/>was <hi rend="italic">Terebinthina Veneta</hi>, and other
          ſoft and <lb/>gentle Medicines of the ſame Tendency, and <lb/>all was well. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_44" n="39"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This is a remarkable Account of a very <lb/>happy Effect from the Uſe of <hi
            rend="italic">Soap</hi>, and an <lb/>Inſtance how free it may be made with, even <lb/>to
          a Degree which is almoſt incredible. But <lb/>then it muſt be conſider'd, that <hi
            rend="italic">this</hi> was like- <lb/>wiſe <hi rend="italic">an almoſt gone Caſe</hi>,
          and of extreme <lb/>Exigence: Every thing elſe, in a manner, had <lb/>been tried, and
          there was no other Chance for <lb/>his Survival. In which ſort of Caſes it is not
          <lb/>only the Judgment, but warrantable, to give <lb/>things of the greateſt Efficacy, and
          that, not <lb/>only in the common trifling Way and Doſes, <lb/>but to the utmoſt Stretch
          that either the Pa- <lb/>tient can bear, or the Medicine ſhall be found <lb/>not to be
          going beyond the <hi rend="italic">anceps Remedium.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is to be obſerved likewiſe, that the Effect <lb/>which this Medicine had, was
          merely to <lb/>bring away the Stuff, Stone, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c. Soap</hi>, more
          <lb/>particularly that of <hi rend="italic">Caſtile</hi>, being, as Dr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Browne</hi>
          <lb/>(immediately previous to this Caſe) has ob- <lb/>ſerv'd, an <hi rend="italic"
            >excellent Diuretick</hi>; the Subtilty of <lb/>its Parts, and <hi rend="italic">the
            Activity and Aſperity of its <lb/>Salts, ſoften'd</hi> by means of their Union <hi
            rend="italic">with <lb/>an Oil</hi>, admirably qualifying it to ſtimulate <lb/>and
          deterge, as well as to relax the Urinary <lb/>Paſſages, and conſequently to facilitate the
          Ex- <lb/>cluſion of any thing that wants to paſs off <lb/>that way. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>How far it is capable of being improv'd in- <lb/>to further Excellencies, and to
          become a <hi rend="italic">Li- <pb xml:id="page_45" n="40"/>
            <lb/>thontriptick</hi>, or poſſeſs'd of the Virtue to break <lb/>or diſſolve the Stone
          in a human Body, I <lb/>won't pretend to determine. Dr. <hi rend="italic">Browne</hi>,
          tho' <lb/>he has mention'd ſeveral things which are <lb/>thought to be ſo, does not ſeem
          to think <lb/>that any thing is really ſo, or much to be <lb/>relied upon for any ſuch
          Purpoſe: And <hi rend="italic"> Tul- <lb/>pius</hi>, that <hi rend="italic">faithful
            Obſerver</hi>, ſays, <q rend="quotes italic diple">Nihil Me- <lb/>dicis frequentius in
            ore quam Medicamen- <lb/>tum Calculos frangens; at vide fis arenoſos <lb/>&amp; molles
            duntaxat intelligas; Silices quippè <lb/>ut vix comminuunt Mallei, ſic profectò mul-
            <lb/>tò minus acris aliquis humor, qui fortaſſis <lb/>aptior foret exedendis tenuibus
            Veſicae tuni- <lb/>cis quam præduris Lapidibus. </q> — Vide <hi rend="italic"> Tul-
            <lb/>pii Obſervationes, Lib. IV. Cap.</hi> 37. The reſt <lb/>of which, becauſe it is not
          altogether foreign <lb/>to the preſent Purpoſe, I ſhall take the liberty <lb/>to ſubjoin
          immediately after <hi rend="italic">the preſent Caſe.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">But I forget</hi> — <hi rend="italic">Phyſick</hi> is <hi
            rend="italic">an ample Field</hi>, <lb/>and there ever have been, and ever will be
          <lb/>Opportunities of adding to, <hi rend="italic">or retrenching <lb/>from</hi>, and
          making ſome Improvements or Al- <lb/>terations or other in Medicine; and there have
          <lb/>ever likewiſe been ſome who have been <hi rend="italic"> Dis- <lb/>creet enough to
            reſerve</hi> the Pleaſure of <hi rend="italic">the <lb/>Knowledge of them to
            themſelves</hi>, altho' at <lb/>the ſame time they have never fail'd to be ſo <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Publick-ſpirited</hi> as to acquaint the World, of <pb xml:id="page_46"
            n="41"/>
          <lb/>whom, and where they were to be had; and <lb/>it is certainly an Argument of a
          refined and <lb/>underſtanding Age there either are any New <lb/>Lights ſtruck out in any
          Branch of Science, </p>
        <q><hi rend="space"><hi rend="italic">vel</hi>
            <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.75)">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* Horatius, lib. 4. Od. ult. Vers. 12. </p>
            </note>
            <hi rend="italic">veteres revocantur</hi>
            <note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.75)">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>† Vulgò, <hi rend="italic">Noſtrums</hi>, or Remedies of ſuperior Excellence to
                <lb/>any as yet known, and yet it is not known what they are, from <lb/>the famous
                  <hi rend="italic">Oleum Anodynum</hi>, &amp;c. of ſome of our moſt eminent
                <lb/>Phyſicians, down to Dr. <hi rend="italic">Cr—m—l M-rt-r</hi>'s new <hi
                  rend="italic">Plan for the <lb/>Practice of Phyſick.</hi>
              </p>
            </note>
            <hi rend="italic">Artes</hi></hi>. </q>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A floral ornament. </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
