<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Jackson: A physical dissertation on drowning</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Rowland Jackson</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">A PHYSICAL DISSERTATION ON DROWNING: in which Submersion, commonly
              call'd Drowning, is shewn to be a long Time consistent with the Continuance of Life,
              from a Variety of unexceptionable tho' surprising Facts, related by the most eminent
              and judicious Authors, and confirm'd by incontestable Evidence; which Facts are
              reconcil'd and accounted for, from the strictest Laws of the Animal Oeconomy. To which
              is Subjoined, The proper Measures for Recovery and Relief; the Obligations we lie
              under to practice them are clearly suggested, and strongly enforc'd; intended for the
              Good of Mankind, by restoring Life to many Persons, who are erroneously supposed to be
              irretrievably drowned. Recommended particularly, to the Consideration of the Surgeons
              of the Navy and Army; who have frequent Opportunities of practising the Methods
              recommended. With an APPENDIX, containing some Methods for the Recovery of those who
              hang themselves, and of Children supposed to be born dead. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T6669</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T6669"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for Jacob Robinson, at the Golden-Lion in Ludgate-Street,
                  MDCCXLVI.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1746</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="2"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="80"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3307454915</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K023735.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: method"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_1"/>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>person breathing with a long tube</figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_3"/>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>A <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">DISSERTATION</hi>
          <lb/>ON THE <lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)">Recovery of PERSONS drown'd.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="space"><lb/>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>Decorative frame around the letter "A".</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <hi rend="dc(3)">A</hi>S Truth in general is of the laſt <w part="I">Im-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">portance</w>, not only in affording a <lb/>noble and exalted Satisfaction to
          the <lb/>Mind, but alſo in forming the <w part="I">Mo-</w><lb/><w part="F">rals</w>, and
          by that Means, promoting <lb/>the moſt valuable Intereſts of <w part="I">So-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ciety</w>; ſo nothing can be a greater Reproach to <lb/>Reaſon, nor a more
          palpable Affront offered to its <lb/>auguſt and venerable Author, than that ignoble
          <lb/>and unmanly Turn of Mind, commonly known by <lb/>the Name of <hi rend="italic"
            >Credulity,</hi> which is no more than an <lb/>implicit Contempt of Reaſon, and all the
          mental <lb/>Powers, producing a Propenſity to believe certain <lb/>Tenets, Doctrines, or
          Facts, without that Degree <lb/>of Evidence, which a Mind ſtudious of Truth <lb/>ought to
          require. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But however odious <hi rend="italic">Credulity</hi> may appear, when
          <lb/>painted in her native Colours, ſhe is nevertheleſs, <pb xml:id="page_4" n="2"
          /><lb/>if we may be allowed the Expreſſion, a <hi rend="italic">Spectre,</hi>
          <lb/>which haunts the various Claſſes and Diſtinctions <lb/>of Mankind, under a Form ſo
          infatuating and <lb/>alluring, as to ſeduce them from the plain and <lb/>amiable Paths of
          Truth, and bewilder them in <lb/>the dark and gloomy Labyrinths of Ignorance, <lb/>Error,
          and Confuſion. This deplorable <w part="I">Obſerva-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> is in no
          Inſtance more effectually verified, <lb/>than in theſe very Men, who profeſs a ſacred <w
            part="I">Ve-</w><lb/><w part="F">neration</w> for Reaſon, and pretend to go wherever
          <lb/>Truth ſhall conduct them; for, we frequently <lb/>find, not only antient, but alſo
          modern <w part="I">Philoſo-</w><lb/><w part="F">phers</w> and Phyſicians, labouring with a
          pompous <lb/>Shew of Learning and Ratiocination, to prove <lb/>that Nature, by her ſtated
          and eſtabliſhed Laws, <lb/>was capable of producing certain Effects, which <lb/>Time has
          afterwards diſcovered never to have had <lb/>any Exiſtence, except in the Imaginations of
          the <lb/>Credulous, or in the chimerical Works of <w part="I">Au-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >thors</w>, who forſaking Fact and Nature, have <w part="I">giv-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >en</w> a full Scope to their Fancy and Invention. <lb/>Thus in former Ages it was
          keenly diſputed, <lb/>how it came about, that a ſmall Fiſh, call'd the <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Remora,</hi> was capable of putting a ſpeedy Stop to <lb/>a Ship under
          Full-ſail; but this pretended Fact <lb/>has, by later and more penetrating Naturaliſts,
          <lb/>been diſcover'd to be abſolutely falſe. And, no <lb/>doubt, the ever memorable
          Rabbit-Woman of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Godalmin,</hi> would have made a conſiderable <w
            part="I">Fi-</w><lb/><w part="F">gure</w> in the Annals of the <hi rend="italic">Royal
            Society,</hi> and <w part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F">forded</w> Matter to the Members
          for copious <w part="I">Diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſertations</w> on the Force of
          Imagination, if ſhe had <lb/>prudently ceas'd Breeding a Day ſooner. This <lb/>bad Piece
          of Conduct, has, however, thrown an <lb/>almoſt irreparable Diſgrace upon <hi
            rend="italic">natural <w part="I">Know-</w><lb/><w part="F">ledge</w>,</hi> by inducing
          the ſober and judicious Part of <lb/>Mankind to imagine, that it was totally employ'd <pb
            xml:id="page_5" n="3"/><lb/>in explaining Viſions and Chimeras. Therefore, if <lb/>we
          intend to philoſophiſe in ſuch a manner as not <lb/>to diſgrace Philoſophy, we muſt have
          Facts duly <lb/>aſcertain'd, before we attempt to explain and <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">count</w> for them; ſince, according to <hi rend="italic">Kercher,</hi> in
          <lb/>his <hi rend="italic">Mund. Subterran.</hi> Lib. 10. <q rend="quotes">'Tis as abſurd
            <lb/>in phyſical Matters, to philoſophiſe without <lb/>Experience, as it is for a blind
            Man to pretend <lb/>to judge of Colours.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Tho' from what has been ſaid, it ſufficiently <lb/>appears, that <hi
            rend="italic">Credulity</hi> is fatal to Truth, yet we <lb/>obſerve in the Minds of ſome
          Men, an arrogant and preſumptuous <hi rend="italic">Scepticiſm,</hi> which, admitting <w
            part="I">no-</w><lb/><w part="F">thing</w> but what is eaſy to the Conception of its
          <lb/>Poſſeſſors, is no leſs prejudicial to the genuine <w part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tereſt</w> of Science, and Philoſophy; for, as, by <lb/>the former we are expos'd to
          the Danger of <w part="I">adopt-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> Error as well as Truth; ſo by
          the latter our <lb/>Minds are, as it were, manacled, and hinder'd <lb/>from giving a
          rational Aſſent to Things and Facts <lb/>cloath'd with the moſt ſtriking and diſtinguiſh'd
          <lb/>Characters of Evidence, for no other Reaſon, than <lb/>that we cannot comprehend
          them. It is, for <w part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtance</w>, a culpable Diffidence, to
          disbelieve the <w part="I">Poſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſibility</w> of a Perſon's retaining a
          latent Principle <lb/>of Life, after he has remain'd ſome Hours, Days, <lb/>and even Weeks
          under Water, ſince numerous <lb/>Facts, related by the beſt Authors, vouch'd by <lb/>the
          moſt candid Witneſſes, and recorded in the <lb/>publick Archives of the moſt penetrating
          and <lb/>ſagacious Nations, concur to remove the ſmalleſt <lb/>Remains of Uncertainty in
          this Point. Beſides, <lb/>I would have the Gentlemen of this Claſs <w part="I"
            >remem-</w><lb/><w part="F">ber</w>, that their Conduct beſpeaks an inſupportable
          <lb/>Degree of Pride, and amounts to a formal <w part="I">De-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >claration</w>, that they themſelves are bleſſed with <lb/>Geniuſes far ſuperior to
          others, ſince nothing can <pb xml:id="page_6" n="4"/><lb/>be true, but what is
          comprehenſible by the vaſt <lb/>Extent of their Capacities. And tho' Modeſty and
          <lb/>Common-Senſe, ſhould not direct them to this <lb/>Obſervation, yet what the World
          calls <hi rend="italic">moral Evi-<lb/>dence</hi> ſtands upon Foundations, too ſtable and
          ſure <lb/>to be ſhaken by their frivolous Conceits, or <w part="I">ill-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">grounded</w> Remonſtrances. In a Word, the wiſe <lb/>and thinking Part of
          Mankind will always be <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">duc'd</w> to give their Aſſent
          to Facts ſeen by a <w part="I">ſuf-</w><lb/><w part="F">ficient</w> Number of Witneſſes,
          who have Senſe <w part="I">e-</w><lb/><w part="F">nough</w> to guard againſt Impoſture
          themſelves, and <lb/>Honeſty enough to ſay nothing but what is Truth to <lb/>their
          Neighbours. All theſe advantagious <w part="I">Circum-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtances</w>
          attend the following Narrations, which, for the <lb/>common Benefit of Mankind, have been
          collected <lb/>from Authors of the greateſt Veracity, in order <lb/>to ſhew, that there is
          often a Poſſibility of <w part="I">reſtor-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> drown'd Perſons to
          Life, after vulgar <w part="I">Preju-</w><lb/><w part="F">dice</w>, and a Want of
          ſufficiently extenſive Views <lb/>with Reſpect to the Laws of the animal Oeconomy,
          <lb/>have laid a Foundation for concluding them <w part="I">irre-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >trieveably</w> dead, and paſt all Hopes of Recovery. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Bruhier,</hi> an eminent Phyſician of <hi
            rend="italic">Paris,</hi>
          <lb/>well known to the learned World, and highly <lb/>eſteem'd for his Knowledge in his
          Profeſſion, <w part="I">a-</w><lb/><w part="F">bout</w> three Years ago, publiſh'd a
          Treatiſe on the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Uncertain Signs of Death,</hi> tending to prove,
          that <lb/>many People are interr'd before they are really <lb/>dead; and that there are
          frequent Inſtances of <w part="I">Per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſons</w> who have liv'd many
          Days without <w part="I">Reſpira-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, or any other apparent
          Signs of Life. This <lb/>Doctrine he eſtabliſhes by many inconteſtable <w part="I"
            >Hiſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">tories</w> of People who have actually ſurviv'd their
          <lb/>Funerals, and liv'd many Years after they had <lb/>been buried, upon a Suppoſition,
          that they were <lb/>actually dead. Hence he very judiciouſly infers, <pb xml:id="page_7"
            n="5"/><lb/>that 'tis not imprudent but inhuman, to ſuffer the <lb/>Interment of our
          Friends and Relations, before <lb/>we are convinc'd from the moſt evident Marks, <lb/>that
          they are certainly and irrecoverably deceas'd; <lb/>or till ſuch time as the Beginning of
          Putrefaction <lb/>convinces us, that no Hopes remain of a Revival. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In Confirmation of what this celebrated <w part="I">Phyſi-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">cian</w> has advanc'd, many Examples might be <lb/>found in our own Country,
          which eſcap'd his <w part="I">Re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſearches</w>; and no doubt it
          happens much more <lb/>frequently, than is generally imagin'd; <w part="I"
            >eſpecial-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> in hyſterical Women, in thoſe who have <w part="I"
            >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tracted</w> a Habit of drinking ſpirituous Liquors to
          <lb/>Exceſs, but particularly in thoſe who have been <lb/>guilty (for ſo I can't forbear
          calling it) of taking <lb/>frequent Doſes of Opium, or its Preparations, ſo <lb/>as to
          render Life inſupportable without them, of <lb/>which there are too many Inſtances. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This Doctrine, however true, is not altogether <lb/>modern; for we
          learn from <hi rend="italic">Diogenes Laertius,</hi> that the celebrated <hi rend="italic"
            >Empedocles</hi> acquir'd uncommon <lb/>Honour, by reſtoring a Woman to Life who was
          <lb/>thought to be dead many Days, and whoſe <w part="I">Diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >order</w> he diſcover'd to be only a Strangulation of <lb/>the Uterus, that is, an
          hyſteric Fit. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>We learn, farther, that <hi rend="italic">Heraclides</hi> of <hi
            rend="italic">Pontus,</hi> a <lb/>noted Philoſopher, wrote a Treatiſe upon this <w
            part="I">ve-</w><lb/><w part="F">ry</w> Subject, which he intitled, <foreign
            xml:lang="el">###Greek omitted###</foreign>, <hi rend="italic">Of <lb/>the Diſtemper in
            which the Patient is depriv'd of <lb/>Reſpiration.</hi> In this he aſſerted, that the <w
            part="I">Diſor-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w> might continue thirty Days, during which
          <lb/>there was no Reſpiration, or any other Signs of <lb/>Life, without any Marks of
          Putrefaction; and <lb/>that notwithſtanding, the Patient might at laſt <w part="I"
            >re-</w><lb/><w part="F">cover</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In Conſequence of the frequent Interments of <lb/>People before they
          were really dead, Dr. <hi rend="italic">Bruhier,</hi>
          <pb xml:id="page_8" n="6"/><lb/>in 1745, publiſh'd a ſmall Pamphlet, containing
          <lb/>Propoſals for the Regulation of Funerals, and the <lb/>Prevention of ſuch calamitous
          Diſaſters; which he <lb/>endeavours to have confirm'd by the Legiſlature; <lb/>for, ſays
          he, how many Women weary of their <lb/>Husbands, and Husbands equally weary of their
          <lb/>Wives; how many Children who have either a <lb/>real or an imaginary Reaſon to be
          diſſatisfied with <lb/>their Parents; and, eſpecially, how many <w part="I"
            >cove-</w><lb/><w part="F">tous</w> and neceſſitous Heirs, who have long waited <lb/>for
          the happy Moment, which was to put him in <lb/>Poſſeſſion of an opulent Fortune, may not
          abuſe <lb/>the Liberty the Law affords them of burying their <lb/>Friends at the End of
          twenty-four Hours, at <lb/>which Time they may, poſſibly, be really alive, <lb/>and
          capable of a Recovery. And to prove this <lb/>Regulation the more neceſſary, he relates
          the <w part="I">fol-</w><lb/><w part="F">lowing</w> Hiſtories. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>A Woman about eighty Years old, being taken <lb/>for dead, was about
          to be laid out as ſuch, when a <lb/>Perſon, who had perus'd his Treatiſe, oppos'd the
          <lb/>Deſign. Next Morning the Woman was found <lb/>recover'd from her profound Syncope,
          which, <lb/>conſidering the intenſe Cold of the Seaſon, had <lb/>probably prov'd a real
          Cauſe of her Death, had <lb/>ſhe been taken out of her Bed. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is alſo ſufficiently known, that Cardinal <hi rend="italic"
              >Spi-<lb/>v<unclear>#</unclear>ſa,</hi> firſt Miniſter to the King of <hi
            rend="italic">Spain,</hi> being <lb/>ſuppoſed dead, and committed to a Surgeon in
          <lb/>order to be embalm'd, thruſt away the Hand <lb/>which conducted the fatal Inſtrument,
          which put <lb/>a real End to his Life. But notwithſtanding this <lb/>Accident, the
          barbarous Surgeon proceeded to <lb/>finiſh the Operation. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But as Submerſion, or Drowning, is the Subject <lb/>of our preſent
          Enquiry, I ſhall only farther take <lb/>Notice of the Hiſtories relating thereto. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_9" n="7"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The celebrated <hi rend="italic">Kunckel,</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
            >Ephemerid. Nat. <lb/>Curios.</hi> informs us, that a young Man had the <w part="I"
            >Miſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">fortune</w> to fall from a Boat into the Water, and <lb/>ſunk
          to the very Bottom, about fifteen hundred <lb/>Paces, from the Shoar, which he did not
          reach <lb/>till two Hours after. However, as it is natural <lb/>for Perſons to give an
          Account of the ſeveral <lb/>Circumſtances attending their reſpective States of
          <lb/>Calamity and Diſtreſs, the young Man inform'd <lb/>thoſe who had the Curioſity to
          enquire into his <lb/>Condition during that Time, that whilſt he was <lb/>making the moſt
          ſtrenuous Efforts to preſerve his <lb/>Life, he thought of nothing but God, and the
          <lb/>Means of recommending himſelf to his Favour and <lb/>Acceptance; that the Voice of
          his darling Siſter, <lb/>who wept bitterly on the Shore, for the Fate of <lb/>her Brother,
          had ſerv'd to conduct him to the <lb/>Land; that the Diſturbance of the Water by thoſe
          <lb/>who ſought for him, and the Lamentations of the <lb/>People on the Shore, were not
          only diſtinctly <lb/>heard by him, but alſo prov'd extremely <w part="I">ſhock-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ing</w> and uneaſy to him; that he thought his <w part="I">Re-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſpiration</w> was carried on, without his knowing in <lb/>what Manner, that the
          Water had not penetrated <lb/>into any of the Cavities of his Body; and that he <lb/>was
          hot, inſtead of being cold. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The ſame judicious Author informs us, that he <lb/>had an Opportunity
          of examining a Fiſherman, <lb/>who fell from a Boat into the ſame Place, and was, <lb/>by
          Means of the Ice, kept under Water for three <lb/>Days, but upon his being found, appear'd
          full of <w part="I">Vi-</w><lb/><w part="F">gour</w>, ſaid that he enjoy'd good Health,
          and <w part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F">firm'd</w>, that the moſt remarkable Circumſtance
          of <lb/>which he had been conſcious was, that a large <lb/>Bladder had been form'd around
          his Head for his <lb/>Preſervation. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_10" n="8"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The memorable Accident which befel the <hi rend="italic">Swiſs
            <lb/>Diver</hi> is ſo well atteſted, and accompanied with <lb/>ſuch a peculiar Train of
          Circumſtances, that it <lb/>cannot fail to make the moſt lively Impreſſions <lb/>upon
          every Perſon capable of the ſmalleſt Degree <lb/>of Reflection. As Neceſſity lays a
          Foundation for <lb/>Induſtry, which frequently cannot be employ'd, <lb/>but in a manner,
          which is either prejudicial to <lb/>Health, or fatal to Life, ſo this adventurous Man
          <lb/>follow'd the Buſineſs of plunging into the Water, <lb/>and ſearching thoſe Holes in
          which he imagined <lb/>the larger and better Sort of Fiſhes were lodg'd. <lb/>Accordingly,
          being employ'd as Dr. <hi rend="italic">Bruhier</hi>
          <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">lates</w> the Story, to furniſh a Diſh of Fiſh for a
          <lb/>Company, who intended to regale themſelves with <lb/>a fine Dinner, he cheerfully
          undertook the Taſk. <lb/>His Employers, in the mean Time, accompanied <lb/>him to the
          Brink of the River, and ſeeing him <lb/>plunge into the Water, retir'd, not in the leaſt
          <lb/>doubting but he would keep his Word. The <lb/><hi rend="italic">Swiſs,</hi> however,
          happening not to bring the Fiſh <lb/>at the Hour appointed, the Company, when the
          <lb/>Afternoon was pretty far advanc'd, went to the <lb/>Banks of the River, in order to
          know the <w part="I">Rea-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſon</w> of their Diſappointment. As the
          Clothes of <lb/>the Diver lay on the River-ſide, ſo they ſoon <w part="I">ſu-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſpected</w> his deplorable Fate, and accordingly <w part="I">or-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">der'd</w> him to be ſearch'd for with Hooks, in the <lb/>Place into which they
          had ſeen him plunge. The <lb/>Efforts for this Purpoſe were not in vain, for he <lb/>was
          at laſt found, and taken out of the Water, <lb/>tho' wounded in ſeveral Parts. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As this unfortunate Man had been under Water <lb/>for nine Hours, ſo
          the Curate of the Place, whoſe <lb/>Profeſſion call'd for ſome Care of a Perſon in ſuch
          <lb/>a Situation, had a Mind that he ſhould be <w part="I">forth-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >with</w> interr'd; and he had been infallibly <w part="I">commit-</w><pb
            xml:id="page_11" n="9"/><lb/><w part="F">ted</w> to the Grave, had not the celebrated
          Mr. <hi rend="italic">Egly,</hi>
          <lb/>a Member of the Royal Academy of <hi rend="italic">Inſcriptions,</hi>
          <lb/>who obſerv'd a Kind of Ebullition in the Water <lb/>diſcharg'd from his Mouth,
          poſitively affirm'd <lb/>that he was not dead. For that Gentleman juſtly <lb/>aſcrib'd
          this Ebullition to the languid and <w part="I">imper-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceptible</w>
          Remains of Reſpiration. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This Conduct of Mr. <hi rend="italic">Egly,</hi> however <w part="I"
            >uncom-</w><lb/><w part="F">mon</w>, yet made ſo deep an Impreſſion upon the
          <lb/>Spectators, that they carried the unfortunate <w part="I">Di-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ver</w>, into an adjacent Houſe, where having laid <lb/>him out at full Length, they
          compreſs'd his <w part="I">Ab-</w><lb/><w part="F">domen</w>, in order to procure a
          Diſcharge of the <lb/>Water he had ſwallow'd. By this Means having <lb/>in three Quarters
          of an Hour evacuated a <w part="I">conſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">derable</w> Quantity of
          Water, he mov'd one of his <lb/>Legs, a Circumſtance which ſufficiently evinc'd <lb/>that
          he ſtill retain'd ſome faint Remains of Life. <lb/>For this Reaſon he was, by Mr. <hi
            rend="italic">Egly</hi>'s Orders, <lb/>wrap'd up in warm Sheets, and gradually <w
            part="I">reftor-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> to a natural Heat. Then being laid in a warm
          <lb/>Bed, and his Life becoming gradually more <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſpicuous</w>, a liberal Veneſection was made, which <lb/>was ſucceeded by a Sigh, then
          by a ſlight <w part="I">Know-</w><lb/><w part="F">ledge</w> of what had befallen him, and
          ſoon after by <lb/>a total Reſtitution of Health; and tho' Gratitude <lb/>is rarely to be
          met with in the Breaſts of the <w part="I">Vul-</w><lb/><w part="F">gar</w>, yet this
          important Service, ever after touch'd <lb/>the Heart of the <hi rend="italic">Swiſs,</hi>
          with the higheſt and moſt <lb/>lively Senſe of the Obligations he lay under to <lb/>Mr.
            <hi rend="italic">Egly.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Durham,</hi> a Gentleman ſufficiently <w
            part="I">celebrat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> for his untainted Integrity, and extenſive
            <w part="I">Learn-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>, in his <hi rend="italic"
            >Phyſico-Theology,</hi> quotes the following <lb/>Hiſtory from <hi rend="italic"
            >Pechlinus,</hi> an Author of no leſs <w part="I">Can-</w><lb/><w part="F">dour</w> and
          Reputation. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_12" n="10"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>About eighteen Years ago, a Gardner of <hi rend="italic"
            >Fron-<lb/>ningholm,</hi> now ſixty-five Years old, and ſufficiently <lb/>vigorous and
          robuſt for a Perſon of that Age, <lb/>made a generous Attempt to reſcue an <w part="I"
            >unfortu-</w><lb/><w part="F">nate</w> Neighbour who had fallen into the Water; <lb/>but
          being too fool-hardy, he ventur'd upon the <lb/>Ice, which broke, and let him fall into
          the River, <lb/>which at that Part was eighteen Ells in Depth: <lb/>He went
          perpendicularly to be Bottom, in which <lb/>his Feet ſtuck for ſixteen Hours before he was
          <lb/>found. He himſelf ſays, that he was no ſooner <lb/>under Water, than he became rigid,
          and loſt not <lb/>only the Power of Motion, but alſo all his Senſes, <lb/>except that of
          hearing, which was affected by the <lb/>Ringing of ſome Bells at <hi rend="italic"
            >Stockholm.</hi> He at firſt, <lb/>alſo perceived a Kind of Bladder before his Mouth,
          <lb/>which hinder'd the Ingreſs of the Water by that <lb/>Paſſage tho' it enter'd freely
          into his Ears, and <lb/>produc'd a Dulneſs of Hearing for ſome Time <lb/>after. This
          unfortunate Man was in vain ſought <lb/>for during ſixteen Hours, at the End of which
          <lb/>Time he was taken up by Means of an Hook fix'd <lb/>in his Head, and upon his total
          Recovery ſaid, <lb/>that he was ſenſible of that particular Part of his <lb/>Fate.
          However, whether from the prevailing <w part="I">Cu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtom</w> of the
          Country, or the Perſuaſion of <w part="I">particu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lar</w> Perſons,
          certain Attempts were made in order <lb/>to reſtore him to Life: For this Purpoſe he was
          <lb/>wrap'd up in Blankets, leſt the Air entering too <lb/>precipitately into his Lungs
          ſhould prove fatal to <lb/>him. In this Condition, being gradually warm'd <lb/>by Means of
          Sheets, he was rubb'd and ſtimulated <lb/>till the Motion of his Blood, which had been
          <lb/>check'd for ſo many Hours, return'd. At laſt he <lb/>was totally reſtor'd by Means of
          Cordials, and <w part="I">an-</w><lb/><w part="F">tiapoplectic</w> Liquors. He as yet
          bears the Mark of <lb/>the Hook, and ſays, that he is ſtill ſubject to <w part="I"
            >vi-</w><pb xml:id="page_13" n="11"/><lb/><w part="F">olent</w> Head-achs. This ſingular
          Accident, atteſted <lb/>by the Oaths of Perſons who had been <w part="I"
            >Eye-wit-</w><lb/><w part="F">neſſes</w> to it, induc'd the Queen to give him an <w
            part="I">an-</w><lb/><w part="F">nual</w> Penſion, and he was introduc'd to the Prince,
          <lb/>in order to give an Account of what had <lb/>befallen him. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The celebrated <hi rend="italic">Pechlinus</hi> has wrote the Hiſtory
          of <lb/>a Woman, who remaining under Water for three <lb/>whole Days, was happily reſtor'd
          to Life, almoſt <lb/>in the ſame manner as the Gardner. This Fact, <lb/>was ſo notorious,
          that the learned <hi rend="italic">Tilaſius,</hi>
          <w part="I">Libra-</w><lb/><w part="F">ry-keeper</w> to the King of <hi rend="italic"
            >Sweden,</hi> and in whoſe <lb/>Time the Woman was ſtill alive, gave the <w part="I"
            >follow-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> Certificate of it, which is ſtill kept in the <w
            part="I">Ar-</w><lb/><w part="F">chives</w> of the <hi rend="italic">Acad. Natur.
            Curios.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">There lately was in</hi> Dalia, <hi rend="italic"
            >commonly called</hi>
          <w part="I">Wormſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">land</w>, <hi rend="italic">a Woman of the Name
            of</hi> Margaret Larſdotter, <lb/><hi rend="italic">who having the Misfortune to be
            thrice drown'd, <lb/>remain'd the firſt Time, ſhe being then young, for three <lb/>whole
            Days under Water, but the two other Times <lb/>had more ſpeedy Relief afforded her. She
            died in</hi>
          <lb/>1672, <hi rend="italic">in the ſeventy-fifth Year of her Age.</hi> Telaſius. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Tho' this Accident, and the Delivery from it, <lb/>happening ſo many
          different Times to the ſame <lb/>Perſon, may be ſome be look'd upon as fabulous <lb/>and
          romantic, yet upon the whole it appears to be <lb/>cloath'd with the moſt genuine
          Character of Truth <lb/>and Evidence; for is it credible, that a Man of <lb/>Probity,
          Candour, and learning, as we may <w part="I">rea-</w><lb/><w part="F">dily</w> ſuppoſe the
          Librarian of a rich and powerful <lb/>Monarch to be, ſhould in a manner ſo poſitive and
          <lb/>circumſtantial, dare to affirm a Fact, which was <lb/>only ſuſpect, and much leſs one
          that was <w part="I">abſo-</w><lb/><w part="F">lutely</w> falſe? Is it probable that a Man
          of <hi rend="italic">Pechlinus</hi>'s Character, who is no leſs univerſally than juſtly
            <pb xml:id="page_14" n="12"/><lb/>applauded for his extenſive Erudition and <w part="I"
            >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſummate</w> medicinal Knowledge, ſhould compoſe <lb/>an
          elaborate Treatiſe in order to explain the <w part="I">Poſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſibility</w> of this Fact, without taking due Pains to <lb/>have its Reality
          ſufficiently confirm'd and <w part="I">aſcer-</w><lb/><w part="F">tain'd?</w> or, in a
          word, is it to be ſuppoſed, that <lb/>this Phyſician, who was look'd upon as the <w
            part="I">Glo-</w><lb/><w part="F">ry</w> and Ornament of the <hi rend="italic"
            >Swediſh</hi> Nation, ſhould <lb/>have the Impudence, to appeal to all the <hi
            rend="italic">Literati</hi>
          <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Sweden,</hi> for the Truth of a Fact, which had <lb/>not the
          Sanction of ſufficient Evidences? Why <lb/>ſhould we be more ſcrupulous than <hi
            rend="italic">Pechlinus</hi>'s <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">temporary</w>
          Authors, who never call'd the Truth <lb/>of this Fact in Queſtions? The celebrated <hi
            rend="italic">Bartholin,</hi>
          <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">Act. Med. Haffn. Tom.</hi> 3. <hi rend="italic">Obs.</hi> 42.
          ſpeaks of it <lb/>in the following manner; <q rend="quotes">I can by no Means <lb/>remain
            diffident with reſpect to the Truth of a <lb/>Story confirm'd by the concurring
            Teſtimonies <lb/>of ſo many Witneſſes of Candour and <w part="I">Vera-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">city</w>; and of which <hi rend="italic">Pechlinus</hi> has demonſtrated
            <lb/>the Poſſibility by other Examples of a ſimilar <lb/>Nature: I am only ſurpris'd,
            that ſo ſingular a <lb/>Narrative, ſhould be ſo long buried in Oblivion, <lb/>in a
            Nation otherwiſe ſo curious and fond of <lb/>Diſcoveries.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But we ſhall have no manner of Reaſon to doubt <lb/>of this Fact
          recorded by <hi rend="italic">Pechlinus,</hi> when we <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >flect</w>, that other celebrated Phyſicians and <w part="I">Philoſo-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">phers</w>, aſſure us of the Truth of other Accidents <lb/>highly ſimilar and
          analogous to it. Thus <hi rend="italic">Alexan-<lb/>der Benedicius,</hi> Lib. x. Cap. 9.
          ſpeaks in the <w part="I">fol-</w><lb/><w part="F">lowing</w> manner. <q rend="quotes"
            >Life has been frequently ſeen <lb/>reſtor'd to Perſons who have remain'd under
            <lb/>Water during forty-eight Hours.</q> The ſame <lb/>Author, for this very Reaſon,
          thinks it highly <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F">proper</w>, to inter drown'd and
          hyſteric Patients, <lb/>till ſeventy-two hours after their ſuppos'd Death. <pb
            xml:id="page_15" n="13"/><lb/><hi rend="italic">Borelli,</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
            >Cant.</hi> 2. <hi rend="italic">Obs.</hi> 2. informs us, that, <q rend="quotes">a <w
              part="I">cer-</w><lb/><w part="F">tain</w> Perſon of Diſtinction having remain'd for
            <lb/>a long Time under the Water, was taken for <lb/>dead when he was found; but proper
            Efforts <lb/>being made to reſtore his Life, he was rous'd <lb/>from his ſuppos'd Death,
            and long ſurviv'd his <lb/>Misfortune.</q> Beſides, the Credibility of the <lb/>Fact,
          told by <hi rend="italic">Pechlinus,</hi> is ſufficiently confirm'd <lb/>by the Suffrage
          of the learned and judicious <hi rend="italic">Zac-<lb/>chias,</hi> who, in his 79th
          Conſultation, wrote in <w part="I">or-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w> to determine, whether
          the Return of Life to <lb/>a young Man who had remain'd an Hour under <lb/>Water, was
          miraculous, and as ſome <w part="I">ſuperſti-</w><lb/><w part="F">tious</w> People would
          have it, to be aſcrib'd to a <lb/>Perſon of ſuperior Sanctity, ſpeaks in the <w part="I"
            >follow-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> manner. <q rend="quotes">This Event is ſo far from
            being <lb/>miraculous, that it can hardly come under the <lb/>Denomination of
            ſurpriſing, ſince vaſt Numbers <lb/>of Perſons have return'd to Life, after having
            <lb/>been drown'd, or ſuffocated in any other <w part="I">man-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ner</w>, not only for ſome Hours, but alſo during <lb/>one, and even three whole
            Days; becauſe the <lb/>Suppreſſion of Reſpiration in the Water, had <lb/>occaſioned an
            Oppreſſion of the Spirits, and <lb/>had brought on an apoplectic Paroxyſm, which
            <lb/>render'd them apparently dead, tho' their Lives <lb/>were really preſerv'd by
            Tranſpiration, which <lb/>augmenting gradually, laid a Foundation for <lb/>a free
            Reſpiration.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Poſſibility of retaining a Principle of Life <lb/>for a long Time
          under Water, is ſtill more <w part="I">ſur-</w><lb/><w part="F">priſingly</w> confirm'd by
            <hi rend="italic">Kunckel,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Miſcellan. Nat. Curios. Decad.</hi>
          3. <hi rend="italic">An.</hi> 5 &amp; 6. <hi rend="italic">Obs.</hi> 71. where he
          <lb/>ſpeaks in the following manner. <q rend="quotes">I am <w part="I">ſuffici-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ently</w> ſenſible, that in <hi rend="italic">Sweden,</hi> no one Doubts of
            <lb/>the Poſſibility of retaining Life under Water for <lb/>eight Days; and that the
            ſollowing Accident is <pb xml:id="page_16" n="14"/><lb/>by no Means call'd in Queſtion
            by thoſe who <lb/>live near the Place where it happened. Some <lb/>Time ago, about four
            Leagues from the Town <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Falung,</hi> a Painter fell from a Boat
            into the <lb/>Water in ſuch a manner, as to remain upright <lb/>with his Feet at the
            Bottom. He was in vain <lb/>ſearch'd for during eight Days; at the End of <lb/>which
            Time, he appear'd alive on the Surface <lb/>of the Water. The Magiſtrate and Clergyman
            <lb/>of the Place, ask'd him the following Queſtions. <lb/>Whether he had reſpir'd all
            the Time of his <lb/>Submerſion? To which he anſwer'd, He knew <lb/>nothing of the
            Matter. Whether he had thought <lb/>upon God and recommended his Soul to him? <lb/>To
            which he reply'd, Very often. Whether he <lb/>could ſee and hear? To which he anſwer'd,
            <lb/>Yes, and ſaid that he would often have laid <lb/>hold of the Hooks employ'd in
            finding him, if <lb/>he could have mov'd his Arms. He alſo, <w part="I">add-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ed</w>, that the Fiſh prov'd highly offenſive and <lb/>uneaſy to him, by the
            Attacks they made on his <lb/>Eyes; and being ask'd by what Means he <w part="I"
              >guard-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> againſt theſe Attacks, he anſwer'd, by <w part="I"
              >mov-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> his Eye-lids. As to his Senſe of hearing, <lb/>he
            affirm'd, that nothing wrs more ungrateful, <lb/>and even painful, to him than ſtriking
            the <w part="I">Sur-</w><lb/><w part="F">face</w> of the Water; and that in a particular
              <w part="I">man-</w><lb/><w part="F">ner</w>, he was affected with a violent Pain of
            his <lb/>Ears, which was forthwith communicated to his <lb/>whole Body, every Time
            People came to draw <lb/>Water in Buckets. When he was ask'd, <w part="I"
              >Whe-</w><lb/><w part="F">he</w> had been ſenſible of Hunger, and diſcharg'd <lb/>his
            Excrements? He reply'd, that he had not. <lb/>Being interrogated, Whether he had ſlept?
            he <lb/>anſwer'd, he knew nothing of it, but believ'd <lb/>he had, becauſe he was ſome
            time depriv'd of <lb/>all Senſation and Reflection; adding, that all <pb
              xml:id="page_17" n="15"/><lb/>the Thoughts he remember'd to have paſs'd in <lb/>his
            Breaſt, had only God, and the Means of <lb/>his own Deliverance, for their Objects.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Nature and Circumſtances of the Accident <lb/>now related, lay a
          ſufficient Foundation, for our <lb/>believing the following memorable Event, <w part="I"
            >eſpe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cially</w> as it happened to a Perſon of Diſtinction,
          <lb/>and is atteſted as authentic by Men of Learning <lb/>and Probity. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Gocellinus,</hi> a young Man, and Nephew to one
          <lb/>of the Archbiſhops of <hi rend="italic">Cologne,</hi> had the Misfortune <lb/>to fall
          into the <hi rend="italic">Rhine,</hi> and was not found for fifteen <lb/>Days after; and
          being laid in an adjacent Church, <lb/>in order to be interr'd, ſoon return'd to Life, and
          <lb/>ſurviv'd the Accident a long Time. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As there are a great many ſecret Things in <w part="I">Na-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ture</w>, and probably numberleſs latent Circumſtances <lb/>in the animal
          Oeconomy, with which we are <w part="I">en-</w><lb/><w part="F">tirely</w> unacquainted;
          and as Perſons of a curious <lb/>and attentive Turn of Mind, daily obſerve <w part="I"
            >Acci-</w><lb/><w part="F">dents</w>, which they before thought impoſſible, ſo we
          <lb/>have no Reaſon to doubt of ſurpriſing Facts, <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >lated</w> by Men of Learning and Candour, nor <w part="I">for-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >mally</w> to deny the Truth of Events, which at firſt <lb/>appear incredible. Of this
          Kind, is the following <lb/>Narrative. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The celebrated Mr. <hi rend="italic">Burmann</hi> aſſures us, that in
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Boneſs</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Pithovia,</hi> he heard a
          funeral Sermon <lb/>preach'd upon the Death of one <hi rend="italic">Laurence Jones,</hi>
          <lb/>a Man of ſeventy Years of Age, who as the Preacher <lb/>ſaid, was drown'd when
          ſixteen Years old; and <lb/>continued ſeven Weeks under Water, <w part="I"
            >notwithſtand-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> which, he return'd to Life, and enjoy'd good
          <lb/>Health. However viſionary and romantic this <w part="I">Ac-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cident</w> may appear, in the Eyes of thoſe who <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tend</w> to have diveſted their Minds of vulgar <w part="I">Er-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >rors</w>, yet it has met with Credit from the moſt <w part="I">pe-</w><pb
            xml:id="page_18" n="16"/><lb/><w part="F">netrating</w> and ſagacious Authors who liv'd
          at the <lb/>Time in which it happen'd. Thus the learned and <lb/>judicious <hi
            rend="italic">Langelott,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Miſcellan. Natur. Curioſ.
            <lb/>Decad.</hi> 1. <hi rend="italic">An.</hi> 6. <hi rend="italic">Obs.</hi> 20, not
          being able to <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceive</w> how a Perſon can preſerve a
          Principle of Life <lb/>ſo long, without the Aſſiſtance of the Air, in <w part="I"
            >Wa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ters</w> ſo cold and full of Nitre, as thoſe of <hi
            rend="italic">Sweden,</hi>
          <lb/>and not being ſatisfied with ſimilar Accidents <lb/>daily happening to ſome Birds and
          Infects, is yet <lb/>ſo far from doubting of the Truth of this <w part="I"
            >Acci-</w><lb/><w part="F">dent</w>, that he applies to the learned Members of <lb/>the
            <hi rend="italic">Acad. Natur. Curios.</hi> for their Opinion and <lb/>Explication of
          it; by which Means he imagin'd <lb/>that effectual Meaſures for reſtoring many drown'd
          <lb/>Perſons might be diſcover'd. Beſides, it is by no <lb/>Means probable that a Man of
          Mr. <hi rend="italic">Burmann</hi>'s <w part="I">Ve-</w><lb/><w part="F">racity</w> would
          forge ſuch a Story, in order to ſee <lb/>what enormous Lengths Credulity was capable of
          <lb/>carrying his Fellow-Creatures; nor is it poſſible <lb/>that the Clergyman, ſhould,
          from the Pulpit, <w part="I">aſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſert</w> this Fact as true, if it had
          not really been ſo, <lb/>ſince <hi rend="italic">Laurence Jones,</hi> was a Native of the
          Place, <lb/>and well known to every one of his Audience. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But upon the Whole, granting that this <w part="I">Narra-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tive</w> of <hi rend="italic">Laurence Jones</hi> was falſe, which however
          <lb/>we have no Reaſon to believe, yet the Recital of <lb/>it has a great Tendency not
          only to illuſtrate our <lb/>Subject, but alſo to produce happy Effects in Life; <lb/>for,
          1ſt, It is certainly the genuine and <w part="I">uncontro-</w><lb/><w part="F">verted</w>
          Intereſt of the Public, to be appriz'd of the <lb/>Poſſibility of a Perſon's retaining a
          Principle of <lb/>Life for a long Time under Water; 2dly, The <lb/>Concluſion to be drawn
          from this ſeemingly <w part="I">mira-</w><lb/><w part="F">culous</w> Effect is, that if
          after a long Time, a <w part="I">Bo-</w><lb/><w part="F">dy</w> is taken out of the Water,
          without the Signs <lb/>of Putrefaction, it is the Duty of thoſe who find <lb/>ſuch a Body,
          to treat it as if there were ſtill a <pb xml:id="page_19" n="17"/><lb/>Poſſibility of
          reſtoring it to Life; and 3dly, If it <lb/>is certain from uncontroverted Facts, that
          Perſons <lb/>have retain'd Life under Water for ſeveral Days, <lb/>there is no Reaſon,
          from the Laws of the animal <lb/>Oeconomy, and the hitherto known Properties <lb/>of the
          animal Fluids, to disbelieve that the like <lb/>ſhould happen to Perſons who have alſo
          remain'd <lb/>under Water for ſeveral Weeks. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As our Modeſty ought always to be <w part="I">propor-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tion'd</w> to the difficult and intricate natures of the <lb/>Subjects we
          pretend to conſider, ſo we frankly <lb/>acknowledge, that theſe and other ſimilar <w
            part="I">Acci-</w><lb/><w part="F">dents</w>, as it were, bewilder the Mind, and perplex
          <lb/>the moſt penetrating Capacities, when they attempt <lb/>to account for them; ſince we
          have never yet <lb/>diſcover'd wherein the conſtituent Principle of <lb/>Life exactly
          conſiſts, and ſince there are various <lb/>Properties both of the Solids and Fluids of the
          <lb/>human Body, to which we are intire Strangers. <lb/>Some however, affirm, that a
          Principle of Life <lb/>may in the deplorable State of Submerſion, be <w part="I"
            >re-</w><lb/><w part="F">tain'd</w> for a long Time, becauſe the Coldneſs of <lb/>the
          Water renders the Circulation ſlower, and <lb/>ſupperſſes the Tranſpiration of the vital
          Air <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tain'd</w> in the Blood; whilſt at the ſame Time,
          <lb/>ſome Portions of the Air lodg'd in the Water, <lb/>probably penetrate into the Bodies
          of ſuch <w part="I">Per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſons</w>. But <hi rend="italic">Platerus</hi>
          and <hi rend="italic">Bartholin</hi> ſeem to account <lb/>in a more rational and
          ſatisfactory manner for <lb/>Phænomena of this Kind. The former of theſe <lb/>Authors, in
          explaining how a Woman, who was <lb/>drown'd in the <hi rend="italic">Rhine,</hi> for
          murdering her own <lb/>Child, return'd to Life after ſhe was found, <w part="I"
            >af-</w><lb/><w part="F">firms</w>, that this Accident was the Effect of a <w part="I"
            >Syn-</w><lb/><w part="F">cope</w>, in which Reſpiration and the Motion of <pb
            xml:id="page_20" n="18"/><lb/>the Heart are ſtopt. Now 'tis certain from <w part="I"
            >Expe-</w><lb/><w part="F">rience</w> and Obſervation, that theſe two Functions <lb/>may
          be ſuppereſs'd without the actual Loſs of Life, <lb/>as is frequently obvious in violent
          Syncopes, and <lb/>hyſteric Paroxyſms, from which the Patients do not <lb/>often recover
          in an Hour or more, during which <lb/>Time, the ſlighteſt Indications of Life by the Pulſe
          <lb/>and Reſpiration, are not to be obſerv'd. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>If any one ſhould ſay, that it beſpeaks an <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">pardonable</w> Exceſs of Credulity, to believe that a <lb/>Syncope may laſt for
          a Week or longer, and that <lb/>conſequently the Motion of the Heart and Pulſe <lb/>may be
          for that Time ſuſpended, without <w part="I">neceſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſarily</w>
          producing Death; we may juſtly reply, <lb/>that hitherto no Perſon has diſcover'd wherein
          the <lb/>Eſſence and Principle of Life conſiſts; and that <lb/>there are in Nature various
          Phaenomena, which <lb/>ſeem to prove, that the Motion of the Heart, <lb/>and the
          Circulation of the Humours, are rather <lb/>palpable Signs of the Exiſtence of Life, than
          its <lb/>proximate and immediate Cauſes. This Doctrine <lb/>we ſhall endeavour to
          eſtabliſh, in a ſtrictly <w part="I">ana-</w><lb/><w part="F">logical</w> manner, by
          comparing thoſe Events which <lb/>happen to Vegetables and the Brute Creation, <lb/>with
          ſimilar Accidents which befall Mankind. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>For this Purpoſe we ſhall firſt conſider the State <lb/>and Condition
          of ſuch Plants, as retain a <w part="I">Princi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ple</w> of Life and
          Vegetation during the whole <w part="I">Win-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w>. All the
          Difference, according to <hi rend="italic">Pechlinus,</hi>
          <lb/>between theſe, and the Plants of the animal Kind <lb/>is, that in the latter the
          Principle of Motion is <lb/>weaker, and the Texture of the Fibres leſs firm; <lb/>whereas
          the former contain a much larger <w part="I">Quan-</w><lb/><w part="F">tity</w> of Oil,
          and have the Spirit ſubſervient to their <lb/>Vegetation repell'd by the Cold, to the
          Bulbs, <pb xml:id="page_21" n="19"/><lb/>Roots, and Seeds, where it circulates in a
          languid <lb/>manner, without having Force to propel Buds, <lb/>Flowers, and Bloſſoms, till
          the kind and genial <lb/>Hears of the Spring, render it more powerful and <lb/>active. Why
          may we not, therefore, ſuppoſe that <lb/>ſomething analogous to this may happen in ſome
          <lb/>human Bodies, who have been under the Water <lb/>for ſome Time. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This is not the only Inſtance in nature, which <lb/>we can bring in
          Confirmation of our Doctrine; <lb/>for certain Inſects paſs the whole Winter in <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Chryſalides,</hi> or conſiderably hard Pellicules, <w part="I"
            >with-</w><lb/><w part="F">out</w> diſcovering the ſmalleſt Signs of Life, tho'
          <lb/>'tis certain they are not dead, ſince a ſmall <w part="I">De-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >gree</w> of Heat only, is requiſite to produce their <lb/>laſt Metamorphoſis. The
          Reaſon of this apparent <lb/>Death, is the Cold of the Atmoſphere, ſo <w part="I"
            >inſpiſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſating</w> their Fluids, as that they can only circulate
          <lb/>in a faint and languid manner, round an highly <lb/>minute and ſmall Center. The
          Degree of <w part="I">Fluidi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ty</w> which they retain, is however, ſo
          conſiderable, <lb/>that a more intenſe Cold than we perceive on the <lb/>Earth, is
          incapable of totally coagulating them, <lb/>as is ſufficiently evinc'd by the curious <w
            part="I">Experi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ments</w> of Mr. <hi rend="italic">Reaumur.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This Phaenomenon is not only obſerv'd in the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Chryſalides</hi> of Inſects, but the <hi rend="italic">Seminal Principle</hi> is
          <lb/>alſo preſerv'd free from Coagulation, and without <lb/>diſcovering the ſmalleſt Sign
          of Life, in Eggs, <lb/>which may be conſider'd as the <hi rend="italic">Chryſalides,</hi>
          or <w part="I">Pel-</w><lb/><w part="F">licules</w> of Animals whoſe Life is perceptible.
            <w part="I">A-</w><lb/><w part="F">quatic</w> Inſects, alſo, plunge themſelves into the
          <lb/>Mud, where they remain without Motion, till the <lb/>Spring; which holds equally true
          of Frogs and <lb/>Toads, according to <hi rend="italic">Valentinus,</hi> in <hi
            rend="italic">Diſſert. Epiſtol.</hi> 4. <pb xml:id="page_22" n="20"/><lb/>The like
          happens to ſome terreſtrial Inſects; for <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Reaumur</hi> has by
          Experiment and <w part="I">Obſerva-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> ſufficiently evinc'd,
          that Ants during the <lb/>whole Winter, remain apparently dead, till the <lb/>Approach of
          the Spring. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>A third and more powerful collateral Proof of <lb/>this Doctrine, is
          drawn from the Conſideration of <lb/>ſome Animals, whole Blood is warm, and <w part="I"
            >circu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lates</w> in the ſame manner with that of the Human
          <lb/>Species; ſince in theſe alſo the Circulation and <lb/>Reſpiration are ſuppreſs'd
          during the Winter, <lb/>but return in the Spring. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Thus of Swallows it may be ſaid, that during <lb/>one Half of the Year
          they are dead, and the other <lb/>alive. <hi rend="italic">Olaus Magnus,</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">Scheffer,</hi> in a Letter <lb/>wrote to <hi rend="italic">Hevelius,</hi>
          affirm, that in ſome northerly <lb/>Countries, it is very common for Fiſhermen to
          <lb/>find in the Water large Cluſters of Swallows, <lb/>which in the Beginning of the
          Autumn, had thus <lb/>pil'd themſelves up. Thoſe Authors alſo inform <lb/>us, that ſome
          Species of Swallows, ſpontaneouſly <lb/>ſeek a Refuge in the Waters, others take their
          <lb/>Flight to foreign Climates, others conceal <w part="I">them-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſelves</w> in the Holes of old and decay'd Buildings, <lb/>in the Sand, and in their
          own Neſts; and that <lb/>others finding a Decay of Strength in their <w part="I"
            >Paſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſage</w> to other Countries, plunge themſelves into the
          <lb/>Sea, where they remain till the genial Spring <lb/>rouſes their latent Principle of
          Life and Motion. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The celebrated <hi rend="italic">Kircher,</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
            >Mund. ſubterran.</hi> Lib. <lb/>8. Sect. 4. informs us, that the Inhabitants of
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Peloponeſus,</hi> and other Territories of the <hi rend="italic"
            >Archipe-<lb/>lago,</hi> have told him, that every Year, they <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſerv'd</w> large Quantities of Storks and Swallows <lb/>flying thro' their
          Countries from <hi rend="italic">Egypt</hi> and the <pb xml:id="page_23" n="21"
          /><lb/>Coaſts of <hi rend="italic">Lybia,</hi> and that theſe latter when fatigu'd
          <lb/>with flying, plac'd themſelves, to the number of <lb/>five or ſix, on the Back of a
          Stork, whom they <lb/>recompens'd by an uninterrupted and melodious <lb/>Song. There, are,
          therefore, continues the <w part="I">Au-</w><lb/><w part="F">thor</w>, ſome Swallows which
          fly from one Country <lb/>to another; but 'tis equally certain from <w part="I"
            >Expe-</w><lb/><w part="F">rience</w>, that the Swallows of cold Climates make <lb/>no
          ſuch Voyages; but during the Winter conceal <lb/>themſelves in Caves, Lakes, Rivers, Seas,
          and the <lb/>Cavities of Trees. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Olaus Magnus,</hi> in Lib. 15. Chap. 10. informs
          <lb/>us, that ſuch Swallows as are taken out of the <lb/>Water before the due Time, do not
          live long; <lb/>and adds, that the Inhabitants of <hi rend="italic">Tivoli,</hi> when
          <lb/>ſhewing him Mount <hi rend="italic">Sciſſo,</hi> which Name it receives <lb/>from a
          fooliſh Report of its being divided at the <lb/>Crucifixion of our Saviour, aſſur'd him,
          that in <lb/>the Winter-Seaſon, large Quantities of Swallows <lb/>apparently dead were to
          be found on it; <w part="I">where-</w><lb/><w part="F">as</w> no ſuch Animals are to be
          found there in <lb/>Summer. He then quotes <hi rend="italic">Cyſatus,</hi> who in his
          <lb/>Deſcription of <hi rend="italic">Switzerland</hi> affirms, that about <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Chriſtmas,</hi> ſome Workmen when digging up the <lb/>Earth for laying the
          Foundation of a public <w part="I">Edi-</w><lb/><w part="F">fice</w>, found a
          ſubterraneous Cave, from which flew <lb/>about twenty or more Swallows. Whence the <w
            part="I">Au-</w><lb/><w part="F">thor</w> concludes, that all theſe Birds do not paſs
          <lb/>the Sea at their Diſappearance, but that ſome <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tire</w> into the Cavities of Mountains, others in <w part="I">Hol-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >low-Trees</w>; but that this moſt frequently happens <lb/>in northerly Climates. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Fortunus Licetus,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Tr. de
            Feriis Altric. Animal. <lb/>Diſp.</hi> 19. affirms, that in upper <hi rend="italic"
            >Poland,</hi> every <lb/>Perſon may be experimentally convinc'd, that the <pb
            xml:id="page_24" n="22"/><lb/>ſame Swallows which in Summer build their Neſts <lb/>upon
          the Tops of Houſes, towards the End of <lb/><hi rend="italic">September</hi> plunge
          themſelves into Ditches and <w part="I">Ri-</w><lb/><w part="F">vers</w>, where they
          remain conceal'd till about the <lb/>Middle of <hi rend="italic">May.</hi> He, alſo,
          informs us, that when <lb/>the Inhabitants ſeeing Fiſh thro' the Ice, break it <lb/>in
          order to catch them, they alſo frequently find <lb/>Cluſters of Swallows adhering to each
          other, <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w part="F">out</w> diſcovering the ſmalleſt Signs of
          Life, till <lb/>they are brought to a Stove, where they ſoon <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">turn</w> to Life. But what is ſtill more remarkable <lb/>is, that as ſoon as
          the <hi rend="italic">Polanders,</hi> who imagine it <lb/>unlawful to kill theſe Swallows,
          ſet them at <w part="I">Li-</w><lb/><w part="F">berty</w>, they forthwith fly back to the
          Water, and <lb/>plunge themſelves into it. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The celebrated <hi rend="italic">Huet,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi
            rend="italic">Avranches,</hi>
          <lb/>who travell'd thro' <hi rend="italic">Sweden,</hi> informs us, that <w part="I"
            >be-</w><lb/><w part="F">tween</w>
          <hi rend="italic">Caen</hi> and the Sea, along the Shore of the <lb/>River <hi
            rend="italic">Orne,</hi> there are many Caves, in which, <w part="I">dur-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ing</w> the Winter, have been found large Cluſters of <lb/>Swallows, ſuſpended
          like ſo many Bunches of <lb/>Grapes; and that the like was long ago obſerv'd in <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Italy.</hi> For <hi rend="italic">Pedo Albinovanus,</hi> in the Elegy he
            <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">pos'd</w> on the Death of <hi rend="italic"
            >Mecaenas,</hi> ſpeaks of the <w part="I">Re-</w><lb/><w part="F">treat</w> of the
          Swallows to the Rocks, as an <w part="I">infalli-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w> Sign of the
          Approach of Winter. </p>
        <q rend="diple quotes"><lb/><l>Congelantur Aquæ, ſcopulis ſe condit Hirundo, </l>
          <lb/><l>Verberat egeledas garrula vere Lacus. </l></q>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Bodin,</hi> quoted by <hi rend="italic">Camerarius,
            Cant.</hi> 7. <hi rend="italic">Hiſt.</hi> 71. <lb/>informs us, in the ſecond Book of
          his <hi rend="italic">Theatre of <lb/>Nature,</hi> that when the People who inhabit the
          <lb/>Coaſts of the <hi rend="italic">Baltic</hi> Sea, are employ'd among the <lb/>Rocks in
          ſearching for yellow Amber, they <w part="I">fre-</w><pb xml:id="page_25" n="23"/><lb/><w
            part="F">quently</w> find large Cluſters of Swallows. <hi rend="italic"
            >Camera-<lb/>rius</hi> ſubjoins, that ſome Authors affirm, that <q rend="quotes"
            >Swal-<lb/>lows conceal themſelves in the Bottom of the <lb/>Sea, where they ſleep till
            the Appearance of a <lb/>proper Seaſon for their quitting it; but this is
            <lb/>impoſſible ſince they have Lungs, and for that <lb/>Reaſon muſt neceſſarily periſh
            in ſuch a <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">dition</w>.</q> But however ſpecious and
          concluſive <lb/>this Reaſoning of <hi rend="italic">Camerarius</hi> may appear, yet 'tis
          <lb/>certain that the Truth of Facts, which have <w part="I">actual-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ly</w> happened, can never be invalidated. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Franciſeus de Frankenau</hi> in his Medicinal
          Satyres, <lb/>confirms this Opinion with Reſpect to Swallows, <lb/>by the Authorities of
            <hi rend="italic">Lauremberg,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Acer. Philol.</hi>
          <lb/>Lib. 3. Cap. 71; of <hi rend="italic">Iſaac Voſſius,</hi> in his <hi rend="italic"
            >Append. <lb/>de Lucis Natur.</hi> Cap. 1; of <hi rend="italic">Deuſingius,</hi> in <hi
            rend="italic">Vindict. <lb/>Fæt.</hi> Sect. 5; and of <hi rend="italic">Fournier,</hi>
          in his Geography, <lb/>who in Part 1. Lib. 2. Cap. 5. informs us, that <lb/>they are
          commonly found in the <hi rend="italic">Norwegian</hi>-Seas, <lb/>as alſo in the Lakes and
          Rivers of <hi rend="italic">Sileſia, <w part="I">Po-</w><lb/><w part="F">land</w>,
            Bohemia,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Moravia;</hi> and that in the <w part="I"
            >Be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ginning</w> of the Autumn, large Numbers of them <lb/>plunge
          themſelves into Wells. The ſame Author, <lb/>alſo, eſtabliſhes his own Opinion by the
          additional <lb/>Suffrages of <hi rend="italic">Cromerus,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Hiſt.
            Polon,</hi> Lib. 1; of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hevelius;</hi> of <hi rend="italic"
            >Marcellus Donatus,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Hiſt. Med. <lb/>Memorab.</hi> Lib. 4. Cap.
          12. and of <hi rend="italic">Helvicius,</hi> in <lb/>his Epigrams. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The celebrated Mr. <hi rend="italic">Falconet,</hi> whoſe Judgment
          <lb/>and Veracity render his ſingle Word a ſufficient <lb/>Evidence, informs us, that
          being in the Houſe of <lb/>a Gentleman of <hi rend="italic">Breſt</hi> in the Winter
          Seaſon, he ſaw <lb/>a Servant bring in a Kind of Maſs or Lump, which <lb/>appeared to be
          Earth, and which ſome Fiſhermen <lb/>had caught in their Nets. By waſhing it carefully,
            <pb xml:id="page_26" n="24"/><lb/>in order to diſcover what it was, it was found to
          <lb/>be a Group of Swallows, which reſum'd Life by <lb/>being expos'd to the Fire for ſome
          time. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Swallows are not the only Birds which conceal <lb/>themſelves in the
          Bottoms of Rivers, in order to <lb/>paſs the Winter; for <hi rend="italic">John Baptiſte
            de Fulgoſa,</hi>
          <w part="I">for-</w><lb/><w part="F">merly</w> Doge of <hi rend="italic">Genoa,</hi>
          affirms, that <hi rend="italic">Gervas <w part="I">Tibel-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >lerius</w>,</hi> wrote to <hi rend="italic">Otho</hi> the Fourth, that ſome <w part="I"
            >Per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſons</w> having thrown their Nets into a River of that
          <lb/>Country in the Winter Time, they brought to <lb/>Land a large Quantity of Storks,
          which were <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">parently</w> dead, with their Beaks fix'd
          in each <lb/>other's Fundament; but they were ſoon reſtor'd <lb/>to Life, by means of
          Heat. The ſame Author <lb/>adds, that in 1467, near <hi rend="italic">Metz</hi> in <hi
            rend="italic">Lorrain,</hi> a large <lb/>Number of apparently dead Storks were found in
          <lb/>a River, and that being put into a warm Bath, <lb/>they recover'd Life. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The learned <hi rend="italic">Voſſius,</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
            >Append. de Lucis Natur.</hi>
          <lb/>informs us, that at the Approach of Winter, Storks, <lb/>Herons, and ſome other Birds
          of the like Nature, <lb/>do not fly to <hi rend="italic">Egypt,</hi> or into more
          temperate <w part="I">Cli-</w><lb/><w part="F">mates</w>, but plunge themſelves into
          Ditches and <lb/>Marſhes. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Poſſibility of retaining Life for a long Time <lb/>under Water, is
          ſtill farther evinc'd, by conſidering <lb/>thoſe Birds with which our Fields and Foreſts
          are <lb/>richly ſtock'd in Summer; but which are not to be <lb/>ſeen in Winter. If it
          ſhould be ſaid, that theſe, <w part="I">dur-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> the Winter, live
          upon the Stores they have amaſs'd <lb/>in the Summer; I anſwer, that they are by no Means
          <lb/>provident againſt future Want. Hence they muſt <lb/>neceſſarily conceal themſelves,
          in Places ſuited to <lb/>their particular Natures; and as it is equally <w part="I"
            >im-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſſilble</w> for them, as for the human Species, to live <pb
            xml:id="page_27" n="25"/><lb/>awake without Aliments, 'tis more than probable <lb/>that
          during the whole Winter, they are, as it were, <lb/>lock'd up in ſo lethargic a Sleep,
          that they ſuſtain <lb/>no Loſs or Diſſipation of their Fluids, and <w part="I"
            >conſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">quently</w> require no Reparation. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>If it ſhould be ask'd, whether theſe Animals, <lb/>during ſuch a
          State, retain a real Principle of Life? <lb/>I anſwer, that the Thing is not only
          probable, but <lb/>may be alſo evinc'd from Fact and Experience, <lb/>ſince the moſt
          celebrated natural Hiſtorians and <lb/>Phyſicians give us ſtrong and uncontroverted <w
            part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtances</w> of this Kind. Thus in <hi rend="italic"
            >Ephemerid. Nat. <w part="I">Cu-</w><lb/><w part="F">rios</w>.</hi> we are inform'd,
          that a certain Gentleman in <lb/>the Winter Seaſon, order'd an hollow Trunk of a
          <lb/>Sallow Tree, which by his Direction had been cut <lb/>down the preceding Autumn, to
          be laid on the <lb/>Fire; but a ſmall Portion of it happening to be <lb/>left in a Corner
          of the Room, he had the Curioſity <lb/>to examine it, and upon his doing ſo, found <w
            part="I">Fea-</w><lb/><w part="F">thers</w> arrang'd and diſpos'd in a natural Manner:
          <lb/>Theſe he gently pluck'd off, and underneath found <lb/>the Fleſh of a ſmall Bird
          which he believ'd to be <lb/>dead, though he could not diſcover to what <w part="I"
            >Spe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cies</w> it belonged. However, with reſpect to this
          <lb/>Circumſtance, he was ſoon undeceiv'd; for having <lb/>expos'd it to the Influence of
          the Fire, it ſoon <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">cover'd</w> palpable Signs of Life.
          Something <w part="I">ſimi-</w><lb/><w part="F">lar</w> and analogous to this, no doubt,
          happens with <lb/>reſpect to many of thoſe Quadrupeds which <w part="I">inha-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">bit</w> our Foreſts, for Want of a Nouriſhment <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">per</w> to give their Blood that Degree of Fluidity, <lb/>which is abſolutely
          neceſſary to its Circulation, <lb/>ſince it is certain, that a far ſmaller Number is to
          <lb/>be ſeen in Winter than in Summer. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>After theſe Examples of an apparent Death in <lb/>Birds whoſe Blood is
          warm, we have no Reaſon <lb/>to be ſurpriz'd at <hi rend="italic">Pechlinus,</hi> when he
          affirms, that in <pb xml:id="page_28" n="26"/><lb/>the Winter Time, Fiſhes not only appear
          dead, <lb/>but are conſequently cover'd over with a Cruſt of <lb/>Ice in their Holes,
          without having the vital <w part="I">Prin-</w><lb/><w part="F">ciple</w> deſtroy'd in
          them; for they begin to live <w part="I">a-</w><lb/><w part="F">freſh</w>, when the Heat
          of the Atmoſphere, or an <lb/>artificial Fire, melts the Ice. The like, continues the
          <lb/>Author, happens to Serpents, Toads, Frogs, <w part="I">Tortoi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſes</w>, and in a Word all amphibious Animals, when the <lb/>Cold inſpiſſates their
          Juices; which being naturally <lb/>viſcid, are conſequently more proper to prevent
          <lb/>the Diſſipation of that vital Spirit, which is <w part="I">abſo-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >lutely</w> neceſſary to reſtore them to Life. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>'Tis to be obſerv'd, that thoſe Fiſhes which have <lb/>been thus
          frozen, do not long ſurvive their artificial <lb/>Reſtitution to Life; becauſe the Froſt
          having <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter'd</w> the Principles of their Blood, the
          vital Spirit, <lb/>when beginning to act and unfold itſelf, can no <lb/>longer form a Maſs
          of Fluids of an uniform <w part="I">Na-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w>. Thus Wine when
          frozen, and artificially <lb/>thaw'd, contracts a diſagreeable Flavour, becauſe <lb/>the
          Solution being procur'd in an unnatural <w part="I">Man-</w><lb/><w part="F">ner</w>,
          hinders the ſpirituous Part of the Wine from <lb/>mixing with its other Principles, in the
          ſame <w part="I">Or-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w> and Proportion as before. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>What <hi rend="italic">Pechlinus</hi> advances with Reſpect to Fiſhes,
          <lb/>is entirely conformable to the Opinion of <hi rend="italic">Theo-<lb/>phraſtus,</hi>
          in <hi rend="italic">Tr. de Piſcibus in ſiceo degeritibus,</hi> where <lb/>we are
          inform'd, that the Inhabitants of <hi rend="italic">Pontus,</hi>
          <lb/>frequently find Fiſhes in the Ice, which diſcover no <lb/>Signs either of Motion or
          Senſation, till they are <lb/>put into a Fiſh-Back, or laid among Straw. This
          <lb/>Circumſtance, according to <hi rend="italic">Theophraſtus,</hi> happens
          <lb/>particularly to the Gudgeon, and ſome other Fiſhes <lb/>of a ſimilar Nature. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The laſt Proof of the Poſſibility of a Perſon's <lb/>retaining a
          Principle of Life for a long Time under <lb/>Water, without a Supply of Aliments for the
            <pb xml:id="page_29" n="27"/><lb/>Purpoſes of Nutrition, is drawn from a <w part="I"
            >Conſidera-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of ſome Quadaupeds, as the Hedge-Hog, <lb/>the
          Marmotte, the Dormouſe, and ſome others, <lb/>which in the Beginning of Winter concealing
          <lb/>themſelves in the Earth, are ſeiz'd with ſo <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >found</w> a Sleep that they appear to be dead, ſince <lb/>neither the Pulſation of
          their Arteries, nor their <lb/>Reſpiration are perceptible. This Circumſtance, <lb/>no
          doubt, induc'd the celebrated <hi rend="italic">Harvey</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Lib.
            <lb/>de Generat. Animal. Exercit.</hi> 50, to ſpeak in the <lb/>following Manner: <q
            rend="quotes">Some ſanguineous Animals <lb/>live long without any Pulſe, and lie
            conceal'd <lb/>during the Whole of the Winter, <w part="I">notwithſtand-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ing</w> which they remain alive, tho' their Heart <lb/>retains no Motion, and
            their Reſpiration ſtops, <lb/>juſt as it happens to Perſons attack'd with <w part="I"
              >Sin-</w><lb/><w part="F">copes</w>, and hyſteric Fits, whoſe Pulſe is totally <w
              part="I">a-</w><lb/><w part="F">boliſh'd</w>.</q> Tho' <hi rend="italic">Harvey</hi>
          was the glorious <w part="I">Diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">coverer</w> of the Circulation of
          the Blood, and may <lb/>for that Reaſon be ſuppos'd to be a keen <w part="I"
            >Advo-</w><lb/><w part="F">cate</w> in its Behalf, yet 'tis ſufficiently obvious from
          <lb/>this Paſſage, that he did not believe it abſolutely <lb/>neceſſary to the
          Preſervation of Life. But <hi rend="italic">Pechli-<lb/>nus,</hi> whether from Prejudice,
          or rational <w part="I">Deducti-</w><lb/><w part="F">ons</w> from what he had obſerv'd, is
          of Opinion, <lb/>that in theſe Animals, Reſpiration is carried on, <lb/>by a Motion of the
          Diaphragm, ſo inſenſible as to <lb/>eſcape the Eye of the Obſerver. He alſo obſerves,
          <lb/>that in this State, it is neceſſary their Reſpiration <lb/>ſhould be ſuch, becauſe if
          it was perform'd in the <lb/>uſual Manner, the Motion of the Blood would be <lb/>ſo
          likewiſe; in conſequence of which, the <w part="I">Tranſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">piration</w>
          and Neceſſity for Aliments would be <w part="I">e-</w><lb/><w part="F">qually</w> ſtrong;
          a Circumſtance incompatible with <lb/>the Condition of theſe Animals, which lie hid <w
            part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w> the Earth during the whole Winter. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_30" n="28"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Tho' theſe Relations may poſſibly appear very <lb/>ſingular and
          ſurpriſing to Perſons unacquainted <lb/>with Natural Hiſtory; yet they infallibly prove,
          <lb/>that in the brute Creation at leaſt, Reſpiration, the <lb/>Circulation of the Blood,
          and Pulſation of the <w part="I">Ar-</w><lb/><w part="F">teries</w> may ceaſe for a long
          Time, without the total <lb/>Extinction and Deſtruction of Life. Now is it <lb/>not highly
          probable, or rather abſolutely certain, <lb/>that ſomething ſimilar and analogous to this
          may <lb/>happen to human Creatures, who have the <w part="I">Misfor-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tune</w> to be drown'd, ſince in both, the Solids and <lb/>Fluids act and move by the
          ſame Laws, ſo in both <lb/>Suffocation muſt be the ſame Thing, and <w part="I"
            >conſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">quently</w> its Effects remov'd by the ſame Means? </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Beſides, there is by no Means any Reaſon for <lb/>believing, that an
          Inſtance of this ſurprſing <w part="I">Abſti-</w><lb/><w part="F">nence</w> and Want of
          Food, prodnc'd by ſuch a <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">found</w> and lethargic
          Sleep, as that of the Marmotte, <lb/>is not to be found among the human Species; for
          <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">Miſcellan. Academ. Natur. Curios. An.</hi> 8. <hi rend="italic"
            >Obs.</hi> 67. <lb/>the celebrated <hi rend="italic">Ludovicus,</hi> firſt Phyſician to
          the <lb/>Duke of <hi rend="italic">Saxe-Gotha</hi> informs us, that a young Girl, <lb/>who
          for ſome Fault ſhe had committed being <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">prehenſive</w>
          of a ſevere Chaſtiſement from her <w part="I">Pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">rents</w>, retir'd
          to the moſt conceal'd Part of a <lb/>Thicket, where, ſeven Days after her Elopement,
          <lb/>ſhe was found lying on her Belly with all the <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >parent</w> Signs of Death, except that her Limbs <lb/>were ſtill flexible and pliant;
          her Viſage was <lb/>overſpread with a viſcid Phlegm, which was <w part="I">co-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ver'd</w> with an hoary Kind of Down, and with the <lb/>falling Leaves which
          had adher'd to it. Her <lb/>Mouth and Noſtrils were entirely full of a thick <lb/>Mucus:
          But notwithſtanding theſe ſeemingly <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">couraging</w>
          Circumſtances, the Phyſician call'd to <lb/>her Aſſiſtance, order'd her Body to be warm'd
          by <lb/>Means of Friction; Then, with warm Water, <pb xml:id="page_31" n="29"
          /><lb/>waſhing away the Phlegm which cover'd her Face, <lb/>and the viſcid Mucus which
          obſtructed her Mouth <lb/>and Noſtrils, he pour'd into her Mouth a <w part="I"
            >Spoon-</w><lb/><w part="F">ful</w> of Brandy, which ſeem'd to go down her <lb/>Throat,
          and was the only Cordial he had at hand. <lb/>Upon exhibiting a ſecond Spoonful, ſhe
          fetch'd a <lb/>Sigh, and a third made her open her Eyes. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>We now proceed, to conſider the moſt proper <lb/>and efficacious
          Meaſure to be taken for the Relief <lb/>of drown'd Perſons; for which Purpoſe we ſhall
          <lb/>previouſly inveſtigate and aſcertain the genuine <lb/>Cauſe of Suffocation. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Not only the antient Schools of <hi rend="italic">Greece</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">Ara-<lb/>bia,</hi> but alſo moſt of the ſucceeding Phyſicians, <lb/>till
          the Days of <hi rend="italic">Platerus,</hi> imagin'd that the <w part="I"
            >Suffo-</w><lb/><w part="F">cation</w> was produc'd by the Water which enter'd <lb/>into
          the Stomach, Breaſt, and Lungs; in <w part="I">Conſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">quence</w> of
          which falſe Notion they thought <w part="I">them-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſelves</w> fully
          authoriz'd to attempt its Diſcharge <lb/>with all poſſible Expedition. For this Purpoſe
          <lb/>they order'd drown'd Perſons to be ſuſpended by <lb/>the Feet, or laid upon their
          Bellies, on a Hogſhead <lb/>or Tub, which was to be agitated from one Side <lb/>to the
          other, imagining that by this Poſition, <lb/>the Abdomen and Breaſt being compreſs'd, and
          <lb/>the Head hanging down, the Agitation of the <lb/>Veſſel, muſt neceſſarily facilitate
          the Evacuation <lb/>of the Water, which they ſuppos'd was alſo <w part="I">fa-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">vour'd</w> by the declining Situation of the ſuperior <lb/>Part of the Body.
          With the ſame Intention, they <lb/>alſo order'd ſuch Meaſures as had a Tendency to
          <lb/>excite Vomiting. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But as a falſe Theory never fails to lay a <w part="I"
            >Foun-</w><lb/><w part="F">dation</w> for a dangerous Practice, ſo we have juſt
          <lb/>Reaſon to condemn this Method of Suſpenſion, or <lb/>hanging by the Heels; for the
          Water ſwallow'd <lb/>by drowning Perſons deſcends into the Stomach, <pb xml:id="page_32"
            n="30"/><lb/>and not into the Thorax, ſo that it cannot prevent <lb/>their Recovery.
          This Circumſtance muſt happen, <lb/>not only ſo long as a Perſon retains a Senſe of his
          <lb/>State and Condition, but alſo afterwards; for as <lb/>the Water is hinder'd from
          entring into the <w part="I">Arte-</w><lb/><w part="F">ria</w> Trachaea and Lungs by a
          mechanical Effort, in <lb/>which Reaſon has no ſhare, ſo the Lungs may in <lb/>this State
          be compar'd to an empty Bottle plung'd <lb/>in Water, into which the Fluid does not enter,
            <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">cauſe</w> the Air it contains reſiſts its Acceſs,
          and this <lb/>the rather happens, becauſe the Motion of the <lb/>Breaſt, deſtin'd to
          attract the Air, at that Time, <lb/>totally ceaſes, and conſequently nothing forces the
          <lb/>Water to enter and fill up its Place. This <w part="I">Doc-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >trine</w> is not only evinc'd from the Structure of the <lb/>Parts, but alſo confirm'd
          by Experience. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Thus the learned <hi rend="italic">Platerus,</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
            >Queſt.</hi> 5. <w part="I">poſitive-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> affirms, that if
          drown'd Perſons ſwallow any <lb/>Water, the Quantity of it is too ſmall to prove
          <lb/>mortal to them; becauſe he always found but <w part="I">ve-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ry</w> little of it in their Stomachs. He alſo adds, <lb/>that moſt of the Water which
          appears to be <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">charg'd</w> from the Mouths of Perſons
          ſuſpended by <lb/>the Heels, really flow'd from their Cloaths. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Nymman,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Tr. de Vita foet.
            in Utero,</hi> ſpeaks <lb/>thus, <q rend="quotes">Who could believe that a Foetus ſo
            long <lb/>included in the Uterus, where it moves all its <lb/>Limbs, ſhould yet never
            move its Jaw-bone, <lb/>nor open its Mouth. Beſides, it always has its <lb/>Noſtrils
            open, notwithſtanding which it has <w part="I">ne-</w><lb/><w part="F">ver</w> been
            obſerv'd that the Liquor of the <w part="I">Am-</w><lb/><w part="F">nios</w> has enter'd
            its Body. Thus it is with the <lb/>Human Foetus, as with thoſe who are drown'd,
            <lb/>ſince in diſſecting many of theſe laſt, I have <lb/>hardly found a Pint of Water in
            their Bodies.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the <hi rend="italic">Miſcellan. Nat. Curios. An.</hi> 2. <hi
            rend="italic">Obs.</hi> 251. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Wepfer,</hi> gives an Account of the
          Anatomy of <pb xml:id="page_33" n="31"/><lb/>ſome Beavers, one of which was drown'd. The
          <lb/>Author having open'd the <hi rend="italic">Arteria Trachæa,</hi> no <lb/>Water was
          diſcharg'd from the Lungs; but there <lb/>were about four Ounces of Water, like the <w
            part="I">Waſh-</w><lb/><w part="F">ings</w> of Fleſh, found in the right Cavity of the
          <lb/>Breaſt, and about three Ounces of the ſame Kind <lb/>in the Left. This Extravaſation
          the Author <w part="I">juſt-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> ſuppoſes produc'd by the
          Expreſſion of a bloody <lb/>Lymph from the Pores of the Bronchia of this <lb/>Animal,
          which had for a long Time ſtruggled <w part="I">a-</w><lb/><w part="F">gainſt</w> ſo
          violent a Death as that of Drowning. <lb/>Neither pure Water nor Water ting'd with Blood,
          <lb/>were obſerv'd either in the <hi rend="italic">Arteria Trachæa,</hi> or in <lb/>the
            <hi rend="italic">Bronchia.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Bhonius,</hi> in the Appendix to his Treatiſe <hi
            rend="italic">de <w part="I">Re-</w><lb/><w part="F">nuntiat</w>. Vuln. Diſs.</hi> 2.
          informs us, that in <w part="I">diſſect-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> a great many Women
          drown'd for murdering <lb/>their Children, he had ſhewn the Spectators, that <lb/>there
          was little or no Water in their Lungs and <lb/>Abdomen; and adds, that in order to render
            <w part="I">him-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſelf</w> more certain with Reſpect to this
          Circumſtance, <lb/>he had, drown'd ſeveral Animals, in whoſe Cavities, <lb/>tho' drown'd
          alive, he had never perceiv'd any <lb/>Water. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Dethardingius,</hi> at preſent Profeſſor of Medicine
          <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">Coppenhagen,</hi> in a Letter wrote when he was <lb/>Profeſſor
          at <hi rend="italic">Roſtoch,</hi> in 1714, gives us an Account <lb/>of the Diſſection of
          a Soldier, who attempting to <lb/>make his Eſcape from a Garriſon, was drown'd in <lb/>a
          Ditch, and upon being open'd had in his <w part="I">Sto-</w><lb/><w part="F">mach</w> only
          about a Pint of Beer, which he had <lb/>drank ſome Time before. The Profeſſor took
          <lb/>care previouſly to appriſe the Spectators, that <lb/>there would not be a ſingle Drop
          of Water in his <lb/>Breaſt, which as well as his Abdomen, was very <lb/>much elevated;
          and the Event verified the <w part="I">Pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">diction</w>. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_34" n="32"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Johannes Conradus Becker,</hi> in his Treatiſe <hi
            rend="italic">de <lb/>Submers. Mort. Sin. Pot. Aq.</hi> gives us the four <lb/>following
          Hiſtories. A Dog, ſays he, being <lb/>drown'd and lying in the Water for an Hour, his
          <lb/>Abdomen, Stomach, and Inteſtines, appear'd <w part="I">tu-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >mified</w> and inflated, tho' a ſingle Drop of Water <lb/>was not found in them. The
          Lungs were, alſo, <lb/>inflated, without containing Water, like thoſe of <lb/>hang'd
          Perſons, but immediately collaps'd upon <lb/>ſuffering the Air to eſcape thro' an Inciſion
          made <lb/>in the <hi rend="italic">Arteria Traehæa.</hi> The Author ſubjoins, that
          <lb/>this Obſervation render'd the Doctrine of the <w part="I">An-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tients</w> highly ſuſpected by him. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The ſecond, is the Hiſtory of a Peaſant, taken <lb/>from the Water,
          after he had been ſome Weeks in <lb/>it, and was entirely putrified. After opening his
          <lb/>Duodenum, two Ligatures were made on that <w part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >teſtine</w>, which was very much inflated, and from <lb/>the Aperture of which nothing
          was diſcharg'd, but <lb/>a Liquor which was Chyle mix'd with Beer, of <lb/>which the
          Peaſant had, at a Market, drank ſo <w part="I">li-</w><lb/><w part="F">berally</w>, as to
          intoxicate himſelf. The <w part="I">Tumefacti-</w><lb/><w part="F">on</w> of the Stomach,
          laid a Foundation for <w part="I">ſuſpect-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> that it contain'd a
          large Quantity of Water, <lb/>tho' upon laying it open, nothing was found but a <lb/>Pint
          of a Liquor, whoſe Smell exactly <w part="I">reſem-</w><lb/><w part="F">bled</w> that of
          Beer. The Lungs were ſo much <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">flated</w>, that when an
          Inciſion was made in the Breaſt, <lb/>they burſt out; but their Inflation was ſpeedily <w
            part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſipated</w>, by making an Aperture in the <hi
            rend="italic">Arteria <lb/>Trachea,</hi> thro' which the Air was diſcharg'd with <lb/>a
          conſiderable Noiſe. In cutting the Lungs into <lb/>Pieces, no extraordinary Signs of
          Humidity were <lb/>perceiv'd, nor were any preternatural <w part="I">Circum-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſtances</w> obſerv'd, except Spots of different Colours. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The third Hiſtory, is that of a Woman drown'd <lb/>in a Well, in whoſe
          Inteſtines nothing but Chyle <pb xml:id="page_35" n="33"/><lb/>was diſcover'd, neither was
          there any Water in the <lb/>Lungs. The Inteſtines collaps'd upon making a <lb/>ſmall
          Puncture in them, and an Aperture being <lb/>made in the Arteria Trachea, the Air eſcap'd
          thro' <lb/>it from the Lungs with ſome Noiſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The fourth and laſt Hiſtory related by <hi rend="italic">Becker,</hi>
          is <lb/>that of a Man who was found ſtanding upright in <lb/>a Baſon, where he had
          remain'd under Water for <lb/>five Days. His Stomach, which was large, was <lb/>only
          inflated with Wind, and hardly contain'd ſix <lb/>Ounces of a whitiſh Liquor. The Lungs
          being <lb/>equally inflated, collaps'd upon cutting the Arteria <lb/>Trachea, from which
          the Air was diſcharg'd with <lb/>a conſiderable Noiſe. When he was found, two
          <lb/>Spoonfuls of Water were not diſcharg'd from his <lb/>Mouth. <q rend="quotes">He was,
            however, continues <hi rend="italic">Becker,</hi>
            <lb/>every where ſurrounded with Water, but <lb/>that Element, notwithſtanding the
            Minuteneſs <lb/>of its Parts, could not penetrate into the <w part="I">Arte-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ria</w> Trachea and Oeſophagus, in order to fill the <lb/>Cavities of the
            Viſcera; an evident Proof that <lb/>theſe Parts were ſo defended againſt every Thing
            <lb/>that made an Attempt to enter them, that the <lb/>Water itſelf could not force a
            Paſſage into <lb/>them.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>From theſe Obſervations, the celebrated Author <lb/>concludes, that
          the Abſence of Water in the Lungs <lb/>and Inteſtines, is not a Proof that a Perſon has
          <lb/>been thrown into the Water after his Death. This <lb/>Obſervation is of the laſt
          Importance to thoſe whoſe <lb/>Buſineſs it is to make Reports before Courts of <w part="I"
            >Ju-</w><lb/><w part="F">dicature</w>, tho' it is contrary to that of <hi rend="italic"
            >Rodericus à <lb/>Caſtro,</hi> adopted by many Philologiſts and <w part="I"
            >Crimi-</w><lb/><w part="F">naliſts</w>, and among others by <hi rend="italic"
            >Feltman</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Tr. de <w part="I">Ca-</w><lb/><w part="F">davero</w>
            inſpiciendo,</hi> Cap. 21. But as in the Opinion <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Becker,</hi>
          the Lungs are not inflated in thoſe who <lb/>are thrown into the Water after Death, ſo we
          may <pb xml:id="page_36" n="34"/><lb/>from their Inflation draw a Proof, that the Perſon
          <lb/>was alive when drown'd, or put into the Water. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Since, therefore, it is ſufficiently obvious, both <lb/>from the
          Structure of the Parts, and the <w part="I">Authori-</w><lb/><w part="F">ties</w> of the
          moſt penetrating Anatomiſts, that little <lb/>or no Water enters the Bodies of drown'd
          Perſons, <lb/>ſo 'tis equally obvious, that the Practice of <w part="I">hang-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ing</w> by the Heels, is not only uſeleſs, but muſt alſo <lb/>contribute to
          deſtroy thoſe Remains of Life which <lb/>may poſſibly be loſt; for by ſuch a Suſpenſion,
          the <lb/>whole Column of the Blood convey'd to the Heart <lb/>by the inferior <hi
            rend="italic">Vena Cava,</hi> will neceſſarily preſs upon <lb/>that convey'd by the
          ſuperior <hi rend="italic">Vena Cava,</hi> where the <lb/>Blood being interrupted in its
          Courſe, muſt <w part="I">neceſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſarily</w> regurgitate into the
          jugular Veins, and <w part="I">conſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">quently</w> into the Head,
          where, by its Quantity and <lb/>Weight, it retards the Motion of the Spirits, whoſe
          <lb/>free Progreſs is abſolutely neceſſary to reſtore the <w part="I">Cir-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">culation</w> of the Blood, on which Life in a great <lb/>Meaſure depends. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As it is of great Importance, to know the Cauſe <lb/>of the Inflation
          of drown'd Perſons, ſince it is not <lb/>produc'd by the Water they ſwallow, ſo the <w
            part="I">learn-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>
          <hi rend="italic">Dethardingius</hi> accounts for it in the following <lb/>manner, <q
            rend="quotes">Thoſe, ſays he, who die in the Water, <lb/>are not deſtroy'd for Want of
            Air, but by <lb/>means of too large a Quantity of it; they do <lb/>not die in
            Expiration, but in Inſpiration; and <lb/>in a Word, nothing more reſembles each <w
              part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſpiration</w>, than the Phaenomena obſerv'd in
            <lb/>drown'd Perſons; for if we attentively conſider <lb/>what happens to ourſelves, we
            perceive that the <lb/>Breaſt is as it were lengthen'd, the Abdomen <lb/>elevated, and
            the Flanks inflated, and that this <lb/>State ſubſiſts, ſo long as we draw in the Air,
            or <lb/>retain it in the Breaſt. Now the ſame Things <lb/>happen in drown'd Perſons,
            only with this <w part="I">Dif-</w><pb xml:id="page_37" n="35"/><lb/><w part="F"
              >ference</w>, that in the latter, the Inſpiration is <lb/>perform'd with Rapidity and
            Violence, whereas <lb/>in the former it is carried on quietly and without <lb/>any
            Effort. In Perſons not drown'd, a <w part="I">Depreſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſion</w>
            ſucceeds the Elevation; but in drown'd <lb/>Perſons the Elevation of the Abdomen, and
            the <lb/>Elongation of the Breaſt ſubſiſt; by which means, <lb/>all the Parts continue
            in a State of Expanſion. <lb/>This is, no doubt, the Meaning of thoſe, who <lb/>look
            upon the Death of drown'd Perſons as a <lb/>Suffocation, and pretend that the Cauſe of
            it, <lb/>and that of ſtrangled Perſons is the ſame; for <lb/>thoſe two Kinds of Death
            have a great <w part="I">Reſem-</w><lb/><w part="F">blance</w> and Analogy, as is
            ſufficiently obvious <lb/>from the Elevation of the Abdomen, which in <lb/>hang'd
            Perſons ſubſiſts after their Death.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>From this Theory 'tis ſufficiently eaſy to <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ceive</w>, that the Inflation of the Lungs, is the Cauſe <lb/>of the Death of
          drown'd Perſons; accordingly <lb/><hi rend="italic">Dethardingius</hi> from the preceding
          Doctrine draws <lb/>the following Concluſions; <q rend="quotes">The Veſicules of <lb/>the
            Lungs are inflated by the Air, the Bronchia <lb/>are lengthen'd, the Blood Veſſels
            diſtributed <lb/>thro' the whole Body of the Lungs, are <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">preſs'd</w>; and tho' the Elongation of the <w part="I">Bron-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">chia</w> aſſiſts the Entry of the Blood into the large <lb/>Veſſels, as well
            thoſe proper to the Lungs, as <lb/>the bronchial Artery and Vein, as thoſe which
            <lb/>are only ſubſervient to the Circulation, as the <lb/>pulmonary Artery and Vein, yet
            the Circulation <lb/>is not carried on equally in the Capillaries; ſince <lb/>the
            Preſence of a rarified Air in the Veſicules <lb/>compreſſes the Blood, and forcing it to
            ſtop <lb/>there, hinders it from paſſing into the Left <w part="I">Ven-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">tricle</w> of the Heart, in order to accompliſh the <lb/>Circulation. Now as
            ſoon as there is a <w part="I">conſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">derable</w> Retardation in
            this important Function, <pb xml:id="page_38" n="36"/><lb/>the vital Motions alſo
            gradually ceaſe, and <lb/>Death approaches inſenſibly.</q>
        </p>
        <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="44"/>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
