<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Huxham: An essay on fevers and their various kinds</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>John Huxham</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">An essay on fevers and their various kinds, as depending on different
              constitutions of the blood: with dissertations on slow nervous fevers; on Putrid,
              pestilential, spotted fevers; on the small-pox; and on pleurisies and peripneumonies. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T53084 </idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T53084"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for S. Austen, in Newgate-Street, MDCCL. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1750</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="15"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="288"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="28"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW106719260</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: disease"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="15"/>
    <body>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <figure>
        <figDesc> </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">AN <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">ESSAY </hi>
          <lb/>on <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">FEVERS, </hi></hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">And their different <hi rend="sc">Kinds</hi>. </hi>
      </head>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <div type="chapter">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>CHAP. I. </head>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Of the moſt ſimple Fevers. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(4)">T</hi>HE great <hi rend="italic">Boerhaave</hi>, in his admi-
          <lb/>rable <hi rend="italic">Aphoriſms de cognoſcendis &amp; <lb/>curandis Morbis</hi>,
          begins with the <lb/>Diſeaſes of a ſimple Fibre; and <lb/>indeed the only Method, to
          attain to any con- <lb/>ſiderable Knowledge in any Science, is to begin <lb/>from the very
          Elements of that Science; for <lb/>whatſoever is moſt ſimple is more eaſily under-
          <lb/>ſtood, than that which is more complex: Me- <lb/>thod and Perſpicuity are the natural
          Conſe- <lb/>quence of ſuch a Procedure. </p>
        <pb n="2"/>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>Thus, in examining into the Nature of Fe- <lb/>vers, it ſeems moſt proper to conſider
          the <lb/>moſt ſimple of the Kind firſt. — Let us ſuppoſe <lb/>then a Perſon, both as to
          his <hi rend="italic">Solids</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Fluids</hi>, <lb/>in perfect
          Health, engaged in violent Exerciſe, <lb/>as by Running, or the like: This, if long con-
          <lb/>tinued, will greatly encreaſe the Velocity, Fric- <lb/>tion, and Heat of the Blood,
          which, when <lb/>conſiderably above natural, are called a <hi rend="italic">febrile
            <lb/>State</hi>. — Here is then the moſt ſimple Fever, ari- <lb/>ſing from nothing but
          the encreaſed Action of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Solids</hi> on the <hi rend="italic"
            >Fluids</hi>, and the Re-action of <lb/>the latter on the former; which ſoon ſubſides
          <lb/>on the Ceſſation of the Motion, or violent Ex- <lb/>erciſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>Let us next ſuppoſe another perfectly healthy <lb/>Perſon, expoſed to cold moiſt Air,
          by which <lb/>his Perſpiration may be conſiderably ſuppreſ- <lb/>ſed; hence will follow an
          encreaſed Quantity <lb/>of Humors, and an encreaſed Effort of Na- <lb/>ture to throw them
          off, and remove the Ob- <lb/>ſtructions: Whence a feveriſh Habit will fol- <lb/>low, which
          however frequently ſoon wears <lb/>off by the kindly relaxing Warmth of a Bed, <lb/>or the
          like, aſſiſting Nature's Endeavours. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>A third, of an equally good Conſtitution, <lb/>drinks too largely of Wine, or other
          ſpirituous <lb/>Liquors; which, encreafing the Quantity of <lb/>Humors, and alſo the
          Motion of the Blood <lb/>by its ſtimulating Quality, produces a Fever, <pb n="3"/>
          <lb/>which in like Manner ſoon goes off, by Abſti- <lb/>nence, <hi rend="italic"
            >&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>In any one of theſe Caſes, only a ſimple Ephe- <lb/>mera, or ſhort Fever, is
          generated. — But if, in <lb/>the firſt Cafe, the Blood was ſo violently agita- <lb/>ted
          and rarefied, as that, by its great <hi rend="italic">Impetus</hi>, <lb/>and Dilatation of
          the Veſſels, ſome of the red <lb/>Globules were forced into the <hi rend="italic">ſerous
            Arteries</hi>; <lb/>an inflammatory Obſtruction would be form- <lb/>ed: As we ſee even
          externally, when the red <lb/>Globules are forced into the Veſſels of the <hi
            rend="italic">Tu- <lb/>nica Conjunctiva</hi> of the Eye, where only <hi rend="italic"
            >Lymph</hi>
          <lb/>or <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> ſhould paſs. And if withal the Velocity <lb/>and Heat
          of the Blood ſhould be ſo great, as to <lb/>diſſipate much of its thinneſt Part; the
          Remain- <lb/>der would be left groſs and thick, and leſs fit <lb/>for a free Circulation
          through the <hi rend="italic">Minima Vaſ- <lb/>cula</hi>; and the very Serum would be
          turned into <lb/>a Kind of Jelly. — For a Heat, not much greater <lb/>than the Heat in a
          common Fever, will coagu- <lb/>late the Serum of the Blood; the Conſiſtence of <lb/>which
          Jelly will be in Proportion to the Vio- <lb/>lence and Duration of the Heat. — Here then,
          <lb/>I ſay, by the mere ſimple accelerated Motion <lb/>of the Blood, an inflammatory Fever
          would be <lb/>produced, of much longer Duration, and more <lb/>dangerous Conſequence. —If
          the Inflammation <lb/>ſeizes the Lungs, a Peripneumony; if the <hi rend="italic">Pleu-
            <lb/>ra</hi>, a Pleuriſy; if the Brain, or its Mem- <pb n="4"/>
          <lb/>branes, a Phrenzy is generated.—And theſe <lb/>Diſorders prove much more ſevere,
          where, an- <lb/>tecedent to this violent Motion of the Blood, <lb/>there was a great
          Strength of the Fibres, and a <lb/>great Denſity and Quantity of Blood. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>If in the ſecond Caſe, the Obſtruction of the <lb/>Pores and Perſpiration be very
          conſiderable, <lb/>the Fibres ſtrong and tenſe, the Blood much in <lb/>Quantity and very
          thick, Fevers of the ſame <lb/>Kind enſue. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>If in the third Caſe, to tenſe Fibres and much <lb/>viſcid denſe Blood, a great
          Quantity of Wine, <lb/>or other ſtimulating Liquors, be added; both <lb/>the Quantity and
          Velocity of the Blood may be <lb/>ſo greatly encreaſed, as to bring on a dangerous
          <lb/>acute Fever, which too often follows drunken <lb/>Debauches. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>Now as any one of the above Cauſes may <lb/>ſingly produce a Fever; on the
          Concurrence of <lb/>two, or all three, a more violent one, <hi rend="italic">cæteris pa-
            <lb/>ribus</hi>, will ariſe. Thus, from cooling too ſudden- <lb/>ly after vehement
          Exerciſe, as by expoſing the <lb/>Body to very cold Air, and ſtopping the Sweat <lb/>and
          Perſpiration at once, a very dangerous in- <lb/>flammatory Fever will come on; which will
          <lb/>be much more violent, if the Blood had been <lb/>heated and encreaſed by a large
          Quantity of <lb/>any ſpirituous Drink immediately before.—By <lb/>the bye, nothing ſo
          effectually carries off the <lb/>ill Conſequences of a drunken Bout, as keep- <pb n="5"/>
          <lb/>ing warm, and lying long in Bed to ſoak it out, <lb/>as they call it. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>Now conſidering the proximate Cauſes of <lb/>theſe Fevers, the Method of Cure is very
          ob- <lb/>vious, which is by leſſening the Velocity, Quan- <lb/>tity, and Acrimony of the
          Blood as ſoon as poſ- <lb/>ſible. — But nothing ſo ſoon abates the too rapid <lb/>Motion,
          Quantity, and Heat of the Blood as <lb/>Bleeding; for by this Means the red Globules
          <lb/>of the Blood and <hi rend="italic">Vis motrix</hi> are leſſened — By <lb/>Bleeding
            <hi rend="italic">ad Deliquium</hi>, as <hi rend="italic">Galen</hi>, and ſome of
          <lb/>the ancient Phyſicians, did in inflammatory <lb/>Fevers, the Blood's Motion almoſt
          quite ceaſes <lb/>for a ſhort Time. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>Bleeding therefore is certainly the firſt <hi rend="italic">In- <lb/>tention</hi> in
          the Cure of Fevers, that ariſe from <lb/>too great a Quantity, and too rapid a Motion
          <lb/>of the Blood; and the longer it is neglected, <lb/>the more viſcid and acrimonious is
          the Blood <lb/>rendered, by diſſipating its more thin Part, <lb/>condenſing the red
          Globules, and heating the <lb/>Serum to ſuch a Degree, as to turn it into a <lb/>Kind of
          Jelly. — And, by exalting the animal <lb/>Salts and Oils to a greater and greater Degree
          <lb/>of Acrimony (which is always in Proportion to <lb/>the Intenſity and Duration of the
          Heat) the <lb/>whole Maſs grows putrid at length, and unfit <lb/>for animal Uſes. —
          Beſides, whatever Obſtructi- <lb/>ons may be formed either in the extreme <lb/>Branches of
          the <hi rend="italic">ſanguine</hi>, or Beginings of the <pb n="6"/>
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſerous Arteries</hi>, are apt to be more and more <lb/>radicated by
          the too violent Motion of the <lb/>Blood. — So that the Neglect of Bleeding, at the
          <lb/>Begining of any acute Diſeaſe, is very often <lb/>never to be compenſated in the
          ſubſequent <hi rend="italic">Sta- <lb/>dia</hi> of the Fever; when the <hi rend="italic"
            >Impaction</hi> of the <lb/>obſtructing Matter is ſo far advanced, and the
          <lb/>Thickneſs and Viſcidity of the Humors ſo great, <lb/>as to elude the Force of all
          Manner of Attenu- <lb/>ants and Diluents. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>In general, the Quantity of the Blood to be <lb/>taken away is to be determined by
          the Strength <lb/>of the Patient and his Pulſe; by the Intenſe- <lb/>neſs of his Fever,
          Heat, and the Vehemence <lb/>of his Symptoms, as to Pain, Difficulty of <lb/>Breathing,
            <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> — Nay, the very <hi rend="italic">Bulk</hi> of the Per-
          <lb/>ſon is to be conſidered alſo; for certainly, <hi rend="italic">cæ- <lb/>teris
            paribus</hi>, a big ſtrong Man can bear to loſe <lb/>more Blood than a ſmall ſtrong Man.
          — 'Tis <lb/>ſafer however to take away too little, than <lb/>too much at a Time, as the
          Operation may be <lb/>ſo ſoon and ſo eaſily repeated, and as often as <lb/>may be
          indicated. — If the Pain, Heat, Difficul- <lb/>ty of Breathing, <hi rend="italic"
            >&amp;c.</hi> abate not after Bleeding, <lb/>it ſhews the Neceſſity of drawing more
          Blood. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>And here let me caution the younger Prac- <lb/>titioner not to be deceived by an <hi
            rend="italic">oppreſſed Pulſe</hi>, <lb/>which is often the Conſequence of too great a
          <lb/>Fulneſs of Blood; this is manifeſt, by the Vi- <lb/>brations of the Artery becoming
          more free and <pb n="7"/>
          <lb/>ſtrong after Bleeding in ſuch Caſes, as daily Ex- <lb/>perience evinces.—If he is
          doubtful in the Caſe, <lb/>let him apply his Finger to the Pulſe in the <lb/>other Arm,
          while the Patient is bleeding; and, <lb/>if he finds it flag conſiderably, flutter, or
          inter- <lb/>mit, it is Time to deſiſt; if it beats ſtronger <lb/>and more open, he may
          proceed with Safety <lb/>and Succeſs. — There are indeed ſome very <lb/>apt to faint on
          Bleeding from a natural Laxity <lb/>of the Fibres, and Want of that due Elaſticity,
          <lb/>which ſhould contract the Veſſels in Proportion <lb/>to the Evacuation. — Theſe
          ſhould be bled in a <lb/><hi rend="italic">recumbent Poſture</hi>, and the Orifice may be
          fre- <lb/>quently ſtopped for a ſhort Time, whereby <lb/>Fainting will be in a great
          Meaſure prevented. — <lb/>Theſe Perſons, though they have too lax Fi- <lb/>bres and
          Veſſels, are often plethoric, and of <lb/>Courſe require Bleeding; eſpecially where the
          <lb/>Load of the Humors begins to overbear the <lb/>Power of the Heart, which is the
          common <lb/>Caſe in an oppreſſed Pulſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>Bleeding not only leſſens the Quantity and <lb/>Velocity of the Blood, but it alſo
          makes Room <lb/>for the Entrance of diluting Liquors into it. — <lb/>Proper Dilution is
          abſolutely neceſſary in all <lb/>Fevers, eſpecially in the ardent and inflamma- <lb/>tory;
          for in theſe the Blood is rendered too <lb/>thick and viſcid by the Diſſipation of the
          thin- <lb/>neſt Parts of it, and the remaining Serum is <lb/>more and more incraſſated, or
          jellied, by the <pb n="8"/>
          <lb/>great and continued Heat: So that cooling, <lb/>thin, diluting Liquors are neceſſary
          to ſupply <lb/>the continual Waſte of the Lymph and Serum, <lb/>and to keep the whole Maſs
          in a due Degree of <lb/>Fluxility. — Theſe, in general, ſhould be of the <lb/>aceſcent,
          and ſomewhat alſo of the ſaponace- <lb/>ous Kind. Of the former, as they are very
          <lb/>cooling, and prevent the Encreaſe of the alca- <lb/>leſcent Acrimony of the Humors,
          which would <lb/>otherwiſe be continually advancing by the great <lb/>Friction and Heat of
          the Blood: (for the ani- <lb/>mal Salts are greatly exalted, and made more <lb/>corroſive,
          by the feveriſh Heat, and the animal <lb/>Oils are by the ſame Cauſe turned rancid at
          <lb/>length, and highly acrid: The ſweeteſt Oils, <lb/>or Butter, by great Heat, become
          vaſtly cau- <lb/>ſtic.) — Of the latter, as they not only diſſolve <lb/>the <hi
            rend="italic">Lentor</hi> better, but alſo keep the Humors <lb/>more properly mixed, by
          uniting the Salts, <lb/>Sulphurs, and Waters more intimately with <lb/>the Blood. I have
          often known pure Water, <lb/>drank plentifully in acute Fevers, rendered <lb/>almoſt as
          pale and inſipid as when drank ;(which, <lb/>by the Way, is a very dangerous Symptom.)
          <lb/>Water, as Water, will not unite with oily Li- <lb/>quors; ſo that when the Serum of
          the Blood <lb/>hath been jellied by Heat, and its oily Part ex- <lb/>alted, and encreaſed,
          by melting down the Fat <lb/>in the <hi rend="italic">Membrana adipoſa</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> it is no Wonder <lb/>that plain Water neither mixes well with
          the <pb n="9"/>
          <lb/>Blood, nor proves an effectual Diluent. Hence <lb/>therefore follows the Neceſſity of
          mixing ſome- <lb/>thing ſaponaceous with it, as Sugar, Syrup, <lb/>Jellies, or <hi
            rend="italic">Rob</hi> of Fruits, as Currants, Raſber- <lb/>ries, Cherries, or the like.
          — Juice of Lemons, <lb/>or Oranges, by mixing a little Sugar with it, <lb/>and a proper
          Quantity of Water, becomes a <lb/>very grateful Drink, and anſwers the Intention <lb/>of a
          Diluent both acid and ſaponaceous. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>Befides the Uſe of Diluents as to the Hu- <lb/>mors of the Body, no ſmall Advantage
          will <lb/>ariſe from them as to the Fibres and Veſſels, <lb/>which they tend to relax;
          eſpecially when they are <lb/>drank ſomewhat warm. — Now too great a Ten- <lb/>ſion of the
          Fibres, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> is naturally concomi- <lb/>tant to great Velocity,
          Heat, and Denſity of <lb/>the Blood, which always attend, or rather are the <lb/>very
          Eſſence of an inflammatory Fever. — Eve- <lb/>ry one knows what tepid Bathing will do
          exter- <lb/>nally; and it may be eaſily ſuppoſed that ſub- <lb/>tepid Diluters internally
          will have an analogous <lb/>Effect. — In all theſe Views, the Blood is render- <lb/>ed
          leſs rapid, leſs viſcid, and, in Conſequence, <lb/>leſs hot; which are Matters of the
          higheſt Im- <lb/>port in the Cure of ardent and inflammatory <lb/>Fevers. It may be added,
          that obſtructed Ca- <lb/>pillaries, and obſtructed Perſpiration, are by <lb/>ſuch Means
          moſt ſafely and effectually remedi- <lb/>ed, the Humors being rendered <hi rend="italic"
            >fluxile</hi>, and <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">minima Vaſcula permeable</hi>. For it is
          to be <pb n="10"/>
          <lb/>noted, that where gentle and general Sweats <lb/>follow plentiful Dilution, with
          Liquors of a <lb/>cooling relaxing Nature, they are commonly <lb/>critical, and ſoon carry
          off the Fever. I ſay, <lb/>gentle Sweats; for profuſe ones ſhould never <lb/>be encouraged
          in the Begining of Fevers, as <lb/>they drain off the thinneſt Part of the Blood, <lb/>and
          leave the Remainder too thick, viſcid, and <lb/>apt to obſtruct. — In a particular Manner
          I have <lb/>often obſerved them of the higheſt ill Conſe- <lb/>quence in the Begining of
          Pleuriſies, Peri- <lb/>pneumonies, and the Small-Pox. — And for the <lb/>ſame Reaſon,
          profuſe Diſcharges by Stool, and <lb/>thin Urine, are hurtful. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>But the moſt pernicious Method of raiſing <lb/>Sweats in the Begining of Fevers, is
          by giving <lb/>hot volatile alexipharmac Medicines, ſtoving <lb/>up the Patients in hot
          Air, and ſmothering them <lb/>almoſt with Loads of Bed-cloaths; for theſe <lb/>encreaſe
          the Motion and Heat of the Blood al- <lb/>ready too violent, and add Fewel to the Fire:
          <lb/>Nay, very often, they are ſo far from raiſing <lb/>Sweat, that they prevent it, by
          hurrying on <lb/>the Blood with too great Rapidity to give off <lb/>any natural and
          regular Secretions. — It is well <lb/>known, the higher the Fever, the leſs the Ex-
          <lb/>cretions by Sweat, Urine, Saliva, and the <lb/>like. — </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>Certainly, if mere encreaſed Motion of the <lb/>Blood can bring on a Fever, whatever
          will en- <pb n="11"/>
          <lb/>creaſe that Motion will continue and augment <lb/>it, which theſe Methods and
          Medicines are <lb/>known to do. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>For theſe Reaſons alſo Bliſters, which throw <lb/>an acrid ſalt into the Blood, and
          greatly ſtimu- <lb/>late the Fibres, are very improper in the Be- <lb/>gining, at leaſt,
          of all ardent and inflammato- <lb/>ry Fevers. — Yet how often do we ſee, in the
          <lb/>common Practice, a Patient bled largely, then <lb/>bliſtered, and forthwith put under
          a Courſe of <lb/>hot alexipharmac Boluſſes, Cordials, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.?</hi>
          <lb/>Which is juſt as rational as to pull out Part of <lb/>too large a Fire firſt, and
          then forthwith endea- <lb/>vour to quench the Remainder, by throwing <lb/>on Gunpowder, or
          Spirit of Wine; — or to lay <lb/>on Whip and Spur to an Horſe on the Fret, <lb/>when we
          would ſtop him; which is really the <lb/>Caſe in Bliſtering, where the oſcillatory Power
          <lb/>of the Veſſels is too great, and the Motion of <lb/>the Fluids too rapid. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>After Bleeding, cooling, emollient, laxative <lb/>Clyſters are of very great Uſe in
          the Cure of <lb/>acute Fevers, even at the very Begining, to <lb/>bring off the indurated
          Excrements, which fre- <lb/>quently are pent up within the Inteſtines, and to <lb/>give a
          Diſcharge to any bilious acrid Matter, <lb/>which might otherwiſe, in Part at leaſt, be
          <lb/>reſorbed by the <hi rend="italic">Lacteals</hi>, &amp;c. into the Maſs of <lb/>Blood.
          — Beſides, they are a Kind of warm, re- <lb/>laxing Fomentation to the Parts in the <hi
            rend="italic">Pelvis</hi>
          <pb n="12"/>
          <lb/>and lower Belly, and both derive from the <lb/>Head and <hi rend="italic"
            >Præcordia</hi>, and promote a Diſcharge <lb/>of Urine alſo. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>A gentle lenient Purge, likewiſe, is often of <lb/>the greateſt Service, more
          effectually to cleanſe <lb/>the inteſtinal Canal of the <hi rend="italic">putrid
            Saburra</hi>. But <lb/>I would always adviſe to ſuch as act chiefly in <lb/>the <hi
            rend="italic">primæ Viæ</hi>, as <hi rend="italic">Manna</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Cream
            of Tartar</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Sal cathartic</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
            >Glauberi</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Rhubarb</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Tamarinds</hi>,
          <lb/>and the like: — All <hi rend="italic">draſtic Purgers</hi> are certainly <lb/>very
          pernicious, and ſo are all the hot <hi rend="italic">aloetic</hi>
          <lb/>Tinctures, Pills, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> — Indeed, all profuſe Purg- <lb/>ing
          is hurtful, as it drains off too much of the <lb/>lymphatic Part of the Blood, and
          thickens the <lb/>remaining. — When Nature ſeems to have too <lb/>great a Tendency that
          Way, firſt a Doſe of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Rhubarb</hi>, then a little of the <hi
            rend="italic">Species è Scordio</hi>, <lb/>with a <hi rend="italic">diacodiate</hi>
          Anodyne, or the like, may be <lb/>proper. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>In very Deed, little more ſeems neceſſary in the <lb/>Cure of ardent inflammatory
          Fevers, than pro- <lb/>per and well-timed Evacuations, and plentiful <lb/>cooling
          Dilution, with a few nitrous Medicines, <lb/>and the acid ſaponaceous Juices of
          Vegetables; <lb/>for theſe not only tend to keep the Blood in a <lb/>due Degree of
          Fluidity, but alſo to prevent its <lb/>running into a putrid State: — In giving theſe
          <lb/>freely, we do but follow Nature (our beſt <lb/>Guide) that earneſtly demands them. —
          For how <lb/>averſe ſoever ſhe may be to Meat in Fevers, ſhe <pb n="13"/>
          <lb/>ardently deſires Drink; and it is a Symptom of <lb/>very bad Omen when ſhe doth not,
          till the Fe- <lb/>ver conſiderably abates, at leaſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>If, from any of the above Cauſes, an inflam- <lb/>matory Fever ſhould ſeize a Perſon
          that had an <lb/>antecedent ſharp State of Humors, the Fever <lb/>would prove much the
          more violent: becauſe <lb/>the acrimonious Salts would act as ſo many <hi rend="italic"
            >Sti- <lb/>muli</hi>, accelerate the Blood's Motion, and pro- <lb/>duce a ſpeedier and
          greater Putreſcence of it. <lb/>— Hence therefore the utmoſt Neceſſity of <lb/>Dilution in
          ſuch Caſes, to diſſolve and waſh <lb/>off the Salts offending, (for nothing but a wate-
          <lb/>ry <hi rend="italic">Menſtruum</hi> will diſſolve Salts) and likewiſe <lb/>Medicines
          oppoſite in Nature to the peccant <lb/>Acrimony. — But the Diluters alſo ſhould have
          <lb/>ſomething of the Saponaceous in them, for Rea- <lb/>ſons hinted at above; eſpecially
          when the oily <lb/>Parts of the Blood are greatly encreaſed by the <lb/>Melting down of
          the Fat by the Heat of the <lb/>Fever: which often happens to a ſurpriſing <lb/>Degree,
          and very ſuddenly, in ſome very fat <lb/>Perſons, and which continually grows more
          <lb/>and more acrid and rancid, and requires ſome <lb/>ſaponaceous <hi rend="italic"
            >Medium</hi> to unite it with the aque- <lb/>ous Parts; otherwiſe it produces the moſt
          fatal <lb/>Obſtructions, and higheſt Degree of Acrimony. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>As to the Manner of Dilution, I think the <lb/>Sick ſhould be allowed to drink as
          freely, and <lb/>as often as they pleaſe, but not forced to load <pb n="14"/>
          <lb/>their Stomachs with too large Draughts at a <lb/>Time; which create a <hi
            rend="italic">Nauſea</hi>, Indigeſtion, <lb/>and Wind, with great Anxiety and
          Reſtleſneſs, <lb/>and, in the Event, Vomiting, or Purging. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>The Practice of <hi rend="italic">Aſclepiades</hi> was in Nothing <lb/>more monſtrous
          than in denying all Manner of <lb/>Drink to the Sick, for the firſt three Days of <lb/>the
          Fever: And he is very far from keeping up <lb/>to the Rule, he lays down, of curing <hi
            rend="italic">tutò</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ce- <lb/>leriter</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >&amp; jucundè</hi>; when, as <hi rend="italic">Celſus</hi> ſays, <hi rend="italic"
            >convelle- <lb/>bat vires ægri luce</hi>, <hi rend="italic">vigilia</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">ſiti ingenti</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ſic ut <lb/>ne os quidem primis
            diebus elui ſineret</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Celſ</hi>. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Lib</hi>.
          3. <hi rend="italic">Cap</hi>. 4. — I am ſure that he did not learn this <lb/>from the
          great <hi rend="italic">Hippocrates</hi>, nor from Reaſon, <lb/>Nature, or Experience. —
          But this Man from a <lb/><hi rend="italic">Declaimer</hi> turned <hi rend="italic"
            >Phyſician</hi>, and ſet himſelf up <lb/>to oppoſe all the Phyſicians of his Time; and
          <lb/>the Novelty of the Thing bore him out, as it <lb/>frequently doth the <hi
            rend="italic">Quacks</hi> of the preſent Time; <lb/>and ever will, whilſt the Majority
          of the World <lb/>are Fools. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>I think ſmaller Draughts, frequently given, <lb/>the beſt Way of Dilution: For, of
          the fame <lb/>Quantity of Liquor drunk in a certain Time, <lb/>more is like to be imbibed
          by the abſorbing <lb/>Veſſels, planted thick from the Mouth to the <lb/>Stomach, by
          frequently ſipping it down, than <lb/>if ſwallowed at once in a full Draught; becauſe
          <lb/>it is in this Way more frequently, and much <pb n="15"/>
          <lb/>longer applied to theſe Veſſels. — Beſides, when <lb/>ſwallowed, the Action of the
          Stomach and In- <lb/>teſtines is more effectual in ſqueezing it into the <lb/>Lacteals and
          meſaraic Veſſels, when in ſmall <lb/>Quantities, than when they are, as it were, de-
          <lb/>luged with the Liquor. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>Moreover, Dilution and Relaxation may be <lb/>further carried on by emollient
          Fomentations, <lb/>tepid Baths, cooling lenient Clyſters, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> —
          <lb/>Bathing of the Arms and Hands, Legs and <lb/>Feet, and alſo of the <hi rend="italic"
            >Hypochondria</hi>, is of very <lb/>great Service in Fevers of the inflammatory
          <lb/>Kind; (the good Effects of which I once ex- <lb/>perienced on myſelf) but the <hi
            rend="italic">Fotus</hi> ſhould not <lb/>be much hotter than the preſent Temper of the
          <lb/>Body, which may eaſily be adjuſted by a <hi rend="italic">Ther- <lb/>mometer</hi>.
          This Method not only ſupplies the <lb/>Blood with Moiſture through the abſorbing Veſ-
          <lb/>ſels, but alſo greatly tends to open the obſtruct- <lb/>ed, and produce a general
          Relaxation of Fi- <lb/>bres, now commonly too rigid. In very dry <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >ſtrigoſe</hi> Conſtitutions, it cannot but be of the <lb/>greateſt Service. — The Skins
          and Bladders of <lb/>Animals, when very dry, will tranſmit nothing; <lb/>but, when
          moiſtened, Water, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> will paſs <lb/>through their Pores. — And
          the Drinking fre- <lb/>quently of tepid, emollient Liquors is at the <lb/>ſame Time a Kind
          of an internal relaxing <hi rend="italic">Fotus</hi>
          <lb/>to the <hi rend="italic">primæ Viæ</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Præcordia</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> which is of <lb/>no ſmall Conſequence, eſpecially in Inflam-
            <pb n="16"/>
          <lb/>mations of the Lungs, Pleura, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> — I ſhall on- <lb/>ly
          further add on this Head, that this was the <lb/>Practice of the Ancients, who gave little
          elſe <lb/>in Fevers, beſides thin Watery Diluents, <hi rend="italic">Ptiſan</hi>
          <lb/>or Barley-water, <hi rend="italic">Hydromel</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Oxymel</hi>,
          &amp;c. and <lb/>uſed very frequent Fomentations and Clyſters. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>As encreaſed Velocity of the circulating Hu- <lb/>mors will of itſelf bring on a
          Fever, all Cauſes <lb/>that encreaſe the Blood's Motion will encreaſe <lb/>the Fever; the
          Strength of the Fever there- <lb/>fore will be in a compound <hi rend="italic">Ratio</hi>
          of the mov- <lb/>ing Powers, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> ſtrong tenſe Fibres, much
          <lb/>denſe rich Blood, and many acrid Salts in it, <lb/>which ſtimulate the Heart and
          Arteries to more <lb/>frequent and vehement Contractions. — The <lb/>large Uſe of very
          ſalt and ſpiced Meats will <lb/>raiſe a feveriſh Heat, even in the moſt healthy. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>On the contrary, the weaker and more lax <lb/>the Fibres, the thinner and poorer the
          Blood, <lb/>the leſs vehement the Fever. — This is the Caſe <lb/>in what we call <hi
            rend="italic">ſlow</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">nervous Fevers</hi>; which <lb/>are
          generated by low, watery, unwholeſome <lb/>Diet, crude waſhy Fruit, rainy warm and wet
          <lb/>Seaſons, long and great Anxiety of Mind, De- <lb/>jection of Spirits, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> — Here indeed a Kind <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Lentor</hi>,
          or <hi rend="italic">Ropineſs</hi> of the Humors, is alſo <lb/>generated, and is a
          proximate Cauſe of the <lb/>Diſeaſe; but it is not of the inflammatory <lb/>Kind (or what
          the Ancients called <hi rend="italic">Phlegma <lb/>phlegmonodes</hi>, which is
          particularly inherent in <pb n="17"/>
          <lb/>the red globular Parts of the Blood) for it ſub- <lb/>ſiſts chiefly in the ſerous and
          lymphatic Veſſels, <lb/>which hence become obſtructed; and from ſuch <lb/>a poor ropy
          State of the Blood few animal Spi- <lb/>rits are generated, and they are irregularly ſe-
          <lb/>creted and diſtributed: hence the nervous Symp- <lb/>toms, which denominate the
          Fever. — And yet <lb/>as there are Obſtructions formed, the ſtagnant <lb/>Lymph grows more
          and more acrimonious, <lb/>which brings on more or leſs of a Fever, known <lb/>by the
          Quickneſs of the Pulſe, irregular Heats, <lb/>Chills, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> — All
          the Humors of the Body <lb/>grow more and more corroſive, the longer they <lb/>ſtagnate;
          even hydropric Swellings of the Legs, <lb/>though at firſt as cold as Marble, become at
          <lb/>laſt highly inflamed, the Humors at length ſo <lb/>very acrid as to produce an
          Eryſipelas, Veſica- <lb/>tions, Ulcers, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> as is often
          obſerved at the <lb/>Cloſe of Dropſies. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>Now as the Seat of <hi rend="italic">theſe Fevers</hi> ſeems chiefly <lb/>in the <hi
            rend="italic">ultima Vaſcula</hi>, or the ſerous and lym- <lb/>phatic Arteries, and
          perhaps in the very Ori- <lb/>gin of the Nerves; and as they are always at- <lb/>tended
          with too great a <hi rend="italic">Flaccidity</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Torpor</hi> of
          <lb/>the Nerves and Fibres, and the Obſtructions lie <lb/>more remote from the great Road
          of the cir- <lb/>culating Blood; it is no Wonder they are not ſo <lb/>eaſily affected by
          Medicines, and ſo readily re- <lb/>moved, as if their Cauſe lay more particularly <lb/>in
          the ſanguineous Veſſels. — Beſides it muſt be <pb n="18"/>
          <lb/>conſidered, that the Nerves and Fibres are not <lb/>preſently reſtored to their due
          Tone. — Hence <lb/>we in Fact ſee that this Kind of Fevers is <lb/>both longer in forming,
          and much longer in <lb/>being carried off, than a common inflamma. <lb/>tory Fever. </p>
        <p rend="indent ">
          <lb/>Theſe two Sorts of Fevers ſeem to have in a <lb/>great Meaſure oppoſite Cauſes, and
          in Conſe- <lb/>quence very different Symptoms and Effects. <lb/>— Let us conſider ſome
          intermediate febrile <lb/>State, which will elucidate this whole Affair. <lb/>Turn we
          therefore our Thoughts on an inter- <lb/>mittent Fever. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter">
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center space">CHAP. II. </head>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">Of intermitting Fevers. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE common procatarctic Cauſes of Agues <lb/>are a moiſt, foggy
            <hi rend="italic">Atmoſphere</hi> exhaling <lb/>from a ſwampy, moraſs Soil, or a
          Continuance <lb/>of cold, rainy, thick Weather; hence in low, <lb/>fenny Countries Agues
          are <hi rend="italic">endemic</hi>, and in ſuch <lb/>Seaſons <hi rend="italic"
            >epidemic</hi>. By ſuch Conſtitutions of the <lb/>Air the Fibres are too much relaxed,
          and re- <lb/>gular Perſpiration obſtructed, which ſoon cre- <lb/>ate a <hi rend="italic"
            >Lentor</hi> of the Blood, and that Obſtructi- <lb/>ons and ſome Degree of Stagnation in
          the ulti- <lb/>mate Branches of the <hi rend="italic">ſanguineous Arteries</hi>; as is
          <lb/>manifeſt from the Coldneſs, Paleneſs, and Li- <pb n="19"/>
          <lb/>vidity of the Fingers, Nails, Lips, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> which
          <lb/>immediately precede and begin the <hi rend="italic">Rigor</hi> of <hi rend="italic"
            >an <lb/>aguiſh Paroxyſm</hi>. — The Blood hence recoils up- <lb/>on the Heart, and all
          the Powers of Nature <lb/>rouſe up to remove the Obſtructions; which <lb/>are ſoon carried
          off by the hot Fit, in Sweats, <lb/>turbid Urinej, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> — We ſee
          a Kind of aguiſh <lb/>Paroxyſm brought on by Bathing in very cold <lb/>Water; Paleneſs,
          Coldneſs, Shivering, a Stop- <lb/>page of the Blood in the <hi rend="italic">cutaneous
            Arteries</hi>, and <lb/>Repulſion towards the Heart: you are no <lb/>ſooner out of the
          Bath than the Heart, Arteries, <lb/><hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> overcome the Reſiſtance
          from the prece- <lb/>dent <hi rend="italic">Conſtriction</hi>, and bring on an univerſal
            <hi rend="italic">Glow</hi>
          <lb/>of Heat. But, if the Perſon bathed be weak, <lb/>the Water very cold, and the
          Continuance in <lb/>it long; he may die in the cold Bath, as a weak- <lb/>ly Patient may
          in the cold Fit, (which common- <lb/>ly happens) the Heart not being able to over-
          <lb/>come the Reſiſtance. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If the Fibres are pretty ſtrong, the <hi rend="italic">Lentor</hi>
          <lb/>and Obſtructions not very great; the Paroxyſm <lb/>eaſily wears off by this Effort of
          Nature. — But <lb/>if the <hi rend="italic">Lentor</hi> and Obſtructions are great, the
          <lb/>Fibres ſtrong and more tenſe; the Fever runs <lb/>very high in the hot Fit, and is
          readily changed <lb/>by wrong Management into an <hi rend="italic">acute Continual</hi>.
          <lb/>— Indeed it is obſervable that ſome epidemic <lb/>Agues, in ſome Conſtitutions, at
          firſt put on <lb/>the Appearance of ardent Fevers, and then <pb n="20"/>
          <lb/>break into Quotidians, or Tertians; and it is not <lb/>uncommon for a Quotidian, or
          Tertian, to be <lb/>changed by a very hot Regimen at the Begin- <lb/>ing, as volatile
          Spirits, Brandy, Pepper, Snake- <lb/>root, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> (which are too
          often quacked upon <lb/>the poor Patient) into an inflammatory Fever <lb/>with Frenzy,
          Pleuriſy, or Peripneumony. — <lb/>So that the Conſtitution of the Solids and Fluids,
          <lb/>in ſome Kinds of Agues, ſeems not greatly dif- <lb/>ferent from that of inflammatory
          Fevers. — I <lb/>well remember, that the <hi rend="italic">Catarrhal Fever</hi>, which
          <lb/>ſpread through all <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi> under the Name of <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Influenza</hi> in the Spring, 1743, frequently be- <lb/>came pleuritic, or
          peripneumonic; and as fre- <lb/>quently, after two or three Days, ran into a
          <lb/>Quotidian, or Tertian: the Difference of the <lb/>Conſtitutions of the Patients, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> thus altering <lb/>the Face and Nature of the Diſeaſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Sometimes quotidian, ſemi-tertian and ter- <lb/>tian Fevers, are very rife and
          cotemporary <lb/>with epidemic Pleuriſies, and Peripneumonies; <lb/>as particularly in
            <note n="*" rend="size(0.5) italic" place="bottom">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Vid. Obſ. noſtr. de Aere &amp; Morb. Epidem. Vol. II. Martio, <lb/>Aprili,
              Maio, 1744. </p>
          </note> 1744: — The cold Seaſon, in <lb/>ſome Conſtitutions, bracing up the Fibres ſo
          <lb/>high, and condenſing the Blood into ſuch a <lb/>Degree of Viſcoſity, as to bring on
          theſe in- <lb/>flammatory Fevers on taking Cold, or other <lb/>Accidents; — whilſt, on
          Perſons of a more lax <lb/>Syſtem of Nerves and Fibres, and more weak, <pb n="21"/>
          <lb/>watery Humors, it only raiſed the Powers of <lb/>the oſcillatory Veſſels ſo high, and
          warmed the <lb/>Blood ſo much, as to carry off the ill Conſe- <lb/>quences of deficient
          Perſpiration, and ropy <lb/>heavy Juices, by repeated Fits of a regular In-
          <lb/>termittent. — Thus we often ſee Perſons of low <lb/>Spirits, and a leucophlegmatic
          Habit of Body, <lb/>raiſed into a feveriſh Diſpoſition by the Uſe of <lb/>warm
          invigorating Medicines, Chalybeates, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
          <lb/>And if this Turn of Nature be well managed, <lb/>it generally ends in their perfect
          Recovery. — <lb/>If you can change a ſlow nervous Fever into a <lb/>regular Intermittent,
          you ſoon cure your Pa- <lb/>tient. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But further, I have more than once known <lb/>Pleuriſies, Peripneumonies, and
          inflammatory <lb/>Rheumatiſms, reign very much in a cold, dry <lb/>Spring, and a great
          Number of Intermittents <lb/>ſucceed them in the following warmer Months; <lb/>the Heat
          abating the Rigidity of the Fibres, <lb/>and reſolving in ſome Meaſure the Viſcoſity
          <lb/>and Denſity of the Blood: Whereas had the <lb/>Solids continued more tenſe, and the
          Blood <lb/>more denſe and viſcid, inflammatory Fevers <lb/>would have been the
          Conſequence, on taking <lb/>Cold, or the like; which now only produced <lb/>an aguiſh
          Diſorder. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Regular <hi rend="italic">vernal Intermittents</hi> have many Times <lb/>very
          ſalutary Effects, by breaking the <hi rend="italic">Lentor</hi>
          <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">morbid Coheſions</hi> of the Blood; as a Storm <pb n="22"/>
          <lb/>purges a thick foggy Atmoſphere. The in- <lb/>vigorating Power of the advancing
          Spring, and <lb/>the encreaſing genial Warmth and Dryneſs of <lb/>the Air, by rarefying
          and attenuating the hea- <lb/>vy, ſizy Humors, and opening the Pores, are <lb/>the Reaſons
          why vernal Agues go ſo eaſily off <lb/>at the Approach of Summer. And probably <lb/>the
          enlivening, attenuating Influences of the <lb/>growing Spring, actuating the Powers of Na-
          <lb/>ture to throw off the heavy, ropy <hi rend="italic">Colluvies</hi>, <lb/>that in ſome
          may be conſiderably amaſſed du- <lb/>ring a cold moiſt Winter, may be one Reaſon, <lb/>at
          leaſt, of the Frequency of Agues in the <lb/>Spring Seaſon. — It is certain, all Nature at
          that <lb/>Time of the Year undergoes a Kind of <hi rend="italic">Orgaſm</hi>; <lb/>even
          the torpid Vegetables regain freſh Life, <lb/>and their concreted Juices reſume new
          Motion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It appears from <note n="*" rend="size(0.5) italic" place="bottom">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* See Dr. <hi rend="roman">Langriſh</hi>'s Modern Theory, &amp;c. Chap. V. </p>
          </note> Experiments, that the <lb/>Blood in Quotidians is more denſe and tenaci- <lb/>ous
          than in Tertians, in Tertians than in Quar- <lb/>tans; ſo that in Quotidians, <hi
            rend="italic">cæteris paribus</hi>, it <lb/>comes neareſt an inflammatory State: And it
          is <lb/>commonly noted, that if the Fever, from a <lb/>regular Tertian, runs into a
          Semi-tertian, or <lb/>Quotidian, or greatly anticipates the Time of <lb/>the regular
          Paroxyſm; a remittent, or conti- <lb/>nual Fever is forthwith the Conſequence. — And
          <lb/>this is too often effected by a very hot Regi- <lb/>men, or a too haſty Uſe of the
          Bark. — Indeed <pb n="23"/>
          <lb/>we very frequently ſee that Quotidians, and <lb/>double Tertians, (which, by the bye,
          are of- <lb/>tentimes the ſame Thing) will not bear the <lb/>Bark at the Begining; till
          the ſaline Draughts, <lb/>proper diluting Attenuants, and, in ſome Caſes, <lb/>Bleeding,
          Purging, and Vomiting have been <lb/>made Uſe of. — In Truth, I never think it pru-
          <lb/>dent, in ſuch Kinds of Intermittents, to give <lb/>the Bark, in any Form, till after
          four or five <lb/>Paroxyſms at leaſt, and after having drawn more <lb/>or leſs Blood from
          Perſons pretty much inclin- <lb/>ed to the plethoric; — and this Method is more
          <lb/>eſpecially to be obſerved in vernal Agues. — I <lb/>muſt further note, that as
          nothing is more <lb/>effectual in curing Agues than well-timed Vo- <lb/>mits, and thoſe
          too repeated; (as Nature ſhews <lb/>us, by making this one of her conſtant Efforts <lb/>in
          the Paroxyſm) ſo previous Bleeding makes <lb/>them much more ſafe, in full ſanguine
          Habits, <lb/>eſpecially when given in the Paroxyſm; which <lb/>is frequently practiſed
          with great Succeſs. — Nor <lb/>is this a new Practice; for <hi rend="italic">Celſus</hi>
          adviſes, <hi rend="italic">cum <lb/>primum aliquis inhorruit, &amp; ex horrore incaluit,
            <lb/>dare ei oportet potui tepidam aquam ſubſalſam, &amp; <lb/>vomere eum cogere</hi>.
          Lib. iii. Cap. 12. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>We ſee then that ſome Kinds of Agues bor- <lb/>der too near on the inflammatory
          State, and re- <lb/>quire a cool Regimen, proper Dilution, and, <lb/>many Times, Bleeding
          to ſome Degree, as <lb/>well as other Evacuations. I have known it <pb n="24"/>
          <lb/>neceſſary to join Nitre to the Bark during the <lb/>whole Proceſs of Cure, and even
          ſometimes <lb/>to ſuſpend its Uſe for a Day or two, and give <lb/>Salt of Wormwood and
          Juice of Lemons with <lb/>Infuſion of Chamomile-flowers and <hi rend="italic"
          >Sevil</hi>-orange <lb/>Rind, or the like. — If an Intermittent runs into <lb/>an
          inflammatory continual Fever, Bleeding and <lb/>a gentle cool Purge will ſoon reduce it to
          its <lb/><hi rend="italic">Type</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But as ſome Intermittents are apt to run up <lb/>into an inflammatory Fever, far the
          greater <lb/>Number, eſpecially in the autumnal Seaſon, are <lb/>diſpoſed to ſink into low
          irregular Remittents, <lb/>putrid or ſlow nervous Fevers. It is not a very <lb/>rare Thing
          to find a Quotidian fall into a Ter- <lb/>tian, thence into a Quartan, and at laſt end in
          <lb/>a Dropſy; and this particularly in ſome Sea- <lb/>ſons and Places. This evidently
          ſhews that <lb/>the Fibres grow more and more enervate, and <lb/>the Blood very vapid and
          watery. — Even vernal <lb/>Tertians, which oftentimes cure themſelves in <lb/>a favourable
          Seaſon, prove many Times exceed- <lb/>ing obſtinate in wet, rainy Summers, and the
          <lb/>Patients are exceeding apt to relapſe on the <lb/>ſlighteſt Occaſions: This was
          particularly ob- <lb/>ſervable in the wet, cold Summers of 1734 and <lb/>1735 <note n="*"
            place="bottom" rend="size(0.5) italic">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Vid. Obſ. noſtr. de Aere &amp; Morbis Epidemic. Vol. I. </p>
          </note>. — In ſuch Caſes I have known the daily <lb/>Uſe of the Fleſh-bruſh, and frequent
          cold <pb n="25"/>
          <lb/>Bathing, of very great Uſe in preventing Re- <lb/>lapſes. — Perhaps it is the
          Winter-cold, bracing <lb/>up the Fibres, that commonly puts a Stop to <lb/>Agues in that
          Seaſon; for it hath been noted, <lb/>that they are often very ſtubborn in a warm
          <lb/>moiſt Winter. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Improper Evacuations by Bleeding and Purg- <lb/>ing, an unwholeſome, groſs, glutinous
          Diet, <lb/>vapid ropy Drinks, as ſtagnant heavy Water, <lb/>foul Beer, and the like,
          render theſe Agues ve- <lb/>ry <hi rend="italic">anomalous</hi>, obſtinate and dangerous,
          and <lb/>make them frequently degenerate into malig- <lb/>nant, putrid, or ſlow nervous
          Fevers; other- <lb/>wiſe they end in Dropſies, Jaundice, or univer- <lb/>ſal Obſtructions
          of the <hi rend="italic">Viſcera</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>, <lb/>and
          frequently in Diſeaſes of the <hi rend="italic">Genus nervo- <lb/>ſum</hi>. — In a Word
          whatever takes down the <lb/>Spring of the Fibres too much, and weakens <lb/>the <hi
            rend="italic">Craſis</hi> of the Blood, will be productive of <lb/>theſe Miſchiefs; and
          this eſpecially, when due <lb/>Perſpiration is frequently interrupted by cold <lb/>damp
          Air, Want of due Exerciſe, groſs heavy <lb/>ſlimy Diet, as Fiſh, Lettuce, Cucumbers, and
          <lb/>other watery inſipid Fruits, which are known <lb/>to ſuppreſs the Perſpiration
          greatly. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Theſe Obſervations then evidently ſhew the <lb/>Neceſſity of uſing a warm,
          invigorating, atte- <lb/>nuating Regimen in the Cure of Agues, which <lb/>affect Perſons
          of a lax Habit of Body, and a <lb/>poor thin Blood; in a particular Manner when <pb n="26"/>
          <lb/>a wet, foggy Atmoſphere prevails. — Under <lb/>ſuch Circumſtances the <hi
            rend="italic">Cortex</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Peru</hi>, however <lb/>good and
          carefully choſen, frequently proves <lb/>ineffectual, unleſs aſſiſted with proper Alexi-
          <lb/>pharmacs, as <hi rend="italic">Rad</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Serpentar</hi>. <hi
            rend="italic">Virgin</hi>. — <hi rend="italic">Contra- <lb/>yerv</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
            >Myrrh</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Camphire</hi>, &amp;c. — After four or five
          <lb/>Paroxyſms, warm Chalybeates may be added <lb/>with very great Succeſs. — But never be
          too <lb/>haſty in giving the <hi rend="italic">Bark</hi>, or Chalybeates, where <lb/>the
          Patient hath a <hi rend="italic">yellow Caſt of the Countenance</hi>, <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">a tenſe Abdomen</hi>, and a very coſtive Habit of <lb/>Body. — In which
          Caſe <hi rend="italic">mercurial</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ſaponaceous</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">Deobſtruents</hi> with <hi rend="italic">Rhubarb</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >Aloetics</hi>, <hi rend="italic">regenerate</hi>
          <lb/>or <hi rend="italic">ſoluble Tartar</hi>, ſhould be premiſed; nay they <lb/>may in
          ſome Caſes be very conveniently joined <lb/>with the <hi rend="italic">Bark</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>From the whole then of what hath been ſaid <lb/>on this Head, it appears that a
          regular Terti- <lb/>an is a <hi rend="italic">Medium</hi> between an inflammatory and a
          <lb/>ſlow nervous Fever; and that, on the one <lb/>Hand, the Conſtitution of the Solids
          and Fluids <lb/>may be ſo highly wrought up as to fire the <lb/>Blood into a continual
          Inflammatory; and that, <lb/>on the other, it may be ſo far depreſſed as to <lb/>bring on
          the low <hi rend="italic">Influent</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">ſlow nervous Fe-
            <lb/>ver</hi>. — And hence the Cauſe and Cure of ſuch <lb/>Fevers reſpectively ſeem to
          be obvious. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Now as every Kind of Fever is a Struggle of <lb/>Nature to relieve herſelf from
          ſomething op- <lb/>preſſive, we ſhould always favour her Endea- <pb n="27"/>
          <lb/>vours by the moſt proper Means that Reaſon <lb/>and Experience ſuggeſt. But we ſhould
          be <lb/>very cautious, at the Begining eſpecially, how <lb/>we proceed in ſpurring on, or
          bridling her <lb/>Efforts, till we have well conſidered the Na- <lb/>ture, Quantity, and
          Quality of the Diſeaſe, <lb/>and the Conſtitution of the Patient. In order <lb/>to this it
          will be highly neceſſary to make a di- <lb/>ligent Examination into theſe two Things; <hi
            rend="italic">1ſt, <lb/>the State of the Solids</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">2dly, that
            of the Fluids</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter">
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>CHAP. III. </head>
        <head rend="align-center italic space">
          <lb/>Of the State of the Solids. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">P</hi>Robably all that we call Firmneſs of Body, <lb/>and Strength
          of Conſtitution, is originally <lb/>owing to the <hi rend="italic">rudimental Stamina</hi>
          of our Bodies; <lb/>and on the ſtrong, or weak, Texture of them, <lb/>in a great Meaſure,
          depends our future proſ- <lb/>perous, or adverſe Health. — There was indeed <lb/>a
          determined Conſtitution and Strength of Fi- <lb/>bres deſigned by Nature, and any
          Deviation <lb/>from it may be called a Diſeaſe; which may a- <lb/>riſe from weakly
          Parents, Errors in Diet, Ex- <lb/>erciſe, and many other Things: And this De- <lb/>viation
          I would have heedfully attended to in <lb/>Practice. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A due Proportion of <hi rend="italic">Tenſity</hi>, conſiſtent with <lb/>a proper
          Degree of <hi rend="italic">Flexibility</hi>, conſtitutes the <pb n="28"/>
          <lb/>happy <hi rend="italic">Medium</hi> in which perfect Health conſiſts. <lb/>Too great
          a Degree of Rigidity tends to waſte <lb/>the nutritious Juices too ſuddenly, and ends in
          <lb/>a <hi rend="italic">Maraſmus</hi>; as too great a Laxity of the Veſ- <lb/>ſels makes
          them liable to be overloaded, and <lb/>brings on a <hi rend="italic">Leucophlegmatia</hi>,
          or Dropſy. The <lb/>former over-digeſts the animal Fluids, the lat- <lb/>ter doth not
          ſufficiently aſſimilate what is taken <lb/>in by Way of Nutriment. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A very ſtrong elaſtic Set of Veſſels act with <lb/>great Force on the contained
          Fluids, and pro- <lb/>duce much Friction, and of Courſe great Heat, <lb/>and withal a
          conſtant and large Diſſipation of <lb/>the more ſubtile and aqueous Parts, which ren-
          <lb/>der the Blood-Globules, in Proportion, more <lb/>numerous, more denſe and compact,
          and the <lb/>Humors in general more viſcid; as is evident <lb/>by the State of the Blood
          always obſervable in <lb/>ſtrong laborious People, which is ever of this <lb/>Kind. —
          Where this conſiderably overbears the <lb/>Standard of Nature, it becomes <hi
            rend="italic">conſtitutional <lb/>Diſeaſe</hi>, and cauſes a perpetual Fever, as it
          <lb/>were, and at long Run ends in <hi rend="italic">Atrophy</hi> and a <lb/>compleat <hi
            rend="italic">Maraſmus</hi>, if ſome violent inflamma- <lb/>tory Diſeaſe doth not ſnap
          them off much <lb/>ſooner; and to which they are exceedingly lia- <lb/>ble, and from
          which, on Account of the denſe <lb/>viſcous State of the Blood, the Rigidity and
          <lb/>Contraction, or <hi rend="italic">Stricture</hi> of the Veſſels, they <lb/>eſcape
          wiſh much greater Difficulty than others <pb n="29"/>
          <lb/>of ſofter Fibres, and a more weak, but fluxile, <lb/>Blood. There is no Advantage
          without an Al- <lb/>lay; the Roſe hath its Prickles; theſe Diſad- <lb/>vantages flow even
          from the higheſt Health and <lb/>Vigor: <hi rend="italic">Human Frailty!</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In ſuch Conſtitutions the Uſe of emollient <lb/>farinaceous Drinks and Diet are
          highly pro- <lb/>per, and frequent ſubtepid Bathing, eſpeci- <lb/>ally in very dry, and
          very cold Weather. <lb/>— Where Perſons of ſuch a Frame fall into <lb/>inflammatory
          Fevers, as Pleuriſies, Peripneu- <lb/>monies, or the like, I would always adviſe
          <lb/>great Plenty of tepid, watery, emollient Dilu- <lb/>ents to be perpetually ſipped; by
          which Means <lb/>the warm Vapor relaxes the Parts and Paſſages <lb/>of the Lungs, and
          promotes a freer Flow to <lb/>the Blood through them, and a more eaſy and <lb/>copious
          Expectoration; at the ſame Time that <lb/>the Blood is thus moſt effectually diluted. —
          <lb/>Withal Fomentations, emollient and diluting, <lb/>moderately warm (not too hot)
          ſhould be ap- <lb/>plied to the Feet, Legs, Hands, Arms, <hi rend="italic">Hy-
            <lb/>pochondria</hi> and Breaſt; which have oftentimes <lb/>a ſurpriſing good Effect,
          and are of infinitely <lb/>greater Advantage and Efficacy than ſome of <lb/>the <hi
            rend="italic">indigeſtible Traſh of the Shops</hi>, upon which ſo <lb/>much <hi
            rend="italic">Streſs</hi> was formerly laid. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I have known the prepoſterous Uſe of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">cold Bath</hi>, on a
            <hi rend="italic">ſtrigoſe</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">too rigid Habit</hi> of
          <lb/>Body, of exceeding great Detriment; for that <pb n="30"/>
          <lb/>even yet augments the <hi rend="italic">Corrugation</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
            >Tenſity</hi>. <lb/>— You may generally obſerve that moſt, who <lb/>uſe the cold Bath,
          grow ſomewhat thinner, <lb/>though more vigorous and active. — Some Years <lb/>ſince I was
          conſulted by a Gentleman of a thin <lb/>ſcraggy Habit of Body, but of much natural
          <lb/>Vivacity of Spirit, and one that conſtantly uſed <lb/>much Exerciſe, and had long
          accuſtomed him- <lb/>ſelf to cold Bathing in the Sea very frequently, <lb/>even ſometimes
          in very cold Weather: He <lb/>waſted daily in his Fleſh, and at length became <lb/>weak
          and very low-ſpirited. — I judged, that <lb/>by this Method the fibrous Syſtem was over-
          <lb/>braced, and that too much of the finer <hi rend="italic">Lymph</hi>, <lb/>and even of
          the <hi rend="italic">Liquidum nervoſum</hi>, was forced <lb/>off by the Pores, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> For he all this while <lb/>uſed a ſufficient Quantity of
          Food, and had no <lb/>extraordinary ſenſible Evacuation. — I put him <lb/>on a ſoft,
          relaxing, nouriſhing Diet, forbad <lb/>him the Uſe of the Cold-Bath, and at laſt ſent
          <lb/>him to uſe the Waters at the <hi rend="italic">Bath</hi>: — The E- <lb/>vent was,
          that he ſoon recovered much better <lb/>Health, Spirits and Fleſh. Nothing on the
          <lb/>contrary more effectually ſtrengthens weak, <lb/>lax Fibres than cold Bathing: By
          this weak, <lb/>flabby, rickety Children are ſoon invigorated, <lb/>as it were to a
          Miracle. — Indeed in the Times <lb/>of Popery and Ignorance, when the Prieſts were
          <lb/>Knaves, and the People Fools, many a <hi rend="italic">Well</hi>
          <lb/>was ſanctified for nothing but pure <hi rend="italic">cold Water</hi>, <pb n="31"/>
          <lb/>the Virtues of which the <hi rend="italic">Miracle-mongers</hi> whol- <lb/>ly
          attributed to a <hi rend="italic">Saint</hi> of their own making. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Doctrine of the ancient <hi rend="italic">Methodiſts</hi>, with <lb/>Reſpect to
          the <hi rend="italic">Strictum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Laxum</hi>, if rational- <lb/>ly
          purſued, might be of great Service in the <lb/>Practice of Phyſic; though they indeed fre-
          <lb/>quently confounded them both in Theory and <lb/>Practice. But <hi rend="italic"
            >Boerhaave</hi> hath made many ra- <lb/>tional and valuable Obſervations on the Diſ-
          <lb/>eaſes of too tenſe, and too lax Fibres, which <lb/>are of exceeding great Uſe in
          Practice. — There <lb/>ſeems to be another <hi rend="italic">Species of Fibres</hi> not
          taken <lb/>Notice of, which may be called the <hi rend="italic">tender</hi>, or <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">delicate Conſtitution of the Solids</hi>, which is moſt <lb/>readily and
          highly affected with Pleaſure, or <lb/>Pain; but in which the <hi rend="italic"
            >Stamina</hi> are ſo ſlender, <lb/>that a very ſlight Accident breaks them. This <lb/>is
          often obſerved in thin, fair Perſons, of a ve- <lb/>ry delicate Frame, but exceedingly
          lively; in <lb/>whom the <hi rend="italic">Spirit</hi> is willing, though the <hi
            rend="italic">Fleſh</hi> is <lb/>weak: Such very often fall into a <hi rend="italic"
            >Hæmoptoe</hi>, <lb/>or other <hi rend="italic">Hemorrhages</hi>, Colliquations, and a
          <lb/>pulmonary <hi rend="italic">Phthiſis</hi>, and thence become what <lb/>is peculiarly
          called Conſumptive. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>We have taken a ſhort View of the ill Ef- <lb/>fects of a too great <hi rend="italic"
            >Stricture</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Tenſion</hi> of the <lb/>Solids; let us next
          curſorily ſee what Diſadvan- <lb/>tages ariſe from their too great Laxity. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Weak Veſſels do not ſufficiently act on the <lb/>contained Fluids, they do not
          ſufficiently <hi rend="italic">com- <pb n="32"/>
            <lb/>minute</hi>, <hi rend="italic">round off</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
            >aſſimilate</hi> the chylous Par- <lb/>ticles: — Indeed the Chyle itſelf, where the Or-
          <lb/>gans of Digeſtion are weak, is never well pre- <lb/>pared. — Where the Veſſels have a
          due Tone, <lb/>and act with Vigor on the nutritious Juices <lb/>which they receive from
          the Stomach, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> no <lb/>chylous irregularly formed Particles
          are to be <lb/>found in the Blood after a few Hours from the <lb/>Repaſt; but, in weakly
            <hi rend="italic">leucophlegmatic</hi> People, <lb/>they are never, or not till after a
          very long <lb/>Time, reduced into Blood-globules, and a pro- <lb/>per <hi rend="italic"
            >Serum</hi>. — Beſides in theſe lax Habits the <lb/>Blood itſelf is not ſufficiently
          actuated, and dri- <lb/>ven on with Force enough to keep a due vital <lb/>Warmth, nor to
          work up the Salts and Sul- <lb/>phurs, or Oils, to ſuch a juſt Degree of <hi rend="italic"
            >Tenuity</hi>, <lb/>as may fit them to ſerve the Purpoſes of animal <lb/>Nature; nor are
          the red Globules of the Blood <lb/>(the great Principle of Life and Heat) duly
          <lb/>compacted, and moulded into a ſufficient <lb/>Roundneſs and Firmneſs. — Hence
          irregular <lb/>Concretions in the Veſſels, a <hi rend="italic">Lentor</hi>, or <hi
            rend="italic">Ropi- <lb/>neſs</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">Lymph</hi>, few animal Spi- <lb/>rits, and all the Secretions weak and
          imper- <lb/>fect. — From the whole follow <hi rend="italic">Cachexy</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">leuco- <lb/>phlegmatic</hi> and dropſical Diſorders, irregular
          <lb/>intermittent and remittent Fevers, or thoſe of <lb/>the ſlow nervous Kind; the Humors
          running <lb/>into a Kind of Putreſcence for Want of due Mo- <lb/>tion and Circulation, and
          ſtagnating in the <hi rend="italic">ul- <pb n="33"/>
            <lb/>tima Vaſcula</hi>, on Account of the Obſtructions <lb/>continually forming from the
          Want of a due <lb/>Action of the Veſſels, which do not ſufficiently <lb/>agitate,
          comminute and protrude their Con- <lb/>tents. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Now all Humors of the Body, that ſtagnate, <lb/>ſoon begin to corrupt and grow
          acrimonious; <lb/>and that too many Times to ſuch a Degree as <lb/>to bring on Fevers of
          the worſt Kind: For <lb/>though the Circulation may be very languid, <lb/>from the
          Weakneſs of the contracting propel- <lb/>ling Veſſels, yet it is ſufficient to cauſe ſome
          <lb/>Degree of feveriſh Heat from the ſtimulating <lb/>Acrimony, and at laſt a general
          Putrefaction; <lb/>witneſs the <hi rend="italic">chlorotic Fevers</hi>, which very often
          <lb/>prove of exceeding dangerous Conſequence. — <lb/>Cold hydropic Tumors of the Legs
          frequently <lb/>end in a Kind of Eryſipelas and Gangrene. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A due Conſideration therefore of the State <lb/>of the Solids is a Matter of high
          Importance to <lb/>Phyſicians, not only in chronic, but alſo in <lb/>acute Diſeaſes; for
          they are generally the pri- <lb/>mary efficient Cauſes of the particular States of
          <lb/>the Fluids. For Inſtance, we may naturally <lb/>conclude that a Man of a robuſt
          Conſtitution, <lb/>ſtrong, rigid Fibres, and uſed to much Exer- <lb/>ciſe, hath a denſe
          rich Blood, inclining to ſuch <lb/>a Degree of Viſcidity, as will bring on Inflam-
          <lb/>mations on the Acceſſion of a feveriſh Diſorder; <lb/>and, of Courſe, that timely
          Bleeding is the <pb n="34"/>
          <lb/>proper Way to prevent it: On the contrary, that <lb/>a weak, lax, flabby Conſtitution
          hath a poor, <lb/>thin, watery Blood, and cannot bear Bleeding <lb/>well, nor large
          Evacuations. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A diligent Enquiry of this Nature is of vaſt <lb/>Concern in the Begining of acute
          Diſeaſes, par- <lb/>ticularly in the Small-pox, and other eruptive <lb/>Fevers; ſo as to
          determine one to bleed, or <lb/>not to bleed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>For Inſtance, where a ſtrong Man, with a <lb/>ſtrong Pulſe, is ſeized with violent
          Symptoms <lb/>of the Small-pox, it would be unpardonable <lb/>not to bleed before the
          Eruption; for we cannot <lb/>but ſuppoſe the inflammatory Fever muſt run <lb/>high in ſuch
          a Conſtitution; but it would be <lb/>great Raſhneſs to bleed Perſons of a weak, lax
          <lb/>Habit, unleſs ſome very urgent Symptom de- <lb/>manded it. — Yet how little is this
          regarded in <lb/>the vulgar Practice? For ſome bleed, and vo- <lb/>mit, of Courſe, upon
          the leaſt Appearance of <lb/>an Attack of the Small-pox; whereas others <lb/>are ſo
          fearful of weakening their Patients, that <lb/>they ſuffer them to die of the
          Inflammation, <lb/>even abſtracted from the Virulence of the Diſ- <lb/>eaſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If a Phyſician hath a previous Knowledge of <lb/>the Patient, he can be at no great
          Loſs in judg- <lb/>ing of his Conſtitution; and therefore <hi rend="italic">Celſus</hi>
          <lb/>rightly pronounces, <hi rend="italic">cum par ſcientia ſit utiliorem <pb n="35"/>
            <lb/>tamen medicum eſſe amicum quam extraneum</hi>
          <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.5) italic">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Præfat. ſub finem. </p>
          </note>. <lb/>When that is not the Caſe, hard firm Fleſh, <lb/>dry Skin, great Heat,
          Thirſt, and Colour, hot <lb/>Breath and violent Pains, with a ſtrong, tenſe, <lb/>quick
          Pulſe, are pretty evident Symptoms of <lb/>ſtrong, very elaſtic Fibres, and of an ardent
          or <lb/>inflammatory Fever. — A weak, quick, ſoft <lb/>Pulſe, no great Heat, or Colour,
          little Thirſt, <lb/>pale Urine, a ſoft Fleſh and Skin, clammy, <lb/>partial, irregular,
          cold, or profuſe Sweats, with <lb/>Heavineſs and Anxiety, rather than ſevere <lb/>Pains,
          and a moiſt, though perhaps a white <lb/>coated, or foul Tongue, denote the contrary. —
          <lb/>But in Truth theſe Things are rather to be <lb/>learned from Experience, than taught
          by Pre- <lb/>cept: — Therefore I ſhall ſay no more on this <lb/>Head. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter">
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>CHAP. IV. </head>
        <head rend="align-center italic">
          <lb/>Of the State of the <hi rend="sc">Fluids</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE State of the Fluids ſhould next be <lb/>conſidered, which,
          in a great Meaſure, <lb/>depends, as was ſaid before, on the Condition <lb/>of the Solids. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>There is then, <hi rend="italic">1ſt</hi>, a State of the Blood, in <lb/>which the
          Humors are too denſe and viſcous, <lb/>in which the Blood-globules are in too great <pb
            n="36"/>
          <lb/>Quantity, and too cloſely compacted or con- <lb/>denſed, in which the ſerous Globules
          are ſo <lb/>likewiſe: — In a Word, in which the whole <lb/>Maſs of the Fluids is too
          glutinous, and too <lb/>apt to concrete into a ſolid Form. — Perſons of <lb/>vigorous
          Conſtitutions, of ſtrong Fibres, that <lb/>uſe much Exerciſe, and a full Diet, are pecu-
          <lb/>liarly ſubject to this State. — Now when the <lb/>Blood-globules are very denſe, and
          in great <lb/>Quantity, and the Veſſels very ſtrong and <lb/>elaſtic, a great <hi
            rend="italic">Momentum of Motion</hi> muſt be <lb/>produced in the circulating Fluids,
          and of <lb/>Courſe great Friction, and much Heat, which <lb/>both diſſipates the more
          fluid Parts of the Blood, <lb/>and encreaſes its Viſcoſity; ſo that the Reſidue
          <lb/>becomes very glutinous, and leſs fit to paſs the <lb/>extreme Branches of the
          capillary Arteries; <lb/>and hence Obſtructions, hence Inflammations. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Beſides great Heat tends to coagulate the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>; a Heat,
          not much above the common <lb/>Heat in an ardent Fever, will turn the <hi rend="italic"
            >Serum</hi> of <lb/>the Blood into a Jelly, as is found by Expe- <lb/>rience: — Hence,
          when Blood is drawn off in <lb/>high inflammatory Fevers, it appears covered <lb/>over
          with a thick glutinous Coat, or <hi rend="italic">Buff</hi>, as it <lb/>is called; I have
          ſeen it in ſome ſevere pleu- <lb/>ritic and rheumatic Diſorders near an Inch <lb/>thick. —
          That it is thus formed by the febrile <lb/>Heat, is manifeſt; for at the firſt Bleeding,
          at <lb/>the very Begining of the Fever, it ſhall often <pb n="37"/>
          <lb/>appear appear pretty florid, tho' very denſe; whereas <lb/>on the ſecond, third, or
          fourth Bleeding, when <lb/>the Heat hath had a longer Continuance, and <lb/>been encreaſed
          to a greater Degree, it becomes <lb/>exceeding ſizy, and covered over with a very
          <lb/>thick Buff: — And indeed, in general, the <lb/>ſtronger the Fever, and the Perſon
          from whom <lb/>it is drawn, ſo much the more thick and tena- <lb/>cious. — And this in a
          particular Manner hap- <lb/>pens in Fevers attended with violent Pain, as <lb/>Pleuriſies,
          Rheumatiſms, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c:</hi> — For the Pain <lb/>being a <hi rend="italic"
            >Stimulus</hi>, which greatly encreafes <lb/>the Motion, Friction, and Heat, it <hi
            rend="italic">incraſſates the <lb/>Serum</hi> in Proportion to its Vehemence. — And
          <lb/>the inflammatory <hi rend="italic">Size</hi> alſo ſticking in the ex- <lb/>treamly
          ſmall Veſſels of the Membranes, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
          <lb/>over-diſtends them, and produces further In- <lb/>flammations and Pains; ſo that they
          mutually <lb/>encreaſe one the other. Tho' this denſe State <lb/>of Blood, in Health, is
          attended with great <lb/>bodily Strength, a ſtrong firm Pulſe, and much <lb/>natural Heat;
          yet, on the Acceſs of a Fever, <lb/>it produces very violent Symptoms, quickly <lb/>fatal,
          unleſs prevented by timely Bleeding, <lb/>cooling, diluting, emollient Drinks and Medi-
          <lb/>cines. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But further, an Over-fulneſs of even good <lb/>Blood is a Degree of Diſeaſe, and
          therefore <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hippocrates</hi>
          <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5) italic">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Aphirſm 3. Sect. i. </p>
          </note> pronounces the <hi rend="italic">athletic</hi> GREEK <pb n="38"/>
          <lb/>dangerous, and <hi rend="italic">Celſus</hi> elegantly ſays from him, <lb/>that
          Perſons of ſuch a Habit <hi rend="italic">ſuſpecta habere <lb/>bona ſua debent</hi>
          <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.5) italic">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Lib. II. Cap. 2. </p>
          </note>. — Such a <hi rend="italic">Plethora</hi> not only <lb/>over-diſtends the
          ſanguineous Arteries, but alſo <lb/>too much dilates the Orifices of the ſerous and
          <lb/>lymphatic Arteries; by which, on the ſlighteſt <lb/>Occaſions, the Blood-globules are
          forced into <lb/>them, and form Obſtructions <hi rend="italic">errore loci</hi>, as
          <lb/>it is called: Whence Inflammations and Rup- <lb/>tures of the Veſſels frequently
          follow, particu- <lb/>larly in the Brain and Lungs. — Here nothing <lb/>will relieve equal
          to Blood-letting, which (if <lb/>not too immoderate) is ſo far from weakening, <lb/>that
          it ſtrengthens the Patient, by reſtoring a <lb/>due <hi rend="italic">Æquilibrium</hi>
          between the Solids and Fluids: <lb/>The keeping up of which however is a Matter <lb/>of
          great Nicety in ſome Caſes and Conſtitu- <lb/>tions; tho', in general, it admits of a
          conſi- <lb/>derable <hi rend="italic">Latitude</hi>, even conſiſtent with Health.
          <lb/>Some delicate, florid, plethoric People ſuffer <lb/>immediately from a very ſmall
          Degree of over, <lb/>or under, Living; and I have known ſome <lb/>Men of this
          Conſtitution, that have had as re- <lb/>gular a <hi rend="italic">menſtrual
          Diſcharge</hi>, by ſome Kind of <lb/>Hæmorrhage, as the more delicate Sex. — The <lb/>beſt
          bred, and moſt accurately fed, <hi rend="italic">Cock</hi>, will <lb/>not hold his <hi
            rend="italic">athletic State</hi> above twenty-four <lb/>Hours <note n="†"
            place="bottom" rend="size(0.5) italic">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>† See Dr. <hi rend="roman">Bryan Robinſon</hi> on <lb/>the Food and Diſcharges of
              human Bodies, <hi rend="roman">p. 119</hi>. </p>
          </note>, and dwindles from it ſurpriſingly <pb n="39"/>
          <lb/>ſoon — <q><hi rend="italic">Quia non ultra progredi poteſt, retro, quaſi <lb/>ruinâ
              quâdam, revolvitur</hi>
          </q>, as Celſus <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.5) italic">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Lib. II. Cap. 2. </p>
          </note> ſays of a <lb/>plethoric Man. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>There is, <hi rend="italic">2dly</hi>, a Conſtitution, or Craſis of <lb/>the Blood,
          quite oppoſite to the former, in <lb/>which there are too few Blood-globules, and
          <lb/>thoſe too looſely compacted; and in which <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi> is
          too watery and vapid, and ſome- <lb/>times of a ropy ſlimy Nature. From this <lb/>weak
          pituitous Blood all the Secretions are <lb/>imperfect, and not ſufficiently participant of
          an <lb/>animal Nature; the <hi rend="italic">Bile inert</hi>, the animal Spi- <lb/>rits
          flat and deficient, the <hi rend="italic">Saliva</hi> a mere <hi rend="italic">inſipid
            <lb/>Mucus</hi>, and ſo on. — Hence univerſal Indige- <lb/>ſtion, Weakneſs, Coldneſs,
          Paleneſs, <hi rend="italic">Caco- <lb/>chymy</hi>, Dropſy, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
          — In a Word, ſuch a ſlow <lb/>Motion of the Humors, that at length, for <lb/>Want of a due
          Circulation, they run into mor- <lb/>bid Concretions obſtructing the Veſſels in ſome
          <lb/>Places, and ſtagnating in others, where they <lb/>fall into ſpontaneous Corruption,
          productive at <lb/>laſt of ſuch a Degree of Acrimony, as to end <lb/>frequently in Fevers
          of a very malign Nature, <lb/>and dangerous Conſequence: And this the <lb/>more ſo, as the
          Veſſels, in ſuch a miſerable <lb/>Conſtitution, have greatly loſt their Elaſticity,
          <lb/>and the Blood its moſt vital Principles: — So <lb/>that, in the Event, either the <hi
            rend="italic">ſlimy Lentor</hi> ſtag- <lb/>nates up to the Heart, or the corrupted Hu-
            <pb n="40"/>
          <lb/>mors corrode and deſtroy the moſt delicate <lb/>and eſſential Parts of the animal
          Fabric, parti- <lb/>cularly the <hi rend="italic">Compages</hi> of the Brain, where the
          <lb/>Humors naturally move exceeding ſlow, and <lb/>the Veſſels are of the moſt tender
          Structure. — <lb/>Thus as too rapid a Circulation often burſts <lb/>the minute Veſſels; ſo
          the Humors, moving <lb/>too ſlowly, ſtagnate, corrupt, and at length <lb/>corrode them. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Theſe two different States of the Fluids may <lb/>not improperly be called
          conſtitutional, as they <lb/>naturally follow the reſpective State of the So- <lb/>lids;
          ſo as that a ſtrong rich Blood always at- <lb/>tends a ſtrong elaſtic Set of Veſſels, and
          a <lb/>weak watery Blood a relaxed Habit of Body: <lb/>where either conſiderably deviates
          from the <lb/>Standard of Nature, it becomes a real Diſor- <lb/>der, and is to be duly
          regarded in whatever <lb/>concurring Diſeaſe happens <note n="*" place="bottom"
            rend="size(0.5) italic">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Ardent and inflammatory Fevers are naturally the Effect <lb/>of over-elaſtic
              and rigid Fibres, and a very denſe viſcid <lb/>Blood; as the low and ſlow nervous Kind
              are of a too lax <lb/>State of Veſſels, and a weak and thin Blood. — But there are
              <lb/>ſeveral Diſeaſes, eſpecially thoſe ariſing from Contagion, which <lb/>are common
              to both. </p>
          </note>. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="41"/>
      <div type="chapter">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>CHAP. V. </head>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Of the diſſolved and putrid State of the <lb/><hi rend="sc">Blood</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">B</hi>UT, beſides theſe, there is moreover a <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >third State of Blood</hi>, of more dangerous <lb/>Conſequence than either; I mean a
          State of it, <lb/>that more immediately tends to <hi rend="italic">Diſſolution</hi> and
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Putrefaction</hi>: — This is evidently the Caſe in <lb/>ſome <hi
            rend="italic">Scorbutics</hi>, (as they are called) where, <lb/>without any
          conſiderable, antecedent, ſenſible <lb/>Diſorder (more than perhaps a Kind of Laſſi-
          <lb/>tude and Langour) Perſons have, on a ſud- <lb/>den, an Eruption of violet-coloured,
          livid, or <lb/>even black and blue Spots all over their Body, <lb/>and forthwith fall into
          profuſe, and ſometimes <lb/>dangerous, and even fatal <hi rend="italic">Hæmorrhages</hi>,
          when <lb/>they have ſcarce thought themſelves, or been <lb/>thought by others, to be under
          any Manner of <lb/>Diſorder. — Abundance of Inſtances of this Kind <lb/>happen: I have
          ſeen a great many both in <lb/>Children and grown Perſons, and frequently <lb/>foretold
          the enſuing Hæmorrhage. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Where <hi rend="italic">Women</hi> have ſuch Eruptions, or black <lb/>or blue <hi
            rend="italic">Vibices</hi>, or large irregular Spots like <lb/>Bruiſes, they are always
          ſubject to a vaſt Over- <lb/>flow of the <hi rend="italic">Catamenia</hi>, if not to other
          profuſe <lb/>Hæmorrhages. — Nay when Perſons of either <lb/>Sex are affected with theſe
          Appearances, they <pb n="42"/>
          <lb/>are apt to bleed exceſſively from the ſlighteſt <lb/>Wound, and very often without
          any, from the <lb/>Gums, Noſe, Guts, or urinary Paſſages. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Blood of ſuch Perſons, when it hath <lb/>been drawn off, in order to prevent the
          further <lb/>Progreſs of the Hæmorrhage, as was imagin- <lb/>ed, (which by the Way is very
          improper, un- <lb/>leſs there are very manifeſt Signs of a <hi rend="italic">Ple-
            <lb/>thora</hi>) always appears a <hi rend="italic">mere Gore</hi> as it were, <lb/>not
          ſeparating into <hi rend="italic">Craſſamentum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Serum</hi>, as
          <lb/>uſual, but remaining in an uniform half-coagu- <lb/>lated Maſs, generally of a livid,
          or darker Co- <lb/>lour than uſual, tho' ſometimes it continues <lb/>long very florid; but
          it always putrefies very <lb/>ſoon. — It is even obſervable, that the <hi rend="italic"
            >Breath</hi>
          <lb/>of ſuch People moſt commonly ſtinks much <lb/>before the Eruption, and their <hi
            rend="italic">Urine</hi> frequently <lb/>ſmells very rank; evident Signs of the begin-
          <lb/>ing <hi rend="italic">Putridity</hi> of the Humors; which, growing <lb/>more and more
          acrimonious, at length erode <lb/>the Veſſels. For theſe Kinds of Hæmorrhages <lb/>often
          happen to Perſons, that have not the <lb/>leaſt Sign of a <hi rend="italic">Plethora</hi>,
          no full, no very quick <lb/>Pulſe, little or nothing of a feveriſh Habit, <lb/>nor under
          the Uſe of violent Exerciſe; ſo that <lb/>they happen from the Corroſion, not the <hi
            rend="italic">Rup- <lb/>ture</hi>, of the Veſſels broke open by too great a
          <lb/>Quantity and Velocity of the Blood. — In ſome <lb/>very tender and delicate
          Conſtitutions indeed, <lb/>a very ſmall Effort will ſometimes burſt their <pb n="43"/>
          <lb/>fine thin Veſſels, as is obſervable in ſome, who <lb/>are ſubject; to a <hi
            rend="italic">Hæmoptoe</hi>, or Bleeding at the <lb/>Noſe from every ſmall Accident; but
          theſe <lb/>Hæmorrhages are ſeldom attended, or pre- <lb/>ceded, with livid, or
          violet-coloured Erupti- <lb/>ons, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> — In theſe Caſes Drawing
          of ſmall <lb/>Quantities of Blood is proper, to abate the too <lb/>great <hi rend="italic"
            >Impetus</hi> on the tender Veſſels, even tho' <lb/>there may be no apparent <hi
            rend="italic">Plethora</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Tho', I am perſuaded, the above-mention- <lb/>ed Hæmorrhages moſt commonly ariſe from
          <lb/>an <hi rend="italic">acrimonious State of the Humors</hi>, which <lb/>breaks the <hi
            rend="italic">Craſis of the Blood</hi>, and corrodes <lb/>the Extremities of the
          capillary Arteries; <lb/>yet they ſometimes alſo happen from a too <lb/>looſe Contexture
          of the Blood-globules, not <lb/>ſufficiently compacted by the Action of the <lb/>Heart,
          Arteries, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>; for Want of which they <lb/>become <hi
            rend="italic">oblate Spheroids</hi>, or irregularly formed <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Moleculæ</hi>, inſtead of <hi rend="italic">regular Spheres</hi>, and of <lb/>Courſe of
          a greater Diameter, and a leſs firm <lb/>i than natural. — But it appears from
          <lb/>microſcopical Obſervations (eſpecially thoſe <lb/>made with the <hi rend="italic"
            >Solar Microſcope</hi>) that the Blood- <lb/>globules, in paſſing thro' the minuteſt
          Rami- <lb/>fications of the ſanguineous Arteries, change <lb/>their globular, into a very
          oblong Figure fre- <lb/>quently, in order to paſs thro' theſe exceeding <lb/>ſmall
          Veſſels. — And it is eaſy to conceive how <lb/>thoſe looſely cohering Globules may be
          broken <pb n="44"/>
          <lb/>in their Paſſage, as the enlarged Bulk makes <lb/>their <hi rend="italic"
            >Tranſit</hi> more difficult. — Now as theſe <lb/>broken Parts are of much leſs Diameter
          than <lb/>the original Globules, they may readily enter, <lb/>and even paſs thro' ſome of
          the excretory <lb/>Ducts, and tranſude <hi rend="italic">per Diapedeſin</hi>, as the An-
          <lb/>cients called it. — That this is ſo in Fact ſeems <lb/>to appear from the bloody
          Urine, Stools, and <lb/>other Hæmorrhages, which ſometimes happen <lb/>without any Manner
          of Pain, Violence of Mo- <lb/>tion, or the leaſt Suſpicion of the Rupture of <lb/>any
          Veſſels: — Nay, I have more than once or <lb/>twice ſeen in malignant Fevers, and that too
          <lb/>where the Motion of the Blood was far from <lb/>being very rapid, a Kind of <note
            n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.5) italic">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Dr. <hi rend="roman">Hodges</hi>, of the Plague, obſerved purple Sweats in it,
              <lb/>and ſome like Blood. </p>
          </note> bloody Sweat <lb/>from the <hi rend="italic">Axillæ</hi>, tinging the Linnen
          almoſt of <lb/>a <hi rend="italic">Burgundy</hi> Wine Colour. — And it is obſerva-
          <lb/>ble, that when this Sort of Hæmorrhages <lb/>happens from the Noſe, the Matter is a
          thin <lb/><hi rend="italic">bloody Ichor</hi>, not concreting, as Blood com- <lb/>monly
          doth from the Noſe of Perſons in Health, <lb/>or in an inflammatory Fever, which is gene-
          <lb/>rally very thick, ſhining and florid: — Some <lb/><hi rend="italic">chlorotic
            Girls</hi> are vaſtly apt to bleed from the <lb/>Noſe, and yet their Blood doth but juſt
          colour <lb/>a linnen Cloth. — The <hi rend="italic">Petechiæ</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >Vibices</hi>, or livid <lb/><hi rend="italic">Stigmata</hi>, that very often attend
          theſe Hæmor- <lb/>rhages, ſhew that the Blood-globules are diſ- <pb n="45"/>
          <lb/>ſolved, or broken down, and enter into the <lb/>ſerous Arteries, <hi rend="italic"
            >Vaſa exhalantia</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c</hi>; where <lb/>ſticking faſt they form
          theſe Appearances. — <lb/>And I have particularly noted, in ſome putrid, <lb/>malignant
          Fevers, a Kind of yellow, or rather <lb/>dim <hi rend="italic">Petechiæ</hi>
          <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.5) italic">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Vid. Obſ. noſtr. de Aere &amp; Morb. Epidem. Vol. I. Ann. <lb/>1735, Mart.
              &amp; Aprili; &amp; Vol. II. Anno 1740, Junio. </p>
          </note>, vaſtly numerous, and of not <lb/>leſs fatal Omen than the others: Here the
          <lb/>Blood-globules were broken into ſuch ſmall <lb/>Particles, as to have quite loſt
          their original <lb/>Colour when combined. Perhaps the fuligi- <lb/>nous Sweats, and
          dark-coloured, or black Urine <lb/>with a livid Sediment, which ſometimes hap- <lb/>pen in
          Fevers of the malignant Kind, ariſe <lb/>from a broken corrupted State of the Blood-
          <lb/>globules: I have ſeen ſeveral Times the Urine <lb/>rendered almoſt quite black,
          depoſiting an im- <lb/>menſe Quantity of Matter nearly of the Co- <lb/>lour of <hi
            rend="italic">Coffee-grounds</hi>. — And we are ſometimes <lb/>ſurpriſed to ſee the Face
          and Hands of the <lb/>Sick grow <hi rend="italic">dirty</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
            >ſooty</hi> as it were, tho' all <lb/>imaginable Care was taken to keep them clean. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Beſides there are ſome Things that ſeem to <lb/>deſtroy the <hi rend="italic"
            >Copula</hi> of the Blood-globules, and <lb/>greatly promote the <hi rend="italic"
            >Seceſſion</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">ſix ſerous <lb/>Globules</hi>, that compoſe
          them, one from ano- <lb/>ther; particularly <hi rend="italic">Laurel-water</hi>, which
          makes <lb/>the Craſſamentum vaſtly leſs denſe, and exceed- <pb n="46"/>
          <lb/>ingly more ſoft and tender than natural, and <lb/>turns the Serum red, or of the
          Colour of <hi rend="italic">Bur- <lb/>gundy</hi> Wine, as appears from the curious Ex-
          <lb/>periments <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.5) italic">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Dr. <hi rend="roman">Mead</hi> of Poiſons, 3d Edit. p. 270. </p>
          </note>of Dr. <hi rend="italic">Nicholls</hi> and Dr. <hi rend="italic">Langriſh</hi>
          <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5) italic" n="†">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>† See his Experiments on Brutes. </p>
          </note>. <lb/>— The Bite of the Serpent <hi rend="italic">Hæmorrhous</hi>
          <note n="‖" rend="size(0.5) italic" place="bottom">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>‖ See <hi rend="roman">Lucan</hi>, <hi rend="roman">Dioſcorid.</hi>
              <hi rend="roman">Nicander</hi> in <hi rend="roman">Theriacis</hi>, &amp;c. <lb/>Dr.
                <hi rend="roman">Mead</hi> of Poiſons. </p>
          </note> cauſes <lb/>ſuch a Diſſolution of the Blood, that it breaks <lb/>forth from all
          Parts of the Body, even the <lb/>very <hi rend="italic">Pores</hi>, and kills by an <hi
            rend="italic">univerſal Hæmor- <lb/>rhage</hi>. Poſſibly <hi rend="italic">profuſe
            Sweat</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Diarrhæa</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Dia- <lb/>betes</hi>, and
          ſpontaneous Salivations, may ariſe <lb/>from a Kind of Diſſolution of the ſerous Glo-
          <lb/>bules. — A long and large Uſe of <hi rend="italic">Mercury</hi> will <lb/>turn the
          whole Maſs of Blood into a mere wa- <lb/>tery <hi rend="italic">Colluvies</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="79"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
