<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Ayscough: A short account of the nature and use of spectacles.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>James Ayscough</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">a short account of the nature and use of spectacles. In which is
              recommended, A Kind of Glass for Spectacles, preferable to any hitherto made use of
              for that Purpose. By James Ayscough,Optician, At the Great Golden Spectacles in
              Ludgate-Street, London. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T27156</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T27156"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed in the year, MDCCL.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1750</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="15"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library"/>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3309401201</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K032515.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: method"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front> </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_2" n="3"/>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>Two horizontal lines, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>A <lb/><hi rend="sc size(1.25)">Short Account</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">of the</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(1.25)">Nature and Uſe of Spectacles</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">M</hi>Y Deſign in the following Tract is <lb/>to explain the Structure
        of the Eye, <lb/>and the Nature of Viſion, ſo far as <lb/>is neceſſary to underſtand the Uſe
        and Ad- <lb/>vantage of Spectacles. The Method of <lb/>chuſing the beſt Sort of Glaſſes, and
        ſuch as <lb/>are ſuitable to the different Defects of the <lb/>Eye in different Perſons; and
        to recommend <lb/>a Kind of Glaſs, for this Purpoſe, much pre- <lb/>ferable to any that has
        been hitherto made <lb/>uſe of. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Nature of Viſion, and Uſe of Spec- <lb/>tacles, will be beſt explain'd, by the com-
        <lb/>mon Experiment of the dark Room, or as <lb/>it is uſually called the <hi rend="italic"
          >Camera Obſcura</hi>, which <lb/>is this. In any Room that is pretty much <lb/>darken'd,
        let an Hole be made in the Win- <pb xml:id="page_3" n="4"/>
        <lb/>dow-Shutter, in which Hole place a convex <lb/>Lens, or round globular Glaſs; then
        hold- <lb/>ing a Sheet of white Paper within the <lb/>Room, at a proper Diſtance from the
        Hole, <lb/>(which you will find by Tryals) you will <lb/>ſee on the Paper the Pictures of
        all Objects <lb/>before the Hole, both in their juſt Propor- <lb/>tions, and in their proper
        Colours, only <lb/>they will be upſide down. If the Paper remain <lb/>in the ſame Place, and
        in the Room of the <lb/>aforeſaid convex Glaſs, or Lens, one that <lb/>is flatter be uſed,
        the Picture upon the white <lb/>Paper will then be confuſed; but by placing <lb/>a convex
        Spectacle-Glaſs before the Lens of <lb/>a due Convexity, the Image on the Paper <lb/>will
        again be render'd diſtinct. If a more con- <lb/>vex Lens than the firſt be uſed, the Image
        on <lb/>the Paper will again be confus'd, but may <lb/>be render'd diſtinct, by placing in
        this caſe <lb/>a concave Spectacle-Glaſs before the Lens. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This Experiment exactly repreſents the <lb/>Manner of Viſion by the Eye; for the Eye
        <lb/>is of a globular or convex Form, reſembling <lb/>the Lens plac'd in the Hole in the
        Window- <lb/>Shutter, the outſide Coat of which is call'd the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Cornea</hi>, and gives the convex Shape to the <lb/>aqueous or watery Humour contain'd
        with- <lb/>in it: On the Bottom of the Eye is expanded <lb/>a fine Membrane call'd the <hi
          rend="italic">Retina</hi>, which <pb xml:id="page_4" n="5"/>
        <lb/>reſembles the white Paper mention'd in the <lb/>Experiment; on this Membrane the
        Pictures <lb/>of all external Objects are form'd. When <lb/>the Pictures are form'd diſtinct
        on the <hi rend="italic"> Reti- <lb/>na</hi>, then the Object appears clear and di-
        <lb/>ſtinct; if the Pictures on the <hi rend="italic">Retina</hi> are con- <lb/>fuſed, then
        the Object appears hazy and <lb/>confuſed. This Account of the Eye, and <lb/>the Cauſe of
        Viſion, is farther confirm'd by <lb/>theſe Arguments; that Anatomiſts, when <lb/>they have
        taken off from the Bottom of the <lb/>Eye, that outward and thickeſt Coat call'd the
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Dura Mater</hi>, can then ſee the Pictures of <lb/>Objects lively
        painted on the <hi rend="italic">Retina.</hi> And <lb/>theſe Pictures propagated by Motion
        along <lb/>the Fibres of the optick Nerves into the <lb/>Brain, are the Cauſe of Viſion.
        For, ac- <lb/>cording as theſe Pictures are perfect or im- <lb/>perfect, the Object is ſeen
        perfectly or im- <lb/>perfectly. If the Eye be ting'd with any <lb/>Colour, (as in the
        Diſeaſe of the Jaundice) <lb/>ſo as to tinge the Pictures in the Bottom of <lb/>the Eye with
        that Colour, then all Objects <lb/>appear ting'd with the ſame Colour. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From hence we ſhall eaſily ſee the Uſe of <lb/>Spectacles; for the Humours of the Eye
        de- <lb/>cay by old Age, ſo as by ſhrinking to make <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Cornea</hi>
        grow flatter than before, in <lb/>which Caſe the Light will not be refracted <pb
          xml:id="page_5" n="6"/>
        <lb/>enough, and for want of a ſufficient Re- <lb/>fraction will not converge to the Bottom
        of <lb/>the Eye, but to ſome Place beyond it; and <lb/>by Conſequence will paint in the
        Bottom of <lb/>the Eye a confuſed Picture, and according <lb/>to the Indiſtinctneſs of this
        Picture the Ob- <lb/>ject will appear confuſed, juſt as the Image <lb/>on the Paper became
        confuſed, when a <lb/>Lens flatter than juſt, was ſubſtituted in the <lb/>Room of the right
        one. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This is the reaſon of the Decay of Sight <lb/>in old Men, and ſhews why their Sight is
        <lb/>mended by Spectacles. For the convex <lb/>Glaſſes ſupply the Defect of Plumpneſs in the
        <lb/>Eye; and by increaſing the Refractions <lb/>make the Rays converge ſooner, ſo as to
        <lb/>convene diſtinctly at the Bottom of the Eye, <lb/>if the Glaſs has a due Degree of
        Convexity, <lb/>exactly in the ſame manner as the Defect of <lb/>the too flat Lens was
        corrected, and the <lb/>Picture render'd diſtinct, by placing a Spec- <lb/>tacle-Glass of
        due Convexity before it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And the contrary happens in ſhort-ſighted <lb/>Men, whoſe Eyes are too plump; for the
        <lb/>Refractions being now too great, the Rays <lb/>converge and convene in the Eyes before
        <lb/>they come at the Bottom; and therefore <lb/>the Picture made in the Bottom, and the Vi-
        <lb/>ſion cauſed thereby, will not be diſtinct, un- <lb/>
        <pb xml:id="page_6" n="7"/>
        <lb/>less the Plumpneſs of the Eye be taken off, <lb/>and the Refraction diminiſh'd by a
        concave <lb/>Glaſs of a due Concavity, juſt as the Con- <lb/>fuſion of the Image occaſion'd
        by the Uſe of <lb/>too convex a Lens was remedied, by placing <lb/>a Spectacle-Glaſs of a
        due Concavity before <lb/>it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This in general is the Manner in which the <lb/>Defects of the Eye are remedied by the
        uſe <lb/>of Glaſſes. But theſe Defects are neither <lb/>the ſame in different Perſons of the
        ſame <lb/>Age, nor in the ſame Perſons at different <lb/>Ages. The Defects of the Eye are
        partly <lb/>natural, and partly ariſe from Habits of <lb/>looking either at very remote, or
        very near <lb/>Objects; in the former Caſe we flatten the <lb/>Eye a little, in the latter
        we draw it up into a <lb/>more convex Form to ſee diſtinctly; and by <lb/>Habit the Eye will
        acquire and retain that <lb/>Form, and will have a fix'd Shape, either too <lb/>flat, or too
        globular for Objects at a mode- <lb/>rate Diſtance. We ſee this confirm'd by <lb/>every
        Day's Experience, for Engravers, <lb/>Watchmakers, Chaſers, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        by frequently <lb/>forcing their Eyes into too convex a Form, <lb/>to ſee minute Objects
        very near; at laſt have <lb/>their Eyes fix'd in this Form, and become <lb/>ſhort-ſighted,
        eſpecially if they are uſed to <lb/>theſe Buſineſſes very young, while the Coats <pb
          xml:id="page_7" n="8"/>
        <lb/>of the Eye are tender and pliable. On the <lb/>contrary, Sailors and Husbandmen, by
        look- <lb/>ing out for diſtant Objects, are rarely or <lb/>ever ſhort-ſighted, and want the
        Aſſiſtance <lb/>of convex Glaſſes very ſoon, becauſe the <lb/>Habit of flattening the Eye to
        ſee remote <lb/>Objects, at laſt fixes it in this Form. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From hence we may ſee that the Defects <lb/>of all perſons Eyes will likely alter,
        accord- <lb/>ing as they accuſtom themſelves to ſuch Ha- <lb/>bits as may either increaſe or
        diminiſh theſe <lb/>Defects. Beſides this, Age itſelf alters the <lb/>Form of the Eye,
        making the Eyes of moſt <lb/>Perſons grow flatter, eſpecially thoſe who <lb/>ſee well at a
        moderate Diſtance, when young <lb/>Perſons, naturally ſhort-ſighted, ſeldom find <lb/>any
        conſiderable Alteration in the Eye; but <lb/>when they do alter, I have obſerved that
        <lb/>they oftener grow more ſhort-ſighted than <lb/>otherwiſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Since therefore the Defects of the Eye, <lb/>and the Glaſſes proper to remedy theſe De-
        <lb/>fects vary ſo much, both in different Per- <lb/>ſons and different Ages, I ſhall now
        lay <lb/>down ſome Rules, by which every one may <lb/>chuſe not only good Glaſſes in their
        Kind; <lb/>but ſuch too, as are beſt ſuited to the Form <lb/>and Shape of their own Eye.
        Every good <lb/>Eye has one certain Diſtance (or nearly ſo) <pb xml:id="page_8" n="9"/>
        <lb/>of ſeeing a common Print to read with Eaſe: <lb/>When the Eye begins to grow too flat,
        you <lb/>will find yourſelf obliged to hold your Book <lb/>at a greater Diſtance; you may
        obſerve alſo, <lb/>that if you read, write, or work any long <lb/>Time, a ſort of Dizineſs
        like a Cobweb will <lb/>appear before your Eyes, or if you read by <lb/>a Candle you find it
        neceſſary to hold the <lb/>Paper behind it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe are Signs of the want of Spectacles, <lb/>and whenever this appears to be the
        Caſe, <lb/>no Perſon ſhould be without them; for your <lb/>Endeavours to ſee what you cannot
        without <lb/>great Difficulty, ſtrains and weakens the <lb/>Eye, and by this you receive
        more Injury <lb/>in a Month or two, than perhaps you other- <lb/>wiſe would do in as many
        Years, with the <lb/>Aſſiſtance of ſuch Glaſſes, as would ſupply <lb/>that Defect, and
        render the Viſion diſtinct <lb/>and eaſy. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The next Thing then to be conſidered is, <lb/>what Degree of Convexity is ſufficient to
        <lb/>ſupply this Defect. In order to make a <lb/>proper Choice, hold a ſmall Print at the
        Di- <lb/>ſtance, at which you was uſed to read di- <lb/>ſtinctly, when your Eyes were good,
        which <lb/>with moſt People is about nine or ten Inch- <lb/>es, then chuſe a Pair of
        Spectacles of ſuch a <lb/>Degree of Convexity as render the Letters <pb xml:id="page_9"
          n="10"/>
        <lb/>as plain as they uſed to appear before your <lb/>Sight was defective; if you chuſe them
        too <lb/>young, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> not convex enough, they will <lb/>ſcarce remedy
        the Defect of the Eye; and <lb/>you will not ſee diſtinctly, unleſs the Print <lb/>is ſo far
        off, that the Letters will appear too <lb/>ſmall to be read. If you chuſe them too old,
        <lb/>that is too convex, you will then be obliged <lb/>to flatten the Eye to compenſate the
        over <lb/>great Convexity, and thereby be in danger <lb/>of increaſing that Defect, which
        Age natu- <lb/>rally brings on. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But in many curious Pieces of Workman- <lb/>ſhip, there is an abſolute Neceſſity of
        view- <lb/>ing the Object under a larger Angle, that <lb/>the moſt minute Parts may be
        obſerv'd. In <lb/>this caſe, Glaſſes of a larger Convexity may <lb/>be uſed, and if the Work
        be brought nearer <lb/>to the Eye, its Form will not be much al- <lb/>tered, but the ſhorter
        time theſe Objects are <lb/>view'd the better. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For ſhort-ſighted Perſons, the beſt way is <lb/>to look through a concave Lens at ſome
        di- <lb/>ſtant Object, and the leaſt Concave of all <lb/>the Glaſſes, through which you can
        ſee it di- <lb/>ſtinctly, is the beſt. I divide all my Glaſſes <lb/>into 20 Degrees, mark'd
        1, 2, 3, and ſo <lb/>on. When a Perſon has fitted himſelf, I <lb/>ſet down his Name, with
        the Number of the <pb xml:id="page_10" n="11"/>
        <lb/>Glaſs choſen, which prevents any more <lb/>Trouble of Tryal, or even going for it;
        <lb/>but ſuch Perſon may be ſupplied by ſending <lb/>a Servant or Letter, unleſs any
        material Al- <lb/>teration of the Eye ſhould happen. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A Perſon whoſe Reſidence is in the Coun- <lb/>try, and has no Opportunity of making
        that <lb/>Tryal, may nearly as well be fitted by the <lb/>following Method; <hi
          rend="italic">viz.</hi> Let the Perſon take <lb/>a common Print, and move it to the Eye,
        <lb/>till he ſees diſtinctly, then meaſure the ex- <lb/>act Diſtance from the Eye to the
        Paper: By <lb/>ſending an Account of that Diſtance to any <lb/>Perſon in the Trade, they may
        be fitted to a <lb/>ſufficient Degree of Exactneſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I come now to point out the Defects of <lb/>the Glaſſes themſelves, and the way of diſ-
        <lb/>covering theſe Defects. Now theſe are ei- <lb/>ther a falſe Figure, Veins in the Glaſs,
        or <lb/>the Colour of it. And firſt for the Figure. <lb/>Take any common Print, lay it on a
        Table, <lb/>then hold the Spectacles in your Hand at a <lb/>good Diſtance from the Eye, and
        looking <lb/>through them, remove them gradually from <lb/>the Paper, till the Spectacles
        are at the focal <lb/>Diſtance from it, which in a convex Glaſs <lb/>is ſomewhat nearer to
        the Print, than the <lb/>Point at which it begins to appear conſuſed. <lb/>If the Spectacles
        are ſalſe, the Object through <pb xml:id="page_11" n="12"/>
        <lb/>the Middle of the Glaſs will appear regular <lb/>and diſtinct, but through the Edges
        diſtorted <lb/>and confuſed. Thus if you view any croſs <lb/>Lines, which form ſmall Squares
        through a <lb/>falſe ground Glaſs, the Squares in the Mid- <lb/>dle will appear with ſtrait
        Sides, diſtinct, <lb/>and all of a Size; but thoſe near the Edges, <lb/>with crooked Sides,
        of a different Bigneſs, <lb/>and confuſed; ſo that the whole Appear- <lb/>ance will neither
        be like the Original, nor <lb/>all Parts of it diſtinct at the ſame Diſtance. <lb/>If you
        view it through a true Glaſs, it will <lb/>be perfectly like the original Figure, only
        <lb/>bigger, and diſtinct in every Part. And as <lb/>you gradually remove the Glaſs beyond
        the <lb/>Focus, all Parts of the Object will become <lb/>indiſtinct together. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To diſcover the Veins in convex Glaſſes, <lb/>place a Candle from you about five or ſix
        <lb/>Yards, then looking through the Glaſs move <lb/>it from your Eye, till you fill it full
        of <lb/>Light, and you will then diſcover every <lb/>Vein and Speck in it. Theſe Veins
        always <lb/>diſtort Objects, and in the Object Glaſſes of <lb/>Teleſcopes and Microſcopes
        are eſpecially <lb/>miſchievous, ſince all theſe Errors are much <lb/>magnified by the
        Eye-Glaſs. Specks differ <lb/>from Veins; for Specks are only ſmall o- <lb/>pake Spots,
        which do not diſtort the Ob- <pb xml:id="page_12" n="13"/>
        <lb/>ject, but only intercept an inconſiderable <lb/>Part of the Light coming from it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For the Colour of Glaſs, the whiteſt has <lb/>been generally made uſe of for
        Spectacles, <lb/>but I am inclin'd on many Accounts to pre- <lb/>fer another Sort before it,
        or any other Ma- <lb/>terial that has been made uſe of for this Pur- <lb/>poſe: For the
        common white Glaſs gives <lb/>an offenſive gla<unclear>r</unclear>ing Light, very painful
        and <lb/>prejudicial to the Eyes; inſomuch, that <lb/>ſome adviſe green or blue Glaſs, tho'
        it <lb/>tinge every Object with its own Colour, ra- <lb/>ther than this white Sort. That
        which I <lb/>would recommend, is of a finer Compoſition <lb/>than any commonly uſed; its
        Colour is the <lb/>fineſt of any, and being a little ting'd with <lb/>Blue, it takes off the
        glaring Light from the <lb/>Paper, and renders every Object ſo eaſy <lb/>and pleaſant, that
        the tendereſt Eye, may <lb/>thro' it view any thing intently, without <lb/>Pain. But,
        beſides this, there are many <lb/>other Reaſons for rejecting the common <lb/>white Glaſs,
        for 'tis of a ſofter Body than <lb/>any other, and will not receive ſo true a <lb/>Figure in
        the poliſhing, as a Glaſs of a <lb/>harder Nature will, neither will the Poliſh <lb/>itſelf
        be ſo fine and beautiful, nor of ſo long <lb/>Continuance; for if it lies by any conſide-
        <lb/>rable Time, it will change to a reddiſh Co- <pb xml:id="page_13" n="14"/>
        <lb/>lour, which is owing to the Nature of the <lb/>Materials it is compoſed of; beſides,
        this <lb/>Sort of Glaſs is generally found to be very <lb/>full both of Specks and Veins;
        inſomuch, <lb/>that one can hardly ſee any Spectacles made <lb/>of this Sort of Glaſs that
        are free from it. <lb/>That which I would here recommend is of <lb/>an harder Nature, ſuch
        as will receive a <lb/>true Figure, and will take a very fine and <lb/>high Poliſh, is
        perfectly tranſparent, and <lb/>the freeſt of any from Veins and Specks. <lb/>I have always
        found this much preferable to <lb/>any other Sort, both in Teleſcopes and Mi-
        <lb/>croſcopes, where the leaſt Faults are diſ- <lb/>cernable, eſpecially in the
        Object-Glaſs, <lb/>where every Error in the Image, they form, is <lb/>greatly magnified by
        the Eye-Glaſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Brazil</hi> Pebbles, and Rock Cryſtal Stones <lb/>are much cried up
        by ſome for Spectacles; <lb/>they are indeed very hard, and therefore <lb/>will take a true
        Figure and a good Poliſh; <lb/>but, beſides a glaring Whiteneſs, all theſe <lb/>Stones have
        a Grain much like the Iſland <lb/>Cryſtal <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.75)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* See Sir <hi rend="italic">Iſaac Newton's</hi> Optics, Book 3. Quere 25. </p>
        </note>; and not only a Grain, but like <lb/>that too, a double <hi rend="italic"
          >Refraction</hi>, ſo that all Ob- <lb/>jects appear double: Thus inſtead of one
        <lb/>Letter there will appear two, one over the <lb/>other. What Confuſion this muſt
        occaſion <pb xml:id="page_14" n="15"/>
        <lb/>in the Print of a Book may be eaſily gueſs'd <lb/>at; and tho' this is ſometimes not
        great, ſo <lb/>that the Letters are not much confuſed, <lb/>yet it will occaſion an Hazineſs
        and Indi- <lb/>ſtinctness, very like that of ſome Copper- <lb/>Plate Prints, which have been
        moved a <lb/>little on the Plate while they were printing <lb/>off. If any one has a Mind to
        be fully ſa- <lb/>tisfied of the Fitneſs of theſe Bodies for <lb/>Spectacles, let him try to
        uſe them for the <lb/>Object-Glaſs of a Teleſcope. Every one <lb/>converſant in Opticks
        knows, the greateſt <lb/>Exactneſs in Figure, the moſt perfect Free- <lb/>dom from Veins,
        and the cleareſt Sub- <lb/>ſtances are always requiſite to make a good <lb/>Object-Glaſs in
        a long Teleſcope. But, if <lb/>theſe Subſtances are ſo far from being pre- <lb/>ferable,
        that they are the worſt of all others <lb/>for that Purpoſe, ſo that it is ſcarce poſſible
        <lb/>to make any Teleſcope at all with them; <lb/>they muſt, of Courſe, be the worſt of all
        others <lb/>for Spectacles too, tho' their Faults are not <lb/>ſo eaſily diſcern'd in ſo
        ſimple an Inſtrument. </p>
      <trailer rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
