<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Battie: A treatise on madness</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>William Battie</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">A treatise on madness. By William Battie M.D. Fellow of the College
              pf Physicians in London, And Physician to St. Luke's Hospital.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T51638 </idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T51638"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Whiston, and B. White, in Fleet-Street,
                  M,DCC,LVIII.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1758</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="7"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="99"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108691187</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: disease"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="7"/>
    <body>
      <pb n=""/>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>A horizontal double-line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A horizontal double-line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <head rend="sc align-center space">
        <lb/>a <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">TREATISE </hi>
        <lb/>on <lb/><hi rend="size(2.5)">MADNESS. </hi>
      </head>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>SECT. I. </head>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>The Definition of Madneſs. </head>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">M</hi>ADNESS, though a terrible and at <lb/>preſent a very frequent
          calamity, is <lb/>perhaps as little underſtood as any <lb/>that ever afflicted mankind.
          The names alone <lb/>uſually given to this diſorder and its ſeveral <lb/>ſpecies, <hi
            rend="italic">viz. Lunacy</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Spleen</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >Melancholy</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Hurry <lb/>of the Spirits</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
            >&amp;c.</hi> may convince any one of the <pb n="2"/>
          <lb/>truth of this aſſertion, without having recourſe <lb/>to the authors who have
          profeſſedly treated on <lb/>this ſubject. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Our defect of knowledge in this matter is, I <lb/>am afraid, in a great meaſure owing
          to a defect <lb/>of proper communication: and the difficulties <lb/>attending the care of
          Lunaticks have been at <lb/>leaſt perpetuated by their being entruſted to Em-
          <lb/>piricks, or at beſt to a few ſelect Phyſicians, <lb/>moſt of whom thought it
          adviſeable to keep the <lb/>caſes as well as the patients to themſelves. By <lb/>which
          means it has unavoidably happened that <lb/>in this inſtance experience, the parent of me-
          <lb/>dical ſcience, has profited little, and every Prac- <lb/>titioner at his firſt
          engaging in the cure of Lu- <lb/>nacy has had nothing but his own natural ſenſe <lb/>and
          ſagacity to truſt to; except what he may <lb/>perchance have heard of Antimonial vomits,
          <lb/>ſtrong purges, and Hellebore, as ſpecifically anti- <lb/>maniacal: Which traditional
          knowledge however, <lb/>if indiſcriminately reduced to practice, a little <lb/>experience
          will ſoon make him wiſh he had been <lb/>an entire ſtranger to. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>There is therefore reaſon to hope, that an at- <lb/>tempt to diſcover the cauſes,
          effects, and cure of <lb/>Madneſs, will meet with a favourable reception; <lb/>ſince,
          whatever may be the event, the intention <pb n="3"/>
          <lb/>is right; and it is ſome comfort to think that no- <lb/>thing of this nature, even
          though it ſhould fall <lb/>ſhort of what is aimed at, can in its conſe- <lb/>quences be
          entirely uſeleſs. For the judicious <lb/>reader will at leaſt be hereby inclined to turn
          <lb/>his thoughts to the ſame ſubject, and may even <lb/>receive inſtruction from the
          miſcarriages of ſuch <lb/>an undertaking. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But the peculiar misfortune juſt now mention- <lb/>ed, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
          want of proper communication, though <lb/>the chief, is not the only hindrance to our
          know- <lb/>ledge: for Madneſs hath moreover ſhared the <lb/>fate common to many other
          diſtempers of not <lb/>being preciſely defined. Inaſmuch as not only <lb/>ſeveral
          ſymptoms, which frequently and acciden- <lb/>tally accompany it, have been taken into the
          ac- <lb/>count as conſtant, neceſſary, and eſſential; but <lb/>alſo the ſuppoſed cauſe,
          which perhaps never ex- <lb/>iſted or certainly never acted with ſuch effect, <lb/>has
          been implied in the very names uſually given <lb/>to this diſtemper. No wonder therefore
          is it, <lb/>whilſt ſeveral diſorders, really independent of <lb/>Madneſs and of one
          another, are thus blended <lb/>together in our bewildered imagination, that a
          <lb/>treatment, rationally indicated by any of thoſe <lb/>diſorders, ſhould be
          injudiciouſly directed againſt <lb/>Madneſs itſelf, whether attended with ſuch ſymp-
          <lb/>toms or not. Much leſs can we blame the Phy- <pb n="4"/>
          <lb/>ſician, who being prejudiced by the ſuppoſed <lb/>cauſe couched in the name of the
          diſtemper <lb/>he has to deal with at every new or full Moon <lb/>attenuates, evacuates,
          or alters the peccant hu- <lb/>mours by medicines peculiarly adapted to the <lb/>black or
          ſplendid Bile, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>In order therefore to avoid this miſchievous <lb/>confuſion of ſentiment as well as
          language, and <lb/>that we may fix a clear and determinate mean- <lb/>ing to the Word <hi
            rend="italic">Madneſs</hi>; we muſt for ſome <lb/>time at leaſt quit the ſchools of
          Philoſophy, and <lb/>content ourſelves with a vulgar apprehenſion of <lb/>things; we muſt
          reject not only every ſuppoſed <lb/>cauſe of Madneſs, but alſo every ſymptom which
          <lb/>does not neceſſarily belong to it, and retain no <lb/>one phœnomenon but what is
          eſſential, that is <lb/>without which the word <hi rend="italic">Madneſs</hi> becomes
          nuga- <lb/>tory and conveys no idea whatever: or, in other <lb/>words, no definition of
          Madneſs can be ſafe, <lb/>which does not, with regard at leaſt to ſome <lb/>particular
          ſymptoms, determine what it is not, <lb/>as well as what it is. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Firſt then, though too great and too lively a <lb/>perception of objects that really
          exiſt creates an <lb/>uneaſineſs not felt by the generality of men, and <lb/>therefore
          diſcovers a præternatural ſtate in the <lb/>inſtruments of Senſation, and tho' ſuch
          uneaſi- <lb/>neſs frequently accompanies Madneſs, and is there- <pb n="5"/>
          <lb/>fore ſometimes miſtaken for it; nevertheleſs An- <lb/>xiety is no more eſſentially
          annexed to Madneſs, <lb/>ſo as to make part of our complex idea, than <lb/>Fever,
          Head-ach, Gout, or Leproſy. Witneſs the <lb/>many inſtances of happy Mad-men, who are
          <lb/>perfectly eaſy under what is eſteemed by every <lb/>one but themſelves the greateſt
          misfortune hu- <lb/>man nature is liable to. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Secondly, though too little and too languid a <lb/>perception of things that really
          exiſt and are ob- <lb/>truded with force ſufficient to excite ſenſation in <lb/>the
          generality of men, diſcovers as præternatural <lb/>a ſtate or diſorder in the inſtruments
          of Senſation <lb/>as uncommon Anxiety, and tho' it ſometimes at- <lb/>tends Madneſs, and
          is likewiſe miſtaken for it, <lb/>eſpecially by the <hi rend="italic">French</hi> who call
          Mad-men and <lb/>Fools by the ſame name; nevertheleſs ſuch defect <lb/>of Senſation is no
          more eſſentially annexed to <lb/>Madneſs than the former ſymptom of Anxiety, <lb/>which
          that very frequent ſymptom of Madneſs <lb/>ſufficiently proves. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But— <q rend="italic">qui ſpecies alias veris capiet, commotus habe- <lb/>bitur </q>
          — And this by all mankind as well as the <lb/>Phyſician: no one ever doubting whether the
          <lb/>perception of objects not really exiſting or not <lb/>really correſponding to the
          ſenſes be a certain <lb/>ſign of Madneſs. Therefore <hi rend="italic">deluded
            imagination</hi>, <pb n="6"/>
          <lb/>which is not only an indiſputable but an eſſential <lb/>character of Madneſs, (that
          is without which, all <lb/>accidental ſymptoms being removed from our <lb/>thoughts, we
          have no idea whatever remaining <lb/>annexed to that ſound) preciſely diſcriminates
          <lb/>this from all other animal diſorders: or that man <lb/>and that man alone is properly
          mad, who is fully <lb/>and unalterably perſuaded of the Exiſtence or of <lb/>the
          appearance of any thing, which either does <lb/>not exiſt or does not actually appear to
          him, and <lb/>who behaves according to ſuch erroneous per- <lb/>ſuaſion. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Madneſs, or falſe perception, being then a <lb/>præternatural ſtate or diſorder of
          Senſation; be- <lb/>fore we attempt to diſcover its cauſes effects and <lb/>cure, it will
          be neceſſary for us to inveſtigate the <lb/>ſeat the cauſes and the effects of natural
          Senſa- <lb/>tion. For the conſideration of the abuſe or fault <lb/>of any thing
          neceſſarily brings that very thing <lb/>into compariſon with what it was when ſound
          <lb/>and perfect; and 'tis impoſſible for us rationally <lb/>to amend or reſtore what
          never was the object of <lb/>our thoughts. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Be it therefore our firſt endeavour to contem- <lb/>plate natural Senſation: if haply
          this moſt diſtin- <lb/>guiſhing property of animal life may ſupply us <lb/>with actual and
          poſitive knowledge of ſome mat- <pb n="7"/>
          <lb/>ters that relate to the preſent ſubject; or at leaſt <lb/>may point out to us what it
          is that herein ſur- <lb/>paſſes our imperfect underſtandings. A ſcience <lb/>negative
          indeed, and by no means ſo ſatisfactory <lb/>to the pride and ſpeculative curioſity of man
          as <lb/>the former, but very often as uſeful and as con- <lb/>ducive to the attaining
          practical truth. </p>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>An ornamental illustration in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
      <pb n="8"/>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>SECT. II. </head>
        <head rend="align-center space italic">
          <lb/>The Seat of natural Senſation. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">W</hi>Hoever is conſcious that he hears, ſees, <lb/>or feels, and
          beholds all animals he <lb/>is converſant with acting juſt in the <lb/>ſame manner as he
          does when he hears, ſees, or <lb/>feels, muſt acknowledge that his own and every
          <lb/>other animal body is as really endued with Sen- <lb/>ſation as that it exiſts. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Whoever attentively contemplates in what <lb/>manner he and every other animal is
          affected by <lb/>external impulſe, muſt acknowledge that ſome <lb/>parts of the ſame body,
          however animated, are <lb/>quite inſenſible, ſome endued with a leſs degree <lb/>of
          Senſation than others. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Whoever is moreover ſufficiently verſed in A- <lb/>natomical reſearches, and has
          learnt to ſeparate <lb/>thoſe parts of an animal body, which, however <lb/>contiguous or
          cloſely connected, are nevertheleſs <lb/>really diſtinct from each other, very readily
          diſco- <lb/>vers ſeveral ſoft fibres, each of which is actually <lb/>diviſible into many
          ſmaller of the ſame kind, as <lb/>far as his eye can trace; and he by analogy <lb/>juſtly
          concludes that each of thoſe ſmaller fibres <pb n="9"/>
          <lb/>is as capable of being ſtill farther and farther <lb/>divided beyond the reach of
          viſion, and even of <lb/>human imagination. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Theſe ſoft fibres are all connected with the <lb/>contents of the cranium, and in
          different parts <lb/>of the body they are collected into faſciculi; <lb/>every one of
          which is enveloped by a continua- <lb/>tion of thoſe very membranes which within the
          <lb/>cranium contain the ſubſtance of the brain and <lb/>its medullary appendages. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Every ſuch faſciculus as well as the ſeveral <lb/>fibres it is reſolveable into is
          called <hi rend="italic">a Nerve</hi>: a <lb/>name borrowed indeed from the ancients, but
          <lb/>uſed by them in a very different ſignification. <lb/>For by <hi
            rend="italic size(0.5)">νε<unclear>ΰ</unclear>ρον</hi> and <hi rend="italic">nervus</hi>
          neither the <hi rend="italic">Greeks</hi> nor <hi rend="italic">La- <lb/>tins</hi> meant
          any thing ſoft and medullary, but on <lb/>the contrary the hard and elaſtic ſubſtance of a
          <lb/>tendon or ligament; as the word <hi rend="italic size(0.5)">άπονεύρωσις</hi>, ſtill
          <lb/>retained by the moderns to ſignify the faſcia or <lb/>membrane expanded over and
          connecting the <lb/>muſcular fibres, ſufficiently ſhews. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Every nerve, which is within the reach of <lb/>our obſervation, is extended between
          the <hi rend="italic">me- <lb/>dulla oblongata</hi> or its appendage the <hi rend="italic"
            >medulla ſpi- <lb/>nalis</hi> and the place of ſuch nerve's deſtination. <lb/>But every
          ſuch nerve is thus extended in a man- <pb n="10"/>
          <lb/>ner very different from the diſpoſition of the <lb/>blood-veſſels, and indeed of all
          other portions of <lb/>the ſame body which are called ſimilar. For <lb/>in its paſſage it
          neither is ſplit into ramifications, <lb/>nor is it at all connected with any contiguous
          <lb/>parts of the body, except with ſome ſubſtances <lb/>equally nervous called ganglions
          chiefly obſer- <lb/>vable in the meſentery. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>If a nerve in a living body be diſtracted by <lb/>external force, there immediately
          ariſes an ex- <lb/>quiſite ſenſation called pain. Which ſenſation is <lb/>always in a
          direct proportion to the quantity of <lb/>ſuch diſtracting force; and which never ceaſes
          <lb/>either untill the diſtracting force is removed or <lb/>is become unactive, or untill
          the material par- <lb/>ticles which conſtitute the ſaid nerve are by this <lb/>diſtraction
          irrecoverably diſunited. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>If to a nerve in a living body be applied any <lb/>acrimonious objects, that is ſuch
          portions of mat- <lb/>ter whoſe ſurfaces are full of angles, and which <lb/>when aſſiſted
          with proper impulſe are therefore <lb/>capable of diſtracting the particles that
          conſtitute <lb/>the nervous ſubſtance, there immediately ariſes <lb/>the ſame painful
          ſenſation: which is always in <lb/>a direct proportion to the quantity and acuteneſs
          <lb/>of ſuch acrimonious angles, and to the impulſe <lb/>with which they are impacted, and
          which con- <pb n="11"/>
          <lb/>tinues as long as in the former caſe of viſible <lb/>diſtraction occaſioned by
          external force. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Thoſe parts of an animal body, in which the <lb/>greateſt quantity of nervous fibres
          is manifeſtly <lb/>contained, and in which ſuch nervous fibres lie <lb/>the moſt expoſed
          and undefended by any other <lb/>matter that conſtitutes the ſame body, are the
          <lb/>ſooneſt and the moſt affected whenever any ex- <lb/>ternal objects are applied with
          force ſufficient to <lb/>excite ſenſation. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Thoſe membranes, which not only within <lb/>the cranium ſurround the brain, but which
          alſo <lb/>ſerve as ſheaths to the ſeveral appendages of the <lb/>brain, collecting them
          into nervous faſciculi all <lb/>over the body as far as the eye can trace, are <lb/>indeed
          every where contiguous to and ſeem in- <lb/>timately connected with the medullary
          ſubſtance <lb/>they contain: nevertheleſs upon the application <lb/>of any external
          objects they all diſcover no ex- <lb/>traordinary ſigns of ſenſibility, any more than
          <lb/>ſeveral other membranes in the ſame body, which <lb/>are equally vaſcular and
          elaſtic. Witneſs the <lb/>many well atteſted caſes of eroſions and other <lb/>accidents of
          the dura mater unattended with <lb/>any degree of pain. </p>
        <pb n="11"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>All which conſtant and uncontroverted ob- <lb/>ſervations prove, 1. That the nervous
          or me- <lb/>dullary ſubſtance derived from or rather com- <lb/>municating with the brain
          is the ſeat or inſtru- <lb/>ment of natural Senſation: 2. That no other <lb/>matter
          whatever, whether animated or not, is <lb/>ſuch ſeat or inſtrument. </p>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>An ornamental illustration in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
      <pb n="13"/>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>SECT. III. </head>
        <head rend="align-center space italic">
          <lb/>The ſuppoſed Cauſes of natural Senſation. </head>
        <p rend=" space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HAT the medullary or nervous ſub- <lb/>ſtance continued from
          or rather con- <lb/>nected with the brain is the ſeat of Sen- <lb/>ſation, is a point now
          ſo univerſally agreed upon, <lb/>that perhaps it might have been ſufficient barely <lb/>to
          have aſſerted it without any formal proof. <lb/>Happy ſhould we be, if the cauſes of
          Senſation <lb/>were as clearly and inconteſtably ſettled. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But I am afraid before any right or ſatisfactory <lb/>notion can be formed concerning
          this matter, <lb/>we muſt get rid of ſome opinions, which how- <lb/>ever abſurd have of
          late paſſed upon many for <lb/>real knowledge. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The reaſon of this difference, which at pre- <lb/>ſent ſubſiſts between the diſcovery
          of the ſeat, <lb/>and the diſcovery of the cauſes of Senſation, is <lb/>not in the things
          themſelves that have been en- <lb/>quired after, but in the manner of enquiry.
          <lb/>Becauſe in fixing the ſeat of Senſation we have <lb/>been content with facts that are
          apparent to all <lb/>men, and which if any one ſhould controvert, <lb/>he muſt diſclaim
          the evidence of his own ſenſes: <pb n="14"/>
          <lb/>But in aſſigning the cauſes of Senſation ſeveral <lb/>things have been aſſumed as
          matters of fact, <lb/>which have never been diſcovered, and which <lb/>may at leaſt with
          equal probability be denied <lb/>as admitted. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>For here the Hypothetical Genius, forgetful <lb/>that he hath Nature's works for his
          contempla- <lb/>tion, and deſpiſing that poor pittance of know- <lb/>ledge which the real
          appearance of things ſup- <lb/>plies every one with as well as himſelf, hath <lb/>dared
          without any warrant to coin new ideas; <lb/>hath made free with air, water, æther, nay
          even <lb/>electrical fire; and imagining that to be pro- <lb/>bable which is barely
          poſſible, and then heighten- <lb/>ing this aſſumed probability up to matter of fact,
          <lb/>he takes one large ſtride more and roundly aſ- <lb/>ſerts that <hi rend="italic">the
            brain is a gland; that its cortical <lb/>portion is a convolution of ſecretory veſſels
            deſigned <lb/>to ſeparate from the blood one or other of thoſe ele- <lb/>mentary
            ſubſtances, which he hath by ways un- <lb/>known introduced into the carotid arteries
            for this <lb/>his preſent purpoſe; that the medullary portion of <lb/>the brain and
            nerves is nothing elſe but a collection <lb/>of excretory ducts ſerving to convey this
            elemen- <lb/>tary matter to all the ſenſible parts of the body: <lb/>which matter either
            by undulation or retrograde <lb/>motion imparts to the Senſorium commune all thoſe
            <lb/>impulſes it receives from ſuch external objects as <pb n="15"/>
            <lb/>affect the extremities of the nervous filaments</hi>. <lb/>This excrement therefore
          of the brain tho' in- <lb/>viſible is the neceſſary cauſe of ſight, tho' im- <lb/>palpable
          the ſufficient cauſe of feeling, and <lb/>tho' an animal Spirit the material cauſe of ani-
          <lb/>mal Senſation. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Now, as the ſecretion of ſuch a nervous fluid <lb/>and conſequently its very
          exiſtence depends en- <lb/>tirely upon the analogy that is ſuppoſed to lie <lb/>between
          the brain and every glandular ſubſtance, <lb/>in caſe the brain is very unlike a gland in
          any <lb/>material circumſtance, this whole machinery is <lb/>immediately deſtroyed. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Admitting therefore, what has never yet been <lb/>proved, that the cortical portion
          of the brain re- <lb/>ſembles the ſecretory organ of a gland, yet the <lb/>medullary or
          nervous ſubſtance is different from <lb/>all excretory ducts whatever: inaſmuch as no ex-
          <lb/>cretory duct is ever found but what is immedi- <lb/>ately detached from the gland
          whence it iſſues; <lb/>whereas on the contrary the ſuppoſed glandular <lb/>or ſecretory
          ſubſtance of the brain is continued <lb/>to every part ſupplied with nerves, and theſe
          <lb/>nerves the ſuppoſed excretory ducts, after that <lb/>they have left the cranium and
          their glandular <lb/>origin the brain, wherever they are capable of <lb/>being examined,
          remain as cloſely connected <pb n="16"/>
          <lb/>not only with the cortical or ſecretory portion of <lb/>the brain, but even with the
          productions of the <lb/>dura and pia mater, as the medullary ſubſtance <lb/>itſelf whilſt
          contained within the cranium. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>This obſervation alone would be ſufficient to <lb/>deſtroy the very foundation of a
          nervous fluid, <lb/>if any Hypotheſis whatever could deſerve a ſeri- <lb/>ous
          conſideration. But it may be feared that a <lb/>ſolemn confutation of chimæras will appear
          equal- <lb/>ly ridiculous as an attempt to eſtabliſh them; <lb/>and he may perhaps incur
          the ſuſpicion of inſa- <lb/>nity which theſe theoriſts have deſerved, who <lb/>ſhall fight
          in earneſt with ſhadows, and miſpend <lb/>his time in offering reaſons, why the ſolid con-
          <lb/>ſtituent parts of the medullary ſubſtance con- <lb/>tained in every nerve bid fairer
          for ſupplying us <lb/>with the material cauſe of Senſation, than a fluid <lb/>never yet
          diſcovered, and which its very authors <lb/>confeſs was once foreign to the body, and even
          <lb/>extracted from dead and putreſcent matter ſpi- <lb/>rited up, we know not how, into
          animality. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Let us therefore quit this enchanted ground to <lb/>thoſe, if ſuch there be, who are
          ſtill inclined to <lb/>diſpute upon it; and in order to clear our way <lb/>a little more
          to the real cauſes of Senſation, let <lb/>us divert our attention to a very common phraſe,
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">viz. weakneſs of nerves</hi>, which tho' not pro- <pb n="17"/>
          <lb/>feſſedly ſyſtematical, like the former ſcheme of <lb/><hi rend="italic">animal
            ſpirits</hi>, is nevertheleſs extremely deluſive; <lb/>inaſmuch as it ſeems indirectly
          to offer another <lb/>ſolution of the phœnomenon in queſtion, and to <lb/>aſcertain the
          cauſe of Senſation. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>For ſince the word <hi rend="italic">weakneſs</hi>, when joined with <lb/>material
          ſubſtances, can convey no idea but a <lb/>lax cohæſion of ſuch particles as conſtitute
          thoſe <lb/>ſubſtances; therefore the phraſe <hi rend="italic">weakneſs of
          <lb/>nerves</hi>, which denotes a morbid exceſs of Senſa- <lb/>tion, ſeems to imply that
          Senſation itſelf is ow- <lb/>ing to the looſe cohæſion of thoſe material par- <lb/>ticles
          which conſtitute the nervous ſubſtance, in- <lb/>aſmuch as the quantity of every effect
          muſt be <lb/>proportionable to its cauſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>By this inaccurate manner of talking, the <lb/>moſt diſtinguiſhing property of animal
          nature is <lb/>in danger of being blended with inanimate mat- <lb/>ter. For, if the caſe
          really were what theſe <lb/>words ſeem to import, all bodies whoſe particles <lb/>do not
          cohære with too great a degree of proxi- <lb/>mity would be nervous, that is endued with
          Sen- <lb/>ſation. But, ſince no portion of matter, however <lb/>looſely compacted, is
          nervous except it is part of <lb/>an animal body, therefore the medullary ſub- <lb/>ſtance
          of a nerve is endued with Senſation not <lb/>becauſe its conſtituent particles are looſely
          united: <pb n="18"/>
          <lb/>and every nervous filament, tho' it conſiſts of <lb/>parts extended and not too
          cloſely cohæring, is <lb/>confeſſedly as diſtinct from every other material <lb/>ſubſtance
          conſiſting of parts extended and equally <lb/>cohæring, as a man from a carcas, or an
          horſe <lb/>from an equeſtrian ſtatue. </p>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>An ornamental illustration in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
      <pb n="19"/>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>SECT. IV. </head>
        <head rend="align-center space italic">
          <lb/>The real Cauſes of natural Senſation. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">S</hi>ENSATION, however perplexed it may <lb/>ſeem to thoſe who too
          curiouſly enquire <lb/>into its nature, is to the modeſt obſerver <lb/>as clear in idea
          and as fully to be accounted for, <lb/>at leaſt to all uſeful intents and purpoſes, as any
          <lb/>phœnomenon whatever. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>For is not what we feel a plain matter of fact, <lb/>of which we are not only certain
          and conſcious <lb/>ourſelves, but which we are likewiſe capable of <lb/>communicating to
          others by words or ſigns? <lb/>And are we not perfectly well acquainted with <lb/>many
          things, which when impelled with force <lb/>ſufficient will make us feel; and which it is
          <lb/>frequently in our power to apply, remove, or <lb/>avoid, as beſt ſuits our intereſt? </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>It is the heedleſs or rather the wilful neglect <lb/>of preciſely ſeparating theſe
          many evident and <lb/>external cauſes of Senſation as well from their <lb/>unknown and
          internal operations as from their in- <lb/>termediate and equally unknown effects, that
          has <lb/>created ſuch difficulties in contemplating this <lb/>phœnomenon. </p>
        <pb n="20"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>For the mutual cohæſion of material particles, <lb/>as eſſential to our idea of an
          animal body as <lb/>ſenſe itſelf, but not better accounted for, hath <lb/>however been
          looked upon as a thing much leſs <lb/>myſterious. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Which ſeeming diverſity can be owing to no- <lb/>thing elſe, but becauſe the
          generality of man- <lb/>kind have contented themſelves with the uſeful <lb/>and the
          attainable knowledge of ſuch external <lb/>objects, as will harden or ſoften thoſe bodies
          <lb/>they are applied to, without enquiring too nice- <lb/>ly why the conſtituent
          particles of thoſe bodies <lb/>are more or leſs united upon ſuch application; <lb/>or
          indeed why they are united at all: whereas <lb/>the philoſopher in his contemplation of
          ſenſible <lb/>matter is not content with knowing certainly <lb/>like other men what
          objects externally applied to <lb/>a nerve will create, increaſe, or deaden ſenſation,
          <lb/>but moreover conjectures why; and attempts by <lb/>any means whatever to aſſign the
          manner in <lb/>which theſe external objects act upon, and the <lb/>changes they produce in
          the nervous ſubſtance <lb/>previous to ſenſation their laſt effect; which ef- <lb/>fect,
          for reaſons beſt known to himſelf, ſeems <lb/>to demand a more explicit ſolution than the
          co- <lb/>hæſion of material particles. </p>
        <pb n="21"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>In endeavouring therefore to aſſign the cauſes <lb/>of Senſation, be it one of our
          chiefeſt cares to <lb/>diſtinguiſh them from one another as effectually <lb/>in our mind,
          as they are really different in their <lb/>nature, and to ſeparate what we actually and
          <lb/>uſefully know from what we are, and perhaps <lb/>ſhall always be without any great
          damage, en- <lb/>tirely ignorant of. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>For which purpoſe, it may not be amiſs to <lb/>premiſe a few conſiderations on cauſes
          in gene- <lb/>ral; which will illuſtrate the ſubject of our pre- <lb/>ſent enquiry and at
          the ſame time be confirmed <lb/>thereby. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Firſt then, by obſerving that any one phœno- <lb/>menon frequently follows another,
          we conclude <lb/>that the ſecond is owing to the firſt; and hence <lb/>we get the ideas of
            <hi rend="italic">cauſe</hi> and <hi rend="italic">effect</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Secondly, by obſerving that any one phœno- <lb/>menon never fails to follow another,
          we con- <lb/>clude that the firſt is not only a cauſe but alſo a <lb/>ſufficient cauſe of
          the ſecond. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Thirdly, by obſerving that the ſecond phœ- <lb/>nomenon never occurs but in
          conſequence of the <lb/>firſt, we further conclude that the firſt is not <pb n="22"/>
          <lb/>only a cauſe but a neceſſary cauſe of the ſecond, <lb/>which is therefore called the
            <hi rend="italic">cauſa ſine qua non</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Fourthly, by obſerving that the ſecond phœ- <lb/>nomenon follows the firſt without
          either the evi- <lb/>dent or the demonſtrated intervention of any <lb/>other phœnomenon as
          neceſſary or at leaſt ac- <lb/>ceſſary to its exiſtence, we conclude that the <lb/>firſt
          phœnomenon is moreover the immediate <lb/>cauſe of the ſecond. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Fifthly, by obſerving either that the firſt phœ- <lb/>nomenon is not always ſucceeded
          by the ſecond, <lb/>or that the ſecond is not always preceded by the <lb/>firſt, we
          conclude that the firſt phœnomenon is <lb/>either not a ſufficient or not a neceſſary, but
          <lb/>merely an accidental cauſe of the ſecond. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Sixthly, by obſerving or by admitting as un- <lb/>deniable that any one or more
          phœnomena in- <lb/>tervene between the firſt and the laſt in queſtion, <lb/>we plainly
          diſcover that the firſt is remote, and <lb/>that the ſeveral other intervening phœnomena
          in <lb/>their order approach nearer and nearer to the <lb/>immediate cauſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Seventhly, a very little reflection upon cauſes <lb/>and effects as thus ſtated will
          make us conclude <lb/>that the remote and accidental cauſes of any <pb n="23"/>
          <lb/>effect may be many, but that the ſufficient and <lb/>neceſſary as well as the
          immediate cauſe can <lb/>be but one. Since either of two cauſes ſuppoſed <lb/>ſufficient
          will render the other unneceſſary; and <lb/>either cauſe ſuppoſed neceſſary will render
          the <lb/>other inſufficient. Which unavoidable conclu- <lb/>ſion, by the way, might be
          extended beyond <lb/>ſecondary agents or inſtruments, improperly cal- <lb/>led cauſes, and
          would give an additional proof, <lb/>if any was wanting, to the unity of the firſt, the
          <lb/>neceſſary, the ſufficient, and indeed ſtrictly <lb/>ſpeaking the ſole cauſe of all
          things. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Thus, to inſtance in our preſent ſubject; ſight, <lb/>hearing, taſte, ſmell, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> which frequently ſuc- <lb/>ceed the application of external
          objects, are look- <lb/>ed upon by us as the effects of ſuch external ob- <lb/>jects; and
          we in common diſcourſe refer our ideas <lb/>back to thoſe objects as to their cauſes, as
          when <lb/>we ſay <hi rend="italic">we ſee the ſun , we hear the drum</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But, foraſmuch as the external objects of ſenſe, <lb/>however forcible their
          application may be, do not <lb/>always and in all animal bodies create ſight, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
          <lb/>And moreover, as the very ſame perceptions do <lb/>ſometimes, at leaſt in diſordered
          ſubjects, ariſe <lb/>without any external object that really affects <lb/>them; it is
          impoſſible but every ſuch external <lb/>object muſt be meerly accidental, and by no <pb
            n="24"/>
          <lb/>means the ſufficient or the neceſſary cauſe of <lb/>ſuch its nervous effect: Which
          ſufficient and ne- <lb/>ceſſary cauſe is therefore internal, that is it in- <lb/>hæres in
          the very frame and conſtitution of the <lb/>nervous ſubſtance itſelf; whereby alone ſuch
          <lb/>ſubſtance is rendered capable of being affected <lb/>by any external object ſo as to
          create Senſation; <lb/>and without which internal cauſe no thing what- <lb/>ever would
          actually become an object of our <lb/>ſenſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>For the ſame reaſon all ſuch external cauſes <lb/>are not only accidental but
          likewiſe remote. <lb/>Since the neceſſary and ſufficient cauſe at leaſt <lb/>muſt
          intervene; and beſides, before an external <lb/>object can create any ſenſation whatever,
          it <lb/>muſt produce ſeveral intermediate effects, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
          <lb/>motion, impulſe, and preſſure: all which pre- <lb/>cede not only ſight, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> thereby excited, but <lb/>alſo precede that particular
          internal affection of <lb/>the nerve itſelf, whatever it is, which is the im-
          <lb/>mediate, the neceſſary, and the ſufficient cauſe <lb/>of ſuch perception. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The accidental and remote cauſes of Senſa- <lb/>tion, as alſo their intermediate
          effects, provided <lb/>ſuch effects are external to the nervous ſub- <lb/>ſtance, very
          readily diſcover themſelves, and are <lb/>clearly comprehended. For indeed they are all
            <pb n="25"/>
          <lb/>bodies that lye within our obſervation (many <lb/>of which are within our reach) and
          the motion <lb/>and impulſe of thoſe bodies, or of particles emit- <lb/>ted therefrom,
          upon the organs of ſenſe: which <lb/>every one not only has a clear idea of, but is
          <lb/>moreover certain of their exiſtence, motion, and <lb/>impulſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Now, as no body whatever can be capable of <lb/>creating Senſation in conſequence of
          its motion <lb/>and impulſe, without preſſing upon the nerve af- <lb/>fected by ſuch
          impulſe; therefore preſſure of the <lb/>medullary ſubſtance contained in the nervous
          <lb/>filaments approaches nearer in order to the im- <lb/>mediate cauſe of Senſation, than
          the motion and <lb/>impulſe of any external object. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Preſſure of the medullary ſubſtance contained <lb/>in the nervous filaments cannot
          indeed be ima- <lb/>gined without ſome alteration in the former ar- <lb/>rangement of
          thoſe material particles which con- <lb/>ſtitute that ſubſtance. But we have no idea
          <lb/>whatever, either viſible or intellectual, how and <lb/>in what manner thoſe particles
          are by ſuch <lb/>preſſure differently juxtapoſited, previouſly to <lb/>Senſation thereby
          excited. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Whence it undeniably follows that preſſure <lb/>upon the medullary ſubſtance
          contained in the <pb n="26"/>
          <lb/>nervous filaments is the laſt in order of all thoſe <lb/>cauſes of Senſation, which
          we have any idea of. <lb/>Thus far and no farther our knowledge in theſe <lb/>matters
          reaches, limited by the outſide of the <lb/>ſeat of Senſation; what paſſes within being
          meer <lb/>conjecture. For if a new poſition of medullary <lb/>particles, which is an
          immediate and unavoidable <lb/>effect of external preſſure, does not diſcover it-
          <lb/>ſelf any more than their conſtitutional arrange- <lb/>ment; what account can we with
          any the <lb/>leaſt degree of modeſty pretend to give of all the <lb/>alterations in the
          nervous ſubſtance ſtill ſubſe- <lb/>quent to ſuch preſſure and to change of place
          <lb/>thereby occaſioned; a regular ſeries of which <lb/>may, for any thing we know to the
          contrary, <lb/>precede the immediate cauſe of ſenſation. </p>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A small ornament in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
      <pb n="27"/>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>SECT. V. </head>
        <head rend="align-center space italic">
          <lb/>The ſalutary Effects of natural Senſation. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">S</hi>ENSATION is always accompanied with <lb/>ſome degree of
          pleaſure or uneaſineſs; no <lb/>animal being indifferent to what he ſees, <lb/>hears, or
          feels. Theſe additional and in ſome <lb/>degree inſeparable affections demonſtrate the di-
          <lb/>rect tendency of Senſation to the preſervation of <lb/>life; inaſmuch as every one
          ſpontaneouſly flies <lb/>from thoſe objects which hurt and are at enmity <lb/>with him,
          and covets ſuch as create ſatisfaction <lb/>and are ſuitable to his intereſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But, tho' no one at firſt ſight would doubt <lb/>whether the perception of pleaſure
          is agreeable <lb/>to his nature, and conducive to its preſervation; <lb/>it may with great
          reaſon be doubted by thoſe <lb/>who reflect a little whether ſuch perception, <lb/>however
          convenient it may ſeem to animal life, <lb/>is alone inſtrumental in its preſervation, and
          <lb/>without the intervention of the contrary affection <lb/>ever conduces to health. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>For uneaſineſs is ſo interwoven in the very <lb/>frame of mortals, that even the
          greateſt preſent <pb n="28"/>
          <lb/>ſatisfaction implies the removing or ſtifling the <lb/>greateſt uneaſineſs which
          before diſquieted. And <lb/>a ſenſe of future pleaſure, as it excites deſire, in <lb/>that
          very deſire implies a preſent uneaſineſs ade- <lb/>quate to the ſuppoſed enjoyment of the
          pleaſure <lb/>in expectation. By which preſent uneaſineſs, <lb/>according to Mr. <hi
            rend="italic">Locke</hi>'s juſt obſervation, the <lb/>will is determined. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>However paradoxical therefore it may ſeem, <lb/>nothing is more true than that
          Anxiety, a real <lb/>evil, is nevertheleſs productive of real good; and, <lb/>tho'
          ſeemingly diſagreeable to Nature, is abſolute- <lb/>ly neceſſary to our preſervation, in
          ſuch a man- <lb/>ner, that without its ſevere but uſeful admoni- <lb/>tions the ſeveral
          ſpecies of animals would ſpeedily <lb/>be deſtroyed. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>For firſt, are not hunger and thirſt very ſalu- <lb/>tary Anxieties? By which the
          nerves of the <lb/>mouth œſophagus and ſtomach excite all ani- <lb/>mals from the firſt
          moment of their birth to ſeize <lb/>on ſuch objects, as are capable of relieving thoſe
          <lb/>natural and healthy but agonizing ſenſations. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Now the real good produced by the gratifica- <lb/>tion of theſe appetites is by no
          means to be pla- <lb/>ced in their preſent gratification alone. What- <lb/>ever he may
          imagine, who being ignorant of the <pb n="29"/>
          <lb/>animal œconomy looks no farther than the actual <lb/>pleaſure which accompanies the
          ſtifling ſuch ſen- <lb/>ſations. For the end herein propoſed by the <lb/>Author of Nature
          is undoubtedly the refection <lb/>of that very body which hungers and thirſts; <lb/>whoſe
          conſtituent particles by the inevitable ef- <lb/>fects of vital action are in a continual
          flux and <lb/>decay; whereas the efficient or coercive cauſes <lb/>of eating and drinking
          are thoſe ſenſations alone, <lb/>which torment every animal to a very good pur- <lb/>poſe.
          Who perhaps would not otherwiſe give <lb/>himſelf the trouble of opening his mouth, much
          <lb/>leſs by hard labour earn food wherewith to fill <lb/>it; even tho' he ſhould be
          aſſured that the loſs <lb/>of meat and drink to-day, tho' not at all incon- <lb/>venient
          to him at preſent, will be ſenſibly felt <lb/>to-morrow by his diſtempered body, and that
          <lb/>his idleneſs and faſting will be ſoon attended <lb/>by fatal conſequences. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Secondly, the introducing freſh air into the <lb/>lungs being as neceſſary for the
          immediate con- <lb/>tinuance of life, as it is for other purpoſes of <lb/>the animal
          œconomy which are more remote, <lb/>and at preſent unknown; therefore every ani- <lb/>mal
          provided with organs of reſpiration, whether <lb/>awake or ſleeping, draws into his breaſt
          and ex- <lb/>pels a quantity of external air ſufficient to diſ- <lb/>tend them from the
          firſt moment of his birth <pb n="30"/>
          <lb/>till the laſt period of life. Which alternate <lb/>action, if he either careleſsly or
          obſtinately omits <lb/>it, he is very ſoon compelled to perform by that <lb/>inexpreſſible
          Anxiety which attends a long de- <lb/>tention of air once admitted as well as the re-
          <lb/>fuſing admiſſion to any air at all. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Thirdly, foraſmuch as voluntary exerciſe of <lb/>the body is no leſs requiſite to the
          due circula- <lb/>tion and ſecretions of the animal fluids, and the <lb/>ſalutary
          conſequences thereon depending, than <lb/>the propulſive action of the heart and the reſi-
          <lb/>lition of the arterial tubes; which the ill effects <lb/>of a ſedentary life
          ſufficiently prove; therefore <lb/>the uneaſy ſenſation that is always occaſioned by
          <lb/>ſatiety and the weariſome condition of idleneſs <lb/>determine all animals, to whom
          activity is thus <lb/>neceſſary, frequently to alter their place of reſi- <lb/>dence, and
          to remove from thoſe objects they <lb/>have long been converſant with, however plea-
          <lb/>ſing and eagerly ſought for they might once have <lb/>been. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Fourthly, all the afore-mentioned inſtances <lb/>of uneaſy ſenſation, however nearly
          allied to <lb/>and often ending in ſickneſs, are nevertheleſs <lb/>the natural effects of
          perfect health. But be- <lb/>ſides theſe there occur ſeveral other anxieties, <lb/>which
          are the unavoidable effects of real ſickneſs <pb n="31"/>
          <lb/>and moreover frequently determine the will of <lb/>the patient to ſuch things as are
          capable either <lb/>of relieving the preſent diſorder or of prevent- <lb/>ing its
          miſchievous conſequences. Thus, to in- <lb/>ſtance in one particular, feaveriſh heat
          threatens <lb/>putrid obſtructions, and at the ſame time occa- <lb/>ſions intenſe thirſt
          and an almoſt inſatiable crav- <lb/>ing for acidulated water. Which deſire, if not
          <lb/>contradicted by the officious and ill-tim'd care of <lb/>the by-ſtanders, procures a
          remedy that is both <lb/>diluting and antiſeptic. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Laſtly, tho' the nervous energy be neither <lb/>abſolutely neceſſary nor alone
          ſufficient to excite <lb/>muſcular action, yet ſuch is the connection be- <lb/>tween the
          nervous and muſcular fibres, however <lb/>really diſtinct from each other, that animal
          ſen- <lb/>ſation often inſtantaneouſly precedes animal ac- <lb/>tion, ſo as to have
          confounded theſe two qua- <lb/>lities, or at leaſt to have made the one appear <lb/>the
          immediate and only cauſe of the other. <lb/>And, what chiefly deſerves our notice whilſt
          we <lb/>are conſidering the ſalutary effects of Senſation, <lb/>Convulſion itſelf, a
          diſtempered exceſs of animal <lb/>motion, which is a frequent effect of uneaſy
          <lb/>Senſation, ſometimes becomes its ſudden and ef- <lb/>ficacious remedy, by removing
          the material <lb/>cauſe of ſuch uneaſy Senſation, and that without <pb n="32"/>
          <lb/>any determination or interpolation of the will <lb/>whatever. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>All which nervous appetites as well as muſcu- <lb/>lar motions, that either preſerve
          or reſtore health, <lb/>and are ſeemingly excited by ſomewhat rational- <lb/>ly
          forecaſting their ſalutary ends, have given riſe, <lb/>I ſuppoſe, to ſome modern
          metaphorical expreſ- <lb/>ſions, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic">Anima</hi> invented by <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Willis</hi> and deifyed by <hi rend="italic">Stahl</hi>. Which figurative
          <lb/>words, tho' not quite philoſophical, are innocent <lb/>and even uſeful, in caſe they
          are applied only to <lb/>avoid periphraſes in relating medical matters of <lb/>fact. But
          young Practitioners, who are often <lb/>told that they are to imitate and aſſiſt Nature,
          <lb/>muſt take great care not to be miſguided by the <lb/>literal ſenſe of words, or fancy
          any thing like <lb/>perſonal conſciouſneſs and intellectual agency in <lb/>the animal
          œconomy. For in ſuch caſe of miſ- <lb/>apprehenſion theſe and the like expreſſions be-
          <lb/>come as abſurd as all the exploded <hi rend="italic">Faculties of <lb/>the
            Ancients</hi>, and, what is much worſe, may be <lb/>as miſchievous as an inſtrument of
          death in the <lb/>hands of a Madman. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="33"/>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>SECT. VI. </head>
        <head rend="space italic hanging">
          <lb/>The Cauſes and Effects of Anxiety and Inſenſi- <lb/>bility, two ſpecies of Senſation
          diſordered tho' <lb/>not deluſive. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">H</hi> AVING contemplated the ſeat cauſes <lb/>and effects of
          natural and true Senſa- <lb/>tion; before we proceed to conſider <lb/>deluſive Senſation,
          the only ſubject of this en- <lb/>quiry, it may be not improper to take ſome no- <lb/>tice
          of thoſe two other diſorders of the ſame <lb/>quality, which were excluded from our
          definition <lb/>of Madneſs, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> præternatural <hi rend="italic"
            >Anxiety</hi> or Sen- <lb/>ſation too greatly excited by real objects, and its
          <lb/>contrary <hi rend="italic">Inſenſibility</hi> or Senſation not ſufficiently
          <lb/>excited by real objects, tho' acting with their uſual <lb/>force and tho' capable of
          engaging the attention <lb/>of all other healthy animals of the ſame ſpecies. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>For, although Madneſs in its proper ſenſe be <lb/>clearly diſtinct from the too
          lively or the too lan- <lb/>guid perception of things really exiſting, it how- <lb/>ever
          very often is preceded by or accompanied <lb/>with the firſt and as often terminates in
          the ſe- <lb/>cond of theſe two diſorders. Beſides the being <lb/>too much affected by
          external impulſe, tho' it <pb n="34"/>
          <lb/>does by no means imply Senſation materially de- <lb/>luſive, inaſmuch as the ideas
          excited by ſuch im- <lb/>pulſe are referred to true and correſponding ob- <lb/>jects; yet
          the quantity of concomitant affection <lb/>not being proportionate and therefore not in
          all <lb/>reſpects correſponding to the natural quantity of <lb/>its real cauſe hath
          apparently ſome deviation from <lb/>abſolute truth, and from the natural and uſual
          <lb/>circumſtances of this animal function. And Sen- <lb/>ſation not proportionate to real
          impulſe, tho' it <lb/>is not ſtrictly ſpeaking deluſive, hath however as <lb/>great a
          deviation from abſolute truth as exceſſive <lb/>Senſation itſelf. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Now Senſation, which in its moſt natural and <lb/>perfect ſtate is ſooner or later
          attended with ſome <lb/>degree of uneaſineſs, may with very little addi- <lb/>tion be
          heightened into Anxiety either by the too <lb/>great or too long continued force of
          external ob- <lb/>jects, or by the illconditioned ſtate of the nerve <lb/>itſelf, whereby
          it is rendered liable to be too <lb/>much affected with the uſual action of ſuch ex-
          <lb/>ternal objects. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>This illconditioned ſtate of the nerve may be <lb/>inhærent in the internal proper
          and unknown <lb/>conſtitution of the medullary ſubſtance, or it <lb/>may be external to
          that ſubſtance, and ariſe from <lb/>the loſs or defect of thoſe membranes which en- <pb
            n="35"/>
          <lb/>velope and ſheathe the ſeat of Senſation, and are <lb/>deſigned to protect it from
          ſuch rude attacks and <lb/>impreſſions as might otherwiſe endanger the diſ- <lb/>ſolution
          of ſo ſoft a matter. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>For, whenever thoſe integuments are quite re- <lb/>moved from a nerve which is endued
          with no <lb/>more than a common ſhare of ſenſibility, An- <lb/>xiety muſt enſue the
          application of any external <lb/>objects that are capable of exciting natural Sen-
          <lb/>ſation. And in fact we find that the laying <lb/>bare any ſenſible part and expoſing
          it to the <lb/>common air, which uſually refreſhes the body <lb/>whilſt cloathed with
          ſkin, immediately diſtracts <lb/>us with intolerable torment. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>For the ſame reaſon Anxiety, which follows <lb/>an entire removal of the nervous
          ſheaths, will in <lb/>ſome degree ariſe whenever thoſe ſheaths are not <lb/>ſtrong and
          ſufficiently compacted ſo as to anſwer <lb/>the purpoſe of defence. That is the ſenſation
          <lb/>of the nervous or medullary fibres, tho' they con- <lb/>tinue the ſame, will be in a
          reverſe proportion <lb/>to the cohæſion of thoſe minute particles which <lb/>conſtitute
          the ſolid and elaſtic fibres. And in <lb/>fact we find that Anxiety is almoſt always the
          <lb/>conſequence of morbid laxity, except where the <lb/>intervention of fat, lymph, or
          viſcid congeſtions <pb n="36"/>
          <lb/>owing to ſuch laxity ſubſtitute an occaſional de- <lb/>fence. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>No wonder is it then that the ſtraining or <lb/>looſening the ſolid parts of human
          bodies ſhould <lb/>frequently render thoſe bodies liable to be vio- <lb/>lently affected
          by ſuch objects as are ſcarce felt <lb/>or attended to by other men, who enjoy a na-
          <lb/>tural or artificial ſtrength and compactneſs of <lb/>fibres. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>And from hence we are enabled to annex a <lb/>true and intelligible meaning to that
          expreſſion <lb/>before taken notice of, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">weakneſs of nerves</hi>. <lb/>Which word <hi rend="italic">weakneſs</hi>
          would not have been ſo <lb/>improper, if it had been joined in idea not to <lb/>that
          ſubſtance which is ſtrictly nervous, but to <lb/>its integuments and contiguous membranes;
          and <lb/>if laxity, an accidental and remote cauſe of ex- <lb/>ceſſive and therefore
          uneaſy Senſation, had not <lb/>been thereby made liable to be miſtaken for its
          <lb/>immediate neceſſary and ſufficient cauſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Whatever may be the cauſe of Anxiety, it <lb/>chiefly diſcovers itſelf by that
          agoniſing impati- <lb/>ence obſervable in ſome men of black <hi rend="italic"
            >November</hi>
          <lb/>days, of eaſterly winds, of heat, cold, damps, <lb/><hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
          Which real miſery of theirs is ſometimes de- <lb/>rided by duller mortals as a whimſical
          affectation. <pb n="37"/>
          <lb/>And of the ſame nature are the perpetual tem- <lb/>peſts of love, hatred, and other
          turbulent paſ- <lb/>ſions provoked by nothing or at moſt by very <lb/>trifles. In which
          ſtate of habitual diſeaſes ma- <lb/>ny drag on their wretched lives; whilſt others,
          <lb/>unequal to evils of which they ſee no remedy but <lb/>death, raſhly reſolve to end
          them at any rate. <lb/>Which very frequent caſes of ſuicide, though ge- <lb/>nerally
          aſcribed to Lunacy by the verdict of a <lb/>good-natured Jury, except where the deceaſed
          <lb/>hath not left aſſets, are no more entitled to the <lb/>benefit of paſſing for
          pardonable acts of madneſs, <lb/>than he who deliberately has killed the man he <lb/>hated
          deſerves to be acquitted as not knowing <lb/>what he did. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Among the morbid effects of Anxiety or the <lb/>præternatural exceſs of Senſation
          one, which fre- <lb/>quently attends upon it and more particularly <lb/>demands our
          attention, is Spaſm or the præter- <lb/>natural exceſs of muſcular action. Which ſtate
          <lb/>of morbid motion, tho' ſometimes ſalutary as has <lb/>been before obſerved, is oftner
          occaſioned by this <lb/>nervous diſorder to no good purpoſe whatever; <lb/>and, when very
          violent or of long continuance, <lb/>is neceſſarily productive of numberleſs evils and
          <lb/>of acute and chronical diſtempers, which if not <lb/>relieved in time almoſt always
          end in death. </p>
        <pb n="38"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Another effect of Anxiety or of the præterna- <lb/>tural exceſs of Senſation is the
          nervous diſorder <lb/>directly contrary to it, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> Inſenſibility,
          that <lb/>is a præternatural defect or total loſs of Senſa- <lb/>tion. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Whether this entire change from one extream <lb/>to the other is owing to the
          material inſtruments <lb/>of Senſation having been ſtrained by Anxiety or <lb/>rather by
          ſome of its cauſes, cannot perhaps be <lb/>determined with any degree of certainty. But
          <lb/>thus much is clear in reaſon that any diſtraction, <lb/>which is ſufficient to
          diſunite or break in pieces <lb/>the medullary ſubſtance, muſt be ſufficient to <lb/>make
          it unfit for its function; and it is as un- <lb/>deniable in fact that Anxiety is
          frequently either <lb/>attended with ſuch ſpaſmodic diſorders or occa- <lb/>ſioned by ſuch
          external injuries as muſt neceſſari- <lb/>ly diſtract the nerves thereby affected. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Not that Inſenſibility is owing to no other <lb/>cauſe except Anxiety. For it is at
          leaſt as often <lb/>occaſioned by the internal and unknown con- <lb/>ſtitution of the
          nervous or medullary ſubſtance <lb/>itſelf, which was either formed imperfect at firſt
          <lb/>or hath ſince degenerated. </p>
        <pb n="39"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>And, beſides the internal and unknown de- <lb/>fect in the ſeat of Senſation,
          Inſenſibility may as <lb/>often be aſcribed to another cauſe external to <lb/>the nerve
          and ſufficiently underſtood. For, <lb/>ſince the nervous integuments or neighbouring
          <lb/>membranes do ſheathe the medullary ſubſtance, <lb/>and thereby prevent the morbid
          exceſs of its <lb/>energy; whenever the fibres that compoſe thoſe <lb/>integuments or
          membranes are præternaturally <lb/>compacted and of too cloſe a texture, inſtead <lb/>of
          moderating they undoubtedly muſt deaden or <lb/>deſtroy Senſation. And for the ſame reaſon
          <lb/>thoſe nerves that are pillowed with fat, ſoaked <lb/>in lymph, or ſtifled by
          obſtructed veſſels, cannot <lb/>and in fact do not receive a proper that is a ſen-
          <lb/>ſible impulſe from external objects, altho' ſuch <lb/>objects are rightly and
          forcibly applied, and al- <lb/>though the nervous ſubſtance itſelf is perfectly
          <lb/>ſound, and in its internal conſtitution fitted for <lb/>the efficacious reception of
          ſuch external im- <lb/>pulſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But, whatever may be the cauſe of Inſenſi- <lb/>bility, its ill effects are many and
          as obvious as <lb/>they are unavoidable, and need not be here <lb/>enumerated. For they
          are all thoſe diſorders in <lb/>the animal œconomy, which Senſation in its <lb/>natural
          vigour was deſigned to prevent. The <pb n="40"/>
          <lb/>defect therefore or loſs of this ſalutary and vital <lb/>quality muſt either hurry on
          or ſuffer the ſickly <lb/>body to approach nearer and nearer to the laſt <lb/>period of
          animal life. </p>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>An ornamental illustration in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
      <pb n="41"/>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>SECT. VII. </head>
        <head rend="align-center space italic">
          <lb/>The Cauſes of Madneſs. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">W</hi>Hoever is ſatisfied with our account of <lb/>the ſeat and
          cauſes of natural and true <lb/>Senſation, will acknowledge that the <lb/>one immediate
          neceſſary and ſufficient cauſe of <lb/>the præternatural and falſe perception of objects,
          <lb/>which either do not exiſt, or which do not in <lb/>this inſtance excite ſuch
          ſenſation, muſt be ſome <lb/>diſorder of that ſubſtance which is medullary and
          <lb/>ſtrictly nervous. And moreover, as he cannot <lb/>diſcover the natural and internal
          conſtitution of <lb/>this medullary ſubſtance, which renders it fit for <lb/>the proper
          perception of real and external im- <lb/>pulſe or rather of the ideas thereby excited; he
          <lb/>muſt for the ſame reaſon own that he is unable <lb/>to diſcover wherein conſiſts that
          præternatural <lb/>and internal ſtate of the ſame nervous matter, <lb/>which diſpoſes it
          to be without any ſuch impulſe <lb/>affected by thoſe very ideas, that would have
          <lb/>been preſented to the imagination, if the ſame <lb/>nervous matter had been acted
          upon by ſome- <lb/>thing external. Or, to ſpeak more technically, <lb/>foraſmuch as the
          one immediate neceſſary and <lb/>ſufficient cauſe of the perception of real objects <pb
            n="42"/>
          <lb/>is unknown, we muſt likewiſe remain entirely <lb/>ignorant of the one immediate
          neceſſary and ſuf- <lb/>ficient cauſe of the perception of Chimæras, <lb/>which exiſt no
          where except in the brain of a <lb/>Madman. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But, altho' the immediate and internal cauſe of <lb/>deluſive as well as of true
          Senſation is abſolutely <lb/>hid, many remoter and external cauſes thereof <lb/>frequently
          diſcover themſelves to the by-ſtander, <lb/>notwithſtanding that the idea thus excited is
          not <lb/>by the patient himſelf referred to any one of thoſe <lb/>true cauſes, but to
          ſomething elſe, which may <lb/>or may not exiſt, and which certainly does not <lb/>in this
          particular caſe act upon the affected or- <lb/>gan. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Thus, to inſtance in a very common accident, <lb/>the eye that is violently ſtruck
          immediately ſees <lb/>flames flaſh before it; which idea of fire <lb/>preſented to the
          imagination plainly ſhews that <lb/>thoſe material particles which conſtitute the
          <lb/>medullary ſubſtance of the optic nerve are af- <lb/>fected by ſuch blow exactly in
          the ſame manner, <lb/>as they are when real fire acts upon the eye of <lb/>a man awake and
          in his ſenſes with force ſuffi- <lb/>cient to provoke his attention. Thus variety of
          <lb/>ſounds diſturb the ear that is ſhocked by the <lb/>pulſation of veſſels, by the
          inflammation or other <pb n="43"/>
          <lb/>obſtruction of thoſe membranes which line the <lb/><hi rend="italic">meatus
            auditorius</hi>, by the intruſion of water, and <lb/>in ſhort by any material force
          external to the <lb/>medullary portion of the ſeventh pair of nerves; <lb/>which force
          hath no connection with any ſono- <lb/>rous body, that by its elaſtic vibration commu-
          <lb/>nicates an undulatory motion to the intermediate <lb/>air. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Now ſuppoſe that any one perfectly awake <lb/>without the accident of ſuch a blow
          ſees fire, or <lb/>without the pulſation of veſſels, inflammation, or <lb/>any obſtruction
          in the <hi rend="italic">meatus auditorius</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
          <lb/>hears ſounds; or ſuppoſe that the idea of flame <lb/>really excited by a blow is by
          him referred to an <lb/>houſe on fire, or the idea of ſound excited by <lb/>the pulſation
          of veſſels, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> is referred to a mu- <lb/>ſical inſtrument,
          which is not near enough to be <lb/>heard, or is not really played upon; the man <lb/>who
          is ſo miſtaken, and who cannot be ſet right <lb/>either upon his own recollection or the
          informa- <lb/>tion of thoſe about him, is in the apprehenſion <lb/>of all ſober perſons a
          Lunatic. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>From whence we may collect that Madneſs <lb/>with reſpect to its cauſe is
          diſtinguiſhable into two <lb/>ſpecies. The firſt is ſolely owing to an internal
          <lb/>diſorder of the nervous ſubſtance: the ſecond is <lb/>likewiſe owing to the ſame
          nervous ſubſtance be- <pb n="44"/>
          <lb/>ing indeed in like manner diſordered, but diſor- <lb/>dered <hi rend="italic">ab
            extra</hi>; and therefore is chiefly to be at- <lb/>tributed to ſome remote and
          accidental cauſe. <lb/>The firſt ſpecies, until a better name can be <lb/>found, may be
          called <hi rend="italic">Original</hi>, the ſecond may <lb/>be called <hi rend="italic"
            >Conſequential Madneſs</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The internal diſorder of the medullary ſub- <lb/>ſtance, or the cauſe of Original
          Madneſs, for the <lb/>ſame reaſon as the immediate neceſſary and ſuf- <lb/>ficient cauſe
          of true Senſation, can be but one: <lb/>but the external and accidental cauſes of Conſe-
          <lb/>quential Madneſs, as well as of true Senſation, may <lb/>be many. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Now no external cauſe whatever can be ſup- <lb/>poſed capable of exciting deluſive
          any more than <lb/>true perception, except ſuch cauſe acts materially <lb/>upon the nerve
          thereby diſordered, and that <lb/>with force ſufficient to alter the former arrange-
          <lb/>ment of its medullary particles. Which force <lb/>neceſſarily implies impulſe and
          preſſure in delu- <lb/>ſive Senſation, in the ſame manner and order as <lb/>it does in the
          perception of objects really correſ- <lb/>ponding thereto. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Preſſure therefore amongſt all the external and <lb/>diſcoverable cauſes of falſe as
          well as of true per- <lb/>ception is in our apprehenſion the neareſt to ſuch <lb/>its
          apparent effect. As to the intermediate al- <pb n="45"/>
          <lb/>terations of the medullary ſubſtance, that may <lb/>really precede deluſive
          Senſation, they are all as <lb/>much unknown as are the nervous effects which
          <lb/>intervene between the preſſure made by any ex- <lb/>ternal object and the true and
          adequate idea of <lb/>that very object. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But, altho' Conſequential Madneſs cannot be <lb/>ſuppoſed without ſome ſort and
          degree of preſ- <lb/>ſure upon the nerves, nevertheleſs every ſort and <lb/>degree of
          preſſure does not always and unavoid- <lb/>ably produce Conſequential Madneſs. For the
          <lb/>nerves may ſuffer external impulſe, and yet the <lb/>preſſure thereby occaſioned
          either may not have <lb/>force ſufficient to excite any idea at all; or it <lb/>may act
          with too great a force and in ſo ſhock- <lb/>ing a manner as to diſſolve or greatly
          diſunite <lb/>the medullary matter; in which caſe Senſation, <lb/>which can never exiſt
          but whilſt that matter does <lb/>properly cohere, inſtead of being perverted will <lb/>be
          aboliſhed, or at leaſt ſuſpended untill the con- <lb/>ſtituent particles are reunited. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>What this particular ſort and degree of preſ- <lb/>ſure is, which is capable of
          creating deluſive Sen- <lb/>ſation, we are not able to aſcertain; becauſe the
          <lb/>different circumſtances of the unknown ſubject <lb/>acted upon will make the nervous
          effects variable <lb/>and oftentimes contrary, notwithſtanding the ac- <pb n="46"/>
          <lb/>tion of the known cauſe conſidered <hi rend="italic">per ſe</hi> is in <lb/>all
          reſpects the ſame. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But, altho' we cannot exactly deſcribe the <lb/>particular ſtrength of that external
          impulſe which <lb/>excites, any more than we can diſcover why it <lb/>excites deluſive
          ideas; thus much we may rea- <lb/>ſonably conclude in general that all material ob-
          <lb/>jects, which by their action or reſiſtance occa- <lb/>ſion a ſufficient but not too
          great a preſſure upon <lb/>the medullary ſubſtance contained in the nerves, <lb/>may be
          the remoter cauſes of Conſequential Mad- <lb/>neſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Which concluſion is not only agreeable to <lb/>reaſon, but is moreover confirmed by
          matter of <lb/>fact and almoſt every day's experience. Witneſs <lb/>the internal exoſtoſes
          of the cranium, the indu- <lb/>rations of the ſinus's and proceſſes of the Dura
          <lb/>Mater, which have frequently been found in <lb/>thoſe who died mad; witneſs the
          intropreſſion <lb/>of the ſkull or concuſſion of the head, which if <lb/>not apoplectic is
          almoſt always attended with a <lb/>delirium. And indeed every one, who contem- <lb/>plates
          ſeveral caſes of Conſequential Madneſs and <lb/>thoſe accidents which precede the ſame,
          will <lb/>find that preſſure of the medullary ſubſtance <lb/>ſomewhere or other collected
          intervenes between <lb/>ſuch accidents and theſe their delirious effects. </p>
        <pb n="47"/>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>One caſe of Conſequential Madneſs that proves <lb/>the intervention of ſuch preſſure
          is an effect of <lb/>Inſolation or what the <hi rend="italic">French</hi> call <hi
            rend="italic">coup du Soleil</hi>. <lb/>An inſtance of which I lately met with in a Sai-
          <lb/>lor, who became raving mad in a moment while <lb/>the Sun beams darted
          perpendicularly upon his <lb/>head. Which maniacal effect of heat could be <lb/>attributed
          to no aſſignable cauſe, except either to <lb/>the violent impreſſion of the Sun's rays
          upon the <lb/>medullary ſubſtance of the brain, which the cra- <lb/>nium in this caſe was
          not able to defend, or to <lb/>the intermediate rarefaction of blood contained in <lb/>the
          veſſels of the Dura or Pia Mater, which veſſels <lb/>being ſuddenly diſtended compreſſed
          the ſame <lb/>medullary ſubſtance. Of the ſame nature and <lb/>owing to the ſame
          rarefaction of fluids in the <lb/>brain are thoſe delirious fevers called Calentures;
          <lb/>one of which was, I ſuppoſe, miſtaken for the <lb/>plague by the <note place="bottom"
            n="*" rend="size(0.75)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Dr. <hi rend="italic">Dover</hi>. </p>
          </note> Author of the <hi rend="italic">Phyſicians laſt Le- <lb/>gacy</hi>, and treated
          with bleeding <hi rend="italic">uſque ad animi <lb/>deliquium</hi>, which indeed is its
          only cure. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Another caſe of Conſequential Madneſs is a <lb/>ſudden inflammation ariſing in thoſe
          membranes <lb/>which ſurround and therefore when thus diſtend- <lb/>ed compreſs the
          contents of the cranium and its <lb/>nervous appendages. This ſtate of inflammation <pb
            n="48"/>
          <lb/>whilſt the patient lives diſcovers itſelf by the ſud- <lb/>den redneſs of the eyes
          external coat, which is <lb/>a part or rather a production of the Dura Mater: <lb/>and
          that membrane after death is frequently upon <lb/>diſſection found turgid and diſcoloured
          with a <lb/>red bloody ſuffuſion, juſt in the ſame manner <lb/>as if it had been
          artificially injected. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Another caſe of Conſequential Madneſs is a <lb/>gradual congeſtion of ſerum or other
          fluid mat- <lb/>ter upon the ſame membranes which envelop the <lb/>medullary ſubſtance;
          whereby thoſe membranes, <lb/>tho' not with equal danger as when they are ſud- <lb/>denly
          inflamed, yet with the ſame delirious ef- <lb/>fects compreſs their nervous contents. This
          ſe- <lb/>rous congeſtion is diſcoverable by the opaque and <lb/>cloudy appearance of the
          cornea, for the ſame <lb/>reaſon as an inflammatory tumor in the Dura <lb/>Mater is
          betrayed by the external coat of the eye <lb/>being tinged with blood. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Preſſure of the medullary ſubſtance, the near- <lb/>eſt in our apprehenſion to
          Madneſs of all its <lb/>known and remoter cauſes, moſt frequently and <lb/>moſt
          effectually produces this its nervous effect, <lb/>whilſt it acts upon the contents of the
          cranium, <lb/>as is evident from the caſes above-mentioned. <lb/>But, altho' the brain is
          undoubtedly the princi- <lb/>pal ſeat of deluſive ſenſation, nevertheleſs it is <pb n="49"/>
          <lb/>not the only one: foraſmuch as the ſame ſangui- <lb/>nary or ſerous obſtructions are
          capable in any other <lb/>nervous part of the body of exciting falſe ideas as <lb/>well as
          in the brain, at leaſt to ſome degree and <lb/>in proportion to the quantity of medullary
          matter <lb/>there collected ſo as to be ſufficiently compreſſed <lb/>by ſuch obſtructions.
          Thus the ſtomach, inteſ- <lb/>tines, and uterus, are frequently the real ſeats of
          <lb/>Madneſs, occaſioned by the contents of theſe viſ- <lb/>cera being ſtopt in ſuch a
          manner as to compreſs <lb/>the many nervous filaments, which here commu- <lb/>nicate with
          one another by the meſenteric gan- <lb/>glia, and which enrich the contents of the ab-
          <lb/>domen with a more exquiſite ſenſation. Thus <lb/>the glutton who goes to-bed upon a
          full ſtomach <lb/>is hagridden in his ſleep. Thus <q rend="italic space indent">
            <lb/>Men prove with child as powerful fancy works: <space dim="vertical" unit="lines"
              quantity="1"> </space>
          </q>
          <lb/>And patients truly hypochondriacal or hyſterical <lb/>refer that load of uneaſineſs
          they feel in their <lb/>bellies to ſome imaginary object, which if it really <lb/>exiſted
          and acted upon their ſenſes would excite <lb/>the very ſame idea. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="50"/>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>SECT. VIII. </head>
        <head rend="align-center space italic">
          <lb/>The Cauſes of Madneſs. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">F</hi>Oraſmuch as præternatural preſſure upon <lb/>the nerves is in
          human apprehenſion the <lb/>neareſt to deluſive ſenſation thereby ex- <lb/>cited; whatever
          injury creates ſuch preſſure muſt <lb/>be a remoter cauſe of Conſequential Madneſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Under this head therefore of remoter cauſes <lb/>are to be ranked the internal
          exoſtoſes of the <lb/>cranium, the induration of the Dura Mater, the <lb/>fracture and
          intropreſſion of the ſkull and con- <lb/>cuſſion of the head, as alſo, if it were of any
          <lb/>ſervice in the cure of madneſs to enumerate <lb/>them, the many and various accidents
          theſe de- <lb/>lirious injuries may be owing to. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>To the ſame number of remoter cauſes we <lb/>muſt add morbid diſtenſions of the
          veſſels conti- <lb/>guous to the medullary ſubſtance. And, as ſe- <lb/>veral caſes
          mentioned in the foregoing ſection are <lb/>clearly reſolvable into ſuch diſtenſions,
          whoſe re- <lb/>moval or diminution will frequently be ſufficient <lb/>to anſwer our
          intention and is almoſt always ne- <lb/>ceſſary and ſerviceable in the cure of this
          diſtem- <pb n="51"/>
          <lb/>per; it may be of uſe to ſpend a little time in <lb/>examining into the nature and
          origin of thoſe <lb/>vaſcular diſtenſions which end in Conſequential <lb/>Madneſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Whoever has attended to the accidents that <lb/>animal bodies are liable to muſt have
          obſerved <lb/>that ſeveral membranes, which in their natural <lb/>ſtate appear ſmooth and
          even, are ſometimes <lb/>ſuddenly at other times gradually elevated be- <lb/>yond the
          ſurface or plane they before helped to <lb/>compoſe. To the firſt of theſe two caſes wri-
          <lb/>ters on Surgery have given the name of <hi rend="italic">Tumors <lb/>by Fluxion</hi>,
          to the ſecond that of <hi rend="italic">Tumors by Con- <lb/>geſtion</hi>; thereby
          aſcribing the quick or ſlow ap- <lb/>pearance of theſe ſwellings to the different mo-
          <lb/>tion of the fluids themſelves, which materially <lb/>formed them, and which according
          to the me- <lb/>dical philoſophy then in faſhion contained all the <lb/>reſources of life
          health and ſickneſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Now, altho' the diſcovery of the blood's cir- <lb/>culation hath demonſtrated that
          the fluids are <lb/>paſſive in every circumſtance of animal life whe- <lb/>ther ſound or
          diſtempered, it will however be <lb/>very uſeful in proſecuting the preſent enquiry to
          <lb/>take into our account the caſes themſelves as diſ- <lb/>tinguiſhed from one another
          by their different <lb/>manner of appearance which cannot be contro- <pb n="52"/>
          <lb/>verted, and then endeavour to aſſign other rea- <lb/>ſons for ſuch their appearance,
          which not only <lb/>really exiſt, but which alſo are ſufficient to pro- <lb/>duce either
          ſpecies of tumor. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Tumors then by Fluxion ending in Madneſs <lb/>are either veſſels diſtended by the
          rarefaction of <lb/>their proper and natural contents, as in the caſe <lb/>of Inſolation;
          or, which is the moſt frequent ac- <lb/>cident, they are the ſame veſſels obſtructed by
          <lb/>the ſudden intruſion of improper fluids into <lb/>ſmaller canals which were never
          deſigned to give <lb/>either a paſſage or admittance to ſuch contents, <lb/>as in the caſe
          of Inflammation. Now this change <lb/>of place and forcible propulſion of fluids from
          <lb/>their natural ducts into improper receptacles muſt <lb/>apparently be owing to ſome
          power external to <lb/>the fluids ſo propelled, which power either was <lb/>not excited or
          did not effectually act the moment <lb/>before ſuch delirious obſtructions took place. But
          <lb/>the ſpaſmodic conſtriction of thoſe muſcular fi- <lb/>bres which ſurround the
          extremities of arteries <lb/>and veins, and are at reſt till ruffled by ſome ac-
          <lb/>cident, is a power occaſionally excited, and <lb/>when acting with ſufficient force
          is capable of <lb/>driving the blood out of its natural channels into <lb/>veſſels not
          originally fitted for its reception. And <lb/>it is moreover a repeated obſervation that
          Mad- <lb/>neſs frequently ſucceeds or accompanies Fever, <pb n="52"/>
          <lb/>Epilepſy, Child-birth, and the like muſcular diſ- <lb/>orders; and that the
          tumultuous and viſibly ſpaſ- <lb/>modic paſſions of joy and anger are all at leaſt
          <lb/>for a time maniacal. But theſe paſſions con- <lb/>ſtringe the muſcles of the head and
          neck, and <lb/>therefore like a ligature force the blood that was <lb/>deſcending in the
          jugular veins back upon the <lb/>minuteſt veſſels of the brain. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Spaſm therefore, when it is productive of tu- <lb/>mors by Fluxion or of ſudden
          diſtenſions in the <lb/>veſſels contiguous to the nervous ſubſtance, as alſo
          <lb/>ſpaſmodic paſſions ſuch as joy and anger are to <lb/>be reckoned amongſt the remoter
          cauſes of Mad- <lb/>neſs. Not but that the ſame muſcular conſtric- <lb/>tion is often
          excited by the application of ſeveral <lb/>external objects; which objects are therefore
          to <lb/>be added to the ſame claſs. For beſides the ma- <lb/>ny well atteſted caſes of
          poiſons or medicines, <lb/>which as ſoon as ſwallowed convulſe the body <lb/>and
          intoxicate the underſtanding, ſuch as Hem- <lb/>loc, and the root lately miſtaken for
          Gentian, <lb/>ſuch as Opium when adminiſtered to ſome par- <lb/>ticular patients, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> The many bottle-com- <lb/>panions whoſe pulſes beat high and
          quick, whoſe <lb/>faces are fluſhed with blood in the ſame manner <lb/>as if they were
          ſtrangled, who are firſt wild and <lb/>then ſtupid, who drink till they ſee double, and
          <lb/>then drink on till they cannot ſee at all, as well <pb n="54"/>
          <lb/>as the crowds of wretches that infeſt our ſtreets <lb/>and fill our hoſpitals,
          evidently prove to the vulgar <lb/>as well as to the Phyſician that vinous ſpirits in-
          <lb/>ſtantaneouſly provoke an irregular action of the <lb/>muſcles ſucceeded by temporary
          delirium; and <lb/>that, if the ſame noxious draughts are taken in <lb/>too large doſes or
          frequently repeated, they be- <lb/>come a very common tho' remoter cauſe of con-
          <lb/>tinual madneſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>If any one rather ſuppoſes that ſuch external <lb/>objects, which produce Madneſs,
          act immediate- <lb/>ly upon the nerves thereby affected, and that <lb/>ſpaſm, tho' an
          undoubted effect of the ſame ob- <lb/>jects, is the companion and not the intervening
          <lb/>cauſe of their delirious effect: However probable <lb/>the contrary opinion may ſtill
          appear to thoſe, <lb/>who conſider that ſpaſm never fails to precede or <lb/>to accompany
          the nervous diſorders ſubſequent <lb/>to ſuch application, and moreover that ſpaſm is
          <lb/>ſufficient to produce maniacal ſymptoms; never- <lb/>theleſs the neareſt known cauſe
          of Madneſs re- <lb/>mains exactly the ſame, and theſe external ob- <lb/>jects are ſtill to
          be reckoned among its remoter <lb/>cauſes, which ever opinion is the more probable.
          <lb/>Since it is impoſſible for any one of them to act <lb/>at all upon the nerves without
          motion impulſe <lb/>and preſſure in the ſame manner and order, as <lb/>if they had
          previouſly occaſioned muſcular con- <pb n="55"/>
          <lb/>ſtriction and vaſcular obſtruction its moſt uſual <lb/>effect. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>As for Tumors by Congeſtion ending in Mad- <lb/>neſs, that is to ſay thoſe loads of
          fluids which <lb/>gradually overcharge the veſſels contiguous to the <lb/>nerves, and by
          compreſſing a ſufficient quantity <lb/>of medullary matter create deluſive ſenſation as
          <lb/>effectually as does inflammation or any ſudden <lb/>diſtenſion of the ſame veſſels:
          ſuch gradual or <lb/>chronical congeſtions are frequently, tho' not al- <lb/>ways, an
          effect of a very different ſort of muſ- <lb/>cular conſtriction, eaſily diſtinguiſhable
          from the <lb/>former by its manner of invaſion and continu- <lb/>ance. For this ſpaſmodic
          action of the muſcu- <lb/>lar fibres is very gentle at firſt, and ſo far from
          <lb/>alarming either the patient or his friends, that <lb/>for ſome time it is very little
          attended to or even <lb/>diſcernable. But what it wants in violence is <lb/>more than made
          up by its obſtinate duration and <lb/>encreaſe: inaſmuch as it ſeldom remits, and is
          <lb/>with great difficulty relieved by art. This ſpe- <lb/>cies therefore of ſpaſm muſt
          likewiſe be added <lb/>to the remoter cauſes of Conſequential Mad- <lb/>neſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>To ſuch conſtant muſcular conſtriction, and <lb/>to the gradual or chronical
          congeſtions in the <lb/>brain or meſenteric viſcera thereby occaſioned, <pb n="56"/>
          <lb/>the deſpairing bigot, incapable in his own ap- <lb/>prehenſion of being pardoned by
          infinite mercy, <lb/>or predeſtined by infinite juſtice to eternal mi- <lb/>ſery before he
          had a being, the moping lover, <lb/>the motionleſs widow or mother bereft of her
          <lb/>children, may at firſt view be aſcribed. Who <lb/>all wear <hi rend="italic"
            >contractæ ſeria frontis</hi>, and diſcover the <lb/>fixed muſcular marks of paſſions
          ſlower indeed <lb/>in their operation than the turbulent ſtorms of <lb/>joy or anger, but
          which in conſequence of preſ- <lb/>ſure upon the nerves are as much the remoter
          <lb/>cauſes of Madneſs, and indeed ſooner or later <lb/>are as deſtructive to every animal
          power. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The ſame Tumors by Congeſtion, capable <lb/>with intervening preſſure of creating
          Conſequen- <lb/>tial Madneſs, are indeed oftentimes an effect of <lb/>laxity in the
          overloaded veſſels themſelves. But <lb/>even this weakneſs, if traced to its original,
          will <lb/>frequently be found owing to one of the two <lb/>aforementioned ſpecies of
          muſcular conſtriction. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>To ſuch vaſcular laxity ariſing from muſcular <lb/>ſpaſm may be referred the many
          inſtances of <lb/>Madneſs occaſioned by præmature, exceſſive, or <lb/>unnatural Venery, by
          Gonorhœas ill cured with <lb/>loads of Mercury and irritating Salts, by fevers, <lb/>and
          other ſuch like convulſive tumults. And <lb/>from hence we may account for the chimærical
            <pb n="57"/>
          <lb/>dreams of infirm and ſhattered Philoſophers, <lb/>who after having ſpent many days
          and nights <lb/>without cloſing their eyes in unwearied endea- <lb/>vours to reconcile
          metaphyſical contradictions, <lb/>to ſquare the circle, to diſcover the Longitude or
          <lb/>grand Secret, have at laſt fallen half aſleep, and <lb/>who by exceſſive attention of
          body have ſtrained <lb/>every animal fibre, and may without a metaphor <lb/>be ſaid to
          have cracked their brains. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>But, altho' laxity ariſing from ſpaſm is moſt <lb/>commonly the cauſe of gradual
          obſtructions end- <lb/>ing in deluſive Senſation, nevertheleſs the ſame <lb/>delirious
          tumors by Congeſtion, more eſpecially <lb/>thoſe that act upon the nervous matter contain-
          <lb/>ed in the abdomen, are formed ſometimes <lb/>without laxity or any ſpaſmodic diſorder
          <lb/>whatever, either by exceſs of eating or by <lb/>defect of voluntary motion: which
          motion is juſt <lb/>as neceſſary to a due propulſion of the fluids <lb/>thro' the uterine
          and hæmorrhoidal veſſels, and <lb/>thro' the many and intricate ramifications of the
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">vena portæ</hi>, as is the action of the heart or the
          <lb/>reſilition of the veſſels themſelves. Gluttony <lb/>therefore and idleneſs are both
          to be added to <lb/>the remoter cauſes of Conſequential Madneſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>To the firſt is owing the meagrim of the Epi- <lb/>cure. To the ſecond, perhaps more
          than to a <pb n="58"/>
          <lb/>ſpirit of lying, may be aſcribed the temptations <lb/>of St. <hi rend="italic"
            >Anthony</hi> and the lazy Monks his followers, <lb/>the extaſies of ſendentary and
          chlorotic Nuns, <lb/>and their frequent converſations with Angelic <lb/>miniſters of
          grace. Not to mention what now <lb/>and then happens to the ſenior Recluſes in our
          <lb/>Proteſtant Monaſteries at <hi rend="italic">Oxford</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
            >Cambridge</hi>. </p>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>An ornamental illustration in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="41"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
