<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Wesley: The desideratum: or, electricity made plain and useful</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>John Wesley</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">THE DESIDERATUM: OR, ELETRICITY Made PLAIN and USEFUL. By a Lover of
              Mankind, and of Common Sense.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T16531</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T16531"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed: and sold by W. Flexney, under Gray's Inn Gate, Holbourn
                  E. Cabe, Ave-Mary Lane George Clark, in Litt'e Carter Lane; George Keith,
                  Grace-Church Street T. Smith, under the Change and at the Foundery, in Moorfields,
                  MDCCLX. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1760</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="6"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="72"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3307919020</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K028112.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: method"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="5"/>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div n="I" type="part">
        <pb xml:id="page_7"/>
        <head rend="align-center space"><lb/>THE <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">DESIDERATUM:</hi>
          <lb/>OR <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">ELECTRICITY made PLAIN. </hi></head>
        <p rend="indent" n="1"><lb/>I. 1. <hi rend="dc(3)">F</hi>ROM a thouſand Experiments it <w
            part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pears</w>, that there is a fluid far more <lb/>ſubtle
          than Air, which is every where diffuſed thro' <lb/>all Space, which ſurrounds the Earth
          and pervades <lb/>every Part of it. And ſuch is the extreme <w part="I">Fine-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ness</w>, Velocity and Expanſiveneſs of this active <lb/>Principle, that all
          other Matter ſeems to be only <lb/>the Body, and this the Soul of the Univerſe. This
          <lb/>we might term <hi rend="italic">Elementary Fire;</hi> but that it is hard <lb/>for us
          to ſeparate the Ideas of <hi rend="italic">Fire</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Burning:</hi>
          <lb/>Altho' the latter is in reality but a preternatural <lb/>and violent Effect of the
          former. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="2"><lb/>2. It is highly probable this is the general <w part="I"
            >Inſtru-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w> of all the Mo<unclear>#</unclear>ion in the
          Univerſe: From this <lb/><hi rend="italic">pure Fire,</hi> (which is properly ſo called)
          the vulgar <lb/><hi rend="italic">Culinary</hi> Fire is kindled. For in Truth there is
          <lb/>but one Kind of Fire in Nature, which exiſts in <lb/>all Places and in all Bodies.
          And this is ſubtle and <lb/>active enough, not only to be, under the Great <lb/>Cauſe, the
          ſecondary Cauſe of Motion, but to <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duce</w> and
          ſuſtain Life thro'out all Nature, as well <lb/>in Animals as in Vegetables. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_8" n="10"/>
        <p rend="indent" n="3"><lb/>3. To this effect the learned Biſhop of <hi rend="italic"
            >Cloyne</hi>
          <lb/>obſerves, "The vital Flame is ſuppoſed to be the <lb/>Cauſe of all the Motions in the
          Body of Man, <lb/>whether natural or voluntary. And has not Fire <lb/>the ſame Force to
          animate thro'out, and actuate <lb/>the whole Syſtem of the World? Cheriſhing, <w part="I"
            >heat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>, fermenting, diſſolving, ſhining, and operating
          <lb/>in various Manners, as various Subjects offer, to <lb/>employ, or to determine it's
          Force? It is <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſent</w> in all Parts of the Earth and
          Firmament, tho' <lb/>latent and unobſerved, till ſome Accident produces <lb/>it into Act,
          and renders it viſible in it's Effects." </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="4"><lb/>4. This great Machine of the World requires <lb/>ſome ſuch
          conſtant, active and powerful Principle, <lb/>conſtituted by it's Creator, to keep the
          heavenly <lb/>Bodies in their ſeveral Courſes, and at the ſame <lb/>Time give Support,
          Life and Increaſe to the <w part="I">vari-</w><lb/><w part="F">ous</w> Inhabitants of the
          Earth. Now as the Heart <lb/>of every Animal is the Engine which circulates the <lb/>Blood
          thro' the whole Body, ſo the Sun, as the <lb/>Heart of the World, circulates this Fire
          thro' the <lb/>whole Univerſe. And this Element is not capable <lb/>of any eſſential
          Alteration, Increaſe or Diminution. <lb/>It is a Species by itſelf; and is of a Nature
          totally <lb/>diſtinct from that of all other Bodies. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="5"><lb/>5. That this is abſolutely neceſſary both to feed <lb/>common
          Fire, and to ſuſtain the Life of <w part="I">Ani-</w><lb/><w part="F">mals</w>, it ſeems
          may be learn'd from an eaſy <w part="I">Experi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w>. Place a Cat,
          together with a lighted Candle, <lb/>in a cold Oven: Then lute the Door cloſe, having
          <lb/>fixt a Glaſs in the Middle of it: And if you look <lb/>thro' this, you may obſerve,
          at one and the ſame <lb/>Inſtant, the Candle goes out, and the Animal dies. <lb/>A plain
          Proof, that the ſame Fire is needful to <w part="I">ſuſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">tain</w> both
          culinary Fire and animal Life: And a <lb/>large Quantity of it. Some doubtleſs pervades
          the <lb/>Oven Door; but not enough to ſuſtain either <lb/>Flame or Life. Indeed every
          Animal is a kind of <lb/>Fire-Engine. As ſoon as the Lungs inſpire the <pb xml:id="page_9"
            n="11"/><lb/>Air, the Fire mingled with it is inſtantly <w part="I">diſperſ-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ed</w> thro' the pulmonary Veſſels into the Blood: <lb/>Thence it is diffuſed
          thro' every Part of the Body, <lb/>even the moſt minute Arteries, Veins and Nerves.
          <lb/>In the mean Time the Lungs inſpire more Air and <lb/>Fire, and ſo provide a conſtant
          Supply. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="6"><lb/>6. The Air ſeems to be univerſally <w part="I"
            >impregnat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> with this Fire, but ſo diluted, as not to hurt
          <lb/>the Animal in Reſpiration. So a ſmall Quantity <lb/>of a Liquor dropt in Water, may
          be friendly to an <lb/>human Body, tho' a few Drops of the ſame <w part="I">Li-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">quor</w>, given by themſelv<unclear>#</unclear>s, would have occaſioned
          <lb/>certain Death. And yet you cannot conceive one <lb/>Particle of the Water, without a
          Particle of the <lb/>Medicine. 'Tis not impoſſible, this may be one <lb/>great Uſe of Air,
          by adhering ſo cloſely to the <lb/>elementary Fire, to temper and render ſalutary to
          <lb/>the Body, what would otherwiſe be fatal to it. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="7"><lb/>7. To put it beyond diſpute, that this Fire is <lb/>largely mixt
          with the Air, you may make the <w part="I">fol-</w><lb/><w part="F">lowing</w> Experiment.
          Take a round Lump of Iron, <lb/>and heat it to a Degree called a <hi rend="italic"
            >welding</hi> Heat: <lb/>Take it out of the Fire, and with a Pair of <w part="I"
            >Bel-</w><lb/><w part="F">lows</w> blow cold Air upon it. The Iron will then <lb/>as
          effectually melt, as if it were in the hotteſt Fire. <lb/>Now when taken out of the Forge,
          it had not Fire <lb/>enough in it to conquer the Coheſion of it's Parts: <lb/>But when
          this Fire is join'd with that which was <lb/>mixt with the Air, it is ſufficient to do it.
          On the <lb/>ſame Principle we account for the Increaſe of a <lb/>Coal or Wood Fire by
          blowing it. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="8"><lb/>8. And let none wonder that Fire ſhould be ſo <lb/>connected
          with Air, as hardly to be ſeparated. As <lb/>ſubtle as Fire is, we may even by Art attach
          it to <lb/>other Bodies; yea, and keep it Priſoner for many <lb/>Years: And that either in
          a ſolid or a fluid Form. <lb/>An Inſtance of the firſt we have in Steel: Which <lb/>is
          made ſuch, only by impacting a large Quantity <lb/>of Fire into Bars of Iron. In like
          Manner we <pb xml:id="page_10" n="12"/><lb/>impact a great Quantity of Fire into Stone, to
          <lb/>make Lime. An Inſtance of the ſecond Kind we <lb/>have in Spirits, wherein Fire is
          impriſon'd in a <lb/>fluid Form. Hence common Spirits will burn all <lb/>away. And if you
          throw into the Air Spirits <w part="I">rec-</w><lb/><w part="F">tified</w> to the higheſt
          Degree, not one Drop will <lb/>come down again, but the univerſal Fire will take <lb/>hold
          of and abſorb it all. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="9"><lb/>9. That this Fire ſubſiſts both in Air, Earth, <lb/>and Water;
          that it is diffuſed thro' all and every <lb/>Part of the Univerſe, was <hi rend="italic"
            >ſuſpected</hi> by many of the <lb/>antient Naturaliſts, and <hi rend="italic"
            >believed</hi> by the great Sir <lb/><hi rend="italic">Iſaac Newton.</hi> But of late
          Years it has been fully demonſtrated: Particularly, by Mr. <hi rend="italic">Stephen
            Gray,</hi>
          <lb/>a Penſioner at the <hi rend="italic">Charterhouſe;</hi> who ſome Years <lb/>ſince
          preſented to the Royal Society, an Account <lb/>of many Experiments he had made, whereby
          this <lb/>ſubtle Fluid became clearly perceptible both to the <lb/>Sight and Feeling.
          Becauſe the Glaſs Tube, by <lb/>Means of which thoſe Experiments were made, <lb/>was
          obſerved when rubbed to attract Straws and <lb/>other light Bodies (a known Property of
          Amber, <lb/>called in <hi rend="italic">Latin Electrum</hi>) <hi rend="italic">theſe</hi>
          Experiments <lb/>were termed <hi rend="italic">electrical:</hi> A Word which was ſoon
          <lb/>affixt to that ſubtle Fluid itſelf, and every Thing <lb/>pertaining to it. But
          improperly enough: Seeing <lb/>the attracting (or ſeeming to attract) Straws and
          <lb/>Feathers, is one of the moſt inconſiderable of all <lb/>the Effects, wrought by this
          powerful and <w part="I">uni-</w><lb/><w part="F">verſal</w> Cauſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="10"><lb/>10. It was afterwards found, that a Glaſs Globe <lb/>was on
          ſome Accounts preferable to a Glaſs <lb/>Tube: Particularly, as it was leſs Labour to turn
          <lb/>the one for ſome Hours together, by means of a <lb/>ſmall Wheel, in the mean Time
          rubbing it with a <lb/>dry Hand, or a little Cuſhion, than to rub the <lb/>Tube for ſo
          long a Time. It w<unclear>#</unclear>s likewiſe <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſerved</w>, that a greater Quantity of ethereal Fire <lb/>might be <hi rend="italic"
            >collected</hi> by this Means than by the other. <pb xml:id="page_11" n="13"/><lb/>I ſay
            <hi rend="italic">collected;</hi> for that Fire is no more <hi rend="italic"
            >created</hi> by <lb/>rubbing, than Water is by pumping. The grand <lb/>Reſervoir
          thereof is the Earth, from which it is <lb/>diffuſed thro' all the other Parts of common
            <w part="I">Mat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w>. Accordingly in theſe Experiments, the
          Globe <lb/>rubbing againſt the Cuſhion, collects Fire from it. <lb/>The Cuſhion receives
          it from the Frame of the <lb/>Machine; the Frame of the Machine from the <lb/>Floor. But
          if you cut off the Communication <lb/>with the Floor, no Fire can be <hi rend="italic"
            >produced,</hi> becauſe <lb/>none can be <hi rend="italic">collected.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="11"><lb/>11. In the Year 1746, Mr. de <hi rend="italic"
            >Muſchenbroek,</hi>
          <lb/>Profeſſor of natural Philoſophy at <hi rend="italic">Leyden,</hi> was led <lb/>by a
          caſual Experiment, into many new <w part="I">Diſcove-</w><lb/><w part="F">ries</w>. Theſe
          were chiefly made by Means of a <lb/>large but thin Glaſs Phial. The beſt way to <w
            part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">pare</w> which is, to coat it with thin Lead; to line
          <lb/>it on the inſide with Leaf-Gold, to within two <lb/>Inches of the Top, and to faſten
          ſome Tinſel Fringe <lb/>to the Bottom, (or to the End of the Wire within <lb/>the Phial)
          ſo as to touch the Gold Lining. By <lb/>this Wire going thro' the Cork, the Phial is hung
          <lb/>on any metallic Body, which communicates by a <lb/>Wire, with the Globe or Tube. This
          metallic <lb/>Body has been term'd, <hi rend="italic">the prime Conductor,</hi> as it
          <lb/>conducts or conveys the Fire collected by the Tube <lb/>or Globe, either into the
          Phial, or into any other <lb/>Body communicating therewith. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="12"><lb/>12. But all Bodies are not capable of receiving <lb/>it. There
          is in this Reſpect an amazing <w part="I">Differ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ence</w> between
          them. The Excrements of Nature, <lb/>as Wax, Silk, Hair, will not receive the ethereal
          <lb/>Fire, neither convey it to other Bodies: So that <lb/>whenever in circulating it
          comes to any of theſe, <lb/>it is at a full ſtop. Air itſelf is a Body of this <lb/>Kind;
          with great Difficulty either receiving or <lb/>conveying this Fire to other Bodies: So are
          Pitch <lb/>and Roſin (Excrements, as it were, of Trees). To <pb xml:id="page_12" n="14"
          /><lb/>theſe we may add Glaſs, Amber, Brimſtone, dry <lb/>Earth, and a few other Bodies.
          Theſe have been <lb/>frequently ſtiled <hi rend="italic">Electrics per ſe;</hi> as if they
          alone <lb/>contain'd the <hi rend="italic">electric Fire:</hi> An eminently improper
          <lb/>Title, founded on a palpable Miſtake. From the <lb/>ſame Miſtake, all other Bodies,
          which eaſily <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceive</w> and readily convey it, were
          term'd <hi rend="italic">Non <w part="I">elec-</w><lb/><w part="F">trict</w>;</hi> on a
          Suppoſition, that they contain'd no <lb/><hi rend="italic">electric Fire:</hi> The
          contrary of which is now <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">low'd</w> by all. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="13"><lb/>13. That this Fire is inconceivably ſubtle, <w part="I"
            >ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pears</w> from it's permeating even the denſeſt <w part="I"
            >Me-</w><lb/><w part="F">tals</w>, and that with ſuch Eaſe, as to receive no <w part="I"
            >per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceptible</w> Reſiſtance. If any one doubt, whether it
          <lb/>paſs thro' the Subſtance, or only along the Surface of Bodies, a ſtrong Shock taken
          thro' his own <w part="I">Bo-</w><lb/><w part="F">dy</w>, will prevent his doubting any
          longer. It <w part="I">dif-</w><lb/><w part="F">fers</w> from all other Matter in this,
          that the <w part="I">Par-</w><lb/><w part="F">ticles</w> of it repell, not attract, each
          other. And <lb/>hence is the manifeſt Divergency in a Stream of <lb/>electrical Effluvia.
          But tho' the Particles of it <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">pell</w> each other, yet
          are they attracted by all other <lb/>Matter. And from theſe thr e, the extreme <w part="I"
            >ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F">tlety</w> of this Fire, the mutual Repulſion of its Parts,
          <lb/>and the ſtrong Attraction of them by other <w part="I">Mat-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ter</w>, ariſes this Effect, that if a Quantity of <w part="I">elec-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tric</w> Fire be applied to a Maſs of common Matter <lb/>of any Bigneſs or
          Length, (which has not already <lb/>got its Quantity) it is immediately diffuſed thro'
          <lb/>the whole. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="14"><lb/>14. It ſeems, this Globe of Earth and Water, <lb/>with its
          Plants, Animals, Buildings, have diffuſed <lb/>thro' their whole Subſtance, juſt as much
          of this <lb/>Fire as they will contain. And this we may term <lb/>their <hi rend="italic"
            >natural Quantity.</hi> This is not the ſame in all <lb/>Kinds of Matter: Neither in the
          ſame Kind of <lb/>Matter in all Circumſtances. A ſolid Foot of one <lb/>Kind of Matter (as
          Glaſs) contains more of it than <pb xml:id="page_13" n="15"/><lb/>a ſolid Foot of another
          Kind. And a Pound <lb/>Weight of the ſame Kind of Matter, when <w part="I"
            >rare-</w><lb/><w part="F">fied</w>, contains more than it did before. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="15"><lb/>15. We know that this Fire is <hi rend="italic">in</hi> common
          <lb/>Matter, becauſe we can pump it <hi rend="italic">out,</hi> by the Globe <lb/>or Tube:
          We know that common Matter has <lb/>near as much of it as it can contain, becauſe if we
          <lb/>add a little more to any Portion of it, the <w part="I">addi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tional</w> Quantity does not enter, but forms a Kind <lb/>of Atmoſphere round it. On
          the other Hand, we <lb/>know that common Matter has not more of it <lb/>than it can
          contain. Otherwiſe all looſe Portions <lb/>of it would repel each other; as they
          conſtantly do, <lb/>when they have ſuch Atmoſpheres. Had the Earth, <lb/>for Inſtance, as
          much electric Fire in Proportion, <lb/>as we can give to a Globe of Iron or Wood, the
          <lb/>Particles of Duſt and other light Matter, would <lb/>not only repel each other, but
          be continually <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">pelled</w> from the
            E<unclear>#</unclear>rth. Hence the Air being <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſtantly</w> loaded therewith, would be unfit for <w part="I">Re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſpiration</w>. Here we ſee another Occaſion to adore <lb/>that Wiſdom, which has made
          all Things by <lb/>Weight and Meaſure. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="16"><lb/>16. The Form of every electric Atmoſphere, is <lb/>that of the
          Body which it ſurrounds: Becauſe it is <lb/>attracted by every Part of the Surface, tho'
          it <w part="I">can-</w><lb/><w part="F">not</w> enter the Subſtance already replete.
          Without this Attraction, it would not remain round the <w part="I">Bo-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >dy</w>, but diſſipate into the Air. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="17"><lb/>17. The Atmoſphere of an electrified Sphere, is <lb/>not more
          eaſily drawn off, from any one Part of <lb/>it than from the other, becauſe it is equally
            <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tracted</w> by every Part. But it is not ſo with <w
            part="I">Bo-</w><lb/><w part="F">dies</w> of other Figures. From a Cube it is more
          <lb/>eaſily drawn off at the Corners than at the Sides: <lb/>And ſo from the Corners of
          Bodies of any other <lb/>Form, and moſt eaſily from the ſharpeſt Corners. <lb/>For the
          Force with which an electrified Body <w part="I">re-</w><pb xml:id="page_14" n="16"
            /><lb/><w part="F">tains</w> it's Atmoſphere, is proportion'd to the <w part="I"
            >Sur-</w><lb/><w part="F">face</w> on which that Atmoſphere reſts. So a <w part="I"
            >Sur-</w><lb/><w part="F">face</w> four Inches ſquare retains it's Atmoſphere, <lb/>with
          ſixteen Times the Force that one of an Inch <lb/>ſquare does. And as in pulling the Hairs
          from an <lb/>Horſe's Tail, a Force inſufficient to pull off an <lb/>Handful at once, could
          eaſily pull it off Hair by <lb/>Hair: So tho' a blunt Body can't draw off all the
          <lb/>Atmoſphere at once, a pointed one can eaſily draw <lb/>it off, Particle by Particle. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="18"><lb/>18. If you would have a ſenſible Proof, how <lb/>wonderfully
          pointed Bodies draw off the electric <lb/>Fire, place an Iron Shot of four Inches Diameter
          <lb/>on the Mouth of a dry Bottle. Suſpend over it a <lb/>ſmall Cork-Ball by a ſilken
          Thread, juſt ſo as to <lb/>reſt againſt the Side of the Shot. Electrify the <lb/>Shot, and
          the Ball will be repelled four or five <lb/>Inches from it. Then preſent to the Shot ſix
          or <lb/>eight Inches off the Point of a ſharp Bodkin. The <lb/>Fire is inſtantly drawn
          off; ſo the Repulſion ceaſes, <lb/>and the Ball flies to the Shot. But a blunt Body
          <lb/>will not produce this Effect, till it is brought <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">in</w> an Inch of the Shot. If you preſent the Point <lb/>of the Bodkin in the
          Dark, you may ſee <w part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F">times</w> at a Foot Diſtance, a
          Light gather upon it <lb/>like a Glow-worm, which is manifeſtly the Fire it <lb/>extracts
          from the Shot. The leſs ſharp the Point <lb/>is, the nearer it muſt be brought, before you
          can <lb/>ſee the Light. And at whatever Diſtance you ſee <lb/>the Light, you may draw off
          the electric Fire. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="19"><lb/>19. To be convinced that pointed Bodies <hi rend="italic"
            >throw</hi>
          <lb/>off, as well as <hi rend="italic">draw</hi> off the Fire, you may lay a <lb/>long
          ſharp Needle on the Shot. It cannot then be <lb/>electrified, ſo as to repel the Ball,
          becauſe the Fire <lb/>thrown upon it, continually runs off, at the Point <lb/>of the
          Needle: From which in the Dark you may <lb/>ſee ſuch a Stream of Light, as in the
          preceeding <lb/>Inſtance. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_15" n="17"/>
        <p rend="indent" n="20"><lb/>20. While the electric Fire, which is in all <w part="I"
            >Bo-</w><lb/><w part="F">dies</w>, is left to itſelf, undiſturb'd by any external
          <lb/>Violence, it is more or leſs denſe, according to the <lb/>Nature of the Body which it
          is in. In denſe <w part="I">Bo-</w><lb/><w part="F">dies</w> it is more rare: In rare
          Bodies it is more denſe. <lb/>Accordingly every Body contains ſuch a Quantity <lb/>of it,
          rare or denſe, as is ſuitable to it's Nature. <lb/>And there is ſome Reſiſtence to every
          Endeavour <lb/>of altering it's Denſity, in the whole of any Body, <lb/>or in any Part of
          it. For all Bodies reſiſt either <lb/>the Increaſe or Diminution of their natural <w
            part="I">Quan-</w><lb/><w part="F">tity</w>. And on the other Hand, when it has been
          <lb/>either increaſed or diminiſhed, there is a Reſiſtence <lb/>to it's Return to it's
          natural State. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="21"><lb/>21. With regard to the different Reſiſtence made <lb/>by
          different Bodies, in either of theſe Caſes, it is an <lb/>invariable Rule, that Glaſs,
          Wax, Roſin, <w part="I">Brim-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtone</w>, Silk, Hair, and ſuch like
          Bodies, reſiſt the <lb/>moſt: And next to theſe, the Air, provided it be <lb/>dry, and in
          a ſufficient Quantity. That this <w part="I">Re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſiſtence</w> is leaſt
          in Metals, Minerals, Water, <w part="I">Quick-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſilver</w>, Animals and
          Vegetables: Which we may <lb/>rank together, becauſe the Difference in their <w part="I"
            >Re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſiſtence</w> is very inconſiderable: And that in theſe
          <lb/>Bodies the Reſiſtence is greater, when their <w part="I">Sur-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >face</w> are poliſh'd, and extended in length, than <lb/>when their Surfaces are rough
          and ſhort, or end in <lb/>ſharp Points. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="22"><lb/>22. When a Body has more electric Fire forced <lb/>into it,
          than it has naturally, it is ſaid to be <w part="I">elec-</w><lb/><w part="F">tified</w>
          <hi rend="italic">poſitively.</hi> When Part of the natural <w part="I">Quanti-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ty</w> is taken away, it is ſaid to be electrified <hi rend="italic"
            >negative-<lb/>ly.</hi> Now when an Iron Bar is <hi rend="italic">negative'y</hi>
          electrified, <lb/>the Fire drawn out, does not go in again as ſoon <lb/>as the Experiment
          is over, but forms an <w part="I">Atmoſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">phere</w> round it, becauſe
          of the Reſiſtence it finds in <lb/>it's Endeavour to dilate itſelf, either into the Air
          <lb/>or into the Bar. And when it is electified <hi rend="italic">poſitively,</hi>
          <pb xml:id="page_16" n="18"/><lb/>the ſame Kind of Atmoſphere is form'd, by the <lb/>Fire
          accumulated upon it. Whether therefore <w part="I">Bo-</w><lb/><w part="F">dies</w> are
          electrified negatively or poſitively, and <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">main</w> ſo
          when the Experiment is over, there are <w part="I">ſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">milar</w>
          Atmoſpheres ſurrounding them, which will <lb/>produce ſimilar Effects. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="23"><lb/>23. But we can electrify no Body beyond a <w part="I"
            >cer-</w><lb/><w part="F">tain</w> Degree: Becauſe when any is electrified to <lb/>that
          Point, it has an Atmoſphere round it <w part="I">ſufficient-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w>
          ſtrong to ballance any Power that endeavours to <lb/>electrify it farther. Nor is the
          electric Fire either <lb/>from the Tube or the Globe, able to force its Way <lb/>thro'
          this. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="24"><lb/>24. And in the ordinary Courſe of Nature, this <lb/>ſubtle,
          active Fluid, which not only ſurrounds <w part="I">eve-</w><lb/><w part="F">ry</w> groſs
          Body, but every component Particle of <lb/>each, where it is not in abſolute Contact with
          it's <lb/>neighbouring Particle, can never be idle, but is <lb/>ever in Action, tho' that
          Action be imperceptible <lb/>to our Senſes. It is ever varying it's Condition, tho'
          imperceptibly, in all Parts of all Bodies <w part="I">what-</w><lb/><w part="F">ever</w>;
          and electrifying them more or leſs, tho' not <lb/>ſo forcibly as to give ſenſible Signs of
          it. All <w part="I">Bo-</w><lb/><w part="F">dies</w> then, and all their component
          Particles, when <lb/>in their natural Situation, have round their <w part="I"
            >Surfa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ces</w>, where they are not in abſolute Contact with
          <lb/>other Surfaces, an imperceptible Atmoſphere <w part="I">ſuffi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cient</w> to ballance the ſmaller Force with which they <lb/>are attack'd: Every Way
          ſimilar to the perceptible <lb/>Atmoſphere of Bodies forcibly electrified. In theſe
          <lb/>imperceptible Atmoſpheres is placed the Power <lb/>which reſiſts their being
          electrified to an higher <lb/>Degree than they are naturally. And this Power <lb/>lies in
          the Elaſticity of the ſubtle Fluid, every <lb/>where diſperſed both round all Bodies and
          in <lb/>them. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="25"><lb/>25. Glaſs is very difficultly electified, which ſeems <lb/>to
          prove it has a very denſe electric Atmoſphere. <pb xml:id="page_17" n="19"/><lb/>Metals
          are eaſily electrified. Conſequently they <lb/>have rare and therefore weakly-reſiſting <w
            part="I">Atmoſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">pheres</w>. But as Heat rarefies all Bodies, ſo if
          Glaſs <lb/>be heated to a certain Degree, even below melting, <lb/>it will give as free a
          Paſſage to the electric Fire, <lb/>as Braſs or Iron does: The Atmoſphere round it
          <lb/>being then rendered as rare as that of Metals. Nay, <lb/>when melted, it makes no
          more Reſiſtence than <lb/>Water. But it's Reſiſtence increaſes, as it cools. <lb/>And when
          it is quite cold, it reſiſts as forcibly as <lb/>ever. Smoothly-poliſh'd Wax reſiſts as
          much as <lb/>Glaſs. But even the ſmall Heat raiſed by rubbing, <lb/>will render it's
          Atmoſphere as rare as that of <w part="I">Me-</w><lb/><w part="F">tals</w>, and ſo
          intirely deſtroy it's Reſiſtence. The <lb/>ſame is true of Roſin and Brimſtone. Even the
          <lb/>Heat ariſing from Friction, deſtroys the Reſiſtence <lb/>which they naturally make to
          being electrified: A <lb/>ſtrong Proof, that the Reſiſtence of all Bodies <w part="I"
            >there-</w><lb/><w part="F">to</w>, is exerted at their Surfaces, and cauſed by an
          <lb/>electric Atmoſphere of different Denſities, <w part="I">accord-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ing</w> to different Circumſtances. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="26"><lb/>26. Moſt Experiments will ſucceed as well with <lb/>a Globe of
          Brimſtone, as with one of Glaſs. Yet <lb/>there is a conſiderable Difference in their
          Nature. <lb/>What Glaſs repells, Brimſtone (as alſo Roſin) <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tracts</w>. Rubbed Glaſs emits the electric Fire: <lb/>Rubbed Brimſtone, Roſin
          and Wax receive it. <lb/>Hence if a Glaſs Globe be turned at one end of a <lb/>prime
          Conductor, and a Brimſtone one at the other, <lb/>not a Spark of Fire can be obtain'd; one
          receiving <lb/>it in, as faſt as it is given out by the other. Hence <lb/>alſo if a Phial
          be ſuſpended on the prime <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ductor</w>, with a Chain
          from it's Coating to the <w part="I">Ta-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w>, and only one Globe
          turned, it will be <w part="I">elec-</w><lb/><w part="F">trified</w> (or <hi rend="italic"
            >charged,</hi> as they term it) by twenty turns <lb/>of the Wheel: After which it may be
            <hi rend="italic">diſcharged,</hi>
          <lb/>that is, unelectrified, by twenty Turns of the other <lb/>Wheel. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_18" n="20"/>
        <p rend="indent" n="27"><lb/>27 The Difference between <hi rend="italic">Non Electrics</hi>
          <w part="I">(vul-</w><lb/><w part="F">garly</w> ſpeaking) and <hi rend="italic">Electrics
            per ſe,</hi> is chiefly this. <lb/>1. A <hi rend="italic">Non Electric</hi> eaſily
          ſuffers a Change, in the <lb/>Quantity of Fire it contains. It's whole Quantity <lb/>may
          be leſſen'd by drawing out a Part, which it <lb/>will afterwards reſume. But you can only
          leſſen <lb/>the Quantity contain'd in one of the Surfaces of an <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Electric:</hi> And not that, but by adding at the ſame <lb/>Time an equal Quantity to
          the other Surface. So <lb/>that the whole Glaſs will always have the ſame <lb/>Quantity in
          it's two Surfaces And even this can <lb/>only be done in Glaſs that is thin: Beyond a <w
            part="I">cer-</w><lb/><w part="F">tain</w> Thickneſs we know no Power that can make
          <lb/>this Change. 2. The ethereal Fire freely moves <lb/>from Place to Place, in and thro'
          the Subſtance of <lb/>a <hi rend="italic">Non Electric.</hi> But thro' the Subſtance of an
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Electric</hi> it will by no Means paſs. It freely <w part="I"
            >en-</w><lb/><w part="F">ters</w> an Iron-Rod, and moves from one End to <lb/>another,
          where the Overplus is diſcharged. But <lb/>it will not enter, or move thro a Glaſſ-Rod. <w
            part="I">Nei-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> will the thinneſt Glaſs which can be made,
          <lb/>ſuffer any Particle of it entering one of it's <w part="I">Sur-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >faces</w>, to paſs thro' to the other. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="28"><lb/>28. Indeed it is only Metals and Liquids, that <lb/>perfectly
            <hi rend="italic">conduct</hi> (or tranſmit) this Fire. Other <w part="I">Bo-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">dies</w> ſeem to conduct it, only ſo far as they contain <lb/>a Mixture of
          theſe; accordingly, moiſt Air will <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">duct</w> it, in
          Proportion to it's Moiſtneſs. But dry <lb/>Air will not conduct it at all: On the
          contrary, it <lb/>is the main inſtrument, in confining any electric <lb/>Atmoſphere, to
          the Body which it ſurrounds. Dry <lb/>Air prevents it's diſſipating (which it does
          preſently <lb/>when <hi rend="italic">in vacuo</hi>) or paſſing from Body to Body. <lb/>A
          clear Bottle full of Air, inſtead of Water, <w part="I">can-</w><lb/><w part="F">not</w>
          be electrified. But exhauſted of Air, it is <w part="I">elec-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >trified</w> as effectually as if it was full of Water. <lb/>Yet an Electrical
          Atmoſphere and Air, do not <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">clued</w> one another. For
          we breath in it freely, <pb xml:id="page_19" n="21"/><lb/>and dry Air will blow thro' it,
          without altering it at all. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="29"><lb/>29. When a Glaſs Phial is electrified, <w part="I"
            >whate-</w><lb/><w part="F">ver</w> Quantity of Fire is accumulated on the <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ner</w> Surface, an equal Quantity is taken from the
          <lb/>outer. Suppoſe, before the Operation begins, the <lb/>Quantity of Fire contain'd in
          each Surface, is <lb/>equal to twenty Grains: Suppoſe at every Turn of <lb/>the Globe, one
          Grain is thrown in: Then after <lb/>the firſt Stroke there are twenty one within, <w
            part="I">nine-</w><lb/><w part="F">teen</w> only without: After the ſecond, the inner <w
            part="I">Sur-</w><lb/><w part="F">face</w> will have twenty-two, the outer but eighteen:
          <lb/>And ſo on, till after twenty Strokes, the inner <lb/>will have forty, the outer none.
          And the. <w part="I">Opera-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> ends: For no Power or Art of Man
          can throw <lb/>any more on the inner Surface, when no more <lb/>can be taken from the
          outer. If you attempt to <lb/>throw more in, it is thrown back thro' the Wire, <lb/>or
          flies cut in Cracks thro' the Sides of the Phial. <lb/>The Equilibrium cannot be reſtored
          in this Phial, <lb/>but by a Communication form'd between the inner <lb/>and outer
          Surface, by ſomething external, touching <lb/>both the outer, and the Wire which
          communicates <lb/>with the inner Surface. If you touch theſe by <lb/>Turns, it is reſtored
          by Degrees: If both at once, <lb/>it is reſtored inſtantly. But then there is a Shock
          <lb/>occaſioned by the ſudden paſſing of the Fire thro' <lb/>the Body, in it's Way from
          the inner to the outer <lb/>Surface. For it moves from the Wire to the <w part="I"
            >Fin-</w><lb/><w part="F">ger</w>, (not from the Finger to the Wire, as is <lb/>commonly
          ſuppoſed). Thence it paſſes thro' the <lb/>Body to the other Hand, and ſo to the outer <w
            part="I">Sur-</w><lb/><w part="F">face</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="30"><lb/>30. The Force with which this Shock may be <lb/>given, is far
          greater than one would conceive. <lb/>It will kill Rats, Hens, or even Turkeys in a <w
            part="I">Mo-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w>: Others, that are not quite killed, it ſtrikes
          <lb/>blind. It will give Polarity to a fine Needle, <w part="I">mak-</w><pb
            xml:id="page_20" n="22"/><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> it point North and South, as if
          touched by a <lb/>Loadſtone. It will invert the Polarity of a <w part="I">Com-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">pass</w>, and make the North Point turn to the South. <lb/>At the ſame Time the
          Ends of the Needles are <w part="I">fine-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> blued like the Spring
          of a Watch. It will melt <lb/>off the Heads and Points of Pins and Needles: And
          <lb/>ſometimes the whole Surface of the Needle is run <lb/>and appears as it were
          bliſter'd, when examined by <lb/>a magnifying Glaſs. It will melt thin Gold or <w part="I"
            >Sil-</w><lb/><w part="F">ver</w>, when held tight between two Panes of Glaſs,
          <lb/>together with the Surface of the Glaſs itſelf, and <lb/>incorporate them in a fine
          Enamel. Yea a ſtrong <lb/>Spark from an electrified Phial, makes a fair Hole <lb/>thro' a
          Quire of Paper doubled: Which is thought <lb/>good Armour againſt the Puſh of a Sword, or
          <lb/>even a Piſtol Bullet. And 'tis amazing to obſerve <lb/>in how ſmall a Portion of
          Glaſs, a great Electrical <lb/>Force may be. A thin Glaſſ-Bubble, about an <lb/>Inch
          Diameter, being half filled with Water, <w part="I">part-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> gilt
          on the outſide, when electrified gives as <lb/>ſtrong a Shock as a Man can well bear:
          Allowing <lb/>then that it contains no more Fire after charging <lb/>than before, how much
          Fire muſt there be in this <lb/>ſmall Glaſs! It ſeems to be a Part of it's very <w
            part="I">Sub-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtance</w>. Perhaps if that Fire could be ſeparated
          <lb/>from it, it would be no longer Glaſs. It might in <lb/>loſing this loſe its moſt
          eſſential Properties, it's <lb/>Tranſparency, Brittleneſs, and Elaſticity. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="31"><lb/>31. Some have not improbably ſuppoſed, that all <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Electric</hi> Bodies, ſo called, are by their original <w part="I"
            >Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtitution</w>, thro'ly ſaturated with Electric Fire: That
          <lb/>it remains fixt in them, (unleſs while the Texture <lb/>of thoſe Bodies is quite
          alter'd by Liquefaction) <lb/>that Fire fixt in a Body conſtitutes an <hi rend="italic"
            >Electric,</hi> and <lb/>all Bodies where it is not fixt are <hi rend="italic">Non
            Electrics.</hi>
          <lb/>Agreeably to which they ſuppoſe that in all <hi rend="italic">Non
            <lb/>Electrics,</hi> the Original Fire, looſely inhering, is <lb/>eaſily driven on by
          the new collected Fire, which <pb xml:id="page_21" n="23"/><lb/>then poſſeſſes its Place:
          But that in <hi rend="italic">Electrics</hi> the <lb/>Original Fire being impacted into
          their Subſtance, <lb/>and therefore more firmly inhering, will not give <lb/>Way to, or be
          driven on by, the new collected <lb/>Fire. Such is Air in particular; with the Particles
          <lb/>of which the original Fire is cloſely incorporated. <lb/>Dry Air ſeems to be ſo fully
          ſaturated with it, that <lb/>it is ſcarce capable of receiving any more: <w part="I"
            >Where-</w><lb/><w part="F">as</w> all n<unclear>#</unclear>w-collected Fire is
          continually <w part="I">endeavour-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> to return into the Earth.
          Let Wires be <w part="I">elec-</w><lb/><w part="F">trified</w> ever ſo ſtrongly, yet the
          Moment any Part <lb/>of them is touch'd by a Perſon ſtanding on the <lb/>Floor, they are
          electrified no longer; all the Fire <lb/>eſcaping thro' him into the Earth. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="32"><lb/>32. Upon the Principles of Electricity, we may <lb/>give a more
          rational Account, of many <w part="I">Appearan-</w><lb/><w part="F">ces</w> in Nature,
          than has yet been done: Of <w part="I">Thun-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w> and Lightning in
          particular. In order to which <lb/>we may obſerve, all electrified Bodies retain the
          <lb/>Fire thrown into them, till ſome Non-electric <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >proaches</w>: To which it is then communicated with <lb/>a Snap, and becomes equally
          divided. Electric Fire <lb/>is ſtrongly attracted by Water, and readily mixes <lb/>with
          it. And Water being electrified, the Vapours <lb/>ariſing from it, are equally
          electrified. As theſe <lb/>float in the Air, they retain the additional Fire, till
          <lb/>they meet with Clouds not ſo much electrified. <lb/>Then they communicate it with a
          Shock. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="33"><lb/>33. The Ocean is compounded of Water, and <lb/>Salt; one an
          Electric, the other not. When there <lb/>is a Friction among the Parts near its Surface,
          the <lb/>Fire is collected from the Parts below. It is then <lb/>plainly viſible in the
          Night, at the Stern of every <lb/>failing Veſſel. It appears from every Daſh of an
          <lb/>Oar: In Storms the whole Sea ſeems on Fire. The <lb/>Particles of Water then repell'd
          from the electrified <lb/>Surface, continually carry off the Fire as it is <w part="I"
            >col-</w><lb/><w part="F">lected</w>. They riſe and form Clouds which are <w part="I"
            >high-</w><pb xml:id="page_22" n="24"/><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> electrified, and retain
          the Fire till they have an <lb/>Opportunity of diſcharging it. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="34"><lb/>34. Particles of Water riſing in Vapours, attach
          <lb/>themſelves to Particles of Air. One Particle of Air <lb/>may be ſurrounded by twelve
          Particles of Water as <lb/>large as itſelf, all touching it, and by more added <lb/>to
          them. Particles of Air thus loaded would be <lb/>drawn nearer together by the mutual
          Attraction of <lb/>the Particles of Water, did not the Fire, Common <lb/>or Electric,
          included therein, aſſiſt their mutual <lb/>Repulſion. Hence they continue ſuſpended. But
          <lb/>if Air thus loaded, be compreſs'd by adverſe Winds, <lb/>or by being driven againſt
          Mountains, or if it be <lb/>condenſed by the Loſs of it's Fire, it will continue
          <lb/>ſuſpended no longer, but will deſcend in Dew. And <lb/>if the Water ſurroun ing one
          Particle of Air comes <lb/>into contact with that ſurrounding another, they <lb/>naturally
          coaleſce into a Drop, and ſo deſcend in <lb/>Rain. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="35"><lb/>35. The Sun ſupplies common Fire to all <w part="I"
            >Va-</w><lb/><w part="F">pours</w>, riſing either from Sea or Land. Vapours <lb/>having
          both this and Electric Fire, are better <w part="I">ſup-</w><lb/><w part="F">ported</w>
          than thoſe which have this only. For when <lb/>Vapours riſe into the coldeſt Region, the
          common <lb/>Fire may fail. But the Cold will not diminiſh the <lb/>Electric: This is
          always the ſame. Hence Clouds <lb/>raiſed from freſh Waters, from moiſt Earth, or
          <lb/>growing Vegetables, more eaſily deſcend and <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >poſite</w> their Waters, as having but little Electric<lb/> Fire, to keep the Particles
          ſeparate from each other. <lb/>So that the greateſt Part of the Water raiſed from <lb/>the
          Land, falls on the Land again. But Clouds <lb/>raiſed from the Sea, having both Fires, and
          much <lb/>of the Electric, ſupport their Water far more <w part="I">ſtrong-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ly</w>, and being aſſiſted by Winds, may bring it <lb/>from the Middle of the
          wideſt Ocean to the Middle <lb/>of the broadeſt Continent. And yet a Way is <w part="I"
            >pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">vided</w> whereby theſe alſo are readily brought to <w
            part="I">de-</w><pb xml:id="page_23" n="25"/><lb/><w part="F">poſite</w> their Water.
          For whenever they are driven <lb/>againſt Mountains by the Winds, thoſe Mountains
          <lb/>take away their Electric Fire: And being cold, the <lb/>common alſo: Hence the
          Particles immediately cloſe. <lb/>If the Air was not much loaded, the Water falls in
          <lb/>Dew on the Top and the Sides of the Mountain. <lb/>If it was, the Electric Fire being
          taken at once <lb/>from the whole Cloud, it flaſhes brightly, and <lb/>cracks loudly. And
          the Particles inſtantly <w part="I">coaleſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">cing</w> for want of that
          Fire, fall in an heavy <lb/>Shower. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="36"><lb/>36. When a Ridge of Mountains ſtops the <lb/>Clouds, and draws
          the Electric Fire from the Cloud <lb/>firſt approaching it, the next when it comes near
          <lb/>the firſt, now deprived of it's Fire, flaſhes into it, <lb/>and depoſites it's own
          Water. The third Cloud <lb/>approaching, and all that ſucceed, act in the ſame
          <lb/>Manner; as far back as they extend, which may <lb/>be for ſeveral hundred Miles.
          Hence the continual <lb/>Storms of Thunder, Lightning and Rain, on the <lb/>Eaſt Side of
          thoſe va<unclear>#</unclear>t Mountains, the <hi rend="italic">Andes,</hi> which
          <lb/>running North and South, intercept all the Clouds <lb/>brought againſt them from the
            <hi rend="italic">Atlantick</hi> Ocean. In <lb/>a plain Country, there are other Means
          to make <lb/>them drop their Water. For if an electrified Cloud <lb/>coming from the Sea,
          meets in the Air a Cloud <lb/>coming from the Land, and therefore not <w part="I"
            >electri-</w><lb/><w part="F">fied</w>, the firſt will give it's Flaſh into the latter,
          and <lb/>thereby both will be made to depoſite their <w part="I">Wa-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ter</w>. The Concuſſion of the Air contributes alſo to <lb/>ſhake down the Water, not
          only from thoſe two <lb/>Clouds, but from others near them. When the Sea <lb/>and Land
          Clouds would paſs at too great a Diſtance <lb/>from each other, they are mutually
          attracted till <lb/>within the Diſtance. For the Sphere of Electrical <lb/>Attraction is
          far beyond the flaſhing Diſtance. And <lb/>yet where a Cloud contains much Fire, it may
          <lb/>ſtrike at a conſiderable Diſtance. When a <w part="I">Con-</w><pb xml:id="page_24"
            n="26"/><lb/><w part="F">ductor</w> has but little Fire in it, you muſt approach
          <lb/>very near before you can draw a Spark. Throw <lb/>into it a greater Quantity of Fire,
          and it will give <lb/>a Spark at a greater Diſtance. But if a Gun <w part="I"
            >Bar-</w><lb/><w part="F">rel</w>, when electrified, will ſtrike and make a Noiſe,
          <lb/>at the Diſtance of an Inch, at what a Diſtance, and <lb/>with how great a Noiſe, may
          ten thouſand Acres <lb/>of electrified Cloud ſtrike? No Wonder that this <lb/>ſhould melt
          Metals (which our artificial Flaſh does <lb/>in ſome Degree) tho' perhaps not ſo properly
          by <lb/>it's Heat, as by inſinuating into the Pores, and <w part="I">cre-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ating</w> a violent Repulſion between the Particles of <lb/>the Metal it paſſes
          thro'. This overcomes the <w part="I">At-</w><lb/><w part="F">traction</w> whereby they
          cohere, and ſo melts the <w part="I">me-</w><lb/><w part="F">tallic</w> Body. And this
          accounts for its melting a <lb/>Sword in the Scabbard, or Gold in the Pocket, <lb/>without
          burning either. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="37"><lb/>37. But Thunder Clouds do not always contain <lb/>more than
          their natural Quantity of Electric Fire. <lb/>Very frequently they contain leſs. And when
          this <lb/>is the Caſe, when they are negatively electrified, <lb/>altho' the Effects and
          Appearances are nearly the <lb/>ſame, yet the Manner of Operation is different. <lb/>For
          in this Caſe, it is really the Fire from the <lb/>Mountains, or other Part of the Earth
          which ſtrikes <lb/>into the Cloud; and not, as we imagine, Fire from <lb/>the Cloud which
          ſtrikes into the Earth. And we <lb/>may eaſily conceive, how a Cloud may be <w part="I"
            >nega-</w><lb/><w part="F">tively</w> electrified. When a Portion of Water is <w
            part="I">rare-</w><lb/><w part="F">fied</w> into a thin Vapour, the Fire it contains is
            <w part="I">rare-</w><lb/><w part="F">fied</w> too. Conſequently it has then leſs than
          it's <lb/>natural Quantity of Fire. Such a Cloud therefore <lb/>coming within a due
          Diſtance of the Earth, will <lb/>receive from it a Flaſh of Electric Fire; which
          <lb/>Flaſh, to ſupply a great Extent of Cloud, muſt <w part="I">of-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ten</w> contain a great Quantity of Fire. Such a Cloud <lb/>alſo paſſing over Woods of
          tall Trees, may ſilently <lb/>receive ſome Supply, either from the Points of the <pb
            xml:id="page_25" n="27"/><lb/>Boughs, or from the ſharp Ends and Edges of the
          <lb/>Leaves. The Cloud thus ſupplied, flaſhes into <lb/>other Clouds that have not been ſo
          ſupplied; and <lb/>thoſe into others, till an Equilibrium is produced, <lb/>among all that
          are within a ſtriking Diſtance of <lb/>each other. And hence are repeated Strokes and
          <lb/>Flaſhes, till they deſcend in Showers to the Earth, <lb/>their Original. Rain,
          eſpecially when in large <lb/>Drops, generally brings down the Electric Fire: <lb/>Falling
          Snow often: Summer Hail, always, tho' <lb/>ſilently. Conſequently, any of theſe may
          prevent <lb/>Thunder and Lightning; or at leaſt, abate it's <lb/>Violence. Rain is helpful
          in another Reſpect <w part="I">like-</w><lb/><w part="F">wiſe</w>. By wetting Men or
          Beaſts, it ſaves many <lb/>Lives. For if your Cloathes are thro'ly wet, and a <lb/>Flaſh
          of Lightning ſtrikes the Top of your Head, <lb/>it will run in the Water over the Surface
          of your <w part="I">Bo-</w><lb/><w part="F">dy</w> into the Ground: Whereas if your
          Cloaths <lb/>were not wet, it would go thro' your Body. Hence <lb/>a wet Chicken cannot be
          killed by a Stroke from the <lb/>Phial; whereas a dry one is kill'd in an Inſtant.
          <lb/>See here alſo the Wiſdom and Goodneſs of Him, <lb/><hi rend="italic">who ſendeth
            forth Lightning with the Rain!</hi> It <lb/>ſhould likewiſe be obſerv'd, that wherever
            <w part="I">electrifi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> Clouds paſs, Spires, Towers, Chimneys,
          and <lb/>high Trees, as ſo many Points, draw the Electric <lb/>Fire, and the whole Cloud
          frequently diſcharges <lb/>there Therefore it is highly dangerous in ſuch a <lb/>Storm, to
          take Shelter under a Tree. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="38"><lb/>38. Common Fire (if it be any thing more, than <lb/>a different
          Modification of the ſame Element) is <lb/>more or leſs in all Bodies, as well as
          Electrical. If <lb/>there be a ſufficient Quantity of either in any <w part="I"
            >Bo-</w><lb/><w part="F">dy</w>, it is inflamed. But when the Quantity of <w part="I"
            >com-</w><lb/><w part="F">mon</w> Fire therein is ſmall there needs more <w part="I"
            >Elec-</w><lb/><w part="F">tric</w> Fire to infl<unclear>#</unclear>me it. Where the
          Quantity of <lb/>common Fire is greater, leſs of the Electric will <lb/>ſuffice. So if
          Spirits are heated, a ſmall Spark <w part="I">in-</w><pb xml:id="page_26" n="28"/><lb/><w
            part="F">flames</w> them. If they are not, the Spark muſt be <lb/>greater. Sulphureous
          Vapours, whether riſing <lb/>from the Earth, or from Stacks of moiſt Hay or <lb/>Corn, or
          any other heated and reeking Vegetable, <lb/>contain ab ndance of common Fire. A ſmall <w
            part="I">Ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">dition</w> of Electric then will inflame them. <w
            part="I">There-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w> they are eaſily kindled by Lightning. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="39"><lb/>39. Any who would be clearly convinced of the <lb/>Nature of
          Lightning, may make the following <w part="I">Ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">periment</w>. Make a
          ſmall Croſs of two thin Strips <lb/>of Wood, the Arms being juſt ſo long, as to reach
          <lb/>the four Corners of a large, thin Silk Handkerchief <lb/>when extended. Tie the
          Corners of this to the <lb/>Extremities of the Croſs; and ſo you have the <w part="I"
            >Bo-</w><lb/><w part="F">dy</w> of a Kite: Add to this a proper Tail, Loop <lb/>and
          String, and it will riſe in the Air like one made <lb/>with Paper: But this is
            fi<unclear>#</unclear>ter to bear the Wind <lb/>and Wet in a Storm without tearing. To
          the Top <lb/>of the Croſs fix a ſharp pointed Wire, riſing a Foot <lb/>above it. Tie a
          Silk Ribbon to the End of the <lb/>Twine next the Hand; and where the Silk and <lb/>Twine
          join, faſten a Key. Raiſe this Kite when <lb/>a Thunder-Storm is coming on: But he that
          holds <lb/>the String, muſt ſtand in a Porch, or under ſome <lb/>other Covering, that the
          Ribbon may not be wet. <lb/>He muſt likewiſe take particular Care, that the <lb/>Twine do
          not touch the Top or Side of the Porch. <lb/>As ſoon as the Thunder-Cloud comes over the
          <lb/>Kite, the pointed Wire draws the Electric Fire <lb/>from it. The Kite and all the
          Twine are then <lb/>electrified, as plainly appears by this, that the looſe <lb/>Filaments
          of the Twine ſtand out every way, and <lb/>are attracted by an approaching Finger. And
          when <lb/>the Kite and Twine being wet, conduct the Fire <lb/>freely, it will ſtream from
          the Key, on the <w part="I">Ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">proach</w> of the Knuckle. By this Key
          the Phial <lb/>may be charged, and all other Experiments made, <lb/>as by the Globe. And
          this is a Demonſtration, <pb xml:id="page_27" n="29"/><lb/>that the Electric Fire thereby
          obtain'd, is the very <lb/>ſame with that of Lightning. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="40"><lb/>40. May not the Knowledge of this Power in <lb/>pointed Bodies,
          of drawing off the Fire contain'd <lb/>in theſe Clouds, ſuggeſt to us a very probable <w
            part="I">Me-</w><lb/><w part="F">thod</w>, of preſerving Houſes, Churches, Ships from
          <lb/>the Stroke of Lightning? Might we not fix on <lb/>the higheſt Part of them, upright
          Rods of Iron <lb/>made ſharp as Needles, and gilt, to prevent <w part="I">ruſt-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ing</w>, which otherwiſe would hinder their free <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">veyance</w> of the Electric Fire? From the Foot of <lb/>thoſe Rods (which need
          not be above half an Inch <lb/>diameter) a Wire may paſs down the Outſide of <lb/>the
          Building into the Ground; or down round one <lb/>of the Shrouds of a Ship, and down her
          Side, till <lb/>it reaches the Water. Would not theſe Rods <w part="I">ſi-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">lently</w> draw off the Electric Fire, before the Cloud <lb/>was nigh enough to
          ſtrike? And thereby in a good <lb/>Meaſure ſecure us from that moſt ſudden and <w part="I"
            >terri-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w> Miſchief! Let it not be objected, that the <w
            part="I">uſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> this probable Means of preventing a threatning
          <lb/>Danger, would imply any Denial of, or Diſtruſt <lb/>in, Divine Providence Not at all:
          We know <lb/>the Creator of the Univerſe, is likewiſe the <w part="I">Go-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">vernor</w> of all Things therein. But we know <w part="I">like-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">wiſe</w> that he gove ns by ſecond Cauſes; and that <lb/>accordingly it is his
          Will, we ſhould uſe all the <lb/>probable Means he has given us, to attain every
          <lb/>lawful End. It is therefore no more an <w part="I">Impeach-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ment</w> of his Providence, when we foreſee a Storm <lb/>of Lightning and Rain, to
          ſhelter our Houſe (as far <lb/>as we are able) from the one, than to ſhelter <w part="I"
            >our-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſelves</w> in that Houſe from the other. Is it not juſt
          <lb/>as innocent (if it be poſſible) to keep our Rooms <lb/>tight from Lightning, as from
          Wind and Water? </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="41"><lb/>41. It may not be improper to add one or two <lb/>Obſervations,
          before we proceed to what is of more <lb/>Importance. Scarce any Phenomenon in Nature <pb
            xml:id="page_28" n="30"/><lb/>has been eſteem'd more difficult to be accounted for
          <lb/>than thoſe luminous Appearances in the Sky, term'd <lb/><hi rend="italic">Aurora
            Borealis,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Northern Lights.</hi> But theſe <w part="I"
            >al-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſo</w> may be rationally explain'd, upon the Principles <lb/>of
          Electricity. We often ſee Clouds at different <lb/>Heights, paſſing different Ways, North
          and South <lb/>at the ſame Time. This manifeſtly proves <w part="I">differ-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ent</w> Currents of Air, one of them under the other. <lb/>Now as the Air
          between the Tropics is rarefied by <lb/>the Sun, it riſes; the denſer Air preſſing into
          it's <lb/>Place. The Air ſo raiſed, moves North and South, <lb/>and if it has no
          Opportunity before, muſt deſcend <lb/>in the Polar Regions. When this Air with it's <w
            part="I">Va-</w><lb/><w part="F">pours</w> deſcends into contact with the Vapours <w
            part="I">ariſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> there, the Electric Fire which it brought <w
            part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">gins</w> to be communicated, and is ſeen in clear
          <lb/>Nights; being firſt viſible where it is firſt in <w part="I">Mo-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tion</w>, namely in the moſt Northern Parts. But from <lb/>thence the Streams of Light
          ſeem to ſhoot <w part="I">Souther-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w>, even to the Zenith of
          Northern Countries. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="42"><lb/>42. Another Phenomenon of a totally different <lb/>Kind, may be
          accounted for on the ſame <w part="I">Princi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ples</w>, altho' Mr. <hi
            rend="italic">Prior</hi> ſuppoſes <hi rend="italic">Solomon</hi> himſelf to <lb/>ask, as
          a Queſtion which he could not anſwer, <q rend="quotes"><lb/><l>Whence does it happen, that
              the Plant which well </l>
            <lb/><l>We name the <hi rend="italic">Senſitive,</hi> ſhould move and feel? </l>
            <lb/><l>Whence know her Leaves to anſwer her Command, </l>
            <lb/><l>And with quick Horror fly the neighbouring Hand? </l></q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Allowing for Poetical Amplification the plain Fact <lb/>is this. The
          Senſitive Plant, as it were, ſhrinks <lb/>away, as ſoon as your Hand approaches it. And
          <lb/>from a turgid and vivid Appearance, inſtantly droops <lb/>and hangs it's Leaves. Now
          ſuppoſe this Plant to <lb/>contain more Electric Fire than any other Plant or <pb
            xml:id="page_29" n="31"/><lb/>Animal, it muſt or Courſe communicate that Fire, <lb/>to
          any other that touches it. And if ſo, it's Leaves <lb/>and Branches muſt be in a languid
          State, till they <lb/>have recover'd their natural Quantity. To illuſtrate <lb/>this, ſet
          any ſmall Tree in a Pot on a Cake of <lb/>Brimſtone. Electrify it and it grows extremely
          <lb/>turgid, ſo as to erect it's Leaves. But the <w part="I">Mo-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ment</w> you touch one of them, the whole Tree <lb/>droops, and hangs all it's Leaves
          and Branches. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>To throw all the Light I can on the Subject, I <lb/>ſubjoin a few
          Extracts from ſeveral other Writers. </p>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center"><lb/>An Extract from Mr. <hi rend="italic">Watſon</hi>'s
            Experiments and <lb/>Obſervations. </head>
          <p rend="indent" n="1"><lb/>1. When two Plates, the one electrified, the <lb/>other not,
            were brought near each other, the <w part="I">Flaſh-</w><lb/><w part="F">es</w> of <hi
              rend="italic">bright Flame</hi> were ſo large, that in a dark <lb/>Room, I could
            diſtinctly ſee the Faces of 13 <w part="I">Per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſons</w>. P. 6. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="2"><lb/>2. A Piece of large blunt Wire was hung to the <lb/>Conductor.
            To the End of this when electrified a <lb/>black Surface not electrified being brought
            near, <lb/>(tho' not near enough to cauſe a Snap) a Bruſh of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Blue
              Flame,</hi> quite different from the former, iſſued <lb/>of more than an Inch long,
            and an Inch thick. P. 7. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="3"><lb/>3. If a Perſon ſtrongly electrified lays his Hand <lb/>on the
            Cloaths of one that is not, eſpecially if they <lb/>are thin Woollen or Silk, they both
            feel as it were <lb/><hi rend="italic">many Pins pricking</hi> them, as long as the
            Globe is <lb/>in Motion. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="4"><lb/>4. If Oil of Turpentine be ſet on Fire in a <w part="I"
              >Veſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſel</w> held by one electrified, <hi rend="italic">the
              Smoke</hi> ariſing <w part="I">there-</w><lb/><w part="F">from</w>, received againſt a
            Plate held at a Foot <w part="I">Diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">tance</w> from the Flame, by
            one ſtanding on Roſin, <lb/>will enable him to Fire warm Spirits of Wine. <lb/>The
            Electric Strokes have been likewiſe felt, upon <lb/>touching the ſecond Man, when the
            Plate he held <pb xml:id="page_30" n="32"/><lb/>in the Smoke has been between ſeven and
            eight <lb/>Feet above the Flame. P. 8. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="5"><lb/>5. Take burning Spirits of Wine inſtead of Oil <lb/>of
            Turpentine: And if the ſecond Man hold the <lb/>End of an Iron Rod at the Top of the <hi
              rend="italic">Flame,</hi> he <lb/>may k ndle other warm Spirits held near his Finger.
            <lb/>Hence we find that either Smoke or Flame <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ducts</w> the Electric Fire, and does not perceptibly <lb/>diminiſh it's Force. P 9. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="6"><lb/>6. If the Wire of the Phial be not touched, the
            <lb/>electrified Water or Steel Duſt will retain it's <lb/>Force many Hours, may be
            convey'd ſeveral Miles, <lb/>and will afterward exert it's Force upon touching <lb/>the
            Wire. P. 16. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="7"><lb/>7. If an Egg is hung on the Conductor, and a <lb/>Perſon
            graſping the electrified <unclear>#</unclear>hial with one Hand, <lb/>brings the Palm of
            his other near the Bottom of the <lb/>Egg, he receives a ſmart <unclear>#</unclear>troke
            on the Hand, as <lb/>with a Ferula, and his Hand ſeems full of a more <lb/>red Fire than
            is uſually obſerved. P. 24. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="8"><lb/>8. Any Number of Perſons communicating with <lb/>each other,
            the firſt of whom graſps the Phial, and <lb/>the laſt touches the Conductor, receive the
            ſame <lb/>Shock as if it was <unclear>#</unclear>ne only. P. 25. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="9"><lb/>9. The Electric Force always deſcribes a <w part="I"
              >Cir-</w><lb/><w part="F">cuit</w>, and moves in the ſtraiteſt Line it can, <w
              part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">tween</w> the Conductor and hial. P. 26 </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="10"><lb/>10. To prove th<unclear>#</unclear>s, while the Machine ſtood
            on <lb/>Wax, I ſtood upon the Floor; and putting one <lb/>Hand on the Machine, touch'd
            the Gun Barrel <lb/>with the other. Upon this Fire iſſued, and the <lb/>ſnapping
            continued as long as I held my hand on <lb/>the Machine, but no longer This ſhew'd at
            once, <lb/>that the Electric Fire paſt from the Floor thro' my <lb/>Body to the Machine.
            P 36. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="11"><lb/>11. If the Electric Fire is not ſtopt, no Sign of <lb/>it's
            Preſence is obſervable in the Bodies ſuſpended <lb/>to the Globe. Tho' it throws ever ſo
            much of this <pb xml:id="page_31" n="33"/><lb/>Fire upon them, it paſſes from them to
            the Floor <lb/>whence it came. But if it is ſtopt, it is then <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">cumulated</w> in or upon theſe Bodies: Altho' this can <lb/>be done only to a
            certain Degree, after which it <lb/>continually diſperſes. If when it is accumulated, a
            <lb/>Man ſtanding on the Floor touches thoſe Bodies, <lb/>the Snap is felt, and the Fire
            is ſeen. But this <lb/>ſnapping is not when the Fire paſſes off <w part="I"
              >continual-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w>, as from a Piere of blunt Wire hung to the
            <lb/>Barrel, and a Han<unclear>#</unclear> brought near it. Then it <w part="I"
              >ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pears</w> like a blue Cone of Flame, with it's Point
            <lb/>towards the Wire. When the Hand is held at a <lb/>proper Diſtance there is a Blaſt
            therefrom, as of <lb/>cold Air. If you <unclear>#</unclear>o not determine the Electric
            <lb/>Fire to a Point, it is diſperſed from all parts of the <lb/>electrified Body: But
            if you do, by thus holding <lb/>your Hand near the Fire, you ſee how it paſſes to
            <lb/>the Floor, and ſo into the Earth. The Globe <w part="I">there-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >fore</w> only circulates this Fire, which is collected by <lb/>it's Friction againſt
            the Hand or Cuſhion, and <lb/>which is conſtantly ſupplied to theſe from the Earth.
            <lb/>And accordingly the <unclear>#</unclear>ngr<unclear>#</unclear>ſs of it, as well as
            the <lb/>Egreſs is viſible. For, if while any unelectrified <lb/>Body touches the
            Barrel, you bring your Finger near <lb/>the Wood-Work of the Machine, you will ſee
            <lb/>the Bruſh of Blue Flame ſet in from it to the Wood-<lb/>Work. And this Flame paſſes
            diverging into the <lb/>Machine, and continues as long as the Barrel is <lb/>touched. P.
            44. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="12"><lb/>12. That the Electric Atmoſphere which <w part="I"
              >ſur-</w><lb/><w part="F">rounds</w> all electrified Bodies, extends to a <w part="I"
              >conſider-</w><lb/><w part="F">able</w> Diſtance, appears from their attracting a fine
            Thread, at the Diſtance of ſome Feet. If no <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >electrified</w> Body is near, this Atmoſphere ſeems to be equally ſpread over that
            which is electrified. But if one unelectrified is brought near, the greateſt Part of it
            is determined that Way; whence the Attraction of the other Parts of the electrified Body
              <pb xml:id="page_32" n="34"/>is conſiderably diminiſhed. This is the Cauſe of Electric
            Repulſion, which does not operate, till the Electric Ether is ſufficiently accumulated.
            This Repulſion is ſtrongeſt in <unclear>#</unclear>hoſe Parts of the electrified Body,
            where unelectrified Bodies are brought near it. For by theſe the Electric Blaſt, which
            otherwiſe is general, is particularly <w part="I">deter-</w><lb/><w part="F">mined</w>.
            P. 46. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="13"><lb/>13. When the Machine is placed upon Roſin, <lb/>if a Man
            ſtanding likewiſe on Roſin, touches the <lb/>Barrel while the Globe is turning, he will
            receive a <lb/>Snap or two, and no more. But if he touch the <lb/>Wood-Work of the
            Machine with one Hand, and <lb/>the Barrel with the other, he receives Snaps again,
            <lb/>which continue as long as he touches the Machine, <lb/>and no longer. Here the Man
            by touching the <lb/>Machine with one Hand, becomes a Part thereof; <lb/>and by turning
            the Globe, Part of the Electric <lb/>Fire inherent in his Body, is tranſmitted to the <w
              part="I">Bar-</w><lb/><w part="F">rel</w>; but it is reſtored to him, on his touching
            the <lb/>Barrel with his other Hand. If inſtead of <w part="I">touch-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ing</w> the Machine or Barrel he holds his Finger <lb/>near either, or both,
            you ſee the Fire go out and <lb/>return. P. 64. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="14"><lb/>14. May we not gather from the preceeding <lb/>Experiments,
            1. That the Attraction and <w part="I">Repul-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſion</w> of
            electrified Bodies, is owing to the Flux of <lb/>Electric Ether? 2. That this Ether is
            no other <lb/>than pure Fire? 3. That this Fire appears in <w part="I">dif-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ferent</w> Forms, according to it's different <w part="I"
              >Modifica-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions?</w> When brought towards a Point is it not a
            <lb/>lambent Flame? When nearer ſtill, may we not <lb/>both hear and feel it? And does
            not it's lighting <lb/>up Spirits demonſtrate, that it is real Fire? 4. That <lb/>this
            Fire is intimately connected with all Bodies, <lb/>tho' leaſt of all with pure, dry Air?
            We have <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">tracted</w> it from Water, Flame, Smoke, red
            hot <lb/>Iron; and from a Mixture 30 Degrees colder than <pb xml:id="page_33" n="35"
            /><lb/>the freezing Point. 5. That it is extremely ſubtle <lb/>and highly Elaſtic? 6.
            That the Electric Machine <lb/>may as properly be term'd a <hi rend="italic"
              >Fire-Pump,</hi> as Mr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Foyle</hi>'s Machine, an <hi
              rend="italic">Air Pump?</hi> And laſtly, that <lb/>Fire is not Mechanically producible
            from other <lb/>Bodies, but is an original, diſtinct Principle? </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">An Extract from Mr.</hi> Wilſon<hi
              rend="italic">'s Diſſertation on</hi>
            <w part="I">Elec-</w><lb/><w part="F">tricity</w>. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Prop. 1. When two Bodies equally replete with <lb/>Electric Matter
            approach each other, no Flame or <lb/>Snap will enſue. P. 5. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Prop. 2. Two Bodies equally electrified repel <lb/>each other. P. 6. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Prop. 3. An Electric Body interpoſed between <lb/>a Perſon and the
            Earth, prevents his exciting <w part="I">Elec-</w><lb/><w part="F">tricity</w> in
            another Body by Friction. P. 11. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Prop. 4. If there is originally a certain <w part="I"
              >Quanti-</w><lb/><w part="F">ty</w> of Electric Matter in a Body of a given <w
              part="I">Mag-</w><lb/><w part="F">nitude</w> and Denſity; and that Matter be equally
            <lb/>diſtributed therein, by it's Elaſtic Force, according <lb/>to the Denſity of the
            Parts: Upon increaſing the <lb/>Quantity of Matter by adding other Bodies of the
            <lb/>ſame Kind, the Quantity of Electric Matter will <lb/>be increaſed in the ſame
            Proportion. P. 14. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Prop. 5. As Electric Bodies act on light <w part="I">Bo-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">dies</w> that are not electrified, ſo unelectrified Bodies <lb/>act on the
            Electric Matter contain'd in electrified<lb/> Bodies. P. 16. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Let a Wire be electrified in the Dark, and if <lb/>you hold any
            unelectrified Body 7 or 8 Inches from <lb/>the End of it, a Stream of Fire will iſſue
            from it, <lb/>which will diverge to that Body. But the <w part="I">Diver-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">gency</w> will leſſen as it approaches it, till the Rays <lb/>become
            parallel. If the Body be held not directly <lb/>before the End of the Wire, but wide of
            it at <lb/>about two Inches Diſtance, the Fire will deſcribe <lb/>curvilinear Rays
            towards that Body. P. 17. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_34" n="36"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Hence it appears, that unelectrified Bodies act in <lb/>like Manner
            with electrified: Only the acting Force <lb/>of the one being increaſed by Friction, is
            greater <lb/>than that of the other. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Prop. 6. When two equally Electric <w part="I">Atmoſ-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">pheres</w> are brought ſo near as to touch, they repell <lb/>each other with
            a Force equal to their <w part="I">Denſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ties</w>. P. 19. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Prop. 7. If while a Fluid ſurrounds a Globe <lb/>which is
            electrified and turn'd round an Axis <w part="I">paſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſing</w> thro'
            it's Center, an unelectrified Body be held <lb/>near the Equator of it, the Fluid will
            riſe <w part="I">ſucceſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſively</w> towards that Body, as it turns
            round, in <lb/>like Manner as the Sea is affected by the Moon. <lb/>P. 23. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Shock given by the Phial is in Proportion <lb/>to the Size of
            it, the thinneſs of the Glaſs, and <lb/>the Number of Points in contact with it's <w
              part="I">Sur-</w><lb/><w part="F">face</w>. P. 25. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center"><lb/>An Extract from Mr. <hi rend="roman">Martin</hi>'s
            Eſſay on Electricity. </head>
          <p rend="indent" n="1"><lb/>1. The <hi rend="italic">Electric Matter</hi> is emitted from
            ſome <lb/>ſort of Bodies when rubb'd, which are call'd <hi rend="italic"
              >Elec-<lb/>trics.</hi> P. 9. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="2"><lb/>2. By other Sorts of Bodies, therefore term'd <lb/><hi
              rend="italic">Non-Electrics,</hi> it is not emitted. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="3"><lb/>3. It will run off to all <hi rend="italic"
              >Non-Electrics,</hi> but it <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtrained</w> by all
            Electrics. </p>
          <p rend="indent" n="4"><lb/>4. It ſhines like a <hi rend="italic">Flame,</hi> and is
            emitted with a <lb/><hi rend="italic">Snap:</hi> If towards a <hi rend="italic">Non
              Electric,</hi> the Fire is <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">denſed</w>, leſs or
            more, and ſo appears of a bluiſh, <lb/>Purple, Yellow, or White Colour. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>When the Electric Fire is not ſo much <w part="I"
              >condenſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> as to explode, as in Thunder and Lightning it
            <lb/>goes off in a dilated Stream of purple Flame, <w part="I">great-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ly</w> reſembling that Part of the <hi rend="italic">Aurora Borealis,</hi>
            <lb/>which appears in Streams of Light. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_35" n="37"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>When it is little condenſed, it appears <hi rend="italic"
              >bluiſh,</hi> as <lb/>all other faint Lights do: When a little denſer, it <lb/>appears
              <hi rend="italic">Purple:</hi> When denſer ſtill, it looks <hi rend="italic"
              >Yellow,</hi>
            <lb/>like Candle Light: When highly condenſed, it is <lb/>clear and <hi rend="italic"
              >white,</hi> like the Light of the Sun. So <lb/>the White Lightning is of all others
            moſt fierce. <lb/>So Phoſphorus rubb'd a little, ſpends itſelf in an <lb/>harmleſs Blue
            Flame: But upon a greater <w part="I">Attriti-</w><lb/><w part="F">on</w>, kindles into
            a White Flame, and burns with <lb/>an outragious and unquenchable Fire. p. 17. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>And as Lightning pervades ſoft Subſtances <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">hurt</w>, but diſſolves hard and compact Bodies, ſo <lb/>Electric Fire
            pervades the ſoft, muſcular Parts of <lb/>the Body, but violently ſtrikes the Bones and
              <w part="I">Ten-</w><lb/><w part="F">dons</w>. Again, as thoſe denſer Parts of
            Lightning <lb/>which we call Thunder-Bolts, ſtriking againſt hard <lb/>Bodies, glance by
            Reflection to different Parts, ſo <lb/>this Fire, ſtriking againſt the Elbow, is
            reflected <lb/>from thence acroſs the Breaſt, to the other <w part="I">El-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">bow</w>. p. 18. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Indeed different Perſons are affected thereby in <lb/>a very
            different Manner. Some are extremely <w part="I">ca-</w><lb/><w part="F">pable</w> of
            it, ſome not: And ſome are not <w part="I">ſuſcep-</w><lb/><w part="F">tible</w> of it
            at all: A Perſon, for Inſtance, who has <lb/>the Small-Pox, cannot be electrified by any
            Means <lb/>whatever. p. 20. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Experiment 1. On the Axis, in the Center of <lb/>my Globe, is fixt a
            circular String of Threads. <lb/>When the Globe is at reſt, they all hang down:
            <lb/>When it is in Motion, they all extend themſelves <lb/>from the Center, ſtrait
            toward the inner Surface of <lb/>the Globe (like the Spokes of a Coach-Wheel) <lb/>which
            they nearly touch. Thus they continue till <lb/>the Electric Virtue ceaſes, and then
            gradually fall <lb/>down, as at firſt. p. 22. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 2. While they are extended, if you move <lb/>your Hand toward
            the Surface of the Globe, they <lb/>move every Way toward the Hand. Hence we ſee <pb
              xml:id="page_36" n="38"/><lb/>the amazing Subtlety of this Fire, which pervades
            <lb/>Glaſs as readily as if nothing were in the Way. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 3. Place a Hoop of Fine Threads round <lb/>the Globe in Motion,
            and all of them will ſtand <lb/>perpendicular to the Surface. Hence we learn that
            <lb/>the Electric Power acts equally, both within and <lb/>without the Globe, and in
            Directions <w part="I">perpendicu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lar</w> to it's Surface. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 4. If the Room be then darken'd, the <lb/>Ends of the Threads
            on the Outſide, will be all <lb/>tipt with Fire. But thoſe within are not, which
            <lb/>ſhews that this Power acts only <hi rend="italic">ab intra</hi>
            <w part="I">out-</w><lb/><w part="F">wardly</w>. p. 23. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 5. An Iron Rod being hung on Silken <lb/>Strings, with one End
            about ¼ of an Inch from the <lb/>Globe, will at the other End (which terminates in
            <lb/>a conical Point) emit a Purple Flame diverging <lb/>every Way. Hold your Finger
            within ¼ of an Inch, <lb/>and the Fire will iſſue more largely. p. 24. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 6. Hold your Finger ſtill nearer, and the <lb/>Rays will be ſo
            condenſed as to run to it in a <lb/>Stream of Yellow Flame; which is alſo ſenſible to
            <lb/>the Feeling, as a gentle Wind, and ſmells like the <lb/>Fire of Phoſphorus. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 7. If you put your Finger on the Rod, <lb/>the Flame inſtantly
            diſappears, the Fire all running <lb/>off upon the Finger. But take it off, and the
            <lb/>Flame appears again. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 8. Apply your Finger near a Tin Tube <lb/>ſo ſuſpended, and you
            may ſee the Fire, and both <lb/>hear and feel the Snap. p. 25. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 14. Under an electrified Plate, put ſome <lb/>Leaf-Gold or
            other light Subſtances on another <lb/>Plate unelectrified: And it will be attracted and
            <lb/>repell'd alternately, between the two Plates. For, <lb/>each Time it touches the
            lower Plate, it diſcharges <lb/>he Electric Fire, and ſo becomes again <w part="I"
              >attract-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w>. p. 28. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_37" n="39"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 18. If to a Gun Barrel you adapt a <lb/>ſmall Tin Cup, and pour
            in Water; a Perſon <lb/>holding his Finger perpendicular over the Water, <lb/>within ¼
            of an Inch of it's Surface, will find the <lb/>Water riſe in Form of a Cone to meet his
            Finger, <lb/>and from the Top of it, a Stream of Fire will iſſue <lb/>to the Finger and
            ſnap as uſual p. 30. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 19. A dry Spunge is an <hi rend="italic">Electric.</hi> But if
            <lb/>it be dipt in Water, and then hung on the Barrel, <lb/>put your Finger near it, and
            the Fire iſſues out, and <lb/>the Drops which before fell very ſlowly, will now
            <lb/>fall very faſt. If the Room be darkened, they will <lb/>appear as Drops of Fire. p.
              3<unclear>#</unclear>. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 20. A Syphon hung on the Cup, drops <lb/>very gently till it is
            electrified; but then the <w part="I">Wa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> runs in a Stream,
            which in the Dark is like a Stream of Fire. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 21. Open a Vein in a Perſon ſtanding on the Roſin, and the
            Blood will fly out to a certain Diſtance. But let him be electrified, and it will ſpin
            out with a much greater Force, and to a far greater Diſtance. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 24. If Mercury be put for Water, the Electric Force is
            ſomething greater, but in no <w part="I">Pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">portion</w> to it's
            Denſity. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 25. When the Mercury is ſaturated, the <lb/>Electric Streams
            will iſſue thro' the Wire more <w part="I">co-</w><lb/><w part="F">piouſly</w> than from
            the Phial of Water, and will <lb/>ſnap of themſelves, which the Streams iſſuing from
            <lb/>the Water never do. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 27. The electrified Phial will not retain <lb/>the Fire very
            long: But if you hold it up in a <lb/>dark Room, it will be ſeen to go off from the
            <lb/>Point of the Wire, in a ſmall white Flame. p. 34. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 30. A Cup of Water held by an <w part="I">electri-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">fied</w> Perſon will emit Fire more forcibly than his <lb/>Body. p. 35. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_38" n="40"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 32. A Perſon ſtanding on the Ground, <lb/>cannot eaſily kiſs an
            electrified Perſon ſtanding on <lb/>the Roſin. p. 36. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 38. If a ſquare Piece of Leaf Gold be <lb/>placed between two
            Plates, about two Inches <w part="I">aſun-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w>, one of them
            electrified, the other not at firſt <lb/>it will be attracted, and repell'd alternately,
            till in <lb/>a while it will loſe its Motion, and remain <w part="I">ſuſ-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">pended</w> between them. p. 39. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 42. If the Globe be exhauſted of Air, <lb/>and then turn'd, the
            electric Fire will act wholly <lb/>within the Globe, where it will appear (in a dark
            <lb/>Room) as a Reddiſh or Purple Flame, filling the <lb/>whole Globe. But this, as the
            Air is re-admitted <lb/>into it, will gradually diſappear. In this Caſe, the
            <lb/>electric Fire is confined within, by the elaſtic Air <lb/>on the Outſide. p. 40.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center"><lb/>An Extract from Mr. <hi rend="roman">Watkins</hi>'s
            Account of electrical <lb/>Experiments. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>When the Machine is to be uſed, the Globe <lb/>ſhould be wiped
            clean, with a clean, dry, warm <lb/>Flannel, it's Pivots oil'd, and the Cuſhion and
            <lb/>Phial warmed. In damp Weather, there ſhould be <lb/>a Fire in the Room. p 4. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 4. Let an unelectrify'd Plate, with <w part="I"
              >ſcour-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> Sand upon it, be held 5 or 6 Inches under an
            <lb/>electrify'd Plate, and the Sand will be ſo attracted <lb/>and repell'd, as to
            reſemble a ſtormy Shower. p. 16. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 7. If a Glaſs Ball, of 4 or 5 Inches <w part="I"
              >dia-</w><lb/><w part="F">meter</w>, be hung by a Wire to the Gun-barrel, and <lb/>a
            Ball of ¾ of an Inch diameter, exceeding thin, <lb/>placed on a ſmooth Plate, be brought
            near it, this <lb/>will not only be attracted by the large Ball, but <lb/>will perform
            continual Revolutions round it, <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">actly</w> as the
            Planets do round the Sun. p. 22. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 9. Hang a Loadſtone on the Barrel, and <lb/>a Key on the
            Armature of it: And if you bring <pb xml:id="page_39" n="41"/><lb/>your Finger near the
            Key, it will ſnap and emit <lb/>Fire. A plain Proof that the electric and magnetic
            <lb/>Power no way hinder each other. p. 25. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 35. A Sparrow kill'd by the electric <lb/>Shock, was found
            livid without, as if kill'd with a <lb/>Flaſh of Lightning, and moſt of the Blood
            Veſſels <lb/>within were burſt. Animals ſhock'd on the Head, <lb/>if not kill'd, are
            commonly ſtruck blind. p. 55. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 41. Ice held by an electrify'd Perſon, <lb/>will fire warm
            Spirits of Wine. p. 61. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Exp. 43. Mr. <hi rend="italic">Watſon</hi> put an Ounce of Oil of
            <lb/>Vitriol, an Ounce of Iron Filings and four Ounces<lb/> of Water, into a Flask. An
            Ebullition enſued. <lb/>An electrify'd Perſon applied his Finger to the <lb/>Mouth of
            the Flask. The Vapour took fire, and <lb/>burnt out of the Neck a long Time. p. 63. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>From an Experiment made by Mr. <hi rend="italic">Watſon,</hi> and
            <lb/>others, it appear'd, that the electric Fire <w part="I">circulat-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ed</w>, without Interruption, from the <hi rend="italic">Surry</hi> Side of
            <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Thames</hi> over <hi rend="italic">Weſtminſter</hi> Bridge,
            to the <hi rend="italic">Weſt-<lb/>minſter</hi> Side, and thence thro' the River to the
              <hi rend="italic">Surry</hi>
            <lb/>Side again, which is upwards of 800 Yards. Spirits <lb/>of Wine alſo were fired at
            the ſame Diſtance. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>From this, and ſeveral other Experiments, it <w part="I"
              >ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">peared</w>, that Diſtance, ſimply conſidered, did <w part="I"
              >lit-</w><lb/><w part="F">tle</w>, if at all, impair the Force of the electric Shock. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>They afterwards convey'd this Shock thro' a <lb/>Circuit of four
            Miles, and ſound the Motion of <lb/>the electric Fire to be nearly, if not quite, <w
              part="I">inſtan-</w><lb/><w part="F">taneous</w>. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="31"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
