<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Turner: An account of the extraordinary medicinal fluid, called
          æther</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Matthew Turner</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">AN ACCOUNT OF THE EXTRAORDINARY MEDICINAL FLUID, CALLED
              ÆTHER.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T135342</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T135342"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Liverpool</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Printed by John Sadler, MDCCLXI.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1761</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="2"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="16"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3309824259</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K107077.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: medicine"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE Publiſher of the following ſhort <w part="I"
            >Ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">count</w> of the ÆTHER having prepared, <lb/>and ſucceſſfully
          made Uſe of it in his private <lb/>Practice, for ſeveral Years, has at length <w part="I"
            >deter-</w><lb/><w part="F">min'd</w> to endeavour to extend it's Utility, by thus
          <lb/>making it public; as he knows of no one who <lb/>has ever publiſhed it's <hi
            rend="italic">medicinal Virtues;</hi> or <w part="I">offer-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>
          it to Sale in it's <hi rend="italic">Perfection;</hi> or given the <w part="I"
            >Cri-</w><lb/><w part="F">teria</w> by which they who are unacquainted with <lb/>it
          might diſtinguiſh the <hi rend="italic">Genuine</hi> from the <hi rend="italic"
            >Spuri-<lb/>ous:</hi> And he doubts not but every candid Perſon <lb/>who examines it,
          will agree with him, That it <lb/>carries with it the ſtrongeſt Marks of a valuable
          <lb/>Addition to the <hi rend="italic">Materia Medica,</hi> and therefore <lb/>ought to
          lie no longer in Obſcurity. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>

      <pb xml:id="page_3"/>
      <head rend="align-center"><lb/>AN <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">ACCOUNT </hi><lb/>OF THE <lb/><hi
          rend="dc(2)">ÆTHER, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </hi></head>
      <p rend="space"><lb/>
          <figure><figDesc>Decorative frame around the letter "T".</figDesc></figure>
        <hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HIS truly extraordinary Chemical <w part="I">Pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">paration</w> is
        not a new Diſcovery, having <lb/>been known and eſteemed, as a valuable <lb/>Curioſity, by
        many of the greateſt <w part="I">Che-</w><lb/><w part="F">miſts</w> and Philoſophers, both
        Ancient and <lb/>Modern; particularly by Sir<note place="bottom" n="*">* Quere 31ſt, at the
          End of his Optics. </note>
        <hi rend="italic">Iſaac Newton,</hi> and the <lb/>Honourable<note place="bottom" n="†">†
          Treatiſe on the Producibleneſs of Chemical Principles. </note> Mr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Boyle,</hi> who both mention it in their <lb/>Works, tho' not by this Name: And therefore
          <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w> any Thing is ſaid of it's Virtues as a
        Medicine, it <lb/>may not be improper to explain the Nature of it, and <lb/>enumerate a few
        of it's remarkable Properties, <w part="I">conſider-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> as a
        Curioſity in Chemiſtry, in which Light chiefly <lb/>it has hitherto been view'd by thoſe who
        have been <lb/>acquainted with it. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is a kind of <hi rend="sc">Ethereal Oil</hi>,
        produced by the <lb/>Decompoſition of the Vinous Spirit by Means of the <lb/>Vitriolic Acid,
        and differs eſſentially both from Vinous <lb/>Spirits and Eſſential Oils in ſeveral
        Reſpects, tho' it <lb/>agrees with them in ſome, as will appear hereafter: <lb/>But as the
        Vinous Spirit may be decompoſed by means <lb/>of all the three Mineral Acids, <hi
          rend="italic">viz.</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Vitriolic,</hi> the <pb xml:id="page_4"
          n="4"/><lb/><hi rend="italic">Nitrous</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Marine,</hi> and as
        theſe all act differently <lb/>on the Spirit, they will, of Courſe, produce three <w
          part="I">dif-</w><lb/><w part="F">ferent</w> Kinds of ÆTHER; which, from the Name <lb/>of
        the Acid employ'd in making them, are term'd <hi rend="italic">Ma-<lb/>rine, Nitrous,</hi>
        or <hi rend="italic">Vitriolic:</hi> The laſt only is the Kind <lb/>here underſtood, it's
        Properties being more ſingular and <lb/>extraordinary, and, as an ÆTHER, more perfect
        <lb/>than either of the others; the Reaſon of which ſeems <lb/>to be, that the <hi
          rend="italic">Vitriolic Acid</hi> is a much ſtronger Agent <lb/>on the Spirit, and more
        perfectly decompoſes it, than <lb/>either the <hi rend="italic">Nitrous</hi> or <hi
          rend="italic">Marine.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is the moſt light, moſt volatile, and moſt <w
          part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">flammable</w>, of all known Liquids: It ſwims upon the
        <lb/>higheſt rectified Spirit of Wine as Oil does upon <w part="I">Wa-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ter</w>, and flies away ſo quickly as hardly to wet a Hand <lb/>it is dropped upon; from
        which Properties it probably <lb/>has obtained it's Name. It is ſo readily inflammable,
        <lb/>as to take Fire at the approach of a Candle, before the <lb/>Flame touches it. Any
        Electrified Body will alſo <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duce</w> the ſame Effect. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is one of the moſt powerful Solvents known in <w
          part="I">Che-</w><lb/><w part="F">miſtry</w>: It is neither <hi rend="italic">acid</hi>
        nor <hi rend="italic">alcaline,</hi> and therefore is <lb/>perfectly free from that faline
        Acrimony with which all <lb/>the common Volatile Spirits abound: It has a greater
        <lb/>Affinity with Gold than <hi rend="italic">Aqua Regia</hi> has, altho' it will <lb/>not
        diſſolve it in the Maſs, or whilſt in it's Metallic <lb/>Form; but if you add ÆTHER to a
        ſolution of <lb/>Gold in Aqua Regia, it preſently takes all the Gold <lb/>from it's former
        Solvent, keeping it perfectly <w part="I">diſſol-</w><lb/><w part="F">ved</w> and ſuſpended,
        without the leaſt Precipitation; <lb/>and becomes of a yellow Colour: The ÆTHER, <lb/>thus
        ſaturated with the Gold, does not mix with the <lb/>Aqua Regia, but may readily be ſeparated
        from it by <lb/>ſimple Decantation, and thus a true and ſafe <hi rend="italic">Aurum
          </hi><pb xml:id="page_5" n="5"/><lb/><hi rend="italic">potabile</hi> is readily prepared
        for thoſe who want ſuch a <lb/>Medicine. The Union of theſe two Subſtances is very
        remarkable, one being the heavieſt ſolid Body we know, <lb/>and the other the lighteſt
        Liquid. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> ÆTHER is remarkably cold, when dropped <lb/>upon
        the Hand, and it affects the Thermometer in an <lb/>extraordinary Manner; for if the Ball of
        either a <w part="I">Mer-</w><lb/><w part="F">curial</w> or Spirituous Thermometer be
        immerſed in it, <lb/>the Spirit or Mercury immediately ſinks conſiderably, <lb/>tho' both
        the ÆTHER and the Thermometer have <lb/>ſtood a ſufficient Time together to be brought to
        the <lb/>temperature of the Room, before the Experiment was <lb/>made. The Thermometers dipt
        into Water, or Spirit <lb/>of Wine, in the ſame Manner, ſuffer not the leaſt <w part="I"
          >Al-</w><lb/><w part="F">teration</w>. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">They</hi> who chuſe to ſee a further Account of the
        <lb/>ſingular Effects which this curious Fluid produces, may <lb/>peruſe what Doctor <hi
          rend="italic">Frobenius,</hi> a <hi rend="italic">German</hi> Chemiſt, has <lb/>publiſhed
        concerning it, in the Philoſophic Tranſactions <lb/>for the Years 1733 and 1741. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> the moſt valuable Qualities of the ÆTHER <lb/>are
        it's <hi rend="italic">medicinal</hi> ones; it having been found by <w part="I"
          >repeat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> Experience to be an excellent Remedy in moſt <hi
          rend="italic">ner-<lb/>vous Diſeaſes;</hi> particularly in <hi rend="sc">Fits</hi> of all
        ſorts, whether <hi rend="italic">Epileptic, Convulſive, Hyſteric, Hypochondriac,</hi> or <hi
          rend="italic">Para-<lb/>lytic:</hi> In habitual <hi rend="sc">Head-aches, Gout, <w
            part="I">Rheuma-</w><lb/><w part="F">tism</w>, Pains in the Stomach, Windy Disorders
          <lb/>of the Stomach and Intestines, Hooping Cough, <lb/>Asthma, Pleuritic Pains</hi>, and
          <hi rend="sc">Deafnfss</hi>; all <lb/>which Diſeaſes have, in a ſingular Manner, been
        removed <lb/>by it; and that the Publiſher may contribute all the <w part="I">Aſ-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſiſtance</w> he can in extending the uſe of this Medicine, the <lb/>following
        Methods of applying it are given, which have <lb/>been attended with Succeſs. </p>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_6" n="6"/>
        <head rend="italic align-center"><lb/>Particular Directions for uſing the <hi rend="roman"
            >ÆTHER</hi>. <lb/><hi rend="roman">In the HEAD-ACH</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">A Fit</hi> of the Head-ach is almoſt inſtantly removed
          <lb/>by applying the ÆTHER externally to the <w part="I">Fore-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >head</w>, by means of a bit of Linen Rag, in the Manner <lb/>hereafter directed for
          it's external Application. Or it <lb/>may be applied to any other Part of the Head where
          <lb/>the Pain lies, being firſt ſhaved, if neceſſary. If the <lb/>Pain is violent, a Doſe
          of it ſhould be alſo taken <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">wardly</w>. In ſtubborn
          Caſes it will likewiſe be <w part="I">ſervice-</w><lb/><w part="F">able</w> to ſnuff a
          little of the ÆTHER up the Noſtrils, <lb/>either alone or mixed with equal Parts of
          Lavender <lb/>Water, <hi rend="italic">Hungary</hi> Water, or Brandy; or it may be more
          <lb/>convenient to apply a bit of Linen Rag, wetted with <lb/>ÆTHER, up the Noſtrils. Any
          of theſe Means, <lb/>or all of them, muſt be repeated if the Pain is ſo <w part="I"
            >ur-</w><lb/><w part="F">gent</w> as to require it. To cure this Diſorder radically,
          <lb/>when it is of long ſtanding, and to prevent it's <w part="I">Re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >turn</w>, the Medicine muſt be taken inwardly for a <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſiderable</w> Time every Night at Bed-time, or in violent <lb/>Caſes, every
          Night and Morning, in a ſmall Draught <lb/>of cold Water, according to the General
          Direction for <lb/>taking it inwardly, given p. 11. In ſome particular <lb/>Caſes, Vomits
          are very ſerviceable. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>A VERTIGO. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">A Vertigo</hi>, Giddineſs, or Swimming in the Head,
          <lb/>will generally be removed by proceeding in the ſam <lb/>Manner as for the Head-ach.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>The EPILEPSY. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>No Diſeaſe is more difficult to cure than the <w part="I"
            >Epi-</w><lb/><w part="F">lepſy</w> or Falling-Sickneſs; yet ſeveral Inſtances have <pb
            xml:id="page_7" n="7"/><lb/>occurred where the moſt violent Degrees of it have been
          <lb/>cured, even in grown Perſons, by taking a Doſe of this <lb/>Medicine regulary every
          Night and Morning for a <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſiderable</w> Time. The Doſe
          muſt be regulated <w part="I">accord-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> to the Age of the
          Patient, as mentioned in the <lb/>General Direction, Page 11. If a Pain is felt in
          <lb/>any Part of the Head, the ÆTHER muſt be <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">plied</w>
          to that Part occaſionally, and it muſt be <w part="I">previouſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w>
          ſhaved, if neceſſary. It will be proper to give a <lb/>ſmall Doſe of <hi rend="italic"
            >Tinctura Sacra,</hi> or of the <hi rend="italic">Pill. Rufi,</hi>
          <lb/>at proper Intervals, as once a Week or Fortnight. <lb/>It will alſo, in moſt Caſes,
          be neceſſary to give now <lb/>and then a Vomit. If it be ſuſpected that the Patient
          <lb/>has Worms, proper Medicines to deſtroy them ought <lb/>alſo to be given. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>In CONVULSIONS. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> Convulſions, or Convulſive Diſorders, give the
          <lb/>ÆTHER inwardly, a Doſe two three Times a <lb/>Day, or oftener, according to the
          exigence of the Caſe; <lb/>and it ſhould alſo be applied externally to the <w part="I"
            >Fore-</w><lb/><w part="F">head</w>, or any other Part of the Head, during the Fit.
          <lb/>If the Patient is full of Blood, bleeding is neceſſary, and <lb/>if Coſtive, a Doſe
          of <hi rend="italic">Manna, Senna,</hi> or any gentle <w part="I">Lax-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ative</w>, or a Clyſter, ſhould be given. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>Hyſteric and Hypochondriac DISORDERS. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> Medicine has excellent Effect in <hi
            rend="italic">Hyſteric Fits,</hi>
          <lb/>and in all that Train of Symptoms which Hyſteric and <lb/>Hypochondriac Perſons are
          ſubject to; ſuch as Riſings in <lb/>the Throat threatning Suffocation, difficult
          Breathing, <lb/>Flutterings and Palpitations of the Heart, frequent <lb/>Fainting, Lowneſs
          of Spirits, violent Pains in the <lb/>Head, Languor of the whole Body, Dullneſs of the <pb
            xml:id="page_8" n="8"/><lb/>Mind and Senſes, with conſtant Anxieties and <w part="I"
            >Inqui-</w><lb/><w part="F">etude</w>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> The Doſe muſt be
          repeated according to <lb/>the urgency of the Symptoms; and the Medicine muſt <lb/>be
          continued ſome Time after the Complaints <w part="I">diſap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pear</w>,
          to prevent a Relapſe. It will be ſerviceable <w part="I">du-</w><lb/><w part="F">ring</w>
          the Uſe of the ÆTHER, eſpecially in Caſe of <lb/>Coſtiveneſs, to take at proper Intervals
          a gentle Purge, <lb/>ſuch as <hi rend="italic">Tinctura Sacra, Pill. Rufi, Rhubarb,</hi>
          or <hi rend="italic">Glau-<lb/>ber's Salts.</hi> Bodily Exerciſe of all ſorts contributes
          <lb/>greatly to the Cure of theſe Complaints, eſpecially <w part="I">Ri-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ding</w> on Horſeback. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>PALSY. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">Palſies,</hi> and all Paralytic Complaints, the Patient, if <lb/>a grown
          Perſon, muſt take the quantity of a Tea Spoonful <lb/>of the ÆTHER every Night and
          Morning. The Doſe <lb/>muſt be leſſened in young People, according to their <lb/>Age. It
          will alſo be proper to ſnuff a little of it up <lb/>the Noſtrils once or twice a Day, or
          apply a bit of Rag <lb/>wetted with it up the Noſtrils. The ÆTHER muſt <lb/>alſo be
          applied externally to the Part affected, at leaſt <lb/>once every Day. It ſhould likewiſe
          be applied now and <lb/>then to the Forehead, or any other part of the Head,
          <lb/>eſpecially if the Tongue, Eyes, or any part of the <lb/>Face or Head be affected. If
          the Arms or Hands are <lb/>Paralytic, the Application ſhould be made to the <w part="I"
            >low-</w><lb/><w part="F">er</w> and back Part of the Neck, as well as to the Part <w
            part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F">fected</w>. If the Diſeaſe has ſeiz'd the Thighs, Legs,
          or <lb/>Feet, the Application muſt not only be made to them, <lb/>but likewiſe to the Back
          Bone, at the Loins. As this <lb/>Medicine cannot, on account of it's Volatility and <w
            part="I">Pun-</w><lb/><w part="F">gency</w>, be properly applied to the Whole of a <w
            part="I">Paraly-</w><lb/><w part="F">tic</w> Limb at once, but only to a ſmall Part of
          it, the <lb/>Application therefore may be made ſometimes to one <pb xml:id="page_9" n="9"
          /><lb/>Part, and ſometimes to another, as ſhall be thought <lb/>proper. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> Diſeaſe will require a longer or ſhorter <w
            part="I">Continu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ance</w> of theſe Means, according to the Degree
          of it, <lb/>and the Time it has continued. A Vomit ſhould be <lb/>given, and repeated now
          and then as the Patient can <lb/>bear it; but if Vomits ſeem too fatiguing, a Doſe of
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tinctura Sacra</hi> may be given in their room. Paralytic
          <lb/>Patients ſhould uſe as much Bodily Exerciſe as poſſible, <lb/>and the Head, Neck, and
          the whole Spine, as well as <lb/>the Parts affected, ſhould be frequently rubbed with a
          <lb/>hot and dry Cloth till they appear red. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>GOUT. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> Medicine is of ſingular Service in the <hi
            rend="italic">Gout,</hi> not <lb/>only while it continues in the Limbs, but particularly
          <lb/>when it flies inwards, and attacks the Head, Stomach, or <lb/>any of the internal
          Parts; in which Caſes a few Doſes will <lb/>not fail to give preſent Relief. It ſhould be
          taken in the <lb/>Quantity of a Tea Spoonful, two or three Times every <lb/>Day, or
          oftener, if the Caſe be violent, during the <w part="I">Gou-</w><lb/><w part="F">ty</w>
          Fit. It carries off the Gouty Matter by Urine, which <lb/>it renders very thick and
          turbid. At any Time when <lb/>there is a Neceſſity to abate the exceſſive Pain in the
          <lb/>Part affected, the ÆTHER may be applied to it <lb/>externally, according to the
          Method given p. 12. It <lb/>will be proper to continue taking the ÆTHER once <lb/>or twice
          a Day for ſome Time after the Fit is gone, <lb/>and to begin taking it again about the
          Time of it's <lb/>expected Return; by which Means, tho' it may not <lb/>prevent the Return
          of the Fit, which in many Caſes <lb/>perhaps ought not to be deſired, yet it will ſhorten
          it's <lb/>Continuance, and moderate the Pain of it. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <pb xml:id="page_10" n="10"/>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>RHEUMATISM. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> Rheumatic Complaints the Patient muſt take a
          <lb/>Doſe of this Medicine every Night and Morning, or <lb/>oftener, if the Pains are
          violent; and it muſt be <w part="I">conti-</w><lb/><w part="F">nued</w> till the Diſeaſe
          is removed, or longer, to prevent <lb/>a Relapſe. If the Pain is fixed in any particular
          Part, <lb/>the ÆTHER muſt be applied to it twice a Day, as <lb/>directed hereafter. It
          muſt be obſerved that <unclear>#####</unclear>
          <lb/>very much conduces to the Cure of obſtinate <unclear>#</unclear>ic <lb/>Rheumatiſms,
          and muſt be repeated at proper Intervals <lb/>if neceſſary; the Blood in this Diſeaſe
          being generally <lb/>very ſizy. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="align-center italic"><lb/>Diſorders of the <hi rend="roman">Stomach</hi> and <hi
            rend="roman">Inteſtines.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> Medicine preſently cures Flatulent Cholics,
          <lb/>removes all Windy Diſorders of the Stomach and <w part="I">In-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >teſtines</w>, and corrects Acidities lodged there. It is alſo <lb/>found to have
          excellent Effect in correcting that <w part="I">Weak-</w><lb/><w part="F">neſs</w>, or bad
          Habit of the Stomach and Inteſtines, <lb/>which ſtudious Perſons, and ſuch as lead
          ſedentary <lb/>Lives, are particularly ſubject to, and is attended with <lb/>four
          Belchings, Heart-burn, Windy Diſtenſions, Pain <lb/>and Uneaſineſs in the Stomach and
          Bowels. It muſt <lb/>be taken every Night and Morning, according to the <lb/>General
          Direction below. Care ſhould be taken to <lb/>prevent Coſtiveneſs in theſe Caſes, which is
          beſt <w part="I">remo-</w><lb/><w part="F">ved</w> by chewing <hi rend="italic"
            >Rhubarb,</hi> or taking it any other way, <lb/>or by a Doſe of <hi rend="italic"
            >Manna,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Glauber's Salts,</hi> taken <w part="I">oc-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">caſionally</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> ÆTHER is an extraordinary Diuretic in <lb/><hi
            rend="sc">Dropsies</hi>: It is an excellent Medicine in an <hi rend="sc">Asthma</hi>,
          <lb/>and the <hi rend="sc">Hiccup</hi>; and may be looked upon as a <w part="I"
            >Spe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cific</w> in that Diſeaſe of Children called the <hi rend="sc"
            >Hooping-<lb/>Cough</hi>, or <hi rend="sc">Chin-Cough</hi>; in all which Caſes it muſt
            <pb xml:id="page_11" n="11"/><lb/>be taken inwardly, according to the General <w
            part="I">Directi-</w><lb/><w part="F">on</w> below, and the repetition of the Doſe muſt
          be <w part="I">regu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lated</w> by the violence of the Diſeaſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">A</hi>
          <hi rend="sc">Dose</hi> of it taken at going to Bed, after <w part="I">Drink-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ing</w> too freely, has been found to prevent the <w part="I">Head-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ach</w>, Sickneſs, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> which uſually follow next
          Morning. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> has removed <hi rend="sc">Deafness</hi>, and
          Hardneſs of <w part="I">Hear-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>, by moiſtening a little Cotton
          with a few Drops <lb/>of it, putting it into the Ear, and holding the Finger <lb/>for a
          few Minutes over it, at the ſame Time ſnuffing <lb/>a few Drops of it, mixed with Spirit
          of Lavender, up <lb/>the Noſtrils, or putting a bit of Rag wet with the <lb/>ÆTHER alone
          up the Noſtrils. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> has frequently removed a temporary <hi rend="sc"
            >Dimness of <lb/>Sight</hi>, attended with a Swimming or Uneaſineſs in <lb/>the Head, by
          external Application to the Forehead; <lb/>and is a promiſing Medicine in that Sort of
          Blindneſs <lb/>called a <hi rend="sc">Gutta Serena</hi>, and in Beginning <hi rend="sc"><w
              part="I">Cata-</w><lb/><w part="F">racts</w></hi>, in which Caſes it ſhould be taken
          inwardly, as <lb/>well as applied to the Forehead, and up the Noſtrils. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is likewiſe found to be of great Service in <w
            part="I">remo-</w><lb/><w part="F">ving</w>
          <hi rend="sc">Pleuritic Pains</hi>, and <hi rend="sc">Stitches</hi> in the Side, <lb/>by
          applying it to the affected Part, in the Manner <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >rected</w> for external Application. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="italic align-center"><lb/>The Method of taking the <hi rend="roman">ÆTHER</hi>
          Inwardly. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> General Doſe for a grown Perſon is a common
          <lb/>Tea Spoonful; and the beſt Vehicle to take it in is a <lb/>ſmall Draught of Cold
          Water. If it be only ſtirred <lb/>in the Water with the Spoon, and the Mixture drank
          <lb/>immediately it ſtrikes the Noſtrils by it's Volatility, <lb/>but may be thought by
          ſome as agreeable when <lb/>ſo taken as when the two Liquors are more <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">timately</w> mixed, by ſhaking them together in a Phial, <pb
            xml:id="page_12" n="12"/><lb/>and from thence pouring them into a Glaſs to be
          <lb/>drank; for tho' it has but little Smell in this Manner, <lb/>it is more warm to the
          Palate than in the other. The <lb/>Patient may uſe the Way of Mixing he likes beſt, and
          <lb/>if he has any Objection to Water, may take it in any <lb/>other agreeable cold
          Liquor. Children in the Month <lb/>may take two or three Drops for a Doſe; thoſe of a
          <lb/>Year old may take ſeven or eight Drops; thoſe of five <lb/>or ſix Years old may take
          from twenty to twenty-five <lb/>Drops, and ſo encreaſing according to their Years: <lb/>Or
          it may perhaps be better, in giving it to Children, <lb/>to mix a Tea Spoonful of ÆTHER,
          with a convenient <lb/>Quantity of Water, and, ſhaking it well, give at a <lb/>Doſe about
          one twentieth Part of this Mixture to a Child <lb/>a Month old; about one eighth Part to a
          Child <lb/>twelve or fourteen Months old; to thoſe about five <lb/>Years old one third
          Part of the Mixture; half of the <lb/>Mixture to thoſe about ſeven Years old, and two
          thirds <lb/>of it to thoſe about fourteen Years old. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="align-center italic"><lb/>The Method of applying the <hi rend="roman">ÆTHER</hi>
          Externally. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>To apply it Externally, you muſt procure a Bit of <lb/>Linen Rag, of
          ſuch a Dimenſion as to be conveniently <lb/>covered by the Palm of the Hand; moiſten this
          Rag <lb/>with a little of the ÆTHER as it lies upon your <lb/>Palm, and inſtantly apply it
          to the Part affected, <w part="I">preſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſing</w> it very cloſe, ſo as
          to prevent the Eſcape of it's <lb/>Fumes, for two or three Minutes, in which Time the
          <lb/>Rag will be found dry, and may be taken away. It <lb/>will be more convenient, on
          ſome Occaſions, (as in <lb/>applying it to Paralytic Parts, Rheumatic Pains, and <lb/>the
          Gout, to place the Rag upon a Piece of a ſoft, thin <lb/>Bladder; and, when moiſten'd with
          the ÆTHER, <lb/>to bind it gently upon the Part. A ſlight Redneſs uſually <pb
            xml:id="page_13" n="13"/><lb/>appears upon the Part after the Application, but it
          <lb/>quickly vaniſhes; but it may ſometimes happen, where <lb/>the Skin is very tender and
          too much ÆTHER has <lb/>been applied to the Forehead, or within the Ears, that <lb/>it may
          affect the Skin more than the Patient chooſes; <lb/>which is avoided by applying a leſs
          Quantity for the <lb/>future. This is the Secret of a preſent famous <w part="I"
            >Practi-</w><lb/><w part="F">tioner</w>, who having a Method ſometimes of concealing
          <lb/>his Application, is ſaid to cure the Head-ach, fixed <lb/>Rheumatic Pains, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> by the Touch of his Hand. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is very eaſy to conceive, from the extreme <w
            part="I">Sub-</w><lb/><w part="F">tlety</w> of this Medicine, that it muſt produce many
            <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">cellent</w> Effects in ſuch Diſeaſes as thoſe above
            <w part="I">menti-</w><lb/><w part="F">oned</w>, as it is converted into Vapour by a
          much leſs <lb/>Heat than the common Animal One; ſo that being <lb/>ſwallowed, it can
          hardly ſubſiſt in any Part of the human <lb/>Body under any Form but that of an extremely
            <w part="I">pene-</w><lb/><w part="F">trating</w> volatiliz'd Vapour; and it is
          perceptible by <lb/>it's Smell, as it paſſes thro' the Pores of the Skin, <w part="I"
            >ſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">veral</w> Hours after taking; ſo that it's ſtay in the Body
          <lb/>is longer, and it's Effects there more durable, than <lb/>might be expected from ſuch
          a ſubtle Subſtance. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Notwithstanding</hi> the extreme Subtlety of the
          <lb/>ÆTHER, it is perfectly innocent and ſafe to take, <lb/>as it contains nothing that is
          acrimonious or corroſive; <lb/>ſo that it may be given even to the youngeſt Children
          <lb/>without Heſitation. It neither purges nor vomits; nor <lb/>does it encreaſe any of
          the ſenſible Evacuations, <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">cept</w> that of Urine, and
          ſometimes that of Sweat, if <lb/>taken when in Bed; but as it is ſo diſtinctly perceived
          <lb/>by the Smell paſſing thro' the cutaneous Pores of thoſe <lb/>who take it, it is
          highly probable that it encreaſes <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſenſible</w>
          Perſpiration. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_14" n="14"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Another</hi> obſervable Property in this Medicine is,
          <lb/>that it does not coagulate or thicken the Serum of the <lb/>Blood, but thins it; and
          therefore has direct contrary <lb/>Effects to all the common Spirituous Compoſitions, when
          <lb/>either taken inwardly, or externally applied, and is <w part="I">eſ-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſentially</w> different from the moſt ſubtiliz'd Vinous <w part="I"
            >Spi-</w><lb/><w part="F">rits</w>; for tho' Spirit of Wine is uſed in making it, yet
          <lb/>it is ſo far decompoſed by the Proceſs, that it's Nature <lb/>is entirely changed. In
          conſequence of this Quality in <lb/>the ÆTHER, the Publiſher has ſucceſſfully diſſolved
          <lb/>ſome particular obſtinate Tumours, by applying it to <lb/>them, when other Means have
          failed—This Hint He <lb/>hopes will not paſs unnoticed by the Gentlemen of the
          <lb/>Faculty, as it is evident no Application whatever can <lb/>equal it in Subtlety and
          Diſſolving Power. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>THE Medicine ſo much celebrated in <hi rend="italic">Germany,</hi> and
          <lb/>ſo frequently commended and uſed in Practice by the <lb/>late famous Profeſſor <hi
            rend="italic">Hoffman,</hi> under the Title of his <lb/><hi rend="italic">Liquor
            Mineralis Anodynus,</hi> was nearly of the ſame <w part="I">Na-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ture</w> with the ÆTHER, but not ſo powerful, nor ſo <lb/>highly ſubtilized. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Repeated</hi> Experience has confirmed the Efficacy of
          <lb/>this Medicine in all the Diſeaſes before mentioned; and <lb/>from the Conſideration
          of it's uncommon Qualities, it <lb/>may be preſumed to be an excellent Remedy in many
          <lb/>others, if judiciouſly given: Hence it ſeems ſurpriſing <lb/>that ſo valuable an
          Addition to the <hi rend="italic">Materia Medica</hi> as <lb/>the ÆTHER doubtleſs is,
          ſhould have been ſo much <lb/>neglected, or ſo little known; but the Reaſons are,
          <lb/>that the Proceſs whereby it was made was kept ſecret <lb/>by ſome who rated the
          Preparation at a very <w part="I">extrava-</w><lb/><w part="F">gant</w> Price, and not
          ſufficiently attended to by others, <lb/>who conſider'd it only as a Chemical Curioſity,
          not as <lb/>a Medicine. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_15" n="15"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> chief Merit the Publiſher of this Account <w
            part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">tends</w> to, is, <hi rend="italic">the aſcertaining
            the Medicinal Virtues of this <lb/>curious Preparation,</hi> by ſeveral Years
          Experience, and <lb/>making them more publickly known; <hi rend="italic">the reducing it's
            <lb/>Price,</hi> which has hitherto been ſo extravagant that had <lb/>it's Virtues and
          Properties been known, only a ſmall <lb/>number of the afflicted could have enjoy'd the
          Benefit <lb/>of it; and, <hi rend="italic">the bringing it to a greater Degree of <w
              part="I">Perfec-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> than any hitherto ſold;</hi> what he
          offers being a <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">fectly</w> rectified Vitriolic ÆTHER. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> may not be improper to give the Marks by
          <lb/>which good ÆTHER may be known. It is <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">fectly</w>
          colourleſs, except it has receiv'd ſome accidental <lb/>Tinge from the Cork of the Phial
          in which it has been <lb/>kept; and ſo volatile as to ſtrike the Noſe very <w part="I"
            >power-</w><lb/><w part="F">fully</w>. It's Smell is more or leſs ſulphureous, <w
            part="I">accord-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> to the management of ſome Part of the
          Proceſs. <lb/>Wetting the Finger with it, or dropping a little upon <lb/>the Hand, it
          vaniſhes inſtantly, and leaves no Moiſture <lb/>behind; ſo that the Part ſcarcely ſeems to
          have been <lb/>wet. Half a Dozen Drops, dropped together upon <lb/>a Table, will diſappear
          in a few Seconds of a Minute, <lb/>and leave only the Appearance of a large oily Ring <w
            part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">hind</w>; but if it leaves the leaſt Watery or
          Spirituous <lb/>Moiſture, or does not evaporate in much leſs than a <lb/>Minute, it is not
          good. The beſt ÆTHER will <lb/>diſſolve in, or mix with, a certain Quantity of Water;
          <lb/>and that is the beſt which requires the largeſt Quantity <lb/>of Water to diſſolve
          it: If, therefore, to ſix Tea <w part="I">Spoonſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ful</w> of Water in
          a ſmall Phial, you add one of the <w part="I">Æ-</w><lb/><w part="F">THER</w> to be
          examined, cork up the Phial, and <lb/>ſhake them very well together; and upon ſtanding a
          <lb/>little while ſome part of the ÆTHER appears at <lb/>Top, in form of Oil, ſufficient
          to cover the ſurface of <lb/>the Mixture, it may be pronounced good, (provided it <pb
            xml:id="page_16" n="16"/><lb/>alſo anſwers in the other Methods of Trial) and the
          <lb/>more appears the better is the ÆTHER; but if <lb/>none appears, or not enough to
          cover the ſurface of <lb/>the Mixture, it was either adulterated, or not well <w part="I"
            >rec-</w><lb/><w part="F">tified</w>. If to this Mixture of ÆTHER and Water <lb/>you add
          a little <hi rend="italic">Salt of Tartar,</hi> and any Fermentation <lb/>enſues, the
          ÆTHER was not well rectified. Upon <lb/>ſhaking briskly a Phial containing ÆTHER, if the
          <lb/>Bubbles, or Proof as they are uſually called, do not <w part="I">diſap-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">pear</w> in leſs Time, and in larger Bubbles, than any <w part="I"
            >o-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> Liquor, (the Vinous Alcohol perhaps excepted.)
          <lb/>'tis not Genuine. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is the more neceſſary to obſerve theſe Rules of
          <lb/>proving the Quality of the ÆTHER, as the <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >perfect</w> Sorts have been found to diſagree with the <lb/>Stomach, and produce other
          bad Effects, beſides <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">appointing</w> the Patient's
          Expectation. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> ÆTHER that has the foremention'd <w part="I"
            >Pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">perties</w>, (for there are Preparations ſold by the ſame
          <lb/>Name, which are very imperfect Imitations of it) is <lb/>made and ſold by M. TURNER,
          Surgeon, in <hi rend="italic">Liverpool.</hi>
          <lb/>The Ounce Phial <hi rend="italic">two Shillings;</hi> the Half Ounce <hi
            rend="italic">one <lb/>Shilling.</hi> The Phials are ſquare; the Word ÆTHER
          <lb/>inſcribed on one Side, and M. TURNER on the <w part="I">op-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >poſite</w>, and ſealed with a Lion gardant, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> Proper
          <lb/>Abatement will be made to Druggiſts, Apothecaries, <lb/>or the Gentlemen of the
          Faculty who uſe any <w part="I">conſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">derable</w> Quantity. To
          prevent it's eſcape and loſs, a <lb/>ſmall Quantity of Water is put into each Phial, which
          <lb/>ſhould be kept with the Cork downwards, by which <lb/>Means the ÆTHER is prevented,
          by the <w part="I">interpoſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of the Water, from evaporating. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> Publiſher has alſo appointed it to be ſold by
          <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">R. Board,</hi> Chemiſt and Druggiſt, in <hi rend="italic"
            >Grace-church-<lb/>ſtreet;</hi> and Mr. <hi rend="italic">J. Wilkie,</hi> Bookſeller, at
          the Bible in <lb/>St. <hi rend="italic">Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, LONDON: and Mr. <hi
            rend="italic">Peter <lb/>Wilſon,</hi> Bookſeller, in <hi rend="italic">Dame-ſtreet,</hi>
          <hi rend="sc">Dublin</hi>. </p>
      </div>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
