<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Störck: A necessary supplement to the former essays on the medicinal
          virtues of hemlock</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Anton Freiherr Von Störck</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">A NECESSARY SUPPLEMENT To the former ESSAYS on the MEDICINAL VIRTUES
              OF Hemlock. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">N10419</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N10419"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for T. Becket and P. A. De Hondt, in the Strand,
                  M,DCC,LXII. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1762</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="3"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="47"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">Countway Library of Medicine</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3307815806</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K006138.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: medicine"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2" n="iii"/>
        <head rend="align-center dc(2)"><lb/>PREFACE. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>F we read with attention the hiſtories <lb/>of
          grand remedies, we ſee, their <w part="I">effi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cacy</w> was ever
          warmly diſputed, at all <lb/>times, and in all places. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>There were phyſicians, who <w part="I">immedi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ately</w> condemned them, and proſcribed <lb/>them as hurtful. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But others, upon different experiments, <lb/>praiſed and commended
          them, as moſt <lb/>ſalutary. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>By theſe learned diſputes the thing was <lb/>at laſt rightly
          determined, and applied to <lb/>common uſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I plainly foreſee, the ſame will happen <lb/>to <hi rend="sc"
            >Hemlock</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But in the mean time I am very ſorry, <lb/>to ſee ſome medical people,
          of great rank, <lb/>give a premature and harſh ſentence <w part="I">a-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >gainſt</w>
          <hi rend="italic">hemlock;</hi> and to condemn it, and <lb/>to diſſuade others from it, as
          a poiſonous <lb/>and uſeleſs plant. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This ſavours of too great a deſire of <lb/>contradiction; and is
          repugnant to all <w part="I">rea-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſon</w> in medicine. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_3" n="iv"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But the moſt cruel thing that has <w part="I">hap-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >pened</w> to me, is, to find thoſe to be my <lb/>enemies, whom I always treated with
          <lb/>the greateſt reſpect; to whom I have done <lb/>all manner of good offices; and whoſe
          <lb/>duty it rather was, to take my part, than <lb/>to hurt me. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But I am neither concerned at that, <lb/>nor thirſt after revenge. And
          that theſe <lb/>my adverſaries may acknowledge, I am <lb/>no ways diſaffected to them on
          that <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">count</w>, although I may differ in opinion;
          <lb/>I write theſe obſervations for their <w part="I">ho-</w><lb/><w part="F">nour</w>;
          offer and dedicate them, with all <lb/>due reſpect, to them. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Bur I do not by any means deſire, that <lb/>they ſhould ſhew me any
          favour. Let <lb/>them only love the truth; act like juſt <lb/>judges; and ingenuouſly own,
          whatever <lb/>is for the good of the ſick. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As for the idle clamours of ſome, I am <lb/>indifferent about them,
          and deſpiſe them. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Whoever dreads the rattling of leaves, <lb/>let him avoid a wood. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_4"/>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>A NECESSARY <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">SUPPLEMENT</hi>
          <lb/>UPON <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">HEMLOCK. </hi></head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> Have already ſhewn, and confirmed, <lb/>in two
          former volumes, the virtue <lb/>and efficacy there is in <hi rend="italic">hemlock.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>For that reaſon there was no occaſion, <lb/>that I ſhould write any
          thing more on <lb/>that ſubject. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But as there are ſtill many, who do <lb/>not rightly conceive my
          notions about <lb/><hi rend="italic">hemlock;</hi> and doubt its <hi rend="italic"
            >ſpecies,</hi> and <w part="I">cha-</w><lb/><w part="F">racter</w>; it was neceſſary to
          give a figure <lb/>of the plant. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_5" n="2"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And that this might be rightly done, <lb/>and made clear and plain to
          every one, <lb/>without any danger of error, I entreated <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Crantz,</hi> the famous and <w part="I">indefati-</w><lb/><w part="F">gable</w>
          Profeſſor of the Inſtitutions of <w part="I">Me-</w><lb/><w part="F">dicine</w>, and of
          the <hi rend="italic">materia medica,</hi> to bring <lb/>this plant into his botanical
          garden, and <lb/>to take care to have it well <w part="I">deline-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ated</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This he did willingly, and gave me <lb/>this table, drawn and engraved
          by the <lb/>learned Mr. <hi rend="italic">Cipps,</hi> a candidate in phyſic. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>From this any one, the leaſt verſed <lb/>in botany, may know the plant
          at firſt <lb/>ſight, and diſtinguiſh it from all others. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But as for the extract of it, it is not <lb/>every where prepared to
          my mind. For <lb/>they take a large quantity of the expreſſed <lb/>juice, which they boil
          in a copper veſſel, <lb/>on a fierce fire; whence ariſes a ſtrong <lb/>fetid ſteam, which
          is the beſt part of <lb/>the medicine, that flies off: and beſides, <lb/>they do not take
          proper care to purify <lb/>the juice and extract. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>By theſe means is prepared a black <lb/>maſs, that is tough, and with
          little of the <lb/>genuine fetid flavour. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_6" n="3"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But when it is prepared in my way, <lb/>it ought to be a thick
          extract, of a dark <lb/>greeniſh colour, with a moſt ungrateful <lb/>fetid flavour, much
          like the ſmell of <lb/>mice. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Some have mixed other herbs with <lb/><hi rend="italic">hemlock,</hi>
          and ſome leave the herb freſh <lb/>gathered in a heap for ſeveral days, by <lb/>which it
          grows flaccid; part of it <w part="I">cor-</w><lb/><w part="F">rupts</w>; and the juice
          grows roapy and <lb/>ſlimy. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Others do not boil the juice as ſoon <lb/>as it is expreſſed, but wait
          for a day <lb/>or two, till they have leiſure; by which <lb/>the juice changes, and loſes
          its virtue. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>On this occaſion I thought it would <lb/>not be improper, to give an
          account of <lb/>ſome cures, that I have made with <hi rend="italic">hem-<lb/>lock</hi>
          alone, ſince my ſecond treatiſe on <lb/>that ſubject was publiſhed. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In doing this I ſhall be ſhort, that I <lb/>may not interrupt the
          leiſure, or conſume <lb/>the time, that is ſo precious to <w part="I">phyſi-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">cians</w>, by tedious narrations. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>When I ſay I gave <hi rend="italic">hemlock,</hi> I mean <lb/>its
          extract; which I take notice of, that <lb/>there may be no diſpute about words. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_7" n="4"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nor have I always added the doſe of <lb/>the medicine; becauſe I have
          almoſt <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">ways</w> begun with a ſmall quantity, and
          <lb/>gradually encreaſed it, till a good effect <lb/>enſued: then I ſtopped, and never <w
            part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">creaſed</w> the doſe afterwards. </p>
        <div n="1" type="case">
          <head rend="align-center "><lb/>CASE I. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Man of about thirty years of age,
            <lb/>complained, for ſeveral months, of a <lb/>violent pain, and continual heat, in his
            <lb/>belly: he had no appetite; the urine <lb/>flowed as in a ſtrangury; his ſtools were
            <lb/>frequent, ſmall, hot, joined with a <hi rend="italic">tenes-<lb/>mus;</hi> the
            complexion pale, and the whole <lb/>body emaciated. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Remedies of every kind were tried, <lb/>but did no ſervice : ſleep
            was rather <lb/>diſturbed, and his ſtrength began to fail. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Hemlock</hi> alone gave him relief in <lb/>the ſpace
            of three months: his appetite <lb/>returned; the ſtools became natural; his <lb/>urine
            was made freely; he gained ſtrength, <lb/>and a perfect ſtate of health. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="case">
          <pb xml:id="page_8" n="5"/>
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE II. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Youth of fifteen had a tumor for <lb/>three
            months, of the ſize of a <w part="I">wal-</w><lb/><w part="F">nut</w>, on his left
            cheek. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>A <hi rend="italic">fiſtula,</hi> weeping an <hi rend="italic"
              >ichor,</hi> penetrated <lb/>into this tumor. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The phyſicians and chirurgeons had <lb/>here tried their art for a
            long time to no <lb/>purpoſe. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>But upon giving <hi rend="italic">hemlock,</hi> the tumor
            <lb/>diſappeared; the <hi rend="italic">fiſtula</hi> cloſed; and all <lb/>his pains
            ceaſed. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="case">
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE III. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Woman, forty-odd years old, had a <lb/>very
            bad ſpreading tetter or ringworm <lb/><hi rend="italic">(ſerpiginem)</hi> on her hand,
            above a <w part="I">twelve-</w><lb/><w part="F">month</w>, ſo that the skin was cracked
            to <lb/>the fleſh in ſeveral places. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Neither external remedies, nor <w part="I">inter-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">nal</w> purges, and ſweetners of the blood, <lb/>gave any relief. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Hemlock</hi> cured her within two <lb/>months. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="case">
          <pb xml:id="page_9" n="6"/>
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE IV. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Woman, paſt thirty, perceived a <hi
              rend="italic">ſcir-<lb/>rhus</hi> of a large ſize in her right-<lb/>breaſt, for
            ſeveral months. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>A plaſter was applied, by which both <lb/>the hardneſs and ſize of
            the breaſt were <lb/>encreaſed, and the ſwelling ſpread under <lb/>the arm-pit. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The tumor became of a purple <w part="I">co-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >lour</w>, with here and there livid ſtreaks, <lb/>and the pain ſo exceſſive, that ſhe
            could <lb/>neither ſleep day nor night. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>At length ſeveral knots or tubercles <lb/>roſe on the tumor, which
            threatened a <lb/>very bad exulceration. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>I being called in, deſired that ſhe would <lb/>lay aſide all kind of
            plaſters, and cover <lb/>the breaſt only with a ſoft linen cloth. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Internally I gave only the extract of <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >hemlock.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the ſpace of eight days the pain <lb/>almoſt entirely ceaſed; the
            colour of the <lb/>tumor changed; and the tubercles <w part="I">ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ſided</w>. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>In nine weeks the breaſt came to its <lb/>natural ſtate. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_10" n="7"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The greateſt doſe was half a drachm a day. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="case">
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE V. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Woman, of twenty-ſeven years of <lb/>age,
            throwed up every thing ſhe <w part="I">ſwal-</w><lb/><w part="F">lowed</w> for three and
            twenty weeks, and <lb/>was almoſt conſumed by it. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Phyſicians, chirurgeons, quacks, and <lb/>old women, had tried all
            their skill, <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w part="F">out</w> any amendment of the
            diſorder. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>I ordered twenty grains of the extract <lb/>of <hi rend="italic"
              >hemlock,</hi> in a mixture of four ounces; <lb/>of which ſhe took a ſpoonful every
            two <lb/>hours; and in a ſhort time the vomiting <lb/>ceaſed; ſhe recovered her
            appetite, and <lb/>her ſtrength. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>And it is now three months, ſince any <lb/>ſigns of the vomiting
            have returned. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="6" type="case">
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE VI. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Man of ſeventy had an ulcer in his <lb/>arm
            for five years: a ſharp humor <lb/>that weeped out of it continually fretted <pb
              xml:id="page_11" n="8"/><lb/>the parts adjacent, and excited burning <lb/>puſtules. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The remedies that were applied anon <lb/>relieved the diſorder, but
            the itching ſoon <lb/>returned, with a fretting of the cuticle; <lb/>and the ulcer began
            to weep a moſt ſharp <lb/>humor. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The patient then took, by my advice, <lb/>ſix grains of the extract
            of <hi rend="italic">hemlock,</hi> every <lb/>morning, and as many every evening,
            <lb/>for five weeks: outwardly was applied <lb/>the plaſter of <hi rend="italic"
              >diapompholyx:</hi> and now in <lb/>ſix months the ulcer is quite healed, and <lb/>the
            old man enjoys perfect health. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="7" type="case">
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE VII. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Noble old lady had both her breaſts
            <lb/>large and ſcirrhous. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>A plaſter irritated the diſorder, and <lb/>brought on great pain. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The nipple of the right-breaſt was <lb/>twice as large as uſual,
            ulcerated, and <lb/>continually weeped a ſharp, corroſive <lb/>ichor. The tumor had
            ſpread under the <lb/>arm-pits. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_12" n="9"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The good old lady could hardly ſpeak, <lb/>much leſs laugh, or
            breathe freely, through <lb/>pain. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The taking of <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> immediately
            <lb/>amended the diſorder; the nipple was <lb/>reduced to its natural ſize in four
            weeks; <lb/>and in four months both breaſts were <lb/>cured. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>There was no occaſion to increaſe the <lb/>doſe above eighteen
            grains a day. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="8" type="case">
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE VIII. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Man, about thirty, had a tumor larger
            <lb/>than a man's fiſt, for a long time, <lb/>on the right ſide of his neck. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>He was, beſides, cachectic; and <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >plained</w> of violent pains, all over his <lb/>body, and in all his limbs; which <w
              part="I">tor-</w><lb/><w part="F">mented</w> him night and day. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe complaints leſſened his <w part="I">appe-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >tite</w>; he waſted away; and looked ill, <lb/>of a dark yellow complexion. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Whatever remedies he took were of <lb/>no ſervice. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>But as ſoon as he conſulted me, I <lb/>gave him, <hi rend="italic"
              >hemlock;</hi> by which in a few <pb xml:id="page_13" n="10"/><lb/>days he grew
            better, and in two months <lb/>was quite well. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="9" type="case">
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE IX. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Woman, of thirty ſix years of <lb/>age,
            laboured under malignant <w part="I">ul-</w><lb/><w part="F">cers</w>, for two years;
            which had eat <lb/>into the tip of the noſe, the noſtrils, <lb/>and the whole upper lip;
            ſo as to <w part="I">ren-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w> the whole viſage a moſt frightful
            <lb/>ſight. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>All theſe parts were livid, hard, <lb/>ſwelled; and violent pain
            deprived the <lb/>miſerable object of reſt. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>A ſharp thin humor, continually <lb/>weeping, corroded the adjacent
            parts. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Purges, antiſcorbutics, mercurials, <lb/>ſweetners of the blood,
            made no <w part="I">alter-</w><lb/><w part="F">ation</w>; if it were not, that the <w
              part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">order</w> ſeemed to grow much worſe. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Upon the taking of <hi rend="italic">hemlock,</hi> a copious
            <lb/>ichor, but much milder, was diſcharged; <lb/>and immediately the ſwelling of all
            <lb/>the parts fell; the pain ceaſed; and <lb/>the livid colour was changed to a <w
              part="I">na-</w><lb/><w part="F">tural</w> one. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_14" n="11"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>In three weeks time a great change <lb/>was obſerved for the better;
            and the <lb/>patient grew much ſtronger, and plump. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>She then abſtained for ſome time from <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >hemlock;</hi> but matters ſoon grew worſe; <lb/>and the pains encreaſed. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>But as ſoon as ſhe began to uſe <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi>
            <lb/>again, all the bad ſymptoms went off: and <lb/>by a continued uſe of it for ſix
            weeks the <lb/>ulcers were cicatriſed; and the ſwelling <lb/>diſappeared. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="10" type="case">
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE X. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Woman of thirty-two, had a pain in <lb/>her
            right groin for ſix years, with a <lb/>a hard tumor; and an acrid purulent <w part="I"
              >hu-</w><lb/><w part="F">mor</w> dropped from the womb. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>She imputed the cauſe of this diſorder <lb/>to her laſt lying-in,
            which was a <w part="I">trouble-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſome</w> one; in which the midwife
              <w part="I">extrac-</w><lb/><w part="F">ted</w> the after-birth with great force. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Neither baths, nor medicines, which <lb/>ſhe had taken for ſix
            years, had any effect <lb/>on her diſorder. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>But by the uſe of <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> the tumor
            <lb/>diſappeared in ſix weeks; the pain ceaſed; <lb/>and the ſharp flux ſtopped. </p>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_15" n="12"/>
        <div n="11" type="case">
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE XI. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Man of twenty-nine, was troubled <lb/>with
            various venereal maladies for <lb/>many years, but was never perfectly cured. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The glands of the neck, groins, about <lb/>the ears, under the
            arm-pits, &amp;c. at laſt <lb/>ſwelled; and created great pain night <lb/>and day. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Antivenereal remedies, that are <w part="I">other-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">wiſe</w> the beſt in theſe caſes, increaſed the <lb/>diſorder; ſo that a
            conſumption was feared. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>On that account he refrained from all <lb/>medicines, by the advice
            of his phyſicians. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>From that he grew neither better nor <lb/>worſe; if it were not,
            that his pains were <lb/>often moſt ſevere. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>At laſt he was forſaken by his <w part="I">phyſi-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">cian</w> in ordinary; who ſaid, he would <lb/>leave the caſe to nature. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>But this patient had ſeen the good <w part="I">ef-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">fect</w> of <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> in ſome others; from <lb/>which he
            had conceived ſuch hopes, that <lb/>he came to me, and asked, if this <w part="I"
              >medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cine</w> might not be proper for his caſe. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_16" n="13"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>I immediately adviſed it, and he was <lb/>cured in two months; the
            ſcirrhous <w part="I">tu-</w><lb/><w part="F">mors</w> quite diſappearing. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="12" type="case">
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE XII. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Virgin, of ſeventeen, had a <hi
              rend="italic">ſpina ven-<lb/>toſa</hi> in her right-arm for three years; <lb/>with
            very ugly ulcers. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Innumerable medicines, both external <lb/>and internal, had no
            effect. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The belly grew hard, and big; an <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >cruciating</w> pain ſeized the limbs; and a <lb/>cachexy came on, with a loſs of
            ſtrength, <lb/>and emaciated habit. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Hemlock</hi> alone reduced the belly to its
            <lb/>natural ſize; cured the pains, cachexy, <lb/>and emaciated habit; and healed the <w
              part="I">ul-</w><lb/><w part="F">cers</w>, and <hi rend="italic">ſpina ventoſa.</hi>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div n="13" type="case">
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE XIII. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Boy, ſeven years old, had all the
            <lb/>glands of his neck, and about the ears, <lb/>ſcirrhous, big, and painful. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>His belly was moreover hard, and <lb/>ſwelled. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_17" n="14"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Six grains of the extract of <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi>
            <lb/>were given in the morning, and as many <lb/>in the evening; the effects of which
            were <lb/>ſo ſpeedy, that all the ſwellings ſubſided <lb/>within ten weeks. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="14" type="case">
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE XIV. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>A Woman, of twenty-five, had a violent <lb/>cough for four years,
            and a very <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">agreeable</w> itching over her whole
            body. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>White, pellucid, burning and <w part="I">corrod-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ing</w> puſtules frequently broke out all over <lb/>the skin. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>By a long uſe medicines ſhe at laſt <lb/>began to grow conſumptive. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>In this condition I gave her twice a <lb/>day four grains of the
            extract of <hi rend="italic">hem-<lb/>lock;</hi> upon which ſhe immediately ſpit <lb/>a
            very tough glutinous matter in <w part="I">quanti-</w><lb/><w part="F">ties</w>; the
            itching went off; her ſtrength <lb/>returned; with a perfect ſtate of health, <lb/>and
            good habit of body. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>This doſe of the medicine was not to <lb/>be encreaſed; becauſe it
            did as much as <lb/>could be deſired. </p>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_18" n="15"/>
        <div n="15" type="case">
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE XV. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Man about ſixty, after an intermittent
            <lb/>fever, had his belly ſwelled; the right <lb/>hypochondre tight and hard; a yellow
            <lb/>complexion, without any appetite; and <lb/>excruciating pains in the night-time in
            <lb/>his limbs, which were emaciated. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Hemlock</hi> entirely reſtored him. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="16" type="case">
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE XVI. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Man of ſeventy, had laboured under <lb/>a
            moſt violent vomiting, now for the <lb/>third month; which could not be ſtopped <lb/>by
            any remedy. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Hemlock,</hi> diſſolved in a mixture, ſoon
            <lb/>ſtopped and removed it. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="17" type="case">
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE XVII. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Rickety child, three years old, could
            <lb/>neither ſtand on its legs, nor breathe freely. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Hemlock</hi> carried off the whole diſorder;
            <lb/>ſo that the child breathed eaſily; ran <pb xml:id="page_19" n="16"/><lb/>about
            briskly; and enjoyed better health <lb/>than the reſt of his brethren. I have <lb/>many
            like caſes. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>In ſome, four or ſix grains a day are <w part="I">ſuf-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ficient</w>: but in others the doſe ſhould be <lb/>encreaſed to ten, twelve,
            and twenty grains. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="18" type="case">
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE XVIII. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Virgin, of ſix and twenty, was ſubject
            <lb/>to moſt violent hemorrhages from the <lb/>womb for ſome years: and when the
            <lb/>flux of blood ſtopped, a thick, yellow, <lb/>acrid matter was diſcharged from the
            <lb/>womb, which corroded every thing. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Other eminent phyſicians, and myſelf, <lb/>tryed innumerable
            remedies for a long <lb/>time: but the patient found no relief from <lb/>them; ſhe
            rather grew cachectic, and <lb/>ſwelled. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>In ſuch a ſtubborn caſe, I was willing <lb/>to try, what <hi
              rend="italic">hemlock</hi> alone would do; and <lb/>for that purpoſe I gave her every
            day <lb/>three pills, each weighing three grains. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>After a few days I perceived, the <w part="I">co-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">lour</w> of the body was changed to a natural <lb/>one; ſhe gathered
            ſtrength, with a good <pb xml:id="page_20" n="17"/><lb/>appetite; and made urine
            plentifully, <lb/>with much glutinous matter. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>In a month's time, the whole diſorder <lb/>put on a very different
            appearance. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>For reſpiration, which was before <w part="I">ſuf-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">focated</w> with the leaſt motion, became <lb/>free; the anxious palpitation
            of the heart <lb/>ceaſed; and reſt was eaſy and quiet. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>But what was moſt remarkable, the <lb/>hemorrhagies of the womb
            ſtopped; and <lb/>the menſtrual flux appeared in due time, <lb/>in due quantity, and
            quality. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The matter, that flowed from the <lb/>womb, was no longer thick, nor
            acrid. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>In two months ſhe appeared to all to <lb/>be in perfect health; and
            only a little <lb/>mild ſerum weeped from the womb. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="19" type="case">
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CAXE XIX. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Man, about ſixty, had a tumor under <lb/>his
            chin, as big as a gooſe's egg, and <lb/>as hard as a ſtone, and painful; which
            <lb/>remained immoveable, without any <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">teration</w>;
            notwithſtanding the application <lb/>of remedies, both external and internal, <lb/>for a
            long time. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_21" n="18"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>But <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> looſened and diſcuſſed it,
            <lb/>in the ſpace of two months. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="20" type="case">
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE XX. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Cachectic, melancholic woman, of <lb/>forty,
            began to decay by degrees. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>No manifeſt fault could be diſcovered <lb/>in the whole body, to
            which this diſeaſe <lb/>could be attributed. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The face was of the color of the <lb/>earth; the eyes ſunk; voice
            weak; a <w part="I">fre-</w><lb/><w part="F">quent</w> palpitation of the heart;
            reſpiration <lb/>was ſhort and uneaſy, on a little hard <lb/>exerciſe; and the appetite
            quite loſt. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The uſual remedies in like caſes <lb/>afforded no relief. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>But three ounces of <hi rend="italic">hemlock,</hi> taken by
            <lb/>degrees, reſtored the appetite, vigor of <lb/>body, and chearfulneſs of mind;
            mended <lb/>the cachexy; and now this woman enjoys <lb/>perfect health, to the
            admiration of all. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>A cachexy, with an emaciated habit, <lb/>if it does not proceed from
            an internal <lb/>latent <hi rend="italic">vomica,</hi> or ſome corrupted bowel, <lb/>is
            generally cured by <hi rend="italic">hemlock.</hi>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div n="21" type="case">
          <pb xml:id="page_22" n="19"/>
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE XXI. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Boy of ten years of age, miſerably <lb/>torn
            with ulcers from a <hi rend="italic">ſpina ven-<lb/>toſa</hi><note place="bottom" n="*"
              rend="italic size(0.5)">* A ſpina ventoſa per totum corpus miſerè exulceratus.
            </note>, all over his body, and upon every <lb/>joint, as well as in the face, and about
            <lb/>the eyes, emaciated, and totally <w part="I">cachec-</w><lb/><w part="F">tic</w>,
            took various things for ſeveral years <lb/>from the beſt phyſicians, but to no <w
              part="I">pur-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſe</w>; the diſeaſe always grew worſe. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Upon giving <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> all the ulcers
            <lb/>healed, and the ſcars are not ugly. Large <lb/>pieces of the bones came off. He has
            <lb/>now good ſtrength, a natural complexion, <lb/>and ſound habit of body. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>He has now taken every day, for <w part="I">ſeve-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ral</w> weeks, a whole drachm of the <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >tract</w> of <hi rend="italic">hemlock,</hi> the doſe having been <lb/>gradually
            increaſed. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="22" type="case">
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE XXII. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Woman above forty, has now for <lb/>two
            years laboured under an open <lb/><hi rend="italic">cancer,</hi> moſt miſerably
            ulcerated. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_23" n="20"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>By the internal and external uſe of <hi rend="italic"
              >hem-<lb/>lock,</hi> the whole ulcer is now almoſt <w part="I">heal-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ed</w>. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>She was before totally emaciated; with <lb/>night ſweats; and loſs
            of appetite. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>But now ſhe has gathered ſtrength; the <lb/>complexion is good;
            ſleep quiet; the pain <lb/>is gone; the ſweats have ceaſed; and the <lb/>emaciated habit
            is no more to be <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">cerned</w>. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>A drachm and a half of the extract <lb/>of <hi rend="italic"
              >hemlock</hi> is ſtill given every day. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>In another woman thirty-odd years old, <lb/>I reduced a large open
              <hi rend="italic">cancer</hi> to a ſmall <lb/>ſize by the ſole uſe of <hi
              rend="italic">hemlock,</hi> in ſix <lb/>weeks; and a <hi rend="italic">cicatrix</hi>
            now begins to be <lb/>formed. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe caſes occurred to me in my <lb/>practice in the city. But as
            for thoſe <lb/>things that I have ſeen in the hoſpital, <lb/>which are certainly
            wonderful, and <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerve</w> the attention of the
            learned world, <lb/>I could not relate them here; becauſe Mr. <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >Collin,</hi> my excellent collegue, is faithfully <lb/>deſcribing them, and will ſoon
            commit <lb/>them to the preſs. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_24" n="21"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>We daily ſee ſo good and ſo manifeſt <lb/>effects of <hi
              rend="italic">hemlock</hi> in the hoſpital, that not <lb/>only the ſtudents of phyſic,
            but other <lb/>ignorant people, who are about the ſick, <lb/>are aſtoniſhed, and wonder
            at them. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nevertheleſs there are ſome caſes, in <lb/>which there is no
            ſucceſs. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>For if the diſeaſe is got to too great <lb/>a height; or the whole
            habit is deſtroyed, <lb/>who is there that will cure? or from <lb/>what method of
            practice can we <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">miſe</w> health? </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>We neither perform, nor deſire, <w part="I">mi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >racles</w> from our medicines; but we wait <lb/>to ſee how far we can go by art. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>If we meet with any obſtacle, we <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ſider</w>, whether that is to be overcome by <lb/>art: when we cannot do
            that, we <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">knowledge</w>, that we are but men, and
            <lb/>are yet ignorant of many things. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>We do not imagine, that we are <w part="I">ſupe-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >rior</w> in art to others; but daily deſire to <lb/>be taught by the meaneſt. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>But we likewiſe deſire others, that they <lb/>will be of the ſame
            mind towards us, if <lb/>we err, or have erred; and that they will <lb/>ſhew our error
            in friendſhip and decency; <pb xml:id="page_25" n="22"/><lb/>then we ſhall neither bluſh
            to be taught <lb/>better things, nor prove obſtinate. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>COROLLARIES. </head>
          <div n="1" type="corollary">
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>I. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE extract of <hi rend="italic"
                >hemlock</hi> is a very <w part="I">inno-</w><lb/><w part="F">cent</w> medicine. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>It may, by gradually increaſing the <lb/>doſe, be given to the
              quantity of two, <lb/>three, or four drachms a day. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>And the uſe of ſo great a doſe may be <lb/>ſafely continued for
              ſeveral weeks. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Hemlock</hi> neither hurts infants, children,
              <lb/>the middle-aged, the old, decrepit, <w part="I">wo-</w><lb/><w part="F">men</w>
              big with child, the embryo's in the <lb/>womb, noble nor plebeian. </p>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="corollary">
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>II. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Hemlock</hi> neither excites a greater <lb/>motion,
              nor other diſturbance, in the <w part="I">cir-</w><lb/><w part="F">culation</w> of the
              blood. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>It neither cools, nor heats. </p>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="corollary">
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>III. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The extract of <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> is a moſt <w
                part="I">effi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cacious</w> medicine. </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_26" n="23"/>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>But it ſometimes, although rarely, <lb/>moves the belly; and much
              more rarely <lb/>excites vomiting; ſometimes it increaſes <lb/>perſpiration; but it
              very often diſcharges <lb/>a plentiful glutinous urine. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>But in many patients it does not <w part="I">ſen-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">ſibly</w> increaſe any evacuation. </p>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="corollary">
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>IV. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The extract of <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> has the greateſt
              <lb/>reſolving quality; and often penetrates, <lb/>and reaches to parts, which the
              moſt <lb/>powerful remedies hitherto known could <lb/>not touch. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>It opens obſtructions; and by that <lb/>means reſtores a free
              circulation of the <lb/>blood, when it is diſturbed, and <w part="I"
                >obſtruc-</w><lb/><w part="F">ted</w>. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Hence it removes a languor, <w part="I">numb-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >ness</w>, and pain in the limbs, proceeding <lb/>from that cauſe. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>It renders the mind ſerene, and the <lb/>body ſtrong and active. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>It increaſes the ſecretions; whence it <lb/>often makes the ears,
              noſe, mouth, and <lb/>jaws moiſt, when dry; and makes them <lb/>perſpire. </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_27" n="24"/>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Men who have no children, from an <lb/>immeability or obſtruction
              of the veſſels, <lb/>it renders fruitful. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>It removes a hardneſs or mucoſity in <lb/>the wombs of women;
              opens a paſſage <lb/>for the menſtrual flux, obſtructed from <lb/>that cauſe; and
              prepares a fit place for <lb/>conception. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>It cures children of the rickets. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>It often removes a numbneſs, coldneſs, <lb/>inſenſibility, and
              decay of the limbs; and <lb/>makes the natural heat return, with <w part="I"
                >vi-</w><lb/><w part="F">gorous</w> and brawny muſcles, and the <w part="I"
                >ne-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceſſary</w> ſenſations. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>For the ſame reaſon it frees the veſſels <lb/>of the eyes;
              reſtores weak ſight; and <lb/>ſometimes cures blindneſs <hi rend="italic">(gutta
                ſerena.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>This remedy often cures the deaf; <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">ſtores</w> the loſt ſenſe of ſmelling, and an <lb/>impediment in ſpeech is
              often removed <lb/>by the uſe of it. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>A rheumatiſm, or inveterate and <w part="I">obſti-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">nate</w> aches of the joints, are cured by its <lb/>reſolving quality. </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_28" n="25"/>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="corollary">
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>V. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Hemlock</hi> often reſolves tumors <w part="I"
                >ariſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> from obſtructions; and carries off <lb/>even old
              ſcirrhuſes, that reſiſt all other <lb/>the moſt efficacious remedies. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nor does it ſignify, in what part of the <lb/>body ſuch tumors
              lurk; it acts with equal <lb/>energy on all parts: thus it removes <w part="I"
                >ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtructions</w> in the ſublingual and <w part="I"
                >ſubaxil-</w><lb/><w part="F">lary</w> glands, about the ears, in the neck,
              <lb/>under the arm-pits, in the breaſt, belly, <lb/>groins, anus, vagina, uterus,
              penis, <w part="I">ſcro-</w><lb/><w part="F">tum</w>, teſticles, <hi rend="italic"
                >&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>It often cures a dropſy, by reſolving <lb/>the hard ſwellings <hi
                rend="italic">(ſcirrhos)</hi> of the <lb/>belly. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>It ſoftens the hard and ſtuffed bellies of <lb/>children, and
              brings them to a natural <lb/>ſtate. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Hence it often mends a cachexy; and <lb/>cures a conſumption
              itſelf, or hectic <lb/>fever. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>It diſſolves tubercles <hi rend="italic">(ſcirrhos)</hi> of the
              <lb/>lungs; and promotes a glutinous ſpitting: <lb/>hence it removes a difficulty of
              breathing, <lb/>night ſweats, and a decay. </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_29" n="26"/>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>It diſſipates tumors of the joints; and <lb/>reſtores a due
              flexibility and motion of <lb/>the parts. </p>
          </div>
          <div n="6" type="corollary">
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>VI. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Hemlock</hi> ſometimes diſſolves <w part="I"
                >cata-</w><lb/><w part="F">racts</w>, or obſtructs their growth. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>And, by that means, preſerves ſight; <lb/>ſharpens it; or reſtores
              it when loſt. </p>
          </div>
          <div n="7" type="corollary">
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>VII. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>It corrects the acrimony of the blood, <lb/>and removes diſeaſes
              proceeding from it. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>It cures ſharp defluxions; ſaltiſh <w part="I">hu-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">mors</w>; itching; tetters and ringworms; <lb/>the worſt ſcald head; and an
              inveterate <lb/>ſcab or itch that reſiſts every thing elſe. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>It cures the moſt malign ulcers, fiſtula's, <lb/>and ſinuſes. </p>
          </div>
          <div n="8" type="corollary">
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>VIII. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>It removes a <hi rend="italic">caries,</hi> and takes off a
              <lb/>rottenneſs <hi rend="italic">(corruptionem)</hi> of the bones; <lb/>and promotes
              a ſeparation of the ſcales. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Hence it is a remedy in a <hi rend="italic">ſpina ventoſa.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_30" n="27"/>
          </div>
          <div n="9" type="corollary">
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>IX. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>It cures a <hi rend="italic">cancer,</hi> or mends its <w part="I"
                >viru-</w><lb/><w part="F">lence</w>; brings on a laudable ſuppuration, <lb/>and
              eaſes the pains. </p>
          </div>
          <div n="10" type="corollary">
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>X. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is a remedy in a malign <hi rend="italic">fluor albus;</hi>
              <lb/>and in an inveterate and obſtinate <hi rend="italic">go-<lb/>norrhœa.</hi>
            </p>
          </div>
          <div n="11" type="corollary">
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>XI. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>It ſtops vomiting, and the moſt <w part="I">obſti-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">nate</w> heart-burns. </p>
          </div>
          <div n="12" type="corollary">
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>XII. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>It carries off the relicts of a venereal <lb/>diſtemper, that
              yield to no other remedy. </p>
          </div>
          <div n="13" type="corollary">
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>XIII. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Hemlock</hi> cures the diſeaſes, that <w part="I"
                >en-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſue</w> after a malignant ſmall-pox. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>To confirm this, Dr. <hi rend="italic">Lebmacker,</hi> an
              <lb/>eminent phyſician of this city, wrote me <lb/>the two following hiſtories. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The firſt is the hiſtory of his own ſon, <lb/>which was thus: </p>
            <q>
              <p rend="indent">'My ſon, an infant five <lb/>months old, otherwiſe in perfect health,
                <lb/>was ſeized with the ſmall-pox on the <pb xml:id="page_31" n="28"/><lb/>26th of
                February, 1760; which, <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">though</w> diſtinct, was
                not of ſo good a <lb/>kind. </p>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>On the ninth day of the diſeaſe a <w part="I">ſud-</w><lb/><w
                  part="F">den</w> diarrhoea came on, whence all the <lb/>puſtules on the left-ſide
                from head to <lb/>foot ſunk in, while thoſe on the right-<lb/>ſide remained full. </p>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>On this the left-arm, knee, and foot <lb/>ſwelled to an enormous
                ſize, with great <lb/>pain and inability; which the poor <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w
                  part="F">fant</w> made us ſenſible of by its ſhrieks, <lb/>if it was touched. </p>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>No aperture could be made in theſe <lb/>tumors, either by nature
                or art; but they <lb/>were cured in four months time by the <lb/>skill of an expert
                chirurgeon, Mr. <hi rend="italic">Le-<lb/>ber,</hi> without any impediment in the <w
                  part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of the parts. </p>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>But as the croſs child could not be <lb/>prevailed upon to take
                any medicine, <lb/>either in the time of the ſmall-pox, or <lb/>thereafter; and his
                mother's milk, with <lb/>a milk diet, were not ſufficient to <w part="I"
                  >aſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſuage</w> the virulence of the variolous <lb/>matter, his
                whole body was in time <lb/>covered with innumerable ugly ichorous <pb
                  xml:id="page_32" n="29"/><lb/>ulcers, from the crown of the head to <lb/>the ſoles
                of the feet; ſo that he had <w part="I">no-</w><lb/><w part="F">thing</w> but a
                ſwelled belly, and ulcerated <lb/>skin, to cover the bones. </p>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>The child being thus left in this <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w
                  part="F">plorable</w> condition, till it was one and <lb/>twenty months old, that
                is, till June <lb/>1761, all hopes of its recovery were <lb/>over, as it grew worſe
                and worſe every <lb/>day. I was willing, however, to try, <lb/>what the extract of
                  <hi rend="italic">hemlock,</hi> given as <lb/>we could, might do in ſuch a caſe. </p>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>From the beginning of June, then, I <lb/>gave him daily two
                grains, one in the <lb/>morning, in a weak decoction of coffee <lb/>and toaſted
                barley, with milk; and <w part="I">ano-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> in the evening,
                in chocolate, that <lb/>he might not diſcern it. </p>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>I ſo increaſed the doſe by degrees, <lb/>that he took daily ſix
                grains, without <lb/>any regard to his diet. </p>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>By theſe means the ulcers began to <lb/>afford a good <hi
                  rend="italic">pus,</hi> to be cleanſed, to <lb/>heal up, and to diſappear over the
                whole <lb/>body; only a ſcab or two remaining <lb/>among the hair of his head. </p>
              <pb xml:id="page_33" n="30"/>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>By the middle of July he had got ſo <lb/>much ſtrength, that he
                could run up <lb/>and down very briskly, both within <lb/>doors and without, with
                his head <w part="I">up-</w><lb/><w part="F">right</w>, and his eyes clear and open;
                  <w part="I">nei-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> fearing the rays of the ſun, nor a
                <lb/>candle, which he could not bear for <lb/>two months before, on account of his
                <lb/>inflamed eyes, which made him hang <lb/>his head, and put his hands to his
                eyes, <lb/>whenever any light came before them. </p>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>Thus by degrees the child, that was <lb/>before intolerably
                croſs, now runs about <lb/>all day with chearfulneſs at his play.' </p>
            </q>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>He took ſix drachms of the extract of <lb/><hi rend="italic"
                >hemlock,</hi> but no other medicine. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now, my good readers! if we had only <lb/>this ſingle caſe to
              vouch it, would not <lb/><hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> deſerve the greateſt praiſe? </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Hemlock</hi> was given to an infant <lb/>quite
              extenuated, covered with ulcers, <lb/>and in the worſt cachectic habit of body,
              <lb/>of which he was cured. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Hemlock</hi> then is an innocent <w part="I"
                >reme-</w><lb/><w part="F">dy</w>, and it is an efficacious one. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>There are, indeed, ſome terrible <w part="I">cal-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">culators</w> in medicine, who will, perhaps, <pb xml:id="page_34" n="31"
              /><lb/>attribute this cure, to the decoction of <lb/>toaſted barley, infuſion of
              coffee, <w part="I">choco-</w><lb/><w part="F">late</w>, or to the force of nature. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>But they muſt know, that this child <lb/>took thoſe drinks before
              he uſed the <hi rend="italic">hem-<lb/>lock,</hi> but grew worſe upon it: ſo that we
              <lb/>can neither attribute his recovery to the <lb/>force of nature, nor to this
              drink. But <lb/>as ſoon as the extract of <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> was
              <lb/>given, the infant began to grow better. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Whence, O <hi rend="italic">hemlock!</hi> the praiſe is due
              <lb/>to thee. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The ſecond hiſtory is the following <lb/>one, communicated to me
              by the ſame <lb/>learned gentleman. </p>
            <q>margQuotes<p rend="indent"><lb/>'About the end of June, 1761, I met <lb/>by chance a
                certain noble lady of three <lb/>and twenty, who had been afflicted with <lb/>the
                confluent ſmall-pox eighteen years <lb/>before, the ſad remains of which ſhe
                <lb/>ſtill bewails; for beſides the loſs of her <lb/>right eye, ſhe had an ulcer,
                with a hard <lb/>ſwelling, on her right cheek. </p>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>Various remedies, as ſhe ſaid, both <lb/>internal and external,
                had been tried to <lb/>heal this ſore; but they were all, even <lb/>to a ſalivation
                itſelf, given in vain. </p>
              <pb xml:id="page_35" n="32"/>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>Remembring the ſucceſs of the <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w
                  part="F">tract</w> of <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> in a like diſeaſe, I <w
                  part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">viſed</w> the ſame to her. </p>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>Altho' ſhe was now tired of <w part="I">medi-</w><lb/><w
                  part="F">cines</w>, yet ſhe conſented to it. </p>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>She began then, on the firſt of July, <lb/>to take every day
                eight grains of the <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">tract</w> of <hi
                  rend="italic">hemlock.</hi>
              </p>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>Taking off the plaſter, of what kind <lb/>I know not, I took
                care to have the <w part="I">ul-</w><lb/><w part="F">cer</w> fomented with a
                linen-cloth, dipt <lb/>in a decoction of <hi rend="italic">hemlock.</hi>
              </p>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>In eight days the tumors appeared to <lb/>be both leſs, and
                ſofter; and there <lb/>ſeemed to be ſome ſlight tokens of a <w part="I"
                  >ci-</w><lb/><w part="F">catrix</w> forming on the lips of the ulcer. </p>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the mean time, proud fleſh <lb/>ſprung up here and there in
                the <w part="I">mid-</w><lb/><w part="F">dle</w> of the ulcer; which was taken off
                <lb/>by ſprinkling the powder of <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi>
                <lb/>upon it. </p>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>The cruſt occaſioned by this, I took <lb/>off with honey of
                roſes, mixed with the <lb/>ſame powder: which were repeated, <lb/>as often as the
                proud fleſh ſprang up <lb/>again. </p>
              <pb xml:id="page_36" n="33"/>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the mean time I increaſed the <lb/>pills, ſo that for three
                weeks paſt ſhe <lb/>has taken every day thirty two grains. </p>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>This doſe I have hitherto continued, <lb/>intermitting now and
                then a day or <lb/>two. </p>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>About this time, the tumors, and <lb/>hardneſs, almoſt entirely
                went off; the <lb/>ulcer began to be cleanſed, to be dried <lb/>up, and to be
                covered with a thin skin; <lb/>and thus it has remained cloſed now for <lb/>ſix
                weeks. </p>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>She will go on with the ſame doſe of <lb/><hi rend="italic"
                  >hemlock,</hi> till the cicatrix is ſound. </p>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>She has now taken, from the <w part="I">begin-</w><lb/><w
                  part="F">ning</w> of June to the end of September, <lb/>four ounces of the extract
                of <hi rend="italic">hemlock.</hi>
              </p>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>She received no benefit from any <lb/>other medicine for
                eighteen years. </p>
              <p rend="indent"><lb/>But now, by the uſe of <hi rend="italic">hemlock,</hi> ſhe
                <lb/>finds her appetite to be increaſed; ſhe <lb/>grows plump; is free from
                rheumatic <lb/>pains, which ſhe was before troubled <lb/>with; and has no other
                complaint.' </p></q>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Is there any man in his ſenſes who <lb/>doubts of the efficacy of
                <hi rend="italic">hemlock?</hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Since <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> operates on the virulent <pb
                xml:id="page_37" n="34"/><lb/>remains of the <hi rend="italic">Small-Pox,</hi> a
              queſtion <w part="I">a-</w><lb/><w part="F">riſes</w> upon it; whether it may not be
                <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">lowable</w> to give it, in a malignant <w
                part="I">vario-</w><lb/><w part="F">lous</w> diſtemper itſelf, in a ſpare doſe, by
              <lb/>a prudent hand, with judicious and <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >vident</w> care? it is agreeable to nature, and <lb/>appears from an infinite
              courſe of <w part="I">experi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ence</w>, that vegetables of
              whatever kind <lb/>may be digeſted in our ſtomachs, and <lb/>converted into the
              inquiline juices of the <lb/>body; but minerals cannot. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Vegetables</hi>, <hi rend="italic">then, are more
                eaſily <lb/>borne by our nature, and are by far more <lb/>ſafe and agreeable to
                it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Therefore if it was allowable to others <lb/>to uſe <hi
                rend="italic">mercury,</hi> and antimony, in a <w part="I">viru-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >lent</w> ſtate of the <hi rend="italic">Small-Pox,</hi> why may <lb/>not we be
              allowed, without any remorſe, <lb/>to try <hi rend="italic">hemlock,</hi> ſince the
              beſt remedies yet <lb/>known do nothing; theſe two caſes of <lb/>the learned <hi
                rend="italic">Lebmacher</hi> were very <w part="I">neceſſa-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >ry</w> here, to make this propoſition appear <lb/>worthy of approbation. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>I have likewiſe, from other phyſicians <lb/>both of this and
              foreign countries, ſome <lb/>excellent caſes relating to <hi rend="italic"
                >hemlock,</hi> in <lb/>which it proved ſucceſſful: and I have <pb xml:id="page_38"
                n="35"/>others, in which it did not ſucceed ſo well; <lb/>but I have thought proper
              to reſerve all <lb/>theſe for another time. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>ADMONITIONS. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HESE Corollaries are deduced from, <lb/>and
            confirmed by, repeated <w part="I">experi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ence</w>. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>But I beſeech all, and every phyſicians, <lb/>not to perſuade
            themſelves, that I am of <lb/>ſuch an opinion as to believe, that theſe <lb/>rules are
            general, and that <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> ought <lb/>always to cure. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>I ſay and openly own, that I have <w part="I">like-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">wiſe</w> had patients of all kinds, to whom <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >hemlock</hi> was of no ſervice; altho' it was <lb/>indicated from a ſimilitude of the
            diſeaſe. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>But I do not believe, there are any, <lb/>who will doubt of the
            truth of the caſes I <lb/>have related. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>But if any one makes a ſcruple about <lb/>the truth of the matter,
            and ſuſpects my <lb/>probity, let him go to the <hi rend="italic">illuſtrious Van
              <lb/>Swieten;</hi> who has the names of the <w part="I">pati-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ents</w>, and an account of their place of <lb/>abode. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_39" n="36"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Happy me! who have an opportunity <lb/>to practice phyſic under the
            auſpices of ſo <lb/><hi rend="italic">great a man.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>I have ſeen patients labouring under the <lb/>worſt <hi
              rend="italic">cancer</hi> of the breaſt, whom <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi>
            <lb/>ſoon relieved: but there were ſeveral <lb/>others, to whom <hi rend="italic"
              >hemlock</hi> only afforded <lb/>ſome relief, but did not cure them: others <lb/>found
            no alteration from the uſe of <hi rend="italic">hem-<lb/>lock:</hi> one or two could not
            bear <hi rend="italic">hemlock.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>I would have the ſame to be underſtood <lb/>of other diſeaſes, for
            which I have <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">mended</w>
            <hi rend="italic">hemlock.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>For I only contend, that <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> is
            <lb/>ſometimes of ſervice, and does wonders, <lb/>where other the moſt famous and <w
              part="I">extol-</w><lb/><w part="F">led</w> medicines do nothing. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>If other phyſicians ſtill find other <w part="I">reme-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">dies</w>, we may be able, in time, to cure the <lb/>moſt difficult diſeaſes. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Truly! I congratulate myſelf, when I <lb/>hear, there are ſeveral
            phyſicians, who <lb/>follow my example about divers <w part="I">vegeta-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">bles</w>. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>How many thouſands of plants are <lb/>there, whoſe virtues we are
            ignorant of? <lb/>But to diſcover theſe, there are required <pb xml:id="page_40" n="37"
            /><lb/>induſtry, labor, provident care, and a <lb/>mind free from all ſects. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Neither ſhould you ſwear by the <w part="I">dic-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >tates</w> of a maſter. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Moreover, it is always to be <w part="I">remem-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >bered</w>, that there are limites both to art <lb/>and medicines. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now when <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> is ſometimes of
            <lb/>ſervice, but at other times does nothing <lb/>in the ſame diſeaſe; it is certain
            there <lb/>muſt be ſome latent difference, the <w part="I">diag-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >noſtic</w> ſigns of which are yet unknown to <lb/>us; nor am I alone ſufficient to
            determine <lb/>thoſe things; and for that reaſon I have <lb/>not hitherto been able, to
            give any <w part="I">cer-</w><lb/><w part="F">tain</w> rules. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>But they who might and ought to <lb/>have aſſiſted me, deſired to be
            excuſed. <lb/>Yea they have even, by ſharp cenſures, <lb/>and repeated harangues to the
            ſons of <lb/>art, condemned and proſcribed my works, <lb/>and would have them deſtroyed
            by fire <lb/>and ſword. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Ah me! miſerable fate of man. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>In my two treatiſes on <hi rend="italic">hemlock,</hi> I have
            <lb/>related both the caſes that were <w part="I">ſucceſſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ful</w>,
            and thoſe that proved unſucceſſful: <pb xml:id="page_41" n="38"/><lb/>and moreover I
            always admoniſhed, that <lb/><hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> would not prove of equal
            ſervice <lb/>to all: I ſaid farther, in my ſecond book, <lb/>it was enough to me, if I
            ſhall preſerve <lb/>and cure one patient in a hundred by the <lb/>uſe of <hi
              rend="italic">hemlock,</hi> who could not be reſtored <lb/>by other medicines. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>If every one of the other ninety-nine <lb/>phyſicians will do as
            much as I have done, <lb/>then all the hundred patients will be <lb/>cured. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Could any man write with more <w part="I">ſin-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >cerity</w> and honeſty? It is allowable to <lb/>propoſe our experiments faithfully
            and <lb/>cautiouſly to the world: but after that <lb/>every phyſician is at liberty, to
            uſe ſuch <lb/>a remedy, or to let it alone. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>I neither deſire honor, glory, immortal <lb/>fame, nor profit: I
            would only deſire to <lb/>be uſeful to mankind, afflicted with ſo <lb/>many miſerable
            diſtempers; and would <lb/>be willing to relieve ſuch calamities. This <lb/>is the duty
            of every phyſician; I beg, <lb/>then, that others would give me no <w part="I"
              >diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">turbance</w>. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>I have given to the ſick ſome hundred <lb/>pounds of the extract of
              <hi rend="italic">hemlock,</hi> and can <pb xml:id="page_42" n="39"/><lb/>affirm, with
            a ſafe conſcience, that I <w part="I">ne-</w><lb/><w part="F">ver</w> hurt any one. For
            when I ſaw things <lb/>to be in a right way, I went on boldly, <lb/>continued, and
            increaſed the doſe: but <lb/>as ſoon as I obſerved (which very rarely <lb/>happens) that
            the ſick did not do well <lb/>from it, I forbore, and laid aſide <hi rend="italic"
              >hemlock.</hi>
            <lb/>This is the rule of art. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Since then this medicine prudently <lb/>given cannot hurt, our art
            requires, that <lb/>it ſhould be farther recommended to all; <lb/>in order to make
            numbers of trials, which <lb/>may be collated together, and compared <lb/>according to
            their ſigns, ſymptoms, and <lb/>events. Then let the reaſons and cauſes <lb/>be inquired
            into, why <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> is <w part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >times</w> of ſervice, and makes a radical <lb/>cure; and why it ſometimes does
            nothing <lb/>in the ſame diſeaſe. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Upon ſeeing the difference, and <w part="I">find-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ing</w> out the cauſe, it will appear, how <lb/>far the efficacy of <hi
              rend="italic">hemlock</hi> may extend. <lb/>And then a reaſon may be given, why
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> does not act equally upon all. It <lb/>may then
            likewiſe be determined, with <lb/>what caſes it evidently agrees; and in <lb/>what it
            performs nothing. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_43" n="40"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe obſervations being rightly <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >geſted</w>, we may be able to apply ſome <lb/>other remedy, in caſes where <hi
              rend="italic">hemlock</hi> is <lb/>inactive. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>By ſuch means the bounds of our art <lb/>will be extended, to the
            great benefit of <lb/>the community. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>In ſome caſes, where <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> had not <lb/>the
            effects I expected from it, I have <lb/>tried other remedies; and not without
            <lb/>ſucceſs. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>If that was not ſufficient, I have <w part="I">ano-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ther</w> ready. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Thus I ſhall aſcend by degrees; and I <lb/>hope in God, that he will
            proſper my <lb/>endeavours, which are only intended for <lb/>the welfare of my
            neighbours. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>I here faithfully promiſe my <w part="I">adver-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ſaries</w>, I ſhall employ the more pains upon <lb/>thoſe things, the more they
            endeavour to <lb/>interrupt and hinder me. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>While I do what is right, I fear no <lb/>body. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Although <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> is a moſt innocent
            <lb/>remedy, yet I could wiſh, that every <lb/>phyſician would always begin with a
            <lb/>ſmall doſe, and gradually increaſe it. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_44" n="41"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>For we know, how ſtrange and diverſe <lb/>the peculiar temperaments
            of men are; <lb/>whence there may be ſome, who may <lb/>not bear this remedy. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>By a ſmall doſe then, no one will <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">mit</w> a fault: becauſe a good phyſician <lb/>will diſcontinue a medicine,
            where he <lb/>obſerves any ſiniſter event. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>But it is always to be well obſerved, <lb/>whether that event may be
            owing to the <lb/>medicine; or to the ſymptoms that <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >company</w> the diſeaſe; or to an error in <lb/>the non-naturals. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>There are ſome, who are tormented, <lb/>vomit, are ſeized with a
            fever, and faint <lb/>away, only from taking crabs eyes, which <lb/>are certainly a moſt
            innocent medicine: <lb/>and why ſhould there not be others, who, <lb/>from ſome latent
            cauſe, may be ill <w part="I">affect-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> with <hi rend="italic"
              >hemlock?</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>But is <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> therefore no medicine?
            <lb/>Ought <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> to be condemned on that <lb/>account? No
            prudent phyſician will think ſo. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>If the uſe of <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> proves prejudicial
            <lb/>to any, it is not to be attributed to the <lb/>medicine, but to the fault of the <w
              part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſcriber</w>; <pb xml:id="page_45" n="42"/><lb/>if we
            take the thing in a ſtrict, <lb/>and true medical ſenſe. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Symptoms of a different nature from <lb/>the diſeaſe are often
            complicated with it: <lb/>and then it is requiſite, that other <w part="I"
              >reme-</w><lb/><w part="F">dies</w> ſhould be applied, beſides <hi rend="italic"
              >hemlock.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>If ſpaſms or convulſions prove <w part="I">trouble-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ſome</w>, antihyſteric nervine remedies are <lb/>wanted. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>If pains are violent, paregorics and <lb/>opiates become neceſſary.
            A high fever, <lb/>and full pulſe, require cooling nitrous <lb/>remedies. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>In a putrid ſtate of the juices, or if an <lb/>intermittent fever
            comes upon the uſe of <lb/><hi rend="italic">hemlock,</hi> the bark is added to it. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Sometimes purging is needful, <w part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >times</w> bleeding. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Too great a flow of ſharp humours on <lb/>a part requires an iſſue,
            or ſeton. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Neither ought a fomentation or <w part="I">cata-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >plaſm</w> of <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> always to be applied <lb/>outwardly; but
            they are to be changed, <lb/>according to the judgment and experience <lb/>of a good
            phyſician, or chirurgeon. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>If ulcers are dreſt with lint, great care <lb/>ſhould be uſed in
            taking it off; leſt the <pb xml:id="page_46" n="43"/><lb/>threads adhering to the naked
            veſſels <lb/>ſhould be torn off with force, which <lb/>might hurt every thing: a
            hæmorrhage <lb/>might enſue, from which proud fleſh, <lb/>ſprings up. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>They ſhould all be firſt moiſtened <lb/>with the weakeſt infuſion of
              <hi rend="italic">hemlock,</hi> or <lb/>other proper liquid. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The more urging ſymptoms often <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >mand</w>, that the uſe of <hi rend="italic">hemlock,</hi> both <w part="I"
              >ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">ternal</w> and internal, ſhould be left off for <lb/>ſome
            time; till theſe are either cured, <lb/>or at leaſt mitigated. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>We ſhould endeavour to palliate <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >orders</w> in thoſe perſons, who do not bear <lb/><hi rend="italic">hemlock;</hi> ſo
            long as we are unacquainted <lb/>with any other remedy. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The bones, tumors, <hi rend="italic">ſcirrhuſes,</hi> are often
            <lb/>attended with great pain in their <w part="I">inner-</w><lb/><w part="F">moſt</w>
            receſſes: I have often obſerved in <lb/>ſuch caſes, there was an eroſion, or <w part="I"
              >corrup-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, in that place: but a corrupted part <lb/>ſhould
            be ſeparated from the ſound, which <lb/>cannot be done without an external <w part="I"
              >aper-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w>, made by a cauſtic application, or
            <lb/>chirurgical inſtrument; but by the uſe <pb xml:id="page_47" n="44"/><lb/>of <hi
              rend="italic">hemlock</hi> it is often made <w part="I">ſpontane-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ouſly</w>. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Then corrupted matter iſſues forth, <lb/>and there is a ſinuous
            ulcer. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The leſs intelligent imagine, that this <lb/>corruption proceeds
            from the uſe of <hi rend="italic">hem-<lb/>lock:</hi> although upon the continued uſe
            <lb/>of it in the ſame caſe, whether internal <lb/>or external, perfect health often
            enſues. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>I have ſometimes ſeen certain <hi rend="italic">ſcirrhuſes</hi>
            <lb/>in the glands diſſolved by the uſe of <hi rend="italic">hem-<lb/>lock,</hi> but new
            ones appeared in other parts. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>That ſeemed ſtrange: but the ſick <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ways</w> found themſelves well in other <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ſpects</w>; ſo that I continued the ſame <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >medy</w>, and cured the patients. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Such things never frighten the ſkilful: <lb/>and therefore we ought
            not immediately <lb/>to change the medicine. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>In diet, farinaceous unfermented <w part="I">ſub-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ſtances</w> are to be avoided; and likewiſe <lb/>too acrid ſpices. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Acids are allowed for a condiment; but <lb/>when they are too
            predominant, they are <lb/>not ſo proper. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_48" n="45"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Good wine does not hurt thoſe, who <lb/>are uſed to it. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Friction, or great motion, in the part <lb/>affected, generally
            increaſe the diſeaſe. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is very conducive to a cure, for the <lb/>ſick to live in a free
            and open air, and to <lb/>preſerve a chearful and right diſpoſition <lb/>of mind. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Sadneſs, melancholy, diſturbances of <lb/>the mind, retard and
            hinder the cure; <lb/>occaſion new diſorders; and often turn <lb/>a <hi rend="italic"
              >ſcirrhus</hi> to a <hi rend="italic">cancer.</hi>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The time in which <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> may cure, <lb/>and
            reſolve tumors, cannot be <w part="I">determin-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>For ſometimes that is ſoon done, <w part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">times</w> very ſlowly. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nor is the nature of ulcers, tumors, <lb/>or cancers, always the
            ſame. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>I gave a woman <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> in a large doſe
            <lb/>for tumors of the neck, more than two <lb/>years, without any alteration in the <w
              part="I">tu-</w><lb/><w part="F">mors</w>: but as her menſes flowed more
            <lb/>plentifully, her ſtrength was greater, mind <lb/>more chearful, and the whole habit
            of <pb xml:id="page_49" n="46"/><lb/>body much better, ſhe deſired herſelf, <lb/>that I
            would not deny her thoſe pills. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>At length, after two years and a half, <lb/>the tumors were
            diſſolved, and everything <lb/>reduced to a natural ſtate. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nor did the long uſe of it do any <lb/>harm. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>I have another woman, who took only <lb/>two grains of <hi
              rend="italic">hemlock</hi> in the morning, <lb/>for a cancer of the breaſt; and
            although <lb/>ſhe was a woman of ſeventy, there enſued <lb/>ſo good and ſudden a change,
            and <w part="I">dimi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nution</w> of the tumor, that both the <w
              part="I">by-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtanders</w> and myſelf were aſtoniſhed. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>This woman made urine moſt <w part="I">plenti-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >fully</w>, with much glutinous ſediment. But <lb/>when ſhe abſtained one day from <hi
              rend="italic">hemlock,</hi>
            <lb/>the urine was in a ſmall quantity, and <lb/>without the ſediment. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>In diſeaſes about the kidnies, bladder, <lb/>and urinary paſſages,
              <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> ſometimes <lb/>has moſt excellent effects. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>It ſometimes cures a retention of urine, <lb/>and ſtrangury; and
            often eaſes pains <lb/>in making urine, ſooner than <hi rend="italic">opium.</hi>
          </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_50" n="47"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Nor is the extract of <hi rend="italic">hemlock</hi> to be <w
              part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſpiſed</w>, in diſorders ariſing from a ſtone. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>From what hath been ſaid, it appears, <lb/>that <hi rend="italic"
              >hemlock</hi> is highly worthy of being <lb/>tried. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the mean time I do not affirm, it <lb/>has any ſpecific virtue;
            but I expect the <lb/>mutual aid of good phyſicians, to eſtabliſh <lb/>rules about it. </p>
          <trailer rend="italic align-center"><lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_51"/>
        <figure>
          <head><lb/>Colchicum Autumnale Eng. Meadow-Saffron.</head>
          <figDesc>depiction of a meadow Saffron (apparently confused with hemlock)</figDesc>

        </figure>
        <p>Auguſtin: Cipps Medic: Stud: delin. Viennae 1763.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
