<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Morley: An essay on the nature and cure of the king's evil</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>John Morley</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">AN ESSAY ON THE NATURE and CURE OF THE KING's EVIL; DEDUCED FROM
              OBSERVATIONS and PRACTICE. The SECOND EDITION: With an ADDITION of REMARKABLE CASES of
              poor Sufferers, cured by the Author. Seriously recommended to the Perusal of all
              unhappy Persons and Families labouring under any Scrophulous Complaints, which have
              hitherto eluded all Attempts to remove them. Facts are stubborn Things.</title>
            <edition n="2"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">N1487</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N1487"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for James Buckland, at the Buck, in Pater-Noster-Row; and
                  sold by T. Toft, in Chelmsford, M.DCC.LXIII.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1763</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="12"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="63"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">Huntington Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3309392492</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K000923.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: disease"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_1"/>
        <p rend="align-center">
          <lb/><hi rend="size(3)">ESSAY</hi>
          <lb/>ON THE <lb/><hi rend="size(1.75)">NATURE and CURE</hi>
          <lb/>OF THE <lb/><hi rend="size(2)">KING's EVIL; </hi>
          <lb/>DEDUCED FROM <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">OBSERVATIONS and PRACTICE. </hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="align-center ">
          <lb/>[Price One Shilling.] </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_3"/>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/><hi rend="size(2)">INTRODUCTION</hi>
          <lb/>TO THIS <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">SECOND EDITION. </hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">I</hi>T is not from any Vanity of appearing <lb/>in Print,
          eſpecially a ſecond time, af- <lb/>ter ſuch ungenerous Uſage as I have <lb/>met with from
          Perſons calling them- <lb/>ſelves Reviewers, but to make myſelf <lb/>uſeful in my
          Generation to unhappy Suf- <lb/>ferers, as far as I am able. I refuſe not <lb/>the pooreſt
          Perſon my Aſſiſtance (as well <lb/>as the Rich) if they come to my Houſe. <lb/>The
          Pleaſure I feel by relieving the Af- <lb/>flicted, overbalances all the Cavillings, <pb
            xml:id="page_4"/>
          <lb/>Sneers, and ill-natured Reflections of <lb/>Reviewers, or any other Writers for
          <lb/>Bread, who ſpeak Evil of the Things <lb/>that they underſtand not. Let them an-
          <lb/>ſwer me by ſolid Arguments, confirmed <lb/>by as many real Cures as I have done;
          <lb/>then I ſhall rejoice to hear ſo many more <lb/>miſerable Objects have been relieved
          <lb/>from their Diſorders by my ſtirring up <lb/>the Attention or Ambition of others to
          <lb/>Practice with more Succeſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As the King's Evil is a Diſeaſe few of <lb/>the better Sort care to own, I muſt beg
          <lb/>to be excuſed from naming ſuch Per- <lb/>ſons, but only ſome few of their Caſes.
          <lb/>As to the lower Sort, I ſhall give their <lb/>Caſes in the plaineſt Manner I can,
          that <lb/>the People of common Underſtanding, <pb xml:id="page_5"/>
          <lb/>without any Phyſical Knowledge, may <lb/>in a great Meaſure judge whether their
          <lb/>Complaints are Scrophulous or not. I <lb/>have alſo inſerted the Names, and
          <lb/>Places of Abode, of ſuch Perſons, that <lb/>by diſcourſing with the Parties them-
          <lb/>ſelves, their Friends or Neighbours, <lb/>they may be ſatisfied of the Truth of
          <lb/>the Matters of Fact, and receive far- <lb/>ther Information as to their own Com-
          <lb/>plaints. And as I make no Profit by <lb/>my Practice, it is evident, I need no
          <lb/>Arts to influence People to declare Un- <lb/>truths in my Favour. Greater Num-
          <lb/>bers of Cures I might have added, but <lb/>hope theſe will be ſufficient, to ſatiſ-
          <lb/>fy any unprejudiced Perſon, that the <lb/>King's Evil, or other Scrophulous Diſ-
          <lb/>orders, may be relieved much oftener, <pb xml:id="page_6"/>
          <lb/>and with more Eaſe and Safety, as well <lb/>as with leſs Charge to the Patients,
          <lb/>than the Generality of Practitioners are <lb/>willing to allow, or the unhappy Suffe-
          <lb/>rers have hitherto experienced. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_7"/>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>THE <lb/><hi rend="size(3)">PREFACE. </hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="space italic">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>LADY of my Family <lb/> having many Years made <lb/>it her
          Pleaſure, to endea- <lb/>vour the Relief of all ſuch poor <lb/>Perſons as were afflicted
          with ſcro- <lb/>phulous Diſorders, or the King's <lb/>Evil, and were recommended to
          <lb/>her by Surgeons, or other Practi- <lb/>tioners; and having been very ſuc-
          <lb/>ceſſful in curing many ſuch Caſes, <lb/>as they had given up and recom- <lb/>mended
          to her, made me very in- <lb/>quiſite with her after her Method <lb/>of Practice. She very
          readily in- <lb/>formed me of the Nature and Way <lb/>of applying her Remedies, but
          <lb/>would never (during her Life) im- <lb/>part to me the Names of the Things <lb/>ſhe
          made uſe of, or the Method of <lb/>Preparation, but always told me <pb xml:id="page_8"
            n="iv"/>
          <lb/>I ſhould find a full Account amongſt <lb/>her Papers after her Death, which <lb/>I
          did (being her ſole Executor.) <lb/>With other Things, I found the <lb/>following Letter
          to her, from an <lb/>eminent Surgeon. </p>
        <lb/>
        <div>
          <salute rend="sc">Madam, </salute>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">once</hi> more ſollicit your hea- <lb/>venly Benediction, and the
            ſalu- <lb/>tary Effects of your renowned <lb/>Secret, which the World is from <lb/>God
            and yourſelf, greatly obliged <lb/>for, in Behalf of this poor un- <lb/>happy Lad (<hi
              rend="italic">B. P.</hi> by Name) who <lb/>is attended with the King's Evil <lb/>in
            his Foot, and has been ſo for <lb/>eleven Months; who I entirely <lb/>ſubmit to your
            Care (Providence <lb/>being your peculiar Guide) in the <lb/>mean while, I remain in
            Confor- <lb/>mity to Facts, </p>
          <signed rend="indent">
            <lb/>Your ſincere Convert, <lb/>And a Public Well-wiſher, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
          </signed>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_9" n="v"/>
        <div>
          <p rend="indent italic">
            <lb/>THIS Letter, among many o <lb/>thers, from Surgeons and Apothe- <lb/>caries,
            together with the great Cures <lb/>which ſhe daily did, made me very <lb/>ſeriouſly
            reflect, how uſeful a Per- <lb/>ſon ſhe had been to all the human <lb/>Species, which
            had applied to her <lb/>in Time, being chiefly of the loweſt <lb/>Claſs of Mankind,
            whoſe Health <lb/>and Limbs were their only Liveli- <lb/>hood: Theſe were often relieved
            <lb/>with her Purſe, and always with <lb/>her Medicines, and Advice Gratis; <lb/>as alſo
            all others, who applied to <lb/>her for Relief in this deplorable <lb/>Malady. Theſe
            Conſiderations, and <lb/>the great Number of unhappy Poor, <lb/>(unable to pay a Surgeon
            or Apo- <lb/>thecary) daily preſenting themſelves <lb/>to me; and I knowing the Safety
            of <lb/>the Method, and Medicines uſed in <lb/>this Diſorder, was imboldened to
            <lb/>endeavour the Relief of my Fellow- <lb/>Creatures, by following the Lady's <pb
              xml:id="page_10" n="vi"/>
            <lb/>Rules of doing good, for Charity <lb/>Sake; which I have followed ſome <lb/>Years,
            with ſuch Succeſs (for which <lb/>I thank God) as ſurprizes even my <lb/>own ſelf. Such
            Objects of Com- <lb/>paſſion having been relieved, as paſs <lb/>all Belief of any, but
            ſuch as have <lb/>been Eye-witneſſes of the Facts, from <lb/>firſt to laſt. Since I have
            been in <lb/>Poſſeſſion of the deceaſed Lady's <lb/>Notes and Memorandums, I have
            <lb/>read over many Authors who have <lb/>treated of this Diſorder. <hi rend="roman">Dr.
              Gibbs</hi>
            <lb/>on this Subject, writes, "That if we <lb/>take a View of what the moſt emi-
            <lb/>nent Authors have ſaid of this Diſ- <lb/>eaſe, we ſhall find their Notions of
            <lb/>it to be of little Uſe, and very few <lb/>Accounts of their Succeſs in curing
            <lb/>Diſorders of this Nature." And tru- <lb/>ly I am much of the ſame Opinion. <lb/>But
            this great Good have I learnt <lb/>by reading their Works, and from <lb/>thence
            obſerving the Operations of <pb xml:id="page_11" n="vii"/>
            <lb/>my own Preſcriptions, that I have <lb/>much improved both the Method and
            <lb/>Medicines I at firſt uſed. I pre- <lb/>ſcribe no painful Applications, cut-
            <lb/>ting or cauterizing, bliſtering, or <lb/>nauſeous Loads of Phyſick, but ſuch
            <lb/>Things only, as Children of half a <lb/>Year old, to the Aged of Seventy, <lb/>may
            have without the leaſt Hurt or <lb/>Pain, and with great Safety be ad- <lb/>miniſtred to
            them. And I can juſtly <lb/>challenge any Perſon that has been <lb/>under my Care, and
            followed my <lb/>very eaſy Directions only, to allege <lb/>the contrary. So that I can,
            with <lb/>great Truth aſſert, That I have <lb/>done ſome Good, and no Harm. <lb/>The
            Cure of this Diſtemper by the <lb/>Lady's Method, is no new Thing, <lb/>but has been in
            ſome Meaſure uſed <lb/>one hundred and fifty Years ago, <lb/>as I have met with in an
            old Au- <lb/>thor; and having ſeen ſuch won- <lb/>derful Effects from it, admire what
              <pb xml:id="page_12" n="viii"/>
            <lb/>can be the Reaſon of its being for- <lb/>got, ſhall I ſay, or not uſed by the
            <lb/>Gentlemen of the Faculty: But it <lb/>is not according to their Method of
            <lb/>Practice. That I am no Phyſi- <lb/>cian, Surgeon, or Apothecary, the <lb/>Reader
            will eaſily ſee, by my not <lb/>uſing hard Words, or technical <lb/>Terms of Art, to
            puzzle and con- <lb/>found him; and my Patients all <lb/>know I am none of the Faculty,
            by <lb/>refuſing Fees. All that come to <lb/>me, are welcome to my Advice and
            <lb/>Aſſiſtance Gratis. What Neceſ- <lb/>ſaries are wanted, they may buy of <lb/>whom,
            and where they pleaſe. The <lb/>inward Pleaſure I enjoy on ſeeing <lb/>any poor
            Sufferers relieved by my <lb/>Means, makes me very ample Sa- <lb/>tisfaction for all the
            Pains I can <lb/>take for their Recovery. </p>
          <lb/>
          <dateline rend="size(0.5)">Auguſt 28, <lb/>1760. </dateline>
          <signed rend="align-right sc">
            <lb/>John Morley. </signed>
        </div>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_13"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>AN <lb/><hi rend="size(2)">ESSAY, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </hi>
      </head>
      <div>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE Scrophula, or what is vul- <lb/>garly called the King's
          Evil, I <lb/>ſhall now conſider. The Word <lb/>Scrophula (ſays a learned Writer) ſignifies
          <lb/>a præternatural Tumour or Humour, <lb/>produced by a particular Acidity of the
          <lb/>Serum of the Blood, either in Gland, <lb/>Muſcle, or Membrane, which it both
          <lb/>coagulates and indurates, or in the Mar- <lb/>row, which it always diſſolves, and
          alſo <lb/>putrifies the Bone. Let us conſider a lit- <lb/>tle this Definition: It ſays, it
          is a præ- <lb/>ternatural Tumour, or Humour; who <lb/>doubts the Truth of the King's Evil,
          Tu- <lb/>mours and Ulcers being contrary to the <lb/>Intention and Deſign of Nature, and
          <lb/>conſequently are præternatural? Next it <pb xml:id="page_14" n="10"/>
          <lb/>ſays, it is produced (that is, a Tumour or <lb/>Humour) by a particular Acidity of
          the Se- <lb/>rum of the Blood. This ſeems indeed to be <lb/>the general Opinion of moſt
          Authors I have <lb/>met with on this Subject, who uſually <lb/>follow each other, like
          Pack-Horſes in the <lb/>ſame Track: But that other Cauſes may <lb/>have the ſame Effects,
          I ſhall by and by <lb/>endeavour to demonſtrate. The Nature <lb/>of Acidity, according to
          this Definition, <lb/>both coagulates and indurates. Coagu- <lb/>lation is performed on
          Milk by Acids, <lb/>that is, turning the Milk into a Curd, it <lb/>ſuppoſes the Acidity,
          or Sourneſs of the <lb/>Serum of the Blood does the ſame, that <lb/>is, curdles in the
          fine Veſſels it enters into. <lb/>But becauſe Vinegar, Lemon Juice, <hi rend="italic"
            >&amp;c.</hi>
          <lb/>are acid on the Tongue, muſt they be ſo <lb/>in the Blood? What mad Work muſt
          <lb/>Vinegar, or other Acids produce, mixt <lb/>with it, let every one judge? Pray think
          <lb/>what Quantities of Vinegar <hi rend="italic">Newmarket</hi>
          <lb/>Jockeys drink for a Month or two toge- <lb/>ther, to reduce themſelves to a proper
          <lb/>Weight for Riding Races, and then tell <lb/>me of any Inſtance of the Scrophula be-
          <lb/>ing produced by that Regimen. Beſides, <pb xml:id="page_15" n="11"/>
          <lb/>if this was the Caſe, why ſhould not the <lb/>Serum be as ſoon coagulated or curdled
          <lb/>in the large Veſſels as in the finer? which <lb/>we ſee it is not, though the Serum
          of the <lb/>Blood contains a proportional Quantity of <lb/>this particular Acidity in the
          large Veſſels, <lb/>as well as in the ſmall: And I am apt <lb/>to think, that the larger
          the Quantity of <lb/>Liquor, the ſooner it will turn ſour, and <lb/>more ſharp the
          Acidity; which I take to <lb/>be the Reaſon, why the Vinegar Makers <lb/>uſe ſuch large
          Casks, even to the holding <lb/>a hundred Barrels of Liquor in one Body. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">have</hi> obſerved my Patients that have <lb/>had Sores or Ulcers in
          their Mouths or <lb/>Throats, have never complained of, or <lb/>perceived any Sourneſs or
          Acidity of Taſte, <lb/>from the purulent Matter they have ſpit <lb/>out, though I have
          been very inquiſitive in <lb/>that Particular, but they have always de- <lb/>clared they
          had a very ſalt Taſte from <lb/>the Matter diſcharged by Spittle. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">That</hi> there is in the Spirit of human <lb/>Blood a great Hoſtility
          (according to Mr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Boyle</hi>) or an Antipathy in reference to
          <lb/>Acids, has been plainly intimated, and <lb/>likewiſe to many Sorts of Acid Spirits,
            <pb xml:id="page_16" n="12"/>
          <lb/>as of Spirit of Salt, Spirit of Nitre, Spi- <lb/>rit and Oil of Vitriol, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> and not only <lb/>againſt factitious Acids, but natural ones
          <lb/>too, which he proves by many Experi- <lb/>ments, as the Curious may ſee in his Na-
          <lb/>tural Hiſtory of human Blood, where he <lb/>alſo ſays, as far as he has been able to
          <lb/>obſerve, the Spirit of human Blood is <lb/>manifeſtly preferable to that Claſſis,
          that <lb/>many call Volatile Alcalies, becauſe it <lb/>makes ſuch great Conflicts with
          divers <lb/>Acid Spirits, as Spirit of Salt, Aqua For- <lb/>tis, <hi rend="italic"
            >&amp;c.</hi> and it will immediately turn Sy- <lb/>rup of Violets from blue to green,
            <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
          <lb/>performing ſuch other Things, that may <lb/>be expected from Volatile Alcalies as
          ſuch. <lb/>And he ſeems ſtrongly to intimate, that <lb/>there are very few (if any Acid
          Particles <lb/>at all) in the Blood, or even in the digeſ- <lb/>tive Ferment of the
          Stomach. But that <lb/>great Quantities of Volatile alcalious Salts <lb/>are contained in
          the Spirit of human Blood, <lb/>he proves by many undeniable Experi- <lb/>ments, which if
          true, muſt naturally de- <lb/>ſtroy all Acidity in the Blood itſelf; ſo <lb/>that
          conſequently, it cannot be a particu- <lb/>lar, or any Acidity at all in the Blood,
          <lb/>that produces the Scrophula. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_17" n="13"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Though</hi> Spirit of Salt and Oil of Vi- <lb/>triol (which are ſtrong
          Acids) will pro- <lb/>duce a Curd-like Subſtance dropped into <lb/>the Serum of the Blood,
          ſo will Oil of <lb/>Tartar per Deliquium (which is a ſtrong <lb/>alcalizate Salt) and alſo
          highly rectified <lb/>Spirit of Wine, and many other alcalious <lb/>Subſtances, do the
          like. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">From</hi> what has been ſaid, it appears, <lb/>that there can be no
          Acidity at all in the <lb/>Blood: But much Alcaline Salt there is <lb/>very capable of
          producing all the Symp- <lb/>toms and ſcrophulous Complaints attend- <lb/>ing this
          Diſorder. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> Induration ſpoken of in the ſame <lb/>Definition, I take to be
          only the Curd- <lb/>like Matter, hardned by Length of Time, <lb/>and thruſt or ſqueezed
          cloſer together by <lb/>the Addition of more of the ſame Mat- <lb/>ter. That the Marrow in
          the Bones is <lb/>diſſolved, I have had no Opportunity to <lb/>obſerve, by not ſeeing any
          Amputation <lb/>performed in this Diſorder. That the <lb/>Bones often ſcale, and throw off
          Honey- <lb/>comb-like Exfoliations, or Pieces, and <lb/>are alſo much corroded, I have
          frequently <lb/>met with. But why will not a ſharp <pb xml:id="page_18" n="14"/>
          <lb/>coroſive Salt cauſe this Corroſion on hu- <lb/>man Bones, as well as common Sea Salt
          <lb/>on the ſofter Bones and Griſtle-like Sub- <lb/>ſtances of raw Beef, when long ſalted
          in <lb/>the Pickling-Tub? I make no doubt but <lb/>it will. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> Reaſon why this Diſeaſe is called <lb/>the King's Evil, as I
          apprehend, is be- <lb/>cauſe it has been often cured by the Royal <lb/>Touch of our Kings
          in this Iſland, from <lb/><hi rend="italic">Edward</hi> the Confeſſor's Time (and how
          <lb/>long before I have ſeen no Account) down <lb/>to the late Queen <hi rend="italic"
            >Anne</hi>'s Reign. This <lb/>has been the Subject of much debate <lb/>amongſt the
          Learned, becauſe great Cures <lb/>have been ſometimes effected that Way, <lb/>when other
          Means have miſcarried; and <lb/>other Means have often ſucceeded, when <lb/>the Royal
          Touch has failed. What then <lb/>ſhall we ſay? In my humble Opinion, <lb/>there is
          ſomething in the Nature of Gold <lb/>itſelf very beneficial in this Diſorder, I <lb/>don't
          mean laid into the Hand of the <lb/>Phyſician by Way of Fee, or pocketed <lb/>by a Surgeon
          or Apothecary, but worn <lb/>about the Patient's Neck, by a white Sat- <lb/>tin Ribband,
          hanging down to the Pit of <pb xml:id="page_19" n="15"/>
          <lb/>the Stomach. How often are Gold Ear-rings <lb/>and Gold Beads for Necklaces worn for
          <lb/>what People call Kernels, in and about the <lb/>Neck and Throat, and for ſore Eyes,
          <lb/>which are all common Appearances in this <lb/>Diſtemper, and not without ſome
          Benefit, <lb/>as I believe many young Women can <lb/>teſtify? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">verily</hi> believe that Gold being con- <lb/>tinually worn at the
          Pit of the Stomach, <lb/>next the Skin, has often had great and <lb/>good Effects, but
          then People will not <lb/>attend with Patience enough the Succeſs <lb/>of ſuch a gentle
          operating Remedy; for <lb/>no doubt, but the fine Effluvia of the <lb/>Gold being
          conſtantly heated by the Sto- <lb/>mach, and continually rubbed againſt it, <lb/>will
          inſinuate many of its fine Particles <lb/>through the Pores of the Skin into the
          <lb/>Blood and Spirits, and mixing in Time <lb/>with the Juices of the Body, have very
          <lb/>ſalutary Effects. But then I would re- <lb/>commend a Piece of fine Gold, without
          <lb/>alloy, as large as a 36 <hi rend="italic">s.</hi> Piece, to be uſed <lb/>for that
          Purpoſe. But this is too charge- <lb/>able an Application for my poor Patients <lb/>Uſe,
          though I ſincerely think in many <pb xml:id="page_20" n="16"/>
          <lb/>Caſes it would be very beneficial, eſpe- <lb/>cially to young Subjects, whoſe
          Stomachs <lb/>are warm, and the Diſeaſe in its Infancy. <lb/>Scrophulous Caſes, ſays Dr.
            <hi rend="italic">Leigh,</hi> may <lb/>be ranked amongſt the <hi rend="italic">opprobria
            Medico- <lb/>rum,</hi> or Scandal of Phyſicians; and after <lb/>his Deſcription of the
          Diſtemper in its <lb/>various Appearances and Effects, con- <lb/>cludes; I could wiſh our
          learned Chirur- <lb/>geons in this Caſe, would make their ut- <lb/>moſt Applications, for
          the Diſcovery of <lb/>ſome Specifick, to correct this Humour. <lb/>You ſee, this learned
          Gentleman ingeni- <lb/>ouſly owns, the Nature and Cure of this <lb/>Diſeaſe was very
          little known by any of <lb/>the Faculty in his Time. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Sir</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">Richard Blackmore</hi> ſays it exceeds <lb/>the Penetration and Capacity
          of human <lb/>Underſtanding, to unravel and diſplay <lb/>thoſe anomalous Clues and
          Convolutions <lb/>proper to ſtrumous Swellings, and to ſet <lb/>their Nature and
          Conſtitution in a clear <lb/>and diſtinct View; and that the acuteſt <lb/>Men cannot
          penetrate and clearly unfold <lb/>the eſſential Difference of this Diſeaſe. <lb/>This, I
          think, ſufficiently ſtrengthens Dr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Leigh</hi>'s Obſervations of
          the ſmall Progreſs <pb xml:id="page_21" n="17"/>
          <lb/>that has been made in the Nature and <lb/>Cure of the King's Evil. Having but
          <lb/>juſt mentioned the Opinions of theſe two <lb/>learned Phyſicians, for more particular
          <lb/>Accounts I refer the Reader to their <lb/>Works, and ſhall proceed with my own
          <lb/>Thoughts and Obſervations. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Setting</hi> aſide then the Doctrine of <lb/>Acid and Alcaly, let us
          conſider the Na- <lb/>ture of Salts, and whether they are capa- <lb/>ble of producing the
          Complaints and Ap- <lb/>pearances appendent to ſcrophulous Diſor- <lb/>ders. That human
          Blood abounds with <lb/>great Quantities of Volatile Salts (is ſuffi- <lb/>ciently
          demonſtrable by obſerving only the <lb/>Sweat and Urine) which are compoſed of
          <lb/>Corpuſcules, or Particles of very differing <lb/>Shapes and Sizes, as Mr. <hi
            rend="italic">Boyle</hi> clearly <lb/>proves, who after many Experiments, has
          <lb/>found, that theſe ſaline Concretions exhi- <lb/>bit very different Appearances; ſome
          are <lb/>ſtrait, ſome crooked, with various Inter- <lb/>ferings, repreſenting Branches of
          Trees, <lb/>Hartſhorn, Feathers, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> Yet, ſays he, <lb/>theſe
          ſeem not to be conſtant Repreſenta- <lb/>tions depending upon the particular Na- <lb/>ture
          of human Blood, but caſual Figura- <lb/>tions that depend upon ſeveral accidental
          <lb/>Cauſes and Circumſtances. Now this <lb/>Scrophula is very often an hereditary Diſ-
          <lb/>eaſe, and conveyed by Parents: How fine <lb/>then muſt the Seeds (if I may ſo call
            <pb xml:id="page_22" n="18"/>
          <lb/>them) of this Diſtemper be? yet ſo it is. <lb/>As every Acorn contains an Oak rapt up
          <lb/>within its Surface, till Time and Vege- <lb/>tation diſcover its Trunk and ſpreading
          <lb/>Branches; ſo is it with this Diſorder. If <lb/>the Seeds are born with us, they lie
          dor- <lb/>mant in our Blood till a proper Time and <lb/>a convenient Diſpoſition of that
          Liquor, and <lb/>the nervous Juices of the Body, cauſe <lb/>them to grow and expand into
          grievous <lb/>Complaints, and terrible Symptoms. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> Blood, which ſeems to be the <lb/>principal Seat of this
          Diſorder, is divided <lb/>into two Parts; the one called the Fibrous, <lb/>conſiſting of
          great Numbers of fine ſmooth <lb/>red Globules, continually floating in the <lb/>other,
          which is a clear lympid Liquor, <lb/>called the Serum, or ſerous Part, which <lb/>conveys
          theſe fine Globules to all Parts of <lb/>the human Fabrick, in ſome Degree or <lb/>other.
          Now if any of theſe red Glo- <lb/>bules are broken change their Figure, <lb/>or are
          obſtructed in their Paſſage by the <lb/>Serum becoming glutinous, or being in <lb/>too
          ſmall or too large a Quantity, or diſ- <lb/>ordered by any præternatural Commotion <lb/>or
          Ferment, the Circulation through the <lb/>fineſt Veſſels will be the firſt impeded and
          <lb/>hindered, as in the Glands, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> Now <lb/>think, if it is
          not agreeable to Reaſon, <lb/>that as the Globules and Serum of the <lb/>Blood may both
          contain a larger Portion <pb xml:id="page_23" n="19"/>
          <lb/>of theſe Volatile Salts when the Blood is <lb/>diſordered by any præternatural Cauſe;
          <lb/>and may not theſe Salts ſhoot into very <lb/>different Figures and Sizes from what
          <lb/>they were in their natural State, according <lb/>to the Nature of the Humours or
          Diſtem- <lb/>pers that are latent in the Blood? And <lb/>as theſe Salts are frequently of
          very per- <lb/>plexing and entangling Figures, may we <lb/>not reaſonably ſuppoſe, that
          thoſe irre- <lb/>gular figur'd Bodies (carried along in the <lb/>Road of Circulation) by
          croſſing and en- <lb/>tangling each other, may cauſe Stoppages <lb/>and Obſtructions in
          the fine Tubes and <lb/>Strainers of the Body, as the Glands par- <lb/>ticularly are? And
          by a continual Acceſ- <lb/>ſion of theſe perplexing Bodies, diſtend <lb/>the obſtructed
          Veſſels (by Length of Time) <lb/>into Tumours, which are often indurated <lb/>or hardened,
          till ſometimes by their cor- <lb/>roſive Quality they fret their Way through <lb/>the
          Skin, and break into Ulcers. What <lb/>can this proceed from, but the red glo- <lb/>bular
          Particles, or fibrous Part of Blood, <lb/>being ſtopped by the figur'd Salts, and <lb/>the
          ſerous Part ſtrain'd as through a Net <lb/>or Sieve from the fibrous? The Serum <lb/>for
          want of theſe ſmooth red globular <lb/>Particles being mixed with it, becomes <lb/>clear,
          tenacious, and ſizey, the minute <lb/>Parts of the Serum not being ſufficiently
          <lb/>ſeparated and divided by thoſe ſmooth <pb xml:id="page_24" n="20"/>
          <lb/>Globules as before, and rubbing againſt <lb/>each other, are thereby rendered acrimo-
          <lb/>nious and fretting, and become produc- <lb/>tive of grievous Complaints, hard to be
          <lb/>removed. Tumours and Ulcers gene- <lb/>rated by theſe or the like Means, are
          <lb/>brought to a good Digeſtion with great <lb/>Difficulty, and very probably not till
          the <lb/>remaining red globular Particles of the <lb/>Blood can be again mixed in ſome De-
          <lb/>gree with the clear Serum, and form one <lb/>circulating Fluid of Blood and Spirits
          as <lb/>before, which I ſuppoſe to be effected by <lb/>melting, abſorbing, altering or
          removing <lb/>thoſe ſaline acrimonious Particles that <lb/>formed the Obſtructions. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Now let us conſider likewiſe the fi- <lb/>brous Part of the Blood, or red Glo-
          <lb/>bules, which being unable to pervade or <lb/>paſs this Rete or Strainer produced by
          <lb/>theſe irregular figur'd Salts, and to ac- <lb/>company the Serum in its Progreſs, are
          <lb/>there ſtopped, and being ſpqueezed and <lb/>crowded cloſe together for want of this
          <lb/>Liquor to float them forward through the <lb/>fine Veſſels, obſtruct the Spirits,
          putrify <lb/>and turn into a Curd-like Subſtance, till <lb/>it is digeſted by Art or
          Nature into a ſoft <lb/>Pus or Matter, and ſo expelled its Neſt. <lb/>What is more common
          than to ſee large <lb/>ſcrophulous Ulcers (eſpecially in the more <lb/>fleſhy Parts) look
          of a deep red Colour <pb xml:id="page_25" n="21"/>
          <lb/>far round their Lips or Edges, which I <lb/>apprehend to proceed from theſe red
          <lb/>Globules being ſeparated from the Serum, <lb/>and ſtagnating in thoſe Parts, until a
          <lb/>proper Digeſtion is procured, and then <lb/>the Redneſs gradully diſappears, and at
          <lb/>the ſame Time you may often obſerve a <lb/>clear tranſparent Liquor ſtand in dewy
          <lb/>Drops on that red Surface of the Skin <lb/>through which it has exudated? Which
          <lb/>I think a ſufficient Demonſtration that <lb/>the ſerous Part of the Blood is in this
          Diſ- <lb/>order ſtrained or ſeparated from the fi- <lb/>brous, and viſible even to the
          naked Eye. <lb/>And I have always found by Experience, <lb/>that as the Quantity of this
          clear limpid <lb/>Liquor has decreaſed, the Ulcer has diſ- <lb/>charged a more laudable
          Pus, the Red- <lb/>ness inſenſibly worn off, and then the <lb/>Ulcer has healed up with
          very little Ap- <lb/>plication more than dry Lint. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Should</hi> I attempt to mention all Parts <lb/>ſubject to this
          Diſorder, I muſt name <lb/>every individual of the human Fabrick, <lb/>for I know of none
          exempt from this ter- <lb/>rible Malady, no not even the Bones <lb/>themſelves; for in my
          Courſe of Practice <lb/>I have had this verified by repeated Ob- <lb/>ſervations: I have
          had a Patient afflicted <lb/>with Tumours and Ulcers from the Crown <lb/>of the Head to
          the Sole of the Foot, <lb/>and in above twenty different Places be- <pb xml:id="page_26"
            n="22"/>
          <lb/>ſides at once, the major Part of which <lb/>have been cured by the Application of
          <lb/>dry Lint only, and the Remainder by <lb/>very ſimple Applications, and but very
          <lb/>little Phyſick. But ſuch bad Caſes re- <lb/>quire much Time to make a perfect Cure.
          <lb/>For any-body muſt think, that a Diſeaſe <lb/>brought into the World with one, and ſo
          <lb/>interwoven with the Conſtitution, and <lb/>grown up with it, muſt have much Time
          <lb/>and Patience ere it can be totally ſubdued <lb/>and eradicated from the Blood and
          Spi- <lb/>rits. Though I have never ſeen any Diſ- <lb/>ſections of the human Body, yet I
          <lb/>may gueſs from what I obſerve without, <lb/>that the Stomach, Bowels, and Inteſtines,
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> are no leſs diſordered within, which <lb/>muſt
          infallibly be the Source of many fa- <lb/>tal Conſequences, unleſs removed by Art <lb/>or
          Nature, as ſometimes may be the Caſe. <lb/>Every the leaſt Tube or Strainer in the
          <lb/>whole human Frame may poſſibly be tor- <lb/>mented by the Seeds of this Diſorder, as
          <lb/>they begin to expand, and long before <lb/>they arrive to a Bulk perceiveable by the
          <lb/>Eye or Touch. Unuſual Prickings and <lb/>Daſhings, and Sickneſs at the Stomach,
          <lb/>and Uneaſineſs in many Parts, are com- <lb/>mon Complaints in the beginning of this
          <lb/>Diſeaſe: What can theſe proceed from, <lb/>but the Aſſemblage of ſharp, ſaline, in-
          <lb/>terfering Particles, endeavouring to force <pb xml:id="page_27" n="23"/>
          <lb/>their Way through theſe fine Strainers <lb/>by Stops and Starts. The upper Lip
          <lb/>ſwelled, Eyes inflamed, the Glands about <lb/>the Jaws, Neck, Throat, and Shoulders,
          <lb/>tumified, ſhow this Diſorder rather ſooner <lb/>(though not always) than moſt other
          <lb/>Parts. The Backs of the Hands, Elbows, <lb/>Arm-Pits, Ribs and Ancles, are fre-
          <lb/>quently affected, and as the Diſorder en- <lb/>creaſes, the ſofter Bones feel its
          Effects, <lb/>which if they exfoliate, are often cured, <lb/>if not, uſually terminate in
          malignant <lb/>Ulcers of a cancerous Nature, and bring <lb/>the Patient at Length to an
          End. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">That</hi> the King's Evil is a Diſeaſe, <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſui
            Generis,</hi> or after its own Kind, I can <lb/>readily admit. But then how often is it
          <lb/>complicated and blended with others, as <lb/>the Gout, Venereal Evil, White Swel-
          <lb/>lings in the Knees, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> which ſeem to <lb/>have a near
          Affinity with it, by affecting <lb/>the Bones and Joints much in the ſame <lb/>Manner? But
          the various Combinations <lb/>and Degrees of each particular Malady <lb/>that may at the
          ſame Time ſeize on the <lb/>human Syſtem, I believe is impoſſible to <lb/>be diſtinguiſhed
          and aſcertained. Then <lb/>how can we range the various Swellings <lb/>common or
          extraordinary, that ariſe on <lb/>the Surface of the Body, or lie almoſt <lb/>concealed
          among the Muſcles, and are at- <lb/>tended with ſuch novel Appearances every <pb
            xml:id="page_28" n="24"/>
          <lb/>Day, without knowing every particular <lb/>Degree, of every particular Diſeaſe, and
          <lb/>their Conſequences, that may poſſibly be <lb/>at once uniting in the ſame Body and
          its <lb/>Members? What may probably be the <lb/>immediate Cauſe of this Diſtemper, I
          <lb/>have already hinted at; but the more re- <lb/>mote ones, I may venture to aſſert, are
          as <lb/>numerous as the different Appearances of <lb/>Tumours and Ulcers in all Parts of
          the <lb/>Body put together. I ſhould ſoon wade <lb/>out of my Depth, if I attempted to un-
          <lb/>fold ſuch intricate and perplexing Combi- <lb/>nations, or the Forms and eſſential
          Pro- <lb/>perties of thoſe fine Particles of hidden <lb/>Matter, as may contribute to the
          Forma- <lb/>tion of the King's Evil, and have puzzled <lb/>ſo many judicious and learned
          Phyſicians, <lb/>and may ſtill do ſo for Ages to come. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">shall</hi> now proceed to ſay ſomething <lb/>relative to the Cure of
          this obſtinate Diſ- <lb/>eaſe. If we ſearch the moſt eminent <lb/>Authors in purſuit of a
          Cure for this Diſ- <lb/>temper, we ſhall find ourſelves miſerably <lb/>diſappointed, ſays
          a late Writer: I ſay ſo <lb/>too. Therefore as their Preſcriptions ſel- <lb/>dom anſwer
          the deſired End, I ſhall take <lb/>no Notice of them, but purſue my own <lb/>Way of
          Thinking. I have no great Opi- <lb/>nion of diſcuſſing of Tumours (unleſs <lb/>the Face is
          likely to be much deformed by <lb/>them, eſpecially of the Female Sex; or <pb
            xml:id="page_29" n="25"/>
          <lb/>when the Eyes are inflamed, and very <lb/>troubleſome, then I think ſuch a Remedy
          <lb/>is juſtifiable) becauſe the peccant Matter <lb/>is only removed from one Part to
          another, <lb/>and not cured, but ſtill ſubſiſts in the <lb/>Blood and Spirits, and may
          poſſibly be <lb/>thrown on a more noble and dangerous <lb/>Part, and do much more Harm
          than can <lb/>be eaſily imagined. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">My</hi> Patients have often told me (to <lb/>uſe their own Way of
          Expreſſion) that <lb/>they have had Swellings in their Necks, <lb/>or other Places, and
          Neighbour ſuch a <lb/>one told 'um, if they did them with <lb/>Vinegar, 'twould put them
          away, which <lb/>it ſometimes did, but in a little Time <lb/>others aroſe in their Stead
          in other Parts, <lb/>that would not yield to their old Remedy. <lb/>If they were Pariſh
          Poor, and looked af- <lb/>ter by the Year, they fell to my Share, <lb/>becauſe nothing was
          to be got by them, <lb/>and 'twould coſt a deal of Trouble and <lb/>Expence for Phyſick
          for ſuch poor <lb/>Wretches, who were better out of the <lb/>Way. How unhappy are poor
          People, <lb/>to be thus cruelly uſed by ſome mercenary <lb/>Phyſick-Mongers? How many
          funeſt Ex- <lb/>amples are in every one's Memory (if <lb/>they would recollect a little)
          of ſome <lb/>Neighbours, or Acquaintance, that have <lb/>even deſtroyed themſelves, by
          backing <lb/>or ſtriking in Humours (as it is called) <pb xml:id="page_30" n="26"/>
          <lb/>and repelling them to ſome mortal Part? <lb/>This Practice is too frequent with the
          <lb/>Fair Sex; I hope they will think ſeriouſly <lb/>for the future, and do ſo no more. If
          any <lb/>Reaſons occur to make Repellents neceſ- <lb/>ſary, I then order proper Purgatives
          to <lb/>carry off the morbifick Matter, cleanſe <lb/>the Blood, and prevent any Danger
          from <lb/>ſuch a Revulſion. Iſſues or Setons I never <lb/>uſe, and often dry them up, for
          I could <lb/>never perceive any Benefit accrue to the <lb/>Patient from them. If Ulcers
          diſcharge <lb/>the offending Matter lodged in or near <lb/>them, why ſhould we invite it
          another <lb/>Way, and not follow the Road Nature <lb/>has pointed out? What are Ulcers,
          but <lb/>ſo many natural Iſſues, which will diſ- <lb/>charge themſelves, if a good
          Digeſtion is <lb/>procured, as long as any offending Mat- <lb/>ter ſubſiſts in or near
          them, and then dry <lb/>up of courſe, unleſs hindred by Art? <lb/>Why then ſhould we make
          an artificial <lb/>Ulcer that Nature wants not? Nay, is <lb/>even detrimental to it, by
          encreaſing a <lb/>Diſcharge, which we are endeavouring to <lb/>diminiſh, and wholly
          ſubdue. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Salt</hi> Water being much in Vogue, I <lb/>ſhall give my Thoughts on
          it as a Remedy <lb/>for the King's Evil. I had a Patient <lb/>troubled with a very painful
          Inflamma- <lb/>tion of the Eyes, which had baffled the <lb/>Skill of all ſhe had applied
          to in <hi rend="italic">London,</hi>
          <pb xml:id="page_31" n="27"/>
          <lb/>(and being a Perſon of Fortune, be ſure no <lb/>Advice was wanting) ſhe was ſent to
          the <lb/>Sea Side to drink the Salt Water, which <lb/>ſhe did for a Month, and returned
          much <lb/>worſe: When I ſaw her, I ſoon perceived <lb/>the Diſorder to be ſcrophulous; ſhe
          kept <lb/>in a dark Room, not being able to abide <lb/>the leaſt Gleam of Light,
          complained of <lb/>intolerable daſhing Pains in her Forehead, <lb/>and Eyes, which
          diſcharged great Quan- <lb/>tities of clear Water, ſo ſcalding and cor- <lb/>roſive, that
          it excoriated the Skin where <lb/>it flowed down the Cheeks. This Lady's <lb/>Complaints
          were afterwards removed by <lb/>a moſt ſimple and eaſy Remedy, which I <lb/>apply in thoſe
          Caſes, and ſeldom miſs of <lb/>a Cure. What I would obſerve from this <lb/>is, that the
          ſaline Particles of the Water, <lb/>which ſhe drank ſo long, added more <lb/>Matter of a
          ſimilar Nature to what was <lb/>too abundant in the Blood and Spirits al- <lb/>ready,
          which entirely convinces me that <lb/>drinking Salt Water is wrong in ſcrophu- <lb/>lous
          Caſes of the Eyes; and bathing for <lb/>them, I believe, to be equally hurtful, <lb/>for
          we know many ſaline Particles may <lb/>in bathing be abſorbed through the Pores <lb/>of
          the Skin by the Blood, and ſo unite <lb/>with thoſe already there. Obſerve what <lb/>Lord
            <hi rend="italic">Bacon</hi> ſays, <q rend="quotes">As it ſeemeth Salt <lb/>draweth
            Blood, as well as Blood draw- <lb/>eth Salt. </q> That is, they reciprocally <pb
            xml:id="page_32" n="28"/>
          <lb/>attract each other. Extirpating of tumi- <lb/>fied Glands (which is no unfrequent
          Prac- <lb/>tice) I have never uſed, either by the <lb/>Knife, or Cautery, actual or
          potential; <lb/>neither can I approve the Method, though <lb/>I own its the moſt painful.
          I have had ſome <lb/>Patients with me, whoſe Glands have <lb/>been thus treated, and to
          all Appearance <lb/>quite cured, and for a Time well; but <lb/>as the Humour was not
          thereby eradicated <lb/>out of the Blood and Spirits, it broke out <lb/>again in freſh
          Places, which brought them <lb/>to me. Theſe freſh Complaints I have <lb/>afterwards cured
          with eaſy and gentle <lb/>Applications. Sometimes indeed, where <lb/>the Diſorder has been
          mild, and invaded <lb/>but few Glands, and the Seeds of the Diſ- <lb/>eaſe wholly
          contained in them, Extirpa- <lb/>tion has done the Deed. But if theſe <lb/>tumified Glands
          can be reduced to their <lb/>natural State by a leſs dangerous and <lb/>painful Way
          (though indeed not ſo quick- <lb/>ly) and no Danger of any Tumours ari- <lb/>ſing
          elſewhere: Which ſhall we chooſe, <lb/>the more quick, painful, and uncertain, <lb/>or the
          more ſlow, eaſy, and ſure Method <lb/>of Cure? How many have been ſalivated <lb/>without
          receiving any Good? Inſtances <lb/>of this Kind I have met with in my Prac- <lb/>tice,
          more than once. A learned Phyſi- <lb/>cian writes, <q rend="quotes">A Salivation is found
            by <pb xml:id="page_33" n="29"/>
            <lb/>Experience incapable of eradicating this <lb/>obſtinate Diſeaſe, notwithſtanding it
            <lb/>has ſuch peculiar Specifick, and almoſt <lb/>certain Virtue to remove the Venereal
            <lb/>Evil. </q> Which plainly proves (as I <lb/>think) the Seeds or Cauſes of the two
          <lb/>Diſtempers to be very different; and <lb/>confutes the vulgar Notion, that the Ve-
          <lb/>nereal Evil is the Parent of the King's <lb/>Evil; for if they both ſpring from the
          <lb/>ſame Original, why are they not removed <lb/>by the ſame Means? Which we find they
          <lb/>are not; but when united in the ſame <lb/>Subject, its rational to think they
          encreaſe <lb/>each others Malignity, and render the <lb/>Cure more uncertain and
          difficult. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Most</hi> People afflicted with ſcrophu- <lb/>lous Diſorders in their
          Eyes, are very <lb/>fond of hood-winking or covering them <lb/>from the Light and Air,
          which is the <lb/>worſt Method they can take, for it not <lb/>only encreaſes the
          Inflammation, but in- <lb/>vites the Humour that Way, and conſe- <lb/>quently occaſions a
          greater Diſcharge from <lb/>them, which ſhould be carried off ano- <lb/>ther Way, and
          which is often of ſo cor- <lb/>roſive a Nature, as to excoriate and fret <lb/>the Skin of
          the Face, as it diſtils down <lb/>the Cheeks: I always make them throw <lb/>away their
          Coverings, either going to Bed, <lb/>or riſing in the Morning, to prevent tak- <lb/>ing
          Cold, by too ſuddenly expoſing their <pb xml:id="page_34" n="30"/>
          <lb/>Eyes; and my Succeſs has always war- <lb/>ranted this Practice. After diſapproving
          <lb/>others Proceedings in the Cure of this <lb/>Diſorder, it may be asked, why I don't
          <lb/>publiſh my own, which I think ſo much <lb/>better? To ſuch Enquirers I anſwer:
          <lb/>The Medicines I uſe are very innocent <lb/>and common Things, but the Prepara-
          <lb/>tion is curious and difficult, and takes <lb/>much Time to compleat. Should I di-
          <lb/>vulge it, very few People (except the <lb/>Compounders of Medicine) would attend
          <lb/>the Proceſs, or take the Trouble of it; <lb/>and how little Good will a vitiouſly
          pre- <lb/>pared Medicine do, is obvious to any one: <lb/>And as the common Labourers, and
          Han- <lb/>dicraftſmen, their Wives and Children, <lb/>make the Bulk of my Patients, it is
          above <lb/>their Capacity, and of no Uſe to tell <lb/>them any Thing about it, more than
          <lb/>what is neceſſary to their right managing <lb/>themſelves under the Regimen I direct,
          <lb/>and to give them the plaineſt and ſimpleſt <lb/>Directions poſſible, as well as to
          uſe the <lb/>eaſieſt Means for their Recovery. As to <lb/>the Sellers of Medicines, I
          think they <lb/>can have no claim to reap any Advantage <lb/>from my Labour and
          Experience. The <lb/>better Sort of Families infected by this <lb/>Diſeaſe are really more
          to be pitied, than <lb/>the very loweſt Claſs of the People, for <lb/>they are but too
          often amuſed with falla- <pb xml:id="page_35" n="31"/>
          <lb/>cious and flattering Accounts of their own <lb/>real Diſorders (of this in
          particular, and <lb/>as Dr. <hi rend="italic">Radcliff</hi> truly obſerved) kept in
          <lb/>Miſery for their Money. And to every <lb/>one in general I ſay, nobody has any
          <lb/>Cauſe to complain of keeping the Thing <lb/>to myſelf, for every one that pleaſes,
          and <lb/>has the King's Evil, may apply to me, <lb/>and reap the ſame Benefit, as well as
          if <lb/>they knew the whole Proceſs. (Great I <lb/>know) is the general Clamour againſt
          Se- <lb/>crets, Noſtrums, and old Wives Medi- <lb/>cines, as ſome pleaſe to call them; but
          I <lb/>would fain know, if any prudent Perſon <lb/>would refuſe to be cured by a ſafe and
          in- <lb/>nocent Medicine, unleſs he knew the <lb/>whole particular Preparation and Compo-
          <lb/>ſition; or becauſe I don't chooſe to make <lb/>that Diſcovery of my Methods that pub-
          <lb/>lick Curioſity or Cenſure may expect? <lb/>Did Dr. <hi rend="italic">James</hi>
          publiſh the Preparation of <lb/>his Fever Powder, yet I believe few Peo- <lb/>ple in their
          Senſes would ſcruple the Uſe <lb/>of it? If the candid, humane, and ge- <lb/>nerous
          Phyſicians an Surgeons ſmile on <lb/>my Endeavours for the Publick Good, let <lb/>the
          envious, ſnarling, and covetous Prac- <lb/>titioners blame me if they pleaſe, for not
          <lb/>treating my Patients <hi rend="italic">Secundum Artem</hi> (as <lb/>they term it)
          that is, by not making long <lb/>Bills. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_36" n="32"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">shall</hi> mention but one Thing more: <lb/>Many People who have ſeen
          the amazing <lb/>Effects of my Applications, often tell me, <lb/>they hope I will not let
          the Secret, and <lb/>its Improvements, die with me; I do not <lb/>intend it ſhall; for I
          carefully write down <lb/>every Patient's Complaints, the Methods <lb/>I uſe, and the
          Succeſs that follows, as far <lb/>as I can be informed by themſelves or <lb/>Neighbours,
          who come to me on their <lb/>Recommendation, by which Means I <lb/>frequently hear of
          People I have cured, <lb/>who living at a Diſtance, and being free <lb/>from their
          Complaints, take no further <lb/>Notice of me; though all I deſire for <lb/>my Trouble is,
          to hear from themſelves, <lb/>either by Letter, or Word of Mouth, <lb/>when they are well:
          But all my Patients <lb/>are not ſo forgetful of their Benefactor. M <lb/>y Papers and
          Obſervations relating to <lb/>the Cure of the King's Evil, I hope will <lb/>fall into the
          Hands of my Executor: And <lb/>may he uſe them to the Benefit of Man- <lb/>kind in
          general, an the Poor in particu- <lb/>lar, with the ſame Succeſs, and charitable
          <lb/>Intentions, as I have done. </p>
        <trailer rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_37" n="33"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">P</hi>HILIP WINTERFLOOD, late of <lb/>Halſted in Eſſex, a Journeyman
          Bar- <lb/>ber, aged 35, now living at the Sign of <lb/>the Periwig over againſt the White
          Horſe <lb/>at Mile-End near London, was about <lb/>Eight Years ago miſerably afflicted
          with <lb/>ſeveral ſtrenuous Ulcers under both <lb/>Breaſts; and being a fat Man ſome of
          <lb/>them were above an Inch deep and diſ- <lb/>charged much foul corrupted Matter, and
          <lb/>had done ſo a long Time, had evaded all <lb/>Methods of Cure, and when I ſaw him
          <lb/>was a very deplorable Object. This Per- <lb/>ſon had the Diſorder hereditary, many of
          <lb/>his Family having been greatly afflicted <lb/>with it. He has travelled many Parts of
          <lb/>England ſince, and been ſeen with much <lb/>Admiration by many Perſons who have
          <lb/>talked with him. I cured him in about <lb/>Six Months, and he continues well to
          <lb/>this Day, and has ſent me ſeveral poor Pa- <lb/>tients who have travelled on Foot
          near <lb/>Fifty Miles to my Houſe, who I believe <lb/>don't repent their Journeys. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>WIDOW of Joſeph Prentice of <lb/>Halſted, aged 70 Years, ſome Years ago <lb/>had the
          Evil in her Eyes, and was re- <pb xml:id="page_38" n="34"/>
          <lb/>lieved, and held well ſeveral Years, but <lb/>her Eyes growing very bad again with
          <lb/>great daſhing Pains in her Head, and a <lb/>ſmall Tumor ariſing on her Shoulder, ſhe
          <lb/>applied to me; I cured her Eyes and the <lb/>Tumor ſubſided with very little Trouble,
          <lb/>and ſhe remained perfectly free from her <lb/>Complaints, till her Death, ſome Years
          <lb/>after. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>JACOB HOGYOTT, Son of Samuel <lb/>Hogyott, Husbandman, of Grinſted-Green <lb/>in
          Halſted, aged 18, had a large Scropho- <lb/>lous Swelling under his Chin, and many
          <lb/>Scropholous Tumors and Ulcers on each <lb/>Side the Neck; ſome broke and run clear
          <lb/>Water, and ſome good Matter. This <lb/>Lad I cured in Nine Months, and is now
          <lb/>gone to Service and capable to earn his <lb/>Living as a Husbandman; was recom-
          <lb/>mended by Mr. Vaughan, a very eminent <lb/>Surgeon, who could do him no Service. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>REBECCA BROWN, Daughter of <lb/>Jerry Brown of Coln Engain, Eſſex, Huſ- <lb/>bandman,
          aged 12 Years, had ſeveral <lb/>running Scropholous Sores about her Neck <lb/>and
          Shoulders, otherwiſe a florid well <lb/>looking Girl; my very eaſy Methods cur- <lb/>ed
          her in about Four Month. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_39" n="35"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>JONATHAN WADE, of Braintree, <lb/>recommended to me for the King's Evil <lb/>by Mr.
          Stapletyon Surgeon, of Braintree, <lb/>Eſſex. When he came to me, he had <lb/>two large
          running Sores near the Elbow <lb/>on the left Arm, and one about an Inch <lb/>above the
          Ancle on the left Leg, and a <lb/>Sore in the Palm of his left Hand; had <lb/>all the
          Sores Six Months before I ſaw <lb/>him; moſt of his Relations had the Evil. <lb/>About a
          Year after his Brother came and <lb/>told me he was quite cured. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>WILLIAM BROWN, belongs to Goſ- <lb/>feld in Eſſex, aged 19, had the Evil <lb/>much in
          both Eyes, very much inflamed <lb/>with great Pains in the Fore-part of his <lb/>Head; run
          ſometimes clear Water very <lb/>ſalt, and ſometimes Corruption from the <lb/>Corners of
          his Eyes, and very impatient <lb/>of Light. His Mother had the Evil in <lb/>her Family,
          and came to tell me her Son <lb/>was now quite well by my Means. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>SARAH NORMAN, Daughter of <lb/>Francis Brewer, on the Burr-Walls at <lb/>Bath in
          Somerſetſhire, aged 14 Years. <lb/>Her Upper-lip much ſwelled, and both <lb/>Eyes much
          inflamed; theſe Diſorders I <lb/>ſoon cured by a very eaſy Method. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_40" n="36"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>EDWARD POTTER, Son of Rich- <lb/>ard Potter of Pedmarſh in Eſſex, aged 12 <lb/>Years,
          ſent by Mr. Maniſtree, Apothe- <lb/>cary of Halſted, had when he came to <lb/>me a Sore on
          the Back of both Hands and <lb/>four running Ulcers in the Calf of his left <lb/>Leg; he
          is now quite well, and his Fa- <lb/>ther has got him out to Service, and came <lb/>to
          thank me for the Cure of his Son. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>ROBERT WADE, of Bocking in <lb/>Eſſex, Shoemaker, aged 15 Years. A Sore <lb/>on the
          Inſide of the right Knee, and a <lb/>large Swelling (broke about a Week be- <lb/>fore he
          came to me, and run clear Wa- <lb/>ter) on the Outſide the left Thigh, from <lb/>a ſmall
          Orifice, and very hollow for two <lb/>or three Inches above and below. About <lb/>eight
          Months after his firſt coming to me, <lb/>he came to thank me being quite well. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>SARAH EVERITT, Daughter of <lb/>John Everitt of Earl's Coln, Husband- <lb/>man, aged
          19 Years; ſhe had a large <lb/>Swelling on the left Side the Neck, and <lb/>the ſame Side
          of the Face and under the <lb/>Chin much ſwelled, had this Complaint <lb/>four Years
          before ſhe came to me; ſhe <lb/>had been with a Surgeon, who tried to <lb/>cure her, but
          not ſucceeding, pronounced <pb xml:id="page_41" n="37"/>
          <lb/>it the King's Evil, gave her up, and then <lb/>ſhe came to me, and is now well. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>ANN MEAD, Wife of Samuel Mead, <lb/>of Great Wrating in Suffolk, Husband- <lb/>man,
          aged 34, came recommended to me <lb/>by Mr. John Smith, Surgeon of Little <lb/>Theorloe,
          for the Evil very bad in her <lb/>Eyes, in November 1757; and in April <lb/>1758, I
          received the following Letter from <lb/>her. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>SIR, This comes to acquaint you, <lb/>that by God's Bleſſing and your Kindneſs
          <lb/>to me, I am quite reſtored to Sight. I <lb/>am ſo well recovered that at preſent I
          have <lb/>not the leaſt Diſorder in my Eyes. I re- <lb/>turn you my ſincere Thanks for the
          <lb/>Trouble you gave yourſelf on my Behalf, <lb/>having received that Benefit from you
          <lb/>which I could not find from ſeveral Doc- <lb/>tors I applied to, which was very
          charge- <lb/>able to me. That Almighty God will be <lb/>pleaſed to ſhower down his
          Bleſſings upon <lb/>you, both temporal and ſpiritual, for ex- <lb/>tending your Charity to
          the Diſtreſſed, is <lb/>and ſhall be the conſtant Prayer of, </p>
        <lb/>
        <salute>SIR, </salute>
        <signed rend="indent hanging">
          <lb/>Your moſt humble Servant, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ann Mead.</hi>
        </signed>
        <lb/>
        <dateline><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 23, 1758. </dateline>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_42" n="38"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">TITUS WELLS </hi>, Son of John Wells <lb/>of Sudbury in Suffolk, aged
          14 Years, <lb/>ſent to me by Mr. E. Grove Surgeon; <lb/>when he came to me, he had a large
          <lb/>running Sore on the left Side his Neck, <lb/>had been ſo about a Year, and a very bad
          <lb/>Ulcer on the left Thigh, a Sore on the <lb/>Back of his left Hand, and ſeveral ſmall
          <lb/>Swellings about the Neck and left Elbow; <lb/>was with me about a Twelvemonth after,
          <lb/>all his Sores quite well. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">SIMON SMITH</hi>, of Great Wading- <lb/>feild in Suffolk, was
          recommended to me <lb/>by Mr. Robert Upcher, Surgeon of Sud- <lb/>bury, being greatly
          afflicted with the <lb/>King's Evil in his Eyes; he had ſome <lb/>Swellings under his
          Chin, upon remov- <lb/>ing of which, the Humor fell into both <lb/>his Eyes, and reſiſted
          all Endeavours to <lb/>remove it, till he came to me; he is now <lb/>very well by my
          Aſſiſtance. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">JOHN TUFF</hi>, of Stebing in Eſſex, <lb/>aged 14, came to me with a
          ſcropholous <lb/>running Sore on the Side of the left Foot, <lb/>and a ſmall Sore on each
          Groin, his Noſe <lb/>inflamed and run much clear Water and <lb/>very ſcabbed; his Brother
          Thomas Tuff, <lb/>aged 11 Years, had ſeveral Sores broke <pb xml:id="page_43" n="39"/>
          <lb/>on the right Side his Neck. The above <lb/>Brothers were ſent to me by Mr. Staple-
          <lb/>ton, Surgeon of Braintree, I have cured <lb/>them both. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">CATHERINE ANDERSON</hi>, aged <lb/>11 Years, living with Mrs Whitting
          in <lb/>Cullum-ſtreet, London, had the King's <lb/>Evil very much in both Eyes, had Advice
          <lb/>to no Purpoſe. I was then deſired to ſee <lb/>her. I ſoon removed the Diſorder and
          <lb/>cured der Eyes. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">MARY PRENTICE</hi>, of Coln En- <lb/>gain, Eſſex, ſingle Woman, aged
          50. <lb/>This Woman was cured about 30 Years <lb/>ago of the King's Evil with many bad
          <lb/>Sores all over her, held well till within <lb/>ſix Months, when a large Sore broke
          out <lb/>on the Outſide of the left Leg a little above <lb/>the Ancle and greatly
          inflamed; I remov- <lb/>ed this Complaint entirely in a few <lb/>Months. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Let the following ſpeak for itſelf; the <lb/>Lad is quite well by my Endeavours. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">SIR</hi>, ſonce more offer my Solicitations in <lb/>Behalf of a poor
          Lad belonging to Great <lb/>Waldingfield (Tho. Newton), who has <lb/>laboured under the
          King's Evil, for twelve <pb xml:id="page_44" n="40"/>
          <lb/>Months paſt, in his Eyes. I hope your Aſ- <lb/>ſiſtance to the above Subject, which I
          know <lb/>will be gratefully acknowledged, and may <lb/>the Almighty grant you Succeſs in
          this <lb/>and all others, and great may be your <lb/>Reward both here and hereafter, which
          <lb/>are the hearty Prayers of, </p>
        <lb/>
        <salute>Sir, </salute>
        <signed rend="indent hanging">
          <lb/>Your humble Servant (tho' unknown) <lb/><hi rend="italic">Robert Upcher,</hi>
          <lb/>Surgeon in Sudbury. </signed>
        <lb/>
        <dateline>Sudbury, <hi rend="italic">Jan.</hi> 31, 1759. </dateline>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>ELIZ. BAYLEY, Daughter of Mr. <lb/>Robert Bayley, Baker at Chelmsford, <lb/>aged 10
          Years, had a Scropholous Diſor- <lb/>der fell into her left Eye after the Small <lb/>Pox,
          with a large white Speck on the Pu- <lb/>pil, which continued ſeven Years before <lb/>I
          ſaw it. Her Father and Mother both <lb/>joined in a genteel Letter of Thanks, to
          <lb/>acquaint me that her Sight was perfectly <lb/>well, and ſhe returns me all the Thanks
          <lb/>ſhe can poſſibly give. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>ANN GAY, Daughter of George Gay <lb/>Soldier, of Bocking Church-ſtreet in Eſ-
          <lb/>ſex, aged 6 Years. A ſmall running Sore <lb/>on the right Arm and one under the left
          <lb/>Ear, and a large Tumor gathering under <pb xml:id="page_45" n="41"/>
          <lb/>the left Eye, and very bad in her Health; <lb/>the Tumor afterwards broke withinſide
          <lb/>of the lower Eyelid, and diſcharged a <lb/>great Quantity of thick Matter; is now
          <lb/>perfectly recovered by my Methods, and <lb/>in a very good State of Health; her Mo-
          <lb/>ther brought her to ſhow me, and thank'd <lb/>me. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>MARY ANN ALSTONE lived at <lb/>Mrs. Hancock's, on the Burr-Walls at <lb/>Bath in
          Somerſetſhire, aged ſeven Years <lb/>and a half, had her upper Lip greatly <lb/>ſwelled,
          and ſome ſmall Tumors in her <lb/>Neck. I was at Bath ſome time after, <lb/>and found her
          perfectly well by my Di- <lb/>rections. Her Mother went a nurſing, <lb/>and was removed to
          one Mattins a Scourer <lb/>in Horſe-ſtreet, Bath. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>MARY, Daughter of Geo. Newman, <lb/>Gardener in the Hollow Way, over the <lb/>Bridge
          in Bath, aged 10 Years, had a <lb/>Scropholous Ulcer on the Point of her <lb/>right Elbow,
          and one on the Back of her <lb/>right Hand; on my next being at Bath, her <lb/>Mother
          brought her to me quite well, <lb/>and ſhowed me a large Piece of Bone that <lb/>had
          ſeparated from her Elbow, all per- <lb/>fectly ſound. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_46" n="42"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>SARAH LAMB, of Booking Church- <lb/>ſtreet, aged 31 Years, ſent by Mr. Sta-
          <lb/>pleton Surgeon, Jo. Blawer Churchwar- <lb/>den, and Tho. Chandler Overſeer; had
          <lb/>many Tumors and Ulcers on her Arms, <lb/>and Legs, and Face, ſome opened by a
          <lb/>Surgeon, ſeveral Sores in her Mouth and <lb/>Throat, with great Difficulty of Swal-
          <lb/>lowing, and great Heat in her Throat <lb/>and Stomach, and raiſed much corrupt
          <lb/>Matter by Spit, which ſhe told me always <lb/>taſted very ſalt, but not ſour, bit-
          <lb/>ter, ſweet, or acid like Vinegar. This <lb/>Woman came to me about a Year after,
          <lb/>to thank me for the Benefit ſhe had re- <lb/>ceived; the Tumors all gone, the Ul-
          <lb/>cers healed up, raiſes no putrid Matter, <lb/>and has no Complaint, but a very little
          <lb/>Stiffneſs ſometimes in the Throat, after <lb/>ſwallowing a large Morſel. Her Mother
          <lb/>died of the King's Evil. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>WILLIAM BURGETT, aged Eight <lb/>Years, Son of William Burgett, belong- <lb/>ing to
          Cripplegate Pariſh, London, works <lb/>with Mr. Aſhmole at Holloway Mount, <lb/>helps to
          make Lamp-black. This Boy <lb/>had the King's Evil very bad in both Eyes, <lb/>and the
          upper Lip much ſwelled, about <lb/>three Months. After he was with me, I <pb
            xml:id="page_47" n="43"/>
          <lb/>received a Meſſage from his Father, to <lb/>thank me, for curing his Son, who was
          <lb/>now very well by my Directions. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>MABLE BULLINGBROOKE, <lb/>Daughter of John Bullingbrooke, Carpen- <lb/>ter of Long
          Melford in Suffolk, aged 16 <lb/>Years, ſent by Mr. Fairfax, Surgeon: <lb/>Both her Eyes
          much inflamed, upper Lip <lb/>ſwelled, and the Noſe diſcharged much <lb/>clear Water. This
          Diſorder had been in- <lb/>creaſing four Years ſince it firſt appeared; <lb/>ſhe is now
          well, as I have heard from <lb/>many People that know her, but never <lb/>heard from
          herſelf, according to Promiſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Mr. AMBROSE DEATH the Young- <lb/>er, is troubled with an Opthalmy, which <lb/>from
          its Stubborneſs in not yielding to <lb/>the uſual Evacuations in that Caſe pre-
          <lb/>ſcribed, I do imagine to be ſtrumous, and <lb/>upon that Account do recommend him as
          <lb/>a King's Evil Patient. </p>
        <signed>John Burch, Sur- <lb/>geon in Lavenham, Suffolk, </signed>
        <dateline>Nov. 5, 1759. </dateline>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This Perſon I cured in a little Time, <lb/>and he has remained very well, without
          <lb/>the leaſt Complaint to this Day. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_48" n="44"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>ROBERT HEATHERLY, Son of <lb/>the Reverend Mr. Heatherly, late Mi- <lb/>niſter of
          Clavering in Eſſex, formerly <lb/>Maſter of the School in St. Bartholo- <lb/>mew's
          Hoſpital, London, aged 23 Years, <lb/>had been an Out-patient there, for the <lb/>King's
          Evil, had the ſecond Joint of his <lb/>Thumb ſo affected that the Bone was di- <lb/>geſted
          out, and had ſeveral other Places <lb/>healed up. Not long after, the Diſorder <lb/>fell
          into both his Eyes with ſome ſmall <lb/>unbroken Tumors in the Neck, and un- <lb/>der both
          Ears, and had been blind ſome <lb/>Months, and thus came to me with both <lb/>Eyes covered
          over, unable to do any <lb/>Thing. He had a Brother a Surgeon, <lb/>whoſe Endeavours with
          the Hoſpital Sur- <lb/>geons proving ineffectual, he came to <lb/>me. I have reſtored his
          Sight ſo well <lb/>that he kept a Writing School ſince, and <lb/>afterwards went a
          Privateering, and told <lb/>me himſelf that he was quite well, and <lb/>had not the leaſt
          Scropholous Complaint, <lb/>and was two or three Days at my Houſe <lb/>after his Cure. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>ANN NUNN, Daughter of John <lb/>Nunn, Farmer, of Laindon Hills in Eſ- <pb
            xml:id="page_49" n="45"/>
          <lb/>ſex, aged 21 Years, had a large Scro- <lb/>pholous Tumor on the right Side of the
          <lb/>Jawbone, opened by Mr. Earl of Horn- <lb/>don, but as he could not heal it up, ſhe
          <lb/>came to me; I perfected the Cure, and <lb/>ſhe was well, at Service, when I heard
          <lb/>of her ſome time after. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I was deſired to ſee a young Gentle- <lb/>man in London, aged 26 Years, about <lb/>a
          Year after he had fell down on both his <lb/>Knees, a white lymphatick Swelling had
          <lb/>been increaſing on his right Knee, not- <lb/>withſtanding the following Means had
          <lb/>been uſed, as he himſelf told me; firſt <lb/>the Knee was treated as a common Bruiſe,
          <lb/>and rub'd with Oils, to no Effect; after- <lb/>wards poulticed with white Bread and
          <lb/>Milk, Lees of Beer near a Month, with- <lb/>out Advantage; then fomented with an
          <lb/>Infuſion of Camomile, to no Purpoſe; <lb/>then a Bliſter, (run but little) no
          Benefit; <lb/>then Leeches applied twice, ſix at a Time, <lb/>ſignified nothing; was at
          Bath, after- <lb/>wards at Southampton, and uſed the uſual <lb/>Methods at both Places,
          and all theſe <lb/>Trials had no Effect on the Swelling. <lb/>He had alſo a ſmall
          Scropholous Tumor, <pb xml:id="page_50" n="46"/>
          <lb/>red and inflamed, on the Point of the <lb/>Breaſt-bone. Some Months after he had
          <lb/>been under my Care, he wrote me as fol- <lb/>lows: I am ſure all the Pleaſure I enjoy
          <lb/>this Summer is totally to be attributed to <lb/>your Kindneſs; for had I not been ſo
          happy <lb/>as to have been under your Direction, <lb/>moſt likely I ſhould not have gained
          the <lb/>Uſe of my Limbs ſo ſoon, if ever, which <lb/>lays an everlaſting Obligation on
          your <lb/>very humble Servant. And afterwards, <lb/>in another Letter, he ſays, I am ſur-
          <lb/>prizingly recovered in regard to my Knee. <lb/>Theſe, I hope, will ſatisfy any
          reaſonable <lb/>Perſon of the Benefit this Gentleman re- <lb/>ceived by my Means. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <lb/>
        <dateline rend="hanging">Great Stambridge, near Rochford in <hi rend="italic">Es-
            <lb/>ſex,</hi> October 5, 1762. </dateline>
        <lb/>
        <salute>Mr. Morley, Sir, </salute>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I JOSEPH LAMBERT return you <lb/>kind Thanks for curing my Daughter Ann <lb/>Lambert
          of the King's Evil. She is as <lb/>well as ever. Sir, I can but love and <lb/>thank you
          for your Civility. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This little Girl was ſix Years old, had <lb/>her upper Lip very much ſwelled three
            <pb xml:id="page_51" n="47"/>
          <lb/>Quarters of a Year. Mr. Swain, an Apo- <lb/>thecary at Rochford, judged it Scropho-
          <lb/>lous. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The following Letter I received July <lb/>the 17th, 1762, from PHILIP SHELLY,
          <lb/>Weaver at Clove Clare in Suffolk. </p>
        <lb/>
      </div>
      <div>
        <salute>Mr. Morley, Sir, </salute>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I ſend to you, returning many humble <lb/>and hearty Thanks for the great Benefits
          <lb/>I have received by you, being at your <lb/>Houſe, May the 28, 1762, having the
          <lb/>Evil in my Eyes, and not able to bear <lb/>the Light in the Houſe, and by your
          <lb/>Help and God's Mercy, is able to work <lb/>abroad; Thanks be to God and you for
          <lb/>it; I being a poor Man, am not able to make <lb/>you any other Amends. If I was, I
          <lb/>ſhould not think any Thing too much for <lb/>you, for the great Benefits I have
          receiv- <lb/>ed by you; but I hope you will accept <lb/>the ſame as if I ſent you a
          Preſent, ſo I <lb/>remain your humble Servant, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Philip Shelly.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I give the Reader his Letter verbatim, <lb/>as I do all others that I quote. This
          <lb/>Man's Eyes had been much diſorder'd ſix <pb xml:id="page_52" n="48"/>
          <lb/>Months, run hot ſcalding Water, and <lb/>much white Matter from the Corner of
          <lb/>his left Eye, and his upper Lip ſwelled. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>SUSANNA SPOWERS, Wife of <lb/>Martin Spowers, Mariner, aged 26, lately <lb/>living at
          Mr. Vines's near Sir William <lb/>Warron's Square in Wapping, London, <lb/>had a large
          Tumor, very hard and livid, <lb/>on the lower Part of the left Breaſt next <lb/>the Arm,
          which had been extirpated by <lb/>Mr. Caywood, Surgeon and Apothecary, <lb/>near by,
          judged to be a Cancer; but as <lb/>he did not cure it, about a Month after, <lb/>ſhe came
          to me. Then the whole Breaſt <lb/>was inflamed, with two more Tumors <lb/>riſing on the
          lower Part, and ſome ſmall <lb/>Scropholous Complaints running about. <lb/>Theſe Tumors
          afterwards broke, and diſ- <lb/>charged Matter as the other, which are <lb/>all now well;
          and one other large Tu- <lb/>mor, about the Middle of the Breaſt, I <lb/>diſperſed without
          breaking. The whole <lb/>Breaſt is now quite firm and well, <lb/>ſmooth, ſoft, and of its
          natural Colour <lb/>and Size, as before, except the Sear, <lb/>which ſtill remains as a
          Proof the Sur- <lb/>geon had been there. Whilſt in the <pb xml:id="page_53" n="49"/>
          <lb/>Country under my Care, the Surgeon let <lb/>her know, ſhe had better come to Lon-
          <lb/>don, and he would go with her to an <lb/>Hoſpital, to have her Breaſt taken off,
          <lb/>before the Cancer ſhould be fixt, for then <lb/>it would be incurable. Note; Many
          ſcro- <lb/>phulated Breaſts are miſtaken for Can- <lb/>cers, and have been treated as
          ſuch, to <lb/>the irreparable Damage of the poor Suf- <lb/>ferers. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A young Lady in London, at the Age <lb/>of 4 Years, had two Scrophulous Ulcers,
          <lb/>on each Arm one, both dried up by the <lb/>Uſe of the Bark, by Order of one of
          <lb/>the principal Phyſicians in London; but <lb/>ſoon after the Diſorder broke out, with
          a <lb/>deep Ulcer on the Calf of each Leg. <lb/>Then I was applied to, and healed them
          <lb/>up, but ſoon after neglecting my Direc- <lb/>tions, the Humor fell into both Eyes;
          <lb/>then I was again applied to, and remov- <lb/>ed that Diſorder; and ſhe is now free
          <lb/>from any Scrophulous Complaints what- <lb/>ever. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Mr. John Joſeph, Surgeon at Whit- <lb/>ham in Eſſex, recommended to my Care <pb
            xml:id="page_54" n="50"/>
          <lb/>Suſanna Milbanks, aged 18 Years, for <lb/>the King's Evil. She had ſix or ſeven
          <lb/>Tumors opened by him, and healed, and <lb/>kept well ſix Months: then the Diſorder
          <lb/>fell into both her Eyes. Her right Eye <lb/>had been burnt when a Child very much,
          <lb/>ſo will never be otherwiſe, the left Eye <lb/>perfectly clear and well, and all her
          Sores <lb/>perfectly well and ſound, and herſelf in <lb/>good Health. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>JOHN BUTCHER, of the Pariſh <lb/>of Booking in Eſſex, Bayweaver, aged <lb/>30 Years,
          came to me from Bugden in <lb/>Huntingtonſhire, being quartered there, <lb/>and belonging
          to Captain Carter's Com- <lb/>pany of the Eſſex Militia. He firſt felt <lb/>a daſhing Pain
          ſuddenly ſtrike into the <lb/>lower Joint of the Forefinger of his <lb/>right Hand, and in
          about a Month all <lb/>the other Fingers and Thumb were af- <lb/>fected in the ſame
          Manner, and ſo con- <lb/>tracted, that he could not ſtir them even <lb/>with the other
          Hand, without great Pain, <lb/>and then but very little. No Diſcolo- <lb/>ration, or any
          perceivable Tumor, or pre- <lb/>ternatural Heat to the Touch of himſelf, <lb/>or others.
          His Captain who was a Sur- <lb/>geon, and knowing ſeveral of his Rela- <pb
            xml:id="page_55" n="51"/>
          <lb/>tions were greatly afflicted with the King's <lb/>Evil, pronounced it ſuch; he ſoon
          after <lb/>was diſcharged as uncapable of Service. <lb/>I reſtored this Man to the full
          Uſe of his <lb/>Hand, Fingers and Thumb, by the <lb/>Means I make uſe of in Scrophulous
          Caſes; <lb/>which I think is a Proof this was a Species <lb/>of the King's Evil. He was
          afterwards <lb/>again admitted as a Militia Man in Cap- <lb/>tain Mayhews Company, being
          perfectly <lb/>well, having the Uſe of his Hand as for- <lb/>merly. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>ELIZ. REYNOLD, Wife of Jo. <lb/>Reynold of Halſted, Farmer, aged 25 <lb/>Years, came
          with her Lips much ſwoln, <lb/>the Inſide of the Noſe and upper Lip <lb/>broke out, and
          very ſcabby, a large con- <lb/>glomerated Tumor being increaſing three <lb/>Quarters of a
          Year, under the right Ear, <lb/>and ſeveral ſmall Tumors on the left Side <lb/>the Neck.
          She told me ſome Months <lb/>after, that all the Swellings were entirely <lb/>gone, her
          Health never better, and not <lb/>the leaſt Complaint. Note; I diſperſed all <lb/>the
          Tumors, ſo that no viſible Signs re- <lb/>main to ſhow ſhe ever had the King's <lb/>Evil. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_56" n="52"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>MARY COOK, Wife of Ed. Cook, <lb/>Husbandman of Coln Earls in Eſſex, <lb/>aged 27
          Years. Ten Years before ſhe <lb/>came to me, a large Stick fell on the <lb/>Middle of the
          Outſide of her right Thigh, <lb/>and bruiſed it much, and was very pain- <lb/>ful at times
          for five Years; then a large <lb/>Swelling aroſe where 'twas bruiſed, broke <lb/>and run
          above a Quart of white Matter, <lb/>and now diſcharges chiefly Water, ſcald- <lb/>ing and
          corroſive. The Orifice ſmall as <lb/>a Pea, the Diſcharge very great, and a <lb/>Surgeon
          having probed the Ulcer and <lb/>found it very hollow, ſeveral Inches both <lb/>above and
          below the Orifice. About four <lb/>Months after, her Husband came and <lb/>told me, his
          Wife was twenty Pound bet- <lb/>ter, and ſome Months after that her Mo- <lb/>ther came and
          told me, ſhe was quite <lb/>well. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>MARY PRENTICE, Daughter of <lb/>Abraham Prentice, Jun. of Coln Engain, <lb/>aged a
          Year and a half, had a Tumor un- <lb/>der the left Ear, and ſeveral ſmall Swell- <lb/>ings
          ariſing in divers Parts, inherited this <lb/>Scrophulous Diſorder from her Father's
          <lb/>Family, who came to thank and tell me, <lb/>the Child was quite cured. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_57" n="53"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>BENJ. REED of Gosfeild in Eſſex, <lb/>Husbandman, aged 35, recommended <lb/>by Mr.
          Maniſtree, Apothecary, both his <lb/>Eyes much inflamed, and diſcharged ſome <lb/>very
          ſcalding Water, and was ſo blind he <lb/>had not ſeen the Sun or any Object for <lb/>two
          Months before he came to me, and <lb/>had a ſmall Tumor under his left Ear, <lb/>and is
          now well by my Remedies. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>JOHN DRINKMILK, Son of Adam <lb/>Drinkmilk of Barrow in Suffolk, Farmer, <lb/>aged 24
          Years, had about a Year ago a <lb/>large Swelling under the left Arm diſperſ- <lb/>ed by a
          Surgeon, and afterwards the Hu- <lb/>mor fell into the left Wriſt and Hand, <lb/>which
          were much ſwelled, and growing <lb/>uſeleſs. His Father had the King's Evil <lb/>help'd
          thirty Years ago, and now I have <lb/>removed the Son's Complaints. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>WILL. ARDLEY, Weaver of Cog- <lb/>geſhall in Eſſex, aged 40 Years, had been <lb/>much
          troubled with the Tooth-ach and <lb/>Ear-ach; then a Sore broke Withinſide the <lb/>left
          Cheek, and diſcharged near a Pint of <lb/>ſtinking Matter at ſeveral times; then a large
          <lb/>Tumor aroſe on the left under Jaw-bone, <lb/>and broke into three Ulcers, and
          diſcharged <lb/>much Matter; then the Ulcer within the <pb xml:id="page_58" n="54"/>
          <lb/>Mouth healed up, and it was with ſome <lb/>Difficulty he could open his Mouth. All
          <lb/>theſe running Sores I quite cured in about <lb/>five Months, with the perfect Uſe of
          his <lb/>Jaw-bones, and has no Complaints what- <lb/>ever remaining, and came to thank me
          <lb/>for the Cure. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>SARAH ROWLAND, of Wickham <lb/>Brooke in Suffolk, aged 18 Years, had a <lb/>very
          large ſoft Tumor under the right <lb/>Ear, been four Months increaſing, and
          <lb/>pronounced ſcrophulous by Mr. Dun- <lb/>thorne Surgeon of Lidgate in Suffolk,
          <lb/>ſome of her Family having had the King's <lb/>Evil; ſhe is now well by my Means. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>ANN BAKER, of Braintree in Eſ- <lb/>ſex, Widow, aged 45 Years, recom- <lb/>mended by
          the Rev. Mr. Morgan the Vi- <lb/>car. She had ſeveral Holes in her Toes, <lb/>with an
          Appearance like the St. Anthony <lb/>Fire, on both Arms, Neck, Breaſt and <lb/>Face, and
          very hot, and many ſmall <lb/>Water-bladers and running Pains about <lb/>her Joints, and
          ſome ſmall Swellings about <lb/>the Neck and Throat, but none broke; <lb/>ſeveral of her
          Relations had the King's <lb/>Evil. She came to thank me ſometime <lb/>after, being quite
          well. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_59" n="55"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A little Miſs in London, aged 5 Years, <lb/>had a troubleſome Scurfineſs on her Head,
          <lb/>which made it very difficult to be kept <lb/>clean, and ſmall Eruptions often appear-
          <lb/>ing and diſappearing on divers Parts, <lb/>leaving a dry Scurf, and many ſmall Tu-
          <lb/>mors like Peas about the Neck. She is <lb/>now very well by my Directions. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>WILL. FIELD, Serjeant in the 109th <lb/>Company of Marines, belongs to Chat- <lb/>ham
          in Kent, aged 23 Years; he came <lb/>to me with a Tumor riſing under each <lb/>lower
          Jaw-bone. He is now well; and <lb/>brought his Wife afterwards, with a bad
          <lb/>Scropholous Complaint; but are both <lb/>gone from my Neighbourhood, ſo I can
          <lb/>ſay nothing as to her. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A Lady in Norfolk, about 25, had a <lb/>large Scrophulous Ulcer near the left
          <lb/>Ancle, and pricking daſhing Pains in her <lb/>Joints. When I firſt ſaw her, ſhe
          bathed <lb/>daily in the Salt-water, which had ſo <lb/>ſwelled and inflamed her Leg, ſhe
          could <lb/>hardly ſtand. I begg'd her to leave off <lb/>Bathing, which ſhe did, and in
          forty- <lb/>eight Hours ſhe found Eaſe; and in ſome <lb/>Months after I had a Letter from
          her, <pb xml:id="page_60" n="56"/>
          <lb/>that her Complaints were by my Direc- <lb/>tions entirely removed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A young Lady in Norfolk, aged 12 Years, <lb/>about three Years ago had a ſmall
          <lb/>hard Tumor under the left Nipple, which <lb/>ſeems now no more; but when ſhe came
          <lb/>to me, had a ſmooth, flatiſh, ſoft Tumor <lb/>about the Bigneſs of half a Crown, ga-
          <lb/>thering above the Nipple of the ſame Breaſt, <lb/>which had been under the Management
          <lb/>of a regular Phyſician ſometime without <lb/>any apparent Advantage; but is now by
          <lb/>my Aſſiſtance entirely removed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Mrs. BROWN, Wife of Mr. Brown <lb/>at the Bell in Clare Suffolk, aged 27 Years,
          <lb/>brought me the following from Mr. <lb/>Hawes a Surgeon. </p>
        <lb/>
      </div>
      <div>
        <salute>SIR, </salute>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Mrs. Brown, the Bearer hereof, hath <lb/>for ſome Months laboured under a Diſeaſe
          <lb/>in her Breaſt, which the Surgeons term a <lb/>Schirrhus. Various Applications hath
          been <lb/>tried, and many Medicines taken, which <lb/>have only ſerved to alleviate her
          Com- <lb/>plaints, without laying a Foundation for <lb/>healing. This Diſeaſe hath ſo near
          an <lb/>Affinity with the Evil, that I do not think <lb/>but it may be really called ſuch.
          I <pb xml:id="page_61" n="57"/>
          <lb/>wiſh you may be ſo fortunate as to direct <lb/>ſomewhat that may be ſerviceable, and
          am, </p>
        <lb/>
        <salute>SIR, </salute>
        <signed rend="indent hanging">
          <lb/>Your humble Servant, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Rich. Hawes.</hi>
        </signed>
        <lb/>
        <dateline>Cavendiſh, <lb/>Aug. 23, 1761. </dateline>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Mrs. Brown was a fat luſty Woman: <lb/>About a Year ago had a large Tumor roſe
          <lb/>in her right Breaſt, and gathered in nine <lb/>ſeveral Places, and opened by a Sur-
          <lb/>geon, and diſcharged much, but that be- <lb/>ing though inſufficient to leſſen the
          Breaſt, <lb/>two Setons were made quite thro' the <lb/>Breaſt, (which was very large)
          cloſe to <lb/>the Ribs, in the Form of a Croſs, and <lb/>as the Silk rotted out, in ten or
          twelve <lb/>Days, more Silk was put in, and ſhe had <lb/>ſeven or eight Ulcers in other
          Parts of the <lb/>Breaſt. Several Surgeons met, to take off <lb/>the Breaſt, and told her
          if it was not <lb/>taken off ſhe could not live to Michaelmas <lb/>Day following; that her
          Breaſt would rot <lb/>off in a Week or two, if not cut off. This <lb/>was the State of the
          Breaſt when I under- <lb/>took it. November the 30th following, <lb/>I ſaw this Woman; all
          the Ulcers well <lb/>healed, and the Breaſt firm, and the Wo- <lb/>man in good Health a
          Spirits, without <lb/>any Complaints whatever. Feb. 27, 1762, <pb xml:id="page_62" n="58"/>
          <lb/>ſhe was with me again, and ſhow'd me her <lb/>right Breaſt ſound and firm, but told
          me that <lb/>about three Weeks before, on taking Cold, <lb/>ſhe felt a daſhing Pain in her
          left Breaſt, <lb/>which ſhe ſhewed me. There was a ſmooth <lb/>ſoft Tumor riſing on the
          upper Part, above <lb/>the Nipple, which had encreaſed faſt, with <lb/>ſome daſhing Pains.
          I ordered her proper <lb/>Remedies for this new Complaint. April <lb/>the 4th, her Husband
          came to tell me the <lb/>Tumor was broke, and diſcharged in ſeve- <lb/>ral Places round
          the Nipple. I ordered ac- <lb/>cordingly, and Sept. the 6th, 1762, her <lb/>Husband came
          again and told me her <lb/>Breaſt had been quite well 2 Months paſt, <lb/>and his Wife in
          good Health a Spirits, <lb/>no Complaint at all, and that the Day be- <lb/>fore he came
          ſhe was brought to-bed of a <lb/>fine Girl, and both like to do very well. <lb/>I ſaw her
          ſome Days after, examined her <lb/>right Breaſt, which had loſt the Nipple, all
          <lb/>continued firm, and alſo her left Breaſt, <lb/>but ſhe had no Milk in it, but no Com-
          <lb/>plaint whatever. Note, it is very eaſy to <lb/>obſerve from this Caſe that if Mrs.
          Brown's <lb/>right Breaſt had been taken off, it would <lb/>have avail'd nothing, from the
          other being <lb/>diſordered in the like Manner. After hav- <lb/>ing cured Mrs. Brown's
          right Breaſt, I re- <pb xml:id="page_63" n="59"/>
          <lb/>ceived from the before-mentioned Mr. <lb/>Hawes the following. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <lb/>
        <salute>SIR, </salute>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I muſt now congratulate your Succeſs <lb/>in curing this Diſeaſe, which is more rife
          <lb/>by far than uſed to be, and likely to make <lb/>ſad Ravages among Mankind. Mrs. Brown
          <lb/>I hear is purely. I am, </p>
        <lb/>
        <salute>Worthy Sir, </salute>
        <signed rend="indent hanging">
          <lb/>Your moſt obedient humble Servant, <lb/><hi rend="italic">R. Hawes.</hi>
        </signed>
        <lb/>
        <dateline>Cavendiſh, <lb/>Nov. 26, 1761. </dateline>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Febr. The 17th, 1763, her Husband <lb/>came to my Houſe, told me his Wife was <lb/>in
          all reſpects perfectly well, and his little <lb/>Girl a fine thrifty Child. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A young Woman unmarried, aged 26, <lb/>had a large Tumor on the left Buttock,
          <lb/>had been opened four times by a Surgeon, <lb/>at leaſt ſix Inches in Length, who told
          <lb/>her he durſt not cut any more, but muſt <lb/>apply Cauſticks. She had two ſmall Ul-
          <lb/>cers on the Small of her Back, and her <lb/>Eyes greatly inflamed. The Buttock
          <lb/>ſeemed almoſt divided into two. About <lb/>eight Months after, this young Woman
          <lb/>came to thank me, being well, without <lb/>any Remains of her Diſorder, and uſed <pb
            xml:id="page_64" n="60"/>
          <lb/>no other Means for her Recovery than I <lb/>had directed. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <lb/>
        <salute>To Mr. Morley, </salute>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>SIR, I ſend you a Man from Bradfield <lb/>Mainger, afflicted with the running Evil,
          <lb/>owing in my Opinion to the ill Manage- <lb/>ment of the Apothecary, when ill with
          <lb/>the Fever; if you can poſſibly aſſiſt him, <lb/>hope your good Endeavours will not be
          <lb/>wanting, from yours, &amp;c. R. R. Cox, a <lb/>Surgeon at Great Welnetham, Suffolk. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This Man was Rob. London, Son of Rob. <lb/>London of Bradfield in Suffolk, aged 32
          <lb/>Years. About twelve Weeks after hav- <lb/>ing had this Fever, thirteen Tumors roſe
          <lb/>about the Legs, Thighs and Buttocks, and <lb/>had been all opened by Mr. Cox, and had
          <lb/>diſcharged monſtrouſly, which had re- <lb/>duced him to a meer Skeleton: he was
          <lb/>brought to me in a Cart with a Bed made <lb/>in it, being unable to move Hand or
          Foot, <lb/>or to be moved without great Trouble. <lb/>I went out to ſee this poor Man in
          the <lb/>Cart: he looked ſo like a dead Corps, that <lb/>People that ſaw him ſet out from
          home <lb/>never expected to ſee him return alive, <lb/>his Stomach gone, and Viſage ſo
          ghaſtly. <lb/>This was Aug. 31, 1761: and Sept. the <lb/>10th, I received the following
          from Mr. <lb/>Cox the Surgeon. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_65" n="61"/>
        <lb/>
        <salute>SIR, </salute>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>According to your Orders, have made <lb/>uſe of the Medicines, but have ſince
          <lb/>been obliged to open three more Abſceſ- <lb/>ſes, from which found a Sanguinous
          <lb/>Matter, filled with a corrupted, from <lb/>each Sore a large Quantity. Think the
          <lb/>others begin to heal, excepting two, which <lb/>are in the Calf, the other in the
          muſcu- <lb/>lar Part of the Thigh: the Stomach holds <lb/>well, and cannot find by the
          Face and <lb/>Pulſe, he is ſo much exhauſted, as Na- <lb/>ture would be thought to be
          under his Af- <lb/>flictions. The 23d of October following, <lb/>Mr. Cox wrote me Word my
          Patient at <lb/>Bradfeild was well, and in October 1762, <lb/>I ſaw his Father, who told
          me his Son <lb/>held well, and went to London every <lb/>Week with Carrier's Waggon from
          Bury <lb/>in Suffolk. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Mr. HARRISON, Apothecary, ſent <lb/>me Suſan Ottley of Bocking in Eſſex, <lb/>ſingle
          Woman, aged 26 Years. She came <lb/>to me with almoſt numberleſs Ul- <lb/>cers, and
          fungous Excreſcencies, extended <lb/>from the Top of the right Shoulder, <lb/>quite down
          to the Nipple of her right <lb/>Breaſt, which diſcharged a moſt foul and <pb
            xml:id="page_66" n="62"/>
          <lb/>ſtinking Matter. She had an Ulcer on the In- <lb/>ſide the Arm, cloſe to her Arm-pit,
          and a <lb/>deep one on the Shoulder almoſt by her <lb/>Arm-pit, and one withinſide the
          Arm, a- <lb/>bout 3 Inches above the Elbow, and one <lb/>almoſt under the right Buttock, a
          bad <lb/>Stomach, and very had State of Health; <lb/>had the Evil hereditarily, having a
          Siſter <lb/>died of it, and another Siſter who had it <lb/>much in her Eyes, which I
          cured. This <lb/>Woman has now all her Ulcers entirely <lb/>well, the fungous Excreſcences
          all healed <lb/>up, ſmooth and ſound, has recovered a <lb/>good Stomach, a florid
          well-looking Coun- <lb/>tenance, and perfect good State of Health, <lb/>by my Endeavours
          only; but this Subject <lb/>was many Months under my Care, ſo that <lb/>I uſually ſaw her
          every eight or ten Days, <lb/>or I could have been of little Service in <lb/>ſuch a bad
          Caſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>MARY BINGHAM, Wife of Adam <lb/>Bingham, Husbandman, late of Craſſing, <lb/>now
          living at Patiſwick in Eſſex, aged <lb/>28 Years, was led to me, being totally
          <lb/>deprived of her Sight. She told me ſhe <lb/>had not ſeen her Hand or Child for 12
          <lb/>Months paſt. Both her Eyes looked al- <lb/>moſt as covered over with Cobwebs of a <pb
            xml:id="page_67" n="63"/>
          <lb/>leaden dead Colour, run much ſcalding <lb/>Water, mixt with thick white Matter
          <lb/>from the Corners of her Eyes, and almoſt <lb/>continually daſhing Pains about her
          Fore- <lb/>head, and many Scrophulous Breakings <lb/>out, about the Corners of her Mouth,
          <lb/>and ſeveral other Places. I bleſs God, I <lb/>have reſtored this poor Woman to her
          <lb/>Sight, ſo well as to dreſs her Children, <lb/>and ſpin, which ſhe does for her
          Liveli- <lb/>hood daily, as ſhe did before ſhe was diſ- <lb/>eaſed. </p>

        <trailer rend="align-center">
          <lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
