<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Home: An inquiry into the nature, cause, and cure of the croup</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Francis Home</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">An INQUIRY into the Nature, Cause, and Cure of the CROUP.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T9373</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T9373"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: printed for A. Kincaid and J. Bell, MDCC,LXV. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1765</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="60"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3307242095</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K024534.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: midwifery"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front> </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
      <head rend="align-center"><lb/>AN <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">INQUIRY</hi>
        <lb/>INTO THE <lb/><hi rend="sc">Nature, Cause</hi>, and <hi rend="sc">Cure</hi>
        <lb/>OF THE <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">CROUP.</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">angina membranacea</hi></head>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HE Science of Medicine has been, <lb/>gradually,
        advancing for theſe two <lb/>thouſand years by paſt; and is now <lb/>brought to a great
        degree of <w part="I">improve-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w>; perhaps to as great a degree,
        every <lb/>circumſtance conſidered, as the difficulty of <lb/>the art, the limitation of the
        human <w part="I">facul-</w><lb/><w part="F">ties</w>, and the continual attempts to further
        <lb/>refinement, too often conducted merely by <lb/>fancy, will admit of. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">One</hi> uſed to conſider the progreſs of the
        <lb/>different arts, their gradual advancement to <lb/>perfection, and their ſubſequent
        decay, may <pb xml:id="page_3" n="4"/><lb/>be apt to contemplate, with ſome alarm, the
        <lb/>preſent ſituation of phyſic. More attention <lb/>is paid to the claſſing of diſeaſes,
        as if they <lb/>were natural and permanent entities, than <lb/>to the complete hiſtory of
        each particular <lb/>one; more to the ſub-diviſion and ſplitting <lb/>of them into ſeparate
        ſpecies, from ſome <lb/>ſlight difference in the ſymptoms, than to <lb/>the general turn and
        complexion of the <lb/>whole diſeaſe; more to the novelty and <lb/>change of application,
        than to the <w part="I">improve-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w> of what is already diſcovered
        and in <lb/>uſe. Theſe, a ſpeculative mind will be apt <lb/>to conſider as proofs of too
        great <w part="I">refine-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w>, and diſtant marks of a future
        change. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is by a cloſe attention to the hiſtory <lb/>of
        particular diſeaſes, that the ſcience has <lb/>made ſuch great advances. The accuracy of
        <lb/>ancient and modern authors hath left few <lb/>diſeaſes untouched. By deſcribing every
        <lb/>circumſtance belonging to them, and the <lb/>appearances, which occurred, on inſpecting
        <lb/>the bodies after death, they have <w part="I">aſcertain-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>
        moſt diſeaſes, and laid a foundation for <lb/>arriving at as certain a knowledge of the <pb
          xml:id="page_4" n="5"/><lb/>reſt, as the narrow limits of our powers will <lb/>allow. For
        caſes in medicine are the <w part="I">expe-</w><lb/><w part="F">riments</w> of this branch
        of Natural <w part="I">Philoſo-</w><lb/><w part="F">phy</w>. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">There</hi> is one diſeaſe, however, which <lb/>had
        entirely eſcaped all regular <w part="I">examina-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>; and
        concerning which, there was <w part="I">lit-</w><lb/><w part="F">tle</w> to be learned by
        inquiry, and ſtill leſs <lb/>from books; I mean the <hi rend="sc">Croup</hi>. I never
        <lb/>have ſeen any thing written on this ſubject, <lb/>except a Theſis, where the author
        gives us <lb/>no facts; and claſſes it amongſt the ſpaſmodic <lb/>diſtempers, to which it
        has no reſemblance, <lb/>either in its progreſs or cure. The <hi rend="italic">Catarrhus
          <lb/>ſuffocativus</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Etmuller,</hi> tho' it reſembles the
        <lb/>Croup in many particulars, yet appears to be <lb/>a very different diſeaſe in ſome
        ſymptoms, <lb/>in the cure, and appearances after death. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Dr</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">Ruſſel,</hi> in his Oeconomy of Nature, <lb/>deſcribes, in a few lines, a
        diſeaſe very ſimilar <lb/>to this, in moſt of its ſymptoms: But it ſeems <lb/>not exactly
        the ſame, as it was attended with <lb/>ulcers about the larynx, and terminated <w part="I"
          >of-</w><lb/><w part="F">ten</w> in a ſphacelus of the lungs. Beſides, <pb xml:id="page_5"
          n="6"/><lb/>had it been the ſame diſeaſe with our Croup, <lb/>the ſame appearances muſt
        have occurred, <lb/>upon diſſection, to him as to us. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I <hi rend="sc">shall</hi>, therefore, treat this diſeaſe <lb/>as
        entirely unknown as to its nature, cauſe, <lb/>effects, and cure; and try how far our facts
        <lb/>will carry us towards a diſcovery of theſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>How ſo ſingular and dangerous a diſeaſe <lb/>has been totally neglected,
        while ſuch <w part="I">atten-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> has been paid to moſt others, is
        not the <lb/>leaſt ſurpriſing circumſtance belonging to it. <lb/>Its external features ought
        to have been <w part="I">ſuf-</w><lb/><w part="F">ficient</w> to have rouſed an inquiſitive
        ſearcher <lb/>into diſeaſes; its internal appearances, if but <lb/>once ſeen, muſt have
        raiſed, from their <w part="I">ſin-</w><lb/><w part="F">gularity</w>, the ſtrongeſt deſire
        to inveſtigate <lb/>its nature. But theſe ſeem to have been more <lb/>than counterbalanced
        by its local ſituation; <lb/>the unfrequency of its appearance; the <w part="I"
          >ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F">jects</w> which it attacked, theſe being <w part="I"
          >general-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> children, and unable to give a diſtinct <w part="I"
          >ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">count</w> of their complaints; the rapidity of <lb/>its courſe;
        the apparent eaſineſs of its <w part="I">ſymp-</w><lb/><w part="F">toms</w>; and their
        ſimilitude to other catarrhal <pb xml:id="page_6" n="7"/><lb/>or peripneumoniac diſtempers.
        Theſe ſeem <lb/>to be ſufficient reaſons for its being ſo long <lb/>undiſtinguiſhed and
        undeſcribed, without <lb/>laying us under any neceſſity of looking on <lb/>it as a new
        diſeaſe. Probably it has exiſted <lb/>more or leſs in all ages; for the ſame <w part="I"
          >pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">ductive</w> cauſes muſt have operated formerly, <lb/>as they do
        at preſent. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> diſeaſe happens, or at leaſt is <w part="I"
          >ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerved</w>, ſo ſeldom in this city, that very few <lb/>caſes muſt
        occur to any particular perſon, <lb/>during the courſe of a whole lifetime. To <lb/>have the
        power of ſeeing more, one muſt put <lb/>himſelf in the way of intelligence, eſpecially
        <lb/>at places ſituated on the coaſt. By that <lb/>means, I have had an opportunity of
        attending <lb/>more caſes, than otherwiſe would have fallen <lb/>to the ſhare of any one.
        The danger of the <lb/>ſymptoms under ſuch apparent eaſe, and the <lb/>ſingularity of its
        appearances after death, in <lb/>the firſt examination, excited my curioſity. <lb/>The
        ſubſequent caſes were ſufficient to ſhow <lb/>me its nature, tho' perhaps not to point out
        <lb/>a certain cure. That is not always allowed <lb/>to mortals. To be able, however, to <w
          part="I">diſtin-</w><pb xml:id="page_7" n="8"/><lb/><w part="F">guiſh</w> it from other
        diſeaſes; to diſcover the <lb/>nature of it; to point out when it is cureable, <lb/>and when
        not; perhaps to lay a foundation <lb/>for improvement in its moſt deſperate ſtate; <lb/>that
        is the deſign of the following pages. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>To be the firſt author in treating a diſeaſe; <lb/>to have no aſſiſtance
        from preceding <w part="I">experi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ence</w>, is a ſituation a little
        uncommon in theſe <lb/>modern times. To this cauſe, and to the <lb/>rarity of the diſeaſe,
        muſt be imputed my <lb/>not bringing it to that degree of <w part="I">improve-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ment</w>, that I could wiſh; and that has <w part="I">hap-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >pened</w> in other diſeaſes. If this can ſerve <lb/>for a foundation to excite others to
        inquire, <lb/>to preſerve, and to communicate facts <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſerved</w> by them, my labour will be well <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F"
        >ſtowed</w>. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> diſeaſe appears to belong peculiarly <lb/>to
        children; and the younger they are, <w part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> they are
        weaned, the more liable they ſeem <lb/>to it. On the breaſt, they appear leſs <w part="I"
          >ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F">ject</w> to it; or, which is as probable, as they <lb/>cannot
        tell their complaints, it is taken for <lb/>ſome other diſeaſe. I never ſaw, or heard of
        <lb/>one, above twelve years of age, affected by <pb xml:id="page_8" n="9"/><lb/>it. After
        this the body gains a ſtrength <lb/>capable of reſiſting the cauſe, or of expelling <lb/>it
        when received. About this time, or a <w part="I">lit-</w><lb/><w part="F">tle</w> after,
        very great changes happen in the <lb/>human frame. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It ſeems, likewiſe, in a great meaſure, to <lb/>have a local ſituation;
        and to be very <w part="I">ſel-</w><lb/><w part="F">dom</w> found at any great diſtance from
        the <lb/>ſea-ſhore. It appears much leſs in <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh</hi>
        <lb/>than in <hi rend="italic">Leith,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Muſſelburgh.</hi> It is
        often <lb/>ſeen along the coaſt of <hi rend="italic">Fife;</hi> and is very <lb/>common, I
        am told, along the coaſt of <hi rend="italic">Air-<lb/>ſhire</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
          >Galloway.</hi> Tho' I never heard of <lb/>it in the neighbouring coaſt of <hi
          rend="italic">England,</hi> yet <lb/>probably it is to be found there too. The <lb/>ſame
        cauſes, that kept it from being ſo long <lb/>attended to here, may ſtill make it neglected
        <lb/>there. Very wet and marſhy ſituations, <lb/>ſometimes, produce it. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>IN the firſt hiſtory of a diſeaſe, it becomes <lb/>abſolutely neceſſary,
        to ſet down the caſes <lb/>and the facts, as they really happened. In <lb/>diſeaſes, that
        have already been deſcribed, it <lb/>is ſufficient to enumerate the ſymptoms, as <lb/>they
        generally appeared, by which the <w part="I">diffe-</w><lb/><w part="F">rence</w> betwixt
        that ſpecies, and any of the <pb xml:id="page_9" n="10"/><lb/>former, may be obſerved. But
        in a new <lb/>diſeaſe, as little ought to be left to the fancy <lb/>or judgment of the
        hiſtorian as poſſible; for, <lb/>from the natural appearance of the ſymptoms, <lb/>all our
        reaſoning and concluſions muſt take <lb/>their riſe. As caſes are analogous to the <w
          part="I">expe-</w><lb/><w part="F">riments</w> of Natural Philoſophy, they ought <lb/>to
        be deſcribed as circumſtantially. <hi rend="italic">Hippo-<lb/>crates,</hi> that great
        hiſtorian of diſeaſes, treats <lb/>his epidemics, as they were new diſtempers, <lb/>in this
        way. </p>
      <div n="1" type="case">
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE I. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">March</hi> 15th. Was called to Miss****, <lb/>aged
          fifteen months, of an inflammatory <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtitution</w>, and
          living within a quarter of a <lb/>mile of the ſea-ſhore. The day before, ſhe <lb/>had
          appeared duller and hotter than uſual. <lb/>This morning ſhe was attacked with a <w
            part="I">diffi-</w><lb/><w part="F">culty</w> of breathing. Her pulſe was ſtrong,
          <lb/>and about 135 in a minute; five ounces of <lb/>blood was immediately taken from her.
            <w part="I">Af-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> which, ſhe was ſeized with the ſharp <w
            part="I">ſtri-</w><lb/><w part="F">dolous</w> voice, which I can reſemble to <w part="I"
            >no-</w><lb/><w part="F">thing</w> more nearly than the crowing of a <pb
            xml:id="page_10" n="11"/><lb/>cock; and which is the true diagnoſtic ſign <lb/>of this
          diſeaſe. She had a quick and high <lb/>breathing, and unuſual heat in her <w part="I"
            >fore-</w><lb/><w part="F">head</w>, and palms of her hands. Her feet and <lb/>hands
          were ſwelled, and had an ædematous <lb/>appearance. As her pulſe was ſtill ſtrong, five
          <lb/>ounces of blood was again taken from her, <lb/>which ſeemed to eaſe her greatly. The
          <lb/>ſteams of warm water and vinegar made her <lb/>ſpit up, and did her ſervice. Her
          belly <lb/>was kept conſtantly looſe with <hi rend="italic">magneſia alba;</hi>
          <lb/>and that night a bliſter was applied round <lb/>her neck. On the third day, ſhe was a
            <w part="I">lit-</w><lb/><w part="F">tle</w> eaſier; but the voice ſtill remained
          ſhrill, <lb/>the breathing high, and pulſe ſtrong. At <lb/>night four leeches were applied
          to her throat; <lb/>and the orifices, conſtantly fomented with <lb/>warm water, continued
          blooding for four <lb/>hours. Next morning all the ſymptoms <lb/>went off. In this caſe,
          the repeated <w part="I">blood-</w><lb/><w part="F">ings</w>, eſpecially the local one,
          with internal <lb/>and external fomentation, did moſt <w part="I">remark-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">able</w> ſervice. I was not ſo certain about the <lb/>effects of the bliſter.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="case">
        <pb xml:id="page_11" n="12"/>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE II. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>MISS ******, aged eighteen months, <lb/>healthful, living near a great
          loch, and <w part="I">a-</w><lb/><w part="F">bout</w> a mile diſtant from the ſea, was
          ſeized, <lb/><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 30th, with the Croup. She had <w part="I"
            >im-</w><lb/><w part="F">mediately</w> loſt five ounces of blood by leeches, <lb/>and
          had got a vomit. Next morning, ſhe <lb/>had taken a ſecond vomit, after which I firſt
          <lb/>ſaw her. Her voice had the characteriſtical <lb/>ſhrillneſs, only, when ſhe raiſed
          it, or <w part="I">cough-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>. Her breathing was quick. Pulſe about
          <lb/>130. and rather weak. Dry, rough, ſhort <lb/>cough. She had no pain in ſwallowing,
          but <lb/>ſhowed uneaſineſs when ſhe turned about her <lb/>head. Urine clear, and without
          ſediment. <lb/>The ſteams of warm water and vinegar, and <lb/>a bliſter round the neck,
          were ordered. In <lb/>the evening ſhe was better, and her lungs <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">peared</w> ſomewhat moiſter. That night ſhe <lb/>reſted pretty well; and on the
          third day her <lb/>voice was natural, except when ſhe coughed. <lb/>She had a running at
          the noſe, and there was <lb/>a cloud in the urine. The vomit repeated. <lb/>On the fourth
          day, the voice was ſtill <w part="I">ſome-</w><pb xml:id="page_12" n="13"/><lb/><w
            part="F">what</w> unnatural. The urine now depoſited <lb/>a light ſediment, which laſted
          for three or <lb/>four days, during which ſhe gradually <w part="I">reco-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">vered</w>. She had the ſame diſeaſe again ſix <lb/>months after, but in a
          ſlighter manner. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="case">
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE III. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">A Child</hi> two years old, who had had <lb/>the ſmall
          pox ſix weeks before, had been <lb/>ſeized, Auguſt 8th, with the croupy voice.
          <lb/>Leeches had been applied, and bliſters <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">hind</w>
          the ears, and to the throat: On the <lb/>12th, I ſaw him, and ſound his <w part="I"
            >breath-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> bad, great ſtuffing, ſhrill voice, and a
          <lb/>ſwelling externally on the ſuperior part of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">trachea.</hi>
          Pulſe 140. Every thing <w part="I">look-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> ill. Steams, external
          fomentation, <w part="I">poul-</w><lb/><w part="F">tices</w>, and ſeveral leeches were
          applied to the <lb/>throat. 13th, the child greatly relieved, <lb/>more chearful, and
          voice more natural. <lb/>14th, pulſe much better, and the <w part="I"
            >peculiari-</w><lb/><w part="F">ty</w> of voice and the ſwelling almoſt gone. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I <hi rend="sc">need</hi> not relate more caſes of this <lb/>kind, as
          ſuch like commonly occur, and as <pb xml:id="page_13" n="14"/><lb/>they are ſufficient to
          prove its nature in this <lb/>ſituation. The only remark that I ſhall <lb/>make is, that
          the ſymptoms of theſe three <lb/>patients, and their cure, ſhow plainly the <lb/>Croup, in
          this ſtate, to be a diſeaſe of an <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">flammatory</w>
          nature, attacking the organs of <lb/>voice and reſpiration, particularly the <w part="I"
            >ſupe-</w><lb/><w part="F">rior</w> parts of the <hi rend="italic">trachea,</hi> and
          that the local <lb/>inflammation often ends by reſolution. This <lb/>diſeaſe appears to be
          confined chiefly to the <lb/><hi rend="italic">trachea,</hi> as the patients have no pain
          in <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">glutition</w>; as they generally complain, when
          <lb/>they are of an age to ſpeak, of a dull pain in <lb/>the upper part of it; as
          ſometimes an <lb/>external ſwelling is ſeen there; and as the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >fauces</hi> are at moſt but a little redder. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Let</hi> us now ſee what light other <w part="I"
            >ſitua-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w> of the diſeaſe, and inſpection into the
          <lb/>morbid body, will give us. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="case">
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE IV. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">September</hi> 29th, 1760, was called to <lb/>a boy of
          ſeven years of age, who had been <lb/>ſome days ſick. He lived on <hi rend="italic"
            >Leith</hi> bridge, had <pb xml:id="page_14" n="15"/><lb/>been ill of the chin-cough the
          preceeding <lb/>winter, and had recovered of the meaſles <w part="I">a-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">bout</w> ſix weeks before this. He had been <w part="I">fre-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">quently</w> purged, and had been tolerably well, <lb/>excepting a ſlight cough,
          till he was ſeized, <lb/>four days before I ſaw him, with fever, heat, <lb/>thirſt, and
          the ſhrill croupy voice. When I <lb/>ſaw him, his pulſe was quick, with a little
          <lb/>degree of hardneſs, but not ſtrong. He <w part="I">ſwal-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >lowed</w> eaſily; but complained of a pain in <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">trachea,</hi>
          when he ſpoke, or when I preſſed <lb/>it with my fingers. His face had been <w part="I"
            >ſwel-</w><lb/><w part="F">led</w>. Great drought. Breathing high, <lb/>but not very
          quick. He ſometimes <w part="I">expecto-</w><lb/><w part="F">rated</w>, and had often
          frothy <hi rend="italic">ſaliva</hi> upon his <lb/>lips. The urine had a white ouzy
          ſediment. <lb/>His ſenſes and his head were quite clear and <lb/>diſtinct. He was
          immediately blooded, and <lb/>at night had leeches applied to his throat, <lb/>and a
          bliſter round it. The next day his <lb/>pulſe was weaker, and beat 175 in a <w part="I"
            >mi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nute</w>. Breathing quicker, and often altered. <lb/>Diſtinct
          in all his ſenſes. Died that night. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_15" n="16"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">On</hi> laying open the parts, there was no <w part="I"
            >ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pearance</w> of any inflammation on the <hi rend="italic"
            >fauces.</hi>
          <lb/>But, to my great ſurpriſe, the whole ſuperior <lb/>internal ſurface of the <hi
            rend="italic">trachea</hi> was covered <lb/>with a white ſoft thick preternatural coat
          <lb/>or membrane, eaſily ſeparable from it, and <lb/>generally lying looſe upon it, and
          purulent <lb/>matter lodged below, and around it. The <lb/>ſubjacent parts were red; but
          no great <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">gree</w> of inflammation. As we ſearched
          <lb/>downwards, the ſame appearances continued <lb/>thro' the ramifications of the <hi
            rend="italic">aſpera arteria,</hi>
          <lb/>tho' the membrane ſeemed here ſofter, <w part="I">thin-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w>,
          and to become of a more purulent <w part="I">na-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w>. All the
          branches of the windpipe and <lb/><hi rend="italic">bronchiae</hi> were filled with
          purulent matter; <lb/>and we could eaſily ſqueeze it out, in great <lb/>plenty, from all
          theſe pipes. The ſubſtance <lb/>of the lungs was quite ſound, and in a <w part="I"
            >natu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ral</w> ſtate. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">These</hi> circumſtances appeared, at that <lb/>time, ſo
          new and ſurpriſing to me, that I <lb/>looked on them as accidental, and not the
          <lb/>natural effects of the diſeaſe. But I was ſoon <lb/>convinced of the contrary. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="5" type="case">
        <pb xml:id="page_16" n="17"/>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE V. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">October</hi> 5th. I <hi rend="sc">was</hi> called-to the
          laſt <lb/>boy's ſiſter, aged five years, who had been <lb/>obſerved, only the day before,
          to complain of <lb/>a dull pain in the throat. She had been <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">mediately</w> blooded, and had got a mixture of <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſpt.
            minder.</hi> and <hi rend="italic">theriac,</hi> with a bliſter to the <lb/>neck. She
          had been in a conſtant ſweat <lb/>ſince ſhe began to take the mixture. When <lb/>I ſaw her
          ſhe had the dry ſhrill voice, and <lb/>difficult breathing, with great motion of the
          <lb/>ribs and <hi rend="italic">ſcapulae.</hi> Her face was a little <w part="I"
            >ſwel-</w><lb/><w part="F">led</w> and red; deglutition eaſy. Her pulſe <lb/>was quick,
          and of a proper degree of ſtrength. <lb/>What ſhe expectorated ſeemed to be of a <w
            part="I">pu-</w><lb/><w part="F">rulent</w> nature. Her ſenſes were all in the <w
            part="I">na-</w><lb/><w part="F">tural</w> ſtate. Leeches were immediately <w part="I"
            >ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">plied</w> to her neck, and afterwards a warm <lb/>fomentation,
          and the ſteams of warm water <lb/>and vinegar: theſe appeared to give her ſome<lb/> eaſe.
          At night ſhe ſeemed worſe, and could <lb/>not ly long in one poſture. She was vomited
          <lb/>with the <hi rend="italic">ſyr. ſcillit.</hi> and threw up a great deal <lb/>of groſs
          ropy defluxion. I tryed her with a <pb xml:id="page_17" n="18"/><lb/>mixture of camphire
          and nitre. The next <lb/>day her pulſe was 152, and weaker. The <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >amygdalæ</hi> appeared a little ſwelled, and <w part="I">cover-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ed</w> with <hi rend="italic">mucus.</hi> She had a little difficulty <lb/>of
          deglutition. Frequent reachings. She <lb/>called often for drink, but drunk little at a
          <lb/>time. Tongue white and furred. <w part="I">Breath-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> rather
          quicker to-day, and often altered. <lb/>Eat ſome ſpoonfuls of panada and wine. <lb/>She
          was ordered an emollient injection, and <lb/>garlick cataplaſms to her feet. In the <w
            part="I">after-</w><lb/><w part="F">noon</w>, all the ſymptoms were worſe. The
          <lb/>injection had operated thrice. Breathing <lb/>difficult and quicker. Great
          reſtleſſneſs and <lb/>anxiety. Pulſe weaker and intermitted. She <lb/>died in the evening,
          all her ſenſes being <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtinct</w>, and having eat
          ſomewhat juſt before. <lb/>What ſhe ſpit up appeared thin; but what <lb/>came up, with the
          ſhort ſtiffled cough, was <lb/>always thick and yellow, like matter. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>WHEN ſhe was opened by Mr <hi rend="italic">Gibſon</hi>
          <w part="I">Sur-</w><lb/><w part="F">geon</w>, we perceived the glands at the root of
          <lb/>the tongue turgid, covered with <hi rend="italic">mucus,</hi> and <lb/>their
          excretories open. The <hi rend="italic">amygdalæ</hi>
          <lb/>were larger than uſual; but neither they, <pb xml:id="page_18" n="19"/><lb/>nor the
          neighbouring parts, were inflamed. <lb/>All about the <hi rend="italic">glottis</hi> was
          covered with a tough <lb/>viſcid <hi rend="italic">mucus.</hi> When the <hi rend="italic"
            >trachea</hi> was <w part="I">open-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> no inflammation appeared;
          but all its <w part="I">ſu-</w><lb/><w part="F">perior</w> internal ſurface, particularly
          the back <lb/>part, next the <hi rend="italic">oeſophagus,</hi> was covered with a
          <lb/>ſoft half-diſſolved-like-membrahe, detached <lb/>from the ſubjacent parts, lying
          looſe like the <lb/>blankets of a bed that has been lain in, and <lb/>matter like <hi
            rend="italic">pus</hi> on each ſide of it, and betwixt <lb/>it and the membrane of the
            <hi rend="italic">trachea.</hi> Some <lb/>of the ſmall glands about the <hi
            rend="italic">glottis</hi> were <lb/>turgid. The farther down we ſearched, the <lb/>more
          purulent matter we found; but no <w part="I">mem-</w><lb/><w part="F">brane</w> appeared
          here. When we came to <lb/>where the <hi rend="italic">trachea</hi> enters the lungs, by
            <w part="I">ſqueez-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> them, we could force out thro' it a
          great <lb/>deal of whitiſh glutinous liquid. The ſame <lb/>matter appeared in all the
          ramifications of <lb/>the lungs, and they ſeemed to be intirely full <lb/>of it, as we
          could ſqueeze it our, mixed with <lb/>a little blood, from the ſmalleſt diviſions of
          <lb/>that canal. The ſubſtance of the lungs <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">peared</w>
          quite ſound. The internal coat of <pb xml:id="page_19" n="20"/><lb/>the ſtomach ſeemed,
          likewiſe, very ſoft, and <lb/>covered with a great quantity of <hi rend="italic"
            >mucus.</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="6" type="case">
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE VI. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">January</hi> 3d. I was called to a boy of <lb/>ſeven
          years of age, at <hi rend="italic">Muſſelburgh,</hi> who had <lb/>gone about till this
          morning, but had <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">plained</w> for four days of a great
          difficulty in <lb/>his breathing, and of a conſtant dull pain <w part="I">a-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">bout</w> the head of the <hi rend="italic">trachea,</hi> attended with <lb/>a
          ſhrill voice. As his pulſe was quick, and <lb/>his breathing difficult, the Surgeon had
          that <lb/>morning taken twelve ounces of blood from <lb/>him, and given him <hi
            rend="italic">Gum. Ammon. Sal. C. C. <lb/>gr.</hi> iv. When I ſaw him, at night, his
          pulſe <lb/>was very frequent and weak, his breathing <lb/>quick; ſtill a little pain about
          the head of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">trachea;</hi> no inflammation to be ſeen in the
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">fauces,</hi> and his urine depoſited an ouzy <w part="I"
            >ſedi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w>. His voice was feeble, and the <w part="I"
            >ſhrill-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w> had gone off. As I ſaw he would ſoon <lb/>die, I
          deſired the Surgeon to open him, and <lb/>to be particularly attentive to every <w
            part="I">circum-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtance</w> in the whole courſe of the <hi
            rend="italic">trachea,</hi> as <pb xml:id="page_20" n="21"/><lb/>ſome unuſual
          appearances, there, had <w part="I">occur-</w><lb/><w part="F">red</w> to me in this
          diſeaſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">He</hi> told me, afterwards, that the lungs <lb/>were
          not in the leaſt inflamed; that he found, <lb/>a little below the aperture of the <hi
            rend="italic">glottis</hi> a <lb/>quantity of what appeared to him pure <w part="I"
            >mat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w>; but had not obſerved whether or not <lb/>there was
          any membrane, nor whether the <lb/>ramifications of the <hi rend="italic">trachea</hi>
          were filled with <lb/>the matter. This, however, muſt certainly <lb/>have been the caſe,
          as matter was actually <lb/>found in the ſuperior parts of the <hi rend="italic"
            >trachea,</hi>
          <lb/>as his lungs appeared otherwiſe ſound, and <lb/>could not be the cauſe of his death;
          and as <lb/>he had the ſame purulent ſediment in his <lb/>urine, which I had obſerved in
          the former <lb/>caſes, and which attends all collections of <lb/>matter, in whatever part
          of the body they <lb/>are contained. To our purpoſe, it is <w part="I">ſuffici-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ent</w>, that matter of a purulent kind, was <lb/>found in the <hi
            rend="italic">trachea.</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="7" type="case">
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE VII. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>A <hi rend="sc">Bookbinder's</hi> child, four years old, <lb/>in this
          town, was ſeized with a cough and <pb xml:id="page_21" n="22"/><lb/>quick breathing,
          Saturday October 5th, <lb/>1763. As it appeared of the croupy kind, <lb/>he was blooded
          with leeches that day, and <lb/>bliſtered next day. After this he ſeemed <lb/>better, and
          went coughing thro' the houſe <lb/>that week. Sunday 13th, I firſt ſaw the <lb/>child. The
          voice was rather more hoarſe <lb/>than uſual in the croup; the pulſe very quick, <lb/>and
          the breathing very laborious, with a <lb/>little pain in the throat in ſwallowing. Dry
          <lb/>ſhort cough. I ſuſpected that there was a <lb/>conſiderable mixture of the <hi
            rend="italic">angina</hi> with the <lb/>croup here. Leeches were applied to the
          <lb/>neck, with fomentation and ſteams. 14th, <lb/>Breathing much better, and all the
          ſymptoms <lb/>eaſier. 15th, All the ſymptoms worſe. Pulſe <lb/>and breathing very quick.
          Died the 16th. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The <hi rend="italic">trachea,</hi> when opened by Mr <hi
            rend="italic">Wood</hi>
          <lb/>ſurgeon, was covered, for half an inch from <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">glottis</hi>
          downwards, with a firm white <lb/>thick membrane, from which, for an inch <lb/>further
          down, was a ſoft yellowiſh purulent-<lb/>like matter, not yet hardened. All the <w
            part="I">mem-</w><lb/><w part="F">branes</w> of the <hi rend="italic">trachea</hi> were
          entire under theſe, <lb/>but much inflamed and red. In ſome parts <pb xml:id="page_22"
            n="23"/><lb/>of the lungs, the veſicles contained the ſame <lb/>kind of matter, but in
          no great quantity. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="8" type="case">
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE VIII. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">October</hi> 20th, 1763. A girl, aged four years,
          <lb/>coughed a little, was out the day <w part="I">fol-</w><lb/><w part="F">lowing</w>,
          and, at night, the cough increaſed <lb/>with hoarſeneſs. On the 22d, Mr <hi rend="italic"
            >Wood,</hi>
          <lb/>the family-ſurgeon, by accident, ſaw her <w part="I">play-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ing</w>, and obſerving her breathing laborious, <lb/>and her pulſe quick, tho' ſhe was
          otherwiſe <lb/>well, he blooded her. 23d, She was worſe, and <lb/>had a bliſter applied to
          her throat and back, <lb/>and got an injection. 24th, I ſaw her firſt; <lb/>her breathing
          quick, and hoarſe; pulſe 180; <lb/>urine with an ouzy ſediment; and was told, <lb/>that
          ſhe had coughed up, what ſeemed to the <lb/>family, pure matter. By her breathing, more
          <lb/>of the ſame kind ſtill ſeemed to be left <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >hind</w>. She eat and drank without any pain. <lb/>To expel the matter, if poſſible, ſhe
          got a vomit <lb/>of ſquills; but nothing came away. 25th, <lb/>She was much in the ſame
          way; and I <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerved</w> ſome matter mixed with the <hi
            rend="italic">ſaliva,</hi>
          <pb xml:id="page_23" n="24"/><lb/>that ſhe had coughed up. Breathing <w part="I"
            >ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceeding</w> quick, and laborious. Ordered the <lb/>ſteams of
          warm vinegar to be drawn into the <lb/>lungs, on purpoſe to produce a fit of <w part="I"
            >cough-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>; but it had no ſuch effect, and ſhe died <lb/>in the
          evening. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>WHEN the <hi rend="italic">trachea</hi> was opened, by Mr <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Wood,</hi> the whole internal ſurface was <w part="I">cover-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ed</w> with a membrane for three inches <w part="I">down-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >wards</w> from the <hi rend="italic">glottis.</hi> This membrane was <lb/>compleat all
          around, did not adhere to the <lb/><hi rend="italic">trachea,</hi> and came off in the
          ſhape of a <w part="I">hol-</w><lb/><w part="F">low</w> tube. The natural coats of the <hi
            rend="italic">trachea</hi>
          <lb/>ſeemed entire, and not ulcered. The ſubſtance <lb/>of the lungs was quite ſound; but
          the veſicles <lb/>of the left lobe were filled with yellow thick <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >pus,</hi> which ſunk in water. The new formed <lb/>membrane had ſome degree of
          tenacity; and, <lb/>when ſteeped in milk-warm water for two days, <lb/>did not diſſolve,
          but preſerved ſome degree <lb/>of coheſion. Mo fibres could be obſerved <lb/>in it. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>THE preceeding facts excited the curioſity <lb/>of ſome gentlemen, and
          have been confirmed <pb xml:id="page_24" n="25"/><lb/>from ſimilar obſervations made by
          them, and <lb/>which they lately tranſmitted to my hands. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="9" type="case">
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE IX. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Mr</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">Wardrobe</hi> Surgeon related to me the the <lb/>following caſe. A boy,
          eight years of <lb/>age, and healthful, had been ill two days. <lb/>His breathing was
          difficult; his voice was <lb/>croupy; he was feveriſh, and had all the <w part="I"
            >o-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> ſymptoms of the diſeaſe. He was <w part="I"
            >blood-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>, bliſtered, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> but all to
          no purpoſe; <lb/>and died the fourth day. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> whole <hi rend="italic">trachea,</hi>
          externally, appeared <lb/>ſwelled, and rather oedematous than <w part="I"
            >inflam-</w><lb/><w part="F">matory</w>. When he opened it, the whole <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſide</w> was covered with a ſoft, thick, <w part="I"
            >pale-co-</w><lb/><w part="F">loured</w> membrane, which eaſily ſeparated from <lb/>the
          parts below; thoſe had a ſlight degree <lb/>of inflammation. When he purſued the <w
            part="I">ra-</w><lb/><w part="F">mifications</w> of the <hi rend="italic">trachea</hi>
          thro' the lungs, <lb/>there was found, there, a conſiderable quantity <lb/>of real <hi
            rend="italic">pus,</hi> which ſeemed to fill all thoſe <lb/>pipes. The lungs themſelves
          were ſound. <lb/>Nothing can be liker the former caſes than <pb xml:id="page_25" n="26"
          /><lb/>this; and as Mr <hi rend="italic">Wardrobe</hi> had no occaſion <lb/>of ever ſeeing
          it again, he had concluded, as <lb/>I had done before, in ſimilar circumſtances, <lb/>that
          it was an anomalous caſe. It now <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pears</w> to be the
          common courſe of nature, in <lb/>that diſeaſe, when mortal. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="10" type="case">
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE X. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> following caſe, in confirmation of <lb/>the
          preceeding, was communicated to me <lb/>by Mr <hi rend="italic">Balfour</hi> Surgeon, and
          which I ſhall <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">liver</w> in his own words. <hi
            rend="italic">November</hi> 1ſt 1763, <lb/>I was deſired to viſit a child, between two
          <lb/>and three years old, living at the <hi rend="italic">Canonmills.</hi>
          <lb/>His face was fluſhed; his breathing laborious; <lb/>his cough of the hard croupy
          kind; his pulſe <lb/>was frequent; his tongue clean; with little <lb/>drought, and no
          pain. I was informed by <lb/>the parents, that the child had been very <lb/>healthful; but
          for eight days paſt had been <lb/>troubled with a cough, which did not put <lb/>on the
          preſent appearance till the night <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w> I was
          called; and that the child had, <lb/>till that time, gone about, and eat his meat
          <lb/>heartily. They had then applied leeches to <pb xml:id="page_26" n="27"/><lb/>his
          neck, which bled a great deal, and <lb/>had with difficulty been ſtopt. I <w part="I"
            >immedi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ately</w> took away, from the jugular vein, two
          <lb/>cupfulls of blood more, which was ſizy; and <lb/>being informed, that he ſometimes
          reached, <lb/>I ordered a vomit of <hi rend="italic">tinct. ipecacuanh.</hi> with <lb/>an
          addition of <hi rend="italic">acet. ſcillit.</hi> which was given <lb/>about an hour after
          he was blooded, and <lb/>brought up a great deal of tenacious <hi rend="italic"
            >mucus.</hi>
          <lb/>That night, he got a bliſter to his back, and <lb/>the ſaline mixture every two
          hours. <hi rend="italic">Nov.</hi>
          <lb/>2d, His Pulſe was as frequent, but not ſo <lb/>firm. All the other ſymptoms rather
          worſe. <lb/>He was ordered a decoction of the bark; the <lb/>oily ſaline mixture, to be
          taken internally; <lb/>and the camphorated volatile oil, to be <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">plied</w> externally. The child took two or <lb/>three doſes of the decoction
          and mixture; <lb/>but towards the evening, the ſymptoms <w part="I">grow-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ing</w> worſe, the medicines were diſcontinued. <lb/>The child died next
          morning. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">When</hi> the <hi rend="italic">trachea</hi> was laid
          open, I <lb/>thought that a ſuppuration had happened; <lb/>but, upon nearer inſpection,
          found, that it <lb/>was only the <hi rend="italic">mucus</hi> which had acquired a pu- <pb
            xml:id="page_27" n="28"/><lb/>rulent colour; and that it was formed into a
          <lb/>membranous cruſt, which every where lined <lb/>the internal membrane of the <hi
            rend="italic">trachea,</hi> from <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">larynx,</hi> to its entrance
          into the <hi rend="italic">thorax.</hi>
          <lb/>This preternatural membrane appeared <w part="I">thick-</w><lb/><w part="F">eſt</w>
          about the middle of the <hi rend="italic">trachea;</hi> and, there, <lb/>ſeemed almoſt to
          fill up the paſſage. It was <lb/>ſo firm, that a conſiderable portion <w part="I"
            >ſeparate-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>, at once, leaving the natural membrane <lb/>of the
            <hi rend="italic">trachea</hi> bare and ſound, and with the <lb/>appearance of a ſlight
          inflammation. I put <lb/>a conſiderable portion of the preternatural <lb/>membrane into
          water; and, after that, it ſtill <lb/>retained a degree of tenacity, but had <lb/>too
          little firmneſs to be preſerved. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="11" type="case">
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE XI. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Mr</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">Wood</hi> Surgeon gave me the following. <lb/>A child, about ſixteen
          months old, was <w part="I">ſeiz-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> with the Croup, and died the
          ſeventh <lb/>day. On opening the body, there was found <lb/>in the lower part of the <hi
            rend="italic">larynx,</hi> and <lb/>beginning of the <hi rend="italic">trachea,</hi> a
          ſubſtance of <lb/>a membranous appearance, adhering <w part="I">ſlight-</w><pb
            xml:id="page_28" n="29"/><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> around the inſide of theſe parts.
          <lb/>When it was removed, the membranes <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">trachea</hi> were
          found entire, and <lb/>ſomewhat redder than uſual. Along the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >trachea</hi> and bronchial branches, there was a <lb/>conſiderable quantity of <hi
            rend="italic">mucus.</hi> It was frothy, <lb/>and ſomewhat tenacious. This <hi
            rend="italic">mucus</hi>
          <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">tended</w> as far as the membranous <w part="I"
            >appear-</w><lb/><w part="F">ance</w>, and downwards into the minuteſt <lb/>branches of
          the <hi rend="italic">bronchiae,</hi> in which it had a <lb/>yellowiſh purulent
          appearance. The ſurface <lb/>of the lungs was ſomewhat reddiſh. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="12" type="case">
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE XII. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> following caſe, which was <w part="I"
            >communi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cated</w> to me by—, I think worth relating; <lb/>as it
          ſhows the diſeaſe in a different <w part="I">ſitu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ation</w> from all
          the preceeding; indeed, <lb/>under ſuch circumſtances, as I never had <lb/>an opportunity
          to ſee, and muſt appear <lb/>very ſeldom in, for it is the only one of its <lb/>kind that
          I have heard of. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Miss</hi> ******, about nine years old, was <lb/>ſeized
          with a ſlight cough, on the 25th of <pb xml:id="page_29" n="30"/><lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >October,</hi> owing to rainy weather, and wet <lb/>feet. On the 26th, when I ſaw her
          firſt, the <lb/>ſcarcely had any heat, thirſt, or ſickneſs, and <lb/>no pain of any kind,
          except when ſhe <w part="I">cough-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>, or was fretted, which
          bringing on a quick <lb/>inſpiration, ſhe then felt ſome ſlight pain in <lb/>the windpipe,
          a little below the <hi rend="italic">rima glottidis.</hi>
          <lb/>Her voice was ſhrill, like that of a young <lb/>cock. She was blooded; got a gentle
          vomit; <lb/>emolient cataplaſms to her feet; and a bliſter <lb/>to her back. 27th,
          Symptoms no better. <lb/>No difficulty of deglutition, and no redneſs <lb/>to be ſeen in
          the throat. She never <w part="I">expec-</w><lb/><w part="F">torated</w> any thing like
            <hi rend="italic">pus</hi> or phlegm, during <lb/>the whole courſe of the diſeaſe.
          Steams of <lb/>warm water were tried. 28th, Her cough <lb/>was inceſſant for ſome hours,
          during which, <lb/>ſhe coughed up a piece of a membrane. This <lb/>I believed to be a part
          of what lines the <lb/><hi rend="italic">trachea,</hi> as it had a mortified <w part="I"
            >appear-</w><lb/><w part="F">ance</w>, and was like black ſhagg ſilk. She <lb/>died ſoon
          after this. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Upon</hi> opening the body, the diſeaſe <w part="I"
            >ſeem-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> ſeated, ſolely, in the head of the <hi rend="italic"
            >trachea,</hi>
          <lb/>as its membrane appeared to me mortified <pb xml:id="page_30" n="31"/><lb/>two inches
          downwards. Below that, the <lb/><hi rend="italic">trachea,</hi> and its branches, ſeemed
          quite <lb/>ſound. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> was very natural for one, who had <lb/>never any
          opportunity of ſeeing this diſeaſe <lb/>in its natural ſituation, to think, that a <w
            part="I">mor-</w><lb/><w part="F">tification</w> had ſeized on the coats of the <hi
            rend="italic">tra-<lb/>chea.</hi> But to one who has been <w part="I"
            >accuſtom-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> to inſpect bodies, in this diſeaſe, it muſt
          <lb/>appear probable, that it was only the <w part="I">preter-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >natural</w> and morbid membrane become black, <lb/>which gave the <hi rend="italic"
            >trachea</hi> the appearance of <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> mortified.
          No wonder that the coats of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">trachea</hi> were thought to be in
          a <w part="I">gangre-</w><lb/><w part="F">nous</w> ſtate, when I imagined they had <w
            part="I">ſuppu-</w><lb/><w part="F">rated</w> in the firſt caſe, that I met with. The
          <lb/>coughing up a piece of the membrane, ſhows <lb/>that it was this looſely adhering
          one, and <lb/>none of the natural ones, which are ſo <w part="I">firm-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ly</w> attached; and which, having no fleſhy <lb/>parts below, could not have been ſo
          eaſily <w part="I">ſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">parated</w>. This, then, appears to differ in
          no <lb/>other point from the others, but only that <lb/>here the morbid membrane had dryed
            <pb xml:id="page_31" n="32"/><lb/>and turned black; whereas, in all the former, <lb/>it
          was moiſt and white. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">These</hi> are all the caſes, that I have kept <lb/>an
          account of, or received from others. Tho' <lb/>few, they are leading ones, and ſufficient
          to <lb/>eſtabliſh many material facts and <w part="I">circumſtan-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ces</w>, that have hitherto been unknown, with <lb/>regard to this diſeaſe. We will now
          draw, <lb/>from them, ſome concluſions; which, as we <lb/>have proceeded ſo cautiouſly,
          will be the <lb/>more certain. If we add any reaſoning, to <lb/>ſet theſe concluſions in a
          clearer light, we ſhall <lb/>keep as cloſe as poſſible to ſettled <w part="I"
            >experi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w>; and ſhall give it only as probable <w part="I"
            >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">jecture</w>, finding fault with no perſon who may <lb/>reaſon
          differently. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Corollary</hi> I. It ſeems eaſy, in general, <lb/>to
          diſtinguiſh the Croup from all other <lb/>diſeaſes hitherto deſcribed. A peculiar ſharp
          <lb/>ſhrill voice, not eaſily deſcribed; a <w part="I">remark-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >able</w> freedom from all complaints, when in <lb/>imminent danger, ſo that they will
          eat a <w part="I">mi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nute</w> before they expire; a quick laborious
          <lb/>breathing; a frequent pulſe, ſometimes <lb/>ſtrong at firſt, but always ſoft and weak
            <w part="I">to-</w><pb xml:id="page_32" n="33"/><lb/><w part="F">wards</w> the end;
          ſcarce any difficulty of <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">glutition</w>, or remarkable
          inflammation in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">fauces;</hi> a dull pain, often, and ſometimes
          an <lb/>external ſwelling in the upper part of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">trachea;</hi>
          ſenſes quite diſtinct to the laſt; and <lb/>all the ſymptoms moſt rapid in their progreſs,
          <lb/>characteriſe ſufficiently this diſeaſe. I have <lb/>not mentioned a cough, as that
          ſymptom is <lb/>ſometimes abſent; and when it attends the <lb/>Croup, it is not of the
          common kind, but more <lb/>ſhort and ſtiffled, and leſs convulſive, with <lb/>little or no
          expectoration. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> other ſymptoms, that often attend <lb/>it, ſuch
          as a red ſwelled face, œdematous <lb/>feet, drought, urine ſometimes with, and, at
          <lb/>other times, without a ſediment, reachings, <lb/><hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> are
          not ſo conſtant as the former; and <lb/>therefore, are not ſo characteriſtical. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Those</hi> not converſant in this diſeaſe, <w part="I"
            >of-</w><lb/><w part="F">ten</w> miſtake peripneumoniacal complaints, <lb/>and ſevere
          colds, for it; and, as they <w part="I">frequent-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> cure theſe,
          they are apt to look on it as <lb/>not ſo dangerous. But we have ſeen, that <lb/>the lungs
          are totally free from any <w part="I">inflam-</w><lb/><w part="F">mation</w>, and are not
          the ſeat of the diſeaſe. <pb xml:id="page_33" n="34"/><lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Catarrhus
            ſuffocativus</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Etmuller</hi> ſeems, <lb/>likewiſe, to have been
          a peripneumony. And, <lb/>as he deſcribes no peculiarity in the voice; as <lb/>the
          ſymptoms ſeem to have been, apparently, <lb/>ſeverer; and as it returned, at ſtated and <w
            part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">gular</w> periods, we muſt conſider them as <w part="I"
            >dif-</w><lb/><w part="F">ferent</w> diſeaſes, tho' ſimilar in many points. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As this diſeaſe has different vulgar names, <lb/>for I am told, that
          on the weſt coaſt, they call <lb/>it the <hi rend="italic">Chock,</hi> or <hi
            rend="italic">Stuffing,</hi> a technical one becomes <lb/>abſolutely neceſſary. A name
          is beſt given <lb/>from the apparent ſymptoms, which are <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ways</w> conſpicuous, while the cauſe is <w part="I">general-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ly</w> hidden, and often doubtful. The <w part="I">lead-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ing</w> ſymptoms here, are, the ſhrill voice, and <lb/>difficult breathing. It,
          therefore, may <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">perly</w> be called <hi rend="italic"
            >Suffocatio ſtridula.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Corol.</hi> II. As it appears peculiar to a <lb/>certain
          age, and local, in a great meaſure, as <lb/>to its ſituation, ſo it ſeems to attend
          certain <lb/>ſeaſons of the year. All the preceeding caſes <lb/>ſhowed themſelves during
          the courſe of the <lb/>winter, from the month of <hi rend="italic">October</hi> to the
          <lb/>month of <hi rend="italic">March,</hi> except one in <hi rend="italic">Auguſt,</hi>
          <lb/>which was probably owing to the antecedent <pb xml:id="page_34" n="35"
          /><lb/>ſmall-pox; for long catarrhs from the ſmall <lb/>pox, meaſles, or chin-cough, are
          ſtrong <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">diſponent</w> cauſes to this diſeaſe. The
          moiſt <lb/>and cold weather in winter, ſeems to have <lb/>great power in producing this
          diſeaſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Corol.</hi> III. Very different have been the
          <lb/>opinions, with regard to the ſeat of the <hi rend="italic">Suf-<lb/>focatio
            ſtridula.</hi> Some placing it in the <hi rend="italic">glot-<lb/>tis</hi> and its
          muſcles; ſome in the coats of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">trachea;</hi> while others have
          fixt its ſeat in the <lb/>lungs themſelves. None of all theſe <w part="I"
            >opini-</w><lb/><w part="F">ons</w> appear to be true. The <hi rend="italic"
            >glottis</hi> is never <lb/>found contracted or inflamed; the lungs <lb/>are quite
          ſound; and the coats of the <hi rend="italic">trachea</hi>
          <lb/>ſeem to ſuffer only by ſecond hand. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> ſeat of this diſtemper appears to be <lb/>the
          cavity of the wind-pipe. The place firſt, <lb/>and moſt particularly, affected, is the
          upper <lb/>part of the <hi rend="italic">trachea,</hi> about an inch below the <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">glottis;</hi> for in that part they complain of a <lb/>dull pain; the
          external ſwelling has been <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerved</w> there; and the
          morbid membrane we <lb/>have found ſtretching from that place <w part="I">down-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">wards</w>. The back part of the <hi rend="italic">trachea,</hi> where
          <lb/>there are no cartilages, ſeems, from the <w part="I">in-</w><pb xml:id="page_35"
            n="34"/>
          <gap reason="repetition" unit="pages" quantity="2"/><pb xml:id="page_36" n="35"/>
          <pb xml:id="page_37" n="36"/><lb/>ſpection of thoſe that die of this diſeaſe, to be
          <lb/>its firſt and principal ſeat, as this morbid <lb/>membrane is often found there, when
          it is in <lb/>no other part. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>No wonder that the morbid appearances <lb/>are chiefly found there;
          for, there, are <w part="I">lodg-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> the greateſt number of
          glands, deſigned <lb/>for the ſecretion of <hi rend="italic">mucus.</hi> This fluid is <w
            part="I">ſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">parated</w> from glandular bodies, depoſited <w
            part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">twixt</w> the different membranes, which are <w
            part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">forated</w> by an infinite number of almoſt <w
            part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F">perceptible</w> ſmall holes, that give a paſſage
          <lb/>to the excretory ducts of theſe glands. The <lb/>largeſt of theſe lye on the outer,
          and <w part="I">poſte-</w><lb/><w part="F">rior</w> ſurface of that membrane, which
          ſerves, <lb/>on the back part, to make up the deficiency <lb/>of the cartilages, as they
          are not compleat <lb/>circles. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> ſome of the former caſes, the whole <lb/>glands,
          at the root of the tongue, and the <lb/><hi rend="italic">amygdalæ</hi> were turgid, and
          the parts covered <lb/>with <hi rend="italic">mucus.</hi> In the mucous glands, in
          general, <lb/>this diſtemper ought to be conſidered, as <w part="I">ori-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ginally</w> ſeated; but, from particular cauſes, <lb/>more directed to thoſe of
          the <hi rend="italic">trachea;</hi>
          <pb xml:id="page_38" n="37"/><lb/>where, from the nature of the part, it <w part="I"
            >be-</w><lb/><w part="F">comes</w> viſible in a different ſhape. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Corol</hi>. IV. Various have been the <w part="I"
            >the-</w><lb/><w part="F">oretical</w> opinions of people, who never had <lb/>the
          opportunity, or gave themſelves the <lb/>trouble, to ſearch into the real cauſe of this
          <lb/>diſtemper. Some have attributed it to ſpaſms <lb/>of the muſcles, that contract the
            <hi rend="italic">glottis.</hi>
          <lb/>That it was not occaſioned by ſpaſms of the <lb/>muſcles, that contract the <hi
            rend="italic">larynx,</hi> might <lb/>have appeared from the ſymptoms <w part="I"
            >them-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſelves</w>. Had this been of the claſs of <w part="I"
            >ſpaſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">modic</w> nervous diſeaſes, it would have come <lb/>in
          paroxyſms, with remiſſion and <w part="I">exacerba-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>; the
          urine would always have been pale; <lb/>convulſions would have come on before death;
          <lb/>and antiſpaſmodics, inſtead of evacuants, <lb/>would have been the remedies. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Had</hi> theſe muſcles, or any of the coats of <lb/>the
            <hi rend="italic">trachea,</hi> been inflamed or mortified, as <lb/>others have thought,
          the pain would have <lb/>been greater than it is, before the <w part="I"
            >mortifica-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>; and the pulſe would have been <w part="I"
            >ſtrong-</w><lb/><w part="F">er</w>, than it generally is, as the parts are
          <lb/>membranous. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_39" n="38"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">If</hi>, according to the opinion of many, the
          <lb/>lungs had been inflamed and ſuppurated; the <lb/>cough would have been more inceſſant
          and <lb/>violent; the pulſe full and ſoft; with a <w part="I">ſen-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſation</w> of weight in the breaſt, ſizy blood, <lb/>dry tongue, and delirium. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> all theſe fanciful erroneous opinions <lb/>fall
          to the ground, when we once inſpect the <lb/>morbid body. From that true ſource of
          <lb/>knowledge, we learn, that the cauſe of this <lb/>diſeaſe is a preternatural white,
          tough, thick <lb/>membranous cruſt, covering, often for many <lb/>inches, the inſide of
          the <hi rend="italic">trachea.</hi> This <w part="I">mem-</w><lb/><w part="F">brane</w> is
          of ſo tenacious a conſiſtence, that it <lb/>can remain ſoaking in warm water, for <w
            part="I">ma-</w><lb/><w part="F">ny</w> days, without diſſolving. It is not <w part="I"
            >at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tached</w> to the parts below, but is eaſily <w part="I"
            >ſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">parable</w> from them, as there is always <w part="I"
            >mat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> behind it. When it ends, the <hi rend="italic"
            >trachea</hi> is <lb/>covered with good <hi rend="italic">pus,</hi> or purulent <hi
            rend="italic">mucus;</hi>
          <lb/>as are, generally, the ramifications of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">bronchiæ</hi> and
          veſicles, which, in ſome caſes, <lb/>were quite filled with it. To account how <lb/>this
          matter, as there is no ulceration; and <lb/>how this membrane are formed, we muſt
          <lb/>trace things from their ſource. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_40" n="39"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> blood conſiſts of three principal parts,
          <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">craſſamentum, ſerum,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">lymph;</hi> the
          laſt <lb/>of which is a diaphanous liquor, full of <w part="I">ge-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >latinous</w> and nutritious particles. This <lb/>liquor very ſimilar to the white of an
          egg, <lb/>is coagulable by heat, alkohol, acids, and by <lb/>every method which attracts
          or evaporates <lb/>the watery particles. This coagulable part, <lb/>probably, is the
          nutritious part of our <lb/>blood. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> gelatinous lymph abounds more in <lb/>young
          animals, than in thoſe come to <w part="I">matu-</w><lb/><w part="F">rity</w>. <hi
            rend="italic">Geoffroy le Cadet,</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Mem. Acad. <lb/>des
            Sciences,</hi> for the year 1730, by many <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >periments</w> ſhows us this fact; and makes it <lb/>appear, that there is twice as much
          nutritive <lb/>jelly in veal, as in beef. The final reaſon for <lb/>this is ſelf-evident;
          for young creatures, on <lb/>account of their growing, require a greater <lb/>ſupply of
          nouriſhment. Children muſt, <w part="I">there-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w>, abound more
          with it than men. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The <hi rend="italic">mucus</hi> ſeparated from glands, in <w part="I"
            >diffe-</w><lb/><w part="F">rent</w> parts of the body, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
          noſe, <hi rend="italic">fauces, <w part="I">œſo-</w><lb/><w part="F">phagus</w>,</hi>
          ſtomach, guts, <hi rend="italic">trachea,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">bronchiæ,</hi>
          <lb/>appears to be very analogous to this lymph. <pb xml:id="page_41" n="40"/><lb/>The
          former differs from the latter, only, in <lb/>its greater ſpiſſitude; and this alteration
          is <lb/>brought about after its ſecretion, the more <lb/>watery parts being volatilized
          and diſſipated, <lb/>while the more heavy and viſcous remain <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">hind</w>. This <hi rend="italic">mucus</hi> is extremely diſpoſed to
          <lb/>inſpiſſation, as appears from experiments. <lb/>Even the admiſſion of cold air into
          the <hi rend="italic">tra-<lb/>chea</hi> thickens this <hi rend="italic">mucus,</hi>
          often, to ſuch a <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">gree</w>, that it ſtagnates in the
          glands, and all <lb/>ſecretion is entirely ſtopt. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> children, as well as in old people, this
          <lb/>ſecretion is plentiful, owing to the great <lb/>quantity of it they contain, and to
          the laxity <lb/>of their veſſels. This evacuation is <w part="I">particu-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">larly</w> increaſed during the cold and moiſt <lb/>weather of winter, when the
          perſpiration is <lb/>diminiſhed, and the glandular ſecretions <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">creaſed</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> evacuation is promoted by all <w part="I"
            >ſti-</w><lb/><w part="F">mulants</w>, operating on the <hi rend="italic">trachea</hi>
          and lungs, <lb/>as we obſerve from the effects of ſnuff, and <lb/>the ſmoak of tobacco.
          The maritime air <lb/>ſupplies a <hi rend="italic">ſtimulus,</hi> calculated to increaſe
          the <lb/>ſecretion from the <hi rend="italic">mucus</hi> glands of the <hi rend="italic"
            >trachea</hi>
          <pb xml:id="page_42" n="41"/><lb/>and lungs. Along with the moiſture, <w part="I"
            >ſweep-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> from the ſea by the winds, is carried <lb/>likewiſe,
          a great quantity of ſea-ſalt; as every <lb/>thing, at ſome diſtance from the ſhore, taſtes
          <lb/>ſalt. This inſpired into the lungs, <w part="I">ſtimu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lates</w>
          the orifices of the tracheal glands, and <lb/>increaſes the mucous ſecretion. This effect
          <lb/>will happen more particularly in children, as <lb/>their nerves are more irritable,
          than thoſe of <lb/>people advanced in years. Hence we find, <lb/>that, in moiſt winter
          weather, particularly <w part="I">a-</w><lb/><w part="F">long</w> the ſea-ſhore, children
          ſhould have an <lb/>unuſual ſecretion of <hi rend="italic">mucus,</hi> from the glands
          <lb/>of the wind-pipe. Diſeaſes, ſuch as the <w part="I">ſmall-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >pox</w>, meaſles, chin-cough, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> and other <w part="I"
            >na-</w><lb/><w part="F">tural</w> cauſes, have the ſame effect in increaſing <lb/>this
          diſcharge. When theſe are combined, <lb/>there exiſts the greateſt prediſpoſition to this
          <lb/>diſeaſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">When</hi> there happens a very great <w part="I"
            >ſecre-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of this coagulate fluid from the glands <lb/>of the
            <hi rend="italic">trachea</hi> in children, they are either not <lb/>ſufficiently
          attentive, or often too young, to <lb/>ſpit it up. The thinner parts are carried off
          <lb/>during expiration, while the remainder is <pb xml:id="page_43" n="42"/><lb/>thickened
          and compreſſed, by the obſtruction, <lb/>that the narrowneſs of the <hi rend="italic"
            >glottis</hi> muſt make <lb/>to the exit of the air from a larger canal. <lb/>Every
          circumſtance encourages its <w part="I">concre-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> into a ſolid
          firm membrane, while the <lb/>more internal parts of the <hi rend="italic">mucus,</hi>
          continuing <lb/>ſtill fluid, and the continual ſecretion of <lb/>more, keep it ſeparated
          from the parts <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">low</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> how happens it that we find pure <lb/>matter,
          which ſinks in water, behind the <lb/>membrane, and in the different ramifications <lb/>of
          the <hi rend="italic">trachea,</hi> when there is no ulceration? <lb/>Matter does not ſeem
          to be formed, as was <lb/>generally thought, by the veſſels of the ulcer; <lb/>but to
          exiſt in the blood, particularly in the <lb/>ſerous and lymphatic liquors, nearly in the
          <lb/>fame ſtate; and to be, probably, the true <w part="I">nu-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >trititious</w>, nay, perhaps, the coagulable part <lb/>of our fluids. Dr <hi
            rend="italic">Pringle,</hi> in his ingenious, <lb/>uſeful, and accurate experiments,
          upon <w part="I">ſep-</w><lb/><w part="F">tic</w> and antiſeptic ſubſtances, found, that
          the <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſerum,</hi> when ſtagnating, and expoſed to heat, <lb/>let fall
          a white ſubſtance like <hi rend="italic">pus;</hi> and, from <lb/>thence, juſtly,
          concludes, that the <hi rend="italic">pus</hi> of ulcers <lb/>is formed, in the ſame way,
          by the <w part="I">evapora-</w><pb xml:id="page_44" n="43"/><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of
          the more watery particles, and the <lb/>ſubſiding and inſpiſſation of this part. This
          <lb/>fluid ſhows a great tendency to become ſolid, <lb/>by reſtoring quickly all loſs of
          ſubſtance. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">There</hi> cannot be a fitter ſituation, for <lb/>the
          formation of <hi rend="italic">pus</hi> from the mucous <w part="I">ſecre-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tion</w>, than the <hi rend="italic">trachea</hi> and lungs. There the
          <lb/>ſame ſecretion, evaporation, ſtagnation, and <lb/>heat exiſts, as in an ulcer; and,
          therefore, <lb/>the ſame conſequence ſhould, and does, <w part="I">hap-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">pen</w>. We often ſee real <hi rend="italic">pus</hi> ſpit up in the <lb/>end
          of a cold. Perhaps this change from <lb/><hi rend="italic">mucus</hi> to <hi rend="italic"
            >pus,</hi> happens before the membrane <lb/>is formed, as <hi rend="italic">pus</hi>
          ſhows ſuch a tendency to <lb/>aſſume a ſolid form, and is deſigned by <w part="I"
            >Na-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w> to repair all deficiencies in the ſolids. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> diſeaſe now appears of a very <w part="I"
            >ſingu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lar</w> nature, and unlike any other that we <lb/>know. <hi
            rend="italic">Du Haen</hi> has, indeed, lately told <lb/>us, that he has ſometimes
          found, in diſſection, <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">viſcera</hi> covered, externally, with a
          white <lb/>tough cruſt. I wiſh he had given us the <lb/>hiſtory of ſome of theſe patients.
          He <w part="I">ima-</w><lb/><w part="F">gines</w>, that it was formed from the <w part="I"
            >inflam-</w><lb/><w part="F">matory</w> cruſt in the blood; but, here, there <lb/>never
          is found any. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_45" n="44"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I <hi rend="sc">have</hi> lately met with a deſcription in <lb/>the
          Philoſophical Tranſactions abridged, Vol. <lb/>3d, page 68th, of a membrane formed in the
          <lb/>inſide of the <hi rend="italic">trachea.</hi>
          <q rend="quotes">A boy five years <lb/>old, died of a conſumption. A year <w part="I"
              >be-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w> his death, he was troubled with a dry <lb/>cough,
            which continued ever after, ſpitting, <lb/>now and then, a little quantity of blood.
            <lb/>Ten or twelve days before he died, his <lb/>nurſe took notice of ſome thick skins
            he <lb/>ſpit up. His Phyſcian, having <w part="I">exami-</w><lb/><w part="F">ned</w> one
            of them, ſound, it had the ſhape <lb/>and conſiſtence of a veſſel, which made <lb/>him
            think it might perhaps be ſome <w part="I">veſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſel</w> of the
            lungs. The child being dead, <lb/>I opened the body. In the left ſide of <lb/>the lungs,
            I found a little purulent <hi rend="italic">ſanies.</hi>
            <lb/>The inſide of the <hi rend="italic">trachea</hi> was incruſtated <lb/>with a ſlimy
            membrane, which I took off <lb/>from the <hi rend="italic">trachea,</hi> and the
            branches in the <lb/>lungs, inſomuch that that <hi rend="italic">pellicula</hi> made
            <lb/>a perfect veſſel, from the <hi rend="italic">larynx</hi> to the <w part="I"
              >ve-</w><lb/><w part="F">ry</w> extremities of the <hi rend="italic">bronchiæ,</hi>
            from which <lb/>it came off very eaſily, without breaking <w part="I">ei-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ther</w> the trunk, or the branches. It adhered <pb xml:id="page_46" n="45"
            /><lb/>to the inward coat of the <hi rend="italic">trachea,</hi> only by <lb/>ſome ſmall
            filaments, which were ſo <w part="I">ten-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w>, that they broke
            off eaſily; and made <lb/>me think, the production of that <w part="I"
              >extraor-</w><lb/><w part="F">dinary</w> veſſel was nothing but the <w part="I"
              >mucila-</w><lb/><w part="F">ginous</w> humour, continually diſcharged <lb/>by the
            glands of the <hi rend="italic">trachea,</hi> grown more <lb/>clammy by the diſtemper,
            and ſo dry that <lb/>it could not be ſpit out; this incruſting <lb/>the inſide of the
              <hi rend="italic">trachea</hi> and <hi rend="italic">bronchiæ,</hi> and <lb/>growing
            thicker, was at laſt ſhaven off by <lb/>the violent fit of coughing the child was
            <lb/>ſometimes taken with, and then was <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">newed</w>
            again by the ſucceeding <hi rend="italic">mucus.</hi> This <lb/>new veſſel would not
            diſſolve in hot water. <lb/>The veſſels of the lungs, that is the <hi rend="italic"
              >tra-<lb/>chea</hi> and <hi rend="italic">bronchiae,</hi> the pulmonary arteries
            <lb/>and veins, were as whole as could be.</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> appears, by the diſſection, that there <lb/>was
          no impoſthume formed in the lungs; and <lb/>that the child died from this preternatural
          <lb/>membrane. Perhaps, many of the <hi rend="italic">polypus</hi>'s, <lb/>thrown up from
          the bronchial veſſels of grown <lb/>up people, might have the ſame origin. <pb
            xml:id="page_47" n="46"/><lb/>Theſe caſes ſhow, how apt the <hi rend="italic">mucus</hi>
          is to <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">quire</w> a ſolid form. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">We</hi> have an account, in the <w part="I"
            >Philoſophi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cal</w> Tranſactions abridged, vol. 2d, of a <w
            part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">eaſe</w> in <hi rend="italic">Cornwall,</hi> called
          the <hi rend="italic">morbus <w part="I">ſtrangula-</w><lb/><w part="F">torius</w>,</hi>
          which, from the puſtles, <hi rend="italic">petechiæ;</hi> and <lb/>putrid diſpoſition of
          the fluids, appears more <lb/>nearly allied to the malignant ſore throat, <lb/>altho' it
          ſometimes attacked the <hi rend="italic">aſpera <w part="I">arte-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ria</w>.</hi> A caſe is, there, related, where a <w part="I">hol-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >low</w> membranous coat, of the ſhape of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">trachea</hi> and
          its branches, was coughed up, <lb/>and ſuppoſed to be the natural membrane of <lb/>theſe
          parts. Another ſimilar to the former <lb/>came up afterwards. The patient lived about
          <lb/>a day after this. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Corol.</hi> V. There appears, from the <w part="I"
            >pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceeding</w> facts, two very different ſituations of <lb/>the
            <hi rend="italic">Suffocatio ſtridula;</hi> the former more <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">flammatory</w>, and leſs dangerous; the latter <lb/>leſs inflammatory, and
          highly dangerous. <lb/>In the former, the pulſe is generally ſtrong; <lb/>the face red;
          drought great; and they agree <lb/>with evacuations: In the latter, the pulſe is <lb/>very
          quick, and ſoft; great weakneſs; tongue <pb xml:id="page_48" n="47"/><lb/>moiſt; leſs
          drought; great anxiety; and <lb/>evacuations haſten death. The former may <lb/>be called
          the inflammatory; and the latter, <lb/>the purulent ſtate. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">These</hi> are two very different ſtages of <lb/>the
          diſtemper, and muſt be carefully <w part="I">diſtin-</w><lb/><w part="F">guiſhed</w> by
          the practitioner, that he may <lb/>know how to direct his applications; or, at <lb/>leaſt,
          how to form a juſt <hi rend="italic">prognoſis;</hi> as he is, <lb/>generally, not called
          till the patient is in <lb/>the latter ſtage. If this diſeaſe comes on <lb/>with an old
          habitual cough, or by ſlow <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">grees</w>, the inflammatory
          ſtage will ſcarcely be <lb/>perceivable. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>IF the pulſe is very ſoft and feeble, <w part="I">eſpeci-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ally</w> after being ſtrong; or any purulent <w part="I">mat-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ter</w> comes up with ſpitting, vomiting, or <lb/>coughing, which happened in
          ſome of the <lb/>former caſes, we have a proof that the <w part="I">pu-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">rulent</w> ſtate is, already, formed. <w part="I">Experi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ence</w> has taught me another mark, by which <lb/>I can diſtinguiſh theſe different
          ſtates. I <lb/>have obſerved, that the urine, which, <w part="I">du-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ring</w> the inflammatory ſtate, is thin, had <lb/>always, after the purulent ſtate
          came on, a <pb xml:id="page_49" n="48"/><lb/>light ouzy purulent ſediment, ſuch as people
          <lb/>have from matter collected any where, that <lb/>has no vent outwards. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>NO wonder, that the matter is ſpeedily <lb/>abſorbed, in this
          ſituation, as it is contained <lb/>in the <hi rend="italic">bronchiae</hi> and veſicles,
          and of courſe <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F">bibed</w> by the whole internal ſurface
          of the <lb/>lungs and <hi rend="italic">trachea;</hi> a ſurface infinitely <w part="I"
            >great-</w><lb/><w part="F">er</w> than any impoſthume can have. Hence <lb/>the blood
          will be ſuddenly filled with it; and <lb/>the urine have that white purulent ſediment,
          <lb/>which ariſes from abſorption of matter. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> the latter ſtage, we find the membrane
          <lb/>compleatly formed. Is it ſo in the former? <lb/>I ſuſpect that it has not yet got a
          firm <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſiſtency</w>; otherwiſe evacuations would not
          <lb/>have ſo ſudden and ſalutary an effect, as they <lb/>produce in this ſtage. Perhaps,
          the turgid and <lb/>inflamed glands are but yet expelling the <lb/>thick <hi rend="italic"
            >mucus,</hi> which is circulating thro' the <lb/>veſſels in too great a quantity, and in
          too <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſpiſſated</w> a ſtate. This is ſtrongly confirmed
          <lb/>by the great quantity of <hi rend="italic">mucus,</hi> ſound in <lb/>the ſtomach, and
          the ſwelling of the mucous <lb/>glands at the root of the tongue. Even <w part="I"
            >af-</w><pb xml:id="page_50" n="49"/><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> death we perceive ſome
          degree of <w part="I">inflam-</w><lb/><w part="F">mation</w> in the coais of the <hi
            rend="italic">trachea,</hi> which <lb/>probably has been greater at the beginning,
          <lb/>when the flux of humour commeneed, and <lb/>the irritation was ſtronger. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Corol.</hi> VI. It ſeems to be no very <w part="I"
            >dif-</w><lb/><w part="F">ficult</w> matter to account, from the cauſe, <lb/>for all the
          ſymptoms of this diſeaſe. A <w part="I">ſtrait-</w><lb/><w part="F">ening</w> of the <hi
            rend="italic">trachea,</hi> and dryneſs of the parts, <lb/>will mechanically alter the
          voice, and make <lb/>it more ſhrill; for we find in all wind <w part="I"
            >inſtru-</w><lb/><w part="F">ments</w>, the notes are acute in proportion to <lb/>the
          ſmallneſs of the bore. Mr <hi rend="italic">Balfour</hi>
          <w part="I">ſur-</w><lb/><w part="F">geon</w> told me, that he attended a child in a
          <lb/>diſeaſe, which, from the ſimilarity of voice, <lb/>appeared to him the Croup. The
          child died. <lb/>When opened, a piece of ſhell, which the <lb/>child had ſucked in with
          it's breath, was <w part="I">ly-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> acroſs the <hi rend="italic"
            >trachea,</hi> about an inch below <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">glottis,</hi> and the
          membrane was <w part="I">infla-</w><lb/><w part="F">med</w> and dry. Here was an
          artificial Croup <lb/>raiſed, from which we may evidently <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ceive</w> how the voice is altered in the natural <lb/>diſeaſe. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_51" n="50"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">When</hi> there appears to be a great <w part="I"
            >quan-</w><lb/><w part="F">tity</w> of <hi rend="italic">mucus</hi> circulating in the
          veſſels; when <lb/>there is, often, ſo much <hi rend="italic">mucus</hi> or <hi
            rend="italic">pus</hi> in all the <lb/>pipes of the lungs; when there is a <w part="I"
            >preterna-</w><lb/><w part="F">tural</w> membrane formed in the <hi rend="italic"
            >trachea;</hi> no <lb/>wonder that Nature excites a fever, her <w part="I"
            >ge-</w><lb/><w part="F">neral</w> and conſtant reſource, when ſhe is <w part="I"
            >vio-</w><lb/><w part="F">lently</w> attacked and in danger. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Considering</hi> the acuteneſs of the fever;
          <lb/>conſidering the obſtruction in the <hi rend="italic">trachea, <lb/>bronchiæ,</hi> and
          veſicles; with what difficulty the <lb/>air muſt gain admiſſion to diſtend them; and
          <lb/>what hindrance that muſt give the blood <lb/>circulating through the lungs; a
          laborious <lb/>breathing muſt, neceſſarily, attend the other <lb/>ſymptoms. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">As</hi> the blood paſſes with ſome difficulty <lb/>thro'
          the lungs, an unuſual weakneſs muſt <lb/>certainly come on, the face become <w part="I"
            >ſwell-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>, and the extremities appear œdematous. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">To</hi> account for that total want of pain, <lb/>or ſo
          ſlight a one that they don't attend to <lb/>it, unleſs when asked, is a matter of ſome
          <lb/>difficulty. That the membrane of the <w part="I">wind-</w><lb/><w part="F">pipe</w>,
          in general ſo very irritable from every <pb xml:id="page_52" n="51"/><lb/>ſlight cauſe,
          ſhould calmly bear the preſence <lb/>of ſuch a quantity of matter, and of ſo thick <lb/>a
          membrane, is not the leaſt ſurprizing <w part="I">cir-</w><lb/><w part="F">cumſtance</w>
          of this uncommon diſtemper. The <lb/><hi rend="italic">mucus</hi> being a humour natural
          to theſe parts; <lb/>its ſlow and gradual collection and <w part="I">inſpiſſa-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tion</w>; freſh <hi rend="italic">mucus</hi> conſtantly ſeparated, which
          <lb/>hinder the membrane from hurting the <hi rend="italic">tra-<lb/>chea,</hi> unleſs in
          motions of the neck; theſe <lb/>reaſons may account, in part, for the <w part="I"
            >dimi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nution</w> of that natural irritability, which <w part="I"
            >re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſides</w> in theſe places. But they do not ſatisfy <lb/>me
          altogether. We cannot expect to have <lb/>all our doubts removed. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Corol.</hi> VII. This diſeaſe appears, in <w part="I"
            >ge-</w><lb/><w part="F">neral</w>, to be a very dangerous one, and the <lb/>more ſo, as
          it is ſilent in its progreſs, and <lb/>gives no viſible alarm, till death is near at
          <lb/>hand. The firſt ſtage of this diſtemper, <w part="I">of-</w><lb/><w part="F">ten</w>,
          paſſes unobſerved; and, before we ſee <lb/>it, is beyond all remedy. As it happens, <w
            part="I">fre-</w><lb/><w part="F">quently</w>, to young children, who are unable <lb/>to
          ſpeak or deſcribe their feelings, we have <lb/>double reaſon to be afraid. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_53" n="52"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">If</hi> we be not called till the third or fourth
          <lb/>day; if the breathing appears much affected, <lb/>the pulſe quick and weak, the face
          red, <lb/>great anxiety, and frequent toſſing, the <w part="I">dan-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ger</w> is great and preſſing. But if we ſee the <lb/>patient the firſt or ſecond day
          of the attack; <lb/>if the breathing is not very bad; the pulſe, <lb/>though frequent,
          ſtrong, and firm; and <lb/>more eſpecially, if the voice is only altered, <lb/>in its
          ſtronger exertions of crying or <w part="I">cough-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>, but more
          natural in its common ſtate, <lb/>we may entertain hopes of a recovery. The <lb/>firſt
          ſign commonly of ſafety, is the cough <lb/>becoming ſtronger and leſs dry, with that
          <lb/>peculiar ſound which attends moiſtened <lb/>lungs; for this ſhows that the membrane
          is <lb/>not formed, or is already diſſolved, and that <lb/>the inflammatory ſtate is
          abated. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> caſe ſeems very deſperate, when the
          <lb/>membrane is once formed, and the lungs <lb/>filled with matter. In the latter caſe,
          the <lb/>patient is ſoon ſuffocated, as effectually, tho' <lb/>more ſlowly, as if he was
          immerſed over the <lb/>head in it. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_54" n="53"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> appears, from the preceeding caſes, <lb/>that
          the membrane, alone, is ſufficient to <lb/>kill, as there was but little matter found
          <lb/>in the lungs of ſome of them. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Desperate</hi> as the caſe is, the patient's
          <lb/>recovery is, perhaps, not altogether <w part="I">impoſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſible</w>. Nature, by the means of a critical <lb/>cough, may eject the membrane and
          matter; <lb/>though, indeed, the ſenſation of theſe parts, <lb/>by which it muſt
          effectuate this, ſeems <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">moſt</w> altogether deſtroyed.
          If that <w part="I">happen-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>, the patient would recover, as the
          lungs <lb/>are quite ſound. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> one of the former caſes, part of the
          <lb/>membrane was thrown up, but the patient <lb/>died. I was told by Mr <hi rend="italic"
            >Gibſon</hi> ſurgeon, <lb/>that a patient of his eſcaped, after <w part="I"
            >throw-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> up a great quantity of matter, and <lb/>coughing up
          large pieces of a membrane. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> following curious caſe was <w part="I"
            >commu-</w><lb/><w part="F">nicated</w> to me, lately, by Mr <hi rend="italic">Rae</hi>
          ſurgeon. <lb/>A boy betwixt five and ſix years of age, <lb/>was ſeized, Auguſt 5th, 1764,
          with a ſlight <lb/>cold and hoarſeneſs. On the 8th, had a <w part="I">dif-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ficulty</w> of breathing, the ſhrill voice, and a <pb xml:id="page_55" n="54"
          /><lb/>little fever. As the boy was in a natural ſweat, <lb/>he ordered a mixture with <hi
            rend="italic">Spt. Minder.</hi> 9th, <lb/>Pulſe quicker, and no expectoration. Was
          <lb/>blooded, got an injection, and had a bliſter <lb/>applied to his throat. 11th, This
          morning <lb/>he was told, that, after a ſevere fit of <w part="I">cough-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ing</w>, a membrane-like ſubſtance, about two <lb/>inches long, pretty tough,
          and reſembling a <lb/>piece of thin white leather, had been thrown <lb/>out. In the
          evening, ſome <hi rend="italic">pus</hi> was <w part="I">obſer-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >vable</w> in the phlegm expectorated up, and <w part="I">ea-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſily</w> diſtinguiſhable from it. The boy did <lb/>not recover his voice for three
          months. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Art</hi>, though not in the way of internal
          <lb/>medicine, may attempt effectuating the ſame <lb/>end. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Corol.</hi> VIII. We have had occaſion to <lb/>ſee, in
          the preceeding caſes, great variety of <lb/>different applications, and their good or
          <lb/>bad ſucceſs. Let us deduce ſome general <lb/>rules with regard to practice. In the <w
            part="I">inflam-</w><lb/><w part="F">matory</w> ſtate, bleeding appears to have been
          <lb/>attended with immediate good effects, and <lb/>to be a powerful remedy in this
          ſituation. <lb/>This ought to be done expeditiouſly and <lb/>plentifully, while the pulſe
          will allow it. It <pb xml:id="page_56" n="55"/><lb/>is beſt to take blood at firſt, with
          the <w part="I">lan-</w><lb/><w part="F">cet</w>, ſo that a ſufficient quantity may ſoon
          be <lb/>drawn off; and, afterwards, by leeches, <w part="I">appli-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ed</w> to the upper and fore part of the throat. <lb/>Their orifices, when kept open by
          the <w part="I">appli-</w><lb/><w part="F">cation</w> of warm wet-cloths, will allow the
          <lb/>blood to onze from them for many hours. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> ſeems neceſſary to keep the patient's <lb/>belly
          conſtantly looſe, by ſuch medicines as <lb/>children will take; for we ought to be <w
            part="I">ve-</w><lb/><w part="F">ry</w> attentive not to ſet them a-crying, as that
          <lb/>may ſuddenly ſuffocate the child. For this <lb/>purpoſe, I generally uſe tablets of
            <hi rend="italic">magneſia <lb/>alba,</hi> made palatable with ſugar. Some of <lb/>the
          cooling reſolvent ſalts, ſuch as the <w part="I">chry-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtaliſed</w>
          <hi rend="italic">ſal polychreſt,</hi> diſſolved in whey, will <lb/>be of ſervice,
          provided the patient will <w part="I">peace-</w><lb/><w part="F">ably</w> take them. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Blisters</hi>; applied round the neck, <w part="I"
            >af-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> the veſſels are well emptied, do great <lb/>ſervice.
          They ſeem to do none, when <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">plied</w> before this time;
          nay, if the ſtate is <lb/>very inflammatory, muſt do much hurt, <lb/>from their violent
            <hi rend="italic">ſtimulus</hi> on the veſſels. <lb/>Emollient fomentations and
          cataplaſms, <w part="I">ap-</w><pb xml:id="page_57" n="56"/><lb/><w part="F">plied</w>
          round the neck, are of conſiderable <lb/>uſe, and keep up a local evacuation. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">These</hi> evacuations operate in ſeveral <w part="I"
            >dif-</w><lb/><w part="F">ferent</w> ways, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> by thinning the
          denſe <hi rend="italic">mu-<lb/>cus,</hi> while yet circulating in the blood; by
          <lb/>diverting its flux from the parts affected, as <lb/>there is a great communication
          and conſent <lb/>betwixt the different <hi rend="italic">mucous</hi> glands thro' the
          <lb/>body; but, particularly, by increaſing the <lb/>abſorbent power of the veſſels on
          emptying <lb/>them; by which means the purulent <w part="I">mat-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ter</w> will be ſucked in from the lungs. It was <lb/>found in the urine of one of the
          foregoing <lb/>convaleſcent patients. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> reſolvent and gently ſtimulating <lb/>ſteams of
          warm water and vinegar, drawn in <lb/>with the breath, ſeemed always to have an
          <lb/>immediate good effect. Is it from diſſolving <lb/>the thick <hi rend="italic"
            >mucus,</hi> and ſo oppoſing its <w part="I">concre-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion?</w> That
          is probably the caſe, as the <w part="I">pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tient</w> always ſpits a
          great deal after it, and <lb/>the lungs appear moiſter. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Vomits</hi> are, frequently, given in this <lb/>ſtage of
          the diſeaſe. They are, generally, <lb/>thought to be of uſe; but I never ſaw any <pb
            xml:id="page_58" n="57"/><lb/>advantage ariſing from them. I rather <w part="I"
            >ſu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſpect</w> that they muſt be often pernicious, as <lb/>they
          increaſe the ſecretion of <hi rend="italic">mucus</hi> in the <lb/>lungs, without
          expelling it, which is the <w part="I">ve-</w><lb/><w part="F">ry</w> circumſtance that,
          if poſſible, we ought, <lb/>to guard againſt. The evacuation that they <lb/>make otherways
          is but ſmall. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Gentle</hi> ſudorifics may be of ſervice, as <lb/>they
          divert the flux from the more internal <lb/>parts to the external. Others think that
          <lb/>theſe are of uſe; and preſcribe the <hi rend="italic">Vin. emet.</hi>
          <lb/>in ſmall quantities. I cannot ſay that I ever <lb/>ſaw any great advantage from them. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> when the membrane is once <w part="I"
            >form-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>, or the purulent matter, in great quantity,
          <lb/>collected in the lungs, evacuations can be <lb/>no longer of any uſe; they rather
          hurt, as <lb/>the pulſe is then weak. Hence the reaſon, <lb/>why people differ about the
          effects of <w part="I">evacu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ations</w> in this diſeaſe; ſome deeming
          them <lb/>the only certain remedy, while others hold <lb/>them to be deſtructive. Both
          have built <lb/>their opinion on facts and obſervation. But <lb/>as their applications
          were made in different <lb/>ſtages of the diſtemper, the effects behoved <pb
            xml:id="page_59" n="58"/><lb/>to be different. What was the only remedy <lb/>in the
          inflammatory ſtate, muſt appear <w part="I">hurt-</w><lb/><w part="F">ful</w> in the
          purulent. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> this ſtate of purulency we plainly ſee,
          <lb/>that nothing can do ſervice, but what brings <lb/>up the matter from the lungs, and
          that <w part="I">ſpee-</w><lb/><w part="F">dily</w> too. And pray what medicines can do
          <lb/>this? Vomits only evacuate, immediately, <lb/>the ſtomach; but by means of the <w
            part="I">ſympa-</w><lb/><w part="F">thy</w> of the nerves, they often bring on a
          <lb/>coughing, during their action. They might <lb/>be of ſervice, if they had this
          ſalutary effect; <lb/>but I never ſaw them anſwer this purpoſe, <lb/>though often given
          with that deſign. The <lb/>nerves are, indeed, ſo unactive, that we <lb/>can entertain no
          reaſonable hopes from this <lb/>quarter. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Shall</hi> we endeavour to excite a cough, <lb/>by the
          means of effluvia, or ſteams inſpired <lb/>into the lungs? That has been tried, to no
          <lb/>purpoſe; for the membrane which covers the <lb/><hi rend="italic">trachea,</hi> and
          the <hi rend="italic">mucus</hi> or matter which <w part="I">co-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >vers</w> the lungs, render theſe parts inſenſible <lb/>to any external irritation. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_60" n="59"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>To effectuate a ſolution of the morbid <lb/>membrane, after it is once
          completely formed <lb/>and conſolidated, ſeems to me impoſſible by <lb/>any internal or
          external medicine that I know. <lb/>To effectuate its expulſion appears equally
          <lb/>impoſſible. We have, then, no method <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">maining</w>
          to ſave the patient's life, but that <lb/>of extraction. That cannot be done thro'
          <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">glottis.</hi> When the caſe is deſperate, <lb/>may we not try
            <hi rend="italic">bronchotomy?</hi> I can ſee no <lb/>weighty objection to that
          operation, as the <lb/>membrane can be ſo eaſily got at, and is <w part="I">ve-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ry</w> looſe. Many a more hazardous <w part="I">opera-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tion</w> is daily performed. I would propoſe, <lb/>however, that it ſhould be firſt
          tried on a <lb/>dead ſubject, that we may proceed with all <lb/>manner of caution and
          aſſiſtance. But <lb/>ſomething ought to be tried in this <w part="I">dange-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">rous</w> ſituation. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">We</hi> have now brought our Inquiry to a
          <lb/>concluſion. The facts, we hope, will <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pear</w>
          curious, exact, and ſufficiently <w part="I">nume-</w><lb/><w part="F">rous</w> for our
          purpoſe; the method ſuch as <lb/>as is uſed in mathematics and natural <w part="I"
            >philo-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſophy</w>, for diſcovering unknown truths; and <pb
            xml:id="page_61" n="60"/><lb/>the concluſions new, ſurpriſing, and <w part="I"
            >natu-</w><lb/><w part="F">rally</w> ariſing from the facts. If we have not <lb/>brought
          this Inquiry to that degree of <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">fection</w>, in every
          point, that we could have <lb/>wiſhed, we have the ſatisfaction, at leaſt, to <lb/>think,
          that, ſo far as we go, our diſcoveries <lb/>are certain, as they are built on the <w
            part="I">foun-</w><lb/><w part="F">dation</w> of Nature. Shunning, with all <w part="I"
            >ima-</w><lb/><w part="F">ginable</w> care, fruitleſs and deceitful <w part="I"
            >ſpecula-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w>, however entertaining, we have <w part="I"
            >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtantly</w> kept our facts and experiments <lb/>in view, as
          the only road to the <w part="I">improve-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w> of medicine, and
          the good of <w part="I">man-</w><lb/><w part="F">kind</w>. </p>
        <trailer rend="italic align-center"><lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
