<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: Inoculation made easy.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Inoculation made easy: Containing a full and true discovery of the
              method practised in the county of Essex. ... With a true receipt to make the
              preparative powders, repellent pills, and the punch used in inoculation.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">N2355</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N2355"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for the author; and sold by R. Withy, at the Royal
                  Exchange; T. Vernor and J. Chater, on Ludgate-Hill; and L. Hassall, at
                  Chelmsford.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1766</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="3"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="11"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">National Library of Medicine</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3308125369</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K001562.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: method"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2" n="iii"/>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>TO THE <lb/><hi rend="size(2)">PUBLIC</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE terrible Havock the <hi rend="italic">Small Pox</hi> hath
          of late made amongſt <lb/>Mankind in ſeveral Parts of the World, together with the
          <lb/>fearful Apprehenſions ſo many Thouſands now lie under, dreading <lb/>the Effect of
          this fatal and ſore Diſorder, induces me to offer the <lb/>following Pages to the Public.
          For I cannot appear juſtifiable to <lb/>myſelf, that a Secret which hath never failed to
          procure this Diſtem- <lb/>per in the moſt ſafe, eaſy, and mild Manner, ſhould be any
          longer <lb/>kept from the Public. But, in the Proſecution of this (perhaps) <lb/>a few
          Individuals, whoſe principal Motive is Self-Intereſt, may be <lb/>offended at my
          publiſhing a Subject to the World which they think <lb/>ſhould be confined to the Faculty
          only. <hi rend="italic">Salus Populi,</hi> I think, will <lb/>hold good in the Matter, and
          to anſwer this Purpoſe more effectually <lb/>I ſhall omit all ſet Phraſes and technical
          Terms; as the Intention <lb/>of this is not meant to diſplay the Grammarian or Orator,
          Humanity <lb/>being the leading Principle, for Advantages I want none. Humane <lb/>it muſt
          evidently be, to point out a certain, plain, and infallible Me- <lb/>thod of relieving the
          Diſtreſſes of our Fellow-Creatures; few <lb/>Diſorders having produc'd more public
          Calamity than that loathſome <lb/>Diſtemper, and from Time to Time, the moſt eminent
          Phyſicians <lb/>have on thoſe Occaſions found themſelves at their <hi rend="italic">ne
            plus ultra.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Therefore a Method which is here offer'd, not only regarding <lb/>the Preparation of
          the Patient, but likewiſe the Treatment during <lb/>the whole Cure; the Efficacy of which
          being hereby laid open to <pb xml:id="page_3" n="iv"/>
          <lb/>the Public, the ſurprizing ſalutary Service reſulting will ſpeak more <lb/>for the
          Author than any pompous Apology. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Diſcoveries of any Kind, however rational or beneficial, are ge- <lb/>nerally
          received with ſome Degree of Dubiety: It muſt not there- <lb/>fore ſeem ſtrange if this of
          mine ſhould be objected to by ſome, <lb/>who, for want of other Arguments, will quarrel
          with it on a religious <lb/>Account: But to thoſe good People I ſhall ſtate this Caſe of
          Con- <lb/>ſcience by obſerving. That the Almighty God in his great Mercy to <lb/>Mankind
          hath taught us a Remedy to be uſed to prevent the fatal <lb/>Effects of the <hi
            rend="italic">Small Pox,</hi> upon the Uſe of which, the Patient will <lb/>be unattended
          with thoſe direful and dreadful Apprehenſions, ſo <lb/>long the Companions of this
          Diſtemper; and in conſequence of the <lb/>Means here offered, neither Health nor Life in
          Danger. To theſe <lb/>People I appeal, whether a Chriſtian may not employ this Remedy,
          <lb/>and be very thankful to a Supreme Being for his Good Providence <lb/>in cauſing
          Mankind to be able to make a Diſcovery, ſo beneficial <lb/>and valuable in its Nature; and
          the peculiar Bleſſing attending the <lb/>Succeſs thereof, evidently to be produc'd by the
          Thouſands which <lb/>have happily and ſafely recovered without Pain, or even Confinement
          <lb/>to their Beds. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But poſſibly there may be thoſe, whom no Arguments can prevail <lb/>upon. I ſhall
          therefore ſpend no more Time in the Attempt to <lb/>convince them of the Lawfulneſs and
          Goodneſs in the Practice of <lb/>Inoculation, but refer them to Experience, which will
          certainly <lb/>open the Eyes of thoſe few Oppoſers to this ſafe and ſalutary Method.
          <lb/>The whole of which I have endeavoured to lay down in a plain and <lb/>eaſy (tho' not
          elegant) Dreſs; for my Endeavour is to be underſtood <lb/>by every Body, and the Reader
          may depend that no Medicine is here <lb/>offered but what is founded upon, and is the
          Reſult of, long Obſer- <lb/>vation and Experience. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I ſhall conclude with obſerving, that thoſe who make uſe of the <lb/>Means here
          offered them will be ſufficiently convinced of the Humanity <lb/>and Integrity of the
          Author. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_4" n="5"/>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A horizontal double-line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <head rend="sc size(1.5) space align-center">
        <lb/>INOCULATION <lb/><hi rend="space">Made Easy, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </hi>
      </head>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="3"> </space>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HE fatal Conſequences which in general attend that loath-
        <lb/>ſome and very dangerous Diſtemper, the <hi rend="sc">Small Pox</hi>, the <lb/>dreadful
        Havock it has made, from Time to Time, amongſt <lb/>Mankind has induced ſeveral humane,
        learned, and able Men, to uſe <lb/>their utmoſt Endeavours to find out a Method to render
        this alarmîng <lb/>Diſorder more mild and favourable. <hi rend="sc">Inoculation</hi> was
        then thought <lb/>on. The <hi rend="italic">Greeks</hi> are ſaid to be the firſt Nation that
        practiſed this <lb/>Method; the <hi rend="italic">Turks</hi> are ſuppoſed to have borrowed
        it from them, <lb/>and practiſed it with the greateſt Succeſs, not only for the <hi
          rend="italic">Small <lb/>Pox</hi>, but even for the <hi rend="italic">Plague</hi> itſelf.
        The frequent Accounts we <lb/>had of their great Succeſs in almoſt putting a total Stop to
        the Fata- <lb/>lity of this ſore Diſtemper, induced us to follow their Example; <lb/>but,
        however this may be, it was practiſed by us at firſt with no <lb/>very conſiderable Succeſs,
        yet it proved much more favourable in its <lb/>Effects than the natural Kind. This
        occaſioned ſeveral others to <lb/>attempt a ſtill farther Improvement, and has from Time to
        Time, <lb/>been brought to a ſtill greater Degree of Perfection, ſo that out of an
        <lb/>Hundred Patients, perhaps only Two or Three have loſt their Lives; <lb/>tho' a great
        Part of them have had the Diſtemper in a very ſore and <lb/>terrible Manner. But by the
        Aſſiſtance of an Almighty Providence <lb/>we have now brought it to the very utmoſt and
        greateſt Degree of <lb/>Perfection imaginable; ſo that in fact it now ceaſes to be any
        longer <pb xml:id="page_5" n="6"/>
        <lb/>a Diſtemper; for what can be a greater Proof, what can aſcertain <lb/>the Excellency of
        this new Method more than the plain and con- <lb/>vincing Demonſtrations we have now before
        our Eyes, and the <lb/>Thouſands of living Witneſſes to prove it? for Nine Thouſand
        <lb/>People or more, who have been inoculated, (within Thirty Miles <lb/>round the Town of
          <hi rend="italic">Chelmsford</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Eſſex,</hi> and within the Space of
        <lb/>theſe two laſt Years) not a Single Patient has loſt his Life; and <lb/>what is ſtill
        more extraordinary, they have had this Diſtemper in ſo <lb/>mild and favourable a Manner,
        that the greater Part of them have <lb/>been capable of carrying on their Trades and
        Buſineſs during the <lb/>whole Time, not being confined by it one Hour to their Bed or
        <lb/>Room; except out of a Complement to thoſe who have not had it, <lb/>and would be
        fearful of catching it from them, may have induced <lb/>ſome to keep up a few Days, but not
        from the Effect of the Diſtem- <lb/>per. This Method has alſo theſe ſeveral Advantages with
        it; <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
        <lb/>That it has been tried and anſwers with all Ages and Complexions, <lb/>on every
        Conſtitution; the robuſt and infirm, the black and the fair, <lb/>the corpulent and the
        lean; and in each extreme Seaſon of the <lb/>Year, the Summer and the Winter. Nor has it
        failed in any one <lb/>Inſtance; the Patient being ſubject to very ſlight Symptoms, ſenſible
        <lb/>of very little Sickneſs; nor do what few Eruptions they have, ever <lb/>leave any Scars
        or Pits behind them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I think it unneceſſary to ſay any thing farther in Behalf of this <lb/>excellent Method
        of recovering the Diſtemper. Therefore ſhall <lb/>immediately proceed to lay before my
        Readers the Manner and Me- <lb/>dicines, which will anſwer all thoſe extraordinary Virtues
        above <lb/>mentioned. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Firſt</hi>, As to the Manner of preparing the Body to receive the
        <lb/>Infection.—But as the Preparation is material, and of ſome Im- <lb/>portance, I hope no
        one, who intends to be inoculated, will be ſo <lb/>far an Enemy to themſelves, as not to be
        ſtrictly careful and atten- <lb/>tive to the Rules here laid down; which are meant to lower
        the <lb/>Blood and Humours, and render the Body ſufficiently prepared to <lb/>receive the
        Infection in the moſt favourable Manner. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>You muſt abſtain from all Salt Proviſions whatever, nor muſt you <lb/>eat any Kind of
        Meat or Butter; nor drink Beer or Spirituous Liquors, <lb/>not even Wine; Cheeſe and ſpiced
        Foods are likewiſe prejudicial.— <pb xml:id="page_6" n="7"/>
        <lb/>But to make it more clear, I have ſet down a Regimen, or Method <lb/>of preparing,
        which muſt be continued and perſevered in for Nine <lb/>Days at leaſt, and is as follows: </p>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Directions for preparing for Inoculation. </head>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Diet</hi> for <hi rend="sc">Breakfast</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Tea, Coffee, or Chocolate, with dry Toaſt, or ordinary Cake; <lb/>Rice-Milk:
            Milk-Gruel: Skimmed Milk, Honey and Bread, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>For <hi rend="sc">Dinner</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Plumb or Plain Pudding with Vinegar Sauce, which is made by <lb/>adding Sugar and
            Vinegar to a proper Quantity of boiled Flour and <lb/>Water: Rice-Pudding:
            Apple-Pudding: Apple-Pye: Rice-Milk: <lb/>Frumenty: And the Productions of the
            Kitchen-Garden, with the <lb/>Uſe of Salt. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>For <hi rend="sc">Supper</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Any of the above Spoon Meats: Roaſted Potatoes: Turnips, <hi rend="italic"
              >&amp;c.</hi>
            <lb/>But, if it can be complied with, going to Bed <hi rend="italic">Supperleſs</hi>,
            and to <lb/><hi rend="italic">eat ſparingly</hi> even at other Meals, will be moſt
            proper; and, as <lb/>obſerved above, abſtain from all Fleſh, Butter, Cheeſe, and Spiced
            <lb/>Food. Moſt Kind of Fruits may be eaten at pleaſure, except on the <lb/>Phyſical
            Days. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="subsection">
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>DRINK. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In common it may be Toaſt and Water, Milk and Water, Lemon <lb/>and Water, or
            Imperial Water; abſtaining from all ſpirituous, <lb/>vinous, and malt Liquors. Moderate
            Exerciſe withal is neceſſary. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Directions for taking the <hi rend="roman">Preparative Powders</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>After having ſtrictly obſerved the foregoing Rules for Nine Days, <lb/>you muſt take
          one of the Papers of Powders at Bed-Time, in the <lb/>Pulp of a roaſted Apple, or any
          Jelly, and next Morning a Paper <lb/>of the Salts, diſſolved in a little boiling Water,
          drinking plentifully <lb/>of Water-Gruel, Cheeſe-Whey, or Small Tea, as they work. The
          <lb/>Patient ſhould be very careful of Cold, during the Operation of <pb xml:id="page_7"
            n="8"/>
          <lb/>the Phyſic; and if it does not operate Six or Eight Times in about <lb/>Six Hours, it
          will be neceſſary to take half another Paper of the <lb/>Salts, (more or leſs as Occaſion
          requires). Or if they be vomited <lb/>up ſhortly after being taken, as ſoon as the
          Sickneſs is entirely off, <lb/>one of the other Papers of Salts muſt be given. The other
          Powders <lb/>and Salts are to be taken as above, omitting Three Days between <lb/>each
          Doſe. The Deficiency of Salts may be had at an Apothecary's: <lb/>It will be requiſite for
          the Patient to have a Stool on each of the <lb/>intermediate Days during the Preparation,
          in order to which Stew'd <lb/>Prunes, Roaſted Apples, or Tamarinds, ſhould be eaten
          occaſionally. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>I ſhall now inform my Reader how to make every Medicine to be <lb/>uſed throughout
          the Diſorder, and firſt the <hi rend="sc">Preparative Powders</hi>
          <lb/>are as follows. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Take ten Grains of Calomel and one Grain of factitious Cinnabar, <lb/>and mix them
          well together for one Doſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>A Child of ſix Years old may take a fourth part of a Paper; from <lb/>eight Years old
          to twelve half a Paper, and from twelve Years old <lb/>to fifty a whole Paper; from ſixty
          Years old to an hundred half a <lb/>Paper; be careful not to omit taken the Salts in the
          Morning as before <lb/>ordered; the Salts are <hi rend="italic">Glauber</hi>'s Salts. A
          grown Perſon may take <lb/>from half an Ounce to an Ounce, Children half an Ounce only:
          <lb/>Theſe <hi rend="sc">Powders</hi> greatly cleanſe the Blood, are not only very effec-
          <lb/>tual to prepare the Body for the <hi rend="italic">Small-Pox</hi>; but may alſo be
          depend- <lb/>ed upon as a never failing Remedy for Worms, as it ſcours away thoſe
          <lb/>roped viſcid Humours which are apt to breed them in the Bowels; they <lb/>may be
          taken with the greateſt Safety by Men, Women and Children, <lb/>obſerving the above Rules:
          they are good likewiſe in Cutaneous Diſ- <lb/>orders, ſuch as Foulneſs of the Skin, or
          Sores or Ulcers, and teterous <lb/>Eruptions, the Itch and Leproſy; and thoſe who are
          unwilling to <lb/>be Inoculated, yet fearful of catching the <hi rend="italic"
            >Small-Pox</hi>, in the natural <lb/>Way, may in a great Meaſure, be ſecured from it by
          taking the above <lb/><hi rend="sc">Powders</hi>, for it Purifies the Blood in ſuch a
          Manner as to render it leſs <lb/>liable to the receive the Infection. Or if the Diſtemper
          ſhould be <lb/>caught after taking the <hi rend="sc">Powders</hi>, the Patient may depend
          upon having <lb/>it in a more favourable Manner. Theſe <hi rend="sc">Powders</hi> are alſo
          very valu- <pb xml:id="page_8" n="9"/>
          <lb/>able as a Common Purge in the Spring of the Year, but Salts muſt <lb/>in all Caſes be
          taken after them. Obſerve, that when Children from <lb/>two to five Years old are to be
          Inoculated, it will not be proper <lb/>to give them the <hi rend="sc">Powder</hi>, but
          inſtead of which you muſt give them <lb/>a Dram of Manna diſſolved in warm Milk or Water,
          repeat it each <lb/>Day, and continue it for a Week or ten Days, at the End of which
          <lb/>time you may Inoculate them. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>After the Patient has ſufficiently prepared himſelf by ſtrictly follow- <lb/>ing the
          Directions for the Regimen; that is, having Dieted himſelf <lb/>one Week, and the next
          Week dieting as before, and taken his <hi rend="sc"> Pow- <lb/>ders</hi>, he is now fit
          for Inoculation, which is very eaſily perform'd <lb/>as follows: You muſt get ſome Matter
          out of a Ripe Pock upon the <lb/>Point of a Needle, ſharp-top Pen-knife, or Launcet, and
          with any of <lb/>theſe Inſtruments (having the freſh Matter on its point) you muſt
          <lb/>make a ſmall Inciſion or Prick on the Arm, between the Elbow <lb/>and the Shoulder;
          you need only make the ſmalleſt Drop of Blood <lb/>appear, and wiping the mattery Part of
          the Inſtrument on the Place, <lb/>'tis done. In about four or five Days the Inoculated
          Part will grow <lb/>a little red; in a few Days more it will riſe to a Kind of Puſtule ha-
          <lb/>ving Matter in it; after which it decreaſes and goes away of itſelf. <lb/>Several of
          my Patients have only had this Eruption, and no other <lb/>Appearance of the <hi
            rend="italic">Small-Pox</hi> upon them; but it is as effectual as <lb/>having a large
          Number of Puſtules. In about ſix or ſeven Days af- <lb/>ter the Inoculation, the Patient
          ſometimes feels a Kind of a ſlight <lb/>Pain in the Inoculated Arm, in his Back and Head,
          but all thoſe <lb/>Symptoms ſoon go off. About five Days after the Inoculation, the
          <lb/>Patient (if of a robuſt groſs Habit of Body) muſt at Night, going to <lb/>Bed, take
          one of the <hi rend="italic">Repellent Pills</hi>; if it operates but little, take an-
          <lb/>other in the Morning; if that ſhould have no conſiderable Effect, <lb/>take two more
          Pills again at Night; on the contrary take only one, <lb/>the remainder to be taken the
          next Morning. The Intention of theſe <lb/>Pills are to carry off the Matter which would
          occaſion Eruptions. <lb/>The Pills are made as follows <note place="bottom" n="†"
            rend="size(0.5)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>† The Patient muſt obſerve to continue ſtrictly to the Regimen till all the
              Symptoms <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Small Pox</hi> have left him: which from the
              Preparation to the Recovery is gene- <lb/>rally about three Weeks. </p>
          </note>. </p>
        <div type="subsection">
          <pb xml:id="page_11" n="10"/>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Repellent Pill</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="hanging">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Take</hi> ten Grains of Kermes Mineral <note place="bottom" n="*"
              rend="size(0.5)">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>* For the Virtues of Kermes Mineral, <hi rend="italic">See</hi> Dr. <hi
                  rend="italic">James</hi>'s Diſpenſatory. </p>
            </note>, twenty Grains of the beſt <lb/>Succotrine Aloes, and ten Grains of Camphor, add
            a ſufficient <lb/>quantity of Spirits of Wine to make them into a Maſs for Pills,
            <lb/>which is done by beating them together in a Mortar; of this Com- <lb/>poſition make
            four Pills. </p>
          <p rend="italic hanging">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">N. B.</hi> You muſt firſt pound the Camphor with a few drops of
            Spirits <lb/>of Wine, then mix the other Ingredients. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Some few have a ſlight Fever at the time of breeding the Pock, <lb/>thoſe are
            deſired to drink plentifully of the following Decoction, or <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >Punch</hi>, as it is termed in <hi rend="italic">Eſſex</hi>. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The Patient may have it made, or make it himſelf, the Effects of <lb/>which is to
            carry off the Fever. The Receipt is as follows. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take unground Oats a Handful, and boil them for ſome time in <lb/>a Quart of
            Spring-Water, then ſtrain it, with which mix half an <lb/>Ounce of Stibiated Nitre, half
            an Ounce of Citron, or Lemon-Juice, <lb/>and an Ounce and half of the Sirup of Violets.
            About ſix or ſeven <lb/>Days after Inoculation this Liquor ſhould be drank very
            plentifully, as <lb/>it tends from its cooling Quality to carry off every Symptom of the
            <lb/>Fever.—[The Ingredients may be had at any Apothecary's; nor <lb/>muſt the Patient
            be without it.] </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>But to make this uſeful Liquor more cheap and eaſy to the Poor, <lb/>I have ſet
            down another Method of making of it, which in a great <lb/>Meaſure will anſwer all the
            Intentions of the firſt, and is as follows. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Boil a Handful of Oats in a Quart of Spring-Water, add to it after <lb/>it is
            ſtrain'd, half an Ounce of Salt-Petre; ſharpen this Liquor with a <lb/>little Lemon
            Juice or Vinegar, and ſweeten it to the Palate with <lb/>brown Sugar or Honey. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This will not be ſo pleaſant as the firſt Method of making it, tho' <lb/>almoſt as
            effectual; by drinking plentifully of this the Fever will be <lb/>almoſt immediately
            lowered: The firſt taking of it ſhould be to drink <lb/>half a Pint, or more at going to
            Bed at Night. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>I have now gone through the whole Progreſs of the Cure, and if all <lb/>the Rules
            here laid down are ſtrictly attended to, the Patient may de- <lb/>pend upon having the
            Diſtemper in the moſt favourable manner. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_12" n="11"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The great Succeſs which in general attends this Method of Ino- <lb/>culation is no
            ways ſurpriſing; nor need we wonder at ſo many <lb/>dying with it that have it in the
            Natural Way; for when we come <lb/>to conſider, that while the contagious Matter is
            exerting its Malig- <lb/>nity upon the Humours, (which is generally ſeven or eight Days)
            <lb/>Quietneſs, Moderation in Diet, together with cleanſing Medicines, <lb/>and every
            thing elſe is ſtrictly obſerved in Inoculation; whereas ma- <lb/>ny incur the Natural
            Diſtemper on a ſudden, when the Blood is <lb/>heated with Wine and Exerciſe, by which
            means all the Symptoms <lb/>muſt neceſſarily prove more ſevere and dangerous. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>I would alſo obſerve, that I do not pretend to perſuade the Public, <lb/>that all
            the Inoculators in <hi rend="italic">Eſſex</hi> make uſe of theſe Medicines exactly
            <lb/>as here ſet down, or that all of them make uſe of the ſame Com- <lb/>poſitions: I
            only ſay that the greateſt Succeſs may be depended upon <lb/>from a proper uſe of theſe
            Medicines, they having all that Virtue <lb/>comprehended in them, which is neceſſary to
            render the Diſorder <lb/>mild and favourable, as I have happily experienced by the
            Number <lb/>of Patients, who have recovered from this Diſtemper without being
            <lb/>confined to their Bed or ſcarce ſenſible of any Pain. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>I ſhall conclude this Treatiſe with ſome few Cautions to thoſe who <lb/>take the
            Medicines. Thoſe of a very weak and delicate Conſtitution, <lb/>may prepare with taking
            only half a Paper of the <hi rend="sc">Powders</hi> at a time <lb/>with the Salts, and
            go on till all the Papers are taken. In caſe the <lb/><hi rend="sc">Powders</hi> ſhould
            cauſe the Mouth to water, or an Inclination to <lb/>Spitting, (which I never knew happen
            in the Courſe of my Practice) <lb/>upon ſuch an occaſion, the Patient muſt take larger
            Doſes of Salts, <lb/>and about an Hour after take near half an Ounce of Flour of Brim-
            <lb/>ſtone, which will prove an effectual Remedy. Be careful of the <lb/>Subject which
            you Inoculate from, that it be a mild and favourable <lb/>Sort, and that the Perſon is
            free from any other Diſtemper. The <lb/>Patient, as I have before obſerved, muſt the
            firſt Week prepare by <lb/>Diet, &amp;c. the next Week prepare to take the <hi rend="sc"
              >Powders</hi>, (living as <lb/>by Direction above) then Inoculate, and upon breeding
            the Pock, <lb/>drink plentifully of the <hi rend="italic">Punch</hi> before mentioned,
            and the Patient will <lb/>find this Method anſwer his moſt ſanguine Wiſhes. </p>
          <p rend="indent italic">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">N. B.</hi> In about a Week after the <hi rend="roman"
              >Small-Pox</hi> is quite over, it would <lb/>be neceſſary for the Patient to loſe a
            little Blood, and take a Doſe of Salts. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <trailer rend="sc align-center space">
        <lb/>The END. </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
