<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Farrer: A short treatise on onanism</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>William Farrer</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">A SHORT TREATISE ON ONANISM; OR, The Detestable Vice of
              SELF-POLLUTION. Describing the Variety of nervous and other Disorders, that are
              occasioned by that shameful Practice, or too early and excessive Venery, and directing
              the best Method for their Cure.</title>
            <edition n="2"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">N23046</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N23046"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed and sold by Fletcher and Co. Book-Sellers, at the
                  Oxford-Theatre, the North-Side of St. Paul's Church-Yard, 1767.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1767</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="5"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="39"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="6"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">Countway Library of Medicine</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3308065916</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K013381.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: disease"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>A SHORT<lb/>
          <hi rend="size(1)">TREATISE</hi><lb/> ON<lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)"> ONANISM.</hi>
        </head>
        <lb/>
        <l>Phyſicians are agreed that Copulation, </l>
        <lb/>
        <l>When age adult, and high-brac'd nerves invite, </l>
        <lb/>
        <l>Shou'd neither be immoderately deſired, </l>
        <lb/>
        <l>Nor dreaded to exceſs. The good old man </l>
        <lb/>
        <l>Is by his tame frigidity admoniſhed, </l>
        <lb/>
        <l>Not to engage in the dull drudgery, </l>
        <lb/>
        <l>Miſtaken for enchanting ſcenes of pleaſure; </l>
        <lb/>
        <l>Leſt thus he ſnap his feeble thread of life. </l>
        <lb/>
        <l>But what more baſe, more noxious to the body, </l>
        <lb/>
        <l>Than by the power of fancy to excite </l>
        <lb/>
        <l>Such lewd ideas of an abſent object; </l>
        <lb/>
        <l>As rouſe the organs form'd for nobler ends, </l>
        <lb/>
        <l>To ruſh into th' embraces of a phantom, </l>
        <lb/>
        <l>And do the deed of perſonal enjoyment! </l>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_3"/>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>THE <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">PREFACE.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>THIS little Treatiſe was at firſt not intended to be publiſhed <w
            part="I">ſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">parate</w>, but only to be annexed to <w part="I"
            >ano-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> work of the author's, printed at the ſame time,
          entitled, <hi rend="italic">Obſervations on <w part="I">Spe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cific</w>
            Medicines,</hi> &amp;c. But as many may have an occaſion to peruſe this part without the
          other, who would not care to be at the expence of purchaſing both together, a few copies
          were printed off ſeparate for this reaſon. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_4" n="viii"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>All the merit which the author <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tends</w> to in this, as well as in the other Treatiſe, is, his having offered to <w
            part="I">man-</w><lb/><w part="F">kind</w> the means for relief, eſtabliſhed upon
          reiterated experience, (the moſt infallible foundation for the ſcience of phyſic) which
          will ſcarce ever fail of giving ſatisfaction to the miſerable <w part="I">pa-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tient</w>; eſpecially if the rules and <w part="I">direc-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tions</w> preſcribed, and given with the medicines herein recommended, are ſtrictly
          adhered to. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In long protracted and obſtinate caſes, which will not eaſily yield to
          the <w part="I">gene-</w><lb/><w part="F">ral</w> method of cure, herein mentioned, the
          author deſires to be conſulted <w part="I">ei-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> in perſon or
          by letter. He requeſts thoſe who <hi rend="italic">ſend</hi> their caſes, to be very
          particular with reſpect to the ſymptoms of their indiſpoſition, length of time they have
          been afflicted, what means <pb xml:id="page_5" n="ix"/>they have already uſed, and
          likewiſe their age, preſent degree of ſtrength, conſtitution, habit of body, &amp;c. and
          all letters, (poſt-paid) directed to him, to be left at Mr <hi rend="italic"
          >Fletcher</hi>'s and Co. <w part="I">book-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſellers</w>, at the <hi
            rend="italic">Oxford-Theatre,</hi> on the <hi rend="italic">North-Side</hi> of <hi
            rend="italic">St. Paul's Church Yard,</hi> ſhall have due attention paid them, and be
          anſwered with all the ſpeed that the diſtance of place will admit of. </p>
        <dateline>LONDON, <hi rend="italic">Nov.</hi> 1766. </dateline>
        <signed>W. FARRER. </signed>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_6"/>
      <head rend="align-center"><lb/>A SHORT <lb/>TREATISE<lb/> ON<lb/> ONANISM. </head>
      <p rend="space"><lb/>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>Decorative frame around the letter "M"</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <hi rend="italic">MASTUPRATIO,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Ma-<lb/>nuſtupratio;</hi> Manual
        Stupration, or Self-Pollution, <lb/>is a vice hardly to be named, much leſs <lb/>to be
        practiſed in a country, where virtue, <lb/>decency, or politeneſs, have the leaſt <w
          part="I">re-</w><pb xml:id="page_7" n="12"/><lb/><w part="F">gard</w> paid to them; and
        this abominable and <lb/>unmanly practice is productive of the moſt <lb/>deplorable, and
        generally incurable <w part="I">diſor-</w><lb/><w part="F">ders</w>. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Providence has implanted in human <w part="I">na-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ture</w> what is by ſome called, <hi rend="italic">the Paſſion <lb/>of Love,</hi> and by
        others, <hi rend="italic">the Appetite of Luſt,</hi>
        <lb/>for very wiſe purpoſes; but has given us <lb/>reaſon to reſtrain this neceſſary
        inclination, <lb/>and keep it within due limits. Every day, <lb/>however, furniſhes us with
        caſes which <lb/>evince, that reaſon is not always a ballance <lb/>againſt the appetites;
        for boys regardleſs, <lb/>or perhaps ignorant of the conſequences, <lb/>too frequently
        indulge themſelves in this <lb/>prepoſterous method of venery; and it is <lb/>beyond a
        doubt, that many, more <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">vanced</w> in years, who are long
        immured in <lb/>colleges and cloiſters, and at laſt elope <lb/>from their cells, utterly
        deſtitute of ſcience, <lb/>and equally unacquainted with the world <lb/>and books, are not
        leſs guilty of this <w part="I">enor-</w><lb/><w part="F">mous</w> vice. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_8" n="13"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe by a moſt deteſtable kind of <lb/>magic, conjure up at pleaſure an
        ideal <hi rend="italic">Ve-<lb/>nus,</hi> and thus never want an opportunity <lb/>of
        enjoying an imaginary miſtreſs. The <lb/>frequent repetition of theſe execrable <w part="I"
          >plea-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſures</w> induce an infinitude of the worſt <w part="I"
          >diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">orders</w>; ſuch as Lethargies, Vertigo's, <lb/>Atrophys,
        Apoplexies, Palſies, Lowneſs <lb/>of Spirits, Hypochondriacal Diſorders, <lb/>Amauroſes, a
        Tabes Dorſalis, and the worſt <lb/>ſpecies of a Gonorrhæa, moſt commonly <lb/>attended with
        an utter impotence as to <lb/>real enjoyments; beſides an innumerable <lb/>train of various
        nervous complaints, ſuch <lb/>as are the frequent attendants upon a <w part="I"
          >de-</w><lb/><w part="F">clining</w> age, when the vigour of youth <w part="I"
          >be-</w><lb/><w part="F">gins</w> to wear off. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe diſorders chiefly derive their <w part="I">ori-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">gin</w> from thoſe univerſal convulſions, that <lb/>always attend the emiſſion of
        the <hi rend="italic">Semen;</hi>
        <lb/>and if we conſider the human body, as made <lb/>up of flexible pipes, and yielding
        fluids, <lb/>we ſhall readily underſtand how <w part="I">Convul-</w><pb xml:id="page_9"
          n="14"/><lb/><w part="F">ſions</w> wear out the conſtitution, and <w part="I"
          >pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duce</w> theſe effects, viz. by deſtroying the <lb/>ſtrength and
        elaſticity of the ſolid parts. <lb/>And that the extacy which accompanies <lb/>venereal
        enjoyments is of the nature of a <lb/>convulſion, is not hard to be conceived. <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Quincy,</hi> in his explanation of <hi rend="italic">Sanctorius</hi>'s
        <lb/>Aphoriſms expreſſly ſays, that <q rend="diple">At the <lb/>time of coition, the fibres
          are intenſely <lb/>drawn up; that too frequent uſe of this <lb/>exerciſe, cannot but be
          very prejudicial to <lb/>health by overſtraining and deſtroying the f<lb/>orce of the
            fibres<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Sect iv. Aphoriſm i. </note></q>;
        the natural <w part="I">conſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">quence</w> of which muſt be a ſpringyneſs
        and <lb/>action upon their contents. Hence <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſpiration</w> is leſſened,<note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† Mala a nimio
          Coitu orta mediate a Perſpiratione.<lb/>Sanctor. Sect. vi. Aphoriſm iii. </note> the
        fluids run into <lb/>preternatural coheſions, and obſtructions are <lb/>generated. And this
        morbid condition is <lb/>ſtill augmented by an exceſſive loſs of the <pb xml:id="page_10"
          n="15"/><lb/><hi rend="italic">Semen</hi> itſelf, ſince the blood is thereby <lb/>robbed
        of its moſt pure, balſamic, and <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">vigorating</w>
        particles. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Beſides, it is worthy of remark, that <lb/>people who are accuſtomed to
        ſuch <w part="I">filthi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w>, are not ſo eaſily cured of any <w
          part="I">chro-</w><lb/><w part="F">nical</w> diſtemper as thoſe who are free from <lb/>it;
        for as <hi rend="italic">Celſus,</hi> ſpeaking about venereal <lb/>intercourſes, prudently
        remarks, <hi rend="italic">Caven-<lb/>dumne in ſecunda valetudine adverſæ preſidia
          <lb/>conſumantur:</hi> that is, <q rend="quotes">We ſhould take <lb/>care of conſuming
          wantonly in a ſtate <lb/>of health, what would be our ſupport <lb/>during ſickneſs.</q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Semen verile,</hi> is a fluid of the <lb/>moſt
        elaborate and noble production in <lb/>the whole body, except that of the nerves, <lb/>if
        ſuch there be; and it is this vital feed <lb/>which makes men hot, robuſt, hairy, <lb/>of a
        ſtrong and deep voice, bold and <lb/>courageous, and fit to contrive, or <w part="I"
          >exe-</w><pb xml:id="page_11" n="16"/><lb/><w part="F">cute</w> any enterprize. Men are a
        proof of <lb/>this; whereas they who are deſtitute of <w part="I">vi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tal</w> Seed, are wrinkled, pale, weak, of a <lb/>ſhrill voice, without hair, beardleſs
        and <w part="I">ef-</w><lb/><w part="F">feminate</w>; ſuch are eunuchs. For we know
        <lb/>from experience, when the ſecretory <w part="I">or-</w><lb/><w part="F">gans</w> of
        this juice are deſtroyed by <w part="I">caſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">tration</w> before the time
        of puberty, as is <lb/>frequently done in <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi> to preſerve the
        <lb/>voice; or if by any accident a man is <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">prived</w> of
        his teſticles after this age, the <lb/>deſtruction of theſe marks of verility alſo
        <lb/>follow, in confirmation of this <hi rend="italic">Boerhaave</hi>
        <lb/>has given us an inſtance of fact. <q rend="quotes">There <lb/>was, ſays he, an intrepid
          ſoldier, who, <lb/>aſpiring after the reward propoſed by <lb/>the general, to him who
          would firſt fix <lb/>the ſtandard in the enemies fort, climbed <lb/>through the thick
          battery of the enemy, <lb/>but unfortunately the fire of a cannon <lb/>took off both his
          teſticles; yet he <w part="I">reco-</w><lb/><w part="F">vered</w>, and became at length <w
            part="I">effemi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nate</w>, not in mind but in body. The
          <lb/>ſtrength of the ſeveral muſcles of the <lb/>genital parts ſtill continued, and <w
            part="I">no-</w><pb xml:id="page_12" n="17"/><lb/><w part="F">thing</w> towards his
          virility but his teſticles, <lb/>and yet his voice ſoon altered, and beard <lb/>fell off,
          &amp;c.</q> But the man who is <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">tentive</w> of the
        ſeminal juices, becomes bold, <lb/>hardy and ſtrong, like the beaſts of the <lb/>foreſt;
        witneſs the <hi rend="italic">Athletæ</hi> of old, who <lb/>led chaſte lives. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Therefore as the <hi rend="italic">Semen</hi> is, as it were, <lb/>the
        flower and choiceſt part of the blood <lb/>and nervous fluid, ſo venery ought to be
        <lb/>only moderately uſed; leſt too great an <lb/>evacuation of this ſubſtance prove <w
          part="I">preju-</w><lb/><w part="F">dicial</w> to health. A frequent ejection of <lb/>the
          <hi rend="italic">Semen</hi> requires a ſound and vigorous <lb/>habit of body, becauſe it
        exhauſts the <lb/>ſtrength, and weakens the perſon; hence <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Pythagoras</hi> when asked, when coition was <lb/>to be uſed, wiſely anſwered, <q
          rend="quotes">When <lb/>you have an inclination to render <w part="I">your-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſelf</w> weaker.</q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>As venery then only agrees with perſons <lb/>of robuſt and vigorous
        conſtitutions, ſo <pb xml:id="page_13" n="18"/><lb/>the uſe of it is principally beneficial
        to <lb/>health, after the ſtomach is empty, and <lb/>perſpiration duly performed, eſpecially
        if <lb/>the perſon has ſlept well, and taken <w part="I">ali-</w><lb/><w part="F">ments</w>
        of a nutritive quality, and eaſy <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F">geſtion</w>. All theſe
        things are of ſuch a <lb/>nature, as to increaſe the ſtrength and <w part="I">vi-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">gour</w> of the body, and conſequently to <lb/>favour venery, or at leaſt prevent
        the bad <lb/>effects it would otherwiſe have. It is alſo <lb/>to be obſerved, that it is
        more ſalutary in <lb/>Spring than at any other ſeaſon of the year. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The perſon who would often engage <lb/>in venery, ought to guard againſt
        all ſurfeits, <lb/>hunger, labours, exceſſive ſtudies, <w part="I">vene-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſections</w>, watchings, purges, and every <lb/>thing which can in the leaſt impair and
        <lb/>deſtroy the ſtrength. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Celſus</hi> obſerves, </p>
      <q rend="quotes">
        <p rend="indent">That we ought not too <lb/>eagerly to purſue, or too ſollicitouſly to
          <lb/>avoid, intercourſes with the tender ſex. <pb xml:id="page_14" n="19"/><lb/>Pleaſures
          of this kind, rarely indulged, <lb/>render the body alert and active, but if <lb/>too
          frequently repeated, weak, languid, <lb/>and inactive. And as the proper <w part="I"
            >de-</w><lb/><w part="F">gree</w> of theſe pleaſures is not to be <w part="I"
            >eſti-</w><lb/><w part="F">mated</w> by the number of repetitions, <lb/>but by the
          conſtitution, the age, and <lb/>the ſtrength of the perſon; ſo we may <lb/>take it for
          granted, with reſpect to this <lb/>particular, that the enjoyment which is <lb/>neither
          followed by weakneſs, nor <w part="I">ſuc-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceeded</w> by pain, is not
          prejudicial. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The day is the worſt ſeaſon for <w part="I">plea-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſures</w> of this kind, eſpecially if they are <lb/>ſucceeded by a full meal; the night
          is leſs <lb/>hazardous, but even then ſubſequent <lb/>fatigue, with long watching, render
          it <lb/>improper. It is alſo to be abſtained <lb/>from in ſummer, becauſe at that time,
          <lb/>it is ſubject to throw the humours into <lb/>preternatural commotions. </p>
      </q>
      <pb xml:id="page_15" n="20"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>But as moderation in every thing <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tributes</w> to health, ſo likewiſe does <w part="I">tempe-</w><lb/><w part="F">rate</w>
        venery, and every one ought carefully <lb/>to conſider what his conſtitution can bear.
        <lb/>For a very robuſt perſon may ſafely indulge <lb/>himſelf in a degree of venery, which
        would <lb/>remarkably weaken one of a worſe <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſtitution</w>. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Perſons of a tender and delicate habit of <lb/>body, and weak <hi
          rend="italic">Craſis</hi> of blood and <w part="I">ſpi-</w><lb/><w part="F">rits</w>,
        ſhould by no means indulge <w part="I">them-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſelves</w> in venereal
        engagements, without <lb/>great moderation and caution; thoſe who <lb/>are either too young,
        or too old, and thoſe <lb/>who are lately recovered from a diſeaſe, <lb/>ought alſo to
        abſtain from venery, leſt they <lb/>bring on too great a relaxation of the <lb/>nerves, and
        by overſtraining the fibres that <lb/>compoſe all the parts of their bodies, <w part="I"
          >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">jure</w> and weaken their ſeveral functions in <lb/>the animal
        ſyſtem, and become liable to all <lb/>thoſe diſorders that have been already <w part="I"
          >men-</w><lb/><w part="F">tioned</w>. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_16" n="21"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Thus they, who by nature were ſtronger <lb/>than others, have, by
        intemperance, <w part="I">ren-</w><lb/><w part="F">dered</w> themſelves much weaker than
        thoſe <lb/>who were naturally weak; and thoſe who <lb/>were much weaker by nature, have, by
        <lb/>their temperance, become ſuperior in <lb/>ſtrength, to thoſe who were ſtronger; for
        <lb/>nothing renders an animal robuſt, but the <lb/>ſeminal juice, which is therefore of
        great <lb/>efficacy and importance towards health, <lb/>ſtrength and magnanimity, as well as
          <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">creation</w>. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>But as there are too many, who do not <lb/>attend to the rules here laid
        down, ſo <lb/>much as would be convenient for them, <lb/>perhaps the following caſe may be
        of ſome <lb/>importance, to ſuch as have not yet <w part="I">utter-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ly</w> deſtroyed their conſtitutions, by an <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >moderate</w> purſuit after pleaſures. </p>
      <q rend="quotes">
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>A young man of twenty-five years of <lb/>age, of a
          phlegmatico-ſanguine habit, and <pb xml:id="page_17" n="22"/><lb/>who from his very
          infancy, had a tender <lb/>conſtitution, when about fifteen years <lb/>of age, learnt of a
          wicked ſchool-fellow, <lb/>the execrable trick of <hi rend="italic">Maſtupration.</hi> He
          <lb/>indulged himſelf in this vile and <w part="I">unman-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w>
          practice, very frequently, even <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">moſt</w> daily, from
          the fifteenth to the <lb/>twenty-third year of his age, and applied <lb/>himſelf at the
          ſame time to writing in <lb/>a very ſmall character; by which means <lb/>he contracted
          ſuch an exceſſive <w part="I">weak-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w> of his head and eyes,
          that theſe <lb/>latter were frequently convulſed, during <lb/>his prepoſterous
          entertainment. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Some time ago, while he was <w part="I">wick-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >edly</w> employed in this manner, and his <lb/>deſign upon the very point of being
          <lb/>executed, ſome perſon or other <w part="I">unex-</w><lb/><w part="F">pectedly</w>
          knocked at his chamber door, <lb/>which accident put him into ſuch <w part="I"
            >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">fuſion</w>, that the ultimate ſcene of his <w part="I"
            >di-</w><lb/><w part="F">verſion</w> was left unaccompliſhed. Upon <lb/>this he
          immediately felt ſo exquiſite a <lb/>pain, and ſo vehement a tenſion in his <pb
            xml:id="page_18" n="23"/><lb/>teſticles, and ſpermatic veſſels, that he <lb/>could not
          walk without the utmoſt <w part="I">diffi-</w><lb/><w part="F">culty</w>. The force of his
          genius, and the <lb/>ſight of his eyes, ſeemed at the ſame <lb/>time to be diminiſhed and
          impaired. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Though he had the danger, with <lb/>which this execrable practice
          threataned <lb/>him, in full view, yet after the pain <lb/>of his teſticles was removed,
          he was <lb/>ſo much infatuated as to repeat his <lb/>crime, and begin afreſh his former
          courſe; <lb/>but he was ſoon after ſeized with the <lb/>like pain in his genitals, and
          eſpecially <lb/>in his teſticles, where the pain was <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >companied</w> with a very conſiderable <w part="I">ten-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſion</w>.
          By the uſe of external and <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ternal</w> medicines for
          about half a year, <lb/>he alſo got this diſorder removed, but <lb/>with ſome difficulty. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Soon after he was ſeized with a <w part="I">ſwel-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ling</w> in thoſe veſſels, which go to the <pb xml:id="page_19" n="24"/><lb/>left
          teſticle. The ſwelling appeared <lb/>larger than ordinary after his meals, <lb/>but was
          not accompanied with pain, <lb/>unleſs, when by his folly he brought a <lb/>ſtimulus on
          the parts; but though it <lb/>was void of pain, it was attended with <lb/>another very
          unlucky circumſtance, for <lb/>it remains with him to this very day. <lb/>To this was
          joined ſo great a <w part="I">weak-</w><lb/><w part="F">in</w> his head and eyes, that
          when he was <lb/>about to read any thing, he ſeemed to <lb/>be drunk, and fluſhed with
          wine; the <lb/>pupils of his eyes were extremely <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >lated</w>, and his eyes themſelves racked <lb/>with darting pains, accompanied with
          <lb/>ſome degree of tenſion; his eye-lids <lb/>ſeemed, as it were, oppreſſed with a
          <lb/>kind of weight; in the morning they <lb/>were conglutinated together, and <w part="I"
            >wa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tered</w> very much; but this was not all, <lb/>for both
          corners of his eyes, beſides <lb/>the violent pains with which they were <lb/>racked, were
          alſo clogged and ſtuffed <lb/>with a whitiſh kind of matter. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_20" n="25"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In this deplorable ſtate he was obliged <lb/>to give over reading, and
          interrupt the <lb/>courſe of his ſtudies, for the ſpace of <lb/>ſix months, during which
          time he only <lb/>employed himſelf in exerciſe and <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >creation</w>, and in taking the medicines, <lb/>which were judged proper for one in his
          <lb/>condition; by which means he recovered <lb/>ſo far, as to be able to apply himſelf
          <lb/>to his ſtudies for two or three hours a <lb/>day, which he can ſtill do; but if at
          <lb/>any time he ſhould chance to protract <lb/>his application, and lengthen out his
          <lb/>ſtudies beyond their ſtated time, he is <lb/>immediately ſeized with the above <w
            part="I">ſymp-</w><lb/><w part="F">toms</w>; beſides, he was become ſo lean <lb/>that
          his body was little more than a <lb/>skeleton; and though his appetite was <lb/>good, yet
          he was indiſpoſed after his <lb/>meals, and was affected with a kind of <lb/>drunkenneſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But when he got a juſter ſenſe of <lb/>things, and had for almoſt the
          ſpace of <pb xml:id="page_21" n="26"/><lb/>two years abſtained from his former
          <lb/>practices, and from all commerce with <lb/>women, he began to be troubled with
          <lb/>very frequent nocturnal pollutions, by <lb/>which he found his body gradually more
          <lb/>and more weakened, and his ſtrength <lb/>impaired; ſo that now what ſeemed
          <lb/>principally to be regarded was the <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">moval</w> of
          this imbecility, which was after <lb/>ſome time entirely cured, by the uſe <lb/>of my <hi
            rend="sc">Strengthening Electuary</hi>, <lb/>of which more will be ſaid hereafter. </p>
      </q>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>From this account, we learn, that Venery <lb/>uſed either too ſoon or
        too often, not only <lb/>impairs the ſtrength of the body in <w part="I">gene-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ral</w>, but alſo debilitates the noble functions <lb/>of the brain and eyes, to
        ſuch a <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">gree</w>, that the loſs becomes almoſt <w
          part="I">irre-</w><lb/><w part="F">parable</w>. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I have had an opportunity of ſeeing a <lb/>great many caſes, where
        perſons well <w part="I">ad-</w><pb xml:id="page_22" n="27"/><lb/><w part="F">vanced</w> in
        years, have by immoderate <w part="I">ve-</w><lb/><w part="F">nery</w>, not only brought
        upon their eyes <lb/>redneſs, darting pains, accompanied with <lb/>tenſion, a heavy
        ſenſation, as if a weight <lb/>was laid upon them, and a frequent <w part="I"
          >ſhed-</w><lb/><w part="F">ding</w> of tears, but likewiſe ſuch a <w part="I"
          >weak-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w> of ſight, that they were rendered <w part="I"
          >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">capable</w> either to read or write; and I have <lb/>found that
        in theſe very caſes, the pupils <lb/>were always dilated, as they are in a <hi rend="italic"
          >Gutta <lb/>Serena,</hi> by reaſon of the weakened, or <lb/>loſt tone of the muſcular and
        nervous <lb/>ſibres which ſurround them. But why <lb/>need I ſtop here? ſince I myſelf knew
        two <lb/>caſes, in which a <hi rend="italic">Gutta Serena</hi> itſelf was <lb/>brought on by
        exceſſive venery, and a long <lb/>ſeries of grief. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Hence it appears how great and <w part="I">ſur-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >prizing</w> a conſent there is between the <w part="I">ſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">minal</w>
        parts, or rather the ſpirituous <w part="I">ſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">minal</w> fluid itſelf,
        and the fabric of the <lb/>eye, which is compoſed of the fineſt <w part="I">mem-</w><pb
          xml:id="page_23" n="28"/><lb/><w part="F">branes</w>, nerves and muſcular fibres, as
        <lb/>well as the moſt clear and tranſparent <lb/>fluids. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The lymphatic ſeminal fluid is almoſt <lb/>of the ſame nature and
        quality with that <lb/>fluid which is ſecreted in the brain, and <lb/>diſtributed through
        all the nerves of the <lb/>body; for which reaſon, the more <w part="I">plenti-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ful</w> the evacuation of the former is, the <lb/>more ſcanty and defective the
        ſecretion of <lb/>the other in the brain muſt of courſe be. <lb/>Hence alſo a reaſon may be
        aſſigned why <lb/>thoſe youths, who begin too early to taſte <lb/>the forbidden joys of <hi
          rend="italic">Venus,</hi> ſuſtain a <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſiderable</w>
        loſs of memory, and are <w part="I">render-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> unfit for ſtudy; and
        likewiſe why <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſons</w> farther advanced in years, who
        are <lb/>exceſſively addicted to venereal pleaſure, <lb/>loſe their ſtrength, and bring on a
          <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">mature</w> death. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_24" n="29"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The reaſon of the nocturnal pollutions <lb/>in the caſe juſt recited, is
        very plain; for <lb/>the more copious and frequent the afflux <lb/>of the humours,
        eſpecially of the ſeminal <lb/>matter, has been to the organs deſtined for <lb/>generation,
        either by the force of <w part="I">ima-</w><lb/><w part="F">gination</w> or otherwiſe; I ſay
        the more <w part="I">fre-</w><lb/><w part="F">quent</w> and copious ſuch an afflux has
        <lb/>been, the more the ſpermatic veſſels are <lb/>dilated and relaxed, and the ſeminal
        juice <lb/>for that very reaſon, flows into them in a <lb/>greater quantity, and lays a
        foundation <lb/>for thoſe wanton ideas, and ſeminal <w part="I">excre-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tions</w>, which even during ſleep affect <w part="I">peo-</w><lb/><w part="F">ple</w> of
        a warm imagination. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>But the moſt formidable ſpecies of this <lb/>diſeaſe, is when the
        retaining veſſels are ſo <lb/>extremely relaxed, as to permit the <w part="I"
          >ſemi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nal</w> juices to paſs off upon the ſlighteſt <lb/>ſtimulus, as
        a luſcious idea, or converſation <lb/>with a woman, after ſtraining at the <w part="I"
          >diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">charge</w> of the excrements, or after riding <pb
          xml:id="page_25" n="30"/><lb/>on horſeback in conſequence of a <w part="I"
          >relaxa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>. In the night time the ſame accident <lb/>happens
        from venereal dreams, with a <w part="I">ſen-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſation</w> of enjoyment;
        and this is <w part="I">frequent-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> attended with a continual
        weeping, or <lb/>gleet, which exhauſts the ſtrength of the <lb/>patient. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The matter of this flux is an humid, <lb/>thin, cold, colourleſs
        ſubſtance, called by <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hippocrates,</hi> a <hi rend="italic">Liquid
          Semen</hi><note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* <hi rend="italic">Burnet.
            Hippocrat.</hi> Contract. p. 114. </note> which is void <lb/>of fœcundity: for how is it
        poſſible that <lb/>nature thus refrigerated, ſhould emit a <lb/>prolific juice? Thoſe
        afflicted with this <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">order</w> muſt of neceſſity become
        old in <w part="I">ha-</w><lb/><w part="F">bit</w> of body, ſlow, languid, dull, ſpiritleſs,
        <lb/>ſilent, feeble, wrinkled, unactive, pale, <w part="I">ef-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >feminate</w>, of a weak appetite, cold, with <lb/>a heavineſs of the limbs, and a
        numbneſs <lb/>of the legs, weak, lazy, and indiſpoſed <pb xml:id="page_26" n="31"/><lb/>for
        all manner of action; in many ſubjects <lb/>this diſorder is the forerunner of a Palſy;
        <lb/>but it oftener terminates in that ſpecies of <lb/>a Conſumption, called by phyſicians
          <hi rend="italic">Tabes <lb/>Dorſalis.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>A <hi rend="italic">Tabes Dorſalis</hi> is a violent diſorder,
        <lb/>little treated of by phyſicians, though <w part="I">ful-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w>
        deſcribed by <hi rend="italic">Hippocrates</hi><note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">†
          Tabes Dorſalis ex ſpinali medulla oritur, præcipue <lb/>vero recentes ſponſos &amp;
          libidinoſos corripit, febris <lb/>ſunt expertes, bene comedunt, &amp; colliquantur. Quod
          <lb/>ſit ita affectum perconteris, aſſeret ſibi videri, ex <w part="I">ſu-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">perioribus</w> partibus a capite velut formicas in ſpinam <lb/>demitti, cumque
          urinam &amp; ſtercus reddit, ſemen <lb/>genitale copioſum &amp; liquidum ei prodit, neque
            <w part="I">gene-</w><lb/><w part="F">ratio</w> fit, &amp; inter dormiandum, cum uxore
          dormiat <lb/>necne veneris Iudibria patitur. Cumque alias, tum <lb/>præcipue per locum
          arduum, iter facerit, aut <w part="I">cucur-</w><lb/><w part="F">rerit</w>, anheloſus,
          &amp; imbecilis evadit. Caput gravatur, <lb/>&amp; aures ſonant. Hic temporis progreſſu
          vehementibus <lb/>febribus correptus, perit ex lipyria febre. <hi rend="italic">Burnet.
            <lb/>Hippocrat.</hi> Contract. p. 114. </note>. The <w part="I">ſymp-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">toms</w> which preſage this Conſumption, I <lb/>have for the moſt part obſerved
        to be theſe, <lb/>an hypochondriacal oppreſſion, melancholy, <pb xml:id="page_27" n="32"
        /><lb/>and too much thoughtfulneſs, pain in <lb/>the back, and often in the head, an aching
        <lb/>pain, rolling and hanging down of the <lb/>teſticles, a weakneſs of memory and ſight,
        <lb/>and a decay of ſtrenght; there is a ſenſe <lb/>of weight and giddineſs of the head, and
        <lb/>a ringing in the ears, and as the diſorder <lb/>proceeds, all the ſymptoms are
        increaſed, <lb/>the legs ſwell, as in dropical caſes; in <lb/>ſome, Ulcers ariſe on the
        loins, ſome of <lb/>which are healed, whilſt others riſe in their <lb/>ſtead. At laſt, a
        violent Cataract ariſing, <lb/>the patient is rendered totally blind; theſe <lb/>are
        followed by ſome others; as a thirſt, <lb/>an hectical diſpoſition, an Atrophy, a <w
          part="I">waſt-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> of the fleſh, &amp;c. &amp;c. till at laſt the
        <lb/>body is brought to the higheſt degree of a <lb/>Conſumption; and that very often <w
          part="I">with-</w><lb/><w part="F">out</w> any cough, or any other remarkable <lb/>ſign of
        a Conſumption of the Lungs. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe are the moſt common diſorders <lb/>that enſue from the exceſſive
        uſe of <hi rend="italic">Venery,</hi>
        <lb/>and the prepoſterous practice of <hi rend="italic">Self-Pol-<lb/>lution,</hi> for the
        cure of which I have two <pb xml:id="page_28" n="33"/><lb/>medicines which I ſhall
        recommend; the <lb/>firſt, which anſwers the firſt intention of <lb/>cure, <hi rend="italic"
          >viz.</hi> the ſtopping of the Gonorrhæa, <lb/>is my <hi rend="sc">Strengthening
          Electuary</hi>, which <lb/>braces up and ſtrengthens the weakened <lb/>and relaxed ſolids,
        warms and invigorates <lb/>the habit, promotes digeſtion, and thereby <lb/>furniſhes the
        diſpirited and impoveriſhed <lb/>blood, with laudable and benign chyle. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The other medicine is my <hi rend="sc">Restorative <lb/>Nervous
          Elixir</hi>, which is perhaps the <lb/>moſt ſtimulating <hi rend="italic">Reſtorative</hi>
        that medicine <lb/>can produce, and in the laſt decays of life, <lb/>will ſtill ſupply the
        vital lamp with ſome <lb/>recruits; it is good in all Languors, <w part="I">Weak-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ness</w>, and Decays of the conſtitution, for <lb/>it ſtrengthens all parts of
        the body, <w part="I">eſpe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cially</w> the ſtomach, when relaxed and
        <lb/>diſordered with frequent debauches, and <lb/>by reſtoring the oſcillation of the
        fibres, <lb/>quickens the various motions, and gives <lb/>freſh vigor to the animal
        functions. It is <pb xml:id="page_29" n="34"/><lb/>an admirable remedy for thoſe who have
        <lb/>been in a manner wore out with venereal <lb/>engagements, eſpecially if their pleaſures
        <lb/>have been purchaſed at the expence of a <lb/>few ſalivations, or a frequent uſe of <w
          part="I">mer-</w><lb/><w part="F">curial</w> medicines, and it will revive any
        <lb/>conſtitution that it not quite mouldered <lb/>into rottenneſs. But they beſt deſerve
        ſuch <lb/>a <hi rend="italic">Reſtorative,</hi> who by acute diſeaſes, ſuch <lb/>as
        malignant Fevers, the Small-Pox, and <lb/>the like, have been ſo broke and ſhattered <lb/>in
        their conſtitutions, as hardly to be <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w part="F">in</w> a
        poſſibility of recovery. For in ſuch it <lb/>will to admiration repair the impoveriſhed
        <lb/>juices, and fill again the veins with a warm, <lb/>generous, nutritive blood. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is excellent in diſeaſes of the head, <lb/>ariſing from a conſent
        with the ſtomach, <lb/>ſuch as the Vertigo, Head-ach, Sleepy <lb/>Diſeaſes, dread of an
        Apoplexy, <w part="I">Weak-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w> of the memory and ſight, and a
        noiſe <lb/>or ringing in the ears. In Scrophulous <pb xml:id="page_30" n="35"/><lb/>habits
        alſo, which are leaning towards <lb/>Conſumptions, it will be of the utmoſt <lb/>ſervice.
        And when young perſons are not <lb/>ſo early happy in their conjugal embraces <lb/>as many
        wiſh to be, and it be ſuſpected <lb/>from a coldneſs, and inſufficiency upon <lb/>that
        account on either ſide, the uſe of this <lb/>medicine cannot fail to render their <w
          part="I">inter-</w><lb/><w part="F">courſe</w> prolific, as it actually romoves the
        <lb/>cauſes of impotency in one ſex, and of <lb/>ſterility, or barrenneſs, in the other. But
        <lb/>the uſe of it is varily to be indulged, leſt <lb/>with it be kindled a heat that
        reaſonable <lb/>coition cannot aſſuage. And let ſuch as <lb/>indulge themſelves too laviſhly
        in theſe <w part="I">en-</w><lb/><w part="F">joyments</w>, be careful how they ſpur nature,
        <lb/>and prompt with ſuch helps, leſt they <lb/>run off their life and ſtrength too <w
          part="I">precipi-</w><lb/><w part="F">tately</w>, for the beſt conſtitutions in the
        <lb/>world, wear out and ſink under the <w part="I">fre-</w><lb/><w part="F">quent</w>
        repetition of ſuch profuſion, as the <lb/>frequent ſtraining any elaſtic body <w part="I"
          >what-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſoever</w>, will weaken more and more it's <lb/>ſpring, till it
        is quite loſt, notwithſtanding <lb/>all the helps of art to preſerve it. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_31" n="36"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>To conclude. The omnipotent Creator <lb/>has given us <hi rend="italic"
          >Paſſions</hi> for very wiſe and good <lb/>ends; which ſeem to be, that thereby we
        <lb/>may be urged with a kind of impetuoſity <lb/>to ſhun evil, and embrace good; wherefore
        <lb/>the paſſions are not bad in themſelves, it <lb/>is by their exceſs that they become
        vicious, <lb/>when they riſe to ſo extravagant a pitch, as <lb/>not to be governed by the
        dictates of <lb/>reaſon. But we ought to uſe our beſt <lb/>endeavours to keep them within
        proper <lb/>bounds, and the more difficult the conflict, <lb/>the more glorious will be the
        victory. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>We have all a natural propenſity to <lb/>pleaſures; but theſe are of two
        very <w part="I">dif-</w><lb/><w part="F">ferent</w> ſorts, the ſenſual and the mental.
        <lb/>Senſual pleaſures engroſs the greateſt part <lb/>of mankind, while theſe few only, <hi
          rend="italic">quos <lb/>equus amavit Jupiter,</hi> are taken with the <lb/>beauties of the
        mental. And the reaſon <lb/>why ſo many run after pleaſures of the <lb/>firſt ſort, ſeems to
        be, becauſe they hardly e<lb/>ver allow themſelves an opportunity of <pb xml:id="page_32"
          n="37"/><lb/>taſting the ſweets of an upright conſcience, <lb/>or of feeling that joy,
        which ariſes to a <lb/>good man, from the moderation of his <w part="I">ir-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">regular</w> deſires; and being entirely devoted <lb/>to the gratification of
        their ſenſual <w part="I">appe-</w><lb/><w part="F">tites</w>, they never give attention to
        the real <lb/>charms of virtue. Wherefore whoſoever <lb/>deſires to enjoy this ſolid
        happineſs, ought <lb/>to enure himſelf by degrees to the love of <lb/>virtue, and ever
        carefully to avoid adding <lb/>fuel to the fire of his paſſions. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Appoſite to theſe ſentiments is that <w part="I">ſay-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ing</w> which <hi rend="italic">Cicero</hi> puts into the mouth of <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Cato,</hi> as by him received from the great <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Archytas</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Terentum; that nature never <lb/>afflicted mankind
          with a more capital plague, <lb/>than bodily pleaſure; the eager deſires of <lb/>which
          ſpur on to enjoyment with ungovernable <lb/>raſhneſs.</hi><note place="bottom" n="*"
          rend="size(0.5)">* De Senectute. Cap. <hi rend="italic">xii.</hi>
        </note>
      </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_33" n="38"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>And the reſt of what that great <w part="I">philoſo-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >pher</w> has written on this ſubject, muſt <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">light</w>
        the mind of every wiſe man in the <lb/>peruſal. Wherefore, <hi rend="italic">Virtue</hi>'s
        exclamation <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">Silius Italicus,</hi> is very juſt: <q
          rend="italic size(0.7)"><lb/><l rend="italic size(0.7)">Quippe nec ira Deum tantum, nec
            tela, nec hoſtes, </l>
          <lb/><l>Quantum ſola noces, animis illapſa voluptas<note place="bottom" n="*">* Punicorum.
              Lib. <hi rend="italic">xv.</hi> Ver. <hi rend="italic">94.</hi>
            </note>. </l>
          <lb/><l>Pleaſure by gliding on the minds of men, </l>
          <lb/><l>More miſchiefs haſt thou wrought than hoſtile arms, </l>
          <lb/><l>Than wrath of Gods. </l></q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>But as the due government of the <w part="I">paſſi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ons</w> ſtrengthens the mind, ſo temperance <lb/>in diet renders the body leſs expoſed to
        <lb/>theſe turbulent motions. And this rule <lb/>holds good, not only in thoſe, who are
        <lb/>naturally of a hot conſtitution, but even <lb/>in thoſe who curb their appetites; <w
          part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">cauſe</w> it keeps them in a ſtate of <w part="I"
          >tranqui-</w><lb/><w part="F">lity</w>. And this is the way in general to <lb/>reſiſt
        theſe evils, or at leaſt to diminiſh <lb/>their effects. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_34" n="39"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>As for thoſe who would have us to be <lb/>entirely devoid of paſſions,
        and to <w part="I">ſup-</w><lb/><w part="F">press</w> all the affections of the mind, as if
        <lb/>they were ſo many evils; they certainly <lb/>have a wrong notion of the wiſdom, and
        <lb/>goodneſs of the Almighty Creator, who <lb/>has inſerted, and, as it were, interwoven
        <lb/>them into our frame for excellent purpoſes; <lb/>for they are not only beneficial to <w
          part="I">indivi-</w><lb/><w part="F">duals</w> upon many occaſions, but even <w part="I"
          >ne-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceſſary</w> for keeping up ſociety and <w part="I"
          >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">nexions</w> between mankind. </p>
      <trailer rend=" align-center"><lb/>FINIS </trailer>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_35"/>
        <head rend="align-center dc(2)"><lb/>ADVERTISEMENT. </head>
        <div type="part">
          <head rend="italic indent hanging"><lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Medicines</hi> recommended in
            this Treatiſe, <lb/>with full directions for their uſe, may be <lb/>had by the author's
            particular order, of <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="roman">Fletcher</hi> and Co. bookſellers, at the
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">Oxford-Theatre,</hi> the <hi rend="roman">North-Side</hi> of <hi
              rend="roman">St. <lb/>Paul's Church-Yard;</hi> and by their <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">pointment</w> in moſt of the principal Towns in <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >England.</hi>
          </head>
          <list>
            <item><lb/>1. <hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HE <hi rend="italic">Reſtorative Nervous
                Elixir,</hi>
              <lb/>for the recovery of decayed and <lb/>broken conſtitutions. For thoſe who have
              <lb/>been in a manner wore out with venereal <lb/>engagements, by long courſes of <w
                part="I">mer-</w><lb/><w part="F">curial</w> medicines, or by ſalivations; for <pb
                xml:id="page_36"/><lb/>all thoſe nervous and other diſorders, that <lb/>ariſe from
              the ſhameful practice of Self-<lb/>Pollution; for Venereal Impotency; and <lb/>for all
              diſorders of the head and nerves <lb/>which proceed from a weakneſs and <w part="I"
                >debi-</w><lb/><w part="F">lity</w> of the nervous ſyſtem. In bottles at <lb/>10s.
              6d. </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>2. <hi rend="italic">A Strengthening Electuary,</hi> for the <lb/>cure of that
              ſpecies of Gonorrhœa, which is <lb/>owing to a weakneſs of the ſeminal veſſels.
              <lb/>It cures all kinds of Agues, and all <w part="I">diſor-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >ders</w> of the ſtomach and primae viæ, which <lb/>proceed from a relaxation and
              decay of <lb/>their tone (the common conſequence of <lb/>hard drinking) an overflowing
              of the <lb/>Menſes and Lochia, and prevents <w part="I">Abor-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >tion</w>. In pots at 5s. 3d. </item>
          </list>
        </div>
        <div type="part">
          <pb xml:id="page_37"/>
          <head rend="italic indent hanging"><lb/>Where alſo may be had the following <hi
              rend="roman">Spe-<lb/>cific Medicines,</hi> recommended by the author <lb/>in his <hi
              rend="roman">Obſervations on Specific <w part="I">Medi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >cines</w>,</hi> &amp;c. viz. </head>
          <list>
            <lb/>
            <item>1. <hi rend="italic">A Pectoral Elixir,</hi> for the cure of all <lb/>diſeaſes of
              the breaſt; ſuch as Coughs, <lb/>Catarrhs, Fluxions, Difficulty of <w part="I"
                >Breath-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>, Aſthmas, Empyemas, Conſumptions, <lb/>(if
              curable) and Vomica of the Lungs. — <lb/>It cures the Tooth-Ach if applied with a
              <lb/>bit of cotton, and all kinds of Wounds <lb/>and Bruiſes. In bottles at 4s. </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>2. <hi rend="italic">A Specific Tincture,</hi> &amp;c. for the cure of <lb/>every
              kind of Dropſy. In parcels at 7s. 6d. </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>3. <hi rend="italic">A Cephalic Electuary,</hi> for the certain <lb/>cure of the
              Epilepſy (if it is not hereditary) <lb/>and Palſy; for Virtigo's and all kinds of
              <lb/>Convulſions, and particularly for that odd <lb/>diſorder called <hi rend="italic"
                >St. Vitus's Dance.</hi> In pots <lb/>at 10s. 6d. and 5s. 3d. </item>
            <pb xml:id="page_38"/>
            <lb/>
            <item>4. <hi rend="italic">Anodyne Mineral Balſam,</hi> for the cure <lb/>of the
              Jaundice, for Fits of the Stone and <lb/>Gravel; for the Heart-burn and Cholic;
              <lb/>and outwardly, for all contractions of the <lb/>limbs, and fixed pains of the
              Gout and <lb/>Rheumatiſm. In bottles at 3s. 6d. </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>5. <hi rend="italic">Catholic Pills,</hi> for the Diſeaſes peculiar <lb/>to Women;
              ſuch as a Chloroſis, or Green <lb/>Sickneſs, and a Suppreſſion of the Menſes; <lb/>and
              particularly for all the various hyſteric <lb/>and nervous Diſorders incident to the
                <w part="I">fe-</w><lb/><w part="F">male</w> Sex, in the decline of life, when
              <lb/>the Menſes ceaſe. As alſo for the cure of <lb/>all hyſteric and hypochondriac
              diſorders. <lb/>In boxes at 3s. 6d. </item>
            <item><lb/>6. <hi rend="italic">An Eſſence,</hi> for the cure of every <w part="I"
                >ſpe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cies</w> and degree of the Venereal Diſeaſe, <lb/>Flying
              Pains and Head-Achs, the relicks <lb/>of ill cures. A few drops of this <w part="I"
                >medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cine</w> in a glaſs of water is a doſe, and in
              <lb/>ſlight caſes, in eight or ten days, the cure <pb xml:id="page_39"/><lb/>is
              effected, without any inconveniency <lb/>to the patient. It is alſo excellent in the
              <lb/>Leproſy and Scurvy, and all diſorders that <lb/>proceed from an impurity of the
              blood <lb/>and humours. In bottles at 3s. </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>7. <hi rend="italic">A Chymical Fluid,</hi> for the certain cure <lb/>of the Itch,
              and all defadations of the skin, <lb/>and for healing old and inveterate Ulcers.
              <lb/>In bottles at 1s. 6d. </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>8. <hi rend="italic">Worm Powders,</hi> for the cure of all <lb/>kinds of Worms,
              whether in infants or <lb/>adults. In parcels at 2s. </item>
          </list>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>For a more particular account of theſe <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >Remedies,</hi> and the diſeaſes in which they <lb/>are proper, ſee the author's <hi
              rend="sc">Observations</hi>, <lb/>&amp;c. above-mentioned; price 2s. 6d. which
            <lb/>may be had at each place where the <w part="I">medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cines</w>
            are ſold. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_40"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>N. B. All theſe <hi rend="italic">Specific Remedies</hi> are
            <lb/>ſigned by the author in his own hand <lb/>writing, and ſealed with his coat of
            arms, <lb/>to prevent impoſitions. They will keep <lb/>any length of time after they
            have been <lb/>opened, provided they are again well <w part="I">ſtop-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ped</w>, or tied over, and will be equally <w part="I">ef-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ficacious</w> ſeven years after, as when they <lb/>were firſt purchaſed. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
