<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Merande: A succinct account of a machine, newly invented for the cure
          of præternatural curvatures of the spine</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>D. Merande</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">A Succinct Account OF A MACHINE, Newly invented for the CURE of
              PRÆTERNATURAL CURVATURES OF THE SPINE: Together with a Detail of several Cases, in
              which this MACHINE has been tried with great Success. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T9372</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T9372"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for T. Jones, in Great May's Buildings, St. Martin's Lane;
                  sold also at his other shop in the Strand facing Hungerford Market,</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1768</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="24"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3308605794</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K024533.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: method"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_1"/>
        <p rend="align-center"><lb/>A <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">Succinct Account </hi><lb/>OF A <lb/><hi
            rend="dc(3)">MACHINE</hi>, <lb/>Newly invented for the CURE of <lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)"
            >PRÆTERNATURAL CURVATURES</hi>
          <lb/>OF THE <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">SPINE:</hi>
          <lb/>Together with a Detail of ſeveral Caſes, <lb/>in which this MACHINE has <lb/>been
          tried with great Succeſs. </p>
        <p rend="align-center"><lb/>By D. MERANDE, M. D. </p>
        <p rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">LONDON:</hi>
          <lb/>Printed for T. JONES, in <hi rend="italic">Great May's Buildings, St. <w part="I"
              >Mar-</w><lb/><w part="F">tin's</w> Lane;</hi> ſold alſo at his other ſhop in the <hi
            rend="italic">Strand</hi>
          <w part="I">fac-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>
          <hi rend="italic">Hungerford Market.</hi> 1768. </p>
        <p rend="align-center"><lb/>[Price Sixpence.] </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(4)">A</hi> Præternatural curvature of the <lb/>bones
        generally produces ſome <lb/>diſorders in the œconomy of the <lb/>human body; but, that of
        the ſpine in <w part="I">par-</w><lb/><w part="F">ticular</w>, gives riſe to the moſt
        alarming <lb/>ſymptoms, which may lead on to the death <lb/>of the patient: this will not
        appear <w part="I">ſur-</w><lb/><w part="F">priſing</w>, if we conſider the importance of
        <lb/>thoſe functions, which may be obſtructed <lb/>or injured in this diſeaſe; for from the
        union <lb/>of all the vertebræ together, a bony <w part="I">pyra-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >mid</w> preſents itſelf, forming a canal lined <lb/>by the membranes proceeding from the
        <lb/>brain, which contains the ſpinal marrow, <lb/>and ſerves to defend it from external
        injuries. <lb/>The column of the ſpine makes alſo a part <lb/>of the cavity of the breaſt,
        bears up the <lb/>ribs, ſupports internally ſeveral organs <w part="I">eſ-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſential</w> to life, and connects the <w part="I">mediaſti-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >num</w>, that membrane, which divides the <lb/>breaſt into two cavities, for the lodgment
        <lb/>of the lungs. We readily conceive if this <lb/>column ſhould be thrown out of its <w
          part="I">natu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ral</w> direction, it is impoſſible, but that the
        <lb/>marrow which it contains ſhould ſuffer in <lb/>a greater or leſs degree. The nerves
        which <pb xml:id="page_3" n="4"/><lb/>iſſue from the diſtended or compreſſed <lb/>part, will
        act but imperfectly upon the <lb/>parts to which they are diſtributed; from <lb/>whence
        proceed that weakneſs and <w part="I">exte-</w><lb/><w part="F">nuation</w> obſervable in
        the lower extremities <lb/>of moſt deformed perſons; if the ſpine is <lb/>bent in ſuch a
        manner as to take off from <lb/>the cavity of the breaſt, the diſorder <w part="I"
          >be-</w><lb/><w part="F">come</w> ſtill worſe in its conſequences, for <lb/>the lungs not
        finding room enough to <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">pand</w>, cannot draw in a
        quantity of air <w part="I">ſuf-</w><lb/><w part="F">ficient</w> for each inſpiration; ſo
        that the maſs <lb/>of blood bereft of the advantages derived <lb/>from a free and
        uninterrupted reſpiration, <lb/>becomes ſo impoveriſhed, as hardly to <w part="I"
          >ſuf-</w><lb/><w part="F">fice</w> for the ſimple nouriſhment of the <lb/>parts, much
        leſs, to contribute what is neceſſary <lb/>for their growth. The heart even is <w part="I"
          >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">fined</w> by the male conformation of the <w part="I"
          >tho-</w><lb/><w part="F">rax</w>, and is incapable of exerting its whole <lb/>power in
        expelling the blood; the <w part="I">circula-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> therefore is more
        ſlowly carried on, <lb/>the ſecretions are imperfect, and all the <lb/>vital functions
        become languid, not only the <lb/>important organs of life within the breaſt <lb/>are
        injured by this diſorder, but its effects <lb/>are ſometimes manifeſted alſo in the total
        <lb/>deſtruction of the animal œconomy, and <lb/>ſome of the ableſt practitioners have
        traced <pb xml:id="page_4" n="5"/><lb/>moſt fatal accidents from this cauſe: <w part="I"
          >often-</w><lb/><w part="F">times</w> the pleura being ſtretched or <w part="I"
          >ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtructed</w>, becomes inflamed, and forms <w part="I"
          >præ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ternatural</w> adheſions with the lungs, or elſe <lb/>the
        veſſels of that membrane being <w part="I">incapa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w> of abſorbing
        the ſuperfluous part of <lb/>that fluid with which it is lubricated, a <lb/>dropſy is
        formed, which is the more <w part="I">dan-</w><lb/><w part="F">gerous</w>, as the cauſe
        which firſt produced <lb/>it, is continually increaſing: at other <lb/>times, the lungs
        become ſchirrous, or <w part="I">ab-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſcede</w>; and an empyema enſues,
        which is <lb/>generally mortal. Doctor Gliſſon, in his <lb/>treatiſe on the rickets,
        declares, that, in <lb/>the courſe of his enquiries, with regard to <lb/>the cauſes and
        effects of this diſorder, he <lb/>had often found appearances ſimilar to <lb/>thoſe
        abovementioned, in the breaſt of <lb/>children who had died of the rickets: <lb/>without
        paying any attention to the ſtate of <lb/>the bones which enter into the compoſition <lb/>of
        the breaſt, he aſcribes all thoſe effects to <lb/>the immediate impreſſion of a virus which
        <lb/>he calls ricketty, upon the injured organs; <lb/>but, ſince it is well known that the
        form <lb/>of the breaſt is frequently much altered in <lb/>ricketty perſons, is it not more
        reaſonable <lb/>to imagine, that the morbid appearances <lb/>obſerved by Gliſſon, were
        either owing to <pb xml:id="page_5" n="6"/><lb/>the ſtretching of the pleura, or the <w
          part="I">preſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſure</w> upon the lungs, by the ribs, the <w part="I"
          >ſter-</w><lb/><w part="F">num</w>, or the vertebræ warped. This change <lb/>in the make
        of the breaſt is not always <lb/>productive of ſuch fatal conſequences; it <lb/>ſhould ſeem,
        as if the organs could <w part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F">times</w> accommodate
        themſelves to <w part="I">confine-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w>; when the alteration takes
        place very <lb/>gradually; at other times, the new form <lb/>which the breaſt acquires,
        preſerves the <lb/>ſame extent of cavity, as it would have had <lb/>in the natural ſtate; we
        need not therefore <lb/>be ſurprized, to ſee many people living for <lb/>many years, with
        this infirmity; nor even, <lb/>to find ſome amongſt the number, who <w part="I"
          >en-</w><lb/><w part="F">joy</w> a tolerable ſtate of health. But, we <lb/>ſhould be
        greatly miſtaken, if we were to <lb/>infer from hence, that the curvature of the <lb/>ſpine
        is never the cauſe of death; on the <lb/>contrary, however frequent the inſtances <lb/>may
        be of perſons living a length of time <lb/>with this complaint, the number of thoſe <lb/>who
        periſh by it, is certainly more <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſiderable</w>. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>This diſorder may ariſe from various <lb/>cauſes, among the moſt
        frequent, we may <lb/>reckon the neglect of thoſe, who have the <lb/>care of children;
        either in dreſſing them <lb/>improperly, or ſuffering them to throw <pb xml:id="page_6"
          n="7"/><lb/>themſelves into, and habitually contract <lb/>improper attitudes. A natural or
          <w part="I">acciden-</w><lb/><w part="F">tal</w> weakneſs of the ligaments or muſcles
        <lb/>of the ſpine, may alſo give riſe to this <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">eaſe</w>;
        as it muſt neceſſarily take off from <lb/>the ſtrength of the column, which will
        <lb/>therefore give way, and bend under the <lb/>weight of the head, and the upper <w
          part="I">extre-</w><lb/><w part="F">mities</w>; a greater or leſs power of the <w part="I"
          >muſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">cles</w> on one ſide of the ſpine, than on the <lb/>other, may
        be reckoned as another cauſe <lb/>of its deformity; but, it is moſt generally <lb/>owing to
        a ricketty habit of body. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Although moſt authors concur in <w part="I">aſſign-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ing</w> this diſpoſition as the moſt frequent <lb/>cauſe of the curvature of the ſpine,
        yet they <lb/>by no means agree about the manner in <lb/>which it acts ſo as to produce this
        effect; <lb/>Gliſſon aſcribes it to an irregular <w part="I">diſtribu-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tion</w> of the nutritious juice in the bones; <lb/>which being more liberally diffuſed
        upon <lb/>one ſurface than another, will not allow <lb/>them as they are growing, to
        preſerve their <lb/>natural form. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The late Mr. Petit, member of the <w part="I">aca-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >demy</w>, in his excellent treatiſe on the <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">eaſes</w>
        of the bones, ſays after Mayow, that <lb/>bones will not bend, unleſs they have been
        <lb/>previouſly ſoftened by a vitiated ſtate of <pb xml:id="page_7" n="8"/><lb/>the juices,
        which ſerve to nouriſh them; <lb/>that, in that caſe, the muſcles and tendons <lb/>being
        extenuated, and ſhortned by the <lb/>ricketty virus, pull the bones by their <w part="I"
          >elaſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">tic</w> power more forcibly on one ſide, than <lb/>on the
        other, ſo that they are obliged to <lb/>give way, as a bow does, when its ſtring <lb/>is
        ſhortned. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>However ſpecious this explanation may <lb/>appear, it is certainly
        difficult to <w part="I">deter-</w><lb/><w part="F">mine</w> whether the bones are made <w
          part="I">crook-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>, becauſe they are drawn to one ſide, <lb/>by
        the muſcles being previouſly ſhortned, <lb/>or, whether the muſcles do not rather
        <lb/>ſhorten themſelves, by their own power of <lb/>contraction, after the bones have been
        once <lb/>bent, and can no longer counterpoiſe that <lb/>action, as they were uſed to do:
        either of <lb/>theſe ſolutions appearing equally probable, <lb/>there is certainly,
        independent of them, <w part="I">ano-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> more apparent cauſe of
        this diſorder, <lb/>which is, the weight of the head and the <lb/>upper extremities, upon
        the ſpine. This <lb/>circumſtance has not eſcaped Mr. Petit's <lb/>obſervation, who takes
        notice of it as <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">curring</w> with the other cauſes. What
        has been<lb/> ſaid, relates only to children, or ſuch as <lb/>are young; but there are
        cauſes which may <lb/>throw the ſpine out of it's natural direction, <pb xml:id="page_8"
          n="9"/><lb/>at all times of life; ſuch as, any hard <lb/>work, which keeps the body
        conſtantly <lb/>bent, and habituates it little by little to <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">main</w> in that ſtate; thoſe who carry heavy <lb/>burdens on their head or
        ſhoulders, and <lb/>thoſe who manure the ground, have <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >monly</w> the ſpine bent forwards; as well as <lb/>moſt old husbandmen. Old age, which
        <lb/>debilitates the action of the ligaments and <lb/>muſcles, frequently produces the ſame
          <w part="I">ef-</w><lb/><w part="F">fect</w>, but in theſe inſtances the diſorder is
        <lb/>attended with few if any bad ſymptons; <lb/>becauſe, the curvature is made very <w
          part="I">gra-</w><lb/><w part="F">dually</w>, and that the extent of the thorax <lb/>is
        not diminiſhed by it. There are even <lb/>ſome perſons in whom this crookedneſs <lb/>throws
        the ſternum at a greater diſtance <lb/>from the ſpine; in theſe, the cavity acquires <lb/>a
        greater extent, and a remarkable ſtrong <lb/>voice, which they are often obſerved to
        <lb/>have, plainly indicates, that their lungs are <lb/>not in the leaſt confined. I ſhall
        not enter <lb/>into a more explicit account of the cauſes <lb/>and effects of this
        deformity; my preſent <lb/>deſign, being only to propoſe a new method, <lb/>to prevent, or
        ſet it to rights, when it will <lb/>admit of a cure. The chief curative <w part="I"
          >indi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cation</w> is to reſiſt the progreſs of the diſeaſe <lb/>in the
        beginning; and if the ſpine is already <pb xml:id="page_9" n="10"/><lb/>bent, to endeavour
        to make it ſtraight again, <lb/>by a conſtant and gradual extenſion. The <lb/>means
        heretofore uſed, to anſwer this <w part="I">pur-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſe</w>, have been
        inſufficient; the method <lb/>which I propoſe will always ſucceed, when <lb/>employed in
        proper caſes, and put in <w part="I">prac-</w><lb/><w part="F">tice</w> with neceſſary
        precaution. To be <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">vinced</w> of the truth of this
        aſſertion, we <lb/>need only conſider, that a ſtick, however <lb/>ſlender it may be, can
        ſupport a <w part="I">conſidera-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w> weight, while it remains
        ſtraight and <lb/>upright, but, if it happens to deviate in <lb/>the leaſt from the ſtraight
        line, it ſoon gives <lb/>way entirely to the weight. The ſame <lb/>thing may be ſaid of the
        vertebral column; <lb/>if by any accident it ſhould be thrown out <lb/>of it natural
        direction, the weight of the <lb/>head and upper extremities, will not fail <lb/>to increaſe
        the deviation; eſpecially in <w part="I">chil-</w><lb/><w part="F">dren</w>, whoſe bones
        have not yet acquired a <lb/>neceſſary firmneſs; and, in a ſhort time <w part="I"
          >dif-</w><lb/><w part="F">ferent</w> ſymptoms ſhew themſelves agreeably <lb/>to the
        different way in which the ſpine may <lb/>be bent. It may perhaps be objected that
        <lb/>although the ſpine is naturally bent in <w part="I">ſeve-</w><lb/><w part="F">ral</w>
        places, yet it is not leſs capable of <w part="I">ſup-</w><lb/><w part="F">porting</w> the
        weight of the incumbent parts: <lb/>but this will be readily anſwered if we <w part="I"
          >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſider</w> that nature, by giving the ſpine theſe <pb
          xml:id="page_10" n="11"/><lb/>various incurvations, has divided the <w part="I"
          >preſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſure</w>, and by this means guarded the <w part="I"
          >co-</w><lb/><w part="F">lumn</w>, againſt the effects which the weight <lb/>of the parts,
        it is deſigned to ſupport, <lb/>might otherwiſe have produced, and, that <lb/>the ſpine
        reaps this advantage from the <w part="I">ſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">tuation</w> of thoſe
        organs, by which is is <w part="I">ena-</w><lb/><w part="F">bled</w> to perform it's various
        motions: but, <lb/>the poſition of the muſcles, which is only <lb/>relative to the natural
        inflexions of the <lb/>ſpine, cannot poſſibly be of any ſervice <lb/>when the bones are
        warped inwards, or to <lb/>either ſide; to put a ſtop therefore, to the <lb/>progreſs of the
        diſeaſe it is neceſſary, that <lb/>the vertebræ ſhould be brought back to <lb/>their natural
        poſition, and that they ſhould <lb/>be ſo maintained, till ſuch a time as the <lb/>ſpine has
        acquired a degree of firmneſs, <w part="I">ſuf-</w><lb/><w part="F">ficient</w> of itſelf,
        to counteract a power which <lb/>is always attempting to bend it more and <lb/>more. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It has always been thought neceſſary to <lb/>apply for help in theſe
        caſes, and parents, <lb/>alarmed merely by the idea of deformity <lb/>which their children
        are threatned with, <lb/>never fail to conſult ſome perſon whom they <lb/>can confide in;
        but, how manifold ſoever <lb/>may have been the means hitherto uſed for <lb/>this purpoſe,
        they have been all contrived <lb/>upon one and the ſame principle, which is, <pb
          xml:id="page_11" n="12"/><lb/>a certain degree of preſſure upon the moſt <lb/>projecting
        part. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Sometimes, a bodice is uſed, made firm <lb/>with whalebone, and guarded
        in thoſe parts <lb/>where it is intended to preſs; ſometimes, <lb/>it is a croſs made of
        iron, and at other <lb/>times in ſhort, it is ſome kind of machine <lb/>invented for
        compreſſion: but, the ſlighteſt <lb/>reflection upon the ſtructure of the parts, <lb/>will
        readily account for the little ſucceſs all <lb/>theſe trials have been attended with. What
        <lb/>effect indeed can preſſure poſſibly have in <lb/>thoſe caſes where the ſpine is bent
        inwards <lb/>or latterally; eſpecially, if the curvature is <lb/>at the middle or lower part
        of the column? <lb/>The compreſſing machines have then no <lb/>immediate bearing upon the
        ſpine; they <lb/>muſt therefore act upon the ribs: but, theſe <lb/>buttreſſes, whoſe
        poſition is oblique, will <lb/>more readily give way according to the <w part="I"
          >mo-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of their articulation, than they will be <lb/>able to
        force out the vertebræ; this <w part="I">preſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſure</w> which muſt
        neceſſarily therefore <w part="I">incom-</w><lb/><w part="F">mode</w> of reſpiration, loſes
        alſo its effect on <lb/>the ſpine, more particularly on account of <lb/>the circular form of
        the ribs, and their <lb/>flexibility; ſo that the proportion of force <lb/>acting upon the
        vertebral column is reduced <lb/>almoſt to nothing. The vertebræ of the <lb/>loins when bent
        laterally or inwards, are <pb xml:id="page_12" n="13"/><lb/>not more likely to be redreſſed
        by any <w part="I">preſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſure</w> of this kind, for the thickneſs of the
        <lb/>muſcles and integuments which cover this <lb/>part, does not make a ſufficient
        reſiſtance, <lb/>to communicate the effect which the <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >preſſing</w> body ſhould have upon the <w part="I">verte-</w><lb/><w part="F">bræ</w>: to
        theſe impediments, we may add <lb/>the weight of the head and upper <w part="I"
          >extre-</w><lb/><w part="F">mities</w>, which will always act upon the <lb/>ſpine, unleſs
        the patient is kept conſtantly <lb/>in bed, which might be attended with many <lb/>other
        inconveniences. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The only caſe therefore, in which this <lb/>preſſure could take any
        effect, would be, <lb/>where the ſpine was bent from within <w part="I">out-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">wards</w>: for then by acting immediately <w part="I">up-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >on</w> the vertebræ projecting, the progreſs <lb/>of the diſorder might perhaps be
        prevented; <lb/>but the pain and conſtraint which muſt <w part="I">ne-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ceſſarily</w> follow ſuch an operation would be <lb/>almoſt inſupportable. The ſpinal
        proceſſes <lb/>of the vertebræ are ſo projecting in theſe <lb/>patients, that the ſlighteſt
        degree of <w part="I">preſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſure</w> cauſes great pain, and whatever
        care <lb/>we may take in wadding and guarding both <lb/>the compreſſing bodies, and the
        parts which <lb/>are to be compreſſed, they are never able <pb xml:id="page_13" n="14"
        /><lb/>to bear this preſſure for any length of <lb/>time<note place="bottom" n="*"
          rend="size(0.5)">* We may ſee a remarkable proof of this in the inſtance of <lb/>Madame de
          Montomorency as related by Lazarus <lb/>Riverius; from which caſe it may be inferred, that
          the <w part="I">vio-</w><lb/><w part="F">lence</w> of the torture cauſed by the preſſure
          in the only caſe <lb/>where it could poſſibly be of any ſervice, appears to be a
          <lb/>ſufficient reaſon for rejecting it entirely. </note>. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Gliſſon being himſelf convinced of the <lb/>inſufficiency of all theſe
        methods, <w part="I">acknow-</w><lb/><w part="F">ledges</w> the neceſſity of extending the
        ſpine <lb/>in order to make it ſtraight again; but the <lb/>ſort of extenſion which he
        propoſes not <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> conſtant, is ſtill inadequate: this
          <w part="I">me-</w><lb/><w part="F">thod</w>, practiſed in England, is called <w part="I"
          >ſwing-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>; it conſiſts, in ſuſpending the child <lb/>with
        ſtrings diſpoſed in ſuch a manner, <lb/>that the body may be entirely ſupported by <lb/>the
        head and upper extremities; and to <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">creaſe</w> the degree
        of extenſion, weights are <lb/>ſometimes added to the feet. In this <w part="I"
          >ſitua-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> they endeavour to divert the child, <lb/>that he may
        be induced to continue this <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">erciſe</w> as long as
        poſſible; but however <lb/>delighted he may be at firſt, at feeling <w part="I"
          >him-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſelf</w> ballanced in the air, yet a wearineſs <lb/>ſoon ſeizes
        all his limbs, and at the end of <lb/>a quarter of an hour at moſt, he begs to be
        <lb/>releaſed from his confinement. It is <lb/>evident, that the effect of extenſion for ſo
          <pb xml:id="page_14" n="15"/><lb/>ſhort a time, muſt be very trifling; and <lb/>the weight
        of the parts during the reſt of <lb/>the day, ſoon deſtroys any little advantage <lb/>which
        may have been gained by it. If the <lb/>ſame exerciſe is repeated, the alternate <w part="I"
          >exten-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſion</w>, and greater bearing down of the parts <lb/>after the
        fatigue of it, weakens the muſcles <lb/>and ligaments ſo much that the ſpine becomes
        <lb/>more pliant, and its curvature is increaſed. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>From what has been ſaid, it is evident, <lb/>that nothing but a conſtant
        and gradual <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">tenſion</w> can poſſibly prevent, or redreſs
        a <lb/>præternatural inflexion of the ſpine; and that <lb/>none of the methods hitherto
        practiſed, are <lb/>ſufficient for this purpoſe. It remains <w part="I">there-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">fore</w> that the method which I now offer to <lb/>the public ſhould be proved
        fully to anſwer <lb/>this intention, and that it is conſequently far <lb/>more beneficial
        than any yet propoſed. The <lb/>two moſt eſſential circumſtances in this <lb/>method are a
        whalebone bodice, and a <w part="I">ma-</w><lb/><w part="F">chine</w> rather complicated in
        its ſtructure, <lb/>though extremely ſimple in its effect. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The whalebone bodice differs from a <lb/>common quilted waiſtcoat only,
        in being <lb/>laced at the fore part, and being fitted cloſe <lb/>to the hips and os ſacrum. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The machine may be divided into three <lb/>pieces. The firſt, is a plate
        of braſs having <lb/>the form of a rectangle, a little blunted at <pb xml:id="page_15"
          n="16"/><lb/>the angles, at each of which there is a <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >foration</w> made, to receive the flat heads of <lb/>ſome ſcrews, after they have paſſed
        through <lb/>correſpondent holes made for that purpoſe, <lb/>through the whole thickneſs of
        the bodice; <lb/>this plate, by its conſtruction, ſerves to <w part="I">ſup-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">port</w> the beam or <hi rend="italic">ſuſpenſory,</hi> which is the <lb/>ſecond
        piece; this beam is made of a piece <lb/>of well tempered ſteel, the body and <lb/>foot of
        which are of equal thickneſs; it <lb/>muſt be two lines and an half in breadth; <lb/>the
        foot and body of the beam muſt be <lb/>ſtraight, and continued, ſo as to extend as <lb/>far
        as the curvature in this ſame piece, which <lb/>terminates at the fore part of the head. If
        <lb/>the head is thrown ſo much to one ſide, as <lb/>to cauſe what is called the caput
        obſtipum, <lb/>the beam muſt then be twiſted, and its <lb/>upper branch bifurcated. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The third piece, or head dreſs, is the <lb/>moſt complicated part of the
        machine; it <lb/>conſiſts firſt in a cap made of any kind of <lb/>ſoft cloth, the borders of
        which are to be <lb/>four fingers broad, and to have two button <lb/>holes made through
        them; ſecondly, in a <lb/>fillet, made long enough to ſurround the <lb/>head; thirdly, in a
        buckle, with a double <lb/>ſhape, each chape, furniſhed with two <lb/>tongues; the fourth
        part of the head dreſs, <lb/><unclear>#</unclear> a fillet of braſs which becomes gradually<lb/>
        <unclear>##</unclear>in, it is bent towards it's flat ſurface, and <pb xml:id="page_16"
          n="17"/><lb/>is fitted to the double buckle. The fifth <lb/>part is a ſmall plate of braſs
        or ſteel made <lb/>round, through a hole in the middle of <lb/>which, paſſes a pretty large
        hook, which is <lb/>ſituated underneath this plate, in order to <lb/>receive, or let through
        the end of the <lb/>beam, which by ſupporting the head and <lb/>upper extremities, gradually
        lengthens the <lb/>ſpinal column, and preſerves it in its natural <lb/>and perpendicular
        direction. It may be <lb/>imagined from the number of pieces which <lb/>this machine is
        compoſed of, that it's <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">plication</w> is very difficult,
        but any perſon <lb/>who has the care of a child, and who has <lb/>ever ſo ſmall a ſhare of
        underſtanding may <lb/>be taught in time to manage it with <w part="I">ſuc-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">cess</w>. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I have alſo other methods beſides this <lb/>Machine, for perſons of a
        more advanced <lb/>age in whom it is ineffectual, without the <lb/>uſe of a ſwing, in which
        I put them for <lb/>ſeveral hours together. My ſwing differs <lb/>from <hi rend="sc"
          >Glisson</hi>'S eſſentially, ſince it neither <lb/>confines nor gives any pain to the
        patient. <lb/>and that his limbs do not grow benumbed <lb/>as they do with the other ſwing
        commonly <lb/>uſed in this country; and which cannot be <lb/>continued longer than a quarter
        of an hour <lb/>at a time. I can even venture to ſay, that <lb/>any perſon who will confine
        himſelf much <pb xml:id="page_17" n="18"/><lb/>to his bed, may be cured in the ſpace of
        <lb/>three months. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The advantages of this machine are <w part="I">evi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >dent</w>; it keeps the ſpine extended as much <lb/>and for as long a time as one may
        think <lb/>neceſſary; the patient is able to walk with <lb/>it, and can even employ himſelf
        as much as <lb/>he pleaſes. It does not hinder young ladies <lb/>from playing on the
        harpſichord, learning to <lb/>dance, to draw, or to write. Children, <lb/>who from the
        dangerous ſtate of their health <lb/>have been obliged to wear it all night long, <lb/>have
        ſtill ſlept as uſual. I even ſaw an <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtance</w> of a girl
        of eight years old at Paris, <lb/>who finding herſelf relieved, fell ſo faſt <lb/>a-ſleep in
        her chair immediately after the <lb/>machine had been put on, that her mother <lb/>thought
        her dead, and told me the next day, <lb/>that being at firſt apprehenſive that the <w
          part="I">ma-</w><lb/><w part="F">chine</w> had killed her child, ſhe had a great <lb/>mind
        to take the whole off. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>This is not a matter of mere ſpeculation, <lb/>for although the reaſons
        here alledged, might <lb/>be ſufficient to prove that this method is <lb/>preferable to any
        other, yet the great <w part="I">ſuc-</w><lb/><w part="F">cess</w> which has attended the
        practice of it, <lb/>in all the caſes where it has been hitherto <lb/>uſed, will eſtabliſh
        this preference in a <pb xml:id="page_18" n="19"/><lb/>more inconteſtable manner; which I
        ſhall <lb/>endeavour to do by the following obſervations. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the month of September 1764, a lady <lb/>twelve years old was ſeized
        with a violent <lb/>and conſtant cough, which could not be <lb/>appeaſed; this was
        accompanied with a <w part="I">fe-</w><lb/><w part="F">ver</w> which extenuated her to a
        terrible degree. <lb/>The remedies which were adminiſtered to <lb/>her in a provincial
        convent, where ſhe was, <lb/>proved unſucceſſful. Her parents had her <lb/>brought back to
        Paris, where all the <w part="I">aſſiſtan-</w><lb/><w part="F">ces</w> which medicine could
        furniſh were again <lb/>tried with as little efficacy as before; and ſhe <lb/>was thought to
        be in great danger of her life. <lb/>I perceived, although I only ſaw her in bed, <lb/>that
        ſhe kept herſelf always bent; and that <lb/>her face bore evident marks of a ricketty
        <lb/>habit. I deſired leave to look at the ſpine, <lb/>which I found very much warped
        laterally <lb/>in two places, the five upper vertebræ of <lb/>the back were thrown from the
        right to the <lb/>left ſide and forwards; the three following <lb/>vertebræ were in their
        natural direction, but <lb/>were twiſted ſo that their bodies bearing to <lb/>the left,
        diminiſhed conſiderably the right <lb/>ſide of the thorax; the ſour lower vertebræ <lb/>of
        the back and the three upper vertebræ of <lb/>the loins were incurvated from the left to
        <lb/>the right ſide; ſo that when ſhe was ſitting, <lb/>the whole body bore upon the right
        hip. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_19" n="20"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I told the parents that all the bad <w part="I">ſymp-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">toms</w> which this child laboured under, were <lb/>owing to a confinement of the
        organs within <lb/>the breaſt; and that, inſtead of giving her <lb/>medicines internally,
        the only way to effect <lb/>a cure, was, to ſet the ſuffering parts at <lb/>eaſe quickly.
        The little ſucceſs which was <lb/>to be expected from the methods commonly <lb/>uſed,
        induced me to contrive a machine, <lb/>nearly ſimilar to the one above deſcribed. <lb/>This
        machine although very rude at that <lb/>time, and much leſs convenient than the <lb/>one I
        uſe at preſent, had notwithſtanding ſo <lb/>good an effect, that in a ſhort time, the
        <lb/>ſymptoms which endangered life being <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">moved</w>, the
        lady recovered her uſual <w part="I">full-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w> and health. The
        curvature of the ſpine <lb/>has alſo diſappeared, and ſhe is at preſent <lb/>very well
        ſhaped. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>This was the firſt trial of the machine; <lb/>the ſucceſs attending it,
        and the frequent <lb/>opportunities which have ſince offered of <lb/>applying it, have
        induced me to endeavour <lb/>to bring this method to a greater degree of <lb/>perfection;
        and the courſe of three years <lb/>application to this circumſtance, has taught <lb/>me the
        following particulars. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>By this method therefore, we may expect <lb/>to cure any children whoſe
        ſpine is crooked, <pb xml:id="page_20" n="21"/><lb/>provided that their age does not exceed
        12 <lb/>or 13 years; and provided, we may depend <lb/>upon the perſons who have the care of
        them, <lb/>ſo far as to be aſſured that they will oblige <lb/>them to wear the machine
        conſtantly. The <lb/>number of children who have been cured at <lb/>this age is too
        conſiderable to give an <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">count</w> of them here, it may
        be ſufficient to <lb/>ſay, that many cures of this kind have been <lb/>performed, under the
        inſpection of ſome <w part="I">mem-</w><lb/><w part="F">bers</w> of the academy: Mr. <hi
          rend="italic">Louis,</hi> the perpetual <lb/>ſecretary, has ſeen one inſtance in a little
        girl <lb/>between 7 and 8 years of age: Mr. <hi rend="italic">Andouillè</hi>
        <lb/>firſt ſurgeon to the king in reverſion, has <lb/>ſeen, with Mr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Didier,</hi> a member of this <lb/>academy, another young lady who has been <lb/>ſet to
        rights in a ſhort ſpace of time; ſhe <lb/>was only ſix years old, and the curvature <lb/>was
        not yet very conſiderable; the ſame Mr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Didier</hi> has ſeen other
        patients cured in the <lb/>ſame manner. A young lady of nine years <lb/>old has been cured
        under the inſpection of <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">De la Malle,</hi> counſellor of the
        academy; <lb/>and the cure of another of eight years old <lb/>has been ſeen by Monſieur <hi
          rend="italic">Ruffell,</hi> director <lb/>of the academy. When a more advanced <lb/>age
        fruſtrates the hopes of an entire cure, on <lb/>account of the ſpine not having a ſufficient
        <lb/>degree of flexibility to give way to the force <pb xml:id="page_21" n="22"/><lb/>of the
        machine, it may then be applied <lb/>with intention to put a ſtop to the farther
        <lb/>progreſs of the diſorder, and it ſhould be <lb/>wore in ſuch circumſtances till age has
        ſo <lb/>far ſtrengthened the ſpine, that all danger <lb/>is removed, Mr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Houſtet,</hi> antient director of <lb/>the academy, entruſted to my care a lady of
        <lb/>14 years old, whoſe ſhape was deformed; <lb/>this lady has not been quite cured though
        <lb/>ſhe wore the machine for one year and an <lb/>half; but the inconvenience, far from <w
          part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">creaſing</w> as it would have <corr>done<sic>done
            done</sic></corr> without <lb/>this aſſiſtance, has been much leſſened, ſo <lb/>that
        there is now no appearance of any <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">formity</w> when the
        lady is dreſt.—When the <lb/>crookedneſs of the ſpine has begun very <lb/>early in life, and
        has gained very <w part="I">conſidera-</w><lb/><w part="F">bly</w>, we cannot aſcertain the
        cure, but <lb/>ſtill the caſe is not to be given up as <w part="I">irreme-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">diable</w>; eſpecially, if there is no diſtortion <lb/>of the vertebræ: Mr. <hi
          rend="italic">Duclos,</hi> member of <lb/>the academy, ſent me in the year 1765, a
        <lb/>little boy, aged 9 years, whoſe ſpine was ſo <lb/>very crooked, that his chin was
        ſupported <lb/>by his breaſt; and the ſternum made a very <lb/>great projection forwards;
        the lower <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">tremity</w> on the left ſide being weaker than
        <lb/>on the right, had given way to the weight <lb/>of the body, and was conſiderably bent
          <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">wards</w> at the articulation of the thigh bone <pb
          xml:id="page_22" n="23"/><lb/>with the tibia: the child could ſcarcely <lb/>ſupport
        himſelf; he could not ſleep, and, <lb/>cried out ſo much in the night time, that <lb/>his
        parents were afraid he ſhould die. When <lb/>the child had wore the machine for a <w
          part="I">fort-</w><lb/><w part="F">night</w>, he began to grow better in his health,
        <lb/>his ſleep and appetite returned, and he ſoon <lb/>after recovered, and became plump as
        uſual; <lb/>his ſhape now deviates very little from the <lb/>natural ſtate, and what is
        ſtill more <w part="I">remark-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w>, his limb recovered itſelf ſo far
        without <lb/>any other aſſiſtance, that there now remains <lb/>but a very ſlight bend, which
        will probably <lb/>wear off in time. The diſtortion of the <lb/>vertebræ reſiſts the power
        of the machine <lb/>more than other circumſtances; on which <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">count</w>, we ſhould take care not to make an <lb/>inconſiderate prognoſtic. In
        thoſe caſes where <lb/>the age of the patient, or the advanced ſtate <lb/>of the diſeaſe,
        will not permit us to expect <lb/>a compleat cure, the machine will always <lb/>be of ſo
        much ſervice, as to reſtore health. <lb/>Two ladies who were each of them between <lb/>14
        and 15 years age, were reduced to ſuch a <lb/>degree of Maraſmus, that it was concluded
        <lb/>they had but a ſhort time to live; the ſpine <lb/>was ſo crooked that the natural
        length of <lb/>their ſhape was diminiſhed by one half at <lb/>leaſt; the breaſt had almoſt
        loſt all marks <lb/>of its firſt appearance, and conformation; <pb xml:id="page_23" n="24"
        /><lb/>their breathing was ſhort, their power of <lb/>digeſtion was deſtroyed, and they
        ſuffered <lb/>continual pains all over the body; ſo that <lb/>theſe children could ſcarcely
        be ſaid to live, <lb/>but rather ſeemed to be going ſlowly and <lb/>gradually down to the
        grave. The uſe of <lb/>the machine has reſtored health to each of <lb/>them; they have
        recovered their fullneſs, <lb/>one of them is even grown fat; they can <lb/>both go up the
        ſteepeſt ſtair-caſe without <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> out of breath; which
        they could not have <lb/>done before without infinite trouble and <w part="I">op-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">preſſion</w>; their ſhapes are not entirely rectified, <lb/>the little deformity
        remaining, can eaſily be <lb/>hid by their dreſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Such are the ſimple means, to which <lb/>many perſons owe the recovery
        of their <lb/>health, and the beauty of their ſhapes. <lb/>My wiſhes would be fulfilled, if
        by <w part="I">adopt-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> this invention, practitioners ſhould <w
          part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">firm</w> the poſſibility of curing a diſorder, the
        <lb/>moſt moderate effect of which, is, to <w part="I">occa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſion</w> a
        deformity which laſts as long as life. </p>
      <trailer rend="align-center"><lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
