<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Büchner: An easy and very practicable method to enable deaf persons to
          hear</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Andreas Elias Büchner</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">AN EASY AND VERY PRACTICABLE METHOD TO ENABLE DEAF PERSONS TO HEAR:
              Together with A brief Account of, and some Reflections and Observations upon, the
              several Attempts formerly made for the Benefit of such Persons. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T32400</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T32400"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for Mess. Hawes, Clarke, and Collins, Booksellers in
                  Paternoster-Row, MDCCLXX.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1770</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="6"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="57"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3307569732</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K035511.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: method"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_3" n="i"/>
        <head rend="align-center dc(2)"><lb/>INTRODUCTION. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HE more extenſively uſeful, <lb/>and the more
          adapted to <lb/>the occaſions of life, the matters <lb/>are which an author takes upon
          <lb/>him to lay before his readers, the <lb/>more he anſwers that end, which <lb/>every
          virtuous man ought, in <w part="I">ju-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtice</w>, to propoſe to
          himſelf in every <lb/>addreſs to the Public, and the <lb/>more ſuch matters claim the <w
            part="I">atten-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> and patience of the reader. <lb/>Theſe
          conſiderations have <w part="I">princi-</w><pb xml:id="page_4" n="ii"/><lb/><w part="F"
            >pally</w> weighed with me in favour of <lb/>the preſent undertaking, and I <w part="I"
            >pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">miſe</w> myſelf, on this occaſion, the <lb/>approbation of
          every one, who can <lb/>put a due value on the enjoyment <lb/>of his ſenſes, as well as of
          him, who <lb/>can be ſenſible of the great <w part="I">diſad-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >vantage</w> ariſing from the loſs of any <lb/>of them. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Sight and hearing are <w part="I">undoubt-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >edly</w> two of the principal external <lb/>ſenſes, as they ſupply us with the
          <lb/>knowledge of a far greater number <lb/>of external objects, than the other
          <lb/>ſenſes put together; which, though <lb/>indeed of conſiderable, are yet of <lb/>a
          more limited uſefulneſs, and their <lb/>impairment or loſs more tolerable; <lb/>but blind
          or deaf, what melancholy <lb/>objects! Both blind and deaf, what <lb/>accumulated woe! </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_5" n="iii"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I wave, at preſent, the ſeveral <lb/>attempts wich have been made, in
          <lb/>order to correct the manifold defects <lb/>of ſight, at leaſt to leſſen or render
          <lb/>them tolerable, confining my <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">flections</w>, on
          this occaſion, to that <lb/>of hearing; and, for that purpoſe <lb/>I ſhall relate the
          ſeveral means <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">viſed</w>, in order to amend this ſenſe,
          <lb/>when impaired, or retrieve it, when <lb/>intirely loſt; or by help of the <lb/>other
          ſenſes, and a tolerable degree <lb/>of underſtanding in the patient, to <lb/>render its
          loſs, in ſome meaſure, <lb/>more tolerable: And laſtly, I ſhall <lb/>ſelect, among the
          ſeveral methods <lb/>propoſed, that, which to me <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >pears</w>, to be the eaſieſt and moſt <lb/>ſimple. But, previous to this, I <lb/>ſhall
          briefly explain the reaſons of <lb/>the principal defects of the ſenſe of <lb/>hearing,
          both from their cauſes, <pb xml:id="page_6" n="iv"/><lb/>and from the ſtructure of the
          outer <lb/>and inner ear; and then more <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">curately</w>
          determine the greater or <lb/>leſs utility of the methods hitherto <lb/>employed, in order
          to amend theſe <lb/>defects. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>

      <pb xml:id="page_7"/>
      <head rend="align-center"><lb/>AN <lb/>EASY AND PRACTICABLE <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">METHOD</hi>,
          <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
      </head>
      <div n="1" type="chapter">
        <head rend="italic align-center"><lb/><hi rend="roman">CHAP. I.</hi> Containing reflections
          preparatory to the following diſcourſe. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">A</hi>MONG the defects, to which the <lb/>ſenſe of
          hearing is ſubject, the <lb/>greateſt, without diſpute, is the <lb/>entire loſs thereof,
          or that, which, in a <lb/>word, we call <hi rend="italic">deafneſs.</hi> This, when <w
            part="I">ei-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> brought into the world, or contracted
          <lb/>before a child comes to the uſe of his <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >derſtanding</w>, and before he learns to ſpeak, <lb/>renders him very unhappy, as
          thereby he <lb/>continues to be ſpeechleſs or dumb, and <pb xml:id="page_8" n="2"
          /><lb/>thus precluded all ſocial intercourſe. And <lb/>this is the reaſon, why perſons
          born deaf, <lb/>are at the ſame time alſo dumb, if not <lb/>taught to ſpeak by ſome
          peculiar devices, <lb/>or by means of the other ſenſes. To this <lb/>defect of hearing, we
          are to claſs that <lb/>which is called <hi rend="italic">difficulty of hearing;</hi>
          which, <lb/>beſides that it comes neareſt to abſolute <lb/>deafneſs, proceeds, for the
          moſt part, <lb/>from the ſame cauſes, only in a leſs <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >gree</w>; all the other defects of this ſenſe, as <lb/>not being to our preſent
          purpoſe, we ſhall <lb/>wave at this time. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>All the ſenſes have from nature their <lb/>proper organs, which are in
          a certain <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">terminate</w> manner affected and altered by
          <lb/>external objects; and firſt, in that they <lb/>propagate theſe affections or
          alterations to <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">common ſenſory,</hi> and thereby render our
          <lb/>ſenſations complete, and communicate <lb/>them to the ſoul. Now, as deafneſs is
          <lb/>the inability to perceive thoſe tremulous <lb/>or vibratory motions of the air, which
          <lb/>produce ſound; the cauſe of this defect <lb/>muſt neceſſarily be, either in the organ
            <w part="I">it-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſelf</w>, namely the ear, or in its connection
          <lb/>with the common ſenſory, the vibrations <pb xml:id="page_9" n="3"/><lb/>of the air
          being prevented from producing <lb/>the neceſſary and determinate alterations in
          <lb/>thoſe parts of the human body. The ſame <lb/>thing holds with reſpect to difficulty
          of <lb/>hearing, as being only a leſs degreee of <lb/>deafneſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The ear conſiſts of ſeveral diſtinct parts, <lb/>which together concur
          to produce the <lb/>ſenſe of hearing. Hence, if the cauſes of <lb/>deafneſs, or of a
          difficulty of hearing, are <lb/>in the ear itſelf, one or more parts thereof <lb/>muſt be
          injured, that is, be in a <w part="I">preterna-</w><lb/><w part="F">tural</w> ſtate. To
          ſhew this the more <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtinctly</w>, it is neceſſary to
          conſider thoſe <lb/>parts ſeparately, and to explain the <w part="I">preter-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">natural</w> alterations which occaſion deafneſs, <lb/>or a difficulty of
          hearing. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Anatomiſts commonly divide the parts <lb/>of the ear into two ſorts,
          namely, thoſe <lb/>which belong to the external ear, and are <lb/>ſituate without the
          temporal bones; and <lb/>into thoſe that conſtitute the inner ear, <lb/>compriſing all the
          parts that lie within <lb/>the ſaid bones. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>To the firſt ſort belongs that which is <lb/>properly called the outer
          ear, and the <hi rend="italic">mea-<lb/>tus auditorius,</hi> or auditory paſſage or canal,
            <pb xml:id="page_10" n="4"/><lb/>the inner part of which laſt, anatomiſts <lb/>generally
          refer to the inner ear; but it <lb/>may be here very commodiouſly treated, <lb/>together
          with the external parts, as being <lb/>only a paſſage from them. As the <w part="I"
            >diffe-</w><lb/><w part="F">rent</w> defects of that which is properly <lb/>called the
          external ear, if, in other reſpects, <lb/>the aperture of the auditory paſſage is not at
          <lb/>the ſame time affected, may produce a <w part="I">diffi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >culty</w> of hearing, or other defect of this <lb/>ſenſe, but are never the cauſes of
          perfect <lb/>deafneſs; ſo I ſhall not inſiſt on this, <lb/>but directly handle the ſeveral
          defects <lb/>of the auditory paſſage, as an <w part="I">exter-</w><lb/><w part="F">nal</w>
          part of the ear, ſo far as they are <lb/>to my preſent purpoſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The uſe of the auditory paſſage is, to <lb/>propagate the vibrations
          of the air, <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">municated</w> externally thereto, by
          repeated <lb/>repercuſſions in its cavity, to the inner <lb/>parts of the ear: And thence
          it is <w part="I">neceſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſary</w>, that this paſſage be neither <w
            part="I">obſtruct-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>, nor extraordinarily conſtricted or
          <lb/>ſtraitened. In the firſt caſe, deafneſs is <lb/>the conſequence; in the laſt, a
          difficulty <lb/>of hearing at leaſt. The firſt defect often <lb/>ariſes either from a long
          accumulated, a <pb xml:id="page_11" n="5"/><lb/>condenſed, or a greatly indurated ear-wax,
          <lb/>or from foreign bodies introduced into <lb/>the auditory paſſage; as for inſtance,
          <lb/>cherry-ſtones, peas, lead-ſhot, &amp;c. or from <lb/>tumours and impoſthumes, or from
          fleſhy <lb/>or ſpungy excreſcences therein; or, very <lb/>often from the concretion of its
          ſides <lb/>from ſuch impoſthumes; or, laſtly, from <lb/>a pellicle or membrance growing
          acroſs <lb/>it, as is frequently obſerved in new-born <lb/>children. The other defect of
          the <w part="I">audi-</w><lb/><w part="F">tory</w> paſſage, namely, its too great <w
            part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtriction</w>, may ariſe from the very ſame
          <lb/>cauſes, if we only except the preternatural <lb/>membrane ſtretched acroſs it, or the
            <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtruction</w> of the auditory paſſage by fluid
          <lb/>matters, which diffuſe themſelves on every <lb/>ſide. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The ſecond ſpecies of the parts of the <lb/>ear, mentioned above,
          conſtitutes the <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ner</w> ear, and compriſes the
          membrane of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">tympanum,</hi> or drum, its cavity, the <w part="I"
            >la-</w><lb/><w part="F">byrinth</w>, the <hi rend="italic">tuba Euſtachii,</hi> and the
            <w part="I">audi-</w><lb/><w part="F">tory</w> nerves. The membrane of the <lb/>drum
          receives by the auditory paſſage the <lb/>tremulous motions or vibrations of the air,
          <lb/>which it farther diffuſes in its cavity, and <pb xml:id="page_12" n="6"/><lb/>in the
          labyrinth. But particularly in the <lb/>drum we find four ſpecies of defects, which
          <lb/>prevent its ordinary uſe: One, the too <lb/>great flaccidity of its membrane, whereby
          <lb/>it is unfitted for vibrations or tremulous <lb/>motions, and ſo tranſmits ſounds,
          either not <lb/>at all, or but faintly, to the other inner <lb/>parts. And hence we may
          judge, how it <lb/>happens, that a phlegmatic conſtitution, <lb/>moiſt and purulent ears,
          damp air, foggy <lb/>and rainy weather, and the like, often <lb/>increaſe a difficulty of
          hearing, to a pitch <lb/>of perfect deafneſs. The other defect of <lb/>the membrane of the
          drum is directly <lb/>oppoſite to this, and conſiſts in an <w part="I">extra-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ordinary</w> tenſion thereof; which, when to <lb/>ſo conſiderable a degree, as
          too much to <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſiſt</w> the inſinuating tremulous air,
          and <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">vent</w> its vibrations, gives riſe in like <w
            part="I">man-</w><lb/><w part="F">ner</w> to a difficulty of hearing, and even <lb/>to
          perfect deafneſs; as may be often <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerved</w> in the
          caſe of elderly people, and <lb/>emaciated conſtitutions. Both theſe <w part="I"
            >de-</w><lb/><w part="F">fects</w>, flaccidity and tenſion, may alſo ariſe <lb/>from an
          undue action of the muſcles, <lb/>moving the ſmall auditory bones. But as <lb/>ſuch
          conſiderations would carry us to <w part="I">ana-</w><pb xml:id="page_13" n="7"/><lb/><w
            part="F">tomical</w> and philoſophical niceties, we ſhall <lb/>wave them at preſent, as
          not greatly to <lb/>our purpoſe. The complete induration, <lb/>or even oſſification of the
          membrane of <lb/>the drum, is the third defect; which may <lb/>beſides, from the ſame
          cauſes mentioned <lb/>before, under the extraordinary tenſion of <lb/>this membrane,
          impair the hearing. And <lb/>laſtly, its laceration conſtitutes the fourth <lb/>defect,
          which, indeed, does not ſo ſoon <lb/>vitiate the hearing; as the air, inſinuating
          <lb/>into the auditory paſſage, can freely paſs <lb/>into the inner parts of the ear, and
          put <lb/>them in motion: but then, by this <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F">mediate</w>
          contact, the juſt mentioned tender <lb/>and ſenſible inner parts are blunted and
          <lb/>rendered unfit for farther regular <w part="I">ſen-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſations</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The cavity of the drum, and the <w part="I">laby-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >rinth</w> are, indeed, as conſiſting of bones of <lb/>a more durable ſubſtance than all
          the parts <lb/>of the ear hitherto mentioned, ſometimes, <lb/>however, ſubject to ſeveral
          untoward <w part="I">acci-</w><lb/><w part="F">dents</w>, whereby the hearing may be <w
            part="I">inju-</w><lb/><w part="F">red</w> or depraved. For as they are covered
          <lb/>with a very tender and extremely ſenſible <lb/><hi rend="italic">perioſteum,</hi>
          which may be affected with <pb xml:id="page_14" n="8"/><lb/>inflammation and impoſthume,
          and thereby <lb/>be either deſtroyed, or ſo indurated, that <lb/>no communicated
          vibrations of the air can <lb/>any longer put them in due motion: Or, <lb/>alſo, as theſe
          cavities are ſometimes ſo <lb/>choaked up with purulent matter, as to <lb/>become unfit
          for propagating the vibratory <lb/>motions of the air; or that at length there
          <lb/>ſometimes enſues from the <w part="I">impoſthuma-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of the
            <hi rend="italic">perioſteum,</hi> a caries of the bones <lb/>themſelves, which may
          intirely deſtroy <lb/>the whole of this curious piece of <w part="I">mecha-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">niſm</w>, and unfit it for its deſtination. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the laſt place, before I touch on the <lb/>defects of the auditory
          nerve, I muſt <w part="I">far-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> mention the <hi rend="italic"
            >tuba Euſtachii,</hi> which <lb/>ſome reckon among the parts of the <w part="I"
            >exter-</w><lb/><w part="F">nal</w> ear, but which I refer to the internal, <lb/>becauſe
          the bony part of this paſſage lies <lb/>between the temporal bone and the <hi
            rend="italic">os <lb/>multiforme;</hi> beſides, the entire paſſage lies <lb/>concealed
          in the cavity of the mouth: <lb/>And running from the cavity of the drum <lb/>to the
          palate, and terminating behind the <lb/>tonſils, with an aperture in the mouth, is
          <lb/>partly bony, partly cartilaginous, and <lb/>partly membranous, and internally lined
            <pb xml:id="page_15" n="9"/><lb/>with a fine membrane full of mucoſe <lb/>glands: This
          paſſage, I ſay, ſerves <w part="I">princi-</w><lb/><w part="F">pally</w> to renew or ſhift
          the air, which is <lb/>lodged in the inner cavities of the ear, in <lb/>order to prevent
          its intire loſs of elaſticity <lb/>by a too long confinement there. When <lb/>this paſſage
          therefore is either obſtructed, <lb/>or intirely deſtroyed, the air, contained in <lb/>the
          ear, will be unfit for the reception and <lb/>propagation of that determinate degree of
          <lb/>vibratory motion, which is neceſſary for <lb/>the act of hearing. The obſtruction of
          <lb/>this paſſage often ariſes from a critical and <lb/>catarrhous accumulation of mucus,
          from <lb/>an incraſſation and induration of this <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cumulated</w> mucus; from the ſwelling of <lb/>the mucoſe glands; from membranous
          <lb/>and fibrous excreſcences; which, upon <lb/>the eroſion of the inner membrane of
          <lb/>this paſſage, ſometimes happen, <w part="I">particu-</w><lb/><w part="F">larly</w> by
          a venereal taint; and from <w part="I">num-</w><lb/><w part="F">berless</w> other cauſes.
          The eroſion in this <lb/>caſe happens in the ſame manner, as was <lb/>mentioned in the
          eroſion of the membranes <lb/>of the bones of the ear. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The auditory nerve is the laſt, but yet <lb/>a principal part of the
          internal ear, and <pb xml:id="page_16" n="10"/><lb/>the alone <hi rend="italic"
            >copula,</hi> or tie, by which this <w part="I">pe-</w><lb/><w part="F">culiar</w> organ
          of ſenſation is connected with <lb/>the common ſenſory. Whence alſo its <lb/>due and
          regular diſpoſition is <w part="I">abſolute-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> neceſſary, in
          order to communicate to <lb/>the ſoul, by means of this ſenſe, its <w part="I"
            >pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">per</w> perceptions and ſenſations. This <w part="I"
            >com-</w><lb/><w part="F">munication</w> or intercourſe of motion is <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">terrupted</w>, when the ſubtle fluid, called <lb/>the nervous
          juice by phyſiological writers, <lb/>is obſtructed in its regular motion and <lb/>paſſage
          through theſe nerves and their <lb/>principal branches. Moſt pathologiſts <lb/>reckon
          principally, among the cauſes of <lb/>this interrupted paſſage, the obſtruction <lb/>of
          the nerve. But as from phyſiological <lb/>principles, it does not appear, how this
          <lb/>extraordinary ſubtle fluid ſhould be <w part="I">incraſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſated</w>, or the fibres of the nerves drawn <lb/>together or contracted; the
          obſtruction in <lb/>this caſe muſt be the ſame as when in the <lb/>nutricious veſſels, and
          within the <hi rend="italic">involucra</hi>
          <lb/>or ſheaths of this nerve, accumulated, <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >durated</w>, or even extravaſated juices from <lb/>lacerated veſſels, being collected,
          compreſs <lb/>the nervous fibres. The principal defect, <lb/>which in theſe nerves can
          poſſibly <w part="I">inter-</w><pb xml:id="page_17" n="11"/><lb/><w part="F">rupt</w> the
          motion of the nervous juice, is, <lb/>ſecondly, their compreſſion; which may <lb/>ariſe
          either at their origin, or near the <lb/>common ſenſory, or in their entire length,
          <lb/>either internally or externally, by <w part="I">accumu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lated</w>
          or even extravaſated blood, or other <lb/>juices of the adjacent parts; as alſo in the
          <lb/>ear itſelf, from a <hi rend="italic">caries</hi> or <hi rend="italic">exoſtoſis</hi>
          of its <lb/>bones; which laſt has often been obſerved, <lb/>particularly in venereal
          caſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Beſides theſe defects of the auditory <lb/>nerve hitherto mentioned,
          we are <w part="I">princi-</w><lb/><w part="F">pally</w> to attend to the ſeat of this <w
            part="I">diſor-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w>, and to its greater or leſs diſtance from
          <lb/>the common ſenſory. For, when <w part="I">deaf-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w> ariſes
          from compreſſion, or even <w part="I">ero-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſion</w> of the nerve
          ſpread over the labyrinth, <lb/>there ſtill remains a reſource to ſupply this <lb/>defect
          in another and that an ingenious <lb/>manner; and even to produce ſuch <w part="I"
            >ſenſa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w>, as are otherwiſe communicated to <lb/>the ſoul by
          the organ of hearing. But <lb/>if the origin of the nerve, namely, that <lb/>part thereof
          which lies neareſt the <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">mon</w> ſenſory in the brain,
          is injured, it is <lb/>not in the power of art to reſtore the ſenſe <lb/>of hearing. Yet
          by all this I would not <pb xml:id="page_18" n="12"/><lb/>on any account deny, but that
          dumb <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſons</w> of this claſs, might by the eye, by
          <lb/>a long, careful, and attentive obſervation <lb/>of the different motions of the mouth
          in <lb/>the act of ſpeaking, be brought, at laſt, <lb/>to underſtand the thoughts of thoſe
          about <lb/>them; as in <hi rend="italic">Amman</hi>'s method, of which <lb/>hereafter.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="chapter">
        <head rend="italic align-center"><lb/><hi rend="roman">CHAP. II.</hi>
          <lb/>An account of the attempts formerly made <lb/>for the relief of the deaf. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">H</hi>OW various ſoever the cauſes of <lb/>deafneſs
          and difficulty of hearing, <lb/>hitherto mentioned, may be, many have, <lb/>for a long
          time paſt, eſpecially more <w part="I">lat-</w><lb/><w part="F">terly</w>, been employed
          in the queſt and <lb/>diſcovery of the means of removing ſome <lb/>way or other, or at
          leaſt of diminiſhing <lb/>this calamity. The many eſſays for this <lb/>purpoſe, made by
          phyſicians and inquirers <lb/>into nature, may be very properly <w part="I"
            >divi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ded</w> into two claſſes. To the firſt I refer <lb/>that
          method, according to which, a <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſon</w>, either
          naturally deaf, or become ſo <pb xml:id="page_19" n="13"/><lb/>by ſome accident, may, by
          means of the <lb/>other ſenſes, without the intervention of <lb/>the organs of hearing, or
          any part of them, <lb/>be enabled to have thoſe perceptions, <lb/>which others obtain by
          the ſenſe of <w part="I">hear-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>. The ſecond claſs, on the
          contrary, <lb/>compriſes thoſe methods, in which the <lb/>auditory nerve itſelf is put in
          motion, and <lb/>thus the very ſenſation produced in the <lb/>ſoul, which we uſually call
          hearing. This <lb/>method again is twofold: One, in which <lb/>the vibratory motion of
          ſound is <w part="I">propaga-</w><lb/><w part="F">ted</w> to the auditory nerve, by means
          of <lb/>the ordinary, but, in other reſpects, faulty <lb/>parts of the organ of hearing;
          by the <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">tervention</w> of ſome other bodies, and by
          <lb/>a variety of ingenious devices. The other <lb/>method, on the contrary, conveys ſound
          <lb/>in like manner to the auditory nerve, and <lb/>thus produces the ſenſation of
          hearing, not <lb/>only by means of the ordinary channels <lb/>and organs, but alſo by
          means of the <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">joining</w> firm parts of the head. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Several phyſicians and other learned <lb/>perſons have been at great
          pains on the <lb/>diſcovery and improvement of the firſt <lb/>method, in order, by the
          other ſenſes, <pb xml:id="page_20" n="14"/><lb/>particularly the ſight, without the <w
            part="I">inter-</w><lb/><w part="F">vention</w> of the auditory organs, to produce
          <lb/>in the ſoul the perceptions peculiar to the <lb/>ear. But moſt of theſe attempts have
            <w part="I">on-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> occaſionally and incidentally proved of
          <lb/>any benefit to the hearing: As moſt of <lb/>them have, in all their attempts, made it
          <lb/>their principal view, to enable the deaf <lb/>perſon to ſpeak; though, indeed, the <w
            part="I">fre-</w><lb/><w part="F">quent</w> and attentive obſervation of the <w part="I"
            >mo-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w> of the mouth and other parts, which <lb/>concur to
          form articulate ſounds, may <lb/>give ſuch a degree of readineſs to thoſe <lb/>wretched
          perſons, as to enable them to <lb/>underſtand and diſtinguiſh, with <w part="I"
            >extraor-</w><lb/><w part="F">dinary</w> quickneſs, all the motions of a <lb/>ſpeaker,
          and thus alſo clearly to <w part="I">compre-</w><lb/><w part="F">hend</w> all that is
          ſpoken. Nature herſelf <lb/>has formed moſt perſons uncommonly <w part="I">do-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">cile</w> in this reſpect, though otherwiſe not <lb/>endued with the brighteſt
          parts. <w part="I">Expe-</w><lb/><w part="F">rience</w> very day almoſt ſhews, that deaf
          <lb/>perſons may obſerve by the mouth, that <lb/>which others ſpeak; and their uncommon
          <lb/>and great attention is the reaſon, that <lb/>they have the misfortune to be generally
          <lb/>taken by the common people for very <lb/>arch and roguiſh. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_21" n="15"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But this very natural device, namely by <lb/>means of the niceſt
          obſervation of the <w part="I">mo-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w> of the mouth in the act
          of ſpeaking, <lb/>employed in order to hear, and by <w part="I">imitat-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ing</w> the very ſame motions alſo to ſpeak, may <lb/>be reduced to ſeveral
          rules, limited and <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">termined</w> by the genius of every
          language <lb/>ſpoken, and thereby the learning them <lb/>made much eaſier. This is that
          device, <lb/>in which, for a century and a half back, <lb/>many learned men have employed
          their <lb/>thoughts; among whom <hi rend="italic">Peter Pontius, <lb/>Paul Bonnetus,</hi>
          Dr. <hi rend="italic">Wallis, Holder, <w part="I">Sib-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſcota</w>,
            Franciſcus Mercurius Van <w part="I">Hel-</w><lb/><w part="F">mont</w>,</hi> but above
          all others, <hi rend="italic">John Conrad <lb/>Amman,</hi> have moſt of all diſtinguiſhed
          <lb/>themſelves. It would carry me too far, <lb/>and be inconſiſtent with my preſent <w
            part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſign</w>, were I to recite here all the attempts
          <lb/>made by theſe learned men to this <w part="I">pur-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſe</w>, and
          their ſucceſs therein. Suffice <lb/>it therefore to give a ſhort account of the
          <lb/>lateſt attempt in that way, namely, that <lb/>of Dr. <hi rend="italic">Amman;</hi>
          and at the ſame time to <lb/>point out its principal defect; but as to <lb/>the others,
          briefly only to mention their <lb/>writings, or other accounts we have of <pb
            xml:id="page_22" n="16"/><lb/>them. <hi rend="italic">Peter Pontius,</hi> a Spaniſh <w
            part="I">Bene-</w><lb/><w part="F">dictine</w>, who lived towards the cloſe of <lb/>the
          ſixteenth century, made the firſt eſſay <lb/>in this way, and taught deaf perſons both
          <lb/>to write and to ſpeak. His method, <lb/>which he did not himſelf deſcribe, was
          <lb/>afterwards improved by <hi rend="italic">Paul Bonnetus,</hi> a <lb/>maſter-gunner of
          the king of Arragon, <lb/>and explained in a particular writing, <w part="I"
            >en-</w><lb/><w part="F">titled</w>, <hi rend="italic">Reduccion de las letras, y arte
            para <lb/>enſenar hablar los mudos;</hi> i. e. The <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſolution</w> of the letters, with the art of <w part="I">ena-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >bling</w> dumb perſons to ſpeak, Madrid, <lb/>1620, in 4to. Dr. John Wallis, who <w
            part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> both the former applied himſelf to <lb/>improve
          this art, gave a deſcription <w part="I">there-</w><lb/><w part="F">of</w>, both in his
            <hi rend="italic">Tractatus <w part="I">grammatico-phy-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſicus</w> de
            loquela,</hi> and in his letter to the <lb/>honourable Mr. Boyle, <hi rend="italic">de
            ſurdis mutiſq; <lb/>informandis.</hi> The former tract is alſo <w part="I"
            >pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">fixed</w> to his <hi rend="italic">Grammatica linguae <w
              part="I">Angli-</w><lb/><w part="F">canae</w>,</hi> publiſhed in 1653, and was <w
            part="I">after-</w><lb/><w part="F">wards</w> often publiſhed with Dr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Amman</hi>'s <lb/>writing. But the latter we have in the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >philoſophical tranſactions,</hi> No. 41; as alſo <lb/>in the <hi rend="italic"
            >Ephemerides acad. nat. curioſor, Dec.</hi>
          <lb/>1. <hi rend="italic">Ann.</hi> 1, in <hi rend="italic">append.</hi> p. 11. &amp; <hi
            rend="italic">ſeqq.</hi>
          <pb xml:id="page_23" n="17"/><lb/>About the ſame time Dr. <hi rend="italic">Holder,</hi>
          ſubdean <lb/>of the king's chapel, publiſhed in 1669, <lb/>in 8vo, a book, called <hi
            rend="italic">Elements of ſpeech,</hi>
          <lb/>&amp;c. together with the art of teaching deaf <lb/>and dumb perſons to ſpeak. In the
          year <lb/>immediately following, namely 1670, <lb/>George Sibſeſta publiſhed, alſo at
          London, <lb/>the following book, namely, <hi rend="italic">Deaf and <lb/>dumb man's
            diſcourſe, or concerning thoſe <lb/>who are born deaf and dumb;</hi> to which he
          <lb/>ſubjoined a treatiſe, <hi rend="italic">De ratione loquelae <w part="I"
              >cre-</w><lb/><w part="F">aturarum</w> animatarum.</hi> Laſtly, the <w part="I"
            >youn-</w><lb/><w part="F">ger</w>
          <hi rend="italic">Van Helmont</hi> attempted to explain <lb/>more diſtinctly, the natural
          formation of <lb/>the letters of the alphabet, for the <w part="I">bene-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">fit</w> of the deaf and dumb; but the has <lb/>confined himſelf to the Hebrew
          language, <lb/>and given his rules in his <hi rend="italic">Alphabetum <w part="I"
              >na-</w><lb/><w part="F">turale</w> Hebraicum,</hi> which has been ſeveral <lb/>times
          reprinted: I have ſeen an abſtract <lb/>of it under the following title, <hi rend="italic"
            >Franciſci <lb/>Mercurii ab Helmont alphabeti verè naturalis <lb/>breviſſima delineatio,
            quæ ſimul methodum <lb/>ſuppeditat, juxta quam, qui ſurdi nati ſunt, <lb/>ſix informari
            poſſunt, ut non alios ſolum <w part="I">lo-</w><lb/><w part="F">quentes</w> intelligant,
            ſed et ipſi ad ſermonis <pb xml:id="page_24" n="16"/>
            <pb xml:id="page_25" n="17"/>
            <pb xml:id="page_26" n="18"/>uſum perveniant, Ann.</hi> 1667, in 12mo, <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">cum fig.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But above all others, <hi rend="italic">John Conrad <lb/>Amman,</hi> a
          phyſician of Amſterdam, <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">tinguiſhed</w> himſelf more,
          towards the end <lb/>of the laſt century, by his ingenious <lb/>method of teaching the
          deaf and dumb to <lb/>ſpeak: And after having happily ſucceeded <lb/>in his method, not
          only on a deaf and <lb/>dumb girl at Harlem, but alſo on his <lb/>own daughter, and on
          ſeveral others, he <lb/>publiſhed, in 1692, at Amſterdam, his <lb/>Tract of <hi
            rend="italic">Surdus loquens,</hi> in 8vo, wherein <lb/>he laid open the whole of his
          method. <lb/>Which being afterwards publiſhed in <lb/>Engliſh by Daniel Foot, and highly
            <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">proved</w> by the learned, he gave a new <lb/>and
          more enlarged edition of it at <w part="I">Amſter-</w><lb/><w part="F">dam</w> in 1700, in
          8vo, under this title, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Diſſertatio de loquela, qua non ſolum vox
            <lb/>humana et loquendi artificium, ex originibus <lb/>ſuis eruuntur, ſed et traduntur
            media, quibus <lb/>ii, qui ab incunabulis, ſurdi et muti fuerunt, <lb/>loquelam
            adipiſci, quiq; difficulter loquuntur, <lb/>vitia ſua emendare poſſint.</hi> And
          afterwards <lb/>there came out ſeveral editions thereof, a <lb/>proof of the good
          reception it met with <pb xml:id="page_27" n="19"/><lb/>from the public. On this
          foundation <lb/><hi rend="italic">William Kerger</hi> eſtabliſhed his method <lb/>in his
          epiſtle <hi rend="italic">De ſurdo-mutorum cura,</hi>
          <lb/>publiſhed in the appendix to the <hi rend="italic">Ephe-<lb/>merid. Acad. nat.
            curioſor. Cent.</hi> I. &amp; II. <lb/><hi rend="italic">p.</hi> 233. <hi rend="italic"
            >ſeqq.</hi> accommodating his <w part="I">inſtruc-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w> to the
          German language, together <lb/>with a ſuccinct account of his predeceſſors <lb/>in the
          ſame method of treatment. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The whole of this method reſts on that <lb/>well known phyſiological
          principle, <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">conteſtably</w> confirmed by daily
          experience, <lb/>namely, that we communicate our thoughts <lb/>to each other by means of
          articulate ſounds, <lb/>formed by the organs of ſpeech, which <lb/>we call language: And,
          by a daily <w part="I">prac-</w><lb/><w part="F">tice</w>, we inſenſibly learn to form
          with <lb/>every conception, a certain articulate <lb/>found. The ſimple articulate ſounds
          are <lb/>generally four and twenty, and in ſeveral <lb/>languages fewer, called letters of
          the <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">phabet</w>; which, when combined according <lb/>to
          certain rules, and pronounced at once <lb/>like a ſingle articulate ſound, are called
          <lb/>ſyllables, and a farther combination forms <lb/>that which we call words. But all
          theſe <lb/>articulate ſounds, in order to their <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >duction</w>, require, at the ſame time, a <w part="I">cer-</w><pb xml:id="page_28"
            n="20"/><lb/><w part="F">tain</w> viſible alteration and motion in the <lb/>organs of
          ſpeech, namely, the lips, teeth, <lb/>tongue, cheeks, larynx, &amp;c. For <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtance</w>, all ſounds, articulated by a bare <lb/>aperture of
          the mouth in different degrees, <lb/>are called vowels: And all others, <w part="I"
            >form-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> by means of the other parts, are <lb/>mutes or
          conſonants. And, indeed, the <lb/>accurate attention to, and careful <w part="I"
            >imita-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of, all the particular motions <w part="I"
            >requi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſite</w> to the articulation of ſounds, <w part="I"
            >conſti-</w><lb/><w part="F">tute</w> the whole of <hi rend="italic">Amman</hi>'s
          method. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As in this, or in any other method of <lb/>the ſame kind, the organs
          of hearing <lb/>contribute nothing to the effect, it may <lb/>indeed, be employed in all
          the defects <lb/>and imperfections of the auditory organs, <lb/>by which either deafneſs
          or a difficulty <lb/>of hearing is produced. This method, <lb/>however, is ſubject to
          ſeveral <w part="I">conſidera-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w> imperfections, which render it
          greatly <lb/>inferior to ſome of the following methods, <lb/>by which the auditory nerve
          itſelf is at the <lb/>ſame time made to be affected. In the firſt <lb/>place, let us
          ſuppoſe a caſe, and which <lb/>actually happens, as appears from the <lb/>hiſtory of
          diſeaſes, namely, that ſuch a <lb/>perſom is born deaf, dumb, and blind. <pb
            xml:id="page_29" n="21"/><lb/>No one, certainly, though more dexterous <lb/>than <hi
            rend="italic">Amman</hi> himſelf, could, by that <w part="I">me-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >thod</w>, impart the conceptions, which, in <lb/>other reſpects, ariſe from the ſenſe
          of <lb/>hearing. But then it may be alledged, <lb/>that if he cannot ſee, he may feel, at
          leaſt. <lb/>I grant, that he may learn to ſpeak in that <lb/>manner: But then, for one in
          this <w part="I">condi-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, to lay his hands on the mouth and
          <lb/>throat of the ſpeaker, would appeal <w part="I">clum-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſy</w> and
          aukward: Not to mention, that <lb/>in forming ſounds, ſeveral motions are <lb/>performed
          with the tongue, the teeth, the <lb/>cheeks, the gums, &amp;c. moſtly obſervable <lb/>by
          the eye, but not properly to be felt, <lb/>without interrupting the ſpeaker at the
          <lb/>ſame time. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The ſecond imperfection in this method, <lb/>conſiſts principally in
          confining the <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceptions</w> imparted, barely to
          language. <lb/>All thoſe raviſhing ſenſations, which, in <lb/>other reſpects, the ſenſe of
          hearing is <w part="I">ſuſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceptible</w> of, are here quite loſt; nor
          can <lb/>the thrilling motions of the organs of <lb/>ſpeech, inſtantaneouſly loſt in each
          other, <lb/>when raiſed with that rapidity in the <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >preſſions</w> of the deeper Paſſions, as to <pb xml:id="page_30" n="22"/><lb/>ſtrike
          and ſurprize the hearers, be once <lb/>diſtinguiſhed by, much leſs yield, that
          <lb/>melting ſenſation to a perſon ſo wretched. <lb/>Much leſs could a skilful muſician
          throw <lb/>him into thoſe ſoft and calm raptures, <lb/>when under his hands, the ſtrings,
          in <w part="I">har-</w><lb/><w part="F">mony</w> truly divine, thrill the hearer with
          <lb/>unſpeakable delight. Thirdly and laſtly, <lb/>take a perſon of little or no natural
          abilities, <lb/>and attempt to teach him in this manner; <lb/>I am fully perſuaded, that
          all the pains <lb/>taken with him, would be quite loſt: Not <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Amman</hi> himſelf, with all his art and <lb/>practical skill, could hope to ſucceed in
          a <lb/>caſe of ſuch indocility. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I now proceed to the ſecond order of <lb/>the attempts made to reſtore
          hearing to <lb/>the deaf, by putting the auditory nerve <lb/>itſelf in motion, thereby
          producing the <lb/>ſenſation of hearing. I have already <lb/>ſhewn above, that this order
          may be <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">perly</w> divided into two ſorts. To the firſt
          <lb/>belong the methods of propagating ſound <lb/>in a due degree of motion, by the
          ordinary <lb/>though faulty organs of hearing, quite to <lb/>the auditory nerve. To this
          we may juſtly <lb/>refer all thoſe contrivances, which, either <pb xml:id="page_31" n="23"
          /><lb/>by peculiar inſtruments, or other means <lb/>or devices, raiſe or heighten the <w
            part="I">moti-</w><lb/><w part="F">ons</w> and repercuſions of the air in the <w
            part="I">chan-</w><lb/><w part="F">nels</w> and cavities of the ear; when thoſe
          <lb/>parts are ſo faulty as not to be put into the <lb/>proper vibratory motions by the
          ordinary <lb/>action of ſound. And in this caſe it is <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ways</w> requiſite, that the auditory channel <lb/>be open. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>When the auditory channel is thus open, <lb/>or the other parts of the
          inner ear <w part="I">connec-</w><lb/><w part="F">ted</w> therewith are ſuſceptible of
          ſome, <lb/>though a very faint degree of, vibratory <lb/>motion, and only require a
          greater <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of the inſinuating air than is
          neceſſary <lb/>in a natural ſtate, there hence ariſes a <w part="I">dif-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ficulty</w> of hearing, and not a perfect <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >gree</w> of deafneſs. Now as among the <w part="I">ſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">veral</w>
          methods of propagating ſound, by <lb/>means of the parts mentioned, to the <w part="I"
            >au-</w><lb/><w part="F">ditory</w> nerve, in natural order, they are <lb/>only of
          ſervice in difficulty of hearing, <lb/>but not in the caſe of perfect deafneſs; I
          <lb/>ſhall therefore mention only, in brief, <lb/>ſome of the means of this ſpecies of
          <lb/>method. And one of the beſt known, <lb/>and which nature herſelf, for the moſt <pb
            xml:id="page_32" n="24"/><lb/>part, points out, is, to apply the hand <lb/>bent and
          hollow to the ear, and <w part="I">there-</w><lb/><w part="F">by</w> not only to convey a
          greater <w part="I">quan-</w><lb/><w part="F">tity</w> of vibrating air to the auditory <w
            part="I">chan-</w><lb/><w part="F">nel</w>, but likewiſe to raiſe or heighten <lb/>its
          repercuſſions. With this view <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſo</w>, ſuch perſons
          generally ſet the mouth <lb/>wide open, when they want to hear more <lb/>accurately; that
          the air, reflected from <lb/>the palate, may be forced through the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >tuba Euſtachii</hi> into the cavity of the drum, <lb/>and thereby render more intenſe
          the <w part="I">vi-</w><lb/><w part="F">bration</w> of the air. But then we are to
          <lb/>ſuppoſe this laſt mentioned channel to <lb/>have no obſtruction. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And this very heightening the action of <lb/>ſound, is procured by
          means of peculiar <lb/>inſtruments. Of this ſort are acouſtic <lb/>trumpets or horns,
          inſtruments commonly <lb/>well known, and which require no <w part="I">parti-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">cular</w> notice to be taken of them here. <lb/>Somewhat leſs known is the
          ingenious <lb/>acouſtic drum of Father <hi rend="italic">Sebaſtian Truchel,</hi>
          <lb/>a Carmelite monk, which, in 1718, he <lb/>preſented to the royal academy of ſciences
          <lb/>at Paris, and which had their approbation. <lb/>This drum conſiſts of gold-beater's
          ſkin, <pb xml:id="page_33" n="25"/><lb/>which is originally ox gut. This ſkin is
          <lb/>ſtretched either on a round or an oval <lb/>hoop, as is commonly done in drums; ſo
          <lb/>that when faſtened to the ear, it forms, <lb/>with the natural membrane of the drum
          of <lb/>the ear, a perfect drum; the artificial ſkin <lb/>exhibiting the part which is
          ſtruck upon; <lb/>the ear itſelf again and the auditory <w part="I">chan-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">nel</w>, the kettle or hollow cavity of the <lb/>drum; and the natural membrane
          of the <lb/>drum of the ear, the undermoſt skin of <lb/>the drum. The artificial skin had,
            <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">fides</w>, over it, a raiſed cover, in ſhape of
          <lb/>a box, whoſe aperture was turned to the <lb/>mouth of the ſpeaker. A perſon hard of
          <lb/>hearing in both ears, may, by means of <lb/>a ſemicircle of braſs or ſilver, which
          goes <lb/>round the hinder part of the head, under <lb/>the hair or peruke, faſten two
          ſuch drums <lb/>to his ears. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>We are now at length come to the <lb/>other method of the ſecond claſs
          or order, <lb/>compriſing thoſe means which convey <lb/>found, and thereby reſtore actual
          hearing <lb/>by extraordinary ways, and not by means <lb/>of the natural auditory channel,
          to the <lb/>auditory nerve. But before I explain the <pb xml:id="page_34" n="26"
          /><lb/>peculiar methods under this head, I muſt <lb/>here borrow three prepoſitions as <w
            part="I">princi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ples</w>, from natural philoſophy and <w part="I"
            >ana-</w><lb/><w part="F">tomy</w>, as they properly afford a natural <lb/>foundation
          and reaſon for all the methods <lb/>that are now to follow, and to all the <lb/>remarks
          that may occaſionally offer, as <lb/>we proceed. In the firſt place, ſound is
          <lb/>propagated by bodies elaſtic, and <w part="I">ſuſcepti-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w>
          of a vibratory motion. Secondly, <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">pagation</w> of
          ſound is interrupted by ſofter <lb/>interpoſing parts, unſuſceptible of any, or <lb/>of
          but faint vibrations. Thirdly, the bones <lb/>of the skull, in which the auditory nerves
          <lb/>are lodged, form, with the upper <w part="I">maxil-</w><lb/><w part="F">lary</w>
          bone, one continued hard and elaſtic <lb/>body, uninterrupted in their connection <lb/>by
          any ſofter parts, and hence extremely <lb/>well adapted for the propagation of <lb/>found. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As I have adduced theſe prepoſitions <lb/>principally with the view
          that the <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tentive</w> reader may have them conſtantly
          <lb/>in his eye, either in paſſing a judgment <lb/>on, or in explaining, the ſeveral
          methods, <lb/>which, indeed, produce the ſenſe of <w part="I">hear-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ing</w> by means of the auditory nerve, but <pb xml:id="page_35" n="27"/><lb/>not by
          the natural auditory channel, to <lb/>which claſs alſo my own method, which <lb/>I am now
          about to explain, does belong; <lb/>ſo I ſhall at preſent, firſt, hiſtorically relate
          <lb/>the ſeveral imperfect attempts of this kind: <lb/>And then, ſecondly, deſcribe my own
          <lb/>method, in all its circumſtances, and in <lb/>the whole of the manner of procedure.
          <lb/>Thirdly and laſtly, explain it in its <w part="I">phy-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſical</w>
          and phyſiological principles, and at <lb/>the ſame time determine the particular
          <lb/>caſe, in which it is abſolutely <w part="I">inapplica-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>We have extant experiments of a long <lb/>ſtanding, the firſt careful
          attention to <lb/>which is generally, at leaſt by Father <hi rend="italic"
            >Kir-<lb/>cher,</hi> in his <hi rend="italic">Muſurgia univerſalis,</hi> P. II. <lb/>p.
          559. aſcribed to the celebrated <w part="I">Neapo-</w><lb/><w part="F">litan</w>
          <hi rend="italic">John Baptiſta Porta;</hi> namely, that <lb/>we can, for inſtance, hear
          the ſound of a <lb/>ringing fork, when ſtriking its fore-part, <lb/>or prongs, on another
          hard body, we hold <lb/>its handle to the teeth. The very ſame <lb/>thing is obſervable in
          a pair of tongs, a <lb/>ſteel wire, a ſword-blade, &amp;c. when ſtruck <lb/>in the ſame
          manner, and applied to the <lb/>teeth. Moreover, that we diſtinctly hear <pb
            xml:id="page_36" n="28"/><lb/>all the tones or notes of a muſical <w part="I"
            >inſtru-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w>, when played upon, on taking it in <lb/>the teeth,
          or touching it with a wire, <lb/>ſword-blade, &amp;c. held in the ſame <w part="I"
            >man-</w><lb/><w part="F">ner</w>. Travellers, who happen to ſtray in <lb/>the night,
          upon laying the head, <w part="I">eſpeci-</w><lb/><w part="F">ally</w> the hinder part,
          cloſe to the earth, <lb/>may hear diſtinctly, at the diſtance of a <lb/>German mile or
          more, people going, <w part="I">ri-</w><lb/><w part="F">ding</w>, or travelling. In this
          manner, ſome <lb/>of the inhabitants of <hi rend="italic">Halle</hi> could, on the
          <lb/>neighbouring eminences, hear all the <w part="I">can-</w><lb/><w part="F">non</w>
          fired in the glorious battle of <hi rend="italic">Roſbach,</hi>
          <lb/>in as diſtinct and plain a manner, as if at <lb/>no great diſtance from the action,
          though <lb/>at that time full four German miles off. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Conrad Victor
            Scheider,</hi> ſo celebrated for <lb/>his deſcription of the mucoſe glands of the
          <lb/>noſe, in his book, <hi rend="italic">De oſſibus temporum,</hi>
          <lb/>publiſhed at Wittemburg in 1653, in 8vo, <lb/>p. 43, relates the ſame thing of ſome
            <w part="I">pea-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſants</w>, who ſticking their ſtaves in the
          <lb/>earth, held one end in their teeth; to <lb/>wave other inſtances at preſent. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>All theſe experiments ſucceed as well, if <lb/>not better, with deaf
          perſons, than with <lb/>thoſe that have their hearing: As thoſe <pb xml:id="page_37"
            n="29"/><lb/>laſt, upon ſtopping their ears, feel a <w part="I">ting-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ling</w> and whizzing from the included air, <lb/>which the former are without.
          The proof <lb/>of this I refer to the experience of all <lb/>deaf perſons who will make
          the trial. For, <lb/>caſes, where deafneſs cannot be relieved <lb/>by this method, and
          which I ſhall <w part="I">men-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> towards the concluſion, are
          very rare: <lb/>Nay, the practice of ſetting the mouth <lb/>wide open, in difficulty of
          hearing, in <w part="I">or-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w> more diſtinctly to hear, is in
          ſome <lb/>meaſure reducible hither: Though, in <lb/>explaining this obſervation, I muſt
          differ <lb/>from very great phyſicians, who would <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >count</w> for this manner of hearing, ſolely <lb/>from the air inſinuated into the <hi
            rend="italic">tuba <w part="I">Eu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtachii</w>;</hi> which I ſhall
          more fully treat <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">low</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>That the methods of hearing but juſt <lb/>mentioned, without the uſe
          of the <w part="I">ordi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nary</w> organs of hearing, has been <w
            part="I">confirm-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> by the repeated obſervations of <w part="I"
            >phyſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cians</w> and inquirers into nature, I ſhall <lb/>briefly
          illuſtrate from ſome credible <w part="I">hiſto-</w><lb/><w part="F">ries</w>, which may,
          at the ſame time clear <lb/>up, and ſhew the different application of <lb/>the method I am
          now upon. <hi rend="italic">Boerhaave,</hi>
          <pb xml:id="page_38" n="30"/><lb/>a man, whoſe teſtimony is every where
          <lb/>unexceptionable, tells us in his <hi rend="italic">Praelecti-<lb/>ones academicae in
            proprias inſtitutiones <w part="I">me-</w><lb/><w part="F">dicas</w>,</hi> T. IV. p.
          414. according to <w part="I">Hal-</w><lb/><w part="F">ler's</w> edition, of a deaf
          Muſician, who, <lb/>laying hold with his teeth in the upper <lb/>parts of his lute, at the
          tuning pegs, <lb/>played in a manner perfectly juſt, and <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">cording</w> to all the rules of art, without <lb/>the leaſt miſtake or blunder.
          Like <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtances</w> we have in <hi rend="italic"
            >Ingraſſias,</hi> in his <hi rend="italic">Com-<lb/>mentarii in Galeni librum de
            oſſibus, Schelha-<lb/>mer</hi> in his book <hi rend="italic">De auditu,</hi> and in <hi
            rend="italic">Du <lb/>Verney,</hi> in his treatiſe on hearing. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Du Verney,</hi> juſt now mentioned, as alſo <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">De Lanis,</hi> in his <hi rend="italic">Magiſt. natur. &amp; artis,</hi>
          <lb/>p. 928, and others, have farther obſerved, <lb/>that deaf perſons have been enabled
          to hear <lb/>extremely well, if, in ſpeaking, one ſhould <lb/>direct the ſound over and
          againſt the head. <lb/>A curious inſtance of this we find in the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Ephemerides academ. nat. curioſor. decur.</hi>
          <lb/>i. <hi rend="italic">ann.</hi> i. <hi rend="italic">obſerv.</hi> xxxv. which is the
          <lb/>more remarkable, as the principal <w part="I">cir-</w><lb/><w part="F">cumſtance</w>
          therein lies buried in the <w part="I">rub-</w><lb/><w part="F">biſh</w> of trifling quack
          medicines. <hi rend="italic">Ema-<lb/>nuel Ramireſius de Cariour,</hi> a Spaniard, is <pb
            xml:id="page_39" n="31"/><lb/>the inventor of this method, of whom <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Petrus a Caſtro,</hi> phyſician to one of the <lb/>Dukes of Mantua,
          learned it, and to <lb/>whom we owe the account. The whole <lb/>of it conſiſted in the
          following particulars. <lb/>In the firſt place, the patient, according as <lb/>his
          conſtitution might require, was to uſe <lb/>a proper laxative, and then once or twice
          <lb/>a ſomewhat ſtronger purgative; after <lb/>which the head was to be ſhaved at the
          <lb/>coronal ſuture, for a hand's-breadth, and <lb/>often rubbed, eſpecially morning and
            <w part="I">eve-</w><lb/><w part="F">ning</w>, with the following ſalve: Take three
          <lb/>ounces of the beſt brandy, two drams of <lb/>purified ſaltpetre, one ounce of oil of
          bitter <lb/>almonds, ſet the whole to boil gently, till <lb/>all the brandy is evaporated,
          then pour to <lb/>it an ounce of orange water, <hi rend="italic">(aqua naphæ)</hi>
          <lb/>ſtir it with a ſpatula, till it turns of the <lb/>conſiſtence of a thin ſalve.
          Laſtly, early <lb/>every morning the patient muſt clean,<lb/> perfectly well, his head and
          eyes, and <lb/>clear his ears and noſe, rinſe his mouth, <lb/>and chew ſome maſtich, or
          other fragrant <lb/>ſubſtance, and then do his hair back with <lb/>an ivory comb; this
          done, the ſpeaker is <lb/>to direct his voice juſt over the ſhaven <pb xml:id="page_40"
            n="32"/><lb/>part, and the deaf perſon comes to hear <lb/>perfectly and diſtinctly every
          word that <lb/>is ſpoken: And thus the deaf learn, not <lb/>only to hear, but to ſpeak.
          The reaſon <lb/>of all this, will appear below. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But as the methed of <hi rend="italic">Ramireſius</hi> is <w part="I"
            >at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tended</w> with many inconveniences, and as <lb/>it muſt be
          very troubleſome, not only to <lb/>the patient, on account of ſuch antecedent
          <lb/>preparation, but to the ſpeaker alſo. The <lb/>following methods of producing this
          ſenſe, <lb/>by means of ſome elaſtic body held to the <lb/>teeth, claim, by much, the
          preference: <lb/>Of this the experiments adduced above <lb/>are ſufficient proofs. But the
          following <lb/>account, taken from the <hi rend="italic">Breſlaw collection,
            <lb/>Eſſay</hi> 21. p. 330. is ſtill a fuller proof. <lb/>A man at <hi rend="italic"
            >Copenhagen</hi> had, by diſtemper, <lb/>loſt his hearing, to ſuch a degree, as not to
          <lb/>have the leaſt ſenſe of firing of cannon, <lb/>the beating ever ſo many drums, nor of
          any <lb/>other the moſt violent motions: At laſt, <lb/>he accidentally fell on a method,
          by which <lb/>he could perfectly well underſtand any <lb/>ſpeaker, and write down all that
          he ſaid; <lb/>and this he did by means of a ſtick of <lb/>wood, of a moderate length, one
          end of <pb xml:id="page_41" n="33"/><lb/>which he held to, or took in his teeth, <w
            part="I">reſt-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> the other end againſt the place where
          <lb/>the ſpeaker ſtood. And thus at church <lb/>he could underſtand the preacher, and
          <lb/>write down the ſermon, upon ſeating <lb/>himſelf juſt under the pulpit, with his face
          <lb/>towards it, and one end of the ſtick, while <lb/>the other was between his teeth,
          reſting <lb/>againſt the foot of the pulpit. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>About ten years ſince, <hi rend="italic">John Paul <w part="I"
              >Bau-</w><lb/><w part="F">mer</w>,</hi> a young phyſician of <hi rend="italic"
            >Franconia,</hi>
          <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">dertook</w> to improve this method: And in <lb/>a
          writing, which we ſhall preſently <w part="I">men-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, he
          pretended, he himſelf had deviſed <lb/>the whole of the method, explaining it <lb/>from
          the nature of the ſenſe of hearing, <lb/>and from the different manner of <w part="I"
            >propa-</w><lb/><w part="F">gating</w> ſounds; but now and then <w part="I"
            >ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F">thing</w> eſcapes him, which bewrays, that <lb/>he was not
          altogether unacquainted with <lb/>that which others had attempted before <lb/>him in that
          way. He publiſhed his <w part="I">me-</w><lb/><w part="F">thod</w> in an inaugural
          diſputation at Erfurt <lb/>in 1749, under the following title, <hi rend="italic"
            >Pro-<lb/>dromus methodi ſurdos a nativitate faclendi <lb/>audientes &amp;
            loquentes.</hi> The whole conſiſts <lb/>in taking a ſtick, made of an elaſtic body, <pb
            xml:id="page_42" n="34"/><lb/>or glaſs, ſteel, copper, bell-metal, ſilver, <lb/>&amp;c.
          flat and broad at both ends, to <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">vent</w> its touching
          the lips; and being thus <lb/>made fit for the due propagation of ſound, <lb/>one end of
          this ſtick the deaf perſon takes <lb/>between his teeth, and the ſpeaker the <lb/>other,
          with this precaution, however, <lb/>that neither of them ſhall touch the ſtick <lb/>with
          the tongue or lips: In this manner, <lb/>the deaf perſon hears every word that is
          <lb/>uttered. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In order the more fully to eſtabliſh the <lb/>utility of this method,
          the author gives <lb/>an inſtance in his ſecond remark, § 6. of <lb/>a young woman of
          twenty-four, who <lb/>learned to hear in this manner, though <lb/>with an old ruſty piece
          of a ſword-blade, <lb/>about two feet long: For, upon <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >nouncing</w> only a few words, ſhe, with a <lb/>ſmile, and pointing to her head, <w
            part="I">inti-</w><lb/><w part="F">mated</w>, that ſhe perceived every word that
          <lb/>was ſaid, and directly attempted to <w part="I">imi-</w><lb/><w part="F">tate</w>
          them. But, as there are many defects <lb/>in this method, as namely, that the ſtick
          <lb/>muſt not be touched either with the lips <lb/>or the tongue, in which caſe, all the
            <w part="I">lin-</w><lb/><w part="F">gual</w> and labial letters, as b, d, f, l, m, <pb
            xml:id="page_43" n="35"/><lb/>&amp;c. muſt be uttered indiſtinctly; to obviate
          <lb/>which, the author, indeed, has, § 15 and <lb/>17. of his diſputation, propoſed
          another <lb/>method, by uſing an acouſtic tube, and a <lb/>ſpeaking trumpet. If the firſt,
          the deaf <lb/>perſon muſt take it in his teeth, and the <lb/>ſpeaker muſt pronounce at the
          wide end <lb/>of the tube; which purpoſe a common <lb/>funnel will anſwer as well: But if
          a <lb/>ſpeaking trumpet, the deaf perſon muſt <lb/>open his mouth very wide, while the
          <lb/>ſpeaker, who pronounces through it, holds <lb/>its upper broad part cloſe to the
          teeth of <lb/>the deaf perſon, yet without touching <lb/>them. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="chapter">
        <head rend="italic align-center"><lb/><hi rend="roman">CHAP. III.</hi>
          <lb/>An account of the beſt and eaſieſt method to <lb/>make deaf perſons hear. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>O conclude, all the methods <w part="I"
            >hither-</w><lb/><w part="F">to</w> metioned under this ſecond claſs, <lb/>are rendered
          far more commodious, more <lb/>perfect, and of far more general utility, <lb/>by
          conſidering a peculiar inſtance of an <lb/>ingenious deaf perſon, who gave the <w part="I"
            >great-</w><pb xml:id="page_44" n="36"/><lb/><w part="F">eſt</w> attention to every
          incident that offered <lb/>to his obſervation: And this method I <lb/>ſhall now propoſe at
          full length, as the <lb/>eaſieſt and beſt to enable deaf perſons to <lb/>hear. I am not,
          indeed, the firſt who <lb/>publiſhed the account, and an <w part="I">explana-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tion</w> of it; as an unknown author, under <lb/>the initial letters C, F, W.
          has already <lb/>deſcribed it in the Harlem Journal for the <lb/>year 1754, <hi
            rend="italic">p</hi> 393. <hi rend="italic">ſeqq.</hi> but as both his <lb/>hiſtorical
          part is erroneous and imperfect, <lb/>and the explanation of its circumſtances, <lb/>and
          the obſervations made thereon, are <lb/>groundleſs and falſe; I had the whole <lb/>matter
          more fully and more juſtly <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſcribed</w>, a year and an
          half ſince, in an <lb/>academical diſputation, defended under <lb/>my preſidentſhip, with
          the following title, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Diſſertatio ſiſtens novæ methodi, ſurdos <w
              part="I">red-</w><lb/><w part="F">dendi</w> audientes, phyſicas &amp; medicas
            rationes.</hi>
          <lb/>But as ſuch diſſertations ſeldom come into <lb/>the hands of any, but of phyſicians,
          I <lb/>ſhall here, firſt, relate the hiſtory of this <lb/>deaf perſon, in all its
          circumſtances, <w part="I">toge-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> with the manner in which he
            <w part="I">reco-</w><lb/><w part="F">vered</w> his hearing. Then, ſecondly, give <lb/>a
          rational explanation, grounded on <w part="I">phy-</w><pb xml:id="page_45" n="37"/><lb/><w
            part="F">ſical</w> and medical principles, of all the <lb/>incidental circumſtances
          obſervable <w part="I">there-</w><lb/><w part="F">in</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>A reputable merchant of <hi rend="italic">Weſel,</hi> in the
          <lb/>Duchy of <hi rend="italic">Cleves,</hi> a venerable, hoary, old <lb/>man of
          ſeventy-eight, had, as early as his <lb/>twentieth year, a great difficulty of hearing,
          <lb/>which, as far as he could recollect, was <lb/>occaſioned, either by a violent fall,
          or by <lb/>a profuſe bleeding at the noſe. The moſt <lb/>promiſing means againſt this
          diſorder <lb/>proved ineffectual, it rather growing upon <lb/>him from year to year, till,
          at laſt, he <lb/>became quite deaf, unable to underſtand a <lb/>ſingle word, without
          bawling loud in his <lb/>ears. Both German and Dutch <w part="I">phyſi-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">cians</w>, who were conſulted on this <w part="I">occa-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſion</w>, could not, with all their art and <lb/>skill, afford any relief: At length,
          after an <lb/>accurate examination of the external organs <lb/>of hearing, the caſe was
          deemed incurable. <lb/>However, he procured a variety of acouſtic <lb/>tubes from
          Amſterdam, in order to afford <lb/>ſome relief to thoſe who wanted to ſpeak <lb/>with him:
          But their uſe was afterwards <lb/>laid aſide, as being attended either with <pb
            xml:id="page_46" n="38"/><lb/>much inconvenience, or as never <w part="I"
            >procu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ring</w> any diſtinct degree of hearing. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Afterwards marrying, and having two <lb/>of his eldeſt children, a ſon
          and a <w part="I">daugh-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w>, taught to play on the ſpinnet, he
          often <lb/>came up to it, and eagerly wiſhed to hear <lb/>the muſic: As the muſic-maſter
          once <lb/>happened to ſay, that it was very poſſible <lb/>for him to hear, if, according
          to an old, <lb/>and well known experiment, he held a <lb/>thin ſtick, or a tobacco-pipe,
          with the <lb/>one end on the bridge of the ſound-board, <lb/>and with the other to the
          upper teeth; <lb/>this he inſtantly tried, and was greatly <lb/>pleaſed, that he could
          both plainly <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtinguiſh</w> each note, and, as he
          thought, <lb/>much ſtronger than formerly, at his beſt <lb/>hearing. But all this was
          ineffectual to <lb/>make him underſtand perſons ſpeaking, <lb/>till an accidental trial
          procured him alſo <lb/>this happineſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the year 1749, he had the good <lb/>fortune to light, by mere
          accident, on a <lb/>peculiar method, by which any perſon, <lb/>at the diſtance of twenty,
          or even thirty <lb/>paces, may, without greatly ſtraining his <lb/>voice, ſpeak to be
          underſtood. This <pb xml:id="page_47" n="39"/><lb/>happened as follows: As one time this
          <lb/>deaf perſon had all his family about him, <lb/>and was pleaſing himſelf with his <w
            part="I">daugh-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter's</w> playing, by means of his <w part="I"
            >tobacco-</w><lb/><w part="F">pipe</w>; his brother, who happened to be <lb/>preſent,
          alledged, that as he could plainly <lb/>diſtinguiſh the ſounds or notes of the <w part="I"
            >ſpin-</w><lb/><w part="F">net</w>, he might alſo, in the ſame manner, <lb/>underſtand
          the articulate ſounds of a <w part="I">ſpea-</w><lb/><w part="F">ker</w>. For this
          purpoſe, his brother took a <lb/>ſpeaking-trumpet, and holding the <w part="I"
            >nar-</w><lb/><w part="F">row</w> part, or mouth-piece, to the upper <lb/>teeth of the
          deaf perſon, he uttered a few <lb/>words at the upper or wider part thereof: <lb/>This
          trial, however, proved unſucceſſful, <lb/>the deaf man not being ſenſible of the leaſt
          <lb/>articulate ſound. But he himſelf directly <lb/>fell upon a device, which proved more
          <lb/>ſucceſſful. The brother was to hold the <lb/>rim of the wide end of the <w part="I"
            >ſpeaking-trum-</w><lb/><w part="F">pet</w> to his upper teeth, and he himſelf to
          <lb/>do the like with the lower end, or <w part="I">mouth-</w><lb/><w part="F">piece</w>:
          Upon which, his brother had <lb/>ſcarce uttered a couple of words, but he <lb/>directly
          repeated them with the greateſt <lb/>joy, and alſo aſſured him, that he <w part="I"
            >under-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtood</w> them more diſtinctly than if he had <pb
            xml:id="page_48" n="40"/><lb/>bawled them in the loudeſt manner in <lb/>his ear. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The deaf man did not ſtop here: In <lb/>order to be convinced, whether
          the <w part="I">ſuc-</w><lb/><w part="F">cess</w> was not owing to the ſtructure of the
          <lb/>ſpeaking-trumpet, or whether the ſame <lb/>thing might not ſucceed with other <w
            part="I">bo-</w><lb/><w part="F">dies</w>; he directly tried, in the ſame <w part="I"
            >man-</w><lb/><w part="F">ner</w>, his tobacco-pipe, and a little <w part="I"
            >wood-</w><lb/><w part="F">en</w> ſtick, and to his great joy found it not <lb/>only
          poſſible, but that the ſpeaker might <lb/>even ſpeak as low as he pleaſed, ſo the
          <lb/>voice were only audible. The curioſity <lb/>of this man and his friends did not reſt
          <lb/>here; they wanted to know, at what <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtance</w> one
          might converſe with him: <lb/>For this purpoſe, they took thin ſticks <lb/>or ſlips of
          wood, of different lengths, and <lb/>one, in particular, ſix feet long, an inch
          <lb/>broad, and of the thickenſs of the back <lb/>of a knife. At Weſel, and in the <w
            part="I">coun-</w><lb/><w part="F">try</w> round about, they call ſuch ſticks
          <lb/>flooring-ſlips or laths, which they uſe in <lb/>filling up the openings of the boards
          of <lb/>the flooring, when ſtarting aſunder: And <lb/>ſuch ſlips are the more commodious,
          as <lb/>being thin, they the leſs hinder the <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >nunciation</w>, <pb xml:id="page_49" n="41"/><lb/>and as in other reſpects, they
          produce the <lb/>ſame effect in propagating ſound: And <lb/>even, by means of a bundle of
          them tied <lb/>together, the loweſt ſound is diſtinctly <lb/>audible, when the by-ſtanders
          can ſcarce <lb/>perceive any. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The farther trials and obſervations, <lb/>which were made in the uſe
          of this <w part="I">me-</w><lb/><w part="F">thod</w>, have been confirmed by the <w
            part="I">follow-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> experiments. In the firſt place, upon
          <lb/>bawling in the loudeſt manner, in the <lb/>mouth of the deaf perſon, through a large
          <lb/>tin funnel, without touching the teeth, or <lb/>even without the funnel, not a ſingle
          word <lb/>was underſtood. Secondly, if the ſlip of <lb/>wood be held too faſt with the
          finger, or <lb/>laid hold on with ſhut lips, the voice <lb/>proves very indiſtinct. But
          thirdly, if held <lb/>with the teeth, the ſenſation is extremely <lb/>weak. Fourthly, if
          the ſlip be held to the <lb/>under teeth, there is not the leaſt ſenſe of <lb/>hearing.
          Whereas, fifthly, the voice is <lb/>perceptible and diſtinct, upon bringing, <lb/>in uſing
          the ſlip, the tongue to the palate <lb/>or to the teeth. Sixthly, the voice is leſs
          <lb/>perceptible on joining the teeth together, <lb/>than on their ſtanding aſunder.
          Seventhly, <lb/>though the mouth be full of water, the <pb xml:id="page_50" n="42"
          /><lb/>hearing is not in the leaſt diminiſhed. <lb/>Eighthly, when a braſs or iron wire is
          held <lb/>to the teeth, the deaf perſon hears nothing <lb/>at all; but held between the
          teeth, a <w part="I">lit-</w><lb/><w part="F">tle</w>. Ninthly, the deaf perſon may hear
          <lb/>very well, on holding, by the lower rim, <lb/>a beer-glaſs, to the upper teeth; or
          if, <lb/>with the mouth ſhut, he preſſes it <w part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F">what</w>
          hard juſt under the noſe, and <w part="I">ano-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> perſon directs
          his voice up the glaſs, <lb/>cloſe to it; all which anſwers not with a <lb/>wine-glaſs.
          Tenthly and laſtly, the <w part="I">ſpea-</w><lb/><w part="F">ker</w> muſt have good ſound
          teeth, <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w part="F">out</w> any looſe ones, at leaſt in the upper
          <lb/>jaw, as then the voice is very indiſtinct. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As the explanation of all the methods <lb/>hitherto treated, and the
          obſervations <w part="I">oc-</w><lb/><w part="F">caſionally</w> offering thereon, are
          founded <lb/>on the three phyſical and medical <w part="I">propo-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſitions</w>, advanced above; all that is <w part="I">neceſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſary</w> here, is to make a cloſer application <lb/>of them to the preſent caſe, and
          from <lb/>the conſequences thence drawn, give a <lb/>ſufficient proof of the
          commodiouſneſs and <lb/>utility of the laſt method propoſed, to <lb/>procure hearing to
          the deaf. And thus, <lb/>in the firſt place, I ſhall briefly handle <pb xml:id="page_51"
            n="43"/><lb/>the propagation of ſound, ſo far as is <w part="I">ne-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ceſſary</w> to my preſent purpoſe. Secondly, <lb/>mention thoſe parts of the body,
          which <lb/>either obſtruct, or promote this <w part="I">propaga-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tion</w>. Thirdly, deduce from their ſeveral <lb/>cauſes the peculiar obſervations,
          made in <lb/>the foregoing paragraph. Fourthly and <lb/>laſtly, determine briefly thoſe
          caſes, in <lb/>which the application of this method does <lb/>not take place. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Inquirers into nature ſhew, that the <lb/>propagation of ſound depends
          principally <lb/>on elaſtic bodies, that is, ſuch, whoſe <lb/>parts reſiſt the action .of
          another body upon <lb/>them, and which, when thereby altered <lb/>in ſituation, reſtore
          themſelves to their <lb/>former ſtate, from a force, not ariſing from <lb/>their gravity,
          but peculiar to them. For, <lb/>ſound is nothing other but the tremulous, <lb/>or
          vibratory motion, ariſing from <w part="I">elaſti-</w><lb/><w part="F">city</w>, of the
          minuteſt air-particles, whereby <lb/>a peculiar ſenſation is produced in the <w part="I"
            >au-</w><lb/><w part="F">ditory</w> organs. Now, as this vibratory <lb/>motion, and the
          ſound produced thereby, <lb/>are ſolely owing to the elaſticity of bodies, <lb/>we may
          thence fairly infer, that all elaſtic bodies <lb/>are ſonorous; for inſtance, glaſs, <pb
            xml:id="page_52" n="44"/><lb/>bell-metal, copper, ſilver, ſteel, &amp;c. But, <lb/>in
          order to one body's acting upon <w part="I">ano-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w>, they muſt
          come either into mediate <lb/>or immediate contact with each other. <lb/>For, action at
          diſtance, <hi rend="italic">actio in diſtans,</hi> is <lb/>both, by phyſical and
          metaphyſical <w part="I">prin-</w><lb/><w part="F">ciples</w>, a non-entity, a mere fancy.
          Now, <lb/>as daily experience ſhews, that ſound <lb/>takes its riſe at a diſtance from the
          ear, <lb/>and thus only mediately, namely, by <w part="I">ano-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ther</w> intervening body, puts in motion <lb/>the auditory organs; it follows hence,
          <lb/>that the body producing this mediate <w part="I">ef-</w><lb/><w part="F">fect</w>,
          muſt be elaſtic, as the propagation <lb/>of ſound is not poſſible by means of any
          <lb/>other body. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The elaſtic body, which commonly <lb/>propagates ſound, is the air;
          but it is <lb/>poſſeſſed of this virtue from no other <lb/>quality, but from that of its
          elaſticity. <lb/>Conſequently, all elaſtic bodies without <lb/>exception anſwer this
          purpoſe, ſo that they <lb/>only affect the organs of hearing, or are <lb/>continuous with
          them. Of this we have <lb/>undoubted proof from well-known <w part="I">expe-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">riments</w>. Beſides the inſtances adduced <lb/>above, it is a thing we may
          daily <w part="I">ob-</w><pb xml:id="page_53" n="45"/><lb/><w part="F">ſerve</w> in
          muſical inſtruments. The tremor <lb/>or vibration, imparted to the ſtring of a
          <lb/>ſpinnet or violin, and the like inſtruments, <lb/>is propagated from it to the
          bridge, and <lb/>thence again to the ſound-board; and in <lb/>the inſtance we are now
          upon, from the <lb/>bridge of the ſpinnet to the tobacco-pipe, <lb/>and thence farther on,
          till it reaches, and <lb/>puts into a ſimilar motion, the organs of <lb/>hearing; and the
          parts themſelves of our <lb/>body are adapted for this propagation. For <lb/>inſtance,
          hang a little bell, cymbal, pair <lb/>of tongs, &amp;c. by means of a metal wire <lb/>or
          gut-ſtring, on the finger, and with <lb/>that finger ſtop the ear, and ſtrike upon or
          <lb/>move any of theſe bodies, and the ſound <lb/>is perfectly well perceived: Or take a
          <lb/>watch by the chain between the teeth, and <lb/>ſtop the ears cloſe, and you will very
            <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtinctly</w> hear it go. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As in theſe caſes, the ſound is <w part="I">propa-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >gated</w> from the mouth to the ear, though <lb/>the air, which is put in motion, is no
          <lb/>ways connected with the external ear; in <lb/>that caſe it muſt be, that the parts of
          <lb/>the head, lying between the mouth and <lb/>the organ of hearing, are the means of <pb
            xml:id="page_54" n="46"/><lb/>propagation. But as it is well known <lb/>from phyſical
          grounds, that ſoft parts, <lb/>ſuſceptible of little or no degree of <w part="I"
            >vibra-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, are not only in themſelves incapable <lb/>of
          propagating ſound, but even obſtruct, <lb/>or, at leaſt, diminiſh its farther <w part="I"
            >propaga-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, when happening to interrupt the <lb/>connection
          of the hard and elaſtic parts: <lb/>The hard and elaſtic parts, therefore, of <lb/>the
          body, uninterrupted in their cloſe <lb/>connection or continuity by the <w part="I"
            >inter-</w><lb/><w part="F">vention</w> of ſofter parts, are alone fitteſt for <lb/>this
          purpoſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I ſhall now briefly mention, as I <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >miſed</w> above, all theſe hard parts of the <lb/>head, with their ſeveral connections
          with <lb/>each other; from all which, their <w part="I">capa-</w><lb/><w part="F">city</w>
          or incapacity to propagate ſound will <lb/>be more eaſily and certainly determined;
          <lb/>and ſhall begin with the under parts, <lb/>where, according to the experiments above
          <lb/>mentioned, the communication and <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">pagation</w> of
          ſound took its riſe; and thus <lb/>ſhall proceed to the upper parts. And <lb/>firſt, the
          teeth offer to conſideration, <lb/>which are parts extremely hard and firm, <lb/>and by an
          articulation, called <hi rend="italic">gomphoſis,</hi>
          <pb xml:id="page_55" n="47"/><lb/>wedged or fixed immoveably in their <w part="I"
            >ca-</w><lb/><w part="F">vities</w> or ſockets, in both the jaw-bones, <lb/>ſo as not to
          drop out even in a skeleton. <lb/>In the ſecond place, follows the under <lb/>jaw-bone,
          both whoſe <hi rend="italic">apophyſes condyloi-<lb/>deae</hi> are obliquely inſerted in
          the <hi rend="italic">fovea gle-<lb/>noides</hi> of the temporal bone, and move <lb/>over
          the oblique eminence of the ſame <lb/>bone, by means of the <hi rend="italic">cartilago <w
              part="I">interar-</w><lb/><w part="F">ticularis</w>.</hi> Thirdly, the upper maxillary
          <lb/>bones come to be conſidered, whoſe <w part="I">hin-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w> and
          inner part is immediatly connected <lb/>with the <hi rend="italic">apophyſes
            pterygoides</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">os <lb/>ſphenoides;</hi> but the fore-part
          firmly <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">nected</w> with the palatine to the <hi
            rend="italic">oſſa palati,</hi><lb/> and with the zygomatic proceſſes to the <hi
            rend="italic">os <lb/>zygomaticum.</hi> Then, fourthly, follows <lb/>the juſt mentioned
            <hi rend="italic">os jugale,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">zygomati-<lb/>cum,</hi> which, by
          a peculiar proceſs, is <lb/>cloſely connected, backwards, with the <lb/>temporal bone.
          Fifthly, the palatine <lb/>bones are connected with the <hi rend="italic">os
            cuneiforme</hi>
          <lb/>by the pterygoidal proceſſes. Sixthly, the <lb/><hi rend="italic">os cuneiforme</hi>
          lies in the middle, between <lb/>the ſaid bones, and forms, as it were, the <lb/>common
          copula or tie of theſe and of the <lb/>temporal bones; ſeeing it is connected <pb
            xml:id="page_56" n="48"/><lb/>forwards with the palatine bones by the <lb/>pterygoid
          proceſſes, and by the temporal <lb/>proceſſes, called by ſome the greater wing <lb/>of the
          os cuneiforme, with the <hi rend="italic">os ſquamo-<lb/>ſum</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
            >petroſum</hi> of the temporal bone. <lb/>Hence, ſeventhly, it appears, that the
          <lb/>temporal bone is immediately connected <lb/>with the <hi rend="italic">os jugale</hi>
          and <hi rend="italic">cuneiforme,</hi> and <w part="I">me-</w><lb/><w part="F">diately</w>
          with the palatine bones, and both <lb/>the maxillary bones, and with the teeth; <lb/>yet
          ſo, as that the connection with the <lb/>inferior maxillary is interrupted by an <w
            part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">terpoſing</w> cartilage. Eighthly, the <w part="I"
            >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">nection</w> of the temporal with the other <lb/>bones of the
          cranium, as the <hi rend="italic">oſſa frontis, <lb/>ſincipitis,</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">occipitis,</hi> is either mediate, <lb/>by means of the <hi rend="italic"
            >os cuneiforme,</hi> or <w part="I">imme-</w><lb/><w part="F">diate</w>, by means of the
          ſutures; which <lb/>laſt, in more advanced years, intirely <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">appear</w>. Ninthly and laſtly, to this head <lb/>we refer the <hi
            rend="italic">tuba Euſtachii,</hi> a canal, <w part="I">part-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w>
          bony, partly cartilaginous, and partly <lb/>membranous, and cloſely connected with
          <lb/>the temporal bone. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>From this connection of bones, we <lb/>may plainly ſee, that ſound is
          propagated <lb/>by ſuch of them, as are continuous, and <pb xml:id="page_57" n="49"
          /><lb/>cloſely connected together, and are, as <lb/>much as may be, either bare and naked,
          or <lb/>only covered with thinly expanded ſoft <lb/>parts: Of this kind are principally
          the <lb/>upper teeth, then the upper maxillary <lb/>bone; alſo all the bones of the
          cranium, <lb/>when ſtript of their hair, and their other <lb/>ſofter parts, are a little
          ſtretched, either <lb/>by the hand, or ſome aſtringent. And this <lb/>is the foundation of
            <hi rend="italic">Ramireſius'</hi> method, <lb/>very eaſily explicable from that which
          we <lb/>have juſt ſaid. On the contrary, where <lb/>there is neither no perfect and
          continuous <lb/>connection of bones with each other, <w part="I">par-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ticularly</w> with the temporal, which <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tains</w>
          the internal ear, or where too many <lb/>ſofter parts lie round or between the bones,
          <lb/>the propagation of vibratory motion, and <lb/>conſequently of ſound, is, according to
            <w part="I">phy-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſical</w> principles, impoſſible: On this <w
            part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">count</w>, neither the under maxillary bone, <lb/>nor
          the <hi rend="italic">tuba Euſtachii,</hi> can properly <w part="I">propa-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">gate</w> ſound. Of the laſt we are, moreover, <lb/>to obſerve, that being
          membranous from <lb/>the pterygoid proceſſes to its opening into <lb/>the mouth, and
          partly alſo lax, and on that <lb/>account exhibiting a ſomewhat collapſed <pb
            xml:id="page_58" n="50"/><lb/>paſſage, the vibrating air cap neither be <lb/>conveyed in
          ſufficient quantity, to the cavity <lb/>of the drum, nor produce in it the due
          <lb/>vibratory motion. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As ſound may be propagated by all <w part="I">ela-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſtic</w> bodies, in cloſe connection or <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tact</w>
          with each other; ſo in this caſe may <lb/>be of ſervice all thin ſlips of wood, <w
            part="I">Spa-</w><lb/><w part="F">niſh</w> reeds, ſword-blades, tobacco-pipes,
          <lb/>&amp;c. when preſſed to the above-mentioned <lb/>hard and elaſtic parts of the head,
          which <lb/>ſtand connected with the temporal bones. <lb/>Now, as among all the elaſtic
          bodies juſt <lb/>mentioned, the fibres of wood are <w part="I">remark-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ably</w> tough and flexible, and on account of <lb/>their looſe and open texture, give
          no great <lb/>reſiſtance to vibratory motions, but rather <lb/>afford them greater ſcope;
          ſo thin ſlips <lb/>of wood, or ſlender Spaniſh reeds, are beſt <lb/>adapted for the
          purpoſes of propagating <lb/>ſound to the elaſtic parts of the head, and <lb/>to the
          organs of hearing. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>From the principles hitherto advanced, <lb/>may be explained all thoſe
          experiments, <lb/>which were made on occaſion of actually <lb/>employing this method, and
          briefly recited <lb/>above. The firſt experiment, either with <pb xml:id="page_59" n="51"
          /><lb/>the large funnel, or with barely ſpeaking <lb/>into the mouth of the deaf perſon,
          in <w part="I">or-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w> to produce the ſenſe of hearing, <w
            part="I">miſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">carried</w> in the execution: For, as in this
          <lb/>caſe, the air alone is to communicate to <lb/>the teeth, and other elaſtic parts <w
            part="I">connect-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> with them; a vibratory motion; it is in
          <lb/>general unfit for this purpoſe, as it comes <lb/>greatly rarified from the mouth of
          the <lb/>ſpeaker, and conſequently, greatly <w part="I">dimi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >niſhed</w> in activity and elaſticity: Beſides; <lb/>from the property common to all
          forced <lb/>fluids, as ſoon as it has eſcaped the mouth <lb/>of the ſpeaker, it expands
          every way, and <lb/>thereby becomes ſtill more weakened in <lb/>its efficacy, and
          conſequently cannot, in <lb/>that caſe, overcome the reſiſtance of the <lb/>teeth, and
          other elaſtic parts of the mouth <lb/>of a deaf perſon, nor put them into <w part="I"
            >vibra-</w><lb/><w part="F">tory</w> motion, ſufficient to produce the ſenſe <lb/>of
          hearing. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The ſecond, third, and ſixth <w part="I">experi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ments</w>, in which the voice proved too <lb/>weak and imperceptible to the deaf man,
          <lb/>when the ſlips of wood were held too faſt <lb/>with the ſingers, or ſhut lips and
          teeth, as <lb/>alſo when held to the ſhut teeth, may be <pb xml:id="page_60" n="52"
          /><lb/>explained in the ſame manner. From the <lb/>foregoing propoſitions it is evident,
          that <lb/>the ſofter parts of our body interrupt the <lb/>progreſs of ſound, receiving
          indeed the <lb/>vibratory motion, but for want of the <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >quiſite</w> re-action not propagating it far <lb/>enough: And for this there is alſo <w
            part="I">ano-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> reaſon, namely, that in the three <w part="I"
            >for-</w><lb/><w part="F">mer</w> methods of applying the ſlip of wood, <lb/>the ſame
          degree of force muſt put in <w part="I">mo-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> a far greater
          quantity of the vibratory <lb/>air, than can happen in different and <w part="I"
            >op-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſite</w> circumſtances, whence, of neceſſity, <lb/>a leſs
          effect muſt enſue: Now, as in the <lb/>third and ſixth experiments, a greater ſhare
          <lb/>of vibration is loſt in the under jaw-bone, <lb/>the ſenſation thereof muſt, of
          courſe, be <lb/>extremely weak and indiſtinct. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And this farther explains the fourth <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">periment</w>, by which the deaf perſon <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ceived</w> not the leaſt ſound, on holding the <lb/>ſlip to the under teeth. To explain
          this <lb/>obſervation there can be no difficulty, when <lb/>we recollect the connection of
          the under <lb/>jaw-bone with the temporal: The under <lb/>jaw-bone having its connection
          with the <lb/>reſt of the bones of the head, only by <pb xml:id="page_61" n="53"
          /><lb/>means of ſoft interpoſing parts, namely, <lb/>a ſoft cartilage, which, beſides, on
          account <lb/>of the conſtant moiſtneſs of thoſe parts, is <lb/>lower, receiving, indeed,
          the vibratory <lb/>motion, but directly again loſing it, and, <lb/>as it were, deadening
          it, in its ſofter <w part="I">ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtance</w>, for want of the
          requiſite re-action; <lb/>how is it poſſible then to expect any <w part="I"
            >alte-</w><lb/><w part="F">ration</w> in the other bones of the head from <lb/>the
          vibratory motion of this bone? </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The fifth experiment, on the contrary, <lb/>is ſomewhat more difficult
          to explain: <lb/>For, as here the tongue, a ſofter part, is <lb/>brought to the palate and
          teeth, and yet <lb/>that which another utters remains diſtinct <lb/>and perceptible to the
          deaf perſon, it <lb/>ſhould ſeem, that this experiment <w part="I">contra-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">dicts</w> the ſecond, third, and ſixth. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But here we are to conſider, that, in <lb/>the firſt place, the tongue
          is applied <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">hind</w> the teeth. 2dly, That all ſoft
          parts, <lb/>as fully appears from phyſics, receive not <lb/>ſuch a quantity of vibratory
          motion, as do <lb/>hard bodies: Whence it is, as the teeth <lb/>are as it were wedged in
          the upper <w part="I">ma-</w><lb/><w part="F">xillary</w> bone, being a hard part, the
          greateſt <lb/>ſhare of vibration will go to the jaw, and <pb xml:id="page_62" n="54"
          /><lb/>only a ſmaller ſhare thereof to the tongue: <lb/>But, if you ſlip the tongue
          forwards over <lb/>the teeth, the ſame thing happens as in <lb/>lips together; either no
          ſound at all, or <lb/>but very indiſtinctly, being perceivable <lb/>by the deaf perſon. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The ſeventh obſervation, namely, that <lb/>the hearing is not
          diminiſhed, though the <lb/>mouth be full of water, is eaſily accounted <lb/>for; as we
          learn from philoſophy, that <lb/>there is much elaſtic air in water, adapted <lb/>for the
          propagation of ſound; as <w part="I">ſuffici-</w><lb/><w part="F">ently</w> appears from
          the example of divers, <lb/>who, under water; perceive the ſound <lb/>produced above
          water: Now, as water <lb/>perfectly encreaſes the continuity of the <lb/>parts in the
          mouth, and propagates the <lb/>vibrations produced by ſound from the <lb/>teeth to the
          maxillary bones, and the <lb/>pterygoid proceſſes of the <hi rend="italic">os
            cuneiforme,</hi>
          <lb/>we may, from the connection of theſe <lb/>parts with the temporal bones, eaſily
          judge, <lb/>that the ſenſation of ſound is rather <w part="I">heigh-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tened</w> than diminiſhed by the water in the <lb/>mouth. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In order to explain the eighth <w part="I">experi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ment</w>, which was made with a braſs or <pb xml:id="page_63" n="55"/><lb/>iron wire,
          two things, in particular, are <lb/>to be remarked; firſt, that ſuch metal <lb/>ſtrings or
          wires are a great deal firmer than <lb/>wood, and conſequently require a greater
          <lb/>degree of force, in order to vibrate, than <lb/>is poſſible to be produced by the air
          in <lb/>ſpeaking: Secondly, that their baſe of <lb/>contact with the teeth is by much too
          <lb/>ſmall, for them to communicate a <w part="I">ſuffici-</w><lb/><w part="F">ent</w>
          degree of motion to the whole range <lb/>of bones reaching quite to the ear: And <lb/>this
          is the very reaſon, that by laying hold <lb/>on it with the teeth, the points of contact
          <lb/>being encreaſed, the deaf perſon comes <lb/>to have ſome degree of ſenſation. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The happy effects produced with the <lb/>beer-glaſs, and the
          unſucceſſful attempts <lb/>with the wine-glaſs, which was the <lb/>ninth experiment, ſeem
          to depend, either <lb/>on the greater compaſs of the former, <lb/>or on ſome degree of
          compreſſion <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duced</w> in the air ſpoken into it,
          which <lb/>thereby communicates its vibratory motions <lb/>and repercuſſions to the
          elaſtic glaſs, and <lb/>by that means to the teeth and upper <w part="I">jaw-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">bone</w>, though the lips interpoſe or lie <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tween</w>, as they acquire a greater degree of <pb xml:id="page_64" n="56"
          /><lb/>cloſeneſs in their texture, and greater <w part="I">ſuſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ceptibility</w> to propagate ſound, by the <lb/>greater degree of preſſion, made on
          them <lb/>with the rim of the glaſs: Whereas, a leſs <lb/>portion of air goes into the
          wine-glaſs, <lb/>beſides, its compaſs is ſmaller, and the <lb/>greater maſs of foot or
          ſtalk, diminiſhes <lb/>the motion of the air, ſo as to prevent its <lb/>communicating to
          the teeth a ſufficient <lb/>pitch of vibration. And laſtly, the reaſon <lb/>why, according
          to the tenth obſervation <lb/>or experiment, the looſe teeth of the upper <lb/>jaw
          rendered ſpeaking indiſtinct to the <lb/>deaf perſon, is eaſily underſtood, when we
          <lb/>reflect, that, in order to propagate a <w part="I">vibra-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tory</w> motion, a cloſer continuity of elaſtic <lb/>parts is requiſite. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As the ſenſation, which is perceived in <lb/>the act of hearing,
          produced by the <w part="I">me-</w><lb/><w part="F">thods</w> of the ſecond order of the
          ſecond <lb/>claſs, ſeems to be formed almoſt in the <lb/>middle of the brain, backwards at
          the <hi rend="italic">me-<lb/>dulla oblongata,</hi> we may hence, according <lb/>to
          anatomical grounds, judge, that the <w part="I">vi-</w><lb/><w part="F">brations</w>
          produced by ſound, put the <w part="I">audi-</w><lb/><w part="F">tory</w> nerves in
          ſenſation, from the <hi rend="italic">os <w part="I">petro-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſum</w>,</hi> quite to their origin: And hence <pb xml:id="page_65" n="57"/><lb/>ariſes
          this practical propoſition, that the <lb/>eaſy method we have been hitherto upon, <lb/>to
          procure hearing to the deaf, is adapted <lb/>to all perſons afflicted with deafneſs, be
          the <lb/>other auditory organs injured how they may, <lb/>provided the auditory nerves are
          not <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtructed</w>, injured, or quite deſtroyed at their
          <lb/>origin: For, this laſt is the only caſe, in <lb/>which the preſent method is not
          applicable, <lb/>and on ſuch melancholy objects all labour <lb/>and pains are loſt. </p>
        <trailer rend="align-center"><lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
