<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title> LMEMT Corpus - Arnaud De Ronsil: Remarks on the composition, use, and effects of the
     extract of lead</title>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Compiler</resp>
     <persName xml:id="IT">
      <forename>Irma</forename>
      <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
     </persName>
     <persName xml:id="TH">
      <forename>Turo</forename>
      <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
     </persName>
     <persName xml:id="ALe">
      <forename>Anu</forename>
      <surname>Lehto</surname>
     </persName>
     <persName xml:id="VM">
      <forename>Ville</forename>
      <surname>Marttila</surname>
     </persName>
     <persName xml:id="RO">
      <forename>Raisa</forename>
      <surname>Oinonen</surname>
     </persName>
     <persName xml:id="PP">
      <forename>Päivi</forename>
      <surname>Pahta</surname>
     </persName>
     <persName xml:id="MR">
      <forename>Maura</forename>
      <surname>Ratia</surname>
     </persName>
     <persName xml:id="CS">
      <forename>Carla</forename>
      <surname>Suhr</surname>
     </persName>
     <persName xml:id="JT">
      <forename>Jukka</forename>
      <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
     </persName>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
     <persName xml:id="WA">
      <forename>Wilma</forename>
      <surname>Andersson</surname>
     </persName>
     <persName xml:id="EC">
      <forename>Emanuela</forename>
      <surname>Costea</surname>
     </persName>
     <persName xml:id="DV">
      <forename>Diana</forename>
      <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
     </persName>
     <persName xml:id="SK">
      <forename>Sami</forename>
      <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
     </persName>
     <persName xml:id="MK">
      <forename>Mirella</forename>
      <surname>Klinga</surname>
     </persName>
     <persName xml:id="SKo">
      <forename>Sami</forename>
      <surname>Koskinen</surname>
     </persName>
     <persName xml:id="ALi">
      <forename>Aatu</forename>
      <surname>Liimatta</surname>
     </persName>
     <persName xml:id="HR">
      <forename>Heikki</forename>
      <surname>Rajala</surname>
     </persName>
     <persName xml:id="JR">
      <forename>Jenni</forename>
      <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
     </persName>
     <persName xml:id="AW">
      <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
      <surname>Walraff</surname>
     </persName>
    </respStmt>
    <sponsor>
     <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
    </sponsor>
    <funder>
     <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
     <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
    </funder>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
    <date>forthcoming</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblStruct>
     <monogr>
      <author>
       <persName>Georges Arnaud De Ronsil</persName>
      </author>
      <title type="main">Remarks on the composition, use, and effects of the extract of lead of Mr.
       Goulard, and of his vegeto-mineral water. By G. Arnaud, Doctor in Physic and Master in
       Surgery, The only Person authorized to sell this Extract, composed by Mr. Goulard
       himself.</title>
      <edition n="1"/>
      <idno type="ESTC">T46796</idno>
      <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T46796"/>
      <imprint>
       <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
       <pubPlace>
        <placeName>London</placeName>
       </pubPlace>
       <publisher>
        <persName>London: printed for the author in Church-Street, St. Ann's Soho, and sold by P.
         Elmsly, successor to Mr. Vaillant, Bookseller in the Strand, MDCCLXX.</persName>
       </publisher>
       <date>1770</date>
      </imprint>
      <extent>
       <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
       <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
       <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="28"/>
      </extent>
     </monogr>
     <note type="source_copy">
      <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
      <idno type="ECCO">CW3307240853</idno>
      <idno type="TCP">K044037.000</idno>
     </note>
    </biblStruct>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: medicine"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  
 </teiHeader>
 <text xml:lang="eng">
  <front> </front>
  <body>
   <div>
    <pb xml:id="page_2" n="3"/>
    <head rend="align-center"><lb/>ON THE <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">EXTRACT</hi>
     <lb/>OF <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">LEAD.</hi>
    </head>
    <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">I</hi>T is not my intention here to deſcant on <lb/>the
     praiſes of Mr. Goulard's remedy.<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.7)">* See Mr. Goulard's
      work, ſold by P. Elmſly <w part="I">ſucceſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſor</w> to Mr. Vaillant,
      Bookſeller in the Strand. </note>
     <lb/>That is already too well known throughout <lb/>Europe, to want any aſſiſtance from my pen.
     <lb/>My views coincide entirely with thoſe of the <lb/>author, in endeavouring to bring it to
     ſtill <lb/>greater perfection, by conſidering it with more <lb/>preciſeneſs both as to it's
     compoſition and uſe. <lb/>To be ignorant of theſe would be a fault, <lb/>willingly to conceal
     it's ſuperior virtues, <lb/>would be an injury to ſociety, and a mannes <lb/>of proceeding very
     different from the author's, <lb/>who has publiſhed all his knowledge on the <lb/>ſubject
     without reſerve. </p>
    <pb xml:id="page_3" n="4"/>
    <p rend="indent"><lb/>This medicament, juſtly looked upon by thoſe <lb/>of the faculty, who are
     free from prejudice, as <lb/>the beſt and moſt univerſal topic in ſurgery, <lb/>may very
     properly be ſubſtituted in the place <lb/>of all others generally preſcribed: it will
     <lb/>frequently prove efficacious when the reſt have <lb/>failed, and will repair the diſorders
     they have <lb/>brought upon the conſtitution. </p>
    <p rend="indent"><lb/>I don't pretend to mention this medicine <lb/>as a new diſcovered one, on
     the contrary, <lb/>we have received it from antiquity, known <lb/>by the name of <hi
      rend="italic">Acetum Litargiri;</hi> but by its <lb/>having been ill made, <hi rend="italic"
      >mal-a-propos</hi> applied, <lb/>and preſcribed in improper quantities, it <lb/>was for ſome
     time out of repute, and <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w part="F">out</w> the aſſiſtance and the
     vigilance of Mr. <lb/>Goulard's ſpeculative turn, who has had <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
      part="F">ſolution</w> enough to ſtem the torrent of <w part="I">oppoſi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
      >tion</w>, this remedy, like many others, by having <lb/>been improperly made and as
     improperly <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">miniſtred</w>, would have fallen into the <w
      part="I">poſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſeſſion</w> only of the quacks. For want of proper
     <lb/>vinegar the baſis of this medicine it <w part="I">frequent-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w>
     deceived the practitioners, who, from not <lb/>knowing its properties and the real method of
     <lb/>compoſing it, entirely laid it aſide. But it has <lb/>of late been too minutely conſidered
     to be <lb/>any longer neglected, and is now looked <lb/>upon, by the impartial part of mankind,
     to <lb/>be one of the greateſt ornaments of the <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
      >penſatories</w>, as well as the moſt efficacious <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">medy</w>
     in ſurgery. It is then to Mr. Goulard, a <pb xml:id="page_4" n="5"/><lb/>skilful ſurgeon of
     Montpellier, we owe its <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">vival</w>; which could never have
     been effected, <lb/>but by a man of his eminence, and like him <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w
      part="F">empt</w> from vulgar prejudice, which has <w part="I">hither-</w><lb/><w part="F"
      >to</w> laid to the charge of this ſalutary remedy <lb/>faults, from which the experiments of
     many <lb/>famous in their profeſſion are now <w part="I">endeavour-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>
     to clear it in favour of mankind. </p>
    <p rend="indent"><lb/>When this extract is made with natural <lb/>vinegar, and the ſtrongeſt
     which can be <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">cured</w> in the ſouth of France, where
     nature <lb/>in favourable years, and in particular <w part="I">can-</w><lb/><w part="F"
      >tons</w>, furniſhes this vegetable liquor with <lb/>more virtues, than any art of the <w
      part="I">vinegar-</w><lb/><w part="F">makers</w> can poſſibly endow it with, it poſſeſſes
     <lb/>all the diſperſing, cooling, and reſolving qualities <lb/>proper for dividing the
     glutinous ſtagnated <lb/>matter in the obſtructed veſſels; it relaxes them <lb/>when too much
     contracted, and reſtores to the <lb/>ſolids and fluids the proportion of circulation
     <lb/>neceſſary for preſerving the animal œconomy <lb/>in a ſtate of health. The common
     vinegars, <lb/>owing their ſtrength to ſal armoniac, to pepper, <lb/>and the dung of the
     feathered kind, which can't <lb/>fail of robbing this extract of the qualities <w part="I"
      >ne-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceſſary</w> for its perfection, as do likewiſe other <lb/>factitious
     vegetable acids, ſuch for example, <lb/>as are brewed in England, and in the <w part="I"
      >nor-</w><lb/><w part="F">thern</w> countries, under the appearance of <w part="I"
      >vine-</w><lb/><w part="F">gar</w>. The latter, 'tis true, tho' not capable <lb/>of injuring
     the conſtitution, act as <w part="I">ſtimula-</w><lb/><w part="F">tors</w> to the ſtomach; but
     this property is not <pb xml:id="page_5" n="6"/><lb/>ſufficient to perfectly diſſolve the lead,
     or to <lb/>impregnate theſe metallic particles with the <lb/>particular qualities they acquire
     by the <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">dition</w> of tartar natural to thoſe vinegars,
     <lb/>which are made with the ſtrongeſt wines.<note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.7)">† Such
      as are well verſed in the art of chymiſtry, <lb/>know, that natural vinegar contains an
      eſſential oil <lb/>which entirely diſſolves lead, while its acid only divides <lb/>it's parts.
      Mr. Goulard has diſcovered that it is the <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">perty</w> of
      ſome particular vinegars only of the province <lb/>he lives in, to perfectly diſſolve this
      metal, as they <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tain</w> more eſſential oil than the reſt;
      conſequently <w part="I">natu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ral</w> vinegars, when adulterated, or
      factitious one, which <lb/>receive their power of action from the acrid ingredients <lb/>only
      mixed with them, are not only rendered incapable <lb/>of perfectly diſſolving the lead, but
      likewiſe <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">municate</w> an inflammatory quality to the
      extract, very <lb/>different from the cooling and calming one natural <lb/>to it, when made
      with the beſt vinegar. The healing <lb/>quality of lead is evident, from its happy effects,
      when <lb/>applied in its natural ſtate even to ulcerated cancers; <lb/>how much more
      efficaciouſly muſt it then act, when its <lb/>ſaline particles are ſo far divided as to be
      capable of <lb/>being introduced into the ſmalleſt veſſels, and there <lb/>circulate with the
      juices? theſe they attenuate and divide, <lb/>ſo as to return into their proper channel; it is
      very <w part="I">neceſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſary</w> then, that the vinegar; made uſe of for
      the <w part="I">diſſolu-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of the lead, ſhould be natural, well
      choſen, and by <lb/>no means factitious. A chymical analyſis will eaſily <lb/>diſcover the
      defects of vinegar; but, as every one is not <lb/>in a ſituation of making theſe experiments,
      it's merits <lb/>may be aſcertained by the taſte only. Good vinegar, <lb/>when touched with
      the tongue, has a pleaſing acid taſte, <lb/>and leaves a freſhneſs in the mouth, but when
      factitious <lb/>rather appears to inflame the mouth, and throat, which <lb/>ſenſation
      continues for ſome time. </note>
     <lb/>I ſhall not here enter upon the bad qualities <lb/>which may be conveyed to lead by the <w
      part="I">in-</w><pb xml:id="page_6" n="7"/><lb/><w part="F">gredients</w> made uſe of in the
     compoſition <lb/>of factitious vinegars, which are brewed <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F"
      >cording</w> to every one's particular <hi rend="italic">recipe.</hi>
     <lb/>The beſt argument in favor of the extract of <lb/>Saturn, made in particular parts of the
     ſouth of <lb/>France, and againſt any other extract made <lb/>with common vinegars, is, that
     the tartar of <lb/>Languedoc has the preference in chymical <lb/>proceſſes, ſome of which are
     in vain attempted <lb/>without it. Another argument ſtill more <w part="I">cor-</w><lb/><w
      part="F">roborative</w> is that, at Montpellier alone good <lb/>verdigreaſe can be procured,
     on account of the <lb/>ſingular property of its vinegar, and for ſome <lb/>other concurrent and
     unknown reaſons, which <lb/>help to diſſolve the copper the baſis of the <lb/>above drug. For
     the ſame reaſon we may be <lb/>induced to think that the tartarous particles <lb/>of the wine
     of that country, being refined by <lb/>its change into vinegar, may contribute more
     <lb/>efficaciouſly to diſſolve the lead, which <w part="I">experi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ence</w>
     daily proves. Common vinegars help only <lb/>to divide it in parts, ſome of Languedoc <w
      part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">perly</w> elected diſſolve it ſo thoroughly, that
     <lb/>without any ſediment it preſerves its weight, <lb/>a certain proof that it incorporates
     itſelf more <lb/>with this ſpecies of vinegar, which no doubt <lb/>muſt render it's effects
     more efficacious. It is <lb/>certainly owing to this, that the medicine <lb/>we ſpeak of
     poſſeſſes cooling, diſperſing, <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſolving</w> qualities, and
     by no means a repelling <lb/>one, as has been hinted by certain people. <lb/>This requires an
     explanation, which will be <pb xml:id="page_7" n="8"/><lb/>eaſily underſtood by the meaneſt
     capacity, as <lb/>I ſhall endeavour to expreſs myſelf in the <lb/>plaineſt terms. </p>
    <p rend="indent"><lb/>When the lead is divided only, it's parts <lb/>are too groſs and ponderous
     to remain <w part="I">ſuſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">pended</w> in the vegetable liquid its vehicle;
     <lb/>this cauſes it to ſubſide: on ſhaking the bottle, <lb/>they again incorporate with the
     liquid, <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w part="F">out</w> ſuffering a diminution of their volume;
     <lb/>this volume by preventing them from <w part="I">penetrat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> to
     the veſſels tho' the pores of the ſkin <lb/>cauſes them to remain in the tiſſue of thoſe parts,
     <lb/>and, by ſtopping up the paſſages of <w part="I">perſpirati-</w><lb/><w part="F">on</w>,
     gives riſe to what is generally termed <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">pulſion</w>. But,
     when the metal is ſo far diſſolved, <lb/>as always to remain ſuſpended in the vegetable
     <lb/>liquid, its parts are ſo fine and ſo far <w part="I">attenuat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>,
     as not to be diſcernable thro' the moſt <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">fect</w>
     microſcope; they then eaſily penetrate <lb/>the pores of the skin, follow the courſe of the
     <lb/>perſpiratory veſſels, and put in motion the <lb/>inſpiſſated and ſtagnated fluids, which
     they <lb/>again return to the road of circulation. When <lb/>the metallic particles act thus,
     the aquatic <lb/>vehicles, with which they are combined, <lb/>looſen the skin, which was before
     in a ſtate of <lb/>too great tenſion, whilſt the ſpiritous ones <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
      part="F">ſtore</w> to the veſſels that elaſticity of which they <lb/>had been deprived. Thus a
     reſolution of the <w part="I">hu-</w><lb/><w part="F">mours</w> is effected by means of
     tranſpiration <lb/>and circulation: but a wiſe and cautious <w part="I">prac-</w><lb/><w
      part="F">titioner</w> muſt always attend to the progreſs of <pb xml:id="page_8" n="9"
     /><lb/>the complaint, when either putrefaction or a <lb/>degree of malignity is apprehended;
     and care <lb/>ſhould be always taken to mix this with <w part="I">digeſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
      >tives</w>, for critical diſcharges, as by abating their <lb/>heat it will prevent the
     neighbouring parts <lb/>from being affected, and ſecure the patient <lb/>againſt a too copious
     diſcharge which <w part="I">fre-</w><lb/><w part="F">quently</w> attends theſe caſes. </p>
    <p rend="indent"><lb/>The compariſon made between the <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F"
      >tract</w> of Saturn, and its ſalt, commonly called <lb/>the ſugar of lead, will be found
     unjuſt, <lb/>when we conſider, that the latter is made <lb/>with vinegars of all ſorts of
     wines, and that <lb/>thoſe of Switzerland, which produce the <lb/>greateſt quantity of this
     ſugar, are made of <lb/>wines very little impregnated with tartar, and <lb/>that too of an
     inferior quality. But after <lb/>all, this very ſugar of lead, which is quoted <lb/>as a proof
     of the repelling quality to be found <lb/>in our medicine, is it not made uſe of by the
     <lb/>ableſt practitioners, both as an internal and <lb/>external medicine? if ſo, with how much
     more <lb/>confidence may we make uſe of Mr. Goulard's <lb/>extract, properly made, in the above
      <w part="I">circum-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtances?</w> A practice of fifty years, has <w
      part="I">ſuf-</w><lb/><w part="F">ficiently</w> convinced me of its ſuperiority over <lb/>the
     ſugar of lead, which I have known fail, <lb/>when the other has always anſwered my <w part="I"
      >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">tentions</w>. </p>
    <p rend="indent"><lb/>Such, as are thus diſpoſed to criticiſe the <lb/>moſt approved remedies,
     won't give themſelves <lb/>time to reflect, that an accidental failure of <pb xml:id="page_9"
      n="10"/><lb/>ſucceſs might be owing to this extract not <lb/>having been properly made in its
      <w part="I">commence-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w>, or ſucceeding proceſſes, to its having
     <lb/>been given in too great a quantity, or <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">plied</w> cold,
     as indeed the author ſometimes <lb/>recommends with a view only to the <w part="I"
      >tempe-</w><lb/><w part="F">rate</w> climate he writes in: thus have theſe <lb/>people been
     induced, without having any <lb/>regard for themſelves, to confirm the opinion <lb/>of the
     vulgar, who generally attribute the <lb/>death of the patient to the laſt remedy, and <lb/>thus
     ſhamefully take advantage of this <w part="I">fal-</w><lb/><w part="F">lacious</w> argument to
     cry down the good effects <lb/>of the extract of Saturn, and to extol <w part="I"
      >reme-</w><lb/><w part="F">dies</w> at beſt uncertain, often fallacious, and <lb/>which cuſtom
     alone, the tyrant of the mind, <lb/>authoriſes the uſe of both againſt reaſon and
     <lb/>experience. Many examples might be brought <lb/>to refute what perſons, otherwiſe
     reſpectable, <lb/>have thought proper to advance to the <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F"
      >judice</w> of this remedy; but I will refer the <lb/>reader, to many obſervations given by
     the <lb/>author in his treatiſe<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.7)">* Already mentioned
      in the note p. 3. </note>, and to take into <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
      >ſideration</w> here the firſt paragraph of the third <lb/>Formula, page 208, on the
     inefficacy of the <lb/>poultices generally preſcribed. </p>
    <p rend="indent"><lb/>The proofs I have given of the neceſſity of <lb/>procuring the beſt
     vinegar, and the rules I <lb/>ſhall lay down in the ſequel, for the better <lb/>making and
     uſing this extract, having been <pb xml:id="page_10" n="11"/><lb/>approved of by men of
     knowledge and rank <lb/>in this country, ever intent on means to aſſiſt <lb/>the poorer part of
     mankind, have induced <lb/>me to procure a quantity of it from the <w part="I">foun-</w><lb/><w
      part="F">tain</w> head itſelf. I have applied to Mr. <lb/>Goulard for this purpoſe, to whom I
     have <lb/>likewiſe communicated my thoughts on the <lb/>farther improvement and uſe of this
     remedy,<lb/> which I have the ſatisfaction to know entirely <lb/>coincide with his. This
     concurrence of Ideas, <lb/>which originally ſprung from a fifty years <w part="I"
      >ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">quaintance</w>, having been fellow-ſtudents <w part="I"
      >to-</w><lb/><w part="F">gether</w>, has induced me to imitate him on <lb/>other
      occaſions,<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.7)">* See pages 8 and 201 of my treatiſe of
      diſorders of <lb/>the urethra and bladder, ſold by P. Elmſly, bookſeller <lb/>in the Strand,
      in 12mo. the third edition. </note> and has been the means of <lb/>his allowing me to be the
     ſole vender in this <lb/>country of the extract he himſelf made<note place="bottom" n="†"
      rend="size(0.7)">† See the end of theſe remarks. </note>. </p>
    <p rend="indent"><lb/>This topic, which properly ſpeaking is an <lb/>univerſal chirurgical
     medicine and eaſily <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">cured</w>, has this triple advantage
     over others. <lb/>Firſt, it coſts but little; ſecondly, it is <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w
      part="F">pared</w> in an inſtant; and thirdly, it may eaſily <lb/>be conveyed from place to
     place. </p>
    <p rend="indent"><lb/>Whoever is provided with it may prevent <lb/>the bad conſequences of
     bruiſes occaſioned <lb/>either by a fall or blow; it prevents an <lb/>echymoſis, or
     extravaſation of blood, the <lb/>general attendant of fractures and diſlocations, <pb
      xml:id="page_11" n="12"/><lb/>till proper aſſiſtance can be procured to dreſs <lb/>the patient
      <hi rend="italic">ſecundum artem;</hi> in theſe <w part="I">circum-</w><lb/><w part="F"
      >ſtances</w> it ſhould be made uſe of in the <w part="I">begin-</w><lb/><w part="F">ning</w>,
     as it is a known remedy againſt <w part="I">inflam-</w><lb/><w part="F">mations</w> and
     mortifications, the general <w part="I">atten-</w><lb/><w part="F">dants</w> of theſe
     complaints. I ſhall not enter <lb/>into a detail of the other diſorders it will relieve,
     <lb/>but ſhall refer the reader to Mr. Goulard's <lb/>treatiſe; I ſhall only lay down here ſome
     <lb/>few rules for its uſe, drawn from experience, <lb/>which have met with Mr. Goulard's <w
      part="I">appro-</w><lb/><w part="F">bation</w>, both as to that and its compoſition. </p>
    <p rend="indent" n="1"><lb/>I. Every one is ſufficiently acquainted with <lb/>the powerful
     effects of vegetable acids, and <lb/>particularly thoſe of vinegar in regard to <lb/>braſs, to
     deter him from making this extract <lb/>in veſſels of that metal. No precaution is <w part="I"
      >ſuf-</w><lb/><w part="F">ficient</w> to prevent the vinegar from imbibing <lb/>ſome of the
     copper; it is therefore much more <lb/>adviſeable to make uſe of veſſels made either <lb/>of
     glaſs, earth, or pewter. I ſhould have <lb/>been much more uneaſy about a gentleman's
     <lb/>ſervant, who had ſwallowed by chance, the <lb/>8th of December laſt, a certain quantity of
     the <lb/>vegeto-mineral water, had not I been very <lb/>ſure that the extract had not been made
     in a <lb/>braſs kettle. I aſſured the maſter in anſwer <lb/>to his letter, that no bad
     conſequences would <lb/>enſue, but that it would be adviſeable to <lb/>order the patient to
     drink ſome warm water. </p>
    <pb xml:id="page_12" n="13"/>
    <div>
     <head rend="align-center"><lb/>Copy of Mr. **** Letter. </head>
     <lb/>
     <salute>SIR, </salute>
     <p rend="indent"><lb/>One of my ſervants has ſwallowed, by <lb/>accident, ſome of the
      vegeto-mineral water; <lb/>are there any bad conſequences to be <w part="I">appre-</w><lb/><w
       part="F">hended</w>, and what is beſt to be done? It <w part="I">hap-</w><lb/><w part="F"
       >pened</w> about half an hour ago. I am, &amp;c. </p>
     <lb/>
     <p rend="indent"><lb/>8th December 1769. The day after I received the following. </p>
     <lb/>
     <p rend="indent"><lb/>salute SIR, I have the pleaſure to inform you, that <lb/>my ſervant is
      perfectly well to day: he felt <lb/>laſt night ſome pains in his ſtomach, which <lb/>the warm
      water removed, but no ſtitches, no <lb/>cholicks. I am &amp;c. </p>
     <lb/>
     <p rend="indent" n="2"><lb/>9th December, 1769. II. The external qualities, which <w part="I"
       >charac-</w><lb/><w part="F">terize</w> the true original extract of Saturn, <lb/>conſiſt in
      its colour, its ſmell, its weight, its <lb/>conſiſtence, and its taſte: its colour is that of
      <lb/>orange, its conſiſtence a little ſirupy, its ſmell <lb/>empyreumatical, or of burnt
      ſugar, its weight <lb/>a third part more than that of the vinegar; <lb/>ſo that a phial, which
      holds three ounces <lb/>of vinegar, ought to weigh at leaſt four <lb/>ounces when filled with
      the extract; the <pb xml:id="page_13" n="14"/><lb/>thickneſs of this medicine may be as great
      a <lb/>defect as its lightneſs: for, if it weighs more <lb/>or leſs than it ought, it cannot
      but deceive in <lb/>regard to the proportions made uſe of, and <lb/>not anſwer to the
      directions given. See <sic>p. 8.<corr>2<unclear>#</unclear></corr></sic>
     </p>
     <p rend="indent" n="3"><lb/>III. When bad vinegar has imbibed as <lb/>much lead as it can
      poſſibly diſſolve, the <w part="I">ſuper-</w><lb/><w part="F">fluous</w> metallic particles
      are obſerved to ſink <lb/>to the bottom of the bottle, ſuch extract, <w part="I"
       >im-</w><lb/><w part="F">properly</w> called ſo, is but an imperfect diviſion <lb/>of the
      lead, which muſt be rejected for the <lb/>reaſons mentioned in page 8. </p>
     <p rend="indent" n="4"><lb/>IV. From this mixture of lead and <w part="I">vine-</w><lb/><w
       part="F">gar</w> is produced a water called by the <lb/>author vegeto-mineral; and this water
      is <lb/>endowed with excellent virtues, when made <lb/>uſe of in lotions, fomentations,
      injections, and <lb/>baths, and in the different formulæ deſcribed <lb/>by Mr. Goulard, in his
      cerate, poultices, <w part="I">po-</w><lb/><w part="F">matums</w>, liniments, plaiſters,
      &amp;c. but the <lb/>water, of which the vegeto-mineral is <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w
       part="F">poſed</w>, ought to be particularly conſidered in <lb/>its own natural ſtate, before
      it is made uſe of <lb/>to form this medicated water. Every ſpecies <lb/>of water is not proper
      for this uſe. Rain water, <lb/>when purged and filtered, and that of rivers, <lb/>whoſe
      bottoms conſiſt of either ſand or gravel <lb/>free from mud, are to have the preference,
      <lb/>eſpecially after having been purified either by <lb/>ſtanding ſome time, or filtering
      through proper <lb/>paper; ſpring and pump water being <w part="I">impreg-</w><pb
       xml:id="page_14" n="15"/><lb/><w part="F">nated</w> with gypſous or ſelenitous particles,
      give <lb/>riſe to a new change of the metallic ones of the <lb/>lead; and thus a white
      precipitate is formed, <lb/>which will by no means incorporate with the <lb/>water. "Theſe
      effects, ſays a clebrated chy-<lb/>miſt<note place="marg" n="*">* <hi rend="sc">Beaume</hi>'.
      </note>, are owing to a ſeparation of the vitriolic <lb/>acid of the ſelenites from the earth,
      to which it <lb/>was joined, which now mixes with the lead <lb/>of the extract of Saturn, and
      thus forms a <lb/>vitriol of lead. In that inſtant the vinegar <lb/>mixes with the earth of
      the ſelenites, and they <lb/>form together an acetoſe-calcarious ſalt; ſo that <lb/>at the
      ſame time a new diſſolution and a new <lb/>combination are effected. Thus the medicine is
      <lb/>by no means that of the vegeto-mineral water, <lb/>but a mixture of vitriol of lead,
      acetoſe ſalt, <lb/>and brandy. On this occaſion the vitriol of <lb/>lead ſeems to deſcend in
      form of a white <lb/>powder, tho' it is in reality a ſaline matter <lb/>diſſoluble in water;
      the reaſon is, that it <w part="I">can-</w><lb/><w part="F">not</w> be diſſolved without
      difficulty, and that <lb/>there is not a ſufficiency of water to diſſolve <lb/>the whole
      quantity collected: the remainder <lb/>of the water contains in diſſolution a ſmall
      <lb/>quantity of this vitriol of lead. In fine, if you <lb/>add to the precipitate a large
      quantity of <lb/>boiling water, the diſſolution is perfect; which <lb/>proves, that this
      precipitate is a ſaline <w part="I">ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtance</w>." From this argument,
      founded on <pb xml:id="page_15" n="16"/><lb/>natural philoſophy, and confirmed by the
      <lb/>experiments of all who make uſe of water <lb/>not properly purified, may we not conclude
      <lb/>that we have no reaſon to be ſurpriſed that <lb/>this remedy has ſometimes baffled our <w
       part="I">endea-</w><lb/><w part="F">vours?</w> is it not, on the contrary, a ſubject of
      <lb/>aſtoniſhment, that notwithſtanding this <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">cidental</w>
      defect in its compoſition it has ſo <lb/>frequently been crowned with the greateſt
      <lb/>ſucceſs? In fine, the water, which diſſolves <lb/>ſoap the moſt effectually, is to be
      preferred, tho' <lb/>it will be proper firſt to purify it well. When <lb/>the extract is
      thrown into improper water, it <lb/>whitens it only for a time, and then falls to <lb/>the
      bottom, without being able to mix <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">fectly</w> with it
      afreſh; this water becomes <lb/>curdled, and like ſour milk; and in this ſtate <lb/>it is by
      no means to be made uſe of, as not at <lb/>all likely to anſwer our expectations. To this
      <lb/>we may aſcribe the want of ſucceſs, which <lb/>ſerves to prejudice many againſt the
      remedy, <lb/>and to pleaſe others, who are by no means its <lb/>friends for want of being
      better acquainted <lb/>with it. When proper water cannot be <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w
       part="F">cured</w>, care muſt be taken to diſtil others, if <lb/>opportunity ſerves. This may
      be eaſily done <lb/>with the common alembic, taking care to <lb/>throw away ſome pints of the
      firſt diſtilled, <lb/>as it is frequently liable to be foul, by the <lb/>uncleaneſs of the
      head of the ſtill: you muſt <lb/>likewiſe take care to leave about a quarter <lb/>of it in the
      ſtill, before you have finiſhed <pb xml:id="page_16" n="17"/><lb/>your proceſs, to prevent the
      riſing of any of <lb/>its heterogeneous particles. But in caſe of <lb/>neceſſity, where proper
      water is not to be <lb/>had, any kind of water may be uſed, taking <lb/>care to boil and
      filter it thro' paper which is <lb/>not ſtiffened, till ſome of the beſt water can <lb/>be
       procured<note place="marg" n="*" rend="size(0.7)">* It is adviſeable, that all thoſe, who
       make uſe of <lb/>water in common as their drink, would carefully abſtain <lb/>from all that
       are hard, earthy, and ſelenitous, which, <lb/>are apt to diſorder the ſtomach, and give riſe
       to ſtrong <lb/>concretions in the kidneys and other urinary paſſages, <lb/>eſpecially if they
       meet with any ſlimy matter. The <w part="I">on-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> means of
       preventing this is by diſtillation, which <lb/>will ſeparate, even from the pureſt water,
       ſome <w part="I">hetero-</w><lb/><w part="F">geneous</w> ſubſtances; but this muſt be
       effected in <hi rend="italic">bal-<lb/>neo mariæ,</hi> with alembics either of earth or
       glaſs, <lb/>taking care always to throw away the two or three <lb/>firſt pints, that paſs
       into the receiver, to avoid certain <lb/>heterogeneous and volatile ſubſtances, which riſe by
       <lb/>diſtillation, with the firſt portions of water. You muſt <lb/>likewiſe finiſh your
       operation as ſoon as two thirds of <lb/>your water is diſtilled, becauſe what remains in the
       <lb/>ſtill muſt be impregnated more or leſs with noxious <lb/>particles, which the water
       might imbibe, was you to <lb/>continue your proceſs any longer. The water thus <lb/>diſtilled
       muſt be put into bottles well waſhed and <lb/>rinſed with the above diſtilled water. Theſe
       bottles <lb/>muſt be ſtopped with a glaſs ſtopple. If the water has <lb/>been well diſtilled,
       it will preſerve its limpidity, after <lb/>you have poured into it ſome drops of the ſolution
       of <lb/>mercury by ſpirit of nitre. This experiment muſt be <lb/>made upon a ſmall quantity
       of the diſtilled water. </note>. </p>
     <p rend="indent" n="5"><lb/>V. Nothing is of greater conſequence in <lb/>preſcriptions, than
      the aſcertaining the juſt <lb/>proportion remedies of this kind bear to each <pb
       xml:id="page_17" n="18"/><lb/>other: I think the author has rather neglected <lb/>in regard
      to his. Looking upon it himſelf as <lb/>a topical one only, he has been little anxious
      <lb/>about the quantities uſed in lotions, poultices, <lb/>&amp;c. for common caſes; nor is it
      indeed very <lb/>material, but when particular caſes occur; <lb/>ſuch as inflammations of the
      eyes, ears, throat, <lb/>and of other parts endued with no leſs a <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w
       part="F">gree</w> of ſenſibility. The author ſeems to have <lb/>miſtaken the quantity of
      extract proper for <lb/>the occaſion, ſee page 204. where he ſays, <lb/><q rend="quotes">For
       example, (ſpeaking of the eyes) put at <lb/>firſt ten or twelve drops of it (extract of
       <lb/>Saturn) to a common glaſs of water, and <lb/>increaſe them gradually, as the <w part="I"
        >inflamma-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> is ſeen to diſperſe—<hi rend="italic">and
        after,</hi> againſt <lb/>the defluxions of the tympanum of the ear <lb/>and occaſional
       deafneſs, taking care in theſe <lb/>caſes, to add to the drops of the extract, <lb/>double
       the number of drops of <w part="I">campho-</w><lb/><w part="F">rated</w> brandy, though
       common brandy may <lb/>be uſed, as for opthalmies.</q>
     </p>
     <p rend="indent"><lb/>The indefinite meaſure of a glaſs of water <lb/>gives here an equivocal
      ſenſe. It is always <lb/>improper to preſcribe a remedy by meaſure, <lb/>when it is to be uſed
      with circumſpection. <lb/>Nothing can be aſcertained by <hi rend="italic">a glaſs of
       <lb/>water, a coffee ſpoonfull,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">drops.</hi> Theſe <lb/>meaſures
      contain more or leſs according to the <lb/>different places they are uſed in, and drops may
      <lb/>vary according to the conſiſtence of the <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">tract</w>.
      As all meaſures then vary, and ever <pb xml:id="page_18"/>
     </p>
     <div>
      <head><lb/>ENGLISH and FRENCH WEIGHTS compared. </head>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>
       <lb/>PARIS WEIGHT. Grain.           24 Scrupule.         72 3 Dragme.     576 24 8 Once.    
       4608 192 64 8 Marc.   9216 384 128 16 2 Livre. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>
       <lb/>TROY WEIGHT. Pds. Ounc. Drachs. Scrup. Grs. 0: 0: 0: 0: 0 ⅚ 0: 0: 0: 0: 19⅔ 0: 0: 0: 2:
       19 0: 0: 7: 2: 12½ 0: 7: 7: 0: 0 1: 3: 6: 0: 0 </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>
       <lb/>AVOIRDUPOIS WEIGHT. Pounds. Ounces. Drachms. 0: 0: .03 0: 0: .72 0: 0: 2.16 0: 1: 1.28
       0: 8: 10.24 1: 1: 4.48 </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>
       <lb/>TROY WEIGHT. Grain.         20 Scruple.     60 3 Drachm.   480 24 8 Ounce. 5760 288 64
       12 Pound. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>N. B. The Troy Ounce is alſo frequently divided into twenty
       Penny-weights, each conſiſting of twenty-four grains. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>
       <lb/>AVOIRDUPOIS WEIGHT. Ounces. Drachms. 0: .036 0: .731 0: 2.194 1: 1.554 13: 2.651 </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>
       <lb/>PARIS WEIGHT. Marc. Once. Drs. Scr. Grs. 0: 0: 0: 0: 1<unclear>#</unclear> 0: 0: 0: 1: ⅜
       0: 0: 1: 0: 1 4/7 0: 1: 0: 0: 9 1/7 1: 4: 1: 1: 13⅔ </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>
       <lb/>AVOIRDUPOIS WEIGHT. Drachm.   16 Ounce. 256 16 Pound. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>
       <lb/>TROY WEIGHT. Pounds. Oun. Drach. Scr. Grs. 0: 0: 0: 1: 7⅓ 0: 0: 7: 0: 17½ 1: 2: 4: 2: 0 </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>
       <lb/>PARIS WEIGHT. Marc. Onc. Drs. Scr. Grs. 0: 0: 0: 1: 9⅓ 0: 0: 7: 1: 5⅓ 1: 6: 6: 1: 13⅓ </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>N. B. In the Fractions of Grains I have taken the neareſt that could be
       expreſſed by ſingle <lb/>Figures, in thoſe of Avoirdupois Drachms I have made Uſe of
       Decimals. </p>
     </div>
     <pb xml:id="page_19" n="19"/>
     <div>
      <p>
       <lb/>in the ſame country, care muſt be taken, <lb/>where it is poſſible, to make uſe of
       weights, <lb/>and to reduce foreign ones to thoſe of the <lb/>country we live in. The author
       himſelf has <lb/>followed the weights and meaſures of the <lb/>country he does inhabit; I
       will follow the <lb/>Engliſh one, called <hi rend="italic">Troy,</hi><note place="marg" n="*"
        rend="size(0.7)">* Called in French <hi rend="italic">poids de marc,</hi> or ſilver ſmith's
        <lb/>weight. The ſame is uſed in Paris. </note> as it has more <w part="I">affi-</w><lb/><w
        part="F">nity</w> to the Montpellier weight, being <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F"
        >vided</w> like that into ounces, drachms, ſcruples, <lb/>and grains. The Troy pound indeed,
        <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tains</w> only twelve ounces, and the Montpellier
       <lb/>ſixteen, but in the ounce, there is only a <w part="I">dif-</w><lb/><w part="F"
        >ference</w> of ſeven grains and an half, the <hi rend="italic">Troy</hi>
       <lb/>ounce being ſo much heavier than the <w part="I">Mont-</w><lb/><w part="F">pellier</w>.
       In the drachm, the difference is leſs than <lb/>a grain, in the ſcruple, not a third of one.
       The <lb/>grain differs more in proportion, as the <w part="I">Mont-</w><lb/><w part="F"
        >pellier</w> ſcruple is divided into twenty four <lb/>grains, and the <hi rend="italic"
        >Troy</hi> ſcruple into only twenty; <lb/>but for the ſatisfaction of thoſe, who may be <w
        part="I">cu-</w><lb/><w part="F">rious</w> to know the exact difference between the
       <lb/>Engliſh and Montpellier weights, I have added <lb/>a table, in which is expreſſed the
       value of the <lb/>Montpellier pound, half pound, ounce, drachm, <lb/>and grains, both in <hi
        rend="italic">Troy</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Avoir-du-Pois</hi>
       <lb/>weight, as likewiſe the ſeveral values of theſe <lb/>ſorts of weights, compared with the
        <w part="I">Montpel-</w><lb/><w part="F">lier</w> and with each other; and this I imagine
       <lb/>will be the more welcome, as moſt of the <w part="I">au-</w><lb/><w part="F">thors</w>,
       who treat of the compariſon of Engliſh <pb xml:id="page_20" n="20"/><lb/>and French weights,
       are more likely to miſlead <lb/>than to inform their readers. I cannot help <lb/>remarking
       here, that the origin of different <lb/>weights, aroſe from the ancient cuſtom of <w part="I"
        >re-</w><lb/><w part="F">gulating</w> them by that of a barley corn, which <lb/>ſerved as a
       ſtandard for all the reſt, by <w part="I">mul-</w><lb/><w part="F">tiplying</w> them into
       carats, ſcruples, drachms, <lb/>ounces, pounds, &amp;c; but, as it neceſſarily <w part="I"
        >hap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pened</w>, that the barley corns, made uſe of in <lb/>different
       countries, weighed more or leſs on <lb/>account of their ſize, moiſture, or dryneſs, <lb/>it
       gave riſe to the difference of weights, and <lb/>made it difficult to aſcertain preciſely
       thoſe of <lb/>different countries. It is much to be wiſhed <lb/>that the different powers of
       Europe would <lb/>come to a general regulation of weights, it <lb/>would be a change of much
       greater <w part="I">import-</w><lb/><w part="F">ance</w> to trade than that of the old ſtile,
       which <lb/>all nations have not adopted, though there are <lb/>none who would not find their
       account in <lb/>having a general or univerſal ſtandard for <w part="I">mea-</w><lb/><w
        part="F">ſure</w> and weight. This, which was always <lb/>looked on as an impoſſibility,
       would be the moſt <lb/>eaſy to be executed, without any expence to <lb/>governments, and with
       the eaſieſt one for <lb/>every individual. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>But let us now return to the method of <lb/>preſcribing the extract of
       Saturn, and again <lb/>reſume our ſubject, from which this epiſode <lb/>has ſomewhat hurried
       me. I ſhall then make <lb/>uſe of the weight, generally known by the <lb/>name of <hi
        rend="italic">Troy-weight.</hi> The proper and <w part="I">ge-</w><pb xml:id="page_21"
        n="21"/><lb/><w part="F">nerally</w> preſcribed quantity of extract to a <w part="I"
        >bot-</w><lb/><w part="F">tle</w> of pure water,<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.7)"
        >* This ought to weigh 29 or 30 ounces. </note> is two drachms (five penny <lb/>weight) if
       the extract is well made, which <w part="I">quan-</w><lb/><w part="F">tity</w> will make
       about a hundred and ten drops. <lb/>Now, if we ſuppoſe the bottle ought to weigh
       <lb/>twenty-nine <hi rend="italic">Troy</hi> ounces, and a glaſs of water <lb/>to weigh about
       three ounces, the quantity of <lb/>extract, according to the proportion given by <lb/>Mr.
       Goulard, would exceed, or at leaſt be equal <lb/>to that of the vegeto-mineral water
       preſcribed <lb/>by him for common uſes, when, on the <lb/>contrary, the quantity ought to be
       diminiſhed <lb/>conſiderably. So that I would recommend, <lb/>in inflammations of the eyes,
       to put only two <lb/>drops of the extract to every ounce of water, <lb/>and the ſame
       proportion to be obſerved in all <lb/>caſes, where the ſenſibility of the part is <w part="I"
        >equal-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> delicate, eſpecially ſince Mr. Goulard has <lb/>brought
       his extract to ſo great a degree of <lb/>perfection. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The method of counting the drops is to <lb/>have a cork bored from end
       to end, through <lb/>which paſs a tube about the ſize of a ſmall <lb/>quill commonly called a
       pinion; this quill <lb/>muſt be cut off at both ends, like the obtuſe <lb/>end of a
       tooth-pick; and of the two <w part="I">extremi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ties</w> of the tube thus
       cut, one enters into the <lb/>bottle, and the other remains on the outſide <lb/>of the cork.
       By inclining the bottle <w part="I">down-</w><lb/><w part="F">wards</w> and putting the end
       of the fore-finger <pb xml:id="page_22" n="22"/><lb/>upon the aperture of the tube you may
       let <lb/>the drops fall at pleaſure, one after the other. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Mr. Goulard does not recommend his <w part="I">po-</w><lb/><w part="F"
        >matum</w> in opthalmies, and I think with great <lb/>reaſon; greaſy and oleagenous
       ſubſtances are <lb/>always dangerous in inflammations of the <lb/>eyes, and eriſipelatous
       complaints, though <lb/>they are equally adviſeable for thoſe of the <lb/>ears: he ought to
       have recommended the <lb/>frequent waſhing the eyes, externally with <lb/>the vegeto-mineral
       water, and keeping a <lb/>bolſter conſtantly on them, well wetted with <lb/>that water. This
       I have conſtantly practiſed <lb/>with ſucceſs, but you muſt be careful always <lb/>to add
       ſome brandy, and even that which is <lb/>camphorated. This omiſſion, on the part of <lb/>the
       author in his firſt preſcription, gives an <lb/>air of obſcurity to the laſt part of his
       ſecond <lb/>paragraph, by putting you in mind there of <lb/>the neceſſity of making uſe of
       brandy in the <lb/>ſecond preſcription, as well as in the firſt; a <lb/>circumſtance he has
       entirely omitted. Let it <lb/>be remarked, that camphorated brandy on <lb/>all occaſions is
       to be preferred to the <w part="I">non-</w><lb/><w part="F">camphorated</w>, as I ſhall
       endeavour to prove <lb/>in the following article. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="6"><lb/>VI. It is my opinion, that in the caſes, in which <lb/>the author
       recommends the uſe of camphire, <lb/>one of the moſt antiphlogiſtic, and antiſpaſmodic
       <lb/>medicines in phyſic or ſurgery, he does not <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F"
        >ſcribe</w> it in large quantities enough. Camphire <lb/>is one of thoſe medicines we uſe
       too ſparingly, <pb xml:id="page_23" n="23"/><lb/>not being ſufficiently converſant in its
       effects, <lb/>which are always wonderful, whether made <lb/>uſe of externally or internally.
       I would <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">commend</w> a work of Mr. Pouteau, intitled,
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Melanges de Chirurgie,</hi> which would <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
        part="F">vince</w> any one of the good qualities of this <lb/>drug. I know an Engliſh
       gentleman, who <lb/>not only preſerves himſelf from, but cures <lb/>himſelf of many
       complaints by the uſe of <lb/>camphire, of which he takes inwardly a large <lb/>quantity; and
       always carries about him a box <lb/>of it. When I make uſe of this with the <lb/>extract of
       Saturn, it is in large quantities, <lb/>and with ſome precautions different from thoſe
       <lb/>of Mr. Goulard. If it is given in ſmall <w part="I">quan-</w><lb/><w part="F"
       >tities</w>, it has no effect; when mixed with <w part="I">po-</w><lb/><w part="F"
       >matums</w>, cerates, liniments, it is obliged to <lb/>undergo the heat of fire, by which
       means the <lb/>volatile parts of it are evaporated; what <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
        >mains</w> of them, inſenſibly paſſes away, ſo that <lb/>in a few days none is left.
       Whenever the <lb/>vegeto-mineral water is made uſe of, I would <lb/>recommend the ſame
       quantity of <w part="I">campho-</w><lb/><w part="F">rated</w> brandy, as the author
       preſcribes of that <lb/>which is not camphorated. This <w part="I">campho-</w><lb/><w
        part="F">rated</w> brandy ſhould be kept in a bottle well <lb/>corked; you muſt be careful
       likewiſe to fill <lb/>it up now and then, and ſee that the camphire <lb/>you make uſe of for
       this purpoſe is not too <lb/>airy, but that it is freſh, oily, and of a ſtrong <lb/>perfume. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_24" n="24"/>
      <p rend="indent" n="7"><lb/>VII. Mr. Goulard recommends the <w part="I">vegeto-</w><lb/><w
        part="F">mineral</w> water to be warmed only during the <lb/>winter, and to make uſe of it
       in ſummer in <lb/>its natural ſtate. This diſtinction may be a <lb/>very juſt one at
       Montpellier, and in other <lb/>warm climates; but in England and other <lb/>cold countries it
       is abſolutely neceſſary <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">ways</w> to warm it, otherwiſe
       the metallic <lb/>particles are not ſo thoroughly divided; and <lb/>by the water's being
       impregnated with the <lb/>vegetable parts only the repelling <w part="I">proper-</w><lb/><w
        part="F">ty</w>, with which it is reproach'd, only <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
        >mains</w>; the ſame may be ſaid of all cold <w part="I">wa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ters</w>,
       they act as repellents, by cauſing too <lb/>great a tenſion in the fibres they ought to
       <lb/>relax, and the colder they are the greater is <lb/>their repelling power; but when
       warmed, <lb/>they are of a moiſtening, relaxing, ſoftening <lb/>and reſolving quality. But
       particular care muſt <lb/>be taken not to exceed the doſe above <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w
        part="F">ſcribed</w> in inflammatory caſes; Mr. Coſmond <lb/>a celebrated ſurgeon has well
       obſerved that <lb/>the leaden particles, when introduced into the <lb/>veſſels in too large a
       quantity, irritate and <lb/>force them ſo conſiderably, as frequently to add <lb/>to the
       complaint, inſtead of relieving it. This <lb/>is a fault that many, who are ignorant of the
       <lb/>effects of this remedy, frequently fall into; <lb/>and often blame the medicine, when <w
        part="I">them-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſelves</w> are only in fault. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>In caſes, where the lymph only is affected, <lb/>the ſame precaution is
       not neceſſary, as a <pb xml:id="page_25" n="25"/><lb/>drachm or two of extract more may be
       ſafely <lb/>added to each bottle of water. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="8"><lb/>VIII. Such, as are little verſed in the <w part="I"
        >know-</w><lb/><w part="F">ledge</w> of the medicinal virtues of metals, are <lb/>very apt
       to make coſmetic pomatums with <lb/>the vegeto-mineral water. Theſe have <w part="I"
        >fol-</w><lb/><w part="F">lowed</w> the errors handed down to us by our <lb/>anceſtors, who
       have made uſe of lead under <lb/>various forms; others did uſe ſuch as <w part="I"
        >magiſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">teries</w> of pewter and biſmuth, &amp;c. which have <lb/>rather
       ſerved to deſtroy the beauty of the <lb/>skin, than to preſerve it; the reaſon is evident:
       <lb/>theſe metals, by infinuating themſelves into <lb/>the pores, there depoſe ſome of their
        <w part="I">par-</w><lb/><w part="F">ticles</w> the moſt divided, and by firſt opening,
       <lb/>and then filling up theſe pores ſpoil the fineſt <lb/>features. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe metallic particles become of a black <lb/>dye, and plainly ſhew a
       leaden colour, which <lb/>can be concealed only from the eye, by the <lb/>application of a
       white waſh compoſed of the <lb/>ſame drug, which by plaiſtering over the <w part="I"
        >ſur-</w><lb/><w part="F">face</w> of the skin add to its deformity. The <lb/>author of
       theſe remarks begs leave to caution <lb/>the fair ſex from truſting to theſe pomatums,
       <lb/>the compoſition of which is a ſecret, the <w part="I">bet-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w>
       to conceal the known poiſon they are <lb/>fraught with, which for a ſhort time appears
       <lb/>to anſwer their intentions, only to give the <lb/>deeper wound afterwards. Time only can
       <lb/>re-eſtabliſh nature, and the uſe of the <w part="I">poma-</w><lb/><w part="F">tums</w>
       deſcribed by the author in his Treatiſe <pb xml:id="page_26" n="26"/><lb/>on Ruptures, p.
       138, by leaving out the gold <lb/>and the ſaffron, the firſt making the skin black, <lb/>the
       other yellow. This pomatum, without <lb/>altering the skin, ſoftens, and nouriſhes it,
       <lb/>preſerves its tranſparency, deſtroys tetters and <lb/>redneſs, fills up wrinkles, and
       repairs all <w part="I">da-</w><lb/><w part="F">mages</w> done to it, either by the uſe of
       other <lb/>pomatums or paint. This pomatum is <w part="I">infi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
        >nitely</w> ſuperior to that of Saturn, or the cerate <lb/>for removing the piles, for the
       ſcalding of <lb/>the skin, and to remove the ſpots, which <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
        >main</w> after the ſmall pox, if applied to it ſome <lb/>time after the eruption. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="9"><lb/>IX. I muſt here add, that the pure liquid <lb/>extract of
        Saturn,<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.7)">* It is the liquid extract only, which is
        mentioned in <lb/>this Treatiſe. </note> mixed with double the <lb/>quantity of oil of
       turpentine is the moſt <lb/>ſovereign remedy known againſt a ſprain in <lb/>a horſe, by
       rubbing him with this liniment, <lb/>as ſoon as the accident happens, taking care <lb/>to
       keep the part well covered, till you have <lb/>got him home to the ſtable; if he ſhould ſtill
       <lb/>continue lame, or appear in pain, you muſt <lb/>rub him again, before he grows cold, and
       <lb/>repeat this every four hours, keep him well <lb/>cloathed, and allow him but half his
       uſual <lb/>quantity of food, and give him warm water <lb/>with ſome bran in it to promote
       perſpiration: <lb/>it ſeldom happens, if theſe rules are attended <lb/>to, but that the cure
       is compleated in four-<lb/>and-twenty hours.</p>
     </div>
    </div>
    <div>
     <pb xml:id="page_27" n="27"/>
     <head rend="align-center italic"><lb/><hi rend="roman dc(2)">COPY</hi>
     </head>
     <p rend="indent hanging italic"><lb/>Of the <hi rend="roman">POWER</hi> granted to the <hi
       rend="roman">AUTHOR</hi>
      <lb/>of theſe <hi rend="roman">REMARKS,</hi> to provide the <hi rend="roman">PUB-<lb/>LIC</hi>
      with the original <hi rend="italic">EXTRACT</hi>
      <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">LEAD.</hi>
     </p>
     <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> The under writer, counſellor to the <hi rend="sc"
       >King</hi>, <lb/>and perpetual <hi rend="sc">Mayor</hi> of the town of <lb/><hi rend="sc"
       >Alet</hi>; lecturer and demonſtrator royal in <lb/>ſurgery; demonſtrator royal of anatomy in
      <lb/>the college of phyſicians; fellow of the royal <lb/>academies of ſciences in <hi
       rend="sc">Montpellier, <lb/>Toulouse, Lion, Nancy</hi>; penſioner of <lb/>the <hi rend="sc"
       >King</hi> and of the province of <hi rend="sc"><w part="I">Langue-</w><lb/><w part="F"
        >doc</w></hi> for lithotomy, and late ſurgeon to the <lb/>royal and military hoſpital in <hi
       rend="sc">Montpellier</hi>, <lb/>do hereby certify that, in conſequence of the
      <lb/>friendſhip which has ſubſiſted theſe fifty years <lb/>paſt between Mr. <hi rend="sc"
       >George Arnaud</hi> my <lb/>fellow ſtudent and myſelf, I do paſs my <lb/>word by this
      preſent, and engage myſelf to <lb/>ſupply the ſaid Mr. <hi rend="sc">G. Arnaud</hi>, doctor in
      <lb/>phyſic in the univerſity of <hi rend="sc">Tubinguen</hi>, <w part="I">anci-</w><lb/><w
       part="F">ent</w> member of the royal academy of ſurgery, <lb/>lecturer and profeſſor of
      anatomy in the <w part="I">col-</w><lb/><w part="F">lege</w> of ſurgeons at <hi rend="sc"
       >Paris</hi>, and in <hi rend="sc">London</hi>
      <pb xml:id="page_28" n="28"/><lb/>as one of the corporation of ſurgeons of the <lb/>city, to
      ſupply, I ſay, the ſaid Mr. <hi rend="sc">G. Ar-<lb/>naud</hi> and him only in <hi rend="sc"
       >England</hi> with a ſuf-<lb/>ficient quantity of my extract of ſaturn made <lb/>by myſelf,
      in the beſt manner I am able, in <lb/>order to be diſtributed by him, or thoſe <w part="I"
       >com-</w><lb/><w part="F">miſſioned</w> by him, over all the dominions of <lb/>his <hi
       rend="sc">British Majesty</hi>; promiſing beſides <lb/>to ſupply with the ſame no other in
       <hi rend="sc">England</hi>
      <lb/>as long as he ſhall continue to ſell that I have <lb/>ſent him, or ſhall continue to ſend
      him, to <lb/>confirm which I do put here my hand and <lb/>ſeal, this day being the 2d of
      March, 1770. </p>
     <signed rend="align-right">GOULARD. </signed>
     <trailer rend="align-center"><lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
    </div>
   </div>
  </body>

  <back>
   <div>
    <head><lb/>ERRATUM. </head>
    <p rend="indent"><lb/>Page 23, line 21, after Left, read But whenever, &amp;c. </p>
   </div>
  </back>

 </text>
</TEI>
