<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Cadogan: A dissertation on the gout</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>William Cadogan</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">A DISSERTATION ON THE GOUT, AND ALL CHRONIC DISEASES, JOINTLY
              CONSIDERED, As proceeding from the same Causes; What those Causes are; AND A rational
              and natural Method of Cure proposed. Addressed to all Invalids. </title>
            <edition n="2"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T28054</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T28054"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Dodsley, in Pall-Mall, M.DCC.LXXI. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1771</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="8"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="99"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3309050226</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K033011.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: disease"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_1"/>
        <p rend="align-center"><lb/>A <lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)">DISSERTATION</hi>
          <lb/>ON THE <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">GOUT,</hi>
          <lb/>AND ALL <lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)">CHRONIC DISEASES</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="align-center"><lb/>[Price One Shilling and Six-pence.] </p>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="6"/>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_9"/>
      <head rend="align-center"><lb/>A <lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)">DISSERTATION</hi>
        <lb/>ON THE <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">GOUT, &amp;c.</hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space"><lb/>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>Decorative frame around the letter "H".</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <hi rend="dc(2)">H</hi>OWEVER common it may be <lb/>for men that ſuffer to complain <lb/>of
        the evils of life, as the <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">avoidable</w> lot of humanity;
        would <lb/>they ſtop but for a moment to conſider them <lb/>in the light of reaſon and
        philoſophy, they <lb/>would find little or no foundation for them <lb/>in nature; but that
        every man was the real <lb/>author of all of moſt of his own miſeries. <lb/>Whatever doubts
        may be entertained of moral <lb/>evils, the natural, for the moſt part, ſuch as <lb/>bodily
        infirmity, ſickneſs, and pain; all that <lb/>claſs of complaints which the learned call
        <lb/>chronic diſeaſes, we moſt undoubtedly bring <pb xml:id="page_10" n="12"/><lb/>upon
        ourſelves by our own indulgences, <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceſſes</w> or miſtaken
        habits of life; or by <w part="I">ſuffer-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> our ill-conducted
        paſſions to lead us aſtray <lb/>or diſturb our peace of mind. Whatever <w part="I"
          >no-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w> men have been taught or have received <lb/>of other
        cauſes, ſuch as accidental colds, or <lb/>particularities of conſtitution, this or that
        thing <lb/>diſagreeing or ſurfeiting, &amp;c. theſe are too <w part="I">tri-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">fling</w> to produce diſeaſes that commonly laſt for <lb/>life: there muſt be
        ſomething more ſubſtantial, <lb/>ſomething more conſtant and permanent in <lb/>our daily
        habits, to produce ſuch inveterate <lb/>evils. Though if you read authors or conſult
        <lb/>practitioners, what do you find, but that you <lb/>have taken cold, though you know not
        how, <lb/>or that your complaints are gouty, rheumatic, <lb/>bilious, nervous, &amp;c.?
        words that ſatisfy, <lb/>though they give no kind of idea, and ſeem <lb/>to have gained
        credit and aſſent only by the <lb/>politeneſs of phyſicians, who, while they are <lb/>taking
        their patients money, are too well bred <lb/>to tell them diſagreeable truths, and that it
        is <lb/>by their own faults they are ill. To enquire <lb/>a little further into this matter
        may be well <lb/>worth our trouble; the task ſeems to have <lb/>been left for me, and I will
        perform it moſt <lb/>ſincerely. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_11" n="13"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I have long had it in my mind to write upon <lb/>chronic diſeaſes in
        general, in the hope of <w part="I">giv-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> mankind, what moſt
        aſſuredly they have <lb/>never yet had, a few rational ideas about <lb/>them; thinking that,
        if the true original <lb/>cauſes of them were fully and fairly ſet forth, <lb/>men could not
        be ſo capitally miſtaken to <lb/>impute them, as they do, to the falſe and <w part="I"
          >ima-</w><lb/><w part="F">ginary</w>, and therefore apply falſe and imaginary
        <lb/>remedies; nor think that the general health <lb/>of mankind were to be overſet by every
        trifle, <lb/>and the recovery of it lay hid in a few drops or <lb/>powders of any kind. Did
        they better <w part="I">under-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtand</w> the nature of chronic diſeaſes
        in general, <lb/>and whence they proceed, they could not be <lb/>ſo unreaſonable to think
        they might live as they <lb/>liſt with impunity, expecting repeated remedy <lb/>from art;
        or, did they know any thing of the <lb/>nature of medicine, they would find that,
        <lb/>though fits of pain have been relieved, or <lb/>ſickneſs cured by it for a time, the <w
          part="I">eſtabliſh-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w> of health is a very different thing, <w
          part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">pending</w> upon other powers and principles: <lb/>the
        firſt may be and often is done by medicine, <lb/>the other never. That their opinion of <w
          part="I">me-</w><lb/><w part="F">dicine</w> is vain and ridiculous muſt appear, I
        <lb/>think, very evidently to any one who <w part="I">re-</w><pb xml:id="page_12" n="14"
          /><lb/><w part="F">collects</w> that the art of phyſic has now been <lb/>practiſed, more
        or leſs regularly, above two <lb/>thouſand years; and moſt aſſuredly there is <lb/>not yet
        diſcovered any one certain remedy for <lb/>any diſeaſe. Ought not this to make us
        <lb/>ſuſpect that there is no ſuch thing? How can <lb/>it be, when different degrees of the
        very ſame <lb/>diſeaſe require various means and methods, <lb/>and the ſame thing that in
        one degree would <lb/>relieve, or perhaps cure, in another might kill? <lb/>It is by plan,
        by regimen, and ſucceſſive <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">tention</w>, that diſeaſes
        muſt be cured, when <lb/>they are curable; or relieved and palliated <lb/>when they are not.
        The skilful in medicine, <lb/>and learned in nature, know well that health <lb/>is not to be
        eſtabliſhed by medicine; for its <lb/>effects are but momentary, and the frequent
        <lb/>repetition of it deſtructive to the ſtrongeſt <lb/>frames; that if it is to be
        reſtored, it muſt be <lb/>by gently calling forth the powers of the body <lb/>to act for
        themſelves, introducing gradually a <lb/>little more and more activity, choſen diet, and,
        <lb/>above all, peace of mind, changing intirely <lb/>that courſe of life which firſt
        brought on the <lb/>diſeaſe: medicine co-operating a little. That <lb/>this is the truth,
        all who know any thing of <lb/>nature or art muſt know: and I may ſafely <pb
          xml:id="page_13" n="15"/><lb/>take upon me to ſay, that, though I firmly <lb/>believe
        health may be reſtored in moſt caſes that <lb/>are not abſolutely mortal, I am very ſure
        that <lb/>no invalid was ever made a healthy man by the <lb/>mere power of medicine. If this
        be the caſe, <lb/>how muſt the initiated, according as their <w part="I">hu-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">manity</w> is touched, either laugh at or pity the <lb/>poor fooliſh world,
        ſurrendering at diſcretion to <lb/>the moſt ignorant of quacks, pretending to <w part="I"
          >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">fallible</w> remedies which are not in nature. But <lb/>what is
        ſtill more ridiculous, the patients <w part="I">them-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſelves</w> are
        often ſo aſhamed to own they have <lb/>been deluded, that they favour the cheat, by
        <lb/>pretending to relief which they never felt. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I have collected a few materials for this <lb/>work, which I intend to
        put in order, as ſoon <lb/>as I can find time and induſtry enough to ſet <lb/>about it in
        earneſt; and, if I can finiſh it to <lb/>my own ſatisfaction, perhaps I may ſome time
        <lb/>or other trouble the world with it. At <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſent</w> I
        think myſelf particularly called upon <lb/>to ſay ſomething of the gout, as that diſeaſe
        <lb/>was to make a conſiderable part of my plan; <lb/>and, as I ſee now ſo many, and hear of
        more, <lb/>who are throwing away, not only their money <lb/>very fooliſhly, but, as I verily
        believe, the <pb xml:id="page_14" n="16"/><lb/>future health of their lives alſo, in hopes
        of a <lb/>medical cure for it, to ſhew that ſuch hopes <lb/>are chimerical, and
        contradictory to every idea <lb/>of true philoſophy and common ſenſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I ſhall therefore take a few extracts from <lb/>this general plan,
        ſufficient to ſhew the real <lb/>original cauſes of all chronic diſeaſes; which, <lb/>though
        they have been multiplied without end, <lb/>and numberleſs cauſes been aſſigned them, are
        <lb/>certainly not many, and their firſt cauſes very <lb/>few. I think they may very fairly
        be reduced <lb/>to theſe three: Indolence, Intemperance, and <lb/>Vexation. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>From one or more of theſe three cauſes, I <lb/>have undertaken to prove
        that all or most <lb/>chronic diſeaſes are produced; for different <w part="I"
          >diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">eaſes</w> may have the ſame original cauſe, the <lb/>difference
        proceeding from the various degree <lb/>of ſtrength and vigor in bodies; ſo that what
        <lb/>would be gout in one, in another might be <lb/>rheumatiſm, ſtone, colic, jaundice,
        palſy, &amp;c. <lb/>The gout is manifeſtly, and I think <w part="I">confeſſed-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ly</w>, a diſeaſe of the beſt conſtitution, and may <lb/>therefore fairly ſtand
        as a repreſentative of all <lb/>the reſt: as ſuch I ſhall conſider it for the <pb
          xml:id="page_15" n="17"/><lb/>preſent, and ſpeak of theſe cauſes in their order: <lb/>but
        it may be neceſſary to ſay a word or two of <lb/>the gout itſelf before we enquire into its
        cauſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The gout is ſo common a diſeaſe, that there <lb/>is ſcarcely a man in
        the world, whether he <lb/>has had it or not, but thinks he knows <w part="I"
          >per-</w><lb/><w part="F">fectly</w> what it is. So does a cook-maid think <lb/>ſhe knows
        what fire is as well as Sir Iſaac <lb/>Newton. It may therefore ſeem needleſs at
        <lb/>preſent to trouble ourſelves about a definition, <lb/>to ſay what it is: but I will
        venture to ſay <lb/>what I am perſuaded it is not, though contrary <lb/>to the general
        opinion. It is not hereditary, <lb/>it is not periodical, and it is not incurable. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>If it were hereditary, it would be neceſſarily <lb/>tranſmitted from
        father to ſon, and no man <lb/>whoſe father had it could poſſibly be free <lb/>from it: but
        this is not the caſe, there are <lb/>many inſtances to the contrary: it is therefore
        <lb/>not neceſſarily ſo; but the father's having it <lb/>inclines or diſpoſes the ſon to it.
        This is the <lb/><hi rend="italic">cauſa proegumena</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
          >prædiſponent</hi> of the learned, <lb/>which of itſelf never produced any effect at all;
        <lb/>there muſt be joined the <hi rend="italic">cauſa procatarctica,</hi>
        <lb/>or active efficient cauſe, that is, our own <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >temperance</w> or miſtaken habit of life, to <w part="I">pro-</w><pb xml:id="page_16"
          n="18"/><lb/><w part="F">duce</w> it; and accordingly, as this operates more <lb/>or leſs,
        ſo will the gout be. Our parents <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">doubtedly</w> give us
        conſtitutions ſimilar to their <lb/>own, and, if we live in the ſame manner they <lb/>did,
        we ſhall very probably be troubled with <lb/>the ſame diſeaſes; but this by no means proves
        <lb/>them to be hereditary: it is what we do <w part="I">our-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſelves</w>
        that will either bring them on, or keep <lb/>us free. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>If it were hereditary, it would appear in <lb/>infancy and in women,
        which in general it <lb/>does not. I may be told of ſome women <lb/>who have had it. I
        believe never very young, <lb/>nor till they had contributed to it themſelves; <lb/>for
        women, as well as men, may abuſe a good <lb/>conſtitution. I have heard likewiſe of a boy
        <lb/>or two out of a million that had it, or <w part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F">thing</w>
        like it; but theſe boys had been ſuffered <lb/>to ſip wine very early, and been fed and <w
          part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">dulged</w> every way moſt unwholſomely. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Thoſe, who inſiſt that the gout is hereditary, <lb/>becauſe they think
        they ſee it ſo ſometimes, muſt <lb/>argue very inconcluſively; for if we compute <lb/>the
        number of children who have it not, and <lb/>women who have it not, together with all
        <lb/>thoſe active and temperate men who are free <lb/>from it, though born of gouty parents;
        the <pb xml:id="page_17" n="19"/><lb/>proportion will be found at leaſt a hundred to
        <lb/>one againſt that opinion. And ſurely I have <lb/>a greater right from all theſe
        inſtances to ſay <lb/>that it is not hereditary, than they have from <lb/>a few to contend
        that it is. What is all this, <lb/>but to pronounce a diſeaſe hereditary, and <lb/>prove it
        by ſaying that it is ſometimes ſo, but <lb/>oftener not ſo? Can there be a greater
        abſur-<lb/>dity? </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>No diſeaſes are hereditary but thoſe of taint <lb/>or infection, and
        maleformation; the gout is <lb/>none of theſe, and therefore is not hereditary. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>If the gout be a diſeaſe of indigeſtion, and <lb/>therefore of our own
        acquiring, we muſt <w part="I">rea-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſon</w> very ill, or rather not
        reaſon at all, when <lb/>we ſay it is hereditary; for ſurely no man <lb/>will ſay that
        indigeſtion is hereditary, any more <lb/>than intemperance. There are whole nations <lb/>of
        active people knowing no luxury, who for <lb/>ages have been free from it, but have it now
        <lb/>ſince the Europeans have brought them wine <lb/>and ſpirits. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>If the gout be thought hereditary becauſe <lb/>it is incurable by
        medicine, the ſame may be <lb/>ſaid of every other chronic diſeaſe, none of <pb
          xml:id="page_18" n="20"/><lb/>which ever are cured by it, I mean, ſo as <lb/>not to return
        again. When was there a <lb/>man who, having had one fit of <w part="I">rheuma-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">tiſm</w>, ſtone, colic, &amp;c. however happily <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">lieved</w> by art for a time, had it not again <lb/>and again, or ſomething worſe
        in the place <lb/>of it; till he became a confirmed invalid, and <lb/>died long before his
        time; unleſs ſome very <lb/>remarkable alteration took place in the courſe <lb/>of his life
        to confirm his health? So it is in <lb/>the gout: a man gets a fit of it, and by <w part="I"
          >abſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">tinence</w>, patience, time, and nature, the crude <lb/>acrimony
        producing it is ſubdued and <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">hauſted</w>, and he is
        relieved for that time; <lb/>(he might be ſo much ſooner, and very ſafely <lb/>too, by the
        aſſiſtance of art judiciouſly <w part="I">em-</w><lb/><w part="F">ployed)</w> he recovers
        however, and in a few <lb/>months is taken again. Why? Not from <lb/>any thing inherent in
        his conſtitution, but <lb/>becauſe he returned to his former habit of life <lb/>that
        produced it at firſt, and will for ever <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duce</w> it,
        while the ſtrength of his body laſts. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>The truth is, we breed it at firſt, we renew <lb/>it again and again,
        and bring it on ourſelves <lb/>by our own miſtakes or faults, which we <lb/>would fain
        excuſe by throwing them back <lb/>upon our parents, that our complaints may be <pb
          xml:id="page_19" n="21"/><lb/>more juſtly founded. And as bankrupts, <w part="I"
          >un-</w><lb/><w part="F">done</w> by idleneſs and extravagance, for ever <lb/>plead loſſes
        and misfortunes; ſo do we <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">heritance</w> to exculpate
        ourſelves. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is natural enough for thoſe who believe <lb/>the gout hereditary to
        think it alſo periodical, <lb/>as if ſomething innate and inherent in our <lb/>conſtitutions
        produced it at certain times: but <lb/>this is a great niſtake; for, if it were <w part="I"
          >periodi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cal</w>, it muſt be regularly ſo. The only <w part="I"
          >pe-</w><lb/><w part="F">riodical</w> diſeaſe I know is the intermittent fever,
        <lb/>which, till it be diſturbed by the bark or any <lb/>other febrifuge, is as regular as a
        good clock. <lb/>The returns of the gout are always very <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >certain</w>, according to the quantity or quality <lb/>of accumulated indigeſtion within,
        and the <lb/>ſtrength of our bodies. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I come now to ſhew that the gout is not <lb/>incurable. If by the cure
        of it be meant the <lb/>adminiſtering a pill or a powder, or medicine <lb/>of any kind to do
        it, I fear it is and ever will be <lb/>incurable. It has been long and often <w part="I"
          >at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tempted</w> in vain, from the origin of phyſic to <lb/>this day,
        from the firſt quack to the preſent. <lb/>Indeed there is a moſt glaring abſurdity at
        <lb/>firſt ſight, that muſt ſtop any man of <w part="I">com-</w><pb xml:id="page_20" n="22"
          /><lb/><w part="F">mon</w> ſenſe, who has the leaſt inſight into <lb/>nature, or knowledge
        of the human frame: <lb/>for, if the gout be the neceſſary effect of <w part="I"
          >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">temperance</w>, as I hope to ſhew very evidently <lb/>that it is,
        a medicine to cure it muſt be <lb/>ſomething that will enable a man to bear <lb/>the daily
        intemperance of his future life <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">hurt</w> by the gout or
        any other diſeaſe; <lb/>that is, ſomething given now that will take <lb/>away the effect of
        a future cauſe. As well <lb/>might a medicine be given now to prevent <lb/>a man's breaking
        his leg or his neck ſeven <lb/>years hence. One would think the utmoſt <lb/>that any
        rational man could expect from <w part="I">me-</w><lb/><w part="F">dicine</w> was, that it
        ſhould have power to <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">lieve</w> and remove preſent
        diſorders, leaving <lb/>the body quite free, without pretending to <lb/>inſure it from
        future injuries. Here lies the <lb/>error: men think the gout to be ſomething <lb/>latent in
        the body now, which, once well <lb/>eradicated, would never return; not ſuſpecting <lb/>it
        to be no more than each day's indigeſtion <lb/>accumulated to a certain pitch; that, as long
        <lb/>as the vigor of life laſts, always brings on <lb/>every fit, which once well over, the
        man has <lb/>no more gout, nor ſeeds of gout in him than <lb/>he who never had it; and, if
        he did not breed <lb/>it again, moſt certainly would never have it <pb xml:id="page_21"
          n="23"/><lb/>again. A proof of this is, that the gout has <lb/>been often cured by a milk
        diet, which, as <lb/>long as it laſted, has generally kept the patient <lb/>free. But this
        method of cure I cannot <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">prove</w>, becauſe it relaxes
        and enervates the man, <lb/>and does not ſufficiently ſupport the health <lb/>and vigor of
        his body. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Though I think the gout incurable by <w part="I">me-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >dicine</w>, it is ſo far from being incurable in its <lb/>nature, that I am firmly
        perſuaded it may <lb/>be more eaſily and more perfectly cured than <lb/>almoſt any other
        chronic diſeaſe; and this is <lb/>another ſtrong argument that proves it not
        <lb/>hereditary. My reaſon is, that it is <w part="I">confeſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſedly</w>
        a diſeaſe of the ſtrongeſt and beſt <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtitution</w>
        relieving itſelf by throwing off harſh <lb/>and bad humors from the vitals, and out of the
        <lb/>blood upon the extremities, where they do <lb/>leaſt harm to the powers and principles
        of <lb/>life and health; and as theſe humors can be <lb/>nothing more than the daily
        accumulations of <lb/>indigeſtion, if a man can live without <w part="I">breed-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ing</w> conſtantly this indigeſted acrimony, he <lb/>may moſt undoubtedly live
        free, not only from <lb/>the gout, but every other chronic diſeaſe alſo. <lb/>And that he
        may live ſo, not in a perpetual <pb xml:id="page_22" n="24"/><lb/>ſtate of mortification and
        ſelf-denial, but with <lb/>great eaſe and comfort to himſelf, in the trueſt, <lb/>moſt
        philoſophic luxury, I ſhall endeavour to <lb/>prove, I hope to the ſatisfaction of all <w
          part="I">think-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>, reaſonable men. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I have ſaid, that Indolence, Intemperance,<lb/> and Vexation, are the
        original cauſes of all or <lb/>moſt of our chronic diſeaſes: perhaps a few <w part="I"
          >ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">cidents</w> muſt be excepted, to which the ſtrongeſt <lb/>and
        healthieſt are moſt liable; and the effects <lb/>of fevers not happily ended; and which I
        <lb/>except, to obviate all cavil and diſpute with the <lb/>men of art. I believe, to every
        conſiderate <lb/>man, whoſe eyes have been opened ſo as to <lb/>give him the leaſt inſight
        into nature, the <lb/>truth of this propoſition will be ſo ſelf-evident, <lb/>that he muſt
        inſtantly perceive it; and every <lb/>invalid that will be candid enough to do it, <lb/>may
        fairly trace all his complaints up to one <lb/>or other of theſe cauſes. But it may require
        <lb/>ſome explanation to the generality of men, <lb/>who are ſo ſhort-ſighted as never to
        look back <lb/>or forward far beyond the ken of their noſe, <lb/>and therefore never ſee
        either diſtant cauſes <lb/>or effects; and when they are ſick ſeldom <lb/>enquire more than
        for ſome cold or ſurfeit of <pb xml:id="page_23" n="25"/><lb/>yeſterday, and to ſome ſuch
        trifling cauſe <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F">pute</w> diſeaſes that laſt for life. An
        accidental <lb/>cold or even debauch that happens but ſeldom <lb/>can have no ſuch effect;
        and men otherwiſe <lb/>healthy, living in good habits, ſoon get rid of <lb/>both. It is the
        conſtant courſe of life we lead, <lb/>what we do, or neglect to do, habitually every
        <lb/>day, that if right eſtabliſhes our health, if <lb/>wrong, makes us invalids for life. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Men ignorant of the ways of nature in the <lb/>production and ſupport of
        animals, not <w part="I">know-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> what ſhe requires to preſerve
        them in <lb/>health and vigor to their utmoſt period, have <lb/>conceiv'd very ſtrange and
        moſt aſſuredly very <lb/>falſe ideas of diſeaſes in general, and ſeem to <lb/>think every
        diſeaſe a diſtinct kind of being or <lb/>thing, and that there are medicines oppoſed to
        <lb/>each, that will certainly remove and cure it. <lb/>This makes them ſo ſolicitous to
        know the <lb/>name of their complaint, which once <w part="I">aſcer-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tain'd</w>, they think the remedy not far off. <lb/>Poor men! Is not the gout
        ſufficiently <w part="I">diſtin-</w><lb/><w part="F">guiſhed?</w> But where is the remedy?
        Certainly <lb/>not in the precarious skill of preſcribing <w part="I">doc-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">tors</w>, or the ſecret of ignorant and enterprizing <lb/>quacks. They fancy too
        that there is great <pb xml:id="page_24" n="26"/><lb/>variety of conſtitution, with diſeaſes
          <w part="I">unavoid-</w><lb/><w part="F">ably</w> peculiar to each: that certain times of
        <lb/>life muſt produce many, and that it is <w part="I">impoſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſible</w>
        to grow old without ſickneſs of ſome kind <lb/>or other. There is certainly no foundation in
        <lb/>nature for any of theſe opinions, nor is there <lb/>any real eſſential difference of
        conſtitution, <lb/>but of ſtrong or weak, and this is produced <lb/>more by habit than
        nature. The ſtrong by <lb/>bad habits will become weaker, and by good <lb/>the weak
        ſtronger. But the moſt delicate <lb/>frames may be as healthy as the ſtrongeſt, for <lb/>the
        ſame reaſon that a ſquirrel may be as <lb/>healthy as an elephant. There is no diſeaſe
        <lb/>neceſſarily peculiar to any time of life, <w part="I">how-</w><lb/><w part="F">ever</w>
        the changes into the different ſtages of it <lb/>may affect the valetudinary. And it is <w
          part="I">poſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſible</w> for men to live to great age without any
        <lb/>diſeaſe at all, for many have lived to <w part="I">up-</w><lb/><w part="F">wards</w> of
        an hundred with uninterrupted <lb/>health. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Not from the natural defects of our <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſtitutions</w> therefore, but the abuſe of them, <lb/>proceed all our chronic diſeaſes.
        That is, <lb/>from Indolence, Intemperance, or Vexation. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_25" n="27"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Let us now proceed to enquire what muſt <lb/>be the neceſſary effect of
        one or more of theſe <lb/>cauſes acting daily upon the body; whether <lb/>in the ſtrongeſt
        and moſt vigorous frames it <lb/>muſt not be the gout; in weaker, <w part="I"
          >rheuma-</w><lb/><w part="F">tiſm</w>, colic, ſtone, palſy, &amp;c. or any, or all of
        <lb/>the nervous and hyſterical claſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Firſt, of Indolence, by which I do not mean <lb/>inſenſibility, but an
        inactive habit of life, <w part="I">tak-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> the word in the general
        common ſenſe it <lb/>is now uſed. </p>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Of</hi>
          <hi rend="sc">Indolence</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>T ſeems to have been the deſign of <w part="I"
            >Pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">vidence</w> that all men ſhould labor, every <lb/>one for
          himſelf: that ſome are rich enough <lb/>to purchaſe the labor of others is a mere <w
            part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">cident</w> with regard to individuals, in which the
          <lb/>care of Providence appears to be no otherwiſe <lb/>concerned, than having unequally
          diſtributed <lb/>thoſe powers and abilities by which active and <lb/>fiery ſpirits riſe
          uppermoſt to preſerve the <w part="I">har-</w><lb/><w part="F">mony</w> of ſubordination,
          without which ſociety <pb xml:id="page_26" n="28"/><lb/>could never exiſt. The rich and
          great have <lb/>ſo far forgot this firſt principle of nature, that <lb/>they renounce all
          bodily labor as unworthy <lb/>their condition, and are either too lazy or too
          <lb/>inattentive to ſubſtitute exerciſe inſtead of it: <lb/>thus ſacrificing health to
          indulgence and <w part="I">dig-</w><lb/><w part="F">nity</w>, they do not enjoy thoſe
          advantages their <lb/>ſuperior ſtations and fortunes give them; but <lb/>in happineſs fall
          often below the laboring <lb/>hind. I remember to have ſeen a very <w part="I"
            >inge-</w><lb/><w part="F">nious</w> little book upon the origin of evil, in <lb/>which
          labor is conſidered as a great evil. <lb/>The agreeable author muſt ſurely mean when
          <lb/>it is exceſſive, and urged on to the wearing <lb/>and waſting the body; for in
          general labor is <lb/>the firſt principle of good to mankind, and <lb/>to none more than
          the laborious themſelves. <lb/>Does he mean that it would be better for us <lb/>all, did
          the earth ſpontaneouſly bring forth her <lb/>fruits in ſuch abundance, that we ſhould no
          <lb/>more labor or contend for them than we do <lb/>for the air, and have nothing to do
          but baſk <lb/>in eaſe, and riot in enjoyment? If ſo, I can <lb/>by no means agree with
          him; for ſoon, very <lb/>ſoon, in ſuch a ſtate of things, there would <lb/>not be one
          healthy man upon the earth, and <lb/>the whole race muſt quickly periſh. Indeed, <pb
            xml:id="page_27" n="29"/><lb/>I am afraid, notwithſtanding all our <w part="I"
            >unreaſon-</w><lb/><w part="F">able</w> and unphiloſophical complainings, the
          <lb/>utmoſt wit of man cannot remove the leaſt <lb/>evil out of nature, without taking
          with it all <lb/>the good. But begging pardon for this little <lb/>digreſſion, and to come
          back to my own <w part="I">pur-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſe</w>, I think he had been nearer
          the truth, <lb/>had he put Indolence in its ſtead, which is a <lb/>ſource of great evil.
          Nothing undermines the <lb/>foundation of all our happineſs, the health and <lb/>vigor of
          the body, like it, or lays ſuch a train <lb/>of diſeaſes to come. But I muſt endeavor to
          <lb/>ſhew in what manner. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is upon the minuteſt and almoſt inviſible <lb/>parts of the body,
          our beſt health, ſtrength, <lb/>and ſpirits depend: theſe fine parts, commonly <lb/>called
          capillaries, are little pipes or tubes, the <lb/>extended continuations of the larger
          blood-<lb/>veſſels, through which the fineſt parts of the <lb/>blood muſt conſtantly paſs,
          not only to keep <lb/>theſe very ſmall channels always free and open, <lb/>but alſo that
          the particles of the blood may in <lb/>their paſſage be attenuated, broken, and <w
            part="I">rub-</w><lb/><w part="F">bed</w> into globules perfectly ſmooth and round,
          <lb/>and eaſily diviſible into ſtill leſs and leſs, till <lb/>they eſcape the ſight
          aſſiſted even by the <pb xml:id="page_28" n="30"/><lb/>microſcope; which gives ocular
          demonſtration <lb/>of this moſt amazingly minute circulation. <lb/>I have obſerved myſelf,
          and any curious <w part="I">pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tient</w> man may ſee with a good
          microſcope, <lb/>in the pellucid membrane of any living <w part="I">ani-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">mal</w>, this ſurprizing minuteneſs. He may <w part="I">ſe-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >lect</w> and obſerve one ſingle veſſel, the ſmalleſt <lb/>of thoſe that convey red
          blood, many of which <lb/>would not equal the ſmalleſt hair in ſize, <lb/>through which
          the blood may be ſeen paſſing, <lb/>not like a fluid, but a number of little red <w
            part="I">ſo-</w><lb/><w part="F">lid</w> balls puſhing one another on till they come
          <lb/>to the extremity or ramification of the veſſel <lb/>where it divides into two ſtill
          leſs. There <lb/>the firſt globule, ſtopping a little, and <w part="I">recoil-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ing</w>, is puſhed on again till it divides into two, <lb/>and, loſing its red
          colour, paſſes on in the <lb/>ſmaller pipes fitted only to receive the ſerum; <lb/>which
          undergoes the ſame circulation till it be <lb/>refined into lymph, and this into ſtill
          finer <lb/>fluids; which, being thus prepared, eſcape into <lb/>a ſubtility beyond all
          poſſible obſervation. <lb/>Now the ſtrength of the heart and arteries <lb/>alone, in a
          ſedentary courſe of life, is by no <lb/>means ſufficient to keep up and perpetuate this
          <lb/>motion through theſe capillaries, but requires <lb/>the aſſiſtance and joint force of
          all the muſcles <pb xml:id="page_29" n="31"/><lb/>of the body to act by intervals,
          compreſs the <lb/>veins, propel and accelerate the circulation of <lb/>the whole maſs of
          blood, in order to force <lb/>and clear theſe pipes, and to triturate, cribrate, <lb/>and
          purify the fluid paſſing through, forming <lb/>every particle of it into a perfect
          globule, which <lb/>is the form all the atoms of matter muſt take <lb/>from much
          agitation. Without this <w part="I">extra-</w><lb/><w part="F">ordinary</w> occaſional
          aid, the little veſſels would, <lb/>by their natural elaſticity, cloſe up into fibres,
          <lb/>or be obſtructed by rough angular particles <lb/>ſticking in them, and ſtopping all
          paſſage. <lb/>Numberleſs evils of the chronic kind, <w part="I">eſpe-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cially</w> all nervous diſeaſes, owe their origin to <lb/>this cauſe alone. Accordingly
          we ſee moſt <lb/>of thoſe who have lived for any time in a ſtate <lb/>of indolence, grow
          emaciated and pale by <lb/>the drying up of theſe fine veſſels; or, if they <lb/>happen to
          be of a lax habit, having a good <lb/>appetite, and nothing to vex them, they may <lb/>be
          loaded with fat; but they grow pale withal, <lb/>many of thoſe fine pipes being
          nevertheleſs <lb/>cloſed up; ſo that they appear bloated, and <lb/>their fat unwholſome,
          having much leſs blood <lb/>in their veins than thinner people. Hence <lb/>we may learn
          why theſe languid pale perſons <lb/>upon the leaſt motion become faint and <w part="I"
            >breath-</w><pb xml:id="page_30" n="32"/><lb/>the blood hurrying through the larger
          <lb/>veſſels yet free, and, like a crowd obſtructing <lb/>its own paſſage, cauſing a
          dangerous <w part="I">ſuffoca-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>. Or, if they have not been
          long in this <lb/>ſtate, nor the capillaries quite cloſed, they glow, <lb/>eſpecially
          young women, with a momentary <lb/>red, the fine veſſels being for that time <w part="I"
            >ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">panded</w>. Thus inactivity firſt forms <w part="I"
            >obſtruc-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w> in theſe exquiſitely fine parts, upon which
          <lb/>the health and vigor both of body and mind <lb/>depend entirely, and lays the
          foundation of <lb/>many diſeaſes to come; which other <w part="I">conco-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">mitant</w> circumſtances, ſuch as a violent cold, <lb/>exceſs of any kind,
          infection from without, <lb/>or a particular diſpoſition of the body within, <lb/>make
          often fatal to many in this habit of life; <lb/>and which the induſtrious and active never
          <lb/>feel. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now I would ask any reaſonable perſon, <lb/>capable of conſidering
          this operation of nature <lb/>with the leaſt glimmering of philoſophy, or <lb/>even the
          attention of common ſenſe, and moſt <lb/>aſſuredly it concerns every man to conſider it
          <lb/>well, whether he can conceive it poſſible to <lb/>ſubſtitute any medicine to be
          ſwallowed, that <lb/>ſhall act upon the blood and veſſels like the <pb xml:id="page_31"
            n="33"/><lb/>joint force of all the muſcles of the body, <w part="I">act-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ing</w> and reacting occaſionally in a regular <lb/>courſe of moderate daily
          labor or exerciſe. <lb/>Unleſs this can be done, I will venture to <lb/>pronounce that
          there is no ſuch thing as a <lb/>laſting cure either for the gout, or any other
          <lb/>chronic diſeaſe. Yes, Sir, ſays a common <lb/>practitioner, cordials, volatiles,
          bracers, <w part="I">ſtrength-</w><lb/><w part="F">eners</w>, will do this, will keep up
          an increaſed <lb/>circulation. Poſſibly they may for a few hours, <lb/>by doing miſchief
          for many days: but their <lb/>action ſoon ſubſides, and the ſtimulus ceaſes; <lb/>they
          muſt therefore be repeated and repeated <lb/>for life. Woe be to him that takes them;
          <lb/>and to him that leaves them off, unleſs it be <lb/>done with great judgment. While
          they act, <lb/>they coagulate the juices and corrupt the <lb/>whole maſs of blood; and
          when omitted, the <lb/>patient muſt feel all the languors and horrors <lb/>of a crapulary
          fever after repeated debauch; <lb/>and muſt have recourſe to them again and <lb/>again,
          like a dram-drinker, who cannot bear <lb/>his exiſtence but in a ſtate of intoxication.
          <lb/>No, art can never come up to nature in this <lb/>moſt ſalutary of all her operations. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>But theſe obſtructions from crude particles <lb/>of the blood, and
          this inanition of the <w part="I">capilla-</w><pb xml:id="page_32" n="34"/><lb/><w
            part="F">ries</w>, are not all the evils produced by <w part="I">indo-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">lence</w>. That ſprightly vigor and alacrity of <lb/>health which we feel and
          enjoy in an active <lb/>courſe of life, that zeſt in appetite, and <w part="I"
            >re-</w><lb/><w part="F">freſhment</w> after eating, which ſated luxury <lb/>ſeeks in
          vain from art, is owing wholly to <lb/>new blood made every day from freſh food
          <lb/>prepared and diſtributed by the joint action <lb/>of all the parts of the body. No
          man can <lb/>have theſe delightful ſenſations who lives two <lb/>days with the ſame blood,
          but muſt be <w part="I">lan-</w><lb/><w part="F">guid</w> and ſpiritleſs. To introduce new
          juices <lb/>the old muſt be firſt thrown off, or there will <lb/>be no room, there will be
          too great a plethora <lb/>or fulneſs; the firſt cauſe of diſeaſe in many <lb/>caſes. In a
          ſtate of inactivity the old humors <lb/>paſs off ſo ſlowly, the inſenſible perſpiration
          <lb/>is ſo inconſiderable, that there is no void to be <lb/>filled; conſequently by
          degrees the appetite, <lb/>which is the laſt thing that decays, that is, the <lb/>deſire
          of ſupply, muſt daily diminiſh, and at <lb/>laſt be totally loſt. Here art can do wonders;
          <lb/>it can procure evacuations; we can bleed, <lb/>purge, and vomit; but then, to do any
          good <lb/>by theſe, the caſe muſt be recent, before the <lb/>humors are vitiated by too
          long a ſtay in the <lb/>body, which will be the caſe very ſoon, for <pb xml:id="page_33"
            n="35"/><lb/>they are all in a periſhable ſtate, which makes <lb/>their daily renewal ſo
          eſſentially neceſſary to <lb/>health: but then theſe artificial evacuations <w part="I"
            >diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">charge</w> all alike; the new, the middle, and <lb/>the old
          juices; that is, the chyle, the blood, <lb/>the ſerum, and lymph; and by this <w part="I"
            >indiſcri-</w><lb/><w part="F">minate</w> action make ſtrange confuſion in thoſe
          <lb/>that remain: whereas in nature's courſe there <lb/>is a conſtant regular
          tranſmutation and <w part="I">ſuc-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceſſion</w> from one ſtate to
          another; that is, <lb/>from chyle into blood, and blood into ſerum, <lb/>ſerum into lymph,
          and ſo on, till they are all <lb/>in their turn, like wave impelling wave, <w part="I"
            >ha-</w><lb/><w part="F">ving</w> done their office in various ſhapes, <w part="I"
            >ela-</w><lb/><w part="F">borated</w> and ground to ſuch a minute ſubtility <lb/>and
          fineneſs, that they paſs off in the vapor of <lb/>inſenſible perſpiration. In a ſtate of
          indolence <lb/>they do not paſs off either ſo ſoon or ſo <w part="I">regu-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">larly</w> as they ought, becauſe there is not <w part="I">mo-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tion</w>, nor conſequently heat enough to throw <lb/>off the vapor: they lodge
          in the body too long, <lb/>grow putrid, acrimonious, and hurtful many <lb/>ways, like the
          matter formed in an ulcer, <lb/>which, while it is yet ſweet, is more healing <lb/>than
          any balſam the ſurgeon can apply; but <lb/>when confined, it ſoon becomes corroſive,
          <lb/>and like a cauſtic eats it's way all round in <pb xml:id="page_34" n="36"
          /><lb/>fiſtulas to find vent. This ſhews the virulent <lb/>acrimony of theſe confined and
          ſtagnating <w part="I">hu-</w><lb/><w part="F">mors</w>: hence the breath and
          perſpiration, what <lb/>there is of it occaſionally, of indolent people <lb/>is never
          ſweet; and hence in jails, where theſe <lb/>noxious vapors are collected and condenſed
          <lb/>from crouded wretches languiſhing in <w part="I">indo-</w><lb/><w part="F">lence</w>,
          very malignant and peſtilential fevers <lb/>ariſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Perpetual bliſters have been often thought, <lb/>and ſometimes found,
          to be ſerviceable in <lb/>draining off ſome of theſe ſuperfluous juices <w part="I"
            >be-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w> they are much corrupted, and making, <lb/>by a faint
          reſemblance of nature's action, a <lb/>little more room for new; and it is for this
          <lb/>reaſon they do any good at all, by increaſing <lb/>the general circulation, and
          forcing off a <lb/>few of thoſe humors that had circulated too <lb/>long in the body, and
          were becoming acrid: <lb/>for the quantity they diſcharge is ſo trifling, <lb/>that there
          could be no phyſiology, nor even <lb/>common ſenſe, in ſuppoſing the evacuation to <lb/>be
          the benefit procured. By a vomit or a purge <lb/>the diſcharge is a hundred fold more, but
          the <lb/>good obtained not always ſo great, becauſe <lb/>by theſe the humors are
          indiſcriminately thrown <pb xml:id="page_35" n="37"/><lb/>off, and much more of the new
          than the old. <lb/>Many have uſed frequent bleeding to renew <lb/>their blood, and I have
          known it anſwer very <lb/>well to ſome, eſpecially old people who had <lb/>been long
          accuſtomed to it, whom it preſerved <lb/>to great age: but then it muſt be begun in
          <lb/>time, before the whole maſs of humors be <lb/>vitiated, and continued for life. Is it
          not <lb/>ſtrange that men ſhould ſeek and prefer theſe <lb/>violent artificial methods to
          the ſimple, eaſy, <lb/>pleaſant and conſtant action of nature, and <lb/>chuſe rather to
          take a vomit or a purge than <lb/>a walk, and wear a perpetual bliſter than <lb/>make the
          leaſt uſe of their limbs? </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Thus indolence muſt inevitably lay the <lb/>foundation of general
          diſeaſe, and according <lb/>to the conſtitution and a few concomitant <w part="I"
            >cir-</w><lb/><w part="F">cumſtances</w> will be the kind of the diſeaſe: <lb/>in the
          very beſt it may be gout or rheumatiſm; <lb/>in the weaker habits colic, jaundice, palſy,
          ſtone, <lb/>&amp;c. with all of the hyſterical and <w part="I">hypochondri-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">acal</w> claſs. In vain have ingenious men of <w part="I">read-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ing</w> and ſtudy, mental labor and ſedentary life, <lb/>who are more ſubject
          to diſeaſe in general than <lb/>the gay and thoughtleſs, endeavour'd to obviate <lb/>the
          evil by abſtinence, an excellent means of <pb xml:id="page_36" n="38"/><lb/>remedy in many
          caſes, and which few practiſe <lb/>but true philoſophers, who are not the moſt <lb/>likely
          to want it. But yet even they do not <lb/>find it anſwer, and for the reaſons which I
          <lb/>have juſt given; that we cannot live two days <lb/>in health and ſpirits with the
          ſame blood; there <lb/>muſt be a new daily ſupply of that ethereal <lb/>part of our food
          called up to the brain to <w part="I">ſup-</w><lb/><w part="F">port</w> its own, as well
          as the labor of the whole <lb/>body. By this I mean the moſt elaborated <lb/>refined part
          of all our juices, which conſtantly <lb/>repairs and nouriſhes the ſmalleſt veſſels and
          <lb/>fibres; whether I may be allowed to call it <lb/>animal ſpirits or not, is not
          material. <w part="I">When-</w><lb/><w part="F">ever</w> this æther fails, we muſt
          neceſſarily feel <lb/>languor and laſſitude both of body and mind. <lb/>With this
          difference, that in wearineſs of the <lb/>limbs from much action the lees and coarſer
          <lb/>parts are thrown off alſo, and the firſt meal <lb/>and firſt ſleep ſoon ſupplies the
          defect. In <lb/>mental labor the feculence remains to obſtruct <lb/>all appetite; there is
          no room, and therefore <lb/>no call for ſupply; the whole man ſuffers and <lb/>ſinks. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <pb xml:id="page_37" n="39"/>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Of</hi>
          <hi rend="sc">Intemperance</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> COME now to ſpeak of Intemperance, <lb/>for
          Indolence, blunting all our ſenſations, <lb/>naturally leads us to Intemperance: we
          <lb/>want the whip and ſpur of luxury to excite our <lb/>jaded appetites. There is no
          enduring the <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">petual</w> moping languor of indolence:
          we fly <lb/>to the ſtimulating ſenſualities of the table and <lb/>the bottle, friend
          provokes friend to exceed <lb/>and accumulate one evil upon another; a <w part="I"
            >joy-</w><lb/><w part="F">ous</w> momentary relief is obtained, to be paid <lb/>for
          ſeverely ſoon after: the next morning our <lb/>horrors increaſe, and in this courſe there
          is no <lb/>remedy but repetition. Thus whoever is <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >dolent</w> is intemperate alſo, and partly from <lb/>neceſſity; and the evils
          neceſſarily following <lb/>both theſe cauſes often make the rich and <lb/>great more
          wretched than the poor, and the <lb/>ballance of happineſs is held more equally <w
            part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">tween</w> them; for however other things may <lb/>be
          diſtributed, happineſs like water always <lb/>finds its level among men. I wiſh this <w
            part="I">obſer-</w><lb/><w part="F">vation</w> might cure theſe of their envy, and
          <lb/>teach the others how to enjoy their wealth. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_38" n="40"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Before I return to my ſubject, I fear I muſt <lb/>make an apology for
          what I am going to ſay, <lb/>and hope no one will be offended, when I <w part="I"
            >ven-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w> to ſay that nine in ten of all the chronic
          <lb/>diſeaſes in the world, particularly the gout, o<lb/>we their firſt riſe to
          intemperance. Many a <lb/>good man, who piques himſelf upon being the <lb/>moſt ſober
          regular creature alive, and never <lb/>eats but of one or two plain diſhes, as he
          <lb/>calls them, nor exceeds his pint of wine at any <lb/>meal; keeps good hours, and
          never ſleeps <lb/>above eight or nine, may be ſurprized, if not <lb/>affronted, to have
          his diſeaſes imputed to <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">temperance</w>; which he
          conſiders as a great <lb/>crime. And yet he is often ill, ſick in his <lb/>ſtomach,
          troubled with indigeſtion, and crippled <lb/>by the gout. The caſe is, we judge of <w
            part="I">tem-</w><lb/><w part="F">perance</w> and intemperance from our own <lb/>habits,
          without any juſt idea of either. What <lb/>we are uſed to do, and ſee others do, we
          <lb/>think right, and never go up to nature for our <lb/>knowledge. The beſt way to
          explain what <lb/>I mean by intemperance, may be to inquire <lb/>what is nature's law of
          temperance, and to <lb/>deviate from that muſt be conſidered as <w part="I"
            >intem-</w><lb/><w part="F">perance</w>. And here I muſt beg leave to <w part="I"
            >ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerve</w>, that temperance is a thing of which no <pb
            xml:id="page_39" n="41"/><lb/>Engliſhman has or can have the leaſt idea, if <lb/>he
          judges from his own or his neighbors habits. <lb/>To form ſome notion of it he muſt have
          ſeen <lb/>other countries, particularly Spain, Portugal, or <lb/>Italy, and obſerved how
          men live there. What <lb/>they call temperance, or even tolerable living, <lb/>with us
          would be thought downright ſtarving. <lb/>In this view temperance is local and <w part="I"
            >compa-</w><lb/><w part="F">rative</w>; but what I mean is natural temperance <lb/>not
          depending upon place or cuſtom (for I do <lb/>not mean faſting or abſtinence, which can
          <lb/>never be ſalutary but after repletion) and we <lb/>muſt not judge of it from
          countries where a <lb/>piece of bad bread and an onion with a <lb/>draught of water is
          thought a tolerable meal; <lb/>nor from our own, where beggars live better <lb/>than the
          nobles of ſome countries, and where <lb/>we riot in the choice of plenty native and <w
            part="I">exo-</w><lb/><w part="F">tic</w> every day. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>To come then to my idea of it: I think <lb/>there is an abſolute,
          determined temperance, <lb/>to be meaſured by every man's natural <w part="I"
            >un-</w><lb/><w part="F">provoked</w> appetite, digeſtion and conſumption, <lb/>while he
          continues in a good ſtate of health, <lb/>and right habit of life. As long as a man eats
          <lb/>and drinks no more than his ſtomach calls for, <pb xml:id="page_40" n="42"/><lb/>and
          will bear without the leaſt pain, <w part="I">diſten-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>,
          eructation or uneaſineſs of any kind; <lb/>nor than his body conſumes and throws off to
          <lb/>the laſt grain; he may be ſaid to live in a very <lb/>prudent well-regulated ſtate of
          temperance, <lb/>that will probably preſerve him in health and <lb/>ſpirits to great old
          age. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This is nature's law: and the reverſe of it, <lb/>or indeed any great
          deviation from it, muſt be <lb/>intemperance. When we eat without <w part="I"
            >appe-</w><lb/><w part="F">tite</w>, or urge beyond moderate ſatiety, <w part="I"
            >pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">voked</w> by incentives of any kind: when we <lb/>drink
          without thirſt for the ſake of the liquor. <lb/>Indeed I cannot allow him to be ſtrictly
            <w part="I">tem-</w><lb/><w part="F">perate</w> who drinks any wine or ſtrong liquor at
          <lb/>all, unleſs it be medicinally, or now and then <lb/>for the ſake of ſociety and good
          humor, but <lb/>by no means every day. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now let us compare this ſimple idea of <w part="I">tem-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">perance</w> with the common courſe of moſt men's <lb/>lives, and obſerve their
          progreſs from health to <lb/>ſickneſs: for I fear we ſhall find but very few <lb/>who have
          any pretenſions to real temperance. <lb/>In early youth we are inſenſibly led into <w
            part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">temperance</w> by the indulgence and miſtaken <pb
            xml:id="page_41" n="43"/><lb/>fondneſs of parents and friends wiſhing to make <lb/>us
          happy by anticipation. Having thus <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">hauſted</w> the
          firſt degrees of luxury before we <lb/>come to the dominion of ourſelves, we ſhould
          <lb/>find no pleaſure in our liberty did we not <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >vance</w> in new ſenſations, nor feel ourſelves free <lb/>but as we abuſe it. Thus we
          go on till ſome <lb/>friendly pain or diſeaſe bids, or rather forces, <lb/>us to ſtop. But
          in youth all the parts of our <lb/>bodies are ſtrong and flexible, and bear the <lb/>firſt
          loads of exceſs with leſs hurt, and throw <lb/>them off ſoon by their own natural vigor
          and <lb/>action, or with very little aſſiſtance from <w part="I">arti-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ficial</w> evacuations. As we grow older, either <lb/>by nature in due time, or
          repeated exceſſes <lb/>before our time, the body is leſs able to free <lb/>itſelf, and
          wants more aid from art. The <lb/>man however goes on, taking daily more than <lb/>he
          wants, or can poſſibly get rid of; he feels <lb/>himſelf replete and oppreſſed, and, his
            <w part="I">appe-</w><lb/><w part="F">tite</w> failing, his ſpirits ſink for want of
          freſh <lb/>ſupply. He has recourſe to dainties, ſauces, <lb/>pickles, provocatives of all
          ſorts. Theſe ſoon <lb/>loſe their power; and though he waſhes down <lb/>each mouthful with
          a glaſs of wine, he can <lb/>reliſh nothing. What is to be done? Send <lb/>for a
          phyſician. Doctor, I have loſt my <w part="I">ſto-</w><pb xml:id="page_42" n="44"/><lb/><w
            part="F">mach</w>; pray give me, ſays he, with great <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >nocence</w> and ignorance, ſomething to give me <lb/>an appetite; as if want of
          appetite was a <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">eaſe</w> to be cured by art. In vain
          would the <lb/>phyſician, moved by particular friendſhip to <lb/>the man, or that
          integrity he owes to all men, <lb/>give him the beſt advice in two words, <hi
            rend="italic">quære <lb/>ſudando,</hi> ſeek it by labor. He would be thought <lb/>a man
          void of all knowledge and skill in his <lb/>profeſſion, if he did not immediately, or
          after <lb/>a few evacuations, preſcribe ſtomachics, bitter <lb/>ſpicy infuſions in wine or
          brandy, vitriolic <lb/>elixirs, bark, ſteel, &amp;c. By the uſe of theſe <lb/>things the
          ſtomach, rouſed to a little <w part="I">extra-</w><lb/><w part="F">ordinary</w> action,
          frees itſelf, by diſcharging it's <lb/>crude, auſtere, coagulated contents into the
          <lb/>bowels, to be thence forwarded into the blood. <lb/>The man is freed for a time,
          finds he can eat <lb/>again, and thinks all well. But this is a ſhort-<lb/>liv'd deluſion.
          If he is robuſt, the acrimony <lb/>floating in the blood will be thrown out, and <lb/>a
          fit of gout ſucceeds; if leſs ſo, rheumatiſm <lb/>or colic, &amp;c. as I have already
          ſaid. But let <lb/>us ſuppoſe it to be the gout, which if he bears <lb/>patiently, and
          lives moderately, drinking no <lb/>madeira or brandy to keep it out of his <w part="I"
            >ſto-</w><lb/><w part="F">mach</w>, nature will relieve him in a certain time, <pb
            xml:id="page_43" n="45"/><lb/>and the gouty acrimony concocted and <w part="I"
            >ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">hauſted</w> by the ſymptomatic fever that always <lb/>attends,
          he will recover into health; if aſſiſted <lb/>by judicious, mild, and ſoft medicines, his
          <lb/>pains might be greatly aſſuaged and mitigated, <lb/>and he would recover ſooner. But
          however <lb/>he recovers, it is but for a ſhort time; for he <lb/>returns to his former
          habits, and quickly brings <lb/>on the ſame round of complaints again and <lb/>again, all
          aggravated by each return, and he <lb/>leſs able to bear them; till he becomes a <w
            part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">firmed</w> invalid and cripple for life, which,
          <lb/>with a great deal of uſeleſs medication, and <lb/>a few journies to Bath, he drags
          on, till, in <lb/>ſpite of all the doctors he has conſulted, and <lb/>the infallible quack
          medicines he has taken, <lb/>lamenting that none have been lucky enough <lb/>to hit his
          caſe, he ſinks below opium and <lb/>brandy, and dies long before his time. This <lb/>is
          the courſe I have lived to ſee many take, <lb/>and believe it to be the caſe of more whom
          <lb/>I have never heard of, and which any one <lb/>may obſerve in the circle of his
          acquaintance: <lb/>all this chain of evils is brought on and <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">cumulated</w> by indolence and intemperance, or <lb/>miſtaken choice of diet.
          How eaſily might <pb xml:id="page_44" n="46"/><lb/>they have been remedied, had the real
          cauſes <lb/>been known and attended to in time. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I believe I muſt here explain a little more <lb/>fully what I mean by
          provoking the appetite, <lb/>which I take to be the general mode of <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">temperance</w> among men; for cuſtom has made <lb/>all kinds of
          incentives to exceſs ſo common, <lb/>that thoſe of daily uſe, far from being <w part="I"
            >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſidered</w> in the claſs of intemperance, are by <lb/>moſt
          people thought to be not only ſalutary <lb/>but neceſſary; and they never ſuſpect the
          leaſt <lb/>evil from the common decoraments of the table, <lb/>ſalt, pepper, muſtard,
          vinegar; and yet, however <lb/>extraordinary it may ſeem, I will venture to <lb/>pronounce
          that exceſs in any of theſe muſt be <lb/>doubly prejudicial to health; hurtful in <w
            part="I">them-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſelves</w> by their acrimony, they provoke the
          <lb/>appetite beyond natural ſatiety to receive an <lb/>oppreſſive load, which the ſtomach
          itſelf would <lb/>ſoon feel, were it not artificially ſtimulated to <lb/>diſcharge it into
          the blood by wine and ſtrong <lb/>liquors immediately after. Thus one error <lb/>brings on
          another, and when men have eaten <lb/>too much, they drink too much alſo by a <lb/>kind of
          neceſſity. He will certainly be a <lb/>healthier man, who is very moderate in the uſe <pb
            xml:id="page_45" n="47"/><lb/>of theſe things, than he who exceeds; they <lb/>may he
          ſometimes uſeful as medicines; but <lb/>can never add to the wholſomeneſs of our daily
          <lb/>food. To give ſome weight to what I ſay, <lb/>there are whole nations in the world
          that have <lb/>never known any of them, and are healthy, <lb/>ſtrong, and vigorous. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>If this be true of the common provocatives <lb/>at every poor man's
          board, who is there that <lb/>exceeds not nature's law? who is truly <w part="I"
            >tempe-</w><lb/><w part="F">rate?</w> What ſhall we ſay of that ſtudied, <lb/>labored,
          refined extravagance at the tables of <lb/>the rich, where the culinary arts are puſh'd to
          <lb/>that exceſs, that luxury is become falſe to <w part="I">it-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſelf</w>, and things are valued, not as they are good <lb/>and agreeable to the natural
          and undebauch'd <lb/>appetite; but high, inflammatory, rare, out of <lb/>ſeaſon, and
          coſtly; where, though variety is <lb/>aimed at, every thing has the ſame taſte, and
          <lb/>nothing it's own. I am ſorry and aſhamed, that <lb/>men profeſſing luxury ſhould
          underſtand it ſo <lb/>little, as to think it lies in the diſh or the ſauce <lb/>or
          multitude of either; or that urging beyond <lb/>natural ſatiety can afford any real
          enjoyment. <lb/>But this they do by all the reſearches of culinary <lb/>and medical art,
          introducing all the foreign <pb xml:id="page_46" n="48"/><lb/>aids to luxury, every
          ſtimulating provocative <lb/>that can he found in acids, ſalts, fiery ſpices, <lb/>and
          eſſences of all kinds, to rouſe their nerves <lb/>to a little feeling; not knowing the
          more they <lb/>are chafed and irritated the more callous they <lb/>ſtill grow; and the
          ſame things muſt now be <lb/>more frequently repeated, increaſed in quantity, <lb/>and
          exalted in quality, till they know not <lb/>where to ſtop, and every meal they make
          <lb/>ſerves only to overload and oppreſs the ſtomach, <lb/>to foul and inflame the blood,
          obſtruct and <lb/>choak all the capillary channels, bring on a <lb/>hectic fever of
          irritation, that though it raiſe <lb/>the ſpirits for the evening, leaves behind it all
          <lb/>the horrid ſenſations of inanition and crapula <lb/>the next morning; and but that
          nature is ſo kind <lb/>as to ſtop them in their career with a painful <lb/>fit of gout or
          ſome other illneſs, in which ſhe <lb/>gets a little reſpite, they would ſoon be at the
          <lb/>end of their courſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Men bring all theſe evils upon themſelves, <lb/>either not knowing or
          not attending to two <lb/>things: the one, that pleaſure is a coy coquet, <lb/>and to be
          enjoy'd muſt not always be purſued; <lb/>we muſt ſometimes ſit ſtill, that ſhe may come
          <lb/>and court us in her turn: the other, that <w part="I">plea-</w><pb xml:id="page_47"
            n="49"/><lb/><w part="F">ſure</w> and happineſs are as diſtinct things as riot <lb/>and
          enjoyment: beſides, pleaſure is not <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">finite</w>, and
          our ſenſations are limited: we can <lb/>bear but a certain meaſure, and all urging <w
            part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">yond</w> it, infallibly brings pain in it's ſtead.
          <lb/>Let the men of high experience bear me <w part="I">teſti-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >mony</w>, that this is true of all the luxuries of <lb/>the table, wine, muſic, women,
          and every <lb/>ſenſuality. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Theſe men may tell me, perhaps, that I <lb/>have made a mighty fine
          declamation againſt <lb/>luxury and intemperance; but what is this to <lb/>the purpoſe?
          they deſire not to be told of their <lb/>faults, nor to hear diſagreeable truths which
          <lb/>they know already. Have I no art or ſkill <lb/>to reconcile health and luxury, no
          remedy, <lb/>no rare ſecret to repair and reſtore ſenſation <lb/>and vigor worn to rags?
          No Medea's kettle <lb/>to boil anew? If not, do not deſcribe to us <lb/>a life of
          moderation, temperance, and exerciſe: <lb/>it is not worth having upon theſe terms. I am
          <lb/>aware of the unreaſonable expectations of many, <lb/>that their demands would riſe
          high, ſome of <lb/>them to the impoſſible. At preſent I am only <lb/>ſetting forth the
          cauſes; when I come to <pb xml:id="page_48" n="50"/><lb/>talk of remedy, I will endeavour
          to convince <lb/>them that the artificial helps they expect are <lb/>not in nature, but
          that there are in nature <lb/>ways and means by which many gouty, <lb/>broken
          conſtitutions, that have been deſpaired <lb/>of, might be repaired and reſtored to a very
          <lb/>deſirable degree of health and enjoyment. But <lb/>I muſt firſt ſay a word or two to
          the <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">temperate</w> or miſtaken in the middle claſs
          <lb/>of life. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In England all degrees of men are furniſh'd <lb/>with the means of
          intemperance, and therefore <lb/>it is no wonder that moſt men are intemperate. <lb/>If
          they are leſs ſo in other countries, it is not <lb/>that they have more virtue, but they
          want the <lb/>means: their oppreſſive governments, the <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">carious</w> ſtate of property, and their ſuperſtitious <lb/>religion, keep them
          ſo poor that luxury is not <lb/>in their power. They have however this <w part="I"
            >ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">vantage</w> from their poverty, that they are much <lb/>leſs
          afflicted with chronic diſeaſes than we are. <lb/>I verily believe there are more gouts in
            <w part="I">Eng-</w><lb/><w part="F">land</w>, than in all the reſt of Europe: a proof
          <lb/>that good living is more univerſal. But not to the <lb/>advocates for this good
          living do I wiſh to <w part="I">ad-</w><pb xml:id="page_49" n="51"/><lb/><w part="F"
            >dress</w> myſelf; I fear they will be as incorrigible <lb/>as their ſuperiors in higher
          and more refined <lb/>luxury. But there are ſome not intemperate <lb/>from choice, but
          example, habit, cuſtom, <lb/>miſtake, not knowing their daily diet to be <lb/>unwholſome
          and productive of their diſeaſes. <lb/>To theſe it may be of ſome uſe to have the <w
            part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">wholſome</w> pointed out, and their choice <w part="I"
            >direct-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> to better things. Men of laborious <w part="I"
            >oc-</w><lb/><w part="F">cupations</w>, who work in the open air, can and <lb/>do bear
          great exceſſes and much unwholſome <lb/>diet without much hurt: I never knew a ſick or
          <lb/>gouty gardener that was not a remarkable ſot. <lb/>But men of ſedentary trades and
          buſineſs, <lb/>ſhopkeepers of all kinds, feel much ſooner and <lb/>more heavily the ill
          effects of intemperance or <lb/>miſtaken choice in their meat and drink. Their <lb/>firſt
          care therefore ought to be, not to add the <lb/>diſeaſes of intemperance to thoſe of
          inactivity, <lb/>but proportion what they take as well in <lb/>quantity, as in quality, to
          their conſumption. <lb/>But let us ſee how well they do this. They <lb/>all ſay they live
          upon plain things, and never <lb/>indulge in made diſhes; but they will eat <lb/>heartily
          of a gooſe or duck, with a large <w part="I">quan-</w><lb/><w part="F">tity</w> of ſage,
          onion, pepper and ſalt, a pig <lb/>with ſimilar preparation, and a hare with <pb
            xml:id="page_50" n="52"/><lb/>higher and more compounded ſeaſoning. Do <lb/>they ever
          eat veal without ſtuffing, or even a <lb/>leg of mutton without caper-ſauce? If ever
          <lb/>they eat a ſteak or a chop, if it is ſometimes <lb/>without pepper, I believe it is
          never without <lb/>pickles, the worſt of all poiſons. They are <lb/>ſurprized that ſuch
          meals ſhould riſe on their <lb/>ſtomachs with flatulence, ſour and bitter <w part="I"
            >hic-</w><lb/><w part="F">cups</w> and eructations, which if they did not <lb/>keep them
          down with a ſufficient quantity of <lb/>wine or ſometimes a dram, they would be
          <lb/>troubled with all the time of digeſtion. If this <lb/>method ſucceeds ſo far as to
          quiet their <w part="I">ſto-</w><lb/><w part="F">machs</w> for the preſent, they go on
          with it, <lb/>regardleſs or ignorant of future and diſtant <lb/>conſequences. Thus are
          theſe ſharp, harſh, <lb/>hot and inflammatory things forced out of the <lb/>ſtomach into
          the blood, before it has had time <lb/>to dilute and ſubdue, or reject them, and the
          <lb/>ſuperfluous load they bring along with them. <lb/>And thus is laid the foundation of
          every <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">eaſe</w>, that appears when theſe acrid and
          fiery <lb/>particles are accumulated in the blood to a <lb/>certain degree. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>There are others whoſe pretenſions to plain <lb/>diet may ſeem better
          founded, but who <w part="I">never-</w><pb xml:id="page_51" n="53"/><lb/><w part="F"
            >theleſs</w> eat, and are fond of things <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >wholſome</w>, and very unfit for men of ſedentary <lb/>lives, ſuch as ſalted and ſmoked
          fleſh and fiſh <lb/>of all kinds, hams, tongues, heavy flour <w part="I">pud-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">dings</w>, toaſted cheeſe, &amp;c. all which are of <lb/>ſuch hard and
          indiſſoluble texture, that they <lb/>never diſſolve well in the ſtomach of a <w part="I"
            >plow-</w><lb/><w part="F">man</w>: the ſame ſalt, ſeaſoning, and ſmoke, <lb/>which
          harden and preſerve them from <w part="I">putre-</w><lb/><w part="F">faction</w> before
          they are eaten, keep them from <lb/>diſſolution afterwards, ſo that they never are
          <lb/>digeſted at all; nor is it poſſible any good <lb/>nouriſhment ſhould ever come from
          them: <lb/>the ſalts they contain are indeed melted in the <lb/>inteſtinal juices, and get
          into the blood, <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">ducing</w>, in the beſt
          conſtitutions, thoſe tettery, <lb/>itchy, or ſcaly eruptions, commonly but very
          <lb/>erroneouſly called the ſcurvy, which is quite <lb/>another kind of diſeaſe. To this
          kind of food <lb/>is owing the bad health of country people, <lb/>and their children's
          rickety heads and limbs, <lb/>and big and hard bellies. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Another capital miſtake many people fall <lb/>into, who in other
          reſpects are very moderate <lb/>in their diet, is, that the fleſh-meat they eat <lb/>is
          always over-done; if boiled too much, the <pb xml:id="page_52" n="54"/><lb/>juices are
          loſt; if over-roaſted, fried, or <w part="I">broil-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>, the action
          of the fire, continued too long, <lb/>changes the mild animal fleſh into ſomething <lb/>of
          another quality; the fat is made bitter and <lb/>rancid, which fire will always do by the
            <w part="I">ſweet-</w><lb/><w part="F">eſt</w> oil; and the ſcorched outſide of the
          lean, <lb/>dry and acrimonious: the leſs therefore all <lb/>fleſh-meat undergoes the power
          of fire, the <lb/>milder and wholſomer it is. I do not mean <lb/>by this to recommend the
          cuſtoms of Cannibals <lb/>and Tartars who eat raw fleſh; or beaſts of <lb/>prey, that
          devour animals alive: but it may <lb/>be obſerved, that the firſt are free from our
          <lb/>diſeaſes, and the others amazingly ſtrong and <lb/>vigorous. We may learn this from
          them <lb/>at leaſt, that our meat cannot be the <w part="I">whol-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſomer</w> for being, as ſome call it, thoroughly <lb/>done; and that we ſhould learn to
          like it <lb/>with ſome of its red juices unſpoiled by the <lb/>fire. Upon this principle
          the Engliſh cookery <lb/>is to be preferred to the French, who ſtew <lb/>and roaſt to
          rags; and of Engliſh cookery <lb/>broiling muſt be the beſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This leads me to another obſervation, which <lb/>perhaps none but
          phyſicians, or thoſe who <lb/>have ſtudied well the nature of man and his <lb/>aliments,
          are able to make. It is this: that <pb xml:id="page_53" n="55"/><lb/>man being born to
          devour moſt of the fruits <lb/>and animals of the earth and water, there <lb/>ought to be
          a certain proportion of animal <lb/>and vegetable ſubſtances in his food ; the <w part="I"
            >ani-</w><lb/><w part="F">mal</w> tending ſpontaneouſly to putrefaction, the
          <lb/>vegetable correcting that tendency from <w part="I">go-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>
          too far: thus from the due mixture of <lb/>both qualities reſults that neutral property,
          <lb/>equally diſtant from acid as alkali, that is <lb/>eſſentially neceſſary to produce
          good blood. <lb/>This is ſo manifeſt, that whoever will obſerve <lb/>attentively may ſee,
          whenever either of theſe <lb/>prevails in the body, there is ſo ſtrong a <w part="I"
            >de-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſire</w> and longing for things of the other ſort, <lb/>as well
          as pleaſing ſenſation in the palate and <lb/>ſtomach when they are taken, as plainly <w
            part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">dicate</w> the natural want. Let a man have <lb/>lived
          long upon fleſh-meat wholly, he will <lb/>have a moſt eager appetite for fruit and <w
            part="I">vege-</w><lb/><w part="F">tables</w>; and if kept too long without them,
          <lb/>as is the caſe with thoſe who have lived ſome <lb/>time at ſea, will grow ſick of the
          real ſcurvy; <lb/>but if before they are too far gone they reach <lb/>the land, they will
          eat the firſt common graſs <lb/>they can come at, with more avidity than a <lb/>horſe or
          ox, and be perfectly cured by it. <lb/>In like manner they who have lived long <pb
            xml:id="page_54" n="56"/><lb/>upon vegetables (which regimen is often <w part="I"
            >pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſcribed</w> to invalids, eſpecially in the gout) <lb/>will
          have great craving for fleſh-meat. We <lb/>ought to learn from all this to attend
          diligently <lb/>to the calls of nature, and ballance the <w part="I">mix-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ture</w> with due proportion, not only that our <lb/>vitals may have the leſs
          labor in preparing <lb/>and making our juices fit for nouriſhment, <lb/>but to prevent the
          diſeaſes that are peculiar to <lb/>the predominancy of either. And here I may
          <lb/>obſerve, that the error of moſt men's diet in <lb/>every claſs of life is, that the
          acid, crude and <lb/>auſtere, almoſt always abound; not that they <lb/>do not eat
          fleſh-meat enough, but they ſpoil <lb/>it in the preparation and cookery, changing
          <lb/>its animal nature into ſomething worſe than <lb/>vegetable, taking off intirely all
          its tendency <lb/>to diſſolution and putrefaction by ſalting, <w part="I">ſmok-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ing</w>, pickling, potting, and preſerving things <lb/>that in their own ſimple
          nature would ſoon <lb/>corrupt and diſſolve; but by theſe preparations <lb/>are hardened
          and embalmed to keep for years <lb/>like mummies. The ſame may be ſaid of <lb/>every kind
          of made diſhes; the ſalts, ſpices, <lb/>hot herbs, and acids, with which they are
          <lb/>ſeaſoned and compounded, preſerve and harden <lb/>them to keep for ever: the ſauces
          and gravies <pb xml:id="page_55" n="57"/><lb/>they ſwim in have the ſame effect as ſo much
          <lb/>pickle. The things we feed upon ought all <lb/>to be in a periſhable ſtate, or they
          will never <lb/>furniſh the materials of good blood; and <w part="I">what-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ever</w> is hardened or ſeaſoned ſo as to keep long <lb/>before it be eaten,
          ought not to be eaten at all, <lb/>for it will never diſſolve in the ſtomach. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The nature of moſt chronic diſeaſes, and <lb/>their firſt ſymptom
          heartburn, as it is <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">monly</w> called, plainly ſhew
          the original cauſe <lb/>to be acid crudity prevailing in the juices; <lb/>producing
          coagulations, concretions and <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtructions</w> of
          various kinds; all which are very <lb/>manifeſt in the gout, rheumatiſm, ſtone, and
          <lb/>moſt nervous caſes: the remedies alſo, that <lb/>ſometimes relieve and palliate,
          confirm this; <lb/>ſuch as the volatile alkalies, hartſhorn, ſalt <lb/>ammoniac,
          teſtaceous powders, ſope, &amp;c. <lb/>Many may be ſurprized at this, and ſay it <w
            part="I">can-</w><lb/><w part="F">not</w> be; for, though they have theſe diſeaſes,
          <lb/>they take little or no acids: but there are <lb/>many things they take that are
          aceſcent, that <lb/>is, liable to become acid, eſpecially by the heat <lb/>of the ſtomach.
          This they are not aware <lb/>of; but they are in their nature much more <lb/>prejudicial
          than things already ſour; for, <w part="I">be-</w><pb xml:id="page_56" n="58"/><lb/><w
            part="F">ſides</w> that people take not theſe in any <w part="I">quan-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tity</w>, the aceſcent never become ſour but by <lb/>the act of fermentation,
          which, being raiſed <lb/>in the ſtomach where it ought never to <w part="I"
            >hap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pen</w>, produces ſtrange tumults, wind, vapor, <lb/>gas, that
          is, that fume ariſing from <w part="I">ferment-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> liquors of any
          kind, which has been known <lb/>ſometimes to kill at a ſtroke. It may here be
          <lb/>neceſſary to enumerate ſome of thoſe things <lb/>called aceſcent. Theſe are ſweets of
          every kind, <lb/>puddings, cakes, paſtry, creams, confections, <lb/>&amp;c. and every
          thing made of flour, eſpecially <lb/>fermented; bread in particular, ſo far from <w
            part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> the wholſome thing many imagine, is not
          <lb/>only unwholſome by its aceſcency, but, by <lb/>the ſtrong ferment it contains, it
          forces into <lb/>fermentation every thing capable of it, that <lb/>it meets with in the
            ſtomach<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Whoever requires proof of this, may
            have it by <lb/>the following experiment: Put a common toaſt into <lb/>half a pint of
            water, and let it ſtand ſix or eight hours <lb/>near the fire, ſo as to be kept in the
            heat of the human <lb/>ſtomach, and it will be ſour as vinegar. </note>: the bread of
          <lb/>London I fear is particularly ſo; partly by <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ing</w> robbed of its bran, which in ſome degree <lb/>would ſoften and correct it, but
          chiefly by <lb/>having in it, beſides its uſual ferment, a great <lb/>quantity of ſour
          alum, moſt abſurdly added to <pb xml:id="page_57" n="59"/><lb/>make it unnaturally
            white<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* To be convinced of this, boil a pound
            of common <lb/>London bread in a ſufficient quantity of water to make <lb/>it thick as
            gruel. Let it ſtand to ſubſide; pour off the <lb/>clear, and boil away all the water;
            the alum will be <lb/>found at bottom. </note> In this light we <lb/>muſt alſo conſider
          moſt ſorts of ſeaſonings, <lb/>ſtuffings, force-meats, and compounded ſauces. <lb/>But the
          greateſt aceſcent, or rather bane of all, <lb/>high and low, rich or otherwiſe, whoever
          <lb/>they are that take it conſtantly, is wine: wine <lb/>alone produces more diſeaſes
          than all the other <lb/>cauſes put together. All men allow that wine <lb/>taken to exceſs
          is hurtful: they ſee the <w part="I">imme-</w><lb/><w part="F">diate</w> evils that
          follow; but diſtant effects, that <lb/>require more attentive and deducive <w part="I"
            >obſerva-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, very few ſee or believe; and, judging from
          <lb/>preſent and agreeable feelings, they ſay that a <w part="I">lit-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tle</w> wine is wholeſome, and good for every one, <lb/>and accordingly take it every
          day, give it their <lb/>children, and teach them to like it by <w part="I"
            >debauch-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> their natural taſte in the earlieſt infancy:
          <lb/>thus they come to reliſh it by habit, and to be <lb/>uneaſy without it, like
          ſnuff-takers without <lb/>their tobacco; the want is equally habitual <lb/>and unnatural
          in both caſes; for the ſtomach <lb/>wants wine no more than the noſe does ſnuff: <lb/>the
          immediate ſenſation of both, after a little <pb xml:id="page_58" n="60"/><lb/>uſe, is
          pleaſant; but the remote effect of the <lb/>wine taken conſtantly infinitely more <w
            part="I">pernici-</w><lb/><w part="F">ous</w> than of the ſnuff. This hurts the noſe
          <lb/>only; the other accumulating a little <w part="I">indi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >geſtion</w> every day, corrupts all the juices of the <lb/>body moſt eſſentially. And
          though it be often <lb/>taken with a view to promote digeſtion and <lb/>aſſiſt the
          operations of the ſtomach, it <w part="I">manifeſt-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> does harm
          to both. Inſtead of digeſting <lb/>and diſſolving, it hardens, and prevents <w part="I"
            >diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſolution</w>, and curdles and corrupts the milky <lb/>chyle
          and firſt juices produced from our food. <lb/>It warms indeed and ſtimulates the ſtomach
          to <lb/>greater exertion than is natural or neceſſary, and <lb/>thereby enables it to
          diſcharge it's contents the <lb/>ſooner; whence that agreeable feel of warmth <lb/>and
          comfort from it's immediate action. But <lb/>by this extraordinary action it forces our
          food <lb/>out of the ſtomach too ſoon, before it is <w part="I">ſoften-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ed</w>, diſſolved, and properly prepared, and <lb/>ſends it into the bowels
          crude, hard, and <w part="I">au-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtere</w>, in that ſtate to be
          carried into the blood, <lb/>there to produce every kind of diſeaſe. <w part="I"
            >What-</w><lb/><w part="F">ever</w> therefore the advocates for a little wine <lb/>every
          day may think, or argue in favor of it; <lb/>they are moſt undoubtedly in a very great
          error, <lb/>and it were certainly much better and ſafer to <pb xml:id="page_59" n="61"
          /><lb/>drink a bottle and get a little merry once a <lb/>week, drinking water only or
          ſmall beer at all <lb/>other times: in which interval nature might <lb/>totally ſubdue it,
          and recover intirely. Water <lb/>is the only liquor nature knows of or has <w part="I"
            >pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">vided</w> for all animals; and whatever nature <lb/>gives us,
          we may depend upon if, is ſafeſt and <lb/>beſt for us. Accordingly we ſee that when
          <lb/>we have committed any exceſſes or miſtakes of <lb/>any kind, and ſuffer from them, it
          is water <lb/>that relieves. Hence the chief good of Bath, <lb/>Spa, and many other
          medicinal waters, <w part="I">eſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">pecially</w> to hard drinkers. It is
          the element <lb/>that dilutes and carries off crudities and <w part="I">indi-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">geſtions</w>, &amp;c. the mineral virtues they <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tain</w> may make them tolerable to the ſtomach <lb/>in their paſſage, but do,
          as I believe, little <lb/>more in the body: it is the water that cures. <lb/>Wine, if it
          be not one of our own inventions, <lb/>was given us as a cordial in ſickneſs, wearineſs,
          <lb/>ſorrow, and old age, and a moſt ſalutary <lb/>charm it would be for moſt of theſe
          evils, did <lb/>we not exhauſt it's power by daily uſe, and <lb/>inſtead of taking it as
          ſuch, drink it up as <lb/>common draught in youth and health to make <lb/>us mad. I know
          this is a very tender topic to <lb/>touch upon, and too favorite a pleaſure to <pb
            xml:id="page_60" n="62"/><lb/>argue againſt, with any reaſonable hope of
          <lb/>convincing; moſt men having ſo indulged <lb/>themſelves in this bewitching habit,
          that they <lb/>think they cannot live without a little wine <lb/>every day, and their very
          exiſtence depends <lb/>upon it; their ſtomachs require it, nature calls <lb/>for it, St.
          Paul adviſes it, it muſt be good. <lb/>Thus men catch at every ſhadow of an <w part="I"
            >argu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w> that favors their inclinations. St. Paul
          <lb/>adviſes it as a medicine ſometimes, but <w part="I">certain-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ly</w> not every day. There is no medicine I <lb/>know of, that, taken every day, will
          not <lb/>either ceaſe to act entirely, or by acting too <lb/>much do harm. It will be
          ſaid, that many <lb/>drink wine every day without gout, ſtone, or <lb/>any diſeaſe at all
          in conſequence of it. I <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">lieve</w> not many, or I
          ſhould know ſome of <lb/>them. If any are ſo ſtrong as to bear it to old <lb/>age unhurt,
          they muſt be very active as well as <lb/>ſtrong to ſubdue it. But I have nothing to ſay
          <lb/>to theſe; my buſineſs is with invalids who <lb/>complain, and certainly ought not to
          meaſure <lb/>conſtitutions with thoſe above their match. <lb/>The ſame arguments will hold
          equally in favor <lb/>of every other bad habit. Your noſe will <lb/>want it's ſnuff, your
          palate it's ſpices; and <lb/>when the faſhion was for women to be ſmall <pb
            xml:id="page_61" n="63"/><lb/>waiſted, their galled ſides grown callous by <lb/>the long
          compreſſion of the ſtays wanted their <lb/>ſupport. Nature, like a true female, cries
          <lb/>out at the firſt violence, but ſubmits in time, <lb/>is reconciled, and grows fond of
          the raviſher. <lb/>But it is the buſineſs of philoſophers to <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tinguiſh</w> carefully between the real wants of <lb/>nature and the artificial
          calls of habit; and <lb/>when we find theſe begin to hurt us, we ought <lb/>to make the
          utmoſt perſevering efforts to <lb/>break the enchantment of bad cuſtoms; and <lb/>though
          it coſt us ſome uneaſy ſenſations <lb/>at firſt, we muſt bear them patiently; they
          <lb/>will not kill; and a very little time will <w part="I">recon-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cile</w> us to better modes of life. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>There is another capital miſtake many labor <lb/>under in the choice
          of their wine, preferring <lb/>the ſtrong, hot, and coarſe ſorts, Madeira, <lb/>Port,
          Mountain, &amp;c. to the milder, more <lb/>elegant, and certainly leſs unwholſome French
          <lb/>and Italian wines, accounting them better for <lb/>the ſtomach, and good againſt
          wind, &amp;c. My <lb/>obſervation has been, that they who uſe theſe <lb/>ſtrong ſtomach
          wines to cure wind are never <lb/>free from it, and all the gouty diſorders of <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">digeſtion</w>. Indeed, it cannot well be <w part="I"
            >other-</w><pb xml:id="page_62" n="64"/><lb/><w part="F">wiſe</w>; for there is nothing
          ſo repugnant to <lb/>natural digeſtion as the uſe of theſe ſtrong <lb/>liquors, which
          inſtead of diſſolving harden <lb/>every thing; and thus for ever, when the firſt
          <lb/>warmth is gone off, leave a crapulary, crude, <lb/>ſour load of yeſterday to ferment,
          fret, and <lb/>irritate the ſtomach and bowels every day. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Thus have I endeavor'd to point out two of <lb/>the true, primary,
          capital cauſes of the gout, <lb/>and moſt other chronic diſeaſes; and moſt <lb/>ſincerely
          wiſh that what I have ſaid may <w part="I">en-</w><lb/><w part="F">gage</w> thoſe whom it
          moſtly concerns, the gouty, <lb/>the infirm and valetudinary of every claſs, to
          <lb/>obſerve, reflect, and think for themſelves upon <lb/>the hints I have thrown out; in
          which light <lb/>what I have ſaid, muſt be conſidered, rather <lb/>than as logical or
          demonſtrative proof. I <lb/>know the reaſoning and arguments may be <lb/>much improved and
          carried farther, and if I <lb/>had more leiſure I might have attempted it: <lb/>but I am
          well aware of the unſurmountable <lb/>difficulty of convincing men againſt their will
          <lb/>by any arguments at all. I chuſe therefore at <lb/>preſent to invite them to
          ſelf-conviction from <lb/>their own obſervations and experience. I flatter <lb/>myſelf
          they will find it well worth their pains, <pb xml:id="page_63" n="65"/><lb/>to reaſon a
          little more than they do with and <lb/>for themſelves; and it will be a great point
          <lb/>gained for them, if it turn their miſled opinions <lb/>from all that imaginary power
          of reſtoring <lb/>health in any of that multitude of ridiculous <lb/>and moſt truly
          contemptible medicines, that <lb/>are daily obtruded upon the public, with <w part="I"
            >end-</w><lb/><w part="F">less</w> lies to recommend them, by a ſet of the <lb/>pooreſt,
          moſt ignorant and paultry rogues in <lb/>the nation; and engage their attention to their
          <lb/>true remedy, a right inſtitution of life. In <lb/>judging of which, if they find
          themſelves <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">equal</w> to the task, they may be aſſiſted
          by <lb/>men of humanity, skill, and honeſty. </p>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="34"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
