<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Johnson: An account of some societies at Amsterdam and Hamburgh for
          the recovery of drowned personss</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Alexander Johnson</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">An account of some societies at Amsterdam and Hamburgh for the
              recovery of drowned persons, and of similar institutions at Venice, Milan, Padua,
              Vienna, and Psaris; with a collection of authentic cases, proving the practicability
              of extending the benefits of their practice to the recovery of persons visibly dead by
              sudden stoppages of breath, suffocation, stifling, swooning, convulsions, and other
              accidents. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T120895</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T120895"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: sold by John Nourse, in the Strand; S. Leacroft, at
                  Charing-Cross; J. Robson, in New Bond-Street; L. Davis, in Holbourn; J. Wilkie, in
                  St. Paul's Church-Yard; and Richardson and Urquhart, under the Royal-Exchange,
                  MDCCLXXIII.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1773</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="140"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="2"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW104637078</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: method"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="4"/>
      <pb n="3"/>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>Four horizontal lines, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <head rend="align-center space">
        <lb/>A <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">SHORT ACCOUNT </hi>
        <lb/>OF A <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">SOCIETY </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(0.5)">FOR THE </hi>
        <lb/>Recovery of <hi rend="sc">Drowned Persons</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="size(0.5)">AND FOR </hi>
      </head>
      <head rend="hanging">
        <lb/>Such as are Suffocated by <hi rend="sc">Damps</hi> in <lb/><hi rend="sc">Mines</hi>, or
        ſeemingly deprived of <lb/>Life, by <hi rend="sc">Stifling</hi>, <hi rend="sc"
          >Strangling</hi>, <lb/>and other Accidents. </head>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A long horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">O</hi>F the various Inſtitutions formed <lb/>for the Welfare of
        Mankind, none <lb/>appear more worthy of attention, than <lb/>thoſe that are calculated for
        Preſerving <lb/>the Human Species. In the year 1767 a <lb/>few wealthy Gentlemen of the City
        of <pb n="4"/>
        <lb/>Amſterdam, ſtruck with the variety of <lb/>inſtances in which perſons falling into the
        <lb/>water were loſt for want of proper <lb/>treatment, when brought on ſhore, <lb/>formed
        themſelves into a Society <hi rend="italic">for <lb/>the Recovery of Drowned Perſons</hi>.
        Theſe <lb/>Gentlemen have purſued their deſign <lb/>with ſo much zeal and ſucceſs, that in
        <lb/>the ſpace of four years they had the <lb/>ſatisfaction to find, that in not leſs than
        <lb/>a Hundred and Fifty caſes, drowned per- <lb/>ſons were recovered by the means pointed
        <lb/>out by them and recommended in the <lb/>United Provinces by advertiſements and
        <lb/>other publications. Their Firſt Object <lb/>was, to inform the common people, as
        <lb/>well as the inferior practiſers of phyſic, <lb/>in what manner to treat a perſon appa-
        <lb/>rently lifeleſs: and their Second, was to <lb/>animate them by proper rewards to pur-
        <lb/>ſue the methods recommended. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the Inſtructions publiſhed upon <lb/>that occaſion, they gave caution, in the <pb
          n="5"/>
        <lb/>firſt place, to forbear from practices very <lb/>common in moſt countries; ſuch as
        rolling <lb/>the body over a caſk; tying it up by <lb/>the legs, with the head downwards;
        and <lb/>all other rough uſage, intended to diſ- <lb/>gorge water, vulgarly imagined to be
        <lb/>ſwallowed by the drowned perſon. And <lb/>they directed, firſt, to force air into the
        <lb/>body, either at the mouth, or up the <lb/>inteſtines; recommending the ſtimulating
        <lb/>vapour of tobacco as more efficacious than <lb/>common air: and, in the next place, to
        <lb/>ſtrip off the wet clothes; and as ſoon <lb/>as poſſible, to apply external heat to the
        <lb/>body, by means of fire, of friction with <lb/>flannel cloths, or the natural warmth of
        <lb/>two perſons in bed, taking the body be- <lb/>tween them. They directed rubbing the
        <lb/>body all over, eſpecially along the back <lb/>bone, with woollen cloths wetted with
        <lb/>brandy, and ſtrewed over with dry ſalt; <lb/>and the chaffing the temples with a
        volatile <lb/>ſpirit, and holding the ſame to the noſe. </p>
      <pb n="6"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Rewards publiſhed by them for <lb/>attempting the recovery of a drowned
        <lb/>perſon, were the ſum of Six Ducats, or a <lb/>Gold Medal, over and above all expences
        <lb/>attending the ſame, not exceeding Four <lb/>Ducats. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The great ſucceſs of this undertaking, <lb/>and the advantages accruing from it to the
        <lb/>State, has induced each of the ſeveral <lb/>Provinces of the Republic of the Low
        <lb/>Countries to take proper meaſures for <lb/>extending the benefits of it, by enjoining
        <lb/>an obſervance of the Society's directions <lb/>through their reſpective diſtricts. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſalutary effects of this inſtitution <lb/>are now no longer confined to the United
          <lb/>Provinces—<hi rend="italic">The Boards of Health</hi> at Ve- <lb/>nice, at Milan and
        Padua, have adopted <lb/>it—The City of Hamburgh has done the <lb/>ſame—The Empreſs of
        Ruſſia has coun- <lb/>tenanced it in her dominions—The Em- <lb/>preſs Queen of Hungary has
        given very <lb/>particular encouragement to it—And in <pb n="7"/>
        <lb/>France it is at this time under conſidera- <lb/>tion, by what means it may beſt be
        united <lb/>with the general police of the king- <lb/>dom. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is a matter worthy of obſervation, that <lb/>whatever diſcoveries had been made by
        <lb/>the Faculty, of the method of recovering <lb/>Drowned Perſons, prior to the year 1767,
        <lb/>yet till that Period, hardly any other at- <lb/>tempts appear to have been made, but
        ſuch <lb/>as were ſuggeſted, at a time of confuſion <lb/>and diſtreſs, by ignorant people
        who for the <lb/>moſt part are greatly miſled by the un- <lb/>happy prejudices prevailing in
        this mat- <lb/>ter. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The world has been undoubtedly much <lb/>indebted to Dr. <hi rend="italic">Mead</hi>,
        Dr. <hi rend="italic">Winſlow</hi> and <lb/>his Commentator Dr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Bruhier</hi>, Dr. <hi rend="italic">Fother- <lb/>gill</hi>, Dr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Haller</hi>, Dr. <hi rend="italic">Lecat</hi>, Dr. <hi rend="italic">Tiſſot</hi>,
        <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Van Engelen</hi>, Dr. <hi rend="italic">Gummer</hi>, and others,
        <lb/>for very uſeful Obſervations and Eſſays <lb/>upon this ſubject. </p>
      <pb n="8"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſeveral Caſes publiſhed and de- <lb/>ſcribed in the Memoirs of the Dutch
        <lb/>Society, ſufficiently prove the advantages <lb/>ariſing from an obſervance of the Rules
        of <lb/>that Inſtitution. It appears from thoſe <lb/>Caſes, that perſons of all ages, from
        two <lb/>years old to ſeventy-two, have been re- <lb/>covered, though apparently dead when
        <lb/>brought on ſhore; that many perſons <lb/>have been reſtored, who have been im-
        <lb/>merſed from fifteen minutes to an hour and <lb/>a half; and in ſuch inſtances as
        nothing <lb/>leſs than the moſt indiſputable teſtimony <lb/>would render credible. It is
        found by ex- <lb/>perience, that relief may be given, not only <lb/>in drowning, where it
        has been uſual to <lb/>deſpair of it; but in other caſes, ſuch <lb/>as Suffocation by
        Sulphurous Vapours <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* By an order of the Queen of Hungary, perſons ſuffo- <lb/>cated by Damps in her
            Mines, are treated in a particular <lb/><unclear>manner</unclear>, according to
            Inſtructions, and have been recovered. </p>
        </note>; in <lb/>caſes of Strangling, Stifling, and in many <lb/>apparent deaths by Cold,
        Hunger, and <lb/>other cauſes. </p>
      <pb n="9"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From what has been already ſaid, it is <lb/>much to be wiſhed, that ſome means may
        <lb/>be found of giving the benefit of this va- <lb/>luable Inſtitution to Great Britain and
        its <lb/>Colonies. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If the number of accidents is propor- <lb/>tioned to the number of perſons employed
        <lb/>on the water, this kingdom is more in- <lb/>tereſted than any other nation, in the art
        <lb/>of reſtoring drowned perſons. The <lb/>large coal-mines in Great Britain, where
        <lb/>numbers of men are yearly deſtroyed by <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">damps</hi>, which are
        ſo commonly fatal to <lb/>the miners, and the frequent inſtances of <lb/>perſons who come to
        an untimely end, by <lb/>ſtrangling, and other caſualties, render the <lb/>art of reſtoring
        ſuffocated and ſtrangled <lb/>perſons to life, of great conſequence to the <lb/>community. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The author of this account flatters him- <lb/>ſelf that the ſubject of it is worthy of
        <lb/>attention, and ſhall think himſelf happy <lb/>if his deſign of promoting an Inſtitution
          <pb n="10"/>
        <lb/>in Great Britain, with ſome Improvement <lb/>upon thoſe adopted in the neighbouring
        <lb/>nations, in order to which he has already <lb/>taken ſome ſteps, ſhall meet with
        general <lb/>countenance and approbation. </p>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <p rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>The following Caſes are ſelected from the <lb/>Society's Account of the Succeſs of its
        un- <lb/>dertaking, and plainly demonſtrate the <lb/>truth of the foregoing Remarks, and
        <lb/>afford the moſt ſatisfactory evidence that <lb/>all the Ends propoſed by the
        Inſtitution <lb/>have been obtained, except indeed what <lb/>appears by the Caſes
        themſelves, that the <lb/>Society's Inſtructions have been too often <lb/>neglected. </p>
      <p rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/>In all theſe Caſes the Premium offered by the <lb/>Society has been obtained, previous
        to <lb/>which proof muſt be made that the Patient <lb/>had no ſign of life when brought on
        ſhore; <lb/>and the utmoſt care is always taken to <lb/>ſecure a true and faithful account
        of the <pb n="11"/>
        <lb/>circumſtances of each. Many of them <lb/>appear to have been drawn up by illiterate
        <lb/>perſons; therefore ſuch idle circumſtances <lb/>as are nothing to the purpoſe are left
        out <lb/>of this Tranſlation. </p>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE I. </head>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>T <hi rend="italic">Amſterdam</hi>, on the 17th of Sep-
          <lb/>tember, 1767, an old Woman was <lb/>taken out of the <hi rend="italic">Rakin</hi>, a
          deep Canal, in <lb/>which ſhe had lain ſunk a conſiderable time; <lb/>and being ſuppoſed
          dead, was to be car- <lb/>ried away to an Hoſpital for burial: but <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Sybrand Yſerman</hi>, a Skipper of Gouda, <lb/>who had read the Society's
          Advertiſement, <lb/>believing that Tobacco-ſmoke might re- <lb/>cover her, made the trial
          with a lighted <lb/>pipe he had in his mouth: he put it up <lb/>her <hi rend="italic"
            >anus</hi>, and taking the bowl in his <lb/>mouth, blew up the ſmoke of it, and of
          <lb/>another pipe after it, which by degees ſo <lb/>far recovered her, that ſhe was able
          ſoon <lb/>after to be carried home. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="12"/>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE II. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Groningen</hi>, on the 29th of Fe- <lb/>bruary, 1768, the
          daughter of <hi rend="italic">Henry Pie- <lb/>terſz</hi>, a Child of about two years old,
          fell <lb/>head foremoſt into a waſhing-tub, and <lb/>remained ſome time in it
          undiſcovered. <lb/>Its Father having found and taken it <lb/>out, endeavoured to recover
          it by various <lb/>means for the ſpace of half an hour, at <lb/>the end of which time it
          gave ſome <lb/>very faint ſigns of life, and then with- <lb/>out any ſenſible motion in
          its pulſe, <lb/>fell into a ſtrong Convulſion fit. But <lb/>upon continuing the Injection
          of To- <lb/>bacco-ſmoke into its inteſtines, and chaf- <lb/>fing its temples with <hi
            rend="italic">Balſam Vitæ</hi>, and <lb/>holding the ſame to its noſe, it recovered
          <lb/>ſurpriſingly, and in ſo ſhort a ſpace as <lb/>two hours. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE III. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Rotterdam</hi>, on the 11th of February, <lb/>1768, the Wife of
            <hi rend="italic">Arnold Van Deyl</hi>, a <pb n="13"/>
          <lb/>houſe-painter, got up unperceived and <lb/>went out of the houſe in the night
          <lb/>time, and three ſeveral times threw her- <lb/>ſelf into a Canal. She was twice taken
          <lb/>out before ſhe could ſink, and appear- <lb/>ing ſenſible, was left to go home. She
          <lb/>afterwards plunged herſelf a third time, <lb/>ſunk, and remained three quarters of an
          <lb/>hour under water. When ſhe was found <lb/>again, ſhe was taken out, and treated
          <lb/>by <hi rend="italic">Cornelius Maaſwinkel</hi>, a Surgeon, who <lb/>in the ſpace of
          an hour recovered her <lb/>by various means, but principally by the <lb/>injection of
          Tobacco-ſmoke, and then <lb/>putting her in bed to ther Huſband. <lb/>This raſh action was
          committed in de- <lb/>ſpair, becauſe the man her reputed huſ- <lb/>band, by whom ſhe had
          two Children, <lb/>obſtinately refuſed to marry her: after <lb/>this diſaſter he owned
          himſelf in the <lb/>wrong, and conſented to marry her; and <lb/>this deſperate Attempt
          reſtored her to <pb n="14"/>
          <lb/>that happineſs which other means had <lb/>failed to obtain. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE IV. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>ON the 25th day of May, 1768, <lb/>about two Miles from <hi rend="italic"
          >Leiden</hi>, as the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Trekſchuit</hi> from Delft was paſſing on,
          <lb/>the halling-rope broke, and four paſſen- <lb/>gers, then upon deck, fell overboard.
          <lb/>Three of them were ſoon got out; but <lb/>the fourth, named <hi rend="italic">Jan
            Spyker</hi>, a Haber- <lb/>daſher of Amſterdam, went to the bot- <lb/>tom: he was, when
          found and brought <lb/>on ſhore, to all appearances dead. Four <lb/>Charity-Boys belonging
          to Amſterdam <lb/>attempted to recover him, and brought <lb/>him to life again by the
          means directed in <lb/>the Society's Inſtructions. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE V. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Amſterdam</hi>, on the 10th of Au- <lb/>guſt, 1768, one <hi
            rend="italic">Lambert Tuebbes</hi> from <lb/><hi rend="italic">Balk</hi> in Friſeland,
          threw himſelf into <lb/>the Town-ditch, in a fit of deſpair, <pb n="15"/>
          <lb/>and lay immerſed at leaſt twenty mi- <lb/>nutes. He was got out with difficulty,
          <lb/>and in a great degree recovered by <hi rend="italic">Frederic <lb/>Pieterſon</hi>, a
          Surgeon; but remaining weak, <lb/>he was the next day carried to an <lb/>Hoſpital, where,
          notwithſtanding <hi rend="italic">Dr. <lb/>Hagen</hi>'s care, and the attempts of others
          <lb/>to ſave him, he died in the ſpace of two <lb/>days, the diſtreſſing circumſtances he
          had <lb/>long laboured under having too much <lb/>weakened him. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE VI. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Fluſhing</hi> in Zeeland, on the 14th <lb/>of October, 1768, one
            <hi rend="italic">Jan Haſſel</hi>, a Ma- <lb/>rine of twenty-three years of age, and
          <lb/>a German by birth, being in liquor, <lb/>fell from a high bridge into the water,
          <lb/>and remained half an hour immerſed. <lb/>When he was taken out, his eyes were
          <lb/>cloſed, his mouth open, and his face <lb/>blue: he was quite cold, motionleſs,
          <lb/>without any feeling, without breath, or <pb n="16"/>
          <lb/>any ſymptom of life. Half an hour <lb/>more elapſed before he was got into a
          <lb/>houſe and aſſiſtance given him. He <lb/>was then laid before a great fire, rub-
          <lb/>bed with hot cloths dipped in Brandy; <lb/>and in three quarters of an hour he
          <lb/>diſcharged ſome froth at the mouth. <lb/>In half and hour after that, about nine
          <lb/>ounces of blood were taken from him, <lb/>by bleeding at the jugular vein; ſoon
          <lb/>after which he puked up ſome clear <lb/>water. Volatile Spirits were then uſed,
          <lb/>as was alſo the Tobacco Fumigator which <lb/>could not ſooner be obtained, and the
          <lb/>moment a ſufficient quantity of vapour <lb/>was introduced into his bowels, he
          <lb/>gave farther ſigns of life, and threw up <lb/>ſome more water. A little brandy with
          <lb/>a few drops of Spirit of <hi rend="italic">Sal Ammoniac</hi>
          <lb/>was then given him; the Spirit was <lb/>held to his Noſe, and the rubbing was
          <lb/>continued, upon which the blood began <lb/>to circulate, and he was bled at the arm;
            <pb n="17"/>
          <lb/>after which he ſpoke, and deſired to be <lb/>allowed to ſleep, which being complied
          with, <lb/>he ſlept all night, and was well enough <lb/>next day, to continue his journey,
          being <lb/>only a little feveriſh, with a complaint of <lb/>ſoreneſs all over his body.
          The whole <lb/>of this treatment was directed by <hi rend="italic">Joſeph
            <lb/>Raymondon</hi>, a ſurgeon to a Dutch ſhip of <lb/>war. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE VII. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>NEAR <hi rend="italic">Harlingen</hi> in Friſeland, on the <lb/>18th of October,
          1768, the Child of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hendrik Beerendſz</hi>, a Girl of four years
          <lb/>old, fell into a ditch headlong, and ſtuck <lb/>in the mud; and having none but young
          <lb/>children with her, who ran away frightened, <lb/>no alarm or aſſiſtance was
          immediately <lb/>given; but ſhe was ſome time afterwards <lb/>taken out by a perſon coming
          along the <lb/>road, who diſcovered her, and thought <lb/>her quite dead. As he brought
          her into <lb/>town, he met with a Surgeon, one <hi rend="italic">Jan <pb n="18"/>
            <lb/>Schoonebeek</hi>, who directly turned her head <lb/>downwards, and kept ſhaking her
          as ſhe <lb/>was carried home: there he continued the <lb/>ſame motion by other hands for
          more than <lb/>half an hour—when ſhe gave ſome ſigns of <lb/>life, threw up a little
          ſlime, and began a <lb/>crying, after which ſhe was put into a <lb/>warm bed, and
          perfectly recovered. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE VIII. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Weſter-en Hilliger Lee</hi> in the Pro- <lb/>vince of <hi
            rend="italic">Groningen</hi>, on the 6th of Septem- <lb/>ber, 1768, the Son of the
          Reverend Mr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Conradus Woldringh</hi>, a Child aged two <lb/>years
          and five months, running after a <lb/>dog, ſlipt through a hedge into a large <lb/>ditch,
          and after being ſought for more <lb/>than fifteen minutes, was brought home <lb/>quite
          lifeleſs. Its father, called down from <lb/>his ſtudy, examined it attentively, and
          <lb/>concluded it dead. Yet greatly anxious <lb/>for its recovery if poſſible, he ordered
          a <lb/>large fire to be made, and the Child to be <pb n="19"/>
          <lb/>ſtripped. He then took it upon his knees, <lb/>wrapping it up in his own warm night-
          <lb/>gown, held it in an inclined manner, <lb/>with its feet higher than its head, and
          <lb/>with his hands and knees kept its body in <lb/>conſtant agitation. It was after that
          well <lb/>rubbed, and warmed before the fire, then <lb/>fiercely burning, and in the ſpace
          of ten <lb/>minutes it gave ſome faint ſigns of life, <lb/>uttering that little ſound
          frequently heard <lb/>at the moment of children's birth, and it <lb/>bled a little at the
          noſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The rubbing and agitation being now <lb/>continued upon a cuſhion, it began to
          <lb/>groan, and to breath with great difficulty <lb/>—but it ſtill farther recovered with
          the <lb/>perſeverance of this treatment: its night- <lb/>clothes were put on, and it was
          laid in a <lb/>warm cradle by the fire ſide. More than <lb/>half an hour elapſed before it
          regained <lb/>heat in all parts of its body; but as ſoon <lb/>as that was obtained, it
          broke out in a <pb n="20"/>
          <lb/>profuſe ſweat, and the recovery was com- <lb/>pleted. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE IX. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>WITHIN two miles of <hi rend="italic">Rotterdam</hi>, on <lb/>the 9th of November,
          1768, one <hi rend="italic">Hendrik <lb/>Stroiberg</hi>, a labouring man, in liquor,
          <lb/>was drowned in the river <hi rend="italic">Rotte</hi>; he was <lb/>laid upon a
          lighter near the place where <lb/>he was taken up, after an immerſion of <lb/>thirty
          minutes and more. Somer farther <lb/>time elapſed before Dr. <hi rend="italic">John
            Evans</hi>, who <lb/>directed this cure, could find a proper <lb/>place of treatment for
          him: he was then <lb/>ſtripped, his joints were become ſo ſtiff, <lb/>as to render the
          ſtripping him difficult. <lb/>He was put into a warm bed, rubbed, <lb/>and properly
          treated: ſome pulſation was <lb/>found in his arms, when a Surgeon at- <lb/>tempted to
          bleed him, but with little <lb/>effect. Some Tobacco-ſmoke was blown <lb/>up his
          inteſtines, and contributed to his <lb/>recovery. At the end of an hour and a <pb n="21"/>
          <lb/>half, he complained of a difficulty in <lb/>breathing, and an oppreſſion at his
          heart, <lb/>for which an emetic was given him, that <lb/>operated downwards inſtead of
          upwards. <lb/>The next day he had a ſharp pain at his <lb/>breaſt, which was ſcarce
          bearable when <lb/>he breathed: a ſecond bleeding and ſome <lb/>medicines removed that
          pain to his right <lb/>ſide, where it ſettled, yet leſſened by de- <lb/>grees, as he
          recovered. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE X. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Amſterdam</hi>, on the 30th of Novem- <lb/>ber, 1768, one <hi
            rend="italic">Lambert Ploos</hi>, an old <lb/>man, fell from a boat he was puſhing
          <lb/>forward under a bridge, and ſinking to <lb/>the bottom of the canal, was not readily
          <lb/>found, becauſe it was dark: being got out <lb/>at laſt, he was put into a barge, and
          rolled <lb/>on a caſk, though he was cold and ſtiff— <lb/>ſome brandy was poured into his
          mouth, <lb/>and he was carried to a public-houſe, where <lb/>he was laid before a large
          fire, ſtripped, <pb n="22"/>
          <lb/>and rubbed, and had ſome dry clothes put <lb/>on. When he ſhewed ſome ſigns of life,
          <lb/>a meſs of beer and bread, with mace and <lb/>ſome brandy in it, was given him by
          degrees <lb/>as he recovered; which was ſo faſt, that in <lb/>about ſix hours from the
          firſt of the <lb/>accident, he could be conveyed to a boat <lb/>that was to carry him home
          to <hi rend="italic">s'Graveland</hi>, <lb/>where he was perfectly reſtored to health.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE XI. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Rotterdam</hi>, on the 30th of No- <lb/>vember, 1768, a man
          called <hi rend="italic">Jan Joſephus <lb/>van Lel</hi>, being in liquor, fell into the
          river <lb/><hi rend="italic">Maeſe</hi>, in the dark, and was got out as ſoon <lb/>as he
          could be found. Some of the by- <lb/>ſtanders rolled him upon a caſk, and would <lb/>have
          made an end of him ſoon, had not <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Evans</hi> reſcued him out of
          their hands. <lb/>His neck was then rubbed with brandy, <lb/>of which ſome part was poured
          into his <lb/>noſe; and ſome of it getting into his <lb/>mouth, he opened his eyes and
          endea- <pb n="23"/>
          <lb/>voured to ſwallow it. Being got home, <lb/>he was undreſſed, put to bed, rubbed,
          <lb/>and attempted to be blooded, which how- <lb/>ever he would not ſuffer to be done.
          Some <lb/>time after, he voided blood up and down <lb/>from the bruiſes of his being
          rolled, and <lb/>in a few hours afterwards he expired. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The common error of this rough treat- <lb/>ment is ſtill farther exemplified by the
          <lb/>caſe of a young man, drowned in the ſame <lb/>river, who muſt inſtantly have been
          <lb/>killed by the blind zeal of the byſtanders, <lb/>had not an Apothecary, called <hi
            rend="italic">Bezoet</hi>, <lb/>forcibly taken him out of their hands. </p>
        <div>
          <head rend="space align-center">
            <lb/>CASE XII. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Alkmaar</hi> in Holland, on the 19th <lb/>of January, 1769,
            one <hi rend="italic">Lodewick Schoe- <lb/>ning</hi>, a Maltſter belonging to a
            Brewhouſe, <lb/>the Starry Crown, ran into a canal in <lb/>purſuit of his hat, and ſhot
            forward ſo <lb/>far, as not to be found in leſs than fifteen <lb/>minutes; and when he
            was got out, he <pb n="24"/>
            <lb/>ſeemed ſo very lifeleſs and ſtiff as to be <lb/>out of the reach of art. However to
            leave <lb/>no means unattempted, he was firſt rolled <lb/>over a caſk, then carried to a
            brewhouſe, <lb/>laid before a great fire, and undreſſed; <lb/>and ſeeming to give ſome
            ſigns of life, a <lb/>glaſs of Jeneva was poured into his mouth, <lb/>which farther
            recovered him and made <lb/>him throw up ſome water. Another glaſs <lb/>of it, which he
            aſked for, ſet him up ſo <lb/>far, that, though much ſwollen, he was <lb/>able to be
            carried home, where he re- <lb/>covered gradually. </p>
          <div>
            <head rend="space align-center">
              <lb/>CASE XIII. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Leuwarden</hi> in Friſeland, on the <lb/>26th of January,
              1769, the Child of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hendrik Hendriks Gardeniers</hi>, a boy of
              <lb/>three years and ſix months old, fell under <lb/>the ice, and remained there for
              half an <lb/>hour before he could be found: when <lb/>he was taken out, he was dead to
              all ap- <lb/>pearance; but a humane woman, named <pb n="25"/>
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ida Schapeling</hi>, took him into her houſe, <lb/>ſtripped him
              directly, wrapped him up <lb/>in a woolen apron, warmed and rubbed <lb/>him before a
              fire, and chaffed his head <lb/>with warm brandy. After forty minutes <lb/>treatment,
              putting her finger into his <lb/>mouth, ſhe found he bit it, and then ſhe <lb/>poured
              in a ſpoonfull of brandy. After <lb/>this ſhe put the child into a warm bed, <lb/>with
              a ſtone jug of hot water at its feet; <lb/>and by ſuch means made it ſo much
              <lb/>better, that in the ſpace of an hour from <lb/>its firſt being brought into her
              houſe, its <lb/>parents could ſafely carry it away wrapped <lb/>up in a blanket; and
              ſhe had the pleaſure <lb/>to ſee it come to thank her the next day. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The Magiſtrates of <hi rend="italic">Leuwarden</hi> had <lb/>this Caſe publiſhed
              in their town news- <lb/>paper, with all its circumſtances. </p>
            <div>
              <head rend="space align-center">
                <lb/>CASE XIV. </head>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Amſterdam</hi>, on the 25th of Feb- <lb/>ruary, 1769, a
                maid ſervant, drawing <pb n="26"/>
                <lb/>water in the morning, fell into the canal <lb/>before her maſter's door, and
                after ſome <lb/>ſtruggling ſunk to the bottom. She was <lb/>got out, in about a
                quarter of an hour, and <lb/>had not the leaſt ſign of life in her. Air <lb/>and
                Tobacco-vapour were immediately <lb/>blown up her inteſtines: ſhe was ſtripped,
                <lb/>laid before a fire, and was rubbed with <lb/>cloths dipped in brandy, till ſome
                ſigns of <lb/>life were diſcovered, when alſo ſome <lb/>froth appeared upon her
                mouth. An aſ- <lb/>ſiſting Surgeon's apprentice tried to bleed <lb/>her, but got no
                more than a few drops: <lb/>not being ſatisfied with this, he opened <lb/>the
                jugular vein, and took away eight or <lb/>nine ounces of blood. As ſhe recovered,
                <lb/>fourteen or fifteen drops of Spirit of <hi rend="italic">Sal <lb/>Ammoniac</hi>
                were given her in water. Some <lb/>hours afterwards ſhe was put to bed, was
                <lb/>rubbed, and had a Tobacco-clyſter. She <lb/>was alſo bled in her right arm, and
                at <lb/>length came entirely to herſelf; yet com- <lb/>plained of an oppreſſion in
                her breaſt. <pb n="27"/>
                <lb/>At noon ſhe was ordered to be blooded a <lb/>third time. At four in the
                afternoon, <lb/>little complaint remained, but a ſtraitneſs <lb/>over her breaſt,
                which ſhe had before been <lb/>ſubject to, and was afterwards cured. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
              <head rend="space align-center">
                <lb/>CASE XV. </head>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Rotterdam</hi>, on the 8th of April, <lb/>1769, the
                daughter of <hi rend="italic">Meindert den <lb/>Broeder</hi>, a girl of ten years of
                age, fell <lb/>into a ſtagnated deep muddy ditch, <lb/>near the rampart of the town,
                and ſtuck <lb/>in it for ſome time. When ſhe was taken <lb/>out of it, ſhe ſeemed,
                according to the <lb/>account of the Surgeon <hi rend="italic">Hooykaas</hi> who
                <lb/>directed the following treatment, to be <lb/>abſolutely dead, and looked as
                black as if <lb/>ſhe had been hanged, having alſo a quan- <lb/>tity of froth at her
                lips and noſe. She <lb/>was immediately ſtripped, put between <lb/>warm blankets,
                and rubbed. After the <lb/>introduction of ſome Tobacco-vapour into <lb/>the
                inteſtines, a bleeding was attempted, <pb n="28"/>
                <lb/>and only about four ounces of blood ob- <lb/>tained, by drops; the jugular vein
                not <lb/>being practicable, upon account of the <lb/>great ſwelling of the neck and
                head. <lb/>Three perſons then continued to rub, and <lb/>inject ſmoke, for the ſpace
                of an hour, <lb/>when a faint yawning, like that of a de- <lb/>parting patient, gave
                the firſt ſmall ſign <lb/>of life. Some Spirit of <hi rend="italic">Sal
                  Ammoniac</hi>, <lb/>held to the noſe, produced no effect; but <lb/>in an hour and
                a half, ſome ſlight pulſa- <lb/>tion was diſcovered; ſoon after which, <lb/>ſhe
                diſcharged upwards and downwards, <lb/>and then began to move her legs and arms.
                <lb/>At the end of two hours, ſhe began to <lb/>ſcream, and cried out, <hi
                  rend="italic">I am fallen into <lb/>the water</hi>; and afterwards complained of
                <lb/>ſoreneſs all over her body. Some cordial <lb/>was at this time given her, which
                had <lb/>before been fruitleſsly attempted, and now <lb/>ſerved greatly to recover
                her. About an <lb/>hour and a half afterwards, ſhe com- <lb/>plained of a great pain
                in her bowels, and <pb n="29"/>
                <lb/>a difficulty in breathing, for which a <lb/>clyſter with an infuſion of Tobacco
                was <lb/>adminiſtered, and it operated in ſo copious <lb/>a manner, as to give her
                great relief. <lb/>An hour and a half after this, ſhe was <lb/>delirious, and ſtill
                more oppreſſed—it was <lb/>again tried to bleed her, and ſtill without <lb/>ſucceſs;
                but a bliſter was applied to her <lb/>back, and thought to do her good. A
                <lb/>laxative medicine was given her by degrees <lb/>during the night, and had its
                intended <lb/>effect. Next morning ſhe had a violent <lb/>pain in her ſide, and a
                conſiderable op- <lb/>preſſion, for which recourſe was had to <lb/>bleeding, which
                at laſt ſucceeded on her <lb/>hand, and immediately relieved her. The <lb/>next day
                ſhe voided ſome hard, black, <lb/>clayey ſtuff: the day after that, ſhe com-
                <lb/>plained of a pain in her breaſt, which <lb/>was found to proceed from ſome ſkin
                <lb/>being rubbed off during the operation. <lb/>Her tongue remained furred for ſome
                <lb/>days, but was at laſt cleared by a repeti- <pb n="30"/>
                <lb/>tion of the laxative medicine; and ſhe <lb/>then gradually recovered her former
                <lb/>ſtrength, to the great comfort and aſſiſt- <lb/>ance of an old helpleſs father,
                whom this <lb/>girl took care of, whilſt the mother was <lb/>abſent, indefatigably
                working as a chair- <lb/>woman for the ſubſiſtance of her family. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
              <head rend="space align-center">
                <lb/>CASE XVI. </head>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Amſterdam</hi>, on the 9th of April, <lb/>1769, it
                happened at nine o'clock at <lb/>night, that <hi rend="italic">Beetje Harmets</hi>,
                a widow <lb/>woman of ſixty-two years of age, fell <lb/>into the <hi rend="italic"
                  >Keiſersgragt</hi>, and remained im- <lb/>merſed a quarter of an hour. As ſoon as
                <lb/>ſhe was got out, two Surgeon's appren- <lb/>tices, <hi rend="italic">C. de
                  Beer</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">J. A. Beverly</hi>, had <lb/>her ſtripped before
                a fire, bled her, rub- <lb/>bed her hard, eſpecially along the ſpine <lb/>of the
                back, with cloths dipped in brandy, <lb/>and blew ſome Tobacco-ſmoke into her
                <lb/>mouth, which made her throw up ſome <lb/>water, and then ſhe gave ſome ſigns of
                  <pb n="31"/>
                <lb/>life; but ſoon after ſhe was taken with <lb/>ſtrong convulſion fits, nearly
                baffling all <lb/>hopes of farther recovery; yet by perſe- <lb/>verance, and
                reducing a rupture ſhe was <lb/>found to have, ſhe grew ſo much better, <lb/>as to
                be able, in three hours time from <lb/>her immerſion, to be conveyed home in a
                <lb/>carriage. </p>
              <div>
                <head rend="space align-center">
                  <lb/>CASE XVII. </head>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>At <hi rend="italic">Amſterdam</hi>, on the 17th of April, 1769, <lb/><hi
                    rend="italic">Anna Woertman</hi>, a woman of twenty-ſeven <lb/>years of age,
                  belonging to that pleaſant part <lb/>of the city called the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Plantage</hi>, was taken <lb/>out of the water, without its being known
                  <lb/>how long ſhe had lain in it. She was incon- <lb/>ſiderately rolled upon a
                  float, for a quarter <lb/>of an hour, and is ſaid to have voided a good <lb/>deal
                  of water. She was then carried into <lb/>a houſe, where <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bernardus Donſelaar</hi>, an apo- <lb/>thecary, was ſent for, and told ſhe had
                  juſt <lb/>before given ſome very faint ſign of life; <lb/>though in fact ſhe
                  appeared quite lifeleſs, <pb n="32"/>
                  <lb/>was ſtiff, and had green and blue ſpots all over <lb/>her body.—She was laid
                  before a fire in <lb/>blankets, and rubbed with a mixture of <lb/>ſpirit of <hi
                    rend="italic">Sal Ammoniac</hi> and Eſſence of <lb/>Roſemary, along the back
                  bone, the loins, <lb/>the neck, the head and temples, and a <lb/>ſtone jug with
                  hot water was laid at her <lb/>feet. Some farther ſigns of life then ap-
                  <lb/>pearing, ſhe began to ſhake as in the cold <lb/>fit of an ague, ſpake and
                  complained; <lb/>upon which ſome ſpoonfuls of Jeneva <lb/>were given her, and ſhe
                  was blooded—her <lb/>blood was black and thick, not inflamed. <lb/>Being thirſty,
                  ſome milk and water was <lb/>given her; and then ſhe fell into fits ſeem-
                  <lb/>ingly ſtrong enough to carry her off: theſe <lb/>however were removed by a
                  cordial ad- <lb/>miniſtered to her. In the ſpace of four <lb/>hours and a half ſhe
                  was ſo much better, <lb/>as to be carried home, and put to bed to <lb/>her ſiſter,
                  where ſhe fell into a breathing <lb/>ſweat. About five hours afterwards ſhe com-
                  <lb/>plained of a great oppreſſion, and a violent <pb n="33"/>
                  <lb/>pain in all her limbs; for which an aperient <lb/>laxative mixture was given,
                  and which <lb/>made her part with a quantity of watery <lb/>matter. The pain
                  augmenting, and fixing in <lb/>her ſide and breaſt, ſhe was twice bled, and
                  <lb/>her blood being then found much inflamed, <lb/>it was wiſhed to repeat the
                  bleedings; but <lb/>ſhe proved to be too weak: however, a <lb/>bliſter was applied
                  to her ſide; and other <lb/>treatment being opportunely given, ſhe <lb/>was
                  entirely recovered in the ſpace of a <lb/>fortnight, the ſlowneſs of which is
                  attri- <lb/>buted to her having been afflicted ſix <lb/>months before with a
                  fever, and conſtant <lb/>depreſſion of ſpirits, upon account of bad
                  <lb/>circumſtances. </p>
                <div>
                  <head rend="space align-center"><lb/>CASE XVIII. </head>
                  <p rend="indent"><lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Amſterdam</hi>, on the 26th day of
                    <lb/>May, 1769, at midnight, a young woman, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Racheltje
                      Ooms</hi>, taken out of the <hi rend="italic">Damrak</hi>, <lb/>where ſhe was
                    found drowned, was firſt <lb/>rolled upon a caſk, and then carried into <pb
                      n="34"/>
                    <lb/>a houſe, attempted to be bled by <hi rend="italic">Barend
                      <lb/>Boerregter</hi>, a Surgeon, then rubbed and <lb/>chafed with Spirit of
                      <hi rend="italic">Sal Ammoniac</hi>, had <lb/>brandy ſpouted into her mouth,
                    and her <lb/>noſe tickled with a feather—but all this <lb/>being done without
                    effect, ſhe was laid <lb/>before a fire, the rubbing was continued, <lb/>ſome
                    more brandy put into her mouth, <lb/>and after three quarters of an hour, ſome
                    <lb/>pulſation being felt in her left arm, a <lb/>bleeding was performed there,
                    and more <lb/>than twelve ounces of blood taken away; <lb/>after which ſhe gave
                    ſuch ſigns of life, as <lb/>made all farther treatment appear ſuper-<lb/>fluous;
                    and ſhe was able to walk home at <lb/>the end of five hours from the time of
                    <lb/>her being firſt found. </p>
                  <div>
                    <head rend="space align-center">
                      <lb/>CASE XIX. </head>
                      <p rend="indent"><lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Amſterdam</hi>, on the 29th of July,
                    <lb/>1769, a Boy of fourteen years of age, <lb/>called <hi rend="italic">Jacob
                      Voorm</hi>, rowing with ſome <lb/>others in a boat, fell overboard, and <pb
                      n="35"/>
                    <lb/>ſunk directly. More than twenty minutes <lb/>elapſed before he could be got
                    out of the <lb/>water. He was then carried into a houſe, <lb/>where by the
                    direction of <hi rend="italic">Floris Loosjes</hi>, an <lb/>apothecary, he was
                    ſtripped of his clothes, <lb/>laid in a blanket, and rubbed all over;
                    <lb/>Tobacco-ſmoke was blown up into his <lb/>inteſtines, and wind forced into
                    his mouth, <lb/>whilſt his noſe was held cloſe, and this <lb/>repeatedly. He was
                    bled at the arm, and <lb/>nine or ten ounces of blood were taken <lb/>away;
                    after which, upon the appearance <lb/>of ſome ſigns of life, a little brandy was
                    <lb/>put into his mouth; and the room in <lb/>which he was thus treated, being
                    thought <lb/>too cloſe, he was carried into a more airy <lb/>room, where ſome
                    more brandy being <lb/>forcibly ſpouted into his throat, he rouſed <lb/>at once,
                    and ſcreamed out; when he be-<lb/>came quieter, ſome milk and water was
                    <lb/>given him to drink. He was then put <lb/>to bed, had hot cloths applied to
                    him, <lb/>and was well covered up. He grew warm <pb n="36"/><lb/>by degrees,
                    excepting at the ſoles of his <lb/>feet, and was delirious at times; but that
                    <lb/>ceaſing, he complained of a pain and in-<lb/>flammation in his throat,
                    which, by the <lb/>preſcription of a Phyſician, was got the <lb/>better of in a
                        few days, and the lad totally <lb/>reſtored. </p></div>
                  <div>
                    <head rend="space align-center">
                      <lb/>CASE XX. </head><p rend="indent"><lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Rotterdam</hi>, on the 1ſt of Auguſt,
                    <lb/>1769, at the dock, in the <hi rend="italic">Herring-fleet</hi>, <lb/>one
                      <hi rend="italic">Gerrit Schrauwen</hi>, the ſkipper of a <lb/>yacht belonging
                    to Mr. <hi rend="italic">Hogendyk</hi>, in <lb/>changing the ſituation of the
                    ſhed in <lb/>which ſuch pleaſure-boats are kept, ſlipped <lb/>his hold, fell
                    into the water, and ſunk <lb/>directly in a part where the depth was <lb/>not
                    leſs than twenty five feet. A peaſant <lb/>firſt obſerved this ſhed floating by
                    itſelf, <lb/>then diſcovered a hat near it, and con-<lb/>cluding ſome miſchance
                    had happened, <lb/>gave the alarm; upon which ſeveral men <lb/>came with
                    boat-hooks, which proved too <pb n="37"/>
                    <lb/>ſhort, and ſome time elapſed before they <lb/>could get others, none longer
                    being at <lb/>hand. He was at laſt got out by a friend <lb/>of his, one <hi
                      rend="italic">Arnoldus Fynands</hi>, who found <lb/>him at the diſtance of
                    fifty paces from the <lb/>float from which he fell; and it appeared <lb/>that he
                    had endeavoured, as long as his <lb/>ſenſes laſted, to get towards the quay.
                    <lb/>When he was taken out of the water, his <lb/>eyes were cloſe ſhut; his face
                    was diſtorted, <lb/>and looked wan; and his jaw was ſo <lb/>much fixed, that
                    with difficulty his mouth <lb/>was broke open, and brandy was poured <lb/>into
                    it twice without any ſucceſs: more <lb/>than twenty-five minutes were now
                    <lb/>elapſed ſince he firſt fell in; yet his friend, <lb/>with three other
                    workmen of the dock-<lb/>yard, attempted to recover him; they <lb/>ſhook him
                    violently, they by turns rubbed <lb/>his breaſt and belly, ſqueezed his throat,
                    <lb/>and forced ſome water and blood out of <lb/>it. They then carried him to
                    the houſe of <lb/>one <hi rend="italic">Schaardenberg</hi>, a Surgeon, dwelling
                      <pb n="38"/><lb/>at ſome diſtance from the dock, there <lb/>ſtripped him of
                    his wet clothes, and put <lb/>on others dry and warm of the byſtanders.
                    <lb/>They then had recourſe to the uſual treat-<lb/>ment, and could not in leſs
                    than twenty <lb/>minutes obtain any ſigns of life, which <lb/>they did at laſt,
                    when the Surgeon put <lb/>into his mouth ſome ſpiritous liquor, to <lb/>which
                    the patient had always an averſion. <lb/>He <choice>
                      <corr>then</corr>
                      <sic>than</sic>
                    </choice> began to ſcream, called for his <lb/>companion, looked aghaſt, and
                    recovered <lb/>by degrees. When he was ſufficiently <lb/>better, they led him
                    home ſtaggering, and <lb/>throwing up more water and blood. <lb/>During two or
                    three days, he looked <lb/>gloomy, and was low-ſpirited; but ſoon <lb/>after,
                        eſpecially by means of a trip taken <lb/>with his maſter, he recovered entirely.</p>
                  </div>
                </div>
              </div>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE XXI. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Ooſtzaandam</hi> in North-Holland, <lb/>on the eighth of Auguſt,
          1769, a Child of <lb/>three years old, the Son of <hi rend="italic">Albert Maſker</hi>,
            <pb n="39"/>
          <lb/>a Taylor, was taken out of the water, after <lb/>an immerſion of fifteen minutes, and
          <lb/>brought home to its parents. A Surgeon, <lb/><hi rend="italic">J. Van Macheren</hi>,
          by whoſe door it was <lb/>carried, followed it, and took care of it. <lb/>He found the
          child entirely motionleſs, <lb/>its limbs ſupple, its head and face blue, <lb/>and a
          quantity of bloody froth upon its <lb/>mouth and noſe. He ſtripped off its wet
          <lb/>clothes as faſt as poſſible, and put it to <lb/>bed between blankets, with a jug of
          hot <lb/>water at its feet. He then applied the <lb/>Tobacco-vapour pipe, and rubbed its
          <lb/>back bone with fine ſalt and warm brandy. <lb/>He opened its mouth by force, to pour
          in <lb/>ſome brandy and butter, which ran out <lb/>again directly: he held the Spirit of
          Am- <lb/>moniac Salt to its noſe, blew ſnuff into <lb/>it, and tickled it with a feather.
          Soon <lb/>after this, he perceived ſome pulſation in <lb/>a large artery, which encouraged
          him to <lb/>continue his treatment, 'till he heard a <lb/>rattling in its throat, and a
          rumbling in <pb n="40"/>
          <lb/>the belly. Then it began to ſweat, and <lb/>to reach a little, and had a diſcharge;
          <lb/>which ſymptoms did not appear till after <lb/>the ſpace of three hours, at the end of
          <lb/>which it was in a fair way of recovery. <lb/>After having ſome reſt, it was feveriſh
          and <lb/>drowſy; as much beer and butter, and <lb/>weak tea, as could be got down, being
          <lb/>given to it, the amendment was percepti- <lb/>ble. An oppreſſion remaining, ſome ſour
          <lb/>dough was put to its feet, and it became <lb/>well and chearful again the next day.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE XXII. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>IN <hi rend="italic">Amſterdam</hi>, on the 23d of Auguſt, <lb/>1769, <hi
            rend="italic">Samuel Abrahams</hi>, a Jew, who got <lb/>his livelihood by carrying
          greens about for <lb/>ſale, fell from a fiſh-float into the water, <lb/>ſunk, and was got
          out again by two other <lb/>Jews. Some time after, <hi rend="italic">Frans Nicolas
            <lb/>Wickel</hi>, a Surgeon, came to their aſſiſtance, <lb/>got him carried into a
          public houſe, had <lb/>him ſtripped, laid before a fire, and <pb n="41"/>
          <lb/>rubbed all over the body with brandy, and <lb/>took twelve ounces of blood from
            him<unclear>:</unclear>
          <lb/>after which, to continue the treatment <lb/>without interruption, he got the
          aſſiſtance of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Jacob de Koningh</hi>, another Surgeon's appren-
          <lb/>tice, and they together continued rubbing, <lb/>held Spirit of Sal Ammoniac to his
          noſe, <lb/>gave him two Clyſters of an infuſion of <lb/>Tobacco, with ſome ſalt and oil,
          which <lb/>produced a copious evacuation: they <lb/>poured ſome <hi rend="italic">Liquor
            Anodinus</hi> into his <lb/>mouth; he then puked, and came to him- <lb/>ſelf ſo ſpeedily
          that in one half-hour's <lb/>time he aſked for ſome drink. Some milk <lb/>and water was
          then given him, a dry ſhirt <lb/>was put on, and he was laid between blan- <lb/>kets in
          bed, becauſe he complained of an op- <lb/>preſſion upon his breaſt; and half an hour
          <lb/>afterwards, ſitting up in bed, he ſeemed <lb/>taken with a convulſion fit, fell back
          and <lb/>expired. This ſudden death was by ſome <lb/>attributed to the falling ſickneſs,
          to which <lb/>he was ſaid to have been ſubject. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="42"/>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE XXIII. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Amſterdam</hi>, on the 23d of Auguſt, <lb/>1769, the Son of <hi
            rend="italic">Arent van den Bergh</hi>, a Boat- <lb/>man, being a child of ſomewhat leſs
          than <lb/>two years old, fell into a rain-water ciſtern <lb/>with a very narrow mouth,
          into which <lb/>its mother would have ſlid after it without <lb/>any proſpect of
          aſſiſtance, had ſhe not been <lb/>prevented by ſome byſtanders, who them- <lb/>ſelves did
          what they could to get at the <lb/>child, but were obliged to have recourſe <lb/>to a lad,
          who being thin could ſlip down, <lb/>and being held, grope for the child below <lb/>him.
          He did ſo with good ſucceſs, and <lb/>got the child, which was then (poor help- <lb/>leſs
          thing) laid upon a caſk, rolled and <lb/>otherwiſe tormented, to bring it to itſelf
          <lb/>again. One of the aſſiſtants had the pre- <lb/>ſence of mind to uſe a Tobacco-pipe,
          to <lb/>blow its ſmoke up the child's inteſtines; <lb/>upon which ſome ſigns of life being
          diſ- <lb/>covered, it was laid upon its mother's lap, <pb n="43"/>
          <lb/>juſt when Dr. <hi rend="italic">Bernard</hi>, who had been ſent <lb/>for, came in,
          and directed the following <lb/>treatment, of which he himſelf has given <lb/>the account.
          He ordered a good fire to <lb/>be made, got the mother to ſtrip the child, <lb/>and made
          enquiry about what had been <lb/>done prior to his coming.—He then had <lb/>it diligently
          rubbed all over with Jeneva <lb/>and Salt, 'till it uttered a plaintive ſound, <lb/>and
          ſome froth appearing at its mouth and <lb/>noſe, it began to puke.—It now hung its
          <lb/>head over its ſhoulders, ſeemingly diſtreſſed, <lb/>then threw up ſome more phlegm,
          and <lb/>had a diſcharge.—The uneaſy motion of <lb/>the head continued, without the leaſt
          pul- <lb/>ſation in any of the blood-veſſels, 'till at <lb/>laſt, with a third fit of
          puking, ſome beat- <lb/>ing was felt in the left arm.—Then the <lb/>motion of the head
          leſſened, the child <lb/>ſeemed leſs oppreſſed, and began to cry. <lb/>The mother was then
          aſked what it liked <lb/>to drink; and that proving to be beer, a little <lb/>of it was
          warmed with ſome ſugar, and <pb n="44"/>
          <lb/>was drank off with eagerneſs.—It ſeemed <lb/>as yet not rightly recovered, for want
          of a <lb/>more copious diſcharge, for which a mix- <lb/>ture was ordered to be given by a
          ſpoonful <lb/>every hour, the child being kept as warm <lb/>as poſſible in blankets, the
          pungent vapour <lb/>of the Tobacco was not thought farther <lb/>eligible:—it was alſo
          judged that a bleed- <lb/>ing was not adviſable, neither of the <lb/>jugulars being
          turgid, nor any blood veſ- <lb/>ſels diſcoverable in its arms, or on its <lb/>hands. In
          the evening it lay quiet, looked <lb/>about diſtinctly, and, as the mother thought,
          <lb/>grew better viſibly; its hands felt natu- <lb/>rally warm, its pulſe was regular, but
          <lb/>quick as uſual with children of that age.— <lb/>The mixture having had no effect, it
          was <lb/>repeated, and the mother charged to keep <lb/>the child very warm, as it was
          imagined it <lb/>muſt ſweat much in the night, with the <lb/>great quantity of water it
          had ſwallowed; <lb/>and to forward this, ſhe was directed to lay <lb/>a jug with hot water
          at its feet; all which <pb n="45"/>
          <lb/>ſhe exactly complied with. It did ſweat <lb/>conſiderably in the night, and ſtarted
          often <lb/>in its ſleep, 'till about midnight, when it <lb/>began to reſt quietly:—early
          in the morn- <lb/>ing it had two ſtools, after which it aſked <lb/>to ſtay up and be
          dreſſed; which being <lb/>granted, it took its breakfaſt as uſual, <lb/>played about a
          while, and then lay down to <lb/>ſleep again. It recovered perfectly, though <lb/>Dr. <hi
            rend="italic">Bernard</hi> ſays it was of an uncom- <lb/>monly weak frame, and much
          inclined to <lb/>the rickets. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE XXIV. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Zuiderdrachten</hi>, in the province of <lb/>Friſeland, on the
          3d of June, 1769, a Boy of <lb/>three years old, the Child of <hi rend="italic">Cornelis
            <lb/>Gedſers</hi>, a Wool-dreſſer, fell into a ditch, <lb/>out of which he was taken as
          dead. He <lb/>was treated by a Surgeon, who in the ſpace <lb/>of fifteen minutes obtained
          ſome faint ſigns <lb/>of life, but could not in leſs than nine hours <lb/>get him ſo far
          recovered as to ſpeak. He <pb n="46"/>
          <lb/>tried every method, recommended or not, <lb/>except bleeding. He ſhook the child for
          <lb/>a conſiderable time with its head down- <lb/>wards:—he blew air into its inteſtines,
          firſt <lb/>with a Tobacco-pipe, and afterwards with <lb/>a Syringe:—he opened its mouth by
          force, <lb/>and blew air into its throat:—he dried <lb/>its body, chafed it, and rubbed it
          with <lb/>brandy and ſalt along the back bone.— <lb/>He held a volatile ſalt to its noſe;
          tickled <lb/>it with a feather; rubbed the ſoles of its <lb/>feet with a bruſh, and gave
          it two clyſters; <lb/>after all which applications, his endeavours <lb/>were attended with
          the deſired effect. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE XXV. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In the City of <hi rend="italic">Dordregt</hi> in Holland, in <lb/>the month of July,
          1769, it happened that <lb/>a boy of ſix years old, at play on a wharf, <lb/>fell from a
          beam into the water, unnoticed <lb/>by his playfellows, who, when they miſſed <lb/>him,
          ran up to the road to ſeek for him: <lb/>but a younger child, not yet fit to play <pb
            n="47"/>
          <lb/>with the others, and who at ſome little <lb/>diſtance had ſeen him fall in, and ſtood
          <lb/>ſtaring for a time as ſtruck with amaze- <lb/>ment, ran home to tell of this
          accident; <lb/>and at that very moment met its father, <lb/>who was juſt returned from the
          Province <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Zealand</hi>. This unexpected circumſtance
          <lb/>diverted the child from its purpoſe for a <lb/>while; but as ſoon as a moment's quiet
          <lb/>ſucceeded to the great expreſſions of joy <lb/>in the family, the little child took
          the <lb/>opportunity to make them underſtand, <lb/>by broken words and ſigns, that
          ſomebody <lb/>was fallen into the water, and led them to <lb/>the place where it happened;
          upon which, <lb/>immediate ſearch being made, the boy <lb/>was found, and taken out, dead
          to all <lb/>appearance, after having remained for ſo <lb/>conſiderable a time under water.
          He was <lb/>carried home, was undreſſed, had ſome <lb/>tobacco-ſmoke blown up his
          inteſtines, <lb/>and was put into warm blankets, in which <lb/>he gave ſome faint ſigns of
          life, crying <pb n="48"/>
          <lb/>when the ſoles of his feet were tickled, <lb/>but without any other certain ſymptom.
          <lb/>After many more trials, his mother took <lb/>him into bed to her, and by rubbing and
          <lb/>cheering him all night, got him to a <lb/>ſtate of perfect recovery. The ſteady
          <lb/>perſeverance in this treatment is remark- <lb/>able by its being carried on for a
          ſpace of <lb/>time not leſs than twelve hours, and gives <lb/>room to the Surgeon, <hi
            rend="italic">Jan Van Heſpel</hi>, who <lb/>relates the caſe, to utter this exclamation:
          <lb/>— <q rend="diple quotes">Who knows in how many thouſand <lb/>perſons the remaining
            ſpark of life is <lb/>extinguiſhed by injudicious practices! <lb/>when ſpeedy and proper
            endeavours <lb/>might reſtore a ſufficient degree of <lb/>genial heat. </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE XXVI. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Leuwarden</hi> in Friſeland, on the 3d <lb/>of September, 1769,
          a Boy of four years <lb/>and five months old, the Son of <hi rend="italic">Cornelis van
            <lb/>Meningen</hi>, a Tanner, fell into the water, <pb n="49"/>
          <lb/>and ſlid forward from the place at which <lb/>he went in, which was pointed out by
          <lb/>a ſtill younger child who had ſeen the acci- <lb/>dent from the other ſide of the
          canal. After <lb/>more than half an hour's ſearch by ſeveral <lb/>perſons, he was taken
          out by his own <lb/>father, who immediately ran about with <lb/>him in conſtant agitation,
          and had wind <lb/>repeatedly blown up into his inteſtines by <lb/>the aſſiſtants: as ſoon
          as the child was <lb/>brought home, it was ſtripped, the blow- <lb/>ing was continued, and
          it was rubbed be- <lb/>fore the fire 'till it gave ſome faint ſigns of <lb/>life, ſoon
          after which it threw up ſome <lb/>clear water, and voided ſome thin excre- <lb/>ment: it
          was then thought proper to give <lb/>it a little freſh butter melted with brandy, <lb/>to
          make it reach, which it did repeatedly, <lb/>and its ſpeech returned, at which time
          <lb/>it was put to bed well wrapped up; and <lb/>thus by degrees it recovered, ſo as to be
          <lb/>able in the courſe of three days to go to <lb/>ſchool again. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="50"/>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE XXVII. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>At <hi rend="italic">Amſterdan</hi>, on the 8th of September, <lb/>1769, <hi
            rend="italic">Hanna Polak</hi>, a German Jeweſs, <lb/>drawing up a pail of water,
          ſlipped from <lb/>the plank upon which ſhe ſtood, fell into <lb/>the canal, and receiving
          a blow of the pail <lb/>upon her head, was ſtunned, and ſunk at <lb/>once. She was got out
          in eight or ten <lb/>minutes time, and attended by <hi rend="italic">Michiel
            <lb/>Cramer</hi>, an Apothecary, and <hi rend="italic">Iſaac Serrano</hi>, <lb/>a
          Surgeon, the latter of which bled her <lb/>upon the ſpot where ſhe was firſt laid
          <lb/>down: they then got her carried into a <lb/>houſe, where they blew wind into her
          <lb/>lungs and inteſtines; gave her a clyſter, <lb/>and rubbed her back bone with Spirit
          of <lb/>Sal Ammoniac: having no bed, they ſet <lb/>her in blankets on a chair near to a
          German <lb/>ſtove. Three hours elapſed before one <lb/>ſingle ſtroke of a pulſe was felt
          in her,— <lb/>and that ſymptom giving freſh vigour to <lb/>the operators, the rubbing was
          continued; <pb n="51"/>
          <lb/>a ſtimulating clyſter was given her, ſhe <lb/>was kept as warm as poſſible, and began
          <lb/>to perſpire. Two hours and a half after <lb/>that, ſhe began to ſpeak, took ſome
          liquid, <lb/>and threw up ſome water. She fell then <lb/>into convulſive fits, which by
          ſome medi- <lb/>cines were allayed. At the end of ſix <lb/>hours more, ſhe was bled again
          at the foot, <lb/>which compoſed her greatly, and from <lb/>thence forward ſhe gradually
          recovered. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE XXVIII. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Horn</hi> in North-holland, on the 15th <lb/>September, 1769,
          two Boys driving a <lb/>waggon into town, and delivering ſome <lb/>bags of meal at the
          ſlope of the <hi rend="italic">Ruſbrug</hi>, <lb/>a bridge near the north gate of the
          town, <lb/>it happened that the horſe took fright, <lb/>flew acroſs the road, and threw
          the wag- <lb/>gon upſide-down into the ditch, where- <lb/>with a Boy who ſat in the middle
          of it <lb/>was covered, the other who was in the <lb/>fore part of it having jumped off.
          The <pb n="52"/>
          <lb/>Boy who fell under, by name <hi rend="italic">Cornelis Smit</hi>, <lb/>was ſixteen
          years old. Five men of the <lb/>town ran to his aſſiſtance, but knew not <lb/>on what ſide
          of the waggon to get at him: <lb/>after ſome time they eſpied one of his legs
          <lb/>ſticking out a little from under it, and <lb/>in vain endeavoured to pull him out:
          <lb/>the Boy lay upon his back, deeply de- <lb/>preſſed in the mud by the weight of the
          <lb/>waggon, beſide which the horſe was alſo <lb/>in the way:—they then cut his traces;
          <lb/>as ſoon as he found himſelf leſs confined, <lb/>he began to rear and ſtruggle, and
          was <lb/>near trampling the Boy's leg to pieces; <lb/>they held and ſtroked him, 'till he
          was <lb/>quite looſe, and then led him out; after <lb/>which lifting up the waggon, they
          dragged <lb/>out the Boy, and laid upon the bank, <lb/>covered and disfigured with mud,
          and as <lb/>they thought dead beyond doubt. It was <lb/>incumbent upon them however to try
          to <lb/>find out whether any life ſtill remained in <lb/>him, and to recover him if
          poſſible. They <pb n="53"/>
          <lb/>firſt waſhed the mud off his head, face and <lb/>neck, which they found to be black
          and <lb/>blue; they cut the collar of his ſhirt, and <lb/>then poured ſome brandy into his
          mouth, <lb/>by the effect of which upon the muſcles of <lb/>his face, they diſcovered ſome
          motion in <lb/>him, which was ſurpriſing after his having <lb/>been more than a quarter of
          an hour in the <lb/>above deplorable ſituation. They laid him <lb/>upon a caſk, and rolled
          him ſlowly about, <lb/>in expectation of ſome farther ſigns of life, <lb/>which indeed
          returned but faintly: upon <lb/>thoſe indications they put into his mouth <lb/>ſome
          buttered beer with brandy, and rolled <lb/>and ſhaked him again; after which he began
          <lb/>to throw up ſome froth, water and blood. <lb/>He then was carried to a neighbouring
          <lb/>public-houſe, where he was with difficulty <lb/>ſtripped of his clothes, waſhed all
          over <lb/>with warm water, and wiped with hot <lb/>cloths, which ſeemed to reſtore life to
          <lb/>him, for he cried out with it. Some dry <lb/>woolen things were then put on him; he
            <pb n="54"/>
          <lb/>was ſet in a great chair before a good fire; <lb/>and ſomething emetic was twice
          given him <lb/>with ſo much effect, that he vomited up, <lb/>as is ſaid, even clods of
          mud. Thus clear- <lb/>ed, he was put into a warm bed, where at <lb/>firſt he was feveriſh,
          but afterwards reſted <lb/>well; and next day, to the ſurpriſe of all, <lb/>was quite
          recovered, and had not one ſin- <lb/>gle part of his body hurt. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE XXIX. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Amſterdam</hi>, on the 7th of Septem- <lb/>ber, 1769, a Child of
          one <hi rend="italic">Nicolas Vermeulen</hi>
          <lb/>playing upon a bridge fell thro' the rails <lb/>into the water. The mother then big
          <lb/>with child, ſaw the accident out of her <lb/>window, flew down ſtairs, ran to the
          bridge, <lb/>jumped down to ſave it, and was in great <lb/>danger of drowning. The father,
          who at <lb/>that moment got home, finding out what <lb/>was the matter, made haſte to the
          quay, <lb/>and with ſome aſſiſtance got out his wife <lb/>firſt, and afterwards, in a
          quarter of an hour's <pb n="55"/>
          <lb/>time, the child was found, and brought on <lb/>ſhore, to all appearance dead. Several
          <lb/>attempts to recover it were in vain made, <lb/>both on the quay and in the houſe; at
          <lb/>length one <hi rend="italic">Chriſtoffel Roodolphs</hi>, a Surgeon, <lb/>came to
          their aſſiſtance: he had the child <lb/>ſtripped directly, wrapped in warm blan-
          <lb/>kets, and laid before a fire. He then <lb/>took ſome brandy in his mouth, forced
          <lb/>open that of the child, and ſpouted it in: <lb/>he blew his breath ſtrongly into its
          mouth, <lb/>and in about twelve minutes time ſome <lb/>ſigns of life appeared, ſuch as a
          faint reſpi- <lb/>ration, a ſighing, a grinding of the teeth, <lb/>and ſome convulſive
          motion, the ordinary <lb/>progreſſive ſymptoms of recovery. He <lb/>continued his
          treatment for an hour and a <lb/>half longer, and bled the child, after <lb/>which it
          ſeemed quiet for a while, yet was <lb/>a good deal oppreſſed in its breathing. The
          <lb/>next day it was relieved by a ſecond bleed- <lb/>ing, after which it recovered by
          degrees to <lb/>perfect health. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="56"/>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE XXX. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Leyden</hi>, on the 4th of February, <lb/>1769, as <hi
            rend="italic">Jacobus Clavan</hi>, a Tanner's jour- <lb/>ney-man, twenty three years of
          age, was <lb/>ſtepping into a boat to help his ſuper- <lb/>annuated father to row, he
          miſſed his ſtep, <lb/>fell into the water, went down, and com- <lb/>ing up again, he cried
          out, <q rend="italic">I am loſt! </q> then <lb/>ſunk, and remained at the bottom. His
          <lb/>poor father could do no more than feebly <lb/>to call for help. A quarter of an hour
          <lb/>elapſed before he was got out of the water, <lb/>and on ſhore. No ſigns of life
          appeared: <lb/>a good deal more time was loſt before it <lb/>was agreed upon to carry him
          into a houſe, <lb/>and ere he was received into one: and in <lb/>this way half an hour
          paſſed from his firſt <lb/>falling into the water, before any treat- <lb/>ment was
          attempted, when Dr. <hi rend="italic">Jac. <lb/>Smazen</hi> gave him his aſſiſtance by
          ordering <lb/>him to be ſtripped before a good fire, co- <lb/>vered with blankets, and
          rubbed all over: <pb n="55"/>
          <lb/>this was followed with opening a vein in <lb/>each arm, the orifice in the firſt
          having <lb/>yielded but a few drops of blood; but the <lb/>other flowing freely, ſome
          ſmall motion <lb/>was perceived in the body; a little brandy <lb/>was then poured into his
          mouth, and he <lb/>was chafed with ſome more. With this <lb/>aſſiſtance, and the loſs of
          twelve ounces of <lb/>blood, he became ſenſible, threw up ſome <lb/>phlegm, ſeemed
          violently oppreſſed, and <lb/>complained of a great pain in his head and <lb/>breaſt. He
          was then put into a warm bed, <lb/>a cordial was given him, and afterwards a <lb/>meſs of
          buttered beer and bread, with which, <lb/>and ſome reſt, he became ſo much better,
          <lb/>that he was carried home in leſs than nine <lb/>hours from the beginning of the
          accident. <lb/>He did not however recover very faſt, for <lb/>it was more than three days
          before he ac- <lb/>quired his uſual ſtrength. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="56"/>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE XXXI. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Amſterdam</hi>, on the 17th of November, <lb/>1769, it happened,
          that as <hi rend="italic">Antony Witneven</hi>, <lb/>a porter, was leaning againſt ſome
          baſkets <lb/>by the water-ſide, probably ſomewhat in <lb/>liquor, they gave way, and he
          fell into the <lb/>Canal. When he was got out by ſome of <lb/>his fellow porters, they
          pronounced him <lb/>dead:—they nevertheleſs carried him to a <lb/>beercellar, ſet him upon
          his head, ſhook him, <lb/>and gave hime ſome farther rough and very <lb/>improper
          uſage:—notwithſtanding which, <lb/>by ſome warmth and rubbing, he gave <lb/>ſigns of life,
          and recovered in ſome degree, <lb/>but in two days time he died. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This, and other inſtances, help to ſhew <lb/>that a recovery is found more difficult,
          <lb/>where the patient has been much addicted <lb/>to liquor, and where the firſt
          treatment has <lb/>been preceded by rough uſage. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="57"/>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE XXXII. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>IN the ſuburbs of <hi rend="italic">Groningen</hi>, on the <lb/>19th of November,
          1769, the ſon of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Caſper Boſchman</hi>, a boy of nine years
          <lb/>old, waſhing his hands at a hole cut <lb/>in the ice, fell in, and ſlid forward about
          <lb/>eight feet under it. As ſoon as a younger <lb/>brother of his had given the alarm by
          his <lb/>running to fetch a pole, the boy was ſought <lb/>for with it; and his father
          returning from <lb/>church, informed of the accident, ran to <lb/>the place, got into the
          hole, broke the <lb/>ice with his hands, breaſt, and ſhoulders, <lb/>notwithſtanding its
          being two inches thick, <lb/>and having found his child at laſt, ran <lb/>home with it
          upon his arms, ſhaking it <lb/>as he went, though to all appearance dead. <lb/>He ſtill
          ran about with it for a time, in <lb/>the ſame manner, at home, whilſt a fire <lb/>was
          lighting, and then made two women <lb/>ſit down with it before the fire, to rub it
          <lb/>all over with warm cloths, eſpecially along <pb n="58"/>
          <lb/>the back bone, and to ſlap the ſoles of its <lb/>feet with their hands. Soon after
          this <lb/>treatment the child ſeemed to breathe a <lb/>little; and then it was put to bed,
          with a <lb/>ſtone bottle of hot water at its breaſt and <lb/>hands, and heated bricks were
          put to its <lb/>back and feet. As the child recovered, the <lb/>father made it take ſome
          brandy with <lb/>melted butter, which made it puke up <lb/>ſome water and blood; but by
          repeating <lb/>the doſe ſome of it ſtayed upon its ſto- <lb/>mach: ſoon after it appeared
          delirious by <lb/>intervals, which however went off; and <lb/>it recovered gradually
          during the courſe of <lb/>ſeveral days, at the end of which its <lb/>ſtrength returned
          entirely. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE XXXIII. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In the large Canal, near the Town of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ouderkerk</hi>, the <hi
            rend="italic">Trekſchuit</hi> going from <hi rend="italic">Gouda</hi>
          <lb/>to <hi rend="italic">Amſterdam</hi>, in the night, it happened on <lb/>the 22d of
          December, 1769, that one <hi rend="italic">Jan <lb/>Valk</hi>, a bulky man, advanced in
          years, a <pb n="59"/>
          <lb/>paſſenger, fell over-board, ſunk and re- <lb/>mained a quarter of an hour under
          water, <lb/>before the boat could be ſtopped, turned, <lb/>and he got out. As ſoon as he
          was taken <lb/>into the <hi rend="italic">ſchuit</hi>, a ſhopkeeper from <hi rend="italic"
            >Rotter- <lb/>dam</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Pieter Knuijſting</hi>, the perſon who was
          <lb/>ſeated by him before he fell in, took charge <lb/>of him, laid him on cuſhions upon
          the <lb/>middle bench, and deſired ſuch of the <lb/>paſſengers as ſmoked Tobacco, to fill
          <lb/>and light their pipes; of which he made <lb/>ſuch good uſe, that after blowing up
          <lb/>the vapour of ſeven pipes into the inteſtines <lb/>of the patient, he gave ſome ſigns
          of life, <lb/>and brought up a few mouthfuls of water. <lb/>After uſing ſeven more pipes,
          and being <lb/>ſupplied with the handkerchiefs of the <lb/>paſſengers, warmed by means of
          the ſtoves <lb/>generally uſed in the <hi rend="italic">Trekſchuits</hi>, he <lb/>rubbed
          the patient's breaſt and belly with <lb/>them for above half an hour, and by the <lb/>time
          they arrived at the town, he began to <lb/>ſit up, and ſoon after was led into a tavern,
          <lb/>where being undreſſed, he was put to bed <pb n="60"/>
          <lb/>in warm blankets; but not gathering <lb/>warmth, and having complained of exceſ-
          <lb/>ſive cold, a ſtone bottle with hot water <lb/>was laid to his feet, and therewith at
          the <lb/>end of two hours treatment he was much <lb/>recovered: but as ſoon as the town
          gates <lb/>were opened, and a ſurgeon could be got, <lb/>he was let blood, and he
          recovered ſo well <lb/>as to be able to return home in the evening <lb/>of the ſame day in
          another <hi rend="italic">ſchuit</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE XXXIV. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Rotterdam</hi>, on the 31ſt of January, <lb/>1770, the ſtreets
          being ſlippery, it happened <lb/>that <hi rend="italic">Johanna Onkruid</hi>, a Woman of
          about <lb/>fifty-four years of age, drawing water out <lb/>of the Canal before her door,
          fell into the <lb/>water, and ſlipped under the ice without <lb/>being obſerved, and there
          being a lock <lb/>near to the place, ſhe was ſlowly con- <lb/>veyed towards it by the
          current of the <lb/>water: ſhe was afterwards diſcovered by <lb/>another woman alſo
          drawing water, who <lb/>gave the alarm, and had her taken out as <pb n="61"/>
          <lb/>ſoon as poſſible. She was carried home, <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Hendrick van
            Schaardenburgh</hi>, a Sur- <lb/>geon, took charge of her. He firſt poured <lb/>ſome
          brandy into her mouth, had her ſtrip- <lb/>ped, had ſome aired things put on her, laid
          <lb/>her in a warm bed, and put ſtone bottles <lb/>with hot water near her body. After
          that, <lb/>he uſed the Tobacco-vapour pipe, and got <lb/>the body well rubbed all over;
          which being <lb/>done with aſſiduity, for half an hour, he <lb/>then obtained the firſt
          ſigns of life, gave <lb/>her ſome cordial drops in a glaſs of wine, <lb/>and went on as
          before. She began to move <lb/>reſtleſsly after a time, threw up ſome water, <lb/>coughed,
          and ſeemed much oppreſſed, tho' <lb/>ſhe had not then quite recovered her ſenſes. <lb/>She
          got ſomewhat to drink, but could not <lb/>keep it upon her ſtomach; ſhe then had an
          <lb/>evacuation of another kind, and deſired to <lb/>be allowed to ſleep, which ſhe did
          tolerably <lb/>well for ſome hours, but then complained <lb/>of an oppreſſion and great
          pain at her breaſt, <lb/>which leſſened by ſlow degrees, and ſhe re- <lb/>covered, having
          long been tender and aſth- <pb n="62"/>
          <lb/>matic, for which reaſon this ſurgeon did <lb/>not bleed her, but uſed all means to
          re- <lb/>ſtore her to ſtrength ſpeedily, ſhe being <lb/>the only ſupport of an old,
          decrepit, help- <lb/>leſs mother. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE XXXV. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Neykerk</hi> in Friſeland, on the 24th of <lb/>January, 1770,
            <hi rend="italic">Aafke Symons</hi>, wife of <hi rend="italic">Jan <lb/>Reinders</hi>,
          fell into the Town Canal, lay un- <lb/>der the ice for more than half an hour, be-
          <lb/>fore it could be broke enough to get her <lb/>out; and by proper and diligent
          treatment <lb/>afterwards, ſhe was brought to life again, <lb/>and ſpeedily recovered.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE XXXVI. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Hilverſum</hi> in Friſeland, on the 10th <lb/>of February, 1770,
          the ſon of <hi rend="italic">Myndert van <lb/>Goch</hi>, a child of about two years old,
          fell <lb/>into a pit that had little more than a <lb/>foot of water in it, yet a
          ſufficient quan- <lb/>tity to drown the child, which lay in it <lb/>with its head down and
          its heels upwards. <pb n="63"/>
          <lb/>A man coming paſt, after it had lain about <lb/>half an hour, took it out of the pit,
          and <lb/>carried it home, where it was laid by for <lb/>another half-hour, as dead; when
          Doctor <lb/><hi rend="italic">Francis Cordemans</hi> propoſed to attempt its
          <lb/>recovery. He proceeded in the uſual man- <lb/>ner, brought it to life in ſome hours,
          and <lb/>reſtored it to health in a few days. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE XXXVII. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Rotterdam</hi>, on the 26th of February, <lb/>1770, <hi
            rend="italic">Jan Kok</hi>, a Bruſh-maker's lad, of <lb/>fourteen years of age, drawing
          water out of <lb/>the Canal early in the morning before it <lb/>was light, fell in, ſunk
          under a boat, and <lb/>remained there for half an hour. His <lb/>maſter having ſought for
          him elſewhere, <lb/>at laſt groped for him with a hook about <lb/>the place where he
          generally took up <lb/>water, and having found him, had him <lb/>carried home as dead; but
            <hi rend="italic">Jan Hofman</hi>, a <lb/>Surgeon, ſent for, recovered him, and by <pb
            n="64"/>
          <lb/>proper means reſtored him ſo perfectly that <lb/>he returned to his work in a few
          days. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>CASE XXXVIII. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>AT <hi rend="italic">Gouda</hi> in South Holland, it hap- <lb/>pened on the 3d of
          March, 1770, that a <lb/>girl of four years and a half old, the <lb/>daughter of <hi
            rend="italic">Cornelis Krap</hi>, was taken out <lb/>of a canal drowned, and brought
          home. <lb/>She was thought to be dead, was ſtripped, <lb/>rolled up in a ſheet, and laid
          by to be <lb/>buried. But ſome perſons coming in a <lb/>while after, propoſed to make a
          trial of re- <lb/>covery, though ſhe was quite cold and ſtiff. <lb/>They then proceeded to
          treat her, accord- <lb/>ing to the Society's Inſtructions, very aſſi- <lb/>duouſly for the
          ſpace of two hours and a <lb/>half, when they had the ſatisfaction of re- <lb/>ſtoring her
          to life. </p>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="75"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
