<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Graham: The guardian goddess of health</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>James Graham</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">The guardian goddess of health: or, the whole art of preventing and
              curing diseases; and of enjoying peace and hapiness of body and of mind to the longest
              possible period of human existence: with precepts for the preservation and exaltation
              of personal beauty and loveliness. To which is added, an account of the composition,
              preparation, and properties of the three great medicines prepared and dispensed at the
              Temple of Health, Adelphi, and at the Temple of Hymen, Pall-Mall, London. By James
              Graham, M.D.This book is of so much real importance to the health and happiness of
              each individual among the public, that tho' it contains more matter or reading than
              most two shilling pamphlets, it is ordered to be sold for only two pence; - a price
              very inadequate to the prime</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T141037</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T141037"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for the people: and by the rosy heralds of health
                  distributed.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1780</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="39"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="5"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3308524129</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K111051.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: medicine"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front> </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
      <head rend="indent hanging italic"><lb/>A ſhort Deſcription of the Compoſition, Preparation
        and <w part="I">Pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">perties</w> of the THREE GREAT MEDICINES prepared
        <lb/>and diſpenſed at the TEMPLE OF HEALTH, in the centre <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic"><hi
            rend="sc">Royal Terrace, Adelphi</hi>, London:</hi> and which <lb/>are now ſold in
        almoſt every city and great town in the world; <lb/>being perhaps the firſt advertiſed
        Medicines that ſovereign <lb/>Princes, and crowned Heads! were ever adviſed, or by their
        <lb/>Phyſicians permitted to take. </head>
      <p rend="align-center italic"><lb/>(With ample Directions for uſing the Medicines.) </p>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>I. ELECTRICAL ÆTHER! <lb/><hi rend="sc">Or, an aggregate
            compound of the most active faculties <lb/>of the material soul of the universe.
          </hi></head>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HIS admirable Compoſition is one of
          the pureſt and moſt <lb/>ſubtil eſſences in nature. It is a combination, or <w part="I"
            >concen-</w><lb/><w part="F">tration</w> of all her elementary powers, and vivifying
          influences: <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> an eſſence extracted by air,
          magnetiſm, and the electrical or <lb/>celeſtial fire, from the richeſt oriental aromatics,
          &amp;c. with the <lb/>balmieſt and moſt active æther. A few of the richeſt, mildeſt,
          <lb/>and moſt cordial roots, barks, ſeeds, flowers, fruits, gums and <lb/>balſams, which
          flow into this great metropolis from the four <w part="I">quar-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ters</w> of the globe, eſpecially thoſe from Aſia, and the choiceſt of <lb/>the Britiſh
          ſimples, are under my own immediate inſpection ſelected, <lb/>properly prepared, and put
          into maſſy glaſs veſſels, and upon them <lb/>is poured a due quantity of the fineſt
          ætherial ſpirit. They are <lb/>then placed in one of the great metallic globes on the dome
          of the <lb/>electrical Temples of Health and of Hymen, in the Apollo and other
          <lb/>apartments of thoſe GREAT and moſt uſeful Inſtitutions, to be acted <lb/>upon by the
          celeſtial fire, &amp;c. and laſtly, the eſſence is purified by <lb/>filtration upon a new
          principle, which prevents all poſſibility of the <lb/>fineſt and moſt volatile parts
          evaporating. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>The globes are entirely lined with metal in the in—as well
          as <lb/>on the outſide. They are twelve in number, each containing full <lb/>thirty-ſix
          gallons. The glaſs veſſels too, are covered with metal, <lb/>incloſed in curious magnetic
          caſes, and their ſtoppers are pierced <lb/>with glaſs tubes and thick metal rods, which
          end in a multitude of <lb/>points, from which ſtreams of the electrical fire, &amp;c.—are
            <w part="I">conti-</w><lb/><w part="F">nually</w> pouring in upon the æther and
          aromatics, in luminous and <lb/>moſt glorious ſtreams. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>The immenſe quantity of this vivifying reſtorative fire,
          &amp;c. which is <lb/>accumulated in theſe Temples, flows thus into the medicines through
          <lb/>the rods and tubes above-mentioned, which with the magnetic <w part="I"
            >efflu-</w><lb/><w part="F">vium</w> paſſes even through the outſide of the glaſſes,
          &amp;c. to the <w part="I">ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtances</w> contained in them: for
          each of the four great globes <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">comes</w>
          <pb xml:id="page_3" n="3"/><lb/>a genial, <hi rend="italic">cool</hi> OVEN, glowing with
          the plenitude of theſe <w part="I">ſa-</w><lb/><w part="F">lutary</w>, vital, and
          harmonious influences. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>By this curious and moſt wonderful proceſs, like every
          operation <lb/>which I perform on my patients, with this, or with any other part <lb/>of
          my aſtoniſhing and tremendous apparatus, (which, <w part="I">altoge-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ther</w>, in both the Temples, occupies in fact twenty rooms) I have it in
          <lb/>abſolute command and ſubjection acting arbitrarily or at pleaſure <lb/>on the
          medicines,—on my patients—or on any part of their body or <lb/>limbs particularly
          affected, in any quantity, or with any degree of <lb/>power, according to the nature of
          the ſubſtances, or as the various <lb/>conſtitutions, &amp;c.—of my patients require: in
          ſhort, the whole of <lb/>the apparatus employed in making the three Great Medicines <w
            part="I">men-</w><lb/><w part="F">tioned</w> in this Deſcription, if ſolid metal, would
          weigh conſiderably <lb/>above ſeven hundred thouſand pounds. After the above account of
          <lb/>the compoſition and preparation of the electrical æther, it would <lb/>be quite
          unneceſſary for me to dwell on its manifold and ſurprizing <lb/>virtues. Philoſophers,
          phyſicians and chemiſts muſt plainly ſee, <lb/>that by the above means, a rich, yet SIMPLE
            <hi rend="italic">homogene,</hi> and <w part="I">VI-</w><lb/><w part="F">VIFYING</w>
          QUINTESSENCE muſt be produced,—an utter enemy <lb/>to diſeaſes and corruption,—and a
          cordial peace-maker in all ſtrife <lb/>and diſcord in the human body! Theſe facts muſt be
          too obvious <lb/>to <hi rend="italic">every</hi> perſon of even a very common
          underſtanding, to require <lb/>commenting upon. I ſhall juſt ſay that for preventing every
            <w part="I">ſpe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cies</w> of infection, and for curing all low,
          nervous, lingering and <lb/>putrid diſeaſes, nothing on earth can equal this moſt noble <w
            part="I">quin-</w><lb/><w part="F">teſſence</w> which I chuſe to call, ſimply,—<hi
            rend="italic">Electrical Æther;</hi> and as it <lb/>is much eaſier and wiſer to prevent
          diſeaſes, than to cure them, <lb/>I ſhall point out, very briefly, its uſes in the firſt
          place as a <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ventive</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>Firſt, then, all perſons who frequent public places, and who
          <lb/>regard their health, ought never to be without a vial of the <w part="I"
            >electri-</w><lb/><w part="F">cal</w> æther, even in their pocket—thoſe eſpecially who
          are ſubject to <lb/>catch colds and dangerous diſorders,—or who have weakneſs and
          <lb/>oppreſſions at their breaſt and ſtomach,—or a nervous ſyſtem <w part="I"
            >irri-</w><lb/><w part="F">table</w> and relaxed. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>It is well known, by every perſon who knows any thing at all
          of <lb/>medicine or philoſophy, that the air of any place after it has been <lb/>breathed,
          and charged with the phlogiſticated or mephitic breath, <lb/>perſpiration, &amp;c. of even
          the cleaneſt, ſoundeſt and healthieſt perſons, <lb/>—becomes not only altogether unfit for
          reſpiration, but likewiſe <w part="I">abſo-</w><lb/><w part="F">utely</w> and highly
          poiſonous. But how much more dangerous and <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >wholeſome</w> muſt it be, to draw into our lungs, perhaps for ſeveral hours
          <lb/>together, the foul and putrid exhalations which reek from the dirty <w part="I"
            >bo-</w><lb/><w part="F">dies</w> and garments—ſecret ſores—and corrupted lungs crammed
          up in <lb/>places of public amuſement!—I am not at all ſurprized at the ſevere
          <lb/>diſeaſes and ſudden deaths which happen among both young and <pb xml:id="page_4"
            n="4"/><lb/>old. No; but I am aſtoniſhed that <hi rend="sc">many more</hi> do not
          happen; <lb/>and that ſo many rational beings ſhould ſubmit to the drudgery <lb/>and
          danger, not to mention the expence, of attending crouded <lb/>—nonſenſical—public places.
          But as it is in vain to oppoſe the <w part="I">ty-</w><lb/><w part="F">rannic</w> force of
          faſhion, or to ſhake off the mighty influence of <lb/>HABIT, which, with abſolute ſway
          govern every thing that hath <lb/>the breath of life, I would adviſe every prudent perſon
          before they <lb/>go into ſuch places to fortify their body, and harmonize their mind,
          <lb/>with taking a tea ſpoonful of the electrical æther, or nervous <w part="I"
            >æthe-</w><lb/><w part="F">rial</w> balſam on ſugar, or in any thing they like beſt—and
          even to <lb/>ſmell now and then to the former in ſuch places when they <w part="I"
            >ſuſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">pect</w> danger, or when they find themſelves languid or
          oppreſſed. <lb/>—By theſe precautions, many hundreds of the nobility and gentry in
          <lb/>Europe, experience daily from it the happieſt effects; and when they <lb/>return home
          faint, relaxed and exhauſted, from over heated rooms, <lb/>public or private; from
          enervating indulgencies too, <hi rend="italic">(in ſacrificing to <lb/>Venus or
            Bacchus)</hi> or from violent agitations of body and of mind—they <lb/>are preſently
          refreſhed, recruited, compoſed, and invigorated by <w part="I">ſmel-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ling</w> to the electrical æther for a few minutes, by taking a tea ſpoonful <lb/>or
          two of <hi rend="sc">it</hi>, (<hi rend="sc">or rather</hi>, of the nervous ætherial
          balſam) in a glaſs of <lb/>brandy,—of wine,—or of cold water:—or even by pouring a <w
            part="I">lit-</w><lb/><w part="F">tle</w> of the electrical æther into a baſon or quart
          mug half filled <lb/>with hot water, coffee, green tea, or an infuſion of aromatic <w
            part="I">Bri-</w><lb/><w part="F">tiſh</w> herbs, flowers, &amp;c. and breathing over it
          for a few minutes. By <lb/>theſe means, under God! ſweet, ſound, and refreſhing ſleep, and
          <lb/>mental tranquility, are with certainty procured,—and all <w part="I"
            >poſſibi-</w><lb/><w part="F">lity</w> of diſeaſe or decay, effectually warded off:—and
          theſe happy <lb/>effects are rendered ſtill more certain, kindly and laſting, if the
          <lb/>perſons will waſh or bathe their face, neck, hands, feet, and <w part="I"
            >pri-</w><lb/><w part="F">vate</w> parts—<hi rend="sc">especially the latter</hi>, with
          pure <hi rend="sc">cold</hi> water—or <lb/>with milk and water—about blood warm. This
          ſimple and <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">lightful</w> affair of bathing the private
          parts and fundament every night <lb/>and morning, ſummer and winter, in ſickneſs and in
          health, in <lb/>cold milk or water—is of more importance to the bodily health,
          <lb/>youthful beauty, and ſweet deſireableneſs of men and <hi rend="sc">women</hi>, than
          <lb/>any thing I can poſſibly mention or inculcate. If this moſt ſalutary <lb/>practice of
          applying even partially, cold or at moſt tepid water or <lb/>milk, to the ſurface of the
          body and limbs,—if ſimplicity, <w part="I">modera-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>,
          regularity and temperance, in the indulgence of every <w part="I">appe-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tite</w>, and in the gratification of every deſire—in a word, if prudence,
          <lb/>wiſdom, delicacy, virtue, and that genuine religion which flows <lb/>warm and ſilent
          in an everlaſting and ſupremely cordial circulation, <lb/>between THE PERFECTION OF EVERY
          EXCELLENCE— <lb/>THE ETERNAL SOURCE OF LIFE, LOVE, LIGHT AND <lb/>HAPPINESS!—and the
          benevolent—the melting—the enlarged <lb/>human breaſt!—If this ſterling—this all-bleſſing
          religion <lb/>which knows no diſtinction of ſect, church, age or country— <pb
            xml:id="page_5" n="5"/><lb/>and whoſe ſignet of divinity is liberty, forbearance and
          univerſal <lb/>love! — if theſe, with their white-robed attendants who came <lb/>down from
          heaven and who will conduct us thither—namely, <w part="I">Inno-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cence</w>, Activity, and Peace—were permitted to direct and controul <lb/>our thoughts,
          words and actions daily, from our birth to the laſt <lb/>day of life—the image of God
          which he ſtampt on mankind at their <lb/>original creation would be in a great meaſure
          recovered and <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerved—we</w> ſhould continue very long
          and very happily in this <w part="I">tranſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ent—probationary</w>
          ſtate of exiſtence—a hundred years ſeeming but <lb/>as one ſummer's day, while with a
          gradual deſcent, we would glide <lb/>gently and ſweetly down the hill of life, under the
          ſerene and lucid <lb/>influence of its evening sky. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>Behold, here, in a few words, my courteous and intelligent
            <w part="I">rea-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w>, a complete ſyſtem, or the whole Art of
          Health, beauty, <w part="I">love-</w><lb/><w part="F">liness</w>, long-life and happineſs,
          temporal and eternal; <hi rend="sc">which</hi>, if <lb/>properly and conſtantly attended
          to, phyſicians and dignified <w part="I">clergy-</w><lb/><w part="F">men</w>, would be
          almoſt as unneceſſary in the world, as ſoldiers and <lb/>ſolicitors; and as are ſuch codes
          of laws and diſcipline, in church and <lb/>in ſtate as they are at preſent <hi rend="sc"
            >administered</hi> in almoſt every nation on <lb/>earth,—which are in general dark,
          unreaſonable, unjuſt and <w part="I">diaboli-</w><lb/><w part="F">cal</w>, and extremely
          contradictory to the ſpirit, and advancement of true <lb/>religion, ſound policy, and of
          the Healing Art, however agreeable to <lb/>the letter of the law, the canons of the
          churches, or the practice <lb/>of the Royal Colleges of Phyſicians. Millions of the human
            <w part="I">ſpe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cies</w> have felt, and millions do now feel, too
          ſenſibly the truth of <lb/>this aſſertion.—O Law! O Phyſic! O Divinity! when—when will you
          <lb/>undergo a neceſſary ordeal—a thorough, a rational reformation I— <lb/>As to WARS—I
          will not mention them; for my whole frame <w part="I">qui-</w><lb/><w part="F">vers</w>
          with horror even at the thought of them.—Carnage!— bank-<lb/>ruptcies, poverty! —
          devaſtation! —hunger and thirſt,—horrible <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >prehenſions!—forced</w> from our native land;—and all theſe for <lb/>what? why, for the
          honor and Glory of the God of mercy and peace <lb/>—for a punctilio of what is called
          national honor;—too often indeed <lb/>for nothing at all—to obtain an eventual evil—or for
          the acquiſition <lb/>of the ſhadow of a ſhade. I could almoſt venture I think to prophecy,
          <lb/>that the time will come, tho' perhaps it is very diſtant, when the <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">tereſts</w> and differences of nations, and what is called the
          ballance of <lb/>power, will be ſettled by leſs horrible—leſs unnatural—leſs diabolical
          <lb/>means than fire and ſword; and that the children of thoſe men, naval <lb/>and
          military, who are now trained up to, and who glory in ruin and <lb/>devaſtation, carnage,
          theft, depredation and murder, will be taught <lb/>to adorn the ſciences, embelliſh the
          arts, or to illuminate the human <lb/>mind—inſtead of hewing down like ſavage monſters,
          their fellow <lb/>creatures—or of eating up, like drones, the bread of the children of
          <lb/>induſtry. But I beg pardon for making this digreſſion; I beg <lb/>pardon, I mean, of
          their Worſhips and High Mightineſſes, the <lb/><hi rend="sc">clergy</hi>!!! the <hi
            rend="sc">Heroes</hi> or <hi rend="sc">men of war</hi>!! the <hi rend="sc">lawyers</hi>!
          and the <pb xml:id="page_6" n="6"/><lb/>phyſicians, and I will now return to finiſh the
          deſcriptive ſketch of <lb/>the nature and properties of my electrical æther. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>In the courſe of laſt winter I had frequent opportunities of
            <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerving</w> the good effects of this eſſence, and of
          the nervous ætherial <lb/>balſam, upon many Ladies and Gentlemen who were uncommonly
          <lb/>ſuſceptible of the evils which ariſe from the cold rawneſs and fogs <lb/>of this
          variable climate; occaſioning rehumatic complaints in the <lb/>joints, and ſtill more
          particularly in the head and face, with <w part="I">ſwel-</w><lb/><w part="F">lings</w> of
          the cheek and gums, ſore throats, and tickling defluxions <lb/>on the breaſt and lungs. By
          the uſe of theſe two medicines, <lb/>and by keeping the body open with the Imperial Pills,
          thoſe <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">plaints</w> which formerly had confined them
          almoſt conſtantly thro' <lb/>the winter to the houſe were happily prevented; and in others
          <lb/>who were ſeized as uſual, the cough, ſoreneſs of the breaſt, <w part="I"
            >fe-</w><lb/><w part="F">vers</w> and inquietudes were ſpeedily carried off by the
          gentle and <lb/>moderate uſe of theſe precious, and moſt friendly medicines. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>But the electrical æther is more eſpecially neceſſary for
          thoſe who <lb/>attend courts of juſtice, public meetings, ſick perſons, and thoſe
          <lb/>places where hundreds of common people are crammed up in the <lb/>galleries, &amp;c.
          Nothing in nature <hi rend="italic">is</hi> or <hi rend="italic">can</hi> be equal to the
            <w part="I">electri-</w><lb/><w part="F">cal</w> æther, the nervous ætherial balſam, and
          the cool open air in <lb/>curing all, even the very worſt, and moſt confirmed ſpecies of
            <w part="I">low-</w><lb/><w part="F">nervous-putrid</w> fevers; ulcerated and gangrenous
          ſore throats; <lb/>the ſmall-pox,—mortifications, and the whole tribe of putrid <w
            part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſumptive</w>, dropſical, ſcorbutic and paralytic
          diſorders. By only <w part="I">ſmell-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> to, or breathing over
          the æther, and taking now and then a tea <lb/>ſpoonful of it, or of the balſam in a cup of
          white wine,—tar water, <lb/>or common cold water,—the patient always finds inſtant relief,
          and <lb/>generally a perfect cure; while thoſe about him, or in the houſe, <lb/>are
          effectually ſecured from that dangerous malignancy which often <lb/>ſweeps off whole
          families into one common and untimely grave. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>As the effects, or rather the medicines themſelves, fly in a
            <w part="I">mo-</w><lb/><w part="F">ment</w> with the ſwiftneſs of light from the
          ſun—over the whole <lb/>ſyſtem, no other cordial whatever in nature has been found ſo <w
            part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtantaneouſly</w> and ſo laſtingly to recruit the
          ſtrength and ſpirits <lb/>after great fatigue, or violent exertions of body or of mind, <w
            part="I">eſpe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cially</w> in Venereal pleaſures.—They refreſh,
          brace, compoſe, <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">fort</w>, and literally ſpeaking, <hi
            rend="sc">illuminate</hi>, all the bodily,—and thro'<lb/> them—all the mental faculties;
          in ſhort, in all ſevere <w part="I">ill-</w><lb/><w part="F">neſſes</w>, in ſinkings, and
          in faintings in conſequence of ſevere <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">cruciating</w>
          pain, profuſe evacuations of blood, &amp;c. and draining <lb/>weakneſſes of every kind, or
          from whatever cauſes proceeding, <lb/>theſe medicines (eſpecially the nervous ætherial
          balſam) are <lb/>ALWAYS found to produce the moſt aſtoniſhing good effects, <lb/>which are
          manifeſted to the patient, and to every one preſent, <lb/>even the firſt minute they are
          uſed. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <pb xml:id="page_7" n="7"/>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>II. NERVOUS ÆTHERIAL BALSAM! <lb/><hi rend="sc">Or, the
            restorative ætherial oil, for decayed and worn out<lb/>constitutions. </hi></head>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>F the reader can conceive of the
          richeſt—pureſt—and moſt <lb/>ſtrengthening parts of all the cordial and nouriſhing things
          he <lb/>is acquainted with in nature—being extracted, purified, exalted, <lb/>harmonized
          and concentrated into a ſmall compaſs,—he may alſo <lb/>conceive of the nature and
          properties of this precious balſam. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>The Peruvian bark, cinnamon, ſaffron, caſtor, lavender,
          ſage, <w part="I">roſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">mary</w>, red-roſe-buds, electrical nitre,
          ambergriſe, myrrh, amber, and<lb/> benjamin;—the balſams of Tolu and Gilead,—and various
          other <w part="I">bal-</w><lb/><w part="F">my</w> bracers, and fragrant aromatic
          ſtrengtheners are ſelected with my <lb/>own hand, and prepared under my own eye: a pure
          ætherial <w part="I">eſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſence</w>, combined with a certain portion of
          the richeſt and moſt <w part="I">ge-</w><lb/><w part="F">nuine</w> wine, is then poured
          upon the ingredients, and being <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">perly</w> mixed and
          ſecured, they are placed to macerate and digeſt, <lb/>like the electrical æther, under the
          united influences of <w part="I">dephlogiſti-</w><lb/><w part="F">cated</w> or vivifying
          air, æther, magnetiſm and electricity, in the <lb/>great globes which compoſe the
          tremendous pyramids on the domes <lb/>of the Temples. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>From the preſent general ſtile of living—from the luxury,
          folly, <lb/>diſſipation, and enervating indulgences of perſons, perhaps of every
          <lb/>rank, the diſorders which now a days prevail, and which haraſs and <lb/>wear out
          human life, are ſuch as proceed either from condenſed <lb/>fluids, morbid humours, and
          heterogeneous viſcidities in the blood <lb/>or lymph;—or, from irritation, relaxation and
          debility of the <w part="I">ſo-</w><lb/><w part="F">lids</w> and nervous ſyſtem. The
          former however complicated,—how∣ever various in their appearances, are very juſtly
          attributed to <w part="I">vene-</w><lb/><w part="F">real</w>, ſcorbutic, gouty, or
          ſcrophulous humours—and the latter are <lb/>promiſcuouſly and not improperly termed
          nervous; they ariſe chiefly <lb/>from tepid ſoft luxurious and artificial living,
          enervating <w part="I">indulgen-</w><lb/><w part="F">cies</w>, I mean in venereal
          pleaſures, and from drinking daily that <lb/>agonizing yet bewitching poiſon, foreign tea;
          and are often ſo <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">treſſing</w> and oppreſſive to the
          miſerable patient,—as to make riches <lb/>and honours, and even life itſelf a burthen—a
          weary and heavy <w part="I">bur-</w><lb/><w part="F">then</w>, which they would
          gladly,—nay even ſometimes—impiouſly and <lb/>fatally venture to lay down. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>In the former caſes, namely, in viſcidities and impurities
          of the <lb/>blood and juices, from ſcorbutic, venereal, gouty and rheumatic <lb/>humours,
          the Imperial Pills, by and by to be deſcribed, will be <lb/>found in general the ſafeſt
          and moſt certain antidote: and in the <lb/>latter, viz. in all nervous, putrid and
          debilitated habits, this nervous <pb xml:id="page_8" n="8"/><lb/>ætherial balſam is
          without exception the mildeſt and moſt effectual <lb/>remedy that can be met with in the
          whole circle of nature!—for in <lb/>all nervous complaints and weakneſſes;—in all
          convulſions, <w part="I">epi-</w><lb/><w part="F">leptic</w>, apoplectic and hyſteric
          fits, in all obſtructions and <w part="I">irregula-</w><lb/><w part="F">rities</w> in the
          monthly periods of women, particularly at the two <w part="I">cri-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tical</w> and moſt dangerous periods of commencement and final <w part="I"
            >ceſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſation</w>, this Balſam, the Electrical Æther, or the Imperial
          Pills, are <lb/>abſolutely infallable in producing the happieſt effects. For I will
          <lb/>venture to ſay, that there is ſcarce a menſtrual obſtruction in the
          <lb/>world—however complicated, or however confirmed, but what will <lb/>be overcome and
          effectually removed by taking three tea ſpoonfuls of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">electrical
            æther</hi> and as much of the Nerv. Æth. Balſam, mixed <lb/>both together in a pint of
          cold water for three ſucceſſive mornings, <lb/>if the patient is plump and ſanguine; but
          if on the contrary, ſhe is <lb/>lean, cold and languid, ſhe muſt take three tea ſpoonfuls
            <hi rend="italic">of the</hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">nervous ætherial balsam</hi>, and the like quantity of the Electrical
          <lb/>Æther, thrice every day in wine, ſpirits, or herb tea, and continue <lb/>it for only
          three days. In both caſes, and under theſe oppoſite <w part="I">cir-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cumſtances</w>, with due attention to the above diſtinctions, a perfect <lb/>cure will
          undoubtedly take place; eſpecially if plenty of the <w part="I">me-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >dicines</w> be rubbed on the loins and back bone, and in the former <lb/>caſe the
          application of cold water is made to THE PARTS, hands <lb/>and feet, for hours daily,—and
          in the latter caſe warm wine or <lb/>ſpirits and water—be applied daily in like manner.—In
          both, and <lb/>in every caſe, running about in the open air is earneſtly <w part="I"
            >recom-</w><lb/><w part="F">mended</w>.—But when the patient is too much weakened and <w
            part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">duced</w> from the <hi rend="italic">oppoſite
            cauſes,</hi>—namely, too long—too copious and <lb/>profuſe a flow,—and great paleneſs
          and debility brought on; —<hi rend="sc">rest</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">cool
          air,</hi>—the application to the parts, and indeed to every part of the <lb/>body and
          limbs, of cold milk and water, or red wine, and a courſe of <lb/>the nervous ætherial
          balſam, with an infuſion or tea of the Peruvian <lb/>bark, red roſe leaves, and a little
          nitre, with Briſtol or Spa water <lb/>—will build her up into a rock of ſnowy alabaſter,
          ſtudded with <lb/>roſes and ſtreaked with celeſtial blue, removing the cauſes of <w
            part="I">ſte-</w><lb/><w part="F">rility</w>, or barrenneſs,—making her a lovely and
          deſirable <w part="I">compa-</w><lb/><w part="F">nion!</w> —a healthy and a happy
          mother!—But for farther particulars <lb/>relative to theſe delicate and important matters,
          ſee my "Private <lb/>Medical Advice to Married Ladies and Gentlemen; to thoſe eſpecially
          <lb/>who are not bleſſed with children"—with full directions for <w part="I"
            >preven-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, or for ſpeedy and perfect recovery after
          miſcarriages and <w part="I">dan-</w><lb/><w part="F">gerous</w> lyings-in. To be had,
          compriſed and printed in two ſheets <lb/>folio, ſealed up, <hi rend="sc">alone</hi> at my
          Houſe in the Adelphi, and at the <lb/>Temple of Hymen, in Pall Mall, price only One
          Guinea. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>N. B. In the above, ſuch ſimple, natural, and effectual
          means <lb/>for removing the cauſes of barrenneſs in both ſexes as never were
          <lb/>recommended, or even thought of before, in any age or nation, <pb xml:id="page_9"
            n="9"/><lb/>—are pointed out;—and ſuch directions given, as will, if duly <w part="I"
            >at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tended</w> to, make man and wife ſweeter—lovelier—more amiable,
          <lb/>—and more <hi rend="sc">desireable</hi> in the eyes of one another. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>After what has been already ſaid, I need ſcarcely add, that
          in <lb/>all ſcarlet, miliary, jail, bilious, nervous, putrid, ſpotted and ma-<lb/>lignant
          fevers—eſpecially thoſe of the Eaſt and Weſt Indies, <w part="I">Ame-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >rica</w>, &amp;c. theſe medicines are abſolute and ſpeedy ſpecifics. A perſon
          <lb/>armed and provided with theſe, and with the genuine powder of <lb/>Dr. James, need
          not fear any inflammatory fever, or any low, <lb/>putrid, malignant, or biſious fever or
          complaint whatever; in any <lb/>climate, ſeaſon, or in any part of the terraqueous globe.
          Theſe <lb/>will be a moſt complete apothecary's ſhop, and nature, common <lb/>ſenſe, and
          the patient's own feelings—a <hi rend="italic">trio</hi> of the ſafeſt and wiſeſt
          <lb/>phyſicians. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>In every caſe, therefore, where the patient is low, faint,
          feeble <lb/>or emaciated, from ſcorbutic or venereal virus, a ſharp poverty— <lb/>or
          putrid diſſolution of the blood and juices;—or from want of a <lb/>due elaſtic tone of the
          ſolids—ariſing from a deficiency of the vital <w part="I">ſpi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >rits—or</w> of the balmy nervous fluid, this nervous ætherial balſam! <lb/>has not its
          equal in nature;—and this I aver <hi rend="sc">confidently</hi>, from <lb/>very much, and
          very happy experience in actual practice, which in <lb/>all things is the only infallible
          guide—the only incontrovertible <w part="I">evi-</w><lb/><w part="F">dence!</w> Thouſands
          by it alone, have been ſnatched from the grave: <lb/>and ſtill many more thouſands of the
          human ſpecies when languid <lb/>and worn out with diſeaſes, exceſſes, irregularities,
          enormities and <lb/>early imprudencies, have been ſuddenly built up into firm rocks
          <lb/>of blooming health, and intellectual happineſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>I ſhall conclude this ſhort account of this great medicine,
          by <lb/>obſerving, that in all leſſer nervous complaints and uneaſineſſes, <lb/>occaſioned
          by tea, coffee, adulterated wine, or pernicious liquors; <lb/>and in all thoſe little
          lingering fevers, heats and chillineſſes, and <lb/>thoſe tremors and quiverings of body,
          and reſtleſs anxieties, dread, <lb/>horrors, diſcontent and unſettledneſſes of mind, which
          proceed <lb/>merely from an irregular circulation of the blood, or from ſpaſms,
          <lb/>debility, or relaxation of the nervous ſyſtem,—this ætherial balſam <lb/>will always
          be found of immediate ſervice, and by a gentle— <lb/>perſevering courſe of it, and of the
          Imperial Pills, duly attending <lb/>to the directions given with them, a perfect and a
          laſting cure will <lb/>in general be obtained. Becauſe by them the blood and juices
          <lb/>are purified, ſweetened, tempered, and brought to a pure fluid <lb/>ſtate, while the
          ſolids are braced and ſtrengthened, and the nerves <lb/>ſheathed, nouriſhed, ſteadied and
          coiled up. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>Many fanciful, rich, and luxurious people, who are in fact
          in <lb/>good health, and who ought by no means to take this precious <lb/>ætherial balſam,
          or any other medicine, nevertheleſs accuſtom <pb xml:id="page_10" n="10"/><lb/>themſelves
          to take more or leſs of it, and even an imperial pill or two <lb/>every day;—with ſuch
          people, or when at any time they are taken <lb/>into a ſound and tranquil body, they
          produce no other operation or <lb/>ſenſation, than a more genial and brisker flow of the
          blood and animal <lb/>ſpirits,—and that ſpecies of contentment, thankfulneſs, and <w
            part="I">benevo-</w><lb/><w part="F">lent</w> gladneſs of heart, which makes us happy in
          ourſelves, and <w part="I">agree-</w><lb/><w part="F">able</w> to all about us: but where
          they meet with diſeaſes and corruption, <lb/>they encounter them with the boldneſs and
          majeſty of a lion, <w part="I">effec-</w><lb/><w part="F">thally</w> expelling them, and
          leaving a clean and a quiet houſe for health and happineſs to reſide in. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>The nervous ætherial balſam, then, is by very far, and
          without <lb/>exception, the moſt exhilerating, antiſpaſmodic, bracing, <w part="I"
            >reſtora-</w><lb/><w part="F">tive</w>, ſtrengthening, and conſequently antiſceptic
          medicine in the <lb/>world—infinitely ſuperior to the common tinctures of the bark, <w
            part="I">va-</w><lb/><w part="F">lerian</w>, caſtor, ſaffron, lavender, &amp;c.—and
          infinitely more cordial <lb/>and mild than the burning inflammatory ſalts, and fiery fetid
          ſpirits <lb/>of hartſhorn, eau de luce, ſal volatile, and all the liqueurs, drams,
          <lb/>and cordials, foreign and domeſtic, which only bewitch and give a <lb/>temporary
          relief, which muſt ſoon give way to additional horror, <lb/>darkneſs, dejection and
          deſpair. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>III. THE IMPERIAL PILLS. <lb/><hi rend="sc">Or, the universal
            purifiers of the blood and juices.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HIS title was given to them to mark
          their exceeding <w part="I">ſupe-</w><lb/><w part="F">riority</w> over all the analeptic
          or ſtomachic pills, antiſcorbutis <lb/>drops, and alterative purifying medicines that
          perhaps ever were <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">vented</w>, or which are now uſed in
          the world.—In all weakneſſes, <w part="I">op-</w><lb/><w part="F">preſſions</w>,
          flatulencies, cholickly gripings, and windy diſtenſions of <lb/>the ſtomach and bowels,
          eſpecially when thoſe uneaſy, and indeed <lb/>tormenting complaints proceed from
          ſcorbutic, venereal, gouty or <lb/>bilious humours, freting, corroding, and irritating the
          nervous coats <lb/>of the ſtomach and bowels;—or from heats, acidities, crudities and
          <lb/>indigeſtions, occaſioned by full and foul feeding; exceſſive drinking <lb/>of hot and
          foul wines and liquors; heats and colds, or ſurfeits; <w part="I">ir-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >regular</w> and late hours as to ſleep; want of exerciſe, and perſpiration,
          <lb/>&amp;c. &amp;c,—in all ſuch caſes, the Imperial Pills are conſtantly found <lb/>to
          give immediate relief, and if the perſon is prudent and temperate, <lb/>by a regular and
          gentle perſeverance in the uſe of them—a perfect <lb/>and a laſting cure will, with a
          moral certainty, be obtained. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>Theſe pills are a compoſition of the pureſt parts of the
          choiceſt <w part="I">ar-</w><lb/><w part="F">ticles</w> of the <hi rend="italic">Materia
            Medica,</hi> combined and rendered ſtill more <pb xml:id="page_11" n="11"/><lb/>active,
          by the united influences of air, æther, and magnetiſm<note place="bottom" n="*"
            rend="size(0.5)">* Hippocrates, Galen, Celſus, Sir Iſaac Newton, Van Helmont,
            Paracelfus, <lb/>Deſcartes, Sydenham, Boyle, Boerhaave, and many others of the greateſt
              <w part="I">phi-</w><lb/><w part="F">loſophers</w> and phyſicians, ancient and modern,
            that ever bleſſed and enlightened <lb/>the world, <hi rend="italic">prophecied,</hi> and
            in all their writings <hi rend="italic">inſiſted upon it,</hi> that whenever the
            <lb/>practice of phyſic arrived to a high degree of perfection, or medicines were <w
              part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">covered</w> which would effectually eradicate
            diſeaſes, inducing health and peace in <lb/>the body and mind, alleviating the preſſures
            of age, and lengthening human life <lb/>to the longeſt poſſible period, it would be done
            by attending to the ſimple; yet <lb/>divine voice of nature, and by the united
            influences of the great primary <w part="I">princi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ples</w> or
            natural agents which I ſo happily employ for thoſe moſt important <w part="I"
              >por-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſes</w>. Animated by the concurring opinions of thoſe
            great men,—ſtimulated <lb/>by the proſpects which were opened to my view by thoſe bright
            luminaries of <lb/>ſcience!—ſhocked, too, at the very tranſcient, rapid and painful
            progreſs of <lb/>man thro' this world;—and moreover, almoſt mad at the trifling
            abſurdities of <lb/>the ordinary practice in this uſeful but dangerous art—and at the
            too feeble—<lb/>or too harſh effect of moſt medicines as commonly uſed,—I was compelled
            with <lb/>a certain, as it were divine or ſupernatural energy or impulſe, to ſearch for
            wider <lb/>and more rational paths, and more effectual means for the prevention and cure
            <lb/>of diſeaſes; how far I have ſucceeded thoſe who are acquainted with my <w part="I"
              >medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cines</w> and practice, or who even have read my late
            publications, will be able to <lb/>judge.—I will only ſay, that according to my
            abilities, and agreeable to the <lb/>ideas and directions of thoſe great men, I have
            ſtudied and endeavoured to unite <lb/>every affinity that there is between the elements
            and man:—between the ſun, <lb/>moon and ſtars, and man;—and in ſhort between man and
            every thing in the <lb/>great ſyſtem of the univerſe (which affects his body, and thro'
            that his mind) <lb/>however remotely, however inviſibly connected with his frame. But as
            the <lb/><hi rend="italic">perfecting</hi> all this vaſt and moſt comprehenſive ſyſtem
            requires a degree of <w part="I">intelli-</w><lb/><w part="F">geuce</w> far—very far
            ſuperior to what I can pretend to, I truſt that God will raiſe <lb/>up a ſucceſſion of
            men who will carry on and perfect what I have ſo happily <lb/>begun. <p rend="indent"
              ><lb/>In the mean time, I reſpectfully intreat the correſpondence of all men of <w
                part="I">learn-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>, ſcience, and ingenuity; moſt earneſtly
              beſeeching every man and woman <lb/>in the world, <hi rend="italic">without
                exception,</hi> to communicate to me perſonally, by their friends, <lb/>or by
              letter, any thing that they already know, or may hereafter diſcover, for <lb/>the
              cure, alleviation, or prevention of any one diſeaſe; or for rendering human
              <lb/>exiſtence longer or happier on this earth: and likewiſe whatever they now know,
              <lb/>or may hereafter diſcover for the improvement or embelliſhment of religion,
              <lb/>philoſophy, or the uſeful arts; eſpecially in metals and minerals. I will be <w
                part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">tremely</w> happy to be favoured with the opinions
              and conjectures of perſons of <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">genuity</w>, of
              goodneſs of heart, or of excentric brilliant imaginations. And as <lb/>this
              correſpondence will coſt each of my friends individually, but a few pence <lb/>for
              paying the poſtages of their letters, while otherwiſe the aggregate, centring <lb/>in
              me, would coſt probably ſeveral hundred pounds annually; I hope therefore <lb/>that my
              liberal, polite, and ingenious correſpondents will continue to have the <lb/>goodneſs
              to write to me, POST PAID. Their favours ſhall as uſual be <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">giſtered</w>, and a true account of the ſucceſs of what they recommend or
              have <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">covered</w>, ſent to them in whatever part
              of the world they reſide.—Once more for <lb/>the honour and glory of God:—for the good
              and happineſs of the human ſpecies <lb/>in general, I earneſtly invite, and moſt
              ſolemnly exhort every man and woman <lb/>of worth, goodneſs and ingenuity, in whatever
              ſphere of life they move, from <lb/>the imperial throne to the beggar's hut—to the
              above mentioned <w part="I">communica-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w> or
              correſpondence; and by benefactions of money or lands, or teſtamentary<lb/>donations
              to eſtabliſh a fund to defray the expences which neceſſarily attend <lb/>printing
              books, and chemical and philoſophical proceſſes and inveſtigations—<lb/>for the
              adcancement of true, vital, and univerſal religion, for the improvement <lb/>of
              ſcience, and for the embelliſhment and extenſion of the uſeful Arts. </p>
          </note>
          <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">cording</w> to the true principles of electricity, and
          of the philoſophic <lb/>chemiſtry, and are conſtantly acted upon by theſe powerful and
          moſt <lb/>genial agents for ſeveral months in the upper globe, of the pyramidal <pb
            xml:id="page_12" n="12"/><lb/>metal dome of the Temple of Health, which globe alone,
          like each <lb/>of the other three, contains thirty-ſix gallons, and is of the fineſt
          <lb/>burniſhed gold. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>The Imperial Pills are of ſo mild and friendly a nature that
          they <lb/>are found to agree perfectly well with both ſexes and with every age <lb/>and
          conſtitution. They operate firſt by diſſolving all tough, cold <lb/>phlegm or ſlime, and
          other groſs, corrupted, bilious and putrid <w part="I">hu-</w><lb/><w part="F">mours</w>,
          which not only clog and irritate the ſtomach and bowels, but <lb/>form a neſt and
          nouriſhment for thoſe common and moſt deſtructive <lb/>vermin, <hi rend="sc"
          >worms</hi>—which they effectually kill, evacuate and carry off <lb/>by ſtool and urine:
          after that, by continuing their moderate uſe as <lb/>an alterative, without change of
          diet, confinement, or any <w part="I">irk-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſome</w> reſtraint
          whatever, they ſubdue, eradicate, and expel by ſtool, <lb/>urine, and a breathing
          inſenſible perſpiration, all ſcorbutic, gouty, <lb/>rheumatic, venereal, bilious and
          ſcrophulous humours, however <lb/>long they may have lurked and prevailed in the ſyſtem,
          preying on, <lb/>and exhauſting the ſtrength and ſpirits, and undermining and <w part="I"
            >de-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtroying</w> all the ſprings and principles of life. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>Rubbing and exerciſe are univerſally allowed to be good for
          the <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">covery</w> as well as for the preſervation of
          health. Now theſe act by <lb/>exciting the electrical fire in the body which removes
          obſtructions, <lb/>animates and braces. The Imperial Pills therefore, and the Ætherial
          <lb/>Balſam, being filled with the electrical or celeſtial fire, and ſolar <lb/>light,
          which the balmy reſins of which they are compoſed have <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >bibed</w> and do retain, promote all the natural and neceſſary <w part="I"
            >circula-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w>, ſecretions and abſorptions, and conſequently
            <hi rend="italic">muſt</hi> be of the <lb/>greateſt ſervice to thoſe perſons, eſpecially
          to females, who take too <lb/>little free air and exerciſe, tho' at the ſame time they
          live full, and <lb/>are of a coſtive or irregular habit. Upon the ſame grounds they
          <lb/>are found exceedingly beneficial in thoſe heats, ſpaſms, pains, and <lb/>uneaſineſſes
          in females, occaſioned by the <hi rend="italic">periodical</hi> fulneſs of their
          <lb/>veſſels, and <hi rend="italic">from certain other cauſes:</hi> but the good effects
          in gouty, <lb/>ſcorbutic, and rheumatic caſes, and in all eruptions, or pimples of
          <lb/>the face,—ſores or blotches, of the body and limbs, however invete <lb/>rately
          blended in the blood,—however obſtinately confirmed in the <lb/>conſtitution—are really
          aſtoniſhing. The dreadful train of ſufferings <lb/>which the miſerable patients in the
          above caſes endure, and even the <lb/>moſt obſtinate rheumatic ſwellings and weakneſſes of
          the joints, &amp;c. <lb/>yield very readily to the ſuperior efficacy of theſe excellent
          pills;— <pb xml:id="page_13" n="13"/><lb/>and they are a diuretic of ſo ſoft yet ſearching
          a nature, that they <lb/>generally give very ſpeedy eaſe in ſevere fits of the ſtone and
          gravel, <lb/>and by perſevering in a proper courſe of them, and of my Nervous
          <lb/>Ætherial Balſam at the ſame time, and drinking veal broth with <lb/>plenty of gum
          arabic diſſolved in it, or of a decoction of liquorice, <lb/>linſeed, and marſhmallow
          roots poured upon ſhred leeks, and bruiſed <lb/>fennil ſeeds with ſome honey or treacle,
          they often have been found <lb/>to cure radically thoſe moſt painful and moſt excruciating
          diſorders. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>But in all leſs grievous, tho' abundantly troubleſome
          complaints <lb/>of the firſt paſſages—they are an abſolute ſpecific. For they <w part="I"
            >imme-</w><lb/><w part="F">diately</w> reſtore loſt appetite, and correct all hot,
          acrid, and four <w part="I">fer-</w><lb/><w part="F">mentations</w> in the ſtomach and
          bowels, which they ſo genially cool <lb/>and invigotate, as to enable them to concoct and
          extract thoſe fine <lb/>mild nutritious juices of our food and drink, which nouriſh the
          body <lb/>and gladden the ſoul. By theſe means the breath is rendered balmy <lb/>and
          ſweet; the face is cleared from ſcurf, heat and pimples, <w part="I">prema-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ture</w> wrinkles are ſmoothed away and obliterated, and the <w part="I"
            >com-</w><lb/><w part="F">plexion</w> rendered clear, ſmooth freſh and youthful; and all
          theſe <lb/>happy effects are produced inſenſibly as it were, without (as I <lb/>ſaid
          before) confinement, particular regimen in food or drink, or <lb/>hindrance of buſineſs;
          their operation, like the Nervous Ætherial <lb/>Balſam, being ſo mild and congenial to
          human nature, that they may <lb/>be taken under any circumſtance, in any climate, or at
          any ſeaſon of <lb/>the year, tho' when taken merely as a preſerver of health, the ſpring
          <lb/>and autumn ſeaſons are doubtleſs the moſt proper. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>The Imperial Pills therefore, while they fortify the ſtomach
          <lb/>and bowels, and purge the blood and lymph from all morbid humours, <lb/>and <hi
            rend="italic">heterogeneous</hi> ſharpneſſes and viſcidities, they ſo perfectly
          eradicate <lb/>all venereal and ſcorbutic diſeaſes, that I defy the world to bring me
          <lb/>any ſuch caſe if <hi rend="italic">at all curabl,</hi> but what I will radically,
          ſpeedily and <lb/>ſafely cure by a proper courſe firſt of theſe pills, and afterwards of
          <lb/>my Ætherial Balſam, without the uſe of one grain of that horrible <lb/>poiſon,
          mercury. Indeed <hi rend="italic">than</hi> theſe medicines, and my Electrical <w part="I"
            >Sul-</w><lb/><w part="F">phur</w>, there has been no others as yet diſcovered, whatever
          quacks and <lb/>empyries may pretend, which ſo ſpeedily and ſo completely counteract
          <lb/>the deadly effects of mercury, and other violent medicines, which <w part="I"
            >of-</w><lb/><w part="F">ten</w> ſo tear, ſhake, and debilitate the conſtitution as to
          make the dear <lb/>bought cure of the primary complaint, no great bleſſing to the feeble
            <hi rend="italic"><lb/>unnerved</hi> patient. This ſingular and moſt invaluable quality
          of the <lb/>Imperial Pills is ocularly demonſtrated to the patient and to all his
          <lb/>friends, by almoſt inſtantly ſtopping the higheſt ſalivation, throwing <lb/>off the
          pocky or ſcorbutic virus, &amp;c. by ſtool, by urine, and by ſweat: <lb/>and by making the
          quickſilver run off in globules by ſtool in <w part="I">quan-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tities</w> nearly proportioned to thoſe that had been unfortunately uſed. <lb/>Now the
          univerſally <hi rend="italic">allowed,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">two well known</hi>
          effects of mercury <lb/>are to diſſolve and break down the maſs of blood into a ſharp,
          watery <pb xml:id="page_14" n="14"/><lb/>putrid gore;—and to tear, deaden, relax, and
          render tremulous the <lb/>whole nervous ſyſtem; but the Imperial Pills carry the mercury
          and <lb/>all venereal and ſcorbutic humours entirely out of the body, reſtoring <lb/>the
          healthy tone of the ſtomach, bowels, and ſolids in general;—<lb/>and the nervous ætherial
          balſam very ſpeedily warms, and ſteadies <lb/>the cold—quivering—tottering body; reſtoring
          the balmy craſis of <lb/>the blood and juices; ſheathing, bracing, and invigorating the
          dry, <lb/>ſhrunk and tremulous nerves; and abſolutely cures all ſeminal <w part="I"
            >weak-</w><lb/><w part="F">neſſes</w> and debility in both ſexes, from whatever cauſes
          proceeding, <lb/>but thoſe eſpecially which ariſe from ill cured, neglected, improperly
          <lb/>treated or repeated venereal complaints, early imprudencies, <w part="I"
            >irre-</w><lb/><w part="F">gularities</w>, and all unnatural and inordinate exertions
          and <w part="I">indulgen-</w><lb/><w part="F">cies</w> eſpecially in the ſacrifices that
          are made to Venus, or to Bac-<lb/>chus<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* One of
            the peculiar and moſt important properties of my Nervous Ætherial <lb/>Balſam is to
            recover and produce that genial vital warmth, which is ſo different <lb/>from an
            inflaming feveriſh heat. </note>. Let the inventors or proprietors of other medicines
          which are <lb/>ſent abroad into the world, make a parade of their <hi rend="sc"
            >patents</hi>, &amp;c.—<lb/>For theſe great medicines I never thought of ſuch ſecurities
          or <w part="I">ſanc-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w>. No. I am not afraid of any one
          counterfeiting <hi rend="italic">them,</hi> tho' I <lb/>find it has been vainly and
          ridiculouſly attempted. The compoſitions <lb/>are ſo curious and complex, and the
          ingredients ſo very ſubtil, that <lb/>they will not bear to be analyzed by even the moſt
          ſkilful adept in <lb/>philoſophical or pharmaceutical chemiſtry. I repeat it. The <w
            part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">gredients</w> are too coſtly and too numerous,—the
          proceſſes too <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">plex</w> and tedious,—and the apparatus
          employed in the preparation <lb/>of them coſts too many thouſand pounds for moſt
          adventurers, even <lb/>of abilities, in the medical or medicinal line to engage with or
          even to <lb/>think of. They are now, I find, bought by ſome of the moſt <w part="I"
            >emi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nent</w> of the faculty, in various parts of the world as well
          as in <lb/>theſe kingdoms, and exhibited in ſevere dangerous and important <lb/>caſes
          ſometimes as their own preparations: and I aſſure the nobility, <lb/>gentry, and even the
          faculty who are deſirous of knowing every <w part="I">ingre-</w><lb/><w part="F">dient</w>
          in the compoſition of each, or of either of the three medicines, <lb/>that they need only
          apply to me to be fully ſatisfied in every particular <lb/>which they feel themſelves
          intereſted in. To know them is to approve <lb/>of them; and to uſe them once, is to uſe
          and recommend them moſt <lb/>cordially for ever. Such is their intrinſic excellency that
          they will <lb/>bear every teſt—even the teſt—the criterion—the fiery ordeal of <w part="I"
            >ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">perience</w> in the moſt confirmed, and moſt hopeleſs
          caſes:—for they <lb/>have been brought to their preſent high ſtate of perfection by long
          <lb/>and deliberate inveſtigations of the real qualities of medicines, by the <lb/>deepeſt
          reſearches into chemiſtry, enlightened by the important <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">coveries</w> and improvements which have lately been made in natural
          <lb/>philoſophy; and finally, by the niceſt and moſt aſſiduous attention to <lb/>the
          effects and operations of the medicines themſelves, in a moſt <w part="I">ex-</w>
          <pb xml:id="page_15" n="15"/><lb/><w part="F">tenſive</w> courſe of private practice in
          this, as well as in various foreign <lb/>countries; and the invariable reſult of their
          judicious uſe has been <w part="I">effec-</w><lb/><w part="F">tually</w>, to prevent, and
          with certainty to cure moſt diſeaſes to which <lb/>mankind is obnoxious,—but eſpecially
          thoſe which the natives of theſe <lb/>iſlands are liable to at ſea or in foreign
          countries—inſomuch that many<lb/>gentlemen, eſpecially of the army and navy would now
          almoſt as ſoon <lb/>go to ſea without proviſions, or upon along journey without money as
          <lb/>without a certain ſtock of theſe three precious remedies. Indeed, in <lb/>the hands
          of people of prudence and good ſenſe, they ſuperſede the <lb/>need of a travelling
          phyſician, or of any medicine cheſt—for they <lb/>are of themſelves an apothecary's ſhop
          fully adequate to the <w part="I">preven-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> and cure of moſt
          diſeaſes. And ſo thoroughly convinced am I <lb/>of the univerſal ſalutarineſs, and
          ſuperior efficacy of theſe three great <lb/>medicines, that in a <hi rend="sc">very</hi>
          few years I will probably relinquiſh the <lb/>practical part of medicine altogether, but
          continue to diſpenſe theſe <lb/>medicines all over the world, WHILE, for the good of the
          human <lb/>ſpecies of every nation and clime,—even for the children of thoſe <lb/>who
          ſhall be born a thouſand years hence, I will publickly teach <lb/>medicine and philoſophy
          in academical lectures, and from time to <lb/>time publiſh what I am now compiling, viz. a
          complete Syſtem of <lb/>Prophylactic and Practical Medicine; or, the whole art (without
          <lb/>even a ſhadow of reſerve) of preventing and curing diſeaſes. <w part="I"
            >Per-</w><lb/><w part="F">haps</w>, likewiſe, I may ſend into the world, a complete and
          rational <lb/>Body of Divinity, or true vital religion, which I am now likewiſe
          <lb/>preparing; and perhaps, moreover a manual of Human Prudence;—<lb/>or a ſafe and
          complete guide of life: and a <hi rend="sc">simple</hi>, yet full and <w part="I"
            >na-</w><lb/><w part="F">turally</w> digeſted code of laws for civil, political, and
          eccleſiaſtical <lb/>government,—ſubmitted with great deference to thoſe, to whom <lb/>they
          more immediately, and more properly belong. But to return, <lb/>I was obſerving the
          efficacy of <hi rend="sc">the three great medicines</hi> in <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſtoring</w> decayed, conſumptive, and worn-out conſtitutions, or after
          <lb/>ſevere diſeaſes, harſh and improper medicines, or hardſhips and <w part="I"
            >ſick-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w> in foreign hot climates. Upon this ſubject I can
          ſcarce ſay enough. <lb/>Yet to thoſe who are acquainted with the medicines everything
          which <lb/>even I <hi rend="italic">could</hi> ſay, would be quite unneceſſary. What need
          is there to <lb/>expatiate on the genial qualities of the ſun, which are univerſally
          <lb/>felt, and univerſally acknowledged?—I will only obſerve for the <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">formation</w> of the world in general, that in all ſuch caſes,
          they moiſten, warm, refreſh and build up the whole ſyſtem, with bland, <lb/>mild, balmy
          and nutritious juices; and by inducing a free, <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >gular</w>, ſteady and genial circulation of the blood <hi rend="italic">(which is the
            true <lb/>radical moiſture)</hi> ſpirits, and nervous fluid, or that ætherial inviſible
          <lb/>principle which actuates the nerves, and which altogether conſtitute <lb/>the balmy
          life of the body; and, finally, by inducing the due and <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ciprocal</w> action of the ſolids and fluids on each other; or in other
          <lb/>words, that happy <hi rend="italic">equilibrium</hi>—that peaceful balance! which
          nature <pb xml:id="page_16" n="16"/><lb/>delights in, and conſtantly endeavours to
          maintain in the whole <w part="I">vi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſible</w> as well as inviſible
          creation—they produce in the human body <lb/>that peaceful, homogene, tranquil ſtate which
          we call health, and <lb/>which is doubtleſs the natural and original ſtate of all created
          things: <lb/>for pain, diſcord and diſeaſe, are ſo very unnatural, that even pain <lb/>and
          diſeaſe are only a departure from, and imply a poſſibility of <lb/>health,—or the
          attainment of that ſtate which nature pants after, <lb/>and which man originally
          poſſeſſed. All diſtempers are in fact but a <lb/>ſtruggle between the <hi rend="italic"
            >vis vitæ</hi> and the peculiar Miaſma, or <hi rend="italic">Fomes <w part="I"
              >Mer-</w><lb/><w part="F">bi</w>.</hi> Indeed every ſpecies and degree of pleaſure,
          and of bodily and <lb/>mental happineſs which we enjoy in this world, are only the <w
            part="I">irradia-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w> or emanations of this primary principle,
          namely, concord or <lb/>health. This is the <hi rend="sc">great unity</hi>!—the root and
          branches—the <lb/>flowers and the fruits—the ſap and the life of mankind; To contrive
          <lb/>and adapt, from the harmonious combination of the four elements <lb/>acting on
          natural ſubſtances of <hi rend="sc">known efficacy</hi>, ſuch medicines as <lb/>could root
          out diſeaſe, diſcord and ſtrife from the human body, and <lb/>produce, cultivate and
          nouriſh this heavenly unity, hath been my <lb/>conſtant ſtudy, I may ſay, day and night
          for many years. How far <lb/>I have ſucceeded has been long and abundantly obvious, not
          only <lb/>from the prodigious and unprecedented ſale of theſe Great <w part="I"
            >Medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cines</w>; but from the aſtoniſhing and well known numbers
          which <lb/>are daily diſmiſſed from the Temple of Health perfectly cured of <w part="I"
            >diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">eaſes</w> which had baffled all other human means. Now this
          unity or <lb/>health,—this <hi rend="sc">self-remedy</hi> in nature for all her diſorders,
          was the <lb/>ſeal with which God impreſſed every thing at the creation. And it <lb/>was
          THIS in man which was emphatically called, "the <hi rend="sc">image of
          <lb/>god</hi>."—This was paradiſe for man! This was the paradiſe of the <lb/>earth, and of
          all the elements.—But man departing from God, and <lb/>from the innocence and ſimplicity
          in which he was created, brought <lb/>diſcord and diſeaſes into his ſoul and body;—from
          hence proceeds <lb/>his ſhort and uncertain exiſtence in this world; hence flow pain,
          <lb/>diſeaſe and death;—and from hence, too, perhaps all evil and <w part="I"
            >com-</w><lb/><w part="F">motions</w> within and without, in the natural and in the
          moral world. <lb/>All fevers, fermentations, jarrings, reſtleſſneſs, commotions, pains
          <lb/>and diſeaſes in the human body, are, therefore proofs of that <w part="I"
            >hid-</w><lb/><w part="F">den—conſtitutional</w> peace and health which it has loſt, and
            <w part="I">neceſſa-</w><lb/><w part="F">rily</w> gravitates unto, and endeavours to
          regain, altho' it knows not <lb/>the way—nor is it always ſo happy as to meet with, or
          follow, a <lb/>friendly and unerring guide. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>That the above medicines, conjunctly, are ſuch a friend—ſuch
          a <lb/>guide! no one will doubt who has attended properly to the plain, <lb/>open and
          ſimple deſcription which I have given of them; nor will <lb/>any one deny the truth of the
          fact, who has fairly and prudently uſed <lb/>them—even in the moſt deſperate caſes. Theſe
          great medicines <lb/>then, will reſtore health and tranquility—becauſe they reſtore in our
            <pb xml:id="page_17" n="17"/><lb/>body, as I have above ſhewn, that original
          unity,—balance—har-<lb/>mony or <hi rend="italic">equilibrium</hi> which nature delights
          in, and continually ſtrives <lb/>to maintain in all her works—eſpecially in the human body
          and mind, <lb/>as being the moſt perfect and important of all that ſhe has created, or
          <lb/>placed on this terraqueous globe! </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>Theſe, therefore, conjunctly, may juſtly be eſteemed the
          true and <lb/>genuine <hi rend="sc">universal medicine</hi>!—the boaſted and long wiſhed
          for <hi rend="italic">Pri-<lb/>ma Materia!—Aurum potabile!</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
            >elixir vitæ!</hi> of the philoſophers, <w part="I">che-</w><lb/><w part="F">miſts</w>,
          and phyſicians of every age ſince medicine became a ſcience.—<lb/>In theſe three
          medicines, by the wonderful influence of the mighty—primary—ſimple agents upon each other,
          and upon the ſimple <w part="I">ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtances</w> above mentioned,
          which for ſo many ages have been found ſo <lb/>friendly to man—is produced and fixed,—a
          vivifying—homogene <lb/>principle which counteracts diſeaſe, inſures health, and the
            prolonga-<lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of our mortal exiſtence. In the balmy bed of theſe
          three <w part="I">medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cines</w>, all elementary and inteſtine ſtrife
          ceaſes. Here, the active—<lb/>the irreſiſtible powers of air, earth, fire and water blend
          their <w part="I">ſeem-</w><lb/><w part="F">ingly</w> jarring principles, and are at
          peace. Here wih the ſwiftneſs <lb/>of thought, they meet in one common centre. They kiſs
          each other <lb/>as it were,—cordially embrace, and are at reſt in this
          paradiſiacal—<lb/>this balmy bed. For be it known (and however paradoxical it may
          <lb/>appear, it is nevertheleſs a certain—ſublime, and philoſophical truth) <lb/>that the
          quickeſt motion, is the moſt perfect reſt. When a boy whips <lb/>his top into the briskeſt
          motion—it turns about with ſuch exceeding <lb/>ſwiftneſs that it appears perfectly
          motionleſs—and he ſays it is <lb/>aſleep. Would not any thing that could paſs from this to
          the Eaſt <lb/>Indies and back again in the thouſandth part of a moment—be at <lb/>perfect
          reſt?—could a thought—or any thing that could glance or <lb/>be ſhot from your eye in
          London to the fartheſt verge—to the moſt <lb/>diſtant point of the globe and back again in
          the millionth part of the <lb/>time of a twinkle in your eye,—could it be ſaid to move at
          all?—<lb/>Surely not.—When the cauſe of diſeaſe therefore is expelled by theſe <lb/>great
          medicines they <hi rend="sc">instantly</hi> compoſe all ſtrife. I <hi rend="sc">never</hi>
          ſwallow <lb/>any wine, ſpirits, or malt liquor, ſtrong or weak, mixt nor unmixt, <lb/>and
          yet I undergo daily with pleaſure, cheerfulneſs and good health, <lb/>more fatigue of body
          and of mind, than perhaps any other man in <lb/>London;—If, after the buſineſs of the day,
          or when I am forced <lb/>to be up all night when ſent for in great emergencies—I find
          myſelf<lb/>faint and exhauſted,—I immediately draw the vapour of the <w part="I"
            >electri-</w><lb/><w part="F">cal</w> æther with great force into my noſtrils—or pour a
          few <w part="I">tea-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſpoonfuls</w> of it into a baſon of warm water
          and breathe over it;—<lb/>and ordering a few new laid eggs to be beat as it were into a
          thin <lb/>oil, and then mixed with ſome ſugar and <hi rend="italic">very</hi>
          <hi rend="sc">cold</hi> water, I drink <lb/>it off, and eating a bit of biſcuit, rich ripe
          fruits, or dry bread two <lb/>days old, I find myſelf, in a few minutes, perfectly freſh
          and <w part="I">re-</w><pb xml:id="page_18" n="18"/><lb/><w part="F">cruited</w>. But what
          always aſtoniſhes me above meaſure is, the <w part="I">ſeem-</w><lb/><w part="F">ingly</w>
          miraculous effect of my Electrical Æther, or <hi rend="sc">Nervous <w part="I"
              >Æthe-</w><lb/><w part="F">rial</w> Balsam</hi>, of which, when I take a tea-ſpoonful
          or two <lb/>into my mouth upon a bit of ſugar, I feel my body refreſhed, <lb/>braced, and
          ſtrengthened, and my mind enlarged and illuminated, <lb/>in one moment. It darts its
          genial ætherial ſoul with the ſwiftneſs <lb/>of light—or with the inconceivable ſwiftneſs
          above mentioned, through <lb/>every nerve—vein—artery! I deſire to repeat, in other words,
          <lb/>what I have already expreſſed; namely, that if thro' extreme bodily <lb/>fatigue and
          anxiety, I feel myſelf as it were crampt in a cold dark <lb/>room,—in a moment,—by the
          means of the electrical æther, and <lb/>nervous ætherial balſam, I find myſelf ſaluted as
          it were by love,—<lb/>joy, health and harmony! who in a moment fling open celeſtial
          <lb/>ſcenes—and ſmiling, tranſport me on ſoft waving wings—with <lb/>balmy and melodious
          gales, into the ſweet—brilliant, and flowery <lb/>palace where they, the handmaids of <hi
            rend="sc">happiness</hi>, <w part="I">reſide!—illumi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nated</w> with
          ten thouſand lights of virgin wax!—or warmed and <lb/>gilded with a vernal—a meridian ſun!
          But to deſcend from the <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">gions</w> of metaphor. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>Theſe wonderful and moſt genial medicines attune the body,
          and <lb/>thro' it the mind;—or, rather, the mind and the body freed from <lb/>diſcord and
          diſeaſe, recover, by their own energy, their natural <lb/>and original healthy tone and
          brilliancy:—And this happy ſtate <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tained—every</w>
          thing which ſurrounds us appears likewiſe pleaſant, <lb/>gay and harmonious. Like, as in
          muſical inſtruments tuned in <w part="I">uni-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſon</w>, every chord
          which is touched, ſtrikes and calls forth, by its own <lb/>vibratory force alone, a
          correſponding muſical tone from every octave <lb/>in the other inſtruments in the ſame
          room, thus inviſibly touched. <lb/>Theſe are facts perfectly well known to philoſophers,
          and to thoſe who <lb/>have ſtudied muſic as a ſcience. But to return; I ſay, that upon the
          <lb/>grounds of reaſon and common ſenſe, it is no wonder that theſe <w part="I"
            >medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cines</w>, when judiciouſly applied, are ſo efficacious as to
          remove all <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">orders</w> that ariſe from the jarrings
          and diſproportions of the conſtituent <lb/>parts or qualities in human bodies—becauſe
          theſe medicines are <w part="I">a-</w><lb/><w part="F">dapted</w>, and accommodate
          themſelves to all, and health enſues in the <lb/>moſt eaſy, ſimple, and natural manner.
          The wiſe and ſacred writer <lb/>ſays, "That God hath created medicines out of the earth,
          and that he <lb/>who is wiſe will not deſpiſe them."—Now as the qualities or virtues
          <lb/>of all roots, leaves, flowers, fruits and ſeeds,—and of every <w part="I"
            >medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cinal</w> ſubſtance in nature, whether animal, vegetable, or
          mineral, <lb/>muſt undoubtedly reſide in ſome little drops—ſome exquiſitely ſmall
          <lb/>particles of <hi rend="sc">one</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">prima materia!</hi> which is the fountain or centre of<lb/>exiſtence,
          life and health—and as this fountain—or ſource—or <pb xml:id="page_19" n="19"
          /><lb/>centre, is to be found alone by the gift of God; or, in other words, <lb/>by his
          bleſſing on the reverential and aſſiduous labours and <w part="I">inveſtiga-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tions</w> of thoſe who ſearch unweariedly into the vaſt treaſures of <w
            part="I">na-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w>, with a view of promoting the good and
          happineſs of the world, <lb/>and the honour and glory of God!—Whenever therefore, we can
          <lb/>extract and concentrate from the adventitious, groſs, or inactive <lb/>parts—the
          balmy, ſimple, homogeneous and viviſying particles of <lb/>ſubſtances truly medicinal, by
          means of the harmonious combination <lb/>of the great univerſal principles of air, æther,
          magnetiſm, electricity, <lb/>and ſolar light, we need look for no other medicines; and I
          defy any <lb/>phyſician to mention an indication in the cure of any diſeaſe, whether
          <lb/>by altering, attenuating, opening, purifying, ſweating, purging, <w part="I"
            >vo-</w><lb/><w part="F">miting</w>, paſſing off by the kidnies; or by taking off ſpaſms
          and <w part="I">irri-</w><lb/><w part="F">tations—by</w> bracing and comforting the
          nerves,—or by <w part="I">ſtrength-</w><lb/><w part="F">ening</w> and vivifying the whole
          ſyſtem, but may be anſwered in the <lb/>completeſt and moſt friendly manner, by the
          judicious modulations <lb/>and exhibitions of theſe three great medicines. They will
          therefore, <lb/>upon principles perfectly demonſtrable, cure all curable diſeaſes,
          <lb/>gladden the heart, illuminate the mind, and prolong human <w part="I"
            >exiſt-</w><lb/><w part="F">ence</w> to the longeſt poſſible period. Becauſe this exact
          mixture of <lb/>hot and cold, moiſt and dry,—this harmonious tempering of the <lb/>primary
          vital elements, coaleſcing like chords in muſic, muſt be <lb/>peace makers in the ſtrife
          or diſorders of the conſtituent parts and <lb/>qualities of man's body;—and becauſe the
          true quinteſſence of <w part="I">na-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w> is Fire. I don't mean
          the groſs, impure, conſuming, culinary fire <lb/>which we have every day before us in the
          world: by no means. The <lb/>fire which I employ in the cure of diſeaſes, and in the
          preparation <lb/>of thoſe three great medicines, is the true elementary fire, which has
          <lb/>been worſhipped as it were by the philoſophers of all ages. They <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">had</hi>glimpſes of it; and even its dawn gleaming on their horizon filled
          <lb/>them with ideas ſo vaſt and ſublime! that the herd of the world called <lb/>them mad
          enthuſiaſts. How much greater felicity muſt <hi rend="italic">we</hi> enjoy, <lb/>upon
          whom the ſun of ſcience ſhines ſo bright as at this day. How <lb/>much more may <hi
            rend="italic">we</hi> benefit and enlighten the human ſpecies! But <lb/>ſtill, the ſun
          juſt alluded to, is far—very—very far from having <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tained</w> its meridian altitude It even now points, but at ſix o'clock <lb/>of a
          ſummer morning. Yet how faſt—how ſweetly—do the buds of <lb/>every branch of ſcience
          open!—The birds ſing—<hi rend="sc">all nature <w part="I">re-</w><lb/></hi><w part="F"><hi
              rend="sc">joices</hi>!</w> But thoſe charming fields—theſe delightful proſpects tempt
          <lb/>me to wander too far. I will return. The fire I ſay which I employ <lb/>in the cure
          of diſeaſes, and for the preparation of theſe great <w part="I">medi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cines</w>, is the univerſal living fire which connects and moves the whole <lb/>ſolar
          ſyſtem—which animates all nature, and which you, my <w part="I">cour-</w><pb
            xml:id="page_20" n="20"/><lb/><w part="F">teous</w> reader—this book, the chair you ſit
          in, the charming object <lb/>by your ſide, and in a word, every thing in the univerſe is
          full of; <lb/>and which we can now in a moment extract, and make viſible or <w part="I"
            >per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceptable</w> to <hi rend="italic">all</hi> your five ſenſes.
          This fire is the breath of life—the <w part="I">ſpi-</w><lb/><w part="F">rit</w> of
          God!—which he breathed at the creation into man's noſtrils, <lb/>and which gives and
          maintains life throughout all his other works!—<lb/><hi rend="sc">It is the vital
            principle of generation</hi>! the fire which quickens <lb/>the embryo in the womb!—even
          the pure fluid, celeſtial, <w part="I">electri-</w><lb/><w part="F">cal</w> fire which
          pervades, purges, and animates <hi rend="sc">all nature</hi>! <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſuming</w> diſeaſe and corruption—attracting and uniting the four <w part="I"
            >ele-</w><lb/><w part="F">ments—without</w> deſtroying their variety or diſtinct
          powers,—becauſe <lb/>it is itſelf a compoſition of them all—the joy of them all—and in a
          <lb/>word the great band or material ſoul of the univerſe! </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi>, <hi rend="italic">then,</hi> is the
          natural—the celeſtial quinteſſence or inſtuence <lb/>with which thoſe three great
          medicines are impregnated—and <lb/>with which they are replete:—even with the harmonious
          combination of <lb/>the four elementary qualities in <hi rend="sc">one</hi>;—and whenever
          this pure and <lb/>ſimple light, or concord is received into the body—diſeaſe and <w
            part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">cord</w>
          <hi rend="italic">muſt</hi> vaniſh, as the cold and darkneſs of the night muſt vaniſh
          <lb/>at the preſence of the morning—of the ſummer's ſun!—and I will <lb/>now conclude this
          ſhort and very imperfect account of my great <lb/>medicines with aſſuring thoſe ſick and
          infirm perſons who have not <lb/>yet had the happineſs to partake of their ſalutary
          influences,—<lb/>that they are in their nature and operations, eaſy and
          benign,—<lb/>genial and gentle as a dove—ſtrengthening and exhilirating the <lb/>ſoul and
          body of<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Thoſe who <hi rend="italic">will</hi>
            have the ſoul to be <hi rend="sc">immaterial</hi>; will be perhaps highly <lb/>offended
            at my bringing it in upon every occaſion, head and ſhoulders with the <lb/>body. The
            reaſon is, becauſe I can no way ſucceed in ſeparating them. We <lb/>all know that light,
            though ſupremely pure, and infinitely ſubtil—is <w part="I">neverthe-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">less</w> material: and I agree ſo far with the generality of the world, as to
            conſider <lb/>the human ſoul as a ſubſtance (or emanation in conſequence of the
            exquiſite <w part="I">or-</w><lb/><w part="F">ganization</w> of our body)—ſo
            exquiſitely—ſo ſupremely pure and ſubtilias to be <lb/>abſolutely inviſible and
            inconceivable to any or all of our ſenſes. I find that <lb/>the materiality or nature of
            the ſoul is <hi rend="italic">now</hi> a point bitterly diſputed by <w part="I"
              >philoſo-</w><lb/><w part="F">phors</w>. For my own part, I profeſs that I know
            nothing at all about the matter. <lb/>I know, however, that it is a point which we have
            no ſort of buſineſs with;—<lb/>and as, to <hi rend="italic">this,</hi> and all other
            matters which <hi rend="sc">are not essential</hi> to our <w part="I">hap-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">piness</w> in this, or in any other ſtate of exiſtence—and which <hi
              rend="italic">cannot poſſibly be ſettled</hi>
            <lb/>in this world—I think we had better be eaſy, and not quarrel—wrangle—and
            <lb/>diſturb one another about ſuch abſtruſe, metaphyſical, and I may ſay, <w part="I"
              >nonſenſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cal</w>, matters. Thus I have in three words, written
            all that I ever intend to write <lb/>upon this ſubject. </note> thoſe to whom they are
          thankfully and prudently <lb/>adminiſtered:—whilſt at the ſame time they are as ſtrong and
          as <lb/>furious as lions in ſubduing and evacuating diſeaſes, and every thing <pb
            xml:id="page_21" n="21"/><lb/>that is injurious or unfriendly to good health, or to
          human exiſtence. <lb/>But the ſtrength above alluded to, is the ſtrength of a
          protector—<lb/>and the fury, that of love!—becauſe they hurt not the weakeſt or <lb/>moſt
          delicate, in infancy or in old age:—to the former they are as <lb/>milk and honey—to the
          latter, as generous wine, or the ſmootheſt —<lb/>the ſweeteſt oil!—and to purſue the
          metaphor, they are in the laſt <lb/>ſtages, of moſt ſevere and fatal diſeaſes, what freſh
          oil is to an <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">piring</w> lamp—when the flame is, like a
          ſickly ſhadow quivering and <lb/>gaſping in the dry ſocket. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>Theſe great medicincs which are ſold at no other place in
          London <lb/>or Weſtminſter but at the TEMPLE OF HEATH! <hi rend="sc">Adelphi</hi>,
          <lb/>and at the TEMPLE OF HYMEN, in <hi rend="sc">Pall-Mall</hi>, are <w part="I"
            >care-</w><lb/><w part="F">fully</w> put up and ſecured in ſtrong flint vials:—even the
          Imperial <lb/>Pills—becauſe they would immediately loſe their virtue if kept in a
          <lb/>pill-box—or expoſed to the open air. The three medicines are all <lb/>ſold at the
          ſame price, viz.—in vials of five Shillings, Half a Guinea, <lb/>and One Guinea each.—For
          the conveniency of the navy and <w part="I">ar-</w><lb/><w part="F">my</w>,—of the
          commanders of Eaſt and Weſt-India ſhips—and of <w part="I">la-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >dies</w> and gentlemen travelling by ſea or land, proper aſſortments of <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">all the three</hi> medicines, are put up in mahogany cabinets of Five,
          <lb/>Ten, and Twenty-Five Guineas—with very ample, directions. By <lb/>which means not
          only much money to phyſicians, apothecaries, <lb/>&amp;c. may be ſaved, but likewiſe under
          God, the lives of many <w part="I">hun-</w><lb/><w part="F">dred</w> perſons of worth,
          faſhion and of fortune, who travel into <w part="I">fo-</w><lb/><w part="F">reign</w>
          countries—may be yearly preſerved,—who, otherwiſe, might <lb/>be ſwept off by diſeaſes in
          a few days—when abſent from their <w part="I">fa-</w><lb/><w part="F">milies</w>, and far
          diſtant from their affectionate friends. </p>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>Proper allowance is made to merchants and captains of ſhips
          who <lb/>buy them in large quantities for ſale in foreign countries. In all <hi
            rend="italic">fe-<lb/>vers</hi> and <hi rend="sc">relaxations</hi>—and in BILIOU,
          ſpaſmodic putrid <w part="I">malig-</w><lb/><w part="F">nant</w> and conſumptive
          complaints, in the Eaſt and Weſt-Indies, and <lb/>in America—they are immediate and
          abſolute ſpecifics. So that <lb/>any lady or gentleman of ſenſe and liberality, may, <hi
            rend="sc">thus assisted</hi>, <lb/>become ſovereign phyſicians, and often ſave not only
          their own, but <lb/>the life of a friend or of a fellow creature, when apparently at the
          <lb/>point of death—and when given over by even the beſt phyſicians. <lb/>But above all,
          they are moſt earneſtly recommended to people of <lb/>weak nerves and relaxed habits—who
          are particularly ſuſceptible of <lb/>catching colds and infectious diſorders—to thoſe
          likewiſe who are <lb/>apprehenſive of ſtrokes of the apoplexy or pally—and ſtill more, <w
            part="I">eſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">pecially</w> to thoſe under ſentence of death—I mean
          thoſe perſons who <lb/>have already been viſited by thoſe ſudden—dreadful—and mercileſs
          <lb/>harbingers of the awful—the tremendous hour! </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_22" n="22"/>
        <p rend="indent size(0.8)"><lb/>⁂ Any reſpectable perſon, <hi rend="italic">not of the
            faculty,</hi> in any capital city <lb/>or town in Great-Britain or Ireland—or in any
          other part of the <lb/>world, where theſe great medicines are not yet eſtabliſhed,—and
          <lb/>who are very deſirous to vend them, ought to loſe no time in <w part="I"
            >apply-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> to me, thro' their agents or correſpondents in
          London. As <lb/>ready money is expected, a proper allowance is made; but all <w part="I"
            >ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">pences</w> of carriage, advertizing, &amp;c.—muſt be defrayed
          by the <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſons</w> themſelves; and it is an invariable
          rule with me to return <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F">mediately</w> the money for
          what ever quantity may at any time be ſent <lb/>back as unſold.—In order to prevent
          trouble, I think it right to be <lb/>very particular in mentioning the terms or conditions
          upon which I <lb/>diſpenſe theſe medicines all over the globe, for the general good of
          <lb/>mankind, as well as for my own honour and emolument. </p>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="8"/>
    </body>
    <back>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="10"/>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
