<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Berkenhout: An Essay on the Bite of a Mad Dog</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>John Berkenhout</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">An essay on the bite of a mad dog: in which the claim to
              infallibility of the principal preservative remedies against the hydrophobia is
              examined. By John Berkenhout, M.D.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">N2099</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N2099"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for R. Baldwin, Pater-Noster-Row, MDCCLXXXIII.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1783</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="2"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="83"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">Countway Library of Medicine</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3306992075</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K001365.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: disease"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="1"/>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_3"/>
      <head rend="align-center"><lb/>AN <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">ESSAY</hi>
        <lb/>ON THE <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">Bite of a Mad Dog, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </hi></head>
      <p rend="indent" n="1"><lb/>1. <hi rend="dc(4)">I</hi> Know not of any human attempt
        <lb/>which bears a better reſemblance to <lb/>the knight of La Mancha's attack of a
        <lb/>wind-mill, than that of combating vulgar <lb/>errors; of reaſoning againſt received <w
          part="I">opi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nions</w>. The moſt powerful and pointed <lb/>arguments
        generally fall to the ground, <lb/>when oppoſed by the impenetrable ſhield <lb/>of common
        prejudice. Nevertheleſs, in <lb/>the preſent age, when ſcience is hourly <lb/>making ſuch
        rapid advances towards the <lb/>diſcovery of truth; when knowledge is <lb/>ſo much more
        univerſally diffuſed than in <pb xml:id="page_4" n="2"/><lb/>former times, it ſeems not
        unreaſonable <lb/>to hope, that mankind may be perſuaded <lb/>to beſtow a few moments
        unbiaſſed <w part="I">atten-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> on a ſubject confeſſedly of the
        higheſt <lb/>medical importance. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="2"><lb/>2. This ſubject hath indeed been amply <lb/>and learnedly treated
        by ancient and <w part="I">mo-</w><lb/><w part="F">dern</w> phyſicians, in various countries
        and <lb/>languages; in this kingdom particularly, <lb/>by the celebrated Dr. Mead, and the
        no <lb/>leſs famous Dr. James; the latter of <lb/>whom publiſhed, in the year 1760, an <w
          part="I">en-</w><lb/><w part="F">tire</w> volume on Canine Madneſs. Ancient <lb/>authors
        were leſs diffuſe, and were <w part="I">gene-</w><lb/><w part="F">rally</w> ſatisfied with
        tranſcribing from each <lb/>other. Moſt of theſe writers I have <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſidered</w> with attention, and acknowledge <lb/>myſelf much obliged to them for
        many <lb/>important facts: I cannot, however, avoid <lb/>obſerving, that their labours have
        a <w part="I">mani-</w><lb/><w part="F">feſt</w> tendency to confirm the fatal <w part="I"
          >preju-</w><lb/><w part="F">dice</w> which I moſt devoutly wiſh to <w part="I"
          >eradi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cate</w>; I therefore think myſelf juſtified in <lb/>adding a
        ſmall pamphlet to the <w part="I">volumi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nous</w> tracts already
        written on the diſeaſe <lb/>commonly, but improperly, called the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >hydrophobia,</hi> or dread of water. I ſay <pb xml:id="page_5" n="3"/><lb/><hi
          rend="italic">improperly,</hi> becauſe this averſion to water, <lb/>or to drink of every
        kind, is only one <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſymptom</hi> of the diſeaſe in queſtion, and
        <lb/>that not conſtantly nor excluſively; for <lb/>there are many examples on record, <w
          part="I">ſuf-</w><lb/><w part="F">ficiently</w> authenticated, of this ſymptom, <lb/>this
          <hi rend="italic">hydrophobia,</hi> in patients not bitten by <lb/>a dog, or by any other
        animal. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="3"><lb/>3. I am even inclined to aſſert, that the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >hydrophobia</hi> is not generally a ſymptom of <lb/>the diſeaſe produced by the bite of a
        mad <lb/>dog. It rarely happens that the patient <lb/>has any averſion to water or other
        liquid; <lb/>until by experience he finds an inſuperable <lb/>difficulty in ſwallowing. He
        then dreads <lb/>the approach of water, having already <lb/>found that the attempt to
        ſwallow any l<lb/>iquid produces a violent and painful <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >vulſion</w>; ſo that the ſymptom in queſtion <lb/>is rather a real difficulty of
        ſwallowing <lb/>liquids, than a dread of water. As far as <lb/>my own experience reaches, I
        can, with <lb/>great truth, aver, that I have never yet met <lb/>with a ſingle patient, who
        expreſſed any <lb/>averſion to the ſight, ſound, or mention <lb/>of water, until he had
        found, by <w part="I">experi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ence</w>, that drinking gave him pain. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_6" n="4"/>
      <p rend="indent" n="4"><lb/>4. Some years ago, I was ſent for to a <lb/>young gentleman, who,
        about ſix weeks <lb/>before, had been bit in the arm by one of his <lb/>father's hounds. A
        few hours before his <lb/>death, he ſtept into a tub of warm water <lb/>without fear, ſat
        down, and continued in <lb/>it half an hour. I ſhall, in its proper <lb/>place, relate his
        caſe circumſtantially: I <lb/>mention it at preſent only to prove, that <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">hydrophobia</hi> is improperly conſidered <lb/>as a diagnoſtic ſymptom of
        this diſeaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="5"><lb/>5. I am equally inclined to diſpute the <lb/>propriety of the
        denomination <hi rend="italic">rabies <w part="I">ca-</w><lb/><w part="F">nina</w>,</hi>
        canine madneſs; for though perſons <lb/>thus unhappily afflicted are often violently
        <lb/>agitated during a ſhort time previous to <lb/>their death, yet they generally retain
        their <lb/>reaſon to the laſt moment: this diſeaſe, <lb/>therefore, is improperly conſidered
        as a <lb/>ſpecies of madneſs, if by madneſs we <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >derſtand</w>, a diſtraction, ſuſpenſion, or <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >verſion</w> of the reaſoning faculties. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="6"><lb/>6. Writers, fond of ſearching into <w part="I">an-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">tiquity</w> for what is not worth finding, have <lb/>taken great pains to
        diſcover the moſt <w part="I">an-</w><lb/><w part="F">cient</w> authors that have written on
        canine <pb xml:id="page_7" n="5"/><lb/>madneſs. Hippocrates, moſt certainly, <lb/>has not
        ſaid a ſingle word on the ſubject, <lb/>whatever ſome of his wiſe commentators <lb/>may have
        imagined. A learned liſt of <lb/>ancient authors, who have written on the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">hydrophobia,</hi> may be collected from <w part="I">vari-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ous</w> modern writers; but we ſearch in <lb/>vain for uſeful information on this
          <w part="I">ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F">ject</w> among the remains of high antiquity. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="7"><lb/>7. But if the diſeaſe we are about to <lb/>inveſtigate be neither
        a ſpecies of <hi rend="italic">rabies,</hi>
        <lb/>nor <hi rend="italic">hydrophobia,</hi> what ſhall we call it!— <lb/>It were idle to
        diſpute about a mere name; <lb/>but when a miſnomer conveys a falſe idea, <lb/>it is no
        longer a matter of indifference. <lb/>The fatal diſorder communicated to the <lb/>human
        ſpecies by the bite of a mad dog <lb/>is doubtleſs a ſpaſm of the organs of <w part="I"
          >de-</w><lb/><w part="F">glutition</w> and reſpiration; a ſpecies of <hi rend="italic"
          >an-<lb/>gina convulſiva, vel ſuffocativa.</hi> The <lb/>generic term <hi rend="italic"
          >Angina,</hi> is thus defined by <lb/>the learned Boerhaave, in his 783d
          apho-<lb/>riſm—<hi rend="italic">Impedita valde, dolens admodum, vel <lb/>et impedita et
          dolens ſimul, deglutitio atque <lb/>reſpiratio, quæ contingit a cauſa morboſa <lb/>agente
          in partes binis his functionibus <w part="I">inſer-</w><lb/><w part="F">vientes</w>, ſupra
          pulmones et ſupra ſtomachum <pb xml:id="page_8" n="6"/><lb/>poſitas, Angina vocatur;</hi>
        and in aphoriſm <lb/>818, he ſays,—<hi rend="italic">Si convulſionum cauſa <w part="I"
            >quæ-</w><lb/><w part="F">cunque</w> muſculos pharingis laryngeſve <w part="I"
            >oc-</w><lb/><w part="F">cupaverit</w>, oritur ſubita ſuffocativa <w part="I"
            >an-</w><lb/><w part="F">gina</w>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="8"><lb/>8. As I am here writing particularly <lb/>to medical readers, it
        is unneceſſary to <lb/>tranſlate the above quotation. Such <w part="I">read-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ers</w>, after comparing theſe definitions with <lb/>the ſymptoms of the <hi
          rend="italic">hydrophobia,</hi> as it is <lb/>called, will, I believe, acknowledge their
        <lb/>ſurpriſe, that Boerhaave ſhould not rather <lb/>have claſſed it as a ſpecies of <hi
          rend="italic">angina</hi> than of <lb/><hi rend="italic">mania.</hi> Later noſologiſts
        ſeem equally <w part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">fortunate</w> in point of arrangement. In
        the <lb/>ſyſtem of the celebrated Sauvages, we find <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hydrophobia</hi>
        in the claſs <hi rend="italic">Veſaniæ,</hi> and <lb/>order <hi rend="italic"
          >Moroſitates.</hi> His definition of the <lb/>claſs is, <hi rend="italic">error in
          imaginatione, appetitu, <lb/>vel juditio;</hi> of the order, <hi rend="italic">cupiditates
          aut <lb/>averſiones depravatæ.</hi> Now, I appeal, not <lb/>to ſyſtematic writers, but to
        thoſe who <lb/>have attended patients ſuffering under this <lb/>dreadful diſtemper; and I
        requeſt them <lb/>to recollect, whether erroneous <w part="I">imagina-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tion</w>, appetite, or judgment, or depraved <lb/>deſires or averſions, were among the <w
          part="I">ſymp-</w><pb xml:id="page_9" n="7"/><lb/><w part="F">toms</w> they obſerved? As
        to the patient's <lb/>refuſing to drink, it proceeds not from an <lb/>imaginary averſion to
        water, but from a <lb/>real, a painful convulſion in the organs of <lb/>deglutition, excited
        by every effort to <lb/>ſwallow liquids. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="9"><lb/>9. Linneus divides the diſeaſe in <w part="I">queſ-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">tion</w> into two diſtinct genera, <hi rend="italic">viz. Rabies,</hi>
        <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Hydrophobia:</hi> the firſt he defines in <lb/>theſe words, <hi
          rend="italic">Deſiderium mordendi <w part="I">laceran-</w><lb/><w part="F">dique</w>
          innocuos;</hi> the ſecond, thus, <hi rend="italic">Aver-<lb/>ſatio potulentorum cum rigore
          et ſardiaſi,</hi>
        <lb/>adding, <hi rend="italic">ſœpius præcedenti maritata.</hi> He <lb/>places them in the
        claſs <hi rend="italic">Mentales,</hi> and <lb/>order <hi rend="italic">Pathetici,</hi>
        where, from what I have <lb/>ſaid above, they muſt appear to have no <lb/>buſineſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="10"><lb/>10. In Vogel's arrangement, under the <lb/>claſs of <hi
          rend="italic">Febres,</hi> and order <hi rend="italic">continuæ,</hi> we <lb/>find the <hi
          rend="italic">Hydrophobia</hi> thus characterized, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Febris cum
          averſatione liquidorum, ſingultu, <lb/>convulſione, et delirio.</hi> The abſurdity of
        <lb/>making the hydrophobia a continued <lb/>fever is ſo obvious, that it requires no
        <lb/>comment. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_10" n="8"/>
      <p rend="indent" n="11"><lb/>11. Dr. Cullen denominates his ſecond <lb/>claſs of diſeaſes, <hi
          rend="italic">neuroſes,</hi> which he <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">fines—</w>
        <hi rend="italic">Senſus et motus læſi, ſine pyrexia et <lb/>ſine morbo locali. Spaſmi</hi>
        conſtitute the <lb/>third order of this claſs, and of this order, <lb/>the laſt genus is <hi
          rend="italic">hydrophobia,</hi> thus defined <lb/>— <hi rend="italic">Potionis cujuſlibet,
          ut convulſionem <w part="I">pha-</w><lb/><w part="F">ryngis</w> dolentem cientis,
          faſtidium et horror; <lb/>plerumque e morſu animalis rabidi.</hi> Of <lb/>this genus he
        admits two ſpecies, <hi rend="italic">viz. <lb/>vulgaris,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
          >ſpontanea,</hi> the firſt of which <lb/>is the immediate object of our preſent
        <lb/>conſideration. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="12"><lb/>12. Dr. Cullen, with his uſual <w part="I">ſaga-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">city</w>, ſaw the error of former medical <lb/>writers, who miſtook this ſpaſm in
        the <lb/>organs of deglutition, for a ſpecies of <lb/>madneſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="13"><lb/>13. But by what name ſoever we <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">tinguiſh</w> this dreadful diſeaſe, previous to <lb/>our enquiry concerning its
        ſymptoms in <lb/>the human ſpecies, let us endeavour to <lb/>aſcertain thoſe by which it may
        be known <lb/>in the brute, where it originates. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Authors have amuſed themſelves with <lb/>learned diſquiſitions
        concerning the cauſe <pb xml:id="page_11" n="9"/><lb/>of this <hi rend="italic">rabies</hi>
        in dogs, wolves, foxes, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        <lb/>Some accuſe worms within the cranium, <lb/>or under the tongue. Dr. Cheyne aſcribed
        <lb/>it to a ſuperabundance of animal ſalts, <lb/>and Dr. James was of opinion that <w
          part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">tream</w> heat, want of water,<note place="marg"
          rend="size(0.7) italic"> Treat. on canine madneſs, p. <hi rend="italic">20</hi>
        </note> and putrid <lb/>animal food, are generally the cauſe of <lb/>this madneſs in dogs,
        which he calls a <lb/>fever. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="14"><lb/>14. The uſual ſymptoms which <w part="I">indi-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">cate</w> approaching madneſs in a dog, are, <lb/>firſt, an evident diminution of
        his natural <lb/>keen appetite for food. He eats, indeed, <lb/>and laps his milk or water,
        but with <lb/>obvious indifference. His eyes have loſt <lb/>their uſual luſtre; he drops his
        ears and <lb/>tail, ſhews no ſign of hilarity at the <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >proach</w> of his maſter, and his whole aſpect <lb/>exhibits a picture of melancholy,
        perfectly <lb/>intelligible to thoſe who are accuſtomed <lb/>to obſerve this animal with
        attention. In <lb/>a day or two more, he refuſes both meat <lb/>and drink, ſhuns the ſociety
        of other dogs, <lb/>and is equally, after a ſhort reconnoitre, <lb/>avoided by them. He now
        quits his <w part="I">ha-</w><lb/><w part="F">bitation</w>, runs forward, evidently without
        <lb/>having any thing in purſuit, ſnaps at every <pb xml:id="page_12" n="10"/><lb/>animal
        that comes in his way, and within <lb/>forty-eight hours dies convulſed. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="15"><lb/>15. Such are the ſymptoms of this <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">temper</w> in the brute creation; and theſe <lb/>ſymptoms are ſo conſtant and
        unequivocal, <lb/>that all danger might eaſily be prevented, <lb/>by the ſmalleſt degree of
        attention. In <lb/>the firſt ſtage of the diſorder, the dog has <lb/>no propenſity to bite,
        ſo that he may be <lb/>ſeized and tied up without fear. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="16"><lb/>16. Boerhaave has collected from <hi rend="italic"
          >Fra-<lb/>caſtorius</hi> and other writers, a catalogue of <lb/>ſymptoms more numerous,
        and ſomewhat <lb/>different from thoſe above enumerated; but <lb/>as it was not the reſult
        of his own <w part="I">obſer-</w><lb/><w part="F">vation</w>, his deſcription of this, as of
        many <lb/>other diſeaſes, ſhould be read, <hi rend="italic">cum grano <lb/>ſalis.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="17"><lb/>17. Pliny,<note place="marg" rend="size(0.7)"> Hiſt. nat.
          <lb/>Lib. 29, c. 5. </note> in his chapter <hi rend="italic">de medicina
          <lb/>animalium,</hi> tells us, that there is a worm <lb/>under the tongues of dogs, which
        if <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">tracted</w> when they are whelps prevents <lb/>their
        running mad. This doubtleſs was <lb/>a vulgar error of the times in which he <lb/>wrote, and
        thus the univerſal prevalence <pb xml:id="page_13" n="11"/><lb/>of this abſurd opinion down
        to the <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſent</w> age is accounted for. Dr. James
        <lb/>very juſtly ridicules this idea of a worm <lb/>under the tongue.<note place="marg"
          rend="italic size(0.7)"> On can. mad. p. <hi rend="roman">203.</hi>
        </note>—<q rend="quotes">I take it (ſays the <lb/>Doctor) to be a nerve; and this <w
            part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tracting</w> when recently taken away, the <lb/>ideots
          fancy it ſtirs, and believe it a <lb/>worm, towhich it bears no manner of
          <lb/>reſemblance.</q>—He is certainly right <lb/>in believing it not to be a worm; but he
        <lb/>is miſtaken in ſuppoſing it a nerve, for a <lb/>reaſon which himſelf hath adduced, <w
          part="I">name-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w>, its contraction; nerves are not elaſtic.
        <lb/>He is alſo wrong in ſaying, it bears no <lb/>reſemblance to a worm.<note place="marg"
          rend="italic size(0.7)"> De ſed. &amp; caus. morb. lib. <hi rend="roman">1.</hi> eſs <hi
            rend="roman">viii.</hi> art. <hi rend="roman">35.</hi>
        </note> Morgagni <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">bably</w> was nearer the truth, in
        calling it a <lb/>tendinous ligament. Be it what it may, <lb/>it is certainly of uſe to the
        dog and its <lb/>extirpation anſwers no ſalutary purpoſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="18"><lb/>18. Let us now trace the progreſs of <lb/>this fatal diſeaſe in
        thoſe of the human <lb/>ſpecies who have the misfortune to be bit <lb/>by a mad dog or cat.
        The wound, on <lb/>immediate inſpection, diſcovers no ſigns <lb/>of malignity. If it be ſo
        ſuperficial as <lb/>ſcarcely to have drawn blood it generally <lb/>heals without the leaſt
        inflammation, and <pb xml:id="page_14" n="12"/><lb/>in that caſe there is little or no
        danger: on <lb/>the ſecond day it ſeems a mere ſcratch, <lb/>and on the third it is hardly
        viſible. But <lb/>if, on the ſecond morning, we obſerve an <lb/>inflamed circle ſpreading
        from the wound, <lb/>reſembling that which ſurrounds the <lb/>puncture when inoculation for
        the ſmall-<lb/>pox has taken effect, there is reaſon to <lb/>believe that part of the
        poiſonous <hi rend="italic">ſaliva</hi>
        <lb/>of the enraged animal is abſorbed, and the <lb/>conſequent ſymptoms may be rationally
        <lb/>expected. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="19"><lb/>19. Meanwhile the patient takes the <lb/>Ormskirk, or ſome other
        equally infallible <lb/>medicine, is hurried away to the ſea, in <lb/>which he is two or
        three times dipped <lb/>and half drowned; the wound heals, and <lb/>all his apprehenſions
        vaniſh. Unhappily, <lb/>this deluſion alſo vaniſhes in the ſpace of <lb/>five or ſix weeks,
        about which period he <lb/>feels a<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* This ſymptom
          is ſaid to have been firſt mentioned <lb/>by Salius. </note> pain in the part where he was
        bit, <lb/>gradually extending over the whole limb. <lb/>He now recollects his misfortune.
        The <lb/>horrible ſtories he has heard ruſh upon his <lb/>mind, and the hourly expectation
        of <pb xml:id="page_15" n="13"/><lb/>madneſs and death fill his whole ſoul. <lb/>Under ſuch
        apprehenſions it is no wonder <lb/>that he ſhould diſcover ſymptoms of <lb/>impatience,
        anxiety, and even of delirium. <lb/>But theſe ſymptoms proceed from, and <lb/>are always in
        proportion to, his <w part="I">appre-</w><lb/><w part="F">henſions</w>. His reaſoning
        faculties continue <lb/>unimpaired; his pulſe becomes irregular <lb/>and quick; but there is
        no preternatural <lb/>heat, foul tongue, nor any other febrile <lb/>ſymptom. He complains of
        a fullneſs and <lb/>prickling in his throat, and ſwallows his <lb/>ſpittle with difficulty.
        So far from <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">preſſing</w> any averſion to water, he calls
        for <lb/>drink; but in the attempt to ſwallow it <lb/>he is convulſed, and, after two or
        three <lb/>painful efforts, the approach, or even the <lb/>ſight of any liquid produces
        horror. He <lb/>continues ſome time longer to ſwallow <lb/>ſolid food without much pain or
        difficulty. <lb/>At laſt even that is impoſſible. He <lb/>now becomes ſenſible of an
        irreſiſtable <lb/>inclination to ſtruggle, and wiſhes to <lb/>be held; he breathes quick and
        with great <lb/>difficulty, and in a few hours after dies <lb/>convulſed, as if he were
        ſtrangled with a <lb/>cord. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_16" n="14"/>
      <p rend="indent" n="20"><lb/>20. Such, and ſuch only, are the proper <lb/>diagnoſtic ſymptoms
        of this fatal diſorder: <lb/>they are amply ſufficient to diſtinguiſh it <lb/>from any
        other, and are therefore all that <lb/>are neceſſary to be generally known; but <lb/>as a
        diſeaſe ſo frequently mortal cannot be <lb/>too well underſtood, I ſhall proceed to
        <lb/>mention the ſymptoms above omitted, as <lb/>I find them enumerated by the principal
        <lb/>authors that have written on this ſubject. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="21"><lb/>21. <hi rend="italic">Cœlius Aurelianus,</hi> who collected
        <lb/>his hiſtory of the <hi rend="italic">hydrophobia</hi> from <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Eudemus, Soranus,</hi> and other writers with <lb/>whom we are little acquainted, tells
        us <lb/>that the <hi rend="italic">hydrophobia</hi> is immediately <w part="I"
          >pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceded</w> by extreme irritability, unuſual <lb/>motions of the
        body, diſturbed ſleep or <lb/>abſolute wakefulneſs, indigeſtion, <w part="I"
          >ſtretch-</w><lb/><w part="F">ings</w>, yawning, nauſea, imaginary notions <lb/>of bad
        weather, and no appetite for drink. <lb/>To theſe ſymptoms, according to the <lb/>ſame
        author, ſucceed, when the <hi rend="italic">hydro-<lb/>phobia</hi> begins, a deſire to
          drink<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5) italic">* Appetentia bibendi, <hi
            rend="roman">which Dr. James tranſlates,</hi> a violent <lb/>and inſatiable
          thirſt.—Treat. On Can, Madn. p. <hi rend="roman">55.</hi>
        </note>, with <lb/>terror at the ſight, ſound, or name of <lb/>water. The patient is afraid
        even of <pb xml:id="page_17" n="15"/><lb/>fomentations with oil; his pulſe is denſe <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">(denſus)</hi> ſmall and irregular: ſometimes <lb/>a ſmall degree of fever,
        convulſive motions <lb/>of the ſtomach, ſpaſms in the precordia, <lb/>numbneſs of the
        joints, and torpor of the <lb/>inteſtinal canal; frequent inclination to <lb/>make water;
        trembling and catchings of <lb/>the limbs; voice hoarſe, reſembling the <lb/>barking of a
        dog; ſpiral poſture of the <lb/>body, like that of a dog lying on the <lb/>ground; anxiety
        when any perſon enters <lb/>the room, as if apprehenſive that he ſhould <lb/>bring water;
        redneſs of the face and <lb/>eyes; body emaciated, the ſuperior parts <lb/>pale and
        ſweating; <hi rend="italic">veretri frequens tenſio <lb/>cum ſeminis involuntario
          jactu,</hi> &amp;c. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="22"><lb/>22. To the ſymptoms above mentioned <lb/>Boerhaave adds the
          following—Laſſitude,<note place="marg" rend="size(0.7)"> Aphor. <lb/>1138. </note> weight,
        and indolence in every muſcle of <lb/>the body; diſturbed ſleep, frequent <lb/>ſtartings,
        frightful dreams, convulſions; <lb/>conſtant inquietude, depreſſion, ſighing, <lb/>and love
        of ſolitude. If the patient be <lb/>bled, the blood exhibits no morbid <w part="I"
          >ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pearance</w>. He now complains of a <w part="I"
          >ſqueez-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> about his heart. He is terrified not <lb/>only at the
        ſight of any fluid, but even of <pb xml:id="page_18" n="16"/><lb/>any pellucid or reflecting
        body. He <lb/>vomits viſcid bilious phlegm or poraceous <lb/>bile; grows hot and feveriſh.
        To a <lb/>gradual exacerbation of theſe ſymptoms <lb/>are now accumulated a dry projected
        <lb/>tongue, open foaming mouth, extreme <lb/>thirſt, an irreſiſtable inclination to ſpit
        at, <lb/>and bite thoſe that are near him; cold <lb/>ſweats, complete <hi rend="italic"
          >rabies,</hi> and on the fourth <lb/>day the patient dies. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="23"><lb/>23. Dr. Mead copies Boerhaave without <lb/>any material
        alteration, except in ſaying <lb/>that death relieves the patient in two days <lb/>after the
        firſt ſymptom of <hi rend="italic">hydrophobia.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>Sauvages, in his <hi rend="italic">Noſologia,</hi> adds no <lb/>other
        ſymptom to thoſe above related; but <lb/>from Dr. James we learn the following <lb/>very
        curious and material proof of the <lb/>ſalutary inſtinct of dogs, namely, that <lb/>they fly
        from perſons actually infected by <lb/>the bite of a mad animal. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="24"><lb/>24. Such readers as are not acquainted <lb/>with medical authors,
        and particularly <lb/>with the writings of the celebrated <lb/>Leyden profeſſor, will wonder
        why he <pb xml:id="page_19" n="17"/><lb/>ſhould have exhibited ſo numerous a <lb/>catalogue
        of ſymptoms, if it be true, that <lb/>ſo few of them really occur in patients <lb/>afflicted
        with this malady. But his wonder <lb/>will ceaſe, when he is told that <w part="I"
          >Boer-</w><lb/><w part="F">haave</w>, when he began the ſtudy of phyſic, <lb/>found the
        ſcience a mere chaos. He <lb/>immediately conceived the idea of <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ducing</w> it to method, and, after much <lb/>reading, condenſed and arranged his
        <lb/>materials in the form of aphoriſms, <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtituting</w>
        a new ſyſtem of phyſic, which <lb/>aphoriſms he uſed as the text of his <w part="I"
          >acade-</w><lb/><w part="F">mical</w> lectures. All his ſymptoms very <lb/>ſeldom occur in
        the ſame patient: they <lb/>were collected from a variety of authors, <lb/>and are to be
        remembered by phyſicians, <lb/>rather as poſſible <hi rend="italic">phenomena</hi> than as
          <w part="I">abſo-</w><lb/><w part="F">lute</w> diagnoſtics. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="25"><lb/>25. Having thus attended our <w part="I">unfortu-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">nate</w> patient to the final period of his <lb/>life, let us proceed to examine
        the <lb/>morbid appearances in his body upon <lb/>diſſection. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="26"><lb/>26. <hi rend="italic">Cappivacci,</hi> an Italian, was, I <w
          part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">lieve</w>, the firſt anatomiſt who publiſhed <pb
          xml:id="page_20" n="18"/><lb/>an account of any diſſection of this kind. <lb/>His
        obſervations, together with thoſe of <lb/>Zwingerus, Brechtfeld, and other writers,
        <lb/>were republiſhed in the <hi rend="italic">Sepulchretum,</hi> and <lb/>thence collected
        by Boerhaave, and <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">denſed</w> into a ſingle aphoriſm,
        which, for the <lb/>ſake of the Engliſh reader, I will tranſlate.<lb/><note place="marg"
          rend="size(0.7)">
          <hi rend="italic">Aph.</hi> 1140. </note> —<q rend="quotes">The morbid <hi rend="italic"
            >phenomena</hi> diſcoverable <lb/>in the body by diſſection are generally <lb/>the
          organs of deglutition ſomewhat <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">flamed</w>, bilious
          gluten in the ſtomach, <lb/>the gall-bladder full of black bile, the <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">pericardium</hi> dry, the lungs incredibly <lb/>diſtended with blood, the
          heart full of <lb/>blood almoſt dry, the arteries full, the <lb/>veins empty, blood in the
          arteries <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">tremely</w> liquid, and ſcarce coagulating
          <lb/>in the air, all the muſcles, viſcera, <lb/>brain, and ſpinal marrow, dryer than
          <lb/>uſual.</q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="27"><lb/>27. <hi rend="italic">Zwingerus,</hi><note place="marg"
          rend="size(0.7)">
          <hi rend="italic">Epb.</hi> N.C. <hi rend="italic">dec.</hi> 3. a 2. <hi rend="italic"
            >obs.</hi> 104. </note> in a body which he <lb/>diſſected, found the membraneous <w
          part="I">inter-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtices</w> between the cartilaginous circles of
        <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">aſpera arteria</hi> intenſely red, and the <lb/>ſtomach and
        inteſtines ſprinkled with red <lb/>ſpots. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_21" n="19"/>
      <p rend="indent" n="28"><lb/>28. Brechtfeld found the entire tract of <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">œſophagus</hi> narrow,<note place="marg" rend="italic size(0.7)"> Sepulc.
          Anat. </note> and in a ſtate of <lb/>conſtriction. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="29"><lb/>29. M. Tauvry, a French anatomiſt,<note place="marg"
          rend="italic size(0.7)"> Hiſt. R. Acad. an. <lb/><hi rend="roman">1699.</hi>
        </note> found the <hi rend="italic">gula</hi> and <hi rend="italic">aſpera arteria</hi> in a
        ſtate <lb/>of inflammation. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="30"><lb/>30. <hi rend="italic">Morgagni</hi> tells us of an <w part="I"
          >hydro-</w><lb/><w part="F">phobic</w> patient whoſe body,<note place="marg"
          rend="italic size(0.7)"> De. Sed. et Caus. Morb. ep. <hi rend="roman">viii.</hi> art. <hi
            rend="roman">23.</hi>
        </note> though <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſected</w> ſixteen hours after death, in
        a cold <lb/>ſeaſon, was intolerably putrid. Black <lb/>bile was found in the gall-bladder;
        the <lb/>lungs were alſo black, and very offenſive. <lb/>The right auricle of the heart was
        much <lb/>dilated, the left very narrow. The blood-<lb/>veſſels of the brain were all full;
        the brain <lb/>was rather dry. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="31"><lb/>31. The ſame author relates another <lb/>hiſtory of a man who
        died about a month <lb/>after being bit by a mad dog,<note place="marg"
          rend="italic size(0.7)"> Ib. art. <hi rend="roman">25.</hi>
        </note> and whoſe <lb/>body, which was diſſected about twenty-<lb/>four hours after death,
        in the hotteſt <lb/>ſeaſon of the year, was much leſs offenſive <lb/>than the former. His
        neck had a livid <lb/>appearance; the blood-veſſels of the <lb/>ſtomach were as full as if
        they had been <pb xml:id="page_22" n="20"/><lb/>injected; the ſtomach was diſtended with
        <lb/>air, and contained beſides a yellow and <lb/>greeniſh water; part of the liver was
        <lb/>livid, and the gall-bladder was full of <lb/>brown bile; the diaphragm was a little
        <lb/>inflamed; the lungs on the poſterior part <lb/>were tumid with blood, and black; the
        <lb/>upper part of the <hi rend="italic">œſophagus, aſpera arteria, <lb/>pharynx,</hi> and
          <hi rend="italic">larynx</hi> ſeemed nearly <w part="I">gan-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >grenous</w>; in the head, the veſſels of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">meninges</hi> were
        diſtended with blood, and <lb/>the internal ſubſtance of the brain was <lb/>dotted with red
        points; the internal <w part="I">ven-</w><lb/><w part="F">tricles</w> contained a reddiſh
          <hi rend="italic">ſerum.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="32"><lb/>32. In a third diſſection the ſtomach <lb/>was found to contain a
        viſcid cineritious <lb/>fluid,<note place="marg" rend="italic size(0.5)"> Ib. art. <hi
            rend="roman">27.</hi>
        </note> and the gall-bladder a ſmall <w part="I">quan-</w><lb/><w part="F">tity</w> of
        yellow bile; the illiac veins were <lb/>violently diſtended with blood, and their
        <lb/>correſponding arteries quite empty; lungs <lb/>ſtuffed full with <hi rend="italic"
          >craſſamentum,</hi> and in part <lb/>almoſt in a gangrenous ſtate; the heart
        <lb/>contained a ſmall quantity of blood <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſembling</w>
        melted pitch; the organs of <lb/>deglutition ſhewed no other ſigns of <w part="I"
          >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">flammation</w> than a ſlight redneſs at the top <lb/>of the <hi
          rend="italic">pharynx;</hi> but the membrane which <pb xml:id="page_23" n="21"
        /><lb/>inveſts the <hi rend="italic">epiglottis</hi> was criſp and <w part="I"
          >ſhrivel-</w><lb/><w part="F">led</w>; all the veſſels of the <hi rend="italic"
          >meninges</hi> were <lb/>immoderably full of black blood; neither <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">cerebrum, cerebellum,</hi> ſpinal marrow, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >viſcera</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">thorax</hi> and <hi rend="italic">abdomen,</hi> nor
        any <lb/>of the muſcles were more dry than they <lb/>generally are; in the ventricles of the
        <lb/>brain were about three ounces of yellowiſh <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſerum.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="33"><lb/>33. <hi rend="italic">Morgagni,</hi><note place="marg"
          rend="italic size(0.7)"> Ib. art. <hi rend="roman">32.</hi>
        </note> after comparing theſe <lb/>obſervations with thoſe of Mead, <hi rend="italic"
          >Plancus, <lb/>Fabbri, Brogiani,</hi> &amp;c. concludes, that the <lb/>bodies after death
        differ more from each <lb/>other than when living: <q rend="quotes">For (ſays he)
          <lb/>whilſt alive, they all drink with great <lb/>difficulty, and moſt of them not <w
            part="I">with-</w><lb/><w part="F">out</w> horror; but, upon diſſection, we <lb/>find no
          one phenomenon common to <lb/>every ſubject. As to that dryneſs of <lb/>the parts, ſo
          generally obſerved, it is <lb/>by no means univerſal; nor does it <lb/>ſeem to deſerve
          much conſideration, <lb/>becauſe the violent agitations of the <w part="I">pa-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tient</w>, and the conſequent evacuations, <lb/>ſenſible and inſenſible; the
          frequent <lb/>exhibition of alexipharmics, and long <pb xml:id="page_24" n="22"
          /><lb/>abſtinence from liquids, are ſufficient <lb/>to account for it.</q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="34"><lb/>34. On the authority, therefore, of <lb/>Morgagni, who was a man
        of moſt <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">tenſive</w> anatomical reading and experience,
        <lb/>we muſt conclude, that diſſections have <lb/>not hitherto diſcovered the part, or
        parts, <lb/>of the human body particularly affected, <lb/>or injured, and conſequently no
        curative <lb/>indication can thence be deduced. He is <lb/>of opinion, nevertheleſs, that
        the ſeat of <lb/>the diſorder is in the nerves and brain. <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Democritus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gajus,</hi><note place="marg"
          rend="size(0.7) italic"> Cœl. Aurel. Lib. <hi rend="italic">iii.</hi> c. <hi rend="roman"
            >14.</hi>
        </note> two of the moſt <lb/>ancient writers on this ſubject, were of <lb/>the ſame opinion;
        as were alſo the <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ciples</w> of <hi rend="italic"
          >Aſclepiades.</hi> Some of the <w part="I">anci-</w><lb/><w part="F">ents</w> accuſed the
        diaphragm, ſome the <lb/>ſtomach and inteſtines, and ſome the heart. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="35"><lb/>35. Boerhaave,<note place="marg" rend="size(0.7)">
          <hi rend="italic">Aph.</hi> 1142. </note> from the hiſtory and <lb/>compariſon of the <hi
          rend="italic">hydrophobia</hi> with other <lb/>diſeaſes, was induced to believe, that it
        is <lb/>firſt an affection of the nerves; that <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >vulſions</w> of the <hi rend="italic">viſcera</hi> are thence <w part="I"
          >produc-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>; that the blood and humours thence <lb/>become
        vitiated; but that the primary <lb/>ſeat of the diſorder is in the region of the <pb
          xml:id="page_25" n="23"/><lb/>ſtomach. In this laſt part of his theory, <lb/>he followed
        the opinion of <hi rend="italic">Arthemidorus,</hi><note place="marg"
          rend="italic size(0.7)"> Cœl. Aurel. Lib. <hi rend="roman">iii.</hi>c. <hi rend="roman"
            >14.</hi>
        </note>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Artorius,</hi> and the diſciples of <hi rend="italic"
          >Aſclepiades.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="36"><lb/>36. Dr. Mead was perſuaded,<note place="marg"
          rend="italic size(0.7)"> Mechan. Acc. of Poiſons. Eſſay, 3.</note>that the <lb/>ſeat of
        the diſeaſe is in the nervous fluid, <lb/>contaminated by the ſaliva of the dog <w part="I"
          >act-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> as a ferment, and gradually <w part="I"
          >aſſimilat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> the whole to its own degree of morbid
        <lb/>acrimony. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="37"><lb/>37. Dr. James ridicules theſe opinions, <lb/>and roundly
          declares,<note place="marg" rend="size(0.7)"> P. 37. </note> that <q rend="quotes">he does
          not <lb/>believe one ſyllable of the modern <lb/>doctrine of nervous juices and nervous
          <lb/>diſtempers.</q> Previous to the diſplay <lb/>of his own theory, in order to render it
        <lb/>intelligible to readers unacquainted with <lb/>anatomy, he tranſlates, from Boerhaave's
        <lb/>preface to his <hi rend="italic">collection of authors on the <lb/>venereal
          diſeaſe,</hi> a minute deſcription of the <lb/>cellular membrane; to which he adds two
        <lb/>pages more, on the ſame ſubject, from <lb/>Cheſelden. The firſt of theſe begins
          <lb/>thus—<q rend="quotes">This membrane is of a vaſcular <lb/>contexture,</q>
        <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> This is certainly not <lb/>true. If Dr. James had ever read
        ſo <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">mon</w> a book as Haller's <hi rend="italic">Primæ
          Lineæ,</hi> he <pb xml:id="page_26" n="24"/><lb/>would not have quoted Boerhaave and
        <lb/>Cheſelden on this occaſion. His theory, h<lb/>owever, is briefly this—The poiſon <w
          part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tained</w> in the ſaliva of the mad dog is
        <lb/>communicated through the wound made <lb/>by his teeth to the fat contained in the
        <lb/>cellular membrane, which fat, by <w part="I">fer-</w><lb/><w part="F">mentation</w>
        with the ſaliva, is aſſimilated <lb/>into a poiſon; now this fat being mixt <lb/>with the
        blood, and conveyed to the liver, <lb/>by the <hi rend="italic">vena portarum,</hi> the bile
        is <w part="I">contami-</w><lb/><w part="F">nated</w>, and neceſſarily produces all the
        <lb/>ſymptoms obſervable in canine madneſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="38"><lb/>38. To render this theory more <w part="I">intel-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ligible</w>, the Doctor informs the ignorant <lb/>reader,<note place="marg"
          rend="size(0.7)"> P. 77. </note>
        <q rend="quotes">that there is a perpetual <w part="I">inter-</w><lb/><w part="F">courſe</w>
          betwixt the blood veſſels and <lb/>the cellular membrane, and <w part="I"
            >conſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">quently</w> between the contents of both, <lb/>the blood and
          fat.</q>—It is ſomewhat <lb/>ſingular, that this poiſoned fat ſhould, in <lb/>its paſſage
        to the liver, mix with the <lb/>blood without injuring that fluid, which <lb/>throughout the
        entire progreſs of the <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">eaſe</w> is found to differ in
        nothing from <lb/>that of a perſon in health. This <w part="I">obſta-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >cle</w> was too obvious to eſcape the Doctor; <pb xml:id="page_27" n="25"/><lb/>but he
        tumbles over it very clumſily: he <lb/>ſuppoſes, notwithſtanding appearances, <lb/>that the
        blood muſt be ultimately <w part="I">viti-</w><lb/><w part="F">ated</w> by the bile; ſo that
        the blood firſt <lb/>vitiates the bile, and the bile returns the <lb/>compliment to the
        blood. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="39"><lb/>39. Thus, then, according to Dr. <lb/>James, the liver is the
        primary ſeat and <lb/>fountain of the hydrophobia, which <hi rend="italic"
          >viſ-<lb/>cus,</hi> he tells us,<note place="marg" rend="size(0.7)"> P. 82. </note>
        <q rend="quotes">ſupplies the reſt of the <lb/>body with bile in immenſe quantities.</q>
        <lb/>In what phyſiological ſchool the Doctor <lb/>learnt that the reſt of the body is
        ſupplied <lb/>with bile in immenſe quantities is <w part="I">diffi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >cult</w> to imagine. I know of no part of the <lb/>body which is ſupplied with bile
        except the <lb/><hi rend="italic">duodenum,</hi> where, mixing with the <w part="I"
          >di-</w><lb/><w part="F">geſted</w> aliment iſſuing from the ſtomach, <lb/>part of it is
        converted into chyle, and <lb/>thereby bereft of all its bilious qualities, <lb/>and the
        remainder carried through the <lb/>inteſtinal canal, and finally ejected: ſo <lb/>that no
        bile, <hi rend="italic">quaſi</hi> bile, is abſorbed, and <lb/>conſequently no part of the
        body except <lb/>the inteſtinal canal is ſupplied with this <lb/>fluid. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_28" n="26"/>
      <p rend="indent" n="40"><lb/>40. But, if it be true that the liver is <lb/>the part of the
        body chiefly affected in the <lb/>human ſpecies, we may, I think, fairly <lb/>conclude, that
        this <hi rend="italic">viſcus</hi> is alſo the <w part="I">pri-</w><lb/><w part="F">mary</w>
        ſeat of the diſorder in dogs. Now, <lb/>it is very certain, that the liver of a <lb/>mad
        dog, ſuppoſed to be an infallible <lb/>remedy againſt canine madneſs, hath <lb/>been
        frequently eaten without any bad <lb/>effect. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="41"><lb/>41. There is yet another objection to <lb/>Dr. James's <hi
          rend="italic">hypotheſis,</hi> which the <w part="I">ana-</w><lb/><w part="F">tomical</w>
        reader will probably think of <lb/>ſome weight.—Page 78 of his treatiſe, he <lb/>tells us,
        that <q rend="diple quotes">the poiſonous ſaliva <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >hering</w> to the tooth of a dog is <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F">mediately</w>
          communicated to the fat <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſiding</w> in one or more of
          the cells of the <lb/>cellular membrane; that "a ſcratch <lb/>is ſufficient, if it only
          raiſe the cuticle, <lb/>without drawing a drop of blood;" <lb/>for (continues the Doctor)
          this ſubtile <lb/>poiſon, as well as the venereal venom, <lb/>is capable of entering the
          cellular <w part="I">mem-</w><lb/><w part="F">brane</w> when applied to any part not
          <lb/>covered by the <hi rend="italic">cuticula.</hi></q>
      </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_29" n="27"/>
      <p rend="indent" n="42"><lb/>42. Is it poſſible that Dr. James, the <lb/>author of a medical
        dictionary in three <lb/>folio volumes, ſhould not have known, <lb/>that there is no
        external part of the <w part="I">hu-</w><lb/><w part="F">man</w> body which is not covered
        by the <lb/>cuticle. That he was really ignorant of <lb/>this fact is ſtill more evident
        from the <lb/>following paſſage in his 16th page—After <lb/>relating a caſe from Van
        Swieten, who <lb/>quotes it from <hi rend="italic">Palmarius,</hi> of ſeveral <w part="I"
          >chil-</w><lb/><w part="F">dren</w> having caught the <hi rend="italic">hydrophobia</hi>
        by <lb/>kiſſing their father, who had been bit by <lb/>a mad dog, he ſays—<q rend="quotes"
          >In this caſe it is <lb/>very poſſible that ſome of the frothy <lb/>ſaliva might be
          conveyed to the lips or <lb/>the mouth of the children, which, <hi rend="italic">not
            <lb/>being defended by the cuticle,</hi> might <lb/>communicate the contagion, as it <w
            part="I">hap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pens</w> with reſpect to the venereal <w part="I"
            >poi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſon</w>.</q> —Now, it is not only certain that <lb/>the <hi
          rend="italic">glans penis,</hi> the lips, and mouth, are <lb/>covered by the cuticle, but
        that it is <lb/>continued through the fauces, <hi rend="italic">œſophagus</hi>
        <lb/>and inteſtinal canal. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="43"><lb/>43. But the Doctor aſſures us that, for <lb/>the ſaliva of the
        dog to poiſon the fat, <q rend="quotes">a <lb/>ſcratch is ſufficient, if it only raiſes the
            <pb xml:id="page_30" n="28"/><lb/>cuticle.</q> Surely, the Doctor had <w part="I"
          >for-</w><lb/><w part="F">got</w>, that the cellular membrane, with <lb/>which he took ſo
        much pains to make his <lb/>readers acquainted, and in which the fat <lb/>reſides, adheres
        to the <hi rend="italic">internal</hi> ſurface of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">cutis
          vera,</hi> which therefore muſt <w part="I">ne-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceſſarily</w> be
        perforated before the ſaliva <lb/>can be brought into contact with the fat. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="44"><lb/>44. If Dr. James had been at all <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">quainted</w> with the abſorbent lymphatic <lb/>veſſels, whoſe extremities
        perforate the <lb/>cuticle in every part of the ſurface of the <lb/>body, he would not have
        deemed thoſe <lb/>parts only which he ſuppoſed deſtitute <lb/>of this external ſhield
        ſuſceptible of the <lb/>canine poiſon. Though the medical <lb/>world be much indebted to the
        minute <lb/>enquiries of Doctors Monro and Hunter <lb/>for a more perfect intelligence of
        the <lb/>lymphatic ſyſtem, yet the abſorption of <lb/>fluids through the pores of the ſkin
        hath <lb/>been generally known, even prior to the <lb/>days of Galen, who, as a proof of
        this <lb/>fact,<note place="marg" rend="size(0.7) italic"> Gal. de uſu puls. c. <hi
            rend="roman">5.</hi>
        </note> ſays—<hi rend="italic">Si ſitiens balneum ineat, illi ſitis <lb/>ſedabitur.</hi>
        Innumerable experiments have <lb/>been made by later writers in order to <lb/>eſtabliſh this
        doctrine, particularly by <pb xml:id="page_31" n="29"/><lb/>Boyle, Bellini, and many
          others.<note place="marg" rend="size(0.7) italic"> Phil. Tr. No. <hi rend="roman">II.</hi>
        </note> In the<lb/>Philoſophical Tranſactions we read of men <lb/>working in quickſilver
        mines, whoſe bodies <lb/>had imbibed ſo much of that metal, that <lb/>they changed the
        colour of braſs by <lb/>rubbing it with their hands, or even by <lb/>breathing upon it. We
        know that by <lb/>handling turpentine the urine acquires <lb/>a violet ſmell; that tobacco
        will vomit, <lb/>and aloes purge, when externally <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >plied</w>; but the fact moſt univerſally <lb/>known is the conſtant effect of <w part="I"
          >mercu-</w><lb/><w part="F">rial</w> unction. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="45"><lb/>45. Hence it is evident that the <hi rend="italic"
          >cuti-<lb/>cula,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">epidermis,</hi> as it was called by the
        <lb/>Greeks, is no defence againſt the canine, <lb/>or any other poiſon, if the application
        be <lb/>continued ſufficiently to give time for its <lb/>abſorption: it is therefore
        neceſſary, when <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">ſaliva</hi> of a mad dog touches any part <lb/>of
        the ſkin, to wipe it off immediately, <lb/>and waſh the ſpot. The examples, indeed, <lb/>of
        perſons thus infected without a wound <lb/>are not numerous, becauſe thoſe on whoſe
        <lb/>hand or face the <hi rend="italic">ſaliva</hi> reſts naturally wipe <lb/>it off before
        it can be abſorbed. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_32" n="30"/>
      <p rend="indent" n="46"><lb/>46. But, in defence of Dr. James it may <lb/>be urged, that,
        whether the cuticle be <lb/>pervious or not, or in whatſoever manner <lb/>the canine poiſon
        paſs the <hi rend="italic">cutis,</hi> it proves <lb/>nothing againſt that part of his <hi
          rend="italic">hypotheſis</hi>
        <lb/>which eſtabliſhes the fat as the immediate <lb/>receptacle of the poiſon, and its
        future <lb/>vehicle to the liver. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="47"><lb/>47. In reply to this defence, it will be <lb/>ſufficient to
        obſerve, that the bibulous <lb/>lymphatics, by which fluids on the ſurface <lb/>of the body
        are abſorbed, do not diſcharge <lb/>their contents into the cellular texture, <lb/>but,
        creeping along its membranes, <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">municate</w> with larger
        veins which <w part="I">ter-</w><lb/><w part="F">minate</w> in the <hi rend="italic"
          >receptaculum chyli,</hi> the <lb/>thoracic <hi rend="italic">duct,</hi> or jugular vein;
        ſo that the <lb/>canine poiſon, or any other fluid, abſorbed <lb/>from the ſurface of the
        body, cannot <lb/>remain in a ſtate of extravaſation with the <lb/>fat in the cellular web,
        but muſt <w part="I">neceſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſarily</w> be thrown into the general maſs
        of <lb/>circulating fluids<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* <q rend="quotes">I
            ſhall avail myſelf (ſays Dr. James) of but one <lb/>more argument to illuſtrate the
            probability of the <lb/>canine venom being received and foſtered in the <w part="I"
              >mem-</w><lb/><w part="F">brane</w> which contains the fat, or rather in the fat
            <lb/>itſelf. And this I draw from the method of cure; for <lb/>that very medicine which
            cures the venereal diſeaſe, <lb/>whoſe reſidence is in the fat, is alſo found effectual
            <lb/>in preventing and even curing canine madneſs.</q>— <lb/>Unfortunately for this
          argument the venereal diſeaſe <hi rend="italic">does <lb/>not</hi> reſide in the fat.
        </note>. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_33" n="31"/>
      <p rend="indent" n="48"><lb/>48. Dr. James's theory, therefore, being <lb/>contradicted by
        anatomical demonſtration, <lb/>neceſſarily falls to the ground. The <w part="I"
          >hypo-</w><lb/><w part="F">theſis</w> of Boerhaave, Mead, and others, <lb/>who ſuppoſed
        the ſeat of the diſeaſe to be <lb/>in the nervous fluid, is equally <w part="I"
          >inſup-</w><lb/><w part="F">portable</w>, becauſe no ſuch fluid circulates <lb/>in the
        nerves, which are not tubes but <lb/>ſolid fibres, whoſe extremities therefore <lb/>are
        incapable of abſorption. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="49"><lb/>49. If theſe theories be falſe, thoſe who <lb/>read for
        information will ask, where lies <lb/>the truth? If ſuch readers have ſufficiently
        <lb/>attended to the 47th paragraph they will <lb/>eaſily conceive that the poiſonous ſaliva
        <lb/>of the dog is abſorbed by the capillary <lb/>lymphatic veins, whoſe ramifications <w
          part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">pand</w> to every part of the ſurface of the <lb/>human
        body; thoſe veins which imbibe <lb/>the matter communicated by inoculation, <lb/>the
        venereal <hi rend="italic">virus,</hi> water, and infectious <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >miaſmata</hi> from the air. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_34" n="32"/>
      <p rend="indent" n="50"><lb/>50. But, if this be true, why is it <lb/>neceſſary, in order to
        communicate the <lb/>ſmall pox by inoculation, that the <lb/>cuticle ſhould be raiſed?—I
        anſwer: It is <lb/>not neceſſary; but that by this operation <lb/>the communication of the
        diſeaſe is <lb/>rendered more certain, becauſe the matter <lb/>being lodged under the
        cuticle, by <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">taining</w> its moiſture, continues longer
        in a <lb/>fit ſtate for abſorption. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="51"><lb/>51. If it ſhould be further asked, why <lb/>the canine poiſon,
        thus introduced, <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tinues</w> circulating in the body
        five or ſix <lb/>weeks before it produces that diſeaſe, of a <lb/>ſingle paroxiſm, called
        the <hi rend="italic">hydrophobia?</hi>
        <lb/>—I anſwer, that in this it differs from <lb/>other inoculated diſeaſes only in point of
        <lb/>time, In all inoculations there is an <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tervention</w> of ſome days between the cauſe <lb/>and effect; but why that of canine
        madneſs <lb/>requires a longer time for aſſimilation <lb/>and maturity muſt remain a
        myſtery, <lb/>until we are better acquainted with <w part="I">na-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ture's</w>
        <hi rend="italic">modus operandi.</hi> Probably there are <lb/>other contagious diſeaſes
        whoſe malignant <lb/><hi rend="italic">miaſmata</hi> may be equally ſlow in their
        <lb/>progreſs from admiſſion to efficiency. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_35" n="33"/>
      <p rend="indent" n="52"><lb/>52. Some attempts have been made to <lb/>diſcover the nature of
        this canine poiſon <lb/>by the help of microſcopes and chemical <lb/>experiments; but to no
        purpoſe. Dr. <lb/>Mead ſuppoſed it to conſiſt of fiery ſaline <lb/>particles.<note
          place="marg" rend="italic size(0.7)"> Diſſert. Med. de rab. can. Edinb. <hi rend="roman"
            >1771.</hi>
        </note> Dr. <lb/>Heyſham believes it to be <lb/>an acid; but this is mere conjecture. All
        <lb/>we know of the matter is, that it is a <lb/>poiſon <hi rend="italic">ſui generis,</hi>
        which, being abſorbed <lb/>by the lymphatic veins, produces certain <lb/>effects in the
        human body; no <w part="I">mecha-</w><lb/><w part="F">nical</w> nor chemical theory,
        therefore, can <lb/>aſſiſt us in the invention of a remedy <lb/>againſt the bite of a mad
        dog. Analogy <lb/>may poſſibly be of ſome uſe. Chance, <lb/>the great inventor of medicines,
        hath not, <lb/>I think, been ſucceſſful in the preſent <lb/>caſe. Let us, however, proceed
        to the <lb/>moſt important, the therapeutic diviſion <lb/>of our eſſay. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="53"><lb/>53. Mithridates, king of Pontus, about <lb/>two thouſand years
        ago, is ſaid to have <lb/>invented that farrago of more than forty <lb/>ingredients called
        by his name. Hiſtorians <lb/>tell us that, believing it to be an univerſal <lb/>antidote, he
        took a doſe of it every <lb/>morning. In juſtice however to his <pb xml:id="page_36" n="34"
        /><lb/>Pontic majeſty, I muſt not ſuppreſs what <lb/><hi rend="italic">Samonicus</hi> writes
        on this ſubject. <q rend="quotes">When <lb/>Pompy (ſays he) took the baggage of
          <lb/>Mithridates, he found, among his <lb/>papers, the preſcript for compounding <lb/>the
          famous antidote againſt all poiſons, <lb/>invented by that king: he was much
          <lb/>ſurpriſed to find that it conſiſted only <lb/>of twenty leaves of rue, two walnuts,
          <lb/>two figs, and a little ſalt.</q> To whoſe <lb/>inventive genius we are indebted for
        the <lb/>forty ingredients which were afterwards <lb/>added I know not, unleſs to that of
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Damocrates,</hi> under whoſe name this <w part="I">cele-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">brated</w> antidote ſhines conſpicuous even <lb/>in the laſt edition of the
        London <hi rend="italic">Phar-<lb/>macopoeia.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="54"><lb/>54. <hi rend="italic">Andromachus,</hi> a native of Crete,
        <lb/>cotemporary with Galen, not ſatisfied with <lb/>an antidote of forty-five ingredients,
          <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſed</w> one of more than ſixty, which he
        <lb/>called <foreign xml:lang="el">###Greek omitted###</foreign>
        <hi rend="italic">(ſerenitas)</hi> from its ſedative <lb/>or anodyne effect. This
        impertinent <lb/>jumble of ſtuff was afterwards called <lb/>Theriaca, from the Greek word
          <foreign xml:lang="el">###Greek omitted###</foreign>, <hi rend="italic">fera,</hi>
        <lb/>a wild beaſt, being an antidote againſt the <lb/>invenomed bite of mad or poiſonous <pb
          xml:id="page_37" n="35"/><lb/>animals. This notable hodge-podge is <lb/>alſo to be found
        even in the laſt edition <lb/>of the London Diſpenſatory; and, what <lb/>is more
        extraordinary, there are, I am <lb/>told, ſome phyſicians who continue to uſe <lb/>theſe <hi
          rend="italic">theriacas</hi> in their preſcriptions: <lb/>with what intention is beſt
        known to <lb/>themſelves. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="55"><lb/>55. If the inventors of <hi rend="italic">theriacas</hi> had
        <lb/>any ideas at all, they probably thought <lb/>that, in ſo great a number of ingredients,
        <lb/>it was poſſible ſome one of them might <lb/>hit the mark they aimed at, for the ſame
        <lb/>reaſon that ſportſmen prefer a number of <lb/>ſmall ſhot to a ſingle bullet; but I am
        <lb/>rather inclined to think them the <w part="I">inven-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of
        ſome arch apothecary's apprentice, <lb/>who had a mind to try what ſort of a <lb/>medicine
        he could produce by jumbling <lb/>together every drug in the ſhop. Be their <lb/>origin
        however what it might, they are <lb/>certainly the oldeſt antidotes upon record, <lb/>and,
        from the proportion of opium they <lb/>contain, might poſſibly alleviate the <lb/>ſpaſmodic
        ſymptoms incidental to the bite <lb/>of a viper, or of a mad dog. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_38" n="36"/>
      <p rend="indent" n="56"><lb/>56. <hi rend="italic">Dioſcorides</hi> wrote a treatiſe on the
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Theriaca,</hi> in the ſecond chapter of which <lb/>he recommends,
        as a medicine that might <lb/>be depended on for the bite of a mad dog, <lb/>two ſpoonfuls
        of the aſhes of the river crab, <lb/>with half the quantity of gentian, to be <lb/>taken in
        a large glaſs of wine.<note place="marg" rend="size(0.7) italic"> De ſimpl. med. facul.
        </note> Galen <lb/>preſcribes the ſame medicine, with the <lb/>addition of a ſmall quantity
        of <w part="I">frankin-</w><lb/><w part="F">cenſe</w>: the crabs he burnt alive in a copper
        <lb/>diſh, after the riſing of the ſtar <hi rend="italic">Sirius,</hi>
        <lb/>when the ſun was in the conſtellation <lb/><hi rend="italic">Leo,</hi> and on the
        eighteenth day of the <lb/>moon. This invaluable ſecret he learnt <lb/>from old <hi
          rend="italic">Æſerion</hi> the emperic, who, being <lb/>Galen's maſter, muſt have lived <w
          part="I">cotem-</w><lb/><w part="F">porary</w> with <hi rend="italic">Dioſcorides,</hi>
        and might <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">bably</w> be the inventor of this <hi
          rend="italic">infallible <lb/>medicine,</hi> for ſo it was eſteemed by theſe
        <lb/>phyſicians. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="57"><lb/>57. Dr. Mead is of opinion that this <lb/>remedy is recommended
        by the ancients <lb/>upon rational grounds, becauſe it is a <lb/>diuretic; <q
          rend="diple quotes">For (ſays he) the ſureſt <w part="I">reme-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >dies</w> in all ages againſt this venom have <lb/>been ſuch as provoke a great
          diſcharge <lb/>by urine.</q> Reflecting on this <w part="I">circum-</w><pb
          xml:id="page_39" n="37"/><lb/><w part="F">ſtance</w>, this <hi rend="italic"
          >Eſculapius</hi> of his times, <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceived</w> the great
        idea of recommending to <lb/>the world his infallible <hi rend="italic">Pulvis
          Antyliſſus,</hi>
        <lb/>which, at the doctor's requeſt, was <w part="I">ho-</w><lb/><w part="F">noured</w> with
        a place in the London <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pharmacopoeia.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="58"><lb/>58. Whence did Dr. Mead conclude <lb/>that this powder of
        calcined river crabs, <lb/>or crawfiſh (for ſuch he ſuppoſes them to <lb/>have been) would
          <hi rend="italic">promote a great diſcharge <lb/>of urine?</hi> He certainly thought that
        this <lb/>calcination, like the incineration of <w part="I">vege-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tables</w>, would produce an alkaline ſalt. <lb/>If he had poſſeſſed the leaſt degree of
        <lb/>chemical knowledge, he would have <lb/>known that the animal itſelf would burn <lb/>to
        a mere earth, totally inert, and that its <lb/>ſhell would be converted into quick lime,
        <lb/>of which conſequently, with a very ſmall <lb/>proportion of earth, this ſpecific muſt
        <lb/>conſiſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="59"><lb/>59. Dr. James's chemical knowledge <lb/>appears to have been not
        much inferior to <lb/>that of Dr. Mead, whom he thinks <w part="I">to-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tally</w> wrong in tranſlating the <foreign xml:lang="el">###Greek
          </foreign><lb/><foreign xml:lang="el">omitted###</foreign> of <hi rend="italic"
          >Dioſcorides,</hi> and Galen, <hi rend="italic">River <lb/>Crawfiſh.</hi> He is clearly of
        opinion, and <pb xml:id="page_40" n="38"/><lb/>takes ſome pains to prove, that theſe
        <lb/>authors meant a ſpecies of river crab, and <lb/>not crawfiſh. Dr. James prudently <w
          part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerves</w>, that we ought to be very accurate <lb/>in our
        quotations from ancient authors, <lb/><q rend="quotes">leſt the medicine recommended be
          <lb/>miſtaken for ſomething that may not <lb/>poſſeſs the ſame virtues.</q> This is
        <lb/>doubtleſs a wiſe obſervation; but any <lb/>chemiſt's boy would have told him, that
        <lb/>the virtues, whatever they may be, of a <lb/>calcined crawfiſh, crab, or oiſter, are
        <lb/>exactly the ſame; that all ſhells are <w part="I">calca-</w><lb/><w part="F">rious</w>
        earth, and conſequently burn to <lb/>quick lime, in no reſpect different from <lb/>that
        produced by the calcination of chalk, <lb/>lime-ſtone, or marble. But, that Dr. <lb/>James,
        as well as Dr. Mead, ſuppoſed that <lb/>this calcination of river crabs produced an
        <lb/>alkaline ſalt is evident from the following <lb/>paſſage. Speaking of this powder, he
        ſays — <q rend="quotes">I believe it may have ſome efficacy in <lb/>preventing the canine
            madneſs,<note place="marg" rend="size(0.7)"> P. 215. </note> though <lb/>none that can
          be depended upon. This <lb/>opinion is founded on its being an <lb/>highly alkaline
          ſubſtance; and all or <lb/>moſt of the pretended ſpecifics for this <lb/>diſtemper are
          alkaline, and deſtroyers of <pb xml:id="page_41" n="39"/><lb/>acids; as the celebrated
          pancake made <lb/>of oiſter-ſhells, mentioned by Deſſault, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Armenian
            Bole, Tin,</hi> and many other.</q><lb/>Theſe laſt words put the doctor's skill in
        <lb/>chemiſtry quite out of doubt. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="60"><lb/>60. But, as we can hardly ſuppoſe that <lb/>Dioſcorides and Galen
        ventured to give <lb/>their patients two ſpoonfuls of quick lime, <lb/>it is probable that
        they did not calcine <lb/>theſe crabs, or crawfiſh, ſufficiently to <lb/>convert the ſhells
        into lime, though long <lb/>enough to diſſipate the volatile parts of <lb/>the animal. On
        this ſuppoſition this <lb/>ſpecific powder becomes a mere abſorbent <lb/>earth, a <hi
          rend="italic">pulvis è chelis cancrorum,</hi> poſſeſſed <lb/>of no diuretic virtue; yet
        Galen <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">nounces</w> it infallible.<note place="marg"
          rend="size(0.7) italic"> De ſimpl. med facul. L. <hi rend="italic">3.</hi> c. <hi
            rend="italic">34.</hi>
        </note>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="61"><lb/>61. The next diuretic antidote of the <lb/>ancients, <q
          rend="quotes">recommended (as Dr. Mead <lb/>thinks) upon rational grounds,</q> is the
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Spongia Cynorrhodi,</hi> ſponge of the <w part="I">dog-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">roſe</w>, <q rend="quotes">Which (ſays the Doctor) is ſo <lb/>celebrated an
          antidote, that <hi rend="italic">P. Boccone,</hi>
          <lb/>who has written a whole diſcourſe upon <lb/>its virtues, tells us it is called in
          Sicily <lb/><hi rend="italic">Sanatodos,</hi> or All-heal.</q> We alſo in <lb/>this
        country have a common plant <w part="I">dig-</w><pb xml:id="page_42" n="40"/><lb/><w
          part="F">nified</w> with the ſame name, and equally <lb/>inſignificant in its medical
        capacity. Theſe <lb/><hi rend="italic">panaceas</hi> are generally good for nothing.
        <lb/>But Dr. Mead ranks this gall of the briar <lb/>among his animal diuretics, becauſe Mr.
        <lb/>Ray found it to be the nidus of a fly.— <lb/><q rend="quotes">Now (ſays the Doctor) all
          inſects <lb/>abound with a diuretic ſalt.</q>—If the <lb/>lie direct were admiſſible in
        polite <w part="I">conver-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſation</w>, I would ſay, <hi rend="italic"
          >this is not true.</hi> But <lb/>I marvel exceedingly that he did not <w part="I"
          >ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerve</w> that this <hi rend="italic">Sanatodos</hi> of the
        Sicilians is <lb/>called in England a <hi rend="italic">Dog</hi>-roſe, becauſe it
        <lb/>produces a medicine for a mad-<hi rend="italic">dog:</hi> alſo, <lb/>that he forgot to
        inform his readers, that <lb/>this celebrated antidote originated in the <lb/>dream of an
        old woman, as he muſt have <lb/>read in Pliny. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="62"><lb/>62. Dr. Mead, after ſpecifying, from <lb/>the ancients, other
        diuretics, which <w part="I">cer-</w><lb/><w part="F">tainly</w> are <hi rend="italic"
          >not</hi> diuretics, proceeds to the <lb/>recommendation of his infallible <hi
          rend="italic">Pulvis <lb/>Antilyſſus,</hi> which he declared never failed <lb/>of ſucceſs,
        though he had uſed it a <w part="I">thou-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſand</w> times. <q
          rend="quotes">I have often wiſhed (adds <lb/>the Doctor) that I knew ſo certain a
          <lb/>remedy in any other diſeaſe.</q>—Surely <pb xml:id="page_43" n="41"/><lb/>ſuch
        teſtimony, from ſo great a phyſician, <lb/>muſt be more than ſufficient to eſtabliſh
        <lb/>the infallibility of any medicine beyond <lb/>all ſuſpicion: and yet two greater men,
        <lb/>Boerhaave and Van Swieten,<note place="marg" rend="size(0.7)"> Aph. 1147. </note> are
        of opinion <lb/>that it is good for nothing; and Dr. James <lb/>aſſures us, that <q
          rend="quotes">it has been given,<note place="marg" rend="size(0.7)"> Pa. 227. </note>
          <lb/>without ſucceſs, to a great number of <lb/>people and animals in many parts of
          <lb/>the kingdom.</q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="63"><lb/>63. This infallible <hi rend="italic">Pulvis Antilyſſus</hi> is
        <lb/>preſcribed by Dr. Mead in the following <lb/>words— <q rend="quotes">Take of the herb
          called, in <lb/>Latin, <hi rend="italic">Lichen cinereus terreſtris,</hi> in <lb/>Engliſh,
          Aſh-coloured <w part="I">ground-liver-</w><lb/><w part="F">wort</w>, cleaned, dried, and
          powdered, <lb/>half an ounce; of black pepper <w part="I">pow-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >dered</w>, two drachms. Mix theſe <w part="I">toge-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w>, and
          divide the powder into four <lb/>doſes, one of which muſt be taken <lb/>every morning
          faſting for four <w part="I">morn-</w><lb/><w part="F">ings</w> ſucceſſively in a pint of
          cows <lb/>milk.</q>—I have now before me a <lb/>London Diſpenſatory with manuſcript
        <lb/>notes by my worthy friend Dr. Longfield, <lb/>a phyſician deſervedly diſtinguiſhed for
        <lb/>his ſound judgement, and extenſive <w part="I">me-</w><pb xml:id="page_44" n="42"
          /><lb/><w part="F">dical</w> knowledge. On the blank leaf <w part="I">op-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">poſite</w> to the <hi rend="italic">Pulvis Antilyſſus,</hi> he wrote— <lb/><q
          rend="quotes">This is Dr. Mead's famous powder: it <lb/>is moſt certain that it never
          cured one <lb/>perſon bit by a mad dog.</q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="64"><lb/>64. A moderate ſhare of experience in <lb/>the medical powers of
        plants is ſufficient <lb/>to determine <hi rend="italic">à priori</hi> the virtue of this
        <lb/>Lichen, which, together with the reſt of <lb/>its tribe, diſcovers no other ſenſible <w
          part="I">qua-</w><lb/><w part="F">lity</w> than a ſlight degree of aſtringency, <lb/>and
        therefore can have no other effect than <lb/>what may be expected from any other
        <lb/>medicine, aſtringent in the ſame degree; <lb/>unleſs we admit the doctrine of
        ſpecifics, <lb/>to which Dr. Mead would doubtleſs have <lb/>objected, being himſelf a <hi
          rend="italic">ſectator</hi> of the <lb/>mechanical Belini.<note place="marg"
          rend="size(0.7)"> Pb. botan. Frag. meth. mat. Mat. Mid. p. <hi rend="italic">161.</hi>
        </note> — <hi rend="italic">Inſipidæ et inodoræ <lb/>vim medicam vix exercent,</hi> is an
        aphoriſm <lb/>of Linnæus. <q rend="quotes">This rule (ſays Dr. Cullen) <lb/>ſeems to be
          without exception; and it <lb/>is on this account, and not on any <lb/>proper experience,
          that many plants <lb/>are expunged from the <hi rend="italic">Materia Medica,</hi>
          <lb/>as having no taſte or odour which ſhould <lb/>point out in them any active <w
            part="I">quali-</w><lb/><w part="F">ties</w>.</q>—After ſuch evidence, we may, <pb
          xml:id="page_45" n="43"/><lb/>I think, juſtly proceed to the <w part="I"
          >condemna-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of the infallible <hi rend="italic">Pulvis
          Antilyſſus.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="65"><lb/>65. But Dr. Mead, in order to <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">vince</w> the world that he had not adopted <lb/>this medicine without proper
        ſcientific <lb/>inveſtigation, informs his readers, that he <lb/>examined the <hi
          rend="italic">Lichen cinereus terreſtris</hi> by <lb/>diſtillation, and that the reſult of
        his <w part="I">ana-</w><lb/><w part="F">lyſis</w> was, ſome acid water, ſome oil, and
        <lb/>ſome coal that contained fixt ſalt. A <lb/>bunch of docks, of nettles, of thiſtles,
        <lb/>or of any other common weed, would have <lb/>yielded the ſame. This ſort of analyſis
        <lb/>can be of no uſe in diſcovering the <w part="I">medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cal</w>
        virtues of plants. The receipt to make <lb/>this celebrated <hi rend="italic">Pulvis
          Antilyſſus</hi> was firſt <lb/>brought to England by Captain Dampier, <lb/>who called the
        plant Jew's Ear (<hi rend="italic">Tremella <lb/>auricula</hi> of <hi rend="italic"
          >Linnæus</hi>) a kind of aſh-coloured <lb/>fungus, which is frequently found on the
        <lb/>trunks of old trees. But it ſeems Sir <lb/>Hans Sloane was of opinion that the <w
          part="I">Cap-</w><lb/><w part="F">tain</w> was miſtaken; that he certainly meant <lb/>the
        aſh-coloured Liverwort, which, on the <lb/>authority of ſo great a naturaliſt, was <w
          part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">cordingly</w> adopted. Is it not probable <lb/>from this
        hiſtory, that, in rejecting the <pb xml:id="page_46" n="44"/><lb/>original Jew's Ear, Dr.
        Mead ſeized the <lb/>ear of the wrong ſow? </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="66"><lb/>66. The next infallible medicine I ſhall <lb/>examine is that
        which, about thirty years <lb/>ago, was brought from Tonquin by Sir <lb/>George Cobb, when
        he returned from the <lb/>Eaſt Indies. It conſiſts of native and <lb/>factitious Cinnabar
        each twenty-four <lb/>grains, with ſixteen grains of Muſk, <lb/>powdered and mixt well
        together. This <lb/>doſe is to be taken in a glaſs of Arrack <lb/>once only, and repeated
        after an interval <lb/>of thirty days The abſurdity of making <lb/>any diſtinction between
          <hi rend="italic">native</hi> and <hi rend="italic">factiti-<lb/>ous</hi> Cinnabar, which
        are preciſely the ſame <lb/>thing, is too obvious to need a <w part="I">commen-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">tary</w>: it proves, however, the ignorance of <lb/>the Chineſe old woman who
        probably <lb/>invented the medicine, and of all thoſe <lb/>who in preſcribing this powder
        have <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tinued</w> to obſerve the ſame ridiculous <w
          part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">tinction</w>. But, in the compoſition of this
        <lb/>ſpecific, there is another abſurdity of more <lb/>importance. All the cinnabars,
        whether <lb/><hi rend="italic">native, factitious,</hi> or of cinnabar of <hi rend="italic"
          >anti-<lb/>mony,</hi> are mere powder of poſt; <w part="I">abſo-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >lutely</w> inert. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_47" n="45"/>
      <p rend="indent" n="67"><lb/>67. <q rend="quotes">Factitious cinnabar (ſays Dr. <lb/>James) is
          made of three parts of <w part="I">mer-</w><lb/><w part="F">cury</w> to one of ſulphur;
            and,<note place="marg" rend="size(0.7)"> Pa. 155. </note> as I <w part="I"
            >re-</w><lb/><w part="F">member</w>, a pound of good native <w part="I">cin-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">nabar</w> yields near fourteen ounces of <lb/>fluid mercury; and therefore it
          ſeems <lb/>that the good effects of this medicine <lb/>ought to be principally, if not
          entirely, <lb/>aſcribed to mercury.</q>—Dr. James, <w part="I">hav-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ing</w> reſolved to ſport a preparation of <w part="I">mer-</w><lb/><w part="F">cury</w>
        as the only ſpecific for canine <w part="I">mad-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w>, was quite
        ſatisfied with this ſort of <lb/>reaſoning: but <hi rend="italic">we</hi> muſt come nearer
        to <lb/>the point. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="68"><lb/>68. Native cinnabar is the ore of <w part="I">mer-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">cury</w>; that is, mercury mineralized by <lb/>ſulphur, in the proportion of
        about ſix, <lb/>ſeven, or eight parts of the former to one <lb/>of the latter.—Sulphur
        poſſeſſes the <w part="I">ſingu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lar</w> property, in combination with
          <w part="I">mer-</w><lb/><w part="F">cury</w> or antimony, of rendering both theſe
        <lb/>violent metallic ſubſtances inactive. It is <lb/>particularly well known of antimony
        that <lb/>it is more or leſs mild in proportion as <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">regulus</hi>
        is combined with more or leſs <lb/>ſulphur. This chemical fact Dr. James <lb/>muſt have
        known, if he had underſtood <pb xml:id="page_48" n="46"/><lb/>the proceſs for making his own
        fever-<lb/>powder. But mercury, before it can <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">ert</w>
        its ſtimulant power, muſt not only <lb/>be completely extricated from the ſulphur <lb/>with
        which it formed cinnabar, but muſt <lb/>afterwards be divided by trituration, or
        <lb/>diſſolved in a mineral acid. Now, the <lb/>only means of decompoſing cinnabar is by
        <lb/>fire, in, what is called by chemiſts, the <lb/>dry way. In the human body, therefore,
        <lb/>it is impoſſible; but if we could ſuppoſe <lb/>the mercury actually ſeparated from the
        <lb/>ſulphur, not being diſſolved by a mineral <lb/>acid, or otherwiſe divided, it would
        ſtill <lb/>remain in a ſtate of total inactivity: <hi rend="italic">a <lb/>priori,</hi>
        therefore, cinnabar may be <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">nounced</w> inert. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="69"><lb/>69. But, leſt the advocates for this <lb/>Tonquin medicine ſhould
        deem this ſort <lb/>of philoſophical argument inconcluſive, <lb/>let us take the opinions of
        a few eminent <lb/>chemiſts on the ſubject.<note place="marg" rend="size(0.7)"> Pa. 451.
        </note>—Dr. Cullen, in <lb/>his Lectures on <hi rend="italic">Materia Medica,</hi> ſpeaking
        <lb/>of mercurial preparations, ſays— <q rend="quotes">Crude <lb/>mercury, and the
          combination in <w part="I">cin-</w><lb/><w part="F">nabar</w> and <hi rend="italic"
            >Æthiops mineralis,</hi> to which <lb/>may be added <hi rend="italic">Æthiops
            antimonialis,</hi> in <pb xml:id="page_49" n="47"/><lb/>ſo far as it contains mercury,
          can only <lb/>by accident, or indirectly, prove <w part="I">medi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cines</w>.</q>—<q rend="quotes">Triturated with ſulphur,<note place="marg"
            rend="size(0.7)"> Pa. 444. </note>
          <lb/>mercury becomes an inert ſubſtance. <lb/>This I could determine <hi rend="italic">à
            priori,</hi>
          <w part="I">whe-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> it was in the form of Æthiops <lb/>mineral,
          or native or factitious <w part="I">cinna-</w><lb/><w part="F">bar</w>.</q>—Dr. Lewis in
        his Diſpenſatory <lb/>tells us, that <q rend="quotes">cinnabar, like Æthiops,<note
            place="marg" rend="size(0.7)"> Pa. 331. </note>
          <lb/>is inactive.</q>—Cartheuſer, having given a <lb/>large quantity to a dog, ſays, that
        it <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duced</w> no ſenſible effect, but that part of
        <lb/>it paſſed through the inteſtines unaltered, <lb/>and that the remainder was found in
        the <lb/>ſtomach and bowels.—Dr. Longfield, <lb/>whom I have before mentioned, wrote the
        <lb/>following note on the article <hi rend="italic">cinnabaris <lb/>factitia</hi> in the
          <hi rend="italic">Pharm. Col. Reg. Med. <lb/>Londinenſis</hi>—<q rend="quotes">It is a
          ſhame that the <w part="I">cin-</w><lb/><w part="F">nabars</w> are not totally exploded:
          they <lb/>have not the leaſt title to the character <lb/>of nervous medicines; they are
          both <lb/>inert.</q>—But it were unfair to conceal <lb/>from the reader, that a famous
        German <lb/>chemiſt of the laſt century was of a <w part="I">dif-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ferent</w> opinion. He conſidered cinnabar <lb/>as an efficacious medicine, and aſcribed
        its <lb/>virtue to its beautiful colour, with which <pb xml:id="page_50" n="48"/><lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Archeus</hi> is ſo charmed as to neglect the <lb/>diſeaſe which he was
        employed in exiting; <lb/>for it ſeems this <hi rend="italic">Archeus,</hi> this creature of
        <lb/>Van Helmont's diſtempered brain, is <w part="I">won-</w><lb/><w part="F">derfully</w>
        delighted with the colour red. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="70"><lb/>70. In anſwer to all this reaſoning <hi rend="italic">à
          <lb/>priori,</hi> I ſhall be told, that experience is <lb/>the only teſt, and that the
        inſtances upon <lb/>record, of the hydrophobia being cured <lb/>or prevented by the Tonquin
        powder are <lb/>innumerable. In reply to this anſwer— <lb/><hi rend="italic">Firſt,</hi>
        there are examples upon record of <lb/>perſons having died of the hydrophobia <lb/>after
        taking it, particularly in two caſes <lb/>related in the London <hi rend="italic">Medical <w
            part="I">Obſer-</w><lb/><w part="F">vation</w>:</hi><note place="marg"
          rend="size(0.7) italic"> Page <hi rend="italic">195,</hi> and apendix, p. <hi rend="roman"
            >3.</hi>
        </note>
        <hi rend="italic">Secondly,</hi> many other medicines, <lb/>equally infallible and equally
        extolled, <lb/>have deſervedly ſunk into contempt: <lb/><hi rend="italic">Thirdly,</hi> no
        atteſtation of facts will <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">vince</w> a rational being
        that an effect was <lb/>produced without a ſufficient cauſe: now, <lb/>a ſubſtance which is
        demonſtrably inert <lb/>can produce no effect in an animal body, <lb/>and therefore can cure
        no diſeaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="71"><lb/>71. Cinnabar being thus, I think, <lb/>fairly diſpatched, if
        there be any <w part="I">anti-</w><pb xml:id="page_51" n="49"/><lb/><w part="F">dotal</w>
        power in the Tonquin medicine, it <lb/>muſt be attributed to to the antiſpaſmodic
        <lb/>virtue of the musk: Dr. James aſcribes it <lb/>to its alkaline quality— <q
          rend="quotes">Musk (he tells <lb/>us) is an animal ſubſtance, and <w part="I"
            >conſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">quently</w> of an alkaline nature; and as <lb/>alkalies have
          in all ages been <w part="I">recom-</w><lb/><w part="F">mended</w> in this caſe, it ſeems
          at leaſt to <lb/>be not prejudicial.</q>—This is <hi rend="italic">damning <lb/>musk with
          faint praiſe.</hi> But what did <lb/>the Doctor mean by aſcribing to it an <lb/>alkaline
        quality becauſe it is an animal <lb/>ſubſtance? Had he forgot that animal <lb/>matter wants
        the aſſiſtance of fire to <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duce</w> alkali? If every
        ſpecies of animal <lb/>matter be an alkaline medicine, the parings <lb/>of his own nails
        would have done as well. <lb/>Musk, however, is doubtleſs a powerful <lb/>antiſpaſmodic, and
        for that reaſon may be <lb/>of ſervice in the <hi rend="italic">hydrophobia.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="72"><lb/>72. This Tonquin powder is ordered <lb/>to be taken in a glaſs of
        Arrack, doubtleſs <lb/>with no other intention than to cover the <lb/>taſte of the musk.
        This vehicle, <w part="I">how-</w><lb/><w part="F">ever</w>, ſuggeſts an idea, which, though
        I <lb/>may think it extravagant, I will <w part="I">commu-</w><lb/><w part="F">nicate</w>.
        Suppoſe, when the ſymptoms of <pb xml:id="page_52" n="50"/><lb/>the fatal diſeaſe in
        queſtion firſt appear, <lb/>previous to the difficulty of ſwallowing <lb/>liquids, the
        patient were to drink to <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">toxication</w> of any ſtrong
        liquor he may <lb/>chuſe. Who, without trying it, will <lb/>pretend to circumſcribe the
        antiſpaſmodic <lb/>effect of this remedy? It is certainly not <lb/>contra-indicated by any
        febrile or <w part="I">mani-</w><lb/><w part="F">acal</w> ſymptoms. In a forlorn hope no <w
          part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tempt</w> can be too extravagant. It will at <lb/>leaſt
        anſwer one good purpoſe: I mean <lb/>that of relieving the patient from ſeveral <lb/>hours
        of the moſt horrid anxiety that can <lb/>poſſibly be conceived. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="73"><lb/>73. I now beg leave to call the reader's <lb/>attention to the
        mercurial preparation ſo <lb/>ſtrenuouſly recommended by Dr. James <lb/>in his <hi
          rend="italic">Treatiſe on Canine Madneſs.</hi> It is <lb/>called <hi rend="italic">Turpith
          mineral;</hi> it is a precipitate <lb/>of mercury from its ſolution in the <w part="I"
          >Vitri-</w><lb/><w part="F">olic</w> acid, by which it was not only <w part="I"
          >diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſolved</w> but calcined. Whether it be a pure <lb/>calx of
        mercury, without any adheſion of <lb/>vitriolic ſalt, is a matter of diſpute among
        <lb/>chemiſts of the firſt reputation. Monſieur <lb/>Baumè declares poſitively,<note
          place="marg" rend="size(0.7)">Vol. ii. p. 403. </note>
        <hi rend="italic">que, ce precipitè <lb/>eſt abſolument privé de toute acide, lorſqu'il <pb
            xml:id="page_53" n="51"/><lb/>a été lavé à pluſieurs repriſes dans de l'eau
          <lb/>bouillante</hi>—Nevertheleſs, from the effect <lb/>of the medicine, I preſume he is
        miſtaken. <lb/>It is a very rough mercurial, fit only for <lb/>dogs, to which animals Dr.
        James ſeems <lb/>to have given it with ſucceſs. As to its <lb/>effect on the human ſpecies,
        he produces <lb/>no more than one ſingle caſe of a patient <lb/>bit by a mad dog, and cured
        under his <lb/>own immediate care by Turpith mineral, <lb/>He relates, indeed, three or four
        other <lb/>caſes in ſupport of his ſpecific, on the <lb/>authority of perſons of his
        acquaintance; <lb/>but <hi rend="italic">hear-ſay</hi> evidence in this caſe, as in
        <lb/>courts of juſtice, is inadmiſſable.—Dr. <lb/>Raymond,<note place="marg"
          rend="size(0.7) italic"> Med. Obs. append. p. <hi rend="roman">3.</hi>
        </note> phyſician at Marſeilles gave <lb/>ſeven boluſes, containing each four grains <lb/>of
        Turpith mineral, to a patient bit by a <lb/>mad dog: the patient died. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="74"><lb/>74. The Ormskirk medicine, which in <lb/>many parts of this
        kingdom, particularly <lb/>in the North, is deemed infallible, <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">pears</w>, from the report of Dr. Black and <lb/>Dr. Heyſham,<note place="marg"
          rend="size(0.7) italic"> Med. Com. Vol. <hi rend="italic">v.</hi> p. <hi rend="italic"
            >50.</hi></note> to conſiſt of,<note place="marg" rend="size(0.7) italic"> </note>
        <hi rend="italic">Powder of <lb/>chalk,</hi> half an ounce; <hi rend="italic">Armenian
          bole,</hi> three <lb/>drachms; <hi rend="italic">Allum,</hi> ten grains; <hi rend="italic"
          >Powder of <lb/>elecampane root,</hi> one drachm; <hi rend="italic">Oil of aniſe,</hi>
        <pb xml:id="page_54" n="52"/><lb/>ſix drops.—Now, though the chemical <lb/>enquiries of
        theſe gentlemen may not be <lb/>admitted as proof poſitive, yet when the <lb/>reſult of
        experiments made by two able <lb/>chemiſts, at different times, is preciſely <lb/>the ſame;
        when a medicine compoſed of <lb/>the ſuppoſed ingredients has the ſame <lb/>colour, taſte,
        and ſmell, we have the <lb/>ſtrongeſt preſumptive evidence that our <lb/>conjectures are
        well founded; eſpecially, <lb/>when there is no diſcoverable difference <lb/>between the
        effect of the real and <w part="I">ſup-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſed</w> compoſition. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="75"><lb/>75. As to the medical virtues of the <lb/>ingredients
        above-mentioned, they are <w part="I">ſuf-</w><lb/><w part="F">ficiently</w> known.—Chalk is
        a mere <w part="I">abſor-</w><lb/><w part="F">bent</w> earth, without any other power than
        <lb/>that of deſtroying the acid it may meet <lb/>with in the <hi rend="italic">primæ
          viæ,</hi> and, during the <lb/>efferveſcence, of producing a little <w part="I"
          >calca-</w><lb/><w part="F">rious</w> gas, commonly called fixt air.— <lb/>Armenian bole,
        ſuch as is generally ſold <lb/>by the druggiſts, is nothing more than a <lb/>lump of
        pipe-clay, coloured with a little <lb/>red ochre or ruſt of iron.<note place="bottom" n="*"
          rend="size(0.5)">* This Engliſh or Dutch Armenian bole is, in no <lb/>reſpect, inferior to
          the true Oriental, or to any other bole, <lb/>for medical purpoſes. </note>—Allum is an
          <pb xml:id="page_55" n="53"/><lb/>aſtringent, and nothing more.—Elecam-<lb/>pane-root hath
        been generally ranked <lb/>among the Alexipharmics; it is ſaid to <lb/>aſſiſt expectoration,
        and, in large doſes, to <lb/>act as a diuretic and cathartic: it is, <w part="I"
          >how-</w><lb/><w part="F">ever</w>, in no eſtimation, and in ſo ſmall a <lb/>doſe, mixt
        with the other ingredients, can <lb/>produce no effect.—As to the ſix drops of <lb/>oil of
        aniſeed, I preſume their efficacy, in <lb/>the preſent caſe, will hardly be inſiſted
        <lb/>on. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="76"><lb/>76. Poſſibly I may be told, that, though <lb/>theſe ſeveral
        ingredients, ſeparately taken, <lb/>may poſſeſs no extraordinary medical <lb/>powers, yet,
        like other compounds they <lb/>may, when united, form a medicine of <lb/>conſiderable
        virtue.—I acknowledge that <lb/>a powerful medicine may be formed by a <lb/>judicious
        combination of ſimple <w part="I">ingre-</w><lb/><w part="F">dients</w>, preſcribed on
        chemical principles; <lb/>but I am very certain, that an ignorant <lb/>jumble of chalk,
        clay, allum, and <w part="I">elecam-</w><lb/><w part="F">pane</w>, will form nothing but an
          <w part="I">hetero-</w><lb/><w part="F">generous</w> maſs of dirt, that may do harm,
        <lb/>but cannot poſſibly do good in any diſeaſe <lb/>whatſoever. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_56" n="54"/>
      <p rend="indent" n="77"><lb/>77. But, ſay the advocates for the <w part="I">Orm-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">skirk</w> powder, what ſignifies reaſoning <lb/>againſt facts? Are there not a
        thouſand <lb/>examples of the hydrophobia prevented <lb/>by taking this medicine? Would the
          <w part="I">ſa-</w><lb/><w part="F">gacious</w> inhabitants of the northern <w part="I"
          >coun-</w><lb/><w part="F">ties</w> have ſuch faith in a mere <hi rend="italic">ignis
          fatuus?</hi>
        <lb/>—Far be it from me, to doubt the <w part="I">ſa-</w><lb/><w part="F">gacity</w> of the
        northern counties: they are <lb/>by no means ſingular in miſtaking <w part="I"
          >ſhad-</w><lb/><w part="F">dows</w> for realities. All quack-medicines, <lb/>and more than
        half the medicines uſed <lb/>in regular practice, are <hi rend="italic">ignes fatui.</hi>
        What <lb/>are all the vaunted <hi rend="italic">panaceas, theriacas,</hi>
        <lb/>antidotes, and ſpecifics, but <hi rend="italic">ignes fatui,</hi>
        <lb/>deceptions, chimeras? </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="78"><lb/>78. The ſeveral ſpecifics above <w part="I">conſi-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">dered</w> have all ſucceſſively had their day of <lb/>infallibility, and have all
        been equally <lb/>ſupported by experience, the true teſt of <lb/>medical virtue: that is, a
        number of <lb/>people bitten, or ſuppoſed to be bitten, <lb/>by dogs ſuppoſed to be mad,
        have taken <lb/>the Ormskirk, or any other infallible <lb/>powder, and have eſcaped the <w
          part="I">hydro-</w><lb/><w part="F">phobia</w>. But in the <hi rend="italic">London
          Medical <w part="I">Ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſervations</w>,</hi><note place="marg"
          rend="size(0.7)"> Vol. v. p. 195. </note> &amp;c. we have, on the authority <pb
          xml:id="page_57" n="55"/><lb/>of Dr. Fothergill, an inconteſtable proof <lb/>that the
        Ormskirk medicine is not <w part="I">infal-</w><lb/><w part="F">lible</w>: Mrs. Bellamy, who
        was bit by a <lb/>mad cat, took it, and <q rend="quotes">conformed to <lb/>the directions
          given by the vender in <lb/>every reſpect,</q> yet died of the <w part="I"
          >hydro-</w><lb/><w part="F">phobia</w> about four months after, as, I <lb/>make no doubt,
        would all the patients <lb/>that ever took the Ormskirk medicine, if <lb/>they had been
        really infected by the canine <lb/>poiſon. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="79"><lb/>79. This cenſure I do not confine to the <lb/>Ormskirk, nor yet
        to any of the <w part="I">medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cines</w> above-mentioned: it
        comprehends <lb/>every prophylactic remedy taken <w part="I">inter-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >nally</w>. Can any thing be more abſurd <lb/>than to imagine, that a diſeaſe received
        <lb/>into the body by inoculation; a poiſon <lb/>abſorbed by the lymphatic veins, and
        <lb/>mixed with the general maſs of <w part="I">circu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lating</w>
        fluids, can be deſtroyed by a <w part="I">medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cine</w> taken into the
        ſtomach? Is there any <lb/>analogy in the hiſtory of phyſic to <w part="I">autho-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">rize</w> ſuch expectations? Will any powder, <lb/>pill, or bolus, ſtop the
        progreſs of the <lb/>ſmall-pox by inoculation, or prevent it <lb/>from taking effect? Was
        there ever a <w part="I">phy-</w><pb xml:id="page_58" n="56"/><lb/><w part="F">ſician</w>
        weak enough to attempt to prevent <lb/>any other infectious diſorder, after the
        <lb/>poiſonous <hi rend="italic">liquid</hi> or <hi rend="italic">miaſmata</hi> were
        actually <lb/>abſorbed? </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="80"><lb/>80. Having thus, I hope not unfairly, <lb/>conſidered the
        pretenſions to infallibility <lb/>of the ſpecifics introduced and <w part="I"
          >recom-</w><lb/><w part="F">mended</w> by particular men, we are come <lb/>at laſt to that
        ſovereign remedy extolled <lb/>by every writer on canine madneſs, ancient <lb/>and modern,
        and uſed in all countries, in <lb/>every age, from the days of Celſus to the <lb/>preſent
        moment—I mean <hi rend="italic">bathing in cold <lb/>water.</hi> To this part of our ſubject
        I beg <lb/>the reader's particular attention, becauſe I <lb/>am very certain that many lives
        have been <lb/>loſt by a fooliſh dependence on this broken <lb/>reed. I have ſaid that all
        writers on <lb/>canine madneſs, ancient and modern, have <lb/>recommended cold-bathing; but
        I muſt <lb/>except Dr. Falck, the author of <hi rend="italic">The <lb/>Seaman's Medical
          Inſtructor,</hi> and Dr. <w part="I">Fo-</w><lb/><w part="F">thergill</w>, who wrote a
        paper in the <hi rend="italic">London <lb/>Medical Obſervations,</hi><note place="marg"
          rend="size(0.7)"> Vol. v. p. 290. </note> purpoſely to prove <lb/>the inefficacy of
        bathing in the ſea. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="81"><lb/>81. The phyſician laſt mentioned was <lb/>of opinion, that the
        practice of bathing <pb xml:id="page_59" n="57"/><lb/>in ſalt-water, as a preſervative,
        originated <lb/>in a miſtake. Celſus directs the patient,<note place="marg"
          rend="size(0.7) italic"> Celſ. lib. <hi rend="roman">v.</hi> c. <hi rend="roman">27.</hi>
        </note>
        <lb/>actually labouring under the hydrophobia, <lb/>to be thrown unexpectedly into a <w
          part="I">fiſh-</w><lb/><w part="F">pond</w>: if he cannot ſwim, he is to be <lb/>ſuffered
        to flounce and drink, raiſing him <lb/>a little now and then, ſo as to keep him <lb/>from
        drowning; but, if he can ſwim, he <lb/>is to be frequently ducked, that in ſpite <lb/>of
        himſelf he may be ſatiated with water: <lb/><q rend="quotes">Thus (ſays Celſus) his thirſt
          and dread <lb/>of water will be cured at the ſame time.</q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="82"><lb/>82. <hi rend="italic">Celſus</hi> was miſtaken in ſuppoſing
        <lb/>that he could force the patient to drink <lb/>by holding him under water, or that,
        <lb/>after being half drowned, he would look <lb/>on water with leſs horrour, or ſwallow
        <lb/>liquids with greater eaſe. The latter part <lb/>of this diſcipline is daily practiſed,
        by the <lb/>old women at the watering places, on the <lb/>wretched creatures that are ſent
        by old <lb/>women, male and female, from the inland <lb/>country. This practice of drowning
        the <lb/>patient in order to cure him of an averſion <lb/>to water, abſurd as it is, was
        probably <lb/>taken from <hi rend="italic">Celſus,</hi> who, though a ſenſible <pb
          xml:id="page_60" n="58"/><lb/>man, poſſibly without experience or much <lb/>reflexion,
        preſcribed it on the authority <lb/>of ſome Greek writer; but why the ſea <lb/>was
        ſubſtituted for a fiſh-pond, and how <lb/>it came to paſs that what <hi rend="italic"
          >Celſus</hi> ordered <lb/>as a cure for the hydrophobia actually <lb/>preſent, ſhould be
        applied as a <w part="I">prophy-</w><lb/><w part="F">lactic</w>, a preſervative remedy, is
        difficult <lb/>to conceive. </p>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="25"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
