<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Essays on the hepatitis</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Thomas Girdlestone</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Essays on the hepatitis and spasmodic affections in India: founded on
              observations made whilst on service with his Majesty's troops in different parts of
              that country. By Thomas Girdlestone, M.D.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T64134</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T64134"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Murray, No. 32, Fleet-Street,
                  M,DCC,LXXXVII.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1787</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="8"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="65"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3306803595</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K055350.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: disease"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_1"/>
        <p rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">ESSAYS</hi>
          <lb/>ON THE <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">HEPATITIS</hi>
          <lb/>AND <lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)">SPASMODIC AFFECTIONS</hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">IN INDIA</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="align-center"><lb/>[<hi rend="sc">Price Two Shillings</hi>.] </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_3"/>
        <p rend="align-center"><lb/>TO <lb/>THE HONOURABLE <lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)">THE COURT OF
            DIRECTORS</hi>
          <lb/>OF THE HONOURABLE <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">THE UNITED EAST INDIA COMPANY</hi>,
          <lb/>THE TWO FOLLOWING <lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)">ESSAYS </hi><lb/>ARE HUMBLY INSCRIBED,
          <lb/>BY THEIR OBEDIENT SERVANT, <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> AUTHOR. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_4"/>
        <head rend="dc(2) align-center"><lb/>PREFACE. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HE Britiſh poſſeſſions in India are <lb/>now
          become ſo extenſive as to require <lb/>for their defence a numerous body of our
          <lb/>countrymen; many of whom, from the <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">fluence</w> of
          a new and injurious climate, as <lb/>well as other unfavourable changes, fall <lb/>victims
          to the conſequences of emigration. <lb/>The prevention of this fatality may, in ſome
          <lb/>caſes, exceed the utmoſt efforts of medicine; <lb/>but it is certain that in others,
          and thoſe by <lb/>far the greateſt number, the operation of the <lb/>cauſes
          above-mentioned prove chiefly <w part="I">delete-</w><lb/><w part="F">rious</w> from the
          imperfect knowledge hitherto <lb/>attained of the nature of diſeaſes in India. <lb/>Among
          thoſe to which Europeans are <w part="I">parti-</w><lb/><w part="F">cularly</w> expoſed,
          the moſt common, and <lb/>perhaps likewiſe the moſt fatal, is the <w part="I"
            >He-</w><lb/><w part="F">patitis</w>, or Inflammation of the Liver; an <lb/>accurate
          inveſtigation of which muſt <w part="I">there-</w><pb xml:id="page_5" n="viii"/><lb/><w
            part="F">fore</w> be an object of the firſt importance to <lb/>every practitioner in
          that country. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>There are as yet only three publications on <lb/>this diſeaſe in
          England, and they are <w part="I">defec-</w><lb/><w part="F">tive</w>, as they were given
          by their authors, in <lb/>conſequence of ſome caſes which they met <lb/>with at ſea;
          inconſiderable either in number <lb/>or variety when compared with thoſe which <lb/>happen
          in the field. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Author of the preſent Treatiſe <lb/>landed in India with the care
          of a thouſand <lb/>of his Majeſty's troops, and other regiments <lb/>fell to his charge.
          He thus had an <w part="I">oppor-</w><lb/><w part="F">tunity</w> of ſeeing the Hepatitis
          in all it's <w part="I">varie-</w><lb/><w part="F">ties</w> of form, and of attending
          minutely to <lb/>it's phoenomena. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This led him to attempt an innovation <lb/>in the practice, which he
          found ſucceſſful <lb/>for the laſt nine months of his continuance <lb/>in that country. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_6" n="ix"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Since his Eſſay on the Hepatitis has been <lb/>in the preſs, the
          report of four new-raiſed <lb/>regiments being to be ſent to India, has <lb/>induced him
          to add an Eſſay on the <w part="I">Spaſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">modic</w> Affections, which
          preſented <w part="I">them-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſelves</w> immediately on the arrival of
          the <lb/>troops with whom he landed in that <lb/>country. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Spaſms are very likely to be the firſt <lb/>diſeaſes of Europeans in
          India. And as <lb/>the Author recollects no Engliſh Treatiſe <lb/>on the Spaſms in India
          drawn from perſonal <lb/>obſervation, he has given the annexed <lb/>conciſe account,
          rather than delay it's <w part="I">publi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cation</w> until he could
          find leiſure to enlarge <lb/>upon the ſubject. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>He has however omitted nothing either <lb/>in the Hepatitis or Spaſms
          which he can <lb/>think of that has any immediate reference to <lb/>the practical parts of
          theſe ſubjects; though <lb/>he is far from entertaining the idea that he <pb
            xml:id="page_7" n="x"/><lb/>has at length exhauſted either of them by <lb/>his own
          obſervations. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>He truſts that the endeavour to furniſh <lb/>the officer and
          inexperienced practitioner to <lb/>theſe climates with the means of preventing <lb/>and of
          curing two of the moſt formidable <lb/>diſeaſes of the Eaſt, will amply apologize <lb/>for
          the numerous defects which a critical <lb/>reader may, no doubt, diſcern in the <w
            part="I">follow-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> pages. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_8"/>
        <p rend="align-center"><lb/>ON <lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)">SPASMODIC AFFECTIONS </hi><lb/>IN
            <lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)">INDIA</hi>. </p>
        <div>
          <pb xml:id="page_9" n="7"/>
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)">AN ESSAY</hi>
            <lb/>ON THE <lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)">HEPATITIS</hi> IN <hi rend="size(1.7)">INDIA</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HOSE who are converſant in <w part="I"
              >medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cal</w> writings, or have attended much <lb/>to diſſections
            in hoſpitals, know in how <lb/>many patients the liver, which had never <lb/>been
            ſuſpected of any diſeaſe, has been <lb/>found, after death, in a morbid ſtate. It
            <lb/>is a fact, that, in a great number of ſuch <lb/>caſes, the affected part has gone
            through <lb/>all the different ſtages of the latent diſeaſe, <pb xml:id="page_10" n="8"
            /><lb/>without ever exhibiting any of the <w part="I">ſymp-</w><lb/><w part="F">toms</w>
            by which we are taught, in the <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſcription</w> of
            noſologiſts, to diſtinguiſh it. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Without paying any regard to <w part="I">defini-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >tions</w>, I ſhall therefore proceed to a faithful <lb/>relation of the Hepatitis, as
            it appeared in <lb/>ſeveral hundreds of the men and officers, <lb/>during and after a
            campaign of twenty-<lb/>two months, in the Carnatic and Tanjore <lb/>countries of India. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>This diſeaſe is more common to the <lb/>military than to any other
            ſet of people, <lb/>and to thoſe eſpecially who ſerve on the <lb/>Coromandel coaſt, as
            in this quarter the <lb/>fatigues of the troops are the greateſt. In <lb/>Bengal, where
            all the expeditions are <w part="I">car-</w><lb/><w part="F">ried</w> on only by water,
            in veſſels covered <lb/>from the rays of the ſun, and where the <lb/>proviſions are
            better and more regularly <lb/>ſupplied, diſeaſed livers are much leſs <w part="I"
              >fre-</w><lb/><w part="F">quent</w>. From the hiſtory of this diſeaſe, <lb/>it will
            appear not to be ſo acute as is <w part="I">gene-</w><lb/><w part="F">rally</w>
            imagined; but that it may, and very <pb xml:id="page_11" n="9"/><lb/>often does,
            continue in a chronic ſtate, for <lb/>weeks, months, ſometimes years, and <lb/>becomes
            ſuddenly acute by intemperance <lb/>in drinking, or the improper uſe of <w part="I"
              >mer-</w><lb/><w part="F">cury</w>. The ſymptoms of vomiting, <w part="I"
              >hic-</w><lb/><w part="F">cup</w>, or pain of the ſide or ſhoulder, too <lb/>generally
            imagined to be neceſſary <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tendants</w> of this
            diſeaſe, will not be found <lb/>to have accompanied one half of the caſes <lb/>of
            diſeaſed liver, which have gone through <lb/>all their different ſtages. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Without taking any notice of the <w part="I">gene-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ral</w> pathology of the diſeaſe, I ſhall divide <lb/>the phenomena into
            three ſtages, viz. the <lb/>chronic, acute, and ſuppurative; and <w part="I"
              >de-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſcribe</w> them in the order in which they <lb/>appeared. To
            prove the acute ſtage not <lb/>to be alſo a ſuppurative one, I have no <lb/>facts. But
            as one of theſe ſtages always <lb/>yields to a-peculiar treatment, and the <lb/>other
            ſeldom to any, the diſtinction may <lb/>not be unneceſſary. </p>
          <div n="1" type="section">
            <pb xml:id="page_12" n="10"/>
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>THE FIRST, OR CHRONIC STAGE. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">FOR</hi> ſome time before the pain of the
              <lb/>ſhoulder and ſide becomes violent, the <lb/>animal ſpirits are much diminiſhed:
              the <lb/>ſtools begin to be very irregular, ſome <lb/>days ſcarce any, at others very
              profuſe and <lb/>acrid: the countenance is tumid and <lb/>bloated. Sometimes the
              tunica albuginea <lb/>of the eyes is yellow, but more commonly <lb/>of a dull white
              appearance. The ſkin, <lb/>eſpecially of the muſcular parts of the <lb/>body, is dry
              and ſqualid. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The urine is generally more or leſs high <lb/>coloured, and ſmall
              in quantity; the <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſpiration</w> ſcanty and
              partial; the tongue <lb/>dry with thirſt. The ſtomach is extremely <lb/>variable:
              frequently, before dinner, there <lb/>is a momentary ſickneſs, which is almoſt <lb/>as
              inſtantly ſucceeded by a ſenſation of <lb/>hunger. After eating, all theſe ſymptoms
                <pb xml:id="page_13" n="11"/><lb/>are alleviated for an hour or two, and then
              <lb/>ſucceeded, either by heartburn or <w part="I">pain-</w><lb/><w part="F">ful</w>
              gripes; the pulſe is ſmall, hard, and <lb/>quick, eſpecially towards the evening;
              <lb/>the gums contract a hardneſs; the <lb/>ſhoulders appear daily more elevated. In
              <lb/>many there is a dull pain in the lumbar <lb/>region. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>After theſe ſymptoms have continued for <lb/>ſome time, an
              induration of a part of the <lb/>liver may be ſometimes felt, by laying <lb/>the
              patient on his back, with the head <lb/>low, and the knees a little elevated. The
              <lb/>patient frequently continues in this ſtate <lb/>for a conſiderable time, until
              the dejection <lb/>of ſpirits, which always more or leſs <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">tends</w> this diſeaſe, prompts him to the <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">moderate</w> uſe of wine, which ſcarcely ever <lb/>fails to accelerate the
              approach of the acute <lb/>or inflammatory ſtage. </p>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="section">
            <pb xml:id="page_14" n="12"/>
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>THE SECOND, OR INFLAMMATORY STAGE. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">THE</hi> countenance, which, from the
              <lb/>beginning of the preceding ſtage, had <lb/>contracted a morbid appearance,
              becomes <lb/>now, at intervals, more florid than was <lb/>common to the patient even
              in his beſt <lb/>health. The ſtools are ſmall, frequent, <lb/>and reſembling thoſe in
              the dyſentery. <lb/>The pain of the ſhoulder and ſide, which <lb/>before was obtuſe
              and ſhifting, eſpecially <lb/>that of the former, becomes ſuddenly <lb/>very acute.
              When this pain of the ſhoulder <lb/>is felt, it always correſponds with that part
              <lb/>of the liver which is moſt immediately <lb/>diſeaſed; being more or leſs
              anteriorly or <lb/>poſteriorly ſituated, according as the <w part="I">ante-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">rior</w> or poſterior parts of the liver are the <lb/>ſeat of the
              complaint: and with the left <lb/>lobe the left ſhoulder is frequently <w part="I"
                >af-</w><lb/><w part="F">fected</w>. In this ſtage the pain of the <pb
                xml:id="page_15" n="13"/><lb/>ſhoulder is frequently increaſed on every <lb/>motion
              of the diaphragm, attended with a <lb/>troubleſome ſhort cough, and catching of
              <lb/>the breath, in inſpirations, as well as an <lb/>increaſed pain on the region of
              the liver <lb/>being touched. Sometimes the eaſieſt <w part="I">po-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">ſition</w> is on the diſeaſed ſide, at other times <lb/>on the oppoſite;
              but more commonly on <lb/>the back, with the head rather low. The <lb/>Hepatitis, in
              this ſtage, begins its attack <lb/>as often with a flux and teneſmus as <lb/>with a
              fixed pain of the ſhoulder; and in <lb/>this caſe the perſon falls a ſacrifice to a
              <lb/>miſtaken conception of the diſeaſe. <w part="I">Un-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w>
              this fallacious appearance the ſick is <lb/>commonly relieved by ſalts, or ſome <w
                part="I">gen-</w><lb/><w part="F">tle</w> laxatives, until, the acute ſtage being
              <lb/>palliated, the diſeaſe aſſumes the primitive <lb/>chronic form; in which ſtate he
              continues <lb/>with irregular ſecretions, the urine high <lb/>coloured, the
              countenance of a ſallow <lb/>complexion, and every day impreſſed with <lb/>an air of
              additional melancholy. Many <lb/>unfortunate perſons, driven to deſpair, by <lb/>the
              continuance of the complaint for one <pb xml:id="page_16" n="14"/><lb/>or two years,
              have at length periſhed by <lb/>violent means, which their ungovernable
              <lb/>impatience had ſuggeſted. The period <lb/>moſt uſually fatal is the acceſſion of
              the <lb/>third ſtage, which is haſtened by the uſe <lb/>both of aſtringents and
              bitters. </p>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="section">
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>THE THIRD, OR SUPPURATIVE STAGE. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">IN</hi> a few days or weeks after the <w
                part="I">dyſen-</w><lb/><w part="F">teric</w> ſymptoms have abated, the patient
              <lb/>becomes ſo tired of the looſeneſs which <lb/>remains, that he is deſirous of
              having it <lb/>flopped. For this purpoſe, the common <lb/>practice is to order
              aſtringents or bitters, <lb/>which indeed ſoon check the looſeneſs; <lb/>but, in a
              ſhort time after, he is attacked <lb/>with a deep hollow-ſounding cough, from
              <lb/>that ſide of the lungs which correſponds <lb/>to the lobe of the liver moſt
              diſeaſed. </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_17" n="15"/>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Whenever the cough commences the <lb/>greateſt part of that ſide
              of the liver is <lb/>generally occupied with an abſceſs, by <lb/>which its ſubſtance
              is already conſumed; <lb/>though this purulent collection ſeldom gave <lb/>any token
              of its exiſtence, until it had <lb/>opened to itſelf a paſſage through the <w part="I"
                >dia-</w><lb/><w part="F">phragm</w> and lungs, or into the cavity of <lb/>the
              abdomen. In this emergency the <lb/>patient is either ſuffocated by the ſudden
              <lb/>inundation of the lungs, or miſerably <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >pires</w> by the more ſlow effects of incurable <lb/>inanition, which is promoted
              by an <w part="I">uncon-</w><lb/><w part="F">cocted</w> diſcharge of the aliments, <w
                part="I">accom-</w><lb/><w part="F">panied</w> with flatulence and gripes. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Where no aſtringents have been given, <lb/>there are ſometimes
              diſcovered more <w part="I">ſu-</w><lb/><w part="F">perficial</w> ſuppurations, which
              are eaſily <lb/>opened with the knife, and cured in a <lb/>ſhort time. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>But thoſe which ſucceed the ſudden <lb/>ſtoppage of the looſeneſs,
              when this <w part="I">inci-</w><lb/><w part="F">dent</w> is attended with a deep <w
                part="I">hollow-ſound-</w><pb xml:id="page_18" n="16"/><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>
              cough, prove equally mortal, whether <lb/>they point outwardly or penetrate the
              <lb/>cavities. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>In theſe forms the Hepatitis moſt <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">monly</w> made its appearance. But there is <lb/>another ſhape, under which
              it remained for <lb/>years, without running into the more acute <lb/>ſtages,
              eſpecially among the natives and <lb/>thoſe Europeans who had arrived in the
              <lb/>country at a very early period. This form <lb/>is that of an intermittent fever,
              irregular <lb/>in its acceſſions, ſometimes uſhered in by a <lb/>cold, though oftener
              only by a hot ſtage; <lb/>but never without the pulſe becoming <lb/>ſmaller and
              quicker: the duration of the <lb/>hot or ſweating ſtage likewiſe bearing no
              <lb/>proportion to the length or ſhortneſs of <lb/>the cold one. It is called the
              Hill-fever, <lb/>from its being endemic in the hilly parts <lb/>of the Carnatic; and
              is often conſidered as <lb/>incurable. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>In all the caſes I have ſeen of this kind <lb/>the livers were
              diſeaſed, eſpecially the left <pb xml:id="page_19" n="17"/><lb/>lobes; and the
              patients were reſtored to <lb/>health only by treating their complaints <lb/>as
              diſeaſed livers. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Authors generally mention vomitings as <lb/>concomitant ſymptoms
              when the concave <lb/>parts, and hiccups, when the convex parts <lb/>of the liver are
              diſeaſed. But I have ſeen <lb/>both parts impoſthumated without either <lb/>of theſe
              ſymptoms; and indeed have very <lb/>ſeldom met with them in any hepatic
              <lb/>complaints. A nauſea and want of <w part="I">appe-</w><lb/><w part="F">tite</w>
              are much more common in the latter <lb/>ſtages of this diſeaſe. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The pain in this diſeaſe is uſually aſcribed <lb/>to an adheſion
              of the convex part of the <lb/>liver to the peritoneum; the conſequence <lb/>of which
              is, that the patients are induced <lb/>to lie on the diſeaſed ſide. But when the
              <lb/>concave part is affected, to recline on the <lb/>oppoſite ſide is an eaſier
              ſituation. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Mr. Matthews has remarked that only <lb/>perſons in whom the
              thorax is narrow have <pb xml:id="page_20" n="18"/><lb/>any pain in the epigaſtric,
              and thoſe in <lb/>whom it is broad, in the lumbar region. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>But, as far as I ever could obſerve, theſe <lb/>pains alternated
              in each of the patients <lb/>independently of any difference in the <w part="I"
                >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">formation</w> of the cheſt. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Whether the pain of the ſhoulder ariſes <lb/>from the adheſion to
              the diaphragm, as <lb/>ſome have ſuppoſed, or from the junction <lb/>of the phrenic
              nerve, with the third and <lb/>fourth of the cervical, I cannot pretend to <lb/>ſay;
              but that it does not depend always <lb/>upon the enlargement of the liver, I can
              <lb/>with great confidence affirm; having ſeen <lb/>many amazingly enlarged, by
              abſceſſes <lb/>formed in them, where this ſymptom had <lb/>never been obſerved by the
              patients. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The free deſcent of the tranſverſe <w part="I">ſep-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">tum</w>, upon which reſpiration much depends, <lb/>being impeded, a greater
              or leſs degree <lb/>of dyſpnœa muſt neceſſarily enſue. </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_21" n="19"/>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Though no perſons, after the age of <lb/>puberty, are exempted
              from this diſeaſe, <lb/>when expoſed to the operation of the <w part="I"
                >ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">citing</w> cauſes, I have obſerved that thoſe <lb/>of a
              ſanguine temperament were more <lb/>frequently afflicted than any other. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>I never yet ſaw the diſeaſe in any who <lb/>was not an adult. Out
              of twenty <w part="I">drum-</w><lb/><w part="F">mers</w> of the 101ſt regiment, under
              the age <lb/>of puberty, not one was ſeized with it, <lb/>though they were conſtantly
              in the field, <lb/>and performed their marches more regularly <lb/>than any other part
              of the regiment. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The particular circumſtances to which <lb/>our army was expoſed
              were the following, <lb/>which I have therefore ventured to aſſign <lb/>as the remote
              cauſes of the diſeaſe: </p>
            <lg>
              <lb/>
              <l>A hot climate, </l>
              <lb/>
              <l>Injuries of the cranium from the rays <lb/>of the ſun, </l>
              <lb/>
              <l>Abuſe of ſpirits, </l>
              <lb/>
              <l>Paſſions of the mind, </l>
              <pb xml:id="page_22" n="20"/>
              <lb/>
              <l>Violent exerciſe, </l>
              <lb/>
              <l>Bad water, </l>
              <lb/>
              <l>Want of vegetables, </l>
              <lb/>
              <l>Great repletion after long faſting, </l>
              <lb/>
              <l>Abuſe of Mercury. </l>
            </lg>
          </div>
          <div type="part">
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>HEAT. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">HEAT</hi> being one of the moſt <w part="I"
                >univer-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſal</w> of all ſtimulants, has frequently <w part="I"
                >pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duced</w> the beſt effects, by increaſing all the
              <lb/>ſecretions: but though moderate heat, <lb/>like moderate drinking, be frequently
                <w part="I">ſalu-</w><lb/><w part="F">tary</w>, extreme heat, like abuſes of <w
                part="I">dram-</w><lb/><w part="F">drinking</w>, always leaves the ſyſtem more
              <lb/>languid, and conſequently the ſecretions <lb/>leſs copious. And, as the
              circulation <lb/>through the liver is naturally languid, this <lb/>organ is, of all
              the bowels, the firſt to feel <lb/>theſe effects. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="part">
            <pb xml:id="page_23" n="21"/>
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>RAYS OF THE SUN. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">THE</hi> rays of the ſun on the ſcull
              <lb/>prove ſtill a greater ſtimulus to the brain, ſo <lb/>as frequently to produce
              inſtantaneous death. <lb/>Whenever perſons eſcaped with moderate <lb/><hi
                rend="italic">ſun-ſtrokes,</hi> they often had at firſt increaſed <lb/>ſecretions of
              bile, which were ſucceeded <lb/>by a proportionable deficiency. The ſame <lb/>effect
              happens frequently in fractured ſculls. <lb/>At firſt there is a profuſion of bile,
              then <lb/>very little; and ſometimes it is followed <lb/>by abſceſſes; of which there
              are inſtances <lb/>given by Pegreas, Ballonius, Slegius, <w part="I">Pou-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">teau</w>, Velſchius, Paré, Greaume, <w part="I">Binoſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >quius</w>, Marmannus, De Merchettes, <w part="I">Char-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >rieré</w>, Job. Mac Rereanus, Bianchi, and <lb/>other authors. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="part">
            <pb xml:id="page_24" n="22"/>
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>PASSIONS OF THE MIND. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">THE</hi> melancholy which takes place in
              <lb/>the Hepatitis, the diminution of bile in <lb/>melancholy, the increaſed ſecretion
              of <lb/>bile from anger, ſun-ſtrokes and injuries of <lb/>the cranium, with their
              conſequences, all <lb/>ſerve to prove a remarkable ſympathy <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">tween</w> the liver and brain. I am therefore <lb/>inclined to believe,
              that, next to the rays of <lb/>the ſun and exceſſes in ſpirituous liquors, <lb/>all
              the depreſſing paſſions are to be <w part="I">conſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">dered</w> as
              the moſt certain remote cauſes of <lb/>this diſeaſe.<note place="bottom" n="*"
                rend="size(0.5)">* The melancholy which often attends people in <lb/>Britain, after
                very active lives in Aſia, is generally <lb/>attributed to moral cauſes. But perhaps
                the <w part="I">phy-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſical</w> cauſes may have a far greater
                ſhare in its <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duction</w> than has been commonly
                imagined. A <lb/>certain gloom appears to be inſeparable from <lb/>a diſeaſed liver.
                Few perſons who have been <lb/>long in that country, expoſed to the rays of the
                <lb/>ſun by long marches, whoſe livers are not in the firſt <lb/>ſtage of this
                diſeaſe. But admitting this not to be the <lb/>caſe, it has, in the former part of
                this treatiſe, been <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerved</w> that the dark
                haired and melancholic habits <lb/>reſiſt the fatigues beſt; of courſe they are the
                moſt <lb/>likely to reviſit their native country; and they ſeldom <lb/>return to
                Europe until they are able to live luxuriouſly; <lb/>where, from being accuſtomed to
                all the violent ſtimuli <lb/>in nature, they come to ſink into a ſtate of eaſe and
                <lb/>luxury in a country where double their former exerciſe <lb/>had need to be
                exerted to prevent the powers of the <lb/>climate, which are now to them become
                depreſſing. </note>
            </p>
          </div>
          <div type="part">
            <pb xml:id="page_25" n="23"/>
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>BAD WATER. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">CLEGHORN</hi> obſerves that, on the <lb/>eaſt
              ſide of Minorca, where the waters <lb/>are bad, tumefied ſpleens and livers are
              <lb/>common both to men and brutes. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The badneſs of the Carnatic waters may <lb/>be ſufficient argument
              for claſſing it as a <lb/>cauſe, eſpecially when we conſider the great <lb/>quantities
              of it which the men were obliged <lb/>to drink from the extreme heat of the
              <lb/>climate. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="part">
            <pb xml:id="page_26" n="24"/>
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CHANGE OF DIET. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">EVERY</hi> change of diet, from a long
              <lb/>continued one, ſeems to act as a ſtimulus <lb/>on the biliary ducts. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The officers and men who were priſoners <lb/>in chains with
              Tippo-Saib, in the Eaſt <lb/>Indies, were allowed only rice, water, and <lb/>capſicum,
              for the many months they were <lb/>with him. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>When they were releaſed, the animal <lb/>food of every kind which
              they attempted <lb/>to eat, purged them ſo violently that they <lb/>could take it only
              in the ſmalleſt quantities <lb/>for a conſiderable time. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The Britiſh fleet not appearing with the <lb/>ſtore-ſhips, the
              army was reduced to the <lb/>neceſſity of living almoſt entirely on animal <lb/>food.
              The natives of the army, whoſe <lb/>cuſtomary diet is chiefly rice, were all
              <lb/>purged by this change. </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_27" n="25"/>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The like happens both to men and <lb/>officers, after living ſome
              months at ſea on <lb/>the ſame diet; on making a port, the <w part="I">ve-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">getables</w> always produce ſuch copious <w part="I">ſecre-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">tions</w> of bile as oblige them to be moderate <lb/>in their uſe. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The patent dried cabbage was laid in for <lb/>the uſe of the 101ſt
              regiment. They had <lb/>none of it for the firſt month of the voyage; <lb/>but as ſoon
              as they began to eat it they were <lb/>all purged. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>From fiſh alſo the ſame effects have <lb/>been ſeen. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="part">
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>GREAT REPLETION AFTER LONG FASTING. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">AS</hi> the troops were frequently expoſed
              <lb/>to long faſting, they were very apt to <w part="I">over-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >charge</w> their ſtomachs. To prove this to <pb xml:id="page_28" n="26"/><lb/>be a
              highly debilitating cauſe, the following <lb/>recent and well-known fact may be <w
                part="I">men-</w><lb/><w part="F">tioned</w>. At the famine at Madras, in
              <lb/>October 1782, ſeveral native children were <lb/>taken by the Engliſh to their
              tables; by <lb/>their extreme voracity, their viſcera ſoon <lb/>became diſeaſed, their
              bellies tumefied, and <lb/>ſchirrous indurations were to be felt in <lb/>all thoſe who
              had not their diet limited <lb/>for a conſiderable time. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>I ſhall afterwards have occaſion to <w part="I">men-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">tion</w> the effects of mercury, in treating of <lb/>the cure of this
              diſeaſe. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>I ſhall now hazard a few conjectures <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">lative</w> to the proximate cauſe of this diſeaſe; <lb/>though I would not
              be underſtood as being <lb/>dogmatical on a point of ſo much <w part="I"
                >uncer-</w><lb/><w part="F">tainty</w>. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>In conſequence of a relaxation of the <lb/>ſyſtem, eſpecially of
              the ultimate branches <lb/>of the vena portarum, the ſecretion of bile <lb/>is not
              only diminiſhed, but that which is <pb xml:id="page_29" n="27"/><lb/>ſecreted is more
              watery than uſual, and leſs <lb/>endowed with the natural qualities of the <lb/>bile.
              On this account chylification <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">comes</w> imperfect,
              and all the different <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">teſtinal</w> phaenomena are
              produced. <w part="I">Au-</w><lb/><w part="F">thors</w> have related the diſſection of
                <w part="I">pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tients</w> affected with dyſenteries, whoſe
              <lb/>livers were found diſeaſed; and theſe <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >pearances</w> are conformable to the doctrine <lb/>now mentioned. In many caſes of
              chronic <lb/>dyſenteries I found the livers in one of the <lb/>ſtages above deſcribed.
              The ſpaſm of the <lb/>colon, in thoſe complaints, therefore, can <lb/>only be
              conſidered as the effects of the ſtate <lb/>of the bile, and not the proximate cauſe
              of <lb/>this diſeaſe. Though ſalts frequently <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >lieve</w> the tormina and ſpaſms, they never <lb/>are ſufficient to remove the
              diſeaſe, except <lb/>where they induce a new and continued <lb/>energy in the biliary
              ducts, ſo that ſtools <lb/>copiouſly and regularly charged with a <lb/>deep yellow
              bile are produced. As a <w part="I">fur-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> confirmation of
              this opinion, I may <lb/>add, that the moſt obſtinate of theſe <w part="I"
                >dyſen-</w><lb/><w part="F">teries</w> readily yielded to the ſame treatment <pb
                xml:id="page_30" n="28"/><lb/>as the Hepatitis after every other method <lb/>had
              failed. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>From the gradual diminution of bile in <lb/>the Hepatitis, as well
              as the gradual <w part="I">dimi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nutions</w> of energy in the
              ſyſtem, there is <lb/>every reaſon to ſuſpect: the extremities of <lb/>the vena
              portarum to be the ſeat of this <lb/>diſeaſe. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>From the few nerves ſent to the liver, <lb/>there is but little
              reaſon to expect much <lb/>energy through the medium of thoſe <w part="I"
                >or-</w><lb/><w part="F">gans</w>; and on account of the diſtance of <lb/>the vena
              portarum from the heart, there is <lb/>ſtill leſs reaſon to expect much influence
              <lb/>from a <hi rend="italic">vis a tergo.</hi> Why, then, along <lb/>continued
              weakneſs of the ſyſtem ſhould <lb/>always produce diſeaſed livers in India, <w
                part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pears</w> to me not to be ſo difficult a queſtion,
              <lb/>as why the ſame cauſe ſhould not render <lb/>this a more frequent diſeaſe in
              other <w part="I">cli-</w><lb/><w part="F">mates</w>. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>With reſpect to the diagnoſtic ſymptoms, <pb xml:id="page_31"
                n="29"/><lb/>the pain of the ſhoulder and ſide, when it <lb/>exiſts, is a very
              certain characteriſtic of the <lb/>diſeaſe; but it cannot be conſidered as a
              <lb/>pathognomonic ſymptom, as it is by no <lb/>means conſtant. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The elevation of the ſhoulders, as the <lb/>diſeaſe advanced, was
              evident; but this <lb/>poſſibly may take place in other morbid <lb/>affections. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The hardneſs of the gums was a very <lb/>conſtant attendant; but
              this, likewiſe, is <lb/>common to many perſons, both in a ſtate <lb/>of health and
              diſeaſe; and therefore, of <lb/>itſelf, can form no certain diagnoſtic. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The puſhing the fingers againſt the <w part="I">hy-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">pochondres</w> would ſometimes give a ſenſe <lb/>of pain or itching to one
              of the ſhoulders. <lb/>But, upon the whole, I am of opinion that <lb/>the preſence of
              this diſeaſe can only be <lb/>aſcertained by attending to the whole <w part="I"
                >ſuc-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceſſion</w> of phaenomena; as it ſo often exiſts
              <lb/>without the pain of the ſide and ſhoulder, <pb xml:id="page_32" n="30"/><lb/>and
              as the hardneſs of the gums and <w part="I">ele-</w><lb/><w part="F">vation</w> of the
              ſhoulders, appear not of <lb/>themſelves to be evident and ſufficient
              <lb/>diagnoſtics. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the firſt ſtage, if the cure be properly <lb/>attended to, we
              may with certainty <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">nounce</w> a favourable
              termination of the <lb/>diſeaſe. We may be equally confident in <lb/>the prognoſis of
              the ſecond ſtage, when <lb/>the tongue becomes furred, and the gums <lb/>leſs hard
              from the treatment about to be <lb/>recommended. In the third ſtage, the <lb/>tongue
              frequently remains clean, and the <lb/>gums cannot be affected. The prognoſis <lb/>in
              the laſt ſtage can never be favourable, <lb/>unleſs we can be ſure that the
              ſuppuration <lb/>is ſmall and ſuperficial. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The indication of cure in this diſeaſe is <lb/>to reſtore the
              energy of the ſyſtem, and of <lb/>the vena portarum. This may be done <lb/>frequently
              in the firſt, and ſometimes ſecond <lb/>ſtages of the diſeaſe, by change of climate,
              <lb/>and avoiding the other remote cauſes. But <pb xml:id="page_33" n="31"/><lb/>all
              the common methods uſed in northern <lb/>climates proved in theſe caſes ineffectual.
              <lb/>From ſmall doſes of neutral ſalts, ſuch as <lb/>the ſal glauberi given at
              intervals, ſo as to <lb/>keep up a conſtant action, the diſeaſe was <lb/>ſometimes
              brought back from the ſecond <lb/>ſtage to the firſt. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The vitriolic acid was tried frequently <lb/>without any kind of
              advantage: it <w part="I">occa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſioned</w> an unnatural appetite,
              and commonly <lb/>haſtened the progreſs of the diſeaſe. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The bark, and bitters of every kind, <lb/>were attended with
              ſimilar effects. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>As theſe remedies have been long found to <lb/>be ineffectual,
              practitioners of late years <lb/>have had recourſe to mercury, introducing <lb/>it to
              the ſyſtem both by the mouth and <lb/>ſkin; and by this treatment they have <w
                part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">come</w> much more ſucceſſful. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Soon after my arrival in India, I ſaw <lb/>ſeveral caſes treated
              in this manner with <pb xml:id="page_34" n="32"/><lb/>evident advantage. A hard gum
              had always <lb/>been obſerved to be a conſtant attendant <lb/>on this diſeaſe. I had
              not ſeen many caſes <lb/>before I began to obſerve that the patient <lb/>ſeldom or
              never was relieved until the gums <lb/>were made ſore or ſpungy; and when they
              <lb/>could not be thus affected, a ſuppuration <lb/>almoſt always took place. I
              entertained <lb/>hope that this ſtate of the gums would <w part="I">fur-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">niſh</w> me with a certain criterion, to judge <lb/>when a ſufficient
              quantity of mercury was <lb/>thrown into the ſyſtem. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>In this ſtate of uncertainty, I was <w part="I">ſur-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">priſed</w> to obſerve that a ſmall quantity of <lb/>mercury, taken by the
              mouth, affected the <lb/>gums very much, and often without <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">ducing</w> any other ſenſible alteration. On <lb/>the contrary, when a
              large quantity was <lb/>applied to the ſkin, the time required to <lb/>affect the gums
              was much longer, and the <lb/>alterations on the ſyſtem were much greater. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>This obſervation firſt ſugeſted to me the <lb/>ſuppoſition, that,
              when the mercury was <pb xml:id="page_35" n="33"/><lb/>introduced by the ſtomach, it
              might have <lb/>a tendency to paſs off by the mouth before <lb/>the ſyſtem was much
              affected; whereas, <lb/>when it was introduced by the ſkin, a large <lb/>quantity
              could be retained in the ſyſtem <lb/>before the gums became affected: and
              <lb/>therefore, if any advantage was to be <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >pected</w> from mercury in this diſeaſe, this <lb/>latter method, in which larger
              quantities <lb/>could be introduced into the ſyſtem, ought <lb/>naturally to be
              preferred. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The two following caſes, related to me <lb/>by the gentlemen
              themſelves, firſt led me <lb/>to believe the neceſſity of much mercury <lb/>in the
              cure of this diſeaſe. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="align-center italic"><lb/><hi rend="roman">CASE</hi> of Major <hi
                rend="roman">D. C.</hi> taken in <lb/>September <hi rend="roman">1783.</hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Major</hi> D. C. of the Company's <w part="I"
                >ſer-</w><lb/><w part="F">vice</w>, a ſtout, ſtrong-made Highlander, of <lb/>about
              ſixty years of age, after being two <lb/>years in India, began to labour under a <pb
                xml:id="page_36" n="34"/><lb/>liver-complaint, which was relieved by <lb/>mercury.
              As the mercury was only given <lb/>him by the mouth, the gums were <w part="I"
                >fre-</w><lb/><w part="F">quently</w> affected. The relief he always
              <lb/>experienced from its uſe, made him <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tinue</w>
              it as freely as poſſible for near <lb/>twelve months, when the pain of the ſide
              <lb/>and ſhoulder ceaſed. Eighteen years had <lb/>elapſed from this time without his
              ever <lb/>ſuffering a day's ſickneſs. His gums ever <lb/>ſince continuing oozy, and
              his ſaliva <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ternaturally</w> flowing, are the only
                <w part="I">incon-</w><lb/><w part="F">veniencies</w> he is ſenſible of from this
              long <lb/>courſe. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="align-center italic"><lb/><hi rend="roman">CASE II.</hi>
              <lb/>Taken in Sept. <hi rend="roman">1783,</hi> from Capt. <hi rend="roman">L.</hi> of
              <lb/>the Company's Service. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Captain</hi> L. a ſlender young man, of <lb/>about
              twenty-eight years of age, told me <lb/>that, for the two firſt years after his <w
                part="I">ar-</w><lb/><w part="F">rival</w> in India, he laboured under a <w part="I"
                >dy-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſentery</w>, which made his life be deſpaired <lb/>of,
              until he fell under the care of a <w part="I">ſur-</w><lb/><w part="F">geon</w> who
              gave him mercury. This <w part="I">me-</w><pb xml:id="page_37" n="35"/><lb/><w
                part="F">dicine</w> relieved him ſo much that he <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">tinued</w> to take it in conſiderable quantities, <lb/>but all by the
              mouth, and perſiſted in its <lb/>uſe as freely as the gums would permit, <lb/>until
              the diſeaſe was removed. During <lb/>ten years, which was the whole time <w part="I"
                >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">tervening</w> from this courſe, he had enjoyed <lb/>good
              health; but his teeth and gums <lb/>never after recovered their natural <w part="I"
                >appear-</w><lb/><w part="F">ance</w>; and his ſaliva ſtill continued to be <lb/>too
              profuſe. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Beſides pointing out the neceſſity of <lb/>much mercury, the laſt
              caſe had <w part="I">deter-</w><lb/><w part="F">mined</w> me to examine the livers of
              all <lb/>dyſenteric patients in future. An <w part="I">oppor-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >tunity</w> of confirming the good effects <lb/>of ſuch an examination ſoon after
              preſented <lb/>itſelf in the following caſe: </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE III. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>An officer in his majeſty's ſervice, after <lb/>a campaign of
              ſixteen months, during <lb/>which he had ſuffered repeated ſickneſs, <pb
                xml:id="page_38" n="36"/><lb/>was attacked with dyſenteric ſymptoms. <lb/>Having
              uſed ſalts, fomentations, glyſters, <lb/>opium, &amp;c. for eight days, without any
              <lb/>effect, his caſe was thought to be mortal. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>I then ſaw him; and, on examination, <lb/>found the right lobe of
              his liver evidently <lb/>diſeaſed. He was immediately put upon a <lb/>courſe of
              mercurial frictions, which, in <lb/>an hour's time, afforded him more relief <lb/>than
              he had experienced from the firſt <lb/>attack. The frictions were ſucceſſfully
              <lb/>continued; but the exhibition of a few <lb/>grains of calomel, after the ninth
              friction, <lb/>affected the mouth ſo ſuddenly, and ſo <lb/>violently, as to render the
              continuance of <lb/>them impracticable. The dyſenteric <w part="I">ſymp-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">toms</w> diſappeared, but his mouth remained <lb/>for ſeveral days very
              troubleſome. He <lb/>was ſent to the Daniſh ſettlement on the <lb/>coaſt for the
              reeſtabliſhment of his health. <lb/>His mouth was ſcarce well, when he was <lb/>as
              ſeverely attacked with the flux, and a <lb/>pain of the left lobe of the liver. </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_39" n="37"/>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>On the idea that this pain was a ſpaſm <lb/>of the colon,
              fomentations, glyſters, opium, <lb/>and evacuations, were again put in <w part="I"
                >prac-</w><lb/><w part="F">tice</w>. But the patient, finding all to no
              <lb/>purpoſe, determined on having recourſe <lb/>to friction, though contrary to the
              advice <lb/>of all his medical attendants. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>This expedient again afforded him <lb/>ſpeedy relief; and he was
              reſtored to <lb/>health by uſing it as freely as his mouth <lb/>would permit. He ever
              after enjoyed <lb/>good health in India, and is now in <w part="I">Ire-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">land</w>, a living witneſs to his caſe. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The neceſſity which the patient found <lb/>of having recourſe to
              theſe frictions, with <lb/>the great benefit he experienced from <lb/>them, and the
              ſudden ſoreneſs of the <lb/>gums induced by the calomel; all theſe <lb/>circumſtances
              furniſhed me with the firſt <lb/>ſuſpicion of the bad conſequences of giving <lb/>the
              mercury by the mouth. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The ſucceſs of this gentleman's <w part="I">ſe-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">cond</w> recourſe to the frictions came to <pb xml:id="page_40" n="38"
              /><lb/>my knowledge juſt time enough to <w part="I">en-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >courage</w> me to return and adhere to them <lb/>in the following caſe: </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE IV. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>An officer in his majeſty's ſervice, after <lb/>the ſiege of
              Cuddalore, laboured under a <lb/>chronic complaint of the liver, and <w part="I"
                >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tinued</w> in the field until he was attacked <lb/>with
              dyſentery. Fourteen drachms of <lb/>mercurial ointment, applied in the <w part="I"
                >quan-</w><lb/><w part="F">tity</w> of two drachms a day, removed the
              <lb/>dyſentery, without affecting the gums. In <lb/>about two months the dyſentery
              recurred, <lb/>and was again relieved by frictions, <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">tinued</w> during another week. At the <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >tance</w> of ſix or eight days from this period <lb/>he was ſuddenly attacked with
              what he <lb/>thought to be only a painful crick of the <lb/>left ſide of the neck. For
              this complaint <lb/>recourſe was had to topical applications of <lb/>opium and
              volatile liniment, hot flannels, <lb/>and fotuſes, but without any effect; and,
              <lb/>about two hours after, a pain, not leſs <pb xml:id="page_41" n="39"
              /><lb/>violent, was felt about the left <w part="I">hypo-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >chondre</w>, and extended over the ſtomach. <lb/>As the patient had uſed ſuch a
              quantity <lb/>of mercury, recourſe was had to <w part="I">veneſec-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >tion</w>; which rendered the pulſe more <w part="I">fre-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >quent</w>, and the pain more inſuportable. <lb/>The dyſenteric ſymptoms having
              recurred, <lb/>a ſmall doſe of ſalts was now tried, <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">out</w> any benefit. Mercury was again <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >ſolved</w> on, and rubbed in, as before, for <lb/>nine days; but neither afforded
              any relief, <lb/>nor ſo much as affected the gums. In <lb/>compliance with the
              patient's anxiety, <lb/>mercury was exhibited by the mouth. A <lb/>few doſes of
              calomel produced ulcerations <lb/>of the gums, but no ſpongineſs, or <w part="I"
                >re-</w><lb/><w part="F">miſſion</w> of ſymptoms. The mercury was <lb/>diſcontinued
              on account of theſe <w part="I">ulcer-</w><lb/><w part="F">ations</w> about the gums.
              The pain <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">coming</w> more violent, and the quantity
              of <lb/>mercury already uſed being very great, the <lb/>patient began to loſe all
              faith in that <w part="I">me-</w><lb/><w part="F">dicine</w>. Muſtard-plaſters to the
              pained <lb/>part were then tried; but the irritation <lb/>which they excited could not
              be long <pb xml:id="page_42" n="40"/><lb/>endured, and they afforded no relief.
              <lb/>Frictions with hot camphorated oil were <lb/>alſo tried to no purpoſe. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Being now informed of the ſucceſs <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">tending</w> the third caſe, I determined, <lb/>notwithſtanding the
              exhauſted ſtate of the <lb/>patient, to puſh the mercury by the ſkin <lb/>only, until
              the gums ſhould become <w part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F">fected</w>. Half an ounce
              of the ſtrongeſt <lb/>mercurial ointment was rubbed in about <lb/>the back, abdomen,
              and thighs. Before <lb/>this friction was completely finiſhed, the <lb/>patient became
              ſo much relieved, as to be <lb/>able to lie at his full length, in any <w part="I"
                >ſitu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ation</w> but on the diſeaſed ſide. A drachm <lb/>of the
              ointment was continued to be <lb/>rubbed in, night and morning, with <w part="I"
                >evi-</w><lb/><w part="F">dent</w> good effect; and, after the friction <lb/>had
              been repeated twelve times, the gums <lb/>became uniformly ſpongy. From that <lb/>time
              the pain ceaſed, the pulſe became <lb/>ſofter and ſlower, and the patient ſpeedily
              <lb/>returned to a better ſtate of health than <lb/>he had ever before enjoyed in
              India. He <pb xml:id="page_43" n="41"/><lb/>remained more than a year after in the <w
                part="I">dif-</w><lb/><w part="F">ferent</w> parts of that country, without <w
                part="I">ſuf-</w><lb/><w part="F">fering</w> any kind of relapſe. His gums
              <lb/>remained not very long ſpongy, nor did his <lb/>ſaliva continue to flow ſo
              profuſely as in <lb/>thoſe caſes where the mercury had been <lb/>taken by the mouth.
              He is now in <w part="I">Eu-</w><lb/><w part="F">rope</w>, and ſuffers no
              inconvenience from <lb/>change of climate </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>This, and the preceding caſe, impreſſed <lb/>me with an opinion
              that there was an <w part="I">ab-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſolute</w> neceſſity to avoid
              exhibiting <w part="I">mer-</w><lb/><w part="F">cury</w> by the mouth when the patient
              was <lb/>put under a courſe of frictions. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>In order to try whether this opinion <lb/>was well-founded, I
              procured a large <lb/>quantity of good mercurial ointment, and <lb/>proceeded to the
              cure of a variety of caſes <lb/>with the frictions, unaſſiſted by any other
              <lb/>remedy. I now obſerved, that, by this <lb/>method, the gums were much ſlower in
              <lb/>being affected; but, when they were <w part="I">af-</w><pb xml:id="page_44"
                n="42"/><lb/><w part="F">fected</w>, the diſeaſe appeared to be entirely
              <lb/>removed. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Sometimes the patient was relieved two <lb/>or three days before
              the gums were <w part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F">fected</w>. But, more frequently,
              relief was <lb/>not to be expected till a few hours before <lb/>the gums became
              ſpongy; from which <lb/>time the ſecretions, the appetite, the pulſe, <lb/>the
              ſpirits, and the complexion, very <lb/>ſpeedily became natural. I alſo obſerved,
              <lb/>that, where the mercury was given by the <lb/>ſtomach, the gums, after becoming
              ſore, <lb/>remained hard and of a natural colour in <lb/>many places. In other parts
              there were <lb/>troubleſome ulcerations, attended with a <lb/>copious ſpitting.
              Whereas, from <w part="I">mercu-</w><lb/><w part="F">rial</w> frictions alone,
              ulcerations never came <lb/>on ſuddenly, but were always preceded by <lb/>ſuch a
              regular ſwelling and change of <w part="I">co-</w><lb/><w part="F">lour</w> in the
              gums, as to render their <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">vention</w> extremely
              eaſy. I continued in <lb/>India nine months after I had adopted <lb/>this practice.
              All the confirmed liver <lb/>caſes (amounting to an immenſe number) <pb
                xml:id="page_45" n="43"/><lb/>which from that time came under my <lb/>care, were, by
              this method, cured without <lb/>ſuppurations; nor was there any relapſe, <lb/>ſo far
              as I could learn, during my <w part="I">ſubſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">quent</w> reſidence
              in the country. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>I ſhall add the following caſe to thoſe I <lb/>have already given.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CASE V. </head>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Lieutenant C. of the Company's ſervice, <lb/>about twenty-five
              years of age, had <w part="I">fre-</w><lb/><w part="F">quently</w>, after his arrival,
              which was five <lb/>years before, in India, laboured under <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">peated</w> attacks of the Hepatitis. Mercurial <lb/>frictions and pills had
              conſtantly relieved <lb/>him, until a few weeks before I ſaw him: <lb/>he had then
              gone through his uſual courſe <lb/>with but little relief, and his mouth had
              <lb/>become too ſore to perſiſt in any farther <lb/>trial of it. As no medical perſon
              was <lb/>near him, he had recourſe to repeated <lb/>doſes of ſalts. His mouth was
              relieved <pb xml:id="page_46" n="44"/><lb/>by the ſalts, but his diſeaſe continued.
              <lb/>He came under my care about a week <lb/>after, and was immediately put upon the
              <lb/>frictions, with one drachm of mercurial, <lb/>ointment night and morning. Near
              three <lb/>ounces of ointment were uſed in this <w part="I">man-</w><lb/><w part="F"
                >ner</w> before the gums were affected; they <lb/>then began to ſwell and aſſume a
              deep red <lb/>colour. From this time he enjoyed a total <lb/>ceſſation of pain, and
              recovered a better <lb/>ſtate of health than he had ever before <w part="I"
                >ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">perienced</w> in that country. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>After theſe caſes had happened our <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">giment</w> was carried round to Bengal in <lb/>the Vanſittart Engliſh
              Indiaman. This <lb/>ſhip had juſt returned from Batavia; and <lb/>many of her crew
              were then labouring <lb/>under chronic dyſenteries contracted in <lb/>that ſettlement.
              I was asked, by the <w part="I">ſur-</w><lb/><w part="F">geon</w> of the ſhip, to ſee
              one of the worſt <lb/>caſes. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>From what I had then learned of the <lb/>diſeaſes of the country,
              I pronounced the <pb xml:id="page_47" n="45"/><lb/>caſe to be a Hepatitis. The ſurgeon
              <lb/>could hardly be perſuaded of this, as the <lb/>man had never complained of pain
              of the <lb/>ſhoulder or ſide, nor been ſeized either <lb/>with vomitings or hiccups.
              But in two <lb/>days a large tumor in the region of the <lb/>right lobe of the liver
              confirmed my <w part="I">aſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſertion</w>. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The tumor was opened, and about <lb/>three Engliſh pints of matter
              inſtantly <lb/>diſcharged from the liver. The man died <lb/>a few days after the
              operation. The reſt <lb/>of the ſick crew were recovered by <w part="I"
                >treat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> their caſes as diſeaſed livers. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>After relating ſo many inſtances of the <lb/>good effefts of
              mercury, it may be expected <lb/>that I ſhould offer ſome opinion with <w part="I"
                >re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſpect</w> to its mode of operation. On this <lb/>ſubject I
              ſhall be extremely brief. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>As there are no ſtimuli, that I know <lb/>of, which can ſupport,
              for ſo great a <lb/>length of time, an increaſed action of the <pb xml:id="page_48"
                n="46"/><lb/>vaſcular ſyſtem, I preſume this muſt be <lb/>the reaſon why mercury has
              the advantage <lb/>over all other medicines of that claſs, and <lb/>may truly be ſaid
              to poſſeſs very peculiar <lb/>powers. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>But mercury, given by the ſtomach, <lb/>never can be made to keep
              up that <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tinued</w> action, ſo neceſſary for the
              cure of <lb/>this, and perhaps of every other diſeaſe, <lb/>which has been ſlow in its
              progreſs. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Notwithſtanding all I have ſaid of this <lb/>moſt excellent,
              though in the end <w part="I">debili-</w><lb/><w part="F">tating</w> medicine, I am of
              opinion that it <lb/>ſhould never be uſed too ſoon; and that, <lb/>when adopted, it
              ought to be perſiſted in <lb/>regularly. The uſe of ſmall doſes of <w part="I"
                >ca-</w><lb/><w part="F">lomel</w>, as a prophilactic, I am convinced <lb/>has often
              been the means of producing <lb/>this diſeaſe. I would, therefore, adviſe no
              <lb/>perſon to have recourſe to mercury as a <lb/>preventive, nor ever to begin with
              it in <lb/>the firſt ſtage of the diſeaſe; as, during <lb/>that period, a change of
              ſituation and diet <pb xml:id="page_49" n="47"/><lb/>may prove ſufficient to effect
              the cure. <lb/>But, in the ſecond ſtage, the frictions <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">pear</w> to be not only the moſt expeditious, as <lb/>well as the moſt
              ſucceſſful, method of <lb/>treatment. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>It may be proper to obſerve that, <w part="I">dur-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">ing</w> the mercurial courſe, acids ſhould be <lb/>avoided; and animal food
              generally proves <lb/>the beſt kind of diet. Not leſs than a <lb/>drachm of the
              ſtrongeſt ointment ſhould <lb/>be thoroughly rubbed in, either upon the <lb/>ſide, or
              ſome other extenſive ſurface, every <lb/>night and morning. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The mercurial frictions, having relieved <lb/>or entirely removed
              the pain, ought not to <lb/>be diſcontinued until the gums become <lb/>affected;
              otherwiſe the patient is <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſed</w> to a relapſe,
              with a greater tendency <lb/>to ſuppuration. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Sometimes, towards the concluſion of <lb/>the mercurial courſe,
              viz. about the time <lb/>the gums become affected, a kind of <w part="I"
                >eri-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſipilatous</w> eruption breaks out all over the <pb
                xml:id="page_50" n="48"/><lb/>body: but, by a diſcontinuance of the <lb/>mercury,
              this may be ſoon removed. In <lb/>other caſes it was obſerved that the ſtools
              <lb/>firſt becoming copious after the courſe, <lb/>were ſometimes mixed with a great
                <w part="I">quan-</w><lb/><w part="F">tity</w> of gelatinous matter, which had <w
                part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F">thing</w> the appearance of hydatids. As this
              <lb/>ſymptom ſeldom appeared till health was <lb/>returning, no variation of treatment
                <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">came</w> neceſſary. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>Slight pains of the muſcles of the arms, <lb/>thighs, ſhoulders,
              and ſide, remain for <lb/>ſome time after the uſe of mercury; but <lb/>none of them
              are attended with any <w part="I">catch-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> in reſpiration,
              as in the Hepatitis, and <lb/>deſerve no particular attention. For ſome <lb/>time
              after the mercurial courſe, however, <lb/>the great increaſe of perſpiration,
              eſpecially <lb/>about the abdomen, renders it abſolutely <lb/>neceſſary to keep that
              part well covered; <lb/>otherwiſe the hot winds, which blow with <lb/>ſo much force in
              that country, are apt to <lb/>produce violent ſpaſmodic pains of the <lb/>bowels. </p>
            <pb xml:id="page_51" n="49"/>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The appetite becomes exceedingly keen <lb/>after the mercurial
              courſe, and renders the <lb/>greateſt precautions neceſſary that the <w part="I"
                >ſto-</w><lb/><w part="F">mach</w> be not overcharged. The dinner <lb/>ſhould be
              made of one good diſh of roaſt <lb/>meat, or cury, without greaſe, with but a
              <lb/>very moderate uſe of vegetables or fruit. <lb/>Two or three glaſſes of wine after
              dinner <lb/>are as much as ought to be indulged in <lb/>for ſome time. Drinking of
              grog, or any <lb/>ſpirituous liquors, ſhould not be uſed; <lb/>and all warm weak
              drinks ought likewiſe <lb/>to be avoided. As the few glaſſes of wine <lb/>after dinner
              are preſcribed with the view <lb/>of promoting digeſtion, no other liquid <lb/>ought
              to be taken for at leaſt an hour after, <lb/>that the power of the wine may not be
              <lb/>weakened. </p>
            <p rend="indent"><lb/>The mercurial courſe, not unfrequently, <lb/>produces ſo great a
              ſecretion of bile as to <lb/>render the uſe of vegetables and acids <lb/>almoſt, if
              not totally, impracticable. This <lb/>effect ſometimes ariſes to what is called in
              <lb/>India a mercurial flux; and may be then <pb xml:id="page_52" n="50"
              /><lb/>removed, by abſtaining from all acids and <lb/>vegetables and adhering a few
              days entirely <lb/>to a diet of animal food, with the uſe of <lb/>ſpirits and water,
              or Madeira wine. A <lb/>ſimilar flux happens on firſt arriving in <lb/>warm climates,
              which yields to the ſame <lb/>method of cure, being only a preternatural
              <lb/>increaſed ſecretion of bile, occaſioned by <lb/>the abuſe of acids, fruits, or
              vegetables. <lb/>After the Hepatitis is removed, the <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">ſtant</w>, but cautious, uſe of acids, in hot <lb/>climates, proves the
              beſt means of <w part="I">prevent-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> a relapſe. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_53" n="51"/>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>ON <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">SPASMODIC AFFECTIONS</hi>
          <lb/>IN <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">INDIA</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">S</hi>PASMS were the firſt diſeaſes which
          <lb/>appeared amongſt the troops who arrived <lb/>at Madras in October 1782, under the
          <lb/>command of Major General Sir John <w part="I">Bur-</w><lb/><w part="F">goyne</w>.
          More than fifty of theſe freſh <lb/>men were killed by them within the firſt <lb/>three
          days after they were landed in that <lb/>country, and in leſs than a month from <lb/>that
          time, upwards of a thouſand had <w part="I">ſuf-</w><lb/><w part="F">fered</w> from
          attacks of theſe complaints. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The teſtanus or ſpaſm is diſtinguiſhed <lb/>by medical writers into
          various ſpecies, <pb xml:id="page_54" n="52"/><lb/>according either to the particular
          parts <lb/>affected with contraction, or the duration <lb/>of the diſeaſe. But as all
          theſe different <lb/>appearances (at leaſt when not ariſing <lb/>from wounds) ſeem to
          proceed from the <lb/>ſame cauſes, to yield to the ſame method <lb/>of cure, and to afford
          nothing particular <lb/>with reſpeſt to the prognoſis of the diſeaſe, <lb/>I ſhall,
          without ſpecifying their <w part="I">diſtinc-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w>, deſcribe the
          various phænomena, as <lb/>generally obſerved in India. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I muſt, however, previouſly <w part="I">acknow-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ledge</w>, that though I have ſeen many <lb/>wounds in India, I never ſaw a wounded
          <lb/>perſon affected with ſpaſms, except in the <lb/>agonies of death; and therefore I can
          by <lb/>no means affirm that the following <w part="I">obſer-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >vations</w> are equally applicable to thoſe <w part="I">te-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tanic</w> affections, which are deſcribed by <lb/>authors as ariſing from wounds;
          becauſe <lb/>ſuch caſes, from their peculiar exciting <lb/>cauſes, muſt be ſtill more
          untraceable and <lb/>hazardous. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_55" n="53"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The ſymptoms which commonly firſt <lb/>preſented themſelves were
          coldneſs of <lb/>the ſurface of the body, eſpecially of the <lb/>hands; feebleneſs of the
          pulſe, and <w part="I">ſpaſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">modic</w> contractions of the lower <w
            part="I">extre-</w><lb/><w part="F">meties</w>, ſoon extending to the muſcles <lb/>of
          the abdomen, diaphragm, and ribs. <lb/>As the ſpaſms advanced, the muſcles might <lb/>be
          ſeen to aſſume the rigidity of cartilages; <lb/>ſometimes cauſing the body to remain <w
            part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F">moveably</w> extended; ſometimes bending <lb/>the trunk
          through its whole length, <w part="I">an-</w><lb/><w part="F">teriorly</w>; and ſometimes,
          though ſeldomer, <lb/>backwards. The parts in which the <lb/>ſpaſms began generally
          remained rigid; <lb/>but thoſe which were ſubſequently ſeized <lb/>with them, had
          momentary intermiſſions <lb/>of the contractions; the only intervals <lb/>of relief
          experienced by the patient from <lb/>the moſt tormenting pains. The hands <lb/>and feet
          then generally became ſodden, <lb/>with cold ſweats; the nails livid, the pulſe <lb/>more
          feeble and frequent, and the breath <pb xml:id="page_56" n="54"/><lb/>ſo condenſed as to
          be both ſeen and felt, <lb/>iſſuing in a cold ſtream at a conſiderable <lb/>diſtance. The
          thirſt was inſatiable; the <lb/>tongue whitiſh, but never dry; vomitings <lb/>became
          almoſt inceſſant; the ſpaſms, cold <lb/>ſweats, and thirſt, increaſed with the <w part="I"
            >vo-</w><lb/><w part="F">mitings</w>; which laſt, if not checked, ſoon <lb/>terminated
          the exiſtence of the patient. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In this manner, moſt commonly, was <lb/>the ſucceſſion of phaenomena;
          but often <lb/>they were ſo rapid in their attack, that <lb/>they ſeemed to ſeize the
          patient all in <lb/>conjunction inſtantaneouſly. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In ſome few, the extremities remained <lb/>warm; in others alſo the
          ſpaſms were <lb/>only clonic or convulſive. Some died <lb/>in the firſt hour of the
          attack; others <lb/>lived a day or two with remiſſions; when <lb/>they died either of
          univerſal ſpaſms, or an <lb/>apoplexy. On the diſſection of the bodies <lb/>after death,
          it appeared that no injury <pb xml:id="page_57" n="55"/><lb/>had been ſuſtained by the
          brain, liver, <lb/>gall, bladder, ſtomach, or heart. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>All who recovered of this diſeaſe were <lb/>obſerved to have very
          languid ſecretions <lb/>for a conſiderable time after, and frequently <lb/>carbuncles,
          which would ſometimes yield <lb/>neither to bark, opium, nor wine. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>At a general meeting of the faculty at <lb/>Madras, this diſeaſe was
          unanimouſly <lb/>judged to proceed from the four <w part="I">follow-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ing</w> cauſes, viz. </p>
        <lg>
          <lb/>
          <l>Damps from the earth, </l>
          <lb/>
          <l>The not uſing of capſicum, </l>
          <lb/>
          <l>Bad arrack, </l>
          <lb/>
          <l>A coffee made of ſtramonium. </l>

        </lg>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The facts adduced in ſupport of the <lb/>firſt of theſe were, that
          fowls put into <lb/>coops at night, in that ſeaſon of the year, <lb/>and on the ſame ſoil
          that the men ſlept, <lb/>were always found dead the next morning, <lb/>if the coop was not
          placed at a certain <pb xml:id="page_58" n="56"/><lb/>height above the ſurface of the
          earth. <lb/>And as a ſufficient number of cotts had <lb/>nor been previouſly procured for
          all the <lb/>troops, many of them were obliged to <lb/>ſleep on the ground. </p>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="align-center"><lb/>CAPSICUM. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>As the men had not then learned to eat <lb/>capſicum with their
            meat, according to <lb/>the general practice of Aſia, this <w part="I"
              >circum-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtance</w> was conſidered as a prediſponent <lb/>cauſe of
            the diſeaſe. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>A bad kind of arrack, made from ſome <lb/>of the moſt intoxicating
            vegetables, is often <lb/>privately ſold amongſt the ſoldiery, and <lb/>was therefore
            conſidered as one probable <lb/>cauſe of the diſeaſe. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>In reſpect of the coffee made of <w part="I">ſtramo-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">nium</w>, which the natives both ſell and <lb/>drink themſelves, as the
            cheapeſt of all <lb/>modes of intoxication, it muſt be obſerved <pb xml:id="page_59"
              n="57"/><lb/>that there were no proofs of any of the <lb/>men having drank of this
            coffee. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Towards aſcertaining the moſt general <lb/>exciting cauſe of this
            diſeaſe, I ſhall <w part="I">men-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> the following facts. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Drunkenneſs was very ſeverely puniſhed <lb/>in all the newly arrived
            regiments; and <lb/>to prevent detection the men, after the <lb/>rolls were called in
            the evening, uſed to <lb/>drink ſeven or eight large drams, and go <lb/>to bed;
            immediately on awakening, their <lb/>thirſt was uſually ſo great, that they drank
            <lb/>three or four pints of cold water, which <lb/>ſeldom failed to produce the diſeaſe.
            The <lb/>firſt circumſtance which led me to ſuſpect <lb/>this, and which was afterwards
            confirmed <lb/>by the confeſſions of ſeveral of the men <lb/>who recovered, was my
            obſerving that <lb/>all the patients in the worſt caſes were <lb/>brought into the
            hoſpital about four o'clock <lb/>in the morning. They were attacked <lb/>with the
            vomitings, and other ſymptoms, <pb xml:id="page_60" n="58"/><lb/>almoſt immediately
            after they had drank <lb/>the cold water. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>A muſſulman, in the ſouthern parts <lb/>of the Tanjore country,
            having uſed the <lb/>cold bath immediately after coition, was <lb/>ſiezed with an
            univerſal ſpaſm, and died <lb/>in leſs than half an hour. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>An officer, after being twelve months <lb/>in India, became my
            patient, for a large <lb/>venereal ulcer, which laid bare a <w part="I"
              >conſider-</w><lb/><w part="F">able</w> portion of the urethra. After the <lb/>ulcer
            was perfectly healed, and his <w part="I">mercu-</w><lb/><w part="F">rial</w> courſe
            finiſhed, he expoſed himſelf <lb/>in his ſleep to a ſtream of air. On waking <lb/>the
            next morning he found his jaw ſtiff, <lb/>but as the day became hot the ſtiffneſs
            <lb/>went off. On mentioning it to me, he <lb/>was deſired to ſleep warmer for the
            future, <lb/>on the preſumption that it was occaſioned <lb/>by an increaſe of
            perſpiration, and <w part="I">irrita-</w><lb/><w part="F">bility</w> from the uſe of
            mercury. He felt <lb/>no returns of his complaint until near a <pb xml:id="page_61"
              n="59"/><lb/>fortnight after, when he was induced by <lb/>the cloſeneſs and heat,
            during the firſt part <lb/>of the night, again to ſet open the doors <lb/>and windows.
            The winds blowing very <lb/>ſtrong towards the morning awaked him, <lb/>when he found
            himſelf affected with the <lb/>moſt dreadful ſpaſms in every part of <lb/>his body,
            attended with cold ſweats, <w part="I">blind-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w>, and
            ſtiffneſs of his extremeties; all <lb/>which ſymptoms could not be removed <lb/>for the
            ſpace of ſixteen hours. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>This, and the caſe of an officer of the <lb/>Company's ſervice, who,
            immediately after <lb/>the fatigue of a very hot day's march, <lb/>plunged himſelf into
            a tank of cold water, <lb/>are the only two caſes of ſpaſms I ever <lb/>ſaw amongſt
              officers<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* By officers, however, this
              diſeaſe is often <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">founded</w> with the <hi
                rend="italic">coup de ſoliel,</hi> or ſun ſtroke, becauſe <lb/>each, if not attended
              to, very ſpeedily puts a period <lb/>to life. In the firſt or mildeſt attacks of the
              ſun <lb/>ſtroke, it exhibits the phaenomena of a ſynocha; in <lb/>the ſecond, thoſe of
              phrenitis; and in the laſt ſtage, <lb/>ſomnolency, cold ſweats, and death ſometimes,
                <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceded</w> by a few convulſive motions. </note>;
            though above three <pb xml:id="page_62" n="60"/><lb/>hundred of the 101ſt private
            ſoldiers were <lb/>attacked with them on the firſt month of <lb/>their arrival at
              Madras<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Officers, however, as well as
              private men, have <lb/>been ſuddenly killed in that country by ſpaſms, <w part="I"
                >occa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſioned</w> by expoſing themſelves to the winds, with
              nothing <lb/>on but their ſhirts, when wet with perſpiration. This <lb/>will be very
              eaſily conceived by thoſe who are <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">quainted</w>
              with the common method of cooling liquor <lb/>in India, by keeping the ſides of the
              bottles moiſt <lb/>with wet cloths, and expoſed to the evaporating <w part="I"
                >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">fluence</w> of the winds. </note>. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>From all theſe circumſtances I am <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">duced</w> to agree with thoſe authors who <lb/>have conſidered cold<note
              place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† By this expreſſion I mean relative, not
              abſolute <lb/>cold. I ſh<unclear>#</unclear>uld not have thought this explanation <w
                part="I">neceſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſary</w>, as poſitive cold is now ſcarcely by
              any admitted <lb/>in this country, had I not been informed that an <w part="I"
                >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">genious</w> gentleman recommends an ice-houſe for the
              <lb/>cure of <unclear>##</unclear>is diſeaſe, becauſe it is an endemic of the
              <lb/>torrid climates. A gentleman who arrived in India <lb/>with a ſimilar ſpeculative
              opinion, enjoined the uſe <lb/>of the cold bath in a number of tetanic caſes; and
              <lb/>had the mortification to find that, in all, he <w part="I">accele-</w><lb/><w
                part="F">rated</w> the death of the patients ſo quickly, that ſcarce <lb/>any of
              them could ſurvive two minutes alter coming <lb/>out of the bath. The irritability of
              the body is very <lb/>ſenſibly increaſed on the firſt expoſure to the <w part="I"
                >influ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ence</w> of a hot climate. Until that increaſed <w
                part="I">irri-</w><lb/><w part="F">tability</w> be conſiderably diminiſhed, a perſon
              is <w part="I">unſea-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſoned</w>, and remains too weak to bear with
              ſafety the <lb/>meridian heat, or evening dew; neither can he <lb/>ſafely take
              medicines in equal doſes with thoſe who <lb/>are ſeaſoned to a hot climate. </note> as
            the moſt <w part="I">gene-</w><lb/><w part="F">ral</w> exciting cauſe of this diſeaſe. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_63" n="61"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The prognoſis of this diſeaſe is formed <lb/>with greater certainty
            from the warmth <lb/>or coldneſs of the extremeties, than from <lb/>either the
            univerſality of the ſpaſms, or <lb/>the frequency or ſteadineſs of the pulſe. <lb/>Thus
            if the ſpaſms were ever ſo general, <lb/>with warmth of the extremeties, there was
            <lb/>no immediate danger: on the contrary, if <lb/>the ſpaſm was ever ſo trifling, with
              <w part="I">cold-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w>, there was every danger to be feared. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The warm bath, and wrapping up in <lb/>blankets, with the uſe of
            opium, were <lb/>what I at firſt chiefly depended upon in the <lb/>cure of this diſeaſe.
            But what the faculty <pb xml:id="page_64" n="62"/><lb/>there relied on moſt, was the
            liberal uſe <lb/>of hot Madeira wine. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>If one bottle ſhould be thrown up, as <lb/>faſt as it was drank,
            they recommended <lb/>a ſecond and third bottle. But this <lb/>practice is not very
            ſucceſſful: for; in <lb/>the worſt caſes, the reachings are the moſt <lb/>diſtreſſing
            ſymptoms; as the cold ſweats <lb/>and ſpaſms are conſtantly obſerved to <w part="I"
              >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">creaſe</w> with them. And though the thirſt <lb/>be always
            inſatiable, yet to allow no <lb/>more than half an ounce of ſome warm <lb/>liquid at a
            time, and that of the moſt <lb/>cordial kind, with thirty or forty drops <lb/>of
            laudanum, proved a more ſucceſſful <lb/>plan than indulging the patient in a full
            <lb/>draught. This cordial and laudanum I <lb/>uſed to repeat as faſt as it was thrown
            up. <lb/>But when the patient retained a doſe, I <lb/>repeated the cordial, without the
            opium, <lb/>but in the ſame ſmall quantities, and at <lb/>intervals. For a draught of
            any liquid <lb/>was ſure to make the vomitings recur, and <lb/>with them the cold
            ſweats, thirſt, and <lb/>ſpaſms. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_65" n="63"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Afterwards, being in a ſituation where <lb/>the warm bath could not
            be had recourſe <lb/>to, and being then ſatisfied by my own <lb/>obſervations, by the
            teſtimony of many <lb/>of the faculty at Madras, and by the
              <lb/>con<unclear>#</unclear>t<unclear>#</unclear>nt practice of the natives, that
            <lb/>warmth was the moſt ſucceſſful method <lb/>of combating this diſeaſe, I relied upon
            <lb/>repeated injections of warm broth, with <lb/>about thirty drops of laudanum, at the
            <lb/>ſame time adviſing the ſe of general <w part="I">fric-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >tions</w>, with hot dry flannels, and the warm <lb/>cordial draughts, with laudanum
              <w part="I">repeat-</w><lb/><w part="F">edly</w>, until the reachings had ceaſed:
            <lb/>and by theſe means I thought I ſucceeded <lb/>better than ever I had done with the
            <lb/>warm bath. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>For thoſe caſes which were relieved by <lb/>the warm bath oftener
            relapſed, than thoſe <lb/>relieved by the injections. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The practice of the natives in this <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ſeaſe</w> is to uſe frictions, and hot dry ſand, <pb xml:id="page_66" n="64"
            /><lb/>or heat of any ſort; giving likewiſe drams, <lb/>or hot pepper water, to thoſe
            whoſe caſts <lb/>will not admit of the drinking of ſpirits. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>A Dutch phyſician in that country is <lb/>ſaid to have been always
            very ſucceſſful in <lb/>this diſeaſe, by treating it in the following <lb/>manner: to
            ſtrip the patient, lay him on <lb/>a cane couch, under which were placed <lb/>ſtoves of
            fire; to cover the trunk and <lb/>limbs from the air with a blanket, ſo <w part="I"
              >diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſed</w> that the heat from the ſtoves ſhould <lb/>be
            confined about the body; to have <w part="I">fric-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w> at the
            ſame time uſed under the <lb/>blankets, with warm flannel<note place="bottom" n="*"
              rend="size(0.5)">* A to giving opium in a ſolid form, either in this <lb/>diſeaſe or
              cholera morbus, any one muſt ſee the <w part="I">im-</w><lb/><w part="F">propriety</w>
              of it, who conſiders how unfit the ſtomach <lb/>in ſuch caſes is to perform any part
              of its natural <lb/>functions. </note>, and to <lb/>exhibit a doſe of opium in
            ſolution after <lb/>every vomiting. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>As I never had any caſes of ſpaſms after <lb/>learning this method,
            I never had an <w part="I">op-</w><lb/><w part="F">portunity</w> of giving it a trial. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_67" n="65"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>With regard to the accounts related by <lb/>ſome authors of the
            ſucceſſful uſe of <w part="I">mer-</w><lb/><w part="F">curial</w> frictions,
            rubifacients, or of bliſters, <lb/>in the cure of this diſeaſe, I have only to
            <lb/>obſerve, that however univerſal the ſpaſms <lb/>were in all the caſes I have ſeen,
            I never <lb/>ſaw that caſe prove mortal where there <lb/>was ſufficient warmth upon the
            ſurface <lb/>for the ſkin to abſorb mercury, or to be <lb/>made red by bliſters or other
            ſtimulating <lb/>applications. </p>
          <trailer rend="align-center"><lb/>THE END. </trailer>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
