<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Goldson: An Extraordinary Case of Lacerated Vagina</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>William Goldson</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">An extraordinary case of lacerated vagina, at the full period of
              gestation. With observations, tending to show that many cases related as ruptures of
              the uterus, have been lacerations of the vagina.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T88982</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T88982"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Murray, No. 32, Fleet-Street; and C. Elliot,
                  Edinburgh, M,DCC,LXXXVII.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1787</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="6"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="77"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3309269440</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K072268.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: midwifery"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <head rend="align-center size(1.7)"><lb/>INTRODUCTION. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">R</hi>UPTURES of the uterus have <lb/>been conſidered
          as accidents, <w part="I">mor-</w><lb/><w part="F">tal</w>, for the moſt part, in their
          nature. <lb/>When part of the child remains <hi rend="italic">in <w part="I"
              >ute-</w><lb/><w part="F">ro</w>,</hi> authors give ſome general directions <lb/>for
          delivery; but agree in its fatal <w part="I">ten-</w><lb/><w part="F">dency</w>, if the
          child has eſcaped wholly <lb/>into the cavity of the abdomen; <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſidering</w> any attempts to deliver, except <lb/>by the caeſarean operation,
          as fruitleſs. <lb/>This was the opinion of Dr. Hunter: <lb/>his high and deſerved
          reputation has <lb/>ſtampt ſuch authority upon it, that <w part="I">prac-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">titioners</w> in general give up their patient <lb/>for loſt, without
          attempting any thing <pb xml:id="page_3" n="4"/><lb/>for her relief. The cæſarian
          operation, <lb/>in this country, has been attended with <lb/>ſuch ill ſucceſs, that very
          few men are <lb/>bold enough to recommend it, <w part="I">ſuppo-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſing</w> that it would only be an addition <lb/>to the patient's ſufferings, without <w
            part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F">fording</w> any proſpect of relief. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Dr. Douglas, phyſician to the Aſylum,<lb/> ſome months ſince,
          publiſhed a caſe, <lb/>where he ſucceeded in the delivery of a <lb/>child from the cavity
          of the abdomen, <lb/>and the woman recovered; from whence <lb/>he infers, that thoſe
          accidents, which <lb/>admit the child to eſcape through a r<lb/>upture of the uterus, are
          not <w part="I">neceſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſarily</w> fatal, and that the delivery is to
          <lb/>be effected, without having recourſe <lb/>to the caeſarean operation, with more
          <lb/>eaſe than has been imagined. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The caſe, which is now ſubmitted to <lb/>the conſideration of the
          public, was a <lb/>laceration of the vagina, happening <lb/>early in parturition: the
          circumſtances <pb xml:id="page_4" n="5"/><lb/>of which having been clearly marked
          <lb/>during the life of the patient, and <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">firmed</w>
          by diſſection after her death, <lb/>throws a new light upon this part of <lb/>midwifery,
          and renders it probable that <lb/>many caſes deemed irremediable, from <lb/>being
          conſidered as ruptures of the <w part="I">ute-</w><lb/><w part="F">rus</w>, were only
          lacerations of the <w part="I">vagi-</w><lb/><w part="F">na</w>, and admitted of effectual
          aſſiſtance <lb/>from art. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>This caſe, having given riſe to many <lb/>doubts upon the ſubject of
          ruptured <lb/>uterus, induced me to enquire how far <lb/>authors in general have been
          accurate <lb/>in their obſervations. Upon examining <lb/>ſuch caſes as were in my
          poſſeſſion, I <lb/>found, that many which are related as <lb/>ruptures of the uterus, were
          in fact, <w part="I">la-</w><lb/><w part="F">cerations</w> of the vagina. Inſtances of
          <lb/>which I ſhall give in caſes from Vander <lb/>Wiel, Bonetus, Dr. Douglas, Pouteau,
          <lb/>and others. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>From a caſe communicated to me by <lb/>a friend, I am further enabled
          to give <pb xml:id="page_5" n="6"/><lb/>ſome account of the circumſtances <w part="I"
            >at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tending</w> a laceration of the vagina, when, <lb/>the head
          being ſo low as to be wedged <lb/>in the pelvis, the child did not eſcape <lb/>into the
          cavity of the abdomen. On <lb/>examining the circumſtances of ſome <lb/>caſes deſcribed as
          proceeding from <w part="I">rup-</w><lb/><w part="F">tures</w> of the uterus, this appears
            <w part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F">times</w> to have happened without being
          <lb/>diſcovered. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The obſervations annexed, reſpecting <lb/>the circumſtances in which
          lacerations <lb/>of the vagina differ from ruptures of <lb/>the uterus; in the eſcape of
          the child <lb/>or placenta into the abdomen, and the <lb/>obſtructions to delivery; and
          the other <lb/>practical inferences drawn, are ſuch as, <lb/>I hope, will merit the
          attention of <w part="I">prac-</w><lb/><w part="F">titioners</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As Dr. Douglas's obſervations on an <lb/>extraordinary caſe of
          ruptured uterus, <lb/>is the lateſt publication on the ſubject, <lb/>I ſhall have occaſion
          to advert to it <pb xml:id="page_6" n="7"/><lb/>oftener than to any other. If it has
          <lb/>been any means of diſpelling the idea <lb/>of the impoſſibility of recovery in <w
            part="I">acci-</w><lb/><w part="F">dents</w> of this nature, which has ſo long <lb/>been
          the general received opinion, <w part="I">ſup-</w><lb/><w part="F">ported</w> by the
          higheſt authorities; I <w part="I">flat-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> myſelf, that the
          following pages will <lb/>be a further inducement to diſpel our <lb/>fears; as they tend
          to prove the great <lb/>probability there is, that the eſcape of <lb/>the child into the
          cavity of the <w part="I">abdo-</w><lb/><w part="F">men</w> happens oftener from
          lacerations <lb/>of the vagina, than from ruptures of <lb/>the uterus. </p>
        <signed rend="align-right"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Wm</hi>. GOLDSON. </signed>
        <dateline><hi rend="italic">Portſmouth Common,</hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 21, 1787. </dateline>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_7"/>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>AN <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">EXTRAORDINARY CASE </hi><lb/>OF
            <lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)"><hi>LACERATED VAGINA</hi></hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">O</hi>N Auguſt the 20th, 1786, I was <lb/>deſired by
          Mr. William Waller, <lb/>of Goſport, to viſit Mrs. Wilkins, with <lb/>my partner Mr.
          Aylward. She was a <lb/>patient of Mr. Waller's, and had been <lb/>above twenty four hours
          in labour; <lb/>after the membranes had broke, and <lb/>the os internum been conſiderably
            <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F">lated</w>, the labour pains ſuddenly went <lb/>off;
          the child's head could be no longer <lb/>felt, and very dangerous ſymptoms had <lb/>come
          on. We met there, in <w part="I">conſulta-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, his father and
          Dr. Waller. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_8" n="10"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Mrs. Wilkins was a large woman, <lb/>much uſed to laborious exerciſe,
          of a <lb/>dark complexion, about thirty-ſix years <lb/>of age, inclining to be luſty; her
            <w part="I">conſti-</w><lb/><w part="F">tution</w> was naturally ſtrong, and <w part="I"
            >general-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> healthy; ſhe was then in labour with <lb/>her
          fourth child; her former labours <lb/>had been always lingering, but was, at <lb/>each
          time, delivered of a living child, <lb/>without more than ordinary aſſiſtance. <lb/>During
          the preſent pregnancy, ſhe was <lb/>not able to move with ſo much eaſe as <lb/>with her
          former children, complaining <lb/>of much pain in the left hypogaſtrium. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>We were informed by Mr. Waller, that <lb/>he was called to her
          aſſiſtance about a <lb/>fortnight before; but finding that the <lb/>pains were ſpurious,
          he ordered her an <lb/>opiate, which gave her relief, and ſhe <lb/>continued eaſy until
          the preceding day; <lb/>when being again ſent to, about ſix <lb/>o'clock in the morning,
          he then found <lb/>her in labour; after waiting ſome time, <lb/>the pains beginning to
          encreaſe, he made <pb xml:id="page_9" n="11"/><lb/>an examination, and found that the os
          <lb/>internum was dilated to the ſize of a <lb/>crown piece. The membranes broke, <lb/>and
          the waters were evacuated. Upon a <lb/>further examination in the uſual <w part="I"
            >man-</w><lb/><w part="F">ner</w>, the head was found to preſent; but <lb/>being only
          able to reach it with the <lb/>point of his finger, he could not exactly <lb/>aſcertain
          its ſituation, in reſpect to <w part="I">ver-</w><lb/><w part="F">tex</w> or fontinel.
          Conſidering it a <w part="I">linger-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> labour, he waited for the
          efforts of <lb/>nature. The child's head advanced by <lb/>ſlow degrees; and, after ſome
          hours, <lb/>the proſpect of a more ſpeedy delivery <lb/>ſeemed to be apparent, by the
          further <lb/>dilatation of the os internum, although <lb/>the head did not appear to be
          much <lb/>engaged in the pelvis. She was, about <lb/>this time, ſeized with a cramp in her
          <lb/>left foot and leg, which afterwards <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">tended</w> to
          her belly, on the return of <lb/>every pain. While he was directing a <lb/>camphorated
          anodyne liniment, <w part="I">ano-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> ſevere pain came on, which
          cauſed <lb/>her to cry out moſt vehemently, oh the <pb xml:id="page_10" n="12"
          /><lb/>cramp, the cramp! and which, ſhe <w part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F">terwards</w>
          ſaid, ſhe believed was in her <lb/>womb: this was ſoon after followed by <lb/>a diſcharge
          of blood from the vagina, <lb/>which continued for ſome time. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Mr. Waller then obſerved that the <w part="I">la-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >bour</w> pains abated in their ſtrength, and <lb/>that they were ſucceeded by ſuch as
          are <lb/>common in colic, with peculiar <w part="I">twiſt-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> in
          her bowels. He directed an <w part="I">emol-</w><lb/><w part="F">lient</w> glyſter, which
          was repeated with <lb/>an anodyne; but not finding ſo much <lb/>relief from theſe as he
          expected, her <lb/>pulſe being full and quick, he took <lb/>away about eight ounces of
          blood from <lb/>her arm, and left her about two o'clock, <lb/>giving directions, that ſhe
          might be kept <lb/>as cool as poſſible, the weather being <lb/>very warm. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>He ſaw her again, between four and <lb/>five o'clock, and found that
          the true <lb/>labour pains had not returned; but <lb/>that, in addition to the other <w
            part="I">ſymp-</w><pb xml:id="page_11" n="13"/><lb/><w part="F">toms</w>, ſhe then
          complained of <w part="I">conſider-</w><lb/><w part="F">able</w> thirſt; had vomited
          frequently; <lb/>was very reſtleſs; in great pain when <lb/>moved, and felt a great degree
          of pain <lb/>when he put his hand upon her belly. <lb/>Upon examining the ſtate of the
          labour, <lb/>he could feel no preſentation, the child's <lb/>head having receded. In this
          ſituation, <lb/>he thought it proper to repeat the <w part="I">glyſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ter</w>, and ordered her, in the evening, <lb/>another anodyne, together with a ſaline
          <lb/>julep. With hopes that real and <w part="I">effi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cient</w> pains
          would return by the <w part="I">morn-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>, he left her. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>On viſiting her in the morning, very <lb/>early, her attendants
          informed him, that <lb/>ſhe had been very thirſty and reſtleſs all <lb/>night; her
          vomiting had been more <w part="I">ſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">vere</w>, and that ſhe was in
          great pain <lb/>when turned, complaining of a heavy <lb/>lump which ſell from ſide to
          ſide; it <lb/>did not appear from an inſpection of <lb/>the cloths, that there had been
          any fur-<lb/>ther hemorrhage; upon inquiring more par-<pb xml:id="page_12" n="14"
          /><lb/>ticularly, it could not be found that ſhe <lb/>had made any urine, except as it
          came <lb/>away involuntarily. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>On conſidering that there had been <lb/>no return of real pains, and
          that the <lb/>other ſymptoms were more urgent, he <lb/>began to think that her caſe was of
          a <lb/>more ſerious nature than he had at firſt <lb/>apprehended; he therefore thought it
          <lb/>proper, to acquaint her friends with the <lb/>opinion he entertained of the danger of
          <lb/>her ſituation, requeſting them to ſend <lb/>for ſuch other perſons of the faculty as
          <lb/>they might wiſh ſhould be conſulted. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>When we viſited her, which was <lb/>about noon, we found her extremely
          <lb/>reſtleſs, complaining of great pain <lb/>about the region of the pubis; her <lb/>face
          was covered with a cold ſweat; <lb/>her pulſe was moderately full and <w part="I"
            >ra-</w><lb/><w part="F">pid</w>; ſhe felt great anxiety about the <lb/>præcordia; her
          breathing was thick and <lb/>ſhort, with intenſe thirſt, and continual <pb
            xml:id="page_13" n="15"/><lb/>efforts to vomit. As it was obſerved <lb/>that ſhe had
          made no water for ſome <lb/>time, except what, by the urinous ſmell <lb/>of the cloths,
          appeared to have come <lb/>away involuntarily, we determined <lb/>to introduce the
          catheter; but <w part="I">no-</w><lb/><w part="F">thing</w> paſſed, except a little bloody
          <lb/>ſanies. The bleeding was repeated, <lb/>and an antiphlogiſtic treatment agreed
          <lb/>upon. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>When we conſidered her ſituation <lb/>more fully, and compared the
          ſeveral <lb/>ſymptoms, of cramp and ſucceeding <lb/>hemorrhage; the retroceſſion of the
          <lb/>child; her ſevere thirſt; vomiting and <lb/>great pain about the region of the <w
            part="I">pu-</w><lb/><w part="F">bis</w>, with the ſymptoms which occurred <lb/>in the
          caſe of ruptured uterus publiſhed <lb/>by Dr. Douglas; there was ſuch <w part="I"
            >ſimi-</w><lb/><w part="F">larity</w> between them, that we agreed in <lb/>the propriety
          of introducing the hand <lb/>for a more particular examination. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_14" n="16"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>We accordingly viſited her again <lb/>about three o'clock, and Mr.
          William <lb/>Waller proceeded to make an <w part="I">exami-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >nation</w>. There was no difficulty in <w part="I">paſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſing</w> his
          hand: upon the poſterior part <lb/>he felt a conſiderable tumor, which was <lb/>moveable,
          and which was not the child's <lb/>head: he likewiſe found his hand in <lb/>contact with
          the inteſtines; whence it <lb/>was evident that our ſuſpicions were <lb/>well grounded.
          Immediate delivery <lb/>was the only means of relief, and his <lb/>endeavours to get at
          the feet ſoon <w part="I">ſuc-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceeded</w>; they were brought into the
          <lb/>vagina, and ſecured with a nooſe; but <lb/>it required a conſiderable degree of <w
            part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">ertion</w> to diſengage the breech. After <lb/>the arms
          were brought down, the head <lb/>followed with eaſe, little or no <w part="I"
            >diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">charge</w> enſuing. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The child was large, and had been <lb/>dead, no doubt, ever ſince its
          eſcape <lb/>from the uterus. The placenta, which <pb xml:id="page_15" n="17"/><lb/>was
          likewiſe in the cavity of the <w part="I">ab-</w><lb/><w part="F">domen</w>, followed
          without any <w part="I">diffi-</w><lb/><w part="F">culty</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Not being determined as to the <w part="I">na-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ture</w> of the tumor, which Mr. Waller <lb/>felt upon the poſterior part; as the
          <lb/>woman had ſuffered ſo little in <w part="I">deli-</w><lb/><w part="F">very</w>, we
          concurred in opinion, that he <lb/>ſhould again examine the ſtate of the <lb/>parts. Upon
          introducing his hand, he <lb/>ſoon ſound that the tumor receded <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">fore</w> his fingers, and that it was the <lb/>contracted uterus. It was
          evident to <lb/>him that the uterus was not ruptured; <lb/>but that there was a laceration
          of the <lb/>vagina, at the place where it is attached <lb/>to the <hi rend="italic">cervix
            uteri,</hi> through which his <lb/>hand would paſs with eaſe into the <w part="I"
            >ca-</w><lb/><w part="F">vity</w> of the abdomen. The os internum <lb/>was ſo
          contracted, that it would not <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">mit</w> more than two
          fingers, and he was <lb/>convinced that it had not been injured. <lb/>She ſound herſelf
          conſiderably relieved <lb/>when we leſt her at four o'clock. An <pb xml:id="page_16"
            n="18"/><lb/>anodyne was directed to be taken in <lb/>the evening. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>— 21ſt.—We viſited her early in <lb/>the morning, when we found that
          her <lb/>ſpirits were good. Her attendants <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">formed</w>
          us, that ſhe had paſſed a much <lb/>better night than could have been <w part="I"
            >ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">pected</w>. She was capable of turning <lb/>without any
          inconvenience; her thirſt, <lb/>pain in the abdomen, and vomiting, <lb/>were ſtill
          violent. Anodynes, with ſalt <lb/>of wormwood and lemon juice, to be <lb/>taken during the
          efferveſcence, were <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F">rected</w> for her. She had
          frequent ſtools <lb/>with teneſmus. The nurſe was ordered <lb/>to let her drink be mint
          tea with rice <lb/>gruel. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The ſymptoms evidently ariſing from <lb/>the injury done to the
          abdominal <w part="I">viſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">cera</w>, by the child's remaining ſo long
          <lb/>among them, after its eſcape from the <lb/>uterus, induced us to entertain ſome
          <lb/>rays of hope, from the ſucceſs which <pb xml:id="page_17" n="19"/><lb/>had attended
          the caſe related by Dr. <lb/>Douglas, that ſhe might recover; but <lb/>the approach of the
          evening convinced <lb/>us that our hopes were groundleſs. <lb/>Every ſymptom was become
          more <w part="I">ur-</w><lb/><w part="F">gent</w>, with a very diſtreſſing ſenſe of
          <lb/>ſuffocation from globus hyſtericus; ſhe <lb/>had made no water, and, from the <w
            part="I">uri-</w><lb/><w part="F">nous</w> ſmell of the cloths, we could not
          <lb/>entertain the leaſt doubt but that the <lb/>bladder was ruptured, ſpecially when
          <lb/>we called to our recollection, that the <lb/>ſame had been obſerved before delivery. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In this diſtreſſing ſtate, nothing was <lb/>leſt for us to do, more
          than to alleviate <lb/>her pain, and make the ſmall remainder <lb/>of her life as eaſy as
          poſſible; for which <lb/>purpoſe, her anodyne medicines were <lb/>repeated. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>—22d.—The perſons who watched <lb/>with her during the night informed
          us, <lb/>that ſhe had been very reſtleſs; <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">plained</w>
          of great pain in her belly, with <pb xml:id="page_18" n="20"/><lb/>intenſe thirſt, and
          that ſhe had been <lb/>conſtantly vomiting. Her countenance <lb/>was greatly altered; the
          quantity of <lb/>fluid thrown up was out of all <w part="I">propor-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tion</w> to the quantity drank; the teneſmus <lb/>ſtill continued, but without any <w
            part="I">evacu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ations</w>; her anodynes were repeated, <lb/>and an
          opiate glyſter ordered to be <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">jected</w> in the
          evening. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>—23d.—We found her more <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >poſed</w>, and we underſtood ſhe had been <lb/>ſo through the greater part of the night.
          <lb/>She continued in the ſame ſtate until <lb/>about eleven o'clock before noon, when
          <lb/>ſhe died, perfectly ſenſible. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>We obtained permiſſion to open the <lb/>body the ſame evening. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The abdomen was much tumified. <lb/>Upon making a longitudinal
          inciſion <lb/>through the integuments, a quantity of <lb/>confined air ruſhed out. The <w
            part="I">perito-</w><lb/><w part="F">neum</w> was inflamed, and in ſome places
          <lb/>beginning to ſphacelate. The inteſtines <pb xml:id="page_19" n="21"/><lb/>were
          remarkably diſtended with flatus; <lb/>their external coats were tinged with <lb/>yellow,
          and inflamed through their <lb/>whole extent. The ramifications of the <lb/>veſſels
          appeared of a beautiful red, as if <lb/>they had been injected; ſome ſpots were
          <lb/>obſerved in ſeveral places beginning to <lb/>ſphacelate, and they were for the moſt
          <lb/>part connected by a ſlight adheſion to <lb/>each other. The omentum was <w part="I"
            >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tracted</w> and inflamed. There was a <w part="I"
            >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſiderable</w> quantity of bloody ſerum in <lb/>the cavity of
          the abdomen. The whole <lb/>of the viſcera had that appearance, <lb/>which has been
          generally obſerved on <lb/>diſſecting women who have died of a <lb/>puerperal fever. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The uterus and its appendages, in <lb/>ſitu, appeared perfectly ſound,
          excepting <lb/>the left ovarium, which contained about <lb/>fourteen ounces of a
          colourleſs fluid, in <lb/>a ſingle cyſt. There was no appearance <lb/>of the <hi
            rend="italic">veſica urinaria;</hi> on paſſing a <w part="I">ca-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >theter</w>, it went immediately into the <w part="I">ca-</w><pb xml:id="page_20" n="22"
            /><lb/><w part="F">vity</w> of the abdomen, confirming our <lb/>ſuſpicion that the
          bladder was ruptured. <lb/>On raiſing the uterus above the pelvis, <lb/>we were
          immediately convinced how <lb/>accurate Mr. Waller had been in the <lb/>deſcription he
          gave us, on examining <lb/>the ſtate of the parts directly after <w part="I"
            >de-</w><lb/><w part="F">livery</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The os internum and cervix uteri <lb/>were uninjured; the vagina was
          thin, <lb/>and was lacerated tranſverſely on the <lb/>ſuperior part, cloſe to its
          attachment <lb/>to the uterus: the laceration was nearly <lb/>through one half of its
          circumference, <lb/>on the fore part, but inclining to the left <lb/>ſide. The bladder,
          from its connexion <lb/>with the vagina, had ſuffered at the ſame <lb/>time, being
          ruptured through the whole <lb/>of its poſterior part, at leaſt in <w part="I"
            >propor-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> to the ſize of the laceration which <lb/>had taken
          place in the vagina; we <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerved</w> that it had
          extended to the outer <lb/>ſurface of the uterus, tearing off an <w part="I"
            >an-</w><lb/><w part="F">gular</w> piece of its peritoneal coat, about <pb
            xml:id="page_21" n="23"/><lb/>half an inch in length. The uterus was <lb/>contracted to
          the uſual ſize it is <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerved</w> to be, in ſo ſhort a
          ſpace after <lb/>delivery; its peritoneal coat near the <lb/>fundus ſhewed an appearance
          of inci-<lb/>pient mortification. The os <unclear>#####</unclear>
          <lb/>was contracted, as Mr. Walller <unclear>#####</unclear>
          <lb/>ſerved, ſo that, without di<unclear>#</unclear>i<unclear>####</unclear>
          <unclear>#####</unclear>
          <lb/>could not introduce more than two <lb/>fingers. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>As the nature of the caſe was evident, <lb/>we did not proceed further
          in the <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſection</w>, but contented ourſelves with
          <lb/>preſerving the parts. On making an <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ciſion</w>
          into the uterus, it was found, in <lb/>moſt places, to be nearly an inch thick; <lb/>its
          internal ſurface appearing in a <w part="I">heal-</w><lb/><w part="F">thy</w> ſtate, and
          contained a ſmall <w part="I">propor-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of the membrana
          decidua, which <lb/>had been left behind. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_22" n="24"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">L</hi>ACERATIONS of the vagina <lb/>have been
          mentioned by authors, <lb/>as, ſometimes, happening from <w part="I">labori-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ous</w> parturition; but I do not recollect <lb/>to have heard, or read any
          account, <lb/>where the child had eſcaped, by ſuch <lb/>means, into the cavity of the
          abdomen; <lb/>or that they have ever conceived ſuch <lb/>an accident to be probable. I
          have <w part="I">ſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">lected</w> ſome caſes, which are related as
          <lb/>ruptures of the uterus, but which are <lb/>apparently accidents of this nature.
          <lb/>Thus can be reconciled, only, by the <lb/>confuſion into which authors have <w
            part="I">fal-</w><lb/><w part="F">len</w>, in their diviſions of this viſcus. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Anatomiſts, at preſent, are pretty <lb/>nearly agreed in dividing the
          uterus <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">to</w> fundus, cervix, and os internum.
          <lb/>Suppoſing that the whole of the uterus <lb/>meaſures three inches in length, they,
            <pb xml:id="page_23" n="25"/><lb/>for the moſt part, allow the fundus to <w part="I"
            >oc-</w><lb/><w part="F">cupy</w> the ſpace of one inch and a <w part="I"
            >quar-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w>, the cervix to take up one inch and <lb/>three
          quarters, and the os internum to <lb/>project within the vagina about a <w part="I"
            >quar-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> of an inch. But, when we conſider <lb/>how
          indeterminate they have heretofore <lb/>been on this ſubject, we ſhall not be
          <lb/>ſurpriſed, on examining ſome of the <lb/>following caſes, which are related as
          <lb/>ruptures of the cervix, to find them <w part="I">la-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cerations</w> of the vagina. From the <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">current</w>
          teſtimony of writers, it is <w part="I">evi-</w><lb/><w part="F">dent</w>, that the vagina
          has been <w part="I">fre-</w><lb/><w part="F">quently</w> conſidered as the <hi
            rend="italic">collum uteri.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Columbus, in his deſcription of the <lb/>uterus, ſays, 'Colli vel
          cervicis nomine <lb/>in utero non corpus illud, quod ſupra <lb/>deſcripſimus, fed partem
          illam <w part="I">intelli-</w><lb/><w part="F">gimus</w>, in quam mentula, tanquam in
          <lb/>vaginam immittitur<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Columb. de re anat.
            xi. 16. </note>.' </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_24" n="26"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Bartholinus gives the name of <w part="I">'Col-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >lum</w> breve minus,' to that part which is <lb/>now called the cervix; 'Anguſta <w
            part="I">infe-</w><lb/><w part="F">rior</w> eſt inter os uteri et amplitudinem
          <lb/>incipientem, atque collum breve vocari <lb/>poteſt, ad differentiam <hi rend="italic"
            >veri</hi> et longioris <lb/>colli,' which he terms <q >'Collum ipſum,
            <lb/>cervix, five canalis uteri<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Bartholini
              Anatom. i. 30. </note>.'</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Deventer expreſſly takes notice of <lb/>the confuſion which attended
          this <w part="I">divi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſion</w> of preceding writers: <q 
            >'Nomen <w part="I">ta-</w><lb/><w part="F">men</w> vaginæ prefero nomini colli, quia
            <lb/>ſæpius autores, eodem utentes, vaginam <lb/>ab ipſo utero, ægre diſtinguere
              poſ-<lb/>ſunt<note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† Deventer nov. Lum. obſtetr.
              p. 23. </note>.'</q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_25" n="27"/>
        <head rend="align-center dc(2)"><lb/>CASE I. </head>

        <p rend="indent hanging italic"><lb/>A Caſe of lacerated, vagina from <hi rend="italic"><hi
              rend="sc">Van-<lb/>der Weil,</hi></hi> related, by him as a <w part="I"
            >rup-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w> of the uterus. </p>

        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> daughter of Jonas Pergo had <lb/>been delivered
          of four children, having <lb/>very difficult labours with all of them. <lb/>While pregnant
          with the fifth, ſhe <w part="I">ſuf-</w><lb/><w part="F">fered</w> a conſiderable degree
          of <w part="I">uneaſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w>; her pains were much more <w part="I"
            >ur-</w><lb/><w part="F">gent</w>, when in labour, and came on <lb/>earlier than in her
          former pregnancies, <lb/>continuing with violence until the third <lb/>day before
          delivery, when they ceaſed. <lb/>The midwife could not, by any <w part="I"
            >endea-</w><lb/><w part="F">vours</w>, deliver her. The child, which <lb/>was ſuppoſed
          to have been dead ſome <pb xml:id="page_26" n="28"/><lb/>days, and which appeared
          afterwards <lb/>to have been the caſe, from the <w part="I">ſepara-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tion</w> of the cuticle, preſented with its <lb/>hands bent behind its neck, and the
          <lb/>face obliquely upwards towards the <lb/>pubis. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The ſymptoms becoming more and <lb/>more violent, ſhe being not only
          faint and <lb/>feveriſh, with oppreſſion on the <w part="I">praecor-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >dia</w>, attended with rigors; but having <lb/>vomited up ſome green fæces, which
          <lb/>aroſe, he ſays, from the fœtus preſſing <lb/>upon the rectum, ſo that they could
          <lb/>not find their paſſage thence, Cornelius <lb/>Solingius, an experienced ſurgeon, was
          <lb/>ſent for with him to her relief. In a <lb/>ſhort time, he delivered her of a dead
          <lb/>child. As he could not eaſily bring <lb/>away the after birth, he introduced his
          <lb/>hand along the funis, but found that it <lb/>was in contact with the inteſtines,
          before <lb/>it came to the placenta; which was <lb/>ſound, ſoon after, hanging down, in
          <lb/>three parts, within the abdomen, out <pb xml:id="page_27" n="29"/><lb/>of the uterus.
          From the child having <lb/>been expelled three days, the uterus <lb/>was ſo hard and
          contracted, that, at <lb/>firſt, he ſuppoſed it to be a ſcirrhus. <lb/>He ſeparated the
          placenta from the <w part="I">u-</w><lb/><w part="F">terus</w>, to which, he ſays, it
          ſtill <w part="I">adher-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>. The cartilage, which connected
          <lb/>the bones of the pelvis, was ſoft, and <lb/>they were ſeparated from each other
          <lb/>nearly the breadth of a finger. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The woman died the ſame day, and <lb/>the body was opened on the next,
          in <lb/>the preſence of Vander Weil and his <lb/>brother. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The abdomen was much tumified. <lb/>On making an inciſion into it,
          nothing <lb/>eſcaped except a quantity of fœtid air, <lb/>and ſome coagulated blood of a
          good <lb/>colour, which came, he ſays, from the <lb/>cotyledons, or mouths of the veſſels
          of <lb/>the uterus, at the time when the <w part="I">pla-</w><lb/><w part="F">centa</w>
          was detached from it. He paſſed <lb/>his hand through the vagina, and again <pb
            xml:id="page_28" n="30"/><lb/>found himſelf in contact with the <w part="I"
            >inteſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">tines</w>, the uterus receding above the <lb/>pubis. A
          rupture was obſerved at the <lb/>inferior and poſterior part, juſt above <lb/>the os
          internum, at that place where the <lb/>common membrane from the <w part="I"
            >peritone-</w><lb/><w part="F">um</w> covers and ſurrounds the uterus, as <lb/>well as
          the rectum; through which <w part="I">rup-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w> the whole of the
          child, except the <lb/>parts which preſented, had paſſed into <lb/>the cavity of the
          abdomen. This he <lb/>aſſigns as the cauſe why the pains ceaſed, <lb/>and the mother
          became eaſier, a few <lb/>days before delivery<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)"
            >* Stalpaart Vander Wiel, obſerv. rar. med. cent. <lb/>prim. obs. lxvi. </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the examination of this caſe, I ſhall <lb/>confine my remarks to
          the delivery of <lb/>the placenta, and the appearances upon <lb/>diſſection. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>After the child was delivered, <w part="I">Solin-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >gius</w>, finding that the placenta did not <lb/>eaſily follow, introduced his hand
          along <pb xml:id="page_29" n="31"/><lb/>the funis, with an intention to extract <lb/>it,
          but found himſelf in contact with <lb/>the inteſtines, the placenta being, '<hi
            rend="italic">ex-<lb/>tra uterum,</hi>' in the cavity of the <w part="I"
            >abdo-</w><lb/><w part="F">men</w>. The uterus, from which he <w part="I"
            >ſup-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſes</w> the child to have eſcaped ſome <lb/>days before, was
          contracted, and felt ſo <lb/>hard, '<hi rend="italic">ita ut initio ſcirrhum
            crederet.</hi>' <lb/>In the next ſentence, he ſpeaks of <w part="I">ſepa-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">rating</w> the placenta from the uterus: <lb/>this cannot be reconciled with
          what he <lb/>had before related, of the placenta being <lb/>'<hi rend="italic">extra
            uterum,</hi>' otherwiſe than by <w part="I">ſup-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſing</w> that the
          placenta, while in the <lb/>abdomen, adhered to the external <w part="I">ſur-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">face</w> of the uterus; its adheſion to the <lb/>ſurface of the viſcera, in
          ſome other <lb/>caſes, having been found to be very <lb/>conſiderable<note place="bottom"
            n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Douglas's caſe of rupt. uterus, p. 36. Boneti <w part="I"
              >ſe-</w><lb/><w part="F">pulchret</w>. anatom. lib. iii. ſect. 38. </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>A review of the circumſtances, which <lb/>follow the introduction of
          his hand, <lb/>will elucidate the caſe, when compared <pb xml:id="page_30" n="32"
          /><lb/>with the appearances, which were <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerved</w> on
          opening the body, after death. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the firſt place. No mention is <lb/>made of any difficulty in
          introducing <lb/>the hand through the os internum into <lb/>the cavity of the uterus,
          which muſt <lb/>have been conſiderable, from its <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tracted</w> ſtate, if the attempt had been <lb/>made. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Secondly. As his hand came <w part="I">imme-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >diately</w> in contact with the inteſtines, if <lb/>the placenta had been within the
          uterus, <lb/>the inteſtines muſt likewiſe have been <lb/>within it, which does not by any
          means <lb/>appear from the narrative. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>And laſtly. If his hand had been <lb/>within the cavity of the uterus,
          how <lb/>could he have judged of the degree of <lb/>its contraction, ſo as to have thought
          it, <lb/>at firſt, to have been a ſcirrhus? </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_31" n="33"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>If we conſider the caſe as a partial <lb/>ſeparation of the vagina,
          from its <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tachment</w> to the <hi rend="italic">cervix
            uteri,</hi> then every <lb/>one of theſe objections are ſurmounted <lb/>with eaſe: his
          hand, on paſſing along <lb/>the funis, would have found an eaſy <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">troduction</w> into the cavity of the <w part="I">abdo-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >men</w>, and he would have been in <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tact</w> with
          the inteſtines, before his hand <lb/>arrived at the placenta. The uterus <lb/>would have
          been found on the anterior <lb/>part, and have felt contracted like a <lb/>ball, ſo that,
          at firſt, it might have <lb/>been miſtaken for a ſcirrhus; neither of <lb/>which could
          have poſſibly happened if <lb/>his hand had been within its cavity: <lb/>beſides, his
          expreſſion is ſo clear, in <lb/>reſpect to its contraction, 'dure <w part="I"
            >admo-</w><lb/><w part="F">dum</w> compactum atque <hi rend="italic">in ſe</hi>
          <w part="I">contrac-</w><lb/><w part="F">tum</w> comperit,' as to leave no room to
          <lb/>ſuppoſe any thing to have been included <lb/>within it. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>We find that on diſſection, after <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >lating</w> the external appearance of the <pb xml:id="page_32" n="34"/><lb/>abdomen,
          and what iſſued on making <lb/>an inciſion into it, he paſſed his hand, <lb/>he ſays, <hi
            rend="italic">per vulvam,</hi> and again felt the <lb/>inteſtines; and, what is very
          material <lb/>in forming a determination on the <w part="I">na-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ture</w> of the caſe, found the uterus <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceding</w>
          above the pubis, '<hi rend="italic">recedentemque</hi>
          <lb/>ſupra os pubis uterum reperit.' To uſe <lb/>the expreſſion of Dr. Douglas, in his
          <lb/>late, publication, <q >'it fled before the tips <lb/>of his fingers.'</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I think it muſt be evident to every <lb/>one, that the uterus would
          not have <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceded</w> before his hand, if its attachment
          <lb/>to the vagina had remained entire. It <lb/>muſt have reſiſted the touch. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The place where the rupture is ſaid <lb/>to have been was at the
          inferior and <lb/>poſterior part, a little above the os <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ternum</w>, where the common peritoneal <lb/>membrane is continued from the
          rectum <lb/>to the uterus. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_33" n="35"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now the ſame peritoneal coat which <lb/>ſurrounds the whole of the
          abdominal <lb/>viſcera, in its paſſage from the rectum <lb/>to become the external coat of
          the <w part="I">ute-</w><lb/><w part="F">rus</w>, is inflected over that part of the
          <lb/>vagina which is attached to the <hi rend="italic">cervix <lb/>uteri,</hi> beginning
          to form the peritoneal <lb/>coat of the uterus, at the place where <lb/>the vagina is
          joined to the cervix, a <lb/>little above the os internum. In the <lb/>ſame place, on the
          anterior part, the <lb/>vagina was lacerated in the caſe before <lb/>related; and, I
          think, on comparing the <lb/>different parts of Vander Wiel's <w part="I">rela-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tion</w>, with each other, it is clear that the <lb/>injury, in both caſes, was
          nearly ſimilar; <lb/>the only difference being, that in one <lb/>the laceration was in the
          poſterior, and <lb/>in the other in the anterior part of the <lb/>vagina. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_34" n="36"/>
        <head rend="align-center dc(2)"><lb/>CASE II. </head>

        <p rend="indent hanging italic"><lb/>A Caſe of lacerated vagina, as related by <lb/><hi
            rend="sc"><hi rend="italic">Bonetus,</hi></hi> from <hi rend="sc"><hi rend="italic"
              >Leonardus <w part="I">Dol-</w><lb/><w part="F">dius</w>.</hi>
          </hi></p>

        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> the year 1594, a woman of <w part="I"
            >Hage-</w><lb/><w part="F">naw</w>, in Alſace, 40 years of age, who <lb/>had been the
          mother of ſeven children, <lb/>at the full time, but all of them born <lb/>dead, died in
          labour of the eighth, on <lb/>the third day, without being delivered. <lb/>The night
          before, her pains had been <lb/>violent in the extreme; the women who <lb/>were preſent
          made many efforts to <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">liver</w> her, but they were not
          able to <lb/>afford her the leaſt help. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>On opening the body, they were very <lb/>cautious in making their
          inciſion into <lb/>the abdomen, that they might have a <pb xml:id="page_35" n="37"
          /><lb/>diſtinct view of the uterus <hi rend="italic">in ſitu.</hi> The <lb/>muſcles were
          hardly divided, when <lb/>the back of the child was wounded. <lb/>They had no ſuſpicion of
          what it really <lb/>was, ſuppoſing it, at firſt, to be the <w part="I">u-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">terus</w>; but, on continuing the inciſion, <lb/>they found it to be a full
          formed fœtus <lb/>(with ſigns of putridity from the <w part="I">ſepa-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ration</w> of the cuticle) without the uterus, <lb/>in the cavity of the abdomen. It
          lay <lb/>with the face to the ſacrum, and its <lb/>body extended at full length. At firſt,
          <lb/>nothing preternatural was obſerved, <lb/>there being no appearance of <w part="I"
            >contu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſion</w>, wound, ulceration, or abſceſs. <lb/>They wondered
          much at the ſingularity <lb/>of the caſe; but this was cleared up <lb/>when they ſound the
          uterus torn, <w part="I">rup-</w><lb/><w part="F">tured</w>, or rather broken off. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The child was ſtill connected by the <lb/>ſunis to the ſecundines,
          which were <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">tracted</w>, upon the left ſide, towards
          the <lb/>ſpleen, and adhered ſo faſt that they <lb/>had ſome difficulty to ſeparate them.
            <pb xml:id="page_36" n="38"/><lb/>The uterus was ſo contracted, that it <lb/>did not
          exceed the ſize of the placenta. <lb/>Near the cervix, directly under the <lb/>bladder,
          there was a portion of <w part="I">mem-</w><lb/><w part="F">brane</w> hanging down, about
          the <w part="I">thick-</w><lb/><w part="F">ness</w> of the diſſecting knife, and not
          <lb/>exceeding the breadth of half a palm, <lb/>which was a part of the ſeparated <w
            part="I">ute-</w><lb/><w part="F">rus</w>, <hi rend="italic">'uteri abrupti.'</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The reſt of the uterus, with its <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >per</w> orifice, and the ſecundines were <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tracted</w>, ſo that it was totally ſeparated <lb/>from the cervix, or <hi
            rend="italic">'ſinus muliebris,'</hi>
          <lb/>and all the other parts to which it had <lb/>before been attached. He attributes this
          <lb/>accident to the malconformation of the <lb/>pubis, which was too much flattened
            in<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* <unclear>#</unclear>oneti
              ſepoi<unclear>###</unclear>ret, anatom, lib, iii. ſect 38. </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The above caſe requires no comment, <lb/>as I think it is evident that
          there was a <lb/>total ſeparation of the uterus, from its <lb/>attachment to the vagina. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_37" n="39"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I remember to have read a caſe where <lb/>the ſame accident happened,
          from the <lb/>violent efforts of an accoucheur to <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >troduce</w> his hand to deliver. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center dc(2)"><lb/>CASE III. </head>

        <p rend="indent hanging italic"><lb/>The caſe of <hi rend="roman">Mrs. Manning,</hi> as
          related <lb/>by <hi rend="roman"><hi rend="sc">Dr. Douglas.</hi></hi>
        </p>

        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">We</hi> find that the woman, who is the <lb/>ſubject of
          this caſe, was in her 4th <w part="I">preg-</w><lb/><w part="F">nancy</w>, low in ſtature,
          about 30 years of <lb/>age, and of a weak conſtitution, but, in <lb/>general, healthy.
          When the Doctor <lb/>was firſt called to her, the membranes <lb/>had been ruptured eight
          hours, and the <lb/>pains had continued regular from that <lb/>time: yet though the os
          tincae was <w part="I">con-</w><pb xml:id="page_38" n="40"/><lb/><w part="F">ſiderably</w>
          dilated, the child did not <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">vance</w>. He found her
          extremely <w part="I">reſt-</w><lb/><w part="F">less</w>, complaining of exceſſive pain in
          <lb/>the region of the pubis. Each return <lb/>of pain cauſed her to writhe and twiſt
          <lb/>as if ſuffering from violent colic, very <lb/>unlike the urging throes of common <w
            part="I">la-</w><lb/><w part="F">bour</w>; but her pulſe was calm and <w part="I"
            >re-</w><lb/><w part="F">gular</w>, nor did ſhe make any particular <lb/>complaint,
          excepting of the pain about <lb/>the pubis. This being the ſtate of the <lb/>caſe, there
          ſeemed to be no reaſon to <lb/>induce him to precipitate the delivery. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>About nine o'clock the ſame evening, <lb/>the midwife informed him
          that the <w part="I">pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">tient</w> had had a diſcharge of blood from
          <lb/>the vagina, which, however, did not <lb/>continue; and that the pains had ceaſed
          <lb/>about half an hour after ſix o'clock; <lb/>ſince which, retching, with an inceſſant
          <lb/>craving for drink, had come on. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>He now found her face lengthened, <lb/>and bedewed with cold ſweat;
          her pulſe <pb xml:id="page_39" n="41"/><lb/>ſcarcely to be felt; her breathing ſhort
          <lb/>and quick, with great anxiety; but ſtill <lb/>complaining of no pain, excepting about
          <lb/>the pubis. <q >'By examination in the <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >mon</w> way,' he ſays, I could diſtinguiſh <lb/>nothing, excepting a round moveable
            <lb/>ſubſtance, which I ſuppoſed to be the <lb/>head of the child; but being only able
            <lb/>to reach it with my fingers, I could not <lb/>determine with any certainty what it
            <lb/>was. The woman appeared to be <hi rend="italic">in <lb/>extremis;</hi> and my mind
            was ſo wholly <lb/>occupied by her danger, as to preclude <lb/>all reaſoning with
            reſpect to the cauſe.'</q>
          <lb/>He determined upon immediate <w part="I">delive-</w><lb/><w part="F">ry</w>, as the
          only chance of relief. <q >'There <lb/>was no difficulty,' he ſays, 'in paſſing
            <lb/>my hand; and the ſubſtance which I had <lb/>ſuppoſed to be the child, fled before
            the <lb/>tips of my fingers: by following it, I at <lb/>laſt found my hand in a cavity,
            which <lb/>in no ſort reſembled that of the uterus. <lb/>I was then forcibly and
            painfully ſtruck <lb/>with the nature of the caſe; and on <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">amining</w> all round, with caution and <pb xml:id="page_40" n="42"
            /><lb/>gentleneſs, I could with certainty <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >termine</w> that my hand was in the cavity <lb/>of the abdomen: the child being on
            the <lb/>fore part; on the back part, the <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >tracted</w> uterus like an oblong ball; and <lb/>the inteſtines hanging among any <w
              part="I">fin-</w><lb/><w part="F">gers</w>.'</q> There was no obſtruction to the
          <lb/>turning and extraction of the child, <lb/>excepting in the paſſage of the <lb/>head
          through the brim of the pelvis. The <lb/>placenta, which was likewiſe in the <w part="I"
            >ab-</w><lb/><w part="F">dominal</w> cavity, had ſo clung to the <w part="I"
            >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">teſtines</w>, that he was again under the <lb/>neceſſity of
          introducing his hand to <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">tach</w> it, which was not
          difficult. <q >'The <lb/>uterus ſeemed,' he ſays, 'to have been <lb/>ruptured
            tranſverſely, on the lower and <lb/>fore part, ſome diſtance above where <lb/>the vagina
            is connected with it; and it <lb/>was more contracted in its ſize, than I <lb/>thought
            poſſible in the few hours which <lb/>had elapſed ſince the accident.'</q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>After a variety of changes and <w part="I">alarm-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ing</w> ſymptoms ariſing from peritoneal <pb xml:id="page_41" n="43"
          /><lb/>inflammation, the poor woman <w part="I">fortu-</w><lb/><w part="F">nately</w>
          recovered; and in about ſix weeks <lb/>waited upon the Doctor at his own houſe, <lb/>to
          return thanks; when he perſuaded <lb/>her to permit his neighbour Dr. Oſborn <lb/>to
          examine <hi rend="italic">per vaginam.</hi> He thought <lb/>the os tinæ ſomewhat more
          open, <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">ternally</w>, than it uſually is; and Dr.
          <lb/>Douglas himſelf fancied he felt rather <lb/>more fulneſs than is common about the
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">cervix uteri:</hi> but they both agreed, that <lb/>there was
          nothing in the touch ſo <w part="I">dif-</w><lb/><w part="F">ferent</w> from what is
          obſerved in the <w part="I">na-</w><lb/><w part="F">tural</w> ſtate, as to have excited
          any idea <lb/>of previous diſeaſe, had they not known <lb/>the complaint with which ſhe
          had been <lb/>afflicted. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>After examining the body of Mrs. <lb/>Wilkins, and aſcertaining the
          nature of <lb/>the injury, I began to conſider the above <lb/>caſe in a different light,
          from what I <lb/>did on the firſt peruſal of it. The Doctor <lb/>repreſents it as a caſe
          of ruptured <w part="I">ute-</w><pb xml:id="page_42" n="44"/><lb/>I now perceive it to be
          a caſe of <lb/>lacerated vagina. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The circumſtance which he relates, <lb/>of a <q >'round
            moveable ſubſtance,'</q> which <lb/>upon introducing his hand, he found <lb/>to be <q
            >'the contracted uterus like an <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">long</w>
            ball,'</q> was ſo ſimilar to what Mr. <lb/>Waller deſcribed, and which every one <lb/>of
          us had an opportunity of obſerving <lb/>during the diſſection, that I have no <lb/>doubt
          remaining in my own mind, that <lb/>there could have been any difference <lb/>between the
          two caſes. Mr. Waller and <lb/>the other gentlemen who were preſent <lb/>concur likewiſe
          with me in the ſame <lb/>opinion. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the preceding pages, I have had <lb/>occaſion, on a review of the
          caſe from <lb/>Vander Weil, to advert to a ſimilar <w part="I">oc-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >currence</w>, when I expreſſed my doubts <lb/>how the degree of contraction can be
          <lb/>aſcertained, unleſs the hand of the <w part="I">ac-</w><pb xml:id="page_43" n="45"
            /><lb/><w part="F">coucheur</w> has been paſſed on the outſide <lb/>of the uterus. I
          cannot ſuppoſe that, <lb/>while the fundus is contracted above <lb/>the rupture, the os
          internum will remain <lb/>for ſeveral hours, nay days, dilated, and <lb/>ſhew no
          diſpoſition to contract. The <lb/>fibres, I ſhould apprehend, which form <lb/>its texture,
          will aſſiſt its contraction in <lb/>as great a degree as that of the fundus. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Dr. Douglas, as well as Vander Weil, <lb/>found that the uterus
          receded on <w part="I">intro-</w><lb/><w part="F">ducing</w> his hand. Is it poſſible that
          the <lb/>uterus ſhould have receded before his <lb/>hand, if its attachment had been
          entire? <lb/>It muſt have made ſome reſiſtance. Yet <lb/>we find that, when he touched it,
          it fled, <lb/>and upon following it, his hand went, <lb/>not into the uterus, but into a
          cavity <lb/>which in no ſort reſembled it. Can it <lb/>be ſuppoſed from this relation, ſo
            <w part="I">point-</w><lb/><w part="F">edly</w> marked, that his fingers ever paſſed
          <lb/>the os internum? The uterus muſt have <lb/>been fixed, if he had entered into its
          <lb/>cavity; but he ſays, that he was obliged <pb xml:id="page_44" n="46"/><lb/>to follow
          it, and at length found his <lb/>hand within the abdomen, the 'child <lb/>being on the
          fore part, on the back part <lb/>the contracted uterus, like an oblong ball'. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center dc(2)"><lb/>CASE IV. </head>

        <p rend="indent hanging italic"><lb/>A Caſe of lacerated vagina from <hi rend="roman"><hi
              rend="sc">Pou-<lb/>teau,</hi></hi> related by him as a rupture <lb/>of the uterus. </p>

        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">He</hi> was called to the aſſiſtance of a <lb/>woman,
          who had been a conſiderable <lb/>time in labour, under the care of a <w part="I"
            >mid-</w><lb/><w part="F">wife</w>; ſhe had been ſeized the day <w part="I"
            >be-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w> with a hemorrhage, on which the <lb/>child, which had
          before preſented with <pb xml:id="page_45" n="47"/><lb/>the head, was no longer felt. On
            <w part="I">exa-</w><lb/><w part="F">mination</w>, his hand entered at once into <lb/>a
          cavity, which appeared large; on the <lb/>fore part, he felt a round ſubſtance, of
          <lb/>the ſize, but not the ſolidity, of a child's<lb/> head; yet there was not any thing
          to be <lb/>felt, which could aſſure him of a child <lb/>being there. The woman died ſoon
            <w part="I">af-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w>, without being further examined. <lb/>On
          opening the body, the child and <lb/>placenta were found in the cavity of the
          <lb/>abdomen, entirely out of the uterus, <lb/>which was of the ſize of a child's head
          <lb/>of five years old, and was the round <lb/>body which had been felt <hi rend="italic"
            >per vaginam.</hi>
          <lb/>The rupture was on the poſterior and <lb/>interior part, and then about three or
          <lb/>four inches long<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Poutean, page 487.
          </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>When the eaſy introduction of his <lb/>hand into <q >'a cavity
            which appeared <lb/>large,' at a time when the 'uterus was <lb/>contracted to the ſize
            of a child's head;'</q>
          <pb xml:id="page_46" n="48"/><lb/>his perceiving by the touch, during his <lb/>attempt to
          deliver, <q >'a round ſubſtance,'</q>
          <lb/>which afterwards, on diſſection, he found <lb/>to be the contracted uterus, and the
          <lb/>ſtate of the rupture, being then about <lb/><q >'three or four inches
              long<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* When this accident happens in the
              uterus, the ſize <lb/>of the rupture is ſoon diminiſhed. Rungius relates, that
              <lb/>the inteſtines were kept up by his hand, until the rupture <lb/>was ſufficiently
              contracted to prevent their deſcent. Dr. <lb/>Hamiiton ſays, he had an opportunity of
              examining how <lb/>amazingly the rupture was diminiſhed, by the contraction <lb/>of
              the uterus. La Motte obſerves, that, on diſſection, <lb/>the rupture would not admit
              the tip of his little finger; <lb/>and in other caſes we find ſimilar remarks. How are
              we <lb/>then to account for his finding the rupture to be ſo very <lb/>extenſive, at a
              time when the uterus was ſo much con-<lb/>tracted? </note>,'</q> are <w part="I"
            >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſidered</w>, I think that I ſhall not be too <lb/>haſty in
          pronouncing it to have been a <lb/>ſeparation of the uterus from its <w part="I"
            >poſte-</w><lb/><w part="F">rior</w> attachment to the vagina. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>AS in ruptures of the uterus, ſo in <w part="I">la-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">cerations</w> of the vagina, if the head of <lb/>the child ſhould be advanced
          ſo far <w part="I">in-</w><pb xml:id="page_47" n="49"/><lb/><w part="F">to</w> the pelvis
          as to be wedged, before a <lb/>laceration takes place, it will remain <lb/>there, and we
          ſhall be deprived of one <lb/>criterion, the retroceſſion of the <w part="I"
            >pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſenting</w> part, to guide us; the ceſſation <lb/>of the true
          pains muſt lead us then to <lb/>judge of the nature of the caſe, when <lb/>attended with
          vomiting and other <w part="I">ſymp-</w><lb/><w part="F">toms</w>, as deſcribed in the
          relation of the <lb/>preceding narratives. The following <lb/>caſes is an inſtance of this
          kind. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center dc(2)"><lb/>CASE V. </head>
        <p rend="indent hanging italic"><lb/>A caſe of lacerated vagina, where the <lb/>head was
          engaged in the pelvis, before <lb/>the accident took place; <w part="I"
            >communi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cated</w> by a friend. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>A. B. aged about 30, was taken in <lb/>labour with her third child, on
          April <lb/>15th, 1785, at four oclock in the <w part="I">morn-</w><pb xml:id="page_48"
            n="50"/><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>. The waters ſoon came away. On <lb/>examination, the
          head of the child was <lb/>found to be low in the pelvis. A <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſiderable</w> ſtricture was obſerved in the <lb/>vagina, and the ſacrum
          projected rather <lb/>forward at its apex. About five hours <lb/>after ſhe was firſt taken
          in labour, ſhe <lb/>began to complain of pains in her belly, <lb/>which ſhe diſtinguiſhed
          from thoſe of <lb/>labour. At three oclock in the <w part="I">after-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >noon</w>, a phyſician, an eminent teacher <lb/>of midwifery in London, was called in,
          <lb/>at which time, from the degree of <w part="I">ſtric-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w>,
          the part of the head which <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſented</w> could not be
          exactly aſcertained. <lb/>He ordered her an injection, which was <lb/>given, but without
          any effect. On <w part="I">en-</w><lb/><w part="F">quiring</w>, it appeared, that ſince
          ſhe <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">gan</w> to complain of the pain in her <lb/>belly,
          the labour pains had ceaſed. A <lb/>ſingle blade was introduced with eaſe, <lb/>and ſome
          endeavours made to deliver, <lb/>but without ſucceſs. The Doctor, <w part="I"
            >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſidering</w> it wrong to ſtruggle againſt <w part="I"
            >na-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w>, or do any thing without the <w part="I">aſſiſ-</w><pb
            xml:id="page_49" n="51"/><lb/><w part="F">tance</w> of pains, left her, giving
          directions <lb/>for an enema to be injected, and four or <lb/>ſix ounces of blood to be
          taken away. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>He returned at half paſt five, when <lb/>very little alteration could
          be perceived. <lb/>She had no labour pains, and the pains <lb/>continued the ſame in the
          abdomen, <lb/>which ſhe now complained was become <lb/>tender. Injections were ordered,
          copious <lb/>and ſtimulant; four were given without <lb/>any return. The forceps were at
          length <lb/>applied, and uſed moderately, with an <lb/>intent to bring on a return of true
          pains; <lb/>but a ſlight diſcharge of the glyſters was <lb/>the only effect. A little
          ground was at <lb/>length gained, and, by encreaſing the <lb/>force for a conſiderable
          time, ſhe was <lb/>delivered of a dead child: the placenta <lb/>came away immediately
          after. She <lb/>made water frequently during the <w part="I">la-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >bour</w>, and had it drawn off before the <lb/>uſe of the forceps. She was thirſty,
          <lb/>and vomited frequently, though little in <lb/>quantity. By her cries, ſhe did not
          ſeem <pb xml:id="page_50" n="52"/><lb/>to ſuffer more pain, than is uſually felt <lb/>in
          her delivery. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Her pulſe were quick after ſhe was <lb/>in bed; ſhe was diſpoſed to
          vomit, and <lb/>paſſed a reſtleſs night; the pain in her <lb/>belly continued diſtinct
          from after pain. <lb/>She lived until the morning of the 18th, <lb/>during which time her
          pulſe were <w part="I">gene-</w><lb/><w part="F">rally</w> 130 or more, her skin hot, ſhe
            <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">plained</w> of great pain and tenderneſs of
          <lb/>the abdomen; ſhe vomited frequently, <lb/>and her urgings to vomit were great. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>From no local injury being ſuppoſed <lb/>to have happened, and from
          the <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſence</w> of the lochia, and other <w part="I"
            >ſymp-</w><lb/><w part="F">toms</w>, the caſe was conſidered as truly <lb/>puerperal,
          and treated as ſuch. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>On diſſection, the inteſtines were found <lb/>to be inflamed, with an
          exudation of <lb/>lymph on their ſurfaces, and the gall <lb/>bladder was large and
          diſtended with <lb/>bile. The uterus was contracted to the <pb xml:id="page_51" n="53"
          /><lb/>ſize of double fiſt, black, and <w part="I">begin-</w><lb/><w part="F">ning</w> to
          ſphacelate. The vagina was <lb/>found to be lacerated at its connexion <lb/>to the <hi
            rend="italic">cervix uteri,</hi> anteriorly, no <w part="I">veſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tige</w> of the ſtricture remaining<note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)"> Although, in
            the caſe which gave riſe to theſe <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſervations</w>,
            the bladder was unfortunately injured, yet it <lb/>does not follow, that this muſt
            neceſſarily happen always; <lb/>for in this caſe we ſee, that a laceration may take
            place <lb/>on the anterior part, without its being injured; and from <lb/>other caſes we
            are taught, that the poſterior or lateral <lb/>parts are as often liable to the
            accident, as the anterior <lb/>part of the vagina. </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is to be obſerved, that the woman <lb/>had fallen down, a day or
          two before <lb/>ſhe was taken in labour, and that the <lb/>ſame gentleman had delivered
          her, two <lb/>years before, with forceps, on account <lb/>of the ſame ſtricture. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>How far the ſixth caſe quoted by <lb/>Dr. Douglas might be ſimilar to
          the <lb/>above, I have ſome doubts; but the <lb/>circumſtances attending it render it
          <lb/>probable. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_52" n="54"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It appears, that the woman had been <lb/>in labour the beſt part of
          the day, with <lb/>very ſtrong pains, before the rupture is <lb/>ſuppoſed to have taken
          place. The <lb/>head was firmly wedged in the pelvis; <lb/>but, in attempting to open it,
          ſuddenly <lb/>gave way to the force applied. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Now, let us conſider for one moment <lb/>the nature of the caſe. If a
          rupture <lb/>had taken place in the uterus, as the <lb/>head was firmly wedged in the
          pelvis, <lb/>the feet muſt have been the part <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >truded</w>; whence, when I recollect the <lb/>ſtrong contractile power of the
            uterus<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* When a part of the child only has
            eſcaped through <lb/>a rupture of the uterus, the contraction, as related by
            <lb/>authors, is great. Hildanus gives a caſe where the head <lb/>of a child had paſſed
            through a rupture of the uterus, <lb/>which had contracted ſo ſtrongly round its neck,
            that, he <lb/>ſays, it had no doubt been ſtrangled by it. <p rend="align-right"
              ><lb/>Hildani Centur. i. obſerv. 54. </p>
          </note>, <lb/>and the length of time intervening <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tween</w> the attempt to open the head, <lb/>and the time when the rupture is <w
            part="I">ſup-</w><pb xml:id="page_53" n="55"/><lb/><w part="F">poſed</w> to have
          happened, I cannot <w part="I">per-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſuade</w> myſelf that the child
          would have <lb/>eſcaped ſo eaſy into the cavity of the <lb/>abdomen as he found it did. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>If the vagina was lacerated, it is eaſy <lb/>to account for the ſudden
          retroceſſion <lb/>of the child. It is evident, that the <w part="I">ute-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">rus</w> being only attached in one place, <lb/>its reſiſtance againſt the
          preſſure could <lb/>only be partial; the fundus would be <lb/>inclined, and the os
          internum raiſed in <lb/>proportion; therefore, when the head <lb/>was preſſed back, it
          would find an eaſy <lb/>admittance, through the laceration, into <lb/>the cavity of the
          abdomen; from the <lb/>endeavours of the uterus to free itſelf, <lb/>the body with the
          placenta would ſoon <lb/>follow. The rupture being near the <w part="I">cer-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">vix</w> is, I think, ſome ſupport to what I <lb/>have advanced. I ſhall
          likewiſe <w part="I">endea-</w><lb/><w part="F">vour</w> to ſhew, in another place, that
          the <lb/>placenta being in the cavity of the <w part="I">ab-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >domen</w>, may be conſidered as a <w part="I">collate-</w><lb/><w part="F">ral</w> proof. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_54" n="56"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I <hi rend="sc">am</hi> inclined to believe, that the <lb/>whole of
          the child very ſeldom eſcapes <lb/>from a rupture of the uterus. I am, <lb/>however, very
          well convinced, that it is <lb/>always the conſequence of a laceration <lb/>of the vagina,
          unleſs it ſhould happen <lb/>to be as firmly wedged in the pelvis as <lb/>in the caſes I
          have juſt noticed. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>On a review of fifteen caſes quoted <lb/>by Dr. Douglas, we ſhall
          find, that the <lb/>child eſcaped into the cavity of the <w part="I">ab-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">domen</w> in ſeven; in No. VI. VII. X. XI. <lb/>XII. XIII. and XIV. I have
          already <lb/>endeavoured to ſhew that No. VI. and <lb/>XI. were lacerations of the vagina,
          and <lb/>I ſhall draw ſome inferences from No. <lb/>XII. when I come to ſpeak of the <w
            part="I">pla-</w><lb/><w part="F">centa</w> being out of the uterus, tending <lb/>to
          ſhow a degree of probability of that <lb/>being of the ſame nature. Of No. VII. <pb
            xml:id="page_55" n="57"/><lb/>we have a very uncertain account, as, <lb/>from motives of
          delicacy, it is not <w part="I">par-</w><lb/><w part="F">ticularly</w> entered into. No.
          X. without <lb/>doubt, muſt have been a ruptured <w part="I">ute-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >rus</w>. I think that the two laſt cannot be <lb/>conſidered in point, as they were at
          an <lb/>early period of geſtation, and the <w part="I">acci-</w><lb/><w part="F">dents</w>
          happened from external violence. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the remaining eight, No. I. II. III. <lb/>IV. V. VIII. IX. and XV.
          only part <lb/>of the child had eſcaped from the <w part="I">rup-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ture</w>; indeed, in the two firſt, it does <lb/>not appear that any part had eſcaped.
          <lb/>It is therefore evident that, ſetting aſide <lb/>the two caſes from external
          violence, in <lb/>only one out of thirteen the child <w part="I">eſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >caped</w> wholly from a rupture of the <lb/>uterus. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I am alſo inclined to believe, that the <lb/>placenta being in the
          cavity of the <w part="I">ab-</w><lb/><w part="F">domen</w>, is an occurrence which very
            <w part="I">ſel-</w><lb/><w part="F">dom</w> happens, excepting in thoſe caſes
          <lb/>where the vagina is lacerated. The <pb xml:id="page_56" n="58"/><lb/>ſize of the
          rupture, when it happens in <lb/>the uterus, muſt be diminiſhed almoſt <lb/>immediately
          after the child has eſcaped, <lb/>and the contraction of the uterus muſt <lb/>be encreaſed
          by its endeavours to <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">pel</w> the placenta; it is
          therefore almoſt <lb/>impoſſible that the placenta ſhould <w part="I">eſ-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">cape</w> into the abdomen: it might indeed <lb/>ſometimes happen, if the funis
          ſhould <lb/>be much twiſted round the child's neck <lb/>or body. In almoſt every caſe,
          where <lb/>we have a certainty that the accident <lb/>was a rupture of the uterus, we find
          <lb/>that the placenta remained behind. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>When a laceration takes place in the <lb/>vagina, the propulſion of
          the placenta <lb/>is not different from what happens in <lb/>common parturition; as every
            <w part="I">contrac-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of the uterus forces it towards the
          <lb/>os internum, from whence it paſſes after the <lb/>child into the cavity of the <w
            part="I">abdo-</w><lb/><w part="F">men</w>. But when there is a rupture in <lb/>the
          uterus, every contraction muſt be <lb/>an impediment to its propulſion, by <w part="I"
            >di-</w><pb xml:id="page_57" n="59"/><lb/><w part="F">miniſhing</w> the ſize of the
          aperture, thro' <lb/>which it muſt paſs, to be found among <lb/>the viſcera. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the caſe of Mrs. Wilkins, where <lb/>we can entertain no doubt of
          the nature <lb/>of the accident, the placenta was found <lb/>with the child in the cavity
          of the <w part="I">ab-</w><lb/><w part="F">domen</w>. In that of Mrs. Manning, in
          <lb/>thoſe from Vander Weil, Bonetus, and <lb/>Pouteau, and in the ſixth caſe quoted
          <lb/>by Dr. Douglas, all of which I have <w part="I">en-</w><lb/><w part="F">deavoured</w>
          to ſhew were of the ſame <w part="I">na-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w>, the placenta was
          likewiſe found <lb/>among the viſcera. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>There are two more inſtances, among <lb/>the caſes quoted by Dr.
          Douglas, where <lb/>the ſame occurrence is ſaid to have <w part="I">hap-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">pened</w>; in No. X. and XII. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The firſt, communicated by Dr. <w part="I">Garth-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſhore</w>, is againſt the opinion I have <w part="I">form-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>,
          that being, as I have before obſerved, <lb/>evidently a rupture of the uterus. In the <pb
            xml:id="page_58" n="60"/><lb/>other, from Saviard, it appears, that the <lb/>child
          preſented favourably, with every <lb/>appearance that the labour would be <lb/>ſoon
          finiſhed; yet the pains ceaſed at <lb/>once, after two days continuance; the
          <lb/>preſenting part receded, and only the <lb/>placenta was to be felt. She died <w
            part="I">un-</w><lb/><w part="F">delivered</w>; and when the body was <lb/>opened, the
          child and ſecundines were <lb/>in the abdomen among the viſcera, the <lb/>feet of the
          child touching the ſtomach <lb/>of the mother. The inteſtines were all <lb/>fretted, and
          the omentum rotten and <lb/>ſtinking, but the uterus was of the <w part="I">na-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tural</w> appearance. I have not Saviard's <lb/>book to refer to; but I think,
          from a <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">view</w> of this account, I ſhall be able to
          <lb/>draw ſome inferences in my favour. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>From the manner in which he <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >preſſes</w> himſelf, that the uterus was of <lb/>its natural appearance, we may be led
          <lb/>to ſuppoſe that no injury had happened <lb/>to it. When we recollect the <w part="I"
            >circum-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtance</w>, that, after the preſenting part <pb
            xml:id="page_59" n="61"/><lb/>had receded, the placenta alone was to <lb/>be felt, I
          apprehend but a ſmall degree <lb/>of doubt concerning the nature of the <lb/>caſe will
          remain. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>After the body was opened, the <w part="I">ſe-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >cundines</w> as well as the child were found <lb/>in the abdomen. As the placenta was
          <lb/>to be felt on examination, after the <lb/>rupture had taken place, how can it be
          <lb/>ſuppoſed that the rupture was in the <lb/>uterus? The uterus muſt have been at
          <lb/>that time conſiderably contracted, and <lb/>the aperture ſo much diminiſhed, as to
          <lb/>have rendered the eſcape of the <w part="I">pla-</w><lb/><w part="F">centa</w>
          impoſſible. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Hence I am clearly of opinion, that <lb/>the placenta being felt on
          examination, <lb/>after the rupture had taken place, and <lb/>being afterwards found in
          the abdomen, <lb/>is a great proof that the accident was <lb/>not in the uterus, but in
          the vagina. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_60" n="62"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Out of eight caſes, therefore, where <lb/>the placenta was found with
          the child <lb/>in the cavity of the abdomen, there is <lb/>the greateſt probability to
          ſuppoſe that <lb/>ſeven of them were lacerations of the <lb/>vagina. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> difficulty attending delivery, <lb/>when the
          vagina is lacerated, muſt be <lb/>very trifling, when compared to that <lb/>which will
          occur if the accident <w part="I">hap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pens</w> in the uterus. In the
          caſe of <lb/>Mrs. Wilkins, the only reſiſtance was <lb/>in bringing down the breech, which
          <lb/>all the gentlemen preſent agreed aroſe <lb/>from the protuberance of the child's
          <lb/>belly projecting over the fundus of the <lb/>contracted uterus; which, as the <w
            part="I">extrac-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> went on, was brought lower down, <lb/>and,
          of conſequence, preſſed the breech <lb/>of the child over the pubis: after this <lb/>was
          overcome, not the leaſt difficulty <pb xml:id="page_61" n="63"/><lb/>whatever occurred. In
          the caſe of Mrs. <lb/>Manning, it does not appear that there <lb/>was any reſiſtance to
          the delivery of the <lb/>breech; but we find there was a <w part="I">conſi-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">derable</w> obſtruction in the paſſage of the <lb/>head through the pelvis. I
          am <w part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F">what</w> inclined to believe that this might
          <lb/>have ariſen from the ſame cauſe, <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F">though</w> Dr.
          Douglas ſuppoſes it to have <lb/>proceeded from the narrowneſs of the <lb/>pelvis. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In thoſe caſes, where the uterus has <lb/>been ruptured, the
          difficulty will be <w part="I">en-</w><lb/><w part="F">creaſed</w> or diminiſhed, in
          proportion as <lb/>more or leſs of the child has eſcaped <lb/>into the cavity of the
          abdomen. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>If the rupture ſhould be ſo extenſive <lb/>as to admit the child to
          eſcape entirely <lb/>out of the uterus, from the natural <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">poſition</w> of its fibres, the uterus will <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >moſt</w> immediately contract, and the ſize <lb/>of the rupture will become leſs, of <w
            part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſequence</w>, in proportion to the degree <pb
            xml:id="page_62" n="64"/><lb/>of contraction which takes place. If <lb/>the rupture
          ſhould be ſo ſmall as to <w part="I">ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">mit</w> the protruſion of
          part of the child <lb/>only, a ſtricture will be formed upon <lb/>ſuch part as has
          eſcaped, which will <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">quire</w> a conſiderable degree of
          force to <lb/>overcome, as, from its endeavours to <lb/>expel the part which remains, the
            <w part="I">ute-</w><lb/><w part="F">rus</w> will ſtill continue to contract. In
          <lb/>performing the cæſarean operation, M. <lb/>Soumain found that the edges of the <w
            part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">ciſion</w> made in the uterus preſſed ſo cloſe
          <lb/>upon the fœtus, that he could hardly get <lb/>his fingers in to extract it<note
            place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Mem. de l'Acad. Chirurg. Paris, mem. xx.
          </note>. Hence we <lb/>may account for the alternate though <lb/>ineffectual pains, which,
          in ſome caſes, <lb/>have been obſerved to continue for ſome <lb/>time after the rupture
          has taken place; <lb/>and I believe we may be led to form a <lb/>probable opinion that,
          when this <w part="I">hap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pens</w>, ſome part of the child ſtill <w
            part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">mains</w> within the uterus. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_63" n="65"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The hand of the accoucheur, when <lb/>he ſits down to deliver, muſt be
          paſſed <lb/>through the os internum into the cavity <lb/>of the uterus, and from thence
          through <lb/>the rupture. The difficulty attending <lb/>the paſſage of the hand will be in
            <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">portion</w> to the degree of contraction; <lb/>but,
          unfortunately, it is very ſeldom <lb/>that the nature of the caſe is known ſo <lb/>early,
          as to induce us to make any <w part="I">at-</w><lb/><w part="F">tempt</w> to deliver
          before the uterus is <lb/>conſiderably contracted. After the <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ſiſtance</w> from the diminiſhed ſtate of the <lb/>rupture is overcome, and the
          hand <w part="I">paſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſed</w> into the abdomen, the feet, in <w
            part="I">gene-</w><lb/><w part="F">ral</w>, may be ſoon found, and brought <lb/>down
          with ſome eaſe; but as the <w part="I">ope-</w><lb/><w part="F">rator</w> proceeds, and
          the legs come <w part="I">for-</w><lb/><w part="F">ward</w>, every inch of the child, as
          the <lb/>extraction takes place, will create a freſh <lb/>reſiſtance from its increaſing
          bulk. The <lb/>irritation which muſt be given to the <lb/>uterus, by the introduction of
          the hand, <lb/>will increaſe its endeavours to contract, <lb/>and make conſiderable
          addition to the <pb xml:id="page_64" n="66"/><lb/>difficulty. Caldani, of Bologna, in a
          <lb/>letter to Haller, relates ſome <w part="I">experi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ments</w> made
          on the uterus of a bitch, <lb/>which ſhow the great degree of <w part="I"
            >contrac-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> that takes place even after death, <lb/>on any
          ſtimulus being applied to it<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Vide Van
            Swieten's comment. ſect. 1316. </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The nearer likewiſe the rupture <w part="I">hap-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >pens</w> to the fundus or cervis, the greater <lb/>degree of eaſe or difficulty will
          enſue. <lb/>In the firſt inſtance, the extraction will <lb/>be made nearly in a direct
          line. In the <lb/>other, and which moſt commonly <w part="I">hap-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >pens</w>, that part of the child which <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">mains</w> in
          the abdomen muſt form an <lb/>angle with the feet and legs, while they <lb/>are paſſing
          through the vagina, and the <lb/>degrees of ſuch angle will be decreaſed <lb/>or
          increaſed, in proportion as the <w part="I">rup-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w> may happen
          to be, either near the <lb/>cervix, or further towards the fundus. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Very little more exertion will be <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >quired</w> than what is obliged to be made <pb xml:id="page_65" n="67"/><lb/>uſe of in
          a common caſe, where the <lb/>child is turned, when the feet are the <lb/>only parts that
          have eſcaped. When <lb/>the legs have protruded as far as the <lb/>knee, the reſiſtance
          will be <w part="I">conſidera-</w><lb/><w part="F">bly</w> more powerful; as, in ſuch
          caſe, <lb/>the hand muſt be paſſed to a greater <lb/>diſtance through the rupture in
          ſearch <lb/>of the feet: but how much more muſt <lb/>the difficulty be increaſed, if the
            <w part="I">aper-</w><lb/><w part="F">ture</w> ſhould be large enough to admit <lb/>the
          child to paſs out of the uterus as far <lb/>as the hips? Indeed I apprehend this
          <lb/>ſituation to be worſe than when the <lb/>whole of the child has eſcaped; as, in
          <lb/>that caſe, there may be ſome hope that <lb/>the reſiſtance might be overcome, and
          <lb/>the child extracted by the feet; but <lb/>when the child has eſcaped as far as the
          <lb/>hips, ſuch a very conſiderable diſtenſion, <lb/>if not further laceration of the
          rupture, <lb/>muſt take place, and ſo great a degree <lb/>of force muſt be made uſe of to
            <w part="I">over-</w><lb/><w part="F">come</w> the contraction, in order to gain
          <lb/>ſufficient room to bring the feet back, as <pb xml:id="page_66" n="68"/><lb/>leave
          little room to hope for ſucceſs. <lb/>In fact, when I reflect on the very great
          <lb/>difficulties that muſt ariſe when any <lb/>conſiderable part of the child has <w
            part="I">eſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">caped</w>, I do not at all wonder that <w part="I"
            >au-</w><lb/><w part="F">thors</w> have concurred in pronouncing <lb/>the accident
          mortal, and giving no <w part="I">en-</w><lb/><w part="F">couragement</w> for attempting
          relief, <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">cept</w> by having recourſe to the cæſarean
          <lb/>operation. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In addition to Mrs. Manning's caſe, <lb/>of which we have had occaſion
          to ſpeak <lb/>ſo often, eight others are adduced by <lb/>Dr. Douglas, to evince the eaſe
          with <lb/>which delivery may be performed in <lb/>caſes of ruptured uterus. No. I. IV. V.
          <lb/>VI. VII. VIII. IX. and XV. On <w part="I">read-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> them over
          with attention, I have <lb/>obſerved that the ſituation of the child, <lb/>in moſt of
          them, was ſuch as to create <lb/>the ſmaller degree of reſiſtance, <w part="I"
            >accord-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> to the opinion I have entertained <lb/>in reſpect
          to the difficulty attending <w part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">livery</w>. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_67" n="69"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the firſt, which was related to <w part="I">Heiſ-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ter</w> by Rungius, it does not appear that <lb/>the child, or any part of it,
          had ever <lb/>been in the cavity of the abdomen. <lb/>Indeed Dr. Douglas is of the ſame <w
            part="I">opi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nion</w> himſelf, as he ſays, <q >'the recovery
            of <lb/>the patients, No. I. and II. may have <lb/>been in a great meaſure owing to the
            <lb/>viſcera having ſuſtained little or no <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">jury</w>,
            as there is no reaſon to ſuppoſe <lb/>that the child in either caſe had been in <lb/>the
            cavity of the abdomen<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Vide Obſervat. on
              extr. caſe of rupt. uter. p. 66. </note>.'</q> This may <lb/>give us ſome idea of the
          proſpect we <lb/>have of recovery when a rupture takes <lb/>place, but cannot be brought
          to ſhow <lb/>the eaſe with which delivery may be <lb/>performed, when the whole or part of
          <lb/>the child has eſcaped from the uterus. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In No. IV. which is taken from La <lb/>Motte, <hi rend="italic"
            >obſervation</hi> 317, the feet were <lb/>the only parts out of the uterus, and <lb/>the
          rupture was at the fundus; whence <pb xml:id="page_68" n="70"/><lb/>the extraction was not
          attended with <lb/>much difficulty, for two reaſons: the <lb/>endeavours made uſe of were
          in a <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F">rect</w> line, in the firſt inſtance, and in the
          <lb/>ſecond, the feet being the only parts that <lb/>had eſcaped, the hand of the <w
            part="I">accou-</w><lb/><w part="F">cheur</w> was introduced until it came to <lb/>the
          knees, ſo as to bring them down <lb/>and diſengage the feet; after which, no <lb/>more
          difficulty would ariſe than what <lb/>happens in a common caſe of turning. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In No. V. likewiſe from La Motte, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >obſervation</hi> 318, it appears that the child <lb/>had eſcaped out of the uterus as
          far as <lb/>the hips, or even further, part of the <lb/>body being in the cavity of the <w
            part="I">abdo-</w><lb/><w part="F">men</w>. The child was turned, he ſays, <lb/>and
          extracted with conſiderable eaſe; <lb/><hi rend="italic">en moins d'un miſerere,</hi> as
          he expreſſes <lb/>it himſelf. I cannot think, with Dr. <lb/>Douglas, that La Motte's
          obſervations <lb/>are related with ſuch plainneſs and <w part="I">can-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >dour</w>, as to claim our moſt perfect <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >fidence</w>. In this inſtance, we have a <pb xml:id="page_69" n="71"/><lb/>caſe the moſt
          difficult that can poſſibly <lb/>happen, and yet the delivery was <w part="I"
            >per-</w><lb/><w part="F">formed</w> with the greateſt eaſe <w part="I"
            >imagi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nable</w>. I really am of opinion, that the <lb/>relation is
          not founded in fact: I <w part="I">ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">prehend</w> that he has either
          magnified <lb/>the proportion of the child which was <lb/>out of the uterus, or that he
          has <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">cealed</w> the difficulty he muſt have met
          <lb/>with, in caſe ſuch a conſiderable part of <lb/>the child had been in the abdomen. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I have advanced ſome reaſons, in a <lb/>former part of theſe
          obſervations, when <lb/>ſpeaking of the head of the child being <lb/>wedged in the pelvis,
          at the time when <lb/>a laceration happens, tending to ſhow <lb/>that No. VI. was a
          laceration of the <lb/>vagina. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>We have a very defective account of <lb/>No. VII. as from motives of
          delicacy <lb/>to the gentleman who attended the <w part="I">pa-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tient</w>, Dr. Douglas does not think <w part="I">him-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſelf</w> at
          liberty to enter more <w part="I">particular-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> into it. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_70" n="72"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In No. VIII. from Peu, the time <w part="I">elap-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ſed</w> between the accident and the <w part="I">deli-</w><lb/><w part="F">very</w> is
          not related; but I am inclined <lb/>to believe that it was done very ſoon <lb/>after, from
          the apparent facility with <lb/>which it was accompliſhed. There <w part="I"
            >ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">pears</w> likewiſe ſome deficiency in the <lb/>contractile
          power of the uterus, by the <lb/>exceſſive hemorrhage that followed. We <lb/>find however
          that he <q >'delivered with <lb/>great caution to avoid doing further <w part="I"
              >in-</w><lb/><w part="F">jury</w> to the uterus.'</q> This ſeems to <w part="I"
            >inti-</w><lb/><w part="F">mate</w> ſome degree of reſiſtance, altho' <lb/>none is
          mentioned. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Dr. Douglas obſerves, that the great <lb/>contractile power of the
          uterus is <w part="I">fa-</w><lb/><w part="F">vourable</w> to the proceſs of healing, by
          <lb/>bringing the divided parts more into <lb/>contact; <q >'but,' he ſays, 'the
            preſence <lb/>of any conſiderable extraneous <w part="I">ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ſtance</w>, even in the abdomen, ſeems, in <lb/>ſome degree to counteract this power
            of <lb/>contraction<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Douglas's caſe of
              ruptured uterus, p. 56. </note>.'</q> If the uterus after the <w part="I"
            >expul-</w><pb xml:id="page_71" n="73"/><lb/><w part="F">ſion</w> of its contents, does
          not <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tract</w> as in common parturition, we muſt
          <lb/>expect a conſiderable flooding. In the <lb/>above caſe, we are told that it was <w
            part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceſſive</w>. In the caſes of Mrs. Wilkins, <lb/>and the
          others which I have related as <lb/>lacerations of the vagina, the hemorrhage <lb/>was not
          very great<note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* That a conſiderable hemorrhage
            will follow, however, <lb/>from a laceration of the vagina, as well as from a rupture
            <lb/>of the uterus, we have the authority of Veſlingius. 'Bis <lb/>enim notavi, cum
            uteri vagina, ſecundum latus dextrum <lb/>eſſet diſrupta, quamvis foetus extinctus
            integre cum <w part="I">ſecun-</w><lb/><w part="F">dis</w> educeretur; ſubſequente ex
            laceratis hypogaſtricis vaſis <lb/>enormi ſanguinis profluvio, matrem paulo poſt fato <w
              part="I">pari-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> ceſſiſſe.'—J. Veſlingii obſerv. et epiſt.
            45. </note>, and the uterus was <lb/>found contracted to the uſual ſize it <lb/>would
          have been, in the ſame ſpace of <lb/>time, if no extraneous body had been in <lb/>the
          cavity of the abdomen. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In No. IX. from Steidele, it appears <lb/>that the head had eſcaped
          from the <lb/>rupture, he brought down the feet with <lb/>eaſe, but found ſome difficulty
          in <w part="I">ex-</w><pb xml:id="page_72" n="74"/><lb/><w part="F">tracing</w> the reſt
          of the foetus. This <w part="I">dif-</w><lb/><w part="F">faculty</w> muſt evidently have
          ariſen from <lb/>the ſtricture formed by the edges of the <lb/>rupture round the child's
          neck; whence <lb/>I think it cannot be conſidered as much <lb/>ſupport, to evince the eaſe
          with which <lb/>delivery is performed, any more than <lb/>the laſt caſe, where the patient
          expired <lb/>while the accoucheur was endeavouring <lb/>to bring the head through the
          pelvis. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Lacerations</hi> of the vagina, I have <lb/>before
          obſerved, have been taken notice <lb/>of by authors, yet it does not appear that <lb/>they
          have had any idea of the child's <lb/>eſcaping by ſuch means into the cavity <lb/>of the
          abdomen. If the caſe which gave <lb/>riſe to theſe obſervations, in which the <lb/>nature
          of the accident could not be <lb/>miſtaken, and my reaſoning on the <w part="I"
            >dif-</w><lb/><w part="F">ferent</w> caſes I have adduced, are <w part="I">allow-</w><pb
            xml:id="page_73" n="75"/><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> to have any weight, I think I may
          <lb/>venture to draw the following <w part="I">conclu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſions</w>. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Firſt, that the whole of the child <w part="I">eſ-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >capes</w>, into the cavity of the abdomen, <lb/>much oftener from a laceration of the
            <w part="I">va-</w><lb/><w part="F">gina</w> than from a rupture of the uterus. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Secondly, That, from the little <w part="I">diffi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >culty</w> with which delivery is <w part="I">accompliſh-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> in
          lacerations of the vagina, there is <lb/>a greater proſpect of recovery in ſuch
          <lb/>accidents, than when the uterus is the <lb/>ſeat of the injury. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>It is evident that the gloomy idea of <lb/>inevitable death has not
          only been the <lb/>means of checking ſuch endeavours as <lb/>might have been ſometimes
          ſucceſſful, <lb/>but that it has likewiſe been often the <lb/>means of preventing us from
          knowing <lb/>the real nature of the injury. I hope <lb/>practitioners in future will, from
          the <w part="I">for-</w><lb/><w part="F">tunate</w> event of the caſe of Mrs. <w part="I"
            >Man-</w><pb xml:id="page_74" n="76"/><lb/><w part="F">ning</w>, related by Dr. Douglas,
          and the <lb/>new light thrown on the ſubject by the <lb/>caſe I have related of Mrs.
          Wilkins, <lb/>entertain a more favourable opinion of <lb/>the ſucceſs likely to attend
          their <w part="I">endea-</w><lb/><w part="F">vours</w>, in a ſituation where nothing but
          <lb/>immediate delivery can afford the leaſt <lb/>proſpect of recovery. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>When firſt I made my private remarks <lb/>on Mrs. Wilkins's caſe, I
          did not intend <lb/>to enter further into the ſubject, than to <lb/>draw the caſe up ſair,
          and ſend it to <lb/>ſome periodical publication, as worthy <lb/>the attention of the
          medical world. But <lb/>the ſimilarity between it and that of Mrs. <lb/>Manning was ſo
          ſtriking, that the more <lb/>I conſidered it, the more reaſons I ſaw <lb/>to induce me to
          publiſh it in the <w part="I">pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſent</w> form. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The nature of the ſubjct has obliged <lb/>me to enter very fully into
          the merits <lb/>of Dr. Douglas's caſe. That he ſhould <lb/>be liable to
            cr<unclear>#</unclear> in forming an opinion <pb xml:id="page_75" n="77"/><lb/>on the
          nature of the accident, is not to <lb/>be wondered at, when we conſider how <lb/>ſilent
          authors have been upon it, and <lb/>how ſeldom accidents of this nature <w part="I"
            >oc-</w><lb/><w part="F">cur</w>. I have not the honour of being <lb/>known to him; but
          I am confident, <lb/>from the liberality of his ſentiments as <lb/>a gentleman, that he
          will not conſider <lb/>the liberty I have taken as perſonal, or <lb/>in any other light
          than as a diſcharge <lb/>of the duty every man in the profeſſion <lb/>owes to the world.
          It has a claim upon <lb/>us to elucidate any occult part of the <lb/>ſcience, and every
          man is bound by the <lb/>laws of humanity to comply with it, <lb/>whenever an opportunity
          offers. <w part="I">Ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">empla</w> rara non reticenda, etiam cauſa
          <lb/>incognita; ita enim ſcitu digna infinita <lb/>præteribuntur. </p>
        <trailer rend="align-center"><lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
