<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Fournel: An essay on somnambulism, or sleep-walking</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>M. Jean-François Fournel</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">An essay on somnambulism, or sleep-walking: produced by animal
              electricity and magnetism. As well as by sympathy, &amp;c. As performed by the Rev.
              John Bell, Member of the Philosophical Harmonic Society of France, Fellow
              Correspondent to the Museum at Paris, and the Only Person Authorised to Teach and
              Practise that Science in Great Britain, Ireland, &amp;c.</title>
            <edition n="2"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T99653</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T99653"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Dublin</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Dublin: printed for, and to be had of the author, also of Mr. Butler, No.
                  2, Grafton-Street, and other booksellers, MDCCLXXXVIII.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1788</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="3"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="38"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3307578637</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K080184.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: disease"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_1"/>
        <p rend="align-center">
          <lb/>AN <lb/><hi rend="size(2)">ESSAY</hi>
          <lb/>ON <lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)">SOMNAMBULISM</hi>, <lb/>OR <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)"
            >SLEEP-WALKING</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="size(0.5)">PRODUCED BY</hi>
          <lb/>Animal Electricity and Magnetiſm. </p>
        <p rend="align-center">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">As well as by Sympathy, </hi><hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="2"/>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_5"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>AN <lb/><hi rend="size(1.7)">ESSAY </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(0.5)">ON THE PROBABILITIES OF </hi>
        <lb/>Electrical and Magnetical Somnambules, <lb/><hi rend="size(0.5)">OR</hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">SLEEP-WALKERS</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">O</hi>F all the novelties which are created by Animal Electricity and
        Magnetiſm, Somnambuliſm is, doubtleſs, <lb/>the moſt intereſting. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By Somnambuliſm is meant that peculiar ſtate when the <lb/>ſenſes are ſuſpended between
        ſleeping and waking; partak- <lb/>ing of both, and is alſo productive of many phœnomena,
        which each are ſtrangers to. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The patient being reduced to a ſtate of Somnambuliſm, <lb/>without touching him, is
        deaf to all that is near him: <lb/>Motionleſs amidſt the greateſt motions; he ſeems
        ſeparated <lb/>from nature, as if it were, to communicate only with <lb/>the perſon who put
        him into that ſtate. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The latter, owing to Magnetiſation alone, has an inti- <lb/>mate analogy with the
        patient; by the means of a kind of <lb/>an inviſible leaver, he cauſes him to move at his
        pleaſure; <lb/>and ſuch is the power of his influence, that he not only <lb/>makes himſelf
        underſtood by ſpeaking and ſigns, but even <lb/>by the very thought itſelf; and what is
        ſtill more extraor- <lb/>dinary, the Magnetiſer can, by a ſingle contract, commu- <pb
          xml:id="page_6" n="6"/>
        <lb/>nicate his faculty to other people; and from that moment <lb/>there is a conſtant
        communication between the Somnambule <lb/>and his new director. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The patient being put into a ſtate of Somnambuliſm, there <lb/>is in him a want of
        organization, which breaks the equili- <lb/>brium of his ſenſes; ſo that ſome experience an
        extreme <lb/>degradation, whilſt others acquire a prodigious degree of <lb/>ſubtlety. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thus, ſome have their hearing entirely loſt or weakened, <lb/>and their ſight becomes
        prodigiouſly penetrating. In others, <lb/>the privation, both of ſight and hearing, are
        amply com- <lb/>penſated by an incredible delicacy both of feeling and <lb/>taſte. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And in many, a ſixth ſenſe appears to declare itſelf by an <lb/>extreme extent of the
        intellectual faculty, far ſuperior to the <lb/>common altitude of the human mind. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In a word, the phœnomena, attending on the ſtate of <lb/>Somnambuliſm, daily offer new
        ſubjects of aſtoniſhment, <lb/>even to thoſe who ought to be more familiar with them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It remains to conſider, whether thoſe pretended phœno- <lb/>mena are ſuch as is
        propagated; or, whether on the <lb/>contrary, they are nothing the but illuſions, kept up by
        the <lb/>impoſition of ſome ill deſigned perſons and the credulity of <lb/>others. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For it is well known that the human mind, naturally bent <lb/>towards every thing
        marvellous, eagerly ſeizes on whatever <lb/>is flattering to the taſte; and there are
        exalted geniuſſes to <lb/>be found that employ both their head and talents to realize
        <lb/>mere chimeras. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Among the perſons who have been witneſſes to the ſingu- <lb/>larities attending on
        Somnambuliſm, ſome ſtruck with aſto- <lb/>niſhment and admiration, have given full credit to
        its influ- <lb/>ence, and look on it as an irreſiſtible proof of Animal <lb/>Electricity and
        Magnetiſm. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Others, though convinced of the reality of its phœnomena, <lb/>are yet incredulous with
        regard to the cauſe which produced <lb/>them. They had rather ſuppoſe in this affair ſome
        ſecret <lb/>ſpring productive of illuſions; and, though incapable of <lb/>comprehending
        thoſe means of intelligence, they have, <lb/>nevertheleſs, ſuppoſed their exiſtence;
        alledging, for exam- <lb/>ple, thoſe cunning tricks which a ſubtle philoſopher <note
          place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Caumus and Pinetty. </note> made <lb/>uſe to
        aſtoniſh all Paris and London during many years. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_7" n="7"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As to the Phyſicians, moſt of them have diſdained to <lb/>prove witneſſes to the
        eſſects of Magnetical Somnambuliſm, <lb/>under the pretence that it was ſufficient for them
        ſuch a <lb/>phœnomenon was contrary to thoſe notions conſecrated in <lb/>phyſic and
        phyſiology; they have conſidered thoſe pretended <lb/>marvels as mere chimeras unworthy a
        ſerious examination. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There was even a learned body who went ſo far as to for- <lb/>bid their members to
        entertain the leaſt doubt on the ſubject, <lb/>and expelled from their ſociety whomſoever
        have given <lb/>themſelves up to the ſtudy of this new doctrine <note place="bottom" n="†"
          rend="size(0.5)">† A decree of the faculty of Paris, 1784, which is the ſame as they
          <lb/>did for inoculation, which is now adopted by them. </note>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>However, on the other hand, Magnetical Somnambuliſm <lb/>becomes daily more and more
        conſiſtent; a great number of <lb/>people remarkable for their learning, probity, found
        judg- <lb/>ment and ſagacity, certify beyond a doubt the reality of <lb/>Magnetical
        Somnambuliſm; and that contradiction of re- <lb/>ſpectable authorities on both ſides, leave
        the public in ſuſ- <lb/>pence, who, to take a deciſive part in the conteſt, impati-
        <lb/>ently wait until the matter is more fully inveſtigated. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The following impartial reflections may ſerve to fix the <lb/>opinion of impartial
        people on the ſubject of Magnetical <lb/>Somnambuliſm. To treat this object with the more
        ſucceſs, <lb/>I think it is neceſſary to divide the diſcuſſion into three <lb/>parts. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The firſt point to be conſidered, is to know, in fact, the <lb/>public have been
        witneſſes of phœnomena of ſome impor- <lb/>tance, well deſerving to excite their curioſity,
        and of which <lb/>the cauſe ought to be inveſtigated. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Secondly, ſuppoſe the effects ſpoken of deſerved to be <lb/>enquired into, it is proper
        to examine whether they cannot <lb/>reaſonably be ſuſpected of artifice. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Laſtly, admitting it impoſſible to find out the artifice, it <lb/>will remain to
        examine whether they are contrary to com- <lb/>mon notions already received. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="1">
        <lb/>1ſt. Are Magnetical Somnambuliſm phœnomena of ſuch <lb/>an importance as to deſerve the
        curioſity of both the public <lb/>and the learned? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The object of this queſtion is, I believe, very plain and <lb/>obvious; I mean to ſay,
        that previouſly to our being at the <lb/>trouble of examining whether Magnetical
        Somnambuliſm <lb/>be an illuſion, or reality, we muſt eſtabliſh, that, there <pb
          xml:id="page_8" n="8"/>
        <lb/>exiſt, at leaſt ſeemingly, ſome ſingularities which concern <lb/>both the public good
        and the improvement of learning. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Many people, however, might have a right to doubt it, <lb/>becauſe they had no occaſion
        to know the truth of the aſſer- <lb/>tion. They have a right to require to be ſatisfied,
        previ- <lb/>ouſly to the diſcuſſion of the two following propoſitions, viz. <q rend="quotes"
          >That there are either at Paris, Dublin, &amp;c. in the provin- <lb/>ces, or any where
          elſe ſome people, who being naturally <lb/>forced into a ſtate of ſleep, really offer the
          phœnomena which <lb/>we are about to examine. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For if it was not certain that ſuch a ſcene is not to be <lb/>met with ſomewhere, it
        would be a loſs of time to enquire <lb/>into its principle. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is, therefore, a preliminary obligation for any body <lb/>elſe, to eſtabliſh well
        the exiſtence of Magnetical Somnam- <lb/>buliſm, whether right or wrong. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This point was, for a long time, a matter of general <lb/>incredulity. They plainly
        denied that there were any ſuch <lb/>individuals exiſting any where, and the very diſcourſe
        held <lb/>on the ſubject, was looked upon merely as a fable to amuſe <lb/>the public. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The firſt writing, which treated of Magnetical Somnam- <lb/>buliſts, was, if I am not
        miſtaken, a letter from Mr. Cloquet, <lb/>paymaſter of rents at Soiſſons, who, relating what
        he had ſeen at <lb/>Buzanci's treatment, by the Marquis de Puyſegur, <lb/>inſinuated
        ſomething which ſeemed to characteriſe Magne- <lb/>tical Somnambuliſm. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Since that letter, a gentleman, whoſe candor is above all <lb/>ſuſpicion, has conſigned
        in a writing, which is, in every <lb/>reſpect, intereſting, ſeveral phœnomena he had
        obſerved in <lb/><unclear>P</unclear>uzócanci's treatment, ſtill more wonderful than thoſe
        which <lb/>Mr. Cloquet had given a sketch of. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The peruſal of this performance having inſpired ſome <lb/>people of the firſt rank with
        the eager deſire of being wit- <lb/>neſſes to a like Somnambuliſm, the author of the above
        found <lb/>an opportunity of gratifying their curioſity at Paris, in the <lb/>winter of
        1785. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>More than 5000 people have been at liberty to ſee thoſe <lb/>phœnomena true or falſe,
        of which notice was taken both <lb/>in the national and foreign prints. Theſe Somnambules
        un- <lb/>derwent repeated trials, which all met with more or leſs <lb/>ſucceſs. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_9" n="9"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Beſides thoſe mentioned, many more were made at Paris, <lb/>or in ſome other provinces.
        This Somnambuliſm example <lb/>having induced the Magnetiſers to adhere to that part of
        <lb/>Magnetiſm, they applied themſelves to it with more zeal, <lb/>as it ſeemed to be a ſure
        way towards a remedy. Thus, the <lb/>concern of Magnetiſm, and that of the patient, uniting
        <lb/>both to preſcribe that mode of proceeding, it is become the <lb/>common object of all
        Magnetiſers attempts, and in all <lb/>treatment they gloried in ſhewing ſome patient more or
        leſs <lb/>improved. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is evident then that there exiſts many individuals <lb/>ſtruck with a ſeeming
        Somnambuliſm; and I begin to eſta- <lb/>bliſh the queſtion, in order to proceed
        methodically, after <lb/>ſettling conſtant and notorious facts, which might lead to
        <lb/>infallible conſequences. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is then certain and indiſputable, that there are pre- <lb/>tended Somnambules, which
        offer wonderful phœnomena <lb/>to the ſpectators, as compenſative gratification for excited
        <lb/>curioſity. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Now, the queſtion is to know what opinion we ſhould <lb/>form concerning thoſe
        Somnambules; if it be not a feigned <lb/>ſtate, by the means of which they endeavour to
        impoſe on <lb/>the credulity of thoſe whom they are ſurrounded by. </p>
      <p rend="indent" n="2">
        <lb/>2d. How far are Magnetical Somnambules to be be- <lb/>lieved? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Among the Somnambules I am here ſpeaking of, I do <lb/>not include that multitude of
        perſons of both ſexes among <lb/>the common people, <hi rend="italic">who are to be ſeen at
          ſome impoſtors,</hi> and <lb/>may reaſonably be ſuſpected to perform Somnambuliſm,
        <lb/>through imitation, or to make themſelves intereſting, and <lb/>others who are paid for
        it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is a misfortune, conſtantly attending on good things, <lb/>that they can never be
        preſerved in their native purity, nor <lb/>eſcape that mixture which malice or cupidity
        ſeldom fail to <lb/>blend with them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thoſe who, either through prejudice or intereſt, endea- <lb/>vour to diſplay the
        diſcovery, take care to examine it on that <lb/>ſide only, which ſeems to convey an idea of
        apparent <lb/>quackery, and never fail to preſent it to the public in that <lb/>view. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But thoſe who ſincerely wiſh for information, pay but <lb/>little regard to ſuch a
        conſideration, and throwing aſide <lb/>quackery and exaggerations, carefully penetrate as
        far as the <pb xml:id="page_10" n="10"/>
        <lb/>principle itſelf. Thus, a botaniſt, deſirous of procuring <lb/>the fruit of an Almond
        to be enabled to diſcern its true <lb/>quality, is not diſcouraged by the putrid fleſh which
        ſur- <lb/>rounds it; but chearfully lopping all nauſeous ſuperfluities, <lb/>he finds at
        laſt the fruit which is to be the rule of his ſtudy. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In that manner ſhould every unbiaſſed man act, who <lb/>ſincerely ſeeks for truth,
        without having intereſt or deſign to <lb/>deſtroy it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Let us contemptuouſly diſregard thoſe ſuſpicious apparent <lb/>Somnambules, and attend
        to thoſe who, by their civil exiſt- <lb/>ence, their character, manner, &amp;c. are above
        ſuſpicion; <lb/>and in whom, beſides Somnambuliſm, the ſcience is por- <lb/>trayed, and
        brought to the higheſt degree of perfection. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I think thoſe ought to be choſen among patients, in whom <lb/>Somnambuliſm appears to
        be in a higher degree of perfec- <lb/>tion, and ſuch a caution is, in my opinion, very
        material. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In fact, the more imperfect the Somnambule is, the eaſier <lb/>it is to impoſe; if he
        badly anſwers your ſigns, and follows <lb/>your motions in an untoward and ill contrived
        manner, he <lb/>apologizes by ſaying he is not, as yet, arrived to a ſtate of <lb/>perfect
        Somnambuliſm, and the obſervator, who really <lb/>conceives that ſuch a ſtate muſt have its
        degrees, is puzzled, <lb/>on account of his not knowing whether the bad ſucceſs he <lb/>has
        experienced is to be attributed to the untowardneſs of <lb/>the Somnambule, or the
        imperfection of his ſtate. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But when I fix on a Somnambule, recommended as a <lb/>perfect being, it is evident that
        this task is very painful. In <lb/>that caſe, there is neither excuſe nor pretence; the
        obſer- <lb/>vator is eaſy, and Somnambuliſm has a trial to undergo, <lb/>which is to prove
        either his ſhame or his triumph. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Such perfect Somnambules have not been wanting laſt <lb/>year in France; and among
        thoſe who have tried my expe- <lb/>riments, there is one with whom I ſtaid more than half an
        <lb/>hour, and who has before me, and at my pleaſure, executed <lb/>ſuch motions as I
        preſcribed him. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Being at my own diſpoſal, without witneſſes and contra- <lb/>dictors, left nothing
        untried to diſcover the fraud, if there <lb/>had been in the caſe; but the ſwiftneſs of his
        evolutions, <lb/>the preciſion of his movements, a vaſt number of facts which <lb/>it would
        be too tedious to relate, diſconcerted all my at- <lb/>tempts. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_11" n="11"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Many other experiments, which had their intended effects <lb/>with regard to other
        perfect Somnambules, have all given <lb/>me the ſame ſatisfaction. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There are at Paris, and in the provinces, more than 600 <lb/>perſons, who are in the
        ſame predicament. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Therefore, to overthrow the conſequences reſulting from <lb/>ſuch experiments, there is
        no other reſource left, but to <lb/>perſevere in giving out that it was a deceitful trick on
        the part <lb/>of Somnambules. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But ſuch a ſuppoſition carries with it the greateſt difficul- <lb/>ties, and is
        accompanied by improbabilities ſtill more ſhock- <lb/>ing than Somnambuliſm itſelf. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To admit that the phœnomena in queſtion are the reſult <lb/>of impoſition, two things
        are abſolutely required: <list>
          <lb/>
          <item>1ſt. Somnambules muſt have an intention of deceiving. </item>
          <lb/>
          <item>2d. They muſt be endowed with an addreſs to do it. <lb/>But, we muſt firſt confeſs,
            that, among thoſe who have <lb/>already been or are daily inſpired with Somnambuliſm,
            there <lb/>are many above all kind of ſuſpicion. They are reſpectable <lb/>women of
            family, men of ſtability and known integrity, <lb/>people of a plain and ſimple turn of
            mind, children, &amp;c. <lb/>in whom we cannot reaſonably ſuppoſe to exiſt any deſign
            <lb/>or intereſt, to ſeign a like ſituation. </item>
        </list>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Should they be led by any faction, or the intention of per- <lb/>forming Animal
        Electricity and Magnetiſm with any ſeem- <lb/>ing reality? But moſt of them have no concern
        at all, as to <lb/>the fortune of Animal Electricity and Magnetiſm; nay, <lb/>many of them
        had no notion of it at the moment they were <lb/>confirming Magnetical ſleep. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Shall it be ſaid, that, it is poſſible ſome of thoſe indivi- <lb/>duals are encouraged
        by the partiſans of Animal Electricity <lb/>and Magnetiſm, and that they are but a mere
        inſtrument in <lb/>the hands of the latter to favour the ſucceſs of that ſyſtem? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But, for what purpoſe ſhould the partiſans of Animal <lb/>Electricity and Magnetiſm
        have recourſe to ſo capricious a <lb/>ſtratagem? The ſuppoſition, would, at the beſt, be ad-
        <lb/>miſſible, if Somnambuliſm had originally been announced <lb/>as a neceſſary effect of
        Magnetiſm; ſo that they muſt have <lb/>been forced to reſign Animal Electricity and
        Magnetiſm, <lb/>had they been deprived of the reſource tendered them by <lb/>Somnambuliſm:
        but the caſe is very different. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Animal Electricity and Magnetiſm was originally an- <lb/>nounced without the attendance
        of Somnambuliſm. This <pb xml:id="page_12" n="12"/>
        <lb/>ſingularity is a later diſcovery, the reſult of the habitual <lb/>practice of
        Magnetiſm. Even now, there are many Magne- <lb/>tiſers who do not look on Somnambuliſm as
        being an effen- <lb/>tial part of the ſcience, but only as an acceſſary which may
        <lb/>indifferently be united to, or ſeparated from Magnetiſm. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From whence it plainly follows, that if the partiſans of <lb/>Animal Electricity and
        Magnetiſm were in want of a re- <lb/>ſource to impoſe on the public, ſurely they muſt have
        been <lb/>very deſtitute of penetration to embrace ſo ſtrange a <lb/>manœuvre, which carried
        with it a prodigious complication <lb/>of ſprings, and inſuperable difficulties in its
        execution. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And, that had it been an artifice, it would have been <lb/>ſufficient to deter every
        honeſt man from entering or aſſoci- <lb/>ating with it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They muſt then, have only dealt with, and choſen peo- <lb/>ple of profligate manners,
        and of the worſt ſort, to inveſt <lb/>them with that confidence, at the risk of ſeeing it
        betrayed, <lb/>and made public on the very next day. That is not all, they <lb/>muſt have
        found in thoſe individuals an extraordinary ad- <lb/>dress to act ſo difficult a part, and
        deceive the experiments <lb/>of an enlightened and incredulous people, at whoſe tribunal<lb/>
        appearance muſt be made. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Had things been thus tranſacted, Somnambuliſm could not <lb/>have laſted long, and far
        from gaining credit, time would <lb/>ſoon have diſcovered the illuſion and deceit, by the
        difficulty <lb/>of finding actors capable of perpetrating the impoſture. <lb/>But the
        contrary has happened; every day Somnambuliſm <lb/>gets new partiſans, and the credit which
        it conſtantly ob- <lb/>tains, partiſans, and the credit which it conſtantly ob- <lb/>tains,
        plainly contradicts every idea of deceit. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Patients are daily ſeen in that condition, in the very boſom <lb/>of their family,
        under the inſpection of their neareſt rela- <lb/>tions, and thoſe who are the moſt
        intereſted to verify their <lb/>ſituation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Who could believe that ſuch patients, ſurrounded with <lb/>the very horrors of death
        and moſt painful ſufferings, could <lb/>diſſemble for the ſole intereſt of Magnetiſm? Their
        relations, <lb/>fathers, husbands, wives, children—are they then concerned <lb/>in the piot? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Shall it be ſaid that their illneſs is feigned? It is another <lb/>ſuppoſition no leſs
        admiſſible; for beſides that it is no eaſy <lb/>matter to feign a malignant fever, a
        fiuxion, dropſy, and <lb/>other diſeaſes of that kind, there are ſome ſo well averred <pb
          xml:id="page_13" n="13"/>
        <lb/>that no man in his ſenſes could poſſibly doubt their exiſt- <lb/>ence. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Another conſideration may be added here, that is, even in <lb/>ſuppoſing that a healthy
        man could long act the part of a <lb/>ſick man, or the patient take upon himſelf to act the
        Som- <lb/>nambule; and, that people hidden before the curtain, ſhould <lb/>preſide over this
        mummery, I maintain would be impoſſible <lb/>in the execution; and whatever addreſs may be
        ſuppoſed to <lb/>exiſt on both ſides, the deceit muſt ſoon be diſcovered, and, <lb/>indeed,
        after a few moments, I would defy the moſt nim- <lb/>ble buffoon, the moſt expert of all,
        and the moſt inured to <lb/>bodily exerciſes, to aſſect Somnambuliſm before ſcientific
        <lb/>perſons, or execute any ſuch thing as is obſerved among the <lb/>Somnambules, whom I am
        now treating of. I defy any one <lb/>to remain during eight or ten hours, having his eyes
        ſhut, <lb/>and his eyelids quite cloſe together, without one eyelid ſe- <lb/>parating from
        the other during that period of time. Such a <lb/>perſeverance ſeems to be much above the
        reach of human <lb/>power and patience. Who is the man that could remain five <lb/>or ſix
        hours in a motionleſs attitude, without ſhewing the <lb/>leaſt ſenſation of what paſſes
        round him, inacceſſible to every <lb/>emotion, and all the ſudden and unforeſeen ſhocks of
        noiſe <lb/>which his attention ſhall, at periods, be gratified with? <lb/>Who is that
        hiſtrion, ſubtle enough to imitate, with his <lb/>eyes cloſely ſhut, the different ſigns
        which will be preſented <lb/>him, and deſcribe the lines which will be traced with a juſt-
        <lb/>ness and acuteneſs, that no interval ſhall be found between <lb/>the order and the
        compliance. A few experiments of this <lb/>nature would be ſufficient to diſcourage the moſt
        conſum- <lb/>mate Saltimbank, and make him give up his undertaking <lb/>in two hours time. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Now, when we ſee the ſame effects conſtantly repeated, <lb/>without the leaſt effort,
        and multiplied in the preſence of a <lb/>prodigious number of perſons of all ſexes, age, and
        rank, we <lb/>muſt neceſſarily acknowledge that they act through a natural <lb/>impulſe,
        without any aſſiſtance of art: for it is well known <lb/>that nature can eaſily perfect what
        is impoſſible for art to <lb/>execute. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thus, phyſical probabilities concur with moral ones to <lb/>eſtabliſh the reality of
        Magnetical Somnambuliſm.—Som- <lb/>nambuliſm cannot be rejected, without ſuppoſing it a
        deceit <lb/>too palpable to credit, and in whatever manner you act, it <lb/>will prove a
        phœnomenon, either moral or phyſical; and I <pb xml:id="page_14" n="14"/>
        <lb/>confeſs the latter is, by far, eaſier to be conceived than the <lb/>former; for a
        natural phœnomenon, after all, is ſuſcepti- <lb/>ble of an explanation; and the plot of a
        deceit, without in- <lb/>tereſt and motive whatever, is no leſs complicated in its
        <lb/>execution. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A number of people are to be found over whom ſuch con- <lb/>ſiderations, ſtriking as
        they are, can never triumph. What- <lb/>ever difficulties may be encountered with, to make
        thoſe <lb/>ſtratagems ſucceed, they ſuppoſe that ſuch an addreſs takes <lb/>place, becauſe
        they ſay in the things hurtful to reaſon, the <lb/>authority of teſtimonies is of no value. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That evident impoſſibility is a kind of reſentment on that <lb/>part of the public who
        have not ſeen the phœnomena in queſ- <lb/>tion, and inſpire thoſe who have actually ſeen
        them, with <lb/>a certain degree of diffidence. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If a common fact, conſiſtent with the uſual proceedings <lb/>of nature, was only
        agitated, it is in general confeſſed, that <lb/>there would be more proofs than requiſite to
        eſtabliſh its <lb/>credit, on bare words and without having ſeen it. But as <lb/>to a
        phœnomenon, ſo little conſiſtent with nature, which is <lb/>neither explicable nor
        conceivable, and overthrows all re- <lb/>ceived notions, we are authoriſed not only to
        refuſe the teſ- <lb/>timony of others, but even that of our own ſenſes. It is <lb/>after
        ſuch an abſurdity that many learned have been heard <lb/>to ſay, <q rend="quotes">That they
          would not believe it if they ſaw it.</q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Now then it remains to conſider, whether Magnetical <lb/>Somnambuliſm, and the ſeveral
        phœnomena uſually attend- <lb/>ing on it, are as inconceivable as thoſe gentlemen would
        <lb/>inſinuate. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Are Magnetical Somnambuliſms phœnomena repugnant <lb/>to the order of nature? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Phyſicians by affecting the greateſt incredulity in <lb/>Magnetical Somnambuliſm, under
        the mere pretence that <lb/>ſuch phœnomenon is inconceivable, give no ſatisfactory
        <lb/>account of their disbelief, becauſe, that the identical diffi- <lb/>culty they attempt
        to condemn, cannot withhold the victori- <lb/>ous teſtimonies which militate in favour of
        Magnetical <lb/>Somnambuliſm. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The difficulty of conceiving a phœnomenon, by no mean <lb/>deſtroys its reality; we are
        ſurrounded with a multitude of <lb/>natural marvels, which no one has the leaſt doubt about,
        <lb/>though they are incomprehenſible; for it is evident that <pb xml:id="page_15" n="15"/>
        <lb/>nature has preſcribed certain limits which are inacceſſible to <lb/>human conception. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But, perhaps, ſome will ſay, <q rend="quotes">From ſuch a mode of <lb/>reaſoning it
          will then follow that we muſt give credit to <lb/>every abſurdity we hear, and believe the
          greateſt oddities <lb/>in the world; and thoſe who will exact ſuch a belief, ſhall
          <lb/>only have to invoke the great power of nature, and the <lb/>immenſe extent of its
          reſources. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">That way of reaſoning would deprive arts of their rules, <lb/>and baniſh
          principles from ſciences, in order to make room <lb/>for raſh aſſertions, &amp;c. our
          learning, inſtead of being <lb/>ſuſceptible of improvement and enlargement, would fall
          <lb/>again into chaos and confuſion. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But that objection is, by no means applicable; for the <lb/>queſtion is not to admit a
        phœnomenon under the ſingle con- <lb/>ſideration that nothing is impoſſible to nature; it
        is, on the <lb/>contrary, recommended that we ſhould ſubmit to the trial <lb/>of
        contradiction, experience, and reaſoning itſelf, a fact <lb/>certified by a multitude of
        perſons of every denomination <lb/>who have been eye witneſſes to the ſame. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thus, till now, preſumption is ſtill in favour of Somnam- <lb/>buliſm, ſince being
        grounded on the ſtrongeſt conſidera- <lb/>tions; thoſe conſiderations are neither overcome
        nor weak- <lb/>ened by the pretended improbability urged againſt them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But what will then be ſaid, if we were to diſcover that <lb/>Magnetical Somnambuliſm?
        far from offering to the learned <lb/>an inconceivable phœnomenon, incompatible with all
        notions <lb/>admitted both in phyſic and phyſiology; it is on the contrary, <lb/>a natural
        conſequence from thoſe very principles, acceſſary <lb/>of the common notions with which it
        is blended and united <lb/>in a very natural manner? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is what I propoſe to demonſtrate, and in order to <lb/>proceed methodically, I ſhall
        firſt ſucceſſively examine the <lb/>two articles of Magnetical Somnambuliſm, which have ex-
        <lb/>cited the reclamation of the doctors. 1ſt. The facility of <lb/>putting a patient in a
        ſtate of Somnambuliſm. 2d. The <lb/>phœnomena uſually attending on ſuch a ſtate. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Article 1ſt. The Somnambuliſm's communication is <lb/>in the order of the already
        admitted notions in phyſi- <lb/>ology. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is ſomething remarkable to hear many learned men ob- <lb/>ſtinately declare it to be
        abſolutely impoſſible for a patient to <lb/>be put in a ſtate of Somnambuliſm, by any art
        whatever, <pb xml:id="page_16" n="16"/>
        <lb/>when we conſider that it is one of the favourite maxims in <lb/>phyſic, that by the
        aſſiſtance of art all natural revolutions <lb/>may be imitated in the human body. It is on
        that principle <lb/>that the partiſans of inoculation chiefly relied to defend both <lb/>the
        practice and ſucceſs of that proceeding. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>All phyſicians agree, that the art of inoculation conſiſts in <lb/>preventing by a
        factitious indiſpoſition in an individual, <lb/>the real one which nature would have ſoon or
        late oc- <lb/>caſioned. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is ſtill according to the ſame maxim, that phyſicians <lb/>attempt to inoculate many
        kinds of diſtempers, either to <lb/>prevent them, or to make them ſerve as a counterpoiſe to
        <lb/>other diſeaſes; and now the art of curing one diſeaſe by <lb/>another, is eſteemed in
        medicine as a compleat knowledge of <lb/>phyſic. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The caſe being thus, and ſince it is acknowledged that na- <lb/>ture is liable to
        imitation, by introducing ſuch or ſuch <lb/>maladies in the human body, is it ſo ſtrange, ſo
        inconceiv- <lb/>able, that Somnambuliſm ſhould alſo be tranſmiſſible through <lb/>artificial
        means? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Somnambuliſm is by phyſicians entitled a diſeaſe; it is, <lb/>therefore, in that
        quality as in the number of thoſe revolu- <lb/>tions which the power of art introduces. To
        that effect one <lb/>more ſtep is to be made in the career of diſtempers, and ino-
        <lb/>culation: but ſuch an extenſion, far from contradicting the <lb/>principles of
        phyſiology, only confirms them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is expected, however, that phyſicians will oppoſe this <lb/>ſimilitude, in
        eſtabliſhing ſome differences and diſtinctions; <lb/>nay, they will perhaps forget
        themſelves ſo far as to take <lb/>Somnambuliſm from the number of maladies, by diſowning
        <lb/>their noſologiſts in this point. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That no pretence may be left for ſubterfuge, we ſhall be <lb/>intent on maladies and
        diſcourſe ſolely on ſleep. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Neither doctor, or natural philoſophers, have as yet been <lb/>able to explain the
        cauſe of ſleep, nor the manner by which <lb/>it is produced. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Whatever has been ſaid on the ſubject offers nothing but <lb/>mere conjectures, the
        work of imagination; one thing only <lb/>is certain, that ſleep comes on whenever the body
        is in any <lb/>diſpoſition to produce it, and is put in ſuch a diſpoſition by <lb/>the
        aſſiſtance of art. Such is the evident effect of narcotical <lb/>piants, as opium,
        cockle-weed, &amp;c. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_17" n="17"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Now; if there exiſts any art whatever conducive to put the <lb/>body in a diſpoſition
        to ſleep, it is not ſurpriſing at all that <lb/>Magnetical proceedings might alſo produce
        the ſame effect. <lb/>Will they ſay that there is a want of ſimilitude, becauſe in
        <lb/>Magnetical proceedings neither decoctions nor infuſions are <lb/>employed to create
        ſleep? I anſwer that there is no need at <lb/>all to have recourſe either to drink, or any
        drug whatever, <lb/>to convert any one into the ſtate of ſleep; the ſame effect is
        <lb/>produced by a multitude of other means and proceedings; <lb/>and it is even one of the
        particular ſingularities inherent to <lb/>ſleep, that it is produced by an infinitely
        different number of <lb/>cauſes, and which are all contrary to each other. For ex-
        <lb/>ample, if exceſſive heat cauſes ſleep, it is alſo the effect of <lb/>exceſſive cold.
        Soldiers have been ſeen to fall aſleep on the <lb/>ſnow, and even periſh with cold in that
        ſtate of drowſi- <lb/>ness. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If gentle and ſoft friction invite to ſleep, exquiſite ſuffer- <lb/>ings act the ſame;
        which is proved by the example of thoſe <lb/>wretches, who being put to the torture, fall
        aſleep at the <lb/>very moment of their moſt poignant ſufferings. Others are <lb/>ſaid to
        have yielded to ſleep while lying on the wheel. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Gemelli Carreri relates, that when in China he travelled <lb/>with a Tartar, who, every
        night, was obliged, in order to <lb/>procure ſleep, to deſire ſomebody to beat him for a
        while on <lb/>the belly, as they do a drum. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Hunger and the exceſs of food, fatigue and reſt, and cool <lb/>and warm refreſhments
        likewiſe produce ſleep; it is alſo the <lb/>reſult of the increaſe or decreaſe of the blood
        running in the <lb/>brain. It is the effect of bathing as well as bleeding: fever,
        <lb/>which cauſes inſomnies, likewiſe creates drowſineſs; a ſmall <lb/>difference in a doſe
        of wine awakes or makes a man ſleep. <lb/>It would be an endleſs task to ſum up all the
        various cauſe, <lb/>which induce man to that ſtate; whether becauſe theſe <lb/>cauſes
        produce themſelves, or that many different combina- <lb/>tions are likewiſe capable of
        producing ſleep, or becauſe, <lb/>notwithſtanding the ſeeming diſſerence, the reſult is the
        <lb/>ſame. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But in both caſes, one muſt confeſs that the means <lb/>productive of ſleep are
        infinite, and that we are unable to <lb/>determine on their nature or quality. This
        conſideration <lb/>alone, doubtleſs, ſuffices to deſtroy the improbability of a <lb/>ſleep
        ariſing from Magnetical feelings. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thoſe means, which at firſt ſeem ſo extraordinary, ap- <pb xml:id="page_18" n="18"/>
        <lb/>pear far leſs marvellous when compared with others ſtill <lb/>more ſtrange, concerning
        which, not a doubt can be rea- <lb/>ſonably entertained, ſuch as thoſe as have juſt now been
        <lb/>mentioned. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The efficacy of ſimply touching to create ſleep, ſeems be- <lb/>ſides to be a neceſſary
        conſequence, flowing from the general <lb/>law of nature, that has deſigned the five ſenſes
        to ſerve as an <lb/>introduction to ſleep. If touching could not produce it, <lb/>it would
        be the only one deprived of that faculty. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Indeed, if we conſider but a moment the four other <lb/>ſenſes, hearing, ſmelling,
        ſight and taſte, we ſhall perceive <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">them</hi> as many conductors to
        ſleep. No one can deny but <lb/>the ear is a very efficacious way to ſleep: the noiſe of a
        mill, <lb/>the murmur of a river, the ſpouting of waters, a lingering <lb/>converſation, the
        monotony of the voice, a ſlow and melan- <lb/>choly muſic organize the body, more or leſs
        quickly, in a <lb/>manner fit for ſleep. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſmell of aromatical and narcotical plants occaſions a <lb/>drowſineſs, and ſome
        chymiſts have in their works given the <lb/>receipt of ſomniſerous eſſences, which criminals
        have often <lb/>abuſed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Taſte is another introductor to ſleep, and medicine eſta- <lb/>bliſhes thoſe means in
        adminiſtering narcotical phyſics, <lb/>either to procure ſleep to thoſe who naturally want
        it, or to <lb/>render patients inſenſible to painful operations. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is to be obſerved that moſt of the drugs productive of <lb/>that effect, diſplay
        their power, before they have been de- <lb/>compoſed in the ſtomach, even before they are
        come down <lb/>to it, merely by contract of the palate, or tongue; which <lb/>plainly ſhews
        that ſuch an effect belongs to the taſte. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Laſtly, the ſight is no leſs productive of ſleep. Too bright <lb/>a light, by inviting
        the eyelids to ſhut themſelves, inſenſibly <lb/>encourages and cauſes ſleep. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is alſo well known how far reading contributes to in- <lb/>vite ſleep. Many people
        never reſiſt that impreſſion, and even <lb/> they make, upon occaſion, a ſure reſource of
        it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>And it muſt not be ſaid that ſleep is then the effect of <lb/>tediouſenſs, ſince ſleep
        is, for the moſt part, involuntary, <lb/>and comes on in the middle of the intereſting
        lectures we <lb/>could hear other people deliver, without feeling the leaſt <lb/>propenſity
        to ſleep. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is then, doubtleſs, ſight, which in that caſe, ſerves <lb/>as a vehicle to ſleep. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_19" n="19"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From whence it follows, that it is clearly proved that <lb/>ſleep comes in through five
        of our ſenſes; now that obſer- <lb/>vation naturally leads us to think that touching is
        endowed <lb/>with the like power, becauſe the conſtant uniformity which <lb/>is viſible in
        all nature does not permit us to ſuppoſe that <lb/>ſenſe alone would have been made
        particular exception of. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Moreover, a little reflection will ſhew that the above fa- <lb/>culty ought to belong
        to feeling more ſpecially than any other <lb/>ſenſe. It is agreed, that, generally ſpeaking,
        there is but <lb/>one ſenſe, which is feeling, and that the other four are only <lb/>a
        modification of it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſight, hearing, taſte and ſmelling produce no ſenſa- <lb/>tion in us but through
        the means of contact. The light, <lb/>ſound, ſavours and ſmell only act upon us by ſhaking
        the <lb/>nervous tufts of our organs, and ſuch a ſhaking can never be <lb/>obtained before
        they have touched them. This is an uncon- <lb/>trovertible truth. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Feeling, properly ſo called, only differs from other ſenſes <lb/>by its great energy
        and vaſt extent. The other ſenſes occu- <lb/>py but a very narrow place, and are only
        ſuſceptible of a lo- <lb/>cal impreſſion; but feeling, by experience, is ſpread over all
        <lb/>the ſurface of the body: and this is ſufficient to ſhew that <lb/>feeling ought to
        enjoy, in a ſuperior manner, the faculty of <lb/>opening a way to ſleep: for being the chief
        ſenſe, and almoſt <lb/>to ſay the principal one, from which the others are derived, <lb/>how
        is it poſſible to conceive it deprived of a power which <lb/>the ſubordinate ſenſes are
        endowed with? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Laſtly, it is ſo certain that ſleep is introduced by feeling, <lb/>that the faculty
        preſcribe opium taken in topic and applied <lb/>to the skin, which really produces ſleep.
        The touching <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* We may even recollect on that
          account manner of touching <lb/>made uſe of in India, by which means ſlaves procure ſleep
          to their <lb/>maſters; which is called <hi rend="italic">Maſſer.</hi>
        </note>
        <lb/>of an organized body may then, without any marvel, occa- <lb/>ſion ſleep; and it is the
        point I want to clear and anſwer <lb/>fully the objection of improbability. But, will they
        ſay, <lb/>ſuppoſing the Magnetiſers to be endowed with the power of <lb/>producing ſleep,
        there is not the like reaſon to lead us to <lb/>think that they can likewiſe produce
        Somnambuliſm? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The anſwer is plain and obvious. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_20" n="20"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Somnambuliſm itſelf is nothing elſe but a mere modi- <lb/>fication of ſleep. There is
        no Somnambuliſm without <lb/>ſleep. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We might even add that there is no ſleep without Som- <lb/>nambuliſm, and that every
        man is born a Somnambule. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This propoſition, which is apparently a paradox, is no <lb/>leſs inconteſtable,
        provided too much extent is not allowed <lb/>to the meaning of the word Somnambule. Perfect
        ſleep <lb/>is a time of reſt, during which, ſenſations are reduced to a <lb/>ſtate of
        concentration, which diſcovers ſeemingly no other <lb/>ſign of life but reſpiration and the
        motion of the pulſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Imperfect ſleep is that in which ſuch a concentration is not <lb/>complete, ſo that it
        ſtill leaves ſome acceſs for the interior <lb/>diſplay of organs. We ſeldom enjoy the former
        kind of <lb/>ſleep. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In a ſound and natural ſleep, the perſon whoſe mental <lb/>powers were abſolutely in
        ſuſpenſion, preſerves ſtill a more <lb/>or leſs active portion of watching, by the means of
        which <lb/>divers motions are performed: Who does not know that <lb/>during our very ſleep,
        the body is agitated and combines <lb/>itſelf, in order to chuſe an advantageous poſition;
        the hand <lb/>is continually aſſiſting the incommoded parts, property <lb/>adjuſts the bed
        clothes, deſtroys inſects, &amp;c. All theſe <lb/>things doubtleſs belong to the watch, and
        of courſe conſti- <lb/>tute a kind of Somnambuliſm. For we muſt comprehend, <lb/>under that
        denomation, the exerciſe of every motion what- <lb/>ever occaſioned during ſleep. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Moſt men carry ſtill farther the effects of Somnambuliſm, <lb/>ſince there are many
        people who ſpeak during their ſleep, <lb/>make different geſtures, hold diſcourſes of a
        conſiderable <lb/>length, addreſs thoſe whom they think themſelves in com- <lb/>pany with,
        get out of their beds and in again, &amp;c. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>So common are ſuch practices, that they are to be met <lb/>with almoſt in every houſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Whenever Somnambuliſm acquires a more extended pene- <lb/>tration, it produces
        wonderful things. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Then the ſleeper is ſeen writing, working, opening the <lb/>doors, lighting the fire,
        aſcending the tops of houſes, ſwim- <lb/>ming over rivers, currying horſes, &amp;c. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But you muſt obſerve that Somnambuliſm in this laſt de- <lb/>gree is no new ſtate, nor
        contrary to the nature of ſleep; it <lb/>is ſingly a reinforced modification of a ſtate
        natural to man <lb/>and inherent to ſleep; which naturally leads us back to the <pb
          xml:id="page_21" n="21"/>
        <lb/>following propoſition, <q rend="quotes">That every ſleeper is in the com- <lb/>mencement of
          Somnambuliſm;</q> that whoever gives him- <lb/>ſelf up to ſleep is in a near ſtate of
        Somnambuliſm, which <lb/>is to diſplay itſelf in a more or leſs ſtriking manner, ac-
        <lb/>cording to the phyſical conſtitution of the ſleeper, the na- <lb/>ture of his
        diſtemper, and eſpecially according to the diffe- <lb/>rent cauſes which have produced,
        preceded, or accompa- <lb/>nied his ſleep. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From thence it is eaſily conceived that a ſick perſon <lb/>already inclined, either by
        his conſtitution, or the nature <lb/>of his diſeaſe, to a Somnambuliſm in its juvenile
        ſtate, is <lb/>liable to receive with Magnetical ſleep a greater determina- <lb/>tion
        towards Somnambuliſm. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Is ſuch a ſtate uſeful in curing the diſeaſe? Such a queſ- <lb/>tion is not now to be
        diſcuſſed. Whether Somnambuliſm <lb/>be ſalutary or not, it is however certain, that it is a
        depen- <lb/>dent on ſleep, introduces itſelf with it, and ought conſe- <lb/>quently to
        predominate more or leſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There are people whoſe Magnetical drowſineſs is attend- <lb/>ed by no very ſtriking
        ſigns of Somnambuliſm, who are <lb/>only drowſy, and poſſeſs a continual ſomnolency not
        inſen- <lb/>ſible to any thing that may be tranſacted round them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Others are only drowſy for a ſhort time, then awake, <lb/>and fall again into a ſtate
        of drowſineſs. The nuances are <lb/>infinitely multiplied from the very ſleepers, who diſplay
        <lb/>nothing but what uſually appears in a common ſleep to <lb/>thoſe who perform the
        wonderful things ſo much ſpoken <lb/>of in all the world. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is thoſe very marvels that remain to be explained: for <lb/>having fully proved that
        Magnetical proceedings, or a con- <lb/>tact graduate and combined according to principles,
        can pro- <lb/>duce ſleep and then Somnambuliſm; I ſhall be obliged to <lb/>reduce Magnetiſm
        to that rule which is already known. <lb/>But the Animal Magnetiſm's adverſaries will not
        fail to ob- <lb/>ject that Magnetical Somnambuliſm extends ſtill further, <lb/>by offering
        the ſpectacle of a Somnambuliſm of which we <lb/>can have no idea, is attended with
        phœnomena never be- <lb/>fore obſerved in natural Somnambuliſm. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Such is the laſt allegation, which ſerves as a refuge to the <lb/>incredulity of thoſe
        who never ſaw any Somnambule, and <lb/>the disbelief of them who had it in their power to
        ſee and <lb/>be convinced. But it will, in a moment, be deemed ſur- <lb/>priſing, to obſerve
        that Magnetical Somnambuliſm has no- <pb xml:id="page_22" n="22"/>
        <lb/>thing ſuperior to the effects of natural Somnambuliſm; <lb/>that, on the contrary, it
        exactly agrees with the phœno- <lb/>mena of the latter ſtate, which is nothing more than a
        <lb/>more diſcovery; and ſuch a conſideration might be, by <lb/>many people, looked on as a
        victorious argument in favour <lb/>of Magnetical Somnambuliſm. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Article</hi> 2d. Magnetical Somnambuliſm's phœnomena, <lb/>far from being
        inconceivable, are, on the contrary, a neceſ- <lb/>ſary conſequence of Somnambuliſm. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>According to the virulent declamations thrown out <lb/>againſt Magnetical Somnambuliſm,
        repreſenting it as a baſe <lb/>and deceitful trick, unworthy the leaſt credit, it would be
        <lb/>natural to ſuppoſe that ſuch Phœnomena are without pre- <lb/>cedents, and only
        concentered in Magnetical Somnambu- <lb/>liſm. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Such is the prevalent opinion with the public, even <lb/>among the ſenſible part,
        compoſed of people no leſs re- <lb/>markable for their virtues than their learning; but who,
        <lb/>not being familiar with phyſiological phœnomena, muſt <lb/>neceſſarily have adopted
        that way of thinking. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thoſe very perſons might, perhaps, have had a different <lb/>opinion on that matter, if
        it had been in their power to <lb/>know that there exiſts in nature a ſtate abſolutely the
        ſame <lb/>as that given out merely as a feigned one; and, that, the <lb/>ſame phœnomena,
        which are, in the one, pronounced to <lb/>be chimerical, impoſſible and inadmiſſible, are,
        in the <lb/>other looked upon as inconteſtable, and certainly beyond <lb/>any manner of
        doubt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Such a circumſtance makes a material difference; for <lb/>they only refuſe to give
        credit to the phœnomena of Mag- <lb/>netical Somnambuliſm, becauſe reaſon will hardly admit
        <lb/>of facts by which it is hurt, and which are grounded on <lb/>no precedents. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But if credit ought to be given to natural Somnambu- <lb/>liſm, the ſame muſt be
        granted to Magnetical Somnambu- <lb/>liſm; for, it being proved that thoſe phœnomena really
        <lb/>exiſt with regard to one of theſe two ſpecies of Somnam- <lb/>buliſm, it would be to
        contend for contradiction's ſake <lb/>only, to deny the poſſibility of their exiſtence in
        the other. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We muſt then neceſſarily know that there exiſts a ſtate <lb/>of natural Somnambuliſm,
        acknowledged and awarded by <lb/>the faculty, during which, ſleepers execute things impoſ-
        <lb/>ſible for any man awake to perform. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_23" n="23"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Without entering into a detail of the ſingularities alrea- <lb/>dy obſerved on that
        account, I ſhall only mention the <lb/>phœnomena perfectly analogous to thoſe obſerved among
        <lb/>Magnetical Somnambules. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Nothing is more common than to ſee Magnetical Som- <lb/>nambules walk, go towards other
        people, ſpeak to them, <lb/>come back to their places, take a book, paper, ink, in a
        <lb/>word, perform a prodigious number of things which ſup- <lb/>ports the idea of perfect
        reaſon and ſenſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thus is the public juſtly incenſed when any one pre- <lb/>ſumes to inſinuate, that ſuch
        perſons are not in a ſtate of <lb/>ſleep, and that they neither ſee nor hear through their
        <lb/>uſual organs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Some of thoſe Somnambules having their eyes open, <lb/>the ſpectators naturally thought
        they muſt make uſe of <lb/>them, and the faculty themſelves have ridiculed this pre-
        <lb/>tenſion, <q rend="quotes">That people could ſee without the uſe of their <lb/>eyes, and
          having their eyes open, could not make uſe of <lb/>them. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But, unhappily for them, ſuch a puſillanimous obſerva- <lb/>tion loſes much of its
        ſtrength, when we conſider that <lb/>even our learned have conſecrated that very truth in
        one <lb/>of their books, calculated to teach poſterity the actual ſtate <lb/>of our
        knowledge. Open the Encyclopedia, and at the <lb/>word Somnambule, you may read literally
        thus: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">People ſtruck with Somnambuliſm, given up to a <lb/>ſound ſleep, walk,
          talk, write and perform many other <lb/>actions as if they were awake; nay, even ſometimes
          <lb/>with more diſcernment and exactitude; </q> and afterwards, </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">Some Somnambules have their eyes open, but do not <lb/>ſeem to make uſe of
          them. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The learned conſequently (for Encyclopedia is their <lb/>work) are convinced plainly to
        believe, with Magnetiſers, <lb/>that it is poſſible to ſee without the eyes aſſiſtance, and
        that <lb/>though the Somnambule has his eyes open <hi rend="italic">he does not make
          <lb/>uſe of them.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Magnetiſers have often obſerved, that Magnetical Som- <lb/>nambuliſm diſplayed in many
        patients a wonderful ſubtlety of <lb/>ſight, ſo far that they diſcern very delicate objects
        through a <lb/>bandage, or any other intermediate body. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That propoſition, has not been more ſavourably re- <lb/>ceived. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_24" n="24"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They have laughed at the ſtory of a Magnetical Somnam- <lb/>bule, who had written when
        his eyes were covered with a <lb/>head-band, and corrected words, eraſed letters to
        ſubſtitute <lb/>others, upon or near them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They ſaid ſuch a thing ſhould be ſeen before it was be- <lb/>lieved; and even after
        having really ſeen it, they ſuſpected <lb/>the good faith of the Somnambule, ſo
        extraordinary the <lb/>event appeared. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But how could they forget that our learned had before- <lb/>hand prepared us to believe
        thoſe phœnomena, by pre- <lb/>ſenting them to us, as a neceſſary conſequence from Som-
        <lb/>nambuliſm? <q rend="quotes">If you follow a Somnambule, </q> ſays the al- <lb/>ready
        quoted article, <q rend="quotes">it is caſy to perceive, that his <lb/>ſleep, ſo much alike
          when he is awake, offers a prodi- <lb/>gious number of wonderful things. Truth itſelf
          becomes <lb/>incredible. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The author deſpiſing the exaggerations often attending <lb/>on ſuch ſtories, has only
        referred <q rend="quotes">to notorious ſacts, of <lb/>which the truth cannot even be
          ſuſpected. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is after ſuch a preamble, that he relates the ſtory of a <lb/>young Somnambule, a
        clergyman and fellow-ſtudent of the <lb/>Archbiſhop of Bourdeaux. That Prelate uſed to go
        every <lb/>night in that Somnambule's room, as ſoon as he thought <lb/>him aſleep. He
        remarked in particular, that the perſon <lb/>got up, took paper, compoſed and wrote ſermons.
        When <lb/>he had finiſhed a page, he read it over, and repeated it <lb/>very loud; if, adds
        the author, that action was done with- <lb/>out the eyes aſſiſtance, can it be called
        reading? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſame clergyman with his eyes ſhut compoſed mu- <lb/>ſic; a cane ſerved him as a
        compaſs; with it he traced, at <lb/>an equal diſtance, the five neceſſary lines, put in
        their <lb/>ſtead the <hi rend="italic">Key, Flat, Sharp,</hi> then marked the notes which
        <lb/>he had firſt done all white; and when he had finiſhed, in <lb/>taking up again every
        one of them, he made them <hi rend="italic">black,</hi>
        <lb/>ſuch as ſhould have been ſo, and wrote the words under. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It once happened that he wrote them with too <hi rend="italic">large
          <lb/>characters,</hi> ſo that they were not placed directly under their <lb/>correſponding
        notes; he ſoon perceived his miſtake (with- <lb/>out the aſſiſtance of his eyes) and in
        order to mend it, he <lb/>eraſed what he had juſt done, by paſſing his hand over, <lb/>and
        made again lower that muſical line with all poſſible <lb/>preciſion. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_25" n="25"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Prelate to whom we are indebted for theſe particu- <lb/>lars, having placed himſelf
        before the Somnambule to be <lb/>enabled to follow him with more application, obſerved a
        <lb/>very wonderful circumſtance: The young clergyman hav- <lb/>ing put in ſome place of his
        ſermon the words, <hi rend="italic">this divine <lb/>infant,</hi> perceived in reading it
        over again, that theſe two <lb/>words made a diſagreeable diſſonance, and ſubſtituted the
        <lb/>epithet <hi rend="italic">adorable</hi> inſtead of the word <hi rend="italic"
          >divine;</hi> but that altera- <lb/>tion left an imperfection in the phraſe, becauſe there
        was <lb/><hi rend="italic">ce adorable enfant;</hi> the Somnambule perceiving the error,
        <lb/>very dexterouſly added a <hi rend="italic">t</hi> after <hi rend="italic">ce,</hi> ſo
        that it was written <hi rend="italic">cet <lb/>adorable enfant.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Whenever the Somnambule read or corrected what he <lb/>had written, he took care to put
        his fingers on the charac- <lb/>ters that were not yet dry; he made a digreſſion to avoid
        <lb/>rubbing them: a caution he never took when the letters <lb/>were not wet. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is to be obſerved that the Prelate, in order poſitively <lb/>to know whether he made
          <hi rend="italic">any uſe of his eyes,</hi> had imagined <lb/>to put a <hi rend="italic"
          >paſte-board under his noſe;</hi> and it was in that poſiti- <lb/>on he continued the
        operations above-mentioned. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There are facts certified in the Encyclopedia itſelf, <lb/>equally notorious, and above
        all contradiction; which is <lb/>no doubt ſufficient evidently to prove one of theſe two
        <lb/>points, viz. That the Somnambule can ſee without the <lb/><hi rend="italic">aſſiſtance
          of his eyes,</hi> or that his ſight, exalted to an incon- <lb/>ceivable degree, pierces
        through his eyelids and the opa- <lb/>cous bodies. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The memorials of the Academy of Sciences, and the <lb/>phyſicians works, contain a
        prodigious number of obſerva- <lb/>tions which plainly conſirm the facts hinted, and others
        of <lb/>the ſame nature. When an explanation of ſuch a ſingulari- <lb/>ty is demanded, they
        all unite to acknowledge the weakneſs <lb/>of our comprehenſion, and exhort us to admire
        what we <lb/>cannot underſtand. What Encyclopedia ſays on that ac- <lb/>count well deſerves
        to be related. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">How is it poſſible, </q> ſays he, <q rend="quotes">that a man buried in
          <lb/>a <hi rend="italic">ſound</hi> ſleep ſhould hear, walk, write, or ſee; in a word,
          <lb/>enjoy the exerciſe of all his ſenſes, and perform divers <lb/>motions with exactneſs
          and preciſion? </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">We muſt freely own there exiſt many things, the <lb/>reaſon of which we are
          quite ignorant of, and <pb xml:id="page_26" n="26"/>
          <lb/>which we cannot penetrate into, nature has its myſte- <lb/>ries. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The author of the ſame article, after having mentioned <lb/>many ſurpriſing facts,
        which he aſſerts as inconteſtable, <lb/>makes a judicious ſarcaſm againſt thoſe pretenders
        in point <lb/>of learning, who believe nothing but what they can account <lb/>for, and will
        not for a moment ſuppoſe, that there are in <lb/>nature myſteries impenetrable to their
        ſagacity. Let us <lb/>now obſerve the dangerous effect of prejudice. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Whenever the ſame phœnomena are repeated by a Mag- <lb/>netical Somnambule, it is
        inſinuated thoſe concerned in <lb/>them uſe deceit and fraud, becauſe ſuch phœnomena are
        <lb/>contrary to all received notions, and have no inſtance in <lb/>nature to authoriſe a
        belief. But how is it poſſible to re- <lb/>concile ſuch a reclamation with the various
        examples which <lb/>have juſt now been quoted? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>One of the chief objections againſt Magnetical Somnam- <lb/>buliſm is, becauſe it
        offers both <hi rend="italic">contradictions and inconſe- <lb/>quences</hi> with that
        pretended ſubtlety of both ſenſe and feel- <lb/>ing. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It has been obſerved that thoſe Somnambules, ſo diſ- <lb/>cerning with regard to
        certain objects, were altogether in- <lb/>ſenſible of others. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For example, ſuch a man who dexterouſly croſſes a row <lb/>of chairs without touching
        them, and writes or reads through <lb/>a paſte-board, ſhall not ſee whether there are people
        round <lb/>him; he will take one thing for another, and ſhall not <lb/>perceive the fraud
        impoſed on him. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But natural Somnambuliſm's example fully anſwers that <lb/>objection, and the ſuppoſed
        contradiction, far from being <lb/>an argument againſt the reality of Magnetical Somnambu-
        <lb/>liſm, better eſtabliſhes its veracity, ſince it preſents a de- <lb/>gree of reſemblance
        more conſiſtent with natural Somnam- <lb/>buliſm. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The natural Somnambule of Encyclopedia well ſaw his <lb/>paper and letter through a
        paſte-board, and yet could not <lb/>ſee the very perſon who was placed before him, buſily
        <lb/>employed in examining his motions. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſame Somnambule imagining he was walking on <lb/>the border of a river, thought he
        ſaw a child falling into <lb/>the water; immediately he precipitates himſelf on his bed, <pb
          xml:id="page_27" n="27"/>
        <lb/>making the ſame geſtures as a man ſwimming, and after <lb/>having much moved and
        fatigued himſelf, finding the bed <lb/>clothes in a heap, he ſuppoſes it the child, takes it
        up with <lb/>one hand and employs the other to return, by ſwimming <lb/>on ſhore; when he
        thinks himſelf there, he lays himſelf <lb/>on the bed, and rattles his teeth, conveying the
        appearance <lb/>of a man quite wet and cold; he then asks the byſtanders <lb/>for a glaſs of
        brandy to warm him, and as they were giv- <lb/>ing him a glaſs of water he perceived the
        trick, and inſiſt- <lb/>ed on having brandy, which, as ſoon as he has got, he ea- <lb/>gerly
        drinks it, declaring, at the ſame time that it does him <lb/>good. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By that example it is evident that the Somnambule, <lb/>though deceived by the ſight
        and feeling, had his taſte <lb/>ſound and perfect, ſince he well knew how to diſcern
        <lb/>brandy from water. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Such contradictions being hereditary to natural Somnam- <lb/>bules, they ſhould not be
        looked upon as extraordinary in <lb/>Magnetical Somnambules, ſince both Somnambuliſms are
        <lb/>derived from a ſecret diſpoſition which, likely, are very <lb/>near the ſame. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I had many times an opportunity of ſeeing myſelf ſuch <lb/>contradictions, which at
        firſt produced in me a great <lb/>diffidence, becauſe I was not then well acquainted with
        the <lb/>ſingularities inherent to Somnambuliſm. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Two years ago being at the Marquis of <hi rend="italic">Puyſegur</hi>'s I or-
        <lb/>dered a Magnetical Somnambule, whom he ſhewed me, <lb/>to take a hat which was lying on
        a table in the cloſet, and <lb/>to go and put it on the head of ſome of the company. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I did not expreſs my command in ſpeaking, but only by <lb/>ſign in tracing the line
        which I gave him to run over, <lb/>and at the end of which was the hat. The Somnambule,
        <lb/>(whoſe eyes were covered with a paſte-board) got up from <lb/>his chair, follows the
        direction ſhewn with my finger, ad- <lb/>vances towards the table, and takes the hat amidſt
        many <lb/>other objects that were on the ſame table; but before he <lb/>preſented it to the
        perſon, thinks it civil to bruſh it; and <lb/>though there was no bruſh on the table, he
        makes the geſ- <lb/>ture of a man who took one; and holding the hat with his <lb/>left hand,
        he bruſhes it on the three ſides with his right <lb/>hand, puts the imaginary bruſh on the
        table, and carries <pb xml:id="page_28" n="28"/>
        <lb/>the hat, placing it on the head of the indicated perſon. <lb/>Though that Somnambule
        had perfectly fulfilled my inten- <lb/>tion, I conceived ſome diffidence on account of the
        circum- <lb/>ſtance of the bruſh. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>How could that man whoſe ſight and feeling were ſeem- <lb/>ing perfectly ſound, not
        perceive there was no bruſh on the <lb/>table! How could he miſtake himſelf ſo far as to
        think he <lb/>had one in his hand? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From thence I inferred, that having committed ſo groſs <lb/>and palpable a miſtake, he
        was far from having the feeling <lb/>and ſight as ſubtile as they would give to underſtand,
        and <lb/>that there was in the reſt of his operations more addreſs than <lb/>fair practice. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Magnetical Somnambules, whom I have ſince ſeen, <lb/>have all given me reaſon for
        the ſame diſſidence, by diſplay- <lb/>ing contradictions of the ſame nature. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But how great was my ſurpriſe, when, after having con- <lb/>ſulted the works,
        memorials, and relations made on Som- <lb/>nambuliſm, I obſerved the ſame contradictions in
        natural <lb/>Somnambules, and that they were alſo an object of great <lb/>aſtoniſhment to
        ſpectators; ſo what at firſt ſeemed to me <lb/>a motive of ſuſpicion, became at laſt a new
        reaſen to ground <lb/>my perſuaſion. <q rend="quotes">What is inconceivable, </q> ſays <hi
          rend="italic">Pigatti,</hi>
        <lb/>an Italian doctor, (ſpeaking of Somnambules) <q rend="quotes">is, that, <lb/>on certain
          occaſions their ſenſations are very ſubtile, <lb/>whilſt, on others they are very
          impenetrable. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I ſaw in the ſame work an infinite number of other Som- <lb/>nambules, which, after
        having at firſt ſhewn a wonderful <lb/>ſubtlety of ſenſation, ſeemed the next moment to be
        entirely <lb/>deprived of them, by taking one thing for another, and <lb/>confounding the
        objects which could claim no analogy to <lb/>one another. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The moſt aſtoniſhing Somnambule that ever exiſted, is, <lb/>without a doubt, <hi
          rend="italic">John Baptiſt Negretti,</hi> who was both fol- <lb/>lowed and cloſely
        examined during five ſucceſſive nights, by <lb/>a vaſt number of people. Mr. Pigatti, who
        was preſent at <lb/>thoſe experiments, has given an exact and preciſe account <lb/>of them,
        which is found in the <hi rend="italic">Journal Etranger,</hi> March <lb/> 1756. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That Somnambule, having his eyes cloſely ſhut, took <lb/>ſnuff out of a box preſented
        to him, came down many large <pb xml:id="page_29" n="29"/>
        <lb/>ſtairs without groping, heſitation, or even touching, turn- <lb/>ing and ſtopping
        preciſely where he ſhould; placed bot- <lb/>tles, and glaſſes on a ſmall pillar which was in
        his way; <lb/>went and came into the different apartments without run- <lb/>ning againſt any
        thing; ſtopped at doors which were ſhut, <lb/>and opened them; went to draw water from the
        well, <lb/>took out of the buffet napkins, towels, knives, and gene- <lb/>rally all that was
        neceſſary for a table; and performed ma- <lb/>ny other things no leſs ſurpriſing, too
        tedious to relate, <lb/>but which all ſuppoſe an exquiſite ſubtlety in the ſight and
        <lb/>feeling. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Next to this, are to be ſeen miſtakes, which quite con- <lb/>tradict that perfection in
        the ſenſes. After having looked <lb/>for a light, the Somnambule imagines he has a candle in
        <lb/>his hand; without perceiving his error, he thinks he holds <lb/>a candleſtick whilſt it
        is only a bottle; he helps himſelf <lb/>with that pretended light by carrying it along with
        him; <lb/>he draws near the chimney to dry a wet towel, though <lb/>there is no fire; he
        ſalutes the ladies and gentlemen in <lb/>whoſe company he imagines himſelf, whilſt there is
        not any <lb/>ſuch perſon as he ſuppoſes among thoſe that ſurround him. <lb/>He goes to the
        public-houſe, thinking to be accompanied <lb/>by a comrade, though there is not ſuch a
        thing; he pours <lb/>him ſome drink, addreſſes him, and drinks his health, with- <lb/>out
        perceiving he is alone. When buſy in eating a ſallad, <lb/>they take his plate away to
        ſubſtitute a diſh of cabbages im- <lb/>bibed with vinegar and cinnamon, unknown to him: they
        <lb/>take the laſt diſh to ſerve him with a plate of raw fritters, <lb/>and he continues to
        eat; they give him water inſtead of <lb/>wine; at laſt ſomebody jeſtingly rubbing his legs
        with a <lb/>cane, he takes it for the beating of a dog which he ſup- <lb/>poſes near him; he
        falls in a paſſion againſt the dog, looks <lb/>for him, endeavours to beat him, goes and
        ferches a whip <lb/>to chaſtiſe him: after having returned with the whip, ſome <lb/>of the
        ſpectators throw a muff at him; then imagining to <lb/>lay hold of the dog, he beats him
        with violenc<corr>e<sic>#</sic></corr>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There are contradictions to explain that which ſtruck <lb/>me ſo forcibly in the
        Somnambule of the Marquis of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Puyſegur,</hi> on account of the
        imaginary bruſh he <lb/>thought he held. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There are an infinite number of other examples which <lb/>might be quoted, and which
        all tend fully to manifeſt that <pb xml:id="page_30" n="30"/>
        <lb/>inequality of ſenſations and ſenſibility obſerved in the ſeve- <lb/>ral Somnambules. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Library of Medicine, vol. x. p. 477. mentions a <lb/>Somnambule, who getting out of
        his bed at mid-night, <lb/>went to a neighbouring decayed houſe, and of which but
        <lb/>little remained, ſaving the bare walls and ſome pieces of <lb/>timber. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Somnambule mounted to the very top of that houſe, <lb/>and jumped from one beam to
        another, though there was <lb/>under a profound abyſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the ſame work is related a ſtory of another Somnam- <lb/>bule, who, in the night
        time dreſſed himſelf, put on his <lb/>boots and ſpurs, and then leapt on the border of a
        window <lb/>five ſtories high, which he miſtook for his horſe, and in <lb/>that poſture
        agitated himſelf with all the geſtures of a cava- <lb/>lier who rides poſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the two laſt inſtances, there is an inexplicable aſſoci- <lb/>ation of the moſt
        perfect penetration, with the greateſt <lb/>ſtupidity. How a man, who had addreſs enough to
        climb <lb/>up the top of a decayed houſe, and run on a few weak <lb/>beams, could not
        perceive the profound abyſs which lay <lb/>under? and how he, who dreſſed himſelf as a
        cavalier, put <lb/>on his boots and ſpurs, could take the border of a window <lb/>for a
        horſe? To explain thoſe ſingularities, the principle of <lb/>Somnambuliſm, and that want of
        organization which at <lb/>that moment took place in the individual, ſhould be better
        <lb/>known. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That induces Mr. <hi rend="italic">Rehelini,</hi> a colebrated Italian doctor,<lb/> author
        of many obſervations on Somnambuliſm, to ſay, that <lb/>we ought to content ourſelves with
        admiring the wonderful <lb/>effects of that condition which Providence ſeems to preſent
        <lb/>to the learned, in order to confound them, and ſhew the <lb/>narrow compaſs of human
        underſtanding. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The apparent immobility and inſenſibility of Magnetical <lb/>Somnambules, for whatever
        is ſaid or tranſacted round <lb/>them, is alſo experienced in natural Somnambules. He
        <lb/>whom I juſt now ſpoken of, was quite inſenſible to the <lb/>approach of a candle, which
        almoſt burnt his eyebrows. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There is likewiſe in the memorials of the Academy of <lb/>Sciences for the year 1742,
        p. 409, a diſſertation of Mr. <hi rend="italic">de <lb/>Savage de in Croix</hi> on the
        Somnambuliſm of a girl from <pb xml:id="page_31" n="31"/>
        <lb/>Montpellier, exhibiting a ſtriking inſtance of the like in- <lb/>ſenſibility: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">On the 5th of April, 1757, </q> ſays the author, <q rend="quotes">when <lb/>I
          viſited the hoſpital at ten o'clock in the morning I found <lb/>the patient in bed. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">She began to ſpeak with a degree of vivacity and wit, <lb/>which ſhe never ſhewed
          when out of that ſituation; ſhe <lb/>changed now and then her diſcourſe, and ſeemed to ad-
          <lb/>dress many of her friends who were aſſembling round <lb/>her bed; what ſhe uttered
          ſeemed to bear ſome analogy <lb/>with what ſhe ſaid in her attack of the preceding day,
          <lb/>wherein having verbatim related an inſtruction, in the <lb/>way of a catechiſm, which
          ſhe heard the day before, ſhe <lb/>made ſome moral and malicious applications to the peo-
          <lb/>ple of the houſe, whom ſhe took care to mention under <lb/>fictitious names,
          accompanying the whole with geſtures <lb/>and motions of her eyes, which ſhe had opened:
          in a <lb/>word, with all the circumſtances attending on the ac- <lb/>tion done the day
          before; and yet ſhe was in a ſound <lb/>ſleep. It was a very awarded circumſtance which no
          one <lb/>doubted; but foreſeeing I could never preſume to aſcer- <lb/>tain it, unleſs I
          had previouſly rendered ſome formal ex- <lb/>periments, I made them on her ſenſes and
          organs whilſt <lb/>ſhe was in the act of ſpeaking. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">At firſt, as the girl had her eyes open, I thought that <lb/>diſſimulation, if
          there was any in the caſe, could not <lb/>withſtand a ſlap on the hand, or one given
          ſuddenly on <lb/>the face; but this repeated experiment did not either <lb/>occaſion the
          leaſt grimace or interrupt her diſcourſe: I <lb/>had recourſe to another experiment, which
          was to put <lb/>briskly my ſinger to her eye, and to approach a lighted <lb/>wax candle
          near enough to burn her eye-brows; but <lb/>ſhe did not even twinkle on the occaſion. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">Secondly, a hidden perſon made ſuddenly a great <lb/>noiſe in the girl's ear, and
          repeated it with a ſtone againſt <lb/>the bolſter of her bed: at any other time ſhe would
          have <lb/>been trembling with fear, but then ſhe appeared perfect- <lb/>ly indifferent and
          inſenſible to what paſſed. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">Thirdly, I poured in her eyes and mouth ſome bran- <lb/>dy, and ſpirit of
          ammoniac ſalt; I even applied on the <lb/>horny tuniele of the eye, a ſeather's beard,
          then the end <pb xml:id="page_32" n="32"/>
          <lb/>of my finger, but in vain: Snuff blown up her noſe, <lb/>pricking with pins, and
          fingers extorted, had on her the <lb/>ſame effect as on a mere machine; ſhe never gave the
          <lb/>leaſt ſign of ſentiment. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The 10th vol. of the Medicine's library contains a me- <lb/>morial on a female
        Somnambule, who was inſenſible to the <lb/>blows ſhe received with a whip on her naked
        ſhoulders; <lb/>one day they rubbed her back with honey, and in that con- <lb/>dition
        expoſed her in the ſun's meridian to the ſtinging of <lb/>bees, which occaſioned a great
        number of bliſters on her <lb/>body, without ſhewing the leaſt motion in the world: but
        <lb/>when ſhe awoke, ſhe ſeemed to ſuffer acute pain in the af- <lb/>fected places, and
        bitterly complained of the hard uſage <lb/>and treament ſhe had met with. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Concerning that woman, I obſerved an intereſting cir- <lb/>cumſtance, which is
        perfectly conformable to what is now <lb/>paſt; it is becauſe the learned and other
        profeſſors of me- <lb/>dicine declined to go and verify the caſe of that ſleeper, <lb/>under
        the pretence that ſuch a ſtate contradicted the noti- <lb/>ons already received in
        phyſiology. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The author of the relation thus expreſſes himſelf: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">The long ſtay that woman made at Louvain, gave <lb/>every body an
          opportunity of ſeeing her, and ſcrupul- <lb/>ouſly examining ſo extraordinary a
          phœnomenon. The <lb/>ancient profeſſors in that town looking on the event as a <lb/>fable
          and mere chimera, could not take on themſelves to <lb/>increaſe the number of ſpectators.
          It is thus, </q> continues <lb/>the author, <q rend="quotes">that prejudice ſhuts the eyes
          of men of the <lb/>firſt merit, and hinders them from ſtudying and applying
          <lb/>themſelves to the diſcovery of ſeveral things which might <lb/>prove very beneficial
          to monkind—Laſtly, </q> ſays the ſame <lb/>author, <q rend="quotes">the young profeſſors and
          other phyſicians in the <lb/>town, looking on this phœnomenon with an indifferent
          <lb/>eye, ſeriouſly enquired into the caſe of that ſleeper, and <lb/>after a thorough
          inveſtigation, had every reaſon to be <lb/>fully ſatisfied.</q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It will not be amiſs to obſerve, that the author of this <lb/>page is <q rend="quotes"
          >a phyſician of the faculty at Paris. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Such an inſenſibility is true, for the noiſe which ſur- <lb/>rounds Magnetical
        Somnambules does not extend to eve- <lb/>ry kind of noiſe, ſince the Somnambule preſerves
        the facul- <pb xml:id="page_33" n="33"/>
        <lb/>ty of hearing thoſe perſons with whom he is in analogy and <lb/>harmony. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This diſtinction has been deemed, by many, a mere ex- <lb/>travagance, as it is not
        conceivable how, in the ſame in- <lb/>dividual, a faculty could exiſt which lies open only
        to ſuch <lb/>a perſon, and open for all others. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But that wonder, repugnant to reaſon, finds its analogy <lb/>in natural Somnambuliſm,
        wherein Somnambules are ſeen, <lb/>who, though deaf to thundering noiſes and the voice of
        ſe- <lb/>veral people, yet hear very well, and without the leaſt diſ- <lb/>ſiculty, another
        perſon with whom they keep an excluſive <lb/>relation, ſuch as <hi rend="italic">patients,
          nurſes,</hi> or others they have more <lb/>ſpecially approached, as a <hi rend="italic"
          >husband, wife,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">children.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe laſt have not only the faculty of making themſelves <lb/>heard to a natural
        Somnambule, but even that of making <lb/>him <hi rend="italic">ſpeak.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This ſingularity is ſo very remarkable, that many authors <lb/>complain that certain
        perſons avail themſelves of ſuch a <lb/>circumſtance to catch the ſecret of the Somnambule.
        It is <lb/>thus that begins the article Somnambule in Encyclopedia: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">Somnambules are frequently ſeen, </q> ſays that article, <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">who, in their ſleep relate whatever happened to them in <lb/>the courſe of
          the day; ſome anſwer the queſtions made <lb/>them, and hold very conſiſtent diſcourſes.
          There are <lb/>perſons ſo uncandid as to avail themſelves of the condi- <lb/>tion they are
          in, to catch in ſpite of them, certain <lb/>ſecrets which it is much their intereſt to
          conceal. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Obſerve well theſe expreſſions <q rend="quotes">to catch in ſpite of <lb/>them. </q>
        This plainly ſhews the acknowledgment of the <lb/>formal influence which certain perſons
        awake can exerciſe <lb/>over the Somnambule. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But by ſimilar means and proceedings can ſuch a relation <lb/>take place betwixt the
        perſon awake and the Somnambule? <lb/>Magnetiſers pretend, and inſinuate, that the relation
        is <lb/>eſtabliſhed by mere contact, by touching the Somnambule <lb/>in the extremities of
        his fingers or pulſe; or by touching, <lb/>in a like manner, any body elſe in relation with
        him; which <lb/>preſents a kind of reſemblance with the loadſtone. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They have not failed in exclaiming againſt this affertion; <lb/>and when experience has
        ſeemingly convinced them of the <lb/>truth, a deceit has been ſuſpected on the part of the
        pre- <lb/>tended Somnambule. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_34" n="34"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But to what purpoſe then have they recourſe to that pre- <lb/>tended reluctance, to
        admit of ſo ancient an effect, and <lb/>long ſince well known in the world? A proverbial
        expreſſion <lb/>traces us this opinion of old; for, it is well known that <lb/>moſt proverbs
        are but ſcattered remains of forgotten truths. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But as many perſons might refuſe ſuch authority, we <lb/>muſt furniſh them with a
        teſtimony given out by the learn- <lb/>ed themſelves, and which fully evinces the efficacy
        of the <lb/>proceeding taught Magnetiſers. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Henry de Steers,</hi> a Flemiſh phyſician, certifies, that he
        <lb/>knew from his infancy a Somnambule, who, during his <lb/>ſleep, performed wonderful
        things; among others, he re- <lb/>lates that in the middle of night, and during a moſt pro-
        <lb/>found ſleep, he went and took his child out of the cradle <lb/>where he lay, and then
        walked over all the houſe, holding <lb/>the infant in his arms: his wife, who had
        accidentally per- <lb/>ceived this, afraid of the child, followed her husband ſtep <lb/>by
        ſtep, with an intent of aſſiſting them if occaſion requir- <lb/>ed: or, as ſhe had obſerved
        that, in that ſituation her huſ- <lb/>band anſwered all queſtions ſhe put to him, and took
        the <lb/>freedom of interrogating him on the moſt ſecret things ſhe <lb/>wanted to know. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The author obſerves that the husband was in day-time <lb/>very circumſpect with his
        wife on his perſonal affairs, <lb/>which he affected to conceal from her: but being interro-
        <lb/>gated by his wife, when in a ſtate of Somnambuliſm, and <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">holding his child in his arms, </q> then, ſaid the author, he <lb/>plainly
        anſwered all the queſtions put to him by his wife, <lb/>who followed him, and <q
          rend="quotes">then had nothing concealed <lb/>from her, </q> and was often ſurpriſed to
        hear her ſpeaking <lb/>of things which he thought were only known to himſelf. <lb/>Vide
        Library of Medicine, vol. x. p. 463. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The te<unclear>#</unclear>timony of a reſpectable author ſerves firſt to con- <lb/>firm
        that influence ſpoken of in the Encyclopedia, which <lb/>lies in certain perſons <q
          rend="quotes">to oblige the Somnambule to ſpeak <lb/>and declare thoſe very thing which it
          was his inte- <lb/>reſt to conceal. </q> It alſo confirms the poſſibility of finding
        <lb/>out a means to eſtabliſh a <hi rend="italic">relation</hi> between the perſon who is
        <lb/>awake and the Somnambule. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Somnambule we were ſpeaking of, was in no <hi rend="italic">relation</hi>
        <lb/>with his wife, from the moment he entered into the ſtate of <pb xml:id="page_35" n="35"/>
        <lb/>Somnambuliſm; to eſtabliſh a communication, it was neceſ- <lb/>ſary he ſhould have had
          <hi rend="italic">his child in his arms.</hi> Laſtly, ob- <lb/>ſerve, that the
        circumſtance of having his child in his arms, <lb/>perfectly anſwers the proceedings pointed
        out by the Mag- <lb/>netiſers. The child, placed in his father's arms, and on the <lb/>other
        hand ſupported by the hands of a trembling mother, <lb/>eſtabliſhed a relation between the
        husband and wife, through <lb/>the communication and analogy he bore to each of them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thus, that aſtoniſhing marvel, againſt which phyſicians <lb/>have ſo much inveighed as
        a mere chimera, a fable, a fraud, <lb/>has, long ago, been atteſted by one of their authors,
        who <lb/>confirms in the moſt preciſe manner what Magnetiſers had ad- <lb/>vanced.—It is
        eaſy to perceive that Magnetiſers, by putting <lb/>themſelves in harmony with Magnetical
        Somnambules, do <lb/>nothing elſe but procure themſelves that intimate analogy, <lb/>of
        which inſtances are to be found in natural Somnambu- <lb/>liſm, and into the principle of
        which they have neglected <lb/>to enquire. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As to the faculty the Magnetiſers pretend to be endowed <lb/>with, to direct the
        Somnambule's motions, by making him <lb/>go from the right to the left, forwards and
        backwards, in <lb/>a direct and circulary line, after the manner of a loadſtone, <lb/>in the
        preſence of the Carupeas, that faculty is a neceſſary <lb/>conſequence of what has been ſaid
        before; and after having <lb/>admitted and acknowledged the power <q rend="quotes">of making
          a Som- <lb/>nambule ſpeak againſt his will, and declare thoſe very <lb/>things he has a
          material intereſt to conceal, </q> ought not <lb/>have any great objection to admit the
        faculty of directing <lb/>his motions. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>An inſtance quoted by Kaau Boerhaave, will afford an <lb/>idea of the aſtoniſhing
        ſubjection which a man is liable to <lb/>with regard to another perſon with whom he is in
        affinity. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That author ſpeaks of a man who had the whim quickly <lb/>to enter in affinity with all
        thoſe whom he approached. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After a few moments, his body acquired a ſympathetical <lb/>flexibility which forced
        him to imitate, with preciſion and <lb/>rapidity, all the motions he perceived in the perſon
        he had <lb/>fixed upon, as, <q rend="quotes">to move his eyes, lips, hands, arms, <lb/>feet,
          to cover or uncover his head, walk, &amp;c. </q> and all <lb/>this in ſpite of himſelf,
        and through the influence of a ſu- <lb/>perior force, which prompted his ſympathetical
        organs to <lb/>act with thoſe of others. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_36" n="36"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It was an amuſement to hold his hands in the preſence <lb/>of any one who happened to
        make geſtures, and then he <lb/>was extremely agitated, continually ſtruggling and endea-
        <lb/>vouring to ſet himſelf at liberty. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If any kind of ſenſation was required of him, he was in <lb/>thoſe moments conſtrained,
        and anſwered he had the head <lb/>or heart ach. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Boerhaave adds, that in conſequence of that odd kind of <lb/>organization, he was
        obliged to go in the ſtreet with his <lb/>eyes cloſely ſhut, and that he was a very
        troubleſome mem- <lb/>ber of ſociety. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The example of ſuch a ſympathetical ſenſibility may ſerve <lb/>to diminiſh the
        improbability, of the aſſinity and relation <lb/>which Animal Magnetiſm ſeems to eſtabliſh
        between the <lb/>patient and the Magnetiſer; and it is on that account that <lb/>Kaau
        Boerhaave certifies, that a man can, by the means of <lb/>ſuch an affinity well eſtabliſned,
        become <q rend="quotes">a god for another <lb/>man, </q> by making him ſubſervient to his
        will and plea- <lb/>ſure. <hi rend="italic">Sic home homini Deus eſt.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We read in the work of the Marquis de Puyſegur, enti- <lb/>tled, <q rend="quotes"
          >Memorials to ſerve for eſtabliſhing Animal Mag- <lb/>netiſm, </q> many obſervations of
        that nature, concerning <lb/>the patients he had put in a ſtate of Somnambuliſm. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The very firſt perſon, whom, to his great aſtoniſhment <lb/>he put in that ſtate, was
        in ſuch perfect affinity with him, <lb/>that he exactly followed all his motions, and loudly
        repeat- <lb/>ed every air which the Marquis internally ſang. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That ſingularity which at firſt appeared incredible, ac- <lb/>quires (notwithſtanding
        the high character of the author) a <lb/>new degree of authority from the above related
        examples, <lb/>and the teſtimony of the authors, who have ſpoken of that <lb/>kind of
        ſympathetical influence. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The proceedings made uſe of by Magnetiſers find likewiſe <lb/>their analogy and
        authority in natural Somnambuliſm. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <unclear>#</unclear> was uſed to put an end to the ſtate of Som- <lb/>nambuliſm, by
        lightly paſſing the extremity of his fingers <lb/>ever the Somnamoule's eve-lids. It is
        exactly the method <lb/>uſed by Magnetiſers. We read in the work of the Marquis <lb/>de
        Puyſegur, that he made, at his pleaſure, a patient <lb/>change his converſation, by
        deterring him from ſad objects, <pb xml:id="page_37" n="37"/>
        <lb/>and preſenting him with ſome of a more conſoling na- <lb/>ture. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">When I thought, </q> ſays the author, that his thoughts <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">ought to affect him in a diſagreeable manner, I ſtopped <lb/>him, and tried
          to inſpire him with agreeable ones, <lb/>which I eaſily did, and then ſaw him perfectly
          pleaſed, <lb/>and imagining that he either aimed at ſome prize, or <lb/>danced at an
          entertainment. I united thoſe thoughts in <lb/>him, and by that means forced him to move
          himſelf in <lb/>his chair, as in imitation of dancing, &amp;c. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thoſe phœnomena have been ſuſpected, though they are <lb/>fully confirmed by the
        Encyclopedia in the article of Som- <lb/>nambule. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The author of that article, relating a number of wonder- <lb/>ful facts in the
        Somnambule mentioned, continues thus: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">The ſame Somnambule has furniſhed us with a great <lb/>number of
          extraordinary facts: but thoſe which I have <lb/>related are ſufficient to my purpoſe. I
          ſhall therefore <lb/>only add, that whenever I had a mind to make him <lb/>change his
          diſcourſe, leave off ſad and diſagreeable ſub- <lb/>jects, it was ſufficient to paſs a pen
          over his lip, and <lb/>immediately he diſcuſſed quite different queſtion. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>That conformity betwixt both recitals, ſerves to confirm <lb/>the one by the other; and
        if, after that double teſtimony, <lb/>any one is authorized to perſevere in his ſurprize, he
        is <lb/>ſtill more ſo to perſevere in his ſuſpicions. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To conclude, the laſt proof of reſemblance between the <lb/>two kinds of Somnambules
        is, that of waking: they both <lb/>entirely forget whatever they have either done or ſaid
        dur- <lb/>ing their ſleep. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I could, by extending ſuch diſcuſſion, account for the <lb/>communication of thoughts,
        without the aſſiſtance of either <lb/>voice or ſigns, it being eaſy to ſhew that this
        ſingularity is <lb/>not more difficult to be underſtood than the other; that it <lb/>has
        been ſuſpected by ancient phyſiologiſts; and even men- <lb/>tioned in modern works of
        celebrated phyſicians; but I <lb/>think it uſeleſs to expatiate any further on a phœnomenon
        <lb/>with which the different minds are not as yet grown fami- <lb/>liar enough. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>My object is, by no means, to write a complete work <lb/>wherein the ſubject of
        Magnetical Somnambuliſm ſhould <pb xml:id="page_38" n="38"/>
        <lb/>be fully diſcuſſed. I only meant to elucidate ſome ideas, <lb/>and to encourage
        judicious perſons to inveſtigate the matter, <lb/>excite their reflections, and provoke in
        them a philoſophi- <lb/>cal doubt, and laſtly, to encourage them to contribute, <lb/>by
        inveſtigation and obſervations, to reſolve a problem no <lb/>leſs intereſting to mankind
        than conducive to the im- <lb/>provement of Sciences. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In my next I ſhall give an Eſſay on the Theory of Som- <lb/>nambuliſm. </p>
      <trailer rend="align-center">
        <lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
