<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Jones: An inquiry into the nature, causes, and termination of nervous
          fevers</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Robert Jones</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">An inquiry into the nature, causes, and termination of nervous
              fevers: together with observations tending to illustrate the method of restoring His
              Majesty to health, and of preventing relapses of his disease. By Robert Jones, M. D.
              And Member of the Royal Society of the Antiquarians at Edinburgh</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T116073</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T116073"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Salisbury</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Salisbury: printed and sold by B.C. Collins: sold also by S. Crowder,
                  Pater-Noster-Row, London, M.DCC.LXXXIX.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1789</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="19"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="51"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3308868707</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K092929.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: disease"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>TO <lb/><hi rend="size(2)"><hi rend="sc">His</hi> MAJESTY</hi>. </head>
        <lb/>
        <salute rend="italic">Moſt Gracious Sovereign, </salute>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HE object of the following <lb/>ſheets is to explain to your
          <lb/>Majeſty the nature of your late ill- <lb/>ness. I have been anxious in my in-
          <lb/>quiries concerning its origin and pro- <lb/>gress. All diſeaſes of a ſimilar nature
          <lb/>admit of a ſpeedy cure, when properly <lb/>treated. I have therefore been de-
          <lb/>ſirous, as a loyal and affectionate ſub- <lb/>ject, to offer my ſentiments upon your
          <lb/>Majeſty's deranged ſtate of health. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_3"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> thoughts which are inſerted <lb/>in the following ſheets may
          perhaps <lb/>be of ſome utility to your Majeſty. <lb/>And my intentions will be quite ac-
          <lb/>compliſhed, if they contribute, in the <lb/>ſmalleſt degree, to the reſtoration of
          <lb/>your health, and to the prevention of <lb/>relapſes. </p>
        <signed>
          <lb/>I am, <lb/>Your <hi rend="sc">Majesty</hi>'s <lb/>Moſt loyal and devoted <lb/>Subject
          and ſervant, <lb/>ROBERT JONES. </signed>
        <lb/>
        <dateline><hi rend="sc">Salisbury</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Jan.</hi> 1, 1789. </dateline>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_4"/>
        <head rend="align-center dc(2)">
          <lb/>INTRODUCTION. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HE pathology and practice of medi- <lb/>cine are (of all the
          arts and ſciences) <lb/>the leaſt which approach to certainty and <lb/>to truth; and the
          practitioners of phyſic <lb/>are therefore too often diſpoſed to appeal to
          <lb/>conjecture, analogy, and probability, in <lb/>their judgment and treatment of moſt
          diſ- <lb/>eaſes, rather than to reaſon, philoſophy, <lb/>and a ſcientific diſcernment of
          cauſes and <lb/>effects. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Even</hi> from the infancy of this art, we <lb/>find reaſoning from
          falſe principles pre- <pb xml:id="page_5" n="iv"/>
          <lb/>vail, inſtead of obſerving, with accuracy, <lb/>the uniform courſe of nature. The
          ſymp- <lb/>toms of diſeaſes are, therefore, more care- <lb/>fully noticed than their
          cauſes; and the <lb/>practice of phyſic is, conſequently, more <lb/>influenced by <hi
            rend="italic">effects</hi> than by <hi rend="italic">cauſes,</hi> which <lb/>ſhould be
          the ſolid baſis upon which all <lb/>reaſoning concerning diſeaſes ought to be
          <lb/>eſtabliſhed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> innovation which was introduced <lb/>in the practice of phyſic
          by the celebrated <lb/>Dr. Sydenham, was of eſſential importance, <lb/>ſo far as it was
          calculated to eſtabliſh a pro- <lb/>per and rational method of practice in all
          <lb/>diſeaſes of a phlogiſtic or inflammatory <lb/>nature; ſuch as the pleuriſy,
          ſmall-pox, <lb/>meaſles, and diſeaſes of this deſcription. <pb xml:id="page_6" n="v"/>
          <lb/>But it is very evident, that in thoſe of an <lb/>oppoſite nature, ſuch as nervous
          fevers, <lb/>palſies, apoplexies, epilepſies, and all diſ- <lb/>eaſes of this nature, it
          muſt produce a <lb/>different effect: and this is completely <lb/>proved, by its bringing
          on, in theſe modi- <lb/>fications of diſeaſe, the very worſt of conſe- <lb/>quences, and
          even death. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> principles and practice of this diſ- <lb/>tinguiſhed phyſician
          have therefore had a <lb/>bad effect, ſo far as they have been the <lb/>means of
          introducing a dangerous practice <lb/>in nine tenths of the diſeaſes of mankind. <lb/>For
          they have found their way into all the <lb/>principal ſchools of phyſic in Europe, and
          <lb/>prevail, to a great extent in the practice of <lb/>medicine, all over the world at
          this preſent <lb/>time. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_7" n="vi"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">All</hi> nervous diſeaſes, and fevers in par- <lb/>ticular, ariſe more
          frequently from domeſtic <lb/>anxieties, and paſſions of the mind, ſuch as <lb/>grief,
          diſappointment, and deſpair, than <lb/>from any other cauſes whatſoever. And <lb/>in order
          to remove them, it is evident, that <lb/>to increaſe the cauſe is not the method to
          <lb/>remove the diſeaſe. But the idea that ple- <lb/>thora, or too great a quantity of
          blood ex- <lb/>iſts in the body, and is therefore the cauſe <lb/>of theſe diſeaſes, is a
          moſt pernicious doc- <lb/>trine; conſequently bleeding, cupping, a <lb/>ſpare diet,
          purging, and applications of this <lb/>nature, are ſuppoſed to be efficacious in re-
          <lb/>moving of theſe ſeveral diſeaſes; and more <lb/>eſpecially when they affect athletic
          and ro- <lb/>buſt people. This ſuppoſed cauſe, there- <pb xml:id="page_8" n="vii"/>
          <lb/>fore, points out to a moſt dangerous method <lb/>of cure. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> has been the ſtudy of a great part of <lb/>my life to inquire
          into the defects which <lb/>prevail ſo univerſally in the practice of <lb/>phyſic; and I
          hope that the obſervations <lb/>I have made, and the improvements I have <lb/>in future to
          ſuggeſt, may be of ſome uti- <lb/>lity. The bulk of mankind are averſe <lb/>to the ſtudy
          of phyſic, from the tech- <lb/>nical terms, the endleſs multiplication of <lb/>cauſes, and
          the numerous uncouth names <lb/>for diſeaſes and their remedies, which pre- <lb/>vail ſo
          univerſally; therefore private gen- <lb/>tlemen were never remarkable for their
          <lb/>knowledge of this art, although they have <lb/>diſtinguiſhed themſelves often by
          their deep <pb xml:id="page_9" n="viii"/>
          <lb/>inquiries into law, antiquities, &amp;c. A Sel- <lb/>den and a Spelman were private
          gentle- <lb/>men; and no men have been more keen <lb/>in their reſearches concerning
          points of law <lb/>and conſtitutional topics. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>IT is therefore much to be lamented, <lb/>that men of fortune, rank, and learning,
          <lb/>do not bend their minds to inquiries into <lb/>ſubjects of ſo much importance to
          mankind <lb/>as the healing art. The healing art is <lb/>ſurely the moſt intereſting to
          our natures <lb/>of any whatſoever; and yet men of diſ- <lb/>tinction and conſequence in
          general treat <lb/>it as a department of knowledge beneath <lb/>their notice <note
            place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* There is an exception to this remark in an
            illuſtrious <lb/>foreigner, His Serene Highneſs the Prince and Duke de Bouil- <lb/>lon,
            who is not only a profound philoſopher, but a moſt diſ- <lb/>cerning phyſician. </note>.
          The practice of phyſic in <pb xml:id="page_10" n="ix"/>
          <lb/>Great Britain is, at this preſent time, to <lb/>be conſidered as the reſult of
          applying Dr. <lb/>Boerhaave's and Dr. Cullen's principles <lb/>to practice. Theſe ſyſtems
          have been moſt <lb/>compleatly exploded, both as falſe in their <lb/>principles, and moſt
          pernicious in their <lb/>practice <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* See Dr.
            Brown's works, and an Inquiry into the State of <lb/>Medicine, upon the principles of
            inductive philoſophy. </note>. And yet the advocates for theſe <lb/>ſyſtems of medicine
          are ſuffered to domi- <lb/>neer, as it were, over the ſufferings of <lb/>mankind. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> method of treating of nervous fe- <lb/>vers, of every
          deſcription, is in a lamentable <lb/>condition indeed. We hear of thoſe that <lb/>ſurvive;
          and the newſpapers inform us of <lb/>ſome that are dead. We ceaſe to inquire <lb/>into
          cauſes, and we ſit down contented <pb xml:id="page_11" n="x"/>
          <lb/>with viewing of effects. It is, I am for- <lb/>ward to ſay, owing to the
          miſmanagement <lb/>of the fair ſex after laying in, that we hear <lb/>of the death of ſo
          many. It is very likely <lb/>that they may experience a little fever at <lb/>this time;
          but ignorance and miſmanage- <lb/>ment <hi rend="italic">at this period</hi> is likely to
          convert it <lb/>into a nervous, or putrid fever, and death. <lb/>All mankind experience a
          pre-diſpoſition <lb/>to diſeaſes, before they announce them- <lb/>ſelves with all their
          formality and terrors <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* The doctrine of <hi
              rend="italic">pre-diſpoſition</hi> to diſeaſe is perhaps the <lb/>moſt important and
            uſeful department of phyſic. Every <lb/>man feels the approach of diſeaſe before it
            comes on, by a <lb/>variety of different ſymptoms, which are peculiar to every de-
            <lb/>ſcription of men. The Gout is known before it makes its ap- <lb/>pearance, to thoſe
            who have been accuſtomed to it, by flatulent <lb/>complaints in the ſtomach and bowels,
            accompanied with acid <lb/>eructations, and apprehenſions and fear of the diſeaſe. The
            <lb/>ſame is preciſely the caſe with fevers, and with great numbers <lb/>of nervous
            complaints. This is the time that a phyſician has <lb/>it in his power to exert his
            skill and judgment, and before the <lb/>diſeaſe makes its formal appearance; therefore a
            proper know- <lb/>ledge of the doctrine of pre-diſpoſition to diſeaſes, as it is called,
            <lb/>is of the greateſt utility in preventing the acceſſion of them. <lb/>Therefore Dr.
            Willis, with all deference to this phyſician, was <lb/>perfectly erroneous in aſſerting,
            that diſeaſes of the ſame nature <lb/>with that complaint under which his Majeſty has
            laboured are <lb/>liable to relapſes; for the knowledge of a ſtate of pre-diſpo-
            <lb/>ſition to diſeaſe will qualify a diſcerning phyſician to obſerve the <lb/>malady at
            a diſtance, and to prevent the tumult which it cre- <lb/>ates—relapſes, in theſe caſes,
            are therefore accounted for. It is <lb/>natural to ſuppoſe, that his Majeſty will be an
            invalid for ſome <lb/>time to come, and that he will be liable to trifling attacks of
            his <lb/>diſeaſe. During this period, it would be very adviſable that <lb/>there ſhould
            be a phyſician in conſtant attendance, who ought <lb/>to have nothing elſe to do but to
            wait on his royal patient, and <lb/>to obviate every little attack, by proper medicines,
            diet, &amp;c. <lb/>This plan will conſtantly enſure his Majeſty a good ſtate of
            <lb/>health, and enable him, in a ſhort ſpace of time, to be, from <lb/>experience
            alone, his own phyſician. </note>. <pb xml:id="page_12" n="xi"/>
          <lb/>When the diſeaſe takes place, we are not <lb/>in a condition to help ourſelves, and
          we <lb/>therefore are obliged to ſend for the advice <lb/>of thoſe who are ſuppoſed to be
          qualified to <pb xml:id="page_13" n="xii"/>
          <lb/>underſtand it. The patient, at this time, <lb/>is perhaps reſtleſs* <note
            place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">From the reports of his Majeſty's phyſicians of
            the 7th, <lb/>8th, and 9th of December, I am ſtill more ſtrengthened in my <lb/>opinion,
            that his diſeaſe is neither more nor leſs than a nervous <lb/>fever. Every man, in all
            deſcriptions of nervous fevers, is <lb/>rather incoherent, unleſs they are refreſhed by
            ſleep. For a <lb/>want of reſt debilitates the mind and body to a great degree.
            <lb/>This is proved by the invigorating effects of ſleep which his <lb/>Majeſty
            experienced on the 8th and 9th. he report is, <lb/>
            <q rend="quotes">His Majeſty has had more than ſeven hours undiſturbed ſleep <lb/>in the
              night, and is quiet this morning.</q> (Signed) </note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <signed>
        <lb/>
        <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">
  
            <lb/><hi rend="sc">R. Warren.</hi>
            <lb/>
            <hi rend="sc">J. R. Reynolds</hi>. 
        </note> , with a ſevere and heavy <lb/>feeling in the head, cold chills, with great
        <lb/>laſſitude, and full of melancholy apprehen- <lb/>ſions. Or he may labour under a
        delirium, <lb/>and raging fever. An error at this time is <lb/>irretrievable; and hence the
        neceſſity of <lb/>great judgment, and a nice diſcernment of <lb/>cauſes, in the phyſician.
        Bleeding, bliſter- <lb/>ing, vomiting, and purging, will at this <pb xml:id="page_14"
          n="xiii"/>
        <lb/>time encreaſe the malady, and, eventually, <lb/>bring on death. The delirium ariſes
        from <lb/>a weakened condition of the nervous and <lb/>vaſcular ſyſtem in general, but more
        eſpe- <lb/>cially in the brain. Sudorifics and opiates <lb/>produce a temporary relief; and
        it behoves <lb/>thoſe who adminiſter theſe medicines, to <lb/>take particular care that the
        patient is not <lb/>expoſed to the ſmalleſt degree of cold <lb/>during their operation, or
        the delirium will <lb/>be encreaſed, and all the ſymptoms of the <lb/>diſeaſe aggravated to
        an alarming degree. </signed>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">have</hi> had the management of a great <lb/>number of patients
          labouring under ner- <lb/>vous or putrid fevers, and have uniformly <lb/>been ſucceſſful
          in the treatment of this <pb xml:id="page_15" n="xiv"/>
          <lb/>dangerous diſeaſe. But I have obſerved, <lb/>and I have abundance of proofs to
          eſtabliſh <lb/>my obſervation, that it ſometimes happens, <lb/>that what is called a ſtate
          of inſanity, is <lb/>the conſequence of theſe fevers. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A <hi rend="sc">continual</hi> ſtate of delirium will <lb/>either bring on death, or
          a conſiderable re- <lb/>laxation in the blood veſſels of the brain, <lb/>which will <hi
            rend="italic">ſine vi a tergo,</hi> admit of more <lb/>blood within them, than they
          were, in <lb/>their vigorous and healthy ſtate, capable of <lb/>receiving; juſt in the
          ſame manner that <lb/>ſevere ſtudy, hard drinking, ſevere vomit- <lb/>ing, and the
          application of leeches to eyes <lb/>which are inflamed through weakneſs, will <lb/>produce
          a greater degree of inflammation <pb xml:id="page_16" n="xv"/>
          <lb/>in them, by weakening ſtill more theſe <lb/>parts <note place="bottom" n="*"
            rend="size(0.5)">* There are no diſeaſes more obſtinate in their cure than <lb/>ſome
            inflammatory conditions of the eyes. A great number of <lb/>people loſe their ſight by
            tampering with their eyes in this ſitu- <lb/>ation. The great object of ſurgery is to
            prevent the amputa- <lb/>tion of legs and arms, by curing of the diſeaſe, which, how-
            <lb/>ever, in ſome caſes, is abſolutely neceſſary. But ſurgeons, as <lb/>well as
            oculiſts, are too fond of uſing of inſtruments. Ocu- <lb/>liſts are not in general
            ſufficiently qualified to reaſon concerning <lb/>the cauſes of diſeaſes of the eyes,
            much leſs of obſtinate opthal- <lb/>mias, or inflammations affecting theſe organs; hence
            ariſes the <lb/>inveteracy of this diſeaſe. It is therefore probable, that a noble
            <lb/>Lord, once high in office, will loſe the uſe of his eyes from miſ- <lb/>management.
            For the method of treating theſe inflammations <lb/>of the eyes, is diametrically
            oppoſite to the indication of cure. <lb/>They are, from the inflammatory appearance of
            the blood veſ- <lb/>ſels, conceived to be real inflammatory diſeaſes, when the con-
            <lb/>trary, I am ready and willing to prove, is the fact, in nineteen <lb/>times out of
            twenty. I have had the management of a great <lb/>number of patients labouring under
            this obſtinate complaint, <lb/>and have been ſucceſſful in curing every individual that
            has <lb/>been under my care. <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>My motive in introducing of this ſubject is only to <lb/>ſhew, that in caſes of
              mental derangement, the blood veſſels <lb/>within the brain are in the preciſe
              ſituation of debility and re- <lb/>laxation which takes place in the blood veſſels
              which occupy <lb/>the anterior parts of the eyes in obſtinate <hi rend="italic"
                >Opthalmias;</hi> and that <lb/>to invigorate, by all poſſible means, the whole
              ſyſtem, and the <lb/>vaſcular ſyſtem in particular of the parts affected, is the only
              <lb/>cure. </p>
          </note>. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_17" n="xvi"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">There</hi> is no affliction more painful to <lb/>man than the gout; and
          yet important diſ- <lb/>coveries have been made of late, in order <lb/>to ſhew that it
          admits of a ſpeedy cure and <lb/>eaſy management. And I am well con- <lb/>vinced, from my
          own experience, that the <lb/>fear and apprehenſions of what takes place <lb/>in fits of
          this diſeaſe, often produces what <lb/>is called a relapſe. The apprehenſion of <lb/>the
          paſt feelings, and pains, generally <lb/>brings on a renewal of the diſeaſe. And
          <lb/>phyſicians ought to be particularly care- <lb/>ful to prevent their patients from
          going <pb xml:id="page_18" n="xvii"/>
          <lb/>out into the cold in a ſtate of convaleſ- <lb/>cence. Cold applied to the body in
          this <lb/>ſtate, and eſpecially at this time of the <lb/>year, will generally produce a
          relapſe; and <lb/>I ſuſpect that his Majeſty has experienced, <lb/>from this cauſe alone,
          diſagreeable conſe- <lb/>quences, and that very lately. In a ſtate <lb/>of convaleſcence,
          the mind is always me- <lb/>lancholy and dejected; and whatever weak- <lb/>ens the body at
          this time, will, to a cer- <lb/>tainty, bring on a return of the diſeaſe. <lb/>Exceſſive
          heat in ſultry weather produces <lb/>nearly the ſame effects. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> this treatiſe I have endeavoured to be <lb/>as ſhort and as
          conciſe as poſſible. But <lb/>in a future publication, which I have in <lb/>contemplation,
          I intend to offer my opi- <pb xml:id="page_19" n="xviii"/>
          <lb/>nions at ſome length, concerning ſome diſ- <lb/>eaſes which are known by the name of
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Opprobria Medicorum.</hi>
          <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* The Appendix and Notes, which it was my
            original in- <lb/>tention to make a part of this treatiſe, are to be inſerted in a
            <lb/>ſubſequent performance, which is to comprehend in it a great <lb/>variety of
            proofs, which are not taken notice of in this publi- <lb/>cation. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_20"/>
      <head rend="align-center dc(2)">
        <lb/>AN INQUIRY, &amp;c. </head>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">T</hi>HERE is not a diſeaſe which aſſumes <lb/>a greater variety of
        appearances, nor <lb/>has given occaſion to the loquacity and de- <lb/>cided opinions of
        practitioners of Medicine, <lb/>than the complaint which has for ſome <lb/>time paſt
        afflicted our moſt amiable Sove- <lb/>reign. At one time it is ſuppoſed to be <lb/>the Gout,
        at other times the Hypochon- <lb/>driaſis, and at others a Nervous Fever: <lb/>nay, it is
        diſtinguiſhed by almoſt every <lb/>name which is congenial to the medical <lb/>dogmas of
        practitioners of phyſic. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_21" n="2"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> unfortunately happens to mankind, <lb/>that the method of living
        which Phyſi- <lb/>cians in general obſerve, is likely to eſta- <lb/>bliſh a good ſtate of
        health; and hence <lb/>ariſes their implicit faith in books and ſyſ- <lb/>timatical writers.
        They are therefore ſel- <lb/>dom harraſſed with thoſe complaints, which <lb/>ſo conſtantly
        fall to the lot of ſocial, and <lb/>convivial ſpirits, which are commonly <lb/>Fevers, the
        Rheumatiſm, flatulent Com- <lb/>plaints, ſevere nervous Feelings in the <lb/>Head, and over
        every part of the body, <lb/>and the Gout. But while habits of con- <lb/>viviality produce
        theſe effects, the oppoſite <lb/>extreme, ſuch as abſtinence in wine and <lb/>animal food,
        and ſo forth, are attended with <lb/>preciſely the ſame conſequences, and this <lb/>ſtate is
        completely demonſtrated in the pre- <lb/>ſent deranged condition of his Majeſty's
        <lb/>health. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_22" n="3"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">have</hi> long been an enemy to Dr. <lb/>Cullen's practice in general
          <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* See Appendix, Note A. </note>; for I have
        <lb/>ſeen it ſo often attended with the moſt fa- <lb/>tal conſequences, and more eſpecially
        in <lb/>Fevers <note place="bottom" n="†" rend="size(0.5)">† See Appendix to an Inquiry into
          the State of Medicine. </note>. The natural termination of Fe- <lb/>vers is in a ſtate of
        delirium, and, ulti- <lb/>mately, in death, if a deranged condition <lb/>of the intellectual
        powers do not intervene <lb/>to prevent the diſſolution of nature. This <lb/>ſtate is called
        by the name of Madneſs: <lb/>and if human invention was abſolutely ne- <lb/>ceſſary to
        operate this effect, the method <lb/>now in uſe among practitioners of medi- <lb/>cine is
        compleatly equal to produce it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Let</hi> me ask this queſtion, What is it <lb/>that produces the diſeaſe
        known by the <lb/>name of a nervous, or putrid Fever? Every <lb/>phyſician, who has a grain
        of common <lb/>ſenſe, will anſwer, that it is produced by <pb xml:id="page_23" n="4"/>
        <lb/>debilitating cauſes! But in order to re- <lb/>fine upon theſe cauſes, and to ſpin a web
        of <lb/>their own creation, they will inſiſt upon <lb/>the addition of contagion, effluvia
        from <lb/>putrid ſubſtances, exhalations from marſhy <lb/>grounds, &amp;c. &amp;c. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> penetrating Rouſſeau wiſely ſays, <lb/>that "ſcience which
        inſtructs, and me- <lb/>dicine which cures, are both undoubt- <lb/>edly very good; but
        ſcience which deceives, <lb/>and medicine which kills, are bad. Teach <lb/>us how to
        diſcriminate them—there lies <lb/>the difficulty of the queſtion." </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">There</hi> never was an art more full of de- <lb/>ception than the
        practice of phyſic: and <lb/>this is completely illuſtrated, by the fatal <lb/>termination
        of moſt of the diſeaſes which <lb/>are inflicted by Providence upon mankind. <lb/>We are, in
        general, diſpoſed to refer the <lb/>cauſes of fevers, and other diſeaſes, to the <pb
          xml:id="page_24" n="5"/>
        <lb/>influence of phyſical cauſes alone, and to <lb/>overlook the operation of moral cauſes
        al- <lb/>together; whereas it can be proved, that <lb/>moral cauſes are chiefly the
        forerunners of <lb/>moſt diſeaſes depending upon debility; and <lb/>in this ſtate of the
        body, the application of <lb/>phyſical cauſes, ſuch as cold applied to it, <lb/>in a
        debilitated ſtate, heat, contagion, pu- <lb/>trid effluvia, and other powers, operating
        <lb/>upon ſimilar principles, will more effec- <lb/>tually produce diſeaſes of this nature;
        and <lb/>the effect of theſe powers will be the more <lb/>compleat, if to theſe are added
        exceſs of <lb/>every kind, immoderate indulgence in the <lb/>paſſions, fatigues of the mind,
        together <lb/>with the afflictions and pains which are felt <lb/>in every condition of
        mortality, from the <lb/>monarch to the beggar, and which harrow <lb/>up, and conſtantly
        prey upon our minds. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_25" n="6"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A <hi rend="sc">Monarch</hi> is perhaps the moſt ex- <lb/>poſed to theſe cauſes. For
        when we con- <lb/>ſider him in the capacity of the firſt ma- <lb/>giſtrate in the land, it
        is natural to ſup- <lb/>poſe that he muſt be burdened with cares <lb/>and apprehenſions, and
        liable to extreme <lb/>fatigues, both of body and mind, which <lb/>are to be always
        conſidered as the forbod- <lb/>ing vouchers of a bad ſtate of health. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">If nature, ſays Rouſſeau, had decreed <lb/>that we ſhould be ſound in body
          and <lb/>mind, I will venture to aſſert, that a <lb/>ſtate of reflection is a ſtate
          contrary to <lb/>nature; and that a man of meditation is <lb/>a depraved animal. Our
          misfortunes <lb/>originate in ourſelves, and that we ſhould <lb/>have avoided almoſt all
          of them, if we had <lb/>followed the ſimple, uniform, retired <lb/>manner preſcribed to us
          by nature <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Miſs Colbrooke's tranſlation of
            Rouſſeau's thoughts. </note>. </q>
      </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_26" n="7"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">These</hi> obſervations, of this profound <lb/>obſerver of nature, apply
        with much force <lb/>and propriety to the ſubject I am about to <lb/>treat upon. For, as I
        have obſerved before, <lb/>we have, from the moſt exalted of ſitua- <lb/>tions, to the moſt
        humble of human con- <lb/>ditions, our cares and our calamities to <lb/>ſuſtain. Yet it is
        natural to ſuppoſe, <lb/>that the individual who approaches the <lb/>moſt to the path
        preſcribed to us by na- <lb/>ture, experiences the feelings of tran- <lb/>quillity and
        pleaſure, in a more elevated <lb/>capacity, than the perſonage who, from <lb/>his ſituation,
        is conſtantly immured within <lb/>the walls of ſtudy and reflexion; which is <lb/>in a
        continual progreſſion to debilitate the <lb/>body, and to weaken the ſoul <note
          place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* See Note B. </note>. Hence <lb/>ariſe nervous
        complaints of all ſorts; ſuch <lb/>as the hypochondriaſis, epilepſy, palſy, <lb/>apoplexy,
        gout, and other diſeaſes of this <lb/>nature. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_27" n="8"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">have</hi> often been aſtoniſhed to hear, <lb/>that his Majeſty could
        ſuſtain, (without <lb/>being precipitated long before this time <lb/>into a ſtate of
        diſeaſe,) the weighty, and im- <lb/>portant buſineſs, which, like a millſtone, <lb/>muſt
        have hung heavy upon his mind, at <lb/>the ſame time that it was reported, that <lb/>he eat
        chiefly of vegetable food, and drank <lb/>nothing but wine and water. To carry on <lb/>a
        train of thought with vigour and effect, <lb/>or to tranſact buſineſs of conſequence,
        <lb/>which is often very diſagreeable to the <lb/>mind, requires the adventitious aid of
        ſti- <lb/>mulating food, and cordial liquors, or the <lb/>diſeaſes I have taken notice of
        above will <lb/>eventually take place. And phyſicians, as <lb/>well as their patients, will
        be woefully <lb/>deceived, if they ſuppoſe that either the <lb/>Cheltenham waters, or the
        Bath waters, <lb/>or even thoſe of Spa, will operate wonders, <pb xml:id="page_28" n="9"/>
        <lb/>when the enemy, I mean diſeaſe, has <lb/>ſtormed the citadel. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Diseases</hi>, in the commencement of <lb/>their attacks upon the
        conſtitution, are but <lb/>faint reſemblances of what are to happen. <lb/>But they enliven
        our ſenſibilities, and our <lb/>apprehenſions, in proportion to their pro- <lb/>gress; and
        our memories are at this time <lb/>eternally preſenting to us ſcenes in which <lb/>we have
        acted a part. Hence philoſophers, <lb/>as well as moraliſts, are conſtantly declaim-
        <lb/>ing againſt thoſe gloomy ideas which hurt <lb/>their ſolitary hours, and damp their
        moſt <lb/>aſpiring thoughts, by exhibiting things in <lb/>the moſt odious colours
        imaginable. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> cares and anxieties of private indi- <lb/>viduals, as well as of
        thoſe who are placed <lb/>in more elevated capacities, inſenſibly bring <lb/>on diſeaſes,
        and thoſe of a peculiar nature. <pb xml:id="page_29" n="10"/>
        <lb/>And there are ſometimes ſnares, which even <lb/>wiſdom and prudence will not prevent
        our <lb/>falling into. Although a warrior is often <lb/>liable to them, a ſtateſman is
        infinitely <lb/>more ſo, which the hiſtory of mankind <lb/>completely proves. Domeſtic
        anxieties, <lb/>popular tumults, and national diſaſters, <lb/>muſt conſtantly aggravate his
        feelings; and <lb/>theſe marks of ſenſibility will, ſooner or <lb/>later, produce nervous
        diſeaſes. The con- <lb/>dition of ſtateſmen in general is by no means <lb/>applicable to the
        ſituation of the firſt ma- <lb/>giſtrate of his dominions, who has the per- <lb/>petual call
        of his people to the exerciſe of <lb/>every thing that is wiſe, juſt, and benevo- <lb/>lent.
        And when wiſdom, virtue, benevo- <lb/>lence, and prudence, are diſappointed in <lb/>their
        intentions, maladies of a moſt forbid- <lb/>ding aſpect too often take place. Therefore
        <lb/>the only conſolation we can enjoy when we <lb/>are afflicted with diſeaſe, is to ſubmit
        with <pb xml:id="page_30" n="11"/>
        <lb/>patience and philoſophy to the fate of <lb/>men, and to the decrees of fate. Nay, if
        <lb/>a ſtraight waiſtcoat is adviſed by a grave <lb/>phyſician, as a neceſſary appendage to
        our <lb/>miſery, we muſt even ſubmit to this moſt <lb/>infernal, and brutal uſage. And this
        act <lb/>of brutality, I am both free, and bold <lb/>enough to acknowledge, is the
        conſequence <lb/>of employing of thoſe, who are profoundly <lb/>ignorant of the principles,
        and philoſophy <lb/>of the healing art. I have ſaid before, <lb/>that what is commonly
        termed madneſs, <lb/>is brought on by the improper treatment <lb/>of fevers: for this
        diſeaſe is no more here- <lb/>ditary than the Gout, or the ſcrofula, <lb/>which I have
        ſhewn, in my treatiſe upon <lb/>the Gout, to be a diſeaſe depending upon <lb/>the common
        cauſes of a relaxed habit. But <lb/>I need not appeal to a greater authority, than <lb/>my
        late learned preceptor, and worthy friend, <lb/>Dr. Brown, who has had the honour to <pb
          xml:id="page_31" n="12"/>
        <lb/>explain, with the forcible language of <lb/>truth, the nature of this diſeaſe, as well
        <lb/>as almoſt every other incident to man. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> idea leads me to a digreſſion which <lb/>I did not intend to
        make. But as I con- <lb/>ceive it to be of ſome importance to man- <lb/>kind, I intend to
        offer my opinions, at <lb/>ſome length, upon the ſubject, as they <lb/>may be of utility to
        mankind. I ſhall <lb/>therefore conſider the ſubject, both as a <lb/>philoſopher, as well as
        a phyſician; and I <lb/>hope that a diſcerning public will not im- <lb/>pute blame to an
        intention, which has <lb/>the benefit of my fellow creatures before <lb/>me. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">When</hi> I viſited the <hi rend="italic">Biſſetre</hi> at Paris, in
        <lb/>the year 1785, I could not forbear exhi- <lb/>biting my ſenſibilities, and my feelings,
        at <lb/>ſeeing ſuch a number of unfortunate per- <pb xml:id="page_32" n="13"/>
        <lb/>ſons chained down to their ſolitary abodes, <lb/>without any other cauſe, from what I
        could <lb/>learn, than the peculiarity of their conduct, <lb/>or excentricity of their
        behaviour. In the <lb/>courſe of my walk, and obſervations, I came <lb/>to the cell of an
        Engliſhman, who had been a <lb/>captain of a trading veſſel from Dover, and <lb/>who had
        been captured by a French priva- <lb/>teer in the war before laſt <note place="bottom" n="*"
          rend="size(0.5)">* He ſaid that he had been 30 years in conſinement at the <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Biſſetre.</hi>
        </note>. I had two <lb/>Engliſh ladies, a French lady, and a French <lb/>gentleman in my
        company; and as ſoon as <lb/>he found that there were Engliſh in com- <lb/>pany, he ſpoke
        his mind very freely to us, <lb/>and told us his ſtory with the moſt perfect
        <lb/>diſtinctneſs. His mind was perfectly col- <lb/>lected, and he was much diſpoſed to ex-
        <lb/>press the fervency of it during the time we <lb/>were in converſation with him; but the
        <lb/>police of the place rendered it neceſſary that <pb xml:id="page_33" n="14"/>
        <lb/>we ſhould ſaunter on to another abode of <lb/>miſery, and quit the manſion of this ſon
        <lb/>of misfortune. The pleaſures of commu- <lb/>nicating his ſorrowful tale to his country-
        <lb/>women and myſelf being thus abruptly in- <lb/>terrupted, muſt unqueſtionably have af-
        <lb/>fected the feelings of the deſpairing man; <lb/>and we could hear him, upon our depar-
        <lb/>ture, break out into all the wild language <lb/>of fury and deſpair. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi>, as well as many other caſes which <lb/>I could place before my
        reader, during my <lb/>ſtay at this place, is a proof that moral cauſes <lb/>have as great,
        if not a greater influence, <lb/>in creating and perpetuating of nervous <lb/>diſeaſes of
        all kinds, than phyſical cauſes; <lb/>and of that diſeaſe, called <hi rend="italic"
          >mania,</hi> in parti- <lb/>cular. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> leads me, in a natural direction, <lb/>to conſider the
        character and important <pb xml:id="page_34" n="15"/>
        <lb/>truſt generally repoſed by their patients, <lb/>and the friends and relations of their
        pa- <lb/>tients, in practitioners of phyſic. I have <lb/>endeavoured to ſhew, in my Inquiry
        into <lb/>the State of Medicine, that the education <lb/>of phyſicians in general has a
        tendency to <lb/>lead them to engage in diſputes of words, <lb/>while they imagine that they
        are handling <lb/>controverſies of the deepeſt importance and <lb/>concern. It was in order
        to avoid alter- <lb/>cations ſo frivolous and endleſs, that the <lb/>penetrating and learned
        Dr. John Brown <lb/>endeavoured to ſtate, with the utmoſt cau- <lb/>tion and ſimplicity, the
        great <hi rend="italic">deſiderata</hi> of <lb/> medicine, and to frame a plan of his own,
        <lb/>for the removal of all the obſtacles to the <lb/>improvement of this noble art. This
        il- <lb/>luſtrious man ſaw, almoſt intuitively, the <lb/>cobwebs which hung in ſuſpence the
        fate <lb/>of mankind: and if he had not united <lb/>philoſophy, and profound learning, to-
          <pb xml:id="page_35" n="16"/>
        <lb/>gether with much experience, the healing <lb/>art might languiſh in its preſent
        deplorable <lb/>condition for ages to come. </p>
      <q rend="diple quotes">
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>"Ab hujus operis ſcriptore viginti am- <lb/>plius anni diſcende, docendo, nullas me-
          <lb/>dicinæ partes, non diligenter ſcrutando, <lb/>conſumpti. Quoram annorum quinque
          <lb/>primi, aliunde accipiendo, accepta cog- <lb/>noſcendo, credendo, quaſi pretioſam poſ-
          <lb/>ſeſſionem occupando; proximum luſ- <lb/>trum, ſingula clarius explanando, ſub-
          <lb/>tilius excolendo, poliendo; tertium du- <lb/>bitando, quia nihil ad mentem proceſ-
          <lb/>ſerat, algendo, cum multis claris viris, <lb/>cum ipſo vulgo, pro incerta penitus et
          <lb/>incomprehenſibili ſalutiferam artem de- <lb/>plorando; ſine fructu, ſine dulciſſima
          <lb/>rerum menti, luce veri, præteriere, tan- <lb/>taque caduce et brevis ævi mortalis
          pars, <lb/>tam opima, periit. Solo quarto luſtro, <pb xml:id="page_36" n="17"/>
          <lb/>veluti viatori, ignota regione, perditis <lb/>viæ veſtigiis, in umbra noctis erranti,
          per o <lb/>bſcura quædam, quaſi prima diurna, lux <lb/>demum adfulſit." </p>
        <lb/><hi rend="sc align-right">Brun. Med. Elem.</hi>
      </q>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To return, however, to my ſubject. <lb/>Diſeaſes and death are the uniform fate of
        <lb/>mortals. The infirmities of life, and the <lb/>pains of diſeaſe, will naturally obtrude
        <lb/>themſelves upon thoſe in exalted ſituations, <lb/>as well as upon the moſt humble of
        beings; <lb/>and in this condition of things it is, that re- <lb/>flection takes place. In
        the gay and plea- <lb/>ſing moments of feſtivity and health, the <lb/>fleeting moments of
        mirth and diſſipation <lb/>eraze all thoughts from our minds which <lb/>are diſagreeable to
        us <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* See Appendix, Note D. </note>; and hence
        amuſe- <lb/>ments of all ſorts are ſought after by the <lb/>more wealthy, to ſtifle thoſe
        ſentiments of <pb xml:id="page_37" n="18"/>
        <lb/>diſappointment, mortification, and chagrin, <lb/>which muſt, in a greater or leſſer
        degree, <lb/>influence all deſcriptions of individuals; <lb/>but when the cruel hand of
        diſeaſe renders <lb/>man a ſolitary animal, it is then that he <lb/>begins to think of the
        paſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">There</hi> are no diſeaſes which aſſume a <lb/>greater variety of
        appearances than <hi rend="italic">Agues, <lb/>Fevers,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic"
          >Gout.</hi> When the gout flies <lb/>to the head, it renders the feelings of the
        <lb/>patient exquiſitely painful. When the ague <lb/>viſits the head, the feelings are
        preciſely <lb/>the ſame. Nay, in what phyſicians call <lb/><hi rend="italic">nervous
          fevers,</hi> there is the ſame intermiſſion <lb/>of diſagreeable ſymptoms which prevails
        in <lb/>the gout as well as in intermittent fevers. <lb/>The patient is utterly at a loſs to
        explain <lb/>certain ſymptoms which take place in in- <lb/>termittents, ſuch as the ſevere
        and dreadful <lb/>feelings which rack his head, and put him <pb xml:id="page_38" n="19"/>
        <lb/>in momentary expectation of death. The <lb/>ſame is preciſely the caſe in the gout. For
        <lb/>the ſame appearances of the body, ſuch as <lb/>extreme languor, melancholy apprehen-
        <lb/>ſions, a ſtate of deſpair, more or leſs, tre- <lb/>mors, a ſuſceptibility of what is
        commonly <lb/>called catching cold, a propenſity to think <lb/>in a diſagreeable train of
        thought, and ſe- <lb/>veral other ſymptoms of the ſame nature, <lb/>are obſervable in this
        diſeaſe alſo. Putrid, <lb/>or what are termed nervous fevers, diſcover <lb/>a great
        reſemblance in their progreſs and ter- <lb/>mination to theſe foregoing diſeaſes, and are
        <lb/>alſo to be relieved by a ſimilar treatment. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> the numerous hypotheſis of phyſi- <lb/>cians concerning theſe
        three diſtinct modi- <lb/>fications of diſeaſes, form inſurmountable <lb/>barriers to their
        being treated upon ſimilar <lb/>principles; and hence the diffuſion of er- <lb/>ror, and
        unaccountable torpor, which pre- <pb xml:id="page_39" n="20"/>
        <lb/>ſo univerſally among practitioners of <lb/>phyſic, in their treatment of them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">There</hi> is no end to the variety of books <lb/>and diſſertations upon
        medical ſubjects <lb/>written by phyſicians. But the influence <lb/>of the paſſions has
        been, in almoſt all theſe <lb/>verbal diſputes and diſſertations, too un- <lb/>heededly
        paſſed over. <q rend="quotes">An evil, con- <lb/>ceived as barely poſſible, ſometimes pro-
          <lb/>duces fear; eſpecially if the evil be very <lb/>great. A man cannot think on
          exceſſive <lb/>pain and torture without trembling, if <lb/>he runs the leaſt riſque of
          ſuffering <lb/>them. The ſmallneſs of the probability <lb/>is compenſated by the greatneſs
          of the <lb/>evil <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Hume's Eſſays. </note>.
        </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">have</hi> often experienced the truth of <lb/>this obſervation in my
        own perſon. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_40" n="21"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> regulation of the paſſions is, there- <lb/>fore, in all nervous
        diſeaſes, a principal <hi rend="italic">deſi- <lb/>deratum:</hi> and the phyſician who is
        not phi- <lb/>loſopher enough to know how and when <lb/>to apply with ſucceſs his
        penetration in the <lb/>regulation of the paſſions, will very ſeldom <lb/>relieve a nervous
        diſeaſe, or a diſordered <lb/>ſtate of the intellect. What is the reaſon <lb/>that there are
        ſo many receptacles for what <lb/>the ignorant world call mad people? I will <lb/>anſwer
        very frankly, it is becauſe ſo much <lb/>ignorance and want of true philoſophy <lb/>prevail
        among the generality of phyſicians. <lb/>It is an abominable diſgrace to Britain, to
        <lb/>behold ſuch a number of public, as well as <lb/>private mad-houſes, as there are in
        this <lb/>iſland. When an unfortunate man or wo- <lb/>man have been miſmanaged in a dreadful
        <lb/>and alarming diſeaſe, it is propoſed by <lb/>ſome ignorant or intereſted dæmon or
        other, <lb/>to ſend the miſerable object of pity and <pb xml:id="page_41" n="22"/>
        <lb/>compaſſion to ſome place of ſecurity, where <lb/>he has nothing to conſole him but
        cold, <lb/>hunger, and ill uſage. It is impoſſible to <lb/>ſpeak too much at large
        concerning the <lb/>diſeaſes brought upon mankind by the all- <lb/>powerful operation of the
        paſſion of fear, <lb/>in its different modifications. Both Mr. <lb/>Hume, and Rouſſeau,
        ſpeak of this paſſion, <lb/>as to its cauſes and effects; and they ſeem <lb/>to be in ſome
        meaſure right, ſo far as it <lb/>produces diſeaſes of the nervous kind, and <lb/>what are
        vulgarly called maniacal diſeaſes <lb/>among the reſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple quotes">"A <hi rend="sc">dibilitated </hi> body", ſays Rouſ- <lb/>ſeau,
          weakens the ſoul. On this is <lb/>founded the empire of medicine; an art <lb/>more
          pernicious to man than all the ills <lb/>it pretends to cure. For my own part, <lb/>I know
          not of what diſorders phyſicians <lb/>cure us; but I know this, that they give <pb
            xml:id="page_42" n="23"/>
          <lb/>ſome which are very fatal, ſuch as cow- <lb/>ardice, puſillanimity, and the fear of
          <lb/>death. If they cure our body, they kill <lb/>courage. What is the importance of en-
          <lb/>abling carcaſſes to walk? It is man that <lb/>we want, and we never ſee any come
          <lb/>from under their hands <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* See Miſs
            Colebrook's tranſlation. </note>." </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> ingenious philoſopher was in a <lb/>great meaſure right in his
        obſervations. For <lb/>there is not a doubt, but that the method <lb/>adopted by phyſicians
        in former ages, as <lb/>well as in thoſe of our own times, is de- <lb/>ſtructive of that
        principle which upholds <lb/>us in afflictions, as well as in diſeaſe, and <lb/>that is
        courage. I do not at all wonder that <lb/>dramatic writers, ſuch as Moliere, and other
        <lb/>authors of ſagacity and penetration, were <lb/>forward in decyphering the hypocriſy and
        <lb/>artifice which predominate ſo much among <pb xml:id="page_43" n="24"/>
        <lb/>ſome practitioners of medicine. It is quite <lb/>enough to deſtroy a man's courage, in
        a <lb/>ſtate of diſeaſe, to ſee two, three, or more <lb/>phyſicians, dreſſed in black, with
        grave <lb/>countenances, and every affected art which <lb/>formality itſelf can invent <note
          place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* See Appendix, Note E. </note>.—To depreſſed
        <lb/>ſpirits and afflicted minds, ſuch ſymbols <lb/>of compaſſion and relief hold out no
        allure- <lb/>ments to pleaſe and to gratify a diſtempered <lb/>mind, which requires every
        ſolacement <lb/>which virtuous ſenſibility is ever ready to <lb/>communicate to the
        unfortunate. The <lb/>Scriptures ſay, <q rend="quotes">Bleſſed is the peace- <lb/>maker;
        </q> but how much more bleſſed and <lb/>happy muſt that man be, who, by his pro- <lb/>found
        knowledge in his profeſſion, aided <lb/>by that of deep philoſophy, and a know- <lb/>ledge
        of the paſſions, knows how to curb <lb/>them, and when to raiſe them! he muſt <lb/>ſurely
        afford the greateſt of comforts to the <lb/>diſtracted mind, and dibilitated body. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_44" n="25"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">When</hi> I left the univerſity, I flattered <lb/>myſelf with the belief,
        that all diſeaſes were <lb/>to be cured by medicine and diet. And I <lb/>have often
        expreſſed my ſurpriſe, that my <lb/>attempts in ſome inſtances were ineffectual. <lb/>But
        when the patient was dead, ſome un- <lb/>foreſeen circumſtance then made its appear-
        <lb/>ance, which ſufficiently convinced me, that <lb/>corroding cares had long preyed upon
        the <lb/>mind, and that the heart had bled with re- <lb/>peated ſorrows; which has often
        ſince made <lb/>me think, that phyſic and phyſicians are <lb/>but imperfect inſtruments to
        reſtore to vi- <lb/>gour, conſtitutions worn out with cares and <lb/>anxiety. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A <hi rend="sc">poor</hi> man, when reduced in intellec- <lb/>tual and bodily vigour by
        ill uſage, and the <lb/>ſophiſtry and empiriciſm which prevail in <lb/>medicine, is ſent for
        the remainder of his <lb/>days to Bedlam, or ſome other manſion of <pb xml:id="page_45"
          n="26"/>
        <lb/>miſery. The rich man is confined to <lb/>his own chambers, without one gleam <lb/>of
        hope, either to invigorate his body, or <lb/>comfort his mind. He is deprived of the
        <lb/>ſociety of thoſe he loves and reſpects. The <lb/>amuſements which he had been
        accuſtomed <lb/>to are never to refreſhen his waſted ſpirits, <lb/>or his decayed body; and
        in this ſolitary <lb/>and dreadful condition is he to expiate, if <lb/>he has any, all his
        errors and his ſins. I <lb/>would rather, if I had my choice, be car- <lb/>ried about the
        country, as Bajazet the Em- <lb/>peror of the Ottomans was, a ſpectacle for <lb/>fools, and
        worſe than fools, to look at, than <lb/>be a priſoner in the predicament I have
        <lb/>mentioned. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Were</hi> I poſſeſſed of all the eloquence of <lb/>Demoſthenes, Cicero,
        and Tully, I fear I <lb/>ſhould be unequal to utter my ſentiments <lb/>at full length upon
        this important topic; <pb xml:id="page_46" n="27"/>
        <lb/>becauſe I am well aware, that all diſeaſes, <lb/>where the vigour of the mind is
        affected, are <lb/>the reſult of the paſſion of fear, which is a <lb/>moſt debilitating
        paſſion, and is the prin- <lb/>cipal cauſe of almoſt all nervous diſeaſes. <lb/>There is not
        a doubt but that it frequently <lb/>produces convulſive, as well as ſpaſmodic <lb/>diſeaſes;
        and I have been a witneſs to its <lb/>bringing on fits of the gout repeatedly. I <lb/>have
        not a doubt in my own mind but that <lb/>it brings on the hydrophobia, and melan-
        <lb/>cholic diſeaſes, and what phyſicians term <lb/>mania, or madneſs. And I am well con-
        <lb/>vinced, that phyſic, as it is generally prac- <lb/>tiſed, is the moſt ſuitable of all
        profeſſions <lb/>to produce this nervous diſeaſe. If a <lb/>perſon, in a debilitated ſtate
        of the body, is <lb/>bled, bliſtered, vomited, and purged, he <lb/>will, to a certainty,
        experience ſome ſevere <lb/>nervous diſeaſe. But if theſe dibilitating <lb/>powers are added
        to the diſeaſe, it is natural <pb xml:id="page_47" n="28"/>
        <lb/>to ſuppoſe, that death will be the conſe- <lb/>quence, unleſs what phyſicians call
        inſa- <lb/>nity takes place. <q rend="diple quotes">"But even <hi rend="italic"
            >impoſſible</hi>
          <lb/>evils, ſays Mr. Hume, cauſe fear; <lb/>as when we tremble on the brink of <lb/>a
          precipice, though we know ourſelves <lb/>to be in a ſtate of perfect ſecurity, <lb/>and
          have it in our choice whether we <lb/>will advance a ſtep farther. The im- <lb/>mediate
          preſence of the evil influences <lb/>the imagination, and produces a ſpecies <lb/>of
          belief; but being oppoſed by the re- <lb/>flection on our ſecurity, the belief is im-
          <lb/>mediately retracted, and cauſes <hi rend="italic">the ſame <lb/>kind</hi> of paſſion
          as when, from a contra- <lb/>riety of chances, contrary paſſions are <lb/>produced <note
            place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Hume's Eſſays. </note>. </q>" </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> paſſions produce infinitely greater <lb/>effects upon the mind
        when the body is <pb xml:id="page_48" n="29"/>
        <lb/>in a debilitated ſtate, than when it enjoys <lb/>a healthy and vigorous ſtate, whether
        this <lb/>condition of the body ariſes from a too <lb/>ſpare diet, or from a too voluptuous
        one. <lb/>The imagination is infinitely more lively <lb/>with apprehenſion in relaxed
        habits, than <lb/>in vigorous conſtitutions. And hence ari- <lb/>ſes the great neceſſity of
        caution, preſence <lb/>of mind, and minute circumſpection in <lb/>thoſe who are commiſſioned
        to attend the <lb/>ſick. For an error at this time is often ir- <lb/>retrievable, but more
        eſpecially when gen- <lb/>tlemen of the faculty attend patients in ex- <lb/>alted
        ſituations. Their empiriciſm, inſtead <lb/>of aſſuming the bold and decided practice <lb/>of
        Van Helmont, or Paracelſus, now puts <lb/>on an air of timidity, for fear of what are
        <lb/>termed <hi rend="italic">the conſequences.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To contribute, by want of foreſight, or <lb/>a profound and diſcriminating knowledge
          <pb xml:id="page_49" n="30"/>
        <lb/>of diſeaſes, to the death of any department <lb/>of ſociety, is generally a prelude to
        their <lb/>want of buſineſs as phyſicians; and there- <lb/>fore it is natural to preſume,
        that they <lb/>will exerciſe more than common caution, <lb/>and indulge in more than uſual
        timi- <lb/>dity, when they are to preſcribe for their <lb/>Sovereign. As fevers are the
        reſult of de- <lb/>bilitating powers, and conſiſt of debility <lb/>over every part of the
        body, but more eſ- <lb/>pecially in the head, it is to be preſumed, <lb/>that the King's
        phyſicians abſtained from <lb/>bleeding, bliſtering, &amp;c. in their late treat- <lb/>ment
        of him. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">An</hi> unuſual fatality is generally the lot <lb/>of kings, when they
        are ſubjected, by either <lb/>accident or diſeaſe, to the fate preſcribed <lb/>by nature for
        man. In his healthy and <lb/>vigorous ſtate, both of body and mind, he <lb/>is, as it were,
        elevated by the exceſſive obei- <pb xml:id="page_50" n="31"/>
        <lb/>ſance of his courtiers, to a rank infinitely <lb/>ſuperior to the reſt of mankind.—But
        <lb/>obſerve the reverſe! When all-prying <lb/>diſeaſe commits its havock upon his body,
        <lb/>and his mind, then he is reduced to a level <lb/>with the reſt of mankind, if not to a
        greater <lb/>ſtate of mortification, and even humilia- <lb/>tion. That nature, in a great
        meaſure, <lb/>points to relief, is a rule of infinite impor- <lb/>tance in the healing art,
        but never attended <lb/>to as it ought, by thoſe who have the <lb/>management of the ſick. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To regulate the mind in all diſeaſes, but <lb/>more eſpecially in all nervous
        complaints, <lb/>is an object of fundamental importance <note place="bottom" n="*"
          rend="size(0.5)">* The bite of the <hi rend="italic">Tarantula,</hi> they affirm, is to be
          cured by <lb/>muſic; and I do not deny the poſſibility of it in ſome caſes. <lb/>The bite
          of the rattle-ſnake, by the ſnake-root; the ague, by <lb/>the Peruvian bark; the bite of a
          mad dog, by immerſion in <lb/>ſea-water, nearly approaching to drowning the patient; the
          <lb/>ſyphibilic diſeaſe, by mercury; ſchirrous and cancerated parts, <lb/>by preparations
          of hemlock, and ſo forth, <hi rend="italic">ad infinitum.</hi> The <lb/>efficacy of theſe
          medicines, and applications, in theſe particular <lb/>diſeaſes, depend as much in the
          expectation of relief they afford, <lb/>as in any ſpecific virtues they are endowed with.
          I have not <lb/>a doubt, but that the greateſt number of theſe diſeaſes are brought
          <lb/>on through fear, and its effects upon the imagination, and are <lb/>cured more by
          exciting of hope, than from any ſpecific virtue <lb/>of medicine. The death of Dr. Walſh,
          and that of Dr. Pur- <lb/>nel, is to be explained upon the ſame principles. They were
          <lb/>no doubt brought up in the belief, that dangerous conſequences <lb/>muſt reſult from
          inoculating themſelves with matter from putrid <lb/>bodies; and I have not a doubt, but
          the fear ariſing from this <lb/>belief precipitated them into fevers, and miſmanagement
          after <lb/>this into their graves. I have often experienced the effects of <lb/>contagion
          in my own perſon; but being regardleſs of the conſe- <lb/>quences, and being confident in
          my own plan of managing of <lb/>theſe diſeaſes, I never experienced any bad effects from
          con- <lb/>tagion. </note>. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_51" n="32"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">take</hi> from a man the pleaſures that he <lb/>has been accuſtomed to,
        you hurt his peace <lb/>of mind, and deſtroy for ever his ſweet-re- <lb/>poſe. Deprive him
        of his uſual comforts, <lb/>and you make him a miſerable and melan- <lb/>choly being. If a
        man is fond of the plea- <lb/>ſures of a country life, ſuch as farming, <lb/>gardening, the
        ſports of the field, and <lb/>amuſements of this nature, which are con- <lb/>ducive to his
        propenſities as a moral agent, <lb/>you deprive him of the principal comforts <pb
          xml:id="page_52" n="33"/>
        <lb/>which this world is capable of affording <lb/>him. If he is fond of the ſubject of
        moral <lb/>philoſophy, natural philoſophy, or the ſub- <lb/>ject of mechanical knowledge, it
        naturally <lb/>implies, that a deprivation of theſe plea- <lb/>ſures, which are the
        accompanyments of <lb/>his ſolitary hours, are equivalent to the de- <lb/>privation of his
        happineſs. And without <lb/>this celeſtial enjoyment, life, I will venture <lb/>to ſay, is
        not worth enjoying. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Philosophers</hi> have endeavoured to ex- <lb/>plain the cauſes of
        ſuicide, but their at- <lb/>tempts have been ineffectual; becauſe no <lb/>remedy has
        hitherto been applied to the <lb/>diſeaſe. Like the laws of the Romans, <lb/>which were,
        before the reign of the Empe- <lb/>ror Juſtinian, an endleſs ſubject of munici- <lb/>pal
        ordinances, ſo alſo have been the max- <lb/>ims and ſpeculations of men, to put a ſtop
        <lb/>to this unfortunate failure of courage in <pb xml:id="page_53" n="34"/>
        <lb/>man. It would be an endleſs ſubject to <lb/>multiply examples of the cruelties
        exerciſed <lb/>upon men in one form or the other. Mora- <lb/>liſts and philoſophers may
        preach to eter- <lb/>nity upon this ſubject, and never reach at <lb/>the cauſe. They are as
        widely at variance <lb/>with the origin of this unfortunate pro- <lb/>penſity, as the
        greateſt number of phyſici- <lb/>ans are in the proper treatment of nervous <lb/>diſeaſes.
        Even the elegant admonitions of <lb/>Rouſſeau make me ſmile when he pretends <lb/>to ſpeak
        upon the ſubject, and are to be <lb/>conſidered as neither more nor leſs than <lb/>Job's
        comforters. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Every</hi> good and benevolent man is of <lb/>uſe to ſociety during the
        period of his ex- <lb/>iſtence: but deprive this virtuous charac- <lb/>ter, by human
        ordinances, of that pre-emi- <lb/>nence which his goodneſs, his charitable
        <lb/>inclinations, and his univerſal ſentiments <pb xml:id="page_54" n="35"/>
        <lb/>of benevolence prompt him to exerciſe; <lb/>nay, go a ſtep further, ſay that he is in-
        <lb/>ſane, and then you complete, in ſome mea- <lb/>ſure, the cataſtrophe <note
          place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* It is ſaid that Dr. Warren, when examined before
          the <lb/>Privy Council, made uſe of the word <hi rend="italic">inſanity,</hi> as applying
          to <lb/>his Majeſty's diſeaſe, and that he was reprimanded by Lord <lb/>Camden for ſuch an
          expreſſion. If the Doctor had made uſe of <lb/>ſuch language, it is impoſſible for any
          words to be ſufficiently <lb/>ſevere for the noble earl to make uſe of, to curb ſuch a
          wanton <lb/>and unbounded expreſſion of ſpeech. In the inferior conditions <lb/>of life,
          the expreſſion alluded to is equivalent to die deſtruction <lb/>of a man's credit and
          happineſs for ever. But in the more ex- <lb/>alted ſituation of a monarch, it not only
          affects the credit and <lb/>importance of the nation he governs, but muſt fall upon his
          <lb/>offſpring; and the more eſpecially, as this diſeaſe is ſup- <lb/>poſed, without any
          ground for ſuch a ſuppoſition, to be <hi rend="italic">here- <lb/>ditary.</hi>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Dr. Reynolds, upon his examination, ſays, that his Ma- <lb/>jeſty's complaint may
            laſt for weeks, months, and years. And <lb/>I am willing to admit of this prophecy,
            unleſs a different plan <lb/>is purſued than that which has been adopted by the learned
            <lb/>Doctor's friends and himſelf, which, from all accounts that I <lb/>have yet been
            able to learn, muſt encreaſe the malady rather <lb/>than remove it. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When the King went to Cheltenham, I mentioned to my <lb/>friends, who are ready to
            prove what I ſaid, that his diſeaſe <lb/>would be encreaſed, rather than be diminiſhed,
            by his drinking <lb/>of the waters of that place. They were by no means ſuitable <lb/>to
            remove his diſeaſe, but to encreaſe it. I ſuſpected that a <lb/>dropſy, inſtead of a
            fever, would be the reſult of his drinking <lb/>the Cheltenham waters. If Sir George
            Baker, or any other <lb/>phyſician whoſe advice had been called for at that time, had
            <lb/>recommended a proper quantity of Madeira, indulgence in <lb/>animal food, &amp;c.
            inſtead of ice creams, and vegetable prepa- <lb/>rations, he might have the gout in his
            feet, which would be of <lb/>infinite ſervice to him, inſtead of a fever, which
            unfortunately <lb/>has affected the moſt tender part of the nervous ſyſtem. For <lb/>my
            own part, I fee nothing difficult in reſtoring the King to <lb/>his uſual ſtate of
            health; and I ſhould experience infinite plea- <lb/>ſure in being inſtrumental in
            rendering of the ſmalleſt ſervice <lb/>to ſo virtuous a monarch. </p>
        </note>
      </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_55" n="36"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> order to carry folly and ignorance <lb/>ſtill further, deny the
        ſame individual the <lb/>pleaſures of ſeeing and converſing with <lb/>thoſe that are dear to
        him; if he is fond of <lb/>muſic, deprive him of that; if he is deſir- <lb/>ous of ſeeing
        and of converſing with any <lb/>perſon more than another, be ſure that he is <lb/>deprived
        of this conſolation; if his family, <lb/>which are dear to him, and moſt amiable <lb/>in his
        eyes, are requeſted to afford him <lb/>comfort, they are by the ſame authority de- <lb/>nied
        acceſs; if the ſame individual ſhould <lb/>long for wine, and other cordials, to raiſe <pb
          xml:id="page_56" n="37"/>
        <lb/>his drooping ſpirits, this, forſooth, is ſup- <lb/>poſed to be pernicious; and all this
        for no <lb/>other reaſon, but from the mere <hi rend="italic">ipſe dixit</hi>
        <lb/>of a ſet of men, who preſume to hang in <lb/>ſuſpence the fate of men, as well as the
        fate <lb/>of kingdoms. This complication of evils <lb/>is ſufficient to deſtroy the mind, as
        well <lb/>as the body, of any human being. The <lb/>body may be cured by medicine and diet,
        <lb/>but a diſtempered mind requires ſome other <lb/>conſolations beſides thoſe which are
        derived <lb/>from an apothecary's ſhop. Boluſes, and <lb/>pills, and draughts, &amp;c. will
        heal the wound <lb/>which want of diſcernment and ſkill has <lb/>opened;—it requires ſome
        additional aſ- <lb/>ſiſtance to cure ſevere nervous diſeaſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> examination of Dr. Adington be- <lb/>fore the Privy Council,
        concerning the <lb/>ſtate of our moſt worthy and amiable mo- <lb/>narch's health, is now
        before the public, <pb xml:id="page_57" n="38"/>
        <lb/>and I ſhall not therefore heſitate to ſpeak <lb/>my ſentiments upon the occaſion. As I
        <lb/>have not a doubt but that his Majeſty has <lb/>been treated injudiciouſly, from the
        begin- <lb/>ning of his complaint to the preſent time; <lb/>and it will be a duty incumbent
        upon his <lb/>phyſicians to ſtate at full length the condi- <lb/>tion they found him in when
        they were <lb/>conſulted firſt of all, and to publiſh a jour- <lb/>nal of their proceedings.
        It is full time <lb/>that the whole of this diſmal ſtory ſhould <lb/>be held out to public
        notice. The public <lb/>have a right to be acquainted with the <lb/>whole myſtery of their
        proceedings. Their <lb/>reputations as phyſicians ought either to <lb/>ſtand or fall by
        their method of treating <lb/>the King in his late and preſent ſtate of <lb/>health. It is
        to be preſumed that they <lb/>can write, and defend, by their learning <lb/>and ingenuity,
        their practice. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_58" n="39"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Dr. Adington</hi>, it appears, makes a <lb/>diſtinction in what the
        vulgar call inſanity. <lb/>He confidently aſſerts, that it is an <hi rend="italic">heredi-
          <lb/>tary diſeaſe.</hi> I beg leave to enter the liſt <lb/>as an advocate for the contrary
        doctrine. <lb/>And I contend, that this diſeaſe is no more <lb/>hereditary than a common
        fever, or the <lb/>ſmall-pox, but that it is brought on by <lb/>the common cauſes of all
        other diſeaſes. <lb/>In my Inquiry into the State of Medicine, <lb/>I have endeavoured to
        ſhew, that phyſici- <lb/>ans are too often the unthinking copyiſts of <lb/>each other. No
        man is allowed to think <lb/>for himſelf; and if he does, he is hooted at <lb/>as a common
        diſturber. Therefore, what- <lb/>ever Dr. Boerhaave, or Dr. Cullen ſay, is a <lb/>law with
        their diſciples. </p>
      <q rend="diple">
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><q rend="quotes">As man</q>, ſays the immortal Lord <lb/>Bacon, "is but the ſervant
          and interpre- <lb/>ter of nature, he can work and under- <pb xml:id="page_59" n="40"/>
          <lb/>ſtand no further than he ſhall, either in <lb/>action or contemplation, obſerve of
          the <lb/>proceedings of nature, to whoſe laws he <lb/>remains ſubject. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As truth is but one ſimple thing, ſo <lb/>likewiſe is the interpretation of nature.
          <lb/>But the ſenſes are fallacious, the mind <lb/>unſtable, and the cauſe preſſing, yet
          the <lb/>buſineſs of interpretation is rather <hi rend="italic">un- <lb/>common</hi> than
            <hi rend="italic">difficult.</hi>
        </p>
        <hi rend="sc">Nov. Organ</hi>. </q>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">These</hi> aphoriſms of this illuſtrious phi- <lb/>loſopher apply to my
        ſubject. For I am <lb/>ready to prove, to the ſatisfaction of man- <lb/>kind, that the
        diſeaſe under which our <lb/>moſt excellent Sovereign labours, is, from <lb/>all accounts
        upon record, nothing elſe than <lb/>a common nervovs fever. At the ſame time, <lb/>I am
        forward enough to aſſert, and my aſ- <lb/>ſertion ſhall not be deſtitute of proof, if <pb
          xml:id="page_60" n="41"/>
        <lb/>called upon, that it is more uncommon in <lb/>its appearance than difficult to cure.
        And <lb/>I heſitate not to ſay, that I would, at the <lb/>riſque of my life, and every thing
        that is <lb/>dear and valuable to man, undertake to re- <lb/>ſtore him ſoon to the full
        exerciſe of every <lb/>bodily and mental enjoyment, upon a plan <lb/>of diet alone, with
        proper exerciſe, together <lb/>with the management of the paſſions of <lb/>the mind. And
        there is nothing more eaſy <lb/>than to uphold his Majeſty in a ſtate of <lb/>good health,
        when once it is eſtabliſhed. </p>
      <q rend="diple">
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">He</hi> who has not, in the firſt place, and <lb/>above every thing
          elſe, thoroughly ex- <lb/>amined the motions of the human mind, <lb/>and with the utmoſt
          accuracy noted, and <lb/>made a kind of map of the paths of ſci- <lb/>ence, and the <hi
            rend="italic">ſeats of error</hi> therein, will <lb/>find all things under a mask, or,
          as it <pb xml:id="page_61" n="42"/>
          <lb/>were, inchanted; and unleſs he breaks <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">charm,</hi> can
          never interpret it. </p>
        <hi rend="sc">Nov. Organ.</hi>
      </q>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is impoſſible that a private individual <lb/>like myſelf can
        alter, remove, improve, or <lb/>redreſs the prejudices, opinions, and errors <lb/>of men,
        who have the ſanction of mankind <lb/>to tread in the paths of deluſion and error, <lb/>and
        have the inveterate and general preju- <lb/>dices of ages to uphold them in their ca-
        <lb/>reer of deſolation. It may be ſaid of them <lb/>as it was ſaid of Cæſar, <q
          rend="quotes">Cæſar gladium <lb/>cito condidit, nunquam poſuit. </q> Ci- <lb/>cero alſo,
        when he ſpeaks of this great <lb/>man, ſays, <q rend="quotes">Cæſar, ſi ab eo quæreretur,
          <lb/>quid egiſſit in toga, leges reſpondiſſet <lb/>multas et præclaras tuliſſe. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">When</hi> a practice of phyſic deſtructive <lb/>to our natures is pointed
        out by a man <pb xml:id="page_62" n="43"/>
        <lb/>of diſcernment and ſcience, it is natural to <lb/>preſume, that when the ſyſtem of a
        popu- <lb/>lar aſſailant of theſe pernicious doctrines <lb/>becomes general, that the
        opponents of a <lb/>rational ſyſtem of medical knowledge will, <lb/>like Cæſar, ſoon ſheath
        their ſwords, but <lb/>never lay them aſide. Death, one would ſup- <lb/>poſe they conſider,
        as ſome moraliſts do, is <lb/>a cure for all the evils we bring upon our- <lb/>ſelves; and
        that nature is tired of ſuffering <lb/>us to be for ever miſerable. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Fashion</hi>, it muſt be granted, flouriſhes <lb/>too much in human
        affairs; and faſhion <lb/>prevails to an extreme in the healing art. <lb/>If a duke, a lord,
        or any man of faſhion em- <lb/>ploys a phyſician, his tradeſmen muſt ape <lb/>their manners,
        and do the ſame. If a phy- <lb/>ſician, let his ignorance of his profeſſion <lb/>be ever ſo
        great, can afford to keep up the <lb/>formality of an equipage, and ſuitable de- <pb
          xml:id="page_63" n="44"/>
        <lb/>corations, he is ſought after, and feed, <lb/>while men of the greateſt abilities and
        <lb/>learning are ſuffered to walk the ſtreets un- <lb/>heededly. And if a title is
        conferred upon <lb/>them, they arrive at the ſummit of the hill, <lb/>from whence they can
        ſurvey the folly and <lb/>vanity of mankind. They are then in a <lb/>too elevated ſituation
        to be oppoſed or <lb/>queſtioned by itinerant phyſicians. They <lb/>arrive at the <hi
          rend="italic">ne plus ultra,</hi> and muſt be <lb/>obeyed; and can, with the language of a
        <lb/>dictator, ſay, like Cæſar, <q rend="quotes">Leges reſpon- <lb/>deſſet, multas et
          præclaras tuleſſe. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">We</hi> need not wonder that diſeaſes aſ- <lb/>ſume a variety of
        appearances in different <lb/>perſons, no more than we wonder at ſeeing <lb/>different
        conformations of the body and <lb/>the face in men and women. We might <lb/>as well wonder,
        that in habits of ſevere ex- <lb/>erciſe, that the ſweat appears firſt of all <pb
          xml:id="page_64" n="45"/>
        <lb/>on the forehead. If two young men, who <lb/>live preciſely alike, either in abſtinence,
        or <lb/>in hard drinking, or in debauchery of all <lb/>kinds, entail upon themſelves
        diſeaſes, one <lb/>would ſuppoſe that their reſpective com- <lb/>plaints might reſemble, in
        appearance, <lb/>each other; but it is a hundred to one if <lb/>they do; for the more
        athletic may expe- <lb/>rience ſevere nervous feelings, while the <lb/>more feeble is
        hurried off in a putrid fever. <lb/>The ſame is the caſe with the fair ſex; and <lb/>the
        parallel holds good. The one is pre- <lb/>cipitated into convulſions, when the other <lb/>is
        labouring under a diſeaſe diametrically <lb/>oppoſite in appearance. Appearances of
        <lb/>diſeaſes are nothing, the cauſes of diſeaſes <lb/>are the only requiſites in the hands
        of a <lb/>ſkilful and diſcerning phyſician; and when <lb/>the cauſes are before him, if he
        unites phi- <lb/>loſophy with experience, the cure is near <lb/>at hand in all human
        diſeaſes. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_65" n="46"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> method of reſtoring the King to his <lb/>accuſtomed mental and
        bodily vigour, is, in <lb/>my humble opinion, obvious. He ought <lb/>to be indulged in every
        rational propenſity <lb/>which is agreeable to his mind. His illuſ- <lb/>trious conſort and
        family ought to have ac- <lb/>cess to him at all times. He ſhould never <lb/>be
        contradicted, nor thwarted in any thing <lb/>that he can requeſt, either in food or drink,
        <lb/>unleſs he calls for vegetable food, and what <lb/>are called diluting liquors. He
        ſhould now <lb/>indulge in animal food, and a proper quan- <lb/>tity of wine. Muſic,
        provided it is not <lb/>too loud, will be of great ſervice in the <lb/>re-eſtabliſhment of
        his health. He ſhould <lb/>refrain from all kind of ſtudy and buſi- <lb/>ness, unleſs it is
        of an agreeable nature. <lb/>He ſhould avoid going out into the air, <lb/>until the
        complaint leaves him entirely, <lb/>otherwiſe the ſmalleſt chillineſs in the air <pb
          xml:id="page_66" n="47"/>
        <lb/>will convey it into the head. <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* The
          evidence of Sir George Baker, before a Committee <lb/>of the Houſe of Lords, is a compleat
          illuſtration of the prin- <lb/>ciples and importance of the late Dr. Brown's doctrines in
          fe- <lb/>vers, and all other nervous diſeaſes, the cauſes of which conſiſt <lb/>in
          univerſal relaxation. Phyſicians have been too negligent in <lb/>obſerving the effects of
          cold applied to the human body in a <lb/>ſtate of debility; and there is not an evil of
          greater magnitude. <lb/>Marſh Miaſmata, as phyſicians call it, is nothing but cold and
          <lb/>moiſture applied to relaxed habits. But neither the eſſluvia <lb/>ariſing from putrid
          bodies, nor from bales of goods impreg- <lb/>nated with the plague, nor the effects of the
          Grotto Del Cane, <lb/>are by any means more dangerous, than the effects which <lb/>are
          produced by cold upon relaxed habits. I have experienced, <lb/>in my own perſon,
          repeatedly, the effects of what is called <lb/>contagion; and I have alſo experienced, to
          a great degree, the <lb/>effects of cold applied to the body in a relaxed ſtate. But,
          <lb/>if I had my choice in a ſtate of debility, I would rather chuſe <lb/>to be expoſed to
          the opening of goods from the Levant, im- <lb/>pregnated with the contagion of the plague,
          than be expoſed to <lb/>moiſture and cold in the ſame ſituation. <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>His Majeſty's phyſician ſays, that his royal patient had wet- <lb/>ted his feet at
            Windſor, and that he went to St. James's with- <lb/>out changing his ſtockings. This
            circumſtance alone, in the <lb/>King's ſtate of health, was ſufficient to produce
            alarming con- <lb/>ſequences, admitting that no eruption took place, which, from
            <lb/>the evidence of this phyſician, was the caſe at the time. The <lb/>eruption which
            took place upon the body, was of peculiar uti- <lb/>lity in tending to remove the
            diſeaſe. A warm room would <lb/>have been a proper preſcription at this time. And I am
            not <lb/>averſe to the belief, that palſies, apoplexies, and ſudden death, <lb/>are
            often the conſequences of going out into the air when the <lb/>mind is unuſually
            melancholy, and the body is greatly relaxed. </p>
        </note> His body <lb/>ought therefore to be kept very warm <lb/>with flannel cloaths. Soups
        are very pro- <lb/>per. The ſoups he takes ought to be made <lb/>very rich of animal food,
        but much condi- <pb xml:id="page_67" n="48"/>
        <lb/>mentis not neceſſary in theſe preparations. <lb/>His requeſts ought to be implicitly
        ob- <lb/>ſerved. <q rend="diple quotes">"<hi rend="sc">For</hi> the requeſts of kings",
          <lb/>ſays Grotius, "have the ſame power as <lb/>commands; and a denial, how juſt ſo-
          <lb/>ever, ſhall be by them as ill digeſted as <lb/>an injury. </q> It was therefore a
        moſt <lb/>cruel act in thoſe who attended his Majeſty, <lb/>when he ſaw through his window
        ſome of <lb/>the princeſſes walk in the garden, to de- <lb/>prive him of the pleaſure and
        ſatisfaction <lb/>of ſpeaking to his beloved children. I have <lb/>often, in this work,
        endeavoured to impreſs <lb/>upon the minds of my readers, the extreme <lb/>cruelty of
        depriving of mankind of their <lb/>uſual comforts and conſolations in ſome <pb
          xml:id="page_68" n="49"/>
        <lb/>nervous complaints. And what pleaſure <lb/>in nature is there equal to the ſeeing, even
        <lb/>in a ſtate of health, much more in a ſtate <lb/>of diſeaſe, of thoſe we are by nature,
        as <lb/>well as by habits of mutual love and in- <lb/>tercourſe, to cheriſh and to admire. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Another</hi> ſolacement to the mind of <lb/>the King, is to be derived
        from reading to <lb/>him, at proper ſeaſons, thoſe books which <lb/>uſed to afford him
        pleaſure when he was <lb/>in a ſtate of health. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Dr. Willis</hi> appears, from his exami- <lb/>nation before the Houſe of
        Commons, to <lb/>be a very ſenſible and diſcerning phyſician, <lb/>and ſpeaks of the cauſes
        which produce his <lb/>Majeſty's illneſs with perfect diſtinctneſs; <lb/>ſuch as weighty
        buſineſs, ſevere exerciſe, <lb/>extreme abſtemiouſneſs, little reſt, &amp;c. <lb/>Theſe
        cauſes, of themſelves, are ſufficient <pb xml:id="page_69" n="50"/>
        <lb/>to produce a nervous fever, without the <lb/>co-operation of other powers, tending to
        <lb/>produce the ſame effect; ſuch as bleeding, <lb/>bliſtering, the debilitating operation
        of <lb/>James's powders, and other medical pre- <lb/>ſcriptions of the ſame nature. It
        appears, <lb/>however, that the medicines given to his <lb/>Majeſty ſince Dr. Willis has
        been called in, <lb/>have been attended with beneficial conſe- <lb/>quences: And I am
        naturally led to ſup- <lb/>poſe, from the advantages which have <lb/>hitherto reſulted from
        them, that they <lb/>muſt have partaken of opium, which, if <lb/>adminiſtered with judgment
        and caution, <lb/>and ſupported in their efficacy by invigo- <lb/>rating food, and proper
        vinous cordials, <lb/>are qualified to produce the moſt happy <lb/>conſequences. The very
        reverſe is the <lb/>caſe with this medicine when injudiciouſly <lb/>made uſe of, which very
        often happens. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_70" n="51"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">beg</hi> leave to ſubmit one more thought <lb/>upon this ſubject. It
        appears that his <lb/>Majeſty had experienced conſiderable relief, <lb/>during the progreſs
        of his illneſs, in uſing <lb/>the warm bath; and I can venture to ſpeak <lb/>with certainty,
        that the effects of the warm <lb/>bath are prodigiouſly increaſed, by being <lb/>impregnated
        with the Peruvian bark, and <lb/>aromatic herbs of all ſorts. The only in- <lb/>dication of
        cure is therefore to invigorate, <lb/>by all poſſible means, the body, and to af- <lb/>ford
        every conſolation to the mind. This <lb/>plan ought to be ſtudied with much aſſi- <lb/>duity
        by thoſe who attend his Majeſty. <lb/>For whatever produces an encreaſe of bo- <lb/>dily
        relaxation, will, to a certainty, bring <lb/>on a renewal of his diſeaſe. </p>
      <trailer rend="align-center">
        <lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
