<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Hamilton: Practical hints on opium considered as a poison</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Robert Hamilton</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Practical hints on opium considered as a poison</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T112342</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T112342"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Ipswich</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Ipswich: printed and sold by G. Jermyn, in the Butter-Market,
                  M,DCC,XC.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1790</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="2"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="46"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3306723587</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K089963.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: medicine"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front> </front>
    <body>
      <div>
      <pb xml:id="page_3"/>
      <head rend="italic dc(2) align-center">
        <lb/>Practical Hints, &amp;c. </head>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> melancholly accident having, within <lb/>theſe few days, taken
        place in this neigh- <lb/>bourhood, from a quantity of Opium given <lb/>to a young boy, by
        miſtake for a different <lb/>medicine, which ſoon proved fatal, gave <lb/>riſe to the
        following remarks. The Author <lb/>hopes the public will receive them with <lb/>candour,
        ſince they are laid before them to <lb/>guard them in future, and prevent them from
        <lb/>keeping in their houſes, as family medicines, <lb/>drugs of violent operation,
        undiſtinguiſhed <lb/>by proper labels from more innocent ſub- <pb xml:id="page_4" n="4"/>
        <lb/>ſtances of the Materia Medica: or ſhould <lb/>the like again take place, that they may
        <lb/>from theſe hints, be the better prepared to <lb/>put in force the means of cure, he
        ſubmits <lb/>to their conſideration, which on many ſuch <lb/>occaſions, (for too many ſuch
        are on record) <lb/>have been found effectual when they were had <lb/>early recourſe to, and
        ſtrenuouſly applied. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> drug of high uſe, and deſerved eſ- <lb/>timation in Medicine,
        like many others of <lb/>the virulent Vegetable Poiſons, becomes, <lb/>when incautiouſly
        exhibited by thoſe leſs <lb/>acquainted with its powers, and when given <lb/>thro' miſtake,
        ſpeedily deſtructive; chang- <lb/>ing the regular motions of the living body <lb/>into
        irregular and violent; inducing ſtupe- <lb/>faction; convulſions; appoplexy &amp;c. ſoon to
        <lb/>be followed by a total deprivation of life. <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)"
          >* Eos, qui Opium copioſius acceperunt, ſequitur in <lb/>ſomnum gravem collapſio, mentis
          ſopor, et ſenſus ab- <lb/>lienatio cum frigiditate et pruritu vehementi, ita ut hom-
          <lb/>inem exitet. Odor opii per totum corpus effertur, et <lb/>exhalat: maxilla laxatur,
          tumeſcunt labra, irruit ſingul- <lb/>tus, diſtorquetur naſus, adeſt pallor, livor unguium,
          <lb/>præcordiorum divulſio, reſpiratio parva, et frigida, et ad <lb/>finem etiam
          convulſio. Auctore Aëtio. </note>
      </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_5" n="5"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Without</hi> entering into a diſſertation <lb/>on the ſubject at large,
        or a detail of the <lb/>various opinions, and hypotheſes that have <lb/>lately, as well as
        heretofore, been advanced <lb/>relative to its mode of operation as a medi- <lb/>cine, this
        being foreign to my preſent pur- <lb/>poſe, let me at once ſuppoſe ſuch a quan- <lb/>tity
        received into the ſtomach, as muſt in <lb/>a ſhort time induce death, ſhould attempts,
        <lb/>(and theſe almoſt inſtantaneouſly) not be <lb/>made to prevent its baneful effects; and
        <lb/>indeed, admitting them made, it muſt be <lb/>confeſſed, (ſo great may the force of the
        <lb/>poiſon be) that its effects may be exerted <lb/>even in a very ſhort time, altogether
        be- <lb/>yond the poſſibility of obviating, notwith- <pb xml:id="page_6" n="6"/>
        <lb/>ſtanding the moſt diligent application of <lb/>the moſt rational means. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> reflection, however, ſhould not <lb/>ſlacken our endeavours or
        damp our ardour, <lb/>but ought rather to ſtimulate us to a trial <lb/>of all the methods
        that have been known <lb/>to ſucceed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> firſt thing then to which we are to <lb/>turn our attention, is
        the uſe of emetics: and <lb/>let one be thrown down the moſt ſpeedy <lb/>in its
        operation.—Powders of Ipecacuanha, <lb/>Tartariſed Antimony, Vinegar of Squills, <lb/>or,
        perhaps what may ſtill be more quick in <lb/>exciting the action of the ſtomach, White
        <lb/>Vitriol.—The contents of the ſtomach, <lb/>ſuppoſe the operation ſucceeds, ſhould be
        <lb/>examined to find whether any of the Opium <lb/>has been evacuated; this will be eaſily
        diſ- <lb/>covered by its ſmell, and will afford en- <pb xml:id="page_7" n="7"/>
        <lb/>couragement to purſue our firſt advantage, <lb/>by continuing the vomiting till this
        organ <lb/>be compleatly evacuated. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> doſes uſed muſt be in proportion to <lb/>the exigencies of the
        caſe, to the diminiſhed <lb/>energy, and ſenſibility of the nervous ſyſtem <lb/>in general,
        and the ſtomach in particular. <lb/>If the Opium has begun to exert its effects, <lb/>the
        more will be neceſſary; and as there is <lb/>no time to looſe, and inevitable danger, per-
        <lb/>haps death, awaiting, we muſt hazard the <lb/>larger quantities in proportion to the
        ac- <lb/>cuſtomed doſes, and perſiſt in their uſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To prevent ſtupefaction as far as in our <lb/>power, and the conſequent train of bad
        <lb/>ſymptoms, ſtrong agitation may be uſed, <lb/>ſuch as walking, running, ſhaking, &amp;c.
        <lb/>this has been ſtrenuouſly recommended <lb/>by ſeveral Authors. In one caſe, as I am <pb
          xml:id="page_8" n="8"/>
        <lb/>lately informed by a Medical Gentleman in <lb/>this county, whoſe ſiſter was the
        ſubject of <lb/>the trial, it appears to have had no ſmall <lb/>ſhare in the cure. The
        gentleman when <lb/>a child about ſix years of age, having ob- <lb/>ſerved his mother take
        ſomething from a <lb/>bottle in her cloſet, went afterwards and <lb/>brought it to his
        ſiſter, a child about a year <lb/>younger than himſelf, perſuading her to take <lb/>of it,
        which he intended to do alſo, but his <lb/>ſiſter after taking ſome complained it was
        <lb/>bad taſted, on which he took none; ſhe <lb/>ſoon became affected, the family were a-
        <lb/>larmed, and their Apothecary was ſent for. <lb/>Among other things he ordered the child
        <lb/>to be walked about though in a ſtate of <lb/>ſtupefaction, being held up between two
        <lb/>ſervants, and kept in conſtant motion for <lb/>ſeveral hours. She recovered with
        difficul- <lb/>ty <figure>
          <figDesc>sentence crossed by author </figDesc>
        </figure>
      </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_9" n="9"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To theſe ſhould be added Stimulants of <lb/>all kinds, as Volatile Salts to the noſe,
        <lb/>Bliſters to the ſkin, &amp;c. If epiſpaſtics are <lb/>applied, they ſhould be placed on
        the moſt <lb/>ſenſible parts, or joints, as the ancles, arms, <lb/>inſide of the legs, and
        ſoles of the feet, and <lb/>wherever the body is thinneſt of fleſh, and <lb/>the nervous
        fibrillæ moſt numerous. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> may be objected to the uſe of bliſters, <lb/>that they will act
        too ſlowly in a caſe of <lb/>this nature, where expedition is ſo requiſite. <lb/>But without
        attempting formally to remove <lb/>this objection, which we think might be <lb/>eaſily done,
        as it is not their evacuant, but <lb/>their ſtimulant effects for which we con- <lb/>ſider
        them expedient, we ſhall only ſay, <lb/>that their application even in that caſe, <lb/>can
        do no harm by interrupting other <lb/>means; and on this ground alone, I would <lb/>not have
        them omitted. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_10" n="10"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">If</hi> we can rouſe the mind ſo far that it <lb/>will feel pain, ſo far
        one point is thereby <lb/>gained, which adds ſomewhat to our hopes <lb/>of ſucceſs, and
        ſhould quicken our exertions. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I know not how far Electricity might in <lb/>this ſenſe be advantageous. As it is
        acknow- <lb/>ledged, however, one of the moſt powerful, <lb/>though tranſient ſtimulants,
        and as it may be <lb/>applied to the human body, even for a <lb/>length of time, and
        frequency with the <lb/>utmoſt ſafety, we can run no great hazard <lb/>in giving it a trial,
        eſpecially as machines <lb/>for its commodious application are now in <lb/>almoſt every
        body's poſſeſſion. The poiſon <lb/>being of the higheſt ſedative nature, the <lb/>ſtrongeſt
        ſtimulants would ſeem obviouſly <lb/>indicated as its antidote. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> the caſes of drowned perſons, and <lb/>thoſe ſuffocated by the
        fumes of charcoal <pb xml:id="page_11" n="11"/>
        <lb/>&amp;c. the analogy thus far holds good, that <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">this</hi> as in
          <hi rend="italic">thoſe</hi> there is a ſuſpenſion of the <lb/>functions from a
        deprivation of ſenſibility in <lb/>the ſyſtem. In <hi rend="italic">thoſe</hi> Electricity
        is ſtrongly <lb/>recommended. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> writer of theſe hints will not enter <lb/>here into that part of
        the Pathology which <lb/>ſuppoſes the operation of the Opium to be <lb/>by augmenting, or
        rarefying the volume of <lb/>the blood in the ſanguiferous ſyſtem in <lb/>general, and the
        head in particular, where- <lb/>by a turgeſcence, and over-diſtention of <lb/>the Veſſels of
        this organ are ſaid to be parti- <lb/>cuarly preſent, and from which the ſymp- <lb/>toms of
        apoplexy are argued to ariſe. Of <lb/>this opinion among others was the celebra- <lb/>ted
        Mead. He affirms that it enflames the <lb/>Stomach, and rarefies the blood to ſuch a
        <lb/>degree, that the Veſſels cannot again reco- <pb xml:id="page_12" n="12"/>
        <lb/>ver their tone, whereupon apoplectic ſymp- <lb/>toms, &amp;c. will enſue; to prove
        which he <lb/>relates an experiment which he made with <lb/>it on a Dog. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Perhaps</hi> all ſtimulants, (and it appears <lb/>to me, by the bye, that
        all ſubſtances taken <lb/>into the ſtomach exert firſt a ſtimulant <lb/>power, whatever
        their after action may be,) <lb/>have the effect leſs or more of ſending <lb/>a greater
        quantity of blood to the head, <lb/>at leaſt quickening the circulation by which <lb/>the
        face becomes fluſhed; but ſurely ſtimu- <lb/>lants, for this reaſon alone, are not here to
        be <lb/>omitted. The ſtimulant power of the Opium <lb/>ſeems tranſitory, the ſedative ſoon
        follows. <lb/>And now, if we can rouſe the powers of the <lb/>heart to exert their wonted
        action, and <lb/>renew the motion of the blood flowing at <lb/>preſent languidly, we need
        the leſs dread <lb/>this ſuppoſed plethora, as the conſequence <pb xml:id="page_13" n="13"/>
        <lb/>muſt be a more equitable circulation, and <lb/>diſtribution of the blood. I know no
        proof, <lb/>however, that this fluid is augmenting in its <lb/>volume, but that it is in a
        ſtate almoſt of <lb/>ſtagnation is evident. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr. Alſton, in the preſence, and with the <lb/>aſſiſtance of Mr. Fullarton, a gentleman
        <lb/>skilled in microſcopical obſervations, in <lb/>Auguſt 1733, conveyed into the ſtomach
        <lb/>of a frog ſome Opium diſſolved in water, <lb/>and after putting it into a glaſs
        cylinder, they <lb/>adapted the microſcope to the membrane <lb/>between the toes, in ſuch a
        manner, that <lb/>they had a diſtinct view of the circulation <lb/>of the blood in this
        part. The Dr. had <lb/>found before that Opium killed theſe ani- <lb/>mals, and his deſign
        now was to obſerve <lb/>its effects on the circulation; no change, <lb/>however, took place
        either in the colour or <pb xml:id="page_14" n="14"/>
        <lb/>conſiſtence of the blood; but the diminu- <lb/>tion of its velocity was extremely
        evident, <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">for it did not move half ſo ſwiftly as it <lb/>uſed to do in theſe
          creatures. </q> This <lb/>obſervation was repeatedly made; and as the <lb/>effects of the
        Opium went off, the blood <lb/>became gradually quicker in its motion. <lb/>When the frog
        had entirely recovered its <lb/>vigour, they forced more Opium into its <lb/>ſtomach, and
        obſerving again, ſaw again the <lb/>ſame diminution of the blood's velocity. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">From</hi> Mr. Ramſay's experiment (made <lb/>in April 1755) on a dog, we
        have a fur- <lb/>ther proof of the pulſe becoming ſlower. <lb/>The heart of this animal in
        its natural ſtate <lb/>beat <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Vid. Med. Eſs.
        </note> 150 times in a minute. Four minutes <lb/>after the injection of the Opium into the
        <lb/>cavity of the abdomen, he fell down ſenſe- <lb/>less. Mr. R. opened the thorax, which
        <lb/>ſeemed to give the Dog no pain, and he felt <pb xml:id="page_15" n="15"/>
        <lb/>plainly the motion of the heart thro' the <lb/>pleura. It beat now only 76 times in a
        <lb/>minute, and became ſlower. Immediately <lb/>after counting the pulſe, he cut the ribs
        on <lb/>each ſide of the ſternum in the common <lb/>way, and laid them back, by which the
        <lb/>heart was brought into view. It appeared <lb/>quite turgid. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">From</hi> Dr. Whytt's experiments, we <lb/>have likewiſe ample proof of
        the leſſened <lb/>motion of the blood, after the application <lb/>of Opium, <q rend="quotes"
          >the veins,</q> he ſays, "after <lb/>a large doſe of Opium eſpecially thoſe of <lb/>the
        brain become much ſwelled, whence it <lb/>has been thought, that Opium produces its e
        <lb/>ffects in the bodies of animals partly at <lb/>leaſt, by rarefying the blood, and com-
        <lb/>preſſing the brain; but this diſtention of <lb/>the veins ſeems to be no more than a
        con- <lb/>ſequence of a very ſlow motion of the blood <pb xml:id="page_16" n="16"/>
        <lb/>thro' the heart, on account of the inſenſi- <lb/>bility with which this organ is
        affected." <lb/>The Author tells us that in frogs, into <lb/>whoſe ſtomach, and inteſtines
        he had in- <lb/>jected Opium, he not only found the heart's <lb/>auricle, but the great
        viens leading to it <lb/>much diſtended with blood. From all this <lb/>it muſt follow, that
        the heart and arterial <lb/>ſyſtem being ſo reduced in their irritability <lb/>cannot propel
        the blood with ſufficient <lb/>force thro' the larger veſſels near, much leſs <lb/>thro' the
        extreme ones, and leſs ſtill thro' the <lb/>Veins. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr. Leigh gave two grs. of the reſin of <lb/>Opium to a healthy man, of 30 years of
        <lb/>age, his pulſe was then at 60 ſtrokes in a <lb/>minute, half an hour after it roſe to
        72; <lb/>this proves what we have already hinted, <lb/>that the firſt operation of this, as
        well as <lb/>other drugs, is that of a ſtimulus; but be- <pb xml:id="page_17" n="17"/>
        <lb/>hold! in a ſhort time it fell down to 55, <lb/>was full and ſtrong; and now head-ach,
        <lb/>vertigo, and drowſineſs ſucceeded. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> ſame gentleman gave three grs. of <lb/>the gummy part of Opium
        to a young <lb/>woman. In ten minutes her pulſe fell 13 <lb/>ſtrokes; became alſo full and
        ſtrong. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To a third perſon alſo, he gave Opium, <lb/>pulſe roſe ſix ſtrokes in a minute, but in
        a <lb/>quarter of an hour it fell 15, and became <lb/>extremely full. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">On</hi> the ſuppoſition, however, of rare- <lb/>faction of this fluid, as
        well as inflam- <lb/>mation, which has been contended was <lb/>produced. Geoffroy, and
        others of the <lb/>antient <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Dr. Tiſſot is among
          the number who adviſe bleeding, <lb/>from the uſe of Opium, in a quantity too great for
          health, <lb/>in my opinion, without a juſt foundation; he ſays the <lb/>patient is to be
          treated as if he had a ſanguine apoplexy. </note> phyſicians recommended, and <pb
          xml:id="page_18" n="18"/>
        <lb/>practiſed, V. S. without duly conſidering, <lb/>we apprehend, that it is a moſt
        powerfully <lb/>debilitating means, leſſening the vigour of <lb/>thoſe functions which are
        already become <lb/>too debile; and without reflecting, that as <lb/>the ſtomach is the
        place of action, the <lb/>part firſt affected, relief can only be ra- <lb/>tionally ſought
        for by applications chiefly <lb/>to this organ. Should evacuations, how- <lb/>ever, by blood
        letting be at all practiſed, <lb/>ſcarifications on the head, or opening the <lb/>jugular
        veins, or temporal artery would <lb/>appear preferable to general V. Section. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">From</hi> an experiment of the celebrated <lb/>Dr. Mead on a dog, which
        he killed by <lb/>Opium, this practice would ſeem to re- <lb/>ceive ſome countenance, for on
        diſſection <lb/>he found the blood veſſels of the brain very <lb/>full, and took a large
        grume of concreted <lb/>blood from the upper part of it, as he cut <pb xml:id="page_19"
          n="19"/>
        <lb/>into the ſinus longitudinalis.—No extra- <lb/>vaſated ſerum was found either in the
        ven- <lb/>tricles, or any of the membranes. The <lb/>ſtomach was wonderfully diſtended,
        though <lb/>empty of every thing but ſome water and <lb/>Opium; parcels of frothy mucus ſwam
        in <lb/>it, and its inſide was as clean as if ſcraped <lb/>and waſhed from all the ſlime of
        the glands; <lb/>ſome redneſs was diſcovered here and there, <lb/>as if in the beginning of
        an inflammation; <lb/>the pylorus was found contracted. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> even under theſe circumſtances, I <lb/>ſhould be inclined to
        defer opening theſe <lb/>veſſels till ſymptoms of apoplexy had com- <lb/>menced, and other
        means, better adapted to <lb/>the cure, had been purſued ineffectually. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr. Alſton <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* The Doctor denies the
          rarefaction of the fluids in <lb/>theſe caſes. </note> makes a curious obſerva- <lb/>tion,
        which may be mentioned here; <pb xml:id="page_20" n="20"/>
        <lb/>while he viewed the ſlow motion in the <lb/>foot of the frog, as above related, he took
        <lb/>notice that the frequency of the pulſe was <lb/>as uſual, but the heart was weak, and
        had <lb/>not power to propel the fluid with its <lb/>wonted force to the extremities. "One
          <lb/>thing,<q rend="quotes"> ſays he, </q>was obſervable all <lb/>along, that
        notwithſtanding the diminiſhed <lb/>velocity of the blood, there was no ſen- <lb/>ſible
        dimunition in the frequency of the <lb/>pulſe; yet, when there was no circulation, <lb/>or
        progreſſive motion of the blood, in this <lb/>part, (the foot) the pulſe was viſible by
        <lb/>an undulatory motion; that is, the blood <lb/>returned as far back at every <hi
          rend="italic">diaſtole</hi> of the <lb/>heart, as it was protruded by the preceding
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſyſtole;</hi> this continued till the frog was <lb/>quite dead.<q
          rend="quotes">—He opened it, and </q>found <lb/>nothing in its ſtomach but a clear mucus,
        <lb/>like a jelly, a little coloured with the <lb/>Opium. Every thing elſe ſeemed perfectly
        <lb/>natural: this experiment we often re- <pb xml:id="page_21" n="21"/>
        <lb/>peated.<q rend="quotes"> He adds, </q>and it had always <lb/>the ſame appearance and
        event." </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">After</hi> the uſe of the emetics, the next <lb/>practice, that I would
        recommend, is that <lb/>of cathartics, they ſeem to hold the ſecond <lb/>place; nay, both
        emetics and cathartics <lb/>may be conveniently exhibited at the ſame <lb/>time. Theſe, for
        the ſame reaſons we gave <lb/>in the uſe of emetics, ſhould be powerful, <lb/>and of a
        ſufficiently ſtimulating nature. <lb/>Aloetics, with others, from the tribe of re-
        <lb/>ſinous purges have been recommended; the <lb/>powder of jalap, ſcammony, and calomel,
        <lb/>are all active; yet vinegar of ſquills may <lb/>be perhaps conveniently added to the
        <lb/>number; and in ſome reſpects, at leaſt, it <lb/>may be found preferable, as it both
        vomits <lb/>and purges, if adminiſtered to any extent. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Neutral</hi> ſalts, and eſpecially Glau- <lb/>ber's, have been likewiſe
        recommended:— <pb xml:id="page_22" n="22"/>
        <lb/>while we uſe theſe we are not to omit gliſ- <lb/>ters: and theſe may be made of ſalt
        and <lb/>water, or ſtrong brine, to which may be <lb/>added purgative ingredients, as may
        beſt <lb/>ſute the preſcriber's intention: they ſhould <lb/>be thrown up as warm as
        convenient. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. Ramſay injected into the inteſtinum <lb/>rectum of a ſmall dog, a ſolution of two
        <lb/>ſcruples of Opium, in an ounce of water, <lb/>blood warm, to which he added a drachm
        <lb/>of T. Opii. in about a minute his hind <lb/>legs became convulſed, and in a few mi-
        <lb/>mutes more their ſenſibility was ſo de- <lb/>ſtroyed, that when pinced, they ſeemed in-
        <lb/>ſenſible to pain; in ten minutes more he <lb/>became quite ſtupid; fell into a <hi
          rend="italic">"profound <lb/>ſleep,"</hi> and was convulſed. On obſerving <lb/>this, a
        ſtrong ſolution of ſea ſalt, in water, <lb/>was injected into his guts; this purged <lb/>him
        ſeverely, and occaſioned a prolopſus <pb xml:id="page_23" n="23"/>
        <lb/>ani. Soon after he awoke from his ſleep, <lb/>and gradually recovered the uſe of his
        hind <lb/>legs. In a few hours he ſeemed well in <lb/>every reſpect, but could take no food
        for <lb/>ſome time. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Before</hi> the enema be injected, I would <lb/>recommend the uſe of a
        ſuppoſitory, this <lb/>may be prepared in an inſtant, with ſome <lb/>paper twiſted up, of a
        proper thickneſs, <lb/>well covered with oil or hogs lard, and <lb/>introduced per anum. It
        will at once <lb/>bring away the fæces that are hardened, <lb/>and filling up that part, and
        thus give <lb/>room for the enema to penetrate farther <lb/>into the inteſtine. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr. Dobſon's patient, at Liverpool, was <lb/>cured by the uſe of Glauber's ſalts and
        <lb/>emetics. He had ſwallowed, in the ſpace <lb/>of 24 hours, 26 grains of ſolid Opium, <pb
          xml:id="page_24" n="24"/>
        <lb/>in the ſhop compoſition, called pil. ſapo- <lb/>nac. By miſtake for pil. aloetic. an
        ounce. <lb/>The Doctor juſtly concluded, that in all <lb/>probability, this would have
        proved fatal, <lb/>but for the following favourable circum- <lb/>ſtances: Firſt, That the
        Opium was in a <lb/>ſolid form: Secondly, That a ſtrong eme- <lb/>tic was ordered, and
        repeated till it pro- <lb/>duced the deſired effects: And Thirdly, <lb/>That a free
        diſcharge by ſtool was ob- <lb/>tained, by perſiſting in the uſe of Glau- <lb/>ber's ſalts.
        He obſerves what is worthy of <lb/>remark, that the neutral ſalts gave relief <lb/>even
        before they had occaſioned any eva- <lb/>cuation. The ſalts were continued, at <lb/>proper
        intervals, for three days after. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Having</hi> ſtrengthened our hopes, by <lb/>evacuations, per os &amp;
        anum, the next to be <lb/>thought of is that by the perſpirable pores. <lb/>To aſſiſt our
        endeavours here, the pa- <pb xml:id="page_25" n="25"/>
        <lb/>tient ſhould be immerſed in warm water, <lb/>and I ſhould prefer that of a ſtimulant to
        <lb/>that of a relaxing heat; or, the water <lb/>ſhould be ſomewhat above the tepid tem-
        <lb/>perature moſt commonly uſed, when the <lb/>warm bath is applied. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">recommend</hi> this, though at the ſame <lb/>time I am well aware, that
        too great a <lb/>degree of heat is unfavourable to perſpi- <lb/>ration; but we are to keep
        in view the <lb/>want of due ſenſibility; and that ſince, <lb/>for this reaſon, we were
        obliged to aug- <lb/>ment the doſes of emetics and purgatives, <lb/>ſo muſt we now make uſe
        of a higher de- <lb/>gree of heat to produce the ſame effect. <lb/>Thoſe who contend for a
        rarefaction of the <lb/>blood, and the preſence of ſanguinous <lb/>apoplexy, will, no doubt,
        think this part <lb/>of our practice unfavourable to the end we <lb/>have in view, the
        recovery of the patient, <pb xml:id="page_26" n="26"/>
        <lb/>as it will have a tendency to encreaſe the <lb/>rarefaction of the ſanguiferous ſyſtem,
        and <lb/>the fluids in general: but they will remem- <lb/>ber that we thought it more than
        probable, <lb/>ſuch a ſtate of the fluids did not exiſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To aſſiſt us in opening the perſpirable <lb/>pores, diluents and diaphoretics muſt be
        <lb/>conjoined; for without a due proportion <lb/>of diluents we cannot ſo eaſily force a
        <lb/>ſweat. The principle on which I go, by <lb/>adviſing ſweating, is from a ſuppoſition
        <lb/>that the lymphatic ſyſtem has abſorbed part <lb/>of the Opium, and that it is by this
        <lb/>means mixed with the fluids in the ge- <lb/>neral habit. And as our chief view is to
        <lb/>evacuate it as compleatly as poſſible, that <lb/>part of it which has been abſorbed,
        and <lb/>which creates a great ſhare of the ſymp- <lb/>toms, cannot be evacuated by means
        more <lb/>effectual than by ſudorifics. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_27" n="27"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">need</hi> not quote the experiments of <lb/>profeſſor Monro on this
        part of my ſubject. <lb/>He is clear that it is taken up by this ſyſtem <lb/>of veſſels,
        becauſe, among other proofs, <lb/>both urine and ſweat ſmell of it. The <lb/>heart is a
        muſcle very irritable. When <lb/>the Opium is abſorbed, the nerves of its <lb/>inner ſurface
        muſt be affected, becauſe it <lb/>is then applied immediately to them, as <lb/>well as to
        the nerves of the inſide of the <lb/>arteries; and through this medium, as <lb/>well as
        through the nerves of the ſtomach, <lb/>it muſt induce its peculiar ſymptoms. <lb/>The
        diaphoretics, that have been gene- <lb/>rally uſed, were of the warm kind, ſuch <lb/>as
        confect. aromatic. miſtur. camphe- <lb/>rat. &amp;c.— </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A <hi rend="sc">man</hi> who ſwallowed an ounce of L. <lb/>Laud. within the ſpace of an
        hour, in <lb/>ſmall punch, recovered by vomits, purg- <pb xml:id="page_28" n="28"/>
        <lb/>ing, bliſters, and ſweating. And a lady, <lb/>eighteen years of age, who took the ſame
        <lb/>quantity, was cured by much the ſame means. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A <hi rend="sc">child</hi>, of eighteen months old, la- <lb/>bouring under the hooping
        cough, had a <lb/>doſe of elix. paregor. given, with the in- <lb/>tention of moderating the
        cough; the quan- <lb/>tity uncertain. It was adminiſtered at <lb/>night, and the ſymptoms
        were not no- <lb/>ticed till next morning, when deep ſleep <lb/>and convulſions were
        obſerved: recovery <lb/>was here brought about by ſtrong cor- <lb/>dials. The quantity of
        the elix. appears <lb/>not to have been ſo large as to induce <lb/>thoſe ſymptoms that end
        in ſpeedy death. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr. Clark's patient, who in July 1766, <lb/>ſwallowed a drachm of ſolid Opium, was
        <lb/>alſo cured by vomits, purges, gliſters, <lb/>and ſweating. The patient was an adult;
          <pb xml:id="page_29" n="29"/>
        <lb/>he took half a drachm, and repeated the <lb/>doſe at a ſhort interval; in the ſpace of
        <lb/>20 minutes it began to operate. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">There</hi> is reaſon, I preſume, to ſuppoſe <lb/>that ſudorifics, ſome
        ſudorifics, at leaſt, <lb/>blunt the action of Opium. It is well <lb/>known, that when
        emetics, neutral ſalts, <lb/>and Opium are united, a much larger doſe <lb/>of the Opium may
        be adminiſtered with <lb/>ſafety and ſucceſs, as a medicine, than <lb/>when given alone; its
        action by this ad- <lb/>dition being modified. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A <hi rend="sc">proof</hi> of this we have in the com- <lb/>poſition, commonly known by
        the name <lb/>of Dover's ſweating powder. This is an <lb/>union of Opium, ipecac: and
        vitriolated <lb/>tartar. To aſſiſt then both in modifying <lb/>the action of the Opium and
        procuring <lb/>ſweat, either ipecac. in powder, or an <pb xml:id="page_30" n="30"/>
        <lb/>antimonial may be employed in warm <lb/>water, to which a ſmall quantitiy of a
        <lb/>neutral ſalt may be added; the Opium, <lb/>being, as we preſume, already in the ſto-
        <lb/>mach, will form a ſtrong ſudorific, and <lb/>thus, part at leaſt of the offending
        matter <lb/>be converted into an antidote to deſtroy its <lb/>own noxious quality, by
        hurrying it <lb/>through the circulating fluids, and expel- <lb/>ling it by the pores of the
        ſkin. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Should</hi> the patient have loſt the power <lb/>of deglution, for this
        has ſometimes hap- <lb/>pened; theſe, and the other medicines we <lb/>have recommended, muſt
        be forced into the <lb/>ſtomach by a ſmall tube. A woman was <lb/>killed, as Dr. Alſton
        relates, by taking a <lb/>quantity of liniment for the hæmorrhoides <lb/>compoſed of Opium
        and Myrrh, by miſtake <lb/>for a purge. When the miſtake was diſ- <lb/>covered, a vomit was
        given, but though <pb xml:id="page_31" n="31"/>
        <lb/>this was not above three quarters of an <lb/>hour after the bolus had been taken, ſhe
        <lb/>was ſo convulſed as to have loſt the <hi rend="italic">power <lb/>of deglution.</hi>
        She died in ſome hours <lb/>after. Pulſe large, full, and not very fre- <lb/>quent. When her
        phyſician firſt ſaw her, <lb/>there appeared a pale livor on her cheek, <lb/>and in other
        reſpects ſhe was like a per- <lb/>ſon drunk. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">There</hi> are few ſurgeons without hol- <lb/>low bougees; provided
        nothing more con- <lb/>venient be at hand, one of theſe may be <lb/>employed to convey the
        medicines down, <lb/>eſpecially for children, where the æſo- <lb/>phagus is ſhorter than in
        the adult. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">If</hi> the tube be long enough to paſs be- <lb/>yond the epgilottis, or
        the paſſage into the <lb/>lungs, it is all that is requiſite; the liquid, <lb/>of courſe,
        muſt drop into the ſtomach; <pb xml:id="page_32" n="32"/>
        <lb/>and this is no great length, as is well <lb/>known to thoſe who have uſed the probang,
        <lb/>in puſhing down, &amp;c. ſubſtances accident- <lb/>ly ſticking in the throat; or who
        will take <lb/>the trouble to examine the diſtance be- <lb/>tween the lower jaw and the top
        of the <lb/>ſternum, where the trachæa and æſophagus <lb/>dip under it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Several</hi> authors have ſpoken highly <lb/>in favour of acids, both
        among the an- <lb/>tients and moderns, for their power of <lb/>modifying the noxious effects
        of Opium; <lb/>among theſe, alſo, have been men of much <lb/>celebrity. <note place="bottom"
          n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Wedelius, amongſt others, ſtrenouſly aſſerts the <lb/>uſe of
          acids. </note>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To acids Dr. Mead adviſes alkaline ſalts <lb/>to be added. Dr. Cullen embraces the
        <lb/>opinion that acids poſſeſs this power, and <lb/>he ſpeaks of his having found them ſo
          <pb xml:id="page_33" n="33"/>
        <lb/>from his own experience <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* "Another means of
          weakening the powers of <lb/>Opium is the application of acids, and we have found
          <lb/>this very effectual." Cullen's Mat. Med. </note>. We wiſh the <lb/>Doctor had
        mentioned the inſtances to <lb/>which he alludes, and the other means <lb/>which he purſued
        at the ſame time, as we <lb/>would then have been more able to deter- <lb/>mine what ſhare
        they exerted, and what <lb/>might be, at the ſame time, attributed to <lb/>the other methods
        he purſued. He does <lb/>not, however, pretend that it changes the <lb/>nature of this drug;
        for when it is given <lb/>thus in union with Opium, in a large <lb/>enough quantity, he
        allows it to have all <lb/>the ſame effects as Opium alone. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Doctor Webſter, an eminent medical <lb/>teacher, at Edinburgh, and whom I have <lb/>the
        honour to rank as one of my pre- <lb/>ceptors in this ſcience, has the following <pb
          xml:id="page_34" n="34"/>
        <lb/>obſervation, which may be found in his <lb/>Syllabus. "Acids render the ſtomach
        <lb/>leſs capable of being acted on by other <lb/>matters, as ſpirits, ale, &amp;c." In the
        <lb/>courſe of his lectures, the Doctor enlarges <lb/>on the obſervation, by ſaying, that
        "the <lb/>action of Hemlock, Opium, and Ipeca- <lb/>cuanha, are moderated much by the ad-
        <lb/>dition of an acid." </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">An</hi> ingenious phyſician, who has not <lb/>long ſince made many
        experiments on this <lb/>article of the Mat. Med. denies that any <lb/>ſuch effects follow.
        He affirms that acids <lb/>render the ſtomach leſs ſenſible of the <lb/>operation of Opium,
        if given previous to <lb/>it; but ſhould the Opium be firſt admi- <lb/>niſtered, and its
        effects have began, in <lb/>any degree, to appear, the acid then <lb/>cannot leſſen them. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_35" n="35"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>HE gave to a boy, of twelve years of <lb/>age, an ounce of common vinegar; a
        <lb/>quarter of an hour after 40 gutts of L. <lb/>Laud.; in half an hour it produced a ſe-
        <lb/>vere ſickneſs at his ſtomach, but no vo- <lb/>miting. His head now began to be a
        <lb/>little affected, but this did not continue <lb/>long; the pulſe remained ſteady, except
        <lb/>when the nauſea appeared; theſe ſymptoms <lb/>ſoon went off, and the boy was reſtored
        <lb/>to his uſual ſituation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To a healthy young man he gave two <lb/>ounces of the common vegetable acid, and
        <lb/>in a quarter of an hour after 80 gutts of <lb/>T. Opii.; two hours after taking it he
        <lb/>complained of a little nauſea and head- <lb/>ach; theſe ſymptoms continued only a
        <lb/>ſhort time, when he felt himſelf as uſual, <lb/>except a little ſickneſs about the
        ſtomach. <lb/>The Doctor could diſcover no change in <pb xml:id="page_36" n="36"/>
        <lb/>the pulſe whatſover: he made ſimilar ex- <lb/>periments both on dogs and rabbits, and
        <lb/>concludes, by ſaying, "that the Opium <lb/>ſeldom had much effect, if an acid was
        <lb/>previouſly given." </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">He</hi> inſtituted other experiments both on <lb/>frogs and dogs; to
        ſatisfy himſelf farther, <lb/>how far the acid would act if the Opi- <lb/>um was given, and
        had begun to exert <lb/>its effects before the other was exhi- <lb/>bited. His concluſion is
        this,—"That <lb/>the acid, if given after the Opium began <lb/>to operate, had not the
        ſmalleſt power of <lb/>correcting its dangerous tendency." Hence <lb/>it it is plain, if we
        put any credit in the <lb/>experiments of this ingenious gentleman, <lb/>that the
        ſuppoſition of acids correcting the <lb/>deleterious effects of Opium, like many <lb/>other
        of the antient theories, has no ex- <lb/>iſtence in reality, and that, we muſt not, <pb
          xml:id="page_37" n="37"/>
        <lb/>therefore, place our dependance in their <lb/>uſe when the patient is in danger from
        <lb/>the noxious powers of Opium, though <lb/>a different doctrine be ſupported by great
        <lb/>names, both among the antient and <lb/>modern phyſicians. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">How</hi> far diuretics may conduce to the <lb/>cure I dare not determine.
        As our great <lb/>and chief buſineſs is to evacuate the Opium <lb/>from the habit, and as
        the urine is found <lb/>to contain it, which is indicated by its <lb/>ſmell, I am inclined
        to think they may, in <lb/>their turn, be advantageouſly had recourſe <lb/>to. The
        diſcharges by the ſkin are generally <lb/>obſerved to leſſen that by the kidnies; but
        <lb/>both, I am perſuaded, may be forwarded <lb/>to a certain degree at the ſame time. Di-
        <lb/>luents was recommended to keep up a <lb/>ſweat; diluents, in plenty, will excite the
        <lb/>urinary diſcharges: to theſe may be added <pb xml:id="page_38" n="38"/>
        <lb/>medicines more directly ſtimulating the <lb/>urinary organs. Parſley tea may be drank;
        <lb/>ſp. æther. nitros. has been generally conſider- <lb/>ed as having ſpecific effects on
        the kidnies. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Other</hi> methods more effectually for eli- <lb/>minating this poiſon
        from the human body, <lb/>I know of none; and I fully believe, where <lb/>the circumſtances
        are ſuch, that hopes can <lb/>be entertained, none other are neceſſary. <lb/>Let me again
        recommend, however, expedi- <lb/>tion and diligence in their application. Dr. <lb/>Willis
        informs us of a robuſt man, who, <lb/>after taking a large doſe of laudanum, was <lb/>dead
        in ſo ſhort a time as four hours. <lb/>Others have died in ten, twelve, and ſix- <lb/>teen. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr. Leigh gave only five grains to a wo- <lb/>man, and it threw her into violent con-
        <lb/>vulſions; he gave her a few grains of ipe- <pb xml:id="page_39" n="39"/>
        <lb/>cucuanha to remove it, and afterwards 60 <lb/>gutts of æther; ſhe was not well, how-
        <lb/>ever, for two days after. The ſame gen- <lb/>tleman gave to a dog, for an experiment,
        <lb/>an ounce diſſolved in water. In a very ſhort <lb/>time it threw him into convulſions,
        and <lb/>killed him. We may remark, by the bye, <lb/>that his ſtomach was immediately laid
        open, <lb/>and the coats attentively examined, but not <lb/>the ſmalleſt marks of
        inflammation were <lb/>perceivable; a much leſs quantity would <lb/>moſt undoubtedly have
        killed him. Dr. <lb/>Mead gave a quarter of an ounce to a dog, <lb/>and in ſo ſhort a time
        as a quarter of an <lb/>hour he began to ſleep; then was con- <lb/>vulſed; fell into
        univerſal tremblings; <lb/>breathed ſhort and laborious; loſt the uſe <lb/>of both his fore
        and hind legs; and then, <lb/>as the Doctor expreſſes it, "his limbs on <lb/>a ſudden grew
        limber, and he inſtantly <lb/>expired." </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_40" n="40"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">When</hi>, unhappily, this drug has been <lb/>ſwallowed to this quantity,
        our firſt enqui- <lb/>ry ſhould be, how long it has been in the <lb/>ſtomach, and in what
        form it was admi- <lb/>niſtered? whether in a liquid, or ſolid form? <lb/>whether united
        with other ſubſtances, and <lb/>what theſe ſubſtances were? In a liquid <lb/>form it is
        found to exert its effects much <lb/>ſooner than when taken in a ſolid; and <lb/>according
        to the experiments of the Abbe <lb/>Fontana, in conjunction with ſpirits, it <lb/>is the
        more powerfully deleterious. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. Henderſon, the comedian, it has been <lb/>ſaid, died in a ſhort time, by ſome
        miſtake <lb/>in taking Opium; and the ſame has been <lb/>aſſerted of the late Dr. Brown, who
        in a <lb/>ſtate, it ſeems, of intoxication, took up- <lb/>wards of 500 gutts of laudanum,
        and was <lb/>found dead next morning. If this be true, <lb/>it was a new way of taking off
        the effects <pb xml:id="page_41" n="41"/>
        <lb/>of intoxication; if he took it with this <lb/>intention, it was like adding oil to
        extin- <lb/>guiſh flame; for Opium and ſpirituous <lb/>liquors, in their effects, are very
        analogous <lb/>to each other, and the means, in general, <lb/>that cures the one will cure
        the other; <lb/>with this conſideration, that dilution is <lb/>even <hi rend="italic"
          >more</hi> neceſſary, where ſpirits have <lb/>been drank to a dangerous exceſs, than when
        <lb/>Opium has been taken to the ſame extent. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To ſum up the whole; if we do not <lb/>ſpeedily have recourſe to emetics and the
        <lb/>other means already mentioned; all other <lb/>efforts, when ſtrong convulſions and apo-
        <lb/>plectic ſymptoms have taken place, afford <lb/>but little hopes that life can be ſaved.
        If <lb/>the doſe be ſwallowed from even 15 mi- <lb/>nutes to 30 minutes, to an hour, accord-
        <lb/>ing to the ſtrength and age of the perſon, <lb/>and the quantity taken, its operation
        may <pb xml:id="page_42" n="42"/>
        <lb/>have already gone ſuch lengths, and ex- <lb/>erted its baneful powers ſo far on the ge-
        <lb/>neral ſyſtem, as to render every ſucceeding <lb/>attempt to ſave life altogether
        abortive, <lb/>even under the management of the moſt <lb/>active phyſicians of ſteady
        perſeverance, <lb/>and ready thought. </p>
      <lb/>
      <dateline rend="indent"><hi rend="italic">Ipſwich,</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 1, 1790. </dateline></div><div>
      <pb xml:id="page_43" n="43"/>
      <head rend="indent hanging italic">
        <lb/>Beſides the caſe that gave riſe to the fore- <lb/>going reflections, the following
        inſtance of <lb/>the death of a young woman, occaſioned <lb/>by Opium, about three years
        ago, lately <lb/>came to my knowledge; on its being in- <lb/>timated to me, I wrote to the
        gentleman <lb/>under whoſe care ſhe was, during a few <lb/>of her laſt hours, when he
        obligingly ſent <lb/>me the ſubjoined particulars. </head>
      <head type="sub" rend="size(0.5)">
        <lb/>To Dr. HAMILTON, Phyſician, Ipſwich. </head>
      <lb/>
      <salute><hi rend="sc">Dear Sir, </hi>
      </salute>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">I</hi> Am ſorry I cannot ſend you a more <lb/>perfect account of the
        caſe you re- <lb/>quire, than that which you will now re- <lb/>ceive; the girl's name, who
        was the ſub- <lb/>ject of it, I forget <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* Her
          name, as I am told, was Lydia Spratt. </note>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">June</hi> the 3d, 1787, I was ſent for, <lb/>between ſix and ſeven in the
        morning, to <pb xml:id="page_44" n="44"/>
        <lb/>a ſervant girl of a farmer, who lives about <lb/>four miles from hence. The only in-
        <lb/>formation which I received, was, that they <lb/>could not awake her; accordingly, on
        <lb/>my going to her maſter's, I found her in a <lb/>deep ſleep, attended with laborious
        breath- <lb/>ing and great ſweating; knowing that the <lb/>miſtreſs of the houſe frequently
        took lau- <lb/>danum for a complaint in the ſtomach, I <lb/>enquired whether the girl might
        not have <lb/>taken ſome. The phial was accordingly <lb/>ſought for. And miſſing it, upon
        farther <lb/>ſearch, we found it under her pillow, <lb/>and empty. The phial had been filled
        <lb/>the day before, and contained two ounces; <lb/>therefore, from theſe circumſtances, we
        <lb/>made no doubt but ſhe had taken the <lb/>whole about eleven o'clock the preceding
        <lb/>night. I immediately gave her two ſcru- <lb/>ples of ipecacuanha without the leaſt ef-
        <lb/>fect; ſhe did not ſeem to have the power <pb xml:id="page_45" n="45"/>
        <lb/>of deglution at any one time, during my <lb/>attendance, which was four hours; but
        <lb/>the fluids which I gave ſeemed to go <lb/>down her throat without any effort on her
        <lb/>part. She had a florid look, but a languid <lb/>pulſe; however, I bled her about four
        <lb/>ounces; I made a large orifice, but the <lb/>blood came away very ſlowly, and was
        <lb/>very black: I gave her vinegar and brandy, <lb/>mixed with ſome of the ſpirit: ammon:
        <lb/>comp: I likewiſe had her well rubbed in <lb/>different parts of the body with the ſame
        <lb/>mixture. After we had continued this <lb/>method about two hours, I had her car-
        <lb/>ried into the air, and laid upon a caſk, <lb/>which we kept moving about; when
        <lb/>after all I found ſhe remained in a total <lb/>inſenſible ſtate, I had her ſet in a
        chair, <lb/>where ſhe remained till ſhe died, which <lb/>was about another hour. Her breath-
        <lb/>ing became more and more laborious; at <pb xml:id="page_46" n="46"/>
        <lb/>the end of every expiration, there ſeemed to <lb/>be a total inactivity of the lungs
        for ſome <lb/>moments, and the ſucceeding inſpiration <lb/>was long. I ſhould call her
        death, a for- <lb/>getting to breathe. Her eyelids were cloſed <lb/>all the time, and when
        lifted up the pupils <lb/>appeared very much dilated, and not to <lb/>have the power of
        contraction. </p>
      <signed>
        <hi rend="indent">
          <lb/>I remain, Dear Sir, <lb/>Your very humble ſervant, &amp;c. <lb/>R. PRIEST. </hi>
      </signed>
      <dateline rend="size(0.5)"><hi rend="sc">Harleston</hi>, <lb/>July 7, 1790. </dateline>
        </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
