<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Johnstone: Some account of the medicinal water, near
          Tewkesbury</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>James Johnstone</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Some thoughts of the medicinal water, near Tewkesbury; with thoughts
              on the use and diseases of the lymphatic glands. In a letter to Edward Johnstone, M.
              D. A Physician to the General Hospital, Birmingham, &amp;c. </title>
            <edition n="2"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T78406</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T78406"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Tewkesbury</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Tewkesbury: printed and sold by Dyde and Son, M,DCC,XC.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1790</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="3"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="46"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3309399214</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K065111.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: medicine"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <head rend="align-center size(1.75)">
          <lb/>THE <lb/>PREFACE. </head>
        <p rend="indent italic">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HOUGH <hi rend="roman">Walton</hi> Water, is here held out, as
          poſ- <lb/>ſeſſing the ſame Properties and Medicinal Powers as <hi rend="roman">Chel-
            <lb/>tenham</hi> Water, it is not done with the moſt diſtant View, <lb/>to leſſen the
          Reputation of that Water, and the Reſort to <lb/><hi rend="roman">Cheltenham.</hi> On the
          contrary, it is preſumed, it will be <lb/>a Satisfaction to Invalids to be aſſured of
          having within a <lb/>ſmall Diſtance, a Water of the ſame Kind, to which recourſe <lb/>may
          be had, when the Numbers are ſo great at <hi rend="roman">Chelten- <lb/>ham,</hi> as to be
          inſufficiently ſupplied from the Well there. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic">
          <lb/>In this point of View, the Water near <hi rend="roman">Tewkesbury</hi>
          <lb/>muſt be uſeful to <hi rend="italic">Cheltenham</hi> in full Seaſons, and, cannot
          <lb/>injure it in any one, at its priority in uſe, and, the habit of <lb/>Reſort for
          Amuſement, as well as Health, will give <hi rend="roman">Chel- <lb/>tenham</hi> the
          Preference. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic">
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">Tewkesbury,</hi> however, has equally a Right to the <lb/>Benefit of
          its natural Riches, and to the Advantages which <lb/>may accrue to it from the Vicinity of
            <hi rend="roman">Walton</hi> Waters in <lb/>particular. This Borough is ſituated on a
          fertile Plain, at <lb/>the Conflux of the River <hi rend="roman">Avon</hi> with the <hi
            rend="roman">Severn.</hi> The <lb/>Town is well built, and now well paved, and,
          Proviſions <lb/>of every Kind, particularly the fineſt Salmon, are in great <pb
            xml:id="page_3" n="iv"/>
          <lb/>plenty. It communicates by a very good Road, to fine rides <lb/>towards <hi
            rend="roman">Worceſter, Upton,</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Malvern,</hi> and is only
          <lb/>nine Miles from <hi rend="roman">Cheltenham.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="italic indent">
          <lb/>In theſe rides, the various Views of a moſt Pictureſque <lb/>Country, charm the Eye,
          and make the ſalutary Exerciſe <lb/>of riding delightful. <hi rend="roman">Malvern,</hi>
          riſing in benign, Majeſty, <lb/>diffuſes all around a pure and temperate Air; a Water
          <lb/>exceeding all others in elementary Purity; which every <lb/>Year manifeſts its
          ſalubrity in curing Diſeaſes which have <lb/>baſſied the Power of Medicine in other
          Situations. </p>
        <p rend="indent italic">
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">Tewkesbury,</hi> and its Environs, beſides the ſtriking
          <lb/>beauties of the Country, preſent to the Obſervation of the <lb/>curious; A Field of
          Battle where Victory fixed the Crown <lb/>on the Head of <hi rend="roman">Edward</hi> IV.
          A Church, one of the fineſt <lb/><hi rend="roman">Gothick</hi> Structures in <hi
            rend="roman">England;</hi> in which lie the Re- <lb/>mains of <hi rend="roman"
            >Edward</hi> Prince of <hi rend="roman">Wales,</hi> Son of <hi rend="roman">Henry</hi>
          VI. <lb/>cruelly murdered in cold Blood, with the Duke of <hi rend="roman">Somerſet</hi>
          <lb/>and many other Noblemen and Gentlemen who ſhared his <lb/>Fate after that deciſive
          Battle. </p>
        <lb/>
        <q rend="align-center">—Sacros Auſus recludere fontes. </q>
        <p rend="indent italic">
          <lb/>My Motto, is proper in more Senſes than one; for taking <lb/>advantage of the
          Epiſtolary Form; I have attempted to <lb/>illuſtrate the Uſe of the Lymphatic Glands,
          acknowledged <lb/>to be hitherto undiſcovered, as well as to make known the
          <lb/>Properties of a new Medicinal Water. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_4"/>
        <lb/>
        <salute rend="italic">SIR, </salute>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>T length, I ſend you, an ac- <lb/>count of the Experiments,
          made on the Medicinal <lb/>Water near Tewkesbury, of which, ſo much has <lb/>been ſaid at
          Cheltenham, in the courſe of this Seaſon <lb/>and the laſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">first</hi> heard of this Water in paſſing through <lb/>Tewkesbury in
          1786. It had been for ſome time re- <lb/>ſorted to, by Perſons in the Neighbourhood, and,
          <lb/>was reported to have effected Cures in the Diſeaſes <lb/>for which Cheltenham Water
          is ſound to be ſo effica- <lb/>cious, and, on account of which, Perſons of every
          <lb/>Rank, reſort to that Place in ſuch Numbers, as to <lb/>exhauſt ſometimes the Spring
          on which they reſt <lb/>their hopes of recovery. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> Well is ſituated near Walton, a Village <lb/>about a mile
          from Tewkesbury, upon an Eſtate be- <lb/>longing to Nicholas Smithſend, Eſquire. The
          <lb/>Ground about the Well is a deep Clay Soil, under <lb/>which, at the depth of about
          ſeven or eight yards, <lb/>runs a Stratum of blue ſlaty Stone; on piercing this <lb/>Bed
          of Stone, plentiful Springs of Water ariſe, <lb/>which are always more or leſs impregnated
          with Salt. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_5" n="6"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> Well, of which I write, is about twenty <lb/>feet deep. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> Water from the Pump, or ſoon after, hasa <lb/>ſoft, almoſt
          Oleaginous taſte, numerous Air Bubbles <lb/>riſe, and ſparkle in the Glaſs; after it has
          been <lb/>drank, it leaves the Chalybeate, and Saline taſtes on <lb/>the tongue, and when
          ſhook in the Bottle, the He- <lb/>patic ſmell is very perceptible. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Its</hi> reſemblance in taſte, and other appearances to <lb/>the
          Cheltenham Water, ſtrikes every one who makes <lb/>the compariſon. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Its</hi> operation on the Body, alſo, is exactly the <lb/>ſame, a Pint
          or more, acts as a gentle Laxative and <lb/>Diuretic: And it occaſions a ſlight giddineſs
          in ſome <lb/>perſons, in others a ſort of heavy pain in the head. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">These</hi> teſts, though of themſelves, ſufficiently <lb/>convincing,
          will be confirmed by the Experiments <lb/>which I made on the Walton Water, in the Summer
          <lb/>of 1786, and this Summer, in which I had the aſſiſt- <lb/>ance of the worthy Surgeons
          and Apothecaries, at <lb/>Tewkesbury. 1. When the Walton Water is mix- <lb/>ed with Clear
          ſiltered Lime Water, it becomes im- <lb/>mediately cloudy, and, a copious white ſcaly
          preci- <lb/>pitation enſues. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> ſame cloudy appearance ariſes in Lime Wa- <lb/>ter, when the
          Air, ſeparated by Heat from the Wal- <lb/>ton Water, is conveyed by a Pipe and Bladder,
          con- <pb xml:id="page_6" n="7"/>
          <lb/>nected with the two Bottles, into the Bottle, con- <lb/>taining the Lime Water, and
          ſhaken with it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">If</hi> the Walton Water has been taken from the <lb/>Well, twelve or
          more hours, the precipitation by <lb/>Lime Water, does not take place immediately, in
          <lb/>the manner it does in a Glaſs of Water from the <lb/>Pump. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">White</hi> Arſenic, diſſolves more readily in the <lb/>Walton Water,
          than in common Water, and ren- <lb/>ders the Hepatic ſmell thereof, ſtronger and more
          <lb/>perceptible. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="2">
          <lb/>2. <hi rend="sc">When</hi> Walton Water, freſh from the Pump, <lb/>is mixed with an
          Infuſion of Green Tea, the mixture <lb/>aſſumes a Purple Colour, and by ſtanding, the Co-
          <lb/>lour becomes deeper, </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="3">
          <lb/>3. <hi rend="sc">Solution</hi> of Saccharum Saturni, mixed with <lb/>freſh drawn
          Water, becomes brown, and is followed <lb/>by a blackiſh precipitation. This is a teſt of
          the pre- <lb/>ſence of Hepatic Air, which alſo diſcovers itſelf in <lb/>this Water, by its
          characteriſtic Sulphureous ſmell. <lb/>This often is produced by putrifying Vegetables.
          <lb/>Biſhop Watſon, obſerves, that Sulphureous Waters <lb/>are produced in Moraſſes and
          Bogs, from rotten <lb/>Wood; that Shale, a ſtone ſo called, of which there <lb/>is a
          Stratum, extended all over the Country about <lb/>Harrowgate, and from which the Sulphur
          Springs <lb/>there ariſe, contains both Vitriolic Acid and Phlo- <lb/>giſton, the
          conſtituent parts of Sulphur; and ſome <pb xml:id="page_7" n="8"/>
          <lb/>pieces of Shale, when calcined properly, have been <lb/>found to communicate the
          Sulphureous impregnation <lb/>to Water, Ph. Trans. 1786. It is ſufficient to ob-
          <lb/>ſerve, that Walton Water emerges from a bed of <lb/>ſtone, and, of a blue Sulphureous
          ſoft Pyrites, pro- <lb/>bably ſimilar to this, and that the Soil abounds with <lb/>the
          remains of rotten Vegetables reſolved into it, and <lb/>that from one or both theſe
          ſources, it derives the <lb/>Hepatic Gas perceived in it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> blue Sulphureous Pyrites found in digging <lb/>the Ground in
          the Field belonging to the Well-houſe <lb/>near Walton, has exactly the ſame appearance
          and <lb/>properties as that dug, to make a New Well, near <lb/>Fauconberg-houſe, by order
          of his Majeſty. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="4">
          <lb/>4. <hi rend="sc">After</hi> Walton Water has been drawn from <lb/>the Pump ten or
          twelve hours; it no longer becomes <lb/>purple or blackiſh, by the addition of
          aſtringents, <lb/>(No. II.) and a precipitation with Lime Water, does <lb/>not immediately
          enſue, (No. I.) </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="5">
          <lb/>5. <hi rend="sc">Its</hi> Colour neither becomes Green nor Red, <lb/>with Syrup of
          Violets. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="6">
          <lb/>6. <hi rend="sc">It</hi> does not efferveſce with the Vitriolic or <lb/>Nitrous
          Acids. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="7">
          <lb/>7. <hi rend="sc">It</hi> becomes milky by mixture, with the fixed <lb/>Alkali, and
          more ſo with the Volatile Alkali pre- <lb/>pared with Lime. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="8">
          <lb/>8. <hi rend="sc">Solution</hi> of Silver, makes it milky and a fla- <lb/>ky
          precipitation ſubſides. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_8" n="9"/>
        <p rend="indent" n="9">
          <lb/>9. <hi rend="sc">Two</hi> ingenious friends, and accurate obſervers, <lb/>found the
          whole fixed contents of the Water left by <lb/>evaporation, amounted to one ounce in a
          gallon. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="10">
          <lb/>10 <hi rend="sc">After</hi> various evaporations, I found it yield- <lb/>ed exactly
          that quantity. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">When</hi> a Gallon of the Water is reduced by eva- <lb/>poration to two
          ounces and under, a conſiderable <lb/>quantity of an earthy powder remains in the veſſel
          in <lb/>which it was boiled. And when the liquid is ſet to <lb/>cry ſtalliſe, Cryſtals, in
          ſhape and ſize, reſembling <lb/>the Vitriolated Magneſia are formed. They are hexa-
          <lb/>gonal, and when dried in the Sun, are calcined into <lb/>a white powder. The taſte
          cool and bitter. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Some</hi> cubical Cryſtals of marine ſalt, and a de- <lb/>liqueſcent
          bitter lixivium remain. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> powder, dropped by boiling in the veſſel, <lb/>conſiſts of
          Magneſia, and an abſorbent earth, which <lb/>entirely diſſolve in Vinegar, with
          conſiderable eſſer- <lb/>veſcence. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> quantity of large Cryſtals amounted to ſix <lb/>drachms or
          more, from a Gallon of Water, evapo- <lb/>rated in 1786; but, by after experiments, I find
          this <lb/>impregnation is not conſtantly in the ſame quantity, <lb/>and proportion. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="11">
          <lb/>11. <hi rend="sc">Lastly</hi>, the Cryſtals of the Walton Water, <lb/>and, the white
          powder into which theſe dried Cry- <lb/>ſtals ſall, when diſſolved, the Solution is again
          per- <lb/>fect, and clear in an exceedingly ſmall quantity of <lb/>Water. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_9" n="10"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Salt</hi> of Tartar, added to this Solution, becomes <lb/>Milky, and a
          copious white ſediment ſubſides, ſound <lb/>to be Magneſia. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Lime</hi> Water added to the Solution, occaſions a <lb/>Milky
          whiteneſs, and a ſoft Alkaline precipitation, <lb/>but it does not happen near ſo ſoon as
          that made by <lb/>falt of Tarter. </p>
      </div>
     <div>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>SOME FARTHER EXPERIMENTS <lb/><hi rend="size(1.75)">On WALTON WATER, </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="size(0.75)">Made in <hi rend="sc">November</hi>, 1787,</hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="size(1.25)">By JOHN JOHNSTONE, <hi rend="italic">B. A.</hi>
          </hi>
          <lb/>Of MERTON COLLEGE, <hi rend="sc">Oxford</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>THE Water, on which the following Experi- <lb/>ments were tried, had been drawn from
          the Spring <lb/>ſeveral weeks before it was uſed. And though it was <lb/>conveyed from
          Walton to Birmingham in Bottles <lb/>well corked and covered with Wax, yet the appear-
          <lb/>ances which reſult from the preſence of the Volatile <lb/>Ingredients are not to be
          expected in theſe Experi- <lb/>ments. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="1">
          <lb/>1. <hi rend="sc">This</hi> Water did not immediately become Pur- <lb/>ple with
          Tincture of Galls, but by ſtanding it con- <lb/>tracted a dusky greeniſh colour with a
          variegate <lb/>Pellicle at the top. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_10" n="11"/>
        <p rend="indent" n="2">
          <lb/>2. <hi rend="sc">Phlogisticated</hi> Alkali did not occaſion any <lb/>change of the
          colour in the Water. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> fixed Air having eſcaped, the Iron was pre- <lb/>cipitated,
          and of courſe could not exhibit thoſe Ap- <lb/>pearances which it did in the Experiments
          made by <lb/>my Father at the Spring. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="3">
          <lb/>3. <hi rend="sc">Syrup</hi> of Violets made it of a light green Co- <lb/>lour,
          Tincture of Turnſole became brown when <lb/>mixed with it. Tincture of Brazil Wood gave it
          a <lb/>blue caſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> Appearances produced by theſe three Precipi- <lb/>tants were
          occaſioned either by Magneſia or Alkali, <lb/>diſengaged by the eſcape of the fixed Air. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="4">
          <lb/>4. <hi rend="sc">Acid</hi> of Sugar diſcovered Lime, by precipita- <lb/>ting it in
          the form of a white Powder. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="5">
          <lb/>5. <hi rend="sc">Salited</hi> Terra Ponderoſa, by attracting the <lb/>Vitriolic Acid,
          occaſioned a white turbidneſs in this <lb/>Water. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="6">
          <lb/>6. <hi rend="sc">Nitrated</hi> Silver ſhewed the preſence of Ma- <lb/>rine Acid; its
          attraction for it producing a white <lb/>Cloud, which on ſtanding, became of a black
          colour. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="7">
          <lb/>7. <hi rend="sc">An</hi> Alkali, very copiouſly precipitated a white <lb/>Powder,
          which appeared to be Magneſia. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">By</hi> ſeveral Experiments, a quart of the Walton <lb/>Water yielded,
          on Evaporation, 120 <formula notation="fraction">1/2 </formula> grains. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="1">
          <lb/>I. <hi rend="sc">The</hi> reſidue of a Quart of this Water, was firſt <pb
            xml:id="page_11" n="12"/>
          <lb/>mixed with Alcohol, which took up 6 <formula notation="fraction">1/2 </formula>
          grains of it. <lb/>This, by its deliqueſcing in the air, was found to con- <lb/>ſiſt of
          Magneſia. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="2">
          <lb/>II. Diſtilled Water diſſolved 105 grains of it. <lb/>As I could not cryſtalliſe the
          whole, I cannot tell <lb/>the proportion of each Salt, but I had reaſon, both <lb/>from
          what did cryſtalliſe, and from Experiment, to <lb/>ſuppoſe, that Vitriolated Magneſia is
          the moſt abun- <lb/>dant in this Water. A quantity of Alcohol, ſuffici- <lb/>ent to
          precipitate the Baſes of thoſe Salts in which <lb/>there was Vitriolic Acid, was mixed
          with a pint of <lb/>Walton Water. A copious Precipitation enſued, <lb/>which on
          examination proved to be Magneſia alone. <lb/>For on adding Syrup of Violets to the
          Magneſia in <lb/>diſtilled Water, no evidence of Alkali appeared <lb/>more than what
          Magneſia would alone have given. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>To a quart of Walton Water was added a quantity <lb/>of Vegetable Alkali ſufficient
          to precipitate all the <lb/>Magneſia. When the Precipitation was over, the <lb/>whole was
          ſiltered, and the Water ſet to cryſtalliſe. <lb/>The Cryſtals in general, were thoſe of
          Vitriolated <lb/>Tartar, and a few reſembling thoſe of Glauber's <lb/>Salts appeared. A
          very ſmall quantity remained un- <lb/>cryſtalliſed, which perhaps, was common Salt. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="3">
          <lb/>III. <hi rend="sc">Distilled</hi> Vinegar was mixed with what <lb/>the Water left,
          and took up 5 <formula notation="fraction">1/2 </formula> grains of it. On
          <lb/>Examination this proved to be Lime. It had a re- <lb/>markable pungent taſte, did not
          deliqueſce in the <lb/>Air, and formed on the Addition of Vitriolic Acid, <lb/>a kind of
          Gypſum. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_12" n="13"/>
        <p rend="indent" n="4">
          <lb/>IV. <hi rend="sc">An</hi> Alkali diminiſhed the remainder 1 <formula
            notation="fraction">1/2 </formula> grain. <lb/>I could not exactly tell what the Alkali
          took up here, <lb/>but it ſeemed to be a kind of Argillaccous Earth. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="5">
          <lb/>V. <hi rend="sc">The</hi> Alkali left nearly 1 <formula notation="fraction">1/2
          </formula> grain of a black <lb/>looking Earth. This was mixed with diluted Ma- <lb/>rine
          Acid, which diſſolved nearly the whole of it. Phlogiſticated Alkali, dropped into the
          Solution, <lb/>immediately produced a very bright blue Colour. <lb/>I therefore concluded
          that the grain and very ſmall <lb/>quantity more which the Marine Acid had diſſolved
          <lb/>was Iron. The ſmall quantity of Earth which did <lb/>not diſſolve in the Acid, as it
          reſiſted all the above <lb/>mixtures, I concluded to be Siliceous Earth. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">There</hi> appears then to be in a Quart of Walton Water, </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>   Grains, <lb/>I.<hi rend="sc">Of</hi> Ærated Magneſia, —6 <formula
            notation="fraction">1/2 </formula>
          <lb/>II.<hi rend="sc">Of</hi> different Salts, but chiefly Epſom, 105 <lb/>III.<hi
            rend="sc">Of</hi> Ærated Lime, — —5 <formula notation="fraction">1/2 </formula>
          <lb/>IV.<hi rend="sc">OF</hi> Earth, perhaps Argillaceous —1 <formula notation="fraction"
            >1/2 </formula>
          <lb/>V.<hi rend="sc">OF</hi> Ærated Iron, with a little Siliceous Earth 1 <formula
            notation="fraction">1/2 </formula>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Cheltenham</hi> Water (of which I had a few Bot- <lb/>tles) exhibited
          the ſame appearances with Precipi- <lb/>tants, only in ſome inſtances they were more
          ſtriking. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A <hi rend="sc">quart</hi> of Cheltenham Water yielded, on Eva- <lb/>poration, 127
          grains. I tried the Experiments with <lb/>Alcohol and Vegetable Alkali, on Cheltenham,
          with <lb/>the ſame Appearances as with Walton Water, only <lb/>a large Cryſtal of
          Glauber's Salt appeared in the <lb/>Veſſel with the Alcohol. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_13" n="14"/>
        <head rend="align-center size(1.75)">
          <lb/>EXPERIMENT 1. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>SHEWS Walton Water abounds with fixed Air. <lb/>Lime becomes quick, calcined or
          cauſtic, by the ex- <lb/>pulſion of this Air by fire; and being attracted again <lb/>from
          this Water, the Calcareous Matter before held <lb/>in Solution, becomes mild and
          precipitates in form <lb/>of a clear and white powder. The immediate pre- <lb/>cipitation,
          which takes place by the mixture of Wal- <lb/>ton Water with Lime Water, and ſtill more
          clearly <lb/>the Air forced from Walton Water agitated with <lb/>Lime Water, is therefore
          a certain teſt of the pre- <lb/>ſence of fixed Air in Walton Water. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="2">
          <lb/>2. <hi rend="sc">By</hi> this experiment, Iron in a ſmall quantity, <lb/>appears to
          be one of the ſugitive ingredients in the <lb/>Walton Water. This, as well as ſome
          abſorbent <lb/>earth, is kept in a diſſolved ſtate by the fixed Air and <lb/>the
          Sulphureous Gas contained in it: When the <lb/>fixed Air flies off, which it does much
          ſooner than <lb/>the Hepatic Gas, the Iron precipitates, and the Wa- <lb/>ter is no longer
          capable of becoming Purple by <lb/>aſtringents. The action of heat carries off the He-
          <lb/>patic Gas, which appears to hold the abſorbent earths <lb/>in Solution, which are
          left by evaporation; and to <lb/>which the ſoft, almoſt oleaginous taſte, with which
          <lb/>this Water ſtrikes the tongue, is probably owing. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_14" n="15"/>
        <p rend="indent" n="3">
          <lb/>3. <hi rend="sc">The</hi> addition of Saccharum Saturni diſcovers <lb/>the preſence
          of the Hepatic Air, another fugitive <lb/>principle contained in this Water, as well as
          that of <lb/>Cheltenham: But it is much leſs fugitive than fixed <lb/>Air, being often
          perceived, both in the Cheltenham <lb/>and Walton Waters, after they have been bottled a
          <lb/>conſiderable time. This Sulphureous or Hepatic <lb/>Air, found in this and in other
          Waters, has been <lb/>the occaſion of much controverſy among the Gentle- <lb/>men who have
          analyſed Waters: Mr. Kirwan, has, <lb/>probably finally, ſettled the diſpute, by ſhewing
          that <lb/>Hepatic Air is no other, than actual Sulphur kept in <lb/>Solution, in an acrial
          State, by union with the mat- <lb/>ter of heat, Ph. Tr. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="4">
          <lb/>4. <hi rend="sc">It</hi> is evident, from this article, that the fixed <lb/>Air only
          diſſolves and keeps Iron ſuſpended in the <lb/>Water. Its diſappearance ſo ſoon, ſhews its
          very <lb/>volatile Nature, and, the neceſſity of reſorting to <lb/>theſe Springs, to have
          the benefit of a principle and <lb/>ingredient, which gives penetrability, and action to
          <lb/>the Saline contents of the Waters. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="5">
          <lb/>5, 6. <hi rend="sc">Shew</hi> the Salts contained in theſe Waters <lb/>are neutral:
          And, that neither the acid nor the Alkali, <lb/>of which they are compounded, prevail. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="7">
          <lb/>7 — 11. DEMONSTRATE, that Vitriolated Magneſia, <lb/>is the principal Salt contained
          in the Walton Water. <lb/>The attraction of an alkaline Salt, and eſpecially that <lb/>of
          the cauſtic Alkali, with the Vitriolic Acid, is <lb/>greater than that of the Magneſia,
          which is precipi- <lb/>tated in theſe experiments. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_15" n="16"/>
        <p rend="indent" n="8">
          <lb/>8. <hi rend="sc">The</hi> exiſtence of Sea Salt, is manifeſted by <lb/>this
          experiment, and by the cubic Cryſtals formed <lb/>in the reſiduum. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="9">
          <lb/>9, 10. <hi rend="sc">From</hi> all our experiments, fixed Air diſſol- <lb/>ving a
          ſmall quantity of Iron: Hepatic Air, united <lb/>with an abſorbent earth, appear to be the
          fugitive <lb/>ingredients of the Walton Water. The fixed ingre- <lb/>dients diſcovered by
          evaporation and cryſtalliſation, <lb/>appear to be a Vitriolated Magneſia, united with a
          <lb/>little Vitriolated Mineral Alkali, in the quantity <lb/>of ſix or ſeven drachms, in
          one Gallon of Water. <lb/>Magneſia, Lime and abſorbent earth, and a delique- <lb/>ſcent
          bitter Lixivium, conſiſting of ſalited Magneſia <lb/>and Lime, with a few grains of entire
          Sea Salt, alto- <lb/>gether, about a drachm or two to a Gallon. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">That</hi> theſe alſo are the component Medicinal in- <lb/>gredients in
          the Cheltenham Water, appears by the <lb/>analyſis, of the learned Dr. Fothergill, of
          Bath. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> Gentleman, in his very valuable experimen- <lb/>tal enquiry
          into the nature and qualities of Chelten- <lb/>ham Water, p. 42. concludes, "from the
          preceed- <lb/>ing experiments, a Gallon of the Water, wine mea- <lb/>ſure, appears to
          contain the ſubſequent principles, <lb/>nearly in the following proportions: Native
          Glauber <lb/>Salt, with a portion of Epſom Salt, one ounce; Sea <lb/>Salt, five grains;
          Iron combined with fixed Air, <lb/>five grains; Magneſia combined with fixed Air,
          <lb/>twenty five grains; Calcareous earth, or Selenite, <lb/>forty grains; fixed Air,
          combined with phlogiſtica- <pb xml:id="page_16" n="17"/>
          <lb/>ted Air, twenty-four ounce meaſures. To theſe may, <lb/>perhaps, be added a ſmall
          proportion of Hepatic Gas <lb/>or Hepar Sulphuris converted into Vapour by the
          <lb/>ſeparation of its phlogiſton." <note place="bottom" n="(a)" rend="size(0.5)">(a) This
            uſeful Work has been much improved and enlarged in <lb/>the Second Edition. </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">By</hi> this ingenious Work, it appears, and is ſuffi- <lb/>ciently
          known to all who frequent Cheltenham, <lb/>that the Iron is very ſoon precipitated from
          the Wa- <lb/>ter, after it is drawn from the Pump; and, in a ſhort <lb/>time it cannot be
          made to aſſume a purple colour, <lb/>by the addition of aſtringents. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> Salts of the Walton and Cheltenham Waters, <lb/>are both
          ſoluble in a very ſmall quantity of Water, <lb/>equal to their weight nearly: And their
          impreſſion <lb/>on the human ſenſes, and, their action in the bowels, <lb/>is the ſame. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> ſo many points, the Cheltenham and Walton <lb/>Mineral Waters,
          are entirely like each other; a pint <lb/>or leſs of each opens the body; ſome find a
          ſmall <lb/>addition of the Walton, neceſſary to produce the <lb/>ſame effect in the ſame
          degree; others find no dif- <lb/>ference; the purgative Salt is ſomewhat leſs, about a
          <lb/>drachm in a gallon, in my experiments; but the <lb/>quantity of fixed Air, and Steel
          are at leaſt equal. <lb/>The Hepatic Air ſeems to prevail in the Walton <lb/>Water, over
          the Cheltenham, which gives it a moſt <lb/>pleaſing almoſt Oleaginous ſoftneſs, and makes
          it <lb/>highly grateful in taſte, and gentle in operation, and, <pb xml:id="page_17"
            n="18"/>
          <lb/>far more ſuitable in diſeaſes of the kidneys, and uri- <lb/>nary paſſages, than the
          Cheltenham Water itſelf. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Without</hi>, therefore entering into a farther de- <lb/>tail of
          Chymical reſearch, I apprehend the ſimilarity <lb/>of the Walton, to the Cheltenham Water,
          to be ſuf- <lb/>ficiently aſcertained, to warrant its uſe and applica- <lb/>tion in the
          diſeaſes, for which Cheltenham Waters <lb/>have been uſed with advantage. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> analyſis of Mineral Waters, undoubtedly is <lb/>highly uſeful;
          but notwithſtanding the perfection to <lb/>which it is carried by diſcoveries in modern
          Chymiſ- <lb/>try, I apprehend it gives a very imperfect idea of the <lb/>real compoſition
          of Waters; in ſhort, ſuch an idea <lb/>as diffection gives of an animated body, a view of
          its <lb/>parts diſjointed, and ſeparate, very different from that <lb/>union, on which
          ſymmetry and life depend. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is on this account, that the exhibition of the in-
          <lb/>gredients found to compoſe mineral Waters, and the <lb/>imitations of many of them,
          adminiſtred as Medi- <lb/>cines, fall ſhort of the Waters prepared by <lb/>Nature,
          eſpecially when drank at the ſources. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is the ſame in other parts of the Materia Me- <lb/>dica: An
          analyſis, in ſome meaſure, aſſiſts in ac- <lb/>counting for the operation of a Medicine,
          but ſeldom <lb/>enables us to prepare, and compound to perfection, <lb/>the natural
          productions we pretend to imitate. <note place="bottom" n="(b)" rend="size(0.5)">(b) Theſe
            Sentiments have been diſtinguiſhed by the Ap- <lb/>probation of M. <hi rend="sc"
              >Marcard</hi>, his Majeſty's Phyſician at Hanover, <lb/>in his learned Account of the
            Waters at Pyrmout. </note>
        </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_18" n="19"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> uſe, and advantage of Waters, is eſtabliſhed <lb/>by
          experience alone, as well as that of every article <lb/>in the Materia Medica. The
          advantages found from <lb/>the uſe of the Walton Well, in various eruptive di-
          <lb/>ſeaſes, and in old ſordid ulcers, as well as in many <lb/>other diſeaſes, has already
          been ſo conſiderable as to <lb/>confirm the expectation grounded on their being
          <lb/>ſimilar to the Cheltenham Water. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> will undoubtedly be found as much like Chel- <lb/>tenham Water,
          as that Water is like itſelf at differ- <lb/>ent ſeaſons. Seaſons occaſion accidental
          differences <lb/>of ſaturation in all Mineral Waters, the cauſe of <lb/>which, is
          ſometimes known, and ſometimes un- <lb/>known. Rainy ſeaſons, while they make Springs
          <lb/>more abundant, render the Mineral impregnation at <lb/>the ſame time weaker. To this
          alteration, the Wal- <lb/>ton Water muſt be ſometimes liable, as it lies on a <lb/>plain,
          part of which is frequently overflowed with <lb/>Water. But, if by experience, this ſhall
          be ſound <lb/>to have any conſiderable influence, means will be <lb/>uſed to remove the
          inconvenience. An inconveni- <lb/>ence which is very ſeldom likely to happen in dry
          <lb/>and warm ſeaſons, in which, Waters of this claſs, <lb/>are for the moſt part reſorted
          to. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">After</hi> all, I am perſuaded, that the dilution of <lb/>Mineral
          Waters is very ſeldom any injury to the pa- <lb/>tient. The virtues and powers of Mineral
          Water, <lb/>depending principally on the quantity of Water, the <lb/>medium, in which the
          Medicinal ingredients are <pb xml:id="page_19" n="20"/>
          <lb/>ſuſpended; the vehicle which conveys them into <lb/>the ſmalleſt veſſels, and makes
          them capable of re- <lb/>moving obſtructions fixed in them, and in various <lb/>glands;
          hence the ſame Medicinal ingredients, given <lb/>in the uſual forms, have but little
          efficacy in remo- <lb/>ving ſuch diſeaſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> healing powers of the Walton Well, and <lb/>thoſe of its
          Siſter of Cheltenham, are owing to the <lb/>mixture of a neutral compound of vitriolated
          Mag- <lb/>neſia, commonly called Epſom. or Cathartic Salt; <lb/>to vitriolated Mineral
          Alkali, or Glauber Salt, with <lb/>a ſmall portion of ſalited Mineral Alkali, Magneſia,
          <lb/>and Lime, nearly to the quantity of a drachm, in a <lb/>pint of Water; alſo to a
          conſiderable quantity of <lb/>fixed Air, and Hepatic Gas, by the former of which
          <lb/>Iron, and by the latter Magneſia, and abſorbent <lb/>Earth, are held in Solution. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> whole is a compoſition, friendly to appetite <lb/>and
          digeſtion; as well as ſoft, and pleaſing to the <lb/>taſte. It is alſo a penetrating
          deobſtruent, and, atte- <lb/>nuating medicine, and in ſenſible operation, a quick <lb/>and
          gentle Laxative and Diuretic; and when applied <lb/>with diſcretion, it may be continued a
          long time <lb/>without any dimunition of ſtrength. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is obvious, this Water contains Saline ingre- <lb/>dients, and,
          others poſſeſſing different attractive <lb/>powers and aſſinities, which, though ballanced
          in <lb/>the Water; yet, when mixed with animal fluids, <lb/>and Salts in the courſe of
          digeſtion, Chyliſication, <pb xml:id="page_20" n="21"/>
          <lb/>and in circulation with the blood, muſt be ſo chang- <lb/>ed, and varied as to form
          new attractions, and com- <lb/>binations in their courſe through the veſſels, whence
          <lb/>compounds poſſeſſing properties, different from what <lb/>exiſted before, will be
          produced, and the ſyſtem it- <lb/>ſelf will be changed. It is well known, that cold is
          <lb/>generated by diſſolving Salts; and, that while Saline <lb/>Bodies, of different
          affinities, and attractive powers, <lb/>are forming new compounds; ſuch Salts in the pro-
          <lb/>ceſs of mutual attraction, and incorporation, produce <lb/>heat. In this manner, and
          from ſuch cauſes, new <lb/>ſtimuli, with other alterations, take place in the <lb/>glands,
          and remoter veſſels of our ſyſtem, from the <lb/>Salts, combined with other ingredients in
          Mineral <lb/>Waters; and, it is by theſe means, as well as eva- <lb/>cuation, they become
          beneficial, and are really valu- <lb/>able alterative Medicines. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> Walton Waters, being a compound, <hi rend="italic">ſui ge-
            <lb/>veris,</hi> ſimilar to Cheltenham, they both operate pri- <lb/>marily, and
          principally on the inteſtines, as a gentle <lb/>purgative, <q rend="quotes">Their mode of
            operation, (ſays Dr. <lb/>Smith, p. 21, 22,) upon the inteſtines, producing <lb/>an
            eaſy, ſudden diſcharge, is explainable upon the <lb/>principle of the tenuity, and
            uniform diffuſion of <lb/>the ingredients in the Water. For the Water, <lb/>after having
            performed its ſtrengthening, and ex- <lb/>hilarating office upon the ſtomach, paſſes
            quickly <lb/>into the inteſtines as ſluids do, carrying along with <lb/>it, more or leſs
            of all its ingredients, but particu- <lb/>larly its great dilution, and conſequent
            diſperſion <pb xml:id="page_21" n="22"/>
            <lb/>all over the internal ſurface of the canal, vellicates <lb/>the innumerable, little
            exhalent veſſels, with <lb/>which that cavity is crouded, into a plentiful ſecre-
            <lb/>tion; and notwithſtanding the ſtimulus may be but <lb/>ſlight on any particular
            part, on account of the <lb/>minuteneſs of the particles of the Salt; yet as they
            <lb/>are univerſally diffuſed, and act upon the whole <lb/>ſyſtem of exhalents at once,
            a more eopious and <lb/>expeditious evacuation is produced, than what is <lb/>often
            attainable from a much larger quantity of any <lb/>of the other more ſtimulating
            purgatives leſs atte- <lb/>nuated; attended at the ſame time with theſe im- <lb/>portant
            advantages; that as the ſtimulus is gentle, <lb/>no griping pain is likely to be
            excited, and as it is <lb/>ſuperficial, the particles muſt ſoon be waſhed off <lb/>in
            the general current, without leaving behind <lb/>them any of thoſe diſagreeable feelings
            that uſually <lb/>hang in the rear of other Cathartics. </q>
          <note place="bottom" n="(c)" rend="size(0.5)">(c) See Obſervations on the uſe and abuſe of
            Cheltenham Waters, <lb/>by J. <hi rend="sc">Smith</hi>, M. D. Savilian Profeſſor of
            Geometry, Oxford. </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Corollary</hi>. Mineral Waters in general, derive <lb/>their healing
          powers much leſs from the metals, <lb/>earths and ſalts, often inconſiderable in quantity,
          <lb/>which remain after evaporation, than, from the vo- <lb/>latile principles, united
          with them, but diluted in a <lb/>very great proportion of Water; and, they univer-
          <lb/>ſally owe the activity the whole poſſeſſes, to the <lb/>incorporation of the volatile
          and ſugitive principles, <lb/>both with the Water, and, with the groſſer ingre-
          <lb/>dients, combined together moſt intimately. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_22" n="23"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> taſte of the Walton Water, freſh from the <lb/>Spring, as has
          been already obſerved, is at firſt ſoft, <lb/>and afterwards agreeably Saline; the Sulphur
          and <lb/>Iron, are alſo plainly taſted in it, in the quantity of <lb/>a pint, and, often
          leſs, it occaſions two or three lax <lb/>ſtools, and, operates without the leaſt ſickneſs,
          gri- <lb/>ping or any kind of inconvenience. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> quantity of urine is alſo encreaſed: it ſits eaſy <lb/>on the
          ſtomach, and appetite is promoted. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> volatile principles fly off, ſoon after the Wa- <lb/>ter is
          removed from the Well; and, as theſe are ſo <lb/>eſſential to its efficacy, and, render it
          agreeable to the <lb/>taſte and ſtomach, and carry the Saline, invigora- <lb/>ting, and
          deobſtruent contents of the Water into <lb/>the veſſels and glands; it is neceſſary to
          drink it <lb/>from the Pump, or very ſoon afterwards. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">These</hi> Waters not only remove coſtiveneſs, but <lb/>encreaſe
          appetite, and the powers of digeſtion, <lb/>The chylification of digeſted aliment is more
          per- <lb/>fectly elaborated, and, the errors of the firſt digeſti- <lb/>on prevented, and
          remedied in an effectual manner; <lb/>whatever is injurious to health in the ſtomach and
          <lb/>and inteſtines, acidity, and <unclear>#</unclear>ilious putrid matter are
          <lb/>carried out of the body. Worms, and their nidus <pb xml:id="page_23" n="24"/>
          <lb/>are expelled. In this manner the ſeeds of diſeaſe <lb/>will be prevented in the
          chyliferous veſſels; and the <lb/>Chyle itſelf being highly elaborated, and, withal,
          <lb/>diluted with the Water, enters the lacteals, poſſeſ- <lb/>ſing ſuch qualities and
          powers, as bid fair to obvi- <lb/>ate, and remove obſtructions which have taken place
          <lb/>in the channels of the chyle and lymph. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Hence</hi>, obſtructions in the meſentery and glands <lb/>will
          gradually be reſolved, as this Water will be like- <lb/>ly to dilute and diſſolve any
          tenacious matter, inca- <lb/>pable of moving in the chyliferous veſſels, on account
          <lb/>of its glutinous, cheeſe-like, and, ſteatomatous con- <lb/>ſiſtence, and, will
          ſtimulate the veſſels, and, me- <lb/>ſenteric glands, by its Saline contents, ſo as to en-
          <lb/>able them to puſh on any obſtructing matter. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Some</hi> portion of the Waters, being abſorbed, <lb/>will act as a
          powerful deobſtruent in obſtructions of <lb/>the liver. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">By</hi> thinning the Hepatic bile, and, carrying that <lb/>fluid
          regularly into the inteſtines. By preventing <lb/>the ſtagnation of bile in the
          gall-bladder. By gently <lb/>ſtimulating the biliary veſſels, and encreaſing their
          <lb/>action. In a word, by the united inſluence of theſe <lb/>powers, recent obſtructions,
          or older ſcirrhoſities, <lb/>which have taken place either at home, or by reſi- <lb/>dence
          in warm climates, will be remodied. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Calculous</hi> concretions in the biliary ducts, and, <lb/>in the
          gall-bladder, when of a ſize capable of being <pb xml:id="page_24" n="25"/>
          <lb/>carried into the inteſtines, will be diſpoſed to be mo- <lb/>ved thither, by that
          ſtimulus, which acting originally <lb/>on the duodenum, will extend its influence along
          <lb/>the Ductus Choledochus. In like manner, new <lb/>concretions of the biliary kind,
          will be effectually <lb/>prevented. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>So that this Water will be found a very effectual <lb/>remedy for jaundice ariſing
          from gall-ſtones, as well <lb/>as from other cauſes, obſtructing the diſcharge of the
          <lb/>bile into the inteſtines. It will alſo be found uſeful <lb/>in removing obſtructions
          in the ſubſtance of the Li- <lb/>ver; and, in preventing hemmorrhoidal, and other
          <lb/>diſcharges of blood, which moſt frequently originate <lb/>from obſtructions in the
          Liver. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Hemmorrhoidal</hi> ſwellings, and diſcharges of <lb/>blood from other
          cauſes, obſtructing, or retarding its <lb/>motion, and, return through the branches of the
          <lb/>vena portarum, will be eaſed or relieved by a ſeaſo- <lb/>nable uſe of this Water. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> ſoftneſs, which is peculiar to this Water, <lb/>renders it
          proper in diſeaſes of the urinary paſſages; <lb/>as it acts powerfully on the Kidneys, and
          occaſions <lb/>an encreaſed ſecretion there, as well as in the inteſti- <lb/>nal tube;
          gravelly concretions will be prevented or <lb/>waſhed away. As the ſecretion of urine is
          in expe- <lb/>rience, ſound eſſential, for carrying out of the body, <lb/>the Salts and
          Oils, which are prejudicial to health; <lb/>purity of blood will be very greatly promoted
          by the <lb/>encreaſe of this ſecretion; ſo that by the free diſ- <pb xml:id="page_25"
            n="26"/>
          <lb/>charge from this emunctory, along with that from <lb/>the alimentary canal, the ſkin
          will be cleanſed from <lb/>hot red eruptions, and, from ſcaly, and ſcabby in-
          <lb/>cruſtations, which notoriouſly ariſe from a blood, <lb/>and habit overloaded with
          acrid, and impure matter; <lb/>when by exceſs in diet, or by improper food, by im-
          <lb/>perfect digeſtion, or inadequate ſecretion and excre- <lb/>tion, ſuch acrid corrupt
          matter is formed, and <lb/>retained in our bodies. Gentle evacuation, by the <lb/>uſe of
          ſuch Waters, is generally a certain relief under <lb/>theſe circumſtances; this has been
          experienced <lb/>by various perſons, but very remarkably by one <lb/><hi rend="sc"
            >Tanner</hi> from <hi rend="italic">Kidderminſter,</hi> who has had a leprous
          <lb/>eruption removed from his face, and other parts, by <lb/>drinking the Walton Water,
          and, applying it ex- <lb/>ternally; which relief, for ſix years paſt, he had <lb/>not
          obtained by any means whatever. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> preſerving the bile in a fluid ſtate, and, the <lb/>regular
          conveyance of it into the duodenum, will <lb/>powerfully operate in compleating the
          digeſtion, and <lb/>Chylification of the food; and, will give the blood <lb/>thoſe
          properties, which ſupport the health, and, <lb/>vigour of the body.—With that, all
          cutaneous ſoul- <lb/>ness will diſappear, and, the bloom of beauty re-aſ- <lb/>ſume its
          charms, along with the eaſe, and cheerful- <lb/>ness inſeparable from wholeſome ſluids,
          and, from <lb/>good health. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">By</hi> removing the ſomes, which cauſes Scurvies, <lb/>Scrophulous,
          Herpetic eruptions, Leproſies, and, <pb xml:id="page_26" n="27"/>
          <lb/>every kind of cutaneous ſoulneſs, whether of the <lb/>red, and pimply, or the ſcaly,
          and, ulcerous kinds; <lb/>I ſay, by gradually draining off this fomes, and,
          <lb/>ſoliciting its exit from the emunctories, ſuch foul- <lb/>neſſes of the ſkin,
          accompanied with itchings, ſores, <lb/>and, even ſcirrhous, and, cancerous taints, will
          <lb/>often be prevented, removed or palliated. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Chronic</hi> weakneſs, and, dejection of ſpirits, <lb/>ariſing
          frequently from the ſame latent ſources, will <lb/>receive relief from the ſalutary,
          though ſlow opera- <lb/>tion of theſe Waters. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Obstructions</hi> in the uterine ſyſtem, ſuppreſ- <lb/>ſions of the
          menſtrual diſcharge, and, other irregu- <lb/>larities, and, exceſſes peculiar to it; the
          fluor albus, <lb/>ſcirrhous tumours, and other diſeaſes of the womb, <lb/>will in many
          circumſtances and conſtitutions, find <lb/>a uſeful remedy in the Walton Water. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Obstructions</hi> left by the long continuance, and, <lb/>the frequent
          return of intermittent fevers, will, <lb/>probably, yield to a prudent uſe of theſe
          Waters; <lb/>and, they will prepare the patient, and, put him in <lb/>a fit ſtate to
          receive further benefit from the Bark. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Obstructions</hi> in the Lungs, from a ſcorbutic cauſe, <lb/>and, acrid
          humours in the blood, and inve- <lb/>terate ophthalmia's, have been relieved, and, are
          <lb/>likely to be ſucceſſfully treated by the Walton <lb/>Water. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">shall</hi> not give many directions concerning the <pb
            xml:id="page_27" n="28"/>
          <lb/>uſe of this Water, profeſſedly ſimilar to that of <lb/>Cheltenham, the method of
          drinking, of which, <lb/>has been long aſcertained by eſtabliſhed uſage, and, <lb/>the
          public is poſſeſſed of the directions of eminent, <lb/>and, able practitioners explanatory
          of their expe- <lb/>rience, in this point. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> Summer Months are the ſeaſon to drink the <lb/>Walton Waters;
          as they will, in theſe months, and, <lb/>in dry weather be in their moſt perfect ſtate of
          im- <lb/>pregnation. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Like</hi> Cheltenham, the Walton Waters are their <lb/>own preparative;
          three quarters of a pint, drank at <lb/>the Pump, may be taken in the morning, and after-
          <lb/>noon, this quantity may be encreaſed to three half- <lb/>pints afterwards, if the
          former quantity does not <lb/>ſufficiently open the body. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> I would obſerve, that the middle doſes, ſuch <lb/>as merely
          preſerve the body in a lax ſtate, not ex- <lb/>ceeding three ſtools daily, are preferable
          to larger <lb/>doſes, and to greater evacuation; the buſineſs and <lb/>intention, being to
          carry off the ill-digeſted remains <lb/>of meals, perhaps of exceſs, and of luxury, and,
          of <lb/>all kinds of corrupt recrementitious matter lodged in <lb/>the alimentary canal,
          without impairing ſtrength and <lb/>digeſtion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Early</hi> hours are neceſſary to an advantageous uſe <lb/>of the
          Waters at the Well, where only they are <lb/>drank without the loſs of the active Volatile
          ingredi- <pb xml:id="page_28" n="29"/>
          <lb/>ents, which give power to thoſe that are more fixed, <lb/>to penetrate into the
          glands, and ſmalleſt veſſels. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Exercise</hi> ſub dio, is alſo equally proper to ſe- <lb/>cond the
          operation of the Water, and to ſtrengthen <lb/>the body. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">An</hi> eaſy digeſted nutrient diet, conſiſting, when <lb/>it agrees
          with the ſtomach, of milk in the morning <lb/>and at night, of light meats and vegetables
          at dinner, <lb/>with general temperance, and moderation in the uſe <lb/>of vinous liquors,
          rather than total abſtinence from them, <lb/>is highly expedient. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> a ſituation, where excellent fiſh is ſo plentiful, <lb/>it is
          proper to obſerve, that moderation in this article <lb/>will be prudent, as a very
          frequent uſe of fiſh is <lb/>found often prejudicial in diſcaſes of the ſkin, and,
          <lb/>ſometimes produces the more obſtinate diſeaſes of <lb/>that claſs; diſeaſes, for
          which theſe Waters are pe- <lb/>culiarly proper. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is almoſt ſuperfluous to add, that, however <lb/>uſeful it may
          be to entertain the mind with pleaſing <lb/>ſociety, and, an agreeable ſucceſſion of
          amuſements, <lb/>it is always neceſſary to retire to reſt at an early hour, <lb/>and,
          before eleven o'clock at fartheſt to be in bed, <lb/>that the conſtitution may have the
          advantage of <lb/>nature's ſweet reſtorer, balmy ſleep. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> the cutaneous diſeaſes, and, many of the af- <lb/>fections of
          the glands, for which the internal uſe of <lb/>theſe Waters is proper; Baths of different
          degrees of <pb xml:id="page_29" n="30"/>
          <lb/>heat from that of common cold Water, to that of one <lb/>hundred degrees of
          Fahrenheit's ſcale, will be highly <lb/>expedient; this will appear in a ſtronger light,
          from <lb/>what I ſhall offer concerning the ſunctions, and diſ- <lb/>eaſes of the
          lymphatic glands. I apprehend, the <lb/>diſeaſes of theſe glands, are chiefly to be
          reached by <lb/>the means of remedies, which are applied, ſo as to <lb/>be abſorbed by the
          lymphatic veſſels, which paſs to <lb/>the glands. I am confident, that the moſt obſtinate
          <lb/>cutaneous, and glandular diſeaſes would yield to a <lb/>due perſeverance in the
          external and internal uſe of <lb/>Waters and other proper remedies. But what theſe
          <lb/>remedies are, and, alſo the uſe, whether external or <lb/>internal of Mineral Waters,
          and of Medicines of all <lb/>kinds, which are to produce any important and ſalu- <lb/>tary
          conſequence, can only be determined in parti- <lb/>cular caſes, and conſtitutions, by the
          judgment of <lb/>an able, and experienced phyſician. </p>
      </div>
      <div rend="indent">
        <pb xml:id="page_30"/>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/><hi rend="size(1.75)">THOUGHTS</hi>
          <lb/>ON THE <lb/><hi rend="italic size(1.25)">FUNCTIONS</hi> AND <hi
            rend="size(1.25) italic">DISEASES</hi>
          <lb/>OF THE <lb/><hi rend="size(1.75)">LYMPHATIC GLANDS</hi>. </head>
        <pb xml:id="page_31" n="1"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>THE uſe of Mineral Waters in diſeaſes of the <lb/>glands, leads me to offer ſome
          thoughts, which, I <lb/>believe, are either new, or have not been enough <lb/>attended to,
          concerning the uſe, and diſeaſes of the <lb/>lymphatic glands. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> lymphatic ſyſtem, which makes an impor- <lb/>tant article in
          the anatomical diſcoveries of the laſt <lb/>century, has received much improvement in
          this. <lb/>It is not my buſineſs to aſſign to each improver or <lb/>diſcoverer, his due
          proportion of merit. I acknow- <lb/>ledge my obligations to them all. To Haller, Meckel,
          <lb/>Monro, Mr. Hewſon, Dr. William Hunter, and <lb/>Mr. John Hunter, Mr. Sheldon, and Mr.
          Cruik- <lb/>ſhank; who have all contributed, and, ſome of <lb/>them very ſplendidly, to
          perfect the knowledge of <lb/>this important part of the animal ſyſtem; and, let <lb/>them
          not deem it amiſs, that profiting by their labours, <lb/>I endeavour to make them
          ſubſervient to the know- <lb/>ledge of the animal oeconomy, and to the healing <lb/>art. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_32" n="2"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">That</hi> the lymphatic veſſels ariſe from every viſ- <lb/>cus, and,
          from every cavity in the body, as <lb/>well as from the ſkin, and the cellular membrane
          inveſting <lb/>the body, in prodigious, and till lately, in undiſco- <lb/>vered numbers,
          is an anatomical truth of the greateſt <lb/>importance, now clearly demonſtrated, and
          univer- <lb/>ſally acknowledged. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> lymphatic veſſels, and lacteals are of the ſame <lb/>kind,
          and, conſtitute a ſyſtem of veſſels, no where <lb/>connected with the veins, containing
          red blood; but, <lb/>which univerſally terminate in the lacteal ſac and <lb/>duct, and
          convey chyle, and lymph collected in <lb/>every part into the ſubclaviam vein, where it
          mixes <lb/>with the blood, and no where elſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi>, ſole and excluſive function of this ſyſtem of <lb/>veſſels is
          abſorption. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Some</hi>, indeed, have held, that the red veins are <lb/>ſupplementary
          abſorbents, eſpecially on ſome occa- <lb/>ſions; and the illuſtrious Walther and others,
          with <lb/>ſome probability, have aſſigned this office to the ve- <lb/>na portarum,
          eſpecially in diſeaſes, in which the <lb/>conglobate glands of the meſentery are
          ſcirrhous, or obliterated by age, as ſome have ſuppoſed, or, the <lb/>lacteal ſac, and
          duct itſelf is obſtructed. The proofs <lb/>of this are equivocal, and accounted for on
          different <lb/>principles, by the ſchool of Hunter, particularly, by <lb/>that accurate
          anatomiſt, Mr. John Hunter, who <lb/>firſt diſcovered that abſorption is carried on by
          <lb/>the lymphatic veſſels alone. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_33" n="3"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> lacteal, and lymphatic veſſels univerſally <lb/>paſs through
          conglobate glands, before the fluid they <lb/>convey, reaches the lacteal duct; thoſe
          ariſing from <lb/>the inteſtines, enter the different orders of meſen- <lb/>teric glands,
          and, the chyle and lymph depoſited in <lb/>theſe glands, is again abſorbed from them by
          the <lb/>vaſa lymphatica efferentia, in order to be conveyed <lb/>to the thoracic duct.
            <note place="bottom" n="(d)" rend="size(0.5)">(d) Cruikſhank paſſim. p. 76. </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> law is univerſal, and, the lymphatic veins <lb/>wherever they
          ariſe, in no inſtance enter into the <lb/>lacteal duct, without previouſly, and repeatedly
          <lb/>throwing the lymph into the conglobate glands, <lb/>which are an eſſential part of
          this ſyſtem, a part of <lb/>the greateſt importance, for the advantage of which, <lb/>the
          lymph is abſorbed, in order to be conveyed to <lb/>them; and from them the lymph is taken
          up in a <lb/>more purified, and aſſimilated ſtate, and is conveyed <lb/>by the lymphatica
          efferentia into the lacteal ſac and <lb/>duct. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> ſtructure of theſe glands is both vaſcular and <lb/>cellular;
          into theſe cells the lymph is thrown, and <lb/>the abſorbing lymphatics, the lymphatica
          efferentia, <lb/>are the only excretories, to all the conglobate glands; <lb/>the uſes of
          which are acknowledged to be unknown <lb/>and undiſcovered, by gentlemen to whom
          anatomiſts <lb/>are ſo much indebted, Meſſrs. Sheldon and Cruik- <lb/>ſhank, the lateſt
          improvers of the lymphatic ſyſtem. <note place="bottom" n="(e)" rend="size(0.5)">
            <lb/>(e) The ingenious diſcoverers, who have lately ſo much im- <lb/>proved the
            knowledge of the lymphatic ſyſtem, all acknowledge <lb/>their ignorance of the uſe of
            theſe glands. Mr. Cruikſhank, the <lb/>lateſt publiſher on this ſubject, ſays, <q
              rend="quotes">Though we know ſome- <lb/>thing more of the nature, ſtructure and
              diſeaſes, of the lym- <lb/>phatic glands, we know no more of their real uſe than the
              <lb/>ancients. As they inform us, however, of the paſſage of in- <lb/>fections matter
              into the blood; and as from their ſtate, we are <lb/>enabled to judge of the preſence
              or abſence, of other diſeaſes <lb/>the knowledge of them is of great importance, in
              the practice <lb/>of medicine. </q>
            <hi rend="sc">Anatomy of the absorbing Vessels <lb/>of the Human Body</hi>, p. 68, 69.
              <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>"Why the lymphatic's and lacteals terminate firſt in the <lb/>glands. I do not
              know." p. 18. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>
              <q rend="quotes">It will appear ſtrange, that I have ſaid nothing of the uſe of
                <lb/>the abſorbent glands. I avow abſolute ignorance of this mat- <lb/>ter. There
                are none in turtle and in fiſh, and, only two in <lb/>the necks of ſome birds. Why
                there are ſo many in men, and <lb/>quadrupeds, I do not know, nor why they exiſt at
                all. </q> p. <lb/>187, &amp;c. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Once for all, I beg leave to expreſs my opinion of the work <lb/>now quoted, as
              one of the moſt valuable and important acquiſi- <lb/>tions, both to anatomy and
              medicine, this age has produced. </p>
          </note>
        </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_34" n="4"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Yet</hi> it is a matter not only intereſting in the ſci- <lb/>ence of
          phyſiology, to aſcertain their uſe, but is like- <lb/>wiſe neceſſary to enable us to
          underſtand more per- <lb/>fectly the diſeaſes of the glands, and, to treat them <lb/>with
          ſucceſs: we will therefore purſue the enquiry. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A <hi rend="sc">fluid</hi> is conſtantly exhaled into the cavities <lb/>containing
          the viſcera; this fluid is liable to be altered, <lb/>either by remora or mixture; the
          abſorption of this <lb/>fluid is the function of the internal lymphatics, and, <lb/>when
          it is prevented, either by obſtruction of the <lb/>conglobate glands, or, by any other
          cauſe; Dropſies <lb/>in the brain, thorax, pericardium, abdomen, and <lb/>the widely
          diffuſed cellular membrane, ariſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> lymph along with the chyle, and nutritious <lb/>liquors
          prepared from the food in the inteſtinal <pb xml:id="page_35" n="5"/>
          <lb/>canal, is abſorbed by the lacteal and lymphatic veſſels, <lb/>for they are the ſame;
          theſe fluids are immediately <lb/>thrown into the meſenteric glands; and, they are
          <lb/>more numerous there than in other parts, becauſe <lb/>their office is peculiarly
          important, that of perfecting <lb/>the chyle or nutritious fluid, extracted by digeſtion
          <lb/>from food. That fluid is perfected by intercepting <lb/>what is noxious in the cells
          of the conglobate glands, <lb/>where it undergoes a digeſtion before it is abſorbed
          <lb/>by the ſecond and third orders of the lacteal veſſels. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Numerous</hi> lymphatic veſſels, ariſe alſo from the <lb/>ſtomach,
          inteſtines, and from the glandular viſcera; <lb/>from the pelvis, the bladder, and parts
          of genera- <lb/>tion, both in males and females; they obſerve the <lb/>ſame law, and paſs
          through the iliac conglobate <lb/>glands, or others before they enter the lacteal ſac;
          <lb/>and, their uſe is the ſame, to intercept crude, nox- <lb/>ious, unaſſimilated matter,
          which has been ren- <lb/>dered unfit by diſeaſe, or other means to mix imme- <lb/>diately,
          and unaltered, with the blood. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> food we take in, and the air we breathe, <lb/>while they
          convey the neceſſary ſupports of life, <lb/>contain alſo the feeds of diſeaſe and death. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> lymphatic veſſels, which ariſe in the mouth, <lb/>and, from
          the trachea and lungs, (where their num- <lb/>ber is immenſe), convey the fluids they
          abſorb, with <lb/>whatever extraneous matter has been taken up to the <lb/>numerous
          conglobate glands of the neck, to the thy- <lb/>roid gland, thymus, and the glands of the
          lungs, <pb xml:id="page_36" n="6"/>
          <lb/>where it is digeſted before it reaches the thoracic <lb/>duct. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> young animals who take in their food by ſuc- <lb/>tion, in
          which action much is abſorbed by the lym- <lb/>phatics; the glands are very large,
          numerous and <lb/>conſpicuous, the more perfectly to digeſt, and anima- <lb/>liſe the
          crude fluids received by ſuction, with the <lb/>milk. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">When</hi> that period of life is paſſed over, the thy- <lb/>roid glands
          and thymus are not quite ſo neceſſary, <lb/>and abate in ſize, but are never totally
          obliterated. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> pointing out the buſineſs of purifying, and <lb/>animaliſing
          lymph, as the function, of the conglo- <lb/>bate glands in general, I believe I have
          diſcovered <lb/>the uſe of the thymus in infants, and, of the thy- <lb/>roid glands,
          hitherto one of the hidden myſteries <lb/>in anatomy. <note place="bottom" n="(f)"
            rend="size(0.5)">(f) Cruikſhank, ſpeaking of the Thymus, ſays, "I know not <lb/>the uſe
            of this gland;<q rend="quotes"> and of the Thyroid gland, </q>as I have not <lb/>the
            leaſt conception of its uſe, I do not underſtand what functions <lb/>in particular its
            abſorbents perform," p. 183. </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> external ſurface of the body, is no leſs ab- <lb/>ſorptive,
          fluids are imbibed, thirſt abated, urine and <lb/>weight encreaſed from thence. Garlick,
          externally <lb/>applied is ſoon ſmelled in the breath. Turpentine <lb/>gives the urine a
          violet ſmell. Variolous matter, <lb/>and the venereal poiſon introduced by the ſmalleſt
          <lb/>puncture, produce ſimilar diſeaſes, and, previous to <lb/>univerſal infection and
          diffuſion, the inguinal and <lb/>axillary glands, are ſwelled and inflamed by the paſ-
          <lb/>ſage of the poiſon into them. Mercury, the anti- <pb xml:id="page_37" n="7"/>
          <lb/>dote to this poiſon, alſo enters freely by the ſkin. <lb/>Bliſters applied to the
          arms and ſhoulders inflame <lb/>the axillary glands; thoſe of the neck in children,
          <lb/>particularly are made hard and ſore by ulcers behind <lb/>the ears, and in the head,
          and, by bliſters to thoſe <lb/>parts. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Ulcers</hi> and punctures in the legs, and other <lb/>parts, often
          occaſion ſwellings along the lymphatics <lb/>up to, the axillæ, or inguinal glands.
          Purulent <lb/>bubos ariſe frequently from ſuch ulcers, and, from <lb/>matter formed in the
          joints. The axillary glands are <lb/>ſwelled by ſtagnating milk, by cancerous ſwellings,
          <lb/>and inflammations in the breaſt. Cancers in the lips <lb/>and on the face, cauſe
          ſimilar ſwellings under the <lb/>lower jaw, and, in the neck. The ſame glands are
          <lb/>ſwelled by gum boils, and by venereal ſores in the <lb/>lips. Acrid matter abſorbed,
          inflames the lympha- <lb/>tic veſſel, and, the gland, univerſally, between the <lb/>ſeat
          of the matter and ſore, and, the thoracic duct; <lb/>and, its entrance into the body, may
          be prevented <lb/>by cauſtic, or, by the exciſion of the part. Pow- <lb/>ders ſcattered
          over the ſurface of the body are abſor- <lb/>bed, thus calomel is known to enter; and, I
          remem- <lb/>ber a degree of ſalivation, and ſore mouth, produced <lb/>by a ſmall quantity
          of corroſive ſublimate, rubbed <lb/>with crude ſal armoniac and camphire ſcattered on
          <lb/>bed linen, in order to prevent a morbus pediculoſus. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">When</hi> we conſider theſe various facts, that all <lb/>lymphatic
          veſſels perpetually enter the conglobate <pb xml:id="page_38" n="8"/>
          <lb/>glands, and, in the cells, of which theſe glands uni- <lb/>verſally conſiſt, depoſite
          the lymph, which being <lb/>abſorbed once, and, again by larger lymphatics, is <lb/>at
          length conveyed by the great channel, the lacteal <lb/>duct, into the vena cava
          deſcendens, under the left <lb/>calavicle. When we recollect, that the Venereal
          <lb/>Virus, Cancerous and Variolous poiſons, enter the <lb/>body by theſe channels, and,
          and are primarily de- <lb/>poſited in theſe glands, occaſioning there tumours,
          <lb/>ſometimes indolent, ſometimes painful, inflamed and <lb/>ſuppurating. It ſeems clear,
          theſe glands are intend- <lb/>ed by nature, to purify the lymph, before it enters the
          <lb/>blood veſſels, from matter, which may be noxious <lb/>there, by arreſting it in the
          glands, univerſally con- <lb/>nected with abſorbents. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> theſe glands, it is either altered by a concoc- <lb/>ting, and
          digeſting power inherent in them, or when <lb/>it is too noxious to be ſubdued into a
          ſalutary nature <lb/>it remains in the form of a tumour, or eſcapes by <lb/>ſuppuration.
          When it cannot be ſubdued, nor re- <lb/>moved by ſuppuration, and, thoſe ſalutary efforts
          of <lb/>nature fail, it is then abſorbed, and, diffuſes diſeaſe <lb/>in the conſtitution
          at large. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Thus</hi> the glands in the neck, and the thyroid are <lb/>interpoſed
          to intercept crude matter, or noxious Vi- <lb/>rus taken up from the noſtrils, mouth,
          trachea <lb/>and lungs, and other parts about the neck and breaſt, <lb/>more eſpecially in
          very young animals. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> meſenteric glands purify, and digeſt, what- <pb
            xml:id="page_39" n="9"/>
          <lb/>ever is abſorbed with the lymph and chyle from <lb/>the inteſtines. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> axillary, and inguinal glands, alter and in- <lb/>tercept
          whatever extraneous matter may happen to <lb/>be abſorbed from the ſurface of the body, or
          the cel- <lb/>lular membrane. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> glands have the power of aſſimilating into <lb/>a ſound fluid,
          ſuch noxious matter, in very many <lb/>inſtances. But when it is highly virulent as in the
          <lb/>lues, in ſcrophulous, and in cancerous diſeaſes, that <lb/>digeſting and aſſimilating
          function is overpowered, <lb/>the gland remains ſcirrhous, or, is deſtroyed by ſup-
          <lb/>puration, and, the matter enters, and contaminates <lb/>the habit. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> fine, the uſe of theſe glands is to intercept as <lb/>ſponges,
          and to alter as digeſtive organs, whatever <lb/>is unfit to enter into the maſs of blood.
          In ordinary <lb/>caſes, this is effected without obſtruction, or, inflam- <lb/>mation,
          and, then no apparent conſequences detri- <lb/>mental to health appear, and, the depoſited
          matter <lb/>is abſorbed again, and, goes along with the ſound <lb/>lymph. In extraordinary
          caſes, the poiſon remains <lb/>in the gland, and, deſtroys its powers firſt, and its
          <lb/>ſubſtance, and organization afterwards. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> fatal conſequences, which have followed in- <lb/>jections of
          undigeſted alimentary fluids, directly into <lb/>the red veins of living animals, are
          proofs that the <lb/>lymphatic glands have the uſe and function here <pb xml:id="page_40"
            n="10"/>
          <lb/>alledged, and, ſhow, that without the <hi rend="italic">lymphatic digeſ-
            <lb/>tion,</hi> liquors apparently harmleſs, are unfit to mix <lb/>with the blood; and,
          produce fatal effects there. <note place="bottom" n="(g)" rend="size(0.5)">(g) Haller,
            Elem. Phys. Tom. 1. p. 228. </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">How</hi> the glands alter, digeſt, and aſſimilate the <lb/>matter
          abſorbed, and depoſited in them, I know not, <lb/>and ſhall not attempt to explain; I
          think that power <lb/>implanted in them, as well as in the ſtomach and <lb/>inteſtines;
          and, we ſee an important apparatus, ſet <lb/>apart for the purpoſe, by Him! whoſe ability
          is too <lb/>great, in every inſtance to be fully comprehended, <lb/>and interpreted by us
          his creatures. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">From</hi> the uſes here aſcribed to the lymphatic <lb/>glands we ſee,
          why they are moſt numerous, where <lb/>abſorption is greateſt; and, particularly in thoſe
          <lb/>parts, where crude matter is abſorbed. We ſee, <lb/>why the glands are nearly as
          numerous in the neck <lb/>as in the meſentery <note place="bottom" n="(h)"
            rend="size(0.5)">(h) P. 130. </note>; for beſide the matter abſor- <lb/>bed from the
          inſide of the mouth, noſtrils, and <lb/>trachea; the abſorbents from the brain join the
          <lb/>glands of the neck. Though theſe have not been <lb/>traced by anatomiſts; as a
          copious exhalation, and, <lb/>abſorption conſtantly take place in the ventricles of
          <lb/>that organ; as we have reaſon to believe, the Water <lb/>in the internal
          hydrocephalus is ſometimes abſorbed; <lb/>from the general law, we may preſume, that lym-
          <lb/>phatics exiſt in the brain, though not certainly <lb/>traced there <note
            place="bottom" n="(i)" rend="size(0.5)">(i) P. 127, Cruikſhank. </note>; this is
          confirmed by the internal <pb xml:id="page_41" n="11"/>
          <lb/>cephalus often happening in ſcrophulous and ricketty <lb/>children, in whom the
          glands of the neck are ſcirr- <lb/>hous. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is well known, that ſwellings of the glands of- <lb/>ten follow
          cruptive diſeaſes. They ariſe after ſcar- <lb/>let fever, meaſles and ſmall pox. Dropſy,
          is ſome- <lb/>times the conſequence of them all. And I have <lb/>known the hydrocephalus
          internus, as well as other <lb/>Dropſies ſucceed the ſcarlet fever; another preſump-
          <lb/>tive proof, that abſorption in the brain, is carried <lb/>on by lymphatic veſſels, as
          well as in other parts. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">We</hi> alſo, ſee why the glands are more numerous <lb/>in the
          meſentery, through which all the chyle paſſes <lb/>and are ſmaller, and leſs numerous in
          the meſocolon, <lb/>through which hardly any chyle paſſes, whence Mr. <lb/>Cruikſhank is
          led to ſay, "this looks as if the glands <lb/>were intended to produce ſome remarkable
          change <lb/>in the chyle" <note place="bottom" n="(k)" rend="size(0.5)">(k) P. 127.—of
            Cruikſhank. </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> meſenteric glands, as well as the conglobate <lb/>glands in
          other parts, being cellular, as well as vaſ- <lb/>cular, contain a white milky fluid, moſt
          conſpicuous <lb/>and abundant in young animals. Album perpetuo re- <lb/>peri, ſays,
          Haller, Elem. Phys. T. 1. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">These</hi> glands, though greatly leſs in adults than <lb/>in young
          animals, are yet not totally obliterated. <lb/>The illuſtrious Haller, has ſeen the thymus
          in the me- <lb/>diaſtinum, and the glands in the meſentery, and in <pb xml:id="page_42"
            n="12"/>
          <lb/>the inteſtinum rectum in adults; in children, they <lb/>are very large and ſucculent,
          Elem. Phys. T. 1. p. 192. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> lymphatic veſſels being deſtitute of the mo- <lb/>ving impulſe
          of the heart, and having no other prin- <lb/>ciple of motion to carry on the liquors
          abſorbed, but <lb/>that of the irritability of the lymphatic ſyſtem, the <lb/>motion of
          the lymph is neceſſarily liable to be ob- <lb/>ſtructed. Hence obſtructions happen more
          fre- <lb/>quently in the conglobate and lymphatic glands, <lb/>than in the conglomerate
          glands. The liver may be <lb/>excepted, becauſe the blood conveyed into it by the
          <lb/>vena portarum, undergoes a ſimilar retardation in <lb/>that very ſingular vein. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> conglobate glands, are hence univerſally lia- <lb/>ble to
          ſcirrhoſity and obſtruction. The meſenteric <lb/>glands are notoriouſly liable to great
          enlargement and <lb/>hardneſs, and thereby often cauſe a ſlow conſuming <lb/>ſever and
          atrophy in infants. Similar ſwellings in the <lb/>meſenteric glands are ſometimes obſerved
          from <lb/>ulcerated inteſtines after dyſentery. The neck is ſel- <lb/>dom ſtrumous without
          accompanying obſtructions in <lb/>the meſenteric glands. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> thyroid axillary and mammary glands, as <lb/>well as the iliac
          lumbar and inguinal glands are all <lb/>frequently ſound obſtructed and ſcirrhous. In a
          <lb/>word theſe glands are not only obſtructed in venereal <lb/>and cancerous habits; but
          the ſcrophula and rachitis <lb/>likewiſe originate in them, and are principally ſeated
          <lb/>in the glands. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_43" n="13"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> all caſes of obſtructed glands, the chyle and <lb/>lymph, being
          imperfectly aſſimilated, the blood be- <lb/>comes gradually vitiated, and, unfit for
          nouriſhment. <lb/>Hence that acrimony often called ſcorbutic; an ul- <lb/>cerous and even
          cancerous diſpoſition of fluids origi- <lb/>nate. From the ſame ſource the bones become
          brit- <lb/>tle, break in ſome, and are rendered ſoft and flexible <lb/>in others. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">All</hi> theſe facts conſpire to ſhew the importance <lb/>of the
          digeſtive, and aſſimilating power of the <lb/>glands, and, lymphatic ſyſtem, in perfecting
          the <lb/>animal fluids. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> diſeaſed glands, the chyle is not ſufficiently
          <lb/>aſſimilated, and, that defect gradually induces acri- <lb/>mony, and impurity in the
          lymph, which ſoon taints <lb/>the blood and habit univerſally. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is more from this defect, than from the en- <lb/>trance of the
          chyle into the blood, being prevented <lb/>by obſtruction, that maraſmus, and conſumption
          <lb/>follow ſcirrhoſities in the meſentric glands. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>
          <q rend="quotes">It is poſſible, </q> ſays, the ingenious Cruikſhank, <lb/>
          <q rend="quotes">that children, and, even grown perſons, may have <lb/>died of the tabes
            meſenterica from obſtructions in <lb/>the glands, rendering them impervious to the
            <lb/>chyle. </q> But he never ſaw any ſuch ſtagnation of <lb/>chyle, as theſe are
          ſuppoſed to cauſe, on any occa- <lb/>ſion whatever. <note place="bottom" n="(l)"
            rend="size(0.5)">(l) P. 107, Cruikſhank. </note>
        </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_44" n="14"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> lymph, and chyle, enter the blood but in a <lb/>corrupted,
          crude, unanimaliſed ſtate. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">am</hi> confirmed in this opinion, by the experi- <lb/>ments of
          another excellent Anatomiſt, Mr. Sheldon, <lb/>which I ſhall quote from his ſplendid
          Hiſtory of the <lb/>Human Lacteal Veſſels. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> ſubjects, in which the lymphatic glands of the <lb/>meſentery,
          were found entirely obſtructed, ſometimes <lb/>by a curd-like ſubſtance, ſometimes by
          calcareous <lb/>earth, Mr. Sheldon, could puſh injections of quick- <lb/>ſilver from the
          veſſels, below the obſtructed glands, <lb/>to thoſe above them, though not a ſingle
          particle of <lb/>quickſilver, could be made to enter the glands in this <lb/>obſtructed
          ſtate. In this caſe, the collateral branches <lb/>of the lacteal veſſels, which
          communicated with <lb/>thoſe above, were enlarged, and, had conveyed the <lb/>chyle into
          the lacteal duct. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> ingenious Dr. Cheſton, found the cavity of <lb/>the lacteal
          duct totally obſtructed for a conſiderable <lb/>length, by an earthy matter, in a man who
          had a <lb/>Spina Ventoſa of the os ilium. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is probable, the chyle, in this caſe, was con- <lb/>veyed from
          below, into the lacteal duct, above the <lb/>obſtruction, by one or more collateral
          anaſtomoſing <lb/>branches, which are every where numerous in the <lb/>lymphatic veſſels,
          and, frequent in the lacteal duct <lb/>itſelf. This being a proviſion of nature, for
          ſecuring <lb/>more certainly, a regular conveyance of the chyle in- <lb/>to the blood
          veſſels. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_45" n="15"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I remember a melancholy caſe, which ſhews <lb/>the thoracic duct, ſometimes is
          obſtructed in a fatal <lb/>degree; a young lady, high in rank, beautiful in <lb/>perſon,
          and amiable in diſpoſition; had a ſwelling <lb/>in the neck, which extended itſelf under
          the left cla- <lb/>vicle, and there obſtructed the entrance of the tho- <lb/>racic duct
          into the ſubclavian vein ſo completely, <lb/>as to render her incurably dropſical in every
          part of <lb/>her body. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">What</hi> I have now offered, concerning the uſe of <lb/>the glands,
          belonging to the lymphatic ſyſtem, will, <lb/>I apprehend, derive ſupport from the late
          diſcove- <lb/>ries, and will be found uſeful in the treatment of diſ- <lb/>eaſes of the
          glands. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Medicines</hi> taken into the ſtomach, and mixed <lb/>with the chyle,
          are, indeed, in the direct channel, <lb/>to reach the diſeaſed glands of the meſentery. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> this is not the caſe, reſpecting the conglo- <lb/>bate glands
          in other parts. Medicines mixing with <lb/>the blood never directly reach theſe glands.
          and, but <lb/>very remotely, and indirectly affect them; and, this <lb/>is one of the
          reaſons why, diſeaſes in theſe glands, <lb/>have always appeared ſo ſtubborn, and have ſo
          rare- <lb/>ly yielded to the common treatment, and internal <lb/>uſe of Medicine. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> confiding alone to Medicines, conveyed by <lb/>the lacteals
          into the channel of circulation; the in- <lb/>attention to the only entrance into the
          external diſea- <pb xml:id="page_46" n="16"/>
          <lb/>ſed glands, that by abſorption, are I am perſuaded, <lb/>cauſes why thoſe diſeaſes
          have proved ſo obſtinate, <lb/>and rebellious to Medical treatment. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is the cauſe why ſcrophula, and ſcirhous <lb/>glands, have
          become cancerous, and finally incu- <lb/>rable and fatal. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is evident then, that the remedies proper for <lb/>removing
          obſtructions ſhould be applied to ſuch <lb/>parts, from whence the lymphatics ariſe which
          may <lb/>abſorb and conduct them to the glands, the obſtruc- <lb/>tions of which are to be
          removed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Applications</hi> intended to remove glandular ſwel- <lb/>lings in the
          neck, the thyroid gland, the bronchocele <lb/>&amp;c. muſt be made to the head, neck,
          cheeks, and <lb/>mouth internally, as well as externally. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Vapours</hi> inhaled by inſpiration, are proper in <lb/>the diſeaſed
          glands of the lungs. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Remedies</hi> intended to paſs into the axillary <lb/>glands, muſt be
          applied to the arms and breaſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> diſeaſes of the inguinal glands the remedies <lb/>intended to
          paſs into them, and through them, muſt <lb/>be applied to the genitals, and to the legs
          and thighs. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> advantages found from the local application <lb/>of Mercury in
          Venereal ſwellings of the inguinal, <lb/>and axillary glands, and in ulcers of the throat,
          ex- <lb/>emplify this doctrine in that diſeaſe. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_47" n="17"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> holding Medicines intended to remove the <lb/>bronchocele, and
          ſwelled neck, in the mouth <lb/>and under the tongue, is eſſential to give efficacy to
          <lb/>theſe Medicines, as has been long experienced, in <lb/>the Coventry Medicine. The
          ſaline ingredients, <lb/>whether alcaline, or neutral, of which ſuch Medi- <lb/>cines
          uſually conſiſt, are abſorbed by the lymphatic <lb/>veſſels ariſing in the inſide of the
          mouth, and, are <lb/>conveyed directly to the diſeaſed glands with con- <lb/>ſtant good
          effect. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Internal</hi> obſtructions in the meſentery in parti- <lb/>cular, are
          to be relieved by internal Medicines; and <lb/>in every kind of glandular obſtruction
          Mineral Wa- <lb/>ters have been found highly neceſſary and uſeful. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> Chalybeate, the ſulphureous, the ſaline, the <lb/>hot, and the
          cold Waters, have all been tried with <lb/>advantage. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Of</hi> laxative Medicines, the purgative Mineral <lb/>Waters, always
          operate with the leaſt diminution <lb/>of ſtrength, and with the leaſt diſturbance; the
          ap- <lb/>petite is for the moſt part mended under their uſe, <lb/>and important
          alterations in the whole ſyſtem, ariſe <lb/>from continuing to apply to them. Their
          operation <lb/>principally affects the firſt paſſages in clearing away <lb/>what is
          recrimentitious, and hurtful in that ſeat and <lb/>ſource of corruption. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">They</hi> next directly operate on the lacteal veſſels <lb/>and glands;
          they dilute the chyle, and ſtimulate the <pb xml:id="page_48" n="18"/>
          <lb/>lacteals themſelves, which are ſufficiently irritable; <lb/>and remove thereby, both
          the ſource of obſtruction, <lb/>and the obſtructions, which may have taken place, in
          <lb/>the conglobate glands of the meſentery. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> this manner they contribute to the purity, and <lb/>perfection
          of the chyle and lymph, and remove all <lb/>obſtacles, to its perfect digeſtion in the
          inteſtinal ca- <lb/>nal, and in the lacteal veſſels and glands. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Hence</hi> this ſource of tainted fluids being taken <lb/>away from the
          chyle and blood, and no new acrimo- <lb/>nious depoſition falling on the remoter parts of
          the <lb/>body; the lymphatic veſſels and glands, there reaſ- <lb/>ſume their functions,
          and, abſorb and digeſt, what <lb/>was before lodged on the ſkin, and on the adjacent
          <lb/>parts of the ſurface of the body. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Thus</hi>, under the uſe of ſuch Waters, continued <lb/>for a
          ſufficient length of time, depoſitions, eruptions <lb/>and defedations of the ſkin, with
          ulcers and glandu- <lb/>lar ſwellings diſappear. It is thus the Harrowgate,
          <lb/>Cheltenham and Walton Waters prove beneficial. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> Sea Water, acts not only as a powerful in- <lb/>ternal remedy
          in the ſame diſeaſes; but has its effi- <lb/>cacy greatly promoted by bathing; waſhing
          thereby <lb/>away much cutaneous foulneſs, and removing more <lb/>by being directly
          abſorbed into the lymphatic's, and <lb/>conveyed to the diſeaſed glands; at the ſame time,
          <lb/>that a uſeful ſpring and vigour is given to the whole <lb/>conſtitution. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_49" n="19"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">might</hi> illuſtrate the practical importance of theſe
          <lb/>principles by caſes, but this letter being already too <lb/>long, I now commit it to
          your conſideration. To you! <lb/>who joining reading to experience and talents, make
          <lb/>the healing art your ſtudy and delight. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">From</hi> you, my humble but zealous endeavours to <lb/>excite the
          attention of the younger and liberal Gen- <lb/>tlemen of the profeſſion, to improved
          methods of <lb/>curing diſeaſes, are ſure of a candid reception. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As to others whoſe ſole purſuit and ſtudy is gain; </p>
        <lb/>
        <q rend="italic">Quærenda pecunia primum eſt, <lb/>Virtus poſt nummos. </q>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I <hi rend="sc">have</hi> not wrote for them, and have certainly <lb/>no attention to
          expect from them. </p>
        <signed rend="indent hanging">
          <lb/>I am, &amp;c. <lb/><hi rend="italic">JAMES JOHNSTONE.</hi>
        </signed>
        <lb/>
        <dateline rend="size(0.5)"><hi rend="italic">Worceſter,</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">Aug.</hi> 20, <lb/>1787. </dateline>
        <trailer rend="align-center">
          <lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
