<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: A practical display of the philosophical system called
          animal magnetism</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">A practical display of the philosophical system called animal
              magnetism, in which is explained different modes of treating, with some medical
              observations on the diseases of the human body, Which it is peculiarly adapted to
              relieve; Together with The Manner and Reasonableness of Absent Treatment: the Whole
              Calculated to Instruct Every Capacity, in the Rational Principles and Practice, of the
              Misterious Science.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T84443</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T84443"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed in the Year, MDCCXC.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1790</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="2"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="16"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3306914534</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K068860.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: method"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE Science commonly underſtood <lb/>by the Term <hi
            rend="italic">Animal Magnetiſm,</hi>
          <lb/>and which has been ſo long kept out of <lb/>ſight (except to a Few only) is now laid
          <lb/>open for the Information of every En- <lb/>quirer; and I am fully perſuaded, that
          <lb/>any Perſon of an ordinary Capacity, by <lb/>attending to the following Rules, will
          <lb/>be capable of being as uſeful an Operator, <lb/>as thoſe who have obtained it at a
          much <lb/>higher Price; only let him not be diſ- <lb/>couraged in his firſt Attempt; and
          by <lb/>practice he will gain Confidence and Suc- <lb/>cess. </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_3"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>A <lb/>PRACTICAL DISPLAY <lb/><hi rend="size(0.5)">OF THE PHILOSOPHICAL SYSTEM CALLED </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(2)">Animal Magnetiſm</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N order to make this uſeful Science as plain <lb/>as poſſible,
        every thing that has not an im- <lb/>mediate Connection with the practical part of it,
        <lb/>is omitted, that the young Practitioner may not <lb/>be confuſed with the Subject; and
        I am fully per- <lb/>ſuaded, that, by attending to the Directions here <pb xml:id="page_4"
          n="6"/>
        <lb/>given, any one may attain to a ſufficient knowledge <lb/>of the Science to enable him
        to practiſe it for the <lb/>Benefit of himſelf and others, as well as thoſe who <lb/>have
        obtained it at the Price of Twenty or <lb/>Twenty-five Guineas. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In order to treat a Patient with Succeſs, the fol- <lb/>lowing Qualifications are
        eſſentially Neceſſary. </p>
      <list>
        <lb/>
        <item>I. Abſtraction. </item>
        <lb/>
        <item>II. Affection. </item>
        <lb/>
        <item>III. Intention. </item>
        <lb/>
        <item>IV Volition. </item>
      </list>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Abſtraction. Be as much abſtracted as poſſible, <lb/>forget yourſelf and every thing
        around you, and <lb/>take a kind of temporary Poſſeſſion of the Object <lb/>to be treated. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_5" n="7"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Affection. Let your Affection and Benevolence <lb/>go forth towards the Object you are
        about to treat, <lb/>let the whole energy of your Mind be fixed on <lb/>the Patient's
        Relief, and almoſt certain Succeſs <lb/>will enſue. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Intention. Keep up a conſtant Idea of the Com- <lb/>plaint you wiſh to remove, let your
        Intention be <lb/>to adminiſter all the Aſſiſtance in your Power to- <lb/>wards the
        Patient's Recovery; Compaſſion and In- <lb/>tention will contribute much to the Succeſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Volition. The Human Syſtem being poſſeſſed of <lb/>mental Faculties whoſe active Power
        is unknown <lb/>'till it is demonſtrated by practical Operations; <lb/>exert all the
        Volition you are poſſeſſed off, with <lb/>a Determination, if poſſible, to do good to the
          <pb xml:id="page_6" n="8"/>
        <lb/>Object you are treating, and you will often find <lb/>a kind of contacting Senſation,
        effected by the In- <lb/>corporation of Atmoſpheres and the powerful Prin- <lb/>ciples of
        the Science acting upon each Body; and <lb/>the greater the Exertion of thoſe Principles the
        <lb/>more effectual will the Treatment be. </p>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>On the different Modes of Treating. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Several Modes have been practiſed, but I ſhall <lb/>only mention Two, which will be
          quite ſufficient <lb/>for the Purpoſe, one by the Science itſelf, without <lb/>the Uſe of
          the Hands, (for it is a mental Act, <lb/>and the ſtronger the mental Powers the <lb/>more
          efficaicous will the Treatment be.) Here <lb/>abſtract yourſelf, be quite placid and
          ſerene, keep <lb/>up your Intention, and put forth all the Volition <lb/>you are Maſter
          off: By this Means I have ſeen a <lb/>Hand raiſed quite erect that lay paſſive on a Table,
            <pb xml:id="page_7" n="9"/>
          <lb/>without any Action whatever; but let me here <lb/>obſerve, leſt by failing in your
          firſt Attempt, you <lb/>ſhould be diſcouraged, a Perſon who will be faith- <lb/>ful to
          you, that is to ſay, who will make no reſiſt- <lb/>ance, ſhould be choſen, and the more
          delicate the <lb/>Perſon the more eaſily will this Operation be per- <lb/>formed. Whatever
          the Caſe you are about to <lb/>treat may be, be not diſheartened, nor weary, if <lb/>your
          ſanguine Expections ſhould not, at firſt, be <lb/>fully anſwered, but perſevere, make
          repeated <lb/>Trials, the more you practice the greater will be <lb/>your Confidence, and
          the more ſucceſſful your <lb/>Treatment. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The other Mode of treating I ſhall here men- <lb/>is, by Uſe of the Hands with the
          Science, for <lb/>there muſt be a concurrence with each other, the <lb/>Hands will give a
          kind of energy to the Mind, <lb/>and keep the Operator to his Work. The Effect <lb/>of
          this will ſoon be perceived in the Patient, and <pb xml:id="page_8" n="10"/>
          <lb/>alſo by yourſelf, in the Patient the Effects may <lb/>ſometimes be different, but in
          general a warm Sen- <lb/>ſation will take place, at other times the Patient <lb/>will feel
          cold; and the Operator will find a ſort <lb/>of pricking in the the Ends of all his
          Fingers.— <lb/>So much for the Mode of Treating. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The next Thing to be attended to is ſome of the <lb/>Complaints the Human Body is
          ſubject to, and <lb/>which the Operation of this Science is peculiarly <lb/>adapted to
          remove; many Diſorders ariſe from <lb/>Obſtructions and the want of proper Circulation
          <lb/>of the Fluids: the Body is like a curious Machine, <lb/>which if one Wheel be a
          little obſtructed, it affects <lb/>the Whole and when the Diſorder is diſcovered the
          <lb/>Remedy is the more eaſily applied; ſo when any <lb/>Obſtruction is perceived, apply
          the whole Energy <lb/>of the mind to the part affected, and in this, as well <lb/>as every
          other Magnetic Operation, ſeparate as <pb xml:id="page_9" n="11"/>
          <lb/>much as poſſible, every Idea of corporal Action <lb/>and think on mental Power only. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Head-Ach. Whatever obſtructs the free Circu- <lb/>lation of the Blood through the
          Veſſels of the <lb/>Head, may occaſion the Head-ach, which very <lb/>frequently ariſes
          from a foul Stomach; in <lb/>that caſe you muſt treat the Stomach only, by <lb/>moving the
          Hand upwards and downwards, which <lb/>will agitatate the Bile, and relieve the Patient;
          <lb/>but if it ariſes from Obſtructions, the Treatment <lb/>will occaſion an agreeable
          warmth, and aſſiſt Na- <lb/>ture in overcoming the complaint; this will be <lb/>found
          effectual in moſt Diſorders of the Head. <lb/>I have frequently cured the Head-ach, by
          preſſing <lb/>and drawing the Hand ſteadily over the Forehead, <lb/>in leſs than half an
          hour. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Inflammation of the eyes, may be cured by this <lb/>Treatment, only obſerve (during
          the Operation <pb xml:id="page_10" n="12"/>
          <lb/>with the Hand) to exert your Intention, as much <lb/>as poſſible, to draw out the
          Inflammation: By the <lb/>ſame method you may treat Abſceſſes in order to <lb/>bring them
          to a head, if you cannot diſperſe them; <lb/>likewiſe you will find it effectual to
          extract Fire <lb/>from burns of all kinds, in two or three times <lb/>treating, and if not
          very much burnt, in one Treat- <lb/>ment only. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Strains. In treating Strains, which are often at- <lb/>tended with worſe conſequences
          than broken <lb/>Bones; fix your Mind intenſely on the part affect- <lb/>ed, and while you
          are engaged in the method of <lb/>Treatment, as above, the Patient will find an
          <lb/>agreeable glow and warmth pervade the part, <lb/>which will help to reſtore the
          Veſſels to their <lb/>proper Tone. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Deafneſs. The hearing may be hurt by violent <lb/>Colds in the Head, by a Stroke upon
          the Ear, by <pb xml:id="page_11" n="13"/>
          <lb/>hard Wax, or other Subſtances, filling up the <lb/>Cavity of the Ear, all which may
          be removed by <lb/>perſeverance in the Treatment. Place the Patient <lb/>at a little
          diſtance, with the Ear inclining towards <lb/>you: Let your mental Ideas enter the Ear, at
          <lb/>the ſame time moving your Hands backwards and <lb/>forwards, pointing towards the
          Ear, and carry your <lb/>Ideas, as it were, through the Head; and by a con- <lb/>tinuance
          of this Treatment, an agreeable warmth <lb/>will be produced, and the Obſtruction removed.
          <lb/>I have known a Deafneſs occaſioned by a ſtroke <lb/>on the Ear, to have been totally
          removed in a <lb/>quarter of an Hour; and Perſons who had been <lb/>Deaf for many Years,
          have been reſtored to their <lb/>Hearing by repeated Treatments of this Kind; <lb/>but
          great care muſt be taken not to catch Cold <lb/>whilſt the Cure is performing, leſt it
          ſhould render <lb/>the Treatment ineffectual. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">We</hi> now advance to another part of the Sci- <pb xml:id="page_12"
            n="14"/>
          <lb/>ence, that of abſent Treatment, and here it ap- <lb/>pears in a more irrational and
          obſcure point of <lb/>view, to ignorant and prejudiced minds; <note place="bottom" n="*"
            rend="size(0.5)">* An ironical, dogmatical, and not to ſay immodeſt Pamphlet, has been
            <lb/>recently impoſed on the Public for a rational account of Animal Magnetiſm, <lb/>the
            Editor of which ſeems to have attained to no better knowledge of the <lb/>Science he
            explodes, than what has been imbibed from Vulgar Prejudice, <lb/>and the Cant of a few
            old Women. </note> but why <lb/>ſhould this be thought incredible, ſince Expanſion
          <lb/>or Diſtance is allowed to be a relative Idea, which <lb/>belongs only to the Body,
          and has nothing to do <lb/>with the Soul; the Soul is poſſeſſed with inte- <lb/>lectual
          Powers and Affections, ſuch as Thought, <lb/>Reflection, Senſation, Volition or Willing,
          and <lb/>I can as eaſily fix my Mind upon St. Peter's at <lb/>Rome as on St. Paul's in
          London. Diſtance be- <lb/>longs to the Body, as obſerved above, but Thought <lb/>cannot be
          confined, it can travel backward into <lb/>the paſt, or forward into the future, it can
          aſpire <lb/>to things above as well as reflect on things beneath; <lb/>when we want to
          recollect any thing we travel <lb/>back into the paſt, we exerciſe a wiſh to recollect,
            <pb xml:id="page_13" n="15"/>
          <lb/>and often our wiſhes are effectual and the thing <lb/>we want to recollect is brought
          to our Mind: <lb/>Thoughts are in many caſes, influencial, why may <lb/>they not affect
          and remove Diſorders from Per- <lb/>ſons at a diſtance, as well as thoſe at hand?— In
          <lb/>order to perform abſent Treatment, retire; ſit <lb/>down for a few Minutes, be
          perfectly collected, <lb/>and as much as poſſible abſtracted; conſider the <lb/>Powers you
          are poſſeſſed off, and what you wiſh <lb/>to perform to your abſent Friend, form his Idea
          in <lb/>your Mind, fix on it for ſome time, and deſcend <lb/>ſlowly and gradually from the
          Head downwards, <lb/>'till by the power of Sympathy you feel yourſelf, <lb/>as it were, in
          contact with him and find a correſ- <lb/>pondent Pain which you muſt endeavor to remove:
          <lb/>But if you know the Complaint your abſent Friend <lb/>labours under, and would
          relieve him, ſit down, <lb/>collect yourſelf, and then treat him, though abſent, <lb/>in
          the ſame Manner you would if you ſaw him be- <lb/>fore you. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_14" n="16"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">If</hi> upon reading theſe Lines the Science ſhould <lb/>appear a
          Chimera, the Reader is requeſted not to <lb/>cenſure and condemn it 'till he has tried the
          Power <lb/>of it for his own Satisfaction and Conviction, and <lb/>if he finds it
          effectual in one Caſe, let him ſuſpend <lb/>his judgement 'till he has tried it in others,
          and I <lb/>am perſuaded he will not be diſappointed. Let him <lb/>make Trial of raiſing
          the Hand as directed in the <lb/>Mode of Treatment, and he will have occular De-
          <lb/>monſtration of the Power of the Science. </p>
      </div>
      <trailer rend="align-center">
        <lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
