<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Blumenbach: An essay on generation. </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Johann Friedrich Blumenbach</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">An essay on generation. By J. F. Blumenbach, M.D. Aulic Counsellor to
              His Britannic Majesty, and Professor of Physic in the University of Gottingen, &amp;c.
              Translated from the German</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T61381</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T61381"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for T. Cadell, Strand; Faulder, Bond Street; Murray, Fleet
                  Street; and Creech, at Edinburgh.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1792</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="9"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="84"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">Harvard University Houghton Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3309805269</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K053359.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: midwifery"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_1"/>
        <p rend="align-center">
          <lb/>ON <lb/><hi rend="size(2)">GENERATION</hi>. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="7"/>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div n="1" type="section">
        <pb xml:id="page_10"/>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">SECTION I.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent hanging italic">
          <lb/>Of the various Hypotheſes, by which the <lb/>Phenomena of Generation have been
          <lb/>attempted to be explained. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">W</hi>HAT is the nature of that change, <lb/>which takes place
          within a female, <lb/>when after having experienced the <lb/>moſt delightful of all
          ſenſual pleaſures, and <lb/>being duly impregnated, form, and exiſtence <lb/>are about to
          be given to her offſpring? </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_11" n="2"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Few queſtions hare ever awakened more <lb/>general, and more ardent curioſity than
          this; <lb/>for however romantic it may appear to attempt <lb/>to aſcertain the
          obſervations, and thoughts of <lb/>our firſt parents, yet the ſuppoſition is natural,
          <lb/>that the wonderful effects, and as it were <lb/>repeated creations produced by the
          indulgence <lb/>of this inſtinct, muſt firſt have excited their <lb/>ſurpriſe, and then
          led them to a train of re- <lb/>flections. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Conſidering the innumerable times the <lb/>phenomena of generation have occurred
          ſince <lb/>the days of Adam, it becomes a humiliating <lb/>reproach to the underſtanding
          of his deſcen- <lb/>dants, that during all that long ſucceſſion of <lb/>time, they have
          not been able to give any <lb/>ſatisfactory explanation of the matter; eſpe- <lb/>cially
          as it appears to have ſoon become a <lb/>very early ſubject of ſtudy with ſpeculative
          <lb/>men: at leaſt moſt of the phyſiological frag- <lb/>ments of the ancient philoſophers
          and phyſi- <pb xml:id="page_12" n="3"/>
          <lb/>cians, <note place="bottom" n="(a)" rend="italic size(0.5)">(a) For inſtance, thoſe
            of Orpheus, Pythagoras, <lb/>Anaxagoras, &amp;c. </note>, which have been handed down to
          <lb/>us, conſiſt in general of inquiries into the <lb/>myſteries of generation; and indeed
          ſince that, <lb/>there is hardly a period in which the ſame kind <lb/>of reſearches have
          not been more or leſs pro- <lb/>ſecuted. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Even in the darkeſt times of the middle <lb/>ages, when the ſpirit of inquiry ſeemed
          almoſt <lb/>entirely loſt in the lethargy of monaſtic bar- <lb/>bariſm, this ſubject
          appears every now and <lb/>then to have awakened a ſpark of curioſity, <lb/>and to have
          ſtimulated ſome of the holy fathers <lb/>of thoſe times to the compoſition of very
          <lb/>ſenſual and obſcene works, ſome of which <lb/>have reached our days <note
            place="bottom" n="(b)" rend="italic size(0.5)">(b) Such as that of Pope John <hi
              rend="italic">XXth,</hi> or <lb/>Biſhop Abert to Great, or whatever holy father of
            <lb/>the church it was, who wrote that vile book de Se- <lb/>cretis Mulierum. One may
            alſo add Mich. Scotus, <lb/>the ſcrutinizer of natural things. </note>, and ſerve to
          prove <pb xml:id="page_13" n="4"/>
          <lb/>that their authors were at leaſt intereſted in <lb/>the theoretical, if not in the
          practical part of <lb/>generation. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>We are not therefore to be ſurpriſed, <lb/>that the attempt to ſolve this great
          problem <lb/>of nature encreaſed rapidly, beyond the power <lb/>of numbering, leaving no
          paſſage untrod which <lb/>afforded any hopes of leading to a ſolution of <lb/>the myſtery;
          hence there hardly exiſts an- <lb/>other ſpot in the whole region of natural
          <lb/>knowledge, ſurrounded by more intricate la- <lb/>byrinths, or falſe guides than this. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Drelingcourt, a teacher of Boerhaave's, <lb/>collected no leſs than two hundred and
          ſixty- <lb/>two vague hypotheſes on generation, from the <lb/>writings of earlier writers. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In ſpite of the aſtoniſhing variety, and <lb/>number of paths, which ſeemed to lead
          to the <lb/>ſolution of this phyſiological problem, yet they <lb/>are all of them but ſo
          many branches of two <lb/>principal roads; the one conducting to the <pb xml:id="page_14"
            n="5"/>
          <lb/>doctrine of <hi rend="italic">Evolution,</hi> the other to that of <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Epigeniſts.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is either ſuppoſed that the prepared, <lb/>but at the ſame time unorganized
          rudiments <lb/>of the fœtus, firſt begins to be gradually or- <lb/>ganized when it arrives
          at its place of deſti- <lb/>nation at a due time, and under the neceſſary
          <lb/>circumſtances. This is the doctrine of Epi- <lb/>geniſis; </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Or, we deny every ſort of generation, <lb/>and believe that the germ of every animal,
          and <lb/>every plant that ever has lived and ever will <lb/>live, were all created at one
          and the ſame <lb/>time, namely, at the beginning of the world; <lb/>and that all that is
          neceſſary is, that one <lb/>generation ſhould be developed after the <lb/>other. Such is
          the celebrated theory of <lb/>Evolution. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But the manner in which this evolu- <lb/>tion happens, has been differently accounted
          <lb/>for. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_15" n="6"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Heraclitus, ſurnamed the gloomy, and <lb/>Hippocrates, or whoever the author of thoſe
          <lb/>books on regimen was, which appeared un- <lb/>der his name, together with many of
          their <lb/>followers, were of opinion, that thoſe germs <lb/>were ſcattered up and down
          the whole globe, <lb/>where they wandered about, each in ſearch of <lb/>the genitals of a
          ready made relation of their <lb/>own kind, which having once found, they <lb/>took
          lodgement there, threw off their enve- <lb/>lopement, and now became fit for being
          <lb/>themſelves evolved. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If we except the impoſing name of the <lb/>authors to whom this theory is aſcribed,
          it <lb/>has little elſe to recommend it to our atten- <lb/>tion. It is ſo completely built
          on fanciful <lb/>ſuppoſitions, that it would be difficult to ſay, <lb/>what hypotheſis
          might not be credited were <lb/>we to yield the ſmalleſt faith to ſuch a doc- <lb/>trine.
          The late profeſſor Geſner, who wrote <lb/>a commentary on this romance of Hippo-
          <lb/>crates, apologizes for himſelf by adopting the <lb/><hi rend="italic">bon mot</hi> of
          Queen Chriſtina, <q rend="quotes">that the chi- <pb xml:id="page_16" n="7"/>
            <lb/>meras of the ancients were juſt as <lb/>good as thoſe of the moderns. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>More approbation has been given to <lb/>two other theories of evolution, according to
          <lb/>each of which, the germs did not wander <lb/>about, but thoſe of the ſame kind were
          all <lb/>neatly wrapt up, and encaſed one within an- <lb/>other, ſo that the firſt parent
          of each animal, <lb/>and plant was ſuppoſed to contain all the <lb/>germs of every
          ſucceeding generation; co- <lb/>pulation only ſerving to awaken them to their <lb/>ſtate
          of evolution. The only difference be- <lb/>tween the two theories was, that the one
          <lb/>ſuppoſed the germs to inhabit the teſticles of <lb/>their father, whilſt the other
          would have it, <lb/>that they reſided in the ovaria of their mo- <lb/>ther. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>No ſooner was the art of making magni- <lb/>fying glaſſes diſcovered, and by that
          means <lb/>an opening procured to a new world in <lb/>the creation, than the novelty of
          the diſ- <lb/>covery, and facility of its application, by af- <pb xml:id="page_17" n="8"/>
          <lb/>fording an opportunity to a number of micro- <lb/>ſcopical experiments, naturally led
          to the moſt <lb/>unexpected ſights. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Among the great amateurs of this kind <lb/>of amuſement, was one Ludwig von Ham-
          <lb/>mon, a young man born at Dantzig, who <lb/>during the time of his ſtudying medicine
          at <lb/>Leyden, and in the courſe of his microſcopical <lb/>purſuits, diſcovered in the
          month of Auguſt <lb/>1677, in a drop of the ſemen of a cock re- <lb/>cently diſſected, a
          kind of ocean, in which <lb/>ſwam thouſands of little lively active animals. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The ſame unexpected phenomenon was <lb/>alſo obſerved in the ripe ſemen of other male
          <lb/>animals, and in theſe animalculæ were im- <lb/>mediately thought to be ſeen, the
          germs of <lb/>ſubſequent perfect, animals. By this diſcovery, <lb/>a key was ſuppoſed to
          be found, which would <lb/>unlock the whole myſtery of generation. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Now I cannot conceive how ſome pro- <lb/>feſſed philoſophers, and natural hiſtorians
          have <pb xml:id="page_18" n="9"/>
          <lb/>been led to deny life and voluntary motion to <lb/>thoſe animalculæ; but I am ſtill
          more at a loſs <lb/>to imagine, how another ſet of philoſophers <lb/>have been induced to
          dignify theſe animalculæ <lb/>of a ſtagnant animal fluid, to the high rank <lb/>of the
          organized germs of ſucceſſive gene- <lb/>rations. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Without entering into a long and tedious <lb/>detail of all the doubts and
          difficulties, which <lb/>riſe up in oppoſition to ſo ſingular a theory, I <lb/>ſhall
          content myſelf with adding a few reflec- <lb/>tions, which to the moſt uninformed readers,
          <lb/>will appear ſufficient for calling in queſtion <lb/>this imaginary dignity of the
          animalculæ of <lb/>the ſemen of animals. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>How comes it that the animalculæ of <lb/>the ſemen of animals the moſt nearly
          related, <lb/>differ ſo much from each other, whilſt ſcarce <lb/>any two things reſemble
          one another ſo much <lb/>as the animalculæ of animals, the moſt op- <lb/>poſite to each
          other, both in nature and form? <pb xml:id="page_19" n="10"/>
          <lb/>For inſtance, the animalculæ in the ſemen of <lb/>frogs, as repreſented by Mr. von
          Gleichen, <lb/>bear no kind of reſemblance to thoſe of the <lb/>common newt, as
          repreſented by Spallan- <lb/>zani; whereas on the other hand, two drops <lb/>of water
          cannot reſemble each other more <lb/>ſtrongly, than the animalculæ of the ſemen <lb/>of a
          man, and thoſe of an aſs, as repreſented <lb/>by the firſt of theſe accurate obſervers. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This ſame modern advocate for the digni- <lb/>ty of theſe animalculæ, has already
          diſcovered <lb/>two kinds of them in the ſame drop of ſemen of <lb/>a frog, and yet both
          of them are perfectly diſ- <lb/>tinct from thoſe which Roeſel repreſents as
          <lb/>animalculæ of the ſemen of the ſame animal; <lb/>beſides the former were not only
          diſcovered <lb/>in the veſiculæ ſeminales, but alſo in the <lb/>kidneys: mere appearances,
          as evinced by the <lb/>irregular and uncertain ſhape of the inhabi- <lb/>tants of the male
          ſemen, and which irregu- <lb/>larity and uncertainty refutes their pretended <lb/>dignity
          ſo completely, that one might as well <pb xml:id="page_20" n="11"/>
          <lb/>hope with Paracelſus <note place="bottom" n="(c)" rend="italic size(0.5)">(c) On the
            nature of things, addreſſed to John <lb/>Winkclſteiner von Feyburg at Uchtland, in the
            <lb/>ſixth volume of Huſer's edition of his works, <hi rend="italic">p. 263.</hi>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Amatus Luſitanas deſcribes a ſimilar pro- <lb/>duction: Vide Curation, Medicinal
              Cent. <hi rend="italic">VI.</hi>
              <lb/>curat. <hi rend="italic">55,</hi> ſcholi, <hi rend="italic">p. 612.</hi>
              <q rend="quotes">Certo ſcimus chemico <lb/>artificio puerum conflatum eſſe et omnia
                ſua mem- <lb/>bra perfecta contraxiſſe, ac motum habuiſſe, qui <lb/>cum a vaſe ubi
                continebatur eſſet extractus mo- <lb/>veri deſiit. Novit hæc accuratius Julius Ca-
                <lb/>millus vir ſingularis doctrinæ et rerum occulta- <lb/>rum, et variarum hac
                noſtra æſtate magnus ſcru- <lb/>tator et Hetruſca ſua lingua ſcriptor
                diligentiſſimus <lb/>et accuratiſſimus.</q>
            </p>
          </note>, and the Painter <lb/>Gautier <note place="bottom" n="(d)" rend="italic size(0.5)"
            >(d) Vide Generation de l'Homme et des Ani- <lb/>maux, Paris <hi rend="italic">1750.
              12.</hi> Alſo his Obſervations ſur <lb/>l'Hiſt. Nat. <hi rend="italic">1 p.</hi> and
            the miſhapen repreſentation of <lb/>a fœtus drawn by himſelf and coloured after life.
            <lb/>Tab. <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> fig. <hi rend="italic">3.</hi>
          </note>, to be able to produce a perfect hu- <lb/>man embryo from male ſemen, or expect to
          ſee, <lb/>as the famous academician Hartzoeker aſ- <pb xml:id="page_21" n="12"/>
          <lb/>ſures us he did, the little embryo ſitting in the <lb/>body of each animalcule, in
          the ſame crooked <lb/>and confined poſture as in the female womb <note place="bottom"
            n="(c)" rend="size(0.5) italic">(c) Eſſai de Dioptrique, Paris <hi rend="italic">1694.
              4. p. <lb/>230,</hi> where the lynx-eyed man gives an accurate <lb/>figure of a child,
            which he obſerved in the body <lb/>of one of the animalculæ of the ſemen, and which
            <lb/>appeared to him as if anxiouſly expecting its de- <lb/>liverance. </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Long before the animalculæ of the ſemen <lb/>were diſcovered, Joſeph de Aromatariis
          found <lb/>out a third way to explain the myſtery of ge- <lb/>neration, by means of the
          theory of evolution; <lb/>I mean that one which ſuppoſes the ovaria <lb/>of every female,
          even before impregnation, <lb/>to contain a whole proviſion of organized <lb/>molecules or
          germs, perfectly ready for evo- <lb/>lution. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Swammerdam alſo adopted this opinion, <lb/>but owing to the great figure which the
            <pb xml:id="page_22" n="13"/>
          <lb/>animalculæ of the ſemen ſoon afterwards <lb/>made in the world, it remained but
          little <lb/>known until two very diſtinguiſhed authors, <lb/>Haller, and Bonnet, at once
          raiſed its repu- <lb/>tation. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>According to this theory we, and indeed <lb/>all the children of Adam, were at one
          time <lb/><hi rend="italic">ipſo facto,</hi> pent up in the two ovaria of our <lb/>common
          mother Eve. There we lay, as it <lb/>were aſleep, and although aſtoniſhing little
          <lb/>creatures, yet completely organized bodies, <lb/>and perfect miniatures of the forms
          we have <lb/>ſince aſſumed; for ſays Haller, <q rend="quotes"><hi rend="italic">All our
              <lb/>viſcera, and the bones themſelves were then <lb/>already formed, although in a
              kind of fluid <lb/>ſtate.</hi>
          </q> That which we call impregnation, <lb/>is nothing elſe than the action of awakening
          <lb/>the germ from its lethargic ſtate by means of <lb/>the male ſemen, which ſtimulates
          the little <lb/>creature's heart to the firſt pulſation; and ſo <lb/>on. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_23" n="14"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The ſame kind of idea has lately in- <lb/>duced a very celebrated naturaliſt of
          Geneva, <lb/>and a warm advocate of this theory, to plan <lb/>out for us a hiſtory of
          organized bodies pre- <lb/>vious to the ſtate of impregnation, from <lb/>which we learn,
            <hi rend="italic">firſt,</hi> that we are all much <lb/>older than what we ſuppoſe
          ourſelves to be, <lb/>
          <hi rend="italic">ſecondly,</hi> that all mankind are exactly the ſame <lb/>age, the great
          grandfather not a ſecond older <lb/>than the youngeſt of his great grand children,
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">thirdly,</hi> that this reſpectable age, which we <lb/>are all
          of, may be about ſix thouſand years. <lb/>The ſame natural hiſtorian alſo agrees en-
          <lb/>tirely in opinion with Bazin; that ſince that <lb/>charming long ſeries of years,
          when we were <lb/>all packed together along with Cain and Abel, <lb/>and the other two
          hundred thouſand million <lb/>of men, which according to the beſt calcu- <lb/>lations,
          have ſince that period gone <hi rend="italic">quo pius <lb/>Æneas quo Tellus dives et
            Ancus;</hi> in a word, <lb/>ſince the firſt creation, during which time <lb/>we have
          been in a kind of lethargic ſleep, <lb/>though not entirely without motion; that <pb
            xml:id="page_24" n="15"/>
          <lb/>during the whole fifty-ſeven centuries, I ſay, <lb/>previous to our being awakened by
          the above- <lb/>mentioned ſtimulus, we were according to <lb/>Bazin's opinion, always
          growing a little and <lb/>little: for inſtance, we were moſt probably <lb/>rather a little
          bigger at the time we lay beſide <lb/>Cain's nieces, than when all their uncles and
          <lb/>aunts were of the party, as it is very natural <lb/>to ſuppoſe, that we muſt then
          have been conſi- <lb/>derably more pinched for room. In this <lb/>manner our apartment
          became gradually <lb/>more eaſy, and commodious in proportion as <lb/>our forefathers were
          evolved, and we agreed <lb/>with it, for we kept continually ſtretching <lb/>ourſelves
          more and more, until the ſucceſſion <lb/>of evolution came at laſt to our turn!! </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>However extravagant and romantic ſuch <lb/>concluſions muſt appear, yet they follow
          as <lb/>natural deductions from the premiſes of the <lb/>theory, which gave riſe to them.
          In ſupport <lb/>of this theory, its moſt celebrated abettors, <lb/>Haller, and
          Spallanzani, adduced many ex- <lb/>periments, and obſervations, which we ſhall <pb
            xml:id="page_25" n="16"/>
          <lb/>examine more particularly in the next Sec- <lb/>tion. When we conſider how concluſive
          <lb/>and ſtriking theſe obſervations appear to be <lb/>at firſt ſight, we ſhall not wonder
          at the <lb/>general aſſent, which during theſe thirty <lb/>years paſt, has been given to
          the doctrine of <lb/>the pre-exiſtence of complete organized mo- <lb/>lecules in the
          ovaria of females before impreg- <lb/>nation. I myſelf not only believed in the <lb/>truth
          of it, but defended it in many of my <lb/>writings; ſo that in fact the preſent little
          <lb/>volume contains a confeſſion of my former <lb/>errors, in regard to which, I wiſh
          that may <lb/>be true, which Mr. de Luc ſays ſome where <lb/>or other, that, <q
            rend="quotes">An error once detected, <lb/>becomes a more material truth, than many
            <lb/>poſitive ones, which we immediately ac- <lb/>knowledge to be ſuch. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The unexpected ſucceſs of a ſmall ex- <lb/>periment, which I made, however, with a
          <lb/>view of aſcertaining the truth of the doctrine <lb/>of evolution, firſt brought me
          back to the <lb/>point from which I ought to have ſet out, and <pb xml:id="page_26" n="17"/>
          <lb/>opened a new road to a very oppoſite doc- <lb/>trine. He who thus fights with nature,
          may <lb/>from an unexpected ſight, often diſcover her <lb/>moſt concealed treaſures. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>What gave occaſion to the inſtituting <lb/>the experiment was as follows: In one of
          my <lb/>walks during ſome holidays which I ſpent in <lb/>the country, I diſcovered in a
          ſtream, a ſort <lb/>of green armed polypus, which differed from <lb/>the common green kind
          by its long ſpiral <lb/>body, and by having ſhort and rather im- <lb/>moveable tentaculæ.
          With the wonders of <lb/>this little animal, I intended to amuſe my <lb/>country friends.
          The delightful warm ſum- <lb/>mer weather which then prevailed, and the <lb/>hardy
          conſtitution of the polypus itſelf, fa- <lb/>voured the experiments which we made, <lb/>to
          diſcover its power of reproduction ſo much, <lb/>that the act of renewal of the parts
          became <lb/>almoſt perceptible. By the ſecond and third <lb/>day, the maimed and divided
          animal was ſo <lb/>many new ones, each with arms, body, tail, <pb xml:id="page_27" n="18"/>
          <lb/>&amp;c. But we plainly remarked that the re- <lb/>generated animals, although
          ſupplied with <lb/>plenty of proper food, were always much <lb/>ſmaller than before, and a
          mutilated rump, <lb/>always diminiſhed very evidently, both in <lb/>length and diameter,
          in proportion as the loſt <lb/>parts were renewed <note place="bottom" n="(f)"
            rend="italic size(0.5)">(f) It is probable that this circumſtance has <lb/>been either
            totally overlocked by ſuch as were en- <lb/>gaged in obſerving phenomena of greater
            magnitude <lb/>in the hiſtory of this animal, or if it has been ob- <lb/>ſerved by any,
            it does not ſeem to have appeared to <lb/>them, of ſufficient importance to be noticed.
            That <lb/>attentive, and accurate obſerver Roeſel, however, <lb/>ſeems to have noticed
            this fact. Vide Hiſt. der Poly- <lb/>pen, in the third vol. of the
            Inſecten-beluſtigungen. </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Soon after my return to town, I was <lb/>called to a patient who had a caries. The
          <lb/>diſeaſe occupied the lower end of the femur <lb/>immediately above the knee, and had
          cauſed <pb xml:id="page_28" n="19"/>
          <lb/>a pretty extenſive and deep ulcer. It healed <lb/>gradually, but in proportion as the
          wound <lb/>filled up, and the cicactrix formed, all the <lb/>ſurrounding parts ſunk ſo,
          that the edge of <lb/>the cicatrix being almoſt on an equality with <lb/>the neighbouring
          parts, the whole formed a <lb/>broad, though rather ſuperficial excavation <note
            place="bottom" n="(g)" rend="italic size(0.5)">(g) An obſervation which has been alſo
            made <lb/>by Meſſrs. Louis and Fabre, vide their treatiſes Des <lb/>Playes avec perte de
            ſubſtance in the Mem. de l'Acad. de <lb/>Chirzrg. <hi rend="italic">vol. iv. p. 64</hi>
            and <hi rend="italic">106.</hi>
          </note>. <lb/>This was exactly the ſame thing <hi rend="italic">mutatis
            <lb/>mutandis,</hi> with what happened to the po- <lb/>lypus. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I have ſince that period, ſpent a great <lb/>deal of my leiſure moments in the
          further in- <lb/>veſtigation of this ſubject, both in experiment <lb/>and reflection; the
          conſequence of which has <lb/>been to convince me fully. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_29" n="20"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">That there is no ſuch thing in nature, as <lb/>pre-exiſting
            organized germs: but that the <lb/>unorganized matter of generation, after being
            <lb/>duly prepared, and having arrived at its place <lb/>of deſtination takes on a
            particular action, or <lb/>niſus, which niſus continues to act through the <lb/>whole
            life of the animal, and that by it the firſt <lb/>form of the animal, or plant is not
            only deter- <lb/>mined, but afterwards preſerved, and when <lb/>deranged, is again
            reſtored. A niſus, which <lb/>ſeems therefore to depend on the powers of life, <lb/>but
            which is as diſtinct from the other qualities <lb/>of living bodies, (ſenſibility,
            irritability, and <lb/>contractility) as from the common properties of <lb/>dead matter:
            that it is the chief principle of <lb/>generation, growth, nutrition, and reproduc-
            <lb/>tion, and that to diſtinguiſh it from all others, <lb/>it may be denominated
            the</hi> Formative Niſus <lb/>(Bildungſtrieb, or Niſus formativus). </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is to be hoped, that there is no <lb/>neceſſity for reminding the reader, that the
          <lb/>expreſſion Formative Niſus, like that of At- <pb xml:id="page_30" n="21"/>
          <lb/>traction <note place="bottom" n="(h)" rend="italic size(0.5)">(h) Vid. Newton at the
            end of his Optics: <lb/>
            <q rend="diple quotes">"What I call ATTRACTION, may be performed <lb/>by IMPULSE, or by
              ſome other means unknown <lb/>to me. I uſe that word here to ſignify only in
              <lb/>general any FORCE by which bodies tend to- <lb/>wards one another, whatever be
              the CAUSE."</q>
          </note>, ſerves only to denote a power, <lb/>whoſe conſtant operation is known from ex-
          <lb/>perience, but whoſe cauſe, like the cauſes <lb/>of moſt of the qualities of matter,
          is a <hi rend="italic">qualitas <lb/>occulta</hi> to us <note place="bottom" n="(i)"
            rend="italic size(0.5)">(i) <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Qualitas occulta— <q rend="diple quotes">
                <p rend="indent">"Se l'on entend par ce <lb/>mot un principe reel dont on ne peut
                  rendre raiſon <lb/>tout l'univers eſt dans ce cas." &amp;c. ſays Vol- <lb/>taire,
                  vid. his Elemeus de la Philoſphie de Newton. </p>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>And in another place he further adds, "Il <lb/>falloit reſpecter les qualités
                  occultes; car depuis <lb/>le brin d'herbe que l'ambre attira, juſqu'à la
                  <lb/>route que tant d'aſtres ſuiveut dans l'eſpace; <lb/>depuis la formation d'une
                  mite dans un fromage <lb/>juſqu'à la Galexie; ſoil que vous conſiderer, une
                  <lb/>pierre qui tombe, ſoil que vous ſuiviez le cours <lb/>d'une cométe traverſant
                  les deux tout eſt qualité <lb/>occulte." </p>
              </q>
            </p>
          </note> We may ſay of this, as of <pb xml:id="page_31" n="22"/>
          <lb/>all ſimilar powers, what Ovid ſays:—<hi rend="italic">Cauſa <lb/>latet, vis eſt
            notiſſima.</hi> But the great merit <lb/>in the ſtudy of theſe powers, is to aſcertain
          <lb/>more accurately their effects, and to reduce <lb/>them under general laws <note
            place="bottom" n="(k)" rend="italic size(0.5)">(k) One of the moſt learned, and
            ingenious <lb/>Engliſh phyſicians of the preſent time, Dr. G. For- <lb/>dyce, has very
            lately ſaid, in treating a phyſiological <lb/>point ſomething ſimilar to this, <q
              rend="diple">"Although the <lb/>ſtudy of cauſes of original powers be totally abſurd
              <lb/>and futile, yet the laws of their action are ca- <lb/>pable of inveſtigation by
              experiment, and ap- <lb/>plicanle to the evolving much uſeful knowledge."
              <lb/>Philoſoph. Trans. <hi rend="italic">V. LXXVIII. P. 1. p. 36.</hi>
            </q>
          </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>D'Alembert's ſucceſſor, Mr. de Con- <lb/>dorcet, in his Eulogy on Haller, and when
          <lb/>ſpeaking of Irritability, ſays, <q rend="quotes">The truth of <lb/>this doctrine was,
            as uſually is the caſe, at <lb/>firſt denied; but when it was diſcovered, <pb
              xml:id="page_32" n="23"/>
            <lb/>and that could not be done any longer with <lb/>honour, they concluded with
            obſerving, <lb/>that it had been diſcovered long before! </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When it is conſidered that ſome people <lb/>have been lately poſſeſſed of ſufficient
          pene- <lb/>tration to diſcover the doctrine of irritability <lb/>in the writings of Homer,
          and the circulation <lb/>of the blood deſcribed in the books of So- <lb/>lomon the
          Preacher; it would be really aſto- <lb/>niſhing if this doctrine of the Formative
          <lb/>Principle were allowed the merits of novelty, <lb/>and that nothing of the kind were
          to be diſ- <lb/>covered in all the works which have been <lb/>written on the ſubject
          within theſe two thou- <lb/>ſand years paſt <note place="bottom" n="(l)"
            rend="size(0.5) italic">(l) No one has given ſuch a clear proof of <lb/>this as Ad.
            Mich. Birkholz, Philos. et Med. Dr. <lb/>et Facult. Med. Aſſeſs. in his Diſſert. de
            Reſpira- <lb/>tione ejuſque fine ſummo atque ultimo, Lips. <hi rend="italic">1782.</hi>
            <lb/>After informing us, that the animal ſpirits (Spiritus <lb/>vitales) which the blood
            derives from the air, is <lb/>nothing more than the principium vitale of the an-
            <lb/>tients, or the irritability and ſenſibility of Haller, he <lb/>adds, <q
              rend="quotes">Veteres philoſophi hoc principium agnorerint <lb/>vicarium Dei miniſtrum
              et preſidentiam ſuperioris <lb/>agentis, et apud Græcos quidem ſub perſona Jovis
              <lb/>colebatur: Jovis omnia plena! A vetuſliſſimis phi- <lb/>loſophis, a Platone, et
              platonicis Arabibus, et le <lb/>Cat, appellatur anima, ſpiritus et idea mundi, vis
              <lb/>et natura genetrix et plaſtica, ideæ operatrices: a <lb/>Rayo flamma vitalis; ab
              eodem et poſtea imprimis <lb/>a Newtono principium trahens: a chemicis humi- <lb/>dum
              radicale, et quintum elementum: a Colonne <lb/>inviſibilia fermenta: a Blumenbachio
              niſus for- <lb/>mativus. A philoſophis Hermeticis mercurius <lb/>univerſalis et
              philoſophorum: a Thouvenel Gas <lb/>Æroelectricum, ab aliis aliter appellatur. </q>
          </note>;eſpecially as the <hi rend="italic">Vis <pb xml:id="page_33" n="24"/>
            <lb/>Plaſtica</hi> of the ancients, and more particularly <lb/>of the peripatetic
          ſchools, would ſeem as far <lb/>as the concordance of name goes to attempt <lb/>one to
          ſuch a <hi rend="italic">qui pro quo.</hi>
        </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_34" n="25"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I ſhould be extremely happy, however, if <lb/>any perſon would name one of the old
          writers, <lb/>who, in deſcribing the Vis Plaſtica, has given <lb/>ſuch a diſtinct idea of
          it, or ſuch a one as <lb/>correſponds ſo well with the phenomena of ge- <lb/>neration
            <note place="bottom" n="(m)" rend="italic size(0.5)">(m) Of all authors who have treated
            of <lb/>this power, F. Bonamica, the well-known diſciple <lb/>of Ariſtotle, explains
            himſelf perhaps the moſt cor- <lb/>rectly, de formatiane fœtus, <hi rend="italic">p.
              528.</hi>
            <q rend="diple quotes">"Spiritus <lb/>in ærea ſeminis ſubſtantia comprehenſus, aſperſus
              <lb/>autem a calore coeleſti, et vi a patre accepta, et <lb/>ea quam a cælo participat
              in uterum fæminæ con- <lb/>jectus, concoquet materias a fæmena infuſas, <lb/>et pro
              ratiom ipſarum variis modis afficiens efficit <lb/>inſtrumenta. Dum vero ea fabricat
              appellatur. <lb/>Facultas <foreign xml:lang="el">###Greek omitted### </foreign> ſeu
                <foreign xml:lang="el">###Greek omitted### </foreign>. Sed ubi ex- <lb/>tructa
              fuerint inſtrumenta, ut iis uti queat, quæ <lb/>prius erat vis formatrix, illis utens
              degenerat in <lb/>animam." </q>
          </note>, as that which I have attempted <lb/>to give (eſpecially in the Third Section) of
          <lb/>this Eſſay. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_35" n="26"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Profeſſor Wolff of Petersburg, a phy- <lb/>ſiologiſt of great penetration, hath
          explained <lb/>the growth of Animals, and Vegetables by <lb/>another power, which he calls
            <hi rend="italic">Vis Eſſentialis,</hi>
          <lb/>and which one on firſt hearing, might be apt <lb/>to confound with the <hi
            rend="italic">Niſus Formativus.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Whoever takes the trouble, however, <lb/>of peruſing the ſentiments which Profeſſor
          <lb/>Wolff entertains of the <hi rend="italic">Vis Eſſentialis,</hi> as <lb/>given in his
            <hi rend="italic">Theoria Generationis,</hi> will ſoon <lb/>diſcern the great difference
          there is between <lb/>the two <note place="bottom" n="(n)" rend="italic size(0.5)">(n) For
            example, <q>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>
                <bibl rend="italic">p. 12. </bibl> "Vis vegetabilium <lb/>eſſentialis ea eſt wis,
                quà humores ex circumjacente <lb/>terra, vel aliis corparibus colliguntur ſubire
                radicem <lb/>coguntur, per omnem plantam diſtribuuntur, par- <lb/>tem ad diverſa
                loca deponuntur, partem foras <lb/>expelluntur." </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>
                <bibl rend="italic">P. 13. </bibl> Quæ cunque vero ſit hæc vis, ſive
                <lb/>attractrix, ſive propulſiva, ſive æri expanſo debita <lb/>ſive compoſita ex
                omnibus hiſce et pluribus; modo <lb/>præſtet enarratos effectus, et ponatur, poſita
                planta <lb/>et humoribus nutriciis applicatis, id quod experien- <lb/>tia
                confirmatum eſt: ſufficiet ea præſenti ſcopo et <lb/>vocabitur a me Vis vegetabilium
                Eſſentialis:" </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>And in reſpect to the generation of animals, <lb/>
                <bibl rend="italic">p. 73. </bibl> "Embryonem hoc tempore (ovo ſc. <hi rend="italic"
                  >36.</hi> horas <lb/>incubato) ex ſubſtantia ovi nutrire demonſtrant il- <lb/>lius
                volumen auctum, perfectones acquiſitæ, abſen- <lb/>tia cujuſcunque alius materæ
                conſumtio alluminis et <lb/>vitelli ſuccedens, experimenta inferius recenſenda; c
                <lb/>onſequenter: tranſire particular nurients ex ovo <lb/>ad embryonem: et exiſtere
                vin quâ id perficitur <lb/>quæ non eſt ſuſtaltica cordis et arteriarum, neque
                <lb/>hinc facta preſſio in venas vicinas neque harum <lb/>compreſſio a motu
                muſculorum, dirigentem abſque <lb/>canalibus viam determinatibus, adeoque analogam
                <lb/>illi <hi rend="italic">(§. 1.)</hi> quam æque vocabo eſſentialem." </p>
            </q>
          </note>
        </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_36" n="27"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>According to him the <hi rend="italic">Vis Eſſentialis</hi> is <lb/>only that power,
          by which the nouriſhment <lb/>is diſtributed to the different parts of an ani- <lb/>mal,
          or vegetable. This is, indeed, neceſſary <lb/>to the Formative Principle; but it is quite
          <lb/>diſtinct from the principle itſelf. For this <pb xml:id="page_37" n="28"/>
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Vis Eſſentialis</hi> exerts itſelf with equal force in <lb/>the
          growth of even the moſt deformed, and <lb/>unnatural excreſcences of plants, and trees,
          <lb/>&amp;c. where the Formative Principle does not <lb/>ſeem to act at all, or at leaſt
          with no re- <lb/>gularity. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On the other hand, the Vis Eſſentialis <lb/>may be very weak, or deficient, as in
          ſuch <lb/>organized bodies, which are badly nouriſhed, <lb/>whilſt the Formative Principle
          remains in <lb/>full force, and ſo on. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>However unpleaſant it may be to me, <lb/>yet I feel myſelf forced, before entering
          more <lb/>particularly on the nature of the Formative <lb/>Principle, to premiſe a
          refutation of the ar- <lb/>guments which have been brought, and eſpe- <lb/>cially by Baron
          von Haller, in favour of <lb/>evolution of the female egg <note place="bottom" n="(o)"
            rend="italic size(0.5)">(o) But in doing ſo, I ſhall paſs over all <lb/>thoſe arguments
            againſt the doctrine of evolution, <lb/>which have lately appeared in a moſt ingenious
            and <lb/>witty publication, written expreſſly for that pur- <lb/>poſe. Vide Doubts
            concerning the Theory of Evolution, <lb/>in a letter addreſſed to Mons. Sonebier, from
            L. P. <lb/>(Patrin) tranſlated form the original French ma- <lb/>nuſcript into German by
            G. Forſter, Goettengen, <lb/><hi rend="italic">1788.</hi>
          </note>. What con- <pb xml:id="page_38" n="29"/>
          <lb/>ſoles me, however, in being thus obliged to <lb/>diſſent from the opinions of a man,
          to whoſe <lb/>works and writings I owe ſo much, is, partly <lb/>the reflection, that
          whatever uſeful may be <lb/>contained in the preſent ſheets, was occa- <lb/>ſioned by
          examining into, and proſecuting <lb/>his enquiries, and partly my doubts whether <lb/>he
          himſelf might not have altered his ideas, <lb/>and have relinquiſhed, in a great degree,
          his <lb/>old opinions on the ſubject, had he lived to <lb/>have finiſhed that part of the
          laſt edition of <lb/>his Phyſiology <note place="bottom" n="(p)" rend="italic size(0.5)"
            >(p) He himſelf wrote me a letter, dated the <lb/>28th Auguſt <hi rend="italic"
              >1776,</hi> in which he ſays <q rend="quotes">I thank <lb/>Providence for having
              granted me ſo long a life <lb/>as has enabled me to give an improved and
              <lb/>corrected edition of my Phyſiology, without which, <lb/>I muſt have left many
              errors to be detected after <lb/>my death. </q>
          </note>, which treats of this matter. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_39" n="30"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Indeed, had Haller ſtill perſiſted to ſup- <lb/>port the doctrine of evolution, and
          oppoſe <lb/>that of gradual formation, his fame would <lb/>have ſuffered as little from
          it, as Harvey's <lb/>from his denying the exiſtence of the lacteal <lb/>veſſels, or
          Newton's from his disbelief of the <lb/>poſſibility of colourleſs tubes in the fern. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="section">
        <pb xml:id="page_40" n="31"/>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>SECT. II. </head>
        <p rend="indent hanging italic">
          <lb/>Examination of the principal Arguments in <lb/>favour of the ſuppoſed Pre-exiſtence
          of <lb/>Organized Germs in the Ovaria of Fe- <lb/>males, and Refutation of a Doctrine. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">O</hi>N the 13th of May 1758 was read <lb/>before the Royal Society
          of Sciences <lb/>at Göttingen, the celebrated paper of Baron <lb/>von Haller, (then
          preſident of the ſociety) <lb/>on the formation of the heart in the embryo, <lb/>in which
          it was believed an <hi rend="italic">argumentum cru- <lb/>cis</hi> was offered in ſupport
          of the doctrine of <lb/>pre-exiſting germs. The author ſays, That <lb/>he found that not
          only the membrane of the <lb/>yolk of an incubated egg, but alſo its blood- <lb/>veſſels,
          conſtituting what was called the <lb/><hi rend="italic">figura venoſa,</hi> were a
          continuation of the <lb/> membrane and blood-veſſels of the chick. <pb xml:id="page_41"
            n="32"/>
          <lb/>But the yolk of the egg exiſted in the hen <lb/>previous to impregnation, and
          therefore moſt <lb/>probably the embryo alſo, although too ſmall <lb/>to be diſcovered by
          our eyes. The prudent <lb/>author however expreſſed himſelf at firſt very <lb/>cautiouſly
          and in an undecided manner on <lb/>this ſyllogiſm <note place="bottom" n="(q)">(q) <q
              rend="quotes italic size(0.5)">L'evolution commence à me pariotre la <lb/>plus
              probable. </q>
          </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Mons. Bonnet, however, who ſoon after <lb/>publiſhed his work on organized bodies,
          and, <lb/>who was previouſly propoſſeſſed in favour of <lb/>the doctrine of the evolution
          of pre-exiſting <lb/>organic germs, took hold of this obſervation <lb/>of Haller's, and
          pronounced it to be abſolute- <lb/>ly unanſwerable, and conſidered the truth of <lb/>the
          hypotheſis as fully eſtabliſhed by it <note place="bottom" n="(r)" rend="size(0.5) italic"
            >(r) <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Vide his <q>preface to the work alluded to. <lb/><hi rend="roman">Ed. 5th.</hi>
                "Enfin cette deconverte importante <lb/>(que le germe appartenoit à la femelle,
                qu'il pre- <lb/>exiſtoit ainſi a la fæcondation, et que l'evolution <lb/>eloit la
                loi naturelle des etres organisés) que <lb/>j'attendois et que j'avois osé predire
                me fut an- <lb/>noncée en <hi rend="roman">1757,</hi> par Mons. le Baron de Haller
                <lb/>qui la tenoit de la nature elle même." La <lb/>"decouverte de Mr. de Haller
                prouvoit d'une ma- <lb/>niêre inconteſtable que le poulet appartenoit ori-
                <lb/>ginairement à la poule et qu'il pre-exiſtoit à la <lb/>CONCEPTION." </q>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>And in his <q>letter to Mr. von Haller, dated <lb/>30th of October <hi
                  rend="roman">1757,</hi> he ſays, "Vos poulets <lb/>m'enchantent: je n'avois pas
                eſpéré que le ſecret <lb/>de la generation commonceroit ſitôt a ſe devoiler.
                <lb/>C'eſt bien vous, Monſieur, qui avez sçu prendre <lb/>la nature ſur le fait."
              </q>
            </p>
          </note>. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_42" n="33"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Haller alſo allowed himſelf to be daily <lb/>more and more convinced of the force of
          his <lb/>own obſervations, inſomuch that in his later <lb/>writings he made little ſcruple
          of declaring <lb/>them equally deciſive, as his friend Bonnet <lb/>had done. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_43" n="34"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In acknowledging that I myſelf, as well <lb/>as ſome hundred other phyſiologiſts, and
          natu- <lb/>raliſts, looked on this celebrated obſervation <lb/>as the foundation
            ſton<unclear>#</unclear> of the theory of evo- <lb/>lution; I hink I need make the leſs
          ceremony <lb/>in expreſſing my aſtoniſhment how we could <lb/>have allowed ourſelves, as
          in the preſent caſe, <lb/>to attribute ſo much force to an aſſertion <lb/>which abſolutely
          proves nothing! </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>For, granting it to be fully proved that <lb/>there exiſted a continuation between
          the <lb/>membrane and veſſels of the chick and yolk, <lb/>(granting it, I ſay; for, the
          fact as the moſt <lb/>accurate, and ſcrupulous inveſtigation teaches, <lb/>ſtill remains
          uncertain, as every one will rea- <lb/>dily acknowledge who has taken the pains <lb/>of
          examining fecundated eggs,) yet it does <lb/>not follow that the membrane and veſſels,
          <lb/>even if they really were a continuation of <lb/>each other, co-exiſted from the
          beginning. <lb/>Do we not ſee many inſtances in organized <lb/>bodies where this laſt
          mentioned circumſtance <lb/>exiſts, and yet where it is impoſſible to grant <pb
            xml:id="page_44" n="35"/>
          <lb/>the ſuppoſition which has been drawn as a <lb/>concluſion from it. For inſtance, all
          thoſe <lb/>ſingular vegetable productions, which are <lb/>cauſed by the puncture of
          certain infects in <lb/>many plants. Thus the Spongiæ cynosbatæ <lb/>are produced entirely
          in conſequence of the <lb/>puncture of the Cynips in the roſe-buſh. The <lb/>bark of this
          ſhrub is continued over this <lb/>ſpongy and quite <hi rend="italic">accidental</hi>
          production; nay, <lb/>if we take, and cut any freſh branch which <lb/>has ſome of theſe
          ſpongy bodies on it, we <lb/>ſhall find that the wood of the branch appears <lb/>to be an
          evident continuation of the woody <lb/>part of theſe ſubſtances. But ſhall we from
          <lb/>hence conclude, that this accidental produc- <lb/>tion originally co-exiſted with the
          ſhrub <lb/>itſelf, and that in every trunk, and every <lb/>branch of every roſe-buſh in
          the world, the <lb/>enveloped germs of innumerable ſpongiæ <lb/>cynosbatæ ſhould have
          always lain there like <lb/>ſo much hidden wealth, and would have <lb/>always remained ſo
          until the thouſand thou- <lb/>ſandth part of them were by chance excited <pb
            xml:id="page_45" n="36"/>
          <lb/>to evolution by the benevolent puncture of <lb/>a little cynips. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Again, in the animal kingdom, do we <lb/>not often ſee after an accidental
          inflammation <lb/>of any of the viſcera, a new membrane <lb/>formed as it were by the
          effuſion of the <lb/>lymphatic part of the blood; and in the courſe <lb/>of a few days, do
          we not obſerve many blood- <lb/>veſſels produced in this membrane, which <lb/>anaſtomoſe
          with the blood-veſſels of the <lb/>neighbouring viſcera; and yet it would be
          <lb/>ridiculous to ſuppoſe that theſe veſſels co- <lb/>exiſted from the firſt with the old
          ones. <lb/>And for fear that it be objected to us, that <lb/>theſe are mere preternatural
          appearances in <lb/>the diſeaſed ſtate of animals, we beg them <lb/>to recall the late
          celebrated membrana deci- <lb/>dua of Dr. Hunter, which after a fruitful
          <lb/>impregnation, lines the whole cavity of the <lb/>uterus, and whoſe blood-veſſels,
          eſpecially <lb/>where the umbilical chord is inſerted in <lb/>the placenta, are moſt
          evidently connected <pb xml:id="page_46" n="37"/>
          <lb/>and anaſtomoſe with the blood-veſſels of the <lb/>mother. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In all theſe caſes, the new formed mem- <lb/>branes, and their blood-veſſels are the
          mere <lb/>productions of the neighbouring viſcera, <lb/>which renders it probable, that
          the mem- <lb/>brane and veſſels of the embryo in a fecun- <lb/>dated egg, are produced in
          like manner from <lb/>the membrane and veſſels of the yolk. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Mr. Paul <note place="bottom" n="(s)" rend="italic size(0.5)">(s) In the preface to
            the 8th vol. of the Col- <lb/>lection Academique par étrangere, <hi rend="roman">p. 22.
              ſqq.</hi>
          </note>, a natural hiſtorian of great <lb/>penetration, hath objected to Haller's de-
          <lb/>monſtration, that allowing the membranes <lb/>of the yolk with its inviſible veſſels
          to have <lb/>pre-exiſted in the hen, yet it is poſſible that <lb/>the embryo is only
          formed during incubation, <lb/>and that its blood-veſſels afterward unite with <lb/>the
          blood-veſſels of the membrane of the <lb/>yolk, and thus form an anaſtomoſis. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_47" n="38"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Baron von Haller immediately declared <lb/>loudly againſt this objection, and denied
          it <lb/>altogether as a thing <hi rend="italic">impoſſible,</hi> that the ten- <lb/>der
          veſſels of the microſcopic embryo ſhould <lb/>be capable of anaſtomoſing with the large
          <lb/>blood-veſſels of the giant yolk <note place="bottom" n="(t)">(t) <q
              rend="diple italic size(0.5)">Nunquam fieri poteſt ut inter tubulum <lb/>millioneſies
              minorem, et millioneſies majorem con- <lb/>tinuitas oviatur. Elenent. Phyſiol. <hi
                rend="roman">T. VIII. <lb/>P. 1. p. 94.</hi>compare with his firſt lines of Phy-
              <lb/>ſiology, <hi rend="roman">§ 883,</hi> and with the Opera Minora, <hi rend="roman"
                >T. <lb/>XI. p. 419.</hi> . </q>
          </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But what is rather ſingular, is, that <lb/>this ſame moſt ingenious and meritorious
          <lb/>author, who denies the poſſibility of ſuch an <lb/>anaſtomoſis, ſuppoſes without any
          heſitation, <lb/>and in the ſame work <note place="bottom" n="(u)" rend="italic size(0.5)"
            >(u) Elem. Phyſiolog. </note>, when explaining <lb/>human conception, that the very
          minute <lb/>germ as ſoon as it has arrived at the cavity <lb/>of the uterus, forms an
          adheſion with it by <pb xml:id="page_48" n="39"/>
          <lb/>means of its placenta;—And how? Juſt in <lb/>the ſame way that he denies it to the
          embryo <lb/>of the hen; that is to ſay, by an anaſtomoſis <lb/>taking place between the
          microſcopic and <lb/>tender branches of the umbilical veſſels, and <lb/>the giant ones of
          the maternal uterus. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The modern advocates for the theory of <lb/>evolution, have taken this obſervation of
          the <lb/>yolk of the egg, as the prop of their hypotheſis. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Long before this however, the ſpawn of <lb/>the frog had been employed for the ſame
          ſervice. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Near a century indeed before that period, <lb/>Swammerdam announced the wonderful
          diſ- <lb/>covery, that the black points in the ſpawn of <lb/>a frog were ſo many perfectly
          formed little <lb/>frogs, and that they pre-exiſted in the ovariæ, <lb/>although not to be
          diſcovered by the eye. <note place="bottom" n="(w)" rend="size(0.5) italic">(w) <q>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Miracl. Natur. <hi rend="italic">p. 21.</hi> "Admiratione <lb/>dignum eſt,
                nigrum illud punctum, quod in ovis <lb/>ranarum videre eſt, ipſum ranunculum omnibus
                <lb/>ſuis partibus abſolutum; albicantem verum et <lb/>circumfuſum illum liquorem
                non niſi alimentum <lb/>ejus eſſe; quod ipſum ſenſim dilatatum ita at-
                <lb/>tenuatur, ut exire cum velet poſſit," &amp;c. </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>"Magis mirum eſt hunc ipſum ranunculum in <lb/>ovaris uſque adeo exiguum ortus
                et incrementi ſui <lb/>principium habere, ut fere viſum effugiat, ut <lb/>ipſum
                animal ſub hac tantula mole deliteſcat." </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>And a little way further on, he draws the <lb/>general concluſion; "Nullus mihi
                in rerum naturæ <lb/>generationi, ſed ſoli propagatione vel incremento <lb/>partium
                locus eſſe videtur ubi caſus omnis exclu- <lb/>datur." </p>
            </q>
          </note>
        </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_49" n="40"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The good man ſeemed to have had a <lb/>pre-ſentiment of the uncertainty and inſta-
          <lb/>bility of all vain worldly honours, and he <lb/>therefore, as is well known, ſoon
          after be- <lb/>took himſelf to a more ſolid myſterious en- <lb/>joyment, in which Mlle.
          Bourignon bore a <lb/>part. And, indeed, it happened as he appears <pb xml:id="page_50"
            n="41"/>
          <lb/>to have foreſeen; for the ungrateful world <lb/>now aſcribe the merits of that
          diſcovery to <lb/>the celebrated Abbé Spallanzani, who has <lb/>maintained it in ſeveral
          of his writings, but <lb/>more particularly in the ſecond volume of his <lb/>Eſſays <note
            place="bottom" n="(x)" rend="size(0.5)">(x) Diſſertazioni di fiſica animale e vegeta-
            <lb/>bile, <hi rend="italic">T. XI.</hi> in Modena, <hi rend="roman">1780, 8.</hi>
          </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>He calls the little black points of the <lb/>fecundated ſpawn of frogs, Tadpoles, or
          young <lb/>frogs <note place="bottom" n="(y)">(y) <q rend="diple italic size(0.5)">A
              parlare filoſofocamente l'uovo non è <lb/>che il gerino in ſe ſteſſo concentrato, e
              riſtretto, il <lb/>quale mediante la fecondazione ſi ſviluppa ed ac- <lb/>quiſta le
              fatezze di animale. <bibl rend="roman">p. 11. § XVII. </bibl>
            </q>
          </note>; and as this little black point exact- <lb/>ly reſembles the ſame in the
          unfecundated <lb/>ſpawn <note place="bottom" n="(z)">(z) <q rend="diple italic size(0.5)"
              >Queſti globetti non fecondati non ſono <lb/>per verun conto diſtinguibili dai
              fecondati. <bibl rend="roman">§ <lb/>XVIII. </bibl>
            </q>
          </note>, he reaſons agreeably to his logic, <pb xml:id="page_51" n="42"/>
          <lb/>that the tadpoles muſt have exiſted in the <lb/>mother <note place="bottom" n="(a)"
            >(a) <q rend="diple italic size(0.5)">Ma i globetti fecondati non ſono che i <lb/>feti
              ranini, <hi rend="italic">§ XVII.</hi> Adunque i globetti non <lb/>fecondati lo
              ſaranno altreſi; e conſiguemente nella <lb/>noſtra rana il feto eſiſte in lei pria che
              abbiaſi <lb/>la fecondazione del maſchio. <bibl rend="roman">p. 12. § XIX. </bibl>
            </q>
          </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I do not know what would be thought of <lb/>that chemiſt who aſſertes that the Arbor
          <lb/>Dianæ pre-exiſted in a maſs of Amalgam of <lb/>ſilver, becauſe when a weak ſolution
          of ſilver <lb/>was poured on it, a little tree ſeemed to ſpring <lb/>out of it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>One ought to be aſhamed of waſting <lb/>much time in the refutation of an aſſertion,
          the <lb/>falſity of which any unprejudiced perſon who <lb/>is not altogether unaccuſtomed
          to obſervations <lb/>of the kind may convince himſelf of every <lb/>ſpring. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_52" n="43"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Whoever has taken the trouble, accu- <lb/>rately, to examine the ſpawn of the frog
          muſt <lb/>confeſs, that the idea of demonſtrating the little <lb/>black points contained
          in it to be ſo many <lb/>complete formed tadpoles, partakes greatly of <lb/>Brother
          Peters's method of reaſoning in the <lb/>Tale of the Tub, where he demonſtrates to his
          <lb/>brothers that the brown loaf is a piece of ex- <lb/>cellent roaſt mutton. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But the abettors of the theory of orga- <lb/>nized germs have gone a ſtep further in
          ſupport <lb/>of their opinions. They refer to caſes where <lb/>even young girls, in all
          their maiden innocence, <lb/>have become pregnant from the untimely, and <lb/>premature
          evolution of one of theſe organized <lb/>germs. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The concurrence of facts is ſometimes <lb/>moſt wonderful. It happened that in the
          very <lb/>ſame year that Swammerdam announced his <lb/>diſcovery in the ſpawn of the frog,
          that a caſe <lb/>was publiſhed in the <hi rend="italic">Ephem. rerum. nat. curios.</hi>
          <pb xml:id="page_53" n="44"/>
          <lb/>delivered to the ſociety by a celebrated court- <lb/>phyſician of thoſe times Dr.
          Claudius, which <lb/>exactly ſuited as a confirmation of Swam- <lb/>merdam's opinion.—A
          miller's wife was <lb/>delivered of a little girl whoſe belly ſeemed of <lb/>an unuſual
          ſize. Eight days afterwards this <lb/>little big-bellied child was ſeized with ſuch
          <lb/>violent pains and reſtleſſneſs, that every one <lb/>who was preſent thought it could
          not outlive <lb/>the next inſtant. The ſick infant however in <lb/>the mean time actually
          bore a well-formed, ele- <lb/>gant, lively, little daughter about the ſize of <lb/>one's
          middle finger, which was regularly <lb/>baptized. During the time, and after the
          <lb/>birth, the waters, placenta, and all other <lb/>impurities were rightly diſcharged.
          But both <lb/>the little mother and daughter died early the <lb/>following day <note
            place="bottom" n="(b)" rend="italic size(0.5)">(b) I adopt the very words of a
            contemporary <lb/>phyſician, Dr. Otto, who was conſulted by the <lb/>grandmother (the
            miller's wife) during her preg- <lb/>nancy. His nephew has vindicated and illuſtrated
            <lb/>the whole hiſtory in a moſt learned and ſubtile manner. <lb/>D. C. J. Aug. Ottonis
            Epiſtola de fætu puerpera <lb/>ſive de fætu in fætu. Weiſſenfels, <hi rend="roman">1748.
              8</hi>vo. <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>That this extraordinary hiſtory is alſo well <lb/>calculated to intereſt the
              caſuiſt is evident, from the <lb/>Diſquiſitionum filiola, quam act, dierum enfans
              <lb/>vivam enixa eſt babtiſmi capax. </p>
          </note>
        </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_54" n="45"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Baron von Haller very judiciouſly claſſes <lb/>this caſe with another from the
          Tranſactions <lb/>of the Academy of Sciences of Stockholm, <lb/>where on diſſecting a
          young girl, bones, teeth, <lb/>and hairs were found in a tumor of the my- <lb/>ſentery.
          Theſe two caſes he looks on as <lb/>principal evidences for the truth of the doc-
          <lb/>trine of germs pre-exiſting in the mother. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In Schmucker's Miſcellaneous Surgical <lb/>Eſſays an anonymus correſpondent ſends the
          <lb/>hiſtory of the diſſection of a girl, in whom, <lb/>inſtead of an uterus, there was
          found a hard <lb/>hairy body of the ſize of a large walnut, and <pb xml:id="page_55"
            n="46"/>
          <lb/>which reſembled an ill-ſhaped head. It had <lb/>two perfect teeth, and contained in
          its cavity <lb/>ſomething like brain. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Now ſince the abettors of the theory of <lb/>evolution ſo loudly remonſtrate againſt,
          and <lb/>complain of the unfair method of proceeding <lb/>by oppoſing mere argument to the
          facts which <lb/>they bring forward in ſupport of their opini- <lb/>ons, I ſhall for the
          preſent totally abſtain from <lb/>all reaſoning, and endeavour to ſatisfy theſe
          <lb/>gentlemen by adducing fact for fact, obſerva- <lb/>tion for obſervation, and thoſe of
          no leſs won- <lb/>derful, and entertaining a nature than theirs; <lb/>for they will prove,
          that not only men but <lb/>male animals have been equally in a thriving <lb/>way with
          young virgins; and I truſt the teſ- <lb/>timonies of the truth of theſe ſtories will be
          <lb/>found equally reſpectable with thoſe of the <lb/>oppoſite party. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>To the caſe extracted from the Memoirs <lb/>of the Academy of Stockholm I oppoſe one
          <lb/>from the Hiſtory of the Royal Academy of <pb xml:id="page_56" n="47"/>
          <lb/>Sciences of Paris, where an Abbé was inter- <lb/>rupted very <hi rend="italic">mal
            apropos</hi> whilſt inſtituting ſome <lb/>experiments on generation. He was alarmed
          <lb/>by an extraordinary encreaſe of bulk in a cer- <lb/>tain part, which another Abbé
          (the unfortunate <lb/>Abelard) was deprived of in conſequence of a <lb/>ſimilar
          experiment. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The tumor encreaſed ſo much that he <lb/>was obliged to ſubmit to an operation, and
          his <lb/>ſurgeon aſſured the academy that he cut an <lb/>oſſified child <note
            place="bottom" n="(c)">(c) <q rend="diple italic size(0.5)">On y diſtinguoit la tête,
              les pieds, et les <lb/>yeux. </q>
          </note> from the part. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>To the ſtory of the miller's wife I beg <lb/>leave to ſubjoin one from the
          Philoſophical <lb/>Tranſactions of London, where an account is <lb/>given of a male
          greyhound that bore a living <lb/>puppy <hi rend="italic">per anum;</hi> and in the place
          of Drs. <lb/>Otto an Claudius, who witneſſed the truth of <lb/>the firſt fact, I ſhall
          mention two names of <pb xml:id="page_57" n="48"/>
          <lb/>which England ought to boaſt: Dr. Wallis, <lb/>and Edmund Halley. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Laſtly to the anonymous in Schmucker <lb/>I oppoſe an anonymous in the works of the
          <lb/>reſpectable Fr. Ruyſh, who was preſented with <lb/>a ſimilar production. It was a
          bony caſe, <lb/>half as big as a common walnut, together with <lb/>four perfect <hi
            rend="italic">mollares,</hi> and a knot of hair, <lb/>which, he aſſured the doctor, he
          had cut from <lb/>the ſtomach of a male ſubject. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Thus I have adduced authority for au- <lb/>thority; nor do I believe it poſſible for
          any <lb/>one to go more conſcienteouſly to work than <lb/>I have done; and ſo far
          therefore I uſt we <lb/>are quits. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Were I allowed however to ſpeak my <lb/>mind freely on this matter, I ſhould adviſe
          <lb/>all ſuch auxiliary troops to be withdrawn. <lb/>My only reaſon for bringing them on
          the field <lb/>was merely to oppoſe thoſe of my antago- <lb/>niſts. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_58" n="49"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Theſe therefore are the principal argu- <lb/>ments, which, I have to oppoſe to what
          the <lb/>advocates for the theory of evolution conſider <lb/>as the ſtrongeſt, and moſt
          deciſive proofs of <lb/>their theory. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But experience ſupplies me with another <lb/>ſource of facts, which may be uſed as
          argu- <lb/>ments againſt this theory, and which, to <lb/>unprejudiced, and judicious
          readers, ought to <lb/>be ſufficient whereby to aſcertain its true degree <lb/>of
          probability. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>For inſtance, the well eſtabliſhed, and <lb/>univerſal truth; that the firſt
          appearance of a <lb/>newly conceived animal, or plant, is never to <lb/>be diſcovered
          immediately on impregnation, <lb/>even by the moſt powerful armed eye; no <lb/>ſuch thing
          is to be ſeen until a conſiderable <lb/>time has elapſed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is not worth while to enter into a refu- <lb/>tation of the fabulous aſſertion of
          Hippocrates, <lb/>and of ſo many others of his old and worthy <lb/>followers, that
          perfectly diſtinct, and well <pb xml:id="page_59" n="50"/>
          <lb/>formed human embryos were to be ſeen in the <lb/>very firſt days of conception.
          Conſidering <lb/>the few aids, and little opportunity they had <lb/>in thoſe days of
          making ſuch obſervations, <lb/>great allowance is to be made; and the more <lb/>ſo, when
          we conſider that even modern phy- <lb/>ſicians of much more extenſive experience in
          <lb/>theſe matters, have been guilty of ſimilar <lb/>aſſertions. Mauriceau has amuſed us
          with re- <lb/>preſentations of fœtuſſes of one day, and of <lb/>three days and a half,
          &amp;c. and Malpighi and <lb/>Croune have aſſured us that they had ſeen the <lb/>embryo of
          the chick and its appendices in <lb/>the egg of a trod hen before the egg had been
          <lb/>ſate upon. The laſt author indeed obſerved <lb/>it, he ſays, in the addle egg of hens
          that never <lb/>had been cocked. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is impoſſible however to diſcover <lb/>any thing before the third week after
          concep- <lb/>tion, which any cautious and creditable obſer- <lb/>ver would preſume to
          pronounce a human em- <lb/>bryo, and in the fecundated egg nothing can <lb/>be obſerved,
          which has even the moſt diſtant <pb xml:id="page_60" n="51"/>
          <lb/>reſemblance to a chick in the firſt twelve <lb/>hours, nor indeed until the end of
          the ſecond <lb/>day. Previous to this period of time peculiar <lb/>to each animal, and
          vegetable, <note place="bottom" n="(d)" rend="size(0.5) italic">(d) In the hare the firſt
            traces of the young are <lb/>not ſeen until the ninth day; in the ſheep not before
            <lb/>the nineteenth; in the deer not before the ſeventh <lb/>week. </note> it is quite
          <lb/>impoſſible to diſtinguiſh the newly conceived <lb/>offſpring; which circumſtance,
          conſidering <lb/>the perfection, and powers of our microſcopes, <lb/>is by no means
          favourable to the theory of <lb/>evolution. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Nor, is it at all eaſy to comprehend how the <lb/>advocates for that theory make the
          phenomena <lb/>of the accidental origin and growth of certain <lb/>preternatural parts
          agree with their doctrine <lb/>of pre-exiſting organic germs. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A few inſtances of this kind will ſerve <lb/>inſtead of many. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_61" n="52"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A woman conceives, but the fœtus in- <lb/>ſtead of being in the uterus, is ſituated
          in one of <lb/>the Fallopean tubes. The tube at laſt burſts <lb/>from the increaſe of bulk
          of this ſtrayed animal, <lb/>and it falls into the cavity of the abdomen. <lb/>What does
          nature do? She pours out a quan- <lb/>tity of plaſtic lymph, which forms itſelf evidently
          <lb/>into organized membranes, incruſting and <lb/>inveloping the fœtus like a mummy, by
          which <lb/>it is prevented from putrefaction; for were <lb/>this allowed to take place, it
          would occaſion <lb/>certain death to the mother, but who, preſerved <lb/>by this
          contrivance, is enabled to carry the <lb/>troubleſome, though not dangerous load, for
          <lb/>a conſiderable number of years. On opening <lb/>the body after death, we evidently
          perceive <lb/>this new, and, accidentally formed membrane, <lb/>to be richly ſupplied with
          blood veſſels, <note place="bottom" n="(e)" rend="size(0.5) italic">(e) In the eighth
            volume of the Commentaries of <lb/>the Royal Society of Göitingen I have given the
            <lb/>deſcription of a fœtus of this kind which had lain <lb/>eight years within the
            mother. This ſpecimen <lb/>was preſented to the Muſeum of the Academy by my <lb/>very
            worthy friend Mr. Buchner of Gotha. </note>
          <pb xml:id="page_62" n="53"/>
          <lb/>which it would be rather difficult to prove, had <lb/>pre-exiſted in the organic
          germ. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A perſon breaks both bones of the fore- <lb/>arm, but is ſo reſtleſs as to diſturb
          nature in <lb/>her uſual proceſs of healing them, that is, by <lb/>means of a new
          oſſification. In this caſe what <lb/>does ſhe do? She forms a new joint of the <lb/>broken
          ends of both bones; making as it were <lb/>a ſecond elbow which can be moved at
          <lb/>pleaſure without any aſſiſtance from the other <lb/>hand. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Another perſon diſlocates his thigh bone <lb/>from it's natural ſituation in the
          Ilium, and <lb/>nature endeavours to remedy the evil, by for- <lb/>ming a new ſocket for
          it <note place="bottom" n="(f)" rend="italic size(0.5)">(f) In my Oſteology I have given
            numerous <lb/>examples of this, vid. page <hi rend="roman">43.</hi>
          </note>. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_63" n="54"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A child is born with a hydrocephalus, <lb/>occaſioned by mere accidental
          circumſtances; <lb/>ſuch for inſtance as the frequent, and too <lb/>violent connection of
          the father with the <lb/>mother, during the time of her geſtation. <lb/>Owing to this
          diſeaſe, the cranium becomes <lb/>preternaturally diſtended, and immence ſpaces <lb/>are
          left between the very thin, and greatly <lb/>diſtended bones. In order to remedy this,
          <lb/>nature forms detached oſſeous points in theſe <lb/>interſtices, which points, at laſt
          become true <lb/><hi rend="italic">oſſa triquetra,</hi> filling up all the dangerous
          <lb/>voids, and uniting all the bones of the head <lb/>together. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Theſe <hi rend="italic">oſſa triquetra</hi> however do not <lb/>belong to the natural
          ſtructure of the fœtus, and are <lb/>very ſeldom to be met with in the ſculls of
          <lb/>ſavages, or of brute animals. It is hardly <lb/>poſſible therefore that they ſhould
          have pre- <lb/>exiſted in the organic germ: and yet they are <lb/>as perfect bones as any
          others of the head, <lb/>having true, and well formed ſutures. The <lb/>ſutures of theſe
          bones are not always locked <pb xml:id="page_64" n="55"/>
          <lb/>in with the ſutures of the other bones of the <lb/>head; but it often happens, that
          they are ſo <lb/>numerous, and ſo thick together, that thoſe <lb/>in the middle evidently
          conſtruct their own <lb/>ones. What is there however which exhi- <lb/>bits more art than
          the ſtructure of a true <lb/>ſuture; its double, nay treble row of teeth, <lb/>the
          correſponding depreſſions, and the aſto- <lb/>niſhing manner in which they are claſped
          <lb/>together? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The concluſion which naturally follows, <lb/>is, that if perfect bones, new and
          preter- <lb/>natural joints, new organized and vaſcular <lb/>membranes can be formed,
          where there was <lb/>no ground for ſuppoſing a pre-exiſting germ, <lb/>what neceſſity is
          there for this doctrine of <lb/>envelopement? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But the phenomena which occur in the <lb/>generation of mules, ſo completely reſute
          all <lb/>our ideas of pre-exiſting organic germs, that <lb/>one is at a loſs to imagine,
          how, after a due <lb/>attention to this ſubject, ſuch a theory ſhould <pb xml:id="page_65"
            n="56"/>
          <lb/>have found any ſerious abettors. I ſhould <lb/>ſuppoſe that a ſingle experiment, ſuch
          as that <lb/>of Mr. Koelreuter, who by repeatedly produ- <lb/>cing prolific baſtard
          plants, transformed one <lb/>ſpecies of tobacco (<hi rend="italic">nicotiana ruſtica</hi>)
          into <lb/>another (<hi rend="italic">nicotiana paniculata</hi>) ſo completely, <lb/>that
          it had not the ſmalleſt reſemblance to its <lb/>maternal parent; that ſuch an experiment,
          I ſay <lb/>muſt cure the moſt partial advocate for the <lb/>theory of evolution, of his
          error. This <lb/>excellent obſerver, by artificially impregna- <lb/>ting the firſt ſpecies
          of tobacco with the farina <lb/>of the laſt mentioned, obtained prolific baſtard
          <lb/>ſeeds from it, and with the plants which ſprung <lb/>from theſe, he repeated the ſame
          experiment, <lb/>impregnating them with the farina of <lb/>the Nicotiana paniculata. As
          the plants <lb/>which he procured from the ſeeds of this laſt <lb/>combination, differed
          more from the original <lb/>maternal plant, he repeated the ſame proceſs <lb/>with it, and
          proceeded to do ſo with every new <lb/>offſpring, untill he obtained ſix plants, which
          <lb/>in every reſpect appeared perfectly ſimilar to <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
            >paniculata;</hi> ſo that in the claſſical work, <pb xml:id="page_66" n="57"/>
          <lb/>in which he gives a narrative of this, he <lb/>appears perfectly juſtifiable in
          entitling it, <hi rend="italic">A <lb/>complete metamorphoſis of one natural ſpecies of
            <lb/>plants into another.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I know perfectly well, that the favour- <lb/>ers of the theory of evolution endeavour
          to <lb/>explain the production of baſtards, or mules, <lb/>by ſaying, that the male ſemen,
          beſides its <lb/>ſtimulating power of awakening the female <lb/>germs from their ſtate of
          ſtupor, and inactivi- <lb/>ty; alſo aſcribe to it certain <hi rend="italic">formative</hi>
          powers, <lb/>by which the germ may be altered in a certain <lb/>degree, ſo as ſo reſemble
          the father a little. <lb/>But what in the name of Heaven is ſuch a <lb/>ſubterfuge than
          the ſilent acknowledgement of <lb/>the inſufficiency of the germ theory, and of <lb/>the
          neceſſity of having recourſe to formative <lb/>powers, in order to extricate it? If theſe
          <lb/>formative powers, however, are ſo ſtrong as <lb/>totally to change the ſtructure and
          appear- <lb/>ance of the maternal germ, and that in the <lb/>courſe of a few generations,
          it is rather diffi- <lb/>cult to conceive the utility of ſuch a theory. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="section">
        <pb xml:id="page_67" n="59"/>
        <head rend="align-center italic">
          <lb/><hi rend="roman">SECT. III.</hi>
          <lb/>Proofs of the Formative Niſus, and an Attempt to aſcertain ſome of its Laws. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>T is eaſier to overturn, than to eſtabliſh a <lb/>theory; and
          the reproach has been often <lb/>applied to old reformers, that they have ſuc- <lb/>ceeded
          better in attempts of the firſt, than of <lb/>the laſt kind. Yet what Mons. Bonnet ex-
          <lb/>cellently remarks on this ſubject may be very <lb/>true <note place="bottom" n="(g)"
            >(g) <q rend="italic size(0.5)">Demontrer une errcur, c'eſt plus que de- <lb/>couvrir
              une ve<unclear>#</unclear>ité: car l'on peut ignorer beaucoup; <lb/>mais le peut que
              l'on ſcait, il faut au moins le ſavoir <lb/>bien. Preſace de l'Eſſai ſur l'ame. </q>
          </note>, that the detection of an error is often <lb/>of greater conſequence than the
          diſcovery of <pb xml:id="page_68" n="60"/>
          <lb/>a new fact. In this reſpect therefore, I truſt <lb/>the preſent ſheets will at leaſt
          be allowed <lb/>ſome merits, ſince they point out the defects <lb/>of a late beloved, and
          almoſt univerſally <lb/>adopted theory. I hope, however, at the <lb/>ſame time, that the
          one which I give in <lb/>its place will be found more agreeable to what <lb/>we obſerve in
          nature. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>No one can be more fully perſuaded of <lb/>the immenſe gap which exiſts between the
          <lb/>organiſed, and unorganiſed, between the ani- <lb/>mated, and the inanimate world,
          than I am; <lb/>and although I have the greateſt reſpect for <lb/>the penetration of thoſe
          who diſcover a <lb/>gradual ſcale of aſcent and deſcent in the <lb/>works of nature, yet I
          confeſs I am at a loſs <lb/>to gueſs how they make it paſs from organic <lb/>to inorganic
          bodies. Such a reflection, how- <lb/>ever, ought by no means, to deter us from em-
          <lb/>ploying the phenomena of either of theſe <lb/>claſſes of bodies for explaining the
          phenomena <lb/>of the other: and ſo far do I conſider it as <lb/>an argument, not of the
          leaſt importance, for <pb xml:id="page_69" n="61"/>
          <lb/>proving the exiſtence of the Formative Niſus <lb/>in organic bodies, that even in the
          inorganic <lb/>ones there exiſts traces of a Formative Power; <lb/>not of a Formative <hi
            rend="italic">Niſus</hi> however, at leaſt, <lb/>in the ſenſe this word is uſed in this
          work; <lb/>for here it is conſidered as one of the pro- <lb/>perties of the living
          principle, and conſe- <lb/>quently not to be imagined as belonging to <lb/>dead matter:
          but that this laſt Formative <lb/>Power is demonſtrated by the regularity and
          <lb/>invariable ſhape of certain bodies which we <lb/>find to be formed of it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>For only to adduce one or two inſtances, <lb/>we find nothing more elegant, than
          certain <lb/>metallic cryſtallizations, which as to their <lb/>external aſpect, bear ſo
          ſtriking a reſemblance <lb/>to certain organized bodies, that they become <lb/>a very good
          example for explaining to us the <lb/>manner in which bodies are formed from rude <lb/>and
          unorganized matter. Such for inſtance, <lb/>is that ſpecies of native dendritical ſilver,
          <lb/>imbeded in a matrix of quarz from Mexico, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Farnkrautſilber,</hi> and which reſembles the fo- <pb xml:id="page_70" n="62"/>
          <lb/>liage of the fern, or to name ſomething more <lb/>common, that undeſcribable
          beautiful moſs- <lb/>looking texture of braſs, which is obſerved <lb/>in breaking a piece
          of it, after the firſt <lb/>fuſion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Theſe as I have already ſaid, are ad- <lb/>duced as mere examples of the exiſtence of
          <lb/>a Formative Principle in unorganized bodies. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And now for the true formative effort in <lb/>the animated world. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I know no means ſo well calculated for <lb/>rendering the exiſtence, and activity of
          this <lb/>niſus evident to an impartial eye, as to ob- <lb/>ſerve the origin and progreſs
          of ſuch orga- <lb/>nized bodies, which increaſe ſo rapidly in <lb/>bulk, that the action
          of the growth becomes <lb/>almoſt evident; and which are of ſo delicate <lb/>and
          ſemitranſparent a texture, as to be capable <lb/>of being evidently ſeen through with the
          aſ- <lb/>ſiſtance of a microſcope, and a due degree of <lb/>light. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_71" n="63"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The vegetable kingdom ſupplies us with <lb/>a very good example of this kind, in the
          <lb/>ſimple production of a moſt ſimple water <lb/>plant, <hi rend="italic">(conferva
            fontinalis)</hi> which is com- <lb/>monly to be met with every ſpring, in wells,
          <lb/>ponds, and ſprings, or in the wooden pipes <lb/>through which water flows. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The whole plant conſiſts of a ſingle <lb/>uniform ſtraight fine thread, of a bright
          <lb/>green colour, and about half an inch in <lb/>length, and whoſe under extremity is
          generally <lb/>inſerted in a bed of ſlime. As theſe threads, <lb/>however, are extremely
          numerous, and grow <lb/>very cloſe together, they look like a very fine <lb/>fur of the
          moſt beautiful green colour, with <lb/>which conſiderable ſpaces of the places above
          <lb/>mentioned are ſometimes covered. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I have attentively obſerved the propaga- <lb/>tion of this water plant in the
          beginning of <lb/>the ſpring, and to me it appeared to take place <lb/>in the following
          manner. The upper end <pb xml:id="page_72" n="64"/>
          <lb/>of the fibrile began gradually to ſwell, and <lb/>divide into a number of ſmall round
          points, <lb/>which at laſt diſengaged themſelves from the <lb/>parental thread, and in the
          number of ſome <lb/>thouſands, attached themſelves to the ſides <lb/>of the glaſs in which
          I made the experiment. <lb/>Soon afterwards, theſe round bodies began <lb/>to ſhoot out a
          ſmall point, which almoſt <lb/>viſibly lengthened till they had acquired their <lb/>due
          ſize. All this took place in the ſpace of <lb/>twice twenty-four hours, counting from the
          <lb/>firſt moment that the end of the old thread <lb/>began to ſwell. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Both the rapid growth of this plant, <lb/>and its tranſparent texture, afforded me
          means <lb/>of diſcovering not only its ſtructure, but alſo <lb/>the ſlighteſt changes that
          took place in it. <lb/>This kind of moſs is equally ſimple inter- <lb/>nally, as
          externally; and under the ſtrongeſt <lb/>magnifying powers, and by the beſt light, <lb/>we
          can diſcover nothing elſe than a fine ve- <lb/>ſicular appearance, like a green froth,
          ſur- <lb/>rounded by a very thin delicate membrane. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_73" n="65"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But in ſpite of the diſtinctneſs of texture <lb/>of the little green points which
          adhered to <lb/>the ſides of the veſſel, there was nothing to <lb/>be ſeen like the germ
          of an enveloped filament <lb/>in them, ſuch as was ſoon to be produced from <lb/>it: but
          only when the little round body had <lb/>attained a certain degree of perfection, a ſmall
          <lb/>ſhoot ſeemed to ſpring out of it, in ſuch a <lb/>manner, that its act of evolution
          ſeemed to be <lb/>promoted merely by that part of the veſicular <lb/>texture of the round
          point, which was moſt <lb/>contiguous to the filament, paſſing gradually <lb/>over to it.
          As the filament encreaſed in <lb/>length, the little round body gradually de- <lb/>creaſed
          in magnitude, and became of a paler <lb/>colour, ſo that at laſt, when the filament had
          <lb/>arrived at its full growth, there remained juſt <lb/>a perceptible ſwelling at the
          inferior end, and <lb/>which ſerved as a root to the new filament. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>With an equal degree of diſtinctneſs <lb/>with which the progreſs of the Formative
          <lb/>Niſus of this plant becomes conſpicuous, we <lb/>can alſo clearly diſcover it in many
          animals; <pb xml:id="page_74" n="66"/>
          <lb/>eſpecially in ſuch, as like this kind of moſs, <lb/>poſſeſs the advantages of a rapid
          growth, and <lb/>great tranſparency of texture. This is the <lb/>caſe with the armed
          polypi, which on account <lb/>of the miracles they are capable of performing, <lb/>have
          within theſe laſt forty years been an object <lb/>of general ſurpriſe, and admiration. All
          the <lb/>known ſpecies of this animal have a kind of <lb/>gelatinous body, which, whether
          it be of a <lb/>green, yellow or brown colour, &amp;c. is ſtill <lb/>ſufficiently
          tranſparent to be capable of being <lb/>diſtinctly ſeen through, if a proper lens and
          <lb/>light be employed. Its texture is uniform, <lb/>and ſimple, and ſo homogenous,
          conſiſting en- <lb/>tirely of gelatinous points, which ſeem to be kept <lb/>together by a
          ſtill thinner jelly, that nothing <lb/>ſeems concealed from or obſcured to the eye of
          <lb/>the obſerver. Now, when this animal is about <lb/>to produce its young, a ſwelling or
          tumefaction <lb/>takes place on a ſingle ſpot of its body; and <lb/>from this ſwelling
          there ſhoots out firſt the <lb/>cylindrical body, and then the tentaculæ of <lb/>the young
          polypus. Theſe are all of ſo con- <lb/>ſiderable a ſize as to be obſerved with the <pb
            xml:id="page_75" n="67"/>
          <lb/>naked eye: and when we conſider this cir- <lb/>cumſtance, and all the others already
          mention- <lb/>ed, there does not appear the ſmalleſt probable <lb/>ground for ſuppoſing,
          that an organized germ <lb/>had pre-exiſted there, and was now evolving. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I refer it to the internal feelings of <lb/>every one who has attentively obſerved
          this <lb/>kind of production in animals, and plants of <lb/>ſo ſimple a texture as thoſe
          alluded to, and <lb/>who at the ſame time have well attended to <lb/>all the arguments
          brought forward in the fore- <lb/>going fection againſt the doctrine of the
          <lb/>pre-exiſtence of the embryo of the chick in <lb/>the yolk of the egg, whether in
          paſſing in <lb/>his own mind to the generation of the more <lb/>perfect or warm-blooded
          animals (as for <lb/>inſtance by the moſt accurate inveſtigation of <lb/>the phenomena of
          the beginning, progreſs, and <lb/>form of the embryo in the fecundated egg, and <lb/>alſo
          of the many other parts <note place="bottom" n="(h)" rend="size(0.5) italic'">(h) Nidus
            pulli, bulla amnion, figura venoſa, <lb/>&amp;c. </note> which are <lb/>never <pb
            xml:id="page_76" n="68"/>
          <lb/>to be found in the unfecunded one) whether, <lb/>I ſay, his conviction leads him to
          believe in <lb/>the pre-exiſtence of enveloped organic germs; <lb/>or, in the exiſtence of
          a <hi rend="italic">niſus,</hi> by which a new <lb/>being is formed from the unorganized
          mate- <lb/>rials of generation. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>All the arguments which have hitherto <lb/>been deduced from the phenomena of genera-
          <lb/>tion in ſupport of the exiſtence of a <hi rend="italic">Niſus <lb/>Formativus,</hi>
          gains new, and additional weight <lb/>from the conſideration of the phenomena of <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">reproduction;</hi> this ſo wonderful power of <lb/>organiſed bodies by
          which loſt, and mutilated <lb/>parts are again renewed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Generation, and reproduction are both <lb/>modifications of one, and the ſame power;
          <lb/>the laſt being nothing elſe than a partial <lb/>repetition of the firſt. Whatever
          tends to <lb/>elucidate the one, muſt therefore throw light <lb/>on the other. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_77" n="69"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I have frequently repeated the experi- <lb/>ments alluded to in the Firſt Section, by
          <lb/>which I endeavoured to diſcover the power <lb/>of reproduction in the green armed
          polypus, <lb/>and have conſtantly met with the ſame ſuc- <lb/>cess. The little mutilated
          animal was always <lb/>diminiſhed in bulk, in proportion as its new <lb/>arms or new body
          were puſhed out. It be- <lb/>came evident with what efforts nature haſtened <lb/>to renew
          the determinate form of the maimed <lb/>animal, and alſo, that from the ſhort period
          <lb/>of time, and the improbability of the polypus <lb/>having taken a ſufficient quantity
          of nouriſh- <lb/>ment to ſupply materials for the new mem- <lb/>bers (ſince all wounded
          polypi eat leſs than <lb/>uſual); From theſe circumſtances I ſay, it <lb/>became evident,
          that owing to the force of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Formative Niſus</hi> with which the
          parts <lb/>were endowed, the remaining portion of <lb/>the mutilated animal, was in ſome
          degree, <lb/>converted into the new members, and thus <lb/>the diſturbed ſtructure
          renewed. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_78" n="70"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I am well aware, that the advocates for <lb/>the theory of Evolution, will, in order
          to <lb/>help themſelves out of this difficulty, have <lb/>recourſe to an hypotheſis, which
          of all im- <lb/>probable ones, may be ſtiled the moſt ro- <lb/>mantic, and improbable; and
          according to <lb/>which it is ſuppoſed, <q rend="quotes">That in every part of <lb/>the
            polypus, there exiſts innumerable germs <lb/>enveloped, and torpid as it were, which
            <lb/>lie like a hidden ſtore, untill it ſhall pleaſe <lb/>the fancy of a naturaliſt to
            rouſe them <lb/>into action, and free them from their ſtate <lb/>of impriſonment, by the
            enlivening cut of <lb/>a pair of ſciſſars. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Now, let any one compare this expla- <lb/>nation with the naked appearances which
          take <lb/>place in the above, and many other experi- <lb/>ments on the armed polypus, the
          proceſs of <lb/>which are ſo eaſy to be diſcovered.—I ſhall <lb/>at preſent content myſelf
          with relating two of <lb/>theſe experiments. When we take the half <lb/>of two polypi of
          different kinds, for inſtance, <pb xml:id="page_79" n="71"/>
          <lb/>the anterior half of a green one, and the poſ- <lb/>terior half of a brown one, and
          bring them <lb/>together at the bottom of a proper glaſs, they <lb/>join together, and
          form in this manner, one <lb/>of theſe monſters of mythology, repreſenting <lb/>a group
          compoſed of different parts of different <lb/>animals. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>According to the theory of Evolution, <lb/>however, very different phenomena muſt
          have <lb/>occurred. Inſtead of this junction between <lb/>the two halves, each one ought
          to have <lb/>evolved from an organic germ that part of <lb/>which it had been deprived of;
          but this is not <lb/>what we obſerve; it was more natural that <lb/>the two parts ſhould
          join by the means of <lb/>their formative powers, than that each of <lb/>the halves ſhould
          of itſelf have been metamor- <lb/>phoſed to a complete animal by the manner <lb/>deſcribed
          above. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>There is a well known experiment how- <lb/>ever, which is admirably calculated to de-
          <lb/>monſtrate both the improbability of the ſup- <pb xml:id="page_80" n="72"/>
          <lb/>poſed pre-exiſting germs, and at the ſame <lb/>time, the activity of the <hi
            rend="italic">Formative Niſus.</hi>
          <lb/>When we take the polypus, and do not divide <lb/>it in pieces, but merely ſlit open
          its belly <lb/>longitudinally, ſo as to deſtroy that cavity; <lb/>and as it were,
          metamorphoſe the ſhape of <lb/>the animal from a cylindrical to a flat form; <lb/>inſtead
          of a number of organic germs being <lb/>ſet free from the cut edges, and of their being
          <lb/>each evolved, one of the two following oc- <lb/>currences takes place; either the
          animal rolls <lb/>itſelf together in the uſual form, ſo that the <lb/>edges of the wound
          meet and coaleſce, or <lb/>if it remains like a piece of flat tape, it begins <lb/>ſoon
          after to ſwell in the middle, as if it were <lb/>blown up, and there is gradually formed
          within <lb/>it a new belly. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In both theſe caſes there is no occaſion <lb/>for new <hi rend="italic"
            >materials,</hi> all that is done is a mere <lb/><hi rend="italic">reparation</hi> of
          the <hi rend="italic">diſturbed ſtructure.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In man and other warm-blooded animals <lb/>the power of reproduction is much more li-
            <pb xml:id="page_81" n="73"/>
          <lb/>mited; not only on account of the great diverſity <lb/>of materials of which they are
          compoſed, but alſo <lb/>the different quantity of living principle peculiar <lb/>to each
          of theſe materials, and by the mutual de- <lb/>pendance and action which they exerciſe on
          <lb/>each other. And yet we often obſerve in them <lb/>evident marks of this power of
          reproduction, <lb/>tending to confirm all that has been ſaid on this <lb/>head, concerning
          the polypus; nails have been <lb/>obſerved to grow on the ſtump of a finger, even
          <lb/>although the firſt joint was completely loſt <note place="bottom" n="(i)"
            rend="italic size(0.5)">(i) Pecklin and Talp have ſeen inſtances of <lb/>this kind. </note>
          <lb/>It would be rather a bold conjecture to ſuppoſe <lb/>that nature had foreſeen ſuch
          accidents, and had <lb/>therefore ſown all the fingers and toes with the <lb/>organic
          germs of nails, &amp;c. And on the <lb/>contrary, how agreeable to nature is it to
          <lb/>deduce the whole phenomenon from the <lb/>activity of the formative powers, whoſe
          efforts <lb/>are ſufficiently ſtrong to reproduce nails on the <lb/>extremities of the
          fingers, nay even in un- <lb/>uſual parts. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_82" n="74"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Another equally well known, and inter- <lb/>eſting fact of this kind, is, where
          nature en- <lb/>deavours to ſupply the loſs of an extremity, whoſe <lb/>complicated
          ſtructure it would have been <lb/>difficult for her to reſtore, by the production <lb/>of
          a more ſimple and uniform ſubſtance. <lb/>Thus, that celebrated ſurgeon, Morand, gives
          <lb/>the deſcription of a hare, which, a conſiderable <lb/>time before its death, had had
          one of its fore <lb/>legs ſhot off, the place of which nature <lb/>had endeavoured to
          ſupply with a kind of bony <lb/>ſtump, which, although not like the original, <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">quoad materiem,</hi> yet reſembled <hi rend="italic">taliter qualiter
            <lb/>quoad forman</hi>
          <note place="bottom" n="(k)">(k) <q rend="diple quotes italic size(0.5)">C'etoit, to uſe
              his own expreſſion une <lb/>eſpéce de jambe de bois, dont la nature ſcule avoit
              <lb/>faet le pais. </q>
          </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If, as I flatter myſelf, the few phenome- <lb/>na of generation, and reproduction
          already <lb/>taken notice of, are ſufficient to prove the un- <pb xml:id="page_83" n="75"/>
          <lb/>deniable exiſtence of the <hi rend="italic">Formative Niſus,</hi>
          <lb/>there remain many others tending to explain <lb/>its <hi rend="italic">modus
            operandi;</hi> and to aſcertain ſome of <lb/>the laws by which that mode ſeems to be
          <lb/>regulated. I look upon the following to be <lb/>of this kind, that is, as the mere
          reſult of <lb/>undoubted obſervation. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="1">
          <lb/>I. <hi rend="italic">The activity of the Niſus, is, in an <lb/>inverſe ratio, to the
            age of the organized body.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>For however certain it may be, as has been <lb/>formerly remarked, that ſome time is
          neceſ- <lb/>ſary before the firſt marks of the new conceived <lb/>fruit becomes viſible,
          yet it is equally well <lb/>aſcertained, that after this interval, the forma- <lb/>tion
          proceeds with aſtoniſhing celerity. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In general, the embryos of the earlier <lb/>months are repreſented in a very
          unſhapely <lb/>form, but this may be owing either to the <lb/>perſon who gives the
          repreſentation; or to <lb/>this, that ſuch abortions generally ſuffer much <lb/>by
          external violence, are ſqueezed, compreſſed, <pb xml:id="page_84" n="76"/>
          <lb/>or from putrefaction having already begun, <lb/>loſe much of their uncommon elegance,
          which <lb/>otherwiſe render them objects of admiration. <lb/>I poſſeſs ſome of theſe
          beautiful human fœtuſſes <lb/>of the firſt months of pregnancy, eſpecially <lb/>thoſe
          which I received from my dear friend <lb/>Mr. Bückner of Gotha, where in one of five
          <lb/>weeks old, and of the ſize of a common bee, <lb/>all the features of the face, every
          ſinger com- <lb/>plete, every toe, and the organs of generation <lb/>were to be diſtinctly
          ſeen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Now this early activity of the Formative <lb/>Niſus, is by no means confined to the
          external <lb/>form of the embryo, but is ſtill more remark- <lb/>able in the internal
          ſtructure. I have often <lb/>been aſtoniſhed at the early perfection of the <lb/>vicera,
          which I have diſcovered in diſſecting <lb/>recent human embryos of the firſt months.
          <lb/>Thus, merely to mention one circumſtance <lb/>in its head, which was hardly larger
          than a <lb/>pea, the whole cartilaginous <hi rend="italic">baſis cranii,</hi> with
          <lb/>all its depreſſions, apertures, and proceſſes, <lb/>were marked in the moſt ſharp and
          diſtinct <pb xml:id="page_85" n="77"/>
          <lb/>manner, although, indeed, there was not the <lb/>ſmalleſt point of oſſification,
          either in the <lb/>ſphenoid bone, or the petrous part of the <lb/>temporal one. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>However difficult it may be on the ſup- <lb/>poſition of pre-exiſting germs, to
          explain <lb/>what becomes of them for ſo long a time after <lb/>they arrive at the place
          of their deſtination, <lb/>and are fecundated and ſtimulated to evolu- <lb/>tion; it is
          equally difficult to imagine, why <lb/>immediately after this interval, they ſhould
          <lb/>ſo ſuddenly acquire ſo reſpectable a ſize. On <lb/>the contrary, after it has been
          fully underſtood, <lb/>what was ſaid concerning the time neceſſary <lb/>for the
          preparation of the fluids of generation, <lb/>before the Formative Niſus takes place;
          <lb/>there remains nothing puzzling in this, <lb/>that then the new awakened action ſhould
          ſo <lb/>ſoon form the ground work of the new <lb/>animal. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>That the inverſe ratio between the For- <lb/>mative Niſus, and the increaſe of age,
            <pb xml:id="page_86" n="78"/>
          <lb/>continues even after birth, is proved by the <lb/>remarkable eaſe with which
          reproduction takes <lb/>place in very young animals, eſpecially thoſe <lb/>of the lizard
          kind, as in the common newt. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="2">
          <lb/>II. <hi rend="italic">The Formative Niſus is much more <lb/>active in the embryos of
            mamelia, than in <lb/>thoſe of oviparous animals.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In the chick for inſtance, the firſt ap- <lb/>pearance of the ribs is obſerved one
          hundred <lb/>and twenty-nine hours after impregnation. <lb/>This period is equal to the
          nineteenth week <lb/>of geſtation in, the human ſpecies. But I <lb/>have in my poſſeſſion,
          human fœtuſſes, which <lb/>are not more than ſix weeks old, and yet in <lb/>which, the
          cartilaginous rudiments of the <lb/>ribs are to be diſtinctly diſcovered. It would
          <lb/>appear as if nature made greater haſte with <lb/>the formation of viviparous animals,
          to ſecure <lb/>them againſt deformity, from acccidental <lb/>cauſes, ſuch as preſſure,
          external violence, <lb/>&amp;c. from which cauſes all oviparous animals <lb/>are defended
          by their ſhell. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_87" n="79"/>
        <p rend="indent" n="3">
          <lb/>III. <hi rend="italic">In the formation of ſome particular <lb/>parts of any
            organized body, the Formative <lb/>Niſus is much more regular in its proceſs, than
            <lb/>in that of others.</hi> Thus the brain, ſays old <lb/>Conr. Vict. Schneider, a man
          much diſtin- <lb/>guiſhed in phyſiology, is ſeldom or never found <lb/>to deviate from the
          uſual ſtructure <note place="bottom" n="(l)">(l) <q rend="diple quotes size(0.5) italic"
              >In corpore humano, he ſays, nulla <lb/>pars faciem ſuam rarius mutal quam cerebrum.
            </q>
          </note>. On <lb/>the contrary, how great and frequent are the <lb/>variations in many
          other parts, ſuch as in the <lb/>kidneys, and Thoracic Duct, &amp;c. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Amongſt the many deviations of the <lb/>formative proceſs from its uſual courſe,
          theſe <lb/>are principally to be mentioned. </p>
        <p rend="indent" n="1">
          <lb/>1ſt, <hi rend="italic">Where one ſpecies of organic body <lb/>takes on the action of
            that of another.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>To this belong ſome of the moſt unac- <lb/>countable phenomena in nature, which, as
            <pb xml:id="page_88" n="80"/>
          <lb/>far as I am able to judge, cannot be explained <lb/>in any ſatisfactory manner by the
          theory <lb/>of pre-exiſting germs. It is a well-known <lb/>fact, that women have in
          general, and ac- <lb/>cording to the ſtrict laws of nature, only <lb/>one uterus for the
          reception of the new con- <lb/>ceived fœtus. But that moſt of the other fe- <lb/>males in
          the claſs of mamalia, have a double <lb/>one. Yet inſtances are not wanting, where <lb/>a
          real <hi rend="italic">uterus bicornis</hi> has been found in women. <lb/>This
          ſingularity, if I am not miſtaken, is <lb/>accounted for by the previous reflection. In
          <lb/>the ſame manner, I would reckon all thoſe <lb/>hares, which have been ſo frequently
          ob- <lb/>ſerved with ſmall horns like thoſe of deers, <lb/>and alſo many of thoſe ſtrange
          deviations, <lb/>which take place now and then in the ſtruc- <lb/>ture of the vegetable
          kingdom, ſuch as the <lb/>alder-tree with oak leaves, deſcribed by <lb/>Gleditch <note
            place="bottom" n="(m)" rend="size(0.5) italic">(m) Betula alnus quercifolia vid.
            Gleditch <lb/>hinterlaſſene Abbandl. das practiſhe Fortweſen be- <lb/>treffend. </note>
        </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_89" n="81"/>
        <p rend="indent" n="2">
          <lb/>2dly, <hi rend="italic">Where the organs of generation of <lb/>one ſex take on more
            or leſs the ſtructure of <lb/>that of the other.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In our ſceptical day, the poſſibility of <lb/>human hermaphrodites, and that of other
          <lb/>warm-blooded animals, has been much doubt- <lb/>ed. And yet Baron Haller of this
          univerſity, <lb/>and Mr. John Hunter of London, have in- <lb/>ſtituted, and given
          relations of the moſt care- <lb/>ful diſſections of ſuch animals, eſpecially in <lb/>the
          cow, and goat tribes, and which leave no <lb/>room for further doubts in this matter. It
          is <lb/>true, that in none of the inſtances, the moſt <lb/>eſſential parts of generation,
          for inſtance, <lb/>the male teſticles, and female ovaria, were to <lb/>be diſtinctly
          diſcovered in the ſame individual. <lb/>But though the chief form ſeemed to be always
          <lb/>that of one of the ſexes, yet there was evidently <lb/>to be diſcovered in one part
          or another, the <lb/>moſt unequivocal, though imperfect marks of <lb/>the organs of the
          other ſex. In general, the <lb/>male organs lay internally, whilſt the external <lb/>ones
          had more the reſemblance of the female. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_90" n="82"/>
        <p rend="indent" n="3">
          <lb/>3dly, <hi rend="italic">When the formative proceſs does not, <lb/>as in the former
            inſtances, take an action which <lb/>is FOREIGN, but one that is completely
            <lb/>PRETERNATURAL to the individual.</hi>
          <lb/>And yet from an attentive conſideration of <lb/>the aſtoniſhing uniformity, which
          reigns <lb/>amongſt the different kinds of monſters, it <lb/>would appear as if the cauſes
          of the deviation <lb/>in their formation, was regulated by certain <lb/>fixed laws.
          Whoever has ſeen any conſider- <lb/>able number of monſters, or only looked into <lb/>the
          looſe and wretched compilations of re- <lb/>preſentations of them, can hardly have eſcaped
          <lb/>being ſtruck by the reſemblance which unites, <lb/>even to the moſt inconſiderable
          parts, cer- <lb/>tain ſpecies of them, ſo that the individuals of <lb/>that ſpecies, ſeem
          as if they had all been caſt <lb/>in the ſame mould. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>To conclude, there is ſtill one other <lb/>phenomenon, which the reader is at liberty
          to <lb/>explain, either on the principle of pre-exiſting <pb xml:id="page_91" n="83"/>
          <lb/>organic germs, or that of the Formative <lb/>Niſus. Many animal monſters, ſuch for
          in- <lb/>ſtance, as thoſe with two bodies and a ſingle <lb/>head, are of that kind,
          according to the ex- <lb/>press aſſertion of Baron Haller, and other <lb/>evolutioniſts,
          that they cannot have ariſen <lb/>from the accidental growth of two germs, but <lb/>that
          the fault lies in the original monſtroſity <lb/>of a ſingle germ. Now it is ſingular, that
          <lb/>ſuch monſters are only common in animal, <lb/>which have been domeſticated, and that
          they <lb/>are never, or at leaſt ſeldom to be heard of <lb/>in their wild ſtate. Can the
          Author of nature <lb/>have ordained it, that from amongſt the in- <lb/>volved germs of any
          one ſpecies of animals, <lb/>for inſtance, ſwine, the monſters ſhould ar- <lb/>rive at
          evolution, juſt when taken under the <lb/>care of men, and that the monſters ſhould be
          <lb/>produced only by the tame, and not by the <lb/>wild alſo? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On the other hand, there is nothing un- <lb/>reaſonable in ſuppoſing, that after the
          ſub- <lb/>jection of theſe animals, their whole frame <pb xml:id="page_92" n="84"/>
          <lb/>and œconomy ſuffer a very great change; <lb/>that then the Formative Niſus deviates
          in <lb/>ſome degree from its original laws, and there- <lb/>fore theſe animals as they
          degenerate into <lb/>endleſs varieties, are alſo more ſubjected to <lb/>monſtroſity. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Such, in my opinion, are the principal <lb/>obſervations and experiments which ſerve
          to <lb/>prove the exiſtence of the Formative Niſus, <lb/>and to aſcertain ſome of its
          laws; obſervations <lb/>which have drawn my conviction more and <lb/>more from the ſyſtem
          of involved germs, and <lb/>confirmed my belief in the very oppoſite doc- <lb/>trine,
          which I have endeavoured to eſtabliſh. </p>
        <trailer rend="align-center">
          <lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="0"/>
  </text>
</TEI>
