<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: An essay on the rhus toxicodendron</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">An essay on the rhus toxicodendron, pubescent poison oak, or sumach,
              with cases shewing it's efficacy in the cure of paralysis, and Other Diseases of
              Extreme Debility. By John Alderson, M. D. Member of the Royal Medical Society,
              Edinburgh; -Philosophical and Literary Society; Newcastle And Physician to the General
              Infirmary at Hull.</title>
            <edition n=""/>
            <idno type="ESTC">N582</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N582"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Hull</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Hull: printed and sold by Rawson and Co. Sold also by J. Johnson, St.
                  Paul's Church Yard, London; and W. Creech, Edinburgh</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1794</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="3"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="34"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">National Library of Medicine</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3308560568</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K000343.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: medicine"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_1"/>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>depiction of a rhus toxicodendron (poison oak)</figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_3"/>

        <head rend="align-center space"><lb/>TO <lb/><hi rend="sc size(1.5)">JOHN WIDDRINGTON </hi>,
            <hi rend="dc(2)">Eſq.</hi><lb/> OF HAUXLEY,<lb/> IN THE<lb/>
          <hi rend="italic dc(2)">County of Northumberland,</hi><lb/> PRESIDENT of the LITERARY and
          PHILOSOPHICAL <lb/>SOCIETY at NEWCASTLE, </head>

        <p rend="indent"><lb/>IN TESTIMONY OF THE ESTEEM WHICH THE AUTHOR FEELS, AND AS A MARK OF <w
            part="I">FRIEND-</w><lb/><w part="F">SHIP</w>, NATURALLY OCCASIONED BY A FAMILY
          CONNECTION WITH SO AMIABLE A CHARACTER, THIS ESSAY IS, WITH SINCERE REGARD, </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>INSCRIBED. </p>
        <dateline>HULL, Dec. 31, 1793. </dateline>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_4"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>A diſtinguiſhing feature of the preſent times, in a medical point of
        view, is the prevalence of nervous diſorders, and a great increaſe of paralytic affections.
        Their origin is not difficult to be aſcertained. A <w part="I">deter-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >mination</w> appears to pervade all ranks, to call forth into immediate action all the <w
          part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſources</w> of exiſtence, by an employment of the moſt
        powerful agents; and, in the <w part="I">gra-</w><lb/><w part="F">tification</w> of a
        moment, to riſque their whole ſtock of nervous energy. To ſuch inordinate movements, kept up
        by a repeated uſe of the moſt active ſtimulants, may we juſtly look for the cauſe of that
        derangement, which phyſicians have to encounter under the multiplied forms of nervous
        debility. <pb xml:id="page_5" n="2"/>Various chemical, pncumatic, and <w part="I"
          >mecha-</w><lb/><w part="F">nical</w> operations, it is well known, are <w part="I"
          >con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtantly</w> going forward in the human body: and when any of
        theſe is too much <w part="I">accele-</w><lb/><w part="F">rated</w>, or precipitately urged,
        the machine itſelf is deſtroyed, or is rendered uſeleſs. Strongly incited to animal
        gratifications, men become inſenſible to the condition of their preſent exiſtence, which, ſo
        far from implying an inceſſant ſeries of pleaſures, in many caſes ſeems to produce the
        higheſt <w part="I">en-</w><lb/><w part="F">joyments</w> by preceding pain; thus inculcating
        upon human creatures the neceſſity of <w part="I">tem-</w><lb/><w part="F">perance</w>, and,
        in many inſtances, the utility of ſelf-denial. However, as was ſaid, but fewattend to the
        admonitions of their animal conſtitution. They aim at acquiring what Nature, more provident
        than they, has <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">hibited</w> to be attained; and by a
        laviſh uſe of wine, ſpirits, or laudanum, endeavour to procure to themſelves the power of <w
          part="I">perpe-</w><lb/><w part="F">tual</w> enjoyment. They bid defiance to the <pb
          xml:id="page_6" n="3"/>warnings of experience in the fate of others: and ſolicitous only
        to appear replete with ſpirit and animation in the eyes of thoſe with whom they aſſociate,
        (who probably have recourſe to the ſame incitements) they continue to urge on the proceſſes
        of life, till ſome part of the apparatus gives way, and they ſuddenly feel all the ſymptoms
        of a <w part="I">ru-</w><lb/><w part="F">ined</w> conſtitution, not to be repaired by the
        utmoſt efforts of medical skill. Hence <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceed</w> that
        train of nervous ſymptoms, which no leſs impede the operations of the mind, than occaſion
        painful bodily ſenſations: <w part="I">ſen-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſations</w> ſo acute, as to
        drive the unhappy victims into the hands of daring empirics, to whoſe pretended skill they
        too often <w part="I">ſa-</w><lb/><w part="F">crifice</w> thoſe lives and fortunes, which
        ought to have been devoted to the good of their connections. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the proſecution of my ſubject, I ſhall endeavour carefully to avoid
        every thing <pb xml:id="page_7" n="4"/>that has the appearance of abſtract <w part="I"
          >ſpe-</w><lb/><w part="F">culation</w>. I wiſh only to announce what, I conceive, will
        prove a benefit to the public, in alleviating ſome of the moſt <w part="I">di-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſtreſſing</w> diſorders, that are incident to the human frame. I will ſimply
        relate what has taken place under my own obſervation. I will not attempt to account for the
          <hi rend="italic">modus operandi</hi> of the plant, which is the ſubject of the preſent
        eſſay; nor take upon me to decide whether it acts by renewing the <w part="I">ir-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ritability</w> of the ſyſtem, or only by giving energy to the natural powers: nor
        ſhall I preſume to determine whether the nerves, acting as conductors of electricity, are,
        by its means, made capable of tranſmitting a larger quantity of this ſubtile fluid through
        the whole frame, as Aurum Muſivum, when applied to the rubber of an electrical <w part="I"
          >appa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ratus</w>, enables the cylinder to accumulate a much larger
        quantity of that agent—It is <pb xml:id="page_8" n="5"/>my intention only, by the relation
        of facts, to eſtabliſh the uſe of this powerful drug in thoſe diſorders, which uſually
        attend upon an enervated conſtitution. As the plant is not to be found in our Materia Medica
        at preſent, I ſhall, as briefly as poſſible, deſcribe it, give it's hiſtory, and relate the
        caſes in which I have ſucceſſfully employed it; in hopes that the faculty will be induced to
        make a fair trial of it, and, if found worthy of further notice, that they will furniſh the
        world with the reſult of their obſervations. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>My firſt acquaintance with the ſubject of this eſſay began while I was
        examining, about four years ago, the plants in the Nurſery Grounds at Cottingham. I was told
        by the proprietor, of the wonderful effect of the Poiſon Oak; that, if touched by the
        fingers, and not immediately waſhed off, the acrimony it imparts would be <pb
          xml:id="page_9" n="6"/>retained for a long time; that ſhould a perſon accidentally touch
        his eyelids, or any part of the body where the skin uſually corrugates, whilſt the virulence
        of the deleterious particles thus contracted <w part="I">conti-</w><lb/><w part="F">nues</w>
        unimpaired, a ſwelling and <w part="I">trouble-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſome</w> itching would
        come on, and continue for ſome time; and that even ſome of his men had ſuffered ſo much as
        to loſe ſuch parts of the skin by ſphacelation, as the acrid juice had touched. This <w
          part="I">deter-</w><lb/><w part="F">mined</w> me to make further enquiries into it's
        powers; and I ſoon after ſaw in the Analytical Review (to the conductors of which I beg
        leave to make my <w part="I">acknow-</w><lb/><w part="F">ledgements)</w> ſome account of
        experiments made in France, with the <hi rend="italic">Rhus Radicans,</hi> to which this
        plant is cloſely allied, by Mons. Freſnoi; from which it appeared, that he had given the
        diſtilled water and extract of this plant, in caſes of paralyſis of the lower extremities,
        with ſucceſs. <pb xml:id="page_10" n="7"/>This information induced me to hope, that the
        Sumach I now poſſeſſed, might be <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">hibited</w> with equal
        advantage, in the ſame and ſimilar complaints: and though, in the form of diſtilled water
        and infuſion I was not ſucceſſful, yet the event of the caſes ſubjoined, in which I have
        given it in <w part="I">ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtance</w>, has made me ample amends. I
        muſt, however, confeſs, that it's uſe has not been uniformly attended with complete ſucceſs.
        Having always adviſed extreme caution in it's firſt exhibition, it has required a greater
        length of time to produce the deſired effects, than the general impatience, which, I
        apprehend, all medical men have to <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">bat</w> with in
        their practice, will allow; an impatience continually encreaſed by the bold advertiſers of
        ſpecifics for the cure of every diſeaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I have not found that an attempt has at any time been made in this
        country, to aſcertain, by experiments, the power of the <pb xml:id="page_11" n="8"/><hi
          rend="italic">Toxicodendron,</hi> as a medicine. In France it ſeems to have been made the
        ſubject of enquiry for ſome time; for Monſieur Fontana, ſpeaks of the many celebrated
          writers,<note place="bottom" n="†">† "Que les Ecrivains les plus celebres ont communément
          regardé comme un poiſon tres puiſſant, quoique quelques Phyſiciens modernes ne l'aient pas
          trouvé tel pour certains Ammaux." <hi rend="italic">Fontana.</hi>
        </note> who have conſidered it as a moſt virulent poiſon. The experiments <w part="I"
          >how-</w><lb/><w part="F">ever</w>, which he made upon animals, and has related, are not
        neceſſary to be <w part="I">intro-</w><lb/><w part="F">duced</w> here, ſince I hold all
        experiments on animals as inſignificant, and irrelevant to the effects of any medicine on
        the human ſubject. And thoſe made on himſelf go to ſhew merely the manner in which it
        affected the skin, and ſeem to have terrified<note place="bottom" n="*">* "Mais jai été
          forcé d'abandonner, des le <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">mencement</w> mes
          recherches fur cette plante, parceque j'ai eu le malheur de m' en poiſonner moimeme par
          trois fois de ſuite, avee ſes feuilles." <hi rend="italic">Fontana.</hi>
        </note> him from any internal exhibition. </p>

      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_12" n="9"/>
        <head><lb/>RHUS TOXICODENDRON,<note place="bottom" n="*">* For the following botanical
            deſcription of the TOXICODENDRON, I am much indebted to my truly ingenious friend, A. H.
            HAWORTH, Eſq. late of <w part="I">Cotting-</w><lb/><w part="F">ham</w>, now of Little
            Chelſea, whoſe indefatigable induſtry in inveſtigating and critical acumen in
            diſtinguiſhing plants, I have frequently witneſſed. </note>
          <hi rend="italic">PUBESCENT POISON-OAK,</hi> OR, SUMACH. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>RHUS. <hi rend="italic">Lin. Gen. Pl.</hi> 369. <w part="I"
            >PENTAN-</w><lb/><w part="F">DRIA</w> TRIGYNIA, <hi rend="italic">Flores inferi.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Cal.</hi> 5. partitus. <hi rend="italic">Petala</hi>
          5. <hi rend="italic">Bacca</hi> 1. Sperma. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Juſs. Gen. Pl.</hi> p. 369. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Tournef.</hi> 381. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Sectio ** foliis ternatis. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>RHUS <hi rend="italic">Toxicodendron</hi> foliis ternatis: foliolis
          petiolatis angulatis <w part="I">pube-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſcentibus</w>, <pb
            xml:id="page_13" n="10"/>caule radicante, <hi rend="italic">Lin. Sp. Pl.</hi> 381. <hi
            rend="italic">Syſt. Veg.</hi> ed. <hi rend="italic">Murr.</hi> p. 293. <hi rend="italic"
            >Syſt. Veg. Lichf. Soc.</hi> v. 1. p. 230. <hi rend="italic">Syſt. Nat.</hi> ed. 13. <hi
            rend="italic">Gmel. Tom.</hi> 2. 494. <hi rend="italic">Ait. Hort. Kew.</hi> v. 1. p.
          367. <hi rend="italic">Walter Flo. Carolin.</hi> p. 255. <hi rend="italic">Gaert. de Fr.
            et Sem. Cent.</hi> 3. t. 44. f. 5. <hi rend="italic">Bulliard. Herb. Franc.</hi> t. 143.
            <hi rend="italic">Gron. Virg.</hi> 149. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>RHUS foliis ternatis: foliolis petiolatis angulatis pubeſcentibus. <hi
            rend="italic">Clayt. Flo. Virg.</hi> 46. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>RHUS <hi rend="italic">Toxicodendron Hill's Hort. Kew.</hi> p. 453. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>TOXICODENDRON. 2. <hi rend="italic">(pubeſcens.)</hi> foliis ternatis:
          foliolis ovatis <w part="I">inciſo-</w><lb/><w part="F">angulatis</w> pubeſcentibus. <hi
            rend="italic">Mill. Gard. Dict.</hi> ed. 6? <hi rend="italic">Mill. Gard. Cal.</hi> ed.
          14. octavo. p. 166. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_14" n="11"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>TOXICODENDRON tryphyllum folio ſinuato pubeſcente. <hi rend="italic"
            >Tournef. Inſt.</hi> 611. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>TOXICODENDRON 2. <hi rend="italic">Boerh. Ind. Hort. Batt.</hi> 1727.
          2. p. 229. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>HEDERA Virginienſis trifolia. <hi rend="italic">Park. Theat.</hi> 679.
          f. 5. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>HEDERAE Trifoliae Canadenſi affinis Planta, Peregrina, arbor venenata
          quorundam. <hi rend="italic">H. R. Par.</hi> 84. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>HEDERAE Trifoliae Canadenſi affinis, <w part="I">ſur-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">recta</w>, Arbor Tinctoria, virginiana multis. <hi rend="italic">Pluken
            Alm.</hi> 181. H. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>EDERA Trifolia Canadenſis. <hi rend="italic">Corn. Can.</hi> 96. t.
          97. <hi rend="italic">Barr. Icon.</hi> 228. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>VITIS Canadenſis. <hi rend="italic">Muntin Phytogr.</hi> t. 60. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_15" n="12"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>ARBOR Trifoliata venenata virginiana, folio hirſuto. <hi rend="italic"
            >Raj. Hiſt.</hi> 1779. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>THE Pubeſcent Poiſon-Oak or Sumach, is a deciduous ſhrub of moderate
          growth, riſing to the height of about four feet, it is covered with a greyiſh coloured <w
            part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w part="F">what</w> ſtriated bark, which is uſually marked with
          minute ſpots, or glandular <w part="I">appear-</w><lb/><w part="F">ances</w>, not greatly
          unlike the effect of an inſect, they have alſo a diſtant reſemblance to ſome of the
          ſmalleſt ſpecies of <hi rend="italic">Sphoeria,</hi> for like <hi rend="italic"
            >Sphoerioe</hi> they ſeem to ariſe from the wood, and finally cauſe a ſort of <w
            part="I">burſt-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> or opening of the bark, immediately over
          them equal to their own ſize, they further reſemble <hi rend="italic">Sphoerioe</hi> in
          being largeſt on the older and more ſtunted ſhoots, <w part="I">par-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ticularly</w> in the winter ſeaſon; but in all likelihood they are the common excretory
          ducts of the plant, whoſe fluid being exceſſively acrid, may poſſibly require more <pb
            xml:id="page_16" n="13"/>capacious outlets, than ſhrubs of a milder juice. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The lower ſhoots, on and near the ground, in moiſt ſhady ſituations,
          which the plant moſt affects, trail conſiderably like the <hi rend="italic">Rhus radicans
            Linnoei,</hi> (ſmooth rooting Poiſon-Oak or Sumach) and have like that ſhrub, the
          property of ſending down radicles into the earth, by which the plant admits of great
          increaſe, in any of the winter months. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>In ſuch ſituations, however, I have not ſeen it produce ſeeds ſo
          readily, as in drier and more pinching places, where it looſes in a great degree, it's
          radicating principle, grows more ſtiff and robuſt, and <w part="I">pro-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">duces</w> annual crops of pale yellow ſtriated berries. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>There is a remarkable inſtance of this kind, (the ſingularity of which
          induces me <pb xml:id="page_17" n="14"/>to mention it) now exiſting in a <hi rend="italic"
            >wall,</hi> in the Phyſic Garden of the Company of Apothecaries at Chelſea, out of a
          chink in the ſide of which, and near the ground, grows a ſtrong plant of this <hi
            rend="italic">Rhus,</hi> that has proſpered there ever ſince the time of the celebrated
          Miller, and which Mr. Fairbairn, the Company's preſent gardener, obligingly aſſured me,
          was what Miller called the ſecond ſpecies of <hi rend="italic">Toxicodendron,</hi> in his
          Gardener's Dictionary; it is, in all probability, the identical plant from which the
          deſcription in that well known work was made; it ſeeds annually, but none of it's lower
          ſhoots exhibit the leaſt radicating propenſity, although other plants of the ſame kind, in
          the ſhady parts of the ſame garden, have that quality in great <w part="I"
            >perfec-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w>, but I believe they rarely produce ſeeds; ſo much
          do local circumſtances affect and alter the moſt permanent and <w part="I"
            >diſtin-</w><lb/><w part="F">guiſhing</w> characters of vegetables. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_18" n="15"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I believe it is pretty generally known to Gardeners, and others
          concerned in the pleaſant and inſtructive employment of horticulture, that many other
          fibrous plants, which, like the <hi rend="italic">Rhus <w part="I">Toxicoden-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">dron</w>,</hi> poſſeſs the power of encreaſing ing themſelves in any
          conſiderable degree by their roots, have that property <w part="I">material-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ly</w> leſſened, when the place they grow in happens to be dry and poor, for
          nature has chiefly allotted them rich and moiſt habitations, and, with her uſual care,
          conſtructed their conſtitutions accordingly; the alteration ſuch plants undergo, in ſuch a
          ſoil, is doubtleſs in the direction of their juices, which (being fewer) appear to paſs by
          the lower and leſs noble parts, (they had before rendered luxuriantly radicant or
          prolific) and mount upwards by a natural and almoſt inſtinctive impulſe, to feed and
          mature, with collected force, the infant germs which they had before too ſparingly
          ſupplied with nouriſhment. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_19" n="16"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Thus Nature checked by art or accident, in any cuſtomary channel of
          renewing her works, kindly ſearches out and perfects another, that ſhe may not be
          diſappointed in the multiplication of her productions, for <q rend="quotes"><lb/><l>— each
              moſs, </l>
            <lb/><l>Each ſhell, each crawling infect, holds a rank, </l>
            <lb/><l>Important in the plan of Him who fram'd </l>
            <lb/><l>This ſcale of Beings; holds a rank, which loſt </l>
            <lb/><l>Would break the chain, and leave a gap behind </l>
            <lb/><l>Which Nature's ſelf wou'd rue. </l></q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I am not acquainted with any common plant, that more abundantly
          exemplifies the above doctrine, than the Lilly of the Valley, <hi rend="italic"
            >Convallaria majalis Lin.</hi> which is well known to all who poſſeſs a garden, to
          flower freely, and increaſe amazingly by the root, in a moiſt north border, yet few, I
          fancy, have ſeen it produce perfect ſeeds in that ſituation, notwithſtanding the vigour of
          it's growth; but when it is planted and confined in a garden pot, and it's increaſe <pb
            xml:id="page_20" n="17"/>by the root conſequently checked, it will frequently produce
          good ſeeds. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Vinca major et minor,</hi> greater and leſſer
          Periwinkle, <hi rend="italic">Tuſſilago Petaſites,</hi> Butter Burr, and many other
          plants, as remarkable for the ſterility of their ſeeds, as their great increaſe by roots,
          might, in all probability, experience a ſimilar effect, if under ſimilar circumſtances;
          their ſuppoſed ſterility therefore, ſhould ſeem to reſult chiefly from the peculiarity of
          their ſituation and conſtitutions, and not from any real defect in the formation of all,
          or any of their parts of fructification, as has ſometimes been ingeniouſly conjectured by
          botaniſts and others; but, to return to the <hi rend="italic">Rhus Toxicodendron,</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The leaves are alternate and three'd, and F<unclear>##</unclear>nd
          upon remarkable long petioles, the lateral leafits are uſually ſupported on very <pb
            xml:id="page_21" n="18"/>ſhort petioles, which frequently looſe <w part="I"
            >them-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſelves</w> by a kind of dilatation, in the <w part="I"
            >ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtance</w> of the leafits; the terminal leafit has often a
          footſtalk half an inch long or <w part="I">up-</w><lb/><w part="F">wards</w>: all the
          leafits are dull green, have a drooping poſture, and an unpleaſant aſpect, they are
          oval-angulate and nervoſe, with a kind of undulated margin, which ſometimes forms diſtant
          tooth-like <w part="I">crena-</w><lb/><w part="F">tures</w>. The young wood-buds,
          petioles, and the nerves on the underſides of the leafits, are furniſhed with a very
          viſible degree of pubeſcence, on which account I have ventured to give the plant the
          Engliſh name of Pubeſcent Poiſon Oak, or Sumach, for the purpoſe of diſtinguiſhing it from
          the <hi rend="italic">Rhus radicans Lin.</hi> which has conſtantly ſmooth leaves and
          ſhoots. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The flowers are produced in June, July, and Auguſt, on ſhort, crowded
          axilleay racemi, which are paniculate, and in a ſtate <pb xml:id="page_22" n="19"/>of
          nature, dioecious. In our ſpecimens, however, (which were cultivated <w part="I"
            >luxuri-</w><lb/><w part="F">ant</w> ones, and the only ones which we could procure in a
          ſtate of fructification) a few of the flowers were hermaphrodite, and had an encreaſed
          number of parts, particularly, a minute ſix cleft calyx, ſix ſmall lance-oval whitiſh,
          rather ſtriated, petals; and ſix ſhort ſtamina, ſupporting as many antherae. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>When not rendered unnaturally luxuriant by cultivation, the male
          flower conſiſts of a minute calyx with five ſhallow clefts, a corolla of five ſmall
          petals, and five ſtamina which ſupport as many antherae, and the germen in the female
          flower is roundiſh, and when a little magnified, appears <w part="I">ſome-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">what</w> bottle-ſhaped, and ſupports a ſhort ſtylus, which is crowned with
          three very ſmall ſtigmata. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_23" n="20"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The fruit or ſeed arrives at maturity in England about the month of
          October and November, it is a round, dry, <w part="I">pale-yel-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >low</w> ſtriated berry, which is ſomewhat ſcarioſe, and nearly the ſize of a ſmall pea,
          and encloſes one hard compreſſed <w part="I">end-nick-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> kernel,
          which has a thick furrowed mealy covering. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The germination of the ſeed, I am ſorry to add, I have had no
          opportunity of obſerving. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Rhus Toxicodendron</hi> is a native of North
          America, it has been introduced into England ever ſince the year 1640, and was cultivated
          in this country as a curious ſhrub in the time of Parkinſon, who figures it in his
            Theatre.<note place="bottom" n="*">* See <hi rend="italic">Parkinſon</hi>'s Theatrum
            Botanicum and <hi rend="italic">Aiton's</hi> Hortus Keweenſis. </note>
        </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_24" n="21"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I ſhall conclude this long account of ſo common a ſhrub, by obſerving,
          that my ſpecimens did not in all points accord with thoſe preſerved in the Herbarium of
          the great Linnaeus, which were very obligingly twice compared with mine, by the preſent
          learned and well known poſſeſſor of that ineſtimable treaſure; my ſpecimens are larger in
          all their parts, their leafits are leſs undulate, and poſſeſſed of ſomewhat longer
          footſtalks than thoſe of Linnaeus, the lateral leafits of which are nearly ſeſſile, but
          his ſpecimens are ſaid to have been gathered wild in North America, by Kalme, and mine
          were the luxuriant produce of young plants, in the ſtrong moiſt loam of a <w part="I"
            >York-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſhire</w> nurſery,<note place="bottom" n="*">* The nurſery of
            Meſſrs. Phillipſon and Scales, at C<unclear>#</unclear>ttingham, near Hull, in
            Yorkſhire. </note> which circumſtances, I humbly truſt, ſufficiently account for the
          above-mentioned diſparity. </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_25" n="22"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>A ſhort account of caſes in which it has been employed, will enable
          the reader to judge of it's power as a medicine. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>The following caſe is inſerted as drawn up by my ingenious friend Mr.
          B—, an eminent ſurgeon in this neighbourhood, who paid the greateſt attention to the
          exhibition of the medicine, and has related, in a clear and intereſting manner, the
          gradual recovery of his own wife. </p>
        <div n="1" type="case">
          <head><lb/>CASE I. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Mrs. B—, aged 38, always enjoyed remarkable good health, till about
            eight years ago, at which time ſhe complained of a diſorder in her bowels, which ſhe <w
              part="I">de-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſcribed</w> to feel as if the bowels had loſt their
            ſenſation, and that a cold wind ſeemed to riſe up the oeſophagus. As ſhe was coſtive,
            two ounces of the Ol. Ricini were given at four doſes, which having no effect, ſtronger
            purgatives were <w part="I">admini-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtered</w>, but without
            producing a ſtool; after <pb xml:id="page_26" n="23"/>which the ſmoke of tobacco was
            thrown up, the warm bath applied, a doſe of <w part="I">calo-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >mel</w> given, and a bliſter put upon the belly. At length an evacuation was
            obtained; and from the large quantity of cathartic <w part="I">reme-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >dies</w> uſed, the bowels now took on the other extreme, and a violent purging
            enſued.— She now complained of a pricking pain on the right ſide of the abdomen, which
            went off upon her voiding by ſtool a piece of a large plumb ſtone, one ſide of which was
            worn as ſharp as the edge of a knife. After this ſhe was frequently troubled with <w
              part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtinate</w> conſtipations of the bowels, and obliged
            to have recourſe to purgative <w part="I">me-</w><lb/><w part="F">dicines</w>. In the
            year 1789, ſhe had two fits, which, I believe, were epileptic; but, as I happened not to
            ſee her in either of them, I cannot be certain. In the month of September, ſhe was
            ſeized with pains in her hands and feet, which were ſuppoſed to be gouty; and when theſe
            went off, ſhe <pb xml:id="page_27" n="24"/>loſt entirely the uſe of the extenſor muſcles
            of the wriſts, and ſoon after thoſe of the feet, which was followed by the loſs of the
            extenſors of the fingers and toes. A tumour now aroſe upon the metacarpal bones of each
            hand, which ſeemed a ſwelling either of the pcrioſteum or bone itſelf, and had greatly
            the appearance of a ſcrophulous affection, The tumours ſeemed ſometimes likely to
            ſuppurate, but about the end of the year 1790, they gradually diſappeared. The hands now
            looked livid, and the <w part="I">exten-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſor</w> muſcles upon the
            arms and hands waſted and ſhrivelled; her feet felt like logs of wood, and the fingers
            and toes were <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">tracted</w> from the action of the
            flexor <w part="I">muſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">cles</w>; ſhe could not walk without help,
            and when ſhe attempted it, always <w part="I">com-</w><lb/><w part="F">plained</w> of
            ſomething drawing her <w part="I">back-</w><lb/><w part="F">wards</w>. During this time,
            ſhe took a variety of volatile, cardiac, and tonic medicines, but without any good
            effect. In the month <pb xml:id="page_28" n="25"/>of September, 1791, Dr. ALDERSON was
            conſulted, and adviſed her to take the TOXICODENDRON. Six grains of the <w part="I"
              >pow-</w><lb/><w part="F">dered</w> leaves of that plant were infuſed in eight ounces
            of boiling water, a table <w part="I">ſpoon-</w><lb/><w part="F">ful</w> to be given
            three times a day. The whole of this was taken without any <w part="I">ſenſi-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ble</w> effect, except a ſlight pricking <w part="I">ſenſa-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">tion</w> in the feet and hands: </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Oct. 3d, She took one fourth of a grain of the powdered leaves made
            into a bolus with Cons. Cort. Aurant. twice a day. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>4th, The ſame; the pricking <w part="I">ſenſa-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >tion</w> continues, and the arms, to the ends of the fingers, feel as if warm water
            was running-down them. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>5th, Medicines continued three times a day. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>6th, The ſame. In the evening, had an <pb xml:id="page_29" n="26"
            />irregular ſpaſmodic fluttering in the toes. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Oct. 7th, Medicines continued. Was <w part="I">agree-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ably</w> ſurpriſed to find ſhe could extend her fingers and toes a little.
            Her hands a little <w part="I">ſwel-</w><lb/><w part="F">led</w>, and her feet and
            ancles much more ſo. She has, in a great meaſure, recovered the uſe of the extenſor
            pollicis of the right hand, and that of the left in a ſmaller degree; has alſo loſt the
            dead hard ſenſation in her finger ends, which was <w part="I">al-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >ways</w> her conſtant attendant. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>8th, Medicines continued. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>9th, One third of a grain ter die. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>10th, The ſame. Walked up ſtairs <w part="I">with-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">out</w> help, her hands alſo ſtronger and better, but the extenſors of the
            wriſts ſtill inactive. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>11th, The ſame. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_30" n="27"/>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Oct. 12th, Took half a grain ter die. Begins to walk tolerably well,
            and can uſe her hands better, the <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">tenſor</w>,
            adductor, and abductor muſcles of the thumbs, having recovered their action. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>15th, Three grains were made into four boluſes, and one taken three
            times a day. At night the <w part="I">ſen-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſation</w>, as if hot
            water was <w part="I">run-</w><lb/><w part="F">ning</w> down the arms, very <w part="I"
              >trou-</w><lb/><w part="F">bleſome</w>, with the pricking feel in the fingers. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>17th, One grain ter die. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>30th, Takes one grain and a half ter die; and this day perceived
            that ſhe had recovered the uſe of the extenſor muſcles of the wriſts. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>She continued the medicine, gradually <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">creaſing</w> the doſe to four grains ter die, for ſome time longer. It ſeemed
            to act as a <pb xml:id="page_31" n="28"/>gentle aperient, and frequently, when the large
            doſes were taken, occaſioned a ſlight vertigo, with a pain acroſs the forehead, and a
            nauſea for about half an hour after taking it. She has now left off the medicine twelve
            months, has entirely recovered the uſe of her hands, and walks a mile or two very well;
            but the muſcles of the feet are not ſo well recovered as thoſe of the hands, and ſhe
            always lifts the feet very high when ſhe walks; which may be owing to a <w part="I"
              >re-</w><lb/><w part="F">membrance</w> that in her former ſtate, if ſhe attempted
            walking, and met with the ſmalleſt obſtacle, a fall on the face was generally the
            conſequence. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Barton,</hi> July 25, 1793. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="case">
          <head><lb/>CASE II. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>GREG, mariner, complained of the loſs of one ſide, which he
            attributed to falling aſleep upon the deck, after being exhauſted <pb xml:id="page_32"
              n="29"/>by fatigue during a gale of wind. I ordered him half a grain of the powdered
            leaves of the TOXICODENDRON, three times a day. On the ſecond day, he felt an unuſual
            twitching, or convulſive motion, in the arm and leg affected; and when I ſaw him on the
            Monday following, he could, without any aſſiſtance, bring the diſeaſed leg acroſs the
            other, and had much more uſe of his arm. He continued his medicine a week longer, when,
            finding himſelf ſo far recovered, that he could be employed as a pilot on the river, he
            was content not to compleat his cure, leſt it ſhould ſubject him to be impreſſed. He has
            continued in much the ſame ſtate for ſome time paſt, having gotten more uſe of his limbs
            than he ever expected. It is but right to obſerve, that during two years previous to his
            application to me, every other means had, in vain, been employed, to reſtore the action
            of his leg and arm. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="case">
          <pb xml:id="page_33" n="30"/>
          <head><lb/>CASE III. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>Mr. B—, ſurgeen, aged 47, after having endured a complication of
            ills, haemoptyſis, jaundice, meſenterie obſtruction, and <w part="I">gene-</w><lb/><w
              part="F">ral</w> atrophy, loſt the total uſe of all his limbs; and even his mental
            faculties <w part="I">under-</w><lb/><w part="F">went</w> a ſimilar paralyſis. All his
            powers of ratiocination were ſuſpended, and he was reduced to a ſtate nearly as helpleſs
            as that of a child only ſix months <unclear>##</unclear>d. In this ſituation I gave him
            the TOXICODENDRON, half a grain three times a day, which, in the courſe of a week,
            improved his appetite, and removed the habitual coſtiveneſs to which he had long been
            liable. The doſe was gradually increaſed to one grain, three times a day. It produced
            ſome twitching acroſs the abdomen, with irregular or convulſive motion in the limbs; and
            when the nervous influence ſeemed to paſs to the extremities, <unclear>#####</unclear>
            excited in the brain ſuch a ſenſation of pain, as made him frequently <pb
              xml:id="page_34" n="31"/>exclaim moſt violently: but when any one asked him where his
            pain was, he anſwered, he could not mention any particular place, but that all his limbs
            were, as if ſtretched forcibly. This was more eſpecially the caſe after ſleep. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>The doſe was gradually increaſed to three grains four times a day,
            and he has now taken it for three months. His brain has recovered its wonted functions;
            his ſtomach and bowels do their office more completely than for years; he reſts without
            opium, though for a long time in the conſtant habit of taking it; his animal ſpirits are
            wonderfully invigorated; and although he has not yet acquired the perfect uſe of his
            limbs, they ſeem to be recovering their tone, and I have every reaſon to hope, that he
            will, in time, be reſtored to the full enjoyment of life. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="case">
          <pb xml:id="page_35" n="32"/>
          <head><lb/>CASE IV. </head>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>GEORGE. FORD, ſhip carpenter, aged 24, of a ſtrong athletic make,
            and full habit of body, was admitted into the Hull General Infirmary, on Wedneſday the
            13th of November, 1793, for a paralytic affection, which had deprived him of the uſe of
            his right ſide; his recollection was ſo impaired, that he could not give any account of
            the attack himſelf, but his wife informed me, that, for a week before he loſt the uſe of
            his limbs, he had, at times, complained of a dull pain in his head, and numbneſs in his
            right hand and foot; that, by the advice of ſome old woman, he had been blooded on the
            Monday, and that upon going out of doors ſoon afterwards, he was ſuddenly ſeized with
            hemiplegia. In which ſtate he was admitted into the Infirmary, on the Wedneſday
            following. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>A vomit was given him ſoon after his admiſſion, which was followed
            the next day <pb xml:id="page_36" n="33"/>by a warm purgative, and volatile and <w
              part="I">ſti-</w><lb/><w part="F">mulant</w> medicines for the courſe of the firſt
            week; but finding that I was not likely to gain any ground from the uſual plan, and
            being deſirous of trying the power of the TOXICODENDRON in a recent caſe, I <w part="I"
              >order-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> him half a grain of the powdered leaves of this
            plant in pills, three times a day; on the ſecond day, after the exhibition of this
            medicine, he felt a ſudden convulſive twitching, or involuntary motion in certain
            muſcles of the affected ſide; from that moment he found he had the ſame motion at will;
            every ſucceeding day he felt ſome muſcle or other convulſively moved, and it was always
            remarked, by the other patients in the ſame ward, that he poſſeſſed the power of
            voluntarily employing all thoſe muſcles that had been once convulſively affected in
            conſequence of the <w part="I">TOXICODEN-</w><lb/><w part="F">DRON</w>. He regularly
            purſued the <w part="I">medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cine</w>, and gradually increaſed it
            to one grain <pb xml:id="page_37" n="32"/>
            <pb xml:id="page_38" n="33"/>
            <pb xml:id="page_39" n="34"/>every four hours, taking care always to add to the doſe,
            till he found ſome convulſive action was produced. </p>
          <p rend="indent"><lb/>In the courſe of three weeks, in which time every injured muſcle had
            felt the <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">fluence</w> of this powerful drug, he
            regained the free and perfect motion of his leg and arm; and recovered the full
            enjoyment of his mental faculties, which had been equally affected from the firſt
            attack. </p>
        </div>
        <dateline>December 24, 1793. </dateline>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>LATELY PUBLISHED, BY THE SAME AUTHOR, AN ESSAY ON CONTAGION. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>PRICE TWO SHILLINGS. </p>
      </div>
    </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
