<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Hunter: An anatomical description of the human gravid uterus, and its
          contents</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>William Hunter</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">An anatomical description of the human gravid uterus, and its
              contents. By the late William Hunter, M. D. Physician extraordinary to the queen,
              professor of anatomy in the royal academy, and fellow of the royal and antiquarian
              societies, &amp;c. &amp;c.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T54046</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T54046"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Johnson, St. Paul's Church-Yard; and G. Nicol,
                  Pall-Mall, 1794.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1794</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="9"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="88"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3306724619</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K048521.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: midwifery"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_1"/>
        <p rend="align-center">
          <lb/><hi rend="size(0.5)">AN</hi>
          <lb/>ANATOMICAL DESCRIPTION <lb/><hi rend="size(0.5)">OF THE</hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="size(1.5)">HUMAN GRAVID UTERUS</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="size(0.5)">AND</hi>
          <lb/>ITs CONTENTs. </p>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="9"/>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_10"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/><hi rend="size(0.5)">AN</hi>
        <lb/>ANATOMICAL DESCRIPTION <lb/><hi rend="size(0.5)">OF THE </hi>
        <lb/>HUMAN GRAVID UTERUs, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
      </head>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="align-center size(0.7)">
          <lb/>SIZE OF THE UTERUS. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE pregnant uterus undergoes such gradual changes, from the
          <lb/>time of conception to the hour of delivery, that in giving the <lb/>anatomy of this
          part it will be necessary to fix upon some one <lb/>time in the wide period of nine
          months. The latter part of that <lb/>period appears to be the fittest for our purpose, on
          many accounts, <lb/>but especially because the fruit of the womb is then come to its
          <lb/>full perfection, bears examination better, and all the minute <lb/>organization is
          become more the object of sense and experiment. <lb/>We shall therefore be supposed to be
          speaking of the uterus as it <lb/>is in the ninth month, except the contrary be
          particularly ex- <lb/>pressed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The common size of the pregnant uterus may be understood <lb/>by casting the eye over
          the first, second, fourth, eleventh, and <pb xml:id="page_11" n="2"/>
          <lb/>thirteenth plates. <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* This refers to the
            large volume of engravings, illustrating the Anatomy of the Gravid <lb/>Uterus, which
            was published by the author about twenty years ago; and a similar re- <lb/>ference is
            made in some other parts of this Treatise. </note> To be more particular upon the size
          of the <lb/>uterus would answer no useful purpose. And that the difference <lb/>in a
          number of instances will be very considerable, may be readily <lb/>imagined, when we
          reflect that the uterus very commonly con- <lb/>tains a child and placenta, at least twice
          as large in one case as <lb/>it does in another, and frequently at the least six or eight
          times <lb/>more water: besides the variety of size from there being one <lb/>child only,
          or twins, &amp;c. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The size of the uterus appears to depend upon the quantity of <lb/>the liquor amnii
          principally; for though women who have twins, <lb/>or a very large child, are commonly
          observed to be very big, yet <lb/>the greatest number of those who are really very much
          swelled <lb/>out, are so only from a vast quantity of water. In such cases <lb/>there is
          frequently but one child, and that very often a small one. </p>
        <div>
          <pb xml:id="page_12" n="3"/>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>FIGURE OF THE UTERUS. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The general figure of the uterus is oviform; the fundus <lb/>answering to the
            largest extremity of the egg, and the cervix <lb/>and os uteri to the small end: but the
            fundus is larger and more <lb/>flat, or less pointed, in proportion to the lower
            extremity of the <lb/>uterus, than one end of an egg is to the other; and the whole
            <lb/>uterus seems more or less compressed, so as to be broader from <lb/>right to left,
            than it is from the fore part backwards. Besides <lb/>these more constant deviations,
            the figure of the uterus differs <lb/>from the regular oviform, from a variety of
            accidental causes, <lb/>as it adapts itself to the neighbouring parts, to the attitude
            of the <lb/>body, and to the position of the contained child. In order to <lb/>conceive
            these varieties more easily, we must remember that in <lb/>most cases the uterus is not
            so completely filled as to be upon the <lb/>full stretch. Were it out of the body, and
            filled artificially, it <lb/>would easily contain more than it actually does. Thus the
            uterus, <lb/>like a bladder of water not quite full, is plastic, and moulds itself
            <lb/>into various shapes from accidental circumstances. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>As the surrounding parts resist the pressure or weight of the <lb/>uterus
            unequally, according to their different natures, the uterus <lb/>swells out in some
            places, while in others it is pressed inwards. <lb/>Thence it is, that the brim of the
            bony pelvis has commonly the <pb xml:id="page_13" n="4"/>
            <lb/>effect of a belt girding that part of the uterus, and the projections <lb/>of the
            spine, and of the psoæ and iliac vessels, mould the outside of the <lb/>uterus into
            corresponding cavities. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>That the different attitudes of the mother's body should pro- <lb/>duce alterations
            in the figure of the uterus, needs not now a par- <lb/>ticular explanation or proof. The
            weight of the uterus itself, and <lb/>of the adjacent viscera, being differently
            directed, must produce <lb/>some change in the form of the uterus corresponding to every
            <lb/>change of posture, especially as the parts against which the <lb/>uterus will rest
            its weight, in the different postures of the body, <lb/>are of such different natures. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The same plastic state of the uterus makes it adapt its figure <lb/>to the
            circumstances of the child within, and vary as those change. <lb/>We not only in dead
            bodies see the parts of the child making a <lb/>variety of different projections on the
            outside of the uterus; but <lb/>in the living body, all the same variety is frequently
            manifest to <lb/>the touch, in examining the outside of the abdomen. The round
            <lb/>projecting ball made by the child's head or buttocks, is commonly <lb/>very
            perceptible, and in many instances smaller projecting parts <lb/>are so distinctly felt
            through the containing parts of the abdomen, <lb/>as to leave no room to doubt of their
            being knees or elbows. The <lb/>most extraordinary instance which has come to my
            knowledge, <lb/>of the uterus shaping itself to its contents, was a case of twins
            <lb/>which Dr. Mackenzie shewed to me, and which, with many other <pb xml:id="page_14"
              n="5"/>
            <lb/>curious and useful observations, which an indefatigable diligence <lb/>in his
            profession had furnished him with, it is to be feared are <lb/>already in some measure
            lost to the public. In this case, the twins <lb/>with their involucra and waters, did
            not make one compacted <lb/>oval body as usual, but the uterus had stretched into two
            distinct <lb/>bags for containing the respective twins; so that upon the out- <lb/>side
            of the uterus there was a notch dividing it into two apart- <lb/>ments, as deep and
            distinct, in proportion, as the base of the heart <lb/>represented on cards. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In several cases I have observed the uterus to stretch unequally <lb/>in the
            corresponding opposite parts; so that one half, either right <lb/>or left, has been
            considerably larger than the other. And in two <lb/>cases I found the anterior part of
            the uterus much more swelled <lb/>out than the posterior, so that the distance from the
            insertion of <lb/>one Fallopian tube to the other, measured much less upon the <lb/>back
            part than upon the fore part of the uterus; and in some cases <lb/>the reverse has been
            as evident. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The human uterus, in the unimpregnated state, commonly has <lb/>one triangular
            cavity. In many instances it is found subdivided, <lb/>at its upper part, into two
            lateral cavities, so as to resemble the <lb/>two horns of the uterus in a quadruped.
            several specimens of <lb/>such uteri are preserved in my collection. That peculiarity
            will <lb/>perhaps explain the unequal extension of the two sides, right and <lb/>left,
            in some instances of pregnancy; and may likewise explain <pb xml:id="page_15" n="6"/>
            <lb/>this very singular case of twins which Dr. Mackenzie met with: <lb/>we need only to
            suppose that the uterus had originally been sub- <lb/>divided into two horns, and that
            each ovarium had furnished a <lb/>fœtus, which was deposited in the respective side or
            horn of the <lb/>uterus, as in the quadruped. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Upon the whole, we may say that an egg is no more like the <lb/>form of the human
            uterus, than a cylinder like the beautifully <lb/>varied figure of the trunk of the
            human body. It must be ob- <lb/>served likewise, that the cavity does not always
            correspond with <lb/>the outward figure of the gravid uterus. In one instance which
            <lb/>I met with in a dead body, and still preserve, and in another, <lb/>which I was
            very sensible of in a living woman, a part or band of the <lb/>inner stratum of the
            flesh of the uterus had not stretched <lb/>in the same degree with the rest, but made a
            considerable par- <lb/>tition internally; a circumstance which might have increased the
            <lb/>difficulty, as well as the danger of rudely turning the child, or <lb/>taking away
            the placenta with the hand. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <pb xml:id="page_16" n="7"/>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>SITUATION OF THE UTERUS. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The small or lower end of the uterus is placed in the cavity of <lb/>the pelvis.
            This generally contains the greater part of the child's <lb/>head, and fills up the
            cavity of the pelvis so completely, as to <lb/>press the vesica urinaria against the
            symphysis pubis, and the <lb/>rectum against the hollow of the sacrum. The os uteri is
            directed <lb/>against the coccyx, or the lower part of the sacrum. The body <lb/>and
            fundus of the uterus, which for the most part contains all <lb/>the rest of the child
            and the placenta, is so placed in the anterior <lb/>part of the abdomen, from the brim
            of the pelvis upwards to the <lb/>epigastric region, as to be under and before all the
            other bowels in <lb/>immediate contact with the parietes abdominis, occupying the
            <lb/>whole space from one hip bone to the other, and a proportionable <lb/>space from
            these bones upwards as far as the epigastric region. <lb/>The common situation of the
            uterus will be perfectly understood <lb/>by looking at plate first, second, third, and
            fourth. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When the uterus rises up from the cavity of the pelvis into the <lb/>hypogastric
            and umbilical regions of the abdomen by its increas- <lb/>ing bulk, it is no wonder that
            it should instantly mount up before <lb/>the small intestines. Their attachment to the
            loins by the me- <lb/>sentery, would seem to render this necessary; but there is an-
            <lb/>other cause which co-operates towards this effect, and which <pb xml:id="page_17"
              n="8"/>
            <lb/>almost as certainly prevents the epiploon from falling down <lb/>before the uterus,
            though that membrane is naturally so loose, <lb/>that we might conceive it to be spread
            out indifferently either <lb/>before or behind the body of the uterus. Yet in fact this
            fatty <lb/>membrane is commonly found pushed up by the uterus, and <lb/>crowded all
            round the fundus uteri, with the small intestines in <lb/>the epigastric and adjacent
            parts of the hypochondriac regions. <lb/>The cause of all this would appear to be the
            specific lightness of <lb/>those parts in comparison of that of the uterus. The
            intestines <lb/>contain some air, and the epiploon a good deal of oil, which gives
            <lb/>them lightness, and buoys them up above the uterus. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Whoever has any tolerable notion of the shape of the abdomen, <lb/>and situation of
            the cavity of the pelvis, must understand that <lb/>the axis of the uterus is very far
            from the perpendicular line, its <lb/>lower end being turned backwards, and its upper
            end in propor- <lb/>tion turned forwards. This obliquity changes with the attitude
            <lb/>of body, and from many other causes. When erect, the weight <lb/>of the uterus
            presses the fore part of the abdomen into a greater <lb/>rotundity, and then the axis of
            the uterus approaches nearest to <lb/>the transverse or horizontal line; and in a
            recumbent posture, the <lb/>contrary happens from a similar cause. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In the case of a first pregnancy, the uterus stretches itself <lb/>higher up in the
            epigastric region, and its axis comes nearer to <lb/>the longitudinal or vertical
            direction, because the parietes of the <pb xml:id="page_18" n="9"/>
            <lb/>abdomen do not easily give way, and do not swell forwards in <lb/>any great degree;
            but in a woman who has had many children <lb/>there is a more loose and pendulous
            abdomen, and thence the <lb/>uterus does not shoot upwards, but rather forwards, and
            takes <lb/>more of the transverse situation. This oblique direction of the <lb/>uterus
            approaching to the transverse, is more remarkable in very <lb/>short women; because in
            them the chest is so near the pelvis <lb/>that the uterus is stopt in its ascent, and
            forced to shoot forwards. <lb/>The same thing happens, and for a like reason, when the
            pelvis is <lb/>very narrow. For in this case the uterus must be higher, as <lb/>no part
            of it can be lodged in the cavity of the pelvis. In a <lb/>very short and crooked woman,
            with a very narrow pelvis, upon <lb/>whom I saw the Cæsarian section performed, from a
            concur- <lb/>rence of the abovementioned causes, the fundus uteri was <lb/>turned not
            only forwards, but even a little downwards. As she <lb/>lay upon the table, the navel
            and upogastrium could not be <lb/>seen; the navel being situated on what might have been
            called <lb/>the posterior and inferior part of the abdominal tumour. And to <lb/>expose
            that part of the abdomen to the surgeon, it was necessary <lb/>with two assisting hands
            to lift up the fundus uteri, or the most <lb/>prominent part of the abdomen; without
            which the hypogastric <lb/>region would have been inaccessible. Indeed, it was an
            appear- <lb/>ance which, without having seen it, I should never have conceived. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The obliquity of the uterus towards the right or left side is <lb/>not commonly,
            indeed cannot be, very considerable. When it <pb xml:id="page_19" n="10"/>
            <lb/>is of such a size as to possess the whole, or nearly the whole <lb/>space between
            the hip bones, and its lower extremity is fixed <lb/>down to the pelvis, how is it
            possible that it should be turned <lb/>very considerably to one side? A small degree of
            lateral obli- <lb/>quity is very common; and it is natural to suppose that in a
            <lb/>reclined posture, the middle projection of the lumbar vertebræ <lb/>will throw a
            little more than one half of the uterus into the lateral <lb/>cavity between the spine
            and one hip bone. In fact, we know <lb/>that in all the last months of utero-gestation
            the abdomen is <lb/>often more full on one side than on the other. Women say in
            <lb/>such a case, that the child lies on one side; and they judge <lb/>rightly. Where
            the child lies, the bulk must both be more con- <lb/>siderable and more permanent; but
            where there is only uterus, <lb/>placenta, and water, the swelling will be softer, and
            project less. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When the child lies more in one side than in the other, I <lb/>have frequently
            observed that the limb of that side is weaker, <lb/>more benumbed, and more liable to
            cramps and oedematous swell- <lb/>ings. That an awkward position of the child will
            occasion <lb/>spasms in the limb, experience testifies with the clearest evi-
            <lb/>dence. Many women feel that the one depends upon the other; <lb/>and from
            particular motions of the child, can certainly prognos- <lb/>ticate ease or pain till it
            shall alter its situation again. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>As far as I have been able to observe, the mere obliquity of <lb/>the uterus never
            occasions so difficult a labour, as to require any <pb xml:id="page_20" n="11"/>
            <lb/>artful management to bring the os uteri into a proper situation. <lb/>In such
            cases, as in many others, art can do little good, and pa- <lb/>tience will never fail. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Whoever understands the figure and situation of the uterus <lb/>in the last months
            of gestation, will see that in that period a <lb/>case of pregnancy may commonly be
            distinguished from other <lb/>swellings of the abdomen, by outward examination alone.
            The <lb/>flatulent softness, and, when struck, the peculiar sound of the <lb/>bowels
            round the uterus, the circumscribed tumour which the <lb/>uterus forms, and the unequal
            resistance which it makes when <lb/>you press upon the child, or upon the waters, are
            commonly, all <lb/>taken together, so characteristic, as hardly to leave an expe-
            <lb/>rienced and attentive examiner in doubt. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <pb xml:id="page_21" n="12"/>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>OF THE LIGAMENTS, TUBES, AND OVARIA, OF THE <lb/>PREGNANT UTERUS. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It is a common observation, that the ligaments and tubes of <lb/>the pregnant
            uterus are attached lower upon the side of the <lb/>uterus than they were before
            pregnancy. If the reason of this <lb/>has not been so generally known, it is
            nevertheless evident. <lb/>The peritonæal coat of the uterus makes the broad ligament on
            <lb/>each side, much in the same manner as the analogous membrane <lb/>of the intestinal
            tube makes the mesentery. When a woman is <lb/>not pregnant this ligament is of
            considerable breadth, the sper- <lb/>matic vessels pass between its two laminæ, the
            round ligament <lb/>runs downwards, and outwards, on its anterior surface, and the
            <lb/>tube runs in loose serpentine turns upon its upper edge. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>But in proportion as the circumference of the uterus grows <lb/>larger, the broad
            ligaments grow narrower, their posterior la- <lb/>mella covering the posterior surface,
            and their anterior lamella <lb/>covering the anterior surface of the uterus itself. As a
            proof of <lb/>what has been said, we observe that the round ligaments do not <lb/>now
            run down on the fore part of the broad ligaments, but upon <lb/>the fore part of the
            body of the uterus itself; a proof, I say, that <lb/>the peritonæum, which covers the
            uterus at this part, is the very <lb/>membrane which before pregnancy made the anterior
            lamella of <pb xml:id="page_22" n="13"/>
            <lb/>the broad ligament. Farther, in proportion as the fundus uteri <lb/>rises upwards,
            and increases in size, the upper part of the broad <lb/>ligament is so stretched that it
            clings close to the side of the <lb/>uterus, so that in reality the broad ligament
            disappears, no more <lb/>of it remaining than its very root; viz. its upper and outer
            <lb/>corner, where the group of spermatic vessels pass over the iliacs <lb/>immediately
            to the side of the uterus. In this state, though <lb/>the small end of the tube opens
            into the same part of the uterus, <lb/>as before impregnation, yet the tube has a very
            different di- <lb/>rection; instead of running outwards in the horizontal direction,
            <lb/> it runs downwards, clinging to the side of the uterus. And be- <lb/>hind the
            fimbriæ lies the ovarium, for the same reason, clinging <lb/>close to the side of the
            uterus. The fimbriæ and ovarium are <lb/>commonly placed upon the iliac vessels, or
            fleshy brim of the <lb/>pelvis, behind the group of spermatic vessels. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The round ligaments run almost perpendicularly downwards <lb/>from the fundus uteri
            to their passage through the muscles; <lb/>they are considerably enlarged in thickness,
            and are so vascular, <lb/>that when injected, they seem to be little more than a bundle
            of <lb/>arteries and veins. Their arteries are all convoluted. Both <lb/>their arteries
            and veins are branches principally of the spermatics, <lb/>and both evidently anastomose
            with their respective external <lb/>vessels in the groin, or upper part of the labia.
            Even in this en- <lb/>larged state of the round ligaments, it is very difficult to say
            how <lb/>they terminate in the groin; they appear to be insensibly lost. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_23" n="14"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The tubes are more fleshy, vascular, and soft in their sub- <lb/>stance, and are
            less convoluted than in the unimpregnated state. <lb/>The fimbriæ and internal rugæ are
            larger and much more <lb/>beautiful, especially when their vessels are well injected. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The ovaria seem to have undergone no remarkable change, <lb/>except that one which
            contains the corpus luteum; which for <lb/>the most part can be distinguished by a
            rounded fullness, and frequently a considerable prominence, sensible both to the sight
            <lb/>and touch, upon the middle of which there is a small pointed ca- <lb/>vity or
            indentation like a cicatrix. Upon slitting the ovarium <lb/>at this part, the corpus
            luteum appears a round body, of a very <lb/>distinct nature from the rest of the
            ovarium. sometimes it is ob- <lb/>long or oval, but more generally round. Its centre is
            white, with <lb/>some degree of transparency; the rest of its substance has a
            <lb/>yellowish cast, is very vascular, tender, and friable, like glandu- <lb/>lar flesh.
            Its larger vessels cling round its circumference, and <lb/>thence send their smaller
            branches inwards through their sub- <lb/>stance. A few of these larger vessels are
            situated at the cicatrix <lb/>or indentation on the outer surface of the ovarium; and
            are <lb/>there so little covered, as to give that part the appearance of <lb/>being
            bloody when seen at a little distance. When there is <lb/>only one child, there is only
            one corpus luteum; and two <lb/>in case of twins. I have had opportunities of examining
            the ova- <lb/>ria with care in several cases of twins, and always found two <lb/>corpora
            lutea. In some of these cases there were two distinct <pb xml:id="page_24" n="15"/>
            <lb/>corpora lutea in one ovarium; in others, there was a distinct <lb/>corpus luteum in
            each ovarium. In a variety of different cases, <lb/>I have found that the sex of the
            fœtus has no relation to the <lb/>corpus luteum being in the right or left ovarium. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>OF THE THICKNESS OF THE UTERUS. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Those who say that the uterus grows thicker in the same <lb/>proportion that its
            bulk is increased, have probably been de- <lb/>ceived by examining the uterus of a woman
            who died some <lb/>hours or days after delivery. In that contracted state the ute-
            <lb/>rus is often found even two inches thick; but in all those which <lb/>I have
            examined, in the natural distended state, though there <lb/>was some difference, the
            thickness of the uterus was but a little <lb/>more considerable than before
            impregnation. When not in- <lb/>jected, its more common thickness is from one to
            two-thirds of <lb/>an inch; when its vessels, and particularly its veins, are pretty
            <lb/>well filled with wax, its thickness is thereby considerably in- <lb/>creased, more
            especially where the placenta is fixed, on account <lb/>of the number and size of the
            vessels at that part. For this <lb/>reason only, perhaps, the uterus is thickest at that
            part, and for <pb xml:id="page_25" n="16"/>
            <lb/>this reason too it is commonly thicker towards the fundus than <lb/>near the
            cervix. In respect of thickness, I have observed a good <lb/>deal of variety, and such
            inequalities in the same uterus, that <lb/>even where the placenta did not adhere, the
            uterus has been al- <lb/>most twice as thick at one part as at another. I have always
            ob- <lb/>served in opening the uterus, that its thickness is more consider- <lb/>able
            than one could have imagined it to be by feeling it exter- <lb/>nally, where there is a
            fluctuation of the water. Its substance is <lb/>so soft, that the fluctuation then felt
            is like that of water in a <lb/>thin bladder. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>OF THE BLOOD VESSELs OF THE UTERUS. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>There is no circumstance in which the gravid uterus differs <lb/>more from the
            unimpregnated, than in the size and termination <lb/>of its vessels. The arteries, both
            spermatic and hypogastric, are <lb/>very much enlarged. The hypogastric is commonly
            consider- <lb/>ably larger than the spermatic, and we very often find them of
            <lb/>unequal sizes in the different sides. They form a large trunk <lb/>of communication
            all along the side of the uterus; and from <pb xml:id="page_26" n="17"/>
            <lb/>this the branches are sent across the body of the uterus, both be- <lb/>fore and
            behind. The cervix uteri has branches only from the <lb/>hypogastrics, and the fundus
            only from the spermatics; or <lb/>in other words, the hypogastric artery gives a number
            of branches <lb/>to the cervix, besides sending up the great anastomosing branch,
            <lb/>and the spermatic artery supplies the tube and fundus uteri <lb/>before it gives
            down the anastomosing branch on the lateral <lb/>parts of the uterus. All through the
            substance of the uterus <lb/>there are infinite numbers of anastomosing arteries, large
            and <lb/>small, so that the whole arterial system makes a general net-work, <lb/>and the
            arteries are convoluted, or serpentine, in their course. <lb/>Hardly any of the larger
            arteries are seen for any length of way <lb/>upon the outside of the uterus. As they
            branch from the sides, <lb/>where they first approach the uterus, they disappear by
            plung- <lb/>ing deeper and deeper into its substance. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The arterial branches which are most enlarged, are those which <lb/>run towards the
            placenta, so that wherever the placenta adheres, <lb/>that part appears evidently to
            receive by much the greatest <lb/>quantity of blood; and the greatest number both of the
            large <lb/>and small arteries at that part pass through the placenta, and are
            <lb/>necessarily always torn through upon its separation. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The veins of the uterus would appear to be still more enlarged <lb/>in proportion
            than the arteries. The spermatic and hypogastric <lb/>veins in general follow the course
            of the arteries, and like them, <pb xml:id="page_27" n="18"/>
            <lb/>anastomose on the side of the uterus. From thence they ramify <lb/>through the
            substance of the uterus, running deeper and deeper <lb/>as they go on, and without
            following precisely the course of the <lb/>arterial branches. They form a plexus of the
            largest and most <lb/>frequent communications which we know of among the vessels of
            <lb/>the human body. And this they have in common with the ar- <lb/>teries that their
            larger branches go to, or rather come from, that <lb/>part of the uterus to which the
            placenta adheres; so that when the <lb/>veinous system of the uterus is well injected,
            it is evident that <lb/>that part is the chief source of the returning blood. Here too,
            <lb/>both the large and small veins are continued from the placenta to <lb/>the uterus,
            and are always necessarily broken upon the separation <lb/>of these two parts. The veins
            are without valves, and are there- <lb/>fore easily injected. In injecting them, we
            observe that at first <lb/>they become turgid, and project on the outer surface of the
            uterus; <lb/>but in proportion as we throw a greater quantity of wax into <lb/>these
            vessels, they grow more flat and obscure; because the uterus <lb/>itself becomes more
            filled and tense, which has the effect of com- <lb/>pressing the veins that run in its
            substance. As I know no reason <lb/>for calling the veins of the uterus sinuses, and as
            that expression <lb/>has probably occasioned much confusion among the writers upon
            <lb/>this subject, I have industriously avoided it. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <pb xml:id="page_28" n="19"/>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>OF THE LYMPHATICS. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Mr. Cruikshank is the first who observed at this school of ana- <lb/>tomy the
            lymphatics in the gravid uterus; he also injected them <lb/>with mercury, and traced
            them with great success in several sub- <lb/>jects. They are more numerous, and many of
            them larger than <lb/>could have been imagined; from which it is manifest, that a co-
            <lb/>pious absorption is carried on in the uterus towards the mother. <lb/>The
            lymphatics pervade its substance universally; its peritonæal <lb/>coat appears, like
            that of a calf's spleen, to be interwoven with a <lb/>crowded plexus of these vessels;
            and where they get to the sides <lb/>of the uterus, when filled with mercury, some of
            them are even <lb/>larger than a goose-quill. some are remarkably varicose, or en-
            <lb/>larged at particular places. They pass from the sides of the <lb/>uterus, many with
            the spermatic vessels, but the greater number <lb/>and the larger with the hypogastrics.
            Of these last, some pass into <lb/>glands on the side of the vagina; others meet with no
            glands <lb/>till they have reached the side of the pelvis, where they run into <lb/>the
            glands of the iliac plexus, or shoot backwards into the glands <lb/>of the sacral
            plexus; from both of which they pass into the lum- <lb/>bar plexus, where they are lost
            among the absorbents of the lower <lb/>extremities, and the external parts of
            generation. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Besides the lymphatic vessels of the uterus, there are others, as <lb/>we hinted
            above, belonging to the ovaria and Fallopian tubes, <pb xml:id="page_29" n="20"/>
            <lb/>which follow the course of the spermatic arteries and veins. They <lb/>anastomose
            with the lymphatics of the uterus, and terminate in <lb/>glands which are placed upon
            the sides of the lumbar vertebræ, <lb/>near the origin of these blood vessels. Here they
            become mixed <lb/>with the lymphatics of the lumbar plexus, and enter along with
            <lb/>them into the lower end of the thoracic duct. The spermatic <lb/>lymphatics enlarge
            during pregnancy in the same manner as the <lb/>blood vessels; and for this reason they
            are then both most readily <lb/>seen and injected. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The reason why the blood vessels, lymphatics, and nerves of <lb/>the ovaria and the
            Fallopian tubes, have their origin in the loins, <lb/>is the same with that of the
            origin of similar vessels and nerves in <lb/>the male. The ovaria and Fallopian tubes
            are not placed in the <lb/>cavity of the pelvis in the early foetal state, but upon the
            psoæ <lb/>muscles, some little way under the kidneys. It is natural, there- <lb/>fore,
            that their vessels and nerves should arise near the vessels <lb/>and nerves of these
            organs. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <pb xml:id="page_30" n="21"/>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>OF THE NERVES. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>I cannot take upon me to say what change happens to the system <lb/>of uterine
            nerves from utero-gestation but I suspect them to be en- <lb/>larged in some proportion
            as the vessels are. Upon this occasion <lb/>we profess only to give the anatomy of the
            gravid uterus; yet <lb/>since the descriptions of the nerves of the uterus which I have
            <lb/>read, seem to me unsatisfactory, I shall so far go beyond my sub- <lb/>ject as to
            describe the hypogastric nerves, such as they appeared <lb/>to me in a female subject
            carefully dissected for that purpose. <lb/>All the uterine nerves come from the
            intercostals, and pass in the <lb/>form of plexuses with the blood vessels, as in the
            other <lb/>abdominal viscera; so that there is a spermatic and hypogastric plexus of
            <lb/>each side attending the vessels of the same name. They are prin- <lb/>cipally the
            branches of two large cords of the intercostals, which <lb/>run down before and on each
            side of the aorta in the abdomen, <lb/>much in the same manner as the trunks of the
            intercostals run <lb/>down upon the sides of, and behind, that artery. On the left side
            <lb/>this large cord comes down from the semilunar ganglion, partly <lb/>as a
            continuation of the anterior cord of the intercostal from that <lb/>part where it is
            forming the semilunar ganglion, and partly as a <lb/>plexus of nervous filaments coming
            down more forwards from <lb/>the ganglion itself. This cord passes down before the
            beginning <lb/>of the renal artery, all along the side of the aorta. In its way it <pb
              xml:id="page_31" n="22"/>
            <lb/>receives branches from the intercostal, and gives off branches, so <lb/>that it has
            the appearance of a plexus, though the principal cord <lb/>can always be distinguished. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It gives off the renal plexus, which is situated upon the side <lb/>of the
            uppermost vertebra lumborum, and passes to the sinuosity <lb/>of the kidney, behind the
            renal vein; but both before, and behind <lb/>and above, and below, the renal artery. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Opposite to the third vertebra lumborum, the cord gives off <lb/>two pretty large
            branches, and some small filaments of nerves, <lb/>which run down with and before the
            spermatic artery. This <lb/>spermatic plexus may be distinctly traced, with the artery,
            into <lb/>the ovarium and adjacent parts, at the upper part of the broad <lb/>ligament. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Immediately below the origin of the spermatic plexus, oppo- <lb/>site to the same
            third vertebra lumborum, two large branches <lb/>come from the trunk of the intercostal
            nerve, in the common di- <lb/>rection of these communicating branches; viz. forwards,
            down- <lb/>wards, and inwards, which join the great cord, and make it larger <lb/>from
            this conjunction downwards. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>On the right side the cord comes down from the semilunar <lb/>ganglion, close to
            the root of the superior mesenteric plexus and <lb/>artery, giving a few branches only
            to the renal plexus, and runs <lb/>down on the right of the aorta, as the other on the
            left. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_32" n="23"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>And on the right side the renal plexus, which comes chiefly from the semilunar
            ganglion, as it passes towards the kidney, behind the vena cava and renal vein, the
            renal plexus, I say, sends down the spermatic plexus behind the beginning of the renal,
            which soon joins and passes with the spermatic vessels of this side. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The two cords, right and left, may be said to constitute a lum- <lb/>bar plexus all
            along the aorta, which makes the basis of the <lb/>plexuses which accompany the branches
            of that artery; or they <lb/>may be considered as the anterior cords of the intercostals
            in the <lb/>abdomen. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>At the upper part of the fourth vertebra lumborum, the right <lb/>cord gives down a
            considerable branch with the iliac artery, <lb/>which branching, forms a kind of
            sheath-like plexus upon the ar- <lb/>tery in its way to the groin. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>At the bifurcation of the aorta, the right and left cord unite <lb/>upon the fore
            part of the aorta, and make a plexus from that part <lb/>directly downwards as far as
            the lower part of the fifth vertebra <lb/>lumborum, and then finally divide into what we
            may call the <lb/>right and left hypogastric nerve. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>On the right side a pretty large branch comes from the trunk <lb/>of the
            intercostal, on the side of the fourth vertebra lumborum, <pb xml:id="page_33" n="24"/>
            <lb/>which passing downwards, and inwards behind the right iliac ar- <lb/>tery, joins
            the plexus of the two united cords before the last ver- <lb/>tebra lumborum. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The hypogastric nerve passes round the side of the pelvis, be- <lb/>tween the
            peritonæum and the hypogastric vessels, and upon the <lb/>inside of the ureter. At the
            middle of the side of the pelvis, where <lb/>the hypogastric vessels divide, the nerve
            splits into a double <lb/>range of branches; viz. posterior and anterior. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The posterior range goes to the side of the rectum, some <lb/>branches passing to
            the back part, and others to the fore part, of <lb/>the gut; and the first and uppermost
            of those branches are ma- <lb/>nifestly reflected upwards upon the gut, directing their
            course to- <lb/>wards the colon. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The anterior range of branches is the largest, arid may be con- <lb/>sidered as the
            continuation of the trunk of the hypogastric nerve, <lb/>in the form of a plexus. Where
            the hypogastric vessels are pass- <lb/>ing to the side of the uterus and vagina, this
            nerve, situated be- <lb/>hind them, spreads out in branches like the portio dura of the
            <lb/>seventh pair, or like the sticks of a fan, with many communica- <lb/>tions which
            are sent to the whole side of the uterus and vagina. <lb/>The uppermost branches pass
            upwards, in the duplicature of the <lb/>broad ligament, towards the fundus uteri. The
            branches, as <lb/>they go to lower parts of the organ, pass less obliquely, then <pb
              xml:id="page_34" n="25"/>
            <lb/>horizontally, and the lowest of all run downwards on the side <lb/>of the vagina.
            The greatest crowd or number of these branches <lb/>go to the os tincæ, and the adjacent
            parts of the uterus and <lb/>vagina. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>OF THE MUSCULAR FIBRES OF THE UTERUS. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The substance of the uterus is rendered remarkably soft and <lb/>loose in its
            texture by pregnancy; so that when an incision is <lb/>made into it, the wound can
            easily be made to open wide; or if <lb/>a narrow piece of the uterus be cut quite out
            through and through, <lb/>it is so loose and ductile, that it can be readily drawn out
            to at <lb/>least double its natural thickness. This laxity appears to depend <lb/>on two
            causes, viz. the great quantity of large vessels in its com- <lb/>position, and the
            loose connection between the fasciculi of its <lb/>fibres. It would seem probable that
            utero-gestation enlarges the <lb/>cellular connecting membrane, as well as the vessels
            of the uterus. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When we speak of the muscular fibres, it is difficult to treat <lb/>the subject
            with precision. We neither know their external <lb/>appearance, nor their internal
            composition. They only manifest <pb xml:id="page_35" n="26"/>
            <lb/>themselves to our senses, when numbers of them are collected <lb/>into bundles, and
            make what we commonly call muscular fasci- <lb/>culi. In living bodies they manifest
            themselves by motion in the <lb/>part, which we suppose is produced by a contraction or
            accurta- <lb/>tion of the fibres themselves; but that change in the nature of a
            <lb/>muscular fibre, which is the cause of its contraction, is not known. <lb/>This
            contraction in some parts is voluntary, in others is involun- <lb/>tary, and in some it
            is both. In some parts it is quick, and in <lb/>others very slow. The motion which is
            actually observed in the <lb/>uterus of living women, is involuntary and slow. It is
            com- <lb/>monly believed to be muscular motion, and the fibres peculiar to <lb/>the
            substance of the uterus are believed to be muscles. In the <lb/>quadruped, the cat
            particularly, and the rabbit, the muscular ac- <lb/>tion, of the peristaltic motion of
            the uterus, is as evidently seen <lb/>as that of the intestines, when the animal is
            opened immediately <lb/>after death. In many parts, particularly of the internal surface
            <lb/>of the uterus, these fibres have the same striking fasciculated ap- <lb/>pearance
            which we observe in common muscles; yet they are of <lb/>a paler colour, and appear to
            me to be of a harder texture. When <lb/>we know more of the nature of muscular fibres,
            we shall perhaps <lb/>be able to account for this variety. I have taken considerable
            <lb/>pains to trace the arrangement of the uterine fasciculi, but except <lb/>upon its
            inner surface, I have observed nothing but irregularity <lb/>and confusion. On the inner
            surface itself, I have observed some <lb/>variety, and always where the placenta
            adheres, a good deal of <lb/>irregularity. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_36" n="27"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In a woman who died seven days after delivery, I gave up the <lb/>uterus to this
            pursuit, and examined the fibres very carefully. I <lb/>stretched it gradually in warm
            water, then inverted it, to have a <lb/>full view of its inner surface. The remains of
            the decidua had <lb/>been melted down, and passed off with the lochia, so that the
            <lb/>fasciculated stratum of muscular fibres appeared to be bare, and to <lb/>make the
            internal surface of the uterus. In a great number of <lb/>places, but particularly where
            the placenta had been fixed, the <lb/>fasciculi left oval spaces between them for the
            passage of ar- <lb/>teries and veins, somewhat like those separations in the tendi-
            <lb/>nous fibres of the abdomen and loins, where vessels pass out to <lb/>the cellular
            membrane and integuments. The cervix uteri, where <lb/>the penniform rugæ are situated,
            had not such regular nor so <lb/>large fasciculi as the rest of the uterus. In the body
            of the uterus <lb/>the fibres were very regularly circular. The fundus was made up
            <lb/>of two concentric circular plains of fibres, at the very centre of <lb/>which was
            the orifice of the Fallopian tube. The better to con- <lb/>ceive this arrangement of the
            internal muscular fibres, we may <lb/>suppose each corner of the fundus uteri, where the
            tube is in- <lb/>serted, to be stretched or drawn out, so as to make two horns, or
            <lb/>a bifid fundus, as in the quadruped; then if we understand the inner <lb/>fibres to
            be circular in every part of the uterus, we understand <lb/>clearly how they will be
            circular in the human uterus upon its <lb/>body, and likewise circular and concentric at
            each corner of the <lb/>fundus. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_37" n="28"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When this internal stratum was removed, the fasciculated ap- <lb/>pearance and
            regular direction of the fibres was less and less <lb/>apparent, in proportion as I
            dissected outwards; which seemed <lb/>in a great measure to be owing to the infinite
            number of the <lb/>branches and communications of the large veins. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The outer stratum in general was firmer and less vascular; <lb/>that is, had fewer
            large vessels, and therefore was more dense <lb/>than the middle and inner stratum. But
            the lateral parts of the <lb/>uterus, where both the spermatic and hypogastric vessels
            first <lb/>come to it, and anastomose upon its outside, are excepted in this
            <lb/>general observation. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>I afterwards had the most favourable occasion that could be <lb/>desired, for
            examining the fibres upon the inside of the uterus. It <lb/>was the uterus of a woman
            who died at the end of the ninth <lb/>month, without being in labour, and without having
            any flood- <lb/>ing or discharge of waters. When I had examined and taken out <lb/>all
            the contents, I attended particularly to the internal surface of <lb/>the uterus. I
            found it every where covered with a thin stratum <lb/>of the decidua, through which the
            muscular fibres appeared, but <lb/>with some degree of obscurity. Upon rubbing off this
            tender <lb/>membrane with a cloth, it gave me pleasure to see how exactly <lb/>the above
            description agreed with the appearances. And it is my <lb/>opinion, that whenever a fair
            opportunity for examination presents <pb xml:id="page_38" n="29"/>
            <lb/>itself, it will be found more accurate to say, that there are two <lb/>than that
            there is one musculus orbicularis in fundo uteri. <lb/>Ruysch's figure will be found to
            be a tolerable representation of <lb/>either, and the orifice of the Fallopian tube will
            appear in the <lb/>centre of each. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>OF THE MOUTH OF THE UTERUS. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The mouth of the uterus differs considerably in the different <lb/>times of
            utero-gestation. For the greatest part of the nine <lb/>months, that is, till the cervix
            uteri be fully distended, there is a <lb/>projection of both the anterior and posterior
            lip of the os tincæ; <lb/>and in some women this continues till the very time of labour.
            <lb/>But in most women, when they are at their full time, or very near it, <lb/>the os
            uteri is flat, and makes only a small rugous hole, <lb/>often not readily discoverable
            by the touch on the lower or pos- <lb/>terior part of the rounded lower end of the
            uterus. The border <lb/>of this orifice, and the internal surface of the uterus, for an
            inch or <lb/>more all around, is full of little irregular cavities. These contain <lb/>a
            tough gluten, which shoots across, and plugs up the inner <pb xml:id="page_39" n="30"/>
            <lb/>part of the orifice. This gluten is commonly squeezed out from <lb/>all the lacunæ,
            by the dilatation of the os uteri in the beginning <lb/>and progress of the labour; and
            so losing its hold, it falls out. In <lb/>the dead body, when the part is kept some days
            in water, the <lb/>gluten swells out more and more from all these cavities, and then
            <lb/>separates entirely. Then the innumerable lacunæ which con- <lb/>tained it being
            empty, are very visible. And if the gluten has <lb/>been thus carefully taken away, and
            be floated in water, its exter- <lb/>nal surface is seen beautifully ornamented with all
            the processes <lb/>which were drawn out of the innumerable lacunæ. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <pb xml:id="page_40" n="31"/>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>OF THE CONTENTS OF THE PREGNANT UTERUS. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The contents of the pregnant uterus are the secundines, liquor <lb/>amnii, and the
          fœtus. The secundines make the lining of the <lb/>uterus, and the immediate covering of
          the child; they form the <lb/>chain of connection and communication between the bodies of
          the <lb/>mother and child, and carry on that wonderful influence upon <lb/>which the life
          and health of the child depend. There is an obvi- <lb/>ous division of them, into the
          navel string, the placenta, and the <lb/>membranes. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A peculiarity in the secundines with regard to their substance <lb/>is likewise very
          obvious. They are all more or less gelatinous <lb/>and transparent; and there is no
          manifest fibrous texture in any <lb/>part of their substance. Their texture is adapted to
          the tempo- <lb/>rary purpose which they serve. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Another peculiarity in the secundines is, that there is not any <lb/>appearance of
          fat in them, let the mother or child be ever so <pb xml:id="page_41" n="32"/>
          <lb/>adipose, at any period of utero-gestation, neither in the sound or <lb/>natural, nor
          in the morbid state of parts. What, upon a careless <lb/>examination, appears to be fat
          upon the inner surface of the pla- <lb/>centa in many cases, is an accumulation of a
          substance somewhat <lb/>like a tough jelly, with an opaque and yellowish cast; and what
          <lb/>often appears like slender ramifications of fat upon the outer sur- <lb/>face, in
          reality is not fat, but ossifications in that part of the de- <lb/>cidua. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The navel string is a cord made of three large vessels twisted <lb/>together, which
          at one end is fixed to the child's navel, and at the <lb/>other to the placenta. It
          passes, through the liquor amnii, from <lb/>the child to the rest of the secundines. It is
          sometimes little more <lb/>than a foot in length, and sometimes even more than four feet
          <lb/>long. Its more common length is about two feet. When very <lb/>long, it is generally
          entangled round the child's neck. I have <lb/>known it turned four times and an half round
          the neck. I can <lb/>hardly say that I ever saw an instance of a natural labour being
          <lb/>in any degree retarded or rendered difficult by the shortness of <lb/>the navel
          string, or by its being twisted in coils round the child's <lb/>neck. The probable reason
          for the latter is, that in such cases <lb/>there is a proportionable redundancy of length
          in the string, <lb/>which we may suppose had lain in convolutions at the depending
          <lb/>part, and that the child's head gavitating to the same place, had <lb/>thereby
          insinuated itself into the centre of the coils, and so given <lb/>them an opportunity of
          slipping over it, and of being caught, in <pb xml:id="page_42" n="33"/>
          <lb/>labour at least, upon the neck. Where a child is turned indeed <lb/>by the hand of an
          operator, the navel string will often be so en- <lb/>tangled as to occasion real
          difficulties. The thickness of the navel <lb/>string is likewise various, not only from
          the vessels being full of <lb/>blood, or empty, but from the different size of the vessels
          them- <lb/>selves, and more especially from the different quantity of the ge-
          <lb/>latinous substance which connects them. In some it is only of the size of a small
          finger, in others it is thicker than a large thumb. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The three vessels of the navel string are two arteries and a vein. <lb/>I have seen
          several cases where there was only one artery, and it <lb/>was always in proportion
          larger. I never saw two veins: in <lb/>cases of a single umbilical artery, I had supposed
          that the two <lb/>hypogastrics of the fœtus had united at the navel to form one
          <lb/>trunk; but in one fœtus of this kind which we dissected, the hy- <lb/>pogastric
          artery of one side was not reflected to the navel, but <lb/>produced only such branches as
          remain pervious in the adult. <lb/>The umbilical vessels give off no visible branches till
          they come <lb/>to the placenta. There the two arteries anastomose, commonly by <lb/>a
          cross canal, nearly of the size of one of the arteries. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>There is a great variety in the twisting of the vessels of the <lb/>navel string.
          sometimes they are uniformly and closely twisted, <lb/>like a rope, in their whole course;
          and sometimes they run al- <lb/>most quite straight and parallel, especially in that part
          of the <pb xml:id="page_43" n="34"/>
          <lb/>string which is towards the placenta; for near the fœtus it is almost always more or
          less twisted. In some navel strings there is great irregularity from solitary turnings of
          particular vessels, commonly called knots, as we see in twisting a cord where some of the
          constituent threads are longer, and therefore looser than others. The end of the navel
          string which is next the placenta is always less twisted, and more uniform than the end
          which is towards the fœtus. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Whatever be the cause, in most which I have attended to, the <lb/>twisting of the
          navel string has been in the same direction, viz. <lb/>such as would be produced in
          turning the child round upon the <lb/>navel as a centre, by pushing its head towards the
          right side and <lb/>its feet to the left. In two-and-thirty preparations now before me
          <lb/>four only are twisted the contrary way; and of the twenty- <lb/>eight which are
          twisted in the common way, three have the con- <lb/>trary twist, for some inches, at the
          extremity which was towards <lb/>the fœtus. The coat or covering of the navel string,
          which has <lb/>a smooth or polished surface, is composed of the united mem- <lb/>branes
          amnion and chorion, and is almost inseparably joined <lb/>with the parts which it
          incloses. The ligament which goes from <lb/>the bladder of the fœtus to its navel, between
          the umbilical arte- <lb/>ries, commonly called the urachus, or its remains, grows more
          <lb/>slender as it passes along. In the navel string it is hardly per- <lb/>ceptible,
          except near the fœtus. It is like a fine thread, a little <lb/>more white and opaque than
          the rest. When you have found it <pb xml:id="page_44" n="35"/>
          <lb/>near the fœtus, by taking a little pains you may trace it sensibly <lb/>almost the
          whole length of the string. Mr. Cruikshank first ob- <lb/>served this to me. Besides the
          vessels, the remains of the urachus, <lb/>and coat of the navel string, I have observed
          nothing in its compo- <lb/>sition but a fine cellular substance loaded with a transparent
          ropy <lb/>fluid, which gives the part both firmness and bulk. By touching <lb/>the cut
          surface of the fresh navel string, and removing the finger <lb/>slowly, we see the fluid
          so tenacious and ductile, as to be drawn <lb/>out into fine threads some inches in length.
          If the navel string <lb/>be kept some days, its fluid loses entirely that glutinous
          quality, <lb/>and transudes like water; for which reason the string becomes <lb/>then
          supple, and loses greatly of its bulk. In this state, if a small <lb/>blow-pipe be pushed
          into the interstices of the vessels, and proper <lb/>ligatures be made, the whole
          intersticial substance may be ren- <lb/>dered emphysematous and white, like a piece of
          inflated fresh <lb/>lungs. In this condition it may be dried, and then cut up to shew
          <lb/>more distinctly the cellular substance. The great variety that is <lb/>observed in
          the thickness or size of the navel string in different <lb/>parts and in different cases,
          depends principally on the quantity <lb/>of the cellular substance, and not on the bulk of
          the child. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The winding course of the vessels in the navel string we may <lb/>presume, prevents
          their being much affected by any stretching <lb/>force, and the firmness of the
          intersticial substance protects them <lb/>against dangerous compression. These accidents
          might otherwise <lb/>perhaps have occasioned frequent mischief, especially where there <pb
            xml:id="page_45" n="36"/>
          <lb/>is a large child, and a small quantity of the liquor amnii. In such <lb/>a case the
          navel string passing under the arm or ham, or in the <lb/>groin, might have been
          compressed so as at least to have pre- <lb/>vented the return of the veinous blood. The
          same thing might <lb/>have easily happened in those cases where there is actually a knot
          <lb/>formed upon the navel string, while the child is in the womb; <lb/>and that such a
          case sometimes happens I can hardly doubt. If I <lb/>have not been deceived, I have twice
          seen it. </p>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center">
            <lb/>OF THE PLACENTA. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The placenta and the membranes together, make one complete <lb/>unimperforated bag,
            which lines the uterus, and contains the <lb/>child. The placenta is thick, fleshy, and
            exceedingly vascular; <lb/>the membranes are thin, pellucid, and for the most part have
            <lb/>scarcely any apparent red blood vessels. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The figure of the placenta is commonly round and flat, about <lb/>an inch in
            thickness, and a span in breadth. It becomes gradu- <lb/>ally thinner all around at its
            edge, so as to render the change <pb xml:id="page_46" n="37"/>
            <lb/>from the placenta to membranes more imperceptible. The above <lb/>mentioned
            thickness of the placenta is meant of the common <lb/>flaccid state in which we usually
            see it; but when its cellular <lb/>part is well filled with wax, or any fluid, the
            placenta is at least <lb/>two inches thick. Though its figure is generally round, it is
            of- <lb/>ten oblong or triangular, or of an irregular shape; and some- <lb/>times it has
            a small lobe or two, separated and entirely distinct <lb/>from the rest. I have seen it
            oblong and narrow in the middle, <lb/>like the cipher 8, or like the common placentæ of
            twins united <lb/>by an isthmus. When the placenta is very long and narrow, and <lb/>the
            navel string is inserted near one end, it is apt to remain in <lb/>the uterus a
            considerable time after the birth of the child, and to <lb/>occasion flooding and
            faintness before it comes away. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The outer surface which adheres to the womb, and is therefore <lb/>naturally
            convex, is rough, tender in its substance, commonly <lb/>covered with blood, lightly
            subdivided into smaller constituent <lb/>lobes, and, to a common observer, seems to have
            no apparent <lb/>blood vessels, at least none of any considerable size. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Its internal surface, naturally more or less concave, is glossy, <lb/>hard or
            compact in its texture, and beautifully marked with the <lb/>ramifications of the
            umbilical vessels. The navel string, which <lb/>produces these branching vessels, is
            inserted sometimes into the <lb/>very centre, but more commonly a little nearer the
            edge, and of- <lb/>ten into the very edge of the placenta. In at least four different
              <pb xml:id="page_47" n="38"/>
            <lb/>cases, I have seen the navel string terminate on the inside of the <lb/>membranes,
            at the distance of five or six inches from the placenta. <lb/>In all these cases the
            umbilical vessels parted from one another <lb/>even to considerable distances in their
            course upon the membranes, <lb/>and came to the edge and inner surface of the placenta
            at different <lb/>places, even at the opposite parts. The termination or insertion
            <lb/>of the navel string, wherever it happens to be, makes the centre <lb/>of
            ramification for the large vessels on the internal surface of the <lb/>placenta. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Commonly there is only one centre; but in those cases where <lb/>a navel string
            attaches itself to the membranes, there are just so <lb/>many centres of ramification as
            there are trunks of large arteries <lb/>or veins coming separately to the edge of the
            placenta. The in- <lb/>ternal surface of the placenta is covered with the membranes am-
            <lb/>nion and chorion, and the external with the decidua; of which <lb/>hereafter. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The following peculiarity I have often observed in the pla- <lb/>centa. Upon its
            inner surface, at more or less distance from the <lb/>extreme border, there is a
            projecting brim, of the whitish colour of <lb/>pleuritic blood, which gives a hollow
            dish-like appearance to the <lb/>inside of the placenta. The membranes go off from this
            brim, <lb/>and the circumference of the placenta is remarkably thick, form- <lb/>ing a
            convex surface (part of the outer surface of the placenta) <lb/>instead of a thin edge. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_48" n="39"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In considering such a placenta, it would be natural to suppose <lb/>that there had
            been a cell or recess in the uterus corresponding <lb/>to the outward convexity of the
            placenta. I will not pretend to <lb/>explain this peculiarity, because it never occurred
            in any instance <lb/>where I saw the placenta still adhering to the uterus. Perhaps it
            <lb/>will be found to happen, when the ovum attaches itself near one <lb/>of the
            Fallopian tubes, in those women who have the uterus di- <lb/>vided at its fundus into a
            right and left sinuosity, corresponding <lb/>to the horns of that organ in a quadruped.
            I have observed that <lb/>such placentæ part from the uterus after labour with more
            diffi- <lb/>culty, requiring a good deal of patience and cautious assistance; <lb/>and
            frequently after all, the chorion and decidua are found to be <lb/>torn from the
            placenta all around, and left, or a portion of them <lb/>at least, adhering to the
            uterus. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The human placenta, as well as that of quadrupeds, is a com- <lb/>position of two
            parts intimately blended, viz. an umbilical or in- <lb/>fantile, and an uterine portion.
            One is a continuation of the <lb/>umbilical vessels of the fœtus; the other is an
            efflorescence of the <lb/>internal part of the uterus. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The umbilical portion of the placenta is of a simple nature, <lb/>consisting of a
            regular ramification of the arteries and veins of the <lb/>navel string into smaller and
            smaller branches, without any la- <lb/>teral anastomosis, so that when unravelled by
            gentle putrefac- <lb/>tion, motion, and washing, this part takes on the appearance of a
              <pb xml:id="page_49" n="40"/>
            <lb/>tree whose branches divide to almost infinite minuteness, not <lb/>only towards its
            outer surface, but every where through its sub- <lb/>stance. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The two umbilical arteries anastomose freely by a canal of <lb/>communication just
            where they are going to branch out upon <lb/>the placenta, sp that by injecting one of
            them, the other is readily <lb/>filled also. Every branch of an artery is attended with
            a branch <lb/>of a vein; these cling to one another, and frequently, in the sub-
            <lb/>stance of the placenta, entwine round one another as in the navel <lb/>string. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Much has been said, or supposed, about a communication be- <lb/>tween these vessels
            and those of the uterus; but from all the ex- <lb/>periments I have made upon the human
            subject (and upon qua- <lb/>drupeds likewise), it plainly appears that the umbilical
            arteries <lb/>terminate in the umbilical veins, and not in the vessels of the
            <lb/>uterus; and that the blood passes from the arteries into the veins, <lb/>as in
            other parts, and so back to the child again. If the placenta <lb/>be whole in all its
            substance, which is seldom the case, and its <lb/>blood vessels be pretty well emptied
            of their blood, any subtile <lb/>injection thrown into an artery will fill the arterial
            system through <lb/>the whole substance of the part to an amazing degree of minute-
            <lb/>ness, and return so freely by the veins as to fill them very gene- <lb/>rally and
            equally. In the same manner the whole umbilical sys- <lb/>tems may be filled by
            injecting the vein, the fluid returning from <pb xml:id="page_50" n="41"/>
            <lb/>the veins into the arteries. In both these experiments the in- <lb/>jected fluid is
            confined to the umbilical vascular system, none <lb/>escaping at the external surface of
            the placenta, neither by large <lb/>nor small orifices, whether of veins or arteries. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>After common labours the placenta is generally more or less <lb/>torn, and its
            vessels contain a quantity of coagulated blood; on <lb/>both of which accounts it is
            unfit for a successful injection. I <lb/>have generally taken care, by a previous
            management, to procure <lb/>a favourable subject, and would recommend the same method to
            <lb/>those who have the opportunity, viz. when the navel string is <lb/>tied and cut,
            not only allow the end of the string to bleed from <lb/>the placenta, but milk it
            continually till the placenta comes down <lb/>into the vagina; and in taking that away,
            be slow, cautious, and <lb/>gentle, leaving it principally to the gradual pressure from
            the <lb/>mother, and very gentle pulling by the navel string. Thus it will <lb/>neither
            be bruised nor torn; and it will be almost empty of <lb/>blood. Instantly put it into a
            bason of warm water, with the <lb/>inner surface upwards. What blood remains in the
            vessels will <lb/>still be fluid enough to be pressed from those on the surface of the
            <lb/>placenta into, and then along the vessels of the string. Then turn <lb/>up the
            external surface, wash and press it very gently, and clear <lb/>it of all coagula,
            either upon its surface, or in the venal orifices; <lb/>and the whole will be almost
            without blood. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_51" n="42"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When a placenta is finely injected, and then steeped, and fre- <lb/>quently washed
            in clean water, it is evident that the umbilical <lb/>injected vessels do not reach even
            the outer surface of the pla- <lb/>centa, but are only seen through a membrane (decidua)
            which <lb/>covers all that surface. It is rough or ragged, like the inner sur- <lb/>face
            of the uterus, to which it adheres, and by its whiteness be- <lb/>comes very distinct
            from the vascular injected part of the placenta, <lb/>over which it is spread. It
            becomes still more distinguishable <lb/>when the part is put into spirits, which render
            it more opaque <lb/>and whiter. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This membrane is an efflorescence or production of the inner <lb/>membrane of the
            uterus, and is analogous to the uterine fungi of <lb/>quadrupeds. It receives no vessels
            demonstrable by the finest in- <lb/>jections from those of the navel string, yet it is
            full of both large <lb/>and small arteries and veins. These are all branches of the ute-
            <lb/>rine vessels, and are readily filled by injecting the arteries and <lb/>veins of
            the uterus; and they all break through in separating the <lb/>placenta from the uterus,
            leaving corresponding orifices on the <lb/>two parted surfaces. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This decidua, or uterine portion of the placenta, is not a simple <lb/>thin
            membrane expanded over the surface of the part; it pro- <lb/>duces a thousand irregular
            processes which pervade the substance <lb/>of the placenta, as deep as the chorion or
            inner surface; and are <lb/>every where so blended and entangled with the ramifications
            of <pb xml:id="page_52" n="43"/>
            <lb/>the umbilical system, that no anatomist will perhaps be able to <lb/>discover the
            nature of their union. While these two parts are <lb/>combined, the placenta makes a
            pretty firm mass; no part of it <lb/>is loose or floating. But when they are carefully
            separated, the <lb/>umbilical system is evidently nothing but loose floating ramifi-
            <lb/>cations of the umbilical vessels, like that vascular portion of the <lb/>chorion
            which makes part of the placentula in a calf; and the <lb/>uterine part is seen shooting
            out into innumerable floating pro- <lb/>cesses and rugæ, with the most irregular and
            most minutely sub- <lb/>divided cavities between them that can be conceived. This part
            <lb/>answers to the uterine fungus in the quadruped. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In a placenta of nine months, I have never been able to sepa- <lb/>rate the two
            constituent parts otherwise than by some degree of <lb/>putrefaction, and gentle rubbing
            and washing; but this operation <lb/>always destroys the uterine portion, which is more
            tender, and <lb/>melts down by putrefaction sooner than the other. In the pla-
            <lb/>centa of an earlier age, the union of the two constituent portions <lb/>is less
            intimate, and they may both be preserved very entire, like <lb/>the vascular chorion and
            fungus in the quadruped. I did this <lb/>operation in a conception of four months, and
            still preserve the <lb/>uterine part attached to the inside of the uterus. I wished to
            <lb/>give a figure of it, but the processes were so irregular and so <lb/>changeable,
            while floating in water, that the painter could not <lb/>express them; and when taken
            out of water, they collapsed into <lb/>a smooth membranous appearance. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_53" n="44"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>These two portions of the placenta are so interwoven with one <lb/>another as to
            leave innumerable small vacuities, with free com- <lb/>munications, through the whole
            substance. If this cellular struc- <lb/>ture be inflated or injected, the placenta, like
            the corpora cavernosa <lb/>penis, acquires a very considerable increase of thickness,
            and sub- <lb/>sides again when the fluid escapes. This cellular receptacle in the
            <lb/>placenta, cannot be completely filled after it has been parted from <lb/>the
            uterus, because then the fluid, which we may by any con- <lb/>trivance throw in, will be
            discharged at innumerable orifices on <lb/>the outer surface of the placenta; but while
            it remains attached <lb/>to the uterus, all the cells may be easily and completely
            filled by <lb/>injecting any fluid into the arteries or veins of the uterus. These
            <lb/>vessels, and these only, have a demonstrable communication with <lb/>the spongy
            cells of the placenta, which receive the maternal blood <lb/>from the arteries of the
            uterus, and give it back into the veins of <lb/>that part. Both these vessels pass in
            the decidua, and the larger <lb/>branches of both, with little or no ramification,
            terminate abruptly <lb/>in the cells. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The arteries are all much convoluted and serpentine; the <lb/>larger, when
            injected, are almost of the size of crow-quills. The <lb/>veins have frequent
            anastomoses, pass in a very slanting direction, <lb/>and generally appear flattened;
            some of them are at least as big <lb/>as a goose-quill, and many of them are very small. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_54" n="45"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>All around at the very edge of the placenta, there are a great <lb/>number of these
            veins; and many of them run a little way, in the <lb/>direction of tangents to the
            circle, in the very angle between the <lb/>membranes and the placenta. When they have
            been filled by in- <lb/>jection, while the placenta and membranes adhere to the uterus,
            <lb/>and in that state are seen from the inside through the amnion and <lb/>chorion,
            many of them appear evidently to collect their smaller <lb/>branches from the adjacent
            parts of the decidua and of the uterus, <lb/>and throw their trunks into the placenta;
            as if there were a dis- <lb/>position for bringing venal blood into the spongy cavities
            of the <lb/>placenta, from the decidua and inside of the uterus all round the
            <lb/>placenta. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In separating the placenta from the uterus, which is commonly <lb/>practicable with
            the least imaginable force, all these vessels are <lb/>necessarily torn through; and
            then each broken vessel has an <lb/>open mouth upon the inner surface of the uterus, and
            a corres- <lb/>ponding orifice on the outer surface of the placenta. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Notwithstanding the disputes still subsisting among anato- <lb/>mists, whether any
            blood vessels pass between the uterus and <lb/>placenta, and though the texture of these
            vessels be so exceed- <lb/>ingly tender that they break with the least force, they are
            as de- <lb/>monstrable in a proper subject as any vessels in the body, not <lb/>only by
            injections, but in a fresh subject, without any artificial <lb/>preparation. And any
            anatomist who has once seen and under- <pb xml:id="page_55" n="46"/>
            <lb/>stood them, can readily discover them upon the surface of any <lb/>fresh placenta;
            the veins, indeed, he will find have an indistinct <lb/>appearance from their
            tenderness, and frequent anastomoses, so <lb/>as to look a good deal like irregular
            interstitial void spaces: the <lb/>arteries, which generally make a snake-like
            convolution or two <lb/>on the surface of the placenta, and give off no anastomosing
            <lb/>branches, are more distinct. The best time for seeing them is as <lb/>soon as the
            placenta comes away in a common labour. Let its <lb/>surface be instantly washed with
            clean water, that all the loose <lb/>blood may be removed. This renders the ground (the
            decidua) <lb/>lighter coloured, and for that reason makes the vessels, which will
            <lb/>still contain some dark blood, more conspicuous. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If a blow-pipe be thrust into the substance of the placenta any <lb/>where, the air
            which is blown into the cellular part opens and <lb/>rushes out readily by the open
            mouths both of the arteries and <lb/>the veins. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>While the placenta remains adhering to the uterus, any injec- <lb/>tion made by the
            uterine arteries fills not only these vessels, but <lb/>also the cellular part of the
            placenta; and if we continue the <lb/>operation, the injection returns from these cells
            into the veins of <lb/>the uterus, and fills them likewise. The same thing happens, but
            <lb/>in an inverted order, when we begin by injecting the veins of <lb/>the uterus. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_56" n="47"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Thence it is, that in injecting the gravid uterus, if we fill one <lb/>system of
            uterine vessels fully, we can hardly afterwards get the <lb/>injection to run any length
            of way in the other system. There- <lb/>fore when we wish to have both systems pretty
            well injected, we <lb/>must fill the first only moderately, and then the other. And
            <lb/>when the arteries and veins of the uterus have been filled in this <lb/>manner with
            wax of different colours, we observe, in examining <lb/>the placenta, that the wax which
            was thrown into the first sys- <lb/>tem (the arteries for example) is driven towards the
            inside of the <lb/>placenta by the wax which was last thrown in by the other sys-
            <lb/>tem, and which for that reason lodges itself principally in those <lb/>cells of the
            placenta which are next to its outer surface. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>While the placenta and membranes adhere to the uterus, make <lb/>a slit into the
            coat of the navel string; there introduce a blunt <lb/>probe, and force it into the
            cells of the adjacent part of the pla- <lb/>centa; then withdrawing the probe, insinuate
            an injecting-pipe, <lb/>and tie it firmly with a broad thread round the navel string.
            <lb/>You will then find that you can by that pipe fill the whole pla- <lb/>centa
            uniformly in its cellular part, and likewise all the veinous <lb/>system of the uterus
            and decidua, as readily and fully as if you <lb/>had fixed the pipe in the spermatic or
            hypogastric vein; so ready <lb/>a passage is there reciprocally between the cells of the
            placenta <lb/>and the uterine vessels. It is as much reciprocal, and more largely
            <lb/>open, than between the corpus spongiosum and the veins of the <lb/>penis. </p>
          <pb xml:id="page_57" n="48"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>From all these experiments and observations, which have been <lb/>often repeated
            and diligently attended to, with no other desire <lb/>than to discover truth, it seems
            incontestible that the human pla- <lb/>centa, like that of the quadruped, is composed of
            two distinct <lb/>parts, though blended together, viz. an umbilical, which may be
            <lb/>considered as a part of the fœtus, and an uterine, which belongs <lb/>to the
            mother; that each of those parts has its peculiar system <lb/>of arteries and veins, and
            its peculiar circulation, receiving blood <lb/>by its arteries, and returning it by its
            veins; that the circulation <lb/>through these two parts of the placenta differs in the
            following <lb/>manner; in the umbilical portion the arteries terminate in the <lb/>veins
            by a continuity of canal, whereas in the uterine portion <lb/>there are intermediate
            cells into which the arteries terminate, <lb/>and from which the veins begin. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Though the placenta be completely filled with any injection <lb/>thrown into the
            uterine vessels, none of the wax finds its way <lb/>into any of the umbilical vessels;
            and in the same manner fluids <lb/>injected into the umbilical vessels never can be
            pushed into the <lb/>uterine, except by rupture or transudation. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The first time, in the year 1743, that I injected the vein of <lb/>the navel
            string, while the placenta adhered to the uterus, in se- <lb/>parating these two parts,
            it was evident that the injection had <lb/>no where passed farther than the placenta,
            except at one place, <lb/>where a small convoluted vessel (no doubt an artery) was
            traced, <pb xml:id="page_58" n="49"/>
            <lb/>distinctly filled with wax, some little way in the substance of the <lb/>uterus;
            but upon examination, it was evident that there was ex- <lb/>travasation in that part of
            the placenta. And by many trials I <lb/>know that water, or any fluid fit for
            transudation, thrown into <lb/>the umbilical arteries or veins, readily gets into the
            cellular ca- <lb/>vities of the placenta, and thence into the vessels, especially the
            <lb/>veins of the uterus. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="39"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
