<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Beddoes: Considerations on the Medicinal Use, and on the Production of
          Facticious Airs.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Thomas Beddoes</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Considerations on the medicinal use, and on the production of
              facticious airs.</title>
            <edition n="2"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T136216</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T136216"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Bristol</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Bristol: printed by Bulgin and Rosser: for J. Johnson, in St. Paul's
                  Church-Yard, London, 1795.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1795</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="18"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="200"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="11"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107065913</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: method"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="18"/>
        <pb n="9"/>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal double-line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="space align-center">
          <lb/>PART I. </head>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A short horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <p rend="hanging space">
          <lb/>EXPERIMENTS, CAUTIONS, <hi rend="italic">and</hi> CASES, <lb/>tending to illuſtrate
          the medicinal uſe of <lb/><hi rend="sc">Factitious Airs</hi>, and of other ſubſtances,
          <lb/>of which the application to Medicine has been <lb/>ſuggeſted by modern philoſophical
          diſco- <lb/>veries. </p>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A long horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <div type="chapter">
          <head rend="italic space align-center">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">I.</hi>—Of the Atmoſphere. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>T is proved, by ſatisfactory experiments, that the
            <lb/>inferior region of the atmoſphere conſiſts of two <lb/>kinds of air, quite diſtinct
            in many properties. One is <lb/>the kind called <hi rend="sc">Vital</hi>, <hi rend="sc"
              >Dephlogisticated</hi>, or <lb/><hi rend="sc">Oxygene Air</hi>, and by a variety of
            names beſides. The <lb/>other has been named <hi rend="sc">Azotic</hi>, <hi rend="sc"
              >Phlogisticated</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="sc">Foul</hi>, or <hi rend="sc">Bad Air</hi>.
            Where the lower atmoſphere is <lb/>not altered by the breathing of animals, the burning
            of <lb/>fuel, by exhalations from ſubterraneous chemical pro- <lb/>ceſſes or putrefying
            ſubſtances, and ſuch local cauſes, if <lb/>you confine and examine an hundred cubic
            inches, you <lb/>will find twenty-ſeven or twenty-eight to be oxygene, <lb/>and the
            remaining ſeventy-two or ſeventy-three azotic <pb n="10"/>
            <lb/>air. The manner in which air may be analyſed, is <lb/>deſcribed in the writings of
            Dr. Prieſtley, Mr. Scheele, <lb/>Mr. Cavendiſh, and Mr. Lavoiſier. Theſe authors
            <lb/>explain much of the nature of oxygene and azotic air. <lb/>A candle burns in a
            veſſel full of oxygene air with <lb/>dazzling brilliancy, and is conſumed with great
            rapi- <lb/>dity. This air unites with various ſubſtances, and <lb/>turns them ſour, as
            beer and milk. Blood taken from a <lb/>vein is of a dark or livid colour; oxygene makes
            it <lb/>bright, florid or ruddy. You may ſee this difference <lb/>by breaking a clot of
            blood that has ſtood a little time <lb/>in the air; the ſurface will be crimſon, the
            inſide dark, <lb/>and the dark part, now become the ſurface, will turn <lb/>ruddy,
            though covered with ſerum. When black <lb/>blood is put into azotic air, it does not
            become ruddy. <lb/>Azotic air extinguiſhes flame, does not burn when <lb/>mixed, or in
            contact with common air, and is not <lb/>abſorbed by lime-water. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Near the earth, theſe two airs are found mixed with <lb/>ſurpriſing exactneſs. Take
            a cubic foot from ten dif- <lb/>ferent places, and you will find that a little more than
            <lb/>a quarter of each is oxygene; the reſt azotic air. <lb/>There is often likewiſe
            found a little carbonic acid air, <lb/>as one part in an hundred, though no fires burn,
            or <lb/>animals breathe near.—The nice balance of attraction <lb/>between the two
            conſtituent parts of the atmoſphere, <lb/>deſerves notice. Theſe two ſubſtances, when
            cloſely <lb/>united, form nitrous acid: If, therefore, they were <lb/>not, by ſome
            circumſtances, prevented from uniting <lb/>
          </p>
          <p>cloſely, all the oxygene, with part of the azote, would <lb/>be changed into an highly
            corroſive acid, and the <pb n="11"/>
            <lb/>waters of our globe would be converted into <hi rend="italic">aquafortis</hi>.
            <lb/>Again, azotic is lighter than oxygene air; if, therefore, <lb/>they had not ſome
            attraction, they might ſeparate, and <lb/>any animals, that ſhould be immerſed in an
            atmo- <lb/>ſphere of azotic air, would almoſt inſtantly expire: <lb/>The undiluted
            oxygene remaining below would, as we <lb/>ſhall preſently ſee, occaſion violent diſeaſes
            in man, <lb/>as well in many other animals. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter">
          <head rend="italic space align-center">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">II.</hi>—Of the breathing of man and ſimilar animals. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Fix a pipe to a bladder full of air, and, holding your <lb/>noſtrils, breathe the
            air for ſome time, and your diſ- <lb/>treſſed feelings will inform you that it is no
            longer fit <lb/>for breathing. If you transfer this breathed air into an <lb/>inverted
            glaſs jar full of water, and turn up the jar ſo <lb/>as to keep in the air, and admit
            none from the atmo- <lb/>ſphere, you will find that it extinguiſhes a candle, and
            <lb/>deſtroys the life of a ſmall animal, dipped into it. If <lb/>you procure another
            quantity of ſuch air, and add to it <lb/>a little more than one fourth of oxygene air, a
            candle <lb/>will burn in it juſt as in the atmoſphere; and you may <lb/>breathe it as
            long as ſo much freſh air, though it is not <lb/>exactly the ſame; for it contains,
            after being breathed, <lb/>ſome fixed or carbonic acid air, either thrown out <lb/>from
            the blood, or formed in the lungs. Theſe expe- <lb/>riments indicate, that breathing
            renders common air <lb/>unfit for ſupporting life or flame, by depriving it of
            <lb/>oxygene. Various other experiments ſhew further that <lb/>this is the caſe. The
            blood, before it paſſes through <lb/>the lungs, is dark; after paſſing, it is florid;
            dark <lb/>blood in a bladder, expoſed to the atmoſphere, be- <lb/>comes florid
            ſuperficially; and in breathing, the blood <pb n="12"/>
            <lb/>and air are only ſeparated by membranes not unlike a <lb/>bladder. When dark blood
            is introduced into veſſels <lb/>containing oxygene or common air, the blood be-
            <lb/>comes ruddy, and the air is reduced in quantity. <lb/>Hence it appears, that the
            blood conſtantly drinks up <lb/>a portion of the oxygene air received into the lungs;
            <lb/>and from various conſiderations I conclude that it is <lb/>conſumed in the
            contraction of the muſcles, and in the <lb/>formation of ſeveral fluids, ſecreted from
            the blood; <lb/>for the blood, after traverſing the body, comes back <lb/>to the lungs,
            dark, or without the oxygene, which it <lb/>received in paſſing through them. In ſaying
            that this <lb/>principle is <hi rend="italic">conſumed</hi>, I mean no more than that it
            en- <lb/>ters into new combinations; quitting the blood and <lb/>muſcular fibres, and
            forming perhaps an ingredient in <lb/>thoſe ſalts which the bones and fluids are found
            to <lb/>contain.—It has been calculated, that, an healthy man <lb/>requires about five
            cubic feet of air, or 1<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> cubic feet <lb/>nearly
            of oxygene air, every hour. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>So much is premiſed to render the following expe- <lb/>riments and ſpeculations
            intelligible to ſome readers. <lb/>—They will find more in Dr. Goodwin's <hi
              rend="italic">connection of <lb/>life with reſpiration</hi>, Mr. Coleman's <hi
              rend="italic">diſſertation on <lb/>ſuſpended reſpiration</hi>, Dr. Menzies' <hi
              rend="italic">Tentamen de reſpi- <lb/>ratione</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Annales de
              Chimie</hi>, 1791, p. 211), in my <lb/>three publications on the propriety of
            employing <lb/>elaſtic fluids in various diſorders, and the chemical <lb/>authors
            already quoted. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>It appears that the ſkin imbibes and exhales air. It <lb/>will imbibe various
            kinds; but, as it is found in equal <lb/>times to take in three or four times as much
            oxygene <pb n="13"/>
            <lb/>air as any other, it probably ſelects oxygene alone from <lb/>the atmoſphere. Some
            philoſophers ſuppoſe the hu- <lb/>man ſpecies to have exiſted in a monkey ſtate; would
            <lb/>the hair then ſo much prevent the cutaneous abſorption <lb/>of oxygene as the
            cloaths at preſent?—From theſe <lb/>experiments it has been alſo conjectured that immer-
            <lb/>ſion of the naked body or limbs in different airs might <lb/>cure diſeaſes. See Dr.
            Ewart on Cancer, Dilly, Lon- <lb/>don. Monthly Review for November, 1794, p. 301. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter">
          <head rend="italic hanging space">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">III.</hi>—Though the proportion of oxygene in the atmoſphere
            <lb/>may be beſt adapted to the average ſtate of health, may <lb/>the proportion not be
            ſmaller than is beneficial in ſome <lb/>diſorders, and larger than in others? </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Conſiderate perſons will, I conceive, reply, that <lb/>this is probable. I have
            made many experiments on <lb/>animals, to illuſtrate the effect of atmoſpheres of va-
            <lb/>rious conſtitutions. I ſhould have made more, had I <lb/>not been abſent from
            England, or otherwiſe occupied <lb/>for a good part of the laſt 12 months. No
            inveſtigation <lb/>of greater importance or extent, can be imagined. <lb/>This is only a
            rude beginning. Others will aſſiſt in <lb/>continuing the enquiry. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic space">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">IV.</hi>—The effect of breathing oxygene air little diluted. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Dr. Prieſtley and Mr. Lavoiſier found animals <lb/>either to die, or to become
            exceedingly ill in ſuch air, <lb/>while it continues more oxygenated than the atmo-
            <lb/>ſphere, and will ſupport the life of other animals. It <lb/>is not then defect, but
            exceſs of oxygene, that is perni- <lb/>cious here. The heart and arteries pulſate more
            quick- <lb/>ly and forcibly; the eyes grow red and ſeem to pro- <pb n="14"/>
            <lb/>trude; the heat of the body is ſaid conſiderably to in- <lb/>creaſe <note n="(a)"
              place="bottom" rend="size(0.75) align-center">
              <lb/>(a) Girtanner Antiphlogiſtiſche Chemic, p. 263. </note>, ſweat to break out over
            the whole body, <lb/>and fatal mortification of the lungs to come on. Theſe
            <lb/>appearances denote violent inflammation: animals <lb/>have always appeared to me to
            ſuffer extremely, ſoon <lb/>after immerſion in unmixed oxygene air. The human
            <lb/>ſpecies, I think, will be found to vary as widely in the <lb/>manner in which this
            elaſtic fluid affects various indi- <lb/>viduals as in any quality whatſoever. Some, I
            have <lb/>obſerved, not to be very ſenſibly affected by it when <lb/>reſpired pure. To
            my own lungs, it feels like ardent <lb/>ſpirits applied to the palate; and I have often
            thought <lb/>I could not ſurvive the inſpiration of oxygene air as it <lb/>is driven
            from manganeſe by heat many minutes. <lb/>The production of inflammation is fully
            eſtabliſhed by <lb/>diſſection, as others have found, and as appeared from <lb/>the
            following experiment:—A large kitten was kept <lb/>ſeventeen hours in a veſſel
            containing ſeveral cubic <lb/>feet of air from manganeſe, of which about eighty
            <lb/>parts in an hundred might be oxygene. This, and ano- <lb/>ther kitten of nearly the
            ſame ſize, which had lived as <lb/>uſual, were then diſſected in my preſence, by Mr.
            <lb/>Guillemard, of St. John's College, Oxford, who im- <lb/>mediately made the
            following minute of the appear- <lb/>ances:— <q rend="diple">The lungs were of
              a florid red colour in the <lb/>oxygenated kitten (A); in the other (B), they were
              <lb/>pale; the difference was very ſtriking, both in the <lb/>inflated and uninflated
              ſtate; the edge of one lobe <lb/>in A was marked, with livid ſpots (as in mortifi-
              <lb/>cation). The pleura was likewiſe evidently inflamed. <lb/>The heart in A was of a
              florid red colour. The <pb n="15"/>
              <lb/>liver, kidneys, ſpleen, and blood-veſſels of the me- <lb/>ſentery and urinary
              bladder, were of a brightiſh red <lb/>colour. In B, the heart was of a deepiſh colour.
              <lb/>The liver, ſpleen, kidneys, and blood-veſſels in ge- <lb/>neral, were of a bluiſh
              or purple colour. Both kit- <lb/>tens had been ſucceſſively killed by immerſion under
              <lb/>water. Upon opening the head of A, there was no <lb/>appearance of
              inflammation.—The blood veſſels had <lb/>rather a florid colour; but there was no ſign
              of ex- <lb/>travaſation, or more than the uſual quantity of blood. <lb/>In B, on
              raiſing the ſkull, there appeared a quantity <lb/>of blood between the bones and the
              membranes of <lb/>the brain, of which the blood-veſſels were turgid <lb/>with
              dark-coloured blood. </q>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>
            <q rend="diple">In A, the heart readily obeyed the ſtimulus of prick- <lb/>ing:
              The ſpontaneous contractions of the right au- <lb/>ricle and ventricle were frequent;
              they continued <lb/>with little diminution of frequency and force for <lb/>above half
              an hour. In about an hour, they had <lb/>wholly ceaſed. </q>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>
            <q rend="diple quotes">In B, the irritability of the heart was at firſt equi-
              <lb/>vocal. On opening the pericardium half an hour <lb/>after the ſternum had been
              removed, the motions of <lb/>the heart became very viſible; they continued more
              <lb/>than an hour after the firſt expoſure of the contents <lb/>of the thorax. </q>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The univerſally diffuſed florid colour in A was par- <lb/>ticularly ſtriking; So
            was the dulneſs of one heart at <lb/>firſt, and the vivacity of the other: Of the
            latter, I <lb/>believe the ſpontaneous pulſations were in all many <pb n="16"/>
            <lb/>times more frequent and forcible; though this circum- <lb/>ſtance deſerves more
            particular examination than we <lb/>beſtowed upon it. The kitten (A) had eaten ſome
            <lb/>time after being put into the reſervoir, as appeared <lb/>from food introduced at
            the ſame time. The air ſeemed <lb/>to have ſuffered little diminution either in quantity
            or <lb/>quality: The reaſon will appear from a ſubſequent <lb/>experiment. On cutting
            the wind-pipe of A to blow <lb/>up the lungs, a good deal of viſcid mucus flowed out.
            <lb/>This was occaſioned by ſtrong action continued for <lb/>ſome time, and was not ſeen
            in any thing like the ſame <lb/>degree in B. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter">
          <head rend="italic hanging space">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">V.</hi>—Experiments to aſcertain the condition of the ve-
            <lb/>nous blood in animals made to reſpire oxygene air. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>On comparing the experiments made upon blood <lb/>out of the body, I was formerly
            uncertain what might <lb/>be expected to be the effect of hyper-oxygenation of <lb/>the
            ſyſtem upon the colour and other qualities of <lb/>the venous blood. (See my
            Obſervations on conſump- <lb/>tion.) Many ſubſtances, containing oxygene, brighten
            <lb/>venous blood, but oxygenated marine acid, according <lb/>to ſeveral foreign
            chemiſts of reputation, has an oppo- <lb/>ſite effect. Mr. Guillemarde and myſelf often
            noticed <lb/>the dark appearance of the veins in animals charged <lb/>with oxygene, and
            of the blood they diſcharged when <lb/>wounded. To inveſtigate this point more
            particularly, <lb/>one of two equal half-grown rabbits was kept fifteen <lb/>minutes in
            a mixture of three parts of oxygene air <lb/>from heated manganeſe, and one parts of
            atmoſpheric <lb/>air. Both were killed by blows on the back of the <lb/>head, and opened
            nearly at the ſame time. This ex- <pb n="17"/>
            <lb/>periment was made in the preſence of Mr. William <lb/>Clayfield, and Mr. Bowles,
            Surgeon, or Briſtol. In <lb/>the oxygenated rabbit neither the <hi rend="italic">vena
              cava</hi> itſelf, nor <lb/>blood taken from it, appeared leſs dark-coloured; we
            <lb/>thought (but were not certain) that it was rather more <lb/>ſo. The blood of the
            oxygenated rabbit coagulated <lb/>much more rapidly. The liver alſo was of a much
            <lb/>leſs dark colour in this rabbit. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The blood of both gained its uſual florid colour on <lb/>ſtanding expoſed to the
            air. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/><hi rend="sc">Experiment 2.</hi>—Of two equal and nearly full- <lb/>grown rabbits,
            one was kept a quarter of an hour in <lb/>undiluted oxygene air, prepared as before.
            Both were <lb/>then killed and opened, as before, by Mr. Bowles. <lb/>In the oxygenated
            the following were the appearances. <lb/>The veins were certainly not of a lighter
            colour, nor <lb/>the blood. A quantity from the <hi rend="italic">vena cava</hi> of both
            rab- <lb/>bits was received in tea-cups. When it was ſpread <lb/>thin on the ſides of
            the veſſel, we thought the oxyge- <lb/>nated blood had a purple or claret colour, which
            was <lb/>not perceptible in the other; Mr. Bowles likewiſe <lb/>thought its general
            appearance rather darker; its coa- <lb/>gulation, as in the former experiment, was more
            ſpeedy: <lb/>and the coagulum, as I thought on examination af- <lb/>terwards, was
            firmer.—The liver was leſs dark. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>On the margin of the lungs in the oxygenated rabbit, <lb/>we obſerved florid ſpots
            in ſhape and ſituation like <lb/>thoſe I had formerly ſeen on the lungs of animals long
            <lb/>confined in oxygene air; and which I take to be points <lb/>of inflammation. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>We obſerved ſigns of much ſtronger irritability in <lb/>the right auricle and
            ventricle, in the diaphragm and <pb n="18"/>
            <lb/>the intercoſtal muſcles of the oxygenated rabbit. They <lb/>continued longer too in
            this. But conſidering the <lb/>force and frequency of the contractions, the quantity
            <lb/>of action would have been greater in the oxygenated, <lb/>had the irritability
            continued five times as long in the <lb/>other. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Theſe phænomena made me wiſh for an opportu- <lb/>nity of oxygenating animals of
            large ſize, as horſes, <lb/>and of drawing blood from their veins and arteries <lb/>both
            before and afterwards. Such a train of experi- <lb/>ments would form a very intereſting
            ſupplement to Mr. <lb/>Hunter's reſearches concerning the <hi rend="italic">general
              principles <lb/>of the blood</hi>. <hi rend="italic">(See his Treatiſe on the blood,
              inflamma- <lb/>tion, and gun-ſhot wounds, p. 11-100.)</hi> The ſpee- <lb/>dier
            coagulation of the oxygenated venous blood I <lb/>think remarkable, and as it happened
            in three experi- <lb/>ments, it probably was not accidental. The more vi- <lb/>gorous
            action of the oxygenated muſcles too deſerves <lb/>to be compared by a courſe of
            experiments with the <lb/>tendency of oxygenated blood to coagulate ſooner. <lb/>Several
            perſons, of whom all did not know the one <lb/>rabbit from the other, found the boiled
            fleſh of the oxy- <lb/>genated, in both caſes, more ſtringy, harder, and leſs
            <lb/>juicy. The difference was moſt ſenſible in the young <lb/>pair. The greater
            ſtringineſs was apparent on both <lb/>theſe occaſions to the eye. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>We obſerved that the rabbits drank repeatedly du- <lb/>ring their confinement in
            oxygene air. The latter had <lb/>been watered a ſhort time before; I could not learn
            <lb/>whether the former had or not. Perhaps this thirſt <lb/>(if ſuch it was) depends on
            the excitement produced. </p>
          <pb n="19"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The concluſion directly deducible from theſe expe- <lb/>riments, is, that the blood
            parts with that exceſs of <lb/>oxygene upon which its florid colour depends, before
            <lb/>it gets into the larger veins, or indeed into any of the <lb/>viſible veins. The
            altered colour of the ſolids ſhews <lb/>where the oxygene remains. But as we can never
            get <lb/>to the end of our phyſiological enquiries, a further <lb/>problem may be
            propoſed:— <q rend="diple quotes">If the oxygenation be <lb/>continued very long, will
              not the ſolids be ſo <lb/>highly charged as to be able to take no more oxy- <lb/>gene
              from the arterial blood? and will it not paſs <lb/>florid into the veins? </q>—If this
            does not happen, <lb/>there muſt be ſome contrivance in the ſyſtem to throw <lb/>this
            principle perpetually from the ſolids. Thoſe who <lb/>do not think that oxygene combines
            with the blood <lb/>during reſpiration, have only to change the terms of <lb/>my
            concluſion. The fact remains. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter">
          <head rend="italic space align-center">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">VI.</hi>—Experiments with air, containing ſomewhat more
            <lb/>oxygene than the atmoſphere. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>In my letter to Dr. Darwin, I conjectured <q rend="diple quotes">that if
              <lb/>before immerſion divers were to breathe air of an <lb/>higher than the ordinary
              ſtandard, they would be able <lb/>to continue longer under water, </q> (p. 13). I made
            ſe- <lb/>veral experiments to determine whether this ſuppoſi- <lb/>tion was juſt; in
            each two animals of the ſame litter <lb/>were employed; and as ſeveral ſpectators were
            ſome- <lb/>times preſent, they were deſired to fix upon the weakeſt <lb/>for
            oxygenation. The following report I literally <lb/>tranſcribe from my journal, as it was
            ſettled and ſub- <lb/>ſcribed by the ſpectators: <q rend="diple">Auguſt 20th,
              1793. <lb/>Kitten C was placed in a mixture of nearly two- <lb/>thirds oxygene air
              from manganeſe, and one-third <pb n="20"/>
              <lb/>atmoſpheric air; it was kept twenty minutes in the <lb/>veſſel, which was from
              time to time ſupplied with <lb/>oxygene air, ſo as to keep the air better than atmo-
              <lb/>ſpheric air; which was known by dipping a candle <lb/>into it, and obſerving that
              it burned with a brighter <lb/>flame. At the expiration of the twenty minutes, C
              <lb/>and D, which had breathed atmoſpheric air, <lb/>were immerſed in water till
              perfect aſphyxia came <lb/>on. At the inſtant they were taken out, there ap-
              <lb/>peared in both a motion of the lower jaw; C began <lb/>ſenſibly to recover, while
              D lay as dead: In a mi- <lb/>nute and half, C roſe, and began to walk about the
              <lb/>room, ſtaggering at firſt, D being ſill motionleſs or <lb/>nearly ſo; in this
              ſtate it continued for fifteen mi- <lb/>nutes, when, for the firſt time, it raiſed
              itſelf, and <lb/>immediately afterwards fell on its ſide. </q>
          </p>
          <p rend="space sc indentall">
            <lb/>
            <q rend="diple">Christopher Machell. <lb/>Richard Lovell Edgeworth. <lb/>J.
              Guillemard. <lb/>Jas. Sadler. <lb/>Thomas Beddoes. </q>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>
            <q rend="quotes">Kitten D died the next day. </q>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Of many ſimilar experiments, it is ſufficient to ob- <lb/>ſerve, that the reſult
            was always in ſome degree the <lb/>ſame; ſometimes the unoxygenated animal failed to
            <lb/>recover; it was generally noticed that the oxygenated <lb/>ſhewed ſigns of life
            under water the longeſt; and ſome- <lb/>times that it ſtruggled as much as ever after
            its unoxy- <lb/>genated fellow had ceaſed to move. Thus, in an ex- <lb/>periment
            (September 28) a whelp, which had reſpired <lb/>atmoſpheric mixed with one-third of
            oxygene air for <lb/>thirty-four minutes, is regiſtered to have been as much <lb/>alive
            as before immerſion under water, another puppy <pb n="21"/>
            <lb/>of the ſame litter unprepared, and immerſed at the <lb/>ſame time, having become
            motionleſs. Theſe facts <lb/>illuſtrate the query concerning divers. To obviate <lb/>any
            miſtake from difference of conſtitution, the expe- <lb/>riment was ſometimes repeated
            upon the ſame pair of <lb/>animals, one being oxygenated one day, and the other <lb/>the
            next, or the day following. The water in which <lb/>they were drowned, was ſometimes
            heated to the tem- <lb/>perature of the body. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>But as unequal quantities of liquid have been found <lb/>to get down the wind-pipe
            of drowning animals, it <lb/>ſeemed proper to repeat the experiment in another
            <lb/>manner.—Accordingly, of two greyhound puppies of <lb/>the ſame litter, ten days
            old, E the weaker was kept an <lb/>hour and fifty minutes in a mixture of two-thirds of
            <lb/>atmoſpheric air, and one-third of oxygene air from <lb/>heated manganeſe. F was
            left as uſual: Both were <lb/>then immerſed in hydrogene air. F ſoon appeared <lb/>much
            agitated, and expreſſed much uneasineſs. E <lb/>moved very little, and ſoon placed
            itſelf in the couch- <lb/>ant poſture, with the head between the fore-legs and <lb/>the
            muzzle reſting on the bottom of the veſſel. In <lb/>five minutes, F was lying on its
            ſide, now and then <lb/>breathing, which it did leſs and leſs frequently and <lb/>more
            feebly. In ten minutes, this effort was ſcarce <lb/>perceptible: In two minutes more, it
            was not once <lb/>repeated. For the laſt ſix out of the twelve minutes, <lb/>E was ſo
            perfectly ſtill, that we were diſpoſed to be- <lb/>lieve it dead; and a perſon preſent
            ſaid, <q rend="diple quotes">this expe- <lb/>riment will turn out ill for oxygene. </q>
            During theſe <lb/>laſt ſix minutes, E had not inſpired at all; and from <lb/>the firſt,
            the reſpiration was very infrequent. </p>
          <pb n="22"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>At the end of the twelve minutes, both puppies <lb/>were taken out of the hydrogene
            air; E immediately <lb/>cried and ſtruggled, F being quite motionleſs. They <lb/>were
            laid before a fire; E cried, moved, and ſoon <lb/>walked as uſual; F ſeeming quite dead.
            In ſixteen <lb/>minutes, a ſtream of oxygene air was blown into F's <lb/>mouth, but no
            ſign of life appeared. The animal was <lb/>afterwards opened; upon irritating the
            pericardium <lb/>with a pointed knife, ſo as to preſs upon the heart, no <lb/>movement
            followed; the pericardium being removed, <lb/>the heart began to contract ſpontaneouſly;
            a ſtream <lb/>of oxygene air being directed upon the heart, its ac- <lb/>tion became
            more ſtrong and frequent; the number <lb/>of ſtrokes was about ſeventy in a minute. The
            colour <lb/>of the heart (probably from the filling of its own blood <lb/>veſſels)
            changed from pale to red. The difference of <lb/>colour in the tongues of theſe puppies
            was ſtriking, <lb/>after the experiment, even by candle light, that of E <lb/>being much
            more ruddy. The following variation <lb/>ſeems worth tranſcribing from the journal: Of
            two <lb/>puppies of the ſame litter, the weaker G was kept in <lb/>atmoſpheric air mixed
            with one-third oxygene, and H <lb/>for an equal time in atmoſpheric air with one-third
            <lb/>hydrogene. Both were plunged into tepid water. <lb/>H became motionleſs, while G
            moved with force, <lb/>cried on being taken out, and ſeemed little affected. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The effect of oxygene air was very ſtriking in re- <lb/>covering H. It began to
            move, and reſpire the <lb/>moment it was put into a veſſel containing this air. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>It was ſometimes obſerved, that the movements of <lb/>very young puppies under
            water, did not entirely <lb/>ceaſe in leſs than fifteen minutes. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="23"/>
        <div type="chapter">
          <head rend="italic indent space">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">VII.</hi>—Neceſſity of oxygene air to muſcular exertion. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The blood in the veins is dark; in the arteries it is <lb/>bright. When the
            reſpiration is ſtraitened, the ar- <lb/>terial blood becomes darker; when acceſs of
            oxygene <lb/>air is prevented, all the blood becomes dark. In <lb/>drowned and ſtrangled
            perſons, the face, lips, the ſkin <lb/>under the nails, and ſome other parts, are of a
            violet or <lb/>dark blue colour. Here the blood can receive no <lb/>oxygene.—There are a
            number of caſes on record, <lb/>where, from bad conformation of the heart and adja-
            <lb/>cent great blood veſſels, part of the blood only tra- <lb/>verſed the lungs; the
            reſt paſſed into the arteries <lb/>again in the dark diſoxygenated ſtate in which it re-
            <lb/>turns from the veins. Such perſons are always blue <lb/>or livid. They are
            extremely feeble; in walking, are <lb/>ſometimes obliged to ſtop every third ſtep, nor
            can <lb/>they make any exertion of the muſcles without inſtant <lb/>panting and
            wearineſs. They commonly die ſuddenly; <lb/>you will find an account of ſuch individuals
            in <hi rend="italic">the <lb/>Commentaries of the Inſtitution at Bologna <hi
                rend="roman">Vol. 6, <lb/>p. 64.</hi></hi>
            <hi rend="italic">Philoſoph. Tranſactions, <hi rend="roman">vol. 55, p. 72.</hi></hi>
            Me- <lb/><hi rend="italic">dical Obſervations and Enquiries, <hi rend="roman">vol.
                6</hi></hi>, in my <hi rend="italic">Medical <lb/>Obſerv. <hi rend="roman">p.
                62.</hi></hi>
            <hi rend="italic">Abernethy's Surgical Eſſays, <hi rend="roman">part 2.</hi></hi>—
            <lb/>Perſons ill of ſea-ſcurvy, often drop down dead in <lb/>making a ſudden effort, and
            from ſurprize. There is <lb/>reaſon to believe, that either living in confined air, or
            <lb/>on ſalted food, occaſions a deficiency of oxygene in <lb/>the fluids and ſolids. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Hence, if a perſon were to keep quite ſtill, a given <lb/>quantity of air ſhould
            ſerve him to breath longer than <lb/>if he exerted himſelf. Thus ſhould any perſons find
            <lb/>themſelves again in the ſituation of Mr. Holwell and <pb n="24"/>
            <lb/>his fellow-ſufferers in the Black-hole priſon at Cal- <lb/>cutta, their beſt chance
            of ſurviving would probably <lb/>be to forbear vehement ſtruggles. The fever of the
            <lb/>ſurvivors appears to have been occaſioned by the great <lb/>ſtimulating power of
            freſh air, and of the ſenſations <lb/>their eſcape muſt have occaſioned. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The following experiments render probable the ex- <lb/>penditure of oxygene in
            muſcular exertion. They <lb/>do not, however, abſolutely prove this poſition; nor
            <lb/>did their immediate reſult appear to me ſo certain as of <lb/>my other experiments.
            Of two half-grown kittens of <lb/>the ſame litter, one was teazed to make efforts for
            half <lb/>an hour, and then put into an air-tight veſſel, in which <lb/>it lived 48
            minutes; the other lived 56 m. in the ſame <lb/>veſſel; it would require more ſuch cruel
            experiments <lb/>to decide whether ſpeedier death here aroſe from pre- <lb/>vious
            conſumption of oxygene by ſtrong muſcular <lb/>action, and the ſubſequent neceſſity of a
            ſupply. It <lb/>ſhould be obſerved, that the firſt animal was not reſpir- <lb/>ing more
            deeply than the ſecond, at the time they <lb/>were incloſed. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The following fact is remarkable, and countenances, <lb/>but does not rigorouſly
            prove, the hypotheſis. A <lb/>grown cat was incloſed in an air-tight glaſs veſſel.
            <lb/>She immediately became furious to a degree beyond <lb/>what I ever obſerved in any
            animal under experiment. <lb/>The violent agitation continued for 20 minutes. In <lb/>5
            minutes more—25 minutes in all—ſhe appeared <lb/>dead; ſhe was left in the veſſel two
            minutes longer, <lb/>and proved to be quite dead. A lighted candle was <lb/>immediately
            extinguiſhed on being introduced into the <lb/>veſſel. </p>
          <pb n="25"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Into the ſame veſſel another cat of the ſame ſize <lb/>and age nearly, to which a
            ſmall glaſs of white wine <lb/>had been given half an hour before, was introduced.
            <lb/>This cat ſat almoſt perfectly ſtill during the whole <lb/>experiment. It lived 47
            minutes, or nearly twice as <lb/>long as the other. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>In order to vary the experiment, half a glaſs of <lb/>ſherry was given to a kitten
            nearly grown. It was <lb/><hi rend="italic">immediately</hi> put into the ſame receiver;
            and ſet to <lb/><hi rend="italic">ſtruggle very violently</hi>. It ſoon appeared to
            reſpire <lb/>with difficulty. In 15 minutes the reſpirations were <lb/>98 or 100 in a
            minute. It did not reſpire after the <lb/>34th minute, and in 2 minutes more was taken
            out in- <lb/>ſenſible. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>A fellow kitten, no way prepared, was placed in the <lb/>ſame receiver, and
            remained <hi rend="italic">very tranquil</hi> for above a <lb/>quarter of an hour; its
            reſpiration was never ſo fre- <lb/>quent as that of the former; and it raiſed its head
            and <lb/>breathed at the end of 41 minutes. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>We have then <lb/>
            <table rows="7" cols="3">
              <row role="label" rend="align-right">
                <cell/>
                <cell>Minutes. </cell>
                <cell>Minutes. </cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>An haraſſed kitten living </cell>
                <cell rend="align-right">48<hi rend="dc(2)">}</hi></cell>
                <cell rend="align-right">Difference 8. </cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Its fellow, not previouſly haraſſed, </cell>
                <cell rend="align-right">56</cell>
                <cell rend="align-right"/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell rend="hanging">A grown cat not prepared, but furi- <lb/>ouſly agitated, - - - </cell>
                <cell rend="align-right"><hi rend="dc(4)">}</hi>
                  <lb/>25</cell>
                <cell rend="align-right">
                  <lb/>Difference 22. </cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell rend="hanging">Another perfectly tranquil, having <lb/>drank wine, - - - </cell>
                <cell rend="align-right">
                  <lb/>47</cell>
                <cell rend="align-right"/>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell rend="hanging">A large kitten immediately after <lb/>wine, and violent, - - </cell>
                <cell rend="align-right"><hi rend="dc(3)">}</hi>
                  <lb/>34</cell>
                <cell rend="align-right">
                  <lb/>Difference 7. </cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>Its fellow tranquil without wine, </cell>
                <cell rend="align-right">41</cell>
                <cell rend="align-right"/>
              </row>
            </table>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In theſe ſix experiments the ſame veſſel, that is, the <lb/>ſame quantity of air,
            was uſed. It may be ſaid, by a <pb n="26"/>
            <lb/>perſon unuſed to accuracy of terms, <q rend="quotes">no wonder the <lb/>moſt
              exhauſted animals ſhould periſh ſooneſt. </q> By <lb/>conſidering a moment, he will
            perceive, that it is de- <lb/>ſirable to know preciſely in what this exhauſtion
            <lb/>conſiſts. I formerly conjectured that oxygene is con- <lb/>ſumed faſter by an
            animal under the firſt operation of <lb/>wine or other ſuch ſtimulants; and Dr.
            Withering <lb/>afterwards adduced the experience of Mr. Spalding in <lb/>confirmation of
            this conjecture. It is not ſo eaſy to <lb/>make the experiment upon animals; the efforts
            of ſome <lb/>under confinement being ſo much more violent than <lb/>of others. The laſt
            experiment was made with a view <lb/>to this queſtion, but the two preceding incline me
            to <lb/>refer ſpeedier death in this inſtance to the violent <lb/>ſtruggles, rather than
            to the wine. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter">
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">VIII.</hi>—Another comparative experiment with an Ani- <lb/>mal
            charged with oxygene. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Of two half-grown rabbits (K and L) of the ſame <lb/>brood, colour, ſize, and
            apparent ſtrength, K was put <lb/>into a larger reſervoir containing atmoſpheric air
            with <lb/>a little oxygene. After ſome hours it was taken out, <lb/>and placed for an
            hour longer in a mixture of nearly <lb/>equal parts of oxygene and atmoſpheric air. It
            did <lb/>not ſeem to ſuffer in its reſpiration; K and L, which <lb/>latter had remained
            at large in the ſame apartment, <lb/>were then incloſed in a veſſel, and placed in a
            freezing <lb/>mixture. In 20 minutes ſome of the cold brine was <lb/>poured upon the
            bottom of the veſſel in which the <lb/>rabbits were: in 30 minutes L ſeemed affected, in
            45 <lb/>was ſcarce alive, and in 55 was quite lifeleſs, and fro- <lb/>zen ſtiff. They
            were dipped in cold water, and the <lb/>animal recovered perfectly. I obſerved many con-
            <lb/>vulſions and much tremor of the limbs during reco- <pb n="27"/>
            <lb/>very. It was between 8 and 9 o'clock in the evening <lb/>when the rabbits were
            taken out of the veſſel. K, by <lb/>12, had recovered the uſe of its forelegs, and being
            left <lb/>not far from a dying fire within the fender, was found <lb/>in the morning
            running about the room, when it eat <lb/>cabbage leaves freely. It was kept alive for a
            week, <lb/>when the legs appeared diſeaſed from too quick ap- <lb/>plication of heat at
            firſt. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The experiment being repeated without admitting <lb/>liquor into the receiver, the
            reſult was ſimilar. Would <lb/>opium and wine enable an animal to reſiſt the freez-
            <lb/>ing mixture, as oxygene does? </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter">
          <head rend="italic space align-center">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">IX.</hi>—Experiments with oxygene and other airs, largely
            <lb/>diſtributed through the cellular ſubſtance. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Dr. Maxwell, aſſiſted by Dr. Goodwyn and ſome <lb/>other friends of accuracy and
            genius, forced different <lb/>airs under the ſkin of animals, whence every perſon in
            <lb/>any degree acquainted with anatomy, knows they <lb/>would inſinuate themſelves far
            and wide through the <lb/>body, in conſequence of the free communication be- <lb/>tween
            different portions of the cellular ſubſtance.— <lb/>
            <list>
              <item>I. 4<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> pints of <hi rend="italic"
                  >atmoſpherical air</hi> were forced under the <lb/>ſkin of a bitch, weighing 20lb.
                the inciſion was <lb/>cloſed by a ſuture: the animal appeared uneaſy and
                <lb/>indiſpoſed for 36 hours; the puffing did not begin to <lb/>ſubſide before the
                9th day; on the 20th, no air was <lb/>left except a little about the lower part of
                the belly.— </item>
              <lb/>
              <item>II. 3 pints of air, in which a light had burned out, <lb/>were forced under the
                ſkin of a dog weighing 13lb. <lb/>For ſome hours the animal appeared ſtupid. The em-
                <lb/>phyſema or puffing ſeemed to decreaſe during the 3d <pb n="28"/>
                <lb/>day; on the 16th convulſions came on and frequently <lb/>returned; on the 20th
                the dog died, much debilitated. <lb/>In three other experiments nearly the ſame
                phæno- <lb/>mena were obſerved.— </item>
              <item>III. 4 pints of oxygene air <lb/>were infuſed in the ſame manner into another
                dog; <lb/>ſlight uneaſineſs was obſerved for the firſt hour, and <lb/>afterwards the
                animal appeared exceedingly lively <lb/><hi rend="italic">(maxima alacritas)</hi>.
                Next day the emphyſema began <lb/>to leſſen; by the 10th all the air was abſorbed.
                In <lb/>another dog of 19lb. 3<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> pints of
                this air diſappeared in <lb/>8 days; in a third of 21lb. 3 pints in 8 days; in a 4th
                <lb/>of 20lb. 3 pints nearly in 7 days. The 2d and 3d were <lb/>affected as the
                firſt dog; the 4th was in no way affected. <lb/>— </item>
              <item>IV. Carbonic acid air was infuſed into ſeveral <lb/>dogs and rabbits. A large
                quantity (as much as 2 <lb/>pints in a dog of 17lb.) diſappearing during the opera-
                <lb/>tion; the reſt was gradually abſorbed in 4-14 days. <lb/>No inconvenience
                followed, except in one caſe where <lb/>a pint of air infuſed into a rabbit 3 months
                old, occa- <lb/>ſioned uneaſineſs from diſtention; but even here the <lb/>animal eat
                with a good appetite in half an hour. The <lb/>inſtantaneous diſappearance of ſo
                much air in theſe <lb/>experiments, was probably owing to its combination <lb/>with
                the moiſture in the cellular ſubſtance.— </item>
              <item><choice>
                  <corr>V. </corr>
                  <sic/>
                </choice>Inflam- <lb/>mable air (from metallic ſolutions, I ſuppoſe) occa-
                <lb/>ſioned heavineſs and ſhivering in two dogs; 3 pints in <lb/>one 2<formula
                  notation="fraction">1/2</formula> in the other. Some detumeſcence was ob-
                <lb/>ſerved on the 4th day in both; in 13 days the air was <lb/>all gone in the 1ſt,
                and in the 2d in 9 days.— </item>
              <item>VI. 2<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula>
                <lb/>pints of nitrous air were infuſed into a dog of 28lb. <lb/>It howled as if in
                exquiſite pain: in 15 minutes it ſtag- <lb/>gered as if drunk; then convulſions came
                on, and vo- <lb/>miting with involuntary excretions. In 30 minutes <lb/>it lay
                enfeebled on the ground, making deep and labo- <pb n="29"/>
                <lb/>rious inſpirations, in 54<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> it died,
                the convulſions con- <lb/>tinuing to the laſt.—The heart had all its cavities full,
                <lb/>and was quite inirritable. The lungs were of a pale <lb/>ſaffron colour, and
                ſhewed no veſtige of red blood. <lb/>Brain in a natural ſtate. In another experiment
                  1<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula>
                <lb/>pint of nitrous air produced the ſame effects, and death <lb/>in 45 minutes. In
                neither caſe were the external <lb/>muſcles inirritable. Rabbits died juſt as theſe
                dogs, <lb/>and the ſmell of nitrous acid was perceived when the <lb/>lungs were
                inflated and left to collapſe. In this theſis <lb/>(Edinburgh 1787) Dr. Maxwell
                relates other experi- <lb/>ments, in which airs were thrown into the blood-veſ-
                <lb/>ſels. By one (p. 22) he ſhews that elaſtic fluids do <lb/>not prove fatal till
                they get into the cavities of the <lb/>heart. But as theſe latter experiments
                ſuggeſt no <lb/>concluſion concerning the medicinal power of elaſtic <lb/>fluids, I
                need not conſider them at preſent. Mr. <lb/>Achard of Berlin, was the firſt who
                publiſhed experi- <lb/>ments with different aird injected into the cellular
                <lb/>membrane. But Mr. Achard is a writer whom you <lb/>can ſeldom quote with
                confidence. </item>
            </list>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter">
          <head rend="italic space align-center">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">X.</hi>—Experiments with hydrogene and other mephi- <lb/>tic airs. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Dr. Prieſley, (<hi rend="italic">Exp. on Air, N. Ed. <hi rend="roman">I.
              229</hi></hi>), ſays, <lb/>
            <q rend="diple quotes">Inflammable air kills animals as ſuddenly as fixed <lb/>air, and
              as far as can be perceived, in the ſame <lb/>manner, throwing them into convulſions,
              and there- <lb/>by occaſioning preſent death. </q> Dr. Prieſtley does <lb/>not ſay how
            he aſcertained the former part of this aſ- <lb/>ſertion, and I apprehend, it will be
            found erroneous, <lb/>if it regard pure hydrogene. Mr. Scheele could make <lb/>20
            inſpirations without inconvenience; and I have <lb/>ſeen ſeveral perſons breathe ſtill
            oftener from a tube <pb n="30"/>
            <lb/>through which a current of this air ſet, their noſtrils <lb/>not being cloſed (<hi
              rend="italic">Letter to Dr. Darwin, p. 44</hi>). Hence <lb/>I concluded that this
            bland air might with impunity <lb/>be breathed unmixed, longer than any other mephitic
            <lb/>air, except perhaps azotic. Dr. Macdonald of Belfaſt, <lb/>whoſe abilities and
            ſkill in phyſiological reſearches <lb/>muſt be well remembered by all who ſtudied
            medicine <lb/>at Edinburgh ten years ago, confirms me in this opinion. <lb/>
            <q rend="diple">I have tried </q>, (he informs me in a letter dated Auguſt
            <lb/>13, 1794), <q rend="diple quotes"> hydrogen air in five pulmonary caſes,
              in <lb/>two of which it had a very ſudden and a very fa- <lb/>vourable influence. In
              one of the others the <lb/>meaſles ſupervened upon phthiſis, and ſeemed to
              <lb/>decreaſe the firſt diſeaſe.—My patients ſometimes <lb/>reſpired hydrogen air for
              a minute and half at a <lb/>time; the more frequently they repeated the expe-
              <lb/>riment, the more eaſy did it become; but after 15 or <lb/>20 inſpirations I
              always obſerved the face to grow <lb/>dark and livid. I am aſtoniſhed at the length of
              <lb/>time which man can breathe, and animals live in, <lb/>hydrogen air. </q>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Dr. Gilby of Birmingham noted the following ap- <lb/>pearances, and immediately
            afterwards drew out this <lb/>minute. </p>
          <floatingText>
            <body>
              <div>
                <head rend="italic align-center">
                  <lb/>
                  <q rend="quotes">Hydrogene Air. </q>
                </head>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>
                  <q rend="diple">A mouſe immerſed in hydrogene air—from wa- <lb/>ter and heated
                    malleable iron—continued 30 ſeconds <lb/>without ſhewing any mark of diſtreſs;
                    reſpiration <lb/>then became laborious; one minute 33 ſeconds <lb/>from the time
                    of immerſion it inſpired; but it <lb/>moved no more, and when taken out, proved
                    to be <lb/>quite dead. </q>
                </p>
              </div>
              <pb n="31"/>
              <div>
                <head rend="align-center italic">
                  <lb/>
                  <q rend="quotes">Fixed, or Carbonic acid Air. </q>
                </head>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>
                  <q rend="diple quotes">Another mouſe, immerſed in this air, was inſtantly
                    <lb/>affected; and in 15 ſeconds was completely dead. </q>
                  <lb/>A young wood pigeon, in hydrogene air, ceaſed to <lb/>gape and move in 2
                  minutes 35 ſeconds. For 10 or <lb/>15 ſeconds it did not appear incommoded. Its
                  fellow, <lb/>in carbonic acid air, ceaſed to gape and move in 43 <lb/>ſeconds. It
                  ſhewed diſtreſs inſtantly on immerſion. </p>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Very young animals do not drown ſo ſoon as old.— <lb/>Imagining, therefore, that
            young animals would afford <lb/>a more ſenſible ſcale on which to meaſure the power
            <lb/>of different mephitic airs to extinguiſh life, I made the <lb/>following
            experiment. A puppy, four days old, was <lb/>put into a veſſel of hydrogene air from
            heated iron <lb/>and water. It ceaſed to breathe and move twenty-two <lb/>minutes
            afterwards.—Another puppy, of the ſame lit- <lb/>ter, was put into carbonic acid gas: it
            ceaſed to breathe <lb/>and move in one minute and an half.—Comparative <lb/>experiments
            of this kind require repetition; two ap- <lb/>parently ſimilar animals may be tenacious
            of life in <lb/>different degrees, from cauſes not yet diſcovered; <lb/>moreover, if
            immediately before immerſion, one ſhould <lb/>have inſpired, and the other expired, this
            might oc- <lb/>caſion a wrong inference: nor ſhould dependence be <lb/>placed on a
            ſlight difference. By keeping animals, <lb/>ſeemingly equal, in different unreſpirable
            airs, till all <lb/>appearances of life in one or the other had ceaſed; <lb/>then taking
            the ſurvivor out, ſuffering it to recover, <lb/>and after ſome days drowning it again in
            that air in <lb/>which its fellow had periſhed before, I hoped to de- <lb/>termine this
            queſtion certainly for the ſubjects of expe- <lb/>riment, and by analogy for all animals
            of the ſame claſs. </p>
          <pb n="32"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Accordingly, three rabbits of the ſame litter, ſeven <lb/>weeks old, nearly half
            grown, and weighing one pound <lb/>and an half each, were ſucceſſively immerſed in three
            <lb/>different kinds of air. Dr. Gilby being preſent at this <lb/>experiment alſo, noted
            the appearances at the moment <lb/>they occurred. </p>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>A short horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
          <table rows="8" cols="4">
            <head rend="align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Experiment I.—Rabbit X. </hi>
              <lb/>
              <q rend="diple italic">In hydrogene from water and heated malleable iron. </q>
            </head>
            <row role="label">
              <cell/>
              <cell>Minutes, </cell>
              <cell>Seconds, </cell>
              <cell>after immerſion. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>
                <q rend="diple">In </q>
              </cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">1</cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">20</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Moved about, in appear- <lb/>ance little diſtreſſed. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell/>
              <cell rend="align-center">1</cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">50</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Began to breathe ſhort. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell/>
              <cell rend="align-center">2</cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">0</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Viſibly diſtreſſed. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell/>
              <cell rend="align-center">4</cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">15</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Much agitated. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell/>
              <cell rend="align-center">7</cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">0</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Taken out, breathing very <lb/>ſhort and thick. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>
                <q rend="diple">In leſs than </q>
              </cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">17</cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">0</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Completely recovered. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>
                <q rend="diple">In </q>
              </cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">40</cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">0</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">(that is, as ſoon as food <lb/>was offered) began to <lb/>eat.
              </cell>
            </row>
          </table>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>A short horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
          <table rows="6" cols="4">
            <head rend="align-center">
              <lb/>
              <q rend="diple sc">Experiment II.—Rabbit P. </q>
              <lb/>
              <q rend="paradiple italic">In hydrocarbonate air from hot charcoal and water,
                <lb/>twice paſſed through water. </q>
            </head>
            <row role="label">
              <cell/>
              <cell>Minutes. </cell>
              <cell>Seconds. </cell>
              <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>
                <q rend="diple">In </q>
              </cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">0</cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">25</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Breathed ſhort, diſteſſed. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell/>
              <cell rend="align-center">0</cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">35</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Violently agitated, conti- <lb/>nued ſo 15 ſeconds; in-
                <lb/>ſpired at long intervals <lb/>for ſome ſeconds: ſcarce <lb/>alive. </cell>
            </row>
            <pb n="33"/>
            <row role="label">
              <cell/>
              <cell>Minutes. </cell>
              <cell>Seconds. </cell>
              <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>
                <q rend="diple">After </q></cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">1</cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">30</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">No inſpiration or move- <lb/>ment ſeen. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>
                <q rend="diple">In </q></cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">4</cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">0</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Taken out for dead—did <lb/>not recover. </cell>
            </row>
          </table>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>A short horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
          <table rows="7" cols="4">
            <head rend="align-center">
              <lb/>
              <q rend="diple sc">Experiment III.—Rabbit Q. </q>
              <lb/>
              <q rend="quotes"><hi rend="italic">In carbonic acid air, from heated chalk.</hi>
              </q>
            </head>
            <row role="label">
              <cell/>
              <cell>Minutes, </cell>
              <cell>Seconds, </cell>
              <cell>after immerſion. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>
                <q rend="diple"> </q></cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">0</cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">20</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Strongly convulſed. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell/>
              <cell rend="align-center">0</cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">35</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Gaſped at intervals. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell/>
              <cell rend="align-center">0</cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">49</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Has continued gaſping. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell/>
              <cell rend="align-center">1</cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">0</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Nearly dead. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell/>
              <cell rend="align-center">1</cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">15</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Quite dead. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell/>
              <cell rend="align-center">2</cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">0</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Taken out, perfectly ina- <lb/>nimate, did not recover. </cell>
            </row>
          </table>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>A short horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
          <floatingText>
            <body>
              <head rend="sc align-center space">
                <lb/>Experiment IV.—Rabbit R. </head>
              <p rend="indent space">
                <lb/>At the time of making theſe experiments I had not <lb/>pure azotic air at
                command, and had neglected to uſe <lb/>it when I had; the following obſervation
                makes it <lb/>highly probable, that this air is not more ſuddenly <lb/>deleterious
                than hydrogene. A candle having burned <lb/>out in a veſſel full of atmoſpheric air
                in contact with <lb/>lime water, a very ſmall kitten (about 14 days old) <lb/>was
                put into the ſame portion of air; after the death <lb/>of this kitten, which did not
                happen in leſs than 3 <pb n="34"/>
                <lb/>hours, the fellow of the three preceding rabbits was <lb/>introduced; the
                following were the appearances: </p>
              <table rend="space" rows="7" cols="2">
                <row role="label">
                  <cell>Minutes. </cell>
                  <cell/>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell rend="align-center">1</cell>
                  <cell>Breath ſhort—turns round. </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell rend="align-center">3</cell>
                  <cell>In no great diſtreſs, breath ſhort. </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell rend="align-center">5</cell>
                  <cell>The ſame. </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell rend="align-center">7</cell>
                  <cell>Breath ſhorter. </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell rend="align-center">10</cell>
                  <cell>Reſpiration apparently more laborious. </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell rend="align-center">12</cell>
                  <cell>Taken out—very ſoon recovered—a can- <lb/>dle plunged into the veſſel was
                    immediately extin- <lb/>guiſhed. </cell>
                </row>
              </table>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>A short horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
          <table rows="9" cols="3" rend="indentall">
            <head rend="align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Experiment V.—Rabbit X </hi><hi rend="italic">again, <lb/>at the
                interval of ſeveral days in hydrogene air. </hi>
            </head>
            <row role="label" rend="italic">
              <cell>Min. </cell>
              <cell>Sec. </cell>
              <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="align-right">—</cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">—</cell>
              <cell>At firſt very tranquil. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="align-right">2</cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">0</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Snuffs for air round the ſide <lb/>of the veſſel. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="align-right">4</cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">0</cell>
              <cell>Reclined almoſt on its ſide. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="align-right">5</cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">30</cell>
              <cell>Breathes thick—very weak. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="align-right">6</cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">10</cell>
              <cell>Taken out, breathing thick. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="align-right">7</cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">10</cell>
              <cell>Could ſit. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="align-right">8</cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">0</cell>
              <cell>Could move, tho' ſtill weak. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="align-right">9</cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">30</cell>
              <cell>As uſual. </cell>
            </row>
          </table>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>A short horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
          <table rows="6" cols="3" rend="indentall">
            <head rend="align-center">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Experiment VI.—Rabbit X </hi><hi rend="italic">a third time.
                <lb/>At the interval of two days—recent hydrocarbonate, pre- <lb/>pared without
                ſuperfluous ſteam. </hi>
            </head>
            <row>
              <cell rend="align-right">—</cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">—</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Diſtreſſed the moment of <lb/>immerſion. </cell>
            </row>
            <pb n="35"/>
            <row role="label" rend="italic">
              <cell>Min. </cell>
              <cell>Sec. </cell>
              <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="align-right">0</cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">20</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Scratched the veſſel furi- <lb/>ouſly. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="align-right">0</cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">25</cell>
              <cell>Fell on its ſide. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="align-right">0</cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">35</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Motionleſs and inſenſible— <lb/>taken out. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="align-right">—</cell>
              <cell rend="align-right">—</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Lay as dead ſome time; <lb/>finally recovered. </cell>
            </row>
          </table>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Another rabbit of the ſame brood, (before immerſion <lb/>in water, viſibly much
            affected with fear) ſtruggled <lb/>with ſtrength for a minute and an half. At the end
            <lb/>of two minutes, forty ſeconds, it moved; in three mi- <lb/>nutes was taken out, but
            did not recover. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Should theſe experiments be repeated by a perſon, <lb/>careful to procure his
            elaſtic fluids free from offenſive <lb/>acid fumes, the diſtinctneſs of the phænomena I
            ob- <lb/>ſerved, perſuades me that their general reſult will be <lb/>confirmed. Of ſome
            readers, whom the importance <lb/>of the ſubject may lead to take up this pamphlet, the
            <lb/>curioſity will, I fear, be repreſſed be ſenſations, ari- <lb/>ſing from the idea of
            pain endured by the animals. In <lb/>a few caſes, the torture which was inflicted was
            ex- <lb/>ceedingly repugnant to my own feelings; and for this <lb/>reaſon, I have left
            one ſeries of experiments (<hi rend="sc">Sect.</hi> vii.) <lb/>more incompleat than I
            could eaſily have rendered it. <lb/>Againſt drowning, an imputation of cruelty will
            hardly <lb/>lie: Animals, deſtined to this death, may juſt as well <lb/>drown for the
            inſtruction of the phyſician. Beſides, <lb/>did not accuſtomed acts of outrage and
            injuſtice daily <lb/>paſs uncenſured, I know not how he who feeds upon <lb/>the fleſh of
            a ſlaughtered animal can conſiſtently con- <pb n="36"/>
            <lb/>demn inveſtigations, ſeriouſly tending to reſtore or pre- <lb/>ſerve health, though
            conducted at the expence of the <lb/>life and eaſe <choice>
              <corr>of</corr>
              <sic>oſ</sic>
            </choice> animals, unable to reſiſt the power of <lb/>man. I wiſh, with all my heart, I
            could prove that <lb/>moroſe writer in the wrong, who has called the Earth <lb/><hi
              rend="sc">a vast field of battle</hi>, where creature, for <lb/>preſervation, preys
            upon creature, or tortures its fellow <lb/>in purſuit of pleaſure. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Two kittens immerſed, one in carbonic acid, the <lb/>other in hydrogene air,
            afforded a ſimilar reſult; that <lb/>is, the carbonic acid appeared full three times as
            dele- <lb/>terious as hydrogene. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Finally, to render the difference again more diſtinct, <lb/>two equal quantities of
            atmoſpheric, were ſucceſſively <lb/>mixed with an equal bulk of carbonic acid, and of
            hy- <lb/>drogene, air. A rabbit (S) being put into the mixture <lb/>of atmoſpheric and
            carbonic acid air; the following <lb/>obſervations were made. </p>
          <table rend="space" rows="7" cols="3">
            <row role="label">
              <cell/>
              <cell>Minutes. </cell>
              <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell rend="align-center">In </cell>
              <cell rend="align-center">2</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Appeared weak. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell/>
              <cell rend="align-center">4</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Has been couchant for 2 minutes. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell/>
              <cell rend="align-center">6</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Very ſtill. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell/>
              <cell rend="align-center">11</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Reſpiration more laborious. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell/>
              <cell rend="align-center">26</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Extremely weak; ſeems ready to fall <lb/>on one ſide; ſcarce
                alive. </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell/>
              <cell rend="align-center">43</cell>
              <cell rend="hanging">Quite dead.—After the 2d minute it ne- <lb/>ver roſe—death very
                lingering. </cell>
            </row>
          </table>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>A fellow rabbit, T, in atmoſpheric and hydrogene <lb/>air, ſeemed much leſs
            diſtreſſed at firſt; rubbed its <lb/>fore-feet after it had continued in the veſſel 40
            mi- <pb n="37"/>
            <lb/>nutes, and performed ſeveral other actions; much of <lb/>the time it ſat, that is,
            it continued erect before. <lb/>Even at the laſt, no diſtreſs, except quick reſpiration,
            <lb/>was obſervable. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>In 48 minutes it was taken out; it now ſtood firm; <lb/>and though unwilling to
            move; was capable, when <lb/>urged forward, of advancing, without ſtaggering, or
            <lb/>any ſign of great debility. In appearance it had ſuf- <lb/>fered leſs in 48 than
            its fellow in 15 minutes. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter">
          <head rend="italic indent space">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">XI.</hi>—How hydrocarbonate air affects venous blood. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Two fowls were ſtrangled and a rabbit was drowned <lb/>while their fellows were
            immerſed in hydrocarbonate <lb/>air. In all theſe laſt the veins appeared of a brightiſh
            <lb/>red colour<unclear>!</unclear> the liver and heart (which was perfectly
              <lb/><unclear>irritable</unclear>) were alſo of a bright colour. In the others
            <lb/>the liver was dark as uſual; and the heart pale. In the <lb/>hydrocarbonated rabbit
            the fleſh was univerſally of a <lb/>light lively red. The blood from the <hi
              rend="italic">vena cava</hi> had <lb/>the ſame brightneſs; it coagulated about as ſoon
            as the <lb/>livid blood of the ſtrangled fowls and drowned rabbit. <lb/>The boiled fleſh
            of all the fowls had much the ſame <lb/>taſte and toughneſs. The muſcles of the lower
            extre- <lb/>mities of the hydrocarbonated fowls were of a lively <lb/>red. The boiled
            fleſh of the h. rabbit had a pink hue.— <lb/>Of two equal fowls one was put into
            hydrocarbonate <lb/>and one into carbonic acid air; the former was ruddy
            <lb/>throughout, as was well ſeen in the heart cut acroſs. <lb/>In the fowl put into c.
            acid air nothing of this bright <lb/>red colour appeared. The liver I though paler than
            in <lb/>ſtrangled fowls: but I had not one at hand for imme- <lb/>diate compariſon. Of
            this laſt h. fowl the wings and <lb/>breaſt were brown, and the thighs reddiſh. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="38"/>
        <div type="chapter">
          <head rend="italic space align-center">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">XII.</hi>—Reflections on the preceding facts. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The attentive reader muſt have ſeen, even in the reſult <lb/>of theſe ſimple
            extemporaneous experiments, indubita- <lb/>ble proofs of the power of factitious airs
            variouſly to af- <lb/>fect the living frame. It appears that oxygene air, when
            <lb/>inſpired pure, or nearly ſo, increaſes the motions ſo as <lb/>to produce dangerous
            or mortal inflammation; that <lb/>by reddening the blood, it brightens the colour of the
            <lb/>ſolid parts; even that of the liver, which anatomy <lb/>ſhews to be the leaſt
            likely of all the ſolids to be affec- <lb/>ted by any change of the arterial blood: that
            it renders <lb/>animals leſs capable of being drowned or deſtroyed by <lb/>cold; that it
            is expended in muſcular motion, ſince <lb/>animals that have exerted themſelves
            violently, imme- <lb/>diately before confinement in a given quantity of at-
            <lb/>moſpheric air, or during confinement, ſooneſt exhaust <lb/>it of oxygene; and that,
            when it is blown into dogs, in <lb/>the manner veal is blown up by butchers, it produces
            a <lb/>remarkable degree of vivacity. Theſe facts, compa- <lb/>red with ſome of the
            obſervations, which will be given <lb/>in the next paragraph, will prove of uſe in
            directing <lb/>us how to apply this air properly as a remedy; eſpe- <lb/>cially as they
            will appear to have been confirmed ſince <lb/>their firſt publication by obſervations on
            the ſick. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Between unreſpirable airs, there ſeems a remarkable <lb/>difference in their power
            to produce inſenſibility and <lb/>death. Hydrogene appears the leaſt noxious, both
            <lb/>when inſpired alone, or mixed with atmoſpheric air. <lb/>Azote probably differs
            little from hydrogene. Hydro- <lb/>carbonate ſeems extremely deleterious; Mr. Watt
            <lb/>gives evidence of this in the human ſpecies. I <lb/>can add a ſimilar obſervation.
            A perſon in con- <pb n="39"/>
            <lb/>firmed conſumption breathed a quantity of hydrocar- <lb/>bonate, mixed with 4 times
            its bulk of atmoſpheric air: <lb/>he became very ſick, or rather vertiginous; the pulſe
            <lb/>was much quickened, and the extremities became very <lb/>cold. The patient finding
            an abatement of pain in his <lb/>ſide, and of dyſpnoea, returned for another doſe. The
            <lb/>operator, a chemiſt of great ſkill, thinking the former <lb/>doſe too ſtrong, mixed
            50 c. inches of hydrocarbonate <lb/>with 600 of atmoſpheric air. This was reſpired with-
            <lb/>out any ſenſible effect. In a quarter of an hour, 100 <lb/>c. i. of hydrocarbonate
            were mixed with 600 of atmo- <lb/>ſpheric air. The patient breathed at twice about two-
            <lb/>thirds of this mixture, when he was deſired to deſiſt. <lb/>Soon afterwards he
            became vertiginous and nearly <lb/>inſenſible, his pulſe at one period being nearly
            imper- <lb/>ceptible; the ſphincter of the bladder was relaxed; <lb/>after his recovery,
            he was again very cold— <q rend="quotes">intenſely <lb/>cold to his own feelings </q>
            was his expreſſion—as well <lb/>as to the touch. After getting into his carriage, he
            <lb/>fainted; and his pulſe for ſeveral hours continued <lb/>quicker and weaker than
            before. The operator hav- <lb/>ing obſerved, that when much water is added to red-
            <lb/>hot charcoal, carbonic acid air is copiouſly produced, <lb/>in the preparation of
            this laſt portion of air, had added <lb/>ſo little water, that no ſuperfluous ſteam at
            all came <lb/>over; hence it was as pure as can be made: being <lb/>alſo newly prepared,
            it retained all the charcoal it had <lb/>carried up; of which it is well known to
            depoſit part <lb/>on ſtanding. This might lead to conjecture, that the <lb/>greater
            deleterious power of heavy inflammable air <lb/>from water and hot charcoal
            (hydrocarbonate) com- <lb/>pared with that of light inflammable air, depends on <pb
              n="40"/>
            <lb/>the facility of its combination, or at leaſt of the char- <lb/>coal it contains
            with the oxygene of the blood; in con- <lb/>ſequence of which, it ſpeedily diſarms the
            ſyſtem of its <lb/>moving principle. This opinion ſeems countenanced <lb/>by the effect
            of nitrous air, which more quickly de- <lb/>ſtroys life than any of thoſe
            above-mentioned, and <lb/>which is well-known very readily to combine with <lb/>oxygene.
            Death, in this caſe, might be more inſtanta- <lb/>neous, from the inſtantaneous
            production of an highly <lb/>corroſive acid (nitrous acid) and its application to the
            <lb/>whole ſurface of the lungs. But for the rapid effect <lb/>of carbonic acid air, and
            the appearances in XI I can <lb/>aſſign no plauſible reaſon, nor does the above hypo-
            <lb/>theſis ſuit the facts in XI, which with thoſe in X refute <lb/>thoſe eminent
            philoſophers, who have of late ſuppoſed <lb/>that water and ſeveral bland unreſpirable
            airs occaſion <lb/>death, ſimply by excluſion of the oxygene of the atmo- <lb/>ſphere.
            Their action is certainly unequal; and I preſume, <lb/>recovery from aſphyxia in water
            (when but little goes <lb/>down the wind-pipe), hydrogene air, azote, or from
            <lb/>ſtrangulation (where no material organic injury is pro- <lb/>duced), will be much
            more eaſy than from aſphyxia, <lb/>occaſioned by other unreſpirable mediums. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Experiments to diſcover the effects of the long con- <lb/>tinued action of
            aeri-form ſubſtances, would be much <lb/>more curious than ſuch as I have made. They
            would <lb/>thus, in all probability, more deeply and permanently <lb/>affect the living
            ſyſtem. If, for inſtance, an animal <lb/>were kept in an atmoſphere containing <formula
              notation="fraction">20/100</formula>
            <formula notation="fraction">24/100</formula> of oxy- <lb/>gene or ſtill leſs, it would
            perhaps be affected by the <lb/>ſea-ſcurvy. The muſcular fibres, at leaſt, and the
            ſolids <lb/>in general would in all probability be found weak, <pb n="41"/>
            <lb/>tender, or eaſy to be torn. Again, if three equal grow- <lb/>ing animals were kept,
            one in the atmoſphere, the <lb/>other in air of an higher, the third of a lower,
            ſtandard, <lb/>and in all other reſpects treated alike; ſome conſider- <lb/>able
            difference would perhaps be obſerved in their <lb/>growth and vigour.—By frequent
            immerſion in water, <lb/>the aſſociation between the movements of the heart <lb/>and
            lungs might perhaps be diſſolved; and an <lb/>animal be inured to live commodiouſly for
            any time <lb/>under water. If ſome plan, ſimilar to that which I have <lb/>ventured to
            propoſe, ſhould be executed, ſuch pro- <lb/>ceſſes of inveſtigation ought to be carried
            on in the <lb/>Inſtitution. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter">
          <head rend="italic space align-center">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">XIII.</hi>—Some effects of the inſpiration of hydrogene, to elu-
            <lb/>cidate the reſult of the foregoing experiments. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>
            <q rend="diple quotes">When an animal is immerſed in water, <hi rend="italic">his pulſe
                be- <lb/>comes weak and fequent</hi>, he feels an anxiety about his <lb/>breaſt, and
              ſtruggles to relieve it: in theſe ſtruggles, <lb/>he riſes towards the ſurface of the
              water, and throws <lb/>out a quantity of air from his lungs. After this, <lb/><hi
                rend="italic">his anxiety increaſes, his pulſe becomes weaker</hi>; the
              <lb/>ſtruggles are renewed with more violence; he riſes <lb/>towards the ſurface
              again; throws out more air from <lb/>his lungs, and makes ſeveral efforts to inſpire;
              and <lb/>in ſome of theſe efforts, a quantity of water com- <lb/>monly paſſes into his
              mouth; <hi rend="italic">his ſkin then becomes <lb/>blue, particularly about the face
                and lips; his pulſe <lb/>gradually ceaſes; the ſphincters are relaxed</hi>; he falls
              <lb/>down without ſenſation, and without motion. </q>
            <hi rend="italic">(Dr. <lb/>Goodwyn, l. c. pp 33, 4.)</hi> This deſcription of drowning
            <lb/>in water applies, as far as the circumſtances admit of <lb/>compariſon, to the
            effects occaſioned by the reſpiration <lb/>of pure hydrogene. I have remarked them in a
            num- <pb n="42"/>
            <lb/>ber of healthy perſons, who were curious to try how <lb/>long they could breathe
            this air. The frequency and <lb/>debility of pulſe, blueneſs of the lips and coloured
            parts <lb/>of the ſkin, were always obſervable in a minute, or a <lb/>minute and an
            half. Beſides, dizzineſs was felt, and <lb/>the eyes have grown dim; in animals, the
            tranſparent <lb/>cornea has appeared ſunk and ſhrivelled. Several in- <lb/>dividuals
            agree in deſcribing the incipient inſenſibility <lb/>as highly agreeable. One
            conſumptive perſon loved <lb/>to indulge in it; for this purpoſe, contrary to my judg-
            <lb/>ment, he uſed to inſpire a cubic foot of hydrogene at <lb/>a time. This quantity
            moſt commonly produced little <lb/>change in his feelings. Sometimes it brought on al-
            <lb/>moſt compleat aſphyxia. During this proceſs, I have <lb/>felt the pulſe nearly
            obliterated. Afterwards, as he <lb/>recovered, it was ſenſibly fuller, and ſtronger than
            be- <lb/>fore the inſpiration. This fact belongs to a general <lb/>principle now
            beginning to be underſtood; when the <lb/>ordinary powers have been, for a certain time,
            with- <lb/>held from the body, they act with greater effect, as <lb/>holding the fingers
            to the fire after handling ſnow, <lb/>occaſions ſevere aching. For this reaſon, whenever
            <lb/>air with leſs oxygene is to be inſpired, it would ſeem <lb/>more advantageous to
            employ for a long time an at- <lb/>moſphere little reduced, than one ſo low that it can
            <lb/>only be breathed for a ſhort time. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>An obſervation the patient juſt mentioned made <lb/>upon himſelf, ſeems to ſhew the
            neceſſity of oxygene <lb/>to muſcular action. Judging from his feelings, that <lb/>he
            was perfectly recruited after his doſe of pure hy- <lb/>drogene, he has riſen from his
            ſopha with an intention <lb/>to walk about his apartment, but has been ſurpriſed on
            <lb/>riſing, to find himſelf incapable of advancing three <pb n="43"/>
            <lb/>ſteps, till he had reſted ſome time longer. In this caſe, <lb/>was not the ſtore of
            looſely combined oxygene, laid in <lb/>before, expended during the inſpiration of the
            hydro- <lb/>gene, by thoſe motions which are perpetually going <lb/>on in the ſyſtem?
            Did it not require ſome time to re- <lb/>place the neceſſary portion in the muſcles
            remote <lb/>from the heart and lungs? </p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter">
          <head rend="italic space align-center">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">XIV.</hi>—Some particulars relative to oxygene, ſupplemen-
            <lb/>tal to the preceding experiments. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The celebrated Dr. Ingenhouſz in a letter dated <lb/>Auguſt 4th, 1791, mentions to
            me a very curious ex- <lb/>periment, <q rend="quotes">which, </q> says he, <q
              rend="diple quotes">if it be a real fact, <lb/>throws a great deal of light upon your
              ſyſtem; it is <lb/>this:—Bliſter your finger, ſo as to lay bare the na- <lb/>ked and
              ſenſible ſkin. The contact of air will pro- <lb/>duce pain: put your finger into vital
              air, and this <lb/>will give more pain; introduce it into fixed or azo- <lb/>tic air,
              and the pain will diminiſh or ceaſe. </q> Dr. <lb/>Webſter, he adds, was informed of
            theſe circumſtan- <lb/>ces, by a Frenchman, whoſe name does not appear; <lb/>I had often
            heard them indiſtinctly related; and it is <lb/>rather ſurpriſing that the fact has not
            been aſcertained. <lb/>Much of the art of modern ſurgery conſiſts in keeping <lb/>the
            air from wounds and ſome kinds of ulcers: and <lb/>this fact, if the account be true,
            pretty deciſively ſhews <lb/>which ingredient of the atmoſphere is injurious. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>I applied a bliſter an inch long, and half an inch <lb/>broad, to the back of the
            third finger of the left hand. <lb/>When the pain from the action of the cantharides had
            <lb/>entirely ceaſed, I cut away the ſcarf-ſkin of the veſica- <lb/>tion; and was
            ſenſible, the moment the air was admit- <lb/>ted, of a ſharp ſmarting pain. This did not
            continue <pb n="44"/>
            <lb/>ſo ſevere; but the expoſed true ſkin ſenſibly ſmarted. <lb/>Upon tying the neck of
            a bladder, containing carbonic <lb/>acid air from heated chalk, round the root of the
            fin- <lb/>ger, the pain very ſoon ſubſided. While I kept my <lb/>finger in carbonic acid
            air, which was near half an <lb/>hour, I ſhould not have known it had received any
            <lb/>injury. On taking it out, the ſurface had a whitiſh <lb/>appearance—Was this from
            the beginning of the for- <lb/>mation of epidermis?—In the air—the experiment <lb/>was
            made in a warm temperature—the ſmarting re- <lb/>turned; in an hour the expoſed ſkin was
            painful and <lb/>looked angry, as the expreſſion is: I again encloſed it <lb/>in
            carbonic acid air; in ſix minutes I felt no more pain. <lb/>After ſeveral hours I again
            removed the bladder, and <lb/>ſoon felt the ſmarting return. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>During the hour after my finger had been for the <lb/>firſt time taken out of the
            bladder, I had introduced it <lb/>into a phial of oxygene air, for a few minutes, but
            was <lb/>not ſenſible of increaſe of pain; nor can I ſay that the <lb/>redneſs and angry
            appearance was owing to this cir- <lb/>cumſtance. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The following experiments were made on three <lb/>different perſons:— <list>
              <item>1. The raiſed epidermis of a <lb/>bliſtered finger, after all action of the
                cantharides had <lb/>ceaſed, was cut away in carbonic acid air. No pain <lb/>was
                felt. The atmoſpheric air ſlowly mixed with the <lb/>other in the glaſs cylinder, as
                I found by the dull <lb/>manner in which a candle after ſome minutes burned <lb/>in
                it; and now ſome ſlight pain was felt. The finger <lb/>being put into oxygen air, a
                ſmarting came on, and <lb/>laſted 20 minutes; but then became leſs. The finger
                <lb/>was next put into air containing alkaline fumes; and <lb/>the pain was much
                ſeverer than ever.— </item>
              <item>2. A ſecond <pb n="45"/>
                <lb/>bliſter being opened in the air, ſmarting pain came on. <lb/>In a bladder of
                fixed air it ſoon went off.— </item>
              <item>3. The epi- <lb/>dermis was cut off from a bliſter on my own finger, which
                <lb/>I inſtantly plunged into oxygene air; it felt as when <lb/>ſalt is ſprinkled on
                a cut: and the pain was, I am pretty <lb/>ſure, more ſevere than when my former
                bliſter was <lb/>opened in the atmoſhere. In carbonic acid air the <lb/>pain in two
                minutes quite ſubſided, and returned when <lb/>I expoſed the bare ſkin to the
                atmoſphere. </item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>At Oxford, in 1790, I had propoſed to a diſtreſſed <lb/>negro, to try to whiten
            part of his ſkin with oxygena- <lb/>ted marine acid air. He was to exhibit the
            appearance, <lb/>if it ſhould be curious, for the relief of his family. <lb/>His arm was
            introduced into a large jar full of this air, <lb/>and the back of his fingers lay in
            ſome water impreg- <lb/>nated with it at the bottom of the veſſel. It was per-
            <lb/>ceived that he had ulcerations from the itch between <lb/>his fingers; and this
            made me very cautious about the <lb/>experiments. In 12 minutes he complained of ſevere
            <lb/>pain from the ulcers, and the arm was withdrawn. The <lb/>back of his fingers had
            acquired an appearance as if <lb/>white lead paint had been laid upon them, but this did
            <lb/>not prove permanent. A lock of his hair was whi- <lb/>tened by this acid.—Next day
            the ulcers became ex- <lb/>tremely painful, and the hand ſwelled from the inflam-
            <lb/>mation; this deterred him from a continunance of the <lb/>experiment after he was
            cured of his complaint. You <lb/>cannot ſafely impute the effect of this powerfully ſti-
            <lb/>mulating acid to its oxygene alone. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>But the fact ſtated by Dr. Ingenhouſz is very agree- <lb/>able to the common
            phænomena preſented by wounds. <lb/>Moreover, I have lately ſeen cancerous patients
            treated <lb/>by the application of unreſpirable air, with the moſt <pb n="46"/>
            <lb/>aſtoniſhing ſucceſs. In mentioning to Dr. Black the <lb/>introduction of factitious
            airs into the <hi rend="sc">Bath</hi> hoſpital, <lb/>as a ſource of hope, I did not ſo
            ſoon expect an event <lb/>which ages and nations have deſired in vain. Obſer-
            <lb/>vations, extremely analogous to the experiments juſt <lb/>related, were there made
            during the courſe of the treat- <lb/>ment. See Dr. Ewart's pamphlet. Should it be
            <lb/>invidiouſly obſerved by any reader of his narrative, <lb/>that ſomething ſimilar
            had been tried before, it may be <lb/>truly replied, that theſe trials were rather
            diſcourage- <lb/>ments to the new application of elaſtic fluids; and that <lb/>failure
            in former inſtances enhances the merit of the <lb/>recent method. Mr. Magellan's caſe
            ſeems never to <lb/>have been much known in England. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>It ſeems not improbable, that on certain ill-condi- <lb/>tioned ulcers, oxygene
            externally applied has a ſaluta- <lb/>ry effect, by occaſioning greater action, both of
            the <lb/>veſſels which throw out the copious thin diſcharge, <lb/>and of the abſorbents.
            Many ſubſtances, uſually ap- <lb/>plied to ſuch ulcers with ſucceſs, as metallic ſalts,
            <lb/>contain much oxygene, and ſome are moſt highly <lb/>charged with this principle, as
            the red oxyds of metals. <lb/>The following intelligence, if authentic, adds confir-
            <lb/>mation to this opinion, and may prove uſeful. A few <lb/>months ago, I was ſtruck
            with the frequency of ſcro- <lb/>phulous tumours among the poor of the county of
            <lb/>Longford, in Ireland. Suppoſing that neceſſity might <lb/>have occaſioned the trial
            of many methods of cure, I <lb/>enquired whether the people there had not ſome pe-
            <lb/>culiar domeſtic practices in ſuch complaints. A phy- <lb/>ſician referred me to a
            ſimple but very reputable old <lb/>farmer, as remarkably ſucceſsful in ſcrophulous
            ſores. <lb/>With this perſon I had an interview. In his practice, <lb/>he had no view to
            gain; and that, in his principles, he <lb/>had nothing of empirical impoſture, he
            convinced me, <pb n="47"/>
            <lb/>by at once diſcloſing his whole ſecret. He had him- <lb/>ſelf, many years ago, an
            ulceration of the ſubmaxillary <lb/>glands: This, after various unſucceſsful
            applications, <lb/>was healed by a ruſtic practitioner like himſelf. He <lb/>obtained a
            knowledge of the remedy, by which, dur- <lb/>ing a long life, he aſſured me, he had
            himſelf healed <lb/>many ſuch ulcers of the glands about the jaws. He <lb/>was ſo little
            ſpeculative, as never to have attempted <lb/>the cure of an obſtinate ſore in any other
            ſeat. That <lb/>he might effectually inſtruct me, he brought ſpecimens <lb/>of his
            ſimples. They were the leaves and ſtalks of <lb/>wood-ſorrel <hi rend="italic">(oxalis
              acetoſella)</hi>, and the root of mea- <lb/>dow-ſweet <hi rend="italic">(ſpiraea
              ulmaria)</hi>. The ſorrel he prepares <lb/>by wrapping it in a cabbage leaf, and
            macerating it by <lb/>its own juices in warm peat aſhes. This pulp is ap- <lb/>plied as
            a poultice to the ulcer, and left 24 hours: <lb/>the application of ſorrel is four times
            repeated; then <lb/>the roots of the meadow ſweet, bruiſed and mixed <lb/>with the ſour
            head or effloreſcence that appears on <lb/>butter-milk, left in the churn, are uſed in
            the ſame <lb/>manner till the ſore heals, which I was told always <lb/>ſpeedily happens;
            often in two or three weeks. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The following extract of a letter from Mr. Edge- <lb/>worth of Edgeworthſtown,
            contains ſome ſupplemen- <lb/>tary information, and will probably add ſo much to the
            <lb/>credit of my information, as to obtain a trial for the <lb/>remedy. </p>
          <floatingText>
            <body>
              <p rend="indent space">
                <lb/>
                <q rend="quotes">I have learned from Mr. Mills, that when he was <lb/>about eight
                  and twenty, he had two large ſcrophulous <lb/>ſwellings in his neck, one under
                  each ear, near the <lb/>jaw; the marks they had left he ſhewed me. He was
                  <lb/>attended by a ſurgeon in the neighbourhood for ſome <lb/>weeks, without
                  receiving any benefit. A farmer, with <pb n="48"/>
                  <lb/>whom he was acquainted, recommended the applica- <lb/>tion he mentioned to
                  you, by which he was com- <lb/>pletely cured. The man told him the names and
                  <lb/>quantities of the ſeveral ingredients, when he applied <lb/>them, but did not
                  till ſome years afterwards (when he <lb/>was leaving this country for America)
                  apprize him that <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">myſtery of the cure</hi> (this was his
                  expreſſion) de- <lb/>pends entirely upon the ſorrel. This perſon had pre-
                  <lb/>dicted to Mills, that one of the ſores, which had been <lb/>lanced, would not
                  heal ſo ſoon as that which had ſup- <lb/>purated of itſelf; and he found this to
                  be true. Whilſt <lb/>he had ſcrophulous ſwellings, he was weak and un-
                  <lb/>healthy; from the time the wounds were healed, he <lb/>has been ſtrong and
                  active; he is now eighty; and <lb/>whilſt he was relating theſe circumſtances to
                  me this <lb/>evening, he kept pace with my horſe up hill for half <lb/>a mile,
                  without any apparent effort. I mention this, <lb/>becauſe it is a common opinion
                  (I ſuppoſe a vulgar <lb/>error) that healing ſuch ſores is prejudicial to the ge-
                  <lb/>neral health. He has applied this remedy to upwards <lb/>of an hundred
                  different perſons, every one of whom <lb/>have been cured.—Seven years ago I
                  remember <lb/>having ſeen his ſon, who rents a conſiderable farm from <lb/>me,
                  with an enormous ſcrophulous ſwelling on his <lb/>neck; he was too impatient to
                  wait for a ſuppuration of the <lb/>ſwelling, and would have the plaiſter applied
                  to it <lb/>whilſt it was unbroken: the cure was protracted, but it <lb/>was
                  effectual; he has had no return of the complaint; <lb/>a ſlight inequality of
                  ſurface ſtill remains on his neck; <lb/>Mr. Mills has communicated his recipe to
                  ſeveral, and <lb/>in particular to a very intelligent perſon in this neigh-
                  <lb/>bourhood, who has employed it with unfailing ſucceſs. <lb/>All the patients
                  complain of the ſeverity of the appli- <pb n="49"/>
                  <lb/>cation; and in every ulcer to which it is applied, there <lb/>takes place a
                  remarkable change from a dead pale to a <lb/>bright ſcarlet colour. </q>
              </p>
              <dateline><hi rend="italic">July</hi> 17, 1794. </dateline>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>This change of colour indicates communication of <lb/>oxygene, which perhaps the
            oxalic acid of the ſorrel <lb/>contains in ſuch a ſtate of combination as eaſily to part
            <lb/>with a portion. Now Dr. Darwin, in his <hi rend="sc">Zoonomia</hi>, <lb/>attributes
            ſcrophulous ſwellings of the glands to <choice>
              <corr>inirri- <lb/>tability</corr>
              <sic>inirra- <lb/>tibility</sic>
            </choice>, which, as I have conjectured, may ariſe from <lb/>a certain deficiency of
            oxygene. Theſe principles <lb/>would ſupply an obvious theory, were we but certain
            <lb/>of our facts. If however, as the preceding account <lb/>implies, ſorrel produces
            detumeſcence of the glands <lb/>before ſuppuration, its application will be, I ſuppoſe,
            <lb/>a more eligible practice than any now in uſe. Wri- <lb/>ters in the Materia Medica
            may have applied <hi rend="italic">deob- <lb/>ſtruent</hi>—their word of courſe—to this
            plant, but I <lb/>remember no particular commemoration of its virtue <lb/>in ſcrophula.
            Murray, a complier of extenſive read- <lb/>ing, has nothing to this purpoſe.—(<hi
              rend="italic">Apparat. Medi- <lb/>cam.</hi> III. 492-9). </p>
        </div>
        <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="40"/>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
