<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Rollo: An Account of Two Cases of the Diabetes Mellitus</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>John Rollo</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">An account of two cases of the diabetes mellitus: with remarks, as
              they arose during the progress of the cure. To which are added, a general view of the
              nature of the disease and its appropriate treatment, including observations on some
              diseases depending on stomach affection; and a detail of the communications received
              on the subject since the dispersion of the notes on the first case. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T53590 </idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T53590"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed by T. Gillet, for C. Dilly, in the Poultry,
                  MDCCXCVII.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1797</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="16"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="520"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107091803</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: disease"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="16"/>
    <body>
      <div type="part">
        <pb n=""/>
        <head rend="sc align-center space">
          <lb/>of what has been communicated to us <lb/><hi rend="size(0.5)">on the </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="italic size(1.25)">DIABETES MELLITUS, </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="size(0.5)">since the </hi>
          <lb/>DISPERSION OF OUR NOTES <lb/><hi rend="size(0.5)">of </hi>
          <lb/>CAPTAIN MEREDlTH's CASE. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HIS part of our ſubject is extremely <lb/>ſatisfactory; and of
          courſe we enter <lb/>upon it with peculiar gratification. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The moſt valuable of the communications <lb/>have been received ſince the preceding
          part <lb/>of the work has been in the hands of the <lb/>Printer. Therefore, the view we
          have ex- <lb/>hibited of the hiſtory, nature, and treatment <lb/>of the diſeaſe, has
          derived no advantage from <lb/>them. However, they muſt convey ſtrong <lb/>impreſſions of
          the correctneſs, and truth of <lb/>our general principles. That theſe may be- <lb/>come
          perfectly explained and eſtabliſhed, <lb/>we ſolicit a continuance of every commu-
          <lb/>nication tending to throw additional light <pb n="2"/>
          <lb/>on the ſubject. The preſent ſhall be re- <lb/>corded ſeparately, and without any
          remark; <lb/>by which their own importance will appear <lb/>more conſpicuous. Any
          obſervations, or <lb/>concluſions which may be thought neceſſa- <lb/>ry to offer, or draw
          from them, will be ſub- <lb/>joined at the end, or deferred until another <lb/>occaſion. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>We embrace this opportunity of acknow- <lb/>ledging the obligations we are under to
          our <lb/>reſpectable correſpondents—and while we <lb/>admit the honourable teſtimony moſt
          of <lb/>them have conferred on us, the medical <lb/>world muſt generally allow, and
          appreciate, <lb/>the diſintereſted efforts they have manifeſted <lb/>for the improvement
          of medical ſcience. </p>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="hanging italic space">
            <lb/>From <hi rend="sc">Dr. Duncan</hi>, Profeſſor of the Inſtitutes <lb/>of Medicine,
            in the <hi rend="sc">University</hi> of <hi rend="sc">Edin- <lb/>burgh</hi>. </head>
          <dateline rend="align-right italic">
            <lb/>Edinburgh, 13th Jan. 1797. </dateline>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>IN a caſe of Diabetes which I treat- <lb/>ed, about 20 years ago, I found that the
            uſe <pb n="3"/>
            <lb/>of fat meat had a ſurpriſing effect in allevi- <lb/>ating the thirſt, and
            diminiſhing the quanti- <lb/>ty of urine. But the effect was temporary <lb/>only, and I
            have not found it to hold to the <lb/>ſame extent with other patients. The he-
            <lb/>patiſed ammonia will, I hope, attraft the at- <lb/>tention of medical
            practitioners, and obtain <lb/>a fair trial. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>From <hi rend="sc">Dr. Falconer</hi>, of Bath. </head>
          <dateline rend="italic align-right space">
            <lb/>Bath, 13th Jan. 1797. </dateline>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>I SAW, about ſix years ago, a caſe <lb/>of Diabetes in a gentleman, who really got
            <lb/>it by drinking a liquor compounded of treacle <lb/>and eſſence of ſpruce, fermented
            with water <lb/>and yeaſt, forming ſpruce beer, of which he <lb/>drank largely to reduce
            a corpulent habit. <lb/>I tried with him to increaſe the perſpiratory <lb/>evacuations
            by Dover's powder, and the warm <lb/>bath; but did not ſucceed. Indeed he was <lb/>not a
            very tractable patient. I would re- <lb/>commend this remedy with perhaps an in-
            <lb/>creaſed quantity of ipecacuan to your con- <pb n="4"/>
            <lb/>ſideration, as it might produce perſpiration, <lb/>and check the canine appetite.
            Aſtringents <lb/>I have ſeen tried, but with no advantage. <lb/>Might not the mephitic
            alkaline water, im- <lb/>pregnated with ſulphureous gas, be of ſer- <lb/>vice? Might not
            a ſulphureous ointment to <lb/>the ſkin made with ſome rancid animal oil <lb/>be a
            probable remedy? And might not a <lb/>ſolution of ſulphur in oil with ſome opiate,
            <lb/>and mixed with ſtarch or animal mucilage, <lb/>be of ſervice thrown up as a
            clyſter? </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic hanging space">
            <lb/>From <hi rend="sc">Dr. Baillie</hi>, Lecturer on Anatomy <lb/>and Surgery, and
            Phyſiciau of St. George's <lb/>Hoſpital, <hi rend="sc">London</hi>. </head>
          <dateline rend="italic align-right space">
            <lb/>March 2nd, 1797. </dateline>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>MY paper on Diabetes was written <lb/>two years ago, and read at that time to a
            <lb/>ſociety of which I am a member. It was <lb/>determined by the ſociety that it
            ſhould be <lb/>publiſhed, and it became from that moment <lb/>their property. I have,
            therefore, no right <lb/>to comply with your requeſt. I examined <pb n="5"/>
            <lb/>not only the ſtate of the kidneys, but of the <lb/>ſtomach, the inteſtines, the
            glands of the <lb/>meſentery, the liver, the ſpleen, and the <lb/>pancreas, and I do not
            heſitate to mention <lb/>to you generally, that I was induced to be- <lb/>lieve, from
            the morbid appearances in the <lb/>kidneys, that the principal ſeat of the diſeaſe
            <lb/>was in them. This examination was made <lb/>with a view to the different theories
            which <lb/>have been formed about the cauſe of this <lb/>diſeaſe, and I have added upon
            each of them <lb/>a few obſervations. The paper will be pub- <lb/>liſhed, as it was
            written two years ago, and <lb/>nothing will be ſubjoined in conſequence of <lb/>what
            has been done lately. It will make <lb/>me very happy if a method of treating the
            <lb/>Diabetes, which will commonly prove ſuc- <lb/>ceſsful, ſhall be diſcovered, and my
            pleaſure <lb/>will not be diminiſhed by thinking that the <lb/>diſcovery has fallen into
            your hands. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="6"/>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic hanging space">
            <lb/>From <hi rend="sc">Mr. Abernethy</hi>, Aſſiſtant Surgeon <lb/>at St. Bartholomew's
            Hoſpital, and Lec- <lb/>turer on Anatomy and Surgery. </head>
          <dateline rend="italic align-right space">
            <lb/>London, 12th April, 1797. </dateline>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>I TOOK no notes of the diabetic <lb/>caſes which were in St. Bartholomew's Hoſ-
            <lb/>pital, as they did not belong to ſurgery. I <lb/>was only deſirous of knowing if
            the kid- <lb/>neys could form ſugar. Once I had an op- <lb/>portunity of examining the
            blood, and was <lb/>ſatisfied with knowing that the ſerum was <lb/>not at all ſweet. I
            recollect that it was <lb/><hi rend="italic">turbid</hi>. When the patients took milk,
            <lb/>oranges, and ſugar, the quantity of the lat- <lb/>ter matter voided was greatly
            increaſed. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>From <hi rend="sc">Dr. Beddoes</hi>, of Briſtol. </head>
          <dateline rend="italic align-right space">
            <lb/>Briſtol, 10th Jan. 1797. </dateline>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>I LAST night read your caſe of Di- <lb/>abetes with the moſt eager pleaſure, and
            <lb/>have ever ſince reflected on it with the ut- <pb n="7"/>
            <lb/>moſt ſatisfaction. It is a pledge of the ad- <lb/>vance of medicine towards
            ſcientific princi- <lb/>ples. I am curious to know the progreſs <lb/>of the caſe, and
            alſo of Mr. <hi rend="italic">Cruickſhank's</hi>
            <lb/>ingenious reſearches. I had not been ſatis- <lb/>fied with any thing in Diabetes;
            but I think <lb/>your experiments, and practice, have thrown <lb/>a ray of light on this
            obſcure ſubject. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>I have been long looking out for diabetic <lb/>patients, and your obliging
            communication <lb/>will renew my diligence. One patient only <lb/>I knew intimately—he
            has been thrice cured <lb/>by the water here. I did not attend him, <lb/>nor can I learn
            whether his urine was ſweet. <lb/>But it is certain he had thirft, emaciation,
            <lb/>redneſs, voracious appetite, exceſſive diſ- <lb/>charge of urine (probably 20
            pounds in the <lb/>24 hours). He has thrice viſited this place <lb/>in 12 years, and
            each time been recovered <lb/>in a fortnight. No medical man attended <lb/>him, and his
            country doctor is dead. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="8"/>
        <div type="section">
          <dateline rend="italic align-right space">
            <lb/>April 14th, 1797. </dateline>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>YOU aſk my preſent opinion on <lb/>conſumption. Allow me generally to ſay, <lb/>I
            have now no chemical theory of any one <lb/>diſeaſe. I never <hi rend="italic">held</hi>
            any ſuch opinion. In <lb/>different ways (at lectures, and in publica- <lb/>tions), I
            ſtarted conjectures to be compared <lb/>with facts; and now I think all thoſe con-
            <lb/>jectures are ſhewn to be erroneous by facts. <lb/>I uſed to think my hypotheſis on
            ſcurvy <lb/>very probable, and I was confirmed in this <lb/>idea by Dr. Trotter. But I
            at preſent think <lb/>we were both miſtaken. Good, however, <lb/>has ariſen from theſe
            ſpeculations, as they <lb/>have brought forward obſervations which <lb/>otherwiſe
            apparently would never have been <lb/>made, and ſome of theſe obſervations are
            <lb/>uſeful in practice. When I publiſh my <lb/>view of the medical treatment to be
            purſued <lb/>in the pneumatic inſtitution, I will unfold <lb/>what I here ſay, and add
            my reaſons. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="9"/>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>From <hi rend="sc">Dr. Currie</hi>, of Liverpool. </head>
          <dateline rend="italic align-right space">
            <lb/>Liverpool, Feb. 20th, 1797. </dateline>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>IN the courſe of my practice, I have <lb/>met with a few caſes of the Diabetes:
            chief- <lb/>ly in the Liverpool Infirmary. I have ſeen <lb/>it ſtopped in its progreſs
            by opiates, cantha- <lb/>rides, alum and bark: but after the ſaccha- <lb/>rine
            impregnation of the urine, I never <lb/>knew it cured. One caſe I took much <lb/>pains
            with about four years ago: but my <lb/>regiſter, and notes were purloined by ſome
            <lb/>of the pupils, and I never could recover <lb/>them. I uſed the tepid bath in this
            caſe, <lb/>with milk, and with broth; but never could <lb/>diſcover that the patient
            gained any weight <lb/>during immerſion, though I weighed him <lb/>with the utmoſt
            accuracy before and after. <lb/>In a caſe where, in conſequence of an ob- <lb/>ſtruction
            of the pharynx, the patient died of <lb/>hunger, after ſubſiſting without ſwallowing
            <lb/>upwards of thirty days, I had occaſion to <lb/>make the ſame remark. In the
            diabetic <lb/>patient to which I allude, I weighed the in- <pb n="10"/>
            <lb/>geſta, and the egeſta (as far as they are ca- <lb/>pable of being weighed), and I
            found that <lb/>the patient changed a ſeventh part of his <lb/>whole ſubſtance every
            twenty four hours! </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>You will be pleaſed to hear that we have <lb/>at preſent an opportunity of putting
            your <lb/>practice into trial in a caſe of Diabetes now <lb/>in our Hoſpital. It is
            under the care of my <lb/>worthy colleague Dr. Gerard, to whom I <lb/>have communicated
            your notes. From <lb/>him or me you ſhall hear the iſſue. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>I agree with you in the expectations you <lb/>form of the benefit to medicine from
            the <lb/>new chemiſtry. I may mention the appli- <lb/>cation of the nitric acid to the
            cure of lues, <lb/>communicated by Mr. Scott of Bengal to <lb/>Sir Joſeph Banks. I have
            proved this prac- <lb/>tice in various inſtances, and can aſſure you <lb/>of its
            extraordinary ſucceſs. I give one <lb/>drachm of the acid daily in a pint and a
            <lb/>half, or two pints of water. The ſucceſs <lb/>of the nitric acid in this diſeaſe,
            has induced <lb/>me to propoſe its trial in the yellow fever <pb n="11"/>
            <lb/>of the Weſt Indies (in which mercury ſeems <lb/>to be the only remedy on which any
            depen- <lb/>dance is placed) and I have written to Sir <lb/>Joſeph Banks to requeſt his
            taking meaſures <lb/>to bring this remedy under the notice of <lb/>Government. In the
            meantime I have <lb/>written to the Windward Iſlands, and Ja- <lb/>maica, on the
            ſubject. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <dateline rend="italic align-right space">
            <lb/>18th March, 1797. </dateline>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The caſe which I mentioned to you of <lb/>Diabetes has been ſtrictly attended to by
            my <lb/>friend Dr. Gerard, who has noticed all the <lb/>particulars you would wiſh in a
            regular <lb/>journal, which will be tranſmitted to you <lb/>when the iſſue is known. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>We wiſh much to have a ſmall quantity <lb/>ſent by the coach of your hepatiſed
            ammo- <lb/>nia, as we are doubtful whether we have <lb/>ſuccceded in making it here, and
            we think <lb/>the patient is in a ſtate to be benefited by it. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>There is no queſtion about the anti-vene- <lb/>real effects of the nitrous acid.
            That which <pb n="12"/>
            <lb/>I have uſed has been <hi rend="italic">nitrous</hi>, not nitric; for <lb/>I had not
            the latter by me, and I found the <lb/>former ſucceed. Whether it is equally ef-
            <lb/>ficacious with mercury in all caſes, &amp;c. muſt <lb/>be leſt to more extenſive
            experience. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>From <hi rend="sc">Dr. Trotter</hi>, Phyſician to his <lb/>Majeſty's Fleet. </head>
          <p rend="italic indent space">
            <lb/>The communications of Dr. Trotter, contain <lb/>a further account of our ſecond
            caſe of Diabe- <lb/>tes, ſubſequent to the reproduction of the diſ- <lb/>eaſe by the uſe
            of fruits, wine, &amp;c.; and it <lb/>will be perceived, a return to our plan of treat-
            <lb/>ment again removed the diſeaſe; but from ano- <lb/>ther indulgence in forbidden
            things, the diſeaſe <lb/>returned. The conſequences to the patient may <lb/>be very
            readily apprehended. </p>
          <div type="subsection">
            <dateline rend="italic align-right space">
              <lb/>Portſmouth, 27th Jan. 1797. </dateline>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/> I BEG leave to thank you for Cap- <lb/>tain Meredith's caſe, which has afforded
              me <lb/>a fund of information and entertainment. </p>
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>I think with you on the ſubject of pneu- <lb/>matic medicine, and your able
              induction of <lb/>its doctrine, in the maſterly treatment of <lb/>Diabetes, will give
              a vaſt ſupport to the <lb/>truths which it embraces. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <dateline rend="italic align-right space">
              <lb/>3d April, 1797. </dateline>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>IT would have given me much plea- <lb/>ſure to have returned you ſatisfactory an-
              <lb/>ſwers to your queries concerning the urine <lb/>of ſcorbutics; but ſuch is the
              healthy Condi- <lb/>tion of this fleet, from the effectual means <lb/>of prevention,
              that ſcurvy has ſcarcely ap- <lb/>peared for ſome months. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>I have many objections to offer againſt <lb/>former experiments on this ſubject,
              and I <lb/>think the whole unſatisfactory. Where <lb/>trials are to be made, they
              ought to be done <lb/>in the advanced ſtage of the diſeaſe, and <lb/>when the patient
              has for a day or two ab- <lb/>ſtained from ſalted meat, and before recent
              <lb/>vegetables are touched. The urine in ſcur- <lb/>vy is ſmall in quantity, dark
              coloured, and <lb/>may be called highly animaliſed; but its <pb n="14"/>
              <lb/>chemical properties have never been exactly <lb/>aſcertained. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>In ſcurvy there is little thirſt. The ap- <lb/>petite is generally good, even for
              ſalted <lb/>meat; but freſh vegetables are always high- <lb/>ly grateful. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Emaciation ſucceeds the uſe of the acid <lb/>fruits when given in large
              quantities in in- <lb/>veterate caſes, and the appetite declines. I <lb/>have not ſeen
              the exhibition continued <lb/>longer than a cure was neceſſary. The <lb/>urine becomes
              pale, and larger in quantity <lb/>than the liquids taken in. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>In proportion to the quantity of lemon <lb/>juice taken in, ſometimes in a day or
              two, <lb/>the blood regains its florid colour: I have <lb/>known this colour, during
              the cure, brighter <lb/>than in the natural ſtate. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Nitre diſſolved in vinegar, in 152 caſes, <lb/>by two able navy ſurgeons, did not
              produce <lb/>any favourable appearances in ſcurvy. </p>
            <pb n="15"/>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Three caſes of inveterate ſyphilis, have <lb/>been cured here by nitric acid, as
              deſcribed <lb/>by Mr. Scott in Dr. Beddoes laſt work. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>I have viſited your patient the <hi rend="sc">General</hi>
              <lb/>thrice. As ſoon as he returned to your plan <lb/>of diet, the urine became
              natural in quality, <lb/>and decreaſed from eight to three pints a <lb/>day. Whether
              this relief ſhould be perma- <lb/>nent or not, it is deciſive teſtimony of the
              <lb/>efficacy of your practice, more eſpecially <lb/>when we conſider the trial is in
              a caſe of ſo <lb/>many years ſtanding. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>I have never known a caſe of Diabetes <lb/>among ſeamen, nor have any of my naval
              <lb/>acquaintances. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>You have thus added another triumph to <lb/>the pneumatic phyſicians, which
              blends <lb/>with it relief to human miſery hitherto in- <lb/>curable. </p>
            <postscript>
              <p rend="indent space">
                <lb/>
                <label>P. S. </label> Mr. Hatcher ſends his compliments; <lb/>he has juſt ſeen the
                  <hi rend="sc">General</hi>, whoſe urine <pb n="16"/>
                <lb/>the laſt 24 hours did not exceed one pint <lb/>and a half. </p>
            </postscript>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <dateline rend="italic align-right space">
              <lb/>16th April, 1797. </dateline>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>SINCE my laſt I think the <hi rend="sc">Gene- <lb/>ral</hi> has gained ſome
              ſtrength, and looks <lb/>better. He has diligently perſevered in the <lb/>animal diet,
              and taken as much in a veniſon <lb/>ſtate as he could obtain. This being the
              <lb/>caſe, and all kinds of wine, and malt li- <lb/>quors being left off, we cannot
              expect that <lb/>reliſh for food which we obſerve in other <lb/>conditions. Of his
              appetite, however, there <lb/>is no reaſon to complain; his food certainly
              <lb/>nouriſhes. His pulſe in the right arm is <lb/>about 84, of due ſtrength; but at
              the other <lb/>wriſt it has always been different, probably <lb/>you obſerved this at
              Woolwich. A ſlight <lb/>clammineſs is felt in the mouth; but no <lb/>thirſt. He takes
              an opiate and ſleeps well; <lb/>and gets out of doors in this fine weather. <lb/>His
              cough is almoſt gone, and he expecto- <lb/>rates with eaſe. His feet are now comfort-
              <lb/>ably warm, and I think the ſkin begins to <lb/>do its office; the ſcurf has
              fallen off. To- <pb n="17"/>
              <lb/>morrow he will begin to take the following <lb/>chalybeate pills. </p>
            <floatingText type="sub-subsection" subtype="recipe" rend="italic align-center space">
              <body>
                <p rend="hanging">
                  <lb/><hi rend="roman">℞</hi> Rubig. Ferri <hi rend="roman">ʒſſ.</hi>
                  <lb/>Magneſia uſt. gr. xx <lb/>Pulv. Zinzib. gr. x <lb/>Ol. Olivar. fi. maſs.
                  dividenda <lb/>in pil. No. xij—Sum. ij. ter die. </p>
              </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">General</hi> drinks a ſmall tumbler of <lb/>lime water three
              times a day; but the <hi rend="italic">hy- <lb/>drogeno-ſulphurated ammonia</hi>
              rather palled <lb/>the ſtomach, and ſo he left it off. He alſo <lb/>drinks a little
              hollands, or brandy and water; <lb/>being ſpirits free from ſaccharine matter. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Things being in this train in a caſe of <lb/>ſuch long ſtanding, the whole
              account is <lb/>very flattering: ſuffice it to ſay, the patient <lb/>thinks himſelf in
              paradiſe, compared with <lb/>his former ſufferings. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <dateline rend="italic align-right space">
              <lb/>28th April, 1797. </dateline>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>IN my laſt I informed you that I <lb/>had ordered a pill of the Rubigo Ferri for
                <pb n="18"/>
              <lb/>the <hi rend="sc">General</hi>. There appeared ſtrong <lb/>ſymptoms of a
              different diſpoſition of body <lb/>being induced, from that which attended <lb/>the
              diſcharge of the ſaccharine urine. The <lb/>fetor of the urine had become uncommonly
              <lb/>offenſive, a very ſhort time after voiding it. <lb/>There was unuſual languor and
              anxiety for <lb/>the vinous ſtimulus, I therefore thought it <lb/>fair to try the oxyd
              of iron. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>The urine, however, continues much the <lb/>ſame in quantity, and quality; but
              ſtill I <lb/>think for a few days our patient has been <lb/>loſing ground; and though
              the appetite is <lb/>not ſo deficient, the emaciation ſeems to in- <lb/>creaſe. He has
              uniformly hankered after <lb/>the forbidden cup, and though he is ſatisfied <lb/>with
              the idea, that indulgence muſt be fa- <lb/>tal, it is in vain to reſiſt his
              importunities. <lb/>For two days paſt he has taken a glaſs and <lb/>a half-ful of
              Madeira wine—the urine has <lb/>increaſed ſome ounces beyond the uſual <lb/>quantity. </p>
            <pb n="19"/>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>I am ſorry that the fleet being ordered to <lb/>ſea will prevent me from
              detailing the fu- <lb/>ture occurrences of this ſingular caſe. I <lb/>have urged the
              plan to be continued, but <lb/>doubt of its being carefully adhered to. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <p rend="indent italic space">
            <lb/><hi rend="sc">Dr. Trotter's</hi> doubts have, we are ſorry <lb/>to ſay, been fully
            realiſed, as the following ex- <lb/>tract of a letter ſhews. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <dateline rend="italic align-right space">
            <lb/>Portſmouth, 7th May, 1797. </dateline>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>THE <hi rend="sc">General</hi> is gone to Port- <lb/>cheſter to try the effects of
            a change of ſitu- <lb/>ation; but it will be of no avail. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Since Dr. Trotter left him, he has return- <lb/>ed to his favourite plan, and eats
            of every <lb/>thing, as apple-pudding, tea with ſugar, &amp;c. <lb/>and drinks wine. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>His urine has increaſed, it has become <lb/>pale, and ſweetiſh; his thirſt is
            returned; <lb/>in ſhort he has again relapſed into his diſ- <lb/>eaſe. How much this is
            to be regretted! </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="20"/>
        <div type="section">
          <p rend="indent italic">
            <lb/>We ſincerely lament the apparent iſſue of this <lb/>our ſecond caſe of Diabetes
            Mellitus, eſpecially <lb/>as we have every reaſon to think it might have <lb/>terminated
            more favourably. With extreme <lb/>pleaſure we communicate the following letter
            <lb/>from Captain Meredith, as it ſhews the conti- <lb/>nuation of a full
            re-eſtabliſhment of health; <lb/>even under unfavourable circumſtances in diet <lb/>and
            exerciſe. We regret his return to wine, <lb/>as it annihilates our proſpects of the
            prevention <lb/>of gout. We have only to hope, that he will <lb/>be enough guarded, ſo
            as to obviate another at- <lb/>tack of Diabetes. </p>
        </div>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>From <hi rend="sc">Captain Meredith</hi>. </head>
          <dateline rend="italic align-right space">
            <lb/>Ireland, Youghall, 10 May, 1797. </dateline>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>I DID not experience the ſmalleſt fa- <lb/>tigue by my journey from Woolwich to
            <lb/>Plymouth, though I travelled two days and <lb/>a night in the coach. I remained a
            month <lb/>at Plymouth, where my duty was moderate, <lb/>but where the civilities of my
            friends led <lb/>me to frequent indulgencies at the table, <pb n="21"/>
            <lb/>and was tempted to drink wine, though I <lb/>never exceeded a pint of port. On the
            <lb/>20th April, I embarked in perfect health, <lb/>and proceeded by ſea to Ireland. I
            remain- <lb/>ed on board until the 8th inſtant. I was <lb/>ſick at ſea, and frequently
            vomited a ſouriſh <lb/>matter. I diſembarked on the 8th, in good <lb/>health, and we
            marched eight miles, and <lb/>next day ſeventeen miles; we have ſtill 130 <lb/>miles to
            go, and I ſhall walk every inch of <lb/>the ground; for ſo far as we have gone, I
            <lb/>have not been ſenſible of more uneaſineſs <lb/>than what I uſually experienced
            before my <lb/>illneſs, after ſuch a march. My appetite is <lb/>good, but not keen; I
            have no thirſt; ſleep <lb/>well; and feel every way in health. My <lb/>urine never
            exceeds a quart in twenty four <lb/>hours, its colour, ſmell, and taſte are per-
            <lb/>fectly urinous. This morning I weighed <lb/>14<formula notation="fraction"
              >1/2</formula> ſtone. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="22"/>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>From <hi rend="sc">Mr. Marcet</hi>, at preſent of <hi rend="sc">Edin-
              <lb/>burgh</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="italic indent space">
            <lb/>Mr. Marcet is a zealous ſtudent in phyſic, <lb/>and a candidate for a medical
            degree; the ſub- <lb/>ject of his Theſis, Diabetes. Our mutual friend <lb/>Dr.
            Woollcombe, conveyed to him an account of <lb/>Captain Meredith's Caſe previous to the
            diſ- <lb/>perſion of the notes on it. Mr. Marcet an- <lb/>nounced it at Edinburgh, and
            at this time <lb/>there was one patient with the diſeaſe in the <lb/>Infirmary under the
            care of <hi rend="sc">Dr. Hope</hi>, who <lb/>adopted our treatment. An account of this
            <lb/>caſe, by permiſſion of <hi rend="sc">Dr. Hope</hi>, Mr. Mar- <lb/>cet has
            tranſmitted, as alſo an opinion of <hi rend="sc">Dr. <lb/>Rutherford's</hi> with regard
            to the operation <lb/>of the lungs in this diſeaſe. Mr. Marcet is en- <lb/>titled to our
            warmeſt thanks for the intereſt he <lb/>has taken in the ſupport of our ideas of the
            <lb/>diſeaſe; an intereſt founded on his own anxiety <lb/>for the promotion of medical
            ſcience, as perſon- <lb/>ally we are unacquainted. We hope he will <lb/>permit us, in
            this manner, to make our ac- <lb/>knowledgments. </p>
          <pb n="23"/>
          <div type="subsection">
            <dateline rend="italic align-right space">
              <lb/>Edinburgh, 14th April, 1797. </dateline>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Dr. Rutherford</hi> has repeatedly ex- <lb/>preſſed his regret, in
              never having had an op- <lb/>portunity of examining a diabetic body after <lb/>death.
              He is perſuaded that the changes <lb/>have not been looked for where they might
              <lb/>have been found. He believes that the lacteal <lb/>abſorbents, and the lymphatics
              of the lungs, <lb/>would be found enlarged, and perhaps the <lb/>texture of the lungs
              altered. The ſuppoſi- <lb/>tions with regard to the lungs is founded on <lb/>his
              notion, that the difference in the quan- <lb/>tity of urine, beyond the fluids and
              even ſo- <lb/>lids taken in during certain ſtates of the Di- <lb/>abetes Mellitus, is
              to be accounted for, from <lb/>the extraordinary production of water on the
              <lb/>ſurface of this organ, which he ſuppoſes to <lb/>be re-abſorbed; and not from any
              abſorp- <lb/>tion from the ſurface of the body by the ſkin. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <dateline rend="italic align-right space">
              <lb/>4th May, 1797. </dateline>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>I SEND you an extract of the caſe <lb/>of Walker, with Dr. Hope's permiſſion, and
              <lb/>you may do with it whatever you pleaſe. <pb n="24"/>
              <lb/>The effects of the animal diet on the quan- <lb/>tity and quality of the urine
              are perfectly <lb/>evident, though the caſe could not be car- <lb/>ried to an abſolute
              termination, from the <lb/>impatience and inſtability of the patient. <lb/>In
              Hoſpitals, where patients ſee three or <lb/>four times in the day every perſon about
              <lb/>them eating vegetables, a trial of an entire <lb/>diet of animal food can hardly
              be expected. </p>
          </div>
          <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="italic hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Abstract</hi> of a <hi rend="sc">Case</hi> of <hi rend="sc"
                >Diabetes Mel- <lb/>litus</hi>, in the <hi rend="sc">Royal Infirmary</hi>, at
                <lb/><hi rend="sc">Edinburgh</hi>. </head>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <head rend="indent space">
                <lb/><hi rend="sc">James Walker</hi>, a field-labourer, was <lb/>admitted by <hi
                  rend="sc">Dr. Hope</hi> into the <hi rend="sc">Clinical <lb/>Ward</hi>, with a
                confirmed <hi rend="sc">Diabetes</hi>, on <lb/>the <date>1<hi rend="italic">ſt</hi>
                  <hi rend="italic">November</hi>, 1796. </date>
              </head>
              <p rend="indent space">
                <lb/>
                <q rend="quotes" >His appetite is voracious, and his thirſt ſo <lb/>urgent,
                  as to make him deſire from ten to <lb/>ſixteen quarts in twenty four hours. His
                  <lb/>urine is præternaturally copious, and he has <lb/>a frequent inclination to
                  paſs it. It is lim- <pb n="25"/>
                  <lb/>pid, of a light green colour, and having a <lb/>ſlight ſweet taſte. He is
                  much emaciated; <lb/>and his feet and ancles ſwell towards even- <lb/>ing. Pulſe
                  96. Skin parched and rough. <lb/>Body coſtive. </q>
              </p>
              <p rend="indent space">
                <q >
                  <lb/>He recollects, on a froſty morning in De- <lb/>cember 1795, having ſlept ſome
                  hours in <lb/>an open cart. On the May following the <lb/>above ſymptoms appeared,
                  and have increaſ- <lb/>ed ever ſince. He has ſeveral times been <lb/>the object of
                  medical treatment; but with- <lb/>out permanent relief. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>2nd. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Milk daily, and as much drink as he <lb/>chooſes. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>3d. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Urine 22 pounds. Ingeſta 20 pounds. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>4th. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Urine 13 pounds. Ingeſta 17 pounds. <lb/>The urine becomes turbid on the
                  addition of <lb/>lime water; when evaporated it affords an <pb n="26"/>
                  <lb/>extract like molaſſes, which is ſweet to the <lb/>taſte. This matter mixed
                  with lime, ex- <lb/>hales the odour of ammonia. </q>
              </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>From this day to the 29th December, he <lb/>remained nearly in the ſame
                  ſtate, the quan- <lb/>tity of urine fluctuating between 12 and 18 <lb/>pounds in
                  24 hours. During this interval <lb/>he took ſome ferrum vitriolatum in the form
                  <lb/>of pills; uſed the cold ſhower bath, and <lb/>took occaſionally ſome emetics
                  and laxa- <lb/>tives;—the ſtomach being at times derang- <lb/>ed, and the
                  coſtiveneſs very obſtinate. Under <lb/>this treatment he ſeemed to get a little
                  <lb/>ſtronger, but without any important change <lb/>in the general ſymptoms of
                  the diſeaſe. It <lb/>was agreed to try the effects of animal food, <lb/>as lately
                  given with ſucceſs by Dr. Rollo at <lb/>Woolwich, an account of which was tranſ-
                  <lb/>mitted by Dr. Woollcombe to Mr. Marcet. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>December 29th. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/><hi rend="sc">Dr. Hope</hi> gave the following report. <q >In-
                  <lb/>geſta 17 pounds; urine 13 pounds. Five <pb n="27"/>
                  <lb/>pounds of this urine have afforded 5<formula notation="fraction"
                    >1/2</formula> ounces <lb/>of a thick ſaccharine extract. </q>
              </p>
              <p rend="indent space">
                <q >
                  <lb/>He has had for a month, an unpleaſant <lb/>ſenſe of burning heat in the ſoles
                  of his feet <lb/>during the night. </q>
              </p>
              <p rend="indent space">
                <q >
                  <lb/>He is directed to abſtain from vegetable <lb/>food in every ſhape. </q>
              </p>
              <p rend="indent space">
                <q >
                  <lb/>To have two eggs for breakfaſt. Boiled <lb/>meat and ſtakes alternately for
                  dinner. Eggs, <lb/>or cheeſe for ſupper. For drink eight pounds <lb/>of weak beef
                  tea, and two pounds of weak <lb/>peppermint water. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>30th. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Solid ingeſta about two pounds; drink <lb/>ten pounds; urine nine pounds.
                </q>
              </p>
              <p rend="indent space">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Let him have two pounds of fleſh meat <lb/>for dinner; half a pound of cheeſe
                  for ſup- <lb/>per, and three eggs for breakfaſt—drink as <lb/>before. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="28"/>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>31ſt. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Ingeſta (drink, and food) ten pounds; <lb/>urine five pounds, which exhales
                  an unuſu- <lb/>ally ſtrong urinous ſmell. Had a partial <lb/>ſweat over the trunk
                  and head in the night. <lb/>Mouth moiſt; no ſourneſs of ſtomach. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>January 1ſt, 1797. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Solid ingeſta as uſual; drink nine pounds; <lb/>urine eight pounds, more
                  limpid than yeſ- <lb/>terday, and has a ſharp acid odour. The <lb/>breath has the
                  ſame ſmell. The colour of <lb/>the urine, however, is not changed, on ad-
                  <lb/>dition of ſyrup of violets. </q>
              </p>
              <p rend="indent space">
                <q >
                  <lb/>There is ſlight headach and ſickneſs. The <lb/>tongue appears much cleaner
                  than uſual. <lb/>Has had a ſtool. Contin. diæta animalis. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>2nd. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Solid ingeſta the ſame; drink eight <lb/>pounds; urine ſix pounds. No
                  ſickneſs or <lb/>headach; tongue clear; the burning heat <pb n="29"/>
                  <lb/>of the feet as before. One looſe ſtool. <lb/>Contin. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>3d. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Drink 10 pounds; urine 7<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> pounds, of
                  a <lb/>deeper yellow than formerly; tongue natu- <lb/>ral. Contin. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>4th. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Drink ten pounds; urine ſeven pounds. <lb/>Contin. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>5th. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Drink nine pounds; urine 6<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> pounds,
                  <lb/>more yellow, with a peculiar (not urinous) <lb/>odour. Contin. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>6th. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>No report, as laſt night he went out, and <lb/>returned to the ward drunk,
                  and his urine <lb/>could not be meaſured. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>7th. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Drink 7<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> pounds; urine 6 pounds, and
                  it <lb/>has the ſame peculiar ſmell. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="30"/>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>8th. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Drink 7<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> pounds; urine 6 pounds;
                  body <lb/>coſtive. Contin. diæta animalis. Sum: ſta- <lb/>tim pil. rhœi. comp. ℈1
                  et iterum <unclear>e</unclear>ras mane. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>9th. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Drink ſix pounds; urine four pounds; a <lb/>copious ſtool this morning;
                  ſtrength not <lb/>changed ſince he began the animal food. <lb/>Contin. et habeat
                  aq. menth. piper. lbiv pro <lb/>potu. minuatur quantitas decocti carnis ad
                  <lb/>lbiv. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>10th. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Solid food as formerly; drink ſeven <lb/>pounds; urine five pounds; no ſtool.
                  Sum: <lb/>ſtatim pil. rhœi comp. ℈ 1. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>11th. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Drink ſix pounds; urine four pounds; <lb/>three ſtools this morning. Contin.
                  diæta <lb/>animalis. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="31"/>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>12th. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Drink ſix pounds; urine four pounds; <lb/>two ſtools—he thinks his ſtrength
                  is ſome- <lb/>what impaired within theſe two or three <lb/>days. Adeat cras mane
                  balneum frigidum. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>13th. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Drink ſeven pounds; urine five pounds; <lb/>bore the bath well. Contin. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>14th. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Drink eight pounds; urine ſix pounds. <lb/>Contin. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>15th. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Drink eight pounds; urine ſix pounds. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>16th. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Solid food as before; drink eight pounds; <lb/>urine ſix pounds, is of a
                  light ſtraw colour, <lb/>and with the peculiar ſmell it has had for <lb/>ſometime.
                </q>
              </p>
              <pb n="32"/>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>The urine of the 14th being evaporated, <lb/>afforded matter of conſiderable
                  conſiſtence, <lb/>with a ſtrong ſaline, but ſcarcely percepti- <lb/>ble ſweetiſh
                  taſte. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>17th. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Drink eight pounds; urine ſix pounds; <lb/>thinks he is weaker. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>18th. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Drink eight pounds; urine 5<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> pounds.
                  <lb/>Contin. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>19th and 20th. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q >
                  <lb/>Drink each day eight pounds; urine ſix <lb/>pounds. Contin. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>21ſt January. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <q rend="quotes">
                  <lb/>Drink ſeven pounds; urine five pounds. <lb/>He has leſt the Infirmary to-day
                  by his own <lb/>deſire to return to the country. </q>
              </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>4th May. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>Dr. Hope told me a few days ago, that he <lb/>had juſt then received a letter
                from Walker, <pb n="33"/>
                <lb/>who ſays that ſince he left the Infirmary he <lb/>has become weaker; and there
                is ſome ex- <lb/>pectation of his returning ſoon to the Hoſ- <lb/>pital to reſume
                his treatment. </p>
              <p rend="indent space">
                <lb/>But it is doubtful whether when he was <lb/>in the Clinical Ward he obſerved
                ſtrictly <lb/>the diet preſcribed. At leaſt he was accuſ- <lb/>tomed to go about
                freely; and the nurſe <lb/>told me repeatedly, that ſhe ſuſpected he did <lb/>not
                entirely abſtain from indulgencies of eat- <lb/>ing and drinking out of the houſe.
              </p>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic hanging space">
            <lb/>From <hi rend="sc">Dr. Cleghorn</hi>, Lecturer in Chemiſ- <lb/>try, and one of the
            Phyſicians to the Infir- <lb/>mary at Glaſgow. </head>
          <dateline rend="italic align-right">
            <lb/>Glaſgow, May 1, 1797. </dateline>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>SOME months ago I was honoured <lb/>with your excellent pamphlet on Diabetes.
            <lb/>At that moment I had two diabetic pa- <lb/>tients in the Royal Infirmary of this
            place, <lb/>and I began inſtantly to treat them on your <lb/>plan. They are both cured;
            and I have <lb/>delayed ſo long to thank you for your po- <pb n="34"/>
            <lb/>liteneſs, in the hope that I might be able to <lb/>inform you of this new ſucceſs. </p>
          <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
          <floatingText type="subsection" subtype="casereport">
            <body>
              <head rend="align-center">
                <lb/>CASE I. </head>
              <head rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/><hi rend="sc">John M'Lean</hi>, a Porter, Æt. 38. </head>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>December 9th, 1769, </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/><hi rend="sc">Four</hi> months ago had a fever, after <lb/>which, while yet
                  weak, he began to work <lb/>hard. Soon afterwards he obſerved his <lb/>urine more
                  abundant than uſual, amount- <lb/>ing daily to 24 pounds, or more. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>Though his appetite be voracious, he be- <lb/>comes leaner from day to day,
                  and is ſo <lb/>weak that he cannot walk a few ſteps with- <lb/>out panting. His
                  mouth is parched, tongue <lb/>red, thirſt extreme, belly coſtive. Pulſe 84. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>A few days ago he had a ſlight cough, <lb/>with pain in the right breaſt; but
                  theſe <lb/>complaints have abated. </p>
                <pb n="35"/>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>The feelings about the ſtomach when he <lb/>thinks himſelf hungry, differ
                  from thoſe he <lb/>formerly had; they are more uneaſy, and <lb/>the uneaſineſs is
                  leſs removed by taking food. <lb/>He is often troubled with flatulence; and
                  <lb/>complains conſtantly of weakneſs or pain in <lb/>the back and loins. Has uſed
                  no medicines. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>On examining the urine it was found lim- <lb/>pid and very ſweet. A pound of
                  it yielded <lb/>by evaporation more than an ounce of a thick <lb/>brown extract,
                  like treacle in appearance <lb/>and taſte. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>December 10th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>He was ordered an ounce of caſtor oil, <lb/>and the ſame quantity of compound
                  tinc- <lb/>ture of ſenna. His loins were directed to <lb/>be rubbed evening and
                  morning with ano- <lb/>dyne balſam. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>Equal parts of kino and ruſt of iron, form- <lb/>ed into pills of five
                  grains, with extract of <lb/>chamomile, were to be given, two for a doſe
                  <lb/>thrice a day. </p>
                <pb n="36"/>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>His drink and urine were ordered to be <lb/>meaſured daily, and the following
                  reports, <lb/>abridged from the Infirmary Regiſter, ſhew <lb/>the reſult. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>11th and 12th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>One ſtool; urine 28 pounds; has drank <lb/>about 14 pounds, beſides the uſual
                  allow- <lb/>ance of beer and broth. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>13th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Urine 27 pounds; drink 8 pounds; has <lb/>had double allowance of food. Belly
                  natu- <lb/>ral. To take 8 pills daily. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>14th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Feels himſelf a little eaſier and ſtronger. <lb/>To drink a pint of alum whey
                  daily at dif- <lb/>ferent times. To have the oil and tincture <lb/>of ſenna when
                  coſtive. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>In this courſe he perſevered till the 17th <lb/>of January, 1797. The
                  quantity of his <lb/>urine diminiſhed daily. On the 16th De- <lb/>cember it
                  amounted only to 20 pounds; <pb n="37"/>
                  <lb/>next day to 18, next to 15, next to 13; but <lb/>on the 20th it roſe to 16
                  pounds, without <lb/>any cauſe that could be pointed out, unleſs <lb/>the increaſe
                  proceeded from coſtiveneſs. <lb/>Next day it fell again to 13; on the 24th <lb/>it
                  roſe to 15: after which it varied from 13 <lb/>to 7<formula notation="fraction"
                    >1/2</formula> pounds. This was the quantity void- <lb/>ed on the 17th January.
                  It never fell be- <lb/>low 7<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula>; moſt
                  commonly it was between 8 <lb/>and 10 pounds. Meantime the patient con-
                  <lb/>ſidered himſelf as cured. He ſlept com- <lb/>fortably, ſometimes not riſing
                  during the <lb/>night, never oftener than once. The feel- <lb/>ings about his
                  ſtomach were more agree- <lb/>able; his countenance looked leſs ghaſtly, <lb/>and
                  he felt his ſtrength returning apace. <lb/>On examining his urine, however, I had
                  the <lb/>mortification to find it nearly as ſweet as <lb/>ever. I conſidered the
                  cure therefore as <lb/>very incomplete, and I expected that the <lb/>urine would
                  ſoon begin to increaſe, as it had <lb/>uniformly done in every caſe that I have
                  hi- <lb/>therto ſeen, and I have ſeen a conſiderable <lb/>number. </p>
                <pb n="38"/>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>While under this painful apprehenſion I <lb/>received Dr. Rollo's pamphlet,
                  which ſeem- <lb/>ed to me to contain a more diſtinct theory, <lb/>and a more
                  reaſonable practice than I had <lb/>ever met with before. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>As I could not immediately procure the <lb/>hepatiſed ammonia, I ordered him
                  to uſe for <lb/>drink 4 pounds of water containing a drachm <lb/>of lixiva
                  ſulphurata. The alum whey to be <lb/>continued. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>January 18th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Urine 8 pounds, with very little ſweet- <lb/>neſs. Thirſt increaſed, as he
                  thinks, by the <lb/>ſolution. The ſolution was omitted. Four <lb/>drops of
                  hepatiſed ammonia were added to <lb/>a pound of water. Of this he was directed
                  <lb/>to uſe from 2 to 6 pounds daily, (for the <lb/>ſake of brevity I ſhall
                  afterwards call this the <lb/>ammoniated water.) </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>19th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Has taken about 4 drops of the amm. hep. <lb/>Remarkably ſleepy. Urine 7
                  pounds. </p>
                <pb n="39"/>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Omit the alum whey; continue the am- <lb/>moniated water. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>20th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Urine 8 pounds, ſweet. Has uſed vege- <lb/>tables and milk freely. Took 3
                  pounds of <lb/>the ammoniated water. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>The neceſſity of abſtaining from vege- <lb/>tables was explained, and
                  enforced, and he <lb/>was ordered to continue the water. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>21ſt and 22d. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>He took only 2 pounds of the ammo- <lb/>niated water. Urine 8 pounds. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>Two drops were added, making 6 to each <lb/>pound of water. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>23d. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Urine about 7 pounds, leſs ſaccharine; <lb/>has drank 4 pounds of the water. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>From this date to the 30th the urine was <lb/>daily 7 or 8 pounds, and it was
                  leſs ſweet, <pb n="40"/>
                  <lb/>though ſtill perceptibly ſo. On the 30th, <lb/>7 drops were mixed with each
                  pound of <lb/>water, and given as formerly. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>From the 1ft February the patient came <lb/>under the care of Dr. Richard
                  Millar, who <lb/>reſolved to go on with the ſame experiment. <lb/>On the 3d the
                  urine fell to 6<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula>, but was ſtill
                  <lb/>ſweet. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>February 6th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Ammoniated water 4 pounds; urine 7 <lb/>pounds, ſtill ſweetiſh. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>Beſides the medicines, he was deſired to <lb/>drink a pound of lime water
                  daily. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>7th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Ammoniated water 2 pounds; lime wa- <lb/>ter 1 pound; a very good night; no
                  thirſt; <lb/>urine 5<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> pounds, ſweet. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>8th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Ammoniated water 3 pounds; no lime <lb/>water; urine 6 pounds, ſweet. Griping
                  and <lb/>teneſmus. The oil to be repeated. </p>
              </div>
              <pb n="41"/>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>9th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Urine 7 pounds, ſtill ſweet; ammoniated <lb/>water 3 pounds; no head-ach; but
                  there is <lb/>a little pain in the belly. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>10th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Ammoniated water 3 pounds; urine nearly <lb/>7 pounds, not ſo ſweet. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>11th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Ammoniated water 2 pounds; lime wa- <lb/>ter 1 pound; urine 5<formula
                    notation="fraction">1/2</formula> pounds, leſs ſweet. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>12th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Ammoniated water 2 pounds; no lime <lb/>water; urine 6 pounds. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>13th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Ammoniated water 2 pounds; urine 7 <lb/>pounds, ſtill ſweet. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>14th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Ammoniated water 2 pounds; lime wa- <lb/>ter 1 pound; urine above 6 pounds,
                  not ſo <lb/>ſweet. </p>
              </div>
              <pb n="42"/>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>15th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Ammoniated water 3 pounds; urine 6<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula>
                  <lb/>pounds, leſs ſweet. Eight drops of the he- <lb/>patiſed ammonia to each pound
                  of water. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>16th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Ammoniated water 3 pounds; no per- <lb/>ceptible effect from the additional
                  drop; <lb/>urine about 6 pounds, ſtill ſweet. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>17th, 18th, and 19th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Ammoniated water 3 pounds; urine daily <lb/>5<formula notation="fraction"
                    >1/2</formula> or 6 pounds, leſs ſweet. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>He was directed to take 5 drops among a <lb/>little water every ſecond hour,
                  and to ſwal- <lb/>low them immediately after mixture. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>From the 19th to the 23d, the urine was <lb/>from 5 to 6 pounds, much leſs
                  ſweet. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>24th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Several looſe ſtools of a natural ſmell, <lb/>which were checked by a grain
                  of opium in <lb/>the morning; urine about 3 pounds. The <pb n="43"/>
                  <lb/>medicine was omitted for this day, and the <lb/>opium ordered to be repeated,
                  if neceſſary. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>25th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Looſeneſs returned with violent griping, <lb/>and was relieved by a grain of
                  opium and by <lb/>fomenting the belly. Slept well; urine 3 <lb/>pounds, of a
                  natural ſmell, and hardly ſweet. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>The ammonia hepatiſata and lime water <lb/>were repeated; the opium omitted.
                </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>26th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Purging returned. Took a grain of opium <lb/>at 12 o'clock laſt night, ſince
                  which he has <lb/>had 2 looſe ſtools. Urine 3<formula notation="fraction"
                    >1/2</formula> pounds, natu- <lb/>ral. Omit the medicines, repeat the opium,
                  <lb/>if neceſſary. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>27th and 28th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Urine 4 pounds, nearly natural. Medi- <lb/>cines to be repeated. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>March 1ſt-3d. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Urine 5 or 5<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> pounds, nearly
                  natural. </p>
              </div>
              <pb n="44"/>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>4th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Urine 5 pounds, not ſo natural. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>The ammonia hepatiſata never produced <lb/>head-ach; it excited merely a
                  ſenſe of heat <lb/>for a few minutes in the region of the ſto- <lb/>mach extending
                  to the right ſide. Deſired <lb/>to take 50 drops in the day. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>5th and 6th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Urine 5<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> pounds, not ſo natural.
                </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>7th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Urine 5 pounds, neither of a natural ſmell, <lb/>nor is it very ſweet.
                  Directed to take 60 <lb/>drops daily. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>8th and 9th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Took 66 drops. Urine 5 pounds, leſs na- <lb/>tural. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>10th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>This moming took 15 drops at once, <lb/>with no other effect than a ſenſe of
                  heat in <lb/>the ſtomach. Urine 6 pounds, leſs natural <lb/>in taſte and ſmell. </p>
                <pb n="45"/>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Finding himſelf ſtrong enough, he aſked <lb/>leave to go home (to the ſuburbs
                  of Glaſ- <lb/>gow) to manage ſome buſineſs which re- <lb/>quired his preſence. He
                  promiſed to ab- <lb/>ſtain from vegetables, to take his drops, and <lb/>to return
                  if he became worſe. I have ſeen <lb/>him ſeveral times at work, and this day, be-
                  <lb/>ing the 10th of May, I received from his <lb/>own mouth the following
                  account. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>In 24 hours his urine is about 5 pounds. <lb/>He taſtes it very often, and it
                  has never been <lb/>ſweet, but after getting little animal food <lb/>for days
                  together (which has happened more <lb/>than once) it has ſometimes been of a ſour
                  <lb/>ſmell. Formerly he could carry on a wheel- <lb/>barrow three hundred weight;
                  at preſent <lb/>he carries one hundred weight, and he can <lb/>walk as well as
                  ever. Two days ago he <lb/>went expreſs to Paiſley, received an anſwer <lb/>to the
                  letter he carried, and returned to <lb/>Glaſgow in three hours and a half (about
                    <lb/>14<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> miles.) Occaſionally he has
                  taken 60 <lb/>drops a day of the hepatiſed ammonia, <lb/>which he likes, becauſe
                  it gives him an <pb n="46"/>
                  <lb/>agreeable feeling of warmth, and never pro- <lb/>duces any inconvenience. For
                  two weeks, <lb/>however, he has had none, ſince which his <lb/>urine has not
                  increaſed in quantity, has not <lb/>been ſweet, and when evaporated lately by
                  <lb/>himſelf, and by a neighbour of his, whoſe <lb/>curioſity he has excited, it
                  yielded no ſugar. <lb/>The reſiduum could not be diſtinguiſhed <lb/>from that of
                  an equal quantity of healthful <lb/>urine, evaporated at the ſame time with
                  <lb/>great care and ſagacity. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>The only kind of animal food that he can <lb/>procure in ſufficient quantity
                  is blood, which <lb/>he mixes with fat and a little meal. Even <lb/>this homely
                  fare he finds it difficult at pre- <lb/>ſent to procure regularly. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>He was always lean, and is now rather <lb/>more ſo than before his fever; but
                  though <lb/>he works very hard, he thinks himſelf <lb/>ſtronger, and more fleſhy
                  than when he left <lb/>the Infirmary. He ſleeps well; is regular <lb/>in his
                  belly, and free from every complaint, <lb/>except occaſional pains about the
                  muſcles of <pb n="47"/>
                  <lb/>his breaſt and arms, ariſing obviouſly from <lb/>the intenſe colds to which
                  he has been very <lb/>much expoſed, as he plies near the river <lb/>from morning
                  to night. He is the father of <lb/>ſeveral children, but ſince he has been ſeized
                  <lb/>with Diabetes—Coitus nullus. Erigitum <lb/>nunquam: ne quidem ſemel rigeſcit. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>About a month before he left the Infir- <lb/>mary, the other patient gave the
                  ſame ac- <lb/>count of himſelf. </p>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
          <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
          <floatingText type="subsection" subtype="casereport">
            <body>
              <head rend="align-center">
                <lb/>CASE II. </head>
              <head rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/><hi rend="sc">John Roger</hi>, Æt. 40, a Shoemaker. </head>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>January 10th, 1797. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/><hi rend="sc">For</hi> two months his urine has been pro- <lb/>fuſe,
                  amounting daily to 20 pounds or more. <lb/>It is limpid and ſweet, yielding by
                  evapora- <lb/>tion an ounce of thick ſweet matter, like <lb/>treacle, from every
                  pound. </p>
                <pb n="48"/>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>He is thin and weak; habitually thirſty; <lb/>for ſome days paſt has felt
                  pain between his <lb/>ſhoulders, and for a week his legs have been <lb/>œdematous.
                  Appetite keen; pulſe and belly <lb/>natural. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>Knows nothing to which he can attribute <lb/>his complaint. Has uſed bitters,
                  and other <lb/>medicines, without material benefit. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>The aſtringent pills, and alum whey, were <lb/>ordered for him, as for
                  M'Lean. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>12th. </dateline>
                <p rend="align-center">
                  <lb/>Urine 36 pounds. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>13th. </dateline>
                <p rend="align-center">
                  <lb/>Urine 30 pounds. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>14th. </dateline>
                <p rend="align-center">
                  <lb/>Urine 23 pounds. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>15th. </dateline>
                <p rend="align-center">
                  <lb/>Urine 20<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> pounds. </p>
              </div>
              <pb n="49"/>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>16th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Urine 21<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> pounds; thirſt exceſſive;
                  ſleeps <lb/>ill; pulſe full and hard. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>The medicines were omitted. He was <lb/>directed to drink a ſolution of
                  lixiva ſulphu- <lb/>rata, one drachm to four pounds of water, <lb/>and to uſe
                  animal food. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>He got caſtor oil, with tincture of ſenna, <lb/>and at bed-time had a
                  draught, with 25 <lb/>drops laudanum, and 30 of antimonial wine. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>17th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Reſted well; urine 21 pounds; likes the <lb/>drink. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>18th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Three ſtools; was ſick, and vomited after <lb/>ſupper; thirſty; urine 9
                  pounds, ſtill ſweet. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>The ſolution was omitted, and the draught <lb/>repeated. </p>
              </div>
              <pb n="50"/>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>19th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Urine 14 pounds, very ſweet. No ſtool. <lb/>The draught was omitted, and 4
                  drops of <lb/>the hepatiſed ammonia were given in a <lb/>pound of water as for
                  M'Lean. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>Of this ammoniated water, he drank daily <lb/>from 2 to 5 pounds, uſing
                  caſtor oil when <lb/>neceſſary. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>On the 24th his urine amounted to 8 <lb/>pounds only, and was almoſt natural.
                  Next <lb/>day it was 14 pounds, and varied from 10 <lb/>to 13 pounds, being
                  ſometimes more, ſome- <lb/>times leſs ſweet, till January 31ſt, when my
                  <lb/>attendance at the Hoſpital having ceaſed, <lb/>Dr. Millar took charge of this
                  patient alſo. <lb/>The following reports will ſhew the effects <lb/>of the
                  medicine, &amp;c. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>February 5th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Urine 13 pounds, ſtill ſweetiſh; 2 pounds <lb/>of ammoniated water. Has
                  head-ach and <lb/>giddineſs, more or leſs ſevere, according to <pb n="51"/>
                  <lb/>the quantity of ammoniated water that he <lb/>drinks. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>6th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Ammoniated water 3 pounds; urine 14 <lb/>pounds, ſtill ſweetiſh. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>To drink a pound of lime-water daily. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>7th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>From the 22d to the 30th of January, <lb/>each pound of water contained 5
                  drops of <lb/>amm. hep. from the 30th of January to this <lb/>day, each contained
                  6 drops. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>Ammoniated water 2 pounds; urine 12 <lb/>pounds, not ſo ſweet; thirſt abated
                  by the <lb/>lime-water. To-day weak; appetite bad; <lb/>ſkin warm; pulſe natural;
                  no ſtool ſince <lb/>the 5th to have the caſtor oil immediately. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>8th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Ammoniated water 3 pounds; urine 7<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula>
                  <lb/>pounds, ſtill ſweet; head confuſed and un- <lb/>eaſy. </p>
                <pb n="52"/>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>In this ſtate he continued until the 11th. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>Ammoniated water 1<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> pound; lime-wa-
                  <lb/>ter 1 pound; urine 8<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> pounds, more
                  like <lb/>natural urine in taſte, ſmell, and appear- <lb/>ance. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>12th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Ammoniated water 2 pounds; no lime- <lb/>water; urine 9 pounds, ſweeter. For
                  ſome <lb/>days has been ſqueamiſh, with little appe- <lb/>tite, and a tendency to
                  diarrhœa. Together <lb/>with the uſual medicines he was ordered to <lb/>take
                  thrice a day, two ounces of infuſion of <lb/>quaſſi, and a little tincture of
                  rhubarb. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>13th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Ammoniated water 2 pounds; urine 9 <lb/>pounds; appetite better. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>16th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Squeamiſh in the morning. Ammoniated <lb/>water 3<formula notation="fraction"
                    >1/2</formula> pounds; urine 9<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> pounds,
                  not ſo <lb/>ſweet. To have 8 drops of the hepatiſed <lb/>ammonia to each pound of
                  water. </p>
              </div>
              <pb n="53"/>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>17th, 18th and 19th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Took daily of the ammoniated water from <lb/>2 to 3 pounds; urine 8 or 9
                  pounds, leſs <lb/>ſweet. Five drops of the hepatiſed ammo- <lb/>nia, mixed with a
                  little water, were ordered <lb/>every two hours. The urine never fell be- <lb/>low
                  8 pounds a-day; the ſweetneſs dimi- <lb/>niſhed, but never ceaſed entirely. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>March 5th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>He was ordered to take 50 drops of the <lb/>hepatiſed ammonia daily. Urine
                    8<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> pounds. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>The next morning he was ſeized with <lb/>griping and purging. The medicine
                  was <lb/>omitted, and he was directed to uſe an <lb/>aſtringent with opium, if the
                  purging or <lb/>pain ſhould become exceſſive: the aſtrin- <lb/>gent, however, was
                  not needed. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>13th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Ammonia hepatiſata 60 drops; drink 4 <lb/>pounds; urine 9 pounds. </p>
                <pb n="54"/>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>In order to aſcertain the effect of volatile <lb/>alkali without hepatic gas,
                  the former me- <lb/>dicine was omitted, and 20 drops of the <lb/>pure water of
                  ammonia were ordered to be <lb/>taken thrice a day in beef tea. It was gra-
                  <lb/>dually increaſed to 120 drops. The urine <lb/>continued from 9 to 9<formula
                    notation="fraction">1/2</formula> pounds, never en- <lb/>tirely free from ſugar,
                  but more ſo than for- <lb/>merly. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>25th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Drink 2<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> pounds. Aq. ammon. puræ
                  <lb/>gt. 120. Frequent vomiting. Urine ra- <lb/>ther increaſed, very ſweet, and of
                  a morbid <lb/>ſmell. </p>
                <p rend="indent space">
                  <lb/>The medicines were omitted, and he was <lb/>directed to take half a grain of
                  opium im- <lb/>mediately, and the ſame quantity when the <lb/>ſickneſs or vomiting
                  returned, until he had <lb/>taken 2 grains. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>26th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>The ſickneſs abated without opium; urine <lb/>9<formula notation="fraction"
                    >1/2</formula> pounds; medicines ſtill omitted. For <pb n="55"/>
                  <lb/>ſome days he uſed no medicine, except a <lb/>quantity of lime-water for
                  drink; and there <lb/>was no change in the urine. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>30th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Drink 3<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> pounds; urine 8 pounds; a
                  feel- <lb/>ing of weakneſs, and laſſitude in the region <lb/>of the kidneys—a
                  ſmall bliſter was applied <lb/>over each kidney. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>31ſt. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Sweated much during the night. Says <lb/>he is leſs troubled than uſual with
                    <hi rend="italic">enureſis</hi>. <lb/>Pulſe about 115. Drink 4 pounds; urine
                  <lb/>9 pounds, of unnatural ſmell, but not ſweet. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>April 3d. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Iſſues by means of cauſtic were ordered <lb/>to be formed over each kidney.
                  He was <lb/>directed to drink ſparingly, and chiefly <lb/>lime-water, and his diet
                  was regulated with <lb/>more care. For it was found, that all along <lb/>he had
                  uſed a great proportion of vegetables <lb/>for food, and had been guilty of
                  irregularity <lb/>alſo in drinking. He was ordered to get no <pb n="56"/>
                  <lb/>vegetables; however he was allowed one roll <lb/>a day; the reſt of his diet
                  conſiſted of ſoup, <lb/>blood-puddings, and butcher meat roaſted, <lb/>or boiled
                  as he choſe. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>5th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Drink 5 pounds (3 of which lime-water); <lb/>urine 8<formula
                    notation="fraction">1/2</formula> pounds, free from ſugar, of a bit- <lb/>teriſh
                  taſte, but unnatural ſmell. Had vio- <lb/>lent head-ach laſt night (from the
                  iſſues he <lb/>thinks), but is eaſy to-day. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>7th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>This morning had nauſea, heart-burn, <lb/>and head-ach, which are now gone.
                  Drink <lb/>4 pounds (1<formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula> of which
                  lime-water); urine <lb/>hardly 8 pounds, almoſt natural. He was <lb/>deſired to
                  take a ſcruple of ipecacuan, and <lb/>after the vomiting a grain of opium. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>8th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>What he vomited yeſterday had a ſweet <lb/>taſte, belly bound; was giddy this
                  morn- <lb/>ing; pulſe 100; drink about 8 pounds (no <lb/>lime water); urine 6
                  pounds, of more na- <pb n="57"/>
                  <lb/>tural ſmell, but leſs ſalt than yeſterday. To <lb/>have immediately 15 grains
                  of jalap, with <lb/>8 of cinnamon. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>9th and 10th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>The jalap did not move him, and he had <lb/>only one coſtive ſtool after an
                  ounce of caſ- <lb/>tor oil. Thirſt much abated; urine from 5 <lb/>to 6 pounds a
                  day, nearly natural. Ordered <lb/>an ounce of caſtor oil, and one of tincture
                  <lb/>of jalap; one half to be taken inſtantly, <lb/>and the other after three
                  hours. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>11th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Three ſtools. Feels himſelf ſtronger, and <lb/>in better ſpirits. Pulſe 80.
                  Drink 3 pounds <lb/>(no lime-water); urine 6<formula notation="fraction"
                    >1/2</formula> pounds, nearly <lb/>natural. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>12th, 13th and 14th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Thirſt abated; urine from 6 to 7 pounds, <lb/>of natural taſte and ſmell,
                  when evaporated <lb/>it yielded no ſugar. Thus he continued free <lb/>from thirſt,
                  though his mouth was parched <lb/>and dry during the night; he gained ſtrength <pb
                    n="58"/>
                  <lb/>and fleſh; his urine never exceeded 6<formula notation="fraction"
                    >1/2</formula> pounds, <lb/>and ſeemed perfectly natural till the </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>30th. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>When it again became ſweet; having <lb/>been ſtrictly queſtioned, he
                  confeſſed that <lb/>he drank a quantity of ſmall beer yeſterday <lb/>afternoon,
                  and we have found that he has <lb/>committed ſeveral other irregularities. </p>
              </div>
              <div type="sub-subsection">
                <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                  <lb/>May 1ſt. </dateline>
                <p rend="indent">
                  <lb/>Urine again natural. This day he left the <lb/>Infirmary, having promiſed to
                  perſiſt in the <lb/>uſe of animal food, and to retum if he ſhould <lb/>relapſe. He
                  is gone to Irvine, about 30 miles <lb/>diſtant, and nothing has been heard of him
                  <lb/>ſince. </p>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Theſe patients were examined daily in <lb/>the Royal Infirmary of Glaſgow, and the
            re- <lb/>ports were dictated before the Students, of <lb/>whom many examined very
            ſcrupulouſly the <lb/>changes of the urine, and all other circum- <lb/>ſtances
            reſpecting a diſeaſe to which their <lb/>attention was ſtrongly attracted both by the
              <pb n="59"/>
            <lb/>novelty of the treatment, and their having <lb/>ſeen a caſe which ended fatally not
            long <lb/>ago. In copying the reports I have omitted <lb/>every circumſtance that ſeemed
            uneſſential, <lb/>and I have abridged the language ſo far as <lb/>I thought conſiſtent
            with perſpicuity. I <lb/>have dropped the Latin form of preſcribing, <lb/>though it gave
            me ſome trouble to expreſs <lb/>the preſcriptions ſhortly in Engliſh (and <lb/>many of
            them look awkward enough), be- <lb/>cauſe I was deſirous of making the caſes in-
            <lb/>telligible to thoſe who do not practiſe phy- <lb/>ſic, as I hope this very
            intereſting inquiry <lb/>will ſoon excite the attention of the public. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>After ſtripping the caſes of every neceſ- <lb/>ſary detail, I ſhall not load them
            with many <lb/>additional remarks. <hi rend="italic">They ſeem to me very ſtrong
              <lb/>confirmations of your doctrine</hi>, in every point, <lb/>except what regards the
            hepatiſed ammonia. <lb/>At firſt perhaps it was not properly prepared, <lb/>after a
            little while, however, it was; and it <lb/>ſeemed to have very little power over the
            <lb/>urine. In one patient (but he was querulous <lb/>and fanciful), it ſeemed to affect
            the head; <pb n="60"/>
            <lb/>in the other, it ſeemed to act like common <lb/>volatile alkali, by producing an
            agreeable <lb/>ſenſation of warmth in the ſtomach. Our <lb/>patients, indeed, were in
            many reſpects dif- <lb/>ferent from yours; and it is very common <lb/>to find the
            operation of medicines ſtrangely <lb/>modified by the varying habits and ſuſcepti-
            <lb/>bilities of patients. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The alum whey (formed by boiling a <lb/>drachm of alum in a pint of milk) ſeemed
            <lb/>to produce conſiderable effect, at leaſt in re- <lb/>ducing the quantity of urine.
            The caſtor <lb/>oil appears to be the moſt uſeful laxative; <lb/>but no medicine was of
            any permanent ad- <lb/>vantage without the <hi rend="italic">aid of animal food</hi>.
            <lb/>This is more powerful than any medicine, <lb/>and very probably this alone,
            properly ma- <lb/>naged, may be found ſufficient for the cure <lb/>in many caſes. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Whether the cure in our two patients be <lb/>complete or not, is a queſtion which I
            ſhall <lb/>not labour to decide by argument. For my <lb/>own part I think they are
            cured, though <pb n="61"/>
            <lb/>they may never perhaps be ſo ſtrong as they <lb/>were, and both may probably
            relapſe; be- <lb/>cauſe, being poor, they are expoſed to the <lb/>double riſk of ſevere
            labour, and improper <lb/>food. Beſides, on many other occaſions, a <lb/>tendency to
            relapſe is not conſidered as a <lb/>proof of imperfect cure. Is an intermittent <lb/>not
            cured, becauſe one who has had it this <lb/>ſpring, will be found very ſubject to it
            next <lb/>ſeaſon, if he ſhall be expoſed to the cauſe <lb/>which commonly produces it?
          </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <dateline rend="italic align-right space">
            <lb/>Glaſgow, May 22, 1797. </dateline>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>I COULD not ſee the gentleman <lb/>who prepared our hepatiſed ammonia till
            <lb/>this day, and from his account I imagine <lb/>your conjecture is well founded. Ours
            was <lb/>very different from your preparation. Some <lb/>of the hepatic gas was procured
            by pouring <lb/>marine acid on ſulphur and iron filings <lb/>merely rubbed together: but
            the greater <lb/>part was obtained from the iron and ſulphur <lb/>melted together in a
            crucible and then pow- <lb/>dered. In both caſes, the ſmell and taſte of <pb n="62"/>
            <lb/>the volatile alkali continued very ſtrong. I <lb/>am ſatisfied, therefore, that no
            inference re- <lb/>ſpecting the real effect or activity of this <lb/>preparation can be
            drawn from our experi- <lb/>ments. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The diabetic patient who died, was not <lb/>opened. She died at home, and was
            buried <lb/>very ſoon, and ſecretly, in order to prevent <lb/>all application. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Since the caſes were tranſmitted to you, <lb/><hi rend="italic">John Roger</hi> has
            returned from <hi rend="italic">Irvine</hi>. He <lb/>continues well, but has a greater
            appetite <lb/>than uſual. His urine is ſalt, and in a na- <lb/>tural quantity. He is
            able to work. </p>
        </div>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>From ******, ********. </head>
          <p rend="italic indent space">
            <lb/><hi rend="sc">Mr. Ashley Cooper</hi>, at <hi rend="sc">St. Thomas's
              <lb/>Hospital</hi>, having mentioned in one of his <lb/>anatomical demonſtrations our
            views of the na- <lb/>ture of diabetic diſeaſe, a young gentleman pre- <lb/>ſent, who
            had a relation in the country with <pb n="63"/>
            <lb/>the complaint, expreſſed a wiſh to be more par- <lb/>ticularly informed, and was
            referred to us. <lb/>He gave a conciſe account of the Patient; and <lb/>it was
            ſuggeſted, as the Patient was ſo far ad- <lb/>vanced in life, an immediate application
            of our <lb/>treatment to its whole extent might not be ad- <lb/>viſeable, the gradual
            adoption of it was there- <lb/>fore recommended. As the Patient, however, <lb/>had been
            a Phyſician of long practice, though <lb/>now retired, and being immediately under the
            <lb/>charge of a reſpectable Phyſician in extenſive <lb/>buſineſs, we requeſted our
            opinion generally <lb/>might be conveyed along with the printed notes <lb/>of Captain
            Meredith's caſe. This was on the <lb/>19th March, 1797. The following account,
            <lb/>written by the Patient himſelf, we received on <lb/>the 18th May, being only a
            period of two <lb/>months. </p>
          <div type="subsection">
            <dateline rend="italic align-right space">
              <lb/>Guy's Hoſpital, 18th May, 1797. </dateline>
            <salute rend="sc indent">
              <lb/>Sir, </salute>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>THE incloſed account is drawn up <lb/>by my friend the patient himſelf. I think
              <lb/>it incumbent on me to return my beſt <lb/>thanks for your kind and ready advice,
              from <pb n="64"/>
              <lb/>which the patient has derived ſo much ad- <lb/>vantage. </p>
            <signed rend="align-center hanging">
              <lb/>I am, Sir, <lb/>yours, &amp;c. <lb/><hi rend="align-right">G. B. </hi>
            </signed>
          </div>
          <div type="subsection">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Dr. Rollo</hi> may make what uſe he <lb/>pleaſes of the under
              deſcribed caſe, provided <lb/>he does not inſert the name of the Patient, <lb/>or that
              of his Phyſician. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>A gentleman far advanced in life, being <lb/>now in his 77th year, and during
              greateſt <lb/>part of that time in pretty uniform good <lb/>health, except ſome
              attacks of Eryſipelas <lb/>about mid-age, and latterly a chronic rheu- <lb/>matiſm in
              the loins, occaſioning more of <lb/>ſtiffneſs than pain. He was accuſtomed to
              <lb/>live after the common mode of ſober per- <lb/>ſons, or if prone to any exceſs, it
              was chiefly <lb/>in the uſe of ſugar. He began about two <lb/>years ago to feel a
              great increaſe of general <lb/>debility, to which was ſoon adjoined an un- <lb/>uſual
              frequency of diſcharge by the bladder, <lb/>amounting on the whole to rather more <pb
                n="65"/>
              <lb/>than one third of the liquor taken in, and <lb/>it was voided with a forcing kind
              of pain, <lb/>both at the commencement and cloſe of <lb/>the emiſſion; made moſtly in
              ſmall quanti- <lb/>ties at a time. Theſe calls became ſoon ſo <lb/>multiplied in the
              night as greatly to diſturb <lb/>natural reſt; and the mouth and fauces grew <lb/>ſo
              dry as to oblige the patient to keep ſmall <lb/>pebbles rolling continually in the
              mouth <lb/>during the day time. The inſpiſſation of <lb/>the ſaliva was ſuch as to
              make it difficult <lb/>to ſpit out, unleſs previouſly diluted. The <lb/>hands ſhook to
              ſuch a degree that rendered <lb/>it dangerous to ſhave, and hardly poſſible to
              <lb/>write legibly, while the lower limbs felt as <lb/>if ſcarce able to ſupport the
              trunk of the <lb/>body; the feet and ancles ſwelled conſider- <lb/>ably; the thirſt
              was intenſe, but there was <lb/>very little ſhew of fever by the pulſe. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Under theſe circumſtances the opinion of <lb/>an eminent Phyſician in the
              neighbourhood <lb/>was aſked, who recommended lime-water, <lb/>earth of alum,
              afterwards pills of catechu, <lb/>alum, and a ſmall portion of vitriolated zinc. <pb
                n="66"/>
              <lb/>By theſe remedies the forcing at the neck <lb/>of the bladder was a good deal
              relieved; <lb/>but the very diſtreſſing dryneſs of the mouth <lb/>and fauces ſtill
              continued, and was by no- <lb/>thing ſo much ſolaced, as by moiſtening <lb/>with milk
              and water. The urine remained, <lb/>as it had always been, well coloured, frothy
              <lb/>upon firſt emiſſion, and favouring ſtrongly <lb/>of that ſweetneſs, to ſcent and
              taſte, charac- <lb/>teriſtic of diabetic urine. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Upon receiving from a young friend, pu- <lb/>pil at the Hoſpitals in Southwark,
              Dr. <lb/>Rollo's notes on a caſe of this ſort, the Pa- <lb/>tient and his Phyſician
              agreed to avail them- <lb/>ſelves of his plan of treatment, with ſome
              <lb/>accommodation to the circumſtances of the <lb/>individual, and they have found
              reaſon to <lb/>be ſatisfied with the adoption of it. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Vegetable articles of diet had been long <lb/>diſcarded; and the uſe of pure
              ſugar, ſince <lb/>the excellent hints in that communication, <lb/>had been entirely
              laid aſide. Rancid fats <lb/>and putreſcent fleſh could not be admitted <pb n="67"/>
              <lb/>even in idea, without inducing nauſea: in- <lb/>ſtead of theſe were employed
              freſh mutton, <lb/>animal gluten, mucilage, &amp;c. At breakfaſt <lb/>he takes milk,
              with ſome cocoa, or choco- <lb/>late; for ſupper, calves feet jelly with milk,
              <lb/>and ſometimes an addition of ſweet al- <lb/>monds. A moderate allowance of wine
              has <lb/>been continued, as indiſpenſibly neceſſary <lb/>for ſupport; but the leaſt
              acid foreign wines <lb/>have been uſed, and a gradual reduction is <lb/>making in this
              hitherto neceſſary indul- <lb/>gence. Of medicines, the ſaturated ſolution <lb/>of
              ſoda, and Schweppe's ſoda water, have <lb/>been only employed: from the laſt there is
              <lb/>every reaſon to believe a ſhare of the amend- <lb/>ment may be attributed. <floatingText>
                <body>
                  <p><hi rend="italic">See Dr. Falconer's <lb/>letter to us, where he points out the
                    mephitic <lb/>alkaline water as likely to be of advantage in <lb/>this
                    diſeaſe.</hi></p>
                </body>
              </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>The urine does not now conſiderably ex- <lb/>ceed the liquid taken in. In the day
              time <lb/>it is voided frequently, but without pain; <lb/>the night calls are
              diminiſhed to one, very <lb/>rarely two occur. Its colour is good, and <pb n="68"/>
              <lb/>its ſweetneſs can hardly be ſaid to be per- <lb/>ceptible. The exceſſive dryneſs
              of the mouth <lb/>and fauces, that depraved the taſte for any <lb/>aliment,
              particularly bread, and in conſe- <lb/>quence impaired the appetite, is nearly re-
              <lb/>moved. The feet and ancles ſwell a lit- <lb/>tle at times, which may be in ſome
              mea- <lb/>ſure owing to the large proportion of the <lb/>νυχθημερον, during which,
              though the days <lb/>are ſo long, yet the patient is unrecumbent <lb/>ſixteen or
              ſeventeen hours at leaſt. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>With this haſty ſketch you will pleaſe <lb/>preſent my beſt compliments and
              thanks to <lb/>Dr. Rollo. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>From <hi rend="sc">Dr. Gerard</hi>, Liverpool. </head>
          <p rend="italic indent space">
            <lb/>The following caſe is that mentioned in Dr. <lb/>Currie's letter to us, and we
            communicate it <lb/>with the greateſt pleaſure to the public, as be- <lb/>ing drawn up
            with the utmoſt accuracy, and <lb/>containing details of procedure of the utmoſt im-
            <lb/>portance towards perfecting our views of the <pb n="69"/>
            <lb/>nature and treatment of the diſeaſe, and of <lb/>confirming them. </p>
          <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
          <div type="subsection">
            <head rend="align-center">
              <lb/>THE CASE. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">John Clarke</hi>, <hi rend="italic">aged</hi> 38, was received
              <lb/>into the <hi rend="sc">Liverpool Infirmary</hi> under <lb/><hi rend="sc"
                >Diabetes</hi>, on the 9th February, 1797. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>He was a ſoldier in Lord Darlington's <lb/>Light Horſe when they were reduced in
              <lb/>February, 1796. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>At that time he was in good health; <lb/>thinks he might then have weighed about
              <lb/>140 pounds in his clothes; he is 5 feet 7<formula notation="fraction"
                >1/2</formula>
              <lb/>inches in height; has dark hair and grey <lb/>eyes. He always enjoyed good
              health, but <lb/>was ſubject to Pyroſis, and accuſtomed to <lb/>perſpire much.
              Happening to reſide near <lb/>the ſea coaſt, he has from a boy been uſed <lb/>to bathe
              frequently during the ſummer <lb/>months, not for any indiſpoſition, but <lb/>merely
              for gratification; ſometimes he went <pb n="70"/>
              <lb/>into the water twice the ſame day, and ſtaid <lb/>in it 10 or 15 minutes; being
              always of a <lb/>coſtive habit, he alſo drank of the water oc- <lb/>caſionally. He
              diſcontinued the practice of <lb/>bathing, however, whilſt the weather ſtill
              <lb/>continued warm, as early, he thinks, as the <lb/>beginning of Auguſt; his
              habitual perſpira- <lb/>tion leſſened afterwards by degrees, and he <lb/>continued in
              good health till about the end <lb/>of November, 1796, when the perſpiration
              <lb/>entirely ceaſed, and the cuticle became un- <lb/>naturally dry, harſh, and rough,
              and is now <lb/>to all appearance dead, and incapable either <lb/>of perſpiration or
              abſorption, or any kind of <lb/>tranſmiſſion. About this time ſome head- <lb/>ach alſo
              came on, and the bowels became <lb/>in general more coſtive, though he was
              <lb/>ſometimes troubled with a lax for a few <lb/>days. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>With the preceding ſymptoms he was af- <lb/>flicted with a moſt diſtreſſing
              thirſt, which <lb/>was not to be ſatisfied. His appetite was <lb/>increaſed, and yet
              he loſt fleſh daily, and <lb/>grew weaker very faſt, particularly in the <pb n="71"/>
              <lb/>thighs and ſmall of the back, attended with <lb/>pain in the region of the
              kidneys. He alſo <lb/>obſerved, that he made much more urine <lb/>than uſual, and that
              the quantity increaſed <lb/>from day to day. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>It ſhould be remembered, that having no <lb/>other means of getting here, he was
              under <lb/>the neceſſity of walking from 5 to 8 miles <lb/>each day, for 3 ſucceſſive
              days, before he <lb/>reached Liverpool; but this was a whole <lb/>day's work, and a
              great fatigue to him. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Conſidering this to be a caſe, that from <lb/>all former experience might almoſt
              be <lb/>deemed incurable, I wiſhed to conſult my <lb/><hi rend="italic"
                >Colleagues</hi>, <hi rend="sc">Dr. Brandreth</hi> and <hi rend="sc">Dr. Cur-
                <lb/>rie</hi>; therefore I only ordered him a doſe of <lb/>caſtor oil, to remove the
              coſtive ſtate of the <lb/>body. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Thoſe gentlemen ſaw him with me on <lb/>the 11th <hi rend="italic">February</hi>.
              At this time <hi rend="italic">Dr. Currie</hi>
              <lb/>had juſt received a publication from <hi rend="italic">Dr. <pb n="72"/>
                <lb/>Rollo, Surgeon General to the Royal Artillery, <lb/>at Woolwich</hi>, of a caſe
              of Diabetes that he <lb/>had treated with ſucceſs; he had not read <lb/>it; but he
              underſtood that much was attri- <lb/>buted to animal diet. </p>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>On this authority our patient was ordered <lb/>to live chiefly on fleſh and milk;
              he was <lb/>alſo directed to uſe the warm bath, and <lb/>with a view of aſcertaining
              whether the <lb/>generally received opinion that abſorption <lb/>takes place in this
              diſeaſe be true, he was <lb/>deſired to be weighed naked, both before <lb/>he went
              into it, and upon coming out. Dr. <lb/>Currie had obſerved in a caſe of a different
              <lb/>nature, that no abſorption took place in the <lb/>warm bath. The pulſe to be
              counted; and <lb/>the heat of the body aſcertained by placing <lb/>a thermometer under
              the tongue, and to <lb/>note the whole down. </p>
            <div type="sub-subsection">
              <dateline rend="italic align-center space">
                <lb/>February 12th. </dateline>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>He went into the bath for the firſt time, <lb/>when <pb n="73"/>
                <list>
                  <item rend="hanging"><lb/>The pulſe was, <lb/>before bathing, 75, after it, 85. </item>
                  <item><lb/>Heat of the body 91, — 95. </item>
                  <item><lb/>Weight of body 112lb. 4oz. — 112lb. 6oz. </item>
                </list>
              </p>
              <p rend="indent space">
                <lb/>He continued in the bath 12 minutes, <lb/>which having been as high as 116
                degrees <lb/>of Fahr. may have acted as a ſtimulus ſuffi- <lb/>cient both to quicken
                the pulſe and increaſe <lb/>the heat. The 2 ounces he appears to have <lb/>gained
                after having bathed, is not to be at- <lb/>tributed to abſorption, but to water
                remain- <lb/>ing amongſt the hair, and adhering to the <lb/>body; for he had
                unintentionally been over <lb/>the head, and the body had not been wiped <lb/>dry.
              </p>
            </div>
            <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="60"/>
          </div>
          <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="1"/>
        </div>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="152"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
