<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Jenner: An Inquiry Into the Causes and Effects of the Variolæ
          Vaccinæ</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Edward Jenner</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">An inquiry into the causes and effects of the variolæ vaccinæ, a
              disease discovered in some of the western counties of England, particularly
              Gloucestershire, and known by the name of the cow pox. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T54053</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T54053"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed, for the author, by Sampson Low, No. 7, Berwick Street,
                  Soho: and sold by Law, Ave-Maria Lane; and Murray and Highley, Fleet Street, 1798.
                </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1798</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">4⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="4"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="75"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW109178111</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Book on a specific topic: method"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <pb n=""/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE deviation of Man from the ſtate in which <lb/>he was
        originally placed by Nature ſeems to have <lb/>proved to him a prolific ſource of diſeaſes.
        From <lb/>the love of ſplendour, from the indulgences of <lb/>luxury, and from his fondneſs
        for amuſement, he <lb/>has familiariſed himſelf with a great number of <lb/>animals, which
        may not originally have been in- <lb/>tended for his aſſociates. </p>
      <pb n="2"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The Wolf, diſarmed of ferocity, is now pillowed <lb/>in the lady's lap <note
          place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* The late Mr.John Hunter proved, by experiments,
          that the Dog is the Wolf in a degenerated ſtate. </note>. The Cat, the little Tiger of our
        <lb/>iſland, whoſe natural home is the foreſt, is equally <lb/>domeſticated and careſſed.
        The Cow, the Hog, the <lb/>Sheep, and the Horſe, are all, for a variety of <lb/>purpoſes,
        brought under his care and dominion. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>There is a diſeaſe to which the Horſe, from his <lb/>ſtate of domeſtication, is
        frequently ſubject. The <lb/>Farriers have called it <hi rend="italic">the Greaſe</hi>. It
        is an inflam- <lb/>mation and ſwelling in the heel, from which iſſues <lb/>matter poſſeſſing
        properties of a very peculiar kind, <lb/>which ſeems capable of generating a diſeaſe in the
        <lb/>Human body (after it has undergone the modification <lb/>which I ſhall preſently ſpeak
        of), which bears ſo ſtrong <lb/>a reſemblance to the Small Pox that I think it highly
        <lb/>probable it may be the ſource of the diſeaſe. </p>
      <pb n="3"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>In this Dairy Country a great number of Cows <lb/>are kept, and the office of milking
        is performed <lb/>indiſcriminately by Men and Maid Servants. One <lb/>of the former having
        been appointed to apply <lb/>dreſſings to the heels of a Horſe affected with <hi
          rend="italic">the <lb/>Greaſe</hi>, and not paying due attention to cleanli- <lb/>neſs,
        incautiouſly bears his part in milking the Cows, <lb/>with ſome particles of the infectious
        matter ad- <lb/>hering to his fingers. When this is the caſe, it <lb/>commonly happens that
        a diſeaſe is communicated <lb/>to the cows, and from the Cows to the Dairy-maids, <lb/>which
        ſpreads through the farm until the moſt of the <lb/>cattle and domeſtics feel its unpleaſant
        conſe- <lb/>quences. This diſeaſe has obtained the name of <lb/>the Cow Pox. It appears on
        the nipples of the <lb/>Cows in the form of irregular puſtules. At their <lb/>firſt
        appearance they are commonly of a paliſh blue, <lb/>or rather of a colour ſomewhat
        approaching to <lb/>livid, and are ſurrounded by an eryſipelatous in- <pb n="4"/>
        <lb/>flammation. Theſe puſtules, unleſs a timely re- <lb/>medy be applied, frequently
        degenerate into pha- <lb/>gedenic ulcers, which prove extremely trouble- <lb/>ſome <note
          place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">They who attend ſick cattle in this country find a
          ſpeedy remedy for ſtopping <lb/>the progreſs of this complaint in thoſe applications which
          act chemically upon <lb/>the morbid matter, ſuch as the ſolutions of the Vitriolum Zinci,
          the Vitriolum <lb/>Cupri, &amp;c. </note>. The animals become indiſpoſed, and the
        <lb/>ſecretion of milk is much leſſened. Inflamed ſpots <lb/>now begin to appear on
        different parts of the hands <lb/>of the domeſtics employed in milking, and ſome- <lb/>times
        on the wriſts, which quickly run on to ſup- <lb/>puration, firſt aſſuming the appearance of
        the ſmall <lb/>veſications produced by a burn. Moſt commonly <lb/>they appear about the
        joints of the fingers, and <lb/>at their extremities; but whatever parts are af- <lb/>ected,
        if the ſituation will admit, theſe ſuperficial <lb/>ſuppurations put on a circular form,
        with their <lb/>edges more elevated than their centre, and of a <pb n="5"/>
        <lb/>colour diſtantly approaching to blue. Abſorption <lb/>takes place, and tumours appear
        in each axilla. <lb/>The ſyſtem becomes affected - the pulſe is quick- <lb/>ened; and
        ſhiverings, with general laſſitude and <lb/>pains about the loins and limbs, with vomiting,
        <lb/>come on. The head is painful, and the patient is <lb/>now and then even affected with
        delirium. Theſe <lb/>ſymptoms, varying in their degrees of violence, <lb/>generally continue
        from one day to three or four, <lb/>leaving ulcerated ſores about the hands, which, from
        <lb/>the ſenſibility of the parts, are very troubleſome, <lb/>and commonly heal ſlowly,
        frequently becoming <lb/>phagedenic, like thoſe from whence they ſprung. <lb/>The lips,
        noſtrils, eyelids, and other parts of the <lb/>body are ſometimes affected with ſores; but
        theſe <lb/>evidently ariſe from their being heedleſſly rubbed <lb/>or ſcratched with the
        patient's infected fingers. <lb/>No eruptions on the ſkin have followed the decline <lb/>of
        the feveriſh ſymptoms in any inſtance that has <pb n="6"/>
        <lb/>come under my inſpection, one only excepted, and <lb/>in this caſe a very few appeared
        on the arms: they <lb/>were very minute, of a vivid red colour, and ſoon <lb/>died away
        without advancing to maturation; ſo that <lb/>I cannot determine whether they had any
        connection <lb/>with the preceding ſymptoms. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Thus the diſeaſe makes its progreſs from the <lb/>Horſe to the nipple of the Cow, and
        from the Cow <lb/>to the Human Subject. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Morbid matter of various kinds, when abſorbed <lb/>into the ſyſtem, may produce effects
        in ſome degree <lb/>ſimilar; but what renders the Cow Pox virus ſo <lb/>extremely ſingular
        is that the perſon who has been <lb/>thus affected is forever after ſecure from the infec-
        <lb/>tion of the Small Pox; neither expoſure to the <lb/>variolous effluvia, nor the
        inſertion of the matter <lb/>into the ſkin, producing this diſtemper. </p>
      <pb n="7"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>In ſupport of ſo extraordinary a fact, I ſhall lay before my reader a great number of
        inſtances <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">It is neceſſary to obſerve, that
          puſtulous ſores frequently appear ſpontaneouſly <lb/>on the nipples of Cows, and inſtances
          have occured, though very rarely, of the <lb/>hands of the ſervants employed in milking
          being affected with ſores in conſequence, <lb/>and even of their feeling an indiſpoſition
          from that contagion which con- <lb/>ſtitutes the true Cow Pox. They are always free from
          the bluiſh or livid tint ſo <lb/>conſpicious in the pultules in that diſeaſe. No
          erysſipelas attends them, nor do they <lb/>ſhew any phagedenic diſpoſition as in the other
          caſe, but quickly terminate in a ſcab <lb/>without creating any apparent diſorder in the
          Cow. This complaint appears at <lb/>various ſeaſons of the year, but moſt commonly in the
          Spring, when the Cows <lb/>are firſt taken from their winter food and fed with graſs. It
          is very apt to appear <lb/>alſo when they are ſuckling their young. But this diſeaſe it is
          incapable of producing <lb/>any ſpecific effects on the human Conſtitution. However, it is
          of the greateſt con- <lb/>ſequence to point it out here, left the want of diſcrimination
          ſhould occaſion an idea <lb/>of ſecurity from the infection of the Small Pox, which might
          prove deluſive. </note>. </p>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center space">CASE I. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>JOSEPH MERRRET, now an Under Gardener to the <lb/>Earl of Berkeley, lived as a
            Servant with a Farmer near <lb/>this place in the year 1770, and occaſionally aſſiſted
            in <lb/>milking his maſter's cows. Several horſes belonging to the <lb/>farm began to
            have ſore heels, which Merret frequently <lb/>attended. The cows ſoon became affected
            with the Cow <lb/>Pox, and ſoon after ſeveral ſores appeared on his hands.
            <lb/>Swellings and ſtiffneſs in each axilla followed, and he was <lb/>ſo much indiſpoſed
            for ſeveral days as to be incapable of <lb/>purſuing his ordinary employment. Previouſly
            to the ap- <lb/>pearance of the diſtemper among the cows there was no <lb/>freſh cow
            brought into the farm, nor any ſervant employed <lb/>who was affected with the Cow Pox. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>In April, 1795, a general inoculation taking place here, <lb/>Merret was inoculated
            with his family; ſo that a period of <lb/>twenty-five years had elapſed from his having
            the Cow Pox <pb n="10"/>
            <lb/>to this time. However, though the variolous matter was <lb/>repeatedly inſerted
            into his arm, I found it impracticable to <lb/>infect him with it; an effloreſcence
            only, taking on an <lb/>eryſipelatous look about the centre, appearing on the ſkin
            <lb/>near the punctured parts. During the whole time that his <lb/>family had the
            ſmallpox, one of whom had it very full, <lb/>he remained in the houſe with them, but
            received no in- <lb/>jury from expoſure to the contagion. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>It is neceſſary to obſerve that the utmoſt care was taken <lb/>to aſcertain, with
            the moſt ſcrupulous preciſion, that no one <lb/>whoſe caſe is here adduced had gone
            through the Small Pox <lb/>previous to theſe attempts to produce that diſeaſe. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Had theſe experiments been conducted in a large city, or <lb/>in a populous
            neighbourhood, ſome doubts might have <lb/>been entertained; but here, where population
            is thin, and <lb/>where ſuch an event as a perſon's having had the Small Pox <lb/>is
            always faithfully recorded, no riſk of inaccuracy in this <lb/>particular can ariſe.
          </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center space">CASE II. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>SARAH PORTLOCK, of this place, was infected with <lb/>the Cow Pox when a Servant at
            a Farmer's in the neigh <lb/>bourhood, twenty-ſeven years ago <note place="bottom" n="*"
              rend="size(0.5)">* I have purpoſely ſelected ſeveral caſes inwhich the diſeaſe had
              apperearad <lb/>at a very diſtant period previous to the experiments made with
              variolous <lb/>matter, to ſhew that the change produced in the conſtitution is not
              affected by <lb/>time. </note>. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>In the year 1792, conceiving herſelf, from this circum- <lb/>ſtance, ſecure from
            the infection of the Small Pox, ſhe <lb/>nurſed one of her own children who had
            accidentally <lb/>caught the diſeaſe, but no indiſpoſition enſued. - During <lb/>the
            time ſhe remained in the infected room, variolous <lb/>matter was inſerted into both her
            arms, but without any <lb/>further effect than in the preceding caſe. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <pb n="12"/>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center space">CASE III. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>JOHN PHILLIPS, a Tradeſman of this town, had the <lb/>Cow Pox at ſo early a period
            as nine years of age. At the <lb/>age of ſixty-two I inoculated him, and was very
            careful in <lb/>ſelecting matter in its moſt active ſtate. It was taken from <lb/>the
            arm of a boy juſt before the commencement of the <lb/>eruptive fever, and inſtantly
            inſerted. It very ſpeedily <lb/>produced a ſting-like feel in the part. An effloreſcence
            <lb/>appeared, which on the fourth day was rather extenſive, <lb/>and ſome degree of
            pain and ſtiffneſs were felt about the <lb/>ſhoulder: but on the fifth day theſe
            ſymptoms began to <lb/>diſappear, and in a day or two after went entirely off,
            <lb/>without producing any effect on the ſyſtem. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <pb n="13"/>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center space">CASE IV. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>MARY BARGE, of Woodford, in this pariſh, was ino- <lb/>culated with variolous
            matter in the year 1791. An efflo- <lb/>reſcence of a paliſh red colour ſoon appeared
            about the <lb/>parts where the matter was inſerted, and ſpread itſelf rather
            <lb/>extenſively, but died away in a few days without producing <lb/>any variolous
            ſymptoms <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* It is remarkable that variolous
              matter, when the ſyſtem is diſpoſed to reject <lb/>it, ſhould excite inflammation on
              the part to which it is applied more ſpeedily <lb/>than when it produces the Small
              Pox. Indeed it becomes almoſt a citerion by <lb/>which we can determine whether the
              infection will be received or not. It ſeems <lb/>as if a change, which endures though
              life, had been produced in the action, or <lb/>diſpoſition to action, in the veſſels
              of the ſkin; and it is remarkable too, that <lb/>whether this change has been effected
              by the Small Pox, or Cow Pox, that <lb/>the diſpoſition to ſudden cuticular
              inflammation is the ſame on the application of <lb/>variolous matter. </note>. She has
            ſince been repeatedly <lb/>employed as a nurſe to Small-pox patients, without expe-
            <lb/>riencing any ill conſequences. This woman had the Cow <lb/>Pox when ſhe lived in
            the ſervice of a farmer in this pariſh <lb/>thirty-one years before. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <pb n="14"/>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center space">CASE V. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>MRS. H— , a reſpectable gentlewoman of this town, <lb/>had the Cow Pox when very
            young. She received the <lb/>infection in rather an uncommon manner: it was given by
            <lb/>means of her handling ſome of the ſame utenſils <note place="bottom" n="*"
              rend="size(0.5)">* When the Cow Pox has prevailed in the diary, it has often been com-
              <lb/>municated to thoſe who have not milked the cows, by the handle of the milk
              <lb/>pail. </note> which <lb/>were in uſe among the ſervants of the family, who had
            the <lb/>diſeaſe from milking infected cows. Her hands had many <lb/>of the Cow Pox
            ſores upon them, and they were commu- <lb/>nicated to her noſe, which became inflamed
            and very much <lb/>ſwollen. ſoon after this event Mrs. H— was expoſed to <lb/>the
            contagion of the ſmallpox, where it was ſcarcely <lb/>poſſible for her to have eſcaped,
            had ſhe been ſuſceptible of <lb/>it, as ſhe regularly attended a relative who had the
            diſeaſe <lb/>in ſo violent a degree that it proved fatal to him. </p>
          <pb n="15"/>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>In the year 1778 the Small Pox prevailed very much at <lb/>Berkeley, and Mrs. H—
            not feeling perfectly ſatisfied <lb/>reſpecting her ſafety (no indiſpoſition having
            followed her <lb/>expoſure to the Small Pox), I inoculated her with active
            <lb/>variolous matter. The ſame appearance followed as in the <lb/>preceding caſes —
            effloreſcence on the arm without any <lb/>effect on the conſtitution. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center space">CASE VI. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>IT is a fact ſo well known among our Dairy Farmers, <lb/>that thoſe who have had
            the Small Pox either eſcape the <lb/>Cow- Pox or are diſpoſed to have it ſlightly, that
            as ſoon as <lb/>the complaint ſhews itſelf among the cattle, aſſiſtants are
            <lb/>procured, if poſſible, who are thus rendered leſs ſuſceptible <lb/>of it, otherwiſe
            the buſineſs of the farm could ſcarcely go <lb/>forward. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>In the month of May, 1796, the Cow Pox broke out at <lb/>Mr. Baker's, a farmer who
            lives near this place. The <pb n="16"/>
            <lb/>diſeaſe was communicated by means of a cow which was <lb/>purchaſed in an infected
            ſtate at a neighbouring fair, and <lb/>not one of the farmer's cows (conſiſting of
            thirty) which <lb/>were at that time milked eſcaped the contagion. The <lb/>family
            conſiſted of a man ſervant, two dairymaids, and a <lb/>ſervant boy, who, with the farmer
            himſelf, were twice a <lb/>day employed in milking the cattle. The whole of this
            <lb/>family, except Sarah Wynne, one of the dairymaids, had <lb/>gone through the Small
            Pox. The conſequence was that <lb/>the farmer and the ſervant boy eſcaped the infection
            of the <lb/>Cow Pox entirely, and the ſervant man and one of the maid <lb/>ſervants had
            each of them nothing more than a ſore on one <lb/>of their fingers, which produced no
            diſorder in the ſyſtem. <lb/>But the other dairymaid, ſarah Wynne, who never had
            <lb/>the Small Pox, did not eſcape in ſo eaſy a manner. She <lb/>caught the complaint
            from the cows, and was affected with <lb/>the ſymptoms deſcribed in page 5th page in ſo
            violent a <lb/>degree that ſhe was confined to her bed, and rendered <lb/>incapable for
            ſeveral days of purſuing her ordinary voca- <lb/>tions in the farm. </p>
          <pb n="17"/>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>March 28th, 1797, I inoculated this girl and carefully <lb/>rubbed the variolous
            matter into two ſlight inciſions made <lb/>upon the left arm. A little inflammation
            appeared in the <lb/>uſual manner around the parts where the matter was in- <lb/>ſerted,
            but ſo early as the fifth day it vaniſhed entirely <lb/>without producing any effect on
            the ſyſtem. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center space">CASE VII. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>ALTHOUGH the preceding hiſtory pretty clearly <lb/>evinces that the conſtitution is
            far leſs ſuſceptible of the <lb/>contagion of the Cow Pox after it has felt that of the
            Small <lb/>Pox, and although in general, as I have obſerved, they who <lb/>have had the
            Small Pox, and are employed in milking cows <lb/>which are infected with the Cow Pox,
            either eſcape the <lb/>diſorder, or have ſores on the hands without feeling any
            <lb/>general indiſpoſition, yet the animal economy is ſubject to <lb/>ſome variation in
            this reſpect, which the following rela- <lb/>tion will point out: </p>
          <pb n="18"/>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>In the ſummer of the year 1796 the Cow Pox appeared at <lb/>the farm of Mr.
            Andrews, a conſiderable dairy adjoining <lb/>to the town of Berkeley. It was
            communicated, as in the <lb/>preceding inſtance, by an infected cow purchaſed at a fair
            <lb/>in the neighbourhood. The family conſiſted of the farmer, <lb/>his wife, two ſons,
            a man and a maid ſervant; all of whom, <lb/>except the farmer (who was fearful of the
            conſequences), <lb/>bore a part in milking the cows. The whole of them, ex- <lb/>cluſive
            of the man ſervant, had regularly gone through the <lb/>Small Pox; but in this caſe no
            one who milked the cows <lb/>eſcaped the contagion. All of them had ſores upon their
            <lb/>hands, and ſome degree of general indiſpoſition, preceded <lb/>by pains and tumours
            in the axillæ: but there was no com- <lb/>pariſon in the ſeverity of the diſeaſe as it
            was felt by the <lb/>ſervant man, who had eſcaped the Small Pox, and by thoſe <lb/>of
            the family who had not, for, while he was confined to <lb/>his bed, they were able,
            without much inconvenience, to <lb/>follow their ordinary buſineſs. </p>
          <pb n="19"/>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>February the 13th, 1797, I availed myſelf of opportunity <lb/>of inoculating
            William Rodway, the ſervant man above al- <lb/>luded to. Variolous matter was inſerted
            into both his arms; <lb/>in the right by means of ſuperficial inciſions, and into the
            left <lb/>by ſlight punctures into the cutis. Both were perceptibly <lb/>inflamed on the
            third day. After this the inflammation <lb/>about the punctures ſoon died away, but a
            ſmall appearance <lb/>of eryſipelas was manifeſt about the edges of the inciſions
            <lb/>till the eighth day, when a little uneaſineſs was felt for the <lb/>ſpace of half
            an hour in the right axilla. The inflamma- <lb/>tion then haſtily diſappeared without
            producing the moſt <lb/>diſtant mark of affection of the ſyſtem. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <pb n="20"/>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center space">CASE VIII. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>ELIZABETH WYNNE, aged fifty-ſeven, lived as a <lb/>ſervant with a neighbouring
            farmer thirty-eight years ago. <lb/>She was then a dairymaid, and the Cow Pox broke out
            <lb/>among the cows. She caught the diſeaſe with the reſt of <lb/>the family, but,
            compared with them, had it in a very <lb/>ſlight degree, one very ſmall ſore only
            breaking out on the <lb/>little finger of her left hand, and ſcarcely any perceptible
            <lb/>indiſpoſition following it. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>As the malady had ſhewn itſelf in ſo ſlight a manner, <lb/>and as it had taken
            place at ſo diſtant a period of her life, I <lb/>was happy with the opportunity of
            trying the effects of <lb/>variolous matter upon her conſtitution, and on the 28th of
            <lb/>March, 1797, I inoculated her by making two ſuperficial <lb/>inciſions on the left
            arm, on which the matter was cautiouſly <lb/>rubbed. A little effloreſcence ſoon
            appeared, and a tin- <pb n="21"/>
            <lb/>gling ſenſation was felt about the parts where the matter <lb/>was inſerted until
            the third day, when both began to <lb/>ſubſide, and ſo early as the fifth day it was
            evident that no <lb/>indiſpoſition would follow. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center space">CASE IX. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>ALTHOUGH the Cow Pox ſhields the conſtitution from <lb/>the Small Pox, and the
            ſmall Pox proves a protection <lb/>againſt its own future poiſon, yet it appears that
            the human <lb/>body is again and again ſuſceptible of the infectious matter <lb/>of the
            Cow Pox, as the following hiſtory will demonſtrate: </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>William Smith, of Pyrton in this pariſh, contracted this <lb/>diſeaſe when he lived
            with a neighbouring farmer in the <lb/>year 1780. One of the horſes belonging to the
            farm had <lb/>ſore heels, and it fell to his lot to attend him. By theſe <lb/>means the
            infection was carried to the cows, and from the <lb/>cows it was communicated to Smith.
            On one of his hands <pb n="22"/>
            <lb/>were ſeveral ulcerated ſores, and he was affected with ſuch <lb/>ſymptoms as have
            been before deſcribed. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>In the year 1791 the Cow Pox broke out at another farm <lb/>where he then lived as
            a ſervant, and he became affected <lb/>with it a ſecond time; and in the year 1794 he
            was ſo <lb/>unfortunate as to catch it again. The diſeaſe was equally <lb/>as ſevere the
            ſecond and third time as it was on the firſt <note place="bottom" n="" rend="size(0.5)"
              >This is not caſe in general — a ſecond attack is commonly very ſlight, <lb/>and ſo, I
              am informed, it is among the cows. </note>. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>In the ſpring of the year 1795 he was twice inoculated, <lb/>but no affection of
            the ſyſtem could be produced from the <lb/>variolous matter; and he has ſince aſſociated
            with thoſe who <lb/>had the Small Pox in its moſt contagious ſtate without <lb/>feeling
            any effect from it. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <pb n="23"/>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center space">CASE X. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>SIMON NICHOLS lived as a ſervant with Mr. Brom- <lb/>edge, a gentleman who reſides
            on his own farm in this <lb/>pariſh, in the year 1782. He was employed in applying
            <lb/>dreſſings to the ſore heels of one of his maſter's horſes, and <lb/>at the ſame
            time aſſiſted in milking the cows. The cows <lb/>became affected in conſequence, but the
            diſeaſe did not <lb/>ſhew itſelf on their nipples till ſeveral weeks after he had
            <lb/>begun to dreſs the horſe. He quitted Mr. Bromedge's <lb/>ſervice, and went to
            another farm without any ſores upon <lb/>him; but here his hands ſoon began to be
            affected in the <lb/>common way, and he was much indiſpoſed with the uſual
            <lb/>ſymptoms. Concealing the nature of the malady from Mr. <lb/>Cole, his new maſter,
            and being there alſo employed in <lb/>milking, the Cow Pox was communicated to the cows. </p>
          <pb n="24"/>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Some years afterward Nichols was employed in a farm <lb/>where the Small pox broke
            out, when I inoculated him <lb/>with ſeveral other patients, with whom he continued
            <lb/>during the whole time of their confinement. His arm <lb/>inflamed, but neither the
            inflammation nor his aſſociating <lb/>with the inoculated family produced the leaſt
            effect upon <lb/>his conſtitution. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center space">CASE XI. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>WILLIAM STINCHCOMB was a fellow ſervant with <lb/>Nichols at Mr. Bromedge's farm at
            the time the cattle had <lb/>the Cow Pox, and he was unfortunately infected by them.
            <lb/>His left hand was very ſeverely affected with ſeveral cor- <lb/>roding ulcers, and
            a tumour of conſiderable ſize appeared <lb/>in the axilla of that ſide. His right hand
            had only one <lb/>ſmall tumour upon it, and no tumour diſcovered itſelf in the
            <lb/>correſponding axilla. </p>
          <pb n="25"/>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>In the year 1792 Stinchcomb was inoculated with vario- <lb/>lous matter, but no
            conſequences enſued beyond a little <lb/>inflammation in the arm for a few days. A large
            party <lb/>were inoculated at the ſame time, ſome of whom had the <lb/>diſeaſe in a more
            violent degree than is commonly ſeen <lb/>from inoculation. He purpoſely aſſociated with
            them, but <lb/>could not receive the Small Pox. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>During the ſickening of ſome of his companions their <lb/>ſymptoms ſo ſtrongly
            recalled to his mind his own ſtate <lb/>when ſickening with the Cow Pox that he very
            pertinently <lb/>remarked their ſtriking ſimilarity. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <pb n="26"/>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center space">CASE XII. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>THE paupers of the village of Tortworth, in this county, <lb/>were inoculated by
            Mr. Henry Jenner, Surgeon, of Ber- <lb/>keley, in the year 1795. Among them, eight
            patients pre- <lb/>ſented themſelves who had at different periods of their lives
            <lb/>had the Cow Pox. One of them, Heſter Walkley, I attended <lb/>with that diſeaſe
            when ſhe lived in the ſervice of a farmer <lb/>in the ſame village in the year 1782; but
            neither this <lb/>woman, nor any other of the patients who had gone <lb/>through the Cow
            Pox, received the variolous infection <lb/>either from the arm or from mixing in the
            ſociety of the <lb/>other patients who were inoculated at the ſame time. This <lb/>ſtate
            of ſecurity proved a fortunate circumſtance, as many <lb/>of the poor women were at the
            ſame time in a ſtate of <lb/>pregnancy. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <pb n="27"/>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center space">CASE XIII. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>One inſtance has occurred to me of the ſyſtem being <lb/>affected from the matter
            iſſuing from the heels of horſes, <lb/>and of its remaining afterwards unſuſceptible of
            the vario- <lb/>lous contagion; another, where the Small Pox appeared <lb/>obſcurely;
            and a third, in which its complete exiſtence was <lb/>poſitively aſcertained. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Firſt, THOMAS PEARCE, is the ſon of a Smith and <lb/>Farrier near to this place. He
            never had the Cow Pox; <lb/>but, in conſequence of dreſſing horſes with ſore heels at
            <lb/>his father's, when a lad, he had ſores on his fingers which <lb/>ſuppurated, and
            which occaſioned a pretty ſevere indiſpo- <lb/>ſition. Six years afterwards I inſerted
            variolous matter into <lb/>his arm repeatedly, without being able to produce any thing
            <lb/>more than ſlight inflammation, which appeared very ſoon <pb n="28"/>
            <lb/>after the matter was applied, and afterwards I expoſed him <lb/>to the contagion of
            the Small Pox with as little effect <note place="bottom" n="" rend="size(0.5)"> It is
              remarkable fact, and well known to many, that we are frequently <lb/>foiled in our
              endeavours to communicate the Small Pox by inoculation to <lb/>blackſmiths, who in the
              country are farriers. they often, as in the above <lb/>inſtance, either reſiſt the
              contagnion entirely, or have the diſeaſe anomalouſly. <lb/>Shall we not be able now to
              account for this on rational principle? </note>. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center space">CASE XIV. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Secondly, Mr. JAMES COLE, a Farmer in this pariſh, <lb/>had a diſeaſe from the ſame
            ſource as related in the pre- <lb/>ceding caſe, and ſome years after was inoculated with
            <lb/>variolous matter. He had a little pain in the axilla, and <lb/>felt a ſlight
            indiſpoſition for three or four hours. A few <lb/>eruptions ſhewed themſelves on the
            forehead, but they very <lb/>ſoon diſappeared without advancing to maturation. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <pb n="29"/>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center space">CASE XIV. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Although in the former inſtances the ſyſtem ſeemed <lb/>to be ſecured, or nearly
            ſo, from variolous infection, by the <lb/>abſorption of matter from the ſores produced
            by the diſeaſed <lb/>heels of horſes, yet the following caſe deciſively proves <lb/>that
            this cannot be entirely relied upon until a diſeaſe <lb/>has been generated by the
            morbid matter from the horſe on <lb/>the nipple of the cow, and paſſed through that
            medium to <lb/>the human ſubject. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Mr. ABRAHAM RIDDIFORD, a farmer at Stone in <lb/>this pariſh, in conſequence of
            dreſſing a mare that had ſore <lb/>heels, was affected with very painful ſores in both
            his <lb/>hands, tumours in each axilla, and ſevere and general <lb/>indiſpoſition. A
            ſurgeon in the neighbourhood attended <lb/>him, who knowing the ſimilarity between the
            appearance <lb/>of the ſores upon his hands and thoſe produced by the <pb n="30"/>
            <lb/>Cow Pox, and being acquainted alſo with the effects of <lb/>that diſeaſe on the
            human conſtitution, aſſured him that he <lb/>never need to fear the infection of the
            Small Pox; but this <lb/>aſſertion proved fallacious, for, on being expoſed to the
            <lb/>infection upwards of twenty years afterwards, he caught <lb/>the diſeaſe, which
            took its regular courſe in a very mild <lb/>way. There certainly was a difference
            perceptible, although <lb/>it is not eaſy to deſcribe it, in the general appearance of
            the <lb/>puſtules from that which we commonly ſee. Other prac- <lb/>titioners who
            viſited the patient at my requeſt agreed with <lb/>me in this point, though there was no
            room left for ſuſpicion <lb/>as to the reality of the diſeaſe, as I inoculated ſome of
            his <lb/>family from the puſtules, who had the Small Pox, with its <lb/>uſual
            appearances, in conſequence. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <pb n="31"/>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center space">CASE XVI. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>SARAH NELMES, a dairymaid at a farmer's near this <lb/>place, was infected with the
            Cow Pox from her maſter's <lb/>cows in May, 1796. She received the infection on a part
            <lb/>of her hand which had been previouſly in a ſlight degree <lb/>injured by a ſcratch
            from a thorn. A large puſtulous ſore <lb/>and the uſual ſymptoms accompanying the
            diſeaſe were <lb/>produced in conſequence. The puſtule was ſo expreſſive <lb/>of the
            true character of the Cow Pox, as it commonly <lb/>appears upon the hand, that I have
            given a repreſentation <lb/>of it in the annexed plate. The two ſmall puſtules on the
            <lb/>wriſts aroſe alſo from the application of the virus to ſome <lb/>minute abraſions
            of the cuticle, but the livid tint, if they <lb/>ever had any, was not conſpicuous at
            the time I ſaw the <lb/>patient. The puſtule on the forefinger ſhews the diſeaſe in
            <lb/>an earlier ſtage. It did not actually appear on the hand of <pb n="32"/>
            <lb/>this young woman, but was taken from that of another, <lb/>and is annexed for the
            purpoſe of repreſenting the malady <lb/>after it has newly appeared. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center space">CASE XVII. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The more accurately to obſerve the progreſs of the <lb/>infection I ſelected a
            healthy boy, about eight years old, <lb/>for the purpoſe of inoculation for the Cow Pox.
            The <lb/>matter was taken from a ſore on the hand of a dairymaid <note place="bottom"
              n="" rend="size(0.5)">* From the ſore on the hand of Sarah Nelmes. — See the preceding
              caſe and <lb/>the plate. </note>, <lb/>who was infected by her maſter's cows, and it
            was inſerted, <lb/>on the 14th of May, 1796, into the arm of the boy by <lb/>means of
            two ſuperficial inciſions, barely penetrating the <lb/>cutis, each about half an inch
            long. </p>
          <pb n="33"/>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>On the ſeventh day he complained of uneaſineſs in the <lb/>axilla, and on the ninth
            he became a little chilly, loſt his <lb/>appetite, and had a ſlight head-ach. During the
            whole of <lb/>this day he was perceptibly indiſpoſed, and ſpent the night <lb/>with ſome
            degree of reſtleſſneſs, but on the day following <lb/>he was perfectly well. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>The appearance of the inciſions in their progreſs to a <lb/>ſtate of maturation
            were much the ſame as when pro- <lb/>duced in a ſimilar manner by variolous matter. The
            <lb/>only difference which I perceived was, in the ſtate of the <lb/>limpid fluid
            ariſing from the action of the virus, which <lb/>aſſumed rather a darker hue, and in
            that of the effloreſcence <lb/>ſpreading round the inciſions, which had more of an
            eryſi- <lb/>pelatous look than we commonly perceive when variolous <lb/>matter has been
            made uſe of in the ſame manner; but the <lb/>whole died away (leaving on the inoculated
            parts ſcabs and <lb/>ſubſequent eſchars) without giving me or my patient the <lb/>leaſt
            trouble. </p>
          <pb n="34"/>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>In order to aſcertain whether the boy, after feeling ſo <lb/>ſlight an affection of
            the ſyſtem from the Cow-pox virus, <lb/>was ſecure from the contagion of the Small-pox,
            he was <lb/>inoculated the 1ſt of July following with variolous matter, <lb/>immediately
            taken from a puſtule. ſeveral ſlight punctures <lb/>and inciſions were made on both his
            arms, and the matter <lb/>was carefully inſerted, but no diſeaſe followed. The ſame
            <lb/>appearances were obſervable on the arms as we commonly <lb/>ſee when a patient has
            had variolous matter applied, after <lb/>having either the Cow-pox or the Small-pox.
            Several months <lb/>afterwards he was again inoculated with variolous matter, <lb/>but
            no ſenſible effect was produced on the conſtitution. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Here my reſearches were interrupted till the ſpring of the <lb/>year 1798, when,
            from the wetneſs of the early part of the <lb/>ſeaſon, many of the farmerſ' horſes in
            this neighbourhood <lb/>were affected with ſore heels, in conſequence of which the
            <lb/>Cow-pox broke out among ſeveral of our dairies, which <lb/>afforded me an
            opportunity of making further obſervations <lb/>upon this curious diſeaſe. </p>
          <pb n="35"/>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>A mare, the property of a perſon who keeps a dairy in <lb/>a neighbouring pariſh,
            began to have ſore heels the latter <lb/>end of the month of February, 1798, which were
            occaſi- <lb/>onally waſhed by the ſervant men of the farm, Thomas <lb/>Virgoe, William
            Wherret, and William Haynes, who in <lb/>conſequence became affected with ſores in their
            hands, <lb/>followed by inflamed lymphatic glands in the arms and <lb/>axillæ,
            ſhiverings ſucceeded by heat, laſſitude, and general <lb/>pains in the limbs. A ſingle
            paroxyſm terminated the <lb/>diſeaſe; for within twenty-four hours they were free from
            <lb/>general indiſpoſition, nothing remaining but the ſores on <lb/>their hands. Haynes
            and Virgoe, who had gone through <lb/>the Small-pox from inoculation, deſcribed their
            feelings as <lb/>very ſimilar to thoſe which affected them on ſickening with <lb/>that
            malady. Wherret never had had the Small pox. <lb/>Haynes was daily employed as one of
            the milkers at the <lb/>farm, and the diſeaſe began to ſhew itſelf among the cows
            <lb/>about ten days after he firſt aſſiſted in waſhing the mare's <lb/>heels. Their
            nipples became ſore in the uſual way, with <lb/>bluiſh puſtules; but as remedies were
            early applied, they <lb/>did not ulcerate to any extent. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <pb n="36"/>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center space">CASE XVIII. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>JOHN BAKER, a child of five years old, was inoculated <lb/>March 16, 1798, with
            matter taken from a puſtule on the <lb/>hand of Thomas Virgoe, one of the ſervants who
            had been <lb/>infected from the mare's heels. He became ill on the 6th <lb/>day with
            ſymptoms ſimilar to thoſe excited by Cow-pox <lb/>matter. On the 8th day he was free
            from indiſpoſition. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>There was ſome variation in the appearance of the puſtule <lb/>on the arm. Although
            it ſomewhat reſembled a Small-pox <lb/>puſtule, yet its ſimilitude was not ſo
            conſpicuous as when <lb/>excited by matter from the nipple of the cow, or when the
            <lb/>matter has paſſed from thence through the medium of the <lb/>human ſubject.—(See
            Plate, No. 2.) </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>This experiment was made to aſcertain the progreſs and <lb/>ſubſequent effects of
            the diſeaſe when thus propagated. <pb n="37"/>
            <lb/>We have ſeen that the virus from the horſe, when it proves <lb/>infectious to the
            human ſubject, is not to be relied upon as <lb/>rendering the ſyſtem ſecure from
            variolous infection, but <lb/>that the matter produced by it upon the nipple of the cow
            <lb/>is perfectly ſo. Whether its paſſing from the horſe through <lb/>the human
            conſtitution, as in the preſent inſtance, will <lb/>produce a ſimilar effect, remains to
            be decided. This would <lb/>now have been effected, but the boy was rendered unfit
            <lb/>for inoculation from having felt the effects of a contagious <lb/>fever in a
            work-houſe, ſoon after this experiment was made. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center space">CASE XIX. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>WILLIAM SUMMERS, a child of five years and a half <lb/>old, was inoculated the ſame
            day with Baker, with matter <lb/>taken from the nipples of one of the infected cows, at
            the <lb/>farm alluded to in page 35. He became indiſpoſed on the <lb/>6th day, vomited
            once, and felt the uſual ſlight ſymptoms <lb/>till the 8th day, when he appeared
            perfectly well. The <lb/>progreſs of the puſtule, formed by the infection of the virus
              <pb n="38"/>
            <lb/>was ſimilar to that noticed in Caſe XVII., with this exception, <lb/>its being free
            from the livid tint obſerved in that inſtance. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center space">CASE XX </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>FROM William Summers the diſeaſe was transferred to <lb/>William Pead a boy of
            eight years old, who was inoculated <lb/>March 28th. On the 6th day he complained of
            pain in the <lb/>axilla, and on the 7th was affected with the common ſymp- <lb/>toms of
            a patient ſickening with the Small-pox from inocu- <lb/>lation, which did not terminate
            'till the third day after the <lb/>ſeizure. So perfect was the ſimilarity to the
            variolous <lb/>fever that I was induced to examine the ſkin, conceiving <lb/>there might
            have been ſome eruptions, but none appeared. <lb/>The effloreſcent bluſh around the part
            punctured in the <lb/>boy's arm was ſo truly characteriſtic of that which appears
            <lb/>on variolous inoculation, that I have given a repreſentation <lb/>of it. The
            drawing was made when the puſtule was begin- <lb/>ning to die away and the areola
            retiring from the centre. <lb/>(See plate, No. 3.) </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <pb n="39"/>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center space">CASE XXI. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>April 5th: ſeveral children and adults were inoculated <lb/>from the arm of William
            Pead. The greater part of them <lb/>ſickened on the ſixth day, and were well on the 7th,
            but in <lb/>three of the number a ſecondary indiſpoſition aroſe in con- <lb/>ſequence of
            an extenſive eryſipelatous inflammation which <lb/>appeared on the inoculated arms. It
            ſeemed to ariſe from <lb/>the ſtate of the puſtule, which ſpread out, accompanied
            <lb/>with ſome degree of pain, to about half the diameter of a <lb/>ſix-pence. One of
            theſe patients was an infant of half a year <lb/>old. By the application of mercurial
            ointment to the <lb/>inflamed parts (a treatment recommended under ſimilar
            <lb/>circumſtances in the inoculated Small-pox) the complaint <lb/>ſubſided without
            giving much trouble. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>HANNAH EXCELL, an healthy girl of ſeven years old, <lb/>and one of the patients
            above mentioned, received the <pb n="40"/>
            <lb/>infection from the inſertion of the virus under the cuticle of <lb/>the arm in
            three diſtinct points. The puſtules which aroſe <lb/>in conſequence ſo much reſembled,
            on the 12th day, thoſe <lb/>appearing from the infection of variolous matter, that an
            <lb/>experienced Inoculator would ſcarcely have diſcovered a <lb/>ſhade of difference at
            that period. Experience now tells me that almoſt the only variation which follows
            conſiſts in the puſtulous fluids remaining limpid nearly to the time of its <lb/>total
            diſappearance; and not, as in the direct Small-pox, <lb/>becoming purulent.—(See plate,
            No. 4.) </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head rend="align-center space">CASE XXII. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>FROM the arm of this girl matter was taken and inſerted <lb/>April 12th into the
            arms of John Marklove, one year and a <lb/>half old, <lb rend="indentall"/>Robert F.
            Jenner, eleven months old, <lb/>Mary Pead, five years old, and <lb/>Mary James, ſix
            years old. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <pb n="41"/>
            <lb/> Among theſe Robert F. Jenner did not receive the infec- <lb/>tion. The arms of the
            other three inflamed properly and <lb/>began to affect the ſyſtem in the uſual manner;
            but being <lb/>under ſome apprehenſions from the preceding caſes that a <lb/>troubleſome
            eryſipelas might ariſe, I determined on making <lb/>an experiment with the view of
            cutting off its ſource. <lb/>Accordingly, after the patients had felt an indiſpoſition
            of <lb/>about twelve hours, I applied in two of theſe Caſes out of <lb/>the three, on
            the veſicle formed by the virus, a little mild <lb/>cauſtic, compoſed of equal parts of
            quick-lime and ſoap, <lb/>and ſuffered it to remain on the part ſix hours <note
              place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">*Perhaps a few touches with the lapis ſcepticus
              would have proved equally <lb/>efficacious. </note>. It ſeemed <lb/>to give the
            children but little uneaſineſs, and effectually <lb/>anſwered my intention in preventing
            the appearance of <lb/>eryſipelas. Indeed it ſeemed to do more, for in half an <lb/>hour
            after its application the indiſpoſition of the children <lb/>ceaſed <note place="bottom"
              n="†" rend="size(0.5)">†What effect would a ſimilar treatment produce in inoculation
              for the Small- <lb/>pox </note>. Theſe precautions were perhaps unneceſſary as <pb
              n="42"/>
            <lb/>the arm of the third child, Mary Pead, which was ſuffered <lb/>to take its common
            courſe, ſcabbed quickly, without any <lb/>eryſipelas. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <head prev="" rend="align-center space">CASE XXIII. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>FROM this child's arm matter was taken and transferred <lb/>to that of J. Barge, a
            boy of ſeven years old. He ſickened <lb/>on the 8th day, went through the diſeaſe with
            the uſual <lb/>ſlight ſymptoms, and without any inflammation on the arm <lb/>beyond the
            common effloreſcence ſurrounding the puſtule, <lb/>an appearance ſo often ſeen in
            inoculated Small-pox. </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>After the many fruitleſs attempts to give the Small-pox to <lb/>thoſe who had had
            the Cow-pox, it did not appear neceſ- <lb/>ſary, nor was it convenient to me, to
            inoculate the whole of <lb/>thoſe who had been the ſubjects of theſe late trials; yet I
            <lb/>thought it right to ſee the effects of variolous matter on <lb/>ſome of them,
            particularly William ſummers, the firſt of <lb/>theſe patients who had been infected
            with matter taken <pb n="43"/>
            <lb/>from the cow. He was, therefore, inoculated with variolous <lb/>matter from a freſh
            puſtule; but, as in the preceding <lb/>Caſes, the ſyſtem did not feel the effects of it
            in the <lb/>ſmalleſt degree. I had an opportunity alſo of having this boy <lb/>and
            William Pead inoculated by my nephew, Mr. Henry <lb/>Jenner, whoſe report to me is as
            follows: <q rend="quotes">I have inoculated Pead and Barge, two of the boys whom you
              lately infected with the Cow Pox. On the ſecond day the inciſions were inflamed and
              there was a pale inflammatory ſtain around them. On the third day theſe appearances
              were ſtill increaſing and their arms itched conſiderably. On the fourth day the
              inflammation was evidently ſubſiding, and on the ſixth day it was ſcarcely
              perceptible. No ſymptom of indiſpoſition followed. </q>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>
            <q rend="quotes">To convince myſelf that the variolous matter made uſe of was in a
              perfect ſtate I at the ſame time inoculated a patient with ſome of it who never had
              gone through the Cow Pox, and it produced the ſmallpox in the uſual regular manner.
            </q>
          </p>
          <pb n="44"/>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Theſe experiments afforded me much ſatisfaction, they <lb/>proved that the matter,
            in paſſing from one human ſubject to <lb/>another, through five gradations, loſt none of
            its original <lb/>properties, J. Barge being the fifth who received the infec- <lb/>tion
            ſucceſſively from William ſummers, the boy to whom <lb/>it was communicated from the
            cow. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <pb n="45"/>
      <p rend="hanging space">
        <lb/>I ſhall now conclude this inquiry with ſome <lb/>general obſervations on the ſubject,
        and on <lb/>ſome others which are interwoven with it. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Although I preſume it may be unneceſſary to <lb/>produce further teſtimony in ſupport
        of my aſſer- <lb/>tion <q rend="quotes">that the Cow-pox protects the human con-
          <lb/>ſtitution from the infection of the Small-pox, </q> yet <lb/>it affords me
        conſiderable ſatisfaction to ſay, that <lb/>Lord Somerville, the Preſident of the Board of
        <lb/>Agriculture, to whom this paper was ſhewn by <lb/>Sir Joſeph Banks, has found upon
        inquiry that the <lb/>ſtatements were confirmed by the concurring teſ- <lb/>timony of Mr.
        Dolland, a ſurgeon, who reſides in <lb/>a dairy country remote from this, in which theſe
        <lb/>obſervations were made. With reſpect to the <lb/>opinion adduced <q rend="quotes">that
          the ſource of the infection </q>
        <pb n="46"/>
        <lb/>
        <q rend="quotes">is a peculiar morbid matter ariſing in the horſe, </q>
        <lb/>although I have not been able to prove it from <lb/>actual experiments conducted
        immediately under <lb/>my own eye, yet the evidence I have adduced <lb/>appears ſufficient
        to eſtabliſh it. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>They who are not in the habit of conducting <lb/>experiments may not be aware of the
        coincidence <lb/>of circumſtances neceſſary for their being managed <lb/>ſo as to prove
        perfectly deciſive; nor how often men <lb/>engaged in profeſſional purſuits are liable to
        inter- <lb/>ruptions which diſappoint them almoſt at the <lb/>inſtant of their being
        accompliſhed: however, <lb/>I feel no room for heſitation reſpecting the com- <lb/>mon
        origin of the diſeaſe, being well convinced <lb/>that it never appears among the cows
        (except it <lb/>can be traced to a cow introduced among the <pb n="47"/>
        <lb/>general herd which has been previouſly infected, <lb/>or to an infected ſervant) unleſs
        they have been <lb/>milked by ſome one who, at the ſame time, has <lb/>the care of a horſe
        affected with diſeaſed heels. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/> The ſpring of the year 1797, which I intended <lb/>particularly to have devoted to the
        completion of <lb/>this inveſtigation, proved, from its dryneſs, re- <lb/>markably adverſe
        to my wiſhes; for it frequently <lb/>happens, while the farmerſ\rquote horſes are expoſed to
        <lb/>the cold rains which fall at that ſeaſon that their <lb/>heels become diſeaſed, and no
        Cow-pox then <lb/>appeared in the neighbourhood. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The active quality of the virus from the horſes' <lb/>heels is greatly increaſed after
        it has acted on the <lb/>nipples of the cow, as it rarely happens that the <pb n="48"/>
        <lb/>horſe affects his dreſſer with ſores, and as rarely <lb/>that a milk-maid eſcapes the
        infection when ſhe <lb/>milks infected cows. It is moſt active at the <lb/>commencement of
        the diſeaſe, even before it has <lb/>acquired a pus-like appearance; indeed, I am not
        <lb/>confident whether this property in the matter does <lb/>not entirely ceaſe as ſoon as
        it is ſecreted in the <lb/>form of pus. I am induced to think it does <lb/>ceaſe <note
          place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* It is very easy to produce pus from old ſores on
          the heels of horſes. This I <lb/>have often inſerted into ſcratches made with a lancet, on
          the ſound nipples of <lb/>cows, and have ſeen no other effects from it than ſimple
          inflammation. </note>, and that it is the thin darkiſh-looking <lb/>fluid only, oozing
        from the newly-formed cracks <lb/>in the heels, ſimilar to what ſometimes appears <lb/>from
        eryſipelatous bliſters, which gives the diſeaſe. <lb/>Nor am I certain that the nipples of
        the cows are <lb/>at all times in a ſtate to receive the infection. The <lb/>appearance of
        the diſeaſe in the ſpring and the <pb n="49"/>
        <lb/>early part of the ſummer, when they are diſpoſed <lb/>to be affected with ſpontaneous
        eruptions ſo much <lb/>more frequently than at other ſeaſons, induces me <lb/>to think, that
        the virus from the horſe muſt be <lb/>received upon them when they are in this ſtate, in
        <lb/>order to produce effects: experiments, however, <lb/>muſt determine theſe points. But
        it is clear that <lb/>when the Cow-pox virus is once generated, that <lb/>the cows cannot
        reſiſt the contagion, in whatever <lb/>ſtate their nipples may chance to be, if they are
        <lb/>milked with an infected hand. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Whether the matter, either from the cow or the <lb/>horſe will affect the ſound ſkin of
        the human <lb/>body, I cannot poſitively determine; probably <lb/>it will not, unleſs on
        thoſe parts where the cuti- <lb/>cle is extremely thin, as on the lips, for example. <pb
          n="50"/>
        <lb/>I have known an inſtance of a poor girl who <lb/>produced an ulceration on her lip by
        frequently <lb/>holding her finger to her mouth to cool the raging <lb/>of a Cow-pox ſore by
        blowing upon it. The <lb/>hands of the farmers' ſervants here, from the <lb/>nature of their
        employments, are conſtantly ex- <lb/>poſed to thoſe injuries which occaſion abraſions
        <lb/>of the cuticle, to punctures from thorns, and ſuch <lb/>like accidents; ſo that they
        are always in a ſtate <lb/>to feel the conſequence of expoſure to infectious <lb/>matter. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It is ſingular to obſerve that the Cow-pox virus, <lb/>although it renders the
        conſtitution unſuſceptible <lb/>of the variolous, ſhould nevertheleſs, leave it
        <lb/>unchanged with reſpect to its own action. I have <pb n="51"/>
        <lb/>already produced an inſtance <note place="bottom" n="*">* See Caſe IX. </note> to point
        out this, <lb/>and ſhall now corroborate it with another. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Elizabeth Wynne, who had the Cow-pox in the <lb/>year 1759, was inoculated with
        variolous matter, <lb/>without effect, in the year 1797, and again caught <lb/>the Cow Pox
        in the year 1798. When I ſaw her, <lb/>which was on the 8th day after ſhe received the
        <lb/>infection, I found her affected with general laſſi- <lb/>tude, ſhiverings, alternating
        with heat, coldneſs <lb/>of the extremities, and a quick and irregular <lb/>pulſe. Theſe
        ſymptoms were preceded by a pain <lb/>in the axilla. On her hand was one large puſtu-
        <lb/>lous ſore, which reſembled that delineated in Plate <lb/>No. 1. </p>
      <pb n="52"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It is curious alſo to obſerve that the virus, <lb/>which with reſpect to its effects is
        undetermined <lb/>and uncertain previouſly to its paſſing from the <lb/>horſe through the
        medium of the cow, ſhould then <lb/>not only become more active, but ſhould inva-
        <lb/>riably and completely poſſeſs thoſe ſpecific pro- <lb/>perties which induce in the
        human conſtitution <lb/>ſymptoms ſimilar to thoſe of the variolous fever, <lb/>and effect in
        it that peculiar change which for <lb/>ever renders it unſuſceptible of the variolous con-
        <lb/>tagion. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>May it not then be reaſonably conjectured, that <lb/>the ſource of the Small-pox is
        morbid matter of a <lb/>peculiar kind, generated by a diſeaſe in the horſe, <lb/>and that
        accidental circumſtances may have again <lb/>and again ariſen, ſtill working new changes
        upon <pb n="53"/>
        <lb/>it until it has acquired the contagious and malig- <lb/>nant form under which we now
        commonly ſee it <lb/>making its devaſtations amongſt us? And, from a <lb/>conſideration of
        the change which the infectious <lb/>matter undergoes from producing a diſeaſe on the
        <lb/>cow, may we not conceive that many contagious <lb/>diſeaſes, now prevalent among us,
        may owe their <lb/>preſent appearance not to a ſimple, but to a com- <lb/>pound origin? For
        example, is it difficult to <lb/>imagine that the meaſles, the ſcarlet fever, and the
        <lb/>ulcerous ſore throat with a ſpotted ſkin, have all <lb/>ſprung from the ſame ſource,
        aſſuming ſome <lb/>variety in their forms according to the nature of <lb/>their new
        combinations? The ſame queſtion will <lb/>apply reſpecting the origin of many other conta-
        <lb/>gious diſeaſes, which bear a ſtrong analogy to each <lb/>other. </p>
      <pb n="54"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/> There are certainly more forms than one, <lb/>without conſidering the common variation
        be- <lb/>tween the confluent and diſtinct, in which the <lb/>Small-pox appears in what is
        called the natural <lb/>way.— About ſeven years ago a ſpecies of Small- <lb/>pox ſpread
        through many of the towns and <lb/>villages of this part of Glouceſterſhire: it was <lb/>of
        ſo mild a nature, that a fatal inſtance was <lb/>ſcarcely ever heard of, and conſequently ſo
        little <lb/>dreaded by the lower orders of the community, <lb/>that they ſcrupled not to
        hold the ſame intercourſe <lb/>with each other as if no infectious diſeaſe had been
        <lb/>preſent among them. I never ſaw nor heard of <lb/>an inſtance of its being confluent.
        The moſt <lb/>accurate manner, perhaps, in which I can convey <lb/>an idea of it is, by
        ſaying, that had fifty indi- <lb/>viduals been taken promiſcuouſly and infected <pb n="55"/>
        <lb/>by expoſure to this contagion, they would have <lb/>had as mild and light a diſeaſe as
        if they had <lb/>been inoculated with variolous matter in the <lb/>uſual way. The harmleſs
        manner in which <lb/>it ſhewed itſelf could not ariſe from any pecu- <lb/>liarity either in
        the ſeaſon or the weather, for I <lb/>watched its progreſs upwards of a year without
        <lb/>perceiving any variation in its general appearance. <lb/>I conſider it then as a <hi
          rend="italic">variety</hi> of the Small- <lb/>pox <note place="bottom" n="*"
          rend="size(0.5)">* My friend Dr. Hicks, of Briſtol, who during the prevalence of this diſ-
          <lb/>temper was reſident at Glouceſter, and Phyſician to the Hoſpital there, <lb/>(where
          it was ſeen ſoon after its firſt appearance in this country) had opportunities <lb/>of
          making numerous obſervations upon it, which it is his intention to commu- <lb/>nicate to
          the Public. </note>. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>In ſome of the preceding caſes I have noticed <lb/>the attention that was paid to the
        ſtate of the <pb n="56"/>
        <lb/>variolous matter previous to the experiment of <lb/>inſerting it into the arms of thoſe
        who had gone <lb/>through the Cow-pox. This I conceived to be <lb/>of great importance in
        conducting theſe experi- <lb/>ments, and, were it always properly attended to by <lb/>thoſe
        who inoculate for the Small-pox, it might <lb/>prevent much ſubſequent miſchief and
        confuſion. <lb/>With the view of enforcing ſo neceſſary a pre- <lb/>caution I ſhall take the
        liberty of digreſſing ſo <lb/>far as to point out ſome unpleaſant facts, rela- <lb/>tive to
        miſmanagement in this particular, which <lb/>have fallen under my own obſervation. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>A medical gentleman (now no more), who <lb/>for many years inoculated in this
        neighbourhood, <lb/>frequently preſerved the variolous matter intended <lb/>for his uſe on a
        piece of lint or cotton, which, in <pb n="57"/>
        <lb/>its fluid ſtate, was put into a vial, corked, and <lb/>conveyed into a warm pocket; a
        ſituation cer- <lb/>tainly favourable for ſpeedily producing putrefac- <lb/>tion in it. In
        this ſtate (not unfrequently after <lb/>it had been taken ſeveral days from the puſtules)
        <lb/>it was inſerted into the arms of his patients, and <lb/>brought on inflammation of the
        inciſed parts, <lb/>ſwellings of the axillary glands, fever, and ſome- <lb/>times eruptions.
        But what was this diſeaſe? Cer- <lb/>tainly not the Small-pox; for the matter having
        <lb/>from putrefaction loſt, or ſuffered a derangement <lb/>in its ſpecific properties, was
        no longer capable <lb/>of producing that malady, thoſe who had been <lb/>inoculated in this
        manner being as much ſub- <lb/>ject to the contagion of the Small-pox, as if <lb/>they had
        never been under the influence of this <lb/>artificial diſeaſe; and many, unfortunately,
        fell <pb n="58"/>
        <lb/>victims to it, who thought themſelves in perfect <lb/>ſecurity. The ſame unfortunate
        circumſtance of <lb/>giving a diſeaſe, ſuppoſed to be the Small-pox, <lb/>with inefficacious
        variolous matter, having occur- <lb/>red under the direction of ſome other practitioners
        <lb/>within my knowledge, and probably from the ſame <lb/>incautious method of ſecuring the
        variolous mat- <lb/>ter, I avail myſelf of this opportunity of men- <lb/>tioning what I
        conceive to be of great importance; <lb/>and, as a further cautionary hint, I ſhall again
        <lb/>digreſs ſo far as to add another obſervation on the <lb/>ſubject of Inoculation<choice>
          <corr>.</corr>
          <sic/>
        </choice>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Whether it be yet aſcertained by experiment, <lb/>that the quantity of variolous matter
        inſerted into <lb/>the ſkin makes any difference with reſpect to the <lb/>ſubſequent
        mildneſs or violence of the diſeaſe, I <pb n="59"/>
        <lb/>know not; but I have the ſtrongeſt reaſon for <lb/>ſuppoſing that if either the
        punctures or inciſions <lb/>be made ſo deep as to go <hi rend="italic">through</hi> it and
        wound <lb/>the adipoſe membrane, that the riſk of bringing <lb/>on a violent diſeaſe is
        greatly increaſed. I have <lb/>known an inoculator, whoſe practice was <q rend="quotes">to
          cut deep enough (to uſe his own expreſſion) to ſee a bit of fat, </q> and there to lodge
        the matter. The <lb/>great number of bad Caſes, independent of inflam- <lb/>mations and
        abſceſſes on the arms, and the fatality <lb/>which attended this practice was almoſt incon-
        <lb/>ceivable; and I cannot account for it on any <lb/>other principle than that of the
        matter being placed <lb/>in this ſituation inſtead of the ſkin. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>It was the practice of another, whom I well <lb/>remember, to pinch up a ſmall portion
        of the ſkin <pb n="60"/>
        <lb/>on the arms of his patients and to paſs through it <lb/>a needle, with a thread
        attached to it previouſly <lb/>dipped in variolous matter. The thread was <lb/>lodged in the
        perforated part, and conſequently <lb/>left in contact with the cellular membrane. This
        <lb/>practice was attended with the ſame ill ſucceſs as <lb/>the former. Although it is very
        improbable that <lb/>any one would now inoculate in this rude way by <lb/>deſign, yet theſe
        obſervations may tend to place a <lb/>double guard over the lancet, when infants, whoſe
        <lb/>ſkins are comparatively ſo very thin, fall under <lb/>the care of the inoculator. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>A very reſpectable friend of mine, Dr. Hard- <lb/>wicke, of ſodbury in this county,
        inoculated great <lb/>numbers of patients previous to the introduction <lb/>of the more
        modern method by Sutton, and with <pb n="61"/>
        <lb/>ſuch ſucceſs, that a fatal inſtance occurred as <lb/>rarely as ſince that method has
        been adopted. It <lb/>was the doctor's practice to make as ſlight an in- <lb/>ciſion as
        poſſible <hi rend="italic">upon</hi> the ſkin, and there to lodge <lb/>a thread ſaturated
        with the variolous matter. <lb/>When his patients became indiſpoſed, agreeably <lb/>to the
        cuſtom then prevailing, they were directed <lb/>to go to bed and were kept moderately warm.
        Is <lb/>it not probable then, that the ſucceſs of the modern <lb/>practice may depend more
        upon the method of <lb/>invariably depoſiting the virus in or upon the ſkin, <lb/>than on
        the ſubſequent treatment of the diſeaſe? </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/> I do not mean to inſinuate that expoſure to cool <lb/>air, and ſuffering the patient
        to drink cold water <lb/>when hot and thirſty, may not moderate the erup- <lb/>tive ſymptoms
        and leſſen the number of puſtules; <pb n="62"/>
        <lb/>yet, to repeat my former obſervation, I cannot <lb/>account for the uninterrupted
        ſucceſs, or nearly ſo, <lb/>of one practitioner, and the wretched ſtate of the <lb/>patients
        under the care of another, where, in both <lb/>inſtances, the general treatment did not
        differ <lb/>eſſentially, without conceiving it to ariſe from the <lb/>different modes of
        inſerting the matter for the <lb/>purpoſe of producing the diſeaſe. As it is not the
        <lb/>identical matter inſerted which is abſorbed into the <lb/>conſtitution, but that which
        is, by ſome peculiar <lb/>proceſs in the animal economy, generated by it, <lb/>is it not
        probable that different parts of the human <lb/>body may prepare or modify the virus
        differently? <lb/>Although the ſkin, for example, adipoſe mem- <lb/>brane, or mucous
        membranes are all capable of <lb/>producing the variolous virus by the ſtimulus given
        <lb/>by the particles originally depoſited upon them, <pb n="63"/>
        <lb/>yet I am induced to conceive that each of theſe <lb/>parts is capable of producing ſome
        variation in <lb/>the qualities of the matter previous to its affecting <lb/>the
        conſtitution. What elſe can conſtitute the <lb/>difference between the Small-pox when
        communi- <lb/>cated caſually or in what has been termed the <lb/>natural way, or when
        brought on artificially <lb/>through the medium of the ſkin? After all, are <lb/>the
        variolous particles, poſſeſſing their true ſpecific <lb/>and contagious principles, ever
        taken up and con- <lb/>veyed by the lymphatics unchanged into the blood <lb/>veſſels? I
        imagine not. Were this the caſe, <lb/>ſhould we not find the blood ſufficiently loaded
        <lb/>with them in ſome ſtages of the Small-pox to com- <lb/>municate the diſeaſe by
        inſerting it under the <lb/>cuticle, or by ſpreading it on the ſurface of an <lb/>ulcer? Yet
        experiments have determined the im- <pb n="64"/>
        <lb/>practicability of its being given in this way; al- <lb/>though it has been proved that
        variolous matter <lb/>when much diluted with water and applied to the <lb/>ſkin in the uſual
        manner, will produce the diſ- <lb/>eaſe. But it would be digreſſing beyond a <lb/>proper
        boundary, to go minutely into this ſubject <lb/>here. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>At what period the Cow-pox was firſt noticed <lb/>here is not upon record. Our oldeſt
        farmers were <lb/>not unacquainted with it in their earlieſt days, <lb/>when it appeared
        among their farms without any <lb/>deviation from the phœnomena which it now ex-
        <lb/>hibits. Its connection with the Small-pox ſeems <lb/>to have been unknown to them.
        Probably the <lb/>general introduction of inoculation firſt occaſioned <lb/>the diſcovery. </p>
      <pb n="65"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Its riſe in this country may not have been of <lb/>very remote date, as the practice of
        milking cows <lb/>might formerly have been in the hands of women <lb/>only; which I believe
        is the caſe now in ſome <lb/>other dairy countries, and, conſequently, that the <lb/>cows
        might not in former times have been expoſed <lb/>to the contagious matter brought by the men
        ſer- <lb/>vants from the heels of horſes <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* I
          have been informed from reſpectable authority that in Ireland, although <lb/>dairies
          abound in many parts of the Iſeland, the diſeaſe is entirely unknown. The <lb/>reaſon
          ſeems obvious. The buſineſs of the dairy is conducted by women only. <lb/>Were the meaneſt
          vaſſal among the men, employed thereas a milker at a dairy, <lb/>he would feel his
          ſituation unpleaſant beyond all endurance. </note>. Indeed, a know- <lb/>ledge of the
        ſource of the infection is new in the <lb/>minds of moſt of the farmers in this neighbour-
        <lb/>hood, but it has at length produced good con- <lb/>ſequences; and it ſeems probable,
        from the pre- <lb/>cautions they are now diſpoſed to adopt, that the <pb n="66"/>
        <lb/>appearance of the Cow-pox here may either be <lb/>entirely extinguiſhed or become
        extremely rare. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Should it be aſked whether this inveſtigation is <lb/>a matter of mere curioſity, or
        whether it tends to <lb/>any beneficial purpoſe? I ſhould anſwer, that <lb/>notwithſtanding
        the happy effects of Inoculation, <lb/>with all the improvements which the practice has
        <lb/>received ſince its firſt introduction into this <lb/>country, it not very unfrequently
        produces defor- <lb/>mity of the ſkin, and ſometimes, under the beſt <lb/>management, proves
        fatal. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Theſe circumſtances muſt naturally create in <lb/>every inſtance ſome degree of painful
        ſolicitude <lb/>for its conſequences. But as I have never known <lb/>fatal effects ariſe
        from the Cow-pox, even when <pb n="67"/>
        <lb/>impreſſed in the moſt unfavourable manner, pro- <lb/>ducing extenſive inflammations and
        ſuppurations <lb/>on the hands; and as it clearly appears that this <lb/>diſeaſe leaves the
        conſtitution in a ſtate of perfect <lb/>ſecurity from the infection of the Small-pox, may
        <lb/>we not infer that a mode of Inoculation may be <lb/>introduced preferable to that at
        preſent adopted, <lb/>eſpecially among thoſe families which, from <lb/>previous
        circumſtances, we may judge to be prediſ- <lb/>poſed to have the diſeaſe unfavourably? It is
        an <lb/>exceſs in the number of puſtules which we chiefly <lb/>dread in the Small-pox; but
        in the Cow-pox, no <lb/>puſtules appear, nor does it ſeem poſſible for the <lb/>contagious
        matter to produce the diſeaſe from <lb/>effluvia, or by any other means than contact, and
        <lb/>that probably not ſimply between the virus and <lb/>the cuticle; ſo that a ſingle
        individual in a family <pb n="68"/>
        <lb/>might at any time receive it without the riſk of <lb/>infecting the reſt or of
        ſpreading a diſtemper that <lb/>fills a country with terror. Several inſtances have
        <lb/>come under my obſervation which juſtify the <lb/>aſſertion that the diſeaſe cannot be
        propagated by <lb/>effluvia. The firſt boy whom I inoculated with <lb/>the matter of Cow-pox
        ſlept in a bed, while the <lb/>experiment was going forward, with two children <lb/>who
        never had gone through either that diſeaſe or <lb/>the Small-pox, without infecting either
        of them. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>A young woman who had the Cow-pox to a <lb/>great extent, ſeveral ſores which maturated
        having <lb/>appeared on the hands and wriſts, ſlept in the ſame <lb/>bed with a fellow-dairy
        maid who never had been <lb/>infected with either the Cow-pox or the Small- <lb/>pox, but no
        indiſpoſition followed. </p>
      <pb n="69"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Another inſtance has occurred of a young <lb/>woman on whoſe hands were ſeveral large
        ſuppu- <lb/>rations from the Cow-pox, who was at the ſame <lb/>time a daily nurſe to an
        infant, but the complaint <lb/>was not communicated to the child. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>In ſome other points of view the inoculation <lb/>of this diſeaſe appears preferable to
        the variolous <lb/>inoculation. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>In conſtitutions prediſpoſed to ſcrophula, how <lb/>frequently we ſee the inoculated
        Small-pox, rouſe <lb/>into activity that diſtreſsful malady. This circum- <lb/>ſtance does
        not ſeem to depend on the manner in <lb/>which the diſtemper has ſhewn itſelf, for it has as
        <lb/>frequently happened among thoſe who have had it <lb/>mildly, as when it has appeared in
        the contrary way. </p>
      <pb n="70"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>There are many, who from ſome peculiarity in <lb/>the habit reſiſt the common effects
        of variolous <lb/>matter inſerted into the ſkin, and who are in con- <lb/>ſequence haunted
        through life with the diſtreſſing <lb/>idea of being inſecure from ſubſequent infection.
        <lb/>A ready mode of diſſipating anxiety originating <lb/>from ſuch a cauſe muſt now appear
        obvious. And, <lb/>as we have ſeen that the conſtitution may at any <lb/>time be made to
        feel the febrile attack of Cow- <lb/>pox, might it not, in many chronic diſeaſes be
        <lb/>introduced into the ſyſtem, with the probability <lb/>of affording relief, upon
        well-known phyſiolo- <lb/>gical principles? </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Although I ſay the ſyſtem may at any time be <lb/>made to feel the febrile attack of
        Cow Pox, yet I <lb/>have a ſingle inſtance before me where the virus <pb n="71"/>
        <lb/>acted locally only, but it is not in the leaſt proba- <lb/>ble that the ſame perſon
        would reſiſt the action <lb/>both of the Cow-pox virus and the variolous. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Elizabeth Sarſenet lived as a dairy maid at New- <lb/>park farm, in this pariſh. All
        the cows and the ſer- <lb/>vants employed in milking had the Cow-pox; but <lb/>this woman,
        though ſhe had ſeveral ſores upon <lb/>her fingers, felt no tumours in the axillæ, nor any
        <lb/>general indiſpoſition. On being afterwards caſu- <lb/>ally expoſed to variolous
        infection, ſhe had the <lb/>Small-pox in a mild way.—Hannah Pick, another <lb/>of the
        dairymaids who was a fellow-ſervant with <lb/>Elizabeth Sarſenet when the diſtemper broke
        out <lb/>at the farm was, at the ſame time infected; but <lb/>this young woman had not only
        ſores upon her <lb/>hands, but felt herſelf alſo much indiſpoſed for a <pb n="72"/>
        <lb/>day or two. After this, I made ſeveral attempts <lb/>to give her the Small-pox by
        inoculation, but <lb/>they all proved fruitleſs. From the former Caſe <lb/>then we ſee that
        the animal economy is ſubject to <lb/>the ſame laws in one diſeaſe as the other. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The following Caſe which has very lately occur- <lb/>red renders it highly probable
        that not only the <lb/>heels of the horſe, but other parts of the body of <lb/>that animal,
        are capable of generating the virus <lb/>which produces the Cow-pox. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>An extenſive inflammation of the eryſipelatous <lb/>kind, appeared without any apparent
        cauſe upon <lb/>the upper part of the thigh of a ſucking colt, the <lb/>property of Mr.
        Millet, a farmer at Rockhampton, <lb/>a village near Berkeley. The inflammation con- <pb
          n="73"/>
        <lb/>tinued ſeveral weeks, and at length terminated in <lb/>the formation of three or four
        ſmall abſceſſes. The <lb/>inflamed parts were fomented, and dreſſings were <lb/>applied by
        ſome of the ſame perſons who were <lb/>employed in milking the cows. The number of <lb/>cows
        milked was twenty-four, and the whole of <lb/>them had the Cow-pox. The milkers, conſiſting
        <lb/>of the farmer's wife, a man and a maid ſervant, <lb/>were infected by the cows. The
        man-ſervant had <lb/>previouſly gone through the Small-pox, and felt <lb/>but little of the
        Cow-pox. The ſervant maid had <lb/>ſome years before been infected with the Cow-pox,
        <lb/>and ſhe alſo felt it now in a ſlight degree: But the <lb/>farmer's wife who never had
        gone through either <lb/>of the diſeaſes, felt its effects very ſeverely. </p>
      <pb n="74"/>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>That the diſeaſe produced upon the cows by the <lb/>colt and from thence conveyed to
        thoſe who <lb/>milked them was the <hi rend="italic">true</hi> and not the <hi rend="italic"
          >ſpurious</hi>
        <lb/>Cow-pox <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">* See Note in Page 7. </note>,
        there can be ſcarcely any room for <lb/>ſuſpicion; yet it would have been more completely
        <lb/>ſatisfactory, had the effects of variolous matter been <lb/>aſcertained on the farmer's
        wife, but there was a <lb/>peculiarity in her ſituation which prevented my <lb/>making the
        experiment. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Thus far have I proceeded in an inquiry, <lb/>founded, as it muſt appear, on the baſis
        of ex- <lb/>periment; in which, however, conjecture has <lb/>been occaſionally admitted in
        order to preſent to <lb/>perſons well ſituated for ſuch diſcuſſions, objects <pb n="75"/>
        <lb/>for a more minute inveſtigation. In the mean <lb/>time I ſhall myſelf continue to
        proſecute this <lb/>inquiry, encouraged by the hope of its becoming <lb/>eſſentially
        beneficial to mankind. </p>
      <trailer prev="" rend="align-center space">FINIS. </trailer>
    </body>
  </text>

</TEI>
