<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Willis: Receipts for the Cure of all Distempers </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Thomas Willis</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Dr. Willis's RECEIPTS FOR THE CURE OF ALL DISTEMPERS: Together with
              an APPENDIX, Containing the General Forms of Prescription for Vomits, Purges,
              Diureticks, Sudorificks, Cordials, and Opiats. Collected out of the Writings of that
              Learned and Eminent Physician, and Faithfully Translated into English. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T94625</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T94625"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for Thomas Leigh, and Daniel Midwinter, at the Rose and
                  Crown, in St. Paul's Church-Yard, 1701.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1701</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="7"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="226"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="2"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107430310</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Recipe Collections"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="7"/>
    <body>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A horizontal double-line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/><hi rend="size(3.0)">Dr. <hi rend="italic">WILLIS</hi>'s </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(4.0) space">RECEIPTS. </hi>
      </head>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center size(2.0)">
          <lb/>SECT. I. </head>
        <head rend="align-center italic size(3.0) space">
          <lb/>Preſcriptions for Fevers. </head>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A plain, eaſy, and effectual method for curing a <lb/>Tertian Ague, in the
            beginning. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(4)">T</hi>AKE a gentle infuſion of Senna, Ru- <lb/>barb, yellow
            Saunders, and ſalt of <lb/>Wormwood, in ſpring Water: next <lb/>day apply to the wriſts
            the juice of Plan- <lb/>tane and Bay-ſalt: Obſerving a thin Diet during <lb/>the whole
            courſe of the Diſeaſe, and Bleeding if <lb/>the Patient be of a cholerick temperament.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An approv'd Medicine, to be taken every Morning in <lb/>a Tertian Ague. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the ſalt of Wormwood, a ſcruple, in <lb/>a ſpoonful of the juice of
            Oranges. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="2"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Bolus proper to be taken at Night, in a Tertian Ague. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Conſerve of Roſes, half a Dram; <lb/>Diaſcordium, a ſcruple; mix, and
            make a Bolus. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb rend="italic align-center"/>An external Medicine, that by frequent Experience
            <lb/>has cur'd many Chronical Agues. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Flax and Paper, and roll them up into a <lb/>hard ball; and bind it ſo cloſe
            to the wriſt where <lb/>the pulſe beats, that it ſtops in ſome meaſure the
            <lb/>circulation of the blood. By this means the ap- <lb/>proaching fit is certainly
            prevented. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Mixture, ſucceßfully preſcrib'd for a Woman in <lb/>Childbed, under a Quotidian
            Ague. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the magiſtral water of Earth-worms, <lb/>two ounces; Elixir Proprietatis,
            ſix drops: mix; <lb/>and exhibit it twice a day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An external Medicine, experienc'd upon the ſame <lb/>occaſion. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the leaves of Pontick Wormwood, Cen- <lb/>tory, and Southernwood, and Roots
            of Gentian, <lb/>what quantity you pleaſe; boyl all in a cover'd <lb/>veſſel with white
            Wine. Then take the decoction, <lb/>and foment the Stomach with it; applying after the
            <lb/>fomentation a toaſt dip'd in the ſame liquor. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An infallible Medicine for a Quartan Ague. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Peruvian-bark, two Drams; beat <lb/>it into powder, and infuſe it for
            two hours in white <lb/>Wine or Sack (as the Patient's palate directs) in a <lb/>covered
            veſſel. Let the liquor with the floating <lb/>powder be drunk up in bed, upon the
            approach of <lb/>the fit. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="3"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A ſweating and ſleeping Bolus, given with good effect <lb/>on the fifth day of a
            continual putrid Fever. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/>Take of the Conſerve of red Roſes vitriolated, <lb/>Gaſcoign's Powder, a ſcruple;
            Laudanum diſ- <lb/>ſolv'd in Bawm-water, a grain. Mix for a Bolus <lb/>to be taken at
            night. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A ſweating Mixture that cur'd ſeveral of a conti- <lb/>nual Fever, when almoſt
            given over. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take a dram of the Spirit of Hartshorn in a <lb/>little draught of ſome Cordial
            Julep. By this <lb/>means a copious ſweat was rais'd; which was af- <lb/>terwards
            continued by taking a doſe of the Pow- <lb/>der of Contrayerva every ſix hours. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Powder, famous for curing the Malignant Epi- <lb/>demick Fever, that rag'd in the
            year 1643. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Powder of Toads, cleanſed with <lb/>ſalt, and afterwards waſh'd with
            good wine, and <lb/>lightly calcin'd in an earthen Pot, half a dram; to <lb/>be given in
            any liquor. It us'd to raiſe a moſt co- <lb/>pious ſweat, and by that means to throw off
            the <lb/>virulency of the diſeaſe. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An approv'd external Application, to ſecure the <lb/>Throat in the Small Pox. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take a bag of Saffron, dip it in womans milk, <lb/>and faſten it under the Chin. By
            opening the Pores, <lb/>it draws the venom from the Throat. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A noted Medicine that ſtop'd a bleeding in the ſmall <lb/>Pox, when all other
            Medicines were ineffectual. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take a Toad dry'd in the Sun, and pounded <lb/>put it into a bag, and hang it about
            the neck. It <lb/>ſtops the bleeding immediately, and at the ſame <lb/>time draws out
            the venom of the Pox. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="4"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An excellent Mixture for Childbed Fevers, attended <lb/>with a ſuppreſſion of the
            Loches. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Pennyroyal and Bawm-water, of each two <lb/>ounces; Hyſterick-water, two
            ounces; Syrup of <lb/>Mugwort, an ounce and an half; Tincture of <lb/>Saffron, two
            drams; Caſtor ty'd in a rag and hung <lb/>in a glaſs, a ſcruple. Mix, and exhibit three
            or <lb/>four ſpoonfuls ſeveral times a day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A good Medicine to be taken at night in Childbed <lb/>Fevers. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Laudanum a grain; of the Powder of <lb/>Saffron, half a ſcruple. Mix and
            give it in a ſpoon- <lb/>ful of Treacle water. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb rend="italic align-center"/>An excellent Sudorifick in Childbed Fevers. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Oriental Bezoar ſix grains; in a ſpoon- <lb/>ful of Cordial Julep. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A ſucceßful Medicine for Women in Childbed ſeiz'd <lb/>with the Small Pox. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Roots of Tormentil in Powder, two <lb/>drams; the beſt Bole-armenick, a
            dram; Species <lb/>of Hyacinth, half a dram. Mix and make a Pow- <lb/>der: of which half
            a dram is to be taken every <lb/>three hours in a ſpoonful of the following Julep. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take the Waters of Scordium compound, of <lb/>Dragonwort, and of Meadowſweet, of
            each three <lb/>ounces; Vinegar of Treacle, an ounce; Syrup of <lb/>Coral, two ounces;
            burnt Hartſhorn, half a dram. <lb/>Make a Julep. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Powder for Epidemick Intermitting Fevers. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Cream of Tartar, two drams; Powder of <lb/>Crabs-eyes, a dram; Nitre
            putrify'd, half a dram, <pb n="5"/>
            <lb/>Mix, and give half a dram twice a day, avoiding <lb/>the time of the fit. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An excellent Medicine for feveriſh or aguiſh Per- <lb/>ſons, troubled with worms. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of burnt Hartſhorn, two drams; Spirit of <lb/>Vitriol, as much as the powder
            will drink up. <lb/>Doſe, one ſcruple. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An approved Medicine, to prevent the acceſſion of <lb/>the fit, in an Epidemick
            Ague. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Cream of Tartar, Salt of Wormwood, <lb/>and Nettle-ſeeds, of each a ſcruple.
            Mix, and give <lb/>it in the decoction of Sorrel Roots. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Diuretick Decoction and Emulſion, of excellent <lb/>uſe in Convulſive Fevers, or
            ſuch as diſorder <lb/>the Spirits chiefly. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Roots of Scorzonera, Chervil, Grafs, and <lb/>Eringo condited, of each ſix
            drams; one Apple <lb/>ſlic'd; Leaves of Burnet and Meadow-ſweet, of <lb/>each a handful;
            Raiſins, an ounce and a half; <lb/>burnt Hartſhorn, two drams. Being ſlic'd and bruis'd,
            <lb/>let them boyl on a clear fire in four pounds of <lb/>Spring-water, till a third
            part be conſum'd. To <lb/>two pounds of clear ſtraining add of the Syrup of <lb/>the
            Juice of Citrons or of Violets, two ounces; <lb/>Sal Prunel, a dram and a half. Make an
            Apo- <lb/>zeme. Doſe from four ounces to ſix thrice a day. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Or, Let the ſtraining be pour'd on fifteen ſweet <lb/>Almonds blanch; and on the
            four cold Seeds, of <lb/>each a dram. Then bruiſe them, and make an <lb/>Emulſion
            according to art. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An excellent Julep for Convulſive Fevers. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take water of Dragonwort and of black Cher- <pb n="6"/>
            <lb/>ries, of each three ounces; Water of Scordium <lb/>compound, two ounces;
            Treacle-water an ounce <lb/>and an half; Syrop of Clove Gillyflowers, two <lb/>ounces;
            Spirit of Vitriol, twelve drops. Make a <lb/>Julep. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Diuretick Powder, of good uſe in Convulſive Fevers. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Sal Prunel, from half a dram to two <lb/>ſcruples, in ſmall beer or whey,
            ſeveral times a day. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center size(2.0) space">
          <lb/>SECT. II. </head>
        <head rend="italic align-center size(2.0) space">
          <lb rend="italic center-align size(2.0)"/>Recipe's for an Epilepſy or the Falling
          <lb/>Sickneſs. </head>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Vomit to be given in the beginning of an Epilepſy, <lb/>and repeated four days
            before full Moon, <lb/>for ſeveral Months. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>Ake of Crocus Metallorum (or Mercurius Vi- <lb/>tæ) from
            four to ſix grains; ſweet Mercury, <lb/>from ſixteen to twenty grains. Beat 'em together
            <lb/>in a Mortar, and give it in the pap of an Apple, <lb/>or a dram of the Conſerve of
            Borrage. Or, </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Infuſion of Crocus Metallorum (or <lb/>of Mercurius Vitæ) in Spaniſh
            wine, from half an <lb/>ounce to an ounce. Or, </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of <hi rend="italic">Mynſicht</hi>'s Emetick Tartar, from four <lb/>to ſix
            grains. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A gentle Vomit for Epileptick Children and weak <lb/>Perſons. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Salt of Vitriol, from a ſcruple to <pb n="7"/>
            <lb/>half a dram: and after half an hour drink ſeveral <lb/>pints of Poſſet-drink: and
            provoke to vomit with <lb/>a quill, or the finger put into the Throat. Re- <lb/>peating
            the ſame method ſeveral times. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An excellent Purge for the Falling Sickneß. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Roſin of Jalap, half a dram; ſweet <lb/>Mercury, a ſcruple; Caſtor,
            three grains; Con- <lb/>ſerve of Peony-flowers, a dram. Make a Bolus; <lb/>to be taken
            two days after the Vomit; and re- <lb/>peated every month four days before the New
            <lb/>Moon. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Purgative Pills of ſingular uſe in an Epilepſy. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the greater Pillulæ Fœtidæ, two ſcru- <lb/>ples; Roſin of Jalap, five
            grains; With a ſufficient <lb/>quantity of Gum Ammoniac diſſolv'd in ſome Hy-
            <lb/>ſterical water, make five Pills to be taken and re- <lb/>peated as was above
            preſcrib'd. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A purging Powder, good in an Epilepſy. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take threads of black Hellebor macerated in <lb/>Vinegar, dried, and pounded, half
            a dram; Gin- <lb/>ger, half a ſcruple; Salt of Wormwood, twelve <lb/>grains; Oyl of
            Amber two drops. Make a Pow- <lb/>der to be given in the pap of an Apple. Or, </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the compound Powder of Hermodacts, <lb/>a dram; Man's Skull, prepar'd, ſix
            grains. Make <lb/>a Powder, to be taken in a draught of the Deco- <lb/>ction of Hyſſop
            or Sage. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A ſimple and approv'd Specifick, for the Falling Sickneß. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Roots of male Peony, dried and <lb/>pounded, from one to two or three
            drams, and give <lb/>it twice a day (to the poor) in the Decoction of <lb/>Hyſſop, or of
            Caſtor in white wine and water: or <pb n="8"/>
            <lb/>(to thoſe who can afford it) in the following Tin- <lb/>cture. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Tincture of ſingular uſe in en Epilepſy. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Leaves of Miſletoe of the Oak, two drams; <lb/>Peony-roots ſlic'd, half an
            ounce; Caſtor, a dram. <lb/>Put 'em in a cloſe veſſel, with Betony-water (or <lb/>ſimple
            Peony-water) and white wine, of each a <lb/>pound; Salt of Miſletoe of the Oak, or of
            com- <lb/>mon Miſletoe, two drams. Let 'em digeſt upon <lb/>a ſand heat for two days.
            And give three ounces <lb/>with every Doſe of the Powder preſcrib'd but <lb/>now. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Bag, that cures the Falling Sickneß by being <lb/>worn on the pit of the Stomach. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Roots and Seeds of male Peony, of each <lb/>two drams; Miſletoe of the Oak,
            Elk's-hoof, of <lb/>each a dram. Slice them, and bruiſe 'em. Then, <lb/>ſew 'em up in a
            very fine linnen bag to be hung <lb/>about the neck. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Specifick Powder for the Falling Sickneß, recom- <lb/>mended by all Authors. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Caſtor, Opopanax, Dragon's blood, An- <lb/>timony, and Peony-ſeeds, of each an
            equal quan- <lb/>tity: Make a Powder; of which take from half a <lb/>dram to a dram
            every morning in Wine or Black- <lb/>cherry-water. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Powder, uſeful in an Epilepſy. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Man's Scull prepar'd, an ounce; Miſle- <lb/>toe of the Oak, artificial
            Cinnabar, and Elk's- <lb/>hoof, of each half an ounce. Mix and make a <lb/>Powder, to be
            given from half a ſcruple to a ſcruple. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="9"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An Anti-Epileptick Electuary, calculated for thoſe <lb/>who have an Averſion to
            Powders. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take the Conſerves of male Peony and of Lil- <lb/>lies of the Valley, of each three
            ounces; the Seeds <lb/>and Roots of male Peony in Powder, of each two <lb/>drams;
            prepar'd Coral, a dram; Powder of Pearl <lb/>and Man's Skull prepar'd, of each two
            ſcruples; <lb/>Salt of Miſletoe of the Oak, a dram and a half. <lb/>With a ſufficient
            quantity of the Syrup of Coral <lb/>make an Electuary: of which take the quantity
            <lb/>of a Nutmeg morning and evening. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Confection, of good uſe in the Falling Sickneß. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Roots of male Peony pounded, an <lb/>ounce; Peony-ſeeds, half an ounce;
            Miſletoe of <lb/>the Oak, Elk's-hoof, and Man's Skull prepar'd, <lb/>of each two drams;
            Roots of Angelica, Contra- <lb/>yerva, and Virginian Snakeweed, of each a dram;
            <lb/>white Amber, Coral calcin'd, of each a dram; <lb/>Salt of Common Miſletoe, two
            drams; Su- <lb/>garcandy diſſolv'd in <hi rend="italic">Langius</hi>'s Epileptick-water,
            <lb/>eight ounces. Make a Confection, of which take <lb/>the bigneſs of a Nutmeg twice a
            day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Specifick Pills for the Falling Sickneß. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take the Powders preſcrib'd in the above-men- <lb/>tion'd Confection, add to them a
            convenient quan- <lb/>tity of Salt of Amber and Hartſhorn; and with <lb/>Balſam Capaivi
            make a maſs for Pills: of which <lb/>take three or four morning and evening, drinking
            <lb/>above 'em a draught of ſome appropriate Liquor. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An excellent Elixir for the Falling Sickneß. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Hungarian Vitriol, ſix pound. Diſtil <lb/>in a glaſs Retort with a ſand
            heat for 24 hours; <lb/>then let the ſame Retort luted with a large Recei- <lb/>ver, be
            put in a Reverberatory Fornace, that the <pb n="10"/>
            <lb/>acid Spirits may be diſlodg'd by a ſtrong fire. Let <lb/>the whole Liquor diſtill'd
            be drawn off in a leſſer <lb/>glaſs Retort with a ſand heat. Put that into a
            <lb/>matraſs, adding to it Roots of male Peony cut in- <lb/>to ſlices and dried, four
            ounces; Peony-ſeeds, and <lb/>ounce; Man's Skull prepar'd, Elk's-hoof, and red
            <lb/>Coral, of each half an ounce; Miſletoe of the <lb/>Oak, two drams. Let 'em digeſt
            upon a gentle <lb/>heat for ſeveral days, till a Tincture be extracted. <lb/>Then decant
            the liquor, and draw it off in a glaſs <lb/>Retort till a third part only remains,
            keeping the <lb/>liquor thus diſtill'd by it ſelf. To what remains <lb/>pour an equal
            quantity of the moſt rectified Spi- <lb/>rit of Wine impregnated with an infuſion of the
            <lb/>ſame ingredients; and let 'em digeſt for ſix days <lb/>in Horſe-dung. Make an
            Elixir to be given from <lb/>half a ſcruple to a ſcruple: Let the diſtill'd liquor
            <lb/>alſo be given from half a ſpoonful to a ſpoonful. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An Empyrical Medicine, experimented in the Fal- <lb/>ling Sickneß. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Roots and Seeds of Peony, of each two <lb/>drams; Elk's-hoof, and Man's Skull
            prepar'd, of <lb/>each a dram; Miſletoe of the Oak, half a dram. <lb/>Pound 'em coarſly,
            and ſew them up in a red ſilk <lb/>bag to be hung about the neck. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An Amulet, much commended againſt the Falling <lb/>Sickneß. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take the young ſhoot of an Elder, found grow- <lb/>ing on a Willow, and keep it
            about you for a <lb/>preſervative from the Falling Sickneſs. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Plaiſter for the Head, of good uſe for the Falling <lb/>Sickneſs. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Roots and Seeds of Peony, Caſtor, Miſletoe <pb n="11"/>
            <lb/>of the Oak, Man's Skull pounded very fine, of <lb/>each a dram; Betony Plaiſter,
            two drams; Caran, <lb/>Tacamahac, of each two drams. With a ſuffici- <lb/>ent quantity
            of Balſam Capaivi make a Plaiſer, <lb/>to be ſpread on leather and apply'd to the
            Sutures <lb/>of the Head, after it is ſhav'd. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An external Medicine approv'd in the Falling Sickneß. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take the Oyl of Amber, either by it ſelf, or <lb/>mix'd with Oleum Capaivi, and
            anoint the Tem- <lb/>ples and Noſtrils often. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A ſneezing Powder approv'd in the Falling Sickneß. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of white Hellebor, a dram; Caſtor and <lb/>Euphorbium, of each half a dram;
            ſweet Mar- <lb/>joram and Leaves of Rue, of each two drams. <lb/>Make a Powder to be
            ſnuff'd up the N<unclear>oſe.</unclear>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Gargal for the Falling Sickneß. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take the Decoction of Sage or of Hyſſop. <lb/>Diſſolve it in the Confection of
            Muſtard-ſeed; <lb/>and gargal it in the Mouth and Throat. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A diſtill'd Water, to be drunk after the taking of <lb/>the Powders preſcrib'd
            above. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Hungarian Vitriol, four pound; freſh <lb/>Man's Skull pounded, four ounces;
            Peony Roots <lb/>ſlic'd, ſix ounces. Bruiſe all in a Mortar, and pour <lb/>to them two
            pounds of Sack, or ſmall white wine, <lb/>or wine made of the juice of Black-cherries
            fer- <lb/>mented in a Cask. Then diſtill in a glaſs Retort <lb/>with a ſand heat. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Water for the Falling Sickneß. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Raſpings of Box-wood and Hungarian <lb/>Vitriol, of each two pounds; Leaves of
            Miſletoe, <pb n="12"/>
            <lb/>three handfuls; Leaves of Rue, two handfuls. <lb/>Bruiſe 'em together, and pour on
            four pounds of <lb/>Sack. Diſtil in a glaſs Cucurbit with a ſand heat. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Julep, recommended for the Falling Sickneß. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of common Vitriol, ſix pounds; Roots <lb/>of male Peony, ſix ounces; Miſletoe
            of the Oak <lb/>an ounce; green Walnuts, eight ounces. Slice 'em, <lb/>and bruiſe 'em
            together. Then diſtil with a ſand <lb/>heat in a glaz'd Pot with a glaſs Alembick over
            <lb/>it. Take a pint of this liquor; Waters of Black- <lb/>cherries and Lime-tree
            flowers, of each half a <lb/>pound; of the whiteſt Sugar, four ounces. Make <lb/>a
            Julep. Of which take two or three ounces <lb/>twice or thrice a day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Medicine, cry'd up by the Ancients for the Fal- <lb/>ling Sickneß. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Oxymel of Squills, or Mead with Hyſ- <lb/>ſop boyl'd in it, four or ſix
            ounces twice or thrice a <lb/>day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An approv'd Decoction for the Falling Sickneß. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Roots of male Peony, Angelica, Maſter- <lb/>wort, and Valerian, of each ſix
            drams; Leaves <lb/>of Betony, Sage, Lillies of the Valleys, and Penny- <lb/>royal, of
            each a handful; Seeds of Rue and Gith, <lb/>of each three drams; Peony, half an ounce;
            Rai- <lb/>ſins, three ounces; Liquorice, half an ounce. Be- <lb/>ing ſlic'd and bruis'd,
            boyl them in ſix pounds of <lb/>Spring-water, till a third part is conſum'd. To-
            <lb/>wards the end of the Decoction, add half a pound <lb/>or ten ounces of the wine of
            Black-cherries. Strain <lb/>out the liquor, and reſerve it for uſe in cloſe veſſels.
            <lb/>Take of this Apozeme 6 or 8 ounces twice a day. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="13"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A ſimple Medicine, that has cur'd many of the Falling <lb/>Sickneß, when other
            Remedies prov'd ineffectual. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the ſimple Decoction of Guaicum, ſix <lb/>or eight ounces, twice a day. And
            drink a ſecond <lb/>weaker Decoction for common drink. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An effectual method of curing an inveterate Falling <lb/>Sickneß. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take ſweet Mercury till it raiſes a Salivation: <lb/>and after the Salivation is
            over, let a Sudorifick Diet- <lb/>drink be made uſe of. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center size(2.0) space">
          <lb/>SECT. III. </head>
        <head rend="italic align-center size(2.0) space">
          <lb/>Receipts for Convulſive Motions in Children. </head>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Preſervative from Convulſions, for New-born <lb/>Infants. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>Ake a drop of the Oyl of Amber, or half a <lb/>ſpoonful of
            ſome Epileptick water: and give <lb/>it to the New-born Infant, twice a day. On the
            <lb/>third or fourth day cut an Iſſue in its Neck; and <lb/>if its Countenance be
            florid, take an ounce and a <lb/>half or two ounces of Blood out of the Jugular
            <lb/>Veins by Leeches. Anoint its Temples and Neck <lb/>with a Liniment, of the Oyl of
            Nutmegs by expreſ- <lb/>ſion, two drams; Oyl Capaivi, four drams; and <lb/>Amber, a
            ſcruple. At the ſame time hang about <lb/>its Neck, a bag with the Roots and Seeds of
            Peo- <lb/>ny, and a little Elk's-hoof. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="14"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An excellent Electuary, to be taken by the Nurſe, <lb/>to prevent Convulſions in
            the Child. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Conſerve of the flowers of Betony, of male <lb/>Peony, and of Roſemary
            flowers, of each two <lb/>ounces; Powder of the roots and flowers of male <lb/>Peony, of
            each two drams; red Coral prepar'd, <lb/>and the whiteſt Amber, of each a dram; roots of
            <lb/>Angelica and Zedoary prepar'd, of each half a <lb/>dram. With a ſufficient quantity
            of the Syrup of <lb/>Peony, make an Electuary; of which let the Nurſe <lb/>take the
            quantity of a Nutmeg morning and even- <lb/>ing. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Tablets taken with good ſucceſs by Nurſes, to prevent <lb/>Convulſions in Children. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the roots of male Peony, two drams; <lb/>Peony-ſeeds, a dram. Make a
            Powder; to be <lb/>made into Tablets with a ſcruple of the Oyl of <lb/>Amber, and three
            ounces of fine loaf Sugar diſ- <lb/>ſolv'd in the water of Lime-tree flowers, and boyl'd
            <lb/>to a due conſiſtency. Let the Nurſe eat one of <lb/>theſe, weighing half a dram,
            every ſixth hour. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An uſeful Liniment for Children in Convulſions. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take the Oyl of Capaivi and of Caſtor, of each <lb/>two drams; Oyl of Amber, half a
            dram. Make a <lb/>Liniment, to be anointed on the Temples, Noſtrils <lb/>and Neck of the
            Child. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Plaiſter, of good uſe in Children's Convulſions. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Plaiſter Oxycroceum, two parts; <lb/>Galbanum diſſolv'd, one part; Oyl
            of Amber, a <lb/>ſcruple. Make a Plaiſter to be apply'd to the ſoles <lb/>of the Child's
            feet. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="15"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Powder approv'd in Childrens Convulſions. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Man's Skull prepar'd, Peony-ſeeds, Elk's- <lb/>hoof, and Pearl prepar'd, of
            each half a dram; <lb/>Amber-griſe, ſix grains. Make a Powder: and give <lb/>the Child
            ſix grains, three or four times a day, in a <lb/>ſpoonful of the following Liquor. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Julep for a Vehicle to the Powders. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Black-cherry-water, three ounces; <hi rend="italic">Lan- <lb/>gius</hi>'s
            Epileptick water, an ounce; pearl'd Sugar, <lb/>two drams. Mix. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Powder for Childrens Convulſions. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Man's Skull prepar'd and Pearl, of each <lb/>half a dram; Salt of Amber, a
            ſcruple; pearl'd <lb/>Sugar, a dram. Doſe half a ſcruple. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Drops, of ſovereign uſe for Convulſions in Children. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take three drops of the Spirit of Hartſhorn e- <lb/>very ſixth or eighth hour in a
            ſpoonful of the Julep <lb/>preſcrib'd above. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An eaſy Medicine for the Poor, againſt Childrens <lb/>Convulſions. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Powder of the root of wild Vale- <lb/>rian, from half a ſcruple to a
            ſcruple. Give it twice <lb/>a day in a ſpoonful of Milk, or ſome proper liquor. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A famous Medicine, often experimented in the <lb/>Convulſions of Children. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take all the gall contain'd within the Gall-blad- <lb/>der of a ſucking Whelp; and
            give it to the Child <lb/>with the water of Lime-tree flowers. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A diſtill'd Water, for Convulſions in Children. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the roots of male Peony, freſh, and cut <pb n="16"/>
            <lb/>into ſlices, ſix ounces; Hungarian Vitriol, eight <lb/>ounces; Man's Skull, two
            ounces; <hi rend="italic">Langius</hi>'s Epi- <lb/>leptick water, half a pound. Mix and
            diſtil in a <lb/>glaſs Retort with a ſand heat. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A ſovereign Juice for Convulſions in Children. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the roots of male Peony, freſh, and <lb/>ſlic'd four ounces. Bruiſe them in
            a marble mor- <lb/>tar, and pour upon them a pound of Sack. Then <lb/>make a ſtrong
            expreſſion, to which add half an <lb/>ounce of pearl'd Sugar. Reſerve it for uſe in a
            cloſe <lb/>glaſs. Doſe, a ſpoonful or two, twice a day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A ſucceßful Medicine, for Convulſions in Chil- <lb/>dren occaſion'd by Worms. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Powder of the roots of Virginian <lb/>Snakeweed, a dram; Coral calcin'd
            till it becomes <lb/>white, half a dram. Doſe, from half a ſcruple to <lb/>a ſcruple
            twice a day for three days together, (a <lb/>Purge of Mercurius Dulcis and Roſin of
            Jalap be- <lb/>ing premis'd) drinking after it the Decoction of <lb/>Graſs-roots. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Plaiſter for the Belly, in the Convulſions of Chil- <lb/>dren occaſion'd by
            Worms. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Species of Hiera, a dram and a <lb/>half; Venice Treacle, two drams.
            Make a Plai- <lb/>ſter to be apply'd to the Belly. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Fomentation, of good uſe, in the Convulſions of <lb/>Children, occaſion'd by
            ſharp humours in the <lb/>Stomach and Guts. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the leaves of Chamomile ſlic'd ſmall, <lb/>three handfuls; put 'em into two
            bags of fine lin- <lb/>nen or ſilk: which being dipt in warm Milk and <lb/>ſqueez'd, are
            to be apply'd by turns to the Belly. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="17"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Cataplaſm, uſeful on the ſame occaſion. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take the tops or flowers of Mallows ſlic'd; boyl <lb/>them in freſh Butter or
            Hogs-lard; and let them be <lb/>applied to the Belly in the form of a Cataplaſm or
            <lb/>Liniment. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center size(2.0) space">
          <lb/>SECT. IV. </head>
        <head rend="italic align-center size(2.0) space">
          <lb/>Recipe's for Convulſions and Cramps in <lb/>Adult Perſons. </head>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A proper Purge for Convulſions, in which the origine <lb/>and ſource of the Nerves
            is chiefly affected. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>Ake of <hi rend="italic">Crato</hi>'s Pills of <hi
              rend="italic">Amber</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Bontius</hi>'s Pills <lb/>of Tartar,
            two drams; Roſin of Jalap, ſixteen <lb/>grains; Caſtor, a ſcruple; Oyl of Roſemary, or
            <lb/>Oyl of Amber, half a ſcruple. With a ſufficient <lb/>quantity of Gum Ammoniack
            diſſolv'd in Hyſteri- <lb/>cal water, make ſixteen Pills, of which four are to <lb/>be
            taken every ſixth or ſeventh day; vomiting <lb/>and bleeind being premis'd. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A purging Decoction, proper on the ſame occaſion. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Roots of Polipody of the Oak, ſharp <lb/>pointed Dock prepar'd, and Chervil,
            of each ſix <lb/>drams; roots of male Peony, three drams; leaves <lb/>of Betony,
            Germander, Ground-pine, Vervain, and <lb/>male Fluellin, of each a handful; Seeds of
            Baſtard- <lb/>Saffron and Burr-dock, of each three drams. Boyl <lb/>all in four pints of
            Spring-water till the half is con- <lb/>ſum'd. Then add a pint of white Wine. Strain <pb
              n="18"/>
            <lb/>it out into a Matrace: to which put, of the beſt <lb/>Senna leaves, an ounce;
            Rhubarb ſix drams; <lb/>Gummy Turbith, half an ounce; Epithymum, <lb/>yellow Saunders,
            of each two drams; Salt of <lb/>Wormwood and of Scurvy-graſs, of each a dram; <lb/>the
            yellow coats of Oranges, two drams. Let 'em <lb/>ſtand in a cloſe Digeſtion for twelve
            hours with a <lb/>ſand heat. Reſerve the ſtraining for uſe; and, if <lb/>there be
            occaſion, ſweeten it with a ſufficient quan- <lb/>tity of Syrup Augnſtanus, or of the
            Syrup of <lb/>Cichory with Rhubarb. Doſe, ſix ounces, once or <lb/>twice a week. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Specifick againſt Convulſions, calculated for Per- <lb/>ſons of a hot thin
            Conſtitution; in whom <lb/>the origine of the Nerves is affected. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Conſerve of the flowers of Betony, <lb/>Tamarisk, and male Peony, of
            each two ounces; <lb/>Species Diamargariton frigidæ, a dram and a half; <lb/>Peony roots
            and ſeeds, in Powder, of each a dram; <lb/>red Coral prepar'd, two drams; Vitriol of
            Steel, <lb/>two ſcruples; Salt of Wormwood, two drams; <lb/>Juice of Oranges, what
            ſuffices. Make an Ele- <lb/>ctuary, to be taken (to the bigneſs of a Nutmeg) <lb/>twice
            or thrice a day; drinking after it a draught <lb/>of the following Julep. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take the water of Walnuts, ſimple, and Black- <lb/>cherry-water, of each half a
            pound; Water of Snails, <lb/>three ounces; Syrup of male Peony flowers, two <lb/>ounces.
            Make a Julep: Doſe from an ounce and <lb/>a half to two ounces. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Specifick Powder for ſuch Convulſions in a hot <lb/>thin temperament. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of red Coral, ground with the juyce of O- <lb/>ranges on a marble or in a
            glaſs mortar, and dried, <pb n="19"/>
            <lb/>half an ounce; Powder of Miſletoe of the Oak, <lb/>and of the roots of male Peony,
            of each two drams; <lb/>Sugar of Pearl, three drams. Make a Powder, and <lb/>take from a
            ſcruple to half a dram, twice or thrice <lb/>a day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Another Powder for the ſame purpoſe. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Species of Diamargariton frigidæ, <lb/>two drams; Salt of Wormwood,
            three drams; Aron <lb/>roots in powder, a dram. Mix, and make a powder <lb/>to be
            divided into twenty parts: of which take one <lb/>in the morning, and at four of the
            clock after noon. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A plain cheap Powder, for Convulſions in a hot <lb/>thin temperament; relating
            chiefly to the <lb/>origine of the Nerves. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the roots of Butter-burr in Powder, <lb/>an ounce. Doſe, from half a dram
            to a dram <lb/>twice a day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A diſtill'd Water, recommended for ſuch Convulſions <lb/>in a hot thin temperament. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take the leaves of Burr-dock and Aron, of each <lb/>ſix handfuls. Slice 'em, and
            mix 'em together. <lb/>Then diſtil. Doſe, two or three ounces, to be ta- <lb/>ken after
            every doſe of the Powders or Electuary <lb/>above preſcrib'd. To better it, you may add
            two <lb/>drams of our Steel prepar'd, to two pounds of the <lb/>Water. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An Apozem, for the Convulſions of Perſons of a hot <lb/>thin Conſtitution. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take ſhavings of Ivory and Hartſhorn, of each <lb/>three drams; roots of Chervil,
            Burdock and Va- <lb/>lerian, of each half an ounce; leaves of Betony, <pb n="20"/>
            <lb/>Ground-pine, Scolopendrium, and tops of Tama- <lb/>risk, of each a handful; Barks
            of Tamarisk and <lb/>Bitter-ſweet, of each half an ounce. Boyl 'em in <lb/>four pounds
            of Spring-water, till a third be con- <lb/>ſum'd. Then add eight ounces of white Wine.
            <lb/>Strain it into a flaggon, to which put leaves of <lb/>Brooklime and Cuckow-flower,
            of each a hand- <lb/>ful. Let all ſtand in a hot cloſe Infuſion for four <lb/>hours;
            then reſerve the ſtraining in glaſſes cloſe <lb/>ſtopt. Doſe, ſix ounces twice a day,
            after the <lb/>Powders or Electuaries. Sometimes you may in- <lb/>fuſe two drams of our
            Steel in it; and exhibit it <lb/>in the ſame manner. And in the Summer time ex-
            <lb/>change it with the Mineral Spaws. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Specifick Electuary for Convulſions proceeding <lb/>from the origine of the
            Nerves in a phleg- <lb/>matick, cold, fat, conſtitution. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Conſerve of Roſemary-flowers, and of the <lb/>yellow coats of Oranges and
            Limons, of each two <lb/>ounces; Walnuts and Myrobalans, condited, of <lb/>each two in
            number; Aloes-wood, yellow Saun- <lb/>ders, roots of Snakeweed, Contrayerva, Angelica,
            <lb/>and Aron, of each a dram; Vitriol of Mars or <lb/>prepar'd Steel, four ſcruples;
            Salt of Wormwood <lb/>and of Scurvy-graſs, of each a dram. With a <lb/>ſufficient
            quantity of Preſerve of Walnuts, make an <lb/>Electuary; of which take the quantity of a
            Nut- <lb/>meg twice a day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Tablets, of good uſe againſt Convulſions of the <lb/>ſame kind. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take roots of male Peony, Angelica, red Coral <lb/>prepar'd, of each two drams;
            Sugar diſſolv'd in <lb/>Snail-water and boyl'd up to the Conſiſtency of <pb n="21"/>
            <lb/>Tablets, ſix ounces; Oyl of Amber highly recti- <lb/>fied, half a dram. Make
            Tablets weighing half a <lb/>dram a piece: of which one or two are to be ta- <lb/>ken
            twice or thrice a day, drinking after 'em a doſe <lb/>of ſome convenient liquor. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Specifick Pills for Convulſions from the origine of <lb/>the Nerves in a cold
            temperament. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take roots of Virginian Snakeweed, Contra- <lb/>yerva, and Valerian, of each two
            drams; prepar'd <lb/>red Coral and Pearl, of each a dram; Winter's- <lb/>bark and roots
            of Baſtard-Dittany, of each a dram; <lb/>Vitriol of Mars, Salt of Wormwood, of each a
            <lb/>dram and a half; Extract of Centory, two drams; <lb/>Gum Ammoniack diſſolv'd in
            Hyſterical-water, <lb/>what ſuffices. Make a maſs for Pills; four of which <lb/>are to
            be taken in the morning, and at four in the <lb/>afternoon. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Drops, very proper on the ſame occaſion. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Spirit of Hartſhorn, or of Soot, or of <lb/>Man's blood, or of Sal
            Armoniack, from ten to <lb/>twelve drops, morning and evening, in a ſpoonful <lb/>of the
            following Julep. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Water of Earth-worms and of Snails, of <lb/>each four Ounces; Water of Walnuts
            ſimple, four <lb/>ounces; Radiſh-water compound, two ounces; <lb/>double refin'd Sugar,
            two ounces. Make a Julep. <lb/>Doſe, two or ſix ſpoonfuls twice a day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An excellent diſtill'd Water, for Convulſions, from the <lb/>origine of the Nerves
            in a cold Conſtitution. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take leaves of Betony, Vervain, Sage, Cuckow- <lb/>flowers, Aron, Burdock, of each
            two handfuls; <lb/>green Walnuts, in number twenty; ſix coats of <pb n="22"/>
            <lb/>Oranges, and four of Limons; Cardamum and <lb/>Cubebs, of each a dram. Being ſlic'd
            and bruis'd, <lb/>pour to 'em ſix pounds of whey made with Syder <lb/>or white Wine.
            Then diſtil according to Art. Doſe, <lb/>two or three ounces twice a day, after every
            Pow- <lb/>der or Bolus. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A ſtronger diſtill'd Water for Convulſions in a cold <lb/>Conſtitution. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Hoglice clean'd, a pound; Cloves ſlic'd, <lb/>half an ounce; pour to them
            two pounds of white <lb/>Wine; and diſtil in a glaſs Cucurbit. Doſe, an <lb/>ounce twice
            a day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Specifick Medicine for Convulſions, of eaſy and <lb/>cheap preparation, for the
            Poor. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Conſerve of the leaves of Rue, (or <lb/>of the leaves of the Tree of
            Life) made with an e- <lb/>qual part of Sugar, ſix ounces. Take the quantity of <lb/>a
            Nutmeg twice a day, drinking after it the Deco- <lb/>ction of the Seeds and Roots of
            Burdock boyl'd in <lb/>Whey and white Wine. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Specifick Powder and Juice for the Poor. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take the Powder of Hoglice prepar'd, three <lb/>drams; Aniſeſeeds, a dram. Make a
            Powder to <lb/>be divided into ten parts; taking one of 'em twice <lb/>a day.—Or, Bruiſe
            twelve Hoglice in white <lb/>Wine, and expreſs the Juice to be taken twice a <lb/>day.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A ſucceßful Medicine, for Convulſions occaſion'd by <lb/>a ſcorbutick diſpoſition
            of the nervous Juice. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Sulphur of Antimony, ſix grains; <lb/>ſweet Mercury, a ſcruple; Roſin
            of Jalap, four <lb/>grains; Ginger, ſix grains. Beat them together in <pb n="23"/>
            <lb/>a marble Mortar. With a dram of the Conſerve <lb/>of Violets make a Bolus to be
            repeated every ſixth <lb/>or ſeventh hour. It uſes to give two or three Vo- <lb/>mits,
            and three or four ſtools. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Pills, preſcrib'd with good ſucceſs, for Convulſions a- <lb/>riſing from a
            ſcorbutick diſpoſition of the ner- <lb/>vous Juice. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the roots of male Peony, half an ounce; <lb/>Virginian Snakeweed,
            Contrayerva, and Baſtard- <lb/>Dittany, of each two drams; Man's Skull prepar'd, <lb/>a
            dram and a half; Elk's-hoof, two drams; red <lb/>Coral prepar'd and Pearls in powder, of
            each half <lb/>a dram; Salt of Wormwood, two drams; Salt of <lb/>Coral, a dram; Syrup of
            the flowers of male Peo- <lb/>ny, what ſuffices to make a maſs for Pills: four of
            <lb/>which are to be taken twice a day, drinking after <lb/>them a draught of the
            following Julep. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Julep, experienc'd in the ſame caſe. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Water of the flowers of male Peony, of <lb/>black Cherries, and of Walnuts, of
            each four oun- <lb/>ces; <hi rend="italic">Langius</hi>'s Epileptick-water, two ounces;
            Sy- <lb/>rup of Peony-flowers, an ounce and a half; Caſtor <lb/>ty'd in a bag and hung
            in the glaſs, a dram. Make <lb/>a Julep. To a draught of which you may add a <lb/>doſe
            of the Spirit of Hartſhorn. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A proper Julep for Hyſterical Convulſions, or <lb/>Fits of the Mother. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Pennyroyal and Mugwort-water, of each <lb/>four ounces; Briony-water compound,
            two ounces; <lb/>Caſtor ty'd in a bag and hung up in the glaſs, half <lb/>a dram; double
            refin'd Sugar, an ounce. Mix and <lb/>make a Julep: adding to every draught twenty
            <lb/>drops of the Spirit of Hartſhorn. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="24"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Drops, commended in Fits of the Mother. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Tincture of Caſtor, from a ſcruple <lb/>to half a dram; in a draught of
            ſmall beer. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An excellent Tincture for Hyſterick Convulſions. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Aſſa fœtida or Galbanum, two ounces. <lb/>Diſſolve 'em in Spirit of Wine,
            till a red Tincture <lb/>is extracted: a ſcruple of which is to be taken in <lb/>two or
            three ſpoonfuls of Mugwort-water. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Medicine for Fits of the Mother, mightily cry'd <lb/>up by <hi rend="roman"
              >Riverius</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Musk and Dragons-blood, of each a ſcru- <lb/>ple; in three or four ounces of
            Water of Navews. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Medicine, accounted by ſome infallible in Fits <lb/>of the Mother. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take the Seeds of Parſnips or of Columbines in <lb/>Wine or ſome proper Water. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A proper Purge in Hyſterical Caſes. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the greater fetid Pills, a dram; Roſin of <lb/>Jalap, twelve grains; Tartar
            vitriolar and Caſtor, <lb/>of each a ſcruple; with a ſufficient quantity of Gum
            <lb/>Ammoniack diſſolv'd in Hyſterical-water, make <lb/>twelve Pills for three Doſes: to
            be taken once in <lb/>ſix or ſeven days. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A purging Powder, recommended in the ſame caſe. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Roſin of Jalap, eighteen grains; <lb/>Calomelanos, a dram; Caſtor, a
            ſcruple. Make <lb/>a Powder for three doſes; to be taken in the pap <lb/>of a boil'd
              App<unclear>l</unclear>e or Conſerve of Borrage. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An approv'd Specifick for Hyſterical Convulſions. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Fæcula of Briony, Aſſa fœtida, and Caſtor, <pb n="25"/>
            <lb/>of each a dram; Salt of Coral, Amber, and Tin; <lb/>of each half a dram; Galbanum
            diſſolv'd in Hy- <lb/>ſterick-water, what ſuffices to make a maſs. Doſe <lb/>from half a
            ſcruple to a ſcruple, morning and e- <lb/>vening; drinking after it an ounce and a half
            of <lb/>the following Julep. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Mugwort and Pennyroyal-water, of each <lb/>half a pound; Hysterick-water four
            ounces; Tin- <lb/>cture of Caſtor, half an ounce; Syrup of Coral, an <lb/>ounce and a
            half. Mix. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A choice Preſcription for Fits of the Mother. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take the Seeds of wild Parſnips and Nettles, of <lb/>each two drams; Vitriol of
            Steel, a dram; Extract <lb/>of Gentian and Mugwort, of each a dram and a <lb/>half;
            Syrup of Mugwort, what ſuffices. Make a <lb/>maſs, of which take half a dram as above.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A choice Powder for Fits of the Mother. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Roots of Virginian Snakeweed, and Con- <lb/>trayerva, of each a dram and a
            half; Coral pre- <lb/>par'd, Pearl, whiteſt Amber, of each a dram. Make <lb/>a Powder,
            of which half a dram is to be taken <lb/>morning and evening in a proper Vehicle. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An Electuary, of good uſe in Hyſterical caſes. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Conſerve of the flowers of Lillies of the <lb/>Valley, male Peony, and Betony,
            of each two <lb/>ounces; Peony-ſeeds and red Coral prepar'd, of <lb/>each two drams;
            Powder of Baſtard-Dittany, a <lb/>dram and a half; Salt of Wormwood, two drams:
            <lb/>With a ſufficient quantity of the Syrup of Citron- <lb/>peel, make an Electuary.
            Doſe, the bigneſs of a <lb/>Nutmeg, morning and evening. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A choice diſtill'd Water, for Hyſterical caſes. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take leaves of Pennyroyal, Feverfew, both Sou- <pb n="26"/>
            <lb/>thernwoods, Calamint, Nep, both Horehounds, of <lb/>each a handful; Briony-root,
            four ounces; Parſ- <lb/>nip-ſeeds, two drams: Being ſlic'd and bruis'd, <lb/>pour to
            them ſix pound of white Wine or Syder, <lb/>and diſtil according to Art. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Decoction, approv'd in Hyſterical Convulſions. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Roots of Male Peony, Angelica, and Va- <lb/>lerian, of each half an ounce;
            Leaves of Mug- <lb/>wort, Calamint, Pennyroyal, and Miſletoe of the <lb/>Oak, of each a
            handful; Seeds of both the wild <lb/>Parſnips, of each three drams; Raiſins, a handful.
            <lb/>Let them boyl in four pound of Spring-water till <lb/>the half is waſted; then add
            a pint and a half of <lb/>white Wine. Reſerve the ſtraining for uſe in cloſe
            <lb/>Veſſels. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A ſimple and eaſy Infuſion, of good uſe in Hyſte- <lb/>rical caſes. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Seeds of wild Parſnips, bruis'd, two <lb/>ounces: Put 'em into a bottle
            with two pints of <lb/>white Wine. Of which drink two ounces twice a <lb/>day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Purging Pills, of good uſe in Convulſions retain- <lb/>ing to the Hypochondriack
            Illneß. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of choice Senna, an ounce; Rhubarb, ſix <lb/>drams; Epithymum, three drams;
            yellow Saun- <lb/>ders, two drams; Celtick Spike, two drams: Be- <lb/>ing ſlic'd and
            bruis'd, digeſt them in white Wine <lb/>and Fumitory-water, of each ten ounces, for 48
            <lb/>hours. Then take the clear ſtraining, and let it <lb/>evacuate with a gentle heat
            to the conſiſtence <lb/>of an Extract; adding towards the latter end, Pow- <lb/>der of
            Senna, Rhubarb, and Cream of Tartar, of <lb/>each two drams. Beat 'em together in a
            glaſs Mor- <lb/> <pb n="27"/>
            <choice>
              <corr>tar</corr>
              <sic>atr</sic>
            </choice>, and reduce them to the conſiſtency of Pills. <lb/>Doſe, from two ſcruples to
            a dram. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Choice alterative Pills for Hypochondriack Convul- <lb/>ſions in a cold
            Conſtitution of Body. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take the Troches of Rhubarb, Powdre of A- <lb/>ron-roots, and Winters-bark, of each
            two drams; <lb/>Roots of Virginian Snakeweed, Contrayerva, Dia- <lb/>trion Santalon, and
            Crabs-eyes, of each a dram; <lb/>Extract of Gentian and Centory, of each a dram <lb/>and
            a half; Gum Ammoniack diſſolv'd in a ſuffici- <lb/>ent quantity of Water of Earthworms,
            what ſuffi- <lb/>ces to make a maſs for Pills; of which four are to <lb/>be taken in the
            morning, and at four of the clock <lb/>in the afternoon: Drinking after them a draught
            <lb/>of Wormwood or Chalybeatwine. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An Electuary, approv'd in Hypochondriack Con- <lb/>vulſions, with a cold
            Conſtitution. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Conſerve of the yellow coats of Oranges <lb/>and Limons, of each three ounces;
            Myrobalans <lb/>condited, two in number; Species Aromaticæ Ro- <lb/>ſatæ, and
            Winters-bark, of each two drams; Salt <lb/>of Wormwood, two drams; Vitriol of Steel, two
            <lb/>drams (or prepar'd Steel, three drams.) With a <lb/>ſufficient quantity of the
            Juice of Citron-peel, make <lb/>an Electuary: of which let him take the bigneſs of
            <lb/>a Nutmeg twice a day, drinking upon it a draught <lb/>of Wormwood-wine, or of Wine
            in which the <lb/>bark or flowers of Tamarisk are infus'd. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Drops, exceeding all other Medicines in this caſe. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take twelve drops of the Spirit of Soot, or of <lb/>Blood, or of Hartſhorn, twice a
            day, in an appropri- <lb/>ate Vehicle. I have ſeen this more beneficial than <lb/>all
            other Medicines. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="28"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A proper Medicine for Hypochondriacal Convulſi- <lb/>ons in a hot temperament. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Conſerve of Hips, ſix ounces; (or Conſerve <lb/>of Tamarisk flowers, and
            Woodſorrel leaves, of <lb/>each three ounces;) Species Diarrhodon Abbatis,
            <lb/>Confection Alkermes, of each a dram; Ivory in <lb/>Powder, a dram and a half; Salt
            of Tamarisk and <lb/>Wormwood, of each a dram. With a ſufficient <lb/>quantity of Syrup
            of the Juice of Citrons, or Syrup <lb/>of Clove-gilly-flowers, make an Opiat, of which
            <lb/>take the bigneſs of a Nutmeg twice a day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Tablets calculated for the ſame caſe. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Powder of Ivory, two drams; Powder of <lb/>Pearls, a dram; Species Diarrhodon
            Abbatis and <lb/>Diamargariton frigid, of each a dram and a half. <lb/>Make a fine
            Powder, to which add double refin'd <lb/>Sugar diſſolv'd in Bawm-water, and boyl'd up to
            a <lb/>due conſiſtence, ſix ounces. Make Tablets accord- <lb/>ing to Art. Doſe, from a
            dram and a half to two <lb/>drams twice a day. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>To this, we may add our natural Spaws, which <lb/>are always of good uſe; and in
            want of them the <lb/>Artificial Spaws; as alſo whey, and in caſe of an
            <lb/>extraordinary leanneſs Aſſes-milk drunk every day. <lb/>Beſides, Cauteries and
            Iſſues are genarally of good <lb/>uſe in this caſe. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Medicines preſcrib'd with extraordinary ſucceſs <lb/>for a Convulſive Periodical
            Aſthma. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of our Sulphur of Antimony, ſix grains; <lb/>Cream of Tartar, ſix grains. Mix,
            to be taken <lb/>in the pap of a Codline. It will give four or five <lb/>Vomits. </p>
          <pb n="29"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Calomelanos, twelve grains; Roſin of <lb/>Jalap, five grains; Caſtor, four
            Grains. With a <lb/>ſufficient quantity of Gum Ammoniack diſſolv'd, <lb/>make four
            Pills, to be taken four days after the <lb/>Vomit, and repeated after ſix or ſeven days. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Snail-water, ſix ounces; Water of <lb/>Earth-worms, four ounces; Water of
            Pennyroyal <lb/>and Rue, of each four ounces; Hyſterick-water, <lb/>three ounces; Caſtor
            ty'd in a bag and hung in the <lb/><choice>
              <corr/>
              <sic>the </sic>
            </choice>glaſs, half a dram; double refin'd Sugar, an <lb/>ounce. Mix and make a Julep;
            of which take <lb/>ſix or ſeven ſpoonfuls with twelve grains of the <lb/>Tincture of
            Antimony, every day morning and e- <lb/>vening. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>To cure a Convulſive Cough, eſpecially in Children. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Give a gentle Vomit and Purge; apply a Bliſter <lb/>to the Neck, and, if the
            Diſeaſe be obſtinate, cut an <lb/>Iſſue in the nape of the Neck, or in the Arm, or in
            <lb/>the Armpits. Confine them to a Diet-drink or <lb/>Sarſa, China, Saunders, ſhavings
            of Ivory and <lb/>Hartſhorn, with ſome Diuretick Ingredients. For <lb/>a Specifick
            Remedy, Cupmoſs given every day in <lb/>Powder or boyl'd in Milk is commended; to which
            <lb/>we may add the Decoction of Hyſſop, or of Caſtor <lb/>and Saffron. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <pb n="30"/>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center size(2.0) space">
          <lb/>SECT. V. </head>
        <head rend="italic align-center size(2.0) space">
          <lb/>Preſcriptions for the Scurvy. </head>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Purge, to commence the cure of a hot (ſulphureous <lb/>ſaline) Scurvy, if
            vomiting be inconvenient. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>Ake of Senna-leaves, an ounce; Rhubarb, ſix <lb/>drams;
            Epithymum, three drams; Roots of <lb/>Polypody of the Oak, and Engliſh Rhubarb dried,
            <lb/>of each half an ounce; yellow Saunders, two drams; <lb/>Celtick Spike, half a dram;
            Salt of Wormwood, <lb/>two drams. Being ſlic'd and bruis'd, let 'em digeſt <lb/>in a
            Matrace upon a ſand-heat, with white Wine <lb/>and Fumitory-water, of each a pound (or
            with two <lb/>pounds of our Magiſtral Antiſcorbutick-water) for <lb/>two days. Then let
            the clear ſtraining evaporate <lb/>upon a gentle Bath heat to the conſiſtence of Ho-
            <lb/>ny: and after that, add Powder of Senna-leaves <lb/>and Rhubarb, of each a dram and
            a half; <lb/>Species Diatrion Santalon, a dram; Cream of Tar- <lb/>tar, a dram and a
            half. Make a maſs for Pills, to <lb/>be given from half a dram to a dram. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Make a purging Syrup of the ſame Infuſion, by <lb/>evaporating it with a gentle
            heat to a due Conſi- <lb/>ſtence; and adding towards the latter end Manna <lb/>paſs'd
            through a Searce and double refin'd Sugar, <lb/>of each two drams. Doſe, from one to two
            ſpoon- <lb/>fuls. Or, </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Let four or ſix ounces of the Tincture be given <lb/>for a doſe, adding Cream of
            Tartar, half a dram; <lb/>and, if there be need of ſweetning, Syrup of Ap- <lb/>ples,
            three drams. Or, </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>To the Tincture preſcrib'd let ſix drams of clean <pb n="31"/>
            <lb/>Corants be put; and ſet all in a warm digeſtion <lb/>till the Corants ſwell: then
            take them out, and let <lb/>the liquor evaporate to the Conſiſtency of a Syrup,
            <lb/>adding Sugar and Manna paſs'd through a Searce, <lb/>of each an ounce and a half.
            Then put the Co- <lb/>rants in again, and keep the Medicine in a glaz'd <lb/>Veſſel well
            ſtop'd. Or, </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>To the Tincture preſcrib'd, evaporated to a <lb/>half; add freſh Caſſia, and Pulp
            of Tamarinds <lb/>extracted with Antiſcorbutick-water, of each three <lb/>ounces;
            Conſerve of Violets and of Damask Ro- <lb/>ſes, of each two Ounces, the greater compound
            <lb/>Powder of Senna, a dram; Rhubarb in powder, <lb/>half an ounce; Cream of Tartar,
            and Species Dia- <lb/>trion Santalon, of each two drams. Beat all to- <lb/>gether in a
            Stone Mortar, till they're reduc'd to <lb/>the form of an Electuary. Doſe, the quantity
            of a <lb/>Walnut, more or leſs, according to the operation. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Purge in a ſmall quantity, againſt a hot Scurvy, <lb/>calculated for thoſe whoſe
            Stomachs are nice. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Roſin of Scammony, from four to eight <lb/>grains; Cream of Tartar, half a
            ſcruple; Celtick <lb/>Spike, ſix grains. Mix and make a Powder to be <lb/>given in a
            ſpoonful of Panada, or form'd into <lb/>Pills. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Purging Pills, to commence the cure of a cold <lb/>(Nitro-ſulphureous) Scurvy. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Stomachick Pills with Gums, two <lb/>drams; Roſin of Jalap, twenty
            grains, Tartar vitrio- <lb/>lated, ſixteen grains; Oyl of Juniper, half a ſcruple.
            <lb/>With a ſufficient quantity of Gum Ammoniack <lb/>diſſolv'd in Water of Earth-worms,
            make ſixteen <lb/>Pills; to be taken four at a time, once a week. Or, </p>
          <pb n="32"/>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of <hi rend="italic">Bontius</hi>'s Pills of Tartar, a dram and a <lb/>half;
            Roſin of Jalap, twelve grains; Salt of Tar- <lb/>tar, half a ſcruple. With a ſufficient
            quantity of <lb/>Syrupus Auguſtanus, make twelve Pills for three <lb/>Doſes. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Extract of <hi rend="italic">Ruffius</hi>'s Pill a dram; Ex- <lb/>tract
            of black Hellebor, a ſcruple; ſalt of Tartar <lb/>half a dram. With a ſufficient
            quantity of Ammo- <lb/>niacum diſſolv'd, make nine Pills for three days. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A purging Infuſion, Syrup, and Extract, proper <lb/>in a hot Scurvy. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Senna-leaves, an ounce; Rhubarb, ſix <lb/>drams; Mechoacan and Gummy
            Turbith, of each <lb/>half an ounce; ſtrings of black Hellebor, three <lb/>drams; Salt
            of Tartar, two ounces; yellow <lb/>Saunders, a dram and a half; Winters-bark, two
            <lb/>drams. Being ſlic'd and bruis'd, let 'em digeſt for <lb/>two days with two pounds
            of white Wine. Strain <lb/>out the clear Tincture without expreſſion, and <lb/>give ſix
            ounces of it for a doſe. Or, reduce it to <lb/>a Syrup or Extract, after the manner
            above pre- <lb/>ſcrib'd in the Tincture for the cold Scurvy. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A ſtrong purging Tincture for the hot Scurvy. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Salt of Tartar, an ounce; ſmall <lb/>ſpirit of Wine, a pound and a
            half: Let 'em di- <lb/>geſt, till it turns yellow. Pour the liquor off <lb/>the Fæces by
            inclination, and infuſe it in ſtrings of <lb/>black Hellebor ſteep'd in Vinegar, an
            ounce; yel- <lb/>low Saunders, a dram; the yellow coats of Oran- <lb/>ges, a dram and a
            half. Let 'em ſtand in a warm <lb/>and cloſe digeſtion for three days. Take the clear
            <lb/>ſtraining, and diſtil it in a bath heat to a half: <lb/>and keep the remaining
            liquor, of which a robuſt <lb/>perſon may take a ſpoonful, or a ſpoonful and a
            <lb/>half. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="33"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Purgative Decoction for the hot Scurvy. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Roots of ſharp-pointed Dock, Polipody <lb/>of the Oak, ſtinging Nettles,
            Chervil, of each ſix <lb/>drams; leaves of Agrimony and Speedwell, of each <lb/>a
            handful; white and yellow Saunders, of each a <lb/>dram and a half; Baſtard Saffron, an
            ounce; Tar- <lb/>tar of white Wine, half an ounce: Let 'em boyl in <lb/>two pounds an a
            half of Spring-water to a half. <lb/>Then add a pound of Rheniſh Wine, and ſtrain it
            <lb/>preſently; then put into it the beſt Senna, half an <lb/>ounce; Rhubarb, ſix drams;
            ſtrings of black Hel- <lb/>lebor, half an ounce; the yellow coats of Oran- <lb/>ges, two
            drams: Make a cloſe and warm Infuſi- <lb/>on for twelve hours. Then ſtrain out the
            liquor, <lb/>to be kept in a glaſs cloſe ſtop'd, and taken from <lb/>five to ſix drams.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An excellent Menſtruum for extracting Antiſcorbu- <lb/>tick Tinctures and Elixirs. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Spirit of Vitriol Rectified, ſix ounces; <lb/>Spirit of Wine Alcaliſate,
            ſixteen ounces. Mix <lb/>and diſtil in a glaſs Retort with three Cohobations; <lb/>and
            keep the diſtill'd liquor in a glaſs well ſtop'd. <lb/>This Menſtruum extracts the
            Elixir Proprietatis <lb/>with greater eaſe and efficacy than the common <lb/>Menſtruum.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An excellent Antiſcorbutick Tincture, extracted with <lb/>this Menſtruum. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Winters-bark, Aloes-wood, and Roots of <lb/>leſſer Galangal, of each two
            drams; Seeds of Bi- <lb/>ſhops-weed and Water-Creſſes, of each half a <lb/>dram. Bruiſe
            them, and pour on 'em as much of <lb/>the foreſaid Menſtruum as will cover them three
              <pb n="34"/>
            <lb/>fingers over. Let them digeſt in a Matrace in a ſand <lb/>furnace ſix days. Keep
            the ſtrain'd liquor in a cloſe <lb/>Veſſel, to be given to twenty drops, more or leſs,
            <lb/>twice a day, in a ſpoonful of Canary. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Another Tincture of good uſe in the Scurvy. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take the whiteſt Amber, Gum of Ivy, Caranna, <lb/>and Tacamahac, of each a dram;
            Saffron, half a <lb/>dram; Cloves and Nutmegs, of each two ſcruples. <lb/>Being bruis'd,
            pour to them the foreſaid Menſtru- <lb/>um, and extract a Tincture according to Art.
            Doſe <lb/>twenty drops. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Another good Menſtruum for extracting Antiſcor- <lb/>butick Elixirs. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take blew Salt of Tartar, four ounces. Let <lb/>'em digeſt in a Matrace with a
            pound of Spirit of <lb/>Wine Alcaliſate, till the Tincture is extracted. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An Electuary very uſeful in a cold Scurvy. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Conſerve of Scurvy-graſs, Roman Worm- <lb/>wood and Fumitory, of each two
            ounces; Pow- <lb/>der of Winters-bark, Roots of Angelica, and A- <lb/>ron, of each two
            drams; Species Diatrion Santa- <lb/>lon, a dram and a half; Powder of Crabs-eyes a
            <lb/>dram; Salt of Wormwood, two drams. With a <lb/>ſufficient quantity of Syrup of the
            Juice of Citron- <lb/>peel, make an Electuary, to be taken to the big- <lb/>neſs of a
            Nutmeg, drinking after it a draught of <lb/>an Appropriat Liquor. Or, </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Conſerve of the Leaves of Scurvy-graſs, <lb/>and of Brooklime, made with an
            equal quantity of <lb/>Sugar, of each three ounces; Troches of Capers, <lb/>and of
            Rhubarb, of each two drams; Salt of <lb/>Wormwood and of Scurvy-graſs, of each a dram.
              <pb n="35"/>
            <lb/>With a ſufficient quantity of Syrup of the Juice of <lb/>Scurvy-graſs, make an
            Electuary. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An Electuary, commonly preſcrib'd by Dr. <hi rend="roman">Willis</hi>
            <lb/>for a cold Scurvy. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Conſerve of the yellow coats of Oranges <lb/>and Limons, and of the purple
            flowers of the Aſh- <lb/>tree (all made with an equal quantity of Sugar) <lb/>of each
            two ounces; Roots of Contrayerva, a <lb/>dram and a half; Galangal the leſſer, half a
            dram; <lb/>Roots of Aron, two drams; Species Aromaticæ <lb/>Roſatæ, a dram; Salt of
            Wormwood, two drams. <lb/>With a ſufficient quantity of Syrup of the Confi- <lb/>ture of
            Nutmegs, make an Electuary, to be taken <lb/>to the quantity of a Nutmeg, drinking after
            it a <lb/>draught of ſome appropriated liquor. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A cheap Electuary for the Poor, of good uſe in a <lb/>cold Scurvy. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Leaves of Scurvy-graſs, and Brooklime, <lb/>of each four ounces; double
            refin'd Sugar, eight <lb/>ounces. Let 'em be beat together in a Mortar; <lb/>adding
            Winters-bark, half an ounce; Tartar cal- <lb/>cin'd with Nitre, three drams. With a
            ſufficient <lb/>quantity of Sack, make an Electuary, to be taken <lb/>as above. Or, </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Leaves of Scurvy-graſs, a pound; <lb/>Raiſins ſton'd and double refin'd
            Sugar, of each <lb/>half a pound; Fœcula of the Roots of Horſe Rad- <lb/>diſh, two
            ounces. Bruiſe all together in a Mortar, <lb/>and reduce them to the form of an
            Electuary-Doſe, <lb/>the bigneſs of a Walnut twice or thrice a day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Confection recommended againſt a cold Scurvy. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Powder of Aron Roots compound, an <pb n="36"/>
            <lb/>ounce; Winters-bark in Powder, half an ounce; <lb/>Species of Diatrion Santalon and
            Troches of Ca- <lb/>pers, of each two drams; Salt of Wormwood and <lb/>Scuvy-graſs, of
            each a dram and a half; the <lb/>yellow coats of Oranges condited, three ounces.
            <lb/>Beat 'em together in a Mortar. Then add three <lb/>ounces of white Sugar diſſolv'd
            in a ſufficient quan- <lb/>tity of Water of Earth-worms: and make a Con- <lb/>fection
            according to Art. Take of this the quan- <lb/>tity of a Nutmeg twice a day, drinking
            after it an <lb/>appropriate liquor. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Another Confection, proper in the ſame caſe. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Roots of Eringo and Vipers-graſs condi- <lb/>ted, of each two drams; Walnuts,
            Myrobalans con- <lb/>dited, of each two in number; Electuary of Saſ- <lb/>ſafras, ſix
            drams; Powder of Cubebs and Carda- <lb/>mom, of each two drams; Powder of the Roots
            <lb/>of Zedoary and Angelica, of each a dram and a <lb/>half; Salt of Wormwood, two
            drams; With a <lb/>ſufficient quantity of the Syrup of the Confiture of <lb/>Walnuts,
            make a Confection. Or, </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Powder of China-roots and Saſſafras-wood, <lb/>of each half an ounce; yellow
            and white Saunders, <lb/>of each two drams; Seeds of Rocket, Cubebs,
            <lb/>Garden-Creſſes, and Grains of Paradiſe, of each a <lb/>dram and a half; Species of
            Dialacca, Cinnamon, <lb/>Orrice, leſſer Galangal, of each a dram; Salt of <lb/>Wormwood,
            two drams: Conſerve of the yellow <lb/>coats of Oranges, and Sugar of Roſemary-flowers
            <lb/>diſſolv'd in Snail-water, of each three ounces. Make <lb/>a Confection: to which
            (in ſome Scorbutick Ca- <lb/>ſes) you may add three drams of Steel prepar'd <lb/>with
            Sulphur, or two drams of Vitriol of Steel. <lb/>Taking care to exerciſe the Body
            according to its <pb n="37"/>
            <lb/>ſtrength, after every doſe, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> the quantity of a
            <lb/>Nutmeg twice a day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Powder, good in a cold Scurvy. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Powder of Aron, compound, an ounce <lb/>and a half; Winters-bark, half an
            ounce; Cubebs, <lb/>Grains of Paradiſe and Cardamum, of each two <lb/>drams; Salt of
            Wormwood, three drams; Tablets <lb/>of Oranges, three ounces: Make a Powder. Doſe,
            <lb/>a dram in an appropriat liquor. Or add to it ker- <lb/>nels of the Indian Chocolate
            Nut, half a pound. <lb/>Reduce 'em to maſs or paſte in a hot mortar; <lb/>and give two
            drams after the manner of Chocolate, <lb/>in Spring-water, in which the leaves of
            Roſemary <lb/>and Betony, or the roots of Viper's-graſs, or the <lb/>ſhavings of Ivory
            or Hartſhorn, are boyl'd. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Pills, good in a cold Scurvy, calculated for thoſe <lb/>who covet Medicines in a
            ſmall quantity. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Roots of Virginian Snakeweed and Con- <lb/>trayerva, of each two drams;
            Winters-bark, Cu- <lb/>bebs and Rocket-ſeed, of each three drams; Salt <lb/>of Wormwood
            and Scurvy-graſs, of each a dram <lb/>and a half; Extract or Rob of Juniper, half an
            <lb/>ounce. With a ſufficient quantity of Syrup of the <lb/>Confiture of Nutmegs, make a
            maſs for Pills. Doſe, <lb/>four twice a day, drinking after 'em an appropriat
            <lb/>liquor. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Tablets good in a cold Scurvy, for nice Palates. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Powder of Winters-bark and Crabs-eyes, <lb/>of each a dram and a half; Pearl
            in powder, half <lb/>a dram; double refin'd Sugar diſſolv'd in water of <lb/>Earthworms
            and boyl'd up to the conſiſtency of Ta- <lb/>blets, ſix ounces; Spirit of Scurvy-graſs,
            two drams. <pb n="38"/>
            <lb/>Make Tablets according to Art, weighing half a <lb/>dram a piece. Doſe two a day,
            drinking after <lb/>them an appropriat liquor. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Tablets of Oranges, of ſingular uſe in a cold Scurvy. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Rinds of Oranges, Limons, and Citrons, <lb/>preſerv'd, of each an ounce;
            Eringo Roots pre- <lb/>ſerv'd, half an ounce; Pinenut Kernels and Fiſtick <lb/>Nuts, of
            each twenty; Sweet Almonds blancht, <lb/>in number ten; Anniſeed in powder, half an
            ounce; <lb/>Ginger preſerv'd, two ounces; Species Aromaticæ <lb/>Roſatæ and Nutmegs, of
            each a dram and a half; <lb/>Galangal Roots, a dram; Cloves, ten in number;
            <lb/>Ambergrieſe, four grains; Musk and Civet, of each <lb/>two grains; double refin'd
            Sugar diſſolv'd in Roſe- <lb/>water, and boil'd to a conſiſtency for Tablets, a
            <lb/>pound and a half. Make Tablets according to Art. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A ſimple cheap Decoction, recommended by moſt Au- <lb/>thors, in a cold Scurvy. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Leaves of Water-Creſſes, three <lb/>handfuls; of the leſſer Sorrel, two
            handfuls: Be- <lb/>ing ſlic'd, let 'em macerate in ſix pounds of Milk: <lb/>and boyl to
            the conſumption of a third part. Doſe, <lb/>ſix or eight ounces twice a day. This is
            commend- <lb/>ed by many, as alſo the Decoction of Wormwood. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A ſimple Decoction, often experienc'd in a cold Scurvy. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Broom-tops, three handfuls: Slice 'em <lb/>ſmall, and boyl them in three
            pounds of ſtrong Ale, <lb/>till the half is waſted; and give two or three <lb/>ounces of
            the Decoction twice a day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Decoction improv'd by Infuſion, of good uſe in a <lb/>cold Scurvy. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Roots of Vipers-graſs and Chervil, of each <pb n="39"/>
            <lb/>and ounce; Leaves of Agrimony and Groundpine, <lb/>of each half a handful; Burnt
            Hartſhorn, 2 drams; <lb/>Raiſins, half a handful; Boyl 'em in three pounds <lb/>of
            Spring-water, till a third part is conſum'd. Add <lb/>Rheniſh wine, half a pound; and
            ſtrain it out <lb/>preſently into a glaſs veſſel; to which put Leaves <lb/>of
            Scurvy-graſs and Brooklime bruis'd, of each <lb/>half a handful; Orange-peel preſerv'd
            and ſlic'd <lb/>ſmall, half an ounce. Make a cloſe and hot Infu- <lb/>ſion for ſix
            hours: and keep the ſtraining in veſ- <lb/>ſels cloſe ſtop'd. Doſe, ſix ounces twice a
            day, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>
            <lb/>after every Doſe of ſolid Medicines. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Another for the ſame purpoſe. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Whey made with Whitewine or Cyder, <lb/>a pound and a half; Boyl it in
            Roots of Burdock <lb/>and Eringo preſerv'd, of each ſix drams; preſerv'd
            <lb/>Juniper-berries, half an ounce. Boyl the liquor to <lb/>a third part, then ſtrain
            it out into a flagon, to <lb/>which put Leaves of Scurvy-graſs and Brooklime, <lb/>of
            each a handful. Make a cloſe and hot Infuſion <lb/>for ſix hours. Doſe half a pound
            twice a day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An Infuſion of ſingular virtue in a cold Scurvy. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Leaves of Scurvy-graſs, a handful; ſhavings <lb/>of Horſe-Radiſh-roots, half a
            handful; Winters- <lb/>bark bruis'd, two drams; let them be put into a glaſs <lb/>with
            Whitewine (or Cyder) and water of Scurvy- <lb/>graſs, of each a pound. Make an Infuſion
            in a <lb/>Cellar for two or three days. Doſe, ſix or eight <lb/>ounces, twice a day; to
            be taken after every Doſe <lb/>of a ſolid Medicine. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A powerful Antiſcorbutick Juice. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Leaves of Scurvy-graſs, Water Creſſes, <pb n="40"/>
            <lb/>and Brooklime, of each three handfuls; bruiſe <lb/>them; and expreſs a Juice to be
            kept in a glaſs <lb/>cloſe ſtop'd. Doſe, from an ounce and a half <lb/>to three ounces
            in a draught of wine or ſome di- <lb/>ſtill'd water. Or, </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Leaves of Scurvy-graſs, four handfuls; <lb/>Woodſorrel, two handfuls. Bruiſe
            them and ex- <lb/>preſs a Juice, which being put into a glaſs well <lb/>ſtopt will
            quickly become clear, for the acidity of <lb/>the Woodſorrel precipitates the coarſer
            parts of the <lb/>Scurvy-graſs. The ſame thing comes to paſs, if the <lb/>Juice of
            Oranges be mixt with the Juice of Scurvy- <lb/>graſs. The doſe is two or three ounces
            twice a day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An Antiſcorbutick Juice, beneficial in a cold Scurvy. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Leaves of Scurvy-graſs, four hand- <lb/>fuls; Brooklime and Garden
            Creſſes, of each two <lb/>handfuls; long Pepper, three drams; ſhavings of
            <lb/>Horſe-radiſhes, two ounces. Bruiſe all together and <lb/>put 'em into a glaz'd pot
            with two pounds of <lb/>Rheniſh-wine, or Sack, if better lik'd: Stop the <lb/>pot cloſe,
            and let it ſtand for two days in a cold <lb/>Cellar. Then make a ſtrong
              Expr<unclear>e</unclear>ſſion. Doſe <lb/>three ounces twice a day after a Doſe of a
            ſolid <lb/>Medicine. Or, </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Leaves of Scurvy-graſs, three hand- <lb/>fuls; Brooklime, Garden
            Creſſes, and Woodſorrel, <lb/>of each a handful: Bruiſe them, and put to them <lb/>Water
            of Snails and and Earthworms, of each ſix ounces. <lb/>Make a ſtrong expreſſion, to be
            reſerv'd in a glaſs <lb/>cloſe ſtop'd. Doſe, two ounces twice a day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Syrup for a cold Scurvy; retaining the intrinſick <lb/>vertue of the Ingredients. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Leaves of Garden Scurvy-graſs, ſix hand- <pb n="41"/>
            <lb/>fuls; the rinds of four Oranges and two Limons, <lb/>par'd off thin; of the
            ſhavings of Horſe-Radiſh, <lb/>half a handful; long Pepper in powder, three <lb/>drams.
            Bruiſe all together, and epxreſs the Juice; <lb/>which is preſently to be put into a
            glaſs ſtopt very <lb/>cloſe, and plac'd in a cold Cellar, till it ſettles <lb/>clear;
            then pour off the clear liquor by inclination <lb/>into another glaſs, and being ſtop'd
            let it be kept <lb/>in a heat of Balneum Mariæ. In the mean time, <lb/>for every ounce
            of this liquor, take of Sugar, an <lb/>ounce and a half; and let its whole quantity be
            diſ- <lb/>ſolv'd in a little Water of Earth-worms, and <lb/>boyl'd to the conſiſtency of
            Tablets; and whilſt <lb/>it is warm, pour to it the foreſaid liquor by little <lb/>and
            little, ſtirring it with a Spatula. As ſoon as it <lb/>is incorporated, take the
            compoſition off the fire, <lb/>and when it is cold put it into a glaſs: in which
            <lb/>hang up the following bag. Take Cinamon bruis'd, <lb/>a dram; Seeds of Water
            Creſſes and Rocket, in <lb/>Powder, of each, a dram. Mix. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An excellent Water for a cold Scurvy. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Leaves of both Scurvy-graſſes, Brooklime, <lb/>Water Creſſes, and Broom Tops,
            of each three <lb/>handfuls; leaves of Germander and Groundpine, <lb/>of each two
            handfuls; Roots of Horſe Radiſhes, <lb/>half a pound; Roots of Aron, Angelica, and
            Maſter- <lb/>wort, of each four ounces; the outer coats of four <lb/>Oranges and as many
            Limons; Roots of Aromatick <lb/>Calamus, an ounce; Cinamon and Cloves, of each <lb/>half
            an ounce. Being ſlic'd and bruis'd, pour to <lb/>them eight pound of the beſt Cyder. Let
            'em di- <lb/>geſt two days in a glaz'd pot cloſe ſtop'd; then <lb/>diſtill in a common
            Still, and mix the water that <lb/>comes firſt over with the laſt. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The ſimple water of Aron-leaves taken to three <pb n="42"/>
            <lb/>or four ounces twice a day; and likewiſe the ſimple <lb/>water of Scruvy-graſs,
            cohobated often upon freſh <lb/>leaves; are reckon'd very potent Antiſcorbuticks. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An Antiſcorbutick Water, diſtill'd in Winter, when the <lb/>freſh Herbs are ſcarce. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Leaves of Scurvy-graſs, four handfuls; <lb/>Broom tops, Pine tops, Juniper
            tops, of each three <lb/>handfuls; Winters-bark, four ounces: Being ſlic'd <lb/>and
            bruis'd, pour to them of Whitewine, or Cyder, <lb/>or Whey made with either of 'em,
            eight pound. <lb/>Diſtill. </p>
        </div>
        <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="6"/>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="180"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
