<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Kettilby: A Collection of Above Three Hundred Receipts in Cookery,
          Physick and Surgery</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Mary Kettilby</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">A COLLECTION Of above Three Hundred RECEIPTS IN Cookery, Physick and
              Surgery; For the Use of all Good Wives, Tender Mothers, and Careful Nurses. By several
              Hands.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T53670</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T53670"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for Richard Wilkin, at the King's Head in St. Paul's
                  Church-Yard, MDCCXIV.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1714</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="14"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="218"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="12"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107290361</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Recipe collections"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="122"/>
      <div>
        <pb n="123"/>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>A <lb/><hi rend="size(1.75)">COLLECTION </hi>
          <lb/>OF <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)">RECEIPTS </hi>
          <lb/>IN <lb/><hi rend="size(2.0)"><hi rend="italic">Phyſick</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
              >Surgery</hi>. </hi>
        </head>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>Strong <hi rend="roman">Palſey-Water</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(4)">T</hi>AKE the Spirits of five gal- <lb/>lons of the beſt Old
            Sherry- <lb/>Sack, diſtill'd in a Limbeck: <lb/>take Cowſlip-flowers, the <lb/>Flowers
            of Burrage and Bugloſs, and <lb/>of the Lillies of the Valley, of each <lb/>one handful:
            Take alſo Roſemary- <pb n="124"/>
            <lb/>flowers, Sage and Betony-flowers, of <lb/>each one handful: Take each Flower
            <lb/>in their Seaſon, and ſo put into ſome <lb/>of the Spirits aforeſaid, in an open-
            <lb/>mouth'd Glaſs of near a quart, for that <lb/>will hold them all, with the Spirits,
            'till <lb/>you are ready to diſtil the Water; but <lb/>this, and the reſt of the
            Spirits, muſt <lb/>be moſt carefully ſtopt 'till you uſe it: <lb/>Take Lavender-flowers
            in their Seaſon, <lb/>ſtrip them clean from their Stalks, and <lb/>fill a wide-mouth'd
            gallon Glaſs with <lb/>them; pour into them the remainder <lb/>of your Spirits; then
            ſtop them cloſe <lb/>with Cork and Bladder, (as before) <lb/>and let them ſtand ſix
            Weeks to digeſt <lb/>in the Sun; then put all together, theſe <lb/>and the firſt ſteep'd
            Flowers, with all <lb/>the Spirits in both Glaſſes: Add alſo <lb/>Balm, Motherwort,
            Spike-flowers, Bay- <lb/>leaves and Orange-leaves, if to be had, <lb/>of each an ounce,
            cut ſmall, and put <lb/>to the former Flowers and Spirits: <lb/>Diſtil all theſe
            together in a Limbeck; <lb/>make three Runnings of it; firſt a <lb/>quart Glaſs, which
            will be exceeding <lb/>ſtrong; then a pint Glaſs, which will <lb/>be almoſt as good;
            laſtly, receive from <lb/>it a pint Glaſs-full, or as much as runs <pb n="125"/>
            <lb/>ſtrong; for when it runs weak, which <lb/>you may know by its Taſte and Colour,
            <lb/>which will be Whiter, let it run no <lb/>longer: Put your three Runnings all
            <lb/>together: Then take Citron-peel, the <lb/>out-ſide Yellow Rind, or Lemon-peels
            <lb/>thin pared, alſo Pine-ſeeds hull'd, of <lb/>each ſix drams; of Cinnamon one ounce;
            <lb/>of Nutmegs, Mace, Cardamoms, Cu- <lb/>cubies, and Yellow Sanders, each <lb/>half an
            ounce; of Lignum Aloes one <lb/>dram; make all theſe into a groſs <lb/>Powder, putting
            among them alſo half <lb/>a pound of Jujubes new and good, be- <lb/>ing ſtoned, and cut
            ſmall: Put all <lb/>theſe Ingredients into a White Sarſnet- <lb/>bag, to be hung in the
            Water afore- <lb/>ſaid: Take alſo of Prepared Pearls, <lb/>two drams; of Prepared
            Smaragd a <lb/>ſcruple, Amber, <choice>
              <corr>Greaſe</corr>
              <sic>Greate</sic>
            </choice>, Musk, and <lb/>Saffron, of each one ſcruple; of Red <lb/>Roſes, well dried,
            and ſweet one ounce: <lb/>Theſe may be put in a little Bag by <lb/>themſelves, and hung
            in the Spirit, as <lb/>the other: Cloſe it well, that no Air <lb/>gets in, for ſix
            Weeks; then take out <lb/>the Water, and preſs the Bags dry; <lb/>keep the Water in
            narrow-mouth'd <lb/>Glaſſes cloſe ſtopt. </p>
          <pb n="126"/>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>The Uſe of the Water. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>'Tis ſo ſtrong and powerful, that it <lb/>cannot be taken alone, but muſt be
              <lb/>dropt on Crumbs of Bread and Sugar <lb/>by any One, for Prevention: Take it
              <lb/>firſt and laſt, and at our in the After- <lb/>noon: Faſt always before and after
              it <lb/>a full Hour at leaſt. 'Tis of exceeding <lb/>virtue in all Swoonings, Weakneſs
              of <lb/>Heart, and Decay'd Spirits, in all Pal- <lb/>ſeys, Apoplexies, both to help
              in, and <lb/>prevent a Fit; 'twill alſo keep all <lb/>Cold Diſpoſitions off the Liver,
              re- <lb/>ſtores loſt Appetite, and fortifies and <lb/>ſtrengthens the Stomach; 'twill
              alone <lb/>cure a Dropſy, if taken at firſt, and <lb/>the Patient be kept from Small
              and <lb/>Cooling Liquors. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A ſecond <hi rend="roman">Palſey-Water</hi>, made up- <lb/>on the Ingredients of
            the firſt. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/>
            <hi rend="dc(2)">W</hi>HEN the firſt Water has run <lb/>what is Strong, there will be
            <lb/>ſome Small Water at the bottom of the <lb/>Limbeck; pour it out from the Herbs
            <lb/>and Flowers, and drain them; put them <pb n="127"/>
            <lb/>into a gallon of the beſt Sherry, ſo let <lb/>them ſtand cloſe ſtopt five Weeks;
            then <lb/>diſtil them, and let it run as long as it <lb/>continues ſtrong; then pour it
            into the <lb/>Glaſs where the Sarſnet-bags are, and <lb/>let them be in this ſecond
            Liquor cloſe <lb/>ſtopt ſix Weeks; then you may uſe it, <lb/>as the former, with Bread
            and Sugar: <lb/>For tho' this is not ſo powerful as the <lb/>former, 'tis too ſtrong to
            take alone. <lb/>Both theſe are good to bathe Outwardly <lb/>the Part affected with
            Weakneſs by <lb/>Palſey, and generally helps any violent <lb/>Pains or Aches that any
            Part is vexed <lb/>with; but becauſe Bathing waſtes <lb/>moſt, and this Sort is leſs
            coſtly, they <lb/>commonly uſe this ſecond ſort for that. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A very good <hi rend="roman">Snail-Water,</hi> for <lb/>a <hi rend="roman"
              >Conſumption</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE half a peck of Shell-Snails, <lb/>wipe them and bruiſe
            them Shells <lb/>and all in a Mortar; put to them a <lb/>gallon of New Milk; as alſo
            Balm, <lb/>Mint, Carduus, unſet Hyſſop, and <lb/>Burrage, of each one handful; Raiſons
              <pb n="128"/>
            <lb/>of the Sun ſtoned, Figs, and Dates, of <lb/>each a quarter of a pound; two large
            <lb/>Nutmegs: Slice all theſe, and put <lb/>them to the Milk, and diſtil it with <lb/>a
            quick Fire, in a cold Still; this will <lb/>yield near four Wine-quarts of Water
            <lb/>very good: You muſt put two ounces <lb/>of White Sugar-candy into each Bottle,
            <lb/>and let the Water drop on it; ſtir the <lb/>Herbs ſometimes, while it diſtils, and
            <lb/>keep it cover'd on the Head with wet <lb/>Cloths. Take five ſpoonfuls at a time,
            <lb/>firſt and laſt, and at Four in the After- <lb/>noon. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A Good <hi rend="roman">Water</hi> for the <hi rend="roman">Spleen</hi>; <lb/>a
            Cordial. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE four Ounces of Harts-horn, <lb/>one ounce of Cardamoms,
            one <lb/>ounce of Cinamon, one ounce of Saf- <lb/>fron, two handfuls of Red Sage, as
            <lb/>much Balm; ſteep theſe twenty-four <lb/>Hours in two quarts of Sack, or as
            <lb/>much good Brandy, which you pleaſe; <lb/>diſtil it in a cold Still as quick as you
            <lb/>can, and let it drop on four ounces of <pb n="129"/>
            <lb/>Sugar-candy. Drink of this when <lb/>Low-ſpirited. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A Good <hi rend="roman">Water</hi> for the <hi rend="roman">Stone</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE four quarts of White-Thorn- <lb/>flowers, infuſe them in
            two quarts <lb/>of ſtrong White-wine, with two ounces <lb/>of Nutmeg ſliced; let theſe
            ſtand two <lb/>Days, then diſtil it in a cold Still. <lb/>Drink it with Sugar, or
            without, as you <lb/>like beſt. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A <hi rend="roman">Drink</hi> for any <hi rend="roman">Inward Bruiſe</hi>
            <lb/>or <hi rend="roman">Wound</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE one handful of each of the <lb/>Herbs following, <hi
              rend="italic">viz.</hi> Worm- <lb/>wood, Comfrey, Throatwort, Wood- <lb/>Betony,
            Plantain, Mugwort, Bonewort, <lb/>Scabious, Avens, Wild Hony-ſuckle, Egre- <lb/>mony,
            Bramble-buds, Cinquefoil, Spear- <lb/>mint, Senacle, White-bottle, Ribwort,
            <lb/>Daiſy-roots, Dandelion, Bugloſs, Hau- <lb/>thorn-buds: Put to theſe Herbs two <pb
              n="130"/>
            <lb/>quarts of White-wine, and a gallon of <lb/>running Water, and boil it 'till it be
            half <lb/>waſted; then ſtrain it, and add to it <lb/>a quart of Honey; let that boil in
            the <lb/>Liquor ſome time: When 'tis cold, <lb/>Bottle it very cloſe, and keep it for
            Uſe. <lb/>'Twill keep many Years, and is neceſ- <lb/>ſary for all Families; two or three
            <lb/>ſpoonfuls of it taken Morning and <lb/>Night. 'Tis really good for Sores,
            <lb/>Wounds, and Hurts New or Old, in <lb/>Men, Women, and Children: Its Vir- <lb/>tues
            of that kind are too long to men- <lb/>tion: It has broke and brought away <lb/>Inward
            Impoſthumes. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>An Excellent <hi rend="roman">Balſom</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a quart of Spirit of Sack, <lb/>infuſe in it four ounces
            of Sarſapa- <lb/>rilla cut ſhort, two ounces of <hi rend="italic">China</hi>
            <lb/>ſliced thin, one ounce of <hi rend="italic">Virginia</hi> Snake- <lb/>weed cut
            ſmall; put all theſe in a two- <lb/>quart Bottle, and ſet it in the Sun, ſhaking <lb/>it
            twice or thrice a Day, 'till the Spirit <lb/>be tinctur'd as Yellow as Gold; then
            <lb/>clear off the Spirit into another Bottle, <pb n="131"/>
            <lb/>and put to it eight ounces of Gum- <lb/>Guaice; ſet it in the Sun, as before,
            <lb/>ſhaking it very often, 'till all the Gum <lb/>be diſſolv'd, except Dregs, which
            will <lb/>be in ten or twelve Days; then clear <lb/>it a ſecond time from the Dregs, and
            <lb/>put to it one ounce of Natural Balſom <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Peru</hi>; ſhake it
            well together, and <lb/>ſet it in the Sun for two Days; then <lb/>put in one ounce of
            Balm of <hi rend="italic">Gilead</hi>; <lb/>ſhake all well together once more, and
            <lb/>ſet it in the Sun for a Fortnight; 'tis <lb/>then fit for Uſe, and will keep many
            <lb/>Years. Its Virtues are too long to <lb/>inſert: 'Tis good to take Inwardly in
            <lb/>moſt Diſtempers, and proper for all <lb/>Sores or Wounds, by pouring in ſome
            <lb/>Drops, and binding Lint thereon. <lb/>The Doſe, taken Inwardly, is from <lb/>half a
            Spoonful to a whole one, in <lb/>Sugar, or any Liquid Vehicle, for Con- <lb/>ſumptions,
            or any Inward Ulcer: Uſe <lb/>moderate Exerciſe with it. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="132"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>An <hi rend="roman">Oyl</hi> for any <hi rend="roman">Bruiſe</hi> or <hi
              rend="roman">Wound</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of the tender Tops of the <lb/>Bay-Tree, Red-Sage,
            Lavender, <lb/>Wormwood, Plantain, Rue, Tormen- <lb/>til, Scabious, Comfrey, Broom,
            Rape, <lb/>Oſman-royal, Southernwood, Camomil, <lb/>Charity, St. John's-wort,
            Solomon-ſeal, <lb/>Amber, Roſemary, Adders-ſpear, Gol- <lb/>den-Rod, Herb-Robert,
            Ground-pine, <lb/>Sanicle, and Bugle, of each one hand- <lb/>ful; ſhred all theſe very
            ſmall, and in- <lb/>fuſe them in one quart of Oyl-Olive, <lb/>and three pints of
            Neat-Oyl; ſtop them <lb/>cloſe in a Glaſs Veſſel, and let them <lb/>ſtand ten or twelve
            Days in the Heat <lb/>of the Sun; ſtir them every Night <lb/>when you take them in:
            After this, <lb/>boil it over a gentle Fire 'till the Oyl <lb/>is Green; then ſtrain it
            clear from the <lb/>Herbs, and add to the Oyl again, half <lb/>a handful of the Herbs,
            as before, <lb/>ſhred, with one ounce of Oyl of Tur- <lb/>pentine, One ounce of
            Natural-Balſom, <lb/>and one ounce of Oyl of Worms: Digeſt <lb/>all in the Sun, as
            before; boil and <lb/>ſtrain it, and keep it cloſe ſtopt for Uſe. <lb/>It muſt be made
            in <hi rend="italic">May</hi>. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="133"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A <hi rend="roman">Salve</hi> for the <hi rend="roman">King's-Evil</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE one pint of the beſt Sallad- <lb/>Oyl, four ounces of
            Red-Lead <lb/>finely powder'd, as much White-Lead, <lb/>one ounce of Bees-wax thinly
            ſliced, <lb/>of Frankincenſe and the beſt Maſtick <lb/>each one ounce, of <hi
              rend="italic">Burgundy</hi>-Pitch two <lb/>ounces; let all be beaten; boil the
            <lb/>Oyl and Leads ſome little time together <lb/>over a gentle Fire; keep the Oyl ſtir-
            <lb/>ring, while you add the Wax; then boil <lb/>theſe together for half an Hour, ſtir-
            <lb/>ing it conſtantly: Take it off the Fire, <lb/>and ſtir it 'till the Heat is abated;
            <lb/>then add your Maſtick, and keep it <lb/>from the Fire 'till it has done work-
            <lb/>ing: Boil it gently again, and put in <lb/>your Frankincenſe, ſtirring it off the
            Fire, <lb/>as you did before: Set it on again, and <lb/>then add the <hi rend="italic"
              >Burgundy</hi>-Pitch, as before, <lb/>with Care; then boil all together, 'till <lb/>it
            looks like Pitch; ſtir it 'till Cold: <lb/>Leave your Stick in the Middle, and <lb/>the
            next Day ſet it on the Fire to melt <lb/>the Edges; then take it out, and keep it
            <lb/>in an Oyl'd-Paper for Uſe. Let the <pb n="134"/>
            <lb/>Party afflicted ſpread a Plaiſter as big <lb/>as the Swelling is, and apply: If it
            ga- <lb/>ther to a Head, and break, after you <lb/>have waſh'd the Wound with warm
            <lb/>Vinegar, apply ſome Lint rolled in an <lb/>equal quantity of the Salve warm'd,
            <lb/>and Honey; ſpread a Plaiſter of the <lb/>Salve, and when the Corruption is
            <lb/>out, that will heal it. 'Tis Incom- <lb/>parable, and ſafely may be uſed for
            <lb/>any Swelling. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A <hi rend="roman">Drink</hi> for the <hi rend="roman">Evil</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of White Arch-angel two <lb/>handfuls, of Outlandiſh
            Sweet <lb/>Fennel-ſeed bruiſed one ounce, of Li- <lb/>coriſh one ounce: boil theſe
            together <lb/>in two Wine-quarts of Spring-water; <lb/>ſtop it cloſe 'till half be
            conſumed: <lb/>When cold, ſtrain it from the Ingre- <lb/>dients; add to the Liquor two
            ounces <lb/>of Damask-Roſes: Let the Party drink <lb/>of this Liquor Spring and Fall,
            five, <lb/>ſeven, or nine Days together, as you <lb/>beſt find it agree, three times in
            the <lb/>Day, a quarter of a pint Firft and Laſt, <lb/>and at Four in the Afternoon.
          </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="135"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A <hi rend="roman">Drink</hi> for the <hi rend="roman">King's-Evil</hi>, <lb/>and
              <hi rend="roman">Cancer</hi>. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Guaiacum one ounce, Saſ- <lb/>ſafras, Sarſaparilla,
            Sharp-pointed- <lb/>Dock, and Daiſy-Roots, of each half <lb/>an ounce; Arch-angel
            Flowers, and <lb/>Millepedes, of each two large ſpoonfuls; <lb/>Ground-Ivy, and
            Herb-Robert, of each <lb/>one handful: Bruiſe and ſhred all theſe <lb/>Ingredients, and
            put them to ſteep <lb/>one Night in three pints of good clear <lb/>New Ale; ſtrain it,
            and drink no other <lb/>Drink for ſix Weeks, Spring and Fall. <lb/>You may do a larger
            quantity at a time <lb/>for Man or Woman; but you muſt not <lb/>infuſe too much at a
            time, becauſe the <lb/>Herbs are apt to change it. At the <lb/>ſame time, if the
            Swellings are painful, <lb/>anoint with <hi rend="italic">Juice of Rue</hi>, prepared as
            <lb/>follows. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>An <hi rend="roman">Ointment</hi> for the <hi rend="roman">Swellings</hi>
            <lb/>in the <hi rend="roman">King's Evil</hi>. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE two ſpoonfuls of Juice of <lb/>Rue, as much Sallad-Oyl,
            beat <lb/>them well together; then ſet it over <pb n="136"/>
            <lb/>the Fire, and let it boil ſlowly half <lb/>an Hour; add two ounces of Bees-
            <lb/>wax, let it boil a little with this: <lb/>Pour it out, and keep it cloſe cover'd.
            <lb/>'Tis an Incomparable Ointment to uſe <lb/>all the time you take the Diet-Drink.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) hanging space">
            <lb/>A <hi rend="roman">Milk-Water</hi> for <hi rend="roman">Cancer</hi> or <lb/><hi
              rend="roman">King's-Evil</hi>, for thoſe that <lb/>cannot drink an Infuſion. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Roots of <choice>
              <corr>Daiſies</corr>
              <sic>Daſies</sic>
            </choice>, Burdock, <lb/>Guaiacum, Saſſafras, Sarſaparilla, <lb/>China, Tormentil, and
            Hounds-tongue, <lb/>each two ounces; Selandine, Yarrow, <lb/>Plantain, Herb-Robert,
            Agrimony, <lb/>Speedwel, Ground-Ivy, and Cinque- <lb/>foil, of each a large handful;
            Arch- <lb/>angel-flowers, one pint; Sweet-fennel, <lb/>and Coriander-ſeeds, of each one
            ounce: <lb/>Shred and bruiſe all, and put them to a <lb/>gallon of Milk: Draw off as
            much <lb/>as runs good, and drink daily a quarter <lb/>of a pint every four Hours: Into
            each <lb/>Draught ſqueeze the Juice of a ſmall <lb/>ſpoonful of Millepedes. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="137"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>An <hi rend="roman">Ointment</hi> for the <hi rend="roman">Evil</hi>, <lb/>or <hi
              rend="roman">Rickets</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Leaves of Oſmond-royal, <lb/>St. John's-wort, Wormwood,
            Cen- <lb/>taury, White Hore-hound, Germander, <lb/>Ground-Pine, Golden-Rod, Carduus,
            <lb/>Southernwood, Camomil, Tanſy, Pen- <lb/>ny-royal, Sage, Mint, Rue, Lillies of
            <lb/>the Valley, Angelica, Meadow-Saxi- <lb/>frage, of each an ounce; ſhred it
            <lb/>ſmall, and add of Oyl one quart; <lb/>Deer-ſuet, and Claret, of each one pint;
            <lb/>Mace one ounce: Boil theſe 'till all the <lb/>Watery-part is conſum'd: Strain it,
            and <lb/>anoint the Belly and Joints with it all <lb/>the Spring and Fall. This has done
            <lb/>great Cures on Weakly Children. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For a <hi rend="roman">Strain</hi>. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">P</hi>UT the Arm or Leg into a Pail of <lb/>Cold Spring-water, and
            keep it <lb/>there 'till the Water be warm; then <lb/>take it out, and repeat it 'till
            it be <lb/>well, which it will be without apply- <lb/>ing any other Remedy. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="138"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A Good <hi rend="roman">Powder</hi> for <hi rend="roman">Worms</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE an ounce of Worm-ſeed, <lb/>and half an ounce of
            Rhubarb, <lb/>beat both to a fine Powder, and take <lb/>a quarter of an ounce of Powder
            of Pre- <lb/>par'd Coral; mix all three together, <lb/>and let the Child take as much of
            this <lb/>as will lie on a Shilling, for three Morn- <lb/>ings together, drinking a
            glaſs of ſmall <lb/>warm Ale after each Doſe. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>Another <hi rend="roman">Powder</hi> for the <hi rend="roman">Worms</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE an ounce of Sena, a quarter <lb/>of an ounce of whole
            Worm-ſeed, <lb/>a quarter of an ounce of Tanſy-feed, <lb/>a quarter of an ounce of
            Annis-ſeed, a <lb/>few Leaves of Wood-Betony; dry all <lb/>theſe, and beat them together
            very fine; <lb/>mix it into a Bolus with Syrop of <lb/>Turnips. A Child of Nine Years
            old <lb/>may take a quarter of an ounce of this <lb/>Mixture; ſo leſs, or more, for any
            <lb/>other Age. Drink Water-gruel or <lb/>Poſſet-drink in the working. 'Tis good
            <lb/>for Men or Women, as well as Children. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="139"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For <hi rend="roman">Worms</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">B</hi>RUISE a pound of Worm-ſeed, <lb/>and put it into a large
            Still full of <lb/>Spear-mint; draw it off as long as it <lb/>runs Good: Let the Child
            drink three <lb/>ſpoonfuls of this Nine Mornings toge- <lb/>ther. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For the ſame. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">O</hi>NE Drop of Oyl of Brimſtone in <lb/>a little warm Ale, for
            three Morn- <lb/>ings together. Do not exceed one <lb/>Drop for a Child; three is enough
            for <lb/>a Man or Woman. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For the ſame. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>O four pounds of the Husks of <lb/>Wall-nuts, put half a
            pound of <lb/>Worm-ſeed, and as much Flower of <lb/>Brimſtone: Draw it off in a Cold
            Still, <lb/>and let a Tea-cup be taken every Morn- <lb/>ing, for a Month. 'Tis an
            Excellent <lb/>Medicine for <hi rend="italic">Worms</hi>, or <hi rend="italic"
              >Jaundice</hi>, and <lb/>has done great Cures. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="140"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For the ſame. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE one handful of Spear-mint, <lb/>as much Plantain, as
            much Goats- <lb/>Rue, a ſpoonful of Plantain-ſeeds: Stamp <lb/>all together, and ſqueeze
            out the Juice, <lb/>and take two ſpoonfuls of it in a glaſs <lb/>of Sack, three Mornings
            together. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For the ſame; well recommended. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">H</hi>USK and dry an ounce of <hi rend="italic">Sevil</hi>-
            <lb/>Orange-ſeeds, beat them to a fine <lb/>Powder, and give as much as will lie <lb/>on
            a Sixpence, in a ſpoonful of Syrop <lb/>of Peach-bloſſoms: At the ſame time, <lb/>bind
            the Leaves of the Peach-Tree to <lb/>the Navil of the Child. If you have <lb/>no Syrop
            of Peach-bloſſoms, uſe Syrop <lb/>of Black-cherries. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="roman">Red Powder</hi>, for <hi rend="roman">Fevers</hi>, <lb/><hi
              rend="roman">Small-pox</hi>, or <hi rend="roman">Surfeits</hi>. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of Carduus, Rue, Red-Sage, <lb/>Lillies of the Valley,
            Tormentil, <lb/>Pimpernel, Dragon, Betony, Angelica, <pb n="141"/>
            <lb/>Scabious, Speedwel, of each one hand- <lb/>ful; <hi rend="italic"
            >Virginia</hi>-Snake-weed one handful; <lb/>Wormwood half a handful; Agrimony <lb/>and
            Verum, of each a quarter of a <lb/>handful: Shred the Herbs very ſmall, <lb/>and Infuſe
            them in two quarts of <lb/>White-wine, in a Jug, which you <choice>
              <corr>muſt</corr>
              <sic>muft</sic>
            </choice>
            <lb/>ſtop very cloſe, and ſet nine Days in <lb/>the Sun: Then ſtrain the Wine from
            <lb/>the Herbs, and infuſe the ſame quantity <lb/>of freſh Herbs in the ſame Wine;
            <lb/>let it ſtand, as before, nine Days more: <lb/>Then take a pound of Bole-armoniac
            <lb/>finely powder'd; then put as much of <lb/>the Wine (after it is a ſecond time
            <lb/>preſſed out) as the Powder will take <lb/>up, and ſet it in the Sun to dry; and
            <lb/>as it dries up, put in more of the <lb/>Wine, ſtirring it two or three times <lb/>a
            Day, 'till all the Wine be dried up <lb/>in the Powder, ſo as to be fit to <lb/>work
            like Paſte: Then put to it <lb/>one ounce of Diaſcordium, and one <lb/>ounce of
            Methridate, half an ounce of <lb/>Cochineal, one ounce of Powder of <lb/>Red Coral, one
            ounce of Prepar'd Saf- <lb/>fron, forty grains of Bezoar, one ounce <lb/>of Powder of
            Crabs-eyes, one ounce of <lb/>Burn'd Harts-horn, and one ounce of <pb n="142"/>
            <lb/>Prepar'd Pearl; mix theſe in the laſt <lb/>Wetting, and work them all together:
            <lb/>Make them up in Balls, (when well <lb/>mix'd) and dry them in the Sun. Take
            <lb/>forty or fifty grains of this for a Doſe. <lb/>Drink Mace-Ale after it. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>Of <hi rend="roman">Gaſcoign Powder</hi>, a good <lb/>Sort for the ſame Uſes. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE prepar'd Crabs-eyes, Red <lb/>Coral, White Amber very
            finely <lb/>powder'd, of each half an ounce; Burnt <lb/>Harts-horn half an ounce; one
            ounce of <lb/>Pearls very finely powder'd, one ounce <lb/>of Oriental Bezoar, of the
            Black Tops <lb/>of Crabs-claws finely powder'd four <lb/>ounces; grind all theſe on a
            Marble- <lb/>Stone 'till they caſt a Greeniſh Colour; <lb/>then make it into Balls with
            Jelly <lb/>made of <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi> Vipers-Skin, which <lb/>may be made
            and will Jelly like Harts- <lb/>horn. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="143"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) hanging space">
            <lb/>A very good <hi rend="roman">Powder</hi> for a <hi rend="roman">Diz- <lb/>zineſs in
              the Head</hi>, and to <lb/>Prevent <hi rend="roman">Apoplectick Fits</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE the Seeds and Roots of <lb/>Single Piony of each a like
            quan- <lb/>tity, dry and beat them ſeverally into <lb/>a fine Powder; take the weight in
            <lb/>Nutmeg, which you muſt beat, and <lb/>dry, and beat again; mix fine-ſifted
            <lb/>Sugar, and take as much as will lie <lb/>on a Shilling every Morning for a
            <lb/>Month conſtantly. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A <hi rend="roman">Powder</hi> to Stop a <hi rend="roman">Hickock</hi>
            <lb/>in Man, Woman, or Child. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">P</hi>UT as much Dill-ſeed finely pow- <lb/>der'd as will lie on a
            Shilling, into <lb/>two ſpoonfuls of Syrop of Black Cher- <lb/>ries, and take it
            preſently. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="144"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>An Excellent <hi rend="roman">Powder</hi> for <lb/><hi rend="roman"
              >Convulſion-Fits</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE two drams of Piony-roots, <lb/>Miſſletoe of the Oak one
            dram; <lb/>Prepar'd Pearl, White Amber Pre- <lb/>par'd, and Coral Prepar'd, of each half
            <lb/>a dram; Bezoar two grains, and five <lb/>leaves of Gold; make all theſe into a
            <lb/>very fine Powder, and give as much <lb/>of it as will lie on a Three-pence to a
            <lb/>Child of a Month old, and propor- <lb/>tionable to a bigger: Mix it up with <lb/>a
            ſpoonful of Black-cherry-Water, <lb/>which ſweeten with the Syrop of
            <lb/>Black-Cherries: Take it three Days <lb/>together at every Change of the Moon,
            <lb/>to prevent Returns. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A <hi rend="roman">Powder</hi> for <hi rend="roman">Digeſtion</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Gallingale and Setwal of <lb/>each one ounce;
            Long-Pepper, <lb/>Mace, and Nutmeg, of each two <lb/>ounces; Annis-ſeeds,
            Carraway-ſeeds, <lb/>Fennel-ſeeds, and Angelica-ſeeds, of <pb n="145"/>
            <lb/>each half an ounce: Put to theſe, all <lb/>finely powder'd, the weight in fine
            <lb/>powder'd Sugar; take as much as will <lb/>lie on a Shilling after every Meal, and
            <lb/>Drink a glaſs of Simple Carduus-Water <lb/>after it: This has done mighty Cures
            <lb/>to weak deprav'd Stomachs. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A Preſent Remedy for <hi rend="roman">Con- <lb/>vulſion-Fits</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>AKE a Draught of an equal <lb/>quantity of Piony and Simple
            <lb/>Black-Cherry-Water; and for a Man <lb/>put thirty, for a Woman twenty, for <lb/>a
            Child five drops of Spirit of Hart's- <lb/>horn; Drink this in or before a Fit. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>Another for the ſame. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>NFUSE Turnips in a Pot cloſe <lb/>ſtopt, and ſet into a
            Kettle of Wa- <lb/>ter, 'till they are tender enough to <lb/>ſqueeze; then take the
            Liquor clear <lb/>from them; and take three ſpoonfuls <lb/>of it, in one ſpoonful of
            rich Old <hi rend="italic">Mala- <pb n="146"/>
              <lb/>ga</hi>: It has Cured the Falling-Sickneſs <lb/>in grown-up People; but is almoſt
            In- <lb/>fallible for Children. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A <hi rend="roman">Syrop</hi> for <hi rend="roman">Convulſion Fits</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE one pint of ſmall Black- <lb/>Cherry-Water, two pounds
            of <lb/>Black Cherries; bruiſe them Stones and <lb/>all in a Mortar; put theſe with the
            <lb/>Water into a Jug, with two blades <lb/>of Mace, and four tops of Spear-mint;
            <lb/>ſtop the Jugg cloſe, and ſet it into a <lb/>Kettle of Water; Let it ſimper three
            <lb/>Hours over the Fire, then ſtrain it out, <lb/>and let it be boil'd to a Syrop, with
            a <lb/>full pound and half of <hi rend="italic">Lisbon</hi> Sugar to <lb/>each pint of
            that Liquor. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For <hi rend="roman">Convulſions</hi> or <hi rend="roman">Vertigo</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE one ounce of Juniper-Ber- <lb/>ries, two ounces of freſh
              <hi rend="italic">Sevil</hi>
            <lb/>Orange-peel, Male-Piony Roots three <lb/>ounces, Peacocks Dung ſix ounces, Su- <pb
              n="147"/>
            <lb/>gar-Candy half a pound: Infuſe theſe <lb/>in two quarts of Rheniſh, for twenty-
            <lb/>four Hours, in hot Aſhes; then let it <lb/>ſettle; and take two ſpoonfuls of this
            in <lb/>a glaſs of Angelica-Water: It has done <lb/>great Cures. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A Strong <hi rend="roman">Milk-Water</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Mint, Sage and Balm, of <lb/>each two good handfuls,
            Rue, Car- <lb/>duus, Wormwood, and Meadow-ſweet <lb/>of each one handful; chop theſe
            Herbs <lb/>together, and put them with four <lb/>quarts of New Milk, and a whole
            <lb/>Nutmeg ſlic'd, into a Copper Lim- <lb/>beck; from this Quantity you may <lb/>draw
            two Quarts, if you keep an even <lb/>ſlow fire, 'till that Quantity is drawn <lb/>off:
            When you have drawn off what <lb/>you deſign, mix it all together, for the <lb/>Uſe of
            any Feveriſh or Conſumptive <lb/>Perſon. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="148"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="roman">Barley Cinamon-Water</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">P</hi>UT two pounds of Pearl Barley, <lb/>into four quarts of
            Spring-Water, <lb/>draw it off in a cold Still, as long as it <lb/>runs ſweet; Infuſe in
            it half a pound <lb/>of Cinamon, and a quart of Canary; <lb/>Sweeten it, and Drink a
            Draught at <lb/>any time, in a Fever and Looſeneſs. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>Wall-nut-Water. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">G</hi>ATHER a large quantity of <lb/>Green Wall-nuts, in the
            beginning <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">June</hi>, break them in a Mortar, <lb/>and diſtil
            them in a cold Still; keep <lb/>this Water by itſelf, and at <hi rend="italic">Midſum-
              <lb/>mer</hi> do the like, keeping that Water <lb/>by itſelf alſo; about a Fortnight
            after <lb/><hi rend="italic">Midſummer</hi> do the like; and ſo again <lb/>a Fortnight
            after that; then put all the <lb/>four Sorts of Water together, and diſtil <lb/>it off;
            keep it cloſe for Uſe; its Per- <lb/>fections are many: 'Tis good in Con- <lb/>ſumption
            and Surfeits; Drank with <pb n="149"/>
            <lb/>Wine in a Morning, 'tis good for a Pal- <lb/>ſey. A Bottle or two in a Veſſel of
            <lb/>decay'd Wine, revives it: It's good to <lb/>waſh the Eyes and Temples. I have
            <lb/>not met with any Simple Water ſo <lb/>well recommended, or by a Perſon of <lb/>more
            Experience. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A very good <hi rend="roman">Snail-Water</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE at peck of Snails clean wip'd, <lb/>crack them and put
            them into a <lb/>gallon of Milk, with a handful of Balm, <lb/>as much Mint and unſet
            Hyſop, half <lb/>a pound of Dates, as many Figs, and <lb/>one pound of Raiſons of the
            Sun; <lb/>diſtil all together, and let it be the <lb/>conſtant Drink in a Conſumption. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A good <hi rend="roman">Milk-Water</hi> for <hi rend="roman">Surfeit</hi>
            <lb/>or <hi rend="roman">Worms</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of Rue, Wormwood, Car- <lb/>duus and Mint, each three
            hand- <lb/>fuls; cut the Herbs and ſteep them <pb n="150"/>
            <lb/>all Night in two quarts of Milk; diſtil <lb/>it off next Morning in a cold Still;
            <lb/>from this Quantity draw three pints, <lb/>then diſtil this Water over again, with
            <lb/>the ſame quantity of Milk and Herbs; <lb/>ſweeten it to your Taſte, if for Chil-
            <lb/>dren; but for wiſer People, 'tis beſt <lb/>alone. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>Strong <hi rend="roman">Elder-berry-Water</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a Buſhel of Elder-berries, and <lb/>put to them a quart
            of Ale-yeaſt, <lb/>let them ſtand nine or ten Days, ſtir- <lb/>ring it two or three
            times a Day, and <lb/>then diſtil it in a Limbeck: 'Tis a very <lb/>good Cordial in any
            Illneſs. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A <hi rend="roman">Cordial Mint-Water</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE one pound of Mint, ſtript <lb/>from the Stalks, and
            gather'd the <lb/>Day before you weigh it; a quarter <lb/>of a pound of Liquoriſh, thin
            ſlic'd, <lb/>one ounce of Aniſeeds, one ounce of <pb n="151"/>
            <lb/>Carraway-ſeeds, one pound of Raiſons <lb/>of the Sun ſton'd, ſteep theſe together
            <lb/>in a gallon of good ſtrong Claret; diſtil <lb/>it off a Limbeck, or cold Still if
            you <lb/>don't like it ſo hot and ſtrong; let it <lb/>drop on a little fine Sugar,
            through a <lb/>Bag of Saffron. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A good <hi rend="roman">Milk-Water</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE one pound of Carduus, half <lb/>a pound of Wormwood,
            Spear- <lb/>mint, Balm ſhred a little; put them <lb/>into an ordinary Still, with a
            gallon of <lb/>Milk; and diſtil it off leiſurely: 'Tis <lb/>good in any Thirſt. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>Another <hi rend="roman">Milk-Water</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">C</hi>ARDUUS and Wormwood, of <lb/>each one handful, Spear-mint
            two <lb/>handfuls, pick and cut the Herbs, and <lb/>pour upon them a pint of Sack; let
            <lb/>them ſtand all Night, and next Day, <lb/>put them into a cold Still, with a gal-
              <pb n="152"/>
            <lb/>lon of new Milk, or new Whey Cla- <lb/>rified: Draw off while it runs good. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A moſt excellent <hi rend="roman">Drink</hi> for the <lb/><hi rend="roman">King's
              Evil</hi> in the <hi rend="roman">Eyes</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Sage, Celandine, Yarrow, Bi- <lb/>tany, three-Leav'd
            Graſs, Cinq- <lb/>foile, Daiſy-roots and Leaves, of each <lb/>a handful; Honey-ſuckles
            and Ground- <lb/>Ivy, the ſame quantity; pick, waſh, <lb/>dry, and bruiſe them, and put
            to them <lb/>a good quart of White-wine, or Beer, <lb/>ſteep them two Nights and Days;
            <lb/>preſs the Herbs out, and drink four <lb/>ſpoonfuls Morning and Night: Juſt as
            <lb/>you Drink it, ſqueeze in the Juice of <lb/>fifty Millepedes, freſh bruis'd. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A good <hi rend="roman">Sear-Cloth</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE one Pint of Oil of Olives, <lb/>eight ounces of
            Red-Lead, Vir- <lb/>gins-wax four ounces; of Ointment <lb/>of Populion, Oil of Roſes,
            and Oil of <pb n="153"/>
            <lb/>Camomile, of each one ounce; ſet the <lb/>pint of Oil on the Fire, and melt the
            <lb/>Wax in it; then put in the Populion, <lb/>and other Oils; when all is melted,
            <lb/>put in the Red Lead, ſtir all well toge- <lb/>ther, and let them boil 'till they
            are <lb/>Black; then dip in your Cloth. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>An Incomparable <hi rend="roman">Salve</hi> for the <lb/>Eyes. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE two ounces of <hi rend="italic">May</hi> Butter,
            <lb/>one ounce of Virgins-wax, half <lb/>an ounce of Camphire, one ounce of <lb/>Powder
            of Tutty; you muſt firſt put <lb/>your Wax and Camphire, into a Sil- <lb/>ver Porringer,
            and let both melt on a <lb/>gentle ſlow Fire together; conſtantly <lb/>ſtirring 'till
            they be diſſolved, ſome lit- <lb/>tle time after put in your <hi rend="italic">May</hi>
            Butter, <lb/>and diſſolve it with a large ſpoonful of <lb/>Red Roſe-Water; keep it on
            the Fire <lb/>till all be incorporated; then add the <lb/>Powder of Tutty, and mix all
            very <lb/>well; take it from the Air; and when <lb/>you lie to Sleep, gently anoint your
            <lb/>Eye-lid with it. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="154"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="roman">Smallage-Ointment</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a handful of Smallage, as <lb/>much Mallows, and as much
            El- <lb/>der; pick and ſhred all ſmall; put <lb/>them into a Skillet, with a pound of
            <lb/>Mutton-ſuet ſhred ſmall; let all boil <lb/>together: Strain it, and keep it to
            <lb/>anoint any Swelling. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A very good <hi rend="roman">Plaiſter</hi> for a Sto- <lb/>mach Sore with Coughing. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of <hi rend="italic">Burgundy</hi>-Pitch, Roſin,
            <lb/>and Bees-wax, of each one ounce; <lb/>melt theſe together: Then take three-
            <lb/>quarters of an ounce of coarſe Turpen- <lb/>tine, and half an ounce of Oyl of Mace;
            <lb/>melt theſe with the other, and keep it <lb/>for Uſe: When you have Occaſion,
            <lb/>ſpread it on Sheep's-leather prick'd full <lb/>of Holes; and when you lay it on,
            <lb/>grate ſome Nutmeg over it. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="155"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>To give certain Eaſe in the <lb/><hi rend="roman">Tooth-ach</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE <hi rend="italic">French</hi>-Flies, Methridate,
            <lb/>and a few drops of Vinegar; beat <lb/>this to a Paſte, and lay a Plaiſter on
            <lb/>the Cheek-bone, or behind the Ear: <lb/>'Twill Bliſter, but rarely fails to Cure. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">Plaiſters</hi> for a <hi rend="roman">Fever</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">B</hi>EAT two handfuls of Rue, with <lb/>as many Currants, 'till
            they are <lb/>fine, and well mix'd; ſpread it on <lb/>Cloths, and bind it to the Wriſts,
            and <lb/>Soles of the Feet: This draws from the <lb/>Head; and, if laid on in time, does
            as <lb/>much good as Pigeons to the Feet, <lb/>in Extremity. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="156"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) hanging space">
            <lb/>An <hi rend="roman">Ointment</hi> that is good for <lb/>any <hi rend="roman"
              >Ach</hi>, or <hi rend="roman">Swelling</hi>, in Man <lb/>or Beaſt. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of unſet Hyſſop, Goats- <lb/>Rue, Adder-ſpear, Alehoof,
            Worm- <lb/>wood, Camomile, Ladies-mantle, Plan- <lb/>tains, Harts-tongue, Ladder to
            Heaven, <lb/>Southernwood, Red-Sage, Agrimony, <lb/>Bone-wort, Amber-leaves, Bay-leaves,
            <lb/>of each one handful; ſhred theſe, and <lb/>ſtamp them together: Then mix with
            <lb/>them one pound and a half of Butter <lb/>without Salt, and make it up in nine
            <lb/>Balls, and let it lie nine Days; then <lb/>boil it over the Fire gently: When it
            <lb/>looks very Green, ſtrain it off, and <lb/>keep it for Uſe. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This Number of Days, and Balls, <lb/>ſeems ſuperſtitious and whimſical; but <lb/>it
            has been ſo long approv'd in the <lb/>Family from whence I had it, that I <lb/>cannot
            doubt of its Virtues, tho' I ſmile <lb/>at the Preparation. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="157"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>An <hi rend="roman">Ointment</hi> for a <hi rend="roman">Burn</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of Houſleek, ſmooth Plan- <lb/>tain-leaves, and green
            Elder, each <lb/>one Pound; ſtamp them together ſmall; <lb/>put to them a quarter of a
            pint of Wine- <lb/>Vinegar, three ſpoonfuls of Urine, and <lb/>four ounces of Old
            Tallow-Candle, with <lb/>three pints of Oyl-Olive; boil theſe two <lb/>or three Hours,
            ſtirring them con- <lb/>ſtantly with a Stick: Then ſtrain it <lb/>through a new
            Canvas-Strainer, and <lb/>put it on the Fire again, with four <lb/>ounces of Yellow
            Bees-wax ſliced thin; <lb/>let it boil half an Hour this time, and <lb/>pour it into
            Pots. 'Twill keep many <lb/>Years, if ty'd down with Bladders. <lb/>When you uſe it, rub
            White Paper 'till <lb/>'tis ſoft, then ſpread it over with the <lb/>Ointment, and anoint
            the Burn with <lb/>the Ointment: Do it with a Feather, <lb/>and lay the Paper over it:
            Do this <lb/>Morning and Night, 'till 'tis quite Well. <lb/>'Twill Skin the Wound, as
            well as take <lb/>out the Fire; therefore be ſure to uſe <lb/>nothing elſe: 'Twill give
            Eaſe in a <lb/>quarter of an Hour. 'Tis a certain <pb n="158"/>
            <lb/>as well as a quick Cure, if the Vitals <lb/>are not burn'd; and iſ recommended,
            <lb/>on the Experience of a Perſon of great <lb/>Worth and Charity. A third-part of
            <lb/>this Quantity will laſt many Years, and <lb/>may be made very Cheap. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) hanging space">
            <lb/>An <hi rend="roman">Ointment</hi>, which is a cer- <lb/>tain Cure for any <hi
              rend="roman">Scabs</hi>, <hi rend="roman">Pim- <lb/>ples</hi>, or Old Inveterate <hi
              rend="roman">Itch</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a quarter of an ounce of <lb/>Red Precipitate, grind it
            on a <lb/>Marble-ſtone, 'till 'tis as fine as the <lb/>Flower of Brimſtone; mix this
            with <lb/>an ounce of Flower of Brimſtone, and <lb/>work both up with three ounces of
            <lb/>Butter without Salt, as it comes from <lb/>the Churn; mix it very well, and anoint
            <lb/>the Place very thin with the Ointment. <lb/>'Tis not the Nature of it to Check, but
            <lb/>Draw Out the Diſtemper; and in a <lb/>Week or Ten Days Confinement, will <lb/>make
            an abſolute Cure. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>I ſhould ſay many things to recom- <lb/>mend this, being ſure of its Virtues; <pb
              n="159"/>
            <lb/>but it will not need that, to Any-body <lb/>of Judgment. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) hanging space">
            <lb/>A very Good <hi rend="roman">Poultis</hi> for a <hi rend="roman">Sore-
              <lb/>Breaſt</hi>, to Break it, if there <lb/>be Occaſion; and alſo Heal <lb/>it,
            without any other Salve. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of Smallage, Spear-mint, <lb/>and Wormwood, each a good
            <lb/>handful; boil all theſe in Milk, and <lb/>thicken it with Oat-meal: Lay it on
            <lb/>as hot as you can bear it, and repeat <lb/>it when Hard or Dry. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) hanging space">
            <lb/>An Incomparable <hi rend="roman">Ointment</hi> for <lb/>a <hi rend="roman"
              >Strain</hi>, <hi rend="roman">Weakneſs</hi>, or <hi rend="roman">Shrink-
              <lb/>ing</hi> in the <hi rend="roman">Nerves</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Sweet-marjoram, Penny- <lb/>royal, Roſemary-tops,
            Camomil- <lb/>flowers, Lavender-flowers, Sage, and <lb/>young Bay-leaves, of each a
            large hand- <lb/>ful; a very large Nutmeg, and its <pb n="160"/>
            <lb/>weight in Mace; the Rind of four Le- <lb/>mons, and as many Oranges: Stamp <lb/>all
            very fine, and boil it in a quarter <lb/>of a pint of rich <hi rend="italic"
            >Malaga</hi>-Wine, and <lb/>half a pound of unſalted Butter: Let it <lb/>boil 'till the
            Wine is waſted; preſs it <lb/>through a fine Sieve, and keep it cool <lb/>for Uſe. Rub
            it Morning and Night <lb/>before the Fire, on the Part affected. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="roman">French-King</hi>'s <hi rend="roman">Balſom</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Red-Sage, and Rue, of <lb/>each half a pound; young Bay-
            <lb/>leaves, and Wormwood, of each a <lb/>quarter of a pound: Stamp them <lb/>unwaſh'd
            in a Mortar, with a pound <lb/>and a half of Sheep's-ſuet hot from the <lb/>Sheep, 'till
            'tis all of a Colour: Then <lb/>add to it a quart of Oyl-Olive, and work <lb/>that with
            the reſt: Then put it into an <lb/>Earthen Pot well ſtopt for eight Days: <lb/>Then boil
            it on on a ſoft Fire: Being <lb/>ready to take off, pour in three ounces <lb/>of Oyl of
            Spike; let it boil a little toge- <lb/>ther; then ſtrain it, and keep it for <lb/>Uſe:
            Take care it do not burn. It <pb n="161"/>
            <lb/>muſt be made in <hi rend="italic">May</hi>, and will keep <lb/>many Years: Rub'd
            into the ſmall of <lb/>the Back, it eaſes the Stone: The quan- <lb/>tity of half a Pea
            in the Ear, chafed <lb/>in and ſtopt with black Wool, helps <lb/>Pains there; It Cures
            Stiffneſs or Strains, <lb/>in Man or Beaſt; as alſo Bruiſes, <lb/>Over-ſtretching of
            Veins, Fellons, An- <lb/>guiſh, or Swelling of Wounds: It <lb/>eaſes the Cramp; and is a
            good and <lb/>uſeful Balſom in all Families. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For the <hi rend="roman">Biting</hi> of a <hi rend="roman">Mad-Dog</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE four ounces of Rue, four <lb/>ounces of <hi
              rend="italic">London</hi> Treacle, four <lb/>ſpoonfuls of ſcrap'd Pewter, and four
            <lb/>ounces of Garlick; ſtamp the Garlick, <lb/>and boil all in a pottle of Stale ſtrong
            <lb/>Ale; ſtrain this Drink; let that which <lb/>is thick be apply'd to the Wound, and
            <lb/>take nine ſpoonfuls of the clear, for <lb/>nine Days together. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="162"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>An <hi rend="roman">Ointment</hi> for a Child that <lb/>has the Rickets. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE one ounce of Beef Marrow, <lb/>as much Oil of Lillies,
            and Ta- <lb/>marisk, Bees-wax two ounces, Gum <lb/>Ammoniacum diſſolv'd in Vinegar, half
            <lb/>an ounce; Juice of Briany-roots, Smal- <lb/>lage, and Golden-Rod, of each one
            <lb/>ounce; let all boil, 'till the Juice of the <lb/>Herbs be conſumed: With this
            anoint <lb/>the Belly of the Child, rubbing it in <lb/>with your warm Hand by the Fire,
            half <lb/>an Hour every Night. 'Tis good if the <lb/>Belly is Swell'd with Rickets,
            Worms, <lb/>or Ague. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>An <hi rend="roman">Ointment</hi>, for the Back of <lb/>a Weak Ricketty Child. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">P</hi>ICK Snails clean out of the Shells, <lb/>and prick them full
            of Holes, hang <lb/>them up in a Cloth, and put a Baſon to <lb/>catch what drops from
            them; which <lb/>you muſt boil up with Speracity, and <lb/>blades of Mace, of each one
            ounce: <pb n="163"/>
            <lb/>Rub this Ointment along the Back-bone, <lb/>round the Neck, Wriſts, and Ancles.
            <lb/>Uſe this conſtantly Night and Morn- <lb/>ing, and chafe it in by the Fire; this,
            <lb/>with the Drink that follows, has Re- <lb/>cover'd many Weak Children from
            <lb/>Sickneſs, Lameneſs, and Deformity. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>The <hi rend="roman">Ricketty</hi> Drink. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">P</hi>UT an ounce of Rhubarb, three <lb/>hundred live Wood-lice,
            Saſſafras, <lb/>China, and Eringo-roots, of each three <lb/>ounces; Roots of
            Oſmond-royal, two <lb/><choice>
              <corr>ounces</corr>
              <sic>onnces</sic>
            </choice>; Raiſons of the Sun ſton'd, <lb/>two ounces; Hart's-Tongue, two hand-
            <lb/>fuls: Put theſe into ſix quarts of Small <lb/>Ale, and Drink Spring and Fall no
            <lb/>other Drink. 'Tis almoſt infallible <lb/>for weak Children. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A cooling Drink in a <hi rend="roman">Fever</hi> or <lb/><hi rend="roman"
              >Pluriſie</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">P</hi>UT an ounce of Pearl-Barley, into <lb/>three Pints of Water;
            ſhift it twice; <lb/>beat half an ounce of Almonds, with a <pb n="164"/>
            <lb/>bit of Lemon-peel, and a ſpoonful or <lb/>two of the Water; when they are very
            <lb/>fine, waſh the Almond-Milk through <lb/>your Sieve, with three pints of Barley-
            <lb/>Water; in the laſt boiling of this, you <lb/>may put Mellon-ſeeds, and Pumpion-
            <lb/>ſeeds, of each half an ounce; white <lb/>Poppey-ſeeds, half a dram; when theſe
            <lb/>are well boil'd, mix the Liquor with <lb/>the Almonds, and ſtrain all. Sweeten
            <lb/>it with Syrop of Lemons, for a Fever, <lb/>or Syrop of Maiden-hair, and Drink
            <lb/>four ounces every three or four Hours. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>Another <hi rend="roman">Drink</hi> in a <hi rend="roman">Fever</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a little Sage, a little Balm, <lb/>and a little
            Wood-ſorrel, waſh <lb/>and dry them; ſlice a ſmall Lemon, <lb/>(after you have par'd it
            clean from <lb/>the white and bitter part;) To theſe <lb/>Herbs and ſliced Lemon, pour
            three <lb/>pints of boiling Water: Sweeten it to <lb/>your Taſte, and Drink as freely as
            <lb/>you pleaſe. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="165"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>Another <hi rend="roman">Drink</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>O three pints of Barley-Water, <lb/>often ſhifted, put
            Harts-horn, <lb/>and Ivory-ſhavings, of each three <lb/>drams; Quick-graſs-Roots, two
            ounces; <lb/>Currants, one ounce; Red-roſe-Water, <lb/>half a pint; a very little Balm:
            Let it <lb/>boil, and ſweeten it with Syrop of Le- <lb/>mons or Violets. If the Patient
            is <lb/>Coſtive, a few drops of Spirit of Vitriol <lb/>ſerves inſtead of Lemons, when
            that <lb/>cannot be had: Of this you may Drink <lb/>freely in a Fever or Quinſie. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>Another Sort. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">C</hi>LEAR Poſſet-drink, pour'd on <lb/>Wood-ſorrel only, is good,
            and <lb/>allays Thirſt better than any other; <lb/>and Pippins ſlic'd into Milk, is as
            good <lb/>and better than all; if you have a Le- <lb/>mon to ſlice in with them, being
            not <lb/>ſharp enough of themſelves, to turn it <lb/>to a pleaſant clearneſs. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="166"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A cold <hi rend="roman">Caudle</hi> in a <hi rend="roman">Fever</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">B</hi>OIL a quart of Spring-water; let <lb/>it ſtand 'till cold,
            then add the <lb/>Yolk of one Egg, the Juice of a ſmall <lb/>Lemon, ſix ſpoonfuls of
            Sack, and Su- <lb/>gar to your Taſte; Syrop of Lemons <lb/>one ounce, if you have not
            freſh Le- <lb/>mons, does as well; Brew all together <lb/>'till well mixt, then Drink
            freely. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Elder-flower-Water cold ſtill'd, is an <lb/>excellent Drink for Heat and Thirſt;
            <lb/>quicken each draught with five or ſix <lb/>drops of Spirit of Vitriol; and ſweeten
            <lb/>it to your Taſte. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">Wall-nut-Water</hi>, good In <hi rend="roman">Agues</hi>
            <lb/>or <hi rend="roman">Fever</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a pound of Rue, and a <lb/>pound of Green Wall-nuts,
            before <lb/>the Shell be hard, a pound of good <lb/>Figs; bruiſe all and diſtil it: Take
            a <lb/>Draught before your Fit, and try to <lb/>Sweat after it. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="167"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>An excellent <hi rend="roman">Snail-Water</hi> in a <lb/><hi rend="roman"
              >Conſumption</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a peck of large Shell Snails, <lb/>lay them on a hot
            Hearth before <lb/>the Fire; let them lie 'till they have <lb/>done Hiſſing and
            Spitting; then wipe <lb/>them from the Froth, and break them <lb/>in a Mortar; have a
            quart of Earth- <lb/>Worms, ſlit and ſcoured clean with <lb/>Salt and Water; beat them
            with the <lb/>Snails; then take Angelica, Salendine, <lb/>Wood-ſorrel, Agrimony,
            Bearfoot, Bar- <lb/>berry-bark, Great Dock-roots, of each <lb/>two handfuls; Rue half a
            handful, <lb/>Roſemary-flowers, one quart; half <lb/>a pound of Harts-horn, Termarick,
            and <lb/>Fenigreek, of each two ounces; half <lb/>an ounce of powder'd Saffron; and
            three <lb/>ounces of Cloves freſh beat; ſhred theſe <lb/>Ingredients, and Infuſe all in
            three gal- <lb/>lons of Strong Ale, for twelve Hours; <lb/>then diſtil it, and draw off
            what runs <lb/>good; and take three ſpoonfuls of <lb/>this in a Glaſs of Sack or
            White-wine, <lb/>an Hour before every Meal. Uſe <lb/>moderate Exerciſe with it: 'Tis
            high- <pb n="168"/>
            <lb/>ly recommended, and has been us'd <lb/>with conſtant Succeſs in Conſumptions
            <lb/>and Jaundice. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A <hi rend="roman">Poſſet-Drink</hi>, to be taken be- <lb/>fore the <hi
              rend="roman">Fit</hi> of an <hi rend="roman">Ague</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">P</hi>OUR a gallon of clear Poſſet-Drink, <lb/>upon four large
            handfuls of Angeli- <lb/>ca, ſhred ſmall; let it Infuſe, 'till 'tis <lb/>very ſtrong:
            Let the Perſon, if poſſi- <lb/>ble, Drink all, that the Stomach may <lb/>be perfectly
            clear; and go into a <lb/>warm Bed, as ſoon as the Vomit has <lb/>done working: Cover
            yourſelf cloſe, <lb/>and try to Sweat. It has ſeldom fail'd, <lb/>and is a ſafe Vomit. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A good <hi rend="roman">Epidemick-Water</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Rue, Roſemary, Pimper- <lb/>nel, Roſaſolis, Balm,
            Scordium, <lb/>Carduus, Dragon, Marigold-flowers <lb/>and Leaves, Goats-Rue, Mint, and
            <lb/>Angelica, of each two handfuls; take <pb n="169"/>
            <lb/>the Roots of Elecampane, Piony, Ma- <lb/>ſterwort, and Butter-bur, of each one
            <lb/>pound; Gentian, Tormentil, Scorzone- <lb/>ra, and <hi rend="italic"
            >Virginia</hi>-Snake-weed, of each <lb/>four ounces; Saffron one ounce: In- <lb/>fuſe
            all theſe, when ſhred, in two <lb/>quarts of White-wine, one quart of <lb/>Water, and
            one quart of <hi rend="italic">French</hi>-Bran- <lb/>dy diſtil'd, and uſe it in any
            Malignant <lb/>Diſtemper. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) hanging space">
            <lb/>An admirable <hi rend="roman">Poſſet-Drink</hi>, in <lb/>a <hi rend="roman"
              >Pluriſie</hi>, or <hi rend="roman">Shortneſs of <lb/>Breath</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>NFUSE two ounces of Flax-ſeed, <lb/>in a pint of clear
            Poſſet-drink; firſt <lb/>bruiſe the Seeds. Drink this quanti- <lb/>ty at a Draught every
            Morning, and <lb/>at Night, if very Ill. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/> It has the ſame Virtues of Linſeed- <lb/>Oil; but is not ſo hard to take. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="170"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For an <hi rend="roman">Inflammation</hi> in the <lb/><hi rend="roman">Throat</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>NFUSE one large handful of <lb/>Cinqfoile in a quart of
            Water, <lb/>let it boil to a pint; ſtrain it, and <lb/>ſweeten it with Honey very ſweet,
            and <lb/>ſwallow two or three ſpoonfuls often. <lb/>This, tho' a ſimple Medicine, has
            done <lb/>great Cures, and may be rely'd on. <lb/>The Herb is otherwiſe call'd <hi
              rend="italic">Five- <lb/>leav'd-Graſs</hi>. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For a <hi rend="roman">Cough</hi>, and <hi rend="roman">Shortneſs <lb/>of
              Breath</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE eight ounces of Colts-foot <lb/>pick'd clean from the
            Stalks; beat <lb/>it to a perfect Conſerve, with four ounces <lb/>of Brown Sugar-candy,
            four ounces of <lb/>Raiſons ſtoned: When 'tis very fine, <lb/>and well mix'd, add four
            ounces of <lb/>Conſerve of Roſes; then add twenty <lb/>drops of Spirit of Sulphur, and
            ten <lb/>drops of Spirit of Vitriol: Mix it well, <pb n="171"/>
            <lb/>and take as much as a large Nutmeg, <lb/>as often as you pleaſe. I think the
            <lb/>Juice of the Colts-foot, mixt with the <lb/>Sugar-candy, is better than the Leaves,
            <lb/>without ſtraining. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A good Way to make <hi rend="roman">Caudle</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>O four full-quarts of Water you <lb/>may put a pint of Whole
            Oat- <lb/>meal; let it boil very ſlow for five or <lb/>ſix Hours at leaſt; then ſtrain
            it out, <lb/>and put to two quarts three large blades <lb/>of Mace, a full pint and a
            half of White <lb/>or Rheniſh-wine; and make it ſweet <lb/>to your Taſte: And juſt as
            you take <lb/>it off the Fire, ſlice in a Lemon from <lb/>which all the White is cut,
            which is <lb/>apt, by lying long, to make it bitter; <lb/>juſt the Yellow of the Peel
            may be <lb/>put in. A little Salt does very well in <lb/>Caudle, but is not often uſed.
          </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="172"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A very good <hi rend="roman">Purge</hi> in a <hi rend="roman">Fever</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Sena two drams, Rhubarb <lb/>one dram, Tamarinds two
            drams; <lb/>boil theſe in half a pint of Water, 'till <lb/>two-thirds be waſted; To what
            re- <lb/>mains, add half an ounce of Cream of <lb/>Tartar, ſweetened with one ounce of
            <lb/>Syrop of Succory, or Syrop of Roſes <lb/>ſolutive; ſtrain and drink it at a
            <lb/>Draught. In the Working, drink Cla- <lb/>rify'd Whey, rather than Poſſet-Drink.
            <lb/>'Tis good to Cool and Thin the Blood. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>An Incomparable <hi rend="roman">Drink</hi> in a <lb/>Thirſty <hi rend="roman"
              >Fever</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>N ounce <choice>
              <corr>and</corr>
              <sic>an</sic>
            </choice> a half of Tamarinds, <lb/>three ounces of Currants, and two <lb/>ounces of
            ſton'd Raiſons, boiled in <lb/>three pints of Water 'till near one- <lb/>third be
            conſumed. Strain and drink <lb/>this when you are Coſtive. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="173"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A <hi rend="roman">Draught</hi> for a <hi rend="roman">Conſumption</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Mint, and Red Roſe-water, <lb/>of each two large
            ſpoonfuls, Sugar- <lb/>candy finely beat one ounce; warm <lb/>theſe together, with a
            little grated <lb/>Nutmeg; pour to it near half a pint <lb/>of Milk juſt warm from the
            Cow. <lb/>Drink this twice a Day, for ſix Weeks, <lb/>in the Spring. It has recover'd
            many <lb/>from Weakneſs, and Faint Sweats. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>An excellent <hi rend="roman">Electuary</hi> for <lb/>a <hi rend="roman"
              >Conſumption</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Hore-hound, Harts-tongue, <lb/>Liver-wort, Maiden-hair,
            Egri- <lb/>mony, Unſet Hyſſop, Germander, and <lb/>Colts-foot, of each one handful; boil
            <lb/>them in a gallon of Spring-water 'till <lb/>half be conſumed: Then take three
            <lb/>pounds of Live Honey, half an ounce of <lb/>Powder of Elecampane, and an ounce
            <lb/>of Powder of Annis-ſeed; ſift them both <lb/>through a Sieve: Boil theſe together
            <lb/>'till it come to the Conſiſtence of an <lb/>Electuary: Take the quantity of a <pb
              n="174"/>
            <lb/>Nutmeg faſting in the Morning, and <lb/>faſt an Hour after it. Take the like
            <lb/>quantity at Night when you go to <lb/>Bed. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A <hi rend="roman">Poppy-Water</hi> for <hi rend="roman">Surfeits</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">B</hi> REW ten gallons of Strong Ale- <lb/>Wort; when 'tis cool,
            work it with <lb/>Yeaſt, and add as many freſh Red <lb/>Poppies as the Wort will
            conveniently <lb/>wet, ſo that you may ſtir it daily: Let <lb/>the Poppies Infuſe in
            this Wort three <lb/>Days and Nights; then draw it off <lb/>in a Limbeck as quick as you
            can, <lb/>'till the whole is diſtill'd off: Mix <lb/>the Small and Strong together, and
            <lb/>take a glaſs at any time, with or with- <lb/>out Sugar, after a full or diſguſting
            <lb/>Meal. 'Tis not much ſtronger than <lb/>a Simple Water, but has been the only
            <lb/>Cordial of an Infirm Lady, who has <lb/>us'd it ever ſince Fifteen, and ſhe is now
            <lb/>Ninety-ſeven. This of my own know- <lb/>ledge. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="175"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>Another for a <hi rend="roman">Surfeit</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">B</hi>OIL a handful of freſh or dry'd <lb/>Poppies in Ale, with an
            ounce of <lb/>Carraway-ſeeds bruiſed: Sweeten it, <lb/>and drink a large Draught. If the
            <lb/>Stomach is ſo ſick as to diſcharge it, <lb/>repeat it 'till it does ſtay, and Sleep
            <lb/>on it. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A Rich <hi rend="roman">Surfeit Cordial-Water</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE four pound of freſh Red <lb/>Poppies, Infuſe them in
            four <lb/>quarts of Brandy; add to it half a pound <lb/>of Dates ſliced, half a pound of
            Figs <lb/>ſliced, a pound of Raiſons ſtoned; Car- <lb/>raway and Angelica-ſeeds bruiſed,
            of <lb/>each one ounce; Mace, Cinamon, <lb/>Cloves, and Nutmeg, of each a quar- <lb/>ter
            of an ounce; Marigold-flowers, and <lb/>Balm, of each one handful; Sugar- <lb/>candy one
            pound; Hot Angelica and <lb/>Cold, of each one pint: Steep all theſe <lb/>a Month,
            ſtirring them every Day. <lb/>If you have a convenient Place, let it <lb/>ſtand in the
            Sun. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="176"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A Wholſome <hi rend="roman">Cordial</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE one pound of Gentian-roots <lb/>ſliced, common
            Dock-roots ſliced <lb/>half a pound; Centory, both Flowers <lb/>and Leaves, of each half
            a pound: <lb/>Put theſe into a great Glaſs, with one <lb/>pound of Poppies: Pour upon
            theſe In- <lb/>gredients ſix quarts of White-wine: <lb/>Let it ſtand twenty-four Hours
            to <lb/>Infuſe; then draw it off in a Limbeck. <lb/>'Tis Good and Safe in any Illneſs of
            <lb/>the Stomach. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For the <hi rend="roman">Gout</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>AKE a Conſerve of Buck-bean, <lb/>with the weight in
            Sugar-candy; <lb/>beat both fine, and take as much as a <lb/>large Nutmeg, firſt and
            laſt; and drink <lb/>a Tea made of the ſame Herb every <lb/>Morning and Afternoon,
            conſtantly, <lb/>for one whole Year. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This alone, without any other Medi- <lb/>cine, made a perfect Cure in a Perſon
            <lb/>that had been many Years moſt <pb n="177"/>
            <lb/>grievouſly afflicted; and is effectual in <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Scurvy</hi>,
            or <hi rend="italic">Rheumatic Pains</hi>. Where <lb/>the Patient is Weak, and very
            Reſtleſs, <lb/>'tis beſt to mix a third-part <hi rend="italic">Venice</hi>- <lb/>Treacle
            in the Conſerve they take <lb/>when going to Reſt. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A <hi rend="roman">Drink</hi> for the <hi rend="roman">Gout</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">S</hi>Arſaparilla eight ounces, Saſſafras, <lb/>China, and
            Harts-horn-Shavings, <lb/>of each three ounces, Angelica-Roots <lb/>three ounces,
            Raiſons one pound, and <lb/>the Roots of Sweet-ſmelling-Flag three <lb/>ounces, of
            Candy'd Eringo-root half a <lb/>pound; hang theſe in ſix gallons of <lb/>ſmall Ale, when
            you Tun it up: And <lb/>as ſoon as 'tis a Fortnight old, drink <lb/>of it conſtantly. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>'Tis an incomparable <hi rend="italic">Drink</hi> to <lb/>Sweeten the Blood, and
            Correct thoſe <lb/>very Sharp Humours that occaſion <lb/>that diſmal Tormenting
            Diſtemper. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="178"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For the <hi rend="roman">Head-ach</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">D</hi>RY Roſemary before the Fire 'till <lb/>'twill crumble to a
            very fine <lb/>Powder, one pugil of Saffron; and <lb/>with the Powder of Roſemary and
            <lb/>Saffron make the Yolk of an Egg into <lb/>a ſtiff Poultis, and lay it as hot as you
            <lb/>can endure it to the Temples. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For the <hi rend="roman">Stone</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Gravel</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of Caſſia newly drawn one <lb/>ounce and a half, choice
            Rhubard <lb/>in Powder a dram and a half, <hi rend="italic">Cyprus</hi>- <lb/>Turpentine
            well waſhed ſeven drams, <lb/>Spic'd Diatragacanth one ſcruple, Pow- <lb/>der of
            Licorice half a dram; mix it in <lb/>a good quantity of Syrop of Marſh- <lb/>mallows.
            Take the quantity of a <lb/>Wall-nut in a Morning faſting: Drink <lb/>a Draught of plain
            Ale-Poſſet-drink <lb/>immediately after it; then Walk an <lb/>Hour: And after that,
            drink a pint <lb/>(if your Stomach will bear it) of <pb n="179"/>
            <lb/>White-wine Poſſet ſweeten'd with Sy- <lb/>rop of Marſh-mallows. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">N. B.</hi> This was the Preſcription of <lb/>a Learned Phyſician;
            and has been <lb/>long kept as a choice Secret in a very <lb/>Charitable Family, who
            have made <lb/>numberleſs Experiments of it with mi- <lb/>raculous Succeſs, even to
            Diſſolve the <lb/>Stone. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>Another for <hi rend="roman">Stoppage of Water</hi>, <lb/>in the <hi rend="roman"
              >Stone</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE four ſpoonfuls of the Juice <lb/>of Parſley in a pint of
            White-wine; <lb/>ſweeten it with Syrop of Marſh-mal- <lb/>lows, and (if you can) drink
            the <lb/>whole quantity at a Draught. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For the <hi rend="roman">Stone</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>AKE a very ſtrong Decoction of <lb/>Mallows, thus; Put in
            half a peck <lb/>of Leaves into one gallon of Water; <lb/>let it boil to near half the
            quantity: <lb/>Then ſtrain it, and add half as many <lb/>Leaves, and boil it again: Then
            add <lb/>Licorice, ſtoned Raiſons, and Syrop <pb n="180"/>
            <lb/>of Marſh-mallows, of each two ounces; <lb/>and drink continually of this Drink:
            <lb/>It has given Eaſe to many in Extre- <lb/>mity. Obſerve to ſtrain it clean, and
            <lb/>let it ſettle from the Thick before you <lb/>pour it off. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For the <hi rend="roman">Stone</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of good White-wine one <lb/>pint; Fennel, and
            Parſley-water, <lb/>of each one pint: Into this Mixture <lb/>put one ounce of Live
            Wood-lice well <lb/>cleanſed, one Lemon ſliced thin, and two <lb/>ounces of Syrop of
            Marſh-mallows; <lb/>put theſe into a Jug to Infuſe for five <lb/>or ſix Days: Then
            ſtrain it out, and <lb/>let the Patient take four ounces at a <lb/>time, twice a Day. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For the <hi rend="roman">Scurvy</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Scurvy-graſs, Garden-Tanſy, <lb/>Wood-ſorrel, and
            Golden-rod, of <lb/>each one handful; beat theſe Herbs <lb/>to a Conſerve with their
            weight in <lb/>Sugar; add to them an ounce of Pow- <pb n="181"/>
            <lb/>der of Wake-Robin: Take as much <lb/>Syrop of Oranges as will make this <lb/>into
            an Electuary, of which take a <lb/>dram three times a Day, for ſix <lb/>Weeks together,
            in the Spring; drink- <lb/>ing after it the following <hi rend="italic">Drink</hi>. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Garden-Tanſy, Garden Scur- <lb/>vy-graſs, of each ſix
            handfuls; <lb/>Buck-bean, Water-creſſes, Brook-lime, <lb/>and Wood-ſorrel, of each four
            hand- <lb/>fuls, the Peel of ſix Oranges, and one <lb/>ounce of Nutmegs bruiſed; Infuſe
            <lb/>theſe in two gallons of New Strong <lb/>Ale-wort; let it work together a Day
            <lb/>and a Night; then diſtil it off in a <lb/>Cold Still as long as it runs Good:
            <lb/>Mix the Small, and drink a Wine- <lb/>Glaſs-full after every Doſe of the <lb/><hi
              rend="italic">Electuary</hi>. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This has been taken with great Suc- <lb/>ceſs, by People who have been much
            <lb/>afflicted with <hi rend="italic">Scurvy Pains</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
              >Spots</hi>. <lb/>It has, by conſtant Taking, Cur'd a <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >Rhumatiſm</hi>. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="182"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For the ſame. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">O</hi>NE handful of Garden-Tanſy, as <lb/>much Sage, and twice as
            much <lb/>Scurvy-graſs, ſteep'd in two quarts of <lb/>White-wine, or Strong Ale. Drink
            <lb/>half a pint of this Morning and Night. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For the ſame. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>NTO five gallons of well Brew'd <lb/>Small Ale, put in a Bag
            one large <lb/>handful of Fir-tree-Tops cut ſmall, <lb/>two handfuls of Scurvy-graſs, as
            much <lb/>Water-creſſes, one Pound of Burdock- <lb/>root ſcraped and ſliced, the Juice
            and <lb/>Rinds of twelve <hi rend="italic">Sevil</hi>-Oranges; let <lb/>theſe be put in
            while the Ale is Work- <lb/>ing: When it has done, ſtop it down <lb/>'till 'tis Fine;
            then drink of it for a <lb/>Month, or Six Weeks. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Uſe the ſame for a <hi rend="italic">Dropſy</hi>; adding <lb/>only a quarter of a
            pound of Muſtard- <lb/>ſeed, and half a pound of Horſe- <lb/>radiſh-root. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="183"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>An Excellent <hi rend="roman">Purging-Ale</hi> for <lb/>a <hi rend="roman"
              >Dropſy</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">S</hi>ENA four ounces; Saſſafras, and <lb/>Tartar, of each two
            ounces; Jalop, <lb/>and Licorice, of each one ounce; Rhu- <lb/>barb, Coriander, and
            Annis-ſeed, of <lb/>each one ounce; Polypodiam eight <lb/>ounces; Broom-aſhes one quart,
            and <lb/>one ounce of Cloves; put all in a Bag, <lb/>with ſome little Weight to ſink it:
            <lb/>Take Scabious, and Agrimony, of each <lb/>three handfuls; of the Roots of Danes-
            <lb/>wort, one handful, Raiſons of the Sun <lb/>ſtoned one pound, with a little Ginger:
            <lb/>Put theſe Ingredients into ſweet Ale- <lb/>wort, when you put in your Hops, and
            <lb/>let all boil together half an Hour; <lb/>then pour it ſcalding-hot on your Bag
            <lb/>of Drugs: When 'tis cold enough, ſet <lb/>it to Work with Yeaſt: When it has
            <lb/>done Working, ſtop it up for Twelve <lb/>Days, or a Fortnight: Hang the Bag <lb/>of
            Drugs in the Veſſel. Drink a large <lb/>Glaſs of this in the Morning, and at <lb/>Four
            in the Afternoon, unleſs you find <lb/>it Works too much at firſt; if ſo, leſſen <pb
              n="184"/>
            <lb/>your Doſe; but take it Daily, 'till you <lb/>have taken all. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For a <hi rend="roman">Dropſy</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Broom, and burn it by it- <lb/>ſelf, in a clean Oven;
            ſift the <lb/>Aſhes from the Stalks and Coals that <lb/>are not quite conſumed, and put
            two <lb/>full pounds of theſe Aſhes into a two- <lb/>quart Bottle; pour on old Hock,
            'till <lb/>the Bottle is up to the Neck; take care <lb/>'tis not too full; if it has not
            room to <lb/>ferment, 'twill be apt to ſplit the Bot- <lb/>tle: digeſt it in hot Aſhes
            by the Fire, <lb/>or in the Sun, and ſhake it often: <lb/>when it has ſtood three or
            four Days, <lb/>pour off a quart of the clear Lye: if it <lb/>is not perfectly fine,
            decant again and <lb/>again, 'till it is ſo: fill up your Bottle a- <lb/>gain with Hock,
            and do as before, 'till <lb/>all the ſtrength of the Aſhes be out. <lb/>Drink this
            firſt, and at four or five <lb/>in the Afternoon; continue it for <lb/>ſome time, and
            'twill carry off the <lb/>Dropſical Humour: While you take it, <lb/>let the Meat you Eat
            be dry roaſted; <lb/>and your Drink, ſtrong Ale or Wine. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="185"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For the <hi rend="roman">Dropſy</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>IX four ounces of Syrop of Elder- <lb/>berries, with two
            ounces of Oil of <lb/>Turpentine, incorporate them well to- <lb/>gether; and take one
            large ſpoonful of <lb/>this mixture, firſt and laſt, for a Fort- <lb/>night. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Note</hi>, That Sea-bisket, and New <lb/>Raiſons of the Sun (if
            they can be <lb/>had) eaten conſtantly, inſtead of Sup- <lb/>pers, have Cured that
            Diſtemper with- <lb/>out Phyſick: Eſpecially if the Party <lb/>can refrain from ſmall
            Liquors. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For the <hi rend="roman">Jaundice</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">C</hi>UT off the top of a <hi rend="italic">Sevil</hi>-Orange,
            <lb/>and take out as well as you can <lb/>the middle Core and Seeds, without <lb/>the
            Juice; fill the vacancy with Saf- <lb/>fron, and lay the top on again; then <lb/>roaſt
            it carefully without burning, and <lb/>throw it into a pint of White-wine: <lb/>Drink a
            quarter of a pint Faſting, for <pb n="186"/>
            <lb/>nine Days; it greatly ſweetens and <lb/>clears the Blood. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) hanging space">
            <lb/>To Sweeten the <hi rend="roman">Blood</hi>, in <hi rend="roman">Scur- <lb/>vy</hi>,
              <hi rend="roman">Jaundice</hi>, or any Pains <lb/>in the <hi rend="roman">Limbs</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Scurvy-graſs, Maiden-hair, <lb/>Wild Germander,
            Wood-ſorrel, <lb/>Fumitory, of each half a handful; Wild <lb/>Mercury one handful;
            Damask-Roſes <lb/>two handfuls; put theſe into two <lb/>quarts of clarify'd Whey; let
            all ſtand <lb/>'till 'tis ſcalding hot, then ſtrain it off; <lb/>and Drink half a pint
            at a Draught, <lb/>four or five times in a Day, for a <lb/>Month or five Weeks in the
            Spring. <lb/>This is highly recommended in the <lb/>Gout. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A good <hi rend="roman">Bitter Wine</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE two quarts of ſtrong White- <lb/>wine, Infuſe in it one
            Dram of Rhu- <lb/>barb, a Dram and half of Gentian-root, <lb/>Roman Wormwood, tops of
            Carduus, <pb n="187"/>
            <lb/>Centory, Camomile-flowers, of each <lb/>three drams, Yellow peep of Oranges,
            <lb/>half an ounce; Nutmegs, Mace, and <lb/>Cloves, of each one dram: Infuſe all
            <lb/>theſe two Days and Nights; ſtrain and <lb/>Drink a glaſs Faſting, and an Hour be-
            <lb/>fore Dinner and Supper: Add Filings <lb/>of Steel (if 'tis proper) two ounces. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A Pleaſant and Safe <hi rend="roman">Medicine</hi>, <lb/>for the <hi rend="roman"
              >Yellow Jaundice</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">R</hi>OAST a large Lemon 'till 'tis <lb/>ſoft, take care it do not
            break; cut <lb/>it and ſqueeze it (while 'tis very hot) <lb/>upon a dram of Termerick
            ſlic'd or <lb/>grated, and half a dram of Saffron; <lb/>pour upon theſe Ingredients a
            pint of <lb/>good White-wine: Let all Infuſe one <lb/>Night; and in the Morning,
            Faſting, <lb/>take a quarter of a pint of this Liquor; <lb/>ſweeten it to your Taſte
            with Sugar- <lb/>candy; or if your Stomach can bear <lb/>it, the Sugar-candy may be
            omitted; <lb/>repeat this for four Mornings, or longer <lb/>if you have Occaſion. 'Tis
            for the moſt <lb/>part a certain cure. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="188"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For the <hi rend="roman">Stone</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">W</hi>ASH, dry, and very finely Pow- <lb/>der the inner Skin of
            Pigeons- <lb/>Gizzards: Take as much as will lie on <lb/>a Shilling of this Powder, in a
            glaſs of <lb/>White-wine. This does very often <lb/>give eaſe in wracking Pain. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>Another for the <hi rend="roman">Stone</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">D</hi>RY and Powder the Haw-thorn- <lb/>Berries, and take as much
            as <lb/>will lie on a Shilling in a glaſs of White- <lb/>wine: This has done great
            Cures, by <lb/>conſtant taking; it may be taken in <lb/>Ale, if you cannot have Wine;
            the <lb/>Virtue is in the Berry, and has been <lb/>experienc'd to the great eaſe of many
            <lb/>poor People, in Ale as well as Wine; <lb/>but the laſt is beſt: and a Poſſet-
            <lb/>Drink turn'd with White-wine, is a <lb/>proper Vehicle for it. Take it Faſting,
            <lb/>or when in Pain. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="189"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>An excellent <hi rend="roman">Drink</hi> in the <hi rend="roman">Gout</hi>
            <lb/>or <hi rend="roman">Rhumatiſm</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE ſix ounces of Saſſafras; <lb/>Sarſaparilla, and China,
            of each <lb/>four ounces; Liquoriſh and Aniſeeds, <lb/>of each two ounces; Sage of
            Virtue, <lb/>half a handful; Candy'd Eringo-root, <lb/>two ounces; Raiſons and Figs, of
            each <lb/>half a pound: Put all theſe into four <lb/>quarts of Water: let it infuſe over
            a <lb/>ſlow Fire, 'till one third is waſted. <lb/>Strain and Drink it conſtantly, to
            <lb/>ſweeten the Blood. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A good <hi rend="roman">Mouth-Water</hi>, to be us'd <lb/>Daily in the <hi
              rend="roman">Scurvy</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE half a handful of Red-roſe- <lb/>Leaves, three ounces of
            Black- <lb/>thorn-Bark ſlic'd, a bit of Allum; boil <lb/>theſe in a pint of Claret, and
            as much <lb/>Water, 'till a third is waſted; then put <lb/>in the peel of one <hi
              rend="italic">Sevil</hi>-Orange, a hand- <lb/>ful of Scurvy-graſs, and as much Pow-
              <pb n="190"/>
            <lb/>der'd Myrrh as will lie on a Shilling; <lb/>ſtir all together, and let it boil up;
            then <lb/>ſtrain it, and hold a Mouthful as long <lb/>as you can, once or twice a Day:
            It <lb/>faſtens looſe Teeth, and makes the <lb/>Gums grow up to the Teeth. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A Gargle for a <hi rend="roman">Sore Throat</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Plantain, and Red-roſe- <lb/>Water, of each half a pint;
            the <lb/>Whites of Eggs beat into Water, four <lb/>ſpoonfuls; Juice of Houſe-leek, freſh
            <lb/>beat, four ſpoonfuls; as much of the <lb/>Water in which Jews-Ears have been
            <lb/>boil'd; twenty drops of Spirit of Vitriol, <lb/>and an ounce of Honey of Roſes. </p>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>For a <hi rend="roman">Canker</hi> in the <hi rend="roman">Mouth</hi> or <lb/><hi
              rend="roman">Gums</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>IX forty drops of Spirit of Vitriol, <lb/>in an ounce of
            Honey of Roſes: <lb/>Keep the Sore Place always moiſt with <lb/>this mixture; and 'tis a
            certain Cure. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="191"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A <hi rend="roman">Gargle</hi> in the <hi rend="roman">Palſey</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">P</hi>UT a large ſpoonful of Muſtard- <lb/>ſeed, bruis'd, into a
            pint of White- <lb/>wine; drop in Spirit of Vitriol, to <lb/>make it ſharp; and waſh
            your Mouth <lb/>often in a Day, hold it as long at the <lb/>root of your Tongue, as you
            can endure <lb/>it at a time. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>Another <hi rend="roman">Gargle</hi> in the <hi rend="roman">Palſey</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">P</hi>OUR a quart of boiling Water <lb/>upon a very large handful
            of La- <lb/>vender-flowers; let it Infuſe in the <lb/>Aſhes, 'till 'tis very ſtrong;
            ſtrain it, <lb/>and add a ſpoonful of Vinegar, a ſpoon- <lb/>ful of Hungary-Water, and a
            ſpoonful <lb/>of Honey. Waſh your Mouth often <lb/>with this; it is a very good Gargle.
          </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="192"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) align-center space">
            <lb/>A conſtant <hi rend="roman">Daily Waſh</hi> for your <lb/><hi rend="roman"
              >Teeth</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>O one quart of Claret, put an <lb/>ounce of Bole-armoniac,
            half an <lb/>ounce of Myrrh, one dram of Allum; <lb/>Salt of Vitriol, ten grains; an
            ounce <lb/>of Hungary-Water, and two ounces of <lb/>Honey of Roſes; when theſe have
            ſtood <lb/>in a warm Sun, or near the Fire for <lb/>three Days, ſet it by to ſettle; and
            <lb/>pour a ſpoonful of it into a Tea-cup of <lb/>Water, with which waſh your Teeth:
            <lb/>It preſerves them Sound, and makes <lb/>them White. </p>
        </div>
        <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="26"/>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
