<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Browne: Antidotaria; or, a collection of antidotes against the plague,
          and other malignant diseases</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Joseph Browne</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Antidotaria; or, a Collection of Antidotes against the PLAGUE, and
              other Malignant Diseases. Together, with some Decent and Useful Remarks, on the late
              Pharmacopoeia Londinensis, in a Letter to the President and College of PHYSICIANS;
              shewing the Necessity of a farther Reformation of their new London Dispensatory. </title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T26143</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T26143"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Wilcox, at the Green-Dragon in Little-Britain ; and
                  sold by J. Roberts, in Warwick-Lane, 1721.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1721</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="1"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="39"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3307093723</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K032003.000</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Recipe collections"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="page_2"/>
      <head rend="sc"><lb/>TO <hi rend="indent hanging"><lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">The moſt Eminently
          </hi><lb/>Learned, the <hi rend="italic">Preſident</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
            >Com-<lb/>munity</hi> of the <hi rend="sc">Royal <w part="I">Col-</w><lb/><w part="F"
              >lege</w>
          </hi>of <hi rend="size(1.7)"><hi rend="italic">PHYSICIANS,</hi>
            <lb/>LONDON. </hi></hi>
      </head>
      <lb/>
      <salute>Gentlemen, </salute>
      <p rend="space"><lb/>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>Decorative frame around the letter "T".</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <hi rend="dc(4)">T</hi>HE Intention of the following <lb/>Pages, with Difference to your
        <lb/>illuſtrious Body, is with all <w part="I">ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F">miſſion</w> laid at
        your Feet, <w part="I">carry-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> no other Views along with <lb/>it,
        than to promote, the further <lb/>Knowledge of <hi rend="italic">Medicine,</hi> the exact
        and artful <lb/>Compoſition of which is ſo highly <w part="I">Neceſſa-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ry</w>, and conducive to the Welfare of <w part="I">Man-</w><lb/><w part="F">kind</w>,
        and the Utility of the Publick. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I <hi rend="sc">rest</hi> aſſured of a candid Reception <lb/>from the
        Nature of the Deſign, which I <lb/>have the vanity to think you will favour, <lb/>becauſe it
        is only level'd at a Reformation <pb xml:id="page_3" n="4"/><lb/>ſome of the Errors in
        Compoſition that have <lb/>crept into former, and are ſtill retain'd in <lb/>your laſt
        Edition of the <hi rend="italic">London Diſpenſatory,</hi>
        <lb/>and a further Recommendation of the many <lb/>excellent Preſcriptions, which you have
        with <lb/>Juſtice to the <hi rend="italic">Profeſſion,</hi> continued and <w part="I"
          >pub-</w><lb/><w part="F">liſh'd</w> to the World, all which I ſhall <w part="I"
          >en-</w><lb/><w part="F">deavour</w> to ſupport by Authority, Reaſon <lb/>and Experience;
        hence, I flatter myſelf with <lb/>every thing that can be expected from a <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Society</hi> ſo diſtinguiſh'd for univerſal <w part="I">Lite-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">rature</w>, as well as their particular <w part="I">Know-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ledge</w> in <hi rend="italic">Medicine.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> is a meer Trifle which I offer, only <lb/>as an
        Eſſay to what I have ready for the <lb/>Preſs, and to which I doubt not of your <w part="I"
          >ge-</w><lb/><w part="F">nerous</w> Approbation; for as 'the Study of <lb/>your Lives is
        devoted to do Good, ſo you <lb/>will certainly promote every Thing that <lb/>tends to that
        great End; and what is of more <lb/>Importance than to preſerve Life, and <w part="I"
          >re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtore</w> to Man that valuable Bleſſing of <lb/>Health? </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> Collection of <hi rend="italic">Antidotes,</hi>
        altho', <lb/>no <hi rend="italic">Epidemical Diſeaſe</hi> ſhould happen (which <lb/>God in
        his Mercy avert) is of univerſal <lb/>Tendency, and ſpeaks for itſelf: The <w part="I"
          >Au-</w><lb/><w part="F">thors</w> were all Phyſicians of great <w part="I"
          >Experi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ence</w>, ſome of whom liv'd thro' five or ſix <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Plagues,</hi> in which they had been ſingularly <lb/>ſucceſſful; and after
        that devouring Flame <lb/>was Extinguiſh'd, they had in all their <w part="I"
          >ſuc-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceeding</w> Practice, ſtill a mighty Eſteem for <lb/>ſuch
        Antidotes and Alexipharmicks as had <pb xml:id="page_4" n="5"/><lb/>been Serviceable to
        them, when they ſtood ſo <lb/>much in need of their Aſſiſtance, on which <w part="I"
          >Oc-</w><lb/><w part="F">caſion</w> they invented and introduced a whole <lb/>Set or
        Collection of 'em, into Practice among <lb/>which you have the various Preſcriptions of
        <lb/>Sir <hi rend="italic">Walter Rawleigh's</hi> great Cordial, that of <lb/>Sir <hi
          rend="italic">Kenelm Digby's</hi> Diaphoretick, Gaſcoyne <lb/>Powder, with the Goa-Stone,
        and a great <lb/>Variety of the <hi rend="italic">Lapis Contrayerva,</hi> with <lb/>many
        others; all which are very valuable in <lb/>their Kinds, and conſequently, I doubt not
        <lb/>but the Publication of this will meet with <lb/>a Reception equal to the Merits of
        thoſe <lb/>learned Gentlemen, who were the <w part="I">Compi-</w><lb/><w part="F">lers</w>
        of the ſeveral Recipe's and Preſcriptions <lb/>therein contain'd, which were certainly <w
          part="I">Stu-</w><lb/><w part="F">died</w> and found Uſeful for the publick <w part="I"
          >Ser-</w><lb/><w part="F">vice</w>. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Now</hi>, let, me beg leave of your learned <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Society</hi> to make ſome decent and modeſt <lb/>Remarks upon your laſt
        Edition, of your <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pharmacopeia</hi> that from the Juſtneſs of
        <lb/>thoſe Obſervations, you yourſelves may <lb/>Judge of the Neceſſity there is for a <w
          part="I">Refor-</w><lb/><w part="F">mation</w> of the ſame, and from the <w part="I"
          >Speci-</w><lb/><w part="F">mens</w> I ſhall give, make the World ſenſible <lb/>of the
        Uſefulneſs of ſuch an Undertaking, <lb/>which, with the laſt Regards due to your
        <lb/>venerable Body, I ſubmit to impartial <lb/>Judgment. And in the firſt Place, I ſhall
        <lb/>not waſt Time, either upon the Method, or <lb/>Materials you have made Choice of in the
        <lb/>Simples conducive to your <hi rend="italic">Diſpenſatory,</hi>
        <lb/>whether Roots, Barks, Woods, Herbs, <w part="I">Flow-</w><pb xml:id="page_5" n="6"
          /><lb/><w part="F">ers</w>, Fruits, Seeds or the like, but do think <lb/>it wou'd have
        been a Juſtice due to the <lb/>Publick, as well as an Advantage to the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Profeſſion</hi> to have inform'd them, which of <lb/>thoſe Simples moſt
        conſtantly are in Uſe, <lb/>which are ſeldom uſed, and which are <w part="I">ne-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ver</w> uſed at all; which Things are very <w part="I">Ma-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >terial</w>, that Time and Money may not be <lb/>thrown away upon what is perfectly
        Uſeleſs; <lb/>as the Roots of Anthorae an Exotick, <w part="I">cal-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >led</w> the Counter-poiſon to Monkſhood, <lb/>not Traffick'd in, and of no Virtues that
        <lb/>are recommended by the Experience of the <lb/>Faculty. 2dly. Arundinis Saccharina; the
        <lb/>common Reed and Sugar-Cane Roots of no <lb/>Medicinal uſe. The Roots of Kings Spear
        <lb/>or Aſphodel, Male and Female, not Us'd or <lb/>even Sold in the Druggiſt, or
        Apothecaries <lb/>Shops, and many more. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>THE next are thoſe which, are ſeldom, <lb/>or very rarely uſed, ſuch as
        the <hi rend="italic">Hermodactyls,</hi>
        <lb/>Woad, Fullers Thiſtle, Hog-Fennel, Stinking <lb/>Gladon, and an hundred others
        mention'd to <lb/>little or no Purpoſe, which had been better <lb/>left out, both for the
        eaſe of the <w part="I">Apothe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cary</w>, and the Preſcriber, who is at
        firſt <w part="I">em-</w><lb/><w part="F">barraſs'd</w> in ſo large a Field of Materials,
        <lb/>loaded by ſome Authors with great <w part="I">Enco-</w><lb/><w part="F">comiums</w> of
        the Feats they have done in <lb/>Phyſick, which are too apt to flatter and <w part="I"
          >di-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſappoint</w> the Preſumptions of a young <w part="I"
          >Pra-</w><lb/><w part="F">ctitioner</w>. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I <hi rend="sc">shall</hi> paſs by the reſt of the Simples <lb/>in this
        ſhort Account, and leave 'em to a <pb xml:id="page_6" n="7"/><lb/>ſtricter Enquiry, when I
        come to publiſh the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pharmacopeia Reformata,</hi> and ſo proceed to
        <lb/>ſome more material Obſervations, among <lb/>which, I ſhall firſt take Notice of, the <w
          part="I">Oxy-</w><lb/><w part="F">mel</w> ſcilliticum, which you have Preſcrib'd <lb/>juſt
        in the ſame manner as formerly, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
        <lb/>Three <hi rend="italic">Pounds of Clarified Honey, to two Pounds <lb/>of Vinegar of
          Squills;</hi> whereas in Juſtneſs to the <lb/>Operation, and Effects of this <hi
          rend="italic">Medicine,</hi> here <lb/>ſhould be three Pounds of Vinegar of <hi
          rend="italic">Squills,</hi>
        <lb/>to two Pounds of Honey, otherwiſe the <hi rend="italic">Me-<lb/>decine</hi> is ſo
        clogg'd with the Honey, that the <lb/>Efficacy thereof is loſt, and the <hi rend="italic"
          >Acetum</hi>
        <lb/>hath not power to aſſiſt the Digeſtion, cut <lb/>the viſcous Flegm, diſcharge Wind and
        ſour <lb/>Belchings from the Stomach, and ſtrengthen <lb/>the Appetite; for which it is a
        noble <w part="I">Re-</w><lb/><w part="F">medy</w>, was it not ſo very Nauſeous; but it
        <lb/>may be excellently adapted by a skillful and <lb/>judicious Phyſician, who by mixing
        equal <lb/>parts of the <hi rend="italic">Acetum ſcilliticum</hi> and Oxymel w<lb/>ill gain
        his Intentions. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I <hi rend="sc">cannot</hi> be ſurpriz'd that you have <lb/>overlook'd
        this among ſo many other <w part="I">Com-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſitions</w>, which are ſo
        Faulty, that they <lb/>are not capable of being made up or <lb/>if they could, wou'd be of
        no Uſe, ſince <lb/>you are pleas'd to perſiſt in your daily <w part="I">Pra-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ctice</w> to preſcribe Galbanum along with <w part="I">Am-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >moniacum</w>, in order to be diſſolv'd, in black <lb/>Cherry-water, or other the like
        Vehicle, <lb/>and are angry with the Apothecary, when <lb/>he tells you plain, that he knows
        not how <lb/>to diſſolve <hi rend="italic">Galbanum</hi> in an aqueous Body, <pb
          xml:id="page_7" n="8"/><lb/>tho' <hi rend="italic">Ammoniacum</hi> will familiarly do it;
        if <lb/>this Point had been clear'd up in your laſt <lb/>Edition, of the <hi rend="italic"
          >London Diſpenſatory,</hi> and <lb/>new Rules given to the Apothecary, how to <lb/>make
        his Diſſolution of <hi rend="italic">Galbanum,</hi> this <lb/>wou'd have been a great
        Improvement, and <lb/>given a New turn to the Diſpenſations of <lb/>Medicines, but till
        then, we ſhall believe it <lb/>was not ſo artfully Corrected, as we had <lb/>Reaſon to
        expect from Perſons ſo well <w part="I">quali-</w><lb/><w part="F">fy'd</w>; otherwiſe the
          <hi rend="italic">Spiritus Lavendulæ com-<lb/>poſitus</hi> would hardly have remain'd in
        the <lb/>Condition it ſtands, conſidering it is ſuch a <lb/><hi rend="italic">Farrago</hi>
        of inconſiſtences unskilfully <w part="I">blend-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>, the Produce of
        which, is nothing at all; <lb/>when at the ſame time the ſimple Spirit of <lb/>Lavender, is
        ſo excellently uſeful, and may <lb/>be enrich'd at the Phyſician's pleaſure, with <lb/>all
        the Volatile Aromaticks, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> according <lb/>to the Nature of the
        Caſe, becoming by this <lb/>Means a <hi rend="italic">Spiritus Lavendulæ Extemporaneo
          <lb/>Compoſitus.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Your</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">Aqua Pæoniae Compoſita,</hi> or <w part="I">Peony-wa-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ter</w> Compound, is an excellent Preſcription, <lb/>but wants much of what it was from
          <hi rend="italic">Langius,</hi>
        <lb/>who calls it his <hi rend="italic">Epileptick Water,</hi> which <w part="I"
          >Re-</w><lb/><w part="F">ceipt</w> I ſhall give you (as it was Originally) <lb/>in the <hi
          rend="italic">Pharmacopeia Reformata;</hi> in the <w part="I">inte-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >rim</w> it is high time to expunge <hi rend="italic">Gilbert's <lb/>Water,</hi> leaſt
        ſome evil minded People ſhou'd <lb/>deceive themſelves, and others, in putting <lb/>their
        Truſt therein. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">As</hi> to the Treacle of <hi rend="italic"
          >Audromachus,</hi> and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Mithridate,</hi> of which I can find no <w
          part="I">Reforma-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> made in your laſt Edition; it is one <pb
          xml:id="page_8" n="9"/><lb/>grand Medley of a multitude of Simples <lb/>jumbl'd together
        without Order or Deſign; <lb/>the greateſt Part of which are either uſeleſs, <lb/>or
        ineffectual. I ſhall ſatisfie my own <w part="I">Opi-</w><lb/><w part="F">nion</w> only to
        declare that as generally us'd, <lb/>and apply'd, they are both dangerous <w part="I"
          >Me-</w><lb/><w part="F">dicines</w> ill prepar'd, very Hot and of <w part="I"
          >diſagree-</w><lb/><w part="F">able</w> Qualities to the Intentions they are
        <lb/>adminiſtred. The grand Reaſon that has <lb/>induc'd all Sorts of People to the Uſe of
        <lb/>them, have been drawn from the Authority <lb/>and Experience of the Antients; <hi
          rend="italic">Galen</hi> ſays <lb/>they, hath ſpoken in Praiſe of <hi rend="italic"
          >Treacle</hi> in two <lb/>Pieces of his, directed to <hi rend="italic">Piſo,</hi> and <hi
          rend="italic">Pamphi-<lb/>lianus.</hi> To which I anſwer, that the <w part="I"
          >Autho-</w><lb/><w part="F">rity</w> cited, is of no force, becauſe they do <lb/>not
        appear to be <hi rend="italic">Galen's</hi> Writings, but falſly <lb/>attributed to him,
        which is the more <w part="I">Evi-</w><lb/><w part="F">dent</w> from the Stile and Manner of
        Writing, <lb/>which is foreign from that of <hi rend="italic">Galen's,</hi> beſides
        <lb/>there are ſeveral Terms, and Words made <lb/>Uſe of not elſewhere to be found in the
        ſaid <lb/>Author's Works, according to the learn'd <lb/><hi rend="italic">Mercurialis,</hi>
        who ſays, <hi rend="italic">in eo plurima verba a <lb/>Galeno nuſquam uſurpata, fabuloſæ
          aliqua <lb/>&amp; ſtylus totus pene diverſus reperiuntur.</hi> The <lb/>ſame Author ſays,
        there ought not to be the <lb/>leaſt Fault in any of the Simples, that <w part="I"
          >en-</w><lb/><w part="F">ter</w> that Compoſition, ſpeaking of <hi rend="italic">Treacle
          <lb/>Vitium enim unius Medicamenti totum <w part="I">Compoſi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tionem</w> evertit.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Every</hi> Body knows the great Abuſe in <lb/>the Choice
        of Vipers, and that of the <hi rend="italic">Mala-<lb/>bathrum,</hi> which not one in an
        hundred makes <pb xml:id="page_9" n="10"/><lb/>a right Uſe of; beſides this, the <hi
          rend="italic">Myrrh</hi> we uſe, <lb/>ſetting aſide the ſmell, is nothing like that
        <lb/>deſcrib'd by <hi rend="italic">Dioſcorides,</hi> but rather <hi rend="italic"
          >Bdelliams,</hi>
        <lb/>whereas the Troglotick is the fame, and we <lb/>have no <hi rend="italic"
          >Opo-Balſamum,</hi> true <hi rend="italic">Coſtus, Schænanth, <lb/>Dictamny</hi> of <hi
          rend="italic">Crete,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Falernian Wine.</hi> The <w part="I"
          >ge-</w><lb/><w part="F">nerality</w> of the <hi rend="italic">Opium</hi> us'd at this
        Day, is <w part="I">no-</w><lb/><w part="F">thing</w> near ſo fine, or good as <hi
          rend="italic">Mathiolus</hi>
        <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">lates</w>, and ſcarce ſeems to be like what <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Dioſcorides</hi> deſcribes: For it is a perfect <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Meconium</hi> at this Day, as may be evidently <lb/>Proved, </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">Mithridate</hi> commonly met with in <lb/>the Shops, is in the ſame
        Condition, having <lb/>the ſame Faults and Imperfections, and <lb/>therefore ought to be
        rejected, being too hot <lb/>and acrid for the Intentions it is generally <lb/>Preſcrib'd,
        conſequently it wants a <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſiderable</w> Reformation, or
        elſe ought to be <lb/>expung'd the <hi rend="italic">Diſpenſatory.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> Confection of <hi rend="italic">Alkermes,</hi>
        altho' <w part="I">ve-</w><lb/><w part="F">ry</w> prudently diveſted of its Perfumes now
        <lb/>a-days, is a Compoſition very unartfully <lb/>Invented and Deſcrib'd by the <hi
          rend="italic">Arabians,</hi> and <lb/>very little Reform'd and Amended by the
        <lb/>Moderns, who ſtill cloſely purſue the <w part="I">Er-</w><lb/><w part="F">rors</w> of
        the <hi rend="italic">Arabian Phyſicians:</hi> Indeed the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Lapis
          Laruli</hi> has been long ſince thrown out, <lb/>and there remains little behind in this
          <w part="I">Me-</w><lb/><w part="F">dicine</w>, which bears a high Name, but <lb/>what we
        may expect from the Juice or <w part="I">Sy-</w><lb/><w part="F">rup</w> of the <hi
          rend="italic">Chermes-Berry</hi> with better <w part="I">Suc-</w><lb/><w part="F"
        >cess</w>; for as to the <hi rend="italic">Aloes Wood,</hi> we know little <lb/>or nothing
        of it, and the Leaf-Gold <w part="I">there-</w><pb xml:id="page_10" n="11"/><lb/><w part="F"
          >in</w>, is a meer Amuſement to Deceive <lb/>the Credulous. <hi rend="italic"
          >Rondeletius</hi> inſtead of ſpeaking <lb/>in its Praiſe gives a ſevere Caution againſt
        <lb/>the Uſe of it, which is Back'd by Mr. <hi rend="italic">Fer-<lb/>rier,</hi> a Phyſician
        of <hi rend="italic">Tholouſe,</hi> who blames <w part="I">Phy-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſicians</w> for the too plentiful Preſcribing <w part="I">there-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >of</w>: See the <hi rend="italic">Annotations</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
          >Obſervations</hi> of <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Guillemeau.</hi> The Confect of <hi
          rend="italic">Hyacinth</hi>
        <lb/>bears a great Reſemblance to this, only that <lb/>the laſt ſeems to be endowed with no
          <w part="I">Cor-</w><lb/><w part="F">dial</w> Virtue at all: Notwithanding the great
        <lb/>Boaſts made of it, from the Fragments of <lb/>Precious-Stones, that enter the <w
          part="I">Compoſiti-</w><lb/><w part="F">on</w>, by the ſplendid ſhew of which, together,
        <lb/>with the Leaf-Gold, many are induced to <lb/>believe it is capable of performing
        Wonders. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">As</hi> I was treating of <hi rend="italic"
          >Mithridate,</hi> I muſt <lb/>take the Liberty to return to the Subject, to <lb/>ſhew that
        when <hi rend="italic">Pompey</hi> found the Receipt <lb/>thereof written in <hi
          rend="italic">Mithridates</hi> own Hand, <lb/>after the Defeat of that Prince, which he <w
          part="I">e-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſteem'd</w> as a vaulable Secret; it was <w part="I"
          >Com-</w><lb/><w part="F">pounded</w> but of very few Simples, and thoſe <lb/>very common
        ones according to the <w part="I">follow-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>
        <hi rend="italic">Diſtick.</hi>
      </p>
      <lb/>
      <lg>
        <l rend="italic">Antidotus vero multis Mithridatica fertur </l>
        <lb/>
        <l rend="italic">Conſociata Modis, ſed magnus ſcrinia Regis </l>
        <lb/>
        <l rend="italic">Cum rapperet Victor, vilem deprendit in illis </l>
        <lb/>
        <l rend="italic">Syntheſim, &amp; vulgatâ ſatis Medicamina riſit: </l>
        <lb/>
        <l rend="italic">Bis denum rutae folium, ſalis &amp; brevegranum </l>
        <lb/>
        <l rend="italic">Juglandás{que} duas, totidem cum corpore ficus: </l>
        <lb/>
        <l rend="italic">Næcortente die pauco conſperſa Lyaeo </l>
        <lb/>
        <l rend="italic">Sumebat metuens, dederatq; pocula tutor. </l>
      </lg>
      <pb xml:id="page_11" n="12"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> Compoſition then conſiſted, only <lb/>of two
        Walnuts, two Figs, Twenty leaves <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Rue</hi> ſtamp'd together, with a
        little Salt; <lb/>and this was reckon'd a ſovereign Antidote <lb/>againſt any maglignant Air
        for 24 Hours <lb/>together, it being ſufficient for three or four <lb/>Morning Doſes,
        drinking after it a Glaſs of <lb/>white Wine </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> next thing to be enquir'd into, is to <lb/>know
        the Reaſon, why you ſtill admit Leaf-<lb/>Gold into ſeveral Preparations, ſince you
        <lb/>very well know it is neither Cordial, <w part="I">Corro-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >borative</w>, Alterative, or does it any wiſe <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tribute</w> to the Nutrition of the Parts <w part="I">accord-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w>
        to <hi rend="italic">Galen,</hi> in his Commentary on the <lb/>firſt Book of <hi
          rend="italic">Hippocrates, de ratione Victus in <lb/>Acutis.</hi> It can by no Means be
        call'd an <lb/>Alterative, in that the natural Diſpoſition <lb/>of the Body cannot be
        affected by Reaſon of <lb/>the Solidity of its Parts, ſo that it can <w part="I"
          >nei-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> heat or cool, dry or moiſten the ſolid, <lb/>or fluid
        Parts, and how it becomes <w part="I">Purga-</w><lb/><w part="F">tive</w> I cannot imagine;
        all which makes good <lb/>what <hi rend="italic">Julius Caeſar Scaliger,</hi> ſays in his <w
          part="I">Exer-</w><lb/><w part="F">citations</w> againſt <hi rend="italic">Cardan</hi>
        Exerc. 272. There <lb/>ought to be ſome Reſemblance, ſome <w part="I">like-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ness</w> in Configuration of Parts; between <lb/>what gives the Nutriment, and
        the Body <lb/>that receives it. Metals are proper to unite <lb/>with, and feed Metals, but
        are <w part="I">imcompati-</w><lb/><w part="F">ble</w>, and foreign to the ſubſiſtence and
          <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">creaſe</w> of Animals. If Gold is good in any
        <lb/>Diſeaſe, it muſt certainly be ſo in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Hypochondriack,
          Melancholy,</hi> eſpecially when <pb xml:id="page_12" n="13"/><lb/>it is adminiſtred, not
        as the <hi rend="italic">Arabians,</hi><lb/> in Pills or Powders, or as the Chymiſts in
        <lb/>Potions like their <hi rend="italic">Aurum Potabile,</hi> but <w part="I"
          >plen-</w><lb/><w part="F">tifully</w> in Specie, or Golden Showers; nay, <lb/>if the
        Phyſician cou'd but preſcribe <hi rend="italic">Bank</hi>
        <lb/>Bills, his preſcriptions would infallibly Cure <lb/>all the Vapours in Town. This is a
        Specifick, <lb/>even againſt <hi rend="italic">South-Sea</hi> Head-Ach, which, is
        <lb/>otherwiſe an incurable Diſeaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">And</hi> here I cannot forbear to hint at <lb/>the preſent
        uſe of <hi rend="italic">Ivory,</hi> that is ſtill <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >tinued</w>, and recommended in many good <lb/>Medicines, when every Body knows, and is
        <lb/>thoroughly perſwaded that <hi rend="italic">Harts-Horn,</hi> has <lb/>an hundred times
        the Virtue, ſince the <w part="I">o-</w><lb/><w part="F">ther</w> neither diſcovers Smell or
        Taſte, or <lb/>any Quality to recommend it for an <w part="I">ef-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ficacious</w> Medicine; ſeveral Phyſicians have <lb/>long ſince exploded it, as <hi
          rend="italic">Durel Hantin, <lb/>Mercurialis, Baccius, Sylvaticus Eraſtus, <w part="I"
            >Al-</w><lb/><w part="F">bertus</w>, Sebizius,</hi> and others; but <hi rend="italic"
          >Ambroſe <w part="I">Pa-</w><lb/><w part="F">rey</w>,</hi> by dint of Reaſon and
        Experience <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">futes</w>, all the pretended and imaginary <w
          part="I">Qua-</w><lb/><w part="F">lities</w> aſſign'd to this uſeleſs and inſignificant
        <lb/>Drug. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Therefore</hi> it becomes more my <w part="I"
          >Admi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ration</w>, that Gentlemen who have <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ſulted</w>, and weigh'd all theſe things <w part="I">toge-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ther</w> in the Balance of Reaſon, ſhould ſtill <lb/>continue the Uſe of many uſeleſs,
        and <w part="I">ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">travagant</w> Drugs, which are now directed in
        <lb/>the ſeveral Compoſitions of your <hi rend="italic">Diſpenſa-<lb/>tory,</hi> many of
        which are rarely, or not to <lb/>be got at all, and others at a very dear Rate, <pb
          xml:id="page_13" n="14"/><lb/>and good for little or nothing; the firſt of <lb/>which I
        mean is, the Bone of a Stags Heart, <lb/>the others are Ambergreeſe, Musk, and <w part="I"
          >Be-</w><lb/><w part="F">zoar</w> ſo frequently preſcribed on all <w part="I"
          >Occaſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ons</w>, in the laſt of which there are ſo many <lb/>vile
        Cheats practic'd, that it is a pity it <lb/>ſhould lye in the power of avaritious, and
        <lb/>deſigning Men to Cozen and Deceive the <lb/>World, with ſuch vile Frauds. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Two</hi> Parts in three of the Bezoar, of which <lb/>is
        ſold and made Uſe of in the Shops is, <w part="I">Fa-</w><lb/><w part="F">ctitious</w>, and
        the other that is Natural, is <lb/>only fit to Deceive ſuch as are willing to be
        <lb/>Deceiv'd, and take a Pleaſure to be carry'd <lb/>down with the Stream of popular
        Errors. As <lb/>to the Factitious, it is generally made up of <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Gall-Stones,</hi> found in the Gall-Bladders of <lb/>Oxen, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        and <hi rend="italic">Lemnian Earth</hi> findly ground <lb/>with a little <hi rend="italic"
          >Ambergreeſe,</hi> and ſo form'd <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">to</w> Stones of
        various Sizes and Figures; and <lb/>thus the ſubtle Artiſt cheats the Apothecary <lb/>with
        his Counterfeit Stone, and the <w part="I">Phyſici-</w><lb/><w part="F">an</w> comes into
        the Confederacy, by <w part="I">preſcrib-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> his Bezoartick Bolus,
        or Powder to <lb/>pick the Patient's Pocket: This fallacy <w part="I">up-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">on</w> the credulous Sick, will in a little time <lb/>become as deſpicable, as
        the vain <w part="I">Pretenti-</w><lb/><w part="F">ons</w> of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Alchymiſts,</hi> with their <hi rend="italic">Aurum <w part="I">Pota-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tabile</w>,</hi> their <hi rend="italic">Sulphur</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Metals,</hi>
        and <hi rend="italic">Powder</hi> of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Projection,</hi> with which they
        Bubble the <w part="I">Ig-</w><lb/><w part="F">norant</w>, and blind the Eyes of the more
        <lb/>diſcerning part of Mankind. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>I <hi rend="sc">Hope</hi> to God, that you Gentlemen, <lb/>who have both
        Honour, Juſtice and <w part="I">Judg-</w>
        <pb xml:id="page_14" n="15"/><lb/><w part="F">ment</w>, will put a ſtop to theſe Deceits <w
          part="I">where-</w><lb/><w part="F">by</w> the People are Cheated with falſe <w part="I"
          >Medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cines</w>, which under the pompous <w part="I"
          >Pretenſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ons</w> of curing more Effectually, are made <lb/>a Handle
        of, to extract Gold and Silver from <lb/>the Patients Purſe: A Reformation of theſe
        <lb/>things would be a great Advantage to all <lb/>Parties, and who can we expect it from,
        but <lb/>your learned Body, who by your Example, <lb/>and Authority have Power to Reform,
        and <lb/>at the ſame time inform the World what <lb/>your Opinions are in relation to ſuch
          <w part="I">coſt-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> Drugs, as <hi rend="italic">Bezoar,</hi> and
        whether the good <lb/>Effects and Virtues thereof are anſwerable <lb/>to the Phyſicians
        Expectation, and that of the <lb/>Patient; if not, that you wou'd ingeniouſly<lb/> declare
        this Stone naturally, as brought <lb/>from <hi rend="italic">India,</hi> and unſophiſtieated
        hath no <lb/>more Virtue than ſome of our Foreign Earths, <lb/>or Domeſtick Chalks. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> is pretended by the Advocates for this <lb/>Stone,
        that it is a moſt noble <hi rend="italic">Alexipharmick,</hi>
        <lb/>and is both <hi rend="italic">Cordial</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sudorifick,</hi> tho'
        it <lb/>does not appear from the Compoſition of <lb/>its Parts, being Groſs and Earthy, how
        it <lb/>can encreaſe or otherwiſe alter the Motion <lb/>of the Blood, or exhilerate the
        Spirits, <lb/>which it ſeems not to have power to fortifie, <lb/>and ſupport. If this be ſo
        then, let us <w part="I">ſub-</w><lb/><w part="F">mit</w> to the force of Truth, which we
        find <lb/>publiſh'd in the Writings of ſome of the <lb/>beſt Phyſicians of <hi rend="italic"
          >Europe,</hi> which Mr. <hi rend="italic">Guy-<lb/>bert</hi> hath accurately quoted; let
        us ſubmit <lb/>Opinion, I ſay to Truth, which is one and <pb xml:id="page_15" n="16"
        /><lb/>the ſame throughout the World. <hi rend="italic">Nic Boc-<lb/>cangelinus</hi>
        Phyſician to the Empreſs, and <lb/>a very knowing <hi rend="italic">Spaniard,</hi> in a
        Treatiſe of <hi rend="italic">Ma-<lb/>lignant</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Peſtilential
          Fevers.</hi> Chap. 17. <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">demn's</w> the Uſe of <hi
          rend="italic">Bezoar,</hi> thus; ſome make <lb/>up Cordial Powders with <hi rend="italic"
          >Bezoar, Pearl, Coral,</hi>
        <lb/>&amp;c. which ſtrangely Deceive them, for, all <lb/>theſe things encreaſe the
        Obſtructions, which <lb/>encourage the Fever, the Materials being <lb/>groſs, earthy, and
        Unactive, foul the Stomach, <lb/>clog the <hi rend="italic">Lacterals,</hi> and ſtop the <hi
          rend="italic">Meſaraick</hi>
        <w part="I">Veſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſels</w>, ſo that the Blood which is Contaminated
        <lb/>with the malignant Vapours, hath not power <lb/>hereby to refine itſelf. <hi
          rend="italic">Hieron: Ruleus,</hi> a <w part="I">learn-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w>
        Phyſician of <hi rend="italic">Ravenna,</hi> in his <w part="I">Commenta-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ries</w> on the 7th Chap. of the 3d Book of <hi rend="italic">Celſus</hi>
        <lb/>expoſes the Cheat after this manner; I own, <lb/>ſays he, having often preſcrib'd the
          <hi rend="italic">Bezoar <lb/>Stone,</hi> in Malignant, and other Fevers to <w part="I"
          >ſeve-</w><lb/><w part="F">ral</w> Perſons of Quality, from 8 to 16 Grains, I <lb/>never
        could obſerve any good Effect from it, <lb/>by any ſenſible Operation, or Amendment <lb/>in
        the Patient; but this we commonly <w part="I">Pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſcribe</w> to the
        Rich and Great, by way of <w part="I">Com-</w><lb/><w part="F">plement</w>, it being very
        dear: Beſides let <lb/>me Caution you, ſays he, for there are a <lb/>great many Counterfeit,
        or falſe Stones, <lb/>which I found by Experience in the laſt <w part="I">Sick-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">ness</w> of Pope <hi rend="italic">Clement</hi> the 8th, ſo that out of
        <lb/>forty, which were brought me, I cou'd ſcarce <lb/>meet with one good one. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">MARTIANUS</hi> a <hi rend="italic">Roman</hi>
        Phyſician in <lb/>his Commentaries upon <hi rend="italic">Hippocrates,</hi> ſays, <lb/>that
        the <hi rend="italic">Bezoar Stone</hi> is nothing elſe, but a <pb xml:id="page_16" n="17"
        /><lb/>meer Name and Opinion without any <w part="I">Vir-</w><lb/><w part="F">tue</w>, which
        he knows to be true upon <w part="I">re-</w><lb/><w part="F">peated</w> Tryals; <hi
          rend="italic">Rodericus a Fonſeca,</hi> a <w part="I">cele-</w><lb/><w part="F">brated</w>
        Profeſſor at <hi rend="italic">Padua,</hi> in a Tract of his <lb/>on <hi rend="italic"
          >Malignant Fevers,</hi> ingenuouſly owns, that <lb/>he never ſaw any laudable Effect from
        it, <lb/>tho' he had frequently us'd it: <hi rend="italic">Johannes Colle</hi>
        <lb/>a learned <hi rend="italic">Italian,</hi> and Phyſician to the D. of <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Urbino,</hi> in a Book of his call'd <hi rend="italic">Coſmitor <w part="I"
            >Medi-</w><lb/><w part="F">cans</w>,</hi> or a large Treatiſe of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Bezoar Stone,</hi>
        <lb/>makes ſevere Remarks on thoſe, who boaſt of <lb/>the Virtues of <hi rend="italic"
          >Bezoar,</hi> without any Reaſon, <lb/>and on thoſe who uſe it in all Diſeaſes, like
        <lb/>a Stall for all Horſes. <hi rend="italic">Theodorus Angelutius</hi>
        <lb/>ſpeaking of the Cure of <hi rend="italic">Malignant Fevers,</hi>
        <lb/>condemns it in theſe Words; I adviſe all <w part="I">Phy-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ſicians</w>, ſays he, againſt the uſe of this Stone, <lb/>ſince it is a Drug that is good
        for nothing <lb/>at the beſt; and all Men of ſincerity, who <lb/>are moſt worthy of Credit
        confeſs it, and I <lb/>myſelf ſolemnly proteſt, that I never cou'd <lb/>find the Sick
        relieved thereby, how eaſie it <lb/>is, then for every one to Judge of the <w part="I"
          >Dan-</w><lb/><w part="F">ger</w> there is in Confiding in ſo uncertain and <lb/>frivolous
        a Medicine, when the Patient <w part="I">la-</w><lb/><w part="F">bours</w> under a <hi
          rend="italic">Malignant Fever,</hi> inſtead of <lb/>a better approved, and more ſucceſſful
          <w part="I">Re-</w><lb/><w part="F">medy</w>. <hi rend="italic">Thomas Minadous,</hi> in
        his Book of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fevers,</hi> ſays thus; I cannot ſo much, as <w part="I"
          >ad-</w><lb/><w part="F">mit</w>, or have ever met with any occult <w part="I"
          >Qua-</w><lb/><w part="F">lity</w> in this <hi rend="italic">Bezoar Stone,</hi> by which
        means <lb/>it could prove ſerviceable in any Kind of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fevers;</hi> and
        therefore believe they are all <lb/>fabulous Accounts, and old Womens Tales, <pb
          xml:id="page_17" n="18"/><lb/>that have been told either by the <hi rend="italic"
          >Arabians,</hi>
        <lb/>or the Moderns; for I have try'd it ſeveral <lb/>Times in ſeveral Diſeaſes, without
        finding <lb/>any Relief or Advantage from it. <hi rend="italic">Aloiſius <lb/>Mundella,</hi>
        in his Experiments on <hi rend="italic">ſimple <w part="I">Me-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >dicines</w>,</hi> confirms what all the reſt have ſaid, <lb/>whom I have quoted before. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Permit</hi> me, moſt excellent and learned <lb/>Collegues,
        to ſay a Word or two about the <lb/>Drug <hi rend="italic">Sena,</hi> which enters ſo many
        of your <lb/>well choſen Compoſitions, and which I have <lb/>the Vanity to think you have
        not all met <lb/>with in the common Treatiſes of <hi rend="italic">ſimple <w part="I"
            >Me-</w><lb/><w part="F">dicines</w>,</hi> tho' the Subject fell in my way, when <lb/>I
        conſulted all the Authors I could then come <lb/>at in compiling my <hi rend="italic"
          >Hiſtory</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Drugs,</hi> from <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pomet, Lemery
          Tournefort,</hi> &amp;c. The <hi rend="italic">Sena,</hi>
        <lb/>which <hi rend="italic">Meſue</hi> from the <hi rend="italic">Perſians,</hi> calls <hi
          rend="italic">Abal-<lb/>zemer,</hi> is a Plant or Shrub, the Leaves <lb/>whereof Reſemble
        thoſe of Liquorice, it ſhoots <lb/>up and ſpreads with many ſmall Branches, <lb/>which are
        very pliant, the Flowers are <w part="I">yel-</w><lb/><w part="F">low</w>, with certain
        Threads or red Streaks <lb/>underneath, after which ſhoot forth certain <lb/>Follicula or
        Buds cloſely folded, which <lb/>hang upon the Plant, by a ſlender Tail, <lb/>which is very
        fine, and naturally flat; theſe <lb/>Buds when Ripe eaſily fall by the force of <lb/>the
        Wind, and contain in them a Seed which <lb/>is of a greeniſh black Colour, and ſo like
        <lb/>the Stone of a Raiſin, that it is hard to know <lb/>the difference; <hi rend="italic"
          >Serapion</hi> in his Book of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Simples</hi> ſays, theſe Buds are
        longiſh, and in <lb/>form of a Croſs, in which the Seed is lodg'd. <pb xml:id="page_18"
          n="19"/><lb/>They are much Deceived, who think that the <lb/>Tree which <hi rend="italic"
          >Theophraſtus</hi> calls <hi rend="italic">Colutea</hi> to be <lb/>our <hi rend="italic"
          >Sena;</hi> becauſe the <hi rend="italic">Colutea</hi> which the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >French</hi> call <hi rend="italic">Baguenaudier</hi> bears large <hi rend="italic"
          >Follicu-<lb/>les</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Buds,</hi> which the Shepherds and <w part="I"
          >Pe-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſants</w> gather to feed their Cattle with, <w part="I"
          >be-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſides</w>, there is a vaſt difference, in that the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Sena</hi> is an Herb or Plant that laſts but a <lb/>few Months, and the <hi
          rend="italic">Bagnenaudier</hi> is a Tree <lb/>that continues many Years; <w part="I"
          >notwithſtand-</w><lb/><w part="F">ing</w> which the ſame Virtues have been <w part="I"
          >aſcrib-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> to the laſt, as to that of <hi rend="italic"
          >Sena,</hi> and the <lb/>Merchant impos'd upon as well as the <w part="I">Drug-</w><lb/><w
          part="F">giſt</w> in buying the one for the other. <hi rend="italic">Meſue</hi>
        <lb/>ſays, that the <hi rend="italic">Sena</hi> hath much more Virtue <lb/>and Efficacy in
        the Bud than the Leaf, <w part="I">eſpe-</w><lb/><w part="F">cially</w> if of the Dark green
        Colour a little <lb/>bitteriſh, ſtiptick and aſtringent in Taſt, <lb/>and gather'd when
        freſh, for otherwiſe the <lb/>Virtue is loſt. The white Buds are good for <lb/>nothing, the
        green Leaves, better than the <lb/>white, and the thick ones than the thin, but <lb/>the
        Stalks of no Uſe at all; and this agrees <lb/>very well with what <hi rend="italic"
          >Matthiolus</hi> writes in <lb/>his learned Commentaries on <hi rend="italic"
          >Dioſcorides,</hi> he <lb/>ſays indeed, there are two Sorts of theſe <lb/>Buds, the one of
        which is gather'd when dry <lb/>and fallen from the Plant, which have no <lb/>Virtue in
        them, and the other is gathered <lb/>upon the Plant before it is dry and wither'd, <lb/>and
        theſe are thick Leaves, and full of Sap, <lb/>being afterwards skillfully dry'd in the
        <lb/>Shade. </p>
      <pb xml:id="page_19" n="20"/>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Manardus,</hi> a Phyſician of <hi rend="italic"
          >Ferrara</hi>
        <w part="I">main-</w><lb/><w part="F">tains</w>, that the Leaves of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Sena</hi> have a <lb/>greater Purgative Quality than the Buds, <lb/>but then he takes 'em
        for ſuch as dropt from <lb/>the Tree ready dry'd; but <hi rend="italic">Fernelius</hi> who
        <lb/>was undoubtedly a more knowing Judge of <lb/>Medicine, follows <hi rend="italic"
          >Meſue</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Matthiolus</hi> in <lb/>preferring the <hi rend="italic"
          >Buds</hi> to the <hi rend="italic">Leaves,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Syl-<lb/>vius</hi>
        ſubſcribes to the ſame Opinion, in his <lb/>Commentaries upon <hi rend="italic">Meſue,</hi>
        Whoever hath <lb/>a Mind to Uſe the Buds, muſt obſerve this <lb/>Deſcription, but ſuch as
        like the Leaves <lb/>better, muſt chuſe thoſe of the brighteſt <lb/>Colour, large and freſh,
        and free from all <lb/>Smell, rejecting the pale and dead Colour'd <lb/>as uſeleſs. Our
        Druggiſts are often very <lb/>negligent in mixing all together, without <lb/>Choice or
        Diſtinction. With ſubmiſſion to <lb/>the more learned, I think we generally <w part="I"
          >un-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w> Doſe this Medicine in our Compoſitions, <lb/>and
        Preſeriptions. <hi rend="italic">Serapion</hi> orders from a <lb/>Dram, to two Drams in
        Powder, and half <lb/>an Ounce to five Drams in Decoction, <hi rend="italic"
          >Actu-<lb/>arius</hi> only one Dram, and in Decoction half <lb/>an Ounce; <hi
          rend="italic">Fernelius</hi> directs two Drams in <lb/>Powder, and ſix in Decoction, but
        half an <lb/>Ounce in the Infuſion. Your <hi rend="italic">London Di-<lb/>ſpenſatory</hi>
        preſcribes only a Scruple of <hi rend="italic">Sena</hi>
        <lb/>in Powder, and half a Scruple of <hi rend="italic">Rhubarb</hi>
        <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">Polypody</hi> in ſeven Drams of <hi rend="italic">Electuarium
          <lb/>Catholicum,</hi> and two Drams only in the <w part="I">De-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >coction</w> of <hi rend="italic">Gereon,</hi> and in the <hi rend="italic">Lenitive <w
            part="I">E-</w><lb/><w part="F">lectuary</w>,</hi> to one Ounce a Dram of <hi
          rend="italic">Sena,</hi> with a <lb/>Scruple of that and <hi rend="italic">Polypody</hi>
        in Decoction, in <pb xml:id="page_20" n="21"/><lb/>the larger compound Powder of <hi
          rend="italic">Sena,</hi> half <lb/>a Dram, and in the leſs 24 Grains. The <lb/>Magiſterial
        Syrup of Apples hath a Dram of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Sena</hi> to an Ounce, but the Purging
        Syrup <lb/>only a Scruple infus'd to ſix Drams. Syrup <lb/>of Roſes with <hi rend="italic"
          >Sena</hi> hath indeed a Dram to <lb/>ſix Drams of the Syrup. I ſhall conclude <lb/>this
        Head, with the form of a Purging Potion <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Sena,</hi> from an eminent
        Phyſician of our <lb/>own, who Practiced upwards of ſixty Years. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Take</hi> of fine <hi rend="italic">Sena,</hi> cut ſmall
        ſix Drams, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Salt</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Tartar</hi> two Drams,
        Juice of <hi rend="italic">Lemons</hi>
        <lb/>one Ounce, white Wine four Ounces, <w part="I">in-</w><lb/><w part="F">fuſe</w> ſix or
        ſeven Hours, in a Glaſs Veſſel, <lb/>then ſtrain, and infuſe therein all Night <hi
          rend="italic">E-<lb/>lectuary</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Carthamum</hi> three Drams, the
        Juice <lb/>of Apples one Ounce: In the Morning <w part="I">cla-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >rifie</w> this with the white of an Egg, and to <lb/>the ſtrain'd Liquor, add Syrup of
          <hi rend="italic">Roſes,</hi>
        <lb/>with <hi rend="italic">Agarick</hi> ſix Drams, <hi rend="italic">Cinamon-Water</hi> two
        <lb/>Drams, the zeſt of half an Orange Peel. <lb/>Notwithſtanding the large Quantity of <hi
          rend="italic">Sena;</hi>
        <lb/>this is a Medicine of a nice and delicate <w part="I">O-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >peration</w>, without giving Gripes or Colick, <lb/>and yet moves Ten or Twelve times. </p>
      <p rend="indent"><lb/>IN order to introduce our <hi rend="italic">Antidotaria,</hi> it
        <lb/>may not be amiſs to give a Specimen of the <lb/>Reformation of two grand Preſcriptions,
        <lb/>which I have already hinted at to be faulty, <lb/>in the <hi rend="italic">Pharmacopeia
          Londinenſis,</hi> viz. The <lb/>Confect of <hi rend="italic">Alkermes,</hi> and that of
          <hi rend="italic">Hyacinth.</hi>
      </p>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_21" n="22"/>
        <head rend="align-center italic"><lb/>The Confection of <hi rend="roman">Alkermes</hi>
          Reformed. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Take</hi> the Juice of Kermes, ſweet <w part="I"
            >Ap-</w><lb/><w part="F">ples</w>, and Raſpberries, of each ſtrain'd ℔ij, <lb/>Sugar of
          Roſes ℔ij, mix and by a gentle Fire <lb/>boil to the Conſiſtence of Honey. The <w part="I"
            >A-</w><lb/><w part="F">peritive</w> Saffron, or Crocus Martis ℥iij, red <lb/>Roſe Buds
          reduc'd to a Powder, after <w part="I">ha-</w><lb/><w part="F">ving</w> been firſt ſteep'd
          in Juice of Lemons <lb/>ʒvi, <hi rend="italic">Pearl, Coral, Crabs Eyes</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">burnt Hart's-<lb/>Horn</hi> laevigated with Oil of <hi rend="italic"
            >Tartar</hi> per <hi rend="italic">De-<lb/>liq;</hi> of each five Drams, <hi
            rend="italic">Citron Sanders</hi> and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Bezoar,</hi> or <hi
            rend="italic">Contrayerva Stone,</hi> of each ʒſs, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Musk</hi> and
            <hi rend="italic">Ambergreeſe</hi> may be added, at the <lb/>Diſcretion of the
          Phyſician, but it is <w part="I">Judg-</w><lb/><w part="F">ed</w> much better to be left
          out. This <w part="I">Com-</w><lb/><w part="F">poſition</w> is preferable to that of the
          Shops, <lb/>for the Intentions aim'd at, being more <lb/>Cordial and Specifical to drive
          away <w part="I">Melan-</w><lb/><w part="F">choly</w> and the Malignity of the Bilous
          Juices, <lb/>beſides it is better appropriated to ſtop <lb/>Fluxes, and to reſtore
          Strength. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center italic"><lb/>The Confection of <hi rend="roman">Hyacinth</hi>
          Reformed. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Take</hi> of the Seeds of Hyacinth and <w part="I"
            >Vi-</w><lb/><w part="F">per's</w> Bugloſs, of each ℥ſs, of the Roots of <w part="I"
            >Tor-</w><lb/><w part="F">mentil</w>, Biſtort, Contrayerva, Scorzonera, <lb/>Dictamny,
          of each ʒiij, Citron and Orange-<lb/>Peel dry'd of each ʒiſs, Betony and red <lb/>Roſe
          Flowers, of each ʒi, Sorrel and <w part="I">Pur-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſlane</w> Seed, of
          each ℈ij; burnt Hart's Horn, <lb/>yellow Sanders, and white Amber, of each <lb/>ʒij,
          Magiſtery of Pearl and Coral, and <lb/>Crabs-Eyes prepar'd, of each ʒvi Bole, <w part="I"
            >Lem-</w><pb xml:id="page_22" n="23"/><lb/><w part="F">nian</w> and Sileſian Earths, of
          each ʒij, <w part="I">Saf-</w><lb/><w part="F">fron</w> ℈iv, Camphore ℈i, Tincture of
          Kermes-<lb/>Berries, extracted in Juice of Lemon, and <lb/>reduc'd to the Conſiſtence of
          Honey ℥ij; all <lb/>theſe being rightly mix'd, and brought to a <lb/>Powder, may be made
          into a Maſs or <w part="I">Electu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ary</w>, with Syrup of Lemons,
          Mulberries, <lb/><hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">N. B.</hi> In this Compoſition, inſtead of the
          <lb/>Fragments of Precious Stones, or the <w part="I">Hya-</w><lb/><w part="F">cinth</w>,
          our Author has made Choice of the <lb/>Seed which <hi rend="italic">Dioſcorides,</hi> thus
          deſcrib'd, <hi rend="italic">Book</hi> 4. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Chap.</hi> 58. The Seed
          of the <hi rend="italic">Hyacinth,</hi> ſays he, <lb/>is Aſtringent, and Proper for the <w
            part="I">Compotiſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">on</w> of Treacles, Myrrh is omitted, becauſe of
          <lb/>its ingrateful Taſte, and as to the Perfumers of <lb/>Musk and <hi rend="italic"
            >Ambergreeſe,</hi> they may be added <lb/>at the Diſcretion of the Preſcriber. But this
          <lb/>Electuary ſeems better adapted, than that <lb/>of the Shops, being more Cordial and
            <w part="I">Reſto-</w><lb/><w part="F">rative</w>, and may be us'd with good Effect
          <lb/>in Malignant Diſentery's and profuſe <w part="I">Di-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >arrhaea's</w>, as alſo Peſtilential Fevers, Small-<lb/>Pox, <hi rend="italic"
            >&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/><hi rend="size(1.7) sc">Antidotaria</hi>; <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Or, a Collection of</hi> Antidotes, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>I Deſign'd to have given you Sir <hi rend="italic">Walter
            <lb/>Rawleigh's</hi> great Cordial from the original <lb/>Manuſcript, which you have
          taken into your <lb/><hi rend="italic">Diſpenſatory</hi> from <hi rend="italic"
            >Bates,</hi> but the Variations <lb/>are ſo great, and the Articles ſo Numerous, <lb/>I
          refer 'em to a larger Work, and ſhall give <lb/>you Sir <hi rend="italic">Walter
            Rawleigh's</hi> grand <hi rend="italic">Diaphore-</hi><pb xml:id="page_23" n="24"/><hi
            rend="italic"><lb/>tick,</hi> taken from <hi rend="italic">Holten,</hi> who liv'd with
          him, <lb/>and alſo Sir <hi rend="italic">Kenelm Digby's</hi> two ſudorifick <lb/>Waters,
          Vegetable and Mineral, <w part="I">appropri-</w><lb/><w part="F">ated</w> to all burning
          Malignant Fevers and <lb/>Peſtilential Diſeaſes. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>Rawleigh's <hi rend="sc">Diaphoretick</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Take</hi> Mercury ſublimate ℔j. Crude <lb/>Antimony, or
          rather the Regulus ℔ij, <lb/>Grind them well on a Marble, till a Fume <lb/>begin to ariſe,
          then put the Mixture into a <lb/>Bolt-Head or Matraſs, place this in a <w part="I"
            >Cel-</w><lb/><w part="F">lar</w>, and let it ſtand 15 or 20 Hours, till it <lb/>runds
          into Butter, put that into a Glaſs <w part="I">A-</w><lb/><w part="F">lembick</w>, and
          diſtill till nothing will come <lb/>over; encreaſe the Fire till a certain white
          <lb/>Matter appears ſublim'd on the Upper part, <lb/>or Head of the Alembick; then ceaſe
          till <lb/>the Veſſels are cold, and keep the white <lb/>Sublimate a part, or ſeparate, but
          the <w part="I">Reſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">dence</w> remaining in the bottom is to be <w
            part="I">divi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ded</w> into two equal Parts, of which take one
          <lb/>half, and all the Sublimate gain'd before, <lb/>to this pour the Water which aſcended
          in the <lb/>firſt Diſtillation: Drive this till nothing <lb/>further will Diſtil, and the
          Veſſel being <lb/>cool, the <hi rend="italic">Magma,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Caput
            Mortum,</hi> with what <lb/>is Sublimed muſt be Ground together in a <lb/>Glaſs Mortar,
          and Water put in therewith <lb/>to the Alembick: Drive this over again, <lb/>and Repeat it
          7 or 8 times, but give a large <lb/>degree of Fire to the laſt, that the <w part="I"
            >Subli-</w><lb/><w part="F">mation</w> may be exactly Regular: The <w part="I"
            >Glaſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſes</w> being cold Collect your Sublimate, then <pb
            xml:id="page_24" n="25"/><lb/>Grind it again on a Marble, and in a ſmall
          <lb/>ſublimating Furnace, ſublime it Thirty <lb/>or Forty times, Grinding it fine, every
          time, <lb/>theoftener the better; the laſt time it muſt <lb/>be reduc'd to an impalpable
          Powder, and <lb/>put it into a Silver or Gold Veſſel, to <lb/>which pour the beſt Spirit
          of Wine, and <lb/>burn it, reiterating this Work Seven or <lb/>Eight times, at laſt you
          will have a perfect <lb/>dry Powder, to be given from 6 to 12 Grains; <lb/>this was a kind
          of <hi rend="italic">Panacea</hi> to <hi rend="italic">Ralegh,</hi> and <lb/>given in
          Rheumatiſms, Small-Pox, Plague, <lb/>Malignant Fevers, and all cutaneous <w part="I"
            >Di-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſeaſes</w>. It moves powerfully to Sweat. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>Sir <hi rend="italic">Kenelm Digby's</hi> Sudorifick <hi
            rend="italic">Cordial-Water.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Take of the Roots of Scorzonera, <w part="I">Genti-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">an</w>, Elicampane, Cinquefoil, Tormentil, <w part="I">Cy-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >prus</w>, Ariſtolochius of both Kinds, of each ℥iv. <lb/>Zedoary ℥iij, the Husks of
          green Walnuts ℔i, <lb/>of the Leaves of the Orange and Lemon-Tree, <lb/>Bay, Baſil and
          Scordium, of each M. iv, <lb/>the outward Rind of Lemons and Oranges, of <lb/>each ℥x,
          Juniper-Berries ℥viij, Ivy-Berries <lb/>℥xij, clarified Juice of Valerian, Mead ſweet,
          <lb/>Scabious, Marygold, and Carduus, of each <lb/>℔iij Rheniſh Wine, and Rain Water, of
          <lb/>each five Quarts, white Wine Vinegar ℔v; <lb/>bruiſe and mix all theſe together, and
          ſet <lb/>'em in Horſe-Dung a Week, then Diſtill in <lb/>Sand to the Conſumption of half,
          and ſtrain the <lb/>Reſidue, making a ſtrong Expreſſion of the <pb xml:id="page_25" n="26"
          /><lb/>Magma, which Calcine, to white Aſhes: The <lb/>expreſs'd Liquor is to be ſtrain'd
          through a <lb/>triple Filter, Diſtill'd again, till the Cordial <lb/>Extract remains,
          which is to be kept by itſelf, <lb/>the Salt of the <hi rend="italic">Magma</hi> being
          added thereto, <lb/>for the better preſervation and encreaſe of its <lb/>Virtue: Take of
          this Cordial now deſcrib'd <lb/>℔ij. Salt of Tartar ℔ſs, mix and rectifie <lb/>together,
          and to the rectified Water, add <lb/>Antimony Diaphoretick ℥ij, burnt Harts-<lb/>Horn ℥iv;
          Mix and Digeſt in Sand eight <lb/>Days, then Filter. The Doſe is ℥i, to ʒvi, <lb/>by
          itſelf, or in Treacle-water in Malignant <lb/>Fevers, you may add to this, Juice of
          Sorrel, <lb/>or Lemons, and little a Sugar, with half a <lb/>Dram of <hi rend="italic"
            >Contrayerva.</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center italic"><lb/>The Mineral Sudorifick Water of Sir <hi rend="roman"
            >Ke-<lb/>nelm Digby.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Take</hi> of Crude Antimony, ground to a <lb/>ſubtle
          Powder ℥i, Salt of Tartar ʒvi, mix well, <lb/>and put them together for ſome Days, in a
          <lb/>moiſt Place, ſhake often, and at laſt they <lb/>will dry; Repeat this two or three
          times, at <lb/>laſt Grind this finely, put it into a <w part="I">Philoſo-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">phical</w> Egg, bury it in a Sand heat, or <w part="I">ra-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ther</w> a Reverberatory, ſix or ſeven Days, at <lb/>laſt give a Fire of the fourth
          degree of Heat, <lb/>ſo that obſcure Clouds may ariſe, the <w part="I">Mat-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">ter</w> will be of a red Colour, which take out, <lb/>Grind afreſh, and put it
          into a ſtronger Glaſs, <lb/>pour on Spirit of Wine, and Extract, till <lb/>the Spirit is
          tinged of a ruby Dye: Doſe is <pb xml:id="page_26" n="27"/><lb/>from x to xx Drops in any
          convenient <w part="I">Li-</w><lb/><w part="F">quor</w>, as Wine, Treacle or
          Carduus-Water; <lb/>it is a powerful and noble <hi rend="italic">Sudorifick.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Chalybeate Pills,</hi> firſt invented in the <hi
            rend="italic">Pla∣-<lb/>gue</hi> time, for ſtrengthening the Stomach, <lb/>opening
          Obſtructions of the Spleen, and <w part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſipating</w> all the
          Melancholly and malignant <lb/>Vapours. This Preſcription ſeems to carry <lb/>along with
          it the Perfection of the Art <lb/>of Compoſition. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Take</hi> of the Species <hi rend="italic">Hiera
            Picra</hi> ℥ſs, <w part="I">A-</w><lb/><w part="F">loes</w> roſat. ʒij, ℈ij, mix, and of
          this take <w part="I">on-</w><lb/><w part="F">ly</w> ʒiij, ℈i, of pure Vitriol of Iron ℈v,
          red <lb/>Coral, Crab-Eyes, Maſtick, Contrayerva <lb/>Stone, Lapis Lazuli prepar'd finely,
          Salt of <lb/>Worm-wood, of each ℈ij. ſs, Balſam of <hi rend="italic">Pe-<lb/>ru,</hi> as
          much as will make them into a Maſs <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Pills</hi> for ten Doſes. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>Every Doſe of <lb/>which will <w part="I">con-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >tain</w> ʒi, in theſe <lb/>Proportions. <list>
            <lb/>
            <item>Of Hiera Piera, <lb/>and Aloes ℈i, <w part="I">Vi-</w><lb/><w part="F">triol</w>
              of Iron ℈ſs, <lb/>Red, Coral and <lb/>Crabs-Eyes. </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>Maſtick, <w part="I">Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">trayerva</w> Lap. <lb/>Lazuli, and
              <lb/>Salt of <w part="I">Worm-</w><lb/><w part="F">wood</w>. </item>
          </list><lb/>of each gr. v. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center italic"><lb/>Another Compoſition of <hi rend="roman">Steel
            Pills,</hi> to <lb/>the ſame Effect. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Take</hi> of Maſtick ʒij, Benjamin, <w part="I"
            >natu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ral</w> Balſam, Gum Guajacum, red Coral, Pearl,
          <lb/>Crabs-Eyes, burnt Harts-Horn, Ultramarine, <lb/>Salt of Wormwood, of each ʒi, Hiera
          Picra <lb/>℥ſs, Aloes Roſat. ʒij, Salt of Steel, or <w part="I">Vi-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >triol</w> of Iron ʒiſs, with Balſam of <hi rend="italic">Peru,</hi>
          <lb/>make a Maſs. The Doſe is ʒi, taken every Day. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <pb xml:id="page_27" n="28"/>
        <head rend="italic indent hanging"><lb/>A Hiſtory of the ſeveral Compoſitions that <lb/>make
          the <hi rend="roman">Contrayerva-Stone,</hi> which is <lb/>the Grand <hi rend="roman"
            >Antidotarium.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">Contrayerva,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Drake Root,</hi> is an <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Indian</hi> Plant, which ſome Judge to be of the <lb/>Nature of <hi
            rend="italic">Tormentil.</hi> This was firſt <w part="I">intro-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >duced</w> into <hi rend="italic">France,</hi> in 1602, and much <w part="I"
            >pre-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſcrib'd</w> by the Phyſicians at <hi rend="italic">Paris,</hi>
          in the <lb/><hi rend="sc">Piague</hi> there at that Time, when it <lb/>proved of excellent
          Service. The Root is <lb/>tuberoſe and knotty, ſhooting forth many <lb/>Hairs or Fibres of
          a yellowiſh, or rather <lb/>brown Colour, which when chew'd gives an <lb/>Aromatick
          flavour, and leaves an heat upon <lb/>the Tongue, tho' no bitterneſs, or ſtipticity
          <lb/>is obſervable. This grows in both the <hi rend="italic">In-<lb/>dies,</hi> but moſt
          plentifully in the <hi rend="italic">Weſt,</hi> in the <lb/>Kingdom of <hi rend="italic"
            >Peru,</hi> and that Part call'd <hi rend="italic">Ci-<lb/>arche</hi> and <hi
            rend="italic">Tonſuglar.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi> Uſe it for <lb/>Sallet;
          they much covet the Root, which <lb/>they cut in Pieces, and put under the Soles <lb/>of
          their Feet in Winter time: The <hi rend="italic">Goats</hi>
          <lb/>from eating of this Plant, are ſaid to <w part="I">gene-</w><lb/><w part="F">rate</w>
          the <hi rend="italic">Bezoar Stone,</hi> for the <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi>
          <w part="I">ob-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſerve</w> thoſe <hi rend="italic">Goats,</hi> of which
          there are <w part="I">ſeve-</w><lb/><w part="F">ral</w> Kinds, of which one is call'd <hi
            rend="italic">Bicuqua,</hi>
          <lb/>and thoſe which do not feed upon this Plant, <lb/>never generate any of theſe Stones;
          ſo that <lb/>according to this Notion, their <hi rend="italic">Bezoar</hi> ſeems <lb/>to
          be a Concretion of Tartar, or the <w part="I">fæcu-</w><lb/><w part="F">lent</w> Part of
          the Aliment, form'd from the <lb/>Digeſtion of the <hi rend="italic">Contrayerva
            Plant.</hi>
        </p>
        <pb xml:id="page_28" n="29"/>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> Stone in <hi rend="italic">India</hi> is made
          from the <lb/>Juice of the Root, and the whole Plant <w part="I">to-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >gether</w>, this is Reduced into Paſte, and ſo <lb/>form'd into Stones of various
          Sizes. The <lb/>Root is given from a Dram to two, and hath <lb/>had the Power to throw out
          Boils, Blains <lb/>and Carbuncles, with great Succeſs, in the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Plague</hi> Time, which Encouraged the <w part="I">Phyſici-</w><lb/><w part="F">ans</w>
          to invent ſeveral Compoſitions there <lb/>from </p>
      </div>
      <div type="part">
        <head rend="italic align-center"><lb/>The General Materials for the <hi rend="roman"
            >Contra-<lb/>yerva Stone.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">Contrayerva Root,</hi> white Amber, Rock
          <lb/>Chryſtal, Snake-Root, Zedoary, <w part="I">Tormen-</w><lb/><w part="F">til</w>,
          Biſtort, Angelica, red Coral, Camphore, <lb/>Saffron, Crabs-Claws, Crabs-Eyes, burnt
          <lb/>Harts-Horn, Vipers, Carline Thiſtle, <w part="I">But-</w><lb/><w part="F"
          >ter-Bur</w>, Elecampane, Valerian, Pearl, <w part="I">Ma-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtick</w>,
          Cochineal, Iſinglaſs, Lemnian, and <lb/>Sileſia Earth, Ceruſſe of Antimony-Flowers <lb/>of
          ♀, Moſch and Amberbergreeſe to form <lb/>it into a Maſs, the Jelly of Vipers Skins,
          <lb/>Iſinglaſs, Harts-Horn, or an Extract of <lb/>Scordium; or Scorzonera, with the white
          <lb/>of an Egg may be neceſſary. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic indent hanging"><lb/>Various Forms of the <hi rend="roman">Contrayerva
            Stone,</hi>
          <lb/>each of which contain a Doſe, which may <lb/>be multiplied at Diſcretion. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Take</hi> Antimony Diaphoretick ℈i, <w part="I"
            >Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">trayerv</w>. Bezoar Animal, Crabs-Claws, of <pb
            xml:id="page_29" n="30"/><lb/>each gr. x; make a Bole with Jelly of Harts-<lb/>Horn, qs. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Or</hi> Take Diaphoretick Magiſterial <w part="I"
            >Con-</w><lb/><w part="F">trayerv</w>. and oriental Bezoar, of each gr. <lb/>vi.
          Harts-Horn, Pearl, Coral and Crabs-<lb/>Eyes prepar'd, of each gr. v. white Amber,
          <lb/>Lemnian and Sileſia Earth, of each gr. iv. <lb/>Ambergreeſe gr. ij, make a Bole as
          before. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>3dly, <hi rend="sc">take</hi> Ceruſe of Antimony, <w part="I"
            >Magi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtery</w> of Coral, Pearl and Crabs-Eyes, of <lb/>each ℈ſs,
          Saffron and Contrayerva Root, of <lb/>each gr. iv, make a Bole with Jelly of
          Harts-<lb/>Horn, or Mucilage of Quince Seed. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/>4thly, <hi rend="sc">take</hi> Snake Root, Valerian and
          <lb/>Contrayerva, of each ℈ſs, Cochineal and <lb/>Camphere, of each gr. iv. Bol-Arm. gr.
          vi, <lb/>mix and make a fine Powder for one Doſe, <lb/>or a Bole, with Confect of
          Alkermes. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>Bezoar Animal <hi rend="italic">prepared from</hi>
          Harts-<lb/>Horn. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Take</hi> the freſheſt and youngeſt Tips of
          <lb/>Harts-Horn, Calcine to a perfect whiteneſs, <lb/>Grind this to a Powder, and make it
          into <lb/>Troches, with Syrup of Betony or Citron, <lb/>firſt acuated with ſome Drops of
          Oil of <w part="I">Vi-</w><lb/><w part="F">triol</w> or Sulphur by the Bell. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center italic"><lb/>The firſt Notion of the <hi rend="roman">Bezoardick
            Bole.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Take</hi> of the Contrayerva Stone ℥i. <w part="I"
            >Ori-</w><lb/><w part="F">ental</w> Bezoar ℥ſs, Bezoar Animal ℥iv, <w part="I"
            >Ma-</w><lb/><w part="F">giſtery</w> of Coral, Pearl and Crabs-Eyes, of <pb
            xml:id="page_30" n="31"/><lb/>each ℥iiſs, Crabs-Claws ℥iv, white Amber <lb/>℥ij, Lemnian
          and Sileſia Earth ʒvi, Rock <lb/>Chryſtal Calcined into an impalpable <lb/>Powder ʒx, Musk
          ʒſs, with Jelly of Harts-<lb/>Horn, made from a Tincture of Saffron; <lb/>make this into a
          Paſte, from whence Stones <lb/>may be form'd. Take of the ſaid Stone, <lb/>gr. xx.
          Crollius Diaphoretick gr. x, for a <lb/>Doſe, and to raiſe the Alixipharmick power
          <lb/>greater to the whole Compoſition of the <lb/>Stone, add the Liver and Heart of Vipers
          <lb/>ʒij; the Vipers Fleſh and Bones dry'd <w part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">cording</w>
          to Art ℥iv, to which put of the <lb/>Roots of Angelica, Tormentil, <w part="I"
            >Contrayer-</w><lb/><w part="F">va</w>, Zedoary, Scorzonera, Scordium, Rue and
          <lb/>Orange-Water, of each ʒi, made into a Maſs, <lb/>with Jelly of Vipers Skins. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center italic"><lb/>Another COMPOSITION. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Take</hi> of Ceruſſe of Antimony or Flowers <lb/>of the
          ſame, whether red or white ℥v, <lb/>Harts-Horn prepar'd with Syrup of <w part="I"
            >Angeli-</w><lb/><w part="F">ca</w> and Oil of Sulphur ℥ij, Roots of <w part="I"
            >Tormen-</w><lb/><w part="F">til</w>, Scorzoner ℥ij, Butter-Bur, both the <w part="I"
            >Vale-</w><lb/><w part="F">rians</w>, Bunnian Seed, and Galangal, an ℥ſs,
          <lb/>Crabs-Claws, Crabs-Eyes, red Coral, Sileſia-<lb/>Earth, Cochineal, of each ℥i, Salt
          of <w part="I">Car-</w><lb/><w part="F">duus</w>, Mead ſweet, Angelica, Tartar <w part="I"
            >Vitrio-</w><lb/><w part="F">lated</w>, ſal Prunelle, of each ʒij, mix for a <lb/>Paſte,
          with Jelly of Harts-Horn, made up <lb/>with Musk or Saffron, to this may be added,
          <lb/>Vol. Salt of Vipers ℥i. Aur. Fulminans. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_31" n="32"/>
        <head rend="align-center italic"><lb/>The Solar <hi rend="roman">Bezoardick Bole.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Take</hi> Crollius Diophoretick of ♁ gr. <lb/>xij,
          Bezoar oriental gr. viij, Bezoar <w part="I">Ani-</w><lb/><w part="F">mal</w>, Magiſtery
          of Coral and Crabs-Eyes, <lb/>an. gr. vij, Cochineal gr. vi, Aurum <w part="I"
            >Ful-</w><lb/><w part="F">minans</w> gr. iv, Ambergreeſe gr. ij, mix for <lb/>a Doſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="italic">N. B.</hi> If the foregoing Magiſteries are
          <lb/>made with Spirit of Vitriol, Oil of <w part="I">Sul-</w><lb/><w part="F">phur</w>,
          &amp;c. the Medicine will be the more <lb/>Effectual, and better reſiſt the Putrefaction
          <lb/>of the Malignity. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center italic"><lb/>The Northern <hi rend="roman">Bezoartick-Stone.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Take</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">Hartman's</hi> Diaphoretick <w part="I">Antimo-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ny</w>, Magiſtery of Gold, red Coral an. ʒvi, <lb/>common Antimony Diaphoretick,
          Harts-<lb/>Horn Calcined, Crabs-Eyes prepar'd an ℥i, <lb/>Crabs-Claws in Powder ʒij,
          Ambergreeſe ʒi, <lb/>Musk ℈i, make this into Paſte with Jelly of <lb/>Iſinglaſs, in
          Roſe-Water. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center"><lb/>The Southern <hi rend="roman">Bezoartick-Stone.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Take</hi> of the Magiſterial Diaphoretick <lb/>℥i,
          Ceruſſe of ♁ ℥iij, burnt Harts-Horn, <lb/>Crabs-Eyes, of Vipers Fleſh, Cochineal <lb/>an.
          ℥iſs, Magiſtery of Pearl, and <w part="I">Co-</w><lb/><w part="F">ral</w> an. ʒvi,
          Sileſian-Earth ℥i, yellow <w part="I">San-</w><lb/><w part="F">ders</w>, Orange-Peel an.
          ℥ſs, Roots of Valerian, <lb/>Butter-Bur, Scorzonera, Contrayerva, Seeds <pb
            xml:id="page_32" n="33"/><lb/>of Angelica an. ʒvi, Ambergreeſe, Musk an <lb/>ʒſs, make a
          Powder, and then a Paſte with <lb/>Jelly of Hart's-Horn, the Doſe from a ℈i, <lb/>℈ij,
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic indent-hanging"><lb/>In the Year <hi rend="roman">1628</hi>, the
          following <w part="I">Preſcrip-</w><lb/><w part="F">tions</w> of the <hi rend="roman"
            >Contrayerva-Stone</hi> were <lb/>directed. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Take</hi> Contrayerva Root, ℥ij, Hart's-<lb/>Horn
          prepar'd and Lemnian-Earth, of each <lb/>℥i, Cochineal ℥ſs, Margarit ℥iv, Snake-Roct
          <lb/>℥ſs, with Iſinglaſs and Juice of Kermes, <lb/>make a Maſs; whereof take ʒſs, in any
          <lb/>Cordial-Water. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Or, take</hi> Contrayerva, Snake-Root, of <lb/>each ℥i,
          Pearl and Crabs-Eyes an. ℥ſs, <w part="I">Saf-</w><lb/><w part="F">fron</w> ʒij, Cochineal
          ʒij, mix and give ℈ſs, to <lb/>℈i, in any appropriated Vehicle. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="indent hanging italic"><lb/>In the Year <hi rend="roman">1636</hi>, when the <hi
            rend="sc">Plague </hi><lb/>Raged in <hi rend="roman">London</hi>, theſe Forms were
          <lb/>Preſcrib'd. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Take</hi> Crabs-Claws in Powder, Bezoar <lb/>Animal,
          Syrup of Betony, Kermes and <w part="I">Ci-</w><lb/><w part="F">tron</w> an. ℥iv,
          Contrayerva, and Snake-Root <lb/>an. ℥v, Seed of Angelica an. ℥i, Antimony,
          <lb/>Diaphoretick ℥vi, Ambergreeſe ʒij, mix. <lb/>The Doſe is ℈i, to ʒſs. Take
          Contrayerva, <lb/>and Snake-Root, with Crabs-Claws powder'd <pb xml:id="page_33" n="34"
          /><lb/>an ʒij, Pearl, and Coral an. ʒiij, Crollius, <lb/>Diaphoretick of Antimony ʒi. The
          Doſe ℈i. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>The <hi rend="italic">TREACLE-STONE.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Take</hi> the whole Viper reduc'd to <w part="I"
            >Pow-</w><lb/><w part="F">der</w> ℥i, Crabs-Eyes ℥iv, <hi rend="italic">Hartman's</hi>
          <w part="I">Diapho-</w><lb/><w part="F">retick</w>, or Flowers of ♁, fix'd by the Fire
          ℥ij, <lb/>Mother of Pearl, Cochineal, and white <w part="I">Am-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >ber</w> an. ℥iſs, Roots of Tormentil, Biſtort, <lb/>Scorzonera an. ℥ij, Kermes Berry,
          Orange-<lb/>Peel and Angelica an. ℥ſs, Saffron with <w part="I">Ve-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >nice-Treacle</w>, qs. make a Maſs. Doſe ℈ to ʒi. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center italic"><lb/>A Compoſition very Succeſſful in the <hi rend="roman"
            >Small-<lb/>Pox, Meaſles, Milliary-Fever,</hi> &amp;c. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Take</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">Hartman's</hi> Diaphoretick gr. x, <lb/>Contrayerva-Stone, and Bezoar
          an. gr. viij, <lb/>Hart's-Horn prepar'd with Oil of Vitriol, <lb/>Coral, Crabs-Eyes, of
          each gr. vi, Sileſian, <lb/>Lemnian Earth, and Cochineal an gr. v, mix <lb/>for a Doſe in
          Treacle-Water. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center italic "><lb/>The white <hi rend="roman">Contrayerva-Stone.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Take</hi> of the Contrayerva-Root ℥i, Hart's-<lb/>Horn,
          and Crabs-Claws, laevigated on a <lb/>Marble, with Carduus-Water an. ℥i, <w part="I"
            >Magi-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtery</w> of Pearl and Coral an. ℥ſs; make this <pb
            xml:id="page_34" n="35"/><lb/>up with Jelly of Hart's-Horn and Iſinglaſs; <lb/>the Doſe
          ʒſs, to Children ℈i. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center"><lb/>The red <hi rend="roman">Contrayerva-Stone.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Take</hi> of the Contrayerva-Root ℥iſs, <w part="I"
            >An-</w><lb/><w part="F">timony</w> Diaphoretick, Crabs-Eyes an. ʒx, <lb/>Chochineal
          ℥iſs, Bezoar Mineral ℥ſs, Grind <lb/>theſe together, and they will be of an <w part="I"
            >ex-</w><lb/><w part="F">cellent</w> red Colour; the Doſe from ℈i, to ʒſs, <lb/>in the
          Confluent <hi rend="italic">Small-Pox</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Purple-Fe-<lb/>vers.</hi>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center italic"><lb/>Confect of <hi rend="roman">Vipers,</hi> or the Grand
            <hi rend="roman">Antidote</hi>
          <lb/>againſt all Sorts of <hi rend="roman">Poyſon.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Take</hi> Vipers in the <hi rend="italic">Spring,</hi>
          Cut their <lb/>Heads off, and cleanſe them well in white <lb/>Wine; dry them, and reduce
          them with <lb/>their Hearts and Livers to Powder, of this <lb/>ſo prepared, take ℥iv,
          Roots of <w part="I">Contrayer-</w><lb/><w part="F">va</w> ℥ij, Tormentil, Scorzonera an.
          ℥iſs, <lb/>Roots of Avens, Vervain, Carline, Baſtard, <lb/>Saffron, Fraxinel, Cinquefoil,
          Elecampane, <lb/>the outward Rind of the Lemon and Orange <lb/>an. ℥i; Roots of Swallow
          wort, both the the <lb/>Valerians, Burdock, Butter-Bur, <w part="I">Genti-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">tian</w>, Zedoary an. ʒvi, Angelica-Roots ʒſs, <lb/>Leaves of Scordium, Rue,
          Malabathrum, <lb/>Paul's Betony, Sanicle, Winter-green an ʒvi, <lb/>Flowers of Self-heal,
            <hi rend="italic">Spaniſh Broom,</hi> Betony, <pb xml:id="page_35" n="36"
          /><lb/>Mary-gold, Mead ſweet Oranges an. ʒv, <lb/>Seeds of Rue, Scabious, Burdock, Vipers
          <lb/>Bugloſs, Vervain, Sorrel, Purſlane, <w part="I">Cardu-</w><lb/><w part="F">us</w>,
            <hi rend="italic">St.</hi> John's-Wort, Mary-golds, Broom an. <lb/>ʒiij, Citron Sanders,
          Rhodium, Saſſafraſs, <lb/>Coſtus, Schaenath, Calamus Aromaticus, <lb/>Harts-Horn and the
          Raſping of Human <lb/>Sculls, Lemnian Earth, Gum Guajacum, <lb/>Myrrh, Maſtick, Sandarac,
          Olibanum an. <lb/>℥ſs, white Amber, Pearl and Coral <w part="I">prepa-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >red</w>; <hi rend="italic">Hartman's</hi> Diaphoretick of Antimony <lb/>ʒij, Mace,
          Cloves, Cinnamon, Infuſed in <lb/>Juice of Lemon an. ʒvi, all theſe well <lb/>power'd
          ſeparately, may be afterwards <lb/>mix'd together in the following <hi rend="italic"
            >Electuary.</hi>
          <lb/>Take of freſh Juniper-Berries ℔iv, the <w part="I">Par-</w><lb/><w part="F">ings</w>
          of Apples and Quinces an. ℔ſs, Roots <lb/>of Sorrel and Succory an. ℥iv, Scabious, <w
            part="I">Ma-</w><lb/><w part="F">ry-gold</w>, Wood-Sorrel, Borage, the whole <lb/>Plants
          an. M. ij, Flowers of Sage, <w part="I">Roſema-</w><lb/><w part="F">ry</w>, red Roſes,
          Germander, Broom and <lb/>Mugwort an. Pug. iij, Kermes Berries, <lb/>Citron Seeds an. ʒij,
          Orange-Peel and <w part="I">Rho-</w><lb/><w part="F">dium</w> Raſped an. ʒiſs; Boil all in
            <hi rend="italic">Spaniſh</hi>
          <lb/>Wine and Carduus-Water, of each equal <lb/>Parts, to which add Juice of Strawberries,
          <lb/>Raſpberries, Cherries or Quinces ℔ij, ſtrain <lb/>this and Boil the Expreſs'd Liquor
          to the <lb/>Conſiſtence of Honey: Of which take two <lb/>Parts to one of the Spices, or
          Powder <w part="I">be-</w><lb/><w part="F">fore</w> Preſcrib'd, adding thereto upon <w
            part="I">Occaſi-</w><lb/><w part="F">on</w>, to every Doſe of Antimony <w part="I"
            >Diaphore-</w><lb/><w part="F">tick</w> ℈i, Aurum Fulminans ℈ſs, Oil of <w part="I"
            >Sul-</w><lb/><w part="F">phur</w> gr. iv; Doſe ʒſs, to ℈iv. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <pb xml:id="page_36" n="37"/>
        <head rend="align-center italic"><lb/>The Imperial Cordial Water <hi rend="roman">in</hi>
          <w part="I">Peſti-</w><lb/><w part="F">lential-Fevers</w>. </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Take</hi> of the dry'd Roots of <w part="I"
            >Swallow-</w><lb/><w part="F">wort</w>, Angelica, Maſterwort, Gentian, <w part="I"
            >Ele-</w><lb/><w part="F">campane</w> ℥ij, Roots of Carline Thiſtle, <w part="I"
            >Bur-</w><lb/><w part="F">dock</w>, Birthworth, Biſtort, Tormentil, <w part="I"
            >Ga-</w><lb/><w part="F">lingal</w>, Scorzonera, Contrayerva an. ℥iij, <lb/>Leaves of
          Hyſſop, Majoram, Rue, Bay, <lb/>Mint, Balm, Mead ſweet, Wormwood an. <lb/>℔iij, Flowers of
          Centaury, Broom, St. <lb/>Johns-wort, Mary-gold, Sage, Lavender and <lb/>Orange an. ℥i,
          Cinnamon, Cloves, Mace, <lb/>Nutmegs, Zedoary, Galangal, Calamus an. <lb/>ʒx,
          Juniper-Berries, Rhodium and Citron <lb/>Sanders an. ℥iij, Orange-Peel ℥vi,
          Strong-<lb/>Wine, or Brandy ℔xij, Infuſe for 8 or 10 <lb/>Days, then Diſtill, afterwards
          ſweeten with <lb/>Loaf-Sugar, to which add a few Drops of <lb/>Oil of Cinnamon, Burgamot,
          or Eſſence of <lb/>Ambergreeſe. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center"><lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Golden Elixir</hi> of <hi rend="italic"
            >LIFE.</hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">Aurm Potabile</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Blanc</hi> was made <lb/>of the
          beſt Spirit of Wine, Circulated with <lb/>Honey, Musk and Ambergreeſe, according <lb/>to
          the Deſcription of <hi rend="italic">Gabel Rhoverus,</hi> in <pb xml:id="page_37" n="38"
          /><lb/>the ſecond Part of his <hi rend="italic">Antidotarium,</hi> pag. 383. <lb/>This is
          one of the moſt potent Liquors, yet <lb/>ſtill more Penetrating, and Efficacious, <w
            part="I">ac-</w><lb/><w part="F">cording</w> to the following Compoſition; of <lb/>this
            <hi rend="italic">Aurum Potabile,</hi> Extracted without <lb/>Fire ℔vi, <hi
            rend="italic">Aurum Fulminans,</hi> precipiated by <lb/>Oil of Tartar, which is better,
          the Chryſtals <lb/>of Gold, as taught hereafter to prepare ℥ij, <lb/>Choice Pearl ℥iv,
          Sugar-Candy ℔iv, <w part="I">Am-</w><lb/><w part="F">bergreeſe</w> ℥ij, Musk ℥ſs. Saffron
          ℥iv, <w part="I">Spi-</w><lb/><w part="F">rit</w> of Salt, doubly-Extracted ℔i, Spirit of
          <lb/>Wine dephlegmated ℔iv, pour this upon the <lb/>Ambergreeſe, Musk and Saffron to
          Extract <lb/>a Tincture by a gentle Heat; then diſſolve <lb/>the Sugar in Spirit of Honey;
          the Gold <lb/>and Pearl will come to an Eaſie <w part="I">Diſſoluti-</w><lb/><w part="F"
            >on</w> in Spirit of Salt; ſo that in eight <lb/>Days time you will have each of them <w
            part="I">di-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſtinctly</w> prepared in order for a Mixture,
          <lb/>which you are to make in a double <w part="I">Cucur-</w><lb/><w part="F">bit</w>,
          well luted in the Junctures, and <w part="I">bu-</w><lb/><w part="F">ried</w> in a Sand
          Furnace, for forty Days, <lb/>during which time a regular Circulation <lb/>is to be
          perform'd, at laſt Decant from <lb/>thence a clear limpid Liquor, which keep in <lb/>Glaſs
          Viols cloſe ſtop't. The Doſe is from <lb/>two Drops to a Dram; this is the moſt
          <lb/>powerful Corroborative in the <hi rend="italic">Plague,</hi> in <w part="I"
            >Hy-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſterick</w> Suffocations, Faintings, Vertigo's and
          <lb/>Flatulent Diſorders of the Stomach and Bowels. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Chrystals</hi> of Gold are made thus. Take <lb/>of Leaf
          Gold, what you pleaſe, pour thereon <pb xml:id="page_38" n="39"/><lb/>a double or triple
          Part of pure Spirit of <lb/>Salt rectified, make a Diſſolution, and <w part="I"
            >Co-</w><lb/><w part="F">hobate</w> ſix or eight times in an Alembick, <lb/>with an Hole
          quite through the Head of <lb/>it, at laſt force the matter over by a ſtrong <lb/>Fire,
          and the Chryſtals will aſcend to the <lb/>Neck of the Veſſel, theſe Chryſtals are <w
            part="I">diſ-</w><lb/><w part="F">ſolvable</w> in almoſt any Liquor, and to be
          <lb/>ſeparated again by Spirit of Salt, and reduc'd <lb/>to their priſtine Form. </p>
        <p rend="indent"><lb/><hi rend="sc">Thus</hi> Gentlemen, I have given you a <lb/>a ſhort
          Specimen of my deſign'd <w part="I">Reforma-</w><lb/><w part="F">tion</w> of your <hi
            rend="italic">London Diſpenſatory,</hi> and Hope <lb/>as it will be Uſeful to the
          Publick, ſo it will <lb/>meet with a Candid Reception, and hearty <lb/>Approbation from
          your learned Society, <lb/>which is the utmoſt Ambition, of <w part="I">Gentle-</w><lb/><w
            part="F">men</w>, with all </p>
        <lb/>
        <dateline>Die 4 is <lb/>xiij, Ap. <lb/>1721. </dateline>
        <signed><lb/><hi rend="italic">Duty and Reſpect, <lb/>Your moſt Humble, <lb/>moſt Devoted
            and moſt <lb/>Obedient Servant,</hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="size(1.7) sc">J. Browne</hi>. </signed>
        <trailer rend="italic align-center"><lb/>FINIS. </trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
