<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> LMEMT Corpus - Smith: The Compleat Housewife</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Eliza Smith</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">The Compleat HOUSEWIFE: OR, Accomplished Gentlewoman's COMPANION:
              Being a Collection of upwards of Five Hundred of the most approved Receipts in
              Cookery, Pastry, Confectionary, Preserving, Pickles, Cakes, Creams, Jellies, Made
              Wines, Cordials. With Copper Plates curiously engraven for the regular Disposition or
              Placing the various Dishes and Courses. And also BILLS of Fare for every Month in the
              Year. To which is added, A Collection of near Two Hundred Family Receipts of
              Medicines; viz. Drinks, Syrups, Salves, Ointments, and various other Things of
              sovereign and approved Efficacy in most Distempers, Pains, Aches, Wounds, Sores,
              &amp;c. never before made publick; fit either for private Families, or such
              publick-spirited Gentlewomen as would be beneficent to their poor Neighbours.</title>
            <edition n="2"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T122321</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T122321"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Pemberton, at the Golden Buck, overagainst St.
                  Dunstan's Church in Fleet-Street, M.DCC.XXVIII.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1728</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="15"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="318"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="20"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107271552</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Recipe collections"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="15"/>
    <body>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="255"/>
      <div type="section">
        <pb n="256"/>
        <head rend="align-center size(1.5)">
          <lb/>Medicines and Salves. </head>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To cure the Rickets. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(3)">O</hi>PEN a Vein in both Ears between the <lb/>junctures, mix a
            little Aqua-vitæ with the <lb/>Blood, and with it anoint the Breaſt, Sides <lb/>and
            Neck; then take 3 ounces of the green Oint- <lb/>ment, and warm a little of it in a
            Spoon, and <lb/>anoint the Wriſts and Ancles as hot as it may be <lb/>endured: do this
            for 9 Nights juſt before Bed-time; <lb/>ſhift not the Shirt all the time. If the Veins
            do <lb/>not appear, rub it with a little Lint dipp'd in Aqua- <lb/>vitæ, or elſe cauſe
            the Child to cry, and that will <lb/>make the Veins more viſible, and bleed the better.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To make the Drink. </head>
          <p>
            <hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a quart of Spring-water, of Liver-wort <lb/>one handful,
            Liquoriſh, Anniſeeds, Coriander- <lb/>ſeeds, ſweet Fennel-ſeeds, and Harts-horn, of each
              <pb n="257"/>
            <lb/>an equal quantity, 40 Raiſins of the Sun ſton'd, <lb/>14 Figs; boil all theſe
            together till one half is con- <lb/>ſumed, then put in 3 ſpoonfuls of Honey, and
            <lb/>boil it a little more; let it ſtand till 'tis cold and <lb/>ſtrain it out, and put
            in 2 ſpoonfuls of Syrup of <lb/>Gillyflowers, and bottle it up. Take 2 or 3 ſpoon-
            <lb/>fuls Morning and Evening. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>The Green Ointment. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Rue, Camomile, Hyſop, Hogs-Fennel, <lb/>red Fennel,
            Roſemary, Bays, Lady's-mantle, <lb/>Paul's-betony, Water-betony, Balm, Nep, Vale-
            <lb/>rian, Mallows, Nightſhade, Plantane, Comfry, <lb/>Adders-tongue, Roman-wormwood,
            Common- <lb/>wormwood, Vervain, Clary, Agrimony, red <lb/>Sage, Ground-ivy, Feaver-few,
            Self-heal, Meli- <lb/>lote, Bramble-tops, Marſhmallows, Sanicle, Rib- <lb/>wort,
            Mayweed, of each of theſe 2 large handfuls; <lb/>pick and chop them, then take 4 pound
            of Butter <lb/>unwaſh'd, and 3 pound of Boars-Greaſe; melt them <lb/>together and put in
            the Herbs, and let it boil 2 <lb/>hours; then ſtrain it out, let it ſtand a little, and
            <lb/>put it in Pots for uſe. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>Another way to cure the Rickets. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE the Drink thus; Take Polipodium grow- <lb/>ing upon a
            Church or Oak 3 ounces ſcrap'd, <lb/>Liver-wort and Harts-tongue, of each a good
            <lb/>handful; Betony 20 Leaves, white Hore-hound <lb/>and Nep, of each 4 tops; boil all
            theſe together <lb/>in 3 quarts of ſweet Wort, till it is conſum'd to 2 <lb/>quarts;
            then ſtrain it, and when 'tis cold, put to it <lb/>2 quarts of middling Wort, ſo let it
            work toge- <lb/>ther; then put it in a little Veſſel, and when it has <lb/>done working,
            take half a quarter of an ounce of <lb/>Rhubarb ſliced very thin; put it in a little
            Linnen <pb n="258"/>
            <lb/>Bag, with a Stone in it to keep it from ſwimming, <lb/>and hang it in the Veſſel;
            and when 'tis 3 days old, <lb/>let the Child drink of it a quarter of a pint in the
            <lb/>Morning, as much in the Afternoon, at Four a <lb/>Clock, or when the Child will
            take it. You muſt <lb/>likewiſe anoint the Child Morning and Night with <lb/>this
            following Ointment: Take Butter in the Month <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">May</hi>, as ſoon
            as it's taken out of the Churn, and <lb/>waſh it with the Dew of Wheat; to a pound of
            <lb/>Butter, take a handful of red Sage, as much of <lb/>Rue, Camomile, and of ſowed
            Hyſop; boil all <lb/>theſe in the Butter, and ſcum it till 'tis boiled <lb/>clear; then
            ſtrain it out, and keep it in a Gallypot <lb/>for uſe. You muſt anoint the Reins of the
            Back <lb/>and the Ribs, ſtroking it downwards, and upon <lb/>the Small of the Belly, and
            ſwing the Child often <lb/>with the Heels upwards. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To make Charity-Oil. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Poplar Buds in the beginning of <hi rend="italic"
              >May</hi>
            <lb/>one handful, and put them into a pint and <lb/>half of Oil, and half a pint of
            Aqua-vitæ, and cover <lb/>them cloſe, and let them ſtand till the following <lb/>Herbs
            are in ſeaſon; then add to your Buds, Be- <lb/>tony, Charity, Sanicle, the tops of St.
              <hi rend="italic">John</hi>'s Wort; <lb/>when blown; Adders-tongue, Comfry, Self-heal,
            <lb/>Balm, Southern-wood, Penny-royal, Flowers of <lb/>red Sage, Parſley, Clown's
            all-Heal, Balſam, Knot- <lb/>graſs, Sweet-marjoram, Lavender-Cotton, red <lb/>Roſe-buds,
            Camomile, Lavender-tops when blown, <lb/>of each of theſe Herbs a ſmall handful; but of
            <lb/>Poplar-buds, red Roſe-buds, and Adders-tongue, <lb/>double the quantity; gather the
            Herbs in dry <lb/>Weather, and wipe them clean with a Cloth; ſhred <lb/>them pretty
            groſly before you put them in, ſo let <lb/>them ſteep in a ſtone Pot; when all is in,
            cover it <lb/>very cloſe, then ſet them on the Fire in a Skillet, <pb n="259"/>
            <lb/>let them ſimmer with a ſlow Fire five or ſix hours, <lb/>then ſtrain it out. This
            Oil is good for any <lb/>green Wound, Bruiſe, Burn, or Ach, and for <lb/>Bruiſes inward,
            taking a ſpoonful in a little warm <lb/>Sack; and for any outward Swelling warm it, and
            <lb/>anoint the Part affected. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the Gripes. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a glaſs of Sack warmed, and diſſolve <lb/>in it as much
              <hi rend="italic">Venice</hi>-Treacle, or Diaſ- <lb/>cordium, as a Hazel-Nut, drink it
            off going to <lb/>Bed; cover warm. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To ſtay a Looſeneſs. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a very good Nutmeg, and prick it full <lb/>of holes, and
            toaſt it on the Point of a <lb/>Kniſe; then boil it in Milk till much be conſumed;
            <lb/>then eat the Milk with the Nutmeg powdered in <lb/>it, in a few times it will ſtop.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the Strangury. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE half a pint of Plantane-water, one <lb/>ounce of white
            Sugar-candy finely pow- <lb/>dered, two ſpoonfuls of Sallet-Oil, and the Juice <lb/>of a
            Lemon; beat all theſe together very well, <lb/>and drink it off. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For a Drought in a Fever. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of Sal-prunella one ounce, and diſſolve <lb/>it in
            Spring-water, and put as much Sugar <lb/>to it as will ſweeten it; ſimmer it over the
            Fire <lb/>till 'tis a Syrup, and put ſome into Poſſet-Drink, <lb/>and take it two or
            three times a day, or when <lb/>very thirſty. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="260"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Plaiſter for an Ague. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE right <hi rend="italic">Venice</hi> Turpentine, and mix
            with <lb/>it the Powder of white Hellebore-roots, till <lb/>'tis ſtiff enough to ſpread
            on Leather. It muſt be <lb/>laid all over the Wriſt, and over the Ball of the <lb/>Thumb
            ſix hours before the Fit comes. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For a Chin-Cough. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a ſpoonful of Woodlice, and bruiſe them, <lb/>and mix
            them with Breaſt-milk, and take <lb/>them three or four Mornings according as you find
            <lb/>Benefit. It will cure; but ſome muſt take it lon- <lb/>ger than others. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To take off Blackneſs by a Fall. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">R</hi>UB it well with a cold Tallow-Candle as <lb/>ſoon as 'tis
            bruiſed, and this will take off <lb/>the Blackneſs. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To break a Boil. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE the yolk of a new-laid Egg, ſome Honey <lb/>and Wheat-
            flower, and mix it well together <lb/>and ſpread it on a Rag, and lay it on cold. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Poultice for a hard Swelling. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">B</hi>OIL the fineſt Wheat-flour in Cream till <lb/>'tis pretty
            thick, then take it off and put in <lb/>Mallows chopt, ſtir it and apply it as hot as
            can <lb/>be endured; dreſs it twice a day, and make freſh <lb/>every time. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="261"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To ſtay Vomiting. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Aſh-leaves, and boil them in Vinegar <lb/>and Water, and
            apply them hot to the Sto- <lb/>mach; do this often. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Poultice for a ſore Breaſt, Leg or <lb/>Arm. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">B</hi>OIL Wheat-flour in ſtrong Ale very well, <lb/>and pretty
            thick, then take it off and ſcrape <lb/>in ſome Boars-greaſe; let it not boil after the
            <lb/>Greaſe is in; ſtir it well, and apply it hot. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Salve for a Blaſt, Burn or Scald. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE <hi rend="italic">May</hi> Butter freſh out of the
            Churn, <lb/>neither waſh'd nor ſalted, and put into it a <lb/>good quantity of the green
            inner rind of Elder, <lb/>and put it in a Pipkin, and ſet that in a Pot of boil-
            <lb/>ing Water; let it infuſe a Day or two, then <lb/>ſtrain it out, and keep it in a
            Pot for uſe. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For ſpitting Blood. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of Cinnabar of Antimony one Ounce, <lb/>and mix it with
            two ounces of Conſerve of <lb/>red Roſes, and take as much as a Nutmeg Night <lb/>and
            Morning. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To know if a Child has Worms or not. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a piece of white Leather, and peck it <lb/>full of holes
            with your Kniſe, and rub it <lb/>with Wormwood, and ſpread Honey on it, and <lb/>ſtrow
            the Powder of Aloes Socatrina on it; lay <pb n="262"/>
            <lb/>it on the Child's Navel when he goes to Bed, and <lb/>if he has Worms, the Plaiſter
            will ſtick ſaſt, and <lb/>if he have not it will fall. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To ſtop Vomiting. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE half a Pint of Mint-water, one ounce <lb/>of Syrup of
            Violets, a quarter of an ounce <lb/>of Mithridate, and half an ounce of Syrup of
            <lb/>Roſes; mix theſe well together, and let the Party <lb/>take two Spoonfuls firſt,
            and then one Spoonful <lb/>after every Vomiting till 'tis ſtay'd. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To Cure the Tooth-ach. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">L</hi>ET the Party that is troubled with the Tooth- <lb/>ach lie
            on the contrary ſide, and drop three <lb/>drops of the Juice of Rue into the Ear on that
            ſide <lb/>the Tooth acheth, and let it remain an Hour or <lb/>two and it will remove the
            Pain. If a Needle is <lb/>run thro' a Wood-Louſe, and immediately touch <lb/>the aching
            Tooth with that Needle, it will ceaſe <lb/>to ach. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A rare Mouth-Water. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Roſemary, Rue, Celandine, Plantane, <lb/>Bramble-leaves,
            Woodbine-leaves, and Sage, <lb/>of each one handful; beat them, and ſteep them in <lb/>a
            Quart of the beſt White-wine Vinegar two Days <lb/>and Nights, then preſs it well and
            ſtrain it, and <lb/>put to it ſix ounces of Alum, and as much Honey, <lb/>and boil them
            a little together ſoftly till the Alum <lb/>is conſumed; when 'tis cold keep it for uſe.
          </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="263"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To Cure a Cancer. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a Dram of the Powder of Crabs-Claws <lb/>finely ſearc'd
            and made into Paſte with <lb/>damask Roſe-water, and dry'd in Pellets of Lozen-
            <lb/>ges; powder the Lozenges as you uſe them, and <lb/>drink the Powder in Whey every
            Morning faſting. <lb/>If there be a Sore, and it is raw, anoint it with a <lb/>Salve
            made of Dock-roots and freſh Butter, make <lb/>a Seaton or Iſſue in the Neck; keep a low
            Diet, <lb/>keep from any thing that is ſalt, ſour, or ſtrong. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To Cure the Joint-Evil. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE good ſtore of Elder-leaves, and diſtil <lb/>them in a
            cold ſtill; let the Perſon drink every <lb/>Morning and Evening half a Pint of this
            Water, <lb/>and waſh the Sores with it Morning and Evening, <lb/>firſt warming it a
            little, and lay freſh Elder-leaves <lb/>on the Sores, and in a little time you will find
            they <lb/>will dry up: but be ſure to follow it exactly, it <lb/>has cured when all
            other Remedies have failed. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the Green-Sickneſs. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Centaury the Leſs, and Wormwood and
            <lb/>Roſemary-flowers of each one handful, Gen- <lb/>tian-root one Dram, Coriander-ſeeds
            two Drams; <lb/>boil theſe in a quart of Water, ſweeten it with Sy- <lb/>rup of Steel,
            and take four or five Spoonfuls in the <lb/>Morning, and as much in the Afternoon. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To take off Freckles. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Bean-flower Water, or Elder-flower <lb/>Water, or <hi
              rend="italic">May</hi> Dew gathered from Corn, of <lb/>either the quantity of four
            Spoonfuls, and add to it <pb n="264"/>
            <lb/>one Spoonful of Oil of Tartar very new drawn; <lb/>mix it well together, and often
            waſh the Face with <lb/>it: let it dry on. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To make Pomatum. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE almoſt a Dram of white Wax, two <lb/>Drams of
            Sperma-Cete, one Ounce of Oil <lb/>of bitter Almonds, ſlice your Wax very thin, and
            <lb/>put it in a Gallipot, and put the Pot in a Skillet of <lb/>boiling Water: when the
            Wax is melted, put in <lb/>your Sperma-Cete, and juſt ſtir it together; then <lb/>put in
            the Oil of Almonds; after that take it off <lb/>the Fire, and out of the Skillet, and
            ſtir it till <lb/>cold with a Bone Kniſe; then beat it up in Roſe- <lb/>water till 'tis
            white, keep it in Water, and change <lb/>the Wonce a Day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Salve for a Sprain. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a quarter of a Pound of Virgin's-Wax, <lb/>a quarter of
            a pound of Frankincenſe, half <lb/>a pound of Burgamy-pitch, melt them well toge-
            <lb/>ther, ſtirring them all the while till they are mel- <lb/>ted, then give them a
            good boil, and ſtrain them <lb/>into Water; work it well into Rolls, and keep it
            <lb/>for uſe: the more 'tis work'd the better 'tis. Spread <lb/>it on Leather. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A rare green Oil for Aches and Bruiſes. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a Pottle of Oil of Olives, and put it in- <lb/>to a
            Stone Pot of a Gallon, with a narrow <lb/>Mouth , then take Southernwood, Wormwood,
            Sage, <lb/>and Camomile, of each 4 handfuls, a quarter of a <lb/>Peck of red Roſe-buds,
            the white cut from them; <pb n="265"/>
            <lb/>ſhred them together groſly, and put them into the <lb/>Oil, and once a Day for 9 or
            10 Days ſtir them <lb/>well, and when the Lavender-ſpike is ripe, put 4 <lb/>handfuls of
            the Tops in, and let it ſtand 3 or 4 Days <lb/>longer, and covered very cloſe; then boil
            them an <lb/>Hour upon a ſlow Fire, ſtirring it often; then put <lb/>to it a quarter of
            a Pint of the ſtrongeſt Aqua-Vitæ, <lb/>and let it boil an Hour more ; then ſtrain it
            thro' <lb/>a coarſe Cloth, and let it ſtand till 'tis cold, and <lb/>keep it in Glaſſes
            for uſe; warm a little in a Spoon <lb/>or Saucer, and bathe the part affected. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To take out Spots of the Small-Pox. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE half an ounce of Oil of Tartar, and as <lb/>much Oil of
            bitter Almonds, mix it toge- <lb/>ther, and with a fine Rag daub it often on the Face
            <lb/>and Hands, before the Air has penetrated into the <lb/>Skin or Fleſh. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the Cholick. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a dram and half of Dr. <hi rend="italic">Holland</hi>'s
            Pow- <lb/>der, and mix it in a little Sack, and take it <lb/>and drink a Glaſs of Sack
            after it. It gives preſent <lb/>eaſe. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the Scurvy. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a pound of Guaiacum-Bark, and half <lb/>a pound of
            Saſſafras, and a quarter of a pound <lb/>of Liquoriſh; boil all theſe in 3 quarts of
            Water <lb/>till it comes to 3 Pints, and when 'tis cold, put it <lb/>in a Veſſel with 2
            Gallons of Ale; in 3 or 4 Days <lb/>'tis fit to drink; and drink no other Drink for 6
            <lb/>or 12 months, according to the Violence of the <lb/>Diſtemper. It will certainly
            cure. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="266"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the Jaundice. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE ſome Tares (ſuch as you ſeed Pigeons <lb/>with) and dry
            them in an Oven, and beat <lb/>them to Powder, and ſift them, and take a Spoon- <lb/>ful
            of that Powder in a Morning faſting, and drink <lb/>half a Pint of White Wine after it;
            and do this for <lb/>3 Mornings together, and it will cure tho' very <lb/>far gone. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For Corns on the Feet. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE the Yeaſt of Beer (not of Ale) and <lb/>ſpread it on a
            linen Rag, and apply it to <lb/>the part affected; renew it once a Day for three <lb/>or
            four Weeks. It will cure. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For Chill-Blains. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">R</hi>OAST a Turnip ſoft, beat it to maſh, and <lb/>apply it as
            hot as can be endured to the part <lb/>affected. Let it lie on two or three Days, and
            re- <lb/>peat it two or three times. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To ſtop Bleeding inwardly. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE two Drams of Henbane-ſeed, and the <lb/>like of white
            Poppy-ſeed, beat them up with <lb/>Conſerve of Roſes, and give the quantity of a
            <lb/>Nutmeg at a time; or take twelve handfuls of Plan- <lb/>tane-leaves, and ſix ounces
            of freſh Comfry-roots; <lb/>beat theſe and ſtrain out the Juice, and add to it <lb/>ſome
            fine Sugar, and drink it off. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="267"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To ſtop Vomiting. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a large Nutmeg, grate away half of it, <lb/>and then
            toaſt the flat ſide till the Oil ouze <lb/>out; then clap it to the Pit of the Stomach.
            Let it <lb/>lie ſo long as 'tis warm, repeat it often till cured. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To kill a Tetter. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Flower of Brimſtone, Ginger, and burnt <lb/>Allum, a
            like quantity; mix it with freſh <lb/>Butter unſalted, anoint as hot as can be endur'd
            <lb/>at Bed-time, in the Morning waſh it off with Ce- <lb/>landine-water heated; while
            this is continued, the <lb/>Party muſt ſometimes take Cordials to keep the <lb/>Humour
            from going inward. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>An Ointment for a Blaſt. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Velvet-leaves and wipe them clean, and <lb/>chop them
            ſmall, and put them to unſalted <lb/>Butter out of the Churn, and boil them gently till
            <lb/>the goodneſs is out of the Leaves, then ſtrain it in- <lb/>to a Gallipot, and keep
            it for uſe. Lay Velvet <lb/>Leaves over the part after 'tis anointed. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Poultice to ripen Tumours. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE half a pound of Figs, two ounces of <lb/>white
            Lilly-roots, two ounces of Bean-flower <lb/>or Meal; boil theſe in Water till it comes
            to a <lb/>Poultice; ſpread it thick on a Cloth, apply it warm <lb/>and ſhift it as often
            as it grows dry. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="268"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the Teeth. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a Pint of Spring-water, put to it ſix <lb/>Spoonfuls of
            the beſt Brandy, waſh the Mouth <lb/>often with it, and in a Morning roll a bit of Allum
            <lb/>a little while in the Mouth. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For a Drought in a Fever. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>AKE Barley-water, ſweeten it with Syrup <lb/>of Violets, and
            tincture it with Spirit of <lb/>Vitriol; let them drink ſometimes of this; put
            <lb/>Sal-prunella in Beer or Poſſet-drink, and ſometimes <lb/>drink of that, and if they
            are ſick or faint, give <lb/>a Spoonful of Cordial in a Diſh of Tea. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Powder that has reſtored Sight when <lb/>almoſt loſt. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of Betony, Celandine, Saxafrage, Eye- <lb/>bright,
            Penny-royal and Leviſticum, of <lb/>each one handful; of Aniſeeds and Cinnamon of
            <lb/>each half an ounce; take alſo of Grains of Para- <lb/>dice, Ginger, Hyſop, Parſley,
            Origany, Oſier <lb/>of the Mountain, of each one Dram; Galengal <lb/>and Sugar, of each
            one Ounce: make all into a <lb/>fine Powder, and eat of it every Day with your <lb/>Meat
            ſuch a quantity as you us'd to eat of Salt, and <lb/>inſtead of Salt; Oſier, you muſt
            have that at the <lb/>Phyſick Garden. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For a Cough ſettled on the Stomach. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE half a pound of Figs ſliced, Raiſins of <lb/>the Sun
            ſtoned as many, and a ſtick of Liquo- <lb/>riſh ſcraped and fliced; a ſew Aniſeeds and
            ſome <pb n="268"/>
            <lb/>Hyſop waſh'd clean: Put all theſe in a quart of <lb/>Spring-water; boil it till it
            comes to a pint; then <lb/>ſtrain it, and ſweeten it with white Sugar-candy. <lb/>Take
            two or three <unclear>Spoonfuls</unclear> of it Morning and <lb/>Night, and when the
            Cough troubles you. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To Cure a Dropſy. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of Horſe-radiſh Roots, flic'd the long <lb/>way as thin
            as you can, two ounces; ſweet <lb/>Fennel-roots ſliced, two ounces; ſweet Fennel-ſeeds
            <lb/>beaten, two ounces; the tops of Thyme, Winter- <lb/>ſavory, ſweet Marjoram,
            Water-creſſes and Nettle- <lb/>tops, of each one handful, wiped and ſhred ſmall.
            <lb/>Boil theſe in three pints of Spring-water, a quart <lb/>of Sack, and a pint of
            White-wine; cover it cloſe, <lb/>and let it boil till half be conſumed; then take it
            <lb/>off the Fire, and let it ſtand to ſettle three hours; <lb/>then ſtrain it out, and
            to every Draught put in one <lb/>ounce of the Syrup of the five Roots, which you
            <lb/>may have ready made at an Apothecary's; take this <lb/>in the Morning faſting, and
            at three a Clock in the <lb/>Afternoon, and faſt three hours after it. If the Par-
            <lb/>ty have the Scurvy, (which uſually goes with the <lb/>Dropſy) then add a ſpoonful
            of the Juice of Scur- <lb/>vygraſs to each Draught. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For ſtuffing in the Lungs. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE white Sugar-candy, powder'd and ſift- <lb/>ed, two
            ounces, <hi rend="italic">China</hi>-roots, powder'd and <lb/>ſifted, one ounce; Flower
            of Brimſtone, one ounce. <lb/>Mix theſe with Conſerve of Roſes, or the Pap of an
            <lb/>Apple; and take the bigneſs of a Walnut in the <lb/>Morning, faſting an hour after
            it; and the laſt at <lb/>Night, an hour after you have eaten or drank. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="270"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To cure ſpitting of Blood, if a Vein is <lb/><unclear>broken</unclear>. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Mice-dung beaten to Powder, as much <lb/>as will lie on
            a Six-pence; and put it in a <lb/>quarter of a pint of the Juice of Plantane, with a
            <lb/>little Sugar: Give it in the Morning faſting, and <lb/>at Night going to Bed.
            Continue this ſome time, <lb/>and it will make whole, and cure. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To give eaſe in a violent Fit of the <lb/>Stone. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a quart of Milk, and two handfuls of <lb/>dry'd Sage, a
            pennyworth of Hempſeed, one <lb/>ounce of white Sugar-candy: Boil all theſe toge-
            <lb/>ther a quarter of an hour, and then put in half a <lb/>pint of Rheniſh-wine. When
            the Curd is taken off, <lb/>with the Ingredients, put it in a Bag, and apply it <lb/>to
            the grieved part; and of the Liquor drink a good <lb/>Glaſs full. Let both be as hot as
            can be endured. <lb/>If there is not Eaſe the firſt time, warm it again, <lb/>and uſe
            it: It ſeldom ſails. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the Strangury. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE three ſpoonfuls of the Juice of Camo- <lb/>mile, in a
            ſmall Glaſs of white Wine, thrice <lb/>a day, for three days together. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To procure eaſy Labour. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE half a pound of Figs, half a pound of <lb/>Raiſins of
            the Sun, ſtoned; 4 ounces of Li- <lb/>quoriſh, ſcraped and ſliced; one ſpoonful of Anni-
              <pb n="271"/>
            <lb/>ſeeds bruiſed; boil all theſe in 2 quarts of Spring <lb/>Water till one Pint is
            waſted; then ſtrain it out, <lb/>and drink a quarter of a Pint of it Morning and
            <lb/>Evening 6 Weeks before the time. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To procure ſpeedy Delivery when the <lb/>Throws are gone. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE half a Dram of Borax powdered, and <lb/>mixed with a
            glaſs of White-wine, ſome Su- <lb/>gar, and a little Cinnamon-water; if it does no
            <lb/>good the firſt time, try it again two Hours after, <lb/>ſo likewiſe the third time.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To bring the After-Birth. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">G</hi>IVE 30 or 35 drops of Oil of Juniper in a <lb/>good Glaſs of
            Sack. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To prevent After-Pains. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE half an ounce of large Nutmegs, and <lb/>toaſt them
            before the Fire, and 1 ounce of <lb/>the beſt Cinnamon, and beat them together; then
            <lb/>mix it with the Whites of two Eggs, beating it <lb/>together in a Porringer, and
            take every Morning <lb/>in Bed as much as will lie on the point of a Kniſe, <lb/>and ſo
            at Night; and drink after it the following <lb/>Caudle. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take a quarter of a pint of <hi rend="italic">Alicant</hi> Wine or Tent, <lb/>a
            quarter of a pint of red Roſe-water, and a quar- <lb/>ter of a pint of Plantane-water;
            mingle all three <lb/>together, and beat 3 new-laid Eggs, Yolks and <lb/>Whites, and
            make a Caudle of them; put into it <lb/>2 ounces of double-reſin'd Sugar, a quarter of
            an <lb/>ounce of Cinnamon; you muſt boil the Cinnamon <lb/>in the Wine and Water before
            the Eggs are in; <pb n="272"/>
            <lb/>and after all is mixed, put to it half a Dram of the <lb/>Powder of Knotgraſs; take
            of this 6 ſpoonfuls <lb/>Morning and Evening after the Electuary. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>Another for the ſame. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a ſmall quantity of Bole-Armoniac, <lb/>and boil it in
            new Milk. Let the Party <lb/>drink of it Morning and Evening, if it be either <lb/>a
            Woman with Child, or in Child-bed. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take alſo ſome Hog's-dung, and wrap it in a fine <lb/>linnen Rag, warm it well, and
            put it to the lower <lb/>part of the Belly, and it will ſtop immediately. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To ſtop Floodings. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE the White of an Egg, and beat it well <lb/>with 4 or 5
            ſpoonfuls of red Roſe-water, <lb/>and drink it off Morning and Night 9 Mornings
            <lb/>together; it has cured when all other things have <lb/>failed. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Let the party often take Iſing-glaſs boiled or <lb/>diſſolved in warm new Milk, a
            Pint at a time. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Plaiſter for a Weakneſs in the Back. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Plantane, Comfry, Knotgraſs, Shep- <lb/>herds-purſe, of
            each one handful; ſtamp them <lb/>ſmall, and boil them in a pound of Oil of Roſes,
            <lb/>and a little Vinegar; when 'tis well boil'd ſtrain it, <lb/>and ſet it on the Fire
            again, and put into it four <lb/>ounces of Wax, one ounce of Chalk, Bole-Ar- <lb/>moniac
            one ounce, and Terra-ſigillata one ounce; <lb/>boil all well, keeping it ſtill ſtirring,
            then cool it, <lb/>and make it into Rolls, and keep it for uſe; ſpread <lb/>it on
            Leather when you lay it to the Back. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="273"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Drink for the ſame. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE 4 Roots of Comfry, and of Knot-grafs, <lb/>and Clary one
            handful, a ſprig of Roſemary, <lb/>a little Galangal, a good quantity of Cinnamon
            <lb/>and Nutmeg ſliced, the Pith of a Chine of an <lb/>Ox. Stamp and boil all theſe in a
            quart of Muſca- <lb/>dine, then ſtrain it, and put in 6 Yolks of Eggs; <lb/>ſweeten the
            Caudle to your Taſte with double-re- <lb/>fined Sugar, and drink a good Draught Morning
            <lb/>and Evening. Take of Crocus Martis, and Con- <lb/>ſerve of red Roſes mixed together
            3 or 4 times a day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For a Flux. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a Pint of new Milk, and diſſolve in it <lb/>half a
            quarter of a pound of Loaf-Sugar, as <lb/>much Mithridate as the bigneſs of a Walnut;
            give <lb/>this for a Gliſter moderately warm; repeat it once <lb/>or twice if there be
            occaſion. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the falling down of the Fundament. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Ginger and ſlice it, and put it in a <lb/>little Pan,
            heat it by clear well kindled <lb/>Coals, and put it in a Cloſeſtool. Let the Party
            <lb/>ſit over it, and receive the Fume; caſt in the <lb/>Ginger by little and little,
            and keep warm. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To increaſe Milk in Nurſes. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>AKE Gruel with Lentils, and let the Par- <lb/>ty drink
            freely of it; or elſe boil them in <lb/>Poſſet-drink, which they like beſt. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="274"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A good Purge. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>NFUSE an ounce of Sena in a Pint of Water <lb/>till half be
            conſumed; when 'tis cold, add to <lb/>it one ounce of Syrup of Roſes, and one ounce
            <lb/>of Syrup of Buckthorn; mix them well together. <lb/>This quantity makes two ſtrong
            Purges for either <lb/>Man or Woman, and 4 for a Child. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To prevent Miſcarrying. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of Dragons-Blood the weight of a Sil- <lb/>ver
            Two-pence, and a Dram of red Coral, the <lb/>weight of two Barley-corns of Ambergreaſe,
            the <lb/>weight of 3 Barley-corns of <hi rend="italic">Eaſt-India</hi> Bezoar; <lb/>make
            all theſe into a very fine Powder, and mix <lb/>them well together, and keep them cloſe
            in a Box; <lb/>and if you are frighted, or need it, take as much at <lb/>a time as will
            lie on a Penny, and keep very ſtill <lb/>and quiet. Take it in a Caudle made with Muſ-
            <lb/>cadine or Tent, and the ſhucks of Almonds dry'd <lb/>and beaten to Powder, and
            thicken it with Yolks <lb/>of Eggs. Take it in a Morning faſting, and at <lb/>Night
            going to Bed; this do till you are out of <lb/>Danger, and lay the following Plaiſter to
            the Back. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take <hi rend="italic">Venice</hi> Turpentine, and mix with it Bole- <lb/>Armoniac,
            and ſpread it on black-brown Paper <lb/>the length and breadth of a hand, and lay it to
            <lb/>the Small of the Back, keeping Bed. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the Green-Sickneſs. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE an ounce of the Filings of Steel, or ruſty <lb/>Iron
            beaten to Powder, and mix it with two <lb/>ounces of the flower of Brimſtone; then mix
            it up <lb/>into an Electuary with Treacle; the Party muſt <lb/>take the quantity of a
            Nutmeg in the Morning ſaſt- <pb n="275"/>
            <lb/>ing, and at 4 in the Afternoon, and continue it <lb/>till cured. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To procure a good Colour. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Germander, Rue, Fumitory, of each <lb/>a good handful,
            one Pennyworth of Saffron <lb/>tied up in a Rag, half a pound of blue Currants
            <lb/>bruiſed; ſtamp the Herbs, and infuſe all theſe In- <lb/>gredients in 3 Pints of
            Sack over a gentle Fire <lb/>till half be conſumed; drink a quarter of a Pint
            <lb/>Morning and Evening, and walk after it; repeat <lb/>this quantity once or twice. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>You may add a ſpoonful of the following Syrup <lb/>to every Draught. Take 3 ounces
            of the Filings <lb/>of Steel, and put it in a glaſs Bottle with a Dram <lb/>of Mace and
            as much Cinnamon, pour on them a <lb/>quart of the beſt White-wine, ſtop it up cloſe,
            <lb/>and let it ſtand 14 Days, ſhaking the Bottle eve- <lb/>ry Day; then ſtrain it out
            into another Bottle, and <lb/>put 2 pound of fine Loaf-ſugar to it finely beaten;
            <lb/>let it ſtand till the Sugar is diſſolved without ſtir- <lb/>ring it; then clear it
            into another Bottle, and <lb/>keep it for uſe. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A bitter Draught. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of the Leaves of Roman-Wormwood, <lb/>the tops of
            Centaury and St. <hi rend="italic">John's-wort</hi>, of <lb/>each a ſmall handful, Roots
            of Gentian ſliced 2 <lb/>Drams, Caraway-ſeeds half an ounce; infuſe theſe <lb/>in half a
            Pint of Rheniſh, and three Pints of <lb/>White-wine, for 4 or 5 Days; take a quarter of
            a <lb/>Pint in a Morning, filling up the Bottle, and it <lb/>will ſerve 2 or 3 months.
          </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="276"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the Piles. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE calcin'd Oyſter-ſhells, mix it with Ho- <lb/>ney, and
            anoint the Part tenderly Night and <lb/>Morning. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>Another for the ſame. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a Sheet of Lead, and have a piece of <lb/>Lead made like
            a Slickſtone; then between <lb/>them two grind white Lead and Sallet-Oil till 'tis
            <lb/>very fine; put it in a Gallipot for uſe. If the Piles <lb/>are inward, cut a piece
            of old Tallow-Candle and <lb/>dip it in this Ointment, and put it up; if outward,
            <lb/>put ſome on a fine Rag, and put it to them. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the Hemorrhoides inflamed. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">L</hi>ET the Party dip their Finger in Balſam of <lb/>Sulphur made
            with Oil of Turpentine, and <lb/>anoint the Place 2 or 3 times a day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For Coſtiveneſs. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Virgin-Honey a quarter of a pound, and <lb/>mix it with
            as much Cream of Tartar as will <lb/>bring it to a pretty thick Electuary, of which take
            <lb/>the bigneſs of a Walnut when you pleaſe; and for <lb/>your Breakſaſt eat Watergruel
            with common Mal- <lb/>lows boiled in it, and a good piece of Butter; the <lb/>Mallows
            muſt be chopt ſmall, and eaten with the <lb/>Gruel. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To raiſe a Bliſter. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE ſeeds of Clemmatis Peregrina being bound <lb/>hard on any
            Place, will in an hour or two <lb/>raiſe a Bliſter, which you muſt cut and dreſs with
              <pb n="277"/>
            <lb/>Melilot Plaiſter, or Colewort Leaves, as other <lb/>Bliſters. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Likewiſe Leaven mix'd with a little Verjuice, <lb/>and about half a Pennyworth of
            Cantharides Flies, <lb/>and ſpread on Leather the bigneſs you pleaſe, will <lb/>in 9 or
            10 hours raiſe a Bliſter, which dreſs as <lb/>uſual. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>Plaiſter for the Feet in a Fever. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of Briony-Roots one pound, tops of <lb/>Rue a handful,
            black Soap 4 ounces, and <lb/>Bay-Salt 2 ounces; beat all theſe in a Maſh, and <lb/>out
            of this ſpread on a Cloth for both Feet, apply <lb/>it warm, and ſew Cloths over them,
            and let them <lb/>lie 12 hours; if there be occaſion, renew them 3 <lb/>times. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Drink for a Fever. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a quart of Spring-water, and boil in it <lb/>an ounce of
            burnt Harts-horn, a Nutmeg <lb/>quartered, a ſtick of Cinnamon; let it boil a quar-
            <lb/>ter of an hour; when 'tis cold ſweeten it to your <lb/>Taſte with Syrup of Lemons
            or fine Sugar, with <lb/>as many Drops of Spirit of Vitriol as will juſt <lb/>ſharpen
            it. Drink of this when you pleaſe. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>Vomit. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE 7 or 8 Daffodil-Roots, and boil them <lb/>in a Pint of
            Poſſet-drink, and in the work- <lb/>ing drink Carduus-Water a Gallon or more; your
            <lb/>Poſſet muſt be cold when you drink it, and your <lb/>Carduus-Tea muſt be
            Blood-warm: if it works too <lb/>much, put ſome Salt in a diſh of Poſſet, and drink
            <lb/>it off. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="278"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the Hickup. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE 3 or 4 preſerved Damſins in your Mouth <lb/>at a time,
            and ſwallow them by degrees. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the Cramp. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of Roſemary-leaves, and chop them very <lb/>ſmall, and
            ſew them in fine Linen, and make <lb/>into Garters, and wear them Night and Day;
            <lb/>lay a Down-pillow on your Legs in the Night. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For Weakneſs in the Hands after a Palſy. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of the tops of Roſemary, bruiſe it and <lb/>make it up
            into a Ball as big as a great Wal- <lb/>nut, and let the Party roll it up and down in
            their <lb/>Hand very often, and graſp it in the Hand till 'tis <lb/>hot: do this very
            often. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For an old Ache or Strain. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE an ounce of Lucatellus's-Balſam, and <lb/>mix it with 2
            Drams of Oil of Turpentine, <lb/>gently heat it, anoint the Place, and put new
            <lb/>Flannel on it. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the Jaundice. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE half an ounce of Rhubarb made into <lb/>Powder, and beat
            it well with two handfuls <lb/>of good Currants well cleaned; and of this E-
            <lb/>lectuary take every Morning a piece as big as a <lb/>Nutmeg for 14 or 15 Mornings
            together, or <lb/>longer if need require. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="279"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the Cholick. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE half a pint of Dr. <hi rend="italic">Stevens</hi>'s
            Water, as <lb/>much Plague-water, as much Juniper-berry- <lb/>water, and an ounce of
            powder of Rhubarb: ſhake <lb/>the Bottle, and take 4 or 5 ſpoonfuls at a time, <lb/>when
            the Fit is on you, or likely to come. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For a Burn. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>IX Lime-water with Linſeed-oil; beat it <lb/>together, and
            with a Feather anoint the <lb/>Place, and put on a Plaiſter to defend it. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To cure a Place that is ſcalded. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Linſeed-oil, and put to it as much thick <lb/>Cream;
            beat them together very well, and <lb/>keep it for uſe. Anoint the Place that is ſcalded
            <lb/>twice a day, and it will cure it. Put on it ſoft <lb/>Rags; and let nothing preſs
            on it. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>The bitter Draught. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of Gentian-root, three drams; of Camo-
            <lb/>mile-flowers, one ounce; of Roſemary-flow- <lb/>ers, one ounce; of tops of
            Centaury, tops of Ro- <lb/>man Wormwood, tops of Carduus, of each one <lb/>handful. Boil
            all theſe in two quarts of Spring- <lb/>water, till it comes to a quart. You may add a
            <lb/>pint of White Wine to it. Strain it out; and when <lb/>'tis cold, bottle it. Drink
            a quarter of a pint in <lb/>the Morning, and as much at four a Clock in the
            <lb/>Afternoon. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="280"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To draw out a Thorn. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE the Roots of Comfry, and bruiſe them <lb/>in a Mortar
            with a little Boars-greaſe, and <lb/>uſe this as a plaiſter. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For a ſcald Head. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE three ſpoonfuls of Juice of Comfry, two <lb/>Pennyworth
            of Verdegreaſe, and half a <lb/>pound of Hogs Lard: Melt it together, but let it
            <lb/>not boil. Cut off the hair; and anoint the place: <lb/>It will cure it. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the Falling-ſickneſs. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE the After-birth of a Woman, and dry <lb/>it to powder,
            and drink half an ounce there- <lb/>of in a glaſs of White-wine for ſix Mornings toge-
            <lb/>ther. If the patient be a Man, it muſt be the After- <lb/>birth of a female Child;
            if a Woman, the contrary. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the Trembling at the Heart. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>AKE a ſyrup of Damask Roſes, and add <lb/>thereto a ſmall
            quantity of red Coral, Pearl, <lb/>and Amber-greaſe, all finely beaten and powder'd:
            <lb/>Take this ſo long as your Pain continues, about <lb/>a ſpoonful at a time. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For a Pleuriſy, if the Perſon cannot be <lb/>blooded. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of Carduus, the Seeds or Leaves, a large <lb/>handful;
            boil them in a pint of Beer till <lb/>half is conſumed; then ſtrain it, and give it the
            <lb/>Party warm. They muſt be faſting when they take <pb n="281"/>
            <lb/>it, and faſt ſix hours after it, or it will do them <lb/>harm. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To draw a Rheum from the Eyes. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">R</hi>OAST an egg hard, then cut out the yolk, <lb/>and take a
            ſpoonful of Cummin-ſeed, and a <lb/>handful of Bears-foot; bruiſe them and put them
            <lb/>into the white of the Egg, ſo lay it hot on to <lb/>the Nape of the Neck; bind it
            on with a Cloth, <lb/>and let it lie 24 hours, ſo lay on freſh again. It <lb/>will cure
            in a little time. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To clear the Eyes. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE the white of Hens-Dung, dry it very <lb/>well, and beat
            it to powder; ſift it and blow <lb/>it into the Eyes when the Party goes to bed. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For a Pin or Web in the Eye. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE the Gall of a Hare and Honey, of each a <lb/>like
            quantity; mix them together, and take a <lb/>Feather and put a little into the Eye, and
            it will <lb/>cure it in two or three days. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If a Hair or Fiſh-Bone ſtick in the Throat, im- <lb/>mediately ſwallow the yolk of
            a raw Egg, it is a <lb/>very good thing. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To cure the yellow or black Jaundice. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a quart of White-wine, a large red <lb/>Dock-root, a
            Burr-root, that which bears the <lb/>ſmall Burr, two pennyworth of Turmerick, a lit-
            <lb/>tle Saffron, a little of the white of Gooſe-Dung <lb/>that feeds on the Green; boil
            all theſe together a <lb/>little while; then let it run thro' a Strainer: drink <lb/>it
            Morning and Evening three days. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="282"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Plaiſter for the Sciatica. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of yellow Wax a pound, the Juice of <lb/>Marjoram and
            red Sage, of each ſix ſpoon- <lb/>fuls, Juice of Onions two ſpoonfuls; let all theſe
            <lb/>boil together till the Juice is conſumed, and when <lb/>'tis half cold, put in two
            ounces of Turpentine, <lb/>and of Nutmegs, Cloves, Mace, Aniſeeds, and
            <lb/>Frankincenſe, of each one pennyworth finely pow- <lb/>dered; ſtir it well together
            and make a Plaiſter. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>A Sahe for the King5- Evil * </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Salve for the King's Evil. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a Burdock-root, and a white Lilly- <lb/>root; waſh, dry,
            and ſcrape them; wrap <lb/>them in brown paper, and roaſt them in the Em- <lb/>bers;
            when they are ſoft take them out, and cut <lb/>out the burn or hard, and beat them in a
            Mortar <lb/>with Boars-greaſe and Bean-flower: when 'tis al- <lb/>moſt enough, put in as
            much of the beſt Turpen- <lb/>tine as will make it ſmell of it, then put it in a
            <lb/>Pot for uſe. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The Party muſt take inwardly two ſpoonfuls of <lb/>Lime-water in the Morning, and
            ſaſt two hours <lb/>after it, and do the ſame at Four a Clock in the <lb/>Afternoon. If
            there be any Swelling of the Evil, <lb/>they muſt bathe it with this Water a quarter of
            an <lb/>hour together, a little warmed, and wet a Cloth <lb/>and bind it on the Place;
            but if the Skin be <lb/>broken, only waſh it in the Water, and ſpread a <lb/>thin
            Plaiſter of the Salve and lay on it; ſhift it <lb/>once a day; if very bad, you muſt
            dreſs it twice <lb/>a day. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">To make the lime-water.</hi> Take a Limeſtone <lb/>as big as a
            Man's Head, it muſt be well burned; <lb/>put it into ſix quarts of boiling Water, cover
            it <lb/>cloſe, but ſometimes ſtir it; the next day, when 'tis <pb n="283"/>
            <lb/>ſettled pour off the clear Water, and keep it in <lb/>Bottles for uſe. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To cure Burſtenneſs. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Hemlock, and bruiſe it a little, heat <lb/>it pretty
            well, and apply it twice a day, <lb/>without any Truſs, and keep the Party as ſtill as
            <lb/>may be. This has cured, when many other Things <lb/>have failed. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Powder for Burſtenneſs. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a good quantity of wild Musk, Roots <lb/>and all, pick,
            waſh, and dry them; then <lb/>take of Currant-Leaves, Vine-Leaves and Strings, <lb/>an
            equal quantity; then take almoſt a quart of <lb/>Hemp-ſeeds: you muſt lay the Seeds at
            the bottom <lb/>of a Pot, and the Leaves and Roots on the top; <lb/>then put it into an
            Oven, dry them, rub them to <lb/>powder, and ſift them together. The Party muſt
            <lb/>take as much of this Powder as will lie on a Six- <lb/>pence, in a little Ale, in
            the Morning, and at <lb/>Four in the Afternoon, and continue it five <lb/>or ſix Weeks:
            the Powder ſhould be made in <lb/><hi rend="italic">May</hi> if poſſible. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the Chin-Cough. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a ſpoonful of the Juice of Penny-royal, <lb/>mix'd with
            Sugar-candy beaten to powder: <lb/>take this for nine Mornings together. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To cure the Itch without Sulphur. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a handful of Elecampane-root, and <lb/>as much
            ſharp-pointed Dock; ſhred them <lb/>ſmall and boil them in two quarts of Spring-water,
              <pb n="284"/>
            <lb/>till it comes to a Pint; ſtrain the Liquor, and <lb/>with it let the Party waſh his
            Hands or Face two <lb/>or three times a day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the Itch. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of Cammomile and Velvet Leaves, Scurvy- <lb/>graſs, and
            Capons Feather, of each one hand- <lb/>ful; boil theſe in half a pound of Butter out of
            <lb/>the Churm till 'tis an Ointment, then ſtrain it <lb/>out, and mix with it half an
            ounce of black <lb/>Pepper beaten fine; ſtir it in till 'tis cold, and <lb/>anoint the
            Party with it all over: keep on the <lb/>ſame Linnen for a Week; then waſh with warm
            <lb/>Water and ſweet Herbs, and put on clean Linnen. <lb/>Before you begin to uſe this,
            you muſt take Brim- <lb/>ſtone and Milk for three Mornings: keep warm <lb/>and purge
            well after 'tis over. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the Scurvy or Dropſy. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">S</hi>TAMP and ſtrain the Juice of the Leaves of <lb/>Elder, and
            to a quarter of a pint of Juice put <lb/>ſo much White-wine; warm it a little and drink
            <lb/>it off, and do thus for four or five Mornings to- <lb/>gether: if it purge you it
            will certainly do good. <lb/>Take this in the Spring. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For a Looſeneſs. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">B</hi>OIL a good handful of Bramble-Leaves in <lb/>Milk, ſweeten'd
            with Loaf-Sugar; drink it <lb/>Night and Morning. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="285"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For an Ague. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">G</hi>IVE as much <hi rend="italic">Virginia</hi> Snake-root*
            dry'd and <lb/>powdered as will lie on a Shilling, in a Glaſs <lb/>of Sherry or Sack,
            juſt before the cold Fit begins: <lb/>uſe this two or three times till the Ague is gone.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For an Ague. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE an ounce and half of the beſt refin'd <lb/>Aloes, and
            ſteep it in a quart of Brandy; <lb/>infuſe it 48 hours, and take four ſpoonfuls juſt
            <lb/>before the Fit comes. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For an Ague. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a pint of red Roſe-water, and put to it <lb/>an ounce of
            white Sugar-candy, and the Juice <lb/>of three Sevil Oranges; mix all together, and
            <lb/>drink it off an hour before you expect the Fit. It <lb/>cures at once or twice
            taking. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>An Ointment for a Burning or Scald. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a pound of Hogs-Lard, and two good <lb/>handfuls of
            Sheeps-Dung, and a good hand- <lb/>ful of the Green Bark of the Elder, the Brown
            <lb/>Bark being firſt taken off; boil all theſe to an <lb/>Ointment. You muſt firſt take
            out the Fire with <lb/>Sallet-Oil, and a bit of an Onion, and the white <lb/>of an Egg
            beaten well together; then anoint <lb/>with the Ointment, and in leſs than a Week it
            <lb/>will be well. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="286"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Cerecloth. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE 3 pound of Oil-olive, and half a pound <lb/>of red Lead,
            and half a pound of white <lb/>Lead, both powder'd and ſifted; then take 3 <lb/>ounces
            of Virgin's-Wax, 2 ounces of <hi rend="italic">Spaniſh</hi> Soap, <lb/>and 2 ounces of
            Deer's-Suet; put all theſe Things <lb/>into a braſs Kettle, ſetting it over the Fire,
            ſtir- <lb/>ring it continually till it comes to the height of a <lb/>Salve, which you
            may know by dropping a little <lb/>on a Trencher; and if it neither hangs to the
            <lb/>Trencher nor your Fingers it is enough: then dip <lb/>your Cloths in, and when you
            take them out, throw <lb/>them into a Pail of Water, and as they cool take <lb/>them out
            and lay them on a Table, and clap them, <lb/>and when you have done roll them up with
            Papers <lb/>between, and keep them for uſe; they must be <lb/>kept pretty cool. This
            Cerecloth is good for any <lb/>Pain, Swelling, or Bruiſe. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>The yellow Balſam. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE 8 ounces of Burgamy-Pitch, 3 ounces <lb/>and half of
            yellow Bees-Wax ſliced, 1 pound <lb/>of Deer's-Suet, 1 ounce of <hi rend="italic"
              >Venice-</hi>Turpentine, <lb/>beaten up in Plantane-water, half a pint of red
            <lb/>Roſes, a quarter of a pint of Vinegar of red <lb/>Roſes, 24 Cloves of Garlick, and
            of Salt-petre dry'd <lb/>before the Fire half the quantity of a Nutmeg; <lb/>bruiſe the
            Garlick in a Stone Mortar, and ſet the <lb/>Oil, Vinegar, and Garlick, in an earthen
            Pipkin <lb/>over the Fire; let them boil gently half an hour; <lb/>then put in the Pitch
            and Wax, and when that is <lb/>melted, put in the Suet, and 1 ounce of Palm- <lb/>Oil;
            then let it boil a quarter of an hour longer; <lb/>then take it off the Fire, and put in
            the Turpen- <lb/>tine and Salt-petre: ſet it over the Fire again for a <pb n="287"/>
            <lb/>little while; then take it off, and let it ſtand to <lb/>cool, then pour it gently
            into your Gallypots; <lb/>be ſure you put in no Dregs; the Vinegar will <lb/>fall to the
            bottom; tye the Gallypots down with <lb/>Leather. 'Tis an excellent Salve for ſore Legs,
            <lb/>Boils, Whitlows, ſore Breaſts, and may ſafely be <lb/>uſed to draw Corruption out
            of any Sore; put a <lb/>little of it on Lint, and put a Plaiſter of the follow- <lb/>ing
            black Salve over it. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>The black Salve. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a pint of Oil of Olives, 3 quarters of a <lb/>pound of
            yellow Wax, 2 ounces of Frankin- <lb/>cenſe finely beaten and ſearced, 2 ounces of the
            <lb/>beſt Maſtich, 2 ounces of Olibanum, 2 ounces of <lb/>Myrrh, half a pound of white
            Lead finely <lb/>ground, and 2 Drams of Camphire: Boil theſe <lb/>till they are black;
            then let it ſtand a little; oil a <lb/>Board, and pour it on, and oil your Hand, and
            <lb/>make it up in Rolls for uſe. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A calcin'd Water to dry up Ulcers and <lb/>old Sores. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of the beſt Roman-Vitriol 3 ounces, <lb/>Camphire 1
            ounce; beat them into fine Pow- <lb/>der, put them into the bottom of a Crucible, and
            <lb/>fix it in hot Embers; cover it with white Paper <lb/>4 double, and put a little
            Tile on it: Let it be <lb/>well calcined, but not too much; when 'tis cold <lb/>beat it
            into fine Powder, and ſift it; then add to <lb/>it 3 ounces of Bole-Armoniac, beaten and
            ſifted: <lb/>mix all together, and to half an ounce of this <lb/>Powder put a quart of
            Spring or Plantane-water: <lb/>Boil the Water, and when 'tis blood-warm put in <lb/>your
            half ounce of Powder, and ſtir it together in <pb n="288"/>
            <lb/>a Pewter Bafon till 'tis quite cold; then put it <lb/>in a Bottle for uſe. When you
            uſe it, ſhake the <lb/>Bottle, and pour ſome out and uſe it as hot as <lb/>can be
            endured, either by a Syringe, or waſhing <lb/>the Place twice or thrice a day, and uſe
            the follow- <lb/>ing Plaiſter or Salve. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>The Leaden Plaiſter. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of white Lead three ounces, of red Lead <lb/>ſeven
            ounces, of Bole-Armoniac nine ounces; <lb/>beat all into fine Powder, and put to them a
            pint <lb/>of the beſt Oil-olive, incorporate them over the <lb/>Fire, and and let them
            boil gently half an hour, put- <lb/>ting in one ounce of Oil of Exceter; ſtir it conti-
            <lb/>nually, and when 'tis enough, make it up in Rolls. <lb/>This is a drying Plaiſter.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Salve for a Burn or Scald. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE one pound of Mutton-Suet ſhred ſmall; <lb/>melt it, and
            put into it Thyme, Sweet- <lb/>marjoram, Melilote, Penny-royal and Hyſop, of <lb/>each a
            good handful chopp'd ſmall, and let it ſtand <lb/>together four days; then heat and
            ſtrain it out, <lb/>and put in the ſame quantity of Herbs again, and <lb/>let it ſtand
            four days longer; then heat it and <lb/>ſtrain it out, and to that Liquor put five pound
            <lb/>of white Roſin, and two pound of Bees-Wax <lb/>ſliced, and boil it up to a Salve;
            and when 'tis cold <lb/>enough, oil a Board, pour it on it, and make it <lb/>up in
            Rolls: This is an admirable Salve when the <lb/>Fire is taken out. You muſt take out the
            Fire <lb/>with Oil, anoint it with Oil with a Feather; then <lb/>lay on the Plaiſter.
            'Tis good for a ſmall Cut, or <lb/>Iſſue inflamed. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="289"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Green Salve. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE 4 handfuls of Clowns All-heal, ſtamp <lb/>it and put it
            in a Pot, and add to it 4 ounces <lb/>of Boars-Greaſe, half a Pint of Oil-Olive, and
            <lb/>Wax three ounces ſliced; boil it till the Juice is <lb/>conſumed, which is known
            when the Stuff doth not <lb/>bubble at all: then ſtrain it and put it on the Fire
            <lb/>again, adding 2 Ounces of Venice Turpentine; <lb/>let it boil a little and put it
            in Gallipots for uſe. <lb/>Melt a little in a Spoon, and if the Cut or Wound <lb/>be
            deep, dip your Tents in it; if not, dip Lint <lb/>and put on it, and defend the Place
            with a Lea- <lb/>den Plaiſter; dreſs it once a day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For a ſore Breaſt when 'tis broken. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a quarter of a pound of Raiſins of the <lb/>Sun ſtoned,
            and beat them very ſmall; then <lb/>add to it near as much Honey, and beat it toge-
            <lb/>ther into a Salve; ſpread it on a Cloth, and make <lb/>Tents if occaſion. Dreſs it
            once a day; when <lb/>'tis well drawn uſe the yellow Balſam, and black <lb/>or leaden
            Plaiſter. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Poultice for a ſore Breaſt before 'tis <lb/>broken. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">B</hi>OIL white Bread and Milk to a Poultice, then <lb/>put to it
            Oil of Lillies, and the Yolk of an <lb/>Egg; ſet it over the Fire again to heat, and ap-
            <lb/>ply it as hot as can be endured: Dreſs it Morning <lb/>and Night till 'tis broke,
            then dreſs it with the <lb/>Poultice of Raiſins. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="290"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To diſperſe Tumours. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of yellow Wax, Frankincenſe, and Ro- <lb/>ſin, of each
            four ounces; melt them toge- <lb/>ther, ſtrain it out, and when 'tis cool make it in a
            <lb/>Roll, and keep it for uſe. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To keep a Cancer in the Breaſt from in- <lb/>creaſing. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of Lapis Calaminaris 4 ounces all in <lb/>one piece and
            having made it red hot in a <lb/>Crucible 9 times, quench it every time in a Pint of
            <lb/>White Wine; then take 2 Ounces of Lapis Tutty <lb/>and having burnt that red hot in
            a Crucible 3 times <lb/>quench that every time in a Pint of red Roſe-wa- <lb/>ter: Then
            beat the Tutty and the Calaminaris <lb/>Stone together in a Mortar very fine, and put it
            <lb/>in a glaſs Bottle, and put the Roſe-water and white <lb/>Wine to it, and ſhake it
            three or four times a Day <lb/>for nine Days before you begiq to uſe it. You <lb/>muſt
            keep the Wine and the Roſe-water cloſe co- <lb/>vered, when you quench the Stone, that
            the Steam <lb/>does not go out. When you uſe it ſhake it well, <lb/>and dip Rags in it,
            and lay them to the Breaſt; <lb/>let the Rags remain on till 'tis dreſs'd again: It muſt
            <lb/>be dreſs'd twice a day, Night and Morning. The <lb/>clear Water is excellent for
            weak or ſore Eyes. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For a Swelling in the Face. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a handful of Damask-roſe Leaves, boil <lb/>them in
            running Water till they are tender; <lb/>ſtamp them to a Pulp, and boil white Bread and
            <lb/>Milk till 'tis ſoft; then put in your Pulp with a <lb/>little Hogs Lard, and
            thicken it with the Yolk of <lb/>an Egg, and apply it warm. </p>
        </div>
        <pb/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For a ſore Throat. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>AKE a Plaiſter of Paracelſus 4 Inches broad, <lb/>and ſo
            long as to come from Ear to Ear, <lb/>and apply it warm to the Throat; then bruiſe
            <lb/>Houſe-leek and preſs out the Juice, add an equal <lb/>quantity of Honey, and a
            little burnt Allum; <lb/>mix all together, and let the Party often take ſome <lb/>on a
            liquoriſh ſtick. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A purging Diet-drink. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of Garden Scurvy-graſs ſix handfuls, Wa-
            <lb/>ter-Creſſes and Brooklime of each 4 handfuls, <lb/>Peach-Bloſſoms 4 handfuls,
            Nettle-tops and Fumi- <lb/>tory of each 3 handfuls, Monks-Rhubarb 4 ounces, <lb/>Sena 4
            ounces, <hi rend="italic">China</hi> 2 ounces, Sarſaparilla 3 oun- <lb/>ces, Rhubarb 1
            ounce, Coriander and ſweet Fen- <lb/>nel-ſeeds, of each half an ounce; cut the Herbs,
            <lb/>ſlice the Roots, bruiſe the Seeds, put them in a <lb/>thin Bag, and hang them in 4
            Gallons of ſmall <lb/>Ale; after 3 Days drink a Pint of it every Mor- <lb/>ning. Be
            regular in Diet, eat nothing ſalt or <lb/>ſowre. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>Pills to purge the Head. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of the Extract of Rudium 2 Drams, and Pill <lb/>Fetida
            one Dram; mix theſe well together, <lb/>and make it into 12 Pills; take 2, or if the
            Conſti- <lb/>tution be ſtrong, 3 of them at 6 a-Clock in the <lb/>Morning: drink warm
            Gruel, or thin Broth, or <lb/>Poſſet, when they work. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="292"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For a Canker in the Mouth. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Celandine, Columbine, Sage and Fen- <lb/>nel, of each
            one handful, ſtamp and ſtrain <lb/>them, and to the Juice put a Spoonful of Honey,
            <lb/>half a Spoonful of burnt Allum, and as much <lb/>Bole Armoniac beaten fine: mix and
            beat all theſe <lb/>together very well, and wrap a little Flax about <lb/>a Stick, and
            rub the Canker with it: if it bleeds <lb/>'tis the better. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Water for ſore or weak Eyes. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of Ground-Ivy, Celandine and Daiſies of <lb/>each a like
            quantity ſtampt and ſtrain'd, and <lb/>add to the Juice a little Sugar and white
            Roſe-wa- <lb/>ter; ſhake this together, and with a Feather drop <lb/>it into the Eyes;
            this takes away all manner of In- <lb/>flammation, Spots, Itching, Smarting or Web,
            <lb/>and is an excellent thing for the Eyes. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Clyſter for the Worms. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of Rue, Wormwood, Lavender-Cotton <lb/>3 or 4 Sprigs of
            each, a Spoonful of Ani- <lb/>ſeeds bruiſed; boil theſe in a Pint of Milk till the
            <lb/>third part be conſumed; then ſtrain it out, and <lb/>add to it as much Aloes finely
            powdered as will <lb/>lie on a Three-pence; ſweeten it with Honey, and <lb/>give it
            pretty warm; it ſhould be given 3 Mor- <lb/>nings together; and the beſt time is three
            Days <lb/>before the new or full Moon. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="293"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">Lucatellus</hi>'s Balſam. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of <hi rend="italic">Venice</hi>-Turpentine one pound,
            the beſt <lb/>Oil 3 Pints, Sack 6 ſpoonfuls, yellow Wax <lb/>half a pound, natural
            Balſam one ounce, Oil of <lb/>St. <hi rend="italic">John's</hi>-wort one ounce, red
            Sanders well pow- <lb/>dered one ounce; cut the Wax in thin Slices, and <lb/>ſet it over
            the Fire in a large Skillet, and when 'tis <lb/>all melted put in the Turpentine; firſt
            waſh it 3 <lb/>ſeveral times in red Roſe-water, then ſtir them <lb/>well together till
            they boil a little; then take it off <lb/>from the Fire and let it cool. The next Day
            take <lb/>it out of the Skillet and cut it in thin ſlices, that all <lb/>the Water may
            be got out of it; then ſet it over <lb/>the Fire again, and when 'tis melted ſtir it
            well to- <lb/>gether; then put in the Oil, and the Oil of St. <lb/><hi rend="italic"
              >John</hi>'s-wort, and the natural Balſam, and the Sack <lb/>and the Sanders, ſtirring
            them all together very <lb/>well; then let it boil a little while, and take it off
            <lb/>the Fire and ſtir it 2 Hours all one way. When <lb/>'tis cold put it in Gallipots
            and cover them with <lb/>Leather; it will keep good twenty Years, and the <lb/>older the
            better. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Salve for a Cerecloth, for Bruiſes or <lb/>Aches. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a Pint of Oil, 9 Ounces of red Lead, 2 <lb/>Ounces of
            Bees-wax, a Shillings-worth of <lb/>Sperma Cete, 2 ounces of Roſin beaten and ſifted;
            <lb/>ſet all theſe on a ſoft Fire in a Bell-skillet, ſtirring <lb/>till it boils, and
            then try it on a Rag, whether it <lb/>firmly ſticks upon it; when it does ſtick, take it
            <lb/>off; and when you have made what Cerecloths <lb/>you pleaſe, pour the reſt on an
            oiled Board, and <lb/>make it up in Rolls. 'Tis very good for a Cut or <lb/>green Wound.
          </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="294"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>An Ointment for a Cold on the Stomach. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE an Ounce and half of the Oil of Va-
            <lb/>lentia-Scabioſa, Oil of Sweet-Almonds a <lb/>quarter of an ounce, a quarter of an
            ounce of Man's <lb/>Fat, and 4 Scruples of the beſt Oil of Mace; mix <lb/>theſe
            together, and warm a little in a Spoon, and <lb/>Night and Morning anoint the Stomach.
            Lay a <lb/>piece of black or lawn Paper on it. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To make <hi rend="roman">Caſcoigne</hi>'s Powder. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of Powder of Pearl, red Coral, Crabs- <lb/>Eyes, white
            Amber, and Hartſhorn of each <lb/>one ounce; beat them to a fine Powder and ſearce
            <lb/>them. Then take a Dram of oriental Bezoar, and <lb/>a Dram of Ambergreaſe, and mix
            with the Pow- <lb/>ders; then take off the black Toes of Crab's Claws <lb/>beaten to a
            fine Powder, as much as of all the reſt <lb/>of the Powders, for this is the chief: then
            mix all <lb/>well together, and make them up in Balls in Jelly <lb/>of Hartſhorn, and in
            your Jelly infuſe a ſmall quan- <lb/>tity of Saffron to give them a Colour; when you
            <lb/>have rolled them in Balls as big as a Walnut, lay <lb/>them on a <hi rend="italic"
              >China</hi> or Silver Plate to dry; when they <lb/>are fully dry and hard, paper them
            up, and keep <lb/>them for uſe. The Doſe you muſt give at a time is <lb/>to a Man or
            Woman 10 or 12 Grains in Dragon, <lb/>Carduus, or the Lady <hi rend="italic"
            >Allen</hi>'s Water, the Party <lb/>going to Bed, and cover'd warm. The Crabs uſed
            <lb/>in this Powder muſt be caught in <hi rend="italic">May</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
              >Septem- <lb/>ber</hi>, and they muſt not be boiled. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="295"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Water to cure red or pimpled Faces. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a Pint of ſtrong White Wine Vinegar, <lb/>and put to it
            Powder of the <unclear>Roots</unclear> of Orice <lb/>3 Drams, Powder of Brimſtone half
            an ounce, <lb/>and Camphire 2 Drams, ſtamp with a few <unclear>blanch'd</unclear>
            <lb/>Almonds, 4 Oaken Apples cut in the middle, and <lb/>the Juice of 4 Lemons, and a
            handful of Bean- <lb/>flowers; put all theſe together in a ſtrong double <lb/>glaſs
            Bottle, ſhake them them well together and ſet it in <lb/>the Sun for 10 Days; waſh the
            Face with this Wa- <lb/>ter, let it dry on, and don't wipe it off. This <lb/>cures red
            or pimpled Faces, Spots, Heat, Mor- <lb/>phew, or Sunburn. But you muſt eat the follow-
            <lb/>ing Diet for 3 Weeks or a Month. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Cucumbers and cut them as ſmall as Herbs <lb/>to the Pot, boil them in a ſmall
            Pipkin with a piece <lb/>of Mutton, and make it into Pottage with Oat <lb/>meal: So eat
            a Meſs Morning, Noon, and Night <lb/>without Intermiſſion for 3 Weeks or a Month.
            <lb/>This Diet and the Water has cured when nothing <lb/>elſe would do. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A good thing to waſh the Face in. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a large piece of Camphire, the quan- <lb/>tity of a
            Gooſe Egg, and break it ſo that it <lb/>may go into a pint Bottle, which fill with
            Water; <lb/>when it has ſtood a Month, put a Spoonful of it <lb/>in 3 Spoonfuls of Milk,
            and waſh in it. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Wear a piece of Lead beaten exceeding thin for <lb/>a Forehead-piece under a
            Forehead-cloth; it keeps <lb/>the Forehead ſmooth and plump. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="296"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Plaiſter for Worms in Children. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE 2 ounces of yellow Wax, and 2 ounces <lb/>of Roſin, boil
            them half an Hour, ſtirring <lb/>them all the while; ſcum them well and take it off,
            <lb/>and put to it 3 Drams of Aloes, and 2 Spoonfuls <lb/>of Treacle, and boil it up
            again; rub a Board with <lb/>freſh Butter, and pour the Salve thereon, work it
            <lb/>well, and make it up in Rolls: whenyou make the <lb/>Plaiſter, ſprinkle it with
            Saffron, and cut a hole a- <lb/>gainſt the Navel. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>The Stomach Plaiſter. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE of Burgamy-Pitch, Frankincenſe and <lb/>Bees-Wax of each
            one ounce ; melt them to- <lb/>gether; then put in 1 ounce of <hi rend="italic"
              >Venice</hi>-Turpentine, <lb/>and 1 ounce of Oil of Mace; melt it together and
            <lb/>ſpread your Plaiſter on Sheep's Leather; grate on <lb/>it ſome Nutmeg when you lay
            it on the Stomach. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>To make a Quilt for the Stomach. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a fine Rag 4 Inches ſquare, and ſpread <lb/>Cotton thin
            over it; then take Mint and <lb/>ſweet Marjoram dry'd and rub'd to Powder, and
            <lb/>ſtrew it over the Cotton pretty thick; then take <lb/>Nutmeg, Cloves and Mace, of
            each a quarter of <lb/>an Ounce beaten and ſifted, and ſtrew that over the <lb/>Herbs,
            and on that ſtrew half an Ounce of Gallen- <lb/>gal finely powdered, then a thin row of
            Cotton, <lb/>and another fine Rag, and quilt it together. When <lb/>you lay it on the
            Stomach, dip it in hot Sack and <lb/>lay it on as warm as can be endured. This is very
            <lb/>good for a pain in the Stomach. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="297"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the Pains of the Gout. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>IX Barbados-Tar, and Palm-Oil, an equal <lb/>quantity, juſt
            melt them together, and <lb/>gently anoint the Part affected. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A preſent help for the Cholick. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>IX as much Mithridate as a Bean in a Spoon- <lb/>ful of
            Dragon-water, and give it the Party <lb/>to drink, and lay a little Suet on the Navel;
            keep <lb/>in Bed. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Plaiſter for the Cholick. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">S</hi>PREAD the whites of 4 or 5 Eggs well beaten <lb/>on ſome
            Leather, and over that ſtrew on a <lb/>Spoonful of Pepper, and as much Ginger finely
            <lb/>beaten and ſifted, then put this Plaiſter on the Na- <lb/>vel: it often gives
            ſpeedy eaſe. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>For the Ague. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE Smallage, Ribwort, Rue, Plantane and <lb/>Olibanum; beat
            all theſe well together with <lb/>a little Bay-ſalt, and put it in a thin Bag, and lay
            <lb/>it to the Wriſt a little before the cold Fit comes. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="align-center italic">
            <lb/>A Powder for Convulſion Fits. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE a Dram and half of ſingle Piony-ſeed, <lb/>of Miſletoe
            of the Oak one Dram, Pearl, <lb/>white Amber and Coral, all finely powdered, of
            <lb/>each half a Dram, Bezoar 2 Drams, and 5 Leaves <lb/>of Gold; make all theſe up in a
            fine Powder, and <lb/>give it in a Spoonful of black Cherry-water, or if <lb/>you pleaſe
            Hyſterical Water. You may give to a <pb n="298"/>
            <lb/>Child new born, to prevent Fits, as much as will <lb/>lie on a Three-pence, and
            likewiſe at each Change <lb/>of the Moon; and to older People as much as they <lb/>have
            ſtrength and occaſion. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" quantity="21" unit="pages"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
