<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: The Complete Family-Piece</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">The Complete family-piece: and, country gentleman, and farmer's, best
              guide. In three parts. Part I. Containing, a very choice and valuable collection of
              near eight hundred well-experienced practical family-receipts in physick and surgery;
              cookery, pastry and confectionary, with a complete bill of fare for every month in the
              year, and instructions for placing the dishes on a table; for pickling and preserving
              all sorts of fruits, tongues, hams, &amp;c. for distilling and fermenting of all
              compound, simple waters and spirits; for making mum, cyder, and perry, mead and
              metheglin; and for making and preserving all sorts of excellent English wines; with
              good and useful instructions for brewing fine, strong, good, wholesome and palatable
              drinks, as beers, ales, &amp;c. in small quantities, and at easy rates, for the use of
              all private families; with divers other useful and valuable receipts interspersed
              through the whole, particularly Dr. Mead's for the cure of the bite of a mad dog: many
              of which were never before printed, and the others experimentally taken from the
              latest and very best authorities; and being all regularly taken from the latest and
              very best authorities; and being all regularly digested under their proper heads, are
              divided into six different chapters. Part II. Containing, I. Full instructions to be
              observed in hunting, coursing, setting and shooting; with an account of the several
              kinds of dogs necessary for those diversions, and receipts for the cure of all common
              distempers to which they are liable; as also receipts for the cleaning and preserving
              of boots, fire-arms, &amp;c. II. Cautions, rules and directions to be taken and
              observed in fishing, with the manner of making and preserving of rods, lines, floats,
              artificial flies, &amp;c. and for chusing and preserving several sorts of curious
              baits. III. A full and complete kalender of all work necessary to be done in the
              fruit, flower, and kitchen gardens, green-house, &amp;c. with the produce of each, in
              every month throughout the whole year. Part III. Containing, practical rules, and
              methods, for the improving of land, and managing a farm in all its branches; with
              several curious receipts for brinning, liming and preparing wheat, barley, oats,
              &amp;c. for sowing; excellent receipts for destroying of rats and mice; a great number
              of choice receipts for the cure of all common distempers incident to all sorts of
              cattle; and a complete kalender of all business necessary to be done in the field,
              yard, &amp;c. by the farmer, in every month throughout the year. With a complete
              alphabetical index to each part. The whole, being faithfully collected by several very
              eminent and ingenious gentlemen, is now first published, at their earnest desire, for
              the general benefit of mankind.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T162305</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T162305"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London, Printed: and sold by C. Rivington, at the Bible and Crown in St.
                  Paul's Church-yard, 1736.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1736</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="15"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="456"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="44"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">National Library of Scotland</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CB130677011</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Recipe collections"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="15"/>
    <body>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>An ornamented horizontal column. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <head rend="sc align-center space">
        <lb/><hi rend="size(1.25)">the </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="roman size(2.0)">Complete Family-Piece: </hi>
        <lb/>and <lb/><hi rend="roman size(1.5)">Country Gentleman and Farmer's </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="roman size(2.0)">BEST GUIDE, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </hi>
      </head>
      <div type="chapter">
        <head rend="size(1.25) align-center space">
          <lb/>CHAP. I. </head>
        <head rend="italic align-center">
          <lb/>Containing a great Number of Receipts in <lb/><hi rend="roman">Phyſick</hi> and <hi
            rend="roman">Surgery</hi>. </head>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>An excellent Remedy to enrich the <hi rend="roman">Blood</hi>. </head>
          <p>
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(6)">T</hi>AKE Garden and Sea Scurvy-graſs, Sage, <lb/>Brooklime, and
            Water-Creſſes, of each <lb/>three Handfuls, the Juice of one <hi rend="italic"
              >Seville</hi>
            <lb/>Orange; mix all together, and when <lb/>ſtamped and ſtrained, take half a Quarter
            <lb/>of a Pint of the Juice, with half an Ounce <lb/>of Horſe-Radiſh Water, every
            Morning and Night. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For a <hi rend="roman">Pleuriſy</hi>, if the Perſon cannot be blooded. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Seeds or Leaves of Carduus, a large <lb/>Handful; boil them in a Pint
            of Beer till Half is con- <lb/>ſumed; then ſtrain it, and give it warm to the Party. <pb
              n="2"/>
            <lb/>They muſt be faſting when they take it, and faſt ſix <lb/>Hours after it, or it
            will do them Harm. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A very effectual Remedy for the <hi rend="roman">Piles</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Black-lead ſcrap'd fine, mix it with ſome Ho- <lb/>ney, till the Honey looks
            black; then put it into an <lb/>Oyſter-ſhell, and ſet it over the Fire till it grows ſo
            ſtiff, <lb/>that you can make it into a Suppoſitory. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>An excellent Remedy to bring away the <hi rend="roman">Gravel</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take a Quart of Spring-water, and put a Toaſt in <lb/>it; when the Toaſt has ſoak'd
            for ſome Time, take it <lb/>out, and ſweeten the Water very ſweet with good clear
            <lb/>Honey, and drink as much as you can of it every Morn- <lb/>ing, which will make the
            Paſſages ſo glib and ſlippery, <lb/>as to bring away all gravelly or ſandy Matter. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Poultice for a <hi rend="roman">Sore Breaſt</hi>, <hi rend="roman">Leg</hi>, or
              <hi rend="roman">Arm</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Boil Wheat-flower very well in ſtrong Ale, and pretty <lb/>thick, then take it off
            and ſcrape in ſome Boar's Greaſe; <lb/>let it not boil after the Greaſe is in, ſtir it
            well, and <lb/>apply it hot. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For a <hi rend="roman">Canker</hi> in the <hi rend="roman">Mouth</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take the Leaves of Woodbind, Briar, Columbine, <lb/>Red Sage, Sorrel and Violet
            Leaves, of each one Hand- <lb/>ful, and two or three Sprigs of Rue; ſtamp them, ſtrain
            <lb/>the Juice, and boil it with four Ounces of Honey, and <lb/>put in a Bit of Allum,
            the Quantity of a Wallnut, ſcum <lb/>it clean, and waſh the Mouth often with it. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To create a good <hi rend="roman">Appetite</hi>, and ſtrengthen the <hi
              rend="roman">Stomach</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Stomatick-Pill with Gums, <hi rend="italic">Extractum <lb/>Rudii</hi>,
            of each a Dram; Reſin of Jalap, half a Scruple; <lb/>Oil of Anniſeeds, 4 Drops; Tartar
            vitriolated, 1 Scru- <lb/>ple; mix with Syrup of Violets, and make into Pills; <lb/>of
            which take Four or Five over Night. They are of <lb/>excellent Uſe in the Megrims, and
              <hi rend="italic">Vertigo</hi>, by reaſon <lb/>they carry the Humour off from the
            Stomach, which <lb/>fumes up into the Head. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="3"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For a <hi rend="roman">Stitch</hi> in the <hi rend="roman">Side</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take a large Acorn dry'd and powder'd, and Powder <lb/>of Angelica-ſeed, of each a
            like Quantity; drink after <lb/>it a Glaſs of Black Cherry Water. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Remedy for an <hi rend="roman">Aſthma</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Caſtor one Dram, Salt of Steel half a Dram; <lb/>made into very ſmall Pills,
            with Extract of Rue. Theſe <lb/>you may take every Hour till the Convulſion is abated,
            <lb/>drinking three Spoonfuls of the following Julep after <lb/>each Doſe.— Take of
            Black-cherry and Penny- <lb/>royal Water, each an Ounce; of Rue and compound
            <lb/>Briony-Water, each 4 Ounces, with a ſmall Quantity <lb/>of Sugar, made into a
            Julep.—Or a Toad dried and <lb/>powder'd, made into Pills, and taken as above, is a
            <lb/>moſt excellent Remedy, notwithſtanding the common <lb/>Opinion of the great Poiſon
            there is in Toads. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For the <hi rend="roman">Whites</hi>, or any Flux. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take <hi rend="italic">Venice</hi> Treacle and candid Ginger, of each 3 <lb/>Drams,
            half an Ounce of Diaſcordium; of Red Coral, <lb/>Dragon's Blood, and Pomegranat-peel, of
            each 2 Drams; <lb/><hi rend="italic">Crocus Martis</hi> aſtringent, 1 Dram; make it into
            a ſoft <lb/>Electuary with Syrup of Coral; of which give the <lb/>Quantity of a Nutmeg
            every Morning, at Five in the <lb/>Afternoon, and the laſt thing at Night, drinking
            after <lb/>it ſix Spoonfuls of the Infuſion of Red Roſes made acid <lb/>with Spirit of
            Vitriol. It will be neceſſary to purge <lb/>twice or thrice before you take the
            Electuary. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To prevent <hi rend="roman">After-pains</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take nine ſingle Piony-ſeeds powder'd, the ſame <lb/>Quantity of Powder of Borax,
            and a little Nutmeg; <lb/>mix all theſe with a little white Anniſeed-water in a
            <lb/>Spoon, and give it the Woman; and after it, as ſoon <lb/>as poſſible after ſhe is
            laid in Bed, a little Anniſeed- <lb/>water. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>For a <hi rend="roman">Looſeneſs</hi>, or <hi rend="roman">Bloody Flux</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take the Yolks of two new-laid Eggs, and put them <lb/>into a Glaſs of ſtrong
            Cinnamon-water, and drink it all; <pb n="4"/>
            <lb/>Brandy, Rum, Roſa-ſolis, or indeed any ſtrong ſpiri- <lb/>tuous Liquor, will do as
            well as Cinnamon-water, and <lb/>does very ſeldom fail. But this ſhould never be uſed,
            <lb/>but in the greateſt Extremity; becauſe chewing of Rhu- <lb/><choice>
              <corr>barb</corr>
              <sic>bard</sic>
            </choice> is as certain, and carries off the Cauſe; and of all <lb/>the ſudden Cures I
            prefer <hi rend="italic">Venice</hi> Treacle. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>Profeſſors <hi rend="roman">Boerhaave</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Oſterdyke's</hi>
            Regimen preſcribed <lb/>for the Gout. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>They are of Opinion that the Gout is not to be cured <lb/>by any other Means but by
            a Milk-Diet, which will in <lb/>twelve Months time alter the whole Maſs of Blood; and,
            <lb/>in order thereto, the following Directions muſt be ſtrict- <lb/>ly obſerv'd and
            follow'd: </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>I. You muſt not taſte any Liquor, only a Mixture of <lb/>one Third Milk, and two
            Thirds Water, your Milk as new <lb/>as you can get it, and to drink it as often as you
            have Oc- <lb/>caſion for it, without adding any other to it. A little <lb/>Tea and
            Coffee is likewiſe permitted, with Milk. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>II. In a Morning as ſoon as awake, and the Stomach <lb/>has made a Digeſtion, you
            muſt drink eight Ounces of <lb/>Spring-Water, and faſt two Hours after; then eat Milk
            <lb/>and Bread, Milk-Pottage, or Tea with Milk, with a <lb/>little Bread and freſh
            Butter. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>III. At Dinner you muſt not eat any thing but what <lb/>is made of Barley, Oats,
            Rice, or Millet Seed, Carrots, <lb/>Potatoes, Turnips, Spinage, Beans, Peaſe, <hi
              rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> You <lb/>may likewiſe eat Fruit when full ripe, baked Pears
            or <lb/>Apples, Apple-Dumplings, but above all, Milk and <lb/>Bisket is very good, but
            nothing ſalt or ſour, not even <lb/>a <hi rend="italic">Seville</hi> Orange. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>IV. At Supper you muſt eat nothing but Milk and <lb/>Bread. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>V. It is neceſſary to go to Bed betimes, even before <lb/>Nine o'Clock, to accuſtom
            yourſelf to ſleep much, and <lb/>uſe yourſelf to it. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>VI. Every Morning before you riſe, to have your <lb/>Feet, Legs, Arms and Hands,
            well rubb'd with Pieces <lb/>of Woollen Cloth, for half an Hour, and the ſame go-
            <lb/>ing to Bed. This Article muſt be ſtrictly obſerv'd, for <lb/>by this Means the
            Humours, Knobs and Bunches will <pb n="5"/>
            <lb/>be diſſipated, and prevent their fixing in the Joints, by <lb/>which they become
            uſeleſs. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>VII. You muſt accuſtom yourſelf to Exerciſe, as ri- <lb/>ding on Horſe-back, which
            is beſt, or in a Coach, <lb/>Chaiſe, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> the more the better;
            but take Care of the <lb/>cold Weather, Winds, and Rain. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Laſtly, In caſe a Fit of the Gout ſhould return, and <lb/>be violent, which they
            are of Opinion will not, then a <lb/>little Doſe of Opium or Laudanum may be taken to
            <lb/>compoſe you; but no oftner than Neceſſity requires. <lb/>They are of Opinion, that
            your Father or Mother ha- <lb/>ving the Gout, is of no Conſequence, if you will re-
            <lb/>ſolve to follow the foregoing Directions ſtrictly. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A famous Water to preſerve the <hi rend="roman">Eye-ſight</hi>; or if loſt, to
            <lb/>reſtore it. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take a Rye Loaf, without Salt or Leaven; cut it into <lb/>thin Slices, and diſtill
            in a cold Still; take off the Wa- <lb/>ter that comes from it, and drop of it into the
            Eyes <lb/>twice or thrice every Day, for a Month together. This <lb/>Water cured a
            Gentleman after he had been blind a <lb/>whole Year. Take alſo a Rag of <hi
              rend="italic">Holland</hi> Cloth, and <lb/>burn it between two Pewter Diſhes, and of
            the Water that <lb/>comes from it, drop a little into the Eye every Night. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To ſtop <hi rend="roman">Vomiting</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take a large Nutmeg, grate away half of it, and <lb/>then toaſt the flat Side till
            the Oil ouze out; then clap <lb/>it to the Pit of the Stomach. Let it lie ſo long as
            'tis <lb/>warm; repeat it often till cured. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A good <hi rend="roman">Cere-Cloth</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take a Pint and half of Sallad Oil, half a Pound of <lb/>Red-led, a Quarter of a
            Pound of White-led, a Quarter <lb/>of a Pound of Caſtle-ſoap, 2 Ounces of Bees-wax, 2
            <lb/>Ounces of Oil of Bays, 2 Ounces of Barrows-greaſe; <lb/>boil the Leads in the Oils
            till they look brown; then <lb/>put in the reſt, keeping it ſtirring till it works; then
            <lb/>make it into Rolls, firſt oiling your Hands. This ſhould <lb/>boil five Hours. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="6"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To make Dr. <hi rend="roman">Pye's</hi> Drink for the <hi rend="roman">Scurvy</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take both the Sorts of Scurvy-graſs, of Brooklime <lb/>and Water-creſſes, of each
            three Handfuls; 12 <hi rend="italic">Seville</hi>
            <lb/>Oranges cut into Pieces; Winters Bark bruiſed, 3 Oun- <lb/>ces; being all put into
            a Bag, infuſe in 3 Gallons of <lb/>new Ale. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Receipt to help the <hi rend="roman">Lungs</hi> of a Perſon in a <hi rend="roman"
              >Con- <lb/>ſumption</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Anniſeeds finely powder'd, Saffron of Steel, <lb/>each half an Ounce, made
            into Pills with <hi rend="italic">Lucatella</hi>'s <lb/>Balſum. Take five of theſe every
            Morning, and at <lb/>Five o'Clock in the Afternoon, drinking a large Draught <lb/>of
            Water acidulated with <hi rend="italic">Mynſicht</hi>'s Elixir of Vitriol. <lb/>—After
            each Doſe Riding is of ſingular Uſe, and <lb/>Cold-bathing; but above all, frequent
            Bleeding in ſmall <lb/>Quantities; for, as is before obſerv'd, whatever keeps <lb/>the
            Lungs cool, is the only Way to cure Conſumptions; <lb/>and it has been of late
            experienc'd, that crude Mercury <lb/>is the moſt beneficial Thing for the Lungs, taking
            one <lb/>Ounce every Morning. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For a <hi rend="roman">Dropſy</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Horſe-radiſh Roots ſliced thin, and ſweet <lb/>Fennel-ſeeds bruiſed, of
            each 2 Ounces, Smallage and <lb/>Fennel-roots ſliced, of each an Ounce; of the Tops of
            <lb/>Thyme, Winter-ſavory, Sweet-marjoram, Water-creſſes, <lb/>and Nettles, of each a
            Handful; bruiſe the Herbs, <lb/>and boil them in 3 Pints of Sack, and 3 of Water, to
            <lb/>the Conſumption of Half. Let it ſtand cloſe cover'd <lb/>for three Hours; then
            ſtrain it, and drink a Draught of <lb/>it twice a Day, ſweeten'd with Syrup of Fennel,
            faſting <lb/>two Hours after it. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>For <hi rend="roman">Deafneſs</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Dip fine, clean black Wool in Civet, put it into the <lb/>Ear, and as it dries,
            which it will do in a Day or two, <lb/>dip it again, and keep it moiſt in the Ear three
            Weeks <lb/>or a Month. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>For a Sore <hi rend="roman">Stomach</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take half a Sheet of Cap-Paper, cut it into the <pb n="7"/>
            <lb/>Shape of an Heart, and dip it in Brandy and old Can- <lb/>dle-greaſe melted
            together, of each an equal Quantity; <lb/>apply it warm to the Pit of the Stomach. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For a <hi rend="roman">Burn</hi> or <hi rend="roman">Scald</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Laurel Leaves, chop them in Hog's Greaſe; <lb/>ſtrain it, and keep it for Uſe.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For the <hi rend="roman">Gripes</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Warm a Glaſs of Canary, diſſolve in it as much <hi rend="italic">Ve- <lb/>nice</hi>
            Treacle or Diaſcordium as an Hazel Nut; drink it <lb/>off going to Bed, and keep warm.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For a Pain or Heat of the <hi rend="roman">Back</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take 3 Drams of Red Sanders, an Handful of Red <lb/>Roſe Leaves; ſteep a whole
            Night in a Pint of Roſe- <lb/>water; ſtrain, and waſh your Back with the Tincture
            <lb/>twice a Day; after once or twice uſing, you will find <lb/>the Heat to diminiſh,
            and your Back to be greatly re- <lb/>freſh'd. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A very good <hi rend="roman">Purge</hi> in a <hi rend="roman">Fever</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Tamarinds 2 Drams, Sena 2 Drams, and Rhu- <lb/>barb 1 Dram; boil theſe in half
            a Pint of Water till <lb/>two Thirds be waſted; to what remains, add half an <lb/>Ounce
            of Cream of Tartar, ſweeten'd with one Ounce <lb/>of the Syrup of Succory, or Syrup of
            Roſes ſolutive; <lb/>ſtrain, and drink it at a Draught; in the Working drink
            <lb/>clarify'd Whey, rather than Poſſet-drink. 'Tis good to <lb/>cool and thin the
            Blood. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A good <hi rend="roman">Vomit</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take 2 Ounces of the fineſt white Allum, beat it <lb/>ſmall, put it into better
            than half a Pint of new Milk, <lb/>ſet it on a ſlow Fire till the Milk is turn'd clear.
            Let <lb/>it ſtand a Quarter of an Hour, ſtrain it off and drink it <lb/>juſt warm. It
            will give three or four Vomits, and is <lb/>very ſafe, and an excellent Cure for an
            Ague, taken <lb/>half an Hour before the Fit; drink good Store of Car- <lb/>duus Tea
            after it. Or elſe take half a Dram of Hypo- <lb/>cocuana, and Carduus Tea with it. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="8"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A try'd Remedy for <hi rend="roman">Gripes</hi> in Children. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take a ſmall Quantity of Oil of Nutmegs and Worm- <lb/>wood; mix them well, and
            warm them a little, and <lb/>anoint the Child's Navel and Stomach. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>The Cure for a <hi rend="roman">Quincey</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>This Diſeaſe requires as high Bleeding as any; you <lb/>muſt likewiſe open both
            Veins under the Tongue. <lb/>Take Frog's Spawn-Water, Red Roſe-water, and Plan-
            <lb/>tane-water, of each 3 Ounces; Syrup of Mulberries <lb/>2 Ounces, the Whites of 3
            Eggs beaten to a Water; <lb/>gargle your Throat often with theſe. Another Garga-
            <lb/>riſm. Take Spring-water 1 Pint, Cream of Tartar 2 <lb/>Drams, Mercury Sublimate
            half a Dram. Levigate <lb/>theſe very fine, then filtre it off for your Uſe. Purg-
            <lb/>ing is very requiſite. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A preſent Remedy for <hi rend="roman">Convulſion-Fits</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Make a Draught of an equal Quantity of Piony and <lb/>ſimple Black-cherry-water;
            and for a Man put thirty, <lb/>for a Woman twenty, for a Child five Drops of Spirit
            <lb/>of Harts-horn. Drink this in or before a Fit. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>An excellent Remedy for the Cure of the <hi rend="roman">Apoplexy</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Cinnabar of Antimony, and of Mercurius Dul- <lb/>cis, of each 1 Scruple, made
            into a Bolus with Conſerve <lb/>of Hips. Give ſuch Things as cauſe Sneezing, as the
            <lb/>Root of Hellebore, or the Leaves of Aſſarabacca pow- <lb/>der'd. Apply bruiſed
            Garlick to the Hand, Wriſts, and <lb/>Soles of the Feet. Likewiſe give the Julep
            deſcribed in <lb/>the Convulſive Aſthma, making it very ſtrong with the <lb/>Spirit of
            Sal Armoniac. Alſo high Bleeding may be of <lb/>Service. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="roman">Ratcliff's</hi> Receipt for a <hi rend="roman">Cold</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Make ſome Sack-whey with Roſemary boil'd in it; <lb/>mix a little of it in a Spoon
            with 20 Grains of Gaſcoin <lb/>Powder; then drink half a Pint of your Sack-whey
            <lb/>with twelve Drops of Spirit of Harts-horn in it; go to <lb/>Bed, and keep warm. Do
            this two or three Nights to- <lb/>gether. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="9"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Medicine for an <hi rend="roman">Ague</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Mix 15 Grains of Salt of <hi rend="italic">Carduus Benedictus</hi>, and Salt
            <lb/>of Wormwood, with half a Scruple of Tartar Vitrio- <lb/>late, and take them in a
            few Spoonfuls of Rheniſh <lb/>Wine, or any other convenient Vehicle, before the Fit,
            <lb/>or at any Time when the Stomach is empty. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To draw up the <hi rend="roman">Uvula</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Ground-Ivy and heat it well between 2 Tiles, <lb/>and lay it as warm as can be
            born on the Top of the <lb/>Head. The Blood of a Hare dry'd and drank in Red- <lb/>wine
            does ſtop the Bloody-Flux, or any Lask, tho' ne- <lb/>ver ſo ſevere. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="roman">Fryar</hi>'s Directions for curing the <hi rend="roman"
              >Fits</hi> of the <hi rend="roman">Mother</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take 2 Drams of Cream of Tartar; diſſolve it in <lb/>half a Pint of Rue-Water; add
            to it 2 Ounces of Trea- <lb/>cle-water, and take it in the Morning faſting. It al-
            <lb/>ways cures Fits at once or twice taking, tho' the Perſon <lb/>has been given over
            for dead. In all languiſhing Fits of <lb/>the Mother and Spleen, give three or four
            Spoonfuls of <lb/>this Julep: Take of Rue, Balm, and Camomile-water, <lb/>of each 3
            Ounces; of the Tincture of Caſtor, 1 Ounce; <lb/>Treacle-water, 2 Ounces; of <hi
              rend="italic">Confectio Alkermes</hi>, 3 <lb/>Drams; Syrup of Gillyflowers, 2 Ounces;
            mix them <lb/>all together. Let the Patient take once or twice a Week, <lb/>four or five
            of theſe Purging Pills: Take of <hi rend="italic">Pill. Ruffii</hi>, <lb/>and <hi
              rend="italic">Fœtidæ</hi>, of each 1 Dram; of Caſtor, and the <lb/>Troches of Myrrh,
            of each half a Dram; of Oyl of <lb/>Amber, a Scruple; of Balſam of <hi rend="italic"
              >Peru</hi>, half a Dram; <lb/>make into Pills, and take them over-night. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To cure the <hi rend="roman">Biting</hi> of a <hi rend="roman">Mad-Dog</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take a Handful of Rue, Sage, and Cinquefoil, 2 <lb/>Garlick Heads, two Penny worth
            of Treacle, and 2 <lb/>Quarts of ſtrong Ale; boil them all together to a Quart;
            <lb/>ſtrain, and give the Perſon three or four Spoonfuls twice <lb/>a Day. Apply ruſty
            Bacon, Agrimony, and Dittany, <lb/>beaten well together, to the Sore, to keep it from
            feſtering. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="10"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For a <hi rend="roman">Blow</hi> or <hi rend="roman">Hurt</hi> in the <hi
              rend="roman">Eye</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Beat the Leaves of Eye-bright with a rotten Apple; <lb/>lay it on the Eye as a
            Poultice. Repeat it as it grows <lb/>dry. The Juice of the Eye-bright is as good as the
            <lb/>Leaves. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>To cure the <hi rend="roman">Rickets</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Make the Drink thus: Take white Horehound and <lb/>Nep, of each 4 Tops; Betony 20
            Leaves; Liver-wort <lb/>and Harts-tongue, of each a good Handful; Polipodi- <lb/>um
            growing upon a Church or Oak, 3 Ounces ſcrap'd; <lb/>boil all theſe together in three
            Quarts of ſweet Wort till <lb/>it is conſumed to two Quarts; then ſtrain it, and when
            <lb/>'tis cold, put to it two Quarts of middling Wort, ſo let it <lb/>work together;
            then put it in a little Veſſel, and when <lb/>it has done working, take half a Quarter
            of an Ounce <lb/>of Rhubarb ſliced very thin; put it in a little Linnen- <lb/>bag, with
            a Stone in it to keep it from ſwimming, and <lb/>hang it in the Veſſel, and when 'tis
            three Days old, let <lb/>the Child drink of it a Quarter of a Pint in the Morn-
            <lb/>ing, and as much at Four o'Clock in the Afternoon, or <lb/>when the Child will take
            it. You muſt likewiſe anoint <lb/>the Child Morning and Night with this following Oint-
            <lb/>ment: Take Butter in the Month of <hi rend="italic">May</hi>, as ſoon as <lb/>it is
            taken out of the Churn, and waſh it with the Dew <lb/>of Wheat; to a Pound of Butter
            take a Handful of red <lb/>Sage, as much of Rue, Camomile, and of ſowed Hyſop; <lb/>boil
            all theſe in the Butter, and ſcum it till 'tis boiled <lb/>clear; then ſtrain it out,
            and keep it in a Gallipot for <lb/>Uſe. You muſt anoint the Reins of the Back and Ribs,
            <lb/>ſtroaking it downwards, and upon the ſmall of the Belly, <lb/>and ſwing the Child
            often with the Heels upwards. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Remedy for <hi rend="roman">Convulſions</hi> in Children. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Give the Child, according to the Age, from 2 to 7 <lb/>Grains of the true Volatile
            Salt of Amber in any pro- <lb/>per Vehicle. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>An effectual Remedy for an old <hi rend="roman">Strain</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Crown-Soap, a Quarter of a Pound; the <lb/>ſtrongeſt Wort that you can get,
            a Pint; of Brandy, 2 <pb n="11"/>
            <lb/>Ounces; let them all boil together. About the latter <lb/>End, add to it Myrrh and
            Bole Armoniack finely pow- <lb/>der'd, of each 3 Drams: Afterwards let it boil to the
            <lb/>Conſiſtence of a Plaiſter; which ſpread upon Sheep's <lb/>Leather, and apply it to
            the Part affected. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A famous Water to clear the <hi rend="roman">Eyeſight</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Aloes and Sugar-candy, of each 3 Drams; <lb/>of Camphire half a Dram; of
            Red Roſe and Eyebright <lb/>Water, of each 3 Ounces; ſhake them very well to-
            <lb/>gether, and waſh your Eyes with it three Times a Day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Remedy for the <hi rend="roman">Jaundice</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Only take 8 Grains of Turbith Mineral, at Four or <lb/>Five in the Afternoon,
            drinking thin Gruel or Poſſet- <lb/>drink between Motions.—After Four or Five Days
            <lb/>repeat the Turbith as above.—In the intermediate <lb/>Days take half a large
            Spoonful of <hi rend="italic">Mynſicht</hi>'s Elixir of <lb/>Vitriol, in half a Pint of
            Spring Water, three Times a <lb/>Day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For a <hi rend="roman">Bruiſe</hi> occaſion'd by a <hi rend="roman">Fall</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Horſe-dung and Sheep's Suet, of each equal <lb/>Parts; boil them well
            together, and apply warm to the <lb/>Part affected, like a Poultice. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To ſtop <hi rend="roman">Bleeding</hi> inwardly. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take 2 Drams of Henbane-ſeed, and the like of <lb/>white Poppy-ſeed; beat them up
            with Conſerve of Ro- <lb/>ſes, and give the Quantity of a Nutmeg at a Time; or <lb/>take
            12 Handfuls of Plantane Leaves, and 6 Ounces of <lb/>freſh Comfry-roots; beat theſe, and
            ſtrain out the Juice, <lb/>and add to it ſome fine Sugar, and drink it off. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To draw out a <hi rend="roman">Thorn</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take a little Black Soap, and chew ſome Nut-ker- <lb/>nels to mix with the Soap,
            and lay it on to the Place <lb/>griev'd; repeat it till the Thorn comes out. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic hanging space">
            <lb/>A Receipt that cured a Gentleman, who had for a long <lb/>time ſpit <hi
              rend="roman">Blood</hi> in a great Quantity, and was ſo waſted <pb n="12"/>
            <lb/>with a Conſumption, that Dr. <hi rend="roman">Willis</hi> declared it was
            <lb/>impoſſible for him to recover. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Hyſſop-water, and of the pureſt Honey, of <lb/>each a Pint; of Agrimony and
            Coltsfoot, of each an <lb/>Handful; a Sprig of Rue, brown Sugar-candy, Li- <lb/>quoriſh
            ſliced, Shavings of Harts-horn, of each 2 Oun- <lb/>ces; Anniſeeds bruiſed, 1 Ounce; of
            Figs ſliced, and <lb/>Raiſins of the Sun ſton'd, of each 4 Ounces; put them <lb/>all
            into a Pipkin with a Gallon of Water, and boil it <lb/>gently over a moderate Fire, till
            Half is conſumed; then <lb/>ſtrain it, and when it is cold, put it into Bottles, being
            <lb/>cloſe ſtopt; take Four or Five Spoonfuls every Morning, <lb/>at Four in the
            Afternoon, and at Night the laſt thing. <lb/>If you add freſh Water to the Ingredients
            after the firſt <lb/>Liquor is ſtrain'd off, you will have a pleaſant Drink to <lb/>be
            uſed at any time when you are a-dry. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For the <hi rend="roman">Green-Sickneſs</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Centaury the leſs, and Wormwood and Roſe- <lb/>mary-flowers, of each 1
            Handful; Gentian-root 1 Dram; <lb/>Coriander-ſeeds 2 Drams; boil theſe in a Quart of Wa-
            <lb/>ter; ſweeten it with Syrup of Steel, and take Four or <lb/>Five Spoonfuls in the
            Morning, and as much in the Af- <lb/>ternoon. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Receipt for the Cure of the <hi rend="roman">Stone</hi> and <hi rend="roman"
              >Gravel</hi>, whether <lb/>in the Ureters, Kidnies, or Bladder. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Marſh-mallow Leaves, the Herb Mercury, Saxi- <lb/>frage and Pellitory of the
            Wall, of each, freſh gather'd, <lb/>3 Handfuls; cut them ſmall with a Pair of Sciſſars,
            and <lb/>mix them together, and pound them in a clean Stone <lb/>Mortar with a wooden
            Peſtle, till they come to a Maſh; <lb/>then take them out, and ſpread them thin in a
            broad <lb/>glaz'd Earthen Pan, and let them lie, ſtirring them about <lb/>once a Day,
            till they are thoroughly dry, (but not in the <lb/>Sun) and then they are ready, and
            will keep good all <lb/>the Year long. Of ſome of theſe Ingredients ſo dried, <lb/>make
            Tea, as you do common Tea, with boiling hot <lb/>Water, as ſtrong as you like to drink
            it; but the ſtron- <lb/>ger the better, and drink three, four, or more Tea-Cups
            <lb/>full of it, Blood warm, ſweetened with coarſe Sugar, <pb n="13"/>
            <lb/>every Morning and Afternoon, putting into each Cup of <lb/>it, at leaſt half a
            Spoonful, or rather more, of the ex- <lb/>preſs'd Oil of Beech Nuts, freſh drawn, (which
            in this <lb/>Caſe has been experienced to be vaſtly preferable to Oil <lb/>of Almonds,
            or any other Oil) ſtirring them about to- <lb/>gether, and ſo to continue it for as long
            as you ſee Oc- <lb/>caſion. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>For a <hi rend="roman">Swelling</hi> in the Face. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take a Handful of Damask-Roſe Leaves; boil them <lb/>in running Water till they are
            tender; ſtamp them <lb/>to a Pulp, and boil white Bread and Milk till 'tis ſoft;
            <lb/>then put in your Pulp with a little Hog's-Lard, and <lb/>thicken it with the Yolk
            of an Egg, and apply it warm. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To abate the Heat and Violence of <hi rend="roman">Fevers</hi>, by Dr. <hi
              rend="roman">Ed. K.</hi>
          </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Gaſcoign-Powder and of Coral prepar'd, of <lb/>each 1 Dram and a half; of
            purified Niter, or Salt Pru- <lb/>nella, 1 Dram; White Sugar finely powder'd, 6 Drams;
            <lb/>mix, and divide them into 8 equal Parts, of which one is <lb/>to be taken every ſix
            Hours in any convenient Vehicle. <lb/>If the Fever proves peſtilential, let there be
            added to the <lb/>aforeſaid Powders of the Roots of Contrayerva and Vir- <lb/>ginian
            Snakeweed, each 1 Dram. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Draught of the Salts in a <hi rend="roman">Fever</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Black Cherry Water 2 Ounces; Compound Piony <lb/>Water, 1 Ounce; Salt of
            Harts-horn, 1 Scruple; Salt <lb/>of Wormwood, half a Dram; Salt of Amber 3 Grains;
            <lb/>Spirit of Sulphur, 15 Drops: Take this Draught every <lb/>ſix Hours, till you have
            taken eight or ten Draughts. <lb/>This has done very great Cures without the Bark, where
            <lb/>the Fever is <choice>
              <corr>occaſion'd</corr>
              <sic>occafion'd</sic>
            </choice> by a great Cold; it ſweetens and <lb/>cools the Blood, and revives the Spirits
            and Head to Ad- <lb/>miration. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>To ſtop <hi rend="roman">Flooding</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Diſſolve a Quarter of an Ounce of <hi rend="italic">Venice</hi> Treacle in <lb/>4
            Spoonfuls of Water, and drop in it thirty or forty of <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Jones</hi>'s Drops. Take it when Occaſion requires, eſpe- <lb/>cially in Child-bed.
          </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="14"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Preſervative againſt the <hi rend="roman">Peſtilence</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Rue, Sage, Mint, Roſemary, Wormwood <lb/>and Lavender, of each 1 Handful;
            infuſe them in a <lb/>Gallon of the beſt white Wine Vinegar; put all into <lb/>a Stone
            Bottle cloſely cover'd and paſted; ſet the Bottle, <lb/>thus cloſed, upon warm Aſhes for
            eight Days together. <lb/>After which, ſtrain it through a Flannel, and put the
            <lb/>Liquor into Bottles, and to every Quart put an Ounce of <lb/>Camphire; then cork
            the Bottles very cloſe, and it will <lb/>keep ſome Years. With this Preparation waſh
            your <lb/>Mouth, rub your Temples and your Loins every Day; <lb/>ſnuff a little up your
            Noſtrils when you go into the Air, <lb/>and carry about you a Sponge dipt in the ſame,
            when <lb/>you deſire to refreſh the Smell upon any Occaſion, eſpe- <lb/>cially when near
            to any Place or Perſon that is infected. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Cure for the <hi rend="roman">Bite</hi> of a <hi rend="roman">Mad Dog</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take 1 Dram of Aſh-colour'd Liverwort, 1 Dram of <lb/>common Pepper in a Pint of
            warm Milk; repeat this <lb/>for Nine or Twelve Mornings ſucceſſively, uſing a cold
            <lb/>Bath at the ſame time. This Preſcription has a very <lb/>eminent Phyſician now
            living, for its Author, and he ne- <lb/>ver knew it fail, if taken before the Symptoms
            ap- <lb/>pear'd. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>An eaſy and approved Remedy for the <hi rend="roman">Rheumatiſm</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take 5 Ounces of Stone Brimſtone, reduce it to a fine <lb/>Powder, divide it into
            fourteen equal Parts, take one Part <lb/>every Morning in Spring-water. Continue it as
            you find <lb/>proper. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To make <hi rend="roman">Gripe-Water</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take 2 Dozen Bunches of Penny-royal ſhred groſly; <lb/>then take Coriander-ſeeds,
            Anniſeeds, Sweet Fennel-ſeeds, <lb/>and Carraway-ſeeds; bruiſe them all, and put them to
            <lb/>the Herbs in an Earthen Pot; mix them together, and <lb/>ſprinkle on them a Quart
            of Brandy; let them ſtand all <lb/>Night; the next Day diſtil it off, and take ſix,
            ſeven, <lb/>or eight Spoonfuls of this Water ſweeten'd with Syrup of <lb/>Gilliflowers.
            Drink it warm, and go to Bed; cover <lb/>very warm to ſweat if you can; and drink ſome
            of it <lb/>as long as the Gripes continue. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="15"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To give certain Eaſe in the <hi rend="roman">Tooth-ach</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take <hi rend="italic">French</hi> Flies, Mithridate, and a few Drops of
            <lb/>Vinegar; beat this to a Paſte, and lay a Plaiſter on the <lb/>Cheek-bone, or behind
            the Ear. 'Twill bliſter, but ſel- <lb/>dom ſails to cure. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To cure the <hi rend="roman">Shingles</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take the Juice of Houſleek, temper it with a ſuffi- <lb/>cient Quantity of
            Barley-meal, till it comes to the Con- <lb/>ſiſtence of a Cataplaſm; apply it to the
            Part affected, <lb/>renewing it every 24 Hours. Or, take half a Pint of <lb/>Elder
            flower Water, and an Ounce of <hi rend="italic">Hungary</hi> Water, <lb/>mix and dab the
            Part with it often. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="roman">Wadenfield</hi>'s Remedy for <hi rend="roman">Lunacy</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Ground-Ivy 3 large Handfuls ſhred ſmall; <lb/>boif it in 2 Quarts of white
            Wine, till two Parts in three <lb/>be conſumed. Strain, and add to it 6 Ounces of the
            beſt <lb/>Salled Oil; boil it up to an Ointment; let the Patient's <lb/>Head be ſhaved,
            rub and chafe it with the Ointment <lb/>made warm. Then take freſh Herbs, bruiſed and
            ap- <lb/>plied Plaiſterwiſe, tying it on the Top of the Head very <lb/>hard. Repeat this
            every other Day, ten or twelve <lb/>Times; give the Patient three Spoonfuls of the Juice
            of <lb/>Ground-Ivy every Morning faſting, in a Glaſs of Beer <lb/>for the firſt ten
            Days. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>An Electuary for a Pain in the <hi rend="roman">Stomach</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Conſerve of Wood-ſorrel and Mithridate an e- <lb/>qual Quantity; mix it well
            together, and take it Night <lb/>and Morning the Quantity of a Nutmeg; ſo do for fif-
            <lb/>teen Days together. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For a Pain of the <hi rend="roman">Side</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Stone-horſe Dung half a Pound; infuſe 12 <lb/>Hours in a Quart of the
            diſtill'd Water of Carduus, and <lb/>ſweeten with Syrup of Violets. Drink a Draught of
            it <lb/>every four Hours, till the Pain be abated. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="16"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For a <hi rend="roman">Thruſh</hi> in Childrens Mouths. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take a hot Sea-Coal, and quench it in as much Spring <lb/>Water as will cover the
            Coal; waſh it with this five or <lb/>ſix Times a Day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To cure an <hi rend="roman">Aſthma</hi>, or Shortneſs of Breath, by Dr. <hi
              rend="roman">H. S.</hi>
          </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take 3 Ounces of Linſeed-Oil freſh drawn; of Bal- <lb/>ſamick Syrup 1 Ounce, or
            Sugar-candy powder'd half <lb/>an Ounce; mingle them very well, and give a Spoonful
            <lb/>of it often. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Poultice for a <hi rend="roman">Sore Breaſt</hi> before 'tis broken. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Boil white Bread and Milk to a Poultice, then put to <lb/>it Oil of Lillies, and
            the Yolk of an Egg; ſet it over <lb/>the Fire again to heat, and apply it as hot as can
            be en- <lb/>dured. Dreſs it Morning and Night till 'tis broke, then <lb/>dreſs it with
            the Poultice of Raiſins. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For a <hi rend="roman">Sore Breaſt</hi> when 'tis broken. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take a Quarter of a Pound of Raiſins of the Sun <lb/>ſtoned, and beat them very
            ſmall; then add to it near <lb/>as much Honey, and beat it together into a Salve;
            <lb/>ſpread it on a Cloth, and make Tents if Occaſion. Dreſs <lb/>it once a Day; when
            'tis well drawn, uſe the Yellow <lb/>Balſam, and Black or Leaden Plaiſter. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For a freſh <hi rend="roman">Strain</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Linſeed Oil, and rectified Spirit of Wine, <lb/>of each 2 Ounces; Oil of
            Spike 1 Ounce; mix, and <lb/>rub the Part very well with it, and lay to it a Plaiſter of
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">Paracelſus</hi>, with an equal Part of <hi rend="italic"
              >Adburnium</hi>. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For <hi rend="roman">Sore Nipples</hi>, or <hi rend="roman">Kibe Heels</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take a Pint of the beſt Sallad Oil, half a Pound of <lb/>Red Lead, 1 Ounce of Red
            Sealing Wax, and an Ounce <lb/>of Roſin, 6 Ounces of Bees-wax: Put all theſe together,
            <lb/>and let them boil to a Salve; as ſoon as ever it turns <lb/>black, 'tis enough;
            then put it out preſently, or 'twill <lb/>be too hard. When you uſe it, you muſt melt
            it, and <lb/>anoint the Place griev'd, with your Finger ſpread it on <pb n="17"/>
            <lb/>a Cloth, and keep a Plaiſter on it. This may be very <lb/>good; but I think nothing
            ſo effectually cures Kibe <lb/>Heels, as doing them with Camphiriz'd Spirits before
            <lb/>they break. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To provoke the <hi rend="roman">Terms</hi>, and bring away the <hi rend="roman"
              >After-Birth</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Let the Patient take half a Dram of the Troches of <lb/>Myrrh, made into a Bolus
            with Syrup of Mug-wort, <lb/>every Morning and Evening, drinking 4 Spoonfuls of <lb/>the
            following Mixture after it: Take of the Waters of <lb/>Penny-royal and Rue, each 4
            Ounces; of Compound <lb/>Briony-water 3 Ounces; Tincture of Saffron 1 Ounce; <lb/>Syrup
            of Marſh-mallows 2 Ounces. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A good Drink in the <hi rend="roman">Rickets</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Currants and Raiſins of the Sun ſton'd, of each <lb/>1 Handful; Maiden-hair,
            Yarrow, and Speedwell, of <lb/>each 1 Handful; a large Handful of Liver-wort; a
            <lb/>Handful of Dragons Leaves; 9 Leaves of Harts-tongue; <lb/>a Spoonful of Aniſeeds,
            and an Ounce of Liquorice <lb/>ſliced; boil all theſe in three Quarts of ſmall Ale, till
            <lb/>half be conſumed; then ſtrain it, and put it in little <lb/>Bottles, and drink a
            Draught of it every Morning, and <lb/>at Four in the Afternoon. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For a <hi rend="roman">Rheumatiſm</hi>, or Pain in the Bones. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take a Quart of Milk, boil it and turn it with 3 <lb/>Pints of Small Beer; then
            ſtrain the Poſſet on ſeven <lb/>or nine Globules of Stone-Horſe Dung tied up in a
            <lb/>Cloth, and boil it a Quarter of an Hour in the Poſſet- <lb/>drink; when 'tis taken
            off the Fire, preſs the Cloth <lb/>hard, and drink half a Pint of this Morning and Night
            <lb/>hot in Bed. If you pleaſe, you may add white Wine <lb/>to it. This Medicine is not
            good, if troubled with the <lb/>Stone. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An experienc'd Water for a <hi rend="roman">Sore Mouth</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take half a Pint of white Wine Vinegar; of Roch- <lb/>Alum the Quantity of a Nut;
            of Red Sage, Colum- <lb/>bine, and Violet Leaves, of each a ſmall Handful; boil
            <lb/>them together, about the latter End add a Spoonful of <pb n="18"/>
            <lb/>Honey; ſtrain, and ſweeten with a little fine Sugar, and <lb/>waſh your Mouth with
            it every Morning and Evening. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>The Compoſing Draught for the <hi rend="roman">Cholick</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take 2 large Spoonfuls of Mint-water, 2 of Hyſte- <lb/>rickWater, 1 of Oil of Sweet
            Almonds, and 1 Ounce <lb/>of Syrup of Diacodium; if 'tis for a Man, add 10 Drops <lb/>of
            liquid Laudanum, and 20 Drops of Spirit of Harts- <lb/>horn; if for a Woman, only 20
            Drops of Tincture of <lb/>Caſtor; add alſo for either 2 or 3 Drops of Oil of Ju-
            <lb/>niper. Drink this Draught, and, under God, you may <lb/>abſolutely depend on Reſt
            and Eaſe, and a ſafe Cure; <lb/>for the ſame does ſo gently make its Paſſage, as, by
            <lb/>Repetition, is ſure to carry off that ſharp Humour that <lb/>was the Cauſe of this
            Tumult in the Bowels; and then <lb/>an Opiat may be ſafely given, when this Operation is
            <lb/>over; but before, 'tis dangerous. I would very earneſtly <lb/>recommend this
            Method, becauſe 'twas thirty Years the <lb/>ſucceſsful Practice of an excellent
            Apothecary. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A very good Water againſt a <hi rend="roman">Conſumption</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take 3 Pints of the beſt Canary, and a Pint of Mint- <lb/>water, 3 Ounces of
            candy'd Eringo-Roots, 3 Ounces of <lb/>Dates, a Quarter of an Ounce of Mace, 3 Ounces of
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">China</hi> Roots, 3 Ounces of Raiſins ſtoned: Infuſe theſe
            <lb/>twelve Hours in an earthen Pot cloſe covered over a gen- <lb/>tle Fire; when 'tis
            cold, ſtrain it out, and keep it in a <lb/>clean Pan, or Glaſs Jar for uſe. Then make
            about a <lb/>Quart of plain Jelly of Harts-horn, and drink a Quar- <lb/>ter of a Pint of
            this Liquor with a large Spoonful of <lb/>Jelly Night and Morning for two or three
            Months. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To make a Poultice of Turnips, which both ripens and diſ- <lb/>cuſſes any <hi
              rend="roman">hard Swelling</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take 6 large Turnips, ſcrape them clean, and boil them <lb/>in powder'd Beef Broth
            till they are tender; then take <lb/>them out and ſcrape them again, and being bruiſed,
            put <lb/>them into a Pipkin, with a Quarter of a Pound of Mutton- <lb/>Suet ſhred ſmall,
            and 1 Ounce of <hi rend="italic">Venice</hi> Turpentine; <lb/>boil them well together,
            adding 2 Ounces of Oil of Ro- <lb/>ſes. Lay this to the Part affected twice a Day, as
            hot <pb n="19"/>
            <lb/>as it can be endured. This will in a ſhort Time either <lb/>diſcuſs the Humour, or,
            if it tends to Suppuration, will <lb/>both break and heal it. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To make Lozenges ſor the <hi rend="roman">Heart-burn</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of white Sugar-candy 1 Pound, Chalk 3 Oun- <lb/>ces, Bole-armoniac 5 Scruples,
            Crabs-eyes 1 Ounce, Red <lb/>Coral 4 Scruples, Nutmegs 1 Scruple, Pearl 2 Scruples;
            <lb/>let all theſe be beaten and ſifted, and made all into a <lb/>Paſte with a little
            Spring-water, roll it out and cut your <lb/>Lozenges out with a Thimble; lay them to
            dry. Eat <lb/>four or five at a Time as often as you pleaſe. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To cure a <hi rend="roman">Pain</hi> of the <hi rend="roman">Head</hi>, which
            returns at ſet Times <lb/>like an Ague. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take 2 Scruples of Jeſuit's Bark, make it into a Bo- <lb/>lus, with a ſufficient
            Quantity of Syrup of Gillyflowers. <lb/>To be repeated every ſix Hours; being conſtantly
            taken <lb/>for three Days, it ſeldom fails of Succeſs. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Poſſet-drink to be taken before the Fit of an <hi rend="roman">Ague</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Pour a Gallon of clear Poſtet-drink upon 4 large <lb/>Handfuls of Angelica ſhred
            ſmall; let it infuſe till 'tis <lb/>very ſtrong. Let the Perſon, if poſſible, drink all,
            that <lb/>the Stomach may be perfectly clear; and go into a warm <lb/>Bed as ſoon as the
            Vomit has done working. Cover <lb/>yourſelf cloſe, and try to ſweat. It has ſeldom
            fail'd, <lb/>and is a ſafe Vomit. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>An Electuary for a <hi rend="roman">Cold</hi>, or <hi rend="roman">Windy
              Stomach</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Gum-Ganicum 1 Ounce, Cubebs a Quarter of <lb/>an Ounce, Cardamums a Quarter of
            an Ounce; beat <lb/>and ſift all theſe, and mix it with Syrup of Gillyflowers <lb/>into
            an Electuary. Take Night and Morning the Quan- <lb/>tity of a Nutmeg; drink a little
            warm Ale after it. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For a <hi rend="roman">Weakneſs</hi>, or <hi rend="roman">Giddineſs</hi> in the <hi
              rend="roman">Head</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take dry'd Roſemary Tops and Roſe-Leaves, La- <lb/>vender Flowers, Red Sage and
            Mint, of each 1 Hand- <lb/>ful; of Cloves, Nutmegs, Maſtick, Benjamin and Sto- <pb
              n="20"/>
            <lb/>rax, of each half an Ounce; Bruiſe them well; and be- <lb/>ing quilted in red
            Sarcenet, wear next your Head. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>An admirable <hi rend="roman">Snuff</hi> for the <hi rend="roman">Head</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Sage, Roſemary, Lillies of the Valley, the <lb/>Tops of Sweet-marjoram, of
            each half an Ounce; of <lb/>Nutmeg and of Aſarabacca-roots, each 1 Dram; dry <lb/>them,
            and reduce them to a very fine Powder. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To prevent <hi rend="roman">Miſcarrying</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Dragon's-blood the Weight of a Silver Two- <lb/>pence, and a Dram of red
            Coral; the Weight of 2 <lb/>Barley-corns of Ambergreaſe, the Weight of 3 Barley-
            <lb/>corns of <hi rend="italic">Eaſt-India</hi> Bezoar; make all theſe into a very
            <lb/>fine Powder, and mix them well together, and keep <lb/>them cloſe in a Box; and if
            you are frightned, or need <lb/>it, take as much at a Time as will lie on a Penny, and
            <lb/>keep very ſtill and quiet. Take it in a Caudle made <lb/>with Muſcadine or Tent,
            and the Shucks of Almonds <lb/>dried and beaten to Powder, and thicken it with the
            <lb/>Yolks of Eggs: Take it in the Morning faſting, and <lb/>at Night going to Bed. This
            do till you are out of <lb/>Danger, and lay the following Plaiſter to the Back:
            <lb/>Take <hi rend="italic">Venice</hi> Turpentine, and mix with it Bole-Armo-
            <lb/>niac, and ſpread it on black-brown Paper the Length <lb/>and Breadth of a Hand, and
            lay it to the Small of the <lb/>Back, keeping Bed. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>An approved Medicine to bring away a <hi rend="roman">dead Child</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Betony, Hyſſop, and Vervain, of each a ſmall <lb/>Handful; boil them in a Pint
            of white Wine to half a <lb/>Pint, and give to the Patient to drink. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To procure the <hi rend="roman">Menſes</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take a Quarter of an Ounce of pure Myrrh made <lb/>into fine Powder; mix it with 3
            Quarters of an Ounce of <lb/>Conſerve of Bugloſs-flowers; two Days before your Ex-
            <lb/>pectation take this Quantity at four Times, laſt at Night, <lb/>and firſt in the
            Morning. Drink after each Time a <lb/>Draught of Poſſet-drink made of Ale, white Wine
            and <pb n="21"/>
            <lb/>Milk, and boil in it ſome Penny-royal, and a few Ca- <lb/>momile Flowers. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For St. <hi rend="roman">Anthony's Fire</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take one Part fine Spirit or Oil of Turpentine, and <lb/>one Part finely rectify'd
            Spirit of Wine; mix and ſhake <lb/>the Glaſs when you uſe it, anointing the Face gently
            <lb/>with a Feather, or your Finger, not covering it. Do <lb/>it often, and it cures in
            a Day or two; but take Care <lb/>not to come near your Eyes. It ſoftens and heals, tho'
            <lb/>at firſt you think it inflames. You may put more or leſs <lb/>Spirit of Wine, as
            you like. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To provoke <hi rend="roman">Urine</hi> preſently when ſtopped. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In a Quart of Beer boil a Handful of the Berries of <lb/>Eglantine till it comes to
            a Pint; drink it off lukewarm. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For an <hi rend="roman">inward Bruiſe</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of <hi rend="italic">Iriſh</hi> Slate, <hi rend="italic">Sperma Ceti</hi>, of
            each half a <lb/>Dram; make into a Bolus with a Dram of <hi rend="italic">Venice</hi>
            Trea- <lb/>cle. To be taken every Night, drinking a Draught <lb/>of <hi rend="italic"
              >Brunſwick</hi> Beer after it. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To cure an <hi rend="roman">Intermitting Ague</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Fever</hi>,
            without returning. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Jeſuits Bark in fine Powder 1 Ounce, Salt of <lb/>Steel and <hi rend="italic"
              >Jamaica</hi> Pepper, of each a Quarter of an <lb/>Ounce, Treacle of Moloſſoes 4
            Ounces; mix theſe to- <lb/>ge<choice>
              <corr>t</corr>
              <sic> </sic>
            </choice>her, and take the Quantity of a Nutmeg three times <lb/>a Day when the Fit is
            off, and a Draught of warm Ale <lb/>or white Wine after it. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To cure the <hi rend="roman">Falling-Sickneſs</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take the Powder of Miſletoe of the Oak, of Man's <lb/>Skull prepar'd, of each 1
            Dram: Give a Scruple of it <lb/>every Morning in a Quarter of a Pint of Peony Water;
            <lb/>give more or leſs, according to the Age of the Patient. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To cure <hi rend="roman">Burſtenneſs</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Hemlock, and bruiſe it a little; heat it pretty <lb/>well, and apply it twice
            a Day, without any Truſs, and <pb n="22"/>
            <lb/>keep the Party as ſtill as may be. This has cured, when <lb/>many other Things have
            failed. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A moſt excellent <hi rend="roman">Proceſs</hi> in a <hi rend="roman"
              >Conſumption</hi>. </head>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>The Conſerve. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Conſerve of Hips, 6 Ounces. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>The Milk-Water. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Take dry'd Mint 1 Handful, Ground-Ivy 3 Hand- <lb/>fuls, 6 Nutmegs ſliced, 1
              Quart of Snails clean'd and <lb/>bruis'd; diſtil theſe in a Gallon of Milk, and a
              Quart <lb/>of white Wine. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center">
              <lb/>The Syrup. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Take Balſam of Tolu half an Ounce; boil it in 2 <lb/>Pints of Barley-water, till
              half be boiled away; ſtrain <lb/>and add to it as much Sugar as will make it a weak
              <lb/>Syrup. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center">
              <lb/>The Pectoral Pills. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Take Pill of Storax and of Hounds-tongue, each <lb/>half a Dram; mix them, and
              make it into twelve Pills. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>The Purging Pills. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Take Pill Rufus 2 Drams, Salt of Tartar half a Scru- <lb/>ple, Chymical Oil of
              Marjoram 3 Drops; as much Sy- <lb/>rup of Rhubarb as will make it into Pills. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>The Powder. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Take Powder of Crabs-Eyes 1 Ounce, prepar'd Pearl <lb/>a Quarter of an Ounce,
              white Sugar-candy 1 Ounce; <lb/>mix theſe all into a fine Powder. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>The Directions how to take all. </head>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Take as much of the Powder as will lie on a Sixpence <lb/>in half a Pint of Aſs's
              or Cow's Milk, and Barley-wa- <lb/>ter, every Morning; take as much of the Conſerve as
              <lb/>a Cheſnut, thrice every Day, and drink after it ſome of <lb/>the Milk-water,
              ſweeten'd with the Balſamick Syrup; <lb/>take three of the Pectoral Pills going to
              Reſt; and re- <lb/>peat the Doſe, if your Cough diſturbs your Reſt; and <lb/>once a
              Week take four of the Purging Pills at Night; <pb n="23"/>
              <lb/>make an Iſſue in the Arm; and once in a Month, or ſix <lb/>Weeks, take three or
              four Ounces of Blood away. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>This is ſo ſafe and valuable a Method, that I ſhall on- <lb/>ly ſay, that every
              good Judgment muſt approve it. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Drink to preſerve the <hi rend="roman">Lungs</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take 3 Pints of Spring-water, put to it 1 Ounce of <lb/>Flower of Sulphur, and let
            it boil on a ſlow Fire till <lb/>Half is conſumed; then let it ſtand to ſettle, and
            ſtrain <lb/>it out, and pour it on 1 Ounce of Liquoriſh ſcraped, and <lb/>a Dram of
            Coriander-ſeeds, and as many Anniſeeds <lb/>bruiſed. Let it ſtand to ſettle, and drink a
            Quarter of <lb/>a Pint Morning and Night. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>An excellent Medicine for the <hi rend="roman">ſpotted</hi>, and all other <hi
              rend="roman">ma- <lb/>lignant Fevers</hi>, preſcribed by Dr. <hi rend="roman"
              >B—re</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the beſt Virginia Snake-weed and Root of <lb/>Contrayerva finely powder'd,
            of each half a Scruple; <lb/>Goa Stone half a Scruple; Caſtor and Camphire, of each
            <lb/>5 Grains; make them into a Bolus with a Scruple of <hi rend="italic">Ve-
              <lb/>nice</hi> Treacle, and as much Syrup of Peony as is ſuffici- <lb/>ent: To repeat
            the Bolus every ſix Hours, drinking a <lb/>Draught of the following Julep after it: Take
            of Scor- <lb/>zonera Roots 2 Ounces; Butterbur Roots half an Ounce; <lb/>of Balm and
            Scordium of each an Handful; of Cori- <lb/>ander-ſeeds 3 Drams; of Liquoriſh, Figs, and
            Raiſins, <lb/>of each an Ounce: Let them boil in 3 Pints of Con- <lb/>duit-water to a
            Quart; then ſtrain it, and add to it, <lb/>Compound Peony-water 3 Ounces, Syrup of
            Rasber- <lb/>ries an Ounce and half. Let the Patient drink of it <lb/>plentifully. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>The Method of Cure in the <hi rend="roman">Spotted Small-Pox</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>In this Diſtemper bleed in large Quantities, keeping <lb/>the Patient very cool,
            and conſtantly plying him with <lb/>cool Tankards, and ſuch diluting Liquors, giving
            every <lb/>Evening about Five o'Clock, an Ounce, or an Ounce <lb/>and an half of
            Diacodium. If that does not procure <lb/>Reſt, after three Hours repeat it. Sharpen all
            his Malt <lb/>Liquors with Spirit of Vitriol. If it be of the Flux or <lb/>Anomalous
            Kind, the ſeventh Day give him Mercurius <pb n="24"/>
            <lb/>Dulcis and Cinnabar of Antimony, of each half a Scru- <lb/>ple, made into a Bolus
            with any Conſerve; and do the <lb/>like again the thirteenth Day. The tenth Day you may
            <lb/>begin to uſe the following Cordial in ſmall Quantities: <lb/>Take Cowſlip-water,
            Mint-water, Black-Cherry-water, <lb/>of each 3 Ounces; Plague-water and Aqua Mirabilis,
            <lb/>of each an Ounce and a half prepared; Pearl a Dram <lb/>and a half ſweetned with
            fine Sugar. You may ſome- <lb/>times take a Glaſs of Wine, agreeable to a known Max-
            <lb/>im in Phyſick: <hi rend="italic">In declinatione Morbi quo magis calefacis <lb/>eo
              magis Concoctionem promoves</hi>. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>When the laſt critical Day is over, bleed to about <lb/>twelve Ounces, the next Day
            purge, with that ſet down <lb/>in the Gout, taking a quieting Draught of Diacodium
            <lb/>at Night when the Purging is over. Purging and Bleed- <lb/>ing after this, muſt
            upon no Account be omitted; other- <lb/>wiſe the Patient will break out in Boils, and
            will have <lb/>very ſore and weak Eyes for a conſiderable Time. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>An excellent Remedy for <hi rend="roman">Whooping Coughs</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take dried Coltsfoot Leaves a good Handful, cut <lb/>them ſmall, and boil them in a
            Pint of Spring-water, <lb/>till half a Pint is boiled away; then take it off the Fire,
            <lb/>and when it is almoſt cold, ſtrain it thro' a Cloth, ſqueez- <lb/>ing the Herb as
            dry as you can; and then throw it a- <lb/>way, and diſſolve in the Liquor an Ounce of
            brown Su- <lb/>gar-candy finely powder'd, and then give the Child, (if <lb/>it be about
            three or four Years old, and ſo in Propor- <lb/>tion) one Spoonful of it cold or warm,
            as the Seaſon <lb/>proves, three or four Times a Day (or oftner if the Fits <lb/>of
            Coughing come frequently) till well; which will be <lb/>in two or three Days, but it
            will preſently almoſt abate <lb/>the Fits of Coughing. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A bitter <hi rend="roman">Draught</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Leaves of <hi rend="italic">Roman</hi> Wormwood, the Tops <lb/>of
            Centaury and St. John's-wort, of each a ſmall Hand- <lb/>ful, Roots of Gentian ſliced 2
            Drams, Carraway-ſeeds <lb/>half an Ounce: Infuſe theſe in Half a Pint of Rheniſh,
            <lb/>and 3 Pints of white Wine for four or five Days; take a <pb n="25"/>
            <lb/>Quarter of a Pint in a Morning, filling up the Bottle, and <lb/>it will ſerve two
            or three Months. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For <hi rend="roman">rotten</hi> or <hi rend="roman">corrupt Gums</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Roots of round Birthwort and Pomgra- <lb/>nate Bark, of each half an
            Ounce, of Sage Leaves and <lb/>Bramble Tops, of each 1 Handful; of Roch Allum 1
            <lb/>Dram: Boil them in a Quart of Smith's Forge Water, <lb/>till one third Part is
            waſted; ſtrain it, and put to it 2 <lb/>Ounces of Honey of Roſes; mix them well
            together, <lb/>and waſh your Mouth with it ſeveral Times a Day. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For <hi rend="roman">Coſtiveneſs</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Pulp of Caſſia, newly extracted an Ounce <lb/>and half; of Cremor
            Tartari 2 Drams; mix, and give <lb/>the Quantity of a large Nutmeg every Day about an
            <lb/>Hour before Dinner. Continue taking it for a Week <lb/>together. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Receipt to cure the <hi rend="roman">Evil</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Mercurius Dulcis 1 Dram, Antimony revived <lb/>half a Dram. You may give of
            this Medicine three, <lb/>four, or five Grains, according to the Age or Strength <lb/>of
            the Patient. Take this twice a Week. In the inter- <lb/>mediate Days uſe the Diet-Drink
            following: </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>The Diet-Drink. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the Leaves of Senna half a Pound, the Root <lb/>of Monks Rheubarb 7 Ounces,
            the Roots of the ſharp- <lb/>pointed Dock, the Root of Polypody of the Oak, of <lb/>each
            4 Ounces; the Roots of Mizerion 3 Ounces and a <lb/>half; Rue leav'd, Whitlow Graſs, 3
            Handfuls; Rinds <lb/>of Oranges dried 6 Ounces; crude Antimony, groſly <lb/>powder'd, 1
            Pound: Slice and bruiſe theſe; then put <lb/>them in a Bag, and boil them in 4 Gallons
            and a half of <lb/>midling Drink to three Gallons. Take half a Pint every <lb/>Morning,
            increaſing or leſſening the Doſe, according to <lb/>its Operation. By this very Method
            great Numbers <lb/>have been cured. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="26"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>An excellent Bolus for a Cure of <hi rend="roman">Colds</hi>, which in two or
            <lb/>three Days taking will certainly carry it off. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of <hi rend="italic">Venice</hi> Treacle half a Dram, Powder of <lb/>Snake
            Root 12 Grains, Powder of Saffron 6 Grains, <lb/>Volatile Salt of Harts-horn 4 Grains,
            Syrup of Cloves, <lb/>a ſufficient Quantity to make it into a Bolus. To be <lb/>taken
            going to Reſt, drinking a large Draught of warm <lb/>Mountain-Whey or Treacle Poſſet,
            after it. To ſuch <lb/>Conſtitutions as cannot be provok'd to ſweat, Opening a
            <lb/>Vein, or a gentle Purge, will be of great Service. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To ſtop <hi rend="roman">Vomiting</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take half a Pint of Mint-water, an Ounce of Syrup <lb/>of Violets, a Quarter of an
            Ounce of Mithridate, and <lb/>half an Ounce of Syrup of Roſes; mix all theſe well
            <lb/>together, and let the Party take two Spoonfuls firſt, and <lb/>then one Spoonful
            after every Vomiting, till 'tis ſtaid. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To make the <hi rend="roman">Teeth</hi> white. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Mix a little burnt Allum with 6 Spoonfuls of Honey <lb/>and 2 of Celandine Juice,
            and rub the Teeth with it. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For a <hi rend="roman">Bruiſe</hi> in the <hi rend="roman">Members</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take an Handful of Harts-tongue Leaves, dry them <lb/>in a Paper before the Fire;
            beat them to Powder, and <lb/>with the Oil of Roſes make a Cataplaſm, to be apply'd
            <lb/>to the Part affected, renewing it every 24 Hours. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For the <hi rend="roman">Strangury</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take half a Pint of Plantane-water, 1 Ounce of white <lb/>Sugar-candy finely
            powder'd, 2 Spoonfuls of Sallad-Oil, <lb/>and the Juice of a Lemon; beat all theſe
            together very <lb/>well, and drink it off. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For the <hi rend="roman">Black Jaundice</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take an Handful of the long Leaves that grow upon <lb/>the Artichoke Stalks; put
            them into a Pot with 3 Pints <lb/>of Ale; let the Pot ſtand in a warm Place, cloſe co-
            <lb/>ver'd for 12 Hours. Take half a Pint of the Liquor, <lb/>with a Quarter of a Pint
            of white Wine every Morning <pb n="27"/>
            <lb/>faſting, for nine Mornings ſucceſſively; let a Dram of <lb/>Saffron, tied in a Rag,
            be hung in the Pot; the Leaves <lb/>muſt be bruiſed before they are put into the Ale.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>An excellent Preſcription for the Cure of <hi rend="roman">Worms</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Tops of Carduus, Tops of Centory, <hi rend="italic">Roman</hi>
            <lb/>Wormwood, and Flowers of Camomile, (all of them <lb/>dried, and of the lateſt
            Year's Growth that you uſe them <lb/>in) of each a ſmall Handful; cut the Herbs ſmall,
            but <lb/>not the Flowers, and put them, with an Ounce of Worm- <lb/>ſeed bruiſed ſmall,
            into an earthen Jar or Pickling-Pot, <lb/>and pour upon them a Quart of Spring Water,
            cold; ſtir <lb/>all about, and then tie the Pot over with a double Paper, <lb/>and let
            it ſtand 48 Hours, opening and ſtirring it about <lb/>five or ſix Times in that Space.
            At the End of 48 Hours <lb/>ſtrain it thro' a Cloth, ſqueezing the Herbs as dry as
            <lb/>you can, which fling away, and of the Liquor, give to <lb/>a Child from two to four
            or five Years old, half a Spoon- <lb/>ful, more or leſs, mixt with a Quarter of a
            Spoonful of <lb/>Oil of Beech Nuts, every Morning, upon an empty Sto- <lb/>mach, and to
            faſt for about an Hour after it; and alſo <lb/>the ſame Doſe about Four or Five in the
            Afternoon, <lb/>every Day for a Week or ten Days together; by which <lb/>time, if the
            Caſe be Worms, and you make but Obſer- <lb/>vation, you will find them come away, either
            dead or <lb/>alive. Older Children muſt take more, in Proportion <lb/>to their Ages, and
            grown Perſons from three or four to <lb/>ſix or eight Spoonfuls, or more, with always
            half the <lb/>Quantity of the ſaid Oil mixt with each Doſe, and it <lb/>will keep the
            Body ſoluble, and ſometimes a little looſe. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For a <hi rend="roman">Stitch</hi> in the <hi rend="roman">Side</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Roſin, pound and ſift it, and with Treacle mix <lb/>it into an Electuary, and
            lick it up often in the Day or <lb/>Night. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>To increaſe <hi rend="roman">Milk</hi> in Nurſes. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Make Pottage of Lentils, and take it very plentifully. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To cure a <hi rend="roman">ſore Throat</hi> that is inflam'd. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Plantain-water half a Pint; beat it well with <lb/>the White of a new-laid
            Egg; then ſtrain it, and ſweet- <pb n="28"/>
            <lb/>en it with white Sugar; let the Patient waſh his Mouth <lb/>with it as often as he
            pleaſes. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To make <hi rend="roman">Necklaces</hi> for Children in cutting <hi rend="roman"
              >Teeth</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Roots of Henbane, Orpin and Vervain; ſcrape <lb/>them clean with a ſharp
            Kniſe, cut them in long Beeds, <lb/>and ſtring them green; firſt Henbane, then Orpin,
            then <lb/>Vervain; and ſo do till 'tis the Bigneſs of the Child's <lb/>Neck. Then take
            as much red Wine as you think the <lb/>Necklace will ſuck up, and put into it a Dram of
            red <lb/>Coral, as much ſingle Peony-root finely powder'd. Soak <lb/>your Beads in this
            28 Hours, and rub the Powder on the <lb/>Beads. Syrup of Lemons, and Syrup of ſingle
            Peony, <lb/>are excellent to rub the Child's Gums with very fre- <lb/>quently. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>To dry up <hi rend="roman">Milk</hi> in Womens Breaſts. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take a Quantity of Aqua Vitæ and ſweet Butter, <lb/>temper them together, and
            anoint the Breaſts with it, <lb/>laying a Brown Paper betwixt them. Repeat this as of-
            <lb/>ten as the Paper dries, till the Milk is dry'd up. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="roman">Lower's</hi> Purging-Drink for young Children to ſweeten
            <lb/>their Blood. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take half an Ounce of choice Rhubarb ſliced thin, <lb/>burnt Harts-horn bruiſed 1
            Ounce, Raiſins of the Sun <lb/>ſtoned 2 Ounces: Infuſe them in a Pint of Ale and a Pint
            <lb/>of Small Beer 24 Hours. Give two or three Spoonfuls <lb/>at a time, as Occaſion
            requires. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Purge for <hi rend="roman">Hoarſeneſs</hi>, or any Illneſs on the <hi
              rend="roman">Lungs</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take 4 Ounces of the Roots of Sorrel, of Hyſop and <lb/>Maiden-hair, of each half a
            Handful; Raiſins a Quar- <lb/>ter of a Pound ſtoned, Sena half an Ounce, Barley-wa-
            <lb/>ter 2 Quarts; put all theſe in a Jug, and infuſe them in <lb/>a Kettle of Water 2
            Hours; ſtrain it out, and take a <lb/>Quarter of a Pint Morning and Night. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>Lapis Contrayerva. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take Pearl, Coral, Amber, Crabs-Eyes, Oriental Be- <lb/>zoar, each half an Ounce;
            Contrayerva Roots 1 Ounce; <lb/>powder theſe ſeverally very fine; then take the Black
              <pb n="29"/>
            <lb/>Tips of Crabs 4 Ounces, very finely powder'd; and with <lb/>Gelly of Harts-horn,
            made with Dragon-water, a little <lb/>tinctur'd with Saffron: Beat them in a Marble
            Mortar in- <lb/>to a Paſte, and ſo rowl it up into Balls, and dry them. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A new Method for curing the <hi rend="roman">Venereal Diſeaſe</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>It need not be ſaid what direful Accidents daily hap- <lb/>pen to People by
            Salivations, as the Loſs of Teeth, of <lb/>Hearing, of a healthful Conſtitution, and
            often even <lb/>Loſs of Life itſelf: And what makes this Caſe ſtill more
            <lb/>deplorable, is, that it has been generally thought, that <lb/>nothing but an high
            Salivation is the proper and adequate <lb/>Cure for this Diſtemper: But the learned Dr.
              <hi rend="italic">Chicoyneau</hi>
            <lb/>has happily diſcovered and proved the contrary. His <lb/>Method, which is ſometimes
            called, <hi rend="italic">The Montpellier Me- <lb/>thod</hi>, and ſometimes, <hi
              rend="italic">The new French Method</hi>, and which <lb/>is attended with very little
            Pain, and no Danger at all, <lb/>is as follows: </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The Doctor, according as he finds the Patient's Caſe <lb/>to be, ſometimes orders a
            little Blood to be taken away, <lb/>ſometimes a gentle Purge or two to be taken, but
            always <lb/>makes him bathe five or ſix times, and always an Hour <lb/>each time; after
            which the whole Operation conſiſts in <lb/>nothing more than rubbing his Feet, Legs, and
            Arms, <lb/>four, five, or ſix times, as the Caſe requires, with a Mer- <lb/>curial
            Ointment, in ſuch Quantities, and at ſuch proper <lb/>Intervals of Time, that no high
            Salivation may be raiſed <lb/>thereby: Sometimes indeed, but not always, a gentle
            <lb/>moderate Spitting will enſue, nor is it poſſible, in ſome <lb/>Conſtitutions, to
            prevent it; but then 'tis never carried <lb/>high, nor encouraged; 'tis neither
            troubleſome nor dan- <lb/>gerous. The Patient during this time keeps his Cham- <lb/>ber,
            and obſerves a regular Diet; and all he ſuffers is, <lb/>only a little feveriſh Heat and
            Reſtleſsneſs ſometimes for <lb/>a Day or two, when the Operation is at the Height. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>After this Manner only, without any further Trouble <lb/>or Danger, does Dr. <hi
              rend="italic">Chicoyneau</hi> cure the moſt inveterate <lb/>Pox, with all its Symptoms
            and Attendants: 'Tis there- <lb/>fore greatly to be wiſhed, that all our Surgeons and o-
            <lb/>thers, who undertake the Cure of this Diſeaſe, could be <lb/>prevailed on, out of
            regard to the Eaſe and Safety of <pb n="30"/>
            <lb/>Mankind, wholly to lay aſide the old pernicious Way of <lb/>Salivation, and embrace
            this new and ſafe Method. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>There are ſome hundreds of Gentlemen in <hi rend="italic">England</hi>, <lb/>that
            can, from their own Experience, bear Witneſs to <lb/><choice>
              <corr/>
              <sic>to </sic>
            </choice>the Excellency and Efficacy of it. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For the <hi rend="roman">Hemorrhoids</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Diapalma melted down very thin, with Oil <lb/>of Chamomil 1 Ounce; put to
            it Saffron finely pow- <lb/>der'd 1 Scruple; Opium 3 Grains; mix them well, and
            <lb/>being moderately warm, anoint the Part affected. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/><hi rend="roman">Black Cherry Water</hi> for Children. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take 6 Pounds of Black Cherries, and bruiſe them <lb/>ſmall; then put to them the
            Tops of Roſemary, Sweet- <lb/>marjoram, Spearmint, Angelica, Balm, Marigold-flow-
            <lb/>ers, of each a Handful; dried Violets 1 Ounce; An- <lb/>niſeeds and ſweet
            Fennel-ſeeds, of each half an Ounce <lb/>bruiſed. Cut the Herbs ſmall, and mix all
            together, <lb/>and diſtil them off in a cold Still. This Water is excel- <lb/>lent for
            Children, giving them two or three Spoonfuls <lb/>at a Time. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>To make <hi rend="roman">Barley Water</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of Pearl-Barley 4 Ounces; put it in a large Pip- <lb/>kin, and cover it with
            Water; when the Barley is thick <lb/>and tender, put in more Water and boil it up again;
            <lb/>and ſo do till 'tis of a good Thickneſs to drink; then <lb/>put in a Blade or two
            of Mace, or a Stick of Cinna- <lb/>mon. Let it have a Walm or two, and ſtrain it out,
            <lb/>and ſqueeze in the Juice of two or three Lemons, and a <lb/>Bit of the Peel, and
            ſweeten it to your Taſte with fine <lb/>Sugar. Let it ſtand till 'tis cold, and then run
            it thro' <lb/>a Bag, and bottle it out; it will keep three or four Days. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A certain Remedy to take <hi rend="roman">Fire</hi> out of a <hi rend="roman"
              >Burn</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Beat an Apple with Sallad Oil till 'tis a Poultice pretty <lb/>ſoft; bind it on the
            Part; and as it dries, lay on freſh. <lb/>You muſt be ſure to pare, core, and beat your
            Apple <lb/>well, for fear of breaking the Skin of the Burn: But <lb/>if the Skin be off,
            there is not any Thing in Nature ſo <lb/>ſure to take out the Fire. </p>
        </div>
        <pb n="31"/>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Waſh to cure the <hi rend="roman">Itch</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take 1 Quart of Spring-Water, diſſolve in it 1 Dram <lb/>of Sublimate, Cream of
            Tartar half an Ounce: Waſh <lb/>the Puſtules over with this at Night going to Bed.
            <lb/>Change your Linnen, and in three Nights at fartheſt <lb/>you will be well. 'Tis
            neceſſary at leaſt to purge. <lb/>Bleeding is likewiſe very proper. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To deſtroy <hi rend="roman">Buggs</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of the higheſt rectify'd Spirit of Wine, (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
            <lb/>Lamp Spirits) that will burn all away dry, and leave <lb/>not the leaſt Moiſture
            behind, half a Pint; newly di- <lb/>ſtill'd Oil, or Spirit of Turpentine, half a Pint;
            mix <lb/>them together, and break into it, in ſmall Bits, half an <lb/>Ounce of
            Camphire, which will diſſolve in it in a few <lb/>Minutes; ſhake them well together, and
            with a Piece <lb/>of Spunge, or a Bruſh dipt in ſome of it; wet very <lb/>well the Bed
            or Furniture wherein thoſe Vermin har- <lb/>bour and breed, and it will infallibly kill
            and deſtroy <lb/>both them and their Nits, although they ſwarm ever <lb/>ſo much. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For <hi rend="roman">Coughs</hi>, eſpecially ſuch as proceed from thin <hi
              rend="roman">Rheums</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take of choice Olibanum finely powder'd, from 1 <lb/>Scruple to half a Dram; and
            mix carefully with it an <lb/>equal Weight of Sugar-candy, (white or brown) or, in
            <lb/>want of that, of fine Sugar; and let the Patient take it <lb/>at Bed-time in the
            Pap of an Apple, or ſome other pro- <lb/>per Additament, for ſeveral Nights together. If
            it be <lb/>found needful, it may be taken at any other time, when <lb/>the Stomach is
            empty. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To give Eaſe in the Pains of the <hi rend="roman">Stone</hi>, even that of <lb/>the
              <hi rend="roman">Bladder</hi>. </head>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take the tranſparent Spar that grows upon the Veins <lb/>of Lead Ore, and having
            reduced it to a fine Powder, <lb/>give from half a Dram to a whole Dram of it at a time,
            <lb/>in a moderate Draught of ſome convenient Vehicle. <lb/><hi rend="italic">N. B.</hi>
            Though there be (at leaſt in moſt of our <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi>
            <lb/>Mines) two Teguments, as it were, of the Veins of <pb n="32"/>
            <lb/>Lead, that grow cloſe together, yet that which the Dig- <lb/>gers name <hi
              rend="italic">Cawk</hi>, which is white and opacous, is not <lb/>the Medicine I mean;
            but the tranſparent, or at leaſt <lb/>Semi-Diaphanus, which eaſily breaks into ſmooth
            Frag- <lb/>ments, and in the Fire cleaves into ſeveral Pieces, that <lb/>are wont to be
            ſmooth, and prettily ſhaped. </p>
        </div>
        <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="60"/>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="364"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
