<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Gaubius: A Complete Extemporaneous Dispensatory</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Hieronymus David Gaubius</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">A complete extemporaneous dispensatory; or, the method of
              prescribing, compounding, and exhibiting extemporaneous medicines: In which is
              contained at large, The Doctrine of all those Various Forms, both External and
              Internal, which are now in Use; Exemplified with Many Accurate Specimens of Each.
              Translated from the Latin original of the learned Dr. H. D. Gaubius, Present Professor
              of Physic and Chemistry in the University of Leyden.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">N5068</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/N5068"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Carter, at the Black-Moor's Head opposite the Royal
                  Exchange, M.DCC.XLI. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1741</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="19"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="432"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="35"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">Countway Library of Medicine</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107160437</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Recipe collections"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="19"/>
    <body>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>An illustration ... </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <div type="chapter">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>AN <lb/><hi rend="size(1.75)">INTRODUCTION </hi>
          <lb/>TO THE <lb/><hi rend="italic size(1.75)">Method of Preſcribing, <hi rend="roman"
              >&amp;c.</hi>
          </hi>
        </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/>§.1. <hi rend="dc(3)">A</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">Formula</hi> or <hi rend="italic">preſcription</hi>, a- <lb/>mong
          phyſicians, is a rati- <lb/>onal aſſignment and com- <lb/>bination of ſuch pharma-
          <lb/>ceutical remedies as have <lb/>by art been found to be <lb/>proper in particular
          caſes; <lb/>reſpect being had to the <lb/>matter and form of the ingredients and medicine:
          <lb/>ſo that it may be commodiouſly made up by the <lb/>apothecary, and applied with eaſe
          and ſucceſs by <lb/>the patient. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 2. Therefore that branch of the practice of <lb/>phyſic which delivers rules for
          the effecting this <lb/>rational combination (§. 1.), is termed the <hi rend="italic"
            >method <lb/>of preſcribing</hi> forms <hi rend="italic">of medicines</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 3. The <hi rend="italic">matter</hi> of the formula (§. 1.), whe- <lb/>ther it be
          the product of nature or art, is ſup- <lb/>plied from the (ϋλη ίατοικη) <hi rend="italic"
            >materia medica</hi>, or <lb/>pharmaceutical ſtores. The <hi rend="italic">form</hi>
          thereof is va- <lb/>rious, being determined by the very different <pb n="2"/>
          <lb/>circumſtances both of the patient and ingredi- <lb/>ents; as will hereafter more
          evidently appear. The <lb/><hi rend="italic">end</hi> and deſign of it, is, an artful
          preparation and <lb/>juſt adminiſtration of thoſe means by which the <lb/>phyſician
          endeavours to anſwer his indications, and <lb/>effect a cure. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 4. The method of preſcribing (§. 2.) therefore <lb/>compriſes the very laſt part
          which a phyſician is <lb/>to engage with in his profeſſion; this being the <lb/>point to
          which his ſkill in all the other branches <lb/>of the ſcience have a direct tendence: nor
          does a <lb/>complete workman therein hardly ever miſs <lb/>of a happy compenſation for his
          induſtry and <lb/>care. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 5. From hence (§. 3. and §. 4.), the neceſ- <lb/>ſity, uſefulneſs and advantages
          as well as dignity <lb/>of this ultimate branch of the profeſſion, are ſuf- <lb/>ficiently
          obvious. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 6. The formulæ, or preſcriptions, (§. 1.) are <lb/>diſtinguiſhed into (1.) <hi
            rend="italic">officinal</hi>, reſpecting a medi- <lb/>cine made and kept ready for
          future uſes in apo- <lb/>thecaries ſhops; and (2.) <hi rend="italic">extemporaneous</hi>,
          to be <lb/>directly made up and applied for preſent exigen- <lb/>cies. 'Tis chiefly the
          latter of theſe we intend to <lb/>handle in this treatiſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 7. In order to preſcribe either of theſe <hi rend="italic">for- <lb/>mula's</hi>
          (§. 6.), it is ſuppoſed that the phyſician or <lb/>preſcriber has a previous knowledge of,
            <list rend="indentall">
            <item rend="indent">
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>1. The <hi rend="italic">doctrine of indications</hi>; whereby he is
                <lb/>inſtructed whether any thing is to be done, what, <lb/>by what means, and after
                what manner, toge- <lb/>ther with the time, order, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> in
                which the me- <lb/>dicines or inſtruments are to be uſed. </p>
            </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>2. Of the whole <hi rend="italic">materia medica</hi> in all the <lb/><hi
                  rend="italic">three kingdoms</hi>, animal, vegetable and mine- <lb/>ral; inaſmuch
                as they afford the matter (§. 3.) <lb/>of the preſcribed formula: but he ſhou'd be
                <lb/>more particularly verſed in thoſe ſimples and <pb n="3"/>
                <lb/>medicines which are at hand, or proper to the <lb/>country where he practiſes.
                And laſtly, </p>
            </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>3. Of <hi rend="italic">all the preparations in pharmacy</hi>, both
                <lb/>chemical and galenical, ſimple and compound; <lb/>together with the manner in
                which they all <lb/>operate, and the effects they produce in the <lb/>animal ſyſtem:
                for by the knowledge of theſe <lb/>(1. 2. 3.) the phyſician knows how to direct
                <lb/>his choice of ingredients, when he preſcribes <lb/>the formula (§. 1.) </p>
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 8. And indeed it is not a ſuperficial, as is <lb/>too commonly found, but a juſt
          and more exten- <lb/>ſive knowledge of the two laſt: (§. 7. n° 2. 3.), that <lb/>is here
          required for this purpoſe. For who will <lb/>pretend to direct the apothecary how to act,
          that <lb/>is himſelf ignorant of the proper methodſ of act- <lb/>ing, in things of that
          nature? How can any one <lb/>ſelect or make a rational choice of materials which <lb/>he
          has never ſeen, or ſcarce heard of? What <lb/>room has he to foreſee (and conſequently
          prevent <lb/>the bad) effects of applications, who has never <lb/>examined their
          compoſition and texture, nor ex- <lb/>perienced their action on other bodies? — <hi
            rend="italic">He <lb/>therefore that intends for this branch</hi> (§. 2.) <hi
            rend="italic">of the <lb/>profeſſion, will doubtleſs find his account in giving
            <lb/>ſome attention to the practical part of officinal phar- <lb/>macy; in critically
            examining the mechanical ſtruc- <lb/>ture and ſenſible qualities of the</hi> materia
          medica &amp; <lb/>chemica; <hi rend="italic">and in obſerving their effects and manner
            <lb/>of acting on animal bodies</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 9. So that from comparing what has been <lb/>ſaid (§. 7. and 8. with §. 4.), we
          may naturally <lb/>infer that there is required more time and diligence <lb/>than is
          generally ſuppoſed, to qualify one for this <lb/>buſineſs; with regard to which, we are
          going to <lb/>lay down directions according to the beſt of our <lb/>abilities. But a juſt
          treatment and method will <pb n="4"/>
          <lb/>certainly have their force in making the acquiſi- <lb/>tion hereof the more eafy. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 10. Suppoſing therefore the preliminaries <lb/>(mentioned §. 7. and §. 8.),
          requiſite for preſcrib- <lb/>ing forms rationally, to be ſufficiently known; <lb/>we ſhall
          diſtribute the matter of our ſubject <lb/>under three general heads: the firſt of which,
          <lb/>by way of introduction to the reſt, will com- <lb/>priſe the rules and cautions <choice>
            <corr>neceſſary</corr>
            <sic>nececeſſary</sic>
          </choice> to be <lb/>obſerved before preſcribing; the ſecond, will ex- <lb/>hibit what
          relates to preſcriptions in general, with- <lb/>out regarding the particular form; and the
          laſt, <lb/>will contain the particulars of every individual <lb/>form of medicine in uſe,
          with proper examples or <lb/>ſpecimens of each. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <figure rend="space">
          <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>GENERAL RULES <hi rend="italic">and</hi> CAUTIONS <lb/><hi rend="italic">to be
            obſerved before practiſing</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>§. 11. <hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> prudent phyſician never orders any <lb/>thing in his
          preſcription but what he <lb/>has a ſufficient reaſon for, which upon inquiry he <lb/>is
          able to give: ſo that he does not act at random, <lb/>from cuſtom or prejudice, but as the
          indications, <lb/>which he has before rightly deduced and conſider- <lb/>ed, direct him. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 12. He is firſt of all therefore to determine <lb/>rationally, whether in the
          preſent caſe there be <lb/>required any thing to be done on his part. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 13. In conſequence of which determination <lb/>if nature herſelf be found ſtrong
          enough, and in a <lb/>proper diſpoſition to throw off the diſeaſe, if the <lb/>diſorder
          can abſolutely receive no benefit from <lb/>medicines, if its nature or particular
          diſpoſition be <lb/>doubtful and not yet determined, or if it be fore- <pb n="5"/>
          <lb/>ſeen that a cure thereof will bringon a worſe diſ- <lb/>eaſe; it is then both juſt
          and rational to omit pre- <lb/>ſcribing, at leaſt any thing that will much affect <lb/>the
          œconomy, in order to avoid oppreſſing the <lb/>patient both in his body and purſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 14. But to prevent the patient's falling into <lb/>deſpair from being deſtitute of
          phyſical help, and <lb/>to exclude ignominious reflection on the phyſician <lb/>and his
          profeſſion, as ſeeming uſeleſs or imper- <lb/>fect; it is often adviſeable in thoſe
          circumſtances <lb/>(§. 13.), to order ſomething innocent in a pre- <lb/>ſcription; ſuch as
          will do no harm, if they ſhould <lb/>prove of no great benefit. With this view, the
          <lb/>phyſician will acquaint and familiariſe himſelf with <lb/>ſeveral forms conſiſting of
          ſimple ingredients; as <lb/>innocent julaps, mild emulſions, eaſing mixtures,
          <lb/>unactive powders, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> by which ſpecious ſhew of
          <lb/>aſſiſtance, the patient will reſt much more quiet <lb/>and eaſy both in his body and
          mind, than if left <lb/>deſtitute with a harſh prognoſtic. This conſide- <lb/>ration will
          be more particularly uſeful in the un- <lb/>certain and often imaginary diſorders of
          virgins, <lb/>and married women, eſpecially whilſt teeming. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 15. If the phyſician finds by his indications <lb/>that there is room to expect
          ſucceſs from his en- <lb/>deavours, the next ſtep is to determine how and <lb/>by what
          means that may be obtained with the <lb/>greateſt eaſe and expedition: both which we are
          <lb/>directed to by the doctrine of indications, which <lb/>being ſuppoſed already known,
          we ſhall here men- <lb/>tion ſuch only as more immediately relate to our <lb/>preſent
          deſign. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 16. The grand ſcope in a cure being to re- <lb/>cover (<hi rend="italic">tuto,
            cito &amp; jucunde</hi>) ſafely, quickly and <lb/>pleaſantly, the phyſician ſhould
          always have his <lb/>eye fix'd upon that view; as being the point to <lb/>which every
          thing he orders ſhou'd have, as much <lb/>as poſſible, an immediate tendency. </p>
        <pb n="6"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 17. Hence he is directed to ſelect the moſt <lb/>efficacious and proper
          ingredients, and to combine <lb/>them in a manner moſt ſuitable to anſwer his in-
          <lb/>tentions, having a regard both to their matter and <lb/>the form. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 18. His preſcription ſhould alſo contain no- <lb/>thing that will be attended with
          hazard or danger <lb/>in the adminiſtration: tho' in deſperate and un- <lb/>tractable
          caſes, it is allowable to try a new method; <lb/>ſuppoſing it to be conducted with
          judgment, and <lb/>the relations forewarned of the doubtfulneſs of <lb/>ſucceſs in the
          caſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 19. A phyſician that conſults his character <lb/>and intereſt, will never be fond
          of uſing new and <lb/>unexperienced methods and remedies, whilſt there <lb/>are others of
          long ſtanding in practice as ſuitable <lb/>for his purpoſe; and even thoſe, he will order
          <lb/>with the utmoſt circumſpection: reputation being <lb/>oftener loſt and envy got in
          its room, by ſuch at- <lb/>tempts, than thro' ignorance. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 20. He will reject all obſolete and uſeleſs <lb/>medicines, and ſuch as eaſily
          change or corrupt <lb/>by keeping, leſt they prove diſagreeable and hurt- <lb/>ful to the
          patient, or at leaſt obſtruct his inten- <lb/>tion: upon which account, it is
          proportionably <lb/>better for medicines to be made up at the ſhops of <lb/>the moſt
          celebrated apothecaries; becauſe their <lb/>more conſtant and ſpeedy vent gives oftener
          occa- <lb/>ſion for a renewal or freſh making of thoſe medi- <lb/>cines: but ſkill and
          honeſty in compounding, are, <lb/>however, ſtronger recommendations on the behalf <lb/>of
          the apothecary. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 21. Rough medicines are to be always laid <lb/>aſide, where more gentle ones will
          ſerve the turn; <lb/>but if ſuch are uſed, it muſt be with great circum- <lb/>ſpection and
          prudence, eſpecially when intended <lb/>for weak and delicate habits of body, or very ſen-
          <lb/>ſible and nervous parts, leſt the violence of the <pb n="7"/>
          <lb/>remedy raiſe an ill opinion of the phyſician and <lb/>his profeſſion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 22. Medicines which require extraordinary <lb/>ſkill to prepare them, ſhou'd be
          made up and ex- <lb/>hibited with one's own hand, or elſe not be pre- <lb/>ſcribed at all;
          unleſs we be ſufficiently aſſured of <lb/>the faithfulneſs and dexterity of the
          apothecary. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 23. Very coſtly ingredients ſhou'd be ſpar- <lb/>ingly or very little uſed, when
          others more com- <lb/>mon and cheap are as ſuitable for the intention; <lb/>which caution
          we generally find to be obſerved in <lb/>preſcriptions: but ſome allowance muſt be made
          <lb/>for the luxurious daintineſs of the rich, who of- <lb/>ten judge the virtue of a
          medicine by its price. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 24. <hi rend="italic">Exotic</hi> or far-fetch'd remedies, are not <lb/>to be
          ſuperſtitiouſly preferred to ſuch as are the <lb/>product of our own country, when the
          latter are <lb/>equal to our deſign; for the <hi rend="italic">indigenous</hi> ſimples and
          <lb/>compounds are not ſo ſubject to adulteration and <lb/>fraud, nor decay from the
          length of time and <lb/>change of climate, as exoticks are. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 25. It is often prudent to order ſuch things <lb/>as (by their great commonneſs,
          eaſy and frequent <lb/>name, particular ſmell, taſte and other qualities) <lb/>are
          popularly known and diſcoverable, by titles <lb/>the leaſt in uſe, or elſe mix'd and
          veiled with <lb/>other ſubſtances; leſt being diſcovered, the pa- <lb/>tient might be
          diſguſted at them, or elſe deſpiſe <lb/>them as of no efficacy. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 26. We may be more ready and liberal in <lb/>the uſe of particular medicines to
          ſuch as have <lb/>frequently undergone their operation, than to o- <lb/>thers unaccuſtomed
          to 'em; which particularly <lb/>holds good with regard to emetics, cathartics,
          <lb/>opiates, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 27. Such ingredients as are unpleaſant, nau- <lb/>ſeous or troubleſome to be
          taken, ſhould be avoid- <lb/>ed as much as poſſible; or at leaſt ordered in a <pb n="8"/>
          <lb/>very ſmall quantity, and artfully diſguiſed in <lb/>ſomething more agreeable: it
          being generally bet- <lb/>ter to give nothing, than what nature has a parti- <lb/>cular
          abhorrence to; which caution is particularly <lb/>of conſequence with reſpect to very nice
          and <lb/>fanciful women, children, infants, and ſuch as have <lb/>ſome particular
          antipathy, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 28. Hence it is often proper to be ſatisfied, <lb/>that the patient has no natural
          diſguſt and aver- <lb/>ſion to the particular medicine and form pre- <lb/>ſcribed; for
          otherwiſe, remedies extremely well <lb/>adapted to the diſorder, may prove not only in-
          <lb/>effectual, but ſometimes of pernicious conſequence; <lb/>notwithſtanding that be
          brought about by nothing <lb/>more than the imagination or fancy. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 29. The judicious phyſician will aim at ſim- <lb/>plicity with efficacy, and not
          multitude and quan- <lb/>tity of ingredients in his preſcription; ſtudying <lb/>rather a
          conciſe brevity, than a pompous and af- <lb/>fected ſcroll: and accordingly he will ſelect
          his <lb/>materials from the vaſt field of the <hi rend="italic">materia medica</hi>,
          <lb/>not promiſcuouſly, but as they ſtand approved by <lb/>reaſon and experience. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 30. But the younger phyſician, whoſe cha- <lb/>racter and buſineſs are not yet
          ſufficiently eſtabliſh- <lb/>ed, will accommodate his practice, as much as is
          <lb/>conſiſtent with his intention, to the cuſtoms and <lb/>opinions of the age, place,
          and people he is con- <lb/>cerned with: thus he will the more eaſily pave <lb/>the way for
          coming into publick eſteem; but <lb/>when confirmed, and of conſiderable ſtanding in
          <lb/>practice, he may then ſafely diſregard ſuch cir- <lb/>cumſtances. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 31. Natural and ſimple medicines are prefer- <lb/>rable to prepared and compound
          ones, when the <lb/>virtues of both are equally the ſame. For in pre- <lb/>patation and
          compoſition, medicines are not only <lb/>ſubject to change and put on other qualities, but
            <pb n="9"/>
          <lb/>their goodneſs muſt alſo greatly depend on the <lb/>honeſty and dexterity of the
          compounder; whereas <lb/>the conduct and conſtancy of faithful nature greatly
          <lb/>ſurpaſſes all the pretenſions of art. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 32. Tho' the knowledge of every ſimple in <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Materia
            medica</hi> be uſeful to a phyſician, he is <lb/>required to have a more particular
          acquaintance <lb/>with ſuch as are in conſtant practice, and for that <lb/>purpoſe always
          kept ready in the ſhops; leſt he <lb/>ſhould order things which are not ready at hand:
          <lb/>which would be matter of little conſequence, were <lb/>it not for the prevailing
          forwardneſs of ſubſtitut- <lb/>ing one thing for another, without conſulting the
          <lb/>phyſician. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 33. Beſides the properties and doſes of each <lb/>ſimple and compound medicine,
          the young phy- <lb/>ſician will remember the ſeveral <hi rend="italic">ſynonimous appella-
            <lb/>tions</hi> uſually aſſigned to each; that he may not be <lb/>liable to order the
          ſame thing more than once in a <lb/>preſcription, under different titles. Upon the
          <lb/>ſame account he will alſo learn the several <hi rend="italic">general</hi>
          <lb/>appellations, which are for brevity uſed to ſignify <lb/>ſeveral ſimples, as they are
          expreffed in <hi rend="italic">Morellus</hi>
          <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)" n="*">
            <p rend="indent italic">
              <lb/>* See a liſt of theſe general appellations at the end of the Book. </p>
          </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 34. An acquaintance alſo with the ſeveral <lb/>ſeaſons of the year, proper to
          vegitable and ani- <lb/>mal ſubſtances, ſhould not be neglected but had in <lb/>memory;
          leſt he order ſomething to be freſh ga- <lb/>thered, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> in
          autumn or winter, which is to be had <lb/>in that flouriſhing ſtate only in ſpring or
          ſummer. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 35. The different textures and conſiſtences of <lb/>both ſimple and compound
          medicines, muſt alſo <lb/>come into conſideration; to avoid improper forms <lb/>and
          proportions in preſcription. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 36. The mutual affinity and aptitude of the <lb/>ſimples for mixture with each
          other, and of the <lb/>inſtruments and methods by which they muſt be <pb n="10"/>
          <lb/>ſo prepared, ſhould be in like manner learned <lb/>from a rational and practical
          pharmacy; which <lb/>will make for the intereſt both of himſelf and pati- <lb/>ent, and
          preſerve him from being ridiculed by <lb/>the apothecary's man, when he may have occaſion
          <lb/>to mention them in his preſcription. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 37. By remembering the conſtituent ingredi- <lb/>ents of officinal compounds, we
          may avoid an im- <lb/>proper repetition of the ſame ſimples in an ex- <lb/>temporaneous
          form; but indications, ſometimes, <lb/>require ſuch repetition. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 38. Nor is it proper to accumulate many in- <lb/>gredients in one form, which
          differ, indeed, in <lb/>name, but not in their nature and ſpeciſic virtues; <lb/>for that
          would be much the ſame as neglecting the <lb/>caution at §. 33. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 39. Such of the ſelect ingredients as may com- <lb/>modiouſly enter one form,
          ſhould not, without ne- <lb/>ceſſity, be diſtributed into more, reſpect being had <lb/>to
          the opinions and circumftances mention'd <lb/>§. 30; for there are ſome who are much
          diſpleaſed <lb/>with few and ſhort <hi rend="italic">formulæ</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 40. On the other hand, ſimples which have <lb/>no congruity with each other, ſo as
          to mix uni- <lb/>formly, ſhould be left out of the form, or be aſ- <lb/>ſigned to ſome
          other; eſpecially oily and terebin- <lb/>thinate ſubſtances witn watery, and ſuch things,
          <lb/>as upon mixture, change or deſtroy the properties <lb/>of each other, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> of which, particular mention <lb/>will be made hereafter,
          well worth ſpecial ob- <lb/>ſervation. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 41. To avoid in ſome meaſure both theſe <lb/>difficulties (§. 39. <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;</hi> 40.), we muſt oppoſe medi- <lb/>cines not to every trifling,
          but the moſt urgent <lb/>Symptoms; for theſe being the effects or conſe- <lb/>quences of
          the diſeaſe, that, or its immediate cauſe <lb/>being removed, the ſymptoms mult
          ſpontaneouſly <lb/>vaniſh; beſides, the train of ſymptoms is often ſo <pb n="11"/>
          <lb/>numerous and oppoſite, as to make a diſtinct <lb/>treatment of them impracticable
          without confuſion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 42. In very acute diſeaſes, and in ſymptoms <lb/>extremely urgent, it is
          adviſeable to order remedies <lb/>that may be made up and exhibited with the greateſt
          <lb/>eaſe and expedition; that a critical opportunity <lb/>may not be loſt through a want
          of the medicine, or <lb/>a delay of the apothecary. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 43. If the texture of the ingredients ſuit <lb/>them indifferently for ſeveral
          forms, we may, upon <lb/>inquiry, reduce them to that moſt agreeable to <lb/>the patient;
          as many have a particular liking, or <lb/>averſion, naturally or from uſe, more for one
          form <lb/>than another: by which means the phyſician and <lb/>his profeſſion will come
          more into the good opi- <lb/>nion of the patient, as well as taking the medi- <lb/>cine be
          render'd more certain and pleaſant. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 44. On the contrary, we muſt not be ſo ſolli- <lb/>citous about the palate as to
          forget the proper na- <lb/>ture, danger, and ſymptoms of the diſeaſe; nor <lb/>neglect the
          pre-diſpoſing cauſe in the patient's <lb/>habit. Some forms are more ſuitable to one diſ-
          <lb/>eaſe than another. How prepoſterous would it be <lb/>to order an electuary, or bolus,
          in a quinſy,or where <lb/>deglutition is diſſicult, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 45. Nor is the intention of a medicine as <lb/>eaſily anſwer'd by one form as
          another: ſudorifics <lb/>agree beſt with a liquid form, abſorbents with a <lb/>dry one,
          and fœtid, or nauſeous things, with that <lb/>of a pill, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> as
          we ſhall obſerve more at large in <lb/>the ſeveral hiſtories of each particular form. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 46. The age and circumſtances of the pati- <lb/>ent have alſo their force in
          determining the parti- <lb/>cular form of the medicine. Infants ſhould not be
          <lb/>fatigued with internals, when external forms will <lb/>prove as effectual; nor ſhould
          they be ever mo- <lb/>leſted with a bolus, pill, or any thing unpleaſant <lb/>and
          difficult to ſwallow. </p>
        <pb n="12"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 47. The patients natural conſtitution, or ha- <lb/>bit, has, in like manner, ſome
          influence in de- <lb/>manding a variation in the particular form. The <lb/>hot and dry
          require a liquid, the moiſt and phleg- <lb/>matic are benefited moſt by a dry form; but
          theſe <lb/>being of leſs conſequence muſt give place to the <lb/>conſideration of §. 43,
          to 47, which are of greater <lb/>importance <note n="*" place="below">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* The condition of the <hi rend="italic">diſeaſe</hi>, being either <hi
                rend="italic">acute</hi>
              <lb/>or <hi rend="italic">chronic</hi>, has alſo no ſmall influence in deter-
              <lb/>mining the particular <hi rend="italic">form</hi>, and manner of exhi-
              <lb/>bition. — In the <list rend="indentall">
                <item>
                  <p rend="indent"><lb/>(1.) <hi rend="italic">Chronic</hi>, we ſhould gradually
                    inlarge the <lb/>doſe (<hi rend="italic">per</hi> §. 26.), and may more regard
                    the pa-<lb/>late (<hi rend="italic">per</hi> §. 43.) with the patients
                    convenience <lb/>and circumſtances (<hi rend="italic">per</hi> §. 23. 27. 28.
                    29. 46. 47. <lb/>48. 50.); always preferring pills, electuaries, <lb/>wines,
                    ales, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> to a train of boles, draughts, <hi
                      rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
                    <lb/>which appear more formidable and diſcouraging. <lb/>But, the </p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p rend="indent"><lb/>(2.) <hi rend="italic">Acute</hi>, generally require
                    medicines of the <lb/>ſtrongeſt efficacy, to be uſed often,
                    interchange-<lb/>ably, in different <hi rend="italic">forms</hi> for the ſame
                    caſe, and to <lb/>be more aſcertain'd in their doſe; as in boles, <lb/>powders,
                    draughts, drops, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                </item>
              </list>
            </p>
          </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 48. Medicines that are to be taken upon long <lb/>journeys, or continually carried
          about in boxes for <lb/>conſtant uſe, ſhould conſiſt of ingredients the leaſt <lb/>bulky,
          moſt effectual and durable, and reduced to <lb/>a form the moſt convenient and portable. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 49. If a patient finds himſelf better after a <lb/>preſcription, he ſhould
          continue in the uſe of it 'till <lb/>the phyſician finds ſome variation required; nor
          <lb/>is it commendable to make a change therein with- <lb/>out an evident and weighty
          reaſon. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 50. It is, however, allowable and proper, in <lb/>hereditary, or habitual and very
          chronical diſtem- <pb n="13"/>
          <lb/>pers, to vary both the ingredients and form, tho' <lb/>the face of ſymptoms and their
          indications re- <lb/>main the ſame: whereby is ſhewn the ſkill of the <lb/>phyſician and
          the copiouſneſs of his art, and that <lb/>the patient may not be tired out with one form,
          <lb/>nor particular medicines become habitual and uſe- <lb/>leſs to him. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 51. When no benefit ariſes from the uſe of a <lb/>medicine, rather than perſiſt
          therein, it ſhou'd be <lb/>changed, either wholly or in part, at the diſcretion <lb/>of
          the phyſician: but, if noxious, it muſt be <lb/>ſpeedily and altogether ſuppreſſed; for,
          by the <hi rend="italic">ju- <lb/>vantia &amp; ledentia</hi>, or what helps and hurts, we
          <lb/>are dirccted principally how to act. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 52. Laſtly, as a prudent phyſician never re. <lb/>ſcribes but with great attention
          and ClI'CllmſpCt'I%0n <lb/>of mind, ſo he ſhould never lay the formula out of <lb/>his
          hand 'till he has firſt: reviſed it; that he may <lb/>be fure every thing is right,
          diPtinct and clear; <lb/>for it being the too general lot of preſcripriong <lb/>to be made
          up_ by the hands of j0L1I'nCymen <lb/>and apprentices, who are often both ignorant
          <lb/>and careleſs, a ſſip of the pen, or an obſcurify, <lb/>might chance to be of fatal
          confequence to the pa- <lb/>ticnt. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <lb/>
        <head rend="hanging italic">
          <lb/>Of the <hi rend="roman">GENERAL</hi> Circumſtances of pre- <lb/>ſcriptions, excluſive
          of the parſicular form of <lb/>a medicine. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 53. <hi rend="dc(2)">W</hi>E come now to conſider the <hi rend="italic"
            >formula</hi>, <lb/>or preſcription (§. 1.) in general, <lb/>as agreeing with, or common
          to, all forms with- <lb/>out diſtinction; and this we ſhall do (1.) <hi rend="italic"
            >abſtractly</hi>, <lb/>with reſpect to the bill itſelf, and then (2.) in <hi
            rend="italic">com- <pb n="14"/>
            <lb/>poſition</hi>, with reſpect to the circumſtances of its <lb/>conſtituent parts. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 54. With regard to the firſt (§. 53.), we un- <lb/>derſtand every thing that does
          not immediately <lb/>affect or concern the medicine it ſelf; but ſerve ei- <lb/>ther for
          ornament, brevity, or perſpecuity in the <lb/>way of compounding and applying it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 55. The firſt (I.) that occurs among theſe <lb/>(§. 54.), is an arbitrary and
          ſuperſtitious <hi rend="italic">inſcrip- <lb/>tion</hi>, appearing in the front of the
          bill, and con- <lb/>ſiſting in ſome particular characters or letters in- <lb/>timating the
          pious wiſh and inclination of the pre- <lb/>ſcriber: as, †. C. D. J D. JJ. <hi
            rend="italic">α &amp; ω</hi>
          <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)">
            <p rend="indent italic">
              <lb/>* This ſeems to ſmell very ſtrong of a Romiſh or ſuperſtitious <lb/>prieſt-craft;
              but as ſuch hands are ſeldom daubed with phyſic a- <lb/>mong us, we are intirely
              ſtrangers to things of this nature. </p>
          </note>; which <lb/>may be, and are, generally omitted without <lb/>neglecting any thing
          ſerviceable to the patient. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 56. The next (II.) that appears, at the head <lb/>of the preſcription, is that
          conſtantly uſed, abbre- <lb/>viated word (<hi rend="italic">Rec.</hi> or ℞.) <note n="†"
            place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)">
            <p rend="indent italic">
              <lb/>† When the back part of the ℞ is left out, it makes another <lb/>character (♃) of
              the ſame import but more frequent uſe, as being <lb/>leſs known. </p>
          </note>
          <hi rend="italic">Recipe</hi>; importing that <lb/>the apothecary is to <hi rend="italic"
            >take</hi> ſomething, afterwards <lb/>mentioned. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 57. Our buſineſs is now to examine the (III.) <lb/><hi rend="italic">order</hi>,
          or ſeries, in which the things to be thus <lb/>(§. 56.) <hi rend="italic">taken</hi> are
          wrote. This we ſhall perceive <lb/>upon enquiry to vary with every particular <hi
            rend="italic">form</hi> of <lb/>medicine; nor even there, ſhall we find one con-
          <lb/>ſtant and uniform method obſerv'd; as will be <lb/>more apparent in the particular
          hiſtories of each. <lb/>We may, however, obſerve in the general, <list rend="indentall">
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>1. That a diſtinct <hi rend="italic">line</hi> ſhou'd be made of every
                <lb/>ſingle ingredient; not to obſcure them, by <lb/>writing one continuous or in
                the ſame direct- <lb/>ion with the other. </p>
            </item>
            <pb n="15"/>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>2. That ingredients of the ſame kind ſhould <lb/>be placed next to each other;
                roots with roots, <lb/>waters with waters, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
              </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>3. Not to be wanting in the leaſt point of <lb/>order, we ſhould begin and
                range things, that <lb/>differ from each other in ſubſtance, according <lb/>to their
                  <hi rend="italic">quantities</hi>; beginning with the largeſt <lb/>and ending with
                the ſmalleſt, or the reverſe. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>4. Next to that conſideration (n° 3.), the <lb/><hi rend="italic">baſis</hi>,
                or main ingredients (§. 75.) ſhou'd hold <lb/>the firſt place; then, the <hi
                  rend="italic">aſſiſtants</hi> (§. 78.); af- <lb/>ter them, the <hi rend="italic"
                  >correcters</hi> (§. 83.); and laſtly, the <lb/><hi rend="italic">vehicle</hi> (§.
                86.), or what ſerves to make them up. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>5. Such things as have their quantity undeter- <lb/>min'd, or dependant on the
                conſiſtence and bulk <lb/>of the reſt, ſhou'd come generally in the laſt <lb/>place
                of a preſcription. </p>
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Not but there are ſeveral exceptions from theſe <lb/>rules, which will be taken
          notice of in the enſuing <lb/>parts of this treatiſe, and will be therefore worth <lb/>the
          readers obſervation. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 58. For the (IV.) <hi rend="italic">method</hi> of writing, or or- <lb/>dering
          theſe ſeveral ingredients, and their <hi rend="italic">quanti- <lb/>ties</hi>; the more
          diſtinct and intelligible they are ſet <lb/>down, the more commendable: accordingly <list
            rend="indentall">
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>1. The phyſician ſhou'd uſe himſelf to <hi rend="italic">write <lb/>plain</hi>
                and diſtinct; not to neglect and hurry over <lb/>his letters with a careleſs pen.
              </p>
            </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>2. He ſhou'd keep up to <hi rend="italic">cuſtom</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                  >orthogra- <lb/>phy</hi>, to avoid the ſneering of an apothecary or <lb/>his man.
              </p>
            </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>3. An irregular, or confuſed method of wri- <lb/>ting, ſhou'd be avoided as
                much as poſſible; <lb/>and to make things appear with more evidence <lb/>and method,
                ingredients of the ſame kind ſhou'd <lb/>be placed next to each other (<hi
                  rend="italic">per</hi> §. 57. n° 2.): <pb n="16"/>
                <lb/>the general appellation common to each ſimilar <lb/>ingredient ſhou'd be always
                placed firſt, and <lb/>need not be mentioned more than once; as the <lb/>proper
                names of each ſhou'd be placed directly <lb/>under and even with the firſt, in the
                method of <lb/>§. 57. n° I. The ſame is alſo to be obſerved, <lb/>with reſpect to
                ſeveral ingredients following <lb/>each other that are to enter a form in the ſame
                <lb/>quantity; <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> not to write the particular mark <lb/>of
                quantity to each ſingly, but to aſſign only <lb/>one character of quantity to them
                all; before <lb/>which ſhould be inſerted the technical word <lb/><hi rend="italic"
                  >ana</hi> or <hi rend="italic">aa</hi>, which is uſed to denote that the quan-
                <lb/>tity to be <hi rend="italic">taken</hi> of the ſeveral preceeding ingre-
                <lb/>dients muſt be equal or alike, whether it be in <lb/>number, weight or meaſure.
                — There are ma- <lb/>ny ſuch abbreviations in uſe, which will be met <lb/>with in
                the enfuing <hi rend="italic">formulæ</hi>, and ought not to <lb/>be neglected (if
                it were ſafe) becauſe univerſally <lb/>received and eſtabliſh'd by long cuſtom. </p>
            </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>4. Too much brevity in writing is ſtill of a <lb/>worſe conſequence; eſpecially
                when the ingre- <lb/>dients and their quantities are order'd, not by <lb/>common
                letters, but odd characters or figures, not <lb/>conſtantly uſed, and often: falſely
                or imperfectly <lb/>made <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)">
                  <p rend="indent italic"><lb/>* Theſe odd characters, of which the German (and
                    eſpecially <lb/>the chemical) phyſicians were fond, are extremely ſeldom, if
                    <lb/>ever, uſed in preſcriptions among us; and therefore the caution <lb/>ſeems
                    to be directed chiefly to that quarter. But as they frequently <lb/>occur in
                    writers (eſpecially foreigners) in phyſic, pharmacy and <lb/>chemiſtry; and as
                    they may be ſometimes uſed with propriety in a <lb/>preſcription (<hi
                      rend="roman">per §. 25</hi>); it will be proper for the young phyſician
                    <lb/>to acquaint himſelf with the chief of them, agreeable to our au-<lb/>thor's
                    advice in the end of this paragraph: we have therefore fur-<lb/>niſhed our
                    reader with a liſt and explanations of the moſt uſual of <lb/>theſe characters
                    at the end of the book; it being too long to be in-<lb/>ſerted here. </p>
                </note>: by which means it too frequently hap- <lb/>pens that the apothecary is
                brought into a miſ- <lb/>take, either of the ingredient or quantity, to the <pb
                  n="17"/>
                <lb/>great danger of the patient. So that it is more <lb/>prudent to intirely
                relinquiſh ſuch, or elſe to uſe <lb/>thoſe only which are the moſt diſtinct and com-
                <lb/>mon, and the leaſt ambiguous; and then, only <lb/>when (<hi rend="italic"
                  >per</hi> §. 25.) we have ſome particular rea- <lb/>ſon for concealing the
                ingredients of the <hi rend="italic">formula</hi>. <lb/>The characters for weight,
                ſhou'd be expreſs'd <lb/>with the greatneſs exactneſs, by ſuch as love to <lb/>uſe
                them. — And tho' the firſt ſort of char- <lb/>racters are improper to enter
                preſcriptions in <lb/>writing, 'tis yet fit they ſhou'd be known; as <lb/>they
                frequently occur in the works of phyſi- <lb/>cians. </p>
            </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>5. The ingredients of a preſcription ſhou'd be <lb/>wrote for by thoſe <hi
                  rend="italic">names</hi> under which they are <lb/>kept and known in the ſhops;
                notwithſtand- <lb/>ing they ſhou'd be barbarous or improper: by <lb/>which means the
                compounder will be under no <lb/>difficulty, nor fall into any miſtake. But if for
                <lb/>concealment (<hi rend="italic">per</hi> §. 25.) an uncommon term be <lb/>uſed,
                the apothecary ſhou'd have, if it be ne- <lb/>ceſſary, a ſpeedy and private
                intelligence thereof. </p>
            </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>
              <p>
                <lb/>6. The <hi rend="sc">Weights</hi> uſed at preſent in the ſhops <lb/>of
                apothecaries, are 
                <table>
                  <row><cell>℔ the phyſical <hi rend="italic">pound</hi>
                    <hi rend="dc(5)">}</hi>
                    <hi rend="dc(5)">{</hi> ℥ xij. </cell></row>
                  <row> <cell> ℥ an <hi rend="italic">ounce</hi> — ʒ viij. 
                    <hi rend="dc(5)">{</hi> ℥ xij. </cell></row>
                  <row> <cell>ʒ a dram — containing ℈ iij.</cell></row>
                  <row><cell> ℈ a ſcruple — <hi rend="italic">gr.</hi> xx.</cell></row>
                  <row><cell>
                    <hi rend="italic">Gr.</hi> a grain — ß ij.</cell> </row>
                </table>
                <lb/>A grain is ſeldom divided further than into two <lb/>equal parts, whoſe whole
                amount is ſuppoſed <lb/>to be equal to a grain of white pepper or a <lb/>middling
                barley-corn: but it is much the beſt <lb/>to uſe a grain of a determinate or
                ſtanding <lb/>weight, like that of the Goldſmiths; without <lb/>which, this and all
                larger weights thence ariſing, <lb/>as from unity, wou'd be always varying and un-
                <lb/>certain, as <hi rend="italic">Fernelius</hi> obſerves. </p>
            </item>
            <pb n="18"/>
            <lb/>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>7. The phyſical <hi rend="italic">meaſures</hi> now in uſe, are ſuch <lb/>as
                belong either to <hi rend="italic">dry</hi> or <hi rend="italic">liquid</hi>
                ingredients: <lb/>and are </p>
              <list>
                <item>
                  <p rend="indent"><lb/>(1.) <hi rend="italic">Dry</hi>; as the </p>
                  <lb/>
                  <p rend="indent"><lb/>Faſc. <hi rend="italic">Faſciculus</hi>, or a ſmall armfull,
                    being as <lb/>much as can be eaſily graſped by the arm bended <lb/>together, and
                    is equal to twelve handfuls. </p>
                  <lb/>
                  <p rend="indent"><lb/>M. <hi rend="italic">Manipulus</hi>, or handfull, which is
                    as <lb/>much as can be taken up by the whole hand at <lb/>once, and may be
                    compared to four pugills, <lb/>or half an ounce. </p>
                  <p rend="indent"><lb/>Pug. <hi rend="italic">Pugillus</hi>, comprehends as much as
                    can <lb/>be contained between the thumb and two firſt <lb/>fingers, and anſwers
                    to about the whole or half <lb/>of a dram. </p>
                  <lb/>
                  <p rend="indent"><lb/>N°. <hi rend="italic">Numero</hi>, in number, equal or
                    unequal. </p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p rend="indent"><lb/>(2.) <hi rend="italic">Liquid</hi>; comprehending, belides
                    the <lb/>common trading meaſures, alſo the Cyath. <lb/><hi rend="italic"
                      >Cyathum</hi>, which holds about an ounce and an <lb/>half. </p>
                  <lb/>
                  <p rend="indent"><lb/>Cochl. <hi rend="italic"><choice>
                        <corr>Cochlearium</corr>
                        <sic>Coohlearium</sic>
                      </choice></hi>, reckon'd to be about <lb/>half an ounce. </p>
                  <p rend="indent"><lb/>Gutt. <hi rend="italic">Gutta</hi>, or a Drop, which being
                    the leaſt <lb/>of liquid meaſures, is ſubſtituted in room of a <lb/>grain among
                    weights, and may, like that, be <lb/>commodiouſly ſubdivided into two (or more)
                    <lb/>equal parts, being firſt imbibed by a bit of ſu-<lb/>gar, to be afterwards
                    pulveriſed and divided by <lb/>weight: but the quantity under this meaſure
                    <lb/>varies with the ſpeciſic gravity and degree of <lb/>coheſion in the liquid
                    to be ſo meafured; and, <lb/>alſo the quantity of ſurface in contact with
                    <lb/>it, or the largeneſs of the bottle's neck from <lb/>whence it is to be
                    dropp'd; which firſt alſo <lb/>holds good with reſpect to the <hi rend="italic"
                      >Cyathum</hi> and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cochlearium</hi>. </p>
                </item>
              </list>
            </item>
            <pb n="19"/>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>8. With regard to theſe medical diviſions of <lb/>quantity (n° 6. and 7.), we
                may obſerve <list>
                  <item>
                    <lb/>(1.) That every thing, not only ſoft and <lb/>ſolid but alſo liquid, whoſe
                    quantity is requi-<lb/>red to be determined with accuracy and ex-<lb/>actneſs,
                    ſhou'd be portion'd out by weight <lb/>only. </item>
                  <item>
                    <lb/>(2.) The dry meaſures (n°. 7.) are to be <lb/>uſed only for ſuch things as
                    are very bulky, <lb/>and of no ſtrength; as herbs, leaves, flowers, <lb/>ſeeds,
                      <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> The larger kind of ſeeds, bulbous <lb/>roots,
                    the whites and yolks of eggs, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> are <lb/>uſually
                    preſcribed by number. </item>
                  <item>
                    <lb/>(3.) The liquid meaſures (n°. 7.) ſhou'd be <lb/>ſeldom uſed in
                    preſcriptions, unleſs to ſignify <lb/>the particular doſe; by reaſon of their
                    uncer-<lb/>tainty, the meaſures differing with particular <lb/>liquors and
                    countries: but the uſe of weights <lb/>is more conſtant and certain; and if we
                    have, <lb/>notwithſtanding, a fancy for the uſe of mea-<lb/>ſures, we ſhou'd at
                    leaſt know the ſeveral <lb/>weights of different liquors which they can
                    con-<lb/>tain. Strong liquids may be alſo portion'd <lb/>out with more exactneſs
                    by drams, ſcruples and <lb/>grains, than by drops. </item>
                  <item>
                    <lb/>(4.) Number, in preſcribing ingredients, <lb/>with their weights and
                    meaſures, is to be ex-<lb/>preſſed by characters not barbarous (as 1, 2, 3,
                      <lb/><hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>) but Roman (as j, ij, iij, iv, <hi
                      rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>) as being <lb/>more diſtinct and evident. </item>
                  <item>
                    <lb/>(5.) All weights and meaſures are uſually <lb/>ſubdivided into halves, and
                    their half part is <lb/>then ſignified by the character ß. </item>
                  <item>
                    <lb/>(6.) The larger weights and meaſures are <lb/>to be expreſs'd by the
                    characters proper to <lb/>their whole, or half quantities; and not by <lb/>the
                    number of leſſer weights or meaſures they <lb/>contain. </item>
                  <pb n="20"/>
                  <item>
                    <lb/>(7.) Sometimes the weight or meaſure of an <lb/>ingredient is left to be
                    determined at diſcre-<lb/>tion by the apothecary, and is only wrote <lb/>(<hi
                      rend="italic">q. ſ</hi>) <hi rend="italic">quantum ſufficit</hi>, or a
                    ſufficient quantity: <lb/>which might be well enough bore with, had <lb/>the
                    apothecary any conſtant rule to go by, or <lb/>were the quantity and conſiſtence
                    of a me-<lb/>dicine to be always the ſame; but when it be-<lb/>comes on this
                    account very uncertain, it is ad-<lb/>viſeable for the phyſician to determine
                    the quan-<lb/>tity, as may be ſeen under the particular <hi rend="italic"
                      >forms</hi>
                    <lb/>hereafter. </item>
                  <item>
                    <lb/>(8.) Among the ancients, there were many <lb/>other weights and meaſures
                    than theſe (n° 7, <lb/>8.) in frequent uſe; which tho' now obſolete <lb/>and
                    unpractiſed, are yet <hi rend="italic">neceſſary</hi> to be known <lb/>by a
                    phyſician that intends to be converſant with <lb/>their writings, and may be
                    therefore learned <lb/>from <hi rend="italic">Fernelius</hi> and others <lb/>* A
                    liſt and explanation of the ſeveral weights and meaſures <lb/>uſed by the
                    ancient <hi rend="roman">Greek, Roman</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Arabian</hi>
                    physicians (as <lb/>taken from <hi rend="roman">Fernelius</hi>, who is for that
                    end recommended by our au-<lb/>thor,) being rather too large to be conveniently
                    inſerted in this <lb/>place, the reader will meet with that, and ſome others, at
                    the <lb/>end of the book. . </item>
                </list>
              </p>
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 59. The (V.) fifth part of a <hi rend="italic">formula</hi>, or bill, <lb/>is the
            <hi rend="sc">Subscription</hi>, directing the apothecary <lb/>in what <hi rend="italic"
            >form</hi> the phyſician wou'd have the ingre- <lb/>dients made up, the manner in which
          they are <lb/>to be ſo <hi rend="italic">prepared</hi>, and the method in which they
          <lb/>are to be <hi rend="italic">applied</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">exhibited</hi> by him
          to the pati- <lb/>ent. With regard to which, <lb/>
          <list rend="indentall">
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>1. If a preſcription contains but one ingredi- <lb/>ent, which requires no
                extemporaneous prepa- <lb/>ration, it may be ſubſcribed only (<hi rend="italic"
                  >F.</hi>) <hi rend="italic">Fiat</hi>, <lb/>adding the name of the form, <hi
                  rend="italic">v. g. pulvis</hi>, <hi rend="italic">bo- <lb/>lus</hi>, <hi
                  rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
              </p>
            </item>
            <pb n="21"/>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>2. But if it conſiſts of ſeveral, to be only <lb/>mix'd together without other
                preparation; <lb/>there muſt be firſt inſerted (<hi rend="italic">M.</hi>) <hi
                  rend="italic">miſce</hi>, and af- <lb/>terwards (<hi rend="italic">F.</hi>) <hi
                  rend="italic">fiat</hi>, and laſtly the name of the <lb/>form; as <hi
                  rend="italic">e. g. M. F. Bolus</hi>. But in liquid mix- <lb/>tures it is often
                ſufficient to write <hi rend="italic">M.</hi> only; tho' <lb/>it is ſometimes
                requiſite to give a particular ad- <lb/>monition concerning the uniformity or exact-
                <lb/>neſs of the mixture. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>3. If there ſhou'd be required ſome other <lb/>preparation beſides mixture, as
                cutting, brui- <lb/>ſing, digeſting, boiling, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> theſe
                are alſo to <lb/>be inſerted either before or after <hi rend="italic">M.</hi> as
                ſhall ſeem <lb/>moſt proper. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>4. It is then requiſite to add (if neceſſary) the <lb/>number of doſes into
                which the medicine is to <lb/>be diſtributed: where it is alſo frequently pro-
                <lb/>per to admoniſh the apothecary to be very ex- <lb/>act in making every doſe
                equal and alike; be- <lb/>cauſe they often, for expedition, divide a medi- <lb/>cine
                by gueſs or the eye. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>5. Mention is to be ſometimes made of the <lb/>receptacle into which the
                medicine is to be put, <lb/>and of the method of keeping, or cloſe ſtop- <lb/>ping
                the ſame; when they contain things very <lb/>volatile, or foon melting in the air,
                as will be <lb/>hereafter obſerved in particular forms </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>6. Laſtly, the inſtrument whereby, and the <lb/>particular part of the body to
                which, the me- <lb/>dicine is to be applied, are required to be <lb/>ſometimes
                mention'd, when it appertains to the <lb/>apothecary; as will be hereafter obſerved
                in <lb/>the hiſtory of plaſters, lambatives, glyſters, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
                  >&amp;c.</hi>
              </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>7. In all theſe particulars (no 1. to 6.), it is <lb/>beſt for the phyſician to
                be full, and diſtinct or <lb/>clear, and to uſe the terms of art, however bar- <pb
                  n="22"/>
                <lb/>barous; leſt an error be committed thro' his <lb/>own fault, or the apothecary
                ſhou'd be put to a <lb/>nonplus. </p>
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 60. The (VI.) laſt general part of a pre- <lb/>ſcription or <hi rend="italic"
            >formula</hi>, is the <hi rend="sc">Superscription</hi>
          <note n="†" place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)">
            <p rend="indent italic">
              <lb/>† Our author calls it <hi rend="roman">ſignatura</hi>, ſignment. I ſuppoſe we
              need <lb/>not inform our reader that this part of a preſcription is almoſt uni-
              <lb/>verſally left out by our phyſicians; who judge it moſt convenient to <lb/>give
              theſe orders by word of mouth to the patient or his attendants, <lb/>or leave it to
              the diſcretion of the apothecary. </p>
          </note>, <lb/>of the medicine or direction to the patient; which <lb/>is often (tho' not
          always) very neceſſary, inaſmuch <lb/>as it declares the form of the preſcribed medicine,
          <lb/>its virtue, doſe, method and time of adminiſtration, <lb/>the proper vehicle,
          regimen, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> as far as they <lb/>regard the ſick patient and
          his attendants: which <lb/>is to be carried on in the following order, <lb/>
          <list rend="indentall">
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>1. Beneath the <hi rend="italic">Subſcription</hi> (§. 59. n° 1, to <lb/>6.),
                at a diſtance from the line, write the capi- <lb/>tal letter <hi rend="italic"
                  >S</hi>. i. e. <hi rend="italic">ſignetur</hi>, let it be intitled, <hi
                  rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
              </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>2. If there be ſeveral medicines of the ſame <lb/>form and appearance
                preſcribed together for one <lb/>patient; they ſhou'd be marked with the capital
                <lb/>letters A, B, C, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> or numbers, 1, 2, 3, <hi
                  rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> at <lb/>the head or in the margin of each <hi
                  rend="italic">formula</hi>, that <lb/>they may be diſtinguiſh'd from each other;
                and <lb/>then theſe diſtinguiſhing marks are to be inſerted <lb/>after the letter
                  <hi rend="italic">S.</hi> in each <hi rend="italic">Superſcription</hi> or di-
                <lb/>rection: <hi rend="italic">e. g.</hi> (<hi rend="italic">S. lit. A</hi>, <hi
                  rend="italic">vel</hi> n°. 1.). But this is <lb/>unneceſſary where there is but
                one <hi rend="italic">formula</hi> pre- <lb/>ſcribed, or where there is ſeveral, but
                eaſily di- <lb/>ſtinguiſhable from each other. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>3. There muſt be then annex'd the title of the <lb/>medicine, taken from its
                form and virtue, <hi rend="italic">e. g. <lb/>potio purgans</hi>, a purging draught,
                  <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
              </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>4. Next in order, the doſe, way of taking, <lb/>the time when, the vehicle and
                the regimen; <pb n="23"/>
                <lb/>and if any thing elſe is to be obſerved, it ſhou'd <lb/>be mentioned in its
                proper place. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>5. Since this direction (n°. 1. to 4.) contains <lb/>the rules to be obſerved
                by the patient in taking <lb/>or applying the remedy; it ſhou'd be either cut
                <lb/>off from the <hi rend="italic">formula</hi> or preſcription for him to
                <lb/>keep, or elſe (which is the common practice) it <lb/>ſhou'd be tranſlated and
                wrote fair by the apo- <lb/>thecary, on every label that is affix'd to the re-
                <lb/>ceptacle of the medicine, to be tranſmitted there- <lb/>with to the patient.
              </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>6. The ſtyle of the direction ſhou'd be there- <lb/>fore agreeable with the age
                and country wherein <lb/>it is wrote, being conciſe and plain, or very in-
                <lb/>telligible. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>7. In naming the medicine we ſhou'd avoid <lb/>the oſtentatious or quackiſh
                titles uſed by pre- <lb/>tenders, nor ihou'd we ever inhanſe or give it <lb/>an
                hyperbolical epithet; as <hi rend="italic">incomparable</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                  >golden</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">grand</hi>, &amp;c. For tho' theſe may take
                with the <lb/>vulgar and illiterate, it will but expoſe the pre- <lb/>ſcriber to
                laughter and ridicule, among the more <lb/>intelligible part of mankind. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>8. Care is to be alſo taken to hide or omit the <lb/>names of ſuch diſeaſes as
                are indecent or impro- <lb/>per to be mention'd in the directions; as the <lb/><hi
                  rend="italic">lues venerea</hi>, diſorders of the <hi rend="italic">menſes</hi>,
                ſterility, <lb/>impotency, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> For ſuch ſhou'd be either
                <lb/>wholly neglected, or at leaſt ſigniſied by terms <lb/>the leaſt known: as
                exciters of the <hi rend="italic">menſes</hi> may <lb/>be call'd aperients;
                antivenerials, puriſiers of <lb/>the blood; exciters of <hi rend="italic"
                >Venus</hi>, ſtrengtheners, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
                <lb/>And what relates to the method of taking, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
                <lb/>ſhou'd be delivered to the patient, if poſſible, <lb/>by word of mouth. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>9. The doſe of the medicine, when left to <lb/>the patient or his attendants,
                ſhou'd be ordered <lb/>by quantities the moſt commonly known and <pb n="24"/>
                <lb/>eaſy to determine; as by large or tea ſpoons full, <lb/>the ſize of nuts,
                drops, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> But if it be of <lb/>conſequence to have the
                doſe determined to ex- <lb/>actneſs; the diſtribution and exhibition thereof,
                <lb/>may be referr'd to the apothecary. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>10. The method and time of adminiftring the <lb/>remedy, depending upon the
                particular nature <lb/>of the diſeaſe, the medicine itſelf, and many <lb/>other
                circumſtances; ſhou'd be in the general di- <lb/>rected ſo as to ſuit beſt with the
                phyſician's in- <lb/>tention, and the patient's convenience: neg- <lb/>lecting the
                ſcrupulous and ſuperſtitious obſerva- <lb/>tion of times and ſeaſons deduced from
                aſtrolo- <lb/>gy, as both uſeleſs and unbecoming the ſagacity <lb/>of our age. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>11. If there be any occaſion for a vehicle to <lb/>take it in, we ſhou'd
                endeavour to chuſe one, <lb/>that beſides pleaſing the palate, falls in with the
                <lb/>intention of the medicine itſelf. The materials <lb/>for vehicles are uſually
                taken from things that <lb/>are readieſt at hand, grateful or pleaſant to the
                <lb/>patient, or become ſo by common and frequent <lb/>uſe: as ale, wine, broth,
                tea, coffee, juleps, <lb/>wafers, marmalade, roaſted apple, or the like. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>12. A proper <hi rend="italic">regimen</hi>, before, in, and after <lb/>the
                operation of the medicine, is often abſo- <lb/>lutely neceſſary to be obſerved; for
                without this, <lb/>the action of the remedy wou'd be frequently, <lb/>either too
                much increaſed, diminiſh'd, chang'd, <lb/>or wholly deſtroyed. But to determine what
                re- <lb/>gimen will be moſt proper, the doctrine of in- <lb/>dications muſt be
                call'd into conſideration. </p>
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 61. We have been hitherto treating of a <hi rend="italic">for- <lb/>mula in
            general</hi>, excluſive of its particular contents; <lb/>we come now to examine its
          internal compoſition, <lb/>the number of its conſtituent parts, their nature,
          <lb/>quantity, mutual affinity, proportion and the like. </p>
        <pb n="25"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 62. The formula, or preſcript (§. 1. <hi rend="italic">&amp;</hi>
          <lb/>§. 6.) conſiſts either of (1.) only one officinal ſim- <lb/>ple or compound
          preparation; or elſe (2.) of ſe- <lb/>veral ſuch properly combined together: which
          <lb/>firſt, we ſhall call a <hi rend="italic">ſimple formula</hi>; but the laſt, a
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">compound</hi> one. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 63. A ſimple <hi rend="italic">formula</hi> (§. 62.), as it con- <lb/>ſiſts of but
          one officinal preparation ſelected out of <lb/>many, does ſcarce require any other
          reſtriction or <lb/>limitation than that of its <hi rend="italic">quantity</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 64. Its <hi rend="italic">quantity</hi> then, is twofold: (1.) ſo <lb/>much as is
          order'd by the phyſician to be made up <lb/>and ſent to the patient by the apothecary at
          one <lb/>time; or (2.) ſuch a quantity of the firſt as is to <lb/>be applied or
          adminiſtred to the ſick patient at <lb/>once. The firſt, we ſhall call the <hi
            rend="italic">general</hi> quantity; <lb/>the latter, the <hi rend="italic"
            >particular</hi> one, or <hi rend="italic">doſe</hi>: but as the <lb/>quantity of the
          firſt depends upon the number of <lb/>the laſt, we ſhall conſider that before the former. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 65. The <hi rend="italic">doſe</hi> of a medicine comes under two
          <lb/>conſiderations; <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> that of <hi rend="italic">continued
            quantity</hi>, and <lb/>that of <hi rend="italic">number</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 66. The bulk or weight of a doſe, is deter- <lb/>mined by the phyſicians due
          conſideration of the <lb/>condition and circumſtances of both the patient and <lb/>the
          medicine: without which, a well choſen re- <lb/>medy, by exceeding or falling ſhort of its
          juſt <lb/>quantity, may prove either hurtful or at leaft in- <lb/>effectual. To prevent
          this, we muſt therefore at- <lb/>tend <lb/>
          <list rend="indentall">
            <item>
              <p>
                <lb/>1. To the nature of the <hi rend="italic">diſeaſe</hi>, its ſeat, ſtage,
                <lb/>force or degree of ſtrength, cauſes, ſymptoms, <lb/><hi rend="italic"
                  >&amp;c.</hi> that our force may be proportion'd to the <lb/>obſtacle to be
                removed. For as diſeaſes that are <lb/>violent, acute or deep-rooted, are ſcarce to
                be <lb/>overcome but by large doſes; ſo, if we ſhou'd <lb/>overload a ſlight caſe,
                the remedy itſelf wou'd <lb/>prove another diſeaſe. </p>
            </item>
            <pb n="26"/>
            <lb/>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>2. We muſt regard the <hi rend="italic">ſtrength</hi>; depending <lb/>on that
                of the fibre, or the blood's motion, and <lb/>functions of the body: that our
                aſſiſtant means <lb/>may be adiquate the defect, and not prove a bur- <lb/>then
                inſtead of a helping hand. So that large <lb/>doſes will be found to ſuit ſtrong
                bodies; whereas <lb/>the weak can only bear ſmall ones. But we muſt <lb/>carefully
                diſtinguiſh ſtrength that is latent and <lb/>oppreſs'd, from that which is really
                abſent and <lb/>exhauſted. </p>
            </item>
            <lb/>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>3. We muſt have reſpect to the <hi rend="italic">age</hi>: with re- <lb/>gard
                to which, the following general rules may <lb/>be of ſervice for internal medicines. </p>
              <lb/>
              <p rend="indent space">
                <lb/>Suppoſe a doſe proper for a man of a conſiſtent <lb/>age (<hi rend="italic">i.
                  e.</hi>) about 30, or when he has done growing) <lb/>to be </p>
              <table rend="space">
                <row>
                  <cell>as </cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>1, or ʒj. </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>a doſe </cell>
                  <cell>for one of</cell>
                  <cell>14 to 21, will be</cell>
                  <cell><formula notation="fraction">2/3</formula> or ℈ij. </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>— </cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>7 to 14, —</cell>
                  <cell><formula notation="fraction">1/2</formula>, or ʒß.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>4 to 7, —</cell>
                  <cell><formula notation="fraction">1/3</formula>, or ℈j. </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>4 —</cell>
                  <cell><formula notation="fraction">1/4</formula>, or <hi rend="italic">gr</hi>.
                    xv. </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>3 —</cell>
                  <cell><formula notation="fraction">1/6</formula>, or ℈ß. </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>2 —</cell>
                  <cell><formula notation="fraction">1/8</formula>, or <hi rend="italic">gr</hi>.
                    viij. </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>1 — </cell>
                  <cell><formula notation="fraction">1/12</formula>, or <hi rend="italic">gr</hi>.
                    v. </cell>
                </row>
              </table>
              <p rend="indent space">
                <lb/>Old people being obſerved to be twice children <lb/>in their ſtrength and diet,
                as ſuch they ſhou'd be <lb/>alſo conſider'd in this reſpect of doſe; ſo that we
                <lb/>may compare </p>
              <table>
                <row>
                  <cell>an old man of 60,</cell>
                  <cell>to a young man of</cell>
                  <cell>21 years. </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>— — 70,</cell>
                  <cell>— </cell>
                  <cell>14 </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>— — 80,</cell>
                  <cell>— </cell>
                  <cell>7 </cell>
                </row>
              </table>
              <p>
                <lb/>and ſo with the reſt. But it cannot be ſuppoſed that <lb/>theſe rules hold
                always ſo, as not to admit of many <pb n="27"/>
                <lb/>exceptions; for, that there muſt be frequently a <lb/>variation, will appear
                evidently to all who conſi- <lb/>der the diverſity of ſtrength in people of the ſame
                <lb/>age. So that a true eſtimate of the doſe, is hardly <lb/>deducible from the age
                alone. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent space">
                <lb/>4. The <hi rend="italic">ſize</hi> of the body, in people of the <lb/>ſame age,
                does alſo frequently require a variation <lb/>in the doſe; tho' we ſhall find, their
                ſtrength is <lb/>not always proportionable to their ſize. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>5. The <hi rend="italic">temperature</hi> has alſo ſome influence <lb/>upon the
                quantity of a doſe. The bilioſe and <lb/>melancholly can eaſily diſpenſe with a
                larger <lb/>maſs of cooling, moiſtening and relaxing me- <lb/>dicines, than their
                oppoſite temperatures; and <lb/>ſo (<hi rend="italic">vice verſa</hi>) on the
                contrary ſide. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>6. The difference of <hi rend="italic">ſex</hi> has alſo its force. <lb/>Women,
                who are generally of a more delicate <lb/>and weak conſtitution than men, require a
                pro- <lb/>portionable diminution of the doſe. But ſuch as <lb/>are very <choice>
                  <corr>nice and</corr>
                  <sic>niceand</sic>
                </choice> fanciful, will ſometimes throw <lb/>up the doſe notwithſtanding it was
                proportion'd <lb/>to their ſtrength. For ſuch, it is therefore ad- <lb/>viſable to
                let the quantity be as ſmall as poſſible; <lb/>or elſe to ſubdivide a larger doſe
                into ſeveral <lb/>ſmaller parcels. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>7. The particular <hi rend="italic">diſpoſition</hi>, whether morbid,
                <lb/>natural, conſtant, periodical, from the make or <lb/>habit of body, ſex,
                preceeding diſeaſes, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
                <lb/>with the complication of the original diſeaſe, <lb/>may have each their concern
                in determining the <lb/>particular doſe as well as the kind of a medi- <lb/>cine. </p>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>To this head belong a regard to the menſes, <lb/>breeding, lying-in, ſuckling,
                hyſteric fits in wo- <lb/>men, and the hippo in men; with obeſity, tender-
                <lb/>neſs, a weakneſs in ſome particular organ, a defor- <lb/>mity in the back or
                breaſt, the ſtone, an aptneſs to <pb n="28"/>
                <lb/>vomit, with abundance of the like particular indif- <lb/>poſitions. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>8. To be ſtill more particular, it is ſometimes <lb/>very neceſſary to have a
                regard to the individual <lb/><hi rend="italic">conſtitution</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                  >idioſyncraſia</hi>, or particular inclina- <lb/>tion of every patient, as they
                ſtand affected to <lb/>this or that claſs of medicines, or ſome one par-
                <lb/>ticular remedy. Theſe being generally inexpli- <lb/>cable, are to be known only
                by experience, or <lb/>from the patient's relation: thus ſome are pur- <lb/>ged even
                by the ſmell of a <hi rend="italic">cathartic</hi>; while <lb/>others are ſcarce
                affected by double the uſual <lb/>quantity taken inwardly for a doſe. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>9. <hi rend="italic">Uſe</hi> or cuſtom has alſo its force here; for <lb/>a
                large doſe of a medicine will produce leſs ef- <lb/>fect upon one uſed to the ſame,
                than a ſmall <lb/>doſe upon one who is a ſtranger thereto; which <lb/>is very
                obvious in the uſe of narcotics and to- <lb/>bacco. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>10. Nor is the <hi rend="italic">employ</hi> or courſe of liſe to be <lb/>here
                altogether neglected; for as the ſeveral de- <lb/>grees of health and ſickneſs are
                particularly in- <lb/>fluenced thereby; ſo it alſo frequently brings the <lb/>body
                into particular habits, which either in- <lb/>creaſe or diminiſh the action of
                certain medicines. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>11. The particular <hi rend="italic">nation</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                  >people</hi> is to be <lb/>alſo conſider'd with regard to the doſe; as they
                <lb/>have often ſomething in that reſpect ſingular and <lb/>proper to themſelves.
                Thus, the <hi rend="italic">Saxons</hi> and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Weſtphalians</hi>
                <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.5)">
                  <p rend="indent italic"><lb/>* <hi rend="roman">Wedelii</hi> de compoſ. medic.
                    tab. II. </p>
                </note>, are hard to work upon. The <lb/><hi rend="italic">Siameſe</hi> uſe an
                arſenical inſtead of an antimonial <lb/>cup; and the <hi rend="italic">Indians</hi>
                require a doſe of ipecacu- <lb/>anha twenty times as large as the <hi rend="italic"
                  >Europeans</hi>, to <lb/>make them vomit <note rend="size(0.5)" place="bottom"
                  n="†">
                  <p rend="indent italic"><lb/>† Hiſtoire de l'academ royale, 1703. </p>
                </note>. </p>
            </item>
            <pb n="29"/>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>12. A regard to the <hi rend="italic">ſeaſon</hi> of the year is alſo
                <lb/>ſometimes of conſequence: as the ſultry dog- <lb/>days, the hard froſt, or the
                temperate air, diſ- <lb/>poſe the body to be more or leſs affected by <lb/>one and
                the ſame doſe. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>13. The known <hi rend="italic">ſtrength</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                  >virtues</hi> of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">remedy</hi> alſo, when conſider'd with
                their relation <lb/>to the ſeveral preceeding heads, ſtill greatly in- <lb/>creaſe
                the variation of the doſe. Thence, a phy- <lb/>ſician that intends to preſcribe
                forms rationally, <lb/>will make himſelf exactly acquainted with the <lb/>ſeveral
                quantities of medicines found by experi- <lb/>ence, and eſtabliſhed by uſe to be
                proper for one <lb/>doſe: with the ſeveral degrees of that doſe, as <lb/>being
                ſmall, mean or large, with reſpect to the <lb/>preceeding conſiderations; more
                eſpecially he <lb/>will keep in memory thoſe of the capital and <lb/>moſt
                efficacious medicines. But if he would <lb/>bring any ſimple into uſe which has not
                been yet <lb/>ſufficiently experienced, being mindful of the <lb/>rule §. 19. he
                will begin firſt with the leaſt quan- <lb/>tity, afterwards judiciouſly inlarging
                the doſe, <lb/>as he is aſſured of the preceeding unactivity, or <lb/>uſefulneſs of
                the medicine. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>14. Sometimes the high <hi rend="italic">price</hi> of medicines, <lb/>which
                are otherwiſe of no great efficacy, reſtrains <lb/>the doſe to a ſmall compaſs;
                witneſs, prepared <lb/>pearl, gems, oriental and porcupine bezoar, <hi rend="italic"
                  >&amp;c.</hi>
              </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>15. The great <hi rend="italic">bulkeyneſs</hi> of the <hi rend="italic"
                  >matter</hi>, con- <lb/>taining but a due quantity of medicinal parti- <lb/>cles,
                obliges the doſe to be ſometimes leſs than <lb/>is otherwiſe requiſite; left the
                load of inactive <lb/>matter ſhou'd excite a <hi rend="italic">nauſea</hi>: as is
                often the <lb/>caſe in herbs, barks, woods, flowers, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
              </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>16. The <hi rend="italic">unpleaſantneſs</hi> of a medicine, whether <lb/>in
                taſte, ſmell, or other qualities, frequently per- <lb/>ſwades the phyſician to
                preſcribe them in a ſmal- <lb/>ler doſe than the other: as <hi rend="italic">aſa
                  fæt. caſtor. olea, <lb/>&amp;c.</hi> agreeable to §. 27. </p>
            </item>
            <pb n="30"/>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>17. The particular <hi rend="italic">form of the medicine</hi> itſelf,
                <lb/>often reſtrains the doſe to a determinate <hi rend="italic">quantum</hi>.
                <lb/>For many of the forms have certain limits as to <lb/>quantity, which they
                cannot exceed without the <lb/>greateſt neceſſity; as will hereafter appear under
                <lb/>each. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>18. Laſtly, the various external or internal <lb/><hi rend="italic">uſe</hi> of
                a remedy, and its application to different <lb/>parts of the body, are here, alſo;
                to be conſi- <lb/>dered as having ſome influence in determining <lb/>the quantity of
                a doſe. Very wide is the diffe- <lb/>rence between the doſe of a cathartic when it
                is <lb/>to be given by the mouth, and when by way of <lb/>glyſter, <hi rend="italic"
                  >&amp;c.</hi>
              </p>
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Nota.</hi> The limits of our preſent deſign forbid <lb/>me to ſay
          more, or to purſue the theme of <hi rend="italic">doſe</hi> in <lb/>a more ſpecial manner.
          The copiouſneſs and un- <lb/>certainty of the ſubject, being ſcarce determinable <lb/>even
          by general bounds, prevailed with me not to <lb/>inſert (as is uſual) a table exhibiting
          the proper doſe <lb/>of every ſingle remedy. Theſe are liable to ſo many <lb/>exceptions,
          that they cannot be rationally aſcer- <lb/>tain'd to particular caſes, without the ſeveral
          pre- <lb/>ceeding conditions (§. 66. n°. 1 to 18.) are firſt li- <lb/>mited and
          conſider'd. Beſides, we have ſuppoſed <lb/>our reader (<hi rend="italic">per</hi> §. 7.)
          previouſly acquainted with the <lb/>doctrine of indications, and the <hi rend="italic"
            >materia medica</hi>, <lb/>both ſimple and compound; which teaches their <lb/>general
          doſes as well as virtues: and then, what <lb/>will be ſaid of each form in particular,
          will alſo <lb/>reflect much light upon this head. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>§. 67. The <hi rend="italic">number</hi> of doſes (§. 65.) is either <lb/>one, or
          more, being often arbitrary and undeter- <lb/>mined; but it may be generally limited by
          parti- <lb/>cular conſideration; among which, the following <lb/>may be look'd upon as
          general rules. <pb n="31"/>
          <lb/>
          <list>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>1. If one doſe will anſwer the phyſicians in- <lb/>tention; what need of more?
              </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>2. If the medicine be in itſelf unpleaſant, if <lb/>the patient has an averſion
                or diſlike to the taking <lb/>of it, or if the application or taking be difficult
                <lb/>and troubleſome; theſe call for the exhibition of <lb/>as few doſes as
                poſſible. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>3. Medicines, which by keeping, eaſily fer- <lb/>ment and corrupt, grow moiſt
                and liquid, or too <lb/>dry, or elſe exhale and loſe their fineſt parts,
                <lb/>ſhou'd, upon thoſe accounts, be preſcribed in <lb/>but few doſes at a time. The
                different ſtate <lb/>of the atmoſphere, as to heat, moiſture, and <lb/>other
                qualities, has alſo its ſhare in limiting the <lb/>quantity and number of doſes of
                ſuch remedies; <lb/>as thoſe ſtates of the air may more or leſs pro- <lb/>mote ſuch
                inconveniences or defects of particu- <lb/>lar medicines. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>4. If the adequate doſe of a preſcribed medi- <lb/>cine is of a larger bulk
                than can be conveniently <lb/>ſwallow'd at once, if nothing contradicts, it may
                <lb/>be properly divided into many leſſer doſes, to be <lb/>taken at ſmall
                intervals; to prevent it from ex- <lb/>citing a nauſea or vomiting in the patient;
                <lb/>which is a conſideration that takes place princi- <lb/>pally and frequently in
                emetics and ſtrong ca- <lb/>thartics. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>5. If you order potent remedies for a patient <lb/>whoſe caſe, conſtitution,
                and particular condi- <lb/>tion is not yet thoroughly known; it is better <lb/>for
                the juſt doſe to be given in little ſeparate por- <lb/>tions at ſeveral times, that
                we may timely break <lb/>off its uſe upon the leaſt appearance of its im-
                <lb/>propriety. The ſame holds good alſo with re- <lb/>gard to the uſe of new and
                leſs experienced re- <lb/>medies (agreeable to §. 66. n°. 13.) </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>6. If the obſcurity, or inſtability, of the par- <lb/>ticular morbid
                indiſpoſition renders the effect of <pb n="32"/>
                <lb/>the medicine uncertain; if we are obliged to <lb/>preſcribe ſomething (by
                reaſon of §. 14.), it <lb/>ſhould be but in ſmall and few doſes: by which
                <lb/>means, leſs injury can happen to the patient, and <lb/>it may be the more
                eaſily changed for ſome other <lb/>medicine, when that may be required. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>7. When the preparation of a medicine is dif- <lb/>ficult and a long while in
                making up, unleſs <lb/>ſomething forbid, it ſhou'd be preſcribed in <lb/>a larger
                quantity or more doſes; to ſpare the <lb/>time and pains of the apothecary, whoſe
                hands <lb/>are ſometimes too full. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>8. Hence alſo, remedies which are difficultly <lb/>convey'd, and to parts
                remote from apotheca- <lb/>ries, ſhou'd be (<hi rend="italic">cæteris paribus</hi>)
                preſcribed and <lb/>tranſmitted in larger quantities or more doſes. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>9. On the other hand, if the patient lives near <lb/>his phyſician, ſo as to be
                often viſited by him, <lb/>the number of doſes order'd at one time ſhou'd be
                <lb/>few; leſt the phyſician's coming often without <lb/>preſcribing ſhou'd be
                thought much of, or look'd <lb/>upon as dilatory. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>10. When the ſame medicine is required to be <lb/>uſed for a long time
                together; there ſhou'd be <lb/>as many doſes order'd at once as may be conve-
                <lb/>nient. For tho' ſcantineſs of a medicine for mo- <lb/>ney, is a perſuaſive for
                the patient to take it <lb/>when bought; it will hardly encourage him to <lb/>be
                conſtantly purchaſing, eſpecially if it be diſa- <lb/>greeable at the ſame time.
              </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>11. If the exhibition of the medicine is to <lb/>be repeated at ſhort intervals
                of time, the doſes <lb/>muſt be on that account the more numerous; to <lb/>prevent
                the trouble of repeating the preſcription <lb/>and compoſition. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>12. Laſtly, as the patient may like a variety, <lb/>and the different face of
                the ſymptoms require a <lb/>change (<hi rend="italic">per</hi> §. 50.), both in the
                form and me- <pb n="33"/>
                <lb/>medicine, eſpecially in chronical caſes; it may <lb/>be on thoſe accounts
                adviſeable to order the me- <lb/>dicine in a ſmall quantity: that the form and
                <lb/>remedy may be changed the oftener, and at a <lb/>leſs expence to the patient.
              </p>
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 68. The <hi rend="italic">general quantity</hi> (§. 64.) of any form <lb/>fit to
          be preſcribed for the patient at one time, <lb/>may be eaſily eſtimated from a previous
          determi- <lb/>nation of the number or ſize of the proper doſe, <lb/>(<hi rend="italic"
            >per</hi> §. 66. 67.): for, if the bulk or weight of a <lb/>doſe be multiplied by the
          number you would give, <lb/>the product will be the whole quantity to be or- <lb/>der'd
          for the patient in one preſcription. Whence <lb/>it follows, <list rend="indentall">
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>1. That the general quantity will be equal to <lb/>the ſpecial or particular
                one (§. 64.), if only <lb/>one doſe be preſcribed for at one time. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>2. But if we deſign the preſcription ſhould <lb/>contain more doſes than one,
                the leaſt general <lb/>quantity that can be order'd will be doubly <lb/>equal to the
                particular one, or doſe. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>3. If the doſe of a form is to be exactly de- <lb/>termin'd by weight, the
                general quantity ſhould <lb/>be proportioned ſo, as that it may be diſtribu-
                <lb/>ted into proper and exacft doſes, without leaving <lb/>any remainder. But this
                rule is not conſtantly <lb/>and every where obſerv'd; eſpecially if the pre-
                <lb/>ſcription contains many doſes of a form. </p>
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 69. The phyfician ſhould alſo be mindful of <lb/>the particular conſiſtence and
          texture of his ingre- <lb/>dient, when he preſcribes a ſimple formula; that <lb/>it may
          have a natural fitneſs to be reduced into the <lb/>form he deſires. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 70. Laſtly, when his preſcription orders but <lb/>one ingredient, he ſhould be
          careful that it be not <lb/>over ſtrong, nauſeous to the ſmell or taſte, nor <pb n="34"/>
          <lb/>difficult to ſwallow, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> (<hi rend="italic">per</hi> §.
          27.); becauſe a <lb/>ſimple formula does not admit of that correction <lb/>and mixture
          which are neceſſary to conceal thoſe <lb/>diſagreeable qualities; unleſs he will
          compliment <lb/>the patient, by ordering the medicine to be taken <lb/>in ſome proper and
          pleaſant vehicle. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 71. We have been hitherto conſidering a <lb/>ſimple formula: our next buſineſs is
          to treat of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">compound</hi> one (§. 62.); which conſiſting of
          ſeveral <lb/>ingredients, requires greater circumſpection and <lb/>ſkill in is
          preſcription and compoſition. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 72. There ſeems, at the firſt view indeed, to <lb/>be little or ſeldom occaſion
          for extemporaneous <lb/>compoſition; ſince we are furniſhed with ſuch a <lb/>number of
          ſtanding officinal compounds (<hi rend="italic">per</hi> §. 31. <lb/>and 37.): but the
          frequent and great neceſſity we <lb/>are under of forming the officinals into extempo-
          <lb/>raneous compoſitions, is ſufficiently apparent from <lb/>the following. For, <list
            rend="indentall">
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>1. The <hi rend="italic">officinel</hi> ſimples and compounds are
                <lb/>frequently not well adapted to the particular cir- <lb/>cumſtances of the
                patient and his diſeaſe. Their <lb/>doſe is frequently too bulky for their ſtrength,
                <lb/>their compoſition unjuſt or inaccurate, and their <lb/>textures or virtues
                changed or ſpoiled by long <lb/>keeping, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> which
                conſiderations are often e- <lb/>nough to diſſuade one from the uſe of officinal
                <lb/>compounds, tho' they were directly ſuitable for <lb/>the intention. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>2. When the virtues and ſtrength of an offi- <lb/>cinal medicine are too weak,
                and not equal to <lb/>the diſeaſe we would remove; we are then of- <lb/>ten obliged
                to the addition of others, more po- <lb/>tent, in an extemporaneous compoſition.
              </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>3. If its action be too violent, or attended <lb/>with ſome ill conſequence; we
                are then often <lb/>obliged to moderate and correct it by extempo- <lb/>raneous
                compoſition. </p>
            </item>
            <pb n="35"/>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>4. We have frequently ſeveral different in- <lb/>tentions to anſwer at the ſame
                time, which can <lb/>not be done by one officinal ſimple or com- <lb/>pound: while
                the natural diſpoſition of the ſe- <lb/>veral ingredients indicated, to make a
                uniform <lb/>mixture, requires them to be reduced into one <lb/>form (<hi
                  rend="italic">per</hi> §. 39.) </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>5. This compoſition is ſometimes required <lb/>alſo from the ſituation,
                ſenſibility, and other <lb/>circumſtances of the Part to which the medicine <lb/>is
                to be applied or conveyed. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>6. The conſtituent ingredients ſuited to each <lb/>indication do alſo require
                to be combined in a <lb/>form, for the reafons (§. 43. to §. 50.) which
                <lb/>determine the particular form, they being of <lb/>themſelves very unſuitable.
              </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>7. Compoſition ſometimes ſerves to conceal a <lb/>neceſſary remedy (<hi
                  rend="italic">per</hi> §. 25.) </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>8. It is often requiſite, in order to change or <lb/>correct ſome diſagreeable
                ſmell, taſte or colour, <lb/>in an effectual remedy. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p rend="indent">
                <lb/>9. <hi rend="italic">Laſtly</hi>, the vile and received cuſtom of
                <lb/>crouding, without neceſſity, more ingredients <lb/>than are required in an
                officinal compoſition, <lb/>often obliges the phyſician to make a new form:
                <lb/>tho' prudence ſometimes bids the phyſician, <lb/>eſpecially a junior, (<hi
                  rend="italic">per</hi> §. 30.) to pay obedi- <lb/>ence to ſuch old and venerable
                jumbles. </p>
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 73. In the compound formula (§. 71.) we <lb/>are to conſider (1.) its <hi
            rend="italic">component parts</hi>, their num- <lb/>ber, uſe and proportion: (2.) its
            <hi rend="italic">quantity</hi> (§. 64.) <lb/>general, to be made up at once; and
          particular, to <lb/>be taken at once. (3.) And laſtly, its <hi rend="italic"
            >qualities</hi>, <lb/>as ariſing from compoſition or mixture. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 74. The conſtituent parts are four in num- <lb/>ber: (1.) the <hi rend="italic"
            >baſis</hi> or main ingredients; (2.) the <lb/><hi rend="italic">adjuvans</hi>, or what
          promotes the action of the for- <pb n="36"/>
          <lb/>mer; ( 3.) the <hi rend="italic">corrigens</hi>, or correcter of ſomething
          <lb/>improper therein; (4.) and laſtly, the <hi rend="italic">conſtituens</hi>, <lb/>or
          what ſerves to inlarge, mix and make up the <lb/>whole. If there be any <hi rend="italic"
            >dirigens</hi>, which ſome <lb/>make a fifth Part, it may be properly taken in
          <lb/>under the <hi rend="italic">adjuvans</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>§. 75. The <hi rend="sc">Basis</hi> is the principal part in the <lb/>compoſition,
          calculated againſt the immediate cauſe <lb/>and chief ſymptoms of the diſeaſe, being that
          by <lb/>which the phyſician endeavours chiefly to anſwer <lb/>his indications. This is
          required to be preſent in <lb/>every form, even the ſimple one, (§. 63.) where <lb/>it
          often makes the whole formula: being ſometimes <lb/>ſufficient of itſelf alone, without
          any other addi- <lb/>tion; but it is frequently mixed with other things, <lb/>ſuitable to
          make it act with ſafety, eaſe and expe- <lb/>dition, as it ought. </p>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" quantity="18" unit="pages"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
