<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Dossie: The Elaboratory laid open</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Robert Dossie</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">The Elaboratory laid open, or, the Secrets of Modern Chemistry and
              Pharmacy Revealed: Containing many Particulars extremely necessary to be known to all
              Practitioners in Medicine.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T142341</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T142341"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Nourse at the Lamb opposite Katherine-Street in the
                  Strand, MDCCLVIII.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1758</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="15"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="375"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="8"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107567544</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Recipe collections"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="15"/>
    <body>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="84"/>
      <pb n="85"/>
      <div>
        <head rend="size(1.75) align-center">
          <lb/>PART II. </head>
        <head rend="size(1.25) hanging space">
          <lb/>Of the preparation of chemical medi- <lb/>cines: with the ſeveral ſubſtitutions
          <lb/>and adulterations practiſed in rela- <lb/>tion to them; as alſo the beſt means
          <lb/>of detecting ſuch practices. </head>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/>SECTION I. </head>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) hanging">
            <lb/>Of the preparation of thoſe medicines, <lb/>where ſaline ſubſtances make the whole,
            <lb/>or principal part of the ſubject. </head>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center">
              <lb/>Preparation of ſpirit of hartſhorn. </head>
            <p rend="space">
              <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">L</hi>ET pieces of hartſhorn be diſtilled, with <lb/>a fire
              gradually augmented, almoſt to <lb/>the greateſt degree. Spirit, ſalt, and oil will
              <lb/>ariſe: and, the oil being taken from them, let <lb/>the ſpirit, and ſalt, be mixt
              together again; and <lb/>diſtilled with a very gentle heat, and they will <lb/>both
              riſe purer: which operation being ſeve- <lb/>ral times cautiouſly repeated, and a
              proper <lb/>part of the ſalt taken away to be reſerved for <lb/>ſublimation, the
              ſpirit will become limpid as <lb/>water, and have a grateful ſmell. </p>
          </div>
          <pb n="86"/>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Spirit of hartſhorn is one of the capital ar- <lb/>ticles of the chemical
              pharmacy, and has un- <lb/>dergone a greater reſolution, in its price, and <lb/>manner
              of preparation, than any medicine <lb/>whatever. A few years ago, the loweſt rate
              <lb/>it was ſold for, in the moſt wholeſale way, was <lb/>half a crown, or three
              ſhillings per pound: it <lb/>has ſince been reduced to the low price of five
              <lb/>pence or a groat; at which rate, a great part <lb/>of the conſumption has been
              ſupplied, by the <lb/>preparers, to the wholeſale dealers. This is <lb/>done by an
              intire ſubſtitution of other volatile <lb/>ſpirits, diſtilled from ſubſtances much
              cheaper <lb/>than hartſhorn: and by the treating even theſe <lb/>in ſuch a manner as
              diſguiſes their real ſtrength; <lb/>and makes even very weak paſs for extreme
              <lb/>good ſpirit of hartſhorn, though ſold as at this <lb/>exceſſive low price:
              whereas genuine ſpirit of <lb/>hartſhorn, prepared as the above proceſs directs,
              <lb/>can never be afforded with reaſonable profit for <lb/>leſs than two ſhillings per
              pound. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>It is not, however, eſſential, that this medi- <lb/>cine ſhould be prepared from
              horn; but rather <lb/>improper: for volatile ſpirits, obtained from this
              <lb/>ſubſtance, however often they may be recti- <lb/>fied, at leaſt within any
              moderate compaſs, are <lb/>apt to grow brown, foul, and fœtid: ſo that, <lb/>if kept
              for any length of time, they become <lb/>nauſeous and unſightly: whereas, if diſtilled
              <lb/>from bones properly prepared, they require <pb n="87"/>
              <lb/>much leſs rectification; are more palatable and <lb/>grateful to the ſtomach; and
              will retain their <lb/>limpid and colourleſs appearance for a conſi- <lb/>derable
              duration, a quality very valuable to apo- <lb/>thecaries, eſpecially thoſe in the
              country, who <lb/>cannot be continually renewing their ſtock. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The redundance of, and unfavourable qua- <lb/>lity in, the burnt oil of horns, to
              which this un- <lb/>fitneſs to produce good volatile ſpirits is owing, <lb/>ariſe from
              the great quantity of the animal <lb/>gluten which all corneous ſubſtances contain:
              <lb/>this gluten abounding in all parts of animals <lb/>in proportion to their
              tenacity; of which indeed <lb/>it is the cauſe: and being, in fact, nothing but
              <lb/>oil mutually attracting and attracted by the earth, <lb/>which conſtitutes the
              ſolid baſis of the parts. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If we admit all volatile ſalts to be the ſame; <lb/>and conſider, that this
              compound, we call ſpirit <lb/>of hartſhorn, conſiſts of water, volatile ſalt, and
              <lb/>diſtilled animal oil; we ſhall ſee, that, as no <lb/>difference can lie in the
              volatile ſalts, or wa- <lb/>ter; it muſt, if there be any difference at all
              <lb/>betwixt this ſpirit, and that diſtilled from any <lb/>other animal ſubſtance, be
              in the oil only. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Now all diſtilled oils of animal ſubſtances, <lb/>being likewiſe of the ſame
              nature; except that, <lb/>by the action of the fire, ſome are higher ex- <lb/>alted,
              and gaining a more ethereal nature, be- <lb/>come leſs liable to putrefaction; while
              others, <lb/>being leſs changed from their original groſſer <lb/>ſtate, retain ſome
              tendency to putrefy; it muſt <lb/>appear, that there can be no difference in vola-
              <lb/>tile ſpirits, but in their being charged, in a <pb n="88"/>
              <lb/>greater or leſs proportion, with oils that vary <lb/>only in their exaltation, or
              approach to the ethe- <lb/>real ſtate; in the greater degree of which, con- <lb/>ſiſts
              their medicinal excellence: as may be <lb/>eaſily granted, when it is conſidered, in
              what in- <lb/>tention they are taken. If, therefore, it ſhould <lb/>be manifeſt, from
              experiment, that volatile <lb/>ſpirit, extracted from prepared bones, or any
              <lb/>other animal ſubſtance, contains a more ethe- <lb/>real oil, than ſpirit drawn
              from hartſhorn; <lb/>it muſt conſequently be concluded to be a <lb/>more efficacious
              medicine, as well as a much <lb/>more grateful and convenient one, on the ac-
              <lb/>count above mentioned. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Dr. P, in his notes on this article, in the <lb/>tranſlation of, the
              College-Diſpenſatory, ſeems <lb/>to think, this ſpirit ſhould be diveſted as much
              <lb/>as poſſible of the oil. For he places the per- <lb/>fection of the preparation in
              the number of <lb/>rectifications: and on this principle, half a <lb/>guinea an ounce
              has been charged for ſome <lb/>quantities, ſuppoſed to be thus improved. <lb/>But
              certainly there are limits to the proportion of <lb/>oil that ſhould be thus ſeparated
              from the <lb/>ſpirit: for if no oil were neceſſary to the con- <lb/>ſtituency of the
              medicine; but that a pure vo- <lb/>latile ſalt and water made its proper contents;
              <lb/>it might be much better prepared, by making <lb/>a ſolution of volatile ſalt of
              ſal Ammonia- <lb/>cum in water; or diſtilling ſuch a ſpirit <lb/>from a ſolution of
              ſal Ammoniacum with <lb/>ſalt of tartar: but the true compoſition <lb/>of it, is not,
              from volatile ſalts and water a- <pb n="89"/>
              <lb/>lone; but from theſe with the addition of <lb/>ethereal animal oil; which makes,
              with the o- <lb/>thers a volatile ſapo: the oil being evidently an <lb/>ingredient,
              correſpondent to the intention, e- <lb/>qually with the volatile ſalt; as may be
              gathered <lb/>from its affinity with other ethereal oils, as of <lb/>amber, or the
              aromatic vegetables, &amp;c. Which- <lb/>ever of theſe notions we adopt, the ſpirit of
              <lb/>bones ſeems ſtill preferable to thoſe of horn: <lb/>and we ſhall principally
              inquire, how that can <lb/>be beſt and cheapeſt prepared: but for the <lb/>ſake of
              thoſe, who adhere to the old faith, as to <lb/>the ſuperiority of the true ſpirit of
              hartſhorn, to <lb/>other volatile ſpirits diſtilled from other animals, <lb/>or parts
              of them, I ſhall firſt make ſome obſer- <lb/>vations on the regular proceſs above
              given, and <lb/>the beſt manner of performing it: pointing out, <lb/>alſo, the defects
              of the apparatus generally uſed; <lb/>and ſhewing how they may be beſt amended. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The pots, in which this diſtillation is made, <lb/>are much too ſmall; being, in
              general, made <lb/>to contain only three quarters of a hundred <lb/>weight of the
              horn: whereas, with the ſame <lb/>fire and trouble, double or treble the quantity
              <lb/>might be diſtilled together, in larger pots. The <lb/>reaſon for this
              unprofitable manner of work- <lb/>ing, has been the difficulty found in forming <lb/>a
              proper apparatus, for condenſing the diſtilled <lb/>vapour, when raiſed in a greater
              quantity than <lb/>three quarters of a hundred, or a hundred <lb/>weight of materials
              would afford. The moſt <lb/>general way has been to uſe, as a refrigeratory, <lb/>only
              a ſeries of glaſs allodials luted together, <pb n="90"/>
              <lb/>and terminating in a glaſs receiver: but later <lb/>improvements have introduced
              the uſe of a long <lb/>tin tube, joined to the pot by one or two al- <lb/>lodials
              placed next the pot, paſſing into a large <lb/>earthen or ſtone jar, made cloſe at the
              top, <lb/>and venting itſelf again by another tube of the <lb/>ſame kind, terminating
              either in another ſuch <lb/>jar, or a large glaſs receiver. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>This has been found much preferable to the <lb/>firſt method, of uſing glaſs
              allodials alone; <lb/>but both of them are far inferior to that de- <lb/>ſcribed in
              the next proceſs. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>By the beſt of theſe methods, ſix or eight <lb/>days are required, from the
              charging the pot, <lb/>to the finiſhing the operation: for a conſidera- <lb/>ble time
              is taken up, for the drying the lute; <lb/>which is with much trouble laid on, and re-
              <lb/>paired, at ſo many different junctures: and, <lb/>when this tedious part of the
              work is finiſhed, <lb/>the fire muſt be very well regulated, other- <lb/>wiſe the lute
              will be blown off, the ſtench be- <lb/>come intolerable, and a very great waſte made
              <lb/>of the produce of the operation; indeed a con- <lb/>ſiderable waſte, and a very
              bad ſmell, will al- <lb/>ways attend this manner of working, even <lb/>when beſt
              managed. There is indeed a way, <lb/>that has been hitherto overlooked, from the
              <lb/>almoſt univerſal ignorance in principles, of per- <lb/>ſons concerned in theſe
              operations, of prevent- <lb/>ing greatly the ſmell and waſte with the worſt
              <lb/>apparatus. For the force on the lute, being in <lb/>a great degree, owing to the
              air generated in <lb/>that analyſis, which the fire makes of the ele- <pb n="91"/>
              <lb/>ments that compoſe the ſubſtances diſtilled; <lb/>which air being incondenſible,
              as well as highly <lb/>elaſtic, muſt ſomewhere find a vent, as its quan- <lb/>tity
              augments; this air ſtraining the lute, cracks <lb/>and opens it; and preſſing out
              through theſe <lb/>cracks or openings, drives with it, likewiſe, the <lb/>condenſible
              part of the vapour, eſpecially a- <lb/>bout the head, and firſt allodial, which are
              re- <lb/>plete with ſuch vapour; becauſe the heat pre- <lb/>vents almoſt any
              condenſation from being per- <lb/>formed there. If, therefore, a proper vent
              <lb/>ſhould be made in the receiver, or ſome diſtant <lb/>part of the condenſing
              veſſels; by means of <lb/>which, the lute may be kept free from its ef- <lb/>forts,
              and remain intire: the rivus of air <lb/>would paſs forwards to the vent of the ex-
              <lb/>tremity of the ſurface, and drive along with <lb/>it the condenſible vapour that
              forms the di- <lb/>ſtilled ſpirit; which thus coming, in its paſ- <lb/>ſage, in
              contact with the refrigerating ſurface <lb/>of the veſſels, will be for the moſt part
              con- <lb/>denſed, and not blown out through the cracks, <lb/>otherwiſe produced in the
              lute. This vent <lb/>may be likewiſe carried into a ſmall tin pipe, <lb/>communicating
              with the chimney, or aſh- <lb/>hole; by which means, both the elaboratory, <lb/>and
              places contiguous, may be kept free, in a <lb/>great degree, from this troubleſome
              ſmell. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>It would be much better, however, in all <lb/>caſes, to uſe the worm, as a
              refrigeratory, in <lb/>the diſtillation of hartſhorn; according to the <lb/>directions
              given below: for though the ſalt <lb/>would not be obtained, in this part of the pro-
                <pb n="92"/>
              <lb/>ceſs, in ſuch proportion as when allodials are <lb/>uſed: yet a conſiderable
              quantity may be taken <lb/>out of the receiver, uſed in ſuch diſtillation; <lb/>and
              what more may be wanted, may be got <lb/>out of the receivers, uſed in the
              rectification; <lb/>if they be taken off before the ſpirit begins to <lb/>come over
              and waſh the ſalt off the ſides: and <lb/>the ſalt procured by theſe methods, will be
              <lb/>much freer from oil; and, conſequently, much <lb/>leſs troubleſome in rectifying,
              than that taken <lb/>out of the allodials: it being exactly the ſame, <lb/>in the
              reſult, which way it is ſeparated from <lb/>the diſtilled ſpirit; as there will the
              ſame pro- <lb/>portionable quantity remain in it after what is <lb/>taken. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Another defect in the common manage- <lb/>ment of the genuine ſpirit of
              hartſhorn, is, <lb/>the want of a more commodious method of <lb/>ſeparating,
              immediately after the diſtillation, <lb/>the foul oil, which comes over with the
              ſpirit <lb/>and ſalt, and cauſes a conſiderable waſte, when <lb/>taken out by the
              methods now uſed: and, <lb/>which not being very efficacious in freeing it <lb/>from
              the oil, occaſion the ſpirit to be injured <lb/>by being kept too long commixt with
              what is <lb/>left floating upon it. This may be beſt <lb/>remedied by employing the
              tritorium deſcribed in <lb/>the introduction, in the manner below ordered; <lb/>and
              treating the ſpirit according to the ſubſe- <lb/>quent directions there laid down. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>In the proceſs of the college above given, <lb/>the ſalt is ordered to be
              rectified along with the <lb/>ſpirit, before its being taken away to be ſub- <pb
                n="93"/>
              <lb/>limed; which is one of the moſt effectual <lb/>methods of giving it ſome degree
              of purity. <lb/>But the more common way, is to ſeparate it <lb/>from the ſpirit,
              immediately after the diſtilla- <lb/>tion from the materials; by which a conſiderable
              <lb/>delay is avoided in the rectification of the ſpirit. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The number of rectifications intimated to <lb/>be neceſſary in this proceſs, are
              likewiſe fre- <lb/>quently curtailed: though, in order to the <lb/>making the genuine
              ſpirit keep tolerably, there <lb/>ought to be four, and theſe performed at ſome
              <lb/>diſtance of time from each other; the oil <lb/>ſwimming on the ſurface of the
              fluid being care- <lb/>fully ſeparated after each; for fewer rectificati- <lb/>ons,
              performed at intervals of ſome length, <lb/>will render the ſpirit more pure than a
              greater <lb/>number, quicker repeated: as the oil can be <lb/>much more copiouſly
              ſeparated, from the ſpirit, <lb/>by rectification, after the natural ſeparation of
              <lb/>it by its own tendency, which ſhews itſelf by <lb/>a turbidneſs and ſediment,
              than, while they <lb/>remain more perfectly united, as in the limpid <lb/>ſtate they
              are found to be, for ſome time after <lb/>each rectification. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic hanging space">
              <lb/>Method of making ſpirit of hartſhorn, fictitious, <lb/>with reſpect to the
              materials, but perfect, with <lb/>regard to the qualities correſpondent to the in-
              <lb/>tention of medicine. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/> Take any quantity of the bones, from <lb/>whence the fat has been extracted, by
              thoſe <pb n="94"/>
              <lb/>who collect them for that purpoſe: diſtill <lb/>them, and rectify the ſalt and
              ſpirit together, <lb/>taking out a proper quantity of ſalt, which <lb/>will riſe
              before the ſpirit, by changing the <lb/>retort before the ſalt be melted by the
              ſpirit: <lb/>rectify the ſpirit twice more; and, after <lb/>keeping it for ſome time,
              filter it through <lb/>paper. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Theſe materials, both from their own nature, <lb/>and the previous preparation in
              the freeing them <lb/>from all oily ſubſtances, by the long boiling, <lb/>practiſed by
              the people, who collect them, are <lb/>the beſt and cheapeſt materials, from whence
              <lb/>this ſpirit could poſſibly be drawn: they may <lb/>be purchaſed, in London, at
              five ſhillings per <lb/>ton; and they afford a very pure ſpirit, with <lb/>very little
              trouble, as I have before men- <lb/>tioned. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The diſtillation ſhould be performed in the <lb/>pot, with the worm and other
              parts of the <lb/>apparatus, as deſcribed p. 35, into which, be- <lb/>ing put, and the
              cover placed on it; which, <lb/>without lute, will make a cloſe joint, the diſtil-
              <lb/>lation may be immediately begun; and will <lb/>be over, with proper management,
              in ſixteen <lb/>or eighteen hours. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <choice>
                <sic>
                  <pb n="93"/>
                </sic>
                <corr>
                  <pb n="95"/>
                </corr>
              </choice>
              <lb/>The end of the bending pipe, added to the <lb/>end of the worm, for that purpoſe,
              muſt be <lb/>let into the neck of a large receiver placed <lb/>under it; and the tin
              pipe, for carrying off <lb/>the ſmell, ſhould alſo have its bending end put <lb/>into
              the neck of the receiver; and the remain- <lb/>ing opening of the mouth may be made
              good, <lb/>by ſome moiſt, but ſtiff, clay. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>When the receiver appears of a proper ful- <lb/>neſs, it ſhould be taken away;
              and another put <lb/>in its ſtead, in the ſame manner as the firſt; <lb/>and this
              ſhould be repeated as often as they fill. <lb/>The receivers ſhould be emptied, by
              means of <lb/>a tin funnel, into the tin or pewter tritorium <lb/>deſcribed p. 30; and
              the crude ſpirit kept <lb/>there till it be wanted for rectification; or, if <lb/>the
              tritorium will not contain all that may <lb/>happen to be made, this ſpirit may be
              drawn <lb/>off, from it, into a proper bottle, to make room <lb/>for the freſh,
              through the lower tube, which <lb/>alone muſt be uſed for this purpoſe; the upper
              <lb/>one being deſigned for drawing off the oil, which <lb/>will float on the ſpirit,
              and may be eaſily taken <lb/>away from it, by this method, when there is <lb/>a proper
              quantity in the tritorium, and the <lb/>ſpirit raiſes it to a proper height. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If, as will ſometimes happen towards the <lb/>end of the diſtillation, the worm
              ſhould be ſo <lb/>choaked up with the ſalt, ariſing along with <lb/>the ſpirit, that
              the paſſage of the vapours may <lb/>be obſtructed, which may be perceived by the
              <lb/>appearance of the ſmoke through the juncture <pb n="96"/>
              <lb/>of the cover and pot, the ſtopper ſhould be <lb/>immediately taken out of the
              ſmall pipe in the <lb/>upper part of the worm; and, a ſmall tin <lb/>funnel being put
              in it, water ſhould be poured <lb/>into the worm; which will force its way, by
              <lb/>melting the concreted ſalt: and this muſt be <lb/>repeated till the paſſage
              appear free, by the <lb/>running of the water into the receiver with- <lb/>out any
              ſign of obſtruction. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The whole worm muſt be, likewiſe, filled <lb/>with water, by the ſame means, as
              ſoon as <lb/>the operation is finiſhed: the end of the ſmall <lb/>bending pipe, at the
              extremity of the worm, <lb/>being firſt ſtopt with a cork: and this water <lb/>may be
              left in the worm, till the uſe of the <lb/>pot is again wanted; when it muſt be taken
              <lb/>out, and put into the tritorium along with the <lb/>other ſpirit, which it will
              nearly equal in <lb/>ſtrength, by having diſſolved the ſalt con- <lb/>creted in the
              worm, according to the inten- <lb/>tion of its being put there. This ſhould be
              <lb/>carefully remembered: for, on the clearing <lb/>the worm, by this means, of the
              ſalt, which <lb/>is neceſſarily collected there, each diſtillation, <lb/>depends the
              practicability of its uſe. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>After the firſt, and every other diſtillation, <lb/>the oil ſwimming on the
              ſpirit ſhould be care- <lb/>fully ſeparated from it; which may be done, <lb/>by
              paſſing this ſpirit through a large glaſs fun- <lb/>nel, in the bottom of which, a
              piece of cotton <lb/>is ſo placed, that the fluid paſſing through gra- <lb/>dually,
              the oil may be kept from following the <pb n="97"/>
              <lb/>ſpirit, by removing the funnel after the ſpirit is <lb/>gone through it. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The oil ſeparated, in the ſecond and third <lb/>rectifications, ſhould be put
              into a phial, and <lb/>preſerved; in order to make the fictitious ſalt <lb/>of
              hartſhorn. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>After the laſt rectification, the ſpirit ſhould <lb/>be filtered, by means of the
              cullender, &amp;c. <lb/>deſcribed p. 32: and, if it be kept a conſi- <lb/>derable
              time, the filtering may be repeated <lb/>before it be fold, if the quantity be
              conſidera- <lb/>ble. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>This volatile ſpirit is, with regard to the <lb/>medicinal intentions, equal in
              all reſpects, <lb/>and in ſome ſuperior, to the true ſpirit of <lb/>hartſhorn; for
              which at preſent it is gene- <lb/>rally ſold: as is ſometimes, likewiſe, the fol-
              <lb/>lowing kind. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic hanging space">
              <lb/>Compendious preparation of a volatile ſpirit, <lb/>reſembling the above, and the
              true ſpirit of <lb/>hartſhorn. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/> Take volatile ſpirit of ſal Ammoniacum, <lb/>obtained by chalk, or ſalt of
              tartar, but with- <lb/>out lime, one gallon; or two pounds of ſal <lb/>Ammoniacum, and
              the ſame quantity of dry <lb/>pearl aſlies, may be uſed, with a gallon of <lb/>water,
              inſtead of the ſpirit; to this add, of <lb/>the crude ſpirit of hartſhorn, or bones,
              half <pb n="98"/>
              <lb/>a gallon: diſtill them, as in the rectifica- <lb/>tion of ſpirit of hartſhorn,
              and draw off <lb/>the ſpirit, while it comes over of a due <lb/>ſtrength: filter it,
              after it has been kept <lb/>ſome days. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="align-center italic">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>This will in all reſpects reſemble perfect <lb/>ſpirit of haitſhorn, as prepared
              by the firſt pro- <lb/>ceſs; but if it be made of the crude ſpirit of <lb/>hartſhorn,
              like the true ſpirit, it will be apt to <lb/>turn foul and fœtid. That made with the
              ſpirit <lb/>of bones will keep much longer; but not ſo <lb/>well as the produce of the
              former proceſs. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>However this ſubſtitution may reſemble the <lb/>true kind of ſpirit of hartmorn,
              or that drawn <lb/>from bones, it will be inferior with regard to <lb/>the medicinal
              qualities; becauſe, though it <lb/>will appear equally replete with oil, yet it will
              <lb/>not contain ſo great a quantity; and what it <lb/>may contain will be of a
              groſſer, and leſs ethe- <lb/>real nature, as its tendency to grow fœtid, and
              <lb/>foul, evinces; and, if kept anytime, it will be- <lb/>come nauſeous, and be apt
              to rife on the <lb/>ſtomach, like the genuine ſpirit of hartſhorn. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>This ſpirit is, however, much leſs exception- <lb/>able than another kind too
              commonly impoſed <lb/>on the public; which is prepared by means of <lb/>quicklime,
              after the following manner. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <pb n="99"/>
            <head rend="italic align-center">
              <lb/>Sophiſtication of ſpirit of hartſhorn, by means <lb/>of quicklime. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/> To a gallon of crude ſpirit of hartſhorn, <lb/>or bones, add one pound of
              quicklime, <lb/>either at the firſt, or any ſubſequent rec- <lb/>tification; draw off
              the ſpirit, and treat it <lb/>as the genuine. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="align-center italic space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>This is, by much, the worſt ſophiſtication <lb/>of ſpirit of hartſhorn; and
              cannot be too much <lb/>guarded againſt, by all, who are concerned in <lb/>the ſale,
              or uſe, of this medicine. When <lb/>indeed it is drawn off with a due proportion of
              <lb/>ſtrength; and uſed only to ſmell to, its ex- <lb/>traordinary pungency renders it
              very fit for the <lb/>purpoſe: though this end may be equally well <lb/>anſwered by
              volatile ſpirit of ſal Ammonia- <lb/>cum, which is almoſt every where to be had
              <lb/>prepared in the ſame manner: but when this <lb/>kind is drawn off only of the
              apparent ſtrength <lb/>of the true ſpirit of hartſhorn, and impoſed, in its
              <lb/>place, for internal uſe, it is a conſiderable fraud. <lb/>For it is neceſſarily
              very defective, in the quan- <lb/>tity of volatile ſalt; in which the principal effi-
              <lb/>cacy of this medicine conſiſts: the end of uſing <lb/>the lime being to increaſe
              the pungency; and <lb/>make the ſpirit, drawn off, much weaker, ſeem <lb/>equally
              ſtrong, with that impregnated with the <pb n="100"/>
              <lb/>due proportion of volatile ſalt; and by this <lb/>means, to increaſe the
              quantity. Which delu- <lb/>ſion occaſions, therefore, only a part of the <lb/>intended
              doſe to be virtually taken. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If we paid an implicit deference to the au- <lb/>thority of the college, there
              would be another <lb/>reaſon againſt this ſophiſtication: for they have <lb/>condemned
              the uſe of lime with volatile ſalts, <lb/>as rendering them noxiouſly acrimonious, and
              <lb/>corroſive. But, if there were any truth in this <lb/>principle, it muſt hold
              good, alſo, with reſpect <lb/>to fixt alkaline ſalts; and yet we ſee, not only
              <lb/>experience, but even the opinion of this great <lb/>body itſelf, in the ſame
              work, aſſure us of the <lb/>contrary. Nor does it indeed appear from facts, <lb/>that
              there is any perfectly diſſolvable body, <lb/>which can injure by its acrimony, when
              ſuffi- <lb/>ciently diluted. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>This impoſition of the ſpirit of hartſhorn, or <lb/>bones, actuated with
              quick-lime, inſtead of the <lb/>genuine, is, however, ſuppoſed to be eaſily
              <lb/>detectible, by the following means. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic hanging space">
              <lb/>A method uſed for detecting the ſpirit of hartſ- <lb/>horn ſophiſticated with
              quick-lime. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Add ſtrong ſpirit of wine to the ſuſpected <lb/>ſpirit; and if it do not ſoon
              give the ap- <lb/>pearance of little ſparkling bodies, ſwim- <lb/>ming in the fluid,
              and afterwards ſubſiding <lb/>to the bottom, it may be concluded to be ſo- <pb n="101"/>
              <lb/>phiſticated, with quicklime, provided, by the <lb/>pungency, it appear to be of
              due ſtrength. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>The principle, on which the above proof is <lb/>grounded, is this. If ſpirit of
              wine be added <lb/>to water, impregnate with volatile ſalts, in the <lb/>proportion of
              good ſpirit of hartſhorn, it will <lb/>deſtroy, in a certain degree, the diſſolving
              <lb/>power of the water; and, conſequently, a part <lb/>of the ſalt, before diſſolved,
              will ſhoot into <lb/>ſmall chryſtals, which ſhew themſelves, firſt <lb/>in the form of
              little ſparkling bodies, and after- <lb/>wards in that of a ſhining powder at the bot-
              <lb/>tom of the phials, or other veſſel, in which the <lb/>mixture is contained. But,
              if the ſpirit be ſo- <lb/>phiſticated with quick-lime, this will not hap- <lb/>pen,
              from two reaſons; firſt, becauſe quicklime <lb/>changes in ſuch manner, the volatile
              ſalts, that <lb/>they become ſo extremely ſoluble, the water can <lb/>ſcarcely be
              ſaturated with them, in any propor- <lb/>tion; or made to ſhoot them in chryſtals,
              <lb/>tho' they abound in any quantity whatever: <lb/>ſecondly, becauſe the ſpirit, ſo
              ſophiſticated, <lb/>does not contain a ſufficient quantity of ſalts, <lb/>to occaſion
              the chryſtallization of them from <lb/>the weakning the ſoluble power of the water
              <lb/>by the ſpirit of wine, even though their na- <lb/>ture was not changed by the
              action of the <lb/>quicklime. It may therefore be taken as a <lb/>certain criterion,
              that the ſpirit is ſophiſticated <pb n="102"/>
              <lb/>with quick-lime, if no ſuch appearance follow, <lb/>the admixture of the ſpirit:
              but this method <lb/>of trial is nevertheleſs ſo far defective, that no <lb/>inference
              can be drawn from it, with certainty, <lb/>of die ſpirit's being really genuine,
              notwith- <lb/>ſtanding a very plentiful chryſtallization ſhould <lb/>enſue: though it
              has been hitherto looked on, <lb/>as equally concluſive as to that point alſo. But
              <lb/>a method has been contrived of preparing the <lb/>ſpirit in ſuch manner, that
              though the quan- <lb/>tity of volatile ſalt be greatly deficient, and the
              <lb/>appearance of due ſtrength be procured by the <lb/>help of quick-lime; yet on
              this trial, with ſpirit <lb/>of wine, the reſult will be the ſame, as in the
              <lb/>ſpirit od hartſhorn, where no quick-lime was <lb/>uſed; and the ſmall chryſtals
              will be produced, <lb/>in ſuch abundance, as to induce the opinion of <lb/>its being
              extraordinarily good, if this experi- <lb/>ment were a ſufficient teſt. I have ſeen a
              quan- <lb/>tity, not leſs than five hundred weight, treated <lb/>in this manner, which
              paſſed the hands of per- <lb/>ſons, who thought themſelves very ſkilful <lb/>in
              matters of this kind: and I make no doubt <lb/>this additional fraud would be more
              frequently <lb/>practiſed, if known; eſpecially, as it increaſes <lb/>the weight of
              the ſpirit at a very ſmall expence. <lb/>I ſhall therefore omit the teaching the
              method <lb/>of effecting it; and inſtead of that, give a ſure <lb/>way of diſcovering
              where it is practiſed, and <lb/>of determining, moreover, in all caſes, whether
              <lb/>the ſpirit, when it appears of due ſtrength, be <lb/>prepared with lime, or not.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="hanging italic space">
              <lb/>A more certain method of diſcovering, when <lb/>ſpirit of hartſhorn, or other
              volatile ſpirit, <lb/>is ſophiſticated with quick-lime. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Mix ſtrong ſpirit of wine with the volatile <lb/>ſpirit ſuſpected; and, if a
              chryſtalline pow- <lb/>der be produced, let it ſubſide till the fluid <lb/>can be
              poured off; and having put it into a <lb/>ſpoon, hold it near the fire, or over the
              flame <lb/>of a candle: if the powder exhale and diſ- <lb/>appear, it may be
              concluded, that the ſpirit <lb/>is not prepared with lime, but contains a <lb/>due
              proportion of volatile ſalt but if it <lb/>remain after it has undergone, even, a
              <lb/>gentle degree of heat, it may be taken for <lb/>granted, that not only the uſe of
              quick-lime, <lb/>but other eluſive methods have been prac- <lb/>tiſed. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>I ſhall not explain the principles, on which <lb/>this trial is founded, becauſe
              they will be ob- <lb/>vious to perſons, who are any way verſed in <lb/>theſe matters,
              and a farther elucidation would <lb/>lead others into the knowledge of the art it is
              <lb/>intended to explode. But whoever purchaſes <lb/>any conſiderable quantity of
              ſpirit of hartſhorn, <pb n="104"/>
              <lb/>would do well to prove it in this manner; and <lb/>may be aſſured, if it appear
              of due ſtrength by <lb/>its pungency to the noſe, and ſtand this teſt, <lb/>that it is
              not ſophiſticated with lime; but pro- <lb/>perly replete with volatile ſalts. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Salt of hartſhorn. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Let the ſalt be taken out of the receivers, <lb/>after the diſtillation, or out
              of the retorts, <lb/>after the rectification, before it be melted <lb/>by the ſpirit,
              which will riſe afterwards; and <lb/>ſublimed, firſt with an equal weight of chalk;
              <lb/>and afterwards with a little rectified ſpirit of <lb/>wine. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>This is the proceſs given by the college for <lb/>the preparation of this
              medicine. The ſame <lb/>may be done with reſpect to the volatile ſalt, <lb/>obtained
              from bones, which will keep its white <lb/>colour longer, and be much leſs ſubject to
              grow <lb/>fœtid, than that extracted from horn. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The quantity of chalk, here directed, is <lb/>much greater than is requiſite to
              abſorb the oil, <lb/>and prevent its riſing with the ſalt; for which <lb/>reaſon only
              it is added: half the quantity, or <lb/>leſs, will anſwer the end equally well. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The ſpirit of wine, which is deſigned to <lb/>combine with, and waſh down, the
              oil from <pb n="105"/>
              <lb/>the ſalt, does not, on experiment, anſwer the <lb/>purpoſe, in a proportion
              equivalent to the <lb/>inconvenience its elaſtic vapour, joined to that <lb/>of the
              volatile ſalt, produces, during the whole <lb/>operation, by forcing the lute: and it
              will be <lb/>found, on trying both methods, that the ſub- <lb/>limation will ſucceed,
              on the whole, better <lb/>without it. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The ſublimation of the ſalt of hartſhorn is beſt <lb/>performed in a retort, with
              a ſmall receiver; <lb/>the neck of the retort being ſhort and wide. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>After the ſalt of hartſhorn, or even that of <lb/>bones, have been purified, in
              the beſt manner <lb/>they can, by repeated ſublimation, it will ſoon <lb/>grow brown
              and fœtid, by keeping; which is <lb/>a great inconvenience to thoſe who ſell it, and
              <lb/>have not a quick demand. The following <lb/>fictitious kind has been, therefore,
              ſubſtituted <lb/>for it; being not only free from this incom- <lb/>modious quality of
              changing colour; but, alſo, <lb/>prepared with much leſs trouble and expence. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic hanging space">
              <lb/>Fictitious ſalt of hartſhorn, the ſame with the <lb/>genuine in all other
              qualities; and not ſub- <lb/>ject to change colour, or grow fœtid. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Take ſix pounds of the volatile ſalt of <lb/>ſal Ammoniacum; add to it half a
              pound <lb/>of chalk, mixt with two ounces of the oil <lb/>taken off the ſpirit of
              bones, in the rectifi- <pb n="106"/>
              <lb/>cation, as directed p. 97; ſublime them to- <lb/>gether; and ſeparate the white
              part after the <lb/>ſublimation, from that which appears brown; <lb/>the latter being
              reſerved for another ſubli- <lb/>mation, with a freſh quantity. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="align-center italic space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>In making the volatile ſalt of the ſal Am- <lb/>moniacum, a part of it will
              neceſſarily ariſe <lb/>foul, as we ſhall fee below: ſuch foul part <lb/>will very well
              ſerve for this purpoſe. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If it be more convenient, inſtead of taking the <lb/>volatile ſalt already made,
              to conjoin the making <lb/>it, and the converting it into the ſalt of hartſ-
              <lb/>horn, into one operation, the crude ſal Am- <lb/>moniacum, and proper quantity of
              chalk, may <lb/>be uſed according to the proceſs below given: <lb/>and, in this caſe,
              it is beſt to mix the oil with <lb/>chalk into a ſtiff paſte; and, having formed the
              <lb/>mixture into balls, to put them into the retort <lb/>after the other ingredients,
              that they may lie <lb/>out of the reach of the ſtronger heat, which <lb/>would
              occaſion the oil to riſe before the greateſt <lb/>part of the ſalt. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The ſalt, ſo prepared, is indiſtinguiſhable <lb/>from the genuine ſalt of
              hartſhorn, by any other <lb/>means, than keeping it till the continuance of <lb/>its
              white colour ſhall ſhew the difference: and, <lb/>notwithſtanding, I have given it the
              name of fic- <lb/>titious, it is in reality the ſame, with the ſalt ob- <pb n="107"/>
              <lb/>tained by the regular proceſs; except that the oil is <lb/>of a purer, and more
              ethereal nature, than what <lb/>is found in the other: on which account, this <lb/>is
              certainly preferable, for other reaſons, as well <lb/>as its maintaining its
              whiteneſs, and not becom- <lb/>ing fœtid. Since, if we allow all volatile alka-
              <lb/>line ſalts, to be the ſame, this muſt appear a <lb/>better medicine, from the
              qualities of the oil <lb/>it contains; and recommends itſelf ſtill further <lb/>by
              being of a much more cheap and eaſy pre- <lb/>paration than the genuine. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Calcined hartſhorn. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Let pieces of hartſhorn, or the coal which <lb/>comes out of the pot after the
              diſtillation <lb/>of the ſpirit of hartſhorn, be burnt in an <lb/>open fire, till they
              become perfectly white: <lb/>and, then, let them be levigated as other <lb/>earthy, or
              teſtaceous bodies. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>The college of London have directed this <lb/>to be done in a potters furnace:
              and for thoſe, <lb/>who have not occaſion to calcine ſuch quan- <lb/>tities, as may
              anſwer the expence of a proper <lb/>furnace in their own elaboratory, the ſending
              <lb/>the materials to the potters, tobacco-pipe- <lb/>makers, or other ſuch perſons,
              who have very <lb/>ſtrong fires for other purpoſes, will be the <lb/>cheapeſt and
              eaſieſt method. </p>
          </div>
          <pb n="108"/>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Fictitious calcined hartſhorn. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Let the coal of the bones, which re- <lb/>mains, in the pot, after the extraction
              of <lb/>the volatile ſpirit from them, be treated in <lb/>the ſame manner as that of
              hartſhorn. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>This ſubſtitution is very frequently prac- <lb/>tiſed; and, if the bones be
              perfectly calcined, <lb/>the earth will be indiſtinguiſhable from that of <lb/>the
              hartſhorn: being in fact abſolutely the ſame <lb/>ſubſtance. This, therefore, is a
              fraud produc- <lb/>tive of very little miſchief; and may be per- <lb/>mitted where any
              ſuch are allowed. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>It is, however, much more difficult, from their <lb/>texture, to give the bones a
              perfect calcination <lb/>than the horn: and it is, therefore, proper to <lb/>break the
              coal of them, which is uſed for this <lb/>purpoſe, into very ſmall bits; which much
              <lb/>facilitates the operation. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Volatile ſalt of ſal Ammoniacum. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Take of the pureſt chalk, two pounds, <lb/>ſal Ammoniacum one pound, ſublime them
              <lb/>in a retort, with a ſtrong fire. </p>
          </div>
          <pb n="109"/>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>This is the proceſs of the London-college, <lb/>and the common practice: but the
              quantity of <lb/>chalk is much too great; filling the retort un- <lb/>neceſſarily, and
              adding, in ſome degree, to the <lb/>foulneſs of the ſalt; if the chalk, as happens
              <lb/>very frequently, contain any impurities. The <lb/>following is therefore a much
              better propor- <lb/>tion of the ingredients: and the directions be- <lb/>low given for
              the conduct of the operation, if <lb/>obſerved, will produce a whiter ſalt, and with
              <lb/>much leſs expence and trouble, than the me- <lb/>thods commonly practiſed. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Improved proceſs, for the making the volatile <lb/>ſalt of ſal Ammoniacum. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Take the whiteſt ſal Ammoniacum, dry <lb/>it well while in large pieces, and pick
              out <lb/>from it, and ſcrape off every part, which <lb/>appears the leaſt diſcoloured.
              Then take <lb/>the cleaneſt chalk; and dry it thoroughly, <lb/>by heating it as hot as
              boiling water, but <lb/>not hotter: powder it well, and dry it again: <lb/>mix the ſal
              Ammoniacum and the chalk, <lb/>while both are in this dry ſtate, in the pro-
              <lb/>portion of five parts of chalk, to four of <pb n="110"/>
              <lb/>the ſal Ammoniacum: put them into a re- <lb/>tort, with a thick ſhort neck, and
              the orifice <lb/>cut very wide: fit to it a ſmall receiver, with <lb/>a long neck; and
              lute them well together. <lb/>Then put them into a ſand-pot; and ſu- <lb/>blime the
              ſalt, very gradually; never ſuf- <lb/>fering the lower part of the receiver to grow
              <lb/>very hot. Let the fire, however, be raiſed <lb/>to a ſtrong heat at the latter
              part of the <lb/>operation. When the retort and receiver <lb/>are grown cold, break
              the receiver, and ſe- <lb/>parate ſo much of the ſalt as appears white <lb/>and pure,
              from the diſcoloured; and break- <lb/>ing it into lumps, preſerve it carefully from
              <lb/>exhaling, which will dull the tranſparent <lb/>appearance. The leſs ſightly, and
              foul, parts, <lb/>may be uſed for the making the ſpiritus <lb/>volatilis oleoſus; or
              fictitious ſalt of hartſ- <lb/>horn; or purified by reſublimation, if that <lb/>be
              more convenient. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>By this method of diminiſhing the quantity <lb/>of chalk, uſing only ſuch ſal
              Ammoniacum <lb/>as is clean, and employing a ſmall receiver, <lb/>the neceſſity of a
              ſecond ſublimation is taken <pb n="111"/>
              <lb/>away: for the purity of the ſal Ammoniacum <lb/>will occaſion a conſiderable
              quantity of the vo- <lb/>latile ſalt to be pure alſo: and render the re- <lb/>torts
              capable of ſubliming a greater quantity of <lb/>the ſalt, by diminiſhing the quantity
              of <choice>
                <corr>chalk</corr>
                <sic>ohalk</sic>
              </choice>; <lb/>and the uſing at the ſame time a ſmall re- <lb/>ceiver, will cauſe the
              cake of the ſublimed ſalts <lb/>to be of a due thickneſs; which it otherwiſe
              <lb/>cannot be made, without putting the produce <lb/>of two or three of theſe
              operations together, <lb/>and ſubliming afreſh. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The ſcrapings, or foul parts, picked out of the <lb/>ſal Ammoniacum, need not, in
              the leaſt, in- <lb/>hance the expence: for they may be uſed, for <lb/>making the
              volatile ſpirits, or any other ſuch <lb/>purpoſe: neither will the foul parts of the
              ſu- <lb/>blimed volatile ſalt be in the leaſt a loſs, for they <lb/>may be very
              profitably employed alſo, for the <lb/>purpoſes abovementioned. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Great care ſhould be taken, if the powdered <lb/>chalk and ſal Ammoniacum be kept
              after they <lb/>are reduced to that ſtate, either together, or ſe- <lb/>parately, not
              to ſuffer the air to have any acceſs <lb/>to them: for they will immediately attract
              <lb/>moiſture, which is very detrimental to this <lb/>operation; as a very ſmall
              quantity is apt to <lb/>melt down the ſalt from the ſides of the re- <lb/>ceiver into
              the bottom, and diminiſh the thick- <lb/>neſs of the ſublimed cake, on which the pro-
              <lb/>duce of the ſaleable ſalt depends. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>Much caution ſhould be likewiſe uſed, in <lb/>the management of the fire: for, if
              it be pre- <lb/>cipitated, not only a great riſque is run of burſt- <pb n="112"/>
              <lb/>ing the retort, or receiver; but, the ſalt, being <lb/>in too hot a ſtate, to
              form on the ſides, will <lb/>flow down to the bottom of the receiver, and <lb/>produce
              the diſadvantage before mentioned. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>A cake of crude ſal Ammoniacum will <lb/>ſometimes be found on the top of the
              chalk, <lb/>after the ſublimation; as likewiſe in the neck <lb/>of the retort. This
              may be alſo uſed for <lb/>making the volatile ſpirit, and the ſal Ammo- <lb/>niacum,
              as the being mixt with the chalk will <lb/>not in the leaſt injure it for that
              purpoſe. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Volatile ſpirit of ſal Ammoniacum with fixt <lb/>alkaline ſalt. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Take of any fixt alkaline ſalt, one pound <lb/>and half, ſal Ammoniacum, one
              pound, <lb/>water, four pints: with a gentle fire, diſtill <lb/>off two pints. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>This is the proceſs of the London-College; <lb/>in which the quantities ſeem very
              ill adjuſted: <lb/>for one pound of dry pure, fixt, alkaline ſalt is <lb/>more than
              ſufficient, to diſpoſſeſs the volatile <lb/>ſalt of the ſal Ammoniacum of its acid
              ſpirit. <lb/>The quantity of fluid drawn off is likewiſe <lb/>very ſmall, in
              proportion to the quantity of <lb/>ſalt: for volatile ſpirit is extremely ſtrong,
              <lb/>when one fourth part of it is ſalt. This ſalt <pb n="113"/>
              <lb/>may be prepared genuinly, and at a moderate <lb/>expence, in the following
              manner. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Cheaper method of preparing the volatile ſpirit <lb/>of ſal Ammoniacum with fixt
              alkaline ſalt. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Take of ſal Ammoniacum, and pearl <lb/>aſhes, equal parts; add to them about five
              <lb/>times their weight of water; put them into <lb/>the tin alembic deſcribed p. 40;
              and fix two <lb/>receivers to the two arms; place it in the <lb/>ſand-bath; and
              diſtill off the ſpirit, while <lb/>it continues to come off ſtrong: when it
              <lb/>appears weaker, change the receivers, and <lb/>draw off the remainder ſo long as
              the fluid <lb/>partakes of any ſmell of the volatile ſalts. <lb/>Put by the ſtrong for
              uſe; keeping the weak, <lb/>to be added to the water in the next opera- <lb/>tion, of
              the ſame kind; or uſe it along with <lb/>other volatile ſpirit, or ſalt, in the making
              <lb/>the ſpiritus volatilis aromaticus; or for any <lb/>ſuch purpoſe. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>The ſcrapings of the ſal Ammoniacum, de- <lb/>ſigned for the volatile ſalt, may
              be employed <lb/>for this purpoſe: or the foul part of the vola- <pb n="114"/>
              <lb/>tile ſalt itſelf, diſſolved, may be added to this <lb/>ſpirit, when there is any
              convenience in ſo do- <lb/>ing; but the ſolution muſt be firſt filtered, if it
              <lb/>appear in the leaſt turbid. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The uſe of pearl aſhes, inſtead of ſalt of <lb/>tartar, which is directed by the
              Edinburg- <lb/>college, or indeed of any other fixt alkaline <lb/>ſalt, at preſent in
              uſe, is an obvious ſaving; and <lb/>comes within the latitude given by the college
              <lb/>of London. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>This ſpirit, however, is almoſt wholly ex- <lb/>cluded practice, by the uſe of
              that, made with <lb/>quick-lime, notwithſtanding the college of <lb/>London have
              endeavoured, to prohibit the uſe <lb/>of volatile ſpirit made with lime, on account
              <lb/>of its ſuppoſed acrimony; as was before men- <lb/>tioned. But the much greater
              pungency of <lb/>the kind with lime, which renders it much <lb/>fitter for the purpoſe
              of ſmelling to, on which <lb/>account a great part of the demand is made,
              <lb/>together with the inconvenience of keeping an- <lb/>other kind for other uſes,
              occaſions it to be <lb/>almoſt univerſally ſold, inſtead of that with <lb/>alkaline
              ſalt, by the wholeſale preparers and <lb/>dealers in medicine, to the apothecaries and
              <lb/>retailers: and it is, therefore, proper to in- <lb/>quire into the beſt method of
              preparing it: <lb/>eſpecially as one particular medicine, the col- <lb/>lege
              themſelves have given a place to in their <lb/>laſt pharmacopæia, cannot be prepared
              with- <lb/>out it; I mean volatile tincture of the bark, <lb/>which, in the ſpirit
              made with fixt alkaline ſalt, <lb/>becomes only a mucilage. </p>
          </div>
          <pb n="115"/>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Volatile ſpirit of ſal Ammoniacum made with <lb/>quicklime. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Take of ſal Ammoniacum, in fine pow- <lb/>der, one pound, of quicklime, which has
              <lb/>laid in the air till it be broken to powder, <lb/>two pounds; mix them well, and
              put them <lb/>preſently into a retort, with two pounds of <lb/>water: ſhake them, to
              mix the powder and <lb/>water; and place the retort in a ſand-heat; <lb/>diſtill off
              about twelve ounces: but, the <lb/>receiver being changed, about four ounces <lb/>of
              weaker may be alſo drawn off. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>This is the former proceſs, uſed for the pre- <lb/>parations of this ſpirit; but
              it is faulty in ſeveral <lb/>reſpects. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The expoſing the lime to the air, is ſo far <lb/>from neceſſary, as to be very
              injurious to the <lb/>qualities, by which it operates in this proceſs: <lb/>the
              quantity, alſo, of the lime, is much greater <lb/>than needful; both filling the
              retorts with need- <lb/>leſs matter, ſo as to render the produce of the <lb/>operation
              leſs, by even two thirds, than it may <lb/>be by a better proportion of the
              quantities; to <lb/>the great increaſe of the expence and trouble; <lb/>and cauſing
              them, likewiſe, frequently to break <pb n="116"/>
              <lb/>during during the operation; to the loſs of half, or <lb/>more, of the ſpirit. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The powdering the ſal Ammoniacum, or <lb/>making any previous mixture of it with
              the <lb/>lime, before they are put into the retort, is <lb/>likewiſe wholly needleſs;
              for the ſalt will of <lb/>courſe melt in the fluid as the warmth in- <lb/>creaſes. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The quantity of water is likewiſe much too <lb/>ſmall: for at leaſt twice the
              weight of the ſalt <lb/>may be drawn off; according to the proportion <lb/>of the
              college in the ſpirit with ſalt of tartar; <lb/>and, as it is impracticable to draw
              off the whole <lb/>fluid, (becauſe the retort will crack, when the <lb/>lime attains a
              certain degree of dryneſs,) that <lb/>quantity of ſpirit cannot be obtained with this
              <lb/>ſcanty proportion of water. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The following method, therefore, is much <lb/>better; amending theſe ſeveral
              errors; and ac- <lb/>commodating the materials to each other in <lb/>due proportion.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Improved method of making the volatile ſpirit <lb/>of ſal Ammoniacum with
              quicklime. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Take of ſal Ammoniacum four pounds, <lb/>quicklime five pounds, water three
              gallons. <lb/>Quench the lime in part of the water, and <lb/>then put it into the
              pewter alembic for <lb/>making this ſpirit, deſcribed p. 40: add <pb n="117"/>
              <lb/>to it the ſal Ammoniacum, and water; and <lb/>place the retort in the ſand-bath:
              where <lb/>diſtill off ten or twelve pounds, and then <lb/>change the receiver;
              ſuffering, afterwards, <lb/>the ſpirit to diſtill, while any pungency re- <lb/>mains:
              this weaker ſpirit muſt be added, to <lb/>the materials in ſome future operation, in
              <lb/>the place of ſo much water. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>By this diminution of the quantity of lime, <lb/>a retort will, at one operation,
              diſtill at leaſt <lb/>three times as much ſpirit, as in the former <lb/>proceſs: and
              will frequently ſerve a ſecond time <lb/>for the ſame purpoſes; which can never hap-
              <lb/>pen when more lime is uſed. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>It is uſual to draw off four or five times the <lb/>weight of the ſal Ammoniacum;
              and the ſpirit <lb/>will, even then, appear extremely ſtrong: but, <lb/>whoever would
              have this ſpirit correſpondent <lb/>to that of the college, made with fixt alkaline
              <lb/>ſalt, muſt only draw it off in the proportion of <lb/>three times the weight. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The uſe of quicklime, in making the vola- <lb/>tile ſpirit of ſal Ammoniacum, may
              be de- <lb/>tected by the ſame trial of it, by means of <lb/>ſpirit of wine, as has
              been given for the ſpirit <lb/>of hartſhorn: but as the common trial is ſub- <lb/>ject
              likewiſe to the ſame eluſion, as was before <lb/>mentioned, the further means, before
              given, <pb n="118"/>
              <lb/>of aſcertaining the nature of the chryſtals, pro- <lb/>duced on the addition of
              the ſpirit of wine, <lb/>ought alſo to be uſed. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Spiritus ſalis Ammoniaci dulcis; or dulcified <lb/>ſpirit of ſal Ammoniacum. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Take of any fixt alkaline ſalt half a pound, <lb/>ſal Ammoniacum four ounces,
              proof ſpirit <lb/>three pints: diſtill with a gentle heat, till a <lb/>pint and a half
              be come over. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>The proportion of the fixt alkaline ſalt to <lb/>the ſal Ammoniacum is here, as
              before in the <lb/>old proceſs for the volatile ſpirit, double what it <lb/>needs to
              be: the quantity of proof ſpirit is <lb/>likewiſe improper; for either, out of the
              three <lb/>pints employed, half the quantity of real ſpirit <lb/>muſt be leſt behind;
              or the ſpirit, which comes <lb/>over, will contain much too little water, to keep
              <lb/>diſfolved the quantity of volatile ſalt produced: <lb/>for, in order to have
              three ounces diſſolved in <lb/>a pint and half of ſpirit of wine, the ſpirit ought
              <lb/>not to be ſtronger than proof ſpirit. But, as in <lb/>fact, this proceſs, ſo far
              as regards the addition of <lb/>the ſpirif of wine, produces nothing more than <lb/>a
              bare mixture of the ſolution of the volatile <lb/>alkaline ſalt, and the ſpirit,
              (except the rectifi- <lb/>cation of the latter) it may properly be rejected, <pb
                n="119"/>
              <lb/>and the following ſimpler manner ſubſtituted, <lb/>in its place, for obtaining
              the ſame compoſition. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Extemporaneous dulcified ſpirit of ſal Ammo- <lb/>niacum. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/> Take of ſpirit of ſal Ammoniacum, made <lb/>with fixt alkaline ſalt, one pound:
              add to it <lb/>rectified ſpirit of wine half a pound; and <lb/>ſhake them well
              together. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>This will be, in all reſpects, the ſame with <lb/>the other; and may be made,
              occaſionally, with- <lb/>out the trouble of a diſtinct proceſs: but, if the
              <lb/>ſpirit be wanted, free from the appearance of <lb/>ſalt, which will be found in
              this mixture, as <lb/>well as in the ſpirit produced by the proceſs of <lb/>the
              college of London above given, water muſt <lb/>be gradually added, till the fait be
              diſſolved; <lb/>taking care, not to put in more than may be <lb/>ſufficient to that
              end. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Spiritus volatilis aramaticus, or ſal volatile <lb/>oleoſum. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Take of the eſſence of lemons, and eſſen- <lb/>tial oil of nutmegs, each two
              drams, of the <lb/>eſſential oil of cloves, half a dram, dulcified <pb n="120"/>
              <lb/>ſpirit of ſal Ammoniacum, two pints; diſtill <lb/>them, with a flow fire. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>This is a very good and elegant compoſi- <lb/>tion: but the uſe of volatile
              ſpirit, with the <lb/>proper proportion of ſpirit of wine, will equally <lb/>well
              anſwer the end; and ſpare the proceſs for <lb/>the making the dulcified ſpirit. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>In this proceſs, which is that of the college <lb/>of London, it is intended,
              that a part of the <lb/>diſſolved ſalt ſhould remain in the ſpirit; in <lb/>order to
              ſhew, that the ſpirit contains the pro- <lb/>per quantity of ſalt; and that, it is not
              prepared <lb/>with quicklime; but this is really no certain <lb/>teſt of either: for
              there may be a falſe appear- <lb/>ance of volatile ſalt, given by the means above
              <lb/>hinted at, as well in this caſe as in thoſe of <lb/>the ſpirit of hartſhorn, and
              volatile ſpirit of ſal <lb/>Ammoniacum; which ſhould, therefore, be ex- <lb/>plored,
              by the method above given, where there <lb/>is any ground for ſuſpicion of ſuch a
              fraud; as <lb/>I have more than once ſeen this ſophiſtication <lb/>actually practiſed. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The ſpiritus volatilis aromaticus may, how- <lb/>ever, be prepared by a cheaper
              method than <lb/>this proceſs; preſerving both the ſame ſenſible <lb/>and medicinal
              qualities. </p>
          </div>
          <pb n="121"/>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic hanging space">
              <lb/>A cheaper method of making the ſpiritus vola- <lb/>tilis aromaticus, reſembling
              that of the col- <lb/>lege of London, and equally good with reſpect <lb/>to the
              intention. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Take of the volatile ſalt of ſal Ammonia- <lb/>cum, made with chalk, two pounds,
              or the <lb/>volatile ſpirit, made with fixt alkaline ſalt, <lb/>of the full ſtrength,
              ſix pounds; (if the ſalt, <lb/>and not the ſpirit, be uſed, three pints of <lb/>water
              muſt be added;) put the ſpirit, or <lb/>diſſolved ſalt, into a retort, together with
              <lb/>eight pounds of proof ſpirit, half a pound <lb/>of pimento or Jamaica pepper, two
              ounces <lb/>of caſſia lignea, and one ounce of eſſence <lb/>of lemons: place the
              retort in the back <lb/>part of the ſand-bath; and diſtill off the <lb/>ſpirit and
              ſalt till there be a cloudineſs in <lb/>the drops; then change the receiver, and
              <lb/>draw off the remaining fluid while it ap- <lb/>pears to have any ſmell or
              flavour: this <lb/>weaker ſpirit muſt be added to the materials <lb/>with the next
              quantity made. </p>
          </div>
          <pb n="122"/>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>The aromatic ſpirit, thus prepared, will be <lb/>equally good with that of the
              college; and may <lb/>be made with much leſs trouble, and expence; <lb/>if the foul
              part of the volatile ſal Ammoniacum <lb/>be employed for it. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>But it is very frequent, to ſubſtitute in the <lb/>place of theſe kinds, what is
              prepared by means <lb/>of lime: and the greater pungency which the <lb/>lime gives to
              the volatile ſalt in this ſort, often <lb/>impoſes even on apothecaries, not greatly
              verſed <lb/>in the preparation of chemical medicines; and <lb/>makes them believe it
              to be good. Where <lb/>there is no undiſſolved ſalt in it, the diſtinguiſh- <lb/>ing
              this kind, from that properly prepared, re- <lb/>quires a new method of proof; for the
              mixing <lb/>ſpirit of wine, which avails with regard to the <lb/>other volatile
              ſpirits, is here evidently of no <lb/>uſe. The following trial ſhould, therefore, be
              <lb/>made in this caſe, where the ſophiſtication by <lb/>lime is ſuſpected, and the
              ſpirit is found very <lb/>pungent to the noſe. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic hanging space">
              <lb/>Method of diſtinguiſhing when the ſpiritus vo- <lb/>latilis aromaticus is made
              with lime, in the <lb/>caſes where there is no undiſſolved ſalt with it, <lb/>and the
              ſpirit is yet found extremely pungent. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Take a ſmall quantity of the volatile ſal <lb/>Ammoniacum, powdered, and put it
              gra- <pb n="123"/>
              <lb/>dually into a phial, containing the ſpiritus <lb/>volatilis aromaticus, which is
              to be proved: <lb/>ſhake them well together; and if the ſpirit, <lb/>notwithſtanding
              its great pungency, ſenſi- <lb/>bly diſſolve the ſalt, it may be taken for
              <lb/>granted, that it was made with lime; but <lb/>if the ſalt remain intirely
              undiſſolved, or be <lb/>diſſolved but in a ſmall degree, the contrary <lb/>may be,
              with certainty, concluded. </p>
          </div>
          <figure rend="space">
            <figDesc>A horizontal double-line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="size(1.25) align-center">
            <lb/>SECTION II. </head>
          <head rend="italic size(1.25) hanging">
            <lb/>Of the preparation of thoſe medicines, <lb/>where vegetable ſubſtances make the
            <lb/>whole, or principal part of the ſub- <lb/>ject. </head>
          <figure>
            <figDesc>A horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
          </figure>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center">
              <lb/>Salt of wormwood. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Take any quantity of wormwood, either <lb/>ſreſh gathered, or dried gently; put
              it into <lb/>an iron pot; and, with a gentle fire, reduce <lb/>it to white aſhes;
              which are afterwards to <lb/>be boiled in a ſufficient quantity of ſpring <lb/>water,
              ſo as to make a lye: filter the lye, <pb n="124"/>
              <lb/>and exhale it, over a gentle fire, till a brown <lb/>ſalt be left behind; which,
              by repeated ſo- <lb/>lutions, filtrations, and evaporations, may <lb/>be rendered
              white and pure. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>The incineration, or burning, may be better <lb/>performed, upon a clean hearth,
              in ſome place <lb/>where the wind cannot blow away the aſhes: <lb/>and the repeated
              means of purification are <lb/>needleſs, not only becauſe they would fail to
              <lb/>render the ſalt more pure than the firſt filtra- <lb/>tion alone, (provided it be
              performed through <lb/>paper); but, becauſe, if they did produce a pu- <lb/>rity, and
              whiteneſs, in the ſalt, they would <lb/>render it unmarketable; as being wholly un-
              <lb/>diſtinguiſhable from ſalt of tartar. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>This ſalt does not differ from the fixt alka- <lb/>line ſalt, obtained from any
              other vegetable, <lb/>by the ſame means; nor from ſalt of tartar; <lb/>except that in
              the preparation of the laſt, a <lb/>greater calcination being made, the burnt oil is
              <lb/>deſtroyed, which gives to the ſalt of worm- <lb/>wood its brown colour. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>It is very uſual, therefore, to ſubſtitute the <lb/>ſalt of other vegetables, for
              that of worm- <lb/>wood; there being no medicinal difference be- <lb/>twixt them, as
              we have before obſerved; as <lb/>both the fixed ſalts and burnt oils of all vege-
              <lb/>tables are, when pure, alike in their qualities: <lb/>but a fictitious ſalt may
              be made from pure fixt <pb n="125"/>
              <lb/>alkaline ſalt, exactly the ſame with the ſalt <lb/>really obtained from wormwood,
              by the above <lb/>proceſs, if the following means be uſed. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic hanging space">
              <lb/>Fictitious ſalt of wormwood, not differing, in <lb/>any reſpect, from the
              genuine, but with re- <lb/>gard to its production. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Take a little wormwood, and reduce it to <lb/>the ſtate of an imperfect charcoal,
              by burn- <lb/>ing it in a crucible, covered from the air; <lb/>it muſt not
              nevertheleſs be burnt till the <lb/>flaming quality be deſtroyed, but taken from
              <lb/>the fire as ſoon as it is perfectly black. Put <lb/>ſome of this coal, together
              with a pound <lb/>of pearl aſhes, into four pints of water, <lb/>and boil them
              together: let them ſtand till <lb/>they are cool, and then filter through pa-
              <lb/>per, and evaporate to a dry ſalt; to which <lb/>the burnt oil of the coal will
              have imparted <lb/>a proper degree of brownneſs; that, if too <lb/>great, muſt be
              adjuſted by the addition of <lb/>more pearl aſhes purified by the filter. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>This contains unqueſtionably the ſame ele- <lb/>ments, as the true ſalt of
              wormwood: ſince <lb/>the oil, in which alone, there can be poſſibly <pb n="126"/>
              <lb/>ſuppoſed any difference, is here the ſame as in <lb/>that. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>This ſubſtitution may, therefore, be well <lb/>allowed, in any view: and, with
              reſpect to the <lb/>medicinal effects, the ſubſtitution of ſalt of <lb/>tartar, or any
              other fixt alkaline ſalt, for the <lb/>ſalt of wormwood, cannot be condemned on
              <lb/>any maintainable principles, as any way in- <lb/>jurious, or inſufficient to the
              intention of cure; <lb/>according to what we have before ſhewn. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Salt of tartar. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Let crude tartar of either kind, folded <lb/>up in wet brown paper, or contained
              in a <lb/>proper veſſel, be put into the fire, and con- <lb/>tinued there, till all
              the oil be burnt out: <lb/>the ſalt is then to be procured from it, by <lb/>ſolution
              in boiling water; with a ſubſequent <lb/>evaporation, after having been filtered thro'
              <lb/>paper. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If the ſalt be required of a more ſapona- <lb/>ceous and pungent nature, let it
              be fuſed, <lb/>in a crucible, for ſome hours, with a very <lb/>hot fire, till it
              acquire a greeniſh, or blue <lb/>colour. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Salt of tartar was alſo formerly made by de- <lb/>flagrating nitre and tartar:
              which may be done, <pb n="127"/>
              <lb/>by powdering them together, in the proportion <lb/>of two parts of tartar to one
              of nitre; and then <lb/>putting the powder, gradually, by a ſpoonful <lb/>at a time,
              into a crucible, heated red hot; <lb/>which muſt be kept in the fire during the
              <lb/>operation, and for ſome time after: The ſalt, <lb/>being thus duly calcined, muſt
              be diſſolved, <lb/>and purified, as in the other proceſſes, by fil- <lb/>tering. But
              all theſe methods are greatly diſ- <lb/>uſed at preſent; the wholeſale dealers having
              <lb/>learnt the ſecret of preparing a fixt alkaline <lb/>ſalt, by the following much
              more profitable <lb/>method, which is now for the moſt part uſed <lb/>in the place of
              ſalt of tartar. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Fictitious ſalt of tartar. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Take of the beſt pearl aſhes, any quan- <lb/>tity; diſſolve them in boiling
              water, in the <lb/>proportion of a pound to a quart; when <lb/>they are diſſolved, let
              the ſolution ſtand till <lb/>it be cold; and then filter it through paper: <lb/>being
              filtered, evaporate the fluid, till a dry <lb/>ſalt remain; which, being broken into a
              <lb/>groſs powder, muſt be put into a proper <lb/>bottle of glaſs or ſtone, and kept
              carefully <lb/>from the air. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The evaporation may be performed in a <lb/>clean iron pot; but not in an earthen
              pip- <pb n="128"/>
              <lb/>kin; and the greateſt care ſhould be taken <lb/>neither to let the ſolution, or
              ſalt, be put <lb/>into copper, or braſs veſſels, on any account. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>This, according to the principles before laid <lb/>down, is, in all reſpects, the
              ſame as ſalt of tar- <lb/>tar: and fixt alkaline ſalt being a medicine, <lb/>which
              both uſed ſimply, and in the febrifuge <lb/>draughts, is of the higheſt efficacy, and
              con- <lb/>ſumed in very great quantity: the ſubſtitution <lb/>of this cheaper kind for
              the ſalt of tartar, which <lb/>cannot be prepared without much greater coſt <lb/>and
              trouble, is rather a benefit to the public, <lb/>than a detrimental fraud. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The neglect of the caution, above given, of <lb/>avoiding the uſe of braſs or
              copper utenſils, in <lb/>the preparation of ſalt of tartar, or this ſubſti- <lb/>tute,
              frequently occaſions it to be very noxious: <lb/>for by powdering it in braſs mortars,
              from <lb/>which it immediately collects all the ruſt, or <lb/>indeed makes itſelf a
              corroſion if there be the <lb/>leaſt moiſture, an emetic quality is acquired;
              <lb/>which affecting thoſe, who take the ſalt in any <lb/>form, induce them to believe
              the medicine it- <lb/>ſelf diſagrees with them, from its own nature. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The pearl aſhes are frequently adulterated <lb/>greatly with ſea ſalt; but this
              may be perceived <lb/>by the taſte if a ſmall quantity be diſſolved, <lb/>for that
              purpoſe: and though, perhaps, they <lb/>cannot be eaſily procured in a pure ſtate, yet
                <pb n="129"/>
              <lb/>if the ſolution be made in the proportion above <lb/>directed for the water and
              ſalt, the greateſt <lb/>part of the ſea ſalt will chryſtallize, on the <lb/>fluids
              being ſuffered to cool before it be fil- <lb/>tered; and by this, a ſeparation of the
              greateſt <lb/>part will be made; and the remaining ſmall <lb/>part will not deprave
              the fixt alkaline ſalt, for <lb/>any medicinal purpoſe. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Oil of tartar per deliquium. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Take any quantity of ſalt of tartar, <lb/>highly calcined: put it, in any ſtone,
              or <lb/>glaſs, veſſel, of a flat form, into a cellar, or <lb/>any moiſt place: where
              let it ſtand, for <lb/>ſeveral days, till the ſalt be diſſolved, by the <lb/>humidity
              of the air; then filter it through <lb/>paper; or ſeparate the fluid from the dregs
              <lb/>by decantation. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>As this is no way different from any other <lb/>ſolution of the ſalt, of equal
              ſtrength; or, as, if <lb/>any change be produced by this method of ſo- <lb/>lution, it
              can be only a depravity of the alka- <lb/>line quality by the acid of the air, this
              proceſs is <lb/>needleſs: and, therefore, the following extem- <lb/>poraneous method
              of making this deliquium, <lb/>is uſed inſtead of it. </p>
          </div>
          <pb n="130"/>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Extemporaneous method of making oil of tartar <lb/>per deliquium. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Take of fictitious ſalt of tartar, above- <lb/>mentioned, any quantity: diſſolve
              it, by <lb/>boiling, in half its weight of water; and <lb/>filter the ſolution when
              cold. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>If any ſalt precipitate to the bottom of the <lb/>veſſel, in the cooling of the
              ſolution, or be <lb/>found in the filter, it may be ſaved; and put <lb/>to the pearl
              aſhes, when the fictitious ſalt of <lb/>tartar is to be made from them; or uſed for
              <lb/>any ſuch other purpoſe. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>This is a much more expeditious and com- <lb/>modious method, than the tedious
              manner of <lb/>diſſolving the ſalt, by the moiſture of the air: <lb/>which does it ſo
              imperfectly, that a great waſte <lb/>generally accrues. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Soluble tartar. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Take, of any fixt alkaline ſalt, one pound, <lb/>of water, one gallon: to the
              ſalt, diſſolved in <lb/>the water boiling, throw in cream of tartar, <lb/>gradually,
              till the efferveſcence, that before <pb n="131"/>
              <lb/>aroſe on each addition, ceaſe to appear; <lb/>which will be, when, or before,
              three times <lb/>the weight of alkaline ſalt has been thrown <lb/>into it: then filter
              the ſolution through <lb/>paper; and, after a proper evaporation, let <lb/>it be ſet
              to ſhoot into chryſtals; or otherwiſe <lb/>make a total exhalation of the water, that
              <lb/>the ſalt may remain in a ſolid maſs. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>As there is no neceſſity of a boiling heat, <lb/>for the combination of the
              cream, and ſalt, <lb/>of tartar, into the ſoluble tartar; and, as this <lb/>medicine
              is never given in a dry form; it has <lb/>been a practice with ſome, to ſpare all
              parts <lb/>of this proceſs, but the powdering the ingre- <lb/>dients; and to
              ſubſtitute the following ſimple <lb/>preparation, in the place of the other. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Extemporaneous ſoluble tartar. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>Take of any fixt alkaline ſalt, three pounds, <lb/>of cream of tartar, one pound:
              powder, and <lb/>mix them thoroughly together. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic align-center space">
              <lb/>Note. </head>
            <p rend="indent space">
              <lb/>This will, on diſſolving in any fluid, previouſ- <lb/>ly to its being taken,
              become exactly the ſame, <pb n="132"/>
              <lb/>as if it had paſſed through the other omitted <lb/>parts of the above proceſs;
              and cannot, there- <lb/>fore, be deemed a ſubſtitution of a very cri- <lb/>minal
              nature. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>In the preparation of this, it is proper to ob- <lb/>ſerve, ſtrictly, the ſame
              caution, as in the caſe <lb/>of the ſalt of tartar, with regard to copper or
              <lb/>braſs veſſels. </p>
          </div>
          <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="22"/>
        </div>
        <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="242"/>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
