<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Cole: The Lady's Complete Guide</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Mary Cole</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">The lady's complete guide; or cookery in all its branches. Containing
              The most approved Receipts, confirmed by Observation and Practice, in every reputable
              English Book of Cookery now extant, besides a great Variety of others which have never
              before been offered to the Public. Also several translated from the productions of
              Cooks of Eminence who have published in france, particularly M. Commo's Histoire de
              Cuisine, M. Disang's Maitre D'hotel, M. Dupont and M. Valois, M. Troas, and M.
              Delatour, with their respective Names to each Receipt; which, with the Original
              Articles, will form the most complete System of Cookery ever yet exhibited, under the
              following Heads, viz. Roasting, Boiling, Made-dishes, Frying, Broiling, Potting,
              Fricassees, Ragouts, Soups, Sauces, Gravies, Hashes, Stews, Puddings, Custards, Cakes,
              Tarts, Pies, Pasties, Cheesecakes, Jellies, Pickling, Preserving, Confectionary,
              &amp;c. To which is added, in order to rander it as complete and perfect as possible,
              the complete brewer; Containing Familiar Instructions for brewing all Sorts of Beer
              and Ale; including the proper Management of the Vault or Cellar. Also the family
              physician; Consisting of a considerable Collection of approved Prescriptions by Mead,
              Sydenham, Tissot, Fothergil, Elliot, Buchan, and others, including a certain Remedy
              for that formidable Disorder, the Dropsy, recommended by Persons respectable in the
              highest Degree.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T90910</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T90910"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for G. Kearsley, No. 46, Fleet-Street,
                  MDCCLXXXVIII.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1788</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="32"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="479"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="83"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW106277637</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Recipe collections"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="book" rend="roman" xml:lang="eng">
    <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="32"/>
    <body>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="513"/>
      <pb n="514"/>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman size(1.25)">THE FAMILY PHYSICIAN; </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="sc space">or, </hi>
        <lb/><hi rend="size(1.25) space">The Country Lady's Benevolent Employment. </hi>
      </head>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A long horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Want of Appetite. </head>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>F want of appetite proceeds from errors in diet, or any
          <lb/>other part of the patient's regimen, it ought to be changed. <lb/>If nauſea and
          reachings ſhew that the ſtomach is loaded with <lb/>crudities, a vomit will be of ſervice.
          After this, a gentle <lb/>purge or two of rhubarb, or of any of the bitter purging ſalts,
          <lb/>may be taken. The patient ought next to uſe ſome of the <lb/>ſtomachic bitters
          infuſed in wine. Though gentle evacua- <lb/>tions be neceſſary, yet ſtrong purges and
          vomits are to be <lb/>avoided, as they weaken the ſtomach, and hurt digeſtion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Elixir of vitriol is an excellent medicine in moſt caſes of <lb/>indigeſtion,
          weakneſs of the ſtomach, or want of appetite. <lb/>Twenty or thirty drops of it may be
          taken twice or thrice a- <lb/>day, in a glaſs of wine or water. It may likewiſe be mixed
          <lb/>with the tincture of the bark; one drachm of the former to <lb/>an ounce of the
          latter, and two teaſpoonfuls of it taken in <lb/>wine or water, as above. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The chalybeate waters, if drank in moderation, are gene- <lb/>rally of conſiderable
          ſervice in this caſe. The ſalt water <lb/>has likewiſe good effects; but it muſt not be
          uſed too freely. <lb/>The waters of Harrowgate, Scarborough, Moffat, and moſt <lb/>other
          ſpas in Britain, may be uſed with advantage. We <lb/>would adviſe all who are afflicted
          with indigeſtion and want <lb/>of appetite, to repair to theſe places of public
          rendezvous. <lb/>The very change of air, and the cheerful company, will be <lb/>of
          ſervice; not to mention the exerciſe, diſſipation, amuſe- <lb/>ments, &amp;c. <hi
            rend="italic">Tiſſot</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Buchan</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="515"/>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>The Aſthma. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The paroxyſm of an aſthma I muſt leave to the phyſician; <lb/>but as a palliative,
          nothing is of ſo great importance in the <lb/>aſthma, as pure and moderately warm air.
          Aſthmatic people <lb/>can ſeldom bear either the cloſe heavy air of a large town, or
          <lb/>the ſharp, keen atmoſphere of a bleak hilly country; a me- <lb/>dium, therefore,
          between theſe is to be choſen; The air near <lb/>a large town is often better than at a
          diſtance, provided the <lb/>patient be removed ſo far as not to be affected by the ſmoke.
          <lb/>Some aſthmatic patients indeed breathe eaſier in town than <lb/>in the country; but
          this is ſeldom the caſe, eſpecially in <lb/>towns where much coal is burnt. Aſthmatic
          perſons who are <lb/>obliged to be in town all day, ought, at leaſt, to ſleep out <lb/>of
          it. Even this will often prove of great ſervice. Thoſe <lb/>who can afford it, ought to
          travel into a warmer climate. <lb/>Many aſthmatic perſons who cannot live in England,
          enjoy <lb/>very good health in the ſouth of France, Portugal, Spain, <lb/>or Italy. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Exerciſe is likewiſe of very great importance in the aſthma, <lb/>as it promotes the
          digeſtion, preparation of the blood, &amp;c. <lb/>The blood of aſthmatic perſons is ſeldom
          duly prepared, ow- <lb/>ing to the proper action of the lungs being impeded. For <lb/>this
          reaſon, ſuch people ought daily to take as much exerciſe, <lb/>either on foot, horſeback,
          or in a carriage, as they can bear. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Buchan</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Dr. Mead's Preſcription for the Bite Of a Mad Dog. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Take aſh-coloured ground liverwort, cleaned, dried, and <lb/>powdered, half an ounce;
          of black pepper, powdered, a quar- <lb/>ter of an ounce. Mix theſe well together, and
          divide the <lb/>powder into four doſes; one of which muſt be taken every <lb/>morning
          faſting, for four mornings ſucceſſively, in half an <lb/>Engliſh pint of cow's milk, warm. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>After theſe four doſes are taken, the patient muſt go into <lb/>a cold bath, or cold
          ſpring or river, every morning faſting, <lb/>for a month; he muſt be dipped all over, but
          not ſtay in <lb/>(with his head above water) longer than half a minute, if the <lb/>water
          be very cold. After this, he muſt go in three times a- <lb/>week for a fortnight longer. </p>
        <pb n="516"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The perſon muſt be bled before he begins to uſe the medi- <lb/>cine. Dr. Mead
          aſſerts, that he never knew this remedy fail, <lb/>although he has tried it in a thouſand
          inſtances. But Dr. <lb/>Buchan, and ſome others, ſuſpect the Doctor's veracity in
          <lb/>this particular. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Bleeding at the Noſe. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Whenever bleeding at the noſe relieves any bad ſymptoms, <lb/>and does not proceed ſo
          far as to endanger the patient's life, <lb/>it ought not to be ſtopped. But when it
          returns frequently, <lb/>or continues till the pulſe becomes low, the extremities be-
          <lb/>gin to grow cold, the lips pale, or the patient complains of <lb/>being ſick or
          faint, it muſt immediately be ſtopped. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>For this purpoſe, the patient ſhould be ſet nearly upright, <lb/>with his head
          reclining a little, and his legs immerſed in wa- <lb/>ter, about the warmth of new milk.
          His hands ought like- <lb/>wiſe to be put in lukewarm water, and his garters may be
          <lb/>tied a little tighter than uſual. Ligatures may be applied to <lb/>the arms, about
          the place where they are uſually made for <lb/>bleeding, and with nearly the ſame degree
          of tightneſs. <lb/>Theſe muſt be gradually flackened as the blood begins to <lb/>ſtop, and
          removed entirely as foon as it gives over. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Sometimes dry lint put up the noſtrils will ſtop the bleed- <lb/>ing. When this does
          not ſucceed, doſſils of lint dipped in <lb/>ſtrong ſpirits of wine, may be put up the
          noſtrils, or, if theſe <lb/>cannot be had, they may be dipped in brandy. Blue vitriol,
          <lb/>diſſolved in water, may likewiſe be uſed for this purpoſe, or <lb/>a tent dipped in
          the white of an egg, well beat up, may be <lb/>rolled in a powder made of equal parts of
          white ſugar, burnt <lb/>allum, and white vitriol, and put up the noſtril from whence
          <lb/>the blood iſſues. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Internal medicines can hardly be of uſe here, as they have <lb/>ſeldom time to
          operate. It may not, however, be amiſs to <lb/>give the patient half an ounce of Glauber's
          ſalts, and the <lb/>ſame quantity of manna, diſſolved in four or five ounces of
          <lb/>barley-water. This may be taken at a draught, and re- <lb/>peted if it does not
          operate, in a few hours. Ten or twelve <lb/>grains of nitre may be taken in a glaſs of
          cold water and vine- <lb/>gar every hour, or oftener, if the ſtomach will bear it. If a
          <lb/>ſtronger medicine be neceſſary, a tea-cupful-of the tincture of <lb/>roſes, with
          twenty or thirty drops of the weak ſpirit of vi- <lb/>triol, may be taken every hour. When
          theſe things cannot <pb n="517"/>
          <lb/>be had, the patient may drink water with a little common <lb/>ſalt in it, or equal
          parts of water and vinegar. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If the genitals be immerſed for ſome time in cold water, it <lb/>will generally ſtop
          a bleeding at the noſe. I have ſeldom <lb/>known this fail. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Sometimes, when the bleeding is ſtopped outwardly, it con- <lb/>tinues inwardly. This
          is very troubleſome, and requires <lb/>particular attention, as the patient is apt to be
          ſuffocated <lb/>with the blood, eſpecially if he falls aſleep, which he is very <lb/>ready
          to do after loſing a great quantity of blood. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When the patient is in danger of ſuffocation, from the <lb/>blood getting into his
          throat, the paſſages may be ſtopped <lb/>by drawing threads up the noſtrils, and bringing
          them out of <lb/>the mouth, then faſtening pieces of ſponge, or ſmall rolls of <lb/>linen
          cloth to their extremities; afterwards drawing them <lb/>back, and tying them on the
          outſide with a fuſſicient degree <lb/>of tightneſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>After the bleeding is ſtopped, the patient ought to be kept <lb/>as eaſy and quiet as
          poſſible. He ſhould not pick his noſe, <lb/>nor take away the tents or clotted blood, till
          they fall off of <lb/>their own accord, and ſhould not lie with his head low. <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Buchan</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Chambers</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Burns. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In ſlight burns, which do not break the ſkin, it is cuſto- <lb/>mary to hold the part
          near the fire, for a competent time; to <lb/>rub it with ſalt; or to lay a compreſs upon
          it dipped in ſpi- <lb/>rits of wine or brandy. But when the burn has penetrated <lb/>ſo
          deep as to bliſter or break the ſkin, it muſt be dreſſed with <lb/>ſome of the following
          liniment:— </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Take equal parts of Florence oil, or of freſh drawn linſeed <lb/>oil, and lime-water;
          ſhake them well together in a wide <lb/>mouthed bottle, ſo as to form a liniment. It may
          either be <lb/>ſpread upon a cloth, or the parts affected may be anointed <lb/>with it
          twice or thrice a-day; or it may be dreſſed with <lb/>the emollient and gently drying
          ointment, commonly cal- <lb/>led <hi rend="italic">Turner's cerate</hi>. This may be mixed
          with an equal <lb/>quantity of freſh olive oil, and ſpread upon a ſoft rag, and
          <lb/>applied to the part affected. When this ointment cannot be <lb/>had, an egg may be
          beat up with about an equal quantity of <lb/>the ſweeteſt ſalad oil. This will ſerve very
          well till a pro- <lb/>per ointment can be prepared. When the burning is very <pb n="518"/>
          <lb/>deep, after the firſt two or three days it ſhould he dreſſed <lb/>with equal parts of
          yellow <hi rend="italic">baſilicum</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Turner's cerate</hi>,
          <lb/>mixed together. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When the burn is violent, or has occaſioned a high de- <lb/>gree of inflammation, and
          there is reaſon to fear a gangrene <lb/>or mortification, the ſame means muft be uſed to
          prevent it <lb/>as are recommended in other violent inflammations. The <lb/>patient, in
          this caſe, muſt live low, and drink freely of <lb/>weak diluting liquors. He muſt likewiſe
          be bled, and have <lb/>his body kept open. But if the burnt parts ſhould become <lb/>livid
          or black, with other ſymptoms of mortification, it will <lb/>be neceſſary to bathe them
          frequently with warm camphor- <lb/>ated ſpirits of wine, tincture of myrrh, or other
          antiſeptics, <lb/>mixed with a decoction of the bark. In this caſe, the bark <lb/>muſt
          likewiſe be taken internally, and the patient's diet muſt <lb/>be more generous. <hi
            rend="italic">Buchan</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Colds. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Colds are well known to be the effects of an obſtructed <lb/>perſpiration. Ve ſhall
          not ſpend our time in enumerating <lb/>all the various ſymptoms of colds, as they are
          pretty gene- <lb/>rally known. It may not, however, be amiſs to obſerve, <lb/>that almoſt
          every cold is a kind of fever, which only differs <lb/>in degree. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>No age, ſex, or conſtitution, is exempted from this diſeaſe; <lb/>neither is it in
          the power of any medicine or regimen to pre- <lb/>vent it. The inhabitants of every
          climate are liable to catch <lb/>cold, nor can even the greateſt circumſpection defend
          them <lb/>at all times from its attacks. Indeed, if the human body <lb/>could be kept
          conſtantly in an uniform degree of warmth, <lb/>ſuch a thing as catching cold would be
          impoſſible; but as <lb/>that cannot be effected by any means, the perſpiration muſt
          <lb/>be liable to many changes. Such changes, however, when <lb/>ſmall, do not affect the
          health; but, when great, they muſt <lb/>prove hurtful. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When oppreſſion of the breaſt, a ſtuffing of the noſe, un- <lb/>uſual wearineſs, pain
          of the head, &amp;c. give ground to believe <lb/>that the perſpiration is obſtructed, or,
          in other words, that <lb/>the perſon has caught cold, he ought immediately to leſſen
          <lb/>his diet, at leaſt the uſual quantity of his ſolid food, and to <lb/>abſtain from all
          ſtrong liquors. Inſtead of fleſh, fiſh, eggs, <lb/>milk, and other nouriſhing diet, he may
          eat light bread pud- <pb n="519"/>
          <lb/>ding, veal or chicken broth, panada, gruels, and ſuch like. <lb/>His drink may be
          water gruel ſweetened with a little honey; <lb/>an infuſion of balm, or linſeed ſharpened
          with the juice of <lb/>orange or lemon; a decoction of barley and liquorice with
          <lb/>tamarinds, or any other cool, diluting, acid liquor. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Above all, his ſupper ſhould be light; as ſmall poſſet, or <lb/>water gruel ſweetened
          with honey, and a little toaſted bread <lb/>in it. If honey ſhould diſagree with the
          ſtomach, the gruel <lb/>may be ſweetened with treacle or coarſe ſugar, and ſharpened
          <lb/>with the jelly of currants. Thoſe who have been accuſtomed <lb/>to generous liquors,
          may take wine-whey inſtead of gruel, <lb/>which may be ſweetened as above. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The patient ought to be longer than uſual in bed, and to <lb/>encourage a gentle
          ſweat, which is eaſily brought on towards <lb/>morning, by drinking tea, or any kind of
          warm diluting li- <lb/>quor. I have often known this pratice carry off a cold in <lb/>one
          day, which in all probability, had it been neglected, <lb/>would have coſt the patient his
          life, or have confined him for <lb/>ſome months. Would people ſacrifice a little time to
          eaſe <lb/>and warmth, and practice a moderate degree of abſtinence, <lb/>when the firſt
          ſymptoms of a cold appear, we have reaſon to <lb/>believe, that moſt of the bad effects
          which flow from an ob- <lb/>ſtructed perſpiration, might be prevented. But after the diſ-
          <lb/>eaſe has gathered ſtrength by delay, all attempts to remove it <lb/>often prove vain.
          A pleuriſy, a peripneumony, or a fatal <lb/>conſumption of the lungs, are the common
          effects of colds, <lb/>which have either been totally neglected, or treated impro-
          <lb/>perly. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is certain, however, that colds may be too much in- <lb/>dulged. When a perſon,
          for every ſlight cold, ſhuts himſelf <lb/>up in a warm room, and drinks great quantities
          of warm, li- <lb/>quor, it may occaſion ſuch a general relaxation of the ſolids, <lb/>as
          will not eaſily be removed. It will therefore be proper, <lb/>when the diſeaſe will
          permit, and the weather is mild, to <lb/>join to the regimen mentioned above, gentle
          exerciſe; as <lb/>walking, riding on horſeback, or in a carriage, &amp;c. An ob-
          <lb/>ſtinate cold, which no medicine can remove, will yield to <lb/>gentle exerciſe, and a
          proper regimen of the diet. <hi rend="italic">Tissot</hi>. <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Buchan</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Fothergil</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="520"/>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>The Colic. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Colics, which proceed from exceſs and indigeſtion, gene- <lb/>rally cure themſelves,
          by occaſioning vomiting or purging. <lb/>Theſe diſcharges are by no means to be ſtopped,
          but pro- <lb/>moted by drinking plentifully of warm water, or weak poſſet. <lb/>When their
          violence is over, the patient may take a doſe of <lb/>rhubarb, or any other gentle purge,
          to carry off the dregs of <lb/>his debauch. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Colics which are occaſioned by wet feet, or catching cold, <lb/>may generally be
          removed at the beginning, by bathing the <lb/>feet and legs in warm water, and drinking
          ſuch warm dilut- <lb/>ing liquors as will promote the perſpiration, as weak wine
          <lb/>whey, or water gruel with a ſmall quantity of ſpirits in it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Theſe flatulent colics, which prevail ſo much among <lb/>country people, might
          generally be prevented, were they <lb/>careful to change their clothes when they get wet.
          They <lb/>ought likewiſe to take a dram, or to drink ſome kind of warm <lb/>liquor, after
          eating any kind of green traſh. We do not <lb/>mean to recommend the practice of
          dram-drinking, but in <lb/>this caſe ardent ſpirits prove a real medicine, and indeed the
          <lb/>beſt that can be adminiſtered. A glaſs of good peppermint <lb/>water will have nearly
          the ſame effect as a glaſs of brandy, <lb/>and in ſome caſes is rather to be preferred. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The bilious colic is attended with very acute pains about <lb/>the region of the
          navel. The patient complains of great <lb/>thirſt, and is generally coſtive. He vomits a
          hot, bitter, <lb/>yellow-coloured bile, which being diſcharged, ſeems to afford <lb/>ſome
          relief, but is quickly followed by the ſame violent pain <lb/>as before. As the diſtemper
          advances, the propenſity to vo- <lb/>mit ſometimes increaſes ſo as to become almoſt
          continual, <lb/>and the proper motion of the inteſtines is ſo far perverted, <lb/>that
          there are all the ſymptoms of an impending iliac paſſion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If the patient be young and ſtrong, and the pulſe full and <lb/>frequent, it will be
          proper to bleed; after which clyſters may <lb/>be adminiſtered. Clear whey or gruel,
          ſharpened with the <lb/>juice of lemon, or cream of tartar, muſt be drank freely.
          <lb/>Small chicken broth, with a little manna diſſolved in it, or <lb/>a ſlight decoction
          of tamarinds, are likewiſe very proper; or <lb/>any other thin, acid, opening liquor. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In the bilious colic, the vomiting is often very difficult to <lb/>reſtrain. When
          this happens, the patient may drink a de- <pb n="521"/>
          <lb/>coction of toaſted bread, or an infuſion of garden mint in <lb/>boiling water. Should
          theſe not have the deſired effect, the <lb/>ſaline draught, with a few drops of laudanum
          in it, may be <lb/>given, and repeated according to the urgency of the ſymp- <lb/>toms. A
          ſmall quantity of Venice treacle may be ſpread <lb/>in form of a cataplaſm, and applied to
          the pit of the ſtomach. <lb/>Clyſters, with a proper quantity of Venice treacle or liquid
          <lb/>laudanum in them, may likewiſe be frequently adminiſtered. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The general treatment of the nervous colic is ſo nearly the <lb/>ſame with that of
          the iliac paſſion, or inflammation of the <lb/>guts, that we ſhall not inſiſt upon it. The
          body is to be <lb/>opened by mild purgatives given in ſmall doſes, and frequent- <lb/>ly
          repeated; and their operation muſt be aſſiſted by ſoft, oily <lb/>clyſters, fomentations,
          &amp;c. The caſtor oil is reckoned pecu- <lb/>liarly proper in this diſeaſe. It may both
          be mixed with the <lb/>clyſters, and given by the mouth. <hi rend="italic">Arbuthnot</hi>.
            <hi rend="italic">Buchan</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Conſumption. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This diſeaſe generally begins with a dry cough, which <lb/>often continues for ſome
          months. If a diſpoſition to vomit <lb/>after eating be excited by it, there is ſtill
          greater reaſon to <lb/>fear an approaching conſumption. The patient complains <lb/>of a
          more than uſual degree of heat, a pain and oppreſſion of <lb/>the breaſt, eſpecially after
          motion; his ſpittle is of a ſaltiſh <lb/>taſte, and ſometimes mixed with blood. He is apt
          to be <lb/>ſad: his appetite is bad, and his thirſt great. There is ge- <lb/>nerally a
          quick, ſoft, ſmall pulſe; though ſometimes the <lb/>pulſe is pretty full, and rather hard.
          Theſe are the common <lb/>ſymptoms of a beginning conſumption. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Next to proper air and exerciſe, we would recommend a <lb/>due attention to diet. The
          patient ſhould eat nothing that is <lb/>either heating, or hard of digeſtion; and his
          drink muſt be of <lb/>a ſoft and cooling nature. All the diet ought to be calcu-
          <lb/>lated to leſſen the acrimony of the humours, and to nouriſh <lb/>and ſupport the
          patient. For this purpoſe he muſt keep <lb/>chiefly to the uſe of vegetables and milk.
          Milk alone is of <lb/>more value in this diſeaſe than the whole <hi rend="italic">materia
            medica</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I have known very extraordinary effects from aſſes milk in <lb/>obſtinate coughs,
          which threatened a conſumption of the <lb/>lungs; and do verily believe, if uſed at this
          period, that it <lb/>would ſeldom fail; but if it be delayed till an ulcer is <pb n="522"/>
          <lb/>formed, which is generally the caſe, how can it be expected <lb/>to ſucceed? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Some extraordinary cures in conſumptive caſes, have been <lb/>performed by womens'
          milk. Could this be obtained in ſuf- <lb/>ficient quantity, I would recommend it in
          preference to any <lb/>other. If the patient can ſuck it from the breaſt, it is better
          <lb/>than to drink it afterwards. I knew a man who was reduced <lb/>to ſuch a degree of
          weakneſs in a conſumption, as not to be <lb/>able to turn himſelf in his bed. His wife was
          at that time <lb/>giving ſuck, and his child happening to die, he ſucked her <lb/>breaſts,
          not with a view to reap any advantage from the milk, <lb/>but to make her eaſy. Finding
          himſelf however greatly be- <lb/>nefited by it, he continued to ſuck her till he became
          perfectly <lb/>well, and is at preſent a ſtrong and healthy man. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Cows milk is moſt readily obtained of any; and though it <lb/>may not be ſo eaſily
          digeſted as that of aſſes or mares, it may <lb/>be rendered lighter, by adding to it an
          equal quantity of bar- <lb/>ley-water, or allowing it to ſtand for ſome hours, and after-
          <lb/>wards taking off the cream. If it ſhould, notwithſtanding, <lb/>prove heavy on the
          ſtomach, a ſmall quantity of brandy or <lb/>rum, with a little ſugar, may be added, which
          will render it <lb/>both more light and nouriſhing. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>For the patient's drink, we would recommend infuſions of <lb/>the bitter plants, as
          ground-ivy, the leſſer centaury, camo- <lb/>mile flowers, or water trefoil. Theſe
          infuſions may be drank <lb/>at pleaſure. They ſtrengthen the ſtomach, promote digeſ-
          <lb/>tion, rectify the blood, and at the ſame time anſwer all the <lb/>purpoſes of
          dilution; and quench thirſt much better than <lb/>things that are luſcious or ſweet. But
          if the patient ſpits <lb/>blood, he ought to uſe, for his ordinary drink, infuſions or
          <lb/>decoctions of the vulnerary roots, plants, &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">Steevens</hi>.
            <hi rend="italic">Tiſſot</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Buchan</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Chilblains. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Chilblains often attack children in cold weather. They <lb/>are generally occaſioned
          by the feet or hands being kept wet <lb/>or cold, and afterwards ſuddenly heated. When
          children are <lb/>cold, inſtead of taking exerciſe to warm themſelves gradually, <lb/>they
          run to the fire. This occaſions a ſudden rarefaction <lb/>of the humours, and an
          infarction of the veſſels; which be- <lb/>ing often repeated, the veſſels are, at laſt,
          over-diſtended, <lb/>and forced to give way. </p>
        <pb n="523"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>To prevent it, violent cold, and ſudden heat, muſt be <lb/>equally avoided. When the
          parts begin to look red and <lb/>ſwell, the patient ought to be purged, and to have the
          affected <lb/>parts rubbed frequently with muſtard and brandy, or ſome- <lb/>thing of a
          warming nature. They ought likewiſe to be co- <lb/>vered with flannel, and kept warm and
          dry. Some apply <lb/>warm aſhes betwixt cloth to the ſwelled parts, which fre-
          <lb/>quently help to reduce them. When there is a ſore, it muſt <lb/>be dreſſed with
          Turner's cerate, the ointment of tutty, the <lb/>plaſter of cerus, or ſome other drying
          ointment. Theſe ſores <lb/>are indeed troubleſome, but ſeldom dangerous. They gene-
          <lb/>rally heal as ſoon as the warm weather ſets in. <hi rend="italic">Buchan</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Coſtiveneſs. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Coſtiveneſs is increaſed by keeping the body too warm, <lb/>and by every thing that
          promotes the perſpiration; as wear- <lb/>ing flannel, lying too long a bed, &amp;c.
          Intenſe thought, and <lb/>a ſedentary life, are likewiſe hurtful. All the ſecretions and
          <lb/>excretions are promoted by moderate exerciſe without doors, <lb/>and by a gay,
          cheerful, ſprightly, temper of mind. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Thole who are troubled with coſtiveneſs, ought, if poſſible, <lb/>to remedy it by
          diet, as the conſtant uſe of medicines for <lb/>that purpoſe is attended with many
          inconveniencies, and often <lb/>with bad conſequences. I never knew any one get into a ha-
          <lb/>bit of taking medicine for keeping the body open, who could <lb/>leave it off. In
          time, the cuſtom becomes neceſſary; and ge- <lb/>nerally ends in a total relaxation of the
          boweſs, indigeſtion, <lb/>loſs of appetite, waſting of the ſtrength, and death. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When the body cannot be kept open without medicine, I <lb/>would recommend gentle
          doſes of rhubarb to be taken twice <lb/>or thrice a week. This is not near ſo injurious to
          the ſto- <lb/>mach, as aloes, jalap, or the other draſtic purgatives ſo much <lb/>in uſe.
          Infuſions of ſenna and manna may likewiſe be taken, <lb/>or half an ounce of ſoluble
          tartar diſſolved in water gruel. <lb/>About the ſize of a nutmeg of lenitive electuary,
          taken twice <lb/>or thrice a day, generally anſwers the purpoſe very well. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Common Cough. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A cough is generally the effect of a cold, which has either <lb/>been improperly
          treated, or entirely neglected. When it <lb/>proves obſtinate, there is always reaſon to
          fear the conſe- <pb n="524"/>
          <lb/>quences, as this ſhews a weak ſtate of the lungs, and is often <lb/>the fore-runner
          of a conſumption. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When the cough is not attended with any degree of fever, <lb/>and the ſpittle is
          viſcid and tough, ſharp pectoral medicines <lb/>are to be adminiſtered; as gum ammoniac,
          ſquills, &amp;c. Two <lb/>table ſpoonfuls of the ſolution of gum ammoniac may be
          <lb/>taken three or four times a day, more or leſs, according to <lb/>the age or
          conſtitution of the patient. Squills may be given <lb/>various ways; two ounces of
          vinegar, the oxymel, or the <lb/>ſyrup, may be mixed with the ſame quantity of ſimple cin-
          <lb/>namon water; to which may be added an ounce of common <lb/>water, and an ounce of
          balſamic ſyrup. Two table ſpoon- <lb/>fuls of this mixture may be taken three or four
          times a day. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A ſyrup made of equal parts of lemon-juice, honey, and <lb/>ſugar-candy, is likewiſe
          very proper in this kind of cough. <lb/>A table ſpoonful of it may be taken at pleaſure. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In obſtinate coughs, proceeding from a flux of humours <lb/>upon the lungs, it will
          often be neceſſary, beſides expectora- <lb/>ting medicines, to have recourſe to iſſues,
          ſetons, or ſome <lb/>other drain. In this caſe I have often obſerved the moſt <lb/>happy
          effects from a Burgundy pitch plaſter applied between <lb/>the ſhoulders. I have ordered
          this ſimple remedy in the moſt <lb/>obſtinate coughs, in a great number of caſes, and in
          many <lb/>different conſtitutions, without ever knowing it fail to give <lb/>relief,
          unleſs there were evident ſigns of an ulcer in the <lb/>lungs. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But coughs proceed from many other cauſes beſides deflux- <lb/>ions upon the lungs.
          In theſe caſes the cure is not to be at- <lb/>tempted by pectoral medicines. Thus, in a
          cough proceed- <lb/>ing from a foulneſs and debility of the ſtomach, ſyrups, oils,
          <lb/>mucilages, and all kinds of balſamic medicines do hurt. The <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >ſtomach cough</hi> may be known from one that is owing to a <lb/>fault in the lungs, by
          this—that in the latter, the patient <lb/>coughs whenever he inſpires, or draws in his
          breath fully; <lb/>but in the former, that does not happen. <hi rend="italic">Tiſſot</hi>.
            <hi rend="italic">Buchan</hi>. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Chambers</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>The Cramp. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Cramps are often prevented or cured by compreſſion. <lb/>Thus cramps in the legs are
          prevented, and ſometimes re- <lb/>moved, by tight bandages; and when convulſions ariſe
          from <lb/>a flatulent diſtention of the inteſtines, or from ſpaſms begin- <pb n="525"/>
          <lb/>ning in them, they may be often leſſened or cured, by making <lb/>a pretty ſtrong
          compreſſion upon the <hi rend="italic">abdomen</hi>, by means of a <lb/>broad belt. A roll
          of brimſtone held in the hands is fre- <lb/>quently uſed as a remedy for cramps. Though
          this ſeems <lb/>to owe its effects chiefly to imagination; yet, as it ſometimes
          <lb/>ſucceeds, it merits a trial. When ſpaſms or convulſive mo- <lb/>tions ariſe from
          ſharp humours in the ſtomach and inteſtines, <lb/>no laſting relief can be procured till
          theſe are either cor- <lb/>rected or expelled. The Peruvian bark has ſometimes cured
          <lb/>periodic convulſions after other medicines had failed. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>The Dropſy. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Take of broom-ſeed, well powdered and ſifted, one drachm; <lb/>let it ſteep twelve
          hours in a glaſs and half of good rich white- <lb/>wine, and take it in the morning
          faſting, having firſt ſhaken <lb/>it, ſo that the whole may be ſwallowed. Walk after it,
          if <lb/>you are able, or uſe what exerciſe you can without fatigue, <lb/>for an hour and a
          half <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.5)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* If the patient is too weak to uſe other exerciſe after taking the powder, the
              <lb/>body and limbs may be rubbed with a flannel, from time to time, during the
              <lb/>hour and half, giving reſt at intervals, according to ſtrength; and indeed the
              <lb/>practice of this exerciſe for ſome minutes, every night and morning, may be of
              <lb/>great help. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The quantities directed in the recipe have been given alike to men and to
              <lb/>women; and there never has been found reaſon to think that they were too little
              <lb/>for the one, or too much for the other. </p>
          </note>
        </p>
        <p>; after which you muſt be ſure to <lb/>take two ounces of olive-oil; and you muſt not eat
          or drink <lb/>any thing in leſs than half an hour, or an hour, after taking <lb/>the oil.
          Repeat this every other day, or once in three days, <lb/>and not oftener, till cured; and
          do not let blood, or uſe any <lb/>other remedy during the courſe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Nothing can be more gentle and ſafe than the operation of <lb/>this remedy, and it
          often has little or no ſenſible one. If <lb/>the dropſy is in the body, it diſcharges it
          by urine, without <lb/>any inconvenience; if it is between the ſkin and fleſh, it
          <lb/>cauſes bliſters to ariſe on the legs, by which it will run off; <lb/>but this does
          not happen to more than one in thirty; and in <lb/>this caſe no plaſters muſt be uſed, for
          they would hinder the <lb/>diſcharge; but you muſt apply red cabbage-leaves. If the
          <lb/>diſorder is cauſed by wind, it diſpels the phlegm that retains <lb/>the wind. It
          cures the dropſy in pregnant women, without <lb/>injury to the mother or the infant. It
          alſo cures the aſthma, <pb n="526"/>
          <lb/>conſumption, and diſorders of the liver. It is good for the <lb/>bleeding at the
          noſe, and for venomous bites and poiſons. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The efficacy of the above remedy has been proved by the <lb/>cure of upwards of fifty
          dropſical women with child, and by <lb/>that of more than three hundred other people of
          both ſexes. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Not long ſince, this recipe was recommended to a lady, <lb/>who ſeemed to be in, or
          nearly in, the laſt ſtage of a dropſy. <lb/>She was ſo much ſwoln, that ſhe appeared like
          a woman in <lb/>the laſt month of her pregnancy, and her diſorder had re- <lb/>ſiſted
          every thing that had been done for her by the faculty. <lb/>She took the broom-ſeed, but
          could not take the whole of <lb/>the oil; however, in a very few months, her huſband wrote
          <lb/>a letter of thanks for her ſpeedy and ſurpriſing recovery <note place="bottom" n="*"
            rend="size(0.5)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* I refer ſuch of my readers as wiſh to inform themſelves more fully of its
              <lb/>great efficacy, to a ſmall pamphlet publiſhed by Mr. Dodſley, bookſeller, in
              Pall- <lb/><unclear>mall</unclear>, price only ſix-pence. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>The author candidly tells the public, that this recipe is taken from a French
              <lb/>work by <hi rend="sc">Lenery</hi>, called <hi rend="italic"
                    ><unclear>Re<unclear>cue</unclear>il</unclear> de Secrets</hi>, printed at <hi
                rend="italic">Paris</hi>. </p>
          </note>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Soon after, the report of this extraordinary cure induced <lb/>another lady, who was
          afflicted with a dropſy, to make trial <lb/>of the remedy. She was not ſo much ſwoln as
          the former <lb/>lady, but ſhe was exceedingly emaciated, and was ſo weak, <lb/>that ſhe
          was carried like an infant into her carriage, when <lb/>ſhe went to take the air; and ſhe
          had failed of relief from <lb/>the advice of two of the moſt eminent phyſicians in London,
          <lb/>who had pronounced it an aſcites, with encyſted water. Hap- <lb/>pily they were too
          liberal minded to ſet their faces againſt the <lb/>remedy, as ſome others have ſince done,
          becauſe it was not <lb/>of their acquaintance. This lady followed the directions <lb/>of
          the recipe very exactly, and was reſtored to health in a <lb/>few months. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Theſe ſucceſſes induced the lady, at whoſe deſire it is pub- <lb/>liſhed, to
          recommend the remedy with avidity whenever oc- <lb/>caſion offered; and it has pleaſed God
          to crown her endea- <lb/>vours with ſuch wonderful ſucceſs, that ſhe thinks ſhe may
          <lb/>venture to affirm, that ſhe has never known it fail to cure, <lb/>when taken
          according to the recipe, and while there was any <lb/>degree of ſtrength remaining; and
          that it is almoſt as certain <lb/>a ſpecific for the dropſy, as the bark is for the
          intermitting <lb/>fever. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="527"/>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>The Gout. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As there are no medicines yet known that will cure the <lb/>gout, we ſhall confine
          our obſervations chiefly to regimen, <lb/>both in and out of the fit. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In the fit, if the patient be young and ſtrong, his diet <lb/>ought to be thin and
          cooling, and his drink of a diluting <lb/>nature; but when the conſtitution is weak, and
          the patient <lb/>has been accuſtomed to live high, this is not a proper time to
          <lb/>retrench. In this caſe, he muſt keep nearly to his uſual diet, <lb/>and ſhould take
          frequently a cup of ſtrong negus, or a glaſs <lb/>of generous wine. Wine whey is a very
          proper drink in <lb/>this caſe, as it promotes the perſpiration without greatly
          <lb/>heating the patient. It will anſwer this purpoſe better, if a <lb/>tea-ſpoonful of
            <hi rend="italic">ſal volatile oleoſum</hi>, or ſpirits of hartſhorn, be <lb/>put into a
          cup of it twice a-day. It will likewiſe be proper <lb/>to give at bed-time, a tea-ſpoonful
          of the volatile tincture of <lb/><hi rend="italic">guaiacum</hi>, in a large draught of
          warm wine whey. This will <lb/>greatly promote perſpiration through the night. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Many things will ſhorten a fit of the gout, and ſome will <lb/>drive it off
          altogether; but nothing has yet been found <lb/>which will do this with ſafety to the
          patient. In plain, we <lb/>eagerly graſp at any thing that promiſes immediate eaſe, and
          <lb/>even hazard life itſelf for a temporary relief. This is the <lb/>true reaſon why ſo
          many infallible remedies have been pro- <lb/>poſed for the gout, and why ſuch numbers have
          loſt their <lb/>lives by the uſe of them. It would be as prudent to ſtop the
          <lb/>ſmall-pox from riſing, and to drive them into the blood, as to <lb/>attempt to repel
          the gouty matter after it has been thrown <lb/>upon the extremities. The latter is as much
          an effort of na- <lb/>ture to free herſelf from an offending cauſe as the former, <lb/>and
          ought equally to be promoted. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>After the fit is over, the patient ought to take a gentle <lb/>doſe or two of the
          bitter tincture of rhubarb, or ſome other <lb/>warm ſtomachic purge. He ſhould alſo drink
          a weak infu- <lb/>ſion of ſtomachic bitters in ſmall wine or ale, as the Peru- <lb/>vian
          bark, with cinnamon, Virginian ſnake-root, and orange- <lb/>peel. The diet at this time
          ſhould be light, but nouriſhing; <lb/>and gentle exerciſe ought to be taken on horſeback,
          or in a <lb/>carriage. <hi rend="italic">Sydenham</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Tiſſot</hi>. <hi
            rend="italic">Buchan</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="528"/>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>The Gravel and Stone. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Perſons afflicted with the gravel or ſtone, ſhould avoid ali- <lb/>ments of a windy
          or heating nature, as ſalt meats, ſour fruits, <lb/>&amp;c. Their diet ought chiefly to
          conſiſt of ſuch things as <lb/>tend to promote the ſecretion of urine, and to keep the
          body <lb/>open. Artichokes, aſparagus, ſpinach, lettuce, parſley, ſuc- <lb/>cory,
          purſlane, turnips, potatoes, carrots, and radiſhes, may <lb/>be ſafely eat. Onions, leeks,
          and celery, are, in this caſe, <lb/>reckoned medicinal. The moſt proper drinks are whey,
          <lb/>butter-milk, milk and water, barley-water; decoctions of the <lb/>roots of marſh
          mallows, parſley, liquorice, or of other mild <lb/>mucilaginous vegetables, as linſeed,
          limetree-buds, or leaves, <lb/>&amp;c. If the patient has been accuſtomed to generous
          liquors, <lb/>he may drink ſmall gin-punch, without acid. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Dr. Whyte adviſes patients who are ſubject to frequent fits <lb/>of the gravel in the
          kidnies, but have no ſtone in the bladder, <lb/>to drink, every morning, two or three
          hours before breakfaſt, <lb/>an Engliſh pint of oyſter, or cockle-ſhell lime-water. The
          <lb/>doctor very juſtly obſerves, that though this quantity might <lb/>be too ſmall to
          have any ſenſible effect in diſſolving a ſtone <lb/>in the bladder, yet it may very
          probably prevent its growth. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When a ſtone is formed in the bladder, the doctor recom- <lb/>mends Alicant ſoap,
          oyſter or cockle-ſhell lime-water, to be <lb/>taken in the following manner: The patient
          muſt ſwallow, <lb/>every day, in any form that is leaſt diſagreeable, an ounce of <lb/>the
          internal part of Alicant ſoap, and drink three or four <lb/>Engliſh pints of oyſter, or
          cockle-ſhell lime-water. The <lb/>ſoap is to be divided into three doſes; the largeſt to
          be taken <lb/>faſting in the morning early; the ſecond at noon; and <lb/>the third at
          ſeven in the evening; drinking above each doſe <lb/>a large draught of the lime-water; the
          remainder of which <lb/>he may take any time betwixt dinner and ſupper, inſtead of
          <lb/>other liquors. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The patient ſhould begin with a ſmaller quantity of the <lb/>lime-water and ſoap than
          that mentioned above; at firſt, an <lb/>Engliſh pint of the former, and three drachms of
          the latter, <lb/>may be taken daily. This quantity, however, he may in- <lb/>creaſe by
          degrees, and ought to perſevere in the uſe of theſe <lb/>medicines, eſpecially if he finds
          any abatement of his com- <lb/>plaints, for ſeveral months; nay, if the ſtone be very
          large, <pb n="529"/>
          <lb/>for years. It may likewiſe be proper for the patient, if <lb/>he be ſeverely pained,
          not only to begin with the ſoap and <lb/>lime-water in ſmall quantities, but to take the
          ſecond or <lb/>third lime-water inſtead of the firſt. However, after he has <lb/>been
          accuſtomed to theſe medicines, he may not only take <lb/>the firſt water, but, if he finds
          he can eaſily bear it, heighten <lb/>its diſſolving power ſtill more, by pouring it a
          ſecond time <lb/>on freſh calcined ſhells. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The cauſtic alkali, or ſoap-lees, is the medicine chiefly in <lb/>vogue at preſent
          for the ſtone. It is of a very acrid nature, <lb/>and ought therefore to be given in ſome
          gelatinous or muci- <lb/>laginous liquor; as veal-broth, new milk, linſeed tea, a ſolu-
          <lb/>tion of gum arabic, or a decoction of marſh-mallow roots. <lb/>The patient muſt begin
          with ſmall doſes of the lees, as thirty <lb/>or forty drops, and increaſe by degrees, as
          far as the ſto- <lb/>mach will bear it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The only other medicine which I ſhall mention is the <hi rend="italic">uva
            <lb/>urſi</hi>. It has been greatly extolled of late both for the gravel <lb/>and ſtone.
          It ſeems, however, to be in all reſpects inferior <lb/>to the ſoap and lime-water; but it
          is leſs diſagreeable, and <lb/>has frequently, to my knowledge, relieved gravelly com-
          <lb/>plaints. It is generally taken in powder from half a drachm <lb/>to a whole drachm,
          two or three times a-day. It may, <lb/>however, be taken to the quantity of ſeven of eight
          drachms <lb/>a-day, with great ſafety and good effect. <hi rend="italic">Buchan</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>The Gripes in Children. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When an infant is troubled with gripes, it ought not at <lb/>firſt to be doſed with
          brandy, ſpiceries, and other hot <lb/>things; but ſhould have its body opened with an
          emollient <lb/>clyſter, and, at the ſame time, a little brandy may be rubbed <lb/>on its
          belly with a warm hand before the fire. I have ſel- <lb/>dom ſeen this fail to eaſe the
          gripes of infants. If it ſhould <lb/>happen, however, not to ſucceed, a little brandy, or
          other <lb/>ſpirits, may be mixed with thrice the quantity of warm wa- <lb/>ter, and a
          tea-ſpoonful be given frequently, till the infant be <lb/>eaſier. Sometimes a little
          peppermint water will anſwer this <lb/>purpoſe wery well. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="530"/>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>The Hooping, or Chin Cough. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>One of the moſt effectual remedies in the chin-cough, is <lb/>change of air. This
          often removes the malady, even when <lb/>the change ſeems to be from a purer, to a leſs
          wholeſome <lb/>air. This may, in ſome meaſure, depend on the patient's <lb/>being removed
          from the place where the infection prevails. <lb/>Moſt of the diſeaſes of children are
          infectious; nor is it at <lb/>all uncommon to find the chin-cough prevailing in one
          <lb/>town or village, when another, at a very ſmall diſtance, is <lb/>quite free from it.
          But whatever be the cauſe, we are ſure <lb/>of the fact. No time ought, therefore, to be
          loſt in removing <lb/>the patient at ſome diſtance from the place where he caught <lb/>the
          diſeaſe, and, if poſſible, into a more pure and warm <lb/>air. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When the diſeaſe proves violent, and the patient is in dan- <lb/>ger of being
          ſuffocated by the cough, he ought to be bled, <lb/>eſpecially if there be a fever, with a
          hard full pulſe. But as <lb/>the chief intention of bleeding is to prevent an inflammation
          <lb/>of the lungs, and to render it more ſafe to give vomits, it <lb/>will ſeldom be
          neceſſary to repeat the operation; yet if there <lb/>be ſymptoms of an inflammation of the
          lungs, a ſecond, or <lb/>even a third bleeding, may be requiſite. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The body ought to be kept gently open. The beſt medi- <lb/>cines for this purpoſe are
          rhubarb and its preparations, as the <lb/>ſyrup, tincture, &amp;c. Of theſe a tea-ſpoonful
          or two may be <lb/>given to an infant twice or thrice a-day, as there is occaſion. <lb/>To
          ſuch as are farther advanced, the doſe muſt be propor- <lb/>tionally increaſed, and
          repeated till it has the deſired effect. <lb/>Thoſe who cannot be brought to take the
          bitter tincture, <lb/>may have an infuſion of ſenna and prunes, ſweetened with <lb/>manna,
          coarſe ſugar, or honey; or a few grains of rhubarb <lb/>mixed with a tea-ſpoonful or two
          of ſyrup, or currant jelly, <lb/>ſo as to diſguiſe the taſte. Moſt children are fond of
          ſyrups <lb/>and jellies, and ſeldom refuſe even a diſagreeable medicine <lb/>when mixed
          with them. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The garlic ointment is a well known remedy in North <lb/>Britain for the chin-cough.
          It is made by beating in a mor- <lb/>tar, garlic, with an equal quantity of hogs lard.
          With this <lb/>the ſoles of the feet may be rubbed twice or thrice a-day; <lb/>but the
          beſt method is to ſpread it upon a rag, and apply it <lb/>in the form of a plaſter. It
          ſhould be renewed every night <pb n="531"/>
          <lb/>and morning at leaſt, as the garlic ſoon loſes its virtue. <lb/>This is an exceeding
          good medicine, both in the chin-cough, <lb/>and in moſt other coughs of an obſtinate
          nature. It ought <lb/>not, however, to be uſed when the patient is very hot and
          <lb/>feveriſh, leſt it ſhould increaſe theſe ſymptoms. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The feet ſhould be bathed, once in every two or three <lb/>days, in lukewarm water;
          and a Burgundy-pitch plaiſter kept <lb/>conſtantly between the ſhoulders. But when the
          diſeaſe <lb/>proves very violent, it will be neceſſary, inſtead of it, to ap- <lb/>ply a
          bliſtering plaſter, and keep the part open for ſome time <lb/>with iſſue-ointment. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When the diſeaſe is prolonged, and the patient is free from <lb/>a fever, the
          Peruvian bark, and other bitters, are the moſt <lb/>proper medicines. The bark may either
          be taken in ſub- <lb/>ſtance, or in a decoction or infuſion, as is moſt agreeable.
          <lb/>For a child, ten, fifteen, or twenty grains, according to the <lb/>age of the
          patient, may be given three or four times a-day. <lb/>For an adult, half a drachm, or two
          ſcruples, will be proper. <lb/>Some give the extract of the bark with cantharides; but to
          <lb/>manage this, requires a conſiderable attention. It is more <lb/>ſafe to give a few
          grains of caſtor along with the bark. A <lb/>child of ſix or ſeven years of age, may take
          ſeven or eight <lb/>grains of caſtor, with fifteen grains of powdered bark, for <lb/>a
          doſe. This may be made into a mixture with two or <lb/>three ounces of ſimple diſtilled
          water, and a little ſyrup, <lb/>and taken three or four times a-day. <hi rend="italic"
            >Buchan</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Chambers</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>The Jaundice. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This diſeaſe is firſt obſervable in the white of the eye, <lb/>which appears yellow.
          Afterwards the whole ſkin puts on <lb/>a yellow appearance. The urine too is of a ſaffron
          colour, <lb/>and dyes a white cloth of the ſame colour. There is likewiſe <lb/>a ſpecies
          of this diſeaſe called the black jaundice. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If the patient be young, and the diſeaſe complicated with <lb/>no other malady, it is
          ſeldom dangerous; but in old people, <lb/>where it continues long, returns frequently, or
          is compli- <lb/>cated with the dropſy, or hypochondriac ſymptoms, it gene- <lb/>rally
          proves fatal. The black jaundice is more dangerous <lb/>than the yellow. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If the patient be young, of a full ſanguine habit, and com- <lb/>plains of pain in
          the right ſide, about the region of the liver, <lb/>bleeding will be neceſſary. After
          this, a vomit muſt be ad- <pb n="532"/>
          <lb/>miniſtered, and if the diſeaſe proves obſtinate, it may be re- <lb/>peated once or
          twice. No medicines are more beneficial in <lb/>the jaundice than vomits, eſpecially where
          it is not attended <lb/>with inflammation. Half a drachm of ipecacuanha, in powder,
          <lb/>will be a ſufficient doſe for an adult. It may be wrought off <lb/>with weak camomile
          tea, or lukewarm water. The body <lb/>muſt likewiſe be kept open, by taking a ſufficient
          quantity of <lb/>Caſtile ſoap. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I have known Harrowgate ſulphur-water cure the jaundice <lb/>of very long ſtanding.
          It ſhould be uſed for ſome weeks, <lb/>and the patient muſt drink and bathe. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The ſoluble tartar is a very proper medicine in the jaun- <lb/>dice. A drachm of it
          may be taken every night and morn- <lb/>ing in a cup of tea or water-grueI. If it does not
          open the <lb/>body, the doſe may be increaſed. A very obſtinate jaundice <lb/>has been
          cured by ſwallowing raw eggs. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Perſons ſubject to the jaundice, ought to take as much ex- <lb/>erciſe as poſſible,
          and to avoid all heating and aſtringent ali- <lb/>ments. <hi rend="italic">Buchan</hi>.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>The Itch. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The itch is ſeldom a dangerous diſeaſe, unleſs where it <lb/>is rendered ſo by
          neglect, or improper treatment. If it be <lb/>ſuffered to continue too long, it may
          vitiate the whole maſs <lb/>of humours; and if it be ſuddenly drove in, without proper
          <lb/>evacuations, it may occaſion fevers, inflammations of the viſ- <lb/>cera, or other
          internal diſorders. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The beſt medicine yet known for the itch, is ſulphur, which <lb/>ought to be uſed
          both externally and internally. The parts <lb/>moſt affected may be rubbed with an
          ointment made of the <lb/>flowers of ſulphur, two ounces; crude ſal ammoniac, finely
          <lb/>powdered, two drachms; hogs lard, or butter, four ounces; <lb/>if a ſcruple or half a
          drachm of the eſſence of lemon be added, <lb/>it will entirely take away the diſagreeable
          ſmell. About the <lb/>bulk of a nutmeg of this may be rubbed upon the extremi- <lb/>ties,
          at bed-time, twice or thrice a-week. It is ſeldom ne- <lb/>ceſſary to rub the whole body;
          but when it is, it ought not <lb/>to be done all at once, as it is dangerous to ſtop too
          many <lb/>pores at the ſame time. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Before the patient begins to uſe the ointment, he ought, if <lb/>he be of a full
          habit, to bleed, or take a purge or two. It <lb/>will likewiſe be proper, during the uſe
          of it, to take every <pb n="533"/>
          <lb/>morning as much of the flower of brimſtone and cream of <lb/>tartar, in a little
          treacle or new milk, as will keep the body <lb/>gently open. He ſhould beware of catching
          cold, ſhould <lb/>wear more clothes than uſual, and take every thing warm. <lb/>The ſame
          clothes, the linen excepted, ought to be worn all <lb/>the time of uſing the ointment; and
          ſuch clothes as have <lb/>been worn while the patient was under the diſeaſe, are not to
          <lb/>be uſed again, unleſs they have been fumigated with brim- <lb/>ſtone, and thoroughly
          cleaned, otherwiſe they will commu- <lb/>nicate the infection anew <note place="bottom"
            n="*" rend="size(0.5)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Sir John Pringle obſerves, that, though this diſeaſe may ſeem trifling, there
              <lb/>is no one in the army that is more troubleſome to cure, as the infection often
              <lb/>lurks in clothes, &amp;c. and breaks out a ſecond, or even a third time. The ſame
              <lb/>inconveniency occurs in private families, unleſs particular regard is paid to the
              <lb/>changing or cleaning of their clothes, which laſt is by no means an eaſy ope-
              <lb/>ration. </p>
          </note>. <hi rend="italic">Pringle</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>A Diarrhœa, or Looſeneſs. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A looſeneſs, in many caſes, is not to be conſidered as a <lb/>diſeaſe, but rather as
          a ſalutary evacuation. It ought, there- <lb/>fore, never to be ſtopped, unleſs when it
          continues too long, <lb/>or evidently weakens the patient. As this, however, ſome-
          <lb/>times happens, I ſhall point out the moſt common cauſes of <lb/>a looſeneſs, with the
          proper method of treatment. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When a looſeneſs is occaſioned by catching cold, or an <lb/>obſtructed perſpiration,
          the patient ought to keep warm, to <lb/>drink freely of weak diluting liquors, to bathe
          his feet and <lb/>legs frequently in lukewarm water, to wear flannel next his <lb/>ſkin,
          and to take every other method to reſtore the perſpira- <lb/>tion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In a looſeneſs which proceeds from exceſs or repletion, a <lb/>vomit is the proper
          medicine. Vomits not only cleanſe the <lb/>ſtomach, but promote all the ſecretions, which
          render them <lb/>of great importance in carrying off a debauch. Half a <lb/>drachm of
          ipecacuanha, in powder, will anſwer this purpoſe <lb/>very well. A day or two after the
          vomit, the ſame quantity <lb/>of rhubarb may be taken, and repeated two or three times, if
          <lb/>the looſeneſs continues. The patient ought to live upon <lb/>light vegetable food of
          eaſy digeſtion, and to drink whey, <lb/>thin gruel, or barley-water. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A looſeneſs, occaſioned by the obſtruction of any cuſ- <lb/>tomary evacuation,
          generally requires bleeding. If that <pb n="534"/>
          <lb/>does not ſucceed, other evacuations may be ſubſtituted in <lb/>the room of thoſe
          which are obſtructed. At the ſame time, <lb/>every method is to be taken to reſtore the
          uſual diſcharges, <lb/>as not only the cure of the diſeaſe, but the patient's life, may
          <lb/>depend on this. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A periodical looſeneſs ought never to be ſtopped. It is <lb/>always an effort of
          nature to carry off ſome offending matter, <lb/>which, if retained in the body, might have
          fatal effects. <lb/>Children are very liable to this kind of looſeneſs, eſpecially
          <lb/>while toothing. It is, however, ſo far from being hurtful to <lb/>them, that ſuch
          children generally get their teeth with leſs <lb/>trouble. If theſe looſe ſtools ſhould at
          any time prove ſour <lb/>or griping, a tea-ſpoonful of magneſia alba, with four or five
          <lb/>grains of rhubarb, may be given to the child in a little pa- <lb/>nada, or any other
          food. This, if repeated, three or four <lb/>times, will generally correct the acidity, and
          carry off the <lb/>griping ſtools. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>From whatever cauſe a looſeneſs proceeds, when it is <lb/>found neceſſary to check
          it, the diet ought to conſiſt of rice <lb/>boiled with milk, and flavoured with cinnamon;
          rice-jelly; <lb/>ſago, with red port; and the lighter ſorts of fleſh-meat <lb/>roaſted.
          The drink may be thin water-gruel, rice water, or <lb/>weak broth made from lean veal, or
          with a ſheep's head, as <lb/>being more gelatinous than mutton, beef, or chicken-broth.
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Buchan</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>Obſtructions in young Girls. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>After a female has arrived at that period of life when the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >menſes</hi> uſually begin to flow, and they do not appear, but, on <lb/>the contrary,
          her health and ſpirits begin to decline, I would <lb/>adviſe, inſtead of ſhutting the poor
          girl up in the houſe, and <lb/>doſing her with ſteel, aſafœtida, and other nauſeous drugs,
          <lb/>to place her in a ſituation where ſhe can enjoy the benefit of <lb/>free air and
          agreeable company. There let her eat whole- <lb/>ſome food, take ſufficient exerciſe, and
          amuſe herſelf in the <lb/>moſt agreeable manner; and we have little reaſon to fear, but
          <lb/>nature, thus aſſiſted, will do her proper work. Indeed ſhe <lb/>ſeldom fails, unleſs
          where the fault is on our ſide. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>This diſcharge, in the beginning, is ſeldom ſo inſtantane- <lb/>ous as to ſurpriſe
          females unawares. It is generally preceded <lb/>by ſymptoms which foretel its approach; as
          a ſenſe of heat, <lb/>weight, and dull pain in the loins; diſtention and hardneſs <lb/>of
          the breaſts; head-ach; loſs of appetite; laſſitude; pale- <pb n="535"/>
          <lb/>neſs of the countenance; and ſometimes a ſlight degree of <lb/>fever. When theſe
          ſymptoms appear about the age at which <lb/>the menſtrual flux uſually begins, eyery thing
          ſhould be <lb/>carefully avoided which may obſtruct that neceſſary and ſalu- <lb/>tary
          evacuation; and all means uſed to promote it; as ſitting <lb/>frequently over the ſteam of
          warm water, drinking warm di- <lb/>luting liquors, &amp;c. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>After the <hi rend="italic">menſes</hi> have once begun to flow, the greateſt care
          <lb/>ſhould be taken to avoid every thing that may tend to ob- <lb/>ſtruct them. Females
          ought to be exceeding cautious of <lb/>what they eat or drink at the time they are out of
          order. <lb/>Every thing that is cold, or apt to ſour on the ſtomach, <lb/>ought to be
          avoided; as fruit, butter-milk, and ſuch like. <lb/>Firm, and all kinds of food that are
          hard of digeſtion, are <lb/>alſo to be avoided. As it is impoſſible to mention every
          <lb/>thing that may diſagree with individuals at this time, I would <lb/>recommend it to
          every female to be very attentive to what <lb/>diſagrees with herſelf, and carefully to
          avoid it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>From whatever cauſe this flux is obſtructed, except in the <lb/>ſtate of pregnancy,
          proper means ſhould be uſed to reſtore it. <lb/>For this purpoſe, I would recommend
          ſufficient exerciſe, in <lb/>a dry, open, and rather cool air; wholeſome diet, and if the
          <lb/>body be weak and languid, generous liquors; alſo cheerful <lb/>company, and all
          manner of amuſements. If theſe fail, re- <lb/>courſe muſt be had to medicine. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When obſtructions proceed from a weak relaxed ſtate of <lb/>the ſolids, ſuch
          medicines as tend to promote digeſtion, to <lb/>brace the ſolids, and aſſiſt the body in
          preparing good blood, <lb/>ought to be uſed. The principal of theſe are iron, and the
          <lb/>Peruvian bark, with all other bitter and aſtringent medicines. <lb/>Filings of iron
          may be infuſed in wine or ale, two or three <lb/>ounces to an Engliſh quart, and after it
          has ſtood for two or <lb/>three weeks, it may be filtered, and about half a wine glaſs
          <lb/>of it taken twice a-day: or prepared ſteel may be taken in <lb/>the doſe of half a
          drachm, mixed with a little honey, or <lb/>treacle, three or four times a-day. The bark,
          and other bit- <lb/>ters, may either be taken in ſubſtance, or infuſion, as is moſt
          <lb/>agreeable to the patient. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>But the menſtrual flux may be too great, as well as too <lb/>ſmall. When this
          happens, the patient becomes weak, the <lb/>colour pale, the appetite and digeſtion are
          bad, and œdema- <lb/>tous ſwellings of the feet, dropſies, and conſumptions enſue.
          <lb/>This frequently happens to women about the age of forty- <pb n="536"/>
          <lb/>five or fifty, and is very difficult to cure. It may proceed <lb/>from a ſedentary
          life, a full diet, conſiſting chiefly of ſalted, <lb/>high ſeaſoned, or acrid food; the
          uſe of ſpiritous liquors; <lb/>exceſſive fatigue; relaxation; a diſſolved ſtate of the
          blood; <lb/>violent paſſions of the mind, &amp;c. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The treatment of this diſeaſe muſt be varied according to <lb/>its cauſe. When it is
          occaſioned by any error in the pa- <lb/>tient's regimen, an oppoſite courſe to that which
          induced the <lb/>diſorder muſt be purſued, and ſuch medicines taken as have <lb/>a
          tendency to reſtrain the flux, and counteract the morbid af- <lb/>fections of the ſyſtem
          from whence it proceeds. <hi rend="italic">Arbuthnot</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>The Bleeding and Blind Piles. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A diſcharge of blood from the hœmorrhoidal veſſels, is <lb/>called the <hi
            rend="italic">bleeding piles</hi>. When the veſſels only ſwell, and <lb/>diſcharge no
          blood, but are exceeding painful, the diſeaſe is <lb/>called the <hi rend="italic">blind
            piles</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A flux of blood from the <hi rend="italic">anus</hi> is not always to be treated
          <lb/>as a diſeaſe. It is even more ſalutary than bleeding at the <lb/>noſe, and often
          prevents or carries of diſeaſes. It is pecu- <lb/>liarly beneficial in the gout,
          rheumatiſm, aſthma, and hypo- <lb/>chondrical complaints; and often proves critical in
          colics, <lb/>and inflammatory fevers. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In the management of the patient, regard muſt be had to <lb/>his habit of body, his
          age, ſtrength, and manner of living. A <lb/>diſcharge which might be exceſſive, and prove
          hurtful to one, <lb/>may be very moderate, and even ſalutary to another. That <lb/>only is
          to be eſteemed dangerous which continues too long, <lb/>and is in ſuch quantity as to
          waſte the patient's ſtrength, <lb/>hurt digeſtion, nutrition, and other functions
          neceſſary to <lb/>life. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When this is the caſe, the diſcharge muſt be checked by a <lb/>proper regimen, and
          aſtringent medicines. The diet muſt be <lb/>cool, but nouriſhing, conſiſting chiefly of
          bread, milk, cool- <lb/>ing vegetables, and broths. The drink may be chalybeate
          <lb/>water, orange whey, decoctions or infuſions of the aſtringent <lb/>and mucilaginous
          plants, as the tormentil root, biſtort, the <lb/>marſh-mallow roots, &amp;c. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Peruvian bark is likewiſe proper in this caſe, both as <lb/>a ſtrengthener and
          aſtringent: half a drachm of it may be <lb/>taken in a glaſs of red wine, ſharpened with a
          few drops of <lb/>the elixir of vitriol, three or four times a-day. </p>
        <pb n="537"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The bleeding piles are ſometimes periodical, and return <lb/>regularly once a month,
          or once in three weeks. In this <lb/>caſe, they are always to be conſidered as a ſalutary
          diſcharge, <lb/>and by no means to be ſtopped. Some have entirely ruined <lb/>their health
          by ſtopping a periodical diſcharge of blood from <lb/>the hœmorrhodial veins. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In the <hi rend="italic">blind piles</hi>, bleeding is generally of uſe. The diet
          <lb/>muſt be light and thin, and the drink cool and diluting. <lb/>It is Iikewiſe
          neceſſary that the body be kept gently open. <lb/>This may be done by ſmall doſes of the
          flowers of brimſtone <lb/>and cream of tartar. They may be mixed in equal quantities,
          <lb/>and a tea-ſpoonful taken two or three times a-day, or oftener <lb/>if neceſſary. Or
          an ounce of the flowers of brimſtone, and half <lb/>an ounce of purified nitre, may be
          mixed with three or four <lb/>ounces of the lenitive electuary, and a tea-ſpoonful of it
          ta- <lb/>ken three or four times a-day. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Various ointments, and other external applications, are <lb/>recommended in the
          piles; but I do not remember to have <lb/>ſeen any effects from theſe worth mentioning.
          Their prin- <lb/>cipal uſe is to keep the part moiſt, which may be done as <lb/>well by a
          ſoft poultice, or an emollient cataplaſm. When <lb/>the pain, however, is very great, a
          liniment made of two <lb/>ounces of emollient ointment, and half an ounce of liquid
          <lb/>laudanum, beat up with the yolk of an egg, maybe ap- <lb/>plied. <hi rend="italic"
            >Tiſſot</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Buchan</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic align-center space">
          <lb/>The Quinſey, or Inflammation of the Throat. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In general, it proceeds from the ſame cauſes as other in- <lb/>flammatory diſorders,
            <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> an obſtructed perſpiration, or <lb/>whatever heats or
          inflames the blood. An inflammation of <lb/>the throat is often occaſioned by omitting
          ſome part of the <lb/>covering uſually worn about the neck, by drinking cold li- <lb/>quor
          when the body is warm, by riding or walking againſt a <lb/>cold northerly wind, or any
          thing that greatly cools the <lb/>throat, and parts adjacent. It may likewiſe proceed from
          <lb/>the neglect of bleeding, purging, or any other cuſtomary <lb/>evacuation. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The inflammation of the throat is evident from inſpection, <lb/>the parts appearing
          red and ſwelled; beſides, the patient <lb/>complains of pain in ſwallowing. His pulſe is
          quick and <lb/>hard, with other ſymptoms of a fever. If blood be let, it is <lb/>generally
          covered with a tough coat of a whitiſh colour, and <pb n="538"/>
          <lb/>the patient ſpits a tough phlegm. As the ſwelling and in- <lb/>flammation increaſe,
          the breathing and ſwallowing become <lb/>more difficult; the pain affects the ears; the
          eyes generally <lb/>appear red, and the face ſwells. The patient is often obliged <lb/>to
          keep himſelf in an erect poſture, being in danger of ſuffo- <lb/>cation; there is a
          conſtant nauſea, or inclination to vomit, <lb/>and the drink, inſtead of paſſing into the
          ſtomach, is often <lb/>returned by the noſe. The patient is frequently ſtarved at
          <lb/>laſt, merely from an inability to ſwallow any kind of food. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When the breathing is laborious, with ſtraitneſs of breaſt, <lb/>and anxiety, the
          danger is great. Though the pain in ſwal- <lb/>lowing be very great, yet while the patient
          breathes eaſy, <lb/>there is not ſo much danger. An external ſwelling is no un-
          <lb/>favourable symptom; but if it ſuddenly falls, and the diſeaſe <lb/>affects the
          breaſt, the danger is very great. When a quinſey <lb/>is the conſequence of ſome other
          diſeaſe, which has already <lb/>weakened the patient, his ſituation is dangerous. A
          frothing <lb/>at the mouth, with a ſwelled tongue, a pale, ghaſtly counte- <lb/>nance, and
          coldneſs of the extremities, are fatal ſymptoms. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is highly neceſſary that the patient be kept eaſy and <lb/>quiet. Violent
          affections of the mind, or great efforts of the <lb/>body, may prove fatal. He ſhould
          never even attempt to <lb/>ſpeak but in a low voice. Such a degree of warmth as to
          <lb/>promote a conſtant, gentle ſweat, is proper. When the pa- <lb/>tient is in bed, his
          head ought to be raiſed a little higher than <lb/>uſual. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is peculiarly necceſſary that the neck be kept warm; for <lb/>which purpoſe
          ſeveral folds of ſoft flannel may be wrapped <lb/>round it. That alone will often remove a
          ſlight com- <lb/>plaint of the throat, eſpecially if applied in due time. <lb/>We cannot
          here omit obſerving the propriety of a cuſtom <lb/>which prevails among the peaſants of
          this country:—When <lb/>they feel any uneaſineſs of the throat, they wrap a ſtocking
          <lb/>about it all night. So effectual is this remedy, that in many <lb/>places it paſſes
          for a charm, and the ſtocking is applied with <lb/>particular ceremonies. The cuſtom,
          however, is undoubt- <lb/>edly a good one, and ſhould never be neglected. When the
          <lb/>throat has been thus wrapped up all night, it muſt not be ex- <lb/>poſed to the cold
          air through the day, but a handkerchief, or <lb/>a piece of flannel kept about it till the
          inflammation be re- <lb/>moved. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The jelly of black currants is a medicine very much in <lb/>eſteem for complaints of
          the throat; and indeed it is of ſome <pb n="539"/>
          <lb/>uſe. It ſhould be almoſt conſtantly kept in the mouth, and <lb/>ſwallowed down
          leiſurely. It may likewiſe be mixed in the <lb/>patient's drink, or taken any other way.
          When it cannot <lb/>be obtained, the jelly of red currants, or of mulberries, may <lb/>be
          uſed in its ſtead. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Gargles for the throat are very beneficial. They may be <lb/>made of ſage tea, with a
          little vinegar and honey, or by add- <lb/>ing to half an Engliſh pint of the pectoral
          decoction, two or <lb/>three ſpoonfuls of honey, and the ſame quantity of currant
          <lb/>jelly. This may be uſed three or four times a day; and if <lb/>the patient be
          troubled with tough viſcid phlegm, the gargle <lb/>may be rendered more ſharp and
          cleanſing, by adding to it a <lb/>tea-ſpoonful of the ſpirit of <hi rend="italic">ſal
            ammoniac</hi>. Some recommend <lb/>gargles made of a decoction of the leaves or bark of
          the black- <lb/>berry buſh; but where the jelly can be had, this is unne- <lb/>ceſſary. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>An inflammation of the throat being a moſt acute and dan- <lb/>gerous diſtemper,
          which ſometimes takes off the patient very <lb/>ſuddenly, it will be proper, as ſoon as
          the ſymptoms appear, <lb/>to bleed in the arm, or rather in the jugular vein, and to re-
          <lb/>peat the operation as circumſtances require. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It ſometimes happens, before the ulcer breaks, that the <lb/>ſwelling is ſo great, as
          entirely to prevent any thing from <lb/>getting down into the ſtomach. In this caſe the
          patient muſt <lb/>inevitably periſh, unleſs he can be ſupported in ſome other <lb/>way.
          This can only be done by nouriſhing clyſters of broth, <lb/>or gruel, with milk, &amp;c.
          Patients have often been ſupported <lb/>by theſe for ſeveral days, till the tumour has
          broke; and af- <lb/>terwards they have recovered. <hi rend="italic">Huxham</hi>. <hi
            rend="italic">Fothergil</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="25"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
