<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Taylor: Mrs. Taylor's family companion</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName>Margaret Taylor</persName>
            </author>
            <title type="main">Mrs. Taylor's family companion; or the whole art of cookery
              display'd, in the newest and most easy method, being a collection of receipts to set
              out a table cheap, Under the following Heads: Boiling Roasting Frying Broiling Stewing
              Hashing Baking Ragouts Fricassees Made-Dishes Sauces Soups Puddings Pies Tarts Cakes
              Cheesecakes Custards Syllabues Creams Jellis Pickling Preserving Candying Collaring
              Potting Drying, &amp;c. To which are added, instructions for marketing, sundry bills
              of fare, Directions for Clear-Starching, The Lady's Toilet, or Art of Preserving
              Beauty, &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c. The whole calculated to assist the prudent mistress
              and her servant, in providing the cheapest and most elegant Set of Dishes in the
              various Departments of Cookery. By Mrs. Margaret Taylor, Late Cook from the Crown and
              Anchor.</title>
            <edition n="1"/>
            <idno type="ESTC">T222842</idno>
            <ptr type="ESTC-link" target="http://estc.bl.uk/T222842"/>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for W. Lane, Leadenhall-Street, and sold by all other
                  booksellers.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1795</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
              <measure type="count" commodity="front" unit="page" quantity="2"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="body" unit="page" quantity="164"/>
              <measure type="count" commodity="back" unit="page" quantity="2"/>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <orgName type="library">British Library</orgName>
            <idno type="ECCO">CW3309006130</idno>
            <idno type="TCP">K130910.000 </idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Recipe collections"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <front>
      <div>
        <figure>
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>The Corporation Feaſt OR <unclear>#####</unclear> the Roaſt Beef of Old England.
          </head>
        </figure>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="149"/>
      <div type="part">
        <pb xml:id="page_144" n="150"/>
        <head rend="size(1.25) align-center space">
          <lb/>RECEIPTS in PHYSIC. </head>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A good Electuary for an Aſthma. </head>
          <p rend="space">
            <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>AKE four cloves of garlic, roaſt them till <lb/>they are
            ſoft; then bruiſe out the pulp, and <lb/>put it into ſix ſpoonfuls of honey, two
            ſpoonfuls of <lb/>the powder of elecampane, liquorice, anniſeeds, <lb/>and
            coriander-ſeeds, all finely powdered, of each <lb/>one ſpoonful and a half; mix all well
            together, and <lb/>take the bigneſs of a nutmeg morning and night. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Bolus for an Aſthma. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>You muſt take a dram of ſperma-ceti, half a <lb/>ſcruple of lac-ſulphuris, volatile
            ſalt of amber five <lb/>grains, conſerve of hips one ſcruple, balſam of Peru <lb/>ten
            drops, and ſyrup of ſaffron ſufficient to make a <lb/>bolus. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Doſe for an Ague. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Give as much Virginia ſnake-root, dried and <lb/>powdered, as will lie upon a
            ſhilling, in a glaſs of <lb/>ſherry or ſack, juſt before the cold fit begins; uſe
            <lb/>this two or three times till the ague is gone. </p>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_145" n="151"/>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>To prevent a Relapſe of the Apoplexy. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Once every third day, at about four o'clock in <lb/>the morning, take two ſcruples
            of Pilla Cochia the <lb/>greater, and ſleep after them; repeat it ſix times. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A ſneezing Powder for the Apoplexy. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Take one dram of the root of white hellebore, <lb/>two drams of the flowers of
            lilies of the valley; <lb/>mix, and reduce them to a powder, and blow it up <lb/>the
            noſtrils with a quill. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>The following Gliſter is good in an Apoplexy, <lb/>Lethargy, Coma, or Palſy. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Get pellitory of Spain, half an ounce; coloquin- <lb/>tida (tied up in a rag, or
            elſe it will gripe) half a <lb/>dram; rue, two handfuls; boil it in water to twelve
            <lb/>ounces; ſtrain it, and add three ounces of crocus <lb/>metallorum; tincture of
            caſtor, half an ounce; <lb/>ſalt gem, and oil of amber, of each two drams, and <lb/>mix
            all together. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>If it ſtay not with the patient, it muſt be repeat- <lb/>ed; for it is no unuſual
            thing in theſe caſes for <lb/>gliſters to ſlip away preſently, by reaſon that the
            <lb/>inteſtines having their fibres benumbed, and para- <lb/>lytically relaxed, loſe
            their retentive faculty. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Drink for any Inward Bruiſe or Wound. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Take one handful of each of the following herbs, <lb/>viz. wormwood, comfrey,
            throatwort, wood betony, <lb/>plantane, mugwort, bonewort, ſcabious, avens, wild
            <lb/>honey-ſuckle, agrimony, bramble-buds, cinquefoil, <lb/>ſpearmint, ſanicle,
            whitebottle, ribwort, daiſy-roots, <lb/>dandelion, bugloſs, and hauthorn-buds: Put to
            theſe <lb/>herbs two quarts of white-wine, and a gallon of <pb xml:id="page_146" n="152"/>
            <lb/>running water, and boil it till it is half waſted; <lb/>then ſtrain it, and add to
            it a quart of honey; let <lb/>that boil in the liquor ſome time: When it is cold,
            <lb/>bottle it very cloſe, and keep it for uſe. It will <lb/>keep for many years, and is
            neceſſary for all fami- <lb/>lies; two or three ſpoonfuls of it to be taken morning
            <lb/>and night. It is really good for fores, wounds, and <lb/>hurts, new or old, in men,
            women, or children: <lb/>Its virtues of that kind are too long to mention. <lb/>It has
            broken and brought away inward impoſthumes. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A certain Cure for the Bite of a Mad Dog, by <lb/>Dr. Mead. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Let the patient be blooded at the arm nine or <lb/>ten ounces: Then take of the
            herb called in Latin, <lb/>Lichen Cereneus Terreſtris, in Engliſh, Aſh-colour'd
            <lb/>Ground Liverwort, cleaned, dried, and powdered, <lb/>half an ounce; of black pepper
            powdered, two <lb/>drams. Mix theſe well together, and divide the <lb/>powder into four
            doſes, one of which muſt be taken <lb/>every morning faſting, for four mornings ſucceſ-
            <lb/>ſively, in half a pint of cow's milk warm. After <lb/>theſe four doſes are taken,
            the patient muſt go into <lb/>the cold-bath, or a cold ſpring or river, every morn-
            <lb/>ing faſting, for a month: He muſt be dipt all over, <lb/>but not ſtay in (with his
            head above water) longer <lb/>than half an minute, if the water be very cold. <lb/>After
            this he muſt go in three times a week for a <lb/>fortnight longer. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>N. B. The Lichen is a very common herb, and <lb/>grows generally in ſandy and
            barren ſoils all over <lb/>England. The right time to gather them is in the <lb/>months
            of October or November. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Some adviſe, that as ſoon as poſſibly it can be <lb/>done, the wound may be burnt
            with a hot iron; by <lb/>which, part of the venom may be exhaled, and the <lb/>
            <gap reason="illegible"/> prevented from ſpreading itſelf any farther, <pb
              xml:id="page_147" n="153"/>
            <lb/>which good effect is very likely to follow from the <lb/>purſing up the ſmall
            veſſels, and the coagulation of <lb/>the adjacent fluids. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Plaiſter for the Breaſt, to diſſolve curdled Milk. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Take ſperma-ceti, one ounce; white wax, two <lb/>ounces; galbanum, ſtrained with
            vinegar, half an <lb/>ounce; oil of elder, as much as will be ſufficient to <lb/>make a
            plaiſter; it is proper for all tumours of the <lb/>breaſt, occaſioned by the curdling of
            the milk, and <lb/>is good in white ſoft ſwellings, or the evil in the <lb/>breaſt, or
            any hard tumour in any part of the body. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Plaiſter to break a Sore-breaſt. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Seeth a lily-root and piece of leaven in milk <lb/>till the root be ſoft; lay it
            plaiſter-wiſe to the part, <lb/>morning and evening, as hot as you can bear it. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Cerecloth for Swellings in the Breaſt. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Make a cerecloth of oil of linſeed and yellow <lb/>wax, and apply it to the part,
            firſt anointing it with <lb/>linſeed-oil. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To heal a Breaſt when broken. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Take a good handful of parſley, and a good ſlice <lb/>of the fat of bacon, and
            ſtamp them together; put <lb/>to it the yolk of an egg, and ſpread it plaiſter-wiſe
            <lb/>upon a cloth, and lay it upon the breaſt. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>An excellent and tried Remedy for Burns. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Take two parts of the oil of walnuts, and one of <lb/>honey; mix them well together
            over a gentle fire, <lb/>and when they are thoroughly incorporated, dip a <lb/>feather
            in the mixture, and anoint therewith the <pb xml:id="page_148" n="154"/>
            <lb/>part affected, ſo as the ointment may touch it im- <lb/>mediately, and then ſtrew
            on it ſome powder of <lb/>ceterach, or ſpleen-wort, and keep the part quiet, <lb/>and
            defend it from the air. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For Burns and Stenching of Blood. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>For ſtenching of blood, there are but few medi- <lb/>cines which exceed the
            colcother <unclear>o</unclear>f vitriol, whether <lb/>waſhed and freed from its ſalt, or
            not waſhed. It <lb/>is but a common thing, but will do more than a <lb/>thouſand much
            more enobled. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Family Ointment for Chilblains, Kibes, <lb/>Whitloes, Felons, &amp;c. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Take May butter, ſeven ounces; wax, reſin, of <lb/>each four ounces; crude honey,
            ten drams; wheat <lb/>flour, ſix drams: Mix them, and ſpread it upon <lb/>leather; apply
            it to the part affected; change it <lb/>twice a day till it begins to grow well. It alſo
            <lb/>warms, looſens, diſcuſſes, cleans, <unclear>r</unclear>ipens, and digeſts, <lb/>and
            is of known ſervice in the ſpeedy curing of <lb/>felons and whitloes in the fingers; it
            is of ſingular <lb/>uſe to abate inflammations, and bring ſwellings to <lb/>ripeneſs and
            maturity. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For the Cholic. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Slice one ounce of the very beſt rhubarb you can <lb/>get into a quart of ſack; let
            it infuſe twelve hours <lb/>at leaſt; then drink four large ſpoonfuls, and fill
            <lb/>your bottle up again: Drink this quantity once a <lb/>day, for ſix weeks or two
            months, at leaſt. When <lb/>your rhubarb has loſt its virtue, you muſt put freſh.
            <lb/>This has cured ſome people, who could not find eaſe <lb/>in opiates, nor the Bath;
            it muſt be conſtantly con- <lb/>tinued till the bowels and blood are ſtrengthened:
            <lb/>It has done ſuch marvellous cures, even where lau- <pb xml:id="page_149" n="155"/>
            <lb/>danum has failed, that it cannot be ſufficiently <lb/>commended. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>An infallible Cure for a Conſumption. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Take half a pound of raiſins of the ſun ſtoned, a <lb/>quarter of a pound of figs,
            a quarter of a pound of <lb/><unclear>ho</unclear>ney, half an ounce of Lucatella's
            balſam, half an <lb/>ouncce of powder of ſteel, half an ounce of flour of
              <lb/><unclear>ele</unclear>campane, a grated nutmeg, one pound of double-
              <lb/><unclear>re</unclear>fined ſugar, pounded: Shred and pound all theſe
              <lb/><unclear>to</unclear>gether in a ſtone mortar; pour into it a pint of
              <lb/><unclear>sal</unclear>lad oil by degrees; eat a bit of it four times a
              <lb/><unclear>day</unclear>, the bigneſs of a nutmeg; every morning drink
              <lb/><unclear>a g</unclear>laſs of old Malaga ſack, with the yolk of a new- <lb/>
            <gap reason="illegible"/>d egg, and as much flour of brimſtone as will lie
              <lb/><unclear>up</unclear>on a ſix-pence; the next morning as much flour
              <lb/><unclear>of</unclear> elecampane, alternately. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To cure a Cough and Shortneſs of Breath. </head>
          <p rend="indent" n="3">
            <lb/>Take elecampane-roots, boil them very tender, <lb/>
            <gap reason="illegible"/> pulp them fine through a ſieve; take their
              <lb/><unclear>we</unclear>ight in the pulp of coddled pippins; if you have
              <lb/><unclear>a p</unclear>ound weight of both together, boil it in a pint
              <lb/><unclear>and</unclear> half of clarified honey for half an hour; then
              <lb/><unclear>tak</unclear>e one ounce of powder of liquorice, and as much
              <lb/><unclear>pow</unclear>der of anniſeeds; mix all well together, and
              <lb/><unclear>tak</unclear>e a dram morning and night, and in the after- <lb/>noon. It
            is an excellent medicine in an aſthma. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For a Hooping Cough, very good. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>When you have got a quart of ſpring-water, put <lb/><unclear>in</unclear> it a
            large handful of chin-cups that grow upon <lb/>
            <gap reason="illegible"/>, and a large handful of unſet hyſſop; boil it <lb/>
            <gap reason="illegible"/> pint, ſtrain it off, and ſweeten it with ſugar- <lb/>
            <gap reason="illegible"/>. Let the child, as oft as it coughs, take two
              <lb/><unclear>ſpoo</unclear>nfuls at a time. </p>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_150" n="156"/>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>An excellent Powder for Convulſion Fits. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Get two drams of piony roots; miſletoe of the <lb/>oak, one dram; prepared pearl,
            white amber pre- <lb/>pared, and coral prepared, of each half a dram<unclear>;</unclear>
            <lb/>bezoar, two grains, and five leaves of gold; make <lb/>all theſe into a very fine
            powder, and give as much <lb/>of it as will lie on a three-pence to a child of a
            <lb/>month old, and proportionable to a bigger; mix <lb/>it up with a ſpoonful of
            black-cherry water, which <lb/>ſweeten with the ſyrup of black cherries: Take it
            <lb/>three days together, at every change of the moon <lb/>to prevent returns. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Cure for the Cramp. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Take a handful of the herb called perriwinkle <gap reason="illegible"/>
            <lb/>ſome of it bears a blue flower, and ſome white <gap reason="illegible"/>
            <lb/>and alſo take a good handful of roſemary tops, p<unclear>ut</unclear>
            <lb/>them into a pewter diſh, and ſet them upon coals <gap reason="illegible"/>
            <lb/>dry them, and turn them very often, and when they <lb/>are very hot, lay them upon
            the place that is <gap reason="illegible"/>
            <lb/>taken with the cramp, and bind a cloth upon the <gap reason="illegible"/>
            <lb/>when you go to bed, and this will help you; take <gap reason="illegible"/>
            <lb/>off in the morning, and lay on freſh at night. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A good Remedy for the Corns. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Get the yeaſt of beer, not ale, and ſpreading <gap reason="illegible"/>
            <lb/>upon a linen rag, or other cloth, apply it to t<unclear>he</unclear>
            <lb/>part affected, renewing it once every day. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>An excellent Purging Ale for the Dropſy. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Sena, four ounces; ſaſſafras and tartar, of ea<unclear>ch</unclear>
            <lb/>two ounces; jalap and liquorice, of each one oun<unclear>ce;</unclear>
            <lb/>rhubarb, coriander, and anniſeed, of each o<unclear>ne</unclear>
            <lb/>ounce; polypodium, eight ounces; broom aſh<unclear>es</unclear>
            <lb/>one quart, and one ounce of cloves; put all i<unclear>n a</unclear>
            <pb xml:id="page_151" n="157"/>
            <lb/>bag, with ſome little weight to ſink it: Take ſca- <lb/>bious and agrimony, of each
            three handfuls; of <lb/>the roots of daneſwort, one handful; raiſins of the <lb/>ſun
            ſtoned, one pound, with a little ginger: Put <lb/>theſe ingredients into ſweet ale-wort,
            when you put <lb/>in your hops, and let all boil together half an hour; <lb/>then pour
            it ſcalding hot on your bag of drugs: <lb/>When it is cold enough, ſet it to work with
            yeaſt: <lb/>When it has done working, ſtop it up for twelve <lb/>days, or a fortnight:
            Hang the bag of drugs in <lb/>the veſſel. Drink a large glaſs of this in the
            <lb/>morning, and at four in the afternoon, unleſs you <lb/>find it works too much at
            firſt; if ſo, leſſen your <lb/>doſe; but take it daily, till you have taken all. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>Another Medicine for the Dropſy. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Take broom, and burn it by itſelf in a clean <lb/>oven, ſhift the aſhes from the
            ſtalks and coals that <lb/>are not quite conſumed, and put two full pounds of <lb/>theſe
            aſhes into a quart bottle; pour on old hock <lb/>till the bottle is up to the neck; take
            care it is not <lb/>too full; if it has no room to ferment, it will be apt <lb/>to ſplit
            the bottle: Digeſt it in hot aſhes by the fire, <lb/>or in the ſun, and ſhake it often;
            when it has ſtood <lb/>three or four days, pour off a quart of the clear lye; <lb/>if it
            is perfectly fine, decant again and again till it <lb/>is ſo; fill up your bottle again
            with hock, and do <lb/>as before, till the ſtrength of the aſhes be out. <lb/>Drink this
            firſt, and at four or five in the afternoon; <lb/>continue it for ſome time, and it will
            carry off the <lb/>dropſical humours. While you take it, let the meat <lb/>you eat be
            dry roaſted, and your drink ſtrong ale or <lb/>wine. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To cure Deafneſs. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Take an equal quantity of good Hungary water, <lb/>and oil of bitter almonds; beat
            them together, and <pb xml:id="page_152" n="158"/>
            <lb/>drop three drops in the ears going to bed; ſtop them <lb/>with black
              <unclear>wo</unclear>ol, and repeat this nine nights at leaſt. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For a Pain in the Ear. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Get the juice of mountain ſage, oil of fennel, <lb/>oil of bitter almonds, and oil
            of olives, an equal <lb/>quantity of each, and mix them well
              together<unclear>;</unclear>
            <lb/>drop into the pained ear three drops for three nigh<unclear>ts</unclear>. <lb/>It
            will eaſe and draw out any impoſthume, if that <lb/>be the cauſe. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For an Earwig having got into the Ear. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Get rue, and beat it in a mortar; then ſtrain o<unclear>ff</unclear>
            <lb/>the juice, and put it into the ear; then lie do<unclear>wn</unclear>
            <lb/>to reſt on the contrary ear, and when you awake <lb/>the juice will come out, and
            the ear-wig will <unclear>be</unclear>
            <lb/>dead. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>The juice of wormwood, of ſouthernwood, a<unclear>nd</unclear>
            <lb/>rue, an equal quantity put into the ear, will all <lb/>kill any vermin that has got
            into it. The ſtems <unclear>of</unclear>
            <lb/>coffee have often relieved a deafneſs that has been <lb/>occaſioned by the wax
            becoming too hard, which <lb/>they will ſoften and ſet free. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>Dr. Willis's Specific for the Epilepſy. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Take the roots of male piony, dried and powder- <lb/>ed, from one dram to two or
            three twice a day, <gap reason="illegible"/>
            <lb/>the following tincture: </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Take leaves of miſleto of the oak, two drams, <lb/>piony roots ſliced, half an
            ounce; caſtor, a dram<unclear>;</unclear>
            <lb/>let them be put in a cloſe veſſel with betony water <lb/>or ſimple water and
            white-wine, of each one pound<unclear>;</unclear>
            <lb/>ſalt of miſleto of the oak, or the common miſleto <lb/>two drams; digeſt them in a
            cloſe veſſel, in a ſand <lb/>heat for two days. Take three ounces with the <lb/>powder
            above-mentioned. </p>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_153" n="159"/>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Draught for the Epilepſy. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Get powder of wild valerian root, one dram and <lb/>a half; penny-royal water, and
            black-cherry water, <lb/>of each one ounce and a half; ſyrup of pionies, <lb/>two drams;
            mix them, and make a draught. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A Drink for the King's Evil and Cancer. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Take guaiacum, one ounce; ſaſſafras, ſarſapa- <lb/>rilla, ſharp-pointed dock, and
            daiſy-roots, of each <lb/>half an ounce; arch-angel flowers, and millepedes, <lb/>of
            each two large ſpoonfuls; ground-ivy, and herb- <lb/>Robert, of each one handful: Bruiſe
            and ſhred all <lb/>theſe ingredients, and put them to ſteep one night in <lb/>three
            pints of good clear new ale; ſtrain it, and <lb/>drink no other drink for ſix weeks,
            ſpring and fall. <lb/>You may do a larger quantity at a time for man or <lb/>woman; but
            you muſt not infuſe too much at a <lb/>time, becauſe the herbs are apt to change it; at
            <lb/>the ſame time, if the ſwellings are painful, anoint <lb/>with juice of rue,
            prepared as follows: </p>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Take two ſpoonfuls of juice of rue, as much ſal- <lb/>lad-oil, beat them well
            together; then ſet it over <lb/>the fire, and let it boil ſlowly half an hour; add
            <lb/>two ounces of bees-wax, let it boil a little with <lb/>this: Pour it out, and keep
            it cloſe covered. It is <lb/>an incomparable ointment to uſe all the time you <lb/>take
            the diet-drink. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>The red Powders for Fevers, Small-Pox, or <lb/>Surſeits. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Take of carduus, rue, red ſage, lilies of the val- <lb/>ley, tormentil, pimpernel,
            dragon, betony, angeli- <lb/>ca, cabious, ſpeedwell, of each one handful; worm- <pb
              xml:id="page_156" n="160"/>
            <lb/>wood, half a handful; agrimony, verum, of each <lb/>a quarter of a handful: Shred
            the herbs very ſmall, <lb/>and infuſe them in two quarts of white-wine, in a <lb/>jug,
            which you muſt ſtop very cloſe, and ſet nine <lb/>days in the ſun: Then ſtrain the wine
            from the <lb/>herbs, and infuſe the ſame quantity of freſh herbs in <lb/>the ſame wine;
            let it ſtand as before nine days <lb/>more: Then take a pound of bole-armoniac, finely
            <lb/>powdered, and put as much of the wine (after it is <lb/>a ſecond time preſſed out)
            as the powder will take <lb/>up, and ſet it in the ſun to dry; and as it dries up,
            <lb/>put in more of the wine, ſtirring it two or three <lb/>times a day till all the
            wine is dried up in the <lb/>powder, ſo as to be fit to work like paſte: Then <lb/>put
            to it of diacodium and mithridate, one ounce <lb/>each; half an ounce of cochineal; of
            powder of <lb/>red coral and prepared ſaffron, an ounce each; forty <lb/>grains of
            bezoar; of powder of crabs-eyes, burnt <lb/>hartſhorn, and prepared pearl, an ounce
            each: <lb/>Mix theſe in the laſt wetting, and work them all to- <lb/>gether; make them
            into balls, when well mixed, <lb/>and dry them in the ſun. Take forty or fifty grains
            <lb/>of this for a doſe. Drink mace ale after it. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A cooling Drink in a Fever or Pleuriſy. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Put an ounce of pearl-barley into three pints of <lb/>water, ſhift it twice; beat
            half an ounce of almonds, <lb/>with a bit of lemon-peel, and a ſpoonful or two of
            <lb/>the water; when they are very fine, waſh the al- <lb/>mond-milk through your ſieve,
            with three pints of <lb/>barley-water; in the laſt boiling of this you may <lb/>put
            melon-ſeeds and pumpion-ſeeds, of each half an <lb/>ounce; white poppy-ſeeds, half a
            dram; when theſe <lb/>are well boiled, mix the liquor with the almonds, <lb/>and ſtrain
            all; ſweeten it with ſyrup of lemons for a <lb/>fever, or ſyrup of maiden-hair, and
            drink four <lb/>ounces every three or four hours. </p>
        </div>
        <pb xml:id="page_157" n="161"/>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A ſpeedy Remedy for Fits of Vomiting. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Having got a large nutmeg, grate one half of <lb/>it, and toaſt the flat ſide of
            the other 'till the oily <lb/>part begins to ſweat out; then clap it to the pit of
            <lb/>the patient's ſtomach as hot as can be endured, and <lb/>keep it on whilſt it
            continues warm, and then, if <lb/>need be, put on another. This is recommended <lb/>by
            the famous Mr. Boyle. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To ſtop a Vomiting. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Take lemon-juice, half an ounce; ſalt of worm- <lb/>wood a ſcruple; and a little
            white ſugar: Mix, and <lb/>make a Draught, to be repeated two or three times <lb/>a day.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To ſtop a Vomiting, and ſtrengthen the Stomach. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Take ſpearmint, barley, and cinnamon waters, <lb/>of each three ounces; plegue
            water, two ounces; <lb/>ſalt of wormwood, a dram; lemon-juice, one ounce; <lb/>three
            leave of gold; confection of hyacinth, two <lb/>drams; ſyrup of red poppies, an ounce
            and a half: <lb/>Mix, and give four ſpoonfuls every four hours, <lb/>ſhaking the phial.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>For Vomiting and violent Looſeneſs in a Child. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Bleed three times, and apply a cupping-glaſs <lb/>to the navel. Take the red tops
            of gil-go-by-the- <lb/>ground, dry them, and mix them with honey: It <lb/>is good for
            any hoarſeneſs: The tops are to be had <lb/>in May, June, or July. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>A good Powder for Worms. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Take an ounce of worm-ſeed, and half an ounce <lb/>of rhubarb, beat both to a fine
            powder, and take a <pb xml:id="page_158" n="162"/>
            <lb/>quarter of an ounce of prepared coral; mix all <lb/>three together, and let the
            child take as much of <lb/>this as will lie on a ſhilling, for three mornings
            <lb/>together, drinking a ſmall glaſs of warm ale after <lb/>each doſe. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>A Receipt to cure Worms. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Bruiſe a pound of worm-ſeed, and put it into a <lb/><choice>
              <corr>large</corr>
              <sic>arge</sic>
            </choice> ſtill of ſpearmint, and draw it off as long as <lb/>it runs good: Let the
            child drink three ſpoonfuls <lb/>of this nine mornings running. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center space">
            <lb/>To ſtanch Blood in a Wound. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>Take an ounce of copperaſs, made into fine pow- <lb/>der, and half an ounce of bole
            armoniac powdered, <lb/>and mingle them together, and caſt ſome of this <lb/>powder into
            the wound, and it will ſtaunch the <lb/>blood. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">
          <head rend="italic align-center">
            <lb/>For Wounds in the Head. </head>
          <p rend="indent space">
            <lb/>If theſe are attended with contuſion, it may be <lb/>proper to ſhave the adjoining
            parts. Some make <lb/>uſe only of warm wine, oil, vinegar, or oxycrate, <lb/>to
            embrocate them, or rub in. If the wound be <lb/>recent, ſimple, and made by a ſharp
            inſtrument, <lb/>it may be immediately ſtitched up, and covered <lb/>with Emplaſtr. de
            Minio; and this method is <lb/>ſometimes ſucceſsful, even tho' the skull itſelf be
            <lb/>cut, provided no ill ſymptoms indicate a contrary <lb/>method. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <gap reason="sampling" unit="pages" quantity="2"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
