<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Thomson: The good Effects of small Doses of Emeticks and
          Purgatives</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Alexander Thomson</persName>
            </author>
            <title>VI. The good Effects of small Doses of Emeticks and Purgatives frequently
              repeated; by Dr. ALEXANDER THOMSON Physician at Montrose.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical essays and observations, published by a society in Edinburgh</title>
            <author>Philosophical Society of Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: printed by W. and T. Ruddimans, for Messrs. Hamilton and
                  Balfour, Booksellers</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1747</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">5</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">75-77</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108729041</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T132162</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ1_v5_0075">
    <body>
      <pb n="75"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VI.</hi> The good Effects of ſmall Doſes of <hi rend="roman"
          >Emeticks</hi>
        <lb/>and <hi rend="roman">Purgatives</hi> frequently repeated; by Dr. <lb/><hi rend="sc"
          >Alexander Thomson</hi> Phyſician at <hi rend="roman">Mon- <lb/>troſe</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">I</hi>N various Indigeſtions in the Stomach, and <lb/>Fluxions of
        degenerated Humours to the <lb/>chylopoietick Organs, as alſo in the Foulneſſes <lb/>of the
        Lungs from a ſimple Cough or <hi rend="italic">Aſthma</hi>
        <lb/>thro' their whole Train of morbid Conſequen- <lb/>ces, where Emetics and Purgatives
        given in the <lb/>common full Doſes have done no Service, I <lb/>have often found the ſame
        Medicines taken fre- <lb/>quently in ſmall Doſes, of the greateſt Benefit, <lb/>without
        being attended with any Inconveni- <lb/>ence. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The two Medicines I have generally made <lb/>Uſe of in this Way are the <hi
          rend="italic">Emetic Wine</hi> among <lb/>the Emetics, and the <hi rend="italic">Tincture
          of Hiera picra</hi>, <lb/>of the Claſs of Purgatives. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The general Rule I obſerve in ordering theſe <lb/>Medicines, is to divide into a Number
        of ſmall <lb/>Doſes as much of either of the Medicines as <lb/>would be preſcribed to the
        Patient for a full <lb/>Doſe; all which ſmall Doſes are to be taken <lb/>with proper
        Intervals in twenty-four Hours, <lb/>mixed with any proper Vehicle ſuited to the <lb/>Nature
        of the Diſeaſe. I continue this Method <lb/>daily. If the Medicine occaſions <hi
          rend="italic">Nauſea</hi>, <unclear>puk</unclear>- <lb/>ing or Grips, or if the Patient
        chuſes ſome In- <lb/>termiſſion, I forbear to give them a Day. </p>
      <pb n="76"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To explain my Meanings, I ſhall mention <lb/>two or three of the many Caſes I have
        treated <lb/>in this Manner. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A Girl between nine and ten Years of Age <lb/>uſed toward Night, and ſometimes in the
        <lb/>Morning, to throw up a viſcid, ropy Phlegm <lb/>or Mucus from her Stomach and from her
        <lb/>Lungs; her Fleſh became flabby, and her <lb/>whole Body weak and in Diſorder. She got
        <lb/>ſometimes the Emetic and at other Times the <lb/>Purgative in the Manner deſcribed
        above, which <lb/>cured her; and having the ſame good Effect in <lb/>ſeveral Relapſes,
        brought her at laſt to perfect <lb/>Health, which ſhe has now enjoyed a great ma- <lb/>ny
        Years. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A poor Man coughing mixt ulcerous Matter, <lb/>and emaciated to a great Degree with the
        hectic <lb/>Symptoms, had <hi rend="italic">ſix Drachms</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Emetic
          Wine</hi>
        <lb/>mixed with Lib. 2. <hi rend="italic">Infuſ. Succ. Liquor. nigr.</hi>
        <lb/>given him, which he drank daily, in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Nychthemeron</hi>. He
        had at Times a tranſient <lb/><hi rend="italic">Nauſea</hi>, puked and expectorated
        plentifully. <lb/>After he was accuſtomed ſome Days to his Me- <lb/>dicine, the <hi
          rend="italic">Nauſea</hi> ceaſed, and the Expectora- <lb/>tion decreaſed. I increaſed his
        daily Doſe of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Emetic Wine</hi> to an Ounce, intermitting a Day
        <lb/>ſometimes. The purulent Expectoration gra- <lb/>dually went off, and he recovered. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A Lady of a bad Habit of Body and low Spi- <lb/>rits had long laboured under ropy
        variegated <lb/>Vomitings in the Mornings, with Expectora- <lb/><unclear>tive</unclear>
        ſuited thereto. After I had treated her <lb/>with Emetics, Purgatives and other Medicines
        <lb/>in the ordinary Way to little Purpoſe, I gave <lb/>her in twenty-four Hours different
        ſmall Doſes <pb n="77"/>
        <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Infuſ. Hieræ picræ</hi>, till from a ſmall <lb/>Spoonful I
        increaſed the Quantity ſhe took in the <lb/>Day to a Spoonful and a half and two Spoon-
        <lb/>fuls, always refraining the Uſe of it when ſhe <lb/>found any Stirrings in her Belly,
        till they ceaſed. <lb/>Sometimes likewiſe I mixed a little <hi rend="italic">Daffie</hi>'s
          <hi rend="italic">E- <lb/>lixir</hi>. By theſe Means ſhe recoverd. Lately <lb/>ſhe fell
        again into the ſame Way, tried the <lb/>Purgatives in common Doſes without Succeſs, <lb/>but
        recovered again by the Uſe of the ſmall <lb/>Doſes. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
