<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Martin: The Experiment of cutting the Recurrent Nerves carried on
          farther than has hitherto been done</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>George Martin</persName>
            </author>
            <title>VIII. The Experiment of cutting the Recurrent Nerves carried on farther than has
              hitherto been done. In a Letter from Dr. GEORGE MARTIN, Physician at St. Andrews, to
              Mr. Monro Professor of Anatomy at Edinburgh, by whom it was communicated</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical essays and observations, published by a society in Edinburgh</title>
            <author>Philosophical Society of Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh : printed by W. and T. Ruddimans, for Messrs. Hamilton and
                  Balfour, Booksellers</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1747</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">2</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">96-101</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108728263</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T132162</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ1_v2_0096">
    <body>
      <pb n="96"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VIII.</hi> The Experiment of cutting the Recurrent <lb/>Nerves carried
        on farther than has hitherto <lb/>been done. In a Letter from Dr. <hi rend="sc">George
          <lb/>Martin</hi>, Phyſician at St. <hi rend="roman">Andrews</hi>, to Mr. <lb/><hi
          rend="roman">Monro</hi> Profeſſor of Anatomy at <hi rend="roman">Edinburgh</hi>, <lb/>by
        whom it was communicated. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE Moderns have acquired a much exact- <lb/>er Knowledge of the
        Structure of the hu- <lb/>man Body than the Ancients could poſſibly <lb/>come at. We have
        the Advantage of the time <lb/>and Pains they laid out in making their Obſer- <lb/>vations:
        and beſide, can boaſt of many Oppor- <lb/>tunities they were entirely deſtitute of. Yet
        <lb/>we cannot but admire theſe great Men, if we <lb/>will form a Judgment of them from the
        Monu- <lb/>ments of their Genius and Induſtry they left <lb/>behind them, tho' ſome of theſe
        are loſt, and <lb/>many of them, tho' preſerved in Books are <lb/>ſometimes too much
        ſlighted by the over negli- <lb/>gent Poſſeſſors of theſe Treaſures. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2. The firſt Phyſicians had but a very faint <lb/>Notion of the Brain preſiding over
        the Animal <lb/>Syſtem by the Mediation of the ſpinal Marrow <lb/>and Nerves produced from
        it, and diſtributed <lb/>to the reſt of the Body. And we muſt acknow- <lb/>ledge this was
        not ſufficiently underſtood be- <lb/>fore <hi rend="italic">Herophilus</hi> and <hi
          rend="italic">Eraſiſtratus</hi>, the greateſt <lb/>Anatomiſts of Antiquity, who explained
        this <lb/>Scheme, and left the World no Room to doubt <lb/>of this elegant Piece of
        Mechaniſm of the ani- <lb/>mal Body. Phyſicians began to diſſect with <pb n=""/>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>Illustrations.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb n="97"/>
        <lb/>more than ordinary Care both living and dead <lb/>Animals; and they ſoon found, that by
        cut- <lb/>ting, tying or compreſſing any Nerve, or any <lb/>other Way intercepting its
        Communication <lb/>with the Brain, the Parts to which it belonged <lb/>were immediately
        deprived of all Senſe and <lb/>Motion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>3. It was eaſy to confirm this Doctrine by <lb/>Experiments on any of the ordinary
        Nerves. <lb/>But one of the prettieſt Inſtances of it, was the <lb/>making Ligatures upon
        the Veſſels at the Side <lb/>of the Wind-pipe, and immediately ſtriking <lb/>the Animal
        dumb, however noiſy it was before. <lb/>The firſt Makers of this Experiment thought <lb/>the
        Animal turned comatous, or fell aſleep; <lb/>and aſcribing this Effect to the intercepting
        any <lb/>Paſſage of vital Blood from the Heart to the <lb/>Brain, by the Way of the
        Arteries; they gave <lb/>theſe blood Veſſels the Name of <hi rend="italic">Carotids</hi>,
          <lb/><unclear>χ</unclear>αροτιδώυ. But in the Days of <hi rend="italic">Ruffus <note
            n="(a)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7) roman">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) De app. part. i. 34. </p>
          </note></hi>, <lb/>this ſudden Silence of the Animal was found to <lb/>proceed from the
        tying of the adjacent Nerves. <lb/>And <hi rend="italic">Galen</hi>, who ſeems to have
        laboured this <lb/>Affair more than any of his Predeceſſors, evi- <lb/>dently proved <note
          n="(b)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) De decr. Hipp. &amp;c. ii. 6. De util. reſp. v. </p>
        </note>, That tying the Arteries ſolely <lb/>produced little Change on the Animal. In this
        <lb/>Caſe, (laying aſide the captious Cavils and Op- <lb/>poſitions of <hi rend="italic"
          >Hoffman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Vanderlinden</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Wepfer</hi>,
        <lb/>and others of the Moderns, who diſputed a- <lb/>gainſt the Experiments, which however
        eaſy, <lb/>they would not take the Trouble to repeat) we <lb/>muſt conceive the Brain to
        have been furniſhed <pb n="98"/>
        <lb/>by the vertebral Arteries. And ſo he found <lb/>all that the Animal ſuffered in the
        Experiment <lb/>of tying the whole Veſſels at the Side of the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Trachea</hi>, to be a ſudden Obmuteſcence; which <lb/>entirely proceded from the
        intercepting the <lb/>nervous Influence on the Muſcles of the <hi rend="italic">Larynx</hi>:
        <lb/>For he diſcovered <note n="(c)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) De uſ. part. vii. 14. xvi. 4. De loc. affect. i. 7. </p>
        </note> that theſe Nerves were <lb/>derived from the <hi rend="italic">Par vagum</hi>; and
        that they, <lb/>making a Turn under the right ſubclavian Ar- <lb/>tery, and deſcending <hi
          rend="italic">Aorta</hi>, climbed up along <lb/>each Side of the Wind-pipe, to furniſh
        theſe <lb/>Muſcles. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>4. The Oddneſs and Novelty of all this Do- <lb/>ctrine, was in thoſe Days ſurpriſing
          <note n="(d)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) De præcog. ad poſthum. v. </p>
        </note>. The <lb/><hi rend="italic">Virtuoſi</hi> at <hi rend="italic">Rome</hi> knew
        nothing of it; yea <hi rend="italic">A- <lb/>lexander</hi> of <hi rend="italic"
          >Damaſcus</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Peripatetick</hi> and <lb/>Preceptor of <hi
          rend="italic">Boethius</hi>, was reſolved to deny <lb/>and oppoſe it at any rate. He would
        rather <lb/>reſiſt the Evidence of Senſe, than yield any <lb/>thing that might contribute to
        the riſing Glory <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Galen</hi> his Rival. But our Anatomiſt, in the
        <lb/>midſt of a learned and judicious Aſſembly, con- <lb/>ſiſting of Adverſaries as well as
        Friends, by o- <lb/>cular Demonſtration, gave them at once a con- <lb/>vincing Proof of the
        Truth of his Doctrine, and <lb/>of his own extraordinary Skill in Diſſections. <lb/>Yea this
        was confirmed by ſome caſual Obſervati- <lb/>ons made on ſome of our own Species <note
          place="bottom" n="(e)" rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) Galen. de loc. affect. i. 7. </p>
        </note>. An <lb/>unlucky ſcrophulous Boy falling into the Hands <lb/>of an ignorant Surgeon,
        loſt the half of the <lb/>Strength of his Voice, by having one of the <lb/>Recurrent Nerves
        cut along with the Tumour. <pb n="99"/>
        <lb/>However he eſcaped better than another Boy, <lb/>who in the like Caſe was indeed cured
        of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Strumæ</hi>; but, having both the Recurrents ex-
        <lb/>tirpated, was left quite dumb. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>5. This Experiment of cutting theſe Nerves <lb/>in brute Animals, was repeated and
        confirmed <lb/>by <hi rend="italic">Veſalius <note n="(f)" place="bottom"
            rend="size(0.7) roman">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>) Hum. corp. fab. vii. 19. p. 571. </p>
          </note></hi>, otherwiſe, you know, no <lb/>great Favourer of the Doctrines or Glory of
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Galen</hi>. And I myſelf about twelve or thirteen <lb/>Years ago,
        when I was firſt ſetting out to make <lb/>ſuch Experiments, trying it in a Pig, with all
        <lb/>the Circumſpection I was then capable of, found <lb/>it to anſwer exactly. So that tho'
        this elegant <lb/>Operation has been much out of Uſe among <lb/>the Moderns, inſomuch that
        one might have <lb/>ſuſpected it had been given over for want of <lb/>Succeſs, yet, however
        great Regard I have <lb/>to your Judgment and great Skill in Anatomy, <lb/>I could not
        conſent to you, when, from a pre- <lb/>conceived Theory you ſeem to think <note n="(g)"
          place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>(<hi rend="italic">g</hi>) Of the Nerves, p. 19. </p>
        </note>
        <hi rend="italic">it <lb/>probable the Voice would not be entirely loſt, <lb/>tho' both the
          recurrent Nerves were cut, ſo <lb/>long as the ſuperior Branches ſtill ſupply the <hi
            rend="roman">Lar- <lb/>ynx</hi></hi>. It is true that <hi rend="italic">Galen <note
            n="(h)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7) roman">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(<hi rend="italic">h</hi>) De uſ. part. xvi. 4. </p>
          </note></hi> himſelf taught that <lb/>there was on each Side an Inoſculation of the
        <lb/>Extremity of the Recurrent, with one of the ſu- <lb/>perior Branches of the eighth
        Nerve. This was <lb/>copied by <hi rend="italic">Nic. Maſſa</hi>, painted by <hi
          rend="italic">Euſtachio</hi>, and <lb/>confirmed by <hi rend="italic">Willis</hi> and the
        Moderns: But ſtill, <lb/>on Diſſection, I could not find that there was a- <lb/>ny regular
        Diſtribution of Nerves to the proper <lb/>Muſcles of the <hi rend="italic">Larynx</hi>, from
        any other Origin <pb n="100"/>
        <lb/>beſide the Recurrent. This you know I <lb/>gueſſed to be the Caſe: And now I find it to
        <lb/>be true in Fact. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>6. It is plain then, That the Voice muſt be <lb/>loſt, however ſound and free we
        ſuppoſe the <lb/>ſuperior Branches of the <hi rend="italic">Par vagum</hi>. But ſtill
        <lb/>there is ſome hankering Doubt in this Affair; <lb/>and it is propoſed to try this over
        again, and <lb/>keep the Animal alive ſome Weeks, to ſee if <lb/>the Voice would at all
        return. We know not <lb/>of any of the Ancients carrying on the Experi- <lb/>ment thus far;
        except we ſay <hi rend="italic">Galen</hi>'s ſcrophu- <lb/>lous Boys ſhow the abſolute
        Irrecoverableneſs <lb/>of the Voice. But to put the Matter beyond <lb/>all Doubt, I repeated
        the Experiment this Spring <lb/>on a young Sow five or ſix Weeks old, ſome <lb/>Days before
        it was weaned from ſucking, and <lb/>took greater Notice of all the Circumſtances <lb/>than
        I had done formerly. I could obſerve with <lb/>the Ancients, and ſo did two curious young
        <lb/>Gentlemen who aſſiſted me, that upon cutting <lb/>the Nerve on one Side, the Voice was
        not de- <lb/>ſtroyed, only it became weaker; but upon cut- <lb/>ting the other, it was
        entirely loſt, tho', by the <lb/>Sound of the Breath, and the Motion of the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Thorax</hi>, you would manifeſtly have ſeen a <lb/>fruitleſs <hi
          rend="italic">Conatus</hi>, and the Creature ſtraining to <lb/>make a Noiſe. And ſo I very
        well underſtood <lb/><hi rend="italic">Veſalius</hi>, when he ſays, <q rend="italic">Pulchrè
          auditur quàm <lb/>validam efflationem animal citra vocem molia- <lb/>tur, recurrentibus
          nervis cultello diviſis </q>. The <lb/>Creature, when diſmiſſed, ſeemed well enough,
        <lb/>ſucked the Mother for ſome Days, lived with <lb/>the reſt of the Litter ſeemingly
        hearty and well, <lb/>tho' always dumb. It could indeed make ſome <pb n="101"/>
        <lb/>little, juſt audible, grunting Noiſe, but could <lb/>never give a Squeak in the
        ordinary Manner <lb/>of theſe Animals. From the Beginning it <lb/>breathed as if the <hi
          rend="italic">Glottis</hi> were too wide, eſpe- <lb/>cially in the Heat of the Day. And
        this Diffi- <lb/>culty in ſome Weeks began to increaſe upon <lb/>it; ſo that in Proceſs of
        Time it became more <lb/>lazy and ſolitary, frequently retired to the Shade <lb/>by it ſelf;
        by Degrees loſt its Strength and Ap- <lb/>petite, pined away, and at length in about ſix
        <lb/>or ſeven Weeks died. Upon inſpecting the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Larynx</hi>, I could
        not ſay it had undergone any <lb/>great or remarkable Change. The Orifices of <lb/>the
        Ventricles ſeemed, I thought, laxer, and <lb/>a little above them the Membrane of the <hi
          rend="italic">Glottis</hi>
        <lb/>was ſomewhat inflamed on each Side. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>7. The Ancients knew, That the Noiſe of <lb/>the Voice depended on a due Narrowneſs of
        <lb/>the Aperture of the <hi rend="italic">Glottis</hi>. And the Author <lb/>of the Book <hi
          rend="italic">de voce &amp; anhelitu <note n="(i)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7) roman">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(<hi rend="italic">i</hi>) Tract. iii. p. 63. </p>
          </note></hi>, aſcribed to <lb/><hi rend="italic">Galen</hi>, expreſly affirms, <hi
          rend="italic">tunc vox deſtrueretur</hi>: So <lb/>that on the cutting the Recurrent
        Nerves, we <lb/>are to conceive the <hi rend="italic">Glottis</hi> to ſtand open, and
        <lb/>not to be ſhut at the Pleaſure of the Animal. And <lb/>what elſe indeed can we expect,
        when the ner- <lb/>vous Influence on the Muſcles belonging to the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Arytænoid</hi> Cartilages is taken away in ſuch a <lb/>Manner that they can never be
        brought to a due <lb/>Conſtriction, nor the Ventricles of the <hi rend="italic">Larynx</hi>
        <lb/>ſuffer any Variety of Contraction and Dilata- <lb/>tion. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
