<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Monro: Unexpected Cures</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Alexander Monro</persName>
            </author>
            <title>XLVII. Unexpected Cures; by ALEXANDER MONRO, P. A. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical essays and observations, published by a society in Edinburgh</title>
            <author>Philosophical Society of Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: printed by W. and T. Ruddimans, for Messrs. Hamilton and
                  Balfour, Booksellers</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1747</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">6</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">19-27</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108729439</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T132162</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ1_v6_0019">
    <body>
      <pb n="19"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XLVII.</hi> Unexpected Cures; by <hi rend="sc">Alexander
          <lb/>Monro</hi>, P. A. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>F Practiſers in Phyſick and Surgery have <lb/>ſometimes uneaſy
        Minds on account of Pa- <lb/>tients, the Nature of whoſe Diſeaſes they cannot <lb/>judge
        with Certainty; if they are diſappointed <lb/>now and then in the Effects of Medicines; and
        <lb/>if they have the galling Mortification of the Sick <lb/>dying unexpectedly, they have,
        on the contra- <lb/>ry, frequently the Comfort and Pleaſure of be- <lb/>ing ſurpriſed with
        the great Relief which their <lb/>Patients, in very obſcure, or even in Diſeaſes <lb/>which
        they are ignorant of, receive from Medi- <lb/>cines, which either a very diſtant Analogy to
        <lb/>ſome known Diſeaſe, or the Neceſſity of miti- <lb/>gating ſome urgent Symptom, have
        made them <lb/>preſcribe; nay, the Event ſometimes is proſper- <lb/>ous when the Medicines
        are differently applied, <lb/>or have other Effects than the Preſcriber intend- <lb/>ed.
        Though People ſhould be very cautious in <lb/>laying down any general Rule in Practice, and
        <lb/>ought not to found it on one or two Obſervati- <lb/>ons; yet I muſt think ſuch <hi
          rend="italic">unexpected Cures</hi> as <pb n="20"/>
        <lb/>I have hinted at, deſerve to ſtand on Record, <lb/>that, if the Medicines employed are
        not of a ve- <lb/>ry offenſive Nature, they may again be tried in <lb/>ſimilar Caſes; ſo
        that ſick People may have ſome <lb/>more Chance for their Recovery than the com- <lb/>mon
        Methods give. As a Specimen of ſuch <lb/>Caſes, I ſend you the following Medley of pra-
        <lb/>ctical Obſervations. If they are thought uſeful, <lb/>I can furniſh you ſeveral more;
        and dare ſay, e- <lb/>very one of the Gentlemen of your Society can <lb/>add to the Number. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I. A middle-aged healthy Man having bruiſed <lb/>the Extremity of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Penis</hi>, the Part of the <hi rend="italic">Pre- <lb/>puce</hi> where the <hi
          rend="italic">Frænum</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Glans</hi> is, was rai- <lb/>ſed into a
        large <hi rend="italic">cryſtaline Tumor</hi>. Topical a- <lb/>romatick Fomentations and <hi
          rend="italic">Suffumigia</hi> being ap- <lb/>plied to it, and Catharticks being given,
        with- <lb/>out its yielding, a ſmall Seton was put through <lb/>it, with the View of
        allowing ſome of the wa- <lb/>tery Liquor to ouze out, and of bringing on a <lb/>gentle
        Suppuration. Inſtead of this it occaſion- <lb/>ed ſharp Pain, and a violent Inflammation;
        <lb/>which made it neceſſary to take out the Cord, <lb/>and to apply an emollient Poultice
        of Milk and <lb/>Bread. Next Day after this the Tumor was <lb/>greatly diminiſhed; and the
        ſecond Day it diſ- <lb/>appeared, without a Return. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>II. A young Man had a great many pale-red <lb/>Excreſcences, of a very unequal Surface,
        with <lb/>ſmall Necks on the interior Side of the <hi rend="italic">Prepuce</hi>; <lb/>and
        when the <hi rend="italic">Prepuce</hi> was turned back, <hi rend="italic">Cox-
          <lb/>comb</hi> Excreſcences were likewiſe ſeen on as much <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Glans</hi> as he could uncover. The Account <lb/>which he gave of his Diſeaſe to Dr. <hi
          rend="italic">James Dun- <lb/>das</hi> and me, was, That, having a ſmall Wart on <pb
          n="21"/>
        <lb/>the Edge of the <hi rend="italic">Prepuce</hi>, he cut it away with a <lb/>Razor; ſoon
        after which theſe Excreſcences be- <lb/>gan to appear. <hi rend="italic">Mercurial
          Ointments</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Aſtrin- <lb/>gents</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Eſcharoticks</hi>, and ſeveral other Medicines, <lb/>had been tried in vain, and he had
        undergone <lb/>ſix Weeks Salivation without any Benefit; tho' <lb/>he averred ſolemnly, that
        he was ſure they were <lb/>not owing to any venereal Cauſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I tied a Silk Thread very tight round the Neck <lb/>of one of them; he complained of
        ſharp Pain <lb/>while the Nooſe was drawing, which ſoon cea- <lb/>ſed; and in two Days the
        Tumor dropt off, <lb/>leaving the Surface of the Part it roſe from <lb/>ſmooth and ſound.—I
        deſired a young Surgeon, <lb/>who had ſeen me make this Ligature, to take <lb/>the other
        Excreſcences away in the ſame Way. <lb/>When this young Gentleman attempted next <lb/>Day to
        put a Ligature on one of theſe Excre- <lb/>ſcences, he was timorous, and the Patient was
        <lb/>not obſequious; ſo that the Ligature was not <lb/>made tight enough to mortify the
        Tumor. The <lb/>Patient felt very ſharp Pain all that Day; and <lb/>by next Morning a very
        conſiderable Inflamma- <lb/>tion was raiſed; for which he was blooded plen- <lb/>tifully,
        and emollient Fomentations and Poultices <lb/>were applied to the Part. After two Days the
        <lb/>Inflammation abated, and the Excreſcences were <lb/>all conſiderably diminiſhed; and,
        as the Inflam- <lb/>mation went off, they ſhrivelled: So that, after <lb/>eight Days, during
        which the Emollients were <lb/>continued, it could not be known where the Ex-
        <lb/>creſcences had been. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Whether was it the Inflammation or the e- <lb/>mollient Applications which made the
        Cure in <lb/>theſe two Caſes? In my Opinion it was the In- <pb n="22"/>
        <lb/>flammation; and I am confirmed in it by the <lb/>Succeſs which I have ſeen of
        ſtimulating Medi- <lb/>cines in ſlow cold Swellings. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>III. A Man who had been ſubject to the Gout, <lb/>was by Accident burnt ſuperficially
        in the Face <lb/>and Hands. After the Burnings were all ſkin- <lb/>ned, a ſpongy
        Excreſcence, the Baſe of which <lb/>was equal to a Sixpence, roſe out from the Point <lb/>of
        his Noſe; and ſuch another, as broad as a <lb/>Shilling at its Baſe, roſe out from the right
        <lb/>Cheek. They were both of a pale red Colour, <lb/>and of a granulated Surface, throwing
        out from <lb/>imperceptible Pores a thin Liquor, which fell <lb/>down in Drops ſo faſt, that
        a conſiderable Quan- <lb/>tity of it could have been collected in a ſhort <lb/>Time. After
        different Plaiſters, Ointments, A- <lb/>ſtringents, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> had been
        tried to no Purpoſe, I <lb/>covered the Excreſcences with the fine Cotton <lb/>of old Linen,
        ſcraped with a Knife, and wet with <lb/><hi rend="italic">Alcohol</hi>. I deſired the Cotton
        might not be ta- <lb/>ken off, but that it ſhould be wet three or four <lb/>Times a Day with
        the Spirit. After this Appli- <lb/>cation, the ouzing of Liquor decreaſed, and in <lb/>two
        Days ceaſed altogether. The Cotton adhe- <lb/>ring to the Excreſcences, they ſhrivelled, and
        <lb/>at laſt became ſmooth and plain with the other <lb/>Parts of the Skin, leaving only a
        little Redneſs <lb/>for ſome Time. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>IV. A young Man of a weak Conſtitution, <lb/>and thin Habit, having fallen from a
        Height, <lb/>was bruiſed in a great many Parts of his Body, <lb/>and particularly in the <hi
          rend="italic">hypogaſtrick Region</hi>. He <lb/>complained ſoon after of a ſharp Pain in
        the <hi rend="italic">Pe- <lb/>nis</hi>, and Regions of the Bladder. Thoſe he advi- <lb/>ſed
        with ſuſpecting theſe Pains might be cauſed by <pb n="23"/>
        <lb/>ſome Remains of a virulent <hi rend="italic">Gonorræa</hi> which he <lb/>had two Years
        before, injected ſome acrid Medi- <lb/>cines into the <hi rend="italic">Urethra</hi>, which
        increaſed the Pain, <lb/>and occaſioned a conſiderable Inflammation in the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Penis</hi>. When the Inflammation was removed, <lb/>he had great Difficulty
        in making Water, with <lb/>ſharp Pain along the whole <hi rend="italic">Urethra</hi> when it
        did <lb/>paſs. He then took ſeveral Doſes of <hi rend="italic">Sweet Mer- <lb/>cury</hi>,
        drank the Decoction of the Woods; and <lb/>continued ſome time the Uſe of gummous Pills,
        <lb/>with ſome Grains of Mercury in them. The <lb/>Symptoms becoming however worſe, I was
        con- <lb/>ſulted about him four Months after his Fall. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He complained of a torturing Pain at the Root <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Penis</hi>,
        and in the <hi rend="italic">Glans</hi>, when he at- <lb/>tempted to make Urine, which let
        fall a white <lb/>furfuraceous thick Sediment in great Quantity <lb/>when it cooled. I
        adviſed mild mucaginous Me- <lb/>dicines, and an emollient healing Injection, with
        <lb/>Fomentations to the Pained Part. Theſe made <lb/>him a little eaſier, but did not
        remove his Diſ- <lb/>eaſe; and he was ſeized with feveriſh Paroxyſms, <lb/>which had the
        full Type of Ague, but without <lb/>regular Returns. Theſe waſted his Strength and
        <lb/>Fleſh ſo faſt, that there was a Neceſſity to ſtop <lb/>them; with a View to which, and
        to his origi- <lb/>nal Diſeaſe, the following Electuary was order- <lb/>ed: ℞ <hi
          rend="italic">Pulv. patrum, Drach. <hi rend="roman">ii.</hi> Gum. Arabic. <lb/>Drach. <hi
            rend="roman">i.</hi> ſem. Sal. Nitr. Drach. <hi rend="roman">i.</hi> Pulv. mille-
          <lb/>ped. unc. ſem. Sal. Jov. Londin, ſcrup. <hi rend="roman">i.</hi> Syrup. <lb/>diacod.
          q. ſ.</hi> Of this he took the Bulk of a Nut- <lb/>meg twice a Day. The aguiſh Paroxyſms
        went <lb/>off gradually, and the other Symptoms became <lb/>milder, till he was free of all
        his Complaints in <pb n="24"/>
        <lb/>ſome Weeks; and he has continued free of them <lb/>ever ſince. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>V. <hi rend="italic">Alexander Strachan</hi>, Gardener to Mr. <hi rend="italic">Er-
          <lb/>ſkine</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Grange</hi>, had a Cholick, which continu- <lb/>ed a
        Day, in the Beginning of <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 1734; <lb/>after which a painful
        Tumor was obſerved to- <lb/>wards the left Side of the epigaſtrick Region, <lb/>which ſoon
        increaſed, and extended itſelf over <lb/>that whole Region. He took ſome purgative
        <lb/>Medicine, after which he had a conſtant <hi rend="italic">Diar- <lb/>rhæa</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When he was received into the Infirmary 6th <lb/><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 1734, a
        Suppuration ſeemed to be ſo far <lb/>advanced in the Tumor, that the Surgeons felt <lb/>a
        Fluctuation of Liquor lodged deep, and the <lb/>left Part of the Tumor pointed outwards. He
        <lb/>complained of a ſharp Pain in the left Shoulder; <lb/>and the Skin of his Face had that
        leadiſh Colour <lb/>which is almoſt peculiar to People whoſe Livers <lb/>are ſuppurated. His
        Pulſe was quick and low. <lb/>He had no Deſire for Food, and, upon taking it, <lb/>the Pain
        of the <hi rend="italic">Epigaſtrium</hi> was much increaſed. <lb/>He had perpetual Thirſt;
        ſleeped ill in the Night, <lb/>and ſweated much in the Morning, with a <hi rend="italic"
          >Diar- <lb/>rhæa</hi> ſtill upon him. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To promote the Suppuration, a Poultice of <lb/>Oat-meal boiled in Water, with ſome <hi
          rend="italic">Baſilicon</hi>, <lb/>and bruiſed raw Onions, was applied to the <hi
          rend="italic">Epi- <lb/>gaſtrium</hi>, and renewed thrice a Day. Some <lb/>Drops of <hi
          rend="italic">Laudanum</hi> were given at Night to ſtop <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >Diarrhæa</hi>, and to procure Reſt. Mild Food <lb/>and Drink were ordered. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Suppuration ſeemed to advance outwards <lb/>for four Days; the Doſe of the <hi
          rend="italic">Laudanum</hi> be- <lb/>ing gradually increaſed to check the <hi
          rend="italic">Diarrhæa</hi>, <pb n="25"/>
        <lb/>which frequently returned, but without any <hi rend="italic">Pus</hi>
        <lb/>in his Stools. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the fifth Day the Tumor was evidently <lb/>diminiſhed, ſofter and leſs painful; but
        he was <lb/>faint, for which he had Sack-whey allowed him <lb/>to drink ſome times. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>His Poultice and <hi rend="italic">Laudanum</hi> were continued, <lb/>the Tumor
        gradually diminiſhed, and his hectic <lb/>Symptoms went off, without any obſervable E-
        <lb/>vacuation of <hi rend="italic">Pus</hi>; ſo that, <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 26. he
        was diſ- <lb/>miſſed heal and ſtrong. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>VI. A Child eight Months old was ſuddenly <lb/>ſeized with violent <hi rend="italic"
          >epileptic Fits</hi>; after having <lb/>had ſeveral, was let five Ounces of Blood at the
        <lb/>jugular Vein; and ſoon after, being put into a <lb/>Cradle, covered over with a Cloth,
        loſt a con- <lb/>ſiderable larger Quantity of Blood, the Cloaths <lb/>about her being all
        wet, and the Child in a Faint, <lb/>and very pale. She continued weak and pale <lb/>ſeveral
        Days; but never has had any Return of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Epilepſy</hi>, though ſhe
        has ſince that Time un- <lb/>dergone all the common eruptive Diſeaſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>VII. A Woman in the Decline of Life, and <lb/>of a broken Conſtitution, had been
        ſeveral Weeks <lb/>in a rheumatick Fever, out of which ſhe nar- <lb/>rowly eſcaped, after
        repeated Blood-lettings and <lb/>other Medicines. Two Years after ſhe was ſei- <lb/>zed with
        the ſame Symptoms which had appear- <lb/>ed in the Beginning of the former Fever, to wit,
        <lb/>Anxiety, Thirſt, Vomiting, Pains of the whole <lb/>Body, and particularly of the Head,
        with a high <lb/>quick Pulſe. She was taken ill in the Morning, <lb/>and in the Evening
        fourteen Ounces of Blood <lb/>were let at a Vein of the Arm; which gave her <lb/>little or
        no Relief. In the Nigth-time the Blood <pb n="26"/>
        <lb/>burſt out again at the Orifice of the opened Vein, <lb/>and, beſides wetting all the
        Bed-cloaths, was ly- <lb/>ing in Clots at her Side before it was taken no- <lb/>tice of. A
        clean Bandage being then applied, <lb/>ſhe fell aſleep, and awaked next Morning free <lb/>of
        all Complaints. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>VIII. In <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 1739, a ſharp Pain ſtruck <lb/>into my right
        Eye, then gradually ſeized all that <lb/>Side of the Face, contracted the Eye-lids, made
        <lb/>the Tears ruſh out, and affected all the Teeth of <lb/>the Upper-jaw. It began between
        Ten and E- <lb/>leven o'Clock in the Morning, increaſed till a- <lb/>bout Four in the
        Afternoon, decreaſed till Six, <lb/>and then went off, without a critical Evacuation <lb/>of
        any kind, ſo far as I could obſerve. In the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Paroxyſm</hi> my Pulſe
        had no Diſorder in it; and <lb/>in the Intervals I was as well as ever. The
        <lb/>Inconveniency of Confinement at that Seaſon of <lb/>the Year, and the Hope of each Fit
        being the <lb/>laſt, made me ſuffer theſe periodical Pains ten <lb/>Days, without trying to
        remove them by any <lb/>Medicine. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Pain increaſing daily, and making me at <lb/>laſt unable to do my Work, I let ten
        Ounces of <lb/>Blood, and took a Vomit a little Time before I <lb/>expected the <hi
          rend="italic">Paroxyſm</hi> would begin. The Vo- <lb/>mit operated ſeverely, but did not
        prevent the <lb/>Return of the Pain: which continued till the <lb/>Medicine began to go
        downwards, when I was <lb/>relieved: And, having purged twenty Times <lb/>before Night, I
        had no more Return of the Diſ- <lb/>eaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Since that Time I have cured ſeveral of this <lb/>Diſeaſe, by giving them a Vomit, and
        a briſk <lb/>Purgative ſoon after this Operation was over, if <pb n="27"/>
        <lb/>there was no Appearance of the Emetick's acting <lb/>alſo as a Purgative. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>IX. A Man brought a <hi rend="italic">Quartan Ague</hi> and the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >French Pox</hi> from <hi rend="italic">England</hi>. The Ague was in <lb/>vain attempted
        to be cured by the common Re- <lb/>medies; and, in the mean time, the Pox advan- <lb/>ced,
        the nocturnal Pains increaſed, and the foul <lb/>Ulcers in his Throat ſpread. His Phyſician
        (who <lb/>is one of your Number, and from whom I have <lb/>this Account) gave him five
        Grains of <hi rend="italic">Sweet <lb/>Mercury</hi> at Night, immediately after the Fit of
        <lb/>the Ague was over; repeated the Doſe next <lb/>Morning and Evening, and the Morning of
        the <lb/>following Day. After taking theſe four Doſes <lb/>of <hi rend="italic"
        >Mercury</hi>, he had a Fit of the <hi rend="italic">Ague</hi>, which was <lb/>more ſevere
        than any he had formerly under- <lb/>gone; the Fever being higher, with <hi rend="italic"
          >Delirium</hi>, <lb/>but without any other bad Symptom. After the <lb/>Fit was over, the
          <hi rend="italic">Mercury</hi> was repeated as for- <lb/>merly, till the Salivation roſe.
        He never had <lb/>more Appearance of the Ague; and the vene- <lb/>real Symptoms diſappeared
        by the Uſe of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Mercury</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I was willing to borrow this Caſe, becauſe, ſo <lb/>far as relates to the <hi
          rend="italic">Ague</hi>, it was an unexpected <lb/>uncommon Cure of a Diſeaſe little known
        in this <lb/>Country; the <hi rend="italic">Quartan Agues</hi> not having been <lb/>ſeen
        here, except produced in other Countries, <lb/>until within the laſt ten Years; in which
        they <lb/>have been obſerved in ſome Parts of the Coun- <lb/>try, but have not been general.
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
