<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Douglas: Stones in the Kidney, with Remarks on the Operation of
          Nephrotomy</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Jonh Douglas</persName>
            </author>
            <title>XXI. Stones in the Kidney, with Remarks on the Operation of Nephrotomy; by Mr.
              JONH DOUGLAS Surgeon in Edinburgh. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical essays and observations, published by a society in Edinburgh</title>
            <author>Philosophical Society of Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh : printed by W. and T. Ruddimans, for Messrs. Hamilton and
                  Balfour, Booksellers</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1747</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">1</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">185-187</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108727930</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T132162</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ1_v1_0185">
    <body>
      <pb n="185"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXI.</hi> Stones in the Kidney, with Remarks on <lb/>the Operation of
          <hi rend="roman">Nephrotomy</hi>; by Mr. <hi rend="sc"><choice>
            <corr>John</corr>
            <sic>Jonh</sic>
          </choice>
          <lb/>Douglas</hi> Surgeon in <hi rend="roman">Edinburgh</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/>— — Aged 53 Years, of a robuſt Make <lb/>of Body, having large Muſcles, and remark-
        <lb/>ably big Blood-Veſſels, the Veins of his Arm at <lb/>the common Blooding-place being to
        Appear- <lb/>ance an Inch in Diameter, was afflicted, ſince <lb/>four Years old, with a
        violent Pain in his right <lb/>Side about the Region of the Kidney, from <lb/>which he never
        was at any time perfectly free; <lb/>but he often had tolerable Intervals; otherwiſe <lb/>he
        was very healthy. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In his younger Days he was ſalivated by Dr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pitcairn</hi>'s
        Order, and had many different Ad- <lb/>vices from ſeveral other Phyſicians, but ſeldom
        <lb/>got Relief from any thing, but the drinking <lb/>large Draughts of warm Water, even to
        the <lb/>Quantity of three <hi rend="italic">Scots</hi> Pints (12 <hi rend="italic"
          >Pounds</hi>). He <lb/>more than once ſuffered ſuch violent Pain for <lb/>ſome Months,
        that he was obliged to ly the <lb/>whole Time on a Coverlet laid on the Floor; <lb/>the
        Preſſure of his pain'd Side on the hard Floor <lb/>giving him ſome Remiſſion from Pain.
        While <lb/>the Pain continued, all the Urine he paſſed, <lb/>after it had ſtood and cool'd a
        little, became <lb/>like Gleet, or Whites of Eggs. He had often <pb n="186"/>
        <lb/>a <hi rend="italic">Diarrhœa</hi>, without any Gripes, and could at <lb/>Pleaſure even
        then refrain going to Stool for a <lb/>whole Day. And in the ſame Way he could <lb/>retain
        his Urine, till his Bladder was ſo ſull, as <lb/>to diſcharge near three Chopins (6 <hi
          rend="italic">Pounds</hi>) at <lb/>once. Several Meats and Drinks, ſuch as Eggs,
        <lb/>Butter, fry'd Meat, Punch and White Wine <lb/>gave him Pain; ſmall Malt-Liquor rather
        eaſed <lb/>him, for which Reaſon he for ordinary drank <lb/>plentifully of it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About the Beginning of <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 1731, he <lb/>contracted a
        violent Cough, which brought on <lb/>a Conſumption, of which he died, <hi rend="italic"
          >March</hi> 29th <lb/>thereafter; tho' by all Appearance, before that <lb/>Time, his Lungs
        were in exceeding good Con- <lb/>dition. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I was allowed to open his Body before Dr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Robert Lowis</hi> and
        Mr. <hi rend="italic">John Wallace</hi> Surgeon; <lb/>and having always been of Opinion that
        there <lb/>was a Stone in his Right Kidney, I reſolved <lb/>firſt to imitate the Operation
        called by Authors <lb/><hi rend="italic">Nephrotomy</hi>, which is ſaid to have been per-
        <lb/>formed ſucceſsfully by <hi rend="italic">Dominicus de Marchet- <lb/>tis</hi>; but I met
        with ſuch Difficulties, as give me <lb/>great Reaſon to wiſh that either <hi rend="italic"
          >Marchettis</hi> had <lb/>given us the Account of it; or that the previous <lb/>Symptoms
        of <hi rend="italic">Conſul Hobſon</hi> had been ſet down, <lb/>whereby we might be certain
        of the Stones <lb/>having been cut out of the Kidney itſelf; and <lb/>all Suſpicion might
        have been removed of its <lb/>having already made its Way thro' the greateſt <lb/>Part
        perhaps of the containing Organs. The <lb/>Difficulties, I mean, are the Thickneſs of the
        <lb/>common Teguments and Muſcles which was in <lb/>this Body no leſs than 3½ Inches. When
        the <pb n=""/>
        <figure>
          <figDesc>Illustrations of the two kidney stones. </figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb n="187"/>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Peritoneum</hi> was laid bare, I obſerved the <hi rend="italic"
          >Colon</hi>
        <lb/>betwixt it and the convex Surface of the Kid- <lb/>ney; after that Gut was removed, a
        large <lb/>Nerve preſented itſelf, lying juſt acroſs the <lb/>Place where the Kidney ought
        to have been cut. <lb/>And the Depth of my Inciſion was now ſo <lb/>great, that I found it
        impracticable to penetrate <lb/>thro' the Subſtance of the Kidney into the <hi rend="italic"
          >Pel- <lb/>vis</hi>; and therefore I turned the Body into the <lb/>common ſupine Poſture;
        and opening the Kid- <lb/>ney in the ordinary Way of Diſſection, I took <lb/>out the two
        Stones herewith ſent. See <hi rend="italic">Tab.</hi>
        <lb/>III. <hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 5, 6. The largeſt, <hi rend="italic">Fig</hi>. 5.
        weighing <lb/>half an Ounce, was found in the <hi rend="italic">Pelvis</hi>. The <lb/>Figure
        of it you ſee is triangular, with its Sur- <lb/>face ſtuck full of ſmall <hi rend="italic"
          >Granula</hi>, as big as <hi rend="italic">Cori- <lb/>ander</hi>-Seed, which ſeem to have
        been united <lb/>after the Stone has been formed; for they were <lb/>of different Hardneſs
        and Colour, being black, <lb/>whereas the Surface of the Stone below them is <lb/>brown and
        firmer. The leſſer Stone, <hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 6. <lb/>which weighed 16 Grains, and
        is of an irregu- <lb/>lar ſquare Figure, was lodged in the Subſtance <lb/>of the Kidney.
        Beſides theſe two, there were <lb/>a great many other ſmall ſtony Concretions <lb/>diſperſed
        every where in the <hi rend="italic">Tubuli uriniferi</hi>; <lb/>many of theſe were bigger
        than the largeſt <lb/>Grains of Sea-Sand. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
