<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Ayton-Douglas: Of the Cure of the Cholera</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Charles Ayton-Douglas</persName>
            </author>
            <title>LXV. Of the Cure of the Cholera; by Dr. CHARLES AYTON - DOUGLAS Physician in
              Fife.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical essays and observations, published by a society in Edinburgh</title>
            <author>Philosophical Society of Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: printed by W. and T. Ruddimans, for Messrs. Hamilton and
                  Balfour, Booksellers</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1747</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">6</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">140-145</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108729439</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T132162</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ1_v6_0140">
    <body>
      <pb n="140"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">LXV.</hi> Of the Cure of the <hi rend="roman">Cholera</hi>; by Dr.
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Charles Ayton-Douglas</hi> Phyſician in <lb/><hi rend="roman"
        >Fife</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE <hi rend="italic">Cholera</hi>, which is a violent vomiting
        <lb/>and purging of Bile and other acrid Hu- <lb/>mors, being a Diſeaſe ſo acute and deadly,
        as <lb/>frequently to deſtroy a Man in the Space of <lb/>twenty four Hours, when a Phyſician
        is not to <lb/>be had, which is frequently the Caſe in the <lb/>Country; or when a wrong
        Method of Cure is <lb/>preſcribed, which I am humbly of Opinion <hi rend="italic">Et-
          <lb/>mullerus</hi>'s is, who recommends Vomits, Purges, <lb/>and Sudorificks, which ſeems
        to be adding Oil <lb/>to the Flame: I hope therefore my Country- <lb/>men will take in good
        Part my publiſhing a Me- <lb/>thod of curing it by a Medicine which is always <lb/>at hand,
        even in the Houſes of the meaneſt Pea- <pb n="141"/>
        <lb/>ſants; which I have tried often, and never found <lb/>it fail. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If the Patients be not too much exhauſted be- <lb/>fore I am called, I make them drink
        heartily <lb/>of warm Water three or four Times, which <lb/>they always throw up. This
        dilutes, and ſo <lb/>blunts the Acrimony of the Humors, and at the <lb/>ſame Time evacuates
        them. Immediately after <lb/>I adviſe them to drink plentifully of a Decocti- <lb/>on of
        Oat-bread baked without any Leven or <lb/>Yeſt, carefully toaſted as brown as Coffee, but
        <lb/>not burnt; which Decoction ought to be of the <lb/>Colour of Coffee, when it is weak.
        This Pre- <lb/>ſcription I have always found my Patients moſt <lb/>willingly obey, their
        Thirſt being generally ve- <lb/>ry great, and they always affirm that it is moſt
        <lb/>grateful to their Stomachs; and I muſt add, <lb/>that I do not remember that any of
        them ever <lb/>vomited it. I have always uſed Oat-bread; but <lb/>when it cannot be had, I
        doubt not but Wheat- <lb/>bread, or Meal well toaſted may do. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But when the Patient is much exhauſted with <lb/>violent Evacuations upwards and
        downwards, the <lb/>firſt thing that I give him, is a large Draught <lb/>of the above
        mentioned Decoction; and when <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Nauſea</hi> is pretty well ſettled,
        I frequently <lb/>order a Pill of <hi rend="italic">Opium</hi>, to the Quantity of two
        <lb/>thirds of a Grain for an ordinary Perſon, in- <lb/>creaſing or diminiſhing the Doſe,
        according to <lb/>the Age or Strength of the Patient. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But if the Patient be convulſed, and the ex- <lb/>treme Parts cold, and his Pulſe weak
        and inter- <lb/>mitting, then it is proper to give a ſtrong Doſe <lb/>of <hi rend="italic"
          >liquid Laudanum</hi>, becauſe it has its Effect <lb/>ſooner than the <hi rend="italic"
          >Opium</hi>, ſuch as <hi rend="italic">gut.</hi> xxv. for <pb n="142"/>
        <lb/>an ordinary Perſon, in an Ounce of ſtrong Cin- <lb/>namon Water, and afterwards a
        Draught of any <lb/>Wine that is moſt agreeable to the Patient, <lb/>mixed with an equal
        Quantity of the Decocti- <lb/>on; and they may afterwards take the Decocti- <lb/>on to
        quench their Thirſt; and now and then <lb/>they may take a little Wine mixed with it, ac-
        <lb/>cording as they need a Cordial. To prevent a <lb/>Relapſe, which the Patient is not
        able to bear, <lb/>it will be proper to repeat the Opiate in a mo- <lb/>derate Quantity for
        ſome Days, Morning and <lb/>Evening. And Care muſt be taken not to o- <lb/>verload the
        Stomach, or to eat any thing but <lb/>what is of good Nouriſhment, and eaſy to di-
        <lb/>geſt, and grateful to the Stomach. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It may be obſerved, that the above Preſcripti- <lb/>on is to be uſed when the Patient
        is quite ex- <lb/>hauſted, and in the very Jaws of Death; but <lb/>in ordinary Caſes, when
        the Patient is not much <lb/>exhauſted, and Opiates are not to be had, or <lb/>if the
        Patient's Conſtitution diſagrees with them, <lb/>then the Decoction itſelf may be truſted
        to. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>What engaged me to preſcribe the above <lb/>Method of Cure to others, was my having
        tried <lb/>it on myſelf with Succeſs. A great many Years <lb/>ago I was extremely ill of a
          <hi rend="italic">Cholera</hi>, and the <lb/>Evacuation upwards and downwards was ſo vio-
        <lb/>lent, that in the Space of ſix Hours I was not <lb/>able to ſtand unſupported; and I
        vomited <hi rend="italic">Lau- <lb/>danum</hi> and every other thing that could be
        <lb/>thought on: But I longed much for a Draught <lb/>of the Decoction above mentioned, and
        I ima- <lb/>gined that I would not vomit it, although at <lb/>the ſame time I loathed
        violently every other <lb/>thing that any of my Friends that were about <pb n="143"/>
        <lb/>me mentioned to me. As ſoon as a large Quan- <lb/>tity of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Decoction</hi> could be got ready, I drank <lb/>heartily of it, and it ſtopped both the
        vomiting <lb/>and purging. Two or three Days after that, by <lb/>being careleſs about my
        Diet, and the other <lb/>Non-naturals, I relapſed, and was immediately <lb/>again cured by
        the Decoction of toaſted Bread; <lb/>ſince which I have cured great Numbers with <lb/>it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A Lady of my Acquaintance told me within <lb/>this Fortnight, that about eight Days
        before ſhe <lb/>had a ſevere <hi rend="italic">Cholera</hi>, in which ſhe vomited eve-
        <lb/>ry thing that was preſcribed for her; but long- <lb/>ing as earneſtly as Women with
        Child uſe to <lb/>long for any thing, for the Decoction of toaſt- <lb/>ed Oat-bread, ſhe
        drank ſeveral Draughts of <lb/>it with great Pleaſure, and was cured immedi- <lb/>ately. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A Phyſician of my Acquaintance, to whom I <lb/>communicated this Method of Cure,
        aſſures me, <lb/>that the Decoction itſelf, without any other <lb/>thing, cured a Patient of
        his who was brought <lb/>very low by a <hi rend="italic">Cholera</hi>, occaſioned by a <hi
          rend="italic">Saliva- <lb/>tion</hi>, after he had in vain tried every other <lb/>thing
        that he could think on. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This Medicine is not indeed a pompous Com- <lb/>poſition, and has not in it Emeralds,
        Pearls, <lb/>nor oriental Bezoar, recommended by <hi rend="italic">Doleus</hi> and
        <lb/>ſeveral other famous Practitioners. But it is not <lb/>far different from <hi
          rend="italic">Celſus</hi>'s Method of Cure: For <lb/>he <note place="bottom" n="*"
          rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* De re medica, lib. iv. cap. 11. </p>
        </note> preſcribes in the Beginning vomiting with <lb/>warm Water, to be repeated
        frequently; and <lb/>he ſays they ſhould ſmell Pennyroyal dipped in <lb/>Vinegar, or <hi
          rend="italic">Polenta</hi> ſprinkled with Wine; and <pb n="144"/>
        <lb/>a little after that he adviſes the Patient to take <lb/>Wine and Water mixed with <hi
          rend="italic">Polenta</hi>. And <lb/><hi rend="italic">Paulus Ægineta</hi>
        <note n="†" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† Lib. iii. cap. 39. </p>
        </note> preſcribes vomiting with warm <lb/>Water, and after that an Opiate. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Polenta</hi> is mentioned by ſeveral of the anci- <lb/>ent <hi
          rend="italic">Greeks</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Romans</hi>, as a thing generally u-
        <lb/>ſed in their Time. <hi rend="italic">Pliny</hi>
        <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Hiſt. Natural. lib. xxii. cap. 25. </p>
        </note> ſays, that it differeth <lb/>from Barley-meal, in ſo far as it is much toaſt-
        <lb/>ed or parched; and to that he thinks it owes its <lb/>aſtringent Quality, being good
        for the Stomach, <lb/>and that it ſtops a <hi rend="italic">Diarrhæa</hi>: And ſeeing it
        dif- <lb/>fered from Barley-meal, only in ſo far at it was <lb/>fryed or very much toaſted,
        it could be made <lb/>of nothing but Barley fryed or toaſted brown, <lb/>and grinded to
        Powder. And elſewhere <note n="†" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† Lib. xviii. cap. 7. </p>
        </note> he <lb/>deſcribes it to have been made after this Man- <lb/>ner by both the <hi
          rend="italic">Greeks</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Italians</hi>; but he adds, <lb/>that they
        frequently mixed with it a little Lint- <lb/>ſeed, ſome Salt, and ſome Coriander-ſeed. It
        <lb/>is alſo mentioned by <hi rend="italic">Hippocrates</hi>
        <note n="‡" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>‡ Vid. de Affectionibus. </p>
        </note>. And it is de- <lb/>ſcribed by <hi rend="italic">Paulus Ægineta</hi>, as made of
        Barley <lb/>fryed or much toaſted; and he recommends it <lb/>to be drank mixed with Water
        for quenching <lb/>Thirſt <note n="††" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>†† Lib. i. cap. 78. </p>
        </note>. And it appears from the holy Scri- <lb/>ptures to have been uſed by the <hi
          rend="italic">Jews</hi>, as ancient- <lb/>ly as the Reign of King <hi rend="italic"
          >David</hi>
        <note n="**" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>** 2 Sam. cap. xvii. ver. 28. </p>
        </note>. From whom, <lb/>or the <hi rend="italic">Syrians</hi>, it is probable that the <hi
          rend="italic">Greeks</hi>
        <lb/>borrowed it; for by their own Confeſſion they <lb/>were much obliged to the <hi
          rend="italic">Syrians</hi> and other <lb/>Eaſtern Nations for many of their Cuſtoms, as
          <pb n="145"/>
        <lb/>well as for ſome of the politer and more uſeful <lb/>Arts and Sciences: And ſeeing it
        was uſually <lb/>drank mixed with Water, eſpecially with bad <lb/>Water, to make it wholſome
        and well taſted <note n="*" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Plin. natural. hiſt. lib. xxv. cap. 3. </p>
        </note>; <lb/>it is probable that the <hi rend="italic">Arabians</hi>, who were Neigh-
        <lb/>bours to the <hi rend="italic">Syrians</hi>, and inhabited a dry and <lb/>barren
        Country, where little Corn was produced, <lb/>and Coffee-berries grew plentifully with
        little or <lb/>no Culture, found it moſt convenient to make <lb/>their <hi rend="italic"
          >Polenta</hi> of the Berries, or they might uſe <lb/>a Decoction of them toaſted, inſtead
        of the <hi rend="italic">Po- <lb/>lenta</hi> which their Neighbours the <hi rend="italic"
          >Syrians</hi> mixed <lb/>with their Water. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
