<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Plummer: A History of the Rabies Canina</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Andrew Plummer</persName>
            </author>
            <title>LI. A History of the Rabies canina; by Dr. ANDREW PLUMMER Professor of Medicine
              in the University of Edinburgh.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical essays and observations, published by a society in Edinburgh</title>
            <author>Philosophical Society of Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: printed by W. and T. Ruddimans, for Messrs. Hamilton and
                  Balfour, Booksellers</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1747</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">6</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">97-103</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108729439</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T132162</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ1_v6_0097">
    <body>
      <pb n="97"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">LI.</hi> A Hiſtory of the <hi rend="roman">Rabies canina</hi>: by Dr.
          <hi rend="sc">An- <lb/>drew Plummer</hi> Profeſſor of Medicine in <lb/>the Univerſity of
          <hi rend="roman">Edinburgh</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Young Gentleman, about ſeventeen Years <lb/>of Age, who had
        been Apprentice to a <lb/>Surgeon in the Country, and had come to <hi rend="italic">Edin-
          <lb/>burgh</hi> for his Improvement, about the Beginning <lb/>of <hi rend="italic"
          >December</hi> 1728, was bit by a Dog in the mid- <lb/>dle Finger of the right Hand, about
        the Middle <lb/>of the Nail. At firſt he ſaid the Dog belonged <lb/>to a Perſon of his
        Acquaintance; which Dog <lb/>had no Symptoms of Madneſs at the Time: But <lb/>afterwards he
        affirmed, that he was bit by a <lb/>ſmall Dog, which he obſerved ſtraggling on the
        <lb/>Streets, when he was endeavouring to catch him; <lb/>and that he never knew what became
        of the Dog. <lb/>The Wound gave him very little Trouble at firſt; <lb/>and he ſoon cured it
        in the ordinary way. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the Beginning of <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 1729, he firſt <lb/>complained of
        Pain in that Finger, reaching a- <lb/>long the Back of the Hand to the Elbow, accom- <pb
          n="98"/>
        <lb/>panied with a Numbneſs of the Finger. In the <lb/>Night betwixt the 6th and 7th of <hi
          rend="italic">January</hi>, he <lb/>was very hot and reſtleſs, the Pain ſtill increaſing;
        <lb/>ſo that next Morning he went to Dr. <hi rend="italic">Charles Al- <lb/>ſton</hi>, to
        aſk his Advice. He ſhewed him his <lb/>Hand; and told him, that he had been bit by a
        <lb/>Dog ſome Weeks before; but that the Dog was <lb/>ſtill alive, and well. The Doctor
        adviſed him, <lb/>to uſe an emollient and anodyne Fomentation, <lb/>and a cooling Diet.
        Accordingly he fomented <lb/>his Hand for ſome time that Evening; and, <lb/>having taken
        ſome light Slap for Supper, went <lb/>to Bed: But the Sharpneſs of the Pain made him
        <lb/>toſs all Night, and put him in a great Heat and <lb/>Sweat. Being very thirſty, he roſe
        in the Mid- <lb/>dle of the Night, to get ſome Water or Small <lb/>Beer to quench his
        Thirſt. When he got the <lb/>Liquor, he found that he could not drink ſo <lb/>much as he
        inclined, becauſe of ſome Difficulty <lb/>of ſwallowing. In the Morning, he attempted
        <lb/>again to drink; but the Liquor had ſcarce reach- <lb/>ed his Throat, when he was
        ſuddenly convulſed, <lb/>let fall the Cup, and ſaid to his Comrade, that <lb/>he was almoſt
        choaked. Some Hours after, <lb/>when he was getting out of Bed, he ſtaggered, <lb/>and
        complained of Giddineſs of his Head and <lb/>Sickneſs at his Stomach; and intreated his Com-
        <lb/>rade, to bring Dr. <hi rend="italic">Alſton</hi> to viſit him. The Do- <lb/>ctor having
        heard his Complaints, and finding <lb/>him ſtill hot and feveriſh, and his Hand much
        <lb/>pained, ordered him to be blooded immediate- <lb/>ly, and to have a purgative Ptiſan
        given him as <lb/>ſoon as poſſible. After letting ten Ounces of <lb/>Blood, the Pain of his
        Finger abated, and he <lb/>found himſelf eaſier. When the Ptiſan was <pb n="99"/>
        <lb/>brought, he made many Excuſes to ſhift the ta- <lb/>king of it; but, at the Intreaty of
        his Friends, <lb/>he made ſome Attempts; and declared he could <lb/>not ſwallow it. In the
        Evening he was perſua- <lb/>ded to try if he could get over a little ſoft <lb/>Bread ſoaked
        in Sack-whey. He took it into <lb/>his Mouth, rolled it about for ſome time; but, <lb/>when
        he was about to ſwallow it, he ſpit it out <lb/>ſuddenly, and with a convulſive Motion. How-
        <lb/>ever, that Night he ſlept pretty calmly, and had <lb/>a moderate Sweat upon him. Next
        Morning he <lb/>appeared ſomewhat diſordered, ſpoke incohe- <lb/>rently, fetched deep Sighs,
        complained he could <lb/>not breathe, and that ſomething interrupted the <lb/>Motion of his
        Heart. About eleven in the Fore- <lb/>noon, Dr. <hi rend="italic">Alſton</hi> came to viſit
        him. He found <lb/>him very uneaſy, toſſing his Head, and ſhifting <lb/>Poſtures. He
        obſerved that his Mouth was fre- <lb/>quently diſtorted, and other Muſcles of his Face
        <lb/>convulſed; his Breathing quick; and his Pulſe <lb/>frequent, but feeble. He aſked him
        to take a <lb/>little of a Cordial which was at hand. He ſaid, <lb/>he durſt not attempt to
        ſwallow; for it would <lb/>choak him: But, being preſſed to try it, he put <lb/>the Glaſs to
        his Mouth, and poured in the Li- <lb/>quor ſuddenly; but he as quickly threw it out
        <lb/>again, with a kind of Horror and Shivering. <lb/>The Doctor perceiving theſe
        extraordinary Sym- <lb/>ptoms, and apprehending the Lad to be in the <lb/>greateſt Danger,
        went to the Elaboratory about <lb/>twelve o'Clock, where he expected to meet with <lb/>ſome
        of his Colleagues the Profeſſors of Phyſick, <lb/>and carried Dr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Rutherford</hi>, Dr. <hi rend="italic">St. Clair</hi>, and <lb/>me, along with him, to
        his Patient, and, at the <lb/>ſame time, ſent to Mr. <hi rend="italic">Monro</hi>, to meet
        us there. <pb n="100"/>
        <lb/>We found him very much diſordered, like one <lb/>in an Agony, toſſing his Head and his
        Arms. His <lb/>Face was red and blotted, his Eyes wild and ſta- <lb/>ring, conſtantly
        ſquirting out his Spittle; ſome- <lb/>times ſtarting up ſuddenly from his Seat, then
        <lb/>throwing himſelf down upon the Bed. Yet he <lb/>anſwered Queſtions that were put to him
        pretty <lb/>compoſedly: Only he would now and then ſtop <lb/>ſhort of a ſudden, and beg that
        ſuch a Perſon, who <lb/>was his moſt intimate Friend and Comrade, <lb/>might not be admitted
        into the Room; for he <lb/>could not bear the Sight of him, nor hear his <lb/>Name
        mentioned; but could give no Reaſon for <lb/>it. He was deſired to ſip a little Liquor out
        of <lb/>a Tea-pot; he attempted it with great Relu- <lb/>ctancy; but ſpit it out
        immediately, appearing <lb/>to be in the greateſt Diſorder; complaining, that <lb/>his
        Breath was quite ſtopped. The Phyſicians <lb/>retired to a Coffee-houſe, to conſult if any
        thing <lb/>could be attempted with any Probability of Suc- <lb/>ceſs, and carried along with
        them the young <lb/>Man who had been the Patient's Bed-fellow and <lb/>moſt intimate
        Companion, that they might be <lb/>better informed of all that had happened to him. <lb/>He
        aſſured them, that, though he had told Dr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Alſton</hi> that his
        Finger was bit by a Dog belong- <lb/>ing to a Friend, which was then well, without <lb/>any
        Symptoms of the <hi rend="italic">Rabies</hi>; yet, when he re- <lb/>turned home,
        immediately after the Bite, he ſaid <lb/>it was given by a Dog ſtraggling in the Streets,
        <lb/>with a Collar about its Neck; and that he ne- <lb/>ver ſaw the Dog more. He informed
        them like- <lb/>wiſe that the unhappy Lad, at the Time he was <lb/>bitten, had a Gonorrhæa,
        for which he had been <lb/>taking Medicines privately: That his Method <pb n="101"/>
        <lb/>was, to take a Doſe of <hi rend="italic">Mercurius dulcis</hi> at Night, <lb/>and early
        next Morning ſome Purgative; the <lb/>Operation of which was generally over about
        <lb/>Mid-day: After which, he uſed to attend his <lb/>Profeſſors, and go about any other
        Buſineſs. The <lb/>Phyſicians had not ſit long, when another young <lb/>Man, a Comrade of
        the Patient, came in; tel- <lb/>ling them, That, ſoon after their Departure, he <lb/>found
        himſelf much worſe, and believed he was <lb/>a-dying; and therefore intreated him, to call
        <lb/>back the Phyſicians: But, as he was going out, <lb/>the Patient run after him, and fell
        upon him, in <lb/>a moſt outrageous manner; and would have done <lb/>him a Miſchief, if the
        People of the Houſe had <lb/>not come to his Aſſiſtance: That he was carried <lb/>back to
        his Chamber quite furious: That two <lb/>Men were ſcarce able to keep him in his Bed;
        <lb/>and that the Vein which had been opened the <lb/>Day before, had burſt open by the
        Violence of <lb/>his ſtruggling, and was bleeding exceſſively. As <lb/>he lodged in my
        Neighbourhood, I went along <lb/>with the young Man, to ſee in what Condition <lb/>he was
        then, and if any thing could be done for <lb/>him. It was the moſt diſmal Spectacle I had e-
        <lb/>ver ſeen. He was roaring and foaming, gnaſh- <lb/>ing his Teeth, endeavouring to bite
        and tear any <lb/>thing he could come at, with his Hands and <lb/>Teeth: He would bounce
        with ſuch Force, as to <lb/>heave up a Man that was lying acroſs him, and <lb/>make the Bed
        ſhake: His Face, Breaſt, Hands, <lb/>and Linen, were all covered over with Blood <lb/>and
        Sweat. After he had almoſt exhauſted his <lb/>Strength, and was panting for Breath, I ſpoke
        <lb/>to him. He knew me; and anſwered pretty <lb/>calmly. I told him, it was neceſſary his
        Arm <pb n="102"/>
        <lb/>ſhould be bound up, leſt he ſhould faint or die <lb/>by Loſs of Blood. He agreed. And
        as no body <lb/>elſe ſeemed fond of the Employment, I put a <lb/>Compreſs and Roller about
        his Arm, and wiped <lb/>the Sweat and Blood off his Face. As near as I <lb/>could gueſs,
        from the clotted Blood, his Linen <lb/>and Bed-cloaths that were wet with it, he had
        <lb/>loſt about twenty Ounces of Blood in this Fit; <lb/>which had laſted near an Hour. In
        this calm In- <lb/>terval, I aſked him, if he would drink? He ſaid, <lb/>he deſired nothing
        more; for he was exceeding <lb/>thirſty. I took up a Jug that was at hand, with <lb/>Milk
        and Water, and put it to his Mouth. He <lb/>ſnapt at it greedily, and fixed his Teeth in it:
        <lb/>He took in a Mouthful of the Liquor; but ſquirt- <lb/>ed it out again. He was inſtantly
        ſeized with a <lb/>violent Convulſion; which was followed by a <lb/>vomiting of a bilious
        Phlegm, with ſome thick <lb/>black Matter, like clotted Blood. Then the fu- <lb/>rious
        Paroxyſm returned; he raved, and ſtrug- <lb/>gled, and attempted to bite. I adviſed, that he
        <lb/>ſhould be bound carefully to the Bed; and that <lb/>proper Perſons ſhould look after
        him: Which <lb/>was done. Mr. <hi rend="italic">Monro</hi> and I returned in the E-
        <lb/>vening. He was foaming at the Mouth, making <lb/>a hideous Noiſe, rolling about his
        Tongue, and <lb/>making ſuch a Sound as Children wont to do <lb/>when they deſpiſe one that
        talks to them as a <lb/>Babbler. He had a convulſive Motion like the <lb/>Hickup, but
        ſtronger; and his Face was frequent- <lb/>ly diſtorted with Spaſms. Even at this Time he
        <lb/>knew Mr. <hi rend="italic">Monro</hi> and me, though he raved in- <lb/>ceſſantly. He
        continued in this Condition till <lb/>ſix at Night; when, his Strength being quite <pb
          n="103"/>
        <lb/>exhauſted, he lay motionleſs for half an Hour; <lb/>and then expired. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
