<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Monro: Reflections on the Aneurism occasioned by Blood -
          letting</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Alexr. Monro</persName>
            </author>
            <title>XVII. Reflections on the Aneurism occasioned by Blood - letting; by the same.
            </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical essays and observations, published by a society in Edinburgh</title>
            <author>Philosophical Society of Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh : printed by W. and T. Ruddimans, for Messrs. Hamilton and
                  Balfour, Booksellers</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1747</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">2</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">243-249</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108728263</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T132162</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ1_v2_0243">
    <body>
      <pb n="243"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XVII.</hi> Reflections on the <hi rend="roman">Aneuriſm</hi>
        occaſioned <lb/>by Blood-letting; by the ſame. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE Figures herewith ſent will give a bet- <lb/>ter Idea of the
        Situation and Courſe of <lb/>the Arteries of the Arm that are the Subject <lb/>of the
        following Reflections, than any Words <lb/>can; and therefore I ſhall not trouble you with
        <lb/>any verbal Deſcription, but ſhall proceed to the <lb/>Explication of <hi rend="italic"
          >Table</hi> II. </p>
      <figure>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 1. repreſents the moſt ordinary Diſtri- <lb/>bution of
          the humeral Artery. </p>
        <p>
          <list>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>1. A Part of the <hi rend="italic">pectoral</hi> Muſcle. </item>
            <pb n="244"/>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>2. The <hi rend="italic">Biceps flexor cubiti</hi>. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>3. The <hi rend="italic">Coraco-brachialis</hi> Muſcle. </item>
            <item>
              <lb/>iv. The <hi rend="italic">Brachiæus internus</hi>. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>4. The <hi rend="italic">Brachiæus externus</hi>. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>5. The <hi rend="italic">Brevis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Longus Extenſor</hi>. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>6. The <hi rend="italic">Pronator radii teres</hi>. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>7. The <hi rend="italic">Supinator radii longus</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
                >Extenſor <lb/>carpi radialis</hi> drawn outwards by a Thread. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>8. The <hi rend="italic">Supinator radii brevis</hi>. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>9. The <hi rend="italic">Flexor carpi radialis</hi>. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>10. The common Origin of the <hi rend="italic">Palmaris <lb/>longus</hi> and <hi
                rend="italic">Flexor carpi ulnaris</hi>. </item>
          </list>
          <list>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>A The Trunk of the <hi rend="italic">humeral Artery</hi> giving <lb/>off Branches
              in its Courſe to the neighbouring <lb/>Muſcles. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>B The Place below the Joint of the Elbow, <lb/>where it is about to ſplit into
              its two large <lb/>Branches. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>C The <hi rend="italic">radial</hi> Branch. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>D The common Trunk of the <hi rend="italic">ulnar</hi> and <hi rend="italic">me-
                <lb/>dian</hi> Arteries. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>E A Branch going off from the <hi rend="italic">humeral</hi> Ar- <lb/>tery above
              the Elbow toward the internal <hi rend="italic">Con- <lb/>dyle</hi>, behind which it
              anaſtomoſes ſometimes <lb/>by a large Canal with a Branch ſent up from <lb/>the <hi
                rend="italic">Ulnar</hi>, oftner they communicate by a great <lb/>many ſmall
              Branches, and frequently I could <lb/>not diſcover any Conjunction of theſe two Ar-
              <lb/>teries. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>F The Part of the <hi rend="italic">humeral</hi> Artery, where it <lb/>commonly
              begins to be covered by the <hi rend="italic">Aponeu- <lb/>roſis</hi> of the <hi
                rend="italic">Biceps</hi> Muſcle. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>G A Branch ſent up from the radial Artery <lb/>behind the external Condyle of the
                <hi rend="italic">Os humeri</hi>, <pb n="245"/>
              <lb/>to anaſtomoſe with ſuch a Branch of the <hi rend="italic">hume- <lb/>ral</hi>
              Artery as E is. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of the humeral artery and the adjacent muscles on a separate
          fold-out page.</figDesc>
      </figure>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſame Parts are pointed out in the three <lb/>following Figures, by the Letters and
        Cyphers <lb/>employed in the firſt Figure, which makes a <lb/>Repetition of their
        Explication needleſs. </p>
      <figure>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 2. is borrowed from Mr. <hi rend="italic">Cowper</hi>'s
          Scheme <lb/>of Arteries <note n="(a)" place="bottom" rend="size(0.7)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) Appendix to the Anatomy of human Bodies, Tab.
              <lb/>III. </p>
          </note>. </p>
        <p>
          <list>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>α Is a Branch ſent off from the <hi rend="italic">humeral</hi> Ar- <lb/>tery, to
              anaſtomoſe behind the internal Con- <lb/>dyle of the <hi rend="italic">Humerus</hi>,
              with the Artery β, which <lb/>comes from the Trunk of the <hi rend="italic">ulnar</hi>
              and <hi rend="italic">medi- <lb/>an</hi> Arteries. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>H The <hi rend="italic">ulnar</hi> Artery. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>I. The <hi rend="italic">median</hi> Artery. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">k</hi> Branches given to the Muſcles of the Hand <lb/>from the
              humeral Artery, juſt as it is about to <lb/>ſplit into its Branches. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration showing the different branches of the arteries, on a separate
          fold-out page.</figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 3. Shews the <hi rend="italic">humeral</hi> Artery
          dividing <lb/>into two great Branches as it is coming out <lb/>from the Arm-pit. Theſe
          Branches are repre- <lb/>ſented as if they lay at each others Sides, which <lb/>the
          oblique View I gave of them to the Painter <lb/>obliged him to; but the one γ, which
          after- <lb/>wards becomes the <hi rend="italic">radial</hi>, is placed directly an-
          <lb/>terior to the other in the Subject, the <hi rend="italic">ulnar</hi> δ <lb/>lying
          pretty cloſe to the Bone. </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration otherwise similar to the first figure except that the two branches
          of the artery are visible.</figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 4. Repreſents the <hi rend="italic">humeral</hi> Artery
          ſplit- <lb/>ting near the Middle of the Arm, ε being the <pb n="246"/>
          <lb/>larger anterior more ſuperficial Branch, which <lb/>goes on to divide as the <hi
            rend="italic">humeral</hi> Artery in <hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi>
          <lb/>1. does, while the leſſer Branch ζ runs cloſe on <lb/>the Bone to open into the
          common Trunk of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">ulnar</hi> and <hi rend="italic">median</hi>
          Arteries. </p>
        <p>
          <list>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>H The <hi rend="italic">ulnar</hi> Artery. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>I The <hi rend="italic">median</hi> Artery. </item>
            <item rend="indent">
              <lb/>L The Branch marked β in the ſecond Fi- <lb/>gure. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <figDesc>Another illustration showing the two branches of the artery and the adjacent
          muscles, on a separate fold-out page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <p rend="hanging space">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Not.</hi> The Muſcles 6, 9, 10. are here cut <lb/>through, and hang
        over the Cubit, while <lb/>thoſe marked 7, are drawn outwards, that <lb/>the Arteries might
        be diſtinctly ſeen. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>I ſtill preſerve the Arms repreſented by <hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi>
        <lb/>1, 3, 4<choice>
          <corr>.</corr>
          <sic>,</sic>
        </choice>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>By the Diſtribution of the <hi rend="italic">humeral</hi> Artery <lb/>in <hi
          rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 1. it would appear that the Artery <lb/>which is in hazard of
        being hurt by the Lan- <lb/>cet in Blood-letting of the Arm, is for ordina- <lb/>ry the
        Trunk of the <hi rend="italic">humeral</hi> Artery, and that <lb/>the Lancet muſt pierce the
        tendinous <hi rend="italic">Aponeu- <lb/>roſis</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">biceps</hi>
        Muſcle before it touches <lb/>the Artery. To be ſtill more aſſured of this, <lb/>I puſhed
        Pins into the Arms of ſeveral Bodies <lb/>at the ordinary Place where the <hi rend="italic"
          >Baſilick</hi> Vein <lb/>is opened, and where the Cicatrices of for- <lb/>mer Venæſections
        were ſeen; and allowing <lb/>the Pins to remain there, I diſſected the Parts <lb/>till I ſaw
        what has been above aſſerted to be <lb/>true. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Sometimes when the <hi rend="italic">median</hi> Vein is open- <lb/>ed lower than
        ordinary, the <hi rend="italic">radial</hi> Artery may <pb n="247"/>
        <lb/>be hurt; but then its Wound muſt be ſo near <lb/>its Riſe from the Trunk, that it is
        impoſſible <lb/>to make any Ligature on the <hi rend="italic">radial</hi> Artery a-
        <lb/>bove the Aperture; and therefore, ſeeing the <lb/>humeral Artery muſt be tied, if the
        Operation <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">Aneuriſm</hi> is performed, the Conſequen- <lb/>ces
        will be the ſame as if the humeral Artery <lb/>had been wounded. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In all Patients then whoſe Veſſels are diſtri- <lb/>buted in the common Way, without
        any con- <lb/>ſiderable <hi rend="italic">Anaſtomoſis</hi> between the <hi rend="italic"
          >humeral</hi> Ar- <lb/>tery and its large Branches in the Fore-Arm; <lb/>it is in vain to
        expect that any Pulſe ſhould be <lb/>felt at the Wriſt, immediately after the Ope-
        <lb/>ration of the <hi rend="italic">Aneuriſm</hi> is performed; and at <lb/>the ſame Time,
        the Want of a Pulſe there, <lb/>needs not make the Surgeon go on precipitate- <lb/>ly to the
        Amputation of the Member, becauſe <lb/>the numerous ſmall Anaſtomoſes may be ſuffi-
        <lb/>cient to keep Life in it, and may poſſibly be <lb/>gradually enlarged ſo much, as to
        reſtore Vi- <lb/>gour and Strength to it, and even to make a <lb/>perceptible Pulſe at the
        Wriſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the Operation of the <hi rend="italic">Aneuriſm</hi> is per- <lb/>formed at the
        Bending of the Elbow to one <lb/>who has the <hi rend="italic">Anaſtomoſis</hi> repreſented
        in <hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 2, <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">humeral</hi> Artery muſt be
        tied, but the Pulſe <lb/>at the interior Side of the Wriſt will continue, <lb/>and probably
        that on the exterior Side will <lb/>ſoon be reſtored, becauſe the Blood may have <lb/>the
        ſhort retrograde Motion from the Inſerti- <lb/>on of the anaſtomoſing Tube into the <hi
          rend="italic">ulnar</hi>
        <lb/>Artery, to the Place where the <hi rend="italic">radial</hi> Artery <lb/>begins,
        without any great Diminution of its <lb/><hi rend="italic">Momentum</hi>. </p>
      <pb n="248"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thoſe who happen to have ſuch a Diviſion <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">humeral</hi>
        Artery as is repreſented in <hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi>
        <lb/>3. can only have the <hi rend="italic">radial</hi> Artery hurt in Ve- <lb/>næſection,
        and after the Operation of the <hi rend="italic">Aneu- <lb/>riſm</hi> will have a ſtronger
        Pulſe than formerly <lb/>in the interior Side of the Wriſt, but will pro- <lb/>bably want it
        in the exterior Side. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If the Veſſels anaſtomoſe as in <hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 4. you'll <lb/>readily ſee,
        that the anterior Branch only be- <lb/>ing hurt, the Operation of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Aneuriſm</hi> may <lb/>be performed without interrupting intirely the <lb/>Courſe of the
        Blood either in the <hi rend="italic">radial</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ul- <lb/>nar</hi>
        Artery; and therefore the Pulſe may ſtill <lb/>be felt in the common Place on both Side of
        <lb/>the Wriſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I have very little to add, by way of Re- <lb/>marks on the Hiſtory related by Mr. <hi
          rend="italic">Macgill</hi>, <lb/>having, in the Account already given of the
        <lb/>Formation of <hi rend="italic">Aneuriſms</hi>, prevented any Expli- <lb/>cation of the
        principal <hi rend="italic">Phænomena</hi>. I may <lb/>however obſerve, that in that Hiſtory
        we can <lb/>trace the gradual Formation of the <hi rend="italic">Polypus</hi>, <lb/>and from
        the Mixture of the deeper-coloured <lb/>Parts of the Blood then ſqueezed out, with <lb/>ſome
        of the diſſolved cellular Membrane, may <lb/>underſtand how a Liquor like to Coffee made
        <lb/>of half-burnt Beans could be collected within <lb/>this <hi rend="italic"
        >Aneuriſm</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If the common Notion of the <hi rend="italic">true Aneuriſm</hi>
        <lb/>being a <hi rend="italic">Sac</hi> formed by the dilated muſcular <lb/>Coat of
        Arteries, has not had its Riſe from <lb/>Theory only, I would ſuſpect that the firſt
        <lb/>Aſſertors of it, ſeeing the <hi rend="italic">Pleura</hi> covering an <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Aneuriſm</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi>, or the tendinous <hi
          rend="italic">A- <lb/>poneuroſis</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Biceps</hi> here in the Arm
        ad- <pb n="249"/>
        <lb/>hering firmly to ſuch a Tumor, miſtook them <lb/>for the muſcular Coat of the Artery. I
        have <lb/>an Argument for this Suſpicion which ſeems <lb/>very ſtrong to me, whatever it may
        do to o- <lb/>thers who are leſs liable to miſtake one Thing <lb/>for another; it is this,
        that notwithſtanding <lb/>my Theory and Diſſections had brought me <lb/>to think true <hi
          rend="italic">Aneuriſms</hi> to be at leaſt a very <lb/>uncommon Diſeaſe, yet when I ſaw
        Mr. <hi rend="italic">Mac- <lb/>gill</hi> lay the tendinous <hi rend="italic"
          >Aponeuroſis</hi> bare, I was <lb/>ready to have renounced my Opinion, being
        <lb/>perſwaded it was the muſcular Coat of the Ar- <lb/>tery, till he moſt dexterouſly
        proſecuted the <hi rend="italic">A- <lb/>poneuroſis</hi> to its Riſe from the <hi
          rend="italic">Biceps</hi>, and ſo <lb/>fully convinced me of the Miſtake, into which
        <lb/>I ſhould moſt readily have been led without diſ- <lb/>covering it, if the Operation had
        been perfor- <lb/>med in the more ſpeedy Way of laying the <lb/>whole Tumor open by one
        Inciſion. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
