<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: The Effects of the Conessi Bark</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>IV. The Effects of the Conessi Bark, by —. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical essays and observations, published by a society in Edinburgh</title>
            <author>Philosophical Society of Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: printed by W. and T. Ruddimans, for Messrs. Hamilton and
                  Balfour, Booksellers</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1747</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">3</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">30-32</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108900648</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T132162</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ1_v3_0030">
    <body>
      <pb n="30"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">IV.</hi> The Effects of the <hi rend="roman">Coneſſi Bark</hi>, by —. </head>
      <div>
        <salute rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Gentlemen, <lb/>
        </salute>
        <p rend="italic"><hi rend="dc(2)">N</hi>Ot having Allowance from my Friend, who <lb/>wrote
          me the incloſed Letter, to publiſh his <lb/>Name, I cannot take upon me to communicate
          <lb/>it; but can aſſure you, his Integrity, good Senſe <lb/>and Knowledge, are ſuch as may
          give entire <lb/>Credit to his Information; and lately I cured <lb/>an obſtinate Dyſentery
          of three Months ſtand- <lb/>ing, which had yielded nothing to a great Va- <lb/>riety of
          other Medicines, by giving the <hi rend="roman">Coneſſi <lb/>Bark</hi> in the Form
          preſcribed by him. I am </p>
        <signed rend="space align-right">
          <lb/>Your moſt humble Servant, <lb/><hi rend="sc space">Alex<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Monro.
          </hi>
        </signed>
      </div>
      <pb n="31"/>
      <div>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE Tree, of which I gave you ſome of the <lb/>Bark as a
          Specifick in <hi rend="italic">Diarrhœas</hi>, grows <lb/>on the <hi rend="italic"
            >Cormandel</hi> Coaſt in the <hi rend="italic">Eaſt-Indies</hi>, <lb/>where it is called
            <hi rend="italic">Coneſſi</hi>, and is not unlike the <lb/><hi rend="italic"
            >Cadogapala</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Hortus Malabaricus</hi>. The <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">Coneſſi-ſeca</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Coneſſi-bark</hi> of the ſmall
          young <lb/>Branches of the Tree which has leaſt Moſs, or <lb/>external inſipid Scurf on
          it, is to be choſen, <lb/>and all that Scurf is to be ſcraped off. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The clean Bark being pounded into a very <lb/>fine Powder, is made into an Electuary,
          with <lb/>Syrup of Oranges, and taken to the Quantity <lb/>of half a Drachm, or more, four
          Times a Day, <lb/>for three or four Days. The firſt Day it in- <lb/>creaſes the Number and
          Quantity of the Stools, <lb/>but without increaſing the Gripes. The ſecond <lb/>Day the
          Bark is taken, the Colour of the Stools <lb/>is mended; and on the third or fourth Day,
          <lb/>their Conſiſtence generally comes near to a na- <lb/>tural State, when it ſucceeds at
          all. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In recent <hi rend="italic">Diarrhœæ</hi>, ariſing from Irregula- <lb/>rities in
          Diet, without a Fever, this Medicine <lb/>ſeldom fails to make a Cure, if a Vomit of <hi
            rend="italic">I- <lb/>pecacuanna</hi> is given immediately before the Pa- <lb/>tient
          begins the Uſe of the Bark. The ſame <lb/>Management alſo is attended commonly with
          <lb/>Succeſs in Perſons of a lax Habit of Body, who <lb/>are troubled with an habitual <hi
            rend="italic">Diarrhœa</hi> in moiſt <lb/>rainy Weather, a remarkable Itching in the
          <lb/>Skin being felt on the third or fourth Day. To <lb/>ſuch Patients eſpecially, the
          Electuary ought to <lb/>be given Morning and Evening, for ſome Time <lb/>after they are
          ſeemingly cured. Their Drink <lb/>ſhould be Water wherein Rice hath been boil- <pb n="32"/>
          <lb/>ed, and ſometimes Emulſions of the cold Seeds, <lb/>with <hi rend="italic">Sal
            prunell.</hi> are neceſſary. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If there is a Fever with the Looſeneſs, that <lb/>muſt be removed by Bloodings and
          cool Emul- <lb/>ſions, or <hi rend="italic">Decoct. alb.</hi> with <hi rend="italic">Sal
            prunell.</hi> before <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Coneſſi-Bark</hi> is given. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Sometimes when the Cauſe of a <hi rend="italic">Diarrhœa</hi>, <lb/>ſtopp'd by this
          Medicine, lies beyond the inte- <lb/>ſtinal Canal, the Patient, in a few Days after,
          <lb/>complains of a Pain in the right <hi rend="italic">Hypochonder</hi>, <lb/>or in the
          right Shoulder, or over the Stomach <lb/>towards the left Side, cauſing often a dull Senſe
          <lb/>of Pain, near or above the left Clavicle, with a <lb/>feveriſh Pulſe. As ſoon as
          theſe Symptoms ap- <lb/>pear, the Patient muſt be blooded, and his Blood <lb/>will be
          ſizy, or with a tough yellowiſh Cruſt on <lb/>the Top, when it has coagulated. The Quan-
          <lb/>tity of Blood to be taken away, and the repeat- <lb/>ing the Venæſection, muſt be
          determined by <lb/>the Patient's Strength, the Degree of Fever, <lb/>and Sharpneſs of his
          Pain. In ſuch Caſes how- <lb/>ever the Blooding ſeldom removes the Pain en- <lb/>tirely;
          but after the Fever is brought ſufficient- <lb/>ly down by the Loſs of Blood, I have
          ſeldom <lb/>miſſed to complete the Cure, by giving <hi rend="italic">ſweet
            <lb/>Mercury</hi>, or rather <hi rend="italic">Calomel</hi>, for ſome Days, <lb/>in
          ſmall Quantities, as an Alterative. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I ought to obſerve, That the Bark ſhould be <lb/>freſh-powdered, and the Electuary
          new made <lb/>every Day or ſecond Day, otherwiſe the Bark <lb/>loſes its auſtere, but
          grateful Bitterneſs on the <lb/>Palate, and its proper Effects on the Inteſtines. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
