<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Jamieson: A large Steatom passing with the Oesophagus from the Thorax into the
          Abdomen</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>James Jamieson</persName>
            </author>
            <title>XXVI. A large Steatom passing with the Oesophagus from the Thorax into the
              Abdomen; by Mr. JAMES JAMIESON Surgeon at Kelso. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical essays and observations, published by a society in Edinburgh</title>
            <author>Philosophical Society of Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: printed by W. and T. Ruddimans, for Messrs. Hamilton and
                  Balfour, Booksellers</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1747</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">3</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">280-283</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108900648</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T132162</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ1_v3_0280">
    <body>
      <pb n="280"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXVI.</hi> A large <hi rend="roman">Steatom</hi> paſſing with the <hi
          rend="roman">Oeſo- <lb/>phagus</hi> from the <hi rend="roman">Thorax</hi> into the <hi
          rend="roman">Abdomen</hi>; <lb/>by Mr. <hi rend="sc">James Jamieson</hi> Surgeon at <hi
          rend="roman">Kelſo</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">A</hi> Carpenter in this Place, thirty ſix Years of <lb/>Age, of a
        thin Make of Body, aſked my <lb/>Advice about the middle of <hi rend="italic">February</hi>
        1732; his <lb/>Complaints were, Pains at the Heart, in the <lb/>Pit of the Stomach, both
        Sides of the <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi>, <lb/>and betwixt his Shoulders; a great
        Difficulty <lb/>in ſwallowing, and frequent Inclination to vo- <lb/>mit. He told me it was
        about ſix Years, ſince, <lb/>upon a ſudden Grief, he was firſt ſeized with <lb/>the Pain,
        and frequent Palpitations at his Heart, <lb/>and that the other Symptoms came on gradual-
        <lb/>ly afterwards, but never kept him from his or- <lb/>dinary Work till now. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>At my firſt Viſit I took twelve Ounces of <lb/>Blood from his Arm; the Blood was ſizy
        like <lb/>that in a Rheumatiſm. Next Day he took <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pulv. Ipecacuan.
          Drach. ſem. Tartar. Emet. <lb/>Gr. <hi rend="roman">ii.</hi></hi> which purged him four or
        five Times, <lb/>but did not occaſion the leaſt <hi rend="italic">Nauſea</hi>. I gave <pb
          n="281"/>
        <lb/>him alſo Doſes of the <hi rend="italic">Pillul. Cummoſ.</hi> twice a <lb/>Day, waſhing
        them down with <hi rend="italic">Decoct. Amar.</hi>
        <lb/>in which a ſmall Quantity of <hi rend="italic">Sal. Abſinth.</hi> was <lb/>diſſolved;
        cauſed the pained Parts to be fo- <lb/>mented with a ſtrong Decoction of the Aroma-
        <lb/>tick Plants, and applied a large Plaiſter of <hi rend="italic">The- <lb/>riac
          Andromach. Ol. Mac. per expreſſ.</hi> and the <lb/>Powder of the carminative Seeds. The
        Blood- <lb/>ing gave him ſome Remiſſion of Pain, and was <lb/>repeated twice in the
        following Weeks, <lb/>with ſome ſhort Relief each Time. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Finding however his Complaints rather in- <lb/>creaſe, I obliged him to call a
        Phyſician, which <lb/>his Poverty had made him obſtinately refuſe <lb/>to do hitherto; and
        while Dr. <hi rend="italic">Abernethy</hi> was <lb/>ſent for, he ſhewed me a hard painful
        Tumor <lb/>immediately below the <hi rend="italic">Cartilago Xiphoides</hi>, <lb/>which he
        ſaid he had only diſcovered the pre- <lb/>ceding Night. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Doctor</hi> ſuſpecting from the Account the <lb/>Patient gave of
        his Diſeaſe, and from the Ap- <lb/>pearance of this Tumour, that an Abſceſs was <lb/>forming
        in the Stomach, ordered him a Milk <lb/>Diet, and Lintſeed Tea, or a Decoction of <hi
          rend="italic">He- <lb/>dera Terreſt.</hi> or Milk and Water for ordinary <lb/>Drink, and
        cauſed an emollient Cataplaſm to <lb/>be applied to the Tumor. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He continued to turn gradually worſe, till <lb/>about the Middle of <hi rend="italic"
          >March</hi>, when he was at- <lb/>tacked with a vomiting, which none of the dif-
        <lb/>ferent Stomachicks nor Opiats given him could <lb/>reſtrain, but were thrown back again
        as ſoon <lb/>as ſwallowed. His Thirſt became exceſſive and <lb/>perpetual; but all his
        Drink, though taken in <lb/>very ſmall Quantities at a Time, was vomited <pb n="282"/>
        <lb/>as quickly as his Medicines, without increaſing <lb/>his Pains; and a <hi rend="italic"
          >Singultus</hi> ſoon came on, <lb/>which continued till his Death. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He paſſed very little <hi rend="italic">Fæces</hi> by the <hi rend="italic">Anus</hi>,
        and <lb/>theſe were generally procured by gentle Cly- <lb/>ſters. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>His Urine was for the moſt Part limpid, <lb/>when there was any Sediment, it was white. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>During the whole Courſe of this Diſeaſe, the <lb/>Patient's Pulſe was never quick or
        ſtrong, but <lb/>low and languid, and ſometimes intermitted. <lb/>His Pains were always moſt
        ſevere in the Night, <lb/>and at laſt deprived him almoſt entirely of <lb/>Sleep; and for a
        whole Month he did not ly <lb/>down, but ſat in the Bed, or on a Chair bend- <lb/>ed
        forwards with his Head on a Pillow. In <lb/>this melancholy Condition he languiſhed till the
        <lb/>firſt of <hi rend="italic">April</hi>, when he died. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On laying open the <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Abdomen</hi>,
        <lb/>we obſerved a prodigious large ſteatomatous <lb/>Body, which filled a great Part of the
          <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi>, <lb/>being grown to the <hi rend="italic">Pleura</hi> in
        both Sides, to <lb/>the larger Share of the <hi rend="italic">Mediaſtinum</hi> and <hi
          rend="italic">Peri- <lb/>cardium</hi>; and then accompanying the <hi rend="italic"
          >Oeſopha- <lb/>gus</hi>, they paſſed together through the <hi rend="italic">Dia-
          <lb/>phragm</hi>, having enlarged the Paſſage in this Mu- <lb/>ſcle conſiderably, and
        ſtraitning the <hi rend="italic">Oeſopha- <lb/>gus</hi>. After entring the <hi rend="italic"
          >Abdomen</hi>, it was ſtretch'd <lb/>along the <hi rend="italic">Dorſum</hi> of the
        Stomach to the <hi rend="italic">Pylo- <lb/>rus</hi>, which it alſo compreſſed greatly. Both
        <lb/>the Orifices of the Stomach being ſo much con- <lb/>tracted, that I could ſcarce puſh
        my Finger <lb/>through either. I was about to have cut out <lb/>this whole Tumor, to meaſure
        and weigh it, <lb/>but was oppoſed by the Relations; and there- <pb n="283"/>
        <lb/>fore behoved to content myſelf with examining <lb/>its Subſtance as it lay in the Body.
        It was ſo <lb/>hard, my Knife could ſcarce cut it, but after <lb/>a tranſverſe Inciſion,
        ſeveral Sinuſes formed in <lb/>the firm white Subſtance diſcovered themſelves; <lb/>ſome of
        them contained a Matter like a <hi rend="italic">Meliceris</hi>, <lb/>in others, it was
        a-kin to that of the <hi rend="italic">Atheroma</hi>, <lb/>and in a third ſort it was
        purulent and fetid. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Fat of the <hi rend="italic">Omentum</hi> was all waſted, but <lb/>all the other
          <hi rend="italic"><sic>Viſera</sic></hi> were ſound enough. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
