<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Barry: The Bladder become schirrous, from a singular Cause</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Edward Barry</persName>
            </author>
            <title>XXXV. The Bladder become schirrous, from a singular Cause; by Doctor EDWARD
              BARRY, Physician at Cork in Ireland.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical essays and observations, published by a society in Edinburgh</title>
            <author>Philosophical Society of Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh : printed by W. and T. Ruddimans, for Messrs. Hamilton and
                  Balfour, Booksellers</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1747</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">1</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">266-269</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108727930</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T132162</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ1_v1_0266">
    <body>
      <pb n="266"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXXV.</hi> The Bladder become ſchirrous, from <lb/>a ſingular Cauſe;
        by Doctor <hi rend="sc">Edward Bar- <lb/>ry</hi>, Phyſician at <hi rend="roman">Cork</hi> in
          <hi rend="roman">Ireland</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>R. <hi rend="italic">Moſes Dean</hi>, a Gentleman of a con-
        <lb/>ſiderable Family and Fortune, natural- <lb/>ly of a ſtrong Habit of Body, and of a
        ſtrictly <lb/>temperate Manner of Living, while a Child <lb/>had often diſcharged Gravel and
        ſmall Stones <lb/>with his Urine. The Symptoms attending <lb/>ſuch a Diſorder increaſed as
        he grew older; <lb/>and about the Age of Twenty four he was cut <lb/>on the Gripe (as the
        leſſer Operation is com- <lb/>monly called) for the Stone, and a very large <lb/>one was
        taken out of his Bladder. Soon after <lb/>the Wound in the <hi rend="italic">Perinæum</hi>
        was healed, he <lb/>complained of a Pain in that Part; this was <lb/>ſucceded by a hard
        Tumor which gradually <lb/>increaſed in a painful Manner, for the Space <lb/>of twenty one
        Years, at which Time it was ſo <lb/>large, that it was equal to the Size of a Turky
        <lb/>Egg, and prevented him from riding or ſitting, <lb/>but with great Uneaſineſs. One Day
        being in <lb/>a Chariot, he received a ſudden Jolt, which <lb/>gave him ſuch exquiſite Pain,
        that he ſent for <lb/>a Surgeon, and told him that he was determi- <lb/>ned to have the
        Tumor cut out or opened im- <lb/>mediately. The Surgeon tho' ignorant of the <lb/>Nature of
        the Tumor, applied a Cauſtick, and <lb/>afterwards cutting on the <hi rend="italic"
          >Eſchar</hi>, a very hard <lb/>Reſiſtance was perceived, which, by dilating <lb/>the Part,
        he found to proceed from a large <lb/>Stone about four Inches and a half in Length, <lb/>and
        two and a half in Breadth, contained be- <pb n="267"/>
        <lb/>tween the Bladder and <hi rend="italic">Perinæum</hi>. The Stone <lb/>had a ſmall
        riſing Proceſs which was fixed in <lb/>the Orifice of the Bladder. After the Stone <lb/>was
        extracted, the Urine conſtantly flowed out <lb/>of that Orifice, which always obliged him to
        <lb/>keep a Veſſel or Spunge to receive it, till the <lb/>Time of his Death, which was
        ſeventeen Years <lb/>after this laſt Operation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>During that Time ſeveral ſmall Stones paſſed <lb/>thro' that Orifice, which, with the
        Acrimony <lb/>of the Urine perpetually running off, not only <lb/>hindred him from ſitting
        or riding, but made <lb/>his whole Life a conſtant Scene of Miſery. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A Year before <choice>
          <corr>he</corr>
          <sic>de</sic>
        </choice> died, purulent Matter fre- <lb/>quently ſubſided in his Urine; all the Sym-
        <lb/>ptoms continued to increaſe, attended with <lb/>bloody Urine, a Pain in the Region of
        the Kid- <lb/>neys, Colicks and frequent Vomiting. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On diſſecting his Body, at which ſeveral were <lb/>preſent, his Kidneys were found very
        large, <lb/>with an unequal rough Surface, owing to a <lb/>great Quantity of Gravel
        collected in them. A <lb/>large Stone which could not paſs the <hi rend="italic">Ureter</hi>
        <lb/>was lodged in the <hi rend="italic">Pelvis</hi> of the right Kidney, <lb/>which was
        greatly dilated. In the left Kidney <lb/>a large Stone was found in a Bed of Corrup-
        <lb/>tion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the <hi rend="italic">Pelvis</hi> was examined I was at a <lb/>Loſs to find the
        Bladder, nothing that bore the <lb/>leaſt Reſemblance to it appearing, and in the <lb/>Place
        of it a hard ſolid Subſtance was diſcover- <lb/>ed, which I concluded muſt have been the
        Blad- <lb/>der, by the Inſertion of the <hi rend="italic">Ureters</hi> into it, <lb/>which
        diſcharged the Urine into the <hi rend="italic">Fiſtula</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This indurated ſchirrous Bladder had no Ca- <pb n="268"/>
        <lb/>vity but what the ſmall Stream of Urine kept <lb/>open; it weighed thirteen Ounces and
        a quar- <lb/>ter. Cutting thro' it, the Inſide was white, <lb/>and it ſeemed to conſiſt of
        ſeveral diſtinct ſchir- <lb/>rous Glands. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From the Inſertion of the Ureters to the ex- <lb/>ternal Orifice was one continued
        fiſtulous Ca- <lb/>vity. The external Margin of the <hi rend="italic">Perinæum</hi>
        <lb/>was mortified, the Inſide of the <hi rend="italic">Fiſtula</hi> was ul- <lb/>cerated,
        and had large lateral Sinuſes, and that <lb/>Part of the indurated Bladder thro' which the
        <lb/>Urine paſſed was cancerated. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It plainly appears that this uncommon Diſ- <lb/>order was owing to the external Orifice
        in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Perinæum</hi> being healed after the Operation, be- <lb/>fore
        the internal Orifice in the Bladder was u- <lb/>nited; by which means the ſandy Sediment in
        <lb/>the Urine ſubſiding and puſhing thro' it, form- <lb/>ed a Stone between that and the
          <hi rend="italic">Perinæum</hi>, <lb/>which for the Space of twenty one Years in-
        <lb/>creaſed, and dilated the adjacent Parts, till they <lb/>could not admit any further
        Diſtenſion, and <lb/>then the ſmall riſing Proceſs filled the Orifice. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I never viſited this Gentleman till about two <lb/>Years before he died, and by a
        cooling, open- <lb/>ing, Anodyne Regimen, endeavoured to pal- <lb/>liate the Symptoms. This
        was all the Relief <lb/>his Caſe would then admit of; but when the <lb/>laſt Stone was taken
        out, there were two dif- <lb/>ferent Methods by which this preternatural Al- <lb/>teration
        in the Bladder might, I believe, have <lb/>been prevented. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The firſt was by uniting the Orifice in the <lb/>Neck of the Bladder, by firſt reducing
        it to a <lb/>green Wound; but as the Lips of it muſt have <pb n="269"/>
        <lb/>been very callous, this might have been attend- <lb/>ed with great Difficulty and
        Danger. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The next was, by injecting thro' the Ori- <lb/>fice into the Bladder Morning and
        Evening a- <lb/>bout a Pound of any detergent Injection, which <lb/>by that Means might have
        kept it pliable and <lb/>free from Obſtructions, and given artificial <lb/>Motion, which
        might have ſupplied the Defect <lb/>of the natural one, and perhaps in ſome Caſes <lb/>where
        the Habit of the Body is diſpoſed to <lb/>form calculous Concretions, it might be pre-
        <lb/>ferable to the former; for it is certain that a <lb/>great Number of Stones did often
        paſs thro' <lb/>this Orifice, which were too large to be diſ- <lb/>charged by the <hi
          rend="italic">Urethra</hi>, and which might o- <lb/>therwiſe have been more quickly fatal
        to him <lb/>than this Diſorder, in which he miſerably lan- <lb/>guiſhed ſo many Years. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
