<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Willison: A Wound with a hot Iron penetrating the Pelvis</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Andrew Willison</persName>
            </author>
            <title>XV. A Wound with a hot Iron penetrating the Pelvis; by Dr. ANDREW WILLISON
              Physician at Dundee.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical essays and observations, published by a society in Edinburgh</title>
            <author>Philosophical Society of Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: printed by W. and T. Ruddimans, for Messrs. Hamilton and
                  Balfour, Booksellers</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1747</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">4</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">236-238</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108728625</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T132162</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ1_v4_0236">
    <body>
      <pb n="236"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XV.</hi> A Wound with a hot Iron penetrating the <lb/><hi rend="roman"
          >Pelvis</hi>; by Dr. <hi rend="sc">Andrew Willison</hi> Phyſi- <lb/>cian at <hi
          rend="roman">Dundee</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">T</hi>HE Regard Phyſicians and Surgeons have <lb/>for their own
        Character and Reputation, <lb/>makes them often ſhy to undertake the Cure of <lb/>Patients,
        where they have no Hope of Succeſs, <lb/>and may be blamed by the Ignorant, if the Diſ-
        <lb/>eaſe is fatal; nay the Deſpair of doing good is <lb/>ſometimes a Reaſon of proper
        Remedies being <lb/>neglected as needleſs. But as every one can <lb/>ſave himſelf from
        Reproach, by making a due <lb/>Prognoſtick of the Event to the Relations, and <lb/>People
        have recovered beyond Expectation, <pb n="237"/>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">præſtat anceps quàm nullum tentare remedium</hi>, <lb/>the Sick
        ſhould have all the Aſſiſtance which <lb/>the healing Art can give. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By this general Reflexion I would introduce <lb/>the Hiſtory of a Caſe, which contains
        indeed no <lb/>new Method of Cure, but where Nature, with <lb/>a little Aſſiſtance, made a
        Cure of a Diſeaſe <lb/>which I look'd on as deſperate. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the Beginning of <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 1735, a Smith <lb/>puſhed a red-hot
        Iron with ſuch Force into the <lb/>Buttock, an Inch and a half from the <hi rend="italic"
          >Anus</hi>, of <lb/>a young Man of twenty Years of Age, that the <lb/>Point of it came out
        through the <hi rend="italic">Linea alba</hi>, a- <lb/>bout an Inch above the <hi
          rend="italic">Oſſa Pubis</hi>, having <lb/>pierced through the <hi rend="italic"
          >Pelvis</hi>. After ſome Hours <lb/>I ſaw him. His Pulſe was low and intermitting. <lb/>He
        had violent bilous vomiting from time to <lb/>time, great Pains in his Belly, Thirſt, Watch-
        <lb/>ings, cold Sweats and Faintings, with ſcarce <lb/>any Blood from the Orifices of the
        Wound. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I ordered fourteen Ounces of Blood to be let <lb/>from him, and to inject an emollient
        Clyſter <lb/>with Turpentine, which operated well, and he <lb/>was ſomewhat relieved of the
        Pain in his Belly. <lb/>He reſted ill all Night; and, next Morning, <lb/>his Symptoms
        continued, and he had paſſed no <lb/>Urine now twenty Hours after receiving the <lb/>Wound,
        notwithſtanding his having drank <lb/>great Quantities of Liquor. His Pulſe was more
        <lb/>frequent and harder. I cauſed twelve Ounces <lb/>of Blood to be taken, and after
        fomenting his <lb/>Belly well with Emollients, rubbed it with <hi rend="italic">Ol.
          <lb/>Scorpionum</hi>. By which the Pain became much <lb/>leſs. Thirty Hours after
        receiving the Wound <lb/>he voided a little Urine with much <hi rend="italic">Mucus</hi>,
        ſuch <pb n="238"/>
        <lb/>as People with Stones in their Bladder common- <lb/>ly paſs. At Night the Clyſter was
        repeated, <lb/>and brought off a great deal of ropy Slime with <lb/>it. An Emulſion with
        ſome Nitre was given <lb/>for ordinary Drink, and a cordial Julep did him <lb/>much Service
        in moderating the vomiting. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The third Day he again uſed the Fomentati- <lb/>on, Clyſter and Emulſion. His Urine and
        Ex- <lb/>crements came now plentifully by the lower <lb/>Wound near the <hi rend="italic"
          >Anus</hi>, little being evacuated <lb/>the natural Way, except a little ſlimy Urine
        <lb/>which he paſſed with ſharp Pain. I ordered di- <lb/>luted <hi rend="italic"
          >Digeſtive</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Mel-Roſe</hi> warmed, to be <lb/>injected into the
        Wound. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The bad Symptoms continued ten Days, and <lb/>the ſame Medicines were uſed. After this
        Time <lb/>his Urine came the natural Way. In ten Days <lb/>more the Excrements did the ſame,
        and in ſix <lb/>Weeks he was cured, having taken a low ve- <lb/>getable Diet all the Time,
        with thin weak Li- <lb/>quors for Drink, and Opiats at Night. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Towards the End of the Cure he was emaci- <lb/>ated, and had a Cough, but recovered of
        both <lb/>by a Milk Diet. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
