<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Plummer: Experiments on the medicinal Waters of Moffat</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Andrew Plummer</persName>
            </author>
            <title>VIII. Experiments on the medicinal Waters of Moffat; by ANDREW PLUMMER, M. D.
              Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians, and Professor of Medicine in the University
              of Edinburgh.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical essays and observations, published by a society in Edinburgh</title>
            <author>Philosophical Society of Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh : printed by W. and T. Ruddimans, for Messrs. Hamilton and
                  Balfour, Booksellers</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1747</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">1</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">69-77</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108727930</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T132162</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ1_v1_0069">
    <body>
      <pb n="69"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VIII.</hi> Experiments on the medicinal Waters of <lb/><hi
          rend="roman">Moffat</hi>; by <hi rend="sc">Andrew Plummer</hi>, <hi rend="roman">M.
          D.</hi> Fel- <lb/>low of the Royal College of Phyſicians, and <lb/>Profeſſor of Medicine
        in the Univerſity of <hi rend="roman">E- <lb/>dinburgh</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">H</hi>AVING obtained, by the Favour of Mr. <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Miligen</hi>, a conſiderable Quantity of the <lb/>mineral Water of <hi rend="italic"
          >Moffat</hi>, carefully put up at <lb/>the Fountain in the Month of <hi rend="italic"
          >April</hi>, and a Par- <lb/>cel of Stones taken from the Bottom of the up- <lb/>per Well,
        and ſome dug from the ſame Vein <lb/>as it croſſes the Rivulet below the Precipice up-
        <lb/>on which the Wells ſtand, I thought an At- <lb/>tempt to diſcover the Nature of this
        celebrated <lb/>mineral Water, by a chemical Analyſis and o- <lb/>ther Experiments of that
        kind, would not be <pb n="70"/>
        <lb/>unacceptable to the Curious, and might in ſome <lb/>meaſure be uſeful to illuſtrate its
        Effects in the <lb/>Cure of Diſeaſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Above ſixty Years ago Mr. <hi rend="italic">Mackaile</hi> publiſh- <lb/>ed a <hi
          rend="italic">Topographico-ſpagyrical</hi> Deſcription of <hi rend="italic">Mof-
          <lb/>fat</hi> Wells; in which he concludes, but from <lb/>very precarious Principles, that
        this Water is <lb/>impregnated with the <hi rend="italic">putid Sulphur</hi> of <hi
          rend="italic">Antimo- <lb/>ny</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Nitre</hi>; but in another Place
        he thinks it <lb/>neceſſary to add to theſe natural <hi rend="italic">Sal Ammoniac</hi>:
        <lb/>This Gentleman indeed writes in the Dialect of <lb/>an Adept, but moſt unlike a true
        Chemiſt, de- <lb/>clares againſt Experiments, and aſſerts, that an <lb/>Analyſis of the
        Water would be to no Purpoſe, <lb/>and therefore never made the Trial. I ſhall <lb/>not
        trouble the Reader with any further Re- <lb/>marks on this Author, but ſhall impartially re-
        <lb/>late the Experiments I made on this Water, <lb/>and the Stones taken from the Vein on
        which <lb/>it runs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The mineral Water tried by the hydroſtati- <lb/>cal Balance at the Fountain, and
        compared with <lb/>the Water of a Rivulet near the Well, was <lb/>found ſomewhat lighter
        than it; for the ſpeci- <lb/>fick Gravity of the mineral Water was to that <lb/>of the other
        Water as 838 to 840. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The mineral Water brought from <hi rend="italic">Moffat</hi> to <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Edinburgh</hi>, in Bottles well corked and waxed a- <lb/>bout the Neck, had a ſtrong
        ſulphurous Smell, <lb/>but appeared equally limpid and clear as com- <lb/>mon Spring-water,
        tho' at the Fountain it has <lb/>a milky or bluiſh Colour: Upon firſt opening <lb/>the
        Bottle the Water taſted as ſtrong, to my <lb/>Senſe, as when I have drank it at the Well;
        but <lb/>next day, the Bottle being half empty, the <pb n="71"/>
        <lb/>Water had quite loſt its diſtinguiſhing Taſte <lb/>and Smell. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I put ſome Grains of the freſh Powder of Galls <lb/>into a ſmall Quantity of the Water,
        but it did <lb/>not ſtrike a black or violet Tincture therewith, <lb/>tho' I ſet the Glaſs
        in a Sand-heat for ſome <lb/>Hours. A ſtrong Infuſion of red Roſes in com- <lb/>mon Water
        poured into an equal Quantity of <lb/>the mineral Water, was only diluted and made
        <lb/>fainter, as if ſo much ſimple Water had been <lb/>added to the Infuſion, and the ſame
        happened <lb/>with Syrup of Violets. This Water then gave <lb/>no Marks of a chalibeat
        Nature with Galls, nor <lb/>of Acidity with Tincture of Roſes, or Syrup of <lb/>Violets;
        neither did it produce any Efferveſcence <lb/>with alcaline Liquors, as <hi rend="italic"
          >Ol. Tartar. p. d.</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Spir. <lb/>Sal. Ammoniac.</hi> only when the
        firſt was drop- <lb/>ped into the Water, there appeared a faint blue <lb/>Cloud ſuſpended in
        it. Acid Liquors, as <hi rend="italic">Sp. &amp; <lb/>Ol. Vitriol. Sp. Nitr. &amp;c.</hi>
        added to theſe Mix- <lb/>tures with <hi rend="italic">Alcalis</hi>, after an Efferveſcence,
        pro- <lb/>duced a milky Colour, but no Precipitation. <lb/>The ſame acid Liquors dropped
        into the ſimple <lb/>mineral Water made no ſenſible Efferveſcence, <lb/>only the Mixture
        with <hi rend="italic">Sp. Nitri</hi> ſmoaked a little, <lb/>and ſome Bubbles of Air roſe
        from the Bottom, <lb/>but all of them turned the Water more or leſs <lb/>milky. Theſe <hi
          rend="italic">Phænomena</hi> diſcover the ſulphu- <lb/>rous Nature of the Water, but this
        Sulphur <lb/>muſt be very ſubtile, volatile, and in ſmall <lb/>Quantity, ſeeing the Water
        expoſed to the Air <lb/>ſoon loſes that Smell and Taſte which at firſt <lb/>ſo remarkably
        affected the Organs of theſe Sen- <lb/>ſes; and ſeeing acid Liquors cannot ſo unite <lb/>the
        Particles of this Sulphur as to make them <pb n="72"/>
        <lb/>fall to the Bottom, or ſeparate from the Water. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I made a great many Attempts to fix this Sul- <lb/>phur, and render it conſpicuous, but
        without <lb/>Succeſs, and therefore I ſhall not trouble the <lb/>Reader with theſe fruitleſs
        Experiments; only <lb/>there is one which had almoſt led me into a <lb/>Miſtake, until by
        further proſecuting the Ex- <lb/>periment I diſcovered the Truth: But having <lb/>ſpoke of
        this Matter to ſome Gentlemen before <lb/>I knew my Error, I muſt take this Opportunity
        <lb/>to relate the whole Matter. Having put a few <lb/>Grains of <hi rend="italic"
          >Saccharum</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Vitriolum Saturni</hi> (made <lb/>with <hi
          rend="italic">Aq. fort. ſimpl.</hi> diluted with a triple Quan- <lb/>tity of common Water
        and Litharge) into two <lb/>Ounces of <hi rend="italic">Moffat</hi> Water, this preſently
        turned <lb/>of a reddiſh Colour, after ſtanding ſome Minutes <lb/>the Water grew more
        pellucid, and the red <lb/>Particles uniting, fell moſtly to the Bottom, <lb/>and ſome ſmall
        Flakes ſwam on the Surface: <lb/>This Matter ſeparated from the Water re- <lb/>ſembled the
          <hi rend="italic">Sulphur auratum Antimonii</hi>; and <lb/>indeed I imagined that this was
        the Sulphur <lb/>which impregnates the Water coagulated and <lb/>fixed. That I might
        therefore procure a ſuffici- <lb/>ent Quantity of this Matter to diſcover its Na- <lb/>ture
        by other Trials, I got a freſh Parcel of <lb/>mineral Water from <hi rend="italic"
          >Moffat</hi>, and repeated the <lb/>Experiment: I put 3 Drachms of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Vitriolum <lb/>Saturni</hi> by Degrees into 3 Chopins or <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi>
        <lb/>Quarts of the Water, and poured the muddy <lb/>Liquor into a Filter, in which there
        remained <lb/>a Powder not ſo red as in the former Experi- <lb/>ment, but of a browniſh
        Colour, which when <lb/>dry weighed 20 Grains. I put 5 Grains of this <lb/>Powder upon an
        Iron Plate made red hot, it <pb n="73"/>
        <lb/>ſoon melted and ſmoaked a little, but did not <lb/>flame; when the Iron was cold, I
        found upon it <lb/>a thin Scurf of Lead. Upon the reſt of this Pow- <lb/>der I poured ſome
          <hi rend="italic">Ol. Tartar p. d.</hi> and ſet the <lb/>Glaſs to digeſt on a Sand-heat,
        but the Liquor <lb/>acquired no Tincture as it would have done <lb/>from a ſulphurous
        Subſtance: So that in this <lb/>Experiment the Acid of the <hi rend="italic">Vitriolum
          Saturni</hi>
        <lb/>mixing with the Water had let fell ſome of the <lb/>Particles of the Litharge, which by
        Fire after- <lb/>wards returned to Lead. That I might know <lb/>what remained in the Water
        which had paſt <lb/>thro' the Filter, I put about the Half of it into <lb/>an Iron Kettle,
        to evaporate it in haſte, and <lb/>I got a Drachm and 5 Grains of a ſaline or vi-
        <lb/>triolic Subſtance, of a brown Colour, and not <lb/>ſo ſweet and ſtyptick to the Taſte
        as the <hi rend="italic">Vitrio- <lb/>lum Saturni</hi>, which was diſſolved in the Water.
        <lb/>The Difference, I preſume, was owing partly <lb/>to ſome of the Litharge being
        precipitated, part- <lb/>ly to the Iron Kettle in which it was boiled, and <lb/>laſtly to
        ſome of the proper Salt of the Water, <lb/>being united to this vitriolic Subſtance. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Twelve <hi rend="italic">Scots</hi> Pints of the mineral Water was <lb/>diſtilled with
        a gentle Heat, from Glaſs Veſſels, <lb/>with the Joinings luted; the Water which came
        <lb/>over was perfectly limpid, and had no Smell <lb/>or Taſte, but a little <hi
          rend="italic">Empyreuma</hi>; what remain- <lb/>ed in the <hi rend="italic">Body</hi> had
        no Smell either, but taſted <lb/>ſomewhat ſaltiſh. When ¾ or thereby was <lb/>brought over,
        there appeared at the Bottom a <lb/>good Quantity of a muddy Sediment, which I
        <lb/>ſeparated from the Liquor, and carried on the <lb/>Evaporation in a low, wide mouth'd
        Glaſs. <lb/>When the Water was reduced to ſomewhat leſs <pb n="74"/>
        <lb/>than a Chopin, it ſeemed well ſaturated with a <lb/>Salt; for it was thick and bubbled,
        as when a <lb/>lixivial Salt is boiled near to Dryneſs. When <lb/>all was cold, I found at
        the Bottom a dirty Salt, <lb/>mixt with Mud or Earth; the Saline Particles <lb/>were ſo very
        ſmall, that I could not obſerve <lb/>their Shapes; but the Liquor had a very briny <lb/>or
        muriatick Taſte. I proceeded to evaporate <lb/>and cryſtalize the remaining Liquor, (except
        <lb/>two Ounces reſerved for other Trials) till I ga- <lb/>thered all the Salt which weighed
        4 Drachms <lb/>and 2 Scruples. As this Salt was very brown <lb/>and earthy, I diſſolved it
        in ſome of the diſtill'd <lb/>Water, filter'd the Solution, and cryſtaliz'd it <lb/>again;
        then there appeared very clean and beau- <lb/>tiful Criſtals, of an uncommon Figure, of very
        <lb/>different Sizes, but almoſt exactly ſimilar; ſome <lb/>of which are repreſented of
        their natural Bigneſs <lb/>on <hi rend="italic">Plate</hi> I. </p>
      <figure>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 1. Shews a ſmall Cryſtal, but very com- <lb/>plete and
          regular. </p>
        <figDesc>This and other plates of illustrations seem to have not been scanned into ECCO.
        </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 2. Repreſents one of the largeſt, ſome- <lb/>what rugged
          at the Corners. </p>
        <figDesc> </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 5. Is the Reverſe of the former, ſhew- <lb/>ing its
          Stalk. </p>
        <figDesc> </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 3. Shews two joined by one Side. </p>
        <figDesc> </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fig.</hi> 4. Repreſents 2 irregularly blended. </p>
        <figDesc> </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Each of theſe Cryſtals is made up, as it were, <lb/>of four Triangles joined together,
        ſo as to make <lb/>up a little hollow Capſule or Diſh, with Brims <lb/>turned outward or
        horizontally, and ſtands up- <lb/>on a little Pedeſtal or Stalk. Beſides theſe Cry-
        <lb/>ſtals there were others of a cubical Shape, but <lb/>both Sorts had evidently the Taſte
        of Sea Salt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I put two Drachms of the Salt obtained from <pb n="75"/>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Moffat</hi> Water into an Iron Ladle, and ſet it on <lb/>a clear
        Fire, till the Iron was red hot; the Salt <lb/>ſmoaked and crackled much as in the Decre-
        <lb/>pitation of common Salt, but it neither melted <lb/>nor flamed, nor did it much
        diminiſh in <lb/>Weight; for after an Hour's toaſting, it had <lb/>only loſt 18 Grains;
        which makes it evident that <lb/>this Salt is neither <hi rend="italic">Nitre</hi>, nor <hi
          rend="italic">Sal-ammoniac</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This decrepitate Salt, with four Scruples of <lb/>the Salt which had not felt the Fire,
        was put in- <lb/>to a ſmall Glaſs Retort, and, a Drachm of Oil of <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Vitriol</hi> poured upon it, there aroſe copious <lb/>Fumes, which were immediately
        confined, by <lb/>applying a Receiver: The Diſtillation was car- <lb/>ried on with a Fire
        gradually increaſed, the Re- <lb/>ceiver was filled with white Fumes, and there <lb/>came
        over about two Drachms of a volatile <lb/>ſmoaking Spirit, which anſwered all the Chara-
        <lb/>cters of <hi rend="italic">Glauber</hi>'s Spirit of Sea Salt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having diſſolved ſome Silver in <hi rend="italic">Aqua Fortis</hi>, <lb/>I divided the
        Solution into ſeveral Portions; in- <lb/>to one I let fall ſome Drops of the Spirit above
        <lb/>deſcribed; into another I put ſome Grains of <lb/>the Salt of <hi rend="italic"
          >Moffat</hi> Water, into a third ſome of <lb/>the Water evaporated to 1/36, and each of
        theſe <lb/>made a Precipitation of the Silver. All which <lb/>plainly ſhow that this Water
        is impregnated <lb/>with common Salt or <hi rend="italic">Sal-gem</hi>. Altho' the ſa-
        <lb/>line Criſtals obtained from <hi rend="italic">Moffat</hi> Water, differ <lb/>very much
        in Appearance from the Sea Salt <lb/>commonly uſed, yet having diſſolved ſome com- <lb/>mon
        Salt in pure Water, after Filtration, and <lb/>a very ſlow Evaporation, I obſerved many of
        <lb/>the ſaline Particles aſſume a Shape not unlike <lb/>that deſcribed above; but the
        Criſtals of the com- <pb n="76"/>
        <lb/>mon Salt approached nearer to little hollow <lb/>Pyramids, with ſquare Baſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I mentioned before, that I had reſerved two <lb/>Ounces of the Water, when it was
        evaporated <lb/>to 1/36 or thereby, and was ſtrongly impregnated <lb/>with Salt. Into a
        ſmall Quantity of this Brine <lb/>(as I may call it) I let fall ſome Drops of <hi
          rend="italic">Ol. <lb/>Tartar. p. d.</hi> which cauſed no Efferveſcence, <lb/>but
        preſently produced a milky Colour and Co- <lb/>agulation; upon ſtanding a while, the upper
        <lb/>Part of the Liquor turned clear, and of a Whey <lb/>Colour. The ſame happened when <hi
          rend="italic">Spir. Sal. <lb/>Ammon. cum Alcal. fixo</hi> was dropt into another
        <lb/>ſmall Parcel of the ſame Water; ſome Drops <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Spir.
          Vitriol.</hi> put into theſe Mixtures, after <lb/>Efferveſcence, diſſolved the
        Coagulation, and <lb/>rendered the Liquor pellucid: But <hi rend="italic">Sp. Vitriol.</hi>
        <lb/>or other acid Liquors dropt into the Brine by it- <lb/>ſelf, cauſed no Efferveſcence,
        or other Change in <lb/>Colour or Conſiſtence. The Difference between <lb/>theſe Phænomena
        and thoſe formerly obſerved <lb/>in the freſh Water, upon mixing the ſame Li- <lb/>quors, is
        remarkable; for when acid Spirits <lb/>were dropt into the freſh Water, they always
        <lb/>turned it milky, becauſe then the Water was <lb/>impregnated with its Sulphur, which
        the acid <lb/>Liquors, in ſome Meaſure, coagulated ſo as to <lb/>change the Colour of the
        Water: But alcaline <lb/>Liquors added to the freſh Water produced <lb/>little Change,
        becauſe a ſmall Quantity of Salt <lb/>was diſperſed through a great Bulk of Water. <lb/>On
        the other Hand, when the Sulphur was car- <lb/>ried off by Heat, and the Salt gathered into
        <lb/>narrower Bounds, then the Acids had no Effect, <lb/>but the <hi rend="italic"
          >Alcalis</hi> had a conſiderable one, by join- <pb n="77"/>
        <lb/>ing themſelves to the Particles of Salt, and col- <lb/>lecting them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The muddy Sediment which was firſt ſepa- <lb/>rated from the Water, when dry, weighed
        25 <lb/>Grains; it was of a ſandy Colour, and had a <lb/>little Saltneſs on the Tongue. I
        put this Pow- <lb/>der into an Iron Spoon, made red hot, and <lb/>kept it on the Fire; it
        ſmoaked a little, turned <lb/>black on the Surface, afterwards red, and at laſt
        <lb/>perfectly white. When cold it weighed 17 <lb/>Grains, and felt like Chalk. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Earth which was ſeparated from the So- <lb/>lution of the Salt by Filtration,
        weighed 15 <lb/>Grains. It had no Saltneſs, but was more grit- <lb/>ty between the Teeth
        than the former. When <lb/>calcin'd it ſmoaked little, ſcarce changed its Co- <lb/>lour, and
        when cold weighed 10 Grains. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I poured upon ſmall Parcels of theſe earthy <lb/>Subſtances both acid and alcaline
        Liquors; but <lb/>the Remains were ſo ſmall, that I could not <lb/>diſcover whether they
        contained any metallick <lb/>Particles or not. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Stones dug from the Vein, as it paſſes <lb/>thro' the Bottom of the upper Well at
          <hi rend="italic">Moffat</hi>, <lb/>are made up partly of a cryſtaline Spar cut, as
        <lb/>it were, into many poliſh'd Surfaces like Dia- <lb/>monds, partly of a ſhining
        Subſtance of a gol- <lb/>den Colour, but moſtly of a duſky or leadiſh- <lb/>coloured Ore. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Tho' theſe Stones ſeemed to abound in Sul- <lb/>phur, yet none of it would ſublime in
        cloſe Veſ- <lb/>ſels, but to obtain it in ſome Shape, I poured <lb/>upon two Ounces of the
        Ore in Powder a So- <lb/>lution of Salt of Tartar, by Digeſtion this ex- <lb/>tracted a very
        deep-red Tincture, from which<lb/>by<pb n="78"/>
        <lb/>pouring in <hi rend="italic">Spir. Vitriol.</hi> I got a Powder of a Ci- <lb/>tron
        Colour, weighing 17 Grains, which put <lb/>upon a red-hot Iron, made a faint blue Flame,
        <lb/>and had a ſulphurous Smell. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Two Ounces of the ſame Mineral, mixt with <lb/>an equal Quantity of Tartar and Nitre in
        Pow- <lb/>der, was put into a red hot Crucible in a melt- <lb/>ing Furnace; after half an
        Hour's Fuſion, the <lb/>Matter was thrown into an hollow Cone, or <lb/>antimonial Horn, it
        did not ſeparate into a me- <lb/>tallick or reguline Part and <hi rend="italic">Scoriæ</hi>;
        but there <lb/>appeared many ſhining Particles diſperſed thro' <lb/>the Maſs, like very foul
        Antimony. The whole <lb/>was again reduced to a Powder, and Water <lb/>poured on it, which
        acquired a very fetid and <lb/>ſulphurous Smell, and a Taſte much reſembling <lb/>the freſh
        mineral Water, but much ſtronger. <lb/>This Water likewiſe, with Spirit of Vitriol,
        <lb/>afforded a Sulphur like the former. The me- <lb/>tallick Matter, freed from the Salts
        by frequent <lb/>waſhing, was again brought to Fuſion with Ni- <lb/>tre and Tartar, and now
        I found at the Apex <lb/>of the Cone, a Piece of very pure Copper, weigh- <lb/>ing 42
        Grains, which anſwered all the Chara- <lb/>cters of that Metal. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I acknowledge that I could not diſcover any <lb/>Marks of Copper in the Water itſelf,
        by a- <lb/>ny Trials I could make; but as this Water <lb/>waſhes a Vein abounding with
        Copper and Sul- <lb/>phur, and is it ſelf impregnated with Salt, I <lb/>may conclude that
        the Principles contained in <lb/>this medicinal Water, are a very ſubtile and vo-
        <lb/>latile Sulphur, at leaſt ſome conſtituent Parts of <lb/>Sulphur, ſome Particles of
        Copper and <hi rend="italic">Sal-gem</hi>, <lb/>or common Salt. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
