<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Monro: A White Swelling of the Knee</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Alexander Monro</persName>
            </author>
            <title>XVIII. A white Swelling of the Knee; by the same. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical essays and observations, published by a society in Edinburgh</title>
            <author>Philosophical Society of Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: printed by W. and T. Ruddimans, for Messrs. Hamilton and
                  Balfour, Booksellers</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1747</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">4</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">242-244</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108728625</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T132162</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ1_v4_0242">
    <body>
      <pb n="242"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XVIII.</hi> A white Swelling of the Knee; by <hi rend="roman">the
          <lb/>ſame</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>Any Inſtances are daily ſeen of that tor- <lb/>menting,
        dangerous Diſeaſe, the <hi rend="italic">white <lb/>Swelling</hi> of the Joints; but before
        one has an <lb/>Opportunity of examining them by Diſſection, <lb/>to underſtand the Nature
        of the Diſeaſe right, <lb/>the Matter has become ſo ſharp that it erodes <pb n="243"/>
        <lb/>the Bones themſelves, and then one ſees the <lb/>ſame Thing as he would do in a <hi
          rend="italic">Spina ventoſa</hi>. <lb/>I met with one Patient in our Infirmary, whoſe
        <lb/>Joint of the Knee was juſt as far advanced as I <lb/>wiſhed to examine, when it was
        amputated. It <lb/>gave me a better Idea of that Diſeaſe than I had <lb/>before, and
        poſſibly may do ſo to ſome of your <lb/>Readers, which induces me to ſend it to you. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Iſabel Blackadder</hi>, a young Woman of a de- <lb/>licate tender
        Conſtitution, having hurt her left <lb/>Leg by a Fall ſome Years ago, an Ulcer broke
        <lb/>out near her Heel, and ſeveral Pieces of Bone <lb/>caſt out at it; but it recovered ſo
        well, that ſhe <lb/>went to Service again. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the End of 1734, having hurt the ſame <lb/>Leg by another Fall, the Knee ſwelled,
        be- <lb/>came very painful and ſtiff, for which ſhe was <lb/>taken into the Infirmary;
        where, after Blood- <lb/>ing, a few Doſes of <hi rend="italic">Aquila alba</hi>, and Embro-
        <lb/>cation with <hi rend="italic">Aq. mindereri</hi>, the Swelling and <lb/>Pain both
        ſeemed to abate, but ſoon became as <lb/>bad as formerly, and never afterwards yielded
        <lb/>to any Medicines. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Skin of the ſwelled Parts was not diſco- <lb/>loured, and on the Inſide of the
        Joint a Fluctu- <lb/>ation was felt in one or two Points, but the <lb/>Quantity of Liquor
        appeared very ſmall, and <lb/>the Fluctuation had a different Feeling to what <lb/>commonly
          <hi rend="italic">Pus</hi> collected in a Cavity has. Her <lb/>Pains were very ſharp,
        eſpecially upon the leaſt <lb/>Motion of the affected Leg; her Fleſh and Strength
        <lb/>decayed daily, and the hectick Symptoms in- <lb/>creaſed; which at laſt brought her ſo
        low, that <lb/>ſhe could not be raiſed to a ſitting Poſture with- <lb/>out fainting, which
        brought her under the Ne- <pb n="244"/>
        <lb/>ceſſity of ſuffering the Member to be amputated. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In this Condition ſhe was when the Member <lb/>was cut off above the Knee by Mr. <hi
          rend="italic">Douglas</hi>, <lb/>after which ſhe recovered daily, and walks on a
        <lb/>wooden Leg of the ſame Form which <hi rend="italic">Alexan- <lb/>der Sheppard</hi>
        uſed, whoſe Caſe I ſhall ſoon ex- <lb/>tract alſo from the Records of the Infirmary to
        <lb/>ſend you. (See <hi rend="italic">Art.</hi> XXI.) </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the diſeaſed Joint was diſſected, all <lb/>the cellular Membranes, in which Fat is
        natu- <lb/>rally contained under the Skin, between the <lb/>Muſcles and Tendons, and upon
        the Ligaments, <lb/>were found full of a glairy Matter, which had <lb/>inſinuated itſelf ſo
        much every where, and had <lb/>made the other Parts ſo ſoft, that we could <lb/>ſcarce
        diſtinguiſh one from another. In ſeveral <lb/>Places of this glairy Subſtance there were
        ſmall <lb/>Cavities full of <hi rend="italic">Pus</hi>. When the Articulation <lb/>of the
        Knee was opened, all the mucous Glands <lb/>and fatty Membranes were ſeen in the ſame Con-
        <lb/>dition with the exterior Parts; the <hi rend="italic">ſemilunar <lb/>Cartilages</hi>
        themſelves between the <hi rend="italic">Tibia</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Fe- <lb/>mur</hi>
        being quite ſoft, and with the ſame cellular <lb/>mucous Appearance that the Glands had. We
        <lb/>alſo obſerved ſome <hi rend="italic">Pus</hi> within the Cavity of the <lb/>Joint, but
        the Extremities of the Bones were <lb/>ſcarce begun to be eroded. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
