<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: An Account of the DISEASES that were most frequent last
          Year in Edinburgh</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>II. An Account of the DISEASES that were most frequent last Year in Edinburgh.
            </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical essays and observations, published by a society in Edinburgh</title>
            <author>Philosophical Society of Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh : printed by W. and T. Ruddimans, for Messrs. Hamilton and
                  Balfour, Booksellers</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1747</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">2</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">26-33</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108728263</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T132162</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ1_v2_0026">
    <body>
      <pb n="26"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">II.</hi> An Account of the DISEASES that were <lb/>moſt frequent laſt
        Year in <hi rend="roman">Edinburgh</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE <hi rend="italic">Tertian Agues</hi>, which were mention-
        <lb/>ed in the Cloſe of our preceding Year, <lb/>continued likewiſe thro' <hi rend="sc"
          >June</hi>, and Part of <hi rend="italic">Ju- <lb/>ly</hi> 1732. Towards the End of <hi
          rend="italic">June</hi> this Diſ- <lb/>eaſe did not form into regular Paroxyſms, and
        <lb/>perfect Intermiſſions, but appeared more in the <lb/>Shape of a remitting Fever. During
        the Re- <lb/>miſſions, the Pulſe was much ſunk, but as the <lb/>Sweat came on, the Pulſe
        became fuller and <lb/>ſtronger. When the Sweat did not break out, <lb/>the Patients became
        delirious, and ſome con- <lb/>tinued quite deaf for ſome Days. The Urine <lb/>was pale, and
        without Sediment 'till the Diſ- <lb/>eaſe was going off. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Some were cured of this Diſeaſe after two or <lb/>three Paroxyſms, by a Vomit or two,
        but with <lb/>others the Diſeaſe laſted much longer. Bleed- <lb/>ing was not found of Uſe,
        altho' ſome Sym- <lb/>ptoms ſeemed to require it, but Vomiting and <lb/>Bliſtering ſucceeded
        much better, either of <lb/>them bringing out the Sweat when untimely <lb/>ſtopt or
        prevented. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In <hi rend="sc">July</hi> ſome few <hi rend="italic">Tertian Agues</hi> remained;
        <lb/>they were then more regular and gentle than <lb/>before. Towards the End of this Month
        the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Cholera</hi> began to appear; but it was neither ve- <lb/>ry
        frequent nor violent. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In <hi rend="sc">August</hi> many among the poorer ſort of <lb/>People in the Suburbs
        and Villages near <hi rend="italic">Edin- <lb/>burgh</hi>, were taken with ſlow Fevers,
        general- <lb/>ly attended with a violent Head-ach and Ra- <pb n="27"/>
        <lb/>vings; ſome with a <hi rend="italic">Diarrhæa</hi>, others with Pains <lb/>of the <hi
          rend="italic">Rheumatick</hi> kind all over the Body. As <lb/>few of the Sick had Acceſs
        to timely Aſſiſtance, <lb/>ſeveral died in this Diſtemper. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſame Fever continued among the poor- <lb/>er People thro' <hi rend="sc"
          >September</hi> and <hi rend="sc">October</hi>, and <lb/>proved mortal the eighth or ninth
        Day. Be- <lb/>ſides the Symptoms before-mentioned, many <lb/>complained of great Weight of
        their Heads, <lb/>and Drowſineſs, Loathing and Vomiting; o- <lb/>thers had Pains of the
        Breaſt, and difficult <lb/>Breathing. Children in this Fever, beſide the <lb/>Head-ach and
        Drowſineſs, had Pain and tenſe <lb/>ſwelling of the Belly. Moſt of them paſſed <lb/>Worms,
        ſome the <hi rend="italic">Teretes</hi>, others the <hi rend="italic">Aſca- <lb/>rides</hi>,
        and recovered. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In <hi rend="sc">November</hi> ſeveral Children were ſeized <lb/>with ſlight aguiſh
        Fits returning every other <lb/>Day, but laſting only a few Hours, and going <lb/>off
        without Sweating. Between the Paroxyſms <lb/>the Children were pretty eaſy, and their Pulſes
        <lb/>calm. Theſe Fits were eaſily carried off by a <lb/>Vomit or two. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About the ſame time ſeveral People were ta- <lb/>ken with a <hi rend="italic"
          >Cholera</hi>, which did not prove very <lb/>obſtinate. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In this Month likewiſe the Effects of Cold <lb/>appeared in different Shapes, as <hi
          rend="italic">Coughs</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Quin- <lb/>cys</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Rheumatick Pains</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Colick Pains</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Diar-
          <lb/>rhæas</hi>, &amp;c. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From the Beginning, till the Middle of <hi rend="sc">De- <lb/>cember</hi>, ſlow Fevers
        were very rife among <lb/>young People; they continued long, and were <lb/>attended with
        Pains in the Breaſt, and a ſym- <lb/>ptomatick <hi rend="italic">Diarrhæa</hi>, but were not
        deadly. A- <pb n="28"/>
        <lb/>bout the ſame time others were ſeized with Fe- <lb/>vers of the nervous kind, with a
        very frequent <lb/>but low Pulſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 17th, <hi rend="italic">December</hi>, ſeveral People were <lb/>ſuddenly
        attacked with <hi rend="italic">Fevers of Cold</hi>; the <lb/>Numbers increaſed but
        inſenſibly till the 25th; <lb/>after which theſe Fevers became greatly epide- <lb/>mick,
        very few eſcaping them, and continued <lb/>univerſal in this City and Neighbourhood till
        <lb/>the middle of <hi rend="sc">January</hi> 1733, when they be- <lb/>gan to decreaſe, and
        diminiſhed daily till the <lb/>End of that Month. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This Fever began with a Coldneſs, Shiver- <lb/>ing, Swimming of the Head, Pains of the
        Head, <lb/>Breaſt and Back; the Pulſe was very frequent; <lb/>the Appetite quite loſt, and
        remained pall'd <lb/>ſometime after the Diſeaſe was removed. With <lb/>a great many it began
        with a running of Lymph <lb/>at the Eyes and Noſe, which continued for a <lb/>Day; then they
        complained of Pain and Swel- <lb/>ling about their Throats before the Cough be- <lb/>gan,
        and not a few were ſuddenly ſeized with <lb/>the Cough, which, after the third Day, was
        <lb/>inceſſant and conſtant in all, by which they diſ- <lb/>charged great Quantities of <hi
          rend="italic">Mucus</hi>, and had <lb/>their Pains greatly increaſed. Some complain-
        <lb/>ed of ſharp Pains in their Bellies, and had a <lb/><hi rend="italic">Diarrhæa</hi>,
        ſometimes with bloody Stools, e- <lb/>ſpecially if they were not ſufficiently blooded
        <lb/>in the Beginning. Several paſſed their Urine <lb/>in very ſmall Quantity, of a high
        Colour, with- <lb/>out Sediment, and continued to do ſo, ſome <lb/>time after the Fever was
        gone off. Among the <lb/>Children, along with the Cough, many had <pb n="29"/>
        <lb/>violent Vomitings, and ſome a gentle <hi rend="italic">Diar- <lb/>rhæa</hi>, which
        carried off the Diſeaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Fever commonly left the Sick in two or <lb/>three Days; but after the third Day
        ſcarce any <lb/>eſcaped the conſtant tickling Cough. General- <lb/>ly all of them inclined
        to ſweat, and were there- <lb/>by conſiderably relieved. Some had profuſe <lb/>Sweats, with
        copious reddiſh or brown, but not <lb/>lateritious Sediment in their Urine, without a-
        <lb/>ny previous Coldneſs, Shiverings, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> Theſe <lb/>ſoon did
        well, if the Sweating was not diſcou- <lb/>raged by ſome other Evacuation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Bleeding in the Beginning gave Relief to the <lb/>Pains, and weakned the Fever, and
        required to <lb/>be plentiful to many who had violent Head- <lb/>aches, and a Feeling in
        their Eyes as if they <lb/>would have ſtarted out, or to thoſe who had an <lb/>univerſal
        Oppreſſion of the <hi rend="italic">Thorax</hi>, with <lb/>Stitches and Cramps of the
        Muſcles employed <lb/>in Breathing; ſuch in this Condition who de- <lb/>layed Venæſection
        too long, were ſeized with <lb/>a <hi rend="italic">Hæmoptoe</hi>. Some bled a little at the
        Noſe, <lb/>and were quickly well, without any Medicine <lb/>or other Evacuation. A few were
        at once ſei- <lb/>zed with ugly Faintings; when bled they re- <lb/>covered more ſlowly; but
        when ſupported with <lb/>Cordials, they were ſoon well. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Veſicatories were of Service to the Cough, <lb/>and Opiates were of great Uſe, curing
        ſeveral. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the Phlegm began to thicken, Mix- <lb/>tures in which <hi rend="italic">Gum
          Ammoniac</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Oxymel Scil- <lb/>liticum</hi> were the principal
        Ingredients, opened <lb/>the Belly, and did remarkable Service. The <lb/>ordinary <hi
          rend="italic">Pectorals</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Balſamicks</hi> were not ob-
        <lb/>ſerved to do any good. </p>
      <pb n="30"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This Diſeaſe was not of itſelf mortal, but it <lb/>ſwept away a great Number of poor
        old and <lb/>conſumptive People, and of thoſe who were <lb/>much waſted by other Diſtempers.
        As a Proof <lb/>on whom it fell heavieſt, we may remark, That <lb/>though the Number of
        Burials in the <hi rend="italic">Gray- <lb/>friars <choice>
            <corr>Church</corr>
            <sic>Charch</sic>
          </choice>-yard</hi> (where all the Dead of <hi rend="italic">E- <lb/>dinburgh</hi> are
        buried) was double of what it uſes <lb/>to be in the Month of <hi rend="italic"
        >January</hi>, yet the Num- <lb/>ber of thoſe who were buried at the publick <lb/>Charge was
        ſo great, that the Fees of the Bu- <lb/>rials ſcarce did amount to the Sum commonly
        <lb/>received in any other Month. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It was very remarkable, That, notwithſtand- <lb/>ing this Diſeaſe was ſo univerſal
        here, the Peo- <lb/>ple in our Priſon, and the Boys who are nu- <lb/>merous in <hi
          rend="italic">Heriot's Hoſpital</hi>, which is contigu- <lb/>ous to the Weſt Side of the
          <hi rend="italic">Grayfriars Church- <lb/>yard</hi>, and the Inhabitants of the Houſes
        near <lb/>to that Hoſpital eſcaped this Fever and Cough. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This epidemick Diſeaſe which was felt ſoon- <lb/>er at <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh</hi>
        than any other Part of this <lb/>Iſland, ſpread itſelf gradually over all <hi rend="italic"
          >Scotland</hi>. <lb/>It did not reach the moſt Northern and Weſtern <lb/>Parts till about
        fifteen Days after the Time a- <lb/>bove mentioned of its attacking this City. The <lb/>Ship
          <hi rend="italic">Anne and Agnes</hi>, <hi rend="italic">David Littlejohn</hi> Ma-
        <lb/>ſter, having made a Voyage to <hi rend="italic">Holland</hi>, with <lb/>one ſick Sailor
        on Board, returned with the o- <lb/>ther then in perfect good Health, till they made
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Flamborough-head</hi>, where on the 15th of <hi rend="italic">Ja-
          <lb/>nuary</hi> ſix Sailors were taken ill; next Day two <lb/>more were in the ſame
        Condition, and the Day <lb/>thereafter one more fell ſick; ſo that when the <lb/>Veſſel came
        to the Road of <hi rend="italic">Leith</hi>, none on <pb n="31"/>
        <lb/>Board were in Health except one, who was <lb/>ſeized the Day after he came on Shore
        with the <lb/>ſame Diſeaſe which his Comrades had, whoſe <lb/>Symptoms were the common ones
        of the ra- <lb/>ging epidemick Diſtemper. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We believe it will not be improper here to <lb/>mention the Horſes in and about this
        Place, be- <lb/>ing univerſally attacked with a running of the <lb/>Noſe and Coughs, towards
        the End of <hi rend="italic">October</hi>
        <lb/>and beginning of <hi rend="italic">November</hi>, before the Ap- <lb/>pearance of this
        Fever of Cold among Men. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This epidemick Diſtemper above deſcribed, <lb/>ſpread itſelf over all <hi rend="italic"
          >Europe</hi>, and alſo infeſted <lb/>the Inhabitants of <hi rend="italic">America</hi>; ſo
        that it was per- <lb/>haps the moſt univerſal Diſeaſe upon Record. <lb/>The firſt Accounts
        we have of any Thing like <lb/>it this laſt Year in <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi>, was, in
        the Middle <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">November</hi>, from <hi rend="italic">Saxony</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">Hanover</hi>, and o- <lb/>ther neighbouring Countries in <hi rend="italic"
          >Germany</hi>. It <lb/>raged at one Time in <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh</hi>, and <hi
          rend="italic">Baſil</hi> in <lb/><hi rend="italic">Switzerland</hi>. It appeared in <hi
          rend="italic">London</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Flan- <lb/>ders</hi> after the firſt Week
        in <hi rend="italic">January</hi>. Toward <lb/>the Middle of which it reached <hi
          rend="italic">Paris</hi>; and a- <lb/>bout the End of the ſame Month <hi rend="italic"
          >Ireland</hi> began <lb/>to ſuffer. In the Middle of <hi rend="italic">February</hi>, <hi
          rend="italic">Leghorn</hi>
        <lb/>was attacked; and near the End of it, the Peo- <lb/>ple of <hi rend="italic"
          >Naples</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Madrid</hi> were ſeized with it. <lb/>In <hi
          rend="italic">America</hi> it began in <hi rend="italic">New-England</hi> about the
        <lb/>Middle of <hi rend="italic">October</hi>, and travelled Southward to <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Barbadoes</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Jamaica</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Peru</hi>,
        and <hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi>, much <lb/>at the ſame Rate as it did in <hi rend="italic"
          >Europe</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There were alſo ſome People in <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh</hi>
        <lb/>labouring under Fevers of the <hi rend="italic">Pleuritick</hi> Kind, <lb/>and others
        under ſlow tedious ones in the Month <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">January</hi>. </p>
      <pb n="32"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In <hi rend="sc">February</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">Rheumatick</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Pleuritick</hi>
        <lb/>Fevers ſucceeded to the Colds, ſeveral who had <lb/>paſſed through theſe were ſeized
        with thoſe and <lb/>died. The Management of the Sick was no <lb/>other than what is common
        in <hi rend="italic">Pleuriſies</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About this Time alſo ſeveral People died <lb/>ſuddenly. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Pleuritick</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Peripneumonick</hi> Fevers
        <lb/>which began in <hi rend="italic">February</hi>, continued thro' all <lb/><hi rend="sc"
          >March</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>At the ſame Time ſlow Fevers were likewiſe <lb/>frequent without any topical
        Inflammation. In <lb/>moſt Patients theſe Fevers did not appear with <lb/>any violent
        Symptoms, tho' ſome had Ravings, <lb/>but they were neither conſtant nor high. Theſe
        <lb/>Fevers often laſted till the 30th or 40th Day, <lb/>and in ſome to the 60th; and at
        length the Pa- <lb/>tients gradually wreſtled out of them, without <lb/>any remarkable <hi
          rend="italic">Criſis</hi>. The common Reme- <lb/>dies in ſuch Caſes availed little here;
        Bliſter- <lb/>ing was found of much more Service than <lb/>Bleeding. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tertian Agues</hi>, began to appear in <hi rend="italic">March</hi>,
        <lb/>and continued thro' <hi rend="italic">April</hi> and Part of <hi rend="italic"
        >May</hi>, <lb/>tho' not very frequent; many of them went <lb/>off eaſily after four of five
        Fits, without much <lb/>Aſſiſtance from Medicine, others took the com- <lb/>mon Courſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Some ſhort but ſharp Fevers were frequent <lb/>in <hi rend="sc">April</hi>, with an <hi
          rend="italic">Eryſipelas</hi> for the moſt Part <lb/>on the Face, and ſometimes on the
        Body or <lb/>Extremities. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Some few Children had the <hi rend="italic">Small Pox</hi> all <lb/>the Spring, and
        there were rather more in <hi rend="sc">May</hi>, <lb/>they were generally of the diſtinct
        Kind; and <pb n="33"/>
        <lb/>ſeveral had an Eruption like the Baſtard or <lb/><hi rend="italic">Chicken-Pox</hi>. It
        was attended with very little <lb/>Fever, and very ſlight Symptoms; for after a <lb/>little
        Heavineſs and Loſs of Appetite, the Pu- <lb/>ſtules appeared. They were pretty large and
        <lb/>red: They did not ſuppurate, but had a little <lb/>Veſicle of clear Lymph on the Top.
        Some <lb/>new Puſtules appeared for four or five Days <lb/>ſucceſſively like the firſt; and
        about the ninth <lb/>Day all went off. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
