<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: An Account of the most remarkable Discoveries and Improvements in
          Physick</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>XXXVIII. An Account of the most remarkable Discoveries and Improvements in
              Physick made or proposed since the Beginning of the Year 1731. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical essays and observations, published by a society in Edinburgh</title>
            <author>Philosophical Society of Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh : printed by W. and T. Ruddimans, for Messrs. Hamilton and
                  Balfour, Booksellers</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1747</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">1</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">275-287</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108727930</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T132162</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ1_v1_0275">
    <body>
      <pb n="275"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">XXXVIII.</hi> An Account of the moſt remarkable <lb/><hi rend="roman"
          >Diſcoveries</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Improvements</hi> in Phyſick <lb/>made or propoſed
        ſince the Beginning of the <lb/>Year 1731. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(1.5)">M</hi>R. <hi rend="italic">William Houſton</hi> Surgeon has
        accurately <lb/>deſcribed the Plant of which the <hi rend="italic">Contray- <lb/>erva</hi>
        is the Root: The Name he gives this <lb/>Plant is <hi rend="italic">Dorſtenia, Dentariæ
          radice, Sphondylii <lb/>Folio</hi>, of which there are two Kinds, one <hi rend="italic"
          >Pla- <lb/>centâ ovali</hi>, the other <hi rend="italic">Placentâ quadrangulari <pb
            n="276"/>
          <lb/>&amp; undulatâ</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Philoſoph. Tranſact. Numb. <hi rend="roman"
            >421. <lb/>§ 2.</hi></hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">de Juſſieu</hi>, Phyſician and Member of the <lb/>Academy of
        Sciences at <hi rend="italic">Paris</hi>, aſſures us from <lb/>his Experience of the
        ſucceſsful Effects in Dy- <lb/>ſenteries of a thick yellow Bark, which has an
        <lb/>aſtringent gently bitter Taſte, brought firſt in- <lb/>to <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi>
        from <hi rend="italic">America</hi> in 1713, called there <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Simarouba</hi>, and reſembling what is deſcribed <lb/>by the Ancients under the Name of
          <hi rend="italic">Macer</hi>. <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">de Juſſieu</hi> obſerved that
        this Medicine was <lb/>more ſucceſsfully given in Decoction than in <lb/>Subſtance. The Doſe
        he uſually gave was the <lb/>third Part of a Chopin of Decoction, which had <lb/>two Drachms
        of the Bark in it. <hi rend="italic">Memoires de <lb/>l'Acad des Sciences</hi>, 1729. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>An Accident of two Women dying ſuddenly <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">Dublin</hi>, after
        drinking ſome of the common <lb/>diſtilled <hi rend="italic">Laurel Water</hi>, gave Riſe to
        ſeveral Ex- <lb/>periments made upon Dogs with the diſtilled <lb/>Water, and with the
        Infuſion of the Leaves of <lb/>this <hi rend="italic">Lauro-ceraſus</hi>, communicated by
        Dr. <hi rend="italic">Mad- <lb/>den</hi> Phyſician at <hi rend="italic">Dublin</hi> to the
        Royal Society in <lb/><hi rend="italic">England</hi>, and afterwards repeated and confirm-
        <lb/>ed by Dr. <hi rend="italic">Mortimer</hi>, <hi rend="italic">R. S. S.</hi> by which it
        ap- <lb/>peared that both the Water and Infuſion brought <lb/>on Convulſions, Palſy and
        Death, when taken <lb/>by the Mouth or <hi rend="italic">Anus</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
          >Philoſ. Tranſact. Numb. <lb/><hi rend="roman">418. § 7.</hi></hi> and <hi rend="italic"
          >Numb. <hi rend="roman">420. § 3.</hi></hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We are informed from <hi rend="italic">Leyden</hi>, that Dr. <hi rend="italic">Gau-
          <lb/>bius</hi>, who has ſucceded Dr. <hi rend="italic">Boerhaave</hi> in teach- <lb/>ing
        Chymy, gave, in the Beginning of 1731, <lb/>a publick College on Milk; in which he ſhew-
        <lb/>ed a great Variety of Experiments, and, among <lb/>the reſt, prepared its eſſential
        Salt, by boiling <pb n="277"/>
        <lb/>Whey (<hi rend="italic">Serum lactis</hi>) to one half, then filtra- <lb/>ting it; he
        continued the boiling and filtrating <lb/>till it became of the Conſiſtence of a Syrup,
        <lb/>when it was put into a Cellar to cryſtalize, and <lb/>there the Salt formed into a
        Cake, which was <lb/>of a ſaccharous Taſte, and reſembled <hi rend="italic">Manna</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Not.</hi> This Preparation is ſomewhat different <lb/>from that which
          <hi rend="italic">Valentini <note n="(a)" place="bottom" rend="roman size(0.7)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) Medici<unclear>na</unclear> nov.
                antiq<unclear>a</unclear>
              <gap reason="illegible"/>
            </p>
          </note></hi> alledges to be <lb/>the famous <hi rend="italic">Saccharum lactis</hi>, ſo
        much cried up <lb/>by the firſt Preparer of it <hi rend="italic">Ludovicus Teſti <note
            n="(b)" place="bottom" rend="roman size(0.7)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) In epiſtol. </p>
          </note></hi>, <lb/>and recommended by others as an infallible <lb/>Cure of the Gout. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The new Experiments related by Dr. <hi rend="italic">Stahl</hi>, <lb/>in his Book of
          <hi rend="italic">chymical</hi> and <hi rend="italic">phyſical Experi- <lb/>ments</hi>,
        are too numerous for us to enter upon <lb/>an Account of them, and moſt of them relate
        <lb/>more to Phyſicks than Medicine. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Chriſt. Jac. Trew</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Norimberg</hi>
        prefers <lb/>the rectified Spirit of Grain for preſerving ana- <lb/>tomical Preparations in,
        to Spirit of Wine, or <lb/>Compoſitions of <hi rend="italic">Alcohol</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
          >Succinum</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Camphor</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
        becauſe theſe, he ſays, ſoon change into a <lb/>brown Colour, whereas the Spirit from Malt
        <lb/>preſerves its limpid Appearance. When any <lb/>Part is deſigned to be preſerved wet, he
        re- <lb/>commends the waſhing of it with Water, till <lb/>the Water is no more tinctured
        with any Blood; <lb/>the Water is next to be waſhed away with Spi- <lb/>rits, and then the
        Preparation is to be put a- <lb/>mong the Spirits in the Glaſs where it is to be <lb/>kept;
        the Mouth of which is to be very cloſe <lb/>covered with the Glaſs Head, over which a wet
          <pb n="278"/>
        <lb/>Bladder and Leaf-tin are tied. <hi rend="italic">Commerc. literar. <lb/>Norimberg. <hi
            rend="roman">1731.</hi> Semſt. <hi rend="roman">I.</hi> Specim. <hi rend="roman"
            >ix.</hi></hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We learn by private Letters from <hi rend="italic">Leyden</hi>, <lb/>that the Veſſels
        of the cryſtalline Humour of the <lb/>Eye, ſaid in our publick News Papers laſt Year <lb/>to
        have been diſcovered by Dr. <hi rend="italic">Albinus</hi> Profeſ- <lb/>ſor of Anatomy
        there, are all the Branches of <lb/>an Artery, which being ſent off from the Ar- <lb/>tery
        that enters at the central Part of the <hi rend="italic">Retina</hi>, <lb/>paſſes through
        the vitrous Humour, and when <lb/>it reaches the cryſtalline, diſperſes its Branches
        <lb/>along the Surface of that <hi rend="italic">Lens</hi> like <hi rend="italic">Radii</hi>
        till they <lb/>are exceedingly minute, when they pierce into <lb/>its Subſtance. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Albrecht</hi>, Profeſſor of Medicine at <hi rend="italic">Er-
          <lb/>ford</hi>, in his anatomical Obſervations of two <lb/>Men he diſſected, is of Opinion
        that the Blad- <lb/>der of a ſtrong Man may be divided into ſix <lb/>Coats, among which he
        thinks the muſcular <lb/>ought not to be reckoned, becauſe it conſiſts <lb/>of irregular
        ſeparated Bundles of Fibres. He <lb/>obſerved that the Part of a waxy Injection co-
        <lb/>loured with <hi rend="italic">Cinnabar</hi>, which had made its Way <lb/>among the
        cellular Membranes covering the <lb/>Coats of a Vein, left the colouring Powder be-
        <lb/>hind it. After injecting Wax into the left pul- <lb/>monary Vein, he remarked a Vein
        filled with <lb/>the Injection, which ran up on the Outſide of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >Pleura</hi> to four or five Inches diſtance from <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
        >Vertebræ</hi>, and gave off Branches to the <lb/>neighbouring Parts. By accounting for the
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Phænomena</hi> of ſeveral Diſeaſes from this Fact, <lb/>he ſeems to
        think a Communication between <lb/>the pulmonary and thoracick Veſſels always to
        <lb/>obtain. <hi rend="italic">Albrechti Obſerv. Anat. <hi rend="roman">§ 5, 8,
          11.</hi></hi>
      </p>
      <pb n="279"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Jo. Henr. Schulze</hi>, Profeſſor of Medicine at <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Altorff</hi>, having obſerved Wax paſſing, as he <lb/>thinks, through the
        Coats of Arteries and Veins <lb/>when theſe Veſſels were injected, of which that
        <lb/>coloured with red loſt its Colour, while the <lb/>green kept it; endeavours thence to
        account <lb/>for the Secretion of Fat, and the Production of <lb/>an <hi rend="italic"
          >Oedema</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Commerc. literar. Norimberg. <hi rend="roman">1731.</hi>
          <lb/>Semeſt. <hi rend="roman">1.</hi> Specim. <hi rend="roman">v.</hi></hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Senac</hi>'s new Deſcription of the Structure <lb/>of the
        Diaphragm, and his Remarks on the <lb/>Action of this Muſcle are ſo very particular and
        <lb/>connected, that they will not bear ſuch an A- <lb/>bridgment as our Deſign will allow. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Of the ſame kind are Mr. <hi rend="italic">Hunauld</hi>'s Obſerva- <lb/>tions on the
        Structure and Actions of ſome <lb/>Muſcles of the Fingers, and Mr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Winſlow</hi>'s Ac- <lb/>count of Rotation, Pronation, Supination, and <lb/>other circular
        Motions; wherefore we muſt re- <lb/>fer all theſe three to the original Papers in the
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">Memoires de l'Acad. des Sciences</hi>, 1729. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Monro</hi>, Profeſſor of Anatomy here, has <lb/>made ſo many
        Additions to his <hi rend="italic">Oſteology</hi>, and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Treatiſe of
          the Nerves</hi>, which he has tack'd to <lb/>the new Edition lately publiſhed that we can-
        <lb/>not enter into a Detail of them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Winſlow</hi>, in his <hi rend="italic">Expoſition anatomique
          <lb/>de la Structure du Corps humain</hi>, has mended <lb/>every where the common
        Deſcriptions, and has <lb/>added innumerable Particulars that were not <lb/>mentioned before
        him, which make any tole- <lb/>rable Account of ſuch Improvements ſo much <lb/>longer than
        our Work can admit, that we can <lb/>do no more than recommend this Author to <lb/>all who
        wiſh to have a very particular and ge- <pb n="280"/>
        <lb/>nuine Knowledge of the Structure of the hu- <lb/>man Body. He is indeed very ſhort, and
        ex- <lb/>tremely reſerved in explaining the Functions <lb/>and Uſes of the Parts, except in
        his Treatiſe on <lb/>the Muſcles, where he ſhews prodigious Varie- <lb/>ties in the Actions
        of theſe Organs of Motion, <lb/>that never were ſo much as hinted before. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Bryan Robinſon</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Dublin</hi>, in his <hi
          rend="italic">Trea- <lb/>tiſe of the Animal Oeconomy</hi> has endeavoured to <lb/>improve
        on Sir <hi rend="italic">Iſaac Newton</hi>'s Opinions con- <lb/>cerning ſeveral Parts of the
        animal Oeconomy, <lb/>and ſupports his Reaſoning by a Number of <lb/>Experiments and
        geometrical Calculs. He <lb/>ſhews <hi rend="italic">firſt</hi>, the Laws that obtain in the
          <hi rend="italic">Motion <lb/>of Fluids through cylindrical Pipes</hi>, which ſerve
        <lb/>as an Introduction to his Account of the Motion <lb/>of Blood in the Veſſels. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Next</hi>, He argues for <q rend="diple quotes"><hi rend="italic"
            >Muſcular Motion</hi> be- <lb/>ing performed by the Vibrations of a very <lb/>elaſtick
            <hi rend="italic">Æther</hi>, lodged in the Nerves and <lb/>Membranes, inveſting the
          minute Fibres of <lb/>the Muſcles, excited by the Power of the <lb/>Will, Heat, Wounds,
          the ſubtile and active <lb/>Particles of Bodies, and other Cauſes. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">third</hi> Subject he treats of is <hi rend="italic"
          >Reſpiration</hi>; <lb/>on which he contends, <q rend="diple quotes">The Life of Animals
          <lb/>is preſerved by acid Parts of the Air mixing <lb/>with the Blood in the Lungs, which
          Parts <lb/>diſſolve or attenuate the Blood and preſerve <lb/>its Heat, and by both theſe
          keep up the Mo- <lb/>tion of the Heart. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the following Section he argues for <hi rend="italic">Di- <lb/>geſtion</hi> being
        owing to gentle Heat and Motion. <lb/>
        <q rend="diple quotes">By this Heat and Motion the Texture of the <lb/>Nouriſhment is
          changed in the Bodies of A- <pb n="281"/>
          <lb/>nimals: </q> And then, <q rend="diple quotes">The conſtituent ſo- <lb/>lid Parts of
          Animals, according to their ſe- <lb/>veral Natures, are endued with peculiar at-
          <lb/>tractive Powers of certain Magnitudes, by <lb/>which they draw out of the Fluids
          moving <lb/>through them like Parts in certain Quantities, <lb/>and thereby preſerve their
          Forms and juſt <lb/>Magnitudes. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Secretions</hi>, according to our Author, are per- <lb/>formed thus:
          <q rend="diple quotes">The Glands in the Bodies of <lb/>Animals, according to their
          ſeveral Na- <lb/>tures and Diſpoſitions, are endued with pe- <lb/>culiar attractive
          Powers, by which they ſuck <lb/>in various Juices from the Blood. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the <hi rend="italic">laſt</hi> place, he ſhows the Proportion <lb/>of the
        Diſcharges of human Bodies, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> of <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >Perſpiration</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Urine</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Winſlow</hi>, Phyſician and Member of the <lb/>Royal Academy of
        Sciences at <hi rend="italic">Paris</hi>, has pro- <lb/>poſed an Improvement on the ordinary
        Man- <lb/>ner of reducing inguinal or crural <hi rend="italic">Herniæ</hi>, <lb/>namely to
        cauſe the Patient to reſt on his <lb/>Knees and Elbows, while the Surgeon is at-
        <lb/>tempting to reduce the Bowels. <hi rend="italic">Le Dran Ob- <lb/>ſervations
          Chirurgiques, Tom. <hi rend="roman">2.</hi> Obſ. <hi rend="roman">1.</hi></hi> and <hi
          rend="italic">Jour- <lb/>nal de Sçavans, May <hi rend="roman">1732.</hi></hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Cheſelden</hi>, Surgeon at <hi rend="italic">London</hi>, has
        made <lb/>a conſiderable Improvement on the lateral Ope- <lb/>ration for the Stone. Inſtead
        of preſſing his <lb/><hi rend="italic">Catheter</hi> backwards, he cauſes it to be ſupport-
        <lb/>ed as cloſe to the Conjunction of the <hi rend="italic">Oſſa pubis</hi>
        <lb/>as poſſible; and after having made a large Inci- <lb/>ſion into the Teguments, he
        preſſes the Gut <lb/>backwards with the Fore-finger of the left <lb/>Hand, and, having felt
        the Furrow of the <hi rend="italic">Ca- <pb n="282"/>
          <lb/>theter</hi> with his Finger, he introduces his Knife <lb/>with the Edge directed
        forward and down- <lb/>wards upon the Finger into the Furrow, im- <lb/>mediately above the
        ſuperior Part of the <hi rend="italic">Pro- <lb/>ſtata</hi>; and with the Knife in the ſame
        Situation <lb/>he cuts a ſmall Share of the Side of the Bladder, <lb/>its <hi rend="italic"
          >Sphincter</hi>, the Side of the <hi rend="italic">Proſtata</hi>, the Li- <lb/>gament
        through which the ſmall Beginning of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Urethra</hi> paſſes, and the
        bulbous Part of the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Urethra</hi>. After this Inciſion the <hi
          rend="italic">Gorgeret</hi> is in- <lb/>troduced upon the Fore-finger, which has been
        <lb/>kept in the Wound all this Time. The <hi rend="italic">For- <lb/>ceps</hi> is quickly
        introduced, and the Stone is as <lb/>quickly extracted. <hi rend="italic">Douglas</hi>'s <hi
          rend="italic">Appendix to the <lb/>Hiſtory of the lateral Operation</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Garengeot</hi>, Surgeon at <hi rend="italic">Paris</hi>, has much
        <lb/>enlarged his Treatiſe of Chirurgical Operations, <lb/>in the ſecond Edition lately
        publiſhed; the moſt <lb/>conſiderable Improvements in the practical Way <lb/>that we
        remarked to be here added are the fol- <lb/>lowing: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tom.</hi> I. <hi rend="italic">p.</hi> 298. Old Age is an Advantage
        in <lb/>performing the Operations for <hi rend="italic">Herniæ</hi>, becauſe <lb/>old
        Peoples Guts are not ſo liable to inflame or <lb/>gangrene as thoſe of young Perſons. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ibid. p.</hi> 408. He recommends Exerciſe to <lb/>hydropic People
        immediately before they are <lb/>to be tapped, that the groſſer Particles in the <lb/>Water
        of their Belly may be mixed with the <lb/>thinner, and ſo may run out with them. And <lb/>if
        there is Reaſon to ſuſpect any ſuch groſs <lb/>Parts remaining after the Operation, he advi-
        <lb/>ſes the Injection of Barley-water to dilute them <lb/>and bring them away. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tom.</hi> II. <hi rend="italic">p.</hi> 354. He deſcribes a new Way
        of <pb n="283"/>
        <lb/>performing the Operation of the <hi rend="italic">Fiſtula in Ano</hi>; <lb/>it is this,
        Having thruſt a Probe through the <lb/>Gut a little higher than the Bottom of the <hi
          rend="italic">Si- <lb/>nus</hi>, and having drawn out that End by the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Anus</hi> with the Finger introduced into the Gut, <lb/>he makes an Inciſion
        parallel to the Probe, at <lb/>an Inch diſtance from it on each Side, and cuts <lb/>out all
        between the Inciſions. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ibid. p.</hi> 431. A new Method of tying a <lb/>wounded intercoſtal
        Artery, the Invention of <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Goulard</hi> Surgeon at <hi
          rend="italic">Montpelier</hi>, is deſcri- <lb/>bed; the Inſtrument employed is a
        ſemicircu- <lb/>lar or very curve Needle, that has a Groove a- <lb/>long its convex Part,
        and two Holes at ſome <lb/>Diſtance from each other near the Point, pier- <lb/>cing from the
        convex to the concave Side; this <lb/>Needle is fixed into a long ſtraight Handle, <lb/>and
        a Thread is put through the two Holes in <lb/>ſuch a manner, that its Nooſe is on the con-
        <lb/>cave Side, and the two Ends are on the Con- <lb/>vex, in the Groove of which they are
        hid and <lb/>brought down to the Handle. When the <lb/>Needle is thus mounted, and Inciſion
        is made <lb/>croſs three Ribs, that where the wounded Ar- <lb/>tery is being the middlemoſt,
        when theſe are <lb/>diſcovered, the Needle is thruſt through the in- <lb/>tercoſtal Muſcles
        contiguous to the upper Edge <lb/>of that middle Rib, and about an Inch farther <lb/>back
        than where the open Orifice of the Artery <lb/>is, and is puſhed within the internal Surface
        of <lb/>the Ribs downwards, and made to pierce out- <lb/>wards again immediately below the
        under Edge <lb/>of the Rib; as ſoon as the Nooſe of the Thread <lb/>on the concave Side of
        the Needle appears <lb/>without the Muſcles, it is to be raiſed with a <pb n="284"/>
        <lb/>Pin, and the anterior End of the Thread is to <lb/>be drawn out; then the Needle being
        drawn <lb/>back again, brings out the other End with it; <lb/>therefore the Thread being now
        round the Rib, <lb/>is to be tied firmly on it, and the Artery will be <lb/>compreſſed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tom.</hi> III. <hi rend="italic">p.</hi> 187. In performing the <hi
          rend="italic">Trepan</hi>, <lb/>he thinks it better for the Surgeon to reſt his <lb/>Chin
        in a Ring made with the Fingers of the <lb/>Hand that holds the Handle of the Inſtrument,
        <lb/>than to reſt his Forehead on the Back of that <lb/>Hand in the common Way. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ibid. p.</hi> 369. He thinks it is inconvenient for <lb/>Surgeons to
        preſs with the Palm of their Hand <lb/>on the Back of the Amputation-knife in mak- <lb/>ing
        the circular Inciſion round a Limb, but ra- <lb/>ther to make Uſe of Mr. <hi rend="italic"
          >La Peironyer</hi>'s Crotchet <lb/>or Hook at the Point of the Knife, into which <lb/>a
        Finger is put for directing the Knife; or, if <lb/>that is wanting, to take hold of the
        Knife near <lb/>its Point with the Thumb and Fingers of the <lb/>left Hand. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ibid. p.</hi> 423. He is of Opinion that ſoft Com- <lb/>preſſion is
        much more effectual to ſtop <hi rend="italic">Hæmor- <lb/>rhagies</hi> than hard Subſtances. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ibid. p.</hi> 391. He condemns the Uſe of <hi rend="italic"
          >Vitriol</hi>
        <lb/>Buttons, even when Stitches of Arteries give <lb/>way, and would rather truſt to ſoft
        Compreſ- <lb/>ſion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ibid. p.</hi> 414. He adviſes the Amputation of <lb/>the Fore-part of
        the Foot when there is Occa- <lb/>ſion; in doing which, the Knowledge of the
        <lb/>Articulations there only can guide the Operator. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Chineſe</hi> ſeem to have had the Method <lb/>of inoculating the
          <hi rend="italic">Small-Pox</hi> long before it was <pb n="285"/>
        <lb/>introduced into this Weſtern Part of <hi rend="italic">Europe</hi>: <lb/>Their Method
        of Proceding, according to Fa- <lb/>ther <hi rend="italic">d'Entrecolle</hi>'s Account, is
        this; they gather <lb/>the Scabs that come off from a healthy Child <lb/>that has had the
        Small-Pox in a favourable <lb/>Way, and keep them well ſhut up in a <hi rend="italic"
          >China</hi>
        <lb/>Cup till there is Occaſion for them; then ta- <lb/>king four ſmall ones or two large
        ones, and <lb/>putting a Grain of Muſk between them, they <lb/>roll them in a little Cotton,
        and thruſt this <lb/>Tent into the Child's Noſe, where it remains <lb/>till the Symptoms of
        Infection begin to appear. <lb/>The Child on whom this Inoculation is to be <lb/>made is to
        be more than a Year old. If the <lb/>Puſtules appear on the firſt Day of the Fever, <lb/>the
        Child almoſt certainly dies: If they come <lb/>out on the ſecond, the Event is uncertain: If
        <lb/>they do not ſhow themſelves till the third Day, <lb/>the Patient probably will recover.
          <hi rend="italic">Lettres e- <lb/>difiantes &amp; curieuſes ecrites des miſſions etran-
          <lb/>geres par quelques miſſionaires de la compagnie <lb/>de Jeſu, Tom. <hi rend="roman"
            >20. Paris 1731.</hi></hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>D. <hi rend="italic">Stevens</hi> in his <hi rend="italic">Eſſay</hi> on <hi
          rend="italic">Aliments</hi>, prefix- <lb/>ed to his Tranſlation of <hi rend="italic"
          >Dolæus</hi> on the Gout, <lb/>endeavours to prove the gouty Humours to be <lb/>rather of
        an alcaline than an acid Nature, both <lb/>from the Nature of our Fluids, and from the
        <lb/>Diſeaſe being moſt effectually mitigated or cu- <lb/>red by an aceſcent Diet. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>An anonymous Author gives a long Account <lb/>of a <hi rend="italic">Colick</hi>, which
        generally prevails in <hi rend="italic">Amſter- <lb/>dam</hi> during the Winter, and
        deſtroyed many <lb/>of the Inhabitants in 1730. Its Appearance is <lb/>very like to what was
        formerly called the <hi rend="italic">Colick <lb/>of Poictou</hi>, and is here minutely
        deſcribed. <pb n="286"/>
        <lb/>The principal diſtinguiſhing Marks of it being <lb/>Its Obſtinacy, and bringing on
        Convulſions, <lb/>Palſies, and other Diſorders that are common- <lb/>ly called <hi
          rend="italic">nervous</hi>. The Author redargues all the <lb/>different Opinions
        concerning the Nature of <lb/>this Diſeaſe, and endeavours to prove it to de- <lb/>pend on a
        gouty Humour. <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheque raiſonée <lb/>de l'Europe, Tom. <hi
            rend="roman">8.</hi> Art. <hi rend="roman">2.</hi></hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="italic">Lobb</hi>, in his <hi rend="italic">Treatiſe</hi> on the <hi
          rend="italic">Small-Pox</hi>, <lb/>ſeems to diſapprove entirely of Blood-letting in
        <lb/>the Small-Pox; for the only Caſe where he <lb/>would allow of it, is in the Beginning
        of <lb/>the Diſeaſe, in a Patient who has a ſanguine <lb/><hi rend="italic">Plethora</hi>,
        which is again confined to ſo many <lb/>Circumſtances, that ſcarce ever ſuch a Patient
        <lb/>will be met with. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He thinks with Dr. <hi rend="italic">Boerhaave</hi>, that the Diſ- <lb/>eaſe may be
        prevented or cured without any E- <lb/>ruption, but differs from the learned Profeſſor's
        <lb/>Opinion of this being done by the <hi rend="italic">antiphlogiſtick</hi>
        <lb/>Method, and rather thinks a Specifick may be <lb/>found: He propoſes the <hi
          rend="italic">Æthiops Mineral</hi> as a <lb/>Medicine that probably would prove ſuch a
        Spe- <lb/>cifick, and relates ſome Examples of the Diſ- <lb/>eaſe being in his Judgment
        prevented by time- <lb/>ly Uſe of <hi rend="italic">Æthiops</hi>: but before he would recom-
        <lb/>mend it to general Practice, he propoſes to <lb/>have ſufficient Trials of its Effects
        made on <lb/>Malefactors, and lays down all the Regimen <lb/>neceſſary to be obſerved during
        the Trials. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If Dr. <hi rend="italic">Lobb</hi> diſclaims Blood-letting in the <lb/>Small-Pox, Dr.
          <hi rend="italic">Loeber</hi> Profeſſor of Medicine at <lb/><hi rend="italic">Jena</hi>,
        in his <hi rend="italic">Sure Rules to a ſucceſsful Cure of <lb/>the Small-Pox</hi>,
        recommends repeated and plen- <pb n="287"/>
        <lb/>tiful Bleeding, and the greateſt Care to follow <lb/>out the <hi rend="italic"
          >antiphlogiſtick</hi> Method. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
