<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Thomson: An Enquiry into the Natural History and Medical Uses of Several Mineral Steel
          Waters</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Alexr Thomson</persName>
            </author>
            <title>VI. An Enquiry into the natural History and medical Uses of several mineral Steel
              Waters; by Dr. ALEXr. THOMSON Physician at Montrose. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical essays and observations, published by a society in Edinburgh</title>
            <author>Philosophical Society of Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh : printed by W. and T. Ruddimans, for Messrs. Hamilton and
                  Balfour, Booksellers</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1747</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">2</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">43-57</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">12⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108728263</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T132162</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ1_v2_0043">
    <body>
      <pb n="43"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">VI.</hi> An Enquiry into the natural Hiſtory and <lb/>medical Uſes of
        ſeveral mineral <hi rend="roman">Steel Wa- <lb/>ters</hi>; by Dr. <hi rend="sc">Alex<hi
            rend="sup">r</hi>. Thomson</hi> Phyſician at <lb/><hi rend="roman">Montroſe</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">S</hi><hi rend="sc">Teel Spaws</hi> are every where ſo frequent in
        <lb/>this Part of <hi rend="italic">Scotland</hi> where I live, that to <lb/>imagine them
        impregnated with Iron in Sub- <lb/>ſtance, were to conceive the whole Country in <lb/>one
        Mine, for, Exceſs and Defect computed, <lb/>there may be reckoned at leaſt one for every
        <lb/>Pariſh. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Soils out of which theſe mineral Springs <lb/>riſe are various: That near to <hi
          rend="italic">Aberbrothock</hi> is <lb/>in the ordinary poorer ſort of the Soil of this
        <lb/>Country, the upper <hi rend="italic">Stratum</hi> being a gravelly <pb n="44"/>
        <lb/>Clay, below which there is another of Pebble <lb/>Stories intermixed with Sand; under
        this there <lb/>is Sand and Gravel mixed. The Well is in <lb/>the lower Part of a Den or
        hollow Ground, ha- <lb/>ving a Rivulet running by at the Diſtance of a- <lb/>bout fifty or
        ſixty Paces. The Side of the Ri- <lb/>vulet oppoſite to the Well is bounded by a gra-
        <lb/>velly Rock, betwixt the Layers whereof there <lb/>ouzes clear Water dropping over
        Sleeks <note place="bottom" n="(a)" rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) A ſmooth ſhining Clay. </p>
        </note>
        <lb/>ſuſpended thereat; and at the Top of the Rock <lb/>there is a ſmall Well of good
        Fountain Water. <lb/>I evaporated the Water from theſe Sleeks by <lb/>the Heat of the Sun,
        and nothing remained <lb/>but a grey Powder, as of ordinary Clay. A- <lb/>bout three of four
        hundred Paces above the <lb/>Well, and on the ſame Side of the Rivulet, <lb/>there is
        another Spring of common Water; <lb/>but there are no more Rocks near or above the <lb/>Well
        for a conſiderable Way. The Soil of <lb/>moſt other Spaws which I have examined is <lb/>much
        the ſame with that of <hi rend="italic">Aberbrothock</hi>, and <lb/>generally a Rivulet runs
        alſo near them thro' <lb/>common Flintſtone and Sand; particularly, <lb/>this is the Caſe of
        the Well of <hi rend="italic">Kincardine</hi>, which <lb/>is eſteemed in this Country next
        to <hi rend="italic">Aberbro- <lb/>thock</hi>: And I am informed by good Hands, <lb/>that
        the Soil of the Mineral Well at <hi rend="italic">Peterhead</hi>, <lb/>at the Mouth of the
          <hi rend="italic">Murray-Frith</hi>, is much <lb/>the ſame, without any Rocks in its
        Neighbour- <lb/>hood, except the Sea Rocks, to which it is ſo <lb/>near, that it is
        overflowed by high Tides. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There are only three <hi rend="italic">Spaws</hi> that I know here- <lb/>abouts, the
        Soil whereof varies from what I <pb n="45"/>
        <lb/>have juſt now deſcribed; one of theſe is in <lb/><hi rend="italic">Glendy</hi>, beyond
        the fam'd <hi rend="italic">Kairn</hi>, on the Top <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Grampions</hi>: The Soil of this Well is <lb/>Bog, with Moſs-ground round it; and no Rock
        <lb/>is to be ſeen near it. This Spring bubbles up <lb/>between the Moſs and the Gravel at
        its Bottom, <lb/>playing, as it iſſues out, like a Pot boiling, and <lb/>appears of the
        Colour of <hi rend="italic">Oker</hi>, with which <lb/>one's Shoes alſo are coloured when he
        treads <lb/>on the Moſs near the Well. I have ſeen ano- <lb/>ther ſituated in a like Soil in
          <hi rend="italic">Lentretham</hi>, near <lb/>to the Mouth of <hi rend="italic"
          >Gleniſla</hi>; but it does not <lb/>bubble up as the former does. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The only <hi rend="italic">Spaw</hi> of my Acquaintance, that <lb/>hath any thing of
        Rock uncommon in its <lb/>Neighbourhood, is near to <hi rend="italic">Cortachie</hi>, my
        Lord <lb/><hi rend="italic">Airly</hi>'s Seat on the Water of <hi rend="italic"
          >South-Esk</hi>: This <lb/>mineral Fountain is ſituated at the Foot of a <lb/>Hill near to
        the River, having, at the Diſtance <lb/>of forty or fifty Paces, a good many rocky
        <lb/>Stones, which ſhine or ſparkle like <hi rend="italic">Marcaſites</hi>
        <lb/>when they are broken; and Pearls are fiſhed in <lb/>the neighbouring River. I have ſent
        ſome of <lb/>theſe Stones for your Examination; but they <lb/>are not ſo bright or ſhining
        and of ſuch a po- <lb/>liſhed Surface, as others which I have ſeen on <lb/>the other Side of
        that Ridge of the <hi rend="italic">Grampions</hi>
        <lb/>in <hi rend="italic">Gleniſla</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After conſidering the Soils from which theſe <lb/><hi rend="italic">Steel Spaws</hi>
        riſe, and all in their Neighbour- <lb/>hood, I would think that the moſt probable
        <lb/>Account which can be made of their mineral <lb/>Origins may be taken from the
        Diſcoveries of <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Geoffroy</hi>, and of Mr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Lemery</hi> the Son, com- <pb n="46"/>
        <lb/>pared <note place="bottom" n="(b)" rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) Memoires de l'Acad. des Sciences, 1704, 1705, 1706. </p>
        </note>. <hi rend="italic">Geoffroy</hi>, after attempting to make <lb/>Iron with the Clay
        of Brick and Linſeed-oil, <lb/>found, by ſome ſuch Experiments, that there <lb/>was Iron in
        all Vegetables which he could put <lb/>under Trial; for all of them had Particles,
        <lb/>which the Loadſtone, or Needle touched with <lb/>it, attracted. And Mr. <hi
          rend="italic">Lemery</hi>, by expoſing <lb/>Vegetables to the Burning-glaſs, fuſed them
        <lb/>into a metallick Maſs in the ſame manner as <lb/>was done to Filings of Iron; and from
        hence <lb/>takes Occaſion ingeniouſly to account for this <lb/>Mineral's aſcending, its
        Gravity notwithſtand- <lb/>ing, thro' the whole <hi rend="italic">Compages</hi> of
        Vegetables: <lb/>Which he illuſtrated and confirmed ſtill further, <lb/>by his Experiment
        'on Iron diſſolved, firſt by <lb/>Spirit of Nitre, and then by Oil of Tartar, <lb/>when it
          <hi rend="italic">arbored</hi> all over the Surface of the Veſ- <lb/>ſel in a great
        Variety of Branches. What I <lb/>aim at may ſtill be more eaſily conceived from <lb/>what
          <hi rend="italic">Le Givre</hi>, a Man of good Senſe and Learn- <lb/>ing of his Time,
        writes concerning the medi- <lb/>cal Wells of <hi rend="italic">Provence</hi>, to wit, That
        in Trench- <lb/>es digged for diſcovering the Origins of theſe <lb/>Wells, and on the Sides
        of the neighbouring <lb/>Ditches, he found the mineral Fluid drilling <lb/>through its ſmall
        Conduits, and becoming of the <lb/>Conſiſtence of the Dreg of Oil: And then he <lb/>tells us
        the various Colours it aſſumes in Ana- <lb/>logy to <hi rend="italic">Crocus Martis</hi>,
        and deſcribes its diffe- <lb/>rent Degrees of Conſiſtence and Solidity, ac- <lb/>cording to
        its being more or leſs expoſed to <lb/>the Air. It is probable that the like Diſcove-
        <lb/>ries in ſeveral other Parts of <hi rend="italic">France</hi> induced <pb n="47"/>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Lemery</hi> to ſay, that <hi rend="italic">France</hi> abounds in
        Iron e- <lb/>very where; for I believe we have not other- <lb/>wiſe heard of Mines of Iron
        being every where <lb/>in that Country. So that our medical Wells <lb/>may bear a juſt
        Analogy to their mineral Pro- <lb/>geny of Vegetables, if ſuch new Phraſe of <lb/>Language
        may be allowed; and I think the <lb/>Volatility of our <hi rend="italic">Spaws</hi>,
        diſcovered both by <lb/>the Experiments made with them, and by their <lb/>medical Effects,
        of which hereafter, may hence <lb/>be beſt accounted for. Nor needs what I have <lb/>here
        argued for be thought ſurpriſing, ſince <lb/>the beſt Philoſophy hath proved the primoge-
        <lb/>nial Earth, compared with it as at preſent, to <lb/>have been of a more liquid
        Conſiſtence. And <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="italic">Boyle</hi> and Monſ. <hi rend="italic"
          >Tournefort</hi> have diſcover- <lb/>ed the ſame of Gems, Marbles and Corals. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Whatever Truth is in this Doctrine, Mr. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Geoffroy</hi> and <hi
          rend="italic">Lemery</hi>'s Experiments lead us to <lb/>underſtand why <hi rend="italic"
          >Steel Spaws</hi> are ſo frequent; <lb/>and really conſidering how much the Mineral
        <lb/>is diffuſed over all, one would think that all <lb/>Waters ſhould be impregnated with
        it; and <lb/>poſſibly they may be ſo, only the Proportion <lb/>of the Mineral is ſo ſmall in
        moſt Fountains, <lb/>that the common Trials will not diſcover it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I could find no Difference in the ſpecifick <lb/>Gravity of the <hi rend="italic">Steel
          Waters</hi> I tried from that <lb/>of common Fountain Water. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The fixed mineral Contents of the Steel Wa- <lb/>ters of <hi rend="italic"
          >Aberbrothock</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Peterhead</hi> may be <lb/>collected much more
        eaſily than is done in the <lb/>common Method of evaporating the whole <lb/>Water, if the
        mineral Water is put in open <lb/>Bottles ſome Days; for then its Contents pre- <pb n="48"/>
        <lb/>cipitate, and the Water being poured off, will <lb/>let fall any Remains of the
        Mineral, by affuſing <lb/>common Fountain Water: And the Precipi- <lb/>tations may be
        haſtned, by mixing any pro- <lb/>per Adſtringent. The mineral Subſtances thus
        <lb/>collected, are afterwards to be dried in the <lb/>Shade, Sun, or analogous Heat of <hi
          rend="italic">Fire</hi>. In <lb/>this manner they will be got more intire, than <lb/>when
        ſuch a ſtrong Heat is employed as is ne- <lb/>ceſſary in boiling, which may force off the
        moſt <lb/>volatile Subſtances. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After four <hi rend="italic">Scottiſh</hi> Pints of <hi rend="italic">Aberbrothock</hi>
        Wa- <lb/>ter were evaporated leiſurely at the Well, there <lb/>was no Appearance of a
        Pellicule, and the dried <lb/>Powder that remained, weighed, as near as an <lb/>Accident of
        loſing a little of it would allow me <lb/>to judge, between fifteen and twenty Grains;
        <lb/>this I threw into a hot Iron Ladle, when it ſpark- <lb/>led into little <hi
          rend="italic">Flammules</hi>, juſt as the fine Filings <lb/>of Iron uſe to do: But the
        Powder of the Sleeks <lb/>of the Well ſparkled but faintly when ſo tried. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Monſ. <hi rend="italic">du Clo</hi>'s Experiments ſatisfy me, as <lb/>they did him,
        that it is not eaſy to determine <lb/>what Salts theſe Waters contain, or whether <lb/>all
        are impregnated with the ſame kinds of <lb/>Salts: He could find neither <hi rend="italic"
          >Allum</hi> nor <hi rend="italic">Vitriol</hi>
        <lb/>in any of the <hi rend="italic">French</hi> Wells; only in one he <lb/>found ſome
        Reſemblance of the latter: All the <lb/>other Wells gave a Salt, anſwering to a Com-
        <lb/>poſition of <hi rend="italic">Nitre</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sea Salt</hi> mixed in
        va- <lb/>rious Proportions; which probably is the na- <lb/>tural Salt of the Earth
        diſcovered by Mr. <hi rend="italic">Tour- <lb/>nefort</hi>
        <note place="bottom" n="(c)" rend="size(0.7)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) Preface to his Hiſtory of Plants in the Neighbour-
            <lb/>hood of <hi rend="italic">Paris</hi>. </p>
        </note> reſembling in moſt Trials the <hi rend="italic">Na- <pb n="49"/>trum</hi> of the <hi
          rend="italic">Levant</hi>, being neither acid nor al- <lb/>cali, but approaching moſt to
        the latter. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Gall</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Myrobalan</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
          >Granat</hi> Bark were <lb/>chiefly uſed by <hi rend="italic">du Clos</hi>, to diſcover
        the <hi rend="italic">Steel <lb/>Spaws</hi> of <hi rend="italic">France</hi>, and to
        determine the greater <lb/>or leſſer Degrees of the mineral Contents, by <lb/>the higher or
        lower Tincture which they made <lb/>when mixed with the mineral <hi rend="italic">Steel
          Waters</hi>: <lb/>Which Trials have alſo anſwer'd very well with <lb/>me; only, ſeeing the
          <hi rend="italic">Myrobalans</hi> give a reddiſh <lb/>Tincture to ordinary Water, and
        obſerving <lb/>the mineral Waters going upon the ſame Co- <lb/>lour when I uſed them, I have
        choſe to make <lb/>my Trials with the <hi rend="italic">Gall</hi>, and employed either
        <lb/>the Shell intire, or its Tincture, becauſe the <lb/>Powder or its Infuſion generally
        makes the <lb/>Water muddy. Having therefore affuſed the <lb/>ſame Quantity of <hi
          rend="italic">Peterhead</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Aberbrothock</hi>
        <lb/>Waters on like Quantities of <hi rend="italic">Gall</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Peter-
          <lb/>head</hi> Water ſtruck a deep purple Colour, and <lb/>the <hi rend="italic"
          >Aberbrothock</hi> Water became only dilutely <lb/>red, as a <hi rend="italic">Vin
          paillè</hi>; then I added by Degrees <lb/>double the Quantity of common Fountain Wa-
        <lb/>ter to the <hi rend="italic">Peterhead</hi> Water tinctured with the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">Gall</hi>, before it became preciſely like to the Co- <lb/>lour of the <hi
          rend="italic">Aberbrothock</hi> Water with the <hi rend="italic">Gall</hi> in <lb/>it:
        Whereby we may ſee that the Mineral, as <lb/>reached by the <hi rend="italic">Gall</hi>, is
        two Thirds ſtronger in <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Peterhead</hi> than in the <hi
          rend="italic">Aberbrothock</hi> Water. <lb/>The Water of <hi rend="italic">Glendy</hi>
        came neareſt to the <hi rend="italic">Pe- <lb/>terhead</hi> Well in its deep Tincture; next
        to <lb/>this was the Water of <hi rend="italic">Kincardine</hi>: Moſt of the <lb/>other
        Spaws that I have examined give a Tin- <lb/>cture much like that of <hi rend="italic"
          >Aberbrothock</hi>; ſome, a <lb/>little higher; others, ſomewhat lower. </p>
      <pb n="50"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Infuſion of the Sleeks gathered from the <lb/>Stones wherewith the Well of <hi
          rend="italic">Aberbrothock</hi> is <lb/>encompaſſed on the Sides, and covered above,
        <lb/>made with Water or Vinegar, ſtruck a ſtrong- <lb/>coloured Tincture when Galls were
        mixed <lb/>with it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Rectified Spirit of Wine makes no Change <lb/>on the <hi rend="italic">Steel
          Waters</hi>; but when the Gall is af- <lb/>terwards added, the Tincture is higher than
        <lb/>when no Spirit is uſed. The common Spirit <lb/>of Wine mixed with the mineral Water,
        turns <lb/>it of a fine light Violet Colour; and when the <lb/>Gall is added, the Tincture
        becomes more <lb/>duſky than by the Gall alone: Whether is it <lb/>not probable, that the
        rectified Spirit exalts the <lb/>Sulphur, or other active Principles partaking of <lb/>the
        Nature of Sulphur, without making any <lb/>Tincture, but only augmenting that given by
        <lb/>the Gall? whereas the common Spirit gives a <lb/>Tincture, which being confounded with
        that <lb/>of the Gall, forms that duſky Colour. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Our <hi rend="italic">Steel Spaws</hi> which I have tried, appear <lb/>to be ſo very
        volatile, that by the leaſt Acceſs <lb/>of Air after they are taken up from the Well,
        <lb/>all that bears Trial in them goes off, eſpecially <lb/>if they are taken up in a hot
        Sun; you will <lb/>better comprehend this, when I tell you, that <lb/>lately I cauſed two
        Bottles of <hi rend="italic">Aberbrothock</hi> Wa- <lb/>ter to be taken up in my Sight, and
        to be im- <lb/>mediately well cork'd and roſin'd: Next Day, <lb/><choice>
          <corr>t</corr>
          <sic> </sic>
        </choice>he firſt of them I put under Trial anſwered <lb/><choice>
          <corr>ſ</corr>
          <sic> </sic>
        </choice>carce more than ordinary Fountain Water; but <lb/>the other anſwered in the
        ordinary Manner. <lb/>The only Reaſon I could find for this was, the <lb/>cracking of the
        Roſin, and Roughneſs of the <pb n="51"/>
        <lb/>Neck of the Bottle, which hindred the Cork to <lb/>apply ſo cloſe to the Bottle in
        which the firſt <lb/>Water was contained: This taught me to be- <lb/>lieve I had not been
        formerly abuſed, as I ſu- <lb/>ſpected, when I found this and ſome other Wa- <lb/>ters
        brought me to have a ſenſibly vapid Taſte, <lb/>and to contain nothing of the Mineral; tho'
        I <lb/>muſt tell you, that when I formerly had <hi rend="italic">Aber- <lb/>brothock</hi>
        Water under Examination, and did <lb/>not uſe ſo much Precaution as lately, I did not
        <lb/>meet with ſuch Diſappointments; which I can <lb/>attribute to nothing but the
        Difference of the <lb/>Seaſons, the Water being taken up for my late <lb/>Trials in very hot
        Weather. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As I found the <hi rend="italic">Liege</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Piermont Spaws</hi>
        <lb/>giving the ſame Tincture with Galls, and a- <lb/>greeing every other Way, the vinous
        Flavour <lb/>peculiar to theſe foreign Waters only diſtin- <lb/>guiſhing them, ſo I have
        ſeen theſe alſo faint <lb/>of Taſte, and refuſing the uſual Trials, on oc- <lb/>caſion of
        being ill cork'd or roſin'd. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I come now to conſider the medical Uſes of <lb/>theſe Springs. As they evacuate moſtly
        by U- <lb/>rine, but rarely by Stool, and only in the more <lb/>lax and flabby Texture of
        the Bowels, I have <lb/>found them, eſpecially that of <hi rend="italic">Aberbrothock</hi>,
        <lb/>good in nephritick Diſeaſes, ſcouring off Gravel, <lb/>and ſometimes puſhing a Stone
        down. They <lb/>are beneficial in ſcorbutick Foulneſſes, eſpecial- <lb/>ly when the Humours
        are in an aceſcent Diſpo- <lb/>ſition; in all Diſeaſes of the Stomach depend- <lb/>ing on an
        Acid; and in general, they are ſer- <lb/>viceable, and may be uſed more freely in all
        <lb/>Indiſpoſitions, occaſioned by what Phyſicians <lb/>call a morbid Acid in the Body; but
        where the <pb n="52"/>
        <lb/>alcaline or bilious Diſpoſition prevails, they are <lb/>to be more ſparingly, if at
        all, taken. And <lb/>as Obſervation hath evicted the Diſtinction of <lb/>ſuch oppoſite
        Cauſes of Diſeaſes, ſo the Trial <lb/>by Galls, their turning Syrup of Violets, Tin-
        <lb/>cture of Roſes, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> green, diſcover the Alcali <lb/>in them;
        which might have undeceived Men <lb/>from being ſo fond of denominating them ſo
        <lb/>generally <hi rend="italic">Acidulæ</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>My Experience in the Cure of Diſeaſes by <lb/>theſe Waters, will not allow me to ſtate
        uni- <lb/>verſally their comparative Virtues on the high- <lb/>er or lower Degree of
        Tincture from the Mix- <lb/>ture of other Subſtances with them; for I can- <lb/>not ſay
        whether the deeper Colour of <hi rend="italic">Pe- <lb/>terhead</hi> Water with Galls,
        depends on a great- <lb/>er Quantity of the ſame mineral Sulphur, or on <lb/>a firmer
        Combination with its Earth; or whe- <lb/>ther they may not contain a groſſer Sulphur,
        <lb/>or a larger Proportion of Earth than is in <hi rend="italic">Aber- <lb/>brothock</hi>
        Waters. All I can hitherto determine <lb/>by Obſervation is, That in Flaccidneſs, and
        <lb/>too great Relaxation of the Solids, eſpecially <lb/>of the Stomach and other
        chylopoietick Organs, <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">Peterhead</hi> Water has by far the Preemi-
        <lb/>nence: As on the other Hand I have found the <lb/>Uſe of the <hi rend="italic"
          >Aberbrothock</hi> Water of ſingular Ad- <lb/>vantage, in Lowneſs of Spirits and other Ma-
        <lb/>ladies, where the Nerves are ſaid to be affected; <lb/>for which I have alſo ſeen the
          <hi rend="italic">Kincardine</hi> Wa- <lb/>ter beneficial. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>One of our Burghers, about thirty Years of <lb/>Age, of a clean and healthy
        Conſtitution, ha- <lb/>ving met with ſtormy Weather at Sea, fed <lb/>on ſalt Meat, and
        having <choice>
          <corr>had</corr>
          <sic>bad</sic>
        </choice> Succeſs other- <pb n="53"/>
        <lb/>wiſe in a Voyage, returned ſcorbutick, ema- <lb/>ciated, enervated in all the digeſtive
        Powers, <lb/>low ſpirited, and ſo extremely feeble, that he <lb/>could walk or ſit on
        Horſeback with Difficulty: <lb/>After drinking <hi rend="italic">Aberbrothock</hi> Water at
        the Foun- <lb/>tain a few Days, he walked about with Eaſe, <lb/>and with much more Vigour. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A Gentleman of Honour, aged ſixty, of a <lb/>vigorous Body, and who had enjoyed good
        <lb/>Health, impair'd at Times by good Fellowſhip, <lb/>from an Inability to walk without
        Support, re- <lb/>covered Ability to walk with Eaſe by the ſame <lb/>Means in a few Days:
        And he received the <lb/>ſame Benefit in a greater or leſſer Degree for <lb/>ſeveral Years,
        in which he uſed that mineral <lb/>Water. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A Lady in a declining Age, having had Un- <lb/>eaſineſs in her Mind, and becoming
        otherwiſe <lb/>of infirm Health, every accidental Diſorder was <lb/>accompanied with a
        notable ſinking of Spirits. <lb/>After various Medicines that ſeemed at times <lb/>to gain
        on the Diſtemper, which always how- <lb/>ever returned rather worſe, and the Lowneſs <lb/>of
        Spirits ſtill attacking her leſs or more, ſhe <lb/>drank the <hi rend="italic"
          >Aberbrothock</hi> Water at her own Houſe <lb/>in the Spring: The Water was always taken
        <lb/>up at Night, and kept freſh two or three Days, <lb/>and then was renewed. She continued
        the <lb/>Uſe of it a Month, with ſome little Intervals, <lb/>and thereby recovered both
        Health and Spirits. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A Gentleman having ſuffered an aguiſh In- <lb/>diſpoſition ſeveral Years, it ſhifted at
        laſt into <lb/>low Spirits to a great Degree; which he reco- <lb/>vered in good Meaſure, by
        taking to a low <lb/>Diet. When his Symptoms return, as they <pb n="54"/>
        <lb/>often do, the <hi rend="italic">Liege</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Piermont Spaws</hi>
        and <lb/><hi rend="italic">Aberbrothock</hi> Water in its Seaſon are of good <lb/>Uſe to
        him; frequently he prefers the laſt to <lb/>the others, tho' it is brought farther and
        longer <lb/>kept than in the former Caſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I have mentioned theſe two Caſes to ſhew, <lb/>that notwithſtanding the Virtue of the
        Water <lb/>is ſo liable to fly off, yet it proves of good Ef- <lb/>fect at a Diſtance from
        the Fountain; and it <lb/>may prove better this Way, if taken up at a right <lb/>Time, than
        when it is drank at the Well in a <lb/>hot Seaſon, after the Spring hath been expoſed
        <lb/>ſeveral Hours to the Morning Sun. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The beſt Seaſon of drinking theſe Waters is <lb/>doubtleſs in <hi rend="italic"
          >April</hi> and <hi rend="italic">May</hi>, after the Spring <lb/>Rains have fallen, and
        before the Heat of Sum- <lb/>mer comes on; and in the Month of <hi rend="italic"
        >Auguſt</hi>, to <lb/>the Middle of <hi rend="italic">September</hi>, before the Autumn
        <lb/>Rains begin; at both which Seaſons they gene- <lb/>rally taſte moſt of the Mineral: And
        it is com- <lb/>monly obſerved, that in the hotteſt Weather <lb/>theſe Waters taſte moſt
        faint, except after a <lb/>moderate Shower of Rain, when the Taſte turns <lb/>ſtronger, but
        it is weakened after great Rains. <lb/>The Badneſs of the Quarters, and the Pleaſure
        <lb/>and Convenience of walking about in open Air, <lb/>have however determined the Seaſon
        of Uſe to <lb/>the two intermediate Summer Months: But I <lb/>enjoin the People who ask my
        Advice to drink <lb/>this Water rather at home in the proper Sea- <lb/>ſon, and to put the
        cold Air off it at a Fire, if <lb/>it proves cold to the Stomach. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Great Numbers drink the Waters of <hi rend="italic">Aber- <lb/>brothock</hi>, without
        obſerving any Regimen, or <lb/>having any Directions from a Phyſician; nor <pb n="55"/>
        <lb/>do I enjoin any conſiderable Preparation of Bo- <lb/>dy to my Patients, except in very
        remarkable <lb/>Foulneſs of the Juices. Nor do I allow them <lb/>to take Phyſick for
        purging, during the Uſe of <lb/>the Water, if they are not to bath in them. <lb/>The
        Medicine I ordinarily give is <hi rend="italic">Cryſtals of <lb/>Tartar</hi>, to promote the
        Evacuation in the moſt <lb/>ordinary natural Way. With this I ſometimes <lb/>give ſtewed
        Prunes, or ſuch like, to ſtir a ſlug- <lb/>giſh Belly a little. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The vulgar Opinion of all the Benefit of this <lb/>Water being proportioned to the
        Quantity <lb/>drunk, prevails ſo much here, without any Re- <lb/>gard to the Conſtitution,
        and Strength of the <lb/>Patient, or Nature of the Diſeaſe; and ſo ma- <lb/>ny remarkable
        Accidents have happened by <lb/>drinking too much, that there is juſt Reaſon to <lb/>doubt,
        whether the Abuſe of theſe Waters does <lb/>not more Harm than the right Uſe does Good.
        <lb/>My general Rule is not to exceed three <hi rend="italic">Engliſh</hi>
        <lb/>Pints drunk leiſurely, eſpecially till the Eva- <lb/>cuation by Urine begins, chewing
        Cinnamon, <lb/>Carvie, or any other eaſy Aromatick as the Sto- <lb/>mach requires during the
        Drinking, and walk- <lb/>ing in the Intervals of their Drinking and after <lb/>they have
        finiſhed their Day's Doſe, till they <lb/>begin to be ſenſible of Fatigue. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This Rule concerning the Quantity to be <lb/>drunk, and Exerciſe while drinking, I have
        <lb/>found to require one Caution, and one Excep- <lb/>tion. The Caution is taken from the
        Indicati- <lb/>ons in View. When the Springs of the fibrous <lb/>Syſtem are to be ſcrewed up
        by the Force of <lb/>the Mineral, its greater Quantity and ſtronger <lb/>Conſiſtence with
        leſs of the diluent Element <pb n="56"/>
        <lb/>are neceſſary; and therefore the Waters which <lb/>give the higheſt Tincture upon
        Trial, and theſe <lb/>drunk in ſmaller Quantities are preferable: And <lb/>this makes me
        regret that there are no tolerable <lb/>Quarters nor Fields for walking near the <hi
          rend="italic">Glen- <lb/>dy-well</hi>, which is of the higheſt mineral Tin- <lb/>cture,
        next to that of <hi rend="italic">Peterhead</hi>. I have cau- <lb/>ſed it to be brought
        ſometimes to People's <lb/>Houſes, where it did Good; but I have never <lb/>ſeen the Uſe of
        it long enough protracted to <lb/>make any Obſervation of Conſequence thereon. <lb/>If our
        Deſign principally is to waſh the In- <lb/>wards, the weaker Kinds of the mineral Waters
        <lb/>are moſt proper. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Exception to Exerciſe is chiefly in the <lb/>Caſe of great Relaxation of the
        Stomach and <lb/>digeſtive Powers, which makes the Patients li- <lb/>able to throw up their
        Food, as moſt frequent- <lb/>ly happens to Females. I order ſuch to feed a- <lb/>Bed, and to
        ly cloſe till the firſt Digeſtion is ac- <lb/>compliſhed; and this ſerves to good Purpoſe
        <lb/>preventing the Stomach's caſting up its Con- <lb/>teſts. A Gentlewoman ſuppoſed quite
        loſt in <lb/>this Diſeaſe, her inward Powers being altoge- <lb/>ther enervated with a
        miſerable Scene of ſuc- <lb/>ceeding Symptoms during ſeveral Years, was <lb/>at laſt carried
        from this Place to <hi rend="italic">Peterhead</hi>, <lb/>where ſhe drank all the Water
        a-Bed, laying <lb/>herſelf to ſteep after each Draught; by which <lb/>Means ſhe retained
        all: And tho' ſhe got into <lb/>drinking the Water to the Exceſs of a <hi rend="italic"
          >Scottiſh</hi>
        <lb/>Pint a Day, yet ſhe returned perfectly recover- <lb/>ed, and remains ſo theſe ſeveral
        Years. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Aberbrothock</hi> Water has got the Prefe- <lb/>rence to the reſt
        in this Country, moſt Cures <pb n="57"/>
        <lb/>having been made by it. Whether this is ow- <lb/>ing to its Vogue, having occaſioned a
        greater <lb/>Number of Patients to repair to it; or whether <lb/>it depends on its
        intrinſick comparative Virtue <lb/>from the <hi rend="italic">Sulphur</hi>, which I begin to
        diſcover <lb/>more conſpicuous in it than in the others, I <lb/>ſhall not determine; but in
        all ordinary Caſes <lb/>I recommend the neareſt <hi rend="italic">Spaw</hi>, and have fre-
        <lb/>quently ſeen the Effect anſwer, eſpecially by <lb/><hi rend="italic">Kincardine</hi>
        Well, and that on our River of <hi rend="italic">Eſk</hi>, <lb/>in the Skirts of the <hi
          rend="italic">Grampians</hi>; the former <lb/>however comes nearer to <hi rend="italic"
          >Aberbrothock</hi> Water <lb/>in the Cure of nervous Diſeaſes. A Girl in bad <lb/>Caſe of
        the Nerves, as Nature was framing her <lb/>into the Condition of her Sex; and her Bro-
        <lb/>ther, a Boy of ten Years of Age, enervated to <lb/>almoſt a Cripple all over his Body,
        are now <lb/>recovered by drinking and bathing in theſe <lb/>Waters two Seaſons. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
