<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Monro: A Description of the seminal Vessels</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Alexander Monro</persName>
            </author>
            <title>ART. XVI. A Description of the seminal Vessels, by ALEXANDER MONRO, Student of
              Medicine in the University of Edinburgh.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Essays and observations, physical and literary. Read before a society in
              Edinburgh, and published by them. </title>
            <author>Philosophical Society of Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: printed by G. Hamilton and J. Balfour, Printers to the
                  University</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1754</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">1</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">396-402</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107037053</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T136789</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ2_v1_0396">
    <body>
      <pb n=""/>
      <head rend="sc align-center">
        <lb/>Art. XVI. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>A Deſcription of the ſeminal Veſſels, by <hi rend="sc">Ale- <lb/>xander Monro</hi>,
        Student of Medicine in <lb/>the Univerſity of <hi rend="roman">Edinburgh</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HO' all anatomiſts agree, that the ſeed <lb/>ſeparated in the
        teſticle, paſſes thro' <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">epidydimis</hi> to riſe in the <hi
          rend="italic">vas defe- <lb/>rens</hi>; yet few have a right notion of even the
        <lb/>groſſer tubes in which it is conveyed. I have <lb/>luckily made quickſilver paſs
        ſarther in theſe <lb/>ſeminal veſſels, and thereby brought more of <lb/>them into view, than
        I ſee deſcribed in any <lb/>anatomical book; as you may judge by the <lb/>preparations and
        pictures which I now ſend <lb/>you, at my father's deſire. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">De Graaf</hi> had formerly endeavoured, by <lb/>diſſection, to
        unravel the <hi rend="italic">epidydimis</hi>; and <lb/>paints it <note place="bottom" n="*"
          rend="italic size(0.6)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* De Vir. Organ. Tab. 1. Fig. 3. et Tab. 4. Fig. 3. </p>
        </note>, as riſing from the teſticle in ſix or <lb/>ſeven branches, which join at its <hi
          rend="italic">caput</hi> or <lb/>firſt remarkable turn into one pipe, the nu- <lb/>merous
        contortions of which form the body <pb n="397"/>
        <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">epidydimis</hi>, terminating at its other end <lb/>in the <hi
          rend="italic">vas deferens</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> ſeems to have been overlooked, or <lb/>not well underſtood, by
        moſt of the modern <lb/>anatomiſts, who have differed widely, or <lb/>talked with
        uncertainty, about theſe pipes; <lb/>till of late, that the ingenious Dr. <hi rend="italic"
          >Haller</hi>, by <lb/>injecting quickſilver from the <hi rend="italic">vas deferens</hi>,
        in <lb/>the manner propoſed by my father in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Medical Eſſays</hi>
        <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.6)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Vol. v. Art. xx. § 29. </p>
        </note>, and cauſing it to paſs as ſar <lb/>as the teſticle, has been able to explain to us,
        <lb/>with greater accuracy, the ſtructure of this <lb/>intricate organ <note place="bottom"
          n="†" rend="size(0.6)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† Phil. Tranſ. No 494. § xii. </p>
        </note>. He agrees with <hi rend="italic">De Graaf</hi>, <lb/>that the <hi rend="italic"
          >epidydimis</hi>, from the <hi rend="italic">vas deferens</hi> to <lb/>its <hi
          rend="italic">head</hi>, ſeems to be compoſed of a ſingle <lb/>pipe, which he thinks might
        poſſibly be un- <lb/>looſened, as <hi rend="italic">De Graaf</hi> has repreſented; but
        <lb/>does not affirm his having executed it. At <lb/>its <hi rend="italic">head</hi> indeed,
        he could divide it into ten or <lb/>more vaſcular cones, from which veſſels go <lb/>out,
        that, after forming a network with com- <lb/>munications, give off ſtreight pipes which
        <lb/>ſeem to plunge into the body of the teſticle. <lb/>—<hi rend="sc">His</hi> injection
        here generally failed, tho' he <lb/>ſometimes obſerved, that it entered a few con- <pb
          n="398"/>
        <lb/>voluted tubes.—He mentions his having thrice <lb/>ſeen a veſſel going off from about
        the middle <lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">epidydimis</hi> towards the ſpermatic cord,
        <lb/>which he imagines is a <hi rend="italic">lymphatic</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">That</hi> this accurate anatomiſt's improve- <lb/>ments, and the
        additions I am to make to <lb/>them, may be better underſtood; I have firſt <lb/>copied his
        elegant figure, and then ſubjoined <lb/>ſome others I cauſed to be drawn of thoſe
        <lb/>parts. </p>
      <figure>
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Tab.</hi> 3. <hi rend="italic">fig.</hi> 1. from Dr. <hi rend="italic"
            >Haller</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <list>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/>A. The <hi rend="italic">vas deferens</hi>. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/>B. The end or laſt turn of the <hi rend="italic">epidydimis</hi>. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/>C. Its body, as it appears when the exter- <lb/>nal membrane is diſſected off. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/>D. Its <hi rend="italic">head</hi> unlooſened. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">eee. &amp;c.</hi> The vaſcular cones into which it
              <lb/>divides. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">ff.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">vaſa efferentia</hi>, as he
              calls them. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">gg.</hi> The network with communications. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">hh.</hi> The ſtreight veſſels which ſeem to <lb/>plunge into
              the teſticle. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of the different parts of the epididymis on a separate page.
        </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">fig.</hi> 2. The <hi rend="italic">tunica vaginalis</hi> of the te-
          <lb/>ſticle is cut off, and the teſticle, injected <hi rend="italic">e-
            <lb/>pidydimis</hi> and ſpermatic cord, are repreſent- <lb/>ed covered with their
          membranes. <pb n="399"/>
          <list>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/>A. The ſerpentine beginning of the <hi rend="italic">vas <lb/>deferens</hi>. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/>B. The <hi rend="italic">globus minor</hi>, or laſt turn of the <lb/><hi
                rend="italic">epidydimis</hi>, from which the ſmall convo- <lb/>luted veſſel, <hi
                rend="italic">c</hi>, which Dr. <hi rend="italic">Haller</hi> ſup- <lb/>poſes to be
              a lymphatic, riſes.—If it <lb/>is ſo, it has not the valvular ſtructure <lb/>common to
              thoſe veſſels; for I can cauſe <lb/>the quick-ſilver to flow either way in it. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/>D. The <hi rend="italic">corpus pyramidale</hi>. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/>E. The body of the <hi rend="italic">epidydimis</hi>, where the <lb/>convolutions
              ſeen thro' the membranes, <lb/>are larger than they appear in <hi rend="italic"
                >fig.</hi> 1. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/>F. The <hi rend="italic">head</hi>, <hi rend="italic">globus major</hi>, or firſt
              remark- <lb/>able turn of the <hi rend="italic">epidydimis</hi>. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/>G. Its riſe from the teſticle. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <figDesc>An illustration of the testicle, epididymis, and spermatic cord, on a separate
          page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">fig.</hi> 3. and 4. The <hi rend="italic">tunica albuginea</hi> is
          <lb/>taken off from the ſides of the teſticle, and <lb/>turned over upon the <hi
            rend="italic">epidydimis</hi>. <list>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/>A. The <hi rend="italic">tunica albuginea</hi>. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/>B. The teſticle. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">hh.</hi> Dr. <hi rend="italic">Haller</hi>'s ſtreight pipes
              from which </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">ccc.</hi> The ſmall convoluted tubes upon the <lb/>ſides of the
              teſticle are continued. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="italic">dd.</hi> In <hi rend="italic">fig.</hi> 4. Repreſents a number
              of them <lb/>upon the convex part of the teſticle, at <lb/>the greateſt diſtance from
              the <hi rend="italic">epidydimis</hi>. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <figDesc>Two illustrations of the testicle on a separate page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <pb n="400"/>
      <figure>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Fig.</hi> 5. Repreſents the teſticle drawn aſun- <lb/>der in its middle
          from its convex ſurface to- <lb/>wards the <hi rend="italic">epidydimis</hi>. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Fig.</hi> 6. A ſmall piece is in the ſame man- <lb/>ner ſeparated from
          the ſide of it. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> both we obſerve Dr. <hi rend="italic">Haller</hi>'s ſtreight
          <lb/>veſſels entering at <hi rend="italic">hh</hi>; and then dividing into <lb/><hi
            rend="italic">ccc</hi> inumerable convoluted pipes, which com- <lb/>poſe almoſt the
          whole ſubſtance of the teſti- <lb/>cle. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">dd.</hi> A number of them where the injecti- <lb/>on has gone very
          far. </p>
        <figDesc>Two illustrations of the testicle on a separate page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>N. <hi rend="sc">These</hi> preparations had been kept ſe- <lb/>veral months in
        ſpirits, and ſo often handled <lb/>before the drawings were made, that many <lb/>of the
        injected veſſels are deſtroyed, and the <lb/>painter could not diſtinguiſh the membranous
        <lb/>partitions of the teſticle. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>As many of the moſt accurate anatomiſts<unclear>,</unclear>
        <lb/>and even <hi rend="italic">Winſlow</hi>
        <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.6)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Exp. anat. traité de bas ventre. § 488. </p>
        </note>, have imagined, that the <lb/>body of the <hi rend="italic">epidydimis</hi> is
        compoſed of a num- <lb/>ber of pipes.—As Dr. <hi rend="italic">Haller</hi> does not po-
        <lb/>ſitively affirm his having unlooſened it.— <lb/>As the <hi rend="italic">vas
          deferens</hi> is much larger than any <pb n="401"/>
        <lb/>pipe in the <hi rend="italic">epidydimis</hi>, and as it ſeems diffi- <lb/>cult to
        conceive how the ſeed can be propel- <lb/>ed thro' a tube ſo ſmall, ſo much convoluted,
        <lb/>and of ſuch a length as the ſingle one, which, <lb/>according to <hi rend="italic">De
          Graaf</hi>, forms the <hi rend="italic">epidydimis</hi>: <lb/>on theſe accounts, I think,
        there is reaſon to <lb/>doubt this ſtructure which he aſſerts, till we <lb/>have more
        ſatisfying proof of it than has hi- <lb/>therto been adduced.—Such the following
        <lb/>appears to be. If, in attempting to make <lb/>preparations like to thoſe above
        deſcribed, an <lb/>extravaſation happens in any part of the <hi rend="italic">epi-
          <lb/>dydimis</hi>, or if any of its convolutions are tied, <lb/>not a drop of the
        injection can be puſhed <lb/>farther towards the teſticle than this extrava- <lb/>ſation or
        ligature: and, if the <hi rend="italic">epidydimis</hi> is <lb/>cut acroſs, while
        quickſilver is poured into <lb/>the tube fixed in the <hi rend="italic">vas deferens</hi>,
        it ſquirts <lb/>out only at one orifice in this cut part; which <lb/>is the plaineſt and
        moſt convincing demon- <lb/>ſtration of the body of the <hi rend="italic">epidydimis</hi>,
        being <lb/>intirely compoſed of a ſingle tube convoluted <lb/>in a moſt wonderful manner. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Tho'</hi> my injection penetrated far into the <lb/>ſeminal pipes; yet
        ſtill we are unacquainted <lb/>with their origin. <hi rend="italic">De Graaf</hi>
        <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.6)">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* De vir. org. p. 42. </p>
        </note> attempted in <pb n="402"/>
        <lb/>vain to diſcover this by maceration in water<unclear>;</unclear>
        <lb/>nor have anatomiſts ſince his time been more <lb/>ſucceſsful. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I have endeavoured ſeveral times to force <lb/>quick-ſilver from the ſpermatic arteries
        into <lb/>the ſeminal veſſels; but, tho' I made it re- <lb/>turn by the ſpermatic veins, I
        could never <lb/>cauſe it to paſs into theſe convoluted tubes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> I attempted the oftener, becauſe of <lb/>the ſeeming
        probability of our being able to <lb/>determine, better in this than in other glands,
        <lb/>whether ſecretion is performed in continued <lb/>cylindrical canals, according to <hi
          rend="italic">Ruyſch</hi>, or, <lb/>by the intervention of follicles, with <hi
          rend="italic">Mal- <lb/>pighius</hi>; ſince we can ſeparate the parts of <lb/>the
        teſticle, without cutting, and even al- <lb/>moſt without laceration. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
