<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Whytt: Of the Difference between Respiration and the Motion of the
          Heart</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Robert Whytt</persName>
            </author>
            <title>ART. XIX. Of the Difference between Respiration and the Motion of the Heart, in
              sleeping and waking Persons, by ROBERT WHYTT, M. D. &amp;c.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Essays and observations, physical and literary. Read before a society in
              Edinburgh, and published by them. </title>
            <author>Philosophical Society of Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: printed by G. Hamilton and J. Balfour, Printers to the
                  University</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1754</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">1</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">436-446</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107037053</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T136789</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ2_v1_0436">
    <body>
      <pb n="436"/>
      <head rend="sc align-center">
        <lb/>Art. XIX. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Of the Difference between Reſpiration and the <lb/>Motion of the Heart, in ſleeping and
        wa- <lb/>king Perſons, by <hi rend="sc">Robert Whytt, M. D.</hi>
        <lb/>&amp;c. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">O</hi>F all the parts of the human body, there <lb/>is none whoſe
        ſtructure is more ſub- <lb/>tile, and whoſe ſeveral functions and uſes are <lb/>leſs known,
        than thoſe of the brain. It is <lb/>little to be wondered at, therefore, if au- <lb/>thors
        have failed of giving a ſatisfactory ac- <lb/>count of <hi rend="italic">ſleep</hi>, which
        is one particular ſtate <lb/>of this unknown organ.—We have elſewhere <lb/>offered our
        conjectures concerning the reaſon <lb/>why the vital motions continue in time of <lb/>ſleep;
        when the organs of ſenſe become leſs <lb/>fit to receive the impreſſions of external ob-
        <lb/>jects; and when the muſcles of voluntary <lb/>motion are more relaxed and remain at
        reſt <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)" n="*">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Eſſay on the Vital and other Involuntary motions of a- <lb/>nimals, ſect. xii.
          </p>
        </note>. <lb/>But, as reſpiration and the motion of the <pb n="437"/>
        <lb/>heart, ſuffer ſome change in time of ſleep, <lb/><hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> become
        then ſlower, fuller and more e- <lb/>quable, than when we are awake <note place="bottom"
          rend="size(0.6)" n="*">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* <hi rend="sc">Boerhaave</hi> Inſtitut. Med. § 599. </p>
        </note>, it may <lb/>be worth while to enquire a little into the <lb/>reaſon of this <hi
          rend="italic">phaenomenon</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">It</hi> has been ſhewn, that as the dilatation <lb/>of the ventricles of
        the heart, is owing to <lb/>the force of the refluent venous blood; ſo <lb/>their
        contraction is produced, by the ſame <lb/>blood acting upon them as a <hi rend="italic"
          >ſtimulus</hi>
        <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)" n="†">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† Vid. Eſſay on Vital and other Involuntary motions of <lb/>animals, ſect. iii. and
            iv. </p>
        </note>: and <lb/>that the heart can only be affected by <hi rend="italic">ſtimuli</hi>,
        <lb/>in ſo far as it is a ſentient organ, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> en- <lb/>dued with
        feeling <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)" n="‡">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>‡ Ibid. ſect. x. p. 271. &amp;c. </p>
        </note>. Whence it muſt follow, <lb/>that the ſlowneſs of the pulſe in ſleep, and
        <lb/>indeed in every other caſe, can only ariſe <lb/>from one or more of the following
        general <lb/>cauſes, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> 1. A diminution of the ſtimu- <lb/>lating
        quality of the blood. 2. Its ſlower re- <lb/>turn to the heart; or, 3. A leſs degree of
        <lb/>ſenſibility or aptitude for motion in the heart <lb/>itſelf. </p>
      <pb n="438"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I. <hi rend="sc">When</hi> one has eat or drunk a great deal <lb/>before ſleep, his
        pulſe will be, not ſlow, but <lb/>quick and full; becauſe the ſtimulating power <lb/>of the
        blood is increaſed, by a large quantity <lb/>of chyle received into it. Much the ſame
        <lb/>thing may happen from ſleeping in too hot <lb/>an air, or under too great a weight of
        cloaths: <lb/>for we know, that heat quickens the circu- <lb/>lation of the fluids in all
        animals. On <lb/>the other hand, when one has faſted long <lb/>before ſleep, and lies very
        cool, his pulſe <lb/>will, in time of it, be unuſually ſlow. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">But</hi> when the blood is neither loaded <lb/>with new chyle, nor
        altogether deſtitute of <lb/>it; neither too much heated by cloaths or <lb/>the external
        air, nor too cool, thro' want of <lb/>proper covering; its ſtimulating quality will
        <lb/>neither be augmented nor diminiſhed by <lb/>ſleep; but will continue the ſame as in a
        per- <lb/>ſon who is awake in the ſame circumſtances. <lb/>It remains therefore, that the
        ſlowneſs of the <lb/>heart's motion in time of ſleep, be owing, <lb/>either to the ſlower
        return of the venous <lb/>blood to it, or to ſome diminution of its ſen- <lb/>ſibility. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>II. <hi rend="sc">Every</hi> one knows, that the affections <lb/>of the mind diſturb
        the motion of the heart; <pb n="439"/>
        <lb/>that the pulſe is quicker when we ſit or ſtand <lb/>than when we lye; and that the
        action of <lb/>the muſcles of voluntary motion, not only <lb/>promotes the return of the
        blood to the <lb/>heart, but determines it thither, with much <lb/>greater force than uſual.
        In ſleep therefore, <lb/>where the horizontal poſture of the body, <lb/>the quieſcence of
        the voluntary muſcles, and <lb/>compoſure of the mind, all concur to render <lb/>the return
        of the venous blood to the heart, <lb/>more equable and ſlow, the contraction of <lb/>this
        muſcle muſt be renewed at greater inter- <lb/>vals, and with more regularity, than when
        <lb/>we are awake, and the circulation is quicken- <lb/>ed or diſturbed by ſome, or all, of
        the above- <lb/>mentioned cauſes. But, if no farther cir- <lb/>cumſtance, tending to retard
        the heart's mo- <lb/>tion, were found in ſleep, the pulſe ſhould <lb/>be equally ſlow and
        full in a waking perſon <lb/>lying at reſt in a horizontal poſture, and <lb/>whoſe mind is
        compoſed, as in the ſame per- <lb/>ſon in time of ſleep; which, however, does <lb/>not ſeem
        to be entirely the caſe: for tho' the <lb/>difference may be ſmall, and there may be
        <lb/>many cauſes which may render it difficult, by <lb/>obſervation, to determine that
        difſerence with <lb/>any degree of certainty; yet the remarkable <pb n="440"/>
        <lb/>ſlowneſs and fulneſs of the pulſe in the deep <lb/>ſleep, accompanying an apoplexy or
        occaſioned <lb/>by <hi rend="italic">opium</hi>, makes it highly probable, that even <lb/>in
        the much gentler ſleep of perſons in <lb/>health, the pulſe is ſomewhat ſlower and
        <lb/>fuller, than it would be, merely from the <lb/>compoſure of mind, horizontal poſition
        of <lb/>the body, and quieſcence of the muſcles of <lb/>voluntary motion. Let us therefore
        ſee, whe- <lb/>ther the ſlowneſs and fulneſs of the heart's <lb/>motion in time of ſleep,
        may not be in part <lb/>owing, to ſome diminution of the ſenſibility <lb/>of this organ. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>3. In time of ſleep, as the exerciſe of the <lb/>ſeveral ſenſes, is either ſuſpended or
        much <lb/>impaired; ſo the ſenſibility or feeling, with <lb/>which the organs of the body
        are more or <lb/>leſs endued, ſeems to be rendered leſs acute. <lb/>Thus we feel ourſelves
        affected with a kind <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">ſtupor</hi>, when we are juſt ſalling aſleep,
        <lb/>and are then inſenſible of leſſer <hi rend="italic">ſtimuli</hi>. The <lb/>thin rheum,
        which, by irritating the wind- <lb/>pipe, keeps us almoſt perpetually coughing <lb/>when
        awake, gives us little or no diſturbance <lb/>in ſleep; any extraordinary <hi rend="italic"
          >ſtimulus</hi> in the guts <lb/>is alſo leſs perceived then; and hence it is, <lb/>that a
        doſe of any purgative taken at night, is <pb n="441"/>
        <lb/>much longer before it operates, than when it <lb/>is ſwallowed in the morning. If the
        heart <lb/>therefore, like the other organs of the body, <lb/>becomes leſs ſenſible or
        irritable in time of <lb/>ſleep, it will not be ſo quickly excited into <lb/>contraction as
        uſual, by the venous blood ruſh- <lb/>ing into its cavities; and hence its contracti-
        <lb/>ons will not only be more ſlowly repeated, <lb/>but the pulſe will be full, becauſe the
        ventri- <lb/>cles do not contract, till they are much diſ- <lb/>tended with blood. This will
        ſtill further <lb/>appear, if we conſider how remarkably ſlow <lb/>and full the pulſe is, in
        an apoplexy, where <lb/>the ſenſibility of all the parts and their apti- <lb/>tude for
        motion, are much more impaired <lb/>than in common ſleep: and how <hi rend="italic"
          >opium</hi>, which <lb/>occaſions ſleep, and leſſens the ſenſe of feel- <lb/>ing every
        where thro' the body, when given <lb/>in a large doſe, renders the pulſe uncom- <lb/>monly
        ſlow and full. Thus the heart of a <lb/>frog, into whoſe ſtomach and guts I had, an
        <lb/>hour before, injected a ſolution of <hi rend="italic">opium</hi>, <lb/>was obſerved to
        beat near four times ſlower <lb/>than uſual; and the auricle and great veins <lb/>leading to
        the heart, were remarkably diſ- <lb/>tended with blood, as was alſo the ventricle <lb/>of
        the heart before every contraction. At <pb n="442"/>
        <lb/>the ſame time the other muſcles of this ani- <lb/>mal were ſo intirely deprived of
        feeling as <lb/>not to be, in any degree, affected by prick- <lb/>ing or tearing their
        fibres <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)" n="*">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Eſſay on the Vital and Involuntary motions, &amp;c. p. 372. </p>
        </note>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Does</hi> not the ſlower digeſtion of the ali- <lb/>ment in time of
        ſleep, proceed, partly, from <lb/>the periſtaltic motion of the ſtomach and guts <lb/>being
        then repeated after longer intervals? <lb/>In dogs who have got a large doſe of <hi
          rend="italic">opium</hi>, this <lb/>motion is very much leſſened or totally ſuſpend-
        <lb/>ed, the food laſt received into the ſtomach re- <lb/>mains there indigeſted, the guts
        are more <lb/>than <choice>
          <corr>uſually</corr>
          <sic>uſualy</sic>
        </choice> empty, and the lacteal veſſels in- <lb/>viſible <note place="bottom"
          rend="size(0.6)" n="†">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>† <hi rend="sc"><unclear>Kadu</unclear></hi> impet. faciens <hi rend="sc"
              >Hippocrat.</hi> dictum, N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 434. <lb/>435. </p>
        </note>. In ſleep, therefore, not only the <lb/>heart but the ſtomach and guts alſo, become
        <lb/>leſs ſenſible of the <hi rend="italic">ſtimulus</hi> uſually affecting <lb/>them, and
        conſequently repeat their contra- <lb/>ctions more ſlowly. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">De Gorter</hi>, differing from <hi rend="italic">Boerhaave</hi> and
        o- <lb/>ther authors, thinks, that the pulſe muſt be, <lb/>not fuller, but ſofter in time of
        ſleep, becauſe <lb/>the circulation of the blood is allowed, then, <lb/>to proceed more
        ſlowly than when we are a- <pb n="443"/>
        <lb/>wake <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)" n="†">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/><choice>
              <corr>†</corr>
              <sic>‡</sic>
            </choice> Exercit. de ſomno et vigilia. § xl. </p>
        </note>. But, from what has been ſaid, it ap- <lb/>pears, that the fulneſs of the pulſe in
        ſleep, is not <lb/>owing to the quicker circulation of the blood, <lb/>but to a leſs degree
        of ſenſibility in the heart, <lb/>whereby its ventricles are not excited into
        <lb/>contraction, till they have been more fully <lb/>dilated, then uſual, by the returning
        blood. <lb/>It is, however, to be obſerved, that the ful- <lb/>neſs of the pulſe in ſleep,
        may be owing <lb/>partly, to the fluids paſſing, with greater diffi- <lb/>culty, thro' the
        very ſmall lateral arteries, and <lb/>the ſecretory tubes of the glands <note place="bottom"
          rend="size(0.6)" n="*">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>
            <hi rend="sc">Boerhaave</hi> Inſtitut. med. § 597. </p>
        </note>. For we <lb/>know that the fulneſs or ſoftneſs of the pulſe <lb/>does not depend,
        ſolely, upon the quantity of <lb/>blood thrown out by the left ventricle of the <lb/>heart,
        but alſo upon the more or leſs difficult <lb/>paſſage of this fluid thro' the extreme
        arteries; <lb/>ſince, in proportion as theſe are obſtructed <lb/>or open, a greater or leſs
        reſiſtance will be <lb/>oppoſed to the blood projected by the heart. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">After</hi> what has been ſaid of the ſlowneſs <lb/>of the heart's motion
        in ſleep, it will be eaſy <lb/>to ſhew why reſpiration ſhould be performed, <lb/>then, at
        greater intervals. </p>
      <pb n="444"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> cauſe exciting the alternate contracti- <lb/>on of the
        inſpiratory muſcles, is an uneaſy <lb/>ſenſation in the lungs, occaſioned by the <lb/>blood
        puſhed into their veſſels by the right <lb/>ventricle of the heart <note place="bottom"
          rend="size(0.6)" n="*">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Eſſay on Vital and Involuntary motions, &amp;c. p. 176. &amp;c. </p>
        </note>. If then leſs blood <lb/>is ſent, in a given time, into the lungs, in <lb/>ſleep,
        than when we are awake; the neceſſity <lb/>of new ſupplies of freſh air will be leſſened,
        <lb/>and conſequently inſpiration will be perform- <lb/>ed at greater intervals. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Further</hi>, as in time of ſleep, the ſenſi- <lb/>bility of the lungs,
        like that of the heart <lb/>and guts, muſt be ſomewhat impaired, re- <lb/>ſpiration muſt
        alſo, on this account, be per- <lb/>formed more ſlowly; for the inſpiratory <lb/>muſcles
        will not be excited into action till a <lb/>greater degree of irritation, than uſual, be
        <lb/>occaſioned by the blood accumulated in the <lb/>pulmonary veſſels. And, to this it is
        owing, <lb/>that reſpiration is not only ſlower but ſome- <lb/>what deeper in time of ſleep,
        than in a waking <lb/>perſon at reſt in a <choice>
          <corr>horizontal</corr>
          <sic>horrizontal</sic>
        </choice> poſition. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">In</hi> comatous and apoplectic caſes, where <lb/>all the feelings of the
        body are much more <lb/>impaired than in ordinary ſleep, reſpiration is <lb/>not only much
        ſlower and deeper than uſual, <pb n="445"/>
        <lb/>but, ſometimes, after expiration is finiſhed, <lb/>a pauſe of 15, 20, 30, or more
        ſeconds will <lb/>intervene, before a new inſpiration is begun. <lb/>Much the ſame thing
        happens to animals <lb/>who have ſwallowed too great a quantity of <lb/><hi rend="italic"
          >opium</hi>
        <note place="bottom" rend="size(0.6)" n="*">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* Eſſay on the Vital and Involuntary motions, &amp;c. p. 194. </p>
        </note>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Now</hi>, if it be reaſonable to aſcribe the ſlow, <lb/>deep and
        interrupted breathing, in ſuch <lb/>caſes, to the inſenſibility which attends thoſe
        <lb/>diſeaſes of the head; and which <hi rend="italic">opium</hi> never <lb/>fails to
        produce, when taken too liberally; <lb/>are we not hence led to conclude, the leſs re-
        <lb/>markable change of breathing which hap- <lb/>pens in ſleep, to be owing, partly, to the
        <lb/>ſenſe of feeling in the lungs, being then <lb/>ſomewhat diminiſhed, tho' in a much leſs
        <lb/>degree than in thoſe morbid caſes? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">To</hi> conclude with ſumming up what has <lb/>been ſaid in a few words;
        in ordinary ſleep <lb/>the ſenſibility of the heart and lungs ſuffer <lb/>ſo ſmall a
        diminution, that their motions <lb/>will be very little more affected by it, than <lb/>they
        would be from the horrizontal poſition <lb/>and reſt of the body, and compoſure of mind
        <lb/>attending it. In the deeper ſleep, which <lb/>ſucceeds great fatigue, the motions of
        the <pb n="446"/>
        <lb/>heart and lungs will be more obſervably al- <lb/>tered. And, in the moſt profound
        ſleep, oc- <lb/>caſioned by <hi rend="italic">opium</hi> or a morbid ſtate of the
        <lb/>brain, where a general inſenſibility reigns <lb/>over the whole body; the pulſe will
        become <lb/>much more remarkably ſlow and full, and <lb/>reſpiration ſlower and deeper. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
