<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: A Child brought forth at a Rent of the Belly</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>ART. XXIV. A Child brought forth at a Rent of the Belly*.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Essays and observations, physical and literary. Read before a society in
              Edinburgh, and published by them. </title>
            <author>Philosophical Society of Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: printed by G. Hamilton and J. Balfour, Printers to the
                  University</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1756</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">2</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">338-341</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107037544</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T136785</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ2_v2_0338">
    <body>
      <pb n="338"/>
      <head rend="sc align-center">
        <lb/>Art. XXIV. </head>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic space">
          <lb/>A Child brought forth at a Rent of the Belly <note n="*" place="bottom"
            rend="size(0.6) roman">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* <date>May 1. 1755. </date>
            </p>
          </note>. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 1736, <hi rend="italic">Elſpet
            Grant</hi>, in the pariſh <lb/>of <hi rend="italic">Moy</hi>, being with child, took her
          la- <lb/>bour-pains. After they had continued three <lb/>days with the child in the birth,
          two cracks, <lb/>as if the rafters of the houſe had broke, <lb/>were heard about the ſick
          wife, and her bel- <lb/>ly was rent from near the navel, with a <lb/>ſquaint downwards and
          to the left ſide, to <lb/>near the ſhare-bone. At this rent the child <lb/>came into the
          world, the after-burthen was <lb/>brought away, and the intrails were ſeen. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> rent was cured without any other ap- <lb/>plication, than that
          of butter mixed with <lb/>white ſugar, and its ſcar was only as the <lb/>ſcratch of a big
          pin. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">These</hi> facts are atteſted by the judicial <lb/>oaths of <hi
            rend="sc">Anna Kennedy</hi> a midwife, and <hi rend="italic">Mary <lb/>Ogilvie</hi> a
          neighbour, who were preſent when <lb/>the rent was made and the child came out <lb/>of it;
          of <hi rend="italic">Margaret Dallas</hi>, who aſſiſted to <pb n="339"/>
          <lb/>bring away the after-burthen; of <hi rend="italic">Robert <lb/>Smith</hi> who ſaw the
          rent and intrails imme- <lb/>diately after this; and of <hi rend="italic">Iſobel
            Tarrel</hi>, who, <lb/>afterwards examined the ſcar: taken and <lb/>ſubſcribed by <hi
            rend="italic">James Macqueen</hi> younger of <lb/><hi rend="italic">Corribrough</hi>,
          Bailie to the Laird of <hi rend="italic">Mackintoſh</hi>, <lb/>at <hi rend="italic"
            >Moyhall</hi>, <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 22. 1738; of which <lb/>the original
          ſubſcribed copies are kept by the <lb/>Secretaries of the Philoſophical Society of
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Edinburgh</hi>. </p>
      </div>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic hanging">
          <lb/>A Child eſcaping at a Rent of the Womb in- <lb/>to the <hi rend="roman">Abdomen</hi>;
          by <hi rend="sc">Alexander Monro</hi>, <lb/>ſenior, M. D. &amp; P. A. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 1744, I was deſired by Mr.
            <lb/><hi rend="italic">Ramſay</hi> Surgeon here, to witneſs the exa- <lb/>mination of
          the body of a woman who died <lb/>in child-labour without being delivered. The
          <lb/>account given me of this woman was, that <lb/>ſhe was about 35 years of age, and had
          born <lb/>two dead children, and a living one. Being at <lb/>her full reckoning, her pains
          had begun on <lb/><hi rend="italic">Tueſday</hi> morning, and continued in a natural
          <lb/>way, the child advancing towards the birth, <pb n="340"/>
          <lb/>and ſome of the waters coming away all that <lb/>day and <hi rend="italic"
            >Wedneſday</hi>, till <hi rend="italic">Wedneſday</hi> evening, <lb/>when ſitting in a
          chair in labour, ſhe gave <lb/>a ſudden ſpring from the chair, complaining <lb/>of violent
          pain in her belly. The child ne- <lb/>ver was felt afterwards by thoſe who attempt-
          <lb/>ed to aſſiſt her delivery. She conſtantly <lb/>complained of violent pain in her
          belly, with <lb/>her ſenſes and judgment intire, till <hi rend="italic">Friday</hi>
          <lb/>morning, when ſhe died. On <hi rend="italic">Saturday</hi> her <lb/>body was opened. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">After</hi> cleaning away with ſpunges a con- <lb/>ſiderable quantity of
          blood floating in the <lb/><hi rend="italic">abdomen</hi>, we ſaw a ripe child and its
          ſecun- <lb/>dines lying in the lower part of it, a little to <lb/>the right ſide. The
          child, <hi rend="italic">placenta</hi>, and um- <lb/>bilical rope were intire, and the
          membranes <lb/>were as uſual after birth. The woman's <hi rend="italic">ute- <lb/>rus</hi>
          had its <hi rend="italic">fundus</hi> raiſed as high as the navel, <lb/>with its ſubſtance
          ſoft and ſpongy as is com- <lb/>mon in pregnants, nothing preternatural <lb/>appearing in
          its fore-ſide; but when the <lb/><hi rend="italic">fundus</hi> was turned down and
          forwards to- <lb/>wards the <hi rend="italic">oſſa pubis</hi>, a large rent four inches
          <lb/>long was ſeen towards the neck of the womb; <lb/>which being again put into its
          natural ſitua- <lb/>tion, was opened its whole length, in the <pb n="341"/>
          <lb/>middle of its forepart, when we had a bet- <lb/>ter view of the rent, extending from
          very <lb/>near the <hi rend="italic">os uteri</hi> upwards, a little obliquely <lb/>to the
          right ſide. The <hi rend="italic">os uteri</hi> was then ve- <lb/>ry little open. The <hi
            rend="italic">cervix</hi> which is diſtin- <lb/>guiſhable plainly from the <hi
            rend="italic">fundus</hi> in a woman <lb/>not with child, was here extended into the
          <lb/>ſame common ſac with it. The inner ſurface <lb/>of the womb was all ſmooth, ſeeming
          to be <lb/>covered with a fine villous membrane. From <lb/>the larger ſize of the ſinuſes
          at the back and <lb/>upper part of the womb, I judged the <hi rend="italic">pla-
            <lb/>centa</hi> to have been formerly applied there. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
