<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Mackenzie: The History of a compleat Luxation of the Thigh</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>James Mackenzie</persName>
            </author>
            <title>ART. XXI. The History of a compleat Luxation of the Thigh, in a Letter to Dr.
              JOHN RUTHERFOORD, President of the Royal College of Physicians, and Professor of
              Medicine in the University of Edinburgh; by JAMES MACKENZIE, M.D. late Physician at Worceſter*.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Essays and observations, physical and literary. Read before a society in
              Edinburgh, and published by them. </title>
            <author>Philosophical Society of Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: printed by G. Hamilton and J. Balfour, Printers to the
                  University</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1756</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">2</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">317-323</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107037544</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T136785</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ2_v2_0317">
    <body>
      <pb n="317"/>
      <head rend="sc align-center">
        <lb/>Art. XXI. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>The Hiſtory of a compleat Luxation of the <lb/>Thigh, in a Letter to Dr. <hi rend="sc"
          >John Ruther- <lb/>foord</hi>, Preſident of the Royal College of <lb/>Phyſicians, and
        Profeſſor of Medicine in the <lb/>Univerſity of <hi rend="roman">Edinburgh</hi>; by <hi
          rend="sc">James Mac- <lb/>kenzie</hi>, M. D. late Phyſician at <hi rend="roman">Wor-
          <lb/>ceſter</hi>
        <note place="bottom" n="*" rend="size(0.7) roman">
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>* <date>March 6. 1755. </date>
          </p>
        </note>. </head>
      <salute rend="italic indent space">
        <lb/>SIR, </salute>
      <dateline rend="align-right"><hi rend="italic">Feb.</hi> 10. 1755. </dateline>
      <div>
        <p>
          <lb/>
          <q rend="diple quotes"><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE account which I gave you of a
            <lb/>compleat luxation of the thigh re- <lb/>duced at the <hi rend="italic"
              >Worceſter</hi> Infirmary, I now <lb/>ſend in writing, agreeably to your requeſt.
            <lb/>I ſend you alſo Doctor <hi rend="italic">Wall</hi>'s Letter vouch- <lb/>ing this
            diſlocation; and Mr. <hi rend="italic">Jefferys</hi>'s <lb/>narrative of the ſame caſe.
            If you think <lb/>any further proof neceſſary, there are ſtill <lb/>two Phyſicians and
            two Surgeons more, <lb/>alive and well, who were preſent at the <lb/>reduction, and will
            bear witneſs (if requi- <lb/>red) to the truth of this accident, as well <lb/>as the two
            Gentlemen above named, and <lb/>myſelf, who am, &amp;c. </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="318"/>
      <div>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">W</hi><hi rend="sc">Illiam Jones</hi>, a tall, robuſt, heal-
          <lb/>thy Butcher, fifty ſix years old, was <lb/>carried to the <hi rend="italic"
            >Worceſter</hi> Infirmary on the <lb/>ſeventeenth of <hi rend="italic">Auguſt</hi> 1747,
          lame, and in <lb/>grievous pain. His account of himſelf was, <lb/>That he happened
          unfortunately, ſome hours <lb/>before, to ride an unruly horſe, which ran <lb/>away with
          him; and that, making an ef- <lb/>fort to check him, juſt as he was galloping <lb/>over a
          ſtone bridge, the animal reared himſelf <lb/>upon his hinder feet; and immediately fell
          <lb/>backward on his rider. The man was ſtun- <lb/>ned with the fall; but the horſe
          quickly re- <lb/>covered himſelf, and went off full ſpeed, <lb/>dragging poor <hi
            rend="italic">Jones</hi> after him, by his leg <lb/>which was engaged in the ſtirrup.
          The <lb/>horſe was ſoon providentially ſtopped, and <lb/>the man ſet at liberty, but
          unable to move <lb/>his thigh, which he believed was broken. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> Surgeon in waiting, (for four Phyſi- <lb/>cians and three
          Surgeons gave their atten- <lb/>dance in rotation, namely, Doctors <hi rend="italic"
            >Attwood</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="italic">Mackenzie</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Cameron</hi>,
          and <hi rend="italic">Wall</hi>; and Meſſ. <lb/><hi rend="italic">Edwards</hi>, <hi
            rend="italic">Ruſſel</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Jefferys</hi>) having tho- <lb/>roughly
          examined the ſituation and figure of <pb n="319"/>
          <lb/>the parts diſabled and in pain, came to one <lb/>of the Phyſicians, and told him,
          that the <lb/>poor man's thigh was diſlocated; that the <lb/>head of the bone was ſtruck
          quite out of <lb/>the <hi rend="italic">acetabulum</hi>, and lay fairly in the groin.
          <lb/>The Phyſician having, in his younger days, <lb/>attended <hi rend="italic"
            >Boerhaave</hi> (who, ſurely, underſtood <lb/>phyſic and ſurgery as well as any man ever
          <lb/>did), and knowing that, from the prodigious <lb/>ſtrength of the ligaments, and depth
          of the <lb/>ſocket in that articulation, this learned Profeſ- <lb/>ſor was of opinion,
          that the thigh-bone was <lb/>never diſlocated by external violence, but fre- <lb/>quently
          broken near the head: which was the <lb/>true reaſon why ſuch accidents were ſeldom,
          <lb/>or never, cured: the Phyſician, I ſay, perſua- <lb/>ded, that his preceptor was in
          the right, <lb/>obſerved to the Surgeon, that there muſt be <lb/>a miſtake ſomewhere, and
          that there was no <lb/>inſtance on record, which could be depend- <lb/>ed upon, of ſuch a
          luxation as he deſcribed: <lb/>to which the Surgeon replied, <q rend="diple quotes">Sir,
            if you <lb/>will not believe me, you will believe your <lb/>own eyes and fingers
            preſently. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> novelty of the caſe brought all the <lb/>Phyſicians and
          Surgeons to the Infirmary. <lb/>A Skeleton was fetched, and great care ta- <pb n="320"/>
          <lb/>ken, by a ſtrict inquiry into circumſtances, <lb/>to fatisfy all preſent, that the
          bone was not <lb/>broken, but really and fairly diſlocated. <lb/>There is no reaſoning
          againſt facts: the <lb/>toes and knee were turned outwards, the <lb/>diſabled limb was
          longer than the ſound, <lb/>the hip-joint utterly inflexible, and the round <lb/>large
          head of the bone lay obvious to the <lb/>ſight and touch in the groin. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">The</hi> next inquiry was, how this diſloca- <lb/>tion ſhould be
          reduced. All were called to <lb/>conſultation; not one of the Phyſicians or <lb/>Surgeons
          had ever ſeen the caſe before. <lb/>Some of the principal books of modern ſur- <lb/>gery
          were looked into; but one and all de- <lb/>ſcribed the reduction, and recommended
          <lb/>extenſion in ſuch a general, languid, hear- <lb/>ſay, manner, that it was plain they
          were as <lb/>unpractiſed in the caſe, as the Gentlemen <lb/>preſent: nor was any better
          ſucceſs to be <lb/>expected from <hi rend="italic">Galen</hi>'s <note place="bottom" n="*"
            rend="size(0.6)">
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>* Vid. Gal. in librum Hipp. de artic. commentarior. <lb/>lib. 4. aph. 42. </p>
            <p rend="indent">
              <lb/>And indeed the antients ſeem to have been acquainted <lb/>with luxations of the
              hip-joint only in children, or diſtem- <lb/>pered bodies; unleſs we ſhall except <hi
                rend="italic">Paulus Ægineta</hi>, <pb n="321" type="footnote"/>
              <lb/>whoſe various methods of extenſion, in this caſe, whether <lb/>real or ſuppoſed,
              ſome of the moderns have copied, and <lb/>ſome have altered. </p>
          </note> method of reducing <pb n="321"/>
          <lb/>a luxation of this joint by hanging the pa- <lb/>tient to a ſtrong beam by the heels
          with his <lb/>head near the ground. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">After</hi> mature deliberation, it was agreed, <lb/>that, in caſe the
          uſual extenſion did not ſuc- <lb/>ceed, the <hi rend="italic">vis percuſſionis</hi> (which
          is well known <lb/>to increaſe the force to a ſurpriſing degree <lb/>by accelerating the
          motion) ſhould next be <lb/>tried. In order to both, therefore, we provi- <lb/>ded a large
          ſtrong table, of a proper length <lb/>and height, which we faſtened with ſcrews <lb/>to
          the floor, and covered with ſuch blankets <lb/>and bolſters as we wanted; a piece of
          ſtrong <lb/>cloth alſo was laid upon the blankets, un- <lb/>der the patient's back, of
          length ſufficient <lb/>to turn up between his thighs, and paſs over <lb/>his ſhoulders
          down to the floor, where both <lb/>ends were ſecurely fixed, with a view to <lb/>reſiſt or
          counteract the neceſſary extenſion. <lb/>We provided alſo two towels of a conve-
          <lb/>nient length and thickneſs; one of which, <lb/>at the middle, was tied with a tight,
          but <lb/>eaſy knot above the patient's ankle, and the <lb/>two ends twiſted together, were
          given to three <pb n="322"/>
          <lb/>ſtrong men to hold. The other towel was <lb/>in the ſame manner faſtened above the
          knee, <lb/>and the double end given to three more; <lb/>while the Surgeons ſtood ready,
          one with <lb/>his hand on the ball of the diſlocated bone <lb/>to direct it into the
          ſocket, one at the knee, <lb/>and another at the foot to turn them inwards. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When all things were ready, the exten- <lb/>ſion was begun, in the common method,
          <lb/>by the towel-men; but tho' they exerted <lb/>their utmoſt ſtrength, the head of the
          bone <lb/>was not moved in the leaſt, and their effort <lb/>ſerved only to increaſe the
          poor man's tor- <lb/>ture to an intolerable degree. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">Finding</hi> thus the extenſion of no ſigni- <lb/>ficancy; and the
          patient's courage reviving <lb/>after ſome reſpite; the <hi rend="italic">vis
            percuſſionis</hi> was <lb/><choice>
            <corr/>
            <sic>was </sic>
          </choice>carried into execution after the follow- <lb/>ing manner. The towel-men were
          directed <lb/>to ſlacken their towels to a certain point, to <lb/>ſtand with their feet
          firm, their arms ſtreight, <lb/>and their bodies bending a little forward; <lb/>and, upon
          a certain ſignal agreed on, were <lb/>ordered to pull with a vehement and quick <lb/>jerk,
          throwing themſelves back with all their <lb/>might. </p>
        <pb n="323"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="sc">After</hi> every thing was in good order, <lb/>and the aſſiſtants
          appriſed of the nature and <lb/>neceſſity of the operation which they were <lb/>about to
          perform; the ſignal agreed on was <lb/>at laſt given. The towel-men pulled in a
          <lb/>moment with a ſtrong and ſudden ſpring; <lb/>the Surgeons performed their parts
          dexte- <lb/>rouſly; and inſtantly there was a loud craſh <lb/>heard, which made one of the
          Phyſicians <lb/>call out, Alas! the table is broken. But <lb/>at that very moment the
          patient, with a <lb/>thundering voice, cried, It's in, it's in, it's <lb/>in. And ſo it
          really was; for we imme- <lb/>diately found the limb reſtored to its natural
          <lb/>poſition, length, and flexibility. The pa- <lb/>tient was put to bed; and, by a
          proper diet <lb/>and care, recovered his former health, and <lb/>could walk perfectly well
          in three weeks. <lb/>One of the Phyſicians often met him after- <lb/>wards on foot driving
          cattle, and always <lb/>aſked, How he did? To which his con- <lb/>ſtant anſwer was, Very
          well, thank God and <lb/>the Gentlemen. And he can now, upon oc- <lb/>caſion, walk twenty
          miles in a day, without <lb/>fatigue or pain, tho' the injured limb ſtill re- <lb/>mains
          near a quarter of an inch longer than <lb/>the other. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
