<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Monro: Of the Use of Mercury in Convulsive Disorders</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Donald Monro</persName>
            </author>
            <title>ART. XXX. Of the Use of Mercury in Convulsive Disorders, by Dr DONALD MONRO,
              Physician to St George's Hospital, London.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Essays and observations, physical and literary. Read before a society in
              Edinburgh, and published by them. </title>
            <author>Philosophical Society of Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>Edinburgh</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: printed for John Balfour</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1771</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">3</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">551-556</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW107166916</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T136786</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ2_v3_0551">
    <body>
      <pb n="551"/>
      <head rend="sc align-center">
        <lb/>Art. XXX. </head>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="3"> </space>
      <head rend="italic hanging">
        <lb/>Of the Uſe of Mercury in Convulſive Diſor- <lb/>ders, by Dr <hi rend="sc">Donald
          Monro</hi>, Phyſi- <lb/>cian to St George's Hoſpital, London. </head>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="3"> </space>
      <p>
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE convulſive diſorders called <hi rend="italic">opiſ-
          <lb/>thotanus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">tetanus</hi>, which come <lb/>after lying in the
        fields, or being expoſed <lb/>to alternate heat, cold, and moiſture, and <lb/>other ſuch
        cauſes, are very common in <lb/>the Weſt Indies, and other hot climates; <lb/>and are
        ſometimes, though but very rare- <lb/>ly, obſerved in Great Britain. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">They</hi> are mentioned by Hippocrates, <lb/>Celſus, and other antient
        authors; but <lb/>the beſt account we have of them is that <lb/>publiſhed by Dr Lionel
        Chalmers of <lb/>Charleſtown in South Carolina, in the <lb/>firſt volume of <hi
          rend="italic">Medical Obſervations and <pb n="552"/>
          <lb/>Inquiries, by a Society of Phyſicians in Lon- <lb/>don</hi>, where the Doctor, after
        giving a ve- <lb/>ry accurate hiſtory of the ſymptoms and <lb/>cauſes of theſe diſeaſes,
        obſerves, that <lb/>few recover in compariſon of the number <lb/>they attack; and that warm
        baths and <lb/>opiates are principally to be depended <lb/>upon for a cure; which agrees
        with the <lb/>practice uſed in the few caſes of the lock- <lb/>ed jaw, which have been
        ſucceſsfully <lb/>treated in this country. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Most</hi> late practitioners look upon <lb/>theſe diſorders as very
        fatal. The gen- <lb/>tleman, who was phyſician to the naval <lb/>hoſpital at Gibraltar
        during the late war, <lb/>told me, that he had had above forty peo- <lb/>ple under his care
        for the tetanus, attend- <lb/>ed with the locked jaw, who all died, ex- <lb/>cept one,
        notwithſtanding he had uſed e- <lb/>vacuations, baths, and fomentations, and <lb/>had given
        very freely of opiates, and all <lb/>other medicines that he had ever heard re-
        <lb/>commended in ſuch caſes. The diſor- <lb/>der in the one who recovered was occa-
        <lb/>ſioned by a hurt of a finger; and the <pb n="553"/>
        <lb/>amputation of that member on the firſt <lb/>appearance of the locked jaw proved the
        <lb/>cure. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As the remedies hitherto recommended <lb/>for the cure of theſe convulſive diſorders
        <lb/>have proved ſo ineffectual, the following <lb/>account of a ſucceſsful method of cure
        <lb/>by mercurial unctions, communicated to <lb/>me by a gentleman who was formerly a
        <lb/>practitioner in phyſic in the iſland of <lb/>Jamaica, and who has allowed me to
        <lb/>tranſmit it to your ſociety, cannot fail to <lb/>be acceptable. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">While</hi> this gentleman practiſed in Ja- <lb/>maica, he had a great
        number of caſes <lb/>of the tetanus, attended with the locked <lb/>jaw, under his care. At
        firſt, he uſed to <lb/>give very freely of opium, muſk, and o- <lb/>ther medicines of this
        claſs; to bleed, and <lb/>make other evacuations, while he uſed <lb/>baths, fomentations,
        embrocations, and <lb/>other external applications, but all <lb/>without the leaſt ſucceſs;
        and, as he had <lb/>loſt a great many patients without being <lb/>ſo lucky as to make one
        cure, he began <lb/>to believe that this diſorder always pro- <pb n="554"/>
        <lb/>ved fatal, and was not to be cured by <lb/>medicine, notwithſtanding what ſome
        <lb/>practitioners had alledged. However, <lb/>having received an unexpected hint con-
        <lb/>cerning the good effects of the mercurial <lb/>ointment in ſuch caſes, he reſolved to
        <lb/>try it; and ordered the firſt patient that <lb/>offered, to be put into a warm room,
        <lb/>and to be rubbed two or three times a- <lb/>day with the ointment, till ſuch time as
        <lb/>a ſalivation was raiſed, when he, with <lb/>pleaſure, obſerved, that as ſoon as the
        <lb/>mercury began to affect the mouth, the <lb/>convulſions of the muſcles of the jaws,
        <lb/>as well as all the other ſpaſms and con- <lb/>vulſions, ceaſed, and the patient was
        freed <lb/>of all his complaints. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">After</hi> this, he treated every caſe of <lb/>this kind which came under
        his care in <lb/>the ſame manner, and cured twelve, <lb/>which were all who applied to him
        for <lb/>advice ſo early in the diſorder, that there <lb/>was time to bring the mercury to
        the <lb/>mouth before the fatal period was ex- <lb/>pected. A few died in whom the diſeaſe
        <lb/>was ſo far advanced before he ſaw them, <pb n="555"/>
        <lb/>that there was not time to raiſe a ſa- <lb/>livation. None of the caſes which were
        <lb/>under this gentleman's care in the Weſt <lb/>Indies were the conſequences of wounds
        <lb/>or capital operations; nor has he had any <lb/>opportunity of trying it ſince in caſes
        of <lb/>the locked jaw, which ſometimes follow <lb/>capital operations, owing to his having
        <lb/>given over practice; but he thinks, that, <lb/>from the ſimilarity of the complaint,
        <lb/>there is no doubt but that the mercurial <lb/>frictions would be equally efficacious in
        <lb/>ſuch caſes, as when the diſorder comes <lb/>from catching cold, or other ſuch cauſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">He</hi> thinks, that the beſt method of <lb/>raiſing a ſalivation in
        theſe diſorders is <lb/>to put the patient into a room made as <lb/>hot, by means of a fire,
        and being ſur- <lb/>rounded with blankets as the patient can <lb/>bear; and to rub in a
        mercurial ointment, <lb/>made with equal parts of quickſilver and <lb/>hogs-lard, as freely
        and as frequently as <lb/>can be done with ſafety. That the ſoon- <lb/>er the cure is begun
        after the firſt ap- <lb/>pearance of the locked jaw, the better. <lb/>And that, in caſes far
        advanced, the mer- <pb n="556"/>
        <lb/>cury muſt be thrown in as faſt as poſſi- <lb/>ble. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">This</hi> gentleman uſed no preparation <lb/>before he begun the uſe of
        the ointment, <lb/>but ſet his patients to work as ſoon as <lb/>poſſible. He now and then
        gave ſtrong <lb/>opiates to procure reſt, both before and <lb/>after the ſpitting came on;
        but he ob- <lb/>ſerves, that the quantity of opium, and <lb/>the frequency of the repetition
        of its <lb/>doſe, muſt be determined by the ſtate of <lb/>the patient, and the ſymptoms
        which <lb/>occur. Since his return to England, he <lb/>has had one caſe of the ſame kind
        under <lb/>his care, which was cured by the method <lb/>here recommended. </p>
      <dateline rend="hanging space size(0.7)">
        <lb/>Jermyn-ſtreet, London, Jan. 29. <lb/>1766. </dateline>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
