<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Butter: A Treatise on the Kinkcough</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>William Butter</persName>
            </author>
            <title>VIII. A Treatise on the Kinkcough, with an Appendix, containing an account of
              Hemlock, and its Preparations. By William Butter, M. D. Fellow of the Royal College of
              Physicians Edinburgh. 8vo, London. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society of Physicians in
              Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Murray, No. 32, Fleet-Street; Kincaid and Creech,
                  and W. Drummond, Edinburgh; and T. Ewing, Capel-Street, Dublin.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1773</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">1</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">387-397</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108871595</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T153519</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v1_0387">
    <body>
      <pb n="387"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>VIII. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>A Treatiſe on the Kinkcough, with an Appendix, <lb/>containing an account of Hemlock,
        and its Pre- <lb/>parations. By <hi rend="roman">William Butter, M. D.</hi> Fellow <lb/>of
        the Royal College of Phyſicians <hi rend="roman">Edinburgh</hi>. <lb/>8vo, <hi rend="roman"
          >London</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE obſervations on kinkcough, with which <lb/>we are here
        preſented, are divided into <lb/>ſeven chapters. In the firſt of theſe, the author <lb/>ſets
        out with enumerating the ſynonimes for this <lb/>diſeaſe which have been employed by
        different <lb/>authors. He then defines it, A quick and nu- <lb/>merous ſucceſſion of
        violent ſhort coughs, follow- <lb/>ed by a long, ſtrait, and generally ſhrill inſpira-
        <lb/>tion, which coughs and inſpiration are repeated <pb n="388"/>
        <lb/>without intermiſſion, for many ſeconds, or even <lb/>ſome minutes, and often terminate
        in vomiting of <lb/>phlegm. To this definition he ſubjoins a full de- <lb/>ſcription of the
        diſeaſe; and concludes the chapter <lb/>with ſome remarks upon the prognoſtics. Ac-
        <lb/>cording to Dr Butter, a fatal termination of kink- <lb/>cough is owing, either to the
        length of the diſeaſe, <lb/>or the violence of the fits. In infants, he ob- <lb/>ſerves, it
        terminates fatally, from producing <lb/>convulſions, ſuffocation, apoplexy, inflammation
        <lb/>and ſuppuration of the brain, ruptures, and in- <lb/>curvation of the ſpine. In
        pregnant women, it has <lb/>often produced abortion; and, in adults, it occa- <lb/>ſions
        inflammation of the lungs, and its conſe- <lb/>quences, more frequently than in children.
        From <lb/>long continued kinkcough, patients will become <lb/>aſthmatic, conſumptive,
        rickety, or ſcrophulous. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The author conſiders a moiſt ſkin, warm limbs, <lb/>open belly, plentiful
        expectoration, and free vo- <lb/>miting, as good ſymptoms. On the contrary, he <lb/>draws an
        unfavourable prognoſis, when oppoſite <lb/>circumſtances take place. Frequent haemorrha-
        <lb/>gies, he obſerves, protract the diſeaſe, and a pul- <lb/>monary one is apt to induce
        conſumption. In <lb/>patients liable to epilepſy, or other diſorders of <lb/>the brain; in
        ſuch as have weak lungs, or who <pb n="389"/>
        <lb/>have been reduced by a preceeding diſeaſe; the <lb/>kinkcough is often productive of
        the worſt conſe- <lb/>quences. When joined with worms, dyſentery, <lb/>meaſles, ſmall-pox,
        or peripneumonic ſymptoms, it <lb/>is always dangerous. Our author concludes this chap-
        <lb/>ter with obſerving, that theſe prognoſtics, according <lb/>to the common method of
        cure, are uniformly <lb/>juſt; but that a more ſucceſsful treatment will af- <lb/>ford
        exceptions as to the danger. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the ſecond chapter, Dr Butter proceeds to <lb/>conſider the nature of kinkcough. It
        is, our au- <lb/>thor obſerves, an epidemic contagious diſeaſe, of- <lb/>ten complicated
        with other diſorders, forming va- <lb/>rieties worthy of the moſt attentive conſideration.
        <lb/>It is not eſſentially attended with fever; as in the <lb/>intervals the patient is
        entirely free from any <lb/>complaint. It commonly laſts for ſome months, <lb/>returning in
        fits for the moſt part at equal diſtan- <lb/>ces. Much bleeding and purging are hurtful in
        <lb/>it. The moſt famed remedies for it, are gentle <lb/>vomits, ſtomachic laxative
        paregorics, and ſtimu- <lb/>lating antiſpaſmodics. It has often been carried <lb/>off by a
        fright. And the diſſections of thoſe dy- <lb/>ing early in it have diſcovered nothing
        praeter- <lb/>natural. From all theſe circumſtances, he con- <lb/>cludes, that it is a
        nervous ſpaſmodic diſeaſe. </p>
      <pb n="390"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He farther remarks, that an uncommon ſecre- <lb/>tion of mucus takes place in this
        diſeaſe, a free <lb/>diſcharge of which mitigates the ſymptoms: And <lb/>that, in proportion
        as the quantity of ſlime dimi- <lb/>niſhes, the fits become more mild and leſs fre-
        <lb/>quent. From this, he concludes, that a morbid <lb/>irritability of the mucous glands is
        the primary <lb/>affection, and that the ſpaſms are only ſeconda- <lb/>ry. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>An inquiry concerning the ſeat of the kink- <lb/>cough is the ſubject of the third
        chapter. Va- <lb/>rious have been the opinions entertained with re- <lb/>gard to it. Some
        have ſuppoſed it to be in the <lb/>lungs, ſome in the ſtomach, ſome in both, while
        <lb/>others have maintained that it is in the head of <lb/>the wind-pipe or gullet. Dr
        Butter deſerts all <lb/>theſe opinions, and denies that any one of the <lb/>places above
        mentioned is primarily affected. He <lb/>alledges, that ſome part of the inteſtinal canal is
        <lb/>the principal ſeat of the diſeaſe. To confirm this <lb/>opinion, he offers arguments
        drawn from four <lb/>ſources: 1. From the nature of thoſe habits <lb/>moſt ſubject to
        kinkcough. It chiefly attacks <lb/>childrem; and, in them, it is well known that the
        <lb/>inteſtinal canal is more irritable, and conſequent- <lb/>ly more eaſily affected, than
        any other part of their <pb n="391"/>
        <lb/>bodies. 2. From the nature and cure of kink- <lb/>cough, it is obſervable, that thoſe
        children paſs <lb/>moſt eaſily through this diſeaſe, who have an o- <lb/>pen belly; that
        vomits are moſt ſerviceable when <lb/>they promote a gentle looſeneſs at the ſame time;
        <lb/>and that patients labouring under kinkcough bear <lb/>the action of vomits much better
        than they do of <lb/>purgatives. All theſe circumſtances, in the opi- <lb/>nion of our
        author, ſeem to point out the inte- <lb/>ſtines as the ſeat of the diſorder. 3. From the
        <lb/>diſeaſes conſequent upon kinkcough. The chief <lb/>of theſe are, the king's evil and
        rickets; both of <lb/>which, in a particular manner, derive their origin <lb/>from an
        affection of the alimentary canal. <lb/>4. From the periodical returns of the paroxyſms.
        <lb/>Here our author runs a parallel between kink- <lb/>cough and intermittent fever. He
        thinks it the <lb/>moſt probable opinion, that the latter of theſe <lb/>diſeaſes has its
        proximate cauſe in the guts; and <lb/>he is even inclined to ſuppoſe, that all intermit-
        <lb/>tent diſtempers depend upon a primary affection <lb/>of the inteſtinal canal. In
        ſupport of this doctrine, <lb/>he adds the hiſtory of three intermittent diſeaſes,
        <lb/>which were principally cured by evacuations from <lb/>the inteſtines. </p>
      <pb n="392"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The author concludes this chapter with addu- <lb/>cing ſome objections againſt the
        ſuppoſition that <lb/>kinkcough is ſeated either in the ſtomach or lungs. <lb/>He thinks it
        improbable that it is ſeated in the <lb/>lungs, as he alledges that, in this diſeaſe,
        pectorals <lb/>do more harm than good: That a pulmonary <lb/>cough, if not dangerous,
        terminates ſooner than <lb/>kinkcough; and that the rickets and ſcrophula <lb/>are never
        produced by a pulmonary cough. He <lb/>thinks it improbable that it is ſeated in the ſto-
        <lb/>mach, becauſe it is not attended with violent pain, <lb/>ſickneſs, faintiſhneſs, and
        ſuch like ſymptoms; <lb/>and becauſe intermittent diſorders in general can <lb/>never be
        ſuſpected to have their ſeat in the ſto- <lb/>mach, ſince vomits render more diſtinct inter-
        <lb/>miſſions which were formerly obſcure. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having endeavoured to aſcertain the ſeat of <lb/>kinkcough, Dr Butter next endeavours
        to inve- <lb/>ſtigate its cauſes. As the chief prediſpoſing cauſes, <lb/>he points out the
        conſtitutional irritability of chil- <lb/>dren; hereditary prediſpoſition to ſpaſmodic diſ-
        <lb/>orders; the actual exiſtence of ſuch diſorders; a <lb/>redundancy of vitiated humours
        in the ſtomach <lb/>and guts; worms; dentition; cold; and acute diſ- <lb/>eaſes in general.
        The occaſional cauſe he ſup- <lb/>poſes to conſiſt entirely in infectious miaſmata, <pb
          n="393"/>
        <lb/>capable of generating the diſeaſe. Theſe miaſ- <lb/>mata, he thinks, are the growth of
        Europe, in the <lb/>ſame manner as thoſe of the plague, meaſles, and <lb/>ſmall-pox, are of
        warmer climates. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr Butter next preſents us with the hiſtory of <lb/>twenty caſes of kinkcough, in which
        he employ- <lb/>ed hemlock, in different forms, with great ſucceſs. <lb/>Building upon this
        practice, he proceeds, in the <lb/>ſixth chapter, to lay down the cure of kinkcough,
        <lb/>both ſimple and complicated. In the ſimple kink- <lb/>cough, he tells us, there is but
        one indication, <lb/>and that is, to adminiſter hemlock. He directs <lb/>that is ſhould be
        diffuſed in a watery vehicle, be- <lb/>gun in ſmall doſes, and gradually increaſed. For
        <lb/>a child under ſix months old, he directs half a <lb/>grain to be conſumed in a day; for
        one from ſix <lb/>months to two years old, one grain; afterwards <lb/>allowing half a grain
        for every year of the pati- <lb/>ent's age, till he be twenty: Beyond that pe- <lb/>riod, he
        directs that ten grains be given for the <lb/>firſt day's conſumption, gradually increaſing
        the <lb/>doſe according to its effect. If the patient have <lb/>not two ſtools a-day, he
        adviſes that magneſia or <lb/>polychreſt ſalt be added to the hemlock-mixture. <lb/>In the
        cure of kinkcough complicated with worms, <lb/>dyſentery, dentition, ague, ſmall-pox, and
        meaſles, <pb n="394"/>
        <lb/>he recommends, with the employment of hem- <lb/>lock, the exhibition of ſuch medicines
        as are beſt <lb/>adapted to the nature of each particular diſeaſe. <lb/>When kinkcough is
        complicated with pregnancy, <lb/>the ſimple method of cure may, he tells us, be
        <lb/>followed out with ſucceſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This treatiſe on kinkcough is concluded with <lb/>ſome general corollaries drawn from
        the preceed- <lb/>ing obſervations. He alledges, that hemlock is <lb/>ſeldom
        contra-indicated by any peculiarity of <lb/>temperament; that it is a ſafe remedy for kink-
        <lb/>cough, both in the laſt months of pregnancy, and <lb/>firſt months of infancy; that it
        is a certain anti- <lb/>ſpaſmodic; that it is a good medicine in dentition <lb/>and worms;
        that it ſometimes removes fever, <lb/>ſtops immoderate excretions, and promotes ſweat;
        <lb/>that it frequently keeps the belly open, and often <lb/>purges; that ſometimes it
        affects no ſecretion or <lb/>excretion; that it immediately procures better <lb/>nights in
        kinkcough, abates vomiting, and dimi- <lb/>niſhes phlegm; and that, in the ſpace of a week,
        <lb/>it generally removes the kink and other concomi- <lb/>tant ſymptoms, except a ſlight
        cough. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To theſe obſervations on kinkcough, the author <lb/>ſubjoins an appendix concerning
        hemlock and its <lb/>preparations. He here firſt preſents us with the <pb n="395"/>
        <lb/>ſynonimes and botanical deſcription of the plant; <lb/>and then makes ſome remarks on
        its preparati- <lb/>ons, which he divides into internal and external. <lb/>Of the firſt kind
        are, the powder, the extract, <lb/>the pills, and the mixture; and, of the laſt, <lb/>the
        plaſter, the ointment, the poultice, and the <lb/>fomentation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The powder of Hemlock, Dr Butter prepares <lb/>from the leaves, foot-ſtalks, and tender
        parts of <lb/>the ſtem, gathered about the time the flowers be- <lb/>gin to open. Theſe he
        directs to be ſpread on a <lb/>hearth, before a good fire, with a deep fender <lb/>behind,
        to haſten the proceſs of drying. When <lb/>they are ſufficiently friable, they muſt be
        reduced <lb/>to a powder, and preſerved in phials well ſtopped. <lb/>The powder, in this
        ſituation, will retain its effi- <lb/>cacy for ſeveral months. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In order to prepare the extract, the plant, he <lb/>tells us, at the ſame age at which
        it is cut for the <lb/>powder, muſt be gathered over night, that all the <lb/>other parts of
        the proceſs may be finiſhed on the <lb/>following day. After being cut, bruiſed, and
        <lb/>put into hair bags, the expreſſion muſt be con- <lb/>tinued till the drops fall very
        ſlowly. The whole <lb/>of the juice, without depuration, muſt then be <lb/>put into a broad
        glazed platter, and placed over <pb n="396"/>
        <lb/>a charcoal-fire, in a fire-pan. Before it becomes <lb/>very hot, it runs into clots.
        You are then to ſtir <lb/>it frequently with a hemlock ſtalk, keeping up a <lb/>ſufficient
        degree of heat to make the clots move <lb/>about, without cauſing any ebulition. Proceed
        <lb/>in this manner, till the inteſtine motion ceaſes, <lb/>and no effort is made by the
        contiguous maſs to <lb/>fill up any vacuities which the ſtirring may occa- <lb/>ſion in the
        bottom of the platter. You will <lb/>then, ſays he, have an extract of a proper conſi-
        <lb/>ſtence. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For making the pills, he adviſes, that to any <lb/>quantity of the extract, one fifth
        of the powder <lb/>ſhould be added. The maſs thus formed, is to <lb/>be put up in ſtone
        pots, capable of containing a <lb/>pound weight; and in this manner, we are told, <lb/>it
        will keep perfectly well for the ſpace of two <lb/>years. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The hemlock mixture is an extemporaneous <lb/>preſcription, and is made by diſſolving
        from eight <lb/>to twenty, or more grains, of the maſs prepared <lb/>for pills, in eight
        ounces of ſpring water, and ad- <lb/>ding to it half an ounce of proof-ſpirit, and as
        <lb/>much white ſugar. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For the hemlock-plaſter, he gives the follow- <lb/>ing receipt. Take of gum ammoniac
        eight oun- <pb n="397"/>
        <lb/>ces, common vinegar an Engliſh pint; rub them <lb/>together in a marble mortar, till
        the gum be diſ- <lb/>ſolved; then incorporate the ſtrained ſolution with <lb/>four ounces of
        the maſs of hemlock-pills; and af- <lb/>terwards evaporate the whole over a very gentle
        <lb/>heat, to the conſiſtence of a plaſter. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Equal quantities of the maſs of hemlock-pills <lb/>and honey, mixed together without
        heat, conſti- <lb/>tute his ointment. And his poultice is made, by <lb/>mixing either the
        powder of hemlock, or the <lb/>bruiſed leaves, with oat-meal, and a ſmall pro- <lb/>portion
        of honey, adding as much ſpring-water <lb/>as may be ſufficient to bring the other
        ingredients <lb/>to a proper conſiſtence. The hemlock-fomenta- <lb/>tion he directs to be
        prepared, by boiling eight <lb/>ounces of the freſh herb, well bruiſed, in an Eng- <lb/>liſh
        gallon of water, ſtraining the liquor when cold, <lb/>and afterwards heating it for uſe.
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
