<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: Opusculum de Lacte</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>V. Jacobi Bartholomaei Beccarii Opusculum de Lacte. Vid. De Bononiensi
              Scientiarum et Artium Instituto atque Academia Commentarii. Tomi Quinti Pars prima,
              4to, Bonon. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society of Physicians in
              Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Murray, No. 32, Fleet-Street; Kincaid and Creech,
                  and W. Drummond, Edinburgh; and T. Ewing, Capel-Street, Dublin.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1773</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">1</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">161-165</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108871595</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T153519</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v1_0161">
    <body>
      <pb n="161"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>V. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">Jacobi Bartholomaei Beccarii</hi> Opuſculum de <lb/>Lacte. Vid. De
        Bononienſi Scientiarum et Ar- <lb/>tium Inſtituto atque Academia Commentarii. <lb/><hi
          rend="roman">Tomi Quinti Pars prima, 4to, Bonon.</hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">B</hi>Eccarius had formerly publiſhed ſeveral ex- <lb/>periments on
        corns and broths of different <lb/>kinds, which received very general approbation. <lb/>His
        induſtrious reſearches have not ſtopped there. <lb/>In the paper now before us, we are
        preſented with <lb/>the reſult of many experiments which he has <lb/>made on milk. Without
        repeating the experiments <lb/>which had been made by Boerhaave and Macquer <lb/>on this
        ſubject, he takes it up where they had left <lb/>it. Boerhaave, from his experiments, had
        con- <lb/>cluded, that cows milk which was the ſubject up- <pb n="162"/>
        <lb/>on which he chiefly operated, neither contained <lb/>an acid nor an alkali; that it was
        hardly in any de- <lb/>gree ſaline; and that it yielded no ſpirit upon di- <lb/>ſtillation.
        And Macquer was of opinion that it <lb/>contained no ſalt, which was not to be referred
        <lb/>to the tribe of acids, and yielded nothing which <lb/>gave even the ſlighteſt
        indication of volatile al- <lb/>kali. The experiments of our author, however, <lb/>led him
        to form very different concluſions. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>His firſt experiments were made with that fat- <lb/>ty, ſweet-taſted reſiduum, which is
        obtained on the <lb/>ſimple diſtillation of milk. With this he filled a <lb/>retort to about
        two thirds, and ſubjected it to a <lb/>heat, at firſt gentle, but afterwards encreaſed to
        <lb/>a conſiderable degree. In the beginning, a wa- <lb/>tery, limpid, taſteleſs liquor
        aroſe; after this, it <lb/>appeared of a ſtraw colour, and was ſomewhat a- <lb/>cid to the
        taſte; it then became more and more <lb/>of a deep colour, and, at the ſame time, more acid;
        <lb/>towards the end, it became blackiſh and empyreu- <lb/>matic; and, at laſt, upon the
        heat being greatly <lb/>encreaſed, white vapours aroſe and flew about <lb/>the receiver,
        till ſome of them were condenſed <lb/>into a liquid, and others adhered in a ſolid ſtate to
        <lb/>the ſides of the veſſel, in the form of diſtinct <lb/>and beautiful ramifications; in
        the mean time, a <pb n="163"/>
        <lb/>thick foetid oil began to cover the top of the li- <lb/>quor, which put an end to the
        proceſs. In the <lb/>retort, there remained a thick black coloured ſub- <lb/>ſtance. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The next experiments made by the author were <lb/>with the ſerum of the milk. By a very
        gentle <lb/>heat, he drew off all the watery part of the ſerum, <lb/>ſo as to leave nothing
        but what is commonly cal- <lb/>led the ſugar of milk. This he ſubjected to the <lb/>ſame
        proceſs as the maſs laſt mentioned, and with <lb/>preciſely the ſame effect. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From theſe experiments, Beccarius was led to <lb/>imagine, that both the milk, taken
        altogether, and <lb/>the ſerum, when ſeparated from it, contain no in- <lb/>conſiderable
        proportion of a volatile alkaline ſalt. <lb/>To ſatisfy himſelf with regard to this, he next
        en- <lb/>deavoured to inveſtigate the nature of thoſe pro- <lb/>ducts which he had obtained.
        From the common <lb/>teſts by which acids and alkalines are detected, he <lb/>found that the
        fluid which he had obtained was <lb/>an acid. Whilſt the more ſolid ſublimate which
        <lb/>came over at laſt, was evidently of an alkaline <lb/>nature. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having, from theſe experiments, diſcovered that <lb/>both milk and its ſerum contain a
        volatile alkali; <lb/>he obſerves, that an alkali might naturally be ſup- <pb n="164"/>
        <lb/>poſed to be preſent alſo in cheeſe. But, as Mr <lb/>Macquer had been of a different
        opinion, he re- <lb/>ſolved to determine this alſo by experiment. For <lb/>this purpoſe he
        employed a glue, well known to <lb/>joiners, which is prepared from cheeſe by boiling
        <lb/>and preſſure. He was led to prefer this glue to the <lb/>cheeſe itſelf, as he had
        formerly found, that even <lb/>the glue from corn was of an animal and alkaline <lb/>nature.
        Having put ſome of this glue into a retort, <lb/>he expoſed it to a heat at firſt gentle,
        but after- <lb/>wards more conſiderable. There aroſe, at firſt, <lb/>a limpid fluid, then a
        turbid milky one of a uri- <lb/>nous ſmell. After this, there came over a vapour, <lb/>ſome
        of which covered the ſides of the receiver, <lb/>and ſome was converted into an acrid
        liquor, very <lb/>ſimilar to that which is obtained from animal ſub- <lb/>ſtances. Along
        with all theſe products, ſome oil <lb/>came over, which became thicker and blacker as
        <lb/>the diſtillation advanced. The maſs remaining <lb/>in the retort was very dry and much
        burnt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Our author concludes this paper, by pointing <lb/>it out as a ſubject of enquiry,
        whether theſe al- <lb/>kaline ſalts be always preſent in the milk in a de- <lb/>termined
        proportion? or, whether the quantity <lb/>produced may be varied by the means uſed for <pb
          n="165"/>
        <lb/>obtaining them? This queſtion, from the expe- <lb/>riments now before us, he admits,
        that he is un- <lb/>able to determine. But, he obſerves, that, from <lb/>the experiments
        which he has made on wheat, it <lb/>appeared that the proportion of alkaline ſalt, con-
        <lb/>tained in equal quantities of the ſame matter, ne- <lb/>ver varied. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
