<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: Mémoire sur des Insectes sur lesquelles on trouve des
          Plantes</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>XI. Mémoire sur des Insectes sur lesquelles on trouve des Plantes, par M.
              Fougeroux de Bondaroy. Vid. Histoire de l'Académie Royale des Sciences, Année 1769.
              4to, Paris. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society of Physicians in
              Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London : printed for J. Murray, No. 32, Fleet-Street; Kincaid and Creech,
                  and W. Drummond, Edinburgh; and T. Ewing, Capel-Street, Dublin.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1773</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">1</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">405-409</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108871595</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T153519</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v1_0405">
    <body>
      <pb n="405"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>XI. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Mémoire ſur des Inſectes ſur leſquelles on trouve des <lb/>Plantes, par <hi
          rend="roman">M. Fougeroux de Bondaroy</hi>. <lb/>Vid. Hiſtoire de l'Académie Royale des
        Sciences, <lb/>Année <hi rend="roman">1769</hi>. <hi rend="roman">4to, Paris</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>T has often been obſerved, that ſome plants <lb/>grow upon
        others, and derive their nou- <lb/>riſhment from them: But it is by no means ſo ge-
        <lb/>nerally known, that vegetables can take root and <lb/>flouriſh on living animals. Mr
        Fougeroux has <lb/>had an opportunity of obſerving ſome inſtances <lb/>of this extraordinary
        fact. Theſe obſervations, <lb/>together with what other naturaliſts have ſaid up- <lb/>on
        the ſubject, fourniſh matter for the memoir <lb/>now before us. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The plants, of which an account is here given <lb/>by Mr Fougeroux, are perfectly the
        reverſe of the <lb/>worm-plant of China, deſcribed by Mr <unclear>R</unclear>eaumeur <lb/>in
        the year 1726. For, in that caſe, a worm fixes <lb/>its ſnout into the extremity of the
        plant, and de- <lb/>rives nouriſhment from it. But the plants, of <pb n="406"/>
        <lb/>which an account is here given, derive their nou- <lb/>riſhment from the animals. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In this memoir, Mr Fougeroux propoſes to <lb/>point out different inſects upon which
        plants do <lb/>grow; and to propoſe what ſeems to him the moſt <lb/>probable method of
        accounting for this conjunc- <lb/>tion. The greateſt part of the animal plants, <lb/>which
        he has ſeen, grow, he tells us, on the chry- <lb/>ſalis of a fpecies of cicada. The plant
        growing <lb/>on these inſects has got the generic name of Cla- <lb/>varia, becauſe its
        ſtalks and branches, when it has <lb/>any, are terminated by tubercles, which give it
        <lb/>the appearance of a little club. The root of this <lb/>plant, in general, covers the
        body of the inſect, <lb/>and ſometimes is even extended over its head. <lb/>When theſe
        productions have for ſome time been <lb/>preſerved in ſpirits, the plant and animal may be
        <lb/>ſeparated from each other without hurting either. <lb/>Small grooves, formed by the
        rings of the animal, <lb/>may be obſerved running croſs the roots of the <lb/>plant: But no
        veſtige can be found of the root's <lb/>having any where penetrated the body of the in-
        <lb/>ſect. Theſe plants produce fibres differing in <lb/>length and number. The fibres are
        terminated <lb/>by tubercles, which, before the plant arrives at <lb/>maturity, are ſolid;
        but, after that period, they <pb n="407"/>
        <lb/>are found punctured, probably by worms which <lb/>have ſuffered a metamorphoſis upon
        eſcaping from <lb/>them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>According to Mr Fougeroux, plants grow, not <lb/>only on the chryſalis of the cicada,
        but upon the <lb/>cicada itſelf. He ſaw one of this kind upon a ci- <lb/>cada brought from
        Cayenne. The plant, in this <lb/>caſe, differed from the clavaria already mention- <lb/>ed.
        It was a ſpecies of fucus, compoſed of long, <lb/>white, ſilky fibres, covering the body of
        the inſect, <lb/>and extending, from ſeven to eight lines, above <lb/>and below its belly. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The author has found the clavaria formerly de- <lb/>ſcribed growing upon worms. He has
        found it <lb/>chiefly upon thoſe worms which, ſuffering a me- <lb/>tamorphoſis, become
        afterwards a ſmall ſpecies of <lb/>May-bug. This chryſalis, he obſerves, is very
        <lb/>different from that of the cicada, and, even in its <lb/>worm-ſtate, may eaſily be
        diſtinguiſhed from it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After deſcribing theſe different ſpecies of ani- <lb/>mal plants, the author next
        proceeds to offer his <lb/>opinion upon this ſubject. He firſt conſiders <lb/>what had been
        ſaid by Dr Watſon, in the philo- <lb/>ſophical tranſactions, concerning the vegetating fly
        <lb/>of the Caribbee iſlands. Dr Watſon's account of <pb n="408"/>
        <lb/>theſe flies is, that they bury themſelves about the <lb/>month of May, and begin to be
        metamorphoſed <lb/>in June; and that the little plant which grows up- <lb/>on them reſembles
        a branch of coral, is about <lb/>three inches in height, and carries ſmall protube-
        <lb/>rances, where worms are generated, which are <lb/>again converted into flies. The
        author imagines, <lb/>that, in this account, Dr Watſon has been decei- <lb/>ved by the worms
        which he has already mention- <lb/>ed eat into the clavaria, and undergo a change <lb/>in
        the holes which they have there made. Mr <lb/>Fougeroux is rather inclined to adopt the
        opinion <lb/>of Dr Hill, founded upon obſervations made at <lb/>Martinico. There the cicadae
        are very frequent, <lb/>and, during their chryſalid ſtate, bury themſelves <lb/>among dead
        leaves, to wait their metamorphoſis. <lb/>Dr Hill imagines, that the ſeeds of the clavaria
        are <lb/>then attached to them, and are afterwards develo- <lb/>ped, much in the ſame manner
        as the Fungus ex <lb/>pede equino grows upon the hoofs of dead horſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It may appear aſtoniſhing, that the clavaria <lb/>ſhould attach itſelf ſo conſtantly to
        the nymphae <lb/>of the cicadae in America, as it is not obſerved to <lb/>do ſo in other
        countries. For this Mr Fougeroux <lb/>attempts to account, from viewing the clavaria as
        <lb/>a paraſite peculiar to this ſpecies of inſect; from <pb n="409"/>
        <lb/>the great number of the nymphae of cicadea <lb/>which abound in America; and from the
        circum- <lb/>ſtances of the climate and ſoil, which may render <lb/>this phaenomenon very
        common there, although <lb/>it be not obſerved in Europe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Many particulars reſpecting this ſubject pro- <lb/>bably ſtill remain to be
        inveſtigated. Mr Fou- <lb/>geroux, therefore, recommends it to thoſe lovers <lb/>of natural
        hiſtory, who have themſelves an oppor- <lb/>tunity of examining facts of this kind, to
        multiply <lb/>obſervations, by which a full account of this phae- <lb/>nomenon may be
        obtained. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
