<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: On some Improvements on the Electrical Machine</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>VI. An Extract of a Letter from Dr Nooth to Dr Franklin, F. R. S. on some
              Improvements on the Electrical Machine. Vid. Philosophical Transactions, Vol. 63.
              Part. 2. 4to, London. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society of Physicians in
              Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Murray, No. 32, Fleet-Street; Kincaid and Creech,
                  and W. Drummond, Edinburgh; and T. Ewing, Capel-Street, Dublin.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1774</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">2</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">395-398</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108872049</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T153519</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v2_0395">
    <body>
      <pb n="395"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>VI. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>An Extract of a Letter from <hi rend="roman">Dr Nooth</hi> to <hi rend="roman">Dr
          <lb/>Franklin, F. R. S.</hi> on ſome Improvements on <lb/>the Electrical Machine. Vid.
        Philoſophical <lb/>Tranſactions, Vol. 63. Part. 2. 4to, <hi rend="roman">London</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE author of this paper introduces his ob- <lb/>ſervations, by
        remarking, that, while conſi- <lb/>derable improvements have been made in the ſci- <lb/>ence
        of electricity in general, the electrical ma- <lb/>chine has hitherto remained in an
        imperfect ſtate. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To diſcover the cauſe of the uncertainty in the <lb/>action of electrical machines, Dr
        Nooth's atten- <lb/>tion was firſt directed to the appearances produ- <lb/>ced by a machine
        in motion, and to the effects <lb/>which the glaſs and rubber had on each other. <lb/>He
        conjectured that part only of the electrical <lb/>fluid, excited by the friction, was
        carried to the glaſs <lb/>in motion. This ſuppoſition ſuggeſted an expe- <lb/>riment, the
        event of which ſufficiently proved <lb/>that the greateſt part of the excited fluid was, in
        <lb/>general, reabſorbed by the fore part of the cuſhion, <pb n="396"/>
        <lb/>without becoming ſenſible on the ſuperior part of <lb/>the glaſs. This fact being
        aſcertained, he next <lb/>attempted to diſcover ſome method of preventing <lb/>the return of
        the electrical fluid, till it made a re- <lb/>volution upon the globe. After many trials, he
        <lb/>found that this might be effected by the interpo- <lb/>ſition of ſilk, rubbed over with
        bees wax, between <lb/>the fore part of the cuſhion and the globe. When <lb/>the ſilk was
        ten or twelve times doubled, all com- <lb/>munication between the glaſs and the cuſhion
        <lb/>ſeemed to be prevented, and the power of the <lb/>machine was greatly increaſed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having remedied a defect in the anterior part <lb/>of the cuſhion, attention was next
        paid to the po- <lb/>ſterior part of it. As this is the part alone con- <lb/>cerned in
        excitation, the object was to render the <lb/>afflux of electric matter as great as
        poſſible, by <lb/>the application of the moſt perfect electrics. This <lb/>end was obtained
        by confining the amalgam to <lb/>that part where the glaſs firſt comes in contact <lb/>with
        the rubber; and then making a communi- <lb/>cation, by tin-foil, between the amalgam and the
        <lb/>metallic plate, below the cuſhion; or, what an- <lb/>ſwered better than the tin-foil,
        by fixing a piece <lb/>of leather, covered with amalgam, to the poſte- <lb/>rior part of the
        rubber, in ſuch a manner as to <pb n="397"/>
        <lb/>allow about an inch of it to paſs under the cylin- <lb/>der. By either of theſe means,
        the electric mat- <lb/>ter found an eaſy acceſs, and the power of the <lb/>machine was
        incredibly augmented. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From theſe experiments, the author obſerves, <lb/>that it ſhould be an invariable rule,
        in the conſtruc- <lb/>tion of all electrical machines, to place non-con- <lb/>ducting
        ſubſtances at the fore part of the cuſhion, <lb/>and conducting ſubſtances at the poſterior
        part <lb/>of it. With this intention, variouſly conſtructed <lb/>rubbers may be employed;
        but the moſt power- <lb/>ful excitants which Dr Nooth has tried, were <lb/>made of ten or
        twelve doubles of ſilk, ſtuffed with <lb/>hair. The ſupport of the cuſhion alſo, our au-
        <lb/>thor obſerves, ſhould have its conducting and <lb/>non-conducting ſide. For this
        purpoſe, he ad- <lb/>viſes, that it ſhould be made of baked wood, ha- <lb/>ving the
        poſterior part of it covered with tin- <lb/>foil. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr Nooth concludes this paper with ſome ob- <lb/>ſervations reſpecting the diſpoſition
        of the amal- <lb/>gam. To make it adhere to the poſterior part of <lb/>the rubber, he
        recommends that it ſhould be mix- <lb/>ed with pomatum, and that a little hair-powder
        <lb/>ſhould be ſtrewed on during the revolutions of <pb n="398"/>
        <lb/>the glaſs. By attention to theſe principles, he af- <lb/>firms that the electrician has
        nothing to fear from <lb/>the humidity of the atmoſphere, and that the ma- <lb/>chine will
        work equally well in all kinds of weather. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
