<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Bell: Medical Observations</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Thomas Bell</persName>
            </author>
            <title>SECT. II. Medical Observations. The Hiſtory of a Caſe in which two Foetuſes, that
              had been carried near twenty-one Months, were ſucceſsfully extracted from the Abdomen
              by Inciſion. By Thomas Bell, M. D. of the City of Dublin, communicated to Dr Thomas
              Young, Profeſſor of Midwifery in the Univerſity of Edinburgh. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society of Physicians in
              Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Murray, No. 32, Fleet-Street; Kincaid and Creech,
                  and W. Drummond, Edinburgh; and T. Ewing, Capel-Street, Dublin.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1774</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">2</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">72-77</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108872049</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T153519</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v2_0072">
    <body>
      <pb n="72"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>I. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>The Hiſtory of a Caſe in which two Foetuſes, that <lb/>had been carried near twenty-one
        Months, were <lb/>ſucceſsfully extracted from the Abdomen by In- <lb/>ciſion. By <hi
          rend="roman">Thomas Bell, M. D.</hi> of the City of <lb/>Dublin, communicated to Dr <hi
          rend="roman">Thomas Young</hi>, <lb/>Profeſſor of Midwifery in the Univerſity of E-
        <lb/>dinburgh. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">E</hi>Lenor Noon of Grehan, in the county of <lb/>Mayo, aged
        twenty-one, after being mar- <lb/>ried fifteen months, had the uſual ſigns of preg-
        <lb/>nancy. At the expiration of her reckoning, ſhe <lb/>was ſeized with labour-pains,
        which, by her own <lb/>account, were very violent for ſome days, and con- <lb/>tinued near
        three weeks, gradually becoming more <pb n="73"/>
        <lb/>languid, until they entirely ceaſed. After this, <lb/>ſhe perceived no motion in the
        abdomen. But as <lb/>her pains abated, her belly increaſed in bulk, and <lb/>continued to do
        ſo till I ſaw her, which was in Ja- <lb/>nuary 1757, about five months after ſhe was
        <lb/>firſt ſeized with the labour-pains. At this time, <lb/>the whole abdomen was ſo much
        diſtended, that <lb/>I imagined ſhe and her friends had miſtaken the <lb/>caſe, and that it
        had been an aſcites from the be- <lb/>ginning. But, upon minute inquiry, I had too <lb/>much
        reaſon to ſuſpect what afterwards appeared <lb/>to be well founded. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>She was emaciated to the greateſt degree, and <lb/>ſo weak as not to be able to ſtand,
        or even to <lb/>bear being raiſed, without diſtreſs: So that, from <lb/>every circumſtance,
        I judged it impoſſible that ſhe <lb/>could outlive a few weeks, or that any thing could
        <lb/>be done to ſerve her. But, upon going to the <lb/>ſame part of the country, about four
        months af- <lb/>ter, I found her ſtill living. I was then informed, <lb/>that, about a month
        after I had laſt ſeen her, all <lb/>the water had been evacuated from a ſmall rent <lb/>at
        the navel; and had come away in ſuch quanti- <lb/>ties, and with ſuch violence, that near
        four gallons <lb/>were received in a very ſhort time. Mixed with <lb/>this water, there were
        ſome fleſhy ſtrings; and, as <pb n="74"/>
        <lb/>the oozing continued, ſome ſmall bones came a- <lb/>way. This made the caſe evident
        beyond diſ- <lb/>pute; and a ſituation more diſtreſsful cannot be <lb/>conceived;
        particularly, as the poor woman was <lb/>perfectly ſenſible of it with all its horrors, her
        un- <lb/>derſtanding not being in the leaſt impaired. She <lb/>was, if poſſible, more
        emaciated than formerly; <lb/>ſhe had a conſtant hectic fever, and was ſo weak <lb/>as
        ſcarcely to have power to ſpeak diſtinctly. <lb/>Notwithſtanding this, ſhe was very deſirous
        to <lb/>live, and, what is extraordinary, ſhe did not total- <lb/>ly deſpair of it; a
        circumſtance which I really <lb/>believe contributed not a little to ſave her life. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I conſidered that nature had been ſometimes <lb/>remarkably favourable in caſes nearly
        ſimilar, and <lb/>reſolved to aſſiſt its efforts by the application of <lb/>proper
        cataplaſms, in order to promote ſuppura- <lb/>tion, as the integuments round the aperture
        were <lb/>red, and ſore to the touch. But my expectati- <lb/>ons were diſappointed; for, in
        about ſeven weeks <lb/>after, ſhe was rather ſtronger, the charity of the <lb/>neighbouring
        gentry enabling her to procure pro- <lb/>per diet. Beſides this, the opening was ſo clo-
        <lb/>ſed, that with difficulty it admitted a ſmall probe; <lb/>and the redneſs and ſoreneſs
        were gone. </p>
      <pb n="75"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From this time, I determined on the extraction <lb/>of the extraneous bodies by
        inciſion, as the only <lb/>means left for relieving her. On mentioning it <lb/>to her, ſhe
        eagerly deſired that it ſhould be done, <lb/>from a conviction of there being no other
        chance <lb/>left of ſaving her life. However, as her ſituation <lb/>was ſo very unpromiſing
        as to give little hope of <lb/>ſucceſs, I reſolved to have the concurrence of <lb/>more of
        the profeſſion. I had her accordingly <lb/>carried to Galway, which was about twenty miles
        <lb/>from the place of her reſidence, by two men, in a <lb/>covered litter. The fatigue of
        this journey ſhe <lb/>bore much better than could have been expected. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On a conſultation with Doctors Joyce, Ryan, <lb/>and Brown, phyſicians reſiding in
        Galway, we <lb/>agreed upon the neceſſity of an operation; but, <lb/>from many diſcouraging
        circumſtances, could en- <lb/>tertain little hopes of ſucceſs. As the poor woman <lb/>was
        ſtill deſirous of having it done, I performed it <lb/>in preſence of the above phyſicians,
        and of two <lb/>army-ſurgeons, Dr Scott and Mr Hopkins, the <lb/>latter of whom aſſiſted me.
        I made an inciſion <lb/>in the moſt prominent part of the abdomen, ex- <lb/>tending about
        two inches above, and as far be- <lb/>low the navel. At this inciſion I extracted the
        <lb/>bones of two full grown foetus's, for little beſides <pb n="76"/>
        <lb/>the bones now remained. They are ſince depo- <lb/>ſited in the anatomical theatre of
        our univerſity. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>My patient bore the operation better than <lb/>could have been expected. No haemorrhage
        <lb/>enſued; and ſhe recovered her health ſo very <lb/>ſpeedily, as to be able to menſtruate
        in little more <lb/>than three months. In about three months more, <lb/>ſhe was prevailed on
        to cohabit with her huſband. <lb/>She became pregnant in two months after; went <lb/>to her
        full time; and had an eaſy natural labour <lb/>and healthful child. Since that, ſhe has had
        ſix <lb/>more; and enjoys as great a ſhare of health and <lb/>ſtrength of conſtitution as
        moſt people. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>During the operation, I introduced my hand <lb/>ſeveral times into the abdomen, both
        that I might <lb/>extract all the bones and other extraneous mat- <lb/>ters, and that I
        might be able to judge whether <lb/>the foetus's were in the uterus, or in any cyſt
        <lb/>formed for them. Some of the other gentlemen <lb/>preſent did the ſame. But the
        weakneſs of the <lb/>woman prevented us from making ſuch an exa- <lb/>mination as would have
        been ſufficient for deter- <lb/>mining this point with certainty. Moſt of the <lb/>gentlemen
        preſent imagined the former to have <lb/>been the caſe; and indeed, the thickneſs and
        <lb/>firmneſs of the ſubſtance in which the foetus's <pb n="77"/>
        <lb/>were contained, ſeemed to corroborate that opi- <lb/>nion. But, beſides this, the woman
        ſtill perſiſts <lb/>in aſſerting, that the waters came from her in <lb/>that labour in the
        natural way, and in the ſame <lb/>manner that they have done in ſeveral others la-
        <lb/>bours ſince. This aſſertion, if true, muſt put it <lb/>beyond all doubt that the
        foetus's were lodged in <lb/>the uterus, and not in any particular cyſt. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
