<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Jackson: An Account of the Discovery of the Manner of making Isinglass
          in Russia</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Humphry Jackson</persName>
            </author>
            <title>IX. An Account of the Discovery of the Manner of making Isinglass in Russia, with
              a particular Description of its Manufacture in England, from the Produce of British
              Fisheries. In a letter from Humphry Jackson, Esq; F.R.S. to William Watson, M.D.F.R.S.
              Vide Philosophical Transactions, vol. 63. part 1. 4to, London</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society of Physicians in
              Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Murray, No. 32, Fleet-Street; Kincaid and Creech,
                  and W. Drummond, Edinburgh; and T. Ewing, Capel-Street, Dublin.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1774</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">2</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">284-288</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108872049</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T153519</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v2_0284">
    <body>
      <pb n="284"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>IX. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>An Account of the Diſcovery of the Manner of ma- <lb/>king Iſinglaſs in Ruſſia, with a
        particular De- <lb/>ſcription of its Manufacture in England, from <lb/>the Produce of
        Britiſh Fiſheries. In a letter from <lb/><hi rend="roman">Humphry Jackſon</hi>, Eſq; F. R.
        S. to <hi rend="roman">William <lb/>Watſon</hi>, M. D. F. R. S. <hi rend="roman">Vide <hi
            rend="italic">Philoſophical <lb/>Tranſactions, vol. 63. part 1.</hi> 4to, London</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi><hi rend="sc">Singlass</hi>, fiſh-glue, or ichthyocolla, is a
        con- <lb/>ſiderable article of commerce. The fiſh, <pb n="285"/>
        <lb/>from which it is produced has been mentioned <lb/>by ſeveral natural hiſtorians: But
        the proper me- <lb/>thod of manufacturing it has long remained a ſe- <lb/>cret. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The author of the letter now before us intro- <lb/>duces his ſubject, by obſerving,
        that Pomet, from <lb/>whom many others ſeem to have copied their ac- <lb/>counts, has
        greatly miſtaken both the conſtituent <lb/>matter and preparation of iſinglaſs. From his ac-
        <lb/>count of the proceſs, we are led to ſuppoſe, that <lb/>it may be procured from every
        ſpecies of fiſh af- <lb/>fording gelatinous principles. Truſting to the <lb/>authority of
        chemical writers, Mr Jackſon's at- <lb/>tempts to diſcover the conſtituent parts of iſin-
        <lb/>glaſs were at firſt without ſucceſs. Glue, not i- <lb/>ſinglaſs, was the reſult of
        every proceſs. A jour- <lb/>ney to Ruſſia, with a view of diſcovering this ſe- <lb/>cret,
        was as unſucceſsful as his other attempts. <lb/>But, by a ſteady perſeverance, he, at
        length, not <lb/>only gained his end, but, in the purſuit, diſcover- <lb/>ed alſo a reſinous
        ſubſtance, plentifully procura- <lb/>ble in the Britiſh fiſheries, which experience has
        <lb/>confirmed to be poſſeſſed of the ſame proper- <lb/>ties. </p>
      <pb n="286"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In conſidering this ſubject, Mr Jackſon firſt <lb/>gives the reſult of ſome
        experiments, which ſhew <lb/>the impracticability of making iſinglaſs by a pre- <lb/>vious
        ſolution of animal matters, according to <lb/>the proceſs delivered by moſt authors. He then
        <lb/>ſhews, that it is nothing more than certain mem- <lb/>branous parts of fiſhes, diveſted
        of their natural <lb/>mucoſity, rolled and twiſted into various forms, <lb/>and then dried
        in the air. This is proved by the <lb/>following experiment: If long or ſhort ſtapled
        <lb/>iſinglaſs be ſteeped for a few hours in cold water, <lb/>and then untwiſted, the
        membranes of which it <lb/>is compoſed will expand, and reaſſume their for- <lb/>mer
        original hue. By a dexterous addreſs, they <lb/>may even be perfectly unfolded. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The finer ſort of iſinglaſs is prepared from the <lb/>ſounds, or air-bladders, of all
        ſorts of freſh-water <lb/>fiſh. In Muſcovy, however, it is chiefly prepared <lb/>from thoſe
        of the beluga. The book, or ordi- <lb/>nary ſtaple iſinglaſs, ſeems to be prepared from
        <lb/>the inteſtines, and probably alſo from the perito- <lb/>neum of the ſame kinds of fiſh. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The parts of the fiſh from which the iſinglaſs <lb/>is formed, particularly the ſounds,
        are taken out <lb/>while freſh and ſweet, they are then ſlit open, <pb n="287"/>
        <lb/>waſhed from their ſlimy ſordes, diveſted of every <lb/>thin membrane which envelopes
        them, and af- <lb/>terwards expoſed for a little to the air, that they <lb/>may, in ſome
        degree, ſtiffen. When, in this <lb/>ſtate, they are formed into rolls of different length,
        <lb/>and thickneſs, or into what is generally called <lb/>Book and Cake Iſinglaſs, and they
        are afterwards <lb/>completely dried in the open air. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Our author imagines, that the peculiar ſhapes <lb/>in which we at preſent find
        iſinglaſs, were given <lb/>it at firſt, with a view to diſguiſe the real ſub- <lb/>ſtance of
        which it conſiſts. As this, however, <lb/>in the Britiſh fiſheries, would be unneceſſary, he
        <lb/>imagines it will anſwer every purpoſe in its native <lb/>ſtate, without any ſuch
        preparation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As a ſpecies of iſinglaſs, procured from the <lb/>marine fiſheries, may be more
        immediately en- <lb/>couraged, Mr Jackſon propoſes a method of pre- <lb/>paring it from the
        ſounds of cod, and ling. The <lb/>iſinglaſs prepared from the latter of theſe fiſh,
        <lb/>will admit of any ſhape; that from the cod of the <lb/>book-ſhape only. From the
        cartilaginous nature <lb/>of the ſturgeon, it might be imagined that it <lb/>ſhould yield a
        large proportion of iſinglaſs. Up- <pb n="288"/>
        <lb/>on examination, however, this is found not to be <lb/>the caſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This paper is concluded with an account of the <lb/>effects of iſinglaſs on
        compoſitions of plaſter, or <lb/>lime, for ornamenting walls expoſed to the vi-
        <lb/>ciſſitudes of the weather. If it be diſſolved in <lb/>cold water, acidulated with
        vitriolic acid, and <lb/>then mixed with the above compoſitions, it forms <lb/>an
        indiſſoluble firm concrete of extraordinary <lb/>ſtrength and durability. In this
        compoſition, <lb/>the acid quits the jelly, and forms with the lime <lb/>a ſelenitic maſs;
        while, at the ſame time, the jel- <lb/>ly being deprived of its moiſture, by the forma-
        <lb/>tion of an indiſſoluble concrete among its parts, <lb/>ſoon dries, and hardens into a
        firm body. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
