<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: Concerning the medicinal Effects of a poisonous Plant
          exhibited instead of Water - parsnep</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>IV. A Letter from Richard Pulteney, M. D. F. R. S. to William Watson, M. D. F. R.
              S. concerning the medicinal Effects of a poisonous Plant exhibited instead of Water -
              parsnep. Vid. Philosophical Transactions, vol. 62. 4to, London.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society of Physicians in
              Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Murray, No. 32, Fleet-Street; Kincaid and Creech,
                  and W. Drummond, Edinburgh; and T. Ewing, Capel-Street, Dublin.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1774</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">2</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">31-33</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108872049</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T153519</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v2_0031">
    <body>
      <pb n="31"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>IV. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>A Letter from <hi rend="roman">Richard Pulteney</hi>, M. D. F. R. S. <lb/>to <hi
          rend="roman">William Watſon</hi>, M. D. F. R. S. concerning <lb/>the medicinal Effects of
        a poiſonous Plant exhi- <lb/>bited inſtead of Water-parſnep. Vid. Philoſo- <lb/>phical
        Tranſactions, vol. <hi rend="roman">62</hi>. <hi rend="roman">4to, London</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N this letter we are preſented with an account <lb/>of very
        beneficial effects reaped from a plant <lb/>which has hitherto been very little, if at all,
        uſed <lb/>in the practice of phyſic. This plant Dr Pul- <lb/>teney ſuppoſes to have been the
        Oenanthe crocata <lb/>of Linnaeus, which is in general known by the <lb/>Engliſh name of
        Hemlock-dropwort. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The caſe in which he had an opportunity of <lb/>becoming acquainted with its uſe, was
        that of a <lb/>man, who, from the age of fifteen till he arrived <lb/>at forty, was affected
        with a moſt violent cutane- <lb/>ous eruption. With a view to remove it, many <lb/>remedies,
        preſcribed by regular phyſicians, and <lb/>not a few of the boaſted arcana of empyrics, were
        <lb/>employed without any advantage. At length his <lb/>diſorder increaſed very rapidly.
        Beſides the far- <pb n="32"/>
        <lb/>ther ſpreading of the eruption, the integuments <lb/>of his legs thickened much, and
        the limbs ſwelled <lb/>to ſuch a degree as to render him unable to walk. <lb/>While the
        quantity of brawny ſcurf and ſcales <lb/>thrown off, was ſo great, that handfuls of it might
        <lb/>have been taken out of his bed every morning. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In this unhappy ſituation, it was recom- <lb/>mended to him to take every morning, when
        <lb/>faſting, a table-ſpoonful of the juice of water- <lb/>parſnep, mixed with two ſpoonfuls
        of white <lb/>wine: And the perſon who recommended this <lb/>remedy procured him about half
        a pint of <lb/>what he ſaid was the juice of water-parſnep. <lb/>The firſt doſe produced
        ſuch vertigo, ſickneſs, vo- <lb/>miting, cold ſweats, and long continued rigour, <lb/>that
        it had almoſt proved fatal. So ſtrong, how- <lb/>ever, was his deſire of relief, that, with
        the inter- <lb/>miſſion of one day, he repeated it in nearly the <lb/>ſame doſe. It was
        followed by the ſame ſickneſs <lb/>and vomiting as before, but the ſucceeding rigour
        <lb/>was by no means ſo violent. He was obliged, <lb/>therefore, gradually to reduce his
        doſe to about <lb/>half the quantity he had taken at firſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Before he had taken this juice a month, he was <lb/>ſenſible of a very great change for
        the better; <lb/>and, by perſiſting in it for ſome time longer, his <lb/>ſymptoms were
        almoſt entirely removed. It <pb n="33"/>
        <lb/>deſerves to be remarked, that this juice never <lb/>purged him, although, even in its
        reduced doſe, <lb/>it never failed to occaſion vertigo, nauſea, and ſick- <lb/>neſs, which
        were ſoon relieved, if vomiting ſuper- <lb/>
        <choice>
          <corr>vened</corr>
          <sic>veened</sic>
        </choice>. After he had thus far recovered, he de- <lb/>ſiſted from the juice of the plant;
        but, in its <lb/>ſtead, he drank every morning for breakfaſt an <lb/>infuſion of the leaves.
        This infuſion neither ex- <lb/>cited nauſea nor ſickneſs, but always brought on <lb/>a
        ſlight degree of vertigo. The only ſenſible o- <lb/>peration he could obſerve from this
        plant was, <lb/>that it produced an increaſed flow of urine, in <lb/>which there was a
        copious ſediment. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr Pulteney concluded, that the plant which <lb/>was employed in this caſe could not be
        the water- <lb/>parſnep, which is a ſafe and harmleſs vegetable. <lb/>He imagined it
        probable that the oenanthe cro- <lb/>cata, which is very common in that part of the
        <lb/>country, had been uſed in its ſtead. In this ſuſ- <lb/>picion he was confirmed, from
        getting a ſpecimen <lb/>of the plant which had been uſed; and, upon <lb/>farther inquiry, he
        found that it was the juice of <lb/>the root that had been adminiſtered, and not of <lb/>the
        leaves and ſtalks. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
