<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Hewson: An experimental Inquiry into the Figure and Composition of the
          Red Particles of the Blood</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>William Hewson</persName>
            </author>
            <title>X. An experimental Inquiry into the Figure and Composition of the Red Particles
              of the Blood, commonly called the Red Globules. Being a Copy of a Paper lately read
              before the Royal Society. By William Hewson, F.R.S. and teacher of Anatomy. 4to,
              London.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society of Physicians in
              Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Murray, No. 32, Fleet-Street; Kincaid and Creech,
                  and W. Drummond, Edinburgh; and T. Ewing, Capel-Street, Dublin.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1774</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">2</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">289-293</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108872049</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T153519</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v2_0289">
    <body>
      <pb n="289"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>X. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>An experimental Inquiry into the Figure and Com- <lb/>poſition of the Red Particles of
        the Blood, common- <lb/>ly called the Red Globules. Being a Copy of a <lb/>Paper lately read
        before the Royal Society. By <lb/><hi rend="roman">William Hewſon</hi>, F. R. S. and Teacher
        of Ana- <lb/>tomy. <hi rend="roman">4to, London</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">S</hi>INCE the time of Leeuwenhoeck, the red par- <lb/>ticles of the
        human blood have, in general, <lb/>been ſuppoſed to be ſpherical. This figure, how-
        <lb/>ever, has been doubted by Father de la Torré, <lb/>and ſome others; and the induſtrious
        author of <lb/>the diſſertation now before us, whoſe labours, ex- <lb/>erted with the moſt
        happy ſucceſs for the im- <lb/>provement of others, have unfortunately proved <lb/>fatal to
        himſelf, likewiſe controverts this opinion. <lb/>Having made ſome new obſervations on this
        ſub- <lb/>ject, he here preſents them to the public. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He introduces his ſubject, by obſerving, that <lb/>theſe particles in the blood are
        found very gene- <lb/>rally extended over the whole animal creation. <pb n="290"/>
        <lb/>It is, however, by the aſſiſtance of the microſcope <lb/>only, that they can be
        diſcovered. In all the ex- <lb/>periments mentioned in this paper, one excepted, <lb/>the
        ſingle microſcope was employed, which, tho' <lb/>inferior in magnifying powers to the
        compound <lb/>microſcope, is much ſuperior to it in diſtinct- <lb/>neſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr Hewſon affirms, that the human blood, or <lb/>blood of other animals, diluted with
        ſerum; with <lb/>water having one ſixth, or one twelfth of any neu- <lb/>tral ſalt diſſolved
        in it; or with urine, when ſtrong- <lb/>ly impregnated with ſalts, ſhews the particles, im-
        <lb/>properly called globules, to be flat bodies, having <lb/>a dark ſpot in the middle. And
        this figure, he <lb/>obſerves, they not only ſhew in extravaſated blood, <lb/>but alſo in
        that circulating in the veſſels of ani- <lb/>mals. The ſize of theſe particles, he obſerves,
        <lb/>varies, not only in different animals, and in the <lb/>ſame animal at different times,
        but even in the <lb/>ſame animal, and at the ſame time. They are, <lb/>however, upon the
        whole, largeſt in the ſkate, <lb/>and ſmalleſt in the ox, mouſe, cat, bat, and aſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If blood be examined, when diluted with a <lb/>ſtronger ſolution of neutral ſalt than
        that men- <lb/>tioned above, the particles appear ſhrivelled and <pb n="291"/>
        <lb/>contracted. If it be examined without dilution, <lb/>as it flows from a vein, though
        ſpread very thin <lb/>upon talk or glaſs, it appears a confuſed maſs, in <lb/>which the
        particles cannot be ſeen ſeparate from <lb/>each other. It is, therefore, to proper
        dilution, <lb/>that Mr Hewſon attributes his ſucceſs in de- <lb/>tecting the real figure of
        the red particles of the <lb/>human blood. Leeuwenhoeck himſelf allowed, <lb/>that, in
        fiſhs, and amphibious animals, theſe bo- <lb/>dies were flat and eliptical; and our author
        <lb/>imagines it probable, that he concluded them to <lb/>be ſpherical in quadrupeds and in
        the human bo- <lb/>dy, rather from theory than obſervation; for, as <lb/>the blood which he
        examined was not diluted, he <lb/>could not be qualified to deſcribe them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When the particles are diluted with water, they <lb/>appear firſt ſpherical, and then
        diſſolve. When <lb/>they have aſſumed a ſpherical figure, the black <lb/>ſpot before ſeen in
        their middle, may be obſerved <lb/>ſometimes to turn and roll from one ſide to the
        <lb/>other, and ſometimes to ſtick to the ſide of the <lb/>ſphere, like a pea in a bladder.
        The diameter <lb/>of theſe ſpheres is leſs than their largeſt diameter <lb/>when in a flat
        ſhape; and the blackiſh bodies ap- <lb/>pear to be leſs ſoluble than the veſicle containing
          <pb n="292"/>
        <lb/>them, as they remain after the diſſolution of the <lb/>veſicles. From theſe
        obſervations, Mr Hewſon <lb/>concludes, that the particles of the blood are not, <lb/>as
        Father de la Torré ſuppoſed, annular or hollow <lb/>rings, and that the blackiſh ſpot, which
        he ima- <lb/>gined to be a perforation, is a ſolid body contain- <lb/>ed in a veſicle, the
        ſides of which are filled with <lb/>a ſubtile fluid. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Blood, beginning to putrify, when diluted with <lb/>freſh ſerum, or freſh blood diluted
        with putreſ- <lb/>cent ſerum, exhibits particles like mulberries, or <lb/>rough ſpheres, the
        diameters of which are leſs <lb/>than the largeſt diameters of the particles in a <lb/>flat
        ſhape. In blood begining to putrify, the <lb/>particles ſometimes break to pieces, and the
        black <lb/>ſpot is fiſſured through its middle. Theſe phae- <lb/>nomena our author conſiders
        to be farther argu- <lb/>ments againſt the annular ſtructure of the red <lb/>globules. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr Hewſon maintains, that there is nothing <lb/>regular in the number of parts into
        which the <lb/>veſicles break; though Father de la Torré ſuppo- <lb/>ſed each to be compoſed
        of ſeven joints, into <lb/>which they regularly broke down; and Leeuwen- <lb/>hoeck
        imagined, that each globule conſiſted of <lb/>ſix leſſer ones. </p>
      <pb n="293"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After theſe experiments on the blood diluted <lb/>with pure water, and with water
        impregnated with <lb/>different proportions of neutral ſalts, Mr Hewſon <lb/>concludes, that
        the uſe of the ſerum is to preſerve <lb/>the flat ſhape of the veſicles. And, from obſer-
        <lb/>ving, that both a very ſtrong ſolution, and a very <lb/>dilute one, alter their ſhape,
        he thinks it probable, <lb/>that nature has limited the proportion of water and <lb/>ſalts
        in our blood; but that in this proportion there <lb/>is ſome latitude. He imagines likewiſe,
        that the <lb/>mucilage of the lymph has ſome ſhare in preſer- <lb/>ving the flat ſhape of
        the red particles. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
