<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Aikin: he History of a Case, in which a Tumour in the Abdomen, after
          Delivery, was imagined to be a second Child</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>John Aikin</persName>
            </author>
            <title>III. The History of a Case, in which a Tumour in the Abdomen, after Delivery, was
              imagined to be a second Child; but soon after spontaneously disappeared. By Mr John
              Aikin Surgeon at Warrington. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society of Physicians in
              Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Murray, No. 32, Fleet-Street; Kincaid and Creech,
                  and W. Drummond, Edinburgh; and T. Ewing, Capel-Street, Dublin.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1774</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">2</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">300-302</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108872049</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T153519</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v2_0300">
    <body>
      <pb n="300"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>III. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/> The Hiſtory of a Caſe, in which a Tumour in the Ab- <lb/>domen, after Delivery, was
        imagined to be a ſe- <lb/>cond Child; but ſoon after ſpontaneouſly diſap- <lb/>peared. By Mr
          <hi rend="roman">John Aikin</hi> Surgeon at War- <lb/>rington. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>RS P—, of a delicate habit of body, the mo- <lb/>ther of ſeveral
        children, was taken in la- <lb/>bour in the night of October 23. 1773, and de- <lb/>livered
        of a ſmall child, which appeared to have <lb/>been a ſhort time dead. The midwife, upon diſ-
        <lb/>covering that her belly continued much diſtended, <lb/>ſuſpecting that there was ſtill
        another child, ſent <pb n="301"/>
        <lb/>for me. I found the placenta lying looſe in the <lb/>vagina. I removed it; but, upon
        introducing <lb/>my ſinger, I could not feel any other ſubſtance <lb/>preſenting. I then
        laid my hand upon the ab- <lb/>domen, and diſtinctly felt through the thin inte-
        <lb/>guments, a large ſolid ſubſtance, of an irregular <lb/>form, ſtretching high up above
        the navel. I made <lb/>little doubt that this was a ſecond child; and I <lb/>thought I could
        diſcover the protuberances of its <lb/>limbs, and the reſt of its body. However, as
        <lb/>there was no flooding, and as the patient was <lb/>weak and fatigued, I did not think
        proper to at- <lb/>tempt immediate delivery. After waiting, there- <lb/>fore, for ſome
        hours,as no labour-pains came on, I <lb/>gave her an opiate; and left her under the care of
        <lb/>the midwife. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I found her much in the ſame ſtate next morn- <lb/>ing; but the tumour was ſomething
        lower in the <lb/>abdomen. I continued to viſit her daily, and <lb/>found no other ſymptoms
        but thoſe uſually ſuc- <lb/>ceeding labour. The after-pains were moderate; <lb/>the lochial
        diſcharge was at firſt ſmall, but af- <lb/>terwards very conſiderable in quantity, and of a
        <lb/>ſlimy, foul appearance. The tumour gradually de- <lb/>ſcended, ſoftened, and
        diminiſhed; and in leſs <pb n="302"/>
        <lb/>than a fortnight, it was quite imperceptible. The <lb/>patient was at that time as well
        recovered as any <lb/>of her weakly conſtitution could expect, after a <lb/>common delivery.
        Her ſtools were regular, but <lb/>the ſecretion of milk was but ſmall, as had been <lb/>the
        caſe with her at her laſt lying in. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On inquiry, I learned, that her belly was not <lb/>obſerved to be enlarged before
        pregnancy; that <lb/>ſhe bad been in a poor ſtate of health du- <lb/>ring the courſe of her
        pregnancy, having conti- <lb/>nual pain in the region where this tumour was <lb/>found, with
        thirſt, hectic heats, and want of ap- <lb/>petite. She had for ſome years paſt undergone
        <lb/>a good deal of hardſhip and diſtreſs, from cir- <lb/>cumſtances of misfortune. She was,
        at the end <lb/>of ſix weeks after this delivery, in better health <lb/>than ſhe had been
        for many years before. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A practitioner of eminent ſkill and experience <lb/>in this town informs me, that a
        caſe, almoſt ex- <lb/>actly ſimilar to this in its ſymptoms and termina- <lb/>tion, fell
        under his care ſome years ago. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
