<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anderson: Two Cases of Dislocation of the Femur</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Thomas Anderson</persName>
            </author>
            <title>V. Two Cases of Dislocation of the Femur, with an Account of the Method of
              Reduction. By Mr Thomas Anderson Surgeon in Leith. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society in Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Murray, No. 32. Fleet-Street</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1775</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">3</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">424-429</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW109044002</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">N036372</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v3_0424">
    <body>
      <pb n="424"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>V. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Two Caſes of Diſlocation of the Femur, with an <lb/>Account of the Method of Reduction.
        By Mr <lb/><hi rend="roman">Thomas Anderſon</hi> Surgeon in <hi rend="roman">Leith</hi>. </head>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>1. </head>
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N September 1772, Mr Bruce ſurgeon at Muſ- <lb/>ſelburgh ſent
          to me, deſiring I would meet <lb/>him at Lord Abercorn's coal-work, one of the
          <lb/>colliers having diſlocated his left thigh-bone. I <lb/>there found Meſſrs Bruce and
          Stewart ſurgeons <lb/>in Muſſelburgh, and Meſſrs Simpſon and Clarkſon <lb/>ſurgeons in
          Dalkeith, who were juſt begun to at- <pb n="425"/>
          <lb/>tempt the reduction by pullies. With theſe ſe- <lb/>veral trials were made; but the
          lacque round the <lb/>knee ſlipping, it was taken off. By this means <lb/>I had an
          opportunity of examining it. I found <lb/>the left-knee protruding three or four inches
          <lb/>further than the right, and the one could <lb/>not be brought within eight or ten
          inches of the <lb/>other, the foot being turned out. When it <lb/>was moved upwards and
          downwards, if done <lb/>gently, he found little pain; but I obſerved, when <lb/>it was
          nearly, or altogether extended, the head of <lb/>the bone became fixed. And he complained
          <lb/>more when it was in that ſituation, if any rota- <lb/>tory motion was attempted with
          the femur, which <lb/>gave him no uneaſineſs when the thigh was <lb/>brought up towards
          the abdomen. From the a- <lb/>bove appearance, it was certain the head of the <lb/>bone
          was diſplaced from the acetabulum, and <lb/>lodged downwards and inwards, in the large
          fora- <lb/>men of the iſchium and pubis. I was convinced <lb/>that attempting the
          reduction, in the common <lb/>method, with the thigh extended, was improper, <lb/>as the
          muſcles were all put upon the ſtretch, the <lb/>action of which is perhaps ſufficient to
          overba- <lb/>lance any extenſion we can apply. But, by <lb/>bringing the thigh to near a
          right angle with the <pb n="426"/>
          <lb/>trunk, by which the muſcles would be greatly re- <lb/>laxed, I imagined that the
          reduction might <lb/>more readily take place, and with much leſs ex- <lb/>tenſion. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>When I made this examination, he was lying <lb/>on a table on his back. I raiſed the
          thigh to a- <lb/>bout a right angle with the trunk, and, with my <lb/>right-hand at the
          ham, laid hold of the thigh, <lb/>and made what extenſion I could. From this <lb/>trial I
          found I could diſlodge the head of the <lb/>bone. At the ſame time that I did this, with
          my <lb/>left-hand at the head and inſide of the thigh, I <lb/>preſſed it towards the
          acetabulum, while my right <lb/>gave the femur a little circular turn, ſo as to <lb/>bring
          the rotula inwards to its natural ſituation; <lb/>and, upon the ſecond attempt, it went in
          with a <lb/>ſnap obſervable to the gentlemen ſtanding round, <lb/>but more ſo to the poor
          man, who inſtantly cried <lb/>out he was well and free from pain. His knees <lb/>could
          then be brought together; the legs were <lb/>of the ſame length, and the foot in its
          natural <lb/>ſituation. The knees were kept together for ſome <lb/>time, with a roller, to
          confine the motion of the <lb/>thigh; and, in three weeks, he was at his work,
          <lb/>without the leaſt ſtiffneſs in the joint. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="427"/>
      <div>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>2. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>A boy, eight years old, of a ſtrong healthy con- <lb/>ſtitution, while he happened to
          be carried on his <lb/>ſiſter's back, loſt the hold he had of her neck, <lb/>and fell to
          the left-ſide. She, however, held him <lb/>by the legs, which were round her waiſt, ſo as
          to <lb/>occaſion conſiderable ſtreſs to the parts. He was <lb/>carried home, and
          complained of the left thigh <lb/>and haunch, which he ſaid was from a fall <lb/>from his
          ſiſter's back. The parents being poor, <lb/>and imagining it to be only bruiſed, were
          eigh- <lb/>teen days before they called any aſſiſtance. At <lb/>this time I found him
          lying in bed on his back, <lb/>the fore part of the femur turned quite in, the <lb/>knee
          lying on the right thigh, was fully four <lb/>inches ſhorter, the leg turned out, and
          conſider- <lb/>able tenſion and ſwelling on the hip. From the <lb/>appearance, I ſuſpected
          a fracture at the neck of <lb/>the bone; but, on examining it, was ſoon con- <lb/>vinced
          of the diſlocation, and that the head of the <lb/>bone was lodged upwards and backwards
          from <lb/>the acetabulum, in the concave part of the ilium <lb/>where it joins the
          iſchium. The ſmalleſt attempt <lb/>to carry the thigh outwards from the poſition in <pb
            n="428"/>
          <lb/>which it lay, gave him the moſt exquiſite pain, <lb/>and he could only allow it to be
          gently moved <lb/>upwards, if, at the ſame time, the knee was kept <lb/>over to the
          right-ſide. From the motion made <lb/>to diſcover its ſituation, he complained ſo much,
          <lb/>that the reduction was not attempted at that time. <lb/>The hip was fomented, rubbed
          with camphorated <lb/>oil, and a poultice applied for that night. Next <lb/>forenoon 1
          called on him with two young gentle- <lb/>men; he was placed acroſs the bed, the thigh
          <lb/>raiſed ſo as to form an acute angle with the trunk. <lb/>In this ſituation the knee
          lay conſiderably over to <lb/>the right-ſide, and the leg was turned much out- <lb/>wards
          . He was kept down by an aſſiſtant, while I <lb/>laid hold, with both my hands, above the
          knee, at <lb/>the ſame time ſtanding upon the ſide of the bed, <lb/>and pulling upwards, I
          found I could move the <lb/>head of the bone from the place where it was <lb/>lodged; and,
          upon making conſiderable exten- <lb/>ſion, with my left-hand I laid hold of the middle
          <lb/>of the leg, which I brought inwards. By this <lb/>the femur made a circular turn,
          which directed <lb/>its head towards the acetabulum, into which <lb/>it went with a
          ſenſible noiſe. The boy imme- <lb/>diately cried out, that he was well, and could al- <pb
            n="429"/>
          <lb/>low the thigh to be moved gently in any direc- <lb/>tion. The thighs were kept
          together for two <lb/>weeks with a bandage, and, in three weeks, he <lb/>could walk; but
          he complained of ſtiffneſs in the <lb/>joint for a week or two afterwards. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
