<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Percival: The Case of an Angina Pectoris, which terminated
          fatally</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Thomas Percival</persName>
            </author>
            <title>The Case of an Angina Pectoris, which terminated fatally with the Dissection; by
              Thomas Percival, M. D. F. R. S. and S. A. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society in Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Murray, No. 32. Fleet-Street</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1775</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">3</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">180-182</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW109044002</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">N036372</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v3_0180">
    <body>
      <pb n="180"/>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>The Caſe of an Angina Pectoris, which terminated <lb/>fatally with the Diſſection; by
          <hi rend="roman">Thomas Perci- <lb/>val, M. D. F. R. S. and S. A.</hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N N<unclear>ove</unclear>mber 1773, I was deſired to viſit a
          <lb/><unclear>gentleman near Knu</unclear>tsford in Cheſhire, aged <lb/><unclear>upwards
          of fifty</unclear>, who had been, for ſeveral years, <lb/>ſubject to frequent attacks of a
        moſt alarming <lb/>and oppreſſive ſenſation in his breaſt, which he <lb/>knew not how to
        deſcribe. This ſymptom was <lb/>attended with a pain about the middle of the <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">ſternum</hi>, inclining to the left ſide; and he was <lb/>generally
        affected, at the ſame time, with a pain in <lb/>his left arm where the deltoid muſcle is
        inſerted. <pb n="181"/>
        <lb/>As I viſited the patient only once, and took no <lb/>notes of his caſe, I cannot give a
        minute detail <lb/>of it, and muſt content myſelf with ſaying, that I <lb/>apprehended his
        diſorder to be what Dr Heber- <lb/>den hath ſo accurately deſcribed under the name <lb/>of
          <hi rend="italic">Angina Pectoris</hi>. Various anodyne and anti- <lb/>ſpaſmodic remedies
        were preſcribed; but theſe <lb/>produced only a temporary alleviation of his
        <lb/>complaints. And it was obſerved, that nothing <lb/>afforded ſuch inſtantaneous eaſe,
        during the <lb/>paroxyſms of his diſorder, as venaeſection or <lb/>vomiting. In July 1774,
        he died; and his body <lb/>was examined by Mr Allen, an ingenious ſur- <lb/>geon in
        Knutsford, who has favoured me with <lb/>the following account of the diſſection. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The left lobe of the liver was conſiderably en- <lb/>larged, and full of indurated,
        white, tumors; <lb/>and nearly one half of the right lobe was beginning <lb/>to be affected
        in a ſimilar manner. The gall- <lb/>bladder was diſtended with bile; the ſtomach <lb/>was
        hard and ſchirrous, as far as it was in contact <lb/>with the liver; the lungs were pale and
        livid; <lb/>and the blood-veſſels as diſtinct as if they had <lb/>been injected with
        Pruſſian blue. The heart <lb/>and aorta deſcendens were in a ſound ſtate; ve- <lb/>ry little
        water was found in the pericardium, or <pb n="182"/>
        <lb/>mediaſtinum; and there was nothing preterna- <lb/>tural in the appearance of the
        diaphragm. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This gentleman had lived freely, but was not <lb/>ſubject to the gout. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr Heberden has favoured me with the fol- <lb/>lowing remarks upon this caſe. <q
          rend="quotes">The diſſection <lb/>of this ſufferer by the angina pectoris, as well as
          <lb/>that of a few others, which I have heard of, <lb/>teaches us, that the diſeaſe is
          neither owing to <lb/>inflammation, nor to any mal-conformation of <lb/>the parts. We muſt
          not therefore ſeek for the <lb/>cure amongſt the means which lower the <hi rend="italic"
            >vis vitae</hi>; <lb/>and we need not deſpair of finding it elſewhere. <lb/>But we
          ſhould not expect to find it very ſoon, <lb/>when we conſider how little ſucceſs has
          attended <lb/>all our ſearches after a remedy for the gout, and <lb/>for ſome other
          diſtempers, with whoſe natures <lb/>we have had, for ſome thouſand years, ſuch a-
          <lb/>bundant means of being acquainted. </q>
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
