<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: Observations sur la Structure des Parties de la Génération de
          la Femme</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>II. Observations sur la Structure des Parties de la Génération de la Femme; par
              Mr Portal. Vide Histoire de l'Academie Royale des Sciences, Année 1770. 4to, Paris.
            </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society in Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Murray, No. 32. Fleet-Street</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1775</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">3</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">351-358</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW109044002</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">N036372</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v3_0351">
    <body>
      <pb n="351"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>II. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Obſervations ſur la Structure des Parties de la <lb/>Génération de la Femme; par <hi
          rend="roman">Mr Portal</hi>. <lb/>Vide Hiſtoire de l'Academie Royale des Sciences,
        <lb/>Année 1770. <hi rend="roman">4to, Paris.</hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>R PORTAL, after mentioning a va- <lb/>riety of different
        opinions that had pre- <lb/>vailed among anatomiſts reſpecting the parts <lb/>ſubſervient to
        generation in women, propoſes to <lb/>give ſome obſervations of his own on this ſub-
        <lb/>ject. In the memoir before us, he confines <lb/>himſelf to the internal parts of
        generation in wo- <lb/>men. He remarks, in the firſt place, that the <lb/>poſition of the
        uterus is different at different pe- <pb n="352"/>
        <lb/>riods of life. In the foetus of three or four <lb/>months, the uterus is almoſt
        without, and under <lb/>the pelvis; in ſo much, that a line drawn from <lb/>the os pubis to
        the os ſacrum, falls very near the <lb/>neck of the uterus. In a child newly born, the
        <lb/>uterus falls without the level of the ſuperior ſur- <lb/>face of the os pubis. In a
        girl, from fifteen to <lb/>thirty-five years of age, the uterus is placed a- <lb/>bove the
        os pubis, and, in an old woman, it is <lb/>found very far within the pelvis. The axis of
        <lb/>the uterus is almoſt perpendicular in the foetus; <lb/>whereas, in old women, it
        appears almoſt hori- <lb/>zontal. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe differences in the poſition, our author <lb/>attributes to the developement of
        the pelvis. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He obſerves, in the <hi rend="italic">ſecond</hi> place, that the figure <lb/>of the
        uterus is different at different periods of <lb/>life. It reſembles, in ſome meaſure, a
        priſm in <lb/>the foetus, and in infants. In the adult, it is al- <lb/>moſt triangular; and
        it is irregularly rounded in <lb/>old women, even in ſuch as have never had chil- <lb/>dren.
        The cavity of the uterus varies alſo in <lb/>proportion to the different periods of life;
        but, <lb/>in order to obſerve this, it is neceſſary to clear it <lb/>from the peritonaeum
        and ligaments; on its <pb n="353"/>
        <lb/>connection with each of which, he offers a few <lb/>remarks. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The uterus is covered, through its whole <lb/>length, by a duplicature of the
        peritonaeum, <lb/>except the exterior face of the neck; and even <lb/>this part is covered
        by a reduplication of the va- <lb/>gina, more prolonged behind and below, than <lb/>it is
        before and above. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The lamina of the peritonaeum, which covers <lb/>the anterior part of the uterus, is
        folded back <lb/>near to the vagina, in ſuch a manner, as to form <lb/>two kinds of
        ligaments placed beſide the neck of <lb/>the bladder. Above, and upon the ſides, it in-
        <lb/>cludes two bundles of veſſels, and forms the <lb/>round ligaments. This anterior lamina
        ſtretches <lb/>upon the ſides of the uterus, forms the anterior <lb/>lamina of the ligamenta
        lata, and adheres to the <lb/>iliac muſcles; from whence it is reflected for- <lb/>wards,
        covers the anterior portion of the iliac <lb/>muſcle, and joins with the anterior lamina of
        the <lb/>peritonaeum. The poſterior lamina of the ute- <lb/>rus forms, by two
        reduplications, two kinds of <lb/>circular ligaments, in which Mr Sue thought he <lb/>found
        two muſcles. Theſe two ligaments em- <lb/>brace the rectum. The broad ligaments ſtretch
        <lb/>much leſs in height when the uterus is developed <pb n="354"/>
        <lb/>in women with child; the anterior and poſterior <lb/>reduplications of the peritonaeum
        are almoſt effa- <lb/>ced: So that, amongſt other uſes, theſe liga- <lb/>ments ſeem to
        aſſiſt the developements of the u- <lb/>terus. The broad ligaments divide the pelvis
        <lb/>into two anterior apartments; of which, in the <lb/>adult, the one is ſmaller than the
        other; whereas, <lb/>in infants, the two are nearly equal. This is ow- <lb/>ing to the
        different inclination of the os ſacrum, <lb/>which takes place at different periods of life. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The two membranous laminae of the liga- <lb/>ments are eaſily ſeparated. Between them
        we <lb/>find a vaſcular net-work. The uterus alſo may <lb/>be ſlipped out of the
        invelopement of the perito- <lb/>naeum, and removed out of the belly, without <lb/>opening
        the true lamina of the peritonaeum. It <lb/>is neceſſary, however, to tear certain cellular
        pro- <lb/>ductions which run into the fibres, and ſeem to <lb/>give them common ſheaths. Two
        of theſe <lb/>ſheaths are evidently ſeen in the lateral and infe- <lb/>rior parts of the
        uterus, accompanying and inclo- <lb/>ſing the uterine veſſels, in the ſame manner as the
        <lb/>capſule of the liver ſurrounds the vena portarum, <lb/> as <hi rend="italic"
          >Walaeus</hi> has remarked before <hi rend="italic">Gliſſon</hi>; to <lb/>whom, however,
        learned anatomiſts have given <lb/>the honour of the diſcovery. It is this capſule <lb/>that
        ſupports the veſſels in their convolutions, and <pb n="355"/>
        <lb/>which fixes them, by means of muſcular attach- <lb/>ments, to the proper ſubſtance of
        the uterus. Mr <lb/>Portal remarks, that the cellular ſheaths of thoſe <lb/>veſſels are
        ſometimes loaded with fat; and, in <lb/>certain dropſies of the uterus, they are filled with
        <lb/>water. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In regard to the diſcovery of the ligaments of <lb/>the uterus, Mr Portal is of
        opinion, that the an- <lb/>cients were only acquainted with four, and that
        <lb/>Hermondaville, who profeſſed anatomy in France <lb/>about the middle of the thirteenth
        century, and <lb/>whoſe ſurgery is preſerved in manuſcript in the <lb/>King's library, and
        in the library of the Sor- <lb/>bonne, was the firſt who advanced that the uterus <lb/>was
        attached by eight ligaments. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Our author returns now to ſpeak of the cavity, <lb/>which he had already obſerved to
        vary at different <lb/>periods of life. In the infant, it is formed of four <lb/><hi
          rend="italic">planes</hi>; one anterior, which has the figure of a <lb/>parallelogram; two
        lateral and poſterior, which <lb/>join one another; and a bottom, the figure of <lb/>which
        approaches to a triangle. The poſterior <lb/>part, although formed of two planes inclined to
        <lb/>one another, and which form on the back of the <lb/>uterus a projecting angle, is
        raiſed within towards <lb/>the middle. The anterior part, viewed from the <pb n="356"/>
        <lb/>ſide of the uterus, preſents a ſimilar elevation. <lb/>Betwixt the anterior and two
        poſterior planes are <lb/>two kinds of furrows, in which ſeveral projecting <lb/>circular
        lines are obſerved. At this age, the ute- <lb/>rus is thicker towards the neck than the
        bottom; <lb/>the reverſe of this happens in the adult. This <lb/>obſervation was made by Mr
        Sué. Different <lb/>projecting lines are obſerved in the internal ſur- <lb/>face. There is a
        longitudinal one in the middle <lb/>of the poſterior part, which riſes from the poſte-
        <lb/>rior ligament of the os uteri, where it is more <lb/>elevated than at the other
        extremity, which is <lb/>ſometimes forked. Sometimes, in place of one, <lb/>there are found
        two or three projecting and parallel <lb/>lines, about the middle of the poſterior part,
        <lb/>where they ſeparate, inclining towards the ſides. <lb/>From the lateral parts of theſe,
        ſeveral other pro- <lb/>jecting lines riſe, which make the tour of the ute- <lb/>rus, or
        which join to a longitudinal ſtalk, placed <lb/>ſometimes in the middle of the anterior face
        of <lb/>the uterus. Theſe appear as ſo many branches <lb/>united to one trunk, forming a
        kind of tree, <lb/>which Mr Portal thinks may be called <hi rend="italic">arbor vi-
          <lb/>vificans</hi>, to diſtinguiſh it from <hi rend="italic">arbor vitae</hi> vitae of
        <lb/>the cerebellum. Theſe lines, in a young perſon, have <lb/>a reſemblance to a branch of
        the palm-tree. Be- <pb n="357"/>
        <lb/>tween the branches, and chiefly towards the trunk, <lb/>and the os uteri, ſeveral holes
        are obſerved. <lb/>Theſe are the openings of the excretory ducts of <lb/>certain gangliforme
        bodies; from which a <lb/>viſcous matter runs out, upon ſqueezing the ſides <lb/>of the
        uterus. There is not a better way of ma- <lb/>king theſe holes appear, than by broiling a
        piece <lb/>of the ſubſtance of the uterus before a good <lb/>fire. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The <hi rend="italic">cavity</hi> of the uterus is much more contracted <lb/>in the
        adult than in the foetus or infant. The trunk <lb/>of the tree, with its branches, are
        either effaced, <lb/>or the intermediate ſubſtance is raiſed. Thro' <lb/>length of time, the
        ſides of the uterus approach <lb/>one another, which diminiſhes its cavity. Mr <lb/>Portal
        has always found in the uterus, at all ages, <lb/>the ſides thicker than the anterior or
        poſterior <lb/>part. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There are certain excreſcences that riſe on the <lb/>internal part of the uterus of old
        women, even in <lb/>thoſe who had had no children. Theſe have been <lb/>deſcribed by
        authors, but not as happening ſo <lb/>frequently as they really do. Mr Portal found
        <lb/>them in thirteen of twenty women, whoſe bodies <lb/>he had opened on purpoſe. </p>
      <pb n="358"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Our author concludes his obſervations upon <lb/>the uterus, by remarking its extreme
        irritability, <lb/>which he finds to be infinitely greater in the in- <lb/>ternal than the
        external ſurface, in the ſame man- <lb/>ner as Senac and Haller had found with regard
        <lb/>to the heart. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
