<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - White: Observations on the Medical Virtues of Lead
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>William White</persName>
            </author>
            <title>I. Observations on the Medical Virtues of Lead, by, Mr William White, F. A. S.
              Surgeon in York.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society in Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for J. Murray, No. 32. Fleet-Street</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1775</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">3</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">72-80</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW109044002</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">N036372</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v3_0072">
    <body>
      <pb n="72"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>I. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Obſervations on the Medical Virtues of Lead, by, <lb/>Mr <hi rend="roman">William
          White</hi>, F. A. S. Surgeon in <lb/>York. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">C</hi><hi rend="sc">Elsus</hi>, and Dioſcorides of Anazarba, the
        <lb/>celebrated botaniſt, who flouriſhed under <lb/>the reign of Veſpaſian, are, I think,
        the firſt who <lb/>make mention of the various preparations of <lb/>lead, as minium,
        ceruſſa, &amp;c. and, as phyſicians, <lb/>greatly extol their virtues; but they uſed them
        <lb/>only externally. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Lead hath been accuſed, and with great rea- <lb/>ſon, of being the cauſe of the colica
        pictonum, <lb/>when given internally. Its external uſe has been <lb/>alſo much ſuſpected;
        but I think upon too ſlight <lb/>grounds. I have ſeen it uſed ſo freely as a to- <pb n="73"/>
        <lb/>pic, in ulcers, burns, excoriations, &amp;c. that I can <lb/>never ſuſpect a ſmall
        plate of lead put over an iſ- <lb/>ſue, or ſitting in a new painted room, can ever
        <lb/>bring on ſymptoms of the colic of Poictu in even <lb/>the moſt irritable habits.
        However, it is now <lb/>come into univerſal uſe, and claims the moſt di- <lb/>ſtinguiſhed
        place among the topical remedies. In- <lb/>deed its effect in abating inflammation is won-
        <lb/>derful; and, with Meſſrs White, Aiken, &amp;c. I <lb/>cannot but join in eſteeming it
        equally innocent <lb/>as efficacious. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A brewer to a gentleman near this city, ſlipt <lb/>with his arm up to the ſhoulder into
        a vat of boil- <lb/>ing wort, and was ſo miſerably ſcalded, that the <lb/>cuticula came
        entirely off, from the axilla down <lb/>to his finger ends. The pain and inflammation
        <lb/>was very violent, ſo that, after a few hours, I was <lb/>ſent for. Cloths, wet in
        Goulard's aqua ſaturnina, <lb/>were directed to be wrapped about the whole <lb/>arm, and, as
        they grew dry, moiſtened a- <lb/>freſh, for the ſpace of an hour, night and morn- <lb/>ing;
        the arm was then covered with a ſaturnine <lb/>cerat, ſpread upon linen, till the time of
        bathing <lb/>again. The relief was wonderful; the poor man <lb/>really believed it was done
        by witchcraft; ſo ſud- <pb n="74"/>
        <lb/>den and effectual was the ſedative effect of the <lb/>lead experienced. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This man never found any bad effects from <lb/>the application, though uſed in large
        quantities, <lb/>and applied to ſuch a large denudated ſpace, <lb/>where the abſorption muſt
        too have been very <lb/>conſiderable. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A ſtout young man came to our hoſpital, a few <lb/>weeks ago, with a gutta ſerena. He
        got his living <lb/>by working in the lead mines, his buſineſs being <lb/>to detach the ore,
        having no concern in the clean- <lb/>ſing or melting of it. He went to his bed with his
        <lb/>ſight entire; but next morning awoke perfectly <lb/>blind, about twenty weeks ago. He
        never had <lb/>any colicky ſymptoms, or any paralytic affection. <lb/>Whether this ſtate of
        the paralyſis of the optic <lb/>nerves might have been cauſed by lead, I ſhall <lb/>leave to
        others to determine; but I never before <lb/>ſaw the retina in ſuch an abſolute ſtate of
        inſenſi- <lb/>bility. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>May not the effects of lead be underſtood from <lb/>the following conſiderations? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The living ſolids of an animal fibre are en- <lb/>dowed with a power of action, which
        is increaſed <lb/>by any irritating cauſe. This aptitude of the ani- <lb/>mal fibres to be
        acted upon by a ſtimulus, is term- <pb n="75"/>
        <lb/>ed their <hi rend="italic">irritability</hi>. In proportion to the <lb/>weakneſs of
        this power, will the effect of any ſti- <lb/>mulus to the part be leſs apparent, and the
        conſe- <lb/>quent contractions more weak and languid. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Inflammation ſeems to be only a morbid in- <lb/>creaſe of this power of action, the
        effect of an ir- <lb/>ritation more or leſs permanent and violent. Lead, <lb/>eſpecially
        when combined with an acid, hath a <lb/>ſingular effect in diminiſhing the irritability. It
        <lb/>exerts this ſedative power upon every living part <lb/>to which it is applied, both in
        its healthful and <lb/>diſeaſed ſtate. Saturnine preparations are of a <lb/>very aſtringent
        quality; hence I cannot ſuſpect <lb/>them capable of being abſorbed into the ſyſtem.
        <lb/>Would they not rather effectually conſtringe the <lb/>orifices of the abſorbent
        veſſels? We know <lb/>that chalybeates are not capable of being thus <lb/>conveyed into the
        body. It appears to me that <lb/>they cannot exert their effects upon any part of <lb/>the
        body, but in conſequence of an immediate <lb/>application. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Lead is ſaid to have a peculiar effect of exert- <lb/>ing its noxious qualities upon
        the primae viae; but <lb/>let us conſider, that, when taken into the body, it <lb/>is always
        applied in contact with thoſe parts. <lb/>May not the obſtinate colics, conſtipations, and
          <pb n="76"/>
        <lb/>palſies, ſo often the conſequences of its internal <lb/>uſe, be the effects of its
        extreme ſedative power, <lb/>rendering the inteſtines incapable of irritation from
        <lb/>their contents, the conſequence of which will be <lb/>the loſs of their periſtaltic
        motion, which will be <lb/>followed by every ſymptom of the colic of Poic- <lb/>tu? </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I am of opinion, that the preparations of lead <lb/>can never be given internally with
        propriety. The <lb/>numerous and well authenticated inſtances of <lb/>miſchief, reſulting
        from ſuch practice, demands <lb/>our particular attention to guard againſt every <lb/>means,
        by which that metal may be brought into <lb/>immediate contact of the bowels. It is a pity
        <lb/>that we are thus prevented from exhibiting a me- <lb/>dicine ſo powerfully ſedative,
        and capable of allay- <lb/>ing the inordinate actions of the living fibres in <lb/>general.
        Perhaps by ſome now unthought of com- <lb/>bination, its topical action upon the bowels may
        <lb/>be obviated or prevented. Such a mixture, I <lb/>ſhould imagine, might be found to
        anſwer ſome <lb/>important medical indications. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Fuller much recommends a gargle with ſugar <lb/>of lead; and has, if I remember right,
        been bla- <lb/>med for it. It muſt be acknowledged, that ſome <lb/>caution is neceſſary to
        be obſerved in uſing it. <pb n="77"/>
        <lb/>But I have frequently uſed a ſaturnine gargle in <lb/>an eryſipelatous inflammation of
        the fauces, with <lb/>or without aphthae, and with the greateſt ſucceſs. <lb/>We are,
        however, confined in its uſe, from many <lb/>people, children univerſally, being incapable
        of <lb/>uſing either by means of a ſyringe, or otherwise, <lb/>without ſuffering part of it
        to get down into <lb/>the ſtomach, which might be followed by <lb/>ſome diſagreeble
        conſequences. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I have always been fearful of giving lead inter- <lb/>nally, and never have yet adviſed
        it; but certain <lb/>it is, that ſome conſtitutions are much leſs liable <lb/>to ſuffer from
        it than others, proceeding from <lb/>ſome peculiarity of habit, general or topical. By
        <lb/>the latter, I mean ſome peculiar ſtate of the <lb/>nerves of the bowels, by which they
        are leſs apt <lb/>to be diſturbed or affected by ſuch medicines. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I have known repeated inſtances of a continu- <lb/>ed uſe of the tinct. ſaturnina, and
        in conſiderable <lb/>doſes, in caſes of a phthiſis pulmonalis, without <lb/>being followed
        by any ſymptoms of colic: On <lb/>the contrary, it ſeemed to act as a general ſeda-
        <lb/>tive, conſtantly abating the hectic heat and ſweats. <lb/>In one caſe, to which I
        attended particularly, it <lb/>evidently diminiſhed the irritability of the heart <pb n="78"/>
        <lb/>and arterial ſyſtem, ſeldom failing to render the <lb/>pulſe ſlower, by ten ſtrokes in
        a minute. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the contrary, I have known pain, flatulent <lb/>diſtenſions of the bowels, and
        obſtinate conſtipa- <lb/>tions, brought on by a ſingle doſe of that tincture, <lb/>and
        believe that a repetition would have been <lb/>followed by the colic of Poictu. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Saturnine topics have been much blamed, as <lb/>cauſing many bad ſymptoms; but
        probably, in <lb/>many caſes, ſuch diſagreeable effects have been <lb/>rather the
        conſequences of a retropulſion of ſome <lb/>irritating acrimony into the ſyſtem, being gene-
        <lb/>rally obſerved in children, and very irritable ha- <lb/>bits. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Many inſtances are related in authors, of the <lb/>ſpaſmodic colic being brought on by
        ſuch exter- <lb/>nal applications, and I doubt not but with ſuffici- <lb/>ent reaſon. Dr
        Baker has given ſeveral caſes of <lb/>pains in the bowels coming on, ſubſequent to
        <lb/>their uſe; but it is probable, that colica pictonum <lb/>has, at times, been confounded
        with ſome of the <lb/>other ſpecies of colica. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is now a very favourable time for obſerving, <lb/>whether the colic of Poictu, or
        many of the other <lb/>bad effects of an internal uſe of lead, can be ever <pb n="79"/>
        <lb/>produced by it, when uſed externally, as its pre- <lb/>parations are come into
        univerſal uſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I have uſed ſome gallons of the aqua ſaturnina <lb/>of Goulard; and many other
        practitioners, with <lb/>whom I have converſed upon the ſubject, all a- <lb/>gree with me in
        not knowing a ſingle inſtance of <lb/>bad conſequences induced from ſuch applications.
        <lb/>Dr Haygarth, in his letter to Dr Percival, from <lb/>a very plentiful uſe of them in
        the patients who <lb/>ſuffered by the accident at Cheſter, never obſer- <lb/>ved the
        ſlighteſt ſymptom of colic or palſy, tho' <lb/>he was particularly attentive to that very
        ſub- <lb/>ject. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Being upon the ſubject of ſedatives, among <lb/>which the action of cold holds a
        diſtinguiſhed <lb/>rank, an experiment juſt occurs to my mind, <lb/>which I performed after
        Dr Franklin. I wet the <lb/>bulb of Fahrenheit's thermometer with aether, <lb/>and quickened
        the evaporation, by blowing upon <lb/>it with a pair of bellows (done by an aſſiſtant); and
        <lb/>this being continued alternately, for a quarter of <lb/>an hour, the mercury fell from
        54 to 28 degrees; <lb/>or 4 degrees below the freezing point, my finger <lb/>being at laſt
        quite benumbed with the cold. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Might not this be a commodious way of ap- <lb/>plying cold topically in ſome diſorders,
        as in ſu- <pb n="80"/>
        <lb/>perficial inflammations from an external cause, <lb/>the occaſional cauſe being
        previouſly removed, or <lb/>in ſome kinds of headach? &amp;c. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The experiment requires a very pure aether. <lb/>I tried it in vain with ſome that was
        reckoned ve- <lb/>ry good; but I imagine it had been adulterated <lb/>with ſome kind of
        eſſential oil, which hindered <lb/>the evaporation, and rendered the experiment
        <lb/>fruitleſs. By continuing the proceſs, a much <lb/>greater degree of cold may be
        generated. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
