<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Dease: Observations on Venereal Warts</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>William Dease</persName>
            </author>
            <title>IV. Observations on Venereal Warts. By Mr William Dease, Surgeon, Dublin.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society in Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for J. Murray, No, 32, Fleet-street</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1776</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">4</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">335-341</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CB132087767</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T220329</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v4_0335">
    <body>
      <pb n="335"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>IV. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Obſervations on Venereal Warts. By Mr <hi rend="roman">William <lb/>Deaſe</hi>,
        Surgeon, <hi rend="roman">Dublin</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>MONG the many obſtinate complaints <lb/>that accompany venereal
        infections, I do <lb/>not know any more hard, ſometimes, to remove, <lb/>than venereal
        warts, ſo as not to appear again; <lb/>nor do I know any caſe in which the perſiſting
        <lb/>too long in a courſe of mercurials is attended <lb/>with worſe conſequences; of which
        the following <lb/>caſes are ſtrong examples. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I. A young gentleman, ſometime in 1772, <lb/>contracted a clap, for which, I believe,
        he under- <pb n="336"/>
        <lb/>went no regular treatment. Three months af- <lb/>ter, he came to me for advice about an
        abſceſs on <lb/>the verge of the anus. He told me, that, before <lb/>it appeared, he had a
        ſwelling in the groin, which <lb/>went back. As the abſceſs was full of matter, I
        <lb/>opened it, and finding the rectum thin and bare, <lb/>I ſimply divided it. Every thing
        went on well; <lb/>after the ſuppuration was compleatly formed, as <lb/>there was a ſtrong
        preſumption he was poxed, I <lb/>adviſed him to rub in a dram of mercurial oint- <lb/>ment
        every ſecond night; but with this he would <lb/>not comply; ſo I put him on a courſe of the
        mer- <lb/>curial pill, with a decoction of ſarſaparilla. In <lb/>three weeks he ſeemed quite
        well; but then he <lb/>ſhewed me, for the firſt time, three or four warts <lb/>he had behind
        the glans penis. I rubbed them <lb/>down with lunar cauſtic, and enjoined him to uſe,
        <lb/>at leaſt for three weeks more, the pills and decoc- <lb/>tion. The warts diſappeared,
        as he followed my <lb/>advice; and, after that, he went into the country, <lb/>where he ſoon
        recovered his former robuſt habit <lb/>of body. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Four months after, he came to me, and ſhewed <lb/>me the warts grown again; but ſaid he
        never en- <lb/>joyed better health, and would take no medicine, <lb/>but begged I would give
        him ſome cauſtic, which <pb n="337"/>
        <lb/>I did; and thereby he occaſionally took them <lb/>down, and continued in perfect health
        for a year, <lb/>from the time I firſt had the care of him. But <lb/>then another abſceſs,
        on the other ſide of the anus, <lb/>ſimilar to the first, appeared, which I opened in
        <lb/>the ſame manner I had done before. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Another gentleman of the profeſſion was now <lb/>called in, and, in conſultation, was
        of opinion <lb/>the patient was ſtill poxed, and that it was ab- <lb/>ſolutely neceſſary he
        ſhould be ſalivated. I urged, <lb/>that, though there was a probability it might be <lb/>ſo,
        yet, as I had often ſeen warts remain after re- <lb/>peated ſalivations, when it might be
        preſumed <lb/>the virus was ſubdued, and the complaint but lo- <lb/>cal; and, as our patient
        had, at preſent, a dry <lb/>huſky cough and hoarſeneſs, it would be better <lb/>to treat him
        in a more gentle manner, and wait <lb/>the effect. This advice was not received, and
        <lb/>his friends put him under the care of the other <lb/>gentleman, who removed him to a
        nurſekeeper's, <lb/>where he had him nine weeks in a ſalivation. <lb/>His ſore ſoon healed,
        but the warts remained un- <lb/>altered; his ſtrength was much exhauſted, and, <lb/>the laſt
        week, he began to ſpit blood. It was now <lb/>found, altho' too late, that mercurials would
        not <lb/>do; and, as the laſt reſource, he was ſent to <pb n="338"/>
        <lb/>Wicklow, it being the beginning of May, to drink <lb/>goats whey; but ſpitting of pus
        ſoon ſucceeded <lb/>to that of blood, attended with a conſtant pain <lb/>in the breaſt,
        colliquative ſweats, purgings at <lb/>times, &amp;c. Three weeks before he died, I ſaw
        <lb/>him, and he ſhewed me the warts ſtill unchanged. <lb/>He died, to the laſt degree
        conſumptive, in Au- <lb/>guſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>II. In 1772, A young man, about twenty-one <lb/>or twenty-two, in company with ſome
        other <lb/>young men, being all drunk, lay with a common <lb/>proſtitute. They were all
        diſeaſed in conſe- <lb/>quence. He had a troubleſome heat in making <lb/>urine, but no
        running, and ſoon after a number <lb/>of warts appeared on the glans, and behind it. <lb/>He
        went from one practitioner to another, in the <lb/>country, and took a variety of
        mercurials, with- <lb/>out any alteration, but when he took them down <lb/>by cauſtic; which
        produced but a temporary <lb/>effect, as they ſoon ſprung up afreſh. He at laſt <lb/>came up
        to Dublin to have my advice: He had <lb/>now been for a year diſeaſed, and never had any
        <lb/>other venereal appearance; his conſtitution ſeem- <lb/>ed only affected by the great
        quantity of medi- <lb/>cine he had taken. </p>
      <pb n="339"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As there ſeemed to be no doubt of his being <lb/>poxed, the different treatments he
        underwent, <lb/>having been by no means regular, I adviſed him <lb/>to ſtay under my care
        for ſome time, to which <lb/>he conſented. I began with bleeding and gentle <lb/>purging;
        and put him on a ſoft mild diet, &amp;c. <lb/>and made him take the warm bath. After
        <lb/>twelve days preparation, during which time he <lb/>bathed twelve times, I began with
        the mercurial <lb/>frictions, uſing only a dram of ointment each <lb/>time; and he continued
        them ſo as not to let the <lb/>mercury affect his mouth; he left the warts <lb/>without any
        application, and waited the event. <lb/>In ſix weeks, not finding them likely to go off,
        <lb/>I rubbed them with the lunar cauſtic; but in a <lb/>little time they grew up as big as
        ever. I then <lb/>had recourse to the lapis infernalis, and made the <lb/>whole interior
        part of the prepuce, and exterior <lb/>of the glans ſlough off; but ſtill they grew up
        <lb/>again; and, after he had been under my care for <lb/>ten weeks, during which time he
        rubbed in five <lb/>ounces of ointment, the two laſt of which made <lb/>him ſpit, to ſee the
        effect, I was obliged to ſend <lb/>him into the country, in danger of a hectic, <lb/>the
        warts being as large as ever. </p>
      <pb n="340"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>With goats whey, and a milk diet, he recover- <lb/>ed in a ſhort time; but the
        uneaſineſs of mind he <lb/>ſuffered, made him apply to practitioners in the <lb/>country,
        when he took, as he told me, a vaſt <lb/>quantity of pills, &amp;c. He came up to Dublin
        <lb/>once more, after being ten months in the coun- <lb/>try; it was in June, and he was
        much in the ſame <lb/>ſituation as when I firſt ſaw him, affected with <lb/>no other
        complaint but the warts. In conſulta- <lb/>tion with two gentlemen of the profeſſion, it was
        <lb/>agreed he ſhould paſs, after the neceſſary prepara- <lb/>tions, through a courſe of
        frictions, which was <lb/>continued for eight weeks without having much <lb/>effect on his
        mouth. What moſt encouraged us <lb/>was, that the firſt four weeks, the warts ſeemed <lb/>to
        wither and drop off, but, in the latter end, <lb/>grew up a freſh. We tried every kind of
        eſ- <lb/>carotic, ſtrong and weak, thoſe mentioned in the <lb/>Medical Obſervations,
        mercurial purges, &amp;c. to <lb/>no purpoſe. At length we left them off, and put <lb/>him
        on the extract of cicuta, and a light decoction <lb/>of bark. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He now began, after four months from the <lb/>time he came up to town, to grow weak,
        ſweat <lb/>at night, and ſpit ſome blood. He was very <lb/>much emaciated, and loſt his
        appetite, his legs <lb/>ſwelled, and his pulſe was extremely quick. Re- <pb n="341"/>
        <lb/>course was had in vain to aſſes milk, Seltzer wa- <lb/>ter, Peruvian bark, &amp;c. He
        went, in October <lb/>1774, to the country, and died in December fol- <lb/>lowing,
        conſumptive, the warts remaining as large <lb/>as ever. The lungs in both theſe patients
        ſeem- <lb/>ed to be the parts chiefly affected. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>III. A coachman, after ſome claps, not re- <lb/>gularly treated, had warts behind the
        glans, and <lb/>at the opening of the meatus urinarius. He <lb/>applied to me at St
        Nicholas's Hoſpital, in 1770, <lb/>where he was twice ſalivated that year, and took <lb/>a
        variety of medicines; he had them often con- <lb/>ſumed by cauſtic; but ſtill they are at
        preſent, <lb/>1776, as big as they were when I ſaw them firſt. <lb/>He rubs them down, from
        time to time, with <lb/>lunar cauſtic, is robuſt and ſtrong, enjoys excel- <lb/>lent health,
        has been married theſe four years, <lb/>and has had three healthy children. The mo-
        <lb/>ther had never the leaſt complaint, and he has ta- <lb/>ken no kind of medicine ſince
        the firſt year. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
