<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Marcard: The History of a case of the Morbus Niger</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Henry Marcard</persName>
            </author>
            <title>I. The History of a case of the Morbus Niger, with some Remarks on the effects of
              Camphor. By Dr Henry Marcard, Physician at Hannover.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society in Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for J. Murray, No, 32, Fleet-street</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1776</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">4</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">203-210</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CB132087767</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T220329</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v4_0203">
    <body>
      <pb n="203"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>I. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>The Hiſtory of a caſe of the Morbus Niger, with <lb/>ſome Remarks on the effects of
        Camphor. By <lb/>Dr <hi rend="roman">Henry Marcard</hi>, Phyſician at <hi rend="roman"
          >Hannover</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Woman of a very deformed crooked ſhape, <lb/>about 48 years of
        age, had complained, <lb/>many years ago, of very ſevere pains about her <lb/>ſtomach,
        attacking by intervals, and commonly <lb/>accompanied with belching, and a rejection of the
        <lb/>food, or, if ſhe had taken none, of an inſipid <lb/>lymph. The diſorder was allowed to
        be of the <lb/>hyſteric kind, and treated as ſuch, there being no <lb/>apparent reaſon to
        impute it to any other cauſe. </p>
      <pb n="204"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 16th of February 1773, when I was <lb/>called for, I was told that ſhe was then
        attacked <lb/>with thoſe pains, to a degree never before expe- <lb/>rienced; that ſhe had
        vomited up ſome black <lb/>ſtuff like coagulated blood. I found no fever; <lb/>ſhe had great
        nauſea; her tongue was not at all <lb/>furred; ſhe had moſt excrutiating pains in the
        <lb/>hypogaſtric region, and was much affected with <lb/>anxiety. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I ſhould have given her a vomit; but durſt not <lb/>venture upon it, from the
        apprehenſion that the <lb/>rejection of the black matter might be a ſort of <lb/>vomitus
        cruentus, as it afterwards proved not to <lb/>be; and beſides, as it would have been againſt
        <lb/>the common rule, <hi rend="italic">Gibboſis nulla ſunt exhibenda <lb/>vomitoria</hi>;
        which, by the bye, is a principle, I <lb/>think, far too generally pronounced; and there
        <lb/>is no doubt this very woman might have taken <lb/>a vomit with great ſafety, as ſhe
        brought forth, <lb/>notwithſtanding her irregular ſhape, and even the <lb/>apparent
        deformity of her pelvis, ſix healthy chil- <lb/>dren, then all alive. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thinking, however, ſome evacuation proper, <lb/>I ordered ſomething to open the body,
        and the <lb/>emplaſtrum de hyoſciamo to be laid over her bel- <pb n="205"/>
        <lb/>ly. The following day ſhe was remarkably bet- <lb/>ter, and continued ſo all the 18th. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 19th, at once, aroſe a ſevere fever; the <lb/>pains in the region of the ſtomach
        became intole- <lb/>rable; ſhe was conſtantly vomiting, without bring- <lb/>ing up any thing
        particular, and had no ſtools. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I ordered ten ounces of blood to be taken away; <lb/>frequent clyſters, compoſed of
        emollient and ſalt, <lb/>to be given; a bladder with warm water to be laid <lb/>upon her
        ſtomach, and a mixture of lemon juice <lb/>and <hi rend="italic">ſal abſiynthii</hi> to be
        taken ſeveral times du- <lb/>ring the efferveſcence. Towards night I found <lb/>the heat
        abated; ſhe vomited only by intervals of <lb/>an hour, and the clyſters brought away, now
        and <lb/>then, ſomewhat more of the coagulated blood, <lb/>as the friends of the patient
        ſtiled it, which they <lb/>had omitted to keep for my examination. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 21ſt, in the afternoon, I was told that <lb/>the patient was in a dying
        condition, the pains <lb/>being augmented to ſuch a degree, as to produce <lb/>convulſions
        and a cold ſweat. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I own I was now quite at a loſs what to do, <lb/>being entirely ignorant from what
        cauſe theſe <lb/>heavy ſymptoms could riſe. And though I ſuſpect- <lb/>ed the black ſtuff
        might be the origin, yet I <lb/>knew ſo little about its nature, that even that <pb n="206"/>
        <lb/>could give me no directions at all. I reſolved at <lb/>laſt to preſcribe three grains
        of camphor every <lb/>four hours, in an emulſion, with ſome nitre, and a <lb/>good deal of
        ſyrup of white popies, and to order a <lb/>large bliſter upon the part affected. On the
        <lb/>ſame night, about eight o'clock, I was called a- <lb/>gain, and was told that the
        patient, not long af- <lb/>ter having taken the emulſion, began to vomit in <lb/>a moſt
        ſhocking manner; and that the people a- <lb/>bout her really believed ſhe puked moſt part
        <lb/>of her guts away, ſuch ſtrange matters as they <lb/>thought were to be obſerved in what
        ſhe threw <lb/>up. Before my arrival, the vomiting had ceaſed; <lb/>but a large quantity, at
        leaſt ſixteen ounces, of the <lb/>black ſtuff was collected for my examination. <lb/>Upon
        inquiry, I found it to be a matter ſome- <lb/>what like poultice, but leſs adherent; it was
        quite <lb/>black, neither inclining to the red nor to the <lb/>yellow, being neither blood
        nor gall. I put a lit- <lb/>tle of it upon white paper; and, after it was rub- <lb/>bed upon
        the paper, it went clear off from the ſheet <lb/>without colouring it, or leaving any mark
        behind <lb/>beſides moiſture. The patient ſaid, that it had no <lb/>particular taſte. I have
        never ſeen any matter <lb/>more reſembling this, than the contents of a <hi rend="italic"
          >tu- <lb/>mor cyſticus</hi>, an <hi rend="italic">atheroma</hi>, which I found once in <pb
          n="207"/>
        <lb/>the dead body of an old man, juſt under the <lb/>ſpleen. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The patient was much relieved by this evacu- <lb/><choice>
          <corr>ation</corr>
          <sic>tion</sic>
        </choice>, though ſhe became extremely weak; ſhe <lb/>recovered very ſlowly, but did never
        vomit again. <lb/>As often as ſhe complained of nauſea and pains, <lb/>I ordered her
        purgatives and clyſters, and heard <lb/>that they frequently brought off ſomewhat more
        <lb/>of the black matter, with apparent relief. She <lb/>fell afterwards into a ſlight
        fever, and ſome other <lb/>little complaints, of which it is unneceſſary to <lb/>give any
        particular account; but, after two <lb/>months from the beginning of her illneſs, ſhe
        <lb/>was intirely recovered, and had never again an <lb/>attack of her old complaint, the
        pains. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I do not pretend to determine whether this <lb/>ſtuff came from the ſpleen, by means of
        the <hi rend="italic">vaſa <lb/>brevia</hi>, or whether, perhaps, a <hi rend="italic">tumor
          cyſticus</hi> near <lb/>the ſtomach furniſhed the matter. This caſe <hi rend="italic"
          >may</hi>
        <lb/>probably fall under that ſpecies <hi rend="italic">morbi nigri Hip- <lb/>pocratis</hi>,
        whereof he ſays: <q rend="italic">Aeger vigium vomit re- <lb/>luti foecem </q>; but is not
        to be determined, as he <lb/>gives no further deſcription of that ſpecies. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I ſhall forbear mentioning any authors who <lb/>have ſeen ſimilar caſes that proved, I
        find, com- <lb/>monly fatal. One obſervation, however, I cannot <lb/>help adding, concerning
        the effect of camphor <pb n="208"/>
        <lb/>in the preſent caſe. All the <hi rend="italic">vires vitae</hi> ſeemed to <lb/>have
        undergone a very hard ſtruggle by the time <lb/>that I reſolved to try the effect of
        camphor, <lb/>and, ſoon after it was taken, all was brought a- <lb/>bout. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Not long ago, I have ſeen an effect of camphor <lb/>pretty much reſembling this one. A
        woman was <lb/>taken ill of a pleuriſy of the bilious kind. <lb/>After about ſeven days, the
        pleuritic ſymptoms <lb/>diſappeared, and the remaining diſorder was, as <lb/>far as I could
        gueſs, merely bilious. Beſides a- <lb/>cids, I ordered frequent purgatives, and gave
        <lb/>them as ſtrong as I durſt venture upon. They <lb/>had always the deſired effect,
        cauſing ſome ſtools <lb/>every day; but there was no change to the better; <lb/>ſhe rather
        became weaker and weaker. I, how- <lb/>ever, continued for ſome days in the ſame way.
        <lb/>On the 15th day of her illneſs, I found the pa- <lb/>tient very low; ſhe could not well
        ſit in her bed; <lb/>her pulſe was hardly to be felt; though ſhe was <lb/>not light headed,
        ſhe could neither think nor <lb/>ſpeak without great difficulty. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I thought it now neceſſary to try another way, <lb/>and gave her four grains of
        camphor, to be ta- <lb/>ken in four pills, every third hour; and beſides, <pb n="209"/>
        <lb/>ordered ſome wine. Upon my calling again at <lb/>night, the huſband of the patient told
        me that <lb/>theſe few pills had proved very efficacious; and, <lb/>upon inquiry, I was not
        a little ſurpriſed to find, <lb/>that, after the firſt doſe, the patient had ſix ſtools
        <lb/>of green viſcous ſtinking excrements; and that, <lb/>after the ſecond doſe, there
        followed three more; <lb/>after which ſhe found herſelf a little better. From <lb/>that time
        ſhe began to mend; ſhe recovered af- <lb/>terwards, but extremely ſlowly. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As camphor has neither faculties to effect vo- <lb/>miting nor purging, it is ſomewhat
        difficult to <lb/>diſcover what cauſe the effects could be derived <lb/>from, which it
        exerted in theſe two caſes. Nor <lb/>ſhall I preſume to determine whether it acted
        <lb/>thus, by adding to the ſtimulus of the morbid <lb/>matter, or by adding to the
        irritability of the parts, <lb/>or rather by ſupporting the <hi rend="italic">vires totius
          corporis</hi>: <lb/>Be that as it may, this concluſion ſeems very ob- <lb/>vious, that
        camphor might prove many times an <lb/>excellent remedy when the patient grows weak,
        <lb/>whilſt nature intends a ſalutary evacuation; <lb/>though certainly the effects can
        never be ſo evi- <lb/>dent when the evacuation is to come from other <lb/>excretory organs
        than the <hi rend="italic">primae viae</hi>; when the <pb n="210"/>
        <lb/>morbid matter is to be eliminated by inſenſible <lb/>perſpiration, by urine, ſweat, or
        eruptions. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
