<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Scott: Violent Asthmatic Fits, occasioned by the effluvia of
          Ipecacuanha</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>William Scott</persName>
            </author>
            <title>II. Violent Asthmatic Fits, occasioned by the effluvia of Ipecacuanha; by William
              Scott, M. D. of Stamfordham, Northumberland. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society in Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for J. Murray, No, 32, Fleet-street</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1776</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">4</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">75-81</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CB132087767</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T220329</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v4_0075">
    <body>
      <pb n="75"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>II. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Violent Aſthmatic Fits, occaſioned by the effluvia <lb/>of Ipecacuanha; by <hi
          rend="roman">William Scott, M. D.</hi> of <lb/>Stamfordham, Northumberland. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>RS S— of Stamfordham in Northumber- <lb/>land, married a perſon
        of the medical <lb/>faculty in the year 1759, being then about 26 <lb/>years of age. She had
        been always remarka- <lb/>bly healthy before that period, and quite free <lb/>from all
        nervous or other complaints, except a <lb/>trifling headach that uſed to affect her temples
        <lb/>and forehead, ſometimes for a night or ſo, about <lb/>the time of her menſtruation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The firſt year or two after her marriage, ſhe <lb/>enjoyed her uſual good health and
        ſpirits in ge- <lb/>neral; but ſometimes ſhe was afflicted with a <lb/>very troubleſome
        ſhortneſs of breathing, attend- <lb/>ed with a remarkable ſtricture about her throat
        <lb/>and breaſt, and with a particular kind of whee- <lb/>zing noiſe. Theſe fits came on
        very ſuddenly, <lb/>and without any exciting cauſe that at firſt <lb/>could be aſſigned.
        They were often ſo violent, <lb/>as to threaten immediate ſuffocation. They laſted <pb
          n="76"/>
        <lb/>ſometimes for a ſhorter, and ſometimes for a longer <lb/>time, but, in general, went
        off in two or three <lb/>days, and commonly with a ſpitting of a tough <lb/>phlegm, wh:ch
        ſhe ſaid had a diſagreeable metal- <lb/>lic taſte. When theſe fits were off, ſhe enjoyed
        <lb/>her uſual good health and ſpirits. She had chil- <lb/>dren, but ſuffered as little as
        any woman could <lb/>do, either in breeding or lying-in; and it was <lb/>not obſerved that
        ſhe was more ſubject to thoſe <lb/>fits when with child, than at other times. She <lb/>was
        blooded, and took ſome common pectoral <lb/>medicines for them; but without any benefit. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About a year and a half, or two years after <lb/>her marriage, ſhe told her huſband
        that ſhe had <lb/>obſerved theſe fits had always attacked her when <lb/>any ipecacuanha was
        powdered in his ſhop, and <lb/>that ſhe was certain the effluvia of that medicine
        <lb/>immediately brought them on. This was look- <lb/>ed on at firſt as a fancy, and little
        regard paid to <lb/>it for ſome time. However, frequently after this, <lb/>when any of that
        medicine was powdering or put- <lb/>ting up, ſhe uſed immediately to call out, per-
        <lb/>haps from a different room, that ſhe found the <lb/>ipecacuanha, and that they would
        ſee her imme- <lb/>diately affected by it. This I and ſeveral others <lb/>ſaw frequently
        happen, as ſhe had ſaid; ſo that <pb n="77"/>
        <lb/>we were at laſt convinced, to a demonſtration, <lb/>that the effluvia of the medicine,
        ſome how or <lb/>other, ſo affected her nerves, as to bring on a <lb/>very great and
        remarkable degree of ſpaſm, all <lb/>about her throat and breaſt. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having thus had ſeveral repeated proofs of the <lb/>effects the medicine had upon her,
        great precau- <lb/>tion was therefore taken for ſeveral years, never <lb/>to pound any of
        it, but to purchaſe it powdered; <lb/>and alſo care was taken, when weighing or put-
        <lb/>ting any of it up, to ſend her out of the way, or <lb/>to ſome diſtant part of the
        houſe. By theſe <lb/>means, ſhe was kept pretty clear of it for ſeven <lb/>or eight years
        together; during which time ſhe <lb/>enjoyed perfect good health. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Betwixt nine and ten o'clock in the evening <lb/>June 3d 1775, her huſband happening to
        have <lb/>got a quantity of the pulv. ipecacuanha home, <lb/>without conſidering, opened it
        out, and put it in- <lb/>to a bottle: His wife was not far off at the time, <lb/>and then in
        perfect health. Almoſt before it was <lb/>got quite put into the bottle, ſhe called out that
        <lb/>ſhe felt the ipecacuanha affect her throat, on <lb/>which ſhe was immediately ſeized
        with a ſtricture <lb/>upon her breaſt, and a difficulty of breathing. <lb/>She was adviſed
        to walk out into the air, to try if <pb n="78"/>
        <lb/>that would put it off, but it had little or no effect; <lb/>ſhe went to bed ſome little
        time afterwards, was <lb/>exceedingly ill all night, and betwixt two and <lb/>three o'clock
        next morning I ſaw her, when <lb/>ſhe was gaſping for breath at a window, was <lb/>as pale
        as death, her pulſe ſcarce to be felt, <lb/>and, in ſhort, ſeemed evidently to be in the ut-
        <lb/>moſt immediate danger of ſuffocation. She had <lb/>ſeven or eight ounces of blood taken
        from her <lb/>arm; her feet put into warm water; an anodyne <lb/>draught, with ſeven or
        eight drops of laudanum, <lb/>given her; and ſhe took frequently a table ſpoon- <lb/>ful of
        oil of almonds. None of theſe ſeemed to <lb/>have any effect, and ſhe continued much in the
        <lb/>ſame way, with few or no intervals of eaſe, till <lb/>about nine o'clock that morning;
        when, being in <lb/>a manner almoſt exhauſted, ſhe fell into a kind <lb/>of diſturbed ſleep,
        the difficulty of breathing, with <lb/>a wheezing noiſe, ſtill continuing but little aba-
        <lb/>ted. She ſlept ſome little time, and got out of bed <lb/>again about eleven o'clock
        that forenoon, her <lb/>breathing being ſtill very difficult, and her eyes <lb/>looked red
        and a little inflamed. After ſhe got <lb/>up, ſhe became eaſier towards the afternoon, and
        <lb/>it was then ſuppoſed it would go off. Dr Brown, <lb/>an eminent phyſician of Newcaſtle
        upon Tyne, <pb n="79"/>
        <lb/>happening to be in the neighbourhood, called up- <lb/>on Mrs S.; and being told what
        had happened, <lb/>ſaid, he had known a caſe pretty much ſimilar <lb/>from the ſame cauſe;
        and hoped, as ſhe then <lb/>ſeemed better, it would ſoon go off. He recom- <lb/>mended to
        her riding out as ſoon as ſhe was able, <lb/>and to be kept open. Towards bed-time the
        <lb/>ſame evening, the difficulty of breathing return- <lb/>ed, and ſhe was again
        exceedingly ill all night; <lb/>had flannel cloths wrung out of warm water ap- <lb/>plied to
        her feet, breaſt, and throat, with little or <lb/>no advantage; was blooded again about
        ſeven <lb/>o'clock next morning, and had alſo a bliſter ap- <lb/>plied to the back part of
        her neck; ſtill conti- <lb/>nuing now and then a ſpoonful of the oil of al- <lb/>monds. She
        again fell upon ſome ſleep about nine <lb/>in the morning, and continued in bed till betwixt
        <lb/>eleven and twelve; ſhe got up, and was again a <lb/>little eaſier during the day, but
        at night was as bad <lb/>as ever. The ſame ſcene was continued for <lb/>eight days and
        nights ſucceſſively; that is, ſhe <lb/>was generally a little eaſier from about eleven
        <lb/>o'clock in the forenoon, although ſtill far from <lb/>well, till towards ten or eleven
        o'clock at night, <lb/>when the ſhortneſs of breathing always returned <lb/>very violently.
        However, after eight days, ſhe <pb n="80"/>
        <lb/>began to get ſome better reſt at night; the <lb/>aſthmatic fits were neither ſo long
        nor ſo violent; <lb/>and, about fourteen days from the accident, they <lb/>were almoſt
        entirely gone off. Although ſhe is <lb/>now in very good health, ſhe has not yet quite re-
        <lb/>covered her uſual fleſh, ſtrength, and colour. Be- <lb/>ſides the above mentioned
        medicines, ſhe took at <lb/>times, during the firſt eight days, ſmall quantities <lb/>of an
        emulſion of ſpermaceti, lac. ammoniacum, <lb/>and ſucc. liquorit.; had a doſe of cooling
        phyſic; <lb/>rode and walked out a little ſometimes; had a <lb/>few anodyne draughts, with
        ſeven or eight drops <lb/>of laudanum; but it could not be obſerved that <lb/>ſhe got any
        benefit from any of them, except that <lb/>ſhe ſometimes thought the oil of almonds gave
        <lb/>her a little eaſe. She had a ſhow of the menſes <lb/>four or five days after the
        accident, although it <lb/>was then only about the middle of the uſual pe- <lb/>riod; ſhe
        coughed up at times ſome ſmall quanti- <lb/>ties of blood, and had alſo ſome mixed with her
        <lb/>ſtools and urine. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The reaſon why the laudanum, the moſt effec- <lb/>tual and univerſal antiſpalmodic, was
        uſed in ſuch <lb/>ſmall quantities, was, that it was known before, <lb/>that ſhe could never
        bear above eight or nine <lb/>drops of it, as the common doſe uſed to affect <pb n="81"/>
        <lb/>her with violent ſickneſs at ſtomach, giddineſs, <lb/>and pain in her head, to ſo great
        a degree, that, <lb/>for ſome years paſt, ſhe neither would take, nor <lb/>durſt her huſband
        adminiſter, a larger doſe to her. <lb/>At the time the above accident happened, ſhe was
        <lb/>not with child, nor had ſhe had any for ſome years <lb/>before. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The above effects of ipecacuanha I believe very <lb/>ſeldom happen, and, no doubt,
        ariſe from ſome <lb/>peculiarity of conſtitution. Medical writers, at <lb/>leaſt as far as I
        can recollect, ſeem to have taken <lb/>little or no notice of its ever producing ſuch an
        <lb/>effect. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr Leighton, a very reputable ſurgeon-apo- <lb/>thecary in Newcaſtle, told me, that the
        effluvia <lb/>of ipecacuanha had the very ſame effect upon his <lb/>wife, as it is above
        deſcribed to have upon Mrs <lb/>S.; and that he had once, in particular, very <lb/>near loſt
        her, from having ſome of it powdered <lb/>in his ſhop. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ipecacuanha that had the above effects <lb/>upon Mrs S. was the common officinal
        aſh-co- <lb/>loured, or grey kind. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
