<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - White: The History of a Case of Hieranosos successfully treated by the
          Flowers of Zinc</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>William White</persName>
            </author>
            <title>I. The History of a Case of Hieranosos successfully treated by the Flowers of
              Zinc. By Dr William White, Physician at York. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society in Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for J. Murray, No, 32, Fleet-street</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1776</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">4</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">326-331</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CB132087767</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T220329</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v4_0326">
    <body>
      <pb n="326"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>I. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>The Hiſtory of a Caſe of Hieranoſos ſucceſsfully <lb/>treated by the Flowers of Zinc.
        By Dr <hi rend="roman">Wil- <lb/>liam White</hi>, Phyſician at <hi rend="roman">York</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>RS S. a lady of about 42 years of age, <lb/>luſty, and, to
        appearance, of a very <lb/>healthy habit, ſent to deſire my aſſiſtance, and <lb/>gave me the
        following account of herſelf. She <lb/>always had a very weak ſyſtem of nerves; any
        <lb/>ſudden ſurpriſe will render her ſpeechleſs for an <lb/>hour or two, as I myſelf have
        ſeen. An emetic, <lb/>which ſhe is very often neceſſitated to take on <lb/>account of
        violent nauſeas and vertigo, which on- <lb/>ly give way after quitting a great quantity of
          <pb n="327"/>
        <lb/>phlegm from her ſtomach, always had that ef- <lb/>fect. As ſhe could not live without
        frequent e- <lb/>metics, and, at the ſame time, dreaded their <lb/>conſtant effect, ſhe
        deſired me to try ſome medi- <lb/>cine of another kind; at length I found that the
        <lb/>acetum ſcilliticum had a happy effect. She often <lb/>takes it, and it is never
        followed by any degree of <lb/>aphonia. Such is the peculiarity of this lady's
        <lb/>conſtitution, that the gum guaiacum, in whatever <lb/>form, always is followed by loſs
        of ſight for ſome <lb/>hours, by which effect ſhe unerringly knows <lb/>when it has been
        given her, however diſguiſed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>She had good health till the eleventh year of <lb/>her age, and was then taken with the
        chorea <lb/>ſancti viti, which held her a long time. About <lb/>ſixteen ſhe was ſeized with
        the hieranoſos, which, <lb/>notwithſtanding the advice of three phyſicians at <lb/>home, and
        many elſewhere, continued inceſſantly <lb/>for three years. She was then reduced to an ex-
        <lb/>treme degree of weakneſs, and paſt any hopes of <lb/>recovery, her diſorder being ſo
        ſingular, as to <lb/>terrify her friends, who deſired her death, as the <lb/>only releaſe
        from her ſufferings. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>All the claſs of nervous medicines were <lb/>repeatedly tried, muſk, opium, caſtor,
        cam- <lb/>phor, valerian, the cortex, chalybeates, cold <pb n="328"/>
        <lb/>and hot bathing, &amp;c. A ptyaliſm was raiſed with <lb/>calomel, without any effect.
        Iſſues were cut in <lb/>both legs and arms; bliſters alone gave her relief, <lb/>and that
        only for a ſhort time, during the ſerous <lb/>diſcharge. After three years the diſeaſe
        gradu- <lb/>ally abated, by taking ſome pills of Ward's. I <lb/>have ſeen her ſeveral times
        affected with it in a <lb/>ſlight degree for a few hours, after any thing <lb/>which hurries
        her ſpirits. This ſhe patiently ſuf- <lb/>fered, as every thing had been done which me-
        <lb/>dicine could afford her. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In November ſhe began to be much worſe <lb/>than uſual; and, from what ſhe could
        recollect <lb/>of her former ſufferings, thought ſhe was going <lb/>quickly to be as bad as
        in her firſt attack; ſend- <lb/>ing for me, I obſerved as follows. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Complains of a violent pain in the right ſide <lb/>of her face, and univerſal erratic
        pains and ſore- <lb/>neſs. A ſcorching heat all over the ſkin, except <lb/>her feet up to
        the ancles, which are as cold as <lb/>marble. Pulſe not quickened, but full; mouth <lb/>dry,
        but no great thirſt; body coſtive, which is <lb/>indeed her natural habit, ſo as to oblige
        her to <lb/>the frequent uſe of magneſia. Regular as to the <lb/>menſes, the return of which
        ſhe expects in five or <pb n="329"/>
        <lb/>ſix days. Appetite good, rather voracious; but <lb/>her ſpirits are always low after a
        full meal, eſpe- <lb/>cially dinner. Has a violent pain in the loins, <lb/>which often
        ſhifts into firſt one hip, then the o- <lb/>ther; the leg of which ſide is then affected
        with <lb/>ſtupor and numbneſs, ſo that ſhe drags it after in <lb/>walking. Faulters in her
        ſpeech at times, but <lb/>this continues not long. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>All the muſcles in her body in ſtrong convulſive <lb/>motions, not all at the ſame
        time, but ſucceſſively; <lb/>e. g. her face is violently affected, noſe, eyelids,
        <lb/>&amp;c. and her whole head, which is thrown violent- <lb/>ly backward, and often
        twitched from one ſide <lb/>to the other, with violent pain. From hence it <lb/>removes into
        the arms, firſt one, then the other; <lb/>theſe being deſerted, one, or both legs immedi-
        <lb/>ately become convulſed with violent and inceſſant <lb/>motions. Thus, all the external
        parts of her body <lb/>are, by turns, affected. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>She is all the time perfectly ſenſible, and knows <lb/>what limb is going to be next
        affected, by a ſen- <lb/>ſation of ſomething running into it from the <lb/>part already
        convulſed, which ſhe cannot deſcribe <lb/>in words; but ſhe has frequently told me the part
        <lb/>going to be affected, which I always found to be <pb n="330"/>
        <lb/>true, though the tranſition is ſurpriſingly quick. <lb/>A ſlight preſſure upon the part
        gives eaſe, per- <lb/>haps by giving tenſion to the muſcles; but, at- <lb/>tempting once to
        hold her head tight, ſhe told <lb/>me ſhe could not bear it, as it increaſed her <lb/>pains,
        which might ariſe from forcibly prevent- <lb/>ing the free contractions of the convulſed
        muſcles. <lb/>She is eaſieſt in a prone poſture. Such has <lb/>been her ſituation upwards of
        48 hours, with <lb/>ſcarce a moment's remiſſion, by which ſhe com- <lb/>plains of great and
        univerſal ſoreneſs. No words <lb/>can convey an adequate idea of her odd appear- <lb/>ance;
        and I do not in the leaſt wonder that, in <lb/>the times of ignorance and ſuperſtition, ſuch
        diſ- <lb/>eaſes were aſcribed to ſupernatural cauſes and the <lb/>agency of demons. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As ſhe had formerly, in a ſimilar ſituation, ta- <lb/>ken ſo many powerful medicines
        without ſucceſs, <lb/>I own, had not the zinc occurred to me, I ſhould <lb/>have deſpaired
        of trying them again; but, as ſhe <lb/>was deſirous of taking any thing preſcribed, I
        <lb/>ordered a bliſter ad nucham, et florum zinci, gr. <lb/>i. in a pill, twice a day,
        waſhed down with a cor- <lb/>dial julep. This was on the 28th of November. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>29. Bliſter has diſcharged greatly; pulſe leſs <lb/>full; no convulſions this morning;
        complains <pb n="331"/>
        <lb/>of a numbneſs in the right cheek, where her pain <lb/>was; pain in her loins eaſier; no
        numbneſs in <lb/>either leg; ſpirits good this morning. She <lb/>doubled the doſe of her
        pills this day. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>30. Had ſome ſlight twitchings in the night, <lb/>but of ſhort continuance; none this
        morning; <lb/>feels not the least ſenſible effect from the pills; <lb/>ſcarce any ſleep the
        two laſt nights; feet quite <lb/>warm; pulſe natural; an itching, but no ſcorch- <lb/>ing
        heat in the ſkin; has taken ſome magneſia, <lb/>ſum. pil. ii. ter die. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>December 1. Has had a good night; no con- <lb/>vulſions ſince I ſaw her yeſterday; no
        percep- <lb/>tible effects from her pills; in other reſpects, as <lb/>before. Took nine
        pills this day. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2. No complaint ſince yeſterday; bliſter al- <lb/>moſt healed. Sum. pil. iv. ter die. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><sic>5.</sic> On a journey, did not ſee my patient. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>4. No return of the ſpaſms ſince I ſaw her laſt; <lb/>complains of ſickneſs and
        headach, to which ſhe <lb/>is very ſubject, for which I ordered her to take <lb/>an emetic
        of acet. ſcillit. in the evening. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>6. Diſcharged much phlegm, by the puke, as <lb/>uſual; nerves quite firm to-day, and is
        in all re- <lb/>ſpects in good health. Medicines diſcontinued. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
