<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: Dissertatio Inauguralis</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>IV. Caroli Josephi Oehme Dissertatio Inauguralis, de Morbis recens natorum
              Chirurgicis. 4to, Lipsiae.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society in Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for J. Murray, No, 32, Fleet-street</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1776</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">4</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">391-395</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CB132087767</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T220329</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v4_0391">
    <body>
      <pb n="391"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>IV. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">Caroli Joſephi Oehme</hi> Diſſertatio Inauguralis, de <lb/>Morbis
        recens natorum Chirurgicis. <hi rend="roman">4to, Lipſiae</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>NDEPENDENT of the many hereditary diſ- <lb/>orders which
        children receive from their pa- <lb/>rents, ſuch as lues venerea, arthritis, &amp;c. there
        <lb/>are others to which different parts of the body <lb/>become liable, either from
        original mal-confor- <lb/>mation, or from neceſſary violence in ſuch la- <lb/>bours as
        happen to prove difficult. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is to ſuch of the latter as more eſpecially re- <lb/>quire the aſſiſtance of
        ſurgery, that our author's <lb/>obſervations are entirely confined. He treats
        <lb/>ſucceſſively of tumors and depreſſions in the head <lb/>from difficult births, of open
        ſutures, hydroce- <lb/>phalus, hernia cerebri, ſpina bifida, diſeaſes of the <lb/>lips and
        eye-lids, of the tongue and fauces, of diſ- <pb n="392"/>
        <lb/>orders of the breaſt, ſuch as abſceſſes in the <lb/>breaſts and bronchocele; of
        diſeaſes of the um- <lb/>bilicus; all the variety of herniae; affections of <lb/>the
        ſcrotum, urethra, penis, anus; and, laſtly, are <lb/>conſidered diſorders of the extremities
        and com- <lb/>mon teguments. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the cure of the hare-lip, the uniting <lb/>bandage made with threads, which
        decuſſate, <lb/>is much recommended. This invention, which <lb/>by many had been attributed
        to the Engliſh, <lb/>our author gives the credit of to a ſurgeon <lb/>in Leipſic, who, we
        are told, was the firſt who e- <lb/>ver had recourſe to it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In that ſpecies of ranula which occurs in new- <lb/>born infants, extirpation by the
        actual cautery is <lb/>recommended both by Levrete and Delevrye; <lb/>our author, however,
        points out a different treat- <lb/>ment. If the abſceſs be only a collection of pus, <lb/>he
        adviſes it merely to be opened; but, if con- <lb/>tained in a cyſt, the cyſt, he ſays, muſt
        be de- <lb/>ſtroyed, otherwiſe the tumor is very apt to rege- <lb/>nerate. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The hiſtory of a bronchocele, or rather tra- <lb/>chiocele, which came under our
        author's inſpec- <lb/>tion, is here related. It occurred in a new-born <pb n="393"/>
        <lb/>child; and the tumor was ſo large, as to extend <lb/>from the ear and cheek of the
        right ſide, down <lb/>to the breaſt and very near the abdomen. It <lb/>appeared evidently to
        communicate with the aſ- <lb/>pera arteria, and to depend on an eruption of <lb/>air; for,
        during inſpiration, and when the boy <lb/>cried violently, the tumor increaſed; and, on the
        <lb/>contrary, its ſize was regularly diminiſhed in the <lb/>time of expiration. The patient
        having been <lb/>under the management of a different practition- <lb/>er, the treatment had
        recourſe to is not men- <lb/>tioned. In a ſimilar caſe, however, our author <lb/>would
        recommend aſtringent ſpiritous fomenta- <lb/>tions, with a view to get the better of any
        laxity <lb/>of parts that may prevail. And, if a continu- <lb/>ance of ſuch applications
        ſhould not effect a cure, <lb/>he would even adviſe the tumor to be opened, <lb/>ſo that the
        diſeaſed fiſſure may be detected, and <lb/>a coaleſcence, by proper bandages, be obtain-
        <lb/>ed. Another inſtance is mentioned of a conge- <lb/>nital bronchocele, which appeared,
        however, to <lb/>be of the ſtrumous kind. Swellings of this na- <lb/>ture we are adviſed to
        let remain to a more ad- <lb/>vanced age, when either reſolution or extirpa- <lb/>tion may,
        with greater ſafety, be had recourſe <lb/>to. </p>
      <pb n="394"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Such tumors and abſceſſes as frequently oc- <lb/>cur in the breaſts of infants, are
        commonly at- <lb/>tributed to the milk or ſerum which collect in <lb/>them not being
        properly preſſed out. This our <lb/>author allows, is ſometimes the caſe, but he is of o-
        <lb/>pinion, that they more frequently proceed from <lb/>the tight bandages which are
        commonly, though <lb/>very improperly, applied to new-born children. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In treating of the different ſpecies of exom- <lb/>phalus, our author deſcribes a
        particular kind <lb/>of tumor in the hypogaſtric region, to which in- <lb/>fants are liable
        three or four days after birth. <lb/>It frequently extends from the pubis to the um-
        <lb/>bilicus, attended with much pain and hardneſs. <lb/>By diſſection after death, tumors
        of this kind ap- <lb/>pear evidently to be of an inflammatory nature; <lb/>both the
        abdominal muſcles and peritonaeum are <lb/>commonly found affected. They proceed, accord-
        <lb/>ing to our author, from the blood in the umbilical <lb/>cord not being properly preſſed
        out on the ligature <lb/>being put on immediately after birth. Children, <lb/>we are told,
        frequently die of this complaint: <lb/>The remedies recommended are, glyſters, emol-
        <lb/>lient fomentations, and plaſters of the ſame <lb/>kind. </p>
      <pb n="395"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A full account is given by our author of the <lb/>congenital hernia, in which the
        inteſtines deſcend <lb/>by the proceſs of the peritonaeum, and lie in im- <lb/>mediate
        contact with the teſtes. A ſimilar pro- <lb/>ceſs, he ſays, is found in women ſurrounding
        the <lb/>round ligament of the womb; and a deſcription <lb/>is here given of what may be
        termed a conge- <lb/>nital hydrocele, in which the water collected is <lb/>contained in this
        proceſs of the peritonaeum. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
