<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Duncan: The History of a Convulsive Disorder</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Dr Duncan</persName>
            </author>
            <title>III. The History of a Convulsive Disorder, treated by the Use of the Flowers of
              Zinc. By Dr Patrick Dugud, Physician at Durham. Communicated to Dr Duncan.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society in Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for J. Murray, No, 32, Fleet-street. W. Creech, C. Elliot
                  and M. Drummond, Edinburgh.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1777</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">5</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">84-91</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110350931</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v5_0084">
    <body>
      <pb n="84"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>III. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>The Hiſtory of a Convulſive Diſorder, treated by the <lb/>Uſe of the Flowers of Zinc.
        By <hi rend="roman">Dr Patrick <lb/>Dugud</hi>, Phyſician at Durham. Communicated <lb/>to
          <hi rend="roman">Dr Duncan</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">J</hi>ANE HEDLEY, aged nine years, of a <lb/>relaxed habit of body,
        and delicate conſti- <lb/>tution, was ſuddenly, about two years ago, <pb n="85"/>
        <lb/>without any previous indiſpoſition, ſeized with a <lb/>violent convulſive fit; during
        which, the whole <lb/>muſcular ſyſtem was affected with irregular ſpaſ- <lb/>modic
        contractions. Her countenance became <lb/>pale and contracted; her eyes rolled wildly; the
        <lb/>muſcles of the mouth were thrown into a convul- <lb/>ſive grin; her knees were almoſt
        brought to <lb/>touch the ſternum ; whilſt her feet, with the toes <lb/>diſtorted inwards,
        ſeemed to reach the anus. <lb/>Upon undreſſing her, there was obſerved, im- <lb/>mediately
        below the falſe ribs of the left ſide, a <lb/>round and circumſcribed ſwelling, ſoft, and
        yield- <lb/>ing to the touch; which, in this, and all the ſub- <lb/>ſequent paroxyſms, no
        ſooner began to diminiſh, <lb/>than all the other ſymptoms vaniſhed; and ſhe <lb/>was left
        in an abſolute ſtate of ſtupefaction, which <lb/>generally terminated in a profound ſleep. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After this firſt attack, which laſted ſeveral <lb/>hours, the ſame ſeries of ſymptoms
        continued, for <lb/>ſix months, to return, at irregular intervals, three <lb/>or four times
        a week. About this time, ſhe was <lb/>ſeized with a fever, which had almoſt proved fa-
        <lb/>tal. On her recovery from it, ſhe paſſed three <lb/>large round worms, and had no
        return of the ſit <lb/>till two months after, when they again attacked <lb/>her, with all
        their former violence ; and increaſed <lb/>ſo much in frequency, that, at the time I was de-
          <pb n="86"/>
        <lb/>ſired to viſit her, ſhe generally had a fit every <lb/>three hours; which, however,
        ſeldom exceeded <lb/>twenty minutes in duration. I had often an op- <lb/>portunity of ſeeing
        the girl under the paroxyſm, <lb/>and found that it literally anſwered the deſcrip-
        <lb/>tion given me of the firſt attack. I was informed <lb/>by her friends, that ſhe was
        naturally a girl of <lb/>great ſenſibility, quick conception, and a reten- <lb/>tive memory;
        but that her diſorder had ſo much <lb/>impaired the faculties of her mind, that ſhe had
        <lb/>forgot every thing ſhe had formerly learned, and <lb/>hardly knew a ſingle letter of
        the alphabet. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As the girl formerly had paſſed worms, and <lb/>continued to have ſeveral of the chief
        ſymptoms <lb/>which are ſuppoſed to indicate their preſence in <lb/>the inteſtinal canal,
        viz. foetid breath, ſlimy <lb/>ſtools, grinding of the teeth, &amp;c. I thought it <lb/>more
        than probable that all her complaints origi- <lb/>nated from this cauſe; and therefore
        judged it <lb/>proper to put her, for ſome time, upon a courſe <lb/>of anthelmintics. But,
        on finding that, inſtead <lb/>of alleviating the ſymptoms, they evidently ag- <lb/>gravated
        the diſeaſe, I was naturally led to refer <lb/>the whole phaenomena to a peculiar ſtate of
        mo- <lb/>bility in the nervous ſyſtem; and, as the higheſt <lb/>encomiums had been lately
        beſtowed by Gau- <pb n="87"/>
        <lb/>bius, and others, on the flores zinci, in ſpaſmo- <lb/>dic and convulſive diſorders, I
        reſolved to give <lb/>them a trial. And, in order to preclude any <lb/>chance of fallacy
        with reſpect to their effects, I <lb/>laid aſide all other medicines, and, on the 24th
        <lb/>of July 1776, preſcribed the following ſimple <lb/>pill: </p>
      <floatingText><body>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>℞ Flor. zinc. ʒſs. <lb/>Extract. gentian. ʒiſs. ſyr. zingib. q. s. f. <lb/>pilul. No.
          xxx. quarum duas ſumat omni <lb/>m. et v. </p></body>
      </floatingText>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I was ſent for in the afternoon, and informed <lb/>that ſhe had ſcarcely taken the
        pills half an hour, <lb/>when ſhe was ſeized with a ſevere headach, ac- <lb/>companied with
        reaching, vomiting, and gripes. <lb/>I ordered for her a gentle laxative clyſter, and an
        <lb/>anodyne draught, at bed-time; and was told next <lb/>morning, that the nauſea and
        gripes had ceaſed <lb/>on taking the opiate, and that ſhe had fewer ſits <lb/>in the night
        than uſual. On examining the <lb/>flowers of zinc, I found them very ill prepared, <lb/>and
        more like a corroſion of the zinc than a true <lb/>calx. I therefore cauſed ſome to be
        procured, <lb/>which I could depend on as genuine, and gave <lb/>them under the form of a
        powder, as more a- <pb n="88"/>
        <lb/>greeable to the girl, who had a difficulty in ſwal- <lb/>lowing pills. </p>
      <floatingText><body>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>℞ Flor. zinc. gr. xxiv. <lb/>Sacchar. alb. ʒiſs. m. s. a. et. divid. in doſ. xii.
          <lb/>Cap. doſin omni m. et v. </p></body>
      </floatingText>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 30th, ſhe began to uſe the powders, <lb/>which ſat eaſily on her ſtomach; and
        ſhe had on- <lb/>ly taken them two days, when the return of the <lb/>fits became ſenſibly
        leſs frequent. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 4th of Auguſt, I deſired that ſhe ſhould <lb/>take three doſes of her medicines
        every day; and, <lb/>from that period, the fits began to diminiſh ſo <lb/>faſt in the
        frequency of their return, as well as to <lb/>abate in the violence of their ſymptoms, that,
        in <lb/>leſs than a week, they never recurred in the <lb/>night, and not above thrice
        through the day. <lb/>The flatulent ſwelling, (for ſuch I ſuppoſed it to <lb/>be,) formerly
        obſerved to riſe in her ſide, be- <lb/>came ſcarcely perceptible; the muſcular ſyſtem
        <lb/>was now no more thrown into ſpaſtic and con- <lb/>vulſive motions; nor was the
        paroxyſm, which <lb/>had aſſumed the type of a common <hi rend="italic">ſyncope</hi>,
        <lb/>ſucceeded by any ſenſible degree of ſtupor or <lb/>coma. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 11th, her medicine was increaſed to <lb/>ſour dozes a day; after which the
        paroxyſm <pb n="89"/>
        <lb/>never returned oftener than once in the twenty- <lb/>four hours, and rarely laſted
        above five minutes. <lb/>She now began to recover the uſe of her reaſon <lb/>and memory, to
        give pertinent anſwers when ſpo- <lb/>ken to, and to recollect things which ſhe had
        <lb/>learned by heart two years before. She was <lb/>now, for the firſt time, allowed to go
        abroad <lb/>without an attendant. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 14th, ſhe began to take gr. xii. of the <lb/>zinc, and had not any return of the
        fits till the <lb/>morning of the 18th, when, on being hurried <lb/>out of bed, ſhe had a
        ſlight paroxyſm, which <lb/>only laſted about three minutes. She was ſen- <lb/>ſible of its
        approach, and, whilſt it continued, <lb/>ſeemed nowiſe convulſed, As ſhe had experi-
        <lb/>enced no inconveniency from gr. xii. of the zinc, <lb/>I ventured to preſcribe gr. xv.
        a-day, which was <lb/>attended with ſo happy an effect, that the fits <lb/>entirely ceaſed;
        but ſhe continued to be af- <lb/>fected with a ſudden tremor or ſtarting every <lb/>morning,
        much about the ſame time that ſhe had <lb/>been formerly wont to have a ſevere paroxyſm.
        <lb/>Being, however, deſired to take every morning a <lb/><choice>
          <corr/>
          <sic>a </sic>
        </choice>doſe of her medicine before ſhe got out of <lb/>bed, this complaint, in a few days,
        entirely va- <lb/>niſhed, and, with it, every other ſymptom of her <pb n="90"/>
        <lb/>diſorder, both of mind and body. But, as the <lb/>girl was naturally of a relaxed and
        delicate habit <lb/>of body, I thought there was ſtill ſome reaſon to <lb/>apprehend a
        relapſe, and therefore recommended <lb/>to her the uſe of ſea-bathing, as a ſafe and pow-
        <lb/>erful tonic, and well calculated to remove that <lb/>conſtitutional irritability of
        ſyſtem, which ſeemed <lb/>to be the <hi rend="italic">prima mali labes</hi>, and proximate
        cauſe <lb/>of the diſeaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the latter end of Auguſt ſhe began to <lb/>bathe, and perſevered in it for ſome
        weeks; af- <lb/>ter which ſhe was ſent into the country, where <lb/>ſhe ſtaid near two
        months, and returned to town <lb/>perfectly well in every reſpect. She continued <lb/>in a
        ſtate of health till the 3d of December, <lb/>when, having walked out, ſhe dropped down in
        <lb/>a violent convulſion-fit; and was no ſooner out <lb/>of one fit, than ſhe was taken
        with another. I <lb/>did not ſee her till the 5th, when I found her in <lb/>a ſituation,
        that left very little room to doubt of <lb/>the event. Her pulſe was extremely quick and
        <lb/>ſmall, and intermitted every third or fourth pul- <lb/>ſation; her looks were wild and
        ghaſtly; her <lb/>lower extremities were become paralytic; ſhe <lb/>had ſubſultus tendinum,
        ſingultus, and all the <pb n="91"/>
        <lb/>ſymptoms of an approaching diſſolution; which <lb/>accordingly happened next morning. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Tho' the above caſe terminated fatally, it, in <lb/>my opinion, affords the moſt
        convincing proof <lb/>of the powerful and ſalutary effects of the flowers <lb/>of zinc in
        convulſive and ſpaſmodic diſeaſes. I <lb/>have had an opportunity of uſing them in three
        <lb/>other caſes of this nature; in two of which they <lb/>were evidently attended with
        conſiderable advan- <lb/>tage; but, in the third, they entirely failed. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
