<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: Pharmacopoea Suecica</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>IV. Pharmacopoea Suecica, cum gratia et privilegio, S: œ R: œ Majitis. 8vo,
              Holmiae.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society in Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for J. Murray, No, 32, Fleet-street. W. Creech, C. Elliot
                  and M. Drummond, Edinburgh.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1777</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">5</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">62-70</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110350931</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v5_0062">
    <body>
      <pb n="62"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>IV. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Pharmacopoea Suecica, cum gratia et privilegio, <lb/>S:œ R:æ Majitis. <hi rend="roman"
          >8vo, Holmiae.</hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">O</hi>F all the different branches of the medical <lb/>art, there is,
        perhaps, no one which has, <lb/>of late years, undergone greater alteration than <lb/>that
        which reſpects the preparation and compoſi- <lb/>tion of medicines. Beſides which, the
        articles <lb/>employed as medicines have alſo undergone con- <lb/>ſiderable alterations.
        Some articles, at one time <lb/>conſidered as powerful and efficacious medicines, <lb/>are
        at another exploded as totally uſeleſs. And <lb/>daily experience diſcovers uſeful
        properties in <lb/>articles, which were never before employed for <lb/>medical purpoſes. Of
        theſe aſſertions, the pre- <lb/>ſent Pharmacopoeia, as well as ſeveral others of <lb/>recent
        date, affords indubitable evidence. From <lb/>the nature of the work, however, it is
        impoſſible <lb/>for us to give ſuch an analyſis as can convey any <pb n="63"/>
        <lb/>proper idea of it. Yet, we may obſerve, that, <lb/>throughout the whole, this
        publication bears <lb/>evident marks of its being the work of intelligent
        <lb/>practitioners. And we have little doubt in giving <lb/>it as our opinion, that it is to
        be conſidered as, <lb/>perhaps, the beſt Pharmacopoeia yet extant. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After a reſpectful dedication to his Swediſh <lb/>Majeſty, and a ſhort preface, in
        which they ex- <lb/>plain their weights and meaſures, they deliver a <lb/>few general
        pharmaceutical rules. They adviſe, <lb/>that herbs, flowers, and the like, ſhould be quick-
        <lb/>ly dried at a ſlow fire. With reſpect to powders, <lb/>they obſerve, that what is firſt
        obtained, is, in <lb/>general, the beſt. And they direct, that, in ipe- <lb/>cacuanha, the
        woody part ſhould not be uſed. Yet, <lb/>they allow, that, in the caſe of thoſe woody ſub-
        <lb/>ſtances abounding with gums and reſins, as jal- <lb/>lap, Peruvian bark, and the like,
        the powder firſt <lb/>obtained is much inferior to what is got afterwards. <lb/>They
        recommend, that gums and gummi-reſi- <lb/>nous ſubſtances, ſhould chiefly be pounded du-
        <lb/>ring froſt. And, in the preparation of compound <lb/>powders, they give it as a general
        direction, that <lb/>the articles ſhould firſt be pounded, each ſepa- <lb/>rately, and then
        intimately mixed. </p>
      <pb n="64"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To theſe rules follows the catalogue of the <lb/>materia medica, containing thoſe
        articles which <lb/>they direct to be kept in the ſhops, and which <lb/>ſhould not be
        prepared by the apothecary him- <lb/>ſelf. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe articles are arranged in alphabetical order, <lb/>and to each is ſubjoined a
        character, which, al- <lb/>though ſhort, ſerves to give a very clear idea of <lb/>the
        ſubſtance employed. A few examples will <lb/>better explain the manner in which they have
        <lb/>acquitted themſelves in this part of their work, <lb/>than any account of it. </p>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <list rend="italic space">
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Abrotanum</hi>. <hi rend="align-right">Herba. </hi>
              <lb/>Artemiſia abrotanum. <hi rend="sc">Caroli A Linne</hi>. <lb/><hi rend="roman"
                >Spec. plant. edit. 2.</hi> Planta hortenſis ſuffrutico- <lb/>ſa. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Acacia Vera</hi>. <hi rend="align-right">Succus e fructu. </hi>
              <lb/>Mimoſa Senegal. <hi rend="roman">L.</hi> Africana arborea. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Ærugo</hi>. <hi rend="align-center">Cuprum muſto vini corroſum.
              </hi>
            </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Alcana</hi>. <hi rend="align-right">Radix. </hi>
              <lb/>Anchuſa tinctoria. <hi rend="roman">L.</hi> Exotica, Europae auſtra- <lb/>lis,
              Perennis. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Aloe</hi>. <hi rend="roman align-right">Cabalina, hepatica,
                ſocotrina. </hi>
              <lb/>Aloe perfoliata. <hi rend="roman">L.</hi> Exotica Indica. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Anethum</hi>. <hi rend="align-right">Herba Seminea. </hi>
              <lb/>Anethum graveolens. <hi rend="roman">L.</hi> Hortenſis annua. </item>
            <pb n="65"/>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Arnica</hi>. <hi rend="align-right">Folia, flores. </hi>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">Arnica montana L. Suecica, perennis</hi>. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Assa foetida</hi>. <hi rend="roman align-right">Gummi-reſina. </hi>
              <lb/><hi rend="roman">Ferula aſſa foetida. L. Aſiatica, perennis</hi>. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Bdellium</hi>. <hi rend="roman align-right">Gummi-reſina. </hi>
              <lb/>Obſcura. Arabica, palma. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Castoreum</hi>: Et ejus axungia. <lb/>Caſtor Fiber. <hi rend="sc"
                >L. s. n.</hi> Europae ſeptentrionalis. </item>
            <item rend="hanging">
              <lb/><hi rend="sc">Cerussa</hi>: <hi rend="roman">In laminis</hi>. Plumbum aceti
              vapore <lb/>corroſum. </item>
          </list>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe few examples, ſelected from the begin- <lb/>ning of the catalogue, will give ſome
        idea of the <lb/>method which is followed throughout the whole, <lb/>both with reſpect to
        ſubſtances from the vege- <lb/>table, foſſil, and animal kingdoms. With re- <lb/>gard to
        this catalogue, we may fartner obſerve, <lb/>that, although the Stockholm college have re-
        <lb/>jected many articles which ſtill retain a place in <lb/>other foreign Pharmacopoeias,
        yet their cata- <lb/>logue is much more numerous than that of the <lb/>Edinburgh College.
        And it contains above an <lb/>hundred and twenty articles which are not now <lb/>to be found
        in that work. Some of theſe which <lb/>have of late been recommended as uſeful reme-
        <lb/>dies, on the authority of practitioners of credit, <lb/>have never had a place in the
        Edinburgh Phar- <pb n="66"/>
        <lb/>macopoeia. Of theſe, the following ſeem to be <lb/>the chief. <list rend="space">
          <item>
            <lb/>Arnica montana, </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>Auripigmentum, </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>Botrys <hi rend="italic">Chenopodium Botrys L.</hi>
          </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>Cajeput, </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>Camphorata. <hi rend="italic">Camphoroſma Monſpelica</hi>. </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>Cicuta viroſa. </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>Culilavan. <hi rend="italic">Laurus Culilavan L.</hi>
          </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>Faba Ignatii. </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>Inula dyſenterica. </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>Quaſſia. </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>Salicaria. </item>
          <item>
            <lb/>Vanilla. </item>
        </list>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After the liſt of ſimple medicines, or rather of <lb/>the materia medica, they proceed
        to the prepared <lb/>and compounded medicines. The order which <lb/>they have here followed,
        is the arranging the <lb/>whole in an alphabetical liſt. And, although this <lb/>method be
        not altogether without diſadvantages, <lb/>yet it is, perhaps, preferable to moſt others. Of
        <lb/>the various alterations and improvements which <lb/>are propoſed through this part of
        the work, we <lb/>cannot pretend to give an account. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They propoſe that an acetum concentratum <lb/>ſhould be prepared by freezing. And they
        give <pb n="67"/>
        <lb/>it as the ſtandard of ſtrength, that one dram of <lb/>it ſhould ſaturate a ſcruple of
        the ſalt of tartar. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They direct the preparation of an ærugo <lb/>cryſtallizata, by pouring vinegar upon
        verdi- <lb/>grize, and after maceration and decantation, ſub- <lb/>jecting the tranſparent
        fluid to evaporation and <lb/>cryſtallization. This preparation of the verde- <lb/>grize is
        afterwards employed in the preparation <lb/>of the aqua caerulea, or aqua ſaphirina, and for
        <lb/>ſeveral other purpoſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They point out a proceſs for the purification <lb/>of camphor by means of quick lime. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They give the following formula for the pre- <lb/>paration of a ceratum labiale. </p>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <p rend="indentall hanging">
            <lb/>℞. Butyri recentis, inſulſi, libram ſemis <lb/>Paffalarum exacinatarum,
            conſciſſarum, </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Pomorum Borſdorfienſium exacinatorum <lb/>et conſciſſorum, </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Cerae flavae, ſingulorum uncias duas </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Radicis alcannae drachmas duas </p>
          <p>
            <lb/>Coque leniter in vaſe figulino donec humiditas <lb/><unclear>e</unclear>vaporata
            ſit, ſeu guttula carboni candenti im- <lb/><unclear>m</unclear>iffa crepitum non edat.
            Maſſa fervens forti <lb/><unclear>e</unclear>xpreſſione coletur in vas aqua roſarum
            plenum, <lb/><unclear>et</unclear> refrigerata ab aqua hac liberetur. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <pb n="68"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They direct the preparation of a cremor Sa- <lb/>turni, by uniting equal parts of the
          acetu<unclear>m </unclear>
        <lb/>ſaturninum and ſuccus citri, from briſk agitatio<unclear>n</unclear>
        <lb/>in a glaſs mortar. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For the preparation of an electuarium e manna, <lb/>we are preſented with the following
        formula. </p>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <p rend="indentall hanging">
            <lb/>℞. Mannae electae, <lb/>Sacchari albiſſimi, ſingulorum uncias dua<unclear>s, </unclear>
            <lb/>Aquae foeniculi, uncias duas cum dimidi<unclear>a, </unclear>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Solutionem cola cum expreſſione, et ei a<unclear>d-</unclear>
            <lb/>miſſae Radices Iridis Florentinae, in ſubtiliſſimu<unclear>m </unclear>
            <lb/>pulverem tritae, drachmam unam. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Olei amygdalarum dulcium recenter e<unclear>x-</unclear>
            <lb/>preſſi unciam unam, fiat electuarium. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They propoſe an elixir anthelminticum, conſi<unclear>ſt-</unclear>
        <lb/>ing of jallap, baſtard ſafron, ſcammony and ga<unclear>m-</unclear>
        <lb/>boge; rectified ſpirit of wine being employed <unclear>as </unclear>
        <lb/>the menſtruum. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Their emplaſtrum pro cereis rnedicatis, is ma<unclear>de </unclear>
        <lb/>in the following manner. </p>
      <floatingText>
        <body>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>℞. Cerae flavae leni igne liquefactae, libr<unclear>am </unclear>
            <lb/>unam. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Aceti ſaturnini, unciam ſemis, mixtis, et <gap reason="illegible"/>
            <lb/>igne remotis, immerge telas tenues ex quibus <gap reason="illegible"/>
            <lb/>ant l. a. cerei. </p>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
      <pb n="69"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They propoſe the preparation of a gelatina <lb/>pomorum, by expreſſing the juice of
        apples, ad- <lb/>ding to it a fourth part of its weight of white ſu- <lb/>gar, and then
        evaporating to the conſiſtence of a <lb/>jelly. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They obtain an oleum animale by diſtillation <lb/>from calcined hartſhorn, to which is
        added half <lb/>the weight of the oil of hartſhorn. They prepare <lb/>hydragogue pills from
        compounding gum ammo- <lb/>niac, ſquills, aloes, gamboge, and elatarium. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>They introduce two preparations of the fixed <lb/>foſſil alkali, under the titles of
        ſoda depurata, and <lb/>ſoda tartarizata. They introduce a ſpiritus for- <lb/>micarum,
        obtained by the diſtillation of ants <lb/>with ſpirit of wine and water. For purifying the
        <lb/>terra Japonica, they recommend, that it ſhould <lb/>firſt be diſſolved in water, and
        that then, this <lb/>ſolution, after ſtraining, ſhould be evaporated to <lb/>dryneſs. To
        this they give the title of ſuccus <lb/>Japonicus depuratus; and, unqueſtionably, the
        <lb/>name of terra Japonica, which is ſtill retained in <lb/>the Edinburgh Pharmacopoeia, is
        with great <lb/>impropriety applied to a vegetable extract. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Beſides theſe, we might take notice of many <lb/>other articles, which are either
        peculiar to the <lb/>Pharmacopoeia, and are, at the ſame time, valuable <pb n="70"/>
        <lb/>formulae, or which may juſtly be conſidered as <lb/>improvements on ſimilar
        preſcriptions contained <lb/>in thoſe of other colleges. But we ſhall con- <lb/>clude our
        remarks on this work, with obſerving, <lb/>that it terminates with a very uſeful table,
        ſhew- <lb/>ing the proportion of opium, mercury, emetics, <lb/>and purgatives, which enter
        into different com- <lb/>pounds. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
