<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: G. G. Schillingii de Lepra Commentationes</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>V. G. G. Schillingii de Lepra Commentationes. 8vo, Lugduni Batavorum.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society in Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for J. Murray, No, 32, Fleet-street. W. Creech, C. Elliot
                  and M. Drummond, Edinburgh.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1777</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">5</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">260-268</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110350931</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v5_0260">
    <body>
      <pb n="260"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>V. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>G. G. Schillingii de Lepra Commentationes. <hi rend="roman">8vo, <lb/>Lugduni
          Batavorum.</hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HIS diſſertation upon leproſy was wrote by <lb/>Dr Schilling at
        Surinam in the Weſt In- <pb n="261"/>
        <lb/>dies, where the author had frequent opportuni- <lb/>ties of ſeeing and treating this
        diſorder. It is <lb/>now publiſhed, along with two other papers on <lb/>the ſame ſubject, by
        Dr Hahn of Leyden, to <lb/>whom they had been communicated by the au- <lb/>thor. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This diſorder, our author obſerves, is very ea- <lb/>ſily diſtinguiſhed when it has
        arrived at any con- <lb/>ſiderable height; and, on the contrary, during <lb/>its firſt
        ſtages, it is very difficult to detect. It is <lb/>of great conſequence, however, in the
        treatment, <lb/>to be able to diſtinguiſh the diſorder ſoon after <lb/>its commencement; and
        our author mentions <lb/>two circumſtances which he aſſerts to be con- <lb/>ſtant and
        never-failing ſymptoms, viz. a change <lb/>of colour, together with inſenſibility in the
        parts <lb/>affected. The diſcolouration of the ſkin which <lb/>occurs here, is of two kinds;
        ſometimes the parts <lb/>are of a pale red complexion, and on other oc- <lb/>caſions they
        are white, with a tendency to a red <lb/>or livid yellow appearance. In the former caſe,
        <lb/>the hairs growing upon the parts have ſomewhat <lb/>of a yellow or red appearance. In
        the latter, <lb/>they are always white. In both inſtances, the <lb/>diſorder breaks out in
        ſpots of a round figure, <lb/>which, in the beginning of the complaint, are al- <pb n="262"/>
        <lb/>ways exceedingly ſmall. Inſenſibility of the part <lb/>is likewiſe common to both. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When, in courſe of time, the diſorder has ob- <lb/>tained a more firm foundation in the
        ſyſtem, the <lb/>lobes of the ears begin to ſwell, turn hard, and <lb/>ſmall tumours appear
        in different parts of them. <lb/>The ſides of the noſe, lips, and at length the <lb/>whole
        face, ſwell and become red. This redneſs <lb/>of the ſkin, in time, turns into a kind of
        blue, <lb/>which gradually acquires a more livid appearance, <lb/>in proportion to the
        continuance of the diſorder. <lb/>The ſkin is, by degrees, more and more con- <lb/>tracted,
        and forms itſelf into a number of harden- <lb/>ed folds or wrinkles. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In many inſtances, by means of proper atten- <lb/>tion to diet and other circumſtances,
        the diſor- <lb/>der has continued in this ſituation, without ma- <lb/>king any farther
        progreſs, for ten, or even twen- <lb/>ty years. But when, from neglect of proper
        <lb/>management, the diſeaſe again begins to advance, <lb/>the leprous bloatches ſpread from
        the face over <lb/>the whole body, even to the ſoles of the feet; <lb/>and, riſing into
        nodes and ſmall tumours, occa- <lb/>ſion a very diſagreeable deformity of the whole
        <lb/>habit. </p>
      <pb n="263"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It often happens, that the fingers are the parts <lb/>firſt affected with this
        diſorder. Small veſicles <lb/>riſing below the nails, the points of the fingers <lb/>ſwell,
        and loſe their feeling: By degrees the ſe- <lb/>cond phalanx become diſeaſed, but they
        remain <lb/>free from pain, inſomuch that the ſmall bones are <lb/>often taken out without
        giving much uneaſineſs <lb/>to the patient, and on other occaſions they fall <lb/>out of
        their own accord. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the mean time, the perſpiration is entirely <lb/>ſtopped up, by that thickneſs and
        hardneſs of the <lb/>teguments which prevails univerſally over the <lb/>body. Hence the ſick
        fall into cachexies, leuco- <lb/>phlegmatic ſwellings, dropſy, melancholy, and at <lb/>laſt
        are often ſeized with a taedium vitae, which <lb/>terminates in their putting a voluntary
        end to <lb/>their miſerable exiſtence. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The breath in this diſorder acquires an into- <lb/>lerably foetid ſmell; the belly is
        commonly coſ- <lb/>tive, and is with difficulty acted upon by purga- <lb/>tives; the foeces
        are dry, black, and have a burnt <lb/>appearance; the urine is of a red colour, and ad-
        <lb/>heres firmly to the veſſels in which it is collected; <lb/>and the tongue is always dry
        and covered with a <lb/>black cruſt. The blood is commonly very thin; <lb/>that which is
        taken from the veins has, for the <pb n="264"/>
        <lb/>moſt part, a very putrid ſmell; but this circum- <lb/>ſtance was never obſerved by our
        author in blood <lb/>taken immediately from an artery. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In ſome inſtances of this diſorder, the feet are <lb/>the parts chiefly affected, and
        then the complaint <lb/>has been commonly termed <hi rend="italic">elephantiaſis</hi>, not
        <lb/>only from the reſemblance of the diſeaſed feet <lb/>to thoſe of the elephant, but from
        the walk of <lb/>ſuch patients reſembling exactly the ſtep of that <lb/>animal. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In this ſpecies of the complaint, the ſkin and <lb/>other ſoft parts become wonderfully
        expanded, <lb/>at the ſame time that the different ſmall bones <lb/>ſwell conſiderably. The
        toes become thick, and <lb/>at laſt melt down, and run together as if made <lb/>of wax. The
        ſlighteſt affection of the diſeaſed <lb/>parts occaſions a diſcharge of blood, which,
        <lb/>however, is commonly eaſily put a ſtop to. The <lb/>diſorder by degrees ſpreads from
        the toes over <lb/>the whole foot, and from thence proceeds to the <lb/>femur, rendering the
        different articulations in its <lb/>courſe ſtiff and immoveable; at the ſame time <lb/>that,
        in many inſtances, the muſcles and tendons <lb/>concrete ſo firmly together, that the moſt
        ſkilful <lb/>anatomiſt can neither ſeparate or diſtinguish them <lb/>without great
        difficulty. </p>
      <pb n="265"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It has been tried, whether amputation of the <lb/>member, in caſes of this kind, would
        prove be- <lb/>neficial or not; but, as yet, it has never, we are <lb/>told, been found to
        ſucceed. In ſome, a locked <lb/>jaw occurred about the ſeventh day from the o-
        <lb/>peration. This again was commonly ſucceeded <lb/>by tetanus, which at laſt ended in
        death. Others <lb/>died immediately from convulſions; and in ſuch <lb/>as did ſurvive the
        operation for any length of <lb/>time, the wound occaſioned by the operation did <lb/>not
        heal, and the diſorder at laſt ſeized upon the <lb/>other foot. A particular deſcription is
        given by our <lb/>author, of the appearance obſerved on diſſecting <lb/>ſuch limbs after
        amputation: The internal ap- <lb/>pearance of the bones are nearly the ſame, he
        <lb/>obſerves, as thoſe obſerved in bones affected with <lb/>ſpina ventoſa. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Although this diſorder is very frequent in <lb/>ſome of the Weſt India iſlands, and in
        ſome parts <lb/>of the continent of America, yet our author is <lb/>clearly of opinion that
        it is not originally a diſ- <lb/>eaſe of that climate. It was at firſt introduced <lb/>by
        the negroes carried from the coaſt of Africa, <lb/>and has ſince been kept up by an annual
        impor- <lb/>tation of ſlaves from the ſame country: For, al- <lb/>though there are many
        inſtances of the native A- <pb n="266"/>
        <lb/>mericans labouring under complaints of this na- <lb/>ture, yet there are many entire
        tribes in which <lb/>it has never been known; and it occurs with <lb/>thoſe only who have
        frequent intercourſe with <lb/>the African ſlaves. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It has been aſſerted by ſome writers, that le- <lb/>proſy is not communicated by
        contagion; but <lb/>our author is of a different opinion, and has no <lb/>doubt of its being
        a contagious diſorder. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the cure of this diſease, we are directed to <lb/>have three principal objects in
        view. To reſtore, <lb/>as much as poſſible, to a natural ſtate, the per- <lb/>ſpiration of
        the patient; to dilute the juices ſuf- <lb/>ficiently with healthy nouriſhing fluids, ſo
        that <lb/>the acrid particles contained in them may be <lb/>more eaſily expelled; and,
        laſtly, to reſtore a <lb/>due degree of ſtrength to the whole habit. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>With a view to the firſt of theſe indications, <lb/>a frequent uſe of the warm bath is
        much recom- <lb/>mended. At firſt it is neceſſary to have recourſe <lb/>to it with ſome
        caution, as it is apt to induce an- <lb/>xiety and palpitations about the heart, and on ſome
        <lb/>occaſions, convulſions: For this reaſon, the bath <lb/>ſhould not be repeated above
        twice a week, at <lb/>firſt, and the patient ſhould not remain in it a- <pb n="267"/>
        <lb/>bove fifteen minutes at once. He should after- <lb/>wards, we are told, come to uſe it
        twice every day, <lb/>viz. on getting out of bed in the morning, and a- <lb/>gain in the
        evening, on going to reſt. Our au- <lb/>thor remarks, that marſh mallows, flowers of el-
        <lb/>der, and other emollient herbs, make very pro- <lb/>per additions to theſe baths. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>With a view to promote this free perſpiration, <lb/>which is a neceſſary part of the
        cure, gentle exerciſe <lb/>is recommended; and it is the more neceſſary, <lb/>we are told,
        the greater the averſion of the patient <lb/>is to attend to it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In order to dilute properly the diſeaſed fluids, <lb/>and afterwards to throw them out
        from the ſy- <lb/>ſtem, we are directed firſt to exhibit large quan- <lb/>tities of any
        emollient decoction, and afterwards <lb/>to have recourſe to ſome of the more active ſudo-
        <lb/>rifics. During this part of the courſe, the great- <lb/>eſt care is requiſite in order
        to preſerve the pa- <lb/>tient from cold; for if, from expoſure to cold <lb/>wind, the
        perſpiration ſhould again receive a <lb/>check, it never fails to produce ſuch ſymptoms
        <lb/>as always prove very troubleſome, and which, <lb/>on ſome occaſions, end even fatally.
        During this, and <lb/><choice>
          <corr>every</corr>
          <sic>very</sic>
        </choice> other part of the cure, it is neceſſary to keep <pb n="268"/>
        <lb/>the belly open, by the uſe of extract of rhubarb, <lb/>of aloetics, or of other gentle
        laxatives. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>For ſuch putrid ulcers as frequently occur in <lb/>patients infected with leproſy,
        antiſeptic fomen- <lb/>tations are recommended, together with tinctures <lb/>of myrrh,
        aloes, and ſuccinum. We are directed <lb/>to avoid every oily application, and eſpecially
        <lb/>ſuch as are conjoined with mercury; for, as long <lb/>as the ſyſtem remains tainted
        with the leprous <lb/>miaſma, it is always dangerous to have recourſe <lb/>to mercury in any
        form whatever. When the <lb/>general diſorder of the ſyſtem, however, is once
        <lb/>eradicated, mercury may then, we are told, be <lb/>uſed with ſafety; and in that ſtate
        of the complaint <lb/>it is frequently of ſervice for removing ſuch callo- <lb/>ſities of
        the ſkin as often remain after every other <lb/>ſymptom of the diſeaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>With a view to ſtrengthen the ſyſtem, after <lb/>the diſeaſe has been entirely carried
        off, a more <lb/>invigorating diet ſhould be allowed; and the pa- <lb/>tients are directed
        to rub their whole bodies, daily, <lb/>with ſpirits of wine, or with rum; and to fumigate
        <lb/>with the ſmoke of maſtich, olibanum, benzoin, <lb/>lavender, or of any other aſtringent
        herb or <lb/>gum. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
