<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: Dissertatio Medica de Methodo Medendi Variolae</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>VII. Dissertatio Medica de Methodo Medendi Variolae, praecipue auxilio Mercurii.
              Auctore Thoma Fowler, Societ. Med. Edin. Soc. &amp;c.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society in Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for J. Murray, No, 32, Fleet-street. W. Creech, C. Elliot
                  and M. Drummond, Edinburgh.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1777</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">5</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">407-414</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110350931</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v5_0407">
    <body>
      <pb n="407"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>VII. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Diſſertatio Medica de Methoda Medendi Variolae, <lb/>praecipue auxilio Mercurii.
        Auctore <hi rend="roman">Thoma <lb/>Fowler</hi>, Societ. Med. Edin. Soc. <hi rend="roman"
          >&amp;c.</hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>MONG the numerous inaugural diſſerta- <lb/>tions which are
        publiſhed at Edinburgh, <lb/>we have oftener than once preſented our readers <lb/>with an
        analyſis of ſuch as we thought beſt me- <lb/>rited the attention of the public. Theſe almoſt
        <lb/>ſolely conſiſted of ſuch as contained ingenious <lb/>experimental inquiries on
        ſubjects, ſtrictly ſpeak- <lb/>ing, rather philoſophical than medical: And, <lb/>while they
        afforded proof of the induſtry and <lb/>ability of the authors, they, at the ſame time, ſer-
        <lb/>ved to through new light on intricate and impor- <lb/>tant ſubjects. They have,
        however, been, in <lb/>general, the works of young men, who wanted <lb/>experience in the
        practice of medicine. But, <lb/>while the preſent treats of a ſubject purely of a
        <lb/>practical nature, it is, at the ſame time, the work <lb/>of one, who, from long and
        extenſive practice, <lb/>has been enabled to deliver the reſult of judi- <lb/>cious and
        accurate obſervation. </p>
      <pb n="408"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Although the practice of inoculation has been <lb/>attended with the moſt beneficial
        effects in ren- <lb/>dering the ſmall-pox a much leſs mortal diſeaſe, <lb/>yet this practice
        is by no means ſo general, that <lb/>bad caſes, from accidental infection, do not fre-
        <lb/>quently occur. The great object of the preſent <lb/>diſſertation is to deliver proper
        rules for the treat- <lb/>ment of ſuch, and to eſtablish the power of mer- <lb/>cury as a
        ſpecific againſt this contagion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In as far as reſpects the treatment, Doctor <lb/>Fowler thinks that the ſmall-pox may
        be moſt <lb/>properly divided into three ſtages. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>1<hi rend="italic">ſt</hi>, The eruptive ſtage, extending from the <lb/>firſt acceſſion
        of the eruptive fever to the termi- <lb/>nation of the eruption. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2<hi rend="italic">d</hi>, The inflammatory ſtage, extending from <lb/>the time that
        the eruption is compleated, till ſigns <lb/>of debility or putreſcency occur. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>3<hi rend="italic">d</hi>, The ſtage of debility or putridity, extend- <lb/>ing from
        the commencement of the ſymptoms of <lb/>ſuch conditions, till the final termination of the
        <lb/>diſeaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After laying down this general diviſion, he <lb/>next proceeds to offer ſome
        obſervations on the <lb/>treatment to be followed during each of theſe <lb/>ſtages. </p>
      <pb n="409"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The great object which he thinks ought to be <lb/>aimed at during the eruptive ſtage,
        is a diminu- <lb/>tion of the quantity of variolous matter in the <lb/>ſyſtem. And this, he
        thinks, is to be effected in <lb/>two ways: By exhibiting mercury as a ſpecific, <lb/>and by
        moderating the re-action of the ſyſtem <lb/>by the uſe of cathartics, gentle diaphoretics,
        opi- <lb/>ates, blood-letting, antiphlogiſtic regimen, but <lb/>eſpecially by light
        clothing, aceſcent watery li- <lb/>quors, and pure free air. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From the perſuaſion that mercury operates as <lb/>a ſpecific, he holds that it ought to
        be exhibited <lb/>in as great quantities, during the eruptive fever, <lb/>as the inteſtines
        and ſyſtem can bear. And for <lb/>that purpoſe he recommends the following for- <lb/>mulae: </p>
      <floatingText><body>
        <p rend="hanging size(0.8)">
          <lb/>℞ Mercurii dulcis ſublimati ppt. drachmam dimidiam <lb/>Pilularum ex colocynthide cum
          aloe drachmam unam <lb/>Contundendo bene miſce, ut fiat maſſa pilularis. <lb/>Doſis pro
          adultis circiter drachmam dimidiam <lb/>Doſis pro aegris, annos decem natis, circiter
          ſcrupu- <lb/>lum unum. </p></body>
      </floatingText>
      <floatingText><body>
        <p rend="hanging size(0.8)">
          <lb/>℞ Mercurii dulcis ſublimati, ppt. <lb/>Pulveris radicis jalappi <lb/>Florum
          ſulphuris, ſingulorum drachmam unam. <lb/>Diligenter miſce. <pb n="410"/>
          <lb/>Doſis pro aegris annos quinque habentibus, grana <lb/>quindecim. <lb/>——annos tres
          habentibus, grana duodecim. <lb/>——infantibus annum unum natis, grana octo. </p></body>
      </floatingText>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>With regard to infants, he lays it down as an <lb/>univerſal rule, that three fourths
        of the doſe are <lb/>to be given at firſt, and the remainder at the end <lb/>of four hours,
        if looſeneſs has not come on before <lb/>that. He adviſes that this mercurial purgative
        <lb/>ſhould be repeated every ſecond day. And on <lb/>thoſe days on which no purgative is
        taken, he <lb/>orders for an adult five grains of the common <lb/>mercurial pill of the
        London college, or ten <lb/>grains of that of Edinburgh, and for younger <lb/>patients in
        proportion to the age. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>With reſpect to moderating the reaction of <lb/>the ſyſtem, the directions which he
        gives con- <lb/>cerning the uſe of cathartics, diaphoretics, blood- <lb/>letting, and the
        like, are very much the ſame <lb/>with thoſe laid down by other practitioners. But <lb/>we
        ought, perhaps, to conſider it as, in ſome <lb/>meaſure, a peculiarity in modern practice,
        when <lb/>he adviſes a doſe of liquid laudanum to be given <lb/>every night after the
        operation of the cathartic. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>During the ſecond ſtage, our author adviſes, <lb/>that the attention of the
        practitioner be directed <pb n="411"/>
        <lb/>towards obtaining a laudable ſuppuration. And <lb/>this, he imagines, is chiefly to be
        brought about <lb/>by continuing the uſe of the mercury, and by <lb/>counteracting the
        effects of irritation reſulting <lb/>from cutaneous inflammation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>During the third and laſt ſtage, a laudable ſup- <lb/>puration is only to be obtained
        by counteracting <lb/>the diſposition to debility and to putridity. For <lb/>this purpoſe,
        the Peruvian bark, acid elixir of <lb/>vitriol, wine, and opiates, are to be conſidered
        <lb/>as the principal aids. But, beſides theſe, he fur- <lb/>ther adviſes, that the patient
        uſe for aliment fa- <lb/>rinaceous and aceſcent food, and for drink, aci- <lb/>dulated and
        watery fluids. And he conſiders <lb/>it as further neceſſary, that care be taken to a-
        <lb/>void the accumulation of variolous matter on the <lb/>ſurface of the body, to avoid
        unuſual evacuations, <lb/>and to keep the belly gently open. Beſides theſe <lb/>means, in
        ſome inſtances it is alſo neceſſary to <lb/>have recourſe to bliſters. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>While he imagines that, during the two for- <lb/>mer ſtages, this diſeaſe is to be
        treated as inflam- <lb/>matory, he conſiders it during this ſtage, when <lb/>the ſmall-pox
        are of the confluent kind, as aſſu- <lb/>ming the form of a typhus. Hence then a very <pb
          n="412"/>
        <lb/>different mode of treatment becomes neceſſary, <lb/>and in place of farther
        endeavouring to moderate <lb/>reaction, all evacuation muſt be avoided, and en-
        <lb/>deavours employed for ſupporting the vis vitae <lb/>and general tone of the ſyſtem.
        With theſe in- <lb/>tentions the directions which he delivers reſpec- <lb/>ting the uſe of
        Peruvian bark, wine, opiates, <lb/>and other remedies, are little different from <lb/>what
        are delivered by the greater part of the <lb/>moderns. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Beſides the particulars already mentioned, Dr <lb/>Fowler obſerves, that much might
        alſo be ſaid <lb/>reſpecting the means to be employed for miti- <lb/>gating anomalous
        ſymptoms. But, as his prin- <lb/>cipal object in this diſſertation was to eſtabliſh <lb/>the
        power of mercury as a ſpecific, without en- <lb/>tering on the conſideration of theſe, he
        concludes <lb/>this eſſay by offering ſome arguments in ſup- <lb/>port of this opinion. Of
        theſe the following <lb/>are the principal. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>1. He has uniformly obſerved, that, when pa- <lb/>tients under the proceſs of
        inoculation had taken <lb/>calomel by way of purgative, to ſuch an extent as <lb/>gently to
        affect the mouth, the diſeaſe was inva- <lb/>riably mild. </p>
      <pb n="413"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>2. He has found that, when ſmall doſes of <lb/>calomel were given to ſuch an extent as
        to af- <lb/>fect the mouth without inducing catharſis, the <lb/>diſeaſe was equally mild as
        when it had the ef- <lb/>fect of producing evacuation by ſtool. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>3. He has remarked, that, although the num- <lb/>ber of puſtles from inoculation, where
        no mer- <lb/>cury was taken, be often but inconſiderable; yet, <lb/>in conſequence of the
        uſe of mercury, they never <lb/>fail to become more mild, and to terminate ſoon- <lb/>er
        than would otherwiſe be the caſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>4. He has oftener than once had occaſion to <lb/>exhibit mercury to children in
        families where the <lb/>ſmall-pox were particularly ſevere, with the view <lb/>of their
        being afterwards inoculated; but, from <lb/>the occurrence of accidental contagion at the
        <lb/>time, the operation has been prevented. And, <lb/>in theſe caſes, the diſeaſe aſſumed
        the ſame mild <lb/>form as if the infection had been given by ino- <lb/>culation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>5. He has often exhibited to patients, after <lb/>they were affected with the ſymptoms
        of ſmall- <lb/>pox without inoculation, calomel, in full doſes as <lb/>a cathartic, with
        remarkable ſucceſs, the quanti- <lb/>ty of the eruption never being ſo great as might
        <lb/>be concluded from the preceding ſymptoms. </p>
      <pb n="414"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>To theſe arguments, drawn from his own ob- <lb/>ſervation, he ſubjoins the ſentiments
        of ſeveral <lb/>eminent practitioners, which ſeem to confirm the <lb/>ſame doctrine,
        particularly thoſe of Boerhaave, <lb/>Tennent, Mead, Tomlinſon, Blake, and Lett- <lb/>ſome.
        And he concludes his obſervations on <lb/>this ſubject, by anſwering ſome objections which
        <lb/>may be brought againſt this doctrine, particular- <lb/>ly thoſe drawn from caſes where
        the diſeaſe has <lb/>been very ſlight from inoculation without the <lb/>uſe of mercury, and
        thoſe where patients had <lb/>been attacked with the ſmall-pox during a mer- <lb/>curial
        courſe for other diſeaſes, notwithſtanding <lb/>which, this affection was very ſevere. In
        anſwer <lb/>to the firſt, he propoſes many circumſtances <lb/>which muſt at leaſt create
        doubt; and the latter <lb/>he conſiders as a very rare occurrence. Hence <lb/>he thinks it
        might, with equal juſtice, be con- <lb/>tended, that mercury does not cure lues venerea,
        <lb/>or Peruvian bark intermittent fevers, becauſe <lb/>theſe alſo ſometimes fail. While,
        therefore, he <lb/>conſiders theſe objections as of no weight, he <lb/>views the doctrine of
        the ſpecific power of mer- <lb/>cury againſt the variolous infection, as eſtabliſhed
        <lb/>both by the ſentiments of others, and his own <lb/>obſervation. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
