<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Cruttwell: Advice to Lying - in Women, chiefly respecting the Custom
          of drawing the Breasts</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>C. Cruttwell</persName>
            </author>
            <title>II. Advice to Lying - in Women, chiefly respecting the Custom of drawing the
              Breasts. By C. Cruttwell, Surgeon at Bath. 12mo. Bath.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society in Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for J. Murray, No, 32, Fleet-street. M. Drummond, J.
                  Bell, W. Creech, and C. Elliot, Edinburgh.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1779</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">6</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">258-262</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW109877913</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v6_0258">
    <body>
      <pb n="258"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>II. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Advice to Lying-in Women, chiefly reſpecting the <lb/>Cuſtom of drawing the Breaſts. By
          <hi rend="roman">C. Crutt- <lb/>well</hi>, Surgeon at Bath. 12mo. <hi rend="roman"
          >Bath</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE intention of this treatiſe is to en- <lb/>counter a practice,
        which, according to <lb/>our author, is founded on prejudice, and is, at <lb/>the ſame time,
        unnatural, painful, and even <lb/>dangerous. Theſe concluſions are not pre- <lb/>ſented as
        the reſult of ſpeculative reaſoning, <lb/>but as founded on experience; while, at the
        <lb/>ſame time, he aſſures us, that the practice of <lb/>drawing the breaſts, however,
        powerfully ſup- <lb/>ported by cuſtom, may be omitted with ſafety <lb/>and eaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The author introduces his obſervations on <lb/>the ſubject, by giving a ſhort
        deſcription of <lb/>the breaſts, and ſome account of their uſe. <lb/>The ſubſtance of his
        obſervations is, that they <lb/>are glandular bodies, appropriated to the pur- <lb/>poſes of
        ſecretion, and that the liquor ſecreted <lb/>is by nature intended for the great and good
        <lb/>purpoſe of nouriſhing mankind in their infant <lb/>ſtate. While he accounts for the
        white colour <pb n="259"/>
        <lb/>of the milk, from its being a ſecretion which <lb/>takes place almoſt as ſoon as the
        chyle enters <lb/>the blood, he points out alſo the influence <lb/>which food and drink of
        different kinds have, <lb/>as affecting this ſecretion. And from the in- <lb/>fluence of
        intoxicating liquors on infants, if <lb/>taken by the mother when the breaſts are
        <lb/>empty, he concludes that the moſt reaſonable <lb/>method of encountering the diſeaſes
        of infants, <lb/>is from giving medicines by the mouth of the <lb/>mother. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the caſe of thoſe mothers who ſuckle <lb/>their own infants, if the child be put
        early to <lb/>the breaſt, obſtruction will ſeldom be met with; <lb/>but if the child be not
        put to the breaſt before <lb/>the third day, this organ becomes full, turgid, <lb/>and
        ſomewhat painful. In this caſe the infant <lb/>is often unable to draw forth the milk, and
        not <lb/>ſo much from the urgency of preſent ſymp- <lb/>toms, as with the view of preventing
        abſceſſes, <lb/>ſchirrhus, cancer, and the like; it has been a <lb/>common practice to hire
        a woman for the <lb/>purpoſe of drawing the breaſts. By this means <lb/>our author aſſirms,
        that endeavours to prevent <lb/>imaginary evils are productive of real diſeaſe. <lb/>For if
        in this ſtate of fullness and hardneſs, <lb/>the breaſt were guarded againſt every external
          <pb n="260"/>
        <lb/>injury, the ſwelling would ſubſide, even in <lb/>a few hours, and the child might be
        put to it <lb/>with ſafety and with effect. On the other <lb/>hand, external irritation at
        this time, ſuch as <lb/>that which muſt ariſe from drawing the <lb/>breaſts, produces
        inflammation and all its con- <lb/>ſequences, fever, abſceſs, and the like; and
        <lb/>although the author does not poſitively aſſert, <lb/>that theſe accidents proceed only
        from this <lb/>cauſe, yet he affirms, that, in his own practice, <lb/>he never met with any
        inſtance of milk-fever <lb/>or abſceſs in the breaſt, where that organ had <lb/>not been
        drawn, or had not received ſome ex- <lb/>ternal injury. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having formed this concluſion reſpecting <lb/>the cauſe of theſe ſymptoms, Mr.
        Cruttwell <lb/>next proceeds to lay down thoſe directions, by <lb/>which ſuch accidents may
        beſt be prevented. <lb/>Firſt, he conſiders the meaſures which are to <lb/>be followed when
        the child is to be ſuckled <lb/>by the mother; and afterwards, when it is <lb/>not to be
        ſuckled. In the firſt caſe, he adviſes <lb/>that the child ſhould be put to the breaſt in
        <lb/>about twelve hours after delivery; and that, <lb/>previous to this, no food ſhould be
        given it. <lb/>If from neglecting this, the breaſts become <lb/>turgid, and affected with a
        throbbing pain tend- <pb n="261"/>
        <lb/>ing to inflammations, he ſtill adviſes that <lb/>they ſhould not be meddled with. And
        he <lb/>aſſures us, that if the affection be not ſup- <lb/>ported by the heat of the room,
        by cordial <lb/>medicines, hot liquors, or ſimilar cauſes, the <lb/>throbbing and fullneſs
        will cease in ſix, eight, <lb/>or at farthest in twelve hours. When external <lb/>injuries
        have been ſuch, that a cure cannot thus <lb/>be effected, our author adviſes, the applica-
        <lb/>tion of the ſaponaceous cerate, from which he <lb/>tells us that the obſtruction will
        be reſolved <lb/>and the milk re-abſorbed. When this fails <lb/>of effect, and a ſuppuration
        enſues, he adviſes, <lb/>that the matter ſhould be diſcharged merely <lb/>by a flight
        puncture, which he affirms, will <lb/>in all caſes be perfectly ſufficient. And after
        <lb/>an opening is thus made, he thinks, that the <lb/>ſaponaceous cerate is much preſerable
        to thoſe <lb/>poultices which are in general recommended. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The directions which he gives in caſes <lb/>where a child is not to be ſuckled, or
        where, <lb/>from any ſupervening diſeaſe, it becomes ne- <lb/>ceſſary that a child ſhould be
        removed from <lb/>the breaſt, are nearly the ſame with thoſe <lb/>which have been mentioned
        above. He con- <lb/>demns the uſe of all ſpirituous applications or <lb/>plaſters, applied
        with the view of repelling. And <pb n="262"/>
        <lb/>on the other hand, when milk is accumulated <lb/>in the breaſts, ſo as to produce a
        throbbing <lb/>pain, he conſiders the practice of drawing <lb/>them to be both unneceſſary
        and improper. <lb/>He affirms, that when they are left to nature, <lb/>they will never be
        attended with any bad con- <lb/>ſequences. This practice he recommends as <lb/>the reſult of
        long and attentive experience, <lb/>unbiaſſed by prejudice, and ſupported by ſuc- <lb/>ceſs.
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
