<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: Medical News</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>SECT. III. Medical News.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society in Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for J. Murray, No, 32, Fleet-street. M. Drummond, J.
                  Bell, W. Creech, and C. Elliot, Edinburgh.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1779</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">6</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">346-356</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW109877913</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v6_0346">
    <body>
      <pb n="346"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>SECT. III. </head>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <head rend="italic align-center">
        <lb/>Medical News. </head>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <figure>
        <figDesc>An ornamented horizontal line, spanning the whole page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <div type="section">
        <p>
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>He Royal Society of Medicine, lately <lb/>eſtabliſhed at
          Paris, of which we have <lb/>already given ſome account, have lately diſtri- <lb/>buted
          among their members ſeveral printed pa- <lb/>pers, reſpecting the nature and intention of
          their <lb/>inſtitution. Among theſe are the following: </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Lettres patentes du Roi, pour l'etabliſſement <lb/>d'une Société Royale de Medecine,
          données a <lb/>Verſailles au mois d'Août, 1778, regiſtrées en <lb/>parlement le 1<hi
            rend="sup">er</hi> Septembre audit an. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Travaux propoſés aux medecins et phyſi- <lb/>ciens regnicoles &amp; etrangers, par la
          Société <lb/>Royale de Medecine dans ſa Seance publique <pb n="347"/>
          <lb/>tenüe le Mardi 20 Octobre 1778, au College <lb/>Royal de France. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Prix propoſés par la Société Royale de Me- <lb/>decine dans ſa Seance publique, tenüe
          le Mardi, <lb/>20 Octobre, 1778, au College Royal de <lb/>France. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>To the letters patent is ſubjoined, an accu- <lb/>rate liſt of all the members of the
          ſociety, di- <lb/>vided into the five claſſes of, Officiers de la ſo- <lb/>ciété, Aſſociés
          ordinaires, Aſſociés libres, Aſſo- <lb/>ciés regnicoles, Associés etrangers. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is propoſed that the memoirs of the ſo- <lb/>ciety ſhall conſiſt of the following
          ſubjects. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>1. Les Details des deux Seances publiques de <lb/>chaque Année, les Programmes des
          prix, l'Eloge <lb/>des aſſociés Morts, les Noms de ceux qui cor- <lb/>reſpondent &amp; une
          Notice de leurs Ouvrages. <lb/>2. Les Obſervations Meteorologiques, faites <lb/>dans les
          differentes Parties de la France, dont <lb/>le Preſident de la Société a l'Honneur de pre-
          <lb/>ſenter chaque ſemaine les reſultats au Roi. 3. <lb/>La Topographie medicale des
          differentes Villes <lb/>&amp; Cantons. 4°. La Deſcription des Maladies <lb/>Endemiques.
          5°. Celle des Maladies Epide- <lb/>miques. 6°. Celle des Epizooties. 7°. Des
          <lb/>Obſervations de Medecine-pratique. 8°. Des <pb n="348"/>
          <lb/>Obſervations Chirurgicales. 9°. Des Obſer- <lb/>vations Anatomiques. 10°. Des
          Obſervations <lb/>de Chymie-Medicale, &amp; Analyſe des differentes <lb/>Eaux minerales.
            11<hi rend="sup">mo</hi>. Des Obſervations de <lb/>Botanique. 12<hi rend="sup">mo</hi>.
          Des Obſervations de Phy- <lb/>ſique-generale. 13<hi rend="sup">mo</hi>. Les Details des
          Re- <lb/>cherches &amp; Experiences ordonnées par la So- <lb/>ciété. 14<hi rend="sup"
            >mo</hi>. Les Diſſertations qui auront <lb/>remporté les Prix. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>After thus pointing out the different parti- <lb/>culars, which are intended to be
          the ſubject of <lb/>their publications, they conclude with obſerv- <lb/>ing, that there is
          no phyſician or philoſopher <lb/>who may not contribute ſomething to their col-
          <lb/>lection, by beſtowing attention at the place of <lb/>his reſidence to the objects
          mentioned above. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The following queſtions are propoſed as the <lb/>ſubjects of enquiry for the prize
          diſſertations. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I. Determiner quel peut être le meilleur Trait- <lb/>ment de la Rage. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>II. D'établir 1° par l'Analyſe Chymique, <lb/>quelle eſt la Nature des Remedes
          Antiſcorbu- <lb/>tiques proprement dits. 2°. Par l'Obſervation, <lb/>quel doit être leur
          Uſage, &amp; leur combinaiſon <lb/>dans les différentes eſpeces &amp; complications,
          <lb/>&amp; dans les differens degres du Scorbut. </p>
        <pb n="349"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>III. Exiſte-t-il veritablement une Fievre <lb/>Miliaire eſſentielle et diſtincte des
          autres Fievres <lb/>Exanthematiques &amp; dans quelle Conſtitution <lb/>doit-elle être
          rangée. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>IV. Determiner par un Nombre ſuffiſant <lb/>d'Obſervations &amp; d'Experiences
          exactes ſi les <lb/>Maladies contagieuſes, principalement la Pe- <lb/>tite Verole, peuvent
          ſe tranſmettre par l'Inter- <lb/>méde de 1'Air. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>V. D'indiquer la meilleure Methode pour <lb/>guerir promptement &amp; ſurement la
          Gale, con- <lb/>tractée par Communication, comme il arrive <lb/>dans les Caſernes, dans
          les Atteliers, dans les <lb/>Hôpitaux &amp; dans les Priſons. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>VI. Fair connoitre le moyen le plus prompt, <lb/>le moins diſpendieux et en
          même-temps le <lb/>plus ſûr pour guerir la Gonorrhée virulente <lb/>&amp; pour prevenir
          les accidens qui en ſont ordi- <lb/>nairment les ſuites. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Memoirs on theſe different ſubjects, accom- <lb/>panied with a ſealed billet,
          containing the name <lb/>of the author, and marked on the back with <lb/>the ſame motto as
          the memoir, muſt be tranſ- <lb/>mitted to M. Vicq d'Azyr, Secretaire perpe- <lb/>tuel de
          la Société Royale de Medecine, Rue de <lb/>Sepulcre, a Paris. </p>
      </div>
      <pb n="350"/>
      <div type="section">
        <p rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>***** </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Mr. John Aitken, ſurgeon in Edinburgh, who <lb/>has for ſome years paſt delivered
          lectures on <lb/>that branch of the medical art, has at preſent <lb/>in the preſs a work
          entitled, Elements of Syſ- <lb/>tematic Surgery, which will ſpeedily be pub- <lb/>liſhed.
          This work, which is principally intended <lb/>as a text-book for future courſes of
          lectures, is, <lb/>however, written upon ſuch a plan as to be <lb/>adapted for other
          readers. It conſiſts of three <lb/>parts. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>1. Introduction, or Preliminary Obſervations <lb/>reſpecting Medicine; its Diviſion
          into Phyſic <lb/>and Surgery; their Limits, &amp;c. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>2. Chirurgical Noſology, or a Methodical <lb/>Arrangement of Chirurgical Diſeaſes,
          with the <lb/>Synonyma, Definitions, and Remarks on their <lb/>Nature, Seats, Varieties,
          and Remedies. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>3. Chirurgical Operation, or, an Enume- <lb/>ration and Explication of Manual
          Surgery, <lb/>correſpondent to the Noſology. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <p rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>***** </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Dr. John Purcell, one of the profeſſors of <lb/>anatomy in Trinity-College, Dublin,
          has lately <lb/>tranſmitted to the Medical Society of Edinburgh, <pb n="351"/>
          <lb/>an Eſſay, containing many intereſting remarks <lb/>on the operation of the ſection of
          the ſymphiſis <lb/>pubis, which has lately been ſo much the ſubject <lb/>of controverſy at
          Paris. In this paper, among <lb/>other particulars, Dr. Purcell endeavours to <lb/>ſhew,
          that this operation, which has hitherto <lb/>been propoſed only for the extraction of the
          <lb/>fœtus in caſes for which the Cæſarian ſection <lb/>was formerly recommended, promiſes
          to be <lb/>productive of ſtill greater advantage in caſes <lb/>of retroverted uterus,
          which would otherwiſe <lb/>prove fatal. How far his reaſoning upon this <lb/>ſubject is
          ſufficient to render the operation ad- <lb/>viſeable, our readers will be beſt able to
          judge, <lb/>from a candid peruſal of the paper itſelf, which <lb/>will appear in the firſt
          volume of the Tranſ- <lb/>actions of the Medical Society, a work which is <lb/>at preſent
          preparing for the preſs. Mean while, <lb/>the communicating to our readers, this propo-
          <lb/>ſal of Dr. Purcell's, may, perhaps, be of ſome <lb/>uſe; if this practice ſhall ſeem
          adviſeable to <lb/>thoſe, to whom ſuch unfortunate caſes may <lb/>occur. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <p rend="align-center">
          <lb/>***** </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Dr. Odier, of Geneva, in a letter to Dr. <lb/>Duncan, communicates to him the
          following <pb n="352"/>
          <lb/>obſervation reſpecting the uſe of different re- <lb/>medies in fevers of the
          intermittent kind. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>
          <q rend="quotes">We have here repeated the obſervations of <lb/>Dr. Lind on the
            uſe of opium in intermittents, <lb/>and almoſt always with the greateſt ſucceſs. <lb/>We
            give laudanum as he does, to the extent <lb/>of twenty-five drops, half an hour after
            the be- <lb/>ginning of the hot fit, and we find that it <lb/>ſhortens it much. It calms
            the anxiety and <lb/>head-ach, which generally accompany it. It <lb/>brings on ſweating
            much ſooner, and renders <lb/>it more profuſe. It makes even the return of <lb/>the
            paroxyſms more regular; and has, in ſome <lb/>inſtances, been alone ſufficient to ſtop
            the fever <lb/>altogether. In general, however, a few doſes <lb/>of Peruvian bark, with
            ſome purgatives, are <lb/>neceſſary. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>
          <q>We have given opium even in caſes where <lb/>Dr. Lind thinks that it ought not
            to be given, <lb/>and with equal ſucceſs; I mean thoſe in which <lb/>there is much
            delirium, which we have never <lb/>found to be encreaſed by it, but on the con-
            <lb/>trary, much oftener to be removed and always <lb/>to be diminiſhed. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>
          <q>I remember to have ſeen a caſe in St. Tho- <lb/>mas's hoſpital, in London, of
            a quartan ague, <pb n="353"/>
            <lb/>which had laſted two years, and in which Dr. <lb/>Fordyce gave a doſe of Dover's
            powder, with a <lb/>ſweating draught of ſalt of hartſhorn, two <lb/>hours before the fit
            in order to ſtop it. This <lb/>ſucceeded very well. A profuſe ſweat came <lb/>on juſt
            before the hour at which the cold fit <lb/>uſed to return, and it was altogether
            prevent- <lb/>ed. Some doſes of Peruvian bark were af- <lb/>terwards adminiſtered; and
            this fever, which <lb/>had before reſiſted many remedies, even the <lb/>bark itſelf, was
            then in a few days effectually <lb/>cured. </q>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>
          <q rend="quotes">This obſervation we have had many oppor- <lb/>tunities of
            repeating here; not only in quar- <lb/>tan, but alſo in tertian agues; and we find,
            <lb/>that whenever the patient can be brought to <lb/>ſweat, the fit is altogether
            ſtopt. If he does <lb/>not ſweat, the fit is nevertheleſs much dimi- <lb/>niſhed
            thereby. </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <p rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>***** </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On Thurſday, the 28th of October, Dr. <lb/>Duncan will begin at Edinburgh, his
          lectures <lb/>on the Theory and Practice of Medicine. <lb/>This courſe of lectures will be
          concluded about <lb/>the beginning of May. Five lectures are read <lb/>every week, and the
          ſame lecture is repeated <pb n="354"/>
          <lb/>twice every day, viz. between eleven and <lb/>twelve o'clock in the forenoon, and
          between <lb/>five and ſix o'clock in the evening. The fee <lb/>for attendance is two
          guineas; and every ſtu- <lb/>dent has it in his option to attend at either, or <lb/>at
          both hours. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On Saturday, the 30th of October, Dr. <lb/>Duncan will begin a courſe of lectures on
          the <lb/>caſes of patients ſubjected to chronical diſ- <lb/>eaſes. This courſe will alſo
          continue till the <lb/>beginning of May. One lecture being deli- <lb/>vered every
          Saturday. The moſt important <lb/>caſes which occur at the public Diſpenſary will <lb/>be
          ſelected as the ſubjects of theſe lectures; <lb/>and, in treating of each caſe, the
          obſervations <lb/>which are offered will be entirely confined to <lb/>ſuch remarks on the
          hiſtory and method of <lb/>treatment, as appear to be of the greateſt uti- <lb/>lity in
          practice. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>About the beginning of May, Dr. Duncan <lb/>and Dr. Webſter, will begin their courſe
          of <lb/>caſe lectures for the ſummer ſeſſion. This <lb/>courſe will continue for about
          three months, <lb/>and beſides the lectures on the caſes of pa- <lb/>tients, which will be
          delivered every Monday <lb/>and Thurſday, lectures will alſo be given <lb/>every Tueſday,
          Wedneſday, and Friday, con- <pb n="355"/>
          <lb/>taining remarks on the Pharmacopœias of the <lb/>Colleges of Phyſicians of London and
          Edin- <lb/>burgh. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <p rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>***** </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The Dutch Society of Sciences, eſtabliſhed <lb/>at Harlem, in their Programma for the
          year <lb/>1779, beſides the ſubjects for prize diſſerta- <lb/>tions relating to aſtronomy
          and ſome branches <lb/>of general phyſics, have propoſed the follow- <lb/>ing, which are
          more ſtrictly medical. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>1. Quelle eſt la veritable nature des Brouil- <lb/>lards ou exhalaiſons marines qu'on
          nomme en <lb/>Hollande <hi rend="italic">Zeevlammen?</hi> Quels effets produiſ-
          <lb/>ſent-ils, &amp; quels ſont les moyens d'en preve- <lb/>nir les ſuites pernicieuſes? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>2. La pureté de l'atmoſphere a la plus grande <lb/>influence ſur la ſanté des
          habitans d'une ville. <lb/>Celle de <hi rend="italic">Batavia</hi> eſt dans
          l'impoſſibilité d'en <lb/>jouir, par les vapeurs infectés des eaux de la <lb/>riviere, qui
          ſont ou ſtagnantes ou coulantes <lb/>trop lentement, &amp; qui ſe rempliſſent journelle-
          <lb/>ment de pluſieurs milles de livres d'immon- <lb/>dice.—Quels ſeroient les meilleurs
          moyens <lb/>d'accelerer le courant, &amp; d'effectuer une de- <lb/>charge plus prompte
          &amp; plus efficace de ces in- <pb n="356"/>
          <lb/><choice>
            <corr>fections</corr>
            <sic>infections</sic>
          </choice> , afin de procurer a la ville de Bata- <lb/>via un atmoſphere plus pur &amp;
          plus ſalubre? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>3. Quelle eſt l'influence du deſſechiment des <lb/>Marais, Etangs, &amp;c. ſur l'état
          de notre pais? <lb/>Quelles en ſont les ſuites utiles on nuiſibles? <lb/>Et dans le
          dernier cas quelles ſont le precau- <lb/>tions a prendre pour prevenir ces ſuites? </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Those who chuſe to employ themſelves in <lb/>giving anſwers to theſe queſtions, are
          deſired to <lb/>tranſmit them before the firſt of January, <lb/>1780. The anſwers to the
          queſtions propoſed, <lb/>as well as the direction on the back of the <lb/>letter which
          accompanies them, muſt not be <lb/>of the hand-writing of the author, nor ſigned <lb/>by
          his name, or place of abode; but marked <lb/>with a device or motto, and accompanied with
          <lb/>a ſealed letter, having the ſame device for its <lb/>direction, and containing the
          name and addreſs <lb/>of the author. The diſſertations muſt be <lb/>written in the Dutch,
          French, or Latin lan- <lb/>guage, and addreſſed to Mr. C. C. H. Vander <lb/>Aa, ſecretary
          to the ſociety. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Dr. John Hope, profeſſor of Botany in the <lb/>Univerſity of Edinburgh, has lately
          been <lb/>elected a member of the Harlem Society. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
