<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Johnstone: A Treatise on the malignant Angina, or putrid and ulcerous
          Sore Throat</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>J. Johnstone</persName>
            </author>
            <title>IV. A Treatise on the malignant Angina, or putrid and ulcerous Sore Throat. To
              which are added, some Remarks on the Angina Trachealis. By J. Johnstone, M. D. 8vo.
              Worcester.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society in Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for J. Murray, No, 32, Fleet-street. M. Drummond, J.
                  Bell, W. Creech, and C. Elliot, Edinburgh.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1779</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">6</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">267-279</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW109877913</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v6_0267">
    <body>
      <pb n="267"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>IV. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>A Treatiſe on the malignant Angina, or putrid and <lb/>ulcerous Sore Throat. To which
        are added, ſome <lb/>Remarks on the Angina Trachealis. By <hi rend="roman">J. John-
          <lb/>ſtone</hi>, M. D. 8vo. <hi rend="roman">Worceſter</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE principal part of this diſſertation <lb/>was publiſhed five
        years ago, as a theſis, <lb/>at Edinburgh. But the author, having ſince <lb/>that time had
        an opportunity of making ſeve- <lb/>ral valuable additions to it, has now thought
        <lb/>proper to preſent it to the public in its preſent <lb/>form. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr. Johnſtone adopts the definition of this <lb/>diſorder as given by Dr. Cullen, under
        the ſe- <lb/>cond ſpecies of cynanche, viz. <q rend="paradiple">a red painful <lb/>ſwelling
          of the tonſils, and mucous mem- <lb/>brane of the fauces, attended with ulcers, <lb/>which
          are covered with white, or aſh-coloured <lb/>ſloughs, with a putrid exanthematous fever,
          <lb/>and with difficulty of breathing and ſwallow- <lb/>ing </q>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From many paſſages in the writings of Hip- <lb/>pocrates, Celſus, and other ancients,
        Dr. <lb/>Johnſtone endeavours to prove, that they were <pb n="268"/>
        <lb/>well acquainted with this diſeaſe. How far <lb/>he is right in this conjecture, our
        readers will <lb/>beſt determine, from comparing their writings <lb/>with the very full and
        accurate enumeration of <lb/>ſymptoms, which they will find in this treatiſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After giving a very diſtinct hiſtory of the <lb/>diſeaſe, the author next proceeds to
        the <lb/>diagnoſis, or means of diſtinction between <lb/>this and ſome other ſpecies of
        angina. The <lb/>inflammatory angina, is, we are told, of every <lb/>other diſeaſe the moſt
        liable to be confounded <lb/>with the putrid ſore throat. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Children, women, the relaxed, weak, and <lb/>ſickly, are moſt liable to the malignant
        angi- <lb/>na; adults, men, the healthy, and robuſt, are <lb/>moſt ſubject to the
        inflammatory. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The malignant ſpecies is moſt common in <lb/>autumn, and is highly contagious. The in-
        <lb/>flammatory uſually appears in the ſpring, and <lb/>is never contagious. Both of them
        begin <lb/>with ſhivering; but the malignant is more <lb/>commonly attended with ſickneſs,
        vomiting, <lb/>purging, and acute pain of the head, than the <lb/>inflammatory. In the
        former the pulſe is <lb/>quick, weak, unequal, and fluttering; ſome- <lb/>times heavy and
        undoſe. In the latter it is <pb n="269"/>
        <lb/>frequent, ſtrong, full, and hard. The malig- <lb/>nant is attended with but little
        pain; the in- <lb/>flammatory with very acute pain. The ma- <lb/>lignant ſort is always
        attended with proſtration <lb/>of ſtrength, dejection of ſpirits, perpetual an- <lb/>xiety,
        ſighing, and great oppreſſion at the præ- <lb/>cordia, with dull, heavy, watery eyes. But
        <lb/>whenever ſloughs appear, eſpecially if they are <lb/>accompanied with a purple or
        eryſipelatous <lb/>eruption upon the ſkin, there can then be <lb/>no doubt concerning the
        true nature of the <lb/>diſeaſe, and all ſuſpicion of inflammatory an- <lb/>gina muſt
        vaniſh. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There is but one other ſpecies of angina, <lb/>we are told, from which this diſeaſe
        requires <lb/>any diſtinction, and that is, the croup, angina <lb/>inſantium, or ſuffocatio
        ſtridula. A ſmall de- <lb/>gree of attention to the ſeveral diviſions of that
        <lb/>diſtemper, as made by the beſt writers, will ſhew <lb/>that in reſpect to many of the
        caſes there can <lb/>be no diſtinction, becauſe in reality there is <lb/>no difference. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſpaſmodic and inflammatory ſpecies of <lb/>croup, are diſtinguiſhed from this
        diſeaſe in <lb/>the ſame manner as inflammatory angina; but <lb/>with reſpect to the putrid
        ſpecies of croup, as <lb/>it is attended with the very ſymptoms of ma- <pb n="270"/>
        <lb/>lignant angina; as diſſections after death prove <lb/>the trachea to be in it affected
        in the ſame <lb/>manner as in the malignant angina; as the <lb/>writings of Huxham, and the
        experience of <lb/>other phyſicians aſſure us, that the ſtridulous <lb/>voice is a common
        attendant on malignant an- <lb/>gina; and, as all authors agree, that the pu- <lb/>trid
        ſuffocatio ſtridula is increaſed by the ſame <lb/>circumſtances, and cured by the ſame reme-
        <lb/>dies, there cannot be ſtronger reaſons, our au- <lb/>thor remarks, for arranging it
        among the va- <lb/>rieties of malignant angina, and hence he pro- <lb/>poſes the following
        diviſion of malignant <lb/>angina; viz. into angina maligna tonſillaris, <lb/>and angina
        maligna trachealis. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The firſt of theſe comprehends all caſes <lb/>where ulcerations are ſpread over every
        part <lb/>of the mouth and throat, when the larynx is <lb/>not affected, which are marked by
        the ordi- <lb/>nary ſymptoms, and diſcovered by inſpecting <lb/>the mouth and throat. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſecond takes in all caſes where ulcers <lb/>are formed in the larynx and bronchia,
        which <lb/>are diſcoverable by ſharpneſs and ſhrillneſs of <lb/>the voice, increaſed
        difficulty of reſpiration, <lb/>frequent cough, and expectoration of putrid <pb n="271"/>
        <lb/>mucus, at the ſame time that the fauces are <lb/>covered over with white ſloughs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This, we are told, is a diſtinction of ſome <lb/>importance, and deſerves attention,
        from its giv- <lb/>ing much aſſiſtance in forming a prognoſis of <lb/>the event; as when
        ulcers have found their <lb/>way into the trachea, a cure, our author ob- <lb/>ſerves, is
        very ſeldom to be expected. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After enumerating the various prediſpoſing, <lb/>occaſional, and exciting cauſes of
        this diſor- <lb/>der, Doctor Johnstone concludes, that, the <lb/>proximate cauſe conſiſts in
        a putrid acrimony <lb/>conveyed into the ſyſtem, and from which, he <lb/>thinks, all the
        ſymptoms are eaſily explained, <lb/>as ariſing from a debility of the nervous ſyſtem,
        <lb/>and a diſſolved ſtate of the circulating fluids. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the method of cure, our author obſerves <lb/>one general indication to be kept in
        view, is, <lb/>to correct the putreſcent tendency throughout <lb/>the ſyſtem in general, and
        to ſtop the pro- <lb/>greſs of putrefaction in particular parts. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The different remedies recommended by au- <lb/>thors, are here particularly enumerated,
        and <lb/>to each, Doctor Johnſtone ſubjoins his own <lb/>Opinion. </p>
      <pb n="272"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Bleeding</hi>, our author obſerves, has been re- <lb/>commended in
        this diſeaſe by ſome writers; <lb/>but he coincides entirely with Dr. Fothergill, <lb/>in
        condemning the practice; as inſtead of mi- <lb/>tigating any of the ſymptoms, it uniformly
        <lb/>tends to render them worſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Purging</hi>, like every other evacuations, which <lb/>diminiſh much
        the patient's ſtrength, always, <lb/>we are told, does harm, and ought to be <lb/>ſtrictly
        guarded againſt. To obviate coſtive- <lb/>neſs, ripe fruits and occaſional glyſters of the
        <lb/>antiſeptic kind, are recommended in prefer- <lb/>ence to purgatives. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When nauſea is very urgent in the begin- <lb/>ning of the diſeaſe, a gentle emetic is
        then <lb/>recommended both for emptying the ſtomach, <lb/>and for exciting a diaphoreſis. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Bliſters</hi>, notwithſtanding the ſeptic nature <lb/>of cantharides,
        we are told, have been found <lb/>uſeful in this complaint, by raiſing the pulſe, <lb/>and
        ſupporting the vis vita. They are often <lb/>applied with advantage to the throat itſelf. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Whenever nitre has been much employed <lb/>in the fever attending the malignant angina,
        <lb/>it has manifeſtly increaſed the heat and all <pb n="273"/>
        <lb/>the putrid ſymptoms. This might natu- <lb/>rally be expected, our author remarks, in a
        <lb/>fever attended with great depreſſion of the ner- <lb/>vous and circulating powers, from
        a remedy <lb/>which diminiſhes, inſtead of adding to the <lb/>ſtrength of thoſe powers. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A dependence upon ſpiritus Mindereri has <lb/>also, we are told, had bad conſequences,
        <lb/>when the tenuity of the blood was in any <lb/>degree conſiderable. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Fixed air</hi>, as a corrector of putreſcency, is re- <lb/>commended
        upon the authority of different <lb/>practitioners. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Although mercury has been propoſed by <lb/>ſome American phyſicians, in this diſorder,
        <lb/>yet, our author, thinks the practice exceed- <lb/>ingly hazardous, from the known
        evacuating <lb/>powers of mercury: every evacuation in the <lb/>malignant ſore throat, when
        carried to any ex- <lb/>tent, always, he obſerves, proves prejudicial. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">The vegetable</hi>, <hi rend="italic">mineral</hi>, and <hi
          rend="italic">dulcified acids</hi> are <lb/>all recommended in this diſorder; particularly
        <lb/>from their antiſeptic powers. But they cannot, <lb/>we are told, be given with freedom
        to infants <lb/>at the breaſt, becauſe they coagulate the <pb n="274"/>
        <lb/>milk, and ſo tend to produce diſorders of the <lb/>bowels. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pulvis contrayervæ compoſitus</hi>, in ſome cir- <lb/>cumſtances of
        diarrhœa, we are told, may poſ- <lb/>ſibly be uſed with propriety; but, in other
        <lb/>reſpects, it is a remedy without any other <lb/>recommendation than that of cuſtom and
        <lb/>faſhion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Confectio cardiaca</hi>, together with wine and <lb/>other cordials,
        is recommended, as tending to <lb/>make the pulſe fuller and ſtronger, and for <lb/>removing
        anxiety and leſſening ſickneſs. Wine <lb/>however, is ſaid, to be more effectual than
        <lb/>any of the others. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">Myrrh</hi> and <hi rend="italic">camphor</hi>, are both recommended
        <lb/>as powerful antiſeptics; the former, we are told, <lb/>although commonly preſcribed
        only in gar- <lb/>gles, yet may be uſed with much propriety <lb/>internally. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The efficacy of Peruvian bark, in this diſ- <lb/>eaſe, has, we are told, ſurpaſſed the
        healing <lb/>powers, experienced from it in every other <lb/>inſtance. Thoſe who have tried
        it most in <lb/>this complaint, beſt knowing how abſolutely <lb/>it ſubdues the diſeaſe,
        which is more certainly <lb/>cured by the early application of this remedy, <pb n="275"/>
        <lb/>than any diſeaſe, of equal conſequence, by any <lb/>means whatever. It here evidently
        acts as an an- <lb/>tiſeptic and tonic; it corrects putreſcency when <lb/>it is begun, and
        it reſiſts the proceſs of putre- <lb/>faction, by repairing the forces of nature, and
        <lb/>by giving that vigour to the nervous ſyſtem <lb/>which enables it to oppoſe and
        overcome the <lb/>diſeaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As it has been found inconvenient to admi- <lb/>niſter the bark in intermittent and
        remittent <lb/>fevers, at any time but during the intervals <lb/>of paroxyſms; ſo it has
        been queſtioned by <lb/>ſome, whether we ought not to wait for a re- <lb/>miſſion in the
        fever attending the malignant <lb/>ſore throat before we give the bark; but our <lb/>author
        is clearly of opinion, that this cauti- <lb/>ous mode of proceeding is by no means neceſ-
        <lb/>ſary, no inconvenience having ever, he ſays, <lb/>been obſerved to accompany or follow
        the uſe <lb/>of Peruvian bark, at the very height of the <lb/>fever attending this ſore
        throat; nay, we ought, <lb/>he thinks, to give it more frequently and in <lb/>larger
        quantities, in proportion to the height <lb/>of the fever. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As proper additions to Peruvian bark he re- <lb/>commends, decoctions or extracts of
        caſca- <pb n="276"/>
        <lb/>rilla bark, and of lignum Campechenſe, eſpe- <lb/>cially when there appears any
        propenſity to <lb/>diarrhœa. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By a proper combination and application of <lb/>theſe various remedies, in the method
        here <lb/>particularly pointed out by our author, prac- <lb/>titioners will ſeldom fail, we
        are told, to re- <lb/>move the diſorder, excepting in thoſe in- <lb/>ſtances where the
        trachea is affected; which <lb/>not only require ſome variety in the mode of <lb/>treatment,
        but are in reality much more dan- <lb/>gerous than where the mouth and tonſils are <lb/>only
        affected. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Doctor Johnſtone now proceeds to the more <lb/>particular conſideration of the <hi
          rend="italic">angina maligna <lb/>trachealis</hi>; after enumerating the opinions of
        <lb/>all the moſt eminent authors on this diſor- <lb/>der, and having given a diagnoſis,
        between <lb/>the ſpaſmodic, inflammatory, and malignant <lb/>ſpecies of it, he then proceeds
        to the ſpecific <lb/>treatment or method of cure peculiar to the <lb/>latter. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Whenever the larynx and trachea become <lb/>the ſeat of malignant angina, the whole me-
        <lb/>thod of cure directed for its more uſual form, <lb/>muſt then, we are told, be applied
        with unre- <pb n="277"/>
        <lb/><choice>
          <corr>mitting</corr>
          <sic>unremitting</sic>
        </choice> aſſiduity, though we are forbid to <lb/>indulge the ſame pleaſing hopes of ſucceſs
        <lb/>from the application of it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The air of the patient's chamber ſhould be <lb/>well impregnated with the ſteams of
        vinegar, <lb/>myrrh, and honey, which ought to be inceſ- <lb/>ſantly riſing at his bed-ſide
        and he ſhould be <lb/>directed to hold his mouth directly over the <lb/>veſſel, or elſe the
        ſteams muſt be conveyed im- <lb/>mediately into the mouth by means of a funnel. <lb/>Inſtead
        of common vinegar, acetum ſciliti- <lb/>cum has ſometimes been directed to be uſed <lb/>for
        ſteaming, and apparently with effect in pro- <lb/>moting expectoration. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Expectoration is alſo to be promoted by all <lb/>other probable means. To vomit the
        pati- <lb/>ent now and then with oxymel of ſquills, an- <lb/>ſwers this purpoſe, and
        forwards, we are told, <lb/>the ſeparation of the ſloughs; and ſmaller <lb/>dozes of oxymel
        of ſquills with gum ammo- <lb/>niac or aſſafœtida may afterwards be uſed to <lb/>keep up the
        ſame excretion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Assafœtida is here much recommended; and <lb/>after a little uſe, even children come to
        take <lb/>it, we are told, eaſier than gum ammoniac. <lb/>Whilſt the patient is taking the
        Peruvian bark, <pb n="278"/>
        <lb/>the principal remedy to be depended on, a large <lb/>ſpoonful or two of a ſtrong
        ſolution of aſſafœ- <lb/>tida is directed to be given between doſes. <lb/>When the caſe is
        alarming, or the patient ob- <lb/>ſtinately refuſes to take it by the mouth, it <lb/>may
        then be given in a glyſter along with the <lb/>bark. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In ſuch caſes, particularly with infants, when <lb/>medicines are rejected, whilſt the
        danger is <lb/>extreme, <hi rend="italic">antiſeptic baths</hi> are directed; to be
        <lb/>prepared by boiling Peruvian bark, chamomile <lb/>flowers, or myrrh, in a ſufficient
        quantity of <lb/>water, acidulated with a ſmall proportion of <lb/>vinegar. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Bliſters to the throat, back, or neck, are alſo <lb/>recommended; and likewiſe
        poultices, com- <lb/>poſed of garlic, to the feet; which not only <lb/>act as antiſeptics,
        but tend to raiſe the pulſe, <lb/>and to render the breathing eaſy and regular. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If, notwithſtanding all theſe attempts, the <lb/>difficulty of breathing ſhould
        increaſe, where <lb/>the throat is clear from ſloughs, if the pulſe <lb/>be good, and the
        ſymptoms of debility not re- <lb/>markable, as circumſtances are ſometimes apt <lb/>to
        deceive us, inflammation may then be ſuſ- <lb/>pected, and bleeding may very properly be <pb
          n="279"/>
        <lb/>tried; for in this, as in every other dangerous <lb/>diſeaſe, our author concludes, <q
          rend="diple quotes">ſatius eſt <lb/>anceps remedium experiri quam nullum. </q>
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
