<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Stewart: The History of a Case of the Pemphigus Major of Mr.
          Sauvages</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>David Stewart</persName>
            </author>
            <title>III. The History of a Case of the Pemphigus Major of Mr. Sauvages, by Dr. David
              Stewart, Physician in Aberdeen, communicated to Dr. Duncan.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical and philosophical commentaries. By a Society in Edinburgh.</title>
            <author>Society in Edinburgh</author>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for J. Murray, No, 32, Fleet-street. M. Drummond, J.
                  Bell, W. Creech, and C. Elliot, Edinburgh.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1779</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">6</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">79-84</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW109877913</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v6_0079">
    <body>
      <pb n="79"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>III. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>The Hiſtory of a Caſe of the Pemphigus Major of <lb/>Mr. <hi rend="roman"
        >Sauvages</hi>, by Dr. <hi rend="roman">David Stewart</hi>, Phyſi- <lb/>cian in Aberdeen,
        communicated to Dr. <hi rend="roman">Duncan</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Private ſoldier of the 73d regiment, <lb/>aged eighteen years,
        formerly a pedlar, <lb/>and naturally of a healthy conſtitution, was <lb/>received into the
        hoſpital at Aberdeen, on the <lb/>25th of April. About twenty days before <lb/>that he had
        been ſeized with the meaſles, when <lb/>in the country, and in marching to town on <lb/>the
        ſecond day of their eruption, he was ex- <lb/>poſed to cold, upon which they ſuddenly diſ-
        <lb/>appeared. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having arrived in Aberdeen, he was quar- <lb/>tered in a damp, ill-aired, under-ground
        apart- <lb/>ment. He then complained of ſickneſs at <lb/>ſtomach, great oppreſſion about the
        præcordia, <lb/>head-ach, laſſitude, and wearineſs on the leaſt <lb/>exertion, with
        ſtiffneſs and rigidity of his <pb n="80"/>
        <lb/>knees, and other joints; the ſurgeon of the <lb/>regiment viſited him: he was purged,
        but <lb/>with little benefit. About ten days before, he <lb/>obſerved on the inſide of his
        thighs, a number <lb/>of very ſmall, diſtinct, red ſpots, a little ele- <lb/>vated above the
        ſurface of the ſkin, and much <lb/>reſembling the firſt appearance of ſmall-pox. <lb/>This
        eruption gradually ſpread itſelf over his <lb/>whole body, and the puſtules continued every
        <lb/>day to increaſe in ſize. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon being received into the hoſpital, he <lb/>complained of head-ach, ſickneſs at
        ſtomach, <lb/>oppreſſion about the præcordia, thirſt, ſore- <lb/>throat, with difficulty of
        ſwallowing; his tongue <lb/>was foul, his ſkin felt hot and feveriſh, pulſe <lb/>from 110 to
        120, rather depreſſed; belly coſ- <lb/>tive, eyes dull and languid, but without deli-
        <lb/>rium. The whole ſurface of his ſkin was in- <lb/>terſperſed with veſicles, or
        phlyctænæ, of the <lb/>ſize of an ordinary walnut, many of them were <lb/>larger, eſpecially
        on the arms and breaſt. In <lb/>the interſtices, between the veſicles, the ap- <lb/>pearance
        of the ſkin was natural, nor was there <lb/>any redneſs round their baſe; the diſtance from
        <lb/>one to another, was from half an inch to a <lb/>hand-breadth, or more. In ſome places,
        two <lb/>or three were joined together, like the puſtules <lb/>in the confluent ſmall-pox. A
        few veſicles had <pb n="81"/>
        <lb/>burſt of themſelves, and formed a whitiſh <lb/>ſcab, or cruſt. Theſe were moſtly on the
        <lb/>neck and face; others ſhewed a tolerably laud- <lb/>able pus. However, by far the
        greateſt num- <lb/>ber were perfectly entire turgid, and of a <lb/>bluiſh colour. Upon
        opening them, it was <lb/>evident, that the cuticle elevated above the <lb/>cutis, and
        diſtended with a thin, yellowiſh, <lb/>ſemipellucid ſerum, formed this appearance. <lb/>Nor
        was the ſurface of the cutis ulcerated, or <lb/>livid, but of a red florid colour, as when
        the <lb/>cuticle is ſeparated by a bliſter, or ſuperficial <lb/>burning. No other perſon
        laboured under a <lb/>ſimilar diſeaſe, either in the part of the coun- <lb/>try from which
        he came, or when he reſided <lb/>in Aberdeen. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This caſe was treated in the following man- <lb/>ner. The largeſt of the veſicles were
        ſnipped, <lb/>and dreſſed with Uguent. e Lap. Calaminari. In <lb/>the evening he was vomited
        with a ſolution of <lb/>tartar emetic, given in ſmall quantities, and at <lb/>intervals.
        This alſo procured two looſe ſtools. <lb/>And he was ordered for drink, water-gruel,
        acidulated <lb/>with lemon-juice. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>April 16. He ſtill complained of ſickneſs, <lb/>ſome oppreſſion about his breaſt, and
        ſore <lb/>throat; he had ſlept little during the night, <pb n="82"/>
        <lb/>his tongue was foul and blackiſh, his ſkin, <lb/>however, was not ſo hot as the
        preceding day, <lb/>his urine was high-coloured, but had the ap- <lb/>pearance of
        ſeparation; his pulſe 90, and ſoft; <lb/>moſt of the ſores on the trunk of the body
        <lb/>looked clean. Others, particularly where the <lb/>veſicles were confluent, ſeemed
        beginning to <lb/>ulcerate, and to have a bluiſh ſublivid appear- <lb/>ance. They were
        dreſſed afreſh with cerate, <lb/>and he was ordered the following medicines: </p>
      <floatingText><body>
        <p rend="indentall space hanging size(0.7)">
          <lb/>℞ Decoct. Cort. Peruvian, ℥vi. Vini Rubr. Lu- <lb/>ſitan. ℥iii. M. Hujus mixturæ
          capiat. ℥ ß. <lb/>tertia quaque hora. </p></body>
      </floatingText>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>His acidulated drink was continued; and, on <lb/>account of the very offenſive ſmell on
        ap- <lb/>proaching near him, ſome vinegar was placed <lb/>in a baſon before the bed, and
        ſprinkled on <lb/>the floor; and the room was kept properly <lb/>aired. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>April 17. His ſores looked tolerably clean, <lb/>unleſs on his arms and thighs; where
        they were <lb/>livid, a little ulcerated, and diſcharged a bloody <lb/>ichor. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>His head-ach, ſickness, &amp;c. were moſtly <lb/>gone; his tongue was rather cleaner;
        pulſe 68, <lb/>and ſoft. As the decoction of the bark ſit eaſily <pb n="83"/>
        <lb/>on his ſtomach, the following preſcription was <lb/>ordered. </p>
      <floatingText><body>
        <p rend="indentall hanging size(0.7)">
          <lb/>℞ Pulv. Subtiliſſ. Cort. Peruv. 3ß. Vini Rubri <lb/>Luſitan. Aquæ fontan. āā ℥ ß. M.
          ft. Hauſt. <lb/>tertia quaque hora repetend. </p></body>
      </floatingText>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The acidulated drink was continued, and freſh <lb/>dreſſings applied to the ſores. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>April 18. The little ulcers on his arms and <lb/>thighs ſtill diſcharged a bloody
        ichor, and <lb/>looked ill; his other complaints were better; <lb/>pulse 82. The bark had
        not nauſeated him, <lb/>and it was continued as well as his former drink. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>April 19. His ſores looked greatly cleaner <lb/>and better; the fever was gone, his
        pulſe na- <lb/>tural, and had no complaint but weakneſs, and <lb/>a troubleſome itching of
        the ſkin: the Peru- <lb/>vian bark, &amp;c. were continued. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>April 20. Some of the ulcers ſtill poured <lb/>forth a bloody ichor; moſt of them, how-
        <lb/>ever, looked well, and had begun to heal— <lb/>fever gone—medicines continued. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From the 21ſt of April, he went on gaining <lb/>ſtrength, and his ſores appeared to
        heal faſt; <lb/>he was deſired to take only four doſes of bark <lb/>every day; and by the
        27th, his ſores, &amp;c. <lb/>were totally dried up—he had no complaint— <lb/>was diſmiſſed
        cured. </p>
      <pb n="84"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Although I had never before ſeen a caſe ſi- <lb/>milar to the above, yet I did not
        heſitate to <lb/>conclude, that the diſeaſe belonged to the tribe <lb/>of exanthemata; and
        had, in a greater or leſs <lb/>degree, a putrid tendency: having formed this <lb/>idea, it
        was evident, that if a remiſſion of the <lb/>fever could be procured, the bark, with acids,
        <lb/>were the remedies moſt to be truſted to. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon looking into the Noſologia Metho- <lb/>dica of M. de Sauvages, and examining the
        <lb/>different genera of the order of exanthemata, <lb/>I found that the character of his
        93d Genus, <lb/>to which he gives the name of <hi rend="italic">Pemphigus</hi>, al-
        <lb/>moſt coincided in every particular with the <lb/>hiſtory given above; and that of the
        four ſpe- <lb/>cies into which he divides this genus, the pre- <lb/>ſent caſe was clearly
        the firſt of theſe, or the <lb/><hi rend="italic">Pemphigus Major</hi>. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Both Dr. Cullen and Vogel nearly agree <lb/>with Sauvages in their character of this
        genus <lb/>of the exanthemata. The former alſo, gives <lb/>it the name of <hi rend="italic"
          >Pemphigus</hi>, and the latter that <lb/><hi rend="italic">Febris Bulloſa</hi>. Carolus
        Piso too, in his Con- <lb/>ſilia Selecta, gives the hiſtory of a caſe nearly <lb/>ſimilar;
        and the <hi rend="italic">Febris Syneches cum Veſiculis per <lb/>pectus &amp; Collum
          Sparſis</hi> of Dr. Morton, ſeems alſo <lb/>to belong to the ſame genus. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
