<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Duncan: The History of an obstinate Case of Epilepsy</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Dr Duncan</persName>
            </author>
            <title>X. The History of an obstinate Case of Epilepsy, successfully treated by Blood -
              letting: Communicated to Dr Duncan by Dr Robert Hamilton of the 10th Regiment of
              Foot.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries for the year 1780; exhibiting a concise view of the latest
              and most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and
              published by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Fellow of the Royal College of
              Physicians, Edinburgh, and Member of the Royal Societie, of Medicine, of Paris,
              Copenhagen, Edinburgh, &amp;c.</title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for Charles Dilly, in the Poultry.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1780</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">7</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">333-337</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW114391577</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T148075</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v7_0333">
    <body>
      <pb n="333"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>X. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>The Hiſtory of an obſtinate Caſe of Epilepſy, ſuc- <lb/>ceſsfully treated by
        Blood-letting: Communi- <lb/>cated to <hi rend="roman">Dr Duncan</hi> by <hi rend="roman">Dr
          Robert Hamilton</hi>
        <lb/>of the <hi rend="roman">10</hi>th Regiment of Foot. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> Labouring man on the banks of the river <lb/>Buſh, in the north
        of Ireland, having <lb/>been long afflicted with the epilepſy; after <lb/>many a long and
        violent ſtruggle, at length <pb n="334"/>
        <lb/>fell a ſacrifice to the ſuperior ſtrength of the <lb/>foe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>His ſon, a boy of about 12 years of age, <lb/>healthy and ſtrong of his years, as any
        in the <lb/>neighbourhood where he lived, and who never <lb/>had before that the leaſt
        ſymptoms of ſuch an <lb/>affection, fell into fits. The diſeaſe daily ga- <lb/>thered
        ſtrength, and in a ſhort time he be- <lb/>came a moſt miſerable object. From a fair,
        <lb/>ruddy, and healthful complexion, he now <lb/>wore a moſt ghaſtly look, frightful and
        wild, <lb/>and became a mere ſkeleton. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Thus his diſeaſe continued for ſome years, <lb/>ſtill gathering ſtrength. Sometimes,
        for a <lb/>whole day together, he could not be ſaid to <lb/>be out of the fit; for as ſoon
        as he would open <lb/>his eyes to the light, he would fall immedi- <lb/>ately into another. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>His caſe now became deſperate; and his <lb/>friends, as well as the ſympathizing neigh-
        <lb/>bourhood, wiſhed only for death to relieve <lb/>him from his diſtreſs, as they thought
        him <lb/>out of the reach of medical aid. One day <lb/>as he lay ſenſeleſs, and convulſed,
        in which <lb/>condition he had continued from morning till <lb/>evening, while a
        commiſerating crowd were <lb/>gathered around, wiſhing for his end, it ſug- <pb n="335"/>
        <lb/>geſted itſelf to one of the multitude, that per- <lb/>haps bleeding might be of ſome
        uſe; that <lb/>however improbable the ſucceſs might appear, <lb/>yet it was a duty to
        attempt ſomething for <lb/>his relief. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Bleeding is, among the common people, a <lb/>cure for every thing; and what at this
        time <lb/>probably gave him the idea, was the ſchool- <lb/>maſter of the pariſh then joining
        the crowd. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſchool-maſter generally lets blood, as <lb/>one part of his parochial duty. As the
        patient <lb/>was given over long ſince for loſt, the propo- <lb/>ſed remedy met with little
        oppoſition from his <lb/>friends, having as little hopes of its ſucceſs. <lb/>Accordingly
        his arm was tied up, as he lay on <lb/>the ground, and blood let from a large orifice,
        <lb/>(not being over nice in the operation), and <lb/>the blood was allowed to flow on the
        ground. <lb/>Scarcely was this performed, when the boy <lb/>began to look up, and recover
        from the fit. <lb/>Though it was only looked on as a protrac- <lb/>tion, not as a cure of
        the complaint, yet his <lb/>arm was taken care of and bandaged. How- <lb/>ever, to their
        great joy, and contrary to their <lb/>expectation, he recovered perfectly, and has
        <lb/>never ſince had another fit, though it is now <lb/>above a year. In the ſpace of a few
        days his <pb n="336"/>
        <lb/>looks altered, and he ſoon became as fat and <lb/>fair as ever he was in his life. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This relation I had firſt from the miniſter <lb/>of the pariſh, a very worthy man, who
        was <lb/>perfectly acquainted with every thing relat- <lb/>ing to the caſe, and whoſe
        veracity is unqueſ- <lb/>tionable; and again from the ſchool-maſter <lb/>who bled him. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>What I wiſhed moſt to aſcertain, was the <lb/>quantity of blood loſt. This I was not
        able <lb/>ſatisfactorily to learn, as it was ſuffered to flow <lb/>on the ground; but
        according to the ſeveral <lb/>queſtions I put to him, in order to have ſome <lb/>idea of it,
        I think it could not be leſs than <lb/>between two and three pounds. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As this is a diſeaſe that very frequently hap- <lb/>pens, and as yet has kept beyond
        the reach of <lb/>phyſic in moſt inſtances, when it has once <lb/>been confirmed into a
        habit in the conſtitution, <lb/>every thing which has ſucceeded as a cure in <lb/>any caſe,
        whether by accident, as the preſent, <lb/>or otherwiſe, ſhould be faithfully communi-
        <lb/>cated to the public. It is but giving the pa- <lb/>tient a fair trial for his life,
        when one reme- <lb/>dy fails, to have recourſe to another, till we <lb/>have gone through
        every one which ſeems to <lb/>have any probability of ſucceſs, or has ever, <pb n="337"/>
        <lb/>in any inſtance, ſucceeded. Neither bliſters, <lb/>iſſues, ſetons, the actual cautery,
        powder of <lb/>orange-leaves, the preſent much boaſted <lb/>flowers of zinc, and all the
        other claſs of an- <lb/>tiſpaſmodics in daily uſe, will in every caſe <lb/>anſwer; yet no
        one of them is to be overlook- <lb/>ed as uſeleſs. And from the preſent caſe, <lb/>which is
        faithfully related, we ought to turn <lb/>our attention to large bleedings, eſpecially in
        <lb/>ſome habits; and perhaps it may be found to <lb/>ſucceed in more caſes than at firſt
        view we <lb/>might be led to ſuſpect: Its great antiſpaſmo- <lb/>dic powers are known, and
        daily acknowledg- <lb/>ed by all the faculty. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Blood-letting ſeems the more to be depend- <lb/>ed on, from another caſe told me by a
        gentle- <lb/>man, a ſtudent of medicine, to whom I had <lb/>related the preſent. He had
        read, but did <lb/>not then recollect where, of a caſe ſomewhat <lb/>ſimilar: It was of an
        epileptic patient falling <lb/>down in a fit, and accidentally having his <lb/>temporal
        artery opened by ſome ſharp ſub- <lb/>ſtance on which he fell; it bled profuſely be-
        <lb/>fore it could be ſtopped, and the patient was <lb/>radically cured by the hæmorrhagy.
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
