<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: Dissertatio de Sulphure Antimonii aurato liquido</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>VI. Jo. Ern. Theoph. Guerick Dissertatio de Sulphure Antimonii aurato liquido.
              8vo. Erfurti.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries for the year 1780; exhibiting a concise view of the latest
              and most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and
              published by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Fellow of the Royal College of
              Physicians, Edinburgh, and Member of the Royal Societie, of Medicine, of Paris,
              Copenhagen, Edinburgh, &amp;c.</title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for Charles Dilly, in the Poultry.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1780</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">7</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">62-66</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW114391577</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T148075</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v7_0062">
    <body>
      <pb n="62"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>VI. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">Jo. Ern. Theoph. Guerick</hi> Diſſertatio de <lb/>Sulphure Antimonii
        aurato liquido. 8vo. <lb/><hi rend="roman">Erfurti</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE author of this Diſſertation does not <lb/>pretend that he is
        the diſcoverer of the <lb/>remedy here treated of; this he candidly at- <lb/>tributes to its
        real inventor, Dr Chriſtianus <lb/>Jacobus, a celebrated German phyſician and <lb/>chemiſt.
        The intention of the preſent publi- <pb n="63"/>
        <lb/>cation is merely to make more generally <lb/>known a medicine, which he conſiders to be
        <lb/>of very great importance. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The common ſulphur auratum antimonii <lb/>of the ſhops, and likewiſe the kermes mi-
        <lb/>nerale, have long, our author remarks, been <lb/>juſtly eſteemed as the moſt effectual
        prepa- <lb/>rations of antimony. But a continued uſe <lb/>of theſe remedies being frequently
        productive <lb/>of troubleſome affections of the ſtomach, a <lb/>medicine deſtitute of the
        acrimony of either <lb/>of theſe, and at the ſame time poſſeſſed of all <lb/>their
        influence, was therefore much wanted; <lb/>and this, we are informed, is now diſcovered
        <lb/>in the remedy under conſideration. The <lb/>following is recommended by Dr Jacobus as
        <lb/>the beſt way of preparing the medicine. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Take any quantity of the ordinary ſulphur <lb/>of antimony diſſolved in the uſual
        alkaline <lb/>lixivium, let one half of it be evaporated to <lb/>ſuch a conſiſtence that an
        egg may ſwim in <lb/>it; and an equal quantity of the expreſſed <lb/>oil of poppies or of
        almonds being then ad- <lb/>ded to it, the whole is to be well mixed and <lb/>gently boiled
        till the oil be no longer per- <lb/>ceptible; and the other half of the lixivium <lb/>being
        then added by degrees, the boiling is <pb n="64"/>
        <lb/>to be continued till the acrimony of the alkali <lb/>is alſo deſtroyed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The maſs being now of nearly the con- <lb/>ſiſtence of a poultice, is to be put into a
        re- <lb/>ceiver, and being covered with alcohol to the <lb/>depth of five inches, the
        mixture is then to <lb/>be ſet to digeſt for the ſpace of two days. At <lb/>the end of that
        time, a conſiderable quantity <lb/>of watery fluid will be found at the bottom <lb/>of the
        receiver; and the maſs ſwimming in <lb/>it being taken out, is to be dried to the con-
        <lb/>ſiſtence and firmneſs of common ſoap. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſulphur auratum antimonii being thus <lb/>converted into a ſoap, is in this form to
        be <lb/>kept for uſe, and part of it may at any time <lb/>be converted into a liquid by
        being diſſolved <lb/>in ſpirit of wine, which proves for this article <lb/>a very complete
        menſtruum. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This medicine, independently of its con- <lb/>taining the ſulphur of antimony in
        greater <lb/>quantity than any other liquid hitherto diſ- <lb/>covered, is perfectly
        deſtitute of that diſ- <lb/>agreeable nauſeous flavour ſo univerſally ob- <lb/>ſerved in
        every other preparation of this na- <lb/>ture; and the acrimony of the remedy being
        <lb/>effectually deſtroyed by the oil with which <lb/>it is combined, it is thereby
        prevented, as <pb n="65"/>
        <lb/>was already remarked, from producing any <lb/>improper effects upon the ſtomach, while,
        at <lb/>the ſame time, all its influence on the conſti- <lb/>tution is preſerved, as a
        preparation of anti- <lb/>mony. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As a proof of this, various diſorders are <lb/>enumerated, in which this remedy has
        been <lb/>found effectual after every other medicine <lb/>had been tried in vain; and, among
        others, <lb/>a caſe of obſtinate lepra is mentioned, in <lb/>which a complete cure was
        obtained by it in <lb/>the ſpace of two months, after mercury, <lb/>æthiops antimonii, and
        even Plummer's pow- <lb/>der, had been uſed without any ſucceſs. In <lb/>this caſe, five
        grains of the ſoap, in the form <lb/>of pills, were given morning and evening; <lb/>at the
        ſame time that forty drops of the tinc- <lb/>ture were exhibited twice a-day, in a de-
        <lb/>coction of juniper-root. In obſtinate caſes <lb/>of chronic rheumatiſm, this remedy, we
        are <lb/>told, is remarkably efficacious; our author <lb/>himſelf having in ſeveral
        inſtances ſeen it <lb/>uſed with advantage. It is likewiſe recom- <lb/>mended in every caſe
        of lepra, ſcabies, tinea <lb/>capitis, and in all chronic exanthematous diſ- <lb/>orders. </p>
      <pb n="66"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In caſes of chronic aſthma it is ſaid to be <lb/>particularly ſerviceable; and likewiſe
        in drop- <lb/>ſical affections, whether of the whole habit, <lb/>of the breaſt, or abdomen.
        Our author men- <lb/>tions ſeveral remarkable cures performed by <lb/>it in caſes of dropſy. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In caſes of fluor albus, and of gonorrhœa, <lb/>whether from a venereal taint or any
        other <lb/>cauſe, this liquid preparation of antimony is <lb/>recommended as being
        frequently an uſeful <lb/>remedy. In hemicrania too, we are told, it <lb/>has been uſed with
        advantage. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This remedy, however, ſhould never be <lb/>had recourſe to, Dr Guerick remarks, where
        <lb/>there is reaſon to ſuſpect vomica, or any in- <lb/>ternal ulceration; nor ſhould it
        ever be uſed <lb/>where ſymptoms of hectic fever are obſerv- <lb/>able. He gives, as a
        general caution, direc- <lb/>tions for emptying the blood-veſſels in every <lb/>caſe of
        plethora, before this medicine be ex- <lb/>hibited: and he deſires too, that whenever
        <lb/>the ſtomach and bowels are in any degree <lb/>affected, they may be previouſly cleanſed
        of <lb/>all their improper contents. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
