<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Wilmer: Cases and Remarks in Surgery</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>B. Wilmer</persName>
            </author>
            <title>II. Cases and Remarks in Surgery; to which is subjoined, an Appendix, containing
              the Method of curing the Bronchocele in Coventry. - By B. Wilmer, Surgeon. 8vo.
              London.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries for the year 1780; exhibiting a concise view of the latest
              and most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and
              published by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Fellow of the Royal College of
              Physicians, Edinburgh, and Member of the Royal Societie, of Medicine, of Paris,
              Copenhagen, Edinburgh, &amp;c.</title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for Charles Dilly, in the Poultry.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1780</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">7</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">26-35</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW114391577</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T148075</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v7_0026">
    <body>
      <pb n="26"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>II. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Caſes and Remarks in Surgery; to which is <lb/>ſubjoined, an Appendix, containing the
        Method <lb/>of curing the Bronchocele in Coventry.—By <lb/><hi rend="roman">B. Wilmer</hi>,
        Surgeon. <hi rend="roman">8vo. London.</hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE firſt paper in the collection before <lb/>us, contains
        obſervations on ſtrangulated <lb/>herniæ. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr Wilmer having embraced the new doc- <lb/>trine concerning the impropriety of warm
        ap- <lb/>plications in caſes of hernia, the intention of <lb/>this paper is to point out, in
        all ſuch inſtances, <lb/>the ſuperior advantages to be obtained from <lb/>the application of
        cold; and three caſes are <lb/>here inſerted, in which the application of cold <lb/>vinegar
        to hernial ſwellings, ſeemed to have a <lb/>conſiderable influence; by effecting the reduc-
        <lb/>tion of their contents, when in all probability <lb/>the operation for the bubonocele
        would other- <lb/>wiſe have been neceſſary. </p>
      <pb n="27"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The next caſe of any importance contains the <lb/>hiſtory of a patient who died of the
        hydroce- <lb/>phalus internus; with whom mercury was uſ- <lb/>ed without producing any good
        effect. Mr <lb/>Wilmer was called in about the eighth day of <lb/>the diſeaſe, and finding
        the ſymptoms very <lb/>ſtrongly marked, had immediate recourſe to <lb/>mercury.—Calomel
        being given in frequent <lb/>ſmall doſes, while at the ſame time the mercu- <lb/>rial
        ointment was applied outwardly, a ſaliva- <lb/>tion was thereby induced in the courſe of
        <lb/>twenty-four hours. The diſeaſe, however, <lb/>continued to gain ground; the patient
        became <lb/>daily weaker, and died on the ſeventh day <lb/>from the commencement of the
        mercurial <lb/>courſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A young woman, in a fit of deſpondency, ha- <lb/>ving cut her throat, our author was
        ſent for <lb/>to her aſſiſtance, when the whole annular ſub- <lb/>ſtance of the trachea was
        found divided juſt <lb/>beneath the thyroid cartilage; a great deal of <lb/>blood was loſt,
        and the patient was totally in- <lb/>capable of ſpeaking. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By two ſtitches of the interrupted ſuture, <lb/>aſſiſted by ſlips of adheſive plaſter,
        the ſides of <lb/>the wound of the integuments were brought <lb/>into contact. And
        notwithſtanding the occur- <pb n="28"/>
        <lb/>rence of a troubleſome cough, every thing <lb/>went favourably on till the fourth week,
        when <lb/>the external wound being almoſt healed, the <lb/>patient was ſeized with a
        difficulty of breath- <lb/>ing, attended with a ſenſe of ſuffocation; and <lb/>after
        continuance and increaſe of theſe ſymp- <lb/>toms, ſhe died in the ſpace of twenty-four
        <lb/>hours from their firſt appearance. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On diſſection after death, the internal <lb/>wound was found ſo much contracted that
        <lb/>there was merely room for the introduction of <lb/>a probe, which paſſed very freely
        into the tra- <lb/>chea, downwards.—The cicatrix adhered firm- <lb/>ly to the <hi
          rend="italic">inferior</hi> part of the divided trachea; <lb/>but the ſuperior portion had
        retracted half an <lb/>inch, and its cavity was ſo much filled by gra- <lb/>nulations of
        fleſh, that there did not appear <lb/>room for a ſufficient quantity of air to paſs
        <lb/>through it to dilate the lungs; ſo that when <lb/>the external wound became ſo ſmall
        that the <lb/>lungs could not be ſupplied with air from that <lb/>ſource, a difficulty of
        breathing commenced, <lb/>and at length the patient was ſuffocated by <lb/>the very efforts
        attempted by nature for heal- <lb/>ing the divided parts. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Some time before this caſe occurred, our au- <lb/>thor was deſired by Mr. Harrold, a
        neighbour- <pb n="29"/>
        <lb/>ing ſurgeon, to ſee a patient who he had cut <lb/>into the cavity of the trachea
        between the cry- <lb/>coid and thyroid cartilages. In this caſe, as <lb/>in the preceding,
        the integuments only were <lb/>united by ligature; the patient in every re- <lb/>ſpect
        ſeemed to be doing well till the fifth <lb/>night, when he died ſuddenly. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On examining the body, the immediate <lb/>cauſe of death appeared to have depended on
        <lb/>the rupture of a ſmall artery, the blood from <lb/>which, not having a ready external
        paſſage, <lb/>had found its way into the trachea, and there <lb/>formed a coagulum, which
        plugged up the ca- <lb/>vity of the windpipe, and ſuffocated the pa- <lb/>tient, by
        preventing the acceſs of air into the <lb/>lungs.— From theſe caſes our author ſtates it as
        <lb/>a query, whether the ſewing up the windpipe, <lb/>and leaving the external wound open,
        in both <lb/>or either of them, would have afforded a bet- <lb/>ter chance of recovery. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the caſe of a woman ſeized with locked <lb/>jaw and opiſthotonos, as nothing could
        be got <lb/>into the ſtomach from a convulſive motion in <lb/>the muſcles of the thorax
        being induced by <lb/>every attempt to ſwallow, it was thought ne- <lb/>ceſſary to have
        recourſe to glyſters, both with <pb n="30"/>
        <lb/>a view to the exhibition of medicines and of <lb/>nouriſhment. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Eight ounces of mutton-broth were injected <lb/>three times a-day, and every eight
        hours a gly- <lb/>ſter, conſiſting of ſix ounces of water, and two <lb/>drachms of
        laudanum.—The patient remained <lb/>four days in the ſame ſtate, during which <lb/>time ſhe
        did not ſwallow any thing. The <lb/>quantity of laudanum was increaſed in the <lb/>glyſters,
        and the rigid muſcles of the face were <lb/>well rubbed with camphorated oil. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the fifth day, ſhe could ſpeak and open <lb/>her mouth a little; on the ſeventh, ſhe
        could <lb/>ſwallow liquids.—She was then directed to <lb/>take two drachms of laudanum three
        times a- <lb/>day by the mouth.—She every day became <lb/>better, and in a ſhort time was
        almoſt as well <lb/>as uſual; but it was ſix weeks before the muſ- <lb/>cles of the neck and
        back had recovered their <lb/>proper flexibility. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Sir John Pringle having, in his Treatiſe on <lb/>Diſeaſes of the Army, recommended the
        appli- <lb/>cation of bliſters to the pained part of the ab- <lb/>domen, in caſes of ileus,
        our author was there- <lb/>by induced to make trial of their effects in <lb/>that diſorder.
        Three caſes of this nature are <lb/>here related, in which bliſters proved effectual <pb
          n="31"/>
        <lb/>after all the ordinary remedies had been had <lb/>recourſe to in vain. We ſhall here
        give a <lb/>more particular account of one of them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the third of February 1774, Mr Wil- <lb/>mer was deſired to ſee a young man who for
        <lb/>two days had been attended by an apothecary. <lb/>The ſymptoms were, a conſtant and
        acute <lb/>pain below the navel, continual vomiting, hic- <lb/>cough, languid pulſe,
        coſtiveneſs, and a cada- <lb/>verous countenance. He had been bled re- <lb/>peatedly;
        glyſters, fomentations, opiates, and <lb/>a variety of ſolutive medicines, had been ad-
        <lb/>miniſtered, but all without any kind of relief. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A large bliſtering plaſter, with a perforation <lb/>in its centre, was now ordered to
        be applied <lb/>round the navel, and no medicines were then <lb/>preſcribed, that the reſult
        might be more cer- <lb/>tainly known. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Soon after the patient felt any pain from the <lb/>bliſter, he enquired for the
        cloſe-ſtool, and had <lb/>an evacuation, by which he was much relieved. <lb/>The pain of the
        abdomen gradually abated, <lb/>and in a few days he was reſtored to health. <lb/>The effects
        of bliſters in the other two caſes <lb/>related by our author were equally remark- <lb/>able
        with the above. After having given ſome <lb/>remarks upon the treatment of compound <pb
          n="32"/>
        <lb/>fractures and diſlocations, our author concludes <lb/>the publication with an account
        of the method <lb/>of curing the bronchocele, as practifed at Co- <lb/>ventry. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The bronchocele, he obſerves, is a preterna- <lb/>tural enlargement of the thyroid
        gland; and <lb/>as from different circumſtances every attempt <lb/>to extirpate tumours of
        this nature muſt be ha- <lb/>zardous, the cure, he thinks, can only be ex- <lb/>pected from
        the uſe of internal medicines, no <lb/>topical application being ſufficiently active for
        <lb/>producing reſolution. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The medicine which at Coventry has ac- <lb/>quired ſo much reputation for the cure of
        <lb/>this diſeaſe, owes its origin, we are here in- <lb/>formed, to Doctor Bate, who, a
        conſiderable <lb/>time ago, practiſed as phyſician at that place. <lb/>As Mr Wilmer vouches
        for the effects of the <lb/>remedy, at leaſt in young female patients, we <lb/>ſhall here
        give our readers his account of it <lb/>at ſome length. In men, and in all patients
        <lb/>paſt the meridian of life, ſuch effects, he ob- <lb/>ſerves, are not to be expected
        from it as when <lb/>young women are the ſubjects of the diſeaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There are two receipts by which the me- <lb/>dicine is prepared; one of them is for
        certain <lb/>the original preſcription of Doctor Bate. <pb n="33"/>
        <lb/>Which of the two came from him, however, <lb/>our author cannot determine; but they are
        <lb/>both, he remarks, equally efficacious. The <lb/>following are the contents of each: </p>
      <floatingText><body>
        <head rend="sc align-center space">
          <lb/>Number I. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>The day after the moon hath been in the <lb/>full, the patient is to take a vomit—on
          the <lb/>ſucceeding day, a purge is to be adminiſtered <lb/>—on the third night, at going
          to bed, one of <lb/>the following boluſes is to be placed in the <lb/>mouth, under the
          tongue, and, being ſuffered <lb/>to diſſolve gradually, is to be ſwallowed. <lb/>This
          bolus is to be repeated the ſix ſucceeding <lb/>nights. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>Take Calcined ſpunge <lb/>Cork calcined <lb/>Pumice-ſtone burnt, of each ten
          <lb/>grains. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>To be ſeparately powdered, and made into <lb/>a bolus with ſyrup, honey, or mucilage. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On each of the ſeven days that the patient <lb/>takes the preceding bole, the
          following pow- <lb/>der is to be adminiſtered in the forenoon in <lb/>any proper vehicle. </p>
        <pb n="34"/>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>℞. Flor. cham. pulv. <lb/>Rad. gentian. pulv. <lb/>Sum. centaur. min. pulv. aa gr. v.
          m. </p>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>On the eighth day the purge is to be re- <lb/>peated. In the wane of the ſucceeding
          moon <lb/>the ſame proceſs is to be entered into, and re- <lb/>peated a third time, unleſs
          the diſeaſe be cur- <lb/>ed before.—The vomit is only to be taken <lb/>before the firſt
          courſe of medicines. </p></body>
      </floatingText>
      <floatingText><body>
        <head rend="sc align-center space">
          <lb/>Number II. </head>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>℞. Spongiæ calcinatæ dr. ſſ. <lb/>Mellis q. ſ. pro bolo. </head>
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>The <hi rend="sc">Preparation</hi>. </head>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Tie the beſt ſpunge up hard with wet pack- <lb/>thread, and calcine it in a crucible.
          Theſe <lb/>boles are to be uſed as thoſe of the former <lb/>receipt; the bitter powders
          are to be taken, <lb/>and the ſame directions with regard to eva- <lb/>cuations obſerved
          in every reſpect as in No. I. </p></body>
      </floatingText>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A very eminent ſurgeon, who has had ma- <lb/>ny opportunities of ſeeing the good
        effects of <lb/>both theſe preparations, aſſures our author, <pb n="35"/>
        <lb/>that either of them will ſucceed with more <lb/>certainty if the patient takes a vomit
        and <lb/>purge during the <hi rend="italic">increase</hi> of the moon. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The calcined ſpunge for either of theſe pre- <lb/>parations ought to be powdered in a
        glaſs or <lb/>marble mortar. If a braſs one is uſed, the <lb/>ſalts of the ſpunge attract ſo
        much of the me- <lb/>tal as to acquire an emetic property. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
