<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Fitzgerald: Histories of Two Cases</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Samuel Fitzgerald</persName>
            </author>
            <title>IX. Histories of two Cases: The Discharge of a large calcareous Concretion, and
              the Extraction of the Bones of a Fœtus by the Rectum. By Dr Samuel Fitzgerald,
              Physician at Mullingar.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries, for the years 1781-2: exhibiting a concise view of the
              latest and most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected
              and published by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Physician to His Royal
              Highness the Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians,
              Edinburgh, and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen,
              Edinburgh, &amp;c. </title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for C. Elliot, T. Kay and Co. at Dr Cullen's Head, No.
                  332, Strand, London, and C. Elliot, Edinburgh</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1781-1782</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">8</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">329-332</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110324368</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T148076</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v8_0329">
    <body>
      <pb n="329"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>IX. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Hiſtories of two Caſes: The Diſcharge of a large <lb/>calcareous Concretion, and the
        Extraction of the <lb/>Bones of a Fætus by the Rectum. By <hi rend="roman"> Dr Sa- <lb/>muel
          Fitzgerald </hi>, Phyſician at Mullingar. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>
        <hi rend="sc">Lady</hi> of rank in this neighbourhood, <lb/>whoſe name delicacy forbids to
        mention, <lb/><choice>
          <corr>had</corr>
          <sic>hed</sic>
        </choice> laboured for eighteen months under the <lb/>moſt excruciating torture and pains in
        the hy- <lb/>pogaſtric region, particularly towards the back <lb/>and os ſacrum. For the
        laſt three months of <lb/>her illneſs, ſhe was ſo reduced for want of food <lb/>and ſleep,
        that ſhe could not leave her bed, ex- <lb/>cept when taken up to the tepid baths, in which
        <lb/>only ſhe enjoyed any tolerable degree of eaſe. <lb/>In ſhort, life now had become a
        burden, and <lb/>death deſirable to her and all around her. In <pb n="330"/>
        <lb/>this deplorable ſituation, upon the diſcharge of <lb/>an emollient anodyne glyſter, ſhe
        fortunately <lb/>with it paſſed from the rectum a large hard ball <lb/>of an oval figure,
        exceeding in ſize an ordinary <lb/>orange, and ſo ſolid that nothing leſs than the
        <lb/>ſtroke of a hammer could break it. It was of <lb/>a dark cinneritious colour, and of a
        calcareous <lb/>quality in ſubſtance, weighing eight ounces and <lb/>three drams. A total
        liberation from pain imme- <lb/>diately followed its expulſion, and, in a very ſhort
        <lb/>time the hectic and other alarming ſymptoms <lb/>vaniſhed, and the lady is now
        perfectly re-eſta- <lb/>bliſhed in health. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>The other caſe is that of Mary Dardis, a na- <lb/>tive of this town, who, on the firſt
        day of June, <lb/>after the uſual term of geſtation, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> nine
        <lb/>months from her ſecond marriage, was taken ill <lb/>of labour-pains; but theſe being
        rather tedious, <lb/>and cold, as the midwife termed it, I was ſent <lb/>for; and, upon
        examining the ſtate of the ute- <lb/>rus, I could not poſſibly find its orifice, though,
        <lb/>at the ſame time, I clearly perceived a round <lb/>hard bulk through the teguments,
        which I con- <lb/>cluded was the head. In this ſituation, I deſi- <lb/>red ſhe might be
        properly ſupported and pati- <pb n="331"/>
        <lb/>ently wait the increaſe of more efficacious pains, <lb/>and then to appriſe me of it.
        For three days I <lb/>heard nothing from her, and then calling at her <lb/>place of
        reſidence, I found her engaged at her <lb/>ordinary buſineſs, quite well, but uneaſy at not
        <lb/>having been delivered. I told her the right time <lb/>was not yet come; that when it
        did, all would <lb/>be well, and not to fret herſelf on that account. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 10th of February next enſuing, being <lb/>nine months and ten days, her huſband,
        at mid- <lb/>night, called upon me, to let me know ſhe was <lb/>in high labour. Curioſity,
        as well as humanity, <lb/>induced me to viſit her; and, to my great ſur- <lb/>priſe, the
        firſt object that preſented to the touch <lb/>was the foot and leg of the ſkeleton hanging
        <lb/>forth from the rectum. This, by merely hand- <lb/>ling it, readily ſeparated at the
        articulation of <lb/>the knee; and, as no entrance to the womb <lb/>through the vagina was
        yet to be found, I was <lb/>reduced to the painful neceſſity of extracting the <lb/>entire
        ſkeleton, bone after bone, through the <lb/>anus. This loathſome manœuvre continued for
        <lb/>the beſt part of three ſucceſſive days; for the <lb/>intolerable ſtench, and difficult
        acceſs, were ſo <lb/>great, that I could not bear it longer than an hour <lb/>at any one
        time. I ſuppoſe the obliquity of the <pb n="332"/>
        <lb/>womb's elevation was the cauſe of this very pre- <lb/>poſterous birth, that its orifice
        had reached that <lb/>part of the rectum through which the heel of <lb/>the ſkeleton muſt
        have gradually found its paſ- <lb/>ſage; for ſhe had uninterrupted pains in the <lb/>lower
        part of her back during the laſt three <lb/>months, which ſhe called a dry cholic. By clean-
        <lb/>ſing vulnerary injections, and a liberal uſe of the <lb/>Peruvian bark, the woman is
        reſtored to health. <lb/>Though this ſeems ſcarce credible, yet it is lite- <lb/>rally true,
        as may be atteſted by a ſurgeon I <lb/>was obliged to call in, to aſſiſt now and then in
        <lb/>the delivery. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
