<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Kilgour: The History of a case, in which Worms in the Nose...</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Thomas Kilgour</persName>
            </author>
            <title>I. The History of a case, in which Worms in the Nose, productive of alarming
              Symptoms, were successfully removed by the Use of Tobacco. By Mr Thomas Kilgour,
              Surgeon in Jamaica.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries, for the years 1781-2: exhibiting a concise view of the
              latest and most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected
              and published by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Physician to His Royal
              Highness the Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians,
              Edinburgh, and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen,
              Edinburgh, &amp;c. </title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for C. Elliot, T. Kay and Co. at Dr Cullen's Head, No.
                  332, Strand, London, and C. Elliot, Edinburgh</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1781-1782</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">8</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">75-83</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110324368</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T148076</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v8_0075">
    <body>
      <pb n="75"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>I. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>The Hiſtory of a caſe, in which Worms in the Noſe, <lb/>productive of alarming
        Symptoms, were ſucceſs- <lb/>fully removed by the Uſe of Tobacco. By <hi rend="roman">Mr
          <lb/>Thomas Kilgour</hi>, Surgeon in Jamaica. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>
        <hi rend="sc">Gentleman</hi> of Montego-bay in Ja- <lb/>maica, aged twenty-ſix, of a middle
        ſta- <lb/>ture, and robuſt make, about the middle of July <lb/>1777, complained for three
        days, of a ſlight ob- <lb/>tuſe pain in his right upper jaw-bone, root of <lb/>the noſe,
        eye, and forehead of the ſame ſide. <pb n="76"/>
        <lb/>On the evening of the fourth day, the pain be- <lb/>came exceedingly violent, extending
        through the <lb/>third dens molaris, and affecting the right ſide <lb/>of the face and head,
        with ſevere and inceſſant <lb/>ſhootings. He applied next morning to an aſ- <lb/>ſiſtant of
        Mr Thomas Brown, an expert ſur- <lb/>geon in this place, to extract the tooth in which
        <lb/>he felt the greateſt uneaſineſs, imagining his <lb/>complaints originated from it. The
        tooth was <lb/>perfectly ſound, and its extraction was attended <lb/>with no alleviation of
        the pain. At night he <lb/>took an opiate, but it afforded no relief. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I was deſired to viſit him next day. He then <lb/>felt inexpreſſible agony and
        diſtreſs. The eye <lb/>and right ſide of the face were much inflamed, <lb/>but little
        ſwelled. From the right noſtril there <lb/>diſtilled, in large drops, a thin dark coloured
        <lb/>ichor, of a very offenſive ſmell, ſimilar to the diſ- <lb/>charge from a carious bone,
        but more diſagree- <lb/>able. I examined the noſtril, but could perceive <lb/>no ulceration.
        I therefore concluded it muſt be <lb/>a collection of ſome acrid matter in the maxillary
        <lb/>cavity, that occaſioned theſe violent ſymptoms, <lb/>and that the diſcharge from the
        noſe was the <lb/>matter finding its paſſage through that way. </p>
      <pb n="77"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The caſe being alarming, and the fever conſi- <lb/>derable, we called for the
        aſſiſtance of Dr Mur- <lb/>ray, who readily agreeing to our opinion of a <lb/>collection of
        matter being formed in the maxil- <lb/>lary cavity, a perforation was made into it thro'
        <lb/>the ſocket from which the tooth was extracted; <lb/>but no diſcharge of matter followed
        the perfora- <lb/>tion, nor did the pain in the leaſt abate. On <lb/>the contrary, it
        continued to increaſe more and <lb/>more at the root of the noſe; and, about an <lb/>hour
        after the operation, there were voided from <lb/>the right noſtril, two inſects, in
        appearance like <lb/>the maggots formed in putrid meat. On placing <lb/>the patient in the
        light, a vaſt number were per- <lb/>ceived in motion at the upper part of the noſtril.
        <lb/>I introduced a forceps, and took out three or <lb/>four at a time; and, in the courſe
        of that day, <lb/>upwards of thirty. They were in general three- <lb/>fourths of an inch
        long, and one-eighth thick, <lb/>compoſed of rings, ſuddenly tapering towards <lb/>the tail,
        and had a large browniſh head. In ex- <lb/>tracting, they made a ſtrong reſiſtance with what
        <lb/>ſerved them inſtead of feet, and gave a ſenſation <lb/>to my hand like a file drawn
        acroſs a ſoft body. <lb/>When taken out, they were very lively, and <pb n="78"/>
        <lb/>crawled about in the open air a long time before <lb/>they died. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It was ſuppoſed theſe inſects were hatched in <lb/>an ulcer of the noſe, from a
        venereal cauſe, the <lb/>patient being affected with a ſimple gonorrhœa <lb/>about a
        twelvemonth before, which was cured <lb/>in the common way, and without any return of
        <lb/>ſymptoms. This being the idea formed of the <lb/>diſorder, after premiſing the
        neceſſary evacua- <lb/>tions to moderate the febrile ſymptoms, a mer- <lb/>curial courſe was
        entered upon, both with a view <lb/>of correcting the general ſtate of the habit, and
        <lb/>likewiſe from its known qualities, in being offen- <lb/>ſive to worms, to deſtroy the
        inſects. Three <lb/>grains of black precipitate were ordered to be <lb/>given at bed-time,
        along with an opiate; the <lb/>noſtril to be frequently fumigated with cinnabar, <lb/>and a
        ſolution of calomel and camphor, in oil, <lb/>to be thrown up by injection. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having a particular regard for the patient, I <lb/>ſtaid ſeveral hours with him, and
        was much diſ- <lb/>appointed in finding neither the fumigation nor <lb/>injection to have
        the ſmalleſt effect in mitigating <lb/>the pain, or deſtroying the inſects. I therefore
        <lb/>ſet about ſome experiments to find out a remedy <lb/>capable of killing them, and
        happily, in a little <pb n="79"/>
        <lb/>time, diſcovered one that proved ſucceſsful; but <lb/>previous to this attempt, that
        the mercurial ſolu- <lb/>tion might have the fulleſt juſtice done it, I put <lb/>a few of
        the inſects into it, and found them at <lb/>the end of an hour as lively as ever; a clear
        <lb/>proof they were not of a ſpecies to be affected <lb/>by oils or mercury. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The trials I made upon them were as follow: <lb/>I took five wine-glaſſes; into each
        glaſs I put <lb/>two of the maggots; into one glaſs, I poured a <lb/>ſtrong decoction of
        chamomile and wormwood; <lb/>into another, vinous tincture of opium; into the <lb/>third,
        rum; into the fourth, I blew tobacco- <lb/>ſmoke; and into the laſt, I poured a decoction
        <lb/>of tobacco. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The bitter decoction gave them no diſturbance. <lb/>The tincture of opium, at its firſt
        application, <lb/>threw them into violent motion; but in a ſhort <lb/>time they recovered
        and moved about at their <lb/>eaſe. The rum killed them in about ten mi- <lb/>nutes. The
        tobacco-ſmoke, in a few blowings, <lb/>ſhrivelled them to death; and the tobacco de-
        <lb/>coction inſtantly convulſed and deſtroyed them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Next day, by conſent of Dr Murray and Mr <lb/>Brown, the tobacco decoction was injected
        into <lb/>the noſtril, and the fumigation and mercurial in- <pb n="80"/>
        <lb/>jection laid aſide. The black precipitate and <lb/>opiate were ordered to be continued
        at bed- <lb/>time; and, with a view to obviate putrefaction, <lb/>and ſupport the ſtrength,
        two ounces of infu- <lb/>ſion of the bark were adminiſtered every hour <lb/>through the day,
        and the patient indulged in <lb/>a little wine, and ſuch light nouriſhment as he <lb/>could
        take. At firſt the tobacco decoction gave <lb/>a good deal of pain; but in a little time
        became <lb/>pleaſant and agreeable, ſenſibly correcting the fœ- <lb/>tor, and bringing away
        the inſects in great num- <lb/>bers, and in a very weakly ſtate. After uſing it <lb/>a few
        days, ſeldom more than half-a-dozen a- <lb/>day were voided, and theſe frequently dead. At
        <lb/>length, after a courſe of ten days, numbers being <lb/>extracted by the forceps, and
        falling out of them- <lb/>ſelves, ſometimes dead, ſometimes alive, a white <lb/>tranſparent
        ſubſtance, near two inches long, and <lb/>a quarter of an inch broad, and flat, with three
        <lb/>large inſects in it, was brought out by the for- <lb/>ceps, upon which the pain greatly
        abated, and <lb/>from that time the inſects diſappeared. In a <lb/>few days more the
        abraſions of the membrana <lb/>Schneideriana were healed up, and before the <lb/>middle of
        Auguſt, the patient was able to go to <lb/>the mountains to recover his fleſh. </p>
      <pb n="81"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The above mentioned ſubſtance, I preſume, <lb/>had ſerved as a nidus for theſe inſects.
        On the <lb/>ſurface of it were a great many inequalities and <lb/>furrows. It is to be
        obſerved, that this young <lb/>man had been ſubject to an hæmorrhage from <lb/>the noſe,
        from the time he arrived at puberty, till <lb/>he ſettled in this iſland, about five years
        ago, <lb/>ſince which time he has had no attack of it. He <lb/>loſt the ſenſe of ſmelling by
        the right noſtril after <lb/>the hæmorrhage appeared, and has it only in an <lb/>imperfect
        degree by the left; nor has it returned <lb/>ſince he recovered from this diſorder. Might
        <lb/>not this membranous ſubſtance have been form- <lb/>ed of the coagulable part of the
        blood adhering <lb/>about the oſſa ſpongioſa after the hæmorrhage, <lb/>the red particles of
        what remained ſtagnated in <lb/>the noſtril being reabſorbed; and might not this
        <lb/>foreign body, by its ſtimulus, have brought on <lb/>an ulceration of the memb. Schneid.
        whence theſe <lb/>inſects have been generated? One circumſtance <lb/>in the above caſe is
        very aſtoniſhing, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> the <lb/>rapid generation of theſe inſects; as
        I am confi- <lb/>dent I ſpeak within bounds, when I aſſert, up- <lb/>wards of 200 were
        extracted and voided in the <lb/>ſpace of 10 days. </p>
      <pb n="82"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is ſurpriſing, that among all thoſe authors <lb/>who have written on the diſeaſes of
        warm climates, <lb/>there is no mention of maggots in the noſe as a <lb/>diſeaſe that
        ſometimes occurs; and yet I imagine <lb/>it is a complaint that has pretty often come with-
        <lb/>in the knowledge of practitioners; for, ſince the <lb/>above caſe, I have been informed
        of ſeveral in- <lb/>ſtances that have happened in this iſland. The <lb/>moſt remarkable is
        one that occurred ſome years <lb/>ago, to a married woman of this place. Her <lb/>huſband,
        after every thing had been tried in vain <lb/>by the Faculty, one day when ſhe was in the
        <lb/>greateſt agony, poured a quantity of oil of tur- <lb/>pentine into the noſe; and this
        ſeeming to abate <lb/>the pain, he continued to apply it for ſeveral days <lb/>ſucceſſively.
        The event was, the inſects were <lb/>killed, and the noſe reſtored to the ſtate of a
        <lb/>ſimple ulcer, which ſoon healed up. But previ- <lb/>ous to the uſe of the turpentine,
        the unfortunate <lb/>woman had loſt the oſſa naſi, and with this de- <lb/>formity ſhe
        eſcaped. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Another caſe was that of a young man, a few <lb/>miles from this, which happened in
        1776; but <lb/>to him it proved fatal. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr Robert Monro of Hanover-pariſh, a very <lb/>old practitioner, and a man of great
        experience <pb n="83"/>
        <lb/>and medical ſagacity, informed me of a caſe of <lb/>maggots in the noſe he had met
        with, in which, <lb/>after every thing that was tried had failed, he <lb/>thought of uſing
        the tobacco, from knowing its <lb/>powerful effects in killing moſt kinds of vermin.
        <lb/>The conſequence was, the inſects were ſpeedily <lb/>deſtroyed, and the patient in a
        little time reſtor- <lb/>ed to health. And this fact of Mr Monro's, <lb/>who was alſo called
        upon to viſit our patient, <lb/>was what induced us to perſevere in the uſe of <lb/>the
        tobacco, which happily proved ſo efficaci- <lb/>ous. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
