<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Duncan: An Observation on opening the Abdomen and Thorax of a Young
          Lady</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Dr Duncan</persName>
            </author>
            <title>III. An Observation on opening the Abdomen and Thorax of a Young Lady, who died
              after a very short illness; communicated to Dr Duncan, by Mr Richard Paxton, Surgeon
              at Maldon in Essex.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries, for the years 1781-2: exhibiting a concise view of the
              latest and most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected
              and published by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Physician to His Royal
              Highness the Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians,
              Edinburgh, and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen,
              Edinburgh, &amp;c. </title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: printed for C. Elliot, T. Kay and Co. at Dr Cullen's Head, No.
                  332, Strand, London, and C. Elliot, Edinburgh</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1781-1782</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">8</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">90-94</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110324368</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">T148076</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v8_0090">
    <body>
      <pb n="90"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>III. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>An Obſervation on opening the Abdomen and Tho- <lb/>rax of a Young Lady, who died after
        a very <lb/>ſhort illneſs; communicated to <hi rend="roman">Dr Duncan</hi>, by <hi
          rend="roman">Mr <lb/>Richard Paxton</hi>, Surgeon at Maldon in Eſſex. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi> L<hi rend="sc">ADY</hi>, in the 23d year of her age, of a
        <lb/>delicate frame of body and weakly con- <lb/>ſtitution, had, for two years paſt,
        complained of <lb/>a ſlight pain on the right ſide of the thorax, at- <lb/>tended with ſome
        reſtriction in breathing and a <lb/>tickling cough; which ſymptoms rendered her
        <lb/>extremely averſe to any kind of exerciſe. A- <lb/>bout the latter end of Auguſt 1780,
        ſhe was <lb/>ſeized with the ſymptoms of an autumnal re- <lb/>mittent, then prevailing in
        the neighbourhood, <lb/>which readily yielded to the uſual treatment in <lb/>theſe caſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The firſt ſymptoms, however, ſtill attended <lb/>her; the pain in the ſide, and
        reſtriction in brea- <lb/>thing, rather encreaſing till the 15th of Decem- <lb/>ber; on the
        noon of which day, I was again call- <lb/>ed, and found her laid on bed with the follow-
        <lb/>ing complaints: Debilitated quick pulſe, chill- <lb/>neſs even to ſhivering, together
        with acute pain <pb n="91"/>
        <lb/>on the right ſide, or, as ſhe expreſſed, below <lb/>the ſhoulder, and bilious vomiting.
        They told <lb/>me, that as ſhe was ſitting at her needle-work <lb/>in her chamber, to which
        ſhe had retired after <lb/>breakfaſt, ſhe felt, and even heard, ſomething <lb/>give a
        violent ſnap within her breaſt, in that <lb/>part where now ſhe deſcribed the pain to be.
        <lb/>Her mother going into the room ſoon after, ſhe <lb/>exclaimed to her, ſhe ſhould die. I
        begged <lb/>ſhe might be undreſſed, and go to bed; which <lb/>was done, and ſent her over a
        ſaline julep, <lb/>meaning to viſit her again in two or three hours; <lb/>but ere that time
        was elapſed, her father came <lb/>for me, and I found her ſtomach rejecting every <lb/>thing
        ſhe ſwallowed, and every ſymptom exaſpe- <lb/>rated. I confeſſed myſelf totally at a loſs
        for the <lb/>cauſe of the appearances; but being fully ſatis- <lb/>fied of her imminent
        danger, entreated a phyſi- <lb/>cian might be ſent for, which was inſtantly <lb/>agreed
        upon; and Dr Steele from Witham, ſaw <lb/>her about ſeven o'clock in the evening. By his
        <lb/>direction ſhe was bled to the amount of 12 <lb/>ounces; a bliſter was applied to the
        ſide, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The ſymptoms then were, in the Doctor's <lb/>own words, <q rend="diple quotes"
          >Difficult reſpiration, acute pain in <lb/>the right ſide, juſt below the breaſt, pulſe
          fre- <pb n="92"/>
          <lb/>quent and oppreſſed, increaſed heat, frequent <lb/>bilious retchings, countenance
          uncommonly <lb/>anxious: What was very remarkable, the <lb/>pulſe not at all freer from
          the liberal veneſection, <lb/>though the reſpiration was a little relieved. <lb/>My idea
          of the caſe at the time was its being <lb/>a formal pleuritic attack. </q> She paſſed a
        pain- <lb/>ful night without the mitigation of any one ſymp- <lb/>tom. On the morning of
        next day, the Doctor <lb/>found her pulſe <q rend="diple quotes">ſcarcely perceptible, and
          un- <lb/>commonly quick, continual rigors and vomit- <lb/>ings, cold clammy ſweat, <hi
            rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> complained of <lb/>intolerable ſickneſs, and pain only near
          the <lb/>pit of the ſtomach, with a ſenſe of load and <lb/>oppreſſion there. </q> She died
        at two o'clock <lb/>that day, or about 28 hours from the time <lb/>of the ſeizure. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Next day, having obtained leave to open the <lb/>body, it was performed the fame
        evening in pre- <lb/>ſence of, and with the aſſiſtance of three other <lb/>ſurgeons. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The abdomen being much diſtended, appa- <lb/>rently by ſome fluid, a perforation was
        made in- <lb/>to it with a trocar, in the uſual place of tapping <lb/>for an aſcites; by
        which, however, nothing but <lb/>air was let out. </p>
      <pb n="93"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The abdomen was then opened in the uſual <lb/>manner, when the ſtomach and inteſtines
        appear- <lb/>ed greatly diſtended; which diſtenſion ceaſed, <lb/>upon letting out the air
        contained in them. The <lb/>ſtomach, liver, gall-bladder, and inteſtines, in <lb/>every
        other reſpect exhibited a moſt healthy <lb/>appearance; and no obſtruction whatever was
        <lb/>found in the gall-ducts, or any extravaſation in <lb/>the cavity of the abdomen. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The thorax was then opened, the right cavi- <lb/>ty of which was found to contain more
        than <lb/>three pints of reddiſh water, with two cyſts de- <lb/>tached and floating therein;
        one of the cyſts <lb/>ruptured but not quite emptied of its fluid. The <lb/>right lobe of
        the lungs was much compreſſed, <lb/>ſo as to occupy but a trifling part of the cavity.
        <lb/>The left lobe, the heart, and all other parts <lb/>which we examined, were in a
        perfectly ſound <lb/>ſtate; and what is very remarkable, not the leaſt <lb/>adheſion was
        found in either cavity. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>As Dr Steele had expreſſed an earneſt wiſh <lb/>for the diſſection, I tranſmitted the
        account to <lb/>him by the earlieſt opportunity, and ſome time <lb/>after received the
        following: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple quotes">Dear Sir, I am much obliged to you for <lb/>communicating ſo
          immediately the particulars <pb n="94"/>
          <lb/>of the diſſection, which, though it throws ſome <lb/>light on the immediate cauſe of
          our patient's <lb/>death, little enables us to fay what might have <lb/>been done to
          prevent it. One means only <lb/>ſuggeſts itſelf to me, and that, from the ſhort
          <lb/>period between the attack and cloſe of the <lb/>ſcene, a doubtful one. The effuſion
          into the <lb/>right cavity of the thorax aſcertained, Would <lb/>an opening between the
          ribs, into a depending <lb/>part of that cavity, have mitigated the ſymp- <lb/>toms, or
          ſaved life? </q>
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
