<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: Recherches sur la maladie convulsive epidemique</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>VI. Recherches sur la maladie convulsive epidemique attribué par quelques
              observateurs à l'Ergot, et confondue avec la gangrene seche de Solognots. Par M.
              Saillant. Vide Histoire de la Société Royale de Médecine. Tom. 1. 4to. Paris.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries, for the years 1783-1784. Exhibiting a concise view of the
              latest and most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected
              and published by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Physician to His Royal
              Highness the Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians,
              Edinburgh, and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen,
              Edinburgh, &amp;c. </title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for J. Murray, Fleet-Street, and C. Dilly, Poultry; and
                  for W. Gordon and C. Elliot, Edinburgh.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1783-1784</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">9</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">78-83</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110526937</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v9_0078">
    <body>
      <pb n="78"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>VI. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Recherches ſur la maladie convulſive epidemique <lb/>attribué par quelques obſervateurs
        à l'Ergot, et <lb/>confondue avec la gangrene ſeche de Solognots. <lb/>Par <hi rend="roman"
          >M. Saillant</hi>. Vide Hiſtoire de la Société <lb/>Royale de Médecine. Tom. 1. 4to. <hi
          rend="roman">Paris</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N the memoir before us, the author ſets out <lb/>with obſerving,
        that the experiments under- <lb/>taken by the Society, to determine whether the <lb/>ergot
        rye be capable of producing dry gangrene, <lb/>or not, agreed with the obſervations of
        Langi- <lb/>us, Perrault, Dodart, and others; but that, on <lb/>the other hand, there are
        many reſpectable autho- <lb/>rities which exculpate the ergot or ſpurred rye, <lb/>and refer
        to other cauſes the diſeaſe which has <lb/>been attributed to it in Germany and Sweden.
        <lb/>To clear up this matter, Mr Saillant has compared <lb/>together the authors who have
        written upon the <lb/>ſubject. He finds, that they do not agree with <lb/>regard to the
        cauſe of the diſeaſe; but that its <lb/>progreſs and ſymptoms are eſſentially different
        <lb/>from thoſe of the dry gangrene. To prove this, <pb n="79"/>
        <lb/>in the paper before us, he gives a detail of the <lb/>ſymptoms of each of theſe
        diſeaſes; and to this he <lb/>ſubjoins an hiſtorical view of the progreſs of the
        <lb/>convulſive epidemic of Sweden and Germany,the <lb/>cauſe of which is not yet entirely
        determined. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The dry gangrene is characterized, he ob- <lb/>ſerves, by the mortification of ſome one
        of the <lb/>extremities, ſometimes of all of them. Often <lb/>it is preceded by a redneſs,
        which, however, is <lb/>not inflammatory, and by ſome veſications. <lb/>The limb ſwells,
        becomes painful, and has a ſen- <lb/>ſation ſometimes of cold, more frequently of un-
        <lb/>ſupportable heat. The veſſels are obliterated, <lb/>the phlegm becomes black and hard,
        and the <lb/>patient, at the point of death, is happy, if, from <lb/>a ſpontaneous
        ſeparation of the gangrenous part, <lb/>he can ſurvive, with the loſs of his extremities.
        <lb/>The firſt ſymptoms of this diſeaſe are not alarm- <lb/>ing. The pulſe continues for
        ſome time nearly <lb/>in the natural ſtate, and is gradually weakened, <lb/>in proportion to
        the violence of the diſeaſe. <lb/>The blood appears black and thick, and the <lb/>urine in a
        natural condition. The belly is hard <lb/>and tenſe, but the appetite continues, and dige-
        <lb/>ſtion goes on as in health; it is only towards <lb/>the end of the diſeaſe, and even on
        the approach <pb n="80"/>
        <lb/>of death, that diarrhœa uſually comes on. Af- <lb/>ter death, on the examination of the
        body, the <lb/>inteſtines, and other viſcera, are often found <lb/>ſtrewed over with
        gangrenous ſpots. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The cure of this diſeaſe is ſometimes accom- <lb/>pliſhed in the beginning, by profuſe
        ſweats, and <lb/>by a good diet. The medical treatment conſiſts <lb/>in evacuating the primæ
        viæ, in giving inter- <lb/>nally laxative apozems, diuretics and antiſeptics, <lb/>while
        recourſe is had externally to thoſe topical <lb/>applications which are proper for reſiſting
        gan- <lb/>grene, for favouring the ſeparation of the diſ- <lb/>eaſed part, without
        amputation, and for aiding <lb/>ſuppuration. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After this deſcription of the dry gangrene, <lb/>he next proceeds to give an account of
        the con- <lb/>vulſive epidemic affection which has been con- <lb/>founded with it. In that
        diſeaſe, there is not, <lb/>he obſerves, any gangrene. The violent con- <lb/>vulſions are
        its eſſential characteriſtic. It has <lb/>no regular courſe, but returns by paroxyſms;
        <lb/>and while it is in reality leſs dangerous than the <lb/>former diſeaſe, it yet makes
        its attack with much <lb/>more alarming appearances. The patient at <lb/>one time feels as
        if he were burnt with devour- <lb/>ing fire, and ſoon after is ſenſible of cold, simi- <pb
          n="81"/>
        <lb/>lar to what ariſes from the application of water. <lb/>Theſe ſymptoms are accompanied
        with loſs of <lb/>appetite, nauſea and vomiting, which are ſoon <lb/>ſucceeded by an
        inexpreſſible pain. The pa- <lb/>tient, without ſhedding tears, utters lamentable
        <lb/>cries, and the affected members are either con- <lb/>tracted with extreme violence, or
        remain ſtretch- <lb/>ed out with inflexible rigidity. The pains ſoon <lb/>abate, when the
        patient is able to ſtretch the <lb/>contracted membranes, or to bend thoſe that <lb/>have
        been ſtretched; but they return in a freſh <lb/>acceſſion, with the ſame ſeverity. The
        patient <lb/>is no ſooner out of the fit, than he is tormented <lb/>with a voracious
        appetite; and he digeſts with <lb/>ſufficient eaſe, all ſorts of aliment. In particu-
        <lb/>lar years, there ſucceeds ſwelling of the feet or <lb/>hands, and the fingers have been
        covered with <lb/>veſicles full of ſeroſity, the diſcharge of which, <lb/>however, does not
        procure any relief. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The diſeaſe, after ſeveral acceſſions, terminates <lb/>itſelf by ſweat or diarrhœa,
        which is more vio- <lb/>lent when patients eat little, than when they eat <lb/>a great deal.
        But, for the moſt part, there re- <lb/>mains, for the ſpace of ſome weeks, ſeveral in-
        <lb/>conveniencies, ſuch as vertigo, tinnitus aurium, <lb/>deafneſs, loſs or diminution of
        ſight, or the like. <pb n="82"/>
        <lb/>If the affection continues long, it degenerates <lb/>into epilepſy; and if during the
        affection, there <lb/>ſhall occur a mental diſorder, it in general con- <lb/>tinues for
        life. If there occurs an obſtruction <lb/>of the liver, there in general ſupervenes a ſpit-
        <lb/>ting of blood, ſometimes followed by phthiſis, <lb/>by epilepſy, palſy, or in fine, by
        apoplexy. This <lb/>diſeaſe attacks moſt frequently thoſe who are <lb/>plethoric, and in
        that caſe the convulſions are <lb/>the moſt violent. But thoſe of the phlegmatic
        <lb/>temperament are moſt ſubject to comatoſe af- <lb/>fections after it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Some have obſerved blood iſſue from the noſe <lb/>and mouth after death; but they have
        not ob- <lb/>ſerved any alteration in the viſcera, excepting <lb/>that the lungs were much
        inflated and diſtend- <lb/>ed with blood. In other caſes, the liver and <lb/>gall-bladder
        have been much diſtended with <lb/>bile, and an eryſipelatous inflammation has been
        <lb/>obſerved over the whole ſurface of the abdomi- <lb/>nal, and even the thoracic viſcera. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Antiſpaſmodics, he tells us, joined to diapho- <lb/>retics, appear to be the only
        remedies uſeful a- <lb/>gainſt this diſeaſe. Narcotics have ſeemed only <lb/>to aggravate
        the affection. But bleeding and <lb/>purgatives have been employed with ſome ad- <pb n="83"/>
        <lb/>vantage in the beginning of the diſeaſe, accord- <lb/>ing to the circumſtances and
        temperament of <lb/>the patient. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After this account, of the ſymptoms attending <lb/>each of theſe diſeaſes, and of the
        difference in the <lb/>method of treatment, Mr Saillant next proceeds <lb/>to give an
        hiſtorical account of the different peri- <lb/>ods at which the convulſive epidemic has
        manifeſt- <lb/>ed itſelf. He begins with mentioning its occur <lb/>rence in Weſtphalia in
        the year 1597, which he <lb/>conſiders as its firſt appearance in Europe; and <lb/>concludes
        with the epidemic in Sweden in 1754, <lb/>of which an account was publiſhed by Linnæus,
        <lb/>in his Amœnitates Academiæ, who treats of it <lb/>under the title of <hi rend="italic"
          >raphania</hi>, from the idea, that <lb/>it was occaſioned by the raphaniſtrum or char-
        <lb/>lock growing among the barley. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
