<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Bowen: ccount of a singular Tumour in the Groin</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>James Bowen</persName>
            </author>
            <title>V. Account of a singular Tumour in the Groin, removed by Extirpation. By Mr James
              Bowen, Surgeon to the 30th Regiment.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries, for the years 1783-1784. Exhibiting a concise view of the
              latest and most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected
              and published by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Physician to His Royal
              Highness the Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians,
              Edinburgh, and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen,
              Edinburgh, &amp;c. </title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for J. Murray, Fleet-Street, and C. Dilly, Poultry; and
                  for W. Gordon and C. Elliot, Edinburgh.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1783-1784</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">9</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">374-379</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110526937</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v9_0374">
    <body>
      <pb n="374"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>XXX. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Hiſtory of a Caſe of Tetanus ſucceſsfully treated by <lb/>the Uſe of large Doſes of
        Opium. By Mr <hi rend="roman">Wil- <lb/>liam Chavaſſe</hi>, Surgeon at Burford, Oxford-
        <lb/>ſhire. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">S</hi><hi rend="sc">Eptember</hi> 27th 1780. Mr T— B—, <lb/>about ten
        years of age, by a fall from a <lb/>tree, fractured his leg, a few inches above the
        <lb/>articulation with the tarſus. By the violence of <lb/>the ſhock, the tibia was forced
        through the in- <lb/>teguments. In a ſhort time after the accident, <lb/>the fracture was
        reduced, the limb laid in a pro- <lb/>per poſition, the wound dreſſed ſuperficially,
        <lb/>and the patient put upon the antiphlogiſtic plan. <lb/>From the day of the accident to
        the 16th of Octo- <pb n="375"/>
        <lb/>ber, every thing went on favourably; the wound <lb/>ſeemed diſpoſed to heal, the
        fractured limb was <lb/>perfectly at eaſe, and his general health promi- <lb/>ſed a ſpeedy
        and happy recovery. However, on <lb/>this day, the patient complained of a ſlight ſtiff-
        <lb/>neſs of his neck, with a ſcarce perceptible rigi- <lb/>dity of the muſcles ſubſervient
        to the motion of <lb/>the jaw, but ſo trivial as to be little noticed by <lb/>him; and as
        every other circumſtance went on <lb/>favourably, I attributed it to a cold which the
        <lb/>patient had caught by frequently ſitting up in <lb/>his bed without proper covering.
        The rigidity <lb/>and ſtiffneſs increaſing the two following days, <lb/>made me apprehenſive
        of the attack of a teta- <lb/>nus; which opinion was ſtrengthened by that of <lb/>Mr
        Bradley, a very ingenious ſurgeon now <lb/>ſettled at Hartford, and whoſe kind aſſiſtance
        <lb/>during the progreſs of the cure I ſhall on all oc- <lb/>caſions be happy to
        acknowledge. The conti- <lb/>nuance of theſe ſymptoms demanded the uſe of <lb/>opiates.
        Therefore, on the 18th, I ſent him an <lb/>embrocation, with Liniment. ſapon. Tinct. The-
        <lb/>baic. utriuſque par. æq. directing it to be uſed <lb/>with freedom five or ſix times
        a-day. But as <lb/>topical applications alone were not to be truſted <lb/>here, I gave him
        three camphorated draughts in <pb n="376"/>
        <lb/>twenty-four hours, with twenty drops of the <lb/>Thebaic tincture in each. On the
        following <lb/>day, the ſymptoms were ſomewhat alleviated, <lb/>and the medicines were
        continued. The wound, <lb/>during this period, was not in the leaſt altered; <lb/>nor was
        there any other untoward ſymptom, ex- <lb/>cluſive of thoſe already enumerated. On the
        <lb/>20th, there was a little dyſpnœa: a phyſician <lb/>was called in; who made no other
        alteration in <lb/>the patient's medicine, than in reducing the The- <lb/>baic tincture to
        twelve drops to be taken four <lb/>times a-day, leaving, however, diſcretionary <lb/>power
        to increaſe the opiate according to cir- <lb/>cumſtances. On the 21ſt, anodyne cataplaſms
        <lb/>and fomentations were occaſionally applied to <lb/>the fauces: the rigidity and
        difficulty of brea- <lb/>thing increaſing, the laudanum was augmented <lb/>to twenty-five
        drops, to be taken every ſix <lb/>hours; and as the patient was coſtive, an ene- <lb/>ma was
        thrown up, but without effect. The <lb/>ſucceeding day, the jaw was more fixed, deglu-
        <lb/>tition nearly impeded, and his reſpiration more <lb/>diſtreſſingly operoſe; added to
        theſe, we had <lb/>frequent and ſevere ſubſultus tendinum, and the <lb/>bowels ſo
        obſtinately coſtive as to require the <lb/>ſtimulus of two very active clyſters before any
          <pb n="377"/>
        <lb/>effect was produced. The Thebaic tincture <lb/>was increaſed five drops to each
        draught, and <lb/>the anodyne cataplaſms and fotus were fre- <lb/>quently applied. The 23d,
        the jaw remained <lb/>as on the preceding day, but the ſubſultus ten- <lb/>dinum recurred
        with additional violence; the <lb/>wound ſtill retained its former healthy appear-
        <lb/>ance; the laudanum was reduced to twenty-five <lb/>drops every ſixth hour, the patient
        being rather <lb/>comatoſe; a ſtimulating clyſter was adminiſter- <lb/>ed, which brought
        away a ſmall but extremely <lb/>fœtid ſtool. He continued much the ſame on <lb/>the 24th,
        when a terebinthinate clyſter was gi- <lb/>ven, which not only diſpoſed the bowels to be
        <lb/>more ſoluble, but likewiſe induced a very large <lb/>ſecretion of urine. As the coma
        had now left <lb/>the patient, we had again recourſe to thirty <lb/>drops of the Thebaic
        tincture for each doſe. <lb/>The 25th, 26th, and 27th, he continued the uſe <lb/>of his
        medicine, without any variation of the <lb/>ſymptoms. On the 28th, the right ſide (the frac-
        <lb/>ture being on the left) became paralytic; the <lb/>opiate was increaſed to thirty-five
        drops every <lb/>ſix hours; and though the ſubject was ſo young, <lb/>this doſe ſcarcely
        produced any ſenſible effect. <lb/>This plan was purſued to the 31ſt, throwing up <pb
          n="378"/>
        <lb/>occaſionally a purgative clyſter. The evening <lb/>of this day, our patient complained
        of nauſea, <lb/>and, after conſiderable efforts, vomited a large <lb/>quantity of pus.
        November 1ſt, he took a ſa- <lb/>line purgative draught, to remove any purulent
        <lb/>colluvies that might be lodged in the primæ <lb/>viæ. This did its duty: the diſcharge
        from the <lb/>wound till this period had been favourable, but <lb/>was now converted into a
        corroſive ichor; in <lb/>conſequence of which, I increaſed the Thebaic <lb/>tincture to
        forty drops, and to each doſe added <lb/>two ounces of a ſtrong decoction of the bark.
        <lb/>The rigidity of the jaw was much augmented <lb/>on the 2d, and the ſubſultus tendinum
        conſider- <lb/>ably increaſed; forty-five drops of the lauda- <lb/>num were now given with
        the bark, and this <lb/>plan perſiſted in till the 14th, without any the <lb/>leaſt
        variation, taking care to keep the body ſo- <lb/>luble by a free uſe of clyſters. On the
        15th, <lb/>the patient complained of a moſt excruciating <lb/>pain in his thigh; the
        difficulty of breathing was <lb/>much increaſed, and the ſubſultus tendinum ſo <lb/>violent
        as to threaten immediate diſſolution. <lb/>Under ſuch a complication of dangerous ſym-
        <lb/>ptoms, the opiate in a large doſe appeared the <lb/>unicum remedium; ſixty drops of the
        Thebaic <pb n="379"/>
        <lb/>tincture were therefore immediately given. The <lb/>eventual ſucceſs of the medicine
        juſtified the <lb/>practice; for, in leſs than half an hour, the pain <lb/>and ſpaſms were
        effectually removed, and the <lb/>patient thrown into a refreſhing fleep. At the
        <lb/>expiration of ten hours, he awoke, without ſtu- <lb/>por, without fever, and with a
        viſible diminu- <lb/>tion of his late alarming ſymptoms. The rigi- <lb/>dity of the jaw
        inſenſibly abated, reſpiration be- <lb/>came perfectly eaſy, and the wound regained <lb/>its
        former favourable ſtate. The opiate was gra- <lb/>dually diminiſhed to the 30th, when the
        ſubſul- <lb/>tus tendinum and every other diſagreeable <lb/>ſymptom had left him. The wound
        healed in a <lb/>ſhort time, ahd the patient began to walk about <lb/>with very little
        inconvenience, only finding at <lb/>intervals a pricking ſenſation near the fractured
        <lb/>part. This, however, was exceedingly trivial, <lb/>and but of ſhort duration; for, in
        about eigh- <lb/>teen weeks after the accident, a conſiderable <lb/>piece of the tibia
        exfoliated; ſince which to this <lb/>time, he has been perfectly well, and the defor-
        <lb/>mity, the conſequence of the fracture, ſo very <lb/>little as not to be diſcovered but
        by a very cloſe <lb/>examination. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
