<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: Mémoire ſur quelques maladies du Foie qu'on attribue à
          d'autres organes</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>VIII. Mémoire ſur quelques maladies du Foie qu'on attribue à d'autres organes, et
              ſur des maladies dont on fixe ordinairement le Siége dans le Foie, quoiqu'il n'y ſoit
              pas. Par M. Portal. Vide Mémoires de l'Académie Royale des Sciences, année 1777. 4to.
              Paris.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries, for the years 1785. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest
              and most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and
              published by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Physician to His Royal
              Highness the Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians,
              Edinburgh, and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen,
              Edinburgh, &amp;c. </title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for J. Murray, Fleet-Street; and C. Elliot,
                  Edinburgh.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1785</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">10</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">115-122</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110351911</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v10_0115">
    <body>
      <pb n="115"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>VIII. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Mémoire ſur quelques maladies du Foie qu'on at- <lb/>tribue à d'autres organes, et ſur
        des maladies <lb/>dont on fixe ordinairement le Siége dans le Foie, <lb/>quoiqu'il n'y ſoit
        pas. Par <hi rend="roman">M. Portal. Vide </hi>
        <lb/>Mémoires de l'Académie Royale des Sciences, <lb/>année <hi rend="roman">1777. 4to.
          Paris. </hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">O</hi>F all the diſeaſes which afflict mankind, <lb/>none are more
        dangerous than thoſe of <lb/>which we are ignorant of the ſeat. Every viſ- <lb/>cus has a
        texture peculiar to itſelf; it is ſubject <lb/>to affections from which the others are free;
        <lb/>and it is freed from theſe in a manner peculiar <pb n="116"/>
        <lb/>to itſelf. Since, then, the great art of medicine <lb/>is to aſſiſt nature, this can be
        done only when <lb/>the ſeat of the diſeaſe is perfectly known. This <lb/>conſideration has
        induced our author to endea- <lb/>vour to arrive at the diſcovery of truth, by the
        <lb/>examination of dead bodies. And anatomy, it <lb/>muſt be allowed, is in no reſpect more
        uſeful <lb/>in medicine, than in pointing out to us the <lb/>morbid conditions to which
        parts are ſub- <lb/>jected. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the memoir now before us, M. Portal, <lb/>availing himſelf of the information thus
        ac- <lb/>quired, endeavours to point out errors reſpect- <lb/>ing diſeaſes of the liver,
        which his practice has <lb/>diſcovered to him. And here he is not aſha- <lb/>med to own,
        that he has often been miſtaken; <lb/>a confeſſion which merits much higher praiſe <lb/>than
        pretenſions to infallability. For, from an <lb/>acknowledgment of error, an author obtains
        <lb/>the merit of integrity, the advantage of being <lb/>uſeful, and the honour of having
        himſelf diſco- <lb/>vered truths which had formerly eſcaped his <lb/>obſervation. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He ſets out with obſerving, that effuſions in- <lb/>to the right cavity of the cheſt,
        and enlarge- <lb/>ments of theſe lobes of the lungs which it con- <pb n="117"/>
        <lb/>tains, often cauſe ſuch a derangement in the <lb/>ſituation of the liver, that it is
        ſuſpected to be <lb/>obſtructed, although in a perfectly natural <lb/>ſtate. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In confirmation of this aſſertion, he relates <lb/>the caſe of an advocate, whoſe
        ordinary phyſi- <lb/>cian, from the ſymptoms, concluded that he <lb/>was ſubjected to a
        diſeaſe of the liver. Mr <lb/>Portal, when called in conſultation, diſcovered <lb/>a large
        tumour under the falſe ribs of the right <lb/>ſide. And as, while the ſymptoms to which he
        <lb/>was principally ſubjected, loſs of ſtrength and <lb/>appetite, accompanied with
        yellowneſs of the <lb/>ſkin, and the like, indicated an affection of that <lb/>organ, as
        there was no cough, pain of heart, <lb/>purulent expectoration, or any other circum-
        <lb/>ſtance which pointed out an affection of the <lb/>lungs, his opinion perfectly
        coincided with that <lb/>of the ordinary phyſician. On this idea, then, <lb/>they directed
        their practice; but the diſeaſe <lb/>increaſed daily, and a colliquative diarrhœa
        <lb/>ſupervening, the patient was cut off by a ma- <lb/>raſmus. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr Portal was ſo confident of the diſeaſe of <lb/>this patient, that he would not have
        thought of <lb/>opening the body, had it not been his practice <pb n="118"/>
        <lb/>to open every patient who died under his care. <lb/>But how great, ſays he, was my
        ſurpriſe, when <lb/>I found the liver in a perfectly natural ſtate. <lb/>It was in the lungs
        alone that the diſeaſe had <lb/>its ſeat. Theſe were full of obſtructions form- <lb/>ed by a
        ſcrophulous ſubſtance. And in the <lb/>right ſide there were ſeveral abſceſſes commu-
        <lb/>nicating together, from whence was diſcharged <lb/>a conſiderable quantity of purulent
        matter. The <lb/>volume of the lungs thus increaſed, depreſſed <lb/>the diaphragm, and the
        liver was conſequently <lb/>puſhed lower than its natural ſituation. In this <lb/>manner it
        formed, below the falſe ribs of the <lb/>right ſide, that protuberance which was taken
        <lb/>for a large obſtruction. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After this, Mr Portal mentions, ſeveral ſimi- <lb/>lar caſes, particularly that of the
        late Duc de <lb/>Chaulnes, treated by him and by M. Bordeu. <lb/>He remarks alſo, that a
        ſimilar deception may <lb/>take place on the left ſide, from the ſpleen be- <lb/>ing
        diſplaced in the ſame manner. But as its <lb/>ſize is leſs, the enlargement is never ſo
        great. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Another kind of miſtake often committed, is <lb/>that of believing that there is a
        diſeaſe of the <lb/>liver, wherever yellowneſs occurs as a ſymp- <lb/>tom. It is true, he
        remarks, that this colour <pb n="119"/>
        <lb/>is obſervable in many affections of the liver. <lb/>But as there are ſome diſeaſes of
        that viſcus <lb/>which are followed by no yellowneſs, ſo, on the <lb/>other hand, yellowneſs
        often ſupervenes, where <lb/>the liver is perfectly ſound, and where the ſe- <lb/>cretion of
        bile takes place in the moſt regular <lb/>manner. He tells us, that, in ſeveral inſtances,
        <lb/>upon opening the bodies of patients, who died <lb/>from obſtructions in the inteſtinal
        canal, and in <lb/>whom a yellow colour had been obſerved be- <lb/>fore death, he has found
        the lacteal veſſels filled <lb/>with a yellow fluid, bitter to the taſte, and ca- <lb/>pable
        of inflammation when thrown upon the <lb/>fire. Hence he concludes, that when the bile
        <lb/>is obſtructed in the inteſtine, it makes its way <lb/>into the lacteals, and is thus
        inſinuated into the <lb/>blood, though the ſecretion be perfectly natural. <lb/>In the ſame
        manner alſo, he explains the yel- <lb/>low appearance in new born infants. For he
        <lb/>contends, that he has found a ſimilar fluid, not <lb/>only in their lacteal veſſels,
        but in the thoracic <lb/>duct: that, in theſe caſes, he has found the <lb/>gall-bladder
        almoſt empty: that, when the gall- <lb/>bladder, on the other hand, has been much di-
        <lb/>ſtended, there has been no jaundice: and, fi- <lb/>nally, that this yellow colour does
        not take <pb n="120"/>
        <lb/>place where the meconium is freely diſcharged, <lb/>and where, therefore, no
        obſtruction happens <lb/>in the inteſtinal canal. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From theſe circumſtances, he concludes, that <lb/>yellowneſs, in ſome caſes, takes
        place without <lb/>any affection of the liver, but from a reflux of <lb/>bile into the
        blood, through the lacteal veſſels. <lb/>And, in further proof of this doctrine, he tells
        <lb/>us, that, in dogs, he has induced jaundice by <lb/>putting a ligature on the ſmall
        inteſtines. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If, however, on ſome occaſions, diſeaſes <lb/>have been attributed to the liver, where
        it is not af- <lb/>fected; ſo, in other caſes, diſeaſes have had <lb/>their ſeat in this
        viſcus, where the affection has <lb/>been attributed to other organs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The liver, he obſerves, is often ſubjected to <lb/>obſtructions, giving riſe to
        vomiting, where the <lb/>cause of the affection is unknown. In proof <lb/>of this aſſertion,
        he relates two caſes. In the <lb/>firſt of theſe the patient, after being long ſub-
        <lb/>jected to violent vomiting, was cut off by hectic <lb/>fever and atrophia. It was
        imagined, that the <lb/>diſeaſe was ſeated in the ſtomach; but upon <lb/>opening the body,
        that viſcus was found to be <lb/>perfectly ſound, and it was diſcovered, that the
        <lb/>affection entirely depended on an enlargement <pb n="121"/>
        <lb/>and obſtruction of the liver. The ſecond caſe <lb/>is that of the Marchioneſs d'Epagny.
        In her <lb/>ſimilar ſymptoms took place, and the vomiting <lb/>was ſo ſevere as to render
        the cure almoſt de- <lb/>ſperate. When M. Portal was called, by ac- <lb/>curate examination,
        he diſcovered an enlarge- <lb/>ment of the liver. This led him to have re- <lb/>courſe to
        mercurials, and other aperients, by <lb/>which a complete cure was effected. Since <lb/>that
        time, he tells us, that he has treated ſe- <lb/>veral other patients in the ſame manner,
        with <lb/>equal ſucceſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Another affection of the liver, which phy- <lb/>ſicians often overlook, is violent
        hæmorrhage, <lb/>happening from this viſcus, where the blood <lb/>paſſes through the ductus
        communis into the <lb/>inteſtinal canal, and from thence into the ſto- <lb/>mach. He relates
        ſeveral inſtances of this kind, <lb/>and obſerves, that by diſſection after death, he
        <lb/>has often detected miſtakes, the hæmorrhage, <lb/>during the life of the patient, being
        ſuſpected <lb/>to proceed from the ſtomach, and in ſome in- <lb/>ſtances even from the
        lungs, while, in reality, <lb/>it aroſe from the liver. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In concluding this memoir, M. Portal ob- <lb/>ſerves, that he has ſeen enlargements of
        the <pb n="122"/>
        <lb/>liver happily terminated by a large hæmorrhage. <lb/>And as an example of this kind, he
        relates the <lb/>caſe of Mr Aublet, a celebrated botaniſt, who <lb/>was, in this manner,
        entirely freed from a tu- <lb/>mour in the right hypochondrium, productive <lb/>of very
        alarming ſymptoms. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From the different particulars mentioned in <lb/>this memoir, M. Portal infers, that
        reſearches <lb/>of this kind, founded on accurate obſervations, <lb/>cannot fail to be of
        the higheſt utility, and that <lb/>they well merit the attention of phyſicians. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
