<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: Description of a Plant yielding Asafœtida</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>XII. Description of a Plant yielding Asafœtida, in a Letter from John Hope, M. D.
              F. R. S. to Sir Joseph Banks, Bart. P. R. S. Vid. Philosophical Transactions. Vol.
              LXXV. Part 1. 4to. London.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries, for the years 1785. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest
              and most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and
              published by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Physician to His Royal
              Highness the Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians,
              Edinburgh, and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen,
              Edinburgh, &amp;c. </title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>London: Printed for J. Murray, Fleet-Street; and C. Elliot,
                  Edinburgh.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1785</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">10</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">160-164</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110351911</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v10_0160">
    <body>
      <pb n="160"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>XII. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Deſcription of a Plant yielding Aſaſœtida, in a <lb/>Letter from <hi rend="roman">John
          Hope</hi>, M. D. F. R. S. to <lb/><hi rend="roman">Sir Joſeph Banks</hi>, Bart. P. R. S.
        Vid. Phi- <lb/>loſophical Tranſactions. <hi rend="roman">Vol. LXXV. Part 1. <lb/>4to.
          London.</hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>T is near a thouſand years, Dr Hope ob- <lb/>ſerves, ſince
        aſaſœtida was firſt uſed in me- <lb/>dicine, but it is not above ſeventy years ſince <lb/>we
        had any ſatisfactory account of the plant <lb/>which yields it. Kaempfer, who, towards the
          <pb n="161"/>
        <lb/>end of the laſt century, travelled over a great <lb/>part of Aſia, and was in thoſe
        parts of Perſia <lb/>where the aſafœtida is collected, not only <lb/>gives a full account,
        in his Amoenitates Ex- <lb/>oticæ, of the method of obtaining it, but alſo <lb/>deſcribes
        the plant from whence it is obtained, <lb/>but it had never been cultivated in any Euro-
        <lb/>pean garden, till Dr Pallas was fortunate <lb/>enough to raiſe it from ſome ſeeds which
        were <lb/>ſent from the mountains of Ghilanin in Perſia. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the year 1777, Dr Guthrie of St Peterſ- <lb/>burgh, gave to Dr Hope two roots of it
        which <lb/>he had obtained from Profeſſor Pallas. Both <lb/>theſe roots were planted in the
        open ground <lb/>in the botanic garden at Edinburgh. One of <lb/>theſe died, but the other
        did well. It has lately <lb/>flowered and produced ſeed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr Hope availing himſelf of this opportuni- <lb/>ty, preſented the Royal Society of
        London with <lb/>a minute and accurate deſcription of this plant, <lb/>which is now
        publiſhed in their tranſactions, <lb/>and illuſtrated by two elegant engravings, the
        <lb/>one exhibiting the flower, the other the leaves <lb/>of the plant. As Dr Hope's
        deſcription will <lb/>not admit of any abridgment, we muſt here <pb n="162"/>
        <lb/>content ourſelves with obſerving, that the aſa- <lb/>ſœtida growing in the botanical
        garden at Edin- <lb/>burgh, is an umbelliferous plant, of a pale ſea- <lb/>green colour,
        which grows to the height of <lb/>about three feet. That the ſtem is deciduous, <lb/>but the
        root perennial. That every part of <lb/>the plant, when wounded, pours forth a rich
        <lb/>milky juice, reſembling aſafœtida both in ſmell <lb/>and taſte. At times alſo, a ſmell,
        ſuch as a <lb/>faint impregnation of aſafœtida yields, was <lb/>perceivable at the diſtance
        of ſeveral feet. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Although, however, from all theſe circum- <lb/>ſtances, there is reaſon to conclude,
        that this is <lb/>a plant which produces true aſafœtida, yet Dr <lb/>Hope has obſerved, that
        the deſcription and <lb/>drawing preſented by him to the Royal Society, <lb/>differ in many
        reſpects from thoſe formerly <lb/>publiſhed by Kaempfer. Sir Joſeph Banks <lb/>ſuggeſts, in
        a note annexed to this paper, that <lb/>gummi-reſinous ſubſtance, known by the name <lb/>of
        aſafœtida, may, as well as the ſanguis dra- <lb/>conis, and ſome other gums, be
        indifferently <lb/>the produce of various ſpecies of plants; and <lb/>that while Kaempfer
        has deſcribed one, Dr <lb/>Hope has deſcribed another. </p>
      <pb n="163"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>With regard to the method of obtaining gum <lb/>aſafœtida, Dr Hope obſerves, on the
        authority <lb/>of Kaempfer, that, at the proper ſeaſon, the <lb/>root is cut over once and
        again: that from the <lb/>inciſion there flows a thick juice, like cream; <lb/>and that
        this, farther thickened, is the aſafœtida <lb/>of the ſhops. As the juice which the plant
        <lb/>growing in the botanical garden at Edinburgh <lb/>yields, ſeems evidently to be the
        ſame with the <lb/>officinal aſafœtida; and as the plant bears the <lb/>viciſſitudes of our
        climate, growing in the open <lb/>air without protection, and, even in an unfa-
        <lb/>vourable ſeaſon, producing a good deal of ſeed, <lb/>he expreſſes his hope, that it may
        become an <lb/>article of cultivation in this country, of no in- <lb/>conſiderable
        importance. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In addition to the above extract from the <lb/>Tranſactions of the Royal Society, we
        may ob- <lb/>ſerve, that the aſafœtida plant, in the botanic <lb/>garden of Edinburgh, has
        now flowered three <lb/>different times, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> in the year 1782, in
        1784, <lb/>and in 1785. But we are ſorry to learn, that <lb/>none of its ſeeds, though put
        into the hands <lb/>of very able botaniſts and gardeners, have ve- <lb/>getated. </p>
      <pb n="164"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>With the deſcription of the plant growing <lb/>at Edinburgh, Dr Hope ſent to the Royal
        So- <lb/>ciety ſeveral other accurate drawings, particu- <lb/>larly one exhibiting a full
        view of the entire <lb/>plant in flower, which being too large for the <lb/>ſize of the
        Philoſophical Tranſactions, was not <lb/>engraven. We are glad, however, to hear, <lb/>that
        all theſe drawings were alſo ſent by Dr <lb/>Hope's direction to Dr Pallas, who wiſhed to
        <lb/>publiſh, in the Flora Roſſica, a deſcription and <lb/>delineation of this rare plant.
        It is alſo pro- <lb/>bable, that, to gratify the curioſity of this coun- <lb/>try, Dr Hope
        will publiſh an engraving of the <lb/>entire plant, in its moſt perfect ſtate. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
