<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Lee Perkins: The History of a case of Hydrocephalus terminating
          fatally</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>William Lee Perkins</persName>
            </author>
            <title>II. The History of a case of Hydrocephalus terminating fatally, after a
              salivation was excited by the use of Mercury. By Dr William Lee Perkins physician at
              Kingston upon Thames.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries M, DCC, LXXXVI. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest and
              most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and published
              by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Physician to His Royal Highness the
              Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians, Edinburgh,
              and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen, Edinburgh, &amp;c. </title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: Printed for C. Elliot, Edinburgh; and C. Elliot and Co. No 332,
                  opposite Somerset-Buildings, Strand, London.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1787</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">11</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">298-302</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108715662</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v11_0298">
    <body>
      <pb n="298"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>II. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>The Hiſtory of a caſe of Hydrocephalus termi- <lb/>nating fatally, after a ſalivation
        was ex- <lb/>cited by the uſe of Mercury. By <hi rend="roman">Dr Wil- <lb/>liam Lee Perkins
          phyſician at Kingſton <lb/>upon Thames</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">O</hi>N Tueſday (Jan. 10. 1786), I was called <lb/>to ſee Miſs L—, a
        child two years <lb/>and a half old. This was the ſixth day of <lb/>her illneſs, at leaſt of
        that which ſeemed to <lb/>require any attention; though ſhe had been ob- <lb/>ſerved to be
        drooping, or ſlightly ailing, at <lb/>times, for near three months before. The <lb/>ſymptoms
        were as follow. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Pulſe weak, quick, (140 in a minute); con- <lb/>ſiderable heat of the ſkin: Frequent
        red fluſh- <pb n="299"/>
        <lb/>ings in the face; ſickneſs of the ſtomach, <lb/>and retching: Slight ſtupor; from
        which, <lb/>whenever ſhe was rouſed to take either food <lb/>or medicine, ſhe took both with
        great greedi- <lb/>neſs. The pupils of the eyes very much di- <lb/>lated, and continued ſo
        in the ſtrongest light: <lb/>She was likewiſe quite blind, and had been ſo for <lb/>two days
        paſt; the blindneſs being preceded <lb/>by a ſtrabiſmus or ſquinting. Some ſtools were
        <lb/>paſſed this and the preceding day, ſometimes <lb/>of a green, ſometimes of a dark
        colour. Three <lb/>teeth were now diſcovered, juſt come through <lb/>the gums, and another
        ſeemed very near <lb/>through: The tongue and mouth were moiſt <lb/>and clean. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From the principal appearances above- <lb/>mentioned, I did not heſitate immediately to
        <lb/>declare to the parents my opinion, that the <lb/>diſeaſe was occaſioned by water
        collected in <lb/>the ventricles of the brain. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>She had been purged ſeveral times; and <lb/>had bliſters applied about the head and
        neck, <lb/>ſome of which now diſcharged copiouſly. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Apprehending the cauſe of the diſeaſe to be <lb/>as before obſerved, and finding no
        good ef- <lb/>fect from what had been hitherto applied, I <pb n="300"/>
        <lb/>determined to make trial of the method re- <lb/>commended in the Medical Commentaries
        by <lb/>Dr Dobſon and Dr Percival; regretting the <lb/>want of an opportunity for an earlier
        and <lb/>more ſatiſfactory trial. I directed, however, <lb/>that one grain of calomel ſhould
        be given once <lb/>in ſix hours; and that one ſcruple of the ſtrongeſt <lb/>mercurial
        ointment ſhould be carefully rubbed <lb/>into the legs and thighs morning and evening. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Jan. 11th, She had taken four grains of ca- <lb/>lomel, and had three ſcruples of the
        ointment <lb/>rubbed in. All the ſymptoms much the <lb/>ſame. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>12th, She had taken only three grains more <lb/>of calomel, her mouth being faſt ſhut,
        ſo that <lb/>nothing could be got down after yeſterday <lb/>noon; although ſhe had been once
        ſenſible in <lb/>the night, and ſpoken: The ointment was <lb/>therefore directed to be
        rubbed in thrice a- <lb/>day, and a nutritive clyſter to be injected once <lb/>in four or
        five hours. The right-eye was this <lb/>day obſerved to be ſomewhat inflamed, and <lb/>the
        fleſh of the face felt rigid. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>13th, The pulſe very irregular; ſometimes <lb/>ſlower, ſometimes quicker, fluctuating
        be- <lb/>tween 80 and 160, with frequent red fluſh- <pb n="301"/>
        <lb/>ings of the face: The pupils of the eyes more <lb/>contracted; but ſtill blind. The
        other eye <lb/>was this day inflamed; a difficulty of breath- <lb/>ing came on; and the
        ſymptoms in general <lb/>were more unfavourable, and indeed ſeemed <lb/>to indicate a
        gradual tendency to diſſolution. <lb/>The ptyaliſm came on this day. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>14th, The ptyaliſm copious; reſpiration <lb/>ſtill laborious. Convulſions had come on
        laſt <lb/>night, which laſted two hours; and ſhe moan- <lb/>ed much and loud: She had one
        ſtool: No- <lb/>thing could be got down by the mouth. The <lb/>nouriſhing clyſters were
        continued, and a <lb/>ſmall quantity of the ointment rubbed in. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>15th, The convulſions and moanings came <lb/>on again this morning about ſix o'clock,
        and <lb/>continued till between nine and ten: The <lb/>ptyaliſm copious : The right-arm was
        of a <lb/>blackiſh purple colour; and ſhe died the ſame <lb/>day. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Throughout the whole of her illneſs, at <lb/>leaſt that part of it which I ſaw, ſhe lay
        in a <lb/>ſtupor, or ſtate of inſenſibility, without any <lb/>of thoſe ſhriekings which are
        ſo often obſerved <lb/>to happen in the laſt stage of this diſorder. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>After death the head was opened, and up- <pb n="302"/>
        <lb/>wards of four ounces of water were found to <lb/>have been collected in the ſuperior
        ventricles <lb/>of the brain, which guſhed out with great <lb/>force on cutting into them.
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
