<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Duncan: An account of violent Pains from a particular Species of Worm
          under the Skin</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Dr Duncan</persName>
            </author>
            <title>VIII. A Letter from Dr Graham at Stirling to Dr Henry Galloway, giving an account
              of violent Pains from a particular Species of Worm under the Skin. Communicated to Dr
              Duncan.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries M, DCC, LXXXVII. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest and
              most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and published
              by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Physician to His Royal Highness the
              Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians, Edinburgh,
              and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen, Edinburgh, &amp;c. </title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: Printed for C. Elliot, T. Kay and Co. at Dr Cullen's Head, No 332,
                  opposite Somerset-Place, Strand, London; and for C. Elliot, Edinburgh.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1788</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">12</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">366-369</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108716147</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v12_0366">
    <body>
      <pb n="366"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>VIII. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>A Letter from Dr <hi rend="roman">Graham</hi> at Stirling to Dr <lb/><hi rend="roman"
          >Henry Galloway</hi>, giving an account of vio- <lb/>lent Pains from a particular Species
        of <lb/>Worm under the Skin. Communicated to Dr <lb/><hi rend="roman">Duncan</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>N the month of Auguſt laſt I was conſulted <lb/>in the caſe of
        John Stewart, a young <lb/>gentleman about twelve years of age, in the <lb/>country of
        Appin. For ſome time paſt he <lb/>had been afflicted with excruciating pains in <lb/>his
        limbs, and other parts, to ſuch a degree <lb/>as to render his life completely miſerable.
        <lb/>This was aſcribed to his having got his <lb/>cloaths drenched with rain in a boat as he
        <lb/>was fiſhing in the night-time. Believing his <lb/>caſe to be entirely rheumatic (which
        I ſtill <lb/>think it was in ſome degree), I could do little <lb/>more, at ſo great a
        diſtance from medical <pb n="367"/>
        <lb/>help, than to direct him to be wrapped in <lb/>flannel, and to bliſter the parts
        occaſionally <lb/>which were moſt pained. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In January laſt I received a letter from his <lb/>father, dated the 17th of that month;
        of which <lb/>the following is an extract: </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>
        <q rend="diple quotes">I am now favoured with both your let- <lb/>ters; by which I find you
          preſcribe no <lb/>kind of medicines for my ſon, who ſtands <lb/>much in need of relief;
          this very day be- <lb/>ing one of his worſt. But one thing <lb/>has happened to him which
          I dare ſay <lb/>will ſurpriſe you. About eight days ago <lb/>he diſcharged two worms; the
          one from <lb/>his breaſt, the other from his knee. For <lb/>ſome hours before, he was like
          to go di- <lb/>ſtracted with racking pain in both places. <lb/>Ever ſince he had ſome
          reſpite till this <lb/>day. We have one of the worms preſer- <lb/>ved in ſpirits. It is
          near an inch long, all <lb/>in joints in the back, with a hard ſcale on <lb/>it. I am
          poſitive he has more of them, <lb/>from the manner of his complaint now. <lb/>Pray have
          you any knowledge of theſe <lb/>creatures? Or is there any aſſiſtance can <lb/>be given in
          getting quit of them? I am <pb n="368"/>
          <lb/>poſitive he has the rheumatiſm, with this <lb/>unlucky addition. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In anſwer to this I wrote, that the boy had <lb/>probably ſlept on the graſs, or been
        otherwiſe <lb/>expoſed to ſome kind of flies, which, piercing <lb/>the ſkin, had lodged
        their ova in the punc- <lb/>ture. Theſe being hatched, and the maggots <lb/>come to
        maturity, and now probably ready <lb/>to become aureliæ, they made their way <lb/>through
        the ſkin in ſearch of a proper place <lb/>where they might undergo that change; and
        <lb/>that, conſequently, I hoped he would ſoon be <lb/>entirely freed from his troubleſome
        gueſts. <lb/>Meanwhile, I aſked the favour of the father <lb/>to ſend me a few of the worms. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In another letter, dated 24th January, he <lb/>ſays, <q rend="diple quotes">Since I
          wrote my laſt, another worm <lb/>came out of Jack's knee, of which I was <lb/>an
          eye-witneſs, attended with racking pains. <lb/>The pain got to his head two days ago,
          <lb/>and ſo ſwelled it that he ſees but a little in <lb/>one eye. Laſt night he was
          bliſtered be- <lb/>hind his neck; but no relief as yet. In <lb/>ſhort, he is in a
          miſerable ſituation, and <lb/>has loſt his appetite entirely. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Soon after this he diſcharged another worm <pb n="369"/>
        <lb/>from above his eye, and others from different <lb/>places; all, ſo far as I could
        learn, ſuch as <lb/>are expoſed to the air, and to which the flies <lb/>might have had
        acceſs. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A few days ago I had another letter, dated <lb/>the 15th April; which ſays, <q
          rend="diple quotes">Jack is ſtill <lb/>tormented with vehement pain in the foot <lb/>and
          knee alternately; and the cold water <lb/>is the only thing which gives him eaſe. <lb/>No
          ſwelling: and, even in the time of the <lb/>pain, he can ſuffer it to be rubbed hard;
          <lb/>which he could not do when diſcharging <lb/>the worms. And the pain is now quite
          <lb/>different from what it was at that time. <lb/>I ſend a ſmall vial with three of the
          worms. </q>
        <lb/>Theſe I now ſend you, together with a dried <lb/>one in another vial, which appears to
        be of <lb/>the ſame kind, and which I received on the <lb/>15th of February laſt. It was
        diſcharged <lb/>from another young man in the weſtern parts <lb/>of Perthſhire: And I have
        heard of ſeveral <lb/>other boys in the Highlands, who were af- <lb/>flicted with the ſame
        diſorder this laſt win- <lb/>ter. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
