<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Hamilton: On the Benefit of Cyder in the Cure of Dropsy</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Thomas Hamilton</persName>
            </author>
            <title>IX. A Letter to Dr Duncan from Mr Thomas Hamilton Student of Medicine at
              Edinburgh; on the benefit of Cyder in the Cure of Dropsy, and on the induction of
              artificial Emphysema.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries M, DCC, LXXXVII. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest and
              most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and published
              by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Physician to His Royal Highness the
              Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians, Edinburgh,
              and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen, Edinburgh, &amp;c. </title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: Printed for C. Elliot, T. Kay and Co. at Dr Cullen's Head, No 332,
                  opposite Somerset-Place, Strand, London; and for C. Elliot, Edinburgh.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1788</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">12</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">370-374</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108716147</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v12_0370">
    <body>
      <pb n="370"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>IX. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>A Letter to Dr <hi rend="roman">Duncan</hi> from Mr <hi rend="roman">Thomas Ha-
          <lb/>milton</hi> Student of Medicine at Edinburgh; <lb/>on the benefit of Cyder in the
        cure of Dropſy, <lb/>and on the induction of artificial Emphy- <lb/>ſema. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">Y</hi>OUR communicating to the world what- <lb/>ever regards the
        reſtoration of health <lb/>to mankind, or whatever may contribute to <lb/>the advancement of
        any branch of medical <lb/>ſcience, prompts me thus to lay before you a <lb/>fact reſpecting
        the cure of dropſy, which a <lb/>few days ago, I had the happineſs of hearing <lb/>you ſpeak
        of, with ſo much preciſion and <lb/>judgment. I am induced to mention this <lb/>practice, as
        you did not take notice of it in <lb/>your lecture: and perhaps (in this country, <lb/>where
        the article is little made uſe of, and in <lb/>general but little known unleſs at ſome
        parti- <pb n="371"/>
        <lb/>cular taverns in the ſummer ſeaſon) it has <lb/>never had a fair and candid trial by
        indivi- <lb/>duals or practitioners. The article to which <lb/>I allude is the liberal uſe
        of cyder, as practi- <lb/>ſed with very great ſucceſs among the com- <lb/>mon people of
        Devonſhire; a county in Eng- <lb/>land where it very much abounds, and is to <lb/>be had in
        the greateſt perfection, and cheap- <lb/>er than ſmall-beer. I can with confidence
        <lb/>aver, that I have ſeen cures performed by it, <lb/>where no other medicine or regimen
        had <lb/>been uſed, and that too in the advanced ſtate <lb/>of anaſarca or general dropſy:
        And it ſel- <lb/>dom fails in local or partial dropſies, in the <lb/>incipient or advanced
        ſtates. It is drunk of <lb/>plentifully, perhaps to the amount of two or <lb/>three Engliſh
        quarts a-day. Here is then a <lb/>very large quantity of fluid taken, in one day, <lb/>which
        muſt, in ſome meaſure, invalidate the <lb/>prevailing opinion, that the profuſe uſe of
        <lb/>fluids is pernicious in this diſeaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In what particular manner this medicine <lb/>operates, I will not preſume to ſay, as I
        on- <lb/>ly mean to mention the fact. But, with all <lb/>deference and ſubmiſſion to your
        ſuperior <pb n="372"/>
        <lb/>judgment, I ſhall, with the utmoſt diffidence, <lb/>offer you my opinion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In ſo far only as the diſeaſe depends either <lb/>upon a local or general relaxation or
        debility, <lb/>or a loſs of tone and power in the abſorbent <lb/>ſyſtem, or when the
        exhalant is ſo redundant <lb/>as to overpower the abſorbent functions, <lb/>when there is no
        ſuſpicion of ſcirrhus in any <lb/>of the viſcera, or when the diſeaſe has not <lb/>been
        uſhered in by jaundice, it may, in ſome <lb/>meaſure, depend on its cooling aſtringency,
        <lb/>having a moſt peculiarly grateful cordial aci- <lb/>dity, of which thoſe patients are
        particularly <lb/>greedy. Perhaps it may operate gently in <lb/>the way of diureſis and
        catharſis; or as ſti- <lb/>mulating the abſorbent ſyſtem in general. <lb/>But if conjoined
        in the way of regimen or <lb/>drink, along with thoſe very powerful reme- <lb/>dies you
        mentioned, I doubt not of the hap- <lb/>pieſt ſucceſs attending it. It allays the im-
        <lb/>moderate thirſt, and prevents the deſire for <lb/>liquids; which alone is a great
        object. Thus <lb/>it may be ſubſtituted for other drinks, and be <lb/>a convenient vehicle
        for other medicines, as <lb/>the bark, &amp;c. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I here, likewiſe, take the liberty of offer- <pb n="373"/>
        <lb/>ing you a hint reſpecting the nature of em- <lb/>phyſema; which only ſerves further to
        cor- <lb/>roborate your opinion of the nature of that <lb/>diſeaſe. Though the natural
        diſeaſe has ne- <lb/>ver occurred to me, I have ſeen the artificial <lb/>one in the higheſt
        perfection, and in the living <lb/>human body too. This odd ſort of lan- <lb/>guage may
        perhaps ſtartle you a little. It is <lb/>a practice, though happily not a common one,
        <lb/>and as happily little known among the vul- <lb/>gar. But there are a few who know it,
        and <lb/>turn it very much to their advantage; I mean <lb/>among ſeamen and ſoldiers. For
        there is, per- <lb/>haps, no ſet of men (excepting ſlaves) who have <lb/>more frequently
        recourſe to impoſition, and <lb/>who are more ſkilled in producing diſeaſes. <lb/>Theſe men
        make a ſmall puncture or inciſion <lb/>into the cellular membrane of the ſcrotum, <lb/>into
        which they introduce a blow-pipe, and <lb/>inflate the whole ſcrotum to a moſt enormous
        <lb/>ſize, exactly reſembling a rupture; and this <lb/>extends up the inguen to the
        inſertion of the <lb/>chord. This they practiſe to obtain their <lb/>diſcharges from the
        ſervice. And thus the <lb/>ſkill and judgment of ſurgeons, in both army <lb/>and navy, are
        doubly employed, in the de- <pb n="374"/>
        <lb/>tection of impoſture, and the cure and diſco- <lb/>very of real diſeaſe; which every
        charitable <lb/>man muſt allow is not always in the power <lb/>of any human being. I had
        this confeſſion <lb/>from one whom I was employed to examine <lb/>as an object for
        invaliding; whoſe anſwers <lb/>to the queſtions I put to him, reſpecting his <lb/>diſeaſe,
        were ſo evaſive and contradictory, as to <lb/>lead me to ſuſpect a falacy, which I at length
        <lb/>detected. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
