<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Rait: Some Observations on the Endemic Fever of the Coast of
          Guinea</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>William Rait</persName>
            </author>
            <title>VI. Some Observations on the Endemic Fever of the Coast of Guinea; and on the
              Occurrence of Small - pox a few days after birth. By Mr William Rait, Surgeon,
              Dundee.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries M, DCC, LXXXVIII. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest
              and most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and
              published by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Physician to His Royal
              Highness the Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians,
              Edinburgh, and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen,
              Edinburgh, &amp;c. </title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: Printed for C. Elliot, T. Kay and Co. at Dr Cullen's Head, No 332,
                  opposite Somerset-Place, Strand, London; and for C. Elliot, Edinburgh.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1789</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">13</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">313-319</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108771076</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v13_0313">
    <body>
      <pb n="313"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>VI. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Some Obſervations on the Endemic Fever of the <lb/><hi rend="roman">Coaſt</hi> of <hi
          rend="roman">Guinea</hi>; and on the Occurrence of <lb/>Small-pox a few days after birth.
        By Mr <lb/><hi rend="roman">William Rait</hi>, Surgeon, <hi rend="roman">Dundee</hi>. </head>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center space">
          <lb/>1. </head>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE bilious fever, of which I am about <lb/>to ſpeak, is the
          fatal endemic of the <lb/>Torrid Zone. It may be fitly divided into <lb/>two ſtages, the
          inflammatory and the putrid. <lb/>With certain cauſes co-operating, it attacks <lb/>all
          ages and conſtitutions. But it is particu- <lb/>larly the bane of the young, vigorous, and
          <lb/>plethoric; of thoſe whoſe blood is in a ſtate <lb/>moſt liable to favour and produce
          obſtruc- <lb/>tions. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The cauſes moſt obvious in producing bili- <lb/>ous ſever are, firſt, violent
          exerciſe in, or ex- <lb/>poſure to the ſun's heat; drinking of ardent <pb n="314"/>
          <lb/>ſpirits, or any thing that cauſes a copious per- <lb/>ſpiration, provided it gets a
          ſudden check, by <lb/>the application of cold moiſt air; ſudden im- <lb/>merſion in cold
          water, or ſudden expoſure to <lb/>the dew of the evening. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Theſe are the cauſes chiefly producing it <lb/>in the young and plethoric. But the
          aged <lb/>and infirm muſt be acted upon in a different <lb/>way, to produce the ſame
          diſeaſe. Their <lb/>fibres are naturally lax, and the texture of <lb/>their blood
          diſſolved; conſequently, they are <lb/>more liable to be acted on by ſlighter cauſes,
          <lb/>than would produce the ſame ſymptoms in <lb/>younger ſubjects. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>In the firſt ſet, viz. the young and pletho- <lb/>ric, it generally attacks with
          violent ſymptoms <lb/>of inflammation and determination to the <lb/>head; pains in the
          region of the loins; nau- <lb/>ſea, coſtiveneſs, great thirſt, and the pulſe is <lb/>hard
          and quick. In the ſecond ſet, viz. The <lb/>aged and infirm, it attacks with ſymptoms of
          <lb/>nervous atonia; great and ſudden proſtration <lb/>of ſtrength; dejection of ſpirits ;
          the pulſe <lb/>ſmall, quick and fluttering; palpitations, and <lb/>frequent deliquium
          animi. </p>
        <pb n="315"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The indications of cure are, <hi rend="italic">firſt</hi>, To leſſen <lb/>the
          momentum of the blood by proper eva- <lb/>cuations: and that is firſt to be done by bleed-
          <lb/>ing plentifully from a large orifice, from which <lb/>we may often obſerve the moſt
          inſtantaneous <lb/>good effects. Yet I would not adviſe the uſe <lb/>of the lancet beyond
          ten hours from the firſt <lb/>attack; as the violent momentum ſoon looſens <lb/>the
          texture of the red globules, and hurries <lb/>them and the whole maſs of fluids into a
          ſtate <lb/>of putrefaction. The uſe of a warm ſemicu- <lb/>pium is alſo ſometimes of
          advantage; but for <lb/>the above reaſon, it ſhould not be employed <lb/>later than the
          lancet. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>2<hi rend="italic">dly</hi>, To evacuate the primæ viæ of ſordes <lb/>lodged there,
          which is beſt effected by anti- <lb/>monial preparations; and the beſt of that <lb/>claſs,
          in my opinion, is the tartarus antimo- <lb/>nialis. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>3<hi rend="italic">dly</hi>, To evacuate the redundant bile; <lb/>which is beſt done
          by ſmall doſes of antimo- <lb/>nial tartar and neutral ſalts, and plentiful di-
          <lb/>lution with mild teas and gruels. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>4<hi rend="italic">thly</hi>, To deſend the primæ viæ and in- <lb/>teſtines from the
          acrimony of the bile. For <pb n="316"/>
          <lb/>this purpoſe, 1 have generally uſed mucilagi- <lb/>nous and oily glyſters. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>With this treatment, we may commonly be <lb/>able to procure a ſlight remiſſion the
          ſecond <lb/>or third day. Then the practitioner ſhould <lb/>not, even for a moment, delay
          throwing in the <lb/>Peruvian bark. If the ſtomach will eaſily <lb/>bear it, he may throw
          in the bark at the rate <lb/>of half an ounce, or more, every hour. I would <lb/>alſo
          adviſe the copious uſe of the vegetable <lb/>acid, and juices of ripe fruits, as oranges,
          &amp;c. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Provided the bark binds, and occaſions a <lb/>diſagreeable weight at the ſtomach, it
          will be <lb/>neceſſary to add to each doſe a few grains of <lb/>pulv. rhæi. If, on the
          contrary, it paſſes off <lb/>freely by ſtool, I would by no means check it <lb/>for a
          little time: The practitioner will al- <lb/>ways have that in his power, as by adding a
          <lb/>few drops of tinct. Thebaic. he will ſoon <lb/>conquer the bark's tendency downwards. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Theſe are the moſt common indications, <lb/>and the method of cure which I have often
          <lb/>known to ſucceed. It generally has a criſis <lb/>by ſweat, or <choice>
            <corr>diarrhœa</corr>
            <sic>diarrhæa</sic>
          </choice>, about the ninth or <lb/>eleventh day, but is ſometimes protracted till <lb/>the
          thirteenth, when it leaves the patient in <pb n="317"/>
          <lb/>a ſtate of great debility both of body and <lb/>mind; ſo great, that I have known
          patients <lb/>(after the bark and other corroborants have <lb/>been copiouſly uſed)
          incapable of <hi rend="italic">ſeeing</hi>, <hi rend="italic">hear- <lb/>ing</hi>, or <hi
            rend="italic">thinking properly</hi>, for a fortnight or <lb/>three weeks; and during
          that time, their <lb/>imaginations haunted with the moſt frightful <lb/>ideas and fooliſh
          chimeras. Even the terrible <lb/>idea of being hanged, though they endeavour <lb/>to ſum
          up all the little fortitude they were <lb/>then maſters of to get rid of, would ſome-
          <lb/>times haunt their imaginations, till the gene- <lb/>ral flow of the nervous fluid,
          and tenſion of <lb/>the muſcular fibres, were reſtored. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A very common conſequence of bilious <lb/>fever, is ſwelled ankles, which likewiſe
          gene- <lb/>rally ſubſide as the tone of the ſyſtem is re- <lb/>ſtored. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>It is impoſſible to ſay where the inflamma- <lb/>tory ſtage ends, and the putrid
          commences, <lb/>they ruſh ſo rapidly into each other. The <lb/>emetic tartar is beſt
          calculated for the evacua- <lb/>tion of bilious ſordes; for this reaſon, that it <lb/>acts
          in a double capacity, by evacuating bile, <lb/>and at the ſame time determining the cir-
          <lb/>culating fluids to the ſurface. </p>
        <pb n="318"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Theſe ſew curſory remarks are the reſult <lb/>of my own practice, particularly on the
          Coaſt <lb/>of Guinea, and in the Weſt Indies, when I <lb/>was a very young practitioner.
        </p>
      </div>
      <space dim="vertical" unit="lines" quantity="2"> </space>
      <div type="section">
        <head rend="align-center">
          <lb/>2. </head>
        <p rend="space indent">
          <lb/>At a time when I was attending a patient <lb/>under inoculation, a lady, whom I alſo
          attend- <lb/>ed, was ſafely delivered of a male child. Two <lb/>or three days after the
          birth, I was deſired <lb/>to look at ſome ſpots which appeared on the <lb/>face, neck, and
          different parts of the body, <lb/>and which alarmed the friends of the infant. <lb/>I
          immediately pronounced the eruption to be <lb/>that of the ſmall-pox; and in conſequence,
          <lb/>took ſome pains to watch the progreſs. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>From ſome particular circumſtances in the <lb/>caſe of the mother, the child was
          rather fa- <lb/>tigued than nouriſhed, and the eruption came <lb/>but ſlowly out. However,
          it was found at <lb/>laſt neceſſary to put the child out to nurſe; <lb/>and,
          providentially, a very healthy one was <lb/>found: in conſequence of which, in a few
          <lb/>days I perceived the eruption (hitherto rather <pb n="319"/>
          <lb/>flat and tardy) put on a very different aſpect; <lb/>that of filling up, and
          maturating kindly. <lb/>The puſtules blackened, and went off, in the <lb/>uſual manner of
          the beſt diſtinct ſmall-pox. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I know, that ſome in the profeſſion are <lb/>prejudiced againſt the idea of infection
          taking <lb/>place in utero from the mother. But I con- <lb/>ſider this a marked caſe of
          that kind, and a <lb/>full proof of the error of ſuch prejudice. <lb/>It is a certain
          fact, that the ſmall-pox, in the <lb/>natural way, have prevailed in the neighbour-
          <lb/>hood of the child ſince it was put to nurſe, <lb/>without any new infection or
          exanthemata mak- <lb/>ing their appearance. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>And I know an old lady (grandmother to <lb/>the ſaid child), who ſays ſhe was born
          with <lb/>the ſmall-pox. It is certain, ſhe is now up- <lb/>wards of ſixty (in good
          health), and never <lb/>had any other. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Theſe facts I humbly mention to you. <lb/>They involve a number of queries, which I
          <lb/>hope in time will be both put and anſwered <lb/>by ſome of your numerous and very
          ingeni- <lb/>ous correſpondents. I only wiſhed to give <lb/>them ſimply, and without any
          commentary. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
