<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Lane: An Account of two Persons having a Bronchocele</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Timothy Lane</persName>
            </author>
            <title>V. An Account of two Persons having a Bronchocele, wherein the use of Burnt
              Sponge appeared to have a very considerable Effect. By Timothy Lane, F. R. S.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries M, DCC, LXXXVIII. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest
              and most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and
              published by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Physician to His Royal
              Highness the Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians,
              Edinburgh, and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen,
              Edinburgh, &amp;c. </title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: Printed for C. Elliot, T. Kay and Co. at Dr Cullen's Head, No 332,
                  opposite Somerset-Place, Strand, London; and for C. Elliot, Edinburgh.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1789</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">13</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">86-89</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108771076</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v13_0086">
    <body>
      <pb n="86"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>V. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>An Account of two Perſons having a Broncho- <lb/>cele, wherein the uſe of Burnt Sponge
        appear- <lb/>ed to have a very conſiderable Effect. By <lb/><hi rend="roman">Timothy
          Lane</hi>, F. R. S. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE firſt caſe here related, is that of a <lb/>young lady in the
        ſeventeenth year of <lb/>her age. She applied to Mr Lane, in Janu- <lb/>ary 1764, for a
        Bronchocele, which ſhe had <lb/>perceived growing fox about twelve months. <lb/>Mr Lane had,
        at firſt, recourſe to a powder, <lb/>conſiſting of millepedes, and the mercurius
        <lb/>alcalizatus, and to a ſolution of ſoluble tartar. <lb/>Theſe medicines were continued
        for about <lb/>three weeks, without any apparent benefit. <lb/>Mr Lane was then informed,
        that, in ſimilar <lb/>caſes, a lozenge of burnt ſponge, placed <lb/>under the tongue at
        night, when going to <lb/>bed, and remaining there till it gradually diſ- <lb/>ſolved, had
        been of uſe. To this remedy <lb/>he reſolved to have recourſe. To a dram <pb n="87"/>
        <lb/>of burnt ſponge, he added as much ſyrup as <lb/>was neceſſary to give it the proper
        conſiſt- <lb/>ence, and divided this quantity into ſix lozen- <lb/>ges. Theſe had not been
        continued for a <lb/>month, before the tumour gradually diſap- <lb/>peared; and, at the
        diſtance of twelve years <lb/>afterwards, when Mr Lane had an opportu- <lb/>nity of ſeeing
        her, he found that there never <lb/>had been even the ſlighteſt return of her for- <lb/>mer
        complaint. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Soon after this, two other patients labour- <lb/>ing under bronchocele, applied to Mr
        Lane. <lb/>To theſe, alſo, he directed the lozenges, <lb/>but without effect: Nor were they
        more be- <lb/>nefited by any other remedies which he em- <lb/>ployed. But he afterwards
        recommended <lb/>them to a young lady in the fifteenth year of <lb/>her age, having a
        bronchocele, where the <lb/>tumour was on the right ſide of the neck <lb/>only. To her,
        alſo, the lozenges of burnt <lb/>ſponge were directed. When ſhe firſt began <lb/>the uſe of
        them, ſhe found them trouble- <lb/>ſome, as it was unuſual for her to keep any <lb/>thing in
        her mouth in that way. But in a <lb/>ſhort time ſhe ſelt no inconvenience from <lb/>them,
        and went even to ſleep before they <pb n="88"/>
        <lb/>were diſſolved. After ſhe had uſed the lo- <lb/>zenges for about three weeks, ſhe com-
        <lb/>plained of headach. As Mr Lane ſuppoſed <lb/>this to ariſe from coſtiveneſs, he
        directed <lb/>ſome infuſion of ſenna, which relieved her. <lb/>In the ſpace of a month, the
        tumour began <lb/>to decreaſe; and, by the time ſhe had con- <lb/>tinued the lozenges for
        four months, it was <lb/>entirely gone, although it had been of two <lb/>years ſtanding
        before ſhe began the uſe of <lb/>them. Since their uſe, ſhe has had no return <lb/>of her
        complaint. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the former caſe, ſince different reme- <lb/>dies were employed, Mr Lane obſerves,
        <lb/>that it may perhaps be a matter of ſome <lb/>doubt, whether the cure was to be
        attribut- <lb/>ed to the ſponge. But in this caſe, as no <lb/>other remedy was taken, he
        thinks there <lb/>can be little doubt of its eſficacy. From <lb/>the facts which are here
        collected, it appears, <lb/>that the ſponge, employed in this manner, is <lb/>not always
        ſucceſsful. But in a diſeaſe ſo <lb/>obſtinate, it is of no ſmall importance to be
        <lb/>acquainted with a remedy which will ſome- <lb/>times ſucceed. </p>
      <pb n="89"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In a former volume of theſe Commenta- <lb/>ries, the employment of burnt ſponges, in a
        <lb/>different manner, for the cure of broncho- <lb/>cele, is recommended as uſed by Dr Bate
        of <lb/>Coventry; and our readers will ſind a full <lb/>account of his mode of giving it, in
        Mr Wil- <lb/>mer's Caſes in Surgery. It is probable, that <lb/>as little of the eſficacy of
        this article depends <lb/>on its being uſed at night only, and taken in <lb/>a very gradual
        manner, as is directed in Mr <lb/>Lane's mode of exhibiting it, as on its being
        <lb/>employed in the wane of the moon, the <lb/>time preſcribed for uſing it in that of Dr
        Bate. <lb/>But if further experience ſhall demonſtrate, t <lb/>hat a good effect does reſult
        from its em- <lb/>ployment, it will probably alſo aſcertain the <lb/>beſt mode of exhibiting
        it. And the facts <lb/>here related, ſhould at leaſt induce practi- <lb/>tioners to future
        trials, by which its eſficacy <lb/>will either be confirmed, or the fallacy re- <lb/>futed.
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
