<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Vaughan: Remarkable Effects of Cantharides in paralytic
          Affections.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>J. Vaughan</persName>
            </author>
            <title>VII. Remarkable Effects of Cantharides in paralytic Affections. By J. Vaughan, M.
              D. and Physician to the Leicester Infirmary. Vide Memoirs of the Medical Society of
              London, Vol. I. 8vo, London.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries M, DCC, LXXXVIII. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest
              and most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and
              published by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Physician to His Royal
              Highness the Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians,
              Edinburgh, and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen,
              Edinburgh, &amp;c. </title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: Printed for C. Elliot, T. Kay and Co. at Dr Cullen's Head, No 332,
                  opposite Somerset-Place, Strand, London; and for C. Elliot, Edinburgh.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1789</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">13</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">96-103</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108771076</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v13_0096">
    <body>
      <pb n="96"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>VII. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Remarkable Efſects of Cantharides in paralytic <lb/>Affections. By J. <hi rend="roman"
          >Vaughan</hi>, M. D. and <lb/>Phyſician to the Leiceſter Infirmary. <hi rend="roman"
          >Vide</hi>
        <lb/>Memoirs of the Medical Society of London, <lb/>Vol. I. <hi rend="roman">8vo,
          London.</hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">D</hi>R <hi rend="sc">Vaughan</hi> very juſtly obſerves, that,
        <lb/>while paralytic affections are very <lb/>common, they are frequently not to be o-
        <lb/>vercome by the utmoſt efforts of art. <lb/>Hence, any remedy, which promiſes to be
        <lb/>uſeful in ſo dreadful a malady, will be receiv- <lb/>ed both with candour and
        thankfulneſs by <lb/>the medical world. The remedy which Dr <lb/>Vaughan here recommends, is
        cantharides, <lb/>taken in ſubſtance. Many caſes of this diſ- <lb/>eaſe have, he tells us,
        occurred to him, in <lb/>which he has employed this remedy internal- <lb/>ly, both with <choice>
          <corr>ſafety</corr>
          <sic>ſaſety</sic>
        </choice> and advantage. And to <lb/>recommend it to the attention of others, he <pb n="97"/>
        <lb/>here preſents us with one of the moſt impor- <lb/>tant of many caſes which have come
        under <lb/>his cognizance. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A luſty and healthy young man, in the <lb/>twenty-firſt year of his age, being
        violently <lb/>heated, threw himſelf on the ground, and <lb/>fell faſt aſleep. At the end of
        ſome hours, <lb/>he was found utterly incapable of voluntary <lb/>motion, ſenſeleſs, with
        great coldneſs of the <lb/>limbs, and of the ſurface of the body. He <lb/>was deprived of
        the power of ſpeech, and <lb/>his water flowed involuntarily. In this ſtate, <lb/>his
        friends applied to an apothecary for aſ- <lb/>ſiſtance, who bled him, gave him a purge,
        <lb/>and applied a bliſter to his back. After the <lb/>operation of theſe medicines, Dr
        Vaughan <lb/>found him with a very conſiderable degree <lb/>of ſtupor, a frequent, unequal
        reſpiration, <lb/>and a very ſmall and feeble pulſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 28th of March, as he had not had <lb/>a ſtool for ſome days, a warm, ſtimulating
        <lb/>clyſter, with a proportion of ſacred tincture, <lb/>and tincture of jallap, was
        immediately admi- <lb/>niſtered. The whole head was covered with <lb/>a bliſter, as was alſo
        the ſacrum: And a vo- <lb/>latile lineament, with more than the uſual <pb n="98"/>
        <lb/>quantity of cauſtic volatile alkali, was applied <lb/>to the pubis, to the ſpine, and
        to the lower <lb/>extremities. A bolus, conſiſting of a ſcruple <lb/>of volatile ſalt, and
        as much of the cardiac <lb/>electuary, with a grain of cantharides in <lb/>powder, was
        ordered to be taken once every <lb/>ſix hours, and to be waſhed down with a <lb/>ſtrong
        infuſion of valerian, horſe-radiſh, <lb/>muſtard ſeed, and canella alba. This plan <lb/>was
        continued for three ſucceſſive days, with- <lb/>out producing any viſible effect. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 31ſt of March, the volatile ſalt, <lb/>and cordial electuary, were each increaſ-
        <lb/>ed to the quantity of half a dram, and the <lb/>grain of cantharides was added as
        before. <lb/>But, inſtead of being given only once in ſix <lb/>hours, it was ordered to be
        repeated every <lb/>three hours, with the infuſion as before di- <lb/>rected. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 4th of April, as no material change <lb/>had taken place in his diſeaſe, ten
        grains <lb/>more of the volatile ſalt, and a ſecond grain <lb/>of cantharides were added to
        each bolus; <lb/>and this doſe was directed to be repeated e- <lb/>very three or four hours,
        until ſome manifeſt <lb/>effect was produced. This plan was purſued <pb n="99"/>
        <lb/>till the 6th of April. But, on the evening <lb/>of that day, he became very reſtleſs.
        He <lb/>was able to toſs himſelf about; and, although <lb/>he could not articulate any
        words, yet he <lb/>made a great noiſe, expreſſive of much pain, <lb/>frequently applying his
        hand to the region of <lb/>the pubis, as if that were the part more par- <lb/>ticularly
        aggrieved. The bliſter was now re- <lb/>moved from his head, and the part waſhed <lb/>clean.
        A poultice of bread and milk, with <lb/>ſome oil, was applied to the bliſtered part of
        <lb/>the ſacrum, and his medicines were omitted. <lb/>In place of theſe, he was directed to
        drink <lb/>freely of barley-water, with gum-arabic. In <lb/>three day after this, all theſe
        painful ſymp- <lb/>toms were entirely removed: He was be- <lb/>come quite ſenſible: He could
        retain his <lb/>water: And the day following, he could <lb/>ſtand, when ſupported by two
        people. But <lb/>his countenance betrayed ſtrong marks of <lb/>the injury the brain had
        ſuſtained, and be- <lb/>ſpoke a degree of fatuity. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 9th of April, he was directed to <lb/>take once every eight hours, a bolus with
        a <lb/>ſcruple of guaiacum, as much volatile ſalt, and <lb/><choice>
          <corr/>
          <sic>and </sic>
        </choice>one grain of cantharides, drinking with <pb n="100"/>
        <lb/>it an infuſion of valerian. A ſeton was made <lb/>in his neck, and ſtimulating plaſters
        were <lb/>applied to the ſoles of his feet. He conti- <lb/>nued in this courſe till the 21ſt
        of April, <lb/>mending every day. He felt no inconveni- <lb/>ence from the cantharides taken
        to this quan- <lb/>tity: he ſlept well; ate his food with appe- <lb/>tite; and his bowels
        did their office with <lb/>regularity. His intellectual faculties, how- <lb/>ever, were much
        impaired. He had for- <lb/>gotten how to walk, and he had even his <lb/>letters to learn
        again. Nothing which had <lb/>paſſed from the time of his firſt ſeizure, had <lb/>left the
        ſmalleſt impreſſion on his mind. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But, in proportion as he gained ſtrength, <lb/>his mental faculties were reſtored. He
        could <lb/>ſoon walk with the aid of a ſtick: but his <lb/>limbs were feeble; and he ſtill
        continued to <lb/>drag them after him: and he had for ſome <lb/>time little uſe of his left
        hand and arm. It <lb/>was however obſervable, that he gained <lb/>ſomething every day. By
        the 4th of May, <lb/>he was able to walk tolerably well; but <lb/>the weakneſs of the left
        hand and arm ſtill <lb/>continued, though not to ſo great a degree. <lb/>He was now ordered
        an aromatic electuary <pb n="101"/>
        <lb/>with ſteel, and a warm decoction of Peru- <lb/>vian bark, to which was joined the daily
        <lb/>uſe of the cold bath. During the uſe of <lb/>theſe remedies, his progreſs to recovery
        con- <lb/>tinued; and, by the 12th of May, nothing <lb/>remained of his diſeaſe, excepting a
        trifling <lb/>weakneſs in his left hand. He ſoon after <lb/>recovered the entire uſe of this
        organ alſo, <lb/>and had no longer occaſion for any medical <lb/>aſſiſtance. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Although we muſt own that we cannot al- <lb/>together adopt Dr Vaughan's opinion, in
        <lb/>conſidering this caſe as a decided example of <lb/>the benefit to be reaped from the
        canthari- <lb/>des in palſy; yet it at leaſt ſerves to ſhew, <lb/>that in certain
        ſituations, and with ſome ha- <lb/>bits, this article may be taken to a very con-
        <lb/>ſiderable extent with impunity: And, when <lb/>taken in conjunction with the experience
        Dr <lb/>Vaughan has had of the benefit of cantharides <lb/>in other caſes of paralyſis, it
        ſhould at leaſt <lb/>lead to further trials of their employment in <lb/>that affection, when
        it obſtinately reſiſts other <lb/>modes of cure. Of the practice here recom- <lb/>mended, we
        have ourſelves no experience. <lb/>We have indeed ſeen cantharides, even in <pb n="102"/>
        <lb/>ſubſtance, taken internally, both in diabetic <lb/>caſes, and likewiſe with the view of
        increaſ- <lb/>ing the quantity of urine in dropſical affec- <lb/>tions. But in ſome of theſe
        inſtances, where <lb/>it was taken to a much leſs quantity than in <lb/>this caſe, and where
        it had no influence ei- <lb/>ther as augmenting or diminiſhing the diſ- <lb/>charge of
        urine, it induced, probably from <lb/>its action on the neck of the bladder, ſuch
        <lb/>violent ſtrangurious affections, as to give <lb/>very great diſtreſs to the patient:
        And, as <lb/>ſimilar effects may take place in paraly- <lb/>tic caſes, without being in any
        degree ad- <lb/>vantageous to the patient, it ſhould always <lb/>be employed with great
        caution. When in- <lb/>convenience ariſes from its ſtimulating too <lb/>much, Dr Vaughan
        directs the immediate <lb/>ſuſpenſion of its uſe: And he tells us, that <lb/>by this means,
        and allowing at the ſame <lb/>time the free uſe of milk and water as a <lb/>diluent, any
        troubleſome ſymptoms it occa- <lb/>ſions are ſoon removed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr Vaughan obſerves, in a note, that the <lb/>doſe of volatile ſalt which he gave in
        this caſe, <lb/>two ſcruples, viz. every three hours, may ſeem <lb/>to be rather large: But
        he mentions another <pb n="103"/>
        <lb/>caſe, in which he employed it to the extent of <lb/>half an ounce, diſſolved in half a
        pint of <lb/>water-gruel, taken faſting. This doſe was, <lb/>he tells us, continued for
        three weeks, with- <lb/>out producing any effect, either good or bad. <lb/>The patient only
        obſerved, that it heated the <lb/>fauces, and warmed the ſtomach, for a ſhort <lb/>time
        after it was taken. To determine whe- <lb/>ther it had produced any change in the com-
        <lb/>mon maſs of fluids, he ordered ſome blood to <lb/>be drawn from the arm. The blood was
        of <lb/>a more florid colour than uſual; but its tex- <lb/>ture was not in the leaſt broken.
        On the <lb/>contrary, after it had been allowed to ſtand <lb/>for many hours, he thought
        that it yielded <lb/>leſs ſerum than common, and that the craſſa- <lb/>mentum was rather
        firmer than ordinary. <lb/>This fact may be conſidered as a ſtrong evi- <lb/>dence, that it
        has not all thoſe effects upon <lb/>the circulating maſs, which ſome are diſpoſed <lb/>to
        imagine. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
