<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: Æthuſæ Cynapii in Corpore Humano Effectus nocivus</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>vII. Æthuſæ Cynapii in Corpore Humano Effectus nocivus. Auctore Rudolpho
              Buchhave, M. D. Vide Acta Regiæ Societatis Mediæ Hauniensis. Vol. I. 8vo,
              Hauniæ.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries M, DCC, LXXXIX. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest and
              most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and published
              by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Physician to His Royal Highness the
              Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians, Edinburgh,
              and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen, Edinburgh, &amp;c. </title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: Printed for C. Elliot and T. Kay, at Dr Cullen's Head, No 332,
                  opposite Somerset-Place, Strand, London; and for C. Elliot, Edinburgh. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1790</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">14</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">37-42</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108771605</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v14_0037">
    <body>
      <pb n="37"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>II. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Æthuſæ Cynapii in Corpore Humano Effectus no- <lb/>civus. Auctore <hi rend="roman"
          >Rudolpho Buchhave</hi>, M. D. <lb/><hi rend="roman">Vide</hi> Acta Regiæ Societatis Mediæ
        Hauni- <lb/>enſis. Vol. I. <hi rend="roman">8vo, Hauniæ.</hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">S</hi>OON after the publication of Dr Stoërk <lb/>had celebrated the
        praiſes of Cicuta, and <lb/>led to its employment over almoſt all Europe, <lb/>very
        different opinions came to be entertained <lb/>of its effects; and in particular, it was
        often <lb/>accuſed of producing alarming, and even dan- <lb/>gerous conſequences. Theſe, Dr
        Buchhave <lb/>thinks, may not unfrequently proceed from the <lb/>Æthuſa Cynapium, the Cicely
        or Fool's Parſ- <lb/>ley, as it is called in Engliſh, being mixed with <lb/>the conium
        maculatum, or common hemlock, <lb/>the article recommended by Dr Stoërk. To <lb/>this
        opinion our author is led, from ſome caſes <lb/>which fell under his own obſervation; and
        theſe <lb/>he relates in the paper before us. </p>
      <pb n="38"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The firſt caſe, is that of a widow, about forty <lb/> years of age, who had been long
        afflicted with <lb/>carcinomatous ulcers of her face and neck, pour- <lb/>ing forth a very
        fœtid ichor, and, although ſur- <lb/>rounded by callous edges, yet gradually extend-
        <lb/>ing to the neighbouring parts. In other re- <lb/>ſpects ſhe was in good health. Beſides
        laxa- <lb/>tives, Dr Buchhave preſcribed for her hemlock <lb/>pills, which ſhe took without
        any inconvenience <lb/>for the ſpace of two months. But no change <lb/>for the better being
        produced upon the diſeaſe, <lb/>he preſcribed the herb of the hemlock, direct- <lb/>ing an
        ounce of it to be boiled in thirty-two <lb/>ounces of ſimple water; and of the ſtrained li-
        <lb/>quor three ounces were ordered to be taken <lb/>daily, in different portions, for the
        ſpace of <lb/>four or five weeks. But during that time, ſhe <lb/>frequently complained that
        the draughts of her <lb/>decoction excited tremors, vertigo, headach, <lb/>cholic pains,
        vomiting, loſs of ſtrength, and a- <lb/>verſion at food. Dr Buchhave, ſuſpecting that
        <lb/>theſe might proceed from improper regimen, <lb/>directed ſtrict attention in that
        particular, and, <lb/>hoping for better effects, admoniſhed her to <lb/>continue the
        decoction. But being afterwards <pb n="39"/>
        <lb/>informed that conſequences ſtill more alarming <lb/>had taken place, particularly
        violent vomiting <lb/>and ſevere convulſions, and never having known <lb/>theſe to proceed
        from the Conium, he was led <lb/>to examine the plant with which ſhe was fur- <lb/>niſhed;
        and he ſoon found, that a large propor- <lb/>tion of the Æthuſa was mixed with the Conium.
        <lb/>After this ſhe was furniſhed with genuine and <lb/>unmixed hemlock. Of this ſhe formed
        a de- <lb/>coction, and took it in the manner before di- <lb/>rected, without any
        inconvenience. Under the <lb/>uſe of this, the ſymptoms above enumerated <lb/>gradually
        diminiſhed; her ſtrength was daily <lb/>augmented; the malignant ulcers yielded a laud-
        <lb/>able pus; and, in the ſpace of about eleven <lb/>months, ſhe was completely cured. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Soon after this, Dr Buchhave was conſulted <lb/>about the caſe of a woman in the
        country, <lb/>whoſe whole family had died of conſumption. <lb/>She was a little paſt her
        twentieth year, and <lb/>had complained for a long time of difficult reſ- <lb/>piration and
        dry cough. She had taken a va- <lb/>riety of remedies, without obtaining any relief.
        <lb/>Suſpecting tubercles in the lungs, Dr Buch- <lb/>have had recourſe to the Conium, which
        he di- <pb n="40"/>
        <lb/>rected under the form of decoction, half an <lb/>ounce of the plant being boiled with
        thirty- <lb/>two ounces of water to two pounds; and ſhe <lb/>was directed to take three
        ounces of the ſtrain- <lb/>ed liquor every two hours. After it had been <lb/>uſed with
        impunity for twenty-four days, ſhe <lb/>became affected with difficult reſpiration, head-
        <lb/>ach, cholic pains, nauſea, vomiting, laſſitude, <lb/>and torpor. Dr Buchhave ſuſpecting
        a ſimilar <lb/>accident to that formerly mentioned, examined <lb/>the leaves from which the
        decoction had been <lb/>formed; and here alſo he could eaſily diſtin- <lb/>guiſh the leaves
        of the Cicely, mixed with thoſe <lb/>of the Hemlock. To prove beyond doubt that <lb/>the
        ſymptoms mentioned above aroſe from <lb/>the decoction, two other perſons took each a
        <lb/>ſingle ounce of it; and, in the ſpace of a few <lb/>minutes, nauſea and cholic pains
        were excited <lb/>in both. This patient afterwards employed <lb/>the Hemlock, genuine and
        unmixed, without <lb/>ſuffering from thence any inconvenience. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Beſides theſe two, Dr Buchhave relates alſo <lb/>a third caſe, that of a young country
        man, a- <lb/>bout the 20th year of his age. When he ap- <lb/>plied for our author's advice,
        he was affected <lb/>with venereal ulcers on the palate, noſe, and <pb n="41"/>
        <lb/>right cheek. In conjunction with the uſe of <lb/>ſome laxative medicines, he was
        directed to uſe <lb/>a decoction of Hemlock. He prepared this <lb/>during the Summer from
        the plant collected in <lb/>his neighbourhood, and uſed it without any <lb/>inconvenience.
        But being afterwards obliged <lb/>to purchaſe it from an apothecary, it induced <lb/>great
        nauſea, vertigo, languor, and a variety <lb/>of other ſymptoms; and upon examination it
        <lb/>was found, that here nearly equal parts of the <lb/>Cicely and Hemlock were mixed: but
        the Hem- <lb/>lock being afterwards procured free from any <lb/>mixture, he took it without
        any inconvenience; <lb/>and in proceſs of time a complete cure was ob- <lb/>tained. Dr <choice>
          <corr>Buchhave</corr>
          <sic>Buckhave</sic>
        </choice> is of opinion, that here <lb/>the inconvenience reſulting from the Cicely,
        <lb/>was probably leſs conſiderable than would <lb/>otherwiſe have been the caſe, from the
        patient <lb/>having uſed a milk diet. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From theſe caſes Dr Buchhave concludes, <lb/>that the bad conſequences which ſome have
        <lb/>aſcribed to Hemlock, are in reality to be attri- <lb/>buted to other plants being mixed
        with it; and <lb/>he obſerves, that the different umbellatæ are <lb/>often confounded
        together, the conium not on- <lb/>ly being mixed with the æthuſa, but alſo with <pb n="42"/>
        <lb/>the cicuta viroſa, the chærophyllum, the phæl- <lb/>landrium, and ſeveral others. Dr
        Buchhave <lb/>tells us, that, truſting to extenſive experience, <lb/>he can boldly aſſert,
        that Hemlock, if it be not <lb/>productive of a good effect, will at leaſt be fol-
        <lb/>lowed by no bad conſequence, even when given <lb/>in large doſes. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
