<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Duncan: The History of a remarkable Affection of the Legs</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Dr Duncan</persName>
            </author>
            <title>VII. The History of a remarkable Affection of the Legs, terminating fatally.
              Communicated to Dr Duncan, in a Letter from Mr B. Wilmer, Surgeon in Coventry.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries M, DCC, LXXXIX. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest and
              most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and published
              by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Physician to His Royal Highness the
              Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians, Edinburgh,
              and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen, Edinburgh, &amp;c. </title>
          <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: Printed for C. Elliot and T. Kay, at Dr Cullen's Head, No 332,
                  opposite Somerset-Place, Strand, London; and for C. Elliot, Edinburgh. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1790</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">14</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">302-306</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108771605</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v14_0302">
    <body>
      <pb n="302"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>VII. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>The Hiſtory of a remarkable Affection of the <lb/>Legs, terminating fatally.
        Communicated to <lb/>Dr <hi rend="roman">Duncan</hi>, in a Letter from Mr <hi rend="roman"
          >B. Wilmer</hi>, <lb/>Surgeon in Coventry. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>F you ſhould ſuppoſe the incloſed caſe not <lb/>unworthy of a
        place in the next volume <lb/>of your uſeful Commentaries, you will do me <lb/>a favour in
        publiſhing it there. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Mr Gaunt, ſurgeon in Merriden, in the <lb/>county of Warwick, aged fifty-four, about
        <lb/>twelve years ſince had a fever of four months <lb/>continuance, which left him deprived
        of me- <lb/>mory. Notwithſtanding this misfortune, he <lb/>continued his buſineſs, which was
        fatiguing, <lb/>and enjoyed an uninterrupted ſtate of good <lb/>health, till the Spring of
        the year 1787, when <lb/>his appetite for food was become ſo voracious, <lb/>and he ate and
        drank to ſuch a degree, that <pb n="303"/>
        <lb/>his friends were apprehenſive that ſome diſ- <lb/>agreeable conſequences would enſue,
        and ad- <lb/>viſed him, but in vain, to loſe blood, to pre- <lb/>vent a fit of apoplexy; of
        which, from a con- <lb/>ſtant ſleepineſs that attended him, they were <lb/>particularly
        fearful. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 23<hi rend="italic">d</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Auguſt</hi>, in the morning, he
        <lb/>complained of a great coldneſs of his feet; <lb/>walked about to viſit his patients;
        and in the <lb/>evening his legs were bathed in warm milk <lb/>and water. He paſſed the
        night with in- <lb/>quietude; ſlept little, although he took ſeven <lb/>grains of ſoap-pill
        at bed-time; and at times <lb/>was ſlightly delirious. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the ſucceeding day he was ſleepy, kept <lb/>his bed, the coldneſs of his legs
        continuing; <lb/>and no means that were tried produced any <lb/>warmth in them. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>At this time, the ſkin was not cold to the <lb/>touch of the perſon who examined them,
        and <lb/>he had then neither pain nor numbneſs in the <lb/>parts. He now took, every ſix
        hours, half a <lb/>dram of bark, with twenty grains of ſnake- <lb/>root. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Two days from the time he firſt complained <lb/>of the coldneſs, he loſt the ſenſation
        of feel- <pb n="304"/>
        <lb/>ing in both legs; but the ſkin was not in the <lb/>leaſt diſcoloured; and he could move
        his legs <lb/>and feet in all directions. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Bliſters were now applied to the inſide of <lb/>each leg: They occaſioned a diſcharge,
        with- <lb/>out exciting pain. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 2<hi rend="italic">d</hi> of <hi rend="italic">September</hi>, his brother, a
        ſur- <lb/>geon of Birmingham, was conſulted. He or- <lb/>dered the bark to be continued,
        with the ad- <lb/>dition of confect. cardiaca, and the common <lb/>fomentation to be applied
        to his legs. A ca- <lb/>taplaſm alſo of oatmeal and beer grounds was <lb/>directed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">September</hi>8<hi rend="italic">th</hi>. I was deſired to viſit him.
        <lb/>Both his legs at this time were dead, and cold <lb/>as marble. At the parts where the
        bliſters <lb/>had been applied, and the epidermis removed, <lb/>the rete mucoſum had aſſumed
        a chocolate co- <lb/>lour; but, in other reſpects, the ſkin of the <lb/>limbs was not
        diſcoloured, but had exactly the <lb/>ſame pallid appearance as thoſe of a man who <lb/>had
        been dead three or four days. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I applied the point of a knife to the ſkin in <lb/>various parts, without his being
        ſenſible of ir. <lb/>About an inch above each knee he felt the <lb/>knife; and the ſkin was
        there warm. Theſe <pb n="305"/>
        <lb/>circumſtances marked the extent of the morti- <lb/>fication, for the eye could not
        perceive where <lb/>it terminated. He could move both his legs <lb/>from the bed with eaſe.
        His pulſe was rather <lb/>quicker than uſual, but without hardneſs or in- <lb/>termiſſion.
        His urine and ſtools, in quantity <lb/>and quality, were natural. Upon enquiring <lb/>into
        the ſtate of his appetite, he informed me, <lb/>that he had, on that day, dined on cold
        roaſt- <lb/>ed beef and cucumber. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">September</hi>10<hi rend="italic">th</hi>. I viſited him again. He
        <lb/>complained then of ſome pain about his knees. <lb/>Applying my hand to one of them, the
        ſkin <lb/>there was warmer than uſual; and, for the ex- <lb/>tent of ſome inches down each
        leg, the integu- <lb/>ments had the appearance of returning life. <lb/>Below the calf of
        each leg, the ſkin was be- <lb/>coming green; and, nearer the feet, had aſ- <lb/>ſumed a
        complexion of various ſhades, from a <lb/>light green to a faint yellow. His pulſe now
        <lb/>intermitted, about one ſtroke in ten. His tongue <lb/>was furred; and he had been, at
        intervals during <lb/>the night, delirious. On the outſide of the <lb/>left thigh, the
        integuments ſhewed a diſpoſi- <lb/>tion to gangrene, and were diſcoloured for a
        <lb/>conſiderable extent. He anſwered all the que- <pb n="306"/>
        <lb/>ſtions that were aſked him rationally; ſeemed <lb/>perſectly ſenſible of his dangerous
        ſituation, <lb/>and begged I would publiſh his caſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>12<hi rend="italic">th</hi>. The gangrene of the left thigh had <lb/>increaſed much,
        and covered more than half <lb/>the ſurface of the vaſtus externus muſcle. He <lb/>was
        weaker and worſe in every reſpect. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>14<hi rend="italic">th</hi>: The diſeaſe had ſpread rapidly. The <lb/>gangrenous
        diſpoſition had increaſed in the left <lb/>thigh, and appeared in the right. He was
        <lb/>very low, and delirious; and, at ten o'clock at <lb/>night, he died. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I ſhall forbear to relate to you the various <lb/>remedies, internal and external,
        which I re- <lb/>commended in this extraordinary caſe; be- <lb/>cauſe, as they were
        ineffectual, it would be em- <lb/>ploying your time to no uſeful purpoſe. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
