<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Duncan: History of a Case of Insanity, cured by the use of the Digitalis
          Purpurea</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Dr Duncan</persName>
            </author>
            <title>I. History of a Case of Insanity, cured by the use of the Digitalis Purpurea.
              Communicated to Dr Duncan, in a Letter from Dr Joseph Mason Cox, at Fishponds, near
              Bristol.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries M, DCC, LXXXIX. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest and
              most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and published
              by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Physician to His Royal Highness the
              Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians, Edinburgh,
              and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen, Edinburgh, &amp;c. </title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: Printed for C. Elliot and T. Kay, at Dr Cullen's Head, No 332,
                  opposite Somerset-Place, Strand, London; and for C. Elliot, Edinburgh. </persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1790</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">14</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">261</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108771605</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v14_0261">
    <body>
      <pb n="261"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>I. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Hiſtory of a Caſe of Inſanity, cured by the uſe <lb/>of the Digitalis Purpurea.
        Communicated <lb/>to Dr <hi rend="roman">Duncan</hi>, in a Letter from Dr <hi rend="roman"
          >Joſeph <lb/>Maſon Cox</hi>, at Fiſhponds, near Briſtol. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">D</hi>R WITHERING, in the year 1785, <lb/>having related ſeveral caſes
        in which <lb/>the digitalis purpurea ſucceeded in the cure of <lb/>inſanity, and your
        Commentaries for 1786 <lb/>containing two more of the ſame kind, I was <lb/>induced to try
        it in one that occurred to me <lb/>lately. </p>
      <pb n="262"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Having obſerved, from the reports of ſe- <lb/>veral practitioners who had employed it,
        that <lb/>the foxglove poſſeſſed the peculiar property <lb/>of reducing the pulſe, and of
        occaſioning very <lb/>great nauſea, I had recourſe to it in the caſe <lb/>I am now to
        relate, principally as a debili- <lb/>tating power, hoping by its exhibition to bring
        <lb/>on a remiſſion of a moſt furious maniacal pa- <lb/>roxyſm. I was pleaſingly ſurpriſed
        to find <lb/>that the event far exceeded my moſt ſanguine <lb/>expectations; and that by
        means of this power- <lb/>ful vegetable, I was enabled to reſtore a very <lb/>valuable
        member of ſociety to reaſon, and to <lb/>himſelf. And as the hint was ſuggeſted <lb/>through
        the channel of your excellent annual <lb/>publication, I have taken the liberty of troub-
        <lb/>ling you with the particulars of the cafe, <lb/>hoping that you may think it worth
        commu- <lb/>nicating to the world; as ſome one of more <lb/>abilities may improve upon the
        practice, and <lb/>the reſult may ultimately tend to the benefit <lb/>of mankind. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Though the medical world cannot but ac- <lb/>knowledge their gratitude to the labour
        and <lb/>induſtry of the moſt ſkilful anatomiſts of dif- <lb/>ferent ages, for their
        diſſections and inveſti- <pb n="263"/>
        <lb/>gations of ſubjects who have laboured under <lb/>different ſpecies of inſanity, and for
        the accu- <lb/>rate and minute hiſtories handed down to us; <lb/>yet it muſt be ſincerely
        regreted, that the re- <lb/>ſult has been by no means adequate to the <lb/>labour. Our
        knowledge of the human mind, <lb/>and of the connection between it and the <lb/>body, muſt
        ever be very limited, while we <lb/>know ſo little with reſpect to the deſtination <lb/>and
        offices of the ſeveral parts of ſuch a com- <lb/>plicated ſtructure as the brain. Haller aſ-
        <lb/>ſerts, that in ſome caſes of inſanity no preter- <lb/>natural appearance was obſerved;
        and where <lb/>it was diſcovered, we are ſo far from being <lb/>able to perceive an uniform
        connection be- <lb/>tween any one diſorder of the mind, and a <lb/>morbid appearance of the
        contents of the <lb/>ſcull, that the very fame ſtates are exhibited <lb/>after the moſt
        oppoſite diſorders, as phrenzy <lb/>and idiotiſm. But although, as Dr Arnold <lb/>juſtly
        obſerves, much uncertainty will ever <lb/>attend our reſearches into the ſeveral ſpecific
        <lb/>ſtates of the brain reſpectively productive of <lb/>the ſeveral ſorts of inſanity, yet,
        where we can <lb/>ſuſpect the cauſe, though we may be ignorant <lb/>of its mode of action in
        producing the diſeaſe <pb n="264"/>
        <lb/>we are authoriſed, on the moſt rational prin- <lb/>ciples, to place the greateſt hopes
        of ſucceſs <lb/>in the adminiſtration of thoſe remedies which <lb/>are particularly adapted
        to obviate its effects. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It is upon a principle of this kind, that we <lb/>may perhaps account for the influence
        of the <lb/>digitalis in effecting the ſeveral cures imputed <lb/>to it, as well as that I
        am about to relate. <lb/>Since a ſuperabundance of aqueous or ſerous <lb/>fluid,
        extravaſated in the different parts of the <lb/>brain, as in the ventricles, between the
        dura <lb/>and pia mater, &amp;c. have been ſuſpected to be <lb/>the cauſes of inſanity in
        many inſtances; <lb/>ſince we ſee the effects of water in the brain, <lb/>in caſes of
        hydrocephalus; and ſince we know <lb/>that the foxglove has a particular power of
        <lb/>evacuating extravaſated fluids, we may from <lb/>thence be led to explain its efficacy
        in thoſe <lb/>caſes, and in that which I am now to relate. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr P. M., aged 40, rather of a corpulent <lb/>habit of body, naturally of a gay and
        cheerful <lb/>diſpoſition, had for ſeveral years enjoyed an <lb/>uninterrupted continuance
        of health, except- <lb/>ing an occaſional pain in the head, which he <lb/>termed a pulſing
        pain, which however con- <pb n="265"/>
        <lb/>tinued only for a few hours, and left him in <lb/>perfect health. Having by
        indefatigable in- <lb/>duſtry in an active line of buſineſs accumu- <lb/>lated an
        independency, he was induced to re- <lb/>tire, to enjoy the fruits of his labours in eaſe
        <lb/>and affluence. But forgetting that the means <lb/>by which he had amaſſed his fortune,
        were <lb/>the ſource from whence he derived health and <lb/>ſpirits, he quickly became
        liſtleſs and inactive, <lb/>was dejected, peeviſh, and whimſical, and at <lb/>length his
        ideas were confuſed, and his judg- <lb/>ment deluded. He complained of no bodily <lb/>pain,
        excepting his uſual headach, and a ſtiff- <lb/>neſs of his lower extremities, which in the
        <lb/>evening appeared rather ſwoln and anaſarcous. <lb/>He was habitually coſtive, and often
        paſſed <lb/>ſeveral days without a ſtool. His urine was <lb/>diminiſhed in quantity, and at
        the ſame time <lb/>limpid and thin, depoſiting no ſediment. He <lb/>was very ſubject to acid
        eructations and bor- <lb/>borygmi; his appetite was impaired, his thirſt <lb/>increaſed, he
        ſtept but little. His ſleep was <lb/>without refreſhment, and accompanied with
        <lb/>terrifying dreams. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Theſe were his principal original ſymptoms; <lb/>and they gradually increaſed, although
        the <pb n="266"/>
        <lb/>beſt medical aſſiſtance was procured with <lb/>a view to their removal. At length, from
        <lb/>a ſettled melancholy he became moſt furi- <lb/>ouſly maniacal; and it was judged proper
        to <lb/>remove him to ſome place of confinement. <lb/>He was accordingly committed to my
        care, on <lb/>the 22d of June laſt: But, previous to that, <lb/>he had undergone pretty
        ſevere medical diſ- <lb/>cipline. He had been bliſtered on the head, <lb/>the back, and the
        calfs of the legs; he had <lb/>been repeatedly blooded, purged, and vomit- <lb/>ed, and had
        taken draughts, with gum-ammo- <lb/>niac, ſagapenum, tinctura melampodii, ſteel, &amp;c. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>1 found him very much emaciated, his pulſe <lb/>feeble,and beating to eighty and
        upwards in the <lb/>minute; his countenance ſallow, the eyes red, <lb/>ſunk, and looking
        fierce and ſtaring. He had not <lb/>had a ſtool for a week; and the urine continued <lb/>in
        ſmall quantity, and pale, notwithſtanding <lb/>his debilitated ſtate. His ravings and exer-
        <lb/>tions required conſtant confinement and at- <lb/>tendance. Although in general he
        talked in <lb/>the moſt incoherent manner, running from <lb/>one ſubject to another without
        the leaſt order <lb/>or connection, yet he would reaſon on ſome <lb/>topics with the utmoſt
        acuteneſs for a certain <pb n="267"/>
        <lb/>time, but quickly relapſe again into his former <lb/>ravings. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I began my curative attempts by admini- <lb/>ſtering a laxative emollient clyſter: but
        this <lb/>not ſucceeding, I had recourſe to one more <lb/>ſtimulating, which brought off
        ſeveral pounds <lb/>of very fœtid fœces. Thinking, from his pre- <lb/>ſent debilitated and
        emaciated ſtate, that the <lb/>antiphlogiſtic plan had been too rigidly ad- <lb/>hered to, I
        imagined it would be moſt pru- <lb/>dent to ſuſpend the uſe of medicines for a <lb/>few
        days. But the ſymptoms ſuffered no kind <lb/>of remiſſion: he paſſed day after day in
        curſing <lb/>and raving, and night after night without <lb/>ſleep. I then ordered an emetic
        ſolution to <lb/>be prepared, with twelve grains of emetic <lb/>tartar, one grain to be
        exhibited every half <lb/>hour till it operated. But no obvious effect <lb/>was produced,
        till ten grains were taken, when <lb/>full vomiting took place. This brought off <lb/>much
        viſcid phlegm, and bile; but no remiſ- <lb/>ſion of ſymptoms was produced, nor was there
        <lb/>the leaſt languor after the exertion attending <lb/>the operation of the emetic. His
        pulſe con- <lb/>tinued about eighty, though feeble. As he <lb/>had not enjoyed an hour's
        ſleep during the <pb n="268"/>
        <lb/>whole time he had been under my care, I had <lb/>recourſe to repeated doſes of opium,
        under <lb/>the form of paregoric elixir in camphorated <lb/>julep, with the pediluvium
        continued for an <lb/>hour each night, and a laxative draught every <lb/>morning. Having
        continued this for a week <lb/>without the leaſt obvious effect, I almoſt de- <lb/>ſpaired
        of relieving him, from his ſyſtem <lb/>being ſo exceedingly inſenſible to the action <lb/>of
        medicines; which however is no uncom- <lb/>mon caſe with maniacs. But obſerving the
        <lb/>diminiſhed quantity of urine, and a degree of <lb/>tenſion in the left hypochondrium, I
        began to <lb/>ſuſpect a ſerous effuſion, and accordingly had <lb/>recourſe to the common
        diuretics, cream of <lb/>tartar, elaterium, ſquills, mercury, &amp;c.; but <lb/>all of theſe
        failed in producing the deſired ef- <lb/>fect. The latter, indeed, run off by the bow-
        <lb/>els, till corrected by opium, which I exhibited <lb/>once to the amount of two drams in
        ſix hours, <lb/>but without the leaſt ſedative effect. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>At this time, viewing the caſe as a very <lb/>helpleſs one, the idea occurred to me of
        try- <lb/>ing the digitalis, which is repreſented as pro- <lb/>ducing ſuch remarkable
        effects in diminiſhing <lb/>the pulſe. I accordingly prepared a decoction, <pb n="269"/>
        <lb/>by boiling an ounce of the dried leaves of the <lb/>digitalis in a pound and a half of
        water, till it <lb/>was reduced to a pound, and directed three <lb/>ſpoonfuls to be taken
        every third hour. It <lb/>produced no ſeeming effect, till after the third <lb/>doſe. An
        evident nauſea was then produced, <lb/>ſucceeded by full vomiting of viſcid phlegm, <lb/>and
        green crude bile. The flow of urine was <lb/>increaſed, and the pulſe reduced nearly to the
        <lb/>natural ſtandard. The nauſea continued at <lb/>times the two following days, though no
        more <lb/>of the decoction was given. But I was again <lb/>tempted to repeat the doſe, from
        ſo favour- <lb/>able a beginning. The effect was nearly the <lb/>ſame as before, excepting
        that the flow of <lb/>urine was diminiſhed, and ſeveral looſe ſtools <lb/>were produced. I
        therefore ordered another <lb/>doſe of opium, which was ſucceeded by ſive <lb/>hours ſleep,
        the firſt that had been procured <lb/>during the laſt fortnight. I found my patient <lb/>in
        the morning much more compoſed, though <lb/>he complained much of nauſea: he was evi-
        <lb/>dently, upon the whole, much better. I <lb/>therefore omitted the medicine wholly for
        <lb/>three days: but on the fourth all the former <lb/>ſymptoms returning, I had again
        recourſe to <pb n="270"/>
        <lb/>the decoction. It now produced no nauſea, <lb/>but the flow of urine was much
        increaſed. I <lb/>therefore continued ſmall doſes of the decoc- <lb/>tion, with an opiate at
        night, during nine <lb/>days. At the end of that time, my patient <lb/>ſeemed much better,
        both in body and mind. <lb/>He ſpoke with propriety on a variety of ſub- <lb/>jects, and on
        his late complaints with philoſo- <lb/>phic coolneſs, though he complained that he <lb/>had
        but an imperfect recollection of them. <lb/>His appetite mended, and the various functions
        <lb/>became natural. I then left off the medicine <lb/>gradually, each day adding to his
        ſtrength, ap- <lb/>pearance, and recovery. He is now perfectly <lb/>reſtored, and has
        continued for the laſt ſix <lb/>weeks as well as ever he was in his life, with- <lb/>out
        having had any return of his uſual head- <lb/>ach. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
