<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: Dissertatio Medica de Myristica</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>IV. Dissertatio Medica de Myristica. Auctore Frederico Vilhelm Radloff, Præſide
              Car. Pet. Thunberg. 4to, Upſaliæ.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries M, DCC, XC. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest and most
              important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and published by
              Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Physician to His Royal Highness the Prince
              of Wales for Scotland, President of the Royal College of Physicians, Edinburgh, and
              Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen, Edinburgh, &amp;c. And
              Professor of the Institutions of Medicine in the University of Edinburgh.</title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: Printed for Peter Hill, at the Cross; and G. G. J. &amp; J.
                  Robinson, London</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1791</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">15</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">54-62</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108772152</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v15_0054">
    <body>
      <pb n="54"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>IV. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Diſſertatio Medica de Myriſtica. Auctore <hi rend="roman">Fre- <lb/>derico Vilhelm
          Radloff</hi>, Præſide Car. Pet. <lb/>Thunberg. <hi rend="roman">4to, Upſaliæ</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HIS diſſertation, as well as that which <lb/>we have juſt
        conſidered, treats alſo of <lb/>an article which is in very common uſe. And <lb/>the author
        introduces it, by giving the follow- <lb/>ing accurate deſcription of the tree which pro-
        <lb/>duces the genuine nutmeg. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Myristica moschata</hi>: foliis lanceolatis, <lb/>fructu glabro. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Arbor</hi>, magnitudine pyri vel ultra, cortice <lb/>lævi fuſco-cinereo. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Rami</hi>, patentes, ultimi capillares glabri. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Folia</hi>, lanceolata, acuminata, integra, al- <lb/>terna, parum
        nervoſa, glabra, ſupra viridia, ſub- <lb/>tus pallida, digitalia. </p>
      <pb n="55"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Flores</hi>, in ultimis ramulis pedunculati, <lb/>ſparſi, ſolitarii,
        monoici. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Calyx</hi>. Perianthium uniphyllum, trifi- <lb/>dum glabrum. Laciniæ
        ovatæ, erectæ, breves. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Corolla</hi>, nulla. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Stamina</hi>. Filamentum unicum, ſiliforme <lb/>calyce brevius. Anthera
        ſub apice filamenti, <lb/>perforata, ſtriata. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Pistillum</hi>. Germen ſuperum. Stylus <lb/>craſſus, didymus, brevis.
        Stigmata duo, acuta, <lb/>brevia. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Pericarpium</hi>. Drupa ovata, umbilicata, <lb/>glabra, unilocularis,
        lateraliter dehiſcens, in <lb/>pedunculis reflexis pendula. Caro pallide vi- <lb/>reſcens,
        tandem pallida, aſtringens. Nux maci <lb/>reticulata, aurantiaca, cincta rugoſa. Nucleus
        <lb/>rugoſus. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Beſides this ſpecies of the Myriſtica, from <lb/>which the genuine nutmeg is produced,
        ano- <lb/>ther ſpecies is, he tells us, alſo very common <lb/>in India, and ſometimes uſed
        there, which he <lb/>deſcribes under the title of the Myriſtica to- <lb/>mentoſa, and in the
        following terms. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Myristica tomentosa</hi>: foliis ovatis, <lb/>ſructu tomentoſo. </p>
      <pb n="56"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Arbor</hi>, minus, ampla et ramoſa; ramis ra- <lb/>muliſque magis
        craſſis. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Folia</hi>, lato-oblonga, obtuſiuſcula, craſſa, <lb/>nervoſa, ſupra
        viridia, ſubtus pallida, parum <lb/>tomentoſa, palmaria uſque pedalia. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Flores</hi> ad baſin ramulorum, pedunculati, <lb/>ſolitarii, pedunculis
        brevibus, craſſis, tomen- <lb/>toſis. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Fructus</hi>, drupa oblonga, obtuſiſſima, ſub- <lb/>tomentoſa. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/>Beſides theſe two ſpecies, Dr Radloff ob- <lb/>ſerves, that Rumphius has deſcribed and
        deli- <lb/>neated ſome other trees nearly reſembling <lb/>them. But as their parts of
        fructification are <lb/>ſtill undetermined, it cannot be poſitively <lb/>known whether they
        belong to this genus or <lb/>not. Among the Indians, the Myriſtica moſ- <lb/>chata has the
        name of Pala, and the Myriſtica <lb/>tomentoſa, of Pala Lacki; although, in dif- <lb/>ferent
        iſlands, they have different denomina- <lb/>tions. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Myriſtica grows ſpontaneouſly in the <lb/>Molucca iſlands; but it is chiefly
        cultivated in <lb/>Banda, and in three ſmall neighbouring iſlands, <lb/>Neijra, Lontoir, and
        Pulo Aij. From Neijra <pb n="57"/>
        <lb/>it is alleged that the beſt nutmegs are <lb/>brought; but in Pulo Aij are the largeſt
        and <lb/>moſt beautiful trees. In all the other Moluc- <lb/>ca iſlands, the Dutch have now
        deſtroyed and <lb/>rooted up the trees bearing nutmeg. Dr <lb/>Radloff, however, tells us,
        that the induſtrious <lb/>M. Sonnerat found the Myriſtica growing in <lb/>New Guinea. The
        culture of the nutmeg has <lb/>not ſucceeded in the French African iſlands; <lb/>but it is
        found to grow luxuriantly in their <lb/>American ſettlement of Cayenne. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This valuable tree delights in mountainous <lb/>ſituations, but requires, in ſome
        degree, the <lb/>ſhade of other trees, that it may not be ſcorch- <lb/>ed by the heat of the
        ſun. They require <lb/>likewiſe to be defended againſt ſea-winds <lb/>with ſaline
        impregnations. When the trees <lb/>are five or ſix years old, they begin to bear <lb/>fruit;
        but they produce the moſt abundant <lb/>crop in their eighth or ninth year. They <lb/>are
        ſpontaneouſly propagated by the pigeons, <lb/>who ſwallow the whole fruit, but digeſt only
        <lb/>the mace and pulpy part, and diſcharge the <lb/>nut. The Dutch, however, ſow the whole
        <lb/>fruit, and tranſplant the young trees at plea- <lb/>ſure. But the whole care of
        cultivating and <pb n="58"/>
        <lb/>collecting the fruit, is carried on by their <lb/>ſlaves. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Myriſtica may be conſidered as pro- <lb/>ducing fruit through the whole year, as it
        <lb/>flowers and ripens its fruit in a ſort of grada- <lb/>tion; but the ripe nuts are
        chiefly collected at <lb/>three different periods of the year. The <lb/>greateſt crop is
        collected about the end of <lb/>July or Auguſt. At that time, however, the <lb/>mace is
        thin. A ſecond crop is obtained in <lb/>November, and a third in March and April. <lb/>At
        this laſt period the thickeſt mace is ob- <lb/>tained. The ſign of ripeneſs, is, the
        exterior <lb/>covering obtaining a light red colour. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The fruit, when collected, is cut up with <lb/>knives, and the external fleſhy part
        left to pu- <lb/>trefy in the woods. The nuts, thus far clear- <lb/>ed, are brought home,
        and the mace removed <lb/>from them by the aid of a knife. It is expoſ- <lb/>ed to the ſun
        to be dried; during which pro- <lb/>ceſs it acquires a yellowiſh colour. The nut- <lb/>megs
        alſo are expoſed to the ſun for three or <lb/>four days, but are taken into a houſe every
        <lb/>night, leſt they ſhould be hurt by the dews. <lb/>The nuts thus dried, are divided into
        three <lb/>parcels. The firſt, being the largeſt and beſt, <pb n="59"/>
        <lb/>are intended for the European market; a ſe- <lb/>cond ſort is uſed in India; and the
        third kind <lb/>is, in general, only employed for making oil. <lb/>Before the nutmegs be
        exported, they are in <lb/>general infuſed for eight days in lime-water, by <lb/>which it is
        thought they are defended from <lb/>putrefaction and from inſects. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The mace, after being well dried, is put <lb/>into bags, each containing about one
        hundred <lb/>and ſixty pounds. It is, however, in the firſt <lb/>place, ſprinkled with
        ſea-water, leſt it ſhould <lb/>become too brittle, and break into ſmall frag- <lb/>ments. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From the nutmegs in India, two kinds of <lb/>oil are prepared; an expreſſed, and a
        diſtilled <lb/>oil. Of theſe, the diſtilled oil is rarely <lb/>brought to Europe. It is of a
        pellucid ap- <lb/>pearance, and poſſeſſes the full aromatic qua- <lb/>lity of the nut. The
        expreſſed oil is obtain- <lb/>ed from an inferior ſort of nuts. The nuts, <lb/>roaſted and
        bruiſed, are ſubjected to preſſure, <lb/>till a thick oil, nearly of the conſiſtence of
        <lb/>melted butter, is obtained from them; and it <lb/>becomes ſtill thicker after being
        kept for ſome <lb/>time in the ſquare veſſels into which it is re- <lb/>ceived from the
        preſs. </p>
      <pb n="60"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From the mace, when bruiſed and heated, <lb/>an oil is alſo obtained, of a rediſh
        colour, and <lb/>a fatty and bitteriſh taſte, but without excit- <lb/>ing any great ſenſe of
        heat in the mouth. <lb/>From about ſeventeen pounds of mace, half a <lb/>pound of this oil
        is obtained. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The Dutch in India ſometimes preſerve, un- <lb/>der the form of a condiment, with
        ſugar, the <lb/>fruit taken from the tree before it be ripe. <lb/>For this purpoſe, after
        being picked from the <lb/>tree, they are boiled in water, then pierced <lb/>with a needle,
        and afterwards macerated for <lb/>eight or ten days in freſh water frequently <lb/>changed,
        till the whole bitterneſs be removed <lb/>from them. After this, they are put into a
        <lb/>ſolution of ſugar, which, for eight days, is to <lb/>be every day poured off from the
        nuts, heat- <lb/>ed, and then again added to them. They are <lb/>then boiled in this ſyrup,
        and afterwards pre- <lb/>ſerved in glaſs veſſels properly ſhut. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When it is conſidered that the Myriſtica is a <lb/>tree yielding a bloody juice, and
        highly aroma- <lb/>tic, it is not wonderful that it is not entirely <lb/>free from all
        ſuſpicion of a poiſonous quality, <lb/>although, when prudently exhibited, it is uſe-
        <lb/>fully employed both for dietetical and medi- <pb n="61"/>
        <lb/>cal purpoſes. It has however been demon- <lb/>ſtrated, by ſome melancholy examples,
        that <lb/>the halitus, both of the tree and of the fruit, <lb/>have not only been hurtful to
        thoſe impru- <lb/>dently expoſed to them, but have even indu- <lb/>ced death. Several
        examples are mentioned <lb/>by Rumphius, of fatal effects, not only from <lb/>eating the
        nuts, but alſo from ſleeping under <lb/>the tree. From too large a doſe of theſe nuts,
        <lb/>there is induced oppreſſion at the breaſt, diffi- <lb/>cult reſpiration, intenſe
        thirſt, headach, ver- <lb/>tigo, and fatal apoplexy. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>With regard to the medical uſe of nutmegs, <lb/>Dr Radloff obſerves, that they were
        intro- <lb/>duced by the Arabian phyſicians, and are firſt <lb/>mentioned by Avicenna. They
        have been <lb/>long conſidered as uſeful for promoting dige- <lb/>ſtion in weak ſtomachs;
        and, when prudently <lb/>uſed, are often productive of advantage both <lb/>in bloody and
        ſerous diſcharges. In caſes of <lb/>diarrhœa and dyſenteria, toaſted nutmeg, with <lb/>red
        wine, or any ſimilar vehicle, is often uſed <lb/>with advantage. They have alſo been found
        <lb/>uſeful againſt nauſea, vomiting, and cough, <lb/>particularly with pregnant women. </p>
      <pb n="62"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From the external uſe of the nutmeg, or of <lb/>its oil, the ſame danger is not to be
        appre- <lb/>hended as from their internal uſe. In India, <lb/>the expreſſed oil is often
        employed with ad- <lb/>vantage, under the form of friction, to para- <lb/>lytic limbs: and
        in Europe, it is often applied <lb/>to the umbilical region, to allay violent gripes,
        <lb/>or evacuations of the primæ viæ; and, when <lb/>rubbed upon the temples, it has been
        ſaid to <lb/>excite ſleep. The eſſential oil, as well as a <lb/>tincture from the nutmeg, is
        often ſerviceable <lb/>in weakneſs of the ſtomach; and nutmegs, pre- <lb/>ſerved with ſugar,
        are alſo uſed with the ſame <lb/>intention. The wood of the tree is not un- <lb/>frequently,
        in India, employed in houſe-build- <lb/>ing, and for other œconomical purpoſes. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The fruit of the Myriſtica tomentoſa, alſo, <lb/>although of an inferior quality, is
        often, our <lb/>author obſerves, employed for the ſame pur- <lb/>poſes as the genuine
        nutmeg. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
