<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Davidson: History of a singular Case, of an intermittent affecting the
          right Temple</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Samuel Davidson</persName>
            </author>
            <title>IX. History of a singular Case, of an intermittent affecting the right Temple;
              and of a remarkable Tumour in the Abdomen, successfully treated. By Mr Samuel
              Davidson, Surgeon at Rothbury, in Northumberland.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries M, DCC, XC. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest and most
              important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and published by
              Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Physician to His Royal Highness the Prince
              of Wales for Scotland, President of the Royal College of Physicians, Edinburgh, and
              Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen, Edinburgh, &amp;c. And
              Professor of the Institutions of Medicine in the University of Edinburgh.</title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: Printed for Peter Hill, at the Cross; and G. G. J. &amp; J.
                  Robinson, London</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1791</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">15</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">391-398</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108772152</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v15_0391">
    <body>
      <pb n="391"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>IX. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Hiſtory of a ſingular Caſe, of an intermittent <lb/>affecting the right Temple; and of
        a re- <lb/>markable Tumour in the Abdomen, ſucceſsfully <lb/>treated. By Mr <hi rend="roman"
          >Samuel Davidſon</hi>, Surgeon <lb/>at Rothbury, in Northumberland. </head>
      <div>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">W</hi>ILLIAM B—, labourer, aged <lb/>forty-one, applied to me for
          advice, <lb/>on the 9th of January 1789. Fourteen days <lb/>before, he received a ſtroke
          on the right eye <lb/>with a piece of wood, of which he ſoon re- <lb/>covered. About a
          week ago, he was ſeized <lb/>with a ſhivering paroxyſm, which continued <lb/>for two
          hours, and was ſucceeded by a ſevere <lb/>pain in the right eye and temple, which goes
          <lb/>off by a ſweat in the ſpace of two hours. The <lb/>cold fit, and pain, attack
          periodically, about <lb/>nine o'clock, and the paroxyſm continues till <lb/>twelve
          o'clock. When the pain comes on, he <lb/>is deprived of the ſight of that eye; and for <pb
            n="392"/>
          <lb/>the remainder of the twenty-four hours, he is <lb/>free from every complaint. His eye
          is much <lb/>inflamed ; and he is coſtive. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I ordered an emetic to be taken before the <lb/>attack of the next paroxyſm; which
          however <lb/>did not mitigate it. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>Applic. hirud. No. IV. temp. dextr. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>Capt. ſal. Glaub. unc. ſs. ſtatim ex aq. <lb/>fervente. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>Applic. Veſicat. pone dextr. aur. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>℞ Tart. Emet. gr. ¼. Aq. bullient. unc. i. <lb/>Tinct. Opii gtt. xxv. M. Capt. mane
          <lb/>aggred. paroxyſm. feb. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>12<hi rend="italic">th</hi>. The pain continued yeſterday in the <lb/>eye, till
          night. Had five ſtools. The paro- <lb/>xyſm began at eleven o'clock, A. M. this day.
          <lb/>He took the draught, which, he thinks, miti- <lb/>gates the paroxyſm. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>Capt. Pulv. Cort. Peruv. drach. i. <lb/>2da quaque hora. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>13<hi rend="italic">th</hi>. The paroxyſm continued with great <lb/>ſeverity till
          twelve o'clock at night. Had a <lb/>return of the fit at eleven o'clock this fore-
          <lb/>noon. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>Cont. Pulv. Cort. et adde ſingul. dos. <lb/>Pulv. Rhei gr. iij. </p>
        <pb n="393"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>14<hi rend="italic">th</hi>. The fit of ſhorter duration yeſterday. <lb/>The pain in
          the eye came on as uſual; and is <lb/>worſe this day, and much inflamed. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>Rep. Pulv. Cort. Peruv. ſine Rheo. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>Capt. Bol. cum Calomel. gr. v. h. s. ad <lb/>duas vices. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>16<hi rend="italic">th</hi>. The diſeaſe has yielded nothing to <lb/>the courſe he
          has been following. </p>
        <p rend="indentall">
          <lb/>Applic. Veſicat. Cap. </p>
        <p rend="indentall">
          <lb/>Cap. Pulv. Dov. ſcr. i. aggred. paroxyſm. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>18<hi rend="italic">th</hi>. Sweated much yeſterday with the <lb/>powder, which
          prevented the paroxyſm. This <lb/>day the pain is as ſevere as ever. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>Rep. Bol. cum Calomel. gr. v. h. s. et <lb/>Pulv.-Dover. mane. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>Rep. medicament. ad duas vices. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>Applic. hirud. iij. juxta part. affect. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>19<hi rend="italic">th</hi>. Coſtive for four days. The chilly fit <lb/>began, and
          did not take the powder. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>℞ Pil. Aloet. drach. ſs. Calomel, ppt. gr. xx. '' M. f. Pil. vi. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>Cap. ij. h. s. omn. noct. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>Mitt. ſanguin. ex arter. temporal. ad <lb/>unc. vi. </p>
        <pb n="394"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>20<hi rend="italic">th</hi>. Leeches were tried, but did not fix. <lb/>The powder
          prevented the pain. </p>
        <p rend="indentall">
          <lb/>Perg. cum Pulv. Dover. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>21<hi rend="italic">ſt</hi>. Has a fit this day. </p>
        <p rend="indentall">
          <lb/>Rep. Pulv. Dover. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>23<hi rend="italic">d</hi>. The paroxyſm came on yeſterday, <lb/>having neglected the
          powder; and it conti- <lb/>nued with great ſeverity the whole day. His <lb/>mouth is
          nowiſe affected by the Calomel. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>℞ Aq. Minth. pip.—Puræ <hi rend="italic">aa</hi>. unc. viii. <lb/>Pulv. Cort. Peruv.
          unc. ii. <lb/>Sal. C. C. drach. i. M. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>Capt. unc. i. 2da quaq. hor. paroxyſm. <lb/>abſente. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>25<hi rend="italic">th</hi>. The pain returned yeſterday as ſe- <lb/>vere as ever.
          The fit not ſo ſevere. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>℞ Pulv. Ipec. ſcru. i. Tart. emet. gr. i. <lb/>M. f. Pulv. emet. ſtatim ſumend. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>Repet. Miſtur. cum Cort. Peruv. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>27<hi rend="italic">th</hi>. The pain ſtill returns once a day, <lb/>though not with
          ſuch ſeverity as formerly. </p>
        <p rend="indentall">
          <lb/>Rep. Bol. h. ſ. </p>
        <p rend="indentall">
          <lb/>Rep. Miſt. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">February</hi>8<hi rend="italic">th</hi>. The pain did not recur for
          <lb/>three days; but has returned again, ſlightly. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>Applic. Veſicat. tempor. affect. et po- <lb/>ſtea fiat, Fonticul. ope ungt. Epi-
          <lb/>ſpaſt. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>Intermitt. Miſtur. Peruv. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>14<hi rend="italic">th</hi>. The pain ſtill returns ſlightly, at <lb/>times. The eye
          a little inflamed. The iſſue <lb/>is healed up; but he found no benefit from it. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>Mitt. Sang. ad unc. x. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>Sumat. Calomel. ppt. gr. v. h. ſ. in <lb/>form. bol. </p>
        <p rend="indentall hanging">
          <lb/>℞ Infuſ. Senn. unc. iiſs. Tart. Solub. <lb/>drach. i. M. capt. mane. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>20<hi rend="italic">th</hi>. The pain and inflammation are now <lb/>quite gone, and
          the paroxyſm removed en- <lb/>tirely. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I attribute the cure of this caſe to the Bark <lb/>and Calomel. </p>
      </div>
      <figure rend="space">
        <figDesc>A short horizontal line in the middle of the page. </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <div>
        <head rend="sc align-center space">
          <lb/>Case II. </head>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Mrs D—, aged twenty-ſix, a widow-lady, <lb/>the mother of two children, was affected
          with a <lb/>ſwelling under the left ear, which began firſt <lb/>to appear about the month
          of May 1788, and <pb n="396"/>
          <lb/>gradually increaſed in ſize till the month of <lb/>November 1789. It had every
          appearance of <lb/>a ſcrophulous tumour, and was about the bulk <lb/>of a gooſe egg; but
          did not come to ſuppura- <lb/>tion. Notwithſtanding the increaſe of this <lb/>tumour, ſhe
          enjoyed pretty good health and <lb/>ſpirits. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I was called to her on the 16th of November <lb/>1789; when I found her complaining
          of great <lb/>pain in the right ſide of the abdomen, attend- <lb/>ed with nauſea,
          vomiting, and thirſt. Her <lb/>pulſe was ſmall, and beat one hundred and <lb/>thirty
          ſtrokes in a minute. She was alſo co- <lb/>ſtive, and had been ſo for two days. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On farther inquiry, ſhe informed me of a <lb/>tumour ſhe had felt for four months
          paſt, ſitu- <lb/>ated about an equal diſtance between the um- <lb/>bilicus and the ſpine
          of the os innominatum <lb/>on the right ſide. This tumour, which was <lb/>at firſt very
          ſmall, continued increaſing till the <lb/>time I was ſent for, without much pain or un-
          <lb/>eaſineſs, except at times; but which were never <lb/>very ſevere, and always of very
          ſhort duration. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>On examining the tumour, it felt deep- <lb/>ſeated, hard, moveable, and of ſize
          ſufficient to <lb/>fill the whole length of the hand, with a gra- <pb n="397"/>
          <lb/>dual decreaſe of its bulk, towards the os inno- <lb/>minatum and umbilicus. The pain
          in the tu- <lb/>mour, during this attack, was ſo excruciating <lb/>and exquiſite, that ſhe
          could not ſuffer the <lb/>weight of the bed-clothes on the part. Her <lb/>catamenia had
          been always regular; except <lb/>that, for a few months paſt, they had ap- <lb/>peared in
          ſomewhat leſs quantity. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Ten ounces of blood were taken from her <lb/>directly; but the blood had no buffy
          coat. I <lb/>next ordered her repeated doſes of aloetic pills, <lb/>with opium and
          laxative glyſters, to remove <lb/>the coſtiveneſs; and alſo a ſaline julep, to a-
          <lb/>bate the vomiting. Leeches were applied to <lb/>the tumour; and afterwards it was
          rubbed with <lb/>a liniment of camphor and vitriolic æther. In <lb/>the courſe of four
          days, the nauſea and vomit- <lb/>ing, and the pain, gradually diminiſhed, by
          <lb/>obſerving a ſtrict adherence to theſe medi- <lb/>cines; but there was no decreaſe of
          ſize in <lb/>the tumour. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>After the ſymptoms were abated, I ordered <lb/>her gentle exerciſe, the cold bath,
          and put <lb/>her under a courſe of cicuta, conjoined with <lb/>the Peruvian bark. By
          perſiſting in the uſe <lb/>of theſe medicines for three months, the tu- <pb n="398"/>
          <lb/>mour gradually decreaſed; and, at the time <lb/>of writing this account of her cafe,
          ſhe enjoys <lb/>good health and ſpirits, without any return of <lb/>the tumour. It is
          proper to obſerve, that the <lb/>tumour under her ear always remained, and is <lb/>ſtill
          the ſame, without coming to ſuppura- <lb/>tion. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
