<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: Reflexions sur les effets de l'éther vitriolique</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>XI. Reflexions sur les effets de l'éther vitriolique, et de l'éther nitreux, dans
              l'économie animale. Par M. de Lavoisier. Vide Histoire de la Société Royale de
              Médecine, tome IV. 4to, Paris. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries M, DCC, XC. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest and most
              important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and published by
              Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Physician to His Royal Highness the Prince
              of Wales for Scotland, President of the Royal College of Physicians, Edinburgh, and
              Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen, Edinburgh, &amp;c. And
              Professor of the Institutions of Medicine in the University of Edinburgh.</title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: Printed for Peter Hill, at the Cross; and G. G. J. &amp; J.
                  Robinson, London</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1791</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">15</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">150-156</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108772152</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v15_0150">
    <body>
      <pb n="150"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>XI. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Reflexions ſur les effets de l'éther vitriolique, <lb/>et de l'éther nitreux, dans
        l'économie ani- <lb/>male. Par <hi rend="roman">M. de Lavoiſier. Vide</hi>Hiſtoire <lb/>de
        la Société Royale de Médecine, tome IV. <lb/><hi rend="roman">4to, Paris.</hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi>T is, Mr Lavoiſier obſerves, a known fact, <lb/>that all fluids,
        and probably volatile bodies <lb/>in general, by means of certain degrees of <lb/>heat, paſs
        from the ſtate of liquid to that of <lb/>elaſticity; and are transformed into elaſtic
        <lb/>aeriform fluids, with all the phyſical pro- <lb/>perties of air, but without its
        chemical pro- <lb/>perties. This change happens from a de- <lb/>termined degree of heat
        applied to each. <lb/>Thus it happens to vitriolic æther at thirty- <lb/>two degrees of
        Reaumur's thermometer; to <lb/>ſpirit of wine at ſixty-ſix degrees; and to water <lb/>at
        eighty. </p>
      <pb n="151"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By means of a pneumato-chemical appara- <lb/>tus, Mr Lavoiſier transformed a portion of
        vi- <lb/>triolic æther into an inflammable air, with <lb/>which he filled ſeveral glaſs
        veſſels. The æ- <lb/>ther thus converted into a vapour, was found <lb/>to poſſeſs all the
        principal properties of the <lb/>inflammable air of marſhes, or of that which <lb/>is
        obtained from metals on their diſſolution <lb/>by acids. Like theſe, it is neither
        inflammable <lb/>nor combuſtible, as long as it remains alone, <lb/>and is contained in a
        cloſe veſſel. It burns <lb/>only when in contact with atmoſpheric air. <lb/>If, with this
        air, two parts of atmoſpheric air <lb/>be combined, a permanently elaſtic fluid is
        <lb/>formed, which is not condenſed by cold, but <lb/>which has the property of detonation
        when <lb/>it approaches an inflamed body. This per- <lb/>manence is the ſame, when, in place
        of atmo- <lb/>ſpheric air, dephlogiſticated air is employed, <lb/>in the proportion of one
        part to two of the <lb/>inflammable air of æther; but the detonation <lb/>is much ſtronger. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Nitrous æther, he obſerves, preſents all the <lb/>ſame phænomena with an inferior
        degree of <lb/>the thermometer. But, as it is difficult to <lb/>procure nitrous æther always
        exactly the ſame, <pb n="152"/>
        <lb/>the degree of heat is variable, according to <lb/>variations in the æther employed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Without entering into a detail of many o- <lb/>ther curious experiments made with æther
        <lb/>converted into inflammable air, the author <lb/>next proceeds to enquire, how thoſe
        already <lb/>related throw light upon the manner in which <lb/>æther acts in the animal
        œconomy. Since it <lb/>is found that this ſubſtance is volatilized at a <lb/>degree of heat
        lower than that of the internal <lb/>parts of the body, it follows, he obſerves, <lb/>that,
        when introduced into the ſtomach, it <lb/>muſt paſs from the ſtate of liquid to that of
        <lb/>gas, and be transformed into an inflammable <lb/>air. Beſides this, as it is difficult
        to conceive <lb/>that the ſtomach will not poſſeſs ſome portion <lb/>of atmoſpheric air,
        there muſt reſult from this <lb/>mixture, a permanently elaſtic fluid, which <lb/>cannot be
        more condenſed by a degree of heat <lb/>even much below thirty-two of Reaumur. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>By this means, in caſes where the ſtomach, <lb/>either from the fermentation of thoſe
        fluids <lb/>deſtined for digeſtion, or from the uſe of fer- <lb/>menting drinks, is filled
        with elaſtic, gaſſeous, <lb/>or mephitic fluids, ſuch as fixed air, or any <lb/>other, he
        conſiders the vitriolic æther, but <pb n="153"/>
        <lb/>ſtill more the nitrous, as a certain means <lb/>of expelling them. It is, he thinks,
        unqueſ- <lb/>tionably on this account, that æther is an effi- <lb/>cacious remedy in ſome
        ſpecies of megrim, <lb/>particularly in thoſe headachs which ariſe from <lb/>bad digeſtion.
        It will, he imagines, alſo produce <lb/>ſimilar effects in caſes of drunkenneſs, and in
        <lb/>all thoſe caſes in general, where the fermen- <lb/>tation of fluids, either in the
        ſtomach, or in o- <lb/>ther neighbouring parts of the inteſtinal ca- <lb/>nal, has filled
        thoſe viſcera with mephitic ex- <lb/>halations. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Another property of æther, is that of pro- <lb/>ducing a conſiderable ſenſe of coldneſs
        in all <lb/>ſurrounding bodies at the inſtant of its being <lb/>transformed into an elaſtic
        aeriform fluid. If, <lb/>therefore, from any cauſe whatever, there <lb/>ſhould take place a
        conſiderable degree of <lb/>heat in the ſtomach, Mr Lavoiſier thinks, that <lb/>æther will
        neceſſarily be a very proper remedy <lb/>for cooling and ſettling it. And he ſuppoſes it
        <lb/>is from this property, that it derives the <lb/>ſedative effects which have been
        attributed <lb/>to it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From theſe reflections, the author is led to <lb/>make ſome obſervations on the manner
        of ad- <pb n="154"/>
        <lb/>miniſtering æther. He thinks it would be an <lb/>eaſy matter to make it appear, that it
        is often <lb/>better to employ it in ſmall doſes, frequently re- <lb/>peated, than to take a
        large quantity at once. <lb/>Suppoſing, for example, the ſtomach of a pa- <lb/>tient to be
        filled with fixed air, as is the caſe <lb/>in inſtances of drunkenneſs, or at leaſt in cer-
        <lb/>tain inſtances of it; if the firſt doſe of æther <lb/>which has been adminiſtered, has
        been ſuch, <lb/>that there has not ariſen from it a volume of <lb/>inflammable air equal to
        the capacity of the <lb/>ſtomach, that viſcus cannot, by this means, be <lb/>freed from all
        the mephitic elaſtic fluid which <lb/>exiſts there. It is, on the contrary, evident,
        <lb/>that there muſt remain in the ſtomach, a mix- <lb/>ture of fixed air, and of the
        inflammable air <lb/>of æther. In ſuch caſes, it will only be after <lb/>the third or fourth
        doſe of æther, that we <lb/>can conſider the ſtomach as cleaned. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Mr Lavoiſier obſerves, that from this rea- <lb/>ſoning, an objection may naturally be
        ſtarted <lb/>againſt the uſe of æther. It may be alleged, <lb/>that in adminiſtering æther
        in the manner men- <lb/>tioned, to a patient whoſe ſtomach has been <lb/>loaded with a
        pernicious elaſtic fluid, we only <lb/>ſubſtitute one elaſtic fluid to another; and it <pb
          n="155"/>
        <lb/>remains to be proved, that the inflammable <lb/>air of æther is more ſalutary than that
        which <lb/>before exiſted in the ſtomach. To this he <lb/>anſwers, that the inflammable air
        of æther is <lb/>capable of being abſorbed by water and other <lb/>watery fluids; from which
        it follows, that at <lb/>the end of a longer or ſhorter interval, all the <lb/>inflammable
        air of æther will of courſe diſap- <lb/>pear, and be combined with the fluids which <lb/>it
        meets in the ſtomach. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>How far our readers will be diſpoſed to a- <lb/>dopt theſe conjectures of Mr Lavoiſier,
        reſpect- <lb/>ing the action of æther, we will not pretend <lb/>to ſay. We muſt own, that,
        to us, his reaſon- <lb/>ing upon this ſubject appears liable to many <lb/>objections. Æther
        is well known to produce <lb/>very conſiderable effects when applied to dif- <lb/>ferent
        ſenſible parts of the ſurface of the <lb/>body; as, for example, to the forehead in in-
        <lb/>ſtances of headach. May we not therefore <lb/>conclude, that its effects, when acting
        upon a <lb/>part ſo highly ſenſible as the ſtomach, will be <lb/>much more conſiderable,
        both upon that viſcus <lb/>itſelf, and upon the ſyſtem in general, indepen- <lb/>dently of
        the generation of any elaſtic vapour, <lb/>or of the ſenſe of cold which its evaporation <pb
          n="156"/>
        <lb/>produces? But, allowing that there are other <lb/>principles upon which æther, taken
        into the <lb/>ſtomach, may be ſuppoſed to act ſtill more <lb/>powerfully than in the ways
        which he ima- <lb/>gines; yet ſtill, not only the reputation of the <lb/>author, but the
        ingenuity of the thought it- <lb/>ſelf, is ſufficient to recommend it to ſerious
        <lb/>conſideration. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
