<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: Diatribe Medicopolitica de Cauſis quare tot Submerſi in
          Vitam non revocentur</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>XII. D. Sam. Gottl. Vogelii, Seren. Duc. Regn. Megapol. à Conſil. Aul. Med. P. P.
              O. in Univer. Lit. Roſtoch. Diatribe Medicopolitica de Cauſis quare tot Submerſi in
              Vitam non revocentur. Præmiſſa eſt Hiſtoria memorabilis cujuſdam fauſti exempli. 12mo,
              Hamburgi</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries M, DCC, XCI. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest and
              most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and published
              by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Physician to His Royal Highness the
              Prince of Wales for Scotland, President of the Royal College of Physicians, Edinburgh,
              and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen, Edinburgh, &amp;c.
              And Professor of the Institutions of Medicine in the University of Edinburgh.</title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: Printed for Peter Hill, Edinburgh; and G. G. J. &amp; J.
                  Robinson, London</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1792</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">16</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">190-202</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108716658</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v16_0190">
    <body>
      <pb n="190"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>XII. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/><hi rend="roman">D. Sam. Gottl. Vogelii</hi>, Seren. Duc. Regn. <lb/>Megapol. à Conſil.
        Aul. Med. P. P. O. in <lb/>Univer. Lit. Roſtoch. Diatribe Medico- <lb/>politica de Cauſis
        quare tot Submerſi in <lb/>Vitam non revocentur. Præmiſſa eſt Hiſ- <lb/>toria memorabilis
        cujuſdam fauſti exempli. <lb/><hi rend="roman">12mo, Hamburgi</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE learned author of this eſſay intro- <lb/>duces his
        obſervations, by relating a <lb/>remarkable caſe of recovery, after apparent <lb/>death had
        taken place by Drowning. This <lb/>caſe, however, did not fall under his own ob-
        <lb/>ſervation; it occurred at Hamburgh, and was <lb/>communicated to him by Dr Schroeder of
        <lb/>that city, under whoſe direction the means of <lb/>recovery were employed. In this
        caſe, al- <lb/>though the time for which the boy was under <lb/>water was not exactly
        aſcertained, yet it was <lb/>concluded, that he could not have been leſs <pb n="191"/>
        <lb/>than half an hour under water. When he <lb/>was found, there was every appearance of
        <lb/>death. His whole body was not only cold, <lb/>but ſtiff; his lips livid, the balls of
        the eyes <lb/>diſtorted, and the pupils dilated, without even <lb/>the ſlighteſt appearance
        either of circulation <lb/>or reſpiration. After employing means of re- <lb/>covery for
        about an hour and a half, ſome <lb/>convulſive motions at laſt took place, which <lb/>were
        gradually ſucceeded by other ſigns of <lb/>life; ſo that, at laſt, a complete recovery took
        <lb/>place. Dr Schroeder aſcribes the recovery <lb/>chiefly to careful friction over the
        whole ſur- <lb/>face of the body, and to careful inflation of <lb/>the lungs; while, at the
        ſame time, veneſection <lb/>was avoided. And Dr Vogel is of opinion, <lb/>that this caſe
        particularly deſerves to be record- <lb/>ed, becauſe the means of cure were ſo ſimple. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>While ſome ſuch caſes as that before re- <lb/>lated, demonſtrate the poſſibility of
        recovery, <lb/>where appearances are very unfavourable, it <lb/>is yet, our author obſerves,
        much to be re- <lb/>greted, that recoveries upon the whole are <lb/>but rare. In proof of
        this, he mentions ſeve- <lb/>ral large towns, in which, though drowning <lb/>be very
        frequent, yet not a ſingle recovery has <pb n="192"/>
        <lb/>taken place for ſeveral years. An inquiry, <lb/>therefore, into the cauſes why
        recoveries are <lb/>ſo rare, he conſiders as an object well meriting <lb/>attention. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He begins by conſidering thoſe cauſes which <lb/>preclude all hopes of recovery. The
        firſt <lb/>which he points out, is continuance for a cer- <lb/>tain length of time under
        water. From the <lb/>obſervations made by the Humane Society of <lb/>London, he infers, that
        patients will be very <lb/>generally irrecoverable who have been three <lb/>quarters of an
        hour under water. But it is <lb/>unqueſtionably ſafer to extend the term of poſ- <lb/>ſible
        recovery, than to limit it, beyond the <lb/>truth. He thinks, however, that no one can
        <lb/>with juſtice be accuſed of neglect, though he <lb/>have not recourſe to any means of
        recovery, <lb/>if the patient has been two hours, or even <lb/>an hour and a half, under
        water. But in <lb/>many inſtances, we know nothing of the time <lb/>for which the body has
        been under water. <lb/>If, however, in theſe caſes there be evident <lb/>marks of putridity,
        a cadaverous ſmell, and <lb/>general emphyſema; theſe, he thinks, are in- <lb/>dubitable
        proofs, that the body has been ſo <lb/>long in the water as to preclude any poſſibility <pb
          n="193"/>
        <lb/>of recovery. All the other marks of death <lb/>which have been commonly pointed out,
        though <lb/>many of them give a ſtrong preſumption, he <lb/>conſiders as by themſelves at
        leaſt doubtful. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A ſecond ſet of irrecoverable caſes are <lb/>thoſe, where patients taken out of the
        water, <lb/>have not in reality been ſuffocated, but have <lb/>periſhed from ſome other
        cauſe of death. <lb/>Many conſpiring cauſes, at the time of drown- <lb/>ing, may bring on
        fatal apoplexy, ſpaſms, or <lb/>convulſions; or death may have been the con- <lb/>ſequence
        of ſevere injuries to the head, ſto- <lb/>mach, or other very ſenſible parts. From
        <lb/>theſe, and ſimilar circumſtances, a perſon who <lb/>has been but a ſhort time under
        water, may <lb/>yet be in an irrecoverable ſtate. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>A third cauſe, from which caſes are not un- <lb/>frequently rendered irrecoverable, is
        the too <lb/>ſlow application of the means of cure. In this <lb/>particular, he obſerves,
        that very great im- <lb/>provements have of late been made, from the <lb/>contrivance of
        proper boxes, containing all the <lb/>neceſſary apparatus, as prepared by Pia, Gar-
        <lb/>done, Cogan, and others; and particularly, <lb/>what he conſiders as an improvement
        upon all <lb/>the others, that of Mr Kite. But he obſerves, <pb n="194"/>
        <lb/>that, ſrom unaccountable negligence, or indo- <lb/>lence, ſeveral large towns, where
        accidents <lb/>from drowning are very frequent, have never <lb/>hitherto made proper
        proviſions of this kind; <lb/>and he points out his native country, Meck- <lb/>lenburg, and
        the city of his reſidence, Roſtoch, <lb/>as being very deficient in theſe particulars,
        <lb/>notwithſtanding the danger to which they are <lb/>expoſed from the river Warna. He
        enters <lb/>alſo, at conſiderable length, into a detail of the <lb/>plan by which this may
        be obviated. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Another cauſe which he points out, as not <lb/>unfrequently preventing the recovery of
        the <lb/>drowned, is, that the neceſſary aſſiſtance and <lb/>remedies are applied either
        injudiciouſly, or <lb/>without ſufficient diligence. Theſe remedies <lb/>he conſiders as in
        general employed with one <lb/>of four intentions, either for affording irrita- <lb/>tion,
        for increaſing the heat, for producing <lb/>depletion of the veſſels of the brain and lungs,
        <lb/>or for renewing reſpiration; and he gives a <lb/>very full enumeration of the
        particular practices <lb/>referable to each head. He mentions many <lb/>controverſies which
        have ſubſiſted among the <lb/>moſt eminent practitioners, reſpecting almoſt <lb/>every
        article of this numerous liſt; and he ob- <pb n="195"/>
        <lb/>ſerves, that as the mode of cure which is adopt- <lb/>ed, can only be ſucceſsful when
        properly accom- <lb/>modated to the nature of the caſe, want of <lb/>recovery muſt often
        ariſe from neceſſary ig- <lb/>norance of circumſtances. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Terror, confuſion, and perturbation of mind, <lb/>are next pointed out as cauſes by
        which a re- <lb/>covery is ſometimes prevented. By theſe, <lb/>much time is often loſt. From
        every mo- <lb/>ment, however, the danger is increaſed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The laſt cauſe which he points out, as con- <lb/>tributing not a little to render
        recoveries leſs <lb/>frequent than might otherwiſe be the caſe, is <lb/>the too early belief
        of patients being in an ir- <lb/>recoverable ſtate; and, in conſequence of this, <lb/>the
        proper means of recovery not being em- <lb/>ployed for a ſufficient length of time. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From the cauſes being thus pointed out, <lb/>why ſo few recover from drowning, Dr Vogel
        <lb/>imagines, that, on particular occaſions at leaſt, <lb/>ſome of theſe may be
        ſucceſsfully obviated. <lb/>And he ſubjoins a brief account of the method <lb/>of cure which
        he thinks ought in general to <lb/>be adopted. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In taking the body out of the water, all ex- <lb/>ternal injuries, and other rough
        treatment, are, <pb n="196"/>
        <lb/>he obſerves, to be avoided as much as poſſi- <lb/>ble. When it has been conveyed to a
        proper <lb/>ſituation, the wet clothes are to be taken off, <lb/>the whole body is to be
        carefully dried, and <lb/>the mouth and noſe freed from any filth that <lb/>may tend to
        obſtruct the paſſage of air. The <lb/>body muſt be placed with the head ſome- <lb/>what
        raiſed, in ſuch a ſituation that there may <lb/>be free acceſs to it on all ſides, and that
        its <lb/>poſition may be eaſily changed. A proper co- <lb/>verlet, ſomewhat warmed, is then
        to be thrown <lb/>over the whole body, leaving the head free. <lb/>Let aſſiſtants, by
        introducing their hands un- <lb/>der this covering, gently and equably rub the <lb/>whole
        body with dry flannel cloths, impreg- <lb/>nated with the ſmoke of juniper, maſtich, oli-
        <lb/>banum, or ſome ſimilar ſubſtance; the cloths <lb/>being carefully dried, and fumigated
        by other <lb/>aſſiſtants. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>During the time of the frictions, an attempt <lb/>muſt be made to inflate the lungs
        with air, by <lb/>blowing it in at the noſe, or even through the <lb/>glottis, by means of a
        proper tube. The tongue <lb/>being drawn ſomewhat forwards, and this tube <lb/>introduced,
        which is always much preferable <lb/>to bronchotomy, inflation is to be performed, <pb
          n="197"/>
        <lb/>by a man whoſe lungs are ſtrong and ſound, <lb/>with ſuch force, that the air may
        penetrate to <lb/>the extreme veſſels of the lungs of the drown- <lb/>ed perſon; and to
        accompliſh this, the mouth <lb/>and noſtrils, excepting where the tube is in- <lb/>troduced,
        muſt be kept carefully ſhut. The <lb/>cheſt and abdomen thus raiſed, are to be again
        <lb/>gently depreſſed; and the alternate introduction <lb/>and expulſion of air regularly
        continued in this <lb/>manner for a due length of time. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In conjunction with friction and artificial re- <lb/>ſpiration, at intervals of from
        ten to twenty <lb/>minutes, warm ſtimulant glyſters are to be in- <lb/>jected, impregnated
        with an infuſion of tobac- <lb/>co, emetic tartar, oxymel of ſquills, volatile al-
        <lb/>kaline ſpirit, or ſome ſimilar article. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>If, from the continuance of this ſimple me- <lb/>thod for the ſpace of an hour or
        upwards, no <lb/>ſign of life can be detected, Dr Vogel thinks, <lb/>there is much reaſon to
        fear that the patient <lb/>is in an irrecoverable ſtate. Nay, he is even <lb/>perſuaded,
        that not a few will recover as ef- <lb/>fectually from being laid in a proper ſituation,
        <lb/>duly covered, and gently rubbed with the <lb/>hands of aſſiſtants alone, as they would
        do by <lb/>the employment of more numerous practices: <pb n="198"/>
        <lb/>and, whatever be the practices employed, it is <lb/>neceſſary, he tells us, attentively
        to watch the <lb/>firſt returns of life; and when any ſigns of life <lb/>appear, every mode
        of cure is, for a little at leaſt, <lb/>to be laid aſide; leſt, by officious labour, we
        ſhould <lb/>diſturb the more ſalutary operations of nature. <lb/>And he obſerves, <q
          rend="quotes">Gravis regula contra <lb/>quam peccant optimi medici. Feſtina lente;
          <lb/>aliquid naturæ committe, et illi confide ſi tem- <lb/>pus adjuvet. Non plus mederi
          oportet, quam <lb/>quantum vides medendum eſſe. </q>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr Vogel's obſervations on the method of <lb/>treatment in caſes of this kind, are
        concluded <lb/>with ſome remarks on blood-letting. Where <lb/>manifeſt ſigns of apoplexy, or
        exuberance of <lb/>blood, can be detected, and where the drown- <lb/>ed perſon is of a
        robuſt and athletic habit, or <lb/>where he has fallen into the water in conſe- <lb/>quence
        of previous inebriation, there can, he <lb/>thinks, be little doubt, that in order to pro-
        <lb/>mote the return of life, the veins muſt be re- <lb/>lieved from the load by which they
        compreſs <lb/>the brain, and are deprived of their tone. <lb/>But the time of blood-letting,
        the place from <lb/>which it is to be taken, and the extent to <lb/>which it is to be let,
        are matters of no ſmall <pb n="199"/>
        <lb/>conſequence; for in theſe particulars, he ob- <lb/>ſerves, errors are often committed.
        Where <lb/>the ſigns of plethora and turgeſcence are ſtrong, <lb/>it ſhould be performed
        prior to every other <lb/>attempt to cure; and when the blood freely <lb/>and forcibly flows
        from the vein when cut, <lb/>with more confidence may we proceed in the <lb/>diſcharge; but
        where the ſigns indicating <lb/>blood-letting are not conſiderable, it will in <lb/>general,
        he thinks, be proper to delay it, till, <lb/>by the application of other remedies, there be
        <lb/>appearances of returning life; and when per- <lb/>formed at this time with thoſe of
        full habits, <lb/>it has often, he tells us, been obſerved, that <lb/>the pulſe, before
        ſmall and oppreſſed, became <lb/>ſtronger and fuller, and at the ſame time re-
        <lb/>ſpiration more free. Symptoms ſometimes oc- <lb/>cur, which indicate even a repetition
        of blood- <lb/>letting before a perfect recovery; and he con- <lb/>ſiders a repetition as
        requiſite, where there take <lb/>place violent pain of the head or breaſt, long
        <lb/>continued ſopor, delirium, difficult reſpiration, <lb/>violent cough, hæmoptoe, or
        ſymptoms of <lb/>peripneumony. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>But if, in ſome caſes, there be ſymptoms <lb/>thus indicating even the repetition of
        blood- <pb n="200"/>
        <lb/>letting, ſo, in other caſes, where ſigns of re- <lb/>turning life take place, it is to
        be as carefully <lb/>ſhunned, leſt the very primordia of life ſhould, <lb/>as it were, be
        diſcharged with the blood; and <lb/>with the weak and infirm, unleſs from urgent
        <lb/>ſymptoms, it is never, he thinks, to be di- <lb/>rected. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When blood-letting is neceſſary, Dr Vogel <lb/>thinks, there can be no doubt that the
        diſcharge <lb/>ſhould in general be made from the external ju- <lb/>gulars. Where blood
        cannot be obtained from <lb/>theſe, he adviſes it to be let from either tem- <lb/>poral
        artery; for though the arteries be leſs <lb/>diſtended with blood than the veins, they
        <lb/>are more irritable; and if there be the ſmal- <lb/>leſt remains of liſe, a diſcharge
        will not <lb/>fail to be obtained from theſe veſſels. In <lb/>ſuch caſes, alſo, he adviſes
        cupping, with ſca- <lb/>rification, to the head, the neck, and the tem- <lb/>ples, which,
        beſides operating as evacuants, <lb/>are often alſo uſeful as ſtimulants. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The quantity of blood to be let, cannot, he <lb/>obſerves, be eaſily determined, but
        muſt be re- <lb/>gulated by the circumſtances of age, ſex, con- <lb/>ſtitution, and other
        particulars, whether ex- <pb n="201"/>
        <lb/>ternal or internal, which indicate the employ- <lb/>ment of it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It will often happen, that after a patient is <lb/>almoſt entirely recovered from the
        effects of <lb/>ſubmerſion, ſymptoms of a difſerent kind will <lb/>ſupervene. To theſe,
        according to their na- <lb/>ture and tendency, the ſkilful phyſician muſt <lb/>direct proper
        remedies; for without theſe, he <lb/>who had but juſt eſcaped death from drown- <lb/>ing,
        will, as is not unfrequently the caſe, in a <lb/>ſhort time fall a victim to another
        diſeaſe. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr Vogel concludes this treatiſe, by pre- <lb/>ſenting to his readers a catalogue of
        the moſt <lb/>valuable publications which have appeared on <lb/>this important ſubject; but
        he contents him- <lb/>ſelf with merely mentioning the names of thoſe <lb/>who wrote on the
        ſubject of ſubmerſion prior <lb/>to the year 1777. Of the later publications, <lb/>and even
        of the tranſlations into German of <lb/>the writings of Cullen, Goodwyn, Kite, and
        <lb/>other eminent Britiſh authors who have treat- <lb/>ed of this ſubject, he gives the
        titles at full <lb/>length: and he concludes with a liſt of the <lb/>dates of public edicts,
        iſſued by different pro- <lb/>vinces and cities, for making proper proviſions <lb/>againſt
        accidents from drowning. We cannot <pb n="202"/>
        <lb/>help expreſſing a regret, that no Britiſh ſta- <lb/>tute appears in his liſt; for it
        is, we think, a <lb/>ſubject which ſhould not be entirely devolved <lb/>on humane ſocieties,
        or the voluntary exer- <lb/>tions of benevolent individuals. Where the <lb/>ſituation of
        cities, towns, and even villages, is <lb/>ſuch as to render frequent accidents of this
        <lb/>kind unavoidable, it would be wiſdom in the <lb/>Legiſlature to oblige the community to
        make <lb/>proper proviſions for recovery. And we can- <lb/>not help entertaining a hope,
        that this too <lb/>long neglected ſubject may at laſt attract the <lb/>attention of the
        Britiſh Parliament. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
