<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Adair: The History of three Cases of Phthisis Pulmonalis</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>James M. Adair</persName>
            </author>
            <title>III. The History of three Cases of Phthisis Pulmonalis, treated by Cuprum
              Vitriolatum, and Conium Maculatum; two of which terminated favourably. By James M.
              Adair, M. D. formerly Physician at Northallerton, now at Edinburgh.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries M, DCC, XCII. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest and
              most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy, collected and published
              by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Physician to His Royal Highness the
              Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians, Edinburgh,
              and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen, Edinburgh, &amp;c.
              And Professor of the Institutions of Medicine in the University of Edinburgh.</title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: Printed for Peter Hill, Edinburgh; and C. G. J. &amp; J.
                  Robinson, London</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1793</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">17</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">473-480</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108717128</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v17_0473">
    <body>
      <pb n="473"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>III. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>The Hiſlory of three Caſes of Phthiſis Pulmo- <lb/>nalis, treated by Cuprum
        Vitriolatum, and <lb/>Conium Maculatum; two of which terminat- <lb/>ed favourably. By <hi
          rend="roman">James M. Adair</hi>, M. D. <lb/>formerly Phyſician at Northallerton, now at
        <lb/>Edinburgh. </head>
      <div>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">M</hi>R G. D. of Northallerton, aged 19, <lb/>born of ſcrophulous
          parents, of whoſe <lb/>family ſeveral had died of Phthiſis; tall, of a <lb/>ſallow
          complexion, and black hair, conſulted <lb/>me in July 1790. He complained of ſhort,
          <lb/>frequent cough, with ſcanty purulent expec- <lb/>toration; pain of the right ſide,
          about the <lb/>ſeventh rib; laborious breathing; and copious <lb/>night ſweats. His
          appetite was bad; and he <lb/>was conſiderably emaciated, and very weak. <lb/>His pulſe
          was quick and ſoft; and, towards <lb/>evening, he was evidently affected with hectic
          <lb/>fever, which remitted on the appearance of <lb/>the ſweat, about three o'clock in the
          morning. <pb n="474"/>
          <lb/>His tongue was preternaturally red; and the <lb/>white of his eyes, and his teeth,
          had a bluiſh <lb/>pearly caſt. The ſtate of his bowels was va- <lb/>rious; but he was,
          moſt frequently, coſtive. <lb/>In ſhort, he had every ſymptom of genuine <lb/>ſcrophulous
          phthiſis. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Theſe complaints had begun about two years <lb/>before, and had gradually increaſed
          till the <lb/>time he conſulted me. It was the opinion of <lb/>his friends, and of Mr
          Dent, a very reſpect- <lb/>able ſurgeon, who attended him, that he could <lb/>not live
          many weeks. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I began, by directing the uſe of a diet, con- <lb/>ſiſting chiefly of milk, with
          plainly dreſſed <lb/>freſh meat for dinner; and indulged him in a <lb/>little mild ale,
          and a glaſs of wine. The fol- <lb/>lowing medicines were preſcribed: </p>
        <floatingText><body>
          <p rend="indentall hanging">
            <lb/>℞. Vitriol. cærul. gr. x. Solut. ex <lb/>Aq. tepid. unc. v. adde <lb/>Spt. Vitriol.
            ten. gtt. x. Fiat Julepum <lb/>Emeticum. </p>
          <p>
            <lb/>Sign. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Let the patient drink about a pint of warm <lb/>water, and ſwallow, immediately
            afterwards, <lb/>half an ounce of the emetic julap, which will <lb/>almoſt inſtantly
            produce gentle vomiting. <pb n="475"/>
            <lb/>This is to be taken, for the preſent, every o- <lb/>ther evening, at 8 o'clock;
            and, aſter ten days <lb/>ſhall have elapſed, every morning. Should <lb/>half an ounce
            not excite vomiting, an ounce <lb/>may be taken. </p>
          <p rend="indentall hanging">
            <lb/>℞. Pulv. folior. cicut. recens ſiccat. dr. ii. <lb/>Mucilag. Gum-Arab. ſpiff. q. s.
            ut fiat <lb/>maſſa in pilulas xxx. dividenda. </p>
          <p rend="indent">
            <lb/>Let one pill be taken every morning and <lb/>evening; and let the doſe be gradually
            in- <lb/>creaſed, by the addition of one pill every <lb/>fourth day. If vertigo
            ſupervene, let the <lb/>patient lie in bed till it ſubſides. </p></body>
        </floatingText>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>A bliſter was alſo applied to the pained <lb/>part, and a laxative mixture directed
          to be oc- <lb/>caſionally uſed. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>He continued for ſome weeks to uſe theſe <lb/>means, without much apparent benefit;
          ex- <lb/>cept that his appetite and ſtrength were ſome- <lb/>what improved, and that the
          ſweating did not <lb/>appear on the night when the vitriolic emetic <lb/>was taken; an
          effect which, in other caſes <lb/>alſo, I have pretty uniformly obſerved to take
          <lb/>place. His cough, and difficulty of breath- <lb/>ing, however, rather increaſed; and,
          for ſome <lb/>days, we were in almoſt hourly expectation of <pb n="476"/>
          <lb/>his death. The medicines were occaſionally <lb/>intermitted, as the ſymptoms ſeemed
          to re- <lb/>quire. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>From about the beginning of September, <lb/>however, he gradually grew better. His
          cough <lb/>was eaſier, his expectoration more free, and of a <lb/>healthier appearance.
          His hectic fever and night <lb/>ſweats left him; his ſtrength and fleſh return- <lb/>ed;
          and, before the middle of October, he <lb/>had perfectly regained his former health, which
          <lb/>he has ever ſince continued to enjoy, having <lb/>grown conſiderably robuſt. </p>
      </div>
    <div>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Mrs M., aged about 26, of a ſanguine tem- <lb/>perament, very fair, with thin ſkin
          and blue <lb/>eyes, the mother of ſeveral children, conſult- <lb/>ed me in Spring 1791.
          She had been for <lb/>ſome months affected with ſhort cough; with <lb/>ſcanty
          expectoration, of a doubtful nature; <lb/>pain of the left ſide; night ſweats; conſider-
          <lb/>able loſs of appetite, fleſh and ſtrength; a- <lb/>menorrhœa, pulſe weak, but not
          very quick; <lb/>bowels generally coſtive. She had taken ſe- <lb/>veral medicines without
          relief. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>As ſhe ſeemed to labour under incipient <lb/>phthiſis, a milk diet, and the ſame
          medicines <pb n="477"/>
          <lb/>which had been ordered for Mr D., were pre- <lb/>ſcribed for her. She was, by much
          intreaty, <lb/>prevailed on, to allow a bliſter to be applied <lb/>to the pained part. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Under the uſe of theſe remedies, her appe- <lb/>tite and ſtrength daily improved; her
          cough, <lb/>pain, and ſweats, left her, and ſhe recovered <lb/>rapidly. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Some months after, ſhe had a ſlight relapſe, <lb/>from imprudent expoſure to cold and
          moiſture, <lb/>which was ſoon removed, by returning to the <lb/>uſe of the medicines. </p>
      </div>
    <div>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>Elizabeth Sedgwick, a poor woman, aged <lb/>26, mother of three children, conſulted
          me a- <lb/>bout the ſame time with Mr D. She com- <lb/>plained of ſevere cough, with
          copious puru- <lb/>lent expectoration, occaſionally ſtreaked with <lb/>blood; conſiderable
          pain of the left fide of the <lb/>thorax; hectic fever; and night ſweats, alternat-
          <lb/>ing with diarrhœa. Her pulſe was extremely <lb/>quick and weak; her appetite gone;
          her <lb/>ſtrength diminiſhed; and ſhe was much ema- <lb/>ciated. The tongue was florid;
          the teeth and <lb/>eyes pearly. She was ſuckling a poor weakly <pb n="478"/>
          <lb/>child of fifteen months old. She had been af- <lb/>fected in this way for above ſix
          months. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I inſiſted ſtrenuoufly, that ſhe ſhould wean <lb/>the child, which however, ſhe did
          not do; <lb/>probably, becauſe ſhe could not afford to feed <lb/>it otherwiſe. Judging
          that the poor diet ſhe <lb/>had hitherto uſed, might have conſiderable <lb/>ſhare in
          aggravating her complaints, I or- <lb/>dered her to drink a glaſs of port wine occa-
          <lb/>ſionally; and to uſe animal broths, meat, milk, <lb/>and other food of eaſy
          digeſtion, and conſider- <lb/>able nutritive powers; with which ſhe was <lb/>ſupplied, by
          the charity of families in the town. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>At the ſame time, I directed the uſe of the <lb/>hemlock pills, and of the ſolutio
          cupri vitrio- <lb/>lati, in the uſual way, interpoſing the opiates <lb/>or acids, as the
          diarrhœa or night ſweats <lb/>ſeemed to require. She continued to uſe theſe <lb/>remedies
          irregularly during ſeveral months, <lb/>with conſiderable relief. She was evidently
          <lb/>ſtronger, and leſs emaciated. Her cough and <lb/>ſpitting were better, and the night
          ſweats were <lb/>nearly removed. In ſhort, her health was a- <lb/>mended when I left the
          place in September <lb/>1791; but I had not ſanguine hopes of her <lb/>ultimate recovery,
          eſpecially as there was no <pb n="479"/>
          <lb/>probability that ſhe would perſiſt in the uſe of <lb/>the medicines, of which ſhe had
          been long <lb/>heartily tired. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p rend="indent space">
          <lb/>As I have, by accident, loſt the regiſter of <lb/>caſes which contained thoſe of the
          three pa- <lb/>tients here mentioned, I am under the neceſ- <lb/>ſity of deſcribing their
          complaints from memo- <lb/>ry; conſequently, with leſs accuracy than I <lb/>could wiſh.
          This, however, I can vouch for, <lb/>that no circumſtance of importance has been
          <lb/>added or omitted. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>The moſt remarkable circumſtance attend- <lb/>ing the uſe of the blue vitriol, is the
          eaſe and <lb/>expedition with which it operates, and the nar- <lb/>row limits within which
          its effects may be con- <lb/>fined. I have frequently given from one to <lb/>four
          tea-ſpoonfuls of it in the day, as a tonic <lb/>laxative, in phthiſical caſes, while I was
          pre- <lb/>ſcribing it in larger doſes, as an emetic. I pre- <lb/>fer adminiſtering it with
          this view, in the e- <lb/>vening, from its tendency to check the night- <lb/>ſweats; but
          have, not unfrequently, given it <lb/>two or three times in twenty-four hours, when
          <lb/>the dyſpnœa was particularly urgent. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I have, ſometimes, uſed the extractum, or <lb/>ſuccus ſpiſſatus cicutæ, inſtead of
          the powder <pb n="480"/>
          <lb/>of the leaves; but I am rather inclined to pre- <lb/>fer the latter. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I generally preſcribe the tinctura opii am- <lb/>moniata, when the patient complains
          of want <lb/>of ſleep; and, frequently uſe an electuary, com- <lb/>poſed of conſerva
          roſarum, nitre, and a ſmall <lb/>proportion of muriatic acid, or ſal oxalidis ace-
          <lb/>toſellæ, ſo as to render it pleaſantly acidulous, <lb/>with a view to relieve the
          hectic heat and <lb/>ſweats. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I have, ſometimes, employed ſetons inſtead <lb/>of bliſters; and my father's
          experience has led <lb/>him to give them a preference. I have at <lb/>preſent under my
          care, a caſe of phthiſis pul- <lb/>monalis, the hiſtory and reſult of which I ſhall,
          <lb/>probably, communicate at ſome future time; <lb/>in which, the uſe of a ſeton has been
          decided- <lb/>ly beneficial. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>I think it right to mention, what your read- <lb/>ers will doubtleſs anticipate, that
          I have been <lb/>conſulted in many phthiſical caſes, in which <lb/>this plan has not
          proved ſucceſsful. I think, <lb/>however, I may ſafely fay, that it has always
          <lb/>prolonged life, and often rendered it more <lb/>comfortable. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
