<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Lockhart: History of a Singular Tumour on the Neck</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Samuel Lockhart</persName>
            </author>
            <title>VI. History of a singular Tumour on the Neck. By Mr Samuel Lockhart, Surgeon, now
              in the service of the Honourable East India Company.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries M, DCC, XCII. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest and
              most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy, collected and published
              by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. S. Ed. Physician to His Royal Highness the
              Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians, Edinburgh,
              and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen, Edinburgh, &amp;c.
              And Professor of the Institutions of Medicine in the University of Edinburgh.</title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: Printed for Peter Hill, Edinburgh; and C. G. J. &amp; J.
                  Robinson, London</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1793</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">17</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">490-494</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW108717128</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v17_0490">
    <body>
      <pb n="490"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>VI. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Hiſtory of a ſingular Tumour on the Neck. By <lb/>Mr <hi rend="roman">Samuel
          Lockhart</hi>, Surgeon, now in the <lb/>ſervice of the Honourable Eaſt India Com-
        <lb/>pany. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">O</hi>N the 11th of April 1789, I committed <lb/>to writing, the
        following caſe of John <lb/>Anderſon, a diſbanded ſoldier, in the 60th <lb/>year of his age. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About 30 years ago, there appeared on <lb/>the right ſide of the neck, a tumour a-
        <lb/>bout the ſize of a walnut, after receiving <lb/>a kick from a horſe when in the army.
        <lb/>For the following ten years after the ac- <lb/>cident, its increaſe was very
        impercepti- <lb/>ble; and he found very little inconvenience <lb/>from it. But, after this,
        it began to grow <lb/>larger; ſo that, at the end of the next ten <lb/>years, it had got to
        the ſize of the fiſt. It now <pb n="491"/>
        <lb/>became very inconvenient to him, from its <lb/>ſize; for he never had any very acute
        pain in <lb/>it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Being viſibly increaſing, he became very <lb/>anxious to have it removed. He therefore
        <lb/>applied for a conſultation of the medical gen- <lb/>tlemen; firſt at London, then in
        Ireland, and, <lb/>laſt of all, at Edinburgh. But, in all of <lb/>theſe places, he was told
        it would be a very <lb/>dangerous operation, on account of its ſitua- <lb/>tion with reſpect
        to the large veſſels and nerves <lb/>of the neck. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He was now, from the ſize of the tumour, <lb/>forced to quit the ſervice. Ever ſince,
        it has <lb/>been very ſenſibly increaſing, though ſlowly. <lb/>But, within theſe laſt ſix
        years of his life, it <lb/>has grown more rapidly; and, at preſent, is <lb/>of a moſt
        enormous ſize; extending from the <lb/>clavicle, up to his ear, and ſtretching a conſi-
        <lb/>derable way over to the left ſide of the neck, <lb/>both before and behind. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>At firſt, the ſkin was ſtretched equally and <lb/>ſmoothly throughout the tumour. But,
        with- <lb/>in the laſt mentioned period, it has become <lb/>very irregular; and there are
        ſeveral very <lb/>large riſings and depreſſions on its ſurface. </p>
      <pb n="492"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>It has now become ſo inconvenient and <lb/>troubleſome to him, as to render reſpiration
        <lb/>and deglutition difficult. And the motion of <lb/>his under-jaw is very obſcure. He
        cannot <lb/>articulate plainly. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He was naturally a thin man, but very <lb/>active; and enjoyed a very good ſtate of
        health, <lb/>previous to the accident; but, ſince which, <lb/>he has been a good deal
        troubled with dy- <lb/>ſpeptic complaints. His ſleep has, ſome time <lb/>paſt, been a good
        deal impaired. He is much <lb/>emaciated; and his voice is very feeble. Said, <lb/>he rather
        heard with difficulty in the right <lb/>ear. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Within theſe eight days, the tumour has ul- <lb/>cerated on the back part, the edges of
        which <lb/>appear gangrenous; and there are ſeveral <lb/>black ſpots on that ſide of the
        tumour. The <lb/>diſcharge from the ulcer is very fetid, copi- <lb/>ous, and of a dark
        colour. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the 6th of April, a violent hæmorrhagy <lb/>broke out from the ulcer, to the amount
        of a <lb/>pound or two; but was ſtopped by the appli- <lb/>cation of cloths dipped in cold
        water and vine- <lb/>gar. The hæmorrhagy recurred again on the <lb/>7th, to a ſtill greater
        quantity; and was ſtop- <lb/>ped, as in the former. </p>
      <pb n="493"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>No more hæmorrhagy occurred, until early <lb/>in the morning of the 10th, when every
        thing <lb/>was tried in vain to ſtop it. And he died a- <lb/>bout 7 o'clock the ſame
        morning. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He had another tumour, of the ſize of an <lb/>egg, ſtretched over the coronal ſuture,
        of the <lb/>atheromatous kind. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>He had uſed a variety of remedies without be- <lb/>nefit, the compoſition of which he
        did not know. </p>
      <p rend="indent space">
        <lb/><hi rend="sc">Dissection</hi>. On cutting the teguments <lb/>over the tumour, they were
        found preterna- <lb/>turally thickened in ſeveral places. And im- <lb/>mediately beneath, we
        found the Platiſma my- <lb/>oides in the ſame ſtate. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On laying open the tumour, we found it <lb/>principally compoſed of fat; which, in
        ſever- <lb/>al places, was hardened. And, diſperſed a- <lb/>mongſt the fat, we found ſeveral
        pretty large <lb/>cyſts, containing a very fetid matter, of the <lb/>conſiſtence and colour
        of lintſeed-oil. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On examining the root of the tumour, we <lb/>found it adhering by a cellular ſubſtance
        to the <lb/>trunk of the carotid artery, the whole way; <lb/>the muſcles ſo preſſed away, as
        to turn the <lb/>face towards the left ſhoulder. </p>
      <pb n="494"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The trachea was puſhed over to the left <lb/>ſide. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The right ſide of the under-jaw was ſo <lb/>twiſted, that the flat ſide of it turned
        to- <lb/>wards the tumour, and the teeth lay horizon- <lb/>tally in the mouth. Both ſalivary
        and lym- <lb/>phatic glands were found perfectly ſound. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Nothing elſe occurred on diſſection. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>We obſerved, on the ſurface of the tumour, <lb/>ſome very beautiful ramifications of
        veins, in <lb/>a varicoſe ſtate. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The tumour weighed thirty pounds. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
