<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Anonymous: Observatio de Diarrhœa. </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Anonymous</persName>
            </author>
            <title>VII. Observatio de Diarrhœa, cum Obstructions Alvi, haud infrequenti connubio.
              Auctore H. Callisen, M. D. &amp; Prof. Chirurg. Vide Acta Societatis Regiæ Medicæ
              Haunienſis. Vol. II. 8vo, Hauniæ. </title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries M, DCC, XCIII. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest and
              most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and published
              by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. SS. Ed. Physician to His Royal Highness the
              Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal college of Physicians, Edinburgh,
              and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen, Edinburgh, &amp;c.
              And Professor of the Institutions of Medicine in the University of Edinburgh.</title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: Printed for Peter Hill, Edinburgh; and G. G. J. &amp; J.
                  Robinson, London</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1794</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">18</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">120-127</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110324839</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v18_0120">
    <body>
      <pb n="120"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>VII. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Obſervatio de Diarrhœa, cum Obſtructione <lb/>Alvi, haud infrequenti connubio. Auctore
          <hi rend="roman">H. <lb/>Calliſen</hi>, M. D. &amp; Prof. Chirurg. <hi rend="roman"
          >Vide</hi>
        <lb/>Acta Societatis Regiæ Medicæ Haunienſis. <lb/>Vol. II. <hi rend="roman">8vo,
          Hauniæ.</hi>
      </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">D</hi>R CALLISEN ſets out with obſerv- <lb/>ing, that both theory
        teaches, and ex- <lb/>perience confirms, that the ſtimulus of acrid <lb/>matter contained in
        the inteſtines, renders <lb/>the alvine dejections more frequent, and in- <lb/>duces
        diarrhœa: for no diſcharge by the belly <lb/>is obtained, but what is produced by the mat-
        <lb/>ter to be rejected, in conſequence of its ſize, <lb/>weight, acrimony, or ſome ſimilar
        circum- <lb/>ſtance. Where the ſtimulus to the inteſtines <lb/>is conſiderable, unleſs it be
        ſuch as to induce <lb/>inflammation, the expelling power of the in- <lb/>teſtines will be
        proportionally increaſed; <lb/>the derivations of fluids to the inteſtines will <lb/>be more
        copious, and the dejections of ex- <pb n="121"/>
        <lb/>crementitious matter in a fluid ſtate more <lb/>frequent. Hence, among the remote
        cauſes <lb/>of diarrhœa, authors have enumerated fo- <lb/>reign irritations introduced, ſuch
        as poiſons, <lb/>medicines, or the like; acrid matters de- <lb/>poſited in the alimentary
        canal from the ſy- <lb/>ſtem, ſuch as the bile or ſuccus pancreaticus; <lb/>or morbid matter
        generated in the ſyſtem, <lb/>as in caſes of critical and colliquative <unclear>diar-
          <lb/>rhœæ</unclear>: But no writer, Dr Calliſen obſerves, <lb/>has conſidered a hardened
        maſs, formed of <lb/>the excrementitious matters themſelves, as a <lb/>cauſe of this
        affection: nor would ſuch an <lb/>effect, he thinks, appear probable, ſince a col-
        <lb/>lection might naturally be ſuppoſed to in- <lb/>duce rather mechanical obſtruction than
        <lb/>diarrhœa. But the poſſibility of ſuch a <lb/>cauſe of diarrhœa was demonſtrated to him
        <lb/>by the following caſe: A woman in the <lb/>40th year of her age, of a ſpare habit of
        <lb/>body, the mother of ſeveral children, and <lb/>menſtruating regularly, had, for ſeveral
        <lb/>months, been diſtreſſed with anorexia, vo- <lb/>miting, colic pains, particularly in
        the epi- <lb/>gaſtric region and diarrhœa, by which black <lb/>coloured fæces were
        evacuated. When ſhe <pb n="122"/>
        <lb/>applied for Dr Calliſen's advice, he preſcrib- <lb/>ed various ſaline, oily, and
        rhubarbarine <lb/>laxatives; and afterwards, different tonics, <lb/>with ſuitable regimen;
        but without deriving <lb/>any benefit from them. A preſſing colic <lb/>pain ſeemed, to the
        feelings of the patient, <lb/>to be now entirely ſeated in the left hypo- <lb/>chondrium.
        Upon examining the abdomen, <lb/>Dr Calliſen felt a tumour on the left ſide, <lb/>near the
        margin of the falſe ribs, about the <lb/>ſize of a gooſe egg, which gave pain when
        <lb/>touched. Suſpecting this tumour to ariſe <lb/>from obſtruction of the ſpleen, he
        ordered <lb/>alterant pills, conſiſting of ſoap, bitter ex- <lb/>tract, and gum ammoniac;
        and at the ſame <lb/>time he directed external unction with mer- <lb/>cury and camphor.
        Under theſe remedies, <lb/>the vomiting ceaſed, and the pain deſcended <lb/>to the region of
        the loins, on the left ſide; <lb/>the diarrhœa, from which ſhe had five or ſix <lb/>ſtools
        every day, being little changed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>When Dr Calliſen again examined the <lb/>abdomen, at the end of fourteen days after
        <lb/>his former examination, he found that the <lb/>tumour had deſcended from the place it
        then <lb/>occupied, to the region of the loins. The me- <pb n="123"/>
        <lb/>dicines before directed were ordered to be <lb/>continued, as the patient was pretty
        eaſy, <lb/>her ſymptoms being diminiſhed. Some time <lb/>afterwards, ſhe affirmed ſhe was no
        longer <lb/>ſenſible of the tumour, nor could Dr Calli- <lb/>ſen diſcover it by the feel:
        but from that <lb/>period ſhe complained of a peculiar ſenſe of <lb/>preſſure in the rectum,
        and was excruciated <lb/>both night and day with conſtant teneſmus. <lb/>She was at the ſame
        time affected with trouble- <lb/>ſome hæmorrhoidal tumours, and frequent <lb/>bloody
        dejections. To counteract theſe <lb/>ſymptoms, Dr Calliſen directed leeches to be
        <lb/>applied to the anus, emollient and oily in- <lb/>jections, anodynes, and the gummy
        extract <lb/>of aloes. But notwithſtanding theſe, the <lb/>teneſmus ſo far increaſed, that
        the patient, <lb/>under the violence of this complaint, fre- <lb/>quently fainted. A ſlow
        fever, with great <lb/>proſtration of ſtrength, ſupervened, and ſhe <lb/>ſeemed to be in the
        utmoſt danger. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>While the patient was in this deplorable <lb/>ſituation, Dr Calliſen, upon examining
        the <lb/>rectum with his finger, was able to touch a <lb/>hard body; and, judging of the
        ſize of it by <lb/>means of a probe, he concluded that it was <pb n="124"/>
        <lb/>too large to be diſcharged by the efforts of <lb/>nature. From reflecting on the
        ſymptoms <lb/>reſulting from inteſtinal calculi, he now con- <lb/>jectured that his
        patient's complaints aroſe <lb/>entirely from a concretion of that nature, and <lb/>thought
        that no time was to be loſt in extract- <lb/>ing it. Having placed the patient in the ſitua-
        <lb/>tion for the operation for fiſtula in ano, he <lb/>introduced the forceps employed for
        the ex- <lb/>traction of ſtone from the bladder, into the <lb/>rectum. From the diſtance of
        the handles, <lb/>after he had laid hold of the foreign body, <lb/>he concluded, that its
        diameter muſt be a- <lb/>bove four inches, and that it was therefore <lb/>too large to be
        extracted entire by the na- <lb/>tural orifice of the anus. But before think- <lb/>ing of
        enlarging the paſſage, it firſt ſeemed <lb/>proper to attempt to break the foreign body.
        <lb/>This he very eaſily accompliſhed; and it <lb/>ſoon appeared, that it did not conſiſt of
        <lb/>a calculous matter; for he extracted ſe- <lb/>veral fragments of highly fœtid
        excrementi- <lb/>tious matter, of a very firm conſiſtence, <lb/>weighing about two ounces
        and a half. The <lb/>remainder was eaſily brought away, by re- <lb/>peated emollient
        injections. The ſame day, <pb n="125"/>
        <lb/>many hard ſcyballa were ſpontaneouſly eva- <lb/>cuated by the anus. After this, the
        natural <lb/>conſiſtence of the excrements returned, the <lb/>cholic pains, anorexia, and
        hæmorrhoidal <lb/>tumours ſoon ceaſed; and in a ſhort time <lb/>ſhe recovered perfect
        health; care being <lb/>only taken to obviate coſtiveneſs, by proper <lb/>diet, and gentle
        ſaline and oily laxatives. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr Calliſen has no doubt that this excre- <lb/>mentitious maſs was accumulated and
        indur- <lb/>ated in the colon. For the ſmall inteſtines, <lb/>he obſerves, on account of
        their equal <lb/>figure, without cells, and of the greater <lb/>thinneſs of their contents,
        ſcarce admit of <lb/>obſtruction, without ſome other diſeaſe. On <lb/>the contrary, the
        cells of the colon give an <lb/>opportunity for the retention of the more <lb/>firm
        excrements, for their induration, and <lb/>for their gradual increaſe. The concreted
        <lb/>maſs, by its ſize, acrimony, and weight, af- <lb/>fords, he obſerves, an unuſual
        ſtimulus to <lb/>the inteſtines. Hence, in ſuch a caſe, he thinks <lb/>fluids would be
        derived to the inteſtines; <lb/>and from thence, as in the preſent caſe, <lb/>diarrhœa, and
        all the other ſymptoms here <lb/>occurring, would take place. </p>
      <pb n="126"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Through the whole courſe of this patient's <lb/>diſeaſe, for the ſpace of three months,
        diar- <lb/>rhœa was preſent; and he thinks it highly <lb/>probable that this aroſe from the
        irritation <lb/>of the excrementitious globe, ſince that ſymp- <lb/>tom ceaſed almoſt as
        ſoon as it was evacuated. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Dr Calliſen concludes this paper with an <lb/>obſervation, which he thinks of
        importance <lb/>in practice. In every habit, he remarks, <lb/>where the inteſtines are weak
        and irritable, <lb/>a diarrhœa may be preſent for many days, <lb/>even for weeks, and yet
        excrementitious <lb/>matter may be accumulated in ſuch quanti- <lb/>ty, as to be prejudicial
        to the ſyſtem, from <lb/>its acrimony, putridity, and from the dan- <lb/>ger of abſorption,
        particularly in acute diſ- <lb/>eaſes. In caſes of diarrhœa and dyſentery, <lb/>we not
        unfrequently diſcover, he obſerves, <lb/>at the end of ſeveral weeks, numerous hard
        <lb/>ſcyballa evacuated, which could never be <lb/>ſuppoſed to be produced, from the ſmall
        <lb/>quantity of nouriſhment taken during the <lb/>courſe of the diſeaſe. And we find, that
        <lb/>after the evacuation of theſe, the patient <lb/>ſoon recovers. Hence he thinks, that,
        in <lb/>many caſes at leaſt, ſtrong purgatives are <pb n="127"/>
        <lb/>indicated in the beginning of the diſeaſe, for <lb/>thoſe affected with dyſentery and
        diarrhœa. <lb/>He conſiders them as particularly indicated <lb/>in every caſe where foulneſs
        of the tongue <lb/>and an oppreſſive fixed pain at any particu- <lb/>lar part of the
        abdomen, create a ſuſpicion <lb/>of accumulated fæces. And, on the baſis <lb/>of extenſive
        experience, he ventures to af- <lb/>firm, that, in putrid diſeaſes, particularly in <lb/>the
        beginning, although either ſpontaneous <lb/>diarrhœa, or one excited by gentle laxatives,
        <lb/>be preſent, yet that an obſtinate diſeaſe may <lb/>be much more quickly and ſafely
        cured, if <lb/>briſk purgatives be exhibited in due time. <lb/>And, upon the whole, he is
        diſpoſed to <lb/>think, that in putrid diſeaſes, briſk purga- <lb/>tives are to be preferred
        to more gentle ones, <lb/>ſince a ſtate of torpor and inſenſibility of the <lb/>inteſtinal
        canal, and indeed of the whole <lb/>body, often renders the uſe of the latter al-
        <lb/>together ineffectual. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
