<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Bishopric: Case of an Ascites, of Six Months continuance, cured in a
          Month</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Robert Bishopric</persName>
            </author>
            <title>XV. Case of an Ascites, of Six Months continuance, cured in a Month, by the
              exhibition of an Infusion of Tobacco. By Mr Robert Bishopric, Surgeon, York.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries M, DCC, XCIII. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest and
              most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and published
              by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. SS. Ed. Physician to His Royal Highness the
              Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal college of Physicians, Edinburgh,
              and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen, Edinburgh, &amp;c.
              And Professor of the Institutions of Medicine in the University of Edinburgh.</title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: Printed for Peter Hill, Edinburgh; and G. G. J. &amp; J.
                  Robinson, London</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1794</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">18</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">382-386</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110324839</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v18_0382">
    <body>
      <pb n="382"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>XV. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Caſe of an Aſcites, of Six Months continuance, <lb/>cured in a Month, by the exhibition
        of an <lb/>Infuſion of Tobacco. By Mr <hi rend="roman">Robert Bi- <lb/>ſhopric</hi>,
        Surgeon, York. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/>
        <note place="inset" rend="hanging">
          <date>June 25. <lb/>1785. </date>
        </note><hi rend="dc(2)">A</hi>NN BULMER, of Middle- <lb/>thorpe Grange, near York, <lb/>aged
        9 years and a half, about ſix months ago <lb/>became afflicted with an aſcites, in a very
        <lb/>high degree; for the magnitude, tenſion, and <lb/>fluctuation of the abdomen were ſo
        conſider- <lb/>able, that ſhe appeared as fit for the opera- <lb/>tion of the trocar, as any
        patient I ever ſaw <lb/>in my life. There was no other dropſical <lb/>ſwelling. She was
        emaciated, had a dry <lb/>cough, and bad nights; body coſtive, and <lb/>appetite impaired.
        Her urine was very high- <lb/>coloured, and ſo ſcanty, that ſhe only made <lb/>about four
        ounces in twenty-four hours. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I was alſo informed by her aunt (under <lb/>whoſe roof ſhe then was), that ſhe had been
        <lb/>ſeized, near nine months ago, with an ague, <pb n="383"/>
        <lb/>which continued near three months, before <lb/>it was removed by the uſe of medicines:
        <lb/>That the ſwelling of the belly began to make <lb/>its appearance ſoon after the attack
        of the <lb/>ague, and that it continued increaſing for <lb/>four months. Her friends then
        became ſo <lb/>much alarmed, that they applied to an ex- <lb/>perienced phyſician of this
        city for advice; <lb/>and ſhe continued under his care for two <lb/>months. She took the
        medicines preſcribed, <lb/>in a regular manner, but with no apparent <lb/>abatement of the
        diſeaſe; for the ſize of the <lb/>abdomen continued nearly the ſame during <lb/>the period
        of treatment. But, that the diſ- <lb/>eaſe was checked for the time, was obvious; <lb/>for,
        on her omitting the uſe of her medicines <lb/>for about a fortnight before ſhe applied to
        <lb/>me, the ſwelling of her body began immedi- <lb/>ately to increaſe, and continued
        progreſſively <lb/>ſo, until the diſeaſe was attended with the <lb/>unpromiſing appearances
        already deſcribed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From an attentive examination of the <lb/>ſymptoms, I could not forbear conſidering
        <lb/>the condition of the patient as a loſt caſe. <lb/>But having juſt then peruſed Dr
        Fowler's <lb/>pamphlet of Medical Reports on the effects <pb n="384"/>
        <lb/>of Tobacco, in the cure of Dropſies, giving <lb/>an account of ſome extraordinary caſes
        of <lb/>Anaſarca and Aſcites having been ſucceſsfully <lb/>treated, I was encouraged to make
        a trial of <lb/>the medicine. I therefore ordered the patient <lb/>to take from fifteen to
        twenty drops of the <lb/>infuſion of tobacco, prepared according to <lb/>the Doctor's
        directions in his Reports, <lb/>every forenoon, and every evening, in two <lb/>table
        ſpoonfuls of an aqueous vehicle, for a <lb/>week. I alſo ordered that ſhe ſhould be al-
        <lb/>lowed as much nouriſhing food as ſhe could <lb/>take; and that the quantity of liquid
        drunk <lb/>(drinking as little as poſſible), and the quan- <lb/>tity of urine paſſed every
        24 hours ſhould be <lb/>carefully noticed. At the ſame time, I took <lb/>the dimenſions of
        the circumference of the <lb/>abdomen, acroſs the umbilicus, with a tape. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>At the end of the firſt week, I found (my <lb/>directions being ſtrictly obſerved),
        that the <lb/>medicine had agreed with the ſtomach; <lb/>that the urine began to be
        increaſed on the <lb/>ſecond day; that it continued increaſing <lb/>from that time; and
        alſo, that the ſize of <lb/>the abdomen had been leſſening for ſeveral <lb/>days paſt. </p>
      <pb n="385"/>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The doſe of the infuſion was then ordered <lb/>to be increaſed from 20 to 30 drops
        twice a <lb/>day, with the ſame regimen, for a week longer. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>At the end of the ſecond week, I found <lb/>that the effects of the infuſion were ſtill
        more <lb/>conſpicous and ſucceſsful; for the urine <lb/>had gradually increaſed to four
        pints, wine <lb/>meaſure, in 24 hours, although the liquids <lb/>drunk in the ſame ſpace of
        time did not ex- <lb/>ceed a pint; and that, on meaſuring her <lb/>body in the ſame manner
        as at the firſt, it <lb/>was reduced full eleven inches and a half in <lb/>circumference.
        The medicine had kept the <lb/>body gently open every day, and had ex- <lb/>cited a ſlight
        degree of nauſea with the <lb/>larger doſes. The appetite and ſleep were <lb/>become more
        natural; and the patient be- <lb/>gan to recover ſtrength. The body, how- <lb/>ever,
        although wonderfully leſſened, was not <lb/>yet reduced to its natural ſize. I therefore
        <lb/>ordered the medicine and regimen to be <lb/>continued in the ſame manner as before. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>At the end of two weeks more, or a month <lb/>from the commencement of its uſe, the
        ſwel- <lb/>ling of the abdomen was ſtill farther re- <lb/>duced (perhaps three or four
        inches, for I <pb n="386"/>
        <lb/>did not happen to apply the meaſuring tape <lb/>again), and it appeared quite of its
        natural <lb/>ſize. The operation of the medicine, the <lb/>doſe of which was 30 drops twice
        a day, <lb/>continued the ſame on the ſtomach and <lb/>bowels as before; and alſo proved
        equally <lb/>ſo by the kidnies, in proportion to the re- <lb/>duced collection of water in
        the abdomen. <lb/>She had alſo made ſome progreſs in the re- <lb/>covery of her fleſh and
        ſtrength. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In ſhort, this formidable diſeaſe, to the <lb/>aſtoniſhment of all that ſaw it, was
        entirely <lb/>removed by the uſe of infuſion of to- <lb/>bacco alone; for it anſwered every
        purpoſe <lb/>ſo well, the patient had no other medicine <lb/>given her during its
        adminiſtration. For <lb/>fear, however, of an immediate relapſe, I <lb/>thought it prudent
        to direct both the me- <lb/>dicine and the regimen to be continued for <lb/>another
        fortnight; which was attended with <lb/>the uſual operative effects. And now (which <lb/>is
        ſix weeks ſince ſhe came under my care), <lb/>having had no relapſe of her dropſical ſymp-
        <lb/>toms, and her fleſh and ſtrength being much <lb/>reſtored, ſhe appears perfectly free
        from all <lb/>her complaints. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
