<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Duncan: Observations respecting the Guinea Worm</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Dr Duncan</persName>
            </author>
            <title>III. Observations respecting the Guinea Worm. By Mr J. Drummond, Surgeon in the
              Service of the Honourable East India Company. Communicated in a Letter to Dr
              Duncan.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries M, DCC, XCIII. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest and
              most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and published
              by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. SS. Ed. Physician to His Royal Highness the
              Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal college of Physicians, Edinburgh,
              and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen, Edinburgh, &amp;c.
              And Professor of the Institutions of Medicine in the University of Edinburgh.</title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: Printed for Peter Hill, Edinburgh; and G. G. J. &amp; J.
                  Robinson, London</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1794</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">18</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">294-300</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110324839</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v18_0294">
    <body>
      <pb n="294"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>III. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Obſervations reſpecting the Guinea Worm. By <lb/>Mr <hi rend="roman">J. Drummond</hi>,
        Surgeon in the Service of <lb/>the Honourable Eaſt India Company. Com- <lb/>municated in a
        Letter to Dr <hi rend="roman">Duncan</hi>. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">I</hi> AM diſposed to believe, that the Guinea <lb/>Worm ſometimes
        induces ſymptoms, <lb/>which, as far as I know, have not hitherto <lb/>been deſcribed.
        Perſonal experience of the <lb/>diſorder, firſt led me to form this opinion. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>About the end of November 1791, I per- <lb/>ceived an unuſual ſtiffneſs and ſoreneſs in
        <lb/>the inferior part of the gaſtrocnemii muſcles <lb/>of the right leg, at that part where
        the ten- <lb/>dons of both gaſtrocnemii unite to form the <lb/>Tendo Achillis. This ſoreneſs
        was never <lb/>acute, conſequently did not occaſion parti- <lb/>cular inconvenience, or
        prevent me from <lb/>walking. Several days afterwards, I obſerved <lb/>a ſwelling in the
        part; but this was not at- <lb/>tended by an increaſe of pain, nor diſcoloura- <pb n="295"/>
        <lb/>tion. A few days after the occurrence of <lb/>the ſwelling, a ſmall rediſh-coloured
        puſ- <lb/>tule, with a black point in the middle, ap- <lb/>peared on the inſide of the leg,
        about an <lb/>inch above the maleolus internus, on the <lb/>fleſhy part of the leg, and
        behind the tibia. <lb/>This puſtule appeared to contain a watery <lb/>fluid. At the ſame
        time, I felt very diſtinct- <lb/>ly, under the ſkin, a round firm ſubſtance; <lb/>and was
        able to trace the animal with my <lb/>finger to a conſiderable diſtance, extending <lb/>in
        convolutions obliquely towards the poſte- <lb/>rior and upper part of the leg. Though the
        <lb/>diſeaſe was now evident, yet I did not think <lb/>it neceſſary to uſe any remedies,
        with a view <lb/>to expedite the animal's progreſs; nor, in- <lb/>deed, was I acquainted
        with any medicine <lb/>or application which could produce that ef- <lb/>fect. I concluded,
        that he would work his <lb/>way out, and that it would be moſt prudent <lb/>to leave him
        unmoleſted. But, on the night <lb/>of the 17th December, a few days after the
        <lb/>appearance of the puſtule, though I went to <lb/>bed otherwiſe in perfect health, I
        awoke, at <lb/>two in the morning, with a ſenſation of in- <lb/>tolerable itching over the
        whole ſurface of <pb n="296"/>
        <lb/>the body. This ſenſation was ſo extremely <lb/>urgent, that I could not refrain from
        ſcratch- <lb/>ing violently. Soon afterwards, I felt an <lb/>exceſſive heat and pricking in
        my face. On <lb/>looking in a glaſs, I remarked a redneſs and <lb/>fluſhing over my face;
        and the muſcles of <lb/>the face were ſwelled and convulſed. On <lb/>thoſe parts of my ſkin
        where I felt the itch- <lb/>ing, I could diſcover with my finger a thick- <lb/>ening, as it
        were, of the ſkin; it felt as if <lb/>full of hard bumps. While puzzled to ac- <lb/>count
        for theſe ſymptoms, which I had never <lb/>ſeen, nor read, nor heard of, I was attacked
        <lb/>with excruciating pain in my belly, accom- <lb/>panied by violent retching, vomiting,
        and <lb/>looſe ſtools. A little bile and acid matter <lb/>were rejected, by vomiting. But as
        very <lb/>little bile, notwithſtanding the violent retch- <lb/>ing, was brought up, or
        paſſed downwards, <lb/>theſe ſymptoms could not have been occa- <lb/>ſioned by an unuſual
        quantity or acrimony <lb/>of that fluid. The vomiting, as nearly as I <lb/>can gueſs,
        continued with very little inter- <lb/>miſſion above half an hour; during the <lb/>whole of
        which time, the pain continued <lb/>with unabated ſeverity. Theſe ſymptoms <pb n="297"/>
        <lb/>were ſucceeded by violent rigors, which con- <lb/>tinued for ſome hours, and reſembled
        the <lb/>cold ſtage of the paroxyſm of an intermit- <lb/>tent, unuſually ſevere. When the
        vomiting <lb/>ceaſed, I went to bed, and was well covered <lb/>with blankets. The ſenſation
        of cold gra- <lb/>dually abated, and I fell aſleep. The cold- <lb/>neſs and ſhivering were
        not followed by any <lb/>preternatural degree of heat of which I was <lb/>ſenſible; but when
        I awoke in the morning, <lb/>I felt a moiſture on my feet. In the courſe <lb/>of the night,
        the puſtule had burſt, and a <lb/>white firm ſubſtance appeared in the ſpot <lb/>which the
        puſtule had occupied, but ſo deep <lb/>that it could not be laid hold of. The ani- <lb/>mal
        had changed his ſituation during the <lb/>preceding night, and had buried himſelf very
        <lb/>deeply among the muſcles. He had effected <lb/>this ſo completely, that though I felt
        him <lb/>with my finger to a great extent on the 17th, <lb/>yet, on the morning of the 18th,
        there was <lb/>not the ſmalleſt portion perceptible; nor <lb/>could I diſcover the leaſt
        trace, on the ſtrict- <lb/>eſt examination. I felt no inconvenience <lb/>from the attack
        which I have deſcribed on <lb/>the following day, except a little weakneſs; <pb n="298"/>
        <lb/>nor had I afterwards any return of theſe di- <lb/>ſtreſſing ſymptoms. On the night of
        the <lb/>18th, a conſiderable inflammation appeared, <lb/>ſurrounding the ankle; and I found
        it ne- <lb/>ceſſary, on the 19th, to refrain from walking, <lb/>and to confine myſelf to a
        horizontal poſi- <lb/>tion. On the 22d, I drew a ſmall thread <lb/>acroſs the ſurface of the
        ſore, ſo as to touch <lb/>the extremity of the animal, which felt hard, <lb/>and firmly
        fixed in the fleſh. In conſequence <lb/>of this irritation, he threw up a conſiderable
        <lb/>quantity of a watery fluid. Some time after <lb/>this, he entirely diſappeared, and the
        inflam- <lb/>mation abated. A troubleſome ſore remain- <lb/>ed, with a bloody ichorous
        diſcharge, which <lb/>continued until the beginning of February <lb/>1792. It then healed,
        except a ſmall point. <lb/>At this time the animal made his appearance, <lb/>and I was
        enabled to ſecure him with a <lb/>thread. He was wrapped round a ſmall bit <lb/>of ſtick,
        and pulled twice a day, in the com- <lb/>mon manner. At the expiration of twenty <lb/>days
        the extraction was completed. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb rend="space"/>The animal was upwards of two yards in <lb/>length, and of the thickneſs
        of a crow quill. <lb/>After the half was extracted, he gradually <pb n="299"/>
        <lb/>diminiſhed in ſize. I found that, his pro- <lb/>greſs was quickened by the application
        of <lb/>the aloe leaf, as hot as it could be born, to <lb/>that part of the leg which was
        hard, ſwelled, <lb/>and painful. The ſame effect was produced <lb/>by hard friction. A
        greaſy ſubſtance was <lb/>well rubbed on the part, by which means the <lb/>friction could be
        employed for a greater length <lb/>of time, and induced leſs pain. The animal <lb/>was
        coiled up in hard knots, in different <lb/>parts of the leg; and to theſe the friction
        <lb/>was chiefly applied. Theſe remedies, parti- <lb/>cularly the friction, ſeemed to
        ſtimulate the <lb/>animal, and induce him to quit his hold <lb/>more expeditiouſly than he
        otherwiſe would <lb/>have done. The application of a great de- <lb/>gree of heat to the
        part, promoted the form- <lb/>ation of matter around the animal; in con- <lb/>ſequence of
        which he became leſs fixed, and <lb/>was therefore pulled out more eaſily. I am
        <lb/>inclined to believe, that the extraordinary <lb/>ſymptoms which appeared on the night
        of <lb/>the 17th December, were occaſioned by the <lb/>animal having changed his poſition;
        and <lb/>that they might have been prevented, by <pb n="300"/>
        <lb/>making an opening through the ſound part <lb/>of the ſkin, and ſecuring the animal with
        a <lb/>thread. Had this practice been followed, <lb/>perhaps the greater part, if not the
        whole, <lb/>might have been extracted immediately, and <lb/>without farther trouble or
        danger. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
