<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Brown: History of a Case in which a Recovery took place</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Thomas Brown</persName>
            </author>
            <title>IX. History of a Case in which a Recovery took place, after a remarkable Injury
              to the Brain. By Mr Thomas Brown, Surgeon in Musselburgh.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries M, DCC, XCIII. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest and
              most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and published
              by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. SS. Ed. Physician to His Royal Highness the
              Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal college of Physicians, Edinburgh,
              and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen, Edinburgh, &amp;c.
              And Professor of the Institutions of Medicine in the University of Edinburgh.</title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: Printed for Peter Hill, Edinburgh; and G. G. J. &amp; J.
                  Robinson, London</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1794</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">18</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">342-347</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110324839</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v18_0342">
    <body>
      <pb n="342"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>IX. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Hiſtory of a Caſe in which a Recovery took <lb/>place, after a remarkable Injury to the
        Brain. <lb/>By Mr <hi rend="roman">Thomas Brown</hi>, Surgeon in Muſſel- <lb/>burgh. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">C</hi>HARLES BURNET, about 12 years <lb/>old, having, on Thurſday
        evening the 9th <lb/>of May, been engaged with ſome of his com- <lb/>panions in throwing
        ſtones, received a blow <lb/>on his head, which made him fall down, and <lb/>he remained
        inſenſible for a few minutes. <lb/>He was ſoon after led home, and appeared ſo
        <lb/>immaterially hurt, as to require no immedi- <lb/>ate aſſiſtance. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>On the following morning I was ſent for, <lb/>and found him out of bed, complaining
        only <lb/>of ſome ſickneſs, giddineſs, and inclination <lb/>for vomiting; his ſenſes every
        way perfect; <lb/>his ſight and hearing very diſtinct. His pulſe, <lb/>however, was much
        diſordered, not beating <lb/>two ſtrokes alike, in general ſlow, and ſome- <pb n="343"/>
        <lb/>times with the intermiſſion of two or three <lb/>ſeconds. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Upon examining the place where he re- <lb/>ceived the blow, I could only obſerve a
        ſmall <lb/>wound, little larger than a pin head; no tu- <lb/>mour: but, upon preſſing with
        the finger, <lb/>the teguments gave that feel, as if there <lb/>were no bone beneath, with
        ſome faint fluc- <lb/>tuation. Upon enlarging the wound with a <lb/>lancet, I was much
        ſurpriſed with the ap- <lb/>pearance of a quantity of brain, mixed with <lb/>blood.
        Introducing my finger, I felt the <lb/>cranium much broke and beat in, a conſi- <lb/>derable
        way upon the brain. I proceeded <lb/>to enlarge the wound, in the directions that
        <lb/>appeared moſt neceſſary and convenient, ſo <lb/>as to expoſe the whole fracture. A
        ſpace, <lb/>nearly about the ſize of half a crown, was <lb/>ſenſibly depreſſed; and in that
        place where <lb/>two pieces were beat in, the depreſſion ex- <lb/>ceeded half an inch. The
        aſſiſtance of the <lb/>trepan was not neceſſary; and I readily ex- <lb/>tracted one piece,
        about the ſize of a large <lb/>farthing, ſhaped like a wedge. The other <lb/>piece ſeemed to
        adhere pretty firmly by <lb/>its largeſt ſurface. After raiſing it to a <pb n="344"/>
        <lb/>level, I determined to give it a chance of <lb/>uniting. There was a fiſſure extended
        about <lb/>three fourths of an inch, which ſtopped at the <lb/>junction of the frontal bone.
        The fracture <lb/>was ſituated in the left parietal bone, nearly <lb/>in the middle between
        the ſagittal and ſqua- <lb/>mous ſutures, and about an inch from its <lb/>junction with the
        frontal. Having done <lb/>every thing that appeared immediately ne- <lb/>ceſſary, I dreſſed
        up the wound, put my pa- <lb/>tient to bed, and gave every direction that <lb/>appeared
        requiſite, and left him more reliev- <lb/>ed than before the operation, having ſeem-
        <lb/>ingly no complaint. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>I ſhall not give a particular detail of the <lb/>progreſs of the caſe, but content
        myſelf with <lb/>obſerving, that for three or four days the <lb/>ſymptoms were rather more
        unfavourable, <lb/>the giddineſs ſevere, the vomiting almoſt con- <lb/>ſtant, and attended
        with frequent hiccough, <lb/>the pulſe very much affected, and a conſider- <lb/>able languor
        and want of energy over the <lb/>whole ſyſtem. He only once made his urine, <lb/>and had one
        ſtool inſenſibly. His mental <lb/>faculties were at no time deranged. During <lb/>theſe few
        days, I allowed him nothing but <pb n="345"/>
        <lb/>gruel acidulated with lemon, whey, or water <lb/>with a toaſt in it; and made him take
        a ſpoon- <lb/>ful of a mixture every three hours, with <lb/>tinctura thebaica and vitriolic
        acid. No <lb/>ſymptomatic fever appearing, and his pulſe <lb/>becoming flat, I allowed him
        white wine in <lb/>his drinks; and about the fifth day, his vo- <lb/>miting and hiccough
        entirely left him. After <lb/>this period, he uniformly did well; and a- <lb/>bout three
        weeks from the accident, he was <lb/>able to go about the houſe. At this period <lb/>he had
        no complaint whatever, but his pulſe <lb/>was ſtill affected. It however gradually be-
        <lb/>came more regular for about ſix weeks, when <lb/>it was not in the leaſt affected; and
        now he <lb/>undergoes every fatigue, and attends his <lb/>uſual diverſions, without the
        ſmalleſt incon- <lb/>venience. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>There are a few particulars which occur- <lb/>ed during the operation, and in the after
        <lb/>ſtate, which deſerve to be taken notice of. <lb/>Immediately upon allowing vent to the
        brain, <lb/>by enlarging the wound, the boy felt him- <lb/>ſelf inſtantly relieved both from
        ſickneſs and <lb/>giddineſs; and, from being languid and op- <lb/>preſſed, became lively and
        ſtrong. During the <pb n="346"/>
        <lb/>whole operation, he remained ſitting erect in a <lb/>chair, without the ſmalleſt
        tendency to faint. <lb/>When the patient cried ſeverely, ſmall quan- <lb/>tities of the
        brain came out repeatedly; and <lb/>I am confident that this, together with what <lb/>was
        immediately extravaſated, would nearly <lb/>fill a table ſpoon. The motion of the brain,
        <lb/>from the pulſation of the arteries, was very <lb/>diſtinct, and produced ſmall
        evacuations of <lb/>its ſubſtance. This motion continued till <lb/>the wound was quite
        healed, which required <lb/>nearly two months. Its cure was very much <lb/>retarded by the
        piece of bone which I allow- <lb/>ed to remain. I was under the neceſſity of <lb/>extracting
        it a month after; which was eaſily <lb/>effected without any bad conſequence. I <lb/>was but
        little troubled with an excreſcence, <lb/>which ſometimes occurs after the operation <lb/>of
        the trepan. It, however, exceeded the <lb/>ſize of a cherry, was remarkably ſenſible,
        <lb/>and, upon preſſure, I could eaſily produce <lb/>giddineſs or ſickneſs. It put on very
        much <lb/>the appearance of the brain in a ſchirrous <lb/>ſtate. Sneezing, coughing, and
        even ſpeak- <lb/>ing, for a few weeks after the accident, gave <pb n="347"/>
        <lb/>great pain; and the firſt produced ſlight ſtu- <lb/>pidity. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From the whole hiſtory of this caſe, I <lb/>think we may draw the following conclu-
        <lb/>ſions. <list>
          <item rend="indent">
            <lb/>1. That a ſound ſtate of the brain is not <lb/>ſo eſſentially neceſſary to life as
            has been <lb/>imagined. </item>
          <item rend="indent">
            <lb/>2. That it may be very much injured, <lb/>without producing dangerous, or even a-
            <lb/>larming conſequences. And, </item>
          <item rend="indent">
            <lb/>3. That this caſe affords a proof, that the <lb/>brain may be more freely treated,
            provided, <lb/>in every circumſtance, the injury is entirely <lb/>unconnected with
            compreſſion. </item>
        </list>
      </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>This laſt concluſion is clearly pointed out, <lb/>by attending to the ſituation of the
        patient; <lb/>for notwithſtanding the bone was beat in <lb/>upon the brain, the dura mater
        lacerated, <lb/>and a quantity of brain extravaſated between <lb/>the cranium and teguments,
        no alarming <lb/>ſymptom enſued. It can only be explained <lb/>from that quantity of brain
        getting imme- <lb/>diate vent, which was neceſſary to compen- <lb/>ſate for the depreſſion
        of the bone, and con- <lb/>ſequently preventing its power of compreſſion. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
