<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Duncan: Histories of Cases of Petechiæ sine febre terminating fatally. </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Dr. Duncan</persName>
            </author>
            <title>VI. Histories of Cases of Petechiæ sine febre terminating fatally. Communicated
              in a Letter to Dr. Duncan, from Dr. William Tattersall, Physician, Liverpool.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries M, DCC, XCV. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest and
              most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and published
              by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. SS. Ed. Physician to His Royal Highness the
              Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians, Edinburgh,
              and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen, Edinburgh, &amp;c.
              And Professor of the Institutions of Medicine in the University of Edinburgh.</title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: Printed for G. Mudie &amp; Son, South Bridge; and for G. G.
                  &amp; J. Robinson, London</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1795b</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">20</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">289-297</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW109167288</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v20_0289">
    <body>
      <pb n="289"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>VI. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>Hiſtories of Caſes of Petechiæ ſine febre termi- <lb/>nating fatally. Communicated in a
        Letter to <lb/>Dr. <hi rend="roman">Duncan</hi>, from Dr. <hi rend="roman">William
          Tatterſall</hi>, <lb/>Phyſician, Liverpool. </head>
      <p rend="space">
        <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">F</hi>ROM the politeneſs and attention with <lb/>which you treated me
        when a ſtudent, <lb/>as well as from the general intereſt you take <lb/>in the purſuit of
        truth, I am perſuaded that <lb/>you will give the following account a candid <lb/>peruſal;
        and that, if you think it worth a <lb/>place in your very uſeful Commentaries, you <lb/>will
        not with-hold it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Accounts of caſes, when faithfully given, <lb/>are often almoſt equally uſeful, whether
        the <lb/>treatment has been ſucceſsful or not. To <lb/>know what remedies will not ſucceed,
        eſpe- <lb/>cially if they were probable or popular, is the <lb/>road to learn what will
        ſucceed; and, from <lb/>theſe negative accounts, there is frequently <pb n="290"/>
        <lb/>more light thrown upon the nature of diſ- <lb/>eaſes, than from the moſt flattering
        teſtimo- <lb/>ny to the efficacy of medicines. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The diſorder of which I am about to give <lb/>a few caſes, having been known only of
        late, <lb/>and treated by few writers, has not yet ob- <lb/>tained a ſixed appellation. It
        has been called <lb/>by different names, of the reſpective proprie- <lb/>ty of which the
        public muſt judge. Graaf <lb/>has called it Petechiæ ſine febre. You, Sir, <lb/>have called
        it Petechianoſis, or Aimarrhœa. <lb/>Dr. Adair, joining both names, has called it
        <lb/>Hæmorrhœa petechialis. I confeſs, that at pre- <lb/>ſent I am inclined to think, that
        it ought to <lb/>be called either petechiæ ſine febre, or pete- <lb/>chionoſis; for I have
        not found the hæmorr- <lb/>hage either conſtant or conſiderable. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Of this diſorder I have ſeen four caſes. <lb/>The firſt was a woman, of the name of
        Mary <lb/>Ferris, aged forty-five. She was the mother of <lb/>a number of children; if I
        recollect right, ſix <lb/>or ſeven. She ſaid, that the laſt labour but <lb/>one had been
        exceedingly long and painful; <lb/>and that, ſince this time, ſhe had been much
        <lb/>troubled both with leucorrhœa and menorr- <lb/>hagia. She ſeemed to be in poor circum-
          <pb n="291"/>
        <lb/>ſtances, and to have lived ſparingly. She <lb/>had been delivered about eight weeks
        before <lb/>I ſaw her, without any particular circumſtan- <lb/>ces occurring; but ſhe had
        not recovered <lb/>well; and ſhe had laboured under the com- <lb/>plaint above mentioned for
        ſix days. She <lb/>had no hæmorrhage; and the diſcolourations <lb/>of the ſkin were rather
        vibices than petechiæ. <lb/>The proſtration of ſtrength and appetite were <lb/>conſiderable,
        but not great; the pulſe was <lb/>ſixty-eight; and ſhe had no febrile ſymp- <lb/>toms. Under
        the direction of the apotheca- <lb/>ry of the Diſpenſary, ſhe was taking, every <lb/>ſecond
        hour, a wine-glaſs full of a mixture <lb/>which we call Miſtura Peruviana Vinoſa. This
        <lb/>is merely equal parts of decoction of Peru- <lb/>vian bark, and domeſtic or raiſin
        wine. She <lb/>was alſo taking a grain of opium every night. <lb/>I changed the mixture, and
        ſubſtituted the <lb/>decoction of bark, acidulated in the propor- <lb/>tion of two drachms
        of the diluted acid of <lb/>vitriol to eight ounces of the decoction, to be <lb/>taken at
        the ſame diſtance of time, and in the <lb/>ſame quantity; but directed, that in the in-
        <lb/>tervals there ſhould be taken as much red <lb/>Port. I directed that the opium ſhould
        be <pb n="292"/>
        <lb/>continued, and ordered mild laxatives occa- <lb/>ſionally. The diſorder had not yielded
        to <lb/>the remedies of the apothecary; nor did it <lb/>yield to mine. I next employed the
        Peruvian <lb/>bark in ſubſtance, and in greater quantities. <lb/>I alſo increaſed the doſe
        of the other reme- <lb/>dies, but without any benefit. This caſe oc- <lb/>curred during the
        firſt part of ſummer. The <lb/>patient expreſſed a deſire to have ſalad, if I <lb/>thought
        it proper. I neither had given, nor <lb/>was able to give, any remedy that was of
        <lb/>ſervice; and I did not think it right to refuſe <lb/>her. She thought ſhe found
        conſiderable be- <lb/>nefit from the ſalad, of which I underſtood <lb/>ſhe took a large
        quantity. It did not, how- <lb/>ever, effect a cure, for ſhe died in three or <lb/>four days
        after ſhe began to take it. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The next caſe was much more ſingular. A <lb/>family in the Work-houſe, of the name of
        <lb/>Clarke, had the itch. The mother of the <lb/>children was extremely clamorous and im-
        <lb/>pertinent; ſhe was continually aſking for <lb/>wine, and other nouriſhment, merely
        becauſe <lb/>the children had the itch. I underſtood that <lb/>ſhe bore a very bad character
        in the build- <lb/>ings, and accordingly they diſregarded her. <pb n="293"/>
        <lb/>In a few weeks after this, ſhe appeared with <lb/>one of the children, a boy of about
        four years <lb/>old, with a few diſtinct purple eruptions upon <lb/>his body; he had a good
        appetite and good <lb/>ſpirits, and played with other children in the <lb/>court; his pulſe
        was natural. I ſuppoſed <lb/>this appearance might be ſome remainder of <lb/>the itch, or
        ſome effect of heat or dirt, and <lb/>took no farther notice of it. In about a week,
        <lb/>the mother brought him again, and he had <lb/>near four times the number of eruptions;
        <lb/>and they were of a darker colour. He was <lb/>languid, but he continued to walk out,
        and <lb/>had a tolerable appetite. I then allowed him <lb/>milk diet, and a little vinum
        domeſticum, <lb/>thinking his mother would be more likely to <lb/>give this than medicine. I
        directed him to <lb/>be kept as much as poſſible in freſh air, but <lb/>not to walk much. He
        remained much the <lb/>ſame for ſome weeks. I wiſhed to have or- <lb/>dered medicine, but
        deſpaired of the mother <lb/>giving it to him. I, however, ventured to <lb/>order an
        acidulated decoction of bark, and <lb/>directed it to be made as pleaſant as poſſible
        <lb/>with ſyrup, in hopes that he might be indu- <lb/>ced to take it. The mother ſaid that
        ſhe gave <pb n="294"/>
        <lb/>it, but the clerk found a bottle full in her <lb/>houſe; and it was generally ſuppoſed
        that ſhe <lb/>did not give any of it. I then deſired the <lb/>clerk to ſee an anodyne
        draught given at <lb/>night, which I believe he did for ſeveral <lb/>nights. The ſpots
        afterwards became ex- <lb/>tremely numerous and vivid. The ſtrength <lb/>and appetite were
        gone, but the pulſe was <lb/>not quick; and there was no preternatural <lb/>heat. There was
        never any hæmorrhage. <lb/>I now ordered bark in ſubſtance, and the <lb/>pulvis ſtypticus;
        but I believe they were <lb/>never given, unleſs when the clerk, or ſome <lb/>neighbour, ſaw
        now and then a doſe given. <lb/>I mentioned the caſe to two of our phyſicians, <lb/>whom I
        happened to meet, and offered to <lb/>ſhew it to them. They agreed to go with me <lb/>next
        morning, which they did. But when <lb/>we came, we found, to our ſurpriſe, and to <lb/>ſome
        degree of temporary confuſion in my- <lb/>ſelf, that fever had ſupervened. The pulſe
        <lb/>was ſo quick, that it could not be very accu- <lb/>rately counted; I think it was near
        160. The <lb/>child died in the evening. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>Some months after my time of attendance at <lb/>the Work-houſe had expired, Dr. M<hi
          rend="sup">c</hi>Cartney <pb n="295"/>
        <lb/>was attending; and he told me that another <lb/>child of the ſame family was labouring
        under <lb/>the ſame diſorder, and took me to ſee him. <lb/>What his treatment was, I do not
        particular- <lb/>ly remember; but I dare ſay it was very pro- <lb/>per, according to what is
        generally ſuppoſed <lb/>of this diſeaſe; but he told me that the mo- <lb/>ther did not do
        juſtice to the child, and that <lb/>he ſuſpected the medicines were not given. <lb/>This
        child died a few days afterwards. The <lb/>parents were ſmall hardy-looking Welch
        <lb/>people, and had no appearance of ſcrophula. <lb/>They would take care that neither they
        nor <lb/>their children were ſtarved, while they were <lb/>kept by the public. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>The fourth caſe was Thomas Freeman, aged <lb/>ſixty-two. He had lived in part of a
        houſe <lb/>as a lodger, and generally dreſſed his own <lb/>proviſions. He appeared to have a
        dread of <lb/>poverty, and to have lived very ſparingly. For <lb/>ſome days before I ſaw
        him, he had laboured <lb/>under conſiderable weakneſs, attended with <lb/>epiſtaxis, and
        large diſcolourations of the <lb/>ſkin, which were a kind of vibices; but a- <lb/>mongſt
        them, there were many ſmall bright <lb/>petechiæ; the pulſe was natural; the appe- <pb
          n="296"/>
        <lb/>tite tolerable. He could walk a little out to <lb/>ſee his neighbours, and was rather
        unwilling <lb/>to be confined; but was very tractable. I or- <lb/>dered vitriolic acid,
        bark, and wine, which <lb/>I believe he took very regularly, but without <lb/>any benefit. I
        then ordered him to take as <lb/>many oranges as he conveniently could, and <lb/>to continue
        the wine. The vibices decrea- <lb/>ſed, but the petechiæ increaſed very faſt. He
        <lb/>ſeemed, however, to be more cheerful, but <lb/>did not gain any ſtrength. In three days
        <lb/>after, he began to live almoſt entirely upon <lb/>oranges, to which he added a little
        gruel. <lb/>He was removed to the houſe of a daughter, <lb/>in a diſtant part of the town,
        and walked to <lb/>and from the hackney-coach. After this he <lb/>was unable to riſe from
        his bed, grew worſe <lb/>very rapidly, and died in about two days. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>From this account of an almoſt total want <lb/>of ſucceſs, and from the other caſes
        which <lb/>are publiſhed, I think it is evident, that we <lb/>do not yet comprehend either
        the nature or <lb/>the cure of this diſeaſe. It has certainly a <lb/>conſiderable
        reſemblance to ſcurvy, and ap- <lb/>pears to yield the moſt to ſimilar remedies; <lb/>but
        where ſcurvy affects the patients no more <pb n="297"/>
        <lb/>than this diſorder does at firſt, it yields to the <lb/>remedies with much greater
        certainty and ra- <lb/>pidity. </p>
      <p rend="indent">
        <lb/>In the next caſe that occurs, I will try the <lb/>carbonic acid, ripe fruits, and briſk
        fer- <lb/>mented malt-liquors. </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
