<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>LMEMT Corpus - Fowler: An account of the Effects of an overdose of the Terra
          Ponderosa Muriata</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Compiler</resp>
          <persName xml:id="IT">
            <forename>Irma</forename>
            <surname>Taavitsainen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="TH">
            <forename>Turo</forename>
            <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALe">
            <forename>Anu</forename>
            <surname>Lehto</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="VM">
            <forename>Ville</forename>
            <surname>Marttila</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="RO">
            <forename>Raisa</forename>
            <surname>Oinonen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="PP">
            <forename>Päivi</forename>
            <surname>Pahta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MR">
            <forename>Maura</forename>
            <surname>Ratia</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="CS">
            <forename>Carla</forename>
            <surname>Suhr</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JT">
            <forename>Jukka</forename>
            <surname>Tyrkkö</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
          <persName xml:id="WA">
            <forename>Wilma</forename>
            <surname>Andersson</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="EC">
            <forename>Emanuela</forename>
            <surname>Costea</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="DV">
            <forename>Diana</forename>
            <surname>Frank-Väyrynen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SK">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Kalliomäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="MK">
            <forename>Mirella</forename>
            <surname>Klinga</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="SKo">
            <forename>Sami</forename>
            <surname>Koskinen</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="ALi">
            <forename>Aatu</forename>
            <surname>Liimatta</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="HR">
            <forename>Heikki</forename>
            <surname>Rajala</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="JR">
            <forename>Jenni</forename>
            <surname>Riihimäki</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName xml:id="AW">
            <forename>Anna-Lina</forename>
            <surname>Walraff</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Department of Modern Languages, University of Helsinki</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <funder>
          <orgName>University of Helsinki</orgName>
          <orgName>Academy of Finland</orgName>
        </funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
        <date>forthcoming</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright by the publisher. All rights reserved.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>Dr Fowler</persName>
            </author>
            <title>III. An account of the Effects of an overdose of the Terra Ponderosa Muriata.
              Communicated to Dr Fowler, by Mr A. Mather, Surgeon, York.</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title>Medical commentaries M, DCC, XCIV. Exhibiting a concise view of the latest and
              most important discoveries in medicine and medical philosophy. Collected and published
              by Andrew Duncan, M. D. F. R. &amp; A. SS. Ed. Physician to His Royal Highness the
              Prince of Wales for Scotland, Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians, Edinburgh,
              and Member of the Royal Societies of Medicine of Paris, Copenhagen, Edinburgh, &amp;c.
              And Professor of the Institutions of Medicine in the University of Edinburgh.</title>
            <editor>Andrew Duncan</editor>
            <imprint>
              <!--Add additional <placeName/> elements for each additional place of publication.-->
              <pubPlace>
                <placeName>London</placeName>
              </pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName>Edinburgh: Printed for G. Mudie, Edinburgh; and G. G. &amp; J. Robinson,
                  &amp; J. Johnson, London</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date>1795</date>
              <biblScope unit="vol">19</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="page">265-270</biblScope>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure type="format">8⁰</measure>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
          <note type="source_copy">
            <idno type="ECCO">CW110325353</idno>
            <idno type="ESTC">P6675</idno>
          </note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef n="Periodicals"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="article" rend="roman" decls="EMJ3_v19_0265">
    <body>
      <pb n="265"/>
      <head rend="align-center">
        <lb/>III. </head>
      <head rend="italic hanging space">
        <lb/>An account of the Effects of an over-doſe of the <lb/>Terra Ponderoſa Muriata.
        Communicated <lb/>to Dr <hi rend="roman">Fowler</hi>, by Mr <hi rend="roman">A. Mather</hi>,
        Surgeon, <lb/>York. </head>
      <div>
        <p rend="space">
          <lb/><hi rend="dc(2)">T</hi>HE Following caſe affords an inſtance, <lb/>which may not
          ſpeedily recur, of the <lb/>pernicious effect of an over-doſe of terra <lb/>ponderoſa
          muriata. It is drawn up with ſo <lb/>much perſpicuity and accuracy by the gentle- <lb/>man
          who was the ſubject of it, that I can- <lb/>not add any thing to it in theſe reſpects. I
          <lb/>ſhall only premiſe, that he was ſubject to <lb/>frequent attacks of colic, and in the
          inter- <lb/>val thought his ſtomach much ſtrengthen- <lb/>ed, and the motion of the bowels
          duly re- <lb/>gulated by the terra ponderoſa muriata, in <lb/>doſes of 10 or 12 drops,
          three times a day. <lb/>Theſe effects I had obſerved before in ſimilar <lb/>caſes, and
          therefore, recommended the uſe <lb/>of the medicine to him. As he lived at a <pb n="266"/>
          <lb/>conſiderable diſtance from me, I ſent him <lb/>an ounce-phial of it at a time, with
          cau- <lb/>tionary directions reſpecting its uſe. Theſe, <lb/>however, in a moment of
          inattention, he <lb/>had forgot. I conjecture, he muſt have <lb/>taken at that time about
          70 or 80 drops; <lb/>having taken, by his acount, the ſixth part <lb/>of an ounce. The
          conſequences which fol- <lb/>lowed are, I think, worthy the notice of <lb/>the Faculty. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>If you will tranſmit them to Dr Duncan <lb/>for inſertion in the Medical
          Commentaries, <lb/>you will confer an obligation on, Sir, </p>
        <signed rend="align-center">
          <lb/>Your ſincere friend, <lb/>and humble ſervant, </signed>
        <cb n="1"/>
        <dateline rend="italic indent">
          <lb/>York, Auguſt 26th. </dateline>
        <cb n="2"/>
        <signed rend="sc align-right">
          <lb/>A. Mather. </signed>
        <cb n="1 2"/>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head rend="italic">
          <lb/>To Dr Fowler, Phyſcian, York. </head>
        <salute rend="sc space">
          <lb/>Dear Sir, </salute>
        <dateline rend="italic align-right">Freſton, 2d March 1792. </dateline>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>Well acquainted, as I doubt not you are, <lb/>with the uſe of the ſtomachic drops you
          gave <lb/>me, you propably may not have had an op- <lb/>portunity of obſerving the effects
          of their <lb/>abuſe. As a matter of profeſſional curioſity, <lb/>I perhaps may give you
          ſome information on <lb/>the ſubject. </p>
        <pb n="267"/>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>About a fortnight ago, or ſomewhat more, <lb/>I had an attack of the colic; and after
          I <lb/>was relieved, I applied to the drops. I took <lb/>them every day; but only once
          each day, <lb/>and 10 drops at a time. On Thurſday night, <lb/>I took what was meant to be
          the uſual quan- <lb/>tity, but found from the exceſſively ſtrong <lb/>taſte, I muſt have
          made a miſtake. I hap- <lb/>pened to have looked at the bottle juſt be- <lb/>fore I
          dropped them out, to obſerve how <lb/>much remained. When I looked again after-
          <lb/>wards, on account of finding the taſte ſo <lb/>ſtrong, I perceived I had diſminiſhed
          them half <lb/>an inch in depth, certainly rather more than <lb/>leſs. They inſtantly
          produced their uſual <lb/>effect of making me ſqueamiſh. In half an <lb/>hour's time,
          (about 12 o'clock), I began to <lb/>be violently purged without griping, and, at <lb/>the
          ſame time, began to be very much relax- <lb/>ed. This continued till about 2 in the af-
          <lb/>ternoon, by which time, I could only crawl <lb/>along with the aſſiſtance of the
          furniture <lb/>and walls; my knees, and particularly my <lb/>right, was firſt ſeized. When
          the purging <lb/>ſtopped, it was ſucceeded by vomiting, which <lb/>continued till about 8
          o'clock. The diſ- <pb n="268"/>
          <lb/>charge was not great, but very nauſeous, <lb/>both in taſte and apperance. I took
          ſome <lb/>warm camomile tea; but that came off di- <lb/>rectly, and pure. About 3, I was
          helped up <lb/>to bed. The uſe of my limbs was gradually <lb/>taken from me, before the 9
          in the evening. I <lb/>could not produce the leaſt poſſible motion, <lb/>in any joint or
          limb about me. The laſt <lb/>part I loſt the uſe of was my left hand. The <lb/>ſtrokes of
          my pulſe, so long as I could feel <lb/>them, and afterwards, when an apothecary <lb/>in
          this neighbourhood, for whom I ſent, felt <lb/>them, were regular, and as in the uſual
          ſtate <lb/>of my health. My feet were deadly cold, <lb/>though continually wrapped in
          heated ſlan- <lb/>nels. The apothecary was ſent for in the <lb/>evening, and was with me
          about 8 o'clock. <lb/>I told him what I apprehended to be the <lb/>cauſe of my complaint,
          and what I under- <lb/>ſtood from you the medicine was. He ſeem- <lb/>ed to doubt whether
          it could produce the <lb/>effects: he ordered me nothing of medicine <lb/>that night. The
          people about me were then <lb/>prepairing me a bed down ſtairs: he directed <lb/>hot
          bricks to be applied to my feet, as ſoon <lb/>as I was removed, and that they ſhould give
            <pb n="269"/>
          <lb/>me ſome gruel whit brandy in it. After I <lb/>was got to bed, my feet began to burn,
          and <lb/>my whole body to perſpire freely, but not <lb/>profuſely; and continued to do ſo
          through <lb/>the remainder of my illneſs. I could not <lb/>ſleep any part of the night;
          and was very <lb/>uneaſy in every poſture in which I could be <lb/>placed. You may judge
          of my utter debility, <lb/>when I tell you that, in being ſerved with <lb/>ſome toaſt
          ſteeped in gruel, a crum paſſed <lb/>the wrong way, and yet with the utmoſt <lb/>effort I
          could not make the leaſt cough to <lb/>throw it back again. The apothecary ſtill,
          <lb/>however, thought my complaint could ſcarce- <lb/>ly be cauſed by the terra ponderoſa
          muriata, <lb/>but ſeemed diſpoſed to conſider me in a rheu- <lb/>matic fever. He told me,
          he ſhould ſend <lb/>me a mixture to continue and promote the <lb/>perſpiration, which had
          broken out. </p>
        <p rend="indent">
          <lb/>About 2 o'clock on Friday afternoon, I <lb/>perceived ſome little ſtrength in a
          finger, <lb/>and ſome of my toes. About 5 o'clock, I <lb/>was ſenſibly amending; and at 10
          o'clock, <lb/>when my bed was made, I could put part of <lb/>my own clothes on, and walk
          without aſſiſt- <lb/>ance over the floor, from and to the bed. <pb n="270"/>
          <lb/>On being got to bed again, I took the apo- <lb/>thecary's medicine for the firſt
          time; the <lb/>baſis of which, if I may be allowed to pry <lb/>into the myſteries of
          medicine, I conceive to <lb/>be tincture of guaiacum, which directly <lb/>brought on the
          perſpiration, that had been <lb/>rather checked by getting up. That night <lb/>I reſted
          well; and the next day felt no com- <lb/>plaint, exept a ſenſation of wearineſs in the
          <lb/>muſcular parts of my body, very like that <lb/>which follows the day after a hard
          journey. <lb/>I am ſenſibly thinner than I was, but feel no <lb/>remains of my complaint.
          My ſpeedy re- <lb/>covery left me no doubt about the cauſe of <lb/>my complaint. But I
          ſhall not be terrified <lb/>by it from uſing this valuable medicine. I <lb/>brought my
          bottle very low, and ſhall there- <lb/>fore beg you to ſend me two more; one of <lb/>which
          I intend to give away to a man in the <lb/>neighbourhood, to whom I am clear it muſt
          <lb/>be of ſervice, from the ſimilarity of our ſto- <lb/>mach complaints. Dear Sir, </p>
        <signed rend="indent">
          <lb/>Your obliged friend and ſervant, <lb/><hi rend="align-right">J— L— </hi>
          <lb/><hi rend="italic">To Mr Mather. </hi>
        </signed>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
